<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="081712eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
OCTOBER IM« - 9 French franca
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
WEAVING CLOUD BROCADE
These weavers are practising their craft on modern reconstitutions
of a Chinese loom dating from the Ming Dynasty (1368-1644).
Looms of this type, which represent an advanced form of weaving technology, were
used to produce intricately figured fabrics, notably the multi-coloured brocaded silks
with floral and cloud motifs which are known as yunjin ("cloud brocade").
While the weaver operates the loom by pressing treadles with his feet,
an operative seated on top of the machine creates the pattern.
Automation of this technique has proved difficult,
and time-honoured methods are still used to produce this kind of brocade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
October 1988
h^^hhhí t*è
4
7
>^
The Chinese scientific genius
by Robert K. G. Temple
toriPrecursors of modern science
by Joseph Needham
INVENTIONS AND DISCOVERIES
OF AN ANCIENT CIVILIZATION
The observation of sunspots
Cast iron
9
10 ¿2
The cardan suspension
Steel manufacture
T_he chain pump
A cybernetic machine
11
12
13
14
a)
Magic mirrors
Efficient horse harnesses
16
17
The stirrup
The segmental arch bridge
A refined value ofpt
18
19
21
The decimal system
Porcelain
21
22
Matches 23
Biological pest control
Petroleum and natural gas
24
25
The mechanical clock 26
Paper money
Declination of the Earth's
magnetic field
The wheelbarrow
28
29
29
Lacquer 30
The first contour transport canal
Immunology
32
34
Texts : copyright © Multimedia Publications (UK) Ltd
Cover: Illustration of sunspots from a manuscript
by the Ming Emperor Zhu Gaoji (Xuanzong)
entitled Essay on Astronomicaland Meteorological
Presages, written in 1 425. The illustration is
thought to have been made by the Emperor
himself. (See also page 9).
Photo© Cambridge University Library
Back cover: Chinese metallurgists practising their
trade in the presence of the Emperor. Detail from a
19th-century book plate, Bibliothèque Nationale,
Paris
Photo Jean-Loup Charmet © Photeb Archives, Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris
The Courier
A window open on the world 41styear
Published monthly in 35 languages English
French Spanish Russian German
Arabic Japanese Italian Hindi
Tamil Hebrew Persian Dutch
Portuguese Turkish Urdu Catalan
Malaysian Korean Swahili Croato-
Serb Macedonian Serbo-Croat
Slovene Chinese Bulgarian Greek
Sinhala Finnish Swedish Basque
Thai Vietnamese Pashto Hausa
The origins of many of the things the modern world
takes for granted from paper to porcelain, from
mechanical clocks to the harness, steel-making and
the extraction of petroleum and natural gas can be
traced to ancient China. Although for centuries
these and many other achievements of Chinese
inventiveness were forgotten or veiled in obscurity,
in recent years the nature of the Chinese scientific
genius has become increasingly appreciated. This is
largely due to one of the outstanding intellectual
ventures of our time, the research and writings of
Dr. Joseph Needham of Cambridge University,
who has spent over half a century investigating the
history of Chinese science and technology. The
results of Dr. Needham's investigations, and those
of his colleagues at the Needham Research Institute
in Cambridge, are being published in a monumental
work, Science and Civilisation in China, which will
be complete in 25 volumes. (Fifteen have so far
appeared or are passing through the press.)
With Dr. Needham's authorization, an
American science writer, Robert K.G. Temple, has
written a book entitled China, Land ofDiscovery
and Invention which attempts to make this
scholarly research accessible to the general reader.
All the articles in this issue have been extracted
from Mr. Temple's book, with the kind permission
of the publishers. The issue falls into 3 parts : a brief
introduction in which Temple describes the genesis
and importance of Needham's work; a short text in
which Needham sets the question of scientific and
technological activity in a social and economic
context; and descriptions of over 20 discoveries and
inventions. (Most of the descriptions have been
abridged.) A celebration of the Chinese scientific
genius, this issue may also lead readers to speculate
about the surprises that will be revealed when the
history of science and technology in other great
world civilizations comes to be written.
_ 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The Chinese
scientific genius
BY ROBERT K. G. TEMPLE
POSSIBLY more than half of the basic
inventions and discoveries upon
which the "modern world" rests
come from China.
Without the importation from China of
nautical and navigational improvements
such' as ships' rudders, the compass and
multiple masts, the great European
Voyages of Discovery could never have
been undertaken. Columbus would not
have sailed to America, and Europeans
would never have established colonial
empires.
Without the importation from China of
the stirrup, to enable them to stay on
horseback, knights of old would never
have ridden in their shining armour to aid
damsels in distress; there would have been
no Age of Chivalry. And without the
importation from China of guns and gun¬
powder, the knights would not have been
knocked from their horses by bullets
which pierced the armour, bringing the
Age of Chivalry to an end.
Without the importation from China of
paper and printing, Europe would have
continued for much longer to copy books
by hand. Literacy would not have become
so widespread.
Johann Gutenberg did not invent mov¬
able type. It was invented in China. Wil¬
liam Harvey did not discover the circula¬
tion of the blood in the body. It was
discovered or rather, always assumed
in China. Isaac Newton was not the first to
discover his First Law of Motion. It was
discovered in China.
These myths and many others are shat¬
tered by our discovery of the true Chinese
origins of many of the things, all around
us, which we take for granted. It is exciting
to realize that the East and the West are
not as far apart in spirit or in fact as most of
us have been led, by appearances, to be¬
lieve, and that the East and the West are
already combined in a synthesis so power¬
ful and so profound that it is all-perva¬
ding. Within this synthesis we live our
daily lives, and from it there is no escape.
The modern world is a combination of
Eastern and Western ingredients which
are inextricably fused.
Right, detail from a Chinese star map
dating from c. 940 AD. Some 1,350 stars
are shown on the map. They are drawn in
3 colours, white, black and yellow, to
correspond to 3 ancient schools of
astronomy.
Left, hoeing crops during
the Han Dynasty (207 BC-
220 AD). Intensive hoeing
and cultivation of crops in
rows originated in China
around the 6th century BC.
4 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
*t 1
¥
IL
it
9
S
Va
tit
1
Astronomical instruments silhouetted
against the sky at the Beijing
Observatory, built in the 15th century.
Beijing hayhad an astronomical
observatory since the Qin Dynasty
(3rd century BC).
The discovery of this truth is a result of
incidents in the life of the distinguished
British scholar Dr Joseph Needham, au¬
thor of the great work Science and Civi¬
lisation in China. In 1937, aged thirty-
seven, Needham was one of the youngest
Fellows of the Royal Society and a
biochemist of considerable distinction at
Cambridge. He had already published
many books, including the definitive his¬
tory of embryology. One day he met and
befriended some Chinese students, in par¬
ticular a young woman from Nanjing
named Lu Gwei-djen, whose father had
passed on to her his unusually profound
knowledge of the history of Chinese sci¬
ence. Needham began to hear tales of how
the Chinese had been the true discoverers
of this and that important thing, and at
first he could not believe it. But as he
looked further into it, evidence began to
come to light from Chinese texts, hastily
translated by his new friends for his
benefit.
Needham became obsessed with this
subject, as he freely admits. Not knowing
a word of Chinese, he set about learning
the language. In 1942 he was sent to China
for several years as Scientific Counsellor
to the British Embassy in Chongqing. He
was able to travel all over China, learn the
language thoroughly, meet men of science
everywhere he went, and accumulate vast
quantities of priceless ancient Chinese
books on science. After the War,
Needham became Unesco's first Assistant
Director General for the natural sciences.
In July 1946 Needham stated in a lec¬
ture to the China Society in London that:
"What is really very badly needed is a
proper book on the history of science and
technology in China, especially with re¬
ference to the social and economic back¬
ground of Chinese life. Such a book would
be by no means academic, but would have
a wide bearing on the general history of
thought and ideas."
Needham, now back in Cambridge,
went ahead and wrote and is still writ¬
ing the very work which he envisaged,
except for the fact that it is, indeed, very
academic. It is in fact much easier to read
than it looks, but of course is very expen-
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
sive, and even many libraries cannot
afford it. Needham, however, has never
lost his early vision of a work which was
"by no means academic"; he has always
wanted to make his work more accessible
in every possible way. Therefore, when I
approached him in 1984 with the sugges¬
tion that I write a popular book for the
general reader based upon his half cen¬
tury's labours, he agreed more readily
than at the time I could understand. It is
now clear that this was a project which he
had long envisaged, and which he felt he
could no longer hope to accomplish
himself.
In the 1946 lecture which was so
prophetic of his future activities, Dr.
Needham went on to say: "I personally
believe that all Westerners, all people be¬
longing to the Euro-American civiliza¬
tion, are subconsciously inclined to con¬
gratulate themselves, feeling with some
self-satisfaction that, after all, it was
Europe and its extension into the
Americas which developed modern
science and technology. In the same way I
think that all my Asian friends are subcon¬
sciously inclined to a certain anxiety about
this matter, because their civilization did
not, in fact, develop modern science and
technology."
We need to set this matter right, from
both ends. And I can think of no better
single case than the lesson to be drawn
from the history of agriculture. We should
take to heart the astonishing and disturb¬
ing fact that the European agricultural
revolution, which laid the basis for the
Industrial Revolution, came about only
because of the importation of Chinese
ideas and inventions. The growing of
crops in rows, intensive hoeing of weeds,
the "modern" seed drill, the iron plough,
the moldboard to turn the ploughed soil,
The earliest surviving Chinese notations
are records ofdivination incised over
3,000 years ago on "oracle bones"
(tortoise shells or the shoulder blades of
animals). Some oracle bones unearthed
near Anyang are inscribed with
astronomical and calendrical
information such as the names of stars
and data about solar and lunar eclipses.
Left, two Anyang oracle bones bearing
astronomical inscriptions.
and efficient harnesses were all imported
from China. Before the arrival from China
of the trace harness and the collar harness,
Westerners choked their horses with
straps round their throats.
Although ancient Italy could produce
plenty of grain, it could not be transported
overland to Rome for lack of satisfactory
harnesses. Rome depended on shipments
of grain by sea from places like Egypt. As
for sowing methods probably over half
of Europe's seed was wasted every year
before the Chinese idea of the seed drill
came to the attention of Europeans.
Countless millions of farmers broke their
backs and their spirits by ploughing with
ridiculously poor ploughs, while for two
thousand years the Chinese were enjoying
their relatively effortless method.
It would be better if the nations and the
peoples of the world had a clearer under¬
standing of each other, allowing the men¬
tal chasm between East and West to be
bridged. After all they are, and have been
for several centuries, intimate partners in
the business of building a world civiliza¬
tion. The technological world of today is a
product of both East and West to an extent
which until recently no one had ever im¬
agined. It is now time for the Chinese
contribution to be recognized and ack¬
nowledged, by East and West alike.
ROBERT K.G. TEMPLE is an American writer
who specializes in the popularization of science.
His published works, which have been widely
translated, include The Sirius Mystery, and
Conversations with Eternity, a history of divina¬
tion in the Ancient World. He is currently enga¬
ged in the co-production of a television, series
based on his book China, Land of Discovery and
Invention.
Precursors
6 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
of modern science
BY JOSEPH NEEDHAM
THE extraordinary inventiveness, and
insight into nature, of ancient and
medieval China raises two fun¬
damental questions. First, why should the
Chinese have been so far in advance of
other civilizations ; and second, why aren't
they now centuries ahead of the rest of the
world? We think it was a matter of the
very different social and economic sys¬
tems in China and the West. Modern sci¬
ence arose only in Europe in the seven¬
teenth century when the best method of
discovery was itself discovered; but the
discoveries and inventions made then and
thereafter depended in so many cases on
centuries of previous Chinese progress in
science, technology and medicine.
The English philosopher Francis Bacon
(1561-1626) selected three inventions,
paper and printing, gunpowder, and the
magnetic compass, which had done more,
he thought, than any religious conviction,
or any astrological influence, or any con¬
queror's achievements, to transform com¬
pletely the modern world and mark it off
from Antiquity and the Middle Ages. He
regarded the origins of these inventions as
"obscure and inglorious" and he died
without ever knowing that all of them
were Chinese. We have done our best to
put this record straight.
Chauvinistic Westerners, of course, al¬
ways try to minimize the indebtedness of
Europe to China in Antiquity and the
Left, a model reconstructed after a Tang
Dynasty (7th century) original, of a "/»-
counter" or device for measuring
distance. The counter was constructed in
such a way that, as it moved along the
road, one of the 2 drummers would beat
the drum at each li, an ancient Chinese
distance unit corresponding to half a
kilometre.
Middle Ages, but often the circumstantial
evidence is compelling. For example the
first blast furnaces for cast iron, now
known to be Scandinavian of the late
eighth century AD, are of closely similar
form to those of the previous century in
China; while as late as the seventeenth
century all the magnetic compasses of sur¬
veyors and astronomers pointed south,
not north, just as the compasses of China
had always done. In many cases, however,
we cannot as yet detect the capillary chan¬
nels through which knowledge was con¬
veyed from East to West. Nevertheless we
have always adopted the very reasonable
assumption that the longer the time elaps¬
ing between the appearance of a discovery
or invention in one part of the world, and
its appearance later on in some other part
of the world far away, the less likely is it
that the new thing was independently in¬
vented or discovered.
But all these things being agreed, a for¬
midable question then presents itself. If
the Chinese were so advanced in Antiqui¬
ty and the Middle Ages, how was it that
the Scientific Revolution, the coming of
modern science into the world, happened
only in Europe?
The fact is that in the seventeenth cen¬
tury we have to face a package deal; the
Scientific Revolution was accompanied
both by the Protestant Reformation and
by the rise of capitalism, the ascendancy of
the entrepreneurial bourgeoisie. Distinc¬
tively modern science, which then de¬
veloped, was a mathematization of
hypotheses about nature, combined with
relentless experimentation. The sciences
of all the ancient and medieval worlds had
had an indelibly ethnic stamp, but now
nature was addressed for the first time in a
universal and international language, the
precise and quantitative idiom of mathe-
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
This tower for measuring the shadow
cast by the Sun at the winter and summer
solstices was considered by Chinese
astronomers in ancient times to be the
centre of the world. A gnomon (sundial
arm), almost 13 m high, stood upright in
the central niche and its shadow was
measured along the 40-metre-long
horizontal stone scale (foreground). In
its present form the structure is a Ming
Dynasty (1368-1644) renovation of a
building erected around 1276 AD.
*V<* '-'
matics, a tongue which every man and
woman, irrespective of colour, creed or
race, can use and master if given the proper
training. And to the technique of experi¬
ment the same applies. It was like the
merchant's universal standard of value.
How one looks at the primary causative
factor in all this depends on one's own
background. If one is a theologian one
probably thinks that the liberation of the
Reformation was responsible; if one is an
old-fashioned scientist, one naturally
thinks that the scientific movement occur¬
red first and powered all the others; and if
one is a Marxist, one certainly thinks that
the economic and social changes bear the
main responsibility.
One factor which must have great rele¬
vance here is the undeniable circumstance
that the feudalism of Europe and China
were fundamentally different. European
feudalism was military-aristocratic: the
peasantry were governed by the knights in
their manors, and they in turn were sub¬
ject to the barons in their castles, while the
king in his palace ruled over all. In time of
war he needed the help of the lower ranks
in the feudal hierarchy who were bound to
rally to him with stated numbers of men-
at-arms. How different was the feudalism
of China, long very justifiably described
as bureaucratic. From the time of the first
emperor, Qin Shih Huangdi, onwards
(third century BC), the old hereditary
feudal houses were gradually attacked and
destroyed, while the king or emperor (as
he soon became) governed by the aid of an
enormous bureaucracy, a civil service un
imaginable in extent and degree of orga¬
nization to the petty kingdoms of Europe.
Modern research is showing that the
bureaucratic organization of China in its
earlier stages strongly helped science to
grow; only in its later ones did it forcibly
inhibit further growth, and in particular
prevented a breakthrough which has
occurred in Europe. For example, no
other country in the world at the begin¬
ning of the eighth century AD could have
set up a meridian arc survey stretching
from south to north some 4,000 kilo¬
metres. Nor could it have mounted an
expedition at that time to go and observe
the stars of the southern hemisphere to
within 20° of the south celestial pole. Nor
indeed would it have wanted to.
It may well be that a similar pattern will
appear in the future when the history of
science, technology and medicine, for all
the great classical literary cultures, such as
India or Sri Lanka, comes to be written
and gathered in. Europe has entered into
their inheritance, producing an ecumenic¬
al universal science and technology valid
for every man and woman on the face of
the Earth. One can only hope that the
shortcomings of the distinctively Euro¬
pean traditions in other matters will not
debauch the non-European civilizations.
For example, the sciences of China and of
Islam never dreamed of divorcing science
from ethics, but when at the Scientific
Revolution the final cause of Aristotle was
done away with, and ethics chased out of
science, things became very different, and
more menacing. This was good in so far as
it clarified and discriminated between the
great forms of human experience, but very
bad and dangerous when it opened the
way for evil men to use the great discover¬
ies of modern science and divert them to
activities disastrous for humanity. Science
needs to be lived alongside religion, philo¬
sophy, history and aesthetic experience;
alone it can lead to great harm. All we can
do today is to hope and pray that the
unbelievably dangerous powers of atomic
weapons, which have been put into the
hands of human beings by the develop¬
ment of modern science, will remain
under control by responsible men, and
that maniacs will not release powers that
could extinguish not only mankind, but all
life on Earth.
JOSEPH NEEDHAM, British historian of Chi¬
nese science and technology, is director of the
Needham Research Institute in Cambridge,
England. For more than 40 years he has been
engaged on a monumental, multi-volume history
of Science and Civilisation in China (Cambridge
University Press), of which he is the director and
principal contributor.
8 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
INVENTIONS AND DISCOVERIES
OF AN ANCIENT CIVILIZATION
- A
The Editors wish to thank the organizers of a
major exhibition on Chinese science and techno¬
logy, "Chine Ciel et Terre, 5000 Ans d'Inven¬
tions et de Découvertes", for their help in the
preparation of this issue. The exhibition is being
held at the Musées Royaux d'Art et d'Histoire
in Brussels from .16 September 1988 to
16 January 1989.
The observation of sunspots
Most of the sunspots seen in the West before the seventeenth century were
explained away as transits of the Sun by the planets Mercury and Venus.
The theory of "perfection of the Heavens" forbade the admission of any
imperfections on the surface of the Sun.
The Chinese suffered from no such preconceived insistence on "perfec¬
tion". Since sunspots are sometimes large enough to be seen by the naked
eye, the Chinese naturally saw them. The earliest surviving record we have
of their observations would seem to be some remarks by one of the three
known early astronomers in China. He was Gan De, who lived in the
fourth century BC. He and two contemporaries, Shi Shen and Wu Xian,
drew up the first great star catalogues. Their work was fully comparable to
that of the Greek Hipparchos, though two centuries earlier.
The next indication of a sunspot observation dates from 165 BC. We are
told in a much later encyclopaedia, The Ocean ofJade, that in that year the
Chinese character wang appeared in the Sun. This was therefore a sunspot
which appeared not round, but shaped like a cross with a bar drawn across
the top and the bottom. The astronomer D.J. Schove accepts this as the
world's earliest precisely dated sunspot. The recording of sunspot observa¬
tions in the voluminous official imperial histories of China commenced on
10 May 28 BC. But systematic Chinese observations of sunspots probably
began at the latest by the fourth century BC, and only the loss of much
literature of that time denies us more specific information.
Most people today believe that sunspots were first observed in the West
by Galileo, who is also supposed to have been the first person to "invent"
or at least use the telescope. Neither belief is true. Galileo most certainly
did not invent the telescope, though he gave it prominence, and
courageously advocated its use to study the heavens. As for the observation
of sunspots, the earliest clear reference to them so far found in Western
literature is in Einhard's Life of Charlemagne, of about 807 AD.
Later sunspot observations in the West were made by the Arab Abu
al-Fadl Ja'far ibn al-Muqtafi in 840 AD, by Ibn Rushd about 1196, and by
Italian observers around 1457.
Needham has counted the numbers of sunspot observations in the
official histories between 28 BC and 1638 AD, and has found 112 instances.
There are also hundreds of notices of sunspots in other Chinese books
during the centuries. These Chinese records are the oldest and longest
continuous series of such observations in the world.
_ 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Cast iron The Chinese practised the technique of using blast furnaces for making cast
iron from at least the fourth century BC. There were a number of reasons
for this. China had good refractory clays for the construction of the walls
of blast furnaces. The Chinese also knew how to reduce the temperature at
which the iron would melt. They threw in something which they called
"black earth", which contained much iron phosphate. If up to 6 per cent of
phosphorus is added in this way to an iron mixture, it reduces the melting
point from the normal 1130°C to 950°C. This technique was used in the
early centuries, ceasing before the sixth century AD, when proper blast
furnaces came into use which needed no such assistance.
Coal, which gave a high temperature, was used as a fuel from the fourth
century AD, and probably earlier. One method was to put the iron ore in
batteries of elongated, tube-like crucibles, and pack these round with a
mass of coal which was then burnt. This had the extra advantage of
excluding sulphur from the process.
The widespread availability of cast iron in ancient China had many side
effects. It led to the innovation of the cast iron ploughshare in agriculture,
along with iron hoes and other tools. Iron knives, axes, chisels, saws and
awls all became available. Food could be cooked in cast iron pots, and even
toys were made of cast iron. Cast iron statuettes of various animals have
been found in Han Dynasty tombs dating between the second centuries
BC and AD. Cast iron moulds for implements dating from the fourth
century BC have also been discovered. Hoes and axes would have been cast
in these, in either bronze or iron.
The expertise in cast iron enabled pots and pans to be made with very
thin walls, impossible by other iron technology. One extremely important
result was that salt could be mass-produced from evaporated brine, which
can only be done in such thin pans. This in turn led the Chinese to exploit
natural gas by deep drilling. This was in order to tap the energy from the
burning gas to evaporate the vast quantities of brine required for the giant
salt industry (which the Han Dynasty nationalized along with the iron
industry in 119 BC). The salt and gas industries could not have existed
without the cast iron industry.
In the third century BC, the Chinese discovered how to make a
malleable cast iron by annealing (that is, by holding it at a high temperature
for a week or so). It was then not so brittle, and would therefore not shatter
Towering achievement of early Chinese
metallurgy. The 13-m-high Yu Quan
pagoda at Dangyang (Hubei) is entirely
built of cast iron. Erected in 1061, it is the
oldest surviving cast iron pagoda.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Tibetan brass globe lamp. The lamp is
suspended by 4 separate interlocking
rings which ensure that it always
remains upright.
if subjected to a violent shock. This meant that objects like ploughshares
could survive striking large stones with considerable force. Cast iron had
something of the elasticity of wrought iron, but with the much greater
strength and solidity that came from being cast. It was almost as good as
steel.
Some of the ancient Chinese feats of casting iron are so impressive as to
be almost unbelievable, even when the results are before our eyes. For
instance, there is the cast iron pagoda shown on opposite page.
Perhaps the grandest cast iron structure of all was not actually a building.
The Empress Wu Zetian had an octagonal cast iron column built, called the
"Celestial Axis Commemorating the Virtue of the Great Zhou Dynasty
with Its Myriad Regions". It was built in 695 AD upon a base of cast iron
51 metres in circumference and 6 metres high. The column itself was
3.6 metres in diameter and rose 32 metres in the air; on top was a "cloud
canopy" 3 metres high and 9 metres in circumference. On top of this in
turn stood four bronze dragons each 3.6 metres high supporting a gilded
pearl. We have a record of the amount of metal used in this construction
about 1 ,325 tons. The largest single cast iron object ever made (the pagodas
were obviously not a single piece) was erected on the orders of the Emperor
Shizong of the Later Zhou Dynasty in commemoration of his campaign
against the Tartars in 954 AD. This extraordinary object, 6 metres tall, still
stands and is known as the Great Lion of Zangzhou (Hebei). It is not solid,
but its walls vary from 4 to 20 centimetres, in thickness.
The cardan suspension
The "cardan suspension", or gimbals, takes its name from Jerome Cardan
(Girolamo Cardano, 1501-1576). But Cardan neither invented the device
nor claimed to have done so. He merely described it in his very popular
book De subtilitate rerum (1550; "The Subtlety of Things"). It appeared in
Europe as early as the ninth century AD; but it was invented in China by
the second century BC at the latest.
This invention is the basis of the modern gyroscope, making possible the
navigation and "automatic pilots" taken for granted in modern aircraft.
Anyone who has been fortunate enough to enter a nineteenth-century
Gypsy caravan will have noticed affixed to the walls the brass gimbals that
hold lamps which remain upright no matter how violently the cart may jolt
on the road. These interlocking brass rings can be moved around as much
as you like, but the lamp suspended in the centre never turns over. This is
the basic idea of the "cardan suspension". A series of rings inside one
another are each joined at two opposing points, enabling them to twist and
turn freely. Consequently, if a heavy weight, such as a lamp, is positioned
upright in the centre, it will remain upright. Whatever motions might occur
to the rings around it will be taken up by the rings themselves, leaving the
lamp unmoved. By the eighteenth century, Chinese mariners were using a
gimbal-mounted compass. A ship's magnetic compass mounted in this way
was free of disturbance by waves.
The earliest textual reference to gimbals which has been found is in a
poem called Ode on Beautiful Women, composed about 140 BC. More
than three centuries later, about 189 AD, the clever mechanic Ding Huan
was given credit for inventing gimbals a second time.
Gimbals reached Europe after 1,100 years. And 800 years after that, the
English physicist Robert Hooke and others adopted its principle in a new
form, applying power from without rather than stabilizing a central
element within, to formulate that Western invention, the universal joint.
And it was this invention which resulted in the transmission of automotive
power in contemporary motor cars. I
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Steel manufacture
The Chinese were the first to produce cast iron, and were also the first to
make steel from cast iron. This was fully under way by the second century
BC at the latest, and eventually led to the invention of the Bessemer steel
process in the West in 1856. Henry Bessemer's work had been anticipated
in 1852 by William Kelly, from a small town near Eddyville, Kentucky.
Kelly had brought four Chinese steel experts to Kentucky in 1845, from
whom he had learned the principles of steel production used in China for
over 2,000 years previously, and had made his own developments.
Iron, when melted and reformed into ingots, has a carbon content. This
determines the nature of the metal as cast iron or steel, whichever the case
may be. Cast iron is brittle because it contains a considerable quantity of
carbon, perhaps as much as 4.5 per cent. "Decarburization" is the removal
of some or all of this carbon. Remove much of the carbon and you have
steel; remove nearly all the carbon and you have wrought iron. The
Chinese used wrought iron a great deal, most notably perhaps in building
large bridges and aqueducts.
The Chinese invented the suspension bridge, often constructing such
bridges with chains whose links were of wrought iron instead of plaited
bamboo. Cast iron was called "raw iron", steel was called "great iron", and
wrought iron was called "ripe iron" by the Chinese. In order to make iron
"ripe", they clearly understood that the iron was losing a key ingredient,
and they described this as "loss of vital juices". But, without knowledge of
modern chemistry, they could not identify the ingredient as carbon.
The Chinese were not the first to make steel. But they did invent two
particular steel manufacturing processes, of which taking the carbon out of
cast iron was the first. The process of "decarburization" was accomplished
by blowing oxygen on to the cast iron ("oxygenation"). We read of this in
the classic Huainanzi, which dates from about 120 BC.
Making steel by this method was also called "the hundred refinings
method", since it was often done over and over again, the steel becoming
stronger each time. Swords made by this method were highly prized. The
back of the sword, not having an edge, would often be made of the more
elastic wrought iron, and the harder steel would be welded on to it to bear
the cutting edge for a sabre. The carbon content of the steel could be
adjusted depending upon how much oxygen was applied to the molten
iron.
Generally speaking, steel with a higher carbon content is stronger, but
then strength is traded against brittleness. Steel can have a carbon content
of between 0.1 per cent and 1.8 per cent. The Chinese could only make
empirical judgments on the qualities of steel obtained from certain num¬
bers of refinings. If very soft steel was desired, they could go on blowing
more oxygen in, removing increasing amounts of the carbon. And they
practised the world-wide technique of quenching, whereby steel that is
cooled instantly in a liquid when still either red- or white-hot preserves its
inner metallic micro-structure which it would lose if allowed to cool
slowly. On the other hand, cooling steel slowly (tempering) has other
advantages. The Chinese were great masters at manipulating their iron
materials in countless different ways to obtain the exact type of metal they
required.
Around the fifth century AD, the Chinese developed the "co-fusion"
process, in which cast and wrought iron were melted together to yield the
"something in between", which was steel. This is essentially the Martin and
Siemens steel process of 1863, though carried out 1,400 years earlier.
The process was in full swing by the sixth century, from which time we
have a Chinese description of it: "Qiu Huaiwen also made sabres of
'overnight iron'. The method was to bake the purest cast iron, piling it up
with the soft ingots of wrought iron, until after several days and nights, it
was all turned to steel."
We are given precise technical details by Song Yingxing in 1637:
"The method of making steel is as follows. The wrought iron is beaten
Chinese 17th-century print showing
artisans forging an anchor weighing
several tons.
12 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
into thin plates or scales as wide as a finger and around four centimetres
long. These are packed within wrought iron sheets and all tightly pressed
down by cast iron pieces piled on top. The whole furnace is then covered
over with mud (or clay) as well. Large furnace piston bellows are then set to
work, and when the fire has risen to a sufficient heat, the cast iron comes to
its transformation [i.e. melts] first, and dripping and soaking, penetrates
into the wrought iron. When the two are united with each other, they are
taken out and forged; afterwards they are again heated and hammered. This
is many times repeated."
In our own time, experiments have been carried out at the steel works at
Corby in the UK to reproduce the ancient Chinese steel-making techni¬
ques. The experiments were thoroughly successful. A very uniform steel
was obtained, with the carbon from the cast iron spread very evenly
throughout, and a genuine blending of the cast and wrought iron. The
original heating went up to 975°C, and the metal was taken out and forged
with a hand hammer. It was then heated for eight hours at 900°C and came
out beautifully.
The chain pump
One of the inventions of the greatest utility which has spread from China
throughout the world, so that its origins are no longer realized, is the
square-pallet chain pump. It consists of an endless circulating chain bearing
square pallets which hold water, earth, or sand.
This pump can haul enormous quantities of water from lower to higher
levels. The optimum angle of slope at which the chain of pallets can be laid
out is about 24°. So, depending on how well the pallets were fitted to avoid
leakage and on the sturdiness of the machine as a whole, the height that
water can be raised by a single pump is about 5 metres.
By medieval times in China, the pumps had been adapted for use as
conveyors of earth or sand rather than just water. They were thus the first
conveyor belts.
We do not know who invented the chain pump, or exactly when.
Although it may have existed some centuries earlier, we can take as its time
of origin the first century AD. The philosopher Wang Chong refers to its
existence about 80 AD in his book Discourses Weighed in the Balance.
Considerable improvements were made to the design during the next
century. We know this from an account in the imperial history of the time,
which discusses the lack of water in the capital, Luoyang. The history tells
us that the famous eunuch minister Zhang Rang (died 189 AD) ordered
various improvements for Luoyang from the engineer Bi Lan:
"He further asked Bi Lan ... to construct square-pallet chain pumps and
suction pumps, which were set up to the west of the bridge outside the
Peace Gate to spray water along the north-south roads of the city, thus
saving the expense incurred by the common people [in sprinkling water on
these roads and carrying water to the people living along them] ...
Chain pumps had achieved a standard form in China by 828. The
imperial history for that year records:
"In the second year of the Taihe reign-period, in the second month ... a
standard model of the chain-pump was issued from the palace, and the
people of Jingzhao Fu were ordered by the Emperor to make a consider¬
able number of the machines, for distribution along the Zheng Bai Canal,
for irrigation purposes."
The pumps were used for civil engineering works and for draining all
sorts of sites, as well as for irrigation and the supply of drinking water. The
pumps were so spectacular in their results that visiting dignitaries and
ambassadors from neighbouring lands eventually adopted them in their
own countries. H
Raising water for irrigation in
17th-century China, using a two-man
treadle-operated chain pump.
_ 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A cybernetic machine
By the third century AD at the latest, the Chinese had a fully operational,
navigational "cybernetic machine", using the principles of feedback. It was
called the "south-pointing carriage", but had no connection with a magne¬
tic compass. It was a large carriage, 3.3 metres long, 3.3 metres deep, and
2.75 metres wide, surmounted by a jade statue of an "immortal" a sage
who had achieved immortality. The figure's arm was raised, pointing
ahead, and it always faced towards the south, no matter which way the
carriage turned. Even if the road were circular, the jade figure would rotate,
keeping the finger pointing in the same direction. How was this possible in
the third century AD? This machine may have been invented even earlier,
indeed, as much as 1,200 years earlier. An official history for 500 AD
describes how:
"The south-pointing carriage was first constructed by the Duke of Zhou
[beginning of the first millennium BC] as a means of conducting home¬
wards certain envoys who had arrived from a great distance beyond the
frontiers. The country was a boundless plain in which people ¡ost their
bearings as to east and west, so the Duke caused this vehicle to be made in
order that the ambassadors should be able to distinguish north and south."
If this information is correct, the invention would date from about
1030 BC. But Needham suspects that the word "carriage" was inserted in
this account by scribes, and that what is being described is a "south-
pointer", that is, a compass.
The next person credited with building a south-pointing carriage is the
astronomer and scientist Zhang Heng, about 120 AD, although this is also
regarded by Needham as doubtful. The only date which he is prepared to
accept with certainty is the middle of the third century AD, with the
famous engineer Ma Jun as the builder (and, thus, the inventor). The
drawing of a pointing figure of jade, taken from the Universal Encyclo¬
paedia of 1601, was copied from a print of 1341.
If the machine did not use a magnetic compass, how did it work? The
answer is that it had a train of differential gears, similar to those in a modern
automobile. Perhaps the function of a differential gear should be explained
as follows. When a wheeled vehicle is turning a corner the wheels on
opposite sides of the vehicle are clearly going to need to turn at different
rates since the near side is travelling a shorter distance than the far side.
With a hand-cart or horse-drawn carriage, this may not pose such prob¬
lems. But when a vehicle has power being applied to the axle to make the
wheels turn, how is it possible for one wheel to be permitted to speed up a
little, and the other slow down a little, on the same axle? This is made
possible only by an ingenious combination of gear wheels and flywheels:
the differential gear.
When Needham published his volume on mechanical engineering in
1965, he believed that the Chinese had invented the differential gear, and
that it had made its first appearance in this south-pointing carriage. If the
first south-pointing carriage were the one attributed to the Duke of Zhou
about 1000 BC, then the Chinese would indeed have been the inventors;
but we must stay on the side of caution, and assume that the first
south-pointing carriage was made in the second or third century AD. In
that case, we must credit the Greeks with inventing the differential gear, a
fact which became known only in 1975, when Professor Derek Price
published his book Gears from the Greeks. In this work Price wrote the
definitive account of a Greek differential gear dating from 80 BC, which
Price said "must surely rank as one of the greatest basic mechanical
inventions of all time". And although a transmission of this invention from
Greece and Rome to China was possible, it is equally possible that the
differential gear was independently re-invented in China for the south-
pointing carriage.
The precision needed in the construction of the south-pointing carriage
almost defies belief. For the outside road wheels alone, Needham points
out, J. Coales, in The Historical and Scientific Background ofAutomation,
"has calculated that a difference of only one per cent between the wheel
circumferences would lead to a change of direction of the pointing figure of
as much as 90 per cent in a distance only fifty times that between the two
	 14 _
Model reconstruction of a "south-
pointing carriage" based on a description
dating from the 3rd century AD. Owing
to a sophisticated gearing system, the
figure's arm always points southwards,
whatever the direction in which the
carriage is moving.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
' **
wheels." This was because the carriage would veer more and more to one
side if one wheel were smaller (relative slip). So that for this south-pointing
carriage, the size of the road wheels had to be accurate to a margin of error
far less than one per cent, and a commensurate accuracy in size of gear
wheels would have been necessary. This points to engineering of such a
high order that we may well be justified in hesitating to apply the words
"ancient" and "primitive" to it!
The south-pointing device was basically a reversal of the use of the
differential gear in the modern automobile. Today, such gears are used to
apply power to turn the wheels and make the vehicle move. But with the
south-pointing carriage, which was pulled by animals, the power was
transmitted from the wheels, and applied towards the continual adjusting
of the position of the pointing figure. Thus it was the differential gear in the
machine which turned the figure so that it always pointed to the south. And
it did so just as the differential gear operates today, only in reverse.
Needham has called the south-pointing carriage "the first homeostatic
machine in human history, involving full negative feedback. Of course, the
driver had to be included in the loop. But as Coales has acutely pointed out,
an attractive carrot held by the pointing figure might have replaced the
human driver and closed the loop more automatically." Although
Needham has occasionally spoken of the south-pointing carriage as the
first actual cybernetic machine, he has qualified this by saying: "The
south-pointing carriage would have been the first cybernetic machine had
the actual steering corrected itself, as we could easily make it do today."
_ 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
'Magic mirrors5
Those who like to think of China as a land of mystery are well served by the
Chinese "magic mirrors", which are some of the strangest objects in the
world, They are known to go back to at least the fifth century AD, though
their exact origins are unknown. About 1,200 years ago, there still existed a
book entitled Record ofAncient Mirrors, which apparently contained the
secrets of these magic mirrors and their construction, but sadly it seems to
have been lost for over a thousand years.
When magic mirrors came to the attention of the West in 1832, dozens of
prominent scientists attempted to discover their secret. It was a hundred
years before a satisfactory theory of magic mirrors was formulated by the
British crystallographer Sir William Bragg.
What exactly, then, is a magic mirror? On its back it has cast bronze
designs pictures, or written characters, or both. The reflecting side is
convex and is of bright, shiny polished bronze which serves as a mirror. In
many conditions of lighting, when held in the hand, it appears to be a
perfectly normal mirror;
However, when the mirror is held in bright sunshine, its reflecting
surface can be "seen through", making it possible to inspect from a
reflection cast on to a dark wall the written characters or patterns on the
back. Somehow, mysteriously, the solid bronze becomes transparent,
leading to the Chinese name for the objects, "light-penetration mirrors".
But surely, the reader will protest, solid bronze cannot be transparent.
This is true, and there was certainly a trick to it. But it was a sufficiently
good trick to baffle Western scientists for a century, and even the earliest
surviving Chinese discussion of magic mirrors consists of speculation on
how they might work. This occurs in a fascinating work, Dream Pool
Essays, by Shen Gua, published in 1086. Even at this date, Shen Gua
thought of the mirrors as coming from some vague archaic period:
"There exist certain 'light-penetration mirrors' which have about twenty
characters inscribed on them in an ancient style which cannot be inter¬
preted. If such a mirror is exposed to the sunshine, although the characters
are all on the back, they 'pass through' and are reflected on the wall of a
house, where they can be read most distinctly.... I have three of these
inscribed 'light-penetration mirrors' in my own family, and I have seen
others treasured in other families, which are closely similar and very
ancient; all of them 'let the light through'. But I do not understand why
other mirrors, though extremely thin, do not 'let light through'. The
ancients must indeed have had some special art .... Those who discuss the
reason say that at the time the mirror was cast, the thinner part became cold
first, while the raised part of the design on the back, being thicker, became
cold later, so that the bronze formed minute wrinkles. Thus although the
characters are on the back, the face has faint lines too faint to be seen with
the naked eye."
Although differences of cooling rate are not the explanation, Shen Gua
was correct in suggesting that the shiny, polished mirror surfaces concealed
Above, the polished reflecting surface
and (top) the ornamented back of a
bronze "magic mirror". When bright
light is projected at the reflecting surface
and the mirror is held sothatitcastsa
reflection on a dark wall, the ornamental
design on the back becomes visible in the
reflection on the wall. The mirror shown
here is Japanese. The characters Takasago
which form part of the ornamental
design refer to the title of a No play.
16 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
minute variations which the eye alone could not detect. Needham says of
the experiments carried out by European scientists: "Careful and extended
optical experimentation demonstrated that the surfaces of 'magic' mirrors
reproduced the designs on the backs because of very slight inequalities of
curvature, the thicker portions being very slightly flatter than the thinner
ones, and even sometimes actually concave."
The basic mirror shape, with the design on the back, was cast flat, and the
convexity of the surface produced afterwards by elaborate scraping and
scratching. The surface was then polished to become shiny. The stresses set
up by these processes caused the thinner parts of the surface to bulge
outwards and become more convex than the thicker portions. Finally, a
mercury amalgam was laid over the surface; this created further stresses
and preferential buckling. The result was that imperfections of the mirror
surface matched the patterns on the back, although they were too minute to
be seen by the eye. But when the mirror reflected bright sunlight against a
wall, with the resultant magnification of the whole image, the effect was to
reproduce the patterns as i/they were passing through the solid bronze by
way of light beams. As Sir William Bragg said when he finally discovered
this in 1932: "Only the magnifying effect of reflection makes them plain."
Needham rightly calls this "the first step on the road to knowledge about
the minute structure of metal surfaces. "
Efficient horse harnesses
A Han Dynasty rubbing
(c. 1st century BC) showing the use of
the trace harness, with its breast strap, to
pull a carriage whose passengers are
protected from the elements by a
precursor of the umbrella.
From earliest times until the eighth century AD in the West (and, as we
shall see, much earlier in China), the only means of harnessing horses was
by the "throat-and-girth harness". It was an absurd method since the strap
across the throat meant that the horse was choked as soon as he exerted
himself. As long as man was restricted to the use of this pathetic harness,
horsepower was all but useless for transport by cart. Even individual riders
could half-strangle their mounts at a gallop.
Those who read about ancient Rome are often struck by the importance
attached to the shipping of grain from Egypt. Without Egyptian grain,
Rome must starve. But why? What was wrong with grain grown in Italy,
_ 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
one asks? Why was Rome dependent on ships from Egypt in order to be
able to eat? The answer is simply that there was no horse harness capable of
making it possible for Italian grain to be transported to Rome.
In about the fourth century BC the Chinese made a great breakthrough.
A lacquered box of the period bears a painting which shows a yoke across
the horse's chest, from which traces connect it to the chariot shafts. Soon,
the hard yoke across the breast was also abandoned and replaced by the
more satisfactory breast strap, commonly called the "trace harness". There
is no longer a strap across the horse's throat; the weight of the load is borne
by the horse's chest and collar bones.
Experiments have been carried out to establish the relative efficiency of
the different types of harness. Two horses harnessed in the throat-and-
girth fashion can pull a load of half a ton. But a single horse in a collar
harness (described below) can easily pull a ton and a half. With a trace
harness the efficiency is only slightly less.
Needham suggests two factors which may have led the Chinese to invent
the trace harness. There was the motivation of the Chinese, Mongols and
Huns living on the edge of the Gobi Desert where they were always getting
stuck in the sand, from which horses using the throat-and-girth harness
could not extricate them. Secondly, there was the use of human hauliers.
Man's own experience of hauling, for example, boats upstream, meant that
he was quickly aware of the inadequacy of a rope round the neck.
The most efficient harness is the collar harness (see drawing this page).
The earliest evidence for the collar harness in China may be seen in a
rubbing from an ancient brick. It dates from some time between the fourth
and first centuries BC. Therefore, we must consider the collar harness as
having been invented in China by the first century BC at the latest. This is a
full thousand years before its appearance in Europe a century after the trace
harness.
After some time, it was found by the Chinese that the collar could be
used in another and simpler way: traces could be attached from the sides of
the collar directly to the vehicle. It is this form of the collar harness which is
used today all round the world.
The stirrup
For most of the time that man has been riding horses, he has had no
supports for his feet. Stirrups were unknown to most of the great armies of
ancient times the Persians and Medes, the Romans, the Assyrians, the
Egyptians, the Babylonians, the Greeks. The horsemen of Alexander the
Great made their way across the whole of Central Asia without being able
to rest their feet while in the saddle. When galloping or jumping, horsemen
had to hold the horse's mane tightly to avoid falling off. The Romans
devised a kind of hand-hold on the front of the saddle which gave them
something of a grip when the going got rough; but their legs just dangled
whenever they were not pressed tightly against the horse.
Mounting a horse without stirrups was not so easy either. Fierce
warriors took pride in their flying leaps, gripping the mane with the left
hand and swinging themselves up; and some bareback riders still do this
today. Cavalrymen of ancient times used their spears to help them up,
either by hoisting themselves aloft as in pole-vaulting, or by using a peg
sticking out of the spear as a footrest. Otherwise it was necessary to rely on
a groom for a leg-up.
By about the third century AD, the Chinese had remedied this situation.
With their advanced metallurgical expertise they began to produce cast
Collar harnest
Bronze stirrup dating from
the 6th or 7th century AD
18 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Tang Dynasty (618-907
AD) porcelain horse,
harnessed for riding.
\
Bronze bit from a
horse's bridle,
China, 5th century BC
bronze or iron foot stirrups. No inventor of the stirrup is recorded and the
original idea probably came from the occasional use of a loop of rope or
leather to assist in mounting. Of course, such loops could not be used for
riding, because if one fell off, one would be dragged along and come to a
sticky end. Such loops may have been first used by the Chinese, the
Indians, or the nomads of Central Asia bordering on China. The essentials
of the stirrup may thus have originated in the steppes, the product of
ingenious men whose lives were lived on horseback. Apparently from the
third century, the Chinese were casting perfect metal stirrups. The earliest
surviving depiction of a stirrup is on a pottery figure of a cavalryman found
in a tomb in Changsha (Hunan) and dated to 302 AD.
The transmission of stirrups westward took place with the migrations of
a fierce tribe called the Ruan-Ruan, who came to be known as the Avars.
Their cavalry was devastatingly effective because they had the use of
cast-iron stirrups. About the middle of the sixth century, they were driven
westwards and moved across south Russia to settle between the Danube
and the Theiss. By 560, the Avars were a serious threat to the Byzantine
Empire, and the Byzantine cavalry was entirely reorganized in order to
counter them. The Emperor Maurice Tiberius prepared a military manual,
the Strategikon, in 580, specifying the cavalry techniques to be adopted. He
mentions the need to use iron stirrups the earliest mention in European
literature.
Stirrups then spread to the rest of Europe by means of the Vikings and
possibly the Lombards. One Avar-style child's stirrup has even been
excavated in London, brought by a Viking. But the use of stirrups in
Europe (other than by the Byzantines and the Vikings) was long delayed,
for reasons which are not entirely clear. Conventional armies of Europe do
not seem to have adopted them until the early Middle Ages. Perhaps the
lack of metallurgical expertise was a handicap, with stirrups having to be of
wrought rather than cast metal for a long time. Mass production of stirrups
was only possible with cast metal.
The segmental arch bridge
A conceptual breakthrough occurred when a Chinese engineer realized
that an arch did not have to be a semi-circle. A bridge could be built which
was based not on the traditional semi-circular arch but on what is known as
a segmental arch. The way to envisage this is to imagine a gigantic circle
embedded in the ground, of which only the tip shows above ground level.
This tip is a segment of a circle, and the arch it forms is a segmental arch.
Bridges built in this way take less material and are stronger than ones built
as semi-circular arches.
This advance took place in China in the seventh century AD. It was the
concept of Li Chun, the founder of an entire school of constructional
engineering whose influence lasted for many centuries. We are fortunate
that his first great bridge, built in 610, survives intact and is still very much
in use today. Called the Great Stone Bridge, it spans the Jiao river near
Zhaoxian at the foot of the Shanxi Mountains on the edge of the North
China Plain.
Four small whole arches were incorporated within the structure of the
main bridge. They were an innovation of great consequence in bridge-
building, for they were the world's first arched spandrels. Li Chun found
that by punching these holes in the ends of the bridge he could accomplish
several things at once: flood waters could rush through them, lessening the
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The Great Stone Bridge spanning the
Jiao river in northern China.
Constructed in 610 AD, it was renovated
in the 20th century and is still in use.
chance that the main bridge would be swept away at its supports in a
sudden flood; the total weight of the bridge could be lessened, thereby
diminishing the tendency to buckle by the ends sinking down into the river
banks; and vast quantities of material could be saved, which would
normally have gone to make solid ends for the bridge.
The Great Stone Bridge has a span of 37.5 metres. The largest surviving
Roman whole arch bridge, the Pont Saint Martin near Aosta, spans 35.5
metres. But the average whole arch Roman bridge spanned between 1 8 and
25 metres, whereas whole arches in Roman aqueducts had an average span
of about 6 metres.
The greatest segmental arch bridge in China is the famous "Marco Polo
Bridge", often so named because Polo described it at length. Just west of
Beijing, it crosses the Yongding river at the small town of Lugougiao, and is
213 metres in length, consisting of a series of eleven segmental arches
extending one after another across the river, each with an average span of 1 9
metres. It was built in 1189 and is still heavily used by modern truck and
bus traffic. Marco Polo thought this bridge "the finest in the world".
20 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
A refined value oí pi
The irrational numberpz can be computed to an infinite number of decimal
places. It expresses the ratio of the circumference of a circle to its diameter,
a relationship which cannot be framed in terms of whole numbers. (Pi is
needed to compute the area of a circle or volume of a sphere.) The value of
pi was computed by Archimedes to three decimal places, and by Ptolemy
to four decimal places. But after that, for 1,450 years, no greater accuracy
was achieved in the Western world. The Chinese, however, made great
strides forward in computing pi.
One way in which the ancient mathematicians tried to approach an
accurate value forpi was to inscribe polygons with more and more sides to
them inside circles, so that the areas of the polygons (which could be
computed) would more and more closely approach the area of the circle.
Thus, they could try to find a value iorpi, since the circle's area was found
by using the formula containing it. (They could measure the diameter, and
squeeze a polygon whose area they knew into the circle; the only unknown
number would be pi, which could then be calculated.) Archimedes used a
96-sided polygon, and decided thatpi had a value between 3.142 and 3.140.
The Chinese tried to sneak up on pi in the same fashion. Liu Hui in the
third century AD started by inscribing a polygon of 192 sides in a circle,
and then went on to inscribe one of 3,072 sides which "squeezed" even
closer. He was thus able to calculate a value oípi oí 3.14159. At this point,
the Chinese overtook the Greeks.
But the real leap forward came in the fifth century AD, when truly
advanced values for pi appeared in China. The mathematicians Zu
Chongzhi and Zu Gengzhi (father and son), by means of calculations
which have been lost, obtained an "accurate" value of pi to ten decimal
places, as 3.1415929203. The circle used for the inscribing of the polygons
is known to have been 10 feet across. This value for pi was recorded in
historical records of the period, but the actual books of those mathemati¬
cians have vanished over the centuries. Nine hundred years later, the
mathematician Zao Yugin (about 1300 AD) set himself to verify this value
of pi. He inscribed polygons in a circle with the enormous number of
16,384 sides. He thus confirmed the value given by the Zu family.
** m
h h % äftoÄü
^v*
As. V\
¥tS-
/ ^J\ tt
f**\A //" «¡*V *-
m
\^K^ /**\ /^v ff ft
m
ftu%ftz%ftznz#
***#EÄ£-**f
£*»***«$#*
XX&trt&IrküJíL ftf
í^t#^^^^'+ Zk
SÜÄi-PI-frÄHÄPI
m*?2*4HïA#ffl* .
Diagram showing a method used by the
Chinese mathematician Liu Hui in
264 AD to calculate the value ofpi.
The decimal system
The decimal system, now fundamental to modern science, originated in
China. Its use can be traced back to the fourteenth century BC, the archaic
period known as the Shang Dynasty, though it evidently was used long
before that.
An example of how the ancient Chinese used the decimal system may be
seen from an inscription dating from the thirteenth century BC, in which
"547 days" is written "Five hundreds plus four decades plus seven of days".
In computation, the Chinese used counting rods on counting boards. To
"write" ten involved placing a single rod in the second box from the right,
and leaving the first empty, to signify zero. To change the ten to eleven, a
single rod was added in the first box. To "write" 111, single rods were
placed in the first, second and third boxes. Apparently from the earliest
times, the decimal place system for numbers was literally i place system;
the Chinese placed counting rods into actual boxes.
The fact that the decimal system existed from the very beginnings of
mathematics in China gave the Chinese a substantial advantage, laying a
foundation for most of the advances they later made.
_ 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
This basin of ytte ware, with a pale green
glaze, is one of the oldest surviving pieces
of porcelain (3rd century AD).
Porcelain
Ordinary pottery is made from clay baked in a kiln at temperatures ranging
from 500°C to 1150°C, and is called earthenware. Porcelain is something
quite different: it consists of a body of fused clay covered by a glaze, a
glassy substance, and is fired at a high temperature about 1280°C. The
secret of making porcelain lies in the use of a pure clay, kaolin or China
clay, which when fired at a sufficiently high temperature changes its
physical composition, a process known as vitrification, and becomes
translucent and totally impervious to water. The reason why China was
able to "invent" porcelain at a very early age compared to the rest of the
world was that the Chinese potters both found the clay and were able to
produce the high temperature necessary to fuse it.
It now seems that archaeological finds push back the date of true
porcelain to the first century AD. By the third century AD, in any case,
true porcelain was undeniably in use.
By the Song Dynasty (960-1279), porcelain had reached a very high
degree of artistry. Porcelain manufacture by this time was a highly
organized trade employing hundreds of thousands of people. There were
teams of men who specialized in washing the clay, others who concerned
themselves only with glazes, others who maintained the kilns, and so on.
One kiln of this period which has been excavated could accommodate
25,000 pieces of porcelain at a single firing. It was built on the slope of a
hill, the gentle incline of about 15° reducing the speed of the flames
through the kiln. The sophistication of the kilns was most impressive.
Some were fired by burning wood, while others were down-draught
burners of charcoal. Control of the firing process was of the utmost
precision. In the Ming Dynasty (1369-1644), when the famous blue and
white ware was largely produced, the best lustrous quality of the cobalt
blue pigment could only be obtained at certain specific temperatures, and
in a reducing (de-oxidizing) flame.
The secrets of porcelain manufacture were jealously guarded, and
visitors from Europe such as Marco Polo could but gape and wonder.
Porcelain objects were still a very great rarity in Europe by the fifteenth
century. They were gifts for kings and potentates. Not until 1520 did the
first sample of kaolin clay reach Europe, brought by the Portuguese.
Europeans then thought that if only they could find deposits of this white
clay, they would be able to make porcelain. But kaolin clay alone is far
from sufficient for the making of porcelain.
The countless experiments carried on with various earths and solid
substances in furnaces eventually had a most unpredictable result. Scien¬
tists and craftsmen began to notice that upon cooling down again, molten
minerals could crystallize. Until this began to be observed, Western
scientists had been convinced that crystals could only be formed from
liquids. About the middle of the eighteenth century in Europe, the idea
began to gain ground that perhaps the Earth's rocks could have been
formed from the cooling of molten masses of lava. In 1785 the geologist
James Hutton presented his revolutionary new theory of the Earth based
on this idea. And so, one of the great scientific advances in the Western
world took place as a direct consequence of the attempts by Europeans to
find the secret of porcelain manufacture.
White porcelain goblet with thick,
finely-crackled glaze. Tang Dynasty
(618-907 AD).
22 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Traditional kilns for firing porcelain
(late-18th-century painting).
Matches
The first version of a match was invented in the year 577 AD by impover¬
ished court ladies during a military siege, in the short-lived Chinese
kingdom of the Northern Qi. Hard-pressed during the siege, they must
have been so short of tinder that they could otherwise not start fires for
cooking or heating.
Early matches were made with sulphur. A description is found in a book
entitled Records of the Unworldly and the Strange written about 950 by
Tao Gu:
"If there occurs an emergency at night it may take some time to make a
light to light a lamp. But an ingenious man devised the system of impreg¬
nating little sticks of pinewood with sulphur and storing them ready for
use. At the slightest touch of fire they burst into flame. One gets a little
flame like an ear of corn. This marvellous thing was formerly called a
'light-bringing slave', but afterwards when it became an article of com¬
merce its name was changed to 'fire inch-stick'."
There is no evidence of matches in Europe before 1530. Matches could
easily have been brought to Europe by one of the Europeans travelling to
China at the time of Marco Polo, since we know for certain that they were
being sold in the street markets of Hangzhou in the year 1270 or there¬
abouts.
A late-18th-century painting of a
Chinese street vendor selling joss-sticks
and matches.
_ 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Biological pest control
Carnivorous ants, used in China for
many centuries to protect mandarin
orange trees from predators.
For 1,700 years, the Chinese have controlled insect pests by biological
means, using one insect to kill another. Perhaps their most striking and
important use of biological pest control was in the use of yellow citrus
killer-ants to protect mandarin trees. Here is how a text of 304 AD, Records
of the Plants and Trees of the Southern Regions, describes the use of the
carnivorous yellow ants:
"The mandarin orange is a kind of orange with an exceptionally sweet
and delicious taste.... The people of Jiaoshi [Tonkin] sell in their markets
[carnivorous] ants in bags of rush matting. The nests are like silk. The bags
are all attached to twigs and leaves which, with the ants inside the nests, are
for sale. The ants are reddish-yellow in colour, bigger than ordinary ants.
These ants do not eat the oranges, but attack and kill the insects which do.
In the south, if the mandarin orange trees do not have this kind of ant, the
fruits will be damaged by many harmful insects, and not a single fruit will
be perfect."
This biological pest control first came to Western attention when a paper
on the subject was published in the North China Herald on 4 April 1882.
But it was not until a serious outbreak of citrus canker occurred in the
Florida citrus groves in the 1910s that a plant physiologist was sent to
China by the US Department of Agriculture in 1915 to search for canker-
resistant oranges, and discovered the citrus ants. In 1958, a Chinese
scientist, Chen Shou-jian, recommended a renewed study of the ants. Their
use in Chinese orange groves continues to this day.
	 24 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Petroleum and natural gas
It is probably a conservative estimate to say that the Chinese were burning
natural gas for fuel and light by the fourth century BC. The deep boreholes
drilled for brine also yielded natural gas from time to time. These methane
gas deposits tended to occur under the brine, but many boreholes, includ¬
ing those intended for brine, yielded only natural gas and were known to
the Chinese as "fire wells". These boreholes were being drilled systemati¬
cally for brine by at least the first century BC, so that deep supplies of
natural gas were tapped from that date by boreholes going down over
1 00 metres. And the systematic search for natural gas itself by deep drilling
is recorded in the second century AD.
Chang Qu in 347 recorded in his book Records of the Country South of
Mount Hua:
"At the place where the river from Bupu joins the Huojing River, there
are fire wells; at night the glow is reflected all over the sky. The inhabitants
wanted to have fire, and used to ignite the gas outlets with brands from
household hearths; after a short time there would be a noise like the
rumbling of thunder and the flames would shoot out so brilliantly as to
light up the country for several dozen li around. Moreover they use
bamboo tubes to 'contain the light', conserving it so that it can be made to
travel from one place to another, as much as a day's journey away from the
well without its being extinguished. When it has burnt no ash is left, and it
blazes brilliantly."
Bamboo pipelines did indeed carry both brine and natural gas for many
kilometres, sometimes passing under roads and sometimes going overhead
on trestles.
The ignition and use of the natural gas for light and fuel posed problems
which were successfully overcome by the ancient Chinese. Old texts
describe in some detail the complicated arrangements which were even¬
tually adopted to control the burning of natural gas. The gas from the "fire
wells" was fed first into a large wooden chamber about 3 metres below
ground level over the mouth of the borehole. It was basically a cone-shaped
barrel into which an underground pipe also conveyed air. The chamber
therefore acted as a great carburettor, feeding into banks of pipes which led
to other smaller conical chambers which rested on the surface of the earth.
These too took in air, with a variety of entry pipes which could be opened
or closed, so that a fine-tuning of the "engine" was possible by a con¬
tinuous manipulation of the fuel/air mixture. If the pressure of the mixture
were to flag, dangerous flash-backs and explosions could occur, so the
main chamber would be opened up further. But fires could result if the
mixture were too rich, so surplus gas was allowed to escape through what
was called a "sky thrusting pipe" exhaust system.
Flames less than 50 cm high were used for other purposes, such as
providing lights in certain Sichuan towns. The gas was also available for
heating in these towns, though details of how it was employed are lacking.
It seems doubtful that proper gas stoves existed, and it is more likely that
the heating applications were generally for cooking and boiling uses.
Other portable heat sources included petroleum products, which often
went under the name of "stone lacquer" because they looked like lacquer
but seeped from the stones.
The domestic uses of petroleum products seem to have been confined to
modest applications such as oil lamps and oil-fired torches, but they were
used on a large scale for breaking up rocks by fire. Since burning oil could
burn in water, boulders in harbours were sometimes broken apart by
having burning oil poured over them.
Well-head and derricks photographed
over 40 years ago in Sichuan Province.
In foreground, the traditional
bamboo pipes which led the natural
gas to nearby towns.
_ 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The mechanical clock
26 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Model of Su Song's great astronomical
clock of 1092. The framework has been
left uncovered to reveal the mechanism.
The original clock tower was 10 m high,
with a power-driven armillary sphere at
the top for observing the stars. Inside the
tower, a celestial globe (B) turned in
synchronization with the sphere. The
central element was the escapement
(D, and detail below), which was turned
clockwise by water or mercury pouring
from the tank on the right.
V'%%
*<%$.
The Chinese did not invent the first clock of any kind, merely the first
mechanical one. Water clocks had existed since Babylonian times, and the
earliest Chinese got them indirectly from that earlier civilization of the
Middle East.
The world's first mechanical clock was built by the Chinese Tantric
Buddhist monk and mathematician Yixing (683-727). This was actually an
astronomical instrument which served as a clock, rather than simply a
clock. A contemporary text describes it:
"[It] was made in the image of the round heavens and on it were shown
the lunar mansions in their order, the equator and the degrees of the
heavenly circumference. Water, flowing into scoops, turned a wheel
automatically, rotating it one complete revolution in one day and night [24
hours]. Besides this, there were two rings fitted around the celestial sphere
outside, having the sun and moon threaded on them, and these were made
to move in circling orbit	 And they made a wooden casing the surface of
which represented the horizon, since the instrument was half sunk in it. It
permitted the exact determinations of the time of dawns and dusks, full and
new moons, tarrying and hurrying. Moreover, there were two wooden
jacks standing on the horizon surface, having one a bell and the other a
drum in front of it, the bell being struck automatically to indicate the
hours, and the drum being beaten automatically to indicate the quarters.
All these motions were brought about by machinery within the casing,
each depending on wheels and shafts, hooks, pins and interlocking rods,
stopping devices and locks checking mutually [i.e. the escapement]".
Yixing's clock was, like water clocks, subject to the vicissitudes of the
weather. In order to keep the water in them from freezing, torches
generally burnt beside them. Therefore, in the next great clock of which we
have accounts in China, mercury was substituted for water because of the
freezing problem. This clock was built by Zhang Sixun in 976 AD. Zhang
Sixun's clock was apparently much larger than Yixing's. It was certainly far
more complex. The dynastic history of the time describes it:
"... a tower of three storeys each over 3 metres in height, within which
was concealed all the machinery. It was round at the top to symbolize the
heavens and square at the bottom to symbolize the earth. Below there was
set up the lower wheel, lower shaft, and the framework base. There were
also horizontal wheels, vertical wheels fixed sideways, and slanting wheels;
bearings for fixing them in place; a central stopping device and a smaller
stopping device [i.e. the escapement] with a main transmission shaft. Seven
jacks rang bells on the left, struck a large bell on the right! and beat a drum
in the middle to indicate clearly the passing of the quarter-hours. Each day
and night [i.e. each 24 hours] the machinery made one complete revolution,
and the seven luminaries moved their positions around the ecliptic. Twelve
other wooden jacks were also made to come out at each of the double-
hours, one after the other, bearing tablets indicating the time..."
All of these efforts were preparatory for the greatest of all Chinese
medieval clocks, the "Cosmic Engine" of Su Song, built in the year 1092.
Su Song's clock was actually an astronomical clock tower more than
10 metres high, like the previous one of Zhang. But on top of Su Song's
tower was additionally a huge bronze power-driven astronomical instru¬
ment called an armillary sphere, with which one could observe the
positions of the stars. A celestial globe inside the tower turned in synchro¬
nization with this sphere above, so that the two could constantly be
compared. We are told that the observations made on the demonstrational
globe inside and by the observational sphere above "agreed like the two
halves of a tally".
On the front of the tower was a pagoda structure of five storeys, each
having a door through which mannikins and jacks appeared ringing bells
and gongs and holding tablets to indicate the hours and other special times
of the day and night. All of these time-indicators were operated by the
same giant clock machinery which simultaneously turned the sphere and
the globe.
Knowledge of the principles of Su Song's clock spreading to Europe led
to the development of mechanical clocks in the West two centuries later.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Paper money
The Chinese invented paper money at the end of the eighth or beginning of
the ninth century AD. Its original name was "flying money" because it was
so light and could blow out of one's hand. The first paper money was,
strictly speaking, a draft rather than real money. A merchant could deposit
his cash in the capital, receiving a paper certificate which he could then
exchange for cash in the provinces. This private merchant enterprise was
quickly taken over by the government in 812. The technique was then used
for the forwarding of local taxes and revenues to the capital. Paper
"exchange certificates" were also in use. These were issued by government
officials in the capital and were redeemable elsewhere in commodities such
as salt and tea.
Real paper money, used as a medium of exchange and backed by
deposited cash, apparently came into being early in the tenth century, in
the southern province of Sichuan, as a private enterprise. Early in the
eleventh century the government authorized sixteen private businesses or
"banks" to issue notes of exchange; but in 1023 the government usurped
this private enterprise and set up its own official agency to issue bank notes
of various denominations which were backed by cash deposits. The money
issued by this bank had printed on it a notice to the effect that it was good
for only three years, and gave the dates. By 1 107, notes were being printed
with multiple blocks in no less than six colours.
The issuing of paper money by the government took on enormous
proportions. By 1126, seventy million strings (each string being equal to
one thousand pieces of "cash") had been officially issued. Vast amounts of
this paper money were not backed by any deposits, and a horrifying
inflation occurred.
Another problem which soon arose was counterfeiting. Since anyone
can print on pieces of paper, the authority must make the processes of
manufacture of its paper money so intricate that they cannot be exactly
reproduced. Complex manufacturing secrets were thus adopted quite
early, and included multiple colourings, immensely complex designs, and a
mixture of fibres in the paper; The basic material for the paper of paper
money was the bark of mulberry trees, and silk was sometimes incorpor¬
ated. One could hand in soiled or worn-out notes for new ones, but had to
pay the small cost of the printing of the replacement.
When the Mongols came to power in China, they issued a quaint form of
paper money called "silk notes". The deposits behind this currency were
not precious metals but bundles of silk yarn. By 1294, Chinese silk notes
were being used as money as far afield as Persia. In 1965, two specimens of
"silk notes" were found by archaeologists.
Paper money under the later Ming Dynasty was not so effective. The
Ming issued in 1375 a new note called the "Precious Note of Great Ming".
It was issued in one denomination only throughout the 200 years in which
it was the legal tender. This was naturally very inconvenient for all
commercial purposes, although copper coins were permitted to circulate,
and these must have provided the small change necessary in everyday life.
Through inflation, the Precious Note gradually lost its value and was
replaced by silver.
This diagram showing knowledge of the
magnetic declination is taken from an
early 10th-century geomantic treatise. It
is entitled The Directions andEmanations
ofthe Floating Needle, that is, the
compass needle floating in a pool of water
or mercury.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Declination of the Earth's magnetic field
The Earth's magnetic field is oriented slightly askew from what might be
expected. The magnetic North Pole is about 1,900 km from the geo¬
graphical true north of the planet. The difference between a finger pointing
at the true geographical North Pole and a compass needle pointing at the
magnetic North Pole is known as the angle of declination or variation; it is
not constant, and continually shifts. By the eighth or ninth century AD at
the latest, the Chinese had discovered this magnetic declination.
As Needham says, in doing so the Chinese were "antedating European
knowledge of the declination by some six centuries. The Chinese were
theorizing about the declination before Europe even knew of the polar¬
ity...." The magnetic compass and the polarity of the Earth's field are not
mentioned in any Western writing until 1 190 AD, and the Chinese had had
the compass for a good fifteen hundred years before that. In his Dream
Pool Essays of 1086, the medieval Chinese scientist Shen Gua wrote on
magnetic declination that "Magicians rub the point of a needle with a
lodestone; then it is able to point to the south. But it always inclines slightly
to the east, and does not point directly at the south. "
The wheelbarrow
The wheelbarrow was apparently invented in south-western China in the
first century BC by a semi-legendary personage called Guo Yu.
The oldest surviving picture of a wheelbarrow dates from about 1 00 AD.
It is a frieze relief from a tomb-shrine excavated near Xuzhou (Jiangsu)
which very clearly shows a wheelbarrow with a man sitting on it. There are
several other illustrations from this period, the Han Dynasty, indicating
that wheelbarrows were increasingly commonplace.
The earliest descriptions of the construction of wheelbarrows are
couched in coy and obscure language. For the first few centuries, wheel¬
barrows were of great military importance, and specifics of their construc¬
tion were closely guarded secrets. Some carried men on seats, and others
carried supplies. They were also used to form protective movable barriers
against cavalry charges. The ingenuity of the Chinese at exploiting the
wheelbarrow was limitless, and they were even given sails, with which they
could achieve speeds over land or ice of 60 kilometres per hour.
A large variety of designs existed, some with wheels in the dead centre,
with the weight resting entirely on the axle, and others with wheels
forward. Some had tiny wheels, some had huge ones. Additional small
wheels were sometimes fitted in front to ease the passage over potholes and
other obstacles. Practically all shapes and sizes of wheelbarrow existed
and still exist in China.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Lacquer
Carved lacquer box in the shape of a
plum blossom decorated with clouds and
dragons. It was produced during the
reign of the Ming Dynasty Emperor
Longqing (1567-1572).
Lacquer was in use by at least the thirteenth century BC in China. Queen
Fu Hao of that date was buried in a lacquered coffin, discovered when her
intact tomb was excavated in 1976 at Anyang. Needham has written that:
"Lacquer may be said to have been the most ancient industrial plastic
known to man."
Lacquer is obtained rather like rubber, by tapping the sap of tree trunks.
The lacquer tree (Rhus vernicifera, recently named verniciflua by bota¬
nists) is indigenous to China but not to Europe. It is particularly common
in central China, growing at altitudes between 900 metres and
2,000 metres. The trees are tapped in summer and left to recover after a
period of five to seven years, though in some cases they are cut down after
tapping, and an inferior lacquer is obtained from their branches. The
largest amount of lacquer a tree can produce is about 50 grams.
Lacquer is a plastic varnish which has remarkable powers of preserva¬
tion, strength and durability. Strong acids and alkalis cannot damage it; it
cannot be affected by heat less than 200°-250°C; it cannot be damaged by
water or other liquids; it is insoluble to most solvents; and it is resistant to
bacterial attack.
Lacquer was used for kitchen utensils thousands of years ago in China.
Wood, bamboo or cloth utensils coated with many layers of thin lacquer
formed the standard dinner service for rich Chinese in place of bronze
vessels. They were able to withstand the heat of cooking and serving of
food as well as metal. Chinese emperors gave lacquered articles to their
officials as recognition for their services, and the monetary value of
lacquerware actually exceeded that of bronzes.
Lacquer was used in China for furniture, screens, pillows and boxes of
all sorts. It was worn as bonnets and shoes. Weapon accessories, such as
sword scabbards, bows and shields were made of it. Lacquers were often
inlaid with gold and silver or tortoiseshell. The fluidity of the lacquered
surface when applied made possible a form of Chinese decoration which
was as free and spontaneous as could be imagined, and this had a major
impact on ancient Chinese art.
The lacquer industry in ancient China was highly organized, in the
traditional Chinese bureaucratic way. There were both private and state
lacquer manufacturing centres. There is a lacquered wood wine cup which
can be dated precisely to the year 4 AD by an extraordinary inscription
which, besides giving the date of manufacture, lists seven artisans involved
in making the cup and five other officials of the company. Twelve people to
produce a single cup, nearly half of them functionaries who perhaps never
A craftsman cuts decorative
incisions in a lacquer bowl
(late-18th-century painting).
30 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
even saw it! But on the other hand, it indicates also the use of something
very like the modern industrial production-line.
As early as the second century BC, the Chinese had made important
chemical discoveries about lacquer. They found a way to keep it from
going hard by evaporation they threw crabs into lacquer to keep it liquid!
Crustacean tissue does in fact contain powerful chemicals which inhibit
certain enzymes, including the one which makes lacquer solidify!
Needham comments on this bizarre affair as follows:
"There can be no doubt that the ancient Chinese, before the second
century BC, had accidentally discovered a powerful lacease inhibitor. ... So
great an interference with the course of nature, analagous to the arrest of a
spontaneously occurring rigidification and ageing process, must have
seemed highly significant to the alchemists, preoccupied as they were by
the preservation of supple youth and the postponement or elimination of
ankylosis and death."
Not only did the perpetual liquefaction of lacquer pose a model for
immortality, in this proto-industrial biochemistry, but lacquer accompa¬
nied a Chinese from cradle to grave he would be fed as a baby from
lacquer vessels with lacquer ladles, and in death he would be buried in a
beautifully ornamented lacquer coffin.
Red lacquer throne of the Qing Dynasty,
dating from the period 1736-1796.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The first contour transport canal
The world's first contour transport canal, the Magic Canal (Lingqu), was
constructed in China in the third century BC. This was indeed a most
impressive pioneering achievement. It was constructed by the engineer Shi
Lu on the orders of the Emperor Qin Shih Huangdi. The impetus for this
innovative type of canal was to assist in supplying the emperor's armies
sent south in 2 1 9 BC to conquer the people of Yue. We are told by the great
historian Sima Qian that:
"[the emperor] sent the Commanders (Zhao) Tuo and Tu Zhu to lead
forces of fighting-men on boats with deck-castles to the south to conquer
the countries of the hundred tribes of Yue. He also ordered the Superinten¬
dent (Shi) Lu to cut a canal so that supplies of grain could be sent forward
far into the region of Yue."
The Magic Canal is just over 32 kilometres long. Its chief interest is thus
not its length, which is unexceptional. The construction of the Magic
Canal, Jinking as it did two rivers flowing in opposite directions, made
possible the continuous inland navigation of barge transport for a distance
of 2,000 kilometres in a direct line, from the 40th to the 22nd parallel. One
could thus sail inland from the latitude of Beijing in the north as far as
Canton and the sea to what is today Hong Kong. The Magic Canal was
the final link in the chain.
The problem that had to be overcome was that the River Xiang with its
source at Mount Haiyang, flowed northwards, while the nearby River Li
flowed southwards. If only one could get a boat from one to the other!
for the Xiang led eventually to the Chang Jiang and the Li joined a tributary
of the West River and led to Canton. Near the little village of Xing'an, the
Xiang and the Li, in a landscape of limestone hills, are only 5 kilometres
apart. Simply joining them was not sufficient. Another solution had to be
found.
There was a saddle in the hills at this point along which a canal could be
dug. The rivers themselves were unruly and a lateral transport canal had to
be dug alongside the Xiang river for 2.4 kilometres at a more even gradient
than the river itself had. At the other end, some 22 kilometres of the Li river
had to be canalized in order to regulate it and make navigation possible.
Only with the two rivers "tamed" at either end like this could a 5-kilometre
canal then be dug to join them. A mound shaped like a snout was
constructed in the middle of the swiftly running Xiang to divide its flow,
and lead off much of the rushing water. It was backed up by two spillways,
and further spillways were made lower down. Several bridges at Xing'an
were constructed to cross the canal, which was 1 metre deep and 4.5 metres
wide. The system of division of the waters and spillways resulted in only
about three-tenths of the water from the Xiang entering the connecting
canal, so that it was not overwhelmed.
By being built along the contours of the saddle in the hills, the canal was
nearly level. Eighteen flash-lock gates were there by the ninth century at
the latest, reducing the number of towers needed for barges by the tenth or
eleventh century. The Magic Canal came to be considered a sacred
waterway, with a dragon as its governing spirit. A modern railway bridge
goes right over the old Magic Canal, which is still used.
This type of articulated junk used for
transporting freight was specially
designed to negotiate the many sharp
bends and shallows of the Grand Canal,
an immense waterway some
1,800 km long which was completed in
the 14th century. The prow and the stern
of the long, narrow boat can be separated
and sailed independently. The mast can
be lowered to enable the junk to pass
beneath low bridges. Below, the Grand
Canal today, at Wuxi.
32 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Immunology
The origins of inoculation against smallpox in China are mysterious. We know that
the technique originated in the southern province of Sichuan, where there is a
famous mountain called Emeishan which is known for its connections with both
Buddhism and Taoism. The Taoist alchemists who lived as hermits in the caves of
that mountain possessed the secret of smallpox inoculation in the tenth
century AD.
The technique first came to public attention when the eldest son of the Prime
Minister Wang Dan (957-1017) died of smallpox. Wang desperately wished to
prevent this happening to other members of his family, so he summoned physi¬
cians, wise men and magicians from all over the Empire to find some remedy. One
Taoist hermit came from Emeishan. This monk or nun brought the technique of
inoculation and introduced it to the capital.
Inoculation has certain dangers which set it apart from the later technique of
vaccination. When one is inoculated, one has the live virus inserted into one's body.
When the process is successful, one is immune for life. But the process can simply
be one of direct exposure to the disease, so that one ends up with smallpox. With
vaccination, the immunity conferred is only temporary, so that vaccinations have to
be given every few years as "boosters". This is because vaccination uses dead viruses
or some other kind of denatured virus (perhaps a related one) which cannot actually
give one the disease.
At first sight it looks as if inoculation against smallpox must have been madness.
Were not people just being given smallpox every time? The answer is no. And here
we find the subtlety of the Chinese inoculators to be truly astounding. They
practised a variety of methods for the attenuation of the deadly virus, so that the
chances of getting the disease were minimized. First of all, there was a strong
prohibition against taking the smallpox material from people who actually had the
disease. The Chinese conceived of inoculation as a "transplant" of poxy material
imagined as being like beansprouts which were just germinating. "To inoculate" in
Chinese was called zhong dou or zhong miao, meaning "to implant the germs", or
"implant the sprouts".
The method used was to put the poxy material on a plug of cotton, which was
then inserted into the nose. The pox was thus absorbed through the mucous
membrane of the nose and by breathing. (The technique of scratching the skin and
putting the pox on the scratch seems to have developed long afterwards, possibly in
Central Asia as the technique spread westwards.)
Ideally, inoculators chose poxy material from persons who had been inoculated
themselves and had developed a few scabs. They also knew the difference between
the two types of smallpox, Variola major and Variola minor, and they chose
material from the latter, which was a less virulent form. Indeed, the favourite source
of material was from the scabs of someone who had been inoculated with material
from somebody who had been inoculated with material from somebody who had
been inoculated.... In other words, a several-generations attenuation of the virus
through multiple inoculations.
But there were other artificial methods used to attenuate the virus even further,
so that it would be safer still. Here is one account from a work on Transplanting the
Smallpox by Zhang Yan in the year 1741:
"Method of storing the material. Wrap the scabs carefully in paper and put them
into a small container bottle. Cork it tightly so that the activity is not dissipated.
The container must not be exposed to sunlight or warmed beside a fire. It is best to
carry it for some time on the person so that the scabs dry naturally and slowly. The
container should be marked clearly with the date on which the contents were taken
from the patient.
"In winter the material has yang potency within it, so it remains active even after
being kept from thirty to forty days. But in summer theyang potency will be lost in
approximately twenty days. The best material is that which had not been left too
long, for when the yang potency is abundant it will give a 'take' with nine persons
out of ten; but as it gets older it gradually loses its activity, and finally it will not
work at all. In situations where new scabs are rare and the requirement is great, it is
possible to mix new scabs with the more aged ones, but in this case more of the
powder should be blown into the nostril when the inoculation is done."
Needham comments on this and similar passages:
"Thus the general system was to keep the inoculum sample for a month or more
at body temperature (37°C) or rather less. This would certainly have had the effect
of heat-inactivating some 80 per cent of the living virus particles, but since their
dead protein would have been present, a strong stimulus to interferon production
as well as antibody formation would have been given when inoculation was done."
In other words, 80 per cent of the smallpox viruses with which the Chinese were
inoculated would have been dead ones which could not have given anyone
smallpox. Instead, they would (as with vaccination) have stimulated the body to
produce antibodies against smallpox.
The concept of vaccination appeared in
China in the 10th century, when
inoculation against smallpox was
practised. Engraving of a child suffering
from smallpox, above, is taken from the
Golden MirrorofMedicine (1743).
Picture credits
Pages 2, 4-5, 8, 10, 33: Photos Rony Heirman © Commissariat
General for Internationa] Co-operation of the Flemish
Community, Brussels/China-Europe Institute, Louvain/China
International Science Center, Beijing. Pages 4, 17,29: Photos©
The MacQuitty Collection, London. Page 5: (below) Photo
British Library, London © Commissariat General for the
International Co-operation of the Flemish Community, Brussels/
China-Europe Institute, Louvain/China International Science
Center, Beijing. Page 6: Photo Rony Heirman ©Commissariat
General for the International Co-operation of the Flemish
Community, Brussels/China-Europe Institute, Louvain/China
International Science Center, Beijing/Nanjing Museum. Pages 7,
20: Photos Paolo Koch©Rapho, Paris. Pages 11,16: Photos
Rony Heirman © Commissariat General for the International
Co-operation of the Flemish Community, Brussels/China-Europe
Institute, Louvain/China International Science Center, Beijing/
Needham Research Institute, Cambridge, UK. Page 12:
Illustration from Tiangong kaiwu (1637). Pages 14-15,26,27:
Photos ©Science Museum, London. Pages 18, 22-23: Photos ©
Ashmolean Museum, Oxford, UK. Pages 19, 22 (below): Photos
©Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Musée Guimet, Paris.
Pages 21,28-29: Documents from Science and Civdisation in
China, Vols. III & IV, by Joseph Needham, Cambridge University
Press, UK. Pages 23 (above), 30 (below): Photos © Aldus Archive,
London. Page 23 (below): Photo ©John Webb, Victoria and
Albert Museum, London. Page 24: Photo © Bruce Coleman,
Uxbridge, UK. Page 25: Photo Cecil Beaton © Imperial War
Museum, London. Page 31 : Photo© Victoria and Albert
Museum, London. Pages 32-33: Photo Georg Gcrster © Rapho,
Paris. Page 34: Illustration from Clerks and Craftsmen in China
and the West by Joseph Needham, Cambridge University
Press, UK.
34 _
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the world
Published monthly in 35 languages by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
A selection in braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda el Khazen
Spanish edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos,
Miguel Labarca
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille edition:
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions:
Solange Beim
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Non-Headquarters editions
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiiehiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Sri Ram (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Brotdo {Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefrallgazer(Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras t Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Abdul Manaf Saad (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: NasirSeham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name.
Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles expr the opinions
of the authors and do not necessarily r¿present the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the
Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Couner staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement oracceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1)
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2)
University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48100, U.S.A.;(3)N.C.R. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A. ; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691 , U.S.A.
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
r n
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco.' publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
ALBANIA. "Ndermarrja e perpjes se librrt'. Tirana. ARGENTINA. Librería el
Correo de la Unesco - EDILYR. SRL, Tucuman 1685. 1050 Buenos Aires
AUSTRALIA. Books only: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd . P O. Box 33.
Brookvale 2100. NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pry. Subscriptions Dept . P O.
Box 33. Brookvale 2100. NSW. Sub-agents: United Nations Association of
Australia, Victorian Division, 328 Flinders Street, Melbourne 3000 Hunter
Publications. 58a Gipps St , Collingwood. Victoria 3066. AUSTRIA. Gerold
and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools Interna¬
tional. Arab Regional Office. P.O. Box 726. Bahrain; The Arabian Agencies
and Distributing Co.. Al Mutanabi St . PO Box 1 56. Manama BANGLADESH
Kanrn International. GPO Box No; 2141. 64/1 Mampuri Para, Teigaon,
Farmgate. Dhaka. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop.
Cave Hill Campus. P.O Box 64, Bridgetown. BELGIUM. Jean de Lannoy, 202
Ave.duRoi. 1060 Brussels BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, PO Box 91
Gaborone. BRAZIL. Fundaçâo Getúlio Vargas. Serviço del Publicaçoes,
caixa postal 9 042-ZC-05 Praia de Botafogo 188. Rio de Janeiro (RJ) 2000;
Books only Imagem Latinoamericana, Av. Paulista 750, 1 andar, caixa postal
30455. Sao Paulo CEP 01051. BULGARIA. Hemus. Kantora Literatura,
boulevard Rousky 6, Soda. BURMA. Trade Corporation no. (9). 550-552
Merchant Street. Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd.. 1294
Algoma Road. Ottawa. Ontario K1B 3W8. {Stores 61 Sparks Street. Ottawa.
21 1 Yonge St.. Toronto. Sales office: 7575 Trans Canada Hwy, Ste. 305. St,
Laurent, Quebec H4T 1V6. CAMEROON. Cameroon Book Centre. PO Box
123. Limbe, Commission Nationale. BP 1600, Yaounde. CHILE. Editorial
Universitaria S A., Departamento de Importaciones, M. Luisa Santander
0447, casilla 10220. Santiago: Editorial Andres Bello'. Av; R Lyon 946.
Casillo 4256, Santiago de Chile; Dipublic. Antonio Varas 671 , 2o piso, casilla
1 4364, Correo 21 , Santiago. CHINA. China National Publications Import and
Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. COLOMBIA. Instituto Colombiano
de Cultura (Colcultura). Carrera 3A, n° 1 8 / 24, Bogota: Books only Librería
Buchholz Galena. Calle 59. No; 13-13. Bogota CYPRUS. 'MAM', Archbishop
Makanos 3rd Avene. PO Box 1722. Nicosia CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S N T.L..
Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1; For, Slovakia only. Alta Verlag.-Publishers.
Hurbanovo nam. 6.893 31 Bratislava; PNS-UED, Jindrisska 14. praha 1;
Slovart. Gottwaldovo Nam 6. 805 32 Bratislava. DEM. REP. OF YEMEN. 1 4th
October Corporation. PO Box 4227, Aden. DENMARK. Wunksgaard Export-
OG. Tidssknftservice, 35 Norre Sogade. DK-1&/0 Kobenhavn K
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Librería Blasco. Avenida Bolivar. No; 402. esq
Hermanos Deligne. Santo Domingo. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). Un¬
esco Publications Centre, No. 1 Talaat Harb St.. Cairo. ETHIOPIA. Ethiopian
National Agency for Unesco. PO Box 2996. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateemmen Kirjakauppa. P. O. Box 128. SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalainen
Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuia 2 01 640 Vaniaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans. Periodicals only Unesco CPD /
V-1 . rue Miollis. 7501 5 Pans GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchex-
port, Postfach 140, Leninstrasse 16, 7010. Leipzig FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY, For the Unesco Courier' Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kuner
Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57. D5300 Bonn 3: UNO-Verlag. Simrockstrasse 23.
D-5300 Bonn 1; S Karger GmbH, Verlag Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2
D-8034 Germering / München. For scientific maps only. Geo Center, Postfach
800830. 7000 Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Books only: Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., PO Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.. PO 7869. Accra:
The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, PO Box 1 . Legon. Periodicals only:
Fides Entreprises. P.O. Box 14129. Accra GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom? GREECE. Eleftheroudakis SA. International Bookstore. 4 Nikis
Street. Athens, John Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers, P O.
Box 10073. 541 10 Thessaloniki. Greek National Commission for unesco. 3
Akadimias Street. Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co . 13-15 Lock
Road. Kowloon; Federal Publications (HK) Ltd.. Tokwawan. Kowloon; Hong
Kong Government Information Services. Publication Section, Hong Kong;
Periodicals only: Beaconsfield House 6th floor . Queen's Road Central. Victor¬
ia HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT. P.O B 149-H-1389. Budapest 62
ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co., H F. Hafnarstraeti 9. Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.. Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038:
17 Chitaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a. Anna Salai. Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd.,
Bangalore 560001: 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad- 500001 Sub-agents:
Oxford Book and Stationery Co , 1 7 Park St., Calcutta 7001 6: Sandia House,
New Delhi 11 0001. INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers. 29.
J1. Oto Iskandardmata 111, Jakarta; Indira P.T.. Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37.
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco. 1 188 Englac
Ave., Rostam Give Building, P O. Box 11365-4498. Teheran 13158
IRELAND. Periodicals only The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., PO Box
43A, Walkmstown. Dublin 1 2; Books only. TDC Publishers, 1 1 North Frederick
Street, Dublin 7. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions, Inc.. c/o Steimatzky Ltd..
P.O. Box 628. Tel Aviv: A.B C. Bookstore Ltd.. P.O Box 1283. 71 Allenby Rd..
Tel Aviv 61000 ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionana Sansoni. S.p.A.), Via
Lamarmora 45. Casella Postale 552. 501 21 Florence: via Bartolmi 29. 201 55
Milan: FAO Bookshop, via délie Terme di Caracalla, 00100 Rome JAMAICA.
University of the West Indies Bookshop, Mona, Kingston 7. JAPAN. Eastern
Book Service Inc.. 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113. JORDAN
Jordan Distribution Agency, PO Box 375, Amman. Periodicals only Jordan
Book Centre Co Ltd..POBox301, Al Jubeiha. Amman KENYA. East African
Publishing House. PO 30571, Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd. Quran
House. Mangano Street. PO Box 45245. Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco. P.O. Box Central 64. Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co.. Ltd. POB 2942. Kuwait; Periodicals only Farafaila Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541. Kuwait LEBANON. Librairie Antoine A Naufal
et Frères. BP 656, Beirut. LESOTHO Mazenod Book Centre, PO Mazenod.
Maseru. LIBERIA National Bookstore, Mechlin and Carey Streets, PO Box
590. Monrovia; Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd , PO Box 286. Monrovia.*
LUXEMBOURG. Books only: Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxem¬
bourg: Periodical Messageries Paul Kraus. BP 1022, Luxembourg. MALAWI
Malawi Book Service, Head Office, PO Box 30044, Chichin, Blantyre 3.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITANIA GRA.LL-
CO MA . 1 rue du Souk X. Avenue kennedy. Nouakchott. MAURITIUS.
Nalanda Company Ltd.. 30 Bourbon St.. Port-Louis. MEXICO. Librería El
Correo de la Unesco, Actipàn 66, Colonia del Valle. Apartado postal 61 164.
06600 Mexico DF. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins. Monte
Carlo. MORROCCO. Librairie 'Aux belles images'. 282 ave. Mohammed-V.
Rabat, Librairie des écoles, 1 2 ave, Hassan-ll, Casaglanca: Société chenfien-
ne de distribution et de presse. SOCHEPRESS. angle rues de Dînant et St.
Saens, BP 13683, Casablanca 05. MOZAMBIQUE. Instituto National do Livro
e do Disco (INLD). avenida 24 de Julho. 1921 r / d Io andar, Maputo. NEPAL.
Sajha Prakashan Poichowk. Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Books only:
Keesing, Boeken B V . Hogehilweg 13. Postbus 1 118, 1000 BC Amsterdam.
Periodicals: Faxon Europe. P.O. Box 197. 1000 AD Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., PO Box 200, Willem-
stad. Curaçao. NA. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box
14277-Kilbirnie. Wellington. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife: The
University Bookshop of Ibadan, PO 286; The University Bookshop ol Nsukka:
The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum, P.OB. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1:
Universitets Bokhandelen. Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem. Oslo
3: Per/od/ca/s on/y: NarvesenA/S.Litteraturt Jenesten, P.O B 6125Etterstad,
N 0602 Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729. Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre. Regional Office for
Book Development m Asia and the Pacific. 39 Delhi Housing Society. P.O. Box
8950. Karachi 29. PANAMA. Distribuidora Cultura Internacional. Apartado
7571. Zona 5. Panama. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store Inc.. 701 Rizal
Avenue. Manila POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No 7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon ROMANIA.
ARTEXIM Export- Im port. Plata Scienten, no. 1, PO Box 33-16, 70005
Bucharest. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan, Olaya Mam Street, Ibrahim Bin
Sulaym Building. Riyadh SEYCHELLES. New Service Lid.. Kingsgate
House, PO Box 1 31 . Mahe: National Bookshop. PO Box 48, Mahé SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay College. Njala University and Sierra leone Diocesan
Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Righteous Enterprises. P O. Box 562.
Kallang Basin Post Office. Singapore 91 33. SOCIALIST PEOPLE'S LIBYAN
ARAB JAMAHIRIYA. General Establishment for Publishing, Distribution and
Advertising. Soul Al Mahmoudi St., PO Box 959. Tripoli SOMALIA. Modern
Book Shop and General, PO Box uàô, Mogadiscio SPAIN. Mundi-Prensa
Libros SA, apartado 1223. Castelló 37. Madrid 1: Ediciones über, apartado
17. Magdalena 8. Ondárroa (Vizcaya): Donaire, Ronda de Outeiro, 20,
apartado de correos 341, La Coruña: books only: Librería Castells, Ronda
Universidad 13 y 15, Barcelona 7; Librería de la Generalität de Catalunya.
Palan Mo|a. Rambla de los Estudios 1 18, 08 002 Barcelona. SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop. 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.O B. 244,
Colombo 2. SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop. P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco. P.O. Box 2943,
Paramaribo. SWEDEN. A/ B CE. Frilzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Regenng-
sgaian 12, Box 16356. S-103 27 Stockholm 16; For the Unesco Courier
Svenska FN Forbundet. Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm; For
periodicals only - Wennergren-Williams AB. Nordenflychtsvagen 70. S-1 04, 25
Stockholm: Esselte Tidskriftscentralen. Gamla Brogatan 26. Box 62 -101, 20
Stockholm SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich; Librairies
Payot in Geneva Lausanne. Basle. Berne. Vevey. Montreux, Neuchâtel and
Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books Establishment, University ol Aleppo.
Aleppo TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. POB. 9030. Dar-es-
Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd.. 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Ave, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company. 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok; ROEAP. PO Box 1425, Bangkok 10500. TRINIDAD AND TOBA¬
GO. National Commission lor Unesco. 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair, Port-of-
Spam. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No 469. Posta Kutusu
21 9. Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. PO Box 7145. Kampa¬
la UNITED ARAB EMIRATES. Maktabat al Maktaba. PO Box 15408. Al Am.
Abu Dhabi. UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office. PO Box 276, London,
SW8 5DT, H.M. S.O. Bookshops in London. Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham, Bristol; Third World Publications, 151 Stratford Road. Birming¬
ham B11 1RD; for scientific maps only McCarta Ltd.. 122 Kings Cross Rd.,
London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. Bernan-UNIPUB.
Periodicals Department, 461 1-F Assembly Drive. Lanham, MD 20706 4391.
URUGUAY. Ediciones Trecho. S.A., Maldonado 1092. Montevideo. USSR.
V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova 39, Moskva 113095.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladosl. Mica 30/11, Zagreb: Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitar-
jeva 2. Lubliana: Nolit. Terazije 13/ VIII. 11000 Belgrade; periodicals only:
Jugosolvena Kniga, PO Box 36. YU 11001 Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare
Imprimé en France (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C 1 -
Octobre 1988.
Photogravure-impression: Mainy-ImprimeurS-A.
Z.I. route d'Eumpcs, 45330 Malesherbes.
ISSN 0041 -5278
N°10-l988-OPI-88-I-461 A
L J
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
! -
f
12 < "
"»«. -,. * -i . ;. ./.
"w'Vt?
]]>
</page>
</document>
