<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="082165eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Nim
rrii g^iThe Courier
HE FRAGILE
FOREST
A
\*
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
January 1989
The sacred tree
byJacques Brosse
10
Why we need forests
12
The fragile forest
(1) The relentless march ofdeforestation
(2) Towards a Green Revolution inforestry
(3) Thefuelwood crisis
by Sandra Postel and Lori Heise
15
Facts and figures
21	
Rings of time
22	
The greenhouse effect
24	
Arboreal oddities
Photos
26
Farming the forest
by Malcolm Hadley
29
'Use them or lose them'
A recipeforsustainable use
oftropicalforests
bylllarMuul
34
The Christianization ofKievan Russia
The Millennium celebrations
by Metropolitan Juvenaly
Cover: Tropical forest in Costa Rica
Back cover: Seven cypresses and twelve branches
symbolize the creation and its eternal truths.
Detail from a mosaic in the Topkapi palace,
Istanbul (Turkey).
^ Watched over by a single, sacred cedar,
the 15th-century monastery of Puktal
in the Himalayas recalls the Tibetan legend
of the first human couple, born of a forest
monkey and the demon of the rock.
Human beings have a natural affinity with trees.
The world's forests cradled our ancestors
and nurtured them with nuts, berries and other
wild fruit. Later, forests provided the fuel
that warmed the cave dwellings of e'arly man
and then provided the materials with which
he made weapons for hunting and defence, built
huts, log cabins and stockades. Long before this,
however, the tree, or at least its ancestors of
the green plant kingdom, had actually created
the conditions which made human life possible.
When the Earth condensed out of a cloud of
interstellar gas and dust, some 4,600 million years
ago, it was surrounded by a dense atmosphere of
cosmic gases made up largely of carbon dioxide
and carbon monoxide. This primordial
atmosphere was stripped away, but as the planet
began to cool and the molten rock solidified,
gases, including water vapour, carbon dioxide
and nitrogen, were given off and a new
atmosphere began to form around the Earth.
This, however, was an atmosphere without
oxygen; indeed, for the first primitive life forms
that began to develop, some 4,000 million years
ago, oxygen was a deadly poison.
Then, about 3,000 million years ago, there
occurred an evolutionary event of crucial
importance the appearance of organisms
that could tolerate the free oxygen they
discharged into the atmosphere as a waste
product of photosynthesis.
From these organisms developed the plants
which are responsible for the oxygen-rich
atmosphere which made possible the evolution of
animal life, including man. We are all, ultimately,
parasites on plants, and in particular on trees,
which are the major contributors of the oxygen
we need to survive. Trees, therefore,
are an essential element in man's life-support
system. If we fail to protect them we shall
ultimately perish with them.
The Courier
A window open on the world 42nd ye;
Published monthly in 35 languages English
French Spanish Russian German
Arabic Japanese Italian Hindi
Tamil Hebrew Persian Dutch
Portuguese Turkish Urdu Catalan
Malaysian Korean Swahili Croato-
Serb Macedonian Serbo-Croat
Slovene Chinese Bulgarian Greek
Sinhala Finnish Swedish Basque
Thai Vietnamese Pashto Hausa
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The sacred tree
Theties that bound the destinies of
men and trees were so strong,
among the peoples of every
continent, that it is natural to feel anx¬
ious about the future prospects of a
human race, that has broken them. Be
that as it may, if an attempt is to be made
to avert the very real danger that defor¬
estation represents for our planet, it
seems necessary to examine, however
briefly, the relationships that existed be¬
tween men and trees until the present
century.
All over the world there lingers on the
memory of a giant tree, the primal tree,
rising up from the centre of the Earth to
the heavens and ordering the universe
around it. It united the three worlds: its
roots plunged down into subterranean
abysses, its loftiest branches touched the
empyrean. Thanks to the Tree, it be¬
came possible to breathe the air; to all
the creatures that then appeared on
Earth it dispensed its fruit, ripened by
the sun and nourished by the water
which it drew from the soil. From the
sky it attracted the lightning from which
man made fire and, beckoning skyward,
where clouds gathered around its
crown, it bade the life-giving rains to
fall. The Tree was the source of all life,
and of all regeneration. Small wonder
then that tree-worship was so prevalent
in ancient times.
In torrid Egypt the sacred sycamore
reigned, and in icy Scandinavia, land of
the Teutons, Ygdrasill, the ash. Acvat-
tha, the pipai (Ficus religiosa) of India, is
identified with Brahman and at its foot
the Gautama Buddha attained Enlight¬
enment. In China, Kien-mou, the "erect
wood", stood at the centre of the empire
and of the world. For the ancient Mex¬
icans, the cosmic tree sprang up in all its
many colours from the belly of the
earth-goddess in the fifth dimension of
space, which unites the upper realm to
the lower. Until recently, the sacred tree
in Africa was the kilena of the Dogon,
the balanza of the Bambara and the ase
of the Dahomans, the ancestral tree, the
abode of the god and of humanity. Some
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
BY JACQUES BROSSE
American communities went so far as to
regard the sacred tree as the place of
their birth.
In most cases, a god uses the tree as his
dwelling on Earth, thereby making it
sacred; sometimes he speaks to human
beings through the medium of the tree.
In Greece the oracle of Dodona was
given by the rustling of the leaves of the
oak of Zeus, which was interpreted by
the priestesses officiating in the sanc¬
tuary. However, just as the gods come
down from the trees, so human beings
can climb them in order to reach the sky
and meet them there. So it is with the
Siberian shaman who goes up into the
birch tree; so it is with the Arunta initi¬
ate who, in Australia, hoists himself up
to the top of the sacred post, in the form
of a tree without branches.
Some trees bore the mark of a particu¬
lar god and were especially revered. But
all trees were considered to possess a
soul. They were inhabited by spirits
whose bodies they formeddryads,
hamadryads and caryatids in Greece,
lechy and roussalki among the Slav peo¬
ples. Hence no cut could be made in a
tree until the tree-spirit had been re¬
quested to remove itself. The felling of
sacred trees was always punishable by
death. Ronsard, the great sixteenth-cen¬
tury French poet, echoed these folk be¬
liefs in his sublime "Elegy Against the
Woodcutters of Gâtine".
The idea of a divine tree naturally
gave rise to a belief in a sacred grove,
which achieved the status of a religious
institution, not only among the Greeks,
Romans and Celts, but also in Iran,
throughout Asia, and in Africa and
America. Vestiges of these sacred groves
still remain in India, China and Japan,
and among the Berbers in North Africa.
In former times there was no other sanc¬
tuary. The sacred grove inspired rever¬
ence and fear and was ringed around
with severe interdictions, but it was also
the place where initiates gathered and
received secret oral teachings from the
priests. The sacred grove was at the
origin of the temple, whose columns
were initially trees, and later of the
Christian church which still evokes it by
the alignment of its pillars, the semi-
darkness within it, and the soft, col¬
oured light that filters through its
stained glass windows.
In former times kings would sit be¬
neath a majestic tree to administer jus¬
tice. Sometimes the sacred tree consti¬
tuted the heart of the city, which it
protected, and although in the process
of urbanization the traces of this belief
nearly always vanished, examples can
still be found in the writings of Anti¬
quity. In the centre of Eridu, the holy
city, the Sumerians of the third millen¬
nium BC worshipped Kiskanu, the cos¬
mic tree. On the Acropolis in Athens
grew the olive tree planted by Athena,
A Bamboo plantation, Anduze, France
^ Rheims cathedral, France
TJ "The Forest of Steel", Helsinki. Memorial
to the Finnish composerJean Sibelius
(1865-1957)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
who had by that means taken possession
of the land and founded the city. In the
forum at Rome grew the fig tree under
whose boughs Romulus and Remus
were suckled. According to Tacitus the
withering of the tree in the year 58 AD
was considered to be of ill omen. The
following year Nero killed his mother
Agrippina and thereafter gave himself
up to a life of unbounded cruelty and
debauchery, triggering a crisis which
almost brought about the downfall of
the Roman empire.
As well as being linked to the destiny
of cities, trees could also be directly
associated with the fate of individuals. A
particular tree would be seen as a per¬
son's double, affording him protection
and communicating to him its vigour
and also, so it was hoped, its longevity,
which far exceeds that of human beings.
All over the world trees were planted on
the occasion of a child's birth, and there¬
after the twins constituted by the child
and the tree would be considered to
share the same fate. Great care was taken
of the tree, for if it withered, the person
would be in danger. Pliny relates that
one famous Roman poured wine at the
foot of his tree in order to fortify it.
In certain traditional societies, this
custom survived into the twentieth cen¬
tury. In some cases the link between a
person and a tree was established when
an attempt was made to heal a sick child
by passing his naked body three times
through a split made in the living wood.
Once a widespread cure for rickets or
hernia, this ritual would usually be car¬
ried out at sunrise, when the tree's ener¬
gy is at its peak. The sick child would
draw on this energy and the tree take the
sickness upon itself. After the ceremony
the edges of the split would be brought
together and sealed with clay. In this
way a lasting affinity was created be¬
tween child and tree. If the gash in the
tree closed up, the child would be cured,
but if it remained open, the sickness
would persist. If the tree died, so would
the child. When he grew up, a child
treated in this way would take great care
of his tree. Nobody else would be
allowed to touch it.
Equally widespread was the belief
that trees harboured the souls of the
dead. Among some peoples, such as the
Warramunga of central Australia, it was
thought that trees served as a refuge for
souls before their reincarnation. The
ancient Egyptians believed that the spir¬
its (ba) of the newly-dead would alight
in the form of birds on the branches of
the sacred sycamore, and that the Lady
of the Sycamore, the cow-goddess
Hathor, would appear among the
foliage and welcome them with water
and bread. But often the souls are iras¬
cible and dangerous. This was the case in
Korea and many other countries, where
only the souls of those who had died a
violent death took shelter in trees.
Elsewhere trees were believed to har¬
bour souls who had been condemned to
remain on Earth in order to atone for
their sins. In his Légendes de la mort en
Basse-Bretagne ("Legends of Death in
Lower Brittany"), the French folklorist
Anatole Le Braz described remarkable
examples of such beliefs as late as- the
end of the last century. Long ago a dead
man was sometimes seen in a tree where
he could be heard moaning and
groaning. Masses then had to be said for
him in the parish church and afterwards
he came to thank the person who had
thus delivered him. Sometimes trees
could be heard walking in the night
towards a house where they again be¬
came the kinsfolk of the proprietor and
warmed themselves at his hearth.
The choice of trees to be planted in
graveyards thus had to be made with the
utmost care. In Brittany the yew was
chosen as the funerary tree whose roots
grew down into the mouths of those
who were buried beneath it. In the
Mediterranean region the funerary tree
is always the cypress, a symbol of
mourning as long ago as the Cretan era,
but also, on account of its shape which
suggests an eternal flame rising heaven-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Above, pipal tree with altar, Kirtipur, Nepal
Fresco in the royal palace, Bangkok, depicting
the "Bodhi" tree beneath which Gautama
Siddhartha achieved enlightenment, to become
the supreme Buddha.
Below, Egyptian goddess Hathor, Lady
of the sacred sycamore
wards, a symbol of prayer and a pledge
of immortality. In China too the cypress
or another evergreen, the pine, were
chosen to be planted over graves.
For our ancestors, who were attentive
observers of Nature, the different
species of tree also corresponded to, and
in a sense illustrated, the rhythm of the
seasons. In Europe there was in ancient
times a tree calendar which the British
poet and scholar Robert Graves suc¬
ceeded in piecing together again in its
most recent form, as it was known to the
Celts when it formed part of the esoteric
teachings of the Druids. However,
Graves showed that the tree calendar
dated from a much earlier period since it
was already familiar to the Greeks in
pre-classical times. The Celtic calendar
was also an alphabet, paralleling in this
the mnemonic techniques used for the
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
purposes of exclusively oral instruction
by those peoples who prohibited writ¬
ing in order to guard against the divulg-
ence of knowledge that was by its nature
sacred and hence secret.
The tree calendar was called Beth-
Luis-Nion, from the names of the first
three trees of the year, Beth, the birch,
Luis, the rowan, and Mow, the ash.
Beth, Luis and Nion were three con¬
sonants in the early Irish alphabet,
which contained thirteen of them, cor¬
responding in Graves' view to names of
trees. The calendar as restored by him
should be set out as follows:
B for Beth, the birch:
24 December-20 January
L for Luis, the rowan:
21 January-17 February
N for Mo«, the ash :
18 February-17 March
F for Fearn, the alder:
IS March- 14 April
S for Saille, the willow:
15 April-12 May
H for Uath, the hawthorn:
13 May-9 June
D for Duir, the oak:
10 June-7 July
T for Tinne, the holly:
8 July-4 August
C for Coll, the hazel:
5 August- 1 September
M for Muin, the vine:
2 September-29 September
G for Gort, the ivy:
30 September-27 October
P for Peith, the whitten:
28 October-24 November
R for Ruis, the elder:
25 November-22 December
The calendar was based on the lunar
year which, consisting of thirteen
months of twenty-eight days, compris¬
ed only 364 days. There thus remained
an intercalated day, 23 December, the
eve of the winter solstice in this calen¬
dar. This was the most ill-omened day
of all because it was then that the year
died. It was consequently represented
by the yew, the death-tree. The follow¬
ing day, however, 24 December, when
the sun begins again to climb towards its
zenith, the time of Christmas and the
birth of the Divine Child, was governed
by the silver fir, the birth-tree.
The trees in the tree calendar were not
chosen at random. Each one was associ¬
ated with the month when it was at the
height of its beauty, in flower or bearing
fruit. Account was also taken of the
correspondence between the symbolic
value of each species and the time of the
year associated with it.
Does any trace remain of this tree
calendar? If February is the only month
to have retained the same number of
days as the lunar month, plus one in¬
tercalated and therefore ill-omened day
every four years, it is because it was
formerly the month of great purifica¬
tions whereby preparations were made
for the rebirth of the vegetation and the
approach of more clement weather.
May gave its name to the may tree,
generally the 'hawthorn, as in the tree
calendar, which was planted all over
Europe on the occasion of festivities
among village communities, in order to
celebrate the triumph of spring over
winter. And as for the silver fir of
24 December, it has become our
Christmas tree.
Man's brief passage on Earth is symbolized by
this illustration from an Etruscan vase, right.
Man is seen poised between the tree of life
and the tree of death.
Below, the tree, symbol of Christ, flanked by
two horses representing believers. Roman
mosaic in the Bardo Museum, Tunis.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Maya Indians of Central America believed that the Ceiba, or silk cotton tree (below), was
the first tree and the source of all life.
îL. W
What lessons can be drawn from this
multiplicity of beliefs whose universal
character we have just seen? If we con¬
sidered trees to be divine, attributed
souls to them and treated them as mod¬
els for human beings, would we not be
yielding to superstitions from another
age, to obscure, outdated beliefs un¬
worthy of a civilization that purports to
be rationalistic, scientific and strictly
materialistic? In fact, however, it is the
scientists themselves who are beginning
to call into question this dismissive atti¬
tude. In the 1920s, an eminent Indian
physiologist and botanist, Sir Jagadis
Chandra Bose, demonstrated by experi¬
ment that plants have a real sensibility
and a capacity for memorizing which
correspond to a very rudimentary form
of mental life. His experiments have
since been verified and supplemented by
American and especially by Soviet sci¬
entists. In other words, the watertight
divisions that, in the name of an exces¬
sive rationalism, were thought to exist
between plants and animals, and be¬
tween animals and human -beings,
appear unfounded. In a less controver¬
sial area, phytotherapists and ethnobo-
tanists are at present regaining accept¬
ance for traditional plant remedies,
virtually abandoned not so long ago,
many of which derive from trees. In
many cases it can even be said that
certain superstitions of bygone days
are now acknowledged to be based on
real observation.
The Swiss psychologist and psychi¬
atrist Carl Gustav Jung (1875-1961)
showed that the image of the tree still
survives as an archetype in the indi¬
vidual and collective unconscious. In¬
deed, it is one of the most fertile, vital
and universal symbols. In a time of crisis
like the present, it is in himself that man
might usefully rediscover the meaning
of that image and at the same time re¬
cover a sense of union with Nature, of
cosmic harmony which, unhappily for
him, he has often lost.
JACQUES BROSSE, French naturalist and
writer, has published several books on trees and
tree myths. One of them, Les arbres de France:
histoire et légendes, won the 1988 Pierre Delbès
Prize, which was established in memory of a noted
French agronomist and plant ecologist and is
awarded annually for a book which contributes to
the study and preservation of the environment.
Jacques Brosse's latest work, Mythologie des
arbres, will be published this year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The Gray Tree (1912), oil on canvas by Piet Mondrian. Haags Gemeentemuseum, The Hague (Netherlands).
Why we need forests
The conservation and management of
tropical forests are matters of vital impor¬
tance for the peoples of the countries in
which they are situated (some 1 ,600 mil¬
lion people, about a third of the world's
population, live between the Tropics of
Cancer and Capricorn).
With their unique diversity of plant and
animal life, tropical forests represent an
immense, renewable source of food, fibre,
medicines and fuel. If properly managed
they can provide a wealth of useful prod¬
ucts and values.
They provide timber and paper and are
an important source of foreign currency
earnings for tropical countries.
The inappropriately-named minor forest
products (all products other than timber)
can also be of considerable commercial
importance. Rattan, for example, has án
estimated annual value in world trade of
$1,200 million and tends to benefit local
villagers much more directly than many
timber operations.
Other forest products include bamboo,
resins, food, medicinal plants, phar¬
maceutical products, mushrooms and
honey. One conservative estimate values
the annual trade in these products at
$10,000 million.
Tropical forests fulfil other important
functions. They help in the regulation of the
quality and flow of water and they protect
soils from erosion. They are also of great
cultural, spiritual and aesthetic signifi¬
cance to the peoples of the tropics.
Forests are of concern to the world com¬
munity as a whole. They affect the climate
by helping to maintain the Earth's temper¬
ature and are a significant element in the
Earth's carbon budget.
The rare trees and plants of which they
consist constitute a gene pool whose value
has only just begun to be explored in the
search for drugs to cure some of man¬
kind's most serious diseases.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Human beings grew up in forests; we
have a natural affinity for them. How
lovely a tree is. straining toward the sky.
Its leaves harvest sunlight to photo-
synthesize (...) Trees are great and
beautiful machines, powered by sun¬
light, taking in water from the ground
and carbon dioxide from the air, con¬
verting these materials into food for
their use and ours. The plant uses the
carbohydrates it makes as an energy
source to go about its planty business.
And we animals, who are ultimately
parasites on the plants, steal the car¬
bohydrates so we can go about our
business. In eating plants we combine
the carbohydrates with oxygen dis¬
solved in our blood because of our
penchant for breathing air, and so ex¬
tract the energy that makes us go. In
the process we exhale carbon dioxide,
which the plants then re-cycle to make
more carbohydrates. What a marvel¬
lous co-operative arrangement -plants
and animals each inhaling the other's
exhalations, a kind of planet-wide,
mutual, mouth-to-stoma resuscitation,
the entire elegant cycle powered by a
star 150 million kilometres away.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The fragile forest
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
BY SANDRA POSTEL AND LORI HEISE
(1) The relentless march of deforestation
Before the dawn of agriculture,
some 10,000 years ago, the
Earth boasted a rich mantle of
forest and open woodland covering
some 6,200 million hectares. Over the
centuries, a combination of land clear¬
ing for crop production, commercial
timber harvesting, cattle ranching and
fuelwood gathering has shrunk the
Earth's forests to some 4,200 million
hectares a third less than existed in pre-
agricultural times.
For centuries, this reduction in the
Earth's biological stock hindered hu¬
man progress little, if at all. Indeed, the
clearing of trees to expand food produc¬
tion and the harvesting of forest pro¬
ducts were vital aspects of economic and
social development. But the relentless
loss of tree cover has recently begun to
impinge on the economic and environ¬
mental health of numerous nations,
mostly in the developing world. Large-
scale reforestation, combined with con¬
certed efforts to protect remaining
forests, now appears essential to im¬
proving the human prospect.
Most tree planting efforts over the last
several decades have aimed at increasing
supplies of marketable timber, pulp and
fuelwood for cities forest products
that yield obvious economic benefit. By
contrast, reforestation for reasons that
lie outside the monetized economy has
been vastly under-attended. Yet trees
quite literally form the roots of many
natural systems. With the inexorable
march of deforestation, the ecological
integrity of many areas is dis¬
integrating severe soil loss,
aggravating droughts and floods, dis¬
rupting water supplies and reducing
land productivity.
Trees are also a vital component of the
survival economy of the rural poor.
Hundreds of millions of people rely on
gathered wood to cook their meals and
heat their homes. For them, lack of ac¬
cess to wood translates into reduced
living standards and, in some cases,
directly into malnutrition. In addition,
trees and soils play a crucial role in the
global cycling of carbon, the importance
of which has been magnified by the
emergence of carbon dioxide-induced
climate change as arguably the most
threatening environmental problem of
modern times.
Efforts to slow deforestation certain¬
ly deserve redoubled support. But even
if forest clearing miraculously ceased
today, millions of hectares of trees
would still have to be planted to meet
future fuelwood needs and to stabilize
soil and water resources. Increased
planting to satisfy rising demands for
paper, lumber and other industrial
wood products is also crucial. Expand¬
ing forest cover for all these reasons will
reduce pressures on remaining virgin
forest, helping thereby to safeguard the
Earth's biological diversity. At the same
time it will mitigate the build-up of
atmospheric carbon dioxide, which
gives industrial countries sound reason
to step up support for tree planting in
developing countries.
Successfully reforesting large areas of
degraded lands, however, will require
much more than financial commitments
from governments and international
lending agencies. It will take a shift in
emphasis from government foresters
establishing and maintaining commer¬
cial plantations to the much more com¬
plex tasks of starting nurseries in
thousands of villages and encouraging
the planting of multi-purpose trees
along roads, on farms and around
houses. Only by garnering the know-
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
ledge, support and human energy of
rural people themselves -and planting
to meet their basic needs is there any
hope of success.
Dramatic changes in regional forest
cover historically reflect powerful
societal transformations. Beginning in
the sixteenth century, the expanding
agricultural and industrial needs of Re¬
naissance societies spurred the clearing
of large tracts of forest in Western
Europe. France, once 80 per cent for¬
ested, had trees covering only 14 per
cent of its territory by 1789. Both the
French and the English so depleted their
domestic forest resources that they were
forced, by the mid-seventeenth century,
to conduct a worldwide search for ship
timbers in order to maintain their mari¬
time superiority. Similarly, forest cover
in what is now the contiguous United
States totalled some 385 million hec¬
tares in 1630, around the time when the
Pilgrim Fathers arrived. As colonization
spread along the eastern seaboard and
gradually westward, forests dwindled.
By 1920, trees covered 249 million hec¬
tares, more than a third less than when
European settlement began.
Despite growing recognition of the
importance of forests to the economic
and ecological health of nations, sur¬
prisingly little is known with certainty
about the state of forest resources today.
Many countries have not fully inventor¬
ied their forests and the data that do
exist vary widely in quality. A 1982
study by the United Nations Food and
Agriculture Organization (FAO) still
provides the best information available
on tropical forests, even though much of
the data is more than a decade old. Com¬
bining FAO's estimates with those of a
1985 forest assessment by the United
Nations Economic Commission for
Europe and with various individual
country reports yields a rough picture
of the global forest resource base.
Closed forest, where the shade from
tree crowns prevents substantial growth
A forest plantation in Borneo, Indonesia. Plantation forestry is slowing, but not preventing,
deforestation. FAO reports that in the early 1980s 1 1.3 million hectares of tropical forest were
cleared annually, while only 1.1 million hectares of plantations were established.
ft ¿
:^*sw*/<;?i»«*BJfo
. »
Pine trees affected by acid rain ¡n the Vosges
mountains, France. Some 31 million hectares
of forest in central and northern Europe show
signs of damage from acid rain and other forms
of atmospheric pollution.
of grass, covers nearly 3,000 million
hectares worldwide. Another 1,300 mil¬
lion hectares are open woodlands, in¬
cluding, for example, the wooded
savannah of Africa and the cerrado in
Brazil. Collectively, forested lands cover
approximately 4,300 million hectares, an
area almost triple that in crops. Shrub-
land and forest regrowth on temporarily
abandoned cropland bring the total area
supporting woody vegetation to more
than 40 per cent of the world's land.
The most worrisome finding of
FAO's assessment was that tropical
trees were being cut much faster than
reforestation or nature were replacing
them. For tropical regions as a whole,
11.3 million hectares were cleared
annually in the early 1980s, while only
1.1 million hectares of plantations were
established. Thus ten hectares were
being cleared for every one planted. In
Africa, the ratio was twenty-nine to
one; in Asia, five to one. Even these
alarming figures probably under¬
estimate the extent of forest loss in par¬
ticular regions, since tree planting is
often highly concentrated, while cutting
is widespread.
Recent data for individual countries
suggest that forest cover trends in some
regions are even bleaker than FAO's
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
FACTS AND FIGURES
sobering assessment indicates. Satellite
imagery of five States in Brazil, for ex¬
ample, shows that deforestation in parts
of the Amazon has proceeded much
faster than estimates for the entire re¬
gion suggest. Likewise, LANDSAT
data released by the National Remote
Sensing Agency of India reveal that
India's forest cover declined from 16.9
per cent in the early 1970s to 14.1 per
cent in the early 1980s, an average loss of
1.3 million hectares per year. Fortu¬
nately, reforestation is also proceeding
somewhat faster than official estimates
suggest. Spontaneous tree planting by
villagers around farm fields, as wind¬
breaks, or along roadways is frequently
not counted. Indeed, forestry statistics
typically ignore "trees outside of
forests", even though in many areas
they are the primary source of fuel-
wood, fodder and rural construction
materials. In Kenya, for instance, the
number of trees planted by villagers ex¬
ceeds the number established in govern¬
ment plantations. And in Rwanda, scat¬
tered trees planted by rural people col¬
lectively cover some 200,000 hectares,
more than the combined area of the
country's remaining natural forest and
all State and communal plantations.
Nonetheless, the loss of forest cover
in tropical countries remains rampant.
Conversion of forest to cropland is by
far the leading direct cause. Population
growth, inequitable land distribution
and the expansion of export agriculture
have greatly reduced the area of crop¬
land available for subsistence farming,
forcing many peasants to clear virgin
forest to grow food. These displaced
cultivators often follow traditions of
continuous cropping that are ill suited
to fragile forest soils. Eventually, the
soils become so depleted that peasant
colonists must clear more forest to
survive.
Indigenous "shifting cultivators"
clear new fields every few years, allow¬
ing forest regrowth to restore soil fertil¬
ity before they return to clear and plant
again several years later (see article page
26). But even this once sustainable prac¬
tice is being undermined as population
pressures force farmers to recultivate
It is estimated that each year between
11 and 15 million hectares of tropical
forest (an area larger than Austria) are lost.
Tropical forests, which cover only
7 per cent of the world s land area, contain
over half the known plant and animal spe¬
cies, including 80 per cent of insects and
90 per cent of primates.
Half the world's main crops originated in
tropical forests.
25 per cent of drug prescriptions in the
United States owe active ingredients to
plants, but under 1 percent of species
have been investigated It is thought that
about 1 .400 forest plants may have anti¬
cancer potential.
50.000 square kilometres of closed tro
pical forest are logged annually. Loggers
take only between 4 and 10 per cent of
trees, but leave up to one third of the land
surface bare and open to erosion.
80 per cent of all forest lands are owned
by governments.
Europe accounts for 40 per cent of glob¬
al trade in tropical timber by volume and
32 per cent by value.
Over half the European imports of tropic¬
al timber are used for building and joinery.
The remainder goes mostly for plywood,
furniture, transport, packaging and water
resistant pilings.
Data from the Work) Wildlife Funds Special Report
on Conservation ol Tropical Forests
The establishment of logging camps and access roads can involve the destruction of large numbers
of commercially valueless trees.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
In Latin America large areas of tropical
forest are cleared each year to create pasture for
cattle ranching.
land before it has recovered. FAO esti¬
mates that the breakdown of traditional
shifting cultivation patterns is responsi¬
ble for 70 per cent of closed forest clear¬
ings in tropical Africa, nearly 50 per cent
in tropical Asia and 35 per cent in tro¬
pical America.
Population pressures have also trans¬
formed fuelwood collection into an un¬
sustainable practice. Given a choice,
villagers generally gather dead wood
and branches for fuel; they only cut live
wood if nothing else is available or if
they are converting wood to charcoal
for urban markets. Fuelwood collection
is thus an agent of forest destruction
primarily in the arid woodlands of
Africa, where population density is high
and the natural growth rate of vegeta¬
tion is low, and around large cities of
Asia and Africa, where concentrated de¬
mand over-taxes available tree stock.
Recent LANDSAT data show that in
less than a decade forest cover within
100 kilometres of India's major cities
dropped by 15 per cent or more; Delhi
lost a staggering 60 per cent.
Consumer demand in temperate
countries also fosters tropical forest de¬
pletion. Industrial countries' appetite
for tropical hardwoods has encouraged
many governments of developing coun¬
tries to "mine" their forests to earn vital
foreign exchange. As loggers fell com¬
mercially valuable tree species-which
sometimes account for less than 5 per
cent of any given hectare they often
destroy between 30 and 60 per cent of
unwanted trees as well. Roughly two-
thirds of the logging and the
damage-has occurred in Southeast
Asia, although logging is" likely to in¬
crease in Latin America as Asian forests
become depleted.
One additional agent of forest des¬
truction operates in Latin America the
lure of cattle ranching. Between 1961
and 1978, pasture in Central America
expanded 53 per cent, while forests and
woodlands declined 39 per cent. Much
of this conversion was driven by US
demand for cheap beef, although in re¬
cent years Central American beef ex¬
ports have dropped in response to de¬
clining US beef consumption. Similarly,
by the late 1970s an estimated 1.5 mil¬
lion hectares of pasture had been estab¬
lished in the Brazilian Amazon. In 1979,
Brazil eliminated some of the incentives
that had spurred clearing for pasture;
alas, forest clearing continues as a way
of establishing claims in Brazil's highly
speculative land market.
Pressures on temperate forests have
waned substantially following several
centuries of clearing for agriculture.
Forest cover in most European coun¬
tries is now fairly stable; in some it has
even been increasing as marginal agri¬
cultural land reverts to woodland and as
conscious efforts are made to plant
trees. Since the early 1960s, government
and private plantings in the United
Kingdom have increased net forest cov¬
er an average of 30,000 to 40,000 hec¬
tares per year. In France, forest area has
risen substantially from its historic low
of 14 per cent in 1789. About a quarter
of the country is now forested.
Unfortunately, chemical stresses
from air pollution and acid rain today
place a substantial share of European
forests at risk. Trees covering some
31 million hectares in central and north¬
ern Europe are showing signs of damage
linked to air pollutants. Scientists do not^
know how extensive the damage will
become, but it could substantially offset
recent gains made in expanding the con¬
tinent's forested area.
As in Europe, forest cover in the con¬
tiguous United States was comparative¬
ly stable during most of this century,
following the loss of 136 million hec¬
tares between 1630 and 1920. During
the last two decades, however, forest
area has declined as widening grain ex¬
port markets encouraged conversion of
forest to cropland and as urban and
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
industrial development encroached on
woodland. In 1982, forests covered
233 million hectares of the contiguous
States a 10 per cent drop from 1963 and
less than existed in 1920, the previous
low point.
In the developing countries, nothing
in prospect suggests that forest cover
will stabilize any time soon as it has in
many industrialized countries. The
forces behind deforestation remain
strong and planting efforts are woefully
inadequate to reverse the loss of tree
cover.
More than two-thirds of all people
in the developing countries rely on wood
for heating and cooking.
European bison in the Berezinskiy Biosphere
Reserve (Byelorussian SSR). Forests are home
to several million plant and animal species,
and as forests- whether tropical, temperate
or boreal-are cut down or disturbed, more
and more of these species are threatened
with extinction. European bison used
to abound in the virgin forest that centuries
ago stretched from the Baltic Sea to the River
Bug. Relentless overhunting and forest
destruction by successive waves of invaders
brought the European bison to the verge of
extinction. In a notable co-operative effort,
5 of the few bison that remained in the part
of the forest on Polish territory were handed
over to the Byelorussian authorities. Today
several hundred bison flourish in the security
of the Belowezhskaya puscha, the oldest forest
reserve in Europe, and the Berezinskiy
Biosphere Reserve.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE FRAGILE FOREST
(2) Towards a Green Revolution
in forestry
Nature employs a wide variety of
methods for expanding tree
cover-coconuts that float between
tropical islands, aerodynamic seeds and
luscious fruits that attract animal carriers.
Strategies equally diverse and ingenious are
needed to mobilize human energy and finan¬
cial resources for tree planting sufficient to
satisfy fuelwood needs, stabilize soil and wa¬
ter resources and slow the carbon dioxide
build-up.
Tree planting programmes are most effec¬
tive when local people are involved in their
planning and implementation and perceive
their own interest in success. If fodder is a
critical need, for example; a project that pro¬
motes a non-browsable species like eucaly¬
ptus will receive little popular support. Design¬
ing a reforestation project without local input is
like letting a doctor prescribe treatment with¬
out asking the patient what hurts.
A number of tree planting programmes are
meeting with considerable success. In Haiti a
project to encourage agroforestry and tree
farming has included planting more than
27 million seedlings between 1982 and 1986.
Around the world, women's associations,
peasant collectives and church groups have
taken up tree planting; in Kerala, India, alone,
some 7,300 organizations are involved.
In Kenya, the Greenbelt Movement, spon¬
sored by the National Council of Women of
Kenya, has involved more than 15,000 far¬
mers and half a million schoolchildren in
establishing 670 community nurseries and
planting more than two million trees.
In 1 985, annual planting in China doubled to
eight million hectares, giving renewed cause
for optimism. Tree survival rates that had
averaged only 30 per cent may also be im¬
proving. China seems unlikely to achieve its
ambitious target of 20 per cent forest cover by
the year 2000, but the combination of in¬
creased planting and better management, if
sustained, could mean the nation's tree cover
resumes its upward trend.
The late 1 985 launch of the Tropical For¬
estry Action Plan holds promise of elevating
forestry to its rightful place among develop¬
ment priorities. Jointly sponsored by FAO,
UNDP (the United Nations Development
Programme), the World Resources Institute
and the World Bank, the Action Plan calls for
accelerated investments of $8,000 million
over five years in tree-planting projects and
efforts to arrest deforestation.
In his development agenda for 1985 to
1990, Indian Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi
assigned forestry a central place. He almost
tripled funding for forestry, reorgan¬
ized his Ministries to give forestry
new prominence and created" a National
Wastelands Development Board to
spearhead a "people's movement for
afforestation".
What is needed in the coming decade is an
effort somewhat akin to the agricultural Green
Revolution of the 1960s; a dedication to de-
A forestry officer explains details of an FAO-
assisted forestry development project
to villagers near Kathmandu, Nepal.
veloping genetically improved tree species
and to extending widely the technical and
financial resources for reforestation. For¬
estry's Green Revolution, however, needs to
promote indigenous tree species and diversi¬
fied agroforestry systems and must strive to
benefit marginalized populations, including
the landless. Accelerated planting that does
not benefit the poor only masquerades as
success.
A tree-planting campaign in Lesotho
undertaken by the local population.
ms*m*
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
THE FRAGILE FOREST
(3) The fuelwood crisis
Lacking fuelwood, this Zimbabwean woman
uses maize residue to cook a meal.
ENERGY planners in developing
countries face a markedly diffe¬
rent set of challenges over the
coming decades than their counterparts
in industrial countries. Many of the de¬
veloping countries remain tightly wed¬
ded to wood as a primary energy source,
either in its raw form or after conversion
to charcoal. As wood supplies in the
countryside and around cities continue
to dwindle, growing numbers face a
deepening energy crisis. Even after
more than a decade of increasing recog¬
nition of the problem, only halting
progress has been made towards satis¬
fying future fuelwood demand.
More than two-thirds of all people in
the developing countries rely on wood
for cooking and heating. Rural dwellers
depend on wood almost exclusively,
even in oil-rich Nigeria. In many
countries including most of
Africa-wood not only dominates
household energy use, it provides more
than 70 per cent of energy used for all
purposes.
According to the United Nations
Food and Agriculture Organization
(FAO), in 1980 nearly 1,200 million
people in developing countries were
only managing to meet their fuelwood
needs by cutting wood faster than it was
being replaced. Nearly 100 million
people half of them in tropical
Africacould not meet their minimum
needs even by over-cutting the wood¬
lands around them. FAO projected that
by the year 2000 the number of people
lacking wood or over-cutting would
reach nearly 2,400 million, more than
half the projected developing-world
population.
The human and ecological costs of
wood scarcity are already high. In rural
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
parts of the Himalayas and the African
Sahel, women and children spend be¬
tween 100 and 300 days a year gathering
fuelwood. Boiling water becomes an
unaffordable luxury and quick-cooking
cereals replace more nutritious but
slower-cooking foods, such as beans.
Where fuelwood is critically scarce,
people often have no choice but to di¬
vert dried dung and crop residues from
fields to cookstoves, a practice that
diminishes soil fertility and depresses
crop yields. In Nepal, for example, this
diversion reduces grain yields an esti¬
mated 15 per cent.
Rapid urbanization will only magnify
the ecological consequences of increas¬
ing fuelwood scarcity. City dwellers
tend to rely on charcoal rather than
wood because its light weight makes it
more economical to transport from the
countryside. When wood is converted
into charcoal in traditional earthen pits,
more than half the primary wood ener¬
gy is lost. This means that every villager
who moves to the city and switches
from wood to charcoal equals, in energy
terms, two people. Even though urban
areas have traditionally been less depen¬
dent upon fuelwood, urbanization
In Kenya, charcoal is the preferred fuel
for city-dwellers. An improved model (left)
of the traditional/iiostovecancut a Nairobi
household's fuel costs by as much as 50 per cent.
could soon make cities pivotal to
national fuelwood strategies. Indeed,
the World Bank estimates that by the
year 2000 the urban areas of West Africa
will account for 50 to 70 per cent of the
region's total fuelwood consumption.
Experts generally agree that a success¬
ful strategy to meet the fuelwood needs
of the developing countries- must in¬
clude increasing the productivity of
natural forests by making better use of
wood now wasted, including logging
residues and trees cleared for cropland,
by raising the efficiency with which the
wood is burned and by planting more
trees. The World Bank has calculated
that fuel substitution and the use of
more efficient kilns and cookstoves
could reduce fuelwood need's in the year
2000 by about a fourth. Eliminating the
remaining gap between projected sup¬
ply and demand would require planting
the equivalent of 55 million hectares of
high yielding fuelwood plantations, or
2.7 million hectares per year, given a
base year of 1980. If the needed number
of trees were planted less intensively on
farms, around houses and in woodlots,
planting efforts would involve an area at
least four times as large. Actual planting
for fuelwood has averaged about 550
hectares annually, a fifth of what is
needed.
More than a decade of experience
with so-called communal and farm for¬
estry projects has shown clearly that
inspiring large-scale planting of trees is
no easy task. The international donor
community rightly recognized during
the 1970s that villagers in developing
countries themselves formed the only
labour force large enough to plant trees
on the vast areas needed. In many cases,
however, rural people were reluctant to
participate in communal planting be¬
cause they had no idea how the resulting
benefits would be shared. Perhaps the
greatest lesson of the first generation of
fuelwood projects was that villagers
were rarely motivated to plant trees ex¬
clusively for fuelwood.
To outside observers it seems irra¬
tional for people faced with an energy
crisis to be reluctant to plant trees for
fuel. But for most rural dwellers in de¬
veloping countries, fruit, poles, fodder
and shade are higher priorities. They
know that wood, in the form of trim¬
mings and dead branches, will be a
secondary benefit of plantings for these
other purposes. Moreover, people do
not always perceive the national "fuel-
wood gap" that so concerns energy
planners. They may be cutting wood
over and above a sustainable level, yet
still not be experiencing an unacceptable
shortage. And in rural areas where fuel-
wood is not part of the cash economy,
the cost of increasing scarcity is mea¬
sured in women's time, something that
may have little value to male decision¬
makers.
The key to mobilizing villagers is to
promote multi-purpose trees that meet
their immediate needs while also in¬
creasing the woody biomass available
for fuel. Particularly promising is the
potential of agroforestry the com¬
bined production of crops and trees
to raise crop yields while providing
fuelwood and other useful products.
Nitrogen-fixing trees planted in shel-
terbelts or interspersed with crops, for
example, can enhance soil fertility,
increase soil moisture and reduce
erosion.
Agroforestry programmes offer a
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
number of advantages over more tradi¬
tional approaches to addressing the fuel-
wood crisis. They typically cost only 10
to 20 per cent as much as government-
established fuelwood plantations.
Although yields per hectare may be
higher in plantations, agroforestry often
results in greater wood production per
planted tree. Through pruning tech¬
niques known as coppicing and pollard¬
ing, a single tree can yield five to ten
times the wood volume that a plantation
tree would yield upon felling. And in
contrast to communal woodlot projects,
agroforestry does not pose problems
with shared work loads, division of be¬
nefits or the displacement of other pro¬
ductive uses of common land, such as
grazing.
Of course, agroforestry does not
address the fuelwood needs of the mil¬
lions of rural people who do not own
land. Traditionally they have had to col¬
lect wood from common lands or steal it
from forest reserves. Providing fuel for
the landless may well be the greatest
energy challenge facing governments in
developing countries today.
In India, the Government of West
Bengal addressed this problem by allo-
In parts of the African Sahel, women
and children spend up to 300 days a year
gathering fuelwood.
In addition to the many other benefits
they bestow upon mankind, trees pro¬
vide us with an accurate natural calen¬
dar and climatic record.
Many species of tree produce a ring of new
wood every year. The width of the ring (i.e.
the amount of growth) for each year is
determined partly by internal, genetic fac¬
tors and partly by external factors such as
soil and, particularly, climatic conditions. In
a bad year, poor growth is reflected in a
narrow ring, whereas a wide ring indicates
favourable climatic conditions and good
growth. All trees of one species within a
particular area tend to show similar pat¬
terns of rings.
This makes it possible, for example, to
establish the date that a particular tree was
felled by comparing the pattern of rings of
its stump with that of a living tree in the
same forest. A 200-year-old tree will have
a pattern for one hundred of its rings in
common with a tree of the same species
that was cut down one hundred years ago.
By making use of such overlapping pat¬
terns and by studying wood from ancient
buildings and trees preserved in bogs and
fenlands, dendrochronoiogists (scientists
who study the chronological sequence of
annual rings in trees and aged wood) have
succeeded in establishing master chrono¬
logies which, for certain areas, go back to
about 5000 BC.
RINGS OF TIME
Master chronologies enable archaeolo¬
gists and historians to date with accuracy
buildings of which there are no written
records and to see how climatic conditions
varied from one part of a particular area to
another. They also provide a means of
verifying the accuracy of Carbon- 1 4 dating
methods.
z'-UÊl
m
%::Z¿>~:
¿¡ :'
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THE GREENHOUSE
EFFECT
Carbon dioxide in the atmosphere
has an important effect on world
climate. It lets through most of the
short-wave energy directed at the Earth by
the Sun, but retains a high proportion of the
long-wave energy radiated back by the
Earth out toward space. This is known as
the "greenhouse effect", by analogy with
the garden greenhouse whose glass win¬
dows admit solar radiation, but partially
trap the infra-red radiation re-radiated from
within. This causes the temperature in a
greenhouse to rise to a higher level than
that of the free air outside.
Because of the rise in carbon dioxide con¬
centration in the atmosphere (from
265 parts per million in 1850 to 340 parts
per million in 1985), due primarily to the
combustion of fossil fuels (e.g. coal, oil and
natural gas), scientists predict that signifi¬
cant changes in climate patterns will occur
by the end of the century. They foresee a
rise in average global temperature of be¬
tween 3° and 5° Centigrade before the
year 2010.
Temperature increases in the Polar re¬
gions could be three times the global aver¬
age, which would result in rapid melting of
the Polar ice caps. Sea levels could rise by
as much as 5 to 7 metres causing flooding
of vast areas of low-lying land.
Trees normally act as a sink for carbon
dioxide, which they "inhale", returning
oxygen as waste to the atmosphere as
they "exhale". However, when trees are
cleared or burned, the carbon they con¬
tain, as well as some of the carbon in the
underlying soil, is oxidized and released to
the atmosphere. Since 1860 some 90 to
180 thousand million tons of carbon has
been released to the atmosphere as a
result of forest clearing, as compared with
150 to 190 thousand million tons from the
burning of coal, oil and natural gas.
Many scientists consider the warming of
the atmosphere as posing one of the most
serious environmental threats to man. And
forest clearance is doubly harmful since
not only is the carbon "sink" effect of trees
lost, but more carbon is released to the
atmosphere.
IK
'JL .J
A charcoal kiln at the Subri River Forest
Reserve, Ghana. Waste wood from forest
clearing that was once burned is now converted
into charcoal.
eating more than 5,000 hectares of de¬
nuded forestland to landless families for
cash-crop tree farming. Though families
were not ceded title to the land, they
were granted ownership of the trees. To
encourage participation, the Forest De¬
partment supplied free seedlings, ferti¬
lizer, technical assistance and insecti¬
cide, and it offered small cash incentives
based on the number of trees surviving
after three years. The families harvested
the wood for sale after five years and
with the proceeds bought small parcels
of land suitable for farming. While the
trees matured, villagers collected twigs
and branches for fuel. Where a strong
commercial market for wood exists and
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
¿
f
~-
crucial. Such efforts will never com¬
pletely solve the fuelwood crisis as
population growth would soon outstrip
even the most ambitious dissemination
programme. But improved stoves can
benefit individual households while col¬
lectively relieving pressures on natural
woodlands until tree planting pro¬
grammes take hold.
Particularly promising are prospects
for reducing wood consumption in
cities, where rising wood and charcoal
prices provide a powerful incentive to
invest in efficiency. An improved model
of the traditional charcoal jiko in Kenya
can halve fuel use. For the average
Nairobi family spending 170 shillings
(about S8.35) a month on charcoal, the
stove pays for itself in just two months.
In rural households, where wood is
gathered rather than purchased, no
direct economic advantage exists to
boost wood-burning efficiency. Yet
women, who spend much time collect¬
ing wood, have an incentive to construct
improved stoves if they can do so from
free, locally available materials. A par¬
ticularly successful programme in
Burkina Faso promotes an up-graded
version of the traditional three-stone
cookstove, surrounded by a cylindrical
shield made of mud, dung and chaff.
The new model cuts wood use by 35 to
70 per cent, takes only half a day to
make and costs virtually nothing.
SANDRA POSTEL and LORI HEISE are senior
researchers with Worldwatch Institute, Washing¬
ton, D.C., a non-profit research organization
which was created to focus attention on global
problems and is funded by private foundations
and United Nations organizations. The above
article and those on pages 13 and 18 have been
extracted from State of the World 1988: A World-
watch Institute Report on Progress Toward a
Sustainable Society (W.W. Norton, New York/
London, 1988).
/ .-Jv
sufficient degraded forestland is avail¬
able, such a strategy can bring non¬
productive land into use while provid¬
ing the landless with both fuelwood and
added income. Meeting future fuelwood
needs will depend as much on managing
demand as on increasing supply. Many
policies that could significantly reduce
demand attack the broader economic
and social conditions that underlie fuel-
wood shortages. If birth rates today in
Africa were no higher than those in
Asia, for example, Africa's demand for
fuelwood forty years from now would
be reduced by as much as 30 per cent.
Improving the efficiency of cook¬
stoves in developing countries is also
Pollarded alders, Nagaland State, north-eastern
India. Through pruning techniques known
as pollarding and coppicing, a single tree can be
made to yield five to ten times the volume
of wood a plantation tree would yield on felling.
Tv
.. &4
i
VÍ.OS
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Arboreal oddities
The biggest tree (1)
The largest single living objects on Earth
are the Sequoia Pines (Sequoiadendron
giganteum) growing in the Sequoia National
Park, California. The largest of them, known
as the General Sherman, stands 83 metres tall
and has a true girth (at 1.53 metres above
the ground) of 24.11 metres.
The smallest tree (2)
Bonsai (a Japanese word meaning "tray-
planted") trees are ordinary trees and shrubs,
not hereditary dwarfs, that are dwarfed by
pruning their roots and branches. Average-size
bonsai trees grow to a height of around
60 centimetres, but miniature bonsai may be
a mere 5 centimetres tall.
... ¿j£L_ i K-». ~- -3
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The oldest tree (3)
The oldest known living tree is a 4,600-year-old
bristlecone pine (Pinus longaeva) named
Methuselah, growing in the Sierra Nevada,
USA. Photo shows a bristlecone pine
at the Inyo National Forest, California.
The trees with the largest girth (4)
Baobab trees hold the record for tree girth.
Their barrel-shaped trunks may measure up
to 10 metres in diameter.
The fortress tree (5)
In olden days the people of the villages
of Kimré, Mode and Bordo, in Chad, built
fortresses for defence against marauding bands
in the huge branches of the kapok tree (Ceiba
pentandra). The illustration is from an account
of an expedition by the German explorer
Gustav Nachtigal (1834-1 885).
The oak tree with two chapels
in its trunk (6)
Next to the church at Alouville-Bellefosse, near
Yvetot, in the Seine-Maritime Department
of France, stands an oak tree (Quercus robur)
over a thousand years old within whose hollow
trunk two chapels have been constructed. In
1698, the lower chapel (below) was dedicated
to Notre Dame de la Paix.
'%:
5
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
BY MALCOLM HADLEY
Farming the forest
Fire is a tool used extensively in the tropics in the shifting agriculture cycle. Above, a plot being burned prior to planting.
Shifting cultivation has for centur¬
ies been practised successfully,
and with no harmful environ¬
mental effects, by root-crop farmers of
the humid tropics and by dry-rice culti¬
vators of the forested hill regions of
Southeast Asia.
Though it has many variations, this
widespread form of agriculture, also
known as swidden or slash-and-burn
agriculture, basically involves clearing
small areas of forest for crop planting by
cutting down and burning trees and
vegetation. The ash acts as a fertilizer
and the plot is relatively free of weeds.
After a few years of cultivation,
however, the fertility of the land de¬
clines and weeds increase. The shifting
cultivators then move on .to another
area, abandoning the plot to natural re-
growth and recuperation during a fal¬
low phase before returning to the same
plot a number of years later.
Traditional cyclical shifting agricul¬
ture is based on sound ecological princi¬
ples and in the past represented a sus¬
tainable use of the forest. In India, this
jhum cycle, as it is called, used to stretch
over thirty years or more, which gave a
reasonable time for recovery of the
forest and the soil as well as yielding
acceptable returns to the farmer. The
enure jhum operation involved efficient
recycling of resources to maximize
yields, by such means as using crop and
weed residues as organic manure and as
feed in swine husbandry.
However, increased population
pressure (in northeast India population
more than quadrupled between 1900
and 1975) and reduced land area due to
site degradation have forced farmers to
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
resort to very short jhum cycles of only
four or five years. In turn this has
accelerated the land degradation spiral,
further slowed the recovery of soil fer¬
tility and diminished economic returns.
Rapid population growth in many
tropical areas, combined with the many
other social and ecological changes that
have occurred over the past two de¬
cades, has been accompanied by a re¬
lentless increase in the rate and extent of
forest clearing and the intensity of forest
exploitation. Small-scale cultivators,
estimated to number some 250 million,
cause final elimination of around
five million hectares of forest a year and
serious degradation of a further ten mil¬
lion hectares. Although these farmers
are well aware that their activities are
harmful both in general terms and in
terms of their own long-term prospects,
they have nowhere else to go and no
alternative employment outlets.
Because of the rapidity of these
changes, it is important that more effec¬
tive, sustainable forest exploitation be
linked with development that benefits
people who live in or near the forest and
who make use of it. Attempts to achieve
these objectives have, however, been
hampered by lack of information on
how people in various parts of the tro¬
pics interact with the forest and how
they respond to changing economic
opportunities.
Under Unesco's Man and the Bio¬
sphere (MAB) Programme, several field
studies have been made to investigate
this problem. One of these studies, con¬
ducted in East Kalimantan, Indonesia,
produced some unexpected results.
The remote interior Apo Kayan
plateau is the homeland of several
thousand Kenyah people who live in
long-house communities and practise
forest-fallow shifting cultivation. The
study revealed that, far from being the
reckless destroyers of forest that they
had long been thought to be, the
*?*
Crops growing in a clearing created by the "slash-and-burn" technique. Borneo, Indonesia.
Weed invasion under a short shifting agriculture cycle. The plot is covered with Mikania michantha,
a weed which contributes to the regeneration of soil fertility.
I
mi
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Kenyah people maintain, tend and re¬
use sites. For the last 200 years at least,
there has been a fairly consistent con¬
servative pattern of forest exploitation.
In the Apo Kayan, the Kenyah have
converted the virgin forest into a mosaic
of secondary forest of different ages plus
unfelled reserves where they can harvest
products that are rare or non-existent in
secondary forest.
Most swiddens (sections of forest
cleared for agriculture by cutting and
burning) are created on more fertile
soils, on slopes of intermediate grade,
and in secondary forest eight to twenty
years old, with primary forest reserves
being maintained close to the villages.
Results of studies on the seed bank
(the seeds actually present in the soil), of
sampling of one- to four-year-old fields
and of surveys of secondary forest, pro¬
vide consistent evidence that shifting
cultivation at Apo Kayan is a forest-
maintaining agricultural system. Those
tree species common in secondary forest
seem to be particularly well adapted to
regeneration after shifting cultivation
because they re-sprout or their seeds
survive burning.
Many of the cyclical agroforestry sys¬
tems studied to date in the tropics have
been those practised by relatively re¬
mote tribal groups that are largely out¬
side the chain of active commerce. This
suggests that such systems of resource
management are suited only to subsist¬
ence production. However, recent in¬
vestigations carried out by a number of
independent researchers indicate that
they can also be important cash pro¬
ducers.
One study examined a market-
oriented system practised by farmers at
Tamshiyacu, Peru. The Tamshiya-
quinos are a non-tribal group, some
2,000 strong, of mixed Amazonian and
European ancestry, living about
30 kilometres southeast of the regional
market centre of Iquitos. They engage in
a large number of agricultural and ex¬
tractive activities, exploiting a wide vari¬
ety of the land and water resources
available to them.
The techniques used by the Tam-
shiyaquinos include the farming of up¬
land sites under both high forest and
fallow growth of varying ages, the cul¬
tivation of seasonally inundated, low-
lying sites, as well as fishing, hunting
and the extraction of a variety of forest
products. Foods, fibres, handicraft
materials and charcoal are among items
obtained from the fields and forests of
Tamshiyacu that appear on the local
market and the urban market of nearby
Iquitos.
The agroforestry cycle begins with
the cutting of the standing vegetation. In
secondary forest areas, the Tamshiya-
quinos cut down the vegetation but do
not burn it in the typical slash-and-burn
fashion. Instead, the larger woody
vegetation is usually converted into
charcoal.
After clearing, a variety of crops, such
as corn, rice and cow-peas, are planted.
Some of these crops are re-planted dur¬
ing the second year, together with a
number of other crops such as manioc
and peanuts, and a start is made on the
planting of fruit and nut trees.
Annual crop production is gradually
phased out after an initial two- to five-
year period. Fruit and nuts from the
trees become the most important source
of income from the plot and production
may continue for twenty-five to fifty
years if the fields are protected from
cattle. At first, fruit and nut crops are
picked from selected trees, but this is
One stage in a long shifting agriculture cycle:
the ground has been cleared but tree stumps
have been left in situ.
gradually reduced in frequency to once
or twice a year, just before the harvest of
the Umari, the most important tree
crop. As soon as production drops sig¬
nificantly (after between about twenty-
five and fifty years) the larger items of
vegetation (the Umari and the Brazil nut
trees) are cut down and converted into
charcoal.
Following this second round of char¬
coal-making, the field is generally
allowed to Jie fallow for six years or so.
Secondary growth invades the plot and,
according to local farmers, begins to
restore it so that another production
cycle can be set in train.
Most households have several agro¬
forestry fields operating at any one time.
Since these are in different stages of the
production cycle, farmers tend to obtain
an income from the sale of a variety of
resources. This limits the risks inherent
in specialization, spaces out the need for
often scarce labour and assures house¬
holds of some cash flow throughout the
year.
The limited observations so far made
indicate that, thanks to their cyclical
agroforestry methods, the Tamshiya-
quinos enjoy some of the highest aver¬
age annual incomes to be found among
rural dwellers of the region. In one sur¬
vey of thirteen villages in the Iquitos
region, some Tamshiyacu households
were found to have gross yearly in¬
comes of nearly $5,000, and the mean
for village households, some $1,200,
was still above average.
The results of these people/environ¬
ment studies highlight a way forward in
the search for an improved basis for
ecologically sound development in the
tropics that of integrating the re¬
source-based knowledge of local people
(in such areas as multiple-cropping and
the manipulation of swidden fallows)
with modern technological know-how
in flexible ways that are capable of
adapting and being adapted to changing
social and economic circumstances.
.
<^*,
m$m
MALCOLM HADLEY is a staff member of Un¬
esco's Division of Ecological Sciences. A zoolo¬
gist, he is responsible for the co-ordination of
activities in the humid tropics within Unesco's
Man and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
BY ILLAR MUUL
'Use them
or lose them5
A recipe
for sustainable use
of tropical forests
The gaur (Bos gaurus), a forest-dwelling bovine of Malaysia
Current estimates indicate that
about half the world's tropical
rain forests have already dis¬
appeared. The remainder are rapidly
being destroyed. Much of the blame for
this has been placed on the demand for
timber by industrialized countries. But
it seems that only about 15 per cent of
the felled trees are exported. World tim¬
ber demand has actually declined some¬
what in recent years and many timber
producing countries are finding that
only the most desirable wood, such as
species used for expensive veneers, is
worth cutting and hauling out of the
forests. Unfortunately, hundreds of
trees of lesser value are destroyed to get
access to the expensive trees, and the
building of roads, loading areas and log¬
ging camps destroys large tracts of
forest.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Watering seedlings at the tree nursery
of a forestry rehabilitation and diversification
project in north-eastern Thailand.
Another major cause of forest des¬
truction is a variety of agricultural
schemes. Tropical rain forests are quite
tolerant of limited traditional shifting
agriculture (see article page 26) and have
a great capacity to regenerate if not
over-exploited. But, when forests are
totally cut and replaced by monocul¬
tures, in many areas the relatively poor
soils cannot support more than a few
years of harvest. Rain washes away the
thin layer of topsoil. The harsh sun
bakes the remaining soil until it is too
hard to absorb the torrential rains of the
monsoons. Flooding occurs down¬
stream and hydroelectric generating
dams and irrigation schemes become
clogged with silt. Climatic changes
occur, accentuating the differences be¬
tween seasons with too much rain and
those with too little.
All these are sound ecological argu¬
ments for action to conserve the world's
remaining tropical rain forests. But with
rapidly rising populations hungry for
food and land, crippling foreign debt
repayments to make and with the terms
of trade turning against them, the de¬
veloping countries within whose terri¬
tories these forests lie have more im¬
mediate economic and social problems
to resolve. In these circumstances they
have little option but to attempt to sell
yet more timber and to clear more forest
for agricultural use even though they
know this to be against their long-term
interest.
How can these long-term assets be
saved? It needs to be demonstrated that
sustainable use of tropical forests will
provide more local and national income
than clear-cutting and low productivity
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
agricultural schemes, and that forest
conservation must be coupled with eco¬
nomic development.
The exhortations of conservationists
for further research need to be linked to
action to provide alternatives to present
misuse. The contribution of the tropical
rain forests to the maintenance of local
term profit. The goals are to protect the
species diversity that exists in those
forests and to expand the land areas
under protection. ICR's work is sup¬
ported by Unesco's Man and the Bio¬
sphere (MAB) Programme, which first
proposed the conceptnow accepted
by most conservation-oriented
A A forestry extension officer shows a member
of a commune in Hunan Province, China,
the correct method of planting tea oil seeds.
-^ Logs for export float down a river in Borneo,
Indonesia
climatic patterns, particularly rainfall
that maintains agricultural productivity,
needs to be convincingly demonstrated.
Above all, the economic payoff must be
immediate to forestall continuing des¬
tructive use of the forests.
Integrated Conservation Research
(ICR), a US ecological group, has
launched a series of programmes in
Malaysia and China which are aimed at
demonstrating that rain forests are more
valuable if used on a sustainable basis
than if cut down for immediate, short-
groups of coupling economic develop¬
ment with conservation.
The economic development aspect of
the ICR programmes is divided into
three main areas of effort: agroforestry,
ethnobotany, and natural history-
oriented tourism.
Increasing numbers of tropical eco¬
logists are becoming convinced that
multiple species communities are more
likely to survive and be more productive
than monocultures. This idea is fun¬
damental to agroforestry. An excellent
example of this in a very simple "com¬
munity" is to be seen in the Southern
Yunnan Province of China.
Rubber has been successfully grown
in Xishuangbanna, far north of its major
distribution in Southeast Asia.
However, in an unusually cold year,
many of the rubber trees died. Intensive
research resulted in a decision to plant
the rows of trees farther apart than is the
usual practice in areas farther south, to
allow better air circulation at the tree
bases. This enhanced tree survival be¬
cause lethal fungus, encouraged by cold
and damp conditions, did not reach
harmful levels.
Between the rows of trees, tea was
planted in order not to waste the space.
The tea plants became more productive
under the partial shade of the rubber
trees. The vegetation "community"
(two species) also supported a "commu¬
nity" of more than one hundred species
of spider. These were more efficient
than spraying in eliminating the pest
species of insect that feed on tea plants.
Money was saved by not spraying, the
product was cleaner and environmental
contamination with insecticides was
eliminated.
ICR will attempt to combine many
species in agroforestry schemes, includ¬
ing traditional and new food plants,
medicinal plants, commercially valuable
timber, fuel wood, and newly domesti¬
cated animals.
The most striking among the animals
is a species of forest-dwelling cattle
known as the gaur (Bos gaurus). These
magnificent animals are nearing extinc¬
tion as forests disappear and render
them more vulnerable to hunters. Their
meat is highly prized, low in cholesterol
and comprises 65 per cent of the carcass,
which often weighs nearly two metric
tons. Mohd Khan, the Director-General
of Wildlife and National Parks in
Malaysia, is very concerned about these
unique animals and has developed a pro¬
gramme for captive breeding to reintro¬
duce them to areas where they have
become extinct. He is also interested in
developing domestic strains for beef
production.
The Department of Veterinary Sci¬
ences in Malaysia has a programme of
hybridization of the gaur with domestic
cattle. The hybrids grow 60 per cent
faster than domestic cattle. The pure
breeds may, however, have an advan-
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
tage, partly because they are very heat
tolerant. They are the only species of
bovid that sweats. Moreover, their
sweat contains repellents against flies,
ticks, and other ectoparasites, which
means that they are less susceptible to
infectious diseases carried by these
parasites.
The most important characteristic of
this species, however, is that it does not
require grass for food. It is a browser ol
forest edge plant species. Consequently,
forests do not need to be destroyed to
propagate it. The forests are capable of
supporting herds of limited size without
irreversible damage to species diversity.
Embryo transplants into domestic cattle
are planned to accelerate the breeding
programme. Research support for this
programme is being provided by the
Smithsonian Institution's National Zoo
in Washington, D.C., and the Henry
Doorley Zoo in Omaha, Nebraska.
Plants used in traditional medicine
will also be used in the agroforestry
schemes. One plant, in the Trillium
group, is used by inhabitants of Yunnan
to help heal wounds, cure ulcers, and
stop bleeding after childbirth. The
Kunming Institute of Botany, at
Xishuangbanna, China, has isolated the
active ingredients from these plants.
Analyses have revealed their chemical
structure, and work is continuing on the
testing of the effects of these materials
and on the genetics and propagation of
the plants, which grow only in the
forests. Prospects for their commercial
propagation in agroforestry schemes are
very promising.
Schemes such as these attempt to de¬
monstrate the nature of the forest as a
resource. With research and education,
the productivity of these areas can be
diversified as the economic potential of
new species comes to light.
ICR'S programmes also involve natu¬
ral history-oriented tourism. Most peo¬
ple are interested in Nature, and natural
history tourism offers a potential source
of income at the national as well as the
local level. Moreover, both visitors and
the local inhabitants would come to bet¬
ter appreciate the value of natural
resources.
To make the forest species more ac¬
cessible for observation (and research)
special techniques will be used to bring
observers to the canopy level. This is
where the dynamics of the tropical rain
forest occur. Experience indicates that
animals are far less fearful of people
when they are encountered in the
canopy. On the ground, humans are
characteristically regarded as hunters
and are feared.
The technique consists of a series of
suspended walkways supported from
the crowns of the tallest (and strongest)
trees. The US MAB National Commit¬
tee has provided funding for these walk¬
ways for research purposes in Malaysia
and China. A section of the walkways
connects the system to a hillside. Conse¬
quently, one can walk into the canopy
horizontally without the necessity of a
vertical climb. Platforms in the tall trees
are used for observation and photo¬
graphy. Artificial lighting at night will
be used to observe species not active
by day.
Visitors to Kinabalu National Park in
Borneo will be able to see newly-
planned facilities, including an orchid
garden containing most of the native
species, a butterfly farm, and a deer
park. Nature trails allow them to see
many of the 3,500 species of trees that
occur on the island, a bat cave and a
magnificent waterfall. At the end of a
hard day they can soak away their
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Walkways constructed high up in the forest
canopy and used by scientists for research can
also provide tourists with magnificent views
and new insights into the tropical forest.
weariness in natural hot springs that are
piped into tiled tubs.
The tours currently last two weeks,
but special arrangements can also be
made. Through tourism it is hoped to
demonstrate the immediate value of the
rain forests and to expand existing pro¬
tection schemes.
From the practical standpoint, the old
adage "Use them or lose them" seems to
apply to rain forests. It is hoped that
both economic developers and conser¬
vationists will benefit from sustainable
use of forest resources.
Much can be learned from the people
who inhabit these forests concerning
useful products. They are not the ones
who advocate destruction of forests and
replanting the land in monocultures. In
many cases they have a remarkable re¬
spect and regard for the forests, which
have provided them with the means to
survive for generations. With the des¬
truction of the forests they see their own
cultures and survival threatened.
ICR has offered to work with these
people in agroforestry schemes, using
species with which they are familiar.
Through these schemes the group hopes
to restore abandoned lands which were
formerly covered by rain forests, but
have been depleted of nutrients. Legu¬
minous plants which rapidly restore the
nutrients in soil have been identified.
These plants can also be used as highly
nutritious (17 per cent protein) fodder
for livestock, such as the gaur and the
mouse deer. Medicinal plants will be
included, together with a variety of food
plants. Assistance will be provided in
marketing.
If this can be achieved in China and
Malaysia, the forests will have paid their
own way. At a planning workshop held
in October 1988, ICR set a goal of self-
sufficiency within four years for its re¬
search and economic development
programme. Many of the several dozen
participants expressed scepticism. Eco¬
logists are not accustomed to thinking in
such terms. But more of us need to think
in these terms if we are to achieve our
goals of saving significant amounts of
tropical rain forests.
ILLAR MUUL, American ecologist and research
associate of the Smithsonian Institution, Washing¬
ton, D.C., is president of Integrated Conservation
Research (ICR), an organization which seeks to
integrate economic development with conserva¬
tion and research.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The Christianization of Kievan Russia
The Millennium celebrations
The thousandth anniversary of the intro¬
duction of Christianity to Kievan Russia
was widely celebrated during 1988. This
report on the highlights of the year's
events has been written for the Unesco
Courierby Monsignor Juvenaly, Metropo¬
litan of Krutits and Kolomna, a leading
figure in the Russian Orthodox Church
and a member of its Holy Synod.
AT a meeting with Patriarch Pimen
and the Holy Synod of the Russian
Orthodox Church on 29 April
1988, Mr. Mikhail Gorbachev, general
secretary of the Central Committee of the
Communist Party of the Soviet Union,
noted that the State and the Russian Church
have "a common history, one birthplace and
one future".
The programme of celebrations for the
millennium began in June with an assembly
of a Local Council of the Russian Orthodox
Church, which was held in the Trinity and
St. Sergius monastery at Zagorsk, near Mos¬
cow. The Council was attended by ecclesias¬
tical dignitaries and lay representatives from
Orthodox dioceses around the world. En¬
voys from many other Christian Churches
were present at the opening ceremony.
The Council canonized nine Russian
saints; adopted the Statutes of the Russian
Orthodox Church aimed at promoting the
religious life in society today; and issued a
number of appeals and messages to all Rus¬
sian Orthodox Churches, to all Orthodox
Christians practising the old rites, and to
Christians all over the world.
The centrepiece of the Moscow events was
an open-air service at the Danilov monas¬
tery, celebrated before a congregation of
many thousands by clergy from Orthodox
churches in many parts of the world, led by
the Patriarch of Antioch. The monastery,
returned to the Church by the Soviet State in
1983 and since restored, is today the spiritual
and administrative centre of the Russian
Orthodox Church.
Later in June, in a new district of Moscow,
Patriarch Pfmen laid the foundation stone of
a church dedicated to the Holy Trinity to
mark the millennium of Russian Orthodoxy.
The celebrations continued in other his¬
toric religious centres such as Kiev, Vladimir
and Leningrad. Open-air services held in all
these cities drew crowds of worshippers.
In Kiev, the cradle of Russian Orthodoxy,
the festivities took on a special meaning. The
Kiev caves, partly natural and partly man-
made structures excavated in the eleventh
century, once sheltered the first Russian
monks, hermits who had adopted the ascetic
way of life. As none of the city's cathedrals
was large enough to accommodate the
Kievans and pilgrims who wished to com¬
memorate the millennium, a service was held
in Lavrskaya Square, near the entrance to the
Far Caves, by'a number of high dignitaries of
the Russian Orthodox Church. Afterwards,
clergy and guests entered the holy caves,
where psalms were sung in honour of the
saints who had lived and died there.
Later, a service of thanksgiving was held
on the hill crowned by the statue of Prince
Vladimir I of Kiev, who in 988 AD accepted
Christianity on behalf of Kievan Russia.
Thousands of Christians gathered for the
service on the slopes overlooking the place
where, a millennium ago, the mass baptism
of the people of Kiev took place. Canticles
were sung by the choirs of St. Vladimir
cathedral and Odessa theological seminary.
This service was the outstanding event of the
millennium, although celebrations con¬
tinued nationwide, in all the dioceses of the
Russian Orthodox Church.
Photo credits
Front cover, pages 14 (below), 27 (above), 30 (below):
N. Myers © AAA Photo, Paris. Back cover, pages 6, 8:
© M. Random, Paris. Pages 2, 9 (below): © M. Pietri,
Paris. Page 4: C. Ciccione © Rapho, Paris. Page 5
(above): Yan © Rapho, Paris; (below): © Roger-Viollet,
Paris. Page 7 (above): C. Jest © Musée de l'Homme,
Paris; (below): © FAO, Rome. Page 9 (above): ©
Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Musée du Louvre, Paris.
Page 10 (above): © SPADEM, 1988; Haags Gemeente-
museum, The Hague; (below): © Almasy, Paris. Page
11: T. Cazabon © AAA, Paris. Pages 12, 18 (below): ©
Vivant Univers, Namur. Page 14 (above): C. Cuny ©
Rapho, Paris. Page 15: A. Picou © AAA Photo, Paris.
Page 16: Giraudon © AAA Photo, Paris. Page 17 (abo¬
ve): J. Tandel © AAA Photo, Paris; (below): © APN,
Paris. Page 18 (above): © F. McDougall/FAO, Rome.
Page 19: © C. Pennarts. Page 20: © Paul Harrison/
Panos Pictures, London. Page 21 (above): Unesco/Ger¬
da Böhm; (below): P. Berger © Rapho, Paris. Page 22:
M. Cherry/FAO, Rome. Pages 23, 27 (below), 28: © P.S.
Ramakrishnan. Pages 24, 25: (1) H. W. Silvester ©
Rapho, Paris; (2) P. Blouzard © Rapho, Paris; (3, 4) G.
Gerster © Rapho, Paris; (5) Illustration from Le lour du
monde, 1880, by G. Nachtigal, Museum d'Histoire Na¬
turelle, Paris; (6) Malanca © Sipa Press, Paris. Page 26:
D. Ryan © AAA Photo, Paris. Page 29 (above): A.
Visage © Jacana, Paris; (below): Coll. Varin-Visage ©
Jacana, Paris. Page 30 (above): © P. Johnson/FAO,
Rome. Page 31: © F. Botts/FAO, Rome. Pages 32, 33:
© Illar Muul. Page 34: © Russian edition of the Unesco
Courier, Moscow
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
r
The Courier M
A windom open on the -world
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, wilt be supplied on request.)
ALBANIA. *Ndermarrja e perpjes se libnf, Tirana. ARGENTINA. Librena el
Correo de la Unesco - EDILYR. SRL. Tucumán 1685. 1050 Buenos Aires.
AUSTRALIA. Books only:: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.. P.O. Box 33,
Brookvale 2100. NSW: Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept.. P.O.
Box 33, Brookvale 2100. NSW. Sub-agents. United Nations Association o(
Australia. Victorian Division, 328 Flinders Street. Melbourne 3000. Hunter
Publications. 58a Gipps St.. Coilmgwood. Victoria 3066. AUSTRIA. Gerold
and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools Interna¬
tional. Arab Regional Office. P.O. Box 726. Bahrain; The Arabian Agencies
and Distributing Co.. Al Mutanabi St.. PO Box 156, Manama BANGLADESH
Kanm International. GPO Box No: 2141. 64/1 Mampuri Para. Tejgaon.
Farmgate, Dhaka BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Cave Hill Campus. P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown BELGIUM. Jean de Lannoy. 202
Ave. du Roi. 1060 Brussels. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre. PO Box 91
Gaborone. BRAZIL. Fundacáo Getúlio Vargas, Service del Publicaçoes,
caixa postal 9 042-ZC-05 Praia de Botafogo 188. Rio de Janeiro (RJ) 2000:
Books only: Imagem Latinoamericana, Av. Paulista 750. 1 andar, caixa postal
30455. Sao Paulo CEP 01051, BULGARIA. Hemus. Kantora Literatura,
boulevard Rousky 6. Sofia. BURMA. Trade Corporation no. (9). 550-552
Merchant Street. Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd.. 1294
Algoma Road, Ottawa, Ontario K 1 B 3W8. (Stores: 6 1 Sparks Street. Ottawa.
21 1 Yonge St.. Toronto. Sales office' 7575 Trans Canada Hwy. Ste. 305, St.
Laurent, Quebec H4T 1V6. CAMEROON. Cameroon Book Centre. PO Box
123, Limbe. Commission Nationale, BP 1600. Yaounde. CHILE. Editorial
Universitaria S A.. Departamento de Importaciones. M. Luisa Santander
0447, casilla 10220, Santiago; Edilonal 'Andrés Bello'. Av; R. Lyon 946.
Casillo 4256. Santiago de Chile; Dipublic, Antonio Varas 671, 2o piso, casilla
14364. Correo 21, Santiago. CHINA. China National Publications Import and
Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beging COLOMBIA. Instituto Colombiano
de Cultura (Colcultura), Carrera 3A, n° 18 / 24. Bogota; Books only: Librena
Buchholz Galena, Calle 59, No; 13-1 3, Bogota. CYPRUS. "MAM'. Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avene. PO Box 1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.
Spalena 51-113 02. Prague 1; For Slovakia only Alfa Verlag. -Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6.893 31 Bratislava; PNS-UED. Jindnsska 14. praha 1:
Slovart, Gottwaldovo Nam 6. 805 32 Bratislava. DEM. REP. OF YEMEN. 1 41h
October Corporation. PO Box 4227, Aden. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-
OG. Tidssknftservice. 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Librería Blasco. Avenida Bolivar. No: 402. esq
Hermanos Deligne. Santo Domingo. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). Un¬
esco Publications Centre. No. 1 Taiaat Harb St.. Cairo. ETHIOPIA. Ethiopian
National Agency for Unesco, PO Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateemmen Kinakauppa, P. O Box 128. SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalamen
Kirjakauppa Oy. Koivuvaarankuja 2 01640 Vantaa 64 FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans. Periodicals only: Unesco CPD /
V-1 . rue Miollis, 7501 5 Pans. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchex-
port, Postfach 140. Leninstrasse 16. 7010. Leipzig. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum. Deutscher Unesco-Kurier
Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57. D5300 Bonn 3: UNO-Verlag, Simrockstrasse 23.
D-5300 Bonn 1; S. Karger GmbH, Verlag Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2
D-8034 Germering / München. For scientific maps only Geo Center. Postfach
800830, 7000 Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Books only: Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd.. PO Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.. PO 7869. Accra;
The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast: The University Bookshop of Legon. PO Box 1 , Legon. Periodicals only:
Fides Entreprises. P.O. Box 14129. Accra GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom. GREECE. Eleftheroudakis SA. International Bookstore. 4 Nikis
Street. Athens; John Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers. P.O.
Box 10073. 541 10 Thessaloniki. Greek National Commission for unesco. 3
Akadimias Street, Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 13-15 Lock
Road, Kowloon: Federal Publications (HK) Ltd.. Tokwawan. Kowloon; Hong
Kong Government Information Services, Publication Section. Hong Kong;
Periodicals only: Beaconsfield House 6th floor, Queen's Road Central. Victor¬
ia. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B. 149-H-13B9. Budapest 62.
ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co.. H F. Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd . Kamant Marg, Ballard Estate. Bombay 400038;
17 Chitaranjan Ave.. Calcutta 13: 36a. Anna Salai, Mount Road. Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd..
Bangalore 560001: 3-5-820 Hyderguda. Hyderabad- 50000 1 . Sub-agents.
Oxford Book and Stationery Co.. 17 Park St.. Calcutta 70016: Sandia House.
New Delhi 11 0001. INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers. 29.
Jl. Oto Iskandardmata 111, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37.
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco. 1 1 88 Englab
Ave.. Rostam Give Building, P.O. Box 11365-4498. Teheran 13158.
IRELAND. Periodicals only; The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., PO Box
43A. Walkmstown. Dublin 12; Books only.TDC Publishers. 1 1 North Frederick
Street, Dublin 7. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions. Inc.. c/o Steimatzky Ltd..
P.O. Box 628, Tel Aviv; A.B C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283. 71 Allenby Rd..
Tel Aviv 61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionana Sansoni, S p.A ), Via
Lamarmora 45. Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence; via Bartolmi 29. 20155
Milan; FAO Bookshop, via délie Terme di Caracalia. 00100 Rome. JAMAICA.
University of the West Indies Bookshop. Mona. Kingston 7. JAPAN. Eastern
Book Service Inc.. 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113 JORDAN
Jordan Distribution Agency. PO Box 375. Amman. Periodicals only Jordan
Book Cerjtre Co. Ltd.. PO Box 301 , Al Jubeiha. Amman. KENYA. East African
Publishing House, PO 30571. Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd. Quran
House. Mangano Street. PO Box 45245. Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco. P.O. Box Central 64. Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd. POB 2942, Kuwait: Periodicals only: Farafalla Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541 , Kuwait. LEBANON. Librairie Antoine A. Naufal
et Frères, BP 656. Beirut LESOTHO Mazenod Book Centre. PO Mazenod.
Maseru. LIBERIA National Bookstore, Mechlin and Carey Streets. PO Box
590, Monrovia; Cole and Yancy Bookshops Lid.. PO Box 286, Monrovia -
LUXEMBOURG. Books only: Librairie Paul Brück, 22. Grande-Rue. Luxem¬
bourg; Periodical: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 1022. Luxembourg MALAWI
Malawi Book Service, Head Office, PO Box 30044, Chichin. Blantyre 3
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop. Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic St.. Valletta. MAURITANIA GRA.LI.-
CO.MA.. 1 rue du Souk X, Avenue kennedy, Nouakchott MAURITIUS.
Nalanda Company Ltd.. 30 Bourbon St.. Port-Louis. MEXICO. Librería El
Correo de la Unesco. Actipán 66. Colonia del Valle. Apartado postal 61 164,
06600 Mexico DF. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bd des Moulins. Monte
Cario. MORROCCO. Librairie 'Aux belles images". 282 ave. Mohammed-V.
Rabat; Librairie des écoles. 1 2 ave. Hassan-ll, Casaglanca, Société chenfien-
ne de distribution et de presse, SOCHEPRESS, angle rues de Dînant et St.
Saens, BP 1 3683, Casablanca 05. MOZAMBIQUE. Instituto National do Livra
edo Disco (INLD), avenida 24 de Julho, 1921 r/d Io andar. Maputo NEPAL.
Sajha Prakashan Polchowk. Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Books only:
Keesing, Boeken B V.. Hogehilweg 13. Postbus 1 1 18. 1000 BC Amsterdam.
Periodicals- Faxon Europe, P O. Box 197. 1000 AD Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N V.. PO Box 200. Willem-
stad. Curaçao. NA. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P O. Box
14277-Kilbirme. Wellington. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The
University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka;
The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1;
Universitets Bokhandelen, Universrtetssentret. Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo
3: Periodicals only. Narvesen A/S. ütteraturt Jenesten, P.O.B. 61 25 Etterstad,
N 0602 Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre. Regional Office for
Book Development in Asia and the Pacific. 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box
8950, Karachi 29. PANAMA. Distribuidora Cultura Internacional. Apartado
7571, Zona 5. Panama. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store Inc.. 701 Rizal
Avenue. Manila POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki. Warsaw; Ars
Poiona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. ROMANIA.
ARTEXIM Ex port- Import, Piata Scienten, no. 1. PO Box 33-16, 70005
Bucharest. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan, Olaya Mam Street, Ibrahim Bin
Sulaym Building, Riyadh. SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd.. Kingsgale
House. PO Box 131, Mahé; National Bookshop, PO Box 48, Mahé. SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay College. Njala University and Sierra leone Diocesan
Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Righteous Enterprises. P.O. Box 562,
Kallang Basin Post Office. Singapore 91 33. SOCIALIST PEOPLE'S LIBYAN
ARAB JAMAHIRIYA. General Establishment for Publishing, Distribution and
Advertising. Souf Al Mahmoudi St.. PO Box 959. Tripoli. SOMALIA. Modern
Book Shop and General. PO Box ùàô. Mogadiscio. SPAIN. Mundi-Prensa
Libros SA, apartado 1223. Castelló 37. Madrid 1: Ediciones über, apartado
17, Magdalena 8, Ondárroa (Vizcaya): Donaire. Ronda de Ouleiro. 20,
apartado de correos 341. La Corurta; books only: Librería Castells, Ronda
Universidad 13 y 15, Barcelona 7: Librería de la Generalität de Catalunya,
Palan Moia, Rambla de los Estudios 118. 08 002 Barcelona. SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop. 1 00 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.O B 244,
Colombo 2. SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop. P O. Box 1118. Khartoum.
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box 2943.
Paramaribo. SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl Hovbokhandel. Regenng-
sgatan 12. Box 16356. S-103 27 Stockholm 16; For the Unesco Courier:
Svenska FN Forbundet, Skolgrand 2. Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm; For
penodfca/s on//' Wennergren-Williams AB. Nordenflychtsvagen 70, S-104, 25
Stockholm: Esseite Tidsknftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26. Box 62 -101 , 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich; Librairies
Payot in Geneva Lausanne. Basle, Berne. Vevey. Montreux, Neuchâtel and
Zurich SYRIA. Aleppo University Books Establishment, University of Aleppo.
Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. P.O B. 9030. Dar-es-
Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road.
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402. Bangkok; Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9.
Rajdamnern Ave., Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road.
Bangkok: ROEAP. PO Box 1425, Bangkok 10500. TRINIDAD AND TOBA¬
GO. National Commission for Unesco. 18 Alexandra St.. St. Clair. Port-of-
Spam. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A S., Istiklal Caddesi. No 469. Posta Kutusu
219. Beyogiu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, PO Box 71 45, Kampa¬
la. UNITED ARAB EMIRATES. Maktabat al Maktaba. PO Box 15408. Al Am.
Abu Dhabi. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office. PO Box 276, London,
SW8 5DT; H M S.O. Bookshops in London. Edinburgh. Belfast. Manchester,
Birmingham, Bristol; Third World Publications, 151 Stratford Road, Birming¬
ham Bi 1 1RD; for scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd.. 122 King's Cross Rd.,
London WC1X 9DS UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. Bernan-UNIPUB.
Periodicals Department. 461 1-F Assembly Drive, Lanham, MD 20706 4391.
URUGUAY. Ediciones Trecho. SA.. Maldonado 1092, Montevideo. USSR.
V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova 39. Moskva 113095.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/11. Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitar-
ieva 2. Lubljana: Nolit, Terazije 13/ VIII. 11000 Belgrade; periodicals only
Jugosolvena Kniga. PO Box 36, YU 11001 Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd.. P.O. Box 2664. Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare.
L J
Published monthly in 35 languages by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
A selection in braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 757C0 Paris.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Director: Bahgat Elnadl
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Nedacl Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille edition:
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Art Unit / Production: Georges Servat
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions:
Solange Belin
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Non-Headquarters editions
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Sn Ram (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broldo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Riode Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Abdul Manaf Saad (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: PaikSyeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Pcrkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: MarjattaOksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kossler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: NasirSeham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for ayear's issues: 62 FF
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
mav be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name.
Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions
of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the
Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by :(1)
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2)
University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48 100, U.S.A.; (3) N.CR. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 4469 1 , U.S.A.
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Imprime tn France (Printed in France) - Depot legal: Cl -
Janvier 1989.
Photogravure- im pression: Maury-ImprimcurS.A.
Z.I. route d'ritampes, 45330 Maicsherbes.
ISSN 0041-5278
N"l - 1989 -OPI- 88-1 -464 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
