<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="083091eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
JUNE 1989 - 15 French francs
1789
AN IDEA
THAT CHANGED
THE WORLD
IN THIS ISSUE:
AN EXCLUSIVE INTERVIEW WITH
Mr. FRANÇOIS
MITTERRAND
PRESIDENT OF THE FRENCH REPUBLIC
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Today there are no more
unexplored continents, unknown
seas or mysterious islands. But
while we can overcome the
physical barriers to exploration, the
barriers of mutual ignorance
between different peoples and
cultures have in many cases still not
been dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can voyage
to the ends of the earth. But a
different kind of Odyssey now
beckons-an exploration of the
world's many cultural landscapes,
the ways of life of its different
peoples and their outlook on the
world in which they live.
It is such an Odyssey that the
Unesco Courier now proposes to
you, its readers. Each month
contributors of different
nationalities will provide from
different cultural and professional
standpoints an authoritative
treatment of a theme of universal
interest. The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes will be respect
for the dignity of people
everywhere.
The theme of the 56-page
special issue which launches the
new-look Unesco Courier is the
worldwide impact of the idea of
Human Rights. As an opener we
are publishing an exclusive
interview with a leading figure of
our time, the President of the
French Republic, François
Mitterrand.
Future issues will present other
themes and other interviews with
statesmen and women and with
leading creators and thinkers.
Several regular features will also be
appearing in the coming months.
We shall welcome all your
comments, criticisms and
suggestions...
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
CONTENTS
4
Interview with
Mr. FRANÇOIS MITTERRAND
President of the French Republic
Cover: Earth, Sun, Moot 89,
a watercolour by the French painter
Georges Servat (1989)
11
V
1789 : AN IDEA
THAT CHANGED THE WORLD
THE REPUBLIC'S CITIZENS OF HONOUR
by Ehsan Naraghi 12
TOM PAÍNE: THE ANTIMONARCHIST
WHO TRIED TO SAVE A KING
by Jean Lessay 18
IN THE ANTILLES,
'LIBERTY FOR ALU
by Yves Benot 19
THE EAGLE AND THE SPHINX:
BONAPARTE IN EGYPT
by Mahmoud Hussein 24
SIEYES, HERDER, GOETHE: UNIVERSALITY
AND NATIONAL IDENTITY
by Alain Finkielkraut 30
THE REPUBLICAN DREAM
by Simón Bolívar 34
POETRY, FREEDOM AND REVOLUTION
by Sergei S. Averintsev 36
CHOMIN: THE ROUSSEAU OF THE EAST
by Shin'ya Ida 40
CHINA: RETHINKING THE REVOLUTION
by Thilian Zhang 44
THE SPIRIT OF '89
by Tahar Ben Jelloun 48
50
12 FRANÇOIS FURET:
An idea
and its destiny
GLOSSARY 58
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
An exclusive interview with
the President of the French Republic
François Mitterrand
Before the institutional upheavals of 1789, France (along
with the rest ofEurope and North America) experienced
an immense ferment of ideas, an intellectual, ethical, ju¬
ridical and aesthetic revolution which paved the way for
political change. Was this not a moment when secular cul¬
ture came to play a crucially important role as the driving
force ofhistory? Would it not be correct to say that culture
plays a role which is just as important, ifnot more so, than
economics as a source ofdynamism (or inertia) in the evo¬
lution of humanity?
1 ou are right to point out that the French Revolution
did not take place in a void. It was the prolongation, in po¬
litical terms, of profound changes in ways of thinking, feel¬
ing and acting.
Throughout the eighteenth century there was all over
Europe a vast ferment of men and ideasthink of the trav¬
els and debates of the philosophers, scholars and artists of
that timewhich slowly changed the way in which society
regarded itself.
The social and political order was no longer perceived
as an immutable effect of divine will but as a balance which
was both relative (the discovery of the "new world", and
other voyages had revealed the existence of other societies
organized differently) and perfectible (as the victory of the
American rebels had shown).
For many people there emerged a new line of demarca¬
tion between the religiousa matter of personal conviction,
the field of freedom of conscienceand the secular, of which
government was to be an emanation.
This emergence of a secular culture to which you refer
was not in itself hostile to religionone of the great figures
of the Revolution was the Abbé Grégoire, a priest faithful
to his religion and his ministry, and a republicanbut the
affirmation of man's rights and responsibilities on earth.
The evolution of the sciences played a part in this
process. The progress of observation and experimentation
made the worldfrom the secrets of nature to human
relationsincreasingly accessible to understanding, to ration¬
al analysis. Was this not the moment to think of rebuilding
in a different way, with more reason, more justice and more
liberty?
The German philosopher Fichte, who regarded the
Revolution sympathetically, saw in it a proof of the superi¬
ority of man over the beaver, which always rebuilds in an
identical fashion, or over the bee, which invariably arranges
the cells of its hive in the same way.
The new ideas which were spreading at that time,
transmitted in the salons, gazettes, and cafés, thus had a
decisive influence. They not only provided the weapons of
criticism but, in a society blocked by hereditary privilege
and absolutism, in a sense legitimized the transition to
action.
Not that there was a ready-made theory of revolution
waiting to be applied when the moment came. A great deal
of improvisation went on under the pressure of events.
But people did have a kind of compass of which the
Rights of Man were the armature.
However, during the same period, other movements
were defeated, although the aspirations of the revolution¬
aries of Geneva, Batavia or Brabant, of the Italian Jacobins
and the Hungarian patriots, the republicans of Mainz, the
Irish rebels or the Polish resistance were not much differ¬
ent from those of the French.
For history is not made by ideas alone. There must be
a conjunction of economic, social and political conditions
favourable to change. And there must always be the
determinationindividual and collectiveof men.
In the last analysis, they alone are the driving force of
history.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
i^^JW'N' *<% Vt-^-l"- .- -id "?*¥1
Bi ExsSSEüäea
^H
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
<
...Neither self-renunciation nor self-absorption
There is a growing tendency to "localize" or "nationalize" which respect the identity of everyone, co-operate without
culture in the sense that people speak, for example, of arrogance or excessive humility in the priority areas of edu-
French, German, Chinese or Egyptian culture. Is there not cation, science, and culture, the keys to a freely chosen
a twofold danger here of encouraging compartmentaliza- destiny.
tion between cultures and of centring each culture on it- It is in this sense that France is working, with others,
self, of inciting it to turn towards the past rather than the for a Europe with a living culture, for the strengthening of
future? Ofcourse there are many cultural homelands, each links within the French-speaking community, and for recog-
linked to a specific language and history and each bearing nition of the cultural dimension of development aid.
a specific combination ofcreative resources. Some are more On a vaster scale, this is Unesco's raison d'être and the
dynamic and aggressive than others and they must all have ambition of the decade of cultural development launched
the opportunity to express themselvesfully andfreely. What in 1988. For today even more than in 1945, the following
can be done to protect them in such a way that they are three objectives are indissociable: we must educate, seek and
not stifled? create together.
I Finally I would say that I do not believe in the
would not be inclined to agree with you that there is a past/present dilemma, but rather in the force of societies
general tendency for culture to be increasingly confined which know how to use their past to project themselves into
within local or national frontiers. the future.
First of all because the entire history of humanity is one, The project to rebuild, under Unesco auspices, a vast
often violent, sometimes peaceful, of growing contact be- new library at Alexandria is one example of what I have
tween human cultures. in mind; to create modern conditions for access to
In our age, the media build many bridges, multiply in- knowledge on that Mediterranean shore is simultaneously
fluences tenfold and make time contract. to renew links with a prestigious past and to prepare the
The question is whether this will lead to an enrichment future.
of our different cultures and a more fertile dialogue between
them. Or to new dissensions, new inequalities, between those Is there an area where all these cultural homelands are in
who will master the world media and the rest, between those contact, an area of universal values? Could one go so far
who will have access to the perpetually changing field of as to say that before the Enlightenment such an area was
knowledge and the rest. without intellectual landmarks, that it was latent in great
This is a paradox of modern times; we know that the works ofart and literature produced in many countries
wealth of the world lies in the diversity of its cultures, in but that after 1789 it foundphilosophical expression in the
the variety of sensibilities and forms of expertise; we pos- concept ofa universal man, cut loose from all ethnic, con-
sess fantastic means for improving mutual understanding and fessional and social moorings?
communication. But if we are not careful, these instruments T
of co-operation will become instruments of domination. And 1 am tempted to reply with an anecdote. In 1827, Goethe
under the economic or political impulsion of the most ag- was delighted to discover in a Chinese novel themes close
gressive cultures, a pernicious uniformization may come to to those he had used in his epic Hermann und Dorothea. He
prevail. noted enthusiastically that there are placesin this case
So what is the answer? Neither self-renunciation nor self- bookswhere humanity can overcome its divisions. And
absorption. as a consequence he defined a programme in the form of
Next, we must be thoroughly convinced of the impor- a concept, Weltlitteratur [world literature], capable of tran-
tance of what is at stake: there will be no lasting economic scending historic frontiers and cultural particularisms. That
development, no social progress, no solid democracy, no was his answer to your question about a possible area of
world peace without the flowering of cultures which are universal values,
sure of themselves and capable of mutual enrichment. The revolutionaries of 1789 felt no doubt on this score:
Lastly, we must search for forms of cultural solidarity their message was addressed to the whole planet, the rights
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
...educate, seek and create together
of man and the citizen were proclaimed as universal. This In other words, it is not so easy to define the philosophi-
was said with a force that still rings in our ears, and the es- cal area you describe. The recognition of new forms of
sential thing was, for the first time, to say it in this way. determinismeconomic, social and psychologicalhas al-
We know that in practice things turned out somewhat ways raised the question of what is universal in man.
differently. That liberty, armed for war, ended by assum- But, more specifically, is it possible to act if all values
ing in Europe the form and customs of conquest, as Jaurès are relative (to a place, a time, a given culture) and thereby
said. That equality for women, blacks, and the poor, was cancel each other out? If racism is only one idea among
something less than true equality. others, and apartheid is the problem of South Africans alone?
But if the French Revolution was not always faithful Can one do anything but postulate a minimum of univer-
to its principles, it was an ideal in whose name people would sal values in order to pass any kind of judgement outside
fight in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, in a con- one's own immediate sphere and provide a basis for human
text in which national and social questions came to assume solidarity?
greater and greater importance. Many peoples of Europe and Liberty, equality and fraternity are values which have
Latin America, Asia and Africa, would make it their watch- stood up well to the wear and tear of time and have become
word against the domineering pretensions of the West. sufficiently well acclimatized in all latitudes that people have
And when in 1948, after a devastating world war, the continued to defend them. As nothing is ever definitively
need arose to reaffirm human rights, it was again the decla- achieved in this field, there is a long way to go from the
ration of 1789 which inspired the universal declaration set real to the ideal.
forth at the UN. Later the universal declaration was com- I will conclude with the wise definition given by Tzve-
pleted by the declaration of economic and social rights which tan Todorov in his latest work: "the universal is the horizon
had been called for in over a century of workers' struggles, of agreement between two particulars". This dialogue, he
This was not aimed at the universal man cut loose from his adds, is perhaps inaccessible but it is the only worthwhile
social moorings of whom you speak; on the contrary it was postulate,
concerned with people in specific situations, at work and
in society. What about the relationship between politics and culture?
To return to your question, I think a distinction should Is it possible to expect from politicians, above allfrom world
be made between acts which bear political fruit1789, the leaders, an aesthetic of community relations, of relations
Declaration of the Rights of Manand the complex course between man and nature, of essential forms of solidarity
which, especially in the history of ideas, leads to them. between all humanity? Can such an aesthetic draw inspi-
First of all, the radical change of outlook which made ration from the ideal whereby each person should act as
the Revolution possible was a slow gestation which origi- if the meaning of his or her action could be erected into
nated long before the eighteenth century, in the humanism a universal principle?
of the Renaissance, in the coming of the spirit of comparí- T
son which shook the authority of religious revelation, in 1 seem to remember that Kant formulated his categorical
Galilean physics which heralded the Encyclopaedists, in the imperative in similar terms in his Groundwork of the
Wars of Religion which gave rise to the right of tolerance, Metaphysic of Morals. He set forth three moral laws: act
in Montesquieu and La Bruyère who asserted the relativism as if the maxim of your action were to be erected into a
of beliefs and customs. universal law of nature, act in such a way that you always
Secondly, throughout the eighteenth century different treat humanity as an end and never as a means, act as if
sensibilities coexisted, some more universalist, others more your maxim was to serve as a universal law for all reasona-
relativist, than others, the echoes of which are found in ble beings.
modern critical debates on the idea of ethnocentrism, which To my mind it would be entirely beneficial if political
claims to erect into dominant universal values the specific leaders drew inspiration from these rules of conduct laid
contents of a culture, and on the limits of the right to be down by a philosopher who followed the events of 1789
different. very closely!
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Fickle and libertarian, such is the essence of creation.
This only irritates those who fear liberty.
An aesthetic of relationships in the community? In today's world, no one will find salvation by going
It is not for statesmen to define what is beautiful. But against others. The increasing interdependence of economies
they are responsible for encouraging all that forges a link and cultures makes solidarity an obligation,
between people and strengthens the feeling of a common
destiny. Art also has a part to play since it makes use of Political institutions should encourage theflowering ofcul-
dreams, that essential commodity. tures and the circulation oftheirproducts in the freest pos-
Here a striking vista which makes the city more con- sible conditions. But isn't the creative artist always
genial to its users; there a new museum, revealing its treas- necessarily at odds with the politician, even when the lat-
ures to all; elsewhere a restored monument reminding the ter is full ofgood intentions towards the arts? Is it not true
nation of a moment in its history; somewhere else a modern that the artist needs to explore pathways that are anti-
public library, beautiful and useful. institutional?
To provide amenities, to adorn, to make a significant A
statementall this can be done together. IJLbsolutely. The freedom to create is to some extent the
So many cities throughout the world bear the stigma barometer of all liberties. A society which restricts this free-
of degrading forms of urbanization which display an ugly dorn usually attaches little importance to its members,
contempt for people. Other choices are possible which ex- Where people are free neither in their movements nor in
press a desire for a better community life for all and a rejec- their words, the force of creation is weakened even if cou-
tion of laissez-faire, of the haphazard effects of exclusively rageous works appear, condemned to a restricted diffusion,
private interests, of thoughtless conformity. In relation to art, the political authorities bear the
I would not claim that the link between man and na- responsibility you describe: they should create conditions
ture is the same for everyone, for the inhabitant of Buenos propitious for creation and circulation.
Aires and the villager of Casamance, for the Parisian and I would also add an educational dimension, a responsi-
the Baltic fisherman. Some grapple with earth or water day bility towards young people or publics which are relative-
after day, others enjoy them as a form of recreation. ly unfamiliar with creative works. For loving also comes
And yet the risks of exhaustion of certain natural through learning,
resources are of concern to us all; the irremediable destruc- And sometimes too there is an obligation to see that
tion of the atmosphere will spare no one; the community market forces do not reign entirely unchecked, to take, when
has to pay a price for rashly polluted seas. necessary, protective measures simply to defend the freedom
Human development has been based on mastery of na- to create against over-encroaching cultures. The example of
ture. If we forget what we owe to nature and despoil it, then the audiovisual media, at a time when the number of chan-
we may be heading for perdition. Those who work close neis and satellites is rapidly increasing, shows that it is im-
to nature know that an ill-treated piece of land does not yield possible to pay too much attention to this,
its wealth for long. The abuse of power begins with interference in content.
And the city-dweller knows that by creating a garden History has too many regrettable examples of attempts to
or a park among the stones, we do more than embellish the promote an official art exalting the "positive" virtues of a
city, we assert the continuity of a civilization, we indicate given régime,
that human genius is rooted in respect for certain balances. One important feature of the Enlightenment was the
I have cited these examples to show that politicians, and holding of a public debate on aesthetics. Many viewpoints
all citizens, must be more attentive to the essential solidari- were expressed and some of them make us smile todayas
ties between people and between people and their environ- when Diderot recommended historical portraits as a par-
ment, to preserve the vital balances not only for their own ticularly revolutionary art form since they drew the atten-
societies but for the future of the world. tion of the public to the great defenders of its rights.... But
Remember that when Unesco acted to save Borobudur, fortunately no narrowly utilitarian conception of art
Venice or Mont Saint-Michel, it did so because that heritage prevailed.
is part of the memory of all mankind, the common heritage. Fickle and libertarian, such is the essence of creation.
What was valid for the past is even more valid for the future. This only irritates those who fear liberty.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
What cultural project do you personally dream of? What
wouldyou like to achieve with other world leaders between
now and the end of the millennium? Is it possible to im¬
agine a cultural programme on a world scale analagous
to Eureka?
M.Lust I really tell you about my dreams?
Very well. There is one project for my country which
I hold dear and that is the great library of France, the launch¬
ing of which I announced last summer, on the day of our
national festival.
The book and the written heritage are at the heart of
our civilization. During my first mandate, France greatly
developed and modernized its library network. But our Bib¬
liothèque Nationale is too cramped in its old buildings and
cannot, in spite of all efforts, adequately present its presti¬
gious heritage or receive all those who seek access to it, in
some cases after travelling from distant countries.
Whence the idea of building a great library on another
site, radically new in conception, covering a vast field of
knowledge, using the latest technologies of data transmis¬
sion, equally concerned with the audiovisual documents of
today's culture, and eventually forming partwith other
French and foreign librariesof a great network.
I intend to follow the project closely. The building must
be beautiful andwhy not?the site favourable to medita¬
tion, so that everything will combine to celebrate the pleas¬
ure of discovery and study, and encourage the acquisition
of knowledge.
Secondly, what would I like to achieve with other heads
of state between now and the end of the millennium? There
is so much to do if the world is to become less harsh to the
needy, less given to destruction, more respectful of univer¬
sal human rights....
One problem, however, seems to me of extreme and
even frightening importance for the survival of humanity:
the deterioration of the atmosphere.
Everyone must understand that this is not just another
form of pollution; it may spell the end of all life on the
planet. Here everyone must join in the search for a solution.
The United Nations is devoting an interesting research
programme to this problem. But the moment has come for
decision and action.
This is why, on 11 March last, at The Hague, twenty-
four countries signed an appeal urgently calling for the cre¬
ation of an international authority for the environment.
As always in such a case, dogmatisms and egoisms,
draped in a refusal to abandon any fragment of national
sovereignty to a collective authority, are slowing the move¬
ment down. But twenty-four countries, for a start, are de¬
termined to go ahead. Others will follow as they come to
realize what is really at stake.
I wish thereforelong before the end of the
millenniumto see human reason, that virtue so dear to the
hearts of the men of 1789, triumph over the destructive
ravages of laxity and laissez faire.
You mention Eureka, the programme of European tech¬
nological development which now has a sister programme
in the field of the audiovisual.
At the time we faced a choice. Should we wait for unani¬
mous agreement among our partners, or should a few of
us who were determined to act go ahead and leave the doors
wide open for all those who might wish to join us later?
We opted for the second course. Gradually the candidatures
have flowed in, and not only from Europe.
Cultural co-operation at planetary level, which owes
much to Unesco, can also proceed in this way: a project,
a programme, the united determination of some, others who
join in later.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
z
,/
â «£.'.
f
I
V
"*»
J
X
h
WET
>.
\
/
v
\
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
E T 0 R I A L
ri.ll men are born and
remain free, and have
equal rights... " reads the
first article of the
Declaration of the Rights of
Man and of the Citizen
adopted by the Constituent
Assembly between 20 and
26 August 1789. Opposite,
a painting specially
executed for the Unesco
Courier by French artist
Brigitte Salom.
^ 1789
An idea
that changed
the world
R
»ARE are the ideas that, in response to some hitherto unexpressed popular
expectation, trigger a determination for change, mark a break between the past and
the future, and quicken the pace of history.
Rarer still are those ideas which have crossed the frontiers of the time and place
of their conception, and germinated much later in other parts of the world.
How does the great idea of 1789, that of "man as a citizen", stand up today? Root¬
ed in a specific culturethat of Europeand a particular centurythe age of the
Enlightenmentit is now universally accepted. After, it is true, a circuitous jour¬
ney which saw it by turn debated and rejected, ignored and rediscovered, tolerated
by some and demanded by others, until in 1948 it inspired a Declaration of Human
Rights which was adopted by the international community.
Out of this idea, diffused around the world by both French and foreign contempo¬
raries of the 1789 RevolutionBonaparte, Jefferson, Goethe, Mirandaarose a great
hope for universal fraternity. But this hope was gradually thwarted by theories which
affirmed the preeminence of the collective spirit over individual liberty. During a
long period it was betrayed by the process of colonial expansion, which substituted
the notion of the civilizing mission of the West for the dream of the equality of
people everywhere.
In some cases modern movements for national emancipation regarded the principle
of the rights of man and of the citizen with renewed esteem, but often the concept
of the revolutionary state was preferred instead. Finally, in the last decades of the
twentieth century, the Declaration of 1789 has come to be seen as a fundamental
guarantee of freedom for each people and a framework for understanding and co¬
operation between all peoples.
This issue of the Unesco Courier attempts to highlight some milestones on the itine¬
rary whereby this idea born in the wildest dreams of a handful of visionaries has
become part of the common heritage of humanity. 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
' Hi
/x key to the Bastille sent to
George Washington by the
Marquis de Lafayette. It is
today displayed at Mount
Vernon, Washington's home
in Virginia (USA).
On 6 October 1789
thousands of angry Parisian
women marched on Versailles
and demanded to be heard
by the National Assembly. A
delegation was immediately
received in the hall where the
Assembly was sitting as
shown in this engraving by
Jean-François Janinet.
Though many French people departed,
many foreigners arrived. They joined
wholeheartedly in all our agitation;
they came to embrace France. And if
they had to die, they would prefer to do
so rather than live elsewhere. Here,
should theyperish, at least they were sure
of having lived. jules michelet
Liberty and Equality are blessings too
important to be the heritage ofFrance
alone.. Thomas paine
Either the Republic will be universal or
it will not be anacharsis cloots
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
< 1789
An idea
that changed
the world
The Republic's
citizens
of honour
BY EHSAN NARAGHI
E come from Europe, we come from Asia,
we come from America, we are Humanity!"
Thirty-six foreigners, each wearing the costume
of his country, stood at the bar of the National
Assembly. According to the report of the session
of 9 June 1790, it was like being "at the centre
of the world". Pio the Neapolitan was there, don
Pablo Olavidé the Spaniard, the Prussian Baron
Trenckh, Dutch patriots and others too. Their
leader and self-appointed spokesman was a young
Prussian noble who called himself Anacharsis
Cloots. Flanked by an Arab and an African, he
addressed a silent and respectful audience. After
praising the Assembly for the measures it had
taken in favour of the rights of man, he demand¬
ed the honour of participating in the Fête de la
Fédération1 which, he felt, should not be only
a French celebration, but one of all peoples. With
these words, "a humanitarian exhilaration seized
the deputies and, with lively applause, the Assem¬
bly received 'mankind' within its fold".
Anacharsis Cloots:
'The Republic will be universal'
His real name was Jean-Baptiste du Val-de-Grâce,
baron de Cloots. The son of an adviser to the
King of Prussia, the possessor of a great fortune Anacharsis Cloots 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
l'rom top: Benjamin
Franklin, Thomas Jefferson,
William Wilberforce,
Jeremy Bentham.
14
and an impassioned francophile, Cloots had visit¬
ed England, Italy and even Morocco, before his
enthusiasm for the French Revolution caused him
to settle in Paris. He contributed to Parisian
newspapers and donated 12,000 francs to the na¬
tion to arm soldiers in the "sacred war of men
against tyrants". Elected to the National Conven¬
tion in 1792, he dreamed of creating a universal
republic, a federation of all nations. As the French
historian Jules Michelet stated in his Histoire de
la révolution française (1847-1853; "History of the
French Revolution"), for Cloots Paris was "the
cradle and capital of the general confederation of
men [where] the States General of the world will
assemble.... Thus will there no longer be
provinces, nor armies, nor vanquished, nor vic¬
tors. People will travel from Paris to Peking as
easily as from Bordeaux to Strasbourg. The
Ocean, arrayed with ships, will unify its shores.
Orient and Occident will embrace on the field
of the Federation.2 Rome was the metropolis of
the world through war. Paris will be so through
peace...".
Cloots was one of the eighteen non-French
personalities upon whom the Legislative Assem¬
bly, in 1792, bestowed the title of French citizen:
"Considering that the men who, by their
writings and courage, have served the cause of
liberty and prepared the emancipation of peoples
cannot be regarded as foreigners by a nation
whose wisdom and courage have made it free...,
considering finally that, at a time when a nation¬
al convention will determine the destinies of
France and perhaps prepare those of mankind,
it behooves a generous and free people to call
upon its wisdom and confer the right to partici¬
pate in this great act of reason upon men who,
by their opinions, writings and courage, have
proven so eminently worthy, the National As¬
sembly declares the conferring of the title of
French citizen upon Priestley, Paine, Bentham,
Wilberforce, Clarkson, Mackintosh, David Wil¬
liams, Gorani, Anacharsis Cloots, Campe, Cor¬
neille Pauw, Pestalozzi, Washington, Hamilton,
Madison, Klopstock, Kosciuszko, Schiller."
The example of
the young American democracy
Among these eighteen honorary citizens were
four Americans: Thomas Paine, a participant in
the Revolution; George Washington, first presi¬
dent of the United States; James Madison, fourth
president; and Alexander Hamilton, Washing¬
ton's faithful companion. This was no accident.
The French and American Revolutions were
directly related.
The Declaration of Independence of the
American rebels, proclaimed in 1776 at the height
of the conflict with the British, was the symbol
of courage and hope of the young nation. The
Declaration, especially its preamble, appeared to
the French liberal élite as a triumph of the ideals
of progress, liberty and democracy. Until then,
the only European country which boasted of be¬
ing a home for political freedom was Britain. (Did
its constitution not provide Montesquieu with a
model for the separation of powers from which
the Constituent Assembly drew inspiration?) But,
whereas the British empire was not looked upon
favourably by the French, the new American
democracy received their total admiration. It was
to George Washington, through the intermedi¬
ary of Thomas Paine, that the Marquis de
Lafayette offered the key to the fallen Bastille.
In the eyes of the French, one man, by his
knowledge, wisdom and unaffected simplicity,
embodied the virtues of this new nation: Benja¬
min Franklin. Sent to France to represent a na¬
tion which was not yet even a state, it was his
mission to mobilize and channel French aid for
the American cause. According to the French
historian Jean Lessay, when Franklin arrived in
Paris in December 1776, he was already famous
in all the capital's learned societies and cultured
circles because of his scientific work, and espe¬
cially for his invention of the lightning rod, the
impact of which it is hard to imagine today. He
immediately drew on the considerable capital of
sympathy his compatriots enjoyed in France, and
established close relations with politicians and
scientists. The academies, salons and clubs vied
for his attention. When he died in 1790, the Con¬
stituent Assembly decreed three days' national
mourning, at the close of a vibrant tribute
pronounced by Mirabeau.
Jefferson and Paine
After Franklin's mission, the United States Con¬
gress sent to France in 1785 an urbane and learned
politician who had been the principal drafter of
the Declaration of Independence: Thomas Jeffer¬
son (1743-1826).
The revolutionary intellectuals met often and
discreetly at the home of this brilliant and
hospitable ambassador. Numerous historians
have detected his influence in the draft of the
Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the
Citizen presented to the Assembly on 11 July
1789 by his friend, Lafayette. Recalled by George
Washington to occupy the post of Minister of
Foreign Affairs, Jefferson continued to be an ar¬
dent defender of revolutionary France. In 1792,
when the French Republic was proclaimed, he
obtained its recognition by the United States,
long before other countries. During his entire
presidency of the United States (1801-1809), his
friendship for France was unfailing.
Thomas Paine was one of the pioneers of
American democracy. With his political shrewd¬
ness and courage, he played a role of immense
importance in Britain and the United States, as
well as in France. Born in Thetford (England) in
1737, he was a labourer until the age of thirty-
eight, before becoming a writer, philosopher and
militant revolutionary of world renown.
Benjamin Franklin, whom Paine met in Lon-
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
don, encouraged him to migrate to the United
States, where he landed in 1774. Two years later,
he published his masterpiece, Common Sense,
which advocated the independence of the English
colonies. This pamphlet, of which 200,000 copies
were published (for a population of 3,500,000),
made the colonists aware of the necessity of
wresting their independence by force. As one of
his biographers has written, "Washington was the
sword of the American Revolution, Paine was the
pen". Common Sense soon crossed the Atlantic
and was an enormous success in Europe. By May
1776 it had been translated and published in
France.
After the American colonies had achieved
their independence, Paine returned to Europe,
faithful to his motto "My country is the place
where freedom does not yet exist". In 1789 in
London he took up the cause of the French
revolutionaries. To Edmund Burke's attack on
the Revolution set forth in his Reflections on the
Revolution in France, Paine replied with his Rights
ofMan, hundreds of thousands of copies of which
were printed in 1791.
The British government banned the book and
Paine was indicted for treason. He took refuge
in France, where in 1792 he was elected to the
National Convention. There, assisted in the de¬
bates by other deputies who acted as his inter¬
preters, he was, with the Marquis de
Condorcet, the main drafter of the Girondin
Constitution.
From all corners
of Europe...
Among the other Englishmen who were
proclaimed French citizens, David Williams also
helped to draw up the Constitution under the
guidance of Condorcet; James Mackintosh
defended the French Revolution against Burke's
attacks in his Vindiciae Gallicae (1791), translat¬
ed into French and published in Paris in 1792 un¬
der the title Apologie de la Révolution française
("Vindication of the French Revolution"); and
William Wilberforce (1759-1833), co-founder of
the Anti-Slavery Society, was, with his lawyer
friend Thomas Clarkson (1761-1846), a tireless
and ardent pioneer of anti-slavery legislation.
Child prodigy, Oxford graduate at eighteen,
Jeremy Bentham (1748-1832) was one of the
greatest jurists of his time. His first book, A Frag¬
ment on Government, caused a sensation when
it was published anonymously in 1776. Sym¬
pathetic to the French Revolution, he published
four letters in the Courrier de Provence, a
newspaper founded by Mirabeau, an Essay on Po¬
litical Tactics, and a Draft of a Code for the Or¬
ganisation ofthe Judicial Establishment in France.
He wrote a pamphlet for the Convention in 1793,
Emancipate your Colonies. For a long time Ben¬
tham enjoyed greater popularity in continental
Europe and in the United States than he did in
his own country.
^-^
From top: Friedrich
Gottlieb Klopstock, Tadeusz
Kosciuszko, Philippe
Buonarroti, Francisco de
Miranda.
"All law is evil," he wrote, "because all law
is a breach of liberty... Government must be
mindful of two things, the evil of the offence and
the evil of the law." This citizen of the universe,
as he was popularly known, was straightforward,
pleasant, of strict morals, and totally disinterest¬
ed. It was in the Essay on Government (1769) by
the chemist and theologian Joseph Priestley (who
was elected to the National Convention but never
took his seat) that Bentham found the phrase
upon which his life's work was based: "the
greatest happiness of the greatest number".
Fighting
for liberty
For the National Assembly, the German epic and
lyric poet Friedrich Gottlieb Klopstock
(1724-1803) symbolized, along with Schiller, the
enthusiasm of the German intelligentsia for the
Revolution. In 1788 Klopstock wrote an "Ode
for the Convocation of the States General" in
which he predicted the rebirth of France. In April
1792, with the aim of defending France against
the European coalition, he composed a poem en¬
titled "War of Liberty", which he sent to the
Duke of Brunswick, commander-in-chief of the
Prusso-Austrian army. He even sent a constitu¬
tional programme to Roland, one of the revolu¬
tionary leaders. But, like most of the foreign
revolutionaries, he lost his illusions during the
Reign of Terror.
The Pole, Tadeusz Kosciuszko (1746-1817),
future statesman and national hero, participated
as a voluntary officer in the American War of In¬
dependence (1775-1783), where he gained fame
through his heroism and military skill, particu¬
larly in the planning of fortifications. He was
made an honorary citizen of the United States
after being promoted to brigadier-general by
Washington. After his return to Poland in 1784
he fought against the Russians, and in 1793 was
delegated to Paris to solicit help from revolution¬
ary France. While there he presented a pamph¬
let recommending the founding of a republic in
Poland, following France's example. Back in the
United States in 1797, he used money from the
sale of his lands, as well as his pension, to buy
slaves to whom he gave their freedom.
The Italian aristocrat Philippe Michel
Buonarroti (1761-1837) joined the Jacobin Club
and later became a French citizen by decision of
the Convention. Sent to Corsica with special
powers, he was entrusted with the task of
propagating revolutionary ideas there. He was ar¬
rested as a follower of Robespierre, and while in
prison befriended Gracchus Babeuf with whom
he became a leader in the planning of art attempt
to overthrow the Directory government in 1796
known as the "Conspiracy of Equals". In 1828
he published his Conspiration de Babeuf, an ac¬
count of this unsuccessful enterprise. During the
last thirty years of his life he organized a vast net¬
work of secret societies in France and Italy, be- 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Jrrom top: revolutionary
emblems of the "German
Jacobins"; Mary
Wollstonecraft; Etta Palm,
a contemporary miniature
in which the ardent
feminist can be seen
rejecting her husband's
advances.
16
EHSAN NARAGHI,
former director of Unesco's
Youth Division, is an
Iranian sociologist and
writer. He was the authoi
of the first major study of
the brain-drain. His other
publications include
L'Orient et la crise de
l'Occident ("The East and
the Crisis of the West",
Entente publishers, Paris,
1977), and he is currently
preparing a book on the
sociological evolution of
Iran.
tween which he was a tireless emissary of revo¬
lution.
Miranda, forerunner
of Latin American independence
Francisco de Miranda (1750-1816), another
foreigner closely connected with the Revolution,
played an important role in both Europe and in
South America, where he fought for the indepen¬
dence of Venezuela and the Spanish colonies. He
left the Spanish army in 1783 to fight in the
American War of Independence, and then went
to France where he served in the revolutionary
army.
He was a notable commander of French
troops during the campaign against the Austro-
Prussian armies in Belgium. He then went to
London where he became the leader of a group
of South American rebels working for the liber¬
ation of their countries. He formed the Gran Re¬
union Americana ("Great American Union"),
which counted among its members the Argen¬
tine patriot José de San Martín; Bernardo O'Hig-
gins, future liberator of Chile; and Antonio
Nariño, an early champion of Colombian in¬
dependence. The enthusiasm aroused by Miran¬
da's arrival in Caracas in 1810 was such that the
"Patriotic Society", of which Simón Bolívar was
a member, proclaimed the independence of
Venezuela in the following year.
In the name of women citizens...
All credit, finally, to the non-French women who
devoted themselves to the revolutionary cause,
notably the English writer Mary Wollstonecraft
(1759-1797), and the Dutchwoman, Etta Palm.
From the outset, Mary Wollstonecraft was
a supporter of the Revolution, and like Paine and
Priestley published a reply to Burke, her Defence
of the Rights ofMan (1790). She went to live in
Paris and joined the group of British people who
supported the Revolution. A pioneer feminist,
she published in 1792 a book entitled y4 Vindica¬
tion of the Rights of Women.
Etta Palm also intervened in the course of the
French Revolution. L'Orateur du Peuple reports
that, during a meeting of the Cercle Social on 26
October 1790, a speaker expatiating on "the civil
and political status of women in a well constituted
state", was unable to continue his speech. A
woman called for silence and took the floor in
the place of the exhausted orator. Without giv¬
ing anyone time to interrupt her, this "foreign
lady, remarkable for her imposing height, said,
'Gentlemen, could it then be possible that revolu¬
tionary society, which renders unto men their
rights, has rendered Frenchmen unjust and dis¬
honest with regard to women? ... I request, in the
name of all women here present, that the orator
continue.' "
At the close of the meeting, the women sur¬
rounded Etta, who urged them to unite. She
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
founded a "Society of Women Friends of Truth",
a kind of charitable circle which stood up against
prejudice and soon became a centre of feminist
activity. Her first speech as president of the So¬
ciety, addressed to the forty-eight Paris Sections,
denounced the social conditions to which wom¬
en were subjected. Her speeches, read during
meetings in Paris and the provinces, won the ap¬
proval and enthusiasm of women. She was pos¬
sibly the first woman to use a vocabulary of
feminism, and it is probable that her expansive
personality strongly influenced Olympe de
Gouges (1755-1793), author of a "Declaration of
Rights of Women and the Citizen" published in
1792.
Hope and tragedy
Faced with the excesses of the Terror, all these
men and women experienced a period of despair.
A great admirer of the Revolution, the English
poet William Wordsworth (1770-1850) wrote that
the Terror revealed "what man can make of
man". Disillusion reached the depths of his com¬
mitment to the Revolution and pervaded his in¬
tellectual life.
In the space of a few years, the atmosphere
of universal fraternity and human solidarity, un¬
equalled in modern times, which had reigned at
the beginning of the Revolution, gave way to ar¬
bitrary rule and fear. Could Paris, capital of hope
and refuge of the free from all over the world,
be relentlessly pursuing those she had so warm¬
ly welcomed? What had happened? Could it be
explained by the collapse of the Revolution in
face of the absolutist monarchies of Europe? Or
by a gradual move towards dictatorship? Or by
a stroke of fate that Cloots, before mounting the
scaffold, described in these terms: "Revolution,
men have been thy undoing."? How did the
foreigners who rallied to the Republic live
through this drama? What lessons did they learn
from it?
These questions continue to haunt not only
historians but all free people, not only in France,
but throughout the world.
1. The Fête de la Federation was a festival held on 14 July 1790
to commemorate the first anniversary of the fall of the Bastille.
2. The "field of the Federation", now the Champ de Mars in
Paris. Editor.
Left, a Polish engraving
celebrating French liberty
V*
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Thomas Paine
The antimonarchist who
tried to save a King
BY JEAN LESSAY
From L'Américain de la Convention, Thomas Paine,
professeur de révolutions, Perrin publishers, Paris 1987
I
18
T was 11 December 1792, and a trial that the Girondins were unable to
delay any longer was due to open before the Conventionthe trial of King
Louis XVI.
The foremost and most inflexible champion of the Republic, Tom Paine
did not believe in the inviolability of the sovereign. His position on this point
was clear. Louis Capetthe name he was among the first to use to designate
the kingwas subject to the judgement of the French people.
"I think it necessary that Louis XVI be tried, not out of a spirit of ven¬
geance, but because such a step seems to me to be just, legitimate and in con¬
formity with wise policy. If Louis is innocent, let us give him the opportuni¬
ty to prove his innocence. If he is guilty, then let the nation decide whether
he is to be pardoned or punished."
But putting the king to death might provide England, in its turn, with
a pretext to declare war. Would this be in France's interest? Furthermore,
execution of the kingand Paine could bear witness to thiswould be badly
received in America, France's foremost ally, whose help with supplies she
needed at this time. Although they were confirmed Republicans, the Ameri¬
cans had not forgotten that Louis XVI had given them his constant support
during the course of their own revolution. Would not his execution appear,
in some way, as a way of punishing him for having acted thus? Whilst taking
advantage of the pretext of the execution to declare war, hypocritical En¬
gland would delight in seeing the French themselves become the instrument
of their vengeance by killing her former enemy and the ally of her rebel
colonists. Did they really want to give such pleasure to the tyrant George III?
On 15 January 1793, Paine, as a deputy to the Convention, put forward
his arguments before the assembly:
"Citizen President, my hatred of and aversion to monarchy are well
known. They are based on reason and on conviction, and you would have
to take my life before you could eradicate them. Yet my compassion for any
man in his misfortune, whether he be enemy or friend, is just as keen and
sincere..."
There were, he added, grounds for abolishing capital punishment, that
cruel vestige of the monarchical régime; furthermore, the Convention had
been given no mandate to kill anyone. "Abolition of the death penalty has
already been proposed, and I recall with great pleasure the excellent speech
on this subject pronounced by Robespierre in the Constituent Assembly...
Since France has been the first of all the nations in Europe to abolish royalty,
let her be also the first to abolish the death penalty and to substitute for it
some other punishment."
Paine pointed out that it is impossible to eliminate monarchy simply by
eliminating the king, since the execution of Charles I had not prevented
Charles II from coming to the throne. He also drew attention to another
point which was worth consideration. So long as Louis XVI was alive, his
two brothers, the Comte de Provence and the Comte d'Artois, could not
lay claim to the throne. To kill the king would be to furnish them with a
pretext to give free rein to their ambitions as possible successors.
His speech ended with this twofold proposition: that the Convention
should pronounce the sentence of banishment upon Louis Capet and his fa¬
mily, that Louis Capet should be detained in prison until the end of the war
and that the sentence should come into force at that time.
1 he Convention
decrees the abolition of
slavery in the French
colonies on 4 February
1794. Drawing by
Nicolas André Monsiau
(1754-1837).
JEAN LESSAY,
a French writer specializing
in the American
Revolution, has published
studies on Lafayette
(Bordas, Paris, 1983) and
Washington (J.-C. Lattes,
Paris, 1985). His book on
the Count of Rivarol, a
royalist in the era of the
French Revolution, will be
published shortly.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
<F fe- I m
An IDEA
THAT CHANGED
THE WORLD
The ideas and principles of the French
Revolution were fully implemented on
the island ofSan Domingo, one of the
worst ofall colonial societies, the anti¬
thesis ofEnlightenment Europe Here, in
the future Republic of Haiti, came
revolt, the abolition of slavery, and
independence
In the Antilles,
'Liberty for alV
BY YVES BENOT
%HEN the alarm bells of insurrection rang in
Paris in July 1789, what could a plantation slave
in the Antilles, in Guyana or in the Mascarene
Islands know or make of these happenings in a
far-off land? The question is all the more perti¬
nent in that the victory of the people of Paris on
14 July was not achieved swiftly, with the sud¬
denness of a thunder-clap. It was the fruit of sever¬
al months of intense political activity, of waiting,
of hope, of a release of tension expressed in in¬
numerable tracts and pamphlets.
Overseas, the France of the ancien régime
consisted of three social strata: the whites, the
dominant, governing majority, numbering
75,000; the 35,000 "coloureds and free blacks"
(known as mulattos), who were theoretically free,
but whose status was inferior to that of the
whites; and the 750,000-strong mass of black or
half-caste slaves. This population was spread out
over five Caribbean islands (San Domingo, Mar¬
tinique, Guadeloupe, St. Lucia and Tobago), two
islands in the Indian Ocean (the Ile de France,
today Mauritius, and the He Bourbon, today La
Réunion), plus Guyana and St. Louis, the form¬
er capital of Senegal.
Among these overseas territories, both by the
number of slaves and the wealth it engendered,
San Domingo had the lion's share, with at least
two-thirds of the slaves, half the whites and two-
thirds of the half-castes. Yet San Domingo (to be 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
precise the French part of the island with its
northern, western and southern regions, the rest
belonging to Spain) attracts our particular atten¬
tion because another revolution broke out and
triumphed there at the same time as the Revolu¬
tion in France. Reflecting the prosperity of the
slave trade in the mother country, slave-ship ac¬
tivity in the Atlantic and Channel ports (Le
Havre, Honfleur, Saint Malo, Nantes, La
Rochelle and Bordeaux) did not let up: of the
3,300 slaving expeditions recorded from 1713, 420
took place between 1 January 1789 and 31 Janu¬
ary 1793.
The flash-point, a false rumour
The slaves did not wait for the sound of the can¬
non of the Bastille to rise in revolt. Despite the
absence of books and newspapers, the memory
of these heroic uprisings remains alive in the oral
tradition. In San Domingo this memory goes
20
back to 1758 and to the maroon (runaway slave)
insurgent Macandal. None of these uprisings had
succeeded, it is true, but a group of maroons, the
Barohucos, established themselves on the fronti¬
er between the French and Spanish possessions
and by 1784, after almost a century of resistance,
had obtained the recognition of the authorities.
Meanwhile, desertions from work, flight to the
maquis and revolts in one or another plantation
never stopped.
Even before the news of the taking of the
Bastille reached the islands, another false rumour
was abroadthat the king had granted freedom
to the slaves but the governors and the colonists
were opposed to this and were keeping the news
secret. One can speculate that this strange rumour
originated with the convocation of the States
General, the freedom of expression and publica¬
tion conceded temporarily for the period of the
elections and perhaps from the speeches of the
Marquis de Condorcet and the activities of the
Society of Friends of the Blacks. However this
may be, the rumour acted as a spur to the rising
of slaves in Saint Pierre, Martinique, at the end
of August 1789.
When towards the middle of September 1789
the news of the Paris revolt ofJuly finally reached
the islands, it was received with different feelings
and was differently interpreted in the various cir¬
cles of colonial society. For the whites, the liberty
thus acquired simply meant rejection of the pow¬
ers of the governors and other servants of the king
and thus authorization to give free rein to their
convictions and desires. Since these convictions
were not the same for the planters as for the
tradesmen and craftsmen of the towns, violent
conflicts arose. Some proclaimed themselves to
be Patriots (and later Republicans or even
Jacobins), while others declared their loyalty to
the king and to the ancien régime.
Patriot or royalist
but still pro-slavery
The political labels imported from France
changed meaning completely, however, when
used by the whites of the colonies. "Patriots" and
"Royalists" were united in their common pro-
slavery stance and, in San Domingo at least, in
their hatred of their mulatto competitors. This
was not clearly understood in Paris where the
Patriots thought of the "Patriots" of the colo¬
nies as their brothers. The Declaration of the
Rights of Man and of the Citizen was of little con¬
cern to the members of this white minority who
took it for granted that only they could claim the
rights of citizens. Aware of the dangers of the sit¬
uation, however, the whites of San Domingo hur¬
riedly established censorship of mail coming from
France and treated the mere fact of reading the
Declaration to slaves or free coloureds as a seri¬
ous offence.
In San Domingo, the slaves, just like the in¬
habitants of the popular quarters of Paris, saw
in the revolutionary cockade the symbol of
liberty. But here, as in Martinique and
Guadeloupe, those who demanded this liberty
were immediately executed in the traditional
manner, being first beaten and then hanged. From
1789 to 1791, the slave population of San Domin¬
go experienced or was subjected to conflicts be¬
tween whites themselves and between whites and
free coloureds, repression by the whites and the
colonial militia, made up of mulattos, of sporad¬
ic attempts to achieve liberation and the silence
of the French Constituent Assembly on the ques¬
tion of slavery.
In August 1791, there was a massive, violent
uprising by the slaves of the northern plain, the
richest area of the colony. Basing itself on the
provisional ideology of a "King Liberator", this
insurrection upset all previously accepted ele¬
ments of the situation. Despite a series of cam¬
paigns against the slave trade and, to some extent,
against slavery itself, the Constituent Assembly
refused to make any move against the slave sys-
Above and left, Colonists
and Punishments (1989), a
diptych by the Haitian
painter Edouard Duval-
Carrie.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Republican army of
San Domingo (1988), oil
on canvas by the Haitian
painter Edouard Duval-
Carrie. The central figure is
François Dominique
Toussaint, known to
history as Toussaint
¿ouverture (1743-1803). A
former slave, leader of the
black insurgents of San
Domingo, he entered the
service of the French
Republic after the abolition
of slavery. In 1796 he
gradually achieved control
of the island, expelling the
Spaniards, forcing the
British to withdraw, and
setting forth a Constitution
which made him the
president for life of the first
black republic in history,
what is now Haiti.
Arrested on the orders of
Bonaparte, he was deported
to France where he died in
1803.
tern. On the contrary, by recognizing the legali¬
ty of the colonial assemblies, which were domi¬
nated by the large plantation owners, and by
undertaking to make no changes to "the status
of individuals" (in other words, the status of the
slaves) except at the request of the colonial assem¬
blies (in other words, never), the Constituent As¬
sembly reinforced the status quo. This, perhaps,
explains why the slaves, who had at first en¬
thusiastically adopted the symbols of the Paris
revolution, made their appearance on the politi¬
cal scene draped in the white flag of the ancien
régime. In fact, they were no more Royalists than
the "Patriots" of the colonies were Patriots in
the French sense of the word. From the very start
there was no doubt at all about the revolution¬
ary nature of the general uprising of the slaves
of the northern part of the island.
Liberty for all
From the famous night of 23 August 1791, the
insurrectionists numbered 50,000. And the strug¬
gle continued after their leaders were tempted,
in December, to accept the offer of an honoura¬
ble compromise which, in the end, the whites
withdrew. With covert aid from the Spanish
authorities, which became overt after the out¬
break of hostilities with Bourbon Spain in 1793,
they held out throughout 1792. The constant ob¬
jective of the black insurgent army, which was
proclaimed and then achieved by Toussaint Lou-
verture, was "Liberty for All". This did not mean
obtaining freedom for a few slaves at the whim
of their masters, or the recognition of a few
groups of maroons, as had been the case in 1784.
Neither did it mean the kind of conditional
liberty obtained by the North American slaves
who enlisted in the British army at the time of
the War of Independence. The slogan "Liberty
for All" meant the immediate and uncondition¬
al abolition of slavery. Thus it was these slaves,
officially Royalists though they may have been,
and not one or other group of whites or mulat¬
tos, rather hastily assimilated to the colonial
Third Estate, who fought to make the Declara¬
tion of Rights a reality in the Tropics.
A step towards the abolition
of slavery
It might well have been thought that Article I
of the Declaration of the Rights of Man and of
the Citizen of 1789, "Men are born and remain
free and equal in rights...", and, more specifical¬
ly, Article XVIII of the Constitution of the year
I (1793), "No man can be sold or sell himself; his
person is an inalienable property", both implied
freedom for all. Yet the silence of the Constituent
Assembly on this was "echoed" by its successor,
the Legislative Assembly (1791-1792), whose
progress was limited to a concern for equality for 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
mulattos. For nearly a year and a half after that,
the National Convention continued in this way
and the voices raised in protest were ignored.
Among those who spoke out were two men,
Sonthonax and Polverel, then journalists, whom
the Legislative Assembly and then the Conven¬
tion had sent to San Domingo as civil commis¬
sioners with extensive powers, not to abolish
slavery but to supervise the application of the law
of 4 April 1792 on full equality for "coloureds
and free blacks" and nothing more. Of course, ,
they also had to proclaim the Republic and then
ensure the defence of the island after the begin¬
ning of the war with Britain and Spain. It required
>ra«ft«»3£
1 he opening of the States
General by Louis XVI in
the great hall of the Hôtel
des Menus Plaisirs at
Versailles on 5 May 1789.
For the first time since
1614 a King of France
publicly and solemnly
addressed the representatives
of the nation.
22
YVES BENOT,
of France, is a teacher,
journalist and writer.
Among his published works
are Diderot, de l'athéisme à
Vanti-colonialisme ("Diderot,
from Atheism to Anti-
Colonialism", Paris, 1970)
and La Révolution française
et la fin des colonies ("The
French Revolution and the
End of the Colonies", Paris,
1988).
the persistence and resistance of the black insur¬
rection to force them to go beyond the powers
expressly vested in them and to act not only in
conformity with the law but also in accordance
with the dictates of their own consciences. Fur¬
thermore, they had to call on the slaves of the
Cape and the Cape region to put down the white
rebellion led by General Galbaud on 21 June
1793. Of course, the slaves who came to fight for
the Republic were immediately granted their
liberty; but this was still not enough.
Slavery effectively abolished
for the first time
On 29 August, Sonthonax finally decided to
proclaim the immediate and unconditional abo¬
lition of slavery in the northern region. On 21
September, his colleague Polverel followed suit
for the southern and western regions. Unlike the
abolition decrees of the nineteenth century, these
allowed for no form of indemnity for the slaves'
former owners. This was a logical decision in
view of the fact that, according to the Declara¬
tion of Rights, slavery was contrary to natural
law and therefore could not be recognized in
any way.
The two decrees of Sonthonax and Polverel
were the first decrees declaring the abolition of
slavery issued by any slave-trading European
power. The famous decree of the Convention of
16 Pluviôse of the year II (4 February 1794)
abolishing slavery merely ratified a fait accompli
and made it applicable to all French colonies,
something the Committee of Public Safety failed
to do for the Indian Ocean islands or for Saint-
Louis, Senegal. In any event, in San Domingo
there came about a convergence between the con¬
victions of the envoys of the Convention, as well
as Governor Laveaux, and the realityof the situ¬
ation created by the tenacious insurrection of the
former slaves. It required this convergence with
an insurrection that was not merely a distant
aspect of the French Revolution, but a revolu¬
tion in its own right, to convert the abstract
general principles of 1789 and 1793 into the first
effective abolition of the slave system.
It should, however, be emphasized that
whereas in the northern region abolition seems
to have been imposed by the military and politi¬
cal situation, this was not the case in the west and
south. In these two regions the uprising was
either put down, indeed crushed (at Les Cayes),
or else it had no permanence. Thus, Polverel,
who signed the decree of 21 September, effective¬
ly liberated a large number of town and planta¬
tion slaves who, until then, had been forced to
work in servitude.
Toussaint Louverture
rallies to the Republic
Other circumstances arose which led Toussaint
Louverture to inform General Laveaux on 6 May
1794 that he was rallying to the support of the
Republic with an army of between 4,000 and
5,000 men. One of these was the policy adopted
by the British, who invaded the island with the
help of French émigrés and re-established slavery
everywhere. Another was a change of policy by
the Spanish who, having first backed the black
insurrection as a military force, decided to align
themselves with British policy. Another, perhaps,
was a bluff by Sonthonax who, at the end of
February 1794, took the risk of announcing the
abolition of slavery by the Convention, when he
could not have known of itLaveaux and Tous¬
saint Louverture did not receive official confir¬
mation of the Paris decree until the beginning of
July 1794. In any event, since abolition of slav¬
ery was supported only by France, Toussaint
Louverture rallied to the Republic because in that
way his own objective of freedom for all would
be realized.
Under Toussaint Louverture, in the new kind
of state that he was to build with his own hands
in San Domingo, the slogan of liberty for all was
to take on a new meaning, perhaps unique in his¬
tory, just as the constitutional situation of the
colony was unique from 1797 onwards. In that
year, Toussaint Louverture, a general of the
French Republic, was named Governor by Son¬
thonax in the name of France, a position he was
to hold until 1801. In fact, from 1797 he was the
only real power in the colony, the representatives
of the Directory Sonthonax, whom he sent
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
packing in August 1797, Hédouville, who
suffered the same fate a year later, and Roume,
who stayed until 1801no longer took any deci¬
sions. It was a de facto independence, yet formally
within the framework of the French Republic,
the only European power to have made the abo¬
lition of slavery part of its fundamental code of
law.
But independence for whom? Clearly, the
overwhelming majority of the "newly-freed", the
former slaves, benefited from it, but so too did
the mulattos. It is true that Toussaint Louverture
waged war against some of them between 1799
and 1800. Yet this was not a war against mulat¬
tos as such but against the attempt of the southern
region to secede under the mulatto leader, Gener¬
al Rigaud. Before, during and after these hostili¬
ties Toussaint Louverture always hoped that the
mulattos would take their proper place in the
new unitary state. Independence was also on offer
for those whites who were prepared to work
August 1791: the
beginning of the
insurrection of the black
slaves of San Domingo.
within the new system, whether as planters,
magistrates or technicians. Thus, the first state
to emerge from the revolt of a European colony
was, in the widest sense of the term, a non-racial
state in which flourished the equality of men of
a variety of origins, traditions and cultures.
Whites and a mulatto were among the chief
draughtsmen of the constitution Toussaint Lou¬
verture had drawn up in 1801. It was this type
of revolution, based on human fraternity, that
Bonaparte set out to destroy when he came to
power, just as he put an end to the Revolution
in France itself.
Nevertheless, Toussaint Louverture's origi¬
nal initiative, which, after his death in prison in
1803 at Fort-de-Joux in the French Jura, was to
lead to the independence fought for and won by
Dessalines, remains a solid illustration of how the
principles of the Enlightenment and of 1789 were
brought to fulfilment outside the bounds of the
Old World of Europe. 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
>;-; írí*i~ v>
24
Above, the Sphinx at
Giza, a work by
Dominique Vivant, baron
Denon, a French engraver
and administrator who
accompanied Napoleon
Bonaparte to Egypt. Right,
a portrayal of Bonaparte's
entry into Cairo in July
1798, by Auguste Raffet, a
French painter and
engraver of the first half of
the 19th century.
MAHMOUD HUSSEIN
is the pen name of two
Egyptian writers who have
published several books of
political sociology, most
recently Versant sud de la
liberté, Essai sur l'émergence
de l'individu dans le tiers
monde ("The Southern Face
of Liberty, an essay on the
emergence of the individual
in the Third World", La
Découverte, Paris, 1989).
*f£-":
ÜiC .: ü^*.	». -. w «,.-	
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
An idea
that changed
the world
The eagle
and the sphinx
The Egyptian campaign led by BotlUpUTte
Mzpoleon Bonaparte was meant to liber- Jfi Egypt
ate Egyptfrom her overlords and estab¬
lish a regime based on Enlightenment
precepts. However, as a result ofthe clash
of cultures and military failure things
turned out differently. All the same, the
ideas of 1789 took root in Egypt... but
in unexpected ways.
BY MAHMOUD HUSSEIN
I,N March 1798 the executive Directory of the
French Republic decided to despatch a military
expedition to Egypt under the command of
General Bonaparte.
In a paper presented in support of this plan,
French Foreign Minister Talleyrand wrote:
"Egypt was once a province of the Roman
Republic; she must now become a province of
the French Republic. The Roman conquest
marked the period of this beautiful country's
decadence; the French conquest will herald the
era of her prosperity. The Romans seized Egypt
from a line of kings renowned in the arts and
sciences; the French will rescue her from the
hands of the vilest tyrants who have ever existed."
The general in charge of the expedition was
therefore instructed both to "cut off the isthmus
of Suez and to take the necessary measures to en¬
sure for the French Republic full control of the
Red Sea" and "to improve the lot of the native
inhabitants of Egypt by all the means in his
power." 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26
The army was accompanied by a Commission
des Sciences et des Arts, a group consisting of lead¬
ing figures in the sciences and the arts among
whom were such famous men as the mathemati¬
cian Gaspard Monge and the chemist Claude Ber-
thollet as well as a galaxy of talented engineers,
architects, biologists, chemists, writers, painters
and sketch-artists. Taken as a whole, the 165
members of the Commission constituted a verita¬
ble walking encyclopaedia, a modern administra¬
tion in embryo and a "centre of excellence" for
the promotion of intellectual and material
progress.
Make war on the Mamluks
Respect the Egyptians
"Here I am," wrote Monge, "transformed into
an argonaut, carrying the torch of Reason in a
land where for years its light has ceased to
shine...." Bonaparte and his band of scholars were
imbued with the notion that they were going to
Egypt, not only to establish a military base as a
bastion against the British, but also, and above
all, to implant the ideals of 1789, by freeing the
country from the medieval grip of the Mamluk
Beys, reviving agriculture and commerce, estab¬
lishing new industries, overcoming the scourge
of endemic diseases and imposing a modern le¬
gal system....
In a message to the soldiers under his com¬
mand, Bonaparte explained that the objective was
not to force the Egyptians into submission, but
rather to gain their support by defeating their op¬
pressors, the Mamluks. "You will find that the
customs here," he told them, "are different from
those in Europe; you must get used to them. The
peoples amongst whom we shall find ourselves
treat women differently than we do; but in ev¬
ery country the rapist is considered to be a mon¬
ster.... Pillage enriches only a few and brings
dishonour upon all of us..."
"The general officer commanding expressly
forbids all Frenchmen, whether soldiers or
civilians, to enter mosques or to gather at the en¬
trances to mosques.... It is of supreme importance
that each soldier pays for anything he acquires
in the city and that they [the Egyptians] be
neither cheated nor insulted. We must make
friends of them and make war only on the
Mamluks."
A missed rendezvous
The Mamluks were easily vanquished. But despite
this, the Egyptians on the whole did not frater¬
nize with the French. On the contrary, they rose
up in protest against the French presence, some¬
times even making common cause with their lo¬
cal oppressors. A combination of reasons explains
why this should have been so.
In the first place, despite its revolutionary
motives, the French army was an army of occu¬
pation which had suddenly burst in upon a so
cial and cultural arena totally alien to it. Further¬
more, this army belonged to a country of which
the collective Egyptian experience retained the
most bitter memory, that of the pitiless confron¬
tation between Christendom and Islamthe Cru¬
sades. With the exception of a minority of
intellectuals, who were attracted by the secular
French approach, the Egyptian people saw the
French expedition as a new Crusade.
Secondly, the watchwords of liberty, equali¬
ty and responsibility had too new, too disturb¬
ing a ring to minds dominated by the imperatives
of custom and of the community and too strong¬
ly imbued, over the centuries, with a spirit of sub¬
mission to Mamluk despotism. When Bonaparte
informed leading Egyptian personalities of the
creation of a Divan (Council), whose elected
members would administer the country's inter¬
nal affairs, their reply was that the people would
only obey the orders of the Mamluks. As for
equality, in a country where domestic slavery was
still widespread, the concept seemed as bizarre as
it was disquieting.
Finally, the measures taken by Bonaparte to
rationalize the legal code and to modernize the
administration, were seen by many as a provoca¬
tion. In Cairo, the inhabitants lived in family
groups or in close-knit trade guilds, in sectors
separated from one another by gates which were
only open during the day. When the order was
given to de-compartmentalize the city and to re¬
move these gates, a general feeling of uneasiness
and insecurity resulted. The new consolidated
regulations concerning property, inheritance and
Nlembers of Napoleon's
Egyptian expedition
produced a 5-volume
"Description of Egypt"
illustrated with over 3,000
drawings. The
"Description" covered
many facets of Egyptian
life, from arts and crafts
and household objects to
monuments, zoology and
botany. .
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
taxation by-passed the established patriarchal hi¬
erarchies and local customs. The limit was
reached when soldiers penetrated into the vari¬
ous sectors of the city and even into houses to
impose public health precautions against the
threat of plaguecleaning of streets and houses,
washing of clothing and destruction of the be¬
longings of people whose deaths were suspected
of being due to plague. This was seen as a viola¬
tion of the privacy of the home.
Too many changes, introduced too rapidly,
overturned centuries-old values. Popular discon¬
tent, exploited by the Ottomans and the Mam¬
luks and channelled by religious leaders, led to
a succession of riots, which were bloodily sup¬
pressed. The gulf widened between the deep heart
of Egypt and an army decimated by disease, its
fleet destroyed by the British, which was find¬
ing its position increasingly difficult to maintain
and whose only thought was to return home.
Three years after it had set out, the French
expedition ended in complete military failure.
The revolutionary backlash
Paradoxically, it was at this moment that revolu¬
tionary thought began to exercise a deep cultur¬
al, intellectual and political influence. Once the
occupier was no longer physically present, once
the brutalities of oppression were forgotten and
the daily affronts that French behaviour inflict¬
ed on believers and on local traditions were a
thing of the past, the revolutionary message be¬
gan to spread insidiously in the minds of men.
An illustrious witness of these events, the
chronicler Djabarti, relates that no sooner had the
French army left than the former Ottoman and
Mamluk overlords, anxious to re-establish their
weakened authority over the population, began
increasingly to resort to arbitrary measures and
acts of cruelty. The people then began to appreci¬
ate the difference between a modern administra¬
tion and despotic power and to regret the absence
of laws which, though they had jolted them out
of their accustomed ways, at least were universal
in their application. They recalled that Bonaparte
had had soldiers of his own army shot for steal¬
ing a chicken from a peasant, whereas the Mam¬
luks did not hesitate to pillage entire villages.
Some Egyptian intellectuals started to voice
the respect inspired in them by the French scho¬
lars accompanying the expedition and the admi¬
ration they had felt when hearing them explain
their discoveries and inventions and, perhaps even
more, listening as they spoke of life, society and
progress in terms which threw open to them
hitherto unsuspected intellectual perspectives.
What the Egyptians discerned in the words
JVluhammad Ali
(1769-1849), viceroy of
Egypt (1804-1849).
izz£s%J^
of the French was an appeal to overcome their
feelings of inferiority, to take charge of their own
affairs, to think not only of their duties but also
of their rights, to go beyond their present mis¬
fortunes and look to the possibility of change,
to a future which would be more than a cons¬
tant repetition of the past. This was a summons
to escape from a universe dominated by intangi¬
ble, revealed truths and to enter a world open to
question, to experience, to liberty, in which the
mind, guided by reason, could explore an unlimit¬
ed range of possibilities. The more enlightened
spirits of the age began to think that only by fol-
ln this work by Auguste
Raffet, Bonaparte is seen
presiding over the Divan
(Council) in Cairo.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Fighting the Mamluks,
detail from a painting by
the French painter
Théodore Géricault-
(1791-1824)
lowing this path could Egypt be awakened from
the sleep into which she had sunk for centuries
and be given the opportunity to modernize and
recover the prestige that had been hers in the
heroic age of Saladin.
Muhammad Ali,
enlightened despot
Two of these intellectuals, Djabarti and 'Attar,
reflected on how Egyptians could become recep¬
tive to this new way of thinking that had reached
them from the other side of the Mediterranean.
They came to the conclusion that the first thing
to be done was to reform the educational system.
This they thought could be achieved by creating
a new type of school in which a rational approach
based on experience would be taught, and by
sending Egyptian students to France where they
could imbibe the spirit of progress.
Their plans were to be realized thanks to an
unforeseen political occurrence, the seizure of
power by Muhammad Ali. An Albanian by birth
and head of one of the Ottoman brigades sent to
regain control of Egypt at the time when the
French army was preparing to leave, Muhammad
Ali was quick to grasp the radical novelty of the
ideas, the organization and the techniques that
the French expedition had displayed and the ad¬
vantages that could be drawn from them by a
governor anxious to redress a country rapidly fall¬
ing apart.
He began by consolidating his political
authority by allying himself with the country's
spiritual and intellectual leaders and then massacr¬
ing the leading Mamluk chiefs. With the reins of
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
power in his hands, he obtained the Ottoman sul¬
tan's recognition of his status as Governor of
Egypt and then launched into an enterprise com¬
parable in scope to that to be undertaken thirty
years later by the Meiji in Japanthe moderni¬
zation, enforced from the top, of a patriarchal
society.
He reorganized the central structures of the
state, established civil and military manufactur¬
ing plants, and set up an army. He took as models
the officers and scholars of the French expedition,
in all respects except onethe spirit of individu¬
al initiative. For it was not a question of strength¬
ening private as against state enterprise, but of
reinforcing the state against private feudal power.
The door was cautiously opened to Western
science and technology. Scholars and European
specialists were summoned to Egypt. Egyptian
students were sent to Europe. Schools were creat¬
ed in which learning by heart and recitation gave
way to experiment and reasoning.
Agriculture was reorganized and the adminis¬
trative system reunified. The centralized irriga¬
tion system, left in ruins by the Mamluks, was
reestablished. A transportation network was
formed to link the various regions of the coun¬
try to the capital and to the port of Alexandria.
A new police structure was established which
gave the people a sense of security they had not
known for centuries.
Thus, an orderly, enlightened dictatorship
replaced the previous corrupt, anarchic
despotism. The hand of the state became more
strongly felt in the daily life of the people, but,
on the other hand, horizons began to widen and
a sense of space, movement and change began to
permeate a hitherto stagnant existence. For those
called upon to work in the factories or to enlist
in the army, the whole pattern and setting of life
was revolutionized.
Under pressure from the state, the different
strata of society supplied the manpower neces¬
sary for the modernization programme. From the
ranks of the ulemas (the learned of Islam) came
the intellectuals who were to learn the lessons of
the West. From the artisans, and later even from
among the peasantry, came the workers who
were to man the state factories.
A great power in the making
Muhammad Ali did not stop there. If Egypt was
to become an industrial power, it was so that she
could also become an Arab military power. To
create an army modelled on that of Bonaparte
rather thanthat of the Mamluks, Muhammad Ali
took the bold step of introducing conscription.
The peasant communities would provide the rank
and file recruits; the officer corps would be
recruited from among the sons of heads of the
richer families.
Prompted by Muhammad Ali, the moral
shake-up produced by the French expedition was
bringing about a major social upheaval. Starting
from the pinnacle of power, the shock-wave of
the technological characteristics that had brought
about the modernization of the West was now
travelling downwards through the structure of a
traditional community.
In a quarter of a century, Egypt thus became
a great regional power whose armies were on the
advance both north and south and whose victo¬
ries were beginning to galvanize the Arab peo¬
ples. Her political and military élan was to be
disrupted when London and Paris joined forces
to prevent the emergence, around the figure of
Muhammad Ali, of a dynamic, conquering Arab
nation. From then on, Egypt, like the other coun¬
tries south of the Mediterranean, was condemned
to economic colonization.
Pathways to modernity
New pathways had to be taken if the concepts
of the Enlightenment were to suffuse the minds
of men. Intellectuals rather than the state became
the chosen vehicle and the shackles of despotism
were gradually thrown off. The spirit of progress
became associated with the spirit of liberty and
justice. The ideas of the Enlightenment fertilized
trends of thought in which change, reform and
the struggle against the arbitrary were to take on
increasing importance.
Tahtawi, who towards the end of the 1820s
had led the first Egyptian student mission to
France, opened the way to a new, rational con¬
sideration of a modern Egypt in which all should
be equal in the eyes of the law. From then on,
a liberal tradition emerged upon whose roll of
honour are inscribed such prestigious names as
Loutfi Al Sayyed and Taha Hussein, and in the
wake of which, in the aftermath of the First
World War, the national Wafd party was born.
Religious thought itself came into question.
To take up the challenge of the West, reformers
such as Afghani and Abduh called for a "Renais¬
sance", which, for them, meant a return to the
original sources of the Holy Message and the
selective integration of certain European social
contributions.
The great debate on the ways and means of
coming to grips with the modern world was
open. It has continued, on an ever-increasing
scale, right up to the present day.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
%J789
An idea
that changed
the world
Sieyès, Herder, Goethe
Universality
and national
identity
BY ALAIN FINKIELKRAUT
Herder and the German Romantics
contested the universalist concept ofthe
nation which France proposed to the
rest ofEurope in 1789 on the grounds
that each people had a unique "soul".
Goethe was the only thinker ofhis time
to go beyond this contradiction between
the universal and the specific when he
affirmed that all cultures can aspire to
universality.
%
is aHE nation," wrote the Abbé Sieyès,
group of associates living under a common sys¬
tem of laws and represented by a single legisla¬
ture."1 In making use of the term "associates"
he wiped out with a single stroke of the pen the
traditions of a thousand years and consigned
France's national history to the waste-paper
basket. The division of the people into "Three
Estates" was abolishedthere were no longer
nobles, priests, judges, commoners or peasants,
but only people enjoying the same rights and sub¬
ject to the same responsibilities. With a word
Sieyès pronounced the end of the hereditary sys¬
tem; anyone who claimed special legal status
merely on the basis of ancestry was thereby ex¬
cluded from the body of the nation.
Contradicting its own etymological roots, the
revolutionary nation (the word "nation" comes
from the Latin "nasci", meaning "to be born")
thus uprooted individuals, redefining them in
terms of their humanity rather than their birth.
It was.not a question of restoring a collective iden¬
tity to human beings without status or social
moorings; on the contrary, it was a matter of
releasing them from all specific restrictive bonds
and making a radical affirmation of their
tonomy.
Between 1795 and 1799
France was governed by the
Directory. Executive power
was in the hands of 5
Directors elected by a
"Council ofAncients".
Above, Emmanuel Joseph
Sieyès (1748-1836) wearing
his Director's uniform.
au-
30
The nation: a free
and voluntary association
Not only were they freed from the shackles of
their ancestry but also from the spiritual power
La Liberté (1793-1794) by
Nanine Vallain.
Brandishing the pike and
red bonnet of the sans¬
culottes in one hand and
holding the Declaration of
the Rights ofMan in the
other, she treads the chains
of slavery underfoot.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
-
Er
mW
^^^^^^^^^1
m
là 4
H 1
1
- ^H
m
LÉ
'
m -
V N. f-fcl i CVi
¡J <4ç_
- . . -
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Kjoethe (centre) surrounded
by German writers. From
left to right: Wieland,
Lessing, Klopstock, Herder
and Schiller.
which had until then ruled over them. Liberated
from God and from their sires, they were under
the tutelage neither of heaven nor heredity. Asso¬
ciates and not subjects, they were, as Sieyès put
it, represented by the same legislature. The source
and legitimacy of the power to which they sub¬
mitted lay in their decision to live together and
to create institutions that were common to all.
The exercise of that power, its limits and its
nature, were defined by z pact. In short, the
government was a property belonging to the
whole nation and of which princes were never
more than "ministers and trustees who held it
in usufruct". If a king misused the authority con¬
tractually delegated to him and treated it as pri¬
vate property, the nation, as Diderot had already
ALAIN FINKIELKRAUT,
French philosopher and
writer, is a professor at the
Ecole Polytechnique, Paris,
and director of Le Messager
européen magazine. An
English edition of his La
défaite de la pensée has
appeared under the title
The Undoing of Thought
(Claridge Press, 1989).
32
indicated in the Encyclopédie, was entitled to
release him from his oath as though he were "a
minor who had acted without full knowledge of
the facts".2 In other words, power no longer
originated from heaven but from below, from the
earth, the people, the union of wills that consti¬
tuted the collective nation.
The concept of the "nation", therefore, burst
upon the historical scene in opposition to both
the privileges of the nobility and royal absolu¬
tism. The social hierarchy was based on birth and
the monarchy on the divine right of kings. In
place of this view of society and this conception
of power, the French Revolution substituted the
image of a free and voluntary association.
Herein, for the conservatives, lay the origi¬
nal sin, the fatal presumption of the revolutiona¬
ries. In coming together with the aim of
establishing a constitution, they believed that
they were reaffirming the primordial pact from
which society had sprung. They took the social
contract as their authority to establish rule by
assembly. The defenders of traditional ways,
however, responded that there had never been
such a contract; a citizen, they maintained, did
not belong to his nation by virtue of the decrees
of his own sovereign will. This notion was no
more than a chimera.
Herder: universal values
vs. diversity
If the philosophers challenged the power of cus¬
tom, it was because they respected abstract, time¬
less principles. They did not hesitate "to ride
roughshod over prejudice, tradition, seniority,
popular consent, authority, in a word, all that
rules the minds of the masses",3 because, with
Plato, they placed the Good above all that exists.
To back up their assessment of the established
order they referred to an absolute standard, an
invariable, compelling notion of right. The
counter-revolutionaries, unwilling to follow them
to these heady heights, found their spokesman
in the German philosopher Herder.
Instead of testing facts against idealist stan¬
dards, Herder showed that these standards them¬
selves were nothing more than acts with a source
and a context. He replaced Goodness, Truth and
Beauty in their original local setting, removing
these eternal verities from their comfortable posi¬
tion in the heavens and bringing them down to
the tiny patch of earth on which they were born.
There are no absolutes, Herder declared; there
are only local values and fortuitously-formed
principles.
Throughout history, or at least from Plato
to Voltaire, human diversity has been weighed
and judged in the court of values; Herder placed
all universal values in the dock and had them tried
and condemned by human diversity.
It took the crushing defeat of the Prussian
army by Napoleon at the battle of Jena in 1806
and the napoleonic occupation to trigger the real
acceptance of these ideas. Germany, a piecemeal
agglomeration of petty principalities, regained its
sense of unity when faced with an all-conquering
France. Glorification of the collective identity
assuaged the mortification of military defeat and
the degrading subjection it entailed. The nation
compensated for the humiliation it was experien¬
cing by the rapturous discovery of its culture.
"Teutonomania" helped the German people to
forget their country's impotence. The universal
values proclaimed by France were challenged in
the name of a specific "Germanity" and poets and
jurists believed it to be their mission to attest to
this ancestral German spirit. The jurists vaunted
traditional solutions, customs, maxims and
sayings that formed the basis of Germanic law,
a collective work forged by the instinctive, un¬
voiced spirit of the nation. The poet's task was to
defend the national genius against the infiltration
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
of foreign ideas, to cleanse the German language
and to replace words of Latin origin with others
that were purely Germanic, to uncover the
buried treasury of popular songs and, by reviv¬
ing them, to recapture the fresh innocence and
perfection of a folklore which sang in unison of
the specific individuality of the people, untar¬
nished by contact with outside influences.
The philosophers of the Enlightenment de¬
fined themselves as "reason's peaceful law¬
makers".4 Advocates of truth and justice, they
propounded the equity of ideal law against
despotism and abuses. For the German Roman¬
tics everything was the reverse. Jurists and writers
took as their first target the notions of universal
reason and of ideal law. Their task was not to
fight against prejudice and ignorance; it was to
give expression to the irreducible particularity of
their culture, the unique soul of the people,
whose guardians they were.
Art, the bond of universality
On 31 January 1827, Goethe, then at the height
of his fame and in the evening of his life, was talk¬
ing to his faithful friend Johann Peter Eckermann
about a Chinese novel he was reading and which
struck him as quite remarkable. Whereas he had
expected the book to be overwhelmingly strange
and picturesque, he had found in it affinities with
his own verse epic Hermann und Dorothea and
with the novels of the English writer Samuel
Richardson. He was surprised not by the book's
exoticism, but by its lack of it. He was intrigued
by the fact that this text, a lone fragment from
a far-off, little-known land, was not a curiosity.
Through this unlikely contact between himself,
a patriarch of Europe, and this Chinese novel,
through the strange feeling of familiarity it
evoked in him, through this bond stretching
across a gulf of differences, he became aware of
the capacity of the mind to overstep social and
historical boundaries. Rooted in a particular soil,
anchored in an epoch, dated and placed, men
could still escape the fatality of their specific
situations. The divisions between them were not
irrevocable. There were placesi.e. books
where mankind could overcome its fragmenta¬
tion into a myriad of localized mental attitudes.
Dazzled by this realization, Goethe immedi¬
ately drew his conclusions from it. Since litera¬
ture was capable of vanquishing or transcending
differences of time, race, language and culture,
then literature should set to work to do so. This
opportunity became for him an ideal. This uto¬
pia, this somewhere beyond time and place, be¬
came his true vocation. Only those books which
went beyond questions merely of "when" and
"where" were of any value.
Goethe had learned from Herder that for
man, language, environment and history were not
secondary attributes or ornaments added to his
fundamental nature. He was very much aware
that no one can be freed by decree from the par
ticular circumstances of his or her birth. For him,
the ethnic group into which a person is born is
not a fortuitous aspect but a constituent element
of that person's existence. Yet Goethe, and this
is the essential point, refused to make a virtue of
necessity. That we were the issue of a particular
tradition and were formed by being part of a par¬
ticular nation was a fact to which, henceforth,
no one could be blind. In no way should this be
considered as a "value". It was a reality which
should be recognized but not worshipped. Breath¬
ing the same air as the other members of their
tribe, born, like everyone else, into a divided
world at a particular time in history, artists could
not claim right away to have achieved universal¬
ity. They instinctively shared the common way
of seeing and judging things and their personali¬
ties were, at first, in no way different from those
of the collective personality which was the source
both of their initial ideas and the words in which
they expressed them. Yet this was not a reason
to exaggerate their rootedness in a place or a lan¬
guage or to raise it to the level of an absolute.
Like Herder, Goethe recognized the con¬
straints on the mind that arose from its being
rooted in a particular community. Unlike Herd¬
er, however, he called upon art not to reinforce
this dependence but to transcend it. A writer's
works should go beyond the Volksgeist and not
be the expression of it. Human culture should un¬
der no circumstances be reduced to being the sum
of specific cultures. This is why Goethe called
upon poets, artists and thinkers to break out of
the national framework to which Herder and his
followers demanded that they should confine
themselves.
Towards a world culture
In his conversation with Eckermann, Goethe re¬
mained calmly confident, maintaining that time
was working towards the emergence of a world
literature. Nationalist fervour was declining as the
memory of the trauma of the napoleonic con¬
quest became blurred and as political romanticism
went into what seemed like an irreversible
decline. Furthermore, a world economic market
was coming into being which would put an end
to national isolationism. Henceforth, no segment
of humanity could live out its history under
wraps, sheltered from the entanglements of the
world economy. Once impermeable barriers
were becoming porous and it seemed that it
would not long be possible to exclude works of
the mind from the generalized commerce in
commodities.
History, as we know, was to give a more
capricious turn to events...
The oath on the Riitli
(1780), by the Swiss
Romantic painter Johann
Heinrich Fuseli (1741-1825),
portrays a legendary episode
in the liberation of
Switzerland.
1. Qu'est-ce que le Tiers-Etat?,
P.U.F. publishers, Paris, 1982.
2. Denis Diderot. Article on
"Autorité Politique" in'the
Encyclopédie.
3. Diderot. Article on
"Eclecticisme" in the
Encyclopédie.
4. Sebastien Roch Nicolas
Chamfort (1740M794), quoted in
Le sacre de l'écrivain by Paul
Bénichou. José Corti publishers,
Paris, 1973. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The republican
dream
In a famous speech delivered at An¬
gostura in 1819 at the opening of the
Congress of Venezuela, Simón Bolívar
set forth the principles which underlay
his political action and his loyal attach¬
ment to a republican régime based on
liberty and equality guaranteed by a
constitution. Extractsfrom this impor¬
tant text are given below.
34
X HE continuation of authority in a single in¬
dividual has frequently been the downfall of
democratic governments. Repeated elections are
essential in popular systems, because nothing is
more dangerous than allowing the same citizen
to remain in power over a long period of time.
The people become accustomed to obeying him,
and he becomes accustomed to commanding
them; this is how power is usurped and tyranny
takes root. The freedom of the Republic must be
jealously safeguarded, and our citizens should just¬
ly fear that the same magistrate who has governed
them for many years might come to rule them
for ever....
A healthy diet offreedom
Freedom, says Rousseau, is a most succulent dish,
but one that is difficult tb digest. Our frail fellow-
citizens will have to build up their strength long
before they are able to digest the life-giving
nutrient of freedom. Will they, with their limbs
stiffened from such long enchainment, their sight
enfeebled by the darkness of their dungeons, and
their spirit crushed by pernicious servitude, be
able to stride firmly toward the august temple of
freedom? Will they be able to gaze unblinkingly
into its splendid rays, and inhale the pure air
which surrounds it?...
Notwithstanding such painful reflections, I
am overwhelmed with joy at the great steps
which our republic has taken in embarking on
its noble course. Imbued with purpose, inspired
by love of justice, aspiring toward perfection, it
has, with the separation of Venezuela from the
Spanish nation, recovered its independence, its
freedom, its equality and its national sovereignty.
By constituting itself as a democratic republic, it
has proscribed the monarchy, distinctions, nobil¬
ity, exemptions, privileges; it has proclaimed hu¬
man rights and endorsed freedom to act, think,
speak and write. These eminently liberal meas¬
ures can never be praised enough for the purity
which inspired them. The first Congress of
Venezuela has inscribed in the annals of our legis¬
lation, in ineradicable letters, the majesty of the
1 he 35-year-old Simón
Bolivar is shown beside an
allegorical figure of
America in this painting
by Pedro José Figueroa.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
people expressed in all its dignity, with the ratifi¬
cation of a social act such as which will ensure
the happiness of a nation....
The sovereign principle
of equality
Does not the Spirit ofLaws state that these should
be suited to the people making them, that only
by a pure coincidence may those of one nation
meet the requirements of another, that the laws
should be suited to the country's physical condi¬
tion, its climate, the quality of its soil, its situa¬
tion, its extent and its people's way of life; that
they should conform to the degree of freedom
that the Constitution can tolerate, to the religion
of the inhabitants, their interests, commerce, cus¬
toms and traditions? This is the code which we
should consult, and not that of Washington!...
Let us remember that our people are neither
European nor North American; they are a com¬
pound of African and American elements, rather
than an emanation of Europe, as even Spain it¬
self is no longer entirely European because of its
African blood, its institutions and character....
The citizens of Venezuela all enjoy, by virtue of
the Constitution, the interpreter of nature, per¬
fect political equality. Whereas equality may not
have been a guiding principle in Athens, France
and America, we ourselves should affirm it in
order to remedy the distinction which apparently
exists.
My opinion, legislators, is that the fundamen¬
tal principle of our system depends directly and
exclusively on equality being established and prac¬
tised in Venezuela.... Nature creates men unequal
in disposition, temperament, force and character.
The laws correct this difference because they
place the individual in society in such a way that
education, industry, the arts, services and virtues
may give him a fictitious equality, properly called
political and social. It is eminently felicitous in¬
spiration to have gathered all the classes in one
state, the diversity of which has grown with the
propagation of the species. By this step alone,
cruel discord has been torn up by its roots. How
many jealousies, rivalries and hatreds have been
thus avoided!
The lessons of history
We must have equality in order to reshape, so
to speak, the human species, with its political
opinions and public customs, into one single
whole. Then, fixing our gaze on the long road
that lies before us, we must devote our attention
to the dangers to be avoided. History should be
our guide on this journey....
And moving from antiquity to modern times
we find England and France the cynosure of all
the nations and providing eloquent lessons of ev¬
ery kind in the realm of government. The Revo¬
lution of these great peoples, like a radiant
meteor, flooded the world with such a profusion
An idea
that changed
the world
of political brilliance that every thinking creature
has been made aware of what man's rights and
duties are and what constitute the vices and vir¬
tues of governments. Everyone today can appreci¬
ate the intrinsic value of the speculative theories
of modern philosophers and legislators....
Legislators, it is fitting to recall what the elo¬
quent Volney says in his preface to The Ruins of
Palmyra: "To the nascent people of the Spanish
Indies, to the generous leaders who guide them
to freedom: may the errors and misfortunes of
the ancient world teach wisdom and happiness
to the new world." The lessons of experience,
therefore, should not be lost; the consequences
of Greece, Rome, France, England and America
should instruct us in the difficult science of creat¬
ing and conserving our nations with their own
just, legitimate and, above all, fitting laws. We
should never forget that the excellence of a
government does not lie in its theories, in its form
or in its mechanisms, but rather in its appropri¬
ateness to the nature and character of the nation
for which it is devised.
Jcene from Bolivar (1943),
an opera by Darius Milhaud
to a libretto by Jules
Supervielle. The décor of this
1950 Paris Opera production
was designed by Fernand
Léger.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Russian poetry, from Pushkin to Osip
Mandelstam, exalts the love of liberty.
It thus has a natural place in the great
debate opened up by the French
Revolution...
Poetry,
freedom and
revolution
BY SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV
i
11. lina'."
:; .iîiiii
sL::
^
36
1 he Moscow Kremlin at the
. beginning of the 19th
century
1 ushkin (3rd seated figure
from left) at a literary
banquet given by a hooksdler
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
V
1789
An idea
that changed
the world
X AR from the tumult of the streets of Paris in
the fateful year of 1789, lay Moscow, rather like
a small country town with its steep streets glit¬
tering with golden domes and crosses. Moscow,
that highly orthodox and patriarchal capital city,
before the fire of 1812 still had reminders at ev¬
ery turn of days long before Peter the Great.
In the entrance hall of the aristocratic man¬
sion of Piotr Alexandrovich Soymonov, in¬
numerable candles gave off a festive glow. They
were the work of the daughter of the house, a
sensitive and intelligent little girl, not quite seven
years old. Her father was surprisedwhy all these
candles? She told him the reason: "In honour of
the storming of the Bastille and the release of the
poor prisoners!"
This little girl did not, however, throw in her
lot with the Jacobins. Sofia Petrovna (1782-1857),
whose married name was Svechin, belongs to the
history of nineteenth-century Catholicism. She
eventually left Russia because of her religious con¬
victions, and for decades her Paris salon was a
meeting-place for the cream of the Catholic in¬
tellectual élite: the liberals Montalembert and
Lacordaire, the Spanish traditionalist Donoso-
Cortès, and many others.
With her phrase "the release of the poor
prisoners" the child went straight to the point
and hit on what was to be the central theme of
Russian life and culture for the next two centu¬
ries. Barely a year after the storming of the
Bastille, and not unconnected with the fear and
panic spread by the events in France, the writer
Aleksandr Radishchev was arrested because of his
book Journey from St. Petersburg to Moscow,
which, like the Revolution itself, was a radical
postscript to the philosophical thought of the En¬
lightenment. On the road to exile, Radishchev
wrote the following lines, full of black humour:
To blaze a trail where none has trod before
For the fiery daredevils of the written word,
For the pure in heart, for Truth, I go in fear
To Siberia, to prison and to chains.
His premonition was correct. The trail was
blazed for many like him, and along it marched
a succession of new "daredevils of the written
word", to use his blunt, old-fashioned expression.
This, too, is one of the hallmarks of Russian cul-
Nladame Svechin as a
child". Sofia Petrovna
Soymonov (1782-1857), the
wife of General Svechin,
left Russia for France in
1816.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
1 his portrait of the French
poet André Chénier was
made in prison by Joseph-
Benoît Suvée 10 days before
Chénier's execution.
38
ture. A century later, the journalist Vladimir
Korolenko declared that at the gates of heaven
every Russian writer would be asked how many
years he had spent in prison for the sake of truth.
And his contemporary, the literary critic Ven-
gerov, wrote a book with an eloquent title: The
Heroic Nature ofRussian Literature. From the ar¬
rest of Radishchev to the repeated exiles of Push¬
kin, the conscription of Pozhelayev and the
jailing of Dostoevsky, to the execution of
Gumilyov and the fate of other twentieth-century
writers condemned to the camps, the line runs
clear and unbroken.
The example
of André Chénier
The Russian people saw the poet primarily as a
martyr. How many Russian laments have been
composed, from Pushkin to Osip Mandelstam,
on the exile of Ovid? But the Roman poet was
the victim of the Emperor Augustus, and his fate
was less tragic than the fate of those involved in
the greater tragedy arising from the tangled web
of the Revolution and the rifts caused by its in¬
trinsic contradictions.
One poet of 200 years ago, who in the Rus¬
sian poetic tradition founded by Pushkin is im¬
bued with the martyr's special significance, is
André Chénier, the great poet of revolutionary
France. Chénier, the citizen-poet, was inspired by
the Revolution and condemned to death by the
Revolution, which sent him to the scaffold just
before the end of the Terror as a last expiatory
victim to be swallowed by the abyss before it
closed as in the ancient legends. Such a man was
André Chénier, or "Andrei" Chénier, as Push¬
kin called him in the fashion of the day, to be
imitated by twentieth-century poets such as Osip
Mandelstam and Marina Tsvetayeva. In Rus¬
sianizing his name, Russian culture adopted him.
Familiarity with the work and ultimate fate
of Chénier, both in France and abroad, had to
wait until 1819, when the first collected edition
of his poetry was published. And scarcely six
years later, the year of the Decembrist uprising
in Russia (1825), Pushkin wrote the long poem
André Chénier. At the time, throughout Europe,
tears were being shed over Byron's death; and yet
Pushkin, for whom Byron had meant so much,
neglected his memory to answer the call of
Chénier, who had entered the kingdom of the
dead "from the blood-stained block", "in terri¬
ble days".
At the heart of the poem lies Chénier's
monologue before his execution. Pushkin's voice
is in total unison with that of his hero, empha¬
sized by the fact that Pushkin quotes from his
own writings in the course of the monologue.
There is no serious divergence of views between
the two men, as Pushkin explains briefly and elo¬
quently in his notes on the poem. A poet, sim¬
ply because he is a poet, is bound to love Liberty,
and in particular that aspect of freedom which
the Revolution proclaims as essential:
/ salute you, my star of light!
I rendered glory to your celestial face
When, like a spark, it rose, and you were bom
in the midst of the storm,
I rendered glory to your sacred thunder
Scourging the foul citadel,
Scattering in cinders and shame
The ancient, arrogant power...
Pushkin rejoices that "arrogant power"
should be held up to scorn, and welcomes
resistance to "absolutism". But when the sover¬
eign is laid low and those who have vanquished
him are about to mete out his punishment, the
poet, because he is a poet, can no longer see him
as the sovereign and the enemy and is forced to
see him as a human being. Pushkin recounts how,
according to Henri de Latouche, André Chénier's
first publisher, Louis XVI sent a serene and dig¬
nified letter to the National Assembly, request¬
ing the right to appeal to the people against his
death sentence. That letter, signed on the night
of 17-18 January 1793, was composed by André
Chénier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Poetry condemns
the death sentence
The guillotine had already put in an appearance
as the "criminal cleaver" in a profoundly subver¬
sive poem of Pushkin's youth, entitled "Liberty".
No poet can ever freely approve a death sentence
because the very soul of poetry, which is Liberty
itself, cannot survive in the spiritual atmosphere
generated by such sentences. Or so Pushkin fer¬
vently believed.
A century later, pleading for the pardon of
several condemned prisoners, Mandelstam sent a
selection of his verses to Nikolay Bukharin with
the note: "Every line of these poems cries out
against what you intend to do". He thus echoes
a sentiment which inspired a line of Pushkin's
poem Exegi Monumentum, in which Pushkin in¬
cludes among his merits as a poet the fact that
"He sought pardon for the fallen". Poetry can¬
not breathe in the atmosphere of death sentences.
To grow accustomed to it, and consequently to
become one with it, is possible only for "litera¬
ture" in a very limited and altogether odious sense
of the term. Fundamentally, poetry condemns
the act of condemnation, and at a stroke it con¬
demns "literature".
Later Mandelstam said: "There were two
Chénier brothers. The younger, who was con¬
temptible, belonged wholly to literature, and the
elder, sentenced to death, pronounced sentence
on that literature". Thus the tradition of Russi¬
an culture remains true to itself, and the thread
is unbroken from Pushkin to Mandelstam.
There have, of course, been Russian poets
who have renounced Pushkin's creed. The
greatest of these apostates was Vladimir
Mayakovsky, a poet whose stature is undeniable.
But willingness to celebrate violence spells sui¬
cide for poetry, and is followed, as a logical con¬
sequence, by the suicide of the poet himself...
For Marina Tsvetayeva, who also inherited
the mantle of Pushkin, the figure of Chénier in
the years of the Civil War was an absolute
paradigm:
André Chénier has gone to the scaffold,
And I am alive, and this is a great sin.
We must not forget that Pushkin's "creed"
took shape against the backdrop of the French
Revolution, and that it was inspired above all by
the example of Chénier. A return to Pushkin
meant, inescapably, a return to Chénier, whose
monologue in Pushkin can be summed up as fol¬
lows: the fervent love of Liberty as the ¡deal driv¬
ing force behind the Revolution brooks no
compromise, even under the threat of the Ter¬
ror; but the Terror must be condemned precise¬
ly in order to safeguard that driving force.
Chénier criticized the Revolution, not from
the outside, but from within. He took as his
starting-point the principles of the Revolution it¬
self, and used its own language, for he had felt
joy at its advent, and never denied that joy after
all his disenchantments. For Pushkin, this lent
great moral strength to Chénier's criticism and
added much weight to his example. And the en¬
tire Russian poetic tradition of the love of liberty
followed Pushkin in his veneration of Chénier
as the bard who sang not of Tradition, but of
Liberty.
Mandelstam's poem on the death of Commis¬
sar Linde, known to readers of Doctor Zhivago
as Commissar Hintz, is a remarkable hymn of
devotion to Chénier; but whereas in Boris Paster¬
nak's novel the circumstances of this death are
related with a great deal of realism and not
without irony tinged with sympathy, in Mandel¬
stam they are described with a passion that is
perhaps unexpected so long after Chénier's exe¬
cution:
Through civil torment in the dreadful years,
Aflame with noble wrath against the foe
You stride, a citizen, fearless, free and true,
Wherever Psyche beckons you to go.
And while the people, jubilant, may weave
For other men their wreaths of laurel, now
Russia will gladly brave the pits of hell
To lay at last her blessings on your brow.
The cadence of the Revolution
Russian awareness of the French Revolution has
always had a musical quality, a certain harmo¬
ny. It is no mere chance that the Russian
nineteenth-century work in which the subtle
wrath of the citizen comes closest to the French
revolutionary tradition is neither a political
pamphlet, nor a philosophical treatise, but some
personal memoirs in which the most direct
threads run between the conflicts of the soul and
the contradictions of the Revolution.
That work is My Past and Thoughts
(1861-1867), by the journalist and political thinker
Aleksandr Herzen. "Herzen, whose tumultuous
political thought will always have the cadence of
a Beethoven sonata", Mandelstam said of him.
This harmony alone saves the debate from being
conducted in a single dimension in that it draws
the contradictions together, if only fleetingly,
into a persuasive unity, according to Hegel's prin¬
ciple that "truth is the whole".
SERGEI SERGEEVICH
AVERINTSEV,
Corresponding Member of
the USSR Academy of
Sciences, is a leading Soviet
specialist in ancient and
medieval cultures and the
author of some 100
published works, including
a study of early Byzantine
poetics (1977).
1 he Russian writer
Aleksandr Radishchev
(1749-1802)
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The concepts ofthe Enlightenment were
introduced into Japan in the late
nineteenth century by Chomin, who
made a major contribution to the
Japanese democratic movement.
Chomin admired the ideas of1789, but
disapproved of the "revolutionary
drama".
hi
fe.KT
4*M
iJk
{ ¿ -*- ¿ i
¿fee / * i
..;, ¿tar ¿a ,
X ortrait of Chomin painted
during his stay in France
(1872-1874). It is superimposed
on a manuscript page of his
Japanese translation ofJean-
Jacques Rousseau's Social
Contract.
40
Revolutionary allegory in
honour ofJean-Jacques
Rousseau
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
^1789
An idea
that changed
the world
Chomin:
The Rousseau
of the East
BY SHIN'YA IDA
X HE Japanese writer, philosopher and politi¬
cian Nakae Tokusuke (1847-1901), more widely
referred to by his nom-de-plume, Chomin, which
means "a thousand million men of the people",
is best known for his remarkable translation of
Jean-Jacques Rousseau's Social Contract.
In fact, he made two translations of the book:
the first into the standard Japanese of the day,
which he wrote on his return from France in
1874, and the second into classical Chinese, the
language of scholars, which he completed be¬
tween 1882 and 1883, at the height of the move¬
ment for liberty and the rights of the people. His
contemporaries called him "The Rousseau of the
East", a nickname that has stuck.
French studies
Born in 1847, at Kochi, capital of the fief of Tosa
on the island of Shikoku, Chomin learned French
at Nagasaki, where he was sent with a bursary,
and then at Edo (now Tokyo), where he became
a pupil of Murakami Eishun, the father of French
studies in Japan. It seems likely that he read Mon-
signor Daniel's Abrégé chronologique de l'histoire
universelle ("Brief Chronological Outline of
World History") while studying under Muraka¬
mi, who was to publish a translation of it in 1871.
The year 1868 saw the collapse of the
Tokugawa Shogunate and the restoration of Im¬
perial rule, and it was during the first year of the
first Meiji era (Meiji means, literally, "enlightened
rule") that Chomin was admitted to Mitsukuri
Rinano's private school. Mitsukuri was the first
Japanese teacher of French to visit France, hav- 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
dâJÂMSM
1 he Emperor Napoleon III
and royal visitors to the
1867 Paris Universal
Exhibition. At right, the
brother of the Japanese
emperor.
SHIN'YA IDA,
of Japan, is a professor of
literature in Tokyo. His
doctoral thesis, on Nakae
Chomin and France, was
published in 1987.
42
ing the previous year accompanied Prince
Tokugawa Minbu's diplomatic mission to Paris
on the occasion of the World Exhibition. It is
very likely that Chomin read Victor Duruy's
Histoire de France ("History of France") whilst
at this school, since Mitsukuri quotes this work
in his Banxoku-Shinshi ("History of Modern
Times"), published in 1871. It is reasonable to as¬
sume, therefore, that Chomin's interest in Rous¬
seau and the French Revolution dates from this
period.
Discovering
the 'philosophes'
The decisive period in Chomin's life was his stay
in France in the early days of the Third Repub¬
lic, when the country was still suffering from the
ravages of the Franco-Prussian War and of the
Commune. Selected as one of the scholars spon¬
sored by the Japanese Government to accompa¬
ny the diplomatic mission headed by Iwakura
Tomomi, in December 1871, he remained in
France for two years.
Little is known of his life during this period.
He scarcely mentions it in his writings and refer¬
ences to it by his follower and biographer Kotoku
Shusui are both brief and vague. "Although he
was sponsored by the Ministry of Justice, my
master nevertheless studied philosophy, history
and literature, and I have heard that he skimmed
through many history books."
Our research on articles translated and pub¬
lished in the Seiri-Sadan ("Political and Moral
Science Review"), founded by Chomin and his
followers, indicate that while in France he prob¬
ably discovered the eighteenth-century philosophes
(Montesquieu, Voltaire, Rousseau, Mirabeau and
Condorcet) and the radical political writers
(Barni, Naquet, Jules Simon, Laboulaye and
Vacherot). Since passages from L'Histoire
parlementaire de la Révolution Française
("Parliamentary History of the French Revolu
tion"), by Bûchez and Roux, appear in transla¬
tion in the Review, it can be assumed that this
forty-volume work in octavo format was among
the "many history books" that Chomin
"skimmed through".
Rousseau reaches Japan
On his return to Japan in June 1874, Chomin
found his fellow countrymen in a state of fer¬
ment. Two former ministers, Itagaki Taisuko and
Goto Shojiro, both, like Chomin, from Tosa, had
just launched the Jiku-Minken-Unao ("Movement
for Liberty and the Rights of the People"). It was
at this time that Chomin translated Rousseau's
Social Contract (Min'yaku-Ron), thus placing a for¬
midable weapon in their hands. At the school of
French he had established (Furanau-Gaku-Sha,
later Futsu-Gaku-Juku) he gave commentaries on
Rousseau in his classes and the militants of the
movement, most of them young, passed the
manuscript of his translation from hand to hand.
"Weeping, we read the Min'yaku-Ron by Russo",
wrote one of these young men in a poem writ¬
ten in Chinese; at the same time, a Prefect for¬
bade the officials of his Department to read
Rousseau.
In May 1875, Chomin was appointed secre¬
tary to the Senate and assigned to the research
department. For a long time his role in this new
institution remained obscure. Following exami¬
nation of the Journal of the Senate, it is now
known that he had already been appointed secre¬
tary when the drafting office of the Constitution
was set up. He was, therefore, at the very heart
of the team preparing the draft constitution,
although in a relatively lowly capacity, since this
process involved comparing the constitutions of
different countries as and when they were trans¬
lated into Japanese from the French jurist
Edouard-Julien Laferrière's book Constitutions
d'Europe et d'Amérique ("Constitutions of Europe
and America").
At the outset, this draft constitution, com¬
pleted in mid-October 1876, provided for only
one legislative chamber, the Senate. How then
did it come about that, by the end of the year,
it included plans for the creation of a Chamber
of Deputies? We do not know whether Chomin
had a hand in this sudden change in state policy.
However that may be, he left the Senate shortly
afterwards, in January 1877.
Mention should be made of the presence in
the drafting office of Kawazu Sukeyuki, who
alone among Chomin's colleagues could read
French. In September 1876 Kawazu began pub¬
lishing his complete translation of Auguste Mig-
net's Histoire de la Révolution Française (1824;
"History of the French Revolution"). Thus
Rousseau and the Revolution were both involved
in the drawing up of the Japanese draft constitu¬
tion, which is considered to be more liberal in
many respects than the Constitution eventually
adopted.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The spirit
of the French Revolution
The second (1878) and third (1880) amendments
to the draft constitution were definitively reject¬
ed by the government ministers Iwakura Tomo-
mi and Ito Hirobumi, who dismissed them
scornfully as being mere "translations" or "re¬
hashes" of European and American constitutions.
Meanwhile, in April 1881, Chomin and his
friends founded the daily newspaper Toyo jiyu
Shimbun ("Liberty of the Orient"). The move¬
ment for the rights of the people was now at its
zenith. In his editorials, Chomin repeatedly called
for the immediate convocation of a National As¬
sembly which, like its French revolutionary
counterpart, would be empowered to draw up
a constitution. He stressed the need for "rigorous
reasoning" and "firmness of will". He counselled
his young readers against "inflammatory
speeches" or "blind, violent action". For him it
was not a question of doing "what France had
done before", but of "seeking its spirit rather
than imitating its actions".
If the French Revolution was to be "imitat¬
ed" only in its "spirit", what other path was there
to follow? Paradoxically, the one taken by the
British. Since, according to Rousseau's theories,
the British monarchy was compatible with the
nature of the Republic, Chomin preferred it to
the French Republican system. Whilst thus ad¬
vising calm and moderation, he did not fail to
point out that a revolution could break out even
in Japan, if the "high ups"members of the
court, ministers and noblespersisted in exercis¬
ing their authority without regard for the rights
of the people.
Japan on the brink
of revolution?
In October 1881, feeling itself threatened by the
rise of the popular movement, the government
oligarchy took the initiative, promising, in the
name of the emperor, to grant a Constitution by.
1889 and establish a Diet for the year after.
In February 1882, at the time when Ito, who
had been entrusted with the task of drawing up
the Constitution, was about to leave on a study
mission to Germany and Austria, Chomin found¬
ed his Political and Moral Science Review. The first
issue opened with the Declaration of the Rights
of Man of 1793 and in the second Chomin be¬
gan the serialization of Rousseau's Social Contract,
both of which he had himself translated into clas¬
sical Chinese.
Chomin's History ofthe Two Reigns in France
before the Revolution (Kakumei-zen-Furansu-Nisei-
Kiji, December 1886) was published three years
before the promulgation of the Imperial Consti¬
tution, the drafting of which was then approach¬
ing its final stage. In compiling this work Chomin
drew mainly on histories of France by Victor
Duruy and Henri Martin. But why did he stop
Inauguration of the first
Japanese railway line at
Yokohama (1872) by
Emperor Mutsuhito
before 1789 instead of writing, as one might have
expected, a history of the Revolution itself?
Chomin himself provided the explanation
when he revealed a clear dichotomy in his ap¬
preciation of the French Revolution. On the one
hand the Revolution was for him "an unheard-
of event in the annals of history which highlight¬
ed the causes of liberty and equality and which,
by transforming the situation of the European
states, succeeded for the first time in basing po¬
litics on the lofty principles of philosophy". On
the other hand, he saw "from the moment of the
convocation of the States General, the seeds of
growing conflict between the court and the peo¬
ple, conflict which inflamed passions and led to
extremes and excess". Primarily a philosopher
rather than a historian, he was more interested
in "the causes of the Revolution" than in its ac¬
tual unfolding, the ferocity of which he found
unbearable.
Chomin likened the French Revolution to "a
great drama" of which philosophers such as Mon¬
tesquieu, Voltaire, Rousseau and the rest were
"the authors" and in which the great revolution¬
aries such as the Abbé Sieyès, Mirabeau,
Vergniaud, Robespierre and Danton were "the
actors".
Yet how could the actors have staged "the
great drama" written by the authors? Only with
the backing of "public opinion, without which
the undertaking would have had no future and
would have ended up crushed by the mighty
power of the court". The final message that Cho¬
min leaves with us is surely this: addressing his
words "to those who foster a high ambition wi¬
thin the nation" he reminds them of the vital
necessity of "forming public opinion". This is
the key to everything.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
4,
1789
An idea
that changed
the world
China:
rethinking
the Revolution
BY ZHILIAN ZHANG
Reform or revolution? This was the
dilemma faced by Chinese élites in
the nineteenth century. The example of
the French Revolution was at the core
of their debates.
44
\juangxu, emperor of
China (1875-1908).
Influenced by the reformer
Kang Youwei, he wished to
modernize the country but
the Empress Dowager Cixi
(Tz'u-hsi) soon put a stop to
his plans.
IN China, the influence of the French Revolu¬
tion was not immediately felt, and it was only
a century later that the ideals of 1789 were ex¬
plicitly voiced.
There were geographical as well as sociolog¬
ical reasons for this time-lag. In the days of sail¬
ing ships, a despatch took at least eight months
to reach Peking from London. Lord Macartney,
head of the first official British mission to
China, left Portsmouth in September 1792, and
did not reach Peking until August 1793.
The imperial court where he was received had
already heard of the events in France, and
rumours of the upheaval caused by the Revolu¬
tion made anything new subject to suspicion. At
the height of its power and prosperity, China had
no need to think of change. The country had a
stable social structure, with no bourgeoisie, no
ideological contention, no political opposition.
If the peasants were unhappy, they were not yet
organized. In China, the time was not ripe for
reform, still less for revolution.
During the nineteenth century pressure for
social and political change began to mount.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Peasant unrest (from the White Lotus uprisings
in the 1790s, to the Taiping insurrection of
1850-1864), foreign aggression (from the First
Opium War with Britain of 1839-1842 to the
French expeditions of the 1880s), economic
decline and widespread corruption, continuous
population growthall these factors sapped the
foundations of the Middle Empire. The crisis be¬
came acute on the eve of the twentieth century
following defeat at the hands of Japan.
Such were the conditions in which Chinese
élites began to study the French Revolution in
the hope of finding solutions to their own
problems.
Monarchs who lose
the people's confidence
The first significant commentary inspired by the
French Revolution was written by the reformer
Wang Tao (1828-1897). In his Compendium on
France he wrote: "Does the calamitous violence
of republican government always lead to such ex¬
cesses? When the rebel parties, in their cruel fury,
do not shrink from committing regicide, where
are a country's laws? What has happened to the
rulers of nature? It is as if Heaven and Earth had
been reversed and the world was upside down...
In all of history surely there has been no rebel¬
lion worse than this. And yet, at the origin of
these calamities, we find the inability [of the
monarch] to conciliate the masses and win the
confidence of his subjects. Presuming upon their
high position, these monarchs fail to identify with
popular fortunes. And mounting resentment is
enough to bring about the demise of royalty...
Such being the case, can rulers do as they please
and behave irresponsibly?"
Wang Tao condemned the rebels but held the
king responsible for the calamity because he had
alienated himself from the people. This was a les¬
son that rulers should draw from the Revolution.
The stirrings of reform
The tide for radical change rose higher in the
1890s and a generation of reformers emerged,
with Kang Youwei (1858-1927) and Liang Qichao
1 easant rising in a
Chinese village (print
dating from around 1895)
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
(1873-1929) in the forefront. Kang won the con¬
fidence of the Emperor Guangxu (but not that
of the Empress Dowager), and dreamt of reform¬
ing the Empire "from the top". True to the clas¬
sical Chinese tradition of using the past to serve
current policies, he was nevertheless an innova¬
tor in that he used the history of a foreign coun¬
try to convince the emperor and the court.
In the preface to his Account of the French
Revolution, dedicated to Guangxu, Kang uncon¬
ditionally condemned the excesses of this "bloo¬
dy revolt": "There has never been anything more
disastrous than the atrocities of modern revolu¬
tion." His censure of Louis XVI was no less se-
46
vere: "Divine right is not granted permanently.
Only by virtuous means can you keep it; other¬
wise, it will be taken from you. Louis XVI's
promise to grant a constitution did not come
from his own initiative but was given under pres¬
sure. His hesitation and oscillation, his initial
recourse to arms and later disbandment of his
guards, and finally his appeal to foreign interven¬
tion and flight to Varennes, stirred up the indig¬
nation of the people to such an extent that he
was sent to the guillotine and scorned by the
world."
Kang felt that popular feelings should be
calmed rather than excited, because the populace,
once aroused to action, is like a rock rolling down
a steep hill; nothing can halt its course. "It may
have been possible for a single person to tyran¬
nize an ignorant mass. But once the people real¬
ize that the world is made for all and not just for
a few, they envy the rich and strive for power
and prestige."
Kang conceded that all modern constitutional
governments originated in the French Revolu¬
tion: "In spite of its aberrations and tyrannical
violence, it was aided by the trend of the times
and the spirit of the people. Like a huge storm
sweeping over and transforming the great earth,
it was indeed something frightening. As there has
not been anything as grandiose in the annals of
political change, it may also serve as an example."
According to Kang Youwei, the obvious les¬
son was that a reform programme should be
launched from above and a constitutional monar
chy be established before the rebellious people
took matters into their own hands and imposed
radical changes from below.
Kang's contemporary Liang Qichao was one
of the first writers to introduce the ideas of the
Enlightenment to the Chinese. In his Life of
Madame Roland, he called the Revolution "the
Mother of European Civilization"; but he repeat¬
edly cited the alleged final words of his heroine
on the scaffold: "Oh, Liberty, what crimes are
committed in thy name!" He rejected oppression
and revolution in the same breath. He was an ad¬
vocate of "destruction without bloodshed". He
warned the conservatives in high places that to
From left to right: Kang
Youwei; Madame Roland;
Liang Qichao
ZHILIAN ZHANG,
of China, is a professor of
history at Beijing
University. President of the
Association for the Study of
French History, a member
of the International
Commission on the History
of the French Revolution,
and editor-in-chief of a
general history of France,
his published works include
an essay entitled From the
Gauls to De Gaulle.
ignore the aspirations of the people would lead
to a new outbreak of the Terror. At the same
time, he made clear to the "pushers in low places"
that if they unleashed the passions of the masses,
the result would be a blood bath and anarchy,
as in France.
The reforms proposed by Kang and his fol¬
lowers, although mild, were not accepted by
those in power.^Six reformers were decapitated.
Kang was obliged to flee to Hong Kong, while
Liang sought refuge in Japan. The attempt at
change was nipped in the bud.
Bloodshed, the price of liberty
A reaction was bound to assert itself from the
revolutionary camp. Not only in China, but also
in Japan where many radicals took shelter fol¬
lowing the failure of the reforms. A torrent of
pamphlets and political papers imbued with the
ideas of 1789 appeared. In the first decade of the
twentieth century, the French Revolution be¬
came the model for the struggle against feudal op¬
pression.
A radical interpretation of the French Revo¬
lution emerged from the writings of the revolu¬
tionists. Rebutting the counter-revolutionary
ideas of Kang Youwei, they stressed the necessi¬
ty of propagating in China ideas of Enlighten¬
ment and revolution. They exalted the spirit of
sacrifice and recourse to violence. They appealed
to men and parties to unite. For the first time,
the names of Montesquieu, Voltaire, Rousseau,
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Turgot, Helvétius, Sieyès and Fourier were on
the lips of Confucian scholars. Journals published
commentaries on the Declaration of the Rights
of Man and of the Citizen. Several versions of
the Marseillaise were circulated.
Criticizing as ridiculous the notion of "des¬
truction without bloodshed", the revolutionists
upheld, on the contrary, that the success of the
revolution depended on violence and sacrifice.
Ready to give their lives, they vowed "to sacrifice
themselves for the rights of the people and to buy
liberty with bloodshed". Was that not how
despotism had been abolished and natural rights
restored in France? A staunch revolutionist from
Hunan exclaimed: "Have you not known the af¬
fairs in France, the homeland of the Social
Contract, the battlefield of freedom? All was ac¬
complished through violence. The Revolution of
1789 was indeed tragic and violent; those of 1830
and 1848 were no less so. The guillotined head
of the King was paraded through the streets of
Paris, while the throngs of people cried out Vive
la liberté! Thrice have they driven away
their king, fourteen times have they changed their
constitutionalways with much bloodshed. Yet
France has become a strong nation."
But how was the unity of the revolutionary
movement and its leaders to be preserved? The
Chinese revolutionists expressed great admiration
for the Jacobin Club which appeared to them as
a "driving force of the Revolution". But they no¬
ticed with regret that political and personal rival¬
ries between Girondins and Montagnards, then
between Dantonists and Robespierrists, finally
led to the downfall of democracy. A revolution¬
ary patriot, Liu Yazi, drew an analogy between
the disputes of leaders in the French Revolution
and the quarrels of leaders in the Taiping Heaven¬
ly Kingdom, as a warning to his comrades.
Thus the long debate on the virtues and
crimes of the French Revolution gradually rein¬
forced the conviction of those who believed that
China needed revolution, not piecemeal change.
A great 'social laboratory'
A new generation of revolutionary leaders came
to the forefront. Many of them discovered their
calling while listening to accounts of the storm¬
ing of the Bastille. In June 1920, a twenty-two-
year-old Chinese youth wrote these lines for a
classmate who was leaving to study in France:
On your return, you will
Hoist the Flag of Liberty
Sing the Song of Independence
Fight for the Rights of Women
And seek for Equality
In the great social laboratory.
The author's name was Zhou Enlai.
1 he Empress Dowager
Cixi (1835-1908) in 1903,
at centre ofphoto
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The spirit of
'89
BY TAHAR BEN JELLOUN
IS it possible to dispense with revolution and its violence, its terror
and its achievements? Is it normal to think that human rights and
democracy bear the stamp of a time and locality specific to one social
and historical setting? Is it logical thus to deny them their principal
quality, their universality? How is it possible to import consumer goods,
cultural debris and weapons from Europe and at the same time to re¬
fuse to import principles that are as important as flour or sugar? There
are those who accuse Europe, which wants to generalize respect for
human rights and the establishment of democratic political systems,
of wanting "to perpetuate colonial domination"!
What was revolutionary in the achievements of 1789 was their
universal aspect. The human condition may vary from continent to
continent, but there is everywhere and at all times a need for these
same rights. The abolition of slavery was not a minor affair of concern
to a few wretched serfs. It concerned the whole of humanity, without
exception.
We on the sidelines"inhabitants of the suburbs of history... the
uninvited guests who have come in through the servants' entrance of
the West, intruders who come to watch the spectacle of modernity just
as the lights are about to go out. Always late, we were born when his¬
tory was already running out..." (Octavio Paz)look with envious,
ambitious eyes at the memory of others, trying to cleanse the history
of the Revolution of its faults, its injustices and its ugliness. Of the past
two centuries of French history we wish to remember only the pains¬
taking work and the patient advance of the rights inscribed on the col¬
lective mentality of man, whether he be from here or elsewhere, and
with all his differences and similarities.
Yet the road travelled by human rights has been stained with the
blood of European wars and of colonial brutality and then by the hu¬
miliation of man through the violation of his cultural and religious
values. It is as though, to fashion and consolidate itself, Republican
France had to pass through a phase of barbarism. We remain attached
to principles. We cultivate the historical memory, short though it may
be, with its baser moments expunged, so that respect for mankind may
become a right with which no government will be able to compromise.
This right should be inscribed on the very heart of the body politic
by the force of its universality.
If this is achieved, perhaps children will no longer be victims of
famine, drought, disease, work or prostitution. Perhaps men and wom¬
en will no longer have to suffer the humiliations of poverty or be held
hostage to fanaticism and intolerance which like to make people be¬
lieve they can provide answers to serious problems.
For all of this "our thirst for consolation can never be slaked" (Stig
Dagerman), nor our desire for coherence satisfied. We want to cry out:
"stop selling arms while at the same time celebrating human rights and
the bicentenary of the Revolution! Be consistent: the prosperity of some
cannot be built on the misery of others! Crimes are being committed
while you sing the praises of democracy."
1789 is a memory that belongs to the universal heritage; it is in¬
scribed in all of us. We are born with this memory, that is, with the
hope of liberation. Many die without ever having known it.
La Batalla ("The
Battle"), oil on canvas
by the contemporary
Argentine painter
Ana Eckell
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN,
Moroccan writer and
journalist, was awarded
the Goncourt Prize in
1987 for his novel La nuit
sacrée, an English
translation of which is
scheduled for publication
later this year by
Harcourt Brace
Jovanovich.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
I
V
La
V
Pi»
1 / i 1
\Êh M
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
^.1789
An idea
that changed
the world
An idea
and its
destiny
BY FRANÇOIS FURET
The French Revolution proclaimed the
principles of liberty and equality as
universally valid, but the application of
these abstract notions in different societies
has inevitably led to tensions and
compromises. Today, 200 years later,
these issues are more topical than ever.
In this interview with the Unesco
Courier, the noted French historian
François Furet, whose work has opened
up new perspectives on the Revolution,
examines the concept ofthe universality
of man and his rights in the world
context. 51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
La République (1794),
earthenware statuette by
Joseph Chinard. With her
right hand, the figure
unveils a tablet inscribed
Droits de l'homme
("Rights ofMan").
52
PREVIOUS DOUBLE PAGE
1 he Storming of the
Bastille". 18th-century
French school
X HE French Revolution was an attempt to
legislate in the name of universality. Its aim was
the emancipation not only of the French but of
all mankind. To this extent it was an event that
was not merely of national but also of interna¬
tional scope, not simply a political but also a
philosophical revolution.
One of the ambiguities of the revolutionaries'
ambition to emancipate humanity springs from
the fact that their vision of the world was very
eurocentric. When the French spoke of the
universal, they meant by that the bulk of Europe
together with the European appendix consisting
of the newly-independent former British colonies
of America. This was the extent of their horizon.
The whole of the nineteenth century con¬
tinued to be marked by eurocentrism, even for
men like Marx, who spoke of the universe whilst
thinking of Europe. Between Britain, Germany
and France everything was covered. Even within
Europe it was better not to go too far south or
too far east so as not to mar the concept of univer¬
sality. There can, then, be no doubt about it, the
French Revolution legislated in the name of Eu¬
ropean man.
Ambitions bordering on folly
There is, however, another sense in which tht
notion of the universal must be understood: its
abstraction. There is nothing tangible about
universality; it is an abstraction just as universal
man is abstract man. The Revolution declared
that man had no reason to enter into society un¬
less that society guaranteed him the autonomy,
the liberty and the rights which were his before
he entered into the social contract. In other
words, for the Revolution, the essence of man
is his liberty, his autonomy and the fact of his
acceptance only of laws imposed by himself. So¬
ciety must guarantee to each individual all the
rights that are his by virtue of his status as a man.
This is an extraordinary ideal, completely gener¬
al and therefore entirely abstract.
Thus these rights are formal, abstract and
deduced as it were from the natural state of man.
The ambitions of the Revolution, as we can see,
bordered on folly, since they were in contradic¬
tion with the true state of society and of man.
Therein, in large part, lies its tragedy: in the enor¬
mous contradiction between the universal rights
it proclaimed as being inherent in the status of
man and the actual state of society with its poor
and its rich, its dominators and its dominated.
Equality: dream or reality?
Born of the Revolution, modern democracy has,
over the past two centuries, been marked by the
permanent tension engendered by the affirmation
of abstract, universal rights and the experience
of the reality of rights imperfectly achieved. Take,
for example, the notion of equality. This too,
naturally, is an abstract notion, since people are
not equal: both nature and society only turn out
individuals who are unequal, whereas the ambi¬
tion of society is to produce individuals who are
equal. Are they not equal as citizens?
Absolute political and social equality implies
absolute despotism. The only hypothetical situ¬
ation in which people could be strictly equal
would be one in which a single person is placed
over all the others to force them to maintain their
equal status. Not a very enviable situation!
Liberty always produces inequality. This is why,
more and more, we are obliged to see the state
as a compensatory mechanism for the correction
of certain inequalities. It seems to me that the hall¬
mark of a free society is the maintenance of the
difficult, uncertain balance between the growth
of the state and the liberty of the individual.
In the past 200 years there has not been one
example, not even among the most liberal socie¬
ties, of a diminishing state. Look, for example,
at the United States, France, or the United King¬
dom. All these states are growing. Why? In the
name of equality, because each time that a new
right is given to a section of the citizenry, a new
state organism has to be created to guarantee that
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
/..r.- '/(Sf.'/e.. y.,t. i.'/i ,.'.>v.íí
\ W.7C. . *7-' > « ,'.'/.-. r".' . i .VI.'.
i lanting a "tree of
liberty" to the
accompaniment of the local
band, in the presence of the
mayor and members of the
National Guard. Gouache,
18th-century French school
fr«*fe
right. The advance of equality is necessarrily
linked to growth of state mechanisms, with all
that this entails in the way of contradictions be¬
tween the area of state intervention and the area
left free to individual initiative.
The rights of the citizen
or civil war?
As the world became more universal, particular¬
ly through the processes first of colonization and
then of decolonization, the constituent tension
of the French Revolution, between the formal
and the real, the universal and the particular,
again came to the surface. The democratic move¬
ment can be identified with the struggle to reduce
these tensions. Is the Declaration of the Rights
of Man and of the Citizen anything other than
a declaration of a permanent state of civil war
whose purpose is to allow people to become what
they are notthat is to say equals? The dynamic
of democratic societies has consisted essentially
of the progressive integration of those excluded
from equality. And each action in this direction
is the cause of new tensions.
Les femmes des trois
ordres ("Women of the
Three Orders"), a
revolutionary print
showing a peasant woman
burdened with a nun and
an aristocrat.
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
54
1. Indian women demonstrating for
their country's independence, around
1930. In the centre, hands linked in
front of her, is the wife ofMahatma
Gandhi
2. Nlembers of the Kuomintang
("National People's Party") of China,
founded by Sun Yat-sen, in the Paris
workshop of sculptor Paul
Landowski, around 1930.
Landowskys statue of Sun Yat-sen
was erected at Nanking.
3. Sad Zaghlul (1857-1927), founder
of the Wafd national party in Egypt,
speaking around 1920 at a Cairo
demonstration calling for the
withdrawal of British troops.
4. I rocession in Moscow on the
50th anniversary of the October
Revolution of 1917
5. 1 roops of the revolutionary
leaders Pancho Villa and Emiliano
Zapata ride into Mexico City,
December 1914.
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
In the France of 1848, for example, the
problem of the right to work was raised and the
question was asked as to whether property was
a right and, if so, how far it was compatible with
equality. These are very real contradictions.
Property is clearly a right since without it man
is marked out to become a victim of the state.
But if property is too unevenly distributed it cre¬
ates such great social inequality that it eliminates,
for very many, all hope of exercising that right.
Here we have a clear example of the contradic¬
tions resulting from the Declaration of 1789.
This tension, which was the vehicle of all that
constitutes the historic value of the Revolution,
ended up by spawning criticism of the Revolu¬
tion. A current of thought developed which re¬
jected the ideology of rights as being abstract, false
and merely a cover for an iniquitous society and
a mask for bourgeois individualism.
In 1917, a revolution broke out in Russia
which aimed to go beyond these contradictions.
Basing itself on a critique of the rights of man,
its objective was to replace the abstract by the
tangible and formal democracy by the dictator¬
ship of the proletariat. It wanted to resolve the
problem of inequality by abolishing the law of
the market-place and the liberty of the individual.
A strange but necessary
compromise
Thirty years later, the world found itself in a cu¬
rious situation. At the end of the Second World
War, the two conflicting concepts of 1789 and
1917 were obliged to come to terms with one
another.
Among the victors in the war were lined up,
on one side the democracies of Western Europe
and America, more than ever attached to the con¬
cept of human rights after the victory over
nazism, and on the other the Soviet Union, which
had been created on the basis of the opposite
postulate. And the two sides were obliged to
come to an understanding.
Together they had just established the Unit¬
ed Nations system and they had to find some
common ground. This was to be the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights, proclaimed in
1948. The Declaration was the outcome of an odd
but necessary compromise, largely negotiated by
the French jurist René Cassin on one side and
the Soviet diplomat and lawyer Andrey
Vyshinsky on the other. The result was a reflec
tion of their dialoguea balancing game between
two opposing conceptions. It was, nevertheless,
based on a humanistic and democratic ideal, since
the United Nations was founded on the negation
of nazism, that is to say on the notions of law
and liberty.
In order to achieve an agreement, the
Western jurists had to agree to the introduction
of so-called "real" rights. The Declaration of 1948
contains, for example, the notion of the right to
a minimum necessary for life. It was, indeed, an
extremely difficult notion to make a reality in
the poorest countries, and the inclusion of the
right to an adequate standard of living as a hu¬
man right only served to underline the precari¬
ous nature of these rights.
At the prompting of the Soviet camp there
was also a great debate on whether or not the
right to property should be excluded from hu¬
man rights. This was clearly not possible from
the standpoint of the Western powers. Finally,
the Universal Declaration of 1948 bears the stamp
of the contradictions that hovered over its birth.
Its text was meant both to prescribe norms and
to be concrete, to be both universal and specific.
But the more specific definitions you include in
the notion of universality, the more you reduce
its scope. Four decades have gone by since the
Declaration was proclaimed, but the debate goes
on and continues to develop over the contradic¬
tory ideas that are woven into it.
'We must think of ourselves
as free and equal'
For example, there is the great argument as to
whether liberty and equality are fact or fiction.
It is true that people are free and equal to the ex¬
tent that they are no longer subjugated or reduced
to slavery. They are free in body and mind and
free to follow their personal interests and to come
to agreements between themselves. On the other
hand, this liberty and equality are limited, indeed
compromised, in so far as they conceal social, cul¬
tural and individual inequalities and situations in
which one class is exploited by another.
In this sense it can clearly be seen that there
is something false in the notions of liberty and
equality. But from there two conclusions are
open to us. It can be saidand this is my personal
positionthat it is true that we are not all free-
and equal, but we have to think of ourselves in
society as being both free and equal. And the fact
that we are obliged to think in this way changes
the fabric of the social world and creates that ten¬
sion of which I have spoken and that dynamic
that is inherent in democracy.
On the other hand, we can come to the
Marxist conclusion that, since liberty and equal¬
ity are no more than lies, we must go beyond
them, abolish the system that is based on them
and bring about a society radically different from
that of 1789. Since modern democracy is merely
a bourgeois dictatorship in disguise, we should 55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
56
replace the power of the bourgeoisie by the pow¬
er of the proletariat. In this way, since the
proletariat is not an exploiting class, we shall free
society and mankind of all exploitation.
The emergence
of the individual
What seems to me to be inaccurate in this view
of things is the equation of modern democracy
with the dictatorship of the bourgeoisie. This is
not historically true. The French society of 1789
was neither very bourgeois nor really capitalist.
The point that I have made in my books is pre¬
cisely that the French Revolution cannot be con¬
sidered merely as the rise of the bourgeoisie. The
Revolution marks, above all, the emergence of
modern individualism, a process much more all-
embracing than the emergence of a class, since
it transforms the entire social fabric in which the
bourgeoisie is but one element, even if, little by
little, this element is beginning to dominate the
rest.
Evidence that individualism is not simply a
bourgeois quality comes from those countries
that have eliminated the bourgeois economic dic¬
tatorship and where the demand for individual
liberty continues to exist. In the Marxist socie¬
ties of today, the notions of human rights, of the
market-place and of formal democracy are return¬
ing to favour. In other words, the concept of bas¬
ing society on the rights of the individual, far
from being a bourgeois lie, is a genuinely univer¬
sal notion which fulfils a universal hope. There
will never be true equality between all people,
but the idea of equality will always be there on
the horizon. That is what we have to live with.
That is what makes things happen.
The controversy between formal democracy
and class dictatorship is, however, far from be¬
ing over, if only, perhaps, because the message
of the class struggle has got across better than that
of democracy in many non-European societies.
For historical reasons, criticism of rights has been
more successfully propagated than the concept
of rights. The concept of rights was taken with
them by the colonizers and imposed by the gun.
The rights were those of the victors and it was
natural that they should be seen by the van¬
quished as a cover for their domination.
In many non-European countries it might be
said that there was a spontaneous upsurge of
Marxism in the twentieth century, because the
Marxist critique was, if one can put it that way,
inscribed on the very experience of the peoples
of those countries. Or rather, the non-universality
of rights was inscribed on their flesh. The
colonists brought with them both the concept of
rights and the critique of that concept. To the
peoples they colonized, the critique seemed the
better founded of the two, since it coincided more
directly with the reality they were living through
and offered a possible justification for the violence
of their resistance.
I am, of course, talking in terms of general
tendencies. In terms of what actually happened
things were not so clear-cut. At the time of the
colonial shock these societies were essentially pre-
individualisticthe individual was still closely at¬
tached to family, tribe and community. But the
colonists introduced the individualist view of the
world. As a result one world was superimposed
on another, one tied in to traditional links of
solidarity, the other turned towards the ideolo¬
gy of modern democracy, one society dominat¬
ed by the tribal chiefs and village headmen, the
other, superimposed, spreading the word of
universal suffrage.
From all this was to emerge the Revolution¬
ary Institutional Party in Mexico, the Wafd na¬
tional party in Egypt, the Kuomintang in China,
and the Congress Party in India. These were liber¬
al options whose practical achievements remained
limited, which is why this phase was overtaken
by another dominated by the ideology of the class
struggle and revolution. Recently, however, there
seems to have been a swing back to the idea of
rights and democracy.
The democratic dynamic,
a dynamic of conflict
In those places where it had been thought possi¬
ble to draw a line through the rights of the
modern individual, an often tragic economic sit¬
uation has arisen. The pre-capitalist structures
were broken down, but since they have not been
replaced by capitalist market structures, dramat¬
ic difficulties have been experienced. Sometimes
it has not even been possible to provide enough
food for the inhabitants of the towns, or even
for the peoples of the rural areas. The produc¬
tivity of labour has been destroyed and, as Marx
rightly pointed out, the productivity of labour,
the capacity to create wealth, is one of the sanc¬
tions of history. Without these attributes and
without taking into consideration man's relation¬
ship with nature there can be no history.
People are beginning to become aware that
there is no such thing as an historical short cut.
After the communal society we have to go
through the stage of the individualistic society.
We have to come to terms with its tensions.
We have to accept that modern societies are
conflictual societies, and live with the fact
that the democratic dynamic is a dynamic of
conflict.
Beyond a certain point, that raises the ques¬
tion of the governability of modern societies.
French society, to take one example, is not easy
to govern. As soon as a new tension arises, every¬
one takes to the streets. That is what liberty is
and modern society has to learn to live with it.
This is, perhaps, one of the biggest hurdles to be
overcome in any societynot to cling to certain¬
ties, but to accept uncertainties, the unforeseen
and the risks the future holds.
1
Rouget de Lisle singing
the Marseillaise for the
first time. " Painting by
Isidore Pils, 1849. Rouget
de Lisle, an Engineer
captain, composed the
words and music of what
later became the French
national anthem while in
Strasbourg in 1792.
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
The price offreedom
What conclusions, therefore, can we come to
about the fate of the ideas of the Revolution af¬
ter 200 years? Its basic ideas seem to be gaining
ground, yet the difficulties they face if they are
to be put fully into practice are immense.
In the Western societies in which these ideas
have long been accepted, a number of negative
aspects are starting to appear. It is true that these
are countries in which it has become pleasant to
live, because they have found an acceptable
balance of sorts between the liberty of the in¬
dividual and action by the state. But this balance
has been achieved at a very high price. People are
losing interest in community affairs and are less
and less involved in public affairs and the
problems of others. There is less and less solidar¬
ity. All this is very negative. People seem to be
looking after their own interests and this leaves
a great void and a general feeling that something
is lacking in life.
Elsewhere in the world, individual aspirations
concerning liberty and the concept of human
rights are making a strong come-back and are ad¬
vancing on all sides. Yet how are these countries
going to escape the dilemmas specific to com¬
munal societies and find answers to the problems
of the productivity of labour? These are questions
that still await reply.
I should like to conclude by expressing the
hope that the celebration this year of the bicente¬
nary of the French Revolution will be a great
learning experience and will cause people every¬
where to become aware of the real issues and ten¬
sions related to this event. May it help, despite
all the differences and all the contradictions that
exist in the world today, to advance the idea of
the universality of humanity and of human rights.
FRANÇOIS FURET,
French historian and writer,
is director of the Raymond
Aron Institute in Paris.
Among his books translated
into English are Interpreting
the French Revolution
(Cambridge University
Press, 1981) and In the
Workshop of History
(University of Chicago
Press, 1985). He has
recently published La
Révolution 1770-1880
(Hachette, 1988) and, with
Mona Ozouf, a critical
dictionary of the French
Revolution (Flammarion,
1988).
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco
^courier
Published monthty in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45 68 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet, Mouna Chatta,
Majda Dalai, Claudie Duhamel
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (8erne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Sri Ram (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Abdul Manaf Saad (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Seham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bengali: Ahmed Hedayet (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88), Assistant: Marie-
Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89), Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse
Hardy (45.68.45.65), Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Mohamed Salah El Din,
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: Liliane Tasch (45.68.45.66), Special projects:
Ricardo Zamora, Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval
ADVERTISING
Publicat: 17, Boulevard Poissonnière, 75002 Paris.
TEI: 40.26.51.26
Sales director: Benoît Rusier
Advertising director: Daniele Michelet
SUBSCRIPTIONS
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copynght
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is
produced In microform (microfilm and/or microfiche by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Michigan 48100, USA ; (3) NCR. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New-York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and
Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-chief
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France) DEPOT LEGAL : CI JUIN 1989
Photocomposition: The Unesco Courier
Photogravure- impression:
Maury Imprimeur S.A., 2.1. route d'Etampes,
45330 Malesherbes
58 ISSN 0041-5278
The Editors wish to thank
Mr. Nicolas Langlois
for his valuable contribution
to the new editorial conception and design
of the Unesco Courier
GLOSSARY
Ancien régime: the political and social system of France before the Revolution of
1789.
Estates General, also called States General: the representative assembly of the 3
Estates or orders of the realm: the clergy, the nobility, and the Third Estate, which
represented the majority of the people. The Estates General met on 5 May 1789.
The deputies of the Third Estate led in the formation of the National Assembly,
signalling the end of representation based on the 3 traditional orders. On 9 July
1789 the National Assembly proclaimed itself the Constituent Assembly, after it
had claimed the right to produce a constitution for France. The Legislative
Assembly was the Parliament which sat from October 1791 to September 1792,
when it was replaced by the National Convention, which governed until October
1795. Among the first acts of the Convention were the formal abolition of the
monarchy and the establishment of the Republic (September 1792). The Directory
was the régime that replaced the National Convention (1795-1799).
Committee of Public Safety: government body that gained virtual dictatorial
control over France during the Reign of Terror (September 1793-July 1794).
Dantonists: followers of the revolutionary leader Georges Danton (1759-1794).
Girondins: moderate republicans, many of them from the Gironde département,
overthrown in 1793.
Jacobins: members of a radical political club founded during the Revolution. Closely
associated with Robespierre during the Terror, the Jacobin Club was closed in 1794.
It took its name from its meeting place in a former convent of the Dominicans,
who were known in Paris as Jacobins.
Montagnards ("Mountain Men"): radical deputies in the National Convention who
controlled the government during the climax of the Revolution in 1793-1794. So
called because they sat on the higher benches of the Assembly.
Robespierrists: followers of Maximilien Robespierre (1758-1794), the Jacobin leader
who came to dominate the Committee of Public Safety.
Sans-culottes ("without knee breeches"): term originally given to the ill-clad
volunteers of the Revolutionary army; later applied generally to the ultra-democrats
of the Revolution.
Sections: the 48 divisions into which Paris was organized for administrative
purposes in 1790.
NO 6- 1989 OPI 89 1 - 469 A
PHOTO CREDITS
Cover: © Georges Servat, Paris. Back cover, pages 18-19, 17 (below), 28: © Bulloz, Paris. Page 5: R. Melhoul © Sygma, Paris.
Page 7: de Wiidenberg © Sygma, Paris. Page 9: D. Hudson © Sygma, Paris. Page 10: Brigitte Salom © Unesco Courier. Page
12: © Mount Vernon Ladies Association, Va., USA. Pages 12-13, 16 (above), 16-17, 23, 46 (centre), 52-53: © Edimédia; Musée
Carnavalet, Paris. Pages 13 (right), 14 (1): Asbl FAC-AP/Sprl Lefebvre et Gill«, Brussels. Page 14 (2): © IPS, Paris. Pages
14 (3, 4), 18 (left): © National Portrait Gallery, London. Pages 15 (1, 2, 3), 16 (centre), 24-25, 27 (above), 30, 32, 38, 42,
43, 54, (1,2, 3, 5): © Roger Viollet, Paris. Page 15 (4): © RMN, Musée de Versailles. Pages 16 (below), 40: All Rights Reserved.
Pages 20, 21: © Duval-Carrié, Paris. Pages 22, 24 (left), 40-41, 44, 45, 53 (below): © Edimédia, Paris. Pages 26, 37 (right),
39: Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris. Page 31: © Musée de la Révolution Française, Vizille, France. Pages 33, 52: © RMN, Paris.
Page 34: Oronoz © Artephot, Paris. Page 35: © Agence de Presse Bernand, Paris. Pages 36 (below), 37 (above): © APN,
Paris. Page 46 (left & right): Chinese edition of the Unesco Conner, Beijing. Page 47: © Edimédia; Freer Gallery of Art.
Pages 48-49: © AIAP/Bibliothèque des Arts, from Unesco: 40 artists; 40 Years; 40 Countries. Pages 50-51: © Roger Viollet;
Musée de Versailles. Page 54 (above left): © ESA, Paris. Page 54 (4): Bruno Barbey © Magnum, Paris. Pages 56-57: © Lauros
Giraudon; Musée Historique, Strasbourg.
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
1)1 ("I VRATIOX
/'/ DR >fh DE l'homme et ne C/7tn/.\
;* ' DecnsBÚ parla Convention Nationale en 1708
acceptés parle People Français.
/'
Pnr.A3tt\e 1 #
njdr fraxraû, convaincu que 1 oubli rt
* dr* di oit* îulurrt» dr I .Kuiiiii- , 1
le» Irulr» cintra fo* malheur* dn monde, » triol»
nílplJu uuu* «ur *ntt*uuuu«u lôicmiirue or* dioili f« -
IjJÇ ***« ** ntaltrii*blc*,*Jiii qor iona Ira ri lovftM,pouvaut roui -
I paro- Uu* reUck» *ctc* dn Gotri-rvuCiüruf *>ee k Uni dr '- V
[ fonte utllifauoii loriklcuc le kjkVtrt j*uwii* nupruitcr ri «valu- Jfl
pur k tw-ninic; »bu que lr peuple tmi tonionr* dnuul k* \ftix leu^
I baie* dc A ïibn-tr ri dc lou boubrni , Ir ma^illiaf k rrtjkr dr lé* de-'
voir*,k IrvilLfrni- l'okirt de ù uiu>kui . °
I Ko cocdcquciirc, il pj-nrkmr en pir&iirr de lT>rr lñpertur,k denk -
noon Buuuuutt dc* droit* drlbötutur et du ritoveu .
ABTlCIfS mr.MiKn'
1-c Uni dr k lôcieV «1 le boubciu- rounuiiu .
I.c gumeiimiinil rit. udUlur pour outunur » ïhouimr k iouñCniícr dr
le* droit* uatnrrla ci ùiiprrirrûtjUW-
n.
tV* droit* fout lr^ifc,kbbrrir,k tnrrtr, k propriété' .
lll-
Tbua ka uouuue» fout rWii par k uafnre rt drvatri k loi .
I .a loi Hl IrxprrÜuuiTujie rt<Ô4ru*uCue drkxolmifc' ornear; egr rll ,
k BOrJur pour ton*, Toit qn'nV tn-ote**-,!«! quefir pnuáür, cue or prüf
utdomin que ce qm efl jnitr et utile « k lôrirW: rie ur peut dctèiirb c
an . -il mGuuN
\'.
Tona ka rifovm* lauf rtralciurot «Auiâ&iblra an« emploi* poLür» - Ira
pruplra liLiC* UT rwiunn"i.t d»i*tor* nioutï dr p»"étrrei»re* dau* lent*
derhou» que le* verni* et ka tatou* .
VI
I.» liberie cfl lr pouroir Oui apparuT«! ù luouuuc de taire foui ce
qui ne tinrt u*« nu droit* d'anfi tu .eue« pour priuerpe k Mittlre -,
-pour rrcdr k jufliee; uouv lanve -owrdr k toi; là buùtr utocair rll dati»
-» cettr nutxuur ; itr/ñs *au*r rrawe &r/*e W*mWm*r fm&iê ttmtfiit
Ml
lr droit drtuJlùiriVi 1« peiner rt le* opûiiouj,iÔit par k >«rr dck .
urriic. Toil dr ioufe «nier iiuiùrrc, k di-uit dc aaXtouiUrr pailiulrrunit. Le '
blur ^«n-ricrdr* rubra ne penvrnl Cti<r rutrt-dita.
L« ucértrifr d ruourcr ce* droit» iûppolr on k pi ri cure ou lr lomn ur
Î-Crciil du drtpotüiur ,
VIII .
1.* lm etc rouitltr dan* k prol-rúo» »reo* dec p*r k (orirtr à rbanui I
dr (r* tucuibrr* pour k coulCr\*tiou dr là prrlounr, dr ira d:«il* ri de ]
Ira propBicfei
IX
|.a loi dort prote*f*i- k lui II h rt uidñídrteflc routjr l'ap -
prciMou de cru« «pu foncturuf -
Nul UT doit rtrr »renie, «veto, »t del ru* que dam* lr* rua drtmiù
ne* par k loi, ci Irlou le* lôriue* un'rHr a prdri-rte» . Tout rrtnvru «p
iGàti
i q
par
paa r*T;'untr dr k loi doit obeu- a ïudlaitf I u (r mid con- |
la tTlill»ii'r ,
lout *ctr ran-rr' cuntir un bouunr bor* dr* ra» et lana ka lui
(pic U loi drirruumif rll .tibrtran-e et (\xjuaûqnc : crin contar kqurl on ,
««nuro-lt lexcrutcr par k \10lrujrr 1 k droat or lr rrpoukrr p*rk lurrc.
'
CrnT M luKUCiV-i-o*rirt ,r«prdirvoic-iii , ¡ivitct'otnrt , rurníci-oiciif
011 Irroiruf rxrrnlrr dr» aefr* arl>îti*«B-r*, *OnI conpjiblca et doivent
rtrr pnuu-
III.
Toni nnuiiK étant pi-dtaur' iiuioeciit jidqu a ft ipiti art rir dt-*l*rr
ronp*blr, »11 rfl pigr'iudrtuculaUc de larrrtcc» fouir i-irurur qui ne
»rroil pa» urrrkaitr pom- aal-^nCr dr la uriiôiuK-, doff cur icvct-c -
ninit ir|BÙilr p/i .
ur doit rire piocui piWi, ilu**pi-c*aSuirrtr cutrudu ou Irfalciinid
Upprur'tt qii'ru irilndunr W woutdptcc anhncnrriiicut *u dcu't.lj loi
' qui pnuiroit k* dcn(»t otuuii* *\»irt *y»Ac r«u1a*,leroit nur Iviaumir Irllrt,
' rrtriijieirdouiir À U loi finroit nu n-ùur
J.îi lui ur doit drrrnarr (nw de* priora 1Vicie
meut rt rt-idcuuitcirt nrr r-k^Lr*: le» priuc* ctontail.
rtrr utopoittouurraandru^^Kaulc» ahlorirtc»
XVL
le droil dr prcquirir til cdiii iwi appai
nu- rt dr diluofrt- À lou oit dr ir* Inri
irticul a tonl Hto\rii
liirn*, dr lr* meum, di
iruit dc lou traMil n 4c lot- iïidiulric .
DD
Xtd rrnrr dr travail, drcnlntrc, dc rouiiurrrr ur prni eu c ûii« dii à
llnditlkir de» nfovn* .
XX 111
Touf uaa*BiK>pRrfruT*«rrtt-i IcrurcnJ» leiu»; mai* duc peut lr i-eudir j¡t
m être leucbi . S« pcHoùue n'cll p** u»r pn. pnrh4 JÍcuaUt - Ih* kî ur rerou - H
«ort poiut dr domHliritr ( A ur prni rxitic* tamW niçjrauruï dr lóni*,ct dr l*
1 eruunodÀiturc runrr llrtUnnr qni lir. uUr fi rrru^qui 1 ounnuir .
XIX
prol rare pri^r qlc k iiioiudic portioji dr fit ut-ourirtr ÎùiaiOnH/
airui ,ii re n'cil Loilquc U iirrrt^ifc pitblupiivkriilciurut couí'i 1
vu
Nul
roalenfcuirnrpli f c i|-eli lortnuc I* iiercWfr lm
tater Icnrr, rt Ion* U roiuliliou dîme | pllr et prrukÙc Uldcuiuitc
XX.
NJ rontnbunoa or prni être établir ipic ponr i'nu'Kir renriralr, l'on*
kacstoxrtu ont droit dr touronru- a ie^abb^cturut dr* coutributiau*
dun Im-volrr Inuploi , rt dr ara luirrru^T raupte.
XXf
L<-M lr«*ur* |n*Uira fout UUr drrtc lierre . U f«-Íei c doit la inldubmec
aux rttoiru* uudtV omu , lôtt eu Ir^ir iu*r iu *ui du u ^ 1 ¡ I , Í
rawl lr» uMvrn* drnllcr À mu qui 1 qui Lora i'rtal dr uTfrTuuuu*.
on
i:ùub nriiou rlllr brloin dr Ion*. 1^ loricfn dotl tàtoarlrt drlont iàu pouiuv
kipropradrk rail ou pnldiqar, ri luette luilburmon ak poriCr drnxnlr. «
Win «lavu»
I a inmiir ¿oeulr radulr ituv* J action dc Ion * pour aiWer à ruanni kioiaC-
laucr et k ron£rwnon dclr» drorfa ; retir Tar*wnr repaie iurk InniTramrlr na-
XXI Vs* tionak
jjuul H umi rnlWrji Im beutle* de» lónrtioua pnUirpea ne Um* p-i* rlaarcitilS
orVrinmcrap*r k loirrt li k 1 rlpou ï AnIric de Ion» lralauriintuör» âctt pi* aim .
XXV-
Ja feinrraniric iT*îdc d»u» b> pcn^ilr .IlBe rtl uur it uidisiliWr unpi-t-r - H
. otpnntr rt nudiriiaUe
XXVI-
Aurunr poeto» du Jtcnpk ue pmt exrveo k pnrlAanr? da prtuile rn -
tirr, inaia euaonr iccuuii «u lou^rriiu abcuiblcc, doü iouuT ün Ai-mt An
t^ne iotrt nidn«nSn qui uTntyrroit k fnu itvaturtr iùrtn tau1 Uni lui* à
naut |i*f le» Uoiuiur» bine»,
XXVI11.
I H p*i iplr a ton^out » k droit dr inoil', de îTlôr run- cl dc rtuuiqcr J Q
-û.lda,»f k* fCurVihout ftifura .
-XXIX
i rWal dr roneourï
lalÄ^iKitkir*»^
[
nil »
("baque unWonu «un aWi V t
k »úiuii 10tiin'i dc íe* uuuidal»*rra ou ne ic# *
r XXX °
WhWtaou» pnUbrfUr» lout rüciturlruicui Inupot -iii ra^rllr* ur uru
cor eouLdncVa conuitc <k» diHiurtiuik» m iaa»u Ja» -*
mau cuuaaur dra dnuna -
XXXI.
I.c* drlil» dr» ui»tid»fair^»dA ucnpi- ci de le* aoru» ur doiirut )* -
uiaî» rii e unpuiù* . Nid u"a k A-oil oc Te p* êtnidrr ptm
XXXII-
|rr droi<uc«*^caiir^aV*urution*an«n:epoJrt^
ur peut, m «tirmi'aa^^nilmlil.inipruriH ni Inuiir .
XXXIU.
L* rrriMancr » lopprei*<Hi cil k roulctnicure dr» -wire* rWtadc n*nUiuic.
XXXIV
m^mmwdäimm contre k- rorp* lórudH b>r»on'on Inildr le* «jcui -
rfl tpunuif. Il.-v a opprcb*CKi eoun-e rlu»que uirmUrr Unique le
corpa I 1 upaaibtkE
Quand lr Goui-rt nriucut *iok lr* droit* du pctiplc.l'iijnrrrrnou ^luuuuuuî
P«ur |r peuple, ^ ptnu cuaqar poriiou im »nqJc V ¿¡m tjnx ilr»
mi* et k pi lu ludwteuiablr rir* nemn-a . T*» Ammmf	
v*äs»i?iöc-
^ al I
]]>
</page>
</document>
