<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="083412eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
AUGUST 1989 - 15 French francs
Cv*-*»'-?
..:.
'h»^C T-
(
SS*
>*i
fî
I
p
1
'
. - m
-
.«*
.
T/ ' ";.':' á
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters
My Cultural
Development,
Self-Portrait
1982, acrylic on canvas
(1.16 x 0.89 m)
by Juan Carlos Aznar
¡,
^
a» »
\
"In my paintings I
sometimes mix
European influences,
Picasso for example,
with ¡mages from comic
strips and motifs from
pre-Columbian
America," wrote
Argentine artist Juan
Carlos Aznar (born
1937) when he sent us
a photo of this
painting. The French
critic Otto Hahn has
written that Aznar,
"With a rather
disquieting sense of
humour.. .picks up
signals from ordinary
events and creates
incongruous links
between them."
ü-VnOP
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
CONTENTS
4
Interview with
RICHARD ATTENBOROUGH
9 46
STREETSCAPES impressions of city life reflections
BERLIN
THE FRIEDRICHSTRASSE,
A LINK IN THE CHAIN OF HISTORY
by Christiane Mengin 11
TOKYO
A CITY OF TOWERS AND TRADITIONS
by Sarah Zarmati 15
BOGOTÁ
A TRIP ALONG THE SÉPTIMA
by Anne Berty 18
ABIDJAN
A COLOURFUL KALEIDOSCOPE
by Philippe Haeringer 22
MOSCOW
GORKY STREET, FIFTY YEARS OF CHANGE
by Anatole Kopp 26
FAMILIES OF THE WORLD
by Hélène Tremblay
48
SCIENCE
AND SOCIETY
INTERNATIONAL
CO-OPERATION IN SPACE
by David Spurgeon
CAIRO
IN THE HEART OF AN ANCIENT CAPITAL
by Alain Bonnamy 31
HOUSTON
HIGHWAYS IN THE CITY
by Brigitte Ouvry-Vial 35
Cover: Street in Old Cairo
by the French painter Félix Ziem (1821-1911).
Back cover: Mirror image of a city.
A skyscraper in Houston, USA.
BEIJING
THE STREET OF THE GLAZED TILE FACTORY
by Pierre Clement 38
PARIS
UNDER THE ROOFS OF PARIS
by Anne-Marie Chatelet 42
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
The director of Gandhi and Cry Freedom reflects on
the topicality offilms about Third World countries and the
prospects for African cinema.
Richard Attenborough
How did you come to make a film about apartheid?*
I wanted to make a film about South Africa and com¬
missioned several scripts but until I read Donald Woods'
book I had not found a subject which I felt was sufficiently
pertinent or which contained sufficient optimism and hope
for the future. Nor had I found a subject which I felt had
a chance of reaching a sufficiently large number of people.
It seemed to me that to reach only an audience which was
already aware of what was happening in South Africa and
concerned about the situation there was a waste of time.
I wanted to reach people who were indifferent, who didn't
know what was going on and didn't care. It was only when
I read Donald's book that I thought I had found a subject
to which people in many parts of the world would find it
possible to relate.
Most important of all, of course, I wanted to reach.an
American audience because it was, I thought, in the United
States that a fundamental change of attitude towards the
administration of South Africa was likely to be most
influential.
A number of black peoplenot the majority by any
meansbelieve that I dodged the issue and that by not tack¬
ling the subject purely from a black African's point of view
I smudged the edges. I don't agree with that.
I think it is a well made and wonderfully acted film.
The script is immensely skilful, but it may be that my con¬
cern to reach a wider audience in fact resulted in a misjudge¬
ment. Whereas the picture will probably gross something
like $45-50 million worldwide it will gross under $10 mil¬
lion in the United States. I believed that Americans would
* Sir Richard Attenborough's film Cry Freedom (1987) is based on the writ¬
ings of a white South African editor, Donald Woods, who befriended a lead¬
ing black activist, Steve Biko. Biko was arrested and died in police custody.
When Woods attempted to get the truth about Biko's death told, he became
a banned person and was forced to flee South Africa with his family. Editor
go to see it and that black people in particular would be
angry with what is going on in South Africa. I thought that
the pictureeven if it wasn't as incisive as they might have
hopednevertheless had its heart in the right place.
It is fascinating that most black people in the United
States did not go to the movie. It did worse .business in
Atlanta than it did in Los Angeles, although it did terrific
business in Washington, which of course has a large black
population, so I don't really know whether I made a total
miscalculation in assuming that there was an audience in
America who would be interested in this kind of subject.
There is no question whatsoever that the film actually
affected the political debate in some countries and from all
I can gather it was justified in that millions of people have
been affected by it. But the fact remains that with hindsight
I am enormously disappointed in attendances in the States.
Cry Freedom was released at a time when a number of
films were coming out about Africa, just as a number of
films and TVfilms about India appeared around the time
when you made yourfilm Gandhi. How wouldyou account
for this interest in the Third World? Is the present crop of
films about Africa a reflection of nostalgia for British
colonialism or a desire to change apartheid?
It is very difficult to be certain. Suddenly an interest seems
to arise in science fiction, in detective stories, nostalgia,
historical subjects or love stories or whatever.
As far as Gandhi is concerned there is no question what¬
soever that the film opened up Indian material for serious
film-making. Gandhi was in the air for twenty years, and
the studios consistently maintained that nobody was interest¬
ed in India. When I went to see the head of one major stu¬
dio I was told "Who on earth do you think is interested
in a little brown man wearing a shirt and carrying a bean
pole?" It was only because of the enormous attention that
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
ttWät&i
»
âffPÇ*
"íCS^
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
This filmGandhi-
paved the way for an
examination of
imperialism, colonialism
and other related subjects.
Cinema people... began
to realize that if they
simply reflected what was
available on TV then the
cinema would die.
the film attracted long before it came out that financiers be¬
gan to think that the subject might have some potential. This
paved the way for an examination of imperialism, colonial¬
ism and other related subjects.
There is no doubt whatsoever that Indian independence
after the Second World War helped set the scene for indepen¬
dence in Africa, the emergence of the African nations, and
the weight of African opinion on the world stage. Because
of this weight there is a worldwide interest in Africa which
has nothing to do with cinema.
I also think that with the advent of television, cinema
has to some extent moved up a notch or two. The TV soap
operas, detective stories and hospital series now supply the
entertainment that is sought by vast numbers of people and
was previously supplied by the cinema. I think cinema
peoplenot the creative people who have always wanted
to do this sort of thing but the financiers and the
distributorsbegan to realize that if they attempted simply
to reflect what was available on the television screen then
the cinema would die. Cinema had to show something that
was more exciting and stimulating than television. The pos¬
sibility opened up of larger scale movies in non-familiar set¬
tings. India was non-familiar, Africa was non-familiar. Sud¬
denly a number of people like myself who were interested
in making that kind of film found the doors were easier to
push open.
Gandhi was such a success artistically and economical¬
ly that everybody assumed that a film made by the same
person or company about Africa would be just as success¬
ful. If you saw the number of ideas for films about China
which have arrived on my desk since the Italian director
Bernardo Bertolucci's Last Emperor ofChina then you'd real¬
ize how true it is that we in the cinema suppose that suc¬
cess will follow success. I don't think one should look for
any more social significance beyond that.
Do you think there is any kind of link between this post-
colonial nostalgia and the American experience as reflect¬
ed in the large number ofAmerican films about Viet Nam?
I think there is a hankering after the past. Even in India
itself there is a wish to look back to the "good old days",
however appalling they were really. There is sufficient in¬
terest and sufficient of a potential audience to justify those
movies being made. We want to discover how that era
evolved and how the paternalistic attitude of colonialism
manifested itself. But whereas I think there is a terrible sense
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
of guilt in the United States in relation to Viet Nam in the African knowledge and experience of film making is there
minds of a vast number of people, I think the sense of guilt and viable. African countries that want to create an in-
as far as empire and the UK are concerned is minimal. digenous movie industry should be discussing and trying to
understand all the problems involved. The build-up has to
Is it cheaper to film in Africa than to film in Europe, say, come slowly and it has to come out of a strongly-felt desire
or America? How important are the economics in film to create that indigenous industry. If the question is removed
making? into the political arena it will only scare off the financiers
They are undoubtedly very important. I want to make and create a counter-productive situation,
film about Thomas Paine. So I go to a distributor. The On Cry Freedom we had two or three people who were
distributor reads the screenplay and then he may say "Yes, passionate about movies but knew nothing at all about
this interests me". He then goes to the heads of his market- production. One of them, who became head prop man, I
ing and distribution divisions and says "How do you think would have no hesitation in using in the same capacity on
a picture on this subject will do in Europe? Has it got any any picture that I might make in Zimbabwe in the future,
chance in Japan? Where do we stand with this on subsequent
video?" He will then calculate that if the picture costs X In the meantime what happens to him?
dollars they have a chance of getting it back on the assump- He'll have to do something else. Few governments in the
tions made by the distribution people, which are of neces- world have actually accepted the desirability of fostering
sity conservative. The financial viability of a film is based cinema as the primary art form of the century. What is
on quite a small differential. A picture costing $15 million Africa facing? If you could get twenty minutes with Presi-
is acceptable and a picture costing $19 million is not. The dent Mugabe you could perhaps persuade him of the im-
company has to hold down the budget to a figure which portance of creating a film school or making sure that a
is viable. number of people came to a European school. But what is
For a number of years the majority of movies made in Mugabe doing? He's fighting for his country's life. Film
Africa were shot in Kenya. Now if you go and talk to the making has to come so far down on the list. And the heart-
budget people or the production people or the location breaking thing is that whereas I believe that the potential
managers they will say to you Kenya is tough because the really does exist to continue the work that has been begun
prices you have to pay there are very stiff. And so if you with the movies that have been made there, I think my props
are thinking of shooting in Africa you look for other coun- man is in terrible trouble. I get a letter from him every two
tries such as Botswana or Zimbabwe. The difficulty is that or three months asking whether I know of a picture coming
because of the tradition of film making in Kenya you've in. The terrible thing is that the situation has got to be turned
got a background of understanding of the problems involved, round and it must no longer be a question of movies coming
A degree of expertise has been built up. On Cry Freedom, in from outside but of Africans fostering their own cinema
which was filmed in Zimbabwe, if we had been able to find in some way. But because of the problems of Africa, the
a sensational location manager who understood filming who difficulties and the existence of South Africa in its present
was black and who lived in Zimbabwe we would have em- form, the chances of this are very remote. They've estab-
ployed him. He would have known ten times more and un- lished central film laboratories in Zimbabwe and I think
derstood ten times more what our requirements were than many people there really see the potential of cinema. But
somebody from outside who knew nothing about Zim- I think one of the greatest problems facing this totally
babwe. But the difficulty is that you do not find a high lev- understandable desire to say "We are black Africa and we
el of expertise, no one has had an opportunity to acquire will make our own movies" is that there will not be a suffi-
the experience. cient indigenous return from what is made. Somehow or
I believe that the African continent is so exciting, so full other a number of movies will have to be made that can
of drama, so devastating in its imagery that there is no ques- find specialist audiences around the world and bring returns
tion whatsoever that if the African countries themselves are of foreign currency.
prepared to acknowledge that they have to make certain con¬
tributions, then the potential for building up indigenous Unesco Courier interview by Chris Vieler-Porter
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
I
\vV
kàt
<
m
.y
X
m
V** *
%.A W%
'" .«*1
..dB
" fl
"
ta
1
T'H
1 i
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
EDITORIAL
1,
HAT better way into the heart of a country could there be than the streets
of its towns and cities? Here time-worn labyrinthine alleyways...there busy modern
thoroughfaresstreets endow cities with their personality, in some cases balanced
and harmonious, in others overwhelming.
In many parts of the world the urban environment is changing rapidly through
pressures of industrialization, the influx of newcomers from rural areas, and the
incursions of the automobile. Old streets are being torn apart and the memories
of the past enshrined in them are fading. And yet the life of a city is rooted in its
streets and neighbourhoods. Without this fabric etched with so many traces of the
past, what would cities look like and what sort of places would they be?
Many city-dwellers today are organizing themselves to defend their cities against
the threat of dehumanization, and the widespread creation of neighbourhood defence
committees has been a striking urban phenomenon of recent years. What can be
done to encourage urban populations to identify more closely with their environment
and to defend it more effectively?
One answer to this question may be found in a Unesco-supported project entitled
"Memories in a Street" in which seventy cities throughout the world took part three
years ago. The project, which originated in an idea put forward by Robert Delpire,
director of France's National Photography Centre, was organized by the International
Association of Art (IAA) and France's National Academy of Street Arts. It began
in Paris with displays in ten Metro stations which presented a pictorial history of
the French capital. Cities taking part in the operation were invited to select century-
old photos of their historic streets and display them on the spot where they had
been taken so many years before. "Memories in a Street" evoked a wide response
as citizens ransacked their family archives in search of old documents and photos,
while their children combed avenues and alleyways photographing historic features
that caught their eye.
In Paris, Tokyo, Abidjan, Baghdad, Colombo and other great cities people thus got
together to celebrate the life of their streets, past and present. For them perhaps
the rediscovery of the street was a first step towards making their city a more human
place to live in.
Street Scene at Five in
the Afternoon (1887), by
the French painter Louis The Editors wish to thank Mr. André Parinaud, Commissioner-General of the IAA at the time when the
Anquetin (1861-1932). "Memories in a Street" operation was organized, for his help in the preparation of this issue.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Friedrichstrasse,
a link in the chain
of history
BY CHRISTIANE MENGIN
rrom the late 19th century
until the end of World
War I, the Friedrichstrasse
bustled with activity.
X OUR kilometres in length and lying athwart
the boundary between the two parts of the city,
the Friedrichstrasse sums up the history of Ber¬
lin better than any of its other thoroughfares. The
Friedrichstrasse is more representative than, for
example, the Unter den Linden, the wide
boulevard in the east where, during the eight¬
eenth century, Frederick the Great, thirsting for
prestige, erected a number of monumental build¬
ings, or than the Kurfürstendamm, the "Champs-
Elysees" of the western part of the city.
Sleepy suburbs
and unobtrusive houses
At the beginning of the eighteenth century,
Berlin was becoming more and more cramped
within the straitjacket of its ramparts and a new
district, Friedrichstadt, was constructed outside
the city walls. Baroque in style, this outgrowth
was traversed by three streets, the Wilhelmstrasse,
the Friedrichstrasse, which formed the central
axis, and the Lindenstrasse, leading southwards
to the Rondell circus, inspired by the Piazza del
Popólo in Rome. In the middle of the circus stood
a column commemorating the battle of Water¬
loo which marked the south-eastern limit ci the
extension of the city.
Until the late nineteenth century, Friedrich¬
stadt remained essentially a residential suburb
with its rows of identical, unpretentious, two-
storey, bourgeois houses. Here and there an ele¬
gant aristocratic property enlivened the aspect of
this sleepy suburb. Nothing disturbed the calm
of the Friedrichstrasse except the passage of
hearses on their way to the out-of- town cemetery
or the tramp of soldiers heading for the Rondell
parade ground or the Tempelhofer Feld training
ground to the south of the city. Barracks and sta¬
bles added the finishing touch to the somewhat
martial aspect of the Friedrichstrasse.
The arrival of a number of shopkeepers and
craftsmen during the first half of the nineteenth
century gave little indication of the frenetic 11
m p
- »-
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Above, plan of Berlin in 1740 showing the
Friedrichstrasse, the main north-south axis through the new
suburb of the Friedrichstadt. Below left, photo taken in
1871 of the Belle-Alliance Platz, better known as the
Rondell, which gives on to the Friedrichstrasse. Below
right, the Rondell, renamed the Mehringplatz in 1945, as
it is today. The only vestige of the past is the peace column
in the centre, which was erected in 1843.
12
¿J^-^HmSzw
%M fe^£ ** v^^^ ZW yJ
JâlÉfliaaiaMaii»^ üjk^aflB ^a^T . .3
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Krjp^MikmSSi
development that was to change the face of the
Friedrichstrasse following the proclamation of
William I of Prussia as Emperor of Germany in
1871. When this period of frenzied growth and
speculation began, the historic heart of Berlin and
the Unter den Linden were bursting at the seams.
Not a scrap of land was available for building,
so it was in the Friedrichstadt district that the de¬
velopment occurred that was to transform the
somewhat provincial chief city of Prussia into the
capital of the Reich.
The end of a golden age
A vast construction programme turned the once
peaceful Friedrichstrasse into a bustling main
thoroughfare with heavy traffic and lined with
serried ranks of fashionable shops, restaurants,
cafés, night-clubs, theatres and a wide variety
of hotels, business headquarters, banks, insurance
companies and government offices. The "street
of 107 cinemas" housed a host of studios and
workshops of the youthful German motion
picture industry, while newspapers and publishers
established themselves in the nearby Kochstrasse.
The golden age of the Friedrichstrasse lasted
until the fall of the German Empire in 1918. Its
long, narrow perspective, disappearing into the
distance between the contrasting façades of the
three- to five-storey buildings that had replaced
its original houses, has been immortalized in
hundreds of photographs and illustrations.
Passers-by, casual strollers, elegantly-dressed
women and office clerks jostled each other on the
narrow sidewalks beneath a profusion of multi¬
coloured signs. With its trams and old, horse-
drawn buses, the Friedrichstrasse hummed with
the feverish activity of an Empire launching
itself into a tardy but breakneck process of
industrialization.
After the First World War, Germany was
plunged by defeat into an economic slump that
did not spare the Friedrichstrasse. Nevertheless,
although building activity was considerably
slowed down, this centre of Berlin life inspired
several avant-garde architects to conceive some
of their most daring projects. In 1921, on the oc¬
casion of an architectural competition for an
office block at the S-Bahn underground station
in the Friedrichstrasse, Ludwig Mies van der
(checkpoint Charlie, a
border control point on the
Friedrichstrasse. Left, the
Kurfürstendamm, a lively
centre of Berlin life. Right,
the Alexanderplatz, in the
eastern part of the city
between Karl-Marx-Allee
and the Friedrichstrasse, is
part of a vast area which
has been reconstructed
since 1961.
CHRISTIANE MENGIN,
French art historian
specializing in modern
German architecture, is a
lecturer at the University of
Paris I. With a Franco-
German team, she is
preparing a study to he
published shortly on
Franco-German relations
between 1940 and 1950 and
their effects on urban
architecture and planning.
Rohe designed a triangular-shaped glass tower
which presaged the glass and steel buildings he
was to erect in the United States twenty years
later. Around 1930, the functionalist town-
planner Ludwig Hilberseimer suggested that
several blocks on either side of the Friedrich¬
strasse should be demolished and replaced by rec¬
tangular, eight-storey office blocks so as to make
more rational use of space in the business centre.
This visionary project was never realized, but it
was no accident that it was to have been sited in
this lively part of town.
Although its role as the capital's business and
shopping centre continued, artistic and literary
life became concentrated in the west of the city
around the Kurfürstendamm. However, a num¬
ber of the great names of the theatre remained
faithful to the Friedrichstrasse. Max Reinhardt,
in particular, continued to direct many produc¬
tions, at the theatre company which in 1954 be¬
came Bertolt Brecht's Berliner Ensemble and at
the Grosse Spielhaus, transformed in 1919 by the
architect Hans Poelzig into an expressionist
theatre.
A city in ruins
When Hitler came to power in 1933, the
Friedrichstadt district was largely taken over by
the Nazis. They occupied many old buildings in
which they installed the government offices of
the Third Reich. Albert Speer's monumental plan
for Berlin, whose fruition was prevented by the
war, did not include the Friedrichstrasse. Only
the planned redevelopment of Museum Island and
its extension westward would have modified its
appearance slightly. The proposed construction
on either bank of the Spree River of four new
museums would have involved, among other
things, the demolition of the Admiralpalast (to¬
day the Metropol), a popular theatre devoted to
operettas and musical comedies.
In May 1945, after the battle of Berlin, the
centre of the city was in ruins.
When Berlin was divided up between the Al¬
lies, the Red Army, the first on the scene, oc¬
cupied the eastern part of the city. The dividing
line followed the boundaries of the existing dis¬
tricts. Part of the old Friedrichstadt district, in¬
cluding three-quarters of the Friedrichstrasse, was 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
in the Soviet sector. The fourth quarter, to the
south, was allotted to the American sector.
In the hope of a reunification of the city, the
local authorities in the west delayed reconstruct¬
ing the area under their control so as to be able
to do so in collaboration with their counterparts
in the east. At that time, the southern end of the
Friedrichstrasse was a sea of mud from which
arose the sinister shells of a few buildings that had
escaped total destruction by bombing or in the
fighting.
In the east the authorities began to raze
ruined buildings. The winters of the latter years
of the war, when no heating was available, had
seriously damaged the stucco-work and external
ornamentation that had once been one of the
street's attractions. They were removed and the
façades were coated with a beige rendering which
rapidly weathered to a gloomy grey.
The erection of the Berlin Wall, in 1961, set
the seal on the division of the city into two parts.
The Friedrichstrasse took on a new symbolic sig¬
nificance since it was the site of two crossing-
points, the Friedrichstrasse underground station,
which had become a railway station, to the north,
and, to the south, the famous "Checkpoint
Charlie", a reinforced barrier set up in the mid¬
dle of the roadway and reserved for use by
foreigners.
From that time onwards, renovation of the
Friedrichstrasse began in both east and west.
Berlin's 750th anniversary
In the west, the renovation programme began
with the reconstruction of the Mehringplatz, the
former Rondell. The Wilhelmstrasse and the Lin-
denstrasse, which both led to it, were diverted
and it became a pedestrian precinct whose cir¬
cularity was emphasized by the construction, be¬
tween 1968 and 1975, of two rings of massive
buildings.
After 1980, however, this policy gave way to
an altogether different approach to urban reno¬
vation. An attempt was made to conserve build¬
ings that had survived and still bore witness to
the past glories of the Friedrichstrasse. The origi¬
nal street pattern was retained and an effort was
made to take into account the architecture of the
earlier buildings. The aim was to restore this ur¬
ban area, so roughly treated by history, while
keeping in mind the integrality of Berlin, evoked
in 1987 by the city's 750th anniversary.
In the east, too, the reconstruction of the
Friedrichstrasse went on apace. In the early 1980s,
several buildings were under construction, among
them a huge auditorium, the Friedrichstadtpalast,
an international Trade Centre and several modern
hotels, including the Metropol and the Unter den
Linden. Other buildings still in the planning
stageapartment blocks, restaurants, cafés and a
cinemawill all help to restore the former charm
of the Friedrichstrasse.
Skyscraper-studded skyline
in Shinjuku, one of Tokyo's
business districts. Inset,
entrance to Rikugien
Garden.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
A city
of towers
. .an(^
traditions
BY SARAH ZARMATI
IN 1878, an Englishwoman named Isabella Bird
toured Japan on foot, horseback and by sedan-
chair. On her arrival at Shiganawa station (then
one of Tokyo's two railway stations), she noticed
that the houses, temples and public buildings
were all low and in many cases enveloped in a
profusion of greenery. In this great city, which
already had more than 800,000 inhabitants, there
was no sign of smoke nor of factory chimneys.
When she saw the blue waters of the bay and the
fishing smacks drawn up on the shore, she ex¬
claimed "Where is Tokyo?".1
Today Tokyo has over 10 million inhabitants
and the only green spaces are to be found in a
few parks, in temple precincts and around the Im¬
perial palace. Almost all its districts bristle with
tower blocks, while industrial development and
expressways have covered over the waterways,
the beaches and most access roads to the bay,
whose water is now grey. Nevertheless people
still wonder "where is Tokyo?" and especially
how to find their way around there.
There seem to be two independent networks
of streets in Tokyo. There are the functional and
impersonal major arteries, with their imposing
tower blocks, dense traffic and multicoloured
neon signs. There is also a labyrinth of alleys and
passages lined with low-roofed houses, narrow
streets where the pedestrian still takes precedence
over the motorist. The usual landmarks such as 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
major axes, vistas and monuments, that help vi¬
sitors to find their way around a city, either do
not exist or are hard to find. Instead of joining
the different parts of the city, many of the prin¬
cipal streets seem to separate and isolate them.
A conglomeration
of villages
Another of Tokyo's distinctive features is its lack
of a centre, although it bears only a very superfi¬
cial resemblance to that other great city without
a centre, Los Angeles, whose linear development
seems to have been determined by the railway
and later by the automobile. In Tokyo, the major
axes between districts were built after the earth¬
quake of 1923, when the city already had more
than 3 million inhabitants. There is no focal point
partly because Tokyo has developed through the
gradual amalgamation of a number of villages,
which have, unusually, survived intact in the
heart of the modern city.
At one
with nature
Except in the old cities of Nara and Kyoto,
modelled on Changan in China, the geometric
city layout has never been favoured in Japan.
Japanese town planning seems to have been a
response either to military needs, with impasses
and mazy streets built as obstacles to invading
forces, or to have been influenced by factors such
as the natural features of the site, a wish to inte¬
grate with existing buildings and to meet the
changing needs of the population. Whereas many
Western cities have a linear plan which reflects
the primacy of motor traffic, the pedestrian has
always been paramount in Japanese town plan¬
ning. The primacy of nature can still be felt in
Tokyo, where the few vistas are not aligned with
monuments but with natural features such as
Mount Fuji or Mount Tsukuba.
The French scholar Augustin Berque has said
of traditional Japanese town planning that "the
logic of the streets adds to the impression of
movement, of getting somewhere", that "the
journey is more important than the destination",
and that "this weakening of the transit function
subordinates the street to the district which it ir¬
rigates."2 The neighbourhood is the basic unit in
(organized children's
games in Tokyo's Kakigara
district. The street had been
closed to traffic for the day.
1 ea ceremony at the
wisteria festival,
Kameido Tanjin.
SARAH ZARMATI,
American landscape
specialist, is adviser to the
Franco-Japanese Co¬
operation Programme for
Urban Development and a
consultant with the
National Landscape School
at Versailles, France. She is
a member of the editorial
board of Paysage et
Aménagement magazine,
and (with Catherine Royer)
the author of a book on
French parks and gardens
from 1900 to 1945, to be
published later this year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Tokyo. The cultural and social life of the city can
only be understood in terms of each neighbour¬
hood, especially its small traditional streets.
Community spirit
The streets of Tokyo, like those of other Asian
cities, are crowded with market stalls, and daily
life spills out of accommodation which is often
cramped. Pot plants adorn the pavements and
streets as well as windowsills, and casually-dressed
local people can often be seen sitting outside chat¬
ting with their neighbours or taking the air on
fine evenings.
Many community events take place in the
street. Each district organizes traditional festivals,
called matsuri. In Europe, festivals often take
place in public squares, whereas in Japanese ci¬
ties they tend to take the form of a procession.
A festival begins in the temple. A procession then
emerges from the sacred precincts and wends its
way through the streets of the neighbourhood be¬
fore spreading out into spacious avenues. Big
crowds take part in these festivals, and even on
the main roads traffic slows down or stops while
the procession goes by.
The use of public areas for community ac¬
tivities takes other forms. In spring, garlands of
plastic flowers are hung on telegraph poles and
lamp standards to herald the flowering of cherry
blossom and wisteria. Every day, ubiquitous loud¬
speakers announce the end of school and other
events of general interest. Advance warnings of
air pollution are also made by loudspeaker. Each
neighbourhood also has its kooban (small police
station) for maintaining order and providing
visitors with information.
As a result of growing concern about earth¬
quakes and fire, the city authorities are being led
to sacrifice these little streets with their low
wooden houses in favour of wide avenues with
more fire- and quake-proof buildings.
Is one of the most lively features of Tokyo's
traditional way of life destined to disappear?
1. Unbeaten Tracks in Japan, by Isabella Bird. Charles E. Tuttle Co.,
Tokyo, 1973.
2. Vivre l'espace au Japon, by Augustin Berque. Presses Universitaires
de France, Paris, 1982.
1 op, taiko drums are
beaten to celebrate the
flowering of the azaleas in
the Shinto shrine at Nezu.
Above, traditional picnic
under the cherry trees in
Ueno Park.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
A trip along
the Séptima
BY ANNE BERTY
18
X HE Carrera Séptima, more commonly
referred to as the "Séptima", Bogota's Seventh
Avenue, is the Colombian capital's busiest
thoroughfare. In this one avenue are encapsulat¬
ed the personality, the history, the culture and
the daily life of the city, which was founded in
1537 by the Spaniard Gonzalo Jiménez de
Quesada.
This vast, thirty-kilometre-long axis, which
links the richest residential area to the north with
the poorest working-class district to the south,
is also a huge barometer of the social and eco¬
nomic climate of a conurbation with a popula¬
tion of four and a half million, swollen by the
urban explosion of the last forty years.
From Bolivar Square to the old district
of La Candelaria
A thoroughfare like the Séptima is no place for
the pedestrian and the traffic is so dense that
casual strolling is discouraged. However, in the
older districts of Bogotá, the Santa Fé of coloni¬
al times, the Séptima still has a certain human
dimension where it links Bolivar Square with the
Candelaria district, whose carefully restored patri¬
cian houses recall the days of the viceroyalty of
New Granada.
Bolivar Square, or Plaza Mayor, remains the
heart of Bogota's civic, political and religious life.
The Capitol, the Town Hall, the Law Courts and
the Cathedral, representing the four essential ele¬
ments of public life, each occupy one of the four
sides of this huge square, whose stone buildings
exemplify the austerity of colonial town
planning.
Encompassing the styles of every epoch of its
history, this architectural ensemble has witnessed
many historic events. It was the scene of such
glorious occasions as the Declaration of Indepen¬
dence of 20 July 1810 and celebrations of the vic¬
tories of Simón Bolívar, as well as of various
bloody insurrections.
After being long neglected and discredited,
the Candelaria district, with its narrow streets and
ANNE BERTY,
French architect and an
official at her country's
housing ministry, is the
author of a book on
Colombian architecture and
was co-organizer of an
exhibition on the same theme
which was held at the
Pompidou Centre, Paris, in
1980.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
BOGOTA
I anoramic view of the
Carrera Séptima, the
30-km-long thoroughfare
which blends the
architecture of Bogota's
colonial past with bold
modem designs. Above, the
Septima's business district.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
1 ark Towers,
Independence Park, Bogotá,
was built by the architect
Rogelio Salmona between
1968 and 1972.
20
regular, geometric layout, has been revitalized by
intellectuals, artists and cultural organizations.
From the outside, its manzanas (blocks), most of
which are square and divided into long, uniform¬
ly rectangular solares (lots), reveal nothing of their
interior spaciousness. The usually austere, anony¬
mous appearance of these blocks underlines the
fundamentally inward-looking nature of the
buildings of which they are composed.
The few openings that the houses present to
the street are hidden behind fine balconies of slat¬
ted wood or ornamental grilles. Thus domestic
life is shielded, not only from outside eyes, but
also from too open an outward-looking view
which would reduce its intimacy. The life of the
household is organized around a central patio,
which is surrounded by arcades and galleries and
is the focal point of all circulation within the
house, as well as providing the rooms with some
of their light.
The decoration of the floors, the intricate
woodwork of the galleries, the gardens enclosed
with whitewashed cob walls and the presence of
plants and flowers throughout the house, create
in the heart of the city a peaceful and harmoni¬
ous environment.
The splendid chequer-board of La Candelaria
Colonial-style mansions
in the Candelaria district.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
reaches out to the foothills of the Eastern Cor¬
dillera, the natural limit of the "Sabana (savan¬
na) de Bogota", the city's grandiose site. The
proximity of the mountains and the working-class
district to the south lends a picturesque and some¬
what anachronistic air of animation to this area
only a few blocks away from the presidential
palace and some of the major cultural and touris¬
tic points of interest. Donkeys passing by laden
with eucalyptus branches, bundles of wood,
bunches of flowers, and other goods, are a
reminder that Bogota has been swollen by the ex¬
odus from rural areas, and that thousands of
former peasants are struggling to survive in the
city.
Chicha and agua de panela
A host of small boutiques and craftsmen's work¬
shops bring life to the Candelaria district. Much
frequented, they relieve the solemnity of the
colonial-style residences and keep alive old tradi¬
tions. A bar sign hanging in a patio is a reminder
of the chicha (beer made from maize) stalls the
aristocratic families used to keep on the ground
floors of their houses in colonial times and in the
early days of Independence. Further on is one of
1 he cathedral on Bolivar
Square, outlined against the
foothills of the Eastern
Cordillera of the Andes.
the last aguadepanelaria, where a drink sweetened
and coloured with "panela" (sugar-loaf made
from raw sugar-cane) was served, as well as the
famous santafereño chocolate. Everywhere there
is a diversity of small businesses: tiny bookshops,
antique shops, cabinet-makers, shoemakers,
tailors and many other small artisans' stalls.
Returning to the Séptima and passing north¬
wards through Bolivar Square, the village at¬
mosphere gives way to the forms and symbols
of a modern cityglass-clad towers and concrete
skyscrapers. From one end of the avenue to the
other, even on the same sidewalk, there is a strik¬
ing juxtaposition of the relics of a still recent past
and the more aggressive indications of modernity.
This itinerary, in keeping with the spirit of
Bogotá today, evokes a series of contradictory
emotions. It includes a magnificent tower block
in international style, a hamlet with Victorian
overtones and a building cleverly drawing inspi¬
ration from the Bauhaus. One of the finest ex¬
amples of the new Colombian architecture, Park
Towers, was built in Independence Park between
1968 and 1972 by Rogelio Salmona. It
subtly takes advantage of the light and verdure
of the site, and echoes the majestic contours of
the landscape. 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
A colourful
kaleidoscope
BY PHILIPPE HAERINGER
22
AjIKE the continent itself, with its variety of cul¬
tures and climates, the streets of African cities are
rich in contrasts. Some, in sandy areas, are lined
with shrubs and treesmango, avocado, palm and
pawpawbehind which huts with sloping roofs
are concealed. In others the warm colours of
lateritic soil blend with those of the straw and
clay-daubed walls of flat-roofed houses facing
onto inner courtyards. In yet others the houses
are mainly in "carabotte" style (clapboard houses
often built in English cottage fashion). Painted
colonial white, they open out on to verandahs
and lawns. And then there are streets lined with
a succession of façades, some high, some low, of
often uncompleted cement houses, behind which
are overcrowded tenement courtyards.
The latter kind of street is typical of the port
and capital city of Abidjan, Côte d'Ivoire (popu¬
lation between two and three million, one
hundred times greater than fifty years ago), or at
least of its working-class areas, in particular the
"old" Treichville district (developed in 1930),
Koumassi (1950) and the huge suburb of Abobo
which mushroomed around 1970. The dwellings
there are all the samestereotyped, ugly and
strictly functional. As a result of the land and ur¬
ban planning policies adopted, coupled with
population growth and economic expansion,
most of the inhabitants of Abidjan are tenants.
All these houses and courtyards contain rented
properties.
A playground for all
Against this somewhat bleak architectural back¬
ground, worsened by the eternal problem of road
maintenance (though the authorities have made
a major effort to improve the situation in recent
years), the often rutted, muddy, dirty streets of
Treichville, Koumassi and Abobo are, need it be
said, overflowing with life and human warmth.
In these streets which are usually nameless (at best
they have a number), life is intense and firmly
rooted in the present.
It has become a commonplace to evoke the
warmth and exuberance of the crowds which
throng the market-places of Africa and the multi¬
coloured costumes of the women. It is perhaps
less well known that the same animation reigns
in the more remote, less frequented streets. There
are no "dead" streets.
Why is this so? First of all, it is due to the
demographic pattern. The courtyards are full of
children for whom the street is an after-school
playground. Secondly, it is due to the very na¬
ture of these rented, collective dwellings in which
the living accommodation is little more than a
series of cells. As a result, domestic life opens out
on to the street and the neighbourhood. The
street is the playground of both child and adult
and the setting for quiet games of ludo, draughts
or awelé between two, or full-scale neighbour¬
hood tournaments. Games like these make up an
important part of the leisure-time activities of the
inhabitants of Abidjan. In one street in Abobo
there is a draughts school. In another there is a
carpenter who specializes in making tables for
bar-football, a game which has proliferated out¬
side bars in recent years and is also played in the
entrances to some of the courtyards.
Leisure activities such as these are for the
men, but in the life of the street women are even
more in evidence. Housewives, or young wom¬
en who cannot or do not want to leave home to
work, set up in the street as peddlers of knick-
knacks, fritters or grilled maize. Then there are
the water-sellers. There are no longer any public
water-fountains in Abidjan, but here and there
are private watering points at which water can
be bought. The spouts are high up so that women
r~'_
*
$Mr
r/> ',
.
i
<#
#3?
V
\riâ
rUJÀ
'i
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
s <
w
: m
STREETSCAPES ^
ABIDJAN 1
Local market in the
suburb of Treichville.
f -m
tvVrttr
*fc»
Im
. . «*-.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24
rrom top to bottom:
Photographer's shop, Abidjan.
Women wearing multi¬
coloured costumes.
The workshops of many
small traders, such as this
knitwear manufacturer, are
open to the street.
Water is one of the wares
sold at this general store.
customers can fill their recipients without hav¬
ing to take them off their heads. Nearby are the
charcoal-sellers whose wares are in daily demand
for cooking, which is always done on wood or
charcoal. Also close at hand will be the "bou¬
tique", a tiny shop which sells matches, soap,
tomato purée and oil. For their supplies of vegeta¬
bles, fish and meat the women go each day to the
local market.
Calligraphy, trades and crafts
In recent years Abidjan has experienced an ex¬
plosion of crafts, services and trades. The econom¬
ic crisis has accelerated the natural tendency
towards diversification. Trades formerly concen¬
trated on the main thoroughfares are now tend¬
ing to spread throughout the city. Advertising for
them has become more arresting. Calligraphers
specializing in sign-writing and banner design are
in great demand. The art of window-dressing has
developed and new trades and new services are
springing up and prospering.
Dress-makers, for example, who formerly
plied their trade in the market-places or from
premises discreetly located in the depths of the
courtyards, are now opening up in streets oc¬
cupied by ready-to-wear boutiques with attrac¬
tive shop-fronts. Equally striking is the sudden
proliferation of private telephone kiosks, often
associated with such services as photocopying, ex¬
press typing facilities and the plastic covering of
identity papers. They are to be found alongside
small legal and tax advice bureaux and mini es¬
tate agencies, all of which were hitherto unknown
outside the main thoroughfares.
No less remarkable is the upsurge in the num¬
ber of private clinics and other health centres;
even the healers are opening their own "clinics".
Similar innovations are occurring in education,
where private enterprise is coming to the rescue
of the public authorities. In the streets of Abobo,
hoarding after hoarding proclaims the merits of
kindergartens, primary and secondary schools,
evening classes and workshops for apprentices.
An immense variety of crafts are practised in
African streets. In addition to repair men and
"mamy-foutou" (women seWmgfoutou, a dish of
bananas or yams), you will find hairdressers and
hair-braiders, photographers, tailors, shoemakers,
watch "doctors", mechanics, automobile electri¬
cians, coach-builders and welders, brick-makers,
blacksmiths, plumbers, glaziers and cabinet¬
makers, key-cutters, fan specialists, and many
more besides.
Beyond the street, the group
The animation of the street largely compensates
for the anonymity of the urban fabric. It creates
a hierarchy of streets and gives them a soul. It
creates more landmarks: a particularly striking
sign may be popularly adopted as a street name,
as in Aunt Solange Street or Symphony Bar
PHILIPPE HAERINGER,
of France, is director of
research at the French
Institute of Scientific
Research for Development
and Co-operation. Since
1988 he has led a project
designed to test methods of
comparing town planning
models in different parts of
the world. His publications
include two studies on life
in Abidjan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Street. But everything is in a state of constant flux.
The people of Abidjan live in the present. What
room can there be for nostalgia?
It is true that in the old Treichville district
some property owners look back with regret to
the days when they first arrived. Similar feelings
are sometimes expressed in Koumassi and Abobo,
but they are far from being shared by the great
majority of the present population. Only a few
place names remain to evoke the early days,
names such as Avocado-tree, The Other Side of
the Tracks and Wireless (referring to a large tree,
a railway line and a radio transmitter), or the
name of the landowner or the village communi¬
ty which began the development (Ayébi, Agnis-
sankoi, and. so on).
It is not easy for the city-dwellers to identify
with such a new and uniform environment, in
which accommodation is mainly rented by a mo¬
bile and rapidly increasing population. Yet, be¬
yond the still vital ethnic ties, new links are being
established based on geographical proximity over
a wider area than the immediate neighbourhood.
The district, or even the arrondissement (today
called the commune) is supplanting the street.
The activities of groups or associations, whether
they are concerned with sport, games, music, sav¬
ing or investment, professional life, religion or
politics, are all mainly situated at this level.
In this way local loyalties develop, with the
inhabitants closing ranks against the threat of a
sector clearance, even though this alone may not
be enough to halt the bulldozers' advance, or to
demand the provision of amenities. But such in¬
itiatives never get very far. At one time the pub¬
lic authorities and international organizations
hoped that the city-dwellers of Africa would
themselves take a hand in the development and
upkeep of the streets of their cities, but these
hopes were swept away in the rising tide of ur¬
ban expansion.
Thus road maintenance and other infrastruc¬
tures remain the responsibility of the authorities.
Nevertheless these authorities can only view with
satisfaction the remarkable vitality of the trades
and crafts sector and the equally remarkable ca¬
pacity of the people of Abidjan, who come from
all over western Africa, to breathe life into their
city and live together in comparative harmony,
despite their many differences.
Muddy though they may be, the streets of
Abidjan are well worth lingering in.
A family restaurant where
the cooking is done in the
street to attract passers-by.
On the menu are local
dishes such as foutou.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Gorky Street,
fifty years
of change
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
VJORKY Street, Moscow, formerly known as
Tverskaya Street, after the city of Tver (now Kali¬
nin) to which it led, epitomizes the changes the
Soviet capital has experienced over the past fifty
years. As Tverskaya Street it was the main trad¬
ing link between Moscow and Tver, one of the
oldest cities of Russia. Lined with luxury shops,
their signs written in both French and Russian,
it was at that time one of Moscow's liveliest
thoroughfares. It was here that Muscovites had
their first experience of traffic jams, and photo¬
graphs taken at the beginning of the century show
among the bustle of horse-drawn vehicles and
trams the first automobiles imported into Russia.
Despite its commercial importance, Tver¬
skaya Street, like most Moscow streets, was nar¬
row and twisting. For although by the mid-1920s
the city had a population of some two million
inhabitants, it had more the air of an overgrown
village than of the great capital it was to become.
This large village was clearly ill-suited for its role
as capital of the Soviet Union and, in the immedi¬
ate aftermath of the Revolution, a multitude of
plans for its redevelopment were put forward,
ranging from a first project, which would have
made of Moscow a sort of Roman forum but
which never got beyond the blueprint stage, to
a plan dating from 1935, some provisions of
which are still in force. The 1935 plan revolved
around Tverskaya Street, by then renamed
Gorky Street.
A 'model' thoroughfare
The objective of the 1935 plan, the Plan for the
Reconstruction of Moscow, as it was called, was
to make Moscow "a model communist city". It
put an end to the often stormy quarrels between
those who favoured moderate urban decentrali¬
zation and the protagonists of total decentraliza¬
tion. It confirmed the concentric structure of
Moscowopposed by the modernistsand
turned Gorky Street into a "model" thorough¬
fare. Execution of the plan was entrusted to the
architect Arkady Mordvinov who, in the ideo¬
logical struggles of the early 1930s, was responsi¬
ble for the victory of the concept of socialist
realism in architecture over the theories of the
constructivists, who favoured a modern form of
architecture close to that of Le Corbusier or the
German Bauhaus school.
In practical terms, the operation consisted
1 verskaya Street (now Gorky Street)
at the turn of the century.
/»
^&£^7»
> _
»-' '
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
m
¿\
Larger-than-life statue
of workers from
a collective farm.
Aloscow's Main Telegraph
Office on Gorky Street.
basically of widening and straightening Gorky
Street. Several buildings considered to be of lit¬
tle interest were demolished and replaced by
more imposing structures in the new official style,
a mixture of Italian Renaissance and Russian Im¬
perial. Others were detached from their founda¬
tions, jacked up and transported to new sites on
frameworks of railway lines. By the eve of World
War II, Gorky Street looked much as it does to¬
day and was referred to as the "Champs Elysées
of Moscow".
Gastronom No. 1
Going north up Gorky Street, from the junction
with Marx Prospekt to the headquarters of the
Moscow City Soviet, whole chapters of the his¬
tory of the city unfold. The typically fin-de-siècle
National Hotel housed the members of the Soviet
Government and their families when Moscow be¬
came the capital of the USSR. The taller annexe,
built some fifteen years ago a few metres from
the old building, breaks the roofline established
in the 1930s. During the pre-war years, militants
and administrators of the Comintern occupied
the Lux Hotel until the Third International was
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
dissolved in 1943. Farther on is the elaborate win¬
dow display of Gastronom No. 1, the pre-
Revolution delicatessen in which caviare from the
Caspian lay cheek by jowl with foie gras from
France. Elisseiev, the owner of Gastronom, later
emigrated to Paris.
Next stop is a large rectangular square on the
Gorky Street side of which stands the headquart¬
ers of the Moscow Soviet, an eighteenth-century
building designed by the great Russian architect
Matvey F. Kazakov. Opposite stands the Marx,
Engels, Lenin Institute. Built in 1926, its unclut¬
tered style heralds the beginning of modernism
in the Soviet Union. Together with the Main
Telegraph Office (1927), also in Gorky Street,
it is one of the buildings whose completion
coincided with the tenth anniversary of the
Revolution.
The square is the site of two historic monu¬
ments: a statue of Prince Yuri Dolgoruky, the
legendary founder of Moscow, and the offices of
the newspaper Izvestia ("News"). Resolutely
jMoscow City Hall. In
foreground, statue of Prince
Yuri Dolgoruky, Moscow's
legendary founder.
ANATOLE KOPP,
French architect, is a
professor emeritus at the
University of Paris VIII and
a specialist in modern
architecture, especially that
of the Soviet Union. The
latest of his many published
works, a history of Soviet
architecture from 1918 to
1980, is scheduled for
publication in 1990.
modern in style, the Izvestia building dates from
the late 1920s. Its windows were filled with
photographs, graphics and displays heralding a
new era.
Ancient buildings and modern constructions
are, however, the exception. Taken as a whole,
Gorky Street is the work of Arkady Mordvinov
and his collaborators. More than any other
grouping of buildings in Moscow it epitomizes
a bygone architectural era. With its colonnades
and cornices inspired by the palaces of Leningrad
and thence by Italian classicism and the Renais¬
sance, it represents the triumph of socialist real¬
ism in architecture.
Yet the statues that crown these buildings are
not the familiar deities of graeco-roman mythol¬
ogy. They are the heroes, real or imaginary, of
the first Five-Year Plans. Workers, peasants and
Red Army soldiers stand guard over Gorky
Street, bearing witness to an age that strove to
consummate the marriage of architectural forms
and social objectives. 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
STREETSCAPES
CAIRO
A covered street
in old Cairo.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
BY ALAIN BONNAMY
/
In the heart
of an ancient capital
/AIRO does not possess a single noble street,
but a quantity of small ones that twist and turn.
This clearly shows that all the houses were built
at random, everyone building on the plot of land
that pleased him, without asking himself whether
he was blocking a street or not." These remarks
were made in 1657. How far do they apply to
Cairo today?
In the Cairo of the past there was no obliga¬
tion to respect the line of the street when build¬
ing. If a second house or site was acquired on the
opposite side of the roadway, the two plots were
simply joined upexpansion at the expense of the
public thoroughfare. In this way many streets be¬
came blind alleys which served as courtyards
where women gossiped, went about their domes¬
tic tasks, or supervised the games of their numer¬
ous offspring. At the entrance to the alleys, dogs
bared their teeth at would-be intruders.
A source of shade
Other customs made the streets even narrower.
Only a thin strip of sky could be seen between
the balconies with their moucharabys* jutting out
from windows on both sides of the street.
Benches and platforms were permanently in¬
stalled in front of shops and cafés. Merchants and
their wares even invaded the courtyards of
mosques, clung to the façades of monuments or
found a corner below the city walls. They took
over the roadway, forcing passers-by to make
long detours.
Save in exceptional circumstances, the
authorities were powerless to react against these
practices. On one occasion, the Fatimid caliph
al-Hakim had a large chandelier made and want¬
ed to have it delivered to the Amr mosque. To
make room for its passage, the obstacles which
encumbered the streets had to be demolished,
some roadways dug up, and façades and balco¬
nies knocked down. The same thing happened
in 1813, when the pasha's daughter got married.
Two days before the ceremony, police officers
inspected the streets through which the wedding
procession was to pass and ordered buildings
which would hinder the procession to be pulled
down. The narrowness of the streets could only
be justified by the shade they provided but, far
* A wooden latticework screen around a window which permits the
person behind it to see into the street without being seen. Editor
from being the chief reason for it, the shade was
often no more than a happy consequence of the
liberties taken with the streets.
From alleys to avenues
Today there are still two main categories of street
in Cairoopen and covered. There are many
kinds of open streets. A zukak is a blind alley;
an atfa or khanka is an alley without an entrance
gate and without shops, leading into a busier
street, often by steps or through a gateway.
A darb or hara is a local street closed by a
gate. It contains shops but is not more than two
or three metres wide. A sikka was originally a
palm-lined way, or a village street, but later the
word was used to indicate a main street. The
terms qasaba, tarik and shari are reserved for par¬
ticularly lively, rather spacious avenues where
people assemble to discuss business and engage
in trade. The word qasaba has come to mean a
metropolis or capital.
There are also the akaba, a climbing street;
the hadar, a descending street; the djisr, a road¬
way raised above the level of floodwaters; and the
suk, a street where shops or workshops specializ¬
ing in a specific product or service are found.
Proud of their pharaonic past, Egyptians
turned their backs on the thousand years of ar¬
chitecture which preceded their opening to Eu¬
rope after Bonaparte's expedition. Until recently,
the authorities were not much interested in
preserving this urban architectural heritage. Since
the nineteenth century, Egyptian town planners
have always been inspired by a desire for moder¬
nity, and took as their models the Paris of Hauss-
mann and, later, cities of the United States.
Contrary to what happens in some Europe¬
an countries, in Cairo the use of buildings has not
changed over the centuries. Not a single palace,
madrasah or mosque has become a town hall,
ministry, embassy or theatre. Many have decayed
beyond repair, but they are beginning to attract
renewed interest, and an archaeological depart¬
ment has been entrusted with their maintenance.
Palaces and mosques may have been reprieved,
but not more modest buildings, although it is
they which constitute the spatial texture of a
street.
What is the state of this ancient urban fabric
today? A survey carried out over twenty years
ago showed that 6 per cent of the old city was 31
.á^_
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
in a satisfactory condition, 12.5 per cent in a mid¬
dling condition, 36.5 per. cent less than satisfac¬
tory, and 45 per cent in a very bad state. The
situation has not improved since then. Three-
quarters of Cairo's pre-nineteenth-century build¬
ings have now deteriorated beyond repair.
Modernizers and pasticheurs
There are two schools of thought on how to
remedy this situation. The majority, anxious to
rationalize and modernize the old city, favours
the systematic alignment of streets, with cross¬
roads to facilitate the circulation of traffic. A few
mosques and palaces would be preserved like
pieces of sculpture in a glass case, but within this
framework property developers would be given
a free hand.
Others, whom I would call the "historian-
pasticheurs", regard the entire 400 hectares of the
old part of the city as a conservation area. They
would respect the existing fabric, restore what can
still be restored and, undaunted by the hazards
and constraints of pastiche, reconstruct what has
disappeared.
This solution has two disadvantages. The old
city is too closely packed and could not be opened
up sufficiently. Moreover, the project would take
too long and would be too costly and nearly all
the local people of modest or average income
would be driven out.
So, what can be done to revitalize the heart
of the city, which has become run down and
overcrowded and is underequipped to meet the
many needs of its inhabitants? In my opinion, it
must be restructured and renovated in depth,
despite all the inconvenience that implies for the
people living there. The shopkeepers, certain
1 raditional trades and
crafts in Cairo's al-Muski
Street.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
craftsmen, property-owners and others who use
the area are the most likely to accept these dis¬
ruptions. Opening up this sector would reinte¬
grate it into the city centre, and there would
certainly be a big increase in the price of build¬
ing land.
However, so far as I know, no urban renew¬
al of this kind, wherever it has taken place and
under whatever kind of political régime, has yet
succeeded in keeping the poorer members of the
population in an old town centre, however regret¬
table and immoral this may appear to be.
The convivial Cairenes
Old Cairo enjoys a precious assetits public
spaces in which craftsmen can set out their stalls,
shopkeepers and itinerant traders can display
their wares, and the residents can sit down to eat
Al-Mu'izz Street. Top
right, the Qala'un
madrasah and mausoleum.
An old house near the
historic quarter ofBab
Chariya.
and enjoy life. This quality of life is a result of
the gregariousness and conviviality of the Cai¬
renes. But it also owes much to the layout of the
streets. The frequent breaks in their alignment
create spaces in between the flow of people in
street, courtyard, stairway and building. Any new
town planning project will have to preserve this
interstitial fabric, this symbiosis between open
and enclosed spaces.
Between complete order and utter chaos, a
certain degree of urban disorder must be
preserved. But how? By means of a geometrical
pattern that respects the complexity of the spa¬
tial organization. It would be grafted onto the ur¬
ban tissue which is to be preserved, making the
most of the existing space, and would harmonize
new needs with living social customs and prac¬
tices. In this way, perhaps, the old heart of Cairo
would beat again.
ALAIN BONNAMY
is an architect and film¬
maker. His film about
Cairo's City of the Dead,
Le Caire, la cité des morts
(1986), is being shown at
the Modern Art Museum at
the Pompidou Centre,
Paris, as part of an
international exhibition of
contemporary art entitled
Magiciens de la Terre (18
May-14 August, 1989). His
book on the same subject
will be published shortly. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
-
*
r 11
"T
. am**" -*
BjSffffl^ '«JUc
* m ..-r* *
-^.
-A--
7¿Lr*
- ¿Ä-
II
WÊêM
\//
«^ácavaswv
^fSiMju
ÍT
m.
*' /
.. .
t»»«*"*
1 I
»A'JV.- ».- ,'a# a>
i m
r- pi
ÛJ »'
^ -#
a* .
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Highways
in the city
BY BRIGITTE OUVRY-VIAL
E
LOUSTON is a city in trompe l'oeil. It has
at least four downtown areas organized around
ultra-modern tower blocks, and then, as far as the
eye can see, covering nearly 650 square
kilometres, stretches a medley of districts rang¬
ing from the smart to the run-down.
These districts are linked by highways rather
than streets, for the streets of Houston are un¬
like those of many other cities. Even Milam Street
or Louisiana Street, in downtown Houston, are
not quite "streets". Houston is a city of
boulevards and avenues.
Inside the Loop
Each of these long arteries defines an area of the
city, with its own way of life and speciality. Mon¬
trose, with its galleries and museums, is the arts
district. Shepherd is for everyday activitieswith
"' i 1 r
¡f': .
: .i mi! I %
1 iL iimii'iMir.
i_ ,.£& §§&, j jttifcliiiifiM^im.-
^^^^i^S
1,1 1
Ë&.
Vaff^HI HÉÉaV, '
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
BRIGITTE OUVRY-VIAL,
French journalist and
writer, is a regular
contributor to the review
Autrement. She is the
author of Femmes made in
USA, a study of
contemporary women in the
USA (Autrement
publishers, Paris, 1984) and
a biography of Henri
Michaux.
its bagel vendors, its Garden Center, its barbecue
restaurant, drive-in banks and self-service stores
even though you may have to travel several
kilometres to get from one to the other. Kirby
and especially Riveroaks are fashionable residen¬
tial districts whose peaceful acres accommodate
the magnificent Victorian, neo-classical, coloni¬
al or ultra-modern villas of Texan oil tycoons,
financiers and politicians.
The difference between districts is so
pronounced that your address is a good indica-
1 he Houston skyline
transformed by a computer-
generated laser and
firework concert given by
the French composer Jean-
Michel Jarre in 1986
during the annual arts
festival.
tor of your social and professional status. Depend¬
ing on whether you live inside or outside the ring
road known as the Loop, it is possible to make
a rough guess as to how much you might be
worth.
Chevrolets and pickups cruise along freeways
leading into the city, where they become multi-
lane thoroughfares with flower-covered embank¬
ments, link roads or bypasses. Houston's streets
are a vast maze of diversions, interchanges and
junctions through which an endless flow of traffic
is channelled in and out of the city.
Vertical addresses
These enigmatic, paradoxical streets make it
difficult to know where you are. They are enig¬
matic because they do not provide any bearings.
In downtown Houston addresses are vertical.
You go from one skyscraper to another, from Al¬
lied Bank Plaza to the Milam Building or the
Republic Bank. You find your way around not
by looking for street names, but for skyscrapers.
The roads simply provide access to glass and steel
tower blocks whose great height symbolizes the
power of the companies whose headquarters they
are. The interest of a street is defined only by the
beauty of the building that soars above it. The
street has no existence of its own.
If you happen to get lost, you will look in
vain for someone to put you right. No one seems
to be around. Mystified, the new-comer wonders
where everyone can be. As a pedestrian you feel
vaguely out of place because you are alone. Apart
from a few patient souls waiting interminably for
a bus to take them out to the suburbs, the only
animation is that provided by passing traffic. And
sometimesduring the lull between the peak
periods at the beginning and end of office
hoursthere is not even any traffic. Tower block,
avenue, car park. Tower block, avenue, car park.
And so on. Even the department stores close at
lunch-time for lack of custom.
An air-conditioned city
The American myth of the highway has carried
all before it in Houston, a city shaped by and for
the automobile. Even the splendid monoliths
created by the architects of prosperity seem to
pay tribute to the concept of a city planned for
the automobile, a vertical city built in response
to the ups and downs of the cotton and oil in¬
dustries. Houston's latest jewel, the Transco
Tower, has been planned as a freeway sculpture,
to be seen from all sides.
For Houston's white-collar workers, under¬
ground galleries replace streets as they are known
in New York, San Francisco or in the cities of
Europe. Here, because of the torrid heat, people
travel from air-conditioned houses in air-
conditioned cars to air-conditioned offices which
they reach through air-conditioned corridors
beneath the skyscrapers. Street life does exist, as
in every other city, but it goes on in the shop¬
ping galleries located in these corridors, with their
boutiques, restaurants and news-stands.
In this city, which has no real centre, the
streets seem to be works of the imagination,
traced at random. While the controlled environ¬
ment underground has taken over the life of the
city, what remains of nature is left to the streets
outside. It is a science-fiction all-steel nature,
where the plaintive cries of a marsh bird sudden¬
ly pipe out from a roadside tree, one of the few to
have been spared by the flow of concrete.
36
INSET PREVIOUS PAGE
Allen Parkway and Allen
Center, in the heart of
downtown Houston.
Heneath the city's
downtown area is a tunnel
system with shops and
restaurants, providing air-
conditioned access to major
buildings.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
m
ir~i
un-4
\ttjC-
U| \
%1pp§?Jr^¿
^Ävi^HÄ^-
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The street
of the glazed tile
factory
BY PIERRE CLEMENT
VISITORS to Beijing stroll through broad
avenues where it is hard to keep a sense of direc¬
tion. They look in vain for the animation of small
shopping streets. Following first a horizontal then
a vertical line, like the cursor in an electronic
game, they go from north to south and east to
west, unable to escape the grid pattern and the
obstacles it creates to taking short cuts. Every¬
where there are walls, the walls of the Forbid¬
den City and its surrounding districts, house walls
and the screen walls inside gateways.*
The modern town planner has shattered this
geometrical vdream. Even broader avenues have
been traced, so many of them that Beijing is now
enclosed in five concentric circles of ring roads.
And the old horizontal city, with its closely
woven tissue of houses, its inner void of housing
compounds and their courtyards, is now being
replaced by a vast building site of tower blocks
in which it is impossible to discern any kind of
urban order.
An image of power
Beijing is above all a city that reflects power. This
was already the case in the thirteenth century un¬
der the Yuan or Mongol dynasty, which adopt¬
ed the square model of the ancient Zhou capital.
* The brick screen walls, or yingbi, located inside the entrance gate
to housing compounds, were seen as a protection against evil spirits
3 O and prevented curious passers-by from looking inside. Editor
Liulichang Street during
and after reconstruction
work.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
It remained so under the Ming (fourteenth-
seventeenth century), who rebuilt the city in the
fifteenth century when they brought back their
capital from Nanjing (Nanking) in the south to
Beijing.
The town planners of northern China always
confined trading activities to a specific area in
order to keep better control of the flow of people,
and goods. Nowadays, in the Beijing inherited
from the Qing dynasty (seventeenth-twentieth
century), these areas of free circulation revolve
around the Forbidden City, in the East and West
Markets, or lie outside the inner city (also known
as the Tatar City) at the southern end of Tianan¬
men Square, beyond Qianmenthe southern
road leading to Dashalan Street, a masterpiece of
late nineteenth-century commercial architecture.
Liulichang Street, to the west, was a testimo¬
ny to artistic life under the Qing dynasty in the
eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, until recent¬
ly when it became the site of a reconstruction
operation that is original to say the least.
Liulichangjie, or the street of the glazed tile
factory, derives its name from an Imperial facto¬
ry established there at the beginning of the Ming
dynasty to provide the many materialsbricks,
glazed tiles, roof and window decorations-
required to build the Imperial palace when the
capital was transferred to Beijing. This establish¬
ment was demolished at the end of the Qing dy¬
nasty, but in the meantime the district had
attracted booksellers, printers, vendors of paper,
brushes, ink, ink stones, seals and other equip¬
ment used by scholars, sellers of calligraphies and
paintings, bookbinders and antique dealers. The
district became a meeting-place for artists, scho¬
lars and foreigners, who crowded into its almost
200 shops.
A showpiece for tourists
Like the rest of traditional Beijing, the district
around Liulichang Street comprised low,
wooden-framed houses with grey brick walls and
tiled roofs of the same colour, opening onto in¬
ner courtyards surrounded by carved panelling.
Of course, the district had become very dilapi¬
dated, but rather than renovate the old frame¬
work, it was decided to raze the old buildings and
reconstitute them using modern materials and
traditional techniques, combining a desire for the
new with a concern for archaeology.
The project, which was carried out jointly by
Beijing Municipal Council, which owned the
land, and the Ministry of Culture, got under way
in 1978. The first phase of the operations provid¬
ed for the reconstruction of fifty-four art and an-
PIERRE CLÉMENT,
French ethnologist, is a
staff member of the French
Institute of Architecture
and a teacher at the Paris-
Belleville School of
Architecture. The author of
Architecture du paysage en
Extrême-Orient ("The
Architecture of the
Landscape in the Far East",
1987), he has translated into
French a study of the
Chinese house by Liu
Dunzhen. He has organized
an exhibition on Beijing at
the French Institute of
Architecture, and is
currently preparing another
on Shanghai.
tique shops. Only one house built in 1920 and
one nineteenth-century house with a courtyard
located behind a large calligraphy shop, were
spared by the demolishers.
Continuity of style
The West has learned to respect old stone,
original materials and authenticity of style. In the
Far East, however, whether in Japan, Korea or
China, prestigious buildings made of perishable
materials have always been periodically recon¬
structed. While new materials were used, old tech¬
niques continued to be practised, and the original
forms were reproduced. The permanence of the
model took precedence over the use of authen¬
tic materials.
In the case of Liulichang Street, the architects
used the results of historical research to help them
design buildings of the late Qing dynasty. They
made extensive use of concrete for pillars, beams
and other structural elements, but the concrete
was concealed by a rich decoration of bricks, tiles,
carved wood, paintings, lacquerwork and gilding.
All the specialists in the region were mobilized
to help with the project. The reconstitution is
painstaking and ornate, and if the decoration is
still rather garish, the brightness of the fresh paint
will be mellowed by the patina of time. This
first phase of the project cost some twenty mil¬
lion yuan, a sum whose magnitude shows the im¬
portance attached to the operation by the Chinese
authorities.
The fifty-four shops of the new Liulichang
Street, renamed the Street of Culture, today ply
their trade in souvenirs, crafts, antiques, antiquar¬
ian books, paper, brushes and paintings. The
reconstitution applied only to the outer skin of
the district, which was removed by the bulldoz¬
ers. The depth, substance and authenticity of the
area and the conditions under which it developed,
were all ignored. Bruised and battered, the street
is losing the memory of its past, and its former
spirit has gone. This is why Shen Zhanxiang, a
Chinese town planner, has suggested that the ex¬
periment should be regarded as a historical mis¬
take never to be repeated.
Will his warning be heeded? In the meantime
similar projects have been started in other cities.
A street in Xi'an has been "recreated" in the style
of the T'ang emperors (seventh-tenth century).
Similar reconstructions in the old style have also
been effected in Kaifeng and Tianjin. The move¬
ment is spreading elsewhere. In Paris, at the con¬
fluence of the Seine and the Marne, the idea of
building a Chinese city on similar lines is already
being aired.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
i -.Im '»
w
i
,1
» Vi
II
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
Under the roofs
of Paris
sOME Paris streets, such as Rue du Renard (Fox
Street) and Rue du Chat-qui-Pêche (Street of the
Fishing Cat), have names that recall the once-
famous signs that used to hang in them. Others
have rural names, like the Rue du Chemin-Vert
(Green Lane) which at one time meandered be¬
tween vegetable or the Rue des Belles-
Feuilles (Fairleaf Street) of which glimpses could
be had over the wall surrounding an old property.
Yet others evoke crafts and trades, such as the
Rue de la Lingerie (Linen-Drapers Street) and the
Rue du Rouet (Spinning-Wheel Street), or life in
the old days: people crossed the Seine on the fer¬
ry from the end of the Rue du Bac (Ferry Street);
stocks of paving-stones were piled up in the Place
des Grès (Stone Square); a crucifix stood at the
end of the Rue de la Croix-Nivert (Street of the
Cross of Nivert), at the Croix Rouge (Red Cross)
crossroads and in the Rue Croix-des-Petits-
Champs (Street of the Cross of Littlefields).
Many Paris streets are named after prominent
personalities. Landowners often gave their names
to streets that crossed their land. Rue Beaufils and
Rue Baudelique are typical examples. Local
authorities paid tribute to those who had ren¬
dered service to the community by naming streets
after them. The former commune of Vaugirard,
for example, named Rue Fondary after one of its
mayors. A person's fame was often sufficient rea¬
son for a street to be named after him. Three ar¬
chitects are thus honoured in Rue
Théodore-Ballu, Rue Auguste-Perret and Rue
Mallet-Stevens.
The latter, a little street in the 16th Arron¬
dissement designed by the great French architect
Robert Mallet-Stevens, is very modern in style.
Completed in 1927, it consists of five villas and
a caretaker's house. Today the existence of this
architectural masterpiece is threatened by the en¬
croachments of speculators.
The Rue de Rivoli is another of the many ar¬
chitectural shrines which give Paris its characteris¬
tic appearance. From the Louvre to the Place de
la Concorde, the street is striking in its unifor¬
mity and classical restraint, with over 300 iden¬
tical arcades pinpointed at night by individual
hanging lights. The regularity of these freestone
façades gives an impersonal, majestic effect which
was deliberately sought by the architects Pierre
François Léonard Fontaine (1762-1853) and
Charles Percier (1764-1838) during the redevelop¬
ment of the Tuileries district at the end of the
eighteenth century.
BY ANNE-MARIE
CHATELET
A typical Paris roofscape.
Inset, the city as shown in
an early 17th-century
engraving.
ANNE-MARIE
CHATELET,
French architect, is
currently completing a
doctoral thesis on Parisian
primary schools from 1870
to 1914. In 1985 she
organized an exhibition (for
which she also wrote the
catalogue) on the same
theme. She is a regular
contributor to the Bulletin
of the French Institute of
Architecture, for which she
has planned two issues: on
housing in Paris in the
early 1980s (1985) and on
the city of Lisbon (1988).
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
HB
44£S
r
** k^f i
.W^rsE.
EBB
» *1 Í J*~
i~ V
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
' Tí Lit . J
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
í rint depicting demolition
work carried out between
1852 and 1855 before the
construction ofRue des
Ecoles, Paris.
A comer of old Paris, Rue
Frédéric Sauton. In
background, one of the
spires of Notre-Dame
cathedral.
Left, Rue Mallet-Stevens,
in the 16th
Arrondissement of Paris,
was designed by the French
architect for whom it is
named. Far left, the
classical lines ofRue de
Rivoli.
During the nineteenth century, Rambuteau
and Haussmann, who were successively Prefects
of the Seine Departement from 1833 to 1870, gave
Paris the appearance that it has today. They
rebuilt the network of main thoroughfares, car¬
rying through, in fifty years, the most ambitious
road-plahning project in the history of the capital.
A number of routes were opened up to the
outskirts of the city in areas then still little deve¬
loped. New precincts sprang up, like the Europe
district planned in 1826 and then gradually built
up on the site of the old Tivoli gardens. Six roads,
each named after a capital citythe Rues de Con¬
stantinople, de Madrid, de Vienne, de Londres,
de Berlin (now de Liège) and de Leningrad radi¬
ate from the Place de l'Europe, which bridges the
maze of railway lines that run into Saint-Lazare
station. The profile of their opulent apartment
blocks, faced in freestone, conforms to a planning
regulation that links the height of a building to
the width of the street. This resulted in the typi¬
cally Parisian curb roofs with grey-blue slates,
since the steepness of the roof precluded the use
of tiles. The same regulation led to the recessing
of the fifth floor, with an inevitable balcony at
the level of the cornice, and gave rise to a uni¬
form rhythm in which the vertical punctuation
of the windows contrasts with the seemingly in¬
finite cornice line, continued from building to
building.
Some of the new thoroughfares cut through
the heart of densely populated areas and involved
considerable demolition. This, however, was
necessary to improve communications, security
and public health, as well as to embellish the cap¬
ital. Along the great north/south axis, constitut¬
ed by the Boulevard de Sebastopol and the
Boulevard Saint-Michel, the same kind of
nineteenth-century-style buildings are to be
found. These roads, however, are but gashes in
the living urban flesh behind. A stroll round the
labyrinth of narrow streets behind the Place
Saint-Michel, where the Rues de la Harpe, de la
Huchette and du Chat-qui-Pêche intertwine,
reveals buildings of another age, with bulging
walls, narrow façades and windows that on each
storey are smaller than on the one below.
What should we look for in this maze of
streets? The ones reputed to be the longest or the
widest? Those that have survived the hand of
Haussmann or those that bear witness to his
work? Those whose rich outlines were the work
of a single architect or those that offer a mosaic
of styles? Those whose cobbles we walk with
familiar tread or those to which we go with the
reverent step of pilgrims?
The poet Raymond Queneau gives an answer
in these lines:
There are streets that are tubes
There are streets that are arches
There are boulevards dowdy
And others all crowdy
With cars, vans and coaches
There are squares dodecagonal
Some simply infernal
There are sausage-shaped avenues
Where the beetles are ravenous
Canals quite Venetian
And islands West Frisian
Bridges and alleys and dead-ends and quays
Highways and courtyards and footpaths, all
these
For a multiple, motley mosaic of modes
You cannot beat Paris's system of roads...
*Courir les Rues, by Raymond Queneau. Published by Gallimard,
Paris, 1967. 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
REFLECTIONS
'Reflections' is a new Unesco Courier feature. It is intended to stimulate thinking on a topic unrelated
to the main theme of the current issue and will in some cases, as here, enrich our coverage of a
theme treated in a previous issue.
Families of the world
BY HELENE TREMBLAY
In 1983, Hélène Tremblay, of Canada, set out to
investigate and record the daily life of at least one
representative family in every country of the world,
and to publish the results of her enquiries in a
series of books.*
After carrying out research into the social and
economic conditions in each country, Ms. Tremblay
consults academics and social workers who help her
select a family with which to live. She then takes
part in the family's daily life, observing and
listening to its members as they talk about their
problems and aspirations. In the resulting book she
describes a typical day in the family's life. In the
article below Ms. Tremblay presents some reflections
inspired by her experiences on her 'Families of the
World' project.
from left to right:
Mongolia,
Malaysia,
Saint Lucia,
Guatemala,
Samoa,
Malta,
Papua New Guinea,
Canada.
X AMILY life is the one social experience that is
common to all humankind, and sharing this
experience among other families all over the world
is the most powerful force for international
understanding among "ordinary" people that I have
ever witnessed.
There is a particularly urgent need to strengthen
international communication about the family today
when it is feeling the impact of the hurricane of
change that is sweeping through the world.
Everywhere I have found that families are
wondering where the forces of change are taking
them and whether these forces will bring them
better lives.
In the Americas, the Caribbean, East and
Southeast Asia and the Pacific, I have seen some of
the harsh realities millions of families on our planet
face every day. I have accompanied women and
children on the long daily trek to fetch drinking
water which is not always safe. I have lived with
peasant families who were unable to keep up the
anymore." And everywhere grandmothers say with
regret, "Things are not as they used to be."
Young people are impatient to master every
piece of information that comes their way. The old
feel sad and powerless when they see the young turn
their backs on traditional culture. In between these
two groups there is a generation of people in their
late thirties and early forties who act as a buffer and
try to ensure that young and old live happily side
by side and communicate with each other.
Satisfying both groups, however, does not
demand the same responses. The old want the
pattern of their daily lives to be unchanged. They
want to feel that their beliefs are shared. To keep
them happy new ideas must often be filtered and
their impact softened. Meanwhile, the deepest
concern of the world's parents is how to satisfy the
young.
In the developing countries these forces are far
more manifest than in the industrial countries, but
families have less resources to cope with them. To
46
payments on the debt they owed to the local
middleman, and wondered when they would have
to take the road to the city slum. At the other end
of that road I have shared the pitiful but generous
shelter of proud people reduced to the ultimate loss
of dignity caused by rampant disease and chronic
unemployment.
When I visit a country I ask the people I meet
to tell me about their beliefs and traditions.
Invariably someone exclaims, "Oh, grandmother
used to do this or think that, but it is not so
satisfy the aspirations of today's young people, the
buffer generation must find more and more cash.
The first priority, I have found everywhere, is
education, including school clothes, equipment and
transport. Young people are also pushing their
parents out of the subsistence economy in a process
which may start in an apparently trivial way, with
a desire for jeans and T-shirts with a slogan, the
universal uniform of youth. Young people are also
hungry for the new universal music and for the
foreign products that transnational advertising,
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
television and video offer as daily temptations. They
become dissatisfied with the stillness of village life
and the attraction of the city starts to break the spell
of the extended community.
In this way such families are being propelled into
a materialistic society. As they leave the tranquil
shore for the turbulence of a fast-moving river, they
wonder whether they will be carried along to crash¬
ing waterfalls or to calm waters. Neither sociolo¬
gists nor economists seem able to answer this
question of universal concern.
For millions of people living in societies that
have known a regular, predictable, unchanging way
of life for centuries, today is a time of tumult. They
feel with alarm that their lives are spiralling out of
the control of their community and coming under
the influence of a new, international "paramount
chief", who is motivated by cash and materialism
rather than by spirit and soul.
Meanwhile, as societies and individuals try to
understand what is happening, the daily round con¬
tinues. Children must be fed, roofs must be repaired
before the rainy season, and water must be fetched.
Gardens and fields must be planted, weeded and har¬
vested, rents paid, debts met. And whatever may
be happening to the old cultures and values, every
man and woman who wakes up to start a new day
shares with unknown millions elsewhere in the
world the same desire to live through it in dignity
and faith. How much stronger they would feel in
face of the new doubts, if they knew they shared
this desire!
In every home I have found that in almost every
field of change, from family planning to health, from
new divisions of labour in the home to new
economic enterprise in the community, women are
taking the initiative. Everywhere I have been amazed
by the work of women's organizations in unleashing
the full potential of women within the family.
As family size is getting smaller and parents are
realizing that their financial investment in secondary
education should be given to the most eager of their
children, more and more girls have an opportunity
to study. The women argue, rightly, that whereas
men prefer the social and economic challenge of
urban life, many educated women return to their
communities as nurses, social workers and educators.
The example of these educated women devoting
their lives to the improvement of their people's
For at a time when the people of the world are
coming to know that they share the planet with mil¬
lions of others, I find that most people feel lonely,
thinking that their own worries are the worst.
I take to each family I visit pictures of the fa¬
milies whose lives I have shared in other countries
and continents. Wherever I go I am struck by peo¬
ple's eagerness to know how others live. They are
always interested to see the similarities between their
dwellings and those of others, and to discover how
people in different economic and geographical cir¬
cumstances find different ways of solving the
problems of everyday life and realizing the same
universal aspirations.
conditions is giving other women the confidence to
determine their own destinies and those of their
families.
Everywhere relationships within the family are
being exposed to new stresses and tensions by
international communications, especially messages
such as the Western concept of "love" which reach
young people by TV and video. In Southeast Asia
and the Pacific most parents I visited had been
brought together in arranged marriages, but they
all said that they would let their children choose
their partners. The new relationship between these
partners and their families will change the
individuals involved and their society.
Where these changes are concerned, there are
striking contrasts between rural and urban families.
Rural families cannot live in isolation from the
community and from those members of the
extended family who live within reach. Only
through mutual support, help and generosity can
they cope with the forces of nature, poverty, and
lack of understanding from the urban communities
which they feed.
In the cities, however, behaviour patterns which
were once simply inherited from other members of
the extended family are now increasingly being
modelled on those of people from completely
different backgrounds and are thus much more
unpredictable. Limited space and the proximity of
neighbours who are not part of the clan also incite
urban families to keep to themselves, lead people
to behave aggressively in defence of their interests,
and often end in the severance of family ties and
a descent into loneliness. The urban individual and
the rural family vie with each other in the national
community, with governments increasingly called
on to play a mediating role.
In this new and unstable situation, many would
prefer the pace of change to slow down. Not only
family specialists but also the United Nations system
must help nations and families to understand the
forces of change. Surely families beset with doubts
in the face of change would gain insight and courage
if they knew that the same problems are faced by
all those with whom they share the planet.
"The first volume, which describes 46 families in 35
countries of the Americas and the Caribbean, has already
been published in the United States, Canada and France.
The second volume, covering 34 families with whom
Helene Tremblay has lived in 25 countries of East and
Southeast Asia and the Pacific, will be published in 1990. 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND SOCIETY
International co-operation in space
BY DAVID SPURGEON
Canadian scientific journalist based in Ottawa
I WENTY years ago, US astronaut Neil
Armstrong became the first human to
set foot on the Moon. His arrival there
was heralded in the West as the win¬
ning of what was popularly called "the
space race".
In those early days of the space age
we used to hear a lot about the "space
race". Competition between the two
giant space-faring nations, the Soviet
Union and the United States, was
the order of the day. Today that is
changing. The new watchword is co¬
operation. Competition certainly still
exists between the great space powers,
but international co-operation is now
the vogue.
Today, instead of talking about rac¬
ing back to the Moon or on to Mars,
the Soviets and the Americans are at
least thinking about the possibility of
going there together.
The joint statement after the Soviet-
US Summit in 1 988 noted that the two
countries "agreed to expand exchanges
of space science data and of scientists...
They noted scientific missions to the
Moon and Mars as areas' of possible
bilateral and international co¬
operation".
Other kinds of collaboration in
space are already well underway. The
recent ill-fated Phobos probes of the
Soviet Union, destined for the moons
of Mars, for example, were Soviet-built
and launched, but they carried instru¬
ments and employed scientists from
Austria, Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, the
Federal Republic of Germany, the Ger¬
man Democratic Republic, Finland,
France, Hungary, Ireland, Poland, Swit¬
zerland and Sweden. And the USA
provided radio tracking. Similarly, cos¬
monauts from twelve countries (Bulgar¬
ia, Cuba, Czechoslovakia, France, the
German Democratic Republic, Hungary,
India, Mongolia, Poland, Romania, Syria,
and Viet Nam) have flown on Soviet
spacecraft.
The major current US manned
space prioritythe Space Station
48 Freedomis a co-operative venture be
tween that country and Canada, Europe
and Japan. The Space Station will pro¬
vide a permanent manned research
laboratory and spacecraft servicing and
repair facility in space. It will also func¬
tion as a transportation depot from
which spacecraft can depart to distant
parts of the solar system.
Although the United States is the
project director and senior partner, the
US National Aeronautics and Space Ad¬
ministration (NASA) calls the Space Sta¬
tion a "genuine partnership" which
involves "friends with common in¬
terests". The Europeans and Japanese
are each providing a habitable module,
while Canada is building a Mobile Ser¬
vicing System.
Other space-faring nations are co¬
operating not only with the Big Two,
but among themselves. Canada has
partnerships with France, the Federal
Republic of Germany, Japan, Sweden,
the United Kingdom and the USSR.
Japan has co-operated with the USA in
projects other than the Space Station,
and with the European Space Agency,
and intends to conduct research joint¬
ly with Malaysia and Thailand using data
from Japan's Marine Observation Satel¬
lite, MOS-1.
Countries that have conducted
space activities now include, besides
those mentioned above, the Arab
States, Australia, Brazil, China, India and
Indonesia. Most of these, too, have
been collaborative ventures.
The USSR has been particularly ac¬
tive in trying to promote international
space agencies. In June 1988, for the
third year in succession, Soviet delegates
at the United Nations sponsored the
idea of a World Space Organization.
Connected with the United Nations, the
WSO would concentrate its efforts on
peaceful space exploration and preven¬
tion of extension of the arms race to
space. It would develop such projects
as the use of space platforms to moni¬
tor global change and, later, manned
interplanetary missions.
The most comprehensive collabora
tive space activity of all will be the
celebration in 1992 of International
Space Year (ISY). In April 1988, NASA
hosted a meeting at the University of
New Hampshire to which it invited
representatives of twenty-three space
agencies around the world. The agen¬
cies formed an organizationSpace
Agency Forum for the International
Space Year (SAFISY)to meet regular¬
ly to co-ordinate ISY activities, particu¬
larly those associated with studying the
Earth. Such activitiesthe use of space
observations and complementary
ground-based studies to better under¬
stand our planetwill be a feature of
the ISY.
One of these activities will be an ef¬
fort to search among existing data on
the Earth to try to determine whether
there are unequivocal signs that human
activity has been responsible for warm¬
ing of our planet Earth. A US project
planned to study another global change
is the Upper Atmospheric Research
Satellite, scheduled for launch in 1 991 .
It will measure processes in the upper
atmosphere that control the loss of
ozone.
Topex/Poseidon, a joint US-French
project to measure with great accura¬
cy the depth of the oceans, is scheduled
for launch in 1 992. This will help scien¬
tists learn more about global ocean cir¬
culation. It is to be coupled with
Scatterometer, a device to be flown on
a Japanese satellite in the mid-1990s,
which will measure wind stress on the
ocean surface. Together, Topex/
Poseidon and Scatterometer will help us
understand the coupling between the
oceans and the atmosphere.
Finally, to study how the at¬
mosphere and the Earth interact as an
integrated system, a platform will be
placed in polar orbit by the US Space
Station, carrying a comprehensive set
of equipment called the Earth Observ¬
ing System. This will be complement¬
ed by another platform provided by the
European Space Agency and still
another from the Japanese.
Platforms in polar orbit can see the
entire Earth rotating under them. In
time, geostationary platforms (which re¬
main stationary in orbit with respect to
a position on Earth) will be added to fo¬
cus instruments on a single region on
the Earth's surface. Together, they will
provide comprehensive, long-term
measurements of such factors as the
Earth's vegetation, cloud and snow
cover, ocean currents, and even the
production of the simple plants
(phytoplankton) that are the food
source of marine animal life.
All these studies will be com¬
plemented by satellite and ground-
based studies from around the world
particularly through the International
Geosphere-Biosphere Programme of
the International Council of Scientific
Unions (ICSU).
THE SOVIET SPACE
PROGRAMME
In recent years, the Soviet space
programme has been far more active
than the US programme. The American
newsmagazine Time said in its cover
story on 5 October 1987: "In sheer
numbers of launches per year, the
Soviets inched past the US in 1 967, 66
to 58, and have stayed in front since."
Since then, Soviet cosmonauts have
set the long-term space flight record,
two of themVladimir Titov and Musa
Manrovstaying there for a full year.
And in 1988, along with the first, un¬
manned, launching of their Buran re¬
usable spaceship, the Soviets conducted
89 other space missionscompared to
26 by the rest of the world combined.
Major successes were also scored
with Soviet unmanned missions to Ve¬
nus and Comet Halley: the Vega Project
had broad international participation-
six socialist and three market-economy
countries and several international
scientific organizations. The Vega
probes soft-landed on Venus to deter¬
mine the composition of the surface,
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
and balloon probes radioed back data
on the planet's atmosphere.
Later, the Vegas entered the enve¬
lope of Halley's comet to obtain the first
large-scale ¡mages of the comet's
nucleus, from a distance of 8,000-9,000
kilometres. Later again, the West Euro¬
pean spacecraft Giotto, and two
Japanese spacecraft, Suisei and
Sakigake, joined in, with Giotto pass¬
ing even closer to the nucleus520 to
550 kilometres from it.
US MISSIONS
TO VENUS AND JUPITER
After the Space Shuttle Challenger
disaster in January 1986, the US
programme began to pick up momen¬
tum again. Its first interplanetary probe
in a decade was launched on 4 May
1 989. That spacecraft, Magellan, is due
to visit Venus to map the surface, in¬
cluding its land forms and geological
features, using radar. Its findings are ex¬
pected to help answer fundamental
questions about the origin and evolu¬
tion of the planet, which can then be
compared with that of Earth.
Also this year, the Galileo mission
is scheduled to set off on a six-year
voyage, never before attempted, to
Jupiter and its satellites. It will parachute
a probe that will make measurements
Artist's impression of Space
Station Freedom, an
international manned space
complex scheduled to be
placed in orbit in the
mid-1990s. A Space Shuttle
can be seen preparing to
dock.
Soviet Energiva rocket and
Buran Space Shuttle on the
launching pad.
^H I
P^>. aljF^5 IT*
r \
car ^
a*
of the chemical composition of Jupiter's
atmosphere and of those of its satellites.
Galileo will also make measurements of
the Jovian magnetosphere.
The US programme has other
major scientific missions scheduled for
the near future. These include two of
what are known as the Great Observa¬
tories: the Hubble Space Telescope and
the Gamma Ray Observatory. Both are
scheduled for launch early in 1990.
The Hubble telescope will carry
both an optical telescope and ultravio¬
let instruments. It will investigate the na¬
ture of processes occurring in stars and
galaxies, study the history and evolution
of the universe, and confirm the univer¬
sality of physical laws. The Gamma Ray
Observatory will study objects that emit
gamma rays and investigate such
phenomena as neutron stars and black
holes.
Also scheduled for 1990 launch by
the USA are the Cosmic Background Ex¬
plorer and the Roentgen Satellite. The
Cosmic Background Explorer is designed
to measure the remnants of cosmic
microwave radiation believed to date
from the explosive event (the Big Bang)
that some theorists say created the
universe, and will thus have implications
for our understanding of its origin and
fate. The Roentgen Satellite will study
X-ray emission from stars and galaxies.
OBJECTIVE MARS
TheJirst part of a project named Ves¬
ta, which the Soviet Union, France and
the European Space Agency are jointly
planning, is also tentatively scheduled
for the beginning of the 1 990s. Vesta,
a follow-up of Vega, will make a
detailed study of several asteroids and
a comet. Which ones will depend on the
time of launch.
By far the biggest goal for the
Soviets is Mars, first for unmanned ex¬
ploration, and later for manned flight.
One version of such a mission has been
described by Novosti Press Agency's
scientific analyst, Oleg Borisov.
The first stage is planned for
1994-1996, using the rocket Energiva
to loft sophisticated equipment to the
surface, including rovers, drilling units
and balloons for atmospheric studies.
The next mission would come be¬
tween 2000 and 2005, with a lander
bringing back samples of Martian soil
for analysis. If the first two phases were
successful, the first manned flight would
take place between 2005 and 2010.
Borisov reported: "Soviet research¬
ers, pioneers of this mission, call for an
international effort, for participation of
some European countries and the US".
At least one Soviet writer, Vladis¬
lav Shevchenko, a physicist and
mathematician, has repeatedly publi¬
cized the advantages of a manned lu¬
nar base. Last year, through Novosti
Press Agency, he led his article with the
declaration: "It is probable that the
Soviet Union and the United States will
co-operate in exploring Mars and the
Moon".
Last April, according to the US pub¬
lication Aerospace Daily, NASA's Ad¬
ministrator, James C. Fletcher, said that
a US-USSR manned mission to the
Moon was more attractive in the near-
term than a similar voyage to Mars.
Whatever is decided about such
eventual missions, it seems certain we
can look forward to more internation¬
al co-operation in spaceand as a result
more detailed knowledge of the
universe.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50
TheMNESGO
Ä^GOURIER
HIHI
Published monthly in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31. rue François Bonvin, 75015 Pans, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta, Majda Dalai
Public relations: Claudie Duhamel (Tel :45.68.45.86)
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeois
NON -HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Shri Krishna Kumar Singh (Delhi)
Tamil: M Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kessler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitn Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Seham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bengali: Ahmed Hedayet (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88), Assistant: Marie-
Noëlle Branet (45.68.45 89), Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse
Hardy (45.68.45.65), Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Mohamed Salah El Din,
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: Liliane Tasch (45.68.45 66), Cultural projects:
Ricardo Zamora-Perez (Tel. 45.68.45.80),
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval
ADVERTISING
Publicat: 17, Boulevard Poissonnière, 75002 Paris.
Tel.: 40.26.51.26
Sales director: Benoît Rosier
Advertising director: Daniele Michelet
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45 68.45.65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier".
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor
Signed articles reprinted must bear autnor's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unso icited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not recessarly represent the opinions of Unesco or those o*
the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations The Unesco Courier is
produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Michigan 48100, U S.A., (3) N.C R Microcard Edition. Indian
Head. Inc , 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York, US A ¡ (4) Bell and
Howell Co.. Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed m France) - DEPOT LEGAL : CI - AOÛT 1989
Photocomposition. The Unesco Courier
Photog ravu re- ¡m pression :
Maury Imprimeur S.A , Z.I. route d'Etampes.
4S330 Malesherbes
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
ALBANIA. "Ndermarrja e perpjes se librif. Tirana. ARGENTINA. Librería el
Correo de la Unesco - EDILYR, SRL. Tucumán 1685. 1050 Buenos Aires.
AUSTRALIA. Books only:: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33.
Brookvale 2100, NSW: Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O.
Box 33, Brookvale 2100. NSW. Sub-agents: United Nations Association of
Australia. Victorian Division, 328 Flinders Street. Melbourne 3000 Hunter
Publications, 58a G-pps St., Collingwood. Victoria 3066. AUSTRIA. Gerold
and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools Interna¬
tional, Arab Regional Office. P.O. Box 726. Bahrain; The Arabian Agencies
and Distributing Co.. Al Mutanabi St., PO Box 156. Manama BANGLADESH
Karim International, GPO Box No: 2141. 64/1 Manipuri Para, Tejgaon,
Farmgate. Dhaka. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64. Bridgetown BELGIUM. Jean de Lannoy. 202
Ave. du Roi. 1 060 Brussels. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre. PO Box 91
Gaborone. BRAZIL. Fundaçâo Getúlio Vargas. Serviço del Publicaçoes,
caixa postal 9.042-ZC-05 Praia de Botafogo 188, Rio de Janeiro (RJ) 2000;
Books only: Imagem Latinoamericana. Av. Paulista 750. 1 andar, caixa postal
30455, Sao Paulo CEP 01051. BULGARIA. Hemus, Kantora Literatura,
boulevard Rousky 6. Sofia. BURMA. Trade Corporation no. (9). 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd.. 1294
Algoma Road. Ottawa. Ontario K1 B 3W8. {Stores- 61 Sparks Street, Ottawa,
21 1 Yonge St., Toronto. Sales office: 7575 Trans Canada Hwy. Ste. 305, St.
Laurent. Quebec H4T 1V6. CAMEROON. Cameroon Book Centre, PO Box
123. Limbe. Commission Nationale. BP 1600. Yaounde. CHILE. Editorial
Universitaria SA.. Departamento de Importaciones. M. Luisa Santander
0447, casilla 10220. Santiago; Editorial 'Andrés Bello'. Av: R. Lyon 946,
Casillo 4256, Santiago de Chile: Dipublic, Antonio Varas 671 , 2o piso, casilla
14364, Correo 21, Santiago. CHINA. China National Publications Import and
Export Corporation. P.O. Box 88. Beijing. COLOMBIA. Instituto Colombiano
de Cultura (Colcuitura). Carrera 3A. n° 1 8 / 24, Bogota; Books only: Librería
Buchholz Galena. Calle 59, No: 13-13. Bogota. CYPRUS. MAM'. Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avene. PO Box 1 722. Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1; For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. -Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava; PNS-UED, Jmdrisska 14, praha 1;
Slovart. Gottwaldovo Nam 6. 805 32 Bratislava. DEM. REP. OF YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation. PO Box 4227. Aden. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-
OG. Tidsskriftservice. 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1 970 Kobenhavn K.
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Librería Blasco. Avenida Bolivar, No; 402. esq
Hermanos Dehgne. Santo Domingo. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). Un¬
esco Publications Centre. No. 1 Talaat Harb St., Cairo. ETHIOPIA. Ethiopian
National Agency for Unesco. PO Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateemmen Kirjakauppa. P. O. Box 128. SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalainen
Kirjakauppa Oy. Koivuvaarankuja 2 01 640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans. Periodicals only: Unesco CPD /
V-1 . rue MiolliS. 7501 5 Pans. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchex-
port. Postfach 140, Leninstrasse 16. 7010, Leipzig. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum. Deutscher Unesco-Kurier
Vertrieb. Basaltstrasse 57. D5300 Bonn 3: UNO-Verlag, Simrockstrasse 23,
D-5300 Bonn 1; S. Karger GmbH. Verlag Angerhofstrasse 9. Postfach 2
D-8034 Germering / München. For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach
800830. 7000 Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Books only: Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd.. PO Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., PO 7869, Accra;
The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra: The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, PO Box 1 , Legon. Periodicals only:
Fides Entreprises. P.O. Box 14129. Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom. GREECE. Eleftheroudakis SA. International Bookstore, 4 Nikis
Street, Athens; John Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers. P.O.
Box 10073, 541 10 Thessaloniki. Greek National Commission for unesco, 3
Akadimias Street, Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co., 13-15 Lock
Road, Kowloon: Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., Tokwawan, Kowloon; Hong
Kong Government Information Services, Publication Section, Hong Kong;
Periodicals only Beaconsfieid House 6th floor, Queen's Road Central, Victor¬
ia. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B. 149-H-1389, Budapest 62.
ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson and Co., H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykiavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate. Bombay 400038:
17 Chitaranjan Ave.. Calcutta 13: 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2:
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP): 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd.,
Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-agents:
Oxford Book and Stationen/ Co., 1 7 Park St., Calcutta 70016: Scmdia House,
New Delhi 11 0001. INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers. 29.
J1, Oto Iskandardmata ill. Jakarta: Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam Ratuiangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, 1 188 Englab
Ave.. Rostam Give Building. P.O. Box 11365-4498, Teheran 13158.
IRELAND. Periodicals only: The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., PO Box
43A. Walkmstown, Dublin 1 2; Books only: TDC Publishers. 1 1 North Frederick .
Street. Dublin 7. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions, Inc.. Co Steimatzky Ltd.,
P.O. Box 628. Tel Aviv: A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Rd.,
Tel Aviv 61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionana Sansoni, S p. A.), Via
Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence: via Bartolini 29, 201 55
Milan; FAO Bookshop, via délie Terme di Caracalla, 001 00 Rome. JAMAICA.
University of the West Indies Bookshop. Mona. Kingston 7. JAPAN. Eastern
Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku. Tokyo 113. JORDAN
Jordan Distribution Agency, PO Box 375, Amman. Periodicals only: Jordan
Book Cerjtre Co. Ltd., PO Box 301 . Al Jubeiha, Amman. KENYA. East African
Publishing House. PO 30571, Nairobi: Africa Book Sen/ices Ltd, Quran
House, Mangano Street, PO Box 45245. Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco. P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd. POB 2942. Kuwait: Periodicals only: Farafalla Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541 , Kuwait. LEBANON. Librairie Antoine A. Naufal
et Frères, BP 656, Beirut. LESOTHO Mazenod Book Centre, PO Mazenod,
Maseru. LIBERIA National Bookstore. Mechlin and Carey Streets. PO Box
590, Monrovia; Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., PO Box 286, Monrovia.-
LUXEMBOURG. Books only: Librairie Paul Brück, 22. Grande-Rue, Luxem¬
bourg; Periodical: Messageries Paul Kraus. BP 1022, Luxembourg. MALAWI
Malawi Book Service, Head Office, PO Box 30044, Chichin, Blantyre 3.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St., Valletta MAURITANIA GRA.LI.-
CO.MA., 1 rue du Souk X. Avenue kennedy, Nouakchott. MAURITIUS.
Nalanda Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis MEXICO. Librería El
Correo de la Unesco, Actipán 66. Colonia del Valle, Apartado postal 61 164,
06600 Mexico DF. MONACO. British Library. 30 Bd. des Moulins. Monte
Carlo. MORROCCO. Librairie 'Aux belles images', 282 ave. MohammedV,
Rabat: Librairie des écoles. 12 ave. Hassan-ll. Casaglanca; Société cherrfien-
ne de distribution et de presse, SOCHEPRESS. angle rues de Omant et St.
Saens, BP 13683, Casablanca 05. MOZAMBIQUE. Instituto National do Livro
e do Disco (INLD). avenida 24 de Julho. 1 921 r / d 1 ° andar, Maputo. NEPAL
Sa|ha Prakashan Polchowk. Kathmandu, NETHERLANDS. Books only:
Keesing, Boeken B.V., Hogehilweg 13. Postbus 1118. 1000 BC Amsterdam.
Periodicals: Faxon Europe. P.O. Box 197. 1000 AD Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N.V., PO Box 200, Willem-
stad. Curaçao, NA. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box
14277-Kilbirnie, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife: The
University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286: The University Bookshop of Nsukka:
The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bella University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum. P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1;
Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blmdern, Oslo
3: Periodicals only: Nan/esen A/S, Litteraturt Jenesten. P.O.B. 61 25 Etterstad,
N 0602 Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency. 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3, Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for
Book Development in Asia and (he Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society. P.O. Box
8950. Karachi 29. PANAMA. Distribuidora Cultura Internacional. Apartado
7571. Zona 5. Panama. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store Inc.. 701 Rizal
Avenue, Manila. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Patac Kultury I Nauki. Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. ROMANIA.
ARTEXIM Export- Import, Piata Scienteii. no. 1, PO Box 33-16, 70005
Bucharest. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan. Olaya Mam Street. Ibrahim Bin
Sulaym Building, Riyadh. SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd.. Kingsgate
House. PO Box 1 31 . Mahé: National Bookshop, PO Box 48, Mahé. SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay College, Njala University and Sierra leone Diocesan
Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Righteous Enterprises. P.O. Box 562,
Kallang Basin Post Office, Singapore 9133. SOCIALIST PEOPLE'S LIBYAN
ARAB JAMAHIRIYA. General Establishment for Publishing, Distribution and
Advertising. Souf Al Mahmoudi St., PO Box 95?. Tripoli. SOMALIA. Modern
Book Shop and General, PO Box ùào, Mogadiscio. SPAIN. Mundi-Prensa
Libros SA, apartado 1223, Casteilô 37, Madrid 1: Ediciones über, apartado
17. Magdalena 8, Ondárroa (Vizcaya); Donaire, Ronda de Outeiro, 20,
apartado de correos 341, La Corurta: books only: Librería Casteiis. Ronda
Universidad 13 y 15, Barcelona 7; Librería de la Generalität de Catalunya,
Palan Moja, Rambla de los Estudios 118, 08 002 Barcelona. SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop, 1 00 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244,
Colombo 2. SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop. P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box 2943,
Paramaribo. SWEDEN. A/ B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Regering-
sgatan 12. Box 16356. S-103 27 Stockholm 16: For the Unesco Courier:
Svenska FN Fprbundet. Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm; For
penotf/ca/s on/y; Wennergren-Williams AB. Nordenflychtsvagen 70. S-104. 25
Stockholm; Esselte Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan26, Box62-101,20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich; Librairies
Payot in Geneva Lausanne, Basle, Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and
Zurich. SYRIA. Alpppo University Books Establishment. University of Aleppo,
Aleppo.' TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-
Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd.. 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan Panit. Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Ave.. Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road.
Bangkok; ROEAP, PO Box 1425, Bangkok 10500. TRINIDAD AND TOBA¬
GO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair. Port-of-
Spam. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi. No 469. Posta Kutusu
219. Beyoglu. Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. PO Box 71 45. Kampa¬
la. UNITED ARAB EMIRATES. Maktabat al Maktaba. PO Box 15408. Al Am,
Abu Dhabi. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, PO Box 276, London,
SW8 5DT; H.M. S.O. Bookshops in London. Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham. Bristol: Third World Publications, 151 Stratford Road. Birming¬
ham Bi 1 1RD; /or scwnf/fic maps on/y: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Rd..
London WC1X 90S. UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. Bernan-UNIPUB,
Periodicals Department, 4611 -F Assembly Drive, Lanham. MD 20706 4391.
URUGUAY. Ediciones Trecho, S.A., Maldonado 1092, Montevideo. USSR.
V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova 39. Moskva 113095.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost. Mica 30/1 1 , Zagreb; Cankaneva Zalozba, Zopitar-
leva 2. Lubljana: Nolit, Terazije 13/ VIII, 11000 Belgrade; periodicals only:
Jugosolvena Kniga, PO Box 36. YU 11001 Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd , 1 Norwich Union Centre. Harare.
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 8- 1989 OPt-89 1-471 A
PHOTO CREDITS
Cover, pages 44-45: © Bulloz, Paris. Back cover, page 37 (inset): Bill Ross © Cosmos, Paris. Page 2: © Aznar, Paris. Page 3: © Gamma,
Paris. Pages 5, 6: B. Laforet © Gamma, Paris. Page 8: Martin © Artephot, Paris. Pages 10-11: © Ullstein Bilderdienst, Berlin (West). Page
12 (above): © Staatsbibliothek Preuss. Kulturbesitz, Map Section, Berlin (West); (below left): © Roger Viollet, Paris; (below right): Leonard
© Magnum, Paris. Page 13 (left): J. Perno © Explorer, Paris; (centre): J. Windenberger © Rapho, Paris; (right): P. Roy © Explorer, Paris.
Pages 14-15: B. Barbev © Magnum, Paris. Pages 15 (inset), 16, 17: © Zarmati, Paris. Pages 18-19, 20, 21: © Anne Berty, Paris. Page 19
(right): Koene © Explorer, Paris. Page 23: Charliat © Rapho, Paris. Pages 24 (1, 3, 4), 25: © Haeringer, Paris. Page 24 (2): G. Buthaud
© Cosmos, Paris. Pages 26-27: © Russian edition of the Unesco Courier, Moscow. Page 28 (left): Ivanov © APN, Paris; (right): P. Koch
© Rapho, Paris. Page 29: © APN, Paris. Page 30: M.-C. Bordaz © Rapho, Paris. Page 32: St Pierre © Rapho, Paris. Page 33: © A. Bonnamy,
Paris. Pages 34-35: Yamashita © Rapho, Paris. Page 35 (right): Serraillier © Rapho, Paris. Page 36: H. Kokojan © Rapho, Paris. Page 37:
Wheeler © Cosmos, Paris. Pages 38-39, 39 (below right): Unesco/George Ducret. Pages 38 (below left & centre), 41: © P. Clement, Paris.
Pages 42-43: J. M. Charles © Rapho, Paris. Page 43 (inset): © Roger Viollet, Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris. Pages 44 (below left & right),
45: © David Brabyn, Chantilly. Pages 46-47: © Hélène Tremblay, Paris. Page 49 (above): © NASA, Washington, D.C.; (below): © APN Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Museums today are changing perhaps more than ever
before, and the time has come for Unesco's quarterly
magazine museum to have a facelift.
Each number presents a group of articles on a single theme
such as:
Museum architecture past and present;
Great pioneer museums founded after World War II;
Ocean, river and lake port museums;
Museums and literacy work...
Regular features include "Frankly Speaking" (an opinion
piece); a column on the return and restitution of cultural
property to its country of origin; "A city and its museums";
and a "Chronicle" prepared by the World Federation of
Friends of Museums. Plus topical articles on other themes.
The tone of museum is also changing. The magazine will
seek to provide critical analysis of the highly complex issues
facing museums today. At the same time it will strike a
lighter note in a "Quotable Quotes" section and in cartoons
and drawings reflecting the vicissitudes of the world of
museums, such as this one illustrating an account of a
museum where ill-installed ventilation equipment pumped
exhaust fumes from a garage into the exhibition hall.
WàiaZ\
' I N
For the time being, the subscription price of the new-style
museum has not been increased. Why not subscribe now?
Each issue: 48 French francs
Subscription rates (4 issues or corresponding double
issues per year): 156 French francs
UNESCO (UPP/V)
1, rue Miollis, 75015 Paris, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
