<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="083935eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
SEPTEMBER 1989 15 French francs
NESGO
ÏÏÏÏÏÏ COURIER
GREAT EPICS
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters
I
I
tëggl
Hi -aHjaH
In the 15th and 16th
centuries, the great
Portuguese voyages of
discovery marked the start
of a far-reaching process of
dialogue between
continents and civilizations.
In the words of historian
Luis Filipe Barreto, "The
Portuguese practised the
intermingling of cultures
and peoples... purveyed
commodities and
syncretized religions and
customs. ... The Portuguese
discoveries thus made a
fundamental contribution
to the transition from an
age of tightly-knit societies
to a wider, more open
world." (See the Unesco
Courier, April 1989.) Right,
a 17th-century Persian
miniature depicting a
Portuguese.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
CONTENTS
4
Interview with
Jean-Claude Carrière
The Mahabharata,
the Great History of Mankind
11 54
GREAT EPICS
HEROIC TALES OF MAN AND SUPERMAN
THE POET'S TALE
by Mahmoud Hussein
SCIENCE
AND SOCIETY
MAPPING
THE HUMAN GENOME
by Jacques Richardson
12
GILGAMESH,
THE KING WHO DID NOT WISH TO DIE
by Jean Bottéro 18
AENEAS, ROME'S MAN OF DESTINY
by Jean-Paul Brisson 23
THE EPIC OF THE KINGS
by Nahal Tadjadod 29
ILYA THE INVINCIBLE
by Hélène Yvert-Jalu 32
Cover: Dobrynia Nikitich, a legendary hero of
Russian folk epics, fights the dragon. This
miniature by P. Parilov appeared in a collection
of epics published in Moscow in 1938.
Back cover: Narada at the court of the demon
king Ravana. An 18th-century illustration of air
episode from the Ramayana, the great Sanskrit
epic poem of India which recounts the heroic
deeds of prince Rama. The poem is thought to
have been composed by Valmiki around the
beginning of the Christian era.
THE SECRET HISTORY OF THE MONGOLS
by Shagdaryn Bira 36
THE MAHAVAMSA, SRI LANKA'S NON-STOP EPIC
by Ananda W.P. Gurugé 41
SHAKA ZULU, A LIVING LEGEND
by Kalame Iyamuse Bosco
KNIGHTS OF THE FAR WEST
by Gary N. Granville
44
The Editors wish to thank
Ms. Nahal Tadjadod for her
help in the preparation of
49 this is:
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
The French author Jean-Claude Carrière is an internationally known dramatist and screenwriter
who has produced over fifty screenplays, notably for Luis Buñuel and Andrzej Wajda. Some years
ago he adapted for the stage the great Indian epic the Mahabharata. Here he talks about this
remarkable project which took over a decade to complete.
Jean-Claude Carrière
The Mahabharata, the Great History of Mankind
How do you set about making a work like the Mahabharata number was gradually diminished by death. Nevertheless,
accessible to a European or an American? he continued with his work, alone and without reward,
Over the past two or three centuries the West has sue- finally dying at his task. Someone else took up the burden,
ceeded in bringing large numbers of Japanese, Africans, but he too died. The epic has never been completely trans-
Patagonians to a sympathetic understanding of Shakespeare, lated into French. The only complete translation in a non-
Mozart and Picasso. There is no reason why the reverse Indian language is an English translation made by Indians
should not be possible, that Westerners in turn should not and completed in about 1900. In the 1930s, some Ameri-
become attuned to the Shakespeares, the Mozarts and the cans in Chicago embarked upon a new translation, but were
Picassos of other cultures. There are, however, a number obliged to abandon it uncompleted.
of barriers between cultures which are particularly difficult Amazingly, until 1985, the general public in Europe still
to surmount because they are invisible. knew nothing of the Mahabharata.
Take Europe for example. People are still immured
within a cultural fortress. For years other cultures have been 1985 was the year ofthefirst theatricalperformance, direct-
kept at bay. It wasn't until the beginning of the twentieth ed by Peter Brook, of your adaptation of the epic.
century that some avant-garde artists began to break down Yes. The play, The Mahabharata, was performed that
these walls. year at the Avignon festival for the first time. Lasting nine
Before then, from the eighteenth century onwards, there hours, it was performed either in sections on three differ-
had been a handful of solitary pioneers who had set out in ent evenings, or, occasionally, which the actors preferred,
' search of other worlds. It is astonishing to think that the in a single performance lasting all day or all night. The com-
Bhagavadgita, the most famous text in all the East, was not pany consisted of twenty-five actors and included sixteen
translated into English and French until the end of the different nationalities.
eighteenth century, just a few years before the French For three years, the show, in French or in English, was
Revolution... performed to packed and appreciative houses all over the
Internal resistance, especially religious resistance, was world. We soon realized that, in addition to the charm of
fierce. In the fifteenth century, the monk Luis de León was the story, Peter Brook's inspired directing and the talent
imprisoned for five years for translating The Song ofSolomon of the actors, some profound element in this tale from afar
into Spanish, despite the fact that it was a part of the Bible, touched a chord in a totally unprepared Western public in
Bringing into Europe texts foreign to Christian culture was a direct and lasting manner.
an act of heroism which could be undertaken only by people Was it the unmistakable sense of impending doom hang-
of exceptional stature. ing over the world? Was it the unwavering search for the
As for the Mahabharata, it remained unknown in Europe true meaning of doing what was right? Was it the subtle,
until the end of the nineteenth century. To translate the sometimes savage, game of dice with destiny? Was it,
Mahabharata was, it should be noted, a very considerable perhaps, that comic-pathetic vision of characters who for-
undertaking. The epic is fifteen times as long as the Bible, get their divine origin to face up to what the Greeks of the
The poor fellow who embarked on the first French trans- same epoch called "problemata"those questions and con-
lation worked at the task for twenty-five years, on a sub- flicts of daily life in the resolution of which myth gives way
scription basis. At first he had 200 subscribers, but their to tragedy?
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
In Sanskrit Maha means "great", or "total". Bharata is,
first, the name of a legendary sage, second, the name of a
family or clan. Thus the title of the epic can be understood
as "Great Epic of the Bharata Dynasty". But Bharata can
also, by extension, mean "Hindu", or, more generally,
"Man". Thus the story is no more and no less than "The
Great History of Mankind".
In fact; the central narrative of this "great epic of the
world" concerns the long, ferocious struggle between two
related families, the five Pandava brothers, and the Kauravas,
1 he arrival of Queen
Gandhari. This photo and
those on pages 7 to 9 show
scenes from the stage
version of the
Mahabharata (Paris, 1985)
adapted by Jean-Claude
Carrière and directed by
Peter Brook.
\Jpposite page, the five
Pandava brothers.
who number one hundred. This family quarrel, which arises
and intensifies regarding dominion over the world, cul¬
minates in a titanic battle in which the fate of the entire
world is at stake.
How did you summon up the courage to take on such an
immense task? Did you start by reading the text and, ifso,
did you read it in English or in Sanskrit?
It all came about through a mixture of accident and
design. The accident was a chance meeting with an expert in
Sanskrit, Philippe Lavastine, who today is nearly eighty years
old. He invited Peter Brook and me to his home one evening
and began to talk about the Mahabharata in his own genial,
lively manner.
We knew virtually nothing about the subject, our
knowledge being limited to a reading of the Bhagavadgita
made all the more superficial in that we had read it as an
individual document apart from the Mahabharata, of which
it is fully a part. As we sat facing Lavastine, Peter asked him:
"Who is this Arjuna who is mentioned in the Bhagavadgita,
and why does he go to pieces before Krishna talks to him?"
"I shall have to tell you about Arjuna," Lavastine replied,
"but telling you about Arjuna, well..." It took him several
months.
Once or twice a week we would spend a marvellous
evening with Lavastine during which he would recount the
epic to us. Later, I went back to see him on my own and
began taking notes. Like the Greek bards of old, Lavastine
was an exceptionally gifted storyteller. He spoke, he gestic¬
ulated, he laughed, he became the poem.
After four or five months, I was beginning to have a
picture of the work as a whole and to grasp its extraordi¬
nary complexity, its multiple levels of meaning, in which
respect it can only be compared to the works of Shakespeare.
It ranges from the heights of mystic speculation to irresistible
farce. The whole gamut of human emotion and thought is
there portrayed like a rich bouquet.
The effort needed to enter into- the mysteries of the
Mahabharata is commensurate with its complexity. Anyone
approaching it by reading, without preparation, is likely to
put it aside after the first twenty pages. We were lucky that
we came to it not by reading but through the agency of a
storyteller.
Then came the time when you really had to get down to
work...
Within a year I had written a first draft play based on
the Mahabharata, even before getting down to reading it.
I was well aware that this play would never be performed,
but it enabled me, as it were, to harvest the results of my
initial labours. I wanted to see if it was possible to make
an adaptation for the theatre while keeping to the formula
of the epic poem, that of a narration by a storyteller. It was
still no more than a narrative not yet prepared for the
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
theatre, but at least it gave me a time scale and I knew that
the whole story of the Mahabharata could be contained
within a performance time of between five and ten hours.
From this point on, Peter and I knew that we wanted to
"do" the Mahabharata. We had committed ourselves.
The preparatory stage spread over a period of eleven
years, from 1974 to 1985. We continued working on other
things, for the theatre and the cinema, but for both of us
the Mahabharata had become a travelling companion,
whether we were together or apart.
We began the "big read" in 1980. 1 had a photocopy
of the French translation and Peter had one of the Indian
version in English. Each of us started reading individually,
but whenever we had a chance of seeing each other, we ex¬
changed views and shared our joys.
It takes a year to read the Mahabharata in its entirety,
but as we were doing other things at the same time, it took
us somewhat longer. The epic took over our lives. We had
constantly before us this huge white whale, this Moby Dick,
this bright vision; and as we went along, we discovered ex¬
traordinary things that even Lavastine had not told us about.
Then, in 1982, we said to ourselves: "Now is the time
for us to do a joint read-through." It took us six or seven
months, reading together every day in company with Marie-
Hélène Estienne who was collaborating with us. Compar¬
ing the two versions, French and English, we eliminated all
the passages that we felt we could do without (about a third
of the text) and we reread the remainder making a detailed
comparison of the translations. Whenever a problem arose,
we consulted an expert in Sanskrit and went back to the
original text.
By August 1982, we had completed our joint reading
and we had a rough idea of what we wanted to include-
not in theatrical terms, but in terms of content. We also
knew, for example, that we would telescope the events of
the three tourneys that figure in the Mahabharata into one.
Similarly, where the epic recounts two episodes of exile in
the forest, only one would feature in the play. The first ele¬
ments of the theatrical version were beginning to take shape.
At this stage we felt well enough prepared to go to India.
We knew the characters and we could discuss the work with
the Indians on the basis of an almost equal level of back¬
ground knowledge. Starting in 1982, we made a series of
enthralling trips to India to examine all the ways in which
the Mahabharata is staged therein the various dancing
schools and among certain tribes, according to the traditional
Teyyam, Kathakali and Yaksagana dance-drama forms. We
spent a long time working with various troupes. What we
were trying to assess was the presence of the epic in the life
of India today and the precise level of energy required by
each sequence.
What exactly do you mean by that?
India taught us, above all, that a certain dose of vitality,
of necessary energy, has to be put into a show. Not too
much, not too little, just the amount required so that it never
becomes solemn or didactic but remains a lively, lived ex¬
perience. The great lesson we learned from India can be
summed up in two words: "respectful familiarity".
In addition, we wanted to integrate into our vision all
the images of India, from the maharajahs' palaces to the
shanty towns. I made one trip, accompanied by Peter and
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Chloe Obolensky, with the sole aim of visiting one cloth-
seller after another. Strange as this may seem, the warp and
weft, the very texture of a piece of cloth, can help an author
to write more trulyor more concisely.
During these trips, did you remain merely a spectator
absorbing impressions?
No, I also began writing. First, however, I made lists
of words that I forbade myself to use. Words are never in¬
nocent. They exercise their own tyranny and a writer has
to be very aware of this when adapting a text from another
culture.
One has to beware of words which violate, which betray
the text because they are too culturally loaded, because they
exert their own exclusivity, because they erase certain ideas
and images and conjure up others. I could not, for example,
use such words as "knight", "sword", or "sin", or, for more
subtle reasons, "silhouette" or "unhorsed".
Take the word "unconscious". If I had used this word
I would have been perpetrating an imperceptible, but abso¬
lute, irreparable betrayal. In Hinduism and Buddhism there
is a perfectly understood and defined meaning of "uncons¬
cious" which has not the remotest connection with the Freu¬
dian sense of the word, with its sexual connotations, as it
is understood today in the West. In India it is known that
a human being thinks without knowing that he is thinking
and that his consciousness is more widely extended, in all
directions, than his thought.
This concept is rendered in Sanskrit by an expression
which might be translated as something like "the secret
movements of the Atman", Atman meaning "soul", "vital
breath", or "innermost essence". Obviously one cannot put
a phrase like that baldly in a play, any more than one can
translate it by "unconscious". I searched high and low for
an equivalent, which I eventually found in the works of the
great African writer Hampâté Bâ.
Reading his novel Wangrin's Strange Destiny, I found
two very simple words placed side by side: "deep" and
"heart". Juxtaposed, they seemed to me to form a magical
phrase and I used it three or four times in the play. It goes
very well, as when Krishna says to Bhishma: "Do you not
feel it, in your deep heart...?" Imagine how it would have
come across if Krishna had said: "Do you not feel it, in your
unconscious...?"
Later, when reading la potière jalouse (The Jealous Pot¬
ter's Wife), by Claude Lévi-Strauss, I found the same image
of the "deep heart" in a translation from an Amerindian
text. Did he discover it directly, or did he get it, like me,
from Hampâté Bâ? I was much moved to come across it and
to ponder on the beauty of such a linguistic voyage.
You had to eliminate certain words outright from your
vocabulary. Were there other words that, on the contrary,
you made greater use of?
Yes, simple, accessible words which travel across
\Jpposite page, Arjuna and the son
of King Virata go to war.
1 he princesses' night of love.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
cultures without difficulty. Wide-ranging words like
"blood", which means the red liquid flowing in our veins,
the link of kinship, or quality (we refer to a thoroughbred
horse as a blood-horse); the word "heart", which means the
organ that circulates the blood, but also courage (as in the
phrase "take heart") or sincerity (as in heartfelt); the words
"life" and "death". All these are inoffensive, unaggressive
words which have their place in texts which pass readily
from one culture to another.
While keeping the original names of the characters, I
elected to eliminate most Sanskrit words and to find equiva¬
lents. However, I made a few exceptions. I kept the word
"Dharma", for instance, because it is central to the whole
theme. After all, it was to "inscribe Dharma in the hearts
of men" that Vyasa wrote his epic. The concept of Dhar¬
ma is of ancient Indian invention. Dharma is the law which
governs the order of the world. It is also the secret, personal
law of behaviour that each one of us carries within and
which must be obeyed. The Dharma of each individual, if
respected, is the guarantee of the cosmic order. If the Dhar¬
ma is protected, it in turn protects; but if it. is destroyed,
it destroys.
This reciprocity between the singular and the multiple,
between the particular and the general, is peculiar to and
lies at the very heart of Indian thought, as expressed in the
poem; a reciprocity which today, as in the past, evokes many
echoes.
Was it yourpurpose, in choosing these key words, to mark
out the space within which two cultures could sing in har¬
mony with each other, and the one within the other?
Absolutely. I was marking out a territory.
Would you say that the series of trips you made to India
helped you to rediscover the truth of the Mahabharata
because it was there that it was created?
I would say the "truths" of the work, or at least some
of its truths. There is no "single" authentic interpretation
of the Mahabharata. Ask a Hindu holy man from the south
and a marxist professor from Calcutta about it and you will
get different replies, both of them interesting. We do not
claim, finally, to have given "the" truth of the work, simply
one version among manyour version, in the West, in the
1980s.
Nor do I think that we should limit ourselves to com¬
mentaries on the work, interesting as they may be. As the
French specialist on Indo-European mythologies Georges
Dumézil said: "...the essential thing is that it should be beau¬
tiful." In our view, this vast epic, unfolding with the subtle
majesty of a river of inexhaustible riches, defies all analysis,
whether structural, thematic, historical or psychological.
Doors are continually opening, which lead on to other
doors. The Mahabharata cannot be held in the hollow of
one's hand. There are many ramifications. Sometimes seem¬
ingly contradictory, they succeed each wther and intertwine,
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
HHf.
tyr ",<:¿..
BS
:V' I
^H
» 'ff*
y.vpV.V.
W*}-1!
.'. *i ,
A.« .
:*afe
.> p*f
(jpV
*
HamUtHan^aKaS;-
UU
b^b^b^IbIb^ebS ¿skats ËAatf m
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
E I T 0 R I A L
The Golden Knight
(1903), by the Viennese
painter Gustav Klimt
(1862-1918).
TT HETHER composed by unknown poets, transmitted orally and reshaped from
century to century, or written by a single known author, epics relate to the birth of a culture,
the early days of a nation or an empire, sometimes even to the creation of the universe.
Their setting is often an age when human beings first began to exist outside the realm of
the gods. Their heroes are denizens of a zone midway between the temporal and the eternal.
These heroes may no longer be immortal, but they are superhuman. They no longer claim
to be omnipotent; they are fallible, they are capable of hesitation, failure, love, hate and
suffering. But they are endowed with exceptional qualities of determination, intelligence
and energy with which to face their destiny, overcome adversity, and change the order of
things. They are both explorers of the known world and founders of new cities.
Because of these qualities, epic heroes have always been a central part of the shared experience
of traditional societies, which they have furnished with psychological models, ethical, aesthetic
and religious values, and personal examples for everyone to reflect on. Larger than life, freed
from some of the constraints that weighed on their fellows, epic heroes have been a source
of inspiration for many, capturing their imagination and lifting them above life's tribulations
and disappointments.
In village, town and city, bards, poets, storytellers, strolling minstrels and griots sang of
the exploits of these legendary heroes, relieving the monotony of everyday life, keeping
alive the community spirit, and maintaining from generation to generation the continuity ~1
of the national memory.
The epic has thus survived the vicissitudes of history. But in the last few decades many J
barriers to communication have disappeared from the world scene; the image has overtaken
the written word; the storytellers of old have been replaced by television; the mass media
have presented to a world audience individualistic heroes who seek a destiny in which the
traditional and the sacred have no part. How has the epic reacted to this shock?
As a factor of social cohesion in traditional communities, it slowly lost ground. On the
other hand, it took on a new lease of life and reached a far wider audience as the theatre,
the cinema and television seized on the opportunity to adapt versions of ancient legends
and transpose their themes to different periods and settings. An increasingly wide public
made the astonishing discovery that there were affinities between the world's great epics.
Spectators in places as far apart as Avignon or Caracas felt an immediate rapport with the
heroes of Persian or Zulu epics and saw similarities between epic figures which transcended
time and place.
They thus discovered a truth which, although very ancient, is only now being fully revealed:
that the dreams of our past are rooted in kinship, not antagonism, and that they express,
in an infinite variety of contexts and languages, fears of the same mysteries and hopes for
the same joys.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The itinerant poet pays his
annual visit to an Egyptian
village, with memorable
consequences...
The poet's tale
BY MAHMOUD HUSSEIN
W.
12
E were waiting impatiently for the return
of summer, for the rains to stop, for school to
liberate us from its constraints. Our families
would then let us run around the village streets
from daybreak until long after sunset, without
supervision or rebukeunless one of us got hurt
in a fight or an accident.
Summer also meant harvest time, and harvest
time meant weddings. All those who lived off the
land, from the smallest farmer to the wealthiest
landowner, were waiting for the harvest to be
gathered in and sold. This was virtually the only
time of the year when the peasants had any
money and could go to town and buy, each
according to his means, a trousseau for the future
bride. Only with her trousseau would a girl be
ready to leave her father's home for that of her
husband.
For the childrenat a time when radio was
rare and television unknownweddings meant
that troupes of musicians and actors would be
coming to the village. Above all they meant the
arrival of a visitor that we awaited with joyful
anticipation for weeks in advancethe poet.
The poet usually officiated at the "night of
the henna"the eve of the wedding, when the
hands and feet of the bride were painted with hen¬
na. The musicians would play all the next after¬
noon during the presentation of the trousseau
An Egyptian village
storyteller accompanies
himself on a stringed
instrument, the rabab.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
And then the theatre troupe would follow in the
evening, associating the whole village with the
joy of the families which had just been linked by
marriage.
We thrilled to every instant of the festivities.
We loved the familiar music, unchanged since
pharaonic times; and we split our sides laughing
at the twists and turns of these comedies whose
plots turned on conjugal infidelity and just
punishment of the guilty. But for us the highlight
of the entertainment, the moment of jubilation,
was when the poet came on.
We talked about him in the singular, as if
there was only one poet, but actually he was
never alone. He had one or more partners, who
accompanied him on the viol or joined him in
reciting some couplets in time to a rhythm.
The arrival of the- poet
The poet usually turned up during the afternoon.
A few local dignitaries and nearly all the children
would be waiting for him by the roadside at the
entrance to the village. The former would greet
him with words of welcome, the latter with
cheering and clapping. Then, amidst cries of joy,
as if he were the future husband, he would be
escorted to the home of the host family.
There the poet was hidden from our sight.
But news of him constantly filtered out from in¬
side the house via a few well-informed friends
who were either members of the host family or
the kind of pushy children who go everywhere
even if they haven't been invited.
The reports were intermittent or continuous,
depending on the impudence of the inform¬
ers.. .right now the poet is drinking syrup or
coffee.. .now he's taking a nap to set him up for
the long evening ahead.. .now he's having his sup¬
per.. .he's tuning his instruments.
We seized upon this precious information
and discussed its every detail. Every snippet was
a sign that the long-awaited moment was drawing
closeror getting further awaywhen the poet
would at long last take the stage.
A moment increasingly rare and precious
since more and more families were hesitating to
invite the poet.. .and the minute that one family
finally did so we felt an unspoken anxiety spread
through the village and increase until the day of
the poet's arrival.
We also noted that special arrangements were
made in preparation for the evening entertain¬
ment; that meetings were held to try somehow
or other to divide up the space reserved for the
S - s
*,
V,
1 wo episodes from the Hilaliyya. Above, one of the
heroes of the epic, El Zeinati Khalifa (left).
audience between the people of our village and
guests from villages nearby; that the local police
were ready for action; that many guests from the
surrounding countryside, especially the young
ones, were armed with clubs and obstinately re¬
fused to hand them over, in spite of the objec¬
tions of the village dignitaries and elders.
Only gradually did we connect the tension
which reigned among the adults, and the precau¬
tionary measures they took, with the later events
which upset all their calculations and put paid to
their plans to keep events under control.
The performance took place in the village
square, where a platform was set up for the poet
and his troupe. Mats had been placed around the
platform for the guestswith the exception ofthe
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
1 he village of Takruna,
near Zaghwan in Tunisia,
the "Ifriquia" that features
in the epic poem of the
Banou Hilal.
omdah and the dignitaries, for whom seats of
honour were reserved, specially placed at points
where their occupants could leave the square at
the first sign of danger.
The poet appeared on the platform shortly
after the evening prayer, giving the guests time
to make their way to the square after performing
their religious duty. We children took our places
long before, as soon as the lighting of the street
lamps made the evening air shimmer magically.
We crowded as close to the platform as we could,
never giving a thought to what was causing so
much concern to those around us.
We greeted the poet with cries of joy, atten¬
tive to his slightest change of expression. Wé no¬
ticed the proud smiles which our warm welcome
brought to his features; and we even caught the
silent questioning glance which from time to time
betrayed his feelings as he glanced round the
square, as if to detect the places where danger
might be lurking.
Whoever he was, whatever his age, the poet
always told the story of Abou Zeid El Hilali
even though there are many other popular heroes
in the Arab and Egyptian repertoire, such as Seif
Ibn Yazan, Zir Salem, and Ali El Zeibaq. But the
epic of Abou Zeid El Hilali, the Hilaliyya, was
invariably chosen by the poet.
The Hilaliyya is the incident-packed epic
poem of the Banou Hilal tribe, one of those
which left the Arabian peninsula in the aftermath
of the conquests sparked off by the successors of 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
D i A
the Prophet, and moved north, east and west to
build what would become the Muslim world.
The poet (whichever one he was) never be¬
gan the story at the beginning, just as he never
reached the end. We would leave the square
without ever learning where the Hilalian advance
ended. The poet (always) opened and closed his
narrative somewhere in "ifriquia",* at the site
of a city whose people were determined to hold
out against the conquering tribe, whatever the
cost.
He related, in his own fashion, some of the
episodes of the confrontation between the be¬
sieged city and its assailants. The narrative was
punctuated by musical interludes in which the
heroes of the two sides spoke out in turn. Op¬
posing Abou Zeid was the chief of the surround¬
ed tribe, El Zeinati Khalifa. But there were
countless other characters, and anyone listening
to the tale for the first time had a hard time keep¬
ing up with it.
Many romances blossomed between the girls
of one camp and the warriors of the other, com¬
plicating the issues of a struggle in which the
audience's preferences gradually became
inextricably confused. The poet skilfully divid¬
ed his emotional flights between the two oppos¬
ing sides. Whenever he praised the courage of one
side, he went on to recount a new episode which
glorified the other. And when a Banou Hilal
woman declared her love for a Banou Khalifa
man, the poet immediately described the passion
of a Banou Khalifa woman for a Banou Hilal
man.
16
The storm breaks
The poet's art lay in his capacity to hold his
listeners' rapt attention by channelling their sym¬
pathies first to one side, then to the other.. .by
playing on their feelings of joy in victory and sad¬
ness in defeat, by striking a balance between the
tenderness of the love scenes and the violence of
the battle scenes, between the wisdom of the
elders and the audacity of the young.
But this skilled game of checks and balances
could not prevent the audience from splitting
sooner or later into two camps, one taking the
part of the Banou Hilal, the other that of the
Banou Khalifa. Moreover, the supporters of each
side were always virtually equal in number,
heaven knows why. It was as if they were mys¬
teriously reflecting the equilibrium sought by the
poet.
However, -from that moment, the tensions
which permeated the story began to spread
through the audience. The spectators became in¬
volved. As soon as the poet swung the story one
way, the supporters of that side shouted with joy,
while the supporters of the other side jeered their
disapproval.
The task of the poet became increasingly deli-
* In present-day Tunisia. Editor
1 he Egyptian village of
Qurna.
MAHMOUD HUSSEIN
is the pen name of two
Egyptian writers who have
published several books of
political sociology, most
recently Versant sud de la
liberté, Essai sur l'e'mergence
de l'individu dans le tiers
monde ("The Southern Face
of Liberty, an essay on the
emergence of the individual
in the Third World", La
Découverte, Paris, 1989).
J. * s
'iiÍ)
fill I i
cate, his mastery of the situation increasingly un¬
certain. The "night of the henna" rarely ended
with a round of applause. Instead of the audience
dispersing quietly into the night, and the poet and
his troupe peacefully settling into the beds which
had been prepared for them, the evening ended
in an explosion of violence.
It was impossible to pinpoint the moment
when emotion degenerated into confrontation.
Even today we search our memories in vain try¬
ing to establish the sequence of cause and effect
which suddenly turned the festivities sour. A
predictable but unfathomable chain of events led
to a conflict which was all the more strange and
brutal since it had been expected, planned almost,
for days. A word was uttered by someone in the
crowd, in a hollow, scornful voice. There was an
immediate menacing riposte, and a club was
raised, then two, then three...
In the twinkling of an eye, the storm broke.
Blows rained down from all directions. It was as
though the audience had been seized by an ir¬
resistible need to give vent to a terrible, long-pent-
up frustration. No one dreamt of asking where
this frustration originated nor how far things
would go now that the dam had burst.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The village dignitaries slipped away. The poet
and his companions tiptoed off. A cacophony of
police whistles pierced the nocturnal silence.
Street lamps were broken and went out. But the
scuffle continued in the darkblind, relentless,
breathless, until everyone was exhausted, until the
calming of the anger for which the poet's tale was
merely the occasion, its real reasons being buried
in the past, in the silent march of the centuries.
The passing of an era
The years have gone by. The city has removed
us from the slow rhythm of the country. Study
and travel, cinema and television, have slowly
reduced to a faint memory those evenings when
the heroic acts of Abou Zeid and Zeinati came
to life so vividly. The "night of the henna" is
celebrated less and less in the villages. As for the
poets, the children no longer wait at the road¬
side for them. They have gone, never to return.
Thanks to books and films we have disco¬
vered other epics; other heroes from many lands
compete for our affections with those of the
Hilaliyya. Certain episodes from different epics
seem to merge curiously with others, and a resem¬
blance between certain characters has appeared.
Coincidence, mutual influence, a common
source? How can one help but find in the be¬
sieged city of the Banou Khalifa a replica of the
city of Troy, and in numerous episodes of the
Hilaliyya a striking resemblance to parts of the
Iliad?
Surely the atmosphere in which the poets of
the Egyptian countryside recited their works is
comparable to that in which the ancient Greek
poets must have recited their epic songs? Didn't
the Greek poets of old also modify their narra¬
tive to suit their audience, expanding or com¬
pressing certain scenes in response to the
preferences they discerned in their listeners?
Perhaps that is what we miss today. In liter¬
ature and in film, we learn and understand thou¬
sands of new things each day, a thousand things
which only yesterday were beyond us. But we
do not find, nor will we ever find again, the col¬
lective embrace of a stifling square where we hung
on every word of an itinerant poet, whisked away
as if by magic to remote cities where we exor¬
cised the realities of the present by reliving
mythical times. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Gilgamesh,
the king who did not wish to die
After the death of his friend
Enkidu, Gilgamesh is forced to
accept that he too must die one
day. An epic composed thirty-five
centuries ago tells how Gilgamesh,
his dream, of immortality
shattered, comes to terms with the
human condition.
Oerigraph by the German
artist Willi Baumeister
(1889-1955) illustrates two
lines from the Epic of
Gilgamesh: "One double-hour
he travelled; Dense is the
darkness and there is no
light."
18
\Jpposite page, the hero
Gilgamesh is shown holding
a lion cub in this 8th-
century-BC Assyrian bas-
relieffrom the palace of
Sargon II at Khursabad
(Iraq).
%RITTEN over thirty-five centuries ago, the
ancient Mesopotamian epic of Gilgamesh is the
oldest extant epic in world history. Not only is
it an immortal triumph of literary creation, it is
also one of those vivid, venerable documents in
which the innermost thoughts of the most an¬
cient of our forefathers are still discernible
through the mists of the past.
Written in Akkadian, a language distantly
related to Arabic and Hebrew, and inscribed on
clay tablets in impressive, wedge-shaped cunei¬
form script, it covers eleven tablets, each of which
contains about 300 lines; a twelfth tablet was
added later. So far, over a period of more than
a century, about two-thirds of the work has been
recovered as additional fragments have been
found by chance during excavations in the
archaeologically-rich soil of Iraq. Today, despite
the gaps which remain, we can follow most of
the incidents and vicissitudes of the narration in
their sequence. Above all, we have a clear picture
of the scope and significance of the work.
We also know enough to realize that, from
the eighteenth century BC, the author, about
whom we are otherwise totally ignorant, drew
his inspiration from even more ancient folktales,
at least some of which had circulated as short,
individual legends. He succeeded in bringing
together these scattered threads and weaving them
into a coherent, original whole which has come
down tO'.us in the form of this grandiose, tragic
epic.
The human condition
The author took as his hero Gilgamesh, the cen¬
tral figure of these tales, a former monarch of the
country, who must have reigned in the ancient
city of Uruk in the middle of the third millenni¬
um BC. His name tells us little and we have no
other information about him apart from what is
recounted in the old legends. Yet despite his royal
title, duly brought to the reader's attention
throughout the epic, Gilgamesh figures in the nar¬
rative neither in a political or military role for
his battles and victories nor even as a national
hero. He is portrayed simply as a man, as a pre¬
eminent model and representative of each mem¬
ber of the human community.
Throughout the work, his over-riding con¬
cern is neither with conquest, the retention of
power and glory, nor with the prosperity of his
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
BYJEANBOTTÉRO
country and the diffusion of its culture, but with
the desperate search for a solution to the most
terrible of all problemshow to face up to death.
The Gilgamesh epic is first and foremost an ac¬
count of the drama of the human condition as
personified by the ancient king of Uruk, with his
adventures, dreams, hopes, sufferings and his final
acceptance of failure.
With total mastery of his art, the author
depicts the drama of the king's rise and fall. The
first six tablets portray his rise to the summit and
the remaining tablets his downfall. The epic may
have been set down in writing by order of Gil¬
gamesh himself on his return from his lengthy
travels, "weary and worn" after having "seen all
and committed everything to memory". He
wanted to pass on to posterity the essential les¬
son of his life.
The admired and prosperous king of Uruk
is at first depicted as a virtual superman, conscious
of his strength, convinced of his superiority and
tyrannizing the world around him. Alerted by
the grievances of the people, the gods decide to
intervene. They place the matter in the hands of
Enki, the most intelligent among them. Resorting
to a psychological subterfuge, Enki causes the cre¬
ation of a kind of double and counterpart to Gil¬
gamesh, a rival of equal stature and strength who
will strip him of his feeling of uniqueness and
turn him away from his excesses.
A memory, perhaps, preserved in legend, of
ancient antagonisms between the refined city-
dweller and the uncouth, "primitive" nomad, this
double is a "savage", born and raised on the
steppe beyond the limits of the civilized world.
His name, Enkidu ("creature of Enki") recalls his
origins.
Learning of the existence of this phenome¬
non and wishing to draw him to his presence, Gil¬
gamesh sends to him Lascivia, one of many
courtesans given up to the delights of "free love",
a major prerogative of the advanced civilization
of the city. Lascivia seduces Enkidu and converts
him to the ways of city life. The first encounter
between Gilgamesh and Enkidu is far from cor¬
dial. With each of them burning to assert his su¬
periority, they "grappled, with each other,
snorting like bulls". Later, however, "they kissed
one another and formed a friendship", for the
author deliberately sets out to transform the "ser¬
vant" of the legend into the intimate friend and
companion of Gilgamesh, his alter ego. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
The two friends
Together the two companions embark upon the
great and dangerous adventure of the "Cedar
Forest". Popular tradition may have preserved
the memory of an immemorial urge which in¬
cited the people of Mesopotamia, a flat, bare land
of clay and reeds, to venture out to distant moun¬
tains in search of wood for building, stone and
metals. So Gilgamesh and Enkidu head towards
the northwest, towards Amanus and Lebanon.
Already the secret desire to transcend death by
the achievement of fame and glory is taking
shape: "IfIfall, " says Gilgamesh, "I will establish
a name for myself... An everlasting [name] I will
establish for myself."*
In several long stages, of which we have few
details except that each of them is marked by a
dream of good omen experienced by Gilgamesh
and interpreted by his friend, they reach the dark,
silent, mysterious immensity of the forest. Ac¬
cording to legend, the forest is guarded by the
fearsome giant Huwawa (or Humbaba), whom
the two friends finally overcome.
At this point the author, aware of misfortune
brewing quietly in the background, just as a dis¬
tant, scarcely audible murmur presages the com¬
ing of a storm, tells of the heroes' first error, the
first weight placed on the scales that will deter¬
mine their destiny. After hesitating as to the gi¬
ant's fate, they finally kill him. Free now to act
as they please, they cut down vast numbers of
the sacred cedarsthus committing their second
error. Loading the tree trunks on a boat, they sail
down the Euphrates and back to Uruk, where
they are received in triumph.
The two friends are now at the pinnacle of
their glory. However, a further incident occurs
which the author skilfully presents as a success,
but which, added to the two earlier events, will
be fraught with consequence. The goddess Ishtar
suddenly falls in love with Gilgamesh. Aware of
her fickleness, Gilgamesh rejects her advances in
scathing terms. In revenge, she asks her father,
Anu, king of the gods, to send against Uruk the
"Bull of Heaven", in the guise of which, accord¬
ing to legend, a terrible calamity had previously
been visited upon the city..
Gilgamesh and Enkidu slay the monster and
cut it to pieces. But falling once more into the
snare of excess which so often entraps the vic¬
torious, they compound this affront to Ishtar
when Enkidu throws one of the beast's haunches
in her face and threatens to make her a necker¬
chief of its entrails. Unaware of the imminence
of his downfall, Gilgamesh marks his triumph
with a brilliant celebration held in his palace. In
a drunken outburst, he declares himself to be "the
most splendid among the heroes, the most glori¬
ous among men."
Just as in life, in which our greatest successes
often foreshadow and set off a train of events
which leads to defeat or disaster, it is at this point
that the errors of the past have their combined
effect, that the gods react and the storm breaks.
At the start of the seventh tablet, after a terrible
nightmare in which he sees the gods in council
condemn him to death, Enkidu suddenly falls ill,
goes into a gradual decline and realizes that he
is going to die. He curses the courtesan who, by
raising him to a higher station in life, set him on
the road to misfortune, and expires in the arms
of his despairing friend. At first Gilgamesh is un¬
willing to believe that he is dead, refusing even
to heed the hideous appearance gradually taken
on by the dead man's corpse "until the worm fell
upon his face". For the first time the hero is ex¬
periencing real death and seeing the unbearable
image and presentiment of his own death con¬
jured up by the sudden extinction of his friend:
When I die, shall I not be like unto Enkidu?
Sorrow has entered my heart.
To rid himself of the thought with which he
is now obsessed and to find the remedy for death,
whose true face has been so cruelly revealed to
him, Gilgamesh sets off in quest of the secret of
eternal life.
'The gift of life everlasting'
He knows that the gods once gave the gift of ever¬
lasting life to one man, Utanapishtim ("I have
found life") the sole survivor of the Flood, thanks
to whom the continuance of the human race had
been assured. But after granting him this privilege,
the gods had set him apart from other mortals,
sending him to the end of the earth. Gilgamesh
decides to go and seek out Utanapishtim and to
learn from him the secret of this signal favour.
Arriving after an amazing, interminable jour¬
ney at the shores of the last distant sea separat¬
ing him from his goal, he encounters a mysterious
nymph, Siduri (the ale-wife), who lives in that iso¬
lated region and who warns him of the futility
of his quest:
Gilgamesh, whither runnest thou?
The life which thou seekest thou wilt not find.
[For] when the gods created mankind,
They allotted death to mankind,
[But] life they retained in their keeping.
Thou, O Gilgamesh, let thy belly be full;
Day and night be thou merry;
Make every day [a day of] rejoicing.
Day and night do thou dance and play.
Let thy raiment be clean,
Thy head be washed, [and] thyself be bathed
in water.
Cherish the little one holding thy hand,
[And] let thy wife rejoice in thy bosom.
This is the lot of [mankind]...
But lost in his dream of eternal life, he does
not heed her words and continues on his way.
When at last he finds himself in the presence of
Utanapishtim, he asks him outright how he ob¬
tained this miraculous favour of the gods. In re¬
ply, Utanapishtim recounts the story of the
Flood. He tells how the gods decided to destroy
the race of men they had created to serve them,
JEAN BOTTERO,
of France, is director of
studies in philological and
historical sciences at the
Ecole Pratique des Hautes
Etudes, Paris, and a
specialist on ancient
Mesopotamian civilization.
Among his recent published
works are Mésopotamie:
L'écriture, la raison et les
dieux ("Mesopotamia:
Writing, Reason and Gods",
1987) and, with Samuel
Noah Kramer, Lorsque les
dieux faisaient l'homme:
Mythologie mésopotamienne
("When the Gods made
Man: Mesopotamian
Mythology", 1989).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Kjilgamesh and Enkidu destroy the
Bull of Heaven and other monsters.
Plaster cast from an early
Mesopotamian cylinder seal
(2400 BC).
1 he story of the Flood as it is
recorded in the Epic of Gilgamesh.
Babylonian tablet from Nineveh
inscribed with cuneiform writing
(7th century BC).
but who had multiplied and whose noise prevent¬
ed them from sleeping.
Aware of the difficult situation the gods
would find themselves in once men had all
vanished, the god Enki, acting on his own, ar¬
ranged for one man to be spared, with all neces¬
sities, in a boat that would save him from the
Deluge. It was for this reason alone that the grate¬
ful gods had promised Utanapishtim that he
should never die. It was hardly likely that
Gilgamesh would ever find himself in a similar
situation.
Moreover, to show Gilgamesh that he is not
really made for everlasting life, Utanapishtim
challenges him to remain for just six days without
yielding to sleep, that daily rehearsal of death. Gil¬
gamesh takes up his challenge, but falls asleep on
the very first day. There is nothing left for him
to do but to depart, his dream shattered, with
nothing to show for all his efforts and sufferings:
For whom have my hands become weary?
For whom is the blood ofmy heart being spent?
Gilgamesh returns home and the author of
the epic, briefly depicting Uruk as a splendid opu¬
lent city, seems intent on bringing his hero, and
through him all men, back to the joys of this life,
which are, as the nymph Siduri had proclaimed,
"the lot of mankind".-
* Quotations from The Gilgamesh Epic and Old Testament
Parallels, by Alexander Heidel, Phoenix Books, University
of Chicago Press, 1963. 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The adventures ofAeneas chronicled in Virgil's great
poem the Aeneid make a powerful human drama
whose force is undiminished by time.
%
Aeneas, Rome's man
of destiny
BY JEAN-PAUL BRISSON
Aeneas leaves the burning
city of Troy, carrying his
father Anchises on his back.
Marseilles pottery, 18th
century.
Left, "Venus appears to
Aeneas and sends him
Cupid. " Detail of a fresco
by Giovanni Battista
Tiepolo (1696-1770) in the
Aeneid room of the Villa
Valmarana, at Vicenza
(Italy).
RITTEN between 29 BC and 19 BC, the
Roman poet Virgil's epic, the Aeneid, recounts
the adventures of the Trojan hero Aeneas, fruit
of the union of the mortal Anchises with the
goddess Venus.
Having miraculously survived the destruction
of Troy, Aeneas, accompanied by his father, his
infant son lulus and a handful of faithful com¬
panions, sets sail in search of the place, appoint¬
ed by destiny but as yet unknown to him, where
he is to build a new Troy. As his journey unfolds,
he comes to realize that the city's mysterious new
site is situated in Italy, in the region of Latium.
Warrings and wanderings
Before reaching his goal, however, he is fated to
wander the length and breadth of the Mediterra¬
nean for seven years. This is partly because the
utterances of the oracles, who purport to guide
him in his quest, are inevitably far from clear.
A false interpretation of one oracular message
makes him think for a time that his destination
is Crete until, warned of his error by the outbreak
of a terrible plague, he is forced to flee the island.
But the prime cause of his misfortunes is the un¬
relenting hatred of the all-powerful Juno, wife of
Jupiter, the king of the gods.
This hatred stems from an ancient incident
recounted by Homerthe famous judgement of
Paris, the Trojan who dared to award the prize
for beauty to Venus rather than to Juno. As
depicted at the beginning of Virgil's epic, the
queen of Olympus neither can nor wishes to for¬
get what she considers to be a personal affront
for which, through Paris, she holds all Trojans
responsible. She finds it intolerable that a small
group of Trojans should have survived her ven¬
geance and have the temerity to want to rebuild
a city that is for her accursed. No subterfuge that
may prevent Aeneas from achieving his aim and
ensure his final downfall is too low for her.
After seven years of wanderings, Aeneas lands
in Sicily where his old father dies. By now he
knows for certain how and where he will discover
the site to which destiny will lead him and it is
with confidence and a light heart that he sets out
for Italy. Seeing him so near his goal, Juno suc¬
cumbs to a murderous rage and bribes Aeolus,
the keeper of the winds, to unleash a furious tem¬
pest. The Trojan fleet is scattered and largely des¬
troyed; the few survivors are thrown up on the
African coast not far from Carthage.
Thanks to the intervention of Venus, anxious
to ensure the safety of her son, the sovereign of
those parts, the Phoenician queen, Dido, wel¬
comes the shipwrecked survivors with generous
hospitality. Taking advantage of these events in
a further attempt to detain Aeneas far from his
Italian goal, Juno, with the complicity of Venus,
thrusts the unfortunate Dido into the arms of her
Trojan guest.
Surrendering himself to the delights of a mad 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
passion, the Trojan hero forgets his predestined
mission for twelve long months. When Jupiter
imperiously takes him to task, however, he
remembers the duty fate has laid upon him and
leaves Carthage and the delights of love, setting
sail to the light of the funeral pyre on which the
despairing Dido has thrown herself.
A stop at Cumae gives Aeneas, guided by the
Sibyl, the opportunity to descend into the nether
regions where he encounters his father's shade,
who presents to him those who will play lead¬
ing roles in the accomplishment of Rome's fu¬
ture glory. Aeneas next arrives at the mouth of
the Tiber where the fulfilment of a prophecy con¬
firms that his long voyage is over. Recognizing
in him the foreigner his diviners have predicted
will marry his daughter Lavinia, Latinus, the king
of the region, welcomes Aeneas with open arms.
Juno, however, returns to the charge. Arous¬
ing Ihe jealousy of Turnus, a suitor of Lavinia
who cannot bear to find himself set aside in
favour of the newly-arrived stranger, she sets the
scene for a desperate struggle. A long series of
combats ensues in which the warriors of both
camps distinguish themselves by brilliant in¬
dividual exploits.
An epic that reinterpreted history
Finally, weary of the useless carnage, the two
sides make a solemn pact to leave the resolution
of their quarrel to the outcome of a single com¬
bat between Aeneas and Turnus. Aeneas, of
course, emerges victorious and at this point the
epic draws to a close. However, a number of
predictions inserted throughout the poem fore¬
shadow the future course of history that the epic
itself leaves untoldhow lulus, Aeneas' son, will
found the city of Alba from whence, 300 years
later, will come forth Romulus and Remus, the
twin founders of Rome.
The choice of such a subject offered many
advantages. In literary terms it demonstrates
Aeneas and the Shrine
of the Penates. " Detail
from the marble frieze
on the Altar of
the Augustan Peace, Rome
(1st century BC).
Virgil presents Dante
to Homer." Detail of a
fresco by the French painter
Eugene Delacroix
(1798-1863)
in the cupola of the library
of the Senate, Paris.
_ i'
r£rr l IL
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
fidelity to the Homeric tradition without being
a slavish imitation of it. Of the twelve books that
make up the epic, the first six, in which the hero's
perilous voyage from Troy to Italy is recounted,
conjure up in the reader's mind overtones of the
Odyssey; the last six, in which the war in Italy
incited by Juno is related, are an open evocation
of the Iliad.
Yet though the Homeric model was clearly
in the minds of both the poet and his readers, it
was used to tell a quite different tale. Further¬
more, while deliberately placing itself within the
context of Greek epic poetry, the Aeneid appears
to be an extension of it, since the action begins
at the precise point where it ends in Homer
with the capture and destruction of Troy.
Above all, the subject furnished political ad¬
vantages. The legend unfolded in the Aeneid
provided justification for Rome's complex rela¬
tionship with the Hellenic world, which involved
military and political domination coupled
with a certain cultural dependency. Representing
Rome as a resurgence of a Troy destroyed by the
Greeks gave the Roman conquest of Greece the
colouring of legitimate revenge. Virgil did not
miss the opportunity to put into the mouth of
Jupiter, in a lengthy prophecy addressed to Ve¬
nus, a proclamation that Rome would destroy the
most renowned cities of Greece, which were
responsible for the fall of Troy.
Yet Rome was indebted to Greece for this
justificatory legend, which has its roots in the
Iliad. By the end of the fourth century BC, at the
latest, Greek historians had given shape to the
myth of the arrival of Aeneas in Latium and of
his founding of Lavinium (today Pratica di Mare).
Thus began a subtle interplay between victor and
vanquished with the victory of Roman arms over
Greece finding justification in legendary tales
evolved in Greece itself.
JEAN-PAUL BRISSON,
of France, is professor
emeritus at the University
of Paris X, where he taught
Roman civilization and
literature. His published
works include Carthage ou
Rome ("Carthage or
Rome", 1973) and Virgile,
son temps et le nôtre ("Virgil,
his time and ours", 1980). 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Not least of the advantages of Virgil's epic
was that it glorified Augustus, the first Roman
emperor. Adopted by Julius Caesar, Augustus be¬
longed to the Julian family which claimed direct
descent from Aeneas. The claims were support¬
ed by a phonetic play, obligingly echoed by
Virgil, on the name of Aeneas' son. From the
original "Ilus" (which simply means Trojan),
"lulus", then "Iulius", were derived. The philo- .
logists of old were very partial to such
approximations.
The predictions inserted throughout the epic,
foretelling the future grandeur of the descendants
of Aeneas, naturally referred to the one who was
foreseen to be the most illustrious among them
the emperor Augustus. Contemporary readers
had no difficulty in making the link between the
great future foretold for the descendants of the
epic hero and the new regime of their own day.
By the same token, this new regime no longer
appeared to be the result of chance but the fulfil¬
ment of an eternal destiny.
The war that Aeneas was compelled to wage
to secure a firm foothold in Latium also provid¬
ed the opportunity to foretell the coming of the
multi-cultural empire over which Augustus was
to rule. For in his struggle against Turnus, Aeneas
was aided both by a small Greek community
established on the site of the future city of Rome
and by an Etruscan prince. This coalition of
peoples of such diverse culturesLatin, Hellenic
and Etruscanwas already, in itself, a foretaste
of the cultural situation of historic Rome.
Furthermore, at the close of the epic, Juno
renounces her vendetta and accepts the defeat of
her protege Turnus on condition that the newly-
arrived Trojans in turn abandon their customs
and their language and merge with the native
population to constitute a single people. The
Aeneid concludes less with the vision of a bloody
fight to the death than with the promise of the
harmonious fusion of different cultures within
the framework of a political union. Thus the Vir-
gilian epic made Augustus, the prestigious descen¬
dant the oracles were united in telling Aeneas he
would sire, the guarantor of that fusion and that
union.
26
A poem for all time
Though it may have been a piece of topical
propaganda, placed within a historically limited
context, the Aeneid is well worth reading today
because it was written by a very great poet, a
genius of such stature that the style and the events
of his epic narration are rich in connotations and
implications that go far beyond the author's im¬
mediate purposes.
The modern reader will be all trie more at
ease with Virgil in that the hero of his epic is not
cast in the monolithic mould of the Homeric
model. Robots tirelessly performing feats of arms,
Homer's heroes maintain virtually unchanging
patterns of behaviour and feelings throughout his
narrative and the reader leaves them at the end
of the epic as they were at the beginning. Virgil,
however, endows his hero with the full panoply
of human psychological complexity, with doubts,
uncertainties and moments of despair.
The Aeneid breaks new ground in epic poetry
by its use of the narrative technique to reveal the
inner feelings of Aeneas. Instead of being related
by an aloof third person, the dramatic episodes
of the destruction of Troy and the hero's wan¬
derings in search of the site on which his city is
destined to be rebuilt are recounted by an "I"
still pulsating with the excitement of the events
through which he has lived. From the start, a
kind of intimacy is established between the hero
and the reader, to whom he seems to speak per¬
sonally. And this initial intimacy is reflected
throughout the narrative.
By introducing the psychological factor,
Virgil avoids the snare of a simplistic dualism
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Aeneas tells Dido about
the disasters that have
befallen the city of Troy"
(1815). A painting by
Pierre Narcisse Guérin
(1774-1833).
Juno pleads with Aeolus
to unleash the winds
against Aeneas' boat. " A
painting by the Italian
artist Lucio Massari
(1569-1633).
between good and bad people. Dido and Turnus
are, it is true, formidable obstacles to the accom¬
plishment of Aeneas' mission and can be counted
among the negative characters in the epic. But it
would be too simple to leave it at that and Virgil
succeeds in portraying them with sufficient com¬
plexity to make them seem more worthy of com¬
passion than of enmity. His lines on Dido's tragic
suicide are among the most sensitive ever writ¬
ten by a poet of Antiquity and even today it is
impossible to read them without being profound¬
ly moved.
Finally, what makes the Aeneid an epic apart
is its initiatory connotations. The difficulties the
hero has to face to accomplish his mission are a
poetic transposition of the classic ordeals of an
initiation ceremony. Aeneas comes through these
ordeals not only as the victor but as a man trans¬
formed. The Aeneas who finally settles in Latium
is a new man, destined for a new life.
The rites and mysteries of the religions of An¬
tiquity may be of little interest to the modern
reader, but no-one can remain unmoved by this
lesson in self-transcendence, by this splendid ex¬
ample of a mastered fate. 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
%u
l$ ray^gts' i/ ,*
tó^v*
*
^ ,
iri '
3B«
PH
':- y
»P
Haaf afiittiaffli
i
1
Zj-. ZS -S » a/ .
,¿,c^-/ k¿**~r%<J mó&u&A ¥áL*&4i%..,,_ ^ , p^í^^> ^vr-^4
iiftffi.i ty/^é-S' $vá¿sx
mmmm
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Written almost a thousand years ago, The Epic of the
Kings tells the story of the Iranian people from the
time of the world's creation. National epic, landmark
in world literature and a profound expression of the
Iranian soul, Ferdowsi's masterpiece is still read and
recited throughout Iran.
I
The Epic
of the Kings
BY NAHAL TADJADOD
Ferdowsi and the three poets
of the court of Ghazni, the
ancient capital of the powerful
empire of the Ghaznevids, in
what is now Afghanistan.
I he first part of Ferdowsi's
poem The Epic of the Kings
describes how Jamshid, king of
Iran, taught men how to make
weapons of war, to spin and
weave, and to build houses
and ships. Left, a 17th-century
miniature showing Jamshid
giving a lesson in
craftsmanship.
N a square in Teheran, the capital of Iran, there
is a statue of Ferdowsi: the poet holds his Epic
ofthe Kings (Shah-nama) in his hand and gazes at
the peaks of the Alborz mountains. When I was
young, my parents often took me to this place
and while they looked on attentively I recited
these lines by Ferdowsi:
I have toiled painfully these thirty years. I have
restored Iran to life by my verse.
Henceforth I cannot die; for I live, having
broadcast the seeds of my verses.
These words were engraved in the memory
of the child I was then and I know that they have
shaped my innermost identity. There is nothing
astonishing in that. For almost a thousand years
Ferdowsi's poem has been read, recited and
copied in Iran. Even today it is recited in the cafés.
Early on it became our national epic.
Why has it always been so popular? Not
because of the originality of its subjectthe
history of ancient Iran from the time of its first
mythical king to the last sovereign of the Sassanid
dynasty in the seventh century ADnor because
of the novelty of its content. "What I will say,
all have already told," Ferdowsi claimed. The
poet transmitted; he invented nothing. He drew
on old oral traditions and on ancient texts such
as the Avesta, a holy book of the eighth century
BC, or reworked somewhat earlier tales on the
same theme.
The first monument
of Persian literature
This immense poem of 50,000 couplets appeared
in the tenth century, at a key moment in the
history of Iranian culture. Since the fall of the
Sassanids, the literary language of Iran had been
Arabic. Middle Persian, the main vehicle of
Sassanid civilization, was disappearing. At this
moment, a young literature in an Iranian idiom-
Persianemerged in the east. Ferdowsi's poem
would be its first masterpiece.
The Epic of the Kings does not describe the
deeds of a single hero or king nor even a long
adventure. It begins with the creation of the
world and relates the history of fifty reigns on
three distinct planes: the mythical, the epic and
the historical.
The first part relates civilizing myths. The
Pishdadians, the "first created", teach men to
clothe themselves, to work metal, to master fire,
to tame animals and to organize themselves in
society. After ruling for 700 years, King Jamshid,
succumbing to pride, has to yield his throne to
a demoniac creature, the tyrant Zahhak who will
rule for a thousand years. His malign power will
finally be conquered by the justice-loving
Faridun. These heroes, who personify the conflict
between the forces of darkness and light,
constitute a religious theme which is typically
Iranian.
The second, longest and most truly epic part 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
of the poem evokes the reign of the Kaianid kings.
Here, in the centrepiece of the poem, light has
triumphed. Rostam is the champion of all the
heroes who live at the Kaianid court. Prodigious¬
ly strong, loyal to his king and faithful to his
country, he is the terror of the enemy. This peri¬
od is marked by interminable wars against Turan,
a central Asian country whose ruler Afrasiyab is
the sworn enemy of Iran.
In the final part, the poet presents a number
of historical figures but in a rather fantastic light.
He gives a notable account of the conquest of
Alexander the Great (Sekandar), based on the
Alexander legend of the Orient. The ending, even
closer to history, tells of the exploits of the Sas¬
sanid rulers until the end of the dynasty.
Faridun and Zahhak:
the just man and the tyrant
The story of Zahhak the tyrant, told in the first
and most brilliant part of the poem, extols the
sufferings of a martyred people.
The courageous but wayward son of King
Mardas, Zahhak is led astray by Eblis, the devil.
After making a pact with Eblis, Zahhak usurps
the throne. Revealing himself to the king in var¬
ious forms, the devil extends his power further
each day. One day Eblis presents himself in the
guise of a cook. "The diet is not varied," he says,
"for flesh is not eaten," and he wishes Zahhak
to eat all kinds of viands, both birds and
quadrupeds. When the devil, who has gained Zah-
30
Sekandar (Alexander the
Great) is seen visiting the
emperor of China in this
15th-century miniature
illustrating an incident
from The Epic of the
Kings.
NAHAL TADJADOD,
Iranian Sinologist, is the
author of a doctoral thesis
on the influence of
Buddhism on Chinese
Manichaeism which will be
published shortly by
Editions du Cerf, Paris. She
is currently participating in
Unesco's Silk Roads Project.
hak's confidence, embraces him, a black serpent
thrusts its head out of each of the tyrant's shoul¬
ders. Whenever he cuts them off they sprout
anew like two branches of a tree. Then Eblis ap¬
pears again, this time disguised as a physician, and
proposes as a remedy that Zahhak should eat two
human brains each day.
Thus for a thousand years the demons cause
evil to reign and no one dares talk openly of good.
But one night Zahhak dreams that he is laid low
by a young prince who strikes him with a bull-
headed mace and drags him in chains to Mount
Damavand. Plunged in darkness, the world was
as black as a raven's wing. The tyrant consults
the Mubads, the Zoroastrian priests, who read the
stars and tell him that his vanquisher, who is not
yet born, will be called Faridun. "He will hate
you, for his father will die at your hand and you
will also kill the cow that will serve him as nurse.
To avenge the cow he will take up the bull-headed
mace."
Mad with anxiety, the king hunts everywhere
for traces of Faridun. The blessed child is born
at the same time as the most marvellous of cows.
He is entrusted by his mother to the keeper of
the park where the nurse-cow lives, and is
nourished with her milk. One day Zahhak hears
of the park and the cow, kills the fabulous animal
and rushes to Faridun's house. He finds no one
there. Overcome with fear, Faridun's mother has
taken her son to Mount Alborz.
At the age of sixteen Faridun learns of his ori¬
gins from his mother and decides to fight the
tyrant. In anguish Zahhak convokes all the elders
of the land to seek their support. "I desire you
to subscribe to a proclamation on my behalf that
as commander in chief I have sown no seed but
that of uprightness. ..and that I would never fail
to maintain justice." All consent except one man,
Kava the Blacksmith, who rises in protest. "I am
Kava, seeking for justice. Most of the wrong done
to me comes from yourself. It is you who cons¬
tantly thrust the lancet into my heart. Why do
you inflict harm on my children? I had eighteen
alive in the world, and now only one remains."
Overcome with astonishment and fear, Zahhak
restores the man's remaining son to him and asks
him in exchange to add his testimony to the
proclamation. Kava reads the proclamation, tears
it into pieces, and tramples them underfoot.
Kava leaves the palace and the people crowd
around him. Fastening a blacksmith's leather
apron to a spearhead, he calls on the people to
free themselves from the tyrant's yoke. Followed
by a multitude of the stout-hearted, Kava the
liberator sets out in search of Faridun, who agrees
to lead the popular rising. The people of the city
and the army mass before the palace, whose
guards dare not resist. Faridun rides into the
palace without striking a blow and seizes the royal
crown. Attacked by Zahhak, the young prince
shatters Zahhak's helmet with his bull-headed
mace. At that instant the angel Sorush appears
and stops Faridun killing Zahhak. "Do not strike
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
^C3''
VtVV
him down," he says. "His time has not yet come.
Tie him securely inside the mountain." Faridun
then drives the tyrant into the mountains and
wishes to strike off his head, but the angel Sorush
appears again and tells him to leave the captive
in fetters on Mount Damavand to endure an eter¬
nal agony.
A poet of human grandeur
In the person of Faridun, an era of enlightenment
and justice succeeds a long period of obscurity
and tyranny. Here Ferdowsi returns to pre-
Islamic traditions; he takes this idea of an eternal
combat between good and evil from Zoroastrian
eschatology. The interminable wars between Iran
and Turan are the reflection of this. But Ferdowsi
does not profess a naive dualism. He shows that
these two principles coexist in everyone: human
beings can do good as well as spread evil.
Thus, after a thousand years of tyranny, light
and good seem to triumph: the new king, man¬
dated by heaven, serves his people devotedly. But
evil persists, it has not ceased to exist. This is what
the angel means when he twice prevents the
tyrant from being put to death. Zahhak is final¬
ly fettered on the summit of Mount Alborz as
if to show by his existence that the victory of
good over evil has not yet been won.
Ferdowsi bases his poem on the implacable
force of destiny. This quintessentially epic theme
echoes the sense of fatality which is so deeply an¬
chored in the Iranian soul. And yet his charac¬
ters are still men, torn and tortured by doubt and
sensitive to the misfortunes of the age. They are
to be pitied rather than condemned. Zahhak, the
bloody tyrant, the symbol of cruelty, does not
act freely; he has, after all, sold his soul to the
devil. He is merely an instrument. As a great trag¬
ic epic poet, Ferdowsi thus creates terrible situa¬
tions in which a man is led to kill his brother,
or a father kills his son. Links of kinship add gran¬
deur and resonance to the combat waged by the
individual against higher forces.
The Epic of the Kings is still a living epic for
Iranians because it is profoundly in tune with the
Iranian soul. The Iranian peasant, even if he can
neither read nor write, responds to the exploits
of Rostam, the hero par excellence, and weeps
to think of his sufferings when he is compelled
to kill his own son to defend his country.
Neither good nor ill will lastfor ever: thefinest
thing is to leave good deeds to be remembered by.
Ferdowsi's voice still speaks to us across the
ages.
Quotations from the Shah-nama in this article are taken from
the translation by Reuben Levy which was published as The
Epic ofthe Kings by Routledge & Kegan Paul (London, 1967)
and features in the Unesco Collection of Representative
Works. Editor
Above, an episode from
The Epic of the Kings in
which the great folk hero
Rostam slays the dragon
with the help of his valiant
horse Rakhsh. (15th-century
miniature.)
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
llya the invincible
BY HELENE YVERT-JALU
I
32
,N a famous painting by Viktor Vasnetsov, three
valiant knights, breastplated and helmeted,
mounted on powerful chargers, are shown guard¬
ing Russian soil against the enemy. Their names
are llya of Murom, Dobrynia Nikitich and
Aliosha Popovich, and they are the heroes of
Russian byliny or epic poems.
The byliny tradition may go back to the end
of the tenth century. In the large, bright hall of
Prince Vladimir's palace at Kiev, minstrels accom¬
panying themselves on the gusli, a kind of zither,
sang of the extraordinary exploits of bogatyrs (gal¬
lant warriors), while cup-bearers filled the boyars'
and other noblemen's glasses with "a blend of
herbal wine and unchanging honey".
Heroes that live on
Since those times, byliny have been transmitted
orally from generation to generation, an uninter¬
rupted river of poetry in which many historical,
social and geographical currents are mingled.
At the beginning of the twentieth century in
the Arkhangelsk and Lake Onega regions of
northern Russia, rustic bards known as skaziteli
still related these heroic deeds. Usually men of
a ripe old age, they used a special technique to
recount their stories, keeping up a slow rhythm
of three or four beats to the bar, which brought
a majestic grandeur to the old songs. Woodcut¬
ters, fishermen and hunters would gather round,
listening attentively.
Lovers of folk traditions have collected ex¬
amples of this national treasure of historic songs.
In the eighteenth century an Englishman, Richard
James, was the first to transcribe some of them.
Fuller collections which appeared in the follow¬
ing century met with tremendous success, and in¬
fluenced literature (Pushkin, Lermontov, Gogol),
music (Mussorgsky, Rimsky-Korsakov, Borodin),
painting (Vasnetsov, Repin, Vrubel) and films
such as Eisenstein's Alexander Nevsky. The
popularity of these gallant warriors of legend has
even influenced the spoken language. In Russian
today, the word bogatyr designates a man of
llya ofMurom and Soloveï
the Brigand. A 19th-century
example of the Russian folk
art known as lubok.
powerful stature or someone of exceptional
vigour. These epic heroes, mythical figures in the
national consciousness, have scarcely changed
down the ages. Above all, they have kept the pro¬
digious strength which enables them "to crush
ten adversaries with one blow". Let us follow the
exploits of llya of Murom, perhaps the most
popular hero of the Kiev byliny cycle.
llya, a peasant's son, has been paralysed for
thirty years (thirty-three in some versions), when
one day three pilgrims pay him a visit. Twice they
ask him to rise and offer them food and drink.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Even the most terrifying monsters quail before
lion-hearted llya ofMurom. This redoubtable
hero of ancient Russia is still a much-loved
figure ofpopular mythology.
»-TÎV7V f-.'J-JJ*'^
A -Mil!
"Alas," the cripple replies, "I can move neither
arms nor legs." At the third demand, llya
miraculously manages to stand up and walk. He
offers a cup of wine to his guests, who ask him
to drink of it too. He has barely tasted it when
he feels within himself a Herculean strength. The
three men then predict that llya will be a great
warrior and that he will not die in combat, and
they disappear. Thus the crippled llya suddenly
becomes an invincible titan.
Like any Russian peasant of the Middle Ages,
llya first uses his power to clear the surrounding
forest. In the twinkling of an eye, he uproots all
the oaks and hurls so many of them into the
Dnieper that the course of the powerful river is
dammed. He then heads for Kiev to defend Holy
Russia, which is constantly under threat.
In order to procure a mount for himself, llya
follows the instructions of the mysterious pil¬
grims. When he meets up with a peasant leading
a small, shaggy stallion by the bridle, he immedi¬
ately buys it. Then he walks the animal three
times through the morning dew. It turns into a
marvellous steed which "with each stride covers 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
llya ofMurom (centre),
Dobrynia Nikitich (left)
and Aliosha Popovich
(right), the three most
popular knightly heroes or
bogatyrs ofRussian epic
poetry. Painting by Viktor
Vasnetsov (1848-1926).
34
Illustrations from llya of
Murom and the Tsar
Kalin, a cartoon slide
show. Above, the terrible
Tsar Kalin; below,
Vladimir's daughter, the
kind princess.
a full verst (1.06 kilometres), leaping from hill to
hill, over rivers, lakes and forests". Even better,
it can speak and warn its master of imminent
danger.
Before he reaches Kiev, Bya engages in several
combats, including a confrontation with Solov-
eï the Brigand. This "nightingale" (soloveï) is a
strange and terrifying bird which has built himself
a nest in the branches of seven oak trees at a cross¬
roads in the forest. The bird's song bends the lar¬
gest trees tó the ground and strikes humans stone
dead. Not a whit dismayed by this terrible sound,
llya draws his bow and pierces Soloveï's right eye
with an arrow. Soloveï falls from the nest and
llya chains him to his stirrup. The monster's three
daughters, perched in their father's nest, send
their mates to attack llya. Soloveï asks them to
negotiate a ransom for him instead. But their ef¬
forts are in vain, as llya disinterestedly refuses the
precious gifts offered to him.
With his prisoner in tow he arrives at the
prince's palace in Kiev, where Vladimir questions
him. The bogatyr introduces himself and displays
his captive. Vladimir invites Soloveï the Brigand
to sing, but the monster will only obey llya.
Thereupon llya repeats the request, with the
proviso that the bird must sing only half as loudly
as usual, in order to spare the prince and his
courtiers. Soloveï mischievously sings as loudly
as he can, sowing death and destruction. Vladimir
is saved by the sable-lined coat with which he has
covered his head. As a punishment for this act
of disobedience llya cuts off the Brigand's head:
"Thus Soloveï will no longer fill mothers' and
fathers' eyes with tears or make widows of young
women, and will cease to turn little children into
orphans."
llya is appointed ataman, or chief of the
Prince of Kiev's bogatyrs, and from then on
guards the gates of the capital. One day he is
challenged by a giantess armed with an immense
club. She is a polenitsa, a wild beast that roams
the steppe. llya emerges victorious from the ter¬
rible fight that ensues. On discovering that the
giantess is his own daughter, however, he spares
her life. But to avenge her mother, whom llya
has deserted, she goes into his tent while he is
sleeping and with all her might plunges a hunt¬
ing spear into his chest. This would have been
the end of llya, but the spear strikes the cross
weighing a pud-and-a-half {zpud is over 16 kilos),
that he always wears. Awakened by the noise of
metal on metal, llya opens his eyes and tears the
treacherous girl to shreds.
The homeland before the prince
The enemies which have to be fought, in¬
discriminately referred to as Tatars, are always
depicted as caricatures. Idolishche the Pagan is
"two sagens high and one wide" (a sagen is 2.13
metres). "His head is like an enormous vat, and
his eyes are mugs of beer, and the nose on his
face is a cubit's length."
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
fe
Left, A Valiant Knight,
by the Russian artist
Mikhail Vrubel (1856-1910).
:
1$ -V- Z .
HPÜ
Facing the massed ranks of enemy armies
"all black, like black crows"the prince's knights
are often terror-stricken. llya alone proves him¬
self to be a fervent and loyal defender of the
homeland. Despite tempting offers from the ene¬
my, he steadfastly refuses to leave the prince's
service. He nonetheless has good reasons for do¬
ing so, as Vladimir, who bears little resemblance
to the historical figure of the same name, often
rewards the loyal services of his bogatyrs with
ingratitude.
One day, after a quarrel with llya, the angry
Vladimir has him thrown into a deep cellar with
the order to let him starve to death. The other
bogatyrs, indignant over this unjust treatment,
desert the prince's court. Three years go by. Ka¬
lin, the tsar, turns the situation to his advantage
and attacks Kiev with a formidable army.
Vladimir grows afraid and his daughter advises
him to go and set llya free. To his great surprise,
the prince discovers that llya is still alive. The
young princess has dug an underground passage
leading to the dungeon, and each day has brought
the prisoner sweetmeats. Vladimir throws him¬
self at the hero's feet and begs him to save Kiev,
llya agrees to fight "not for the prince, but for
the churches of the Virgin, for Holy Russia, and
for the widows and orphans".
One of Ilya's most characteristic traits is re¬
vealed in this episode: he serves the Russian land,
not an occasionally despotic sovereign. This cou¬
rageous and unselfish peasant with no false pride
unhesitatingly speaks his mind when he sees the
prince abuse his authority. When he is not an¬
gered or engaged in Homeric combat, he is a
good-natured fellow who likes a joke. llya, the
gallant knight, has become a kind of national
hero.
- ii'iiw
Aliosha Popovich, the wily
companion in arms of llya
ofMurom. This hand-
coloured engraving dates
from the 18th century.
HELENE YVERT-JALU,
of France, is a lecturer at
the University of Paris I.
She is the author of a
number of studies on social
and cultural questions in
the Soviet Union. 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
A unique source of contemporary
information about Genghis Khan
and the empire he founded, the
Mongolian national epic blends
folklore and legend with a vivid
account of steppe society in the
twelfth and thirteenth centuries.
The Secret History
of the Mongols
BY SHAGDARYN BIRA
Alan-qua, the legendary
mother of the clan of
Genghis Khan.
36
KJpposite page, Genghis
Khan is shown receiving
distinguished visitors in this
Persian miniature
illustrating Rashid al-Din 's
Jami at-tawarikh, an
important source for
Mongolian history.
JL HE Secret History of the Mongols (Mongyol-un
ni'uca tobca'an) is the earliest surviving literary
monument of the Mongolian people. Its author
is unknown, ?nd although it is widely thought
to have been written in 1240, both its original
title and the exact date of its composition are still
matters for debate.
What is beyond doubt is the fact that The
Secret History is a historical and literary document
of major importance. Not only does it recount
the genealogy of the early Mongol khans and the
life and times of Genghis Khan, founder of a uni¬
fied Mongol state, it also paints a vivid and ac¬
curate picture of the nomadic Mongol way of life
and provides rich source material for an under¬
standing of Mongol society in the twelfth and
thirteenth centuries.
Soviet Academician Boris Vladimirtsov has
described The Secret History as a "history-
chronicle" retold in epic style and "impregnat¬
ed with the aroma of the steppe". A British scho¬
lar, David Morgan, has pointed out that whatever
hesitations historians may feel about the work
as a strictly accurate record of historical events,
there can be no doubt that it provides a unique
and authoritative insight into the way of life, pat¬
terns of thought and beliefs of the thirteenth-
century Mongols.
Genghis Khan, the warrior
who united the Mongol tribes
The Secret History may be divided into three
partsa genealogy of the ancestors of Genghis
Khan, stories about the life of Genghis Khan, and
a short section on his son and successor Ogödei.
The first part records the legendary history
of Mongolia as reconstructed from very ancient
oral traditionsmyths and legends, stories and ac¬
counts of historical events. It opens with the
legend that the forefather of the Mongolian peo¬
ple was "a bluish wolf which was born having
[his] destiny from Heaven above", whose "spouse
was a fallow doe".1 The image of the wolf ap¬
pears in the mythology of many Eurasian peo¬
ples, closely connected with ancestor cults of the
tribal chief or the founder of a clan.
The following well-documented genealogy of
the Mongol khans exalts the glory of the "Golden
Horde" and is the genealogical basis for studies
of the early history of the Mongolian people.
The main theme is developed in the second
part of the epic, in which legend and myth give
way to more reliable historical data. Although
the narrative continues in the epic style, it begins
to assume the characteristics of a chronicle. An
ancient Eastern system of chronology, based on a
twelve-year animal cycle, is used to date events in
the history of the numerous Mongolian tribes and
their unification into a single state by Genghis
Khan, the central figure of the story.
Genghis Khan is portrayed not only as a
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
KSKáMBH
SsmRgt
_ltMH
MÊ
SUggjK
laCKaa^fi
363
'"' . "î 'i
; ,
tKÙ
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38
legendary hero and warrior, the embodiment of
the "steppe aristocracy", but also as a great po¬
litical figure and statesman who decided by his
"iron will" to put an end to the discord among
the Mongol tribes, where anarchy prevailed:
The Heaven with stars
Was turning round about.
The many peoples were at strife.
Not entering into their beds,
They were spoiling one another.
The earth with crust
Was turning backward and forward.
The whole nation was at strife.
Although the main hero of the story is
Genghis Khan, one of the greatest conquerors in
world history, the author does not seem to at¬
tach great significance to his military campaigns
against other countries, as if he had deliberately
ignored that aspect of Genghis' career. On the
other hand, he constantly stresses to readers and
Kjenghis Khan. Painting
on silk of the Yuan period
(13th-14th centuries).
listeners the benefits and privileges to be enjoyed
within a centralized Mongolian state.
The third, much shorter, part of The Secret
History summarizes the reign of Ogödei
(1228-1241), the second great khan of Mongolia.
It is thought to be a later addition to the main
text.
The cult of Light
A work of great literary merit, The Secret Histo¬
ry is a unique phenomenon in the history of
nomadic peoples. It has been compared to monu¬
ments of world literature such as Homer's Iliad
and Odyssey, Alexander Romance literature, the
French Chanson de Roland, and the Russian Lay
of Igor's Campaign.
The Mongolian people lived at a crossroads
of world communications and it would be a mis¬
take to assume that such an epic could have been
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
created by them in isolation from other civiliza¬
tions. The script in which it was written had its
origins in Phoenician, Aramaic and Sogdian sys¬
tems of writing. Close examination of the text
reveals traces of religious and mythological con¬
cepts of ancient Oriental peoples, especially the
influence of the Zoroastrian-Manichaean cult of
Light. This cult is reflected in the Mongolian
legend of the immaculate conception of Alan-qua,
the foremother of Genghis Khan's clan, by the
"Father-Light". Alan-qua recounts her experience
in the epic:
Every night, a bright yellow man entered by
the light of the hole at the top or [by thai] of the
door top ofthe tent and rubbed my belly. His light
was wont to sink into my belly. When he went out,
like a yellow dog he was wont to crawl out by the
beams of the sun or moon.
Scholars have shown that some of the tales in
The Secret History are of very ancient origin and
have a close affinity with Central Asian and Eu¬
rasian legends. The following tale of the five
arrow-shafts tied into a bundle, for example,
recalls a story that was current among ancient Ira¬
nian peoples, particularly the Scythians:
One day, in the spring, while boiling the dried
[flesh of] a sheep, making these herfive sons.. .to sit
in a row, she gave unto each [of them] a single ar¬
row shaft, saying "Break [h\'"...each [ofthem] brake
and cast away. Again, she boundfive arrow shafts
together in a bundle and gave [them unto them],
saying "Break [them]!"Allfive, holding, every per¬
son, the five arrow shafts bound in a bundle, were
in turn not able to break...
She said, 'Ye, myfive sons, were born ofan only
belly. If, like the five arrow shafts ofa little while
ago, ye be each alone, like those single arrow shafts,
[ye] will each [ofyou] easily be broken by any one.
If together [ye] be of one purpose like those arrow
shafts bound in a bundle, how will ye easily be
[broken] by any one?"
Plutarch tells how the Scythian king Skilur
(second to first century BC) gathered all his sons
around him before his death and asked each of
them to break a bundle of darts. When they re¬
fused, the king broke the darts one by one, with
the admonition that, united, his sons would be
invincible.
\jenghis Khan (left) and
Ogödei, his son and
successor.
SHAGDARYN BIRA,
Mongolian historian, is a
member of his country's
Academy of Sciences. He
has published many studies
on the history and culture
of medieval Mongolia,
including a book on
Mongolian historiography
from the 13th to the 17th
centuries which has been
translated into Russian and
Chinese.
A sourcebook
for Oriental historians
Ever since it was written, The Secret History has
been known throughout the Orient, and for 750
years it has been one of the main sources for the
history of other countries of Central Asia as well
as Mongolia. It has been used as a source in fun¬
damental historical works of the Orient such as
fami at-tawarikh, the universal history compiled
by the Persian author Rashid al-Din (1247-1318),
and the Yuan shih ("History of the Yuan Dy¬
nasty"), the famous Chinese chronicle of the
Mongol empire in China (thirteenth to four¬
teenth century).
As a result of Rashid al-Din's work, most of
the contemporary information recorded in The
Secret History has been retold and reinterpreted
in many important historical writings of Central
Asian countries, including those of the Mughal
empire in India.
The Akbarnama, the chronicle of the em¬
peror Akbar and his ancestors written by the
great Mughal historian Abu-1-Fazl (1551-1602),
gives a detailed version of the Alan-qua story
which compares Alan-qua with the Virgin Mary,
raises her to the rank of Mother of God, and
urges: "If you listen to the tale of Mary, believe
the same of Alanguwa (Alan-qua)".2 Abu-1-Fazl
also does his best to prove that Akbar was
descended from the legendary foremother of the
Mongols.
The Secret History has also been esteemed in
China as a valuable source for the history of the
Mongolian people, and fourteenth-century
Chinese bibliophiles actually helped to preserve
the epic for posterity by transcribing into Chinese
characters the original Mongol text, which has
not survived, and by making verbatim and
abridged translations. In 1866, a first Russian
translation of The Secret History was made from
the abridged Chinese version, and since then the
Mongolian masterpiece has become available to
the international academic community.
1. Quotations from The Secret History ofthe Mongols, Vol. I, trans¬
lated into English and edited by Francis W. Cleaves. Harvard
University Press, 1982.
2. From The Akbarnama o/Ahu-l-FazI, translated into English by
H. Beveridge, Delhi, 1972. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The Mahàvamsa is a verse
chronicle which paints a colourful
fresco of Sri Lanka's early history.
Ever since it was written in the
sixth century by a Buddhist monk,
it has been periodically updated.
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
fc The Mahàvamsa,
Sri Lanka's #
non-stop epic
Left, a monk and his
pupil at Anuradhapura, Sri
Lanka. Below, frieze on the
stupa at Sanchi, India,
depicts worshippers around
the Bodhi-tree under which
the Buddha was sitting
when Enlightenment came
to him.
BY ANANDA W. P. GURUGE
IN the last twelve years a group of Sri Lankan
historians and linguists have been meeting regu¬
larly in Colombo to write their nation's histo¬
ry. They are engaged on a remarkable project,
for the history is being written in verse and in
Pali, a classical Indo-Aryan language which is
hardly used today except by the Buddhist clergy
and a small circle of eminent international
scholars.
The historians are bringing up to date Sri
Lanka's national epic poem, the Mahàvamsa or
"Great Chronicle", whose first thirty-seven chap¬
ters in nearly 3,000 Pali verses were composed
by a Buddhist scholar-monk named Mahanama
in the sixth century AD. Publication of the up¬
dated history is awaited with great interest in
Sri Lanka.
The origins of the Mahàvamsa can be traced
at least as far back as the fourth century BC. The
Aryan settlers who had migrated to Sri Lanka
from the Indus and Ganges basins of the Indian
sub-continent possessed an exceedingly keen
historical sense. They kept records of their ex¬
ploits and experiences not merely as ballads or
sagas of folk or literary interest but more syste¬
matically, as historical accounts seeking to assert
their cultural identity as a new nation in a new
land.
Monks who chronicled
the exploits of heroes
The dynastic history of at least two centuries was
already thus recorded before Buddhism was in¬
troduced in the third century BC. With the ad¬
vent of Buddhist monks, Sri Lanka was assured
of the continuing services of reliable and dedicat¬
ed historiographers and custodians of its histori¬
cal tradition.
Buddhism ushered in several centuries of in¬
tense literary activity. While the Tripitaka, the
Buddhist Canon, was preserved in Pali (a liter¬
ary form of the vernacular which the Buddha
used in his discourses), the commentaries élucidât- 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
ing it were produced locally in Sinhala. The
historical sections, known as Sihala-Atthakatha-
Mahàvamsa ("The Great Chronicle of the Sinha¬
la Commentary"), were periodically updated and
comprised information drawn from a number of
sources: early accounts, with mythical overtones,
of waves of Aryan migrations; a detailed and pos¬
sibly documented monastic tradition relating to
crucial events in the history of Buddhism; royal
records of secular and religious achievements in
the form of registers of meritorious deeds accom¬
plished for the benefit of the Buddhist faith on
the one hand, and the general public on the other;
panegyrics and heroic ballads which court poets
and wandering minstrels had produced to enter¬
tain royalty and edify the population.
In keeping with the ancient Indian tradition,
Sri Lanka recognized three categories of heroes:
Dharmavira (heroes of righteousness), Danavira
(heroes of liberality) and Yuddhavira (military
heroes). Many heroes from each category had dis¬
tinguished themselves in the history of the island,
and tales about them had become part of the liter¬
ary heritage.
An imperfect attempt to present this materi¬
al entirely in Pali verse was made in the fourth
century AD in an epic poem known as the
Dipavamsa ("Island Chronicle") whose author is
unknown. The imperfections of the Dipavamsa,
which include grammatical, stylistic and linguis¬
tic inelegance, result from the fact that Pali had
not yet become a literary language and from the
technical problems involved in organizing materi¬
al from different sources. Two centuries later, Ma-
hanama overcame these difficulties and his
Mahàvamsa became the epic poem par excellence
of Sri Lanka.
The main literary value of the Mahàvamsa lies
in its effective use of Pali verse to narrate the his¬
tory of the nation in a straightforward style, with
the expressed purpose of "generating the serene
joy and emotion of the pious".
Excluding the introductory chapters on
Buddhist traditions and history, the Mahàvamsa
is organized as three epics in one:
chapters six to ten: the Vijaya-
Pandukabhaya Epic on the founding and consoli¬
dation of the Sinhala kingdom in Sri Lanka;
chapters eleven to twenty: the
Devanampiyatissa-Mahinda Epic, which tells of the
introduction of Buddhism to Sri Lanka and its
consolidation as the state religion;
chapters twenty-two to thirty-two: the
1 he temple at
Anuradhapura, ancient
capital of the Sri Lankan
kingdom of the same name.
1 ilgrimage to Mount
Mihintale, Sri Lanka.
Legend has it that
Mahinda, son of the Indian
emperor Asoka, alighted on
the mountain around 250
BC when he came to
preach Buddhism
in Sri Lanka.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
ANANDA W.P. GURUGÉ
is Sri Lanka's ambassador to
France and permanent
delegate to Unesco, where he
is a member of the Executive
Board. He is a specialist in
Asian and Buddhist cultures
on which he has written
several books, including The
Mahàvamsa: A New
Annotated Translation with
Prolegomena.
Dutthagamani-Abhaya Epic about the national
hero of the second century BC who reunified the
kingdom by liberating the regions under foreign
domination and left a lasting heritage of magnifi¬
cent monuments to the glory of Buddhism.
Instead of singling out these themes for iso¬
lated treatment, the historian in Mahanama
favoured a chronological narrative. Thus the
Mahàvamsa became a chronicle. The format and
style of the connecting chapters (i.e. chapters
twenty-one and thirty-three to thirty-seven) and
especially the last five chapters provided the
prototype for all later prolongations of the
Mahàvamsa.
25 centuries of written history
Including the current project described above,
there have been as many as seven efforts since the
thirteenth century to update the chronicle. As a
result, Sri Lanka enjoys the distinction of being
perhaps the only modern nation to have main¬
tained an unbroken written history over twenty-
five centuries. What makes this record exception¬
al is that its authenticity has been substantially
established by archaeological, epigraphical and
numismatic evidence and from external literary
sources.
Notable though it is for literary merit and
historical authenticity, the Mahàvamsa is essen¬
tially religious in character. The narration of the
good and evil deeds of kings and other historical
figures seems exclusively intended to draw a
moral. Most chapters end with either an admo¬
nition or a reminder of a basic doctrine of Budd¬
hism. The doctrines emphasized relate to
impermanence, wholesome and unwholesome ac¬
tion, detachment and the proper use of wealth
and power. True to his didactic role, Mahanama
displays an admirable degree of impartiality and
objectivity in assessing the careers and contribu¬
tions of various rulers, including usurpers and
invaders.
Notwithstanding the seriousness of purpose
that is shown in recording the eventful history
of a colourful people, the Mahàvamsa abounds in
"human interest" episodes relating to a wide spec¬
trum of human types. It reflects the noble and
the mean, the wisdom and the foibles, the sub¬
lime and the ridiculous which characterize hu¬
man behaviour at all times and in all societies.
The fact that the epic deals with real people and
not with fictional or depersonalized types adds
to the insights it provides into the strengths and
weaknesses of humankind.
Reconstructing the Indian past
The Mahàvamsa came to the attention of the in¬
ternational academic community in 1826 when
the Pali and Buddhist scholar Eugène Burnouf
translated it into French. His translation was not
published, however, as George Tumour, an En¬
glish civil servant resident in Sri Lanka, was in
the process of publishing the original Pali text
with an English translation. The Mahàvamsa was
to be of considerable value in reconstructing the
ancient history of India.
In the 1830s, the English Indologist James
Prinsep, the Champollion of Indian epigraphy,
deciphered the ancient Brahmi script and began
to read the edicts and pillar inscriptions of an im¬
pressive historical figure whose name appeared
in the inscriptions as "Devanapiya Piyadasi". No
Indian literary record or historical tradition shed
light on a ruler with such a name. Knowing that
the Sinhalas of Sri Lanka had a well-developed
historical sense, Tumour believed that their an¬
cient literary works could help epigraphists and
archaeologists. As he suspected, the Mahàvamsa
established beyond any doubt that Devanapiya
Piyadasi was Asoka, the third emperor of the
Mauryan dynasty, of whom the epic gives a full
account as the foremost patron of Buddhism.
Background information provided by the
Mahàvamsa, in addition to confirming Prinsep's
readings of the inscriptions, proved to be vitally
important for the pioneering research and discov¬
eries of archaeologists in India. On the basis of
evidence from the Sri Lankan epic alone, the
British archaeologist Alexander Cunningham was
able to identify the names and ascertain the sig¬
nificance of a number of holy persons whose rel¬
ics were enshrined by the emperor Asoka in the
stupas at Sanchi and Sonari in central India. The
Mahàvamsa and its predecessor the Dipavamsa
contained detailed information about the mission¬
aries sent to propagate Buddhism in Sri Lanka and
elsewhere under Asoka's patronage. When iden¬
tifying the events represented in the sculptured
gateways of Sanchi, the German art historian
Albert Grünwedel used the Mahàvamsa's account
of how Asoka sent to Sri Lanka a sapling of the
Bodhi-tree under which the Buddha was sitting
when Enlightenment came to him.
Last but not least, the Mahàvamsa has been
indispensable to the archaeologists and historians
of Sri Lanka for whom it has provided the
chronological framework into which their discov¬
eries can be fitted. Many monuments and reser¬
voirs have been identified only by using
information recorded in the epic. Confusions
created by inaccurate popular lore have been
resolved with the aid of the Mahàvamsa even be¬
fore supporting epigraphical evidence was found.
As many as 3,000 inscriptions hitherto studied
could hardly have been dated and interpreted in
any other way.
The efforts in international academic circles
to unravel the mysteries of the Mahàvamsa, on
the one hand, and the Sri Lankan project to bring
it up to date on the other, demonstrate the last¬
ing impact the epic has exercised over the centu¬
ries. One wonders whether the ancient scribes
who kept palace records and the monks who syn¬
thesized them into a historical narrative could
have had any idea of the distinction they were
thus bringing to their motherland. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
An authentic historical
figure who became a
legend, Shaka Zulu has
inspired many African
writers.
Shaka Zulu,
a living legend
BY KALAME IYAMUSE BOSCO
« v'.''
44
1 his engraving by James
Saunders King is the only
authentic portrait of Shaka,
king of the Zulu.
¿SIÉE
2«^Ç«te
... :pw?zWm^
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
s
HAKA Zulu is an outstanding example of a
historical figure who became an epic hero. In the
epic of which he plays the central role, his birth,
rise and fall are closely associated with those of
the Zulu empire.
History relates how the Zulu were a small
clan of the Ngunis, a Bantu people which migrat¬
ed to southern Africa from the north around 1300
AD and settled in the Vaal regions east of the
Drakensberg mountains. The migration trek of
the Ngunis was led by Malendela, who had two
sons, Quabe and Zulu. Little is known of Zulu
except that he became the progenitor of the na¬
tion which bears his name. Chroniclers sum up
his heritage in these terms: "He left the world
cumbered with a grave and richer by a nation.
And therein lie his monument and his fame. No
feats, no follies, not one word of praise of him
is recorded."
A great nation deserves to be born in more
splendid circumstances, however, and this is why
the epic of Shaka is so important. In it Shaka is
attributed with achievements so towering that
they qualify him to usurp from Malendela's son
the role of father of the Zulu people.
Birth of a hero
Shaka was conceived during a pre-marital rela¬
tionship, and his mother Nandi, a member of the
Lengani royal family, only later became the third
wife of his father Senzangakhona, king of the
Zulu. Before his birth, the elders had declared that
his mother was not pregnant but merely har¬
boured ishaka, an intestinal beetle. This "beetle"
later became an emperor.
This beginning of the legend, locating moral
fault in the conception of Shaka as the root cause
of his problems, is important for the structure
of the epic in that it prepares for Shaka's Odys¬
sey of initiation. In fact, Shaka was not really an
illegitimate son, since among the Zulu people pre¬
marital conception was only considered a crime
among the lower strata of society. It was tolerat¬
ed among the aristocracy and both Shaka's par¬
ents were aristocrats.
Shaka's early childhood was unhappy. His
mother's name, Nandi, meant "the Sweet One",
but she hardly lived up to it. Wilful, sharp-
tongued and authoritarian, she was despised by
many, including her husband. Her beauty and her
inferior position in the Zulu royal house pro¬
voked a mixture of jealousy, hatred and scorn,
and Shaka too was treated with derision. This
hostility brought,together mother and son. Shaka
adored his mother and this bond was further
strengthened when the two went into exile.
Banished by Senzangakhona, mother and
child were badly received in Nandi's family.
Their sufferings actualjy became much worse
since a discarded wife had no place in the social
hierarchy. In addition, a child, and especially a
boy, belonged by priority to his father's clan.
Shaka was made to feel the full force of his
mother's humiliation. He was often scolded and
beaten for no valid reason. Defended by nobody
but his mother, he developed into a tough, self-
reliant personality. He was said to have killed a
hyena and saved the girl it was carrying off, and to
have performed other youthful feats of bravery.
Shaka was condemned to enter adulthood prema¬
turely. From this point, the various oral and
written renderings of the epic diverge.
There are two major written versions. Ac¬
cording to one, written by Thomas Mofólo in
1908, Shaka falls into the hands of Issanoussi, an
all-powerful medicine man who helps him com¬
plete his initiation.
The second written version of the Shaka epic
is a poetic rendering by Mazisi Kunene, who is
himself a Zulu. This version is closer to the histor¬
ical facts and to the Zulu literary tradition.* Un¬
like Mofólo, whose version of Shaka's exploits
emphasizes the role of magic, fantasy and supra-
human forces, Kunene dwells more on Shaka's
political, military and visionary qualities. He
takes us directly from Shaka's childhood to his
military apprenticeship under his protector and
mentor, Dingiswayo, the enlightened king of the
Bathethwa, in whose army Shaka becomes a
recruit.
The rise of Shaka
Shaka's intelligence soon brought him to the at¬
tention of Dingiswayo. Above all he distin¬
guished himself as a skilled military leader with
ideas which would revolutionize the art of war.
He advocated the use of the short, wide-bladed
stabbing spear instead of the long throwing spear,
claiming that a soldier who threw his spear not
only disarmed himself, but also armed his ene¬
my. The long spear was also cumbersome and in¬
effective in close combat. According to Shaka, a
good soldier should be a well-trained profession¬
al, hardened and experienced in the techniques
of combat. Dingiswayo listened to his proposals
and gave him the command of a group of young
volunteers who soon proved far superior to all
* Originally written in the Zulu language, Mazisi Kunene's
Emperor Shaka the Great has been published in English as part
of the Unesco Collection of Representative Works by
Heinemann Educational Books Ltd. (1979). Its publication has
not yet been authorized in South Africa in its original form. 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
the other troops. Shaka also did away with the
leather sandals that not only reduced the soldier's
speed but also made his feet soft and vulnerable.
His soldiers toughened their unshod feet by
dancing on hard ground littered with thorns.
Shaka then tried to impress on the soft¬
hearted Dingiswayo the idea that an enemy
should either be completely destroyed or forced
to declare allegiance to him, and that the art of
war should be geared to this goal. To this end
Shaka proposed the use of a "cow-horn" forma¬
tion in battle. Three divisions should be engaged
in battle. The bulk of the army should make a
frontal attack with fresh reserve forces at the rear.
The other two divisions should lie in wait, one
on the left and the other on the right. Once the
enemy was engaged in the frontal attack, the
other two divisions should close in, encircle him
and cut off his retreat. Dingiswayo was reluctant
to put these revolutionary ideas into practice, and
Shaka had to be patient.
The return to Zululand
Shaka's glory could not be complete until he
returned to Zululand as legitimate heir to his
father's throne. Before his death, Senzangakho¬
na had named the cowardly leader Sigujana as his
heir. With the blessing of Dingiswayo, Shaka
marched to claim control over Zululand. His ven¬
ture was successful. At the head of his invincible
regiment and flanked by his two trusty lieu¬
tenants Mgobhozi and Mqoboka, Shaka entered
his father's royal palace and ushered in a new era.
He was now in a position to put his revolu¬
tionary military and political ideas into practice.
Bound by respect and loyalty towards Din¬
giswayo, he waited for the latter's death before
pursuing expansionist policies. When Dingiswayo
was slain by Zwide, the dreaded king of the
Ndwandes, Shaka waged war against Zwide.
He lured Zwide's^ army into a trap by mak¬
ing a tactical retreat which enabled him to gain
better fighting ground and to wear out his ene¬
my through fatigue and famine. Zwide's army de¬
pended on provisions collected or looted in the
battle areas, whereas Shaka had formed a brigade
of young men to look after the provisioning of
his forces during mobile warfare. Since Shaka had
previously devastated the zones along which he
lured the enemy, Zwide's army inevitably suc¬
cumbed to starvation. His army destroyed, Zwide
is said to have disappeared in the open mouth of
a mountain and to have been carried along an un¬
derground stream to the land of the evil dead.
Having conquered the strongest of his adver¬
saries, Shaka now began to strengthen and expand
his empire. He had already formed regiments on
the basis of age: the uFasimba, a brigade of sixteen-
to twenty-year-olds, the isimPholo (the
"bachelors' brigade" of twenty- to thirty-year-
olds) and the amaWombe (the "battlers", com¬
prising married men up to forty years old).
In Shaka's empire, hierarchy was based on
merit. More than ever before he made heroism
a central part of the Zulu ethos. A recognized
hero exercised greater political authority than a
born prince. Later this caused conflicts between
him and his brothers, but it was a guarantee of
equal opportunities for all who served under him.
Anyone who defended the interests of the Zulu
nation became Zulu, and it is often said that most
of his generals and close comrades were not of
Zulu descent.
Shaka's death was the result of heinous in¬
trigues by his envious brothers, Dingane and
Mhalangana, with the complicity of Mbopha, his
army commander. His death is seen by many.
African authors as the ultimate betrayal and the
KALAME 1YAMUSE
BOSCO
is a Ugandan writer based
in Paris. His doctoral thesis,
on order and chaos in the
African novel, will be
published shortly.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
1 oster and scene from a
1976 production of Le
Zoulou, by the Congolese
playwright Tchicaya
UTam'Si, at the 30th
Avignon Festival, France.
The play was performed
by Théâtre Noir,
a troupe ofAfrican
and West Indian actors.
A Zulu kraal or village in
Shaka's day.
murder of a Christ-like figure. The two brothers
leapt from their hiding place and stabbed him
from behind. Mbopha struck at the astonished
Shaka from the front as he fell. Afraid that he
would rise again, the three assailants continued
stabbing at him furiously even after he was dead.
They then placed guards around his corpse in case
he should rise from the dead.
Just before his death the visionary Shaka is
said to have pronounced the words: "So, my
brothers, you are killing me? And you, Mbopha,
son of Sithayi! You think you shall rule Zululand
after my death. No, you shall never rule over it."
Shaka is a figure of the pre-colonial era, which
colonial historians have often endeavoured to
reduce to a subsistence level of village exploits.
His image is a challenge to this prejudice. Afri¬
can poets such as Leopold Sédar Senghor of Sene¬
gal and playwrights such as Zambia's Twanyanga
Mulikita have composed works inspired by the
Shaka epic. In all these plays and poems, Shaka
is depicted as the hero of an Africa seeking to
overcome tribal divisions before the onset of
colonial domination. There is often an underly¬
ing theme that the hero will rise again.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
r-
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Knights of the Far West
BY GARY N. GRANVILLE
The cowboy starred in epics
which unfolded on cinema screens
the world over. Has this modern
knight on horseback ridden into
the sunset for the last time?
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
BUFFAU" B -
50
The Sioux chief Sitting Bull and Buffalo Bill
(William Frederick Cody, 1846-1917) in a spectacular show
which dramatized life in the Wild West.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
NeI O myth is more widespread or more deeply
woven into the fabric of contemporary culture
than that of the western. As the twenty-first cen¬
tury approaches, it is striking that a. historical
phenomenon over a hundred years old should
still be so fresh and alive. The behaviour patterns,
aspirations, styles of dress, and even the kind of
food depicted in westerns have become familiar
models for people the world over to dream about.
Blue jeans, the cowboy's trademark, are the
most popular garment on earth. And clothing,
surely, is the most visible emblem of the image
of themselves people want to project. Hundreds
of millions of would-be cowboys walk around in
jeans. Why has the western had such a universal
impact? Two of the main reasons would seem to
be the archetypal power of the myth, and the
technological and cultural background of the
twentieth century.
From knight to cowboy
The cowboy is the democratic heir of the mythi¬
cal knight in shining armour. He evokes and
adapts for the modern public the countless
legends that have grown up through the ages, all
over the world, around the taming of the horse.
The chivalrous knight is someone who
masters his animal nature, thereby raising him¬
self above other men. He is more powerful, more
mobile and freer than they. He shoulders the
noble responsibility of restoring justice and
defending the weak and the oppressed. But he is
vulnerable, because if he wavers and falls from
grace, he has a long way to fall. He is lonely, too,
for not everyone can become a knight. The at¬
traction of the myth of the chivalrous knight is
rooted in the twofold dream we all harbour, of
achieving self-control and meting out justice. For
a long time the fulfilment of this dream was be¬
yond the reach of most of us.
Then, with the American and the French
Revolutions, the great principle of human equal-
TMlW|M
AND
WrlATTTT
Ideally Did.
OKI TO® B3BH11S
- SCLh6~ -5
ity came to the fore and transformed ways of
thinking. The ideal of the western was the per¬
fect substitute for an over-élitist myth. The dig¬
nity and freedom of the knight were now within
the grasp of everyone, at least in imagination. A
figure from the New World, the cowboy, was
grafted onto an ancient myth, ready to captivate
the whole world.
The Golden Age of the Far West
Then along came the cinema, an invention that
has had inconceivable repercussions. Like Guten¬
berg's printing press, it revolutionized commu¬
nications. It propagated the same dreams to a
worldwide audience. As early production and dis¬
tribution techniques were cumbersome and ex¬
pensive, only a limited number of films were
available to an ever-widening public.
The sheer size of the American market meant
that the United States would play a dominant role
in world cinema: films whose costs had already
I oster for a western
featuring the American
actor Tom Mix and his
famous horse, Tony. In
films Tom Mix portrayed
the decent cowboy,
committed to the struggle
for justice.
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
I" aventuras Extra0Pd¡napias'*í|
LANZADOS AL ABISMO f
\
U V- Ba.íaiana
I\ight, three knights on
horseback (15th-century
French miniature). Left,
Buffalo Bill depicted on the
cover of a Spanish
illustrated magazine.
GARY N. GRANVILLE
is a Paris-based American
writer who has worked in
films, television,
photography and
advertising.
52
been recouped at home could be exported at
prices that defied all competition. Add to this the
extraordinary popularity of American films, and
the result was that the whole world began to see
the same films and to share the same cinema
landscape.
In response to the production needs of a
rapidly increasing output, the American film in¬
dustry set up in California, where there is sun¬
shine practically all the year round. Film-makers
need décors as well as light and actorsand
California has plenty of outstanding natural lo¬
cations, ideal for westerns.
The advent of television meant that the
myths vehicled by the American cinema reached
an even wider audience. The whole planet began
to tune into the Hollywood wavelength. But it
was the Far West, without a doubt, that most
strikingly captured the popular imagination.
Adventure in the wide open spaces and per¬
manent confrontation with danger gave a man
the opportunity to reveal the best (or the worst)
of himself, to go beyond the frontiers of civiliza¬
tion and escape from its reassuring but repressive
grip. What a thrilling experience for modern
man, confined to a world of daily routine and
mundane hopes, ground down by conventions
and constraints!
The end of a myth?
But the values underlying this myth were slow¬
ly turned upside down. The form remained the
same, but the content changed. The ideal became
the anti-hero, not the hero. The search for in-
ÉP
lala^Ha^Rù!
Ijr y**&
dividuality and liberty, the rebellion symbolized
by the western, persisted, but there was a shift
in one of the myth's intrinsic values: belief in di¬
vine justice. This virtually universal idea presup¬
poses that harmony, if disturbed, always
re-establishes itself, in human society as in the cos¬
mos. Order triumphs over disorder. This notion
is expressed in the Oriental "karma", in the
West's "as you sow so shall you reap".
This concept of justice had always been an
integral part of the scenario (the cavalry which
always arrives in the nick of time), or a presup¬
position of the narrative (crime doesn't pay). Just
as the knights of old defending a just cause in¬
variably came out victorious from the "judge-
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
W*4.
r
I
ment of God", it was impossible for the "bad
guy" to draw his gun before the "good guy" in
their ritual duel.The idea that the forces of good
always win in the end gave the myth its transcen¬
dent quality. It is perhaps no coincidence that the
sheriff's badge is a six-pointed star, like Solomon's
seal, a symbol of equilibrium and wisdom.
Until the 1970s, then, audiences delighted in
the triumph of order, which reaffirmed their faith
in justice, honesty, in short, in all the great moral
values. Then ways of thinking changed and these
values were challenged. Everything was called
into question, even myths.
The systematic and sometimes naive moral
stance commended to us by the American cine
ma, particularly in westerns, was no longer in
tune with modern thinking. A reaction was in¬
evitable. The idea of divine justice and the stereo¬
typed hero were less clearly defined. In recent
years most westerns have been pastiches of the
mythical West or have set out to demystify it.
Now the outlaw is defended, even glorified, and
there is a feeling that the other traditional adver¬
saries, the Indians, can no longer be seen as the
bad guys. The keynote is realism, sometimes even
squalor. The solitude of the cowboy has become
selfishness, his dignity has become a form of
provocation. The legendary cowboy no longer
exists. By a curious coincidence, he died around
the same time as John Wayne. 53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND SOCIETY
Mapping the human genome
BY JACQUES RICHARDSON
BPlOLOGISTS, aided by mathemati¬
cians, engineers, computer specialists
and a variety of industrial researchers,
began last January a generation-long ef¬
fort to trace and identify every gene and
related material representing the hu¬
man body's "blueprint". This analysis
of our biological architecture is called
the human genome study"genome"
meaning how a living organism is as¬
sembled in its finest details.
The research is expected to require
between fifteen and thirty years of in¬
vestigation, costing perhaps between
$3,000 and $4,000 million. Sir Walter
Bodmer, president of the British Associ¬
ation for the Advancement of Science,
calls the genome plan the "most excit¬
ing" of all the current, large-scale inter¬
national research ventures.
Why so much costly effort, and for
what purpose? One reason is that, af¬
ter a century of intensive biological
research, we still do not understand pre¬
cisely how the body is built and works
(or sometimes fails to). We still need to
learn the complete instructions for
"making a human being", how these
are communicated through all the
body's cells to the various tissues and
vital organsbrain, heart, liver and so
forthand why some instructions go
wrong.
A second reason is that, once we
have understood how the genome is
constructed and functions, we should
be able to take appropriate precautions
or corrective steps to deal with errors
in the system: disease and disability.
Medicine and public health are thus ex¬
pected to benefit enormously from the
new knowledge. We should then be
able to resolve, thirdly, some of the
many mysteries of human heredity. A
fourth goal is to save some of the en¬
dangered biological species facing pos¬
sible extinction.
Not counting the blood's red cells,
54 your body or mine contains between 1 0
Biologists embark on
a vast new international project
to identify and locate
every human gene.
million million and 100 million million
cells, so that each cubic centimetre of
living tissue contains many millions.
Each microscopic cell has its own
smaller nucleus, within which the "in¬
structions for living" are coded along
an extremely long DNA molecule. DNA,
or deoxyribonucleic acid, is the basic
genetic puzzle solved in 1953 by three
researchers, Francis Crick, Rosalind
Franklin and James Watson.
The animal organism's cells com¬
bine their structures to form increasingly
large and complicated components
so that cell biology is now more and
more important for us to be able to un¬
derstand:
how oxygen helps decompose and
absorb food
how protein (essential in diet) is
manufactured
role of water in transporting
calcium and sodium
how cells reproduce
why cells fall ill, and
why these various mechanisms exist
in so many combinations that each of
us possesses undisputed uniqueness of
body and mind.
THE GENE, THE BASIC UNIT
OF BIOLOGICAL INHERITANCE
The cell's nucleus, the very hub of the
living universe, houses 46 chromosomes
upon which is distributed the DNA ar¬
chitectural information. This very long-
chained substance has four nitrogen-
based components called adenine (A),
thymine (T), cytosine (C) and guanine
(G). Depending on how the A, T, C and
G are linked, they join to form proteins.
We call that portion of DNA linkage
which issues the commands to make an
entire protein a gene.
The genes next combine by thou¬
sands to form the 46 chromosomes cit¬
ed: 23 pairs of them. Because the
chromosomes constituting each pair are
somewhat different, these miniscule
differences serve as markers to identi¬
fy the constituent genes. In reproduc¬
tion, a father and a mother contribute
a gene corresponding to every chromo¬
some pair found in their offspring. It is
the combination of the similarities and
differences that make each of us male
or female, tall or short, black-haired or
blond, dark-skinned or light, prone to
disease (and which ones), long-lived or
otherwise, mentally alert or handi¬
capped, musical, manually dexterous,
sports-minded, and so on.
In terms of poor health, for exam¬
ple, chromosome pair no. 3 is already
known to bear the "disease genes" for
maladies such as certain protein defi¬
ciencies, intolerance to some sugars, a
tendency to develop kidney-cell cancer,
an inability to process thyroid hormone,
or difficulty in breathing.
But the exact location of the
offending gene or genes is difficult to
establish because it is tucked some¬
where along what is a very long chain
indeed. One has to imagine a piece of
cord 1 cm in diameter, but 10,000 km
long! This is the nature of the challenge
facing the genome explorers.
GENE THERAPY
TO CURE DISEASE
What happens after much of the bio¬
logical sleuthing is accomplished?
Remember the second reason, listed
above, for all this effort: to improve
medicine and public health. Here is how
"gene therapy" could be put to work
to cure someone with a medical
problem centred, for example, in bone
marrow. The technique described is al¬
ready familiar to Couner readers (see
March 1987 issue) as that of recom¬
binant DNA, in use today in some plant
and farm-animal biotechnology and in
the pharmaceutical industry.
The appropriate gene (embedded
in some surrounding DNA) is taken from
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
a healthy donor, then "spliced"via a
microscopic chemical methodto a
specially prepared virus. The virus is per¬
mitted to "attack" one of the defective
cells removed from the patient afflict¬
ed with bone-marrow disease. The in¬
fecting virus then inserts the normal
gene, as part of the DNA material the
treated virus has brought with it, into
the DNA of the receiving cell. Finally, the
manipulated or engineered bone-
marrow cells are returned to the pa¬
tient, where they reproduce and be¬
come an entire population of healthy
bone-marrow cells. The patient is now
well.
Before the genome researchers at¬
tain this degree of scientific discovery,
however, there are other factors to be
considered. Hence, the length of time
required for research. Even the experts
cannot be sure, for instance, of how
many genes might exist. Victor McKu-
sick of the Johns Hopkins University in
the United States has advanced a low
estimate of 50,000, although 100,000
may prove to be the case once all iden¬
tification has been completed. So far,
less than 5,000 genes have been given
labels and only 1,500 of these have
been located accurately on their host
chromosomes.
Another factor is that the success
of the undertaking will lie in its appli¬
cation to men and women everywhere.
Both the research and its expected
Genetic Message (1985),
by French artist Nicole d'Agaggio.
results are burdened, furthermore, with
disturbing ethical problems. Who will
establish the authority to perform
genetic interventions? (France has led
the way; President François Mitterrand
has created a special bio-ethical com¬
mission, at national level, chaired by
blood specialist Jean Bernard.) What
might be the technique's effects in
terms of law and justice (on whom
might the technique not be used)? How
can everyone, regardless of social or
economic position, be assured of access
to the new therapies?
The international Human Genome
Organization, known familiarly as
HUGO, a non-profit professional associ¬
ation registered in Switzerland and
headed by Professor McKusick, will
meet in October of this year under the
sponsorship of the American weekly
magazine Science. The experts will ap¬
portion research tasks among almost
300 workers from nearly fifty countries,
prepare to reconstruct important early
biological phases in man's prehistory
(before records were kept), search for
genes involved in immune-response
mechanismssuch as the deficiencies
leading to AIDS, and try to identify
genes responsible for growth disorders
and such devastating illnesses as cystic
fibrosis or Huntington's chorea (a type
of degeneration of the brain and ner¬
vous system).
The HUGO experts include French
Nobel prize-winner Jean Dausset,
Michio Ito of the University of Tokyo,
and Hans Zachau of the University of
Munich. They hope to achieve major
results by the year 2005, calling upon
not only molecular and cell biologists
throughout the world but also on the
fast computing machines available
chiefly in the industrialized countries.
Unesco's Director-General, Federico
Mayor, a biochemist, has appointed a
special consultant to assist in the co¬
ordination of the basic research under
the aegis of United Nations agencies
and throughout the global scientific
family. He has also called directly on the
resources of the Unesco-affiliated Inter¬
national Cell Research Organization,
the Microbiological Resource Centres,
and the International Brain Research
Organization.
JACQUES G. RICHARDSON
was editor of Unesco's international
quarterly journal Impact of Science
on Society from 1972 to 1985.
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 9
Interview with Jean-Claude Carrière
The Mahabharata,
the Great History of Mankind
56
but we never lose the central theme of a looming threat,
to which everything starkly points. We are living in a time
of destruction. The question is, can we avoid it?
What guidelines did you follow in making your adapta¬
tion of the work?
Our first preoccupation was to avoid sacrificing any of
the levels of the work. The Mahabharata says that Krishna
is one of the avatars of Vishnu. Some of the characters be¬
lieve this, others do not. In India there have always been
divergent views on this. For a marxist, Krishna is a phan¬
tasm, for a rishi, a Hindu holy man, he is a god. We take
no sides in the argument since we must eliminate no view¬
point on the basis of this or that a priori judgement. The
uncertainty expressed in the original work has to be respect¬
ed, that's all. Some members of our audiences must be able
to see divinity in Krishna; others must be allowed to doubt it.
Very often in the Mahabharata Krishna does not know
what is going to happen. How can this be? As a god is he
not omniscient? I had a discussion on this point with
Shankaracharya, one of the great living holy men of southern
India. I put the question to him in a number of different
ways, but he eluded it good-humouredly. I asked him how
it could be that, during a battle, Krishna did not know what
was happening on the battlefield as a whole, and that he
could be surprised and even worried. Could a god or a man-
god have human weaknesses? To which Shankaracharya
replied with a smile and said something like: "It is a human
weakness to think so."
When you began writing, did you start at the beginning
of the poem?
No, I started making a patchwork, by writing certain
scenes. In the Mahabharata there are a number of set pieces
or obligatory scenes, such as the one in which Kunti con¬
fesses to Kama that she is his mother. I knew that sooner
or later I would have to write scenes such as this. However,
there were other sequences that were in the form of narra¬
tive in the original and which would have to be turned into
scenes by creating dramatic situations, confronting one
character with another and seeing if anything emerged. A
good third of the scenes in the play are not scenes in the
original poem.
I began, like a dancer, with the set pieces, while still try¬
ing to find the right forms of expression. It took a long time.
I wrote the first scenes either in Paris or in India. I read them
immediately to Peter Brook, to our close collaborators and
to our musicians when they were there. I remember hav¬
ing read scenes in airports between two flights, and one even¬
ing in Madras, in a taxi caught in an interminable traffic
jam. That is how our Mahabharata came into being, in dribs
and drabs, written sometimes on a grubby paper tablecloth
in a café. When I read them out, I could sense whether the
scenes worked, what should be kept in, what should be left
out and what would have to be reworked.
The time came when I had a first draft of all the set
pieces. I then turned to the others, those that had to be in¬
vented, and this was much more difficult. Peter asked me
to take part in the auditions with the actors, to go through
a three- to four-page scene with them as if I myself was an
actor. For Peter and his assistant it was a way of audition¬
ing both the actors and the scene. So I had to take the plunge.
That way you have a much better idea of what works and
what doesn't work. There were scenes that I wrote straight
off, in ten minutes, in which not a word was changed. Then
there were others that I wrote and rewrote twenty-five times
without ever achieving a perfect result.
Finally, there was a really harrowing period. The open¬
ing date for the show was already fixed, auditions were start¬
ing for the actors and I still had not found an overall
structure to hold the whole play together. There was a story,
related in a series of scenes, but how could all these scenes
be made to hang together? I still hadn't found the solution.
We were only four months away from the date fixed
for the first rehearsals. I decided to take a break in the south
of France, in the country house of some friends of mine.
There, for the only time in my life, something quite in¬
describable happened to me, something one reads about in
books without really believing it: inspiration.
It was three o'clock in the morning. Normally I sleep
well, but that night I couldn't sleep. There was something
on my mind. Suddenly, and I couldn't tell you how it hap¬
pened, I saw the first twenty minutes of the play, from which
everything else would follow.
It was the dialogue between the child and the old
storyteller with which the play opens:
-"Can you write?"
-"No, why?"
Then the arrival of Ganesha and the beginning of the
story, everything unfolded before my eyes as if I were a
member of the audience. It was quite extraordinary. I jot¬
ted everything down. The theatrical key had been found.
It was based on a trianglea storyteller, a god and a child
and on an uncertainty: which of the two, Ganesha or
Krishna, had invented the other? The narrator and his
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
listener would see the characters acting out their lives before jected to many alterations and additions. Nevertheless, one
them, could touch them and speak to them. I had the can sense that it is a single work written by a single author,
keystone of my edifice. With relief, I fell asleep. The next Georges Dumézil was also of this opinion,
morning I telephoned Peter and told him about it. "No need I think that this is an important point to make, because
to look any further," he said, "you've got it." the introduction of the notion of an author brings with it
a specifically human element. And this is the point at which
Was it really all over? we deviate from the path of revealed truth to enter the world
Yes and no. The overall structure, the theatrical foun- of the epic. In a certain fashion, for better or for worse, an
dation, was in place. But there was so much left to do. I epic helps a society to become organized. It is the great corn-
attended all the rehearsals, making a thousand and one cor- mon saga, drawing inspiration from the god's, but already
rections to meet the problems the actors encountered. Then, talking about man. This is surely a vital stage in the found-
at every stage, when the performances started, when we ing of a society. Each of the characters in the Mahabharata
made the English version, when we wrote the television has a divine alter ego at first. Little by little they forget that
series, when we went on to the film to which we were put- they are the children of gods; they begin to face up to the
ting the finishing touches, there were many things to review, most trivial and mundane problems and, in so doing, they
For example, it was only when writing the screenplay for become mere humans. This, in a sense, is the function of
the film that I found the solution to a problem I had been the epicto cut the cords that bind the leading actors to
unable to resolve in the play. Today, if it had to be done the heavenly world of the gods and set their feet firmly on
over again, I would write it differently. the ground, to set them face to face with their problems
as individuals and then as citizens. The law, and indeed laws,
Has this tremendous experience left you with any specific aided and reinforced by the prestige of poetry, have to be
ideas about or overall impressions of the Mahabharata or established. In the chaos of the human world, a lasting, co-
ofihe epic form in general? herent order has to be sought and given some apparent
Georges Dumézil thought that the Mahabharata was an justification,
adaptation in epic form of a fifth Veda (ancient Hindu scrip- This seemed very clear to me from the Mahabharata, as
ture) which has been lost. I have neither his erudition nor it does from the Iliad and from the Odyssey. It was the guid-
his authority, but I have come to the same conclusion. While ing concept behind the writing of the play and its direction,
reading the Mahabharata and the Vedas, I could'sense a link At the beginning, Peter Brook's setting was light, ethereal
between them but also a difference. It is not easy to ana- and unreal, bathed in divine grace. Gradually it grew heavi-
lyse; one has to try to feel these things, even when one er, subject to the weight and gravity of life on earth, to end
doesn't altogether understand them. unambiguously in the mire. The earth, as a character, plays
The Vedas are ascribed to no author. They are revealed a progressively more important role. We see a society be-
texts which simply proclaim the truth. All cultures have coming organized and then rent as it cuts itself off from its
similar texts, written or oral, which proclaim the truth, celestial youth,
which tell the people where they came from, what their place
is on this earth and how they must live to maintain that How do you feel after this experience?
place. When an author takes a hand, because he invents, be- In The Conference ofthe Birds, by the Persian poet Farid
cause he creates, he deviates from the path of truth, introduc- od-Din 'Attar, three butterflies discuss the nature of a candle,
ing an untruth or an error, and in a sense becomes an exile The first one approaches it to have a look and comes back
from the community which sees itself reflected in that mythi- saying: "It is light." The second butterfly goes closer, burns
cal truth. its wing and comes back saying: "It burns." The third
Epic poems deviate cautiously from the revealed, mythi- butterfly goes even closer, flies into the flame and does not
cal truth and even from legendary history. An epic is truly return. It has learned what it wanted to know, what it alone
a creative work, the work of an author, even though it at- knows. But it cannot tell the others. This parable cannot
tempts to keep in contact with the myth. The Mahabharata be bettered. There is always a third and last circle to enter,
is, indeed, the work of a creative writer. We can be sure and if you do so you can no longer talk about it. You know,
of this, even though we may not know anything about the but you cannot communicate what you know to anyone
author, because from the beginning to the end of the poem, else,
someone has, as it were, taken events in hand. At the end
we find threads that can be traced back to the beginning. So the theatre is merely the second circle?
And the style of writing is the same. Written down and I recently read a beautiful Persian poem which said:
copied many times between the fourth century BC and the "Last night a voice whispered in my ear: 'No such thing
third century AD, this vast epic has, of course, been sub-, exists as a voice that whispers in the ear at night'."
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
58
Published monthly in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvir, 75015 Paris, France.
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Maikin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: A:ain Levéque, Ñeca El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Saitey (Tel.: 45 68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45 68.46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.6847 15),
Mouna Chatta, Majda Dalai
Public relations: Claudie Duhamel (Tel :45.68.45 86)
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Ma'ie-Dcminique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werne' Merkli (8erne)
Italian: Mario Guidottt (Rome)
Hindi: Shri Krishna Kumar Singh (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S J Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kossler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Seham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bengali: Ahmed Hedayet (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45 88), Assistant: Marie-
Noélle Branet (45.68.45.89), Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse
Hardy (45 68 45.65), Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Mohamed Salah El Din,
Customer service: Ginette Mot reff (45.68.45 64),
Accounts: Liliane Tasch (45 68.45 66), Cultural projects:
Ricardo Zamora-Perez (Tel.: 45.68.45 80),
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval
ADVERTISING
Publicat: 17, Boulevard Poissonnière, 75002 Paris.
Tel.: 40.26.5. 26
Sales director: Beroit Rosier
Advertising director: Daniele Michelet
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel : 45.68.45.65
1 year: 126 French francs 2 years: 234 FF
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier".
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name Non-copyright
photos will be Supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or tnose of
the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations The Unesco Courier is
produced m microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco. ~l
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans. (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann
Arbor. Michigan 48100. USA . (3) N C fT Micocard Edition. Indian
Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York, u S A . (4) Bell and
Howell Co. Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691, USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
{Printed ¡n France) DEPOT LEGAL CI SEPTEMBRE 1989
Photocomposition The Unesco Courier
Photogravure-impression: Maury imprimeur S A . Z I route d'ttampes.
45330 Malesherbes
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor In your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
In local currency, will be supplied on request.)
ALBANIA. 'Ndermarrja e perpjes se libnf. Tirana. ARGENTINA. Librería el
Correo de la Unesco EDILYR, SRL. Tucumân 1685. 1050 Buenos Aires.
AUSTRALIA. Books only:: Educational Supplies Pty. Lid.. P.O. Box 33.
Brookvale 2100. NSW; Periodicals' Dominie Pty Subscriptions Dept.. P.O
Box 33. Brookvale 2100. NSW. Sub-agents: United Nations Association of
Australia, Victorian Division, 328 Flinders Street, Melbourne 3000.Hunter
Publications, 58a dpps St., Collmgwood. Victoria 3066. AUSTRIA. Gerold
and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools Interna¬
tional, Arab Regional Office. P.O. Box 726, Bahrain: The Arabian Agencies
and Distributing Co.. Al Mutanabi St.. PO Box 156. Manama BANGLADESH
Kanm International. GPO Box No: 2141. 64 ,' I Manipun Para. Teigaon.'
Farmgate. Dhaka. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop.
Cave Hill Campus. P.O. Box 64. Bridgetown. BELGIUM. Jean de Lannoy. 202
Ave. du Roi. 1 060 Brussels. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, PO Box 91
Gaborone. BRAZIL. Fundaçâo Getúlio Vargas. Serviço del Pubhcaçoes.
caixa postal 9.042-ZC-05 Praia de Botafogo 188. Rio de Janeiro (RJ) 2000:
Books only; Imagem Latinoamericana, Av. Paulista 750, 1 andar, caixa postal
30455, Sao Paulo CEP 01051. BULGARIA. Hemus. Kantora Literatura.
boulevard Rousky 6. Sofia. BURMA. Trade Corporation no. (9), 550-552
Merchant Street. Rangoon. CANADA. Renoul Publishing Co. Ltd. 1294
Algoma Road. Ottawa. Ontario K1B3W8 (Stores 61 Sparks Street, Ottawa.
21 1 Yonge St.. Toronto. Sales office: 7575 Trans Canada Hwy. Ste. 305. Si.
Laurent. Quebec H4T 1V6. CAMEROON. Cameroon Book Centre, PO Box
123, Limbe. Commission Nationale, BR 1600, Yaounde. CHILE. Editorial
Universitaria SA., Departamento de Importaciones. M Luisa Saniander
0447, casilla 10220, Santiago, Editorial 'Andrés Bello'. Av: R Lyon 946,
Casillo 4256. Santiago de Chile: Dipublic, Antonio Varas 671 , 2o piso, casilla
14364. Correo 21. Santiago CHINA. China National Publications Import and
Export Corporation, P O. Box 88, Beijing COLOMBIA. Instituto Colombiano
de Cultura (Colcultura), Carrera 3A. n° 18 / 24, Bogota; Books only. Librería
Buchholz Galena. Calle 59. No; 13-13, Bogota CYPRUS. MAM", Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avene. PO Box 1 722. Nicosia CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S N T L..
Spalena 51-113 02. Prague 1; For_ Slovakia only: Alla Verlag -Publishers.
Hurbanovo nam 6,893 31 Bratislava: PNS-UED. Jindnsska 14. praha 1:
Slovan, Goftwaldovo Nam 6. 805 32 Bratislava. DEM. REP. OF YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation, PO Box 4227. Aden. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-
OG. Tidsskrittservice. 35 Norre Sogade. DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Librería Blasco. Avenida Bolivar. No: 402. esq
Hermanos Dehgne. Santo Domingo. EGYPT {ARAB REPUBLIC OF). Un¬
esco Publications Centre. No. 1 Talaat Harb St.. Cairo. ETHIOPIA. Ethiopian
National Agency for Unesco. PO Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateemmen Kinakauppa, P. O. Box 126. SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalamen
Kirjakauppa Oy. Ko-vuvaarankuja 2 01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris. Periodicals only. Unesco CPD /
V- 1 . rue Miolhs. 75015 Pans. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchex-
port. Postfach 140, Leninstrasse 16. 7010, Leipzig. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kuner
Vertrieb. Basallstrasse 57. D5300 Bonn 3. UNO-Verlag. Simrockstrasse 23,
D-5300 Bonn 1; S. Karger GmbH. Verlag Angerhofstrasse 9. Postfach 2
D-8034 Germering / München. For scientific maps only Geo Center, Postfach
800B30. 7000 Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Books only Presbyterian Bookshop
Depol Lid.. PO Box 195, Accra, Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.. PO 7869. Accra:
The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, PO Box 1 . Legon. Periodicals only
Fides Entreprises. P.O. Box 14129. Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom. GREECE. Eleftheroudakis SA. International Bookstore, 4 Nikis
Street, Athens. John Mihalopoulos & Son SA. International Booksellers, P O.
Box 10073, 541 10 Thessaloniki. Greek National Commission for unesco. 3
Akadimias Street, Athens HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co . 13-15 Lock
Road, Kowloon: Federal Publications (HK) Ltd . Tokwawan. Kowloon; Hong
Kong Government Information Services. Publication Section, Hong Kong:
Periodicals only. Beaconsfield House 6th floor, Queen's Road Central. Victor¬
ia. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT. POB. 149-H-1389, Budapest 62.
ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co.. H F. Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykiavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd . Kamam Marg. Ballard Estate. Bombay 400038.
17 Chitaranjan Ave.. Calcutta 13: 36a. Anna Salai. Mount Road. Madras 2.
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd
Bangalore 560001: 3-5-820 Hyderguda. Hyderabad-500001. Sub-agents.
Oxford Book and Stationery Co.. 1 7 Park St . Calcutta 70016. Sandia House.
New Delhi 1 1 0001 . INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29.
J1. Oto Iskandardmata 111, Jakarta: Indira P.T.. Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangre 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, 1 188 Englab
Ave. Rostam Give Building, P O. Box 11365-4498. Teheran 13158
IRELAND. Penodicals only; The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., PO Box
43A, Waikmstown. Dublin 1 2: Books only TDC Publishers. 1 1 North Frederick
Street, Dublin 7. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions. Inc., c/o Steimatzky Ltd..
P.O. Box 628, Tel Aviv. A B.C. Bookslore Ltd., P.O. Box 1 283, 71 Allenby Rd .
Tel Aviv 61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionana Sansoni, S p A ), Via
Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552. 501 21 Florence; via Bartolmi 29, 201 55
Milan; FAO Bookshop, via délie Terme di Caracalla. 001 00 Rome JAMAICA.
University of the West Indies Bookshop, Mona, Kingston 7. JAPAN. Eastern
Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113. JORDAN
Jordan Distribution Agency, PO Box 375. Amman. Periodicals only Jordan
Book Cerjtre Co. Ltd.. PO Box 301 , Al Jubeiha, Amman. KENYA. East African
Publishing House. PO 30571. Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd. Quran
House. Mangano Street, PO Box 45245, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco. P.O. Box Central 64. Seoul KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co.. Ltd. POB 2942. Kuwait; Periodicals only: Farafalla Press
Agency, P.O Box SAFA 454 1 , Kuwait. LEBANON. Librairie Antoine A. Naufal
et Frères. BP 656. Beirut LESOTHO Mazenod Book Centre. PO Mazenod,
Maseru. LIBERIA National Bookstore, Mechlm and Carey Streets. PO Box
590, Monrovia; Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.. PO Box 286. Monrovia.-
LUXEMBOURG. Books only: Librairie Paul Brück, 22. Grande-Rue, Luxem¬
bourg: Periodical: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 1022, Luxembourg MALAWI
Malawi Book Service, Head Office. PO Box 30044, Chichin. Blantyre 3
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop. Kuala Lumpur
22-11 MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic St., Valletta MAURITANIA GRALI.-
COMA.. 1 rue du Souk X. Avenue kennedy. Nouakchott. MAURITIUS.
Naianda Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St.. Port-Louis MEXICO. Librería El
Correo de la Unesco, Actipan 66, Colonia del Valle, Apartado postal 61 164.
06600 Mexico DF. MONACO. British Library. 30 Bd. des Moulins. Monte
Carlo. MORROCCO. Librairie Aux belles images', 262 ave. Mohammed-V,
Rabat: Librairie des écoles, 12 ave. Hassan-ll, Casaglanca. Société cheriden-
ne de distribution et de presse. SOCHEPRESS, angle rues de Dînant et St,
Saens. BP 1 3683. Casablanca 05 MOZAMBIQUE. Instituto National do Livro
e do Disco (INLD), avenida 24 de Julho, 1 921 r / d Io andar, Maputo. NEPAL.
Sa)ha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Books only:
Keesing, Boeken B.V.. Hogehilweg 13, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam.
Periodicals: Faxon Europe. P.O. Box 197, 1000 AD Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N V . PO Box 200. Willem-
stad, Curaçao. NA. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P O. Box
14277-Kilbirme. Wellington. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The
University Bookshop of Ibadan. P O 286: The University Bookshop of Nsukka:
The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum. P O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1;
Universitets Bokhandelen, Universiletssentret. Postboks 307 Blmdern, Oslo
3. Periodicals only. Narvesen A/S. Litteraturt Jenesten, P O.B. 61 25 Etterstad.
N 0602 Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency. 65 Shahrah Ouaid-i-azam.
P.O. Box No. 729. Lahore 3: Unesco Publications Centre. Regional Office for
Book Development m Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society. P.O. Box
8950, Karachi 29. PANAMA. Distribuidora Cultura Internacional. Apartado
7571. Zona 5, Panama. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store Inc., 701 Rizal
Avenue. Manila POLAND. Orpan-lmport. Palac Kultury I Nauki. Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch. Krakowskie Przedrmescie No. 7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. ROMANIA.
ARTEXIM Export- Import. Piata Scienteii. no. 1. PO Box 33-16, 70005
Bucharest SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan. Olaya Mam Street, Ibrahim Bin
Sulaym Building. Riyadh. SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd.. Kmgsgate
House. PO Box 131. Mahé: National Bookshop, PO Box 48. Mahé. SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay College, Njaia University and Sierra leone Diocesan
Bookshops. Freetown. SINGAPORE. Righteous Enterprises, P.O. Box 562,
Kallang Basm Post Office. Singapore 9133 SOCIALIST PEOPLE'S LIBYAN
ARAB JAMAHIRIYA. General Establishment for Publishing. Distribution and
Advertising. Souf Al Mahmoudi St.. PO Box 959. Tripoli SOMALIA. Modern
Book Shop and General. PO Box uàô. Mogadiscio SPAIN. Mundi-Prensa
Libros SA. apartado 1223. Castelió 37. Madrid 1; Ediciones Liber, apartado
17, Magdalena 8. Ondárroa (Vizcaya): Donaire. Ronda de Outeiro. 20,
apartado de correos 341, La Coruña: books only: Librería Castells. Ronda
Universidad 13 y 15. Barcelona 7; Librería de la Generalität de Catalunya,
Palan Moja, Rambla de los Estudios 118. 08 002 Barcelona. SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop. 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.OB. 244,
Colombo 2. SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118. Khartoum.
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco. P.O. Box 2943,
Paramaribo. SWEDEN. A/ B C E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel. Regenng-
sgatan 12, Box 16356. S-103 27 Stockholm 16; For the Unesco Courier:
Svenska FN Forbundet. Skolgrand 2. Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm; For
periodicals only Wennergren-Wilhams AB, Nordenflychtsvagen 70, S-104, 25
Stockholm; Esselte Tidskriftscentraien, Gamla Brogatan 26. Box 62 -101, 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag. 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich: Librairies
Payot in Geneva Lausanne. Basle. Berne, Vevey. Montreux, Neuchâtel and
Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books Establishment, University of Aleppo.
Aleppo.' TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. POB. 9030. Dar-es-
Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road.
Siyaeg Phaya Sn, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan Panit. Mansion 9.
Rajdamnern Ave.. Bangkok: Suksit Siam Company. 1715 Rama IV Road.
Bangkok: ROEAP, PO Box 1425. Bangkok 10500. TRINIDAD AND TOBA¬
GO. National Commission for Unesco. 18 Alexandra St . St. Clair. Port-of-
Spam. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S.. Istiklâl Caddesi. No 469, Posta Kutusu
219. Beyoglu. Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. PO Box 7145, Kampa¬
la. UNITED ARAB EMIRATES. Maktabat al Maktaba. PO Box 15408. Al Am,
Abu Dhabi. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office. PO Box 276. London.
SW8 5DT; H.MS.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast. Manchester,
Birmingham. Bristol; Third World Publications. 151 Stratford Road. Birming¬
ham B11 1RD; tor scientific maps only. McCarta Ltd . 122 King's Cross Rd.
London WCiX 9DS. UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. Bernan-UNIPUB,
Periodicals Department, 46Î1-F Assembly Drive, Lanham, M D 20706 4391.
URUGUAY. Ediciones Trecho. S.A.. Maldonado 1092. Montevideo. USSR.
V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga. Ul. Dimitrova 39, Moskva 113095.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost. Mica 30/11. Zagreb: Cankaneva Zalozba, Zopitar-
leva 2, Lubljana: Noht. Terazije 13/ VIII. 11000 Belgrade; periodicals only.
Jugosolvena Kniga, PO Box 36, YU 11001 Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co of Zambia Ltd.. P.O. Box 2664. Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd.. 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare.
ISSN 0041 -S278 NO 9 1989 OPI 89 1 472 A
PHOTO CREDITS
Cover: © Khudojesivennaïa Literatura publishers, Moscow. Back cover, pages 28, 29, 30: © Roland and Sabrina Michaud, Paris. Page 2:
© National Board for the Celebration of the Portuguese Discoveries, Lisbon. Pages 3, 5, 56: © Marcel Salvaro/Unesco Courier. Pages 6, 7,
8, 9: © Gilles Abegg, Paris. Pages 10, 51, 52, 53: © Edimedia, Paris. Pages 12-13: Launois © Rapho, Paris. Page 14 (above): © Association
des Classiques Africains, Paris. Page 14 (below): © Association des Classiques Africains, Paris/Museum of the Geographical Institute, Cairo.
Page 15: Michelangelo Durazzo © ANA, Paris. Pages 16-17: Joseph Viesti © ANA, Paris. Page 18: © Baumeister Archive, Stuttgart. Museum
of Arts and Crafts, Hamburg. Page 19: © Bulloz, Musée du Louvre, Paris. Pages 21, 31: © Michael Holford, London. Page 22: © Roger-
Viollet, Paris/Villa Valmarana, Vicenza. Pages 23, 47 (below), 50: © Roger-Viollet, Paris. Page 24: © Bulloz, Paris/Library of the Senate.
Pages 24-25: © Gallimard, Univers des Formes, Paris. Pages 26-27: © RMN, Musée du Louvre, Paris. Page 27 (above): © Roger-Viollet,
Paris/Galleria Doria, Rome. Pages 32-33, 34 (below), 44, 47 (above): All Rights Reserved. Pages 34 (above), 35 (left): Izobrazitelnoïe Iskusstvo
publishers, Moscow. Page 35 (right): Nauka publishers, Moscow. Pages 36, 39: Embassy of the Mongolian People's Republic, Paris. Page
57: Takase © Artephot, Paris/Bibliothèque Nationale. Page 38: G. Mandel © Artephot, Paris/Collection of the Hetimandel princes. Pages
40-41, 41 (below), 42, 43: © J.-L. Nou, Paris. Page 46: © Gilles Aufray, Avignon. Pages 48-49: David Burnett © Cosmos, Paris. Page 55:
© Josette Brisse, Galerie de Mars, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
<
û
CO
1990
UNESCO
,»<
'aWÏ?-
:pj|^ír:juii^-.-|íE.a.
-
"ft
The World Heritage
Le Patrimoine Mondial
El Patrimonio Mundial
Vncafo UNESCOÄ
VIENT
DE PARAITRE
-M* HP*
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
X y X
	 __	 _/ - 	
1
.._
IMP
i
i O -> o J O i o
y-
IB.'OltJ TTtf
pc*«r * o » °
_»v 3 a p , o , ^ j
S&i
>M>">
mm
P»it:
to \^~^
W
tí> $ « 9 » « i> 3.» -
foi rTTo f» io'i TTcTT ,i)|
/»
/
A
" i :
q
rrter
:
u:
Jl
:X-
\i_¿L_i'
^~3'
Ir
¡»¿¿äs
^0>\u>p)\^xQ
W^a°A°AWa';*
.3a	^\.«'/>- c	
O *> CO O Ou»
jo »-O-a-o-e-
TTT
i	_i
r i
.^M
-
^^»a
V*V
]]>
</page>
</document>
