<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="084191eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
-
/
'
1
^ '<*«*
\
\
OCTOBER 1989
15 French francs
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters
i
¡¡¡A
-as*»
'&&*
£""""*».
We invite readers to send
us photographs to be
considered for publication
in this feature. Your photo
should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be
an example of cross-
fertilization between
cultures. Alternatively, you
could send us pictures of
two works from different
cultural backgrounds in
which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
*isfls&.
JWaaaÄBaS:
Ménilmontant i-_i»
1985, painting (1m x 0.50m)
by Annette Ghéan-Bisciglia m rt.
"I have always dreamed of
the Tropics but have never
been able to go there,"
writes the French painter
Annette Ghéan-Bisciglia.
"But now the Tropics have
come to Paris." The
painting shown here was
inspired by the immigrant
presence in Paris.
y\
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
CONTENTS
Today there are no more
unexplored continents, unknown
seas or mysterious islands. But
while we can overcome the
physical barriers to exploration,
the barriers of mutual ignorance
between different peoples and
cultures have in many cases still
not been dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can voyage
to the ends of the earth. But a
different kind of Odyssey now
beckonsan exploration of the
world's many cultural landscapes,
the ways of life of its different
peoples and their outlook on the
world in which they live.
' It is such an Odyssey that the
Unesco Courier now proposes to
you, its readers. Each month
contributors of different
nationalities will provide from
different cultural and professional
standpoints an authoritative
treatment of a theme of universal
interest. The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes will be respect
for the dignity of man
everywhere.
TheUnesco
^courier
4
Interview with
Jean Lacouture
CHAMPOLLION,"
A HERO OF THE
ENLIGHTENMENT
11
STRANGERS
ON THE SCREEN
CREATURES FROM INNER SPACE
by Claude Aziza
MACUNAÏMA, THE ETERNAL OUTSIDER
by Antonio Rodrigues 14
GERMANS SCREENED
THROUGH FRENCH EYES
by René Prectal 18
AN ORIENT OF MYTH AND MYSTERY
by Abbas Fahdel
TRISTAN AND PAVLOVA
THROUGH THE LOOKING GLASS
by Marilyne Fellous 30
BEHIND THE VEIL
Women on both sides of the camera
by Assia Djebar 34
CHARLIE CHAPLIN,
STRANGER AND BROTHER
by Marcel Oms 38
44
12 REFLECTIONS
'SLAVES OF ONE MAN'
by Chantai de Grandpré
48
SCIENCE
AND SOCIETY
UNDERSTANDING
GLOBAL CHANGE
25 by Alison McKelvey Clayson
Cover: Illustration by Brigitte
Salom
Back cover: Detail of Blaues Bild
("Blue Picture", 1928), by the
German sculptor and painter
Oskar Schlemmer (1888-1943).
The picture forms part of an
exhibition entitled Peinture-
cinéma-peinture to be held in
Marseille, France, from 15
October 1989 to 14 January 1990.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
Jean Lacouture
Champollion, a hero of the Enlightenment
The French writer and journalist Jean Lacouture has travelled the world, notably covering major events in the emergence of the
former colonized peoples. He is also the author of major biographies* in which historical intuition and psychological analysis
are combined with outstanding reportorial talent. In this Unesco Courier interview he describes the intellectual odyssey of Jean-
François Champollion, a man in whom the ideals of Unesco seem to have found expression two centuries before their time.
Your portrait ofJean-François Champollion might have Third World in our time, with such outstanding people as
been specially designed to illustrate Unesco's mission of Taha Hussein, the son of an illiterate peasant and blind into
bringing the world's cultures into closer contact. Your hero's the bargain. Yet he became a university lecturer and then
short life was dominated by his determination to enable a minister, and his literary output was of the highest order.
Europeans to decipher the secrets of Egypt. A career like his, which went straight from almost total ig-
Champollion was born in 1790, towards the end of the norance to a masterly command of ideas and language, is
Enlightenment, of which he was one of the most worthy very striking and indeed moving,
heirs. He was born a few months before the first perfor¬
mance of Mozart's Magic Flute, that crowning glory of the To come back to Champollion, he must surely have had
civilization of the Enlightenment. quite exceptional ability and talent?
Yet he came from Figeac, a small town in the Quercy There were three sides to his genius. In the first place,
region of France, which had scarcely been touched by the he was a highly gifted linguist. In the field of Oriental Ian-
Enlightenment and was still shrouded in darkness. guages, his abilities were quite extraordinary. Before he was
I feel that it is quite staggering, almost Promethean, that fifteen, he had learnt Arabic, Hebrew, Persian, Geez, Syri-
Champollion should have been born in such circumstances, ac and Aramaic. In order to have something to do on Sun-
with a father who was a bookseller but had had little edu- days, he asked his brother to send him a Chinese grammar,
cation, and a mother who may well have been illiterate, and He had already made up his mind to decipher hieroglyphic
yet he should have torn himself away, little by little, from script and he felt that Chinese might prove useful in his
the ties of the land to step out into the world of communi- research. When he was fifteen he started to learn Coptic,
cation and knowledge. Admittedly, he embarked on his but we'll come back to that.
career with the help of his elder brother, who was some- He was also a dedicated historian. The lectures he gave
thing of a pathfinder. No pun intended, but it was his at the University of Grenoble have been found and they
brother who "oriented" him. They were a fascinating pair, show that he was already taking a critical approach to his-
The close rapport that grew up between them was one of tory, a discipline which was starting to equip itself with the
the main factors that prompted me to write the story of tools of scientific thinking.
Champollion. Thirdly, he was an artist, a man with a very keen aes-
The first ray of light in the life of Jean-François was his thetic sense, and that was to be a very important factor in
schooling in Grenoble, first at the lycée and then at the his attempts to decipher hieroglyphs. He was captivated and
university. This was the standard route by which it was pos- inspired by the beauty of Egyptian art. He already sensed
sible to climb the cultural ladder in the late eighteenth and that there was a fundamental link between the art and the
early nineteenth centuries. Champollion was to negotiate it writing of Egypt and that the script itself was an art form,
at prodigious speed. He arrived in Grenoble at the age of ten, His artistic sensibility was therefore to be one of the means
went to the lycée at thirteen and became a university profes- he used to penetrate the mysteries of hieroglyphic script,
sor at nineteen, after having studied at the Collège de France He continually progressed on the linguistic, historical and
and the Ecole Pratique des Langues Orientales in Paris. He aesthetic planes alike,
shot out of the darkness into the light like an arrow. Moreover, he was an extremely generous, warm-hearted
The same kind of lightning career can be seen in the man who loved his fellow men. It was perhaps because he
* Including his recent Champollion, une vie de lumières (Grasset publishers, had nad an Unhappy love-life that he projected OntO Egypt
Paris, 1988). Volume i of his 3-volume life of Charles de Gaulle was pub- the very deep affection he felt within himself and trans-
lished ¡n English in 1988 as Charles de Caulk: The Rebel by Holmes and r ir i . .L J " .. 1 L .L
Meier, New York, who have also published his biographies of lion Blum fo hlS l°Ving Urge mtO the desire to plumb the Secrets
(1982) and Pierre Mendès-France (1984). of that great civilization and identify with it.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
i
i
I
fe
' í#
1%.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Shouldn't his love for Egypt also be seen against the back¬
ground of his time?
It's true that Champollion grew up in a period marked
by what has been called "Egyptomania", when Egypt
aroused great interest. Eighteenth-century Europe was avid
for Egypt in all the senses of that term. Quite apart from
the colonial projects that were afoot and the looting of the
country's works of art, there was also, in many instances,
a disinterested passion for knowledge.
Colonial appetites were whetted by Egypt, as they were
by many other countries. However, Egypt appears to have
been the object of a special fascination, as if the Europe
of the Enlightenment had sensed that it held the secret of
a source of wisdom affecting the whole of mankind.
This period was, quite simply, a second Renaissance. The
_ first Renaissance, in the sixteenth century, had come about
through Europe's rediscovery of Graeco-Roman Antiqui¬
ty, while the second, in the eighteenth century, stemmed
frem its recognition of the ancient cultures of the eastern
seaboard of the Mediterranean, such as Assyria, Babylon,
Persia and, above all, Egypt. Europe was on the look-out
for other civilizations and was intent on discovering the en¬
tire world.
This is the deep-rooted significance of the spirit of the
Enlightenment. Mankind was one and indivisible. The
imprint of mankind should be sought everywhere. True
humanism was universal: it was no longer confined to
Europe, as it had been in the sixteenth century; it was
worldwide. Like Montesquieu and his Persians, Diderot
and his "Savages", and Rousseau and his natural man,
Champollion wondered who the real savages were when a
tribe of Osage Indians visited the Louvre.
What is more, as Champollion saw things, the world
existed not only in space but in time, across the centuries.
He recognized that, in the eighteenth century, mankind ex¬
isted in China, Morocco or Peru just as much as in France,
but also that mankind had existed forty-five centuries earli¬
er, when the Pyramids were being built. In deciphering hi¬
eroglyphs, he made a stupendous vertical breakthrough,
plumbing the depths of the universe and coming closer to
mankind's early roots. In so doing, he demolished many
preconceived notions about human origins.
In his view, Egypt occupied a fundamental place as a
matrix of history. He saw the first organized social unit as
having emerged in Egypt, the source of European civiliza¬
tion filtered through Greece.
It's important to remember that he had had first-hand
information on Egypt from a very early date, through
meeting people who had been there.
Among other things, European "Egyptomania" had
spawned Bonaparte's expedition! Opinions may differ on
the value of the different aspects of that expedition, but its
scientific contribution was clearly admirable. It produced
three treasures which gave rise to all subsequent research,
especially the decipherment of hieroglyphs. These were the
Description de l'Egypte, the illustrated report made by Vivant
Denon, and the Rosetta Stone.
In the first decade of the nineteenth century, people be¬
gan to draw inspiration from the works of Vivant Denon.
The Rosetta Stone began to be studied, and the Description
was published. It was around this time that Champollion
reached manhood. The coincidence between the blossom¬
ing of his own talents and the compilation of a stock of
detailed knowledge on Egypt was entirely fortuitous.
In addition, Champollion was fortunate enough to meet
three remarkable menFourier, Dom Raphael de Monachis
and Cheftitchiwho had been involved with Bonaparte's
expedition. Who could have imagined that Bonaparte would
have the preposterous idea of appointing Joseph Fourier,
the leading French physicist of his time and his companion
in Egypt, as Prefect at Grenoble, where he asked the Cham¬
pollion brothers to help him write the preface to the Descrip¬
tion? Or that Raphael de Monachis, a priest of Greek-Syrian
origin, would come to visit Fourier in Grenoble and make
the acquaintance of the brothers, thereby enabling Jean-
François to improve his Arabic? Or that a Coptic priest
named Cheftitchi would be appointed as an assistant at
a church near to where Jean-François lived? Champollion
was thus granted an opportunity of practising to his heart's
content that little-known language which, he was convinced,
was the key to everything. Champollion's command of the
Coptic language was to be an important factor in the advance
which he gained over his competitors in deciphering the hi¬
eroglyphs, since it was the spoken version of those same
hieroglyphs. No great discoveries are ever made without a
stroke of luck, and luck smiled generously on Jean-François.
Even so, he didn't start out from zero. Research had been
carried out earlier and others were working in the field...
Champollion was, of course, heir to what had gone be¬
fore him. That is true of all inventors. Nothing important
is ever discovered without the previous work of-pioneers
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
who may already have covered two-thirds or even three-
quarters of the ground. The first of his precursors was prob¬
ably Kircher who, as early as the seventeenth century, ad¬
vanced the hypothesis that the language spoken in the palaces
of the Pharaohs was the same as that still heard in psalms
sung in the Coptic churches of Cairo. This was a vital clue.
Drawing of an Egyptian
ornament taken from
Champollion's work
"Egyptian Pantheon, or
Collection of the
Mythological Figures of
Ancient Egypt" (1823-1825).
The second path was opened up by the Abbé Barthélé¬
my, who suggested that the "cartouches", or oval shapes
surrounding some groups of hieroglyphs, contained the
names of kings. Since there were only a few dozen names,
there was only a like number of possible readings in each
cartouche. And there were only a few cartouches in the hi¬
eroglyphic inscription on the Rosetta Stone, one of which
was known to contain the name of Ptolemy, since that name
was mentioned in the Greek translation of the inscription.
The third breakthrough came right at the end of the
eighteenth century, just before the actual discovery of the
Rosetta Stone, when Niebuhr and Zoéga came to the con¬
clusion that the hieroglyphs must contain a number of pho¬
netic values.
After the discovery of the stone, Silvestre de Sacy, the
leading Orientalist of the time, set about deciphering parts
of it. The Swedish diplomat Akerblad thought that it was
possible to draw up an alphabet of fifteen signs, and although
this was to prove unworkable, it enabled ideas on the sub¬
ject to move forward. Eventually, the great English physi¬
cist Thomas Young drew a spectacular comparison between
sets of Greek signs and hieroglyphs on the Rosetta Stone.
Young was the last and most brilliant of Champollion's
precursors. The findings he arrived at by inspired step-by-
step guesswork were ingenious. But there was no underly¬
ing method. It was Champollion who was to find the key
to the hieroglyphic system.
Young had managed to decipher the name of Ptolemy
on the Rosetta Stone more or less correctly. Champollion
adopted a more rigorous approach and found each of the
values composing that name, as well as the name of
Cleopatra. However, his most authentic discovery,
representing the real break with the trial and error methods
of the past, came with his decipherment of the classical Egyp¬
tian names of Ramses and Thothmes.
In what way was that revolutionary?
Until then, peopleprimarily Young, after the rough ap¬
proximations of Akerbladhad managed to read a few
names of Ptolemaic kings and queens, with signs that were
all phonetic, such as Ptolemy (p, t, 1, m) and Cleopatra (k,
1, p, t, r). Two things then seemed credible: that the hiero¬
glyphs were mainly phonetic, representing sounds, and that
they had been invented in the Ptolemaic period to translate
the names of contemporary sovereigns of Greek origin. In
short, the script was confined to that period of decline and
only made it possible to decipher the leftovers of Egyptian
civilization, without providing any clue to the writing of
that civilization at its zenith.
Champollion's revolution was based on two crucial dis¬
coveries, namely that the hieroglyphs were identical from
one Pharaonic era to another and that the underlying prin¬
ciple was that they were composed of a mixture of phonet¬
ic and ideographic elements. That was his "Eureka!". That
was the core of the discovery which led to the realization
that the phonetic approach adopted in the Ptolemaic peri¬
od was nothing more than a late simplification of a general
rule. It was also understood why it had proved so difficult
to find the key to the hieroglyphs. In fact there were two
keys: one phonetic and the other ideographic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
By whatpath did Champollion reach thatfateful moment
of discovery?
He reached it through deciphering the names of Thothmes
and Ramses, two kings from the great classical period of the
18th and 19th dynasties. He came face to face with the main
secret of the script. On a copy of one cartouche which had
been sent to him, he found a red disk, which was bound
to be an ideogram representing the sun. He translated it into
Coptic, which gave him the word Ra, and then, below the
disk, he found two signs with the phonetic values "m" and
"s", giving "mses". By pairing the ideographic and phonetic
values, he came up with "Ramses". In the case of Thothmes,
the ideogram was an ibis, which represented the god Thoth,
with the same two phonetic values "m" and "s". This took
place on 14 September 1822.
Other pieces of the jigsaw fell into place in quick suc¬
cession. Champollion noticed that some words were writ¬
ten from left to right, and others from right to left. He also
discovered that some signs were there merely to signify
gender or a family of meaning. This was how he realized
that Hatshepsut was a woman. The identification of the de¬
terminative signs was another fundamental feature of the
decipherment process.
So the celebrated date of14 September 1822 was a tremen¬
dous moment, the point when he suddenly realized that he
had grasped it all?
Yes. It was a moment of incredible intensity for him. He
had discovered the principle, the key. But he had no sooner
announced the news to his brother than he fell into a sort of
trance. He lay prostrate, as though he had been over¬
whelmed, as if the fantastic sum of the efforts he had made
over a period of twenty years had triggered off an explosion,
like a terrifying discharge which condemned him to exhaus¬
tion and total emptiness, now that the goal had been attained.
Yet it was not all over. There still lay before him the
formidable task of drawing all the conclusions from the
discovery and of systematizing them.
Naturally. But there were two other moments of extreme
intensity in his life. These were when, armed with his dis¬
covery, he went first to Italy and then to Egypt, in search
of the civilization on which he had shed light and which
he was to read like an open book.
In the first place, during his visit to Turin to examine
the wealth of Egyptian treasures in the museum there, he
discovered the beauty of Egyptian art. His reaction was one
of pure emotion. In Paris, the linguist had won the day, but
in Turin it was the aesthete who was overwhelmed. It was
not long before the historian, in his turn, was excited by
the piles of papyri which nobody before him had been able
to decipher.
But there was another dramatic moment, which he
described in a passage worthy of Chateaubriand: the papyri
were so fragile that they crumbled into dust as soon as he
touched them. We can well imagine the feeling that took
hold of him. There he was, so near to his goal, with all the
skills needed to discover, in each of those documents, a page
of history that had lain buried for thousands of years, and
then that page disintegrated in his hands. All those dynasties
that were reunited before his eyes were decomposed in a
flash. It was both marvellous and terrifying for him.
Champollion tells us that these papyri had been taken
from their natural environment. They had been produced
in Egypt from an indigenous plant and were meant to be
covered and kept in bamboo canisters, but here they were,
instead, placed in packing cases, tossed about for weeks on
end on the sea voyage, exposed to the deadly effects of
humidity, and dumped any old how in the rooms of the
Turin museum. Fortunately, museum science has made
progress since then...
Then came, at long last, the voyage to Egypt, where the
country, its light and its people revealed themselves to him.
It was as if his decipherment of the hieroglyphs had
miraculously opened a door to Egypt and enabled him to
identify with its civilization.
The comparison that comes to my mind is with the great
mystics. When Champollion entered the Hypostyle Hall
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Kjkampollion's camp at Philae is depicted in this
watercolour by Nestor L'Hôte, an artist who
accompanied the great French Egyptologist on his
expedition to Egypt in 1828-1829.
or when he descended into the tomb of Ramses VI or of
Seth I, I think that he felt the emotion of a mystic discover¬
ing the countenance of Christ. It was not so much the cul¬
minating point of his work as the crowning glory of his life.
His decipherment of the hieroglyphs gave him a direct in¬
sight into Egyptian civilization. The monuments spoke to
him through their very beauty. He saw their architecture
as a kind of prayer, a form of expression responding to that
of the hieroglyphs. As he said in one of his letters: "Egypti¬
an statuary is a simplified form of hieroglyphic writing."
Whenever a Pharaoh built a temple to his own glory,
the symbolic language he used was more direct and posi¬
tive than that of a cathedral. There was a physical link be¬
tween the art and the writing of the Egyptians. Champollion
threw himself heart and soul into substantiating this idea.
He spent eighteen months in Egypteighteen extraordinary
months during which he went back across the centuries and
fathomed the innermost meaning of Egyptian civilization.
In this setting, the cry he uttered on 14 September 1822 be¬
came a magnificent hymn to knowledge. But it was also to
be his swansong.
What makes that hymn even more moving is the fact
that it projected on Egyptian civilization a beam of light
which swept away a number of preconceived ideas about
Judeo-Christian civilization and which conveyed to Europe
a message glimpsed in the eighteenth century but perhaps not
very well received in the nineteenththat Egypt was the
cradle not only of human history but of religious thought.
Could monotheism have been invented in Egypt? Such
a hypothesis is often accepted. However that may be, the
great Christian Trinity seems to have been founded on that
of Osiris, Isis and Horus. The originality of Christian dog¬
ma is thus called into question. Champollion sparked off
a genuine cultural and spiritual revolution. He clearly felt
this himself, just at the time when he was returning to the
Christian fold. His Song of Egypt was not altogether free
of a note of anguish.
Moreover, Champollion's dialogue was not only with
ancient temples, but with the flesh-and-blood Egyptian
people, with the Egypt of his time.
That's true. Not only was he appalled by the state of op¬
pression and dire poverty to which the Egyptian people were
reduced, but he ran the risk of speaking openly about it to
the Pashanot the most obvious course to take. Muham¬
mad Ali had received him cordially and had allowed him
to go wherever he liked in the country for as long as he
likedand remember that this was scarcely one year after
Egypt had suffered the debacle of the Battle of Navarino
against the French and English fleets. Champollion could
therefore have simply turned a blind eye to the situation,
since his mission was not a humanitarian one. But he chose
not to. Shocked by the sufferings of the Egyptian people,
he made a point of voicing his dismay to Muhammad Ali.
The example he set was not followed by every Orientalist.
He also drafted a fourteen-point memorandum on "the
safeguarding of the monuments of Egypt", a document in
advance of its time. He had very strong views on the need
for the in situ protection of the monuments at their origi¬
nal sites and, above all, on the need to respect the right of
Egyptians to keep their masterpieces of art in their own
country. Some years earlier, when the zodiac in the Tem¬
ple of Hathor at Dendera had been dragged out and shipped
to France to be erected in Paris, Champollion had written
that the best home for the monument was at Dendera itself.
Nor should we forget the plans which Champollion
made for the Egypt of his time, such as the proposal to ex¬
plore the sources of the Nile which he put to Ibrahim Pasha.
The idea of suggesting a peaceful scientific expedition to that
great warrior seems to me to be worthy of the spirit of the
Enlightenment and far ahead of its time.
The two hundredth anniversary of Champollion's birth
will be commemorated in 1790. The time is ripe for a
celebration and I imagine that Unesco will be marking the
occasion.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
E I T 0 R I A L
S
A scene from the film
Alien (1979).
INCE Homo sapiens first trod the earth some five hundred thousand years ago
mankind has been torn between an instinctive fear of the unknown and an
unquenchable thirst for knowledge. For early man all that was unknown was hostile.
The unseen was a menacing presence that lay in wait for the unwary. Only within
the familiar ordered confines of the clan was safety to be found.
Today the bounds of the known world have been extended to their limits, the
frontiers of knowledge have been pushed back and contacts and exchanges with others
have multiplied beyond all expectations. Everywhere men have come to acknowledge
the existence of their fellow men and the destinies of communities and individuals
have become interlinked on a worldwide scale.
The cinema, one of the major art forms of this century, has played an important
role in this process and in making us more fully aware of the diversity of the human
condition. It has shown us the splendours of the Taj Mahal and the Pyramids, the
onion-shaped domes of Moscow, the temples of the Maya, the skyscrapers of New
York. We have seen great cities devastated by earthquake, fire and flood, peoples
decimated by famine and all the man-made horrors of war. We feel that we are
beginning to know what other peoples are like, what they love and what they fear.
Nevertheless, even today, "others" too often continue to be, if not totally unknown,
at least strangers and potential enemies. For this too the cinema bears some
responsibility. The eye behind the camera sometimes sees and records happenings
that seem to confirm our deeply-ingrained prejudices. It would seem that we still
feel threatened by "others", that the need remains to continue to set up boundaries,
to draw demarcation lines, to mark out for ourselves and for our kind a clearly
defined territorywhether physical, spiritual or psychologicalfrom which "others"
are excluded.
We need not despair. More and more film-makers are rejecting facile, stereotypic
representations and showing us the kinship that underlies the glory and the wonder
of the human pageant. The barriers of taboos and fears are being torn down to reveal
"others" miraculously transformed into "brothers".
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Extraterrestrial
phenomena created
for the screen by
directors from
Méliès to Spielberg
often reflect human
fears and anxieties.
Creatures
from inner space
i
12
F it is accepted that science fiction is a literary
form that has existed since Antiquity, then ex¬
traterrestrial phenomena or "ETs", can also be
acknowledged as enjoying the same venerable sta¬
tus. Admittedly, the travellers in the ancient
Greek satirist Lucian's Vera Historia (True Histo¬
ry) and in the seventeenth-century French writer
Cyrano de Bergerac's L'Autre Monde (A Voyage
to the Moon with some account ofthe Solar World)
visited only the Sun and the Moon, the two most
familiar heavenly bodies. But the ET in Voltaire's
Micromégas (1752) came from the star Sirius
whence his rather special outlook. These imagi¬
nary creatures were simply a mouthpiece for their
creators' political, metaphysical or psychological
ideas.
Terrifying ETs which had lives of their own
first appeared in the late nineteenth century in
the stories of H.G. Wells. Their aggressiveness,
as in the case of the Martians in The War of the
Worlds (1897), was a reflection of the imperialis¬
tic currents of the time. This trend persisted for
several decades, at least in the Western world.
Around this time, the extraterrestrial made
its début in the cinema, then in its infancy. In
his celebrated film Le voyage dans la lune ("Trip
to the Moon", 1902), the French director Georges
Méliès depicted the Moon itself as being endowed
with life. After Méliès, who was primarily in¬
terested in magical effects, came the age of the
comic strip and the film cartoon. But the worlds
visited by Flash Gordon and Buck Rogers were
still very like the real world.
Then came the memorable day30 October
1938when Orson Welles terrified millions of
American listeners when he announced during
a radio programme based on H.G. Wells's War
1 oster for Spielberg's E.T.
(1982), in which a crew
member ofan alien
spacecraft is left behind
in a Los Angeles
suburb and makes friends
with a small boy.
BY CLAUDE AZIZA
ofthe Worlds that invaders from "Mars had land¬
ed. Behind these imaginary Martians it was pos¬
sible to glimpse the dark scourge looming on the
other side of the Atlantic.
The war followed, with its horrors and ob¬
sessions, including spy mania. Then, around 1947,
flying saucers began to be spotted at every street
corner. With the coming of the Cold War, hordes
of creatures from outer space invaded cinema
screens, setting a pattern for the next ten years
or more.
The scene was set in 1950 with Kurt Neu¬
mann's Rocketship X-M, which depicted Martians
who had lapsed into the barbarous practices of
the Stone Age. Thereafter, ETs were uniformly
belligerent and repulsive, from the slimy invaders
of Byron Haskin's The War ofthe Worlds (1953),
which was based on H.G. Wells's novel, to the
giant octopuses of Val Guest's The Quatermass Ex¬
periment (1955), the first in a series of adventures
featuring Professor Quatermass, and the
gelatinous mass in Irwin S. Yeaworth's The Blob
(1958).
Some films were less far-fetched, and some¬
times not without ambiguity. In Edgar G. Ul-
mer's The Man from Planet X (1951), the solitary
ET which lands on the Earth and dies there is
actually the forerunner of a coming invasion.
There are both good and bad ETs in Joseph New¬
man's This Island Earth (1955). Robert Wise's The
Day the Earth Stood Still (1951) is the only film
of the period with something positive to say, in
the sense that its hero, Klatoo, brings a message
of peace from another planet.
In the 1960s, détente was the order of the day.
Even though the hideous ET persisted here and
there, times were changing. Japanese films still
showed ETs avid for flesh, as in Inoshiro Hon¬
da's Chikyu Boeigun ("Prisoners of the Martians",
1958), Italian film-goers shuddered when they saw
Mario Bava's Terrore nello spazio (1965), and in
Britain hideous plants were intent on destroying
the human race in Steve Sekely's The Day of the
Triffids (1962), based on a novel by John Wynd-
ham. Americans, however, were already smiling
at the amorous antics of an ET and a pretty
rock'n'roller in T. Graef's The Teenagers from
Outer Space (1959), being moved by a strange
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
In The Day the Earth
Stood Still (1951), Klatoo
(centre) arrives on Earth
from another planet with a
message ofpeace.
CLAUDE AZIZA,
of France, teaches Latin and
history of the cinema at the
University of Paris III
(Sorbonne-Nouvelle). He
writes regularly on the
cinema for the French daily
Le Monde, and has
contributed to a special
issue of CinémAction
magazine on religious films
(October 1988) and to the
catalogue for the Festival of
Biblical Cinema held in
Paris in March 1988.
visitor in H. Green's The Cosmic Man (1959), and
splitting their sides with laughter at the blunders
committed by a Martian played by Jerry Lewis
in Visit to a Small Planet (1959). Had the ET
finally been tamed, domesticated, humanized?
People may have come to realize that political
enemies, whether within or without, were less
dangerous than the enemy stalking in their
unconscious. This was the message, albeit clothed
in symbolism, that was hinted at as early as 1956
in F. McLeod Wilcox's Forbidden Planet.
Aliens and monsters
ETs accordingly seemed to have been discarded
among the unused props, as films began to reflect
the realistic approach demanded by the conquest
of space. Stanley Kubrick's 2001: A Space Odyssey
(1968) marked the end of an era of far-fetched sci-fi
films and raised metaphysical questions amidst a
profusion of scientific detail.
But what science fiction writers called the
"hard science" of the conquest of space did not
satisfy young film-goers who had grown up with
space travel and looked in vain for the fantasy
which their parents had enjoyed. In an effort to
win them over, there was a return to the epic
form. George Lucas's Star Wars (1977) rekindled
childhood dreams and revived medieval legends.
Only a short step separates the epic from mysti¬
cism, and that step was taken by Steven Spielberg
in his Close Encounters of the Third Kind (1977),
in which he retold the Bible in his own fashion,
and subsequently in E.T. (1982), his version of the
New Testament. As the Christ-figure of the space
age with limitless powers, capable of dying and
of coming back to life, the film's hero brought
tears to American eyes. Would ETs now be part
of a world of wisdom and humanism? That was
unfortunately not to be, for new causes of anxiety
were starting to emerge.
The end of the millennium promised to be
apocalyptic. Fear of others was personified in the
"alien", a term which was to have considerable
success and was first used in 1979 in Ridley Scott's
film of that title, in which a monster from outer
space conceals itself in the entrails of its victim.
A year earlier, similar alien creatures had lived
off the brains of human beings transformed into
vegetables in Philip Kaufman's Invasion of the
Body Snatchers. In John Carpenter's The Thing
(1982), the creature is capable of adapting to and
assuming the appearance of all forms of life.
People can no longer trust each other and are
condemned to live with the threat of imminent
annihilation.
Aliens (the title, incidentally, of the sequel
to Carpenter's film, made by James Cameron in
1986) sprouted everywhere, harking back to the
tradition of the 1950s but borrowing the most
gruesome aspects of the popular horror film.
These films covered the whole gamutfrom the
metamorphosis of fathers (H. Broomley Daven¬
port's XTRO, 1986), to menaced progeny (Nor¬
man J. Warren's Inseminoid, 1980), vampires
from outer space (Tobe Hooper's Life Force, 1985)
and a ferocious monster (J. McTierman's Preda¬
tor, 1987). And then to cap it all along came Jack
Sholder's Hidden (1988), in which the Earth is
simply a vast outlet for the aggressive instincts
of an ET which even turns to bank robbery.
A few films have attempted to portray friend¬
ly child ETs (John Hough's Return from Witch
Mountain, 1978), meetings between human and
ET teenagers (Joe Dante's Explorers, 1985), and
understanding visitors who can restore lost youth
(Ron Howard's Cocoon, 1985, and its sequel,
Daniel Patrie's Return ofCocoon, 1988). ETs have
even taken the form of glamorous blondes that
Earthlings can marry, as in Richard Benjamin's
My Stepmother is an Alien (1988).
But, on the threshold of the 1990s, there is
a persistent sense of danger. It may be a danger
that has infiltrated society from within, as in John
Carpenter's They Live (1988), or it may come
from outside, from Martians seeking regeneration
through nuclear energy in the aptly titled televi¬
sion series Contamination, or the New War ofthe
Worlds, made by Colin Chilvers and Winrich
Kolbe in 1988. In the same year Tobe Hooper's
Invadersfrom Mars and Chuck Russell's The Blob
were again on the rampage.
Fortunately, there is some humour among all
these atrocities. In addition to Martians, a come¬
dy by Patrick Read in which the Martians, after
hesitating, decide to take control of Earth, F.
Brown's novel Martians Go Home!, a crazy farce
based on the fantasies of a science fiction writer,
is being adapted for the screen. Such fantasies in¬
spire the thousand-and-one metamorphoses of
ETs, those ambivalent creatures spawned by the
anguish, hopes and repressions latent in every
society. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Macunaïma,
the eternal outsider
From a Brazilian
film-maker, a fable
about individualism
told through the
astonishing
adventures of a
protean hero.
I
BY ANTONIO RODRIGUES
14
N a structured, well-defined society it is easy
to pick out the outsider, the person who is differ¬
ent from everyone else. In France, the United
Kingdom or the Federal Republic of Germany,
the cinema returns repeatedly to the theme of im¬
migration, turning out naturalistic films about
second-generation immigrants. The latter are seen
as foreigners, outsiders, since a clear, if arbitrary,
line of demarcation still separates them from the
local population.
The situation is more complicated in emerg¬
ing countries or in mixed societies. In Brazil, for
example, on the outer edge of the Western world,
a variety of races, cultures and ways of life which
span the archaic and the modern coexist side by
side. Brazil is European in its language, its legal
code and some of its customs, but African in its
beliefs and patterns of everyday life. In this
melting-pot almost anyone could see his neigh¬
bour as an outsider and no one is truly represen¬
tative of any particular social category.
The film Macunaïma, made in 1969 by Joa-
quim Pedro de Andrade (1932-1988), has become
a classic of modern Latin American cinema pre¬
cisely because it succeeded in conveying the cu¬
rious state of "generalized otherness" that exists
in Brazil. One of the merits of the filma fable
in which, provided that you can interpret a few
clues, Brazilian society can easily be recognized
is that it can be understood by and is attractive
to film-goers who have only a superficial
knowledge of Brazil.
The hero, Macunaïma, is a black man born
into an Indian tribe. One day he decides to set
out with his brothers for the big city. On the
way, he walks through a magic fountain and
miraculously turns white (one of his brothers,
who arrives too late, only has the palms of his
hands and the soles of his feet turn white). On
reaching Rio de Janeiro, he has a number of ad¬
ventures. He marries a woman guerrilla fighter,
is widowed and then tries to steal a talisman from
a rich giant. Finally, tired of it all, he returns to
the jungle with a whole range of consumer goods
(air-conditioners, refrigerators, etc.). Caught up
once more in a life of idleness, he ends up being
devoured by a river siren.
The film is an adaptation of a novel of the
same name by Mario de Andrade, published
in 1928. However, the director filled out the
story with new episodes (those concerning the 1 oster for Macunaïma.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
GRANDE ÓTELO PAULO JOSE JRRDB- ffl&
ÄUNflii
£¡¡L RODOLFO AREN« W^ON CO"
TA GOSTOSO,
CORAÇÂQ.TA?
! \!A V
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
NLacunaïma's mother
carries her young son on
her shoulders.
Alacunai'ma's mother and
sister-in-law outside a straw
hut.
Alacunai'ma's enemy, the
capitalist (left) throws a
party.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
guerrillas were of topical interest in Brazil in
1969), and left out passages in the book that were
primarily of linguistic interest. Furthermore, he
adopted the typical stylé of a certain class of
comic film popular in Brazil, particularly in the
sequence dealing with the birth of Macunaïma
and in regard to the physical appearance of the
giant.
Thus the mainspring of Macunaïma, in the
words of its director "a Brazilian film devoured
by Brazil", is otherness.
In turn Indian, Black and White, savage and
city-dweller, proletarian and profiteer, Macunaï¬
ma never belongs to a clear-cut category. He is
always an outsider, even though he seems at ease
in all situations. The notion of otherness implies
a clash between cultures, a confrontation, or at
least a sense of difference. In Macunaïma there
is no clash. The hero goes from one extreme to
the other, from a poverty-stricken tribe to the
financial district of Rio de Janeiro, a city which
he reaches in a truck full of immigrant workers
and in which he mixes with prostitutes, terrorists
who die through their own carelessness (they do
not know how to handle their bombs), and
greedy industrialists. However, Macunaïma is not
just a passive, disillusioned onlooker observing
the world in which he finds himself. Even though
his primary objective is the search for easy pick¬
ings (he becomes a kept man and, to acquire
riches, attempts to steal the giant's talisman), he
takes part, in his own fashion, in the life of the
very different circles in which he moves.
This social mobility and his succession of ap¬
parently disconnected adventures find their own
logic within the context of an extravagant, ex¬
uberant fable. The film tells a story with a be¬
ginning, a middle and an end, with episode
following episode in a far from haphazard
order. Macunaïma is a piece of story-telling rather
than the illustration of a thesis.
The only world to which the hero really be¬
longs is his family, which consists of the entire
tribe into which he was born. Outside this fami¬
ly he constantly finds himself face to face with
a world which he distrusts and in which he sees
only adversaries. Macunaïma takes each succes¬
sive adventure as it comes. A brothel or the
guerrilla girl's hiding-place are for him no more
than provisional, interchangeable stopping-places,
where, with no concern for others' motives, he
looks to his own immediate interests. It is as if
the words of the truck driver who took him to
Rio are still ringing in his ears: "Now it's every
man for himself and the devil take the hindmost."
He is the eternal outsider, never putting down
roots or becoming integrated anywhere. He is the
At the end of the film,
Macunaïma (right) returns
to his tribe from Rio de
Janeiro with a load of
modern gadgets.
new arrival, always embarking on some new en¬
terprise which will never be carried through to
the end. Macunaïma never acquires any more
than a superficial knowledge of those he meets
and himself remains unaffected by these encoun¬
ters. He looks no further than the immediate, all-
devouring present, until the day when he him¬
self is devoured. Not knowing what he is seek¬
ing, he follows his chosen path unquestioningly.
The comic tone of the film and its presenta¬
tion as a fable conceals a deeper truthwe are
hostile or indifferent to outsiders because we do
not know what motivates them. Macunaïma is
not a solitary hero in the style of the wandering
cowboy or lawman of the western; he lives only
for the moment and is constantly having to save
his skin in a world which, in the words of the
director of the film, "is essentially cannibalistic".
For Macunaïma, as for all those without code
or creed and entirely absorbed by themselves,
other people are always an impenetrable mystery
and the world is opaque. Everyone else is
"Them".
ANTONIO RODRIGUES
is a Brazilian film critic
based in Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Although
sometimes drawn as
stereotypes,
German characters
in French films are
often portrayed far
more subtly.
Germans screened
through French eyes
BY RENE PREDAL
18
JL HERE is nothing in French cinema like Ger¬
mania anno zero (1947), in which the Italian direc¬
tor Roberto Rossellini portrayed the material and
spiritual ruins of post-war Germany. Nor is there
anything comparable to All Quiet on the Western
Front (1930), the American director Lewis Mile¬
stone's film version of Erich Maria Remarque's
novel about life in the German trenches of World
War I. There is certainly nothing similar to The
Desert Fox (1951), the film in which another
American director, Henry Hathaway, attempt¬
ed to restore the reputation of Field Marshal
Rommel.
French film-makers do not find it easy to put
themselves in alien shoes, especially when that
alien is a German. Similarly, German roles in
French films are almost always played not by
French actors but by actors of Germanic origin.
Whereas the English actor James Mason played
Rommel in Hathaway's film, the German roles
in Les dimanches de Ville-d'Avray (Serge Bourguig¬
non, 1963) and Lefranciscain de Bourges (Claude
Autant-Lara, 1968) were played by Hardy
Kruger. The bluff intriguing figure of Curt Jür¬
gens became familiar as the German in countless
French-made thrillers; Jess Hahn featured as a
German musician who became a tramp in the
Parisian summer of Le signe du lion (Eric Roh-
mer, 1959); and Gert Froebe was often cast in the
role of the fat, antipathetic German.
Erich von Stroheim carved out for himself
an unusual film career, playing noble, generous
soldiers in La grande illusion (Jean Renoir, 1937)
and Macao, l'enfer du jeu (Jean Delannoy, 1939)
and civilians driven out of Germany by the nazis
in films such as Les disparus de Saint-Agil
(Christian-Jaque, 1938) and Pièges (Robert
Siodmak, 1939).
The nazi as evil personified
French spy films made during the 1930s were
often set outside a specific historical time-frame,
and adversaries were generally treated with
xl scene from French
director Serge
Bourguignon's Les
. dimanches de Ville-
d'Avray (1963), which
describes the friendship
between a former German
pilot suffering from
amnesia (Hardy Kruger)
and a nine-year-old French
girl (Patricia Gozzi).
JTrançois Truffaut's film
Jules et Jim (1962) tells the
story of two friends, an
Austrian (Oskar Werner,
right) and a Frenchman
(Henri Serre) and their
constantly shifting
triangular relationship with
Catherine (Jeanne Moreau).
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
.
»r
is>
M
v»ÉÎ8r
ks£Ê
}
/
1*+*-:
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
1 he friendship between a
captured French officer
(Pierre Fresnay, left) and
the commandant of his
German prison (Erich von
Stroheim) is portrayed in
Jean Renoir's masterpiece
La grande illusion (1937).
chivalrous respect (Deuxième bureau, Pierre
Billon, 1935; Les loups entre eux and L'homme à
abattre, Léon Mathot, 1936-1937; Le capitaine
Benoît, Maurice de Canonge, 1939). Nazism
changed this situation totally.
A shadowy figure whose presence made it¬
self felt in deserted places and in the eyes of his
victims (Nuit et brouillard, Alain Resnais, 1955),
the nazi boss personified the horror of the con¬
centration camp, both in the extraordinary but
true odyssey of Martin Gray (Au nom de tous les
miens, Robert Enrico, 1983) and in Armand
Gatti's L'Enclos (1961).
In' Le sauveur (Michel Mardore, 1971), a
German played by Horst Bucholz passes himself
off as an English parachutist in order to penetrate
the Resistance. He succeeds in this by seducing
and then subjugating an adolescent girl whom he
induces to commit betrayals, with terrible con¬
sequences. In Jacques Rouffio's La passante du
Sans-Souci (1981), based on a novel by Joseph
Kessel, the odious Von Leggaert kills during the
war the father of a small boy whom he maims
for life. He also orders the execution of a liberal-
minded editor and his wife, who had given her¬
self to him in an attempt to save her husband.
Returning several years later as a successful in¬
dustrialist, he is killed by his former victim.
In Shoah (1985), Claude Lanzrnann questions
nazis who participated in the holocaust, and
Klaus Barbie is the subject of another cinéma-
vérité inquiry in Hôtel Terminus (Marcel Ophuls,
1987). Twenty years earlier there had already
been an evocation (this, though, was far from be
ing "direct" cinema) of the trial of Adolf Eich-
mann in La cage de verre (Philippe Arthuys, 1965),
as well as the disquieting Authentique procès de
Carl-EmmanuelJung (Marcel Hanoun, 1966), in
which the characters and the judgement were fic¬
titious but exemplary.
Whereas the Jewish tragedy was treated with
deep respect, the story of the Wehrmacht was
deliberately lampooned in a series of mediocre
comedies in which French cinema practised a clas¬
sic form of compensation therapy. The histori¬
cal fact was that the French army had been
defeated, and script-writers rehashed again and
again the story of isolated individuals who, in the
midst of general pandemonium, use their French
resourcefulness to run rings round German sto¬
lidity. In Papy fait de la Résistance (Jean-Marie
Poiré, 1983) a French grandpa works for the
Resistance under the very nose of fat Marshal
Von Apfelstrudel (Jacques Villeret); in La vache
et le prisonnier (Henri Verneuil, 1959), a French
prisoner of war, played by Fernandel, crosses
Germany with a cow; in La grande vadrouille
(Gérard Oury, 1966) Bourvil and Louis de Funès
succeed in crossing the enemy lines, as do the
squaddies in Mais où est donc passée la septième
compagnie? (Robert Lamoureux, 1973).
The occupation
"Occupation" films constitute a sub-category of
their own among French war films. Members of
the occupying forces appear in minor roles in
often interesting productions such as Léon Morin
20
RENE PREDAL,
of France, is professor of
communications science at
Stendhal University,
Grenoble. He is the author
of many books, studies and
articles on French cinema.
His most recent published
work is Dictionnaire des 900
cinéastes français
("Dictionary of 900 French
Film-makers").
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
1 he Gestapo raids a
French school in Louis
Malle's Au revoir les
enfants (1987), a film based
on an episode from the
director's own childhood.
prêtre (Jean-Pierre Melville, 1961) and Un sac de
bilks (Jacques Doillon, 1976).
However, in other films about the occupa¬
tion, such as Lacombe Lucien (Louis Malle, 1974),
Les violons du bal (Michel Drach, 1974), Les
guichets du Louvre (Michel Mitrani, 1973) and Mr
Klein (Joseph Losey, 1976), "the villains are not
German but French and their cruelty is less phys¬
ical than verbal and indirect ... There are no nazi
brutes, a decision which was less an evasion than
a desire to redefine the enemy ... since the Jews
of Paris lived in greater fear of being denounced
by the French than of German bullets."1
This statement is not always supported by the
evidence. In Les honneurs de la guerre (Jean
Dewever, 1961), for reasons of military honour,
a German officer refuses to withdraw without a
fight at the time of the pull-back of August 1944
and causes a pointless slaughter. And in Au revoir
les enfants (Louis Malle, 1987), the Gestapo tracks
down Jewish children to send them to the death
1. Quotation from
L'holocauste à l'écran,
by Annette Insdorf,
Editions du Cerf, Paris, 1985.
camps. Although Dewever treats the members of
the Resistance hidden in the church no better
than he does the German officer, Louis Malle
depicts a German officer who, to please a pretty
woman, sends packing a French militiaman who
wants to eject a Jew from the restaurant in which
they are dining.
Dissociated from their nazi leaders, the Ger¬
man people are often portrayed sympathetically
by French film-makers. In Le passage du Rhin
(André Cayatte, 1960) Roger, a wartime prisoner
at the Kessler farm in Germany, returns there of
his own accord to rediscover love and dignity.
In Le franciscain de Bourges, Claude Autant-
Lara pays a noble tribute to the saintly friar-nurse
Alfred Stanke. Edgardo Cozarinsky's La guerre
d'un seul homme (1982) gives a picture of occupied
France in which official shots from French news-
reels are combined with disillusioned comments
from the diaries of Ernst Jünger, a German officer
in Parisa unique example of a film in which the 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
leading character is a German portrayed "from
inside".
In a number of iconoclastic films, Germans
are even shown, despite the dramatic circum¬
stances, involved in flirtations, as in Jean-Paul
Rappenau's La vie de château (1965), or caught
up in a Cornelian dilemma, like the German in
Le silence de la mer (Jean-Pierre Melville, 1949,
based on a novel by Vercors), who is uneasy in
the role of occupier and turns away from passion¬
ate love to bury himself in solitude. The German
soldier in Hiroshima mon amour (Alain Resnais,
1959, from a screenplay by Marguerite Duras)
embodies youth and love, but also intolerable
suffering. So often the executioner, the German
here, on the contrary, is an expiatory victim of
the war.
Many French films, therefore, seek out the
man behind the German uniform. Even the
historical inquiry in Le chagrin et la pitié (Marcel
Ophiils, 1969) opens with the wedding in Ger¬
many of the daughter of a Wehrmacht captain
who as a young man had been stationed in
Clermont-Ferrand between 1942 and 1944, thus
attempting to bring together the army and
civilian society, past and present, without any
trace of manichaeism.
This insistence on human complexity is even
more evident in The Memory ofJustice (1976), a
film about the Nuremberg trials in which the
director, Marcel Ophiils, son of the German film¬
maker Max Ophiils and married to a German
woman who was a member of the Hitler Youth
organization, does not hesitate to implicate him-
Alain Delon and Juliet
Berto in a scene from
Joseph Losey's Mr Klein
(1976), a study on the
theme of identity,
indifference and the search
for truth.
c
~ mj /
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
hiiji Okada and
Emmanuelle Riva play the
lead roles in Hiroshima
mon amour (Alain
Resnais, 1959).
self directly. Nazism is thus shown in terms of
its impact on everyday life and not simply as an
ideological concept.
Philippe Nahoun's Une fille unique, which
also appeared in 1976, drew a complex and rather
disquieting fictional portrait. During the summer
of 1935, Sophie, bored and tired of her husband,
a militant communist, becomes attracted to Tho¬
mas, a young German Jew who accidentally kills
a fascist. Thomas comes to exercise a strange fas¬
cination on her. To a journalist who asked why
the young woman should be drawn out of her
humdrum life by a man who happened to be a
both a Jew and a German, Nahoun replied: "be¬
cause it was horrible to be a German Jew in
1935."2 After the black and white judgements of
other films, this work examines nuances that are
too often reserved for portrayals of national
heroes.
In Menaces (1939) Erich von Stroheim played
the role of a poor lodger in a small Paris hotel.
This was the first in a succession of characters
who projected an unexpected image of the Ger¬
man as vulnerable and humiliated. The story of
a former pilot who returns from the war suffer¬
ing from amnesia and attempts to recover a
precarious happiness with a nine-year-old girl,
Les dimanches de Ville-d'Avray, despite occasion¬
al stylistic affectations, is a sensitive film. This
man, a stranger to himself, joins forces with some¬
one else who is excluded from society in an at¬
tempt to build a better world.
Similarly, the character of the Austrian Jules,
m Jules et Jim (François Truffaut, 1962, based on
a novel by Henry-Pierre Roché), is richer and
more profoundly explored than that of his
French friend Jim. He is the first to be deceived
by the woman that they both love, and it is he
who is left when Catherine commits suicide, tak¬
ing Jim to his death with her.
Unlike the German tourist of Ascenseur pour
l'échafaud (Louis Malle, 1957), murdered by a
young car thief who finds him unpleasant, the
young geologist in La maison des borles (Jacques
Doniol-Valcroze, 1969) is the epitome of Ger¬
manic seductiveness; Matthieu Carrière glows
with sun-drenched romanticism opposite Marie
Dubois as the virtuous wife of a man who does
not deserve her.
On the whole, therefore, portrayals of Ger¬
mans in French cinema are less stereotyped than
one might have been led to believe.
. Philippe Nahoun in Cinéma 76, No. 215, November 1976. 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24
Western cinema's
distorted image of
the Arab as a
mysterious and
often shifty figure
from a world of
harems and palm
trees has still not
faded from the
screen.
JXudolph Valentino,
superstar of the silent
screen, in The Son of the
Sheik (1926), one
of the films that created
the stock Hollywood image
of the Arab.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
^
An Orient of myth
and mystery
An alluring picture of the
Orient of the Arabian
Nights is presented in
Jacques Becker's version of
Ali Baba and the 40
Thieves (1960) starring
Fernandel and the Egyptian
dancer Samia Gamal.
BY ABBAS FAHDEL
X HE picture of the Arab in Western cinema is
often a product of fantasy and imagination,
reflecting the West's fascination with and fear of
the Arab Muslim East, that other world so near
and yet so far.
This colourful, mysterious and exaggerated
picture, this Orient made in Hollywood, Paris,
or Rome, would perhaps be less offensive if it was
not peopled by rascally and barbaric Arabs, recog¬
nizable by their shifty looks and dissolute man¬
ner. They are hot-tempered and always seem on
the point of whipping out a dagger. Lustful and
polygamous, they like to kidnap young Western
girls and sequestrate them in their harems.
In fact, Western cinema is no more than a
reflection of widespread prejudices, some of them
dating back to the Crusades, which were widely
held under colonial rule, when, after all, North
Africa was known as the Barbary Coast.
If some films such as Morocco, Casablanca, Un
de la Légion, and The Lost Patrol purport to be
set on Arab soil yet contrive not to show a sin¬
gle Arab, in others Arabs have walk-on parts and
provide a splash of local colour, along with the
minarets, palm trees and camels.
Even so, the range of roles played by male
Arab actors is wider than that available to Arab
women. A man can be a valet, a shoeshine boy,
a guide, a snake charmer, a looter or even an
official, whereas a woman is limited to the roles
of prostitute (in a tradition stretching from Pépé
le Moko in 1936 to Grand frère, which came out
seven years ago) or belly-dancer (La maison du
Maltais). 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
1 he "Moorish woman " is
often depicted in films as a
prostitute, top (Julien
Duvivier's Pépé le Moko,
1936), or as a dancer,
above (La maison du
Maltais, Henri Fescourt,
1927).
26
Scantily dressed, lascivious and voluptuous,
she provides entertainment for legionnaires and
adventurers slumming it in disreputable casbahs.
Occasionally she may display fidelity and hero¬
ism, like Yasmina, the dancer in Fleur de sable
who dies in the arms of a European intelligence
officer after helping him thwart a conspiracy.
Hitchcock's three minarets
Just as little respect is paid to the Arab landscape
as to the people who live in it. Reduced to a hand¬
ful of clichéspicturesque alleys, teeming mar¬
kets and palm groves surrounded by sand
dunesit is no more authentic than Arab charac¬
ters played by Western actors with brown-stained
faces. Lack of authenticity is not confined to films
made in the studio with painted scenery and plas¬
tic palm trees. In many films made on location
in Arab countries the natural beauty of the sur
roundings is heightened with artificial splendours
intended to add to the exotic effect. In The Man
Who Knew Too Much, Alfred Hitchcock shows
not just the famous single minaret of the Kou-
toubia Mosque, Marrakesh, but three of them!
In Pépé le Moko the Algiers Casbah becomes a
hideout for crooks and gangsters, while in
other productions Beirut, Cairo, Tangiers and
Casablanca are shown as capitals of vice, crime
and corruption.
Film-goers should not be surprised, therefore,
to hear Egyptians speaking a Tunisian dialect, or
to see Iraqis dressed like Moroccans. These incon¬
gruities exist because many films set in the Middle
East are actually made in the Maghreb. Some
directors make no distinction between the various
Arab peoples, and others mix up Arabs and Mus¬
lims, thus robbing their works of the little eth¬
nological interest they might otherwise have had.
The casual way in which Western film¬
makers appropriate Arab landscapes, characters
and stories and reshape them as they please in a
rubbishy celluloid Orient is evidence of a long¬
standing unscrupulousness.
The colonial film
After the end of World War I, the Arab rebel¬
lion against foreign domination became increas¬
ingly widespread. Its repercussions reached the
European countries, and the cinema, which could
not ignore such a burning question, also entered
the fray. Thus the colonial film was born and be¬
came popular in the 1920s and 1930s. This kind
of film glorifies the skills of the colonisers (Les
hommes nouveaux and Le bled were made for the
centenary of the French conquest of Algeria) and
what were known as "peacekeeping" operations
(Feu, Lesfils du soleil, Beau Geste, La voix du désert).
Its heroes are the legionnaires and soldiers of the
colonial armies, and the villains are the "recal¬
citrant" Arabs.
Not all the natives are shown as hostile and
treacherous. Sometimes, among the ranks of the
local officials, we come across "good" Arabs who
choose to join the colonial forces and fight against
their rebellious brothers (L'âme du bled, Capitaine
Ardant).
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
1 he police check up on
Algerian immigrants in
France during the Algerian
war in this scene from
Michel Drach's Elise ou la
vraie vie (1971).
On the other hand, Arab revolts, particular¬
ly the most dramatic one in Algeria, are handled
with a great deal of embarrassment. In the 1960s
and 1970s, a few films such as Elise ou la vraie vie,
Muriel, and Le petit soldat, depicted the Algerian
war summarily and indirectly, but only one
French film squarely faced up to the subject, the
American director James Blue's Les oliviers de la
justice, and that was an anachronism since it called
for reconciliation when the breaking point had
already been reached.
It was not until the 1970s that two French
film-makers, René Vautier and Yves Boisset, cou¬
rageously denounced the colonial war in Avoir
vingt ans dans les Aurès and R.A.S., stories of
young conscripts forced to take part in
"mopping-up" operations in Algeria. In 1989, the
director Gérard Mordillât dealt with a similar sub¬
ject in Cher frangin.
The French output is not very substantial in
comparison to the many American films on the
Viet Nam war. The only Western director to
show the war from the Algerian point of view was
the Italian Gillo Pontecorvo, whose courageous
The Battle ofAlgiers was long banned in France.
The Arab-Israeli
conflict
It seemed that the end of the colonial era and the
independence of the Arab countries might her¬
ald the opening of a new chapter of less conten¬
tious relations between East and West. But the
old demons were awakened by the Arab-Israeli
conflict. Some Western directors took sides in
their treatment of this conflict. In Otto
Preminger's Exodus, which retraces the creation
of Israel, all the Arabs are unpleasant characters,
except for one who wants to get along with the
Jewish colonists and is assassinated by his co¬
religionists.
Preminger's 1974 film Rosebud deals with the
Palestinian question from the terrorist angle.
Other American films such as Victory at Entebbe
and The Little Drummer Girl reflect a similar ap¬
proach, while the problems of occupation were
raised by the politically-minded film-maker
Costa-Gavras in Hanna K.
Scene from The Battle of
Algiers (1970), Gillo
Pontecorvo's courageous
film about the Algerian
war (1954-1962). 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
In other films, antagonism between East and
West takes the form of doomed romances be¬
tween Arabs and Westerners. From Fazil, the
story of a Frenchwoman who falls in love with
an Arab prince and eventually escapes from the
harem where she has been confined (and where
a muezzin calls the faithful to prayer by singing
"Oh my love"!), to Pierre et Djemila, a modern
version of the Romeo and Juliet story transposed
to a suburban low-rent housing estate (where
native-born French people and North African im¬
migrants live side by side without mixing), these
films usually end with the death of one of the
protagonists, if not both. Rare exceptions, such
as Baroud and Rex Ingram's The Arab, have hap¬
pier endings.
Certain films, inspired by actual events and
real people, rise above this allegedly insurmount¬
able antagonism and evoke the experience of a
few fervent lovers of the East who have gone in
search of the Arab Muslim world. Such produc¬
tions include L'appel du silence, which tells the
story of Charles de Foucauld, a French viscount
who became a desert hermit, and above all
Lawrence ofArabia, which had a worldwide suc¬
cess. But even in these films, the facts were often
sacrificed to the demands of a fictional treatment.
The East of a Thousand and One Nights
Another kind of film about the East is based on
stories and legends such as the celebrated Thou¬
sand and One Nights. These tales that paint the
splendour and refinement of the golden age of
Arab Muslim civilization in glowing colours pro¬
vide an inexhaustible treasury of wonderful
material which has been adapted for the cinema
with varying degrees of success.
The first screen adaptation of the adventures
of Aladdin appeared as early as 1899. In 1902, it
was the turn of Ali Baba, and in 1919 that of Sind-
bad the Sailor. They were followed by several
hundred more films from the West, including
four masterpieces: the two versions of The Thief
ofBaghdad (USA, 1924 and UK, 1940), Ali Baba
et les 40 voleurs (a comedy starring the French ac¬
tor Fernandel and the delightful Egyptian dancer
Samia Gamal), and the Italian director Pier Paolo
Pasolini's Ilfiore délie mille e una notte. Pasolini
was the only film-maker to show as much interest
in the fantastic and aesthetic aspects of the
tales as the profound wisdom contained in them.
These films often provide pleasant entertain¬
ment, but curiously enough their success has had
the deleterious effect of encouraging many
Western directors to depict an imaginary East
instead of the real thing. The problem is that
some of these "imaginative" films misleadingly
claim to give an accurate picture of Arab life. One
of them, Arthur Joffe's extraordinary Harem,
depicts a fantasy Orient which no Arab would
recognize.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
m¿JM*'%
Recently the cinema has begun to examine
the problems of immigration. Some films about
immigrant communities facing an uphill struggle
to win acceptance popularize widespread clichés
such as that of the delinquent Arab. Others, such
as Yves Boisset's Dupont-La-Joie and Roger
Hanin's Train d'enfer are warm-hearted films
which nevertheless confine the immigrant in the
role of victim and scapegoat. Rainer Werner Fass-
binder's Angst essen Seele auf(Fear Eats the Soul)
and Michel Drach's Elise ou la vraie vie are two
of several exceptional films which offer a critique
of racism while at the same time presenting
complex and subtle portraits of attractive
characters.
The last few years have seen the emergence
of a new generation of immigrants' children who
find it easier than their parents to integrate.
Among them are a number of film-makers includ¬
ing Mehdi Charef, Rachid Bouchareb and Abdel-
karim Bahloul, who have already had some
success in presenting a more complex, subtle and
accurate picture of the Arab community.
David Lean directs Peter
O'Toole and Omar Sharif
(inset in close-up) during
the filming of Lawrence of
Arabia in 1962.
ABBAS FAHDEL,
of Iraq, is a journalist with
the Paris periodical Présence
du Cinéma Français. He has
directed several short films
and has contributed to a
number of books on cinema
and television, including Les
cinémas arabes (Paris, 1986)
and Les télévisions du monde
(Paris, 1988). 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Tristan and Pavlova through
the looking glass
Co-operation,
not caricature, is
the new watchword
in relations
between American
and Soviet cinema.
30
* John Ford's The Lost Patrol
(1934).
X RISTAN, a male American dolphin, and
Pavlova, a female Soviet dolphin, are trained for
combat at military bases in their respective coun¬
tries. Then, one day, they meet under water and
fall in love...
This is the plot of a recent animated cartoon
series co-produced by a Soviet studio and an
American company. Only a few years ago, col¬
laboration between the United States and the
Soviet Union on a theme relating to military con¬
frontation would have been inconceivable. For
Americans, the Russian represented the threat of
communist subversion. The Soviet image of the
American was fuzzier. The West epitomized all
that was alien, but historically its image had
varied from that of the despised adversary to that
of the fascinating model.
In 1908, when Russian cinema was born, the
West already led the field. To conquer the
market, Russian companies had to woo the pub¬
lic with films which were as attractive as Ameri¬
can action films or French comedies of manners.
As early as 1912, in addition to historical dramas
and adaptations of great works of Russian litera¬
ture, many films were made about fashionable so¬
ciety, directly inspired by the Western films the
Russian public loved so much. With few excep¬
tions, such as Yakov Protazanov's Jenny the Ser¬
vant (1917), these stories reflected a taste for
melodrama and tragic endings.
The 1917 revolution and foreign intervention
brought an increasingly strong ideological colour¬
ing to the rivalry between Russian and Western
cinema. The Western countries were no longer
taken as models but as examples of a depravity
which had to be denounced. In Soviet cinema,
America, the symbol of capitalism, became the
rival and the enemy.
Lev Kuleshov's evocatively titled The Extraor¬
dinary Adventures ofMr West in the Land of the
Bolsheviks (1924) strikingly reflects the spirit of
the 1920s. A number of enduring stereotypes
BY MARILYNE FELLOUS
were created in this odd parody of an American
action film. The characters are one-dimensional
representations of the social class to which they
belong. West, the cowboy, is the archetypal
spoiled child. A rich land-owner consumed with
fear and hatred of the Bolsheviks, he sets off for
the Soviet Union with his assistant and
bodyguard, Dejddy. The latter, as a representa¬
tive of the working classes and thus a more at¬
tractive figure, soon finds his way around in a
world very different from his own. Meanwhile,
Jenny, the secretary, has plenty of time to get to
know and like the Soviet Union.
However, while they seemed to be denounc¬
ing the anti-Soviet campaigns which raged in the
United States, the authors of this kind of film did
not take the stereotypes they used too seriously.
In the 1930s, the class struggle and great pow¬
er rivalry intensified, but the trend for remakes
continued unabated. In his memoirs the Soviet
film-maker Mikhail Romm wrote this account of
the origins of his film The Thirteen:
"I was sent for by the Head of Cinematogra¬
phy, Boris Shumyatsky. The script-writer Iossif
Prut was summoned at the same time. Neither
of us knew what for.
" 'A comradehis name is immaterialhas
seen an American film in which a desert patrol
perishes in a combat after carrying out its mis¬
sion,' Shumyatsky said.* 'The film is imperialist
and hysterical, but this comrade has suggested
that something similar should be made about our
frontier guards. Will you try? You can write the
scenario together.'
" 'Can we see the film?'
" 'No, it's already been sent back. But that
doesn't matter. The important thing is that we
need a desert (we've got some terrific ones), front¬
ier guards and Basmachis, and that everyone dies
at the end. Almost everyone, but not everyone,
don't forget that, comrade Mikhail!'
In other words, in order to depict the struggle
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Ldv Kuleskov's The
Extraordinary Adventures
ofMr West in the Land
of the Bolsheviks (1924)
used stereotyped characters
to parody American
comedy films of the 1920s.
against the ideological enemy within, Soviet
cinema fell back on ideas from the ideological
enemy outside its frontiers.
In 1953, in the middle of the Cold War,
Abram Room was commissioned to make a film
called Silver Dust, in which a corrupt American
scientist discovers a method of mass destruction.
He wants to experiment with it on Blacks, but
is prevented by "representatives of the people,
peace campaigners, one of whom is his eldest
son". Finally he sells his discovery at an exorbi¬
tant price to gangsters who murder him. His
younger son, a fascist, dies from the effects of the
terrible silver dust. All the ingredients are there:
corruption by money, the neo-nazi danger, and
the people's struggle for progress and peace.
Ideological struggles
First and foremost, this type of film was a denun¬
ciation of the ideological poison of nazism and
neo-nazism. In OffSeason (1968), which was pat¬
terned on an American spy thriller based on a
true story, a Soviet spy in "a Western country"
is ordered to neutralize a mad scientist who is
nostalgic about nazism. The spy is here the
saviour of humanity, a role which each country
simultaneously and in competition claims for
itself.
In the field of the "ideological struggle", the
films of the Brezhnev period satisfied two de¬
mands. They responded to anti-Soviet films
produced in the United States by using a similar
genre and themes, but above all they illustrated
official policy, which was to seek an agreement
to halt the arms race. Thus the films proclaim
the Soviet desire for peace and at the same time
the absurdity of war, even explaining the tensions
between the two great powers in terms of the
folly of certain individuals.
Sergei Mikaelian's Flight 222, in which a
Soviet dancer refuses to return home from a tour 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
in the United States, is an example of a duplicat¬
ed film. The American intelligence services put
pressure on his wife so that she stays too. This
is a response to the American film White Nights,
in which the dancer Mikhail Baryshnikov, an
emigré to the United States, plays himself.
A. Tumanishvili's Solitary Navigation is an exam¬
ple of an anti-war protest film in which a Soviet
ship manages to avoid a world catastrophe
planned by the commander of an American
atomic submarine who goes mad during the Viet
Nam war.
The rejection of the West appears in another
form, less official but just as durable, in the con¬
flict between Slavophiles and Westernizers. This
issue, which divided the Russian intelligentsia in
the nineteenth century, re-emerged with the re¬
ligious revival in the middle of the 1960s, of
which the flagship film was Andrei Tarkovski's
Andrei Rublev (1966). The epitome of triumphant
technology and the renunciation of spiritual
values, the West hurtles inexorably towards an
apocalypse from which Russia alone can save it.
Konstantin Lopushanski's Letters from a Dead
Man (1986) gives a detailed description of a
nuclear catastrophe which takes place outside the
Soviet Union.
'Eternal Russia'
The West is interesting to these film-makers
above all as a way of asking what lies beyond the
familiar world. Whether the subject is a visit to
another country (in Alov and Naoumov's The
Shore a writer visits a decadent Federal Republic
of Germany), or voluntary or involuntary
emigration (in Naoumov's The Choice two old
friends meet again, one of whom escaped during
the Second World War and now realizes that he
is a failure because he left his homeland; Tarkov¬
ski's Nostalgia, made in Italy in 1983, evokes its
author's exile)all these films show how hard it
is for Russians to live far from their native soil
and how they cannot adapt to a savage, hostile
world which they consider to be on the verge of
bankruptcy.
But this tendency to fall back on the values
of an "eternal Russia" is matched by another
which, by authorizing and even encouraging co-
productions with other countries, establishes the
West as a friendlier place, offering a welcome to
Russian émigrés who bear with them the values
of a past which their country is at last beginning
to rehabilitate.
Here too, an animated cartoon sets the tone.
A US-USSR co-production directed by Efim
Gambourg, its title is Stereotypes. Constructed in
the form of a parody of an American show, it
portrays bearded and threatening mujiks armed
with hammers and sickles and cynical cigar-
smoking businessmen, their feet on the table.
1 he Soviet director
Mikhail Romm's film
The Thirteen (1936), above,
is thought to have been
inspired by John Ford's
The Lost Patrol (1934), below.
»l1-
*^f' %,Z y j
a ;-$*
' V'i&*fl
*?hy. U v.V >.
., *t*
at .,;>'
«."*-
'^3»w.. . #sr ',; <r T
\;->
^ II >
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
MARILYNE FELLOUS,
of France, an expert on
Soviet cinema, is Paris
correspondent of the
specialist journals Sovestski
Ekran (Moscow) and L'art
soviétique (Tbilisi). She is
one of the authors of a
book entitled Film totem,
film tabou (Le Parc, Liège,
1989), and is currently
preparing a doctoral thesis
on the cinema and society
in the Soviet Union.
Nostalgia, filmed in Italy
in 1983 by Andrei
Tarkovski, evokes the
homesickness ofRussians
living far from
their native soil.
1 reliminary sketches for
the animated cartoon
Stereotypes (1988), a
Soviet-American co-
production directed by
Efim Gambourg.
.<
.
I
f
i. ^ \y>>
'/I
..1'
'«ff
ï\:r:
K ^% -a
.,-
V1
tí
an.
Hi
X-
-
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
BY ASSIA DJEBAR
0
An Algerian film¬
maker and writer
reflects on the
image and self-
image of people in
Third World
societies and
especially
on women's new
perceptions
of the world.
34
NE night in December 1976, in a farm rent¬
ed from some peasant farmers 70 kilometres from
Algiers, with a team of seventeen technicians and
two actors, I was shooting an interior night
scenea man looking at his sleeping wife.
Nothing very special about that! Nothing
special about the action... except for the duration
of the look (a minute and a half), or rather of the
double lookmyself, the technicians, and later
the film audience, looking at the man, the Other,
looking at an Algerian woman lying heedlessly
asleep, like a Venus in an Italian Renaissance
painting. It was as if all art (at that time Arab cine¬
ma could, objectively, be said to be at a stage of
development similar to that of Florentine or
Venetian painting of the Quattrocento) had to
begin by going through this first discovery of
how another personthe Otherlooks at a
woman in an unguarded moment and how, in
turn, we look at him looking at her.
In the film, La nouba des femmes du mont
Chenoua, the woman is lying on the marital bed,
her hair bound up in a red scarf; only the pure
lines of her face are visible. I had worked out the
décor down to the last detailthe silky glimmer
of the bedclothes and the pillows contrasting with
the rough whitewashed walls, the carpets on the
floor, and wool, lots of wool all around. Enve¬
loped in the wide bed, the sleeping woman seems
passive, serene. Then, from her few disordered
movements, we gradually sense the beginnings of
a struggle against a nightmarethe memories, as
we will later learn, of a wartime past.
Stolen glances
What of the onlooker, the man motionless in the
doorway of the bedroom looking at his wife?
Will he join her on the bed? No. Though there
is desire in his look (is not the explicit or implicit
impulse of desire an essential ingredient of true
cinema?), it is not observed with sufficient insis¬
tence to suggest shared pleasure, the promise of
intimate union.
The Other's way of looking at the desirable
woman, a look on which we too are spying, is
not the look of a voyeur. Slowly and with increas¬
ing intensity (a minute and a half can be a very
long time), he is, despite himself, contemplating
his impotence and the pain of separation. It is a
look which faces up to and makes more distinct
the dividing line between a couple, between the
sexes.
I should, perhaps, have indicated earlier that
the man is immobilized in a wheelchair which
he has propelled along the wall to the open door.
Even at a distance, the woman fascinates him. His
hand grips the door-frame. Behind the camera,
I capture the movement of the seated man as he
struggles to rise, inch by inch, his face in profile
twisted by the effort, and in the background the
bed, the sleeping woman with the red kerchief-
two masks, one so near, the other so distant.
Long after, I began to wonder if it was really
just by chance that I had decided to shoot this
interior night scene. At the time I had sought
only the pleasure of composition, as much in the
manner of a painter as of a film director. Had
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Behind the veil Women on both sides
of the camera
I not chosen the scene in spite of myself? After
all, for me as a writer, as a film-maker, or simply
as an Arab woman, was not the real problem the
painful search for an answer to the question as
to the nature of the Other's look at woman, in
a culture in which, for centuries, the eye had been
closely guarded? One eye only existed, the eye
of the master of the harem who forbade all visual
imagery and invoked religious taboos to reinforce
this dominance. The look of the Other, unless
it is the look of a voyeur (an aggressive, invasive
look), perceives nothing but the image of the
woman, a mirage enshrouded in poetry and
melancholy.
By looks possessed
This whole question of what it means to be
scrutinized by others is a paramount concern of
Arab cinema today. Yet I feel it is relevant to go
beyond the personal experience I have described
above, and to speak of the placing, in the not too 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
1 hotos taken during the
filming ofLa nouba des
femmes du mont
Chenoua. Left, the
director, Assia Djebar, with
one of the actors. Above,
Algerian village women
who appeared in the film.
36
distant past, of entire societies under the micro¬
scope of the alien eye of the colonizer. Arab, Afri¬
can and Eastern cultures were all thus checked,
recorded and "illustrated" by the scrutiny of the
dominator.
This other eye was that of the Western artist
(the painter of battle scenes, then the orientalist
painter of fantasies, of caravans, bedouins,
dancers, children begging against a background
of sand dunes and ruined mosques), and then of
the traveller-photographer of the years between
1880 and 1900, when the great colonial empires
were at the height of their power. This period
saw a profusion of postcards, which were
despatched in their thousandspictures of beau¬
tiful, more or less scantily clad "fatimas" across
which, or on the back of which, tourists, soldi¬
ers and short-stay residents inscribed their mes¬
sages with apparent indifference.
Thus, for about a century and a half, as in
the days of pagan magic, people were
"possessed"both in the sense of being dominat¬
ed and of being trickedby the annexation of
their image in an operation in which they took
no part. People communicated with each other
on pictures of Arabs or Blacks who themselves
were excluded from communication. Did they
really look at the persons represented? No. Their
images, and their apparent difference, became a
pretext for the circulation of ideas, words and ba¬
nalities without their being even symbolically in¬
volved. The innermost identity of the persons
thus observed was even more totally rejected. It
was as if their difference were no more than a
matter of fashion, of folklore, a mere décor. For
decades, a whole genre of "colonial cinema"
flourished, ranging from documentary to fiction
films; once successful, it has today completely dis¬
appeared. It was as though, everywhere at that
time, blind cameramen were filming mirages.
The look unveiled
And then, suddenly, women began to open their
eyes and look around them. Women who until
then had no right to look, who walked with
lowered eyes, their faces, their foreheads, their
entire bodies enveloped except for a tiny orifice
left so that they could see a few paces ahead. At
last they had a right to the world outside,
to schooling, to study, to space. They forgot
themselves so far as to contemplate the sky, trees,
nature, foam on the waves, to observe the city
streets and crowds, to look at othersother
women, all humanity.
I venture to return to my own modest ex¬
perience of scrutinizing intensively over a period
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
of time, because, for me, the strength of the cine¬
ma lies in its scrupulous, meticulous examination
of ways of looking, in its way of looking at those
who cannot look and of encountering those,
whether men or women, who look for the first
time.
Let us, therefore, go back to the first scene
of La nouba des femmes du mont Chenoua. A
woman is standing with her back to the audience;
all that can be seen of her is her hair and the out¬
line of her head against a wall. She rubs her fore¬
head against the stone wall; perhaps, through
impatience or helplessness, she has just banged
her head against it. Any explanation is possible,
since she refuses to let us see her, rejects me, re¬
jects the camera's scrutiny. Yet this is how I chose
to show her.
She walks on, searching, persisting in her re¬
jection of the audience. Suddenly her voice breaks
out, and with it all her inner feeling of revolt:
"I speak, I speak, I speak!" Then silence. "I
don't want anybody to see me," she says.
And then she adds, and we understand that
the man is also there in the room, waiting:
"I don't want you to see me."
Thus, the heroine of the film, who will live
out her life before us in the next two hours, be¬
gins by proclaiming her refusal to be looked at.
Then she turns and faces us, because, above all,
she wants to speak, to communicate. Perhaps she
is unaware that it is difficult to speak out in front
of others, or that to speak into the void and into
the silence is even more difficult. Yet her desire
to express herself is manifest: "I speak, I speak,
I speak!"
In other words the screen might be no more
than a ribbon of darkness, a non-image pierced
from time to time by the distant profile of a
woman to remind us that the woman is there;
only her voice occupies time-space, to become a
real presencea word preceded by her shadow.
My conclusion is that films made by
womenfrom the Third World as well as from
the Old Worldare an expression of a desire to
speak. It is as though film-making means for
women a new mobility of voice and body, of a
body unobserved and therefore unsubordinated,
with a rediscovered autonomy and innocence. As
a result, the voice takes wings and dances. At last
the outsider is seeing with her own eyes.
Looks exchanged
In La nouba des femmes du mont Chenoua, the
young woman architect who returns to the land
of her childhood does indeed begin to speak, and
she goes out too, rediscovering old haunts. As she
wanders her eyes seek out places, houses, rivers,
even those that have run dry, and forests, even
those that have been burnt down. She meets
other women who look at her in their turn. And
through this exchange of looks, often slow, some¬
times furtive, or simply blank, with the blank-
ness of waiting, dialogues are opened concerning
the present and the past. And all around, these
women among women are accompanied by the
pervasive presence of scores of idle, noisy, laugh¬
ing children and their uncertain bursts of song.
As I follow the heroine, I look at the other
women. Or rather, I watch her, a young indepen¬
dent woman, savouring her rebirth. I watch her
discovering the other women. As she looks at the
peasant women her look opens the flood-gates of
speech, until then firmly closedwomen's talk
about the banalities of daily life and about the
still vivid past, about the embers of memories still
painful despite the balm of forgetfuless. "How
can I weep, when I have no tears left?", exclaims
an old peasant woman, with a dried up face but
a proud bearing.
A woman looks at other women. And in that
look desire plays no part. The barren gap between
human beings disappears, conversations inter¬
weave. Returning home as dusk falls, the young
woman is enveloped in the warmth of those who
have spoken to her. It is as if the voice always
preceded the body and the eyes and thus, far from
the rapine of voyeurism, in these half-blind fum-
blings were to be found love, tenderness and
recognition.
Can it be simply by chance that most films
created by women give as much importance to
sound, to music, to the timbre of voices record¬
ed or captured unawares, as they do to the image
itself? It is as though the screen had to be ap¬
proached cautiously and be peopled, if need be,
with images seen through a look, even a short¬
sighted, hazy look, but borne on a full, com¬
manding voice, hard as stone but fragile and rich
as the human heart.
1 ostcards of the colonial
period showed "beautiful,
more or less scantily clad
fatimas' ... on the back of
which tourists inscribed
messages with apparent
indifference".
ASSIA DJEBAR,
Algerian writer and film¬
maker, is the author of
many short stories and
novels which have been
widely translated. Her first
film, La nouba des femmes
du mont Chenoua
(1976-1977) won the
International Critics' Prize
at the Venice Biennale
in 1979. 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
How Charles
Chaplin created
his "little tramp",
the outsider who
lurks inside
all of us.
Charlie Chaplin, stranger
	 and brother
BY MARCEL OMS
V^HARLIE Chaplin, who was born a hundred
years ago this year, was one of the world's best-
loved public figures, greeted by cheering crowds
wherever he went. Yet he also attracted suspicion,
dislike and even hatred.
There is a disturbing contradiction in these
two extreme responses, neither of which can be
said to be totally undeserved or totally justified.
Perhaps it is the fate of brilliant clowns to em¬
body both the white-faced clown and his stooge,
the auguste, and, when they abandon their
motley, to attract both love and hatred accord¬
ing to the temper of the times, as if they were
trying to reveal themselves, and us, as complete
human beings.
This kind of fundamental misunderstanding
came to a head in 1927, when Chaplin, attacked
by the gutter press and a wide sector of public
opinion, was defended from the fury of his crit¬
ics by the surrealists in a tract entitled Hands off
Love. This text, probably written mainly by
Louis Aragon, contains some admirable expres¬
sions of faith in the Chaplin myth: "Obedient
to the dictates of love, he has always been obe¬
dient to the dictates of love, that is what his life
and all his films unanimously proclaim." And the
text concludes: "Suddenly we understand the
place of genius in this world. It takes possession
of a man, makes him an intelligible symbol and
the prey of real brutes. Genius tells the world the
moral truth which universal folly obscures and
tries to suppress. So thank the man who, on the
vast screen of the West, over there on the horizon
where the suns are setting one by one, today
projects your shadows, great human truths,
perhaps unique moral truths, which are worth
more than all the Earth."
That same year, 1927, Chaplin made The Cir¬
cus. In this film featuring clowns, an equestrienne,
wild beasts, a conjuror and an acrobat, he rev¬
ealed his debt to the traditions of the sawdust ring
and paid tribute to the set pieces, classic acts and
conventions of the circus. A tramp on the run
from the police, Charlie takes refuge in the big
top, disrupts the show, unwittingly puts on a star
performance in the ring, and enters the magic
circle of the circus.
The Circus puts the Chaplin problem in a nut¬
shell. The hero tries to escape his fate and is
trapped inside the show that makes his name.
Then when he wants to escape from the show,
which is alienating him, he has to knuckle un¬
der. This skilful dialectic of rejection and attrac¬
tion encapsulates the Chaplin tramp character.
Although seemingly the most ordinary of men,
he is actually an outsider. He is a rejected out¬
cast, a wanderer desperate for affection, a tramp
destined to beg forever.
The public were loyal to Chaplin partly be¬
cause they recognized him for what he was and
identified with him and partly because they felt
the revulsion we feel for a side of ourselves that
we cannot accept. The surrealists who held out
a friendly hand to Chaplin the victim later strong¬
ly condemned his "sentimentalism". Luis Buñuel
reproached him for allowing himself to be "crip¬
pled by the intellectuals of the whole world" and
for "trying to make us weep with hoary sen¬
timental commonplaces".
38
Charlie the guardian ofan
abandoned child.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
f
^H
daaaHBJhinl
\Born a hundred years ago
A master of
modern comedy
^^ ^^^
H
Jo-»? I -V
f!9H.
Stella
(WC3J^2itai%V- «MRS
tSkt*
î*£K«r*S;
41
"
aV
» h*"
'
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
FROM LEFT TO RIGHT:
The Pilgrim (1923)
The escaped convict .
disguised as a clergyman
preaches his first sermon.
The Gold Rush (1925)
Prospecting for gold in
Alaska, Charlie takes refuge
from a snowstorm in the
cabin of outlaw Black
Larson (right). Also driven
into the cabin is Big Jim
Mackay (centre) a
prospector who has found
gold.
The Circus (1927)
Charlie's accidents in the
ring make a hit with the
audience.
Such passions, contradictions and inconsisten¬
cies reveal the strength of the feelings which
Chaplin has aroused.
The 'little fellow'
Charles Chaplin first visited the United States in
1911 with Fred Karno's music-hall troupe. He
returned the following year and stayed on to ap¬
pear in vaudeville routines whose growing suc¬
cess owed much to the traditions of English music
hall. He soon established a reputation with a
number of classic sketches which he later adapt¬
ed for the cinema. Two of them, A Night in a
London Club and An Evening in an English
Music Hall, were built around the character of a
fractious drunk and could be constantly varied
depending on the reactions of the audience.
When he started out in films in 1914 Chaplin
played bit parts. The screen character for which
he is remembered did not yet exist. He was feel¬
ing his way, trying to find his style. After a long
period of improvisation in which he played ag¬
gressive, vindictive roles, he became a kind of bad-
tempered Harlequin kitted out in the ragged
clothes he remembered from his London days:
"I ended up by thinking of those Englishmen
whom I had so often seen, with their little black
moustaches, their bamboo canes, their ill-fitting
jackets. I decided to model myself on them."
Chaplin's famous duck-footed gait owed
something to Little Tich, an English music-hall
clown with huge, floppy feet, to a drunken old
ostler Chaplin had seen staggering around
Lambeth when he was a child, and to other come¬
dians from Karno's troupe such as Walter Groves
and Fred Kitchen.
Whatever inspired it, this faltering and un¬
certain appearance created the image of the soli¬
tary tramp which Chaplin never changed, even
when, or especially when, the character grew in
humanity, subtlety and range of emotion. "Man,
intoxicated with intelligence, dancing on the
peaks of despair", as the critic Elie Faure said of
Chaplin in 1922, immortalizing this initiation
into endless vagabondage: "Each of his feet, so
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
painful and so burlesque, is one of the two poles
of the spirit. One is called knowledge, the other
desire. By leaping from one to the other he seeks
that centre of gravity of the soul that we no soon¬
er find than we immediately lose again."
Chaplin's quest never ended, even if its course
sometimes disconcerted his warmest admirers.
Haunted by the spectres of a mentally unstable
mother and an alcoholic father who had once
stared at him without recognition in the street,
he channelled into his creation all the love which
had been denied him in his childhood.
Charlie the stranger
As well as performing in the melodrama that he
used as the mainspring of his dialogue with the
public, Chaplin was always an active and mili¬
tant witness of his times, starting with his early
campaigns in support of American intervention
on the side of the Allies in World War I. The
Bond, a not very convincing propaganda short,
and the masterpiece Shoulder Arms, both made
in 1918, were his contribution to the mobiliza¬
tion effort, but above all they were a denuncia¬
tion of the folly of war.
In these films Chaplin refined the character
whose mere appearance was a challenge to the
established order. He became increasingly a
"stranger" in the sense -that Albert Camus gave
to the word in The Myth of Sisyphus (1942):
"Strangeness creeps in: perceiving that the world
is 'dense', sensing to what degree a stone is for¬
eign and irreducible to us, with what intensity
nature or a landscape can negate us. ... Men, too,
secrete the inhuman. At certain moments of lu¬
cidity, the mechanical aspect of their gestures,
their meaningless pantomime, make silly every¬
thing that surrounds them."
Charlie has only to appear at a spa where he
is taking a cure, drunk from the first scene, and
a whole world of hidden vices, shameless gossip
MARCEL OMS,
French educator and
historian of the cinema, is
the author of several
published works, including
a recent study on the
French director Alain
Resnais (1988).
0tt& 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
FROM LEFT TO RIGHT:
Modern Times (1936)
Charlie is caught up in the
machine age.
The Great Dictator
(1940)
"Had I known of the
actual horrors of the
concentration camps, I
could not have made The
Great Dictator. I could
not have made fun of
the homicidal insanity
of the nazis. "
Limelight (1952)
The aging and despondent
music-hall artist
Calvero, who had once
been a great star.
and puritanical preaching is shattered (The Cure,
1917); an escaped convict, he disguises himself in
the stolen clothes of a clergyman, and all kinds
of hypocrisy are unmasked (The Pilgrim, 1923);
a jark-of-all trades in a pawnbroker's shop, he
dismantles and totally destroys a clock in order
to determine its value (The Pawnshop, 1916); on
the run again, he is taken in by a woman and her
pretty daughter whom he saves from drowning.
He wakes up next morning and, a victim of a
comedy of transposition in which each object
seems to suggest something else, he imagines that
the pyjamas he has been lent are prison uniform
and the bars of his brass bed are those of his cell.
Later he drenches the pretty girl's arrogant beard¬
ed swain with soda water, and at the end of an
apocalyptic final scene in which the ladies are
embroiled in a riotous mêlée, he wins the pretty
girlfor an all-too-brief moment (The Adventurer,
1917).
After skilfully denouncing capitalist duplicity
in City Lights (1931), Chaplin attacked the
alienation and loss of creativity produced by the
"mechanical gestures" of mass production in
Modern Times (1936). An idyllic digression in
which Charlie and the waif set up home together
in a shack is a grotesque yet touching variation on
the myth of the golden age which cannot blind us
to the fact that even this dream has become alien.
An artist's testament
The dream turned into a nightmare with the rise
of nazism. The Great Dictator (1940), Chaplin's
first talking picture, is a satire on Hitler (both
Chaplin and Hitler were born in the same month)
in which a Jewish barber is mistaken for a
dictator.
The myth of the clown is the tightrope walk¬
er's poetic response to the values of a world
which is hostile, indifferent and absurd. Chaplin
had perfectly adapted circus skills to the cinema.
His little tramp was an anti-establishment figure,
the caricature of a dandy; his poverty was the
other side of the coin of social success.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
But Chaplin's testament is Limelight, made
in 1952, a film which is not so much an autobi¬
ography in disguise, as critics have said, but a lu¬
cid and serene reflection on the subject of origins.
The film, whose hero Calvero both is and is
not Charlie himself, is set in the places where
Chaplin grew up and at the time when he was
starting out in the cinema, and several members
of the Chaplin family acted in it. But in spite of
many autobiographical allusions, Limelight is
much more than autobiography. This nostalgic
look in the mirror in which wrinkles have etched
the face of youth could perhaps best be described
as a portrait of the artist as a showman. Again
words from Camus' The Myth ofSisyphus spring
to mind: "Likewise the stranger who at certain
seconds comes to meet us in a mirror, the familiar
and yet alarming brother we encounter in our
own photographs is also the absurd."
In a famous scene in The Gold Rush (1925),
all alone in his cabin on New Year's Eve after
the girl he has fallen in love with fails to turn up
to have dinner with him, Charlie faces up to a
kind of death. On a night when the rest of the
world is laughing and celebrating, the lonely out¬
sider spears two bread rolls with forks and makes
the miniature feet thus formed perform a dance.
It was in the midst of the festive season that
Charles Chaplin died, on Christmas Eve 1977. It
is tempting to write a scenario for his last exit...
On a snowy night the wind is howling against
the door of the wooden shack on the edge of the
cliff and the long drop into oblivion. The last log
is flickering out. With a shrug of the shoulders,
Charlie wraps himself in his shroud. He shakes
off the snow, kicks his heels, and with waddling
gait takes leave of the world.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
REFLECTIONS
'Reflections' b a Unesco Courier feature intended to stimulate thinking on a topic unrelated to
the main theme of the current issue and will in some cases, as here, enrich our coverage of a theme
treated in a previous issue.
'Slaves of one man'
BY CHANTAL DE GRANDPRE
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
As a follow-up to our June 1989
issue ("1789: An idea that changed
the world"), we publish this
assessment of the portrayal of the
American Indian in 17th- and 18th-
century French literature.
Descriptions of Indian life were used
by the philosophers of the
Enlightenment as a powerful and
subversive means of expressing
criticism of French society.
Rljafrfr
1k x e-\
k
*$ï^w. 1 F.
,
JL HE discovery of the New World was a power¬
ful influence for change in the social structure of
the ancien régime. The American Indians had made
their appearance in French literature in the six¬
teenth century in the writings of Montaigne, but
it was not until the following century, when France
in her turn ventured into colonization, much later
than Spain, Portugal and Britain, that there emerged
a corpus of travellers' tales in which the Indians took
pride of place.
The first French incursions into North Ameri¬
ca were linked to the fur trade. The Indians of
Nouvelle France had no fabulous cities bursting with
riches to arouse the greed of the European new¬
comers and, in the early days, there was no urge
to acquire land at all costs. Under these circum¬
stances, the Indian was seen as an indispensable
trading partner. He was an equal whom the Europeans
hoped soon to fashion into their own likeness.
With this in mind, from 1632 onwards, the
Jesuits found themselves taking on an evangelizing
role, the success of which depended on the seden-
tarization of the main tribes (with the exception
of the Hurons who were already sedentary and in
JÍVí"- ^1
fe i
L
1; S f M
ijÊt^^F
f 1
«t.
spyf
. ^
wKr aat^a^k
Wl "à *8k.
_j; / y W' f j( Jt'ajfl p
'' , Àà à
rV F
iffYM
f
Jean-Jacques Rousseau, a
portrait by the British
painter Allan Ramsay
(1713-1784).
In 1839 the French king
Louis-Philippe
commissioned from
Théodore Gudin
(1802-1880) this painting
showing the discovery of
the St. Lawrence river
by the French explorer
Jacques Cartier.
whose midst a number of missions were soon
established), and on learning Indian languages. From
then until 1672, the Jesuits sent back to France Re¬
lations (narrative accounts), describing their expe¬
riences in the New World, which met with huge
success. The Indians were unquestionably the leading
characters in these accounts. Their physical
appearance, qualities, defects and beliefs were
described at length, with an infectious curiosity and
sympathy.
The Jesuits were not to remain for long the only
ones interested in the Indians. In the eighteenth cen¬
tury a profusion of texts appeared which confirmed
or contradicted each other. The French traveller and
writer Baron de la Hontan was perhaps the first of
those whose avowed aim was to make a critical as¬
sessment of his contemporaries. In 1703, he
published Voyages du Baron de la Hontan dans
l'Amérique septentrionale ("The Travels of Baron de
la Hontan in North America"). His work was so
successful that it was reprinted twenty-five times bet¬
ween 1703 and 1758. In his Dialogue ou entretiens
entre un sauvage et le Baron de la Hontan ("Dialo¬
gue or Conversations between a Savage and Baron
de la Hontan"), the baron ridicules the evangeliza¬
tion project and reports the words of an Indian,
Adario, who takes issue with the dogmas of the
Catholic Church and then attacks the person of the
king: "... we are born free and closely united, each
as important as anyone else, whereas you are all the
slaves of one man."
In 1724, outraged by the opinions of La Hon¬
tan, Father Joseph Lafitau published Moeurs
des sauvages amériquains comparées aux moeurs des
premiers temps ("Customs of the American Savages
Compared to those of Ancient Times"), a laborious
comparative history of the Indians and the ancient
Greeks designed to demonstrate that the peoples of
the New World were not devoid of religion. He also
aimed to correa the thrust ofJesuit accounts which
had affirmed the lack of any religious beliefs among
the peoples of Canada, so as to convince metro¬
politan France of the need to convert them. Above
all, his book was a vigorous counter-attack against
the views put forward by Baron de la Hontan who
sought additional justification for his atheism in the
standpoint of the Indians.
The Indian as a critical tool
The year 1770 saw the publication of Abbé Raynal's
monumental Histoire philosophique et politique des
établissements et du commerce des Européens dans les
deux Indes ("A Philosophical and Political History
of European Colonies and Trade in the Two In¬
dias"), to which Diderot has been shown to have
made a large contribution.1 Raynal made use of the
Indians as an instrument of criticism, the virulence
of which mounted as edition succeeded edition
between 1770 and 1798. The divine right of
monarchy, property and inequality were all roundly
condemned:
"The inequalities of status which we consider
so necessary .to the maintenance of societies is, in 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
the eyes of a savage, the height of folly ... but what
strikes them as an infamy, as a degradation below
that of wild beasts, is that men, who are by nature
equal, should degrade themselves so completely as
to become dependent upon the desires and whims
of a single man."
Everywhere, and especially among the
philosophers of the Enlightenment, the Indian is
used as a powerful means of expressing criticism of
French society. When Rousseau wrote his Discours
sur l'origine et lesfondements de l'inégalitéparmi les
hommes ("A Discourse upon the Origin and Foun¬
dation of Inequality Among Mankind", 1755), he
did not draw only upon the English example;
since 1750, many works had been written on America
and Rousseau had read Lescarbot, Lafitau and
Baron de la Hontan. From these texts he drew in¬
spiration for his theory of the natural goodness of
man, a commonplace of eighteenth-century litera¬
ture.2 He radicalized and gave a political dimension
to what had previously been limited strictly to the
field of observation.
Nevertheless, the Indian did not represent the
same idea to all the philosophers of the Enlighten¬
ment. In this regard, Voltaire, Rousseau and Diderot
cannot be lumped together, their ideas being often
irreconcilable. The Huron Indian in Voltaire's
story L'Ingénu ("The Innocent") was far from
gentle in his condemnation of French customs and
politics, but his viewpoint is biased in that he was
a false "Noble Savage", being of French parentage.
Voltaire used his Huron to refute Rousseau's
theories on education (L'Ingénu became a savage
although he was naturally a Frenchman), as well as
those of Lafitau on the European origin of the
Indians.
Furthermore, the Enlightenment philosophers
did not exalt the merits of the same Indians; some
preferred the tribes of the north to those of the
south, and vice versa, and the picture they painted
of the Indians varied according to whether they were
progressives (like Diderot) or not (like Rousseau).
Most of them, however, derided the activities of the
Jesuits, who were ferociously caricatured by Voltaire
in L'Ingénu. In this tale surprise is expressed that
the Hurons are not all Catholics. "Haven't the
Reverend Fathers convened them all?" asks
Mademoiselle de Saint-Yves ingenuously (or
perfidiously?).
However opposed to the Jesuits the majority
of the authors of certain travellers' tales and the
philosophers of the Enlightenment may have been,
it cannot be denied that the seed of the ideas they
expressed on inequality, the monarchy and property
was contained in the Jesuits' Relations.
Painstaking and scrupulous observers as they
were, the Jesuits noted down everything they saw.
No doubt they wanted to reform the Indians, but
they also hoped to learn lessons from them that
could be applied to the French. They were thus the
46 first to make comparisons between the two societies
and to weigh their respective values against each
other; and in this confrontation French society did
not always come off best. The Jesuits could not but
approve of the frugal life-style of the Indians and
of their generosity, which was a corollary of the
absence of private property and the concept of
profit. Thus their readers gradually became
accustomed to the idea that man could be happy,
free and equal, without a king, without laws and
without codified rights. The effect of all this on their
contemporaries was undoubtedly detrimental to the
interests of the monarchy, since their eulogies of a
democratic form of government was an implied criti¬
cism of the monarchical system.
Three themes, which were continually being
developed and radicalized throughout the eighteenth
century, appear in the pages of the Jesuits' Relations:
criticism of the monarchy, man's relationship with
nature and the Indian's right to speak out, and
thence his right to power.
The Indians as Republicans
In Nouvelle France, though not in France itself, the
Jesuits were opposed to royal power. They dreamed
of setting up in Canada a system such as they had
launched in Paraguay and Californiaa Jesuit
theocratic state which was often seen as a socialist
state in embryo. They were the first to see the
Indians as "Republicans" in the mould of the
ancient Romans.
For them this assimilation justified their boost¬
ing of the republican governmental system of the
Indians whose egalitarian values and spartan rigour
brought into question the France of the day. Father
Brébeuf, who lived among the Hurons from 1634
until his death, at the hands of the Iroquois, in 1649,
wrote two Relations about the Hurons. In the 1636
version he described in detail their system of govern¬
ment, whose democratic nature he lauded. He relat¬
ed that the Hurons had two chiefs, one for war and
one to take care of internal affairs. The "captains"
of the sub-divisions of these two authorities were
elected on the basis of "their intelligence, populari¬
ty, wealth and other qualities which earned them
esteem in the Land".
In case his meaning was not sufficiently clear,
Brébeuf took care to contrast Huron society with
that of France: "They attain this level of advance¬
ment partly by inheritance and partly by election.
They are not normally succeeded by their own chil¬
dren but by their nephews or their grandchildren.
Even for them succession to these petty kingships
is not automatic, as is the succession of the Dauphin
to the throne of France or of French children to
the heritage of their fathers; it is dependent upon
their having the necessary qualities, on their accept¬
ing the honour and on their being acceptable to the
whole Country."
In this system Brébeuf detected "the spirit of
all republics" and he also praised the freedom of
speech which was the rule among the Indians and
which he saw as being indissociable from the im¬
portance placed on oratory:
"So accustomed are they to this that, since most
of them have good minds, they become alert and
train themselves wonderfully, to the extent that vir¬
tually all of them are able to discuss and reason- clear¬
ly, and in well-rounded phrases, those things about
which they have some knowledge. The Councils
which are held in the villages almost every day, con¬
cerning all kinds of events, are yet another way in
which they learn the art of discourse. Although the
elders hold the centre of the stage and the decisions
taken depend upon their judgement, anyone who
so wishes may attend and everyone has the right
to express an opinion."
The Jesuits' position with regard to nature was
more complex and contradictory. Although they ad¬
mired the way in which the Indians lived in har¬
mony with their natural surroundings, the Jesuits
nevertheless wanted to "civilize" them, in other
words to destroy their privileged links with nature.
Paradoxically, however, they also tried to keep
the Indians away from Europeans. This is where the
widespread notion of the corrupt civilized man first
arose. Although they lived precarious lives, the
savages were better than their European counterparts
and, once convened, would be superior to them.
In praising Indian children, "more lively and more
intelligent" than French children, the Jesuits were
giving their seal of approval to the Indians' "natur¬
al" way of life.
Finally, the Jesuits let the Indians have their say;
and often what they had to say turned into an in¬
dictment.
"These skilful dialecticians," wrote Gilbert
Chinard, "were so enamoured of well reasoned argu¬
ments that they could not help reporting at length
the disquisitions addressed to them by Indians hos¬
tile to their influence. At times they even admitted,
sotto voce, that perhaps their interlocutors were
right."3
The Indian free-thinker
In 1634, while spending the winter with a group of
Montagnais, Father Lejeiine crossed swords with the
witch-doctor in the course of a series of oratorical
jousts in which he did not always come off best. The
witch-doctor evaluated Christian dogma and turned
Lejeune's own arguments against him. When the
Jesuit extolled the merits of life in the next world,
the witch-doctor confessed that he was afraid of dy¬
ing, but assured his opponent that if "I believed that
the other world was so full of delights, I would kill
myself so as to enjoy it". But when the Frenchman
replied that God forbade us to kill ourselves, the
witch-doctor taunted him, as Lejeune reported:
" 'Well, in that case don't kill yourself, I shall
kill you to please you, so that you may go to
Heaven and enjoy the pleasures of which you speak.'
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Illustration from Baron de
la Hontan's book
"Dialogue or Conversations
between a Savage and
Baron de la Hontan"
(Amsterdam, 1704), in
which the author ridicules
the evangelization of the
North American Indians
through a fictitious dialogue
with the Indian Adario.
CHANTAL
DE GRANDPRÉ,
of Canada, is a lecturer in
the literature of Quebec at
the university of Paris X.
She is the author of many
articles and studies
including an essay on
American literature written
in collaboration with Denis
Egan and published in the
encyclopaedia Clartés
(Paris, 1988).
I smiled and replied that I could not accept that any¬
one could take my life without sinning. 'I see very
well,' he replied mockingly, 'that you do not want
to die any more than I do.' "
Quite apart from the fact that the Indian of the
Jesuits was in no sense a "Noble Savage", it was the
Jesuit, the European, who cut a childlike figure, with
no patience, no sense of humour and, above all, no
oratorical talent.
The mythology of the western film has ac¬
customed us to the idea of Indians mumbling halt¬
ingly in the language of the colonists. The Relations
of the Jesuits, on the contrary, portrayed them as
being highly eloquent and stressed the linguistic in¬
competence of Lejeune at whom the Indians scoffed
because he could not express himself correctly in
the Montagnais language. "In the end I told them
that I was a child and that children make their fathers
laugh with their stutterings," he wrote.
The multiplicity of these accounts of scenes from
Indian life, in which the writers are bold enough to
demonstrate the inefficacy of European speech, is
indicative of an overturning of values. By revealing
to their contemporaries the Indian as a critic rather
than as a "Noble Savage", the Jesuits showed that
French society could also be held up to judgement.
This subversive image of the Indian transmitted
in travellers' tales and in the Relations was to con¬
tribute to the ferment of thought of the Enlighten¬
ment. In the writings of a Montesquieu or a Voltaire
(who had the Jesuit missionary Charlevoix as his
source) it strengthened the conviction that the
widening of geographical horizons entailed a
broadening of the mind. Despite their hostility to
the Jesuits, many "philosophers" (Montesquieu,
Grimm, Raynal) saw the "socialist" experiments in
Paraguay in a favourable light. From Montaigne's
essay on "cannibals" to Rousseau's Discourse on In¬
equality, the Indian's role as a social and political
critic grew increasingly important in Western ideol¬
ogy. And this fascination with the Other contribut¬
ed in no small measure to the great explosion of
1789.
1. Michèle Duchet, Diderot et l'histoire des deux Indes ou
l'écriture fragmentaire (1978).
2. Gilbert Chinard, Influence des récits de voyages sur la
philosophie de Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1911).
3. Gilbert Chinard, L'amérique et le rêve exotique dans la
littératurefrançaise au 17e et au 18e siècle (1913, reissued
1970). 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND SOCIETY
Understanding global change
BY ALISON McKELVEY CLAYSON
Fc
OR more than a decade, many scien¬
tists have warned that industry and agri¬
culture were spewing enough gases
into the atmosphere to heat up the
Earth and eventually produce disastrous
climatic changes. The gases are known
as "greenhouse gases", while the phe¬
nomenon of global warming is called
the "greenhouse effect" because the
gases that accumulatelike the glass
panes of the greenhousetrap the
Sun's heat and prevent it from escaping
back into space.
Some of these gases are also res¬
ponsible for destroying the protective
layer of ozone in the Earth's atmosphere.
This too is very serious because without
its protective blanket, the Earth absorbs
increased amounts of ultraviolet radiation
from the Sun, which can cause skin
cancer, cataracts and certain immuno¬
logical diseases.
Despite the scientists' warning,
global warming trends received little
public attention until a string of
weather-related disasters in 1988
seemed to drive the point home. Heat
waves and drought throughout the
United States, hurricanes in the Caribbean,
and flooding in Bangladesh could all be
previews of what will happen with
increasing frequency if the atmosphere
warms by between 2° and 5° by the
middle of the next century, as some
scientists have predicted.
Excess carbon dioxide is the main
48 culprit, although other gases such as the
A cloud of ice in the stratosphere.
Scientists think ice clouds may encourage
chemical reactions leading
to the destruction of the ozone layer.
chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs) used to
pressurize aerosol sprays and insulate
refrigerators are also implicated, as are
natural gases such as methane. Meth¬
ane is produced by bacteria in the guts
of termites and cattle, in the green
muck of rice paddies, in the rotting gar¬
bage of landfills, and in the world's 1 .5
million square kilometres of peat bogs
and tundra.
In 1880, the concentration of car¬
bon dioxide in the atmosphere was 290
parts per million (ppm). It is now about
350 ppm. Most of the extra carbon has
come from burning fossil fuels such as
coal or oil, and as a side effect of de¬
stroying forests: when 1 tonne of carbon
in the form of coal is burnt, it pro¬
duces about 4 tonnes of carbon dioxide.
Studies of air bubbles trapped inside ice
cores from the Antarctic confirm that
roughly the same concentration of car¬
bon dioxide persisted throughout the
past 10,000 yearsuntil the industrial
era disturbed the balance.
Of course, the disasters of summer
1 988 may have had nothing to do with
the greenhouse effect. They may just
have been part of the random and na¬
tural variations in weather that occur
everywhere. The scientists themselves
do not agree in their interpretation of
these events, but no one disputes the
fact that the amount of carbon dioxide
in the atmosphere has increased, that
the rate of climate change is likely to
be faster than at any time in human his¬
tory, and that such change will be fun¬
damentally destabilizing and disruptive
to our planet since living organisms and
the ecosystems they inhabit cannot
adapt that readily to rapid change.
THE CONSEQUENCES
OF GLOBAL WARMING
An increase in world temperatures over
the next fifty years seems likely to cause
a chain reaction. According to com¬
puter models used to predict what might
happen, the greenhouse effect will dra¬
matically alter patterns of rainfall:
some places will be wetter, others drier.
This will affect vegetation, which in turn
will affect the animals that depend on
plants for survival. Changes in vegeta
tion can themselves cause changes in
climate. Global warming may devastate
food crops in some areas, encourage
soil erosion and create conditions in
which pests are unleashed in a new
environment.
The consequences for agriculture
are equally serious: we have seen the
sad effects of the regional warming
trend over the past twenty years in sub-
Saharan Africa, where a growing popu¬
lation, deteriorating soil conditions and
changing climate have combined to
overwhelm the fragile food supply
system, and there have been famine
and misery. In China, the desert is
spreading at the rate of 1,500 square
kilometres a year.
One of the most significant results
of the greenhouse effect is that it causes
the sea level to rise. The oceans have
already risen about 13 cm in the last
century. What would societies do if the
oceans were to rise by 1-1 .5 metres, as
some scientists predict? Major cities like
New York, Bangkok, Calcutta, Rio de
Janeiro and Seoul could be flooded out;
countries like Bangladesh and The
Netherlands might eventually disappear,
while entire populations could become
refugees from low-lying coastal areas.
Another factor in sea level rise is the
melting of icecaps. Researchers suspect
the greenhouse effect to be at work,
for a whole series of massive icebergs
have been breaking off the Antarctic ice
shelf and melting into the sea. Higher
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
global temperatures not only melt polar
ice, they make water expand, thus
causing floods.
THE QUICKENING PACE
OF CHANGE
In 1 800, at the beginning of the Euro¬
pean Industrial Revolution, there were
a thousand million human beings on
the Earth. By 1930 the number had
doubled, and by 1975 it had doubled
again. If current birth-rates hold, then
the world's present population of 5.1
thousand million should double again
during the next 40 years, with 90 per
cent of that growth occurring in poorer,
developing countries.
Still, it is not so much the numbers
that alarmalthough the prospect of
feeding and providing for 10 thousand
million human beings is dauntingbut
rather the effect that Homo sapiens will
have on the Earth's environment, and
the rate at which human-induced change
and degradation will occur. It is the need
to provide for so many people that puts
an unbearable pressure on natural
resources and the environment.
Change is natural. But in recent
years man has accelerated the rate of
changeby profligate burning of fos¬
sil fuels such as oil and coal, by wan¬
ton desecration of forests, by careless
introduction of poisons into the soil and
water supplies, and by uncontrolled
emission of dangerous automobile and
industrial fumes into the airso that the
delicate equilibrium that has always
regulated the total Earth system and its
component parts has been destroyed:
the geosphere (the planet), the at¬
mosphere (the air around the Earth) and
the biosphere (that overlapping area
between the two where life exists) are
out of kilter. Man has undermined his
own life-support system, and the con¬
sequences may well be irreversible. If
they are, then the 10,000 years since
the last Ice Age may have witnessed the
dawn and the decline of modern man.
THE MOST COMPREHENSIVE
STUDY OF EARTH EVER
UNDERTAKEN
To understand what has happened, it
is necessary to understand the impact
of human activity on the environment,
on the concentrations and mixtures of
gases found in the atmosphere, on cli-
A balloon is launched
at Kiruna (Sweden) early in
1989 as part of an international
scientific research
project to monitor the ozone
layer above the Arctic.
mate, and how these interact. The
scientific community has accepted this
challenge, and through a worldwide
non-governmental organization called
the International Council of Scientific
Unions (ICSU), it has launched an inter¬
national study of Global Change known
as the International Geosphere-
Biosphere Programme (IGBP).
The subject of the study is the Earth
itself and the process of change,
whether induced by human beings or
natural forces. The scientists will seek
to describe and explain these occur¬
rences, perhaps also to predict them.
But the ultimate goal of the Programme
is to translate this knowledge into terms
the decision-makers will comprehend so
that appropriate actions can be taken
at national and international levels to
minimize the destructive consequences
of such changes for man's well-being
and survival.
The Global Change study will be
the most comprehensive investigation
of Earth ever undertaken. It will link
scores of research institutions, inter¬
national organizations and academic
centres, and will engage thousands
of scientists in every continent. For
the first time, the work of physicists,
astronomers, biologists, chemists, data
processors, geographers, oceanographers,
meteorologists, palaeontologists, geolo¬
gists, and many other disciplines will be
harnessed for a common objective,
studying and interpreting changes in the
Earth's physical, chemical and biologi¬
cal systems viewed as an interacting
whole.
In 1 988, under the aegis of ICSU,
a Global Action Plan was drawn up by
a Special Committee of 19 scientists
from 16 countries and six continents.
Their Plan identified four basic research
themes.
Documenting and predicting
global change: This will require a
worldwide network of monitoring
"observatories", both on-the-ground
and by remote sensing from space.
Improving understanding of
major forces of change: Variations in
the Earth's orbit and in amounts of so¬
lar energy reaching the biosphere can
have profound effects on life systems.
So can volcanic eruptions of gases and
dust, which some scientists believe may
be held accountable for mass extinc¬
tions of the past. Human activities are
change forces of comparable magni¬
tude. The Global Change Programme
will assess the relative importance of
such factors.
Understanding interactions in
the Total Earth System: The study of
how physical, chemical and biological
systems, including those influenced by
man, interact in a self-regulating Total
Earth System, is a very new science.
Assessing the effects of global
change on our resource base: As
knowledge about global change im¬
proves, it must be used to predict local
and regional effects on resources such
as agriculture, forests, and fisheries.
These themes are very broadtoo
broad, really, to be of much use in de¬
signing specific research projects,
although they are helpful in providing
a general context and framework. In¬
stead, they are being broken down in¬
to smaller chunks and parcelled out
among an expanding number of com¬
mittees and other groups whose mem¬
bers are drawn from institutions
affiliated with ICSU. The interested par¬
ties include Unesco, the World Mete¬
orological Organization (WMO), the
United Nations Environment Program¬
me (UNEP), regional organizations and
national scientific bodies including 37
national committees, to name but a
few. In the interdisciplinary spirit of the
IGBP, the main project areas being de¬
veloped focus on the linkages between
systems. For instance:
Terrestrial biospheric-atmospheric che¬
mistry interactions;
Marine biosphere-atmosphere
interactions;
Biospheric aspects of the hydro-
logical cycle;
Effects of climate change on terrestrial
ecosystems;
Global changes of the past.
A WORLDWIDE PROGRAMME
OF SCIENTIFIC CO-OPERATION
The challenge of a scientific pro¬
gramme like this one is to go beyond
sectoral viewpoints and disciplinary
biases to achieve a sense of the Total
Earth System and the interaction of its
component parts. Two working groups
whose mandates cut across all specia¬
lizations have been established. One will
study the ways in which modern data
and information systems can be used
in handling the vast and complex mass
of data generated by the IGBP, and the
other will look specifically at the es¬
tablishment of Regional Research
Centres. It is proposed to set up about
1 0 multi-purpose centres for the analy¬
sis, interpretation and modelling of data
based on regional observations. These
centres will be linked to worldwide
monitoring networks and research sites.
The IGBP is a long-term effort to
study the causes and effects of global
change. Some projects may be ac¬
complished in a few years, while others
may take 20 to 30 years just to accu¬
mulate a useful data base. What mat¬
ters in the end, however, is that all the
different pieces of the mosaic we call
Earth should be seen as a whole,
without regard to geographical or dis¬
ciplinary boundaries. Only a worldwide
programme of scientific co-operation
and research can hope to achieve such
a goal.
ALISON McKELVEY CLAYSON,
of the United States, is
information officer for the
International Council of
Scientific Unions and the former
Editor of Unesco's environment
journal Nature and Resources.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^COURIER
Published monthly in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue Francois Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief : Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Pans)
50
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta,
Public relations: Claudie Duhamel (Tel :45.68.45.86)
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Kalian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Shn Krishna Kumar Singh (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: SJ Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Seham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bengali: Ahmed Hedayet (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45 88), Assistant: Marie-
Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89), Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse
Hardy (45.68.45 65), Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité,
Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Mamchan Ngonekeo,
Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Customer service: Ginette Mot reff (45.68 45.64),
Accounts: Liliane Tasch (45.68.45.66), Cultural projects:
Ricardo Zamora-Perez (Tel. 45.68.45.80),
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval
ADVERTISING
Publicat: 17, Boulevard Poissonnière, 75002 Paris.
Tel.: 40.26.51.26
Sales director: Benoît Rosier
Advertising director: Daniele Michelet
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non copy right
photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is
produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy. 7S700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Michigan -18100, USA.; (3) N.C.R Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York. USA, (4) Bell and
Howell Co . Old Mansfield Road. Wooster. Ohio 44691, USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Pnnted in France) DEPOT LEGAL : CI OCTOBRE 1989
Photocomposition: The Unesco Courier
Photogravure ¡m pression: Maury Imprimeur SA , 2.1. route d'Etampes,
45330 Malesherbes
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors In countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
ALBANIA. Ndermarrja e perpjes se libnt'. Tirana ARGENTINA. Librería el
Correo de la Unesco - EDILYR. SRL. Tucuman 1685. 1050 Buenos Aires
AUSTRALIA. Books only: Educational Supplies Ply Ltd , P.O. Box 33,
Brookvale 2100. NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty Subscriptions Dept.. P O
Box 33. Brookvale 2100. NSW. Sub-agents United Nations Association of
Australia, Victorian Division. 328 Flinders Street. Melbourne 3000-Hunter
Publications, 58a Gipps Si . Collmgwood, Victoria 3066. AUSTRIA. Gerold
and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools Interna¬
tional. Arab Regional Office. P O Box 726. Bahrain; The Arabian Agencies
and Distributing Co.. Al Mutanabi St.. PO Box 1 56. Manama BANGLADESH
Kanm International. GPO Box No; 2141. 64/1 Manipun Para. Tejgaon.
Farmgate. Dhaka. BAR8AD0S. University of the West Indies Bookshop.
Cave Hill Campus. P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown. BELGIUM. Jean de Lannoy. 202
Ave.duRoi. 1060 Brussels BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre. PO Box 91
Gaborone. BRAZIL. Fundacáo Getúlio Vargas, Servico del Publicaçoes.
caixa postal 9.042-ZC-05 Praia de Botafogo 188, Rio de Janeiro (RJ) 2000;
Books only Imagem Latinoamericana. Av. Paulista 750, 1 andar, caixa postal
30455. Sao Paulo CEP 01051. BULGARIA. Hemus. Kantora Literatura,
boulevard Rousky 6. Sofia. BURMA. Trade Corporation no. (9), 550-552
Merchant Street. Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd. 1294
Algoma Road. Ottawa. Ontario K18 3W8. (Stores 61 Sparks Street, Ottawa.
211 Yonge St , Toronto. Sales office- 7575 Trans Canada Hwy. Ste 305. St.
Laurent, Quebec H4T 1V6. CAMEROON. Cameroon Book Centre. PO Box
123. Limbe. Commission Nationale. BP 1600. Yaounde CHILE. Editorial
Universitaria S A . Departamento de Importaciones. M Luisa Santander
0447, casilla 10220. Santiago: Editorial 'Andres Bello'. Av. R. Lyon 946.
Casillo 4256. Santiago de Chile, Dipublic. Antonio Varas 671 . 2o piso, casilla
14364, Correo 21. Santiago. CHINA. China National Publications Import and
Export Corporation. P O. Box 88, Bei|ing. COLOMBIA. Instituto Colombiano
de Cultura (Colcultura), Carrera 3A, n° 18/ 24, Bogota; Books only: Librería
Buchholz Galena. Calle 59, No; 13-13. Bogota. CYPRUS. 'MAM'. Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avene. PO Box 1 722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S N.T.L..
Spalena 51-113 02. Prague 1; For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag -Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6.893 31 Bratislava: PNS-UED, Jmdnsska 14, praha 1:
Slovart. Gottwaldovo Nam 6, 805 32 Bratislava. DEM. REP. OF YEMEN. 1 4th
October Corporation. PO Box 4227, Aden DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-
OG. Tidsskriltservice. 35 Norre Sogade. DK-1970 Kobenhavn K
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Librería Blasco. Avenida Bolivar. No: 402. esq
Hermanos Deligne. Santo Domingo. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). Un¬
esco Publications Centre. No. 1 Talaat Harb St.. Cairo. ETHIOPIA. Ethiopian
National Agency for Unesco. PO Box 2996. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateemmen Kir|akauppa, P. O. Box 128. SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalamen
Kirjakauppa Oy. Koivuvaarankuja 2 01640 Vantaa 64 FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans. Periodicals only. Unesco CPD /
V-1 . rue Miollis. 7501 5 Pans GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchex-
porl. Postfach 140. Leninstrasse 16. 7010. Leipzig FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum. Deutscher Unesco-Kurier
Vertrieb. Basaltstrasse 57. D5300 Bonn 3; UNO-Verlag. Simrockslrasse 23.
D-5300 Bonn 1. S. Karger GmbH. Verlag Angerhofstrasse 9. Postfach 2
D-8034 Germering / München For scientific maps only Geo Center. Posdach
800830. 7000 Stuttgart 80 GHANA. Books only: Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd.. PO Box 195. Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.. PO 7869. Accra.
The University Bookshop ol Ghana. Accra, The University Bookshop ol Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon. PO Box 1 . Legon Periodicals only:
Fides Entreprises. P.O. Box 14129, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom. GREECE. Eleftheroudakis SA. International Bookstore, 4 Nikis
Street. Athens. John Mihalopoulos & Son SA. International Booksellers. P.O.
Box 10073. 541 10 Thessaloniki. Greek National Commission for unesco. 3
Akadimias Street. Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co , 13-15 Lock
Road, Kowloon; Federal Publications (HK) Ltd . Tokwawan, Kowloon; Hong
Kong Government Information Services, Publication Section. Hong Kong:
Periodicals only: Beaconsfield House 6th floor. Queen s Road Central. Victor¬
ia. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT. P.O B. 149-H-1389. Budapest 62
ICELAND. Snaeb|orn Jonsson and Co.. H.F Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykiavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.. Kamam Marg. Ballard Estate. Bombay 400038:
17 Chitaranjan Ave . Calcutta 13, 36a. Anna Salai. Mount Road, Madras 2:
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd.,
Bangalore 560001: 3-5-820 Hyderguda. Hyderabad -500001 Sub-agents.
Oxford Book and Stationery Co.. 1 7 Park St.. Calcutta 70016; Sandia House.
New Delhi 11 0001. INDONESIA. Bhralara Publishers and Booksellers. 29.
Jl , Oto Iskandardmata 111, Jakarta; Indira P. T.. Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco. 1 188 Englab
Ave.. Rostam Give Building. P O. Box 11365-4498. Teheran 13158.
IRELAND.Penodica/son/y The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd .POBox
43A. Walkmstown. Dublin 12; Booksonly. TDC Publishers. 1 1 North Frederick
Street. Dublin 7. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions. Inc., c/o Steimatzky Ltd .
PO Box 628. Tel Aviv: ABC. Bookstore Ltd. P O Box 1283. 71 AHenbyRd..
Tel Aviv 61000. ITALY. Ucosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni. S p A (. Via
Lamarmora 45. Casella Postale 552. 50121 Florence, via Bartolmi 29, 20155
Milan; FAO Bookshop, via délie Terme di Caracaila. 001 00 Rome. JAMAICA.
University of the West Indies Bookshop. Mona. Kingston 7. JAPAN. Eastern
Book Service Inc. 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku. Tokyo 113. JORDAN
Jordan Distribution Agency. PO Box 375, Amman Periodicals only: Jordan
Book Cerjtre Co Ltd.. PO Box 301 . Al Jubeiha. Amman. KENYA. East African
Publishing House. PO 30571. Nairobi; Africa Book Sen/ices Ltd, Quran
House. Mangano Street. PO Box 45245. Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P O Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co.. Ltd, POB 2942. Kuwait: Periodicals only Farafaiia Press
Agency, P.O Box SAFA 4541 . Kuwait. LEBANON. Librairie Antoine A Naufal
et Frères. BP 656. Beirut. LESOTHO Mazenod Book Centre. PO Mazenod.
Maseru. LIBERIA National Bookstore, Mechlin and Carey Streets. PO Box
590. Monrovia: Cole and Yancy Bookshops Lid.. PO Box 286, Monrovia.-
LUXEMBOURG. Books only: Librairie Paul Brück. 22. Grande-Rue. Luxem¬
bourg: Periodical: Messageries Paul Kraus. BP 1022, Luxembourg MALAWI
Malawi Book Service, Head Office. PO Box 30044. Chichin, Blantyre 3.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur-
22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITANIA GRA LI.-
COMA.. 1 rue du Souk X, Avenue kennedy. Nouakchott. MAURITIUS.
Nalanda Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis. MEXICO. Librena El
Correo de la Unesco. Actipan 66. Colonia del Valle. Apartado postal 61 1 64,
06600 Mexico DF. MONACO. British Library. 30 Bd. des Moulins. Monte
Carlo. MORROCCO. Librairie 'Aux belles images'. 262 ave. Mohammed-V,
Rabat, Librairie des écoles. 1 2 ave. Hassan-ll. Casaglanca. Société chenfien-
ne de distribution et de presse, SOCHEPRESS, angle rues de Dînant et St.
Saens. BP 1 3683, Casablanca 05 MOZAMBIQUE. Instituto National do Livro
edo Disco (INLD), avenida 24 de Julho 1921 r/d Io andar. Maputo NEPAL.
Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Books only
Keesing. Boeken B V.. Hogehilweg 13. Postbus 1118. 1000 BC Amsterdam
Periodicals Faxon Europe, P.O. Box 197. 1000 AD Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N V.. PO Box 200. Willem-
stad. Curaçao. NA. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing. PO. Box
14277-Kilbirme. Wellington. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife: The
University Bookshop of Ibadan. P O 286: The University Bookshop of Nsukka:
The University Bookshop of Lagos: The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum. P.OB 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1;
Universitets Bokhandelen. Unrversitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blmdern, Oslo
3; Periodicals only Narvesen A/S. Litteraturt Jenesten. POB 6 1 25 Erterstad,
N 0602 Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency. 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam.
P.O. Box No. 729. Lahore 3: Unesco Publications Centre. Regional Office for
Book Development m Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society. P O. Box
6950, Karachi 29. PANAMA. Distribuidora Cultura Internacional. Apartado
7571, Zona 5. Panama. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store inc. 701 Ri2al
Avenue, Manila. POLAND. Orpan-lmport. Palac Kultury I Nauki. Warsaw: Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiesae No. 7 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda Livrana Portugal, ma do Carmo 70. Lisbon. ROMANIA.
ARTEXIM Export- Import. Piata Scienten. no. 1. PO Box 33-16. 70005
Bucharest. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan, Olaya Mam Street. Ibrahim Bm
Sulaym Building, Riyadh. SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd.. Kmgsgate
House. PO Box 131 . Mahé. National Bookshop. PO Box 48. Mahé SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay College, Njala University and Sierra leone Diocesan
Bookshops. Freetown. SINGAPORE. Righteous Enterprises. P.O. Box 562,
Kallang Basm Post Office, Singapore 91 33. SOCIALIST PEOPLE'S LIBYAN
ARAB JAMAHIRIYA. General Establishment for Publishing. Distribution and
Advertising. Souf AI Mahmoud: St.. PO Box 959. Tripoli SOMALIA. Modern
Book Shop and General, PO Box ùàô. Mogadiscio. SPAIN. Mundi-Prensa
Libros SA, apartado 1223. Castelló 37, Madrid 1 : Ediciones Liber, apartado
17. Magdalena 8. Ondárroa (Vizcaya): Donaire. Ronda de Oute.ro. 20,
apartado de correos 341. La Coruña. books only: Librería Castells. Ronda
Universidad 13 y 15. Barcelona 7, Librería de la Generalität de Catalunya,
Palan Mo|a. Rambla de los Estudios 1 18, 08 002 Barcelona. SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, POB 244,
Colombo 2. SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop. P O. Box 1118. Khartoum.
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco. P.O. Box 2943,
Paramaribo. SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fntzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel. Regenng-
sgatan 12, 8ox 16356. S-103 27 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier.
Svenska FN Forbundet. Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm: For
periodicals only Wennergren-Williams AB. Nordenflychtsvagen 70. S-104. 25
Stockholm: Esselte Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62-101, 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag. 5 Ranmstrasse, Zurich; Librairies
Payot in Geneva Lausanne. Basle. Berne. Vevey. Montreux, Neuchâtel and
Zurich SYRIA. Aleppo University Books Establishment. University of Aleppo,
Aleppo ' TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. POB. 9030. Dar-es-
Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road.
Siyaeg Phaya Sn, PO Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Ave.. Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road.
Bangkok; ROEAP, PO Box 1425. Bangkok 10500. TRINIDAD AND TOBA¬
GO. National Commission for Unesco. 18 Alexandra St . St. Clair. Port-ot-
Spain. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A S . Istiklàl Caddesi. No 469, Posta Kutusu
219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. PO Box 7145. Kampa¬
la. UNITED ARAB EMIRATES. Maktabat al Maktaba. PO Box 15408. Al Am.
Abu Dhabi. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M Stationery Office. PO Box 276. London,
SW8 5DT; H.M. S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh. Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham, Bristol; Third World Publications, 151 Stratford Road, Birming¬
ham Bi 1 1RD; for scientific maps only. McCarta Ltd.. 122 King's Cross Rd.
London WClX 9DS. UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. Bernan-UNIPUB,
Periodicals Department. 461 1-F .Assembly Drive. Lanham. MO 20706 4391.
URUGUAY. Ediciones Trecho. S A.. Maldonado 1092, Montevideo. USSR.
V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Oimilrova 39. Moskva 113095.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost. Ilica 30/11. Zagreb: Cankarjeva Zalozba. Zopitar-
jeva 2. Lubl|ana; Nolit. Terazije 13 / VIII. 1 1000 Belgrade: periodicals only
Jugosolvena Kniga. PO Box 36, YU 11001 Belgrade ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd.. PO. Box 2664, Lusaka
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd . 1 Norwich Union Centre. Harare.
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 10 1989 OPI-89- 1 473 A
PHOTO CREDITS
Cover, page 3 (left): Brigitte Salom © The Unesco Courier. Page 2: © Annette Ghéan-Bisciglia, Paris. Page 3 (right): S. Bassouls © Sygma,
Paris. Page 5: T. Orban © Sygma, Paris. Pages 6-7: © Roger Viollet, Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris. Pages 8-9: © RMN, Musée du Louvre,
Paris. Page 10: D. Cameron © Sygma, Paris. Page 12: J. Guichard © Sygma, Paris. Pages 13, 16, 17, 19, 20, 31, 32-33 (above), 39, 40, 42-43,
43: Cahiers du Cinéma, Paris. Page 15: Jean Loup Passek, Paris. Page 21: J.L. Bulliard © Sygma, Paris. Pages 22, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28-29, 32
(centre), 37, 40-41, 41: © Abbas Fahdel Collection, Paris. Page 23: © All Rights Reserved. Page 28 (inset): © Sygma, Paris. Page 32 (above),
32-33 (below): © Russian edition of The Unesco Courier, Moscow. Pages 34-35, 36: © Assia Djebar, Paris. Page 42: © Cinémathèque Française,
Paris. Pages 44-45: © Bulloz, Paris, Musée de Versailles. Pages 45, 47: © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris. Pages 48, 49: Bourseiller © Sygma,
Paris. Back cover: © Colorphoto Hinz Allschwil / Musée des Beaux arts, Bale.
Correction (September 1989 issue): Page 14: Photos from Histoire des Beni Hilal et de ce qui leur advint dans
leur marche vers l'Ouest, by M. Galley and A. Ayoub, Association des classiques africains, Paris, 1983. Top
illustration: a lithograph from the Museum of the Institute of Geography, Cairo; lower illustration shows a
Tunisian painting on glass (M. Galley collection) which featured as the cover of the book mentioned above.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
»»;.
T»~
m'*^
^
'3**
»
J "*+ 1'
jT M. ''
t
«if
Following the most arr»brtious archaeological salvage
operation of all timesaving the temples of Abu
Simbel in Egyptian Nubia from being submerged by
the waters of the Nileand the reconstruction of one
of the world's renowned holy places, the Buddhist
sanctuary of Borobudur in Indonesia, Unesco is now
campaigning for the safeguard of 27 other groups
of monuments and sites which are in need of assis¬
tance if they are to survive.
You can play a part in this valuable work by making
a donation, specifying the campaign that you wish
to support.* Contributions may be sent by cheque
to the order of Unesco to the following address: Cul¬
tural Heritage Division, Unesco, 1 rue Miollis, 75015
Paris, France.
* Herat (Afghanistan), Jesuit Missions of the Guaranis (Argentina, Bra¬
zil and Paraguay), Paharpur Vihara and Bagerhat (Bangladesh), Plaza
Vieja of Havana (Cuba), Museums in Aswan and Cairo (Arab Republic
of Egypt), The Acropofes (Greece), Monuments of Guatemala, Monuments
and sites of Haiti, Venice (Italy), Monuments and sites of Malta, Fez
(Morocco), Ancient cities of Mauritania, Kathmandu (Nepal), Moenjo-
daro (Pakistan), San Francisco de Lima (Peru), Island of Goree (Sene¬
gal), Cultural Wangle of Sri Lanka, SukhotJiai (Thailand). Tyre (Lebanon),
Carthage (Tunisia). Istanbul and Goreme (Turkey), Hue (Malta), Sana'a
(Yemen Arab Republic), Wadl Hadramawt and Shibam (People's Demo¬
cratic Republic of Yemen), Montenegro (Yugoslavia), Cultural Heritage
of East Africa (Kenya, Uganda and Tanzania).
*y
?
Ia
*t?Wr'-
J
*Ar*
fc :
Y *
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
V
]]>
</page>
</document>
