<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="085187eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
J
%f>
st
THE FORTUNES OF NONEY
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters
We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
The Messenger
1980, monotype in oils (40 x 35 cm)
by Delia Nimo
Delia Nimo is an Argentine artist whose works have been
described by French critic Michel Conil-Lacoste as "X-rays of
living humanity, clinging to its destiny". Her quest for
universality in art grows directly from the roots of her own
experience. She has said that her underlying theme is always
"humankind at odds with the world."
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY 1990
N N
Today there are no more
unexplored continents,
unknown seas or mysterious
islands. But while we can
overcome the physical
barriers to exploration, the
barriers of mutual ignorance
between different peoples
and cultures have in many
cases still not been
dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can
voyage to the ends of the
earth. But a different kind
of Odyssey now beckonsan
exploration of the world's
many cultural landscapes, the
ways of life of its different
peoples and their outlook on
the world in which they live.
It is such an Odyssey that
the Unesco Courier proposes
to you, its readers. Each
month contributors of
different nationalities provide
from different cultural and
professional standpoints an
authoritative treatment of a
theme of universal interest.
The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes is respect
for the dignity of man
everywhere.
9
THE FORTUNES
OF MONEY
UNCOMMON COIN
by Jean-Michd Servet
WHEN COCOA WAS USED AS CURRENCY
by Piedad Péniche Rivera 16
MOLLUSC MONEY
by A. Félix Iroko 21
DINARS CLUB
by Gérard Krebs 26
WHEELERS AND DEALERS
OF RENAISSANCE EUROPE
by Lucien Gillard 32
THE RISE OF THE GREENBACK
by Jan Kregel 17
PROBLEMS AND PARADOXES OF MONEY
by Ghislain Deleplace 41
The French economist Marie-Thérèse Boyer-Xambeu,
professor of economics at the University of Paris VII,
was special consultant for this issue.
4
Interview with
SEMBENE OUSMANE
Poet of the African cinema
45
IN BRIEF..
46
lo REFLECTIONS
The struggle of day
and night
by Abdol-Hosseyn Zarrinkoub
Carnival in Luanda
by Domingos Van-Dunem
49
MEMORIAL
A Museum for Peace
by Howard Brabyn
50
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
Cover: A miscellany of money
from the collection of the
Museum of the Paris Mint.
Back cover: Money to burn? In
Singapore bundles of imitation
banknotes are set ablaze as
propitiatory offerings at funerals
and at New Year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
N W
Sembène Ousmane
Poet of the African cinema
Sembène Ousmane is one of Africa's
most notable writers and film-makers.
His Borom Saret (1963) was the first
film made by an African on a fictional
subject to be distributed outside Africa.
His films and novels examine the many
faces of a continent emerging from the
colonial era, at grips with the tensions
of independence and modernization.
What does it mean to be a film-maker in Africa these days?
What are the hopes, difficulties and challenges?
Whether they are making films for the cinema or for
television, African film-makers work with images and they
are heirs to the very old but still living tradition of oral story¬
telling. Images can be considered as a development of the
oral tradition insofar as they are addressed to a vast number
of people who, in the Third World in general and especially
in Africa, are unable or in some cases do not even have the
time to read. The image is really a short cut.
Let me give you an example. I like to organize travel¬
ling picture shows. I go to a village and show a film, and
then we have a discussion about it. As a result of what the
audience has seen, heard and remembered, I find out how
useful I am as the creator of the film. Once the lights go
on again, people start to discuss the film. In spite of political
differences and religious divisions, everyone's point of view
is represented, and that's important.
Then I ask them why they need artists. I have put this
question to university teachers and to students in their final
year of secondary school. The answer seems to be that some
of our intellectuals, especially those who are politically com¬
mitted, expect artists to make proposals, to offer solutions
and even, I might add, speaking ironically, to make a revo¬
lution for them by proxy. To hear them, you would think
that art was meant to provide an answer to all their worries.
Art rather than politics?
But art does play a role in politics. Not politics in the
sense of scoring cheap political points, obviously. People
are immersed in art and culture from the cradle to the grave.
In the African tradition, cinema is something which relates
to human beings in their entirety.
Has African cinema developed only recently, with the
emergence ofAfrican film-makers, or does it date back to
colonial times?
In colonial times, the cinema was a form of entertain¬
ment for foreigners. The black African world was only seen
as part of a banana plantation or a coconut grove, or through
stock characters of loyal houseboys and servants. Now,
however, African film-makers are raising real issues.
They may not always raise them successfully, but they are
raising them nevertheless. People are thus slowly starting
to identify with their history and the cinema is becoming
something real.
Would you go so far as to say that the cinema is now the
most powerful form of artistic expression in Africa?
Absolutely! African cinema is a form of self-communion.
There are many things that we have not been taught and
are in danger of losing: with the cinema, we can safeguard
them and people can see them.
Would you say the same of television programmes, which
may have been produced in another African country or
even on another continent?
If a football match is being televised, then people watch
television. Otherwise, they go to the cinema! Some serials
have been relatively successful, but the constant cliff-hanging
becomes boring in the long run. In the ten years since we
have had television in Senegal, we have seen Dallas, Dynasty,
Shaka....
Do serials like Dallas appeal to the general public?
Of course! They represent success and the "American way
of life". They are full of beautiful women in beautiful
settings, full of everything we hate yet dream about. It is
difficult to analyse their attraction in logical terms. They
have an immoral side, but morality no longer comes before
individual success. In colonial times, the land was occupied,
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
but people's minds were free. Even though my relatives
my uncles, for examplemay have been civil servants and
may have worn topees or ties, they returned to their own
culture and their own world when they came home to their
families. They still had something to say to their wives and
children and their neighbours. But television takes possession
of people's minds. Another culture, a completely different
view of things, is brought into the home. The model
of society handed down by our ancestors is smashed
and is replaced by another. That is where the danger of
television lies.
Do you think it is completely destructive?
Yes, completely, because African society is not bringing
forth a fresh culture to contend with this challenge. We are
more familiar with European fairy tales than with our own
traditional stories. There are no traditional story-tellers left
in the towns. Our children go to school and are taught in
a foreign language. When they come out of school, they go
off and watch foreign stories with their parents.
But a society cannot turn backwards. So what should
be done?
The audiences at my travelling picture shows ask me the
same labyrinthine question. In the first place, we must all
know what we want. Naturally, we are all in favour of
individual freedom, but where do we want to go with that
freedom and what do we want to do with it? What do you
do with freedom when you have countries that cannot
educate three-quarters of their children, where unemploy¬
ment is rife, where there is no work, and calamities pour
down on you? Birth is always attended by pain. I was not
present at the Creation, but when Allah created the world,
there must surely have been what we now call a "Big Bang".
There must have been an explosion, because nothing can
be accomplished without an explosion. Life is reborn of
death. You sow seeds and they decompose; a crack opens
up in the earth and they sprout. There is no alternative.
For the people, being free means having the right to work
and to speak out. We all have to wage our own struggle and
to pay for it accordingly.
And what do the people say?
They expect somebody to speak out on their behalf. You
know, black Africa's heritage is a heavy burden. No sooner
had we started to form embryonic states, which were far
from perfect, than we had to contend with the slave trade
in which, incidentally, some Africans took part. For four
or five centuries, some African chiefs were accessories to
this monstrous trade. After that came colonization, which
is perhaps the worst thing that ever happened to us. The
colonialists trained some people, but only to occupy subor¬
dinate positions, not to govern themselves. The colonial
master's presence had become necessary. In the end we
fought for independence, but we did not know what it was
or even who we were. We had a common territory but
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
different cultures. Within each geographical boundary a host
of cultures existed side by side. We are now creating a fresh
culture, but it is based on a language which is not our own.
That is even more serious.
Is this when artists should make their voices heard?
Yes. This is where they come into their own. People listen
to them and expect them to speak out. Historically, no other
creative artists have ever carried as much responsibility as
novelists and film-makers. This takes us to the ancient
African tradition of the "griot". Everybody knows that
griots are crazy. Every village has its "simpleton" who dares
to say out loud what other people only whisper in the
solitude of their huts. We laugh at him, but we acknowledge
that he is right.
There used to be griots; now there are artists, film-makers.
Could this handing down of symbols not be a reason for
hope? After all, perfect democracy can hardly be expected
to emerge from chaos at a single stroke....
In democracy it is up to the people, not the artist, to speak
out. In the past, power was wielded by the elders and by
wise men. Nowadays the pattern has been reversed. The
elders are no longer the fount of knowledge and no one
listens to them any more. What radio, television and the
newspapers say does not originate with them. Society is
being torn apart and people are going crazy as a result. What
I say is that the only way to be happy here is to go crazy.
The countries of the Third World face many challenges.
Are you one ofthose who consider that these challenges come
primarily from outside, or do you think that they emanate
from within the society itself?
Outside the continent we have adversaries and we have
allies. I would say that Africa's real enemiesits long¬
standing enemiesare within. If we are to move forward,
therefore, we must sort out our own problems and rely prin¬
cipally on ourselves. Basically, we have three priorities: we
have to apply our own remedies, however limited, to our
own problems; we have to develop education; and we have
to provide work for the people.
What about freedom of speech?
Speech is a duty in Africa. Every head of a family is
expected to attend village meetings"palavers"to represent
his clan or his household. Moreover, he has to speak, if he
does not want to be thought of as a coward. But he also
has to listen. There is a very fine tradition in the "palaver":
when a man has finished speaking, the oldest member
of the group says "We have heard what you have said and
understood what you have not said". Naturally, nowadays,
in a democracy the scale is different. Every citizen has
to express his or her views. The issues are no longer the
same, but the tradition of the "palaver" could perhaps
open up paths and suggest new ways in which people could
organize themselves.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
T
JLhHE need for a form of money to serve as a medium of exchange
arose at a very early stage in history, and ever since then an astonishing
range of objects has been used for the purpose at different times and
placesfeathers, shells, cocoa beans, silver, gold, and paper notes, to name
but a few. As time went by, the functions of money diversified. A medium
of payment for goods and services, a standard of value and a store of
purchasing power, it eventually became a convention reflecting people's
confidence in society.
The subject of money is full of mystery and paradox. It creates, as Lucien
Gillard points out in this issue, "a coherent area within which people have
a common yardstick with which to assess their credits and debts". Within
this area its use gives rise to inequalities. It is a measure of wealth and, by
the same token, of poverty. It became an attribute of state power, but also,
through fraud, a means whereby the power of the state was contested.
Although a currency is legal tender within fixed boundaries, it is linked by
exchange rates to other currency areas and international markets.
Italian bankers in the
14th century, fresco by the
Florentine artist
Niccolo di Pietro Gerini,
139S.
Often attacked by moralists and rejected by Utopians, sometimes relegated
to a secondary role even by economists but omnipresent in our daily lives,
money has contributed, by facilitating trade and boosting economic activity,
to certain decisive steps in the history of civilization. In this issue we evoke
some milestones in monetary history in the hope that they will help to
throw some light on the role of money in the world today.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Uncommon coin
A variety of unusual objects have been
used since ancient times to finance trade
and cement political and social life
BY JEAN-MICHEL SERVET
K
10
I ECKLACES or bracelets of shells, pearls, teeth,
bones or feathers, fragments of stone or metal,
pottery, pieces of cloth, and other unlikely
objects are labelled as "primitive money" in
many museum collections and ethnographical or
archaeological publications.
Other apparently similar objects are
described as ornaments or jewellery, although
there is no evidence to prove that they were used
for display rather than as money. Their degree
of preservation, which suggests that they were
highly valued by their owners, together with
physical characteristics indicating a non-utilitarian
purpose, may have led archaeologists and students
of prehistory to attribute a purely decorative
function to these treasures which in fact were also
used as money.
Money in ancient civilizations
Over 2,000 years ago, Aristotle observed that
before coins were used people gave things that
they possessed in abundance in exchange for
things they lacked. This practice was known as
metadosis. Ethnologists have described how very
ancient yet strongly hierarchical societies used
complex exchange systems such as the kula of the
western Pacific, the hilaba and the malaki of
central Africa and the potlatcb of the northwest
coast of North America.
Money, like relationships involving hierarchy
and domination, is thus not a modern invention.
It was a feature of even more ancient civilizations
than those of the Mediterranean basin, of the
Near or the Far East, or of Central America. The
circulation of precious objects within and
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Far left: shaped in the form
of a throwing knife, this iron
object from the Central
African Republic was once
used as money. Left,
wampum, shell beads woven
with strips of hide into
strings or belts which the
North American Indians
used in their dealings with
white traders in the 17th and
18th centuries. Below, objects
used in the Solomon Islands
for making shell money.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
between these communities seems to have been
universal, and in a sense to foreshadow the func¬
tions of money as a medium of exchange and as
a unit of account.
But in such ancient societies these basic func¬
tions had not yet become purely economic. They
were an emanation of kinship systems and polit¬
ical alliances, beliefs and cults, which influenced
the supply of labour, organized production and
justified the distribution of wealth.
Money, or in this case "palaeomoney", was
the active instrument of social life. It was used
at times of birth, marriage and mourning, to
declare war and make peace, as compensation for
physical or moral wrongs, and as a means of
propitiating the gods of fertility and death. On
the other hand, it was not yet used to pay debts
or wages or to buy goods.
The scarcity and lack of intrinsic usefulness
which characterize palaeomoney are typical of
some modern forms of money. Palaeomoney also
anticipated the economic and political nature of
modern currencies, on the one hand by setting
a value on different activities and material goods
and thus foreshadowing today's standardized
methods of payment, on the other by reflecting
and reinforcing the hierarchical power relations
between individuals and groups.
Better than barter
The exchange systems of these ancient commu¬
nities were thus much more complex than that
of a simple barter economy.
From very early times, commodities circu¬
lated over great distances. Specimens of durable
materials such as amber and obsidian have been
found hundreds of kilometres from their place
of origin, distances as great as that from southern
Australia to the northern coasts of New Guinea,
and from the Black Sea to Poland and the
Rhineland. As early as the Upper Palaeolithic
Period (35,000-10,000 years ago), Cro-Magnon
man in the Dordogne area of southern France was
Above, Melanesian feather
money consisting of a fibre
rope decorated with red
feathers and fragments of
shell. Right, a bundle of iron
spikes which was used as
money in the Congo (late
19th century).
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
using shells brought from the Atlantic ocean, 200
kilometres away.
At a later stage different societies came to
specialize in the production of a particular item
for exchange and as a means of payment for
produce acquired from other groups. Examples
of such commodities are stone axes, bars of salt,
pottery and bark cloaks. Later still, groups
specializing in trade emerged within these socie¬
ties and travelled tens or even hundreds of
kilometres in the course of their activities.
This is far removed from a barter economy,
where goods are exchanged directly, without any
intermediate transaction. However, the develop¬
ment of an objective system for measuring value
was still limited. The price of the goods ex¬
changed was primarily the expression of a social
relationship between individuals and communi¬
ties. The marketplace was not yet the driving
force behind monetary development.
The first coins
The use of money grew rapidly with the develop¬
ment of states, which managed the surplus wealth
created by the exploitation of slaves, serfs or
peasants, by long-distance trade or the despolia¬
tion of neighbouring peoples. Tributes and taxes
began to be evaluated and methods of payment
for trade in markets and ports began to be stan¬
dardized.
Among the wide range of commodities which
served as money in ancient societiesthe pieces
of cloth and cocoa beans of the Maya and Aztec
empires, the cowrie shells and gold of the West
African kingdoms, the bean-shaped ingots of the
Greek cities, the iron bars of the Hittites, the
barley and wheat of Mesopotamia, the wheat and
copper of Egypt, the millet and silks of China-
coins are of particular interest because their use
has continued to the present day.
At first, coins were only one form of metal
currency. Before coins circulated in China, and
even after they were introduced in the late fourth
Pecuniary portraits
From top to bottom: warrior
with two oxen, Macedonian
octadrachm (early 6th
century BC); silver stater
from the Mcnde wine-
producing region of
Macedonia (5th century BC);
horse (obverse) and palm tree
(reverse), silver tetradrachm
from Carthage (4th century
BC); nymph's bead and
dolphins (obverse) and four-
horse chariot (reverse),
decadrachm from Syracuse
(c. 400 BC); rams' heads and
dolphins, silver stater from
the Creek city of Pbocis
(c. 479-470 BC). 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
century BC, small-scale replicas of spades and
knives were used as money. The first coins were
struck in the seventh century BC in Asia Minor
and in Greece, where some cities were still using
bean-shaped ingots. Small silver ingots punched
with a variety of motifs were used as currency
in India from the same period until coins were
introduced there in the fourth century BC.
The influence of Greece
The cities of ancient Greece played a crucial role
in the history of coinage. For centuries the Greek
numismatic tradition was widely propagated,
either directly or through a complex network
of influences. In the wake of the conquests of
Alexander the Great, whose troops seized pre¬
cious metal from the treasuries of Near-Eastern
potentates and turned it into coinage, Greek coins
were widely distributed in the Mediterranean
countries.
The Romans, who initially used bronze in¬
gots like those of the Etruscans, minted their first
coins in the third century BC under the influence
of the Greek cities of southern Italy. Roman
colonization led to the use of coinage to an extent
unmatched until the European colonial expansion
of the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
Beyond the eastern frontiers of the Roman
empire, between Khorasan and Mesopotamia,
the Sasanian dynasty continued a numismatic
Above, gold di-stater
adorned with the head of the
goddess Athena issued during
the reign of Alexander the
Great (336-323 BC).
Right, Roman and Byzantine
gold coins.
Opposite page,
Greek silver stater depicting
the labyrinth of Knossos,
Crete (c. 450 BC).
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
tradition that displayed a strong Hellenistic
influence and had been transmitted by the
Parthians, whose empire (founded between the
third and the second century BC) stretched at its
height from the Euphrates to Afghanistan. This
Hellenistic tradition also influenced early Islamic
coins, while the Roman tradition was carried on
in Christian Europe.
A similar process occurred in India, which
was subject to waves of Greek influence both
direct and indirect, from the arrival of Alexander's
troops and contact with the Roman empire to
Muslim and European colonization.
The ritual significance
of coins
In all these civilizations, coins were not immedi¬
ately seen as a monetary instrument superior to
other accepted methods of payment, with which
they long coexisted. Metal discs, more or less well-
stamped, could be used in all kinds of ways.
When they changed hands it signified more than
just a commercial transactionit could symbolize
an exchange of gifts or even tribute.
The first coins of the Greek cities were thus
not issued as a direct response to commercial
requirements. Their value was too high to pay
for everyday goods in the marketplace. In long-
EAN-MICHEL SERVET
is a French economist with
a special interest in
"palaeomoney". He is the
author of Nomismata: état
et origines de ¡a monnaie
(1984) and Idées
économiques sous la
Révolution: 1789-1794
(1989), both published by
Presses Universitaires de
Lyon, France.
distance transactions, carried out largely by sea,
the goods themselves were the means of payment.
What then was the original function of these
coins? At first it seems that they were needed in
dealings within and between the Greek cities, and
above all they had a political and religious
function.
This dual role was not however an obstacle
to the use of coins in commerce. The metal of
which they were made had itself been the object
of long-distance transactions since very ancient
times, when trade had important political and
social overtones. The flexibility allowed by
weighed pieces of metal which could be divided
into small units, and their distribution in societies
with widely different customs, gradually estab¬
lished them as the preferred method of trading
and of paying taxes in the ancient world.
Coins stamped with the images of gods and
rulers kept their essentially political function until
the Roman era, when they were issued to com¬
memorate public games or military campaigns.
The sacrificial and ritual significance of coins
persists even today, as when they are buried in
the foundations of buildings and bridges or flung
into fountains and wells as propitiatory offerings,
used symbolically to reinforce marriage contracts,
or placed in the mouths or hands of the dead so
that they can pay their way in the next world.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
i
'*
,^7 si v» /,
BY PIEDAD PENICHE RIVERO
16
When cocoa was
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
used as currency
Money literally grew on trees in parts of
pre-Columbian America, where cocoa
was invested with the magic attributes of
the god Quetzalcóatl and brought wealth
and prestige to those who owned it
Above, Maya stone sculpture
of a warrior. Left,
Quetzalcóatl and his
companion as depicted in an
Aztec manuscript, the
Codex Borbonicus. ^B
'M<LONEY grows on trees," the Spanish
chroniclers who followed the conquistadors to
Mexico noted with amazement when they saw
that cocoa beans were used as currency.
At that time there were three major cocoa-
producing regions: Chontalpa and Soconusco in
Mexico, and the Ulúa basin in Honduras. Produc¬
tion, circulation and consumption of the precious
beans were tightly controlled by the nobles and
merchants of the Valley of Mexico and Yucatán.
Cocoa was expensive because of low yields and
transport problems.
Cocoa was a primitive form of currency and
could not perform all the functions of money.
It was widely used as a medium of exchange, but
to measure value the Aztecs and Mayas tended
to use quachtli, pieces of cotton fabric which
represented a given amount of work.
In Yucatán, one quachtli was equivalent to
450 hours of work. And while we do not know
how many hours it took to make each of the
pieces of cloth which formed part of the tribute
raised by the Aztec emperors, we know that each
one was worth almost 100 cocoa beans. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Above, the Pyramid of Kukulkan at Chichén Itzá, one
of the great cities of the Maya-Toltec civilization, north
of Yucatán, Mexico.
Right, cacao tree (Theobroma cacao). Far right, cacao
fruit cut open to show the seeds (cocoa beans).
18
It seems certain, then, that the value of most
of the goods in circulation could be expressed in
cocoa, but was actually assessed in pieces of cloth
at constant value. Cocoa was used as money
because, unlike the pieces of cloth, it could be
divided up as required.
The ancient Mexicans used cocoa to prepare
chocolate, a ritual drink consumed exclusively by
aristocrats and warriors. Most people only had
the right to pulque, a fermented drink made from
agave. This prohibition strengthened the power
of the aristocracy, since chocolate was supposed
to be the food of the gods and to possess magical
properties.
Aztec 'chocolate soldiers'
Perhaps chocolate was associated with the blood
of human sacrifices, notably when the heart was
torn from victims offered to Quetzalcóatl, the
"plumed serpent", in the Toltec towns of Yucatán
and the Valley of Mexico.
According to Mexican mythology, Quetzal¬
cóatl, the "gardener of paradise", taught men how
to grow cocoa when he lived at the city of Tula.
When he left for the coast, he buried the "cur
rency" of that timesea-shells, feathers and pre¬
cious stones. Cocoa then began to be used as cur¬
rency instead, and was invested with the magic
attributes of the god who had introduced it.
The Aztecs were the last masters of the Valley
of Mexico. Their flourishing empire, which domi¬
nated all the peoples which had fought for con¬
trol of the Valley, owed its prosperity to tribute
rendered by its thirty-eight provinces, among
which Soconusco contributed, according to the
Codex Mendoza, 400 of the 980 loads of cocoa
demanded by the state.
The beans were deposited in "cocoa-houses"
and then taken to the centres of imperial
powertemples and barracks where it is recorded
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
PIEDAD PENICHE
RIVERO,
Mexican anthropologist and
archaeologist, is a former
staff member of the
anthropology faculty at the
University of Yucatán,
Mérida, Mexico. She is the
author of numerous
publications on the Maya
and Itzá civilizations,
including studies on the use
of cocoa beans as wealth
and a symbol of power.
that the Aztec soldiers consumed massive
amounts of chocolate.
Unlike those of the Aztecs, the Maya political
and mercantile élites overlapped, so that cocoa
entered Maya society through trade not tribute.
The circulation of cocoa beans was duplicated
by the production of an equivalent quantity of
cotton squares. Cocoa beans and cotton squares
served as standards of value for all kinds of com¬
modities including certain areas of land which
produced cash crops. Slavery came into being
when manpower was levied from among the
peasant communities. Men were bought and sold
with cocoa. According to the chronicler Diego
de Landa, the Mayas of Yucatán were "Strongly
inclined to trade. They dispatched salt, clothes
and slaves to Ulúa and Tabasco, and bartered
them for cocoa and rows of stones which served
them as money and enabled them to buy slaves
and other fine stones..."
Thanks to Maya and perhaps even Aztec
slaves, the increased productivity of the cocoa-
growing regions probably encouraged the circu¬
lation of cocoa among the lower classes, still
under the control of the aristocracy. Several eth¬
nographic chronicles from colonial times confirm
that cocoa was used as an offering and as a gift
at weddings and funerals.
What role did cocoa play in the accumula¬
tion of wealth? Among the Mayas and the Aztecs
different attitudes prevailed, generally dictated by
social status. In the Valley of Mexico the mer¬
chants had to behave with great circumspection
so as not to offend the emperor. Consequently,
records the chronicler Bernardion de Sahagún,
they were modestly, even poorly dressed. As for
the Pochtec merchants, they were forced by the
avarice of the nobility to give up large quantities
of cocoa as gifts and offerings to temples.
Whereas in the Valley of Mexico the posses¬
sion of cocoa was a status symbol, among the
Itzás of Yucatán fortunes in cocoa ostentatiously
displayed by rich lords who owned many slaves
and opulently decorated palaces also served to
stimulate production since they could be invested
in commercial farming and the acquisition of
captive manpower. This may explain why the
Spaniards retained the use of cocoa as money in
Yucatán, replacing cotton with their own currency,
the real, as an indicator of value, but continuing
to relate it to fluctuations in cocoa production.
Cocoa was still being used in the nineteenth
century to pay the wages of workmen in Yucatán
and other parts of Central America. This is clear
from an account by a North American traveller,
John L. Stephens, who noted in 1842 that in
Yucatán there were no copper coins nor any
specie less than the half real, that the Indians
earned very low wages with which they procured
the bare necessities, and that cocoa beans were
widely used as small change. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
*
f'~£
. , *«*» '
R>i
î*ji
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Mollusc money
Cowries and other colourful shell currencies
have circulated in Africa for many centuries
BY A. FELIX IROKO
Left, girls wearing cowrie
shell headdresses in
Karamoja province,
northeastern Uganda.
Below, cowries braided
into a fibre rope from
Papua New Guinea,
which was used either as
ornamentation or as
money.
X ROM the dawn of time to the twentieth cen¬
tury, many commodities were used as currency
in sub-Saharan Africa. They included metal rods
and bracelets, fabrics, salt, pearls, shirt buttons
and seashells. Of all these mediums of exchange,
shells enjoyed the widest circulation.
Cowries, marginellas and olive shells, of
marine origin, were those most often used.
Cowries (Cypraea annulus and Cypraea moneta)
are white or pale yellow shells the size of a hazel¬
nut, with a humped back and a ventral opening.
They are only found in warm seas, especially in
the South Pacific and the Indian Ocean. Most of
the cowries that circulated in Africa for over a
thousand years came from the Maldive and
Laccadive archipelagos, south-west of India, and
from the islands of Zanzibar and Pemba, off the
east coast of Africa.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Cowries were traded wherever they were
fished or collected, and were often carried as
ballast in Arab, Jewish or European ships sailing
for ports on the African mainland, where they
were sold again.
Marginellas (Marginella) are marine molluscs
whose shells, especially those from the west coast
of Africa, are small and colourful. They are also
found in American tropical waters, notably off
the coast of Brazil.
There are more than 300 species of olive
shells. More elongated than cowries, they have
an agate-like sheen. The species most commonly
used in sub-Saharan Africa was Olivancillaria
nana, found off the coast of Luanda which was
a monetary reserve used exclusively by the rulers
of the Kongo kingdom until the Portuguese
arrived in the late fifteenth century.
Markets for shell
currencies
Until the sixteenth century, the Nzimbu (the
Kikongo name for Olivancillaria nana) was used
as currency in the Kongo kingdom, marginella
shells were used only in the Niger bend, while
cowries were common throughout West Africa,
and, to a certain extent, in Central Africa. Before
the sixteenth century cowries were also used as
currency in Egypt.
From the sixteenth to the late nineteenth cen¬
tury the cowrie was more widely used than any
other form of shell moneyfrom Senegal to
Uganda, from the Sahel to the Slave Coast (Gulf
of Guinea). It was seldom used in the Sahara and
never gained ground either in northern or
southern Africa.
This was also the period when marginella
shells were most widely circulated in West
and Central Africa, where they were used as a
medium of exchange among the Olée, Ngilima,
Tsambitso, Obaa, Koyo, Eboyi and Akwa
peoples of the Congo basin.
Olive shells were always exclusive to the
Bantu, and do not seem to have circulated out¬
side the Congo. In order to ruin the rulers of the
Kongo kingdom, the Portuguese introduced '
other species of olives from the Brazilian coast
and cowries from the Indian Ocean. Inevitably,
Dorsal and ventral views of three varieties of cowrie.
Above left, the eyed cowrie (Cypraea argus); left, the
onyx cowrie (Cypraea onyx); right, the money cowrie
(Cypraea moneta), which has served as currency in
Africa and elsewhere.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
4^. _
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Above, a dancer at a Papua
New Guinea festival
brandishes a shield encrusted
with shell money, a
traditional form of wealth
which features on the
modern 5-kina note, right.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
the Nzimbu was gradually forced out of circula¬
tion. The Portuguese also exported olives from
Luanda and used them as a secondary form of cur¬
rency, along with cowries, in the black slave
traffic in colonial Brazil.
2,000 cowries for a gourd of salt
These shells were not simply used for barter.
They had all the characteristics of money in the
sense that they were measures of value and finan¬
cial reserves as well as mediums of exchange.
They symbolized wealth.
They could be used as cash to buy yams,
knives, cattle and slaves, or to pay for services
rendered. They also served as units of account for
fixing the price of certain commodities without
necessarily being used to pay for them. In the
nineteenth century, the French explorer Louis
Gustave Binger recorded the following negotia¬
tion between two merchants from northern
Ghana: "A gourd of salt is worth 2,000 cowries,
a hundred kola nuts are 1,000 cowries. So I'll give
you 200 kola nuts for a gourd of salt."
Shells thus encouraged trade and were excel¬
lent indicators of fluctuations in the price of
goods at different times and places. They were
assembled in multiples for ease of handling. One
or more holes were pierced in cowries and they
were strung in groups of 12, 20, 40 or 100 accord¬
ing to the number system used in the trading area
where they were in circulation.
Similarly, Musanga (small discs of snail-shell
used as currency in some African countries) were
strung through a central hole to make necklaces.
In the early twentieth century, ten of these neck¬
laces measured from the big toe to the heel were
worth a doti or 3.60 m of indigo-blue cloth, and
ten necklaces measured from the little toe to the
heel were worth a doti of any other cloth.
In some regions of sub-Saharan Africa the use
of shell currencies led to the development of
monetary policies. The authorities controlled the
import and circulation of the shells. Taking steps
to avoid an overabundance of shells, which would
have caused inflation, or scarcity, which would
have inhibited trade, gave them substantial power
over the economy. From Abomey to the Slave
Coast, as in the Congo, rigorous and highly effi¬
cient monetary policies were practised.
Shells began to be withdrawn from circula¬
tion at the beginning of the colonial period and
gradually lost their role as a medium of exchange.
Today only cowries still circulate, on a very small
scale, between the peoples of south-west Burkina
Faso and northern Ghana. This is the only region
in the world where their monetary value has been
preserved to some extent but for how much
longer?
Top, a huge symbolic cowrie
adorns the façade of the
Bank ofMali at Bamako.
Above, a copper ankle-
bracelet, once used as money
in the Congo.
A. FELIX IROKO,
of Benin, is head of studies
in the economic and social
history of Africa at the
National University of
Benin, Cotonou. The
author of over sixty articles
on economic history and
related subjects, he is
currently writing a book on
the use of the cowrie as
currency from 3000 BC to
the present day. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
V
nwff
w
Dinars
club
The first caliphs created an international
monetary system in the seventh century
using coinage that was surprisingly
modern in conception and design
BY GÉRARD KREBS
IN the time of Muhammad, in the early seventh
century, the Arabs did not use money. Perhaps
they had no need of it. Among the nomadic tribes
for which the camel was the main yardstick of
wealth, barter was the most widespread form of
exchange, while in centres of trade such as Mecca
and Medina foreign money such as Byzantine
gold or Persian silver coins had to be used for
large transactions.
Between 636 and 655 AD, the first Arab
invasions which wrenched Syria, Palestine and
Egypt from the Byzantine empire in the West,
and destroyed the Persian Sasanian empire in the
East, brought in vast quantities of precious
metals. The booty included gold and silver plate
as well as coins. But the creation of a new currency
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
(
M
v
i
>
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
was of no urgency to Islam in comparison with
its paramount goal of waging a holy war.
The new Muslim masters adapted themselves
very easily to the existing monetary systems in
the conquered regions, and took them over prac¬
tically unchanged. In the East silver drachms con¬
tinued to be minted bearing the effigy of the late
Sasanian king Khosrow II, although they now
carried the additional inscription "In the name
of Allah" in Arabic. On the Mediterranean sea¬
board the gold solidus and the bronze follis were
retained in their original forms, bearing the bust
or standing figure of the Byzantine emperor
Heraclius and his son, or of Constans II. Some¬
times an Arabic inscription was added and the
Christian symbol of the cross, widely found on
Byzantine coinage, was dropped.
The accession of the Umayyad dynasty in 661
AD marked the beginning of strong administra¬
tive control within the Islamic empire. In the field
of coinage the first steps were taken in Syria and
Palestine towards true Muslim themes, almost
exclusively on copper coins, on the instigation
of caliph 'Abd al-Malik (reigned 685-705). In
Damascus, Edessa and Jerusalem coins were
issued showing the standing figure of the caliph
with hands on a sheathed sword and encircled by
an Arabic legend.
Birth of the dinar
In 696 AD 'Abd al-Malik introduced a coherent
monetary system throughout the empire which
responded to both national and international eco¬
nomic requirements.
For major transactions and trade on a large
scale, the gold dinar of 4.3 grams began to be used.
For the payment of wages and taxes the silver
dirhem of 2.8 grams was introduced, and the
copper fais for everyday use. The relative value
of these coins was not fixed but changed accord¬
ing to the price of the three metals. At first the
dinar was worth 10 dirhems, but its value ap¬
preciated to 14 and even to 20 dirhems at different
periods. The dirhem itself fluctuated between 16
and 24 fais because its weight varied from region
to region.
Top left and right, silver
dirhem issued under the
caliph al-Muqtader (4th
century AH/10th century
AD). Above, silver drachm
of the Sasanian monarch
Bahram II (276-293 AD)
with busts of the king, his
queen and the crown prince.
OPPOSITE PAGE
Above, gold dinar (1st
century AH/7th century
AD). Below, clockwise from
top left: Arab Sasanian
drachm (c. 650 AD) bearing
the inscription "In the name
of Allah"; Arab Byzantine
follis (c. 650 AD); Umayyad
dirhem (122 AH/740 AD);
altun bearing the name of
the Ottoman sultan
Süleyman I the Magnificent
(926 AH/1520 AD);
'Abbasid dirhem (307
AH/919 AD); follis (c. 690
AD) showing the standing
figure of the caliph 'Abd
al-Malik.
PRECEDING PAGE
Camel market, Cairo.
A camel features on the coin,
left, issued during
the 'Abbasid dynasty
(3rd century AH/9th
century AD).
These new coins closely paralleled the foreign
coins which had previously been in circulation.
The dinar, heir (and competitor) of the Byzan¬
tine solidus, took its name from the Roman
denarius. The dirhem was similar in size and value
to the Persian drachm and the fais (plural fulous)
was a direct descendant of the Roman and Byzan¬
tine follis.
On the other hand, the design of the new
coinage was revolutionary. There were no more
allegories, no more titles reflecting the glory of
the ruler, no more portraits. These coins were
Islamic and therefore their exclusive role was to
praise God. Even the caliph's name did not
appear on them, and because the Prophet had
disapproved of the representation of human or
animal forms, the sole inscriptions were profes¬
sions of faith in elegant Kufic script.
This coinage represented a departure from the
Middle Eastern and North African tradition
which was both figurative and personalized, with
portraits of rulers or emblems of cities. Its lon¬
gevity was to be extraordinarythe last coins to
be struck in this tradition were issued in the
Yemen around 1960. The system was remarkably
modern in the sense that no sovereign state had
defined its currency so explicity before. The
Arabs were the first to mark coins with their
name, place of minting and year of issue, dated
from the Hegira in accordance with the Muslim
calendar. In the West, the practice of dating coins
only began to spread widely in the fifteenth
century.
While dinars were minted exclusively in the
Umayyad capital of Damascus, dirhems were
issued in many of the empire's leading cities. The
busiest mints were at Damascus and at Wasit, a
city founded in 703 in the Tigris valley (north¬
west of Basra, Iraq). The decentralization of the
mints, from Spain (Córdoba) to Tunisia, from
Azerbaijan to Afghanistan (Balkh) and Pakistan
(Sind region), gives an idea of the vast size of the
Islamic empire.
The 'Abbasid dynasty overthrew the Umay-
yads in 750 AD, and the development of com¬
merce in the eighth and ninth centuries carried
the use of coinage even further. Baghdad, the new
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Bargaining with buttons
During Bonaparte's Egyptian expedition of
1798 the polished buttons on the French
soldiers' uniforms are said to have been
highly prized in the souks of Alexandria. The
merchants, who were used to seeing nomads
carry their worldly wealth stitched onto their
garments so that they wouldn't lose it in the
desertthis is why so many North African
coins have a hole pierced in themwanted
to be paid with the beautiful shiny pieces of
metal which adorned the foreigners'
uniforms. Delighted at not having to dip into
their wages, the soldiers hacked off their
buttons to pay for their purchases.
Bonaparte's reaction on seeing his men return
from the souk in such a slovenly fashion can
easily be imagined.
Trade and religion
In the twelfth century the gold dinars of the
Fatimid caliphs of Egypt were so highly
valued throughout the Middle East,
especially by Syrian merchants, that the
Christian kingdoms founded in Palestine by
the Crusaders began to issue imitations of
them. These imitations, the so-called
"Saracenic besants", were clumsily produced
at first, but their design was gradually
improved until they were such faithful copies
of the dinar that the horrified papal legate
who accompanied King Louis IX of France
(Saint Louis) on the Crusades in 1250
threatened those responsible with
excommunication for daring to issue coins to
the glory of Allah for commercial profit. A
compromise was reached. The Saracenic
besant was replaced by another issue which
was almost identical to its predecessor but
bore a cross and Arabic inscriptions to the
glory of the Holy Trinity and the Lord
Jesus Christ.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
capital founded in 762, drained off much of the
empire's wealth and rapidly grew into a leading
economic centre with a large gold and silver mint.
Coins continued to be struck in the style of the
earlier dynasties but now they began to carry the
name of the caliph, and later the names of provin¬
cial governors were added. The calligraphy and
design of the coins varied according to the region
of issue, however, as local dynasties in the Span¬
ish, North African and eastern Iranian provinces
asserted their independence.
The splintering
of the empire
In 945, the rebellion of Iranian Buyids marked
the end of 'Abbasid central power. From then
on the Muslim world had no common
currency, and although the terms dinar and
dirhem still referred to gold and silver coins, the
wide range in their weight and purity and the
arrangement of their inscriptions reflected the
ambitions and financial situation of each dynasty.
The sole exception in these politically and eco¬
nomically troubled times was Egypt under the
Fatimids (969-1171). A prosperous country which
controlled the outflow of Sudanese gold and
occupied a strategic position on the main sea
trading routes, it long continued to mint "good"
dinars.
In the thirteenth century, the Mongol inva-
Above, coins worn as
ornaments at the festival of
Marrakesh (Morocco).
Opposite page, The
Moneychanger by the
Austrian artist Rudolf Ernst
(1854-1920).
GÉRARD KREBS,
a French numismatist who
specializes in Oriental
coinage, contributed the ''
historical and numismatic
commentaries to Les
monnaies de l'Islam et du
Proche-Orient (1988), the
catalogue of the Paris
Mint's holdings of Islamic
and Near Eastern
currencies.
sions which ravaged the entire Muslim East-
Baghdad was sacked in 1258 and the 'Abbasid
caliph executedswept away the last vestiges of
the currency system conceived by 'Abd al-Malik.
Soon each country had its own monetary policy
and would issue its own coinage. Not until the
establishment of the Ottoman empire was a com¬
mon currency again in wide circulation. Initially
the Turkish coinage consisted of a silver akce (of
1.2 grams then of 0.8 grams), complemented in
1478 by a gold altun. These coins were in circu¬
lation from Algeria to Turkey and as far as the
Balkans.
Yet this system was not as stable as the earlier
one. Adversely affected from the late sixteenth
century by the massive influx of silver from
Spanish mines in South America, it was modi¬
fied several times and reformed in 1688, but was
never really able to hold its own against Western
currencies. The design of the coins recalled
the ancient tradition of personalized money, '
as although they were non-figurative they
were all dedicated to the glory of the sultan
and often depicted his seal (tughra), his names
and his titles.
Today the countries of the Islamic world
have their own strictly national currencies. The
time when money existed solely for the glorifi¬
cation of God, performing a role which tran¬
scended its economic function and crossed
political boundaries, is over.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Wheelers and dealers of
Renaissance Europe
An influx ofprecious metals from the New
World stimulated the money economy but
also unleashed turbulent forces
BY LUCIEN GILLARD
McLoNEY is generally thought of as a medium
in which prices and values are expressed, a means
of payment and a store of purchasing power. As
the standard by which the value of traded com¬
modities is measured, it creates a coherent area
within which people have a common yardstick
with which to assess their credits and debts.
In sixteenth-century Europe, these areas coin¬
cided with national frontiers, beyond which
money was a kind of standard-bearer for each
nation. A convenient means of payment, money
also promoted the circulation of goods. The spec¬
tacular development of production and trade
in sixteenth-century Europe is thus generally
associated with the growth of the money supply
in the form both of commercial bills and of coins
minted with metal from the Americas.
Finally, as a store of purchasing power,
money introduced a new conception of temporal¬
ity, which made it possible to circumvent much
of the anguish of daily life. Time no longer
belonged entirely to God, but became instead the
32
a . .- '
^
'fSM
y
Left, the fabulous silver mines
of Potosí in Upper Peru
(modern Bolivia) which were
intensively exploited by the
Spaniards during the colonial
period. Engraving by Théodore
de Bry (16th century).
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Weigher of Gold
by the Dutch painter
Gerard Dou (1613-1675).
foundation on which people could base their
plans. The notion of money as capital was recog¬
nized, as is shown by the debates on interest on
loans, on the indexation of debts, on the causes
of price rises and even on the sale of indulgences.
Money, therefore, seems to have fulfilled its
functions satisfactorily and to have contributed
to the strengthening of social ties in Renaissance
Europe. There are, however, two sides to every
coin; money also lay behind such disruptive
forces as monopoly acquisition and exclusion.
And the doubling of the population in Europe
during the Renaissance period only served to
accentuate the turmoil these forces induced.
Debasement of the coinage
The first problems occasioned by money during
this period were related to its issue. Within a
given national territory, the minting and legal
valuation of money was the responsibility of the
political authorities, a principle adopted, after
much vacillation, from Roman law. Despite the
severity of the measures taken against those who
contravened this principle (such as being boiled
alive), the official monopoly to mint coins was
very often contested.
The first frauds were the work of traffickers
in debased coinage which contained less than the
official quantity of precious metal, but was
accepted at the same face value. Debased coins
were to be found everywhere, because minting
techniques were then too rudimentary to ensure
that every coin was exactly the same. Any smart
merchant, money changer, or even tax collector
would carefully sort through the coins that came
into his possession and withdraw the heavier
coins from circulation. All he had to do then to
get more for them than their face value was to
sell them by weight, at a good price, to the gold¬
smiths or silversmiths. Another method was to
shave off minute slivers of the metal before
putting the coins back in circulation, banking on
the reluctance of those receiving them to have
them checked against the official standard (they
ran the risk of having to bear the expense of the
assay if the coin was found to conform to the
standard).
Attempts to put a stop to this practice by
milling the edge of the coins and stamping a circle
around the effigy-head met with little success. No
country succeeded in introducing the new milling
techniques, which could have eliminated these
problems altogether, during the sixteenth
century. Machine methods for producing coins
were both too expensive and strongly opposed
by the workmen who hammer-struck the coins
by hand in the traditional way. Finding that
simply having their likenesses engraved on the
coins was not enough to guarantee their authen¬
ticity, rulers were gradually obliged to require
that coins be weighed at each transaction. Their
attempts, by a plethora of prohibitive edicts, to
prevent the uncontrolled price-fixing of precious 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
metals by goldsmiths and silversmiths proved
equally ineffective.
More radical contradictions became apparent
between counterfeiters and what might be termed
the "anti-coin" diehards. Sixteenth-century coun¬
terfeiters, that is to say minters of fake coins,
tended to specialize in Spanish coins, especially
the smaller ones which were cheaper to make and
more difficult to check. Meanwhile, many rulers
themselves minted imitations of the coinage of
other countries, so as to keep for themselves
the minting tax (in the case of small states that
did not have their own coinage) or to retain
some of the precious metal by minting debased
imitations.
There were some famous examples of coun¬
terfeiting. In France, over a ten-year period, sup¬
porters of the Pope organized the parallel minting
of coins to undermine the official coinage of the
Protestant king. Another such case was that of
the fake Spanish coins struck from cargoes of pre¬
cious metals pirated on their way to Europe from
the Americas.
Following the discovery of the Antilles and
the Americas, Spain embarked on the systematic
exploitation of the precious metals found there.
Twice a year, these metals were brought under
military escort to Seville, where the Spanish
coinage was minted. Imports of metal recorded
during the sixteenth century were impressive:
around 250 tons of gold and 200,000 tons of
Spanish silver 8-real coin
minted in 1597 during the
reign of Philip II.
Below, hammer-striking coins
in France at the time of
Louis XII (1462-1515).
silver, amounts equal to a third of total previous
stocks. Some historians, however, estimate that
clandestine imports not recorded by the Spanish
authorities and destined for rival mints may well
have amounted to as much again.
There have also been less complicated forms
of coinage abuse. One of these consisted of
individuals agreeing amongst themselves to use
coins prohibited by royal decree. Periodically,
monarchs would decree that a specific coin was
no longer legal tender for trading purposes
because it was of unacceptable quality. Such coins
had to be taken to treasury offices to be clipped
and bought back at their value by weight. These
decrees were often ignored by private individuals,
who would fix an agreed value for the coins in
question, particularly when coinage was in short
supply. This is what happened to small Spanish
coins in France during the second half of the six¬
teenth century.
An even more common practice was that of
using authorized coins in trading but at a so-called
"voluntary" value, ignoring the value officially
fixed by the ruler. In those days, and for 200 years
afterwards, the value of coins was taken from
public announcements and not from inscriptions
on the coin itself. Distrust of the official coinage
was thus increasing and in some regions at cer¬
tain times the private value quoted for a coin
could be as much as double that of the official
rate. In these circumstances, the function of
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
money as a generator of homogenous societies
was seriously compromised.
Among the anti-coin lobby there were two
distinct groups. First there were those who re¬
fused to give up barter. Despite the expansion of
trade in goods throughout Europe, barter was still
favoured by countless rural communities. Also
anti-coin, in a sense, were those who clung to the
principle of the weight of precious metals (or even
of salt) as a measure of value, thus excluding from
their transactions the intrusion of any money-
minting public authority.
This principle could be applied in a number
of ways. A so-called "gold clause" could be in¬
cluded in a fixed-term contract stipulating that
payment would be made in a certain weight of
metal or in a certain number of named coins,
whatever their official value at the time as a unit
of account. This clause, a relic from Roman law,
did not disappear for a very long time. In on-the-
spot transactions, distrust of the coinage meant
that payment had to be made in raw metal on
the basis of an agreed tariff. In sixteenth-century
France, between a quarter and a third of all trans¬
actions were concluded in exchange for gold
objects such as rings or goblets or for gold dust
found in rivers (panning for gold was still prac¬
tised) or even filed from coins.
Venture trading
In venture trading between Europe and the rest
of the world, payment in metal was the only
procedure employed. It is true that minted coins
were used for the purchase of silk and spices from
Above, The Usurers by
Marinus van Reymerswael
(Dutch school, 16th century).
Left, early 16th-century
German miniature shows
the banker Jakob II Fugger
the Rich (right) checking the
books with his chief
accountant. Fugger's business
interests stretched across
central and western Europe.
LUCIEN GILLARD,
of France, is a researcher
with the National Centre
for Scientific Research
(CNRS) with a special
interest in the history of
monetary policy and
practice. He is co-author
(with Marie-Thérèse Boyer-
Xambeu and Ghislain
Deleplace) of Monnaie
privée et pouvoir des
princes: L'économie des
relations monétaires à la
Renaissance (1986).
the Orientchiefly the Spanish excellente and the
Venetian sequin up to the mid-sixteenth century,
and after that the Spanish silver real.
These rather rare coins had certain specific
characteristics which'made it impossible to sub¬
stitute others for them. Made of pure metal at
a virtually constant weight of between 3 and 4
grams, they were difficult to imitate and the heads
with which they were stamped guaranteed only
their conformity to this standard. They bore no
unitary value whatever outside the realm which
struck them. In trading between European
countries these coins were exchanged by number
or by weight in pure metal and they had no
monetary status. In this respect, quite apart from
the war, piracy and slave trading that accompa¬
nied it, the venture trading developed by the Eu¬
ropeans did not act as the cement of a world
society.
The same was true of the deposit certificates
that circulated within the various European coun¬
tries. These certificates, which were not replaced
by bank notes until a century or two later, had
been issued from the fourteenth century by
certain bankers against monies deposited in their
coffers. They were the equivalent of a promise
on the part of the banker of immediate payment
on presentation and circulated like cash. 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
The sluggish development of industry and the
crafts was in part the cause and in part the con¬
sequence of the monetary practices of the time.
Not enough wealth was being produced for there
to be a consensus in society about its distribution,
and priority expenditure on wars, land, services
and imported luxury goods benefited primarily
the non-productive social categories. Production
thus remained basically agricultural. Surpluses
were sold locally or at regional fairs, only at cer¬
tain times of the year. Entrepreneurs had not yet
arrived on the scene and the money dealers sym¬
bolized economic activity.
Merchant bankers
Among them were the merchant bankers, who
reached their apogee during the sixteenth centu¬
ry and provide a perfect illustration of the nature
of monetary operations at that time. Since the
Middle Ages, there had been a redistribution of
goods and raw materials between the various
countries of Europe, and luxury goods from the
Orient, and this gave rise to an intensive im¬
port/export trade concentrated on half a dozen
large towns at which fairs were held periodically.
The need to pay for goods purchased at these fairs
gave rise to a specific activitythe conversion,
at a price, of the various national units of account,
that is, money-changing.
Carrying on a tradition dating back to the
Champagne Fairs of the thirteenth century, the
merchant bankers had the monopoly of the pur¬
chase and resale of the ordinary merchants' in¬
ternational debts (bills of exchange). They
acquired their monopoly by their presence at all
the European fairs, forming a network of agents
through which other merchants were obliged to
deal. This monopoly led to an agreed evaluation
of each international debt expressed originally in
the currency of a single country. In this way,
during the sixteenth century, the merchant
bankers, from their headquarters in Lyon, created
what was in effect a Europe-wide monetary
system.
In determining the international value of the
various currencies, the merchant bankers inevita¬
bly came into conflict with their merchant
clients, from whom they extracted a margin of
profit. They also found themselves in conflict
with rulers, who established official rates of
exchange for foreign coinage that was allowed to
circulate in their respective countries. Many var¬
iations and rises in price resulted from these con¬
flicts of interest and these were aggravated by
financial and banking rivalries within the circle
of merchant bankers itself.
Thus, although through its function as a com¬
mon yardstick of value money created social
bonds, it was also, in practice, a cause of dissen¬
sion. And though, in sixteenth-century Europe,
it had become the new divinity, money, like man
in whose image it was created, was still seeking
the limits of its power.
jfHE'UNITED STatVnsS
v y ;/_ Li ií-uj.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
*N ; «.,-.
... BES
11 I'K Ul< \S1
>?
V Y
r
The rise of
the greenback
BY JAN KREGEL
The US dollar brought order to domestic
monetary chaos and went on to become
the leading international currency
Left, "The United States
evoked through the
symbolism of their currency"
(1988-1989), three of a series
of acrylic canvases by Isia
Leviant (born Byelorussia,
1914). Each painting
measures 90 x 210 cm.
Above, silver coin
issued in the state of
Massachusetts in 1787.
I
LafJ .YMERIC,
*^m
N the last half of the nineteenth century, the
British pound sterling ruled supreme as an inter¬
national currency. Of all its possible rivals, the
United States dollar1 seemed the least likely
to take its place. The United States was an inter¬
national debtor of an uncertain quality without
a central bank and without a single unified cur¬
rency system. The dollar only rose to dominance
in the twentieth century as a result of a tortuous
sequence of events which led to the creation of
a central banking authority, the Federal Reserve
System, and to the adoption of the dollar as a lia¬
bility of the federal government.
The United States Constitution adopted in
1789 did not grant the federal government the
exclusive prerogative to issue coins and currency
which was enjoyed by the Crown in European
monetary systems. The absence of clear legisla¬
tion on currency matters created a myriad of
diverse means of payment virtually without any
central control or support. In these chaotic con¬
ditions, foreign coins circulated as legal tender
until 1857, and as late as 1901 an Oregon silver
mine was still issuing its own silver coins for
"commercial use".
In the aftermath of widespread default of cur¬
rencies issued by individual states of the Union,
they were prohibited from issuing paper money.
But nothing prevented them from creating banks, 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38
which were free to issue bank notes. The state
of Kentucky, for example, created a private bank
of which it was sole owner and proceeded to
make payments with its notes. This individualist
tradition in money matters found expression
in "wildcat" banking and the prevalence in
this period of state "free banking" laws which
allowed any individual or association of individu¬
als to open a bank and issue bank notes without
licence or control.
The absence of a national bank meant that
even the federal government had to undertake its
financial transactions either through private
banks or in specie (coin or bullion). In 1840,
President Martin Van Buren instituted the
"Independent Treasury System" which handled
government transactions through nationwide sub-
offices. Since the Treasury was not a bank, and
could not issue notes, all government receipts and
expenditures had to be made in gold or silver.
Expenditures in excess of taxation could not be
financed except by issue of government debt sub¬
scribed in gold.
The Civil War
and the first greenbacks
Many currency arrangements of the late
nineteenth century can be traced back to the need
to finance the Civil War of 1861 to 1865. The
Treasury first issued "demand notes" which were
not legal tender, but were convertible into gold.
But the weak gold reserves of the Treasury soon
led to the suspension of convertibility of these
notes. Thereafter the war effort was financed by
an issue of "United States Notes", based on
nothing more substantial than the faith and credit
of the government. They were popularly called
"greenbacks", the name by which the United
States dollar is still known throughout the world.
The issue of greenbacks had been limited to
$433 million, so in the face of increasing difficulty
in borrowing and of rising expenditures Treasury
secretary Salmon P. Chase decided to apply "free
banking" on a national scale. The National Bank
Act of 1863 allowed any group of five persons
to form a "National Banking Association"
and issue "National Bank Notes" in an amount
equal to their holdings of federal government
bonds deposited with the Comptroller of the
Currency.2
To prevent competition from state bank
notes, a 10 per cent tax was placed on the latter
which soon drove them out of circulation. The
state banks countered by offering payment ser¬
vices by cheque against deposit accounts, which
proved to be an attractive substitute for National
Bank Notes.
By the end of the Civil War, the multiplicity
of means of payment representing the liabilities
of thousands of state banks had been largely
reduced to greenbacks and National Bank Notes,
neither of which were convertible into specie, but
the issue of which was strictly limited. The
money supply of the United States was thus
rigidly fixed, unable to respond to either fluctu¬
ations in trade, nor the frequent panics that
resulted from the failures of the unregulated state
banks (two years after the introduction of free
banking in Michigan, for example, all of its forty
banks had failed).
The dollar set firmly
on the gold standard
As the United States was basically an agricultural
country, the demands on currency were linked
to the harvest. As crops were sold, farmers' bank
deposits built up in the agricultural regions,
leading to a shortage of funds in the urban banks
of the east. The National Bank system of small
individual units had no mechanism to recycle
excess funds, such as was possible in a multi-
branch bank. Furthermore, without a central
bank to lend reserves, there was no way of
meeting these fluctuations apart from sharp
changes in interest rates, or declaring bank failure.
Together with the net drain of specie to the
Independent Treasury and the absence of strict
banking regulations, this led to extreme instabil¬
ity and frequent crises.
This instability was attributed by some to a
lack of specie, an argument exploited by those
interested in making silver the basis of the United
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Clockwise from top left:
machine for printing
banknotes, USA, 1920;
unemployed Americans gather
to barter during the
depression, 1929; $100 note
issued by the Confederate
States of America in 1864,
during the Civil War, which
promises to pay the bearer
"two years after the
ratification of a treaty of
peace"; obverse and
reverse of a $20 gold coin
issued in 1899.
States monetary system. A "Free Silver Move¬
ment" launched by William Jennings Bryan
demanded the free coinage of silver as legal
tender. The 1878 Bland-Allison Act provided for
Treasury silver certificates which became legal
tender in 1886 and the Sherman Silver Act of
1890 made the Treasury virtually liable to
purchase the entire output of United States silver
mines. In 1882 a similar provision was made for
gold certificates, but neither measure gave the
hoped-for elasticity to the currency.
The system created serious international as
well as domestic problems, for fluctuations in the
internal demands for liquidity could only be met
by international gold movements, which in turn
created instability in the international monetary
system. This was particularly striking in 1893,
when the fear that the United States would not
honour its government debt in gold and would
instead pay in silver, whose price was collapsing
on world markets, led to a massive outflow of
gold and widespread bank failures.
Creation of
the Federal Reserve system
The outflow was reversed by the Gold Standard
Act of 1900, which set the dollar firmly on the
gold standard3 and required National Banks to
back their note issues with gold. Between 1899
and 1910 the gold holdings of the public trebled,
as did those of the Treasury. The proportion of
the world's monetary gold stock held in the
United States rose from around 15 to 30 per cent,
at a time when many other countries (Austro-
Hungary, Russia, Japan) were also adopting the
gold standard. As the expansion of gold supplies
was slowing, the accumulation of gold in the
United States caused more difficulties than had
the previous outflow, largely because once the
gold entered the Treasury it could not be drawn
out except to finance a balance of payments
deficit (the country was then in surplus). Given
the Independent Treasury System, gold could not
be used as the basis to create money or to serve
as lending of last resort.
Another banking- crisis in 1907 forcefully
reminded legislators of the need for a national
institution which could respond to fluctuations
in the demand for liquidity in some other way
than by attracting gold from abroad. Such an
institution was finally set up by the Federal
Reserve Act of 1913.
The Act divided the country into twelve dis¬
tricts, each with its own Federal Reserve Bank,
which began operations on 2 November 1914. The
existing National Banks were obliged to join the 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
system by purchasing stock in the Federal Reserve
Banks. The latter were authorized to issue a new
type of currency, the Federal Reserve Note, legal
tender for all debts and the liability of both the
banks and the United States government.
The new note was to replace National Bank
Notes. The issue was backed by gold to a mini¬
mum of 40 per cent, the remaining notes being
issued against commercial paper and other eligible
assets acquired by discount from the member
banks. This arrangement satisfied the need for an
elastic means of payment which could expand and
contract with fluctuations in trade and the situa¬
tion of the banking system. A member bank that
was short of liquidity could acquire it by dis¬
counting its assets in exchange for Federal Reserve
Notes at its District Reserve Bank.
The Federal Reserve Board of governors,
appointed by the President and based in
Washington, D.C., sat rather uneasily over the
Federal Reserve Banks which were owned and
run by private bankers. It was by no means clear
who was responsible for currency policy, but the
bankers clearly had the upper hand.
However, the two prerequisites for the sub¬
sequent international dominance of the dollar had
now been acquired: the massive accumulation of
world gold stock in the United States, which
obliged the international monetary system to
move onto a gold-exchange standard, and the
creation of a unified national currency issued
by a single authority with lender of last resort
capability.
Gold ingots at the Federal
Reserve Bank, New York.
JAN A. KREGEL,
of the United States, is
professor of economics at
the Bologna Center, Italy,
of Johns Hopkins
University, Baltimore, USA.
His published works include
The Reconstruction of
Political Economy (1983),
Inflation and Income Crisis
(1989), both published by
Macmillan, and a number
of articles in the American
Economic Review and The
Journal of Post-Keynesian
Economics.
The position of the United Kingdom was
weakened by the 1914-1918 war, and the dollar
entered the inter-war return to gold on a stronger
basis than sterling. Moreover the United States
economy, after a short recession, was to prosper
in the "roaring 20s" of radio and automobiles.
The massive movement of investment funds
to the United States, first caused by rapid growth
and the stock market boom, then by high interest
rates used to try to break the speculative rise on
Wall Street, severely disrupted international
finance and broke the stability of exchange rates.
The stock market crash of 1929 brought about
massive bank failures, which were far beyond the
ability of the Federal Reserve to offset, and the
consequent collapse of investment values was
responsible for a worldwide depression.
The evidence of widespread bank fraud
which emerged after the Wall Street crash
suggested deficiencies in the supervisory function
of the Federal Reserve Board and in its ability to
regulate monetary policy to prevent even well-
run banks from failing. A series of measures,
including the nationalization of gold, the devalu¬
ation of the dollar to $35 per ounce of gold, and
the 1935 Banking Act which gave the Federal
Reserve Board control over monetary policy,
finally created a system equivalent in its powers
and duties to a European central bank.
Thus the inter-war period strengthened both
the reserve position of the United States and the
domestic financial system. The country was ready
to take over London's role as banker to the world
when the outbreak of the Second World War
made the City unsafe and transformed the United
Kingdom from an international creditor to an
international debtor. The United States became
the world's major creditor. Any country which
wanted to buy goods for post-war reconstruction
had to acquire dollars, and the dollar thus became
the pre-eminent international currency.
1. The Spanish peso, or piece of eight, which circulated in
the Spanish and English colonies of America, was known as
a dollar by the English-speaking peoples. Familiarity with this
coin resulted in the designation of the United States mone¬
tary unit as the dollar in 1792. The word itself is a modified
form of the Germanic word thaler.
2. A Treasury official responsible for the design and issue of
National Bank Notes.
3. On thefull gold standard, gold coins are in circulation and
on demand bank notes can be exchanged for gold. This means
that a country on the gold standard must keep an adequate
reserve of gold to meet demand. On the gold-exchange standard
a country keeps its reserves in another currency that is itself
based on the gold standard. Editor.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
The complex role of the monetary system
in modern societies
BY GHISLAIN DELEPLACE
-«Ät
^í. Í ^ * ».
V .<-
. .»V
J_J
"V
ECONOMISTS often seem to have a very curious
view of money. In the eighteenth century, when
banks were beginning to issue notes, which made
it possible to create money without being depen¬
dent upon the production of precious metals,
economists spread the idea that money was a
secondary phenomenon which could be ignored
in the study of fundamental economic laws. Yet
this viewpoint, which has been dominant ever
since, does not prevent economists from ful¬
minating regularly against the evils of monetary
disorder, which they hold responsible for eco¬
nomic instability, whilst according money only
a secondary role in the functioning of economies.
This doubly paradoxical attitude at least has the
merit of focusing attention on the complexity of
the role money plays in modern societies.
Nevertheless, it was the problem of the
monetary analysis of society that gave impetus
to the development of economic thought in
Renaissance Europe. Money was seen as both the
symbol of merchants' wealth and an attribute of
royal power. At the time, the relationship be¬
tween princes and merchants was the central
theme of monetary analysis and the basis of an
economic theory of society.
This approach was to change radically in the
eighteenth century, as witness these words of the
British philosopher David Hume (1711-1776):
"Money is not, properly speaking, one of the sub¬
jects of commerce; but only the instrument
which men have agreed upon to facilitate the
exchange of one commodity for another. It is
none of the wheels of trade: it is the oil which
renders the motion of the wheels more smooth
and easy."
Making copper coins at the Royal Canadian Mint 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
This purely instrumental view of money was
part of a vision of society in which the market
was the sole regulating mechanism. Its effect was
to leave the monarch, or the state, on the side¬
lines with no co-ordinating role to play between
private agents, since these were all merchants
naturally interlinked within a "commercial
society". It also reduced money to little more
than a veil that cloaked the exchange of goods
and that had to be pulled aside if the realities of
economic phenomena were to be analysed. Any
attempt by the state to take an active hand in the
management of money was therefore seen as a
threat to social harmony, which the laws of com¬
petition were assumed to engender automatically.
Thus the progressive "dematerialization" of
money is seen as a means of simplifying the proce¬
dures of trade. Some object in common currency
within a community is used as money. We have
seen this role fulfilled successively by some form
of metal, gold or silver bullion, coins, gold
certificates, bank notes, cheques and credit
cardsand electronic money is on its way. As a
result of this "dematerialization" process, money
has become nothing more than a transfer mechan¬
ism with no link to any material object as a
guarantee of its value.
A form of wealth
or a transfer mechanism?
However well it matches up to a view of society
that favours the regulating influence of the
market, this liberal, instrumental conception of
money is not without its own paradoxes. Chief
of these is that, leaving aside any question of
intervention by the state, the very nature of
monetary exchanges makes the existence of
"good" money, that is to say an instrument that
properly fulfils its function as a medium of
exchange, difficult, if not impossible.
Unlike barter, in which the buyer of item X
is at the same time the seller of item Y, exchanges
involving money comprise two distinct transac¬
tions which do not take place simultaneously.
The vendor first sells Y for money (i.e. he buys
nothing), and then uses this money to buy X (i.e.
he sells nothing). If money is merely an instru¬
ment of exchange, the person involved in the
transaction will not go ahead with it unless it is
to his advantage. According to the textbooks, one
advantage is that it is easier to find a buyer of Y
and a seller of X than to uncover the double
coincidence of a single person wanting to buy Y
and sell X.
The problem remains, however, of ensuring
that this advantage is not reduced to nothing by
some impediment that will prevent the individual
from using the money obtained from selling Y
to buy X, or that he may not obtain as much of
X with money as he would have done by barter.
For the private individual to choose the mone¬
tary exchange methodand it is essential to the
This Austrian silver thaler
struck in 1780 bears the head
of the archduchess Maria
Theresa. Such coins
circulated from the Red Sea
to the Atlantic.
-
liberal, instrumental approach argument that he
should do soit is necessary that the money he
has obtained as a seller remains a store ofpurchas¬
ing power throughout the period of time that
elapses between the two transactions.
Herein lies the paradox. If the instrument
chosen as money fails properly to fulfil its func¬
tion as a store of purchasing power (in the sense
that there is nothing to guarantee that this pur¬
chasing power will remain constant), those who
hold it will be induced to get rid of it as soon
as they have received it, or even simply to go back
to barter. This is often seen to occur in situations
of hyperinflation.
On the other hand, if the instrument chosen
as money fulfils this function well, the private
Checking banknotes
in the Bank of England,
London (1871).
Opposite page: Top, the
French numismatist Joseph
Pellerin (1684-1782), who
had a collection of 32,500
rare coins. The impact of
inflation in Germany in
1923 is illustrated by the
50,000 million mark note
(centre) and the children
paying for their schooling
with food (below).
* Fiat money is money declared
by a government to be legal tender
though it is not convertible into
specie. Editor
individual will tend to hold it as a form of wealth,
taking it out of circulation and preventing it from
fulfilling its other function as a medium of
exchange.
This phenomenon, which has become
known as "Gresham's Law" (after the sixteenth-
century English financier Sir Thomas Gresham
who observed that "Bad money drives out
good"), was recognized very early on with regard
to metal-based coins. However, it is equally
applicable to fiat money"" since it is based on the
trust placed in it by business as a store of pur¬
chasing power. In the 1930s, the British
economist John Maynard Keynes maintained that
"liquidity preference" was the main reason why a
monetary economy was unable to achieve a stable
level of full employment. At the international
level "Triffin's dilemma" (so named for the
American economist Professor Robert Triffin)
highlighted the fact that, in the 1950s, the United
States was no longer in a position both to ensure
world liquidity and maintain confidence in the
dollar as a reserve currency.
It is thus illusory to consider money as
merely a medium of exchange engendered by
market forces; and if it is taken as a principle that
business people "choose" to hold money simply
on the basis of an economic calculation, this will
increase the risk of monetary disorder.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
In opposition to the liberal, instrumental the¬
ory of money there is the institutional, interven¬
tionist approach, which introduces a number of
interesting concepts. Money is not an appendage
but the sine qua non of the existence of the
market, and its appropriate management
produces less disorder and makes it possible to
act favourably on the economy as a whole.
This concept, however, became associated
with the notion that money is basically created
by the state and that the state's monetary power
is reflected in the institution of legal tender for
fiat money. This was notably the case after the
First World War. This reduction of money to the
status of an attribute of state power itself led to
some paradoxical situations, the main one being
that the history of money is the history of the
struggle of private individuals against this aspect
of state power.
Constraints on the monetary
power of the state
This situation had arisen before with metal-based
money. In the sixteenth century, this money did
not circulate as stamped gold or silver
ingots but as coins, the minting of which was the
monopoly of the monarch and to which he
attributed a legal value in units of account. Gold
and silver were not commodity money; they
became metal coinage by royal decree. Private
business was unceasingly hostile to this legally
fixed circulating value and instead adopted
"voluntary values" which were usually higher.
The depreciation of the currency that resulted
because in practice the unit of account represent¬
ed less gold or silver than officially maintained
was effectively a form of inflation, which went
to show that the monarch could not simply regu¬
late money as he thought fit.
The monetary power of the state was thus
subject to two important constraints. Firstly, the
decisions taken by private business had their
effect on the creation of money, both on the
supply side (the impossibility of ensuring rigorous
control of the minting of metal coinage; the rela¬
tive autonomy enjoyed by the banks in the field
of fiat money), and on the demand side (the
volume of money created being ultimately depen¬
dent on the decisions of individuals as to whether
to bring their gold to the mint or to borrow from
the banks). Secondly, the attitude of private
individuals with regard to the circulation of cur¬
rency could express their resistance to public con¬
trol of the currency and lead to its internal
depreciation (inflation) or external depreciation
(a fall in the exchange rate).
If these two conflicting views of money are
considered together, it can be seen that money
is neither a form of merchandise (with its own
intrinsic value) nor an attribute of state power.
Rather, it is a prerequisite for the existence of
markets and the expression of a certain social
cohesion that enables the state to fulfil its 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44
functions. A monetary regime is a set of rules of
conduct specific to a given society.
What then is the difference between the
money of the past and that of today? It is often
stated that modern money is fiat money, whereas
the money of the past was commodity money;
that the metal-based money of the past had its
own intrinsic value regulated by the mechanisms
of the metal market while the "dematerialized"
money of today is based solely on the confidence
inspired by the state, which imposes its legal
tender. Such an assessment is inadequate. No
of a lender of last resort. This "banks' bank", or
central bank, plays a dual role. On the one hand
it acts as a clearing house for payments between
banks and to this effect sets the bank money rate
in terms of the national monetary unit. Contrary
to what is generally thought, a franc, a dollar or
a pound issued by one commercial bank is not
the same as that issued by another. The accep¬
tance of cheques drawn on this or that bank
and thus the use of bank deposits as money-
implies a system of compensatory payments
organized by a central body.
monetary economy can exist without some form
of abstract unit of account, and this can perfectly
well coexist with a metal-based coinage.
Money today
Modern money can, however, be defined in terms
of two characteristics of a bank-based monetary
regime. Firstly, the banks' issuing function
enables a certain category of people, the entre¬
preneurs, to obtain money on the basis of a
promise offuture activity. Even though bank credit
is today made available to people of all economic
categories, there is a .fundamental difference
between thosein particular wage earnerswho
can borrow on the strength of income received
in the past (or the probability that they will con¬
tinue to receive such income in the future), and
thosethe entrepreneursto whom credit is
advanced on the basis of a planned trading project
the success of which (on which repayment of the
loan depends) is uncertain. This credit issuing
function of the banks thus introduces an element
of social discrimination. It is, however, a factor
that promotes economic dynamism, since, as
Keynes observed, "it allows entrepreneurs to go
ahead with assurance".
Secondly, the banking system is hierarchical
in organization, with the activity of the second
rank of banks being dependent on the existence
Looking into the strongroom
at a major French bank.
GHISLAIN DELEPLACE,
of France, is professor of
economics at the University
of Orleans. He is the
author of Théories du
Capitalisme (Maspéro
publishers, Paris, 1979) and
co-author (with Marie-
Thérèse Boyer-Xambeu and
Lucien Gillard) of Monnaie
privée et pouvoir des
princes: L'économie des
relations monétaires à la
Renaissance (1986), an
English version of which is
currently being prepared for
publication.
On the other hand, the central bank guaran¬
tees the other banks against defaults on loans,
which are a risk inherent in the loan mechanisms
described above, by allowing these banks to
refinance such loans in central bank money. This
method of insurance, while certainly not auto¬
matic, tends through its effects on inflation and
the exchange rate to spread over society as a
whole the burden of the consequences of the
failure of some entrepreneurs to meet their obli¬
gation to repay loans. Nevertheless, as we see
today, it provides the system with a degree of
elasticity which tends to prevent the multiplica¬
tion of bankruptcies.
These characteristics demonstrate that the
origins of the modern monetary system predate
the time when it supplanted metal-based coinage.
To find them we have to go back to the sixteenth
century and the relationship between metal
coinage minted by monarchscentral money
and the bills of exchange that the Italian merchant
bankers circulated throughout Europebank
money.
The yardstick of social intercourse, money
is the embodiment of the rules that make possible
the complex interplay of economies. Paradoxical
in nature since it appears to be the consequence
of the economic activity of which it is a pre¬
requisite, it is hardly surprising that money is
both a matter of practical concern and a source
of theoretical debate.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF » IN BRIEF IN BRIEF
BARCELONA'S GREAT
ARCHITECT ON FILM
The first prize in the 2nd
Lausanne International Festival of
Architecture and Town Planning
Films was awarded to Gaudi by
Manuel Huerga (Spain 1988,
35 mm black and white,
57 minutes). The film covers the
major events in the life and
times of the great Barcelona
architect Antonio Gaudi
(1852-1926).
MUMMIFIED ENZYME
Scientists at the University of
Tubingen, Fed. Rep. of
Germany, have shown an
enzyme extracted from the
cerebral tissue of a 3,100-year-
old mummy to be in perfect
"working order". A control
experiment proved that the
activity of the enzyme was not
due to bacterial contamination.
EUROPEAN LITERACY PRIZE
CREATED
Over a hundred European
artists and intellectuals recently
attended a meeting held at Blois
(France) on the invitation of
France's minister of culture and
communication, Mr. Jack Lang
They decided to convene an
official meeting in Paris later this
year to discuss the "freedom of
movement of cultural property"
and to create an annual
European literary prize which
will be awarded for the first
time in Glasgow (UK) in 1990.
ADVICE TO AN AUTHOR
The noted Algerian writer Kateb
Yacine, whose novel Nedjma
(1956) had a powerful influence
on North African literature
written in French, died in
October 1989. One story about
him illustrates the position of
the writer in societies where
illiteracy is widespread. Yacine
was once stopped in Sidi Bel
Abbes by an old man who said
to him: "It appears that you're a
writer. If you are, then sit down
and listen to me."
NEXT STOP JUPITER
On 18 October 1989 the
American space shuttle Atlantis
launched the spacecraft
Galileo on a 6-year voyage of
some 3,900 million kilometres.
By July 1995 Galileo will be
near enough to Jupiter to
collect detailed information
about the planet and its 16
known satellites. The data
transmitted during the voyage
are expected to be of major
importance In Increasing our
knowledge of the universe.
KASPAROV CRUSHES
COMPUTER
World chess champion Garri
Kasparov, of the USSR, has
defeated Deep Thought, a
high-powered computer created
by graduate students at
Carnegie-Mellon University in
Pittsburgh, USA. In the first
of 2 games, the computer
retired after Kasparov's 52nd
move and 20 hours of play.
In the second Deep Thought
surrendered after 37 moves
and 2 hours. The computer
can analyze a possible
700,000 positions per second
and 5 to 20 moves ahead by
each side. "It's a good player,"
said Kasparov, "but without
position and experience."
NEW DIRECTION FOR
BERLIN PHILHARMONIC
The Italian musician Claudio
Abbado has succeeded Herbert
von Karajan, who died on 16
July 1989, as music director of
the Berlin Philharmonic
Orchestra. He was elected to
this prestigious post last October
by a secret ballot of the
orchestra's 120 musicians.
GENETICS AND
HUMAN RIGHTS
A seminar on the genetic
heritage and human rights was
held in Paris in October 1989.
It was organized by the
European Commission, the
University of Paris VII (Jussieu)
and the European Research
University, in collaboration with
Unesco, the French National
Institute of Health and Medical
Research (INSERM) and the
French ministries of research
and technology and of foreign
affairs. A broad range of issues
relating to genetic research
was discussed by biologists,
medical doctors, philosophers,
jurists and researchers in the
human sciences.
FRENCH RESEARCH BODY
CELEBRATES
50TH ANNIVERSARY
France's National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS),
founded In October 1939, has
reached ¡ts half-century.
With a budget of over
9,000 million francs, some
26,000 employees (researchers,
engineers, technicians and
administrators), 1,300
laboratories (wholly owned or
associated), the CNRS has
co-operation agreements with
55 overseas centres and is
Europe's biggest research
institution.
PSYCHIATRY AND
THE ENVIRONMENT
Over 4,600 psychiatrists from
81 countries took part in the
8th World Congress of
Psychiatry (Athens,
12-19 October 1989). The
participants recognized the
important role played by the
environment, as well as by
genetic factors, in mental
illnesses and their treatment.
WORLD PEACE AND
SECURITY
In a recent interview with the
Paris dally Le Figaro, the
Secretary-General of the United
Nations, Mr. Javier Pérez de
Cuéllar, evoked the role of the
Secretary-General. "I cannot
fight alone," he said. "Member
states must help me. All I have
Is moral force. Political and
military force He with the
Security Council."
SOUTH/SOUTH
CO-OPERATION
Representatives of heads of state
and governments of 15 Latin
American, African and Asian
countries met on 6 and 7
November 1989 in Geneva to
discuss the basis of a plan of
action for South/South co¬
operation. A summit meeting
will be held In May 1990,
probably in India.
THE SPECTRE OF SEVESO
Over 13 years after the
catastrophe at Seveso, near
Milan, laboratory analyses
carried out recently by the
University of Missouri, USA, have
revealed the accumulation of a '
tonne of the highly toxic
chemical dioxin in the subsoil at
a chemical factory in the region
of Cengio, north of Genoa. The
Italian government has asked
the Istltuto Superlore di Sanità, a
public health research institute,
to carry out an independent
analysis and proposes to invite
the World Health Organization
to examine the results.
BAN ON INTERNATIONAL
IVORY TRADE
The 7th conference of CITES
(the Convention on International
Trade in Endangered Species)
ended on 20 October 1989 at
Lausanne with a consensus
decision for a total ban on the
international trade in ivory until
1 992, when the next CITES
conference will be held.
IN BRIEF IN BRIEF IN BRIEF 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
F L E C T I N
THE STRUGGLE OF DAY AND NIGHT
BY ABDOL-HOSSEYN ZARRINKOUB
46
aTiLL Iranians, whatever their reli¬
gious beliefs, language or origins and
wherever they live, are strongly at¬
tached to NowRouz (New Year). This
festival, which does not feature in the
Islamic lunar calendar, begins the
solar year at the spring equinox, 21
March. Lasting around two weeks, it
is the longest of all Iranian feasts and
its rites are the richest in symbolism.
The ceremonial includes customs
from pre-Islamic festivals and rites
introduced by people of non-Iranian
origin, such as the Jews, and even
borrowings from rites practised
elsewhere.
Two weeks before Now Rouz, each
household traditionally grows a plate
of sprouts of wheat, barley or lentils
as omens of a good harvest or as
tokens of fruitfulness in the future.
This significant ritual is followed by
two important celebrations which
mark the closing days of the year and
prepare for Now Rouz proper.
At nightfall on "Ember Wednes¬
day" (Tchahârshamba-souri) a bonfire
of brambles and other dry plants is
lit. Men and women, old and young
leap over the flames shouting "Fire
that burns! Fire! Fire! May your red
come to me and my yellow go to
you!" The light of the flames symbo¬
lizes the Sun. By challenging the set¬
ting Sun to shine more brightly and
to compete with the fire, they urge
it to throw off its winter torpor. Once
the fire has gone out, earthenware
pots and vases filled with water, and
a variety of other objects, are hurled
from the top of the house to shouts
of "Dard-o balâ! Dard-o bale!" ("Pain
and unhappinessl"). Wednesday be¬
ing traditionally considered as a day
of ill-omen, in this way misfortune is
averted and unhappiness symbolically
banished from the house.
On the same day, people try to
foresee the future. The omens are
read in various ways. Women who
want a child, girls who have not yet
found a husband, men who are hop¬
ing to conclude a successful business
deal or even to get married, go out
into the streets or stay behind closed
Y^^
.EU
«.
s^S3?*rNJ,
doors eavesdropping on conversa¬
tions between people they do not
know. They interpret the words they
overhear as omens of the future and
make wishes and pray to try to ward
off misfortune. Another custom is for
women and children in disguise, their
faces hidden, to go out into the
streets at twilight carrying an empty
receptacle and bang on doors with
a spoon. They say nothing but go on
knocking until someone opens a door
and gives them a present.
Purification and fireworks
The second end-of-year celebration,
the "Day of Reckoning" (rouz-e
barat) is the Iranian day of the dead.
On the last Thursday of the year alms
and gifts are distributed at the
cemetery: money, food, halva or new
clothes are given so that the poor can
celebrate the feast. The house is
cleaned from top to bottomthis is
a vestige of a pre-Islamic festival. In
this way the living seek to pay their
debts to the departed and attract the
benevolence of their ancestors.
The "spring cleaning" (Khana
Takani) done before New Year is
more than just a cleaning operation.
From cellar to attic, from carpets to
bedding, everything must be made
as good as new. A new life is dawn¬
ing and the house must be symboli¬
cally purified and thoroughly cleansed
as if it were a human body, by being
carefully washed and by wearing new
clothes.
For the New Year ceremonial, the
plate of sprouting grain and the tray
of the "seven sin" must be placed on
the NowRouz cloth in front of a mir¬
ror lit by as many candles as there are
members of the household, a copy
of the Qur'an, a bowl of milk, a bowl
of yoghurt, and gifts of coins. While
they are waiting for the New Year to
Now Rouz (New Year) festival,
(1984), by Morteza Rafii.
begin, the parents and other older
people pray that the year will be pro¬
pitious and recite the Qur'an to bring
blessings and happiness to the family.
Immediately afterwards, sweetmeats
are eaten. Their taste presages a
happy year.
The tray of the "seven sin" con¬
tains seven products whose names in
Persian, Turkish or Arabic begin with
the letter sin, the initial letter of the
Persian words for green (sabz) and
white (safid), colours which symbo¬
lize respectively the renewal of spring¬
time and the purity that wards off
demons. Today the tradition has
changed: everyone can choose seven
symbols representing renewal, crea¬
tion, abundance and wealth. The
number 7 is a sacred number, as it
was for the Babylonians and the an¬
cient Hebrews, linked to the idea of
creation which runs through all the
symbolism of Now Rouz.
On New Year's Eve, fireworks are
set off in the courtyard of the house
or on the terrace. They symbolize the
combat between dark, gloomy
winter and bright, joyful spring; the
victory of fire over darkness, a re-
enactment of the moment when the
world of shadows is attacked by the
world of light, the moment of
Creation.
On the morning of the big day the
children are given gold coins, cakes
and hard-boiled eggs that have been
painted, decorated and wrapped as
gifts. They have been cooked in a
brew of onion peel, walnut shells or
ABDOL-HOSSEYN ZARRINKOUB,
Iranian historian and specialist in
Oriental literature, is professor of
history at the University of Tehran
and the author of more than
thirty books. His latest work is a
study on the Persian poet Hafez.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
N
straw so that they are coloured
green, brown or yellow. They symbo¬
lize the renewal of the world and they
are a pledge of fruitfulness.
Return to paradise
The first thirteen days of the year are
a time of rejoicing. Children think
only of play and adults of visiting
each other. The real purpose of these
joyful days is to rediscover an origi¬
nal state of purity and equality. Re¬
lations with friends and neighbours
begin anew. People visit everyone,
the mighty and the humble. The peri¬
od of mourning for those who died
the previous year is ended. The
straightjacket of convention is
broken, though indulgence in licen¬
tiousness is not encouraged. Dis¬
tances due to social rank are
abolished. Everyone, rich and poor,
enjoys the same kind of food and
recreations and wears brightly-
coloured new clothes. Work stops in
fields and factories. All the rites per¬
formed at this time look back to a lost
paradise, the original earthly paradise
in which the divine breath infuses
humankind with a feeling of spiritual
fraternity and equality.
On the "Thirteenth day outside"
(Sizdah bedar) the mount of the de¬
mon of cold is driven from the city.
The cereals that have sprouted in the
plate are thrown into the river after
being examined by the elders in an
attempt to predict the weather dur¬
ing the coming year.
This day inaugurates a happy New
Year. Friends and neighbours usual¬
ly organize a picnic in the countryside
at which noodle soup or dishes of rice
in sauce are eaten. People go and see
the streams and rivers swollen with
melted snow. The young play tradi¬
tional games and sports, and the girls
weave together fresh herbs, singing
as they do so in a low voice: "The thir¬
teenth day, next year, at my hus¬
band's, a baby in my arms!" (Sizdah
bedar - sal-e degar khäna-ye
shouhar batcha baqual). No conflict
should be initiated on that day.
In all the rites of Now Rouz,
whatever their origin, there is one
constantly recurring feature: the con¬
flict between light and darkness, in
keeping with the old Zoroastrian du¬
alism. It is no coincidence that legend
should attribute the invention of this
feast to Jamshid or Feridun, legend¬
ary kings and divine heroes who
triumphed over the forces of dark¬
ness. But ¡f Islam has kept up this
Zoroastrian feast, it is because of the
Table spread with ceremonial
objects to celebrate
Iran's New Year festival.
role it plays in the stabilization of the
fiscal year and also because of its
jovial and lively ceremonies which
were highly esteemed at the courts
of the caliphs and the sultans. The
singing and music which always mark
Now Rouz explain why the sufis are
interested in this festival.
CARNIVAL IN LUANDA
BY DOMINGOS VAN-DUNEM
I spent part of my childhood at
Museke Marçal, a poor district of the
city of Luanda where, people used to
say, "the children only bathe when
rain fills the lagoon of Moreira".
There, fifty-odd years ago, my family
and I enjoyed the bittersweet
privilege of taking part in that match¬
less popular spectacle, the Luanda
carnival.
The city was divided into districts,
each of which was the territory of
one of the traditional troupes known
as turmas which with their "kings"
were the life and soul of the carnival.
The two most famous turmas were
O Coraçào (The Heart) and Os Inveja-
dos (The envied ones). Members of
the troupes practised a kind of verbal
jousting known as kazakuta, which
is still the most typical expression of
Luandan folklore.
The turmas began to mobilize in
December, when their most gifted
members rehearsed songs for the car¬
nival. The songs were sung either in
Kimbundu, one of the national lan¬
guages, if they were about unusual
or satirical subjects, or in Portuguese
or in both languages if they were in¬
offensive or ambiguous. The singers
met secretly in private homes or in
rented halls. Violations of secrecy
were severely punished. Dance re¬
hearsals were also held in secret.
The carnival supported a small in¬
dustry, notably the metalworker's art.
Domingos Venenohis name meant
"venom", for although he was a
skinny fellow he was a doughty
fighteris still remembered for the
lamps and the objects decorated with
¡mages and amulets which he made
in complete secrecy. He was a devot¬
ed supporter of O Coráceo, and
worked exclusively for them. Design¬
ers and dressmakers also worked
secretly and exclusively for their
favourite groups.
The first public rehearsal was held
on the first Sunday of January, and
the dress rehearsal took place on the
Saturday before Ash Wednesday
when people prayed to the divinity
that the carnival should take place in
"peace and tranquillity". It cannot be
denied, however, that violent scuffles
often broke out between the turmas.
Early on the Sunday morning the
flags of the turmas were hoisted at 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
the gateways to the districts, in the
midst of crowds of excited children.
Then, to the sound of shouting and
applause, they were carried down¬
town by a gang of strapping fellows.
More and more people joined in the
processions as they wended their way
to Ambuilas, a sports ground in the
middle of a big open space where the
rival groups paraded side by side. The
group that won most applause was
judged the winnerthe verdict was
never disputed.
That afternoon all the huts were
empty. No one would have dreamed
of missing the festival. People flocked
in, even from other towns. The at¬
mosphere was euphoric. The mem¬
bers of the turmas wore devils' masks
and brightly coloured costumes much
admired by the crowd. Whistling and
trumpeting rent the air, drums rolled,
the crowds sang in unison. Then
everyone returned to Ambuilas for
another competition.
O Caraçâo and A Fineza (Subtlety),
eternal rivals, submitted their
costumes to the judgement of the
public.
The king of A Fineza, Kamalundu,
a cobbler with bulging eyes, held
himself majestically, leaning slightly
forward. He waved his right hand,
which he had slipped into a zinc
gauntlet, another emblem of the two
turmas.
The enemy king, Epifanio, now ap¬
peared. He too leaned forward slight¬
ly, brandishing a gauntlet which, as
a metalworker, he had made himself.
Both kings proudly entered the lists,
showing off their beautiful costumes
which were inspired by the royal
finery of old Europe. On their heads
glittered zinc crownswe called
them helmetswhich each one had
decorated so as to outdo the other.
Everyone danced frenetically. The
kings, enthroned amidst their court,
dominated the turmas, surrounded
by figures in disguise, some wearing
black cloaks as emblems of the stu¬
dents they would never be, others
dressed in doctors' or nurses' smocks.
Then all present walked to the palace
to join up with other groups and pay
their respects to the governor, who
stood on the balcony with his distin¬
guished guests and saluted the
revellers.
Tuesday was the day to end all
days. No one let up for a second. An
N
enormous crowd raced here, there
and everywhere, enjoying every
minute. Lovers of jousting tried their
hand at kazakuta. Peals of laughter
rang out incessantly as the kazaku-
teiros made fun of everyone and
mocked the ups and downs of life.
Washerwomen cast an irresistible
spell as they cleverly satirized "ladies"
who only the day before had been
lowly servants. Greengrocers
described their tangles with cus¬
tomers who did nothing but grum¬
ble and protest about the poor
quality and high price of their
vegetables.
The governor declared a holiday,
and we all lived each moment as if
it were our last, as if we were afraid
of losing forever the delights of this
incomparable festival. Men and
women abandoned themselves to
delirium. A mother wandered
around, desperately beating a tin can
with her weary hand as she asked
whether anyone happened to have
seen her son, who had got lost in the
general confusion.
Girls dressed in beautiful white
dominoes alighted like butterflies,
arousing the curiosity of the boys and
the jealousy of lovers.
So the carnival went on until
WednesdayAsh Wednesday ac¬
cording to the liturgical calendar, the
Wednesday of mabangas, the shell¬
fish of good luck.
The troupes were tired. The masks
were falling to pieces. Four people
held out a sheet for a collection to
buy mabangas, which were plentiful
in that region and, copiously washed
down, made a meal during which
people took stock of the year that
was past and made plans for the
future.
DOMINGOS VAN-DUNEM,
Angolan journalist, novelist and
author of socio-linguistic studies,
is currently serving as his
country's ambassador and
permanent delegate to Unesco.
Among his recent works are a
play entitled O panfleto ("The
Tract"), published in 1988.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
M E M 0
A MUSEUM FOR PEACE
BY HOWARD BRABYN
I F you stand in the grassed over
quarry that now forms part of the
gardens of the Memorial Museum for
Peace, on the outskirts of Caen in
Normandy, France, your eye will
perhaps be caught by a seemingly
insignificant, newly-planted sapling.
Under two metres in height, there
is nothing to distinguish it from the
other trees in the garden except the
plaque that informs the curious that it
is a gift from the people of the United
States, a sequoia sempen/irens, a
Redwood, the world's tallest species
of tree, that one day will tower above
its neighbours at its maximum height
of 90 metres or more.
Opened in 1988, the Memorial
Museum for Peace was built to com¬
memorate those who died in the
Battle of Normandy in 1944, the big¬
gest battle in the history of mankind
It also honours the people of Caen,
who saw their city reduced to rubble
around them in the struggle for
liberation.
But the Museum is not just another
memorial, not just another war
museum full of rusty war relics and a
somewhat distasteful hint of glorying
over the vanquished enemy. It is a
monument to the obstinate determi¬
nation of human beings to safeguard
their freedom, and a laboratory in
which to study the causes and
prevention of armed conflict. Today,
it could well claim to be on the way
to becoming the world's first Univer¬
sity of Peace.
In January this year, thirty-four
selected American students are to
come together at the University of
Texas, Austin, to take part in the first
Normandy Scholar Program, spon
sored by the US Normandy Founda¬
tion and devised with the advice of
a board of leading American histori¬
ans. They will spend four weeks at
the University of Texas, eight weeks
at the Memorial Museum for Peace,
and a final two weeks back in Austin.
According to Anthony Stout, Chair¬
man of the US Normandy Founda¬
tion, whose father was closely
involved with General Eisenhower in
the planning and execution of the
Normandy landings, "the idea of this
course is to teach the Second World
War as a 'case study' and to find out
how people who don't want to wind
up in a war wind up in a war".
This "case study" approach will in¬
volve an in-depth examination of con¬
ditions in Europe before, during and
after the two World Wars with the
aim of finding answers to such ques¬
tions as.
How did the Second World War
happen so soon after another, gruell¬
ing war between many of the same
combatants, and could it have been
avoided?
Why were the Allies reluctant to
resist the Nazis until it was almost too
late?
What role did world economic con¬
ditions play as the war approached?
What role was played by the press,
the Churches and other institutions7
Many of these questions and
others raised by the conflict are as
relevant to peace now as they were
in 1939. Many are central to issues
being faced and debated by leaders
today and to issues which will be
faced as society moves into the next
century.
The initial pilot programme will
consist of four major courses covering
the economic background, the cul¬
tural and intellectual history of France
in the European context from the
1880s, communications and an as¬
sessment of the role of all the media,
and leadership and strategy before
and during the Second World War.
The Memorial Museum for Peace
provides the ideal setting for studies
of this kind. Located on the outskirts
of Caen, the pivot around which the
Battle of Normandy revolved, only a
few miles from the beaches at which
the Allied forces landed, it is sited
literally on top of the underground
bunker that served as the command
post of General Wilhelm Richter of
the German 716th Infantry Division
which faced the Anglo-Canadian
forces advancing on Caen. Even
today there are many people still
living in the area who can give first¬
hand accounts of life under the Nazi
occupation and of the battle that
raged throughout Normandy for
seventy-six days.
The Museum is designed as "a
voyage through history", starting
with the signing of the armistice in
1918. Visitors entera huge cylinder,
round which a descending spiral
ramp leads them through an impres¬
sive collection of photographs,
posters, and audio-visual displays
covering the period 1918 to 1938
The scenes depicting "the failure of
peace and the rise of the dictators"
include not only political events such
as the coming to power of Adolf
Hitler or the Anschluss, but also back¬
ground evocations of the Jazz Age,
the world economic depression, the
Wall Street crash of 1 929, and so on.
The ramp leads down to a large
black dome where a huge, out-of-
focus picture of Hitler is projected in
an eerie violet light and the dictator's
voice is heard as a menacing, incom¬
prehensible mumble. The world has
reached the pit of despair.
As visitors move out of the cylinder
they come to the first of a maze of
rooms in which are successively
depicted the French surrender in
1940; France under the Nazi occupa¬
tion and the Vichy Government, with
all the horror of the execution of
hostages and resistance fighters, the
desperate daily search for food; the
entry of the United States into the
fighting and the period of "Total
War"; a restrained treatment of the
deportations, the concentration
camps and the mass murder of the
Jews of Europe, films of the key
points of the war such as the Battle
of Britain, Midway, El-Alamein,
Guadalcanal and Stalingrad.
The next section of the Museum is
perhaps more conventional, with dis¬
plays of weapons and military equip¬
ment that reflect the technological
and industrial progress that the
urgent demands of war provoked.
After climbing up a short stairway
visitors enter an area which sets the
scene for a truly amazing documen¬
tary film, projected on a wide, split
screen and simultaneously showing
the Normandy landings as seen from
both the Allied and German sides.
The grand finale of the visit is
reserved for a film on the defence of
liberty and human rights, an expla¬
nation of the philosophy of the
Museum and a special message of
peace and hope.
Writing about the Museum, its
founding father Jean-Marie Girault,
French senator and mayor of Caen,
declared' "It is our intention to arouse
the consciousness of all men and
women who visit the Museum, from
whatever country, so that they may
realize that the tragedies surrounding
liberty are as much a part of our con¬
temporary world as they are of his¬
tory, and that it is imperative that
each individual person should renew
his efforts on behalf of peace, frater¬
nity and solidarity."
This intention the Memorial
Museum for Peace triumphantly
fulfils Inside its walls there is no
glorification of war but an unforget¬
table lesson in peace.
HOWARD BRABYN,
of the United Kingdom, is a Paris
based writer and journalist. He
was formerly Editor of the
English-language edition of the
Unesco Courier. 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
50
Don't smoke, subscribe!
There has been a striking improve¬
ment in the quality of your magazine
and its illustrations, but the subscrip¬
tion price seems to be at the limit of
what my pupils can afford. However,
it's cheaper than buying cigarettes...
Paul Fidani
Lycée Montmajour, Aries (France)
Putting the record straight
I should like to make some comments
on the interesting article on Arab
mathematics by my colleague Roshdi
Rashed which appeared in your
November 1 989 issue, A mathemat¬
ical mystery tour.
If I am not mistaken, the author has
grouped together as "Arab
mathematicians" all the scholars who
wrote and published their discoveries
in the Arabic language. This is a use¬
ful designation as the vast majority
of scientists and thinkers of the
Islamic world did use that language.
But I think we should remember
that some non-Arabs used Arabic in
their scientific work. Several of the
scholars mentioned in Mr. Rashed's
article, including Khârazmi (rather
than al-Khwarizmi) and Khayyam
(rather than al-Khayyam), were
Iranian. Furthermore, some of them
wrote poetry in their mother tongue.
Khayyam's quatrains are a monument
of Persian, not Arabic, literature.
I am not raising this point out of
chauvinism but simply in order to put
the cultural record straight and above
all to emphasize that the Islamic
world stretches far beyond the
boundaries of Arab language and
culture.
Yann Richard
Châtenay-Malabry (France)
Inherited v. acquired
characteristics
I was irritated by the following state¬
ment in Jacques Richardson's article
on mapping the human genome
("Science and Society", September
1989): "In reproduction, a father and
a mother contribute a gene cor¬
responding to every chromosome
pair found in their offspring. It is the
combination of the similarities and
differences that make each of
us.. .mentally alert, musical, manually
dexterous, sports-minded, and so
on."
I'm not an expert in biology but I've
been interested in the subject for a
long time, especially in genetics with
all its vast perspectives. According to
everything I've read or discovered, the
idea that people's intelligence, ability,
or even tastes should depend on their
genetic makeup has more to do with
ideology than science.
I know that "signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do
not necessarily represent the opinions
of Unesco or those of the editors of
the Unesco Courier", but I'm afraid
that these few words are too fraught
with consequences for the human
race for me to let them pass without
comment.
Christophe Meslin
Athis-Mons (France)
Message of peace
from Anatolia
The preamble to Unesco's Constitu¬
tion contains the following words:
"Since wars begin in the minds of
men, it is in the minds of men that
the defences of peace must be con¬
structed."
I don't know what the third world
war will be like, but the fourth will
be fought with sticks and stones, as
Einstein said. Both world wars caused
terrible suffering, and yet people still
make war. It's shameful!
Education is the only solution.
Young people must be taught the
spirit of peace from childhood on.
They must hate war. They must hold
out flowers and olive branches to
those who want war. War must not
triumph over reason.
Orhan Vatansever
Anatolia (Turkey)
An idea to save the world
The theme of the June 1989 issue
was " 1 789: An idea that changed the
world". Today, however, two
hundred years later, it is evident that
we are in urgent need of fresh ap¬
proaches if we wish to assure the sur¬
vival of life on this planet.
The environmental problem and
the regional conflicts are examples of
the awesome challenges facing hu¬
manity. It is odd that the authors who
occasionally raise these issues all stop
short of the one logical conclusion,
namely that mankind has only one
realistic alternative to universal dis¬
aster and that is a World Federation.
The idea is by no means new. Just
over forty years ago, Albert Einstein
thought that it would come about in
any event...
It is surely time for us to make a
firm effort to shake ourselves out of
our indifferencebefore our collec¬
tive Titanic takes us into an era of
prolonged darkness or sinks outright
into eternal oblivion.
Zeev Raphael
Haifa (Israel)
Berlioz and the Aeneid
I was sorry that Jean-Paul Brisson, in
his article "Aeneas, Rome's man of
destiny" (September 1989), did not
mention the only important modern
work I know of which is based on the
Aeneid, namely Hector Berlioz' opera
Les Troyens. Berlioz read and studied
the Latin text of the Aeneid from an
early age, and took it as the subject
of an opera which was the culmina¬
tion of his mature work as a musician.
Berlioz is still too little known, even
in his native France! Would it be pos¬
sible for the Unesco Courier to pay
tribute to him in a forthcoming issue?
Jean-Michel Cuzin
Sceaux (France)
A wish come true
In the year since I've been a sub¬
scriber to the Courier, I don't think
you have devoted an issue to eco¬
nomics. I should be really interested
to read an economics number be¬
cause of the courses I'm taking at
school.
David-Pierre Gagneur
(age fifteen and a half)
Saint-Denis (France)
PHOTO CREDITS
Cover: Princelle © Unesco Courier.
Back cover, pages 24, 25 (above): ©
Charles Lenars, Paris. Page 2: © Delia
Nimo, Paris. Pages 5, 6, 7: © Cahiers
du Cinéma, Paris. Page 8: © SCALA,
Florence. Pages 10, 12 (above &
below): © Musée de l'Homme, Paris.
Pages 10-11: D. Destable © Musée de
l'Homme, Paris. Page 11 (above): D.
Ponsard © Musée de l'Homme, Paris.
Pages 13 (above left & right, below),
14 (left), 15, 26, 28, 29, 32, 34 (above),
35 (below), 37, 42 (above), 43
(above): © Bibliothèque Nationale,
Paris. Page 13 (centre): © Peter
Clayton, United Kingdom. Pages 14
(right), 34 (below): Roger Viollet,
Paris. Pages 16-17: © René Parcheron
© Artephot, Paris. Page 17: Fred
Mayer © Magnum, Paris. Page 18
(left): René Burri © Magnum, Paris;
(right): J.M. Fatin © Jacana, Paris.
Page 19: S. Cordier © Jacana, Paris.
Page 20: George Rodger © Magnum,
Paris. Pages 21, 25 (below): Oster ©
Musée de l'Homme, Paris. Pages 22,
23: R. König © Jacana, Paris. Pages
26-27: Amedeo Vergani © Rapho,
Paris. Page 30: H. Gruyvaert ©
Magnum, Paris. Page 31: © Sotheby's
Inc., New York. Pages 32-33: ©
Réunion des Musées Nationaux,
Musée du Louvre, Paris. Page 35
(above): Nimatallah © Artephot,
Paris. Pages 36-37: © Isia Leviant,
Paris. Page 38 (above): © Boyer
Viollet, Paris. Pages 38 (centre),
38-39: Collection Viollet, Paris. Page
39 (above): © Harlingue Viollet,
Paris. Page 40: Gigli © Rapho, Paris.
Page 41: Allan Carruthers © Cosmos,
Paris. Pages 42 (below), 43 (centre):
© Jean-Loup Charmet, Paris. Page 43
(below): © Archives Ringart, Paris.
Page 44: Dejardin © Rapho, Paris.
Pages 46, 47 (above): © Morteza
Rafii, Paris. Pages 47 (below), 48: ©
Photothèque DIP/MPLA-PT, from
Angola, Trabalho e Luta. Pages 48, 49:
© Patricia Canina
For your meetings, seminars
and conferences, a number of
rooms are available at Unesco's
Paris Headquarters, as well as
the services of Unesco's ex¬
perienced catering staff. For
further information please call
45.68.15.99 or 45.68.15.97.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
ThellNESCO ,
J^GOURIERI
Published monthly in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Pans)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Maltón, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Russian edition: Georgi Zelenin
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Sen/at
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstem (Tel.: 45 68.46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Public relations: Claudie Duhamel (Tel :45 68 45.86)
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Kumar Singh (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88), Assistant: Marie-
Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89), Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse
Hardy (45.68.45.65), Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité,
Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo,
Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: Liliane Tasen (45.68 45 .66), Cultural projects:
Ricardo Zamora-Perez (45.68.45.80),
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
ADVERTISING
Publicat: 17, Boulevard Poissonnière, 75002 Paris.
Tel.: 40.26 51.26
Sales director: Benoît Rosier
Advertising director: Daniele Michelet
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 68 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
individual anieles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name Non copyright
photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps
Published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations The Unesco Courier is
produced n microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A., (3) N C R Microcard Edition. Indian
Head. Inc . 111 West 40th Street. New York, U SA.; (4) Bell and
Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster. Ohio 44691. US A
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed m France) DEPOT LEGAL CI JANVIER 1990.
Photocomposition: The Unesco Courier
Photogravure-impression: Maury Imprimeur S.A., ZI route d'Etampes.
45330 Malesherbes
SSN 0041-5278
wÊËm WM
SM
wHÊMê
HIB
three good reasons for
offerim your friends a
gift subscription to the
Unesco Courier
It is the only international cultural magazine
published in 35 languages
and read by hundreds of thousands ofpeople
in 120 countries
Each month it explores
the astonishing diversity of
world culture and knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's
mission offurthering "universal respect for
justice, for the rule of law and for human rights
and fundamental freedoms...without distinction
of race, sex, language or religion.."
N° 1 1990 OPI 89 1 476 A
This issue comprises 54 pages and a 4. page advertising insert
between pages 10-11 and 42 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
,. ¡uwt+K* *
;* s
> ,
^-*-
' /-t
]]>
</page>
</document>
