<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="085219eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The I IlNESCO
« ^GOURIER^
The art of
I^l hospitality
.1^
.ai^al .(HL' * ^3
a^^^^F^BBaT^^KV- ' ' BE^- ^^ IM "^M. WF^ J* ^" «.^P
J^ <^¿>! *¡r** . ^^^^jEíí *v '' B_j ' m J
Bv /V/fl I fjfl
Je K ' a^alv r ac~ \[^B
-4t^ aR^^^^^Ê^^^Ê^^^Êtfj ^^aa>
y . /¿j
FEBRUARY 1990
15 French francs
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters
We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
M
A :
-
\ y %
f**U
Women at the fountain, homage to Poussin
1979, diptych, oil on canvas (195 x 260 cm)
by Iba N'Diaye
When painting African subjects, the Senegalese artist Iba N'Diaye sometimes
borrows from the works of European masters. His art is a remarkable blend of the
African and European cultures between which he moves and whose differences and
contradictions he seeks to reconcile. In "Women at the Fountain", an evocation of
women in the Medina, one of the oldest districts of Dakar, he was inspired by the
formal structure of the French painter Nicolas Poussin's "Eliézer and Rebecca"
(1648). The art critic Anne Dagbert has noted that here "N'Diaye reinterprets a
theme which is above all a pretext, a vehicle for the only subject that really
matters: painting itself".
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
FEBRUARY 1990
N N
Today there are no more
unexplored continents,
unknown seas or mysterious
islands. But while we can
overcome the physical
barriers to exploration, the
barriers of mutual ignorance
between different peoples
and cultures have in many
cases still not been
dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can
voyage to the ends of the
earth. But a different kind
of Odyssey now beckonsan
exploration of the world's
many cultural landscapes, the
ways of life of its different
peoples and their outlook on
the world in which they live.
It is such an Odyssey that
the Unesco Courier proposes
to you, its readers. Each
month contributors of
different nationalities provide
from different cultural and
professional standpoints an
authoritative treatment of a
theme of universal interest.
The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes is respect ,
for the dignity of man
everywhere.
4
9
Interview with
Soviet poet
ANDREY
VOZNESENSKY
Y
\^¡.
41
THE ART OF HOSPITALITY IN BRIEF-
ISLANDS OF WELCOME
IN A SEA OF SAND
by Joseph Chelhod 11
*A DESIRE TO RECEIVE GUESTS'
by Georges Lisowski
AFRICAN HOSPITALITY -
A DYING TRADITION?
by Babacar Fall 21
WHERE 'FOREIGNER' MEANS 'GUEST'
by André Kédros
KRUPA SINDHU AND THE BEGGAR
by Prafulla Mohanti
LAND OF A THOUSAND AND
ONE COURTESIES
by Yann Richard 30
PAMPA-ED GUESTS
by Gregorio Manzur 35
FROM HOSPITALITY TO RIGHT OF ASYLUM
by José Augusta Seabra 39
41
REFLECTIONS
The return of the Inca
by Perla Petrich 42
SCIENCE
The disappearance of the
dinosaurs, a scientific enigma
17 by Léonard Ginsburg 44
ANNIVERSARY
The great wall
of medieval Paris
by Arthur Gillette 46
HERITAGE
25 Archaeologists
of the year 2000
by Frédéric Berthault 48
29 LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR 50
Cover: A Tuareg prepares mint
tea in the Djanet oasis, south¬
eastern Algeria.
Back cover: Indian miniature,
Baroda school (18th century).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
I N T E R V I E W
Andrey Voznesensky
ft
6^'
/w í¿e late 1950s the noted Soviet poet
Andrey Voznesensky emerged as a leader of
the literary revival that followed the death
of Stalin. Thirty years later, in the age of
perestroika, he speaks of the cultural ferment
in the USSR today.
*****
ao»v
*****^^>ç-^^
a6»'.** e*1
c rts?L'
.0*.
"^
*** ft,oivce
**>*
*s<
Tío CyxapeBoii 6auiHe pu^aü, Hbsh BcimkhA!
HaA Mockboh ßejieeT obäobcbuihh CTOain.
You are the chairman of a committee that is organizing
a major celebration in the Soviet Union this year to mark
the centenary of the birth of Boris Pasternak. When it is
remembered that until a few years ago some ofPasternak's
works such as his famous novel Doctor Zhivago were
banned in the USSR and others had a very limited circu¬
lation, this means that there has been a big change in your
country's cultural life. Can you tell us something about the
significance of this anniversary celebration?
It will be a great celebration, not only of Pasternak but
of freedom in literature, of freedom for our intellectuals.
Doctor Zhivago was not only a novel, it was a symbol of
intellectual protest against all forms of pressure and dictator¬
ship. Pasternak was not a politician and Doctor Zhivago is
a supremely anti-political novel but it had a strong political
impact.
A campaign against Pasternak was initiated by the then
Soviet leader, Nikita S. Khruschev. Pasternak was expelled
from the Soviet Writers' Union. I don't think Khruschev
had read any Pasternak, but he was afraid of the intelligentsia
and thought that people like Pasternak represented a threat
to the regime.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Also symbolic, I think, is the fact that Pasternak gave
Doctor Zhivago to an Italian publishing house after it had
been rejected for publication by the Soviet periodical Novy
Mir. He wanted contacts outside our culture and he has
become a symbol of our desire for such contacts.
And so we shall not only be celebrating the birth of
Pasternak, but Pasternak as a symbol of our intelligentsia.
We are creating a Pasternak museum in the writers' village
of Peredelkino, where Pasternak had a cottage. Leading
writers from all over the world have been invited to the
anniversary ceremony which will, I think, be welcomed by
millions of people in my country.
Everything is interwoven: literature, politics, religion.
Leading liberals and Patriarch Pimen, the head of the Russian
Orthodox Church, are members of the anniversary com¬
mittee. Freedom of religion and freedom of publication are
closely connected. I am happy that this anniversary will be
celebrated in the Soviet Union, but only a few years ago
it would not have been possible. I am also very happy that
Unesco has included Pasternak's name on its list of outstand¬
ing persons whose anniversaries will be celebrated this year.
Your own poetry has been influenced by Pasternak. How
far do you identify with him?
When I was fourteen years old I sent some of my poetry
to Pasternak and he telephoned me and invited me to come
and see him. From then until I was twenty-eight I was very
close to him and he was my only master. At that time he
was being harshly attacked by the authorities.
Certainly I was influenced by Pasternak but it was a
tragedy for me because he was a genius. I felt in danger of
becoming his slave, of losing my own identity. One summer,
he showed me some of his recent poems and I discovered
that they contained several lines identical to lines I had
written and shown him some time before. He said to me,
ÏS.
SSta
M3 MajïeHbKoro a&a
^thm « Gom-u10^ aw'
*°*opwft »e »op-"*3'
a caM ___ npouecc pacna*
- Zïa«aHTe P»CBSC"!
Ha Win*» h xy^ee-
nam,TO Ba.nK>T»oM
aer. «C.iy»uaMTe
3BOJIM3UMMÏ»
Tfi BXOHU^».
a oCTaBlU1-
way-
fT03T B
HiicraHB
MyZblKy
°CTa/ii,,
í?e Bb'6poc
C °raPO«fKOM
Left, Andrey Voznesensky during a poetry reading he gave in
Moscow in 1978. This page and facing page above, specimens
of "visual poetry" by Voznesensky from his work "Rhapsody
of Disintegration ".
"Andrey, I loved these poems of yours so much that I
imagined that they were mine and included them in my
volume." At first I felt it was a great honour that Pasternak
liked my poems so much, but when I got home I realized
that it was a great tragedy for me since these poems were
no longer mine but Pasternak's. I stopped writing poetry
and started painting. I painted for a year to forget about
poetry. Then I began to write again, and this time it was
my own work, written in my own way, and this really
marked my beginning as a poet.
How would you define Pasternak's qualities as a poet?
Pasternak's poetic style and technique sprang from the
musical exercises he performed as a young man, from his
technical skills as a pianist. His every line, his every word,
works as a musical note, as if he were pressing the keys of
a piano. There are no empty, redundant lines.
But another, more important music can be discerned
through the fabric of his worksthe music of conscience.
The world today is suffering from a lack of conscience. This
is a problem facing all humanity. The music of conscience
can be heard on every page of Doctor Zhivago, the work
which meant most to Pasternak and which ends with these
prophetic words:
"Although the enlightenment and liberation which had
been expected to come after the war had not come with
victory, a presage of freedom was in the air throughout these
post-war years, and it was their only historical meaning."
Perhaps these lines are relevant to what is happening
today.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A selection ofpoems by Pasternak was recently published
in the Soviet Union in an edition ofa million copies and
sold out overnight...
Some of the world's greatest poetry and novels are
best sellers in the Soviet Union. We may have problems
with food and other commodities and perhaps the quality
of life is not good, but our public is very well educated
in literature.
I hope that living standards in my country can be raised
to the same level as in the West, but I am afraid of one
thingthat my country may lose its spiritual depth and cul¬
ture. I do not want our rich past to die. I think that Unesco
has the same aim of helping cultures to survive, in small
nations as well as large.
Coidd you tell us something about your life as a poet?
I never compose poetry with a pen. I walk in the
streets, or preferably in the forest, and if I keep walking
for two hours I have one poem or two poems or three
poems, but if I walk longer I will have a longer poem.
I try to finish the piece the same day with maybe small
changes made later. Tomorrow I shall not be the same
person. The sky will not be the same colour and I shall
not be in the same mood. I love Mayakovsky but I never
write as he did... he had his notebook, he found a rhyme
and he noted it down. Even my geometric poetry is
composed in my mind. I don't know how it happens.
I like reciting my poetry. But I am not an actor and I
do not like actors reciting my poetry because they make
it too theatrical. Reciting poetry for me is not a theatrical
act but an act of creation. When I recite a poem I remember
the time when it was created and improvise the same creative
process.
I have recited my poems in Moscow stadiums to au¬
diences of up to 10,000 people. My biggest audiences num¬
bered up to 14,000 people, although actually I prefer smaller
audiences of not more than 2,000. But Moscow is not
always the capital of Soviet literature. In Novosibirsk, Omsk
and other cities I encountered the same enormous audiences
of people interested in poetrycomplex poetry, not pop
poetry.
What about the new generation of young poets?
Avant-garde literature is sweeping the Soviet Union
today. There are many groups of young poets, not only in
Moscow but in every provincial town and city.
Young writers in the Soviet Union today face two kinds
of problem. First they are starting from scratch and they
need a new coded language and this may seem primitive and
naive. Secondly, our poetry, whether it is political, mystical
or lyrical in content, tends to seem like formula poetry.
These formulas must be broken.
Can you now have unlimited contacts with the West? Do
you find any echoes in European countries or in the United
States?
I would say that intellectuals of different countries form
a sort of "common nation". Even at the worst periods in
Soviet-American relations I enjoyed very good friendships
with poets like Robert Lowell and Allen Ginsberg, and today
there is, for example, one experimental movement in San
Francisco called "language poetry", which has many contacts
with young Soviet poets who are moving in the same direc¬
tion and work in the same style. Poets of my generation
also had and continue to have good contacts with the Beat
poets, people like Allen Ginsberg, Lawrence Ferlinghetti and
Gregory Corso, but I write in a more complex manner than
theirs. I feel closer to Robert Lowell and W.H. Auden.
In other words you believe that literature is something
universal.
Yes. It is impossible to be isolated. By virtue of writing
in a given language you feel that you belong to a nation.
But besides language and national roots there is something
that all writers have in commoninspiration. Perhaps it
comes from space, perhaps it comes from God, perhaps it
is a human instinct, but one thing is certain, the source of
inspiration is common to all poets.
You were trained as an architect. Do you have a visual
approach to literature?
My poetry is visual poetry because we live in the age
of TV, an age of visual thinking, a world of pictures. In the
past grandmother told tales which began "Once upon a
time...." Today people watch before they start to listen. The
present generation likes pictures more than sounds.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
I have painted and sculpted too. As an architect I worked Jerusalem, my first visit to this holy place of the Bible,
with the Georgian artist Zurab Tseretely on a monument Jerusalem represents the Muslim, Jewish and Christian
that was built three years ago in Moscow. It is a language worlds. So many things brought together all in one place!
monument containing only letters, Russian and Georgian. And then my compatriots are very interested in Indian
It is 48 metres high and all the letters are made of metal, philosophy. I think our country is half Asian, half European.
For me this monument is both a poetic and a visual creation. It has something of both and thus brings them together.
I think literature in the next century will be visual and Perhaps our message will have some meaning for Indians
musical. Some time ago I carried out experiments with and other Asians too.
music, reciting poetry on stage and trying to put it into
musical form. Now I am thinking about the integration of Don't you think there is a contradiction here? You talk
music and poetry. I am also trying to bring visual art and about opening up to world culture, but at the same time
poetry together. nationalism is making new frontiers and building barriers
between peoples and nations.
You recently published in Yunost, a youth magazine, a This is a dialectical matter. I want my compatriots to
poem called "Rhapsody ofDisintegration" and you have have food and freedom. We were unable to solve these
said that the word "disintegration" has a very special problems in the nineteenth century, and in the twentieth
meaning at this moment in the history of the USSR. What the possibilities of doing so were blocked by Stalin. We are
did you mean by that? trying to solve these problems now, and while it is true that
I am a poet, not a politician. I sense a process but I do we are facing the problem of disintegration, the ultimate
not want to write about it as a journalist would. As a poet outcome must be a new form of integration. In the past,
I feel that many things are in the process of disintegration integration of the Russian and other nations was imposed
in the USSR and I have written a long poem in which all by force. True integration can only come about through
the words evoke disintegration; it speaks about nationalism, democratic choice, economic co-operation and cultural
political stereotypes and everything which is "disintegrat- development,
ing". The Russian word for "disintegration" is raspad and
the poem's Russian title is very musical: Rapsodia Raspada. Your country is experiencing a period of intensive cultural
For me this is a new step. The Russian public has activity. Why is poetry playing such an important part
become tired of straightforward political news. Last year in this?
the circulation of many literary magazines and newspapers Today there is an explosion of activity in literary circles,
jumped dramatically to millions of copies, but now many in poetry more than in prose. There are many small literary
of them are losing readers because they publish too much groups in all towns and cities and an enormous number of
political material. People are looking for good literature. And them in Moscow. There are some very good poets in rock
so I am writing about these processes not as a journalist but groups. Rock is very important because it is a new thing
as a poet. for us. For years it was forbidden, but now it is everywhere.
Today the Soviet people are trying to overcome the The work of the rock poets is uneven but they are certainly
tradition of slavery in which they have lived for a thousand much freer than our generation. Some groups of young poets
years and find democratic solutions. Changes are on the way. recite their work in the streets, especially in Moscow's first
I am trying to help this process by persistently provoking pedestrian street, the Arbat. They produce what I call "im-
people to free themselves from the stereotypes which have mediate poetry" and sell their poems to the public for three
endured for so long in my country. roubles, sometimes even for one. All this now seems to be
My message is not only for my compatriots. I am trying a part of our life. I want them to experiment more, hoping
to find an international symbolism. I have just been to that it will lead to something really great...
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Apparition II, oil on canvas (162x130 cm) by the French artist Benn (1905-1989)
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
R
I
N ancient Greece, strangers were thought to enjoy divine protection and
were received accordingly. In rural India today, they can still count on a
welcome fit for the gods. Among the Bedouin of the desert, they are sheltered
and protected by their host and all his clan.
From time immemorial people have felt a sacred obligation to share their
bread and salt with the passing stranger. The visitor would be invited to sit
down at the fireside or in the shade of the veranda and offered a lodging for
the night. At a time when they were not protected by law, travellers could,
thanks to the conventions of hospitality, find shelter in a house or community
not their own. In deserts, mountains, steppeland and other regions where
climate and nature were hostile, hospitality could even mean the difference
between life and death.
With the development of long-distance trade, travel and exchange, hospitality
was extended to pilgrims, merchants and diplomats. Great travellers such as
Marco Polo and Ibn Battuta recorded many examples of the generous
hospitality without which their epic journeys across Europe, Africa and Asia
would have been impossible.
What is left today of the hospitable traditions of olden times? In an age of
mass tourism when travel has become a routine matter, a sense of conviviality
doubtless still survives the stresses of big city life where living space is often
in short supply. But above all, hospitality today tends to be more impersonal
and anonymous than in the past. It has even become a matter for legislation.
Bilateral treaties and international conventions define the status of foreigners
and safeguard their person and their rights.
In theory, time-honoured traditions of hospitality are being interwoven with
new values of liberty and democracy. In practice, however, strangers and
foreigners are still all too often the victims of incomprehension and contempt
from their "host" societies. Racial or national prejudices weigh, sometimes
heavily, on those who are today known as "immigrants". It may thus be timely
to recall, as we do in the following pages, some traditions of the hospitality
which was once such a widespread virtue and again awaits recognition as an
expression of tolerance and solidarity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Islands of welcome in
a sea of sand
BY JOSEPH CHELHOD
The master of a Qur'anic
school traces in the
sand the greeting "Salvation
be with you".
JL HERE are two sides to hospitality. In a general
sense, it is part and parcel of the ceremonial and
social activities of each people. More specifically,
it creates a special relationship between host and
guest. Among the Bedouin, who are a byword
for hospitality, guests are placed under the pro¬
tection of their hosts and thereby acquire con¬
siderable rights in accordance with the desert code
of honour. Starting as a simple act of generosity
that consists in looking after someone for a short
time, hospitality thus becomes an institution that
confers almost sacred privileges on the stranger
who is welcomed into one's home.
The Bedouin are not of course the only
people to accord a special status to guests. The
French historian Fustel de Coulanges noted in his
La cité antique (1864), a study of the part played
by religion in the history of Greece and Rome,
that food prepared on an altar and shared among
several persons established an indissoluble union
between themthe stranger who partook of the
meal became a member of the religious commu¬
nity. But the traditional hospitality of the desert
Arabs has wider implications, both in
theory and in practice. A mere glass of water in
which a stranger has simply moistened his lips
gives him the same privileges as a sumptuous
feast. The reason is that the difficulty of surviving
in the parched lands where the Bedouin live has
created a sense of solidarity and replaced anarchy
with a number of beneficent institutions, one of
which is hospitality. Through the gift of food a
stranger to the region can travel in the desert as
freely as the indigenous population.
The first rule of Arab hospitality is that it is
offered free, even if it is provided for several days.
The host would feel offended if he were offered 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
anything in return. But this is not the most im¬
portant feature of Arab hospitality. A set of rules
governs the behaviour of both host and guest.
The first sign of hospitality,
a good campfire
that burns all night long
The desert poets are unstinting in their praise of
those who lavish attention on their visitors and
make sure that they lack nothing. But what they
admire above all is not so much the abundance
or daintiness of the feast offered to the guest,
although these are fully appreciated, as the way
in which the guest is received. Excellent hospi¬
tality must have a tangible and visible form. Its
first sign is a good campfire, which the master
of the tent keeps going all night so that travellers
seeking shelter will know that a welcome awaits
them. The fire must blaze so that it can be seen
from afar. A generous host makes a second fire
on a hilltop which lights up the desert like a light¬
house in an ocean of sand.
Harsh words are reserved for those who,
through avarice, let their fire go out, deliberately
extinguish it or prevent it from being seen so as
to discourage visitors. If the servant responsible
for keeping the fire alight falls asleep and lets it
go out, the watchdog must take over and bark
so that travellers know where to find the tent.
Poets commend the qualities of such dogs whose
barking attracts visitors. Yet sometimes even the
silence of dogs can be favourably interpreted as
evidence of the extreme hospitality of masters
who receive guests so often that their dogs no
longer bark, "indifferent to the approaching
shadow" as one desert poet has put it.
But of course it falls primarily to the master
of the tent to prove himself a worthy host. As
soon as a visitor is announced, he rushes forward
to invite him before the other members of the
group. A smile on his lips, the host proffers greet¬
ings and words of welcome. He must not ask the
visitor his name nor try to find out the purpose
of his journey or how long he intends to stay.
The only questions he can ask concern his guest's
comfort. He must also make the visitor feel at
home and be attentive and thoughtful, anxious
to satisfy his every desire. The guest is invited to
partake of a meal. The host waits upon him,
without touching the food, encouraging his guest
to eat, selecting the tastiest morsels for him,
unwilling to leave him until such time as he
expresses a desire to sleep. Every effort must be
made to ensure that a guest leaves the clan fully
satisfied with the hospitality he has received.
When a host wishes to show his esteem for
a guest, he slaughters a camel in his honour. The
importance he attaches to the guest is reflected
in the size of the chosen animal, and much is
made of the size of the pots in which the food
is cooked. It would be most improper to kill a
chicken, although farming people often do so.
Only an animal of at least the size of a sheep is
considered satisfactory. If a second important
guest arrives, another animal is sacrificed. Blood
must be shed, since it will be used to mark the
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Bedouin hospitality
*Fathallah Sayigh, "Memoirs",
an Arabic dialect manuscript
preserved in the Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris. It was pur¬
chased by the French poet
Alphonse de Lamartine during
his travels in Syria in 1832. A
French translation was pub¬
lished in vol. IV of Lamartine's
Voyage en Orient (1832-1833).
traveller's horse or camel with the distinctive, sign
of the clan that has welcomed him.
Nevertheless, the amount of food provided
is not a criterion of hospitality, which is particu¬
larly appreciated when the person offering it is
not well-to-do. Giving what one has and depriv¬
ing oneself, and even one's family, is the golden
rule of Arab hospitality. Théodore Lascaris, an
emissary of Napoleon, and his Syrian dragoman
Fathallah Sayigh were given shelter by a poor old
widow of the Sardiyya Bedouin in Jordan, who
slaughtered her one and only sheep in their
honour. "Grandmother," they said to her, "why
such waste?" To which she replied: "If you en¬
tered the dwelling of a living person and did not
find hospitality there, it would be as though you
had paid a visit to the dead."*
A guest of the Bedouin is at once
a prince, a prisoner and a poet
The Arab poets who have so effusively sung the
praises of the perfect host say almost nothing
about the guest, considering him to have no more
than a passive, secondary role. In fact, the con¬
duct of the guest is also specifically governed by
the desert code of honour.
He who receives hospitality, say the Bedouin,
is at once an emir, a prisoner and a poet. He is
above all a prince, for he is entitled to every con¬
sideration; but in return he must behave as befits
one who is under an obligation. It is interesting
to note that the verb adàfa, to extend hospitality,
also means to add, to annex, to bind. He who is
received is a prisoner of him who receives as he
must comply in every respect with the instruc¬
tions of his host. In particular, he must occupy
the place assigned to him, be of pleasant disposi¬
tion, not raise his voice and gratefully accept
whatever is offered, even if it is no more than
a bowl of curds. To refuse a specially prepared
dish is to be suspected of harbouring hostile feel¬
ings towards one's host. It is incumbent on the
guest to respect the dwelling into which he is
received, to show deference towards the women
and to refrain from any misdeed. Once he has
taken his leave of the clan, his behaviour will be
that of a poet: wherever he goes he will sing the
praises of the house where he has been given
hospitality and will testify to the consideration
shown to him.
He who commits a culpable act such as theft,
attempted seduction, or lying, violates the rules
of hospitality and is dishonoured for ever. To em¬
phasize the seriousness of the deed, the master
of the tent seizes the dish in which the meal was 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
JOSEPH CHELHOD,
Syrian-born French
sociologist and
anthropologist, is honorary
director of research at
France's National Centre
for Scientific Research
(CNRS). He has published
over a hundred scientific
papers and a number of
books, including a three-
volume study of the history
and civilization of southern
Arabia (1984-1985,
Maisonneuve et Larose
publishers, Paris).
14
served, makes a hole in it and sends it to the clan
of the offending guest. By this symbolic act he
makes it known that the sacred laws of hospitality
have been violated. Henceforth the culprit is
treated with contempt. His testimony is refused,
his company forsaken and every door is closed
to him.
Arab hospitality makes for a special relation¬
ship between host and guest, entailing duties and
rights. It is these legal implications that are its
hallmark.
He who receives hospitality becomes an
inviolable, near-sacred being whom the host,
together with all the members of his family and
indeed of his tribe, is required to protect. The
guest must not be abandoned or delivered into
the hands of his enemies, and no one is allowed to
take revenge on him for a crime committed be¬
fore he was admitted into the tent. What is more,
the host still bears responsibility for his guest even
after he has left the camp. So long as the bread
and salt received in the tent are in the guest's
stomach, he is entitled to the protection of the
person who has given him shelter, unless in the
meantime he has received hospitality elsewhere.
This is what the Bedouin call "the right of salt".
It provides the traveller with a kind of safe-
conduct allowing him to travel freely and without
fear in the lands subject to the jurisdiction of the
host clan or of those who owe allegiance to that
clan or have friendly relations with it.
Hospitality thus begets three fundamental
rights, any infringement of which requires repa¬
ration: the right of the dwelling whose immunity
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
has been violated, the right of the host whose
honour has been outraged, and the right of salt
which has not been respected. Reparation, which
is always substantial, is out of proportion to the
offence, which may be insignificant: wounding
words, a disagreeable allusion, an invidious
gesture. Reparation lies wholly with the guest
who must proclaim in three different dwellings,
holding a white banner in his hand, that the
honour of the master of the tent is intact and that
"his face is white".
Of course city-dwellers and country folk also
welcome strangers, but where they are concerned
the duties of hospitality do not extend beyond
the rules of courtesy. In Arab towns and cities
no particular privilege or right accrues from the
fact of sitting together around the same table.
The delicate art
of pouring mint tea
Many are the occasions when an Arab invites his
friends and neighbours to honour his table: a mar¬
riage, a birth, a circumcision (or baptism in the
case of Christians), a pilgrim's return, the New
Year, religious celebrations or anniversaries. But
this kind of hospitality has little to do with
customary rules of behaviour. It is a matter of
social etiquette and neither rights nor duties are
involved.
The customary rules of desert hospitality
now seem to be dying out, even among the
Bedouin whose numbers are steadily shrinking.
With the possible exception of one indomitable
group living on the edge of the Rub'-al-Khâli,
the Bedouin world will soon be no more than
a memory.
The desert is being conquered by mechani¬
zation and the dromedary is being ousted by the
jeep. Arab hospitality, ever generous and courte¬
ous, is suffering the consequences. Hotels and
stopovers are replacing the black tent of
yesteryear, symbol of a time that regrettably is
no more. Something nevertheless lingers on.
Mindful still of pomp and ceremonial, which in
his mind are indissociable from hospitality, the
Arab will always be concerned about the "white¬
ness of his face", which he would be afraid of
losing if he did not extend the warmest possible
welcome to his guest.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
%**
sV?
"
1
o o
»i«
¿EK?
^ílfet-
A/p i
'
-
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Ä desire to receive guests'
BY GEORGES LISOWSKI
ELOSPITALITY seems to be a virtueif that is
the right word to describe itmore natural to a
rural than to an urban civilization; and the Slavs
of today are still very close to the rural civiliza¬
tion that their ancestors and even their parents
knew.
In the city, asking for hospitality is begging,
asking for charity. Why should a person ask
hospitality from, say, the tenants of the apart¬
ment on the second floor, right, rather than from
those of the third floor, left, or, indeed, from
either of them, rather than go to the hotel oppo¬
site? In the countryside where inns are rare and
journeys are long, requests for hospitality seem
much more natural.
Since the beginning of this century we have
lost all sense of distance. Space probes travel for
years at thousands of kilometres an hour to take
photographs of distant planets, and it is hard for
us to imagine that at the beginning of the century,
before the advent of the automobile, a day's jour¬
ney was 40 kilometres. During my childhood, be¬
fore the Second World War, this was still the case
in eastern Poland. The nearest railway station was
80 kilometres away and, more often than not, the
ancient bus would be under repair. It is in this
context that Slav traditions of hospitality should
be seen.
'Guests are like fish...'
In the Linde, the venerable dictionary of the
Polish language, the word "hospitality" (goscin-
nose) is defined delightfully and somewhat naively
as "a desire to receive guests". It is a pretty con¬
ceit, is it not, the idea of a pleasure that one gives
oneself, of a desire that one satisfies by being of
service to others? This desire, however, was quite
understandable in view of the relative isolation
in which people lived, the boredom of their
dreary autumn evenings and their curiosity about
what was going on in the world at large. Visits
were not limited to an hour or two, as they were
in town. After spending a day getting to your
neighbour's house, you would generally stay for
two or three days, sometimes longer, despite the
Latin saying that has become proverbial in some
European languages: "Guests are like fish, after
three days they stink".
Hospitality of this kind presupposes a certain
Music-making in the home of
a Polish peasant family
about 50 years ago \ 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
level of affluence. Practised between people of
the same social standing, it was a phenomenon
limited to a particular class and smacked more
of sophisticated social intercourse than of charity.
The Poland of old, of the days before the parti¬
tions, claimed to be "a republic of nobles". Un¬
like the other European feudal societies, Poland
had an unusually high proportion of minor
nobles. The higher aristocracy was very limited
in numberapart from those of a few great
princely families, all other titles such as count,
marquis, baron or margrave were imported from
abroadbut the nobility nevertheless accounted
for about 10 per cent of the population and
provided the electoral support of the various great
aristocratic families.
Cutting a dash
All these petty squires, however, considered
themselves to be the equals of the king. At times
they were barely distinguishable from their
peasant neighbours, yet even the most im¬
poverished of them nurtured the highest ambi¬
tions. The snobbery of this social class and its
attachment to appearances have had a marked in¬
fluence, right up to today, on its more or less
direct successor, the Polish intelligentsia.
The virtue of hospitality was cultivated with
fervour in the country residences, the manor
houses and modest country seats of this petty
A farmhouse in the Tatra
Mountains, southern Poland.
Interior of a farmhouse in
Little Poland.
GEORGES LISOWSKI,
of Poland, is a literary
critic, translator and
director of the literary
review Tivorczosc. He has
translated many works of
modern French literature
into Polish and is currently
completing a bi-lingual
(Polish/French) anthology
of poetry in 4 volumes, 2 of
which have been published
by Czytelnik, Warsaw.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Members of an aristocratic
family photographed with
some of their staff outside a
manor near Cracow.
nobility. It was a hospitality which sometimes
reached embarrassing levels. It was not unknown
for the wheels of the coaches in which the guests
had arrived to be removed and hidden in. out¬
houses so that it was impossible for them to leave.
On special occasionsthat is to say, not only at
baptisms, weddings and burials but also during
visits of guests, whether planned or unexpected
the normally frugal way of life gave way to the
heights of extravagance.
Appearances were what mattered! A well-
known Polish saying, still current today, might
be translated as "Run up debts, but show that you
can". On festive occasions people ate and drank
until they were fit to burst.
Poles still often like to provide hospitality be¬
yond their means. An English journalist who
visited Poland a few years ago summed up his im¬
pressions in these words: "In my country, the
shops are full and there are no shortages, but
when you visit people, the table is bare. In your
country, there is a crisis and everything is in short
supply, but when you go visiting, the tables are
groaning with food." Run up debts, but show
that you can!
To be fair, Slav hospitality is not just a matter
of feasting and is not only inspired by curiosity
about the local news. It is heartfelt, truly cordial,
perhaps a little naive and conventional, but totally
sincere. Give an honest answer to a Frenchman
who asks "Comment allez-vous?", or to an
Englishman who says "How do you do?" and
they will both be terribly embarrassed. A Slav
will be equally embarrassed if you reply to his
query about your health with a conventional "ça
or "fine".va
The third time
of asking
Slav hospitality is highly ceremonious. It is not
enough for the hosts to place everything available
in the house on the table and for the guests to
set about these offerings eagerly. The hosts must
insist several times that the guests help themselves
to what is offered. The guests, in their turn, must
politely refuse at least three times. This routine
must be followed so as to demonstrate the sin¬
cerity of the hosts and the good manners of the
guests.
The hold of this ceremonial is still strong
today, even within families. When my father used
to dine with me, he would be quite prepared to
go to bed hungry if I did not insist strongly
enough that he should eat. Eventually it became
a joke. "Don't stand on ceremony in my house!"
"But I'm not standing on ceremony." "All right,
then, one, two, three, I insist three times that you
take some more." "No, no, no, I couldn't", he
would reply before helping himself to some food
which he obviously wanted. Even with his own
son, the custom was too strong for him. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
African
20
This extravagant, at times wearisome, Slav
hospitality shows tinges of oriental influences.
Oriental hospitality, based on religious prohibi¬
tions, is less convivial and has a certain aggres¬
sive quality. While he is under your roof, the
guest is free to do as he pleases, even to the extent,
so it is said, of taking your wife or your daughter
to his beda form of hospitality that I have never
sampled; but once he has stepped outside your
door, you are at liberty to murder him in cold
blood.
I once had a taste of oriental hospitality in
Georgia. It was truly phenomenal. On the first
day, sated, replete, made much of, you feel that
you are in paradise. On the second day, you are
still in paradise, but you say to yourself that if
things go on like this they will finish you off. On
the third, there are no two ways about iteither
you leave or you've had it.
A Danish welcome
The most moving experience of hospitality I have
ever had, however, occurred neither in a Slav
country nor in the Orient, but in Copenhagen.
I arrived there one Saturday, just before midnight,
on the eve of a big football match between
Malmö and Copenhagen. Half Sweden had
arrived on the ferry and not even the smallest
broom-cupboard was available in any of the
hotels. The tourist officeopen at midnight-
had compiled a list of addresses of families
who had offered to put up visitors with nowhere
to go.
I ended up at about one o'clock in the
morning in the home of people who had risen
from their beds, run me a bath and placed sand¬
wiches on the table for me, to the accompaniment
of great gestures of friendshipand all this
without a word being exchanged, since they knew
none of the languages in which I could manage
a few stumbling phrases. I stayed with them for
two days and, when the time came for me to
leave, they got together a few friends to give a
party in my honour, still communicating with
sign language, since their friends were no better
linguists than they were. They refused to let me
pay for the room and I had to go back to the
tourist office and leave the money there. Yet no
one ever talks about Danish hospitality. Now I
have tried to make amends. Forty years later I
have repaid my debt.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
hospitality - a dying tradition?
BY BABACAR FALL
t
SOLIDARITY is a salient characteristic of tradi¬
tional African societies even though they are
organized into hierarchies in which everyone's
place is determined by social status. Solidarity
unites families linked by ties of blood, as well as
groups living in the same area, belonging to the
same village community, and sharing the same
system of values.
But this solidarity may also be extended to
persons outside the group or community. It
fosters mobility and offers an opportunity to
develop sociability. This is why, throughout
Africa, strangers are treated with respect and
courtesy. The old folk say that the true griot*
is the stranger who later praises his host's family
to the skies.
A hearty welcome beneath
the palaver tree
Among the Baulé of Côte d'Ivoire strangers are
warmly welcomed without any questions being
asked about the purpose of their visit. Hospitality
is discreet, salutations courteous: "Welcome, here
you are at home". A seat is offered, and water
in a coconut shell. After the visitor has had time
to relax and recover from the strain of the jour¬
ney, the head of the family invites him to eat.
Seated in the open air or on the veranda, the guest
is asked to dip his hand into a dish of yams and
okra sauce. More dishes follow: chicken, walnut
sauce and other specialities.
The meal is followed by a rest in the court¬
yard or in the main room of the dwelling. Palm
wine is served, conversation starts up and be¬
comes animated, words flow spontaneously. Para¬
bles, tales, proverbs and legends enliven the
conversation in a cheerful atmosphere which
helps the guest to feel really at home.
The visitor is then taken for a stroll through
the village where he is welcomed by the chief or
one of the notables with mock solemnity,
Musicians prepare to welcome visitors outside the
sultan's palace at Agadez (Niger). 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
beneath the palaver tree. He is offered another
jar of palm wine, a sign of the high esteem in
which he is held. The jar is handed around so that
everyone can be associated with the welcome
extended to the guest.
In the Sahel, hospitality is
a family affair
The hospitality of the Sahelians is even more
effusive. Because of the inadequacy or absence of
communication facilities in the Sahel, visitors
always arrive unannounced. But as soon as they
are sighted, people go to meet them. After a
joyful and spontaneous exchange of greetings and
hugs, they are relieved of their bags. Children are
the first to honour this tradition.
This lengthy exchange of greetings is charac¬
teristic of Sahelian cultures. For some Tukulor
or Wolof peoples the act of salutation is the first
and most noble form of courtesy, giving immedi¬
ate cheer and inspiring the greatest friendship. Ac¬
cording to one saying, it is even compulsory to
greet an enemy, since greeting others properly
is an indication of one's own self-esteem.
In the early 1940s, a Dakar student wrote the
following description of the welcome extended
to a visitor by the people of Baol, in central
Senegal: "The guest is received in the hut of his
closest kin. He is given the place of honour,
which is in the middle of the bed. Friends and
relatives have to be introduced and, sitting on
mats, they engage the newcomer in conversation.
One of the daughters of the house offers him cool
water and, if the guest has arrived on horseback,
a young man takes care of his animal. During this
time a slave brings water in a jar, which is placed
within the enclosure where shortly afterwards the
visitor goes and washes himself." When a guest
was fully rested, he was offered two kola nuts,
one red and the other white, so that he could
choose according to his preference.
In fact, hospitality is nearly always a family
affair in the broad sense. The guest is welcomed
by everyone. He is then looked after by people
of his own age. As soon as his arrival is an¬
nounced, members of his age-group make con¬
tact with him at his host's dwelling. As words
of greeting lead on to conversation, the chain of
friendship grows longer. At mealtime dishes are
sent to him and he is invited in turn to visit each
of his new friends. He is expected to show that
he has eaten well, failing which he is liable to be
severely reproached for behaving "like a
stranger". These receptions give rise to some com¬
petition between families. Every effort is made
to please the guest, who responds courteously to
all these attentions. In addition he distributes pro¬
visions of his own, usually produce from home.
At whatever time the visitor arrives, he is
always offered something to eat so that he can
restore his strength after the journey. If the head
of the family is rich he shows his guest how
happy he is to receive him by offering him an
animal (a sheep or a goat) which will be sacrificed
and prepared in his honour.
'On the third day,
give him a tool'
Among the Tukulor, a hospitable people who
live in the Senegal river basin, guests are sheltered
and fed as well as possible, provided that they do
not outstay their welcome. The Tukolor put into
practice a dictum set forth by former Tanzanian
president Julius Nyerere: "When a stranger ar¬
rives, feed him for two days; on the third day,
give him a tool." This rule being generally un¬
derstood and accepted, abuses are rare.
The length of the stay usually depends on the
age of the guest and the nature of his visit, and
varies from a week to a month. Preparations are
then made for the return journey. The day of
departure is set after lengthy negotiations.
Portrait of a Wolof griot by
the Senegalese painter Gora
M'Bengue
Below left, preparing rice for
a festive occasion
Below, villagers of the Côte
d'lvoire's Yakuba people
watch a ritual dance.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
"4 !*.*-.- /
^ÄJK.-
a4 palaver at Bardai, an
oasis in the Tibesti region of
northern Chad
BABACAR FALL,
of Senegal, teaches at the
Cheik Anta Diop
University, Dakar.
Provisions are collected together along with gifts
and messages for the traveller and for relatives
living in his village. The departure is marked by
ceremonial. The marabout is consultedsome
days are auspicious, others are not. Wednesdays
and Fridays are often avoided.
Dying traditions
But traditions of hospitality are dying out as a
result of growing urbanization. Neighbourliness
is less common, and outside their home area
strangers encounter greater difficulties.
Modernization is playing havoc with the pat¬
terns of community life. African cities are ex¬
panding considerably as a result of population
growth, but also because of a nonstop exodus
from the rural areas. Individualism is prevailing
over community spirit.
For a number of reasons, the extended family
is gradually breaking up and giving way to the
nuclear family. This loosening of the bonds of
kinship tends to lead to "me first" attitudes and,
with the economic crisis also playing a part,
generosity and open-handedness are dying out.
Africans living outside their own countries
are often the hardest hit. Foreigners are increas¬
ingly accused of responsibility for the problems
besetting some countries that are labouring under
economic difficulties. Sometimes people from
neighbouring countries are subjected to mass
expulsions.
Yet hospitality, which was once universally
respected, was one of the founding ideals of
African unity in the wake of independence. On
the basis of these traditions of hospitality, the
African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights
provides for the protection of the nationals of
other countries. Article 12 thus stipulates that "A
non-national legally admitted in a territory of a
state party to the present Charter may only be
expelled from it by virtue of a decision taken in
accordance with the law". Paragraph 5 of that
article declares that: "The mass expulsion of non-
nationals shall be prohibited."
Unfortunately, these provisions have on
occasion been violated. Nationalism in the
narrow sense militates against the values of toler¬
ance, openness and self-respect that have since
time immemorial characterized relations with
those who came from afar in the hope of being
given a welcome such as they might find in their
own homes. Is this waning of the traditions of
hospitality symptomatic of a crisis in society?
*In the Sudano-Sahelian area, the griot is both a troubadour,
a bringer of news and a witness to the present and to the past. 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
ÄF»
«ft
i^irr**"^
HS
Y>\.
^
«
***
" v"
'
é
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
fe ;
:-7TBY
'a^Mi
. . ¡Rr
1 ^i
¿ML
ir ' ¡ ;
:>
;Ä
>*»
z
r«*.
Where
'foreigner'
means
'guest'
BY ANDRÉ KÉDROS
XEARS ago, a French friend of mine told me of
a memorable experience he once had while on
holiday in the Péloponnèse.
"I was on my way to the Taiyetos Moun¬
tains," he said. "The sun was setting when my
car broke down near a remote and poor village.
Cursing my misfortune, I was wondering where
I was going to spend the night when I realized
that the villagers who had gathered around me
were vehemently arguing as to who should have
the honour of receiving me as a guest in their
house. Finally, thinking that I would cause less
disturbance to her than I would to a man with
a family, I accepted the offer of an old peasant
woman who lived alone in a little house sur¬
rounded by a courtyard at the edge of the village.
While she was getting me settled into a tiny but
clean and freshly whitewashed room, the mayor
of the village was hitching up his mule to my car
to haul it to a small town some 20 kilometres
away where there was a garage.
"I had noticed three hens running free in my
hostess's courtyard and that night one of them
ended up in a stew on my table. Other villagers
brought me goat's cheese, figs and honey, and,
of course, some ouzo. I ate with a hearty appe¬
tite and, despite my ignorance of the language,
we drank together and made merry till far into
the night. The following day, the garage man
brought back my car which he had patched up.
The engine seemed to be running as well as ever.
He presented me with a very reasonable bill and
with a request that I should drop him off at his
home town on my way.
"When the time came for me to say good¬
bye to my friends in the village, I wanted to
A typical springtime landscape in the Péloponnèse.
Inset, polychrome earthenware relief of Odysseus and
Penelope (5th century BC).
;.
**-?3«
~ Cue
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Acropolis of Athens
(1877) by the French painter
Marcel Lambert (1847-1928).
The work is an imaginary
recreation of the west façade
of the Acropolis as it was at
the time of Pericles (5th
century BC).
reward the old woman for the trouble to which
I had put her and for the hen she had sacrificed
for me. She refused the money I offered with loud
cries of indignation. The more I insisted, the more
vexed she appeared. I too was embarrassed and
upset. I still am. Do you think I should send her
a present from Paris?"
"Do nothing of the kind," I said. "Greek
hospitality is not for sale."
Homeric times
Greek hospitality is part of a long tradition. In
Homeric times it was considered a sacred duty.
When Telemachus left Ithaca in secret in search
of Odysseus, he and his companions were greeted
on the shore at Pylos by Nestor and his sons who
were celebrating the festival of Poseidon. They
were immediately invited to join in the festivi¬
ties. Not until they had eaten and rested did
Nestor declare: "Only now that they have tasted
the pleasures of food is it fitting to ask the
strangers who they are."
Telemachus and his men enjoyed similar dis¬
creet hospitality from the hands of Menelaus. On
learning that Telemachus was the son of his
former brother-in-arms, the king showered him
with sumptuous gifts. These Telemachus refused,
but in the end, so as not to offend his host, he
accepted a silver vase and a scarf woven by Helen.
Meanwhile, Odysseus himself, having braved
the tempest brought down upon him by his
sworn enemy, Poseidon, was cast ashore on the
island of Scheria, naked and with nothing to
indicate who he was. Nevertheless, he was
received with great courtesy by Nausicaa and her
father Alcinous, king of the Phaeacians, who
promised him a ship to take him home even
before Odysseus had made himself known. It was
only after the bard Demodocus had greatly
moved him by singing of the Trojan horse that
Odysseus disclosed his identity and told his hosts
of his adventures and his wanderings.
Landing at Ithaca, where suitors were laying
siege to the virtuous Penelope and squandering
his wealth, Odysseus, aided by the goddess
Athena, disguised himself as a beggar and, in ac¬
cordance with the laws of hospitality, was
received at the palace. He was treated with scorn
by the suitors, but Penelope made ready to wash
his feet. This Odysseus refused to allow and the
task was undertaken by his old nurse Euryclea
who, as she did so, recognized her master by an
old scar from his boyhood.
The Golden Age of Athens
During the fifth century BC, free citizens and
slaves accounted for only half the population of
Athens. The remainder were foreigners. Most of
these "immigrant" Athenians were Greeks from
elsewhere, but they included many Phoenicians,
Phrygians, Egyptians and Scythians. They were
not fully-fledged citizens and could neither be
elected to the Assembly nor become judges. In
other words, they took no direct part in the
political affairs of the city.
Nevertheless, their presence was more than
% Irw
i -r
26
i
FAÇa\CE
RESTAVF
II 0$
'
*Mfc*>w.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
merely tolerated and they enjoyed considerable
rights. Businessmen and craftsmen were allowed
to set up shop and to employ workers or slaves.
Armourers such as Cephalos and bankers such
as Lysias both natives of Syracusepainters like
Polygnotus of Thasos and doctors like Hippo¬
crates of Cos, professors of oratory such as Pro¬
tagoras of Thrace and Gorgias of Sicily, were all
free to exercise their professions without hin¬
drance and to enjoy the prestige that their excel¬
lence merited. As Pericles proudly boasted to
Thucydides: "Our city is open to all. No laws
keep foreigners away or exclude them from the
education or the entertainments available here."
This is all the more understandable since Pericles
himself had Anaxagoras of Clazomenae as his
counsellor and the renowned Aspasia of Miletus
as his mistress.
The Greek tradition of hospitality, and the
spirit of tolerance that went with it, continued
down the centuries, to be found in other guises
in the Middle Ages in the Byzantine empire.
Foreigners who abused
their privileges
To build Constantinople, the emperor Constan-
tine called in 40,000 German workers. When the
task was completed, these foreign workers were
granted the right to remain and gradually merged
into the local population. The same was true of
the Goths, Vandals, Armenians, Persians, Moors
and Ethiopians who had served in Justinian's
army. In the tenth century, the ranks of the im¬
perial armies were full of Russians, Scandinavians,
Khazars, Petchenegs, Georgians andafter the
Battle of Hastings and the conquest of England
by the NormansAnglo-Saxons. Most of these
mercenaries finally settled in Byzantium. Under
the Comnenian dynasty (1081-1180), all these
foreigners, almost equal in numbers to the original
Greeks, had become completely assimilated, a fact
that can only be explained by the enduring Greek
tradition of hospitality.
Some foreigners were, unfortunately, to
abuse that hospitality. From the time of the First
Crusade, Bohemond and his men, who had asked
Alexius Comnenus for the right of passage
through Asia Minor, behaved with callous lack
of restraint in Constantinople. Alexius' daughter
Anne relates in her memoirs how they would
burst into the palace at all hours and how the em¬
peror did nothing to restrain them for fear that
they would attack his people and damage his
property. Later, the Byzantine capital was sacked
by the unbridled soldiery of the Fourth Crusade.
Venice too became involved in these scan¬
dalous abuses. To reward the Venetians for
having helped him in his struggle with the
Telemachus lands on
Calypso's island. Engraving
from an 18th<entury edition
o/Télémaque, a romance by
the French bishop Fénelon
(1651-1715) which is based
on the adventures of
Telemachus in search of his
father, Odysseus.
ANDRÉ KÉDROS
is a Greek author who
writes in French. He has
published thirteen novels,
which have been translated
into as many languages, and
several historical essays
including a study of the
Greek Resistance from 1940
to 1944 (1956, Robert
Laffont publishers, Paris).
Normans, Alexius Comnenus had allowed them
to set up trading centres in certain districts of
Constantinople. Showing scant respect for the
duties they owed in return for the hospitality
offered to them and relying on the naval might
of their native city, the Venetians in Byzantium
soon established a state within a state. The Com-
nenians tried to get rid of them by playing on
the rivalries between Venice, Genoa and Pisa. The
remedy, however, proved worse than the disease.
The Pisans and the Genoese extorted similar ex¬
orbitant privileges from the Comnenians, and
rivalled the Venetians in their arrogance.
Byzantium's over-generous hospitality cer¬
tainly appears to have precipitated the empire's
decline. To open one's doors to the foreigner may
be a virtue, but it should not be done indiscrimin¬
ately. Hospitality may cost you dear when the
foreigner takes advantage of it to place a knife
at your throat.
After the fall of Constantinople, in 1453, 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
..tt-*^ >, w OS
Greece suffered four centuries of Turkish occu¬
pation. Throughout this period the Greeks of the
mountains offered refuge to "Klephts" (thieves)
when they were pursued by the authorities. These
Klephts were, in fact, members of the resistance
fighting the army of occupation. The hospitality
they were thus given was strongly coloured by
a sense of national solidarity and a deep longing
for liberty.
During the Second World War, the nazis
responded to mass demonstrations (such as that
during which the ministry of labour was stormed,
forcing Hitler to abandon the idea of imposing
forced labour on the Greeks) by sealing off whole
districts and making police round-ups. Thousands
of resistance fighters were saved on these occa¬
sions by slipping through doors opportunely
opened by friends, who would take them in and
shelter them.
The fall of Mussolini also gave rise to a
number of hospitable actions. Many Italian
officers and soldiers, themselves former occupiers
of Greece, decided to make a break with Hitler's
forces. They deserted and were hunted down by
the nazis and in some cases massacred. Overlook¬
ing the fact that the Italians had been their ene¬
mies during the Albanian war and had often
treated them with brutal repression, the Greeks
hid them and provided them with civilian cloth¬
ing and with food. Thanks to this hospitality,
thousands of Italians managed to survive until the
liberation.
Even today, the Greek word "xenos" means
both "foreigner" and "guest".
í^i'A;
£ S»5
%i
Time-honoured mode of transport on the
Greek island of Hydra
if ' ' '%V * if
28 &
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Krupa Sindhu and
BY PRAFULLA MOHANTI
the beggar
HeLoSPITALITY is natural in my village. Guests
arrive at any time of the day or night and they
are always welcome. Nobody asks them "Why
have you come?" or "How long are you going
to stay?". They become a part of the family.
Providing hospitality for strangers is a
religious act. A stranger should never leave the
village »displeased. Who knows, he may be
Vishnu, God the Preserver, in disguise.
Stories are told to children to teach them to
be kind and hospitable to strangers: "Once upon
a time there was a Brahmin. His name was Krupa
Sindhu. He was married, but had no children. He
was kind, religious, and so generous that he gave
all his wealth away to the poor. A time came
when he and his wife had nothing to eat.
"One day his wife said, 'We have no relatives.
You must ask a friend to help, otherwise how
can we manage? There's no food in the house.'
"Krupa Sindhu replied, 'I have a friend who
could help us but he lives in a distant place. If
I went to see him he might solve our problem.'
"It was decided that Krupa Sindhu would
visit his friend. His wife borrowed some rice from
a neighbour's house and she made ten pithas (rice
cakes). She divided them into two equal portions,
one for her husband to eat on his journey and
one for herself.
"Lord Vishnu knew this. To test the Brahmin
couple's devotion he came to their house
disguised as an old man. 'I haven't eaten anything
for many days,' he said in a trembling voice.
'Please give me something to eat.'
"When the Brahmin couple looked at him
their hearts were filled with compassion. They
felt it was their duty to look after the stranger.
They invited him into their house as their guest
and the Brahmin's wife gave her portion of the
pithas to the old man to eat.
"Lord Vishnu knew there were only ten
pithas in Krupa Sindhu's house and that his wife
had given him her portion. He wanted to test the
hospitality of the Brahmin couple further, so he
asked for more.
"The Brahmin's wife gave him Krupa
Sindhu's portion and Lord Vishnu ate one more
pitha. That left four which the Brahmin's wife
kept for her husband's journey, and they both
went without food.
"Lord Vishnu was pleased with their
devotion but wanted to test them even further.
'I'm so weak, I have no strength to walk. Can
I spend the night in your house?' he asked.
"Without hesitation they offered the old man
shelter for the night and gave him the remaining
iour pithas for his supper. They only drank water.
"During the night they discussed the
problems of the old man. 'He's so old and weak,
if we had enough money and food we could keep
him in our house and nurse him.'
"Lord Vishnu knew what the Brahmin
couple were saying and blessed them. In the
morning when Krupa Sindhu and his wife got up
they were amazed. Their mud house had changed
into a palace and the old man had disappeared.
They realized what had happened and knelt
down to pray to Lord Vishnu for his kindness."
Money is only the means to an end. Life ends
at Baikuntha, the Land of the Gods. Everybody
wants to go there but only those with punya
(piety) succeed. There is a saying in the state of
Orissa:
Dhana arjane dharma kari
Dharme prapata narahari.
"The aim of wealth is to follow dharma
And only through dharma can God be
reached."
People spend their lives following dharma
doing good works, helping others in every way.
Hospitality plays a major part. Planting trees to
provide shade and fruit for travellers, digging
wells for drinking water, giving food and shelter
to the poor, are typical good works. Many of the
dharmasalas (rest houses) in India have been built
by the wealthy as an act of hospitality.
The villagers are delighted to receive guests.
They are fed, clothed and given presents. When
guests arrive they are offered a pot of water to
wash their hands, face and feet. Then they are
given either a mat or a chair to sit on. Previously
sherbet was offered, but now it is the custom to
give a cup of tea, depending on the time of day.
Guests are never asked "Have you eaten?" or
"Would you like something to eat or drink?".
Food is placed before them and it is impolite for
the guests to refuse. Hospitality means giving
yourself completely to guests and strangers.
PRAFULLA MOHANTI
is an Indian writer and painter whose classic book My Village,
My Life (1973), an evocation of the Indian village in the state of
Orissa where he was born and brought up, has been translated
into Japanese, Norwegian and Danish. Among his other
published works are Through Brown Eyes (1985), a pen-portrait of
the English as he saw them after he went to England to work as
an architect in 1960. His latest book, Changing Village, Changing
Life, will be published later this year.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Land of a thousand and one
courtesies
ALn Islamic tradition handed down by the
Persian poets tells how Abraham, not wishing to
eat alone, once sought to share his meal with an
old man he met in the desert. When the time
came to pray, he realized that his guest was a
Zoroastrian and wanted to send him away. But
an angel restrained Abraham, saying, "God has
fed this man for a hundred years, how could you
refuse him a meal?"
Strangers are invariably surprised by the
ceremonial that unfolds before them on a visit
to an Iranian household. Whatever the time of
day or night, whatever the reason for the visit
or the social status of the visitor, a drink will be
offered first of all. To enter someone's house is
like coming to the end of a journey through the
dust of the desert and slaking one's thirst in a
garden.
Usually the tea is prepared in the Russian
manner, left to brew for a long time in a teapot
standing on a samovar and served with added
water in small glasses. Sugar is not added to
the tea but placed on the tongue. Sweetmeats
are always provided to accompany the golden
liquid. Each town has its own speciality, such
as tamarisk jellies, sugared almonds flavoured
with the essence of Egyptian willow, assorted
baklavas (nut and honey pastries) from Yazd,
all kinds of biscuits, some flavoured with jasmine,
others stuffed with walnuts, pistachios or
almonds...
In summer, to alleviate the torrid heat of the
road, cool syrups made from melon or waterme¬
lon juice are served on arrival. The accomplished
hostess can blend the colours and flavours of
different fruits in the most unexpected ways.
Don't think that you can drop in on someone
and then quietly slip away as soon as your busi¬
ness is concluded. In face of the sometimes ex¬
cessively polite formulas used by the master of
the house when he insists that you stay to eat (in
the case of an unexpected visit it is good manners
not to accept too quickly), you must decide for
yourself what common courtesy requires. Even
if there is little to talk about, a visit should not
last less than an hour, otherwise your friends will
be offended by the implication that they have
failed to entertain you properly.
Conversation follows a ritual course, begin-
30 ning with mutual inquiries about matters of
BY
YANN RICHARD
YANN RICHARD,
of France, is a researcher at
the French National Centre
for Scientific Research
(CNRS). He lived for
several years in Iran, where
he worked with the French
Institute of Iranology,
Tehran. He has published
several studies on Iranian
culture, and is co-author
(with B. Hourcade) of
Téhéran au-dessous du
volcan ("Tehran under the
Volcano", Autrement
publishers, Paris, 1987) and
editor of a collection of
articles on Iran and the
West published by the
Maison des Sciences de
l'Homme, Paris, in 1989.
health. At first bad news is avoided, and it is only
broached after a decent interval in order to spare
people's feelings. Depending on the closeness of
the friendship between them, people either dis¬
cuss general topics or more personal matters.
What is so-and-so up to these days? When the
conversation flags, such basic questions as "How
are you getting on?" are used to get it started
again. It would be a mistake to lose patience with
these conventions, which simply exist to fill gaps
in the conversation and to create a companion¬
able atmosphere.
When your thirst has been quenched you will
be brought dishes of dried fruit, cakes, fresh
fruit.... It has been decided that you will stay and
any pretext will be used to keep you. You can't
leave without tasting our fruit! How can you
refuse, faced with such a tempting array of grapes,
figs, peaches and cucumbers?
Pause between mouthfuls and you will no¬
tice that the room where you are being enter¬
tained does not seem to be in regular use. It is
certainly not the place where the family watches
television or reads the papers. Even poor fami¬
lies have a place where guests can be entertained,
although in modern apartments space is limited.
Wealthier families used to Western-style comfort
keep a guest-room furnished with armchairs and
a sofa, while in more modest rural homes
cushions are arranged around the central carpet.
Guests who have travelled far sleep in the same
room, for which carefully folded sheets, blankets
and a mattress are always at hand and will be laid
on the carpet for the night.
The urbanization of the last thirty years, the
wear and tear of city life, cramped apartments...
all these factors make it increasingly difficult to
offer hospitality. Moreover, travelling has become
commonplace and the arrival of a relative from
the airport after a flight lasting an hour or two
bears little resemblance to that of the exhausted
dust-caked traveller of not so very long ago, who
had suffered extremes of heat and cold and had
not slept for several nights. Such hardships are
only a memory today, when proliferating hotels
and restaurants cater for the growing number of
people who wish to travel anonymously, without
imposing on the hospitality of a relative or friend
and incidentally sparing themselves the duty to
reciprocate.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Detail of a 14th<entury Persian miniature
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
Most large family get-togethers, which are less
common today than they used to be, tend to take
place during the major festivals of the religious
or civic calendar. On these occasions succulent
dishes are laid out on cloths spread over the
carpet, and twenty or thirty people gather to eat.
But in contrast to the welcome ceremonies
described above, people talk as little as possible
during these meals, and eat hurriedly, which is
I
;>j
a pity since people would often be happy to take
a second helping and savour the meal at their
leisure.
Enormous quantities of food are prepared for
thçse family reunions, and if supplies were to run
out, the master of the house would give the
shameful impression that he is ungenerous. When
you have finished, don't forget to say that you are
full. Extra guests commonly turn up at the last
minute, when someone brings along an unexpect¬
ed visitor, a relative or a friend. There are never
any seating problems as everyone squeezes up
around the cloth, and if the meal is served on a
table it is often in the form of a buffet since there
are rarely enough chairs to go round.
Once the meal is over, more tea is served and
the ceremony quickly comes to an end. The
master of the house will beg you to excuse the
frugality of his hospitality and the poor quality
of his food, but of course you will protest by in¬
sisting that your hosts have done everything they
could, that is to say a great deal, and that you
are very grateful to them.
Although the master and mistress of the
house always stay in the background, try to
satisfy your every need and give you the place
of honour, do not think that a guest's role is
simply to relax. First of all you must humbly
The guest-room in a house <
Shiraz (Iran)
Preparing tea
at Yazd (Iran)
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
accept the honours bestowed on you, respond
to the polite remarks addressed to you, and help
yourself to the dishes offered to you even if
you don't want them. All these signs of good
manners will show the host that his attempts at
hospitality have not been in vain. The guest
loses his independence and becomes, as a Persian
saying ironically puts it, "the master's donkey"!
The guest's paramount duty, however, is to
return the courtesy. At New Year (Now Rouz)
a return visit is practically taken for granted, as
anyone who has received guests has been placed
under an obligation to them. It may seem sur¬
prising that people you have just entertained in
your home insist on receiving you the following
day, but to refuse would be embarrassing as it
would put them at a disadvantage and leave them
in your debt. The uninitiated who accept the
lavish hospitality of Iranians often forget this
duty to reciprocate and earn themselves a black
mark socially. One way to make up for not
being able to return the invitation is to bring a
present.
But compensation for generosity may come
much later. Someone from the provinces living
in Tehran or another big city will feel particu¬
larly honoured to receive people from his village,
even if they stay for several days. Such a visit is
a tribute to his social success and raises his stand¬
ing in the neighbourhood. Guests of this kind are
therefore a blessing, because although they may
cost their host something in food and effort, their
visit enhances his prestige.
One benefit of hospitality, and not the least,
is that it puts paid to disagreement and conflict.
While "bread and salt" are being shared there is
no question of perpetuating grievances or of
picking quarrels. A tacit truce by both parties,
host and guest, creates a feeling of solidarity that
nothing can destroy. The same principle, when
institutionalized, guarantees the traditional right
of asylum in places held to be sacred: mosques,
the homes of great ulemas (religious leaders), the
stables or kitchens of the shah or, more recently,
embassies and consulates.
When the time has come to take your leave,
the host will see you out. This is another way
of placing you under an obligation. Among the
formalities of leave-taking, you will often hear
the same words you heard when you arrived. No
irony is intended: this is not a polite way of
showing you the door but a way of assuring you
in all sincerity that the visit has been beneficial
for the household and that you will always be
just as welcome in the future. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
i
z-
j
.
' v-:
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Pampa-ed
guests
BY GREGORIO MAN2UR
a«."SaVätf*!ifcisir?
jTJL region devoted mainly to stock-breeding and
farming, the vast Argentine Pampa (a Quechua
Indian word meaning "flat surface") is a land of
welcome where the practice of hospitality in¬
troduced by the Spanish is rooted in Graeco-
Roman, Arab and Christian traditions.
There are few towns in this vast 600-square-
kilometre plain, which is larger than France and,
for the traveller wishing to cross it, roughly
equivalent to a journey between Amsterdam and
Vienna. It is a land of hamlets and isolated farms,
and the hospitality offered there is special, if not
unique.
For the gauchos, the cowboys of the Pampa
whose nearest neighbours are sometimes several
hundred kilometres away, the arrival of a rela¬
tive, a friend or a stranger used to be regarded
as an event. In our time, trains, aircraft and high¬
ways have partly put an end to this isolation, but
customs have not changed for all that and the
people of the Pampa continue to offer a hospi¬
tality that has ceased to exist in the towns.
Crossing an ocean of land
The traveller who sets out from Buenos Aires or
Montevideo finds himself almost immediately in
an ocean of land before an ever-receding horizon.
Awed by a feeling of immense space and solitude,
he advances along an unending road as straight
as an arrow. If he crosses the dry Pampa in the
west he will be accompanied only by the "bad
lights"the phosphorescent glow from the skele¬
tons of animals that have succumbed to thirst,
hunger or the fury of a puma. In the humid
Pampa of the east he will see, on either side of
the road, behind barbed wire, hundreds of peace¬
fully grazing animals or huge water tanks beside
which horses patiently wait their turn to drink.
The traveller accustomed to short distances
is sure to have forgotten something: spare parts
for the car, food, a map, matches or a torch. More
alarmingly, he may run out of petrol. Vehicles
abandoned by the roadside are a common sight.
Their owners will have had to walk for hours or
perhaps days before reaching an inhabited area.
It is in such situations that, weary, thirsty and
alone, a traveller really appreciates the generous
hospitality of the Pampa.
Seeing him arrive, the gaucho, isolated on his
ranch, will raise his arms and greet him with these
words: "I hail thee Mary most pure." To these
traditional words of welcome the seasoned visitor
will reply: "Conceived without sin."
The Argentine Pampa
Inset, left, a group of travellers stop to rest at a ranch
near Montevideo. Right, gauchos in Argentina's
Corrientes province. 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
The master of the house, after inviting him
in, will then serve him drink and food and start
an animated conversation about the weather and
the difficulty and fatigue of travelling. The visitor
is never asked who he is, where he comes from
or what he is looking for in the region. Wherever
he is from, near or far, he is the messenger of
God. Nothing is too good for him. If the host
does not take a liking to the visitor or is not in
a cordial mood, he nevertheless does his best to
offer what he can. In a rich estancia and a poor
cottage alike, a visitor will find a room, a bed with
clean sheets, a pitcher of water and a bucket or,
if there is one, a bath. The peons or the owner's
sons will go off to tow his car with a tractor or
horses. They will look after the repairs and fill
the car with petrol without a thought of pay¬
ment. A farmer would be extremely offended if
he were offered money in exchange for such a
service.
Asado
gaucho-style
When siesta time is over, at the end of the day,
the national dish is prepared. This is known as
asado and consists of a chunk of meat roasted on
a spit or on a grill by an irreplaceable and much-
respected figure called the asador. Whether he is
a labourer or the owner of the farm, only the
asador is permitted to light the fire and to lay out,
turn over and take off the meat, reputed to be
the best in the world. In the meantime the
woman of the house will attend to the empanadas
(meat pasties) and the desserts.
The asado is more than a traditional form of
hospitality; it is a kind of pagan communion.
Around the roasting meat friendships are formed
as the fruits of the earth, the benefits of work,
are shared. If the sky is overcast the meat will be
cooked in the kitchen fireplace; if the weather
is fine, it will be cooked in the open air. In the
presence of women, propriety demands that the
food be eaten sitting down. But in a gaucho-style
asado, the men use the knives they carry on their
belts to cut off a piece of meat which they place
on a slab of bread and eat standing, sauntering
around the grill, avoiding the curls of smoke and
from time to time helping themselves from the
table laden with salads, wine and pickles.
At the end of the meal, after the dessert, the
evening's entertainment can begin. The fireplace
Preparing asado, the
traditional Argentine
speciality of barbecued meat.
Below, illustration by
Eleodoro Ergasto Marenco for
an edition o/The Gaucho
Martín Fierro, the famous
epic poem by the Argentine
writer José Hernández
(1834-1886).
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
becomes a focus of conviviality. Fresh logs are
put on the fire, larger ones now as they have to
last, for the festivities may go on into the early
hours. And if the fingers of the master of the
house or of some peon are not too numb to play
the guitar or if luck has it that the local payador
(strolling singer) is present, then it won't be long
before the first sounds of music are heard.
As the evening progresses, maté, a brew of
leaves from the plant of the same name, prepared
by the woman of the house, is passed around
among the guests. And as he clears his throat by
drinking an excellent cimarrón (bitter maté), the
payador will perhaps sing of the gaucho Martín
Fierro and his friend Cruz, who fled from the
Christian villages seeking refuge among the
Puelche Indians in the south of Argentina. In
colonial times and during the early period of
independence, many "deserters" took refuge
among the Indians, who also thought that
travellers were to be treated with deference. They
believed that an Indian who died fighting along¬
side such men assumed the form of a thunder¬
bolt or lightning and continued to battle with the
usurper in the afterworld. The ties they formed
with those who sought sanctuary with them and
who shared their fate thus continued to exist even
after death.
As the music subsides and glasses of juniper
wine start being passed around, the host generally
GREGORIO MANZUR,
Argentine writer and
journalist, is a writer and
producer with the French
radio station France-
Culture. His latest work of
fiction, Sangre en el ojo
("Blood in the Eye", 1989),
was awarded a Spanish
literary prize.
offers the visitor a calabash or some other wooden
drinking vessel inlaid with silver to be used for
maté, a powder horn, bolas (braided leather straps
with stone balls at their ends used for capturing
running animals by entangling their legs), or a
cross-patterned poncho. If the visitor is on foot,
it is not unusual for him to receive a horse and
saddle as a gift. "You'll give it back to me some
day," the host will say, "next time you're in the
area."
When the evening draws to an end it is cus¬
tomary for the guest to stand up and thank his
hosts for all the kindness that has been shown
to him. Even if his Spanish is not fluent, it will
still be enough for him to convey his feelings to
these people who are always unstinting in their
generosity, even when they have little for them¬
selves.
In the Pampa, visitors have been known to
receive hospitality for months and indeed years.
Some have taken advantage of this to discover the
region, obtain work and found a home after
sending for their family from abroad, often from
Europe. In this old farm building or that luxuri¬
ous estancia there will be a room reserved for the
guest who lived in it for years and promised to
return. No one will move into it permanently
for at any time the friend of yesteryear may come
back. The man of the Pampa is still waiting for
him with open arms. 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Os óculos de Alvaro de
Campos (1980, "The
spectacles of Alvaro de
Campos"), a painting by the
Portuguese artist Antonio
Costa Pinheiro. Alvaro de
Campos is the name of one
of several imaginary poets
whose lives and works were
created by the Portuguese
poet Fernando Pessoa
(1888-1935).
38
A soldier takes refuge in a
monastery. Detail from a
14th-century manuscript
preserved in the Marciana
library, Venice.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
From hospitality
to right of asylum
BY JOSE AUGUSTO SEABRA
¥,
3rf-X'fat&
ELCOMING visitors, especially foreigners, has
been a sacred duty from the time of Ancient
Greece, when visitors were even believed to enjoy
the permanent protection of the god Zeus. In the
Iliad, Homer showed that to harm a visitor was
contrary to religion.
The sacred tradition of hospitality has lasted
for centuries and is shared by various civiliza¬
tions. From the Middle Ages on, Christian pil¬
grims were lodged and fed in churches and
monasteries, and the Order of the Knights Tem¬
plars was specially founded to ensure their pro¬
tection on their way to Jerusalem during the
Crusades. In Islamic countries, pilgrims travelling
to Mecca were also treated with consideration.
This kindness towards pilgrims can be found in
other religions and is a mark of respect and frater¬
nity that transcends frontiers.
With increasing travel, the duty of hospitali¬
ty, both religious and secular, expanded. The mar¬
itime discoveries enabled peoples to get to know
each other better and to appreciate traditions of
hospitality that were different but often inspired
by the same spirit. This is expressed in such works
of Portuguese literature as Luis de Camôes' The
Lusiads, that great epic poem about the Por¬
tuguese navigators, and Peregrination by Fernào
Mendes Pinto, an enlightened traveller who ven¬
tured into the East where he experienced hospi¬
tality that was often more refined than in the
West.
In the modern world, one category of
foreigners has become particularly important,
that of political exiles. While they have always
been the subject of humanitarian attention, their
status has been more strongly protected since the
proclamation of the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights in 1948. During the French Revo¬
lution, in spite of a certain nationalism, foreigners
and notably those who had fought for liberty 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
were welcomed in France as citizens enjoying full
rights. This practice has been extended to other
countries during the last two centuries.
This obligation, combining tradition and
modernity, has strongly influenced the Por¬
tuguese way of welcoming foreigners. At different
times, under different forms of government,
mainly under the liberal government and the
republic, foreigners who took refuge in our coun¬
try because of their convictions and beliefs were
welcomed in a spirit of solidarity and congenial¬
ity, and this kind of behaviour is typical of the
Portuguese attitude to life. The Portuguese always
leave their doors wide open to visitors, whether
pilgrims, refugees or simply guests. From north
to south, from the coast to the interior, everyone
is happy to entertain generously and gracefully.
This open-hearted attitude is expressed in the
Constitution of the Portuguese Republic of 1976,
a product of the democratic regime which fol¬
lowed the Revolution of the Carnations. Article
15 stipulates that foreigners and stateless persons
shall enjoy the same rights and accept the same
obligations as Portuguese citizens, except for spe¬
cifically national rights, which may be extended
to nationals of Portuguese-speaking countries
under reciprocal agreements or international con¬
ventions.
Sailors' graffiti on a jetty
wall at Horta on the island
of Faial, Azores, which has
been an anchorage since the
days of sailing ships.
JOSE AUGUSTO SEABRA,
Portuguese poet and
essayist, is professor of
literary theory and of
Portuguese literature at the
University of Oporto. A
former member of
parliament and Minister of
Education, he is currently
serving as his country's
Ambassador to Unesco.
Article 33 of the Constitution provides that
"the right of asylum be granted to foreigners and
stateless persons who are persecuted or gravely
threatened with persecution because of their ac¬
tivities in favour of democracy, social or national
freedom, peace between peoples, freedom and hu¬
man rights".
This text incorporates the oldest sources of
our civilization as well as the most recent acqui¬
sitions of democracy. Tolerance and fraternity are
characteristic of the sense of hospitality of Por¬
tuguese democrats, who themselves often ex¬
perienced exile during the period of dictatorship
and colonial war, and found refuge in friendly
nations. When elected as representatives of the
Portuguese people, the former refugees wished
to include in the foundation document of their
own country the sacred principle of hospitality
towards foreigners and stateless persons and es¬
pecially towards those who are persecuted be¬
cause of their convictions and beliefs.
"We are strangers wherever we are", wrote
Fernando Pessoa, the poet of exile and homecom¬
ing. We must know how to welcome each other
everywhere in the world. Like religious pilgrims
or political exiles of all times, we know that
hospitality will be extended to us wherever we go.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF IN BRIEF IN BRIEF
ANCIENT AIR
IN ANTARCTIC ICE
To study the Earth's climate as it
was more than 100 million years
ago, scientists are analysing air
bubbles trapped in the Antarctic
ice which contains samples of
ancient atmospheres. Chemical
analysis of such bubbles has
produced a 160,000-year record
of the concentration of
atmospheric carbon dioxide. The
data is contributing to
knowledge about possible
consequences of the greenhouse
effect, the global warming
caused by the buildup of gases
such as carbon dioxide which
may lead to major changes in
the world's climate.
LOST CROPS OF THE INCAS
Overlooked for almost 5
centuries, some of the many
lush crops cultivated in the
Andes by the Incas before the
Spanish conquest may have
exciting possibilities as an
addition to standard urban diets
and a source of revenue for
Third World countries, according
to The Lost Crops of the Incas, a
recent study by the US National
Research Council. The crops,
which could possibly be
produced not only in the Andes
but in mountainous areas of
Asia and Africa, include
Arracacha, roots that taste like a
combination of celery, cabbage
and roast chestnuts, nuñas,
beans that pop like popcorn;
quinoa, grain containing twice
the protein of wheat, rice or
corn; and fruits such as
chirimoya, which has a taste
reminiscent of papaya, pineapple
and banana.
NEW TECHNIQUE
FOR BURN TREATMENT
A promising new technique for
treating severely burned patients
has been developed by a group
of American researchers who are
cultivating cells from the healthy
parts of patients' skin in layers
of cow protein. "The skin is
much more similar to human
skin than when you use (human)
cells alone," says one of the
researchers, Dr. John F.
Hansbrough, Director of the
Burn Center at the University of
California's San Diego Medical
Center. Grafts produced using
the new technique also seem to
anchor more rapidly to the body
as well as being stronger and
more resilient.
THE LONG AND THE SHORT
OF HEART DISEASE
Short men are twice as likely as
tall men to suffer a heart attack
in middle age, according to an
8-year study of almost 8,000
men funded by the British Heart
Foundation. Of the 1,533 men
in the sample under 1.67 m (5'
6"), 118 had a heart attack, as
against 62 of a similar number
over 1.77 m (5' 10"). The
researchers said that although
shorter men tended to have
higher blood pressure and blood
cholesterol levels and to smoke
more, the decisive factor
appeared to be poorer lung
function.
HOME-GROWN PAPER
Scientists believe a new
generation of crops can be
developed to provide rubber,
newsprint, lubricants and other
products. The US Association
for the Advancement of
Industrial Crops reports
that a Brazilian chemical
company is introducing
guar, a plant which yields a
gum with a wide range of uses
including thickening ketchup,
and vernonia, oil from which
could be used as a paint
thinner. One pilot plant is to be
built in Arizona to extract rubber
from the desert shrub guayule,
and another facility is expected
to open in 1991 in Texas to
process kenaf, a tall fibrous
annual plant, into newsprint.
FAIR PLAY AWARDS
A Soviet-Canadian trans-Arctic
skiing expedition and an
Olympic boxing champion from
Cuba have won the International
Pierre de Coubertin Fair Play
Trophies awarded annually by
the International Committee for
Fair Play under the auspices of
Unesco. In a 91 -day journey, the
13-man ski team crossed the
Arctic Ocean via the North Pole
from the Severnaya Zemlya
Archipelago In the USSR to
World Hunt Island in Canada
Cuban boxer Teófilo Stevenson
won the Trophy for his record of
fair play throughout his career.
REDISCOVERED
MANUSCRIPT BY RLS
A long-forgotten story by Robert
Louis Stevenson, the author of
Treasure Island, has been
rediscovered and published for
the first time. The story, "The
Enchantress", was probably
written in 1 889 when Stevenson
was en route from Hawaii to
Samoa, where he spent the last
5 years of his life. The 27-page
ms. was recently acquired by
Yale University and discovered
by Prof. David Mann. The story
appeared in the autumn 1989
edition of the Georgia Review,
the University of Georgia's
literary magazine.
YOUNG SCIENTISTS SHARE
EC RESEARCH PRIZE
Nine budding scientists from 6
European countries won first
prize in a 1989 European
Community contest to
encourage scientific research
among young people. The
winning entries Included two
devices to help the disableda
typewriter with an eye-operated
control unit, and a walking aid
whereby people can support
themselves by pushing a hand
bar along tracks set into the
walls The scientists, whose ages
ranged from 16 to 21, have
each been awarded a
scholarship worth 5,000
European Currency Units
($5,550)
DICTIONARY OF
SUPERSTITIONS PUBLISHED
A 1,500-entry dictionary of
superstitions, including black cats,
stepping on cracks and knocking
on wood, has been published by
the Oxford University Press.
Authors Moira Tatum and lona
Opie believe that many
superstitions of today are not
only universal but can be traced
back thousands of years beyond
written history. "Although we
know it goes back 4,000 years
to nature worship, the earliest
written reference to knocking on
wood is a 19th-century children's
game," Ms. Tatum said.
RISING CASPIAN FLOODS
COASTAL TOWNS
The Caspian Sea, which borders
on the Soviet Union and Iran,
has risen 1.5 m in the last 10
years, flooding many coastal
towns and baffling scientists,
reports the Soviet news agency
Tass. The Aral Sea, on the other
hand, some 480 km to the east,
is drying up because so much of
its water is being used for
irrigation.
HIGH-PERFORMANCE
PLASTICS USED IN
EXPERIMENTAL HOUSE
A gracious colonial-style house
has been built in Pittsfield,
Massachusetts (USA), as a
laboratory to explore the use of
plastics in housing construction
About one-third of the house,
whose total cost has been
estimated at $10 million, is
made of high-performance
engineering plastics which have
high melting points, create little
smoke when they burn and
have good sound-proofing
properties.
IN BRIEF IN BRIEF IN
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
REFLECT! N
THE RETURN OF THE INCA
BY PERLA PETRICH
\J EEPLY rooted in the experiences
of the peoples of the continent, the
vivid, dynamic epics of Latin America
predate the Spanish conquest by
centuries.
The ancient inhabitants of Mex¬
ico, for whom the epic was of fun¬
damental importance, recorded
countless tales, legends and myths in
Codices, locally produced books con¬
sisting of pictographs combined with
ideograms and phonetic hieroglyphs.
They had centres at which young
people were taught the contents of
these books and the precise wording
in which they should be expressed.
The objective of the teachers at these
centres was to get their pupils to
learn by heart the epic poems, say¬
ings and myths that went with the
illustrations ¡n the Codices.
Most of these Codices, which the
missionaries described as "pagan"
and "works of the devil", were des¬
troyed during the Spanish conquest.
Nevertheless, the evangelizers could
not eradicate the memory nor pre¬
vent the oral transmission of the
great themes of these epics which
have persisted in many cultures. Fur¬
thermore, some of the descendants
of the ancient nobility (such as
Chimalpain and Ixtlilxóchitl) were
quick to adopt the Latin alphabet for
making transcriptions of tales in their
own language. This was how the
Anales de Tlatelolco ("Annals of
Tlatelolco") originated among the
Nahua. This manuscript, now
preserved in the Bibliothèque Nation-
ale in Paris, contains the genealogies
of the ancient rulers and an account
of the Spanish conquest.
Hundreds of poems have sur¬
vived in the same way, such as those
contained in La colección de cantares
mexicanos ("The Anthology of Mex¬
ican Epic Poems"), now in the Nation¬
al Library of Mexico, and in the
42 so-called Manuscrito de los romances
ßWMOOB.ERHO
ATOPM/IARM
[a miyhlftl WM4 aal fdp tA îaa CAI^\l : hi f 'i Wa«. ' fjaca*CCf
miSm
The decapitation of the Inca.
Illustration from a 16th-century Peruvian codex.
de los señores de la Nueva España
("Manuscript of the Romances of the
Gentlemen of New Spain"), now in
the University of Texas library.
The most important Maya
manuscripts are by anonymous
authorsthe Libros del Chilam Balam
("Books of Chilam Balam"), written
in Yucatecan Maya, and the Popol
Vuh, written in Quiche Maya. Both
manuscripts contain historical and
prophetic narratives.
A number of mestizo writers
such as Fernando Alvarado
Tezozómoc, and several Spanish
missionaries, also collated the tradi¬
tions of these peoples and recorded
them in written form. Among the
missionaries who undertook this task
were the monks Andrés de Olmos,
Benavente Motolinía and, most
important of all, Bernardino de
Sahagún who, between 1565 and
1569, wrote, in Spanish, the famous
Historia general de las cosas de la
Nueva España ("General History of
the Things of New Spain"). In this
way many of these epics have come
down to us in the form of written
documents.
Both the Nahua and the Maya
epics contain heroic tales of the peo¬
ples' wanderings in search of a fixed
abode, of the founding of cities and
of the exploits of the heroes associat¬
ed with them.
Among the Nahua, for example,
the epic of Quetzalcóatlwho
was both a divinity and a heroic
founding fatheris a model of its
kind. His story can be pieced together
from texts to be found in a variety
of documents: Los anales de
Cuauhtitlán ("The Annals of
Cuauhtitlán"), La historia Tolteca-
Chichimeca ("The History of the
Toltecs and the Chichimecs") and
La leyenda de los Soles ("The Legend
of the Suns"), all of which are anthol¬
ogies of poems and historico-mythical
texts recorded by indigenous writers
in the middle of the sixteenth
century. They relate how, after long
and bloody struggles against enemies
who sought to introduce the
practice of human sacrifice, the
priest-king of Tula, the repository of
the cultural heritage and guarantor
of the purity of the religion, was
obliged to give up his functions and
disappeared into the sea leaving with
his people a promise that some day
he would return.
The better known Maya epics
are to be found in the Popol Vuh,
written in the sixteenth century
but only discovered at the beginning
of the eighteenth century by Father
Francisco Ximénez, the parish priest
of Chichicastenango, in Guatemala.
In addition to cosmogonie myths
and legends concerning man's
many unsuccessful works, this
book relates the wanderings
of the first four Quiche chiefs in
search of fire and their struggles
to consolidate their power and
dominion.
The Inca epic relates the wander¬
ings of the four tribes which founded
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Quetzalcóatl and 3 other Aztec divinities are shown competing in a ritual game
of pelota in this illustration from the Codex Borbonicus (1325-1521).
Cuzco. According to the versions
collated by the Peruvian ethnologist
J. Ossio, four brothers set out from
four caves accompanied by their
wives. Only one couple, Ayar Manco
and Mama Ocllo, reached the valley
of the Cuzco river. There, on the spot
where Ayar Manco buried his golden
staff deep in the earth, the imperial
capital was built.
Son of the Sun
The Inca epic also provides a typical
example of the vitality and persis¬
tence of mythical narratives among
the indigenous communities of Latin
America. It tells the story of Inkarri,
a god said to be the son of the Sun.
In many accounts this divinity is por¬
trayed as a victim of the Spanish by
whom he was tortured and then be¬
headed. It is believed, nevertheless,
that although separated from the
body, the head is still alive and hid¬
den in a secret place (either in Cuzco
or in the jungle, according to some
of the versions compiled by Ossio).
The head is growing a new body and
when this body is fully grown the son
of the Sun will return as the god who
will pronounce the final judgement
and the restoration of the empire.
This belief still persists today and
each year, in many indigenous com¬
munities in Peru, Ecuador and Bolivia,
during ceremonies in honour of the
local patron saint, representations of
the death of the Inca are organized
and performed. Like Inkarri, the Inca
was worshipped as the son of the
Sun, a fact which allows for the iden¬
tification of the god with the ruler.
During these performances, the ac¬
tors, all of whom are indigenous,
dressed ¡n contemporary costumes,
act out a series of mythical and histor¬
ical events which the folk epic juxta¬
poses within a timeless setting. In this
way an amalgam is made of pre-
hispanic beliefs, interpretations of the
conquest from the standpoint of the
vanquished, and historical happen¬
ings from the execution of Atahual-
pa at Cajamarca in 1 533, by order of
Pizarra, right up to recent events.
The death of the Inca entailed
the defeat of the empire, the end of
an epoch and the beginning of Span¬
ish domination. In all these perfor¬
mances Pizarra appears and beheads
the Inca. In fact, however, Atahual-
pa was garrotted (strangled in a sit¬
ting position). The fact that in the
collective memory strangulation has
been replaced by decapitation shows
that the people associate the death
of the Inca not with that of Atahual-
pa but with that of Sayri Tupac, who
was indeed beheaded and who is
considered by them to have been the
last of the Inca rulers since he resist¬
ed the conquistadors in Vilcabamba
until 1572. This also reinforces the
identification of the Inca with the god
Inkarri, the son of the Sun. This
scenario, as it is still performed, con¬
jures up images which signify that at
some indeterminate time in the fu¬
ture (when the body of the god/lnca
is fully regrown) the ancient civiliza¬
tion will recover all its splendour, will
re-establish its own laws and redistrib¬
ute the land among the descendants
of its rightful owners.
This epic tale and many others
have endured until our day, modified
and recreated by the interplay of in¬
fluences from the indigenous, Euro¬
pean and African cultures that have
coexisted in Latin America since the
end of the fifteenth century. One
consequence of these transforma¬
tions has been a greater similarity be¬
tween themes from the different
cultural regions. However, another
possible explanation of this increas¬
ing similarity is that the history of the
Aztec pictogram showing
the eternal cycle of life and death.
Codex Borgianus (1200-1500).
people of Latin America since the ar¬
rival of the Europeans has developed
within a single contextcolonial
domination and underdevelopment.
Perhaps the similarity of social and
political conditions is tending to unify
the collective imagination.
PERLA PETRICH,
of Argentina, is professor of Latin
American literature at the University
of Paris VIII and a member of the
French National Centre for Scientific
Research's Laboratory of Languages
and Civilizations with an Oral
Tradition (LACITO).
T ' N
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
s N
THE DISAPPEARANCE OF THE DINOSAURS,
.__ A SCIENTIFIC ENIGMA
"* *'; Z
""^aä*-'V
^YY:r^ '
BY LEONARD GINSBURG
VPfc
Ankylosaurus,
an armoured dinosaur
over 4 metres long.
44
lived on Earth for 1 50
million years, from the Triassic to the
Cretaceous Periods, and then became
extinct. Reptiles with elongated legs,
they are a source of interest and
astonishment because of the gigantic
size of some of them, because of
their strange shape and their longevi¬
ty, and because they disappeared
simultaneously from the face of the
Earth 65 million years ago.
Study of their skeletons has
made it possible to reconstitute the
physical appearance of dinosaurs, but
the reason for their disappearance
has proved more difficult to establish.
Specialists in several scientific dis¬
ciplines including biology, physiolo¬
gy, palaeoclimatology, palaeography
and astronomy have tried to solve the
mystery. Many hypotheses have been
proposed, most of them short-lived.
At present there are two conflicting
theories based on diametrically op¬
posed premises and modes of reason¬
ing. According to the first or
"catastrophist" thesis, dinosaurs
were exterminated by extra-terrestrial
objects. The second, or "gradualist"
thesis is centred on the evolution of
geological phenomena.
The killer comet theory
Large amounts of iridium, palladium
and platinum have been found near
Gubbio in central Italy in sediments
deposited during the transition be¬
tween the Cretaceous and the Ter¬
tiary Periodswhat is known as the
K/T boundary. Layers rich in iridium
from the same geological period have
also been found in Denmark, Spain,
France and New Zealand. The Ameri¬
can geologist Walter Alvarez believes
that the fact that the sedimentary
deposits date from the same period
as the extinction of the dinosaurs can¬
not be a mere matter of chance,
and that there is a cause-and-effect
relationship between the two
phenomena.
The scenario proposed by Alva¬
rez in 1980 is as follows: iridium is
a very rare element and its concen¬
tration in a sedimentary deposit must
result, not from the erosion of an¬
cient rocks nor from biochemical
phenomena, but from the impact
made by an extraterrestrial object
that collided with the Earth.
Meteorites are rich in iridium and
Alvarez suggested that a meteorite
with a diameter of between 6 and 1 0
kilometres crashed into the Earth and
raised an immense cloud of terrestrial
dust which mingled with the dust
released by the break-up of the
meteorite itself, blotting out the sun¬
light and preventing photosynthesis
from taking place. This night may
Triceratops
was a plant-eating dinosaur
some 7 metres long.
have lasted between six and ten
years, during which the dinosaurs
died of hunger. The much smaller
mammals may have survived by eat¬
ing seeds and undecomposed plant
residues.
Since it was first put forward, this
theory has undergone several modifi¬
cations. In the iridium-rich layers it has
been observed that the mass of mat¬
ter of terrestrial origin is much less
than that which the impact of a
meteorite could have produced. Thus
the meteorite was replaced by co¬
mets which would have disintegrat¬
ed as they approached the Earth and
unleashed a hail of debris. After that
point the scenario is unchanged.
Falling sea levels
and glaciation
Another theory, which I first put for¬
ward in 1 964, is based on the fact
that what are now known as the
mass extinctions coincided with
regressions of the sea. Each major di¬
vision in the geological time-scale be¬
gins with a marine transgression (the
spread of the sea over land areas) ac¬
companied by the appearance of a
new fauna, and ends with a marine
regression (the retreat of the sea)
which is contemporary with a mass
extinction. It is hard to believe that
the simultaneous occurrence of ma¬
rine regressions and mass extinctions
over a period of 600 million years
could have been fortuitous. There
must have been a direct cause-and-
effect relationship between the fluc¬
tuations of sea level and the renew¬
al of animal life in the course of
geological time.
The neritic regions, which con¬
sist of the belt of shallow water ad¬
joining the seacoast up to a depth of
some 1 20 metres, are those in which
sunlight penetrates most. They are
p=e-"^SI ^
&íís*'
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
l^tfflM^,'a.',>«i«MI..«U.,Aa.,fc.l..JI
consequently the parts of the ocean
which are richest in microflora and
hence, because of the food chain, in
fauna. The great invasions of the sea
were a time of expansion for the
nentic regions. In the Middle Creta¬
ceous, for example, they covered
most of Europe from Brittany to the
Urals. The retreat of the sea during
the Late Cretaceous reduced the area
of this submarine continental plateau
by between 200 and 300 times. Lack
of space led to competition between
the marine animals which lived there.
The fauna were thus reduced natur¬
ally as the space available to them
diminished.
Almost all groups of animals
were affected. Some, such as the am¬
monites, the belemnites and the ma¬
rine reptiles which fed on them,
disappeared totally. Others, such as
the brachiopods and to a much
smaller extent the echinoderms, did
not totally disappear but were strong¬
ly affected. Furthermore, the sea
retreated slowly, over a period of 1 5
million years. The extinction of am¬
monites and other zoological groups
thus took place gradually, as did that
of the dinosaurs.
The extension of the land surface
must have provoked a continentali-
zation of the climate, bringing wider
differences in temperature between
winter and summer. There was also
a general fall in mean annual tem¬
perature.
The dinosaurs, large animals of
variable temperature, were directly
affected by climatic cooling. Their in¬
ternal temperature, like that of all
reptiles, followed the fluctuations of
the surrounding temperature and
when the latter dropped to the limit
of the internal temperature necessary
for biological activity, they perished.
Small reptiles were more resistant
Diplodocus,
a giant dinosaur which probably fed
on soft vegetation.
The biggest known example was 27 metres long.
since they could hibernate or go to
ground, as species do in temperate
regions today. Since their tempera¬
ture is constant, mammals and birds
are less dependent on external climat¬
ic conditions than reptiles and were
thus able to survive the transition be¬
tween the Cretaceous and the Ter¬
tiary Periods.
These two theories have their
supporters and their detractors. The
theory of the killer comet, based as
it is on extraterrestrial phenomena,
has exercised a strong fascination on
the public and received wide media
coverage. It has topical overtones in
an age of space exploration and fear
of thermonuclear destruction. If it
were proved to be correct, it might
also provide an acceptable approxi¬
mation of the effects of a major
nuclear catastrophe on the bi¬
osphere.
More biological in nature and
more global in its scope, the falling
sea level theory explains a greater
number of obscure phenomena, and
provides a link between a range of
geological events. Consequently, it is
more widely accepted by geologists
and palaeontologists. However, it is
complex, technical and unspectacu¬
lar. In a century of speed, record-
breaking and concern for short-term
profit, a theory based on the effects
of a phenomenon which took place
over 15 million years may have less
immediate appeal than its rival.
Megalosaurus,
a dinosaur
some 6 metres long
LEONARO GINSBURG
is a French specialist in anatomy
and vertebrate palaeontology
whose main areas of research are
reptiles and mammals. He has
directed excavations in many
countries and has published over
200 scientific papers.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
ANN
THE GREAT WALL
OF MEDIEVAL PARIS
BY ARTHUR GILLETTE
46
lou can buy no postcards of it.
There are no organized tours to visit
it. Guidebooks are far from loqua¬
cious about it. And no signposts will
lead you along its path. Yet there it
is, numerous vestiges of it at any rate,
many in plain sight of the tens of
thousands of Parisians who pass by
some part of it each day without
knowing what they are seeing
perhaps without even really seeing it.
What is it? Quite simply the
formidable wall built around Paris
from 1190 on the orders of Philip
Augustus, one of the great Capetian
kings of medieval France (reigned
1 179-1223). The rampart's 800th an¬
niversary this year is perhaps a chance
to pierce its undeserved anonymity.
The wall was intended to defend
what had recently become the French
capital against the Anglo-Norman ar¬
mies entrenched a few kilometres
down the Seine, when Philip left for
the Third Crusade to the Holy Land
with Richard the Lionheart in 1191.
That Richard was king of England
only goes to show that alliances were
no simpler then than now.
Today the remains of Philip's wall
enclose an oval space of some 253
hectares which at the time of its con¬
struction was occupied by around
100,000 people, indeterminate
amounts of livestock and countryside
expansive enough to be commemo¬
rated in still-surviving place-names.
There is some disagreement
among archaeologists as to certain of
the rampart's measurements, but de¬
pending on the differing strategic
needs of various parts of the
perimeter it appears that it was 6 to
9 metres high and 2.6 to 2.8 metres
thick at its base, tapering at the top,
along which ran a walkway for look¬
outs and archers. Along the right
(north) bank of the Seine the rampart
was built largely at local merchants'
expense to protect the commerce
that was beginning to thrive in the
relatively peaceful conditions afford¬
ed by the Capetian central
government.
No such source of funds was to
be found on the left bank. Although
there were wealthy monasteries and
other religious establishments, they
had their own fortifications. The
south side of the city was shared by
farmers and the usually penniless stu¬
dents of what became known as the
Latin Quarter because of the com¬
mon language of its plurinational
population. So the king paid for the
wall on the south bank. This was
probably not a gesture of selfless
generosity, but rather seems to have
been a calculated political and psy¬
chological tactic in his struggle
against the still-powerful and still-
numerous feudal lords, over whom
he exercised only indirect control to
which they submitted grudgingly at
best.
In addition to fortified gates at
the entry and exit points of the main
east-west and north-south thorough¬
fares, the wall was punctuated by a
semicircular tower some 6 metres in
diameter every 60 metres or so. Why
this distance? Probably so that bow¬
men on adjacent towers could con¬
trol the span of wall separating them,
as it has been shown that the maxi¬
mum effective range of a crossbow
is about 30 metres.
Unlike fortifications built on
Philip's orders at other cities, the Paris
wall had no moat. A moat was even¬
tually built, a century and a half later,
when during the Hundred Years' War
between England and France Charles
V refurbished the capital's defences
in a project that also included the
construction of the Bastille.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
*v .:<öb^
j
"^>
*<?*ty #1
»1i'iW
'xt*
1 flÇ "^
5 .
S '
-: ..
« ¿
Mal
-^ ~
** asrv
Another reason for the construc¬
tion of the wall may have been the
king's passion for enhancing the in¬
frastructure of French society at a
time when it was emerging from the
more anarchic earlier medieval peri¬
od. During Philip's reign and largely
at his initiative, a flurry of urban con¬
struction was carried out that was
truly worthy of a rising national
capital.
For the first time since the Ro¬
man occupation of Gaul, the main
streets of Paris were paved. The Hôtel
Dieu hospital, which still operates
near its original location, was built.
So was a central enclosed market,
with doors that could be locked at
night, which partly replaced the
peripatetic fairs then common and
put business on a daily rather than
a seasonal basis. Known as Les Halles,
this market was not moved from its
original site to the city outskirts until
the 1970s. Work on Notre Dame
cathedral, begun under Philip's father
Louis VII, proceeded apace, and the
fortress on whose site the Louvre
now stands was built.
Philip's lifelong ambition seems
to have been to forge a powerful cen¬
tral monarchy that directly controlled
an ever-expanding territory. If not yet
a nation, France was already begin¬
ning to assume the substance and
trappings of a state.
The Church was a potential ally
against Philip's enemies, but he had
alienated Rome (for example he had
had his second marriage annulled to
free him for a third) to such an ex¬
tent that he and France were excom¬
municated for a while. This was a very
grave measure, in his subjects' eyes
at least. There remained as a possi¬
ble counterweight to feudal power
the small but steadily growing urban
populations and in particular their
merchant élites.
Philip was not unfailingly solici¬
tous to the nascent bourgeoisie, yet
he often treated it as an ally. On
departing for the Crusades, for exam¬
ple, he broke with tradition and en¬
trusted the keys of the royal treasury
to seven townspeople. He also grant¬
ed charters to guilds of butchers and
drapers and favoured the ascendan¬
cy of the watermen's guild. The
watermen were of vital importance
to ensure Parisian control over trans¬
port of goods into and out of the city
through a network of major rivers
the Marne, Oise and Yonne as well
as the Seine. This move was all the
more astute as at that time land
transport in France was so antiquat¬
ed that it still depended in some
places on the remains of the roads
abandoned by the Romans.
The wall thus may be interpret¬
ed as a political and psychological as
well as a military statement, saying
in effect that "feudalism stops here,
and here begins a qualitatively new
kind of lifeurban life". The city had
begun to offer refuge, anonymity, al¬
ternatives and at least a degree of
freedom unknown in the lords'
domainsa runaway serf who
managed to enter the city and stay
there uncaught for a specified peri¬
od (such as a year and a day) became
a free man.
A glance at a map of Paris will
show how the French capital has
grown in concentric ovals out from
its twelfth-century perimeter wall, the
6 to 9 metres of stone which pro¬
claimed "the city begins here".
Above and opposite page: vestiges of
the rampart which King Philip
Augustus began to build around Paris
in 1190. Photo at far left shows a
narrow building put up in place of a
torn-down section of the wall.
ARTHUR GILLETTE
is the editor of Unesco's
international quarterly Museum
and the author of many articles
on cultural themes.
N N
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
I N the Landes département of south¬
western France, a group of school¬
children visit a rock shelter used by
hunter-gatherers of the Old Stone
Age. The shelter is located on a cone-
shaped mass of debris overlooking a
river at a ford. From this vantage
point early man kept watch as the
animals crossed at different seasons.
The skeleton of a dismembered rein¬
deer unearthed on the site is a tan¬
gible piece of evidence which can
help the children to imagine how the
hunter-gatherers lived in those re¬
mote times.
In the neighbouring départe¬
ment of Lot-et-Garonne, the children
visit Stone Age rock shelters located
at the riverside, suggesting that fish¬
ing was practised there. Nearby
megaliths and objects preserved in
local museums help teachers explain
how man the predator became a
stock-raiser, then abandoned a no¬
madic life and turned to agriculture,
how his growing mastery of fire ena¬
bled him to improve the quality of the
earthenware he made and to develop
metalwork techniques, first with
bronze and then iron.
By on-the-spot study of these
and other sites the children can form
a picture of the changing human im¬
pact on the landscape, as well as
changes in activities and habitat
which took place down the ages in
response to different needs.
The children are taking part in
special "heritage classes",, which
were launched as an experiment in
1982 in the Aquitaine region to
which the Landes and Lot-et-Garonne
départements belong. The purpose of
48 the classes is to introduce young peo-
ARCHAEOLOGISTS
OF THE YEAR 2000
BY FRÉDÉRIC BERTHAULT
pie to the riches of the past and at
the same time encourage them to
contribute in their own way to the
safeguard of the cultural heritage.
As part of the heritage classes,
primary school children up to age
eleven spend a week with their
teachers in places rich in historical
monuments and archaeological re¬
mains. They usually stay in châteaux,
abbeys or other historic buildings,
thus learning at first hand about their
local heritage, which, hopefully, they
will safeguard when they grow up.
After visiting prehistoric sites the
children go on a trip to a flint work¬
shop where researchers show them
the techniques of our distant ances¬
tors. Then they make stone tools, the
efficiency of which they test by using
them to scrape skins or wood.
The vestiges of a forum or the
ruins of a well-preserved fourth-
century villa where the mosaic pav¬
ing of the baths has survived provide
an excellent introduction to the Gallo-
Roman period. From there the chil¬
dren move on to another workshop
where they make a small mosaic
using the methods described by
writers of Antiquity.
Twelfth-century abbeys and
churches, and strongholds of the
fourteenth and fifteenth centuries
provide material to introduce the chil¬
dren to medieval religious, civil and
military architecture, to the ways in
which people thought in the Middle
Ages, their social and political rela¬
tionships and their economic
problems.
The week ends with an evening
get-together at which local musicians
play medieval and Renaissance music
on old ¡nstruments.The music and
dancing bring this initiation into the
local heritage to a festive conclusion.
At the request of both teachers
and pupils, a second, complementary
type of heritage class has been created
to introduce ten- to fifteen -year-olds
to the techniques of archaeology.
It was clearly impossible to allow
the children to excavate real archaeo¬
logical sites which might in any case
turn out to yield few finds and would
be educationally disappointing. In¬
stead a site has been purpose-built
for the budding archaeologists. It
consists of a succession of layers or
levels, each of which corresponds to
a period when the site was occupied.
In particular there are a "prehistor¬
ic" level and a "historical" level, giv¬
ing scope for a wide coverage of the
science and methods of archaeology.
The reconstitution of the "pre¬
historic" level was straightforward.
Knowledge of vestiges left by Euro¬
pean hunter-gatherers and the tech¬
niques of making stone tools is today
sufficiently advanced to enable ar¬
chaeologists to recreate with preci¬
sion the floor of a shelter, a hearth,
a rock-cutting area and other remains
of a prehistoric camp.
The major difficulty arose with
the reconstitution of the "historical"
level, surprisingly perhaps since our
knowledge of later history is more
complete. It would of course have
been possible to reconstitute a piece
of wall in brick or stone, but the or¬
ganizers would in this case have had
to make reproductions of old ear¬
thenware and metal objects, unless
material unearthed during excava¬
tions was usedand this was out of
the question because of the concern
to preserve the heritage.
To solve this problem, it was
decided to create a "contemporary"
level using objects dating from the
1960s picked up on a garbage dump.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Before they start to excavate, the
children are told that they are ar¬
chaeologists in the year 2000 and
that surface inspection has yielded
evidence that the site on which they
are to work had once been occupied.
For confirmation they will have to
carry out a limited excavation of a
4-metre-square area, using archaeo¬
logical tools such as trowels, dental
instruments and paintbrushes. The
levels can easily be identified because
they consist of sand stained with
different colours. During the excava¬
tion, the objects are left in situ.
When each level has been entire¬
ly excavated, a drawing is made of
its structure and the objects it con¬
tains, using decametre sticks, plumb
lines and spirit levels, so that the site
can be reconstituted to scale the next
day in class, when the results are ana¬
lysed and commented on.
There were grounds for thinking
that this "contemporary" level would
hold little interest for pupils, but it has
turned out to be richer from an
educational point of view than any
other. The children recognize most of
the objects and describe their func¬
tions without difficulty. Next they
have to find out the uses of different
parts of the site, such as a kitchen,
part of a bedroom, and a section of
street.
The remains of the entrance to
a house make it possible to distin¬
guish "inside" from "outside". Traces
of garbage outside the house suggest
that this was where the dustbin was
kept. Bed springs and parts of a
television encourage the children to
think that here was an area for rest
and relaxation, while a water tap and
the remains of a washbasin suggest
that they might be in a bathroom
.. £
1
I
V '1aWatiBa».*'.-t->.«t .'S*.'** 0
C » ;!*r..
K? - -
EfcatóiwJ: ' -
tins*, «t*»* W>r>.i
rather than a living room. Kitchen
utensils, gas burners and a refrigera¬
tor grid are unequivocal evidence of
the functions of the area where they
are found. Lastly, information on
empty cans or on fragmented objects
later glued together indicate their ori¬
gins and illustrate the notion of ex¬
change between different regions.
Some idea of culinary practices can
be deduced from the type of uten¬
sils and the food products discovered
on the site.
The children thus learn from eas¬
ily recognizable "archaeological" ob¬
jects how archaeologists excavate
and record their findings and how
they reason when trying to reconsti¬
tute former ways of life.
The excavation then carries on
down to the "prehistoric" layer which
is pitted with holes for stakes and
contains the remains of hearths (char¬
coal, burned pebbles), pieces of flint,
and tools. Building on the experience
they have gained from excavating the
"contemporary" level, the children's
methods have greatly improved. They
now confidently use techniques and
reasoning which were formerly be¬
yond their grasp.
FREDERIC BERTHAULT,
French archaeologist and
historian, is in charge of the
heritage classes offered by the
Aquitaine region of France. He is
the author of a number of articles
on archaeology which have been
published in specialist journals.
Left, young participants in a "heritage
class" visit the remains of a medieval
stronghold at Hastingues in south¬
western France.
H
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
50
Appeal to tree-lovers
Arboretums, collections of little-known
trees, are of scientific, educational and
ornamental interest. Veritable living
museums where the diversity of plant
species can be preserved, they are
of value to professionals such as land¬
scape gardeners and nurserymen and
to students, botanists and everyone
who cares about trees. In France there
are too few arboretums, and many
départements, such as the Isère, have
none at all.
As a tree-lover, I have had the idea
of creating an arboretum in the Isère.
I am twenty-eight years old and hope
to be around long enough to see such
a collection grow.
But I need help in finding land and
financial backing from people who may
know nothing about trees, tend to be
interested in short-term gain, and do
not readily see the use of what appears
to them to be a kind of public forest
or garden.
Support from people who under¬
stand the value of an arboretum and
the wealth of information it can provide
could give a kind of "legitimacy" to my
project and support to my arguments.
I would be very grateful, then, if you
would help my cause by publishing this
letter.
Pierre Eymery
Chemin du Pré Guillet
38320 Herbeys (France)
Internatia lingvo
I think many people would be'glad to
have an opportunity to read your maga¬
zine in Esperanto. Why not start an
Esperanto edition? Excellent translators
do exist.
Renée Correy
Besançon (France)
Meso-American
mathematics
As a long-standing subscriber I find it
very disappointing, to say the least, that
your November 1989 issue devoted to
mathematics did not mention the Meso-
American contribution to maths. Meso-
American peoples from the early Ol-
mecs to the Aztecs, not forgetting the
Mayas, Zapotees and Mixtees, were all
capable of determining the movement
of the planets, in some cases better than
we can today, and of calculating time
accurately. Did they not invent a zero
symbol in the form of a shell which was
just as good as that of the Brahmins?
One might think that your "mathemat¬
ical mystery tour" lost its bearings as
soon as it reached the Atlantic.
You will no doubt reply that in such
and such an issue, in such and such a
year, the subject was covered and that
it will be covered again next year. That
is beside the point. Such an oversight
indicates a flaw in the purpose that
should inspire Unesco, and more spe¬
cifically your magazinethe promotion
of cultural exchanges between peoples.
We Europeans would never have
progressed from the Renaissance to the
industrial age without the contribution
of Meso-American knowledge of food
crops, and our mathematics would not
have developed so rapidly if it had been
confined to the works of a self-satisfied
élite. Some fifty different kinds of fruit
and vegetables brought over in the
holds of Spanish galleons revolutionized
agriculture. This is far from negligible,
as when one has enough to eat, one
has leisure to cultivate the mind and to
attain the poetic heights of
mathematics.
Claude Bergerat
Rueil Malmaison (France)
Courier index
I feel that the cumulative index of the
Unesco Courier covers too long a
period 1948-1987, the magazine's
first forty years. Having been a sub¬
scriber only since 1980, must I wait
another forty years for an index of cur¬
rent issues? That would be a pity, as the
Courier is an excellent working tool for
everyone. Why not publish a decennial
index'
Daniel Clays
Dunkirk (France)
Such a project is under consideration and
a decision will be made shortly.
Editor
Base 60?
In a box on page 1 6 of your November
1 989 issue on mathematics, which was
far beyond my range despite the hopes
raised by your editorial, the date 1989
is written in Mesopotamian numbers as
33 sixties and 9 ones. I'm surprised that
33 is used in a way that seems to me
to be decimal in a number system based
on 60. Is this a mistake, or is there some
explanation I've missed?
Paul Bresson
Bayeux (France)
Editor's note: James Ritter, who
contributed the article on Ancient
Egyptian and Mesopotamian mathematics
to our November issue, replies'
The signs used to write each digit (from
1 to 59) are indeed composed of bits
representing tens and ones. But the
value of a digit is given by its position
vis-à-vis the other digits and is always
a multiple of 1, 60, 602, etc.
What about modern maths?
It was a pleasure to read your issue on
maths. My only regret is there was not
a single article on contemporary
mathematics. It's a shame that the story
comes to a halt in the middle of the
18th century.
Jacques Ibert
Saint-Maurice (France)
PHOTO CREDITS
Cover : P. Vernier © Explorer, Pans.
Back cover : © Roland and Sabrina
Michaud, Paris. Page 2 : © Iba
N'Diaye, Paris. Pages 3 (right), 6 :
Unesco Courier. Pages 4 (above), 5 : ©
A. Voznesensky, Moscow, Page 4
(below) : V. Savostianov © TASS,
Moscow. Page 7 : © TASS, Moscow.
Page 8 : © Benn, Paris. Pages 10-11 :
© Institut d'Orient, Paris. Page 12 :
© Charles Lénars, Paris. Page 13 :
Boisberranger © Hoa Qui, Paris.
Pages 14-15 : Castro © ANA, Paris.
Pages 15, 22 (below right) : Huet ©
Hoa Qui, Paris. Pages 16, 18, 24-25 :
Sioen © Cedri, Paris. Page 17 : ©
Roger Viollet, Pans. Page 19 : C.
Kazor © Rapho, Paris. Pages 20-21 :
© Gert Chesi, Schwaz, Austria. Page
22 (above) : Renaudeau © Hoa Qui,
Paris. Page 22 (below left) : Cassard
© Hoa Qui, Paris. Page 23 : Pavard
© Hoa Qui, Paris. Pages 24 (inset),
27, 38-39 (below) : © Dagli Orti,
Pans. Page 26 : © Ecole Nationale
Supérieure des Beaux Arts, Pans. Page
28 : Errath © Explorer, Paris. Pages
28-29 : © J.L. Nou, Paris. Page 31 :
Roland and Sabrina Michaud ©
Rapho, Paris. Page 32 : © Moghtader,
Paris. Pages 32-33 : G. Gerster ©
Rapho, Paris. Page 34 (inset) : ©
Claude Gonm, Paris. Pages 34-35, 35
(inset) : F. Hers © Cosmos, Paris.
Pages 36-37 : Pkou © A.A.A., Paris.
Page 36 (below) : © Bibliothèque
Nationale, Pans. Pages 38-39 (above) :
© Centro de Arte Moderna, Calouste
Gulbenkian Foundation, Lisbon.
Page 40 : G. Carde © Explorer, Paris.
Page 42 : © All Rights Reserved.
Page 43 (above) : Percheron ©
Artephot, Paris. Page 43 (below) : ©
Dominique Fournier, Paris. Pages 44,
45 : © Ginsburg, Paris. Pages 46, 47 :
Unesco/Arthur Gillette. Pages 48, 49
(above) : © F. Berthault, Bordeaux,
France. Page 49 (below) : © E.
Lerbeil.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
Published monthly in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Pans)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Russian edition: Georgi Zelenin
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel.: 45 68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85}
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Public relations: Claudie Duhamel (Tel. :45 68.45.86)
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prashad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kessler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A M Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
SALES ANO PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88), Assistant: Marie-
Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89), Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse
Hardy (45.68.45.65), Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité,
Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo,
Michel Ravassara, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45 68.45.64),
Accounts: Liliane Tasch (45.68 45.66), Cultural projects:
Ricardo Zamcra-Perez (45.68.45.80),
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
ADVERTISING
Publicat: 17, Boulevard Poissonnière, 75002 Paris.
Tel.: 40.26.51.26
Sales director: Benoît Rosier
Advertising director: Daniele Michelet
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 68 FF
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted trust bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international rep y coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is
produced m microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor. Michigan 48100, U.S.A., (3) N.C.R Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc.. 1 1 1 West 40th Street. New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and
Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A*
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) DEPOT LEGAL : CI FEVRIER 1990.
Photocomposition: The Unesco Courier
Photogravure- impression: Maury Imprimeur S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes,
45330 Maiesherbes
Vient de
paraître
Tableaux de référence
Education
Dépenses de l'enseignement
Science et technologie
Bibliothèques
Edition de livres
Journaux et autres
périodiques
Papier culturel
Archives
Musées et institutions
similaires
Film et cinéma
Radiodiffusion sonore et
télévision
Commerce international
en matière d'imprimés
1064 pages
ISBN 92-3-002561-5
350 francs français
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 2 1990 OPI 90 1 477 A
This issue comprises 54 pages and a 4 page advertisng insert
between pages 10-11 and 42-43
Just
published
Reference tables
Education
Educational expenditures
Science and technology
Libraries
Book production
Newspapers and other
periodicals
Cultural paper
Archives
Museums and related
institutions
Film and cinema
Radio and television
broadcasting
International trade in
printed matter
1,064 pages
ISBN 92-3-002561-5
350 French francs
LES PRESSES
DE L'UNESCO
services des ventes
THE UNESCO PRESS
sales division
LA EDITORIAL
DE LA UNESCO
servicios de ventas
7, Place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
Acaba de
aparecer
Cuadros de referencia
Educación
Gastos de la educación
Ciencia y tecnología
Bibliotecas
Edición de libros
Periódicos y otras
publicaciones periódicas
Papel cultural
Archivos
Museos e instituciones
similares
Películas y cines
Radiodifusión sonora y
televisión
Comercio internacional de
impresos
1064 páginas
ISBN 92-3-002561-5
350 francos franceses
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
' A
* .« « x
St;
11 /'*
*
(f>
:-
s
TV
j.
"»
\
»
a
fc
kv
?
H
\
FY -A
m *frv^-
\
í
V
>"*
.VaVJ
^ ^
/
//
'fi
©a
\ \ \
-' .
:^-.1
i* * f? * * *
L.* * ^ * » ft.
1
*£ v «> «O -f»»
S» Ä Ä. .-"
//,
// 1
^fc
US / ->L
]]>
</page>
</document>
