<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="085577eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
IN PURSUIT
OF THE PAST
I v
i ' *
vi
rr
5 French Ira
.£#££
'
H
M 1205 9004 -15,00 F
3791205O15OO1 90040l
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Hour photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
The Hole in the
Water or Toussaint,
Toussaint Louverture
27 x 36 cm
Indian ink
by Josette Verbestel
"(TOUSSAINT,
TOUSSAINT LOUVERTURE)
A single man who fascinates
the white hawk of white
death
A man atone in the sterile sea
of white sand
An old darky facing the waters
of the sky"
These lines from Cahier d'un
retour au pays natal (Return to
My Native Land), by the
Martinican poet Aimé Cesaire,
prompted a Belgian reader to
make this black and white
drawing. "It was inspired by
an attempt to understand and
to translate an idea in poetry
from another continent", she
JjSißi VO-íeite.1 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
APRIL 1990
N N
Today there are no more
unexplored continents,
unknown seas or mysterious
islands. But while we can
overcome the physical
barriers to exploration, the
barriers of mutual ignorance
between different peoples
and cultures have in many
cases still not been
dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can
voyage to the ends of the
earth. But a different kind
of Odyssey now beckonsan
exploration of the world's
many cultural landscapes, the
ways of life of its different
peoples and their outlook on
the world in which they live.
It is such an Odyssey that
the Unesco Courier proposes
to you, its readers. Each
month contributors of
different nationalities provide
from different cultural and
professional standpoints an
authoritative treatment of a
theme of universal interest.
The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes is respect
for the dignity of man
everywhere.
11
4
Interview with
HINNERK BRUHNS
'A past that won't go awry'
47
IN PURSUIT OF THE PAST IN BRIER.
THE MAKING OF HISTORY 	
47
14
HISTORY AND IDENTITY
Theodor Mommsen, a fiery patriot
by Hmnerk Bruhns
Jules Michelet, prophet-historian
by Christian Amalvi
Fernand Braudel, navigator in time and space
by Christian Amalvi
PORTRAIT
Anna Akhmatova,
'mother courage' of poetry
by Yelena Bydyakova 48
THE ROLE OF THE PAST IN FRENCH LIFE
Educating the nation
by Christian Amalvi
LETTERS TO
15 THE EDITOR
16
18
49
WORLDS ANCIENT AND MODERN
india. From the epic to scientific history
by Claude Markovits li
Indonesia. Pulling together the strands of time
by Denys Lombard 26
Mexico History or destiny?
by Miguel León-Portilla 29
united states A particular view of America
by Olivier Zunz 32
A UNIVERSAL HISTORY-
POSSIBILITY OR PIPE DREAM?
From Hegel to Marx, the saga of the dialectic
by Emmanuel Terray 37
A NEW MODEL FOR A UNIVERSAL HISTORY
World rhythms
by Robert Bonnaud 40
DOCUMENT
Oral tradition as a historical source
by Joseph Ki-2erbo 43
Cover: Le poète, oil on canvas by
the French painter
Jean-Louis Meissonier (1815-1891).
Back cover: L'avenir? Quel avenir?
d'après le Caravage (1984; "The
Future? What Future? after
Caravaggio"), acrylic on canvas
by the Peruvian painter Herman
Braun-Vega.
Special consultant for this
issue: François Hartog,
historian and director of
studies at the Ecole des
Hautes Etudes en Sciences
Sociales, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
I N I W
Some forty years after the guns of the Second World War fell silent, Ernst Nolte, of the Federal
Republic of Germany, fired the first shot in "the battle of the historians". This polemic concerned
the German people's relationship with their past and in particular with their darker memories
of the nazi period. With the reunification of the two Germanys now seemingly inevitable,
historian Hinnerk Bruhns points the way towards the rediscovery of an authentic German identity.
'A past that won't go away'
Hinnerk Bruhns
In 1986, the German historian andphilosopher Ernst Nolte
published an article entitled "A past that won't go away".
The article sparked offa long and impassioned debate that
came to be known as "the battle of the historians". It con¬
cerned the unique nature of the extermination of the Jews
by the nazis, which Nolte contested. The sociologist and
philosopher Jürgen Habermas accused Nolte and other
historians ofbecoming to some extent apologists ofthe Third
Reich. What importance do you attach to this controversy?
The real issue involved was the attitude of present-day
Germans to that specific period of their history. It concerned
the link between the collective memory and the notion of
national identity in the Federal Republic of Germany forty
years after the end of the Second World War.
This quarrel, which is in no sense an academic one, must
be put in context. It is a response to the repeated efforts
by certain leaders to use German history as a political
weapon and to distort the image of history as seen through
German eyes. The objective is to smooth the German
people's tormented relationship with their recent past and
with their history in general. A disturbed German identity
constitutes a destabilizing factor both within and outside
the country.
What are the historical roots ofthat identity?
Therein lies the problem. On this matter there are two
opposing viewpoints. Some hold that in searching for these
roots we have to bypass the period of the Third Reich and
make a direct link with the period that preceded it. Others
maintain that the period 1933 to 1945 was a unique episode
in world history, but that it cannot simply be erased. It
marks a discontinuity, an anomaly which makes it impos¬
sible for Germans ever to have a straightforward relation¬
ship with their history.
To understand this break with the past, we have to go
back to the position in which the Germans found themselves
in 1945. After its unconditional surrender, the German state
had ceased politically, militarily and morally to exist. In
1949, two German states, with diametrically opposed
political and social systems, were soon incorporated into two
equally opposed alliances: The front line of the Cold War
passed through the heart of Germany and its former capital.
The only way that the Federal Republic of Germany could
build itself anew was by making a total break with the past
and adopting Western democratic traditions that hitherto
had been rejected in Germany.
How did historians react to this dramatic chapter ofhistory?
At first they were at a loss. Ever since the nineteenth
century most of them had been convinced that their role
was to work for the construction of a national German state.
German national unity had been proclaimed the historic
German objective and the task of achieving it had been
entrusted to Prussia. This explains why, before the First
World War, history in Germany was not open to the
social and human sciences as it was in other countries. It
sought to be the political history of the national state and
nothing more, and this trend was strengthened after the
signing of the Treaty of Versailles after the war. Thus most
German historians were in a situation in which they were
ready to adopt the perverted nazi concepts of race, of peoples
and of the state and political power.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
After 1945, most historians became interested in ques¬
tions of universal history rather than contemporary topics.
Nevertheless, there were some, like Friedrich Meinecke, who
were critical of the German historiographical tradition. More
often, however, the German drama was seen as an act of
fate. Explanations of it were sought in the inexplicable, in
demoniac possession or in mob psychology. Apart from a
few scholars who had emigrated, such as Sigmund Neumann,
the main body of German historians were totally bereft of
appropriate instruments for studying nazism. The first step,
therefore, was to invent such instruments.
What was the extent of this break with the German
historical past?
Both the Federal Republic of Germany and the German
Democratic Republic were built up under the control of the
victorious Allied Powers and were intent on distancing
themselves from their past and their political traditions. Thus
it was impossible, for them to refer back to the Weimar
Republic, which was then seen as a negative experiment
whose institutions, it was suspected, had facilitated Hitler's
seizure of power. Only the old German federalist tradition
was taken up as a positive element.
The collapse had been so complete that there was no
opposition to this new start. Constitutionally, the young
Federal Republic wanted to be cleansed of all trace of nazism,
yet the higher civil service was impregnated with nazism.
It became officially taboo to mention the past nazi links of
many individuals and institutions. In this way it was hoped
to integrate into the new democratic state, not the past of
individuals, but individuals whose past had been surgically
removed.
Furthermore, the policy of the political and military
integration of the Federal Republic of Germany into the
Western camp implied that the "German question"the
demand for reunificationwould remain unanswered. This
made for a very ambiguous situation. To safeguard this
integration the Federal Republic of Germany was obliged
to refrain from insisting on its status as a fully sovereign
state whilst at the same time declaring itself to be the legal
successor to the Third Reich.
The fiction of the frontiers of 1937 was maintained
and thus of a hypothetical return to those frontiers; on the
other hand, the Federal Republic of Germany had to face
up to the moral and juridical obligation of indemnifying the
victims of German crimes during the Second World War.
In so doing the Federal Republic assumed responsibility for
crimes committed by Germans in the name of Germany.
At the same time, the Federal Republic was obliged to un¬
dertake a permanent effort, unique in history, of keeping
alive the memory of the nazi period so as to be able to in¬
scribe, in the very foundations of its policies, its total rejec¬
tion of this period and its abominations.
How, then, do you explain the all-pervading German
concern with the recent past?
The first decade of the existence of the Federal Republic
of Germany was marked by almost total silence on the
subject of nazi crimes. The wretchedness of post-war con¬
ditions and the demands and the successes of political and
economic reconstruction encouraged a thoroughly pragmatic
approach. Historical memory, at least to outward appear¬
ance, seemed to have lost all importance. In terms of foreign
Monument to the German emperor
William I (1797-1888) at Koblenz
(Fed. Rep. of Germany), former capital
of the Prussian Rhine Province.
¿C&J
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
policy, the Germans made the transition from being the
guilty defeated to the status of partners within the Western
alliance. Citizens and interest groups gave their wholehearted
support to the new state. The Federal Republic was seen
as a provisional solution, the German Democratic Republic
was not recognized and reunification became an objective
to be achieved within the framework of integration in the
Western camp. In the context of the Cold War, the divi¬
sion of Germany made anti-communism and firm attach¬
ment to the West the hallmarks of the identity of the Federal
Republic.
Forty years later, it can be affirmed that the democratic
experiment of the Federal Republic has been a success. The
Germans identify with their institutions, their economic
system and Western democratic values. The Constitution
has become an object of patriotic pride. The prospect of a
united Europe has also strengthened the desire to make a
break with the past. All this has cushioned the shock of the
"loss" of a page of recent history, which was such a heavy
burden to bear.
During the 1950s and 1960s, explanations of the failure
of the Weimar Republic tended to point to its excessive
democratic formalism rather than to the anti-democratic
mentality of the traditional governing elite. In addition, the
theory of totalitarianism, which historically and ideologi¬
cally assimilated nazism and Stalinist communism, helped
to justify the exclusion from German history of the period
\
II *
MUF
" -*
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Top, Hitler, the Führer
(leader), addressing a nazi
rally at Nuremberg.
Above, Nuremberg war
crime trials (1945-1946). The
wall-map shows territory
annexed or occupied by nazi
Germany.
Above left, Hitlerian
propaganda poster from the
early 1930s, bearing the
slogan "No more war!"
Left, Auschwitz, the largest
of the nazi extermination
camps (south of Cracow,
Poland).
of the Third Reich. This was classified as "a régime arbitrar¬
ily imposed on the German people and which could be
explained by Hitler's devilish powers of seduction and the
success with which he manipulated the divided masses", a
thesis denounced by the contemporary historian Hans
Mommsen.
It was not until the end of the 1950s that historians began
to undertake a painful revision of the image Germans had
of their history. The first step was to highlight the authoritar¬
ian elements inherent in the German political system, the
anti-democratic mentality of traditional political elites, the
political inertia of the workers' movement, excessive nation¬
alism and a desire for a powerful state and the specific form
taken by industrial development in Germany.
For the first time the deep underlying causes of the
process which led German politics to the crises of the twen¬
tieth century were brought out into the open. It was no
longer possible to ascribe the rise of nazism solely to the
economic crisis of 1929, to define it as a system of totalitar¬
ian domination imposed on the German people and to treat
it as a parenthesis in the continuity of German history.
What effect did this new awareness among German
historians have upon the great mass of their compatriots?
Did it transform popular comprehension ofGerman history?
During the 1960s, the way in which nazism was
presented in the media and in public debate was radically
transformed. The Eichmann trial and the resumption of
trials of war criminals broke the mantle of silence that had
hung over the question of the extermination of the Jews.
The Germans had been caught up by their own history.
The more public opinion became aware of the full
dimensions and monstrosity of the Holocaust, the more evi¬
dent became its uniqueness and the stronger became the
rejection of this period of history and the refusal of individu¬
als to identify themselves with it. This is how the historian
Eberhard Jäckel underlined the unique nature of the assas¬
sination of the Jews by the nazis: "Never before had a state
decided and announced, on the authority of its supreme
leader, that, as far as this was possible, a certain group of
human beingsincluding old people, women, children and
babes in armswere to be exterminated, and then attempted,
by all the means within its power, to carry through this
decision."
From the 1960s, the memory of Auschwitz became an
"objective reality" in Germany. But such was the strength
of their desire to escape acceptance of this period of their
past that the Germans were not immediately overwhelmed
by the moral shadow that it cast over their history. Ausch¬
witz figured strongly in theatre and literature, but it was
not until 1979, when the "Holocaust" series was shown on
television, that the general public felt its full impact. Fur¬
thermore, with the rise of protest movements and their
global rejection of bourgeois society, suspicion of nazism
began to appear like a gangrene affecting the whole history
of the Federal Republic. But by making an ideological
assimilation between capitalism and fascism, these move¬
ments ended up by taking the sting out of nazism.
At the end of the 1970s, the general public was showing
a renewed interest in history, as witness the success of the
1981 exhibition on Prussia, held in Berlin (West). Even if this
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
did not at first indicate an interest in the nazi past, curiosity
about the history of daily life led on to curiosity about
nazism in daily life. The shadow of the past seemed to be
stretching out even further.
The thinking of historians about the way in which nazi
power succeeded in imposing itself and about its structure
finally came to have political implications. Many stressed
the responsibility of the conservative elites and minimized
the relative importance of the role played by Hitler. They
maintained that Hitler would not have been able to impose
himself had there not been, in the background, an enormous
current of anti-liberal and anti-socialist feeling. This debate
continues today. Those who criticize this analysis because
it takes responsibility away from Hitler are criticized in their
turn for holding that he alone was to blame and thus
absolving the conservative ruling groups.
But as the social ramifications of the Hitler death
machine and the extent of the responsibility of those in¬
volved in its functioning become clearer, the more evident
becomes the extent to which the German bureaucracy and
armed forces were compromised with Hitler. It becomes
more and more difficult to exclude nazism from the general
sweep of German national history.
In spite ofthis, more and more voices can be heard demand¬
ing a "positive identification with the German past". What
is your interpretation of this attitude?
Many conservative historians consider that, in the
interest of political stability, national identity must be
anchored in the past, but that this attachment must be so
oriented as to give rise to a consensus. To achieve this some
are ready to resort to tricks and ruses about the past. But
there is another way of identifying with historyby
choosing the path of lucidity and courage. This is the path
chosen by President Richard von Weizsäcker when he
declared: "guilty or not, we must all accept the past. We
are all involved in its consequences and we are all obliged
to bear witness to it." It is also the approach adopted by
the historian C. Meier, who goes even further and considers
Auschwitz to be an important element in our social identity.
The demand for a selective "healthy" patriotism, which
would efface Auschwitz from German history, disguises
attempts, both deliberate and unwitting, to bring into ques¬
tion the very foundations of the historical identity of the
Federal Republic of Germany. It is perfectly legitimate to
retain the memory of democratic traditions that predate the
Third Reich, or even to emphasize this or that unfulfilled
potentiality of that past. These elements, however, weigh
less heavily in the makeup of the German identity than those
that marked the coming and the horrors of nazism. A lucid
view of history must incorporate the totality of the German
past, including all epochs whether they be positive or nega¬
tive. By the very fact of its birth, the political conscience
of the Federal Republic cannot have an unambiguous, aseptic
relationship with German history.
It is not the task of history to manufacture a tradition
that will receive general approval, but to throw light on
events and to study their causes. This involves continuously
reviewing and providing a historical basis for the ¡mage that
we have of our history, not interpreting it to suit political
necessities. Identity must be understood not as a given fact,
but as an open, pluralist process of reconciling different in¬
terests and points of view. This is one of the advances made
in the German approach to recent historyrecognition that
identity cannot be controlled on the sole basis of the logic
of the national state. Basically, identity can only be an amal¬
gam of a series of identities.
The specific nature of the German identity is the out¬
come of German history, which, in its turn, has always con¬
cerned the history of neighbouring peoples. But this is not
the only reason for their concern. The terrifying path fol¬
lowed by German history after 1933 has also to be seen as
one possible destiny for twentieth-century man and, there¬
fore, as a factor in the general history of European peoples.
Today, the new relationship which has been created between
history and identity in Germany can no longer be seen as
being solely a problem for Germans and their historians.
It must be an integral part of any reflection on the way a
united Europe will portray its history.
Do the events that have taken place in the German
Democratic Republic since November 1989 bring up again,
in a different way, the problem ofthe German identity and
its relationship with the past? What, for example, is the
position of the German Democratic Republic with regard
to nazism?
From the beginning, the German Democratic Republic
defined itself as an anti-fascist state which was intended to
represent a radical departure in terms of its relationship to
German history. The break with the historical past was
erected into state dogma and, as a result, as J. Rovan has
pointed out, the German Democratic Republic refused to
participate with the Federal Republic of Germany in indem¬
nifying victims of the former Reich, to undertake an
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Berlin Wall, before (left) and after its downfall in November 1989.
equivalent effort to keep alive the memory of the crimes
committed, or to seek out war criminals and bring them
to trial. After the failure of the political system established
in that part of Germany, however, society can no longer
concern itself simply with a critique of Stalinism: it will have
to examine the question of the inheritance of the period from
1933 to 1945. The German Democratic Republic could no
longer pick and choose from German history, nor claim
descent solely from the "good" periods of "progressive"
action. As it draws closer to the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many, it will have to share with it the German past.
How can two such divergent historical approaches be recon¬
ciled in view ofa possible confederation or even union of
the two states?
On 9 November 1989, the Germans living in two states
and under two radically different systems can be said to have
found themselves once again members of a single nation.
But for all that, it must not be forgotten that these two popu¬
lation groups have behind them forty years of differing his¬
tories, education and ways of life. Clearly this poses and will
long continue to pose a number of problems. West Germans
obviously see no reason to change their point of view, but,
on the other hand, the collapse of the communist regime
in the Democratic Republic does not imply that the East
German identity will disappear overnight. There remains
a sense of community, strengthened by the common
experience of sufferings and daily difficulties, as well as,
today, a sense of pride in having carried through a successful
revolution. Although the Federal Republic exercises a great
fascination and attraction for them, many East Germans are
still critical of it. They still dream of another kind of "good"
society, of a "true" form of socialism, and believe that they
will be able to bring their own values and ideals to the con¬
struction of a new Germany.
What is the major task facing the historian today?
In the German Democratic Republic, political libera¬
tion will enableindeed, will obligehistorians to make a
critical examination of the history of their country and, as
a result, to ask new questions, to open hitherto inaccessible
archives and to establish others. Now that official history
has vanished, a true history will have to be written. It will
be especially important that East German historians, in par¬
ticular the younger ones, have the opportunity of working
in collaboration with colleagues abroad.
The historian's raw material consists not only of events
and "material" facts, but also of visions based on the imagi¬
nation and memory of peoples. Today we have the impres¬
sion of a quickening pace of history, of living at a point of
new departure or at the end of the post-war period. At such
moments it is up to the historian to recall the weight of the
pastthe Second World War, genocideand to make people
aware of all the changes that have occurred since then. The
historian must act on the collective memory so as to put
people on their guard against the use for political purposes,
whether deliberate or not, of ingrained images and represen¬
tations. In this sense, the historian, in looking towards the
past, is working for the future.
In conclusion, I would like to recall something that Max
Weber said in 1917 about the German nation, quoting a
remark about Russia made by Aleksandr Herzen: "It is not,
and must not be, the land of its fathers, but the land of its
children."
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
I
"The Wheel of Time".
Indian miniature, 19th
century.
N his famous Histories of the Graeco-Persian Wars, Herodotus recorded a struggle
for dominance in the ancient world that spanned almost a hundred years (c. 546 to
448 BC). From its pages there gradually emerges a portrait of the "Greek identity",
or rather paired portraits of Greek and "Barbarian", since there can be no "We" without
a "They".
It is not surprising, therefore, that Cicero called Herodotus "the father of history",
since, whether they are concerned with the immediate or the distant past, historians
inevitably come up against the question of identity, to the extent that the role and
standpoint of the historian might well be defined in terms of this question. This is why
the Editors of the Unesco Courier have taken reflection on the past, and more particularly
on historical identity, as the theme of this second issue devoted to world historiography.
Herodotus was a man of the ancient world but, closer to our times, history and identity
have become ever more intricately intertwined. For the peoples of the former colonies,
the doubly difficult question is how to take back full possession of a past that the
colonizers often exhumed and, in almost the same breath, destroyed, rediscovering it
but judging it in terms of their own history.
Nineteenth-century European historians were obsessed with national unity, a notion
which they approached from different angles but with a passionate, common desire
to discover and promote it. Michelet favoured the direct approach, seeing France
personified rising up before his eyes. Mommsen, less direct, was fascinated by the analogy
between the ancient Roman Republic and its success in creating a united Italy, and
nineteenth-century Prussia fulfilling the same role in Germany.
In the turmoil and confusion of today's world, at the threshold of a new beginning,
the major task of historians, using tools, techniques and criteria appropriate to their
discipline, is surely to examine the notion of identity and to define new identities.
Throughout the modern world, the boundaries of identity, whether physical or symbolic,
are breaking up and becoming entangled and inflamed. Meta-identities (Arab, European)
and mini-identities (regional, ethnic, religious) are being simultaneously invoked. Identity,
it would seem, is a concept in a state of perpetual re-assessment and re-creation.
No definition of identity can fail to take the past into account, but a definition that
is based simply on a return to a "lost" past identity is pure illusion and could lead on
to bloody consequences. It is perhaps at this point, where past and present interlink,
that historians have a special contribution to make; for not only do they work with
and in terms of time, they also have to think themselves into its successive stages.
As the French poet René Char once wrote: "No will or testament bequeaths to us the
heritage of history."
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Three visions of history, three concepts of identity,
emerged from the works of Theodor Mommsen, Jules
Michelet and Fernand Braudel. Yet they shared a
common desire to encourage popular awareness of the
importance of studying the past. Perhaps BraudeVs was
the wider vision. To Marc Block's comment that "there
is no history of France, only a history of Europe", he
replied that "there is no history of Europe, only a history
of the world".
Dawn breaks over the ruins
of ancient Rome.
~%W?
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
history and identity
A
.-. ij
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THEODOR
MOMMSEN
A FIERY PATRIOT
A:
14
historian of Antiquity who was also one of
the greatest writers in the German language,
Theodor Mommsen (1817-1903) made profoundly-
original contributions to knowledge of ancient
Rome. His History ofRome (Römische Geschichte),
the first three volumes of which were published
between 1854 and 1856, earned him the Nobel
Prize for Literature in 1902.
Mommsen was the first historian to apply to
the study of history an array of disciplines ranging
from jurisprudence, linguistics and the history of
literature, to epigraphy, numismatics and ar¬
chaeology. The History ofRome is at once a po¬
litical, cultural, economic and social history. In
his Römisches Staatsrecht (1871-1888; "Roman
Constitutional Law"), he drew a picture of the
Roman state which was long accepted as
authoritative. For Mommsen, the Roman state
was based essentially on the interaction between
the magistrature, the senate and the community
of citizens. From this relationship sprang public
and criminal law, which Mommsen was also the
first to study systematically (Römisches Strafrecht,
1899; "Roman Criminal Law"). In Mommsen's
eyes, however, the key institution was the magis¬
trature, both in the Roman republic and in the
monarchy of early Rome.
Mommsen transformed the study of Antiq¬
uity both through his writings and through his
capacities as an organizer by endowing scientific
investigation of the past with the ambition and
the opportunity to produce great instruments of
research. He was the originator of the Corpus
Inscriptionum Latinarum, and played a major role
in the production of that monumental collection
of Latin inscriptions.
His History ofRome was written in the years
which followed the failure of the revolution of
1848. Hopes had evaporated of seeing Germany
united by the forces of liberalism and democracy.
Mommsen, who attached very great importance
to German unification, was profoundly affected
by this. At that time he supported the policy of
Prussia being carried out by Bismarck and at first
enthusiastically welcomed unification when it
was achieved in 1871.
He saw a historical parallel between Rome
and Prussia. The role of Prussia was to bring
about German unity just as the mission of Rome
had been to unify Italy. For him there was a
resonance between the history of Rome and the
times in which he lived.
He regarded Julius Caesar as the architect of
the Roman state, and believed that under Caesar's
rule the freedom of the Roman citizen was
guaranteed by what he considered to be an ideal
balance between government, law, unity and free¬
dom. But the evolution of the Roman empire
under Augustus, especially the loss of liberties,
brought Caesar's plans to naught, and his dream
of creating a great Italo-Hellenic nation never
came to pass. Mommsen's work ended with the
death of Caesar; the volume which was to deal
with the history of the principate, the first stages
in the reign of Augustus, never appeared.
If Mommsen did not pardon the Roman em¬
perors, he was equally critical of Bismarck for
divesting German unity of its democratic dimen¬
sion and depriving parliament of political power.
He despaired of the attitude of the German bour¬
geoisie which was satisfied with power and
prosperity, and was content to do without civic
liberties. "I have always been a political animal,"
he wrote in his testament, "and wished to be a
citizen. This has not been possible within the
framework of our nation, where the fate of the
individual, even the best, is that of regimentation
and political fetishism."
As a historian, Mommsen was a man of his
time. Even if we no longer assign a purpose to
history, as he did, we can reflect on his concep¬
tion of one of the historian's duties. "Whoever
writes history and especially the history of the
present," he wrote, "has a duty ofpolitical educa¬
tion. He must help those for whom he writes to
choose and define their future attitude to the
Theodor Mommsen
(1817-1903).
Julius Caesar
(100 or 101-44 BC).
state. HINNERK BRUHNS
Otto von Bismarck-
Schönhausen (1815-1898).
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
JULES
MICHELET
PROPHET-HISTORIAN
Wh' HETHER judged by his eventful career or by
his writings, Jules Michelet was no ordinary man.
The son of a modest printer who fell on hard
times brought on by professional and political
difficulties under Napoleon, Michelet was a fine
scholar, succeeding brilliantly in his secondary
and higher education and going on to become a
professor at the Ecole Normale Supérieure (1827),
head of the historical section of the Public Record
Office (1830) and, finally, professor at the Collège
de France (1843).
With his eloquence and ardent republican
convictions, he soon turned his chair of history
and moral philosophy into a political forum
which resounded to his diatribes against the
Jesuits (1843) and his declarations of unshakeable
attachment to the achievements of the Revolution.
His courageous fidelity to the Second Repub¬
lic led to the suspension, in 1851, of his lectures
at the Collège de France and he was dismissed
from his post at the Public Record Office for
refusing to swear allegiance to Napoleon III.
Although he stayed in France, in voluntary
"exile" far from Paris, he remained, like Victor
Hugo, an implacable opponent of "Napoléon le
Petit". At his death, in 1874, a crowd of over
10,000 followed the funeral procession of the man
who had spent his life in reviving the past the
better to ensure a future of liberty and fraternity
for the nation and the people.
The vast corpus of his work was not without
defects. Michelet's aim was to be a historian who
was technically unimpeachable. His work was
based on patient and meticulous research in the
archives. At times, however, he was betrayed by
his poetic imaginationhis apocalyptic vision of
the year 1000, for example, is today unanimously
rejected by the experts. He was also guilty of
flagrant partiality and bad faith with regard, first,
to the Roman Catholic Church, which he pur¬
sued with bitter enmity even into the dim recesses
of the past, and, second, to the French monar¬
chy, whose excesses of all kinds he highlighted
while neglecting to make an overall appreciation
of its achievements. In the end, this "high
priest" of an ideology both humanitarian and
patriotic, secular and Jacobinthe unwilling
inspiration of lyrical outpourings at banquets and
prize-giving ceremonies under the Third Republic-
exasperates rather than charms the reader of today.
To stop at these criticisms, however, would
be to miss the essential and to fail to understand
Michelet's enormous contribution. Through the
pages of his monumental Histoire de France (1833-
1869), this prodigious architect of the past por¬
trayed the countenance of France, endowed the
French nation with a living body, and gave a
voice to the French people.
For Michelet, as he himself would have been
the first to admit, France is a "person" whose
moral and material life is conditioned by its geo¬
graphy. It is no accident that Michelet saluted the
birth of France, in about the year 1000, with a
striking descriptive tableau in which the major
provinces are depicted as physiological organs
essential to the proper functioning of the body
social.
Like Augustin Thierry and François Guizot,
Michelet gave a completely new slant to the pur¬
pose of history. In place of the usual dry record
of the deeds and misdeeds of princes and great
men, he offered an epic account of the birth and
development of the French nation. He saw "The
Nation", not as an abstract, rational entity, but
as a living, suffering being, of flesh and blood,
that had to be apprehended with the heart and
the imagination rather than through the intellect.
He had lived through the heady, dangerous
days of the Paris Commune of 1792 and was the
first to bring to life the rage of the populace that
had punctuated the history of France from the
time of Etienne Marcel to that of Danton. No
one before him had managed to capture the spirit
of an era, in particular of the Middle Ages, with
such poetic and intuitive force. While it is true
that he equated the history of the French people
with Christ's Passion, sometimes in grandilo¬
quent terms, he was driven by a desire to capture
and illustrate the interactions between economic,
political, social and religious events, thus an¬
ticipating by a century the work of the historians
known as the "Ecole des Annales" and, in par¬
ticular, Lucien Febvre's "collective mentalities"
formula of history.
Jules Michelet (1798-1874).
La France,
a bronze by Auguste Rodin
(1840-1917).
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The last thing we should do is to limit our
assessment of Michelet to consideration of the
professor/ historian enveloped in the folds of his
scholar's gown. He was the equal of the giants
of the romantic generation of the 1830s, and with
its vast scope his Histoire de France is close kin to
Balzac's Comédie humaine. Strong in his creative
imagination, Michelet was the first French author
who really set out in search of the"remembrance
of things past". christian amalvi
HISTORY
RESURRECTED
When Michelet was appointed head of the historical
section of the French Public Record Office in 1830, a
hitherto unexplored region of research lay open to him.
w.IHEN first I entered these catacombs of
manuscripts, this necropolis ofnational monu¬
ments, I could well have echoed the words of
the German who, on entering the monastery of
Saint Vanne, declared: "Here is my habitation
and my resting place for all time. "
It was not long, however, before I realized
that the apparent silence ofthese galleries cloaked
a movement, a murmur which was not the
murmur of the dead. All these papers, these
parchments, asked nothing more than to see
again the light ofday. They were not just papers,
they were the lives of men, of provinces, of
peoples. First thefamilies, emblazoned in dust,
cried out against oblivion. The provinces rose
up, protesting that the forces of centralization
had sought to destroy them. The royal or¬
dinances ofour kings proclaimed that the mul¬
titude ofmodem laws had not effaced them. As
the grave-digger on the battlefield said: "Ifwe
had listened to them all, there would not have
, been one dead amongst them. "All were alive,
all spoke out, surrounding the writer with an
army ofa hundred tongues, brusquely silencing
the loud voice ofthe Republic and the Empire.
Easy now, dead sirs, let us proceed in orderly
fashion, ifyou please. You all have your place
in history. Each individual, each community
is as worthy as the next. Fiefdom, monarchy,
republic, all have right on their side.... The
provinces must live again; theforce ofgeography
must bring out the ancient diversity ofFrance.
This diversity must emerge again, but on con¬
dition that, as it graduallyfades, it will be suc¬
ceeded in turn by acknowledgement of the
country. Let the monarchy, let France live
again! Let a great effort ofclassification provide
a guiding thread through this chaos. However
imperfect, such a classification would be of
value. The head may sit awkwardly upon the
shoulders, the legs articulate badly with the
haunches, it is still something to live again.
As I blew away the dust, I saw them rise
up. From the sepulchre one drew a hand,
another a head, as in Michelangelo's "LastJudge¬
ment", or in the Dance of the Deadand this
jerky measure that they danced around me I
have tried to reproduce in this book.
Jules Michelet
a. HISTOIRE ut FRANCE
MICHELET
Cover of a popular edition
of Michelet's Histoire de
France published in Paris
around 1900.
HINNERK BRUHNS,
German historian, is in
charge of the Franco-
German programme of the
French National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS)
and director of studies at
the Ecole des Hautes Etudes
en Sciences Sociales, Paris.
He is the author of a
number of articles and
books, notably on the cities
of Antiquity and on
Mommsen and Weber.
CHRISTIAN AMALVI,
of France, has been a
librarian at the Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris, since 1980.
He has published some fifty
articles and books on the
teaching of history,
historiography, and the
history of national myths
in France between
1789 and 1989.
FERNAND
BRAUDEL
NAVIGATOR IN TIME AND SPACE
BY a strange coincidence, Fernand Braudel, like
Victor Hugo a hundred years before him, was
born when "this century was two years old" and
died at the age of eighty-three. He might have
been remembered only as the author of a dry aca¬
demic treatise on "Philip II, Spain and the
Mediterranean", had he not taken advice offered
in 1927 by Lucien Febvre, the highly original
scholar who was to be a co-founder of the influen¬
tial historical journal Annales, and met the great
Belgian historian Henri Pirenne in 1931. The in¬
fluence of Febvre and the Annales persuaded
Braudel to centre his work on the Mediterranean
world rather than the caprices of Philip II and
to study the empire of the Venetian merchants
and Genoan bankers instead of the Spanish em¬
pire during Spain's Golden Century.
Braudel sought to grasp the original charac¬
teristics, terrestrial and maritime, of the Mediter¬
ranean as a physical and geological entity
transcending national, religious and linguistic
frontiers and to record the fluctuating patterns
of human activity in the areathe unchanging
physical realities of life, mercantile trade, the
meandering course of what he called "battle-
history". To accomplish his project, he evolved
a global method of investigation which could be
applied throughout the region.
He made a famous dissection of history into
three different planes: a history which is virtually
unchanging, silent, mineral, the story of man's
contact with the natural environment; social his¬
tory which relates the life of economic groups,
peasant and urban societies, territorial states; and
the clamour of short-lived events that furrow the
surface of things.
Revolutionary by virtue of its geohistorical
conception of space and time, Braudel's thesis was
published in 1949 as La Méditerranée et le monde
méditerranéen a l'époque de Philippe II (The
Mediterranean and the Mediterranean World in the
Age ofPhilip II), a title in which the sea, not Philip
II, holds precedence. For its author, it opened the
doors of the Collège de France, where Braudel
succeeded Lucien Febvre in the chair of the His¬
tory of Modern Civilization.
Braudel's famous conception of "historical
time", magisterially expounded on 1 December
1950 at his inaugural lecture at the Collège de
France, found its ultimate expression in his major
trilogy Les structures du quotidien, Les jeux de
l'échange, and Le temps du monde (1979). In these
works Braudel constructs a three-storey edifice
as he did in The Mediterranean (although one with
infinitely vaster proportions since he is evoking
virtually all the continents): "at the base, a many-
sided, self-sufficient, routine material life; above,
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Fernand Braudel
(1902-1985).
Below, a 15th-century
portolan (navigational
chart) showing two of the
great maritime cities of the
Mediterranean, Genoa and
Venice. Marciana Library,
Venice.
a more clearly delineated economic life which
tended to merge into the economy of market
competition; on the third storey, capitalist
action."
To make this remarkable global assessment
of the world between the end of the Middle Ages
and the beginning of the industrial revolution,
Braudel invented a new perception of time: the
long term (longue durée). He added to the histori¬
an's equipment highly sophisticated research tech¬
niques borrowed from the human sciences.
"History itself," he admitted, "excites me less
than this associated panoply of the human
sciences... History itself, to be valid, must be in¬
corporated... into the other human sciences and
for their part the human sciences should take into
consideration the historical dimension." Thus
armed, Braudel resembled one of those bold
Renaissance navigators who abandoned the
coastal trade practised by their ancestors and
deliberately set sail for the high seas. For him the
high seas were the total history which Henri
Pirenne, Henri Häuser, Lucien Febvre, Marc
Bloch and Ernest Labrousse had explored before
him and whose first scientific maps he drew.
Braudel was also a peerless organizer who
protected his pioneering experiments and those
of his pupils within a flexible institutional frame¬
work. In 1948 he participated in the foundation
of the 6th Section of the Ecole Pratique des
Hautes Etudes in Paris, which became under his
leadership between 1956 and 1972 an international
centre for the study of the "new history". In 1962
he created and administered until his death
another leading institution for the study of the
social sciences, the Maison des Sciences de
l'Homme. Between 1946 and 1956 he directed
with Lucien Febvre and thereafter alone, the
review Annales, which was instrumental in im¬
planting social and economic history in the
French university system between 1955 and 1965.
Paradoxically, this great scholar who was also
no mean writer, was better known outside
Francein the Mediterranean basin, naturally,
but also in Poland and the United Statesthan
in his own country. The wider French public
only discovered the master of the Annales school
in 1979 when he appeared on the television liter¬
ary programme Apostrophes and talked about his
work Civilisation matérielle, économie et
capitalisme (Civilization and Capitalism, 15th-18th
Century). With Claude Lévi-Strauss and Georges
Dumézil, Braudel was one of the last great French
intellectuals who became a legend in their life¬
time. He was elected to the French Academy in
1984. CHRISTIAN AMALVI 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE ROLE OF THE PAST IN FRENCH LIFE
EDUCATING
THE NATION
BY CHRISTIAN AMALVI
H,
18
LlSTORY occupies such an important place in
French society todayin primary and secondary
schools, at universities, research institutions and
the mediathat it is difficult to imagine that this
has not always been the case. But the facts show
that the great respect for the historian's functions,
notably as a teacher, has not always existed but
is the offshoot of a stormy past. The story can be
divided into three main periods, corresponding to
radical changes in the French cultural landscape.
History on the sidelines:
1660-1814
In institutions of secondary education under the
ancien régime, history was a footnote to the Clas¬
sics. Inordinate importance was attached to Latin.
History was taught only indirectly by way of
historical commentaries on Latin texts, and was
learnt by translating the works of Livy, Sallust,
Caesar, Suetonius, Tacitus, Quintus Curtius and
other Latin authors. It had no independent exis¬
tence outside literature nor were any specialists
trained to teach it.
History was taught in certain colleges but did
not form part of the regular curriculum. It was
taught outside school hours on Sundays and feast
days and during the holidays.
History was considered to have only one
direct educational function, and that was a moral
one. The only real purpose of ancient history was
to provide a fund of moral examples. During the
Renaissance, the study of history was confined
to princes, who were supposed to derive specific
political rules from the past. In the late seven¬
teenth century history teaching was gradually ex¬
tended throughout the ruling classes, a restricted
group comprising the rich bourgeoisie, the no¬
bility and ecclesiastical dignitaries.
Clio, the Muse of history, instructs a young noble.
French allegorical engraving, 18th century.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Although many reform-minded teachers
wished to encourage the use of national history
as a basis for instruction, the bourgeoisie who
supported the Revolution in 1789 were more
familiar with the heroes of Livy and Tacitus than
with the great figures of French history.
The 19th century,
the golden age: 1814-1914
It is commonly said that in France the nineteenth
centurythe age of Augustin Thierry, Jules
Michelet, Hippolyte Taine, Ernest Renan among
otherswas an exceptional period for the writing
of history. This is true of history as an intellectual
and literary activity, but is less true if the place
of history is examined in primary, secondary and
higher education against the background of the
political vicissitudes of France between 1814 and
1914. The alternation of liberal and conservative
regimes had profound repercussions on the
teaching of history, which had mixed fortunes.
The early years, from 1814 to 1830, were not
easy. Scarcely had history been made a compul¬
sory subject in secondary schools, by a decree of
15 May 1818, than it fell out of favour. In 1820,
after the ultra-royalists had come to power,
several chairs of history were abolished in Paris
lycées, as was Guizot's course in modern history
at the Sorbonne.
The period of the July monarchy was, on the
contrary, a golden age. Historical studies were
given a boost by the establishment of the Com¬
mittee of Historical Works in 1834. In 1838
Michelet, who had been appointed head of the
historical section of the Public Record Office
in October 1830 by Guizot, was elected as a
professor at the Collège de France (see page 15).
Most important of all, the regime endeavoured
to give increasing prominence to history in the
lycées and colleges. Starting in 1830 between four
and six new history teachers were appointed
annually on the basis of a competitive examina¬
tion. Between 1830 and 1848 the number of his¬
tory textbooks rose sharply. By the eve of the
1848 Revolution, history was considered to be
a subject of the first importance in secondary edu¬
cation, although its impact had still not reached
the mass of the people.
There were several reasons why the situation
had improved. During this period two celebrated
historians, Guizot and Adolphe Thiers, held
office as premier. At a deeper level, the period
coincided with the Romantic movement which
rediscovered the past in general and the Middle
Ages in particular, just as the first humanists of
the Renaissance had rediscovered Antiquity: as
eras that were gone forever.
In the same way, the watershed of the Revo¬
lution conferred a mythical dimension on French
national history, and in the early nineteenth cen¬
tury learning about it was akin to engaging in a
sacred quest for the origins of the nation. Finally,
La République (1848),
by the French artist
Jules Claude Ziegler
(1804-1856).
at the political level, King Louis-Philippe sought
to steady his shaky throne by appealing to history
to support the claim that his regime was the
"happy medium", the necessary outcome of the
whole of French history and the only govern¬
ment capable of reconciling the ancien régime and
the Revolution.
This momentum was shattered during the
authoritarian years of the Second Empire which
complained that history was a subversive subject!
In 1852 the competitive examination for secon¬
dary-school history teachers was abolished and
Michelet was driven out of the Collège de France
and obliged to resign from his post at the Public
Record Office. For more than ten years order
prevailed in a discipline which had been forced
to toe the line, and it was not until the appoint¬
ment, during the liberal years of the Empire, of
an eminent historian of Rome, Victor Duruy, to
the post of minister of education (1863-1869), that
history recovered its place in the lycées and
colleges and began to be introduced officially into
primary-school curricula. However, Duruy's
liberal reforms were checked by the disasters of
the "terrible year" which saw France's military
defeat at the hands of Prussia in 1870 and the
proclamation of the Paris Commune in the spring
of 1871.
A consensus began to emerge regarding the 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
need to give the whole of society a solid basis of
knowledge about the national past in order to
revitalize the country after its collapse. But
political disagreements re-emerged when the time
came to define the content of history teaching.
The Catholics were bent on resuscitating an ideal¬
ized Middle Ages, a Christian model in which
inspiration for the "salvation of France" was to
be sought. On the left, the Republicans set store
by the study of the Revolution and its aftermath
as a training for enlightened citizens, aware of
their political duties, and as a means of sparing
France the infernal cycle of revolution followed
by monarchist or Bonapartist repression. This
programme of reform only began to be applied
by Jules Ferry and his friends in 1880.
The Third Republic ushered in a second
golden age for history which was to last far longer
than the first under the July monarchy. There
were two main reasons for this. Firstly, positi¬
vism provided historians with a method that had
been tried and tested and with a well-organized
stock of knowledge. Secondly, the Republic had
a far broader social base than the hesitant
Orleanist monarchy and was able as a result to
extend the influence of history to the whole of
French society.
Thanks to the evergreen history textbooks
of Ernest Lavisse (especially those published in
1884 and 1913), the portrayal of the nation's past
became, in primary schools, the natural means
of diffusing Republican ideology among the
broad mass of French people, and provided an
ideal opportunity for the consecration of the
Patrie, of the state as the custodian of national
unity, and of democracy, the daughter of the
French Revolution, in the villages.
At the same time, higher education institu¬
tions ceased to be regarded as places where
fashionable lectures were given and gradually
acquired a pre-eminent role in the training of
secondary-school teachers and as centres for scien¬
tific research modelled on the German universi¬
ties. A law passed in 1902 gave greater weight to
contemporary history in secondary education as
an instrument of civic instruction for the elite,
dedicated to the cult of scientific and social
progress. This edifice, symbolized by the new
Sorbonne rebuilt in the heart of the old Latin
Quarter between 1883 and 1901, was to last, in
spite of increasingly serious fissures, more or less
until the beginning of the 1960s.
20
From positivism to television: 1919-1989
The twentieth century has seen unprecedented
developments in the teaching of history. At
primary level, it was thanks to the patriotic spirit
instilled by the textbooks of Lavisse and his suc¬
cessors that the French poilu held out in the mud
of the trenches for four long years and that the
flame of the Resistance was not extinguished
beneath the nazi heel. The teaching of history in
secondary schools, associated with the teaching
of philosophy, also achieved the purpose set by
the reformers of 1902. It contributed to the emer¬
gence of an elite imbued with republican ideals,
able to withstand the temptation of fascism in
the 1930s and to rebuild a democratic France after
1945. Finally, the reform of higher education
lived up to the hopes placed in it. The French
doctoral thesis has become a masterpiece of
positivism which opens the door to professor¬
ships and is regarded in other countries as an
illustration of the vigour of the French school of
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Still from La Chanson de
Roland (1977; "The Song of
Roland"), a film by Franck
Cassenti on the deeds of the
medieval French epic hero.
Detail from a mural by
François Flameng
(1856-1923) at the Sorbonne,
Paris, depicting 19th-
century French historians.
From left to right, Edgar
Quinet, Abel François
Villemain, François Guizot,
Jules Michelet, Victor
Cousin and Ernest Renan.
historiography. The continual increase in staff
since 1880 has probably been another factor
which has led to the healthy situation of history
in France in this century.
However, this constant progression masks
the serious difficulties experienced by teachers.
If a textbook helped France to win the 1914-1918
war, primary-school teachers between 1919 and
1939 were horrified by the spread of jingoism and
became ardent pacifists. Then again, the often
naive cult of the Revolution and the caricaturing
of the ancien régime have long provoked the anger
of the Catholics, particularly in western France.
Although secondary education experienced a
kind of golden age until 1945, the massive influx
of young people into the lycées and colleges called
into question the task assigned to history teachers
by the bourgeois Republicthe training of
elites and replaced it with responsibility for
educating the nation, which it is not always easy
to discharge.
Furthermore, in the late 1950s many teachers
became critical of an approach to history teaching
which they considered to be rigid and outmoded,
and endeavoured to introduce into the schools
the "new history", largely dominated by eco¬
nomic and social factors, which was being deve¬
loped within the university system by the
members of the editorial board of the journal
Annales. This journal, founded in 1929 by Lucien
Febvre and Marc Bloch, sought to take by storm
the positivist New Sorbonne, which gave pride
of place to political and military events, and to
replace the traditional "battle-oriented history"
by a "problem-oriented history" open to the
fertile methods of the new human and social
sciences: anthropology, sociology, ethnology,
economics and linguistics.
Thanks to the efforts of Fernand Braudel (see
page 16), in the early 1960s the university yielded
to the "Ecole des Annales". But for the profes¬
sion as a whole, this success soon looked like a
pyrrhic victory. After 1969 the teaching of his¬
tory, labelled a "general cultural subject" in
primary education, became virtually moribund.
Ten years later, the attempt to introduce into
secondary education a theme-oriented history
which had little concern for chronology plunged
teachers and parents into confusion. At univer¬
sity level history at the end of the 1960s seemed
in danger of becoming an appendage of the social
sciences, and particularly of sociology, dominated
at that time by Marxism and structuralism.
Twenty years on, history has made a spec¬
tacular recovery. A vigorous press campaign con¬
ducted by the gifted journalist and historian Alain
Decaux, who has become a kind of schoolteacher
to the nation through his presentation of histor¬
ical events on television, has enabled the teaching
of history at primary level to regain its soul. In
secondary education, the errors resulting from
certain reforms have been effaced. Last but not
least, the "history of mentalities" has taken over
from a jaded form of economic history and,
returning to the spirit of Michelet's pioneering
intuitions, has given a new lease of life to the
"Ecole des Annales". Whereas the social and
human sciences, after ruling supreme, are now
in a state of crisis, history, which has struck a deli¬
cate balance between tradition and modernity,
seems to be in sound condition. Historians, who
only yesterday were cooped up in libraries and
archives, have become media figures. In a society
that is stepping into the future while looking back
at the past, they cater to an interest in historical
roots and the archaeological heritage. They will
never be done with teaching, rewriting and
reinterpreting sometimes in the midst of sound
and furythe history of France and the French.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
worlds ancient and modern
India, cradle of an ancient civilization, and the
United States of America, a continent "without a
past" but with a strong imported Puritan tradition,
represent two diametrically opposed temporal and
historical worlds. Between the two extremes lies a
whole gamut of intermediates. Common to all is the
historical quest summed up in Fernand Braudel's
dictum: "The price of nationhood is an unceasing
search for national identity."
Panorama of Tenochtitlán, the capital of the
Aztec empire located where Mexico City now
stands, at the beginning of the 16th century.
¿W * Ç - fi»* ~~ f" " '-+jál ' 	
JS^^MWM.-iil»^	
yj. >^(Wjl
A
i
'a.-'
n»**' "-¿J* ¿z -fr.
/Äía/*-^
»l-*1í«(|
BY- J«^^'"^
* -> I M
iiW^
\m¡
jSX l^jh i#¿M^fe
m3
*3ÉtkT*'\
*M. \$\rJU:fr * J » -^x B l! *«>.'
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
INDIA
Sculpted heads of the late Gupta period (5th-6th
century AD), from Akhnur, near Jammu (Kashmir).
.;- '
lUiiiiiui
-'"Hi'l'lniii
iiiítíHiiijíij1
FROM THE EPIC
TO SCIENTIFIC
HISTORY
BY CLAUDE MARKOVITS
D.'OES India have a history? This question has
always troubled historians, especially in relation
to the long period extending from the Aryan in¬
vasions to the arrival of the Muslims in the
twelfth century. There are two kinds of source
for this period, which saw the emergence and
blossoming of Hindu civilization: normative texts
such as the Vedas and epics on the one hand, and
on the other, archaeological documents.
However, correlating the two presents insur¬
mountable difficulties. Some scholars firmly deny
the historical nature of the epics, which they be¬
lieve to recount purely mythical events without
any historical foundation. They point to the ha¬
ziness of the scattered geographical references
which the epics contain and to the great uncer¬
tainty about when they were composed. Another
school of Indian scholars believes that the find¬
ings of certain recent excavations confirm the
historicity of the events related in the epics.
In fact the quarrel is a philosophical one.
Long ago Hegel proclaimed the non-historical
character of Indian civilization. Stressing that the
"time which elapsed before the appearance of
written history. ..was without objective history
because it had left no subjective history or histor¬
ical account", he drew attention to the contrast
between India, "this country so rich in profound
spiritual achievements", and China, which "pos¬
sessed an outstanding history, going back to the
most remote times".
The lack of ancient Indian historical writings
is undeniable. With the exception of the Kashmir
chronicle, there is no text of a historical nature
prior to the Muslim conquest. Starting in the late
twelfth century, historical texts were written to
the glory of the Muslim sovereigns. The most
illustrious representative of this school of writing
was Ferishta, the historian of the Deccan. This,
imported genre, written in Persian, had only a
.limited influence.
Students of
Indian civilization
.....
The birth of would-be scientific historiography
is linked tothé British' conquest of India, which
began in .1757 and was all but over in 1818. But
this form of writing was inherited from elsewhere
and it was practised only by the colonizers, at
least until around 1830.
Sir w/iiliam Jones (1746-1794), who founded
the Asiatic Society of Calcutta in 1784, laid the 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Scenes from the Ramayana,
the great Sanskrit epic
recounting the heroic deeds
of prince Rama. Malwa
school painting, 17th
century.
J> - Ï- -, £.'
i . -a . Z - O US a.
24
*-i ^3,
^i;;ii.-í^^^'¿^^tfc^iAt¿4.^a_^ii»a;íiy¿
Copper plaque inscribed
with Brahmi characters,
issued by king Salankayana
Nandivarman II (4th
century AD). From Pedda
Vegi (Andhra Pradesh).
A prince pays homage to
Babur (1483-1530), the first
Mughal ruler of India. Late
16th-century miniature.
CLAUDE MARKOVITS,
of France, is director of
research at the National
Centre for Scientific Research
(CNRS), Paris. He is the
author of Indian Business and
Nationalist Policies, 1931-39:
The Indigenous Capitalist
Class and the Rise of the
Congress Party (Cambridge
University Press, 1985).
foundations for a chronology of ancient India.
Most of the members of the Society belonged to
the British ruling elite. Whether judges or ad¬
ministrators, their curiosity about India and
things Indian was not entirely innocent. Getting
to know the country better might help them to
control it more effectively. But they were also
men of the Enlightenment and they wanted to
learn about one of the great civilizations of hu¬
manity. They admired the culture of ancient
India, but considered it inferior to that of classical
Greece, which was a model of perfection for
Europeans at that time.
The most violent attack against the civiliza¬
tion of India was launched by James Mill (1773-
1836), a prominent representative of Utilitarianism
or "philosophical radicalism" and father of the
famous John Stuart Mill. His History of British
India (1817), the earliest attempt to arrive at an
overview of Indian history, attracted wide atten¬
tion and exercised considerable influence.
A senior official of the East India Company
stationed in London, Mill never set foot in India
and worked from secondary sources. Contemp¬
tuous of facts, he regarded history as a branch of
philosophy and poked fun at the gullibility of the
"orientalists". The ancient Hindu writings? Pure
fabrication having no value as a historical
source an attitude still held today by certain In-
dologists. India before the Muslim conquest? A
monotonous succession of despots, each more
barbaric than the last, whose authority was but¬
tressed by the most enormous and most frightful
superstition. The Muslim era? Barely a step away
from the dark ages of Hinduism. The history of
India really began when the Europeans arrived,
especially the British.
Mill did not contribute anything to historical
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
research on India, but he influenced generations
of historians. His division of Indian history into
three periodsancient (Hindu), medieval (Mus¬
lim) and modern (British)although long su¬
perseded, still survives in textbooks. Through his
attacks on the orientalists, he was also instrumen¬
tal in focusing historical studies on the modern
age. Earlier periods were studied by a small circle
of specialists.
As a result, such important discoveries as the
deciphering of Brahmi script in 1833 by James
Prinsep (1799-1840) aroused little interest. There
was a gulf between the research of the orientalists
and historical works in which British authors
concerned themselves mainly with the history of
their compatriots in India.
Mountstuart Elphinstone (1799-1859), who
knew India at first hand and had an openminded
attitude towards Indian culture, broke new
ground. In his History ofHindu andMuhammedan
India (1841) he provided the first plausible com¬
prehensive chronology for ancient Indiathe
main lines of which still remain valid todayand
for the first time included southern India, which
had until then been neglected.
The awakening of
a national consciousness
The following period marked both the zenith
of the imperialist school of history and the
beginnings of a nationalist Indian historiography.
The first indigenous historians, such as Raja
Sivaprasad, author of the Itihas Timir Nasak
(1866), written in Hindi and used as a school text¬
book in northern India, judged their own society
very harshly.
In the 1870s, however, an anti-Western move¬
ment began to take shape, especially in Ma¬
harashtra. Intellectuals, whether writers or
pamphleteers, who took their cue from the rise
of nationalism in Europe, bewailed the lack of
a national historiographie tradition. The great
Bengali writer Bankimcandra Chatterjee
(1838-1894) used the form of the historical novel
to glorify the Hindu past of Bengal. The ques¬
tion of the relations between Hindus and
a *
B
Vast crowds turned out for
the funeral of Gandhi in
1948.
The great "durbar" (formal
reception) held in Delhi in
1903. Illustration from a
contemporary French
newspaper.
V -
* \.
Muslims was already influencing the writing of
history.
The nationalist school of history began to
come into its own around 1910. A growing num¬
ber of its members belonged to the expanding aca¬
demic community. H.C. Raychaudhuri, K.P.
Jayaswal, R.K. Mookerji and H.C. Ojha were in¬
terested in ancient India. They endeavoured to
combat the Hegelian view of a non-historic India
by studying, in particular, the development of
political institutions. Even though their work
does not always meet the scientific criteria of his¬
tory as it is understood today, their role in the
awakening of an Indian national consciousness
is not negligible.
The greatest Indian historian of India,
Jadunath Sarkar (1870-1958), is known mainly for
his work on the end of the Mughal period and
the Marathas. His writings, which are in a vivid
style and show immense erudition, are still widely
read.
Since the 1960s Indian historiography has
drawn nearer to the other social sciences. Major
controversies are regularly generated by historical
studies. This effervescence attests to the vitality
of historical studies in a country that clearly in¬
tends to make its own distinctive contribution
to the history of humanity. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
INDONESIA
PULLING TOGETHER
THE STRANDS
OF TIME
Y DENYS LOMBARD
I
26
N the Indonesian Archipelago, it was not until
the spread of Islam in the fifteenth and sixteenth
centuries that the idea of time as Promethean,
linear, directional and evenly distributed (in
Malay waktu, from the Arabic wakt) gradually
began to win at least partial acceptance.
Today two different and parallel concepts of
time exist in this region. On the one hand there
is historical time, references to which can be
found as early as the seventeenth century in cer¬
tain Malay treatises which mention dated events
and, above all, the collective destiny of the
Muslim community. This homogeneous, neutral
time is punctuated solely by the major festivals
of Islam. On the other hand there is a non-
historical, immobile time in which the days are
distributed according to a traditional system of
classification, still greatly in evidence in Java and
Bali. Each moment, far from being neutral, is con¬
sidered to have a particular density or "key sig-
Temple at Besakih, Bali. nature" which can be discovered only by com¬
plicated calculations and which a person must
know before undertaking any important action.
This duality is essential for understanding the
way in which the idea of history (sejarah) has
developed. For simplicity's sake, it can be said
that the first conception of time gave rise to the
hikayat or Malay stories and that from the second
derived the babad or Javanese chronicles.
The Dutch settlers made two positive con¬
tributions to the civilization of the region. They
brought with them, first, the idea of directional
time, which could not but reinforce the concept
of time in evidence in the hikayat, and, secondly,
a partiality for the systematic study of texts.
However, their outlook was inevitably tainted by
Eurocentrism. Oud en Nieuw Oostindien, written
at the beginning of the eighteenth century by a
pastor, François Valentyn, recounted the history
of the Archipelago and Asia on the basis of
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Batavian chronicles and the fortunes of the Dutch
East India Company. This dual approach, rooted
in both scientific respect for documents and the
unconscious cynicism of the European settler,
became ever more marked in the following
centuries.
A passion for philological enquiry underlay
the search for Malay, Javanese, Balinese, Buginese
and other manuscripts, the study of inscriptions
on stone and copper, and interest in the monu¬
ments of the Indo-Javanese past generally.
However, Eurocentrism lay at the heart of
most of the synoptic studies that came out at
around the same time and which focused on the
periods of Indianization and of the Batavian con¬
quest. Two major themes emerged which were
to complement one another. The first was the im¬
portance of Indian influence, which was confined
to Java and Bali but was essentially beneficial and
led to the creation of great kingdoms, such as
Majapahit in Java, in the thirteenth to fifteenth
centuries and to the development of a fascinating
classical art. The second major theme was the cen¬
tral role of the Dutch East India Company, which
achieved single-handed the feat of bringing
together the scattered islands of the Archipelago
into one large political unit.
The role of the coastal sultanates in the
fifteenth to the seventeenth centuries was syste¬
matically ignored and if Islam was mentioned it
was in order to denounce its baneful effects.
The reaction of the first
nationalists
The early nationalists tried to turn European
intellectual weapons against the Europeans. They
soon realized how useful it would be to recover
the glorious past which the philologists had
restored to them. However, they had a great deal
to do before shaping the national history which
they needed and founding the independent state
of their dreams. The idea of a common historical
destiny was far from being universally accepted.
Nor did the material they found in Dutch text¬
books always make their task easier.
The first signs of the new climate of opinion
appeared at the end of the nineteenth century,
particularly in Java. This awareness of the cul¬
tural heritage was expressed even more clearly by
the members of the Budi Utomo, an association
founded in 1908 by a small group of Javanese
wishing to revive their traditions. In 1911 Doctor
Radjiman, a native of Yogya who had played an
active part in the launching of this movement,
declared before a Dutch audience that there could
be no question of Westernizing the Javanese: "If
the indigenous people are torn from their past
they will become rootless misfits, lost between
two civilizations."
The issues were spelt out in 1935 in a debate
triggered by Sutan Takdir Alisjahbana, who
rejected all nostalgia for the past and thought that
the first priority was to try to imitate the West
in order to catch up. Professor Purbatjaraka, a
native of Surakarta, who had been one of the first
to take over the philological method introduced
by the Dutch, insisted more than anyone else on
the importance of the past: "Only when we are
familiar with the course of our history from the
earliest times shall we be able to organize our
future properly."
Sanusi Pane went even further. Born in
Sumatra but strongly attracted to Javanese cul¬
ture, the man who was to write the first history
of Indonesia (1943-1945) criticized Sutan Takdir's
craving for novelty and praised the sage Arjuna,
the hero of the Mahabharata whose preference
was for spiritual values, unlike the Westerners'
Faust, who did not flinch from selling his soul
for material gain.
A thinker who became acutely aware of the
problem was the Javanese Suwardi Surjaningrat,
better known by the name of Ki Hadjar Dewan-
tara (1889-1959). "We live," he wrote in 1929,
"like the clients of a hotel belonging to others,
who seek neither to improve nor to equip the
house in which they live, because they do not feel
that it is theirs." Dismayed by this passivity, he
wished first to restore to his contemporaries their
dignity and their identity. He was not automati¬
cally hostile to the West but thought that no
association was possible unless the Indonesians
could define their cultural identity.
History during
the Sukarno period
In view of the importance that these nationalists
attached to cultural identity (kepribadian), it may
seem surprising that the Sukarno period did not
produce a truly national history. Sukarno
(Indonesian president from 1949 to 1966) was
fond of repeating that "history must not be
forgotten under any pretext", but the efforts
made at the time to write a general history foun¬
dered on account of numerous differences of
opinion.
The Dutch East India
Company fleet in the bay of
Batavia (now Jakarta),
capital of the Dutch East
Indies. In foreground, a
merchant and his wife.
Painting by Aelbert Cuyp
(1620-1691).
DENYS LOMBARD,
French historian, is director
of studies at the Ecole des
Hautes Etudes en Sciences
Sociales, Paris. A specialist
on the Indian Archipelago
and co-editor of the
interdisciplinary review
Archipel, he is the author of
studies on the sultanate of
Aceh in Sumatra (1967) and
on the history of Java (3
volumes, forthcoming). 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Detail from a bas-relief in
the vast temple complex at
Prambanan, one of the
finest examples of central
Javanese art (late 9th-early
10th century).
28
Fascination with Javanese history is the most
striking feature of Muhammad Yamin's
voluminous works, which sometimes give the im¬
pression of having been written by an official
historian. As early as 1945 Yamin wrote an essay
about Gajah Mada, who was chief minister of the
fourteenth-century King Hayam Wuruk and
reunited Indonesian lands around Java and its
then centre, Majapahit. Above all, he sought to
use the findings of epigraphy or philology to
stimulate the pride of his compatriots and justify
the political demands of his government.
Meanwhile, recent victims of arbitrary Dutch
rule and those who had stood up against the East
India Company were granted the status of local
or national heroes (pahlawan). Many streets were
named after them. This was a widespread
phenomenon. In Java and elsewhere each region
honoured its heroes. Their biographies were
written, they were depicted in imagery, the real
or assumed graves of some of them were restored
and became places of pilgrimage. In 1959 the
authorities drew up an official list of national
heroes.
In addition to this vast hagiographie under¬
taking, ideologists considered to be progressive
were recreating history. A more searching histor¬
ical analysis, the first outlines of a social history,
might have been expected from these intellectuals
who purported to be Marxists. The Madilog
(acronym of Materialisme-Dialektika-Logika),
written by Tan Malaka in 1942-1943, shortly after
his return from exile, and representing the first
dialectical approach to Indonesian history, with
its simple not to say simplistic division into
periods, has more in common with utopianism
than with Marxist analysis.
Less poetic but historically more reliable in
the sense that it contains precise references to
epigraphy and Javanese chronicles is D.N. Aidit's
"Indonesian Society and Indonesian Revolution",
a textbook written in 1957 for the schools of the
Communist Party. It none the less appears to be
no more than window-dressing for ideas imported
from the West. The Marxist tool, instead of
prompting a profound analysis of society and
inspiring an original approach to periodization
highlighting for instance the expansion of trade
in the sultanates in the sixteenth and seventeenth
centuries, or the development of the economy of
the plantations in the nineteenth centuryloses
its fine edge when applied to colonial chronology
and merely serves to rename the different stages.
History and the New Order:
from 1966 to the present
President Suharto's New Order made an effort
to learn from the historical methods developed
in the West. The old idea of a national history
was revived and the groundwork was carefully
laid through numerous seminars for the prepa¬
ration of the six-volume textbook which even¬
tually appeared in 1975. The following
breakdown into periods was adopted and an¬
nounced at a seminar held in Yogyakarta in
August 1970: prehistory, the Indianization period,
the sixteenth-eighteenth centuries, the nineteenth
century, 1900-1942, post-1942. One virtue of such
a time-division, debatable though it may be in
other respects, is that it integrates into the history
of the nation prehistory and protohistory, which
are regarded as essential formative periods before
Indianization. It also recognizes the importance
of the period from the sixteenth to the eighteenth
century, which is no longer considered to be
purely colonial but to have been strongly marked
by Islam and the formation of the sultanates.
Indonesian historiography then underwent a
distinct change. Regional history was taken into
account, and a series of local seminars were or¬
ganized in order to secure the collaboration of
scholars in the provinces and to bring them into
contact with historians. The latter also became
more open to archaeology, although archaeology
and history were still taught separately at the
university. The hagiographical tone was some¬
what tempered by exposure to the facts. A com¬
parative history of South Asia slowly emerged
which held out promise in so far as it allowed
nationalistic prejudices to be overcome.
Institutions which had previously taken little
interest in their history have now adopted a
historical perspective. Among them are the army,
which now has its own history department and
museums, the Protestant and Catholic Churches,
and the state Islamic Institutes, which have begun
preparing a history of Indonesia from the Muslim
point of view. The old practice of hagiography
still looms large, but these recent developments
are leading to consciousness of a linear history
and form part of a slow progression towards what
I have called historical time.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
MEXICO
HISTORY
OR DESTINY?
BY MIGUEL LEON-PORTILLA
ELexicans have always exhibited an obstinate
determination to safeguard the memory of the
major events that have marked their society and
this has coloured the way in which they view
their identity and destiny. From pre-Columbian
times they have been engaged in a continuous
battle to save their history from oblivion.
Knowledge of the past was the foundation on
which their priests and diviners based their as¬
tronomic calculations and their predictions of the
future. Countless archaeological remains from the
two thousand years before the arrival of the
Spaniards in 1519 bear witness to the Mexican
desire to interpret and record the history of gods
and man. The stelae known as danzantes
("dancers") at Monte Albán in the Oaxaca valley,
on which are inscribed a record of the passing
days and years, place-names and the names of
kings and other notables, constitute the oldest
Two of the danzantes
("dancers") stelae carved in
Olmec style, c. 300 BC. Pre-
Columbian city of Monte
Albán, Mexico.
m
yjfr
known chronicle (600 to 300 BC) of the New
World.
The people, or rather peoples, who succeeded
one another on Mexican soil met with mixed for¬
tunes. Bursts of creativity were punctuated by
times of crisis and war which even led to the
abrupt disappearance of entire populations and
civilizations. The memory of these events lives
on in the thousands of inscriptions and the
legends of oral tradition.
The greatest and most tragic clash of cultures
in pre-Columbian civilization was recorded by
some of those who took part in the conquest of
Mexico. Hernán Cortés himself sent five remark¬
able letters (Cartas de Relación) back to Spain be¬
tween 1519 and 1526; and the soldier-chronicler
Bernai Díaz del Castillo (c. 1492-1580), who
served under Cortés, fifty years after the event
wrote his Historia verdadera de la conquista de la
&<
/
.:*S
( i \
m
\ ) n y
*<r-H: /
j
¿L'.-,'
.>.*- .n
i z-
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Zapatistas (1931; "Followers
of Zapata"), a painting by
the Mexican muralist José
Clémente Orozco
(1883-1949).
Nueva Espana ("True History of the Conquest
of New Spain"). The vanquished peoples also left
written records. A manuscript dated 1528, now
in the Bibliothèque Nationale in Paris, recounts
in Náhuatl, the language of the Aztecs, the trau¬
matic fate of the Indians:
All this happened literally before our eyes; we
were aghast and filled with anguish at the piteous
fate which was ours. Broken spears lay strewn about
the ground, men on horseback were everywhere, our
houses were roofless and their walls were red [with
blood]. The water was red also, as ifit had been dyed,
and when we drank it, it had a brackish taste. We
beat our fists against the mud walls at the sight of
our heritage lying in tatters. We sought protection
behind our shields but no shield could protect us in
our isolation...
The beginning
of a new history
This evocation of the tragic fall of the ancient
capital of Mexico contrasts with Bernai Díaz'
equally astonishing description of the city as it
appeared to the conquistadors on their arrival:
We saw the three causeways that led into
Mexico... We saw thefresh water which camefrom
Chapultepec to supply the city.... We saw too that
one could not passfrom one house to another ofthat
great city and the other cities that were built on the
water except over wooden drawbridges.... We saw
cues and shrines in these cities that looked like
gleaming white towers and castles: a marvellous
sight.... We turned back to the great market and the
swarm ofpeople buying and selling.... Some ofour
soldiers who had been in many parts of the world,
in Constantinople, in Rome, and all over Italy, said
that they had never seen a market so well laid out,
so large, so orderly, and so full ofpeople. *
These accounts, from the vanquished and the
30
victorious, record the passing of ancient splen¬
dours and herald the emergence of a new destiny.
How then can Mexicans, as they search for their
identity, ignore the shock of this encounter be¬
tween two peoples, which gave rise to so much
discord yet from which their mixed culture was
born?
There are hundreds of chronicles of "New
Spain", covering three centuries of history. Their
authors wished to record the upheavals they were
witnessing. In the sixteenth century an extraor¬
dinary man, the Spanish Franciscan Bernardino
de Sahagún, assisted by Indians old enough to
have lived through the Spanish conquest or
young enough to be his disciples, gathered invalu¬
able, first-hand information on the pre-
Columbian era. Meanwhile, indigenous chroni¬
clers such as Tezozómoc and Chimalpahin were
writing in their own languagesNáhuatl, Aztec,
Yucatán Mayain order to preserve their history.
A Mexican identity was gradually emerging,
but those who were trying to define it were faced
with a mass of contradictions. Some felt that the
ancient pre-Columbian heritage was dead and
gone. Others foresaw a glorious destiny for "New
Spain". At the same time, more and more
newcomersAfrican slaves, Spaniards from all
walks of life, adventurers from other countries
of the Old Worldwere mingling with the
descendants of the Aztec, Olmec, Maya, Zapotee
and other peoples.
Reasserting Mexican identity
As time went by, the feeling grew that traditional
chronicles should be replaced by a more rigorous
historiography which would help the Mexicans
grasp their identity and learn from the past in
order to prepare for the future. An outstanding
example of the new methodology was the Historia
antigua de México ("History of Ancient Mexico")
by a Mexican Jesuit, Francisco Xavier Clavijero
(1731-1787), which was so popular that it was im¬
mediately translated into several languages. This
was the first cultural history of the country be¬
fore the Spanish conquest. The author empha¬
sized the importance of accepting their ancient
heritage as the only means by which Mexicans
could come to terms with themselves in order to
face the great changes in store.
Clavijero's foresight was soon borne out by
events. Mexico gained its independence in 1821.
Some of those who fought for independence
recorded their views on what the revolution
meant to them as a harbinger of major political,
social, economic and religious change!
The contradictions in Mexican historiogra¬
phy thus reflect the different aims of historians.
Liberals fought to strengthen republican institu¬
tions, while traditionalists, looking to the past,
dreamed of a monarchical system. Historians
* Quotation from The Conquest ofNew Spain by Bemal Díaz,
translated by J.M. Cohen. Penguin Classics, 1963.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
studying the struggles of the new nation attempt¬
ed to resolve the great issues at stake and to ex¬
plain the more tragic episodes.
In 1847-1848 Mexico went to war with the
United States and lost half of its territory. Internal
conflicts in the following years conjured up the
fleeting dream of a new empire, culminating in
the dramatic confrontation between Maximilian,
crowned emperor of Mexico with the support of
France, and Benito Juárez, backed by the Mexican
people. The history of this era, sometimes written
in blood, again raised the tormenting questions:
who were we, who are we now, and what will
become of us?
Historiography in modern Mexico
The most recent convulsion in Mexican history
was the revolution of 1910. The names of its
leading figures have become legendary: Francisco
Madero, Emiliano Zapata, Venustiano Carranza,
Pancho Villa.... The revolution heightened the
Mexican sense of identity and purpose, and was
expressed not only in politics but in the visual
arts, literature and music, as well as in history and
anthropology. From the 1920s onwards the great
muralist painters Orozco, Rivera, Siqueiros
Detail from "Cortés
arriving at Vera Cruz in
1519", one of a series of
frescos by the Mexican
painter Diego Rivera
(1886-1957) illustrating the
Spanish conquest of the
New World. National
Palace, Mexico City.
MIGUEL
LEÓN-PORTILLA,
of Mexico, is currently
serving as his country's
ambassador and permanent
delegate to Unesco.
Professor emeritus at the
Autonomous National
University of Mexico, he is
the author of a number of
books, articles and papers
on pre-Columbian cultures,
which have been translated
into several languages.
took inspiration for their frescos from both past
and present. At the same time a new generation
of historians, sociologists and anthropologists,
better educated and professionally trained, were
concentrating on the obsessive theme of the iden¬
tity and destiny of Mexico.
Historical research on Mexico today, whether
carried out by Mexicans or others, represents a
variety of schools of thought and ideologies. Even
if nationalist tendencies are, at times, apparent,
the highly professional quality of the work of
these historians has to be recognized. The three
main stages in the history of Mexico its pre-
Columbian roots, the mixing of cultures and
its existence as an independent countryare cur¬
rently being studied in depth. Although the main
research centres are in the capital, work is also
being carried out in the most remote regions of
the country. The expansion of historiography is
part of a general movement in which historians
have extended their interest beyond the specifi¬
cally Mexican field.
Faithful to the spirit of their Indian ancestors,
modern Mexicans feel that a people which reflects
on its historical identity comes to understand the
meaning of the present and is better equipped to
face the future. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
UNITED STATES
A PARTICULAR
VIEW
OF AMERICA
BY OLIVIER ZUNZ
I
32
T has often been observed that Americans
experience their history as if it had been mapped
out in advance, as if the future were only an op¬
portunity to improve institutions that are already
solidly established. The key idea, rooted deep in
the nation's consciousness, is the exceptional na¬
ture of the American experience. As the orator
and politician Daniel Webster put it, addressing
the House of Representatives in 1826:
"Whatsoever European experience has deve¬
loped, favourable to the freedom and happiness
of man; whatsoever European genius has invented
for his improvement or gratification; whatsoever
of refinement or polish the culture of European
society presents for his adoption or enjoyment,
all this is offered to man in America, with the
additional advantages of the full power of erecting
forms of Government on free and simple princi¬
ples, without overturning institutions suited to
times long past, but too strongly supported either
by interests or prejudices, to be shaken without
convulsions."
American historians still continue to high¬
light the factors that make their history so ex¬
ceptional. In this they are pursuing the endless
debate on the respective roles of consensus and
conflict, on what unites Americans and what
keeps them apart.
The progressive historians of the early years
of the century set out, in a way, to "democra¬
tize" the country's history. They disputed the
traditional acceptance of the American consensus
and instead stressed the dynamics of domestic
conflicts. Frederick Jackson Turner, for example,
considered that the American character was born
of the strained relations between the seaboard and
the frontier, while for Arthur M. Schlesinger the
tensions were between city and countryside, and
for Charles Beard they were between social
classes.
But the generation of historians writing after
the Second World War turned back to the issue
of consensus. The historians of the 1950s redis¬
covered Alexis de Tocqueville, the author of
Democracy in America (1835-1840), and tried to
define the forces uniting Americans. Louis Hartz,
for example, replied to the German historical
economist Werner Sombart's celebrated question
as to why there was no socialism in the United
States by drawing attention to the lack of long¬
standing feudal constraints, the virtual absence of
class as a motive force in the new nation, and
hence the flexibility of a social system that was
both open and unifying.
The historians of the last twenty years, dis¬
satisfied with these generalizations which in their
view are too theoretical, have been intent on ex¬
ploring as many real-life situations as possible.
With the broadening of the scope of history as
a discipline, the concept of national character has
for the moment lost its explanatory value, while
new areas of research such as the history of the
family and of labour, or urban history, have made
it possible to dispense with a unifying link. The
contrast between consensus and conflict now
seems to be too simple. The national framework
has become inadequate for grasping such major
issues as the economy of the slave trade, migra¬
tion patterns or the development of industrial
capitalism. But key ideas do not die all that easily,
and this concept of the national character, as
amended, is enjoying a fresh lease of life. The con¬
cept is deeply rooted in American life, but where
did it come from?
The first Puritan settlers left an indelible mark
on American history. Their new country was
supposed to set an example to the Old World of
a better society, destined by Providence to serve
Above, Verdict of the People
(1855), a painting by George
Caleb Bingham (1811-1879)
which evokes the festive air
of the early American voting
tradition.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Below, picking cotton on a
Mississippi plantation.
Nineteenth-century
American engraving based
on a painting by
W.A. Walker.
as a model for other nations. That was the mis¬
sion of the American people, as evoked by the
famous declaration made in 1630 by John Win¬
throp, one of the chief figures among the Puritan
founders of New England: "Men shall say of suc¬
ceeding plantations: the Lord make it like that
of New England: for we shall be as a City set
upon a Hill, the eyes of all people are upon us."
The ideal of a self-sufficient egalitarian Puri¬
tan community, centred on religious life and
governed by collective decision-making, may well
never have been fulfilled, not even during the first
generation. Nevertheless, the role of the "com¬
munity" in American life was spelt out from the
outset and served as a reference for following
generations.
In colonial America, two ideological and
social worlds existed side by side and sometimes
mergedthat of the Puritan and that of the
Yankee, born of the challenge which the conquest
of a new territory represented. In New England,
the egalitarian settler villages contrasted with the
trading ports where moral principles were cons¬
tantly eroded as social barriers grew up. Settle¬
ments on the frontier itself were dominated by
a handful of businessmen, such as John Pynchon
in Springfield or the Willards of the Merrimack
Valley, who were more concerned with acquiring
land and gaining ready access to markets than
with seemly behaviour and religious observance.
In the South, of course, the plantation econ¬
omy soon superseded the modest smallholdings
of the original settlers. The republican ideology
of individualism was therefore quick to impose
itself at the expense of community spirit. Well
before blood flowed at Lexington and Concord,
Massachusetts, at the beginning of the War of In¬
dependence, the Puritans had been turned into
Yankees.
The revolution and the intellectual turmoil
caused by the break with Britain once again
prompted Americans to define where they stood
politically, as can be seen from the legal and
philosophical treatises of John Adams and the de¬
bates on the Constitution. Although Americans
rejected the British system of government, they
realized that they could only place their trust in
an elite which had demonstrated its worth. In a
crucial innovation they opted in favour of elected
representatives, citizens who would be exposed
to the possibility of corruption but who were ex¬
pected to abide by certain rules and could, if
necessary, be repudiated.
Once they had won their independence, the
Americans continued to define their position by
extending their territory beyond the Allegheny
Mountains and by developing the economy,
formerly geared solely to the Atlantic trade,
towards the interior of the country. Thomas
Jefferson was intent on creating a nation of in¬
dependent rural landowners in the West: "Those
who labour the earth are the chosen people of
God, if ever He had a chosen people, whose
breasts He has made his peculiar deposit for sub¬
stantial and genuine virtue."
The period when the pioneers rolled back the
frontier contributed most to the formation of the
national character, in the sense in which that term
is usually understood: the practical and inventive
side of the Jacksonian "common man", that "or¬
dinary man" who was always ready with expe¬
dients, not very keen on the arts but skilled at
A wagon train of settlers
crosses the Rocky
Mountains, early 19th
century.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
One of the first automobile
assembly lines at the Ford
factory in Detroit
(Michigan), 1913.
34
OLIVIER ZUNZ, American
historian, teaches at the
University of Virginia,
Charlottesville, USA. He is
the author of The Changing
Face of Inequality: Issues in
Black Literature and
Criticism and Urbanization,
Industrial Development and
Immigrants in Detroit,
1880-1920, both published
by University of Chicago
Press, 1982, and Making
America Corporate,
1870-1920 (forthcoming).
succeeding in whatever he undertook. Frontier
Americans were sometimes rough-hewn, but they
were productive, matter-of-fact, forward-looking
and quick to help one another out. The quality
of life in the new communities depended on a
sense of belonging to institutions. Tocqueville
found this quite amazing, commenting that:
"Government does very little in England, and pri¬
vate individuals do a great deal; in America,
government interference has virtually ceased, and
everything is done by the joint efforts of individu¬
als." Thus the frontier community did inherit
something from its Puritan forebears.
The end of innocence
Was the United States in the mid-nineteenth cen¬
tury composed of many small, loosely linked
communities, or of a few large groups, or had it
become a homogeneous nation?
The war between the North and South is at
the heart of any discussion of national character.
Historians have now gone beyond the debate on
whether the Civil War was inevitable and have
recently begun to raise new aspects of the social
and cultural history of the South in an attempt
to understand the distinctive features of a civili¬
zation built on the master-slave relationship and
the way in which the South kept up racial dis¬
tinctions in defiance of all egalitarian principles.
Political historians also have taken the conflict
between North and South out of the context of
the struggle for or against emancipation and set
it in a wider struggle for American legitimacy,
with each camp claiming the republican heritage
as its own.
Reconstruction of the Union and the transi¬
tion to an industrialized and bureaucratized ur¬
ban nation engaging in worldwide conflicts have
triggered off fresh debates on the end of Ameri¬
can innocence and hence on the end of the ex¬
ceptional nature of its history. The successive
transformations of American society, and the se¬
vere blow dealt by the Great Depression, may
sometimes have caused cracks in the edifice, but
they have also helped to redefine and even in
some cases to strengthen the ideological structure
founded on the exceptional nature of America.
What could be saved of the national character in
a society that was becoming increasingly complex
and powerful, and increasingly inegalitarian?
The pioneer industrialists of the nineteenth
century, such as Francis Lowell who built his tex¬
tile mills at the falls on the Merrimack river, at¬
tracting a labour force of New England farmers'
daughters, dreamed of creating a prosperous and
conflict-free industrial society. There was to be
no "Manchester of America". By the end of the
century, however, large-scale industry was em¬
ploying an unskilled workforce of immigrants
fresh off the ships from Europe.
Was anything left of the Lowell ideals in
Carnegie's Pittsburgh or Ford's Detroit? Fear of
social corruption governed the ideological reac¬
tion of the Protestants to urban proletarianiza¬
tion. The victims of poverty were seen as a threat
to society. Cities became missionary territory.
Only the idea of an open society, whose most
able members could win their place in the sun
by overcoming the barriers of language and
prejudice, could replace the unattainable dream
of a poverty-free society.
A share in the national heritage
The main problem of American social dynamics
was still to be resolved: how to form a homogene¬
ous society from its heterogeneous parts. Some
historians suggested prosperity, which could be
said to have served as a foundation for democracy,
as a linking theme. Others saw the many oppor¬
tunities for individual social advancement as the
key to the equilibrium of American society. Yet
others laid emphasis on the workers' right to
vote. In Europe, demands for the right to vote
added a political dimension to the struggle waged
by the proletariat, but the granting of that right
in America defused the political struggle and
buried class consciousness. For some, social
equilibrium has never been seriously threatened
by the diversity of the American people, since
they all enjoy prosperity, whereas for others a
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
At the turn of the century,
a group of immigrants waits
patiently for a ferry to take
them from Ellis Island to
New York.
balance has been maintained through the skill
displayed by the governing class in warding off
conflicts.
In the mid-twentieth century, America redis¬
covered a strong sense of "togetherness". Im¬
migration controls from the 1920s onwards made
for a more homogeneous society in which the
"melting pot" seemed to have become a reality.
The period of prosperity which followed the Se¬
cond World War and the decline of the European
and Japanese economies left the way clear for the
country's expansion. The level of affluence was
such that intellectuals could speak with confi¬
dence of the end of ideologies. Currents of
thought that had hitherto been separate ran
together to give the country a new sense of
strength and homogeneity. The search for the na¬
tional character was renewed, prompted by the
historians of consensus.
But history is always more complicated than
the sometimes deceptive moments of national
union might suggest. The intellectual explosion
of the 1960s, the country's embroilment in Viet
Nam, the Watergate crisis, the battles about the
legitimacy of the welfare state and the extension
of civil rights, the rediscovery of ethnic heritages,
and women's struggle for equalityin short, the
realities of the "divided society" quickly under¬
mined the idea of consensus.
On the other hand, the idea of there being
a national character has proved more resistant,
for it is over a particular view of America that
political and social battles have beenand are still
beingfought. Where is legitimate America, sym¬
bolized by the Statue of Liberty, with its dual sig¬
nificance of republican liberty and national
diversity? Who can claim America's history as
their own? When these questions are raised, it is
all too often forgotten that the very concept of
unity, so ardently sought after, implies by defi¬
nition the concept of diversity. The two are in¬
separable. All the groups of people which have
helped to build the country since the seventeenth
century claim their share of the national heritage.
American history is, successively, the story of a
compromise between disparate elements, conflicts
between those same elements, mutual unaware-
ness, fragmentation and, at times, consensus.
Reducing it to one or other of these formulas
would be to deprive it of its lifeblood.
*
Ty
«\
.V«
ifh u k*
v -----
A
j***
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
a universal
history-
possibility or
pipe dream?
36
Is there any sense or
purpose in the concept of a
universal history and a
universal identity? The
great philosophers of history
of the nineteenth century
who first propounded this
concept succeeded only
in arresting its development.
Perhaps the time has
come to ask what form a
truly universal history
might take.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Georg Wilhelm
Friedrich Hegel
(1770-1831).
- y i va
.»
..
"Man Masters the Universe
with Technology" (1934),
detail from a 56 m2 mural
by Diego Rivera. Palace of
Fine Arts, Mexico City.
FROM HEGEL
TO
MARX
THE SAGA
OF THE DIALECTIC
BY EMMANUEL TERRAY
I
N the closing years of the eighteenth century,
when the German philosopher Georg Wilhelm
Friedrich Hegel appeared on the scene, philosophical
thought bore the profound imprint of the teachings
of Immanuel Kant.
Kant had left philosophy in a state of apparently
irreconcilable schism. There was the split between
subject and object, the resolution of which was then
seen as the central problem facing the philosopher;
there was the split within the subject, between the
observable individual and the transcendental "I",
which alone was capable of constituting knowledge;
there was the split within the object, between the
phenomenon and the inaccessible "thing-in-itself";
there was the conflict, with regard to human con¬
duct, between the necessity imposed by the world
and freedom of the will, and, in the field of ethics,
between the concepts of duty and happiness.
At each of these levels, Kant placed in opposi¬
tion two terms or elements between which no unity
or harmony seemed conceivable. Whereupon, all
those who came after him set about re-establishing
the lost unity and reconciling the adversaries that
Kant had drawn up in opposing ranks.
The method adopted by Hegel to achieve this
objective was to accept the dichotomy and antagonism
as the outward appearance of present reality and to
propound reconciliation as a future necessity. He
therefore introduced the notion of time into the
relationships between subject and object, between
the rational and the real. These relationships were
no longer to be seen as fixed for all time by "the
nature of things"; they had to be seen in the context
of an evolutionary process during which two op¬
posing elements would change each other and be
transformed into each other.
The process described by Hegel has three main
stages. During the first stage, the concept, the original
and fundamental entity, is formed within the frame¬
work or setting of the ideal, of the abstract. This
gives rise to the great categories of philosophical
thoughtbeing, nothingness, becoming, number,
measure, and so on the classification and study of
which make up the science of Logic.
During the second stage, in a spasm of self-
negation, the concept becomes the thing, reality,
nature. Nature, in fact, is nothing more than the
Karl Marx (1818-1883)
by the Mexican painter
David Alfaro Siqueiros
(1896-1974).
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
:j
38
concept become realitywhich is why it is, by defi¬
nition, understandablebut as such, nature is "the
thing in itself", blind, deaf and dumb.
Then comes the third stage, when the concept
re-asserts itself, yet without losing its quality as
object. This is the stage of history, and history itself
could be described as the process whereby reason
gradually gains ascendancy over the real, which it
orders in conformity with its own requirements. At
the end of the process, reconciliation is achieved,
and unity is restored between subject and object,
so that, as Hegel wrote in the preface to his
Philosophy ofRight, "All that is real is rational and
all that is rational is real".
Absolute knowledge, the driving
force of history
Each of the great periods of history is thus seen as
one of the stages in this process, one of the phases
of the movement by which reason takes control of
the world and submits it to its law. Hegel opens our
eyes to the unity of each historical period. This
unity takes the form of the Volksgeist, or national
spirit. A manifestation of the Weltgeist, or world
spirit, at a particular stage of its historical develop¬
ment, the Volksgeist in its turn inspires and moulds
all the institutions and all the great works of the
historical period concerned. Politics, religion, the
economy, the arts, all bear its imprint. Each epoch
can thus be described as "the expression of a totali¬
ty" in which each element mirrors the other ele¬
ments separately and as a whole.
Naturally, the various nations do not make
equal progress. For each stage, one nation acts as
model and guide, providing us with a criterion by
means of which we can judge to what extent the
other nations' achievements match up to the de¬
mands of historical development.
At the same time, however, each of these dis¬
tinct totalities is provisional only and doomed to
disappear and be replaced. This is because, at the
heart of each of them, the Weltgeist is working away
in subterranean fashion. So long as the reconquest
of the real has not been achieved, so long as there
remains anywhere within the world an enclave of
resistance to the empire of reasonan unexplored
realm of nature, a sector of society where disorder
and confusion reignreason remains unsatisfied. It
undermines the edifices it has itself constructed,
since, having fulfilled their purpose, they would
only become obstacles if they claimed the right to
exist for ever.
This thrust by which the spirit is continually
bringing its own creations into question is driven
by the thought and actions of men, who, neverthe¬
less, are unaware of this. This is what Hegel called
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
"The Coronation of
Napoleon I", by the French
artist Jacques Louis David
(1748-1825).
Right, a deputation from
Silesia pays homage to the
king of Prussia, Frederick II
the Great (1741). Painting
by the German historical
artist Wilhelm Camphausen
(1818-1885).
"reason's trick"using for its own ends agents who
think that they are working for other purposes.
A philosophy of history constructed on these
principles displays some remarkable characteristics.
It is first of all a philosophy of progress. History
has a direction and a purpose and strives towards
the triumph of reason and the spirit, which Hegel
called "absolute knowledge". It is also a dialectical
philosophy. Each period of history is a transitory,
passing stage, marked by contradictions which lead
inevitably to ruin. Finally, it is a philosophy of
necessity. The only objective an actual historical
individualwhether an individual hero or a single
peoplecan aspire to is to fulfil the imperatives of
the world spirit as they appear to be in the historical
period concerned, without attempting to forestall
them, to halt them or, least of all, to reverse them.
The great men of historyAlexander, Caesar,
Napoleonand the great peoples of historythe
Greeks, the Romans and the Prussiansare those
who have succeeded in discerning these imperatives
and have taken them as the watchword of their
actions, thus playing their part in the gradual victory
of the spirit.
The major enigma and difficulty of Hegel's
philosophy of history lies in the notion of absolute
knowledge. The achievement of absolute knowledge
marks the end of history. But was this a distant
prospect, analagous to the Second Coming of Chris¬
tian doctrine, or was it closer at hand and thus
already liable to influence man's actions? Hegel's
stance on this point seems to have varied. He praised
the Napoleonic empire and then the Prussian state
in terms that might seem to suggest that with them
history was coming to an end.
This question was to cause deep divisions among
Hegel's successors. Those who held that reason had
attained its goal became conservative partisans of
the established order. Others had little difficulty in
demonstrating the political and social reality that
disorder and violence were still disputing power
with reason and that, consequently, the march of
history could only be continuing. The latter group
comprised the "Hegelian Left", among whom one
of the most eloquent representatives was the young
Karl Marx.
Marx: from Hegelianism
to the class war
The Marxist edifice is closely dependent on the
Hegelian structure. Marx took from Hegelianism
what is undoubtedly its essential elementthe
dialectical framework. History is seen as a process
having a direction, a beginning and an end. This
process is powered by a force which seeks to con¬
quer and subjugate reality. This conquest passes
through several stages, each stage representing a
partial, limited step towards accomplishment of the
final goal. Although each such achievement is a sign
of progress at the time it occurs, it eventually
becomes an obstacle to further development which
must be destroyed so that the forward movement
can continue until the final goal is reached.
What Marx altered in the Hegelian design was
the nature of the motor that powered the process.
As we have seen, for Hegel, this motor was a kind
of energy inherent in the concept itself, which led
it continually to escape from its own limits and to
absorb whatever it found outside those limits. This
central role accorded to the concept led Marx to
accuse Hegel of idealism. For Marx, the motor of
history was not the abstract dynamism of the
concept, but the needs, the aspirations and desires
of the individuals and the specific groupsfamilies,
nations and classesthat constitute the human race.
These individuals and groups have material
needs. They must feed, clothe and shelter themselves
and they can satisfy these needs only by making use
of the resources of nature. History, then, is first of
all a process whereby people take possession of
nature to make use of it for their own ends. This
process involves both knowledge, through the
advancement of science, and action, through tech¬
nological progress, and can be seen at work in the
development of human productive forces. It is
through this process that people become aware of
the world around them and of their place in that
world. On this basis Marx felt himself justified in
declaring, in contradiction to Hegel, that "it is not
the consciousness of men that determines their
existence, but, on the contrary, their social existence
that determines their consciousness".
Thus Marx put forward his "materialism" in
opposition to Hegelian idealism. In the Marxist
philosophy of history, this materialism is expressed
in the fundamental role given to labour and the
economy. These are described as the "ultimate
determinants" and form the matrix around which
arise the institutions and the characteristic manifesta¬
tions of social life in the fields of politics, law, cul¬
ture and religion.
In their struggle to dominate nature people have
to become organized so that they can, through co¬
operation, obtain the best results through their joint
efforts and also so that they can share the fruits of
their labours. Initially, their work is not very produc¬
tive and provides just enough for the community
to subsist. There is a state of equality in poverty,
which Marx called "primitive communism".
Then comes a stage at which the first increases
in productivity give rise to a small surplus, but this
is too small for all to benefit from it and a struggle
arises as to who shall have it. Thus are sown the
seeds of the class war. A fraction of the society gains
control over the means of production, whatever
form these may takeland, skills, the labour force
and as a result arrogates to itself the monopoly of
the surplus. To ensure this privilege, it also takes
over political power and intellectual leadership.
For each stage in the development of technology
and productive forces there is, of course, a cor¬
responding form of organization of labour and fixed 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
n m\>w mo roo/1
40
Soviet May Day poster, 1920. The caption reads:
"Through the ruins of capitalism, towards a world
brotherhood of workers!"
"production relationships", which in turn support
political "superstructures" and specific cultural
"forms of consciousness".
As progress is made from stage to stage the class
war alters and the protagonists change. Slaves
become serfs and then the proletariat of modern
times. On the other side of the divide, the master
is succeeded by the lord and the lord by the capitalist
entrepreneur. Yet, at each stage, the class struggle
retains- its driving role. This is aptly expressed in
the words of the Communist Manifesto: "All his¬
tory has hitherto been a history of class struggles."
By changing the "motor" Marx also changed
the nature of the necessity that governs the course
of history. Hegelian necessity was an abstract, ideal
necessity and, as such, could not be halted by any
obstacle. From the moment that he considered
human actions as the dynamic of historical develop¬
ment, Marx had to allow for other contingencies.
Collective action implies taking a stand and organiz¬
ing. This in turn implies the possibility of error and
failure. In other words, progress could be slowed
down, halted or side-tracked; its future could not
be detailed in advance.
The Hegelian heritage and the environment
created by the development of evolutionary theory
exercised a powerful joint pressure on Marxist
thought and led to the reinstatement of necessity
to pride of place. Engels, and then the theorists of
the Second and Third International, were the prime
movers in this change of direction, at the end of
which determinism had ousted free will in Marxist
thought. History then appeared as an inevitable suc¬
cession of methods of production leading to com¬
munism and the classless society. That certain
passages from the writings of Marx can be quoted
in support of such an interpretation is undeniable,
but this does not make it any the less a betrayal of
the more original and innovative aspects of his
thinking.
EMMANUEL TERRAY,
of France, is director of
studies at the Ecole des
Hautes Etudes en Sciences
Sociales, Paris. A specialist
on the anthropology of
tropical Africa, he is the
author of Lettres à la
fugitive (Odile Jacob, Paris,
1988) and La politique dans
la caverne (Le Seuil, Paris,
forthcoming).
A NEW MODEL
FOR A UNIVERSAL HISTORY
WORLD
RHYTHMS
BY ROBERT BONNAUD
%HAT are we entitled to ask of a "universal his¬
tory"? First, that it should maintain a certain balance
and not give too large a place to Western history and its
antecedentsthe triumphal progression from the Egypt
of the pyramids to Europe's belle époque. To borrow
the titles of works published during the eighteenth cen¬
tury, we would expect it to be "the history of all the
peoples of the world", or "the history of mankind".
We would also expect it to be more than a series
of separate histories juxtaposed, a parade of witnesses
that are perfect strangers to one another. It would have
to be a comparative history, a confrontation that would
reveal differences and similarities, a drama whose plot
unfolds, a mosaic pieced together to create a global land¬
scape, a common adventure.
Yet this would still not be enough. There might
be one character so central to this drama that, even
if all proportions were respected and all the links were
made, the work as a whole might take on the aspect
of an apologia. This universal history could be a com¬
parative history of all the peoples of the world but yet
be a history that always favoured the same group and
which, however vast and however meticulously exa¬
mined the terrain might be, nevertheless aimed to set
that group off to advantage. Such was the compara¬
tive history written by Max Weber (1864-1920). His
was an impressive, all-encompassing inquiry with India,
China and Islam called for examination before a pains¬
taking judge, but a judge who thought that Western
culture was superior to the others and who felt the need
to provide irrefutable proof of this.
Some brave attempts
Like Copernicus putting the Earth back in its place
among the planets, Oswald Spengler (1880-1936) over¬
turned this vision by "de-Westernizing" history.
Western culture was placed among the eight human
cultures. Like the others with the exception of pre-
Columbian culture which had disappeared, prematurely
assassinatedit was to have its thousand years of his¬
tory (from the year 1000 to the year 2000), passing
through four phases, each of 250 years, with its periods
of greatness and of decline. It demonstrated no greater
originality than the seven other cultures. Its superiority
was an illusion.
Spengler's vision was of cultures of equal worth,
with a common destiny and all subject to the same law
of development. The cohesiveness of universal history
seems, however, to be given the lie by the deep diver¬
sity of cultures, compartmentalized and shut in upon
themselves like monads [indivisible and impenetrable
units]. Could it be that there are eight histories rather
than one? Ethnic particularities fragment humanity and
the "spirit of peoples" effaces the "spirit of the times",
that is to say, the similarities and parallels engendered
by an epoch.
For Spengler, contemporaneity did not mean being
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
\ 1
of the same chronological time. Around 200 BC, the
culture of Antiquity, then in decline (it lasted from
1000 BC to the beginning of the Christian era), ex¬
perienced a wave of religious enthusiasm, a recurrence
of which Spengler detected in Western culture from
1800 AD. Such parallels are valuable, but others, absent
from Spengler's "model", contradict them. For exam¬
ple, around 200 BC the ancient Mediterranean world,
in harmony with the Indian, Chinese and pre-
Columbian worlds, was experiencing a moralistic and
religious wave that swept over all humanity. Similarly,
around 1800, the Western world was not unique; the
religious renewal of that period was not only Catholic
and Protestant, but Orthodox, Islamic, Hindu and
Buddhist as well.
Spengler's model was adapted and improved by
Arnold Toynbee (1889-1975). He added to it the theory
of creative challenge and cultural response, whose pos¬
sibilities are far from having been fully exploited by
social scientists. He rid it of much of the emphasis on
decadence and cultural polycentrism which Spengler
had taken to absurd lengths in his Der Untergang des
Abendlandes (1918-1922; The Decline of the West,
1926-1928).
In his major work, the twelve-volume Study ofHis¬
tory (1934-1961), as well as in some of his other books,
Toynbee propounded a kind of progressionism that
was heedful of convergences of human thought, even
at times of its worldwide synchronism at the universal
turning-points of history. After the Second World War,
however, Toynbee the philosopher of history became
more and more Toynbee the historian and his interest
iii historical universals declined. It is thus difficult
tp speak in the full sense of a "Toynbee model" of
universal history.
Guiseppe Ferrari, universalist
If we are looking for a model of universal history
that attempts to portray the usually barely visible, com¬
monly unsuspected "identity of mankind", that brings
out the unity of the "noösphere" (the wholly human
area of conscious thought) in its structures and
rhythms, that aspires to give a picture of the "human
norm" across the ages, with all its qualitative and quan¬
titative fluctuations, then it is to Guiseppe Ferrari
(1811-1876) that we should turn. Considered in Italy
to be an important social thinker but unknown in
France despite the fact that he lived there for twenty
years, Ferrari published two books that are now vir¬
tually completely forgotten: "The History of State
Politics" (1860), in which he expressed his intuitive
belief in the convergence and temporal coincidence of
world events, and "China and Europe" (1867), in
which he developed this theme.
Similar ideas are to be found in the writings of
other authors of the period: in Antoine-Augustin
Cournot's Traité de l'enchaînement des idéesfondamen¬
tales dans les sciences et dans l'histoire (1861; "The Links
between Fundamental Concepts in the Sciences and in
History"), in which he urged the need for a compara¬
tive history describing the "strange analogies and tem¬
poral coincidences" to be found in Chinese and
European history; in Ernest Renan's Vie defésus (1863;
Life offesus, 1869), in which he affirms that "history
is full of strange temporal coincidences as a result of
which, with no communication between them, widely
separated groups of human beings come simultaneously
to share almost identical ideas and perceptions"; in the
works of Sir Edward Tylor, anthropologist, Quaker
and apostle of brotherly love, who set out in 1855 in
"The Red Tree" (1908-1910),
by the Dutch artist Piet
Mondrian (1872-1944).
ROBERT BONNAUD,
French historian, teaches
the history and theory of
history at the University of
Paris VII. His publications
include Le système de
l'histoire (Fayard, Paris,
1989) and contributions to
the Hachette Atlas
historique (1986).
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
search of the "correspondences" that exist between the
peoples of the world.
Did not the prophet-historian Michelet himself,
from 1825 to 1826, put forward the idea that, since the
history of the world was a "system", we should study
what had happened throughout the world at given mo¬
ments in the pastthe idea, in other words, of basing
a "truly universal history" on worldwide, time-based
cross-sections of history? Did he not also write in La
Bible de l'humanité (1864; "The Bible of Humanity")
that a universal history should give men "the sense of
a common, fraternal past", the feeling that "men have
always thought, felt and loved in the same way"?
Though Ferrari died before the turn of the century,
his ideas are present in the work of certain twentieth-
century writers. In Die Neuentstehende Welt (1927;
"The Burgeoning World"), by the German philo¬
sopher Hermann von Keyserling, contemporaries are
seen as "partial and complementary expressions of
a higher unity"; in one of his biographies, Vie de
Vivekananda, Romain Rolland views separate histories
as "branches of a single tree, which together share the
changes of the seasons". These ideas are also present
in the works of certain authors of universal histories,
such as H.G. Wells' The Outline ofHistory (1920), and
Pierre de Coubertin's Histoire universelle (1926-1927;
"Universal History"). In Vom Ursprung und Ziel der
Geschichte (1949; The Origin and Goal ofHistory, 1953),
Karl Jaspers added the notion of the "axial period"
(roughly 600 to 200 BC) during which time, through¬
out Eurasia, thanks to an exceptional surge of inven¬
tion and innovation, the cultural future of the greater
part of humanity was determined.
Ferrari's ideas are also to be seen in attempts to
produce comparative histories of art (Elie Faure), world
philosophies (Paul Masson-Oursel), world literatures
(René Etiemble), and in the thinking of many impor¬
tant historians, both general historians and orientalists,
such as Karl Polanyi, Marshall Hodgson, Lewis
Mumford, Jan Romein, Gaston Roupnel, Fernand
Braudel, René Grousset, Joseph Needham, Jean
Filliozat and Jacques Berque.
Similar concepts are evoked by those observers
who note with surprise that different or even opposed
cultural and geopolitical areas appear to move in the
same direction, experiencing upsurges and stagnation
at identical periods and that, despite disparities in the
form and degree of change, taken together they provide
a mean of planetary significance, curves on the graph
of progress that are applicable to all humanity, turning-
points that affect the entire noösphere.
Obstacles to be overcome
Nevertheless, the "Ferrari model"the systematic
search for universal rhythms and world turning-
pointshas yet to be applied and there are many ob¬
stacles to its application. The backward state of Western
historical studies on non-Western peoples is one.
"Common sense", of the kind that observes that the
Sun goes round the Earth and that plant life has no
connection with animal life, is another and more
serious obstacle. This kind of "common sense" admits,
the moment that there is some form of contact or
influence transmitted between the histories unfolding
at the four corners of the Earth, that there may be
resemblances between them. Thanks to the "global
village" effect and television screens, history becomes
universal.
It must, however, be acknowledged that long
before the modern media, before the geographical dis¬
coveries of the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries and
the beginnings of the world market, quantitative and
qualitative planetary rhythms existed in the wholly
human world of thought. To my mind, these plane¬
tary rhythms are evidenced in the three areas that make
up this world: that of high level creativity, invention
and thought in the strictest sense of the term; that of
structural change (political, technical, economic and
cultural), of innovation and pioneering activities; and,
finally, that of consolidation, standardization, expan¬
sion and action.
From 1300 to 200 BC, inventive, innovative power
was manifest in the Mediterranean countries (the
Greeks, from Mycene to the Roman conquest), in the
kingdoms of China (from the Yin and the Zhou to the
extinction of the latter and the triumph of the Qin)
and in India. It has recently been discovered, however,
that this power, which has given rise to such expres¬
sions as "the Greek miracle", the "axial period" of his¬
tory and the "lighthouse" of the future, was also an
attribute of the Olmecs of pre-Columbian America.
Today, specialists also date to the same period the emer¬
gence in the Pacific of the Polynesian civilization. For
this period, then, we have two additional, contem¬
porary "miracles". This gives us a better grasp of the
overall explanatory value of examination and cross-
comparison of epochs, of successive human mean
achievement levels.
Another obstacle lies in the fact that whereas his¬
tory is more or less universal, development is more or
less uneven, according to the moment selected. The
world spread of positive innovation varies as does the
range of time-based coincidental convergence. Prehis¬
tory (up to about 3000 BC) was more universal than
historical timesprogress was more evenly spread (the
strength of the evidence now forces us to accept that
the neolithic age originated from multiple points of
departure).
Historical times can be divided into three major
periods: ancient-medieval (from 3000 BC to the
fifteenth century), modern (from the fifteenth century
to the beginning of the twentieth century), and con¬
temporary (which began at about the time of the First
World War). The least universal of these was the second
period (the one, oddly enough, in which the world
market was created), during which almost all impor¬
tant, positive developments occurred in Western
Europe, North America and Japan.
For all that, worldwide parallels and synchronic,
coincident developments continued; they were merely
less obvious. From about 1630 to 1800, China, like the
West, experienced a phase that was more rationalist
than the one that preceded it. The English revolution
of the seventeenth century and the American and
French revolutions of the eighteenth century were not
the only events of this nature to occur in the world,
but they were exceptional in character. This modern
period was very "Western". For four and a half cen¬
turies, great achievements in thought and action were
concentrated in one corner of the globeand for this
reason seemed all the more brilliant and dazzling. But
this remains a unique stage in world history.
The last obstacle to the application of the "Ferrari
model" of history is by no means the least. To be able
to describe the universal turning-points of history, for
them to be revealed and accepted as such, historians
need a theory which is able to determine the unvarying
common elements associated with such turning-points
and which jostle for dominance. Inspired but prema¬
ture, the "Ferrari model" lacks such a theory. Without
an understanding of these few dozen elements and the
countless combinations to which they can give rise,
it is impossible to pin-point the novel quality of an
epoch and to recognize its relative homogeneity
throughout the world in terms of simultaneous changes
of direction in human progress.
Despite the many approaches that have been tried,
it would appear that twentieth-century historians are
still struggling to define the prerequisites of an authentic
universal history. The most important of these precon¬
ditions is full recognition of the existence of world
rhythms. To achieve this goal we shall have to stop
concentrating on the study of a limited section of
humanity, renounce specificity and open history up
to its universal reality.
From top to bottom:
Baule mask, Côte d'Ivoire.
Black polished wood.
Ceremonial mask, pre-
Columbian Chancay
culture, central Peru. Baked
clay painted in three
colours, c. 1100 AD.
Beaten iron mask from
Gaul. 1st century AD.
Bronze Buddha. Thailand,
15th-16th century.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
D U N
Joseph Ki-Zerbo, the noted Burkinabé historian and author of many articles and books including Histoire de l'Afrique
noire (1978; "The History of Black Africa"), here reflects on the importance of oral tradition as a source for the
writing of African history. This key text is an extract from his introduction to Volume I of the General History
of Africa, published in 1981 under the auspices of Unesco (see page 50), of which he was the general editor.
Oral tradition
as a historical source
BY JOSEPH KI-ZERBO
B
Above, a Senegalese griot.
ESIDES the two major sources of African
history (written documents and archaeology),
oral tradition takes its place as a real living
museum, conserver and transmitter of the social
and cultural creations of peoples purported to
have no written records. This spoken history is
a very frail thread by which to trace our way
back through the dark corridors of the labyrinth
of time. Its custodians are hoary-headed old men
with cracked voices, whose memories are often
dim, who have the stickler's insistence on etiquette
(vieillesse oblige!), as behoves potential ancestors.
They are like the last remaining islets in a
landscape that was once imposing and coherent
but which is now eroded, flattened and thrown
into disorder by the sharp waves of modernism.
Latter-day fossils!
Whenever one of them dies, a fibre of
Ariadne's thread is broken, a fragment of the 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44
landscape literally disappears underground. Yet
oral tradition is by far the most intimate and the
richest of historical sources, the one which is
most filled with the sap of authenticity. As an
African proverb puts it, "The mouth of an old
man smells bad, but it says good and salutary
things". However useful the written record may
be, it is bound to stiffen and dry up its subject.
It decants, dissects, schematizes, petrifies: the
letter killeth. Tradition clothes things in flesh and
blood and colour, it gives blood to the skeleton
of the past. It presents in three dimensions what
is often crowded onto the two-dimensional
surface of a piece of paper. The joy of Sundiata's
mother,* overwhelmed by the sudden recovery
of her son, still bursts forth in the warm and epic
tones of the griots of Mali. Of course, we have
to skirt many pitfalls in order to winnow the
material offered by oral traditionto separate the
wheat of fact from the chaff of words that are
only there for the sake of symmetry or polish,
and of set phrases that are only the formal wrap¬
ping of a message from the distant past.
Speech is a weighty matter
It has been said that oral tradition does not
inspire confidence because it is functionalas if
every human message were not by definition
functional, including archives, which by their
very passiveness, and beneath an appearance of
neutrality and objectivity, conceal so many lies
by omission and clothe error in respectability.
It is true that the epic tradition in particular is
a para-mythical recreation of the past, a sort of
psycho-drama revealing to a community its roots
and the corpus of values which nourish its per¬
sonality; a magic passport enabling it to travel
back up the river of time to the realm of its
ancestors. That is why epic and historical utter¬
ance are not exactly the same. The first overlaps
the second, with anachronistic projections for¬
ward and backward in real time, and with con¬
certina effects like those found in the earth in
archaeology. But do not written records suffer
from these enigmatic intrusions too? Here as else¬
where we must seek the nugget of sense, try to
find a detector which identifies pure metal and
rejects slag and dross.
Of course, the Achilles' heel of epic is the
weakness of the chronological sequence. Mixed-
up temporal sequences cause the image of the past
to reach us, not clear and stable as in a mirror,
but like a fleeting, broken reflection on the
surface of a ruffled stream. For example, the use
of the average length of reigns or generations
for measuring distances back into the past by
* Sundiata, founder of the Mali empire in the 13th
century, is one of the most popular heroes of African his¬
tory. Editor
extrapolation from recent periods has been
vigorously disputed, and has to be accepted with
great reserve, since demographic and other
changes may have taken place. Sometimes an
exceptional and magnetic monarch polarizes the
exploits of his predecessors and successors around
his own person, and the others are literally
eclipsed. This applies to certain dynasts in
Rwanda, and to Da Monzón, King of Segou in
the early nineteenth century, to whom the griots
attribute all that kingdom's major conquests.
Furthermore, an oral account taken out of
its context is like a fish out of water: it dies.
Taken in isolation, oral tradition resembles
African masks wrested from the communion of
the faithful and exhibited to the curiosity of the
uninitiated. It loses its significance and life. Yet
it is through that life, because it is always being
taken over by fresh witnesses charged with trans¬
mitting it, that oral tradition adapts itself to the
expectations of new audiences, an adaptation that
relates mainly to the presentation of the message,
although this does not always leave the content
intact. Moreover, some modern sharks and
mercenaries of oral tradition even serve up
rehashes of written texts which they reinject into
the oral one!
Even the content of the message is often
hermetic or esoteric. For the African, speech is
a weighty matteran ambiguous force which can
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
4 V-\ \'
«w\mm
¡m
-
,yZ^Z
make and unmake, which can be the bearer of
evil. That is why the message is not articulated
openly and directly, but wrapped up in fable,
allusion, hints and proverbs that are hard to un¬
derstand for the common run of people but clear
for those who possess the antennae of wisdom.
In Africa, speech is too weighty to be wasted,
and the more authoritative one's position the less
one speaks in public. But if someone says to
another, "You have eaten the toad and spat out
its head", he understands at once that he is being
accused of avoiding part of his responsibilities.
The hermeticism of this "half-speech" shows at
once the inestimable value of oral tradition, and
its limits. It is almost impossible to transfer all
its richness from one language to another, espe¬
cially when that other is structurally and socio¬
logically very remote. Tradition does not stand
up well to translation. When uprooted it loses
its vigour and authenticity, for language is "the
home of being". Many errors ascribed to tradi¬
tion itself are due to incompetent or un¬
scrupulous interpreters.
The solid substance
of historical reality
Be that as it may, the validity of oral tradition
has today been amply proved, and confirmed by
crosschecking with written and archaeological
sources, as in the case of the Koumbi Saleh site,
the Lake Kisale remains and the events of the
sixteenth century as transmitted by the Shona,
which D.P. Abraham has observed to be in agree¬
ment with the writings of Portuguese travellers
of the period.
To sum up, the mode of discourse of oral
tradition, whether in epic or prose, whether
didactic or ethical, may be of historical value
from three standpoints. First, it reveals the values
and usages which motivate a people and condi¬
tion their future acts through representation of
archetypes from the past. In doing this, it not
only reflects but also creates history. When Da
Monzón is addressed as "master of waters and
master of men", this signifies the absoluteness
of his power. But the same stories also show him
constantly consulting his warriors, his griots and
his wives. From the famous line in the Song of
the Bow in honour of Sundiata (Sundiata Tasa),
"Saya Kaoussa malo ye" ("Death is preferable to
dishonour"), we can appreciate that a sense of
honour was one of the values of Malinke society
in the thirteenth century.
The same idea is also beautifully expressed
in the story of Bakary Dian's struggle against the
Fulani of Kournari. The valiant Bakary Dian has
retired in anger to his village, Dongorongo, and
the people come to beg him to return to the head
of the Segou army. He gives way finally when
they touch the sensitive chord of pride and glory:
"Forget old words exchanged. It is your present
name you must think of. For one comes into the
world to make a name. If you are born, grow
up and die without a name, you have come into
the world for nothing, and you have left it for
nothing." Then he cries: "Griots of Segou, since
you have come it is not impossible. I will do what
you ask, for the sake of my fame. I will not do
it for Da Monzón. I will do it for no one in
Right, a historian
consults an elderly
chief in Mali.
Above, musicians in
a Côte d'Ivoire
village. Three of
them are playing the
balafon, a West
African xylophone
with gourd
resonators.
Segou. I will do it just for my reputation. Even
after my death, it will be added to my name."
Similarly, the workings of both civilization and
law can be seen when Silamaka says, "You are
fortunate that I am forbidden to kill messengers".
Second, oral tradition offers incidental
descriptions of facts and objects. The reconstruc¬
tion of the past is by no means wholly fictional.
There are passages of recollection, veins of his¬
tory which are often more prosaic than the vivid
decorations of the epic imagination: "Thus began
this institution of collective herding in Bambara
towns. If you were chosen and made a herdsman,
you became a public Fula. The public Fulani
kept the flocks of the King. They were men of
different races, and their chief shepherd was
called Bonke." Again: "At that time people did
not wear slippers, but leather samaras of tanned
ox-hide, with a strap round the nose [the big toe]
and a strap round the heel."
The epic is strewn with allusions to tech¬
niques and to objects which are not essential to
the action but suggest the setting. "Da Monzón
sent for his sixty Somono paddlers, thirty men at
the prow and thirty at the stern. The canoe was
richly decorated." "Ladders were got ready and
set against the wall. The Segou infantry attacked
and infiltrated the town... The Segou horsemen
launched flaming arrows. The houses of the
village caught alight." Saran, the woman in love
with Da Monzón, goes and wets the Kore war¬
riors' gunpowder... It is only through a careful
analysis, sometimes even psychoanalysis, of the
very psychoses of the transmitters of the tradi¬
tion, and of their audience, that the historian can
get to the solid substance of historical reality.
The number of different versions transmitted
by rival groupsfor example, by the various
griot clients of each noble protector (horon,
dyatigui), far from being a handicap, is on the
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
contrary only a further guarantee for critical his¬
tory. When accounts agree, as in the case of the
Bambara and Fula griots, who belonged to
opposing camps, the authenticity of the evidence
is reinforced. And as is shown in the case of the
Gouro, with whom a liberal and integrationist
exoteric tradition, transmitted by the lineage,
coexists with the oligarchical and hairsplitting
esoteric tradition of the secret society, spoken
history contains self-censoring elements because
of its very different origins. In fact, it is not
private property, but a common fund which
derives from and provides for various groups in
the community.
The important thing is that internal criticism
of these records should be supported by a
thorough knowledge of the genre in question,
its themes and techniques, its codes and stereo¬
types, its set phrases of padding, the conventional
digression, the evolution of the language, the
audience and its expectations of the storytellers.
Above all, the historian must know about the
caste to which the latter belongedtheir rules
of life, how they were brought up, their ideals,
their schools. We know that in Mali and Guinea,
for example, there have for centuries been actual
schools of initiation at Keyla, Kita, Niagassola,
Niani, and so on.
The language of music
This rigid, formal and institutional oral tradition
to which structure has been imparted in training
schools is a third aspect of its historical value.
The structure is usually reinforced and supported
by court music, which is integral to it and un¬
derlines its didactic and artistic elements. Some
of the instruments used, such as the sosso baila
(the balafon of Sumarro Kante), are so old that
they would repay an archaeological investigation
in themselves. But the correspondences between
types of instrument and music, types of song and
African harps,
zither (top centre), and drums.
dance, make up a minutely ordered world, in
which anomalies and later additions are easily
detected.
Every genre has its own special instrument
in each cultural region: the baila (xylophone) or
the bolon (harp-lute) for epic in Mali; the bendre
(a big round one-sided drum made out of a gourd
and beaten with the bare hands) of the Mossi for
the exaltation (often silent) of the zabyouya (noms
de guerre) of the kings; the mvet (harp-zither) for
the tropical Niebelungen of the Fang poet-
musicians. These instruments, the vehicles of
spoken history, are sacred, the object of venera¬
tion. In effect they are part of the artist, and their
importance in communicating the message is all
the greater since, because language is tonal, music
has direct meaning; the instrument becomes the
artist's voice and he does not need to utter a
word. The triple rhythm of tone, intensity and
duration becomes music with meaning, the kind
of "semantic melodism" Marcel Jousse spoke of.
As a matter of fact, music is so much a part of
oral tradition that some stories can only be told
in song. Popular song, which epitomizes the
will of the people in a satirical form, sometimes
spiced with black humour, which still retains
its vitality even in the present age with its
election campaigns, is a valuable genre, com¬
plementing and counterbalancing the evidence
of official records.
What has been said here of music applies
equally to the other modes of expression, such
as the visual arts. As in the bas-reliefs of the king¬
doms of Abomey and Benin, or in Kuba sculp¬
ture, we sometimes find a direct expression of
historical characters, cultures and events.
Thus oral tradition is not just a second-best
source to be resorted to only when there is
nothing else. It is a distinct source in itself, with
a now well-established methodology, and it lends
the history of the African continent a marked
originality.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF IN BRIEF IN BRIEF
Odorous opera
Audiences at a recent
London production of
Prokofiev's opera The Love
of Three Oranges had an
opportunity to smell key
scenes as well as see and
hear them. The opera tells
the story of a prince whose
love for an orange, which
turns into a princess,
triumphs over evil plots. By
scraping cards
incorporating "fragrance
panels" at appropriate
moments, the audience
could smell orange
blossom, bad eggs (demon
scene), rotten meat
(kitchen scene) and an
exotic perfume (finale).
Gene that makes brain
protein discovered
Researchers have located
for the first time a gene
crucial for brain function,
reports the British scientific
journal Nature. The gene is
one of several that tells
brain cells how to make a
protein called a glutamate
receptor which plays an
Important role In the
process of brain cell
communication. Scientists
hope that studies on
glutamate receptors may
lead to the development of
drugs that limit brain
damage in stroke, seizure
or head Injury victims, and
to improved treatment for
learning and memory
disorders.
Dental health
and wealth
Increasing consumption of
junk food and refined
sugar In developing
countries has led to a
marked rise in tooth decay
since the 1960s, says the
World Health Organization
(WHO). A notable
exception is China, whose
children have the healthiest
teeth on the WHO scale
based on the number of
decayed, missing and filled
teeth in 12-year-olds. In the
Industrialized world,
according to the WHO
report on "Trends in Oral
Health and Care", hygiene
and fluoridation
programmes have caused
an improvement In dental
health, with Finland and
Australia highest on the
scale, closely followed by
the USA and Sweden.
Great epics from a
single source?
A single lost oral source
may lie at the origin of
Homer's Odyssey, the
Arabian Nights and the
Babylonian Epic of
Gilgamesh. In a recent
book,* Dr. Stephanie
Dalley has pointed out
major points of similarity
between the works which
suggest that Odysseus,
Gilgamesh and Sindbad
may originate from the
same character. Cross-
fertilization between the
epics may have occurred as
traditional tales were
adapted by storytellers for
different ethnic audiences.
* Myths from Mesopotamia, Oxford
University Press, 1989
Leaning Tower
at full tilt
The Leaning Tower of Pisa
has been closed to the
public so that work can be
carried out to make it
permanently safe without
losing its tilt. Begun In
1174, the 14,000-tonne
white marble Tower is 8
stories high to its belfry,
which was added in 1350.
It is currently leaning over
5 metres from the
perpendicular and is
sinking about 1 mm a year.
Against "lifestyle"
diseases
The World Health
Organization has launched
a programme called
"Interhealth" to promote
healthy living and action
against noncommunicable
diseases caused by choice
of lifestylesnotably by too
much fatty food, salt and
alcohol, by tobacco, lack of
exercise and polluted air.
Noncommunicable diseases
cause 70 to 80 per cent of
deaths in Industrialized
countries and 40 to 50 per
cent in the developing
world, WHO says.
Prehistoric monster
Palaeontologists in
Colorado, USA, have
unearthed the fossilized
remains of a dinosaur
which rivalled the size of
the gigantic carnivore
Tyrannosaurus Rex but
lived 30 million years
earlier. Known as
Epanterias, the beast
was about 15 metres
long, weighed about
4 tonnes and could have
eaten up to 40 tonnes
of meat a year. "It could
even have swallowed
a whole cow," said Mr.
Robert T. Bakker of the
University of Colorado,
leader of the expedition
which discovered the
remains.
Museums and
literacy
Unesco's quarterly
review Museum marks
the start of International
Literacy Year with
its first Issue for 1 990
(No. 165). Articles focus
on museums which
celebrate the history of
the written word,
such as the Sungam
Archives (Rep. of Korea)
and the Gutenberg
Museum, Mainz (Fed.
Rep. of Germany) and on
museums in France,
Kazakhstan (USSR), Cuba
and Nicaragua which
record the spread of mass
literacy. The Issue also
contains a section on
museums In the Pacific
and' regular features
including "A city and Its
museums" (Beijing). The
theme of Museum's next
issue will be "Port
museums around the
world".
Preparing for
catastrophe
As part of Its contribution
to the United Nations
International Decade
for Natural Disaster
Reduction (1990-1999),
the World Health
Organization has opened
a Panafrican Centre for
Emergency Preparedness
and Response In Addis
Ababa (Ethiopia). The
Centre has been set up
to help cope with
catastrophes such as
drought, famine, floods,
cyclones, earthquakes,
wars, and outbreaks
of communicable disease,
all of which have
afflicted Africa in recent
years.
IN BRIEF IN BRIEF IN BRIEF* . .
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
ANNA AKHMATOVA
'MOTHER COURAGE' OF POETRY
BY YELENA BYELYAKOVA
48
IHE life of Anna Akhmatova was a
tragic one. Although she had her mo¬
ments of glory she also experienced
terrible humiliations.
She was born In 1889, and her
youth coincided with an extraordi¬
nary literary flowering, the silver age
of Russian poetry. Her first volume of
verses, Vecher ("Evening") was pub¬
lished in 1912. It was followed two
years later by Chyotki ("Rosary")
which was reprinted eight times and
made her name. The themes of most
of her early poems are meetings and
separations, love and solitude. Their
style Is rigorous, lucid, laconic.
Her poetry was read throughout
Russia, and the critics predicted a bril¬
liant future for this "Russian Sappho".
She published regularlyBelaya
staya (1917; "The White Flock"),
Podorozhnik (1921; "Plantain"), and
Anno Domini MCMXXI (1922).
Unlike many Intellectuals In her
circle, Akhmatova did not emigrate
after the Revolution of October 1917.
Yet In 1923 her work ceased to be
published. The official view was that
her lyrics were alien to the new
generation of readers produced by
the Revolution. Fame was followed
by oblivion: for seventeen years her
name vanished from literature.
Life had other trials in store for
her. In 1921 her first husband, the
poet Nikolay Gumllyov, was executed
after being accused of taking part In
a counter-revolutionary conspiracy.
Her son, the orientalist Lev Gumilyov,
was arrested In 1935 and eventually
spent fourteen years In prison and
exile In Siberia. Her third husband, the
art historian Nikolay Punin, died In
prison.
Yet Anna Akhmatova continued
to write. The anguish she shared with
thousands of other women who
queued outside the prisons of Lenin¬
grad Inspired the cycle Rekvlem
(1935-1940; "Requiem"), which tells
Portrait of Anna Akhmatova (1914), by Nathan Altman (1889-1970).
the tragic story of a mother separated
from her only son. She visited her
friend the poet Osip Mandelstam,
exiled In Voronezh, and wrote poems
filled with foreboding about his Im¬
minent death. She denounced the
Illegal and arbitrary acts which were
being committed In her country, and
exposed the cruelty of Stalin and his
entourage. Fearing arrest, she memo¬
rized her verses rather than write
them down.
In 1940 several poems she had
written before the Revolution were
published. Later, patriotic lyrics she
wrote during the war were published
in several newspapers and
magazines.
But In 1946 she became the
main target of an Ideological cam¬
paign launched against the artistic
and literary intelligentsia by the Cen¬
tral Committee of the Communist
Party, which passed a resolution
condemning the literary reviews
Zvezda ("The Star") and Leningrad
for publishing her poetry, which was
branded as "bourgeois and deca¬
dent", "devoid of an Ideological mes¬
sage" and "alien to the Soviet
people".
The entire printrun of her most
recent collection of poems was des¬
troyed and she was expelled from the
Union of Soviet Writers. For ten years
she was again ostracized. Not until
the thaw which followed the death
of Stalin was she reinstated in the
Writers' Union and allowed to pub¬
lish again. By now the interest In her
poetry was immense.
In the 1 960s Akhmatova became
world famous. Her work was trans¬
lated Into English, French, German,
Italian, Czech, Bulgarian and many
other languages. Many articles,
books and studies were published
about her poetry. In 1964 she
travelled to Italy where she was
awarded the Etna-Taormlna interna¬
tional poetry prize, and In the follow¬
ing year she received an honorary
doctorate from Oxford University.
Anna Akhmatova died on 5
March 1 966. As the years go by the
interest In her work continues to
grow. Her collections of poems are
often reprinted, and unpublished
works are coming to light, Including
some fine patriotic poems which
were virtually unknown in the Soviet
Union until recently. Rekvlem, which
had appeared In the West In the
1960s, was not published In the
Soviet Union until 1987. In 1988, the
Communist Party resolution against
the reviews Leningrad and Zvezda
was officially rescinded and In 1989
Zvezda devoted an entire issue to the
centenary of Anna Akhmatova's
birth.
The city of Leningrad, which
played a major part in her life, was
the centre of the centenary celebra¬
tions In June 1989. A memorial
museum was opened on the Fontan-
ka Embankment, where for over
thirty years she had lived and com¬
posed some of her most tragic
poems. Conferences were organized
by the Russian Literature Institute of
the USSR Academy of Sciences and
the Leningrad Writers' Organization.
At literary and musical evenings lead¬
ing poets read her works and poems
dedicated to her by contemporaries
Including Aleksandr Blok, Marina
Tsvetayeva, Osip Mandelstam, and
Boris Pasternak. Song cycles of her
lyrics set to music by Prokofiev and
Slonlmsky were also performed.
The anniversary provided the
opportunity to pay a fitting tribute to
one of the greatest poets of the
century.
YELENA BYELYAKOVA,
of the USSR, ¡s a correspondent of
the Novosti Press Agency ¡n
Leningrad.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
A .Philip K.UIail.l|ltl
25
Letters to the Editor
High days and holidays
I was very surprised by the conclusion
of Abdol-Hosseyn Zarrlnkoub's article
on Now Rouz, the Iranian New Year
festival, which appeared in the
"Reflections" feature of your January
1990 Issue under the title "The
struggle of day and night". The
author, an eminent Iranian historian,
wrote that "If Islam has kept up this
Zoroastrian feast, It Is because of the
role It plays In the stabilization of the
fiscal year and also because of Its
"jovial and lively ceremonies..."
It Is well known that Islam has
usually respected all earlier practices
whenever these were not socially
harmful. Consequently, there has
never been any attempt to put an
end to the pre-Islamic Now Rouz fes¬
tival In Iran. It has not survived for
"fiscal" reasons, nor because of its
"jovial" character but because It was
tolerated as an established tradition.
Islam has even taken part In
some aspects of this festival. Mr.
Zarrlnkoub must know that on 21
March, the Iranian New Year's Day,
at the precise moment of the spring
equinox, Iranian Muslims recite a
prayer asking "God who transforms
night and day" to change the state
of their soul and direct it towards
goodness.
I am also astonished that Mr.
Zarrlnkoub should write that the sufls
are Interested In this festival because
of the singing and dancing which
accompany it, as if the great sufi
thinkers had been engaged in a search
for such transient enjoyments...
Reza Feiz
Former Permanent Delegate
to Unesco of the Islamic
Republic of Iran
A window
on the world
I have been reading your magazine
for twenty years. For me Its excellent
Illustrations really have been "a win¬
dow open on the world".
Starting with your June 1989
Issue, the magazine's presentation
has been modernized and above all
its contents have become less ab¬
stract. One of the golden rules of
modern journalism, which you are
now observing more closely, is to
present a wide variety of subjects by
showing individual people In specific
situations. Abstract reasoning auto¬
matically requires the kind of lan¬
guage which Is found In official
documents and which gave your ar¬
ticles a cold and arid flavour. It Is the
emotional appeal of an article that
makes a lasting Impact on readers.
Ideas only make a mark when they
evoke an emotional response.
The Interview with Mr. François
Mitterrand was, to my mind, a deci¬
sive step for your magazine and its
new ¡mage. I think you should con¬
tinue to publish regular interviews
with and articles by leading politicians
as well as outstanding figures in
science and culture.
Finally, why not encourage ex¬
changes between peoples In the
fields of science and culture by pub¬
lishing In your letters column the ad¬
dresses of persons seeking contact
with colleagues elsewhere in the
world?
Vladimir Ovchinnikov
(Journalist)
Novosibirsk,
USSR
Arab mathematics
I am very glad that you devoted an
article In your Issue "A Mathemati¬
cal Mystery Tour" (November 1989)
to the history of Arab mathematics,
a subject which Is still not widely
known. However, the article calls for
some comment.
While I fully agree with what Mr.
Rashed says at the end of his Inter¬
view about the continuity of mathe¬
matical thought in the Mediterranean
basin from the time of the Greeks
until the eighteenth centuryI should
be Inclined to say even until todayI
find It hard to subscribe to his other
statements. I shall comment here on
three questions raised by Mr. Rashed.
1 . The originality of al-Khwarizml's
Kitab al-jabr wa'l muqabalah ("The
Book of Integration and Equation"),
which Mr. Rashed seems to take for
granted, Is far from proven. In the In¬
troduction to his book, al-Khwarizmi
Informs us that It ¡s a "summary
(mulakhkhas) of the calculation of in¬
tegration and equation" written at
the request of Caliph al-Ma'mun to
explain "the subtleties and the
difficulties of this form of calculation"
and to make It accessible to the pub¬
lic. Before an explanatory summary
of a science can be written, that
science must already exist.
The originality of the work Is par¬
ticularly difficult to establish since the
only surviving earlier text In which al¬
gebraic techniques are used is the
Arlthmetica, a treatise by the Greek
mathematician Dlophantus of Alex¬
andria which dates from the third
century AD and thus preceded al-
Khwarizml's work by six centuries. It
is true that al-Khwarizmi uses an al¬
gebraic vocabulary which does not
exist in Diophantus' work. But since
no text written later than this and be¬
fore the time of al-Khwarizmi has sur¬
vived, It is Impossible to be certain
about the origin of this vocabulary.
Finally, the problem of the origi¬
nality of al-Khwanzml's work is com¬
plicated by the fact that the formula
used to solve equations of the second
degree, which Is today taught In
secondary school, goes back to
Babylonlan^tlmes.
To say that the style of al-
Khwarizmi's work Is both "algorith¬
mic and demonstrative" Is to obscure
the nature of Its content. It Is not a
"style" that Is in question. Al-
Khwarizmi demonstratesand this Is
vitally Importantthe validity of al¬
gebraic formulas for solving equa¬
tions of the second degree by
geometrical demonstrations accom¬
panied by figures. These figures are
not taken from Euclid's Elements,
which was translated Into Arabic
around the same time as al-
Khwarizmi was writing (the third de¬
cade of the ninth century). The
figures thus do not come from the
Greek mathematical tradition. They
too pose the question of the work's
originality.
2. As for the relationship be¬
tween algebra and geometry, on the
one hand, and the "arithmeticlza-
tlon" of algebra on the other, I can¬
not see to what texts or procedures
of Arab algebra the expressions used
by Mr. Rashed refer. If we refer to the
texts, the development of algebra
and Its relationship with geometry
and arithmetic can be more precise¬
ly and more simply evoked In the fol¬
lowing way.
Arab algebra basically comprises 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
two parts: the solution of equations
of the first, second and third degree,
and the calculation of polynomials
(addition, multiplication, division, the
extraction of the roots of poly¬
nomials).
a) Al-Khwarlzml says of the rela¬
tions between these two parts, al¬
gebra and arithmetic, that the
fundamental objects of algebrathe
unknown and the second power of
the unknownare kinds of number.
Algebra is thus a form of arithmetic.
It cannot have been "arlthmetldzed"
by the successors of al-Khwarizmi.
What Mr. Rashed means by this Is
thus simply a normal but
Importantdevelopment of the cal¬
culation of polynomials.
b) The relations between algebra
and geometry are a little more com¬
plex. They particularly concern the
theory of equations of the second
and third degree.
To solve equations of the second
degree, the Arabs could use the for¬
mula given by al-Khwarizmi which
dates back, as we have said, to
Babylonian times. But the great Arab
mathematicians always accompanied
this formula with geometric demon¬
strations which al-Khwarizmi's suc¬
cessors largely borrowed from Book
II of Euclid's Elements. If the great
mathematicians took the trouble to
demonstrate the algebraic formulas
whereby they solved equations of the
second degree, It was not to make
a "translation" of them which would
in any case have been superfluous.
A demonstration cannot be consi¬
dered as a translation. If they did so
it was, as they said explicitly them¬
selves, to provide a proof of the va¬
lidity of the algebraic formulas used.
3. The attribution to Sharaf al-
Din al-Tusi of "methods such as
derivatives, that were only to be
named as such at a later date" can¬
not be justified by reference to his
writings. This misunderstanding has
been refuted on two occasions, once
by the author of this letter In the
review Annals of Science (44, 1987),
and secondly in an article published
by Mr. Hogendljk, a mathematician
and historian of Arab mathematics,
in the review Historia mathematica
(16, 1989).
Khalil Jaouiche
CNRS, Paris
Dionysian festivals
in Andalusia
In your December 1 989 issue, which
made Interesting reading, Jean Duvig-
naud refers in his article "The festive
spirit" to the "Roclo, the curious An¬
dalusian festival of the Virgin of the
Marshes, In which Arab, Christian
and Gypsy allegories overlap". One
might add that it also bears traces of
allegories reaching back to the Diony¬
sian rituals of Graeco-Roman tra¬
dition.
According to oral tradition, the
statue of the Virgin of the Rocío was
discovered by a hunter In Andalusia
in the early fifteenth century. The fact
that the dominant culture was Islamic
at that time clearly justifies Professor
Duvignaud's remarks about Arab and
Christian allegories. But why leave out
the Dionysian cult which Is known to
have reached the shores of Iberia?
Roman authors tell of the Greek
colonies which were founded nine
centuries before the Christian era In
the marshy estuary of the Guadal¬
quivir (the site of the present her¬
mitage of El Rocío) where other
populations later settled. Vestiges un¬
earthed near the sanctuary suggest
that a Roman temple once stood on
this site.
Traditions once thought lost
sometimes reapppear In a different
form but with all their original vigour,
their specific features and their rites.
Here, perhaps, lies the originality of
Andalusia, whose people have always
lived at a cultural crossroads.
Francisco J. Carrillo
Unesco, Paris
GENERAL HISTORY
OF AFRICA
50
Scholars from many countries are collaborating on Unesco's 8-volume General History of Africa
which is being prepared under the intellectual responsibility of an International Scientific Committee
for the Drafting of a General History of Africa, two-thirds of whose members are African. Africa
is considered as a -totality in this panoramic history which shows the changing relationships
between the various parts of the continent as well as connections with other continents, thus
bringing out the contribution Africa has made to the development of mankind.
Co-published with Heinemann Educational Books Ltd., United Kingdom, and the University of
California Press. Berkeley, United States. Available from academic bookshops throughout the
world or from the Unesco Press, 7 place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Already published
Vol. I: Methodology and African Prehistory, editor J. Ki-Zerbo (cased edition 175 French francs
or the equivalent in any convertible currency)
Vol II- Ancient Civilizations of Africa, editor G Mokhtar (175 FF).
Vol. III. Africa from the Seventh to Eleventh Century, editor M El Fasi (190 FF)
Vol IV: Africa from the Twelfth to Sixteenth Century, editor DT. Niane (190 FF)
Vol. VI The Nineteenth Century until 1880, editor J F A Ajayi (220 FF).
Vol VII. Africa under Foreign Domination, 1880-1935, editor A.A Boahen (190 FF).
Forthcoming
Vol. V: Africa from the Sixteenth to Eighteenth Century, editor B A Ogot.
Vol. VIII Africa since 1935, editor A A. Mazrui.
An abridged paperback edition is in preparation, to be co-published in Europe by
James Currey Publishers, London, and in the United States by the University of California Press
Vol I now published. Vols II and VII forthcoming
. Acknowledgements
Cover: Faillet © Artephot, Paris." Back
cover: © Pestaña, Pans. Page 2: ©
Josette Verbestel, Belgium. Pages 4-5, 14
(above), 37 (left), 39: © Roger Viollet,
Paris. Pages 6, 7: © Keystone, Paris.
Page 8: Morvan © Sipa Press, Paris. Page
9: Wallis © Sipa Press, Paris. Page 10:
Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris. Pages
12-13: Erich Lessing © Magnum, Paris.
Page 14 (centre): J. Ross © Rapho, Paris.
Page 14 (below): © Bulloz, Musée
Carnavalet, Paris. Page 15 (above): © de
Selva-Tapabor, Paris. Pages 15 (below),
19, 31: © Lauros Giraudon, Paris. Pages
16, 25 (below): © Jean-Loup Charmet,
Paris. Page 17 (above): All Rights
Reserved. Pages 17 (below), 22-23, 29:
© Dagli Orti, Paris. Pages 18, 20, 36-37:
© Edimédia, Paris. Page 21: © Cahiers
du Cinéma, Pans. Pages 23 (inset), 24
(centre and below): © J.L. Nou, Paris.
Page 24 (above): © National Museum,
New Delhi. Page 25 (above): Cartier
Bresson © Magnum, Paris. Pages 26, 28:
M. Yamashita © Rapho, Paris. Pages 27,
30, 37 (right): © E.R.L./Sipa Icono,
Paris. Pages 32-33 (above), 33 (right),
34, 35: © IPS, Paris. Pages 32-33
(below): © Bridgeman-Giraudon, Paris.
Pages 38-39: © Réunion des Musées
Nationaux/Louvre, Paris. Page 40: ©
Kharbine Tapabor, Paris. Page 41: ©
Gemeentemuseum, The Hague. Page 42
(top): © Musée de l'Homme, Paris. Page
42 (centre above): © Vautier Decool,
Paris. Page 42 (centre below): © Jean
Suquct, Paris. Page 42 (bottom): ©
Museum of Asian Art/Stedelijk
Museum, Amsterdam. Pages 43, 44-45:
Renaudeau © Hoa Qui, Paris. Page 45:
Ph. Cassard © Hoa Qui, Paris. Page 46:
M. Huet © Hoa Qui, Paris. Page 48: ©
APN Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
Published monthly in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Russian edition: Georgi Zelenin
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Public relations: Claudie Duhamel (Tel.:45.68.45.86)
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prashad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Metra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88), Assistant: Marie-
Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89), Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse
Hardy (45.68.45.65), Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité,
Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo,
Michel Ravassard, Michelle Robillard,
Mohamed Salah El Din, Sylvie Van Rijsewijk
Customer service: Ginette Mot reff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: Liliane Tasch (45.68.45.66), Cultural projects:
Ricardo Zamora-Perez (45.68.45.80),
Mail: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 68 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF,
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply couoon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Couner staff. The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is
produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2: University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor. Michigan 48100, U S A ., (3) N.C.fi. Microcard Edition. Indian
Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York, U.i.A., (4) Bell and
Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) - DEPOT LEGAL . CI - AVRIL 1990
COMMISSION PARITAIRE NO 7' 844 - DIFFUSE PAR lES NMPP.
Photocomposition: The Unesco Courier
Photogravure- impression: Maury Imprimeur S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes.
45330 Malesherbes
JUST
PUBLISHED
Jean.plerre Vé/fs
&r a «-.
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 4 1990 OPI 90 3 479 A
The British public was rather taken aback to learn that there were an estimated
2 million functional illiterates in the United Kingdom, excluding immigrants.
In the United States, the National Assessment of Educational Progress came up
with the figure of 23 million functional illiterates.
...functional illiteracy, in one or other of its forms, affects one in every five
French adults.
...illiteracy and the whole social reality of which it is a symptom are shrouded in
ignorance or indifference.
These passages Through a glass, darkly, by Jean-Pierre Vélis, reflect a phenomenon
largely ignored until recently: functional illiteracy affects millions in the industrialized world.
The author, a French journalist specializing in education, has devoted much time and
effort to this problem. In this reportage he looks at functional illiterates in industrialized
countries throughout the world, recounts their stories and describes efforts to overcome
and eliminate functional illiteracy.
Unesco 1990, 137 pp., ISBN 92-3-102651-8, 75 French francs
On sate in academic bookshops throughout the world and at the Unesco Bookshop
(prepaid orders only), 7 place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, France.
This issue comprises 54 pages and a 4-page advertising insert
between pages 10 1 1 and 42-43
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
w^^^m^^r.
Z^Ê~^
-Z*
Xi.
^-.'
M i-
"*><)
^~'
]]>
</page>
</document>
