<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="086203eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
H
¿¿ e*.
^ *fcs
S
JULY 1990
ILLITERATES
A challenge for our time
v>~,
& ^
M 1206 - 9007 - 15,00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
_l
encounters
We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
The ropes
of silence
1984, oil painting
(60 x 70 cm)
by Simone
"Slav by virtue of her
abrasive humour, Flemish
in her imperturbable
truculence, Latin in the
freedom of her
imagination, German in
her power of expression,
Simone is actually Belgian
and Walloon", writes the
art critic Michel Ducobu.
"Firmly planted on the
feet of Brabant peasants,
her seven pillars of fear,
like a set of skittles,
provide an occasion for
reflection at a time when
the toppling of former
masters is unleashing a
mighty wave of liberating
hilarity in Europe."
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JULY 1990
N N
Today there are no more
unexplored continents,
unknown seas or mysterious
islands. But while we can
overcome the physical
barriers to exploration, the
barriers of mutual ignorance
between different peoples
and cultures have in many
cases still not been
dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can
voyage to the ends of the
earth. But a different kind
of Odyssey now beckonsan
exploration of the world's
many cultural landscapes, the
ways of life of its different
peoples and their outlook on
the world ¡n which they live.
It is such an Odyssey that
the Unesco Courier proposes
to its readers. Each month
contributors of different
nationalities provide from
different cultural and
professional standpoints an
authoritative treatment of a
theme of universal interest.
The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes is respect
for the dignity of man
everywhere.
9
ONE BILLION ILLITERATES
A CHALLENGE FOR OUR TIME
International Literacy Year, 1990
FROM RHETORIC TO REALITY
by John Ryan 10
WORLD LITERACY: WHERE WE STAND TODAY
by Sylvain Lourié 13
REPORTS FROM AROUND THE WORLD
Latin America: illiteracy, democracy and development
by Juan Carlos Tedesco 14
Africa: disturbing trends
by Baba Haidara 15
Asia and the Pacific: responding to the challenge
by Shozo Jizawa 15
The industrialized countries: questions and answers
by Leslie Limage 16
THE MIND TRANSFORMED
by Raja Roy-Singh 21
THE GENDER GAP
by Agneta Lind 24
NATIONAL LANGUAGES AND
MOTHER TONGUES
by Adama Ouane 27
WASTE
by Jean-Pierre Véhs 30
THE PC AND THE 3Rs
by Kenneth Levine 33
4
Interview with
SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV
41
IN BRIEF... 41
DOCUMENT
The new illiterates
by Pedro Salinas 42
SCIENCE
Cold fusiona storm in
a test-tube?
by Dan Clery 46
FORUM
Science for decision-makers:
The International Federation of
Institutes for Advanced Study 48
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR 49
Unesco and International
Literacy Year 50
THE ROAD TO READING
by Ralph C. Staiger 37
Cover: the official
International Literacy Year
poster, designed by Zabcllc
Côté, a Canadian student.
Back cover: a reading lesson in
Patna, Bihar state (India).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
R V I
A leading Soviet medievalist sounds the alarm at the onset
of a hedonistic culture in modern technocratic societies
Sergei S. Averintsev
A sense of écency
You are both a scientist and a man ofculture. How would Then there's the total disappearance of a culture character-
you describe the cultural situation today? What trends ized by a sense of decency or modesty, and finally an absurd
encouraging or disturbingdo you see? ~ syncretism of capitalist and Marxist values that has nothing
The most encouraging factor is the total breakdown of to do with tolerance and even less with a desire for synthesis,
ideological folly. It may return, of courseGod help us if and lumps "Ford", "Freud" and "Marx" together on the
it doesbut only as a kind of sinister mystification. Never same level in a godless world,
again will it lead the human mind astray. Never again. The Libido is invading life. Not a carnal libido. It is as if
blood of innocent victims has washed the altars of these machines have become consumed with lust or human nature
inhuman cults. The errors of the past, the fruits of worthy is becoming machine-like.
thinkers of the late nineteenth century and the beginning.. It's very hard to talk about a sense of decency today,
of the twentieth, have been dethroned along with totalitarian especially in my country where people reject wholesale a
ideologies. The roots of the evil must be sought much earlier code of good behaviour which is forcibly imposed on them
in the history of thought. as though they were eternal children. It is true that this code
There is still reason for anxiety, however. Let's take of conduct is only a caricature of a true culture of decency,
two contemporary anti-utopian works as signposts with Good behaviour cannot replace nobility of soul. It can even
"Impasse" written on themGeorge Orwell's 1984 and be said that the road which leads from good behaviour to
Aldous Huxley's Brave New World. It looks as if we shall nobility of soul is a hard one. On the other hand, the road
be spared the horrors described by Orwell, but we're moving that leads to such deviations as mass hypocrisy is, alas, so
dangerously close to the prophecies of Huxley.1 In our much easier. How can one fail to deplore the fact that rock
everyday lives we can detect warning signs of a brave new groups (at best) and sex shops (at worst) have become the
worlda vulgar hedonism, which in my country can only inevitable accompaniment and even in a sense the emblem
be partially indulged because of the lack of consumer goods of liberal democracy?
but which is all the more powerful since it is unsatisfied. Let's not forget that there is a civic tradition in Europe,
	 however imperfect it may be, and that this tradition was
. ,,. , r,, -. , .i- 1 i imQ u i. established by puritans. The legend that is at the origin of
1. Nineteen Eighty-Four, a novel published in 1949 by the ; r ö ö .
English author George Orwell (1903-1950), evokes a totalitarian the Western ideal of freedom-that to defend the honour
world in which people are at the mercy of a bureaucracy which 0f a virtuous woman the Romans rose up and overthrew
records secret information about them. In Brave New World Mr kings_has become a joke tod It's sad> not onl for
(1932) Aldous Huxley depicts a future in which people are . , , n r r j
psychologically conditioned according to the planned needs of vlrtue but above aü ior freedom.
a technological civilization directed by a few individuals. Editor Today's extreme permissiveness is as different from sin
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
committed in the heat of passion as a cancer is different from
a benign tumour. The defenders of nature who are, thank
God, so active today should remember that human nature
is threatened too, that such a systematic destruction of the
ideal of decency is not restricted to sexual morality and may
have unforeseeable consequences.
The culture of decency belongs to history. Its manifesta¬
tions are recorded in the relativity of history," so that, for
example, the sense of decency of the pagans of Antiquity is,
from a Christian or Muslim point of view, indecent. But
never in history has humanity been able to do without the
principle of decency. Those who study the problem of
mutual comprehension between cultures must take into
account the fact that, for Islam, for example, the universal
sub-culture of sex shops is mortally offensive. I mention
Islam because no one seems to think about Christianity
anymore. Although of course when a sex shop is opened
near York Minster, a medieval cathedral in one of the
oldest cities in Christendom, it is impossible not to see this
as an attack on the rights of believers.
It's not easy for me to talk about this, since in my
country the rights of believers have been treated even more
roughly, and still are, as I know from my experience as a
member of parliament. But take these two examples, one
Orwellian, the other worthy of Huxley. The first is sym¬
bolized by a ruined Church, the second by a church flanked
by a sex shop. I couldn't say which is worse.
Below, Epiphany festival at
the Cathedral of the Nativity
(13th century), in the Kremlin
at Suzdal, Central Russia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The development ofhumanity is comparable to that of a
person. Its path is marked by remarkable cultural gains
but losses seem to be inevitable, too. Which do you think
are the most regrettable of these losses and which do you
consider normal and justified?
It's always a pity to lose something. I can't "justify" any
loss. Humanity can survive without such and such a code
of honour, but not without the very notion of honour. I
am very sad that the classical languages, Greek and Latin,
are disappearing from European life. Fewer and fewer people
will be capable of reading Aristotle in the original, but that's
not the whole point. The far more important question is
whether Aristotelian thought will survive.
Cultures influence each other, but is there a line between
the fertilization ofone culture by another and its destruc¬
tion? Is not every action by one culture vis-à-vis another
a form ofaggression? In any case, is there such a thing as
a "pure" culture?
There is nothing intrinsically aggressive in the action of
one culture on another. A "pure" culture would be just as
absurd as a series of incestuous marriages within the same
family, inevitably resulting in degeneration. The originality
of a culture is measured, among other factors, by its ability
to creatively assimilate outside influences. Nearly all the lines
of the Aeneid contain echoes of Greek verse, but that doesn't
prevent Virgil from expressing the very essence of Rome.
It is usually factors that are not strictly speaking cultural
that are the most destructive of other traditions. The effects
of unbridled consumption, the excessive influence of distant
colonial or imperial centres. As when the Seleucid king
Antiochus IV Epiphanes ordered a small people to forget
that they were the people of the Bible.
The freedom ofhumanity is the freedom of culture. What
can the tide which is carrying the world towards democracy,
pluralism and non-ideological international relations bring
to world culture?
Nothing less than its chance of survival. God knows that
democracy can be accompanied by barbarity, but it can also
be synonymous with culture. In a way it has a choice. But
totalitarianism can never be synonymous with culture, no
matter how strong the cultural forces with which it seeks
to associate itself. The logic of totalitarianism forbids culture
to be culture. This logic has infinitely more weight than the
plebian origins of the seminarist Dzhugashvili or Corporal
Schicklgruber.2 "Freedom of thought" is a pleonastic
expression, because thought only exists when it is free.
Thought can .develop on the foundations of faith, but
it has no place in ideology. Tasks can be fairly divided
between faith and thought. The one can't replace the other
GeageOrodl 1984 le meilleur
Illustration Jean Alessandnni
ALDOUS HUXLEY
Illustration- Michel Simeon
Covers of French editions of
Orwell's 1984 and
Huxley's Brave New World.
because faith, by definition, is concerned with what is tran¬
scendental to thought. Ideology, also by definition, deals
with what should legitimately belong to the realm of
thought, because unlike faith it has no specific object of its
own, it is parasitical. It is an unworthy error for faith to
wish to take the place of thought. But ideology can't do any¬
thing else: it has no choice.
How do you see the future of religions and their place in
the world today and tomorrow? How are the concepts of
religion and freedom connected?
I am absolutely convinced that religious traditions are
stronger than anything else. Their propensity to survive in
extreme conditions is extraordinary. Everything new soon
becomes obsolete, but these traditions endure. After the
worst ordeals, they are regenerated. This has happened
several times in history and today is one of those times.
The major threat to religions isn't the "death" that is
predicted for them, but degeneration. Homo technicus neo-
barbarus, the dominant human species, is more dedicated
to technology than to culture. Early on, he transformed
religion into "parapsychology" or, rather, parapolitics. In
short, a kind of ideology. I once heard an Italian priest
quoting Teilhard de Chardin, for whom I have great esteem,
with an intonation that was all too familiar to my Russian
ears as that with which "the classics of Marxism" were
recited for decades in my country. A religious ideology is
just as inconceivable to me as a scientific ideology, and for
the same reason: the intolerance of ideology denies the very
existence of the need for the spiritual lucidity and the close
perception of objective data that are indispensable to both
the religious impulse and scientific analysis.
2. Joseph Stalin and Adolf Hitler. Editor
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
On the Banks of the Jordan, oil on canvas by the French painter
Georges Rouault (1871-1958).
Religions once inspired great works of art. Are they still
capable ofthat today?
Who knows? Great works of purely Christian inspira¬
tion have been produced in our century. I think of the
paintings of Georges Rouault, the icons of Father Gregory
Krug, a Russo-Estonian hermit working in France, of the
music of Olivier Messiaen, the poems of Charles Péguy and
Paul Claudel, the late work of Vyacheslav Ivanov, and the
novels of Georges Bernanos. That's quite a list. Without their
religious undercurrent, the works of Heinrich Böll, Graham
Greene, Akhmatova, Pasternak, Solzhenitsyn, Alfred
Schnittkeour greatest living composerand so many
others would be unthinkable. And lest I be accused of
prejudice in favour of Christians I will also mention some
Jewish names, if only those of Bialik, Nelly Sachs and Samuel
Agnon. Only ignorance prevents me from adding Muslim
artists to the list. Which said, I'm not entirely convinced
that we shall soon be returning to the days when entire
peoples, borne on a tide of collective enthusiasm, built
cathedrals. I don't expect to see any "New Middle Ages".
Nothing repeats itself. God doesn't repeat anything. He
"always creates anew".
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
\J
rJ-3,
M
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Clay figurines by the
French artist Isabelle Simon
(1990).
Above, emblem of
International Literacy
Year designed by Japanese
graphic artist Koichi
Imakita.
Q
UR world is at once far more populous, more complex and more
interdependent than it was thirty years ago when Unesco defined an illiterate
person as someone "unable to read, write and understand a brief and simple
exposé of facts in relation to his or her daily life".
More populous: the world's population has risen from 3 billion in 1960 to
an estimated 5.3 billion today. Efforts to eradicate illiteracy have been colossal
but they have not kept pace with the demands of explosive rates of population
growth. Almost one billion adults in the world today are still unable to read
or write.
More complex: a technological revolution in telecommunications and
computers has called in question the very concept of "traditional" literacy.
The industrialized countries have discovered that a problem once thought
definitively solved by the provision of free and compulsory education is
obstinately persistent. Meanwhile, in many of the poorest countries, progress
along the road to universal primary education made in the 1970s has been
halted by economic crisis.
And yet in some ways things have not changed. Now as then illiteracy goes
hand in hand with hunger, poverty and isolation. While it may not preclude
knowledge or wisdom, it bars access to modern knowledge and deprives its
victims of a means of active participation in the life of the community. There
is still a widening "gender gap" between male and female literacy.
At the same time the sense of interdependence has become stronger. Whereas
it is for each country to face the problem of illiteracy within its own frontiers
there is a feeling that the question of world illiteracy is of concern to all, and
a realization that measures to improve the situation will be vain if isolated
from attempts to improve conditions of health, housing and employment.
It is in this spirit that 1990 has been proclaimed International Literacy Year
and it is in this spirit too that the present issue of the Unesco Courier has
been prepared to show readers what can and could be done.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
m
«
From rhetoric
to reality
By John Ryan
W,HAT can an International Year achieve?
Does it give an impetus to action or provide an
excuse for inaction, bestowing a conscience-
calming benediction upon a global problem
which perplexes or overwhelms us? The answer
probably depends not so much upon the theme of
the Year, per se, as upon what we are prepared
to do with it. The International Year of Disabled
Persons, which was observed in 1981, for example,
was instrumental in transforming attitudes and
redesigning facilities. Kerbs which had obstructed
wheel-chairs disappeared, traffic signals no longer
10
merely flashed, but also buzzed, and increasingly
ramps and elevators were installed to give the
disabled access to public places. Many of these
changes may have eventually occurred in any
case, but the Year gave fresh impetus to efforts
by and on behalf of the disabled, and armed those
who wanted to act with a reason and occasion
for doing so.
The Year also mobilized the disabled into ef¬
fective interest groups, making them keenly
aware of their numbers and needs. It would be
an exaggeration to say that history was trans¬
formed or the future redesigned by the Year, but,
for the disabled, history was moved into the fast
lane. The Year succeededor succeeded in many
placesbecause it was wanted and needed. The
disabled and their advocates were ready with
practical proposals for converting public aware¬
ness and support into tangible results. Alas, not
all International Years are equally successful.
Some remain almost clandestine events, entered
and exited without perturbation or visible
progress. Only a few cognoscenti seem to know
much about them; others may be vaguely aware;
and most, if asked, would venture that it was the
year of the snake or the pig or whatever.
How will International Literacy Year (ILY)
be remembered? As an event that helped to push
the vision of education for all from rhetoric
towards reality, as 365 days that made a differ¬
ence or at least a beginning, or as a non-event
hardly worth remembering at all? It is evidently
too early to judge. What is certain is that millions
of women and men around the world are engaged
in activities related to ILY, teaching and learn¬
ing in schools and literacy groups, in libraries and
learning centres, and working to promote edu¬
cation and literacy through governmental and
non-governmental organizations, the media and
in countless other places and ways. There are na¬
tional committees or structures for ILY in 109
Unesco member states; hundreds of non¬
governmental organizations have established spe¬
cial committees or programmes for the Year;
United Nations organizations are involved in a
variety of ways, and the mass mediaprint and
electronic alikeare increasing their coverage of
and involvement in literacy during 1990. Thus,
much is happening. How much and with what
effect we will only know when an assessment is
made in 1991.
There can be no doubt that the timing of the
Year is auspicious. 1 he easing of East-West ten¬
sions and the pending end of the "cold war" were
neither envisaged nor imagined in the autumn of
ft
Above, adult literacy class
in Bangladesh.
Left, 80 per cent of the
world's 50 million blind
persons live in developing
countries, where lack of
resources prevents many of
them from achieving
literacy.
JOHN RYAN
is coordinator of Unesco's
International Literacy Year
Secretariat. The author of
numerous studies and articles
on literacy, he was for some
years director of the
International Institute for
Adult Literacy Methods,
Teheran, Iran.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
v ' \/ v * / r x / ir*/ v
1985 when the General Conference of Unesco ap¬
pealed to the General Assembly of the United
Nations to proclaim an International Literacy
Year, nor even in December 1987 when the
General Assembly acted upon that request,
proclaiming 1990 as ILY. These profound changes
in the climate of international relations give spe¬
cial meaning and importance to ILY, for there
is now reason to hope that priorities will change
and attention and resources dedicated to the
preparation for war will be reallocated to the pur¬
suits of peace: to meeting the basic and urgent
needs of humanity.
Education, a victim
of economic crisis
ILY arrives not only at a moment of opportunity,
but also at a time of urgent need. The situation
regarding education is difficult, even dramatic, in
many developing countries, especially in the
poorest among them. The last decade has been
a period of economic crisis and social tensions.
Indeed, contrary to all logic and expectations,
during the last years of the decade, the net capital
flow has been from the poor countries to the rich
ones, from the "have-nots" to the "haves" of the
world. Education has been especially hard hit.
Many countries have seen the goal of universal
t i i .i . .Ull.ll El tllMin/VN*
primary education, a prerequisite for creating a
literate society, slip further from their grasp.
In this International Literacy Year, there are
an estimated 963 million illiterate adults (fifteen
years +) and over 125 million children between
the ages of six and eleven years, who are not en¬
rolled in school and are hence at risk of becom¬
ing the adult illiterates of the twenty-first century.
The situation regarding the education of women
is especially serious: one woman in three is illiter¬
ate, as compared to one man in five. Action is
imperative to check and reverse the decline of
education, the stagnation in growth and the ero¬
sion of quality. Even in the industrialized coun¬
tries, the situation is disquieting. In many such
Above, batik wall hanging
produced in Togo as part of
a women's literacy project
organized by Unesco and
financed by Norway. The
text commemorates
International Literacy Day,
celebrated each year on 8
September.
Above left, poster from the
national literacy campaign
in Nicaragua, 1984.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
societies, one fifth or more of the adult popula¬
tion is unable to cope adequately with the litera¬
cy demands of increasingly complex living and
working environments. It has been calculated that
the economic cost of this situation is enormous.
The human suffering it entails is inestimable.
Conscience and common sense alike demand that
we act vigorously to confront this global
problem, which is so wasteful of human poten¬
tial, so unjust and so unnecessary.
A fundamental
human right
The central message of ILY is, quite simply, that
education matters; it is a vital and pervasive force
in all aspects of life. Education shapes us as in¬
dividuals and as societies. It determines, in very
large measure, what we are and what we aspire
to become. Illiteracy does not preclude
knowledge or wisdom. There is genius in the oral
traditions of all nations and peoples. Yet, in the
modern world, education is the most essential
condition and powerful agent of progress. And
literacy is the vehicle of educationthe means
through which ideas, information, knowledge
and wisdom are expressed and exchanged. Thus,
in a larger sense, ILY is not only about educa¬
tion, but also about progress, development,
justice, equality and opportunity. The right to
education is instrumental to the enjoyment and
responsible exercise of other rights. It is essen¬
tial to effective participation in modern society.
Education is, in brief, the very measure, means
and meaning of development.
Cover of a reader produced
by the Jamaican Movement
for the Advancement of
Literacy (JAMAL). In 1989
JAMAL was awarded the
Nadezhda K. Krupskaya
Prize, presented annually by
Unesco in recognition of
notable contributions to the
struggle against illiteracy.
Children's United Nations,
by Aliki Brandenberg, an
illustration from a picture
book for children produced
by the Asian Cultural
Centre for Unesco (Tokyo)
for International Literacy
Year.
The role of lead organization for ILY, which
the United Nations General Assembly entrust¬
ed to Unesco, is paradoxically that of serving as
a humble and modest animator and facilitator.
If the Year is to have meaning, what will matter
is not what Unesco does, but what happens
around the world. Hence, Unesco's activities have
been selected as a means for setting in motion ac¬
tion in member states, within the United Nations
system, among non-governmental organizations
and through the media. The ultimate measure of
the success of ILY will be the extent to which
it facilitates teaching and learning among children
in schools and adults in literacy groups, in vil¬
lages and in cities, in the "North" and above all
in the "South", where the need is greatest.
For those of us engaged in the activities of
ILY at all levelslocal, national or international
the pages of the calendar are turning with startling
rapidity. Over half of the year is already gone.
We realize that what matters is not so much what
happens in 1990, but what will happen in the
years that follow as a consequence of ILY. We
want ILY to be a summons to action. The world
cannot be made literate in only 365 days, but a
year is a sufficient period of time to make a com¬
mitment and a beginning. That is our goal. We
hope that ILY will be remembered as a sort of
"year of the ox", a year that, perhaps in awkward
and plodding ways, got things moving. A year
which demonstrated that vanquishing illiteracy
is an enormous task, but no longer an impossible
dream. A year that will be looked back upon as
a season of promising beginnings and renewed
commitments.
> rv h>nn'rl nn
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
1
World literacy:
where we stand today
A,T least 960 million people in the world today
are "total" illiterates. According to the definition
established by Unesco thirty years ago, a total il¬
literate is someone who "is unable to read, write
and understand a brief and simple exposé of facts
in relation to his or her daily life". There is also
a considerable number of so-called "functional"
illiterates, for whom reading and writing are not
part of their daily lives, even though at some
period, usually on leaving school, they have been
able to read and write. If the functionally illiterate
adults in the industrialized countriesestimated
by some at between 10 and 20 per cent of their
populationswere to be counted in with the
totally illiterate, the world figure for illiteracy
would exceed one billion adults, the majority of
whom would be women.
The highest concentrations of the totally il¬
literate are to be found in the densely populated
areas of the globe, notably in Asia, where they
number some 700 million (490 million of them
in China and India alone), and in Africa where,
By Sylvain Lourié
The struggle
against illiteracy
can only be
effective as
part of a wider
strategy to
eradicate
poverty,
exclusion and
injustice
in 1985, 54 per cent of the population consisted
of illiterates, of whom 65 per cent were women.
As far as functional literacy is concerned, a
recent (1986) study showed that one adult out of
eight in the United States could not read and that
in the United Kingdom, of a sampling of twenty-
three-year-olds, 13 per cent had difficulty in read¬
ing, writing and counting. Similar figures were
obtained in Canada, France and other industri¬
alized countries.
These figures, however, are but snapshots or
stills from a film which, as it unfolds, enables us
to detect trends and assess the efforts made by
some governments in the fight against illiteracy.
At the end of the Second World War, 75.4 per
cent of the population of Albania, for example,
was illiterate; ten years later this proportion had
been reduced to under 30 per cent. In 1962, 90
per cent of the population of the United Repub¬
lic of Tanzania was illiterate; by 1978 the figure
was down to 53.7 per cent. In 1970, there were
more than ten million illiterates aged over ten in 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Ethiopia; by 1983 this figure had been halved. In
Latin America, Mexico went from an illiteracy
rate of 77.7 per cent in 1900 to one of 9.7 per
cent in 1985. In Cuba, the rate fell in a few
months from 23.6 per cent to 3.9 per cent. In
1984, Nicaragua also succeeded in reducing its rate
from 50 per cent to about 13 per cent in just a
few months.
Some countries, unfortunately, are far from
having achieved such good results. Burkina Faso
and Mali, for example, have illiteracy rates that
exceed 90 per cent. In Afghanistan, Benin, Guinea
Bissau, Liberia and Togo, the rate is over 80 per
cent. In India the rate in 1981 was 67.3 per cent,
that is, more than 200 million people, of whom
120 million were women. In 1982, China had 230
million illiterates (34.5 per cent of the popula¬
tion), of whom 160 million were women.
Illiteracy
and poverty
A glance at some statistics other than those for
illiteracy reveals that one billion human beings
live below the poverty line, that one and a half
billion people lack medical facilities, that one
billion people live in insanitary conditions.
The parallel with the billion total and func¬
tional illiterates speaks for itself; it is difficult not
to recognize that the map of world illiteracy
coincides with that of world poverty. This shock¬
ing fact applies primarily to the developing coun¬
tries, but the odds are that the functional illiter¬
ates in the industrialized countries will almost
always be found among the unemployed and those
who have been left behind by the mainstream of
the economy and of modern technology.
Clearly, then, any discussion of illiteracy will
be merely academic unless it is placed within a
wider social context than that of teaching
methods and of learning to read and count. Il¬
literacy, it must be repeated, is but one form of
marginalization or exclusion. Society has become
polarized into those who have the means to im¬
prove their material and social standing and those
CONTINUED PAGE 18
Reports from
around
WJ the world
Right, a school in
Guatemala; centre, a Burkina
Faso schoolgirl; far right,
outside a post office in
Karachi (Pakistan), a typist
performs an essential service
for those who cannot write
or who need a typed letter.
Left, The Columns of Liberty
(1989), a monumental
sculpture created by 700
pupils of 17 different
nationalities at the Pablo
Neruda secondary school,
Grigny, France.
LATIN AMERICA
Illiteracy,
democracy and
development
.Tor Latin America, the last decade of the
twentieth century is opening against an economic,
social and political background that is complex
and uncertain.
The consequences of this cannot be avoided
in education, where rapid expansion slowed con¬
siderably between 1980 and 1990 and is now
threatening to grind to a halt.
The situation is reflected in the figures for
total illiteracy and for failure at school. The eradi¬
cation of total illiteracy is proving to be exces¬
sively slow. Although Latin America has managed
to reduce the percentage and even the total num¬
ber of illiterate persons, at current rates there will
still be some 38 million of them in the year 2000.
There is clearly a close connection between
illiteracy, poverty, unemployment and under¬
employment, and the fact of living in a rural area
or of belonging to an indigenous ethnic group.
Experience has shown that the struggle against
illiteracy can only pay dividends if it is accompa¬
nied by improvements in health, housing and
employment.
Total illiteracy is also the result of a discri¬
minatory education system. Many South American
children think of their schooldays primarily as a
time of failure. Recent studies indicate that around
30 per cent of pupils repeat a grade in the early
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
years of primary school. Most of those affected
are rural, indigenous or urban slum children
from the poorest familiesthose whose lives are
furthest removed from the cultural model
dominant in school.
A notable feature of Latin American educa¬
tion systems is the marked polarization of school-
age children. On the one hand there is a sizeable
percentage of children who are totally excluded,
and on the other, a relatively large number of
young people who go on to higher education. If
this polarization continues, it will be impossible
to achieve national integration, to strengthen
democracy and to create the conditions for sus¬
tained economic growth.
Simultaneous action is needed at both ends
of the education system: at the primary level to
put a stop to exclusion, and at the higher level
to train researchers and technicians in order to
build up the stock of indigenous creativity which
will bring back economic growth and lead the way
out of the current stagnation.
JUAN CARLOS TEDESCO
AFRICA
Disturbing
trends
In the early 1980s, sub-Saharan Africa had a
much higher rate of illiteracy and a much lower
rate of school enrolment than other regions,
increasing faster than their GNP fell from 20 in
1975-1980 to 12 in the years that followed.
According to Unesco figures, there may be
some 168 million illiterates aged 15 and over in
Africa in 1990, 1C5 million of them women. These
figures doubtless underestimate the true situation
insofar as they are based on rather unreliable
official statistics. In some cases, on the other hand,
they do not take into account those who are literate
in languages other than the official language of
the country.
It is true that in the long run only the provi¬
sion of primary education for all will make it pos¬
sible to attack the problem of illiteracy at its
source. But given the conditions of underdeve¬
lopment in many African countries, further
aggravated by the economic crisis, the implemen¬
tation of universal education is not feasible in the
immediate future, especially in those countries
where there are no places for at least half the chil¬
dren of school age. All these children, together
with the victims of inappropriate education
systems, are condemned to swell the ranks of the
illiterate. In addition to the demographic causes
of the problem there are otherssocial, economic
and political.
Illiteracy can only be vanquished if its global
nature is recognized and policies are adopted to
enrich the human capital of African countries.
Decision-makers must realize that investment in
education and public health brings a high eco¬
nomic return. BABA HAIDARA
ASIA AND THE PACIFIC
lit i XÀ S
although for several decades African governments
had been making a big effort to eliminate illiteracy
among young people and adults. The illiteracy
rate of those over the age of 15 fell from around
75 per cent in 1970 to 64 per cent in 1980 and 57
per cent in 1985.
Unfortunately, this fall was accompanied by
an increase in the number of total illiterates
resulting from rampant demographic growth and
the ineffectiveness of education systemsdespite
the fact that a large part of the region's GNP was
being used to finance them. Since then, certain
negative trends have worsened. The number of
African countries whose education budget was
JUAN CARLOS TEDESCO
is Director of Unesco's Regional Office for
Education in Latin America and the Caribbean,
Santiago de Chile.
BABA HAIDARA
is Director of Unesco's Regional Office for
Education in Africa, Dakar.
SHOZO JIZAWA
is a specialist in human sciences at the University
of Tokyo.
LESLIE LIMAGE
is a member of Unesco's International Literacy Year
Secretariat.
Responding
to the challenge
1 he effort required to carry out mass literacy
campaigns, to provide the necessary post-literacy
work, and to make primary education available
to all, still represents an enormous challenge to
the countries of Asia and the Pacific.
It is true that the literacy rate in the region
rose from 39.6 per cent in 1960 to 60.4 per cent
in 1980 and that during the same period the num¬
ber of literate adults increased from 393 million
to 953 million. It is estimated that the figure for
1990 is 1,377 million, and that it may rise to 1,888
million by the year 2000. But the picture is not
as bright as it may seem. The total number of
illiterates rose from 600 million in 1960 to 628
million in 1980. If this trend continues, the figure
will persist into the early 1990s and will then fall
slightly to 562 million in the year 2000.
In 1990 most of the countries in the region
will, admittedly, have achieved 70 per cent
literacvthe crucial point beyond which it seems
to be proven that the literacy process is self-
perpetuating until illiteracy is virtually eradicated.
Fiji, Malaysia, Viet Nam and the Philippines
are among the eastern and south-eastern Asian
countries which in 1990 should achieve a literacy
rate of 80 per cent, while the Maldives, Mongolia,
Sri Lanka and Thailand will have passed the 90
per cent mark. Four out of five Indonesians and
three out of four Chinese and Turks will also be
literate in 1990.
Nonetheless there will still be 200 million
illiterate persons in China, 23 million in Indonesia
and 8.7 million in Turkey. The problem is more
acute in central and southern Asia: in 1990, the
literacy rate will probably exceed 50 per cent in
India and in Papua New Guinea, and 60 per cent
in Iran, but Bangladesh and Pakistan will achieve
a maximum of 40 per cent, and Bhutan, Nepal
and Afghanistan will not exceed 30 per cent.
The problem of illiteracy in Asia and the
Pacific is also notable for a "gender gap". While the
number of male illiterates fell from 247 million
in 1970 to 233 million in 1985, the number of
female illiterates increased during the same period
from 390 million to 418 million.
To attain the objective of universal literacy by
the year 2000, the countries of Asia and the Pacific
will have to educate 62 million adults (15 years
and over) each year. Aware of the immensity of
the task facing them, these countries launched a
Unesco-coordinated Asia-Pacific Programme of
Education for All (APPEAL) in 1987. The pro¬
gramme concentrates notably on the introduction
of new teaching methods in order to respond to
the basic needs of marginalized rural and urban
populations, women, minorities and the under¬
privileged. SHOZO JIZAWA 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
REPORTS FROM AROUND THE WORLD
The industrialized countries:
questions and answers
By Leslie Limage
1. What does "literacy" mean?
The search for a precise definition of "literacy"
V¿~^ is especially troubling to those who seek a quick
solution to the problem of illiteracy in industri¬
alized countries. Unfortunately, no simple defi¬
nition will do. The meaning of literacy can only
be defined in a specific context and will evolve
as societal and individual needs change. Unesco's
literacy statistics are based on official census data
provided by governments whose national defini¬
tions vary. As such, they must be used with
caution. They are adequate to indicate broad
trends, but a dangerous basis for making precise
comparisons.
"Illiteracy" is also a relative term. The ability
to sign one's name and read simple messages once
constituted all the skills an adult required to be
considered literate. Today, "illiteracy" is variously
defined to range from a total inability to use the
written word to an insufficient mastery of a set
of sophisticated skills. In some industrialized
countries, the terms "computer literacy" and
"cultural literacy" have even come to be used.
In short, literacy skills which are considered satis¬
factory in one context may be seriously insuffi¬
cient in another.
2. What do we know about the extent of
illiteracy?
Since there is a whole range of definitions of
what constitutes literacy in industrialized coun¬
tries, it is not surprising that estimates of the
extent of illiteracy in individual countries vary
and indeed are often contradictory. Figures in the
United States range from 5 per cent to 25 per cent
of the total population. A recent Canadian study
shows some 25 per cent of the adult population
has seriously inadequate literacy skills. In France,
estimates have varied from 2 million to 8 million
illiterates.
3. Illiterate? After 100 years of universal
primary education?
Schools usually work in the dominant lan¬
guages of a society, but many of their students
may speak minority languages at home or come ^
from diverse cultural backgrounds. Thus, equal ¡J
treatment will produce very unequal outcomes.
One child is ready to master a particular learning
task, but another needs remedial work before
doing so. Yet, in some countries, the only form
of remediation is grade repetition: another dose
of what failed the first time.
In recent years, as social expenditures have
been reduced in many industrialized countries,
education budgets have been hard hit. The first
cuts occur in school provisions which are con¬
sidered marginal: compensatory programmes and
remedial tuition. Reduction in educational spend¬
ing also leads to larger classes, fewer materials and
lower teacher morale. A child from a home
which cannot compensate for what is lacking in
school will inevitably fall behind. These young
people do not "relapse" into illiteracy. They
never possessed self-sustaining skills.
4. How did industrialized countries "redis- ¡L
cover" illiteracy?
The economic crisis which began in the early
1970s is largely responsible for the "rediscovery"
of illiteracy in industrialized countries. As tradi¬
tional and low-skill employment was progress¬
ively reduced, it became necessary to retrain large
numbers of young people for employment in
emerging industries. Job training programmes
were established for this purpose, but it was soon
discovered that lack of basic skills, literacy and
numeracy, greatly complicated such training. The
illiterate who previously had been gainfully em¬
ployed suddenly was made visible and defined as
a problem by the dislocations of the economy.
5. What is being done to prevent underachieve-
ment and failure in schools?
In many countries, the measures essential to
prevent underachievement and failure in schools
are under attack. Many countries, facing severe
budget cuts, are turning to the private and volun¬
tary sectors for help. Small-scale projects which
receive much publicity are often taking the place
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
i
Xf
; '
of a long-term public commitment. Literacy is
everybody's business, but private efforts can only ti
complement, not replace, public provision.
6. What is being done to provide adults with
basic skills in literacy and numeracy?
Adult basic skill provision takes place in a wide JÇf
variety of settings. Community colleges and adult
education institutes provide the bulk of tuition
in certain countries. A much smaller but increas¬
ingly important level of provision is offered
by voluntary bodies and charities in a growing
number of states. Slowly, work-place literacy
classes are being developed, especially in commer¬
cial and industrial firms. Community groups are
defining their own needs and setting up appropri¬
ate tuition. Yet with all the various types of pro¬
vision available, not more than 10 per cent of
adults with literacy needs are receiving some form
of tuition.
7. Who is responsible?
A fully literate society is everyone's responsi¬
bility. Community efforts to help pre-school chil¬
dren to enjoy reading are important. Schools
should be endowed with sufficient public
resources to ensure that each child is able
to achieve a minimum proficiency in the use of
the written word. Efforts in schools should be
flexible and varied so that all children, regardless
of home background, find learning enjoyable.
Once a firm commitment from the public sector
is guaranteed, coalitions with business, the volun¬
tary sector, community groups, libraries and the
media should be encouraged. Industrialized coun¬
tries can afford to ensure literacy and numeracy
for all. Indeed, they cannot afford to do otherwise.
8. What can people do to help?
Everyone has a role to play in bringing about
a literate society. Senior citizens are needed to
help the very young, especially when parents are
disadvantaged or heavily burdened with earning
a living for the family unit. Intergenerational liter¬
acy efforts, teaching mothers and children
together, are also important.
...
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 14
18
who are unable to secure for themselves a mini¬
mum standard of well-being. It is in the latter
group that illiterates, who have neither access to
existing sources of knowledge nor the ability to
create new knowledge, are to be found.
Very often, therefore, those whose standard
of living is extremely low are also those who can¬
not communicate with people living only a few
kilometres away simply because they speak differ¬
ent languages or dialects and have no common
system of writing by means of which to exchange
information.
This poverty and this cultural isolation are
accompanied by isolation with regard to what
might be termed the "mechanics" of social life.
The ability to communicate is not only a form
of cultural expression, it is also an essential ele¬
ment in the organization of society, promoting
the association of people with common aims and
the structuring of the community. These are com¬
plementary elements necessary to the creation
and strengthening of the modern social fabric.
Schools of illiteracy
Who are these illiterates? And why do they re¬
main illiterate? They are adults who have not had
access to education, or young adults who have
been unable to complete their schooling or train¬
ing and who live in a milieu to which writing
is alien and thus, after a few years, relapse into
illiteracy.
Does this mean that, in a country where the
illiteracy rate is high but where the rate of school
enrolment is rising rapidly, illiteracy will gradu¬
ally disappear as new groups of children who
have passed through the school system reach
adulthood? Unfortunately, the data available at
present tend generally to record only the num¬
bers enrolling in schools and give no indication
of how long the entrants stay there. The num¬
ber of children enrolled is not the same as the
number of those who remain in school long
enough (a minimum of four years) to attain a rela¬
tively "irreversible" level of literacy.
In recent years there seems also to have been
a tendency for the rate of school enrolment itself
to drop. Many parents no longer see the school
as a means of finding employment and achieving
better living conditions. The economic crisis, in
particular the growing burden of debt, which has
been reflected over the past decade in a reduction
in public expenditureparticularly in expenditure
on social services and educationhas led almost
everywhere to the freezing of teachers' salaries,
with obvious results. The teachers are obliged to
take on other jobs and the time they spend in the
classroom is proportionately reduced. With most
of the education budget devoted to the payment
of salaries, what is left for the purchase of essential
teaching materialstextbooks, exercise books,
pencilsand for the maintenance of school build¬
ings has been pared to the bone. Contact between
teachers and pupils has become less regular and
of lower quality and instead of being a source of
stimulation for the children's creative capabilities,
teaching has been reduced to routine parrotting
of words and numbers. Teaching has lost all its
real meaning.
It is to be feared that if present trends con¬
tinue, far from reducing illiteracy, the school sys¬
tem will in fact be contributing to its increase.
Literacy training
is a political act
In these conditions, it is impossible to consider
the drive for literacy apart from the political con¬
text that has engendered ignorance. I am not
thinking of literacy education as only teaching
people to read, but as a form of basic training
making possible, in the words of the declaration
made by the International Council for Adult Edu¬
cation at Toronto (Canada), in 1987, "the acqui¬
sition of the sum of knowledge necessary" for
the improvement of the living and working con¬
ditions of adults. Literacy campaigns must be
accompanied by change in other areas of society.
This was clearly stated during a symposium
organized by Unesco at Persepolis (Iran) in 1975:
"Literacy work, like education in general, is a
political act. It is not neutral, for the act of
revealing social reality in order to transform it, or
of concealing it in order to preserve it, is political."
A study carried out within the framework of
In 1987 a group of 15
children and 5 teachers
from Evry, France, helped
rebuild the Issa Arame Seek
school at Bargny, Senegal.
iff* *t\
SYLVAIN LOURIE
is Unesco's Deputy Director-
General for Planning,
Budgeting and Evaluation. A
Unesco staff member since
1965, he was Director of the
International Institute of
Educational Planning from
1982 to 1988. He is the
author of Education and
Development: Strategy and
Decision-making in Central
America (1985) and many
studies and articles on aspects
of educational strategy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
ULJl "
International Literacy Year draws the following
conclusions from experience acquired in this field:
"National commitment and political priority for
literacy have been crucial for attaining such posi¬
tive results. Above all, the successful literacy
programmes have been part of a wider process
of mobilization among the people. The successes
achieved have not primarily been a question of
the number of books printed, rural libraries in
operation or vehicles supplied. Although these
components certainly are required for a literacy
programme, they can never substitute for or
inspire mobilization of the people, nor determine
the programme contents or the implementation
approach."*
Only if the entire social, cultural and political
environment is favourably disposed is it possible
to pass from words to action and to encourage
those at whom a literacy campaign is directed
actually to learn to write.
There are many governments whose desire
to reduce illiteracy is virtually nullified because
other priorities (defence, the creation of infra¬
structures, the purchase of manufactured goods,
debt repayment) leave them with insufficient
resources.
Other countries" see their efforts come to
nothing because they have been unable to make
a decision on the language on which a literacy
campaign should be based, or because the cam¬
paign comes up against the passive resistance of
certain sections of the population or even of the
civil service itself.
On the other hand, when there is free circu¬
lation of information within a society, when the
members of the community communicate and
are in a position to participate and to act in the
general interest, literacy teaching plays an effec¬
tive role in general development policy as a sup¬
port for changes in customs and structures that
go far beyond the education of young people and
adults. After all, what is the point of teaching peo¬
ple to read and write if there is no follow-up, no
post-literacy training and no social change which
would enable a person who has learned to read
and write to obtain a loan, for example, to join
a co-operative or to continue his or her studies
within the framework of a lifelong education
programme?
Adult illiterates (age 15 and over) and illiteracy rates
Adult illiterates
(in millions)
Illiteracy rates
(%)
Developing countries in:
Sub-Saharan Africa 133 6 138 8
Arab States 58 6 61 1
Latin America / Caribbean 44 2 43 5
Eastern Asia 297 3 281 0
Southern Asia 374 1 397 3
2000
146 8
65 8
40 9
233 7
437 0
Developing countries (total) 908.1 920.6 918 5
59 1
54 5
176
28 7
57 7
39.4
1990
52 7
48 7
152
24 0
53 8
35.1
40 3
38 1
11 3
170
45 9
28.1
Developed countries (total) 57.0 42.0 23.5
World total 962.6 942.0 26.9
Decrease
1985-2000
188
164
-63
11 7
11 8
11.3
-3.9
-7.9
Unesco's two-pronged strategy
If literacy education is seen as one of the neces¬
sary instruments of emancipation, mobilization,
higher productivity and the satisfaction of in¬
dividual needs, then the whole arsenal of tried and
tested methods and techniques can at last be
brought into play. In this way, step by step, us¬
ing the two-pronged strategy that Unesco has
been propounding for many years, of providing
* International Co-operation in Literacy Training: two good
examples, by Agneta Lind, of the Swedish International
Development Authority (SIDA), and Mark Foss, of the
Canadian Organization for Education and Development. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
effective schooling for children and literacy train¬
ing for adults, spectacular results can be achieved.
As far as adults are concerned, there is not a
single illiterate peasant-farmer who is incapable
of dividing his land among his sons, assessing with
almost scientific accuracy and care the number
of trees, the richness of the soil, its slope, irriga¬
tion and surface area. There is no illiterate who
cannot convey his deepest thoughts verbally.
There is no illiterate who has not learned from his
ancestors and passed on their teachings to his own
children, who, whether literate or not, consider
this heritage to be their most precious possession.
Any literacy teaching strategy or technique must,
therefore, take as its starting point the existing
knowledge of the person to whom this new code
of communication is to be imparted. Only by
gaining an understanding of how illiterate persons
i :
20
communicate and calculate will it be possible to
bring them gradually to understand the new
coding system, which will enable them signifi¬
cantly to widen their range of activities.
Similarly, school systems should fully recog¬
nize that the transmission of factual knowledge
is much less important than the inculcation of
learning skills, and that this goal can be reached
by a wide variety of paths depending upon the
individual, his or her age and social and cultural
condition. Only then will schools cease to be
simply marshalling yards in which all those who
cannot follow the main line route of memoriza¬
tion, deduction and theory are shunted off on
to secondary tracks and dead end sidings. They
will begin to become more empirical in their
approach, to appreciate gestural and artistic qual¬
ities, and to recognize that aptitudes are not all
acquired at the same time and that each individual
follows a pathway that corresponds to his or her
talents, tastes and aspirations. Only when the way
in which each pupil receives information and
Children in Cuzco,
Peru, take part in a
demonstration calling for
the reopening of their
school.
Top, for an immigrant,
illiteracy is but one form
of exclusion.
transforms this into knowledge is seen as being
much more important than the actual nature' of
1 the information imparted to him or her shall we
be able to speak with justification of an improve¬
ment in the quality of teaching.
For literacy to become rooted in the individu¬
al's experience and for education to become the
reflection of each individual's qualities, agents
other than teacherswhose role will always be
decisive, but not exclusivewill have to be
brought into play. Communities and the fami¬
lies involved will become the new "partners" in
an enterprise whose goal must not be access to
the educational system so much as the success of
the educational process.
A huge amount of experience has been ac¬
cumulated and many specialists are now available
who could train teachers, help in the preparation
of teaching materials and assess the motivation and
knowledge of pupils. Thanks to its educational
networks and the experience it has acquired over
the past forty years, Unesco, for its part, is well
placed to promote the exchange of information
and personnel and to contribute to progress in
this field.
Governments may favour strategies based on
literacy campaigns carried out over several years
or on the gradual improvement of the quality of
basic education for children and young people.
Alternatively, they may prefer to adopt a policy
of promoting intensive literacy campaigns involv¬
ing the nation-wide mobilization of resources and
the media or, for example, calling on secondary
level pupils to act as teachers in literacy cam¬
paigns. Such programmes, however, will only
succeed if they are accompanied by a whole range
of measures relating to public health, housing and
to import/export policies.
Undertaken in isolation, literacy campaigns
or educational reforms will remain ineffective.
Only if they become an integral part of an overall
movement of reform and change will they bring
to fruition the hopes expressed in the United
Nations resolution which designated 1990 as In¬
ternational Literacy Year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The mind transformed
By Raja Roy-Singh
A,DULT illiterates were long regarded as people
who were suffering from a kind of disease from
which they could be cured by learning to read
and write. They were thought to be devoid of
higher order cognitive characteristics and to lack
the capacity for abstraction, reasoning and sym-
bolization. Shackled to their immediate ex¬
perience, they had no conception of past or
future. They were mentally tabula rasa and some¬
what childish. The acquisition of literacy was a
leap across the great divide from the "illiterate
mentality" to the "literate mentality".
These myths have been extremely potent.
They helped to create a psychological climate in
which society is seen as divided into a dominant
class and a subservient mass. This attitude,
whether implicit or openly held, gave rise to
methods of teaching literacy in which adult il¬
literates are seen as passive objects to be salvaged
by the literacy process, in which they need not
intervene until they have mastered the salvation-
ary words in the right way and at the right time.
This "salvationary" literacy practice is almost ex¬
clusively based on the technical drills of reading
Once regarded
as the
inculcation
of mechanical
skills, literacy
work with
adults is
increasingly
seen as an
educational
process based
on dialogue
Above, a Tibetan storyteller
at Bodh Gaya, India.
Many adult illiterates have
a rich oral cultural heritage
which shapes their
perception of the world.
and writing and often uses the same methods and
texts which are used for children in their early
grades at school.
It is often forgotten that many illiterate adults
have an oral cultural heritage which is profoundly
important to them and that the ways in which
their oral traditions are stored, renewed and trans¬
mitted have shaped their perceptions and the lan¬
guages in which they think. Furthermore, in
most of the societies to which they belong, liter¬
acy is not new. In some cases it has formed part
of creative and religious life for centuries.
These adults have acquired an array of educa¬
tional experiences, competences and values in
their families, in social groups, in places of work
and entertainment, and in acts of worship. They
have had to learn lessons relating to community
life and understand the values and rules associat¬
ed with their occupations. All these experiences
give meaning to their lives and all of them involve
uninterrupted language learning. Literacy work
that does not recognize these facts and sets out
to teach adults to read and write by rendering
them meaningless to themselves is an exercise in 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
sterility and serves the economic and social forces
that marginalize people and deprive them of their
voice.
Literacy is only authentic if it adds meaning
to people's lives and helps them to understand
real-life problems. If there is no link between liter¬
acy practice and the situation of the learners,
there will be indifference, resistance and rejection.
Literacy as a dynamic
process
Radically new ideas and perspectives on literacy
have been developed in recent decades. Literacy
is no longer viewed as a simple concept bound
up with the coding and decoding of signs in
which the main problems are technical. The liter¬
acy process is no longer conceived of as a train¬
ing process which concentrates exclusively on
"implanting" specific mechanical skills; it is now
recognized as an educational process, as an un¬
folding of human potential.
The exponents of these new approaches do
not use the same terminology and emphasize
different aspects of the literacy process but they
have certain points in common. Firstly, they
recognize that adult learners have a central role
in the process and should be active in defining
their learning needs and the goals which they
serve. Secondly, they regard learning as a continu¬
ous, integral and deepening process of critical
awareness of the self within and the world
without. Thirdly, they see diversity and not
uniformity or homogeneity as the true charac¬
teristic of literacy action. Fourthly, this "dynamic
literacy process" finds its full expression in en¬
gaging and participating in authentic social change
and developments. As the Brazilian sociologist
and educator Paulo Freiré has said, "The literacy
process must relate speaking the word to trans¬
forming reality and to man's role in the
transformation."
The common schema which breaks down the
literacy process into stagespre-literacy, learning
to read and write, post-literacydistorts under¬
standing of the process.
mamé-*
\ t¿5 txBuenc* c**P&
Below, members of the
Unidad de Bibliotecas
Rurales, a network of
libraries serving 465 rural
communities in the
Cajamarca region of
northern Peru. Using
information provided by the
communities, the librarians
are producing a Cajamarcan
encyclopaedia in 20
volumes. Right, covers from
5 of the 6 books already
published. Support for the
project is provided by
Traditions for Tomorrow, a
non-governmental
organization founded in
1986 to help Third World
communities trying to
safeguard their cultural
identity.
muestras
tttSffS"
22
RAJA ROY-SINGH,
of India, is a former
educational adviser in the
Indian Federal Ministry of
Education. He Joined Unesco
in 1964 and was based in
Bangkok where until his
retirement he was closely
involved in international co¬
operation for the promotion
of education in Asia and the
Pacific. This article has been
adapted from a booklet
which forms part of a series
entitled Literacy Lessons,
produced by the
International Bureau of
Education on the occasion of
International Literacy Year
(see page 50).
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Literacy proceeds from the learner, and the
impetus for it has its origin in a diversity of
sources in which the situations of the learners
have a profound influence. In the ultimate anal¬
ysis, the "literacy need" arises m the individual
or social group with a realization, however inar¬
ticulate, of a sense of disharmony or incomplete¬
ness in its particular social "universe" of relations,
meanings and interpretations. As the individual
or group becomes consciously aware of the dis¬
harmony of its own closed "universe", the liter¬
acy process as a reaching out to new meanings
and interpretations begins, transforming the in¬
dividual/group into learners.
The role of dialogue
Learning to read and write is not an isolated act,
nor is its goal only the acquisition of certain cod¬
ing and decoding skills. Indeed, it is a relatively
easy task for an adult to "alphabetize" himself
if he sees a worthwhile purpose to it. It is part
of a larger human process in which perceiving,
knowing, reflection and action are interwoven.
Not least, it is an act that transforms the learner
in the very process by which the learner becomes
aware of the need and possibilities of change.
Along the path from the first stirring of a sense
of disharmony to a state of self-appraising com¬
prehension, the learner becomes aware of the
"necessity" to learn to read and write and thus
to enter a wider field of participation and sharing.
The prime method in the dynamic literacy
process is that of dialogue. Whether it is used in
identifying the generative themes or in heighten¬
ing awareness or in developing instructional texts
and methods, dialogue defines the relationship be¬
tween the learners and the teachers, between
them both and the realm of knowledge, and be¬
tween the oral and written means of communi¬
cation. One of the creative insights of profound
significance that dynamic literacy practice has
contributed to the general education process is the
restoration of dialogue to a central role in educa¬
tion. The mediation of the dialogue process
establishes between learners and educators a rela¬
tionship of equality. It encourages the learners to
raise questions and unmask problems relating to
significant aspects of their lives.
Literacy action proceeds from, builds on and
comes to fruition in a deepening human aware¬
ness, what in Freirían terms is known as conscien-
tization. Its best expression is an accompanying
sense of growing autonomy and freedom.
Literacy action which proceeds from the
learner is inconceivable in any but a decentral¬
ized way. This means a decentralized develop¬
ment structure capable of responding to the
diversity of needs at the local level and, most im¬
portant, capable of creating the mechanisms at
the local level through which the literacy process
is sustained. 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Most of
the world's
illiterates are
women. What
can be done to
break down
the barriers to
literacy faced by
women,
especially in the
poorest
countries?
The gender
gap By Agneta Lind
RI OT long ago a group of newly literate women
from the south coast of Kenya were explaining
the advantages of their recently acquired skills in
reading, writing and calculation. Now they could
sign their names they had more control over
money transactions. They could read medical
prescriptions and instructions. "Our eyes have
been opened," said one of them, expressing the
new sense of pride and increased self-reliance they
all felt.
The preliminary findings from a question¬
naire sent out in September 1988 by World
YWCA to its member associations confirm such
liberating effects of literacy. The responses show
that:
Women who receive literacy training are more
respected in the community and at home.
é '
They are better equipped to search for jobs and
can therefore earn more.
They realize that they can do some jobs which
are traditionally considered to be for men only.
They are more able to run small businesses and
keep records on their own.
They become more effective leaders of women's "
groups.
Their political awareness, participation and
organizational skills are enhanced.
They gain better understanding of their rights.
They are much more capable of helping their
children with their schoolwork.
There are many human, social and econom¬
ic reasons why literacy education for women and
girls should be a priority objective. For many
women, achieving literacy could be one of the
first steps in a process enabling them to take con¬
trol over their lives, to participate on a more
equal basis in society, and eventually to free them¬
selves from economic exploitation and patriarchal
oppression. The sole fact that mothers' level of
education has a positive effect on their children's
health and progress in school should be a strong
enough argument.
The figures show that the gap in literacy rates
between men and women is constantly widening.
Moreover, it seems likely that this "gender gap"
will become even wider as economic constraints
lead to increased demands on women's unskilled
work and push literacy lower down the scale of
priorities of people and governments.
Illiteracy among women and men in Third
World countries is linked to poverty, inequalities
and oppression. The education system introduced
by colonial powers sometimes tended to accen¬
tuate various forms of. discrimination, and the
consequent inequities in access to school account
for most adult illiteracy in Third World countries
today. The traditional division of family and
social roles between the sexes also prevented most
girls from achieving literacy through schooling,
and even when girls were enrolled in schools,
Left, overburdened with
domestic tasks, relatively
few illiterate women
manage to achieve literacy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
t&toc*»*k
educational practices often reinforced their subor¬
dination. Although the open discrimination prac¬
tised during colonial days may be less common
today, patriarchal ideologies and social systems
that disfavour women have persisted.
Yet in many Third World countries, many
women do participate in literacy classes, especially
among the rural population. One reason for this
is that they tend to see literacy as a way of helping
them to cope with responsibilities that were
previously monopolized by their menfolk who
have migrated to the towns in search of work. If
they are literate they can also read their husbands'
letters and write back without having to call in
other people.
Obstacles to learning
But although there are many reasons why women
should want to participate in literacy classes, their
traditional and new occupations do not leave
them much time for regular attendance and effi¬
cient learning. They tend to be overburdened
with domestic tasks such as cooking and cleaning,
fetching water and firewood, as well as farming
and earning money. Frequent child-bearing leaves
little time and energy for learning how to read
and write. Even when mothers do attend classes
they often bring their smallest children. Concen¬
tration is obviously difficult when babies and
toddlers have to be looked after during the lessons.
Only rarely are child-care provisions made
for women during class time, although in some
countries they have been offered literacy courses
in boarding centres, away from competing de¬
mands and duties. Nonetheless, other problems
have arisen such as poorly qualified tutors, short¬
ages of food, uncomfortable living conditions,
and insufficient programme time.
Women are, moreover, directly discouraged
by the attitudes of men, often including male
teachers, to their capacities in the classroom. Hus¬
bands and guardians sometimes even forbid them
to attend literacy classes. The men are afraid that
women who learn more than they do may expose
their ignorance and, above all, challenge their
power position within the family.
Even where women and girls do manage to
acquire elementary literacy skills, it is often more
difficult for them than for men to sustain these
Above, a Togolese woman
makes soap during a literacy
class.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
skills. The reading material at their disposal is
often not designed for their interests and needs,
and in any case they often have less access to it
and less time for reading. The support and mobili¬
zation which take some women and girls through
to literacy tend to dwindle when they become
literate.
One response to these difficulties is to
integrate literacy courses for women into
programmes related to health care, family plan¬
ning, nutrition and income-generation. In prac¬
tice, however, this approach often leads to a
26
neglect of literacy instruction, since the women
are expected to be involved in so many other
activities at the same time.
Women and mass literacy campaigns
The general experience of adult literacy pro¬
grammes, whether organized on a large scale by
the state or on a small scale by non-governmental
organizations, is that without various forms of
mobilizationawakening or creating motivation
the response is weak.
Only national mass literacy campaigns have
successfully managed to mobilize and teach
hundreds of thousands of illiterate women and
men elementary literacy skills. Such campaigns
have taken place in countries where literacy was
part of a national policy for overcoming poverty
and injustice, where both the state and the people
concerned expected literacy to be one of many
factors which would improve social, political and
economic conditions and help develop human
and material resources.
In most of these campaigns the teaching
Peruvian women learning
letters and sounds. This
photo features in a
travelling exhibition
organized by Unesco for
International Literacy Year
(see page 50).
AGNETA LIND
is a staff member of the
education division of the
Swedish International
Development Authority,
Stockholm, and a specialist on
education in Third World
countries. This article has
been adapted from a booklet
which forms part of a series
entitled Literacy Lessons,
produced by the International
Bureau of Education on the
occasion of International
Literacy Year (see page 50).
methods have been traditional, but the contents
have focused on national issues and have includ¬
ed themes stressing equal rights and the need for
women's emancipation and equal participation in
all spheres of society.
In national mass literacy campaigns, as well
as more local campaigns, the degree of women's
participation in particular has depended on com¬
munity attitudes. While a superior and patroniz¬
ing attitude among literacy organizers and
teachers discourages interest, a democratic, open
and involved attitude, treating the learners as
equal adults, and creating an atmosphere of con¬
fidence, has a positive influence on attendance and
results. Local women teachers working with
separate women's literacy groups are often suc¬
cessful in encouraging learning and participation.
The active involvement of local leaders in
favour of literacy activities has often been cru¬
cial for the achievement of high levels of partici¬
pation and learning. In 1971, for example, when
the first drive of the Tanzanian literacy campaign
reached the island of Mafia, the local leaders in¬
sisted that men and women were to participate.
Separate classes for men and women were or¬
ganized. Mobilizing visits by national leaders
were followed up by the appointment of an Area
Commissioner who was a committed adult edu¬
cator himself.
The reason why this support was so impor¬
tant was explained by one woman who was asked
what her husband thought about her participation
in literacy classes. "Yes, he grumbles a bit, as men
do," she said. "Some men are very worried, and
they don't let their wives attend classes. But it's
too late, I think. When the Area Commissioner
held a meeting here both men and women were
asked to come. We didn't dare, in the beginning.
But the cell leader had brought his wife, and she
came back to fetch us. The Area Commissioner
had complained that so few women were present
and said that he would not start the meeting until
everyone had met up. These classes have meant
a lot to us."
Illiterate women often want to become liter¬
ate, but relatively few manage to satisfy this wish.
The constraintstime-consuming duties, short¬
comings in the design of the literacy programmes
^offered, and men's resistanceare often over¬
whelming. It is important not to overload the
learning programmes or to expect women to be
involved in too many programme activities at the
same time. Mass literacy campaigns, genuine
political priority and community support for
literacy have been the most successful factors in
mobilizing women to participate in and complete
literacy programmes. In these campaigns men
have been pressurized to accept women's partici¬
pation in literacy and in other social, economic
and political activities. It is important to promote
awareness of women's rights within literacy
programmes designed for them, and, indeed, this
contributes to the success of such programmes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
National languages and
mother tongues
By Adama Ouane
"
JA '"'a, V 'i^j X lÍ
iXj
IN any literacy teaching project, the choice of
the language to be taught is of paramount impor¬
tance. Highly complex human and cultural fac¬
tors are involved in this learning process, whether
for the child, the continuity of whose affective,
cognitive and psycho-motor development it is the
guarantee, or for the adult, for whom literacy
training will only be motivating if it leads on to
greater participation in the political, economic
and social life of the community to which he or
she belongs.
Literacy teaching in the mother tongue has
a head start, since the pupil begins with an already
acquired knowledge of the language. Literacy
teaching in a foreign language makes learning the
mechanisms of reading and writing considerably
more complicated, since it introduces difficulties
inherent in the acquisition of new vocabulary and
of new ways of thinking.
What is a mother tongue? The "mother" in
the term has no "genetic" or "biological" con¬
notations, but relates to the linguistic community
in which a person is born and brought up. A
mother tongue is the prime means of expression
of an ethnic group and is the instrument of the
socialization of the individual within the basic
social unit, usually the family.
The problems
of access to
literacy in
multilingual
societies
Above, open-air literacy
class in India, where there
are some 1,600 mother
tongues for a population of
almost 800 million people.
According to their status or their function,
mother tongues become community or vehicular
languages when they are also used for inter-ethnic
or inter-community communication. They are
called "national languages" when they constitute
the language of the entire nation or of its main
ethnic components. From this point of view, the
linguistic situation on our planet is extremely
complex, since, including dialects, there are
thought to be between 3,500 and 9,000 languages
in the world, distributed over some 200 sovereign
states.
Mother tongues
and national unity
Very few countries are strictly monolingual.
The situation of multilingual countries varies
according to their history, their social and eco¬
nomic context, and the ethnic composition of
their populations. The relationships between
local languages, the functions they fulfil, the status
it is desired to give them and the educational aims
of the society all influence the definition and
implementation of language policies.
The adoption of a common language can, ob¬
viously, promote national unity. Many decision- 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
makers are convinced that the encouragement of
several languages militates against such unity, and
the risk of accentuating cleavages between com¬
munities and the danger of being left outside the
main currents of knowledge and information
flow are often invoked to justify the choice of
one or a restricted number of national languages,
even, perhaps, a foreign language, as official
languages.
Monolingualism continues to be perceived as
a major element in the founding of a nation. Yet
what heightens dissension is not so much the
plurality of languages as the conflicts of interest
that they express. A plurality of languages should
be seen as an enrichment and as the reflection of
a plurality of cultures.
The substitution of interdependent relation¬
ships for ties based on domination contributes
greatly to national integration. Apart from en¬
suring the development of widely used languages,
the coexistence of several mother tongues guaran¬
tees better mutual understanding between
cultures.
For sociological and sometimes psychological
reasons relating to history, and in particular to
the colonial past of some countries, certain lan¬
guages have become devalued because they are
considered unsuited to express the complexities
of the modern world. Still hovering between the
oral and written forms, they may indeed find it
difficult to cover the vast and changing field of
contemporary science.
The coexistence of several languages necessar¬
ily raises the question of their "parity" or "equal¬
ity". Theoretically, all languages are of equal
value and are intrinsically capable of expressing
the same realities and of developingit is in being
used that they develop and become refined. In
practice, however, their true position depends
upon the status accorded to them as well as the
functions they fulfil and the fields in which they
are used. In this respect, true equality between
languages is impossible. But is it even necessary?
In a plurilingual context the aim should rather
be to achieve complementarity of roles and
functions.
Those who decry the use of mother tongues
in literacy work invoke economic and technical
arguments, pointing out that, in a society with
no basic infrastructure, it is difficult to bear the
cost of the operations necessary to integrate these
languages into the educational system.
It is true that to publish textbooks and primers
in languages that are in the course of becoming
established raises a number of material and tech¬
nical problems. The phonetic and grammatical
structure of languages that have only recently ac¬
quired a written form involves the use of graphic
signs and printing characters that demand a tech¬
nical competence rarely available in the countries
concerned. These, however, are difficulties that
can be reduced by the use of informal teaching
methods and simplified printing techniques.
Between these two extremesmaking use of
all a country's languages, which is practically and
financially impossible, or adopting a single lan¬
guage (often a foreign language), which is cultur¬
ally and politically unacceptablethere lies a
third way: that of a graduated multilingualism,
in which the emphasis is placed on certain lan¬
guages, yet without neglecting the development
of the others.
Within a given national unit, at least two lin¬
guistic levels can always be distinguished, that of
the individual's mother tongue and that of the
main, official language of the state. Sometimes
there may be three, four or even five levels, cor¬
responding to an equivalent number of languages
which it is desirable to know. However, mastery
of the first language, the mother tongue, or of
the variant that replaces it, remains the decisive
step in the individual's linguistic development.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The teaching of the mother tongue leads to
an uncomfortable dilemma: attaching too much
importance to local languages can be a handicap
with regard to economic and scientific matters,
but to ignore them is to condemn them to regres¬
sion. The dilemma resolves itself, however, if the
primary objective is to encourage the emotional
development, the self-discovery and concern for
the future of the community of the person learn¬
ing to read, rather than to ensure the acquisition
of a socially and functionally dominant language.
Different approaches
The mother tongue may be used as the vehicle of
education at all levels of the educational system.
It may enjoy exclusive status, but in some cases
it is used up to a certain level and then replaced
by another language. In other cases, it is used for
the teaching of certain subjects only.
Sometimes the mother tongue is the subject,
but not the medium, of teaching. Literacy work
with adults is often carried out with a partial use
of the mother tongue.
Some national languages are not equipped to
perform effectively all the functions required in a
complete education. In these cases, enrichment of
the language becomes part of the task of literacy
and post-literacy work.
In most of the multilingual countries of
Africa and Asia, in which the language spoken
in the family circle is often not that used by
the authorities or in schools, literacy work is
usually conducted in the local languages. When
these languages have only a recent written tradi¬
tion, literacy work marks the transition from
the oral to the written, with all that that implies
for specific modes of perception and reflection.
Clearly, these countries are attempting to
create and maintain a social, economic and cul¬
tural climate favourable to the written word,
including the greatest possible stimulation and
incitation to written expression.
One of the essential functions of those en¬
gaged in literacy work is to produce, acquire
and manage teaching materials in the national
languages and mother tongues. Some of this
material is printed, some is produced for the
modern media (radio, television, audio-visual
display) and some for the traditional media
(theatre, folklore, various types of games).
Libraries, fairs, exhibitions, listening groups,
study circles and action groups are set up to
make these materials available and to encourage
the largest possible number of people to use
them.
The newly-literate must be placed in an
environment in which they are constantly faced
with the challenge of the written word. Printed
material alone is not enough. The newly-literate
must be involved in activities which are too com¬
plex for them to rely on memory and oblige them
to use written communication. Most of the
French-speaking countries of Africa are thus
trying to familiarize their civil servants and
development personnel with the written forms
of languages used in literacy work. They are
encouraging the use of these written forms in
technical and administrative documents, road
signs, advertisements and the labelling of goods,
as well as the diffusion of books, brochures and
newspapers written in these languages.
The purpose of these measures is to overcome
reservations about, if not disdain for, the lan¬
guages used in literacy work on the pan of officials
most of whom are the product of a different
educational system and who normally use another
form of communication such as a European lan¬
guage (in this case French). They also help to de-
marginalize the newly-literate by offering them a
written environment in which they feel secure.
"Including dialects, there
are thought to be between
3,500 and 9,000 languages in
the world.... Very few
countries are strictly
monolingual." Above left, a
store in Jaipur (India);
centre, a Hong Kong street;
above, shops in Abu Dhabi
(United Arab Emirates).
ADAMA OUANE,
of Mali, is engaged on
research at the Unesco
Institute for Education,
Hamburg (Fed. Rep. of
Germany). Formerly assistant
director-general of the
national directorate for
functional literacy and
linguistics at Bamako, he is
the author of several studies
on the use of national
languages in literacy
campaigns.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Industrialized
countries
discover the
extent of
widespread
illiteracy in their
midst
Waste
By Jean-Pierre Vélis
W.
30
' HEN you read the first line of this article you
have no difficulty at all in deciphering the graphic
signs of which it is composed, grasping the
arrangement of the different terms and under¬
standing their meaning. Without your giving the
matter any thought, your eyes have scanned the
text and your brain has unconsciously mobilized
all kinds of highly complex physiological and
intellectual mechanisms. For you reading is second
nature, so self-evident that you may have forgot¬
ten the effort its acquisition cost you. You can
scarcely imagine life without reading.
As the twentieth century draws to a close,
in the so-called industrialized countries, reading,
writing and arithmetic, the three universally-
accepted components of literacy, are considered
normal skills that everyone must master. Espe¬
cially since in these countries schooling is gener¬
ally compulsory and free, and sometimes has been
so for more than a century, and it is the duty of
the school to teach these skills. It would seem in¬
conceivable that a person who has attended
school for many years should be unable to read
on reaching adulthood, especially in societies
where the written word is practically indispens¬
able to everyday survival. The general reaction
to the existence of illiteracy is one of amazement
and incredulity.
A recent revelation
To be illiterate in a country where for several
decades there has been a struggle against illiteracy
is a far worse handicap than it is in a country
where illiteracy is the general rule. In industrial¬
ized societies the illiterate are the victims of an
unusual form of segregation which often causes
them to feel ashamed. And since they tend to
conceal their existence, it was a long time before
they were noticed. Was this oversight deliberate
or unconscious?
It was in the early 1970s that illiteracy sud¬
denly reappeared as a public issue in the indus¬
trialized countries. In 1972 the British people
were astonished to discover, from the findings of
a small charitable organization, the British
Association of Settlements, that between 7 and 10
per cent of adolescents aged sixteen or more were
barely able to stumble through a simple text
when they left school, and that there were some
two million illiterate people in the United King¬
dom, not counting immigrants.
This revelation was important for several rea¬
sons. It was the first time people realized the full
extent of a phenomenon that was far from mar¬
ginal. (Over the next fifteen years, many indus¬
trialized countries produced official or unofficial
estimates of a comparable order of grandeur1).
Secondly, a campaign to make public opinion
aware of the problem launched by the BBC
Automation tends to reduce
the numbers of unskilled
jobs and has revealed the
existence of "functional"
illiteracy.
Below, Jane Fonda in
Stanley & Iris (1990),
a film by the American
director Martin Ritt which
deals with illiteracy in the
United States.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
programme On the Move and the government
measures to which it gave rise (such as the creation
of an agency for adult literacy), have often been
taken as models. Finally, this revelation en¬
couraged reflection on the concept of illiteracy
and its persistence in wealthy societies that are
proud of their culture and their record of school
attendance.
Another form of illiteracy
There have always been illiterates in the indus¬
trialized countries, but the public has not always
been aware of their existence, and their numbers
gradually declined to the point where they were
statistically negligible. As schooling has become
more widespread and education has become more
democratic, their numbers have constantly
decreased in recent decades while the general level
of education has risen. So is this a question of
much ado about nothing?
These illiterate people are adults who have
attended school and have had some contact with
reading and writing. They may know the alphabet
and even be just about capable of deciphering a
few words. They may be able to write a little.
They may recognize figures and be able to do a
few sums, but their knowledge in these fields is
rudimentary and insufficient for them to cope
easily with everyday life. They are not totally
illiterate, but they are illiterate in the context of
the society in which they live. For this reason
the term most frequently used to describe their
situation is "functional illiteracy", a relative
notion the content of which may vary widely at
different" times, in different countries and even
in different regions.
These functional illiterates are not a recent
phenomenon. A specific form of illiteracy has
arisen in contemporary Western societies in
which structural developments in employment
have resulted in requirements for higher levels of
training and qualification.
In rural societies where there are large num¬
bers of manual and unskilled jobs, the illiterate
managed to achieve social and professional in¬
tegration. This is no longer possible in industri¬
alized societies whose economies in the final
decade of the twentieth century are increasingly
dependent on the services sector. The large-scale
disappearance of unskilled jobs, together with the
constant rise in the qualifications required, is
leaving functional illiterates behind. Whenever a
firm reduces its staff, closes down or introduces
new technologies, workers hitherto considered
competent and efficient are devalued, incapable
of being retrained because their reading, writing
and calculating skills are inadequate. Labelled as
"functional illiterates", they find themselves
queuing up in employment agencies or receiving
some form of public assistance. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
It is not surprising that functional illiteracy
should have been rediscovered in the early
1970sthe time of the first oil crisis, the begin¬
ning of the world economic crisis and the spec¬
tacular rise in unemployment, especially among
young people.
It soon became clear that there was a close
correlation between poverty and illiteracy, though
it was not possible to unravel cause and effect.
Hence the battle against illiteracy from the
beginning has been seen as an activity with social
and humanitarian connotations.
A number of countries have sought the help
of voluntary workersmothers willing to give
their free time or retired peopleon the principle
that people who know how to read, write and
count should be able to pass on their knowledge,
if only for a few hours a week, to those who do
not. Unfortunately there have been many disap¬
pointments and setbacks. Lack of method, teach¬
ing materials suitable only for immigrants, the
absence of training facilities for voluntary
teachers, have led even the most enthusiastic to
despair. In addition, even today, financial
resources are often insufficient, and support from
the authorities is often half-hearted. Where adult
illiterates are concerned, help has almost always
come from voluntary associations supported by
social workers. Some twenty years on, apart from
a few notable exceptions such as the Netherlands
and Portugal, the situation is still unchanged.
More than an economic
challenge
Initially viewed as an educational problem closely
linked to mechanisms of social discrimination,
functional illiteracy in the late 1980s became the
centre of an alarmist economic scenario. In North
America it has been the subject of a number of
reports and studies whose conclusions have been
voiced by political leaders and industrialists
swayed by the simple argument that illiteracy is
expensive both for companies and for the nation
as a whole. "The estimated direct cost of illiteracy
Above, two booklets from a
set produced for adult
literacy students in 1977 by
a British publisher. Each is
based on the vocabulary and
skills needed in an everyday
situation.
Above left, a retired man
from Troyes (France) acts as
volunteer adult literacy
tutor in his spare time.
JEAN-PIERRE VELIS,
a French journalist
specializing in education, is
the author of Through a
Glass, DarklyFunctional
Illiteracy in Industrialized
Countries, published by
Unesco, Paris, 1990. He was
formerly assistant editor-in-
chief of the French journal
L'Education.
to the business world in Canada is some C$4 bil¬
lion. It could actually be higher, since the total
loss to Canadian society is estimated, at the very
least, to amount to C$10 billion a year."2 Func¬
tional illiteracy is expensive today and tomorrow
will be even more so since in the long term it
weakens a country's competitivity on the world
economic market. A US Congressman has
declared that "Members of Congress are begin¬
ning to understand that, as a matter of fact, il¬
literacy is going to determine whether we are
competitive or not competitive in the years to
come."
And so measures to solve the problem cannot
be left exclusively to voluntary workers. A firm
commitment from governments is required. "The
time is clearly past when the government could
look on while the voluntary organizations took
charge of the problem of illiteracy," the Canadian
Prime Minister stated in 1987 when he announced
that his government would be investing C$110
million over a five-year period in an attempt to
solve the problem. In the same vein, the French
Secretary of State for Professional Training,
speaking in 1989, stressed that "The scale of the
task calls for a veritable national crusade. I intend
to ensure that training activities designed to
combat functional illiteracy are rid of the secre¬
tive atmosphere in which they are all too often
shrouded and become one of the main concerns
of the training schemes introduced for people
whose low standards of knowledge currently
exclude them from the labour market.... This
campaign is all the more pressing since such
exclusion is a threat to progress and spells the ruin
of development in the long run. It is economi¬
cally necessary for us to win the battle and it
would be socially unjust not to fight it."
Such is the situation as the 1990s begin
beneath the emblem of International Literacy
Year. This is more than an educational, social or
economic challenge; it is a human challenge. By
the time the industrialized countries enter the
twenty-first century, will they be able to halt the
development within themalas well underway
of a two-tier society, a large majority of whose
members will enjoy the benefits of progress from
which an important dependent minority will con¬
tinue to be excluded, because they are unable, or
not sufficiently able, to read, write and count?
1. The overall total (illiterates, those without schooling and
those who have not completed basic primary and secondary
education) of non-literates over the age of 10 is 36.4% in Spain;
23% in Italy; 23.2% in Greece; one adult in five in France;
24% of adults over 18 in Canada; 13% of those over 17 in
the USA. There are between 300,000 and 500,000 non-literates
in Wallonia and in Brussels (Belgium). According to a survey
carried out in Hungary among a sample of adults, 30% had
never used writing in their lives and 16% had never held a
printed sheet in their hands.
2. The Cost of Illiteracy in Canada, Canadian Business Task
Force on Literacy, Toronto, 1988.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The
microcomputer
has become
an important
support for
new forms
of literacy
Z - \ ?*$ . *{
L. A # ^
/ ^
The PC and the 3 Rs
i
By Kenneth Levine
N a century of almost continuous technological
innovation affecting all the major media of human
communication, the last decade has been partic¬
ularly marked by rapid and striking developments
in telecommunications and the power and cost-
effectiveness of computers. Until recently, the
inculcation of reading and writing skills has been
the pre-eminent and unchallenged objective of
almost all programmes of basic education the
world over, but it is natural that sophisticated
technical developments should prompt some
reflection about the future significance of literacy,
for both individuals and societies.
Among the many issues that arise, we can use¬
fully concentrate our attention, in turn, on three.
Do "traditional" literacy and the medium of
print retain their importance in the face of com¬
petition from new modes of transmitting infor-
Optical fibres (above),
glass filaments no thicker
than a human hair, are
revolutionizing
telecommunications.
mation, and if so, how will they be altered? What
degree of change is likely to take place in the level
and spread of skills constituting literacy? Should
the new media be seen as benign and potentially
democratizing forces, or as sinister additions to
the armouries of already powerful élites and
bureaucracies? We can simplify our task some¬
what by selecting the impact of the personal com¬
puter on literacy as the main example under
scrutiny.
Before tackling these specifi'c questions, there
are two preliminary considerations of a general
kind. The first is an obstacle to sound reasoning
that must be removed. Many of the forecasts and
scenarios that are being dispensed by contem¬
porary commentators contain a debilitating flaw
in their analysis. They assume that the new tech¬
nologies usher in a set of predetermined social and 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
economic consequences that are universal and
irresistiblean assumption often referred to as
"technological determinism".
Many of the scenarios, whether optimistic or
pessimistic in tone, consist of the extrapolation
and generalization of trends from a particular
technical development in a particular society. In
predicting what will happen when that technol¬
ogy emerges in, or is transferred to, other soci¬
eties, little or no allowance is made for the
34
mediation of local economic, political and social
processes.
The second consideration relates to literacy
itself. Literacy is not a unified skill but a plurality
of different capacities. A pedant would insist that
we speak always of "literacies" in an effort to
accommodate the fact, for example, that people
"literate" by all of the conventional benchmarks
may nevertheless not be able to read or write in
"foreign" languages, or even use many of the
specialist applications of writing and print avail¬
able in their own natural language (for example,
notations for music or chemical compounds, pho¬
netic alphabets, proof-reading marks, maps,
timetables, engineering plans, meta-languages for
logical, mathematical or computing purposes).
One of the indirect impacts of new technol¬
ogies is that they alter prevailing social definitions
of the skills (and the level of the skills) that con¬
stitute literacy. It is important clearly to distin¬
guish improving or declining rates of literacy
from shifts in the way in which it is being con¬
ceived and defined.
Let us now take up the question of the dura¬
bility of traditional literacy. One reliable meas¬
ure of its continued importance is the level of
consumption of printed paper, which has shown
steady increases in both developed and develop¬
ing societies over the past decade. Partly through
its close connection with techniques of
bureaucratic organization and project manage¬
ment, the incorporation of reading and writing
into all spheres of life and into a vast assortment
of mundane transactions is at work on a global
scale. The situation is broadly similar for "serious"
writing and publication. Despite the forecasts that
Computerization of the
workplace: (above) India;
(right) Zaire.
have been repeatedly made over the last fifty years
concerning the imminent eclipse of "book cul¬
tures", the statistics show that the market for con¬
ventionally published works has held up in the
face of the expansion of ostensibly "rival" media
such as recorded music, television and video.
Software that takes
the drudgery out of writing
There are several reasons for viewing the advent
of micro-computers as an important support for
the literacy/print combination. The potential of
this kind of equipment as a literacy aid, mainly
within the framework of conventional schooling,
has been recognized for some years. Unfortunate¬
ly, the first generations of computer software for
use in literacy training were, in general, pedes¬
trian in conception, offering little more than drill
exercises on a display screen rather than on paper.
The greatest contribution to literacy studies so
far has come from word processing software
which has eliminated much of the drudgery as¬
sociated in the past with the creation of finely-
tuned and error-free texts, allowing the novice
and the experienced author alike to concentrate
on the creative process and to experiment freely.
Spelling checkers, now often integrated with
word processing software, represent a useful half¬
way house on the road to high-level literacy: they
allow the learner to eliminate errors (and mis¬
types) that would, if uncorrected, detract from
the polish and authority of the resulting text. In
future, grammar and style checkers will extend
this kind of facility, although at present they are
generally crude and unreliable. As significantly
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
KENNETH LEVINE,
of the United Kingdom, is a
lecturer in sociology at the
University of Nottingham.
He is the author of The
Social Context of Literacy
(Routledge & Kegan Paul,
London, 1986).
more powerful hardware and software become
available, the quality of such aids will improve
drastically. Many creative possibilities are also
opened up by the way in which the micro¬
computer can be used as the heart of a "hyperme¬
dia" system that is to say, as the device that con¬
trols the generation of a "performance" involving
text, graphics and sound that is structured inter¬
actively according to the responses of the learner
to the programme.
New ways of learning
The linking of micro-computers to telecommu¬
nications networks is another area of immense
potential, particularly for the study of foreign lan¬
guages. Pupils can send messages to their peers
across continents quickly and relatively cheaply,
adding spice and interest to language studies and
frequently providing the contacts that lead to col¬
laboration on projects and exchanges of person¬
nel. This kind of "electronic mail", which
involves an amalgam of the characteristics of face
to face interaction, telephone contact and letter
writing, has the hallmarks of a distinctive medi¬
um of communication with a unique blend of in¬
timacy, informality and distance.
One of the most important characteristics of
these latter developments is that they promote
a participative form of learning; they permit (and
frequently require) the learner to have a pro¬
active role in decisions about how the pedagogic
project is to be approached, and they are gener¬
ally congruent with a philosophy of releasing the
learning process, as far as possible, from the
physical boundaries of any specific educational
institution.
The next issue concerning possible changes in
the constituent skills of literacy is an important
one with two principal aspects. The first is that
change in the print-bearing medium does direct¬
ly alter the character of reading and writing skills,
but in most cases, only at the margins. Thus, to
the extent that micro-computers become standard
classroom teaching aids, some elements of "com¬
puter literacy" such as familiarity with keyboards
and basic knowledge of the capacities of word
processing systems and their associated equipment
will increasingly be incorporated into popular ex¬
pectations of what literacy signifies, in much the
same way as use of the electronic calculator is be¬
ing assimilated into notions of numeracy.
The second aspect concerns the probability
that, in many societies, "inflation" will lead to 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
i 1* -
gliü&vaí HU1^01 ?w?inlrH
» * -t. LtJL j, o o
-', FfFPT rj F F f £
* t * ni* .
WiA^ ,hîr^V°X YiM°V O
36
Above, musical notation,
16th century.
Left, diagrams of the
structure of the atom, from
New System of Chemical
Philosophy (1808-1810), by
the British chemist and
physicist John Dalton.
a rise in the threshold of the minimum accept¬
able standard of reading and writing (a standard
often referred to as "functional literacy"). This
inflation occurs because literacy is never a purely
instrumental skill; possession or lack of it univer¬
sally carries implications for the individual's
social standing, so there is a tendency to seek the
highest level of attainment possible, irrespective
of the difficulty of the materials that will be
written or read.
Literacy is also the means to gaining educa¬
tional qualifications that can secure entry to
remunerative and prestigious forms of employ¬
ment. In the face of competition, some candidates
for such posts will choose to invest in higher lev¬
els of literacy in order to acquire the advanced
qualifications that give them an advantage over
their rivals. Over time, others will copy their ex¬
ample, until everyone finishes up in their origi¬
nal relative positions. To achieve any advantage,
an individual must now make a further invest¬
ment in literacy and qualifications, fuelling an in¬
flationary spiral of standards. The general
implication of this spiral is that there will be a
need to enhance the attainment targets in many
programmes of basic education and also to offer
more comprehensive provision for intermediate
and advanced language studies.
Finally, are the new technologies essentially
democratic and egalitarian, or threats to civil
liberties and personal freedoms? It has been ar¬
gued, for example, that tools such as desk-top
publishing, which can greatly facilitate the
production of low-cost documentation such as
newsletters and teaching materials, will empower
many marginal and scattered minority groups,
giving them for the first time a collective voice
and identity. It has equally been argued that the
capacity of national governments to acquire the
most powerful available means of information
storage and processing leads to ever greater dangers
of centralized control and cultural uniformity.
As suggested at the start of this article, ab¬
stract generalizations in this area are likely to be
unsound. As with technology generally, in benign
hands the new tools of literacy are themselves be¬
nign. The ends to which they are applied are a
political and cultural consideration determined
within each host society. There is, however, one
significant global aspect: the cost of the new in¬
formation systems, although falling rapidly in real
terms, represents yet another potential source of
inequality between the developed and the de¬
veloping nations.
The new information technologies cannot be
looked to for a once and final solution to the
problem of world literacy. Indeed, we must ac¬
cept that this problem is not of a kind that lends
itself to final eradication since literacy and illiter¬
acy are both relative rather than absolute condi¬
tions. The least literate in any society will always
be seriously disadvantaged, while the fluent will
increasingly demand opportunities to acquire
specialist technical or foreign language literacies.
In all probability, new technologies alone cannot
cope with this rise in expectations, but if they
are developed and implemented in a manner sen¬
sitive to local needs and conditions, they can
make a more than modest contribution to meet¬
ing the literacy aspirations of a new century.!
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The road to reading
* i
i. ~T
///i«!
Ji
By Ralph C. Staiger
WaE enjoy doing the things we do well. A good
football player enjoys outwitting the opposition
as the ball moves towards the goal. A graceful
dancer enjoys the movement, rhythm and music
of the dance. A good reader is more likely to
reach for a newspaper or a book than someone
who stumbles over every word.
A child who is a slow, halting reader will
avoid reading even the most beautifully illustrated
storybook. He or she may try to understand the
gist of a story from the pictures, but will be
unable to enjoy it fully.
Many people believe that the first steps
How adults
can introduce
children
to a lifelong
pleasure
towards reading take place in a school, and that
the teacher has the primary responsibility in guid¬
ing them. This is not wholly true. School read¬
ing books provide some reading experience, but
they are meant to teach children how to read, and
cannot be expected also to ensure that the learn¬
er will derive lifelong pleasure from reading. The
responsibility for creating lifetime readers is a
broad one, shared by family, school, libraries,
bookstores and the mass media.
Even before school starts, a child experiences
much within the family circle which can lead to
reading. Mother, father, brothers, sisters, uncles, 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
aunts, grandparents and friends of the family pro¬
vide the most important early experiences on
which it is possible to build concepts and attitudes
which create a successful reader. The disposition
of the family towards ideas, towards books and
reading, establishes important values which may
stir even the youngest baby.
It is never too early to start. The infant in
its mother's lap who is read toeven if the stories
are not understoodlearns that reading is a com¬
fortable experience and that words and pictures
must be good. Later, when the stories become
pleasurable on a different level, this attitude will
continue. Most children also enjoy the comfort
of hearing the same familiar stories over and over.
Sometimes they gleefully finish sentences. This
does not mean that it is no longer necessary to
read that story. The child is showing apprecia¬
tion and learning has taken place from the story.
Playing games with words
Exposure to languagejust talking to a babyis
important. As children grow, they usually enjoy
word play and word games which help them
show their mastery over words. The whole fa¬
mily can join in the fun of playing games with
words. Active teaching of basic concepts and at¬
titudes is also the responsibility of a parent.
Learning to recognize, name and differentiate be¬
tween colours may seem rudimentary, but it is
an important building block, as are many other
concepts and experiences about which a child will
be expected to know and eventually read.
A mother or father who reads a story to a
child may entice the child to enjoy more difficult
tales. By listening to their parents reading aloud
from books too difficult for them to read them¬
selves, young learners find out how complex
stories take shape and how words are used. Their
understanding of what books can be is enhanced,
and when they later encounter these stories in
their own reading, they are meeting old friends.
Reading to children should continue long after
they have begun to read for themselves.
There is evidence that even in the most
depressed economic conditions, whether a child
becomes a reader or not depends upon a role
model in the family ro provide an example. Par¬
ents who read themselves are likely to have chil¬
dren who read. Parents who discuss what they
have read and invite their children's contributions
to the conversation are directly influencing their
children's reading development. The role model's
enjoyment helps make a reader for the future.
All of this takes time. But it is well worth
the investment. A daily period for family reading
may take several forms. Instead of the parent doing
all the reading, several children may read from
their books and talk about them. An older child
or a parent may start a sentence or a paragraph
and have a younger child try to finish it appropri¬
ately. The resulting discussion (or argument) is
a useful way of developing vocabulary and social
skills and learning about language structure.
After setting the stage for reading and other
intellectual activity, perhaps the most important
contribution a parent can make to readers in the
family is to make sure that books and other
materials are available for them. This does not
RALPH C. STAIGER,
of the United States, is
chairman of the International
Book Committee, an advisory
committee of non¬
governmental 'organizations
with consultative status at
Unesco. He served as
executive director of the
International Reading
Association for 22 years
before his retirement in 1984
and is the author of over 50
publications about reading.
This article has been adapted
from a booklet which forms
part of a series entitled
Literacy Lessons, produced by
the International Bureau of
Education on the occasion of
International Literacy Year
(see page 50).
You can take a book
JO almost anywhere.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
necessarily mean buying books or journals, but
may involve going to the library, borrowing
books from friends and neighbours or making
available books from other sources.
The electronic media play an important role,
too, for films, radio and television can help build
the world of ideas which a reader needs. Televi¬
sion and radio can often be useful instruments
for discussing plots and the use of language, and
for evaluating the worth of a specific programme
collectively. The media can stimulate children to
read more about a subject. If children spend an
inordinate amount of time mindlessly watching
television, it is sometimes necessary to limit the
amount of viewing time and to help them decide
which programmes to watch. Television is a
source of learning about many things. It should
be used with co-operative judgement.
Schools are responsible for sharpening the
reading abilities of young people, but they cannot
The children's corner of a
bookshop.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
be expected to perform the entire task of shaping
perceptual skills, providing experiences and
motivating each pupil for a lifetime of reading.
Teachers can do much to create an atmosphere
in which learning will not be a dreaded memory.
If a sharp-tongued teacher ridicules a poor reader,
the other pupils soon join in. This is inexcusable.
It may teach the victim to avoid reading for life.
Like a parent, a teacher who reads to the class
from a book which he or she has enjoyedeven
though it may be above the class's reading level-
plants seeds for future adult reading. Not only
is an example being set, but the teacher's en¬
thusiasm may be infectious, and the student's
curiosity aroused. Poetry particularly lends itself
to being read aloud.
Encouraging children
to create
Just as there are many kinds of reading materials,
so there are many ways to read. Reading a recipe
is different from reading a news item in the paper.
For most children, stories are the commonest and
most enjoyable kind of reading. Even here,
however, different reading approaches are the
norm. Some children will race through a story
to find out what happened. Others may use the
plot as a launching pad for imaginative thinking
and acting. Such children may become creative
artists.
All children should be encouraged to create.
Their early attempts to write should be en¬
couraged, for a writer is likely to become a read¬
er. Adults should remember that spelling words
is an acquired skill. More literal-minded young-
"The responsibility for
creating lifetime readers is a
broad one..."
sters use reading primarily to gather and deal with
information, although they may also enjoy an im¬
aginative story. Helping to build vocabulary and
suggesting how information can be located and
used may be the most profitable ways of helping
such children. Librarians know how to use refer¬
ence works and can almost always show the
information-gatherer where to look.
Children's interests and attention spans vary;
some maintain regard for what is read, even if
the story is from adult materials which the par¬
ent enjoys and would like to share. When it be¬
comes obvious that the child is no longer paying
attention, it is time to move to books which are
closer to the child's level of interest. The parent's
obvious interest and enjoyment are eloquent,
however, whether the materials are easy or
difficult.
Setting aside a time for family readingan
hour during which parents and children read
something of interest to themis especially use¬
ful in families which discuss their reading as a
matter of course. If the reading hour is perceived
as a form of punishment, it can backfire.
Parents should avoid closing doors to books
and ideas through unwitting ridicule, verbal or
subconscious. "What, nose in a book again!" even
if said in jest, can quench a child's interest quick¬
ly. They should also avoid making discussion
about books and ideas a testing situation, with
penalties for answers which do not agree with a
parent's preconceptions of the subject. Nor
should they force a child to read a book without
previous discussion about it. When reading is a
voluntary activity, it is much more likely to be
relished and continued for life.
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
Soviet-American
magazine launched
in USA
An English-language
scientific quarterly for young
people has been launched as
the result of a joint effort by
three US teachers'
associations and the USSR
Academy of Sciences. The
magazine, entitled Quantum
and based on Kvant, a
popular Soviet magazine for
secondary school students, is
published ¡n Washington,
D.C. Its contents include
articles and problems on
geometry, algebra, physics
and chess, as well as profiles
of famous Soviet and
American scientists.
Air traffic set
to double by the
year 2000
Long-term forecasts of
scheduled passenger and
freight traffic issued by the
International Civil Aviation
Organization (ICAO) indicate
that traffic worldwide
will double by the year
2000, and that European
and American airlines will
be overtaken by those of
Asia and the Pacific.
International traffic is
expected to grow faster
than domestic, ICAO reports,
and the number of
passengers carried is
expected to increase from
1,000 million in 1988
to just under 2,000 million
in 2000.
Nuclear power
Ten new nuclear power
plants were brought on line
in 8 countries in 1989:
Bulgaria, the Federal
Republic of Germany, India,
Japan, the Republic of
Korea, Mexico, the UK and
the USA, reports the
International Atomic Energy
Agency. The world's total
number of operating nuclear
electricity plants now stands
at 435, accounting for nearly
17% of electricity production.
Scanning
the Sphinx
A team of French restoration
experts appointed by Unesco
has tested the structure of
the 4,500-year-old
Great Sphinx at Giza,' Egypt.
The colossal portrait
statue of the Pharaoh
Khephren was scanned
with ultrasonic equipment
in order to diagnose
the condition of
the stone. Initial findings
show that the head is firmly
attached to the neck and
that the quality of the stone
is good.
Unesco aids Bangladesh
Polytechnic for women
The first graduates of the
Mohila Polytechnic Institute
in Dhaka (Bangladesh), all of
whose students are women,
will receive their diplomas in
architecture and electronics
this year. It was to help
promote greater equality of
opportunity for women that
the Government of
Bangladesh founded the
Polytechnic with help from
Unesco and the Kingdom of
Saudi Arabia. The Institute
currently has some 200
students enrolled in its
3-year courses, which are in
great demandabout 1,000
young women applied for 80
vacancies last year.
'Steel collar workers'
and safety
The International Labour
Organisation (ILO) reports
that there are likely to be 10
million robots ¡n the world
by the year 2000. Some
141,000 of these "steel
collar workers" are already
being used in Japan, more
than anywhere else. But as
the number of robots ¡n the
workplace has risen, so has
the number of robot-related
accidents. The ILO has
responded with a study
which sets out basic principles
and practices for working
safely with these machines.
1st stage of Sistine
Chapel restoration
complete
The first phase of the
restoration of Michelangelo's
biblical frescoes in the
Vatican's Sistine Chapel is
now complete, after 8 years
of work. A specially
developed computer system
was used to create a visual
record of the frescoes before
and after restoration.
Accurate to within a
millimetre, the system made
¡t possible to trace
Michelangelo's day-by-day
progress when he painted the
frescoes on the Chapel vault
between 1508 and 1512. The
restorers are now working
on The Last Judgement, on
the altar wall. Work on this
¡s expected to be finished by
1994.
Music for Molière
The original version of
Molière's last play, Le
Malade Imaginaire (1 673),
has been reconstituted
thanks to a discovery by an
American musicologist, John
Powell. In the archives of the
Comédie Française in Paris
Mr. Powell found much of
the manuscript score of
music composed by Marc
Antoine Charpentier to
accompany the play,
originally described as a
"comedy mingled with music
and dance."
Reporting from space
The first journalist in space
will be either Ryoko Kikuchi,
a Japanese camerawoman,
or her colleague Toyohiro
Akiyama. The two are semi-
finalists selected for training
from among 163 employees
of a Japanese private
broadcasting company. The
winner will board a Soviet
Soyuz spacecraft scheduled
for launch on 2 December
1990 and will make live
broadcasts in Japanese for
radio and television during
the 8-day mission.
40th anniversary
of WMO
The World Meteorological
Organization (WMO), a
specialized agency of the
United Nations, celebrates
its 40th birthday this year.
In 1950, WMO succeeded
the International
Meteorological Organization,
a non-governmental
organization founded in
1873. The World
Meteorological Convention
of 1947 provided for the
establishment of a new
organization to promote a
worldwide meteorological
information system,
the standardization and
international exchange
of observations, the
application of meteorology
to other fields, and the
establishment of national
meteorological services in
developing countries.
International
conference on earth
architecture
The 6th international
conference on the
Conservation of Earthen
Architecture will be held
in October at Las Cruces,
New Mexico (USA). It is
being organized by the
Getty Conservation Institute,
the Museum of New
Mexico State Monuments
and ICCROM (International
Centre for the Study
of the Preservation "
and the Restoration of
Cultural Property), under
the aegis of US/ICOMOS
(International Council of
Monuments and Sites).
Topics to be covered
include the history of
earthen architecture,
problems with moisture,
restoration and conservation,
clay chemistry, and seismic
mitigation. It is estimated
that between 30% and
40% of the world's
population today live
in dwellings In which earth
is used as a building
material.
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
After literacy what next? Many of the questions raised
in this essay written nearly half a century ago by a great
Spanish poet are still as topical as ever.
The new
illiterates
By Pedro Salinas
42
In the beginning there was Illiteracy.
Over the centuries and thanks to
God, light gradually dawned, until
today we have compulsory primary
education. Most people, including
many teachers, would agree that the
acquisition of literacy skills, or rather
the ability to read, marks a frontier
so clearly defined that ¡t divides hu¬
manity into two totally different
groups.
On one side of the divide is the
anonymous mass of unfortunate
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
people who are unable to penetrate
the mysteries of the printed word and
remain on the outside, for all the
world as if they were standing on the
shore of a sea across which they
could be borne to marvellous lands,
if only they had a ship to sail in. On
the other side are the legions of the
privileged, who have had the good
fortune to achieve that blessed state
in which they know for certain that
c and o make co, that c and a make
ca and, thanks to this knowledge, can
decipher the posters which proclaim
the magic words: "Coca Cola".
Yet I must confess to harbouring
serious doubts about the authenticity
of this rigorous division of humanity
into literates and illiterates and, in
particular, about using it as a yard¬
stick with which to evaluate people.
Not knowing how to read and
write is natural; all of us come into
the world that way. No one was born
educated. I mean by this that man in
the natural state, at birth, is Illiterate;
but insofar as he is able to learn to
read, he is also potentially literate.
For various reasons which I will
not go into here, society decides to
turn this potential into reality. In other
words, to transform man's innate
capacity to understand letters and
signs into mastery of the art of read¬
ing. This is achieved by means of a
complex process which begins with
a primer and ends goodness knows
where. At the end of these efforts,
referred to as primary education, the
subject is proudly declared to be
literate, a person of superior
distinctionwhich he undoubtedly is.
So far, so good. But the ability
to read is in itself only a potential
state. To know how to read is one
thing, but actually to read is another.
If the newly-literate person does not
exercise his reading skills, what is the
point of learning to read at all?
We now come to the next stage
in this analysis of the true value of
literacy. Let us assume that the poten¬
tial reader takes the next step and
actually becomes a reader. Does this
mean we can say that the objectives
of literacy have been attained? By no
Opposite page, "Innocents
newly saved from the
darkness of illiteracy, from
the dragon of native
ignorance, must be closely
watched."
Right, a page from The
Absurd Alphabet by Walter
Crane (English, late 19th
century).
means, because at this stage a new
scenario unfolds. The Illiterate person
has become literate, the literate
person has become a reader, and the
reader is reading. But what and how
does that person read?
The same question arises again.
Every reader is potentially a good
reader. But will he or will he not
become one? If the answer is yes, we
can say that the aim of literacy has
been achieved: the ability to read
well, in such a way that the word
becomes spirit and texts come to life.
It is clear that the objective of
literacy is rarely fully attained. We
must recognize the existence of those
whom I call the neo-llliterates. These
are people who, although freed from
the hell of total Illiteracy, have not yet
attained the empyrean of reading,
but hover in a limbo somewhere in
between.
I am not referring to those who
cannot read because of a lack of
books or libraries. This kind of prac¬
tical problem Is relatively easy to
solve.... I am thinking rather of those
who can read but do not do so, for
more profound and complex reasons
than the fact that they do not have
a book at hand.
I would suggest that two types
of Illiterates should be recognized.
First, there are the "pure", clas¬
sic, natural illiterates who for some
reason do not know how to read.
Such people may be tragic insofar as
they have the potential to achieve ex¬
cellence but lack the mental stimulus
to realize their potential, which re¬
mains dormant for lack of knowledge
and culture. I feel respect, sympathy
and admiration for this category of
illiterates. In my country, you only
need to stroll awhile In the hills of
Castile or in the olive groves of An¬
dalusia to come across Illiterate peo¬
ple who, when you get to know
them, prove to be as humane, as dig¬
nified in their behaviour and as wise
in their judgement as many people
whose heads are stuffed with
learning.
The other type of Illiterate person
might be described as impure, coun¬
terfeit, the product of modern edu¬
cation and, unwittingly, the
embodiment of its faults. Those who
know how to read, but nevertheless
to all intents and purposes remain
illiterate, I call the neo-illlterates.
This type of "neo-llllteracy" may
be total or partial. Total neo-illlterates
are those who, after learning to read
at school, choose not to use their
reading skills except when they actu¬
ally have to read a letter, scan a
cinema or theatre programme, or
rskcmcU foilotnjthe son i
tke piper,
May h ib principias change
as his years grow riper.
UfoTt^U' t;orth« L*>»icoTr\. keeping
kit ey* on
Tke coveted crown ,aT*a
Its counsel tStLion.
£ot t h» v itto ai»
the Jiink,
The- oliwomanlivtd.on
sat piling to th.wfc !
clin?
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
consult the telephone directory.
Some of them may glance at the
sports pages, thereby enjoying a form
of journalism which is particularly
meritorious since for many people it
provides the only occasion when they
read....
Many of these people are active,
practical andto borrow a fashion¬
able modern term which associates
the mysteries of Greek with those of
engineeringdynamic...
There is also a species of partial
neo-illiterates whose members may
be seen hovering round newspaper
kiosks like bees buzzing round a mag¬
nificent flower, in search of ingre¬
dients with which to make the honey
of their intellectual lives. They never
read books but they are fascinated by
the proliferation of magazines and
the topics they cover. They deserve
sympathy because far from sparing
their efforts as readers, they are prod¬
igal with them. They read voraciously,
poor things, returning home laden
with magazines which they plough
through for hours on end, without
getting much more out of them than
a child playing with a jigsaw puzzle
that he never manages to finish,
never seeing the overall picture in
which everything falls into its rightful
place....
This kind of reader arouses our
compassion. The more he reads, the
further he drifts in this boundless sea
of print, the level of which rises a few
metres every week. The reader of a
book knows where his task begins
and ends; he can relax, take a holi¬
day. A magazine reader, especially if
he is a subscriber, feels pursued as if
by the Furies by these terrible weekly,
bi-weekly or monthly creatures. If
he flags, he will drown in a rising
tide of newsprint. To keep abreast
of the material that pours from the
presses, the reader must make a
titanic effort. A hundred writers
penning articles for a score of maga¬
zines snap at his heels like a pack of
tireless hounds which allow their
quarry no respite....
Several conclusions can be
drawn from this necessarily incom¬
plete portrait gallery of neo-illiteracy.
Firstly, it should never be forgotten
that the word "read" is ambiguous
and so, consequently, are such ex¬
pressions as "learn to read" and
"know how to read". These are com¬
plex expressions which should not be
taken in their most literal, superficial
sense as simply describing the capac¬
ity to understand the most obvious
meaning of the written word. There
is no doubt that the possession of this
simple technique wrests man from his
natural illiteracy and opens up vast
perspectives. But if this aptitude for
expanding the potential of the soul,
for spiritual fulfilment, is not used, he
will find himself in a situation which
Nitu» Leltofspel voor Kinder«) ftl Mounsau Jou lialplubel pour les Enlanli
sounds paradoxical yet is nonetheless
very realthat of an illiterate who
knows how to read. He has been
wrested from pure illiteracy, yet
through disuse or neglect of the
faculty of reading a regressive
mechanism begins to operate which,
sooner or later, will take him back to
his point of departure, or worse-
spiritual illiteracy....
Although this is the harsh truth,
statistics and social convention up¬
hold the fiction that such people
should be counted as literate, and
that they belong to the privileged
group of those who know how to
read. In this, as in much else, the
world does not scruple to accept a
half-truth which it welcomes with
the jubilation which ought to be
accorded to the whole truth, at the
same time feeling vaguely that every¬
one is at once victim and perpetrator
of a confidence trick.
This new group is slowly growing,
and the time has come to name and
confer a status on its members. They
are the neo-illiterates and they are far
more threatening and dangerous
than the pure Illiterates. They do not
lurk In the shadows of ignorance with
the devil nor do they aspire to the
light of divine knowledge. They are
capable of everything yet venture
nothing....
There is a further consequence
of their increasing numbers: we must
abandon our idolatrous and hypnotic
Pages from reading primers: (left)
Franco-Flemish, first half of 19th
century; (above) French, 1940s;
(above right) Russian, second half
of 19th century.
Right, a newsstand in Thailand.
attitude towards the so-called
"problem of illiteracy". Modern
educational policy has a fetish, a
blood-stained deity to which every¬
thing is sacrificed though it guaran¬
tees nothing to its most fervent
worshippers: the struggle against
illiteracy. This phrase, repeated over
and over again in newspapers, maga¬
zines and political rhetoric, strikes
awe into people's hearts....
Some of my readers may feel
indignant at this heretic who has the
temerity to harbour doubts about the
struggle against illiteracy. Yet, if my
argument is, or at least may be, well-
founded, namely that teaching peo¬
ple to read Is not enough, in most
cases, to wrest them from their origi¬
nal spiritual povertyor, as T.S. Eliot
put it, that "only in a very limited
sense can it be said that education
produces culture"it will perhaps be
understood that what I am attempt¬
ing to do is to give to this phrase, this
slogan, this endeavour"the strug¬
gle against illiteracy"a new vigour.
I do not wish to minimize the
tragedy of illiteracy; on the contrary,
I believe that we are faced by two
powerful enemies. One is the long-
familiar, immediately recognizable
enemy on whom our educational big.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
guns are trained; but beside It is
another figure disguised behind the
mask of literacy, deceiving us, making
us believe that it is not a problem,
that it is one of us, one of the workers
in the city of the mind, when in reality
it is the fifth column of total illiteracy,
the sworn enemy, through inert
opposition, of the word become
spirit.
It is of course praiseworthy that
thousands upon thousands of chil¬
dren are today snatched from the
jaws of illiteracy by primary educa¬
tion. But these innocents, newly
saved from the darkness of illiteracy,
from the dragon of native ignorance,
must be closely watched. A terrible
surprise lies in wait. These infants
start out in life armed only with basic
reading and writing skills, confident
in the belief that they have already
conquered their native ignorance,
only to encounter a much more for¬
midable adversary around the next
corner.
This new Circe lures them to her
and turns them into lesser beings,
neo-illlterates who will live content¬
edly in the snug confines of unaware-
ness, with all the material advantages
of the modern world yet sentenced
for life to another form of
ignorancesurfeited, not with the
acorns of Homer's noble oak, but
with the synthetic sustenance that is
the ultimate miracle of progress.
PEDRO SALINAS
(1891-1951),
poet, scholar, dramatist and
essayist, was an outstanding
member of the group of
Spanish writers known as the
"Generation of 1927". He
emigrated to the United States
on the outbreak of the Spanish
Civil War and taught at
Weilesley College, Mass., and
Johns Hopkins University,
Baltimore. A selection of his
love poems in English
translation, To Live in
Pronouns, was published in
1974. This article has been
extracted from his essay "The
new illiterates", first published
in Revista de América (No. 4,
Bogota, April 1945).
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
It seemed like a dream come true.
Two chemists had come up with a
cheap, simple, clean and virtually in-
. exhaustible source of energy. If it had
been true, and could have been
made to work, it would have solved
the energy problems of humankind
for far into the future.
But science does not usually yield
such easy solutions, and this case was
no exception. It is fairly certain now
that the so-called "cold fusion"
phenomenon was not the break¬
through it was initially claimed to be.
No one is yet certain what the
phenomenon ¡s or even if there is a
phenomenon at all, but the events
that have surrounded it since last year
hold many lessons for those who
practice science.
Martin Fleischmann of
Southampton University and Stanley
Pons of the University of Utah, both
respected scientists in the field of
electrochemistry, announced on 23
March 1989 that they had achieved
nuclear fusion in an electrolytic cell.
They had filled the cell, similar to a
glass beaker, with a solution made
from heavy water, in which the
hydrogen in the water molecules is
a rare form known as deuterium.
They immersed In this solution two
Cold fusion-
a storm
in a
test-tube?
By Dan Clery
electrodes, one of platinum and one
of a metal called palladium. They
passed an electric current through
the solution by connecting the elec¬
trodes to a battery. After some time
they found that a large amount of
heat was being produced in the cell,
much more than that generated by
the power of the battery.
Their explanation was simple:
passing an electric current through
the solution freed the deuterium
from the heavy water molecules and
it was then absorbed into the palladi¬
um electrode. Once inside the elec¬
trode, they claimed, deuterium atoms
fused together to form larger atoms
of helium and released energy in the
process. This nuclear reaction is the
same process as that which fuels the
sun and other stars as well as provid¬
ing the destructive power of the
hydrogen bomb.
It was ¡n the 1920s and 1930s,
when scientists were probing the
atomic nucleus and piecing together
its structure, that they realized that
reactions between nuclei could
release large amounts of energy.
Nuclear fission is the reaction where
a large heavy nucleus splits apart into
two or more fragments. A working
fission reactor was first demonstrated
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
in 1 942, and in 1 945 fission was put
to lethal use over Hiroshima and
Nagasaki.
Nuclear fusion is the binding
together of small light nuclei and is
the basis of the devastating hydrogen
bombs developed in the 1950s.
Scientists have been trying for the last
thirty years to harness nuclear fusion
as a peaceful source of energy, but
the methods they have been using are
still probably decades away from suc¬
cess. Fusion has certain advantages
over fission as a source of energy: it
produces little in the way of radio¬
active waste and its fuel is deuterium
and another heavy form of hydrogen
known as tritium, both of which can
be extracted in great abundance from
seawater.
The problem in achieving fusion
is getting the nuclei close enough
together for them to fuse. Nuclei are
composed of protons, sub-atomic
particles which have a positive elec¬
tric charge, and neutrons, which are
neutral. Nuclei thus have a net posi¬
tive charge and, like similar poles of
a magnet, two positive nuclei will
repel each other. This repulsion,
known as the Coulomb barrier, is very
strong, and scientists have tried to
overcome it using huge fusion reac¬
tors about the size of an office block.
There are a number of such reac¬
tors in the United States, the Soviet
Union, Europe and Japan. They are
used to heat up a plasma, a charged
gas, of deuterium and tritium to enor¬
mous pressures and temperatures,
comparable to conditions in the in¬
terior of the sun, and they confine the
plasma with strong magnetic fields.
Under these conditions, nuclei collide
together with such force that fusion
reactions do take place, but in cur¬
rent machines the amount of ener¬
gy put in to create the reaction ¡s
greater than the energy prod.uced by
the fusion so they are not yet feasi¬
ble as sources of energy. There are
a number of alternative methods
such as bombarding small pellets of
fusion material with powerful laser or
particle beams to produce brief bursts
of energy.
Opposite,
electrolytic cell of the
kind used in cold
fusion experiments.
Considering all the time, effort
and money that has been put into
pursuing traditional "hot" fusion
research, it is not surprising that there
was some disbelief when Fleisch¬
mann and Pons announced their
breakthrough with cold fusion in
something akin to a test-tube. Much
of the disbelief was reserved for the
method the discoverers chose to
announce their discovery. Scientific
advances are usually announced by
submitting a paper to a specialist
journal or conference. Before publi¬
cation or presentation to the confer¬
ence, the paper is refereed by other
experts In the field and often changes
are made to ¡t as a result of their
comments. First reports of cold fusion
appeared ¡n London's Financial Times
and New York's Wall Street Journal.
The same day Fleischmann and Pons
held a press conference at the Univer¬
sity of Utah and that evening cold
fusion was on the national television
news.
The search for signs
of fusion
The two Utah chemists were not
the only people who were ex¬
perimenting with cold fusion. Just 75
kilometres from the University of
Utah at Brigham Young University,
Steven Jones, a physicist, had been
working for years on exotic ways of
achieving nuclear fusion. He had de¬
tected signs of fusion in electrolytic
cells similar to those of Fleischmann
and Pons. The two research teams
were aware of each other's work and
had agreed to submit their results
simultaneously to the British journal
Nature on 24 March. When Jones
heard about the press conference at
Utah University on 23 March he went
ahead and sent his results to Nature
only to discover that Fleischmann and
Pons had submitted a paper to
another publication, the Journal of
Electroanalytical Chemistry, on 11
March. The two chemists then went
on to submit a paper to Nature but
when asked to make some altera¬
tions they said they were too busy
with new work and withdrew their
paper.
After publication of a scientific
breakthrough, it is common practice
for other researchers in the same field
to repeat the experiment to confirm
or refute it. Dozens of teams around
the world tried to do so after hearing
the press reports about cold fusion
but they were hampered by lack of
information. Even when Fleischmann
and Pons's paper was published a
couple of weeks after the announce¬
ment, the technical detail was scarce.
The most obvious way to identify
that fusion is occurring is the detec¬
tion of heat. But this is not a simple
matter in an electrolytic cell where
there are many other factors affect¬
ing the heat content of the cell. Other
possible by-products of a fusion reac¬
tion include neutrons, gamma rays
and tritium. Detection of one or more
of these would be strong evidence.
Fleischmann and Pons claimed to
have detected in their original experi¬
ment large amounts of excess heat
as well as gamma rays and neutrons,
but gamma rays can be produced
naturally by rocks, and some neutron
detectors are notoriously inaccurate.
In the weeks that followed the an¬
nouncement, research teams around
the world declared that they had
found heat, or one of the by¬
products, ora combination, but many
found nothing. One of the main dis¬
crepancies in the chemists' claim was
that for the amount of heat they
observed, the number of neutrons
detected was far too low.
Meanwhile, on 26 April, Fleisch¬
mann and Pons appeared before the
Science, Space and Technology Com¬
mittee of the US House of Represen¬
tatives to explain their work. They
requested $25-40 million to set up a
cold fusion institute at the Universi¬
ty of Utah. Their request was refused
but a centre was set up in August
with money from the state of Utah.
Government interest was such that
the Department of Energy set up an
expert panel to investigate the
matter.
The debate among scientists
continued to rage. At a meeting of
the American Electrochemical Socie¬
ty in Texas in early April, Fleischmann
and Pons were hailed as heroes. By
the time of the American Physical So¬
ciety Meeting at the beginning of
May, however, there had been a
growing number of negative ex¬
perimental results. The consensus at a
specially convened meeting at Santa
Fe in late May was ambiguous, with
virtually equal numbers of results for
and against.
The number of unfavourable ex¬
perimental results continued to grow
during the course of the year. On 12
November the Department of Ener¬
gy panel published its report and its
conclusions were unequivocal: "the
experimental results... reported to
date do not represent convincing evi¬
dence that useful sources of energy
will result from the phenomena at¬
tributed to cold fusion... No special
programmes to establish cold fusion
research centres... are justified".
One year after the original press
conference at the University of Utah,
cold fusion still refused to lie down
and die. The new National Cold Fu¬
sion Center in Utah held its first an¬
nual conference and dozens of
papers were presented in support of
the phenomenon. Many reputable
research groups around the world
were still claiming to have detected
one or more of the key signs of cold
fusion. But just one week before the
conference, Nature published a paper
by scientists from the University of
Utah who monitored Fleischmann
and Pons' own electrochemical cells
for five weeks and found no trace of
any unusual nuclear radiation.
The negative paper ¡n Nature has
in some sense polarized the debate.
Some see it as the final nail in the
coffin of cold fusion, while believers
see it as strong evidence that a
strange, unknown type of fusion is
occurring since the production of
heat in the cells cannot be denied. It
seems possible that an interesting
phenomenon is at work, just not the
kind that will solve all the world's
problems.
It could be said of the events sur¬
rounding cold fusion that the scien¬
tific establishment seemed actively to
try to discredit the breakthrough just
because it was so revolutionary. But
the success of the recently discovered
high-temperature superconductors
shows that revolutionary science can
gain recognition. It has also been said
that the cold fusion story gave the
outside world a glimpse of how the
world of science works. In reality, it
gave a very distorted ¡mage of
science: science under extreme stress,
trying to come to terms with some¬
thing that is new and unexplained.
What the world did see was an ex¬
ample of science that was not some
form of miracle cure, nor an ominous
threat to humankind. It was simply
wrong, and with that somehow more
human.
DAN CLERY
¡s a British journalist
specializing In the
popularization of science.
c E
MHH
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
DE
48
"espite the billions of dollars that
are spent on science, much of the
best scientific information and under¬
standing is not getting through to key
decision-makers in government and
business.
To a large extent this is because
government, science and business are
three separate worlds, each with its
own language, cultural norms and
motivations. They are organized
differently and frequently fail to
recognize when there is a need to
work in co-operation. Even when
they do recognize such a need, they
are often unable to communicate.
Furthermore, while relatively lit¬
tle science gets through to business
and government decision-makers,
what does get through is not neces¬
sarily good science. The science that
crosses the barriers Into the worlds
of business and government often
does so only because it is noisy, dra¬
matic or threatening and receives
sensational media coverage.
The International Federation of
Institutes for Advanced Study (IFIAS),
an international association of lead¬
ing independent research institutions,
exists to bring the best science to
decision-makers in government and
business at the national but especially
at the international levels. To do this
effectively, it focuses on a limited
number of selected global issues, and
develops international scientific
research programmes around them.
The dissemination process is carried
out through symposia, seminars and
workshops attended by research
scholars and corporate and govern¬
mental decision-makers, and through
IFIAS publications.
Originally established in 1972 in
Stockholm (Sweden), where it still has
premises, IFIAS today has its interna¬
tional headquarters and secretariat
in Toronto, Canada, and a project
development office at Maastricht,
the Netherlands. IFIAS research
programmes are developed and car¬
ried out through a network of 43
research institutes from 27 countries
which constitute the core of the Fed¬
eration. Their participation in IFIAS ac¬
tivities mobilizes individuals from a
wide range of disciplines and from
many nations in a research effort
which is neither bureaucratic nor
politicized.
In addition to the scientific exper-
YÍ f*
Computer simulation of the seasonal changes in a fruit tree.
The technique makes it possible to visualize plant growth processes.
Science for
decision-makers
THE INTERNATIONAL FEDERATION OF
INSTITUTES FOR ADVANCED STUDY
tise of its member institutes through¬
out the world, IFIAS is supported by
corporate affiliates which contribute
to the development and execution
of its research programmes and help
to bring the results of these
programmes to the attention of the
business community.
The hallmark of IFIAS pro¬
grammes is that they are multi-
disciplinary in character and global in
reach, and seek to be policy relevant.
Efforts are concentrated on issues
which have yet to be comprehensive¬
ly addressed by other organizations.
IFIAS activities are currently
focused on three programmes:
Human Dimensions of Global
Change, Coastal Resources Manage¬
ment, and the International Diffusion
of Biotechnology.
The Human Dimensions of Global
Change Programme (HDGCP) was
launched in 1 987 as a joint initiative
International co-operation is founded on a network of daily
contacts, exchanges and initiatives which create bonds of
solidarity between men and women all over the world. In
addition to the intergovernmental agencies of the United
Nations system, hundreds of non-governmental organizations
(NGOs) today form part of this network. These organizations
exist thanks to the dedication of people with similar professional
interests or common aims who wish to share their experience
and combine their efforts. Our regular feature "Forum" gives
them an opportunity to talk about their activities.
of IFIAS, the International Social
Science Council (ISSC), the United
Nations University (UNU) and Unesco.
Its purpose is to create a network for
research which will bring the resources
of the social sciences and the exper¬
tise derived from the management of
human activities to bear on the anal¬
ysis and understanding of change ¡n
the global environment.
The earth's coastal regions host
much of the world's population and
a large proportion of global economic
activities. Pressures resulting from
continued population growth and an
intensification of economic activities
have increased user-conflicts and en¬
vironmental damage along many of
the world's coastlines. Efforts to
manage coastal zones are usually car¬
ried out in a piecemeal way by differ¬
ent agencies responsible for separate
activities in each area, thus failing to
take into account the complete pic¬
ture of local resources. IFIAS's Coastal
Resources Management Programme
attempts to develop a more integrat¬
ed approach.
New ecological problems have
led to a rethinking of the human role
in transforming the environment and
the need for alternative development
strategies. Biotechnology has the
potential to transform economic sys¬
tems and provide a wide range of
benefits, but it could lead to social,
economic and environmental
problems. IFIAS's International Diffu¬
sion of Biotechnology Programme
grew out of an earlier IFIAS
programme on science and technol¬
ogy in global economic change. The
aim of the programme is to help un¬
derstand knowledge and techniques
relating to biotechnology so that de¬
veloping countries can formulate poli¬
cies that will encourage sustainable
development and ensure that the im¬
minent "biotechnological revolution"
proves as beneficial as possible. A
network of research teams has been
established which involves research¬
ers from both developed and de¬
veloping countries.
IFIAS
c/o Royal Society of Canada
P.O. Box 9734
Ottawa, Ontario
K1G 5J4 Canada
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
Why not an Esperanto
Courier!
Esperanto is a language which is
needed for basic international com¬
munication in our shrinking world
and could be widely used if further
promoted. I would take out a second
subscription to the Courier if an
Esperanto edition were available, and
so might others.
E.M. Wardle
Seaford (United Kingdom)
Many people would like the oppor¬
tunity to read your magazine in
Esperanto. There are Esperanto
speakers in overa hundred countries.
Madame Henri Normand
Tourène (France)
By publishing an Esperanto edition
you would doubtless lose some sub¬
scribers to other language editions,
but you would certainly gain many
more. Esperanto speakers are more
receptive than most people to your
"window on the world". They are
used to dialogue.
A. Legros
Bondy (France)
Smokeless zone
As an enthusiastic stamp collector, I
am pleased to see postage stamps
reproduced on the letters page of
the Courier. But in my capacity as
spokesman for the Danish anti-
tobacco association Landsforeningen
R0GFRIT MIU0, 1 can only deplore
your choice of a stamp depicting a
Danish actress of the 1930s, who In
any case is virtually forgotten today,
smoking a cigarette. Our association
recently wrote to the Danish Minister
of Communications and to the direc¬
tor general of the Post Office to pro¬
test against the use of motifs
associated with smoking and the fact
that no anti-tobacco stamp has yet
been issued in Denmark. Through the
European Non-smokers Union, we
intend to propose a motion calling for
the regular issue of anti-tobacco
stamps at the next European Con¬
ference of Postal and Telecommuni¬
cations Administrations.
Please note that my name ¡s spel¬
led Rojfri, not Rogfri as in the name
of the association to which I belong,
although both words mean "smoke¬
less" in Danish.
Rojfri Andersen
Aalborg (Denmark)
The stamp will be replaced in the next
issue. If you send us an anti-tobacco
stamp, we shall be pleased to reproduce
it on our Letters page. Editor
Return to inner space
I was very interested in the article on
"Creatures from inner space" in your
October 1989 Issue, but I don't agree
with some of the points that were
made. The importance of Star Wars
was not sufficiently emphasized. This
was a watershed in the history of
science fiction movies and it put an
end to the fact that, for decades,
such movies had lagged way behind
written sci-fi. I agree with Claude
Aziza's view that it "rekindled
childhood dreams and revived medie¬
val legends" (as in the search for the
Princess), but the basic theme of the
film seems to be the eternal struggle
between good and evil (¡n this case,
the Galactic Empire versus the rebels).
Also, was E.T. really Spielberg's
version of the New Testament? The
comparison made between the
immortality of Christ and that of E.T.
is understandable, but perhaps
"rekindling childhood dreams" is
more appropriate to this film.
The worlds visited by Flash Gor¬
don and Buck Rogers in the old black
and white serials may have been
"very like the real world", but in the
1 980 movie version of Flash Gordon
(not mentioned in the article), of all
the planets visited by the hero, few
could be compared to anything in the
real world.
An important film of the late
1 980s, Alien Nation, also not men¬
tioned in the article, was subse¬
quently made into a television series
which is now showing in the United
States. It deals with the issue of inte¬
gration and the racism brought about
when E.T. s land on Earth-
reminiscent of today's intolerant
world.
Finally, perhaps a link should be
drawn between the development of
E.T. movies with developments in the
conquest of space. Perhaps new
angles and Ideas will emerge from
science fiction as the race for the first
manned mission to Mars begins.
Jonathan Fenton-Fischer
London
The changing values
of civilizations
Robert Bonnaud's article "A new
model for a universal history: world
rhythms", in your April 1990 issue,
inspires me to make a few com¬
ments. Yes, there is such a thing as
a universal history. Yes, there are fac¬
tors common to the histories of dif¬
ferent peoples. These should not be
sought in synchronisms or universal
turning-points, as all peoples do not
advance at the same speed. Nor
should they be sought in specific
rhythms, for history sometimes leaps
forward, sometimes it is static, and
sometimes it regresses. These univer¬
sal constants are to be found in the
driving force of civilizations: their
values....
The oldest of these values grew
out of the family groupthe genetic
bond of the tribe to their great mythi¬
cal ancestor. This is how ancestor
cults came into being, as did the fer¬
tility cults derived from them and
based on the mother goddess, the
bull or the serpent.
After the tribe, the cultural
extension of the family, the city-state
developed, centred on the temple.
The great ancestor gave way to the
fertility god, represented on Earth by
the priest-king and the priestly élite.
The Hebrews sacrificed bulls to
Yahweh and, by circumcising baby
boys, symbolically offered their god
the virility of the male. The king had
to be of divine origin.
The warrior-figure succeeded
that of the priest. The gods also
became warriors. The serpent gave
way to the eagle, symbolized in myth
as a struggle against the dragon. Just
as the Bible transformed the bull into
the "golden calf", the warrior-figure
turned the serpent, born of the Earth
and of the forces of Nature, into a
hideous and fearsome monster which
would be laid low by the hero. The
minotaur of Greek myth was thus
defeated by the bravery of one man.
This spirit of the great empires of
Antiquity persisted until recently.
Today's major wars are econo¬
mic. Work and money are the predo¬
minant values of Western societies.
The banker of the Middle Ages,
although already very powerful, was
dependent on the warrior. Now ¡t is
the other way round....
The states whose cohesiveness is
currently based on religious values
call on their traditional values as a
source of strength. There is good
reason to fear that this harking back
to the past, which cuts them off
from a changing world, may lead to
a full-scale recurrence of warlike
urges....
As the values of civilization
evolve, the social structures which
cultivate them become more com¬
plex: from the family to the tribe,
from the tribe to the city-state, from
the city-state to the state. The future
value of civilization must be capable
of transcending the structure of the
state, of uniting all states. The Unesco
Courier stands for this value.
Jean-Marie Lang
Metz (France) 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50
LITERACY LESSONS
On the occasion of International Liter¬
acy Year, the International Bureau of
Education (IBE) has prepared a series
of 40 brochures entitled Literacy
Lessons. Written by specialists from
all over the world, the brochures take
stock of current knowledge and ex¬
perience in the field of literacy and
post-literacy work.
The booklets, grouped together
in a box, are available in English and
in French. A Spanish version is being
prepared.
To order a set, please send a
cheque or money order for the
equivalent of US $10, made out to
the Unesco Special Account for
World Literacy, to either:
The International Literacy Year
Secretariat, ED/PBL, Unesco,
7 place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris, France.
or
International Bureau of Education,
P.O. Box 199,
1211 Geneva 20, Switzerland.
Please specify which language version
you require.
A TIME FOR LEARNING
Right, two pictures from a Unesco
travelling exhibition entitled 7990,
International Literacy Year. *
The exhibition consists of a
boxed set of 17 black and white
large-format (30 x 40 cm) photo¬
graphs which illustrate reading, writ¬
ing and learning situations in many
countries. An introductory text and
captions suitable for display are
provided in French, Spanish or English
versions to accompany the pictures.
ILY NEWS
The latest issue (No. 1, 1990) of The
Challenge: ILY News,* a 16-page
illustrated magazine containing
literacy-related news and features,
has just been published (¡n English,
French, Spanish and Arabic versions)
by Unesco's International Literacy
Year Secretariat. Contents include
reports on the World Conference on
Education for All (Jomtlen, Thailand,
March 1990); Kottayam, India's first
illiteracy-free town; articles on literacy
and survival, and women and literacy;
and updates on ILY activities around
the world.
*Copies of the magazine and of the exhibition
are available free of charge from the International
Literacy Year Secretariat, Unesco, 7 place de
Fontenoy. 75700 Pans Please specify which lan¬
guage version you require.
UNESCO
AND
INTERNATIONAL
LITERACY YEAR
HOW YOU CAN HELP
If you wish to assist literacy efforts
in developing countries, Unesco
provides two channels: its Special
Account for World Literacy and its
Co-Action Programme.
The Special Account supports a
wide variety of literacy-related activi¬
ties in all parts of the world. Volun¬
tary contributions finance operations
such as the purchase of paper and
printing material, reading books, text¬
books, pencils, blackboards and other
supplies. They also finance research,
media programmes, the training of
specialists, and the organization of
seminars and study courses. Dona¬
tions to the "Special Account for
World Literacy", may be addressed
to the Education Sector, Unesco, 7
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
If you would like to contribute to
the Unesco Co-Action Programme,
which enables donations to be chan¬
nelled to specific projects in some 20
countries', a catalogue of literacy'and
post-literacy projects aided by the
Programme can be obtained from
The Unesco Co-Action Programme,
BAO/CSF, Unesco (address as above).
RURAL WOMEN
AGAINST ILLITERACY
For some 500 million women who
live in rural areas of the Third World,
life is an unending struggle for sur¬
vival. From morning to night they
work in the fields, transport water
and fuelwood, prepare meals and
take care of their families. The lives
of these women and their attempts
to achieve literacy skills and escape
from poverty, exclusion and silence
are portrayed in a forthcoming book
entitled Inside the Third World: Rural
Women Against Illiteracy, which
will be published by Unesco in Sep¬
tember 1990. The author, Krystyna
Chlebowska, is a Unesco specialist in
the education of women and girls.
English and French versions of the
book can be ordered from the
Unesco Press Sales Division, 7 place
de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. A Spanish
translation will be published later.
HISTORY OF WRITING
EXHIBITION FOR ILY
To mark International Literacy Year,
the European Centre of Educational
Alliances has organized a chronolog¬
ical exhibition on the history of writ¬
ing, from the cryptogram to the
computer. It will be shown at the
International Bureau of Education in
Geneva from 3 to 9 September 1990,
and at Unesco headquarters in Paris
from 24 September to 5 October.
A wide range of ancient bas-
reliefs, both originals and reproduc¬
tions, parchments, books, sculptures,
photographs, prints and paintings will
be displayed. Puppets from all over the
world, each symbolizing a letter of the
alphabet, will illustrate what writing
means to each of the cultures repre¬
sented"freedom" for some, "light"
or "communication" for others.
Painters, sculptors, writers and
musicians wishing to contribute on the
theme "Writing and the artist today"
are invited to contact the European
Centre of Educational Alliances, 34
rue Marius Aufan, 92300 Levallols-
Perret, France; Tel: 47 58 07 45.
Acknowledgements
Cover, page 3 (left): © Zabelle Côté,
Montreal. Back cover, page 14
(right): © Christophe Kuhn, Paris.
Page 2: © Simone, Éelgium. Pages 3
(right), 5 (left): A. Kourbatov
© APN, Moscow. Page 5 (right):
© A. Goryainov, Moscow. Page 6
(left): illustration by Jean Alessandrini
© Gallimard, Paris; (right):
illustration by Michel Simeon © Livre
de Poche, Paris. Page 7: © Reunion
des Musées Nationaux, Pans. Musée
des Beaux-Arts, Dijon/ADAGP 1990,
Paris. Page 8: © Isabelle Simon, Paris.
Page 10: Chrismar ©Fotogram-Stone
International, Paris. Page 11 (above):
©Jörgen Schytte, Copenhagen;
(below left): © Edimedia, Paris;
(below right): Michel
Claude/Unesco. Page 12 (above):
© Literacy Section, Social Welfare
Commission, Jamaica; (below):
© Asian Cultural Centre for Unesco
(ACCU), Tokyo. Page 13: © Charles
Carné, Paris. Pages 14 (left), 18, 19:
All Rights Reserved. Page 15 (left):
G. Boutin © Explorer, Paris. Pages
15 (right), 28-29 (centre), 34, 45
(below): © Ron Giling, Arnhem,
Netherlands. Pages 16-17: ©Roger
Carressa (AFIAP), Toulon, France.
Page 20 (above): Giry © Réa, Paris;
(below): © Anne Périé, La Garenne-
Colombes, France. Page 21: ©Carlos
Freiré, Paris. Page 22 (below left):
© Traditions for Tomorrow. Page 24:
illustration by Mikki Rain/UNFPA,
New York. Pages 25, 38: © Krystyna
Chlebowska, Paris. Page 26:
Herzog/Unesco. Page 27: Henri
Cartier-Bresson © Magnum, Paris.
Page 28 (left): © Monique Piétri,
Paris. Page 29 (right): Patrick
Broquet © Explorer, Paris. Page 30:
© Lumière, Paris. Page 31: Michael
Barnett/Science Photo Library
© Cosmos, Paris. Page 32 (left): F.
Jalain © Explorer, Paris; (above &
below right): © 1977 Carol Morris Si
Ruth Lesirge, Macmillan Education
Ltd., London and Basingstoke. Page
33: Lawrence Manning © Cosmos,
Paris. Page 35: Gaillard © Jerrican,
Paris. Page 36 (above): © Explorer
Archives/Newberry Library, Chicago;
(centre & below): © Explorer
Archives. Page 37: E. David
Robinson/Unesco. Page 39: J.P.
Daudier ©Jerrican, Paris. Page 40: V.
Clement ©Jerrican, Paris. Pages 42,
44, 45 (above): ©J.L. Charmet, Paris.
Private Collection. Page 43: ©J.L.
Charmet, Paris. Bibliothèque des Arts
Décoratifs, Paris. Page 46: University
of Utah, Salt Lake City © Picture-
Group Réa, Paris. Page 48: C. Weiss
© Réa, Paris. CIRAD/CNUSC. Page
50 (above): Dominique
Roger/Unesco; (below): Eric
Schwab/Unesco.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Unesco
^courier
published monthly in 34 languages and ¡n braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Russian edition: Georgi Zelenin
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel.: 45.68 46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Moura Chatta
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic1 (Belgrade)
Chinese: Sher Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88),
Assistant: Marie-Noèlle Branet (45.68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakite, Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk. Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65),
Mail: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 68 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
individual articles and photograpis not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Couner staff. The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the Urited Nations. The Unesco Courier is
produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc . 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A ; (4) Bell and
Howell Co., Old Mansf-eld Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) DEPOT LEGAL : C1 - JUILLET 1990.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP
Photocomposition The Unesco Courier
Photogravure-impression: Maury imprimeur S.A., Z.l. route d'Etampes,
45330 Malesherbes.
Y :y <:>y:
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 7- 1990 -OPI 90 -3 482 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page advertising insert
between pages 10-11 and 42-43
Will the benefits of the Green Revolution of the 1960s and progress in
food production meet the needs of the world population at the end of
this century?
Will the "biotechnological revolution" offer a solution to world food
problems?
How can agricultural development and self-sufficiency be attained,
particularly in developing countries?
Feeding Tomorrow's World
By Albert Sasson is an attempt to answer these and related questions
through a pluridisciplinary approach to human nutrition and food
production. The book, addressed to a wide readership, provides a
remarkable synthesis of the scientific, economic, socio-economic and
environmental aspects of nutrition throughout the world.
Feeding Tomorrow's World (Sextant series, 3)
1990, 805 pages, ISBN 92-3-102083-8, FF225.00; US$53.00; C$56. 50; £34.00
Co-published by Unesco and the Technical Centre for Agriculture and Rural Co-operation (CTA),
'De Rietkampen", Galvanistraat 9, 6716 AE Ede, The Netherlands. Worldwide sales rights: Unesco.
Orders may either be sent direct with payment enclosed to the Unesco Press, Sales Division,
7 place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, France;
or via the national distributor(s) of Unesco publications in your country.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
m %k£\
t Z < I iv\*
H9Ê
Ï. 4.
S
.
? fe
j-* <
*
í
w"
>.i^
558
vt
^/! «H
vY'-'Y
M a
6 !
8 '4 s\
k
J
]]>
</page>
</document>
