<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="086687eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
_l
encounters
We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
TIBET
1990, cloth on canvas
(132 cm x 182 cm)
by Françoise Zavaroni
"The Judaeo-Christian
symbol of the apple is
here formed out of a
two-way rendering, in
Tibetan script, of the
word TIBET," writes the
creator of this tapestry,
Françoise Zavaroni, a
regular reader of the
Unesco Courier.
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
SEPTEMBER 1990
N N
Today there are no more
unexplored continents-
unknown seas or mysterious
islands. But while we can
overcome the physical
barriers to exploration, the
barriers of mutual ignorance
between different peoples
and cultures have in many
cases still not been
dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can
voyage to the ends of the
earth. But a different kind
of Odyssey now beckonsan
exploration of the world's
many cultural landscapes, the
ways of life of its different
peoples and their outlook on
the world in which they live.
It is such an Odyssey that
the Unesco Courier proposes
to its readers. Each month
contributors of different
nationalities provide from
different cultural and
professional standpoints an
authoritative treatment of a
theme of universal interest.
The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes is respect
for human dignity.
11
THE MEDIA
WAYS TO FREEDOM
THE CONSCIENCE OF THE JOURNALIST
by Jean Lacouture
EASTERN EUROPE
TURNING A NEW PAGE
by Karol Jakubowicz
MEDIA EMPIRES:
A NECESSARY EVIL?
by Joseph Fitchett
12
THE PROTECTION OF SOURCES
by Patricia Wilhelm 16
PRIVATE LIFE AND THE PUBLIC EYE
by Jonathan Fenby 20
SENEGAL
THE PRICE OF A FREE PRESS
by Babacar Touré 24
THE PHILIPPINES
BETWEEN FREEDOM AND ANARCHY 27
USSR: THE THAW
CHERNOBYL BEFORE AND AFTER
by Vassil Plioutch 32
THE BURDEN OF FEAR
by Vitali Korotich 33
'WE LOOK INTO THE FUTURE
WITH APPREHENSION AND HOPE'
by Ivan T. Frolov 33
34
UNESCO AND FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION
by Morten Giersmg 37
4
Interview with
GRO HARLEM
BRUNDTLAND
43
IN BRIEF.. 43
DOCUMENT
A cultural battle
by Mario Vargas ¡Josa 44
SCIENCE
Rethinking scientific progress
by Marc Chapdclaine
and Jacques Richardson 46
HERITAGE
A village in the hills
by Edouard Badby 49
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR 50
38
Cover:
Photo P. Robert © Sygma.
Back cover:
Photo R. Bossu © Sygma.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
N T E R V I E W
Gro Harlem Brundtland
Gro Harlem Brundtland, former prime
minister of Norway, is internationally
known as a dedicated champion of
environmental quality. In 1983 she
was invited to chair the World
Commission on Environment and
Development set up by the United
Nations. The Commission's report,
Our Common Future, was recognized
as a document of major importance
when it appeared in 1987.
Here Ms. Brundtland talks frankly
about her approach to current
environmental issues.
Your name is linked with the concept of sustainable ation to leave the future to its successors, who when the
development. How would you define this concept? time came would be able to assume their own destiny, find
It is the central idea in the analysis contained in Our their own solutions, use new natural resources, develop
Common Future, the report produced for the United Nations different technologies and skills, enable life to go on, and
by the independent World Commission on Environment perhaps even improve the human condition. But in our cen-
and Development of which I was the chairman. tury massive population growth has led to increased exploi-
We defined sustainable development as a system of tation of natural resources. Furthermore, it has caused
development that meets the needs of the present without pollution on such a scale that the Earth's atmosphere is being
compromising the ability of future generations to meet their affected to the detriment of our common future. It is now
own needs. We then asked what exactly are the needs of that we must take the decisions that will enable people to
the present and gave our answers in different chapters of live through the twenty-first century. The challenge for our
the report. We made an integrated analysis which incor- generation stems from two specific dangers, the nuclear arms
porates all the different aspects of human life and is rooted race and the threat of pollutiontwo bombs: the nuclear
in an awareness of interdependence between nations. bomb and the bomb resulting from our own pollution.
What is fundamentally at stake is the question of human
rightsnot only those of people today but also those of their What can be done about these two dangers?
children and grandchildren. Since our children and grand- The nation state is not an adequate institution for taking
children cannot take care of their own destiny we must do responsible policy decisions in this sphere. We need an inter-
so on their behalf. In the past it was possible for each gener- national framework within which to take decisions on behalf
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
of ourselves and our children. The nation state has had its
day as the decisive body in world affairs. This is how I see
the situation. Once people lived in separate warring tribal
communities. Then they gradually realized that they needed
a system for assuming common responsibility and taking
political decisions within national borders. The new factor
today is that the nation state is no longer enough. Some tradi¬
tional national authority must be surrendered. This does not
mean undermining our ability as peoples of different nations
to have a considerable influence on our own future; it means
pooling some of that authority so that we can responsibly
take tare of common problems that individual nation states
cannot take care of if they are acting alone.
How can this be done? Some agreements that have
already been made regarding the environment are steps in
this direction. One building block for an international
system of law is that relating to the use of chlorofluoro-
carbons (CFCs), the man-made chemicals that are believed
to be destroying the Earth's ozone layer. Many nations have
agreed on the Montreal protocol, which aims to reduce and
eventually eliminate the use of these chemicals.
But the atmosphere is not only threatened by CFCs;
...there are two specific dangers, the
nuclear arms race and the threat of
pollution. Two bombs: the nuclear
bomb and the bomb resulting from
our own pollution.
it is also threatened by the combustion of fossil fuels and
the intensive use of non-renewable energy sources. At the
same time the developing world will need increasing
amounts of energy to provide for its economic and social
development. This means that energy will have to be saved
in the industrially developed countries. Agreements will have
to be negotiated on the gradual reduction of the energy input
in manufacturing and the service industries. This can be done
by using new technologies and energy-saving techniques.
In many countries 50 per cent of current energy con¬
sumption could be economized, not by reducing economic
growth but by reducing the energy content of that growth.
We must aim for a type of economic growth which uses
less energy and natural resources. And this can only be done
by agreement. There must be sufficient information and
pressure from public opinion so that nations will get together
and take decisions on this issue.
The Brandt Commission imagined processes of this kind
in relation to a new economic equilibrium between North
and South. Its proposals did not lead to important concrete
results. Do you think the world has become more mature
since then?
Yes I do. Not even the most unrealistic optimist today
believes that we can go on polluting the air we have to
breathe. We cannot just turn our backs on the problem of
pollution and hope it will go away. The optimistic indus¬
trialist who once refused to believe that there were any
problems involved in the use of nuclear energy will never
be able to convince people that we can go on using more
and more energy and polluting the atmosphere.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
But even if this hypothetical industrialist accepts that the
future ofhumanity should be taken into account, won't he
say "my job is to make profits"?
That's right. That is why the necessary political decisions
have to be made by governments, not private industrialists.
The market needs political direction. And governments are
dependent on public opinion. If the argument for the future
of humanity is convincing enough governments are bound
to listen to it. In a sense there is no real choice; it's a ques¬
tion of how quickly and how broadly we tackle the problem.
I have met no political leader who believes that we can con¬
tinue "business as usual".
In March 1989 twenty-four government leaders attended
a conference on the global atmosphere held at The Hague.
The participants signed a declaration accepting common
responsibility for our common future with regard to the
atmosphere. The declaration said that changes in policies
should be made through international co-operation and
binding agreements, and that the rich countries should be
willing to pay some of the costs of enabling the poorer coun¬
tries to use new, cleaner technology and to avoid going
through a period of using dirty technology such as the rich
countries have known. If the developing countries are to
reach agreement with the rich countries which have been
polluting for fifty years, then the latter must give them some
of the money and technology they need to avoid causing
pollution and to provide for their future economic and social
development.
It's a joint responsibility, and agreements will have to
be made which include financial compensation. On the
environment issue, I believe that pressure from public
opinion in the richer countries today will be much stronger
and more politically effective than it was when the call was
a moral call saying "People are poor in the Third World.
We should reach out and help them". I personally believe
in that message, but it has not persuaded the rich countries
to fulfil what is, actually, an obligation. On the contrary,
in the 1980s most of the rich countries reduced their develop¬
ment aid to the Third World as a percentage of their Gross
National Product. But if you say, looknot even the rich
can escape from the changes in the atmosphere. If you want
to save your lives and your children's future then you will
have to make an effort. If you don't, people in the developing
world will be increasing the use of energy and there will
be increased pollution. There is no alternative but to accept
political interdependence and make agreements.
To what extent did the meeting at The Hague succeed in
this respect?
At The Hague we made it clear that the institution that
will have to be created to assume responsibility for the
Dead fish in the polluted river Seine (1976).
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
protection of the atmosphere needs to be given wide powers
and that decisions also could be taken on a broad majority
basis. Consensus is sometimes too slow.
Can you really envisage a situation in which an interna¬
tional authority will be able to prevail over a big country?
Yes, I think so. At any rate I hope so. If a big country
tries to go against a broad majority decision about what is
necessary for the health of nations, for basic human values,
then it seems to me clear that there are effective ways in
which the world community can influence that nation. If
there really is a decision that people all over the world seri¬
ously want to take, you cannot get away from it even if
you are strong.
Different countries have different rules, and what one
country considers dangerous another may not.
That is true. And so we need a common authority to
decide. Take the case of toxic wastes. You have to have
someone who can advocate the generally held scientific view
about the degree of danger involved. It's not enough to have
each separate country defining its own position.
But even on critical issues such as the ozone layer we read
authoritative articles which say different things. Some say
that the situation is very dangerous or becoming dangerous,
others that there is no danger at all. Even the scientists do
not always agree.
Yes, that's true. It's a natural result of the pluralism of
scientific communities around the world. But if you bring
together the best institutes and the best scientists from
different parts of the globe and ask them to evaluate a situ¬
ation, then you can find out what is generally accepted at
the highest level. I came across this problem in Norway in
the 1970s when a professor criticized the government for
trying to combat acid rain and to reach agreement on the
question of sulphur dioxide pollution. There was a gener¬
ally held scientific view that acid rain was dangerous and
that the trout and salmon dying in the acidified Norwegian
lakes were only the first signs of a development that would
very soon reach the forests and ruin nature. I was sure that
this view was correct. I went very deeply into the scientific
studies, and as a politician I felt convinced that I was doing
the right thing. But this professor expressed his contrary
viewpoint very clearly and published his views in the press
time and again. It took a lot of time and trouble to fight
him and pollution simultaneously! But ten years later his
criticism subsided because the facts were then so obvious.
Do you think the United Nations system is the institution
through which the necessary changes could come?
think we have built a United Nations system which is
based on the kind of philosophy that I am advocating. The
arguments for it have become stronger over the decades. In
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8
the nineties, I believe the case for global co-operation is com¬
pelling. The United Nations has done a good job, but it has
not matched the expectations of those who created it in 1945.
I don't think we should try to build completely new insti¬
tutions. We should remodel those that already exist, make
them more integrated, and endow the United Nations family
with greater authority and potential. But I do think that
the United Nations system is too split up. There is not
enough common thinking, and there is too much fragmen¬
tation into different sectors.
Do you think that in view of the current changes in the
world it will be possible to stop the drivefor industrializa¬
tion regardless of the consequences? The East European
countries, for instance, are not satisfied with their level of
economic development and would like to industrialize
more.
It is perfectly possible to create sustainable development
patterns in Eastern Europe by investing in the right types
of industrial development. Investments can be made in
Eastern Europe with the aim of cleaning up pollution and
improving economic growth by developing new industries.
I think this is what Western Europe should be doing-
channelling investment resources to where they are most
needed. The result would be increased economic growth in
Europe as a whole.
What about thefear that Western Europe, the United States
andJapan will nowfocus their attention on Eastern Europe
and pay no more attention to Africa, Asia and Latin
America?
I understand that fear and it is felt in many parts of the
developing world. First of all I think that Western Europe,
the United States and Japan should step up their investment
in the developing world. We can carry that burden. United
States aid to Europe after the Second World War was many
times higher than the current level of aid to the developing
countries. Why on earth should it not be possible in the
1990s for the rich countries to double or triple the small
fraction of their GNP which they devote to development
aid? I think the environmental argument is the strongest one
we have. And of course we have no time to lose. Invest¬
ment on behalf of the future will boost economic growth
and also improve the quality of life.
In Eastern Europe and the Third World there is a lingering
feeling that "the West had its chance of industrializing
without bothering about pollution, why not us? Let's do
the same as they did, then we'll see what happens". We
know this would be badfor everybody. Shouldn't this fas¬
cination with industrialization be directed towards new
technologies, and probably new forms of development?
That's true. With information and communications tech¬
nology and other new technologies a high degree of decen¬
tralization is possible. You can have smaller firms employing
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The rich countries,
which have been polluting
for fifty years,
must give the developing
countries some of the money
and technobgy they need
to avoid causing pollution
and to provide for
their future economic
and social development
Opposite, aerosols containing chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)
are partly responsible for the destruction of the ozone layer.
Below, stockpile of toxic gas in the United States.
\ > x ^ .
fewer people engaged in non-polluting activities, in manufac¬
turing and in the service sector, which do not have the nega¬
tive effects of old-fashioned industrial growth. So by saving
resources and using new technologies you can promote eco¬
nomic and social development with less negative side effects.
These are hopeful trends.
A huge effort on the part of world opinion will be neces¬
sary. Do you think disarmament would liberate resources-
minds, men, moneyto make this transition easier? Are
world decision-makers really thinking about this?
I think they are. Already discussions are going on about
this in almost all the West European countries and in the
United States. They have signed treaties for reducing pollu¬
tion in the coming decade which are going to be enormously
expensive. And the only way to absorb these costs is to
channel resources away from the military sector. This is why
the 90s should be a time of great opportunities.
What pan do you think culture can play in this process?
The words we use are interesting. Once people talked
only about development. Then they started talking about
culture, the environment, human rights... These were words
many countries did not like to hear twenty years ago. Today
nobody can escape them. Sometimes one word comes into
vogue, then another. I remember a time in my country when
a big effort was being made to extend the impact of our cul¬
tural policies. Everyone seemed to be talking about culture.
Culture became a catchword and whatever people were
talking about it always seemed to come back to culture in
the end. Then, when environmental issues came on the
agenda, people started to use the word environment instead
of the word culture. What both words really refer to are
essential human values as defined outside the realm of pure
economics. The two concepts obviously overlap when you
examine them closely. So I think that today the word
environment is one that catches people's attention and
reaches over continents, but obviously culture is part of it
and adds to it. The two concepts are interrelated.
You mean they cover the same thing?
Not exactly, but there is often a tendency to broaden the
definition of words. In Unesco, for example, there is a ten¬
dency to define culture so broadly that it encompasses almost
all human activity. The World Health Organization does
the same thing with the concept of health because when they
look at people's health they find that so many other factors
are connected with it. Education is obviously part of cul¬
ture but without education you cannot take erre of your
own health. And without education and without health,
people have no human rights and there can be no develop¬
ment. All these concepts are interrelated to the extent that
they are rooted in human values and rights.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
u
NTIL fairly recent times, knowledge was regarded in most societies as a privileged
possession, an adjunct to the power of kings, priests and mandarins. It was transmitted
confidentially from generation to generation by word of mouth or in jealously guarded
esoteric texts which were only intelligible to initiates.
The story is told of a certain king of ancient Persia who passed sleepless nights when he
learned that the ruler of a nearby Indian land had compiled a written anthology of tales
that were said to enshrine all the wisdom of his people. The king ordered one of his most
trusted counsellors to procure a copy of the anthology, whatever the cost. The counsellor
devoted years of his life to the assignment. He infiltrated the court of the Indian ruler, gained
his confidence, won over some of the courtiers and bribed others until finally he gained
access to the precious manuscript and made a copy of it.
As a general rule, then, information was confined to the corridors of power. When it strayed
beyond them it was because of some kind of breach in the system. Many legends glorify
heroes who risked their lives in attempts to lay their hands on some mysterious formula
or hidden truth. There were occasions when knowledge flowed outside narrow channels,
spread through cities or even entire regions and stimulated open debate among philosophers
and scholarsbut such historical interludes were rare.
The circulation of knowledge has always been closely associated with intellectual emancipation
and the democratization of public life. What is new is that the exceptional situation of
yesterday has become today's general rule. The flow of information is responding to a need
which is widely felt to be irresistible.
This does not mean that knowledge has ceased to be a source of power. It would be more
accurate to say that scientific progress, the development of new communications technologies,
universal demands for freedom, as well as the spread of literacywhich constantly increases
the demand for informationare factors that encourage a trend towards openness and sharing.
More and more information is reaching more and more people. And different forms of
power, the power of economic, academic, political and military institutions, can only
perpetuate themselves through the possession of increasingly specialized knowledge which
today they are able to keep secret for a shorter and shorter time.
The flow of information is thus constantly widening the circle of citizens who are capable
of making choices, as well as multiplying the choices they are called on to make. This
complicates life for those who would like to make people's choices for them. The freedom
to inform has become a categorical imperative. For these reasons Unesco, whose mission
is to promote the freedom of information, attaches the highest priority to its obligation
Freedom of the Press, to support all efforts to multiply and expand the channels through which this freedom can
anonymous engraving, ir j i i i i j-i j i j i
1797. express ltselr, and to resolve the inevitable dilemmas caused by its development.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
by Jean Lacouture
The conscience
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
of the journalist
0,'THER occupations may have suffered more
from the vitriolic pens of satirists, but, although
media professionals seem to arouse less vengeful
feelings of hostility among the general public than
medical charlatans, vacuous military men or over¬
bearing bankers, they nevertheless seem to be
viewed with a mixture of disdain and suspicion.
Long before Guy de Maupassant's Bel-Ami,
with its portrayal of the world of cynical jour¬
nalists, the general public had scant esteem for
this sorry crew which were accused, somewhat
contradictorily, both of undue meddling in the
affairs of their contemporaries and of more or less
consciously, and with varying degrees of disin¬
terest, conniving with the authorities. Recent
opinion polls confirm that little has changed.
Can this be because, with each day that
passes, journalists are more and more closely iden¬
tified with the technology by means of which
their voices are heard, to the extent that they end
up by losing, in the eyes of the public, their
human image? Or is it that the images, the tempo,
the desire for instant reporting reduce everything
to statistics and spectacle, to stop-watch timing
and presentation? Of course not. Communicators
were seen as the instruments of the society in
which they operate long before the days of the
tie-pin microphone or the portable camera. Few
other occupations so fully absorb their practi¬
tioners as does journalismto the point that
André Malraux once wrote to a journalist whose
autobiography he had just read: "How is it that
you can have so little interest in yourself?"
Before becoming established as reporter on
"Channel X" or leader writer for "The Hogs-
norton Gazette", the journalist is the product of
a specific social background, personal history and
educationdetails of which will have been for¬
gotten or discarded along the way. The journalist
is a creature with a conscience that no press
baron, no dominant ideology, no group com¬
plicity can ever completely suppress.
This creature is also prey to twin anxieties
that of the actor on the stage and that of the
author whose words, thrown to the masses each
Shadow and Flight (1987), a collage
by the Japanese artist Yamada. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
day, change their perceptions. It is difficult
enough to live constantly in the public eye; it is
even more difficult to live under the scrutiny of
those whose perceptions one has changed, and in
a way that is no longer evident either to oneself
or to them.
It is against this "opaque transparency" that
the journalist operates, a background which is just
as likely to stimulate as to act as a cold douche
on the ego and which creates a perverse and heady
relationship between writer and reader that amaz¬
ingly enough can last a lifetime, through war and
peace, revelations and denials, sensation and
derision.
That Sarah Bernhardt was able to continue
acting in Phèdre or in L'Aiglon for half a century
may come as a surprise, but not as a shock.
However, that a famous commentator or
newshound can address the same readership about
events ranging from the battlefields of the Marne
to the French generals' putsch in Algeria, without
changing either outlook, opinions or even pen-
name, gives some idea how thick-skinned some
members of the writing profession can be.
The Hiroshima holocaust
The journalist and the journalistic conscience are
engaged in a bitter struggle on many fronts, the
more so since the profession is ill-defined, sub¬
ject to few rules and endowed with less precise
ethical codes than many others.
It is true that, with the advance of science and
the evolution of the law, the medical profession
has been faced with ethical dilemmas and uncer¬
tainties, as borne out by scores of inquiries, tes¬
timonies and debates. Neither lawyers, nor
research scientists with their biological
engineering and their "ultimate weapons", nor
the military men who use their weapons, have
been spared such self-questioning. Nevertheless,
they have their Hippocratic oath, their Bar
Councils and the Geneva Conventions to fall
back on. Journalists have no equivalent.
We might reasonably compare their situation
to that of a guided missile, unaware both of the
nature of its mission and of the purpose of the
hand that guides it, and programmed in such a
way that it is aimed neither at the earth, so as
to avoid accidents, nor at the ocean, so as to avoid
pollution. Given these restraints, journalists are
free, responsible human beings who have only
to do their best to enlighten their contemporaries
about world events without triggering a second
Hiroshima holocaust.
On the face of it, the objective is clearlike
the witness in the box, to tell the truth, the whole
truth and nothing but the truth. In a court of law,
however, the jury demands only the truth as the
witness, as a human being, saw and understood
it, at a particular time, in a particular place and
as it related to certain people. The truth required
of a journalist is a wider, more complex, multi-
faceted truth.
1 t> V
a*..** ,.,_, i Mù- ^
. .. , Vin n
J». M.1 .^n. .
*r^ II J- t *° .#
.«« m f
'-.I a, -,
a.." a- ^1^ '1*11 Jit'
nia 1. fa wu' U Urw **.
... r *sif- « «H erf» - ' rurtt*'
.. -fir«. »a1| " »or
p¡'. -'«' * ",*.iéi; ¡.tí
BJ -vil* % I»**.
*7 mZ'F
"7* liLFiu-ni. 3.-'.*m»
. M' Ï*" »»
r«JI ' '!>* Tu .. _ ., , >.
>< > Ti. > Sût».*..
JEAN LACOUTURE,
French writer and journalist,
was foreign correspondent for
the French daily Le Monde
from 1957 to 1975. He is the
author of major biographies of
Léon Blum (1982), Pierre
Mendès-France (1984), and
Jean-François Champollion
(1988; see the Unesco Courier,
October 1989). Volume I of his
3-volume life of Charles de
Gaulle has been published in
English as Charles de Gaulle:
The Rebel (Holmes and Meier,
New York, 1988).
Returning from wartime deportation, Léon
Blum, who was a journalist for many years, told
his press colleagues that he had learned that the
golden rule for the profession was not "just to
tell the truth, which is an easy thing to do, but
to tell the whole truth, which is much more
difficult". This is all very well, but what is "the
whole truth", and is it possible to define "nothing
but the truth"?
The December 1989 revolution in Romania
brought this question to the forefront again in
a vivid, violent fashion. We all know the extent
to which "the truth", in its simplest, statistical
form, was distorted. The heady excitement that
misled almost all the international media was later
subject to very close analysisin particular by
French writer Jean-Claude Guillebaud who
praised the admirable restraint of the Belgian jour¬
nalist Colette Braekman for her courage in
writing the apparently self-condemnatory words,
"I saw nothing happen at Timisoara".
"I saw nothing happen" does not, of course,
mean "nothing happened". Yet this observation,
which is anathema to any professional commu¬
nicator, should be taught as a model in every
school of journalism. For it is by this formula
that the journalistic conscience must be guided
by the relationship between the truth and what
has been seen, between what can be and what has
been verified. This is both the antithesis of and
synonymous with Blum's "the whole truth"
all that part of the truth that the individual jour¬
nalist can discern.
The journalist's self-questioning is, however,
not concerned only with the accessible part of
the truth, but also with the means employed to
acquire it and the use that can be made of it.
"Investigative journalism" is on the agenda,
and it is now accepted that all methods of inves¬
tigation are permitted. The handling of the
Watergate affair by two outstanding journalists
of the Washington Post seems to have justified a
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Above left, Le Palais
(1983); above, Palace
(1983), two photomontages
by the French artist Patrick
Tosanl.
Below, a scene from All the
President's Men (1976),
Alan Pakula's film on
Watergate in which Dustin
Hoffman (centre) plays one
of the investigative
journalists who worked on
the story.
form of inquiry comparable to that used by the
police and special services in their dealings with
terrorists and drug traffickers.
To question, to revolt against this model may
seem to be the reaction of a dyspeptic old soldier,
of a journalist trained in a "holier-than-thou" tra¬
dition. Yet the vision I have of the journalistic
profession makes me reject certain kinds of
method and various forms of crypto¬
interrogations. I am one of those who feel that
journalism must abide by rules other than those
of the police and of the counter-espionage
services. Perhaps I am wrong.
However, the greatest challenge to the profes¬
sional communicator's conscience concerns the
withholding of information. For having done so
(and admitting it) in the context of the wars in
Algeria and Viet Nam, for having considered
myself capable of drawing a line between what
could be communicated and what should not be
said, for holding myself to be the guardian of the
"just" cause and of "higher interests" than that
of informing the public, I have been subjected to
severe remonstrations. No doubt they were
deserved, particularly when they came from
people who had never, for other ends, been guilty
of systematic and carefully disguised manipu¬
lations.
The rule is clear, it must be "the whole truth
and nothing but the truth". But this must be com¬
plemented by the words of the motto the New
York Times carries beneath its logo"All the
news that's fit to print". This excludes all that is
unworthythat is to say, not only whole
categories of baser journalism, but, from its nobler
forms, the divulgation of information that unduly
affects the life and honour of human beings
whose unworthiness has not been established.
With these guidelines in mind, journalists will
conclude that the major problem they have to
face lies not in the acquisition but in the dissemi¬
nation of their portion of the truth, in estab¬
lishing a balance between what has been ingested
in good faith, in a world in which dross and
deception abound, and what has been regurgi¬
tated. The line between the two is elusive and
constantly moving. The only filter available is the
journalistic conscience.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
How far does the law recognize the journalist's self-imposed duty
not to divulge the source of information given in confidence?
The protection of sources
by Patricia Wilhelm
This time we'll get them."
X
16
PATRICIA WILHELM,
Belgian lawyer, is national
secretary of the Belgian
Journalists' Association. She is
the author of Protection of
Sources: An International
Review of Journalistic and
Legal Practice (Norwegian
Institute of Journalism,
Frednkstad, 1988), a survey
commissioned by Unesco and
carried out by Ms. Wilhelm on
behalf of the International
Federation of Journalists.
.O observe professional secrecy and not to
divulge the source of information obtained in
confidence" is the seventh article of the Declara¬
tion of Rights and Obligations of Journalists,
adopted by the International Federation of Jour¬
nalists in 1972. This dutysince from the point
of view of professional ethics it is indeed an obli¬
gation journalists have towards their
informantsshould be considered in parallel with
the first of the rights set forth in the Declaration:
"Journalists claim free access to all information
sources, and the right to freely enquire on all
events affecting public life. Therefore, secrecy of
public or private affairs may only be opposed to
journalists in exceptional cases and for clearly
expressed motives."
A right or an obligation?
In most countries, journalists have to fight to
obtain official recognition of their right not to
disclose the sources of their information, when
this is given in confidence. However, as a matter
of professional ethics, journalists consider this to
be a duty, an obligation towards their informants
(sources), which is a corollary to their duty to
provide the public with freely collected infor¬
mation.
Whatever the consequences for themselves
may be, journalists thus consider it their duty not
to reveal the identity of their informants or to
allow their identity to become known. Non-
official sources of information are likely to dry
up for fear of retaliation if their anonymity is not
guaranteed. But, if journalists relied exclusively
on official information, they would be reduced
to the status of official mouthpieces, and this con¬
ception of press freedom would bear little rela¬
tion to the public's right to be informed.
This duty of confidentiality is claimed as a
right because most national legal codes do not
exempt journalists from the general obligation of
the citizen to testify in a court of law when called
upon to do so. In other words, journalists are
often faced with an uncomfortable dilemmaon
the one hand they commit themselves to abso¬
lute discretion towards their information sources,
but on the other the authorities deny them the
right to do so.
The public's right
to be informed
Countries that are signatories to the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights nevertheless recog¬
nize, in Article 19, that: "Everyone has the right
to freedom of opinion and expression; this right
includes freedom to hold opinions without inter¬
ference and to seek, receive and impart informa¬
tion and ideas through any media and regardless
of frontiers." It is evident, however, that the
authorities and the courts do not give priority to
this right when it conflicts with other rights
whether collective, such as state security or the
administration of justice, or individual, such as
the right to privacy in libel or slander cases.
This leads to two conclusions.
First of all, when journalists claim the right
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
*m
V
t y r.
Above, photojournalist
Russell Price (Nick Nolte) in
Under Fire (1983), a film by
the American director Roger
Spottiswoode which
examines the moral and
political dilemmas faced by
reporters.
Left, detail of a poster for a
Cuban film festival (1969),
by Rostgaard.
to protect their sources, they are not demanding
a privilege for themselves, any more than they
hold themselves to be the sole beneficiaries of the
freedom of the press and the free flow of infor¬
mation. They are merely the professional link in
the information chain and the protection of their
sources is an essential corollary to the collective
right of the public to be informed. The public
is thus the real beneficiary of this form of secrecy.
Secondly, the right to freedom of opinion and
expression, as well as to the free flow of infor¬
mation, is a fundamental right on a par with other
human rights. Where there is a conflict of rights
it should be remembered that the right to infor¬
mation is a right that concerns society as a whole
and there is therefore no reason for it to be con¬
sidered in any way a "second category" right.
Confidentiality under attack
Is there a need for a specific law to guarantee to
journalists the right to protect their sources? On
the face of it, all that would be needed would be
an exemption from the general obligation to tes¬
tify imposed by law on all citizens.
However, the authorities, in particular the
judicial authorities, have other means of forcing 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
journalists to reveal their sources. They can be
summoned by the police to attend a judicial
inquiry, be called to appear before a parliamen¬
tary committee or to give evidence to a tribunal.
Warrants can be issued for their homes or places
of work to be searched and for items to be seized.
Their telephone calls can be monitored, they can
be sued, or even arrested, as being guilty of, or
accomplices to, a crime or a misdemeanour. They
can even be accused of complicity in a civil ser¬
vant's breach of the professional code of secrecy
or of stealing or receiving official documents.
In libel cases, journalists called upon to prove
the truth of what they have written often have
to choose between revealing the source of their
information, so as to exonerate themselves, and
remaining silent, in accordance with their profes¬
sional code, and finding themselves condemned.
No protective legislation, however well con¬
ceived, can guarantee the free collecting of infor¬
mation. It will always be possible to get round
such a law and bring pressure and intimidation
to bear on the journalist.
For these reasons it is of fundamental impor¬
tance that the principles of freedom of expression,
freedom of the press and the right of the public
to information should not only be a matter for
legislation but should also become embodied in
custom and practice. Political will, in the widest
sense of the term, is needed if freedom of the press
is to become anything more than a pious hope.
Journalists, publishers and trade unions all
have a role to play in the campaign to bring these
problems to the attention of their colleagues, the
public and the authorities. General awareness of
the vital importance of the question of the pro¬
tection of sources, as a corollary to the right to
freedom of information, is an essential adjunct
to legislation on this matter.
A law on the protection
of sources
A number of basic principles that can be used as
guidelines in the drawing up of laws guaranteeing
the highest possible level of protection of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
EL ESPECTADOR ti i
: "
I
líbenles i
I lllf l.( \MI EL ESPECTADOR
i.u^oiá lueves 7 de (fldanfara de ]r,v-
Dlclemt-r©
O L M M J V S
< 2
4 3 6 7 9
10 ti 12 13 14 13 16
17 II It » Il 21 2]
M 23 2« 27 28 M 30
31
:	-	 .'..
J	LU
TH VAI'.INAS I CI'.MHK.MIMIS I KfWSM V.IM III N" 29 322
Otra narco-masacre
Ue de vidimus y
reiilen.irc. de heridos en
oient; »lu ((in Mi'1 kilos de
clin.Hiiil.i ¡¡cl.ilini.s.i (renie
,i Lis instalaciones di.l
DAS, i'ii Hotjiil.i.
Destruidas v.irias
edificaciones del seilet
iloqucmao.
I tiollllosas |ieidld,e.
maleriale
que ' onstltuyd el máa
rori in que se
. glstrsdo en el pata .1
! ; ;í 1 .u historia 1 1
i . ! . ron 1.1 > In 1 y
.1. '1 a 1 sultaron hi tidal
- -i!..! tin 1 arro*bomba
nti -ti ala orienta) ii-¡ 1 dlflclo
.:..<! Departa
IdmlnlstraUvo de Se
til : .. in
1 ,11. . 17 v im de Ba
rto en 1 rplc ilvos
le m misma in
li ¡i Poih ii Nadonal y
del 1 luerpo 1 <->- nk 0 dc Policía
: ¡.i carga 1 ataba 1 om¬
ita pol no retenoa dc media
loni 1. ni.» .i- dinamita gelatinosa
In cjtio t-xplk.t t.l lu¬
ll, r 1 1 tu dévastai Ion que 1 auso
tanto rn <-l edlflck) del Daa
coma fu Inmuebles situados a A
ala redonda, y <-l crátei
'- 3 ho metros <i<- profundidad.
Ii largo y 1 1 80 de ancho
i|u<* quedó en el sillo en donde
T..:i.iji* la explosión.
(Continu* en la p¿{ln« 13-A) Panorama dr nnirrtc y destrucción frente n Jas Instalaciones del DAS. en ef aecharde Aüoquetiiao, cri Bogotá.
"Con fe, valor y
firmeza, pongámonos
de pie para defender
la Patria", insta
Barco. Maza demanda
solidaridad ciudadana.
1 n m- nsaje televisado des¬
di- Tokio. Japón, t-l presidente
Barco repudio el atentado di-
namlteio contri las Instala'
1 lora B del 1>AS e Insto .1 los
. a «i»-- "i on fe,
valor y Hrmcza pangAmonoa de
pie p o. i defender la Paula".
Kl Jefe del rsladn advirtió,
Igualmente, que la democracia
colombiana se encuentra
amenazada por los violentos v
que < gobierno seguirá en lo
tocha contra '-i narcotráfico
pera Impedir que el pois roli».t
bajo 000 Urania sangrienta.
ACCIÓN DE NARCOS. -
Tus »i alentado contra los
il.-pendrIK'tas il<- lo t-ntidad II su
«.irfto. el general Miguel Maza
Márquez aliono que rl mismo
si- trato de una nuevo noción
promovida por los moflas or-
ganfzadaa del narcotráfico
antra el pueblo colombiano.
VALEROSA ACTITUD.-
Al término (le un Consejo de
Ministros que fue convocada en
formo extraordinaria para
analizar los graves hechos de
orden pública que azotan al
pais, los nileíolitos ilrl Gabinete
expidieron un comunicado en el
que respaldan la valerosa no-
sil lón adoptado por rl gobierno
del presidente Barco.
(Tesas siglas 12-Ai
Above, drug traffickers are
denounced in a front page
story from a 1989 Issue of
El Espectador, a leading
Colombian daily. The paper
has been the target of
attacks from organized
crime and several of its
journalists have been killed.
Left, journalist Paul Kerjean
(Patrick Dewaere) engaged
on a dangerous assignment
in Mille Milliards de Dollars
(1981), a film by the French
director Henri Verneuil.
confidentiality of sources can be derived from
legal provisions that already exist, in particular,
in Austria and Sweden.
The Austrian press law, which came into
force in January 1982, allows journalists to refuse
to give evidence in a court of law or, in the con¬
text of an administrative process, to reply to ques¬
tions concerning the identity of the originator or
other source of a piece of information. This right
also exists for publishers and all other workers,
from clerks to printers, and is applicable in all
branches of the media.
The Swedish law provides similar protection,
but instead of granting a right it imposes an obli¬
gation of silence on journalists and others
working in the media, so as to protect the
anonymity of informants. It reinforces this obli¬
gation by a general prohibition of investigation
into the source of information. To ignore this
prohibition is a punishable offence.
The Austrian law is further strengthened by
a general ban on searchesnot only of editorial
offices, but also of all media premises, including
print shops and despatch departmentsand on
the seizure of editorial materialarticles, photo¬
graphs, films, sound recordings and electronic
material. This ban extends also to the homes of
journalists and other media employees.
To sum up, any law on the protection of
sources of information must apply:
to all the medianewspapers, magazines, radio,
television, press agencies, the electronic media;
to all forms of informationarticles, photo¬
graphs, video-tapes, magnetic tapes, computer
materials;
to all personnel engaged in the processing of
informationpublishers, journalists, executives,
technicians, printers.
Such a law must be accompanied by a prohi¬
bition on searches and on the seizure of materials
from places of work or from the homes of jour¬
nalists and other media personnel.
Above all, however, the authorities, and in
particular the judicial authorities, must recognize
that the free flow of information, the youngest
of the human rights, is one of the bases of the
democratic system of which free access to all
sources of information is a sine qua non. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Unjustified
intrusions
by the
sensationalist
press pose a
threat to the
freedom of
information
Private life and
the public eye
by Jonathan Fenby
0,
a»?
"ne definition of news is that it is informa¬
tion which somebody somewhere does not want
published or broadcast. While much of the news
which appears day by day is unlikely to cause
anybody lost sleep, that definition does contain
more than a grain of truth. The information
which makes most impact in the world's
newspapers and airwaves deals with exceptional
eventsthe one airliner which crashes rather than
the thousands which land safely, a change of
direction by politicians rather than the steady
implementation of known policies, the exception¬
ally good or bad crop yield rather than the
average harvest. Often these exceptional events
are, by their nature, news which somebody some¬
where would prefer not to be publicizedfor a
multitude of reasons ranging from political or
business embarrassment to considerations of per¬
sonal grief and pain.
The media's emphasis on the new and the
unusual has often been decried, most notably in
criticism of Western media organizations for con¬
centrating on "bad news" in reporting from
Africa, Asia and Latin America. But it flows
inevitably from the service role of the press and
broadcasting organizations. The media and the
news they transmit cannot exist in a vacuum.
However fine its principles and admirable its
writing, a newspaper without readers would be
a pointless entity.
Satisfying a market is not a sufficient condi¬
tion on its own, but the existence of a market
is a necessary condition for the independent, com¬
mercial media of the kind found in democratic
nations. Without customers, the media become
a collection of propaganda organs for which the
crucial choices on content are made by those who
pay the bills, and it seems to me a matter of
everyday observation that, for the most part,
these customers are interested in information
about the exceptional, the new and the unusual.
Like it or not, it is human nature to be
interested in the occasional aircraft crash rather
than the thousands of safe landings, and the media
cater to this trait. The media, of course, fulfil
many other rolesas commentator, analyst,
observer, cultural guide, provider of good writing
and even of humour. But the primary role is to
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
In 1936, Edward VIII
abdicated from the British
throne and was crea.ed
Duke of Windsor. Left, a
Journalist types his copy on
a portable machine after
being ejected from the
grounds of a château where
the ex-King was staying.
discover and communicate news which is impor¬
tant and relevant to an audience and to do this
effectively the media need a political and social
environment which acknowledges the free pro¬
vision of information to the public as a social
good, rather than something grudgingly accorded
to the media on condition that they behave them¬
selves by standards set by the political authorities.
Those authorities may regard such freedom
as unpalatable in practice, even if they pay lip
service to the general principle of the freedom
of the press. It is only natural that those who exer¬
cise power should find it uncomfortable to have
their failures, misdeeds and secret activities
brought to light. The understandable, if regret¬
table, tendency of those in power to take a res¬
trictive view of what the media should and should
not do is heightened in many democratic coun¬
tries by the adversarial relationship between the
press and broadcasting, on the one hand, and
those in powerbe it in politics, business,
administration or other fields.
The media's role as discoverer and publicizer
of abuses of authority makes an uncomfortable
bedfellow for those who want to get on with run¬
ning things with a minimum of public scrutiny.
Add to that the media's role as critic and com¬
mentator and the adversarial relationship
becomes inevitable if the media are to play their
proper part in open societies.
As a recognition of the need to protect the
media's position in such a relationship, some
countries enshrine freedom of information in
their constitutions. Elsewhere some governments
have adhered to international conventions which
guarantee such freedom. The media in these coun¬
tries may still run into problems with govern¬
ments and in the law courts: given the nature of
the relationship and the way that the media will
always be pressing to the limits of their freedoms,
it would be surprising if they did not. But the
basis from which the argument starts is usually
relatively clear.
Press indiscretions
In my own country, Britain, the situation is much
more cloudy and contains distinct dangers for the
freedom of information. We have no statutory
guarantee of freedom of expression and, in recent
court cases, the media have found themselves
having to argue to show why they should be free
to reportrather than the prosecution being
required to demonstrate why a certain piece of
information should be withheld from the public.
The notion of serving the public interest does
not always carry great weight in such cases. Two
journalists have been fined in recent years for
refusing to disclose the sources of stories. Under 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
a new Official Secrets Act, civil servants who dis¬
close information will not be able to invoke the
public interest as a defence. In one recent case,
the government held that an injunction obtained
against two newspapers on a story prevented all
other newspapers from publishing similar
material, opening the way to blanket bans which,
for instance, could be based on legal action against
small, poor publications unable to fight it
through the extremely expensive British legal
process.
It is not surprising, therefore, that many
people in the British media believe that freedom
of expression is being constrained by political and
legal decisions which take little or no account of
the essential contribution of freedom of informa¬
tion to the public interest. On top of this,
extremely large libel damages running to £1 mil¬
lion or more in several recent cases have added
Below, filming the Bastille
Day procession in Paris.
22
JONATHAN FENBY,
British journalist, is deputy
editor of The Guardian. A
former correspondent for
Reuters and editor of the
agency's international news
services, he has also served as
correspondent in France and
Germany for The Economist
and as home editor and
assistant editor of The
Independent.
to press concerns. Even if a newspaper feels it has
a good case, the prospect of an inconclusive legal
outcome in which it will be left to pay the very
high costs of legal representation may act as
another deterrent to publishing an accurate but
legally tricky report.
This adversarial, exceptional, uncomfortable
part which I have sketched out for the media
inevitably raises a question about how far their
legitimate role in unearthing and publicizing news
should go. When it comes to political scandals,
business frauds or administrative malpractice, the
public service line should be easy to draw: pub¬
lish and, if you are wrong, be damned. Where
things get more difficult is in weighing up the
balance between disclosure in the public interest
and the rights of individuals to privacy.
Not even the most ardent advocates of the
freedom of information would, I think, deny the
individual's right to privacy. The question is at
what point that right ceases to be a protection
against intrusion by the media. "Intrusion" is a
loaded term, with a pejorative implication. But
without intrusion, many of the most notable
media disclosures of wrongdoing would never
have taken place. There is nothing easier than for
a corrupt public figure or a shady businessman
to try to block investigation by the media on the
grounds that reporters are intruding into their
private affairs. Equally, there may be few things
more difficult for an ordinary person than to face
journalists poking into his or her life in the hope
of finding information.
The press on probation
To return to my own country, there have been
several cases recently in which media intrusion
has taken place without any immediately
apparent public interest being served. The parents
of a young television actor who committed sui¬
cide have recently been vocal in attacking what
they see as press harassment as the cause of his
death. In another case, journalists from a tabloid
publication which specializes in sex and sensation
entered the hospital room of another television
star as he was recovering from brain surgery and
took pictures and questioned him before being
ejected by security staff.
Such examples have fuelled calls from some
politicians for greater controls over the press and
stronger protections of privacy against media
intrusion. After two members of parliament
unsuccessfully introduced bills into the House of
Commons to establish the right to privacy, the
government warned last year that the press was
on probation and a special commission was set
up to look at privacy and related matters. This
commissionknown after its chairman, David
Calcutt, as the Calcutt Commissionreported in
June 1990. It laid down measures including
making physical intrusion onto private property
a criminal offence and the threat of statutory con¬
trols if the media are held to have misbehaved
during a twelve-month probationary period of
self-regulation.
The reaction of the media in Britain was over¬
whelmingly hostile. The excesses of some popular
papers which led to the establishment of the Cal¬
cutt Commission are often difficult to excuse.
One commentator referred to such newspapers
as "filthy rags", while others acknowledged that
the behaviour of parts of the tabloid press made
the press as a whole fair game for regulation.
Attempts at self-regulation which the national
newspapers have made over the past year appear
to have had little lasting effect, and have raised
the question of whether tabloid newspaper
proprietors are more ready to risk disapproval
or the falling sales which might result from
greater self-restraint.
But the problem for the media as a whole is
that any system which prevents intrusion into
privacy in the case of an isolated, powerless
individual could also be used to protect those
whom the press and broadcasting should be free
to expose if they are to play their proper role.
The deputy leader of the British Labour Party,
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
A swarm of paparazzi In
Federico Fellini's film La
Dolce Vita (1959), which
describes the life of a
Journalist.
Roy Hattersley, recently acknowledged the differ¬
ence between the privacy of those in public life
and that of private individuals, and added that it
was almost impossible to protect the privacy of
politicians in the same way as that of other
individuals.
The difficulty is where such a line should be
drawn. In most cases, the distinction between
public and private is obvious. But private
individuals can suddenly become subjects of
public interest because they are caught up in
events which make newsand then fall back into
obscurity. Equally, there is a continuing debate
about whether the private lives of public figures
should be subject to the same kind of reserve as
the private lives of private individuals. Should
newspapers report on, say, the way political
leaders spend their leisure time? Or, to take
another example, are the problems of relatives of
well-known figures proper material for news
reports? Should the arrest of the son of a promi¬
nent politician on a drugs charge be treated as if
it concerned a public figure or a private
individual?
Different newpapers and broadcasting sta¬
tions handle such questions in different ways,
according to their own definition of their own
responsibilities and their view of what most
interests the public at which they are aiming. The
diversity of the media in many countries means
that stories which may appear on the front pages
of tabloids may not even be reported in broad¬
sheet quality newspapers. The danger point for
the freedom of information comes when the
public considers that unjustified intrusions into
privacy justify legal restraints on the press.
Newspapers may say that regulation of the press
is worse than irresponsibility by the press. But
if the media are to enjoy the freedom they need
to carry out their job properly, they have to
know how to use that freedomand where abuse
begins.
They cannot expect to be popular with those
in authority, and must be ready on occasion to
be unpopular with at least some of their own
audience. Their role as a source of disclosures and
investigation means that they have to be prepared
to delve into areas which involve sensitive ques¬
tions of privacy, but they have to be certain that
in doing so intrusion is balanced by the public
interest it is serving. When that balance is
achieved, the media are on firm ground. When
it is not, they put their place in society at risk,
and open the door to regulation from those who
regard freedom of information as an irritant
rather than an absolute good.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
In a developing country, the daunting costs
of launching an independent publication
Senegal
The price
of a free press
by Babacar Touré
I
24
N January 1986, a dozen young Senegalese jour¬
nalists founded an independent press group, Sud-
Communication. Almost two years later, they
launched Sud-Hebdo, a weekly which has now
become a yardstick for the African media and a
symbol of hope for the many journalists in Africa
who are endeavouring to throw off the shackles
of the official press.
With limited means and the trust of its
increasingly faithful readers as sole support, Sud-
Hebdo was keen to play its part in consolidating
democracy in Senegal, which would be meaning¬
less without a genuinely free and responsible
press. It also wanted to provide a platform for
certain sections of society excluded from the state-
run media by their non-conformism.
But the battle is far from over. In Senegal,
nothing is done officially to gag the press, but the
economic situation is so bad and the press sub¬
sidy system in the private sector so sketchy that
any attempt to go it alone without attaching
oneself to some group or coterie is tempting
Providence.
High overheads
To escape the clutches of the tax authorities, Sud-
Communication has officially declared itself a
"groupement d'intérêt économique" (joint-
venture consortium), which, however, has the
drawback that Sud-Communication is not per¬
mitted to make a profit: all surplus moneys gener¬
ated by its activities must be reinvested in the
company. But owing to lack of resources, it
cannot for the time being consider setting up a
limited liability company, which although admit¬
tedly more of a target for the tax authorities,
would be better equipped to attract finance.
Turning to the practical side, Sud-Hebdo does
r^j
Jà ià
I] ^L i
m 0^^.
fl
1 '*\Ü-H M
Hi, V I
¡3M. **^4P
A Journalist records
a radio Interview for a
programme on living
conditions in Niger.
BABACAR TOURE,
Senegalese journalist, is
editorial director of the Dakar
weekly newspaper Sud-Hebdo.
Co-founder of Vivre Autrement,
the first French-language
consumers' magazine in Africa,
he is a member of the
management committee of the
West African Union of
Journalists.
not own its premises but rents two facing apart¬
ments in central Dakar, consisting in all of six
rooms with utilities. One serves as the newsroom,
the remainder being occupied by the administra¬
tive and secretarial staff. Lack of space has meant
that a kitchen has been requisitioned to house the
equipment. The monthly rental for the two apart¬
ments is 350,000 francs CFA*.
In many countries, the press enjoys preferen¬
tial rates for telecommunications, but in Senegal
it is regarded as an ordinary customer, subject to
the same system as everyone else. Sud-Hebdo has
therefore had to drop the idea of a telex and con¬
fine itself to a subscription to the International
Press Agency, which supplies national news as
well as dispatches from Agence France Presse.
This onerous monthly subscription (Sud-Hebdo
has to go and fetch the news from the agency)
amounts to 58,500 francs CFA per month. The
bi-monthly telephone bill comes to 400,000 francs
CFA on average, while the electricity bill is about
60,000 francs CFA. To offset the shortcomings
of its communications system, Sud-Hebdo
recently equipped itself with a small computer
hooked up to the telecommunications system and
a fax terminal, thus further adding to its
overheads.
Although to begin with Sud-Hebdo employed
only a dozen people, this number has had to be
substantially increased in order to produce a
quality product within very tight deadlines. The
staff currently consists of eight permanent jour¬
nalists and two photo-reporters, ten freelances,
two sales representatives, four word-processor
operators and three support staff. Their salaries
come to over 3.8 million francs CFA per month,
to which 450,000 francs CFA have to be added
for equipment and ancillary costs.
Each issue, which usually has a print-run of
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
SË£*£I^
yj
C'EST
mmeist
An editorial conference at
the Senegalese weekly
Sud-Hebdo. At head of
table, Babacar Touré, the
editorial director.
10,000, therefore costs 306 francs CFA, but is sold
for 300 francs CFA.
In Senegal, there is only one distribution net¬
work, namely that of the Press Distribution
Agency (ADP), a subsidiary of the French com¬
pany Hachette. This de facto monopoly (legally,
this sector is open to competition) enables ADP
unilaterally to set exorbitant commission rates,
36 per cent of the selling price in the case of Sud-
Hebdo. Together with other independent
newspapers, we have tried on a number of occa¬
sions to shake free of ADP, but have failed owing
to lack of sufficient resources to compete against
such a well-established company, which does its
utmost to beat off competition from potential
rivals.
Selling at a loss would be less absurd if the
shortfall was met from advertising revenue. But 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Below, the newsroom of a
Zambian paper.
Bottom, production of a
rural newspaper In the
United Republic of
Tanzania.
this is not the case. The weight of tradition, the
persistence of archaic management methods and
the backwardness of the economy mean that
advertisers in Senegal still regard buying space in
a newspaper as charity, on a par with alms giving.
This is why a newspaper with the reputation of
Sud-Hebdo earned a mere 40,000 francs CFA per
month on average in 1989 from advertising.
These problems would have been less serious
if Sud-Hebdo had a substantial number of sub¬
scribers, but unfortunately it does not. This is not
through lack of interest on the part of readers,
but because there are no preferential postage rates
for newspapers, which are treated as ordinary
mail.
A newspaper sold by subscription at just
under 300 francs CFA can therefore cost 450
francs CFA when postage is added. Using four
mopeds, we have tried to set up a home delivery
26
service, currently serving about a hundred sub¬
scribers.
Fortunately, Sud-Hebdo has a good sales
record (83 per cent of the total copies printed on
average) and has its own desktop publishing
system (three micro-computers and a laser
printer). This equipment, which is a first for any
newspaper in sub-Saharan Africa, makes it pos¬
sible to save on photocomposition and layout
costs. Outside workphotocomposition for
other newspapers, brochures, theses and books
also brings in 1,970,000 francs CFA per year.
Proclaiming freedom of the press is one thing,
implementing it another. Although it can be
affirmed in principle, in practice it may be res¬
tricted, intentionally or unintentionally, unless
the necessary steps are taken to translate it into
reality.
The Union of Senegalese Information and
Communication Professionals (SYNPICS) has
several times drawn the attention of the authori¬
ties to the deplorable situation of the press,
resulting in the amendment, in 1986, of the Press
Act in force since 1979. A Fund for the Promo¬
tion of the Press was set up but never actually
came to anything. What is more, the Act does
not even stipulate how the Fund is supposed to
function and what criteria are to determine the
allocation of the resources it is supposed to
administer.
Media professionals have also called for a
more equitable distribution of advertising
resources between the state-run media, foreign
publicationswhich take the lion's shareand
the private national press, which is not subsidized.
The grossly unfair contract imposed by the ADP
has always been condemned, but to no avail.
Many newspapers are urgently demanding
tax exemption for the chief items involved in
their production, and also preferential telecom¬
munications rates, again without much success.
Worse still, the new National Printing Centre (a
company in which the state is a majority share¬
holder) recently raised its already prohibitive rates
by 34.2 per cent without warning. As a result,
many newspapers, including the national
monthly radio and television magazine, are now
being printed abroad.
Sud-Hebdo, which in January 1990 had
expanded to twelve pages, was three months later
forced to slim down to eight pages again. It is even
thinking of reducing the print-run, of shedding
some of its staff (already in short supply), and of
reducing costs which cannot be pared down any
further as things stand. In April 1990, Sud-Hebdo
and two other independent weeklies, Wal Fadjri
and Le cafard libéré, held a joint press conference,
followed up by the publication of a joint editorial,
to encourage the authorities to pay greater atten¬
tion to the problems of the press. Senegalese
media people today have had just about as much
as they can take.
* 300 francs CFA (Communauté Financière Africaine)
1 US dollar.
approx.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Philippines !
Between freedom
and anarchy
Demonstration
in support of press
freedom,
Manila.
In the euphoria
of liberation,
the media try
to find
their bearings
Xhe people of the Philippines, who for decades
had been fighting a seemingly losing battle against
an oppressive regime, will remember 1986 as the
year that ushered in a new era. In the February
revolution, millions of Filipinos fought with
nothing but prayers and a firm determination to
restore freedom and democracy to their land. The
phrase that inspired them was "people power".
During those four days in February, the mass
media were very much in the forefront, in¬
forming, mobilizing and directing. What made
this media "coup" even more spectacular was that
journalists were operating in a climate of fear
and apathy created by years of repression. When
Ferdinand Marcos came to power, he trans¬
formed almost overnight what had been regarded
as the freest press in Asia into an instrument for
the perpetuation of his own regime.
For many years, the people oPthe Philippines 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
had no access to media that told them what was
really happening in the country. Information was
manipulated, either by direct censorship or by
self-censorship based on fear. All kinds of infor¬
mation were considered secret, from Marcos's
state of health to government investments and the
transactions of financial institutions. Reporters
could not even obtain statistics on malnutrition
in the Philippines. Secrecy reached such heights
that even certain laws that were passed remained
secret.
Various presidential decrees were designed to
stop the free flow of information. Presidential
Decree 33, for example, penalized the printing,
possession, distribution and circulation of certain
leaflets, handbills and propaganda, while Presi¬
dential Decree 90 penalized any person who
published, distributed, circulated or spread
"rumours, false news or information" that could
prove "divisive" to the people.
The intimidation and harassment of journa¬
lists was a common occurrence. Those who dared
to speak out could lose their jobs, or were the
object of administrative and legal charges. Some
were imprisoned, tortured or even killed. It is esti¬
mated that twenty-seven journalists were killed
during the Marcos years.
Radio station managers and newspaper edi¬
tors were not exempt. They were intimidated,
risked ' imprisonment or found that they no
longer had a paper or station to run. Immedia¬
tely after the imposition of martial law in Sep¬
tember 1972, the government took over the
ownership of a number of media. Others were
shut down. Some of them resurfaced, but the new
owners were friends or associates of President
Marcos. Indictments against the media increased
in force and frequency, creating an all-pervasive
climate of fear and insecurity among media
professionals.
The turning point finally came in August
1983 with the assassination of opposition leader
Benigno Aquino. Suddenly, "alternative" media
began to surface. A handful of tabloid newspa¬
pers and radio stations created by journalists
dared to defy government instructions on how
to handle news stories, despite the constant
harassment and intimidation. Though they had
little or no advertising, they somehow managed
to survive and by late 1985 they had more credi¬
bility than the pro-Marcos "establishment"
media. In the end, they brought about their own
liberation, and in the process they liberated the
country as well.
The new head of government, Corazón
Aquino, the widow of the assassinated opposition
leader, kept her campaign promises. One of her
first acts was to free the media. Presidential
Decrees 33 and 90, which led to the worst abuses
against journalists and media institutions, were
revoked. More than 500 political prisoners, many
of them journalists, were released. A Presidential
Commission was set up to investigate all forms
of human rights violations, past and present.
Shreds of paper flutter from
a Manila building during a
popular demonstration in
1983 following the
assassination of opposition
leader Benigno Aquino.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
1
% m à
t r-
For the media, liberation proved to be heady.
Newspapers sprang up overnight and ran column
after column on opinions and letters to the editor.
Never before had the press, radio and television
enjoyed such freedom. The press promised the
new president a hundred-day "honeymoon"
during which time there was to be no adverse cri¬
ticism of the government. This was intended to
allow the president and ministers time to adjust
and make the transition.
But the "honeymoon" lasted barely a month.
As the then minister of information told a
Washington Post reporter, "...immediately after
the revolution, before anyone had a chance to do
anything wrong, the press turned on the govern¬
ment. There were personal attacks ridiculing the
eccentricity of this or that minister." (He came
under attack himself for delays in issuing press
passes for the presidential palace.)
As the end of the hundred days drew near,
the media began to criticize the president for her
"lack of major accomplishments so far". This
struck Corazón Aquino as eminently unfair.
"Getting rid of Marcos," she stated, "was no
mean feat, and so was the restoration of freedom,
and particularly press freedom." Although she
has publicly regretted the adverse media reporting
which gives the impression that government
policies do not do anyone any good, there is no
doubt that she is committed to freedom of the
press: "I would rather have a press that goes over¬
board than a censored press. ..even if reporters
don't always get their facts straight, and media
reporting sometimes takes 'destructive forms',"
she told the Press Foundation of Asia in April
1986.
The dangers of irresponsible
reporting and sensationalism
Readers in the Philippines today have never had
a greater choice. There are twenty-three newspa¬
pers, not to mention weekly magazines and other
publications, in fierce competition for readers and
advertisers.
To attract readers and stay in business, quite
a few newspapers have been indulging in sensa¬
tional reporting. Rumours are exaggerated out of
all proportion and sometimes presented as hard
facts. Irresponsible reporting is bringing into
question the newly regained credibility of the
media. President Aquino was even led to charge
that "there is too much disinformation going
around". The Archbishop of Manila, Jaime Car¬
dinal Sin, also criticized the media in a pastoral
letter that was read in all the Catholic churches
of the capital, accusing them of "tale-bearing and
vicious rumour-mongering" and asserting that
there was a definite tendency to undermine the
social order in the critical times the Philippines
were going through.
At a national conference on communication
and journalism held in June 1986, a group of 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
"The press destabilized
by rumour."
educators warned that certain publications were
tending towards the type of "wayward" media
that were prevalent during the period preceding
martial law. Certain senior journalists concurred,
especially as far as the "new" journalistic prac¬
tices were concerned, which one of them summed
up as follows: "Mere rumours are blown up as
factual stories. Confidence is sometimes violated.
Some resort to unethical means in getting stories.
All in all, there is mayhem..."
Whereas in the past Filipinos accused the
Western press of depicting their country as if it
were on the brink of civil war, many leaders in
the country agree that today the Filipino press
itself must take a good part of the blame for the
climate of uncertainty. They also accuse the
media of encouraging intrigue among top govern¬
ment officials, a practice that leads to acrimonious
and damaging political infighting.
The military have their own grievances. They
have accused reporters and broadcasters of giving
unusually heavy coverage to communist leaders.
Media professionals retort that the communist
rebel movement is important, and that its leaders
have made themselves readily available for com¬
ments and interviews.
Another common complaint concerns the
type of news covered. By and large, newspapers
are urban-oriented and what happens in the pro¬
vinces tends to be buried in the inside pages. Only
stories of crime, violence or natural disaster make
the headlines.
Among the many shortcomings of the media
in the Philippines, there is a lack of journalistic
professionalism. In spite of the freer environment,
which means that sources of information are
easier to approach, some journalists still rely pri¬
marily on press releases. According to the presi-
30
dent of Radio Philippines Network: "While we
may have gained precious freedom for journalistic
endeavours, some of us still find it difficult to
break the habit of being spoon-fed the news."
During the Marcos regime, the lack of press
freedom gave journalists an easy excuse for not
doing in-depth, investigative stories. Today, one
wonders just how many journalists have the
appropriate skills for that kind of reporting. If
more investigative reporting is not done, it is not
for a lack of issues: hidden wealth, human rights
abuses, the communist insurgency, graft and cor¬
ruption.. .all are stories worth doing in depth.
It may be that the present orientation of jour¬
nalists is part of the unwanted legacy of the past.
Fourteen years of repression stifled not only the
investigative capacities but also the imagination
of Filipino journalists. As the former president
of the National Press Club of the Philippines
noted, during the Marcos years the press was inca¬
pable of fostering young talent to take over from
their seniors. This was manifest when press
freedom was restored: semi-retired and expatriate
journalists had to be pressed back into active duty
to provide staff for the new publications.
Freedom on the airwaves
Traditionally, radio and television were entertain¬
ment oriented, but during the February revolu¬
tion stations became deeply involved in covering
the fast-changing political situation. This depar¬
ture in favour of the news did not last much
beyond the change of regime, though announcers
will now cut into regular programmes to cover
major national events.
The same mixed loyaltiesto Marcos or to
the new regimecan be found among radio and
television commentators. Unfortunately, they are
also open to the same kinds of criticism as the
press. Some radio stations loyal to Marcos have
been accused of "abusing freedom of expression",
to the point of polarizing the population. Even
the government-operated station has been taxed
with subjective reporting and, in some instances,
of systematically taking an anti-government
stance.
Concerned citizens have raised the issue, com¬
plaining of licentious and even seditious use of
the airwaves. "Distortion, libel and sedition are
rife in the broadcasting industry", noted a leading
columnist of the Philippine Daily Inquirer, who
attributed this deplorable situation to "overcrow¬
ding". There are 308 radio stations and 44 televi¬
sion stations, owned and operated by 96
companies. Of these, the government operates 25
radio stations nationwide and one television net¬
work. As a result, station managers tend to
choose "the more sensational broadcasters, who
attack the government instead of trying to main¬
tain a balanced newscast".
Another unhealthy practice in radio and
sometimes in television is the selling of block-
time, whereby the station sells a set number of
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
minutes or hours to an independent producer.
This has led certain unscrupulous broadcasters to
accept funds from politicians and use the time to
attack their opponents.
The new government has been caught bet¬
ween its seemingly sincere desire to foster
freedom of information and the need to protect
the democratic regime that was established by the
1986 revolution. Almost all the editors inter¬
viewed for this study stated that there is no
government censorship in the Philippines today.
There have been a number of cases, however, that
show how fragile freedom can be and how great
the temptation to intervene.
A journalist working for the DYEC People
Power station, for example, claimed that the
management temporarily suspended him for
advocating land reform on his programme.
According to him, the landlords in question, who
also happen to own many businesses in the area,
threatened to withdraw advertising. When
newsmen questioned the validity of official
figures on cases of cholera, the minister of health
refused to give statistics, claiming that they might
adversely affect export industries. And many
observers believe that there have been attempts
to withhold information concerning aborted
coups. In 1986, cases were reported, then denied,
only to be confirmed later, to the confusion of
the public.
Yet no one can accuse the present govern¬
ment of arresting or killing journalists. Cases of
harassment and intimidation have generally con¬
cerned government media, and cases of with¬
holding information are usually about financial
matters.
It is worth noting that when the new govern¬
ment took control of a number of broadcasting
stations, it had no clear-cut policy on their role
and functions. In the aftermath of the revolution,
people were anxious to exercise their newfound
freedom. The management of the government
stations either took no notice or actually con¬
doned criticism of the government and official
personalities as part of the newly regained "demo¬
cratic space".
Thus, as various sectors of society attempted
to destabilize the Aquino administration, the
government found itself helpless. It could not
even count on the state media as allies. When
government station managers decided to dismiss
a number of overly critical commentators, the
latter accused the government of censorship.
The government justified its position by in¬
voking the sanctity of employer-employee loyalty.
Whoever wishes to criticize the government
should first leave government service and join the
privately-owned media. But this position inevi¬
tably raises a question: to whom do journalists
working on state-owned media owe their loyalty?
To government officials only? Or to the public
as well, who pay the taxes needed to keep these
stations operating? Do journalists working for
state-owned media not have a duty to respect the
public's right to full information?
To answer these questions, it could be said
that criticism of the government can be seen as
self-criticism; its aim is to improve government
service and not to malign it. However, it cannot
be denied that there have been cases of intentional
maliciousness designed to destabilize the govern¬
ment. The secretary of state for the press summed
up the situation well: in his opinion, criticism of
the government is permissible so long as presen¬
tation is fair and balanced. If this policy is faith¬
fully implemented by the government and by the
media, then the issue of censorship in the govern¬
ment media can one day be laid to rest.
The newsroom of a Filipino
journal.
Extract from a study by the
Asian Institute of Journalism,
published in The Vigilant Press:
a collection of case studies,
No. 103 of Unesco's Reports
and Papers on Mass
Communication series. Pans,
1989. The study was carried
out by Concepción L.
Madarang, Reynaldo P.
Monreal, Elizabeth K.
Dimasuay, Maria Teresa R.
Robles and Floranel Rosario
Braid (consultant), under the
direction of Ramon R. Tuazon. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
USSR:
the
thaw
Three days after the accident at the
Chernobyl nuclear power plant In the USSR,
a photographer flies over the site.
CHERNOBYL
BEFORE AND AFTER
by Vassil Plioutch
Deputy Editor of
Uteraturna Ukrayina, Kiev
X HE weekly magazine Literaturna Ukrayina
was not part of the clandestine press and does
not date from the age of perestroika. It was
founded in 1927, but it remained virtually
unknown in the West until 26 April 1986, the
date of the explosion at the Chernobyl nuclear
power plant.
A month before the accident, Literaturna
Ukrayina had published a highly-critical article
on the faults of the plant and the lack of
respect paid to technical standards during its
construction. The author of the article and the
editorial staff were inundated with indignant
complaints. They were accused of malice and
of trying to undermine the reputation of hard¬
working engineers. What saved them from the
serious consequences which might have fol¬
lowed publication of this article was...the catas¬
trophe itself! The same cannot be said, alas,
of the thousands of Ukrainians, Byelorussians
and Russians who were bombarded with radi¬
oactive dust. But today the whole world knows
that story.
We can now see how cramped our
common European home is, and how fragile
and vulnerable are the peace and happiness
within it. There is no need to erect a barrier
of medium-range missiles to see it go up in
smoke. A moment of carelessness in the sup¬
posedly peaceful use of the atom is enough.
What is the point, in a country like France,
of painstakingly equipping nuclear plants with
a double or triple security system, when the
slightest act of negligence committed else¬
where is enough to spark off a general catas¬
trophe? Take it from me, as a man working
at Kiev, 120 km from the plant, who receives
a daily dose of radiation: I have first-hand
knowledge of the tragedy of the sick children
for whom Canada sent a second plane-load of
medication, and of the incredible difficulties
in certain districts of Kiev and Jitomirwhich
were not included in the security zone around
the plant and which, four years later, are
having to be urgently evacuated...
In such circumstances, journalists' courage
and public-spiritedness will never be suffi¬
ciently appreciated. We know from personal
experience what they can accomplish. After the
Chernobyl catastrophe, our magazine was so
successful in mobilizing opinion on ecological
problems that we managed to bring about the
closure of a nuclear power plant built on a tec¬
tonic fault in the Crimea, as well as have work
stopped on the Chiguirinsk plant on the banks
of the Dnieper River, the source of water for
35 million people.
Extract from a contribution to the Informal East-West
Press Meeting held at Unesco Headquarters, Paris, 27-2S
February 1990.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
THE BURDEN
OF FEAR
by Vitali Korotich
Editor-in-chief of
Ogoniok, Moscow
I
N 1986, our magazine had less than 300,000
subscribers. Today, there are 4.5 million. It is
the kind of magazine that can only exist in a
country where the government is inefficient.
We receive an enormous quantity of letters
which people should send to government
ministers, if they had confidence in them.
Instead they write to us, journalists who work
for the popular press and, within an unstable
power structure, bear the enormous burden
of responsibility for what is going on in the
country.
People are still living in fear. They are
paralysed with fear. I think that if Unesco
organized a conference on hatred, all that
hatred which has brought together or divided
Europe, much would be learned. Societies have
been built on hatred and contempt for those
who live differently. Only very slowly will we
be able to free ourselves from hatred and fear.
In Eastern Europe we stopped taking an
interest in each other decades ago. For a very
long time, what was happening in Poland,
Czechoslovakia or Bulgaria was of no interest
to Soviet readers. Now that we are facing up
to reality, it is important that we should
understand one another, that we should
approach each other in a new way. We must
help one another to safeguard our newly-
acquired freedom for, it must be emphasized,
the conservative forces understand one
another much better than do those who aspire
to democratic reforms.
We need newspapers and magazines which
could circulate freely in several countries at the
same time. It seems to me essential that we
should start producing European TV
programmes right away. This is highly rele¬
vant to the immediate problem of our survival
and the attitude we ought to have towards one
another.
As yet we have no law on the press in our
country. As in some other countries, much
depends on the goodwill of the people and on
that of the authorities. We must fight to
obtain coherent legislation to guarantee the
freedom of the press, which is still subject to
censorship and other pressures. We are also
facing serious material problems, such as a lack
of paper. The weekly Argumenty i Fakty, which
with a print-run of 33 million has the largest
circulation of any magazine in the world, is
regularly unable to supply hundreds of thou¬
sands of its subscribers through lack of
newsprint. When the circulation of our maga¬
zine began to rise we had to reduce the
number of pages and colour inserts. And
although it is supposed to be a weekly, it actu¬
ally takes over a week to print, with the result
that it appears after our publication date. We
are told that this is the printer's fault, which
is probably true, but it worries me to see tech¬
nical problems like these hindering the
progress of democracy today.
Extract from a contribution to the Informal East-West
Press Meeting held at Unesco Headquarters, Paris, 27-28
February 1990.
A Soviet evening paper rolls off the press.
'WE LOOK
INTO THE FUTURE
WITH
APPREHENSION
AND HOPE'
by Ivan T. Frolov
Editor-ln-chlef of
Pravda, Moscow
MrLORE than ever before, an honest word
freely spoken has a special value for us today....
Even the most bitter truth can motivate people
to perform great feats, while gift-wrapped lies
peddled by the media can breed nothing but
apathy. When words do not square with
everyday reality, they can cause a painful
dualism in the public mind and breed
hypocrisy and double standards.
The objective of perestroïka, or restruc¬
turing, in the Soviet Union is not only to over
haul the economy and improve the social sit¬
uation but to cure the moral ills of society. The
mass media have a special role to play in this
new situation.... Every newspaper, magazine,
radio programme and TV network should
stimulate discussion of the most sensitive issues
in the life of society. Recent developments
have not been uncontroversial and not all
editors welcome their new-found freedom.
Many topics considered taboo in the past are
now being widely debated, but the low level
of culture and lack of civic responsibility pro¬
voke destructive urges and sow confusion in
the minds of people rather than motivating
them to constructive action.
Pravda is published by the Central Com¬
mittee of the Communist Party of the Soviet
Union, and its main objective in the conditions
of glasnost, or openness, is to keep its readers
informed about the life of the Party both at
grass-roots level and at the top.... We had to
overcome a lot of opposition before the paper
began to provide extensive coverage of
meetings of the Politburo, the supreme organ
of the Central Committee, on a regular basis.
In a totally unprecedented development, the
paper published a verbatim report of the
February 1990 Plenary Meeting of the Central
Committee, which was marked by a heated dis¬
cussion of the most sensitive issues in the life
of the country. We are convinced that this was
the right thing to do. We trust our readers and
do not want to conceal difficult problems.
Genuine freedom of speech is unthinkable
without genuine trust between a newspaper
and its readership.
Our main objective is to promote innova¬
tive ideas generated by perestroika, the policy
of the Communist Party and the moral revival
of society.... Our readers expect us to tell them
the truth, complete and undisguised, and we
should avoid sensationalism. In fact Pravda
which means "truth"should speak with the
voice of truth as Lenin understood the word....
What are the prospects for the future and
for the last decade of the twentieth century?
What new developments can we expect this
year? We look into the future with apprehen¬
sion and hope. We are concerned because many
acute problems have not been resolved. The
most pressing problems are to cure the
country's ailing economy, improve the situa¬
tion for consumers, defuse social tensions and
resolve ethnic conflicts.
But we believe that there is hope too, and
it is not just wishful thinking. This hope is sus¬
tained by the success of perestroika and the real
changes brought about by the political and
economic reforms and a new moral climate in
the country. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Restrictions
on the
freedom of
information
have been
lifted
progressively
in Poland,
but media
pluralism still
lies in
the future
Turning
mW J
Golgotha (1966), a poster
34 by Piotr Bednarskl, Poland.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
a new page by Karol Jakubowicz
Detail from a frieze of
paintings In the Gdansk hall
where the first clandestine
congress of Solidarity was
held in 1981.
KAROL JAKUBOWICZ, of
Poland, is editor of Messages
and Opinions, a quarterly
journal of broadcasting
research, and chairman of his
country's Broadcasting Reform
Commission.
IJLs the American sociologist Jeffrey C. Goldfarb
has pointed out, totalitarianism is best understood
as the cultural form necessary for modern
tyranny. The Stalinist power structure sought to
subsume the totality of culture in order to impose
what Orwell called "thought control". When
that proved unattainable, at least in Poland, the
goal of "cognitive control" was pursued instead.
It was assumed that if people had access only to
officially sanctioned news and views, a sufficient
degree of control over their thinking could be
exercised, at least in public. The private sphere
did not matter so much, as long as it was kept
private.
One way of achieving this was by "semantic
control". As Adam Michnik, a leading opposi¬
tion thinker, has put it: "The communists who
arrived at the end of the Second World War suc¬
ceeded in imposing false solutions because they
succeeded in imposing their language." It was a
political language, constructed to automatically
reproduce and perpetuate Communist Party
domination. Inability or unwillingness to use that
language created a "silence barrier" which
precluded successful participation in political life.
Of course, only hermits could avoid func¬
tioning in both public and private spheres and
using both languages, at least to some extent. The
kind of individual and collective schizophrenia
that this produced has to be experienced to be
believed.
Yet, except in the early 1950s, official
thinking was never completely imposed. Firstly,
Polish media always provided extensive informa¬
tion on developments in the Western world, and
Polish television has for two decades now offered
just about every Western programme, series or
film it could afford to buy and which was not
blatantly anti-communist. Secondly, magazines
and newspapers (including one daily) published
by the Roman Catholic Church or by Catholic
organizations, as well as other Churches and
denominations, have always provided a channel
for the expression of dissident views on all
matters of importance to the Polish people.
Finally, since 1976 Poland has had a rich profu¬
sion of underground publishers of magazines and
books which openly questioned the legitimacy
of the country's political system.
Thus the unofficial private sphere obstinately
refused to stay private. It kept intruding into the
official oneand now it has taken over.
Dismantling the monopoly
"Observance of the constitutional principles of
freedom of speech and publication" featured
prominently in third place on the list of twenty-
one demands addressed to the government by
Gdansk shipyard workers in August 1980 during
the strike which provided the impetus for the
birth of the Solidarity movement. A policy docu¬
ment adopted at Solidarity's first congress in 1981
came out in favour of the "socialization of the
media": "The media of social communication are
the property of society and must serve the entire
society and operate under its control." Other
concepts put forward by Solidarity, such as
"access to the media" and "communication as
empowerment", combine respect for the right to
communicate as a basic human right and a means
of satisfying a fundamental social need.
When liberalization of the media system
finally began in 1988, it was prompted by the
desire of a weakening communist system to com¬
promise without giving up control of the major
means of communication. These reforms con¬
sisted mainly of:
1) changing the law to make possible the
emergence of a licensed and supervised private
and/or commercial sector in such areas as book
and newspaper publishing and film production;
2) lifting the many politically-motivated
restrictions on what could be said in the official
media;
3) accepting and creating legal and technical
conditions for the flow of foreign media content
into the country (from satellite television, or from
foreign radio stations whose jamming had already
been stopped by then).
This was hardly enough, however, and so
when the round table conference between the
government and the opposition took place in
spring 1989, Solidarity went back to its original
demands for a radical reform of the media system.
The government adopted a dual policy: more
liberal with regard to the print media, and much
tougher with regard to broadcasting. As a result, 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
publishers no longer needed a licence from the
censorship office to launch a newspaper or
periodicalregistration of its existence was
enough. Censorship was liberalized and many
publications were exempted (especially scholarly
journals and those published by organizations).
Newsprint allocation was to end in 1990, as
indeed it has.
As regards the broadcasting media, however,
the government insisted on retaining both its
monopoly and the institutional controls over
them. Solidarity gained access to air time, but
only in the form of weekly 45-minute
programmes on national radio and television.
Later, the Roman Catholic Church signed an
agreement with Polish Radio and TV which gave
it more extensive access to both national and
regional stations.
When the Solidarity-led government was
formed in autumn 1989, the media monopoly
was thus still intact, as was the apparatus of.
censorshipto say nothing of the legal underpin¬
nings of the system. If freedom of speech and of
information were to prevail, all that had to be
eliminated.
As far as the print media were concerned, the
Communist Party's main tool for maintaining
control was a huge publishing and media con¬
glomerate, RSW Prasa-Ksiazka-Ruch, nominally
a co-operative but in fact run by the Party itself
and serving as its main source of finance. In its
heyday it published 47 per cent of press titles in
Poland, including 70 per cent of the total circu¬
lation of daily and weekly newspapers. It also
monopolized press distribution, ran all the news¬
stands, operated a number of publishing houses,
press agencies, printing plants and so on. The con¬
glomerate has now been dissolved by act of parlia¬
ment, and a special commission is developing a
plan on the disposal of its extensive holdings. All
the newspapers and periodicals once published by
the conglomerate are now free to go their own
way. They can transform themselves into co¬
operatives of their own staff, join with others into
larger entities, seek publishersand stand or fall
on their own merits.
Another act of parliament has abolished cen¬
sorship. If a newspaper or other publication
breaks the law under the penal code, it can of
course be hauled before a court, but otherwise
there are no formal or institutional limitations
on freedom of speech.
The final vestige of the old system of cogni¬
tive control, state monopoly of broadcasting, is
doomed to extinction very soon. Monopoly is to
be abolished and licences will be granted to as
many broadcasters as there are frequencies
available.
A new challenge
The rapid social and economic changes in post-
communist countries have created an unusually
36 high level of need for opportunities for active
communication, especially in the field of politics. .
On the one hand, the many emerging political
parties and groups are seeking support among the
population at large. On the other, individuals are
becoming politically active as they try to affect
the reshaping of the political and social system.
Also, a profusion of publishing and broadcasting
ventures, not necessarily political, have sprung
up as many individuals and groups seek to exer¬
cise the freedom of expression long denied them.
Their financial viability remains to be tested,
however, now that there are no subsidies or cross-
subsidies within larger media organizations.
Recognition of freedom of speech and infor¬
mation, and removal of restrictions on them,
amounts only to what might be called a negative
means of creating the conditions to satisfy the
need to communicate. The traditional Western
concept of freedom of speech, now espoused also
in post-communist countries, allows that freedom
to be realized within the means at the disposal
of each individual or group, making it the
freedom of the well-to-dofreedom of the press
for those who own it.
Thus excessive deregulation, sometimes con¬
ducted in the name of removing all restrictions
on freedom of speech, may be counterproductive.
In addition to promoting the birth and possible
dominance of commercial media, it also lays the
media system open to yet another threat: infiltra¬
tion and takeover or control by foreign capital.
The truly democratic society should recog¬
nize its obligation to provide all its members with
the ways and means of exercising the right to
communicate. Therefore, the challenge before
Poland and other post-communist countries is to
develop a positive, active policy of promoting
democratic and pluralistic media policies and
systems. This requires a commitment to support
or subsidize the founding or running of press and
broadcasting media by minorities and groups
with insufficient resources. Also needed is a new
definition of a public information service, no
longer as one-way communication from the top
down, but as pluralistic and constructive dialogue.
If these policies are adopted, the media system
of post-communist countries will encompass
three sectors:
a financially secure system of public service
broadcasting, fully capable of discharging its obli¬
gations towards society;
socially-motivated privately or collectively
owned media speaking for, on behalf of, or to
various groups, parties, organizations, minorities,
and regional communities, assisted where neces¬
sary out of public funds in line with policies pub¬
licly defined and open to review;
commercial media.
All three sectors are necessary in a fully deve¬
loped media system. If Poland and other post-
communist countries can find a way to ensure
their existence, they will be blazing a trail for
other countries to follow.
by Morten Giersing
fS&sY_~.
Symbol of freedom on a
Belgian wall.
MORTEN GIERSING
is chief of the section of free
flow of Information and
communications research in
Unesco's Communication
Development and Free Flow of
Information Division.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
F,REEDOM of expression is not an op¬
tion but a fundamental human right.
It is affirmed in Article 19 of the
Universal Declaration of Human
Rights and also set forth in the Pre¬
amble to the Declaration in these
terms: "...the advent of a world in
which human beings shall enjoy free¬
dom of speech and belief and free¬
dom from fear and want has been
proclaimed as the highest aspiration
of the common people...".
Freedom of expression goes
hand in hand with freedom of infor¬
mation. Without access to news and
knowledge, it is a limited concept.
This is why press and media freedom
is organically linked to these basic
freedoms.
Certain traditions of press free¬
dom undoubtedly reflect historic de¬
velopments in specific countries. The
subsidies given to newspapers in
some northern European countries
ostensibly to secure press diversity-
would be seen in other parts of the
world, for example in the United
States, as questionable governmen¬
tal interference.
However, across all the differ¬
ences, the concept of press freedom
does have a core meaning, which
commits all societies. Article 1 9 of the
Universal Declaration of Human
Rights states that: "Everyone has the
right to freedom of opinion and ex¬
pression; this right includes freedom
to hold opinions without interference
and to seek, receive and impart in¬
formation and ideas through any
media and regardless of frontiers."
Unesco's Constitution reflects
this universal commitment in its first
article, which stipulates that to real¬
ize its purpose the Organization will
"Collaborate in the work of advanc¬
ing the mutual knowledge and un¬
derstanding of peoples, through all
means of mass communication and
to that end recommend such inter¬
national agreements as may be
necessary to promote the free flow
of ideas by word and image."
The principle of "free flow of in¬
formation" presupposes the ability of
all parties to produce information.
This has been reflected in Unesco's
communication programme by the
unquestioned priority given to the im¬
provement of communication capac¬
ities in the developing countries. The
major elements of this programme
are assistance to national and region¬
al news agencies, notably through
the Southern and Eastern Africa
News Agencies Development project
(SEANAD), and its sister projects in
West Africa (WANAD) and the Carib¬
bean (CANAD); the development of
broadcasting, from the community
level to regional and international ex¬
changes; the setting up of rural
newspapers; and professional train¬
ing schemes.
But should the "free flow" be ac¬
companied by initiatives to ensure a
"balance"of different viewpoints
or of different information sources?
This question has given rise to much
controversy.
Throughout the 1980s, Unesco
spoke of "a free flow and wider and
better balanced dissemination of in¬
formation". But fears were expressed
that the Organization's initiatives to
"better balance" information flows
could impinge on press freedom.
In its new Medium-Term Plan,
covering the years 1990-1995, a for¬
mulation was agreed on which Unesco
hoped would dispel all misunder¬
standings. It underlined Unesco's at¬
tachment to an uncompromising
"free flow of information" and took
great care that every reference to in¬
itiatives to "balance" flows was im¬
mediately followed by an assurance
that this should occur "without any
obstacle to freedom of expression".
A key paragraph in Unesco's Com¬
munication in the Service of Human¬
ity Programme expresses the position
in this way:
"...the concern of the Organiza¬
tion is to ensure a free flow of infor¬
mation at international as well as
national levels, and its wider and bet¬
ter balanced dissemination, without
any obstacle to the freedom of ex¬
pression, and to strengthen commu¬
nication capacities in the developing
countries, so that they may partici¬
pate more actively in the communi¬
cation process."
Recent activities in this area in¬
clude the publication of a collection
of case studies on The Vigilant Press
and a global survey on The Protection
of Sources. A third international study
on the impact of new communication
technologies on information plural¬
ism is forthcoming, and a worldwide
survey of journalists' access to infor¬
mation will be launched in 1991.
While studies and reporting are
important tools in bringing press free¬
dom questions to the forefront of the
international media debate, real ad¬
vances can be measured only in the
actual progress of independent me¬
dia worldwide. The recent emergence
of an independent press in Eastern
Europe was promptly met by an in¬
formal East-West meeting of editors
and journalists convened by Unesco
early in 1990. The meeting has since
led to several practical initiatives, es¬
pecially in the area of journalism and
management training, and a parallel
event on independent media in Africa
is scheduled for late 1990.
Unesco's commitment to free¬
dom of expression, reconfirmed and
revitalized in recent months, is a fun¬
damental part of its mandate. The
defence of press freedom requires
constant alertness. The situation is
not new; it was realized two hundred
years ago at the dawn of modern
democracy, when the distinguished
Irish statesman John Philpot Curran
made his renowned observation:
"The condition upon which God hath
given liberty to man is eternal
vigilance." 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Media empires:
a necessary evil?
by Joseph Fitchett
Giant media
groups have
masterminded
a technological
revolution
with some
unexpected
spin-offs
38
XHE emergence of media mega-groups is one of
the striking features of our age. Sometimes
national, often international, these conglomerates
dwarf the biggest media operations of previous
generations. Sometimes they attain a position
close to horizontal dominance in publishing or
broadcasting in a region or even a nation. Some¬
times they strive for vertical integration, with
holdings in every sector of an industry. This con¬
centration means that they are fewer in number
and therefore stand out from their competitors.
As a result, debate about the proper functioning
of the press seems likely to focus in the next few
years on the role of these media empires.
In the 1980s, international debate about the
media was dominated by quarrels over censorship
and press freedom. This agenda among media-
watchers seems to be losing urgency now that the
Soviet bloc has largely abandoned ideological con¬
frontation and started to pay at least lip service
to the values of Western democracy. In this sense,
the West has "won" the battle against press regu¬
lation in favour of a concept closer to a free
market for the media.
But these quarrels about the power of a free
press have been buried by events, not settled.
Sooner or later, we will have to look again at
the self-congratulatory euphoria among some
Western commentators, who say that changes
in Eastern Europe can be "explained" by the
impact of communications and therefore of
the press. In practice, it is hard to find any evi¬
dence that changes in Eastern Europe, Central
America or China owed much to the role of the
local press.
Western electronic media, by conveying
developments in different Eastern European
countries, undoubtedly heartened opponents of
the regimes in these countries. But "press
freedom" was a rather insignificant part of a
larger symbolic image of "Western" freedom and
prosperity. Extravagant claims about the role of
the media in the revolutionary changes of 1989
must be put on a par with French leaders' habit
of dwelling on the coincidence that the changes
last year occurred simultaneously with celebra¬
tions to mark the bicentenary of the French
Revolution.
Multi-media groups
of a new kind
The issue has already been spotlighted from
another angle in the 1990s: the power of media
groups. Seen by some as a new evil empire, they
may be a necessary evil of our time.
Ironically, the end of the Cold War has
brought about the destruction of the great media
empires that rose and fell in communist-run
nations. So concern has shifted to the role of
Western capitalists forging multi-media groups of
spectacular size and transnational scale. Inciden¬
tally, some of these Western press groups are
seeking a major role in redeveloping the media
in Eastern Europe.
Many of the old familiar questionsin short,
what kind of media is good for you?will be
articulated anew, this time around an emerging
trend in the West to concentrate the media in
fewer, bigger holdings. As we try to get to grips
with this phenomenon, some fundamental ques¬
tions need to be asked. Is the trend inevitable?
Will it enhance or undermine freedom? What will
improve quality and what will weaken it?
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The headlines tell the story, often in a con¬
fused manner, of a fundamental trend toward
media empires of a new kind. Typical flashes
show developments such as media magnates
Rupert Murdoch and Robert Maxwell trying to
fuse newspapers and television; the Japanese com¬
pany Sony and the American media giant,
Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS), bridging
remote cultures; international alliances fighting
for control of French television; technical stan¬
dards converging to allow global broadcasting.
At the start of the 1980s, the media were
glaring exceptions to the overall pattern of re¬
structuring that was being forced on all the tradi¬
tional sectors in industrialized democracies.
Technology had come to the end of a cycle, with
satellite broadcasting finally ready to challenge
the traditional ways of doing business. In many
cases, the inroads of television had driven
newspaper revenues and profits to an all-time
low. Magazines, caught in their old formats,
needed to be massively overhauled and renewed.
Even news agencies were unable to survive unless
they created new kinds of businesses, a notable
example being the spectacular success of Reuters
in developing electronic financial services.
To survive this transitional period, smash
through old habits, bring in new technology and
usher in a new era, the Western media concen¬
trated their assets into fewer, stronger companies
designed to weather the storms of change. Was
it necessarily the best approach? Perhaps there
was no alternative.
The lesson of the 1980s
A major lesson of the 1980s was that any enter¬
prise needed to operate on a vast scale in order
to prosper in a period of global economic muta¬
tion. New technologies seemed to be crackling
to life like an exploding boxcar of ammunition.
Markets were being redrawn as people's habits
changed under the impact of revolutions in trans¬
portation and communications. Suddenly people
in Tokyo and Sào Paulo, New Delhi and New
York, Lagos and Johannesburg, wanted and
expected to consume the same products, from
Japanese-made transistor radios to world-class
entertainment or information services.
Instead of buying radios packaged differently
in each country in order to appeal to local sensi¬
bilities, customers all over the planet turned to
the severe black boxes that were a Sony trade¬
mark andagainst the prevailing wisdom about
marketing caught on as a selling point. The 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
attractions of the readily recognizable, familiar
local product evaporated under the impact of
standardized products. Television around the
world lost much of its local flavour as interna¬
tional products gained more air time.
Analysing this new, fiercer international
competition, specialists frequently used the word
"entrepreneurial", meaning that success required
new ideas from dedicated inventors. The stress
on individual vision and dedication was a
refreshing reminder of virtues such as initiative
and readiness to run risks.
To have lasting success, however, an
entrepreneur needed to be able to sell quickly into
a large market so that he earned enough to
expand. This concern about the size of the market
was the driving force behind the European Com¬
munity's commitment in 1985 to develop a
Europe-wide single market by 1992. The need for
continuous innovation was even a factor in new
Soviet thinking that recognized the need to break
down an empire that was not working in order
to obtain greater diversity of expression and, it
is to be hoped, release more energies.
In most industrialized countries, which do
not have media monopolies, change ran in the
opposite direction. Concerned about being able
to compete profitably, media owners pursued a
visionary concept of expanding their markets
across borders and across sectors, and many of
them sought to diversify their investments in
ways intended to provide profitable synergies. In
France, the publishing group Hachette dreamed
of creating an almost self-sustaining circle of news
media and magazines, publishing, television, films
and even space technology. The plan, to carica¬
ture it only slightly, was that news coverage
would produce stories, which could be turned
into books and then into documentaries or films
which could be transmitted by satellite.
A global market
Similar visions spurred the rise of similarly ambi¬
tious media groups in many countries including
Britain and Italy, Japan and India, Brazil and the
United States. The trend was perhaps pursued
more boldly in Europe than elsewhere: despite
the obstacles of overcoming language barriers,
Europeans were under greater pressure to develop
a single market large enough to recoup the invest¬
ments needed to competein magazines or tele¬
vision, films or even journalismin the global
market.
In the United States and Japan, these pres¬
sures have, on the whole, concentrated media
ownership in fewer, stronger hands: in Europe,
on the whole, they have helped to forge alliances
among different types of media holdings. In both
cases, the objective is to mobilize enough
resources to survive the transition and emerge in
a strong position for the late 1990s.
Beyond their capacity for survival, the
emerging large media groups can be credited with
many benefits, of which the most important is
unquestionably innovation. This may sound para¬
doxical after so many attacks on media groups
accusing them of standardizing their products and
pitching them at the lowest level to obtain the
largest market, but in the process they often
develop technology that restores the autonomy
of new, smaller and stronger competitors.
Large media groups were instrumental in
creating a global market for video cassettes that
contributed to a crisis in the movie industry, espe¬
cially outside Hollywood. Today, revenues from
cassettes exceed the box office earnings from most
films, but the cassette market has provided a
major new revenue source for the industry, espe¬
cially for films intended for smaller, specialized
audiences.
Even films with strong local appeal in their
country of origin were threatened, as the cost of
movie-making grew too high for a single country
to offer a big enough potential market. Now
minority-interest film-makers have more oppor¬
tunities to find investment backing because of
the additional potential revenue from the video
market.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
The broadcasting satellite
Astra.
Televiewing in Japan (left)
and Egypt (right).
Invariably, innovations involve large invest¬
ments, to pay for the new technology and sus¬
tain it long enough for the public to adopt it. By
mobilizing funds, the big media groups have been
the midwives to a global explosion of specialized
magazines on subjects ranging from travel and
women's interests to sexually titillating "true sto¬
ries" or computer services available by telephone.
With German investors now dominating key
sectors in the French market for periodicals and
European proprietors and products making big
inroads in the US market, there can be no doubt
that the improved overall performance of maga¬
zines owes a great deal to the intensified interna¬
tional competition between giant media groups.
Two innovations stand out in any evaluation
of the impact of these mega-groups. The successful
campaign to introduce new printing technology
in Europe must be largely credited to the single-
handed determination of Rupert Murdoch, the
Australian-born publisher whose main business
is now in London. After taking over The Times,
London's venerable mainstream newspaper,
Murdoch introduced electronic production
instead of traditional type-setting, defying the
unions that had prevented other British papers
from switching to the new technology.
It was a daring gamble, risking financial dis¬
aster and even violence, but Murdoch rode out
the unions' siege. His costly victory transformed
the economic outlook for the whole industry. If
The Times could be produced on computers,
without typesetters, so could other newspapers.
As â result, funds quickly emerged for a new
quality dailythe first such fresh start in Fleet
Street since the Second World Warand The
Independent has become The Times's toughest
competitor.
The impact of Murdoch's victory has echoed
beyond Britain, helping newspapers large and
small in other Western European countries to
keep pace with other industries that have had
to override union objections to job-killing
technology.
When the media make the news
The repercussions have been just as great from
a second innovation that could only have come
from a media group with deep enough pockets
to pay for high-flying visions: the Cable News
Network (CNN) of Turner Broadcasting. By
using satellites for worldwide, round-the-clock
broadcasting of news, CNN has revolutionized
our sense of the pace of history and news-
gathering. Government officials take account of
what they call the "CNN factor", meaning that
CNN coverage of breaking news is capable
of turning an event into a global issue almost
instantaneously.
As CNN broadcasts pictures of a press con¬
ference or a natural disaster somewhere in the
world, capitals everywhere else are immediately
involved. Stock markets oscillate, parliamentary
questions are asked, the press starts speculating.
It seems clear already that CNNand the quick¬
ened pace of all media coverage that CNN has
stimulatedis starting to play a role in shaping
the outcome of events. Even if the international
media do not initiate the great human movements
that make history, the coverageinstantaneous,
near to saturation, heavily larded with
commenthas created a new matrix in which
diplomacy must operate. Because of their size, the
big media groups have great potential for
safeguarding the role of the press. A big, rich and
diversified publisher can stand up to the pressures
of a single advertiser or group of advertisersor
even to a government. In an era when many
nations' budgets are no larger than the funds avail¬
able to drug traffickers or even terrorists, it is
reassuring that some of the press is rich and
powerful enough to withstand bribery. Similarly,
big media organizations have the resources to
help protect their journalists, so the freedom of
the pressto get the news and publish itbenefits
from their power.
But the big media groups have often failed 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
to use their potential to improve quality. The pat¬
tern of awards for public-service journalism in the
United States clearly reveals the strength of
smaller, independent papers in this respect. In
covering news of planetary concernecological
and other global trends, problems in developing
countries, defence of human rights the establish¬
ment press, despite its resources, has often trailed
behind smaller, more concerned specialists.
Size, by its very nature, seems to blunt the
sense of individual initiative that so often is the
source of history-making journalism. Small
newspapers, not big media groups, often break
new ground with stories of corruption, pollution
or surprising shifts in public attitudes because
they are close to the local situations. Such sto¬
ries are often pivotal precisely because they are
not on the agenda of the politicians, whose daily
activities are the focus of the metropolitan
newspapers.
Although the big media have the stature to
protect their journalists, they rarely endanger
themselves, either physically or politically. In
Japan, for example, which has the world's largest-
selling newspapers, reporters operate in press
clubs that suppress much of the news, and none
of the newspapers runs the risk of providing more
independent coverage. Even in Britain, few
newspapers have ever rebelled against the system
of government briefing, known as the lobby, that
prevents reporters from identifying the source of
news stories.
The return of quality journalism
Many journalists have found it frustrating to
work in organizations run by media magnates
such as Rupert Murdoch in Britain or Robert
Hersant in France. For example, The Times is
reportedly suffering because Mr. Murdoch's funds
are being heavily drained by his satellite televi¬
sion venture, Sky Channel. Similarly, in France,
the need to put together large groups of investors
for expensive ventures, such as a television
channel, means that multiple political influences
are at work in the media.
Even government intervention, which in
France plays a substantial role in decisions about
who runs newspapers and broadcasting stations,
has been ineffective in imposing any guarantees
about the quality and variety of the content of
publications or programming. While the new
technology offers the potential of a closer match
between media and public by bringing specialized
audiences within commercial reach, so far it has
not noticeably improved the media.
In terms of sheer economic efficiency, there
is mounting evidence that the media behemoth,
far from being a new kind of animal that benefits
from cross-connections among its different limbs,
is liable to prove an inefficient and wasteful crea¬
ture with little sense of direction.
The future, once thought to be bringing
mega-corporations that would provide a full
entertainment cycle starting with the raw
material of events, seems more likely to bring
smaller units newspapers and magazines, televi¬
sion production companies, film-makers,
publishersthat excel in their own specialities.
They can exploit the new technology to operate
profitably in domains and markets once thought
uneconomic.
Similar prospects exist for the media in coun¬
tries with little tradition of modern communica¬
tions. Often accused of squeezing small countries
and weakly defended cultures from the interna¬
tional consciousness, the media groupsby
forging international markets and developing
cheaper technology have opened up wider per¬
spectives in which newcomers in the press and
in entertainment can make themselves heard.
And the strength of the local press in any country
will be a decisive factor in determining how much
and how well the rest of the world follows affairs
there.
To break the constricting old order, we
needed nothing less than the mega-power of the
huge consortia, dedicated to their balance sheets,
to mobilize the vast funds to transform media
technology and markets. It was a necessary evil,
imposing the new technologies that, in turn, will
give back the media to writers and publishers
whose first loyalty is to their audiences.
The Berlin headquarters of
the German media magnate
Axel Springer.
JOSEPH FITCHETT,
American journalist, is a
correspondent on East-West
affairs and other aspects of
international political and
cultural life with the
International Herald Tribune. A
former Middle-Eastern
correspondent for the London
Observer, he appears regularly
as a commentator on
television in the United States
and elsewhere.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF..
Pedal power
More people depend on the
bicycle for private
transportation than on any
other vehicle, according to a
study by the WorldWatch
Institute, a research
organization based in
Washington, D.C. The world's
800 million bicycles
outnumber cars by 2 to 1, and
with an annual production
rate 3 times that of cars, the
gap is sure to widen. Bicycle-
friendly countries include
China, where city workers are
paid an allowance for
commuting by bike; Japan,
whose government funds cycle
parking facilities at stations;
and the Netherlands, which
aims to keep uninterrupted
cycle routes despite the high
density of automobile traffic.
Cabbage and cancer
Scientists have suspected for
years that a wide variety of
fruits and vegetables may help
the body fight cancer. It is
known, for example, that
members of ethnic groups
who consume large quantities
of garlic, onions and leeks
have lower stomach cancer
rates. The journal of the
American National Cancer
Institute recently reported that
a chemical has been identified
in vegetables such as cabbage,
broccoli, Brussels sprouts and
cauliflower which appears to
reduce the risk of breast
cancer by speeding up the
process by which the body
metabolizes the female
hormone oestrogen.
Seeing is believing
A Japanese company has
developed an artificial retina
capable of responding to light
and converting the stimuli into
electrical impulses, just as the
light-sensitive cells in the
eyeball transmit signals to the
brain, although it cannot
differentiate between colours.
Initial applications are likely to
be in the profitable fields of
optics, video and electronics.
European art
in Japan
A new gallery being planned
in Japan will display copies of
some 2,000 masterpieces of
European painting, from the
Renaissance to the 20th
century. Exhibits will include
copies of works by Raphael,
Caravaggio, Renoir, Modigliani
and Matisse.
Saving the African
heritage
The Rome-based International
Centre for the Preservation
and Restoration of Cultural
Property (ICCROM) has
launched a 10-year training
programme for African
museum staff to help preserve
ceremonial masks, handmade
fabrics, carvings and other
artefacts from the ravages of
time, insects, humidity and
neglect. The programme is
budgeted to cost $7 million,
$1.6 million of which have
already been raised from a
number of sources, notably
Unesco.
New archaeological
dating technique
A team of French and
American researchers recently
published an article in the
British scientific journal Nature
which has important
implications for archaeological
and palaeontological dating. A
new technique of measuring
uranium and thorium by mass
spectrometry reveals that
carbon-14 dating is unreliable
for dating fossils more than
9,000 years old. According to
this technique, the cave
paintings at Lascaux (France),
dated at 16,000 years by
carbon-14 tests, are actually
4,000 years older; and the last
period of maximum glaciation,
previously dated to 18,000
years ago, occurred 21,500
years ago.
Getting the best
out of waste
New York (26,000 tonnes per
day), Tokyo (18,600 tonnes
per day) and other cities all '
over the world are grappling
with the problem of
processing a rising tide of
household refuse. Japan has
used rubbish dumped in Tokyo
Bay for the construction of
Haneda airport on land partly
reclaimed from the sea, and
for the creation of an artificial
island which has been turned
into a leisure park. A second
artificial "island of dreams"
(Yumenoshima), is being built
in the same way on a
200-hectare site surrounded by
a dike 12 km long and 20 m
wide, capable of resisting
cyclones and earthquakes. The
site should be filled with
noncombustible materials by
1996.
In a residential suburb of
Chicago, USA, a 9-hole
golf course has been created
on hilly ground formed by
another huge dump.
Run by Waste Management
Inc., a leading American
waste-disposal corporation,
the dump also produces
methane gas which
supplies 9,500 households
with electricity. This
gas reserve, expected to last
30 years, will still be
exploitable long after the
dump is closed.
Medicine for
catastrophe
A number of systems for
providing medical treatment
after major disasters were
presented at an international
medical technology
exhibition held in Paris
last May. One of them
was a prototype machine
which purifies water by
thermocompression. The
machine still has several
drawbacks: 6 cubic metres
of polluted water are
required to produce
1 .5 cubic metres of clean
water, at a temperature
which is far too hot for
immediate use. Oxygen,
essential for anaesthetics
and the revival of disaster
victims, can now be
produced on the spot
at a rate of thousands
of litres, by exploding
cylinders of chlorate.
One problem that has not
yet been solved is
how to preserve the "cold
chain" to stop vaccines,
blood, insulin or heparin, a
basic anticoagulant, from
deteriorating during
transportation or storage.
Science and ethics
The New England Journal of
Medicine has decided not to
publish articles which describe
non-ethical experiments,
independently of their
scientific value. This is a highly
significant decision because of
the reputation of this
prestigious American weekly.
An editorial makes clear that
the issue goes far beyond the
strictly scientific field. What is
at stake is a certain
conception of human rights in
which knowledge, however
far-reaching its scope, is less
important than the means by
which it is acquired.
IN BRIEF. IN BRIEF IN BRIEF. . .
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
u N
A cultural battle
By Mario Vargas Llosa
Wf ITH the fantastic technological
progress made over recent decades
in the audio-visual media, information
has come within the reach of
everyone. And this prodigious revo¬
lution is one of the fruits of liberty,
for it was the free countriesthe
"open societies", to use Karl Popper's
term, that have adopted and
encouraged the democratic way of
life, tolerance, the rule of law and
peaceful coexistence amidst diversity
were the seed-beds of that
individual initiative and industrial
competition that gave rise to the
extraordinary technological advances
thanks to which information is now
part of the universal heritage.
Just as a climate of liberty made
technological development possible,
this development, ¡n turn, has enabled
liberty to take root and spread
throughout the world. With their
ability to illuminate reality, honestly
and objectively, the audio-visual
44
© AIR, Montevideo, 1989
MARIO VARGAS LLOSA,
of Peru, is widely regarded as one of
Latin America's most outstanding
novelists. Among his recent works
translated into English are The War of
the End of the World (Farrar, Straus &
Giroux, New York, 1984/Faber &
Faber, London, 1986), and Who Killed
Palomino Motero? (Farrar, Straus &
Giroux, 1987/Faber & Faber, 1988).
This article has been extracted from a
lecture given at an International
Association of Broadcasting conference
held in Rio de Janeiro in December
1988.
media will have a greater contribu¬
tion to make to the advance of
liberty, of the democratic way of life,
than any other public power or cul¬
tural force.
Ensuring the free flow of infor¬
mation and the right to critical judge¬
ment is the first problem a country
has to solve before it can provide a
satisfactory solution to any of its
other problems. This is no exaggera¬
tion; it is a lesson that has been
learned from historical experience.
Freedom of information and the right
to dissent are more than essential
principles; they are a practical neces¬
sity for societies that really want to
move ahead and are constantly
attempting to overcome their weak¬
nesses.
The only way in which a society
can avoid, not making mistakes, but
persisting in error is by subjecting its
actions constantly to the test of the
free circulation of information and of
critical assessment. For a Latin
American this is a self-evident fact.
The history of Latin American coun¬
tries ¡s rich in examples of the way
in which the best of intentions can
have the most catastrophic results
and of how proposed solutions based
on sentimental attitudes, ideological
principles or abstract concepts,
entirely divorced from practical
experience, can give rise to measures
that are counter-productive in both
economic and social terms.
The 'litmus test'
of critical appraisal
We have seen how populist regimes,
regimes with strong social motivation
and regimes bent on reform have
aggravated poverty and increased
unemployment and even fanned the
flames of violence and social conflict
simply because the models they
attempted to apply had not, as they
were being drawn up, been sub¬
jected to the "litmus test" of critical
appraisal, to the yardstick of reality,
to direct examination by those who
stood to benefit or suffer from them
rather than by their instigators.
Respect for freedom of informa¬
tion and the right to critical appraisal
should, therefore, head the list of
reforms of any government that
desires effectively to improve and
modernize society and remedy ¡ts
defects.
Practically speaking, however,
what is meant by freedom of expres¬
sion and the right to make critical
judgements?
We all know insti ictively when
this freedom exists, wl en it has dis¬
appeared or when it skives only in
a symbolic or pervi rted form.
Nevertheless, I shall offe a definition
which, I feel, sums up what we all
know and feel on this subject.
It might be said that a society
enjoys freedom of expression when,
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
through the various means of com¬
munication, its citizens are able to
criticize the powers-that-be-not only
the political powers, but also the eco¬
nomic, military and ecclesiastical
powers, as well as the representatives
of various social institutions such as
trade unions and, of course, the infor¬
mation media themselves.
The free flow of information and
the right to critical judgement, exer¬
cised through the media, are the
most effective way of blocking the
predisposition to grow and to persist
unimpeded that is inherent in all
power blocs.
This being so, the view is often
expressed, in all good faith, that if the
media are in private hands, they will
necessarily defend the interests and
express the opinions only of those
powerful enough to acquire them.
And there is indeed an element of
danger of this happening, which
must be countered. But if to avoid
this danger the media are placed
under the control of the state, this is
like treating an illness with a cure that
kills the patient.
While it is true that nothing can
be done to counter the rigid censor¬
ship that results from state control,
there are a number of measures that
can be taken to avoid the risks and
perils involved in private ownership
of the media. Therein lies all the
difference.
The conquest of the market
The system of a free press based on
private enterprise is the only one so
far that has been able to guarantee
true freedom of information and a
real right to criticize, but we cannot
ignore the fact that this system too
involves a number of dangers. The
first of these is that the choice of
programmes and their content (for
radio and television) and of articles
(for newspapers) is based solely on
such practical considerations as max¬
imizing profit and market share.
If the purely commercial criterion
of market domination is uppermost,
the inevitable result will be a lowering
of the quality of the media and a
cheapened, popular presentation of
news that can be taken to extremes
that threaten culture. The mediocrity
to which the press, radio or television
can descend, when motivated solely
by a desire to dominate the market
and to displace commercial rivals,
may well have tragic consequences
¡n the long term for both the cultural
and democratic bases of a society.
This is a well-known phenome¬
non, but it is not, as some have
claimed, confined to poor countries
or to countries in which culture is a
privilege reserved for an élite. Cheap¬
ened, popular presentation of infor¬
mation is also to be found in the most
economically and democratically
advanced countries.
With their solid cultural back¬
ground, however, the developed
countries are able to face up to this
danger. France and the United
Kingdom, for example, have suffi¬
cient safeguards to ensure that the
press and the audio-visual media that
serve their readers, listeners and
viewers a daily diet of scandal, do not
destroy the fabric of society or under¬
mine its democratic foundations. In
countries such as those of Latin
America, however, the cultural land¬
scape is still fragile and is characterized
by great disparities and inequalities.
If the media, in particular the audio¬
visual media (which today may provide
90 per cent, even at times 100 per
cent of a society's cultural nourish¬
ment), do not pursue responsible
policies, and if they do not place cer¬
tain criteria, certain minimum cultural
and ethical standards above their
short-term commercial interests,
democracy will indeed be put at very
grave risk.
Nothing is so destabilizing for a
society as the systematic distortion of
reality that is the hallmark of the sen¬
sationalist media. It is vital that those
in charge of radio and television sta
tions and of newspapers recognize
that the products and services they
provide are not in any way com¬
parable to those offered by other
commercial and industrial under¬
takings.
The products and services they
offer are of much greater conse¬
quence and importance than mere
"consumer goods". They influence
behaviour and have an effect on all
the consumer's other activities. They
may sharpen or blunt certain sensi¬
bilities, stimulate or completely inhibit
the imagination and the critical facul¬
ties. They may draw attention to real
problems, but they may also turn the
spotlight on false or non-existent
problems and thus distract attention
from really crucial questions. .
It is essential, therefore, that the
heads of media undertakings, upon
whom rests responsibility for main¬
taining freedom of information,
should fulfil their functions with
ethical and political considerations in
mind, rather than in an exclusively
commercial spirit. This is the only way
to ensure the development of a
democratic culture.
Public opinion
and information
Another danger to be faced is that
of the media being used to serve a
single centre of power, such as, for
example, an economic power bloc.
A democratic society can defend itself
against this danger by eliminating
monopolies, tied payments and
privileges and maintaining an open,
competitive system. If this system
remains open to the forces of com¬
petition, the danger of the media
becoming totally subordinate to an
economic power bloc is virtually
eliminated.
This, however, depends largely
upon the determination with which
the authorities in an open society
ensure the existence of a truly open
and competitive market. It also, of
course, depends greatly upon the
power of public opinion.
The opinion of a democratic,
aware and critical public is the best
defence and protection available to
the media in a free society against the
danger of becoming the creatures of
a single centre of power and in par¬
ticular of the economic power bloc.
In Latin America, however, societies
are not strong enough to overcome
the risk of reality being distorted or
of opinion becoming confused with
news.
It is essential, therefore, for these
societies not only to ensure the tech¬
nical and economic success of their
media enterprises, but also to make
certain that their democratic and cul¬
tural balance-sheets are healthy.
At a time when the countries of
Latin America are struggling to nur¬
ture culture and liberty, the media,
themselves a product of that culture,
must play their part in ensuring that
culture and liberty, having made a
timid appearance on the scene, do not,
as has so often happened before in the
history of the continent, disappear
once more.
A great weight of responsibility
lies with those who form the driving
force behind the media. All those
among us who are the direct
beneficiaries of culture and liberty
and who, thanks to that liberty, are
able freely to express their opinions
in the newspapers, on radio and
television, as well as those who are
in a position to make decisions about
telecommunications, must become
fully aware of what a great privilege
freedom iseconomic freedom,
political freedom and freedom of the
press.
This is a vital battle that we must
not lose. If we lose it, we shall also
have lost a future of civilization and
freedom. If we emerge victorious, we
shall have turned our backs on a past
of decadence, impoverishment, social
injustice and violence, none of which,
objectively speaking, has any reason
to exist in Latin America. 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
N E
Rethinking scientific progress
By Marc Chapdelaine and Jacques Richardson
46
fAs our turbulent century draws to
its close, marking a thousand years
of spectacular growth in knowledge,
a new sensitivity about the state of
mankind can be discerned. This shift
in our cultural "temperature" results,
in part, from a realization that tech¬
nological changewhile greatly im¬
proving nutrition and health, for
instancecan harm the physical
nature of our world.
As part of its vocations in the
fields of information and culture,
Unesco organizes, every few years,
meetings of concentrated reflection
on societal issues affected by progress
in science and technology. In 1986,
some twenty-five specialists met in
Venice to contemplate "Science and
the Boundaries of Knowledge".1
Another two dozen experts from all
over the world met late last year in
Vancouver, Canada, to ponder the
theme "Science and Culture for the
21st Century: Agenda for Survival".
The choice of the word "survival"
may be intimidating, but an eminent
ecologist from Quebec present in
Vancouver, Pierre Dansereau, admit¬
ted that "it is scientists who are part
of the problem".
When our century began, scien¬
tific research was still a disparate
effort on the part of dedicated in¬
dividuals and practical inventorsnot
working in teams, yet motivated by
an intense desire to learn all about
nature and the universe beyond.
Today, stressed Moroccan edu¬
cator Mahdi Elmandjra at Vancouver,
our "learning processes and mental
structures" are relatively unchanged,
but there is a need for "greater fore¬
sight and much more balanced cul¬
tural communication".
Above, crystals of vitamin C (ascorbic acid)
photographed with a polarized microscope.
Below,
the Harz forest in Germany, damaged by acid rain.
Italian historian and philosopher
Nicola Dallaporta interpreted inequal¬
ities between North and South as
"breaks or violations of the sym¬
metries" that long existed among the
world's civilizations. These disrup¬
tions, she claimed, "create the prac¬
tically unlimited capacity of the world
to express in the most delicately
shaded ways" mankind's countless
thoughts and ideas.
Supporting this line of reasoning,
Yujiro Nakamura of Meiji University
in Tokyo noted what he called "cul¬
tural negativity". He explained: "Con¬
tact between different peoples and
nations has not brought mutual
respect, but often violent opposi¬
tion.... A culture should not impose
its rhythm on other cultures."
But asymmetry and negative
reactions can be corrected by what
we learn from nature, according to
Daniel A. Akyeampong, a mathemat¬
ical physicist from Ghana. "At each
stage in the development of science,
the new concepts arising have in¬
fluenced man in his understanding
and appreciation of his culture."
Recalling the rigour of investigation
in the natural sciences, he asked,
"Can nature's inherent symmetry find
pride of place in our social and cul¬
tural values?"
Such consciousness has pervad¬
ed the work undertaken by the
United Nations and its specialized
agencies.
Academician Josef Riman, a
geneticist from Czechoslovakia,
noted that non-governmental organi¬
zations also play a role in reconciling
scientific progress with human
needs, citing the example of the
newly developed Global Change
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Vancouver Declaration
sURVIVAL of the planet has be¬
come of centra! and immediate con¬
cern. The present situation requires
urgent measures in all sectors-
scientific, cultural, economic and po¬
litical, and a greater sensitization of
all mankind. We must make common
cause with all people on Earth against
a common enemy: any action that
threatens balance within our environ¬
ment or reduces our legacy to future
generations. Today, this becomes the
objective of the Vancouver Declara¬
tion on Survival.
Mankind confronting
survival
Our planet is unstablea constantly
changing heat engine. Life appeared
on its surface about four billion years
ago, and developed in balance with
an environment where sudden un¬
predictable change is the norm. The
discovery, over 200 years ago, of free
energy locked in fossil fuels has given
humankind the power to dominate
the whole planetary surface. In an un¬
believably short span of time, un¬
planned and almost mindlessly, our
species has become by far the largest
factor for change on the planet.
The consequences have been
drastic and unique in the history of
our species:
an accelerating increase in popu¬
lation growth over the past 1 50 years
from one billion to over five billion
with a current doubling time of 30
to 40 years;
a comparable increase in the use
of fossil fuels leading to global
pollution, climate and sea-level
change;
an accelerating destruction of the
habitat of life, initiating a massive and
irreversible episode of mass extinction
in the biospherethe basis of the
Earth's ecosystem;
an unimaginable expenditure of
resources and human ingenuity on
war and preparation for war.
This is all licensed by a belief in
the inexhaustible resources of the
planet encouraged by political and
economic systems that emphasize
short term profit and disregard the
real cost of production.
The situation facing mankind in¬
volves the collapse of any balance be¬
tween our species and the rest of life
on the planet. Paradoxically, at the
time when we stand at the threshold
of degeneration of the ecosystem
and degradation of the quality of life,
knowledge and science are now in a
position to provide both the human
creativity and the technology needed
to take remedial action and to redis¬
cover the harmony between nature
and mankind. Only the social and po¬
litical will is lacking.
The origins
of the problem
The origin of our present predica¬
ment lies fundamentally in certain de¬
velopments in science that were
essentially complete by the beginning
of the century. Those developments...
gave human beings a power over na¬
ture that has, until recently, produced
an ever-increasing, and seemingly
boundless, supply of material com¬
modities. Swept up in the exploita¬
tion of this power, humankind has
tended to shift its values to those
promoting the maximal realization of
the material possibilities that this new
power provides. The values associat¬
ed with dimensions of the human
potential that had been the founda¬
tions of earlier cultures were cor¬
respondingly suppressed. The
impoverishment of the conception of
man caused by this omission of other
human dimensions is precisely in line
with the "scientific" conception of
the universe as machine, and of man
as nothing but a cog within it....
However, scientific advances of
the present century have shown this
mechanical view of the universe to be
untenable on purely scientific
grounds. Thus the rational basis for
the mechanical conception of man
has been invalidated.
Alternative visions
In contemporary science, the older
rigid mechanical picture of the
universe is replaced by concepts that
permit a universe that is formed by
a continual creative input that is not
constrained by any mechanical law.
Man himself becomes an aspect of
this creative impulse.... The "self" be¬
comes thereby converted from a de-
terministically controlled cog in a
giant machine to an aspect of a free
creative impulse that is intrinsically
and immediately tied to the universe
as a whole....
The human species has reached
limits in its use of the external world
and also limits in its capacity to live
in a changing social and cultural en¬
vironment. Man's developing percep¬
tions in science suggest that he might
recapture lost beliefs and varieties of
spiritual experience. The present crit¬
ical situation in mankind's occupan¬
cy of the planet requires new visions,
rooted in a variety of cultures, in con¬
templating the future:
The perception of an organic mac¬
rocosm that recaptures the rhythms
of life would allow man to reintegrate
himself with nature and understand
his relationship in space and time to
all life and the physical world.
Recognition that a human being is
an aspect of the creative process that
gives form to the universe, enlarges
man's image of himself and allows
him to transcend the egoism that is
the principal cause of disharmony
among his fellows and between
mankind and nature.
The overcoming of fragmentation
of the body-mind-spirit unity, brought
about by unbalanced emphasis on
any one over the others, allows man
to discover within himself the reflec¬
tion of cosmos and its supreme unify¬
ing principle.
Such visions change the concep¬
tion of man in nature and call for a
radical transformation of models of
development; the elimination of
poverty, ignorance and misery; the
end of the arms race; introduction of
new learning processes, educational
systems and mental attitudes; im¬
plementation of better forms of redis¬
tribution to ensure social equity; a
new design for living based on a
reduction of waste; respect for bio¬
diversity, socio-economic diversi-
ty.and cultural diversity that tran¬
scends outmoded concepts of
sovereignty....
Time is shortevery delay in es¬
tablishing a world eco-cultural peace
will only increase the cost of survival.
We must recognize the reality of
a multi-religious world and the need
for the kind of tolerance that will
enable religions, whatever their
differences, to co-operate together.
This would contribute to meeting the
requirements for human survival and
for the nurturing of the shared core
values of human solidarity, human
rights and human dignity. This is the
common heritage of mankind that
derives from our perception of the
transcendental significance of human
existence, and from a new global
conscience.
September 1989
Signatories to the Declaration
Professor Daniel Afedzi Akyeampong
(Ghana), president, Mathematical
Association of Ghana
Professor Ubiritan d'Ambrosio
(Brazil), professor of mathematics and
pro-rector for university development.
State University of Campinas
Mr. André Chouraqui
(Israel), author, religious studies
Professor Nicola Dallaporta
(Italy), emeritus professor, International
School for Advanced Studies, Trieste
Mr. Pierre Dansereau
(Canada), ecologist, emeritus professor,
University of Quebec, Montreal
Dr. Mahdi Elmandjra
(Morocco), former assistant director-
general of Unesco, president of
Futuribles International
Dr. Santiago Genovès
(Mexico), titular research professor of
anthropology, University of Mexico
Professor Carl-Göran Heden
(Sweden), president, World Academy of
Arts and Science
Dr. Alexander King
(United Kingdom), president. Club of
Rome
Mrs. Eleonora Barbieri Masini
(Italy), president. World Futures Studies
Federation
Dr. Digby McLaren
(Canada), president, Royal Society of
Canada
Professor Yujiro Nakamura
(Japan), philosopher, author and
professor at Meiji University
Mr. Lisandro Otero
(Cuba), author
Mr. Michel Random
(France), writer, publisher
Professor Josef Riman
(Czechoslovakia), president,
Czechoslovak Academy of Sciences
Professor Soedjatmoko
(Indonesia), former rector, United
Nations University
Professor Henry Stapp
(United States of America), physicist,
Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory,
University of California, Berkeley 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
A diatom seen through the
microscope. These tiny algae form the
main element of marine plankton.
programme of the International
Council of Scientific Unions (ICSU).
ICSU, representing about a mil¬
lion scientists throughout the world,
is closely associated with Unesco. Its
Global Change scheme (known as
the International Geosphere-
Biosphere Programme) seeks to
achieve during the coming decade
better understanding of physical and
chemical relations in our planet's sub¬
systems. Riman added that a com¬
parable approach "would be
desirable in the complex study of man
for a better understanding of emo¬
tional and rational behaviour."
Sweden's Carl-Goran Heden, an
eminent microbiologist, strongly sup¬
ported initiatives by such non¬
governmental bodies and pointed to
the success of a group in his country
called IDEA (Innovations for Develop¬
ment Association), which periodically
awards prizes for achievements in the
management of farming, forestry,
fisheries, energy and water resources.
The former rector of the United
Nations University, Indonesia's Profes¬
sor Soedjatmoko, claimed that scien¬
tific progress in coming generations
requires that mankind "make adjust¬
ments in systems and processes of
governance". He foresaw philosophi¬
cal shifts amounting to "change that
may be a precondition for human sur¬
vival, posing challenges to societies
and individuals that are essentially
ethical".
Eleonora Barbieri Masini of Ita¬
ly, who is president of the World Fu¬
tures Studies Federation, cautioned
that we should think of the future in
terms of "alternative scenarios". She
believes that a "scenario of transi¬
tion" will be "sure in any case to take
place because of long-term trends in
population structures" in both de¬
veloping and industrialized countries.
Israeli linguist André Chouraqui
believes that shifts in population dis¬
tribution and a new vision of human¬
ity will evoke new approaches to
communication between peoples. He
recalled that it was once rare for peo¬
ple to speak two or more languages.
Only in the recent past has this lan¬
guage barrier become less common,
but Professor Chouraqui insisted that
at the basis of the cultural-religious
conflict between the Islamic and
Hebraic worlds, for example, "lies a
linguistic problem that should be con¬
fronted as we move tQwards the
twenty-first century".
In appraising the contributions of
science and culture to our well-being
(if not outright survival) in the next
century, perhaps the last word should
come from a professional communi¬
cator, Bernard Ostry, chairman and
chief executive officer of TV Ontario.
Unable to attend the symposium, he
presented a paper ¡n which he em¬
phasized that there is a link between
culture and communication just as
"there is between economy and com¬
munication". Proper use of television
must take account of the need for a
shared culture, rather than "impos¬
ing cultural uniformity. Without diver¬
sity of culture, there can be no true
intellectual and spiritual freedom",
now or in the future.
The Vancouver Declaration (see
page 47) was drafted at the end of
the symposium. Unesco plans to fol¬
low up the Venice and Vancouver
meetings at a session to be held in
Latin America in 1993.
1 . Jacques Richardson commented on this
symposium in Interdisciplinary Science
Reviews (Great Thoughts by the Grand
Canal), Vol 12, 1987
MARC CHAPDELAINE
is director of Unesco's Science and
Technology Policies division.
JACQUES RICHARDSON
was editor of Unesco's international
quarterly journal Impact of Science on
Society from 1972 to 1985.
Holloko
in Hungary
is the only
village on
Unesco's World
Heritage List
- .
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
I H E
A village in the hills By Edouard Bailby
I he road wound its way through
wooded hills or between copses, with
now and then a glimpse of a few
sleepy cows. I was driving in northern
Hungary, looking for a village. Tucked
away at the end of a road, it rarely
appears on maps and the signposts
along the road are somewhat erratic.
At each fork I hesitated: left or right?
Yet Holloko is no ordinary place.
Since 1987 it has been the only
village in the world inscribed on
Unesco's World Heritage List. Situ¬
ated in the Cserhát mountains, some
hundred kilometres north-west of
Budapest, it is still a backwater as far
as large-scale tourism is concerned.
Suddenly, through the foliage of
the trees lining the road, I caught
sight of a green sign and on it, in
white lettering, there at long last was
the name of the village. A few
hundred metres further on, at the
crest of a slope, I came across the first
houses and was beset by doubt.
These were sturdy modern buildings,
surrounded by gardens, of the kind
which has been springing up in the
Hungarian countryside over the past
few years. Could Holloko be a tourist
trap, with a pile of stones passed off
as a historic ruin?
Before long I came across a sign
bearing the World Heritage emblem.
Then, all at once, the look of the
place changed. The real village
sprang into view. As though in a fairy
tale, cottages as white as wedding
gowns, each with a wooden balcony,
appeared along the main street. This
street of uneven cobblestones is
named after Sándor Petöfi, the great
Hungarian revolutionary poet who
died in 1849. With rare exceptions,
cars are not permitted here.
Unlike other Hungarian villages,
which are centred on a church, this
ancient village in the Cserhát moun¬
tains leads to a tiny and charming
whitewashed chapel dating from the
fifteenth century. With its pointed,
slate-covered steeple, it is the last
vestige of the Middle Ages. Inside,
there is no baroque ornamentation,
just plain whitewashed walls and a
wooden ceiling. To the right of the
entrance hangs a crucifix by Ferenc
Kelemen, a local sculptor. On feast
days, old villagers still attend mass in
traditional costume.
No more than a hundred people
live in the old village. Dressed in
typical Hungarian peasant fashion in
black trousers or gaily coloured skirts,
they go about their business, some
bearing pitchforks, others carrying
baskets of vegetables. On the nearby
hills are a few vines, vegetable
gardens, fields of maize and sun¬
flowers. Sheep graze in the
meadows. The farmland is divided
into small plots. I did not see a tractor.
The bucolic landscape adds to the
charm of the village.
The neat rows of immaculate
houses, façades embellished with
finely carved wooden balustrades,
surmounted by tiled roofs with tiny
square windows set in them, are built
in a uniform style characteristic of the
architecture of northern Hungary.
Their patches of garden, filled with
summer flowers, are enclosed by low
fences. Often, above the front door,
there hangs a horseshoe, a garland
of red paprikas, a cob of maize or a
holy picture.
The village museum, situated in
an old house converted for the pur¬
pose, is a perfect reconstruction of a
traditional interior. The front door
leads straight into the main living
room, furnished with a dining table
and benches decked out in embroi¬
dered covers. The kitchen is at the
back and to the left is the bedroom
in which parents and children all
slept. A pair of boots is suspended
from the ceiling to stop mice from
nesting in them during the night. An
adjoining room houses the loom on
which the women embroidered
tablecloths, head-dresses and
cushions. To the right of the living
room is a more spacious room,
reserved for the grandparents, where
farm implements, firewood and pro¬
visions for the harsh winter months
are stacked up in a corner. Porcelain
or pewter plates, generally hanging
from the walls, gaily coloured
blankets, red and green cushions,
and hand-decorated earthenware
vases brighten the place up.
All the houses in Holloko date
from the beginning of the century.
Unfortunately, nothing remains from
earlier periods. The wooden houses
have been reduced to ashes in suc¬
cessive fires. Mongol hordes laid
waste this area in the mid-thirteenth
century, and in the sixteenth the vil¬
lage was sacked by Turkish troops,
who left a garrison of sixty men in a
fortress which towers over the neigh¬
bourhood. The ruins, accessible by a
steep path, are in such a state of dis¬
repair that they have been closed to
visitors for the past seventeen years.
But the fortress, which is indissociable
from the history of Holloko, is now
being restored and will soon regain
its former splendour.
"Now that we are part of the
Unesco heritage," a village woman
told me, "we are no longer anxious
about our future." The entire village
is the focus of attention from both
local and regional authorities. Since
last year it has even had its own post
office, and it also boasts a grocery
store, a primary school, an old
people's home and three small café-
restaurants, which are open until late
in the evening.
To lovers of the past, the local
tourist office rents out at a modest
price a few charming cottages
equipped with modern amenities.
The number of these dwellings is
limited so as not to alter the life of
the village. In the summer season,
romantics can hold weddings and
country dances here, for which the
village women will deck themselves
out in all their finery.
"I was born to make people
happy," says Ferenc Kelemen. Born
at Holloko in 1927, he has worked
with wood since his childhood and
carves allegorical figures, birds, forest
animals and groups of young peasant
girls. There are piles of his sculptures
in the pretty little cottage where he
lives. He was eager to show us a pho¬
tograph of one of his masterpieces,
purchased, as he proudly explained,
by the wife of a French prime
minister.
Ferenc Kelemen is a voluble man
who likes to repeat without any false
modesty that he "has no regrets
about having been born with talent".
His fame has long ago travelled
beyond the wooden fences of his
native village.
EDOUARD BAILBY,
French journalist and former
correspondent with the Paris weekly
magazine L'Express, served for a number
of years as press officer with Unesco's
Office of Public Information.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
rus*
2Y~
' m4iZ**+~
c
"
Traditions for Tomorrow
In your July 1 990 issue on illiteracy you
mention an organization called Tradi¬
tions for Tomorrow which is helping
local communities in Latin America to
safeguard their cultural identity. I am
very interested in this kind of initiative,
which allows marginalized populations
to draw on their past in order to face
their future. I would like to contact this
organization to offer my support
Christine lllouz
Paris
The organization's address is
Traditions for Tomorrow,
P 0. Box 5835, J F. Kennedy Station,
Boston, Massachusetts 02114 Editor
Freedom to smoke
Will it soon be forbidden to smoke...
even on a stamp7
I wish to reply to the letter from a
Danish reader published in the July issue
of the Courier The letter criticizes the
reproduction on your letters page of a
postage stamp showing a woman
smoking a cigarette. I am directly con¬
cerned because I am the unfortunate
person who sent you the stamp1
I ask you not to replace this stamp.
First, out of respect for the woman pic¬
tured on it, Bodil Ipsen, one of the most
famous actresses of the Danish cinema
She is still so well-known that this year,
the centenary of her birth, a set of
records has been issued on which she
reads stones by such Danish writers as
Karen Blixen.
I also make this request out of
respect for the freedom of the
individual, which is cherished by the
friends of Unesco It is quite possible to
smoke without annoying other people
As far as I know there are places set
aside for non-smokers almost every¬
where Why do the latter want to bully
smokers and impose their own tastes
on them? May I say in passing that I am
myself a non-smoker1
The consequence of this kind of
censorship will be endless. Pictures of
people smoking will have to be with-
jU drawn from all the world's museums
Letters to the Editor
and, at the request of certain religious
sects, you will have to abstain from pub¬
lishing photographs of bare-headed
women.
I take this apparently innocuous
matter very seriously indeed.
Frederic Parrot di Giusto
Viby J. (Denmark)
One cigarette = 5 rem
While visiting the French nuclear studies
centre at Saclay I saw a notice giving
figures for the radiation emitted by
different objects or elements Two
figures caught my attention: an X-ray
emits 50 rem; a cigarette, 5 rem * While
there have been attempts to make
people afraid of radiation by X-rays,
practically no thought has been given
to that produced by cigarettes. A
twenty-a-day smoker will receive a radi¬
ation dosage equivalent to two X-rays1
If this information was printed on all
cigarette packets and repeated every
day on radio and television, there would
surely be fewer cases of cancer caused
by smoking.
Eugénie Guichard
Saint-Michel-Sur-Orge
(France)
* The rem ("Roentgen equivalent man")
is a unit of radiation dosage
A tree by any other name
The trees shown in the photograph on
page 43 of your May 1990 issue are
probably baobabs, as described, but I
don't believe they belong to the Adan-
sonia digitata species. They are probably
a related species of Adansonia which
occurs mainly in Madagascar
What a pity that the common
names of the trees mentioned in the
article which this photograph illustrates
were not accompanied by their Latin
names This would have made the
article more comprehensible to
botanists, ecologists and foresters
Michel Baumer
International Council for
Research in Agroforestry
Nairobi (Kenya)
Further reading?
You used to publish bibliographies
which allowed readers to find out more
about subjects that interested them.
Why have you stopped doing this7
Wouldn't it be possible to revive the tra¬
dition7
Gilles Mercier
Poitiers (France)
The publication of bibliographies in 35
language editions poses problems
Some editions are not interested in lists
of books in French and English, and
cannot always compile a bibliography
of their own. We are nevertheless con¬
cerned about the question you raise and
are seeking a solution Editor
Nuclear power in the Crimea
I am a student. I love our planet and am
deeply concerned about the future of
my country and the world at large But
most of all I am concerned about the
region where I live, the Crimea.
Much harm is being done to our
peninsula and the people who live on
it I can't bring myself to be silent about
this, if only because of the nuclear plant
which is now being constructed and is
arousing widespread protest and indig¬
nation This unique site badly needs pro¬
tection against such developments. I
should like to contribute to the defence
of the environment Could you put me
in touch with the Greenpeace organi¬
zation7
Yuri Belski
Sebastopol (USSR)
The address of the Greenpeace
Environmental Trust is
30-31 Islington Green,
London NI 8XE, England
Editor
Acknowledgements
Cover, page 3 (left): P. Robert
© Sygma, Paris. Back cover:
R. Bossu © Sygma, Paris. Page 2:
© Françoise Zavaroni, Lurech.
Pages 5, 25, 34: All Rights
Reserved. Pages 6-7: Jean-Claude
Francolon © Gamma, Paris. Page 8
(above left): © Hervé Bernard,
Paris. Pages 8-9: David Burnett
© Gamma, Paris Page 10:
© Edimedia, Paris. Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris. Pages 12-13:
© Galerie Claude Samuel, Paris.
Pages 13 (above), 22 (right):
© Gaiizère, Paris. Pages 14, 15
(above): © Patrick Tosani, Paris.
Page 15 (below): Tony Korody
©Sygma, Paris. Pages 16, 30:
©Mutio, Paris. Pages 17 (above),
18, 23: ©Collection Kipa, Paris.
Page 17 (below): ©Association des
Trois Mondes, Paris. Collection
ICAIC, Havana. Page 19: © La
Sept, Paris. Page 20: © Keystone,
Paris. Page 21: G. Rancinan
© Sygma, Paris. Page 22 (left):
Bruno Barbey © Magnum, Pans.
Page 24: © Almasy, Paris. Page 26
(above): © Ron Giling, the
Netherlands; (below): Unesco/I.
Forbes. Pages 27, 28-29: Peter
Marlow © Magnum, Paris. Pages
28, 45: ©Kinkas, Pans. Page 31:
A. Hernandez ©Sygma, Paris.
Page 32: Shone © Gamma, Paris.
Page 33: Alcxei Solomonov
©APN, Paris. Pages 35, 41
(above): © Sygma, Pans. Pages
36-37: Gilles Pcrcss © Magnum,
Paris. Page 39: Constantine Manos
© Magnum, Pans. Page 40: Elliott
Erwitt © Magnum, Paris. Page 41
(below): Abbas © Magnum, Paris.
Pages 42, 46 (below): Patrick Piel
© Gamma, Paris. Page 44: Hector
Lopez © Vu, Pans. Page 46
(above): David Parker/Science
Photo Library, London © Cosmos,
Paris. Page 48 (above left): Eric
Gravé/Science Photo Library,
London © Cosmos, Pans. Pages 48
(right), 49: © Edouard Bailby,
Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco
^courier
Published monthly in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Pans, France
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbma
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Russian edition: Georgi Zelenin
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel 45 68.46 90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel 45 .68.46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: A"me Brächet (Tel 45 68 47 1 5).
Mouna Chatta
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Mane Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mano Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: h Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catatan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dares Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S J Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Man-i Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A M Sharafuddm (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
' SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45 68 45 88),
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45 68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Mane Thérèse Hardy (45 68 45 .65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité. Jacqueline Louise Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Dm,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk, Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45 68 45 64),
Accounts: (45 68 45.65),
Mail: Martial Amegee (45 68 45 70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45 68 47 SO)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel 45 68 45 65
1 year; 126 French francs 2 years 234 FF.
Binder for one year's issues 68 FF
Developing countries
1 year 99 French francs 2 years: 180 FF
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may bo reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name Non copyright
photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage Signed adíeles express ihe opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Couner staff The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations The Unesco Couner is
produced m microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco. 7
Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans, [¿) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann
Arbor. Michigan 48100. U S A , (3) N C R Microcard Edition. Indian
Head, inc , 1H West 40th Street. New York, U S A . (4) Bell and
Howell Co . Old Mansfield Road. Wcoster. Ohio 44691, USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed m France) DEPOT LEGAL CI SEPTEMBRE 1990
COMMISSION PARITAIRE NO /1844 DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP
Photocomposition The Unesco Courier
Photogravure impressior Maury Imprimeur S A . Z I route d'Etampes.
45330 Malesherbes
gift subscription to the
Unesco Courier
It is the only international cultural magazine
published in 35 languages
and read by hundreds of thousands of people
in 120 countries
Each month it explores
the astonishing diversity of
world culture and knowledge
It associates its readers wié Unesco's
mission offurthering "universal respect for
justice, for the rule of ¡aw and for human rights
and fundamental freedoms...without distinction
of race, sex, language or religion..."
ISSN 0041 S278 NO 9 1990 OPI 90 3
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4 page advertising insert
between pages 10 11 and 42 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
