<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="087907eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
MARCH 1991
rv:
v ...
M 1205 9103 18.00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
_l
encounters We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication In this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds In which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
BLUE EYES
1990, oil on canvas
(41 x24cm)
by Henri Landier
This work by the French
painter and engraver
Henri Landier has been
drawn to our attention by
Mme Y. Servin. "In it can
be seen the white mask of
a girl in a Japanese Nô
play," she writes, "and
echoes of a seventeenth-
century painting, Servants
in a Bath-house, appear in
the slanted eyes, generous
mouth, and strands of dark,
hair. The influence of
Japanese art is equally
unmistakable in the
enigmatic expression,
hinting at humour."
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
MARCH 1991 CONTENTS
4
Interview with
MANU DIBANGO
The|
a
e IJnesco
^courier
Publ.ihtd moflttil, In 3S leftfuafet ftfld M Br*,li«
The Governments of the States
parlies to this Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare.
"that since wars begin In the minds
of men. it is In the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded, if it is not to
fail, upon the Intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect knowledge of
each other's lives
Extract from th* Preamble to
Cortttitution of UNESCO,
London. 16 November 1945
tl»
8
A WORLD OF MUSIC
by Isabelle Leymarie
THE BIRTH OF THE BLUES
by Etienne Bours and Alberto Nogueira 12
BRAZIL: A KALEIDOSCOPE OF SOUND
by Mario de Aratanha 15
TEX-MEX MUSIC
by Manuel Peña 20
LATIN JAZZ 22
THE ROCKERS' LAMENT
by Aleksandr Sokolansky 28
ECHOES FROM AFAR
by Véronique Brindeau 30
FROM GUITAR TO QANUN
by Julien Jalal Eddin Weiss 34
SONG OF INDIA
by Romain Maitra 35
40
LISTENING
Recent records
by Isabelle Leymarie and
Claude Glayman
41
IN BRIEF..
42
WORLD HERITAGE
Ouro Prêto, city of black gold
by Augusto C. da Silva Telles
44
ENVIRONMENT
Coping with
uncertainty
by Michel Bâtisse
48
THE SILK ROADS
Threading
through the past
15 by François-Bernard Huyghe
50
'WORLD MUSIC OR SOUNDS OF THE TIMES
by Alain Gardinier 37
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
Cover design specially
created for this issue
of the UNESCO Courier
by the Iranian
graphic artist Bita Seyedi.
Back cover: In Ochre and
Yellow with Sheet Music
(1990), collage and acrylic on
canvas-covered panel (48.9 x
38.7 cm) by the American
artist Robert Motherwell.
Special consultant
for this issue:
Isabelle Leymarie
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A'
Xiäl
*<
INTERVIEW
MANU
DIBANGO
Born in Cameroon, Parisian by
adoption, Manu Dibango is one of the
first musicians to blend traditional
African music and jazz. His music
has been called American in France,
European in Africa, and African in the
United States, but he refuses to be
labelled and proclaims that he
belongs to the "race of musicians".
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
What are your earliest memories?
I was born at Douala in Cameroon. My father
and mother were Protestants. When I was very-
young they enrolled me at the village school
where I first learned Douala, one of my country's
main languages. After school I went to the
chapel, where my mother led the women's choir
and the pastor commented on the Old and New
Testaments translated into Douala. It was there
that I caught the magical virus of music.
Were you a musical family?
My father was a civil servant, a job which car¬
ried some prestige. At that time there was no
radio. But we were lucky enough to have a
gramophone. I listened to it surreptitiously when
my parents weren't there. My mother was a
dressmaker and taught apprentices at home. We
sang all day long. I was the conductor. What I
liked most of all was to marshal the voices into
a human instrument that sounded right and true.
Eventually the tunes I learned became so much
a part of me that later on when I was in France
and heard a Bach cantata that I had learned at
chapel I thought at first that I was listening to
music from back home...
What kind of music did you listen to when
you went out?
After being a German colony, Cameroon
became a French protectorate. When the French
navy came to Douala, they brought modern
Western music with them. African performers
played in the bars and hotels where white people
stayed. When the Africans came back to the dis¬
trict where they lived, they taught us the
fashionable tunes. Well, more or less... We chil¬
dren changed these approximations in our turn.
There was also initiation music, which was
played with drums and wooden instruments such
as tom-toms. And we heard traditional guitarists
at weddings and funerals.
But the guitar isn't an African instrument...
Yes and no. The guitar reached Cameroon
with the Portuguese in the fourteenth century. In
Cameroon we use the guitar to play assico, dance
music which is also found in Nigeria. Its rhythm
is binary and not ternary like jazz. The Cameroo-
nian guitarist achieved the feat of playing tune¬
fully, harmoniously and percussively.
There was also another form of popular
music, Ambass B, an abbreviation for "Ambas¬
sade de Belgique", a derivative oí assico, but more
strongly marked by Western influences. This
music originated with the Africans who worked
for the whites. Within a few years it had become
popular. It's immediately recognizable, with a
harmony from the West and a typically
Cameroonian rhythm.
When you heard Western music in Cameroon,
did you feel that you were listening to foreign
music?
When I was a child I didn't know the differ¬
ence. We assimilated the songs we learned from
the sailors and gave them a flavour of our own.
We were curious and absorbed all forms of music
without troubling to find out in each case what
came from the blacks and what came from the
whites....
What about instruments?
My African schoolteacher played the violin
and the piano. The Cameroonians quickly
adopted the musical instruments introduced by
the Westerners. Some Cameroonians even played
string quartets.... I came across these instruments
at the chapel and at home. They were part of
my life.
How did you become a musician?
My elder brother had a guitar. I wasn't allowed
to touch it, of coursethat's why I played it! I
also had a harmonica that my father had bought.
I was feeling my way. It was only when I arrived
in France at the age of fifteen that my father paid
for me to have piano lessons. I soon realized that
I was a musician because I loved music. But at
that time I never dreamed of becoming a profes¬
sional.
Why did you go to France?
To study for a diploma, as some of us chil¬
dren did in those days. I took piano lessons as
well. I should have liked to learn the violin, but it
was too late. You have to start when you are five.
The piano plus Protestantism add up to jazz.
This is certainly one of the key factors in my
musical environment. In jazz you always find
traces of gospel, the religious melodies which
American blacks transposed into their music.
How happy I was the first time I heard Louis
Armstrong humming on the radio! Here was a
black voice singing tunes that reminded me of
those I had learned at the temple. I immediately
felt at one with the warmth of that voice and
with what it was singing. The voice is the most
beautiful instrument.
How did you discover the saxophone?
By chance. I chose the piano. But the sax began
as a joke between pals: "You're getting on our
nerves with your piano... Can't you play the
sax?" "OK!" I accepted the challenge and then
I got down to business. I took lessons. And as
a good jazz-lover I daydreamed about American
jazz musicians. Our heroes at that time were
black American sports champions and musicians
like Sugar Ray Robinson, Louis Armstrong and
Duke Ellington.
When was this exactly?
The middle and late 1940s. In Paris it was
the time when Saint-Germain-des-Prés was
musically a very exciting place to be. We Africans
came from the provinces to Paris just to listen
to jazz, Latin American musicmambo,
sambaand the beguine from the Caribbean.
Creole music had an important place in France
in the 1950s.
But jazz was your favourite music. What did
it bring you?
A kind of freedom, fresh scope for the imagi¬
nation. Jazz is the invention of a link between
one continent and anothereven if the story
behind it is a terrible one. But the most beau¬
tiful flower can grow on a dunghill.
You're thinking of slavery?
Of course. The dunghill is slavery and all its
works. The flower is jazz, the fruit of what came
from the West, on the one hand, and from Africa
on the other. It is the twentieth-century music
par excellence. It even introduces you to other
kinds of music. Through jazz I discovered all the
music that I love, starting with classical music.
Jazz is a much more rigorous form of music than
is generally thought.
What do you mean by that? Aren't you con¬
tradicting what you said about freedom a
moment ago?
Not at all. Improvisation is easier if there is
a solid framework for it. In jazz you know the
theme in advance; it's Gershwin or Duke
Ellington. Everyone is supposed to know it. The
jazz musician expresses himself within this pre-
established framework. It's like the subject for
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
an essay at school which you have to structure
into a beginning, a middle and an end. A jazz
musician will never play the same piece in the
same way twice. In classical music, on the other
hand, you have to reproduce down to the last
note exactly what the composer created. The jazz
musician thus has a certain freedomthe most
wonderful kind because it's the most difficult.
What happened after your encounter with
jazz?
When my parents realized that I was
neglecting my studies, they stopped my
allowance. I had to learn more about musical
technique and literature. It was essential. In the
cabarets where I worked, for example, I had to
provide the accompaniment for a ballet or for
a singer. This was invaluable experience and
helped to shape my musical personality. I treat
music like painting, and I learned to orchestrate
and mix sounds and instrumentsto marry
colours together. Gradually I became aware of
my identity.
Yourpersonal, national or cultural identity?
All of them. First of all there were the sounds
of independence movements. At the end of the
1950s, after passing my baccalaureate, I left
France and went to Brussels where I intended
to continue my studies and at the same time earn
my living. In 1960 negotiations were being held
in Brussels under United Nations auspices about
an independence agreement between Belgium and
the Congo. In the Porte de Namur district where
I lived, I experienced the tensions and clashes
between whites and Africans. I discovered the
price that history makes people pay.
All the same I had the good fortune to be
hired as bandleader at the Anges Noirs, a
fashionable nightclub run by a Cape Verdean,
which was frequented by the leaders of new-born
Zaire. For the first time an African band, African
Jazz, arrived from Zaire to record in Europe. Its
leader, the famous Zairian singer Joseph Kaba-
sélé, spent his nights at the Anges Noirs. At that
time all Brussels and all Africa were dancing to
Indépendance cha-cha, the record he made when
Zaire became independent.
You never left the black music scene?
Of course I did. The nightclub where I was
working belonged to a black man, but not all
the entertainers were black. Whites from Europe
and America, West Indians and Latin Americans
all turned up at the Anges Noirs and met Africans
there. I even played Gypsy music there. All this
music, of course, was based on rhythm. In addi¬
tion to the tango and the paso doble, people
danced the samba, the cha-cha and the mambo.
We also played jazz for dancing. No one kind
of music dominated our repertoire.
How did you discover African music in the
strict sense of the term?
My meeting with Kabasélé led to a series of
lucky breaks. He liked the way I played the sax,
and invited me to record Congolese music with
him. The records we made together were a
tremendous success. In 1961, the first piano
recording I madeAfrican Jazz had no pianist-
had a wonderful reception in Zaire, which was
the chief market for black music in Africa
because of the powerful radio transmitter the Bel¬
gians had built there! Everybody in Africa
listened to Radio Kinshasa, which broadcast until
three o'clock in the morning.
While I was in Zaire, I started to compose.
Then, in the mid-1960s, I returned to Cameroon.
I saw my country with new eyes. The doors of
Africa were slowly opening for me.
How did it feel to be back in your native
country?
I returned to Cameroon twelve years after I
had left.... I really wanted to rejoin the society
from which I had come. But I had lived in
another society, with other rules. It's hard to go
back to your country after being away for so
long. .
Do you mean that after your long stay in the
West youfelt somewhat remote from the society
into which you had been born?
Yes, I found an environment that was more
restrictive for the individual than that which I
knew in Europe. I was no longer very familiar
with the rules of that society, but I was still
strongly attached to it. A break is inevitable and
normal for anyone who has a foot in two
cultures. The important thing is not to lose your
soul. And to be at one with yourself you need
to know who you are.
Was music a way of resolving these con¬
tradictions?
It was one way. It is the most spontaneous,
natural form of contact between one person and
another. It starts with the voice. The voice in
itself is music. You make music as soon as you
leave your mother's womb. People have always
used sounds to soften or harden human feelings.
Music is one of the essential factors of knowledge.
Dialogue is first and foremost a form of music.
But once you have learned something you
have to learn it over again. You have to go
beyond the environment in which you have been
shaped. That's the kind of curiosity researchers
and creators have and I think you find it in all
crafts and professions, not just music. Basically
it's a universal problem.
It's also the problem of the universal.
What do you mean by the universal?
That's a really difficult question. Universal in
the singular or the plural? Is there plurality in
universality? I don't know. For some, univer¬
sality is an idea which has emerged from Western
civilization alone. Let's say rather that if the
people of the West didn't actually invent the idea,
they knew better than anyone else how to sell
it. It's their talent for marketing.... Others didn't
use it in the same way, that's all.
Let's accept their formulation of universality
as a working definition and ask a few questions.
Can anything else be grafted on to it? It's like
asking whether a law can be amended. Can the
universal be amended? Or, if you prefer, the
universal seems to me as an African an attrac¬
tive garment but one that's a bit tight.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
You have been writing music since the 1960s.
What public do you write for? For the whole
world or rather for Africans?
Neither one nor the other. I try to reach the
human being.
A tension leading to the universal...
Perhaps because of the noble side of music.
Because anyone can communicate with anyone
else by means of musical vibrations. Since I like
people who listen to me, I am ready to listen to
people too. I am always ready to get to know
other kinds of music. At least I have learned to
learn. I am always guided by my curiosity.
What has been the most important factor in
your creative work?
This curiosity. My appetite for getting to
know others. But what does it mean to say that
one creates? I would be more inclined to say that
one participates. Sound is a magma. You have
to give it a form. It's never the same. But you
always mould the same magma.
So you've been doing that for thirty years?
What contribution have I made? I have built a
bridge between my starting point and my curi¬
osity. I contribute a sound which is unmistak¬
ably African. I add my difference.
But in Africa doesn't your music sound some¬
what foreign?
At first people in Africa said that I made
Western music, that I was a black-white. I carried
that label around for a long time. In France people i
often told me that I made American music. And|
when I went to the United States, the Americans |
thought that I made African music. It's impos¬
sible to be more of a traitor than that!
A gift has no race. There is a race of musicians
and that's all there is to it. To belong to that race
you need knowledge. The musician, even more
than the composer, hears agreeable sounds around
him and digests them. He likes them, they are
part of him. The voices of Pavarotti and Barbara
Hendricks have taught me to love opera. In my
imaginary museum they join Louis Armstrong,
Duke Ellington, and Charlie Parker. I haven't
found anyone better. Mozart doesn't stop me
from being African. I like mixtures.
In a sense you span several continents.
you're a musician you don't say to your¬
self when you get up in the morning "I make
African music", you say "I want to make music".
And that's that.
DISCOGRAPH Y
O Bosso and Soul Makossa (1972). Super Kumba
(1974). Africadelic (1975). Film music (1976):
L'herbe sauvage (Côte d'Ivoire), Ceddo (Senegal),
Le prix de la liberté (Cameroon). Gone Clear
(1979). Ambassador (1981). Waka Juju (1982,
distr. Sonodisc). Soft and Sweet and Mélodies
africaines, vols. 1 & 2 (1983). Abele Dance and
Surtension (1984, distr. RCA). Tarn Tam pour
l'Ethiopie (1985). Electric Africa (with Herbie
Hancock and Wally Badarou, 1985). Afrijazzy
(1986, Soul Paris/distr. Mélodie). Double live
album recorded at Francofolies (1988,
BUDA/distr. Mélodie). Polysonlk (1990, Bird
Productions, distr. BMG).
Above, Manu Dibango
with the French musician and composer
Michel Portal. Left, with the American
trumpeter Don Cherry.
Isn't choosing instruments a problem?
It's the same for all musicians! When you've
learned to play an instrument you become a
good, average or excellent instrumentalist. The
important thing is to have a sound that sticks
in people's minds. Why are Stan Getz, Arm¬
strong or Manu so immediately recognizable?
Each has a sound that gets across. ,
But ifyou introduce into a given musical cul¬
ture instruments which are alien to itthe piano
or saxophone into Arab music for exampledo
you not destroy something in that music?
Yes, of course. But you never get ahead
without breaking something. When Arab instru¬
ments were invented there was, of course, a code.
But is that code immutable or can it change? Can
you add instruments to a music which existed
without them? It's for the musicians to answer
that question first. It's the instrumentalist who
will say: "Hey, this instrument does nothing for
me." Or else, "That one gives me something that
I'm going to adapt to the music I play."
How do you get the best out of a new
instrument?
Let me give you an example. There is a tradi¬
tional African instrument that I adore. It's a kind
of zanza with wooden tongues. I wanted to
include it in my own idiom, but it can only be
played in a certain tonality. What could I do?
In the piece that I composed, I prepare for it to
come in by a modulation. Then I play for a while
with the zanza, in its own specific style and
«?mode. The next problem is to phase out the
äzanza and bring in something else.
And so I decided to include the instrument
Swithout altering its nature. But you might also
¿want to modify its sound: "Hey, the zanza
S sounds good, but if I add a bit of cotton here or
la matchstick, won't I get a quarter tone more?"
lit' s a personal choice.
You don't see it in terms ofcultural references?
I The references ought to come naturally. In
S music there is neither past nor future, only the
j present. I must compose the music of my time,
g not yesterday's music. I have always been accused
I of "pinching". How can you create if you don't
take from that which gives the age its substance?
|All creators have something of the vampire in
them: painting, literature, and journalism func¬
tion like music.
Some musicians are afraid of reaching that
universal. But without that perspective what are
we here for? What's the point of curiosity,
energy, movement, if we live for seventy years
tucked away in a corner, bound hand and foot?
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
A world of music
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
by Isabelle Leymarie
Rock festival
¡n Rio de Janeiro.
Vjivilizations have always influenced and
enriched one another culturally through bor¬
rowing, osmosis and acculturation. With the
development of intercontinental communications
networks and the audiovisual media, the speed
at which these processes take place is accelerating
at a tremendous rate. Music, a source of enjoy¬
ment which transcends linguistic barriers, is one
of the more positive aspects of these exchanges.
As early as the eighth century, one of the
farthest-reaching currents of musical cross-
fertilization was making its way around the globe.
Indian music travelled to Central Asia, Iran and
Afghanistan, and also to the Middle East, where
it influenced Arab music. Arab music in turn
spread throughout North Africa to Spain, where
it gave rise to flamenco, then after the expulsion
of the Arabs from the Iberian peninsula, back
down to North Africa, where "Andalusian"
music was born.
Nevertheless, until colonial expansion and
the slave trade turned the world music order
upside down, musical traditions remained fairly
localized, centred on a village, a tribal group, or
a region, and varying from place to place in much
the same way as regional dialects, dress or
cooking.
Music has had clearly defined social and ritual
functions since very early times. In some cultures
it remained the exclusive domain of certain
individuals or groups. Among the Wolof and
Malinke peoples of West Africa, the griots were
the sole repositories of music, of genealogies, and
of the oral tradition, which they transmitted from
generation to generation. Griots were even
obliged to marry within their own group.
Many young griots today, however, perform
in modern settings and use such instruments as
saxophones and electric guitars. In Senegal this
mixture of traditional rhythms and pop music has
resulted in a new musical style called mbalax.
In Japan some musical instruments are still
associated exclusively with specific professions.
They include the geisha's shamisen and the biwa,
which is played only by blind bards. At the same
time, the Japanese are great consumers of Western
music, and in particular of French popular songs.
When, at the beginning of the sixteenth
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
century, the Portuguese and other European
colonists established themselves in Africa and
began exporting thousands of black slaves to the
Americas, an entirely new genre, "creóle" music,
was born. Portuguese-influenced music from
Cape Verde, Mozambique and Angola, and then
Afro-Cuban, Afro-Brazilian, Caribbean and Afro-
American music developed. Instruments of
African origin such as bongos, congas, timbáis,
claves (rhythmsticks) and maracas, began to be
used, notably in Cuba, and new musical forms
such as son, son montuno, bolero, guaracha and
rumba gradually emerged.
From tango to rock
In the 1920s, jazz, which had emerged as a hybrid
of Afro-American and European music and had
become associated with Art Nouveau and Moder¬
nism, blew a wind of freedom over America and
Europe. It imposed its black aesthetic on white
culture and became one of the most important
forms of popular music of the twentieth century.
It influenced and inspired composers such as
Gershwin and Debussy, and painters such as
Matisse and Mondrian. In the same way, the
tango, a blend of Bantu rhythms and Argentine
expressionism, then the rumba in the 1930s,
mambo in the 1940s, cha-cha-cha and rock 'n' roll
10
in the 1950s, all Afro-American creations, gained
world-wide popularity.
Black music is still the common denominator
(though not the only one) of most popular music
today. Funk, disco, soul, rap, rock, reggae, samba,
bossa nova, soca, Afro-beat, juju, highlife and
zouk all have African roots to some extent. In
France, Georges Moustaki, Claude Nougaro and
Bernard Lavilliers are enthusiastically exploring
Afro-Brazilian rhythms, and Nana Mouskouri is
branching out into gospel singing. In the United
States, Paul Simon has made a recent album with
Cameroonian and Brazilian musicians, and in
Japan Ryuiji Sakamoto has called on the Senegalese
The Indian-born musician
Najma plays a traditional
portable organ at a concert in
Paris (1990).
singer Youssou N'Dour to bring a little warmth
to his rather precise instrumentation.
After the Second World War, the LP record
and television contributed to the spread of pop
music, which American musicologist Peter
Manuel has described as the most significant event
in twentieth-century music: "Socio-economic and
technological development brought a bewildering
array of new styles, instruments and expressions
into being, and pop music reached a much larger
audience than any other art form ever has."
Rock music, created by Afro-American musi¬
cians like Chuck Berry and Bo Diddley and taken
up by Elvis Presley and other white singers,
became a symbol of revolt and protest for youth
the world over. It disrupted the American con-
formism of the 1950s, inspiring a new style of
dressingjeans, T-shirt and leather jacketand
revolutionizing standards of behaviour.
New forms of musical syncretism appeared
in the 1960s with the hippy-era craze for Asian,
and particularly Indian, music. Miles Davis and
John Coftrane introduced the use of Eastern-
inspired modes in jazz, and the Beatles brought
the Indian sitar to pop music. But this infatua¬
tion with exoticism made little impact on highly
structured musical forms which already possessed
a strong identity, just as attempts to mix jazz and
classical music have always failed.
During the next decade the record industry
contributed to the trend for musical blending.
The term "fusion" was coined to describe cer¬
tain types of hybrid music which were created
artificially, often from a basis in jazz, using
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Synthesizers to produce a uniform sound which
was culturally neutral and could reach very large
audiences. The Crusaders (who, significantly,
changed their name from The Jazz Crusaders) and
the saxophonist Stanley Turrentine are represen¬
tative of this trend. Most jazzmen agreed,
however, that this "fusion" was really only "con¬
fusion", a juxtaposition of distinct musical styles
which lost all their originality in the mixing
process.
Musicians who find
inspiration in other cultures
Frontiers also opened in the once compartmen¬
talized world of classical music, where an exciting
process of exchange between East, West and
Africa began. Steve Reich has used Ghanaian
drumming rhythms in his compositions, Philip
Glass has written music inspired by Pygmy poly¬
phony and several Asian composers produce
music that combines both Asian and Western
elements.
Several historical and social factors are
responsible for the present intensification of
musical blending: urbanization, decolonization
and immigration all contribute to population
movements and cultural mixtures. In the world's
great cities composite ethnic groups have deve¬
loped such as the Hispanics in New York, the
Jamaicans in London, the Californian, Texan and
New Mexican Chícanos and the Africans and
second-generation Arab immigrants in Paris. All
these groups are exposed to the multiple musical
Above, the Senegalese
singer Youssou N'Dour
and Ryuiji Sakamoto of
Japan.
Right, the Malinke griot Mory
Kante (1986).
ISABELLE LEYMARIE,
French ethnomusicologist, is a
journalist, educator and
producer of music
programmes for radio and
television, notably in France
and the United States. Since
January 1989 she has been
responsible for programming
jazz at the Châtelet Theatre
and Auditorium, Paris. She has
published many articles on jazz
and Latin American rhythms in
specialist periodicals.
influences of their environment and are searching
for their own modes of expression.
The present trend towards "world music"
may well entail a certain amount of cultural
imperialism, but more significantly it is indica¬
tive of a genuine human desire to open up cul¬
turally and go beyond political ideologies and
national borders. It is also somewhat counter¬
balanced by a worldwide renewal of regional
popular music and the increasing interest of
Western musicologists in non-Western music.
This is particularly evident in the numerous
"multicultural" music festivals that take place
every year at Lille, Angoulême and La Rochelle
in France, in the seminars organized by the New
School in New York, in the enthusiasm of
Japanese teenagers for African and Latin rhythms
and in the ever-growing number of mixed-
repertoire groups (such as Xalam and Ultrama¬
rine in Paris) whose members are themselves of
different ethnic backgrounds.
Young people in towns and cities, torn
between conflicting values, often find an emo¬
tional outlet in rock, jazz, rap or pop music that
makes them feel that they belong to a larger inter¬
national community, that they have a global iden¬
tity where tensions subside and conflicts are
resolved.
Is there reason to hope that the increasingly
close contact between the world's different forms
of music, reflecting a deeply-felt need for com¬
munication and mutual understanding, will lead
to greater humanism and a general enrichment
whereby different cultures, in opening up to one
another, will strengthen their own originality?
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
How far have
African musical
traditions
survived in
rock, jazz and
blues, whose
origins can be
traced back to
the slave
trade?
The birth of the blues
«U*
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
by Etienne Bours
and Alberto Nogueira
IN 1954, Elvis Presley recorded his first single.
On one side was his version of "That's All Right
Mama" by Big Boy Crudup, a black man, a blues
singer and the father of rock 'n' roll, and on the
other was "Blue Moon of Kentucky" by the
white father of bluegrass country music, Bill
Monroe. This was a key moment when black
music was transmuted by alchemy into white,
and white music into black. Presley turned up
in the right place at the right time. All he had
to do was pick the ripe fruit from the many
branches of trees whose roots had for centuries
been drawing sustenance from far away.
Many kinds of music which have since
become part of our culturerock, blues, jazz,
soul, rhythm and blues, and spirituals; reggae,
calypso and merengue from the Caribbean; samba
and capoeira from Brazilwould never have
existed if it had not been for the infamous trade
in "ebony wood". Today musicians who seek
their roots as well as new sources of inspiration
are creating exciting forms of hybrid music.
From Africa to the Americas
How long did Africa remain part of the musical
heritage the slaves took with them to the
Americas? Does it still provide inspiration for the
music we know today? Many writers have gone
back to Africa to try to answer these questions.
They have tried to discover the origins of the
blues and of jazz, revealing the incredible distance
that has been covered, always emphasizing the
possible linksand the inevitable breaks
between African traditions and Afro-American
music. On both sides of the Atlantic, music has
developed different idioms. "Any similarity to
what is heard in the African countries has disap¬
peared," wrote the Cuban writer Alejo Car-
pentier in 1977.1
These new forms of music were created and
developed by black people, but cross-fertilization
had diluted African memories to varying degrees,
depending on where the black communities were
established and the social conditions that existed
there.
"We might be called a people of dancers,
musicians and poets, since important events such
as a triumphant return from war or any other
reason for popular rejoicing, are celebrated by
Late 19th-century American
poster advertising a black and
white minstrel show.
dancing accompanied by appropriate music and
singing," wrote Olaudah Equiano, an Ibo slave
taken to Virginia in 1756.2 These celebrations
were not always tolerated. As a rule, the black
slaves in Latin America lived in relatively closed
communities and were able to preserve some
tribal customs as well as their traditional rites and
ceremonies. Catholicism allowed a certain lati¬
tude towards African religious practices in a con¬
text that was often syncretistic. As a result, ritual
music survived in such countries as Brazil, Haiti
and Cuba, where many cults of African origin
are still practised.
In contrast, the slaves who were transported
to the United States via the Caribbean, where
some features of their African culture were modi¬
fied or obliterated, had to live in fairly close con¬
tact with their white owners. All their ancestral
beliefs and means of self-expression were affected
from the start. In the despair of captivity they
clung to their cults, but practised them in secret.
Some of these cults survived, surreptitiously min¬
gling with white Protestantism and receiving a
new lease of life through contact with the waves
of black slaves imported from Haiti, Martinique
and Guadeloupe. Although certain beliefs were
expressed through a veil of symbolism, or
through the fervent singing of spirituals, other
African gods were worshipped in the open air,
in the depths of the Mississippi bayousas in the
case of the Vaudou cult, known as Hoodoo in
the southern United States.
Secular music, on the other hand, was forced
to comply with new functions in a new environ¬
ment that was hostile to African traditions. All
that survived were songs and dances that were
compatible with the economic and social struc¬
ture of the New World, such as the work songs
("field hollers"), born of African call and response
chants, which allowed the slaves to pace their
work and keep the overseer's whip at bay.
'Any Westerner
who dances is
unwittingly
paying tribute
to the genius
of Africa'
Abdelwahab Bouhdlba,
Pluralisme social
et pluralisme culturel,
Louvain, 1970.
1. "The Blacks in Latin America:
Africa's imprint on the art and
life of another continent", the
UNESCO Courier, August-
September 1977.
2. Paul Oliver, Savannah
Syncopators/African Retentions in
the Blues, Studio Vista, London,
1970. See also the April 1987
edition of the UNESCO Courier,
"Travellers* Tales". Editor 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The slaves could also use their talents to
entertain their masters. Many of them played the
fiddle, fife or drums. More than one escaped slave
sought by his owner was described as an excel¬
lent singer or a skilled fiddle-player. They
fashioned their instruments out of whatever
materials were available, notably inventing var¬
ious forms of lute that developed into the banjo.
This instrument, which became virtually synony¬
mous with black music, took pride of place in
the minstrel shows which began to be produced
in the early nineteenth century. These entertain¬
ments, in which the music was provided by white
men with blackened faces, were parodies of the
life and culture of the blacks. Strangely enough
black musicians eventually played their own ver¬
sions of some of the songs, and even appeared in
the shows in their own right.
Musicians who refuse
to compromise with the market
The contact between English and Irish ballads and
1 4 dances, European instruments, work songs, the
Above, a Brazilian musician
playing the berimbau, an
instrument used in candomblé
music, which is very popular
in Bahia state.
Above left, the American
trumpeter, singer and
bandleader Louis Armstrong in
1958.
Top, the American jazz singer
Ella Fitzgerald.
ETIENNE BOURS
is a Belgian journalist who
specializes in music. He has
taken part in many radio
programmes on traditional
music, and is currently working
with the Médiathèque de la
Communauté Française in
Belgium.
ALBERTO NOGUEIRA,
Portuguese journalist, is music
adviser at the Médiathèque de
la Communauté Française in
Belgium.
cries of slave and master, spirituals and gospel
songs, gave rise to the bluesblack music in
essence, but already black American. The blues,
which came from the deep South, are crucial to
the history of the great intermixture of cultures
in North America. After the birth of the blues,
black music began to be recorded, along with
what could be described as the products of the
second wave of cultural fusion. In the early
recordings, the art of the rural blues singers
appeared in its raw and authentic state. It would
never be heard in quite the same way again.
In 1900 eight out of ten black people still
lived in the countryside. By 1930, half of them
were living in industrial towns and cities. This
exodus from the countryside gave birth to other
forms of musical expression such as urban blues,
rhythm and blues, and soul music. New commer¬
cial imperatives also emerged. Black music was
gradually being subjected to the laws of the
market. Did these developments lead to authentic
or spurious forms of cultural fusion? This was,
in fact, the last stage in a long journey, during
which the music had grown further and further
away from its original functions, and perhaps had
become so thoroughly blended that it managed
to please everybody.
At the same time, many musicians refused to
compromise their art for the market. To realize
this, one need only listen to Joseph Spence, a
remarkable guitarist from the Bahamas whose
music resists commercial exploitation and the
constraints of the recording studio. His work is
an authentic cultural blend, a mixture of different
traditions which have gradually become entan¬
gled and most of whose musical expressions have
been tinted black.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Braß: a kaleidoscope of sound
by Mario de Aratanha
THE mixing of races and cultures in Brazilian
music reflects the history of this continent-sized
nation, where the Portuguese arrived in 1500 and
the Africans half a century later; where white
people married Indians, Indians married Africans,
and Africans married whites. This racial mixing
has produced one of the richest and most original
of the planet's musical heritages.
Exporting its styles and stars worldwide,
Brazilian music reflects a multi-faceted cultural
framework that currently includes at least half
a dozen fundamentally different traditions. Brazil
itself provides a huge market for recorded music.
About 80 million discs are sold there each year,
almost 70 per cent of which are of the country's
own musicthis in spite of the almost total con¬
trol of distribution by big, foreign-owned mul¬
tinationals.
Combing the country from north to south,
musicologists have already identified 365 different
basic rhythms in Brazilian music. The Jesuits
started putting together this musical kaleidoscope
when they incorporated Indian dances into their
ceremonies. The mix was later enriched by the
African cultures that came over on the slave ships.
It was then refined with the arrival of the Por¬
tuguese court in Brazil in 1808; spread by the
coffee boom of the mid-nineteenth century;
professionalized by the coming of the radio; and
carried across the seas by the cinema, record and
video industries.
The process is still continuing, and in so
doing is becoming more technologically and cul¬
turally aware. On the one hand, computers have
invaded the recording studios, the "electric trios"
of Salvador de Bahia use special effects worthy
of a Spielberg movie, and the urban young dance
to the sounds of Brazilian rock. But on the other,
Rio's pagodes and the afoxés of Bahia are cons¬
ciously returning to their African roots.
At the same time, a cultural interchange is
under way. While the lambada is fashionable with
European dancers, the young blacks of Bahia do
the samba-reggae. Tom Jobim has moved to New
A country the
size of a
continent,
where racial
and cultural
intermixture
has given birth
to rich and
original forms
of music
Left,
Gilberto Gil.
Below,
Maria Bethania.
Below left,
Gal Costa.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
York, and Gilberto Gil and Milton Nascimento
continue to conquer foreign markets. Media
superstars like David Byrne and Paul Simon
record with Brazilian musicians, following in a
tradition of cross-fertilization that earlier included
Hollywood's discovery of Carmen Miranda, Walt
Disney's Pepe Carioca cartoons, and Fred Astaire
and Ginger Rogers flying down to Rio to dance
the maxixe.
Indians and whites
Brazil's first cultural marriage was that of the
white settlers with the indigenous population.
The Jesuits introduced into their ceremonies the
catarete, a dance of the Tupi Indians, who were
the first to compose Brazilian songs in Por¬
tuguese. The limited penetration of black music
into the Northeast hinterland has helped the
ancient blending of local wind instruments with
Arab strings, as imported by the Portuguese, to
survive there. In this arid region, you can still see
characters recalling the troubadours and minstrels
of medieval Europe, guitarists and poets of the
people who travel from fair to fair singing songs
drawn from history, present-day reality, or the
dream world. In their improvised solos and duets,
Indian and Iberian sounds blend.
Closer to the coast, the music becomes more
rhythmic, percussive and African. In the urban
zone around Recife and in the neighbouring Per-
nambuco sugar-cane district, the massive black
presence makes itself felt musically in the
maracatú, the dance of the carnival parades. This
music of the Northeast coast, stretching from
Bahia to Recife and on up to Maranhâo, is of all
Brazil's styles the one that best balances Indian,
16
white and black elements in its traditions. A
similar sort of popular aesthetic also makes its
presence felt further north, as far as the Amazon
estuary, where Caribbean echoes can be heard.
The rural areas of the states of Sao Paulo and
Paraná are now among the wealthiest parts of
Latin America. Helped by this prosperity, the
dupla caipira popular, country-style music
reflecting the songs of Paraguay's Guaraní
Indianshas become one of the most saleable
musical commodities in the country, particularly
since its influence reached the city of Sào Paulo,
an industrial megalopolis with 10 million
inhabitants.
Farther south, on the vast pampas grazing-
lands, new musical horizons come into view:
those. of the Rio de la Plata, whose native music
shows the influence of the milongas, rancheras and
chamantes of Argentina and of Uruguay.
Rio, cultural capital
The two richest musical regions of Brazil are
those surrounding Bahia, in which the black
influence predominates, and around Rio de
Janeiro, Brazil's cultural capital, where most of
the nation's styles meet. All the different regional
currents, whether from Africa, Bahia, the North¬
east or anywhere else, come together in Rio.
Brazilian radio got under way there; and it is in
Rio that television is at its most creative, that
most of the recording studios and music busi¬
nesses are based, and that the labour market is
most welcoming. As a result, Rio draws musicians
from all corners of the nation.
Since the end of the last century, Rio has been
an ethnic melting pot. Nonetheless, it has its own
musical traditions, the samba and the choro,1
which began to develop after the abolition of
slavery in 1888. But even earlier, from the time
of the arrival of the Portuguese royal family
eighty years before, African lundus were already
combining with European songs. On the whole,
however, black music was confined to the slave
quarters, while the élite danced first the gavotte
and the minuet, and later the polka and the waltz.
After their emancipation, former slaves who
had a profession set themselves up in the Cidade
Nova, near the centre of the city. The rest ended
up in the least favoured districts, beside the
railway lines and on the heights of the morros.
The different economic and cultural levels of the
two groups were reflected in the development of
two distinct musical traditions. On the one hand
there was the sophisticated sound of the maxixe
and the choro; on the other the samba of the hill-
shanties, more percussive and well-suited to street
parades at carnival time. From this tradition the
samba schools were to develop. It was around this
time, at the turn of the century, that Rio had its
first professional musicians, in the sense in which
we use the term today.
The first foreign influences on Brazilian
music came in by way of the cinema in the 1930s.
Left, samba musician
Martinho da Vila in 1985.
Above, a scene at the Bahia
carnival.
MARIO DE ARATANHA
is a Brazilian journalist, record
producer and organizer of
cultural events.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
But it was in the following decade, the time of
President Roosevelt's "good neighbours" policy,
that the cultural interchange between Brazil and
the United States really gathered momentum.
Carmen Miranda left for Hollywood, and
American music flooded onto the Brazilian
market.
Good neighbours
The 1940s and 1950s were the years of dance
music par excellence, and Brazil's traditional
rhythms competed with Caribbean boleros and
American blues and foxtrots. It was the start of
the consumer era that has continued to the
present day. The top stars drew their inspiration
from the romantic songs popularized by cinema
and the record industry. The fashion was for
things foreign; inspired by cool jazz and by
bebop, Rio's music was getting ready for the
bossa nova.2
When Joào Gilberto arrived in Rio from
Bahia with the batida, his own particular guitar
rhythm, he found the ground ripe for the bossa
nova, which conquered first Brazil and then the
United States. The 1960s therefore reversed the
tendency to cultural importation that marked the
previous decade and saw the beginning of a new
cross-fertilization, one that was not simply ethnic
but cultural. Aided by radio, the record industry,
show business and television, the Rio music bus¬
iness took off. Elis Regina, Caetano Veloso, Gil¬
berto Gil, Gal Costa, Maria Bethania, Milton
Nascimento, Chico Buarque, Tom Jobim: around
the big names different musical trends coalesced,
all linked under the general label of Brazilian pop.
These urban sounds remain among the most
important musical influences in the nation to
this day.
This was the era of the great pop festivals,
with Beatlemania serving as a backdrop. But the
rock guitar of Brazilian pop soon gave way to
Tropicalism, a cri de coeur for moral and aesthetic
liberty launched by Caetano Veloso and Gilberto
Gil. Political dissent invaded the realm of music,
growing into full-blooded revolt against the mili¬
tary dictatorship set up in 1964. Under the new
rulers, harsh artistic censorship joined up with
police violence to silence a generation.
Yet the movement was strong enough to 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
survive censorship by seeking refuge in exile
or in metaphor. Poetry slipped in between the
lines of the texts the censors scanned. Neverthe¬
less, the general tendency of the 1970s was
towards a less political music. The samba returned
to popularity with Paulinho da Viola, Beth
Carvalho and Martinho da Vila.
Eclectic and electric
The devastating effects of twenty years of mili¬
tary dictatorship hit the intelligentsia of Brazil's
cultural capital hard. The great names of the 1960s
survived, but successors were hard to find. In the
1980s the greatest opportunities were for the most
commercial kind of rock music, whose artistic
triumph was assured by media coverage. Rita Lee
became a superstar, Alceu Valença created his
own hybrid, forrock,3 funk invaded the black
suburbs of the big cities, and all-Brazilian rock
groups made their appearance: Paralamas do
Sucesso, Cazuza and the Barâo Vermelho, Ultraje
a Rigor, Titas and Legiào Urbana.
Yet in reaction to the growing homogeniza-
tion of the FM radio hits, a new trend in favour
of cultural conservation and a return to roots also
developed. Over the past few years, black music
has found new life in the pagodes, gatherings of
samba musicians in suburban Rio backyards that
have produced such names as Zeca Pagodinho,
Almir Guineto, Fundo de Quintal and Jovelina
Pérola Negra.
The return to sources is most pronounced,
though, in Bahia, where so much of Brazilian
music has had its origins. Bahia has been the
home of black culture ever since the arrival of
the first Bantu slaves; and even though its racial
background and customs are not dissimilar to
Rio's, its atmosphere remains more authentic
as does its music, which retains close ties to the
religious cults originating in Angola, Nigeria,
Senegal or Guinea-Bissau. Preserved for centuries
in the rites of the candomblé, it finally freed itself
from them at the end of the last century, win¬
ning popularity early in the present one.
In the 1930s, the first Bahia carnivals were
dominated by the afoxés, groups of musicians with
a religious bent that paraded in the streets like
the samba schools of Rio, but to a slow, almost
funereal beat known as the ijexa. The tradition
was broken in the following decade by two
revolutionaries, Dodo (who was black) and
Osmar (who was white). They joined to form the
Trio Elétrico, the group that was to alter com¬
pletely the nature of the Bahia carnival. They
made their debut on an old Ford truck with an
amplified guitar and cavaquinho (a small, four-
stringed instrument). Six or seven percussionists
paraded behind them on foot. The new style soon
caught on, and the size of the bands playing it
grew, along with the volume of sound they
produced and the musical influences they exerted.
In their treatment of radio hits, Rio march
tunes znàfrevos4 from Recife, the three or four
"electric trios" of the early days soon adopted
a fast beat. Whenever one of them crossed the
path of an afoxé band, it tended to throw the
slower ensemble out of time, to such an extent
that the afoxé musicians in their turn had, in self
defence, to speed up the tempo. This competi¬
tive spirit gave a hallucinatory quality to the
Bahia carnival that was one of the elements in
its success: starting out as a four-day event, it was
soon running not far short of three months. And
the three or four trios of the 1940s grew to
number eighty or more.
The trios vastly improved their equipment
in the 1970s. Mounted on lorries fitted with loud¬
speakers, they could make themselves heard over
much greater distances, drawing ever-bigger
crowds. Gradually these motorized stages became
more imposing even than Rio's allegorical car¬
nival floats. The trio called Coca-Cola, for
example, advertised their presence with a gigantic
mobile bottle, while Caetanave travelled in a
spaceship complete with special effects. Some of
the lorries were even equipped with lifts.
Amplification, the use of electronic instru¬
ments and the influence of urban rhythms linked
Folk engravings from
Northeast Brazil and
the cover of a compact
disc featuring the Trío
Elétrico Dodo & Osmar.
A P
PB*- ..[I«10"
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
to rock have modernized the music of the trios,
which has now moved onto the radio and records
thanks to Osmar's son, Armandinho, and espe¬
cially to the Novos Bahianos, successors to the
Tropicalism of Gilberto Gil and Caetano Veloso.
Bahian music is coming to terms with modern
technology; in future its customary vitality will
take different forms, some traditional, others
progressive.
Effervescent Bahia
In the competitive atmosphere of the 1980s, when
Brazilian pop vied for audiences with rock and
with romantic ballads, it was Bahia that walked
away with the prizes. Luis Caldas came on the
scene, as did the lambada, which originated in the
Caribbean but was soon integrated into Bahia
swing. One of the characteristics of the city's
musical tradition is that wherever it takes its
influences from, be it California, Rio de Janeiro,
Jamaica or Dahomey, they quickly become
Bahian.
Practically all the city's music-making centres
on the annual carnival. Even new, professional
bands like Chiclete com Banana, Mel, Reflexus
and Cheiro de Amor retain links with the
politically-aware street bands in the afoxé tradi¬
tion, including Olodum, Ara-Ketu, the Filhos de
Gandhi and many others, among them the same
groups that speeded up the ijexa beat to protect
themselves from the "electric trios".
The musicians work all the year round,
flooding the now self-sufficient Bahia market
with their records. The crowds live their music
in an atmosphere of effervescence. The influence
of Jamaica, and the political force of the
Rastafarian movement are strong; they have com¬
bined to make a demi-god of Bob Marley, and
the samba-reggae has become a classic example
of cultural cross-fertilization.
The aesthetic of the back-to-Africa movement
does not follow any established model. At the last
carnival, for instance, Ara-Ketu featured wind
instruments, guitars and synthesizers alongside
traditional African drums; while the authenticity
of Olodum's traditional drumming caught the ear
of Paul Simon. In the Africanization process, new
and old, local and foreign, come together; and the
people, who only want to dance, love it all.
A samba school.
1. The choroliterally, "lament"
is a mixture of European styles,
notably the schottische, waltz,
tango, polka and habanera.
2. Bossa nova means "new wave" in
Portuguese.
3. A contraction of forró dance
originating in the Northeastand
rock.
4. The frevo is a dance with Iberian
and Brazilian roots and a frenzied
rhythm. Editor 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The music of
Texas-Mexicans
expresses
the tensions of
a community
that remains
deeply
attached to its
cultural roots
while aspiring
to be part of
American
society
Tex-Mex music by Manuel Peña
THE American southwestthe states of Texas,
New Mexico, Arizona and Californiawas once
a part of Mexico. And, despite the lapse of almost
150 years since the United States annexed the ter¬
ritory, the Mexican-Americans of the southwest
still maintain a staunch allegiance to Mexican cul¬
ture, notably where music is concerned. This is
particularly marked among the people of New
Mexico, while the Mexican-Americans of Los
Angeles lay claim to a more recent but vigorous
musical tradition. Yet among Americans of Mex¬
ican descent, only in Texas do we find such deep
and robust folk traditions as those embodied in
música tejana, or "Tex-Mex" music. In fact, the
Texas-Mexicans have developed two distinctive
musical traditions, each with its preferred instru¬
ments and style, whose influence extends far
beyond the Texas borders: the conjunto (also
known as música norteña) and the orquesta tejana,
or simply orquesta.
Although only the conjunto is truly
indigenous to the Texas-Mexicans, both forms of
music possess vigorous and original features. And
if popular success can be taken as a criterion of
quality, then the wide diffusion of both the
conjunto and the orquesta throughout the
American southwest and beyond testifies to the
musical genius of the Texas-Mexicans.
Why have the Texas musicians been the
leading innovators among Mexican-Americans of
the southwest, and what are the factors that con¬
tribute to the cultural significance enjoyed by the
"Tex-Mex" tradition? The answer lies in the
nature of the contact between Anglo-Americans
(Anglos) and Mexican-Americans. In short, the
cultural and innovative vigour of the conjunto
and the orquesta derives from the special role each
has fulfilled in defining and mediating the inter-
cultural conflict that has existed between these
two communities in Texas.
There is no doubt that the Texas-Mexicans
bore the brunt of the Anglos' arrival, but they
did not yield easily to Anglo domination. In the
ensuing climate of intercultural resistance and ani¬
mosity, forms of expression that defined and con¬
trasted the two groups flourishedfor example,
the various stereotypes that each continues to
hold about the other.
The development of the conjunto and the
orquesta cannot be explained without reference
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Left, the Conjunto Bernai
(around 1965) and (far left)
Narciso Martínez and Santiago
Almedia, two leading figures
in conjunto music (1938).
Above, Beto Villa and his
orquesta (around 1948).
Top, an orquesta of working
men (around 1915).
MANUEL PENA,
an American anthropologist
specializing in the music and
folklore of the Mexican-
Americans, is a professor of
humanities at California State
University, Fresno. He is the
author of The Texas-Mexican
Conjunto: History of a Working-
Class Music.
to this culturally charged atmosphere, but it
would be an oversimplification to ascribe their
vigour solely to that conflict. Since the beginning
of the century another factor has complicated the
issuethe opposition in Texas-Mexican society
between two distinct socio-economic groups, the
working class and an upwardly-mobile group
striving for middle-class status.
The conjunto,
soul of popular culture
The rapid evolution of the conjunto into a
mature, standardized style between 1935 and 1960
can be linked to the cultural strategies of the
téjanosthe mass of working-class people
employed in unskilled and semi-skilled jobs in
ranching, agribusiness, and retail services. A
musical style forged by a class which faced dis¬
crimination not only from an oppressive Anglo
community, but from an unsympathetic (if small)
Texas-Mexican middle class, the conjunto is
historically rooted in the working-class conscious¬
ness. In their preference for a unique folk style
which they themselves created, the tejano
workers have voiced their most profound cultural
and aesthetic identity, embodied in their choice
of instruments, genres and styles (all of them of
Mexican character), and the appropriate context
for their performance.
Of course, long before the modern conjunto
ensemble of diatonic button accordion, twelve-
string guitar, electric bass and drums had become
standardized, the accordion had become a
favourite instrument among the workers on both
sides of the Texas-Mexico border. Cheap German
models, with their single row of melody buttons,
were easily obtainable for the dances of the
téjanos and norteños (the people of northern
Mexico).
But the popularity of the accordion did not
go unchallenged. The Anglos, and later the
upwardly-mobile Texas-Mexicans, were quick to
condemn conjunto music. For example, in 1880
the San Antonio Express commented disparagingly
on the fandangos where the téjanos danced,
usually to accordion music: "These fandangos are
becoming so frequent they are a great curse to
the country. The respectable class of Mexicans
do not attend them."
Despite such condemnations, by both Anglos
and the "respectable class of Mexicans", the
accordion and its dances flourished, acquiring a
powerful presence that has endured to this day.
Particularly during the generally prosperous post¬
war years (1946-1960), the modern conjunto
experienced a rapid maturation and wide dispersal
in Texas and beyond. In the hands of such notable
talents as Narciso Martínez, Valerio Longoria,
Tony de la Rosa, Paulino Bernai, Ramón Ayala,
Flaco Jiménez and Estaban Jordán, the conjunto
has maintained an unchallenged supremacy
among working-class Texas-Mexicans.
The social strategy
of the orquesta
In contrast to the conjunto, the orquesta style of
music has tended, since the 1920s at least, to be
more "respectable" in that it has rpaintained a
strong association with the genteel elfcments of
Texas-Mexican society. Although orquestas
existed among the working class since the late
nineteenth century, they were poorly equipped
groups with a collection of makeshift instru¬
ments. This was especially true of rural areas,
where the lack of social and economic resources
made it difficult to maintain a well-organized
ensemble.
In the late 1920s, a new kind of dance
orquesta patterned on the American swing bands
began to gain currency, particularly in the larger
cities with their sizeable middle class. With a line¬
up of a least one trumpet, one saxophone, and
a rhythm section of guitar, bass, drums and (occa¬
sionally) piano, the new orquestas soon acquired 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
a unique Texas-Mexican character and had gained
a solid foothold by the late 1930s.
These ensembles clearly articulated the strate¬
gies of the small but growing middle class, which
became particularly influential after the Great
Depression of the 1930s. This group attempted
to distance itself from the Mexican workers and
sought to imitate the lifestyles of middle-class
Anglo-America. Hence its demand for American
music, which was generously represented in
orquesta repertoires by foxtrots, boogie-woogie
and swing music.
But the orquestas did not by any means res¬
trict themselves to American music. In fact the
hallmark of the Texas-Mexican orquesta soon
became its extreme stylistic diversity. It had far
more faces than any of the musical styles that
influenced it (including the conjunto). Even a cur¬
sory listening to the commercial recordings made
since the 1940s reveals the eclectic repertoire,
ranging from American swing to conjunto folk¬
songs, through Latin American dances such as the
danzón and the bolero. The orquesta has a charac¬
teristic tendency to transform the Mexican bolero
into the Tex-Mex polka, a unique genre that oscil¬
lates between an American and a Mexican pulse
by frequently interrupting the Latin American
beat with several bars of swing.
The stars of the Tex-Mex orquesta are Beto
Villa, who is considered the originator of the
style, and Little Joe Hernández, whose innova¬
tions revolutionized its development. Villa, who
became immensely popular throughout the
southwest after the release of his first recordings
in 1946, was most acclaimed for his folksy, "ran¬
chero" polkas, although he successfully blended
these homegrown polkas with the more cos¬
mopolitan rhythms of the American foxtrot and
the Latin American bolero and danzón.
Little Joe introduced a fresh wave of innova¬
tions in the early 1970s by infusing the Tex-Mex
polkas of Beto Villa with a strong dose of
American jazz and rock. This new sound, which
took the Mexican-American community by
storm, soon came to be known as la onda chicana
("the Chicano wave"). Such was Little Joe's
success that his orquesta became virtually synony¬
mous with Chicano music during the 1970s.
Throughout the southwest, amateur orquestas
were all striving to duplicate his original style.
The cultural significance of the orquesta is
inextricably linked both to the working-class
roots of the upwardly-mobile Texas-Mexicans and
to their desire to become more Americanized.
The orquesta, aware of this bicultural exis¬
tence, vacillated between Mexican and American
styles and genres, between its folk roots and its
newfound urban modernity, and between its
working-class origins and its increasing affluence.
The historical importance of the orquesta thus
may be said to lie in the desire of the Mexican
middle class to overcome the contradiction
between attempts at assimilation and a persistent
ethnic allegiance.
A musical blend
which takes its
harmonic
concepts and
instrumentation
from jazz, and
its themes,
rhythms and
beat from Afro-
Latin cultures
Latin
BY the time jazz got under way in New
Orleans in about 1920, the African drum, banned
in America during the slavery era, had completely
disappeared. So practitioners of the new music
borrowed the big bass drum of the military
bands, topped with a cymbal, which provided the
rhythm for the famous black parades that wended
their way through the city's streets at carnival
time or was used to accompany funerals. The
drum served essentially as a metronome; it simply
kept time, with almost no attempt at improvisa¬
tion. Eventually the military drum gave way to
the familiar jazz drum-kit, but even so American
percussionists kept to fairly rudimentary
rhythmic patterns right up to the bebop era of
the 1940s.
In Cuba, however, where the African
inheritance was still very much alive, the popular
musicians of the day used a whole range of tradi¬
tional percussion instrumentscongas, bongos,
timbáis, kettledrums, claves (rhythmsticks),
maracas, güiras (grooved calabashes)that
allowed them to build up rhythms in splendid
confusion. Jazz musicians began to borrow these
Afro-Cuban instruments in the 1940s.
As early as the end of the nineteenth century,
however, black ragtime pianists in America had
begun to use a bass line derived from the
habanera, which the Creole pianist and composer
Louis Moreau Gottschalk had brought back with
him from Cuba some decades earlier. This motif,
marked by a time-lag between the two hands, was
taken up by the father of the blues himself, W.C.
Handy, who travelled to Cuba in 1910 with the
American army, and it was later adopted by such
other pianists as "Professor Longhair", himself
a native of New Orleans. Jelly Roll Morton, the
self-styled inventor of jazz, had it in mind when
he talked of the "Latin tinge" in his music.
When -New Orleans's famous red-light dis¬
trict, Storyville, was closed down for good in the
late 1920s, many musicians found themselves out
of work and decided to travel north. New York
became the new capital of jazz, and Fletcher Hen¬
derson, Duke Ellington and a host of other
pianists helped light up the nights of Harlem,
then in the midst of its famous renaissance.
Several Cuban musicians, notably the flautist
Alberto Socarras, were attracted by the efferves¬
cent musical climate.
Puerto Ricans, who had gained American
nationality in 1917, were also moving into town.
They settled first in Brooklyn, then in East
Harlem, a former Jewish and Italian district that
quickly won the name of "El Barrio". Together
with the Cubans, they opened theatres and clubs
that provided a market for Latin rhythms. But
the outlets remained limited, so many Latin musi¬
cians were also forced to learn to play American
music.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
JAZZ
Jazz meets Cuban music
Socarras started by playing the Cotton Club and
in black revues, recording the first flute solos in
jazz with Clarence Williams, Sidney Bechet's and
Louis Armstrong's producer. Once he had built
up a reputation, he founded a big band that mixed
classical music, Cuban rhythms and jazz. His
music was a total novelty at the time, and one
contemporary American critic wrote of the
"savage intensity" of the band's rhythm section.
Although Socarras was black, he overcame racial
barriers in many clubs that had previously been
closed to coloured bands, taking his tropical
drums as far afield as Illinois and Nebraska.
The Puerto Rican trombonist Juan Tizol also
embarked on an American jazz career, joining the
Duke Ellington orchestra in the late 1920s. For
Ellington he composed the first Latin jazz
numbers, Caravan and Perdido. He also introduced
Above, the Cuban
percussionist Mongo
Santamaría.
Right, the Cuban singer and
bandleader Machito in Paris
(1975).
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Ill ILL!!
his boss to the structure of Cuban music which,
unlike jazz which allows its soloists complete
freedom of invention, is based on a very precise
superposition of rhythms, each of which has its
own particular part to play in an acoustic tapestry
that is constantly changing. The conga follows
one predetermined line, the bongo another. Bass
and piano both also make their own contribu¬
tion to the polyphonic rhythms. Whatever notes
they may be playing, Cuban musicians must
respect a particular style of phrasing that neo¬
phytes (and even experienced jazzmen) often find
hard to pick up.
Other American bandleaders, among them
Chick Webb and Cab Calloway, fell for the
charms of the bolero, guaracha and rumbaall
three of them Cuban imports. In turn, jazz made
its first tentative incursions into Cuba. Duke
Ellington went to Havana in 1933, and American-
style big bands began to be formed there. But
New York in the early 1940s was the real home
of the fusion of jazz and Cuban music that
became known first as "cubop" (from Cuba and
bebop) then as Latin jazz once other rhythms
were added to it.
In the late 1930s Mario Bauza, a one-time
trumpeter with Cab Calloway who had grown
tired of the watered-down Cuban music then to
be heard from Xavier Cugat's orchestra and other
dance bands, decided to form an ensemble that
would blend real Cuban rhythms with jazz. He
named his new band the Afro-Cubans, brought
his brother-in-law, the singer Machito (his real
name was Frank Grillo), over to join it, and won
the backing of Calloway's arranger. At first the
music was rough-edged; the band brought
together Cubans, Puerto Ricans and an American
trumpet-player, all of whom would riff wildly
together at the end of the choruses. The trumpet-
player sometimes stumbled on the Cuban
rhythms, and the Latin members at first had
difficulties with the complex harmonies of jazz.
But Bauza gradually succeeded in blending the
two musical languages, and the ensemble soldered
itself into a cohesive whole. The Afro-Cubans
made their public debut at an East Harlem club
in 1940, and their daring new music soon won
over the dancers. American drummers were par¬
ticularly struck by the bongos, never having seen
bare-handed drumming before.
Some Americans criticized the new music for
The early days of the Cotton
Club in New York (1927), with
Duke Ellington at the piano
(left).
Three famous American jazz
musicians: saxophonist
Charlie Parker with bassist
Tommy Potter and trumpeter
Miles Davis (1947).
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
evoking the caricature of a "primitive" Africa as
fostered by Hollywood films. Gradually, though,
jazzmen lent an ear. Attracted by the band's sig¬
nature tune Tanga, Stan Kenton in 1947 hired the
percussionists to record his big hit The Peanut
Vendor. But his grandiloquent style of jazz did
little justice to true Cuban music. On the other
hand Charlie Parker, who cut some tracks with
the Afro-Cubans in 1950, at once caught the spirit
of the music. His alto saxophone flies high on
Mango Mangué, Okidoke, Canción and Jazz,
weaving a web of melody over a background of
torrid rhythm.
A stunning conga player
from Havana
The other great catalyzer of Latin jazz was Dizzy
Gillespie. From the moment of his arrival in New
York he fell in love with Cuban music, whose
verve reminded him of the black rhythms of his
native South Carolina. He first played with
Socarras, who taught him Cuban rhythms, then
became friendly with Bauza, who brought him
into the Calloway band. It was Bauza who, in
1946, recommended to Gillespie the extraordi¬
nary percussionist Chano Pozo, recently arrived
from Cuba. Vain and a brawler, Pozo had built
up a solid reputation in Havana as a conga player
and composer. He belonged to a secret mutual
aid society, the nanigo, that had originated in
Nigeria and whose membership was limited to
men who had proved their courage and virility.
He was therefore well-placed to understand Afro-
Cuban ritual chants and the more arcane features
of the rumba.
Impressed by his drumming, singing and
dancing, Gillespie hired Pozo to play in his big
band. But the Cuban's rhythms clashed with
those of the band's existing drummer, Kenny
Clarke, since the downbeat of traditional jazz
differed from that of Cuban music. Gillespie set
about explaining jazz phrasing to Pozo, and the
results were the classics of Latin jazz Manteca and
Tin Tin Deo.
Latin jazz was also gathering momentum in
Cuba, where some excellent bands were formed.
But the Havana clubs, catering for the foreign
tourist trade, generally preferred to hire bland
cosmopolitan showbands rather than feature the
invigorating local music. Nonetheless, the instru¬
ments and harmonies of jazz fused with Cuban
percussion and rhythms in the remarkable big
bands led by Bebo Valdés and Benny Moré.
Back in New York, Chano Pozo was shot
dead in a Harlem bar in December 1948 at the
age of thirty-three. But he had paved the way for
a stream of other Latin percussionists to record
with jazz musicians.
Cuban jazz moved out of the limelight in the
late 1950s. It was Dizzy Gillespie who reanimated
the Latin sound in the ensuing decade by bringing
in fresh, Brazilian blood. On a trip to Rio he
heard the popular samba and bossa nova, and
brought the new sounds back with him to New
York. In fact bossa nova, which had been created
by the guitarist Joào Gilberto and popularized
by the composers Carlos Jobim and Vinicius de
Moraes and the guitarist Baden Powell, already
reflected a jazz influence. Unlike samba, which
was carnival music, bossa nova was calm and
sophisticated, full of refined and unexpected har¬
monies. Its principal charm, though, lay in its dis¬
tinctive driving rhythm, the batida, born of a
slight asynchronization between the melody and
its accompaniment that created a climate of
ambiguity, as though the music were floating, sus¬
pended between beats.
Stan Getz made the new rhythm his own, and
even while he was still coming to grips with its
complexities made the album Bossa Nova that was
to be one of his greatest successes. Cannonball
The American trumpeter,
singer and bandleader Dizzy
Gillespie in Paris in 1990.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26
Adderley, Charlie Byrd and the musicians of
the Modern Jazz Quartet (which played with the
Brazilian guitarist Laurindo Almeida) also showed
an interest in the subtle, swaying rhythms of
bossa nova and in the samba's irrepressible
energy.
In the early 1950s, Latin jazz combos gradu¬
ally supplanted the big bands, made obsolete by
the rise of rock 'n' roll. In 1953 the English pianist
George Shearing formed a group in California
that included several Cuban percussionists, one
of whom was Mongo Santamaría. Shearing
brought discs by local pianists back from Havana;
he was particularly struck by their rhythmic
understatement and their habit of playing
melodic lines with both hands at once.
New York combos
and Havana big bands
The other great combo of the 1950s was formed
by Santamaría himself in New York, for as well
as being an outstanding percussionist in the Afro-
Cuban tradition he was also a formidable talent
scout. First he hired the still-unknown Brazilian
pianist Joâo Donato, then Chick Corea, Hubert
Laws and other future jazz stars. In the 1960s
Santamaría spent some time in Brazil, fascinated
by Afro-American music as well as Latin rhythms
(Watermelon Man was his first big hit). He
managed to integrate these different influences
in a cohesive style that reflected his own strong
personality.
In the 1970s, the young Colombian Justo
Almario, a magisterially talented flautist, sax¬
ophonist, arranger and composer, collaborated
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Above, the Cuban trumpeter
Arturo Sandoval during a
concert in Cuba (1989).
Above left, Carlos Jobim (left)
and Vinicius de Moraes, two
great Brazilian exponents of
bossa nova.
Left, the Brazilian musician
Milton Nascimento in 1986.
with Santamaría, bringing fresh dynamism to the
line-up. Witness the superb The Promised Land,
in which a richly harmonic passage for flute and
saxophone follows a prelude reflecting the
influence of John Coltrane; while Almario's
improvisation with Al Williams on Songfor You
is one of the most exquisite and rigorously con¬
structed flute solos to be heard in either the
jazz or Latin traditions. On his Ubane album,
Santamaría introduced the cumbia, a traditional
Colombian rhythm played on the hand drum,
while on Red Hot he featured a richly melodic
little samba of Almario's.
Politics cut Cuba off from America after
1960, but young Cuban musicians nonetheless
continued eagerly to soak up the jazz influence.
It came as a surprise to Dizzy Gillespie, when he
visited Havana in 1977, to find just how high a
standard the local musicians had maintained. His
present big band includes three Cubans: the trum¬
peter Arturo Sandoval, whom he met in Havana;
the drummer Ignacio Berroa; and the saxophonist
Paquito D'Rivera. Gillespie, a long-time connois¬
seur of tropical rhythms, also hired, alongside his
American sidemen, a Puerto Rican percussionist,
a Panamanian pianist, a Dominican saxophonist,
three Brazilians and a trombone player of Mex¬
ican descent.
Two years after Gillespie's Cuban trip, the
Havana-based band Irakere, mixing African
drums, electric guitars and synthesizers, swept
into the United States like a musical whirlwind,
carrying off a Grammy awardthe nation's
highest music-industry honour.
The present generation of Cuban musicians
remains open to outside ideas, but combines the
search for a determinedly new sound with the
desire to remain within the island's musical
heritage. Among the best of them is the young
pianist Gonzalo Rubalcaba, a scion of one of the
island's most distinguished musical dynasties
whose group has performed successfully at several
international festivals.
Brazil, like Cuba traditionally a musical
melting pot, also has an active Latin-jazz scene.
To create original sounds, the Zimbo Trio,
guitarists Egberto Sigmondi and Toninho Horta,
the saxophonist Paolo Moura, the pianist Wagner
Tiso and the multi-instrumentalist Hermeto
Pascoal all draw on a variety of sources: samba,
bossa nova, the folk traditions of the Northeast
coast, and the music of the African-inspired cults,
batucada, candomblé and afoxé.
Hailing from Belo Horizonte, Milton Nas¬
cimento draws inspiration from his native Minas
Gerais for his moving and dream-like music, full
of unfamiliar harmonies, whose rhythms are
unlike those of the samba and the bossa nova. The
poignant beauty of his compositions has attracted
the attention of such American jazz musicians as
Stanley Turrentine, Sarah Vaughan and Herbie
Hancock, all of whom have provided loving
cover versions.
On the whole, however, the Brazilian music
industry has not proved very welcoming to Latin
jazz, so many of the best practitioners such as
Airto Moreira, Tania Maria, Eliane Elias and
Dom Salvador have found larger audiences for
their music abroad, particularly in the United
States. In American clubs and recording studios,
the jazz and Latin traditions continue to enrich
each other as happily as in the past, and Brazilian
music still offers jazz its subtle harmonic palette.
In New York, a magnet for people of many
cultures, Latin jazz is currently engaged in a
process of intense cross-fertilization. Besides the
Brazilians, there are Argentine musicians drawing
on the lyrical inspiration of the tango, Colom¬
bians with the warm rhythms of the cumbia,
Dominicans with the turbulent merengue, as well
as musicians brought up to the rhythms of the
languid Jamaican calypso, the cadenced tambor-
cito of Panama and the fiery bomba and plena
of Puerto Rico. New York Puerto Ricans like
Tito Puente, growing up at the meeting place of
all these divergent styles, integrate many different
influences in their music, including jazz, soul,
salsa and Afro-Cuban and Puerto Rican folklore.
The Cubans who arrived after 1980, among them
Paquito D'Rivera and Ignacio Berroa as well as
the master-drummers Daniel Ponce and Puntilla,
also spice their music with the rhythm of the
songo, invented in Havana in the 1970s, as well
as with elements of the black traditional music
of their homeland.
Today Latin jazz is enjoyed around the world
by a growing number of enthusiasts. Bands from
Africa, Japan and Europe happily try their hand
at it, showing that while it is sometimes difficult
for the different nations to reach political accord,
musical unity is already a reality.
KL« 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Can Russian rock survive now that it has
emerged from underground?
In foreground, Pyotr
Mamonov, lead singer of a
Russian rock group.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
CM
- / /-
-64-
\ :\
'/ ,
1
r .ça
The rockers1 lament
by Aleksandr Sokolansky
Re
ALEKSANDR SOKOLANSKY
is a Soviet art and drama
critic. His many publications on
the theory and practice of the
modern theatre, the avant-
garde and rock culture include
"The Images of Russian
Rock".
LOCK is more than music, it's a way of life,"
said Boris Grebenshikov, a leader of the Russian
rock movement in the 1980sa time when most
Russian rockers were well acquainted with
poverty, underground existence and persecution.
Rock music became assimilated into Russian
culture between the late 1960s and the late 1970s,
when it was perceived as bearing a dynamic and
attractive image of Western civilization. To listen
to this kind of music or to play in a rock group
was a relatively safe form of dissidence.
In the early days even the most rudimentary
equipment was in short supply, and for rockers
access to a stage or concert hall was difficult.
Singing to guitar accompaniment in private apart¬
ments became a tradition which is still widespread
today. The movement was strongly influenced
by such immensely popular poets and song¬
writers as Vladimir Vysotsky, Bulat Okudjava
and Aleksandr Galich. Rock lyrics, rich with
social and political meaning, are usually more
important than the music itself.
Russia's rock generation belonged to a cul¬
ture of dissatisfaction, disillusion and frustration.
"We know a new dance, but we have no legs.
We went to see a new film, but they suppressed
it," sang the Leningrad group Aquarium,
expressing all their resentment at a way of life
which disgusted them but seemed unchangeable.
In the early 1980s the rock generation estab¬
lished close contact with young post-avant-garde
artists, poets, film and theatre directors. They
lived and worked in the same underground
atmosphere conducive to an active exchange of
ideas. In this period rock music grew into a
unique and original phenomenon of Russian cul¬
ture. Tastes were shaped by such groups as
Aquarium, Kino, and Zoo, whose lead singer
Mike Naumenko included both traditional rock
'n' roll and captivating ballads in his repertoire.
Popularized clandestinely and through the
samizdat press, Russian rock gradually established
itself as authentic modern folklore. It mocked
official light music and came into direct confron¬
tation with the cultural establishment of an
authoritarian society. The repressive campaign
that was launched against rockers in 1983
wrecked many lives but failed to crush the rapidly
developing movement. By the mid-1980s the rock
movement was still working underground but it
had already developed a production network and
a recording industry.
In the mid-1980s the social climate relaxed
somewhat, giving rise to a new wave of optimism.
Perhaps the world had still not changed for the
better, but people had at least acquired a certain
freedom in their relations with it. The new frame
of mind was characterized by a spirit of solidarity
and a desire for action. Rock music rapidly
evolved a less aggressive, more thoughtful
philosophy.
Then, at last, it came out into the open. Rock
records were issued, mass concerts were held, tel¬
evision programmes were devoted to rock music,
and groups toured the country. Paradoxically,
however, legalization of rock music was followed
by a period of decline. In a more open society,
rock ceased to be a universal language of com¬
munication between non-conformist youth.
Many intellectuals also lost their enthusiasm for
it. Perhaps Russian rock was capable of anything
except becoming just another art form. The new
generation wants soft drinks; rock is too strong
a brew.
Nevertheless, a few Russian rock groups are
entering the 1990s with confidence. The most
prominent among them is DDT, whose lead
singer Yuri Shevchuk claims he is ready to meet
any challenge. Perhaps the swan song of Russian
rock has not yet been sung. 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Echoes
from afar
Music from
other cultures
has helped
many
composers to
discover their
creative
identity
by Véronique Brindeau
T
30
HE Paris Universal Exposition of 1889 revealed
to Debussy the music of Java and the theatre of the
Far East. The musical results of this shock were
soon to appear in his work. What concerns us
here, however, is the extent to which Debussy's
discovery was a sign of the times of which he was
a witness. For in his attitude, his willingness to
listen to the music of other cultures and assimi¬
late elements of it into his own creative activity,
this composer so often cited for his role in the
modern movement was anticipating the
behaviour of many later musicians.
Debussy's encounter with Asian music did
not lead him to borrow phrases, to imitate or
adopt the superficial colouring of another style.
In a word, it did not lead him to exoticism. What
now began to appear in his works, particularly
his piano pieces, was in part a new sense of dis¬
tance but above all a confirmation of styles of
composition that were already apparent but now
became more pronounced.
Debussy might have reflected the influence
of Javanese music in a more direct and literal way.
His attraction for what he saw in it tells us some¬
thing about the kind of person he was, in the
sense that he seems to have taken from a world
of sounds that was unfamiliar to him something
thatwith his fascination for timbre and
resonancehe already possessed. This was the
time when he was writing Pagodes for piano,
which recalls the Javanese slendro scale.
Encounters and
metamorphoses
One of the many questions this story brings to
mind is how the profound changes of the present
century, and especially the revolution in commu¬
nications and in recording techniques, have
affected the impact of similar discoveries on other
composers.
Encounters with cultures radically different
from their own have marked an important step
in the work of many twentieth-century artists,
not only musicians but painters who experienced
a revelation when they discovered African art or
Chinese wash drawings, or even painting in oils
and pastel.
What has for the most part been new in this
century is that musicians have no longer limited
their use of foreign models simply to imitative
borrowing. Theirs has been no tourist's glance
at an unfamiliar culture. This is not, of course,
to deny that many compositions have revelled in
the idiom of their models, from Erik Satie's La
Tyrolienne to the tearoom chinoiserie of Ravel's
L'Enfant et les sortilèges-Ravel, who so skilfully
harmonized his Cinq mélodies grecques and com¬
posed his Chansons madécasses with far-away
Madagascar in mind.
What we have seen is a rapid metamorphosis,
in which composers have striven to incorporate
as organically as possible in their own music
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
In a studio in New Mexico
(USA), composer Tony Hymas
(at the keyboard)
records his work Oyaté with
American Indian saxophonist
Jim Pepper.
elements that they had discovered in other musi¬
cians' work. I say other "musicians", because I
think that it makes more sense to talk of the
process in terms of learning from other
individuals and forms of music rather than from
styles that are specific to different world regions.
It is worth pointing out at this juncture that
the very idea of cultural intermixture implies that
traditions are in some curious way "pure",
whereas they are, of course, virtually inextricable
from a highly complex pattern. To divest them
of all the blends and alloys that have gone into
them as they have been shaped by the history of
peoples, their instruments, and their wanderings
is to simplify the picture and introduce notions
of frontiers jealously defined and defended.
How important are cross-cultural encounters
for composers? Often when the change in their
work is closely scrutinized, all it boils down to
is the discovery of a particular scoreand the
study of that score, for without study the initial
impression would leave only a passing wave of
enthusiasm and not stimulate any real creative
power. The role that Asian theatre played in
Debussy's creative development could in this
respect be compared to works closer to his own
tradition that also inspired him, such as Mus¬
sorgsky's opera Boris Godunov, or even the
writings of the French poet Pierre Louys.
The work of Oliver Messiaen raises the same
question. Peruvian folklore plays a part in
Harawi, and deci-talasrhythms borrowed from
Indian musicwere of crucial importance in his
work on intervals; but the influence of India, like
that of Japanese court music on his Sept hai-kai,
was eventually melded into a language that was 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
the composer's own, taking its place along with
such other influences as plainsong, bird-calls and
the Christian faith.
Recognizing oneself in others
For several contemporary composers, however,
contact with non-European music has had a more
profound effect, taking them on something other
than a mere armchair voyage, to the land of their
inspiration. Some have visited the country that
caught their attention, or even studied under one
of its master-musicians.
Look at the work of these musicians more
closely, however, and you will find that the
payoff, however much it may have deepened the
first shock of discovery, invariably only went to
confirm the initial effect. Take Steve Reich's fas¬
cination with Ghanaian drumming, for example.
In fact he only spent three weeks in Ghana
studying it. What he learned served to confirm
and develop tendencies that were already
apparent in his work, notably in his researches
into the superimposing and separating of musical
units and the signals needed to break a pattern
in moving on to the next phase of a composition.
Reich's experience calls to mind that of Jean-
Claude Eloy with regard to Japan. Eloy disco¬
vered oriental traditions at a point in his life as
a composer when, as with Reich, something new
was emerging in his work, encouraging him to
break with the academic traditions which had
shaped him but which were perhaps starting to
seem constrictive. In Japanese music he found an
image of his own musical aspirations.
An encounter of this type is not so much a
matter of imitating or intermingling styles as a
way of recognizing elements of oneself in
someone else. And that process need not involve
exotic cultures. For Bartok, for Kodaly, for all
those composers, particularly in Scandinavia,
whose work was initially shaped more by aca¬
demic tradition than by the sounds around them,
the route to self-discovery lay not in the Far East
or Africa but at home.
Ransacking the shelves
of history
For many composers, though, distance is synony¬
mous with freedom, particularly in matters of
rhythm, pitch or tonality. Such has certainly been
the case for the Japanese composer Takemitsu,
who first fell in love with Western music, then
VERONIQUE BRINDEAU
is a French musicologist.
Formerly in charge of the
Contemporary Music
Documentation Centre in
Tokyo, she is currently working
with Espaces Nouveaux, an
acoustics research centre in
Paris. She is a regular
contributor to a number of
specialist periodicals.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Left, Djamchid Chemirani of
Iran plays the zarb, a goblet-
shaped drum, with the
American musician David
Hykes (1990).
Below, a selection of compact
discs produced by Unesco.
returned to study his own musical tradition, and
whose work now flows freely from both these
sources of inspiration.
Such examples raise the question of whether
there is a difference in kind between seeking inspi¬
ration from foreign cultures and from history
the repository to which composers traditionally,
and peacefully, apply. In effect, all sources,
whether near or far, are grist to the composer's
mill. Half-cuckoo and half-bee, he takes up his
lodging where he will and turns whatever
nourishment he finds there into musical honey.
As a consequence, any reference a Western com¬
poser makes to an Asian or an African theme,
no matter how respectful or closely-studied it
may be, may have relatively little significance as
compared with the influences that same artist has
picked up, consciously or not, from his
predecessors. For is there really any difference in
the mechanism by which, say, listening to
Mongol songs would influence a musician's
development as compared with studying the way
in which one of his own precursors treated the
melodic unit?
Music of other times
and other places
Thus a sense of affinity may draw a composer
to study, often in a detailed way, either the music
of distant lands or the past traditions of his own
country. Both Mauricio Kagel and François-
Bernard Mâche, in their very different ways, take
into aesthetic account the tonality of the instru¬
ments of the Middle Ages as well as of non-
European cultures and of rare languages.
John Cage chooses opera as the starting-point
for a playful process of superimposition and of
assemblage in his unique work Européra (1990),
which includes references to more than a hundred
operas from the repertoire. Stockhausen made use
of hymns from all over the world in his 1967
work, Hymnen.
These cultural intermixtures also lead even¬
tually to a fusion of genres, a breaking down of
barriers between different categories of music.
When Pierre Boulez conducts a work by Frank
Zappa, or when Michel Portal alternates between
playing jazz and Mozart (or when he improvises
with traditional musicians, as in a recent Lille
Festival performance appropriately entitled Métis¬
sages or "cross-fertilizations"), the contours
separating contemporary music from jazz and
rock disappear.
This process seems to be largely in the hands
of musicians who practise improvisation. There
was a time when groups like Can and the Sun
Râ Orchestra recruited would-be Stockhausens;
but now for the most part composers of "serious"
contemporary music choose to remain strictly
within the boundaries of their own musical tra¬
ditions. The dismantling of barriers is mainly left
to the exponents of so-called "crossover" music,
whose very name indicates the route they intend
to take.
It is not certain that the music of distant lands
holds an attraction for composers today. The
wealth of recordings now available means that it
is as easy to listen to Eskimo songs or Tibetan
horns as to baroque opera, without the need to
seek the help of native teachers or of musicol¬
ogists.
The scarcity factor has gone. Now horizons
are closer, and material is freely available. Artists
are confronted by an immense Tower of Babel.
It is up to them to open, at a rate of their own
choosing, whichever window on the world's
music takes their fancy. Now, in fact, the most
important thing might well be to forget much of
what they hear, the better to achieve the crucial
metamorphosisthe one that transforms that
first, blinding encounter with other music into
their own, individual work.
uss,ASS?P*
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From guitar to qanun
when I was in my teens I
began to learn the classical
guitar, which pianists and
violinists tend to regard as a
somewhat marginal instrument
because its intimate sound is
more suited to solo performances
than orchestral work. Its
repertoire is extraordinarily
eclectic, but the dominance of
Hispanic folk music made me
familiar with particularly
effective kinds of musical
intermixture very early in my
career.
During a long stay in the
Caribbean I studied jazz
harmonies and Brazilian and
Afro-Cuban rhythms. This
liberated me from the rigid
written repertoire of my classical
training and allowed me to
improvise within a framework of
harmonic rules which though
complex were much less
restrictive. I felt that I was
getting rid of the heavy chains
that bound me to repetitive
exercises which were alien to the
essence of music and left no
room for either emotion or
imagination.
I already thought that living
forms of music, both popular
and classical, had an
incomparable vitality and
expressive force. I became
interested in other types of
improvisation, and as I
progressed I composed a number
of contemplative works laced
with Ravelian dissonances and
Afro-Cuban, Brazilian and Indian
rhythms.
I soon learned that the
spontaneous creation of a
rhythmic and melodic idiom was
not exclusive to jazz but was the
basis of traditions such as that of
classical Arab-Islamic music,
which does not suffer from its
lack of a harmonic structure but
celebrates the divine unity of a
spare and graceful monody, pure
34 and penetrating, full of hidden
The unusual career of
Julien Jalal Eddin Weiss
meaning, which the prolixity of
harmony would disguise and
deaden.
I discovered this Arab music
by chance, while listening to a
recording by Munir Bachir, one
of the great masters of the
qanun. I had already come across
the taqsim, an Arab-Turkish
form of improvisation, but the
qanun was a revelation.
For the next six years, I
worked on both the guitar and
the qanun. Then, in 1984, the
Tunisian singer Hedi Guella
invited me to play in the first
part of his show at the Carthage
festival, in front of 7,000 people.
The public were indifferent to
my performance with the guitar,
but they greeted my qanun
playing with enthusiasm. From
that moment on, I knew that I
would dedicate myself to the
qanun.
Ever since then my work has
had something in common with
that of a musicologist. Apart
from the daily ritual of practice,
I have studied at length the
history of Islamic music and
civilization, concentrating
primarily on the work of the
great Orientalists. I have
rediscovered many vocal and
instrumental pieces, both
structured and improvised,
which were useful for
comparative study, but also as
the basis of arrangements for the
Al Kindi ensemble which I was
then setting up, and as additions
to my repertoire as a soloist.
I explored different classical
traditions: the Syrian mwwashah,
the Egyptian dawr, the Iraqi
maqam, the Persian
tshaharmezrab, the Turkish
bashraf. Each of these opened up
a new dimension for me: the
lack of orchestral ornamentation
and the virtuosity of Persian
music; the Bedouin ruggedness
and majesty of Iraqi music; the
melodramatic cadences of
Egyptian music; the mystical
depth and surgical precision of
Turkish music; and the multiple
facets of the Andalusian music of
North Africa.
My compositions are
impregnated with all these
diverse musical forms. The
Western influence is also present,
although in small doses these
days. One of the blends I like
best can be heard in Wash
Bagdadi, a piece for the qanun in
which I introduced Persian
musical effects into Iraqi
rhythms and added hints of
Kurdish phrasing and the Somali
pentatonic scale.
I have however composed one
polyphonic work, inspired by
the sober romanticism of Erik
Satie, and on occasion I have
enjoyed playing in iconoclastic
mixed sessions. I have played the
qanun with the Paris Symphony
Orchestra and the chorus of
Radio France on film
soundtracks, with Arab-French
rock singers, and in a
performance of the medieval
music of Guillaume de Machaut
and Adam de la Halle.
But the most extraordinary
experience I have ever had was
when I performed a work by the
contemporary composer Francis
Bayer with an ensemble made up
exclusively of traditional
instrumentsthe Tibetan
trumpet, the Turkish ney, the
shenay of Benares, the Japanese
koto, the Indian sitar, the
Balinese gamelan, the rain rod of
the Australian Aborigines, the
gong of the opera of Beijing, the
Iranian zarb, and the Indian
tabla. For someone like me, who
seeks musical marriages of all
kinds, this was something quite
unique.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
'#
SS****
*,,*
Soné of India
by Romain Maitra
From Messiaen
to the Beatles,
the vogue
for Indian music
in the West
Above, the Indian ensemble
Shakti, which was formed by
British musician John
McLaughlin.
ROMAIN MAITRA
Is an Indian journalist, writer
and cultural anthropologist.
He is currently working at the
Maison des Sciences de
l'Homme, Paris, on a study of
the ¡mage of the Indian world
presented by French
film-makers.
IN any cross-cultural transfer, complete idea-
systems never travel easily. Only fragments tend
to be transmitted. In the case of the influence of
Indian classical music on the music of the West,
technical elements such as raga (colour or mood),
scales and timbre have sometimes been adopted
by Western composers and integrated into their
individual styles and conceptions.
Aleksandr Scriabin and Gustav Holst were
among the European composers who have been
influenced by Indian culture and music. Both
were interested in theosophy, a nineteenth-
century synthetic religion that brought Indolo-
gists, philosophers, quacks and generous society
ladies together beneath the all-embracing canopy
of Hinduism. Scriabin's ideas about emotion and
colour perhaps owe something to the concept of
raga, and Hoist incorporated some of the hymns
of the Rig Veda in his Planets. The French com¬
poser Olivier Messiaen admired the melodic con¬
tours and ornamentations of Indian music, and
developed a rhythmic theory which seems to be
inspired by Indian tala or pattern of beats. In his
piece Oiseaux exotiques, the percussive passages
execute tala as a counterpoint to the music of
string and wind instruments.
The modern American composers Henry
Cowell and Alan Hovhaness used elements of
Indian music in their Madras Symphony and
Madras Sonata respectively. Lou Harrison and
John Cage also had deep and perceptive Indian
musical connections. In his Construction in Metal
Cage was inspired by shrutis or microtonalities,
and in his Sonatas and Interludes for piano he
attempted to express in music the sthai bhavas,
the abiding states of emotion which help conjure
up the aesthetic response of rasa or flavour.
More recently, La Monte Young and Terry
Riley have had a strong connection with India
through their guru Pandit Pran Nath, who taught
them Hindustani vocal music. In his The Well-
Timed Piano, Young used raga scales moving
in and out of the texture against the continuous
drone of the piano. It is also possible to detect
in the works of Philip Glass and Steve Reich
the hidden fibres of oriental inspiration. John
Barham is a Western composer who has used
the piano as if it were a santur, or Persian
dulcimer.
Indian music and
Western jazz and pop
A notable surge of interest in Indian classical
music began in the West and especially in the
United States in the 1950s, at a time when
American society was waking from the conser¬
vatism of the post-war era. The atmosphere of
experimentation and change was symbolized by
concern for Civil Rights, by the creation of the
Peace Corps, and by the growth of a number of
protest movements. With the spread of the 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
.
Beatles Paul McCartney and George Harrison
during a trip to India in 1968.
The Indian sitarist and composer
Ravi Shankar (left)
with the American composer Philip Glass.
36
alternative culture of the young and its penchant
for holy gurus and the magical, mythical image
of India and its religion, Indian music became an
important part of the new scene.
By the 1960s, Indian music was attracting
large audiences in London, Paris, New York,
Chicago, Los Angeles and other big European
and American cities. It seemed fresh and exciting,
with deep spiritual qualities and tranquillity.
Many jazz-lovers thought that it resembled jazz
because of its potential for improvisation, the
scope it offered for the artist and the resources
of the Indian scalar or modal system.
Its great popularity was due to individuals
such as Ravi Shankar, Ali Akbar Khan, Yehudi
Menuhin and George Harrison, rather than to
groups or movements. Ravi Shankar played a par¬
ticularly important role. In order to make Indian
music more accessible to Western audiences, he
departed from Hindustani tradition by starting
his concerts with a short piece which was fol¬
lowed by increasingly longer items. As he said
in the introduction to his recording of Concerto
for Sitar and Orchestra: "the listener will not find
much harmony, counterpoint or sound patterns
he is used to, and which form the basis of Western
classical music. I have consciously avoided these,
only using them minimally, because they arc
elements which, if emphasized, can spoil or even
destroy the raga-bhava (the mood and spirit of
the raga)."
George Harrison successfully endorsed this
effort to introduce unfamiliar Indian music to
audiences used to Western pop by removing some
of the difficulties. The exotic tone of the sitar can
be heard in the song "Norwegian Wood" on the
Beatles' album Rubber Soul (1965) and in "Within
You Without You" on Revolver (1966).
Another approach to Indian music was
adopted by the jazz trumpeter Don Cherry in his
piece Humus, which is based on a series of simple
themes, sounds, rhythms and two ragas, although
the trumpet is not exactly an ideal instrument for
producing the characteristic microtonal glides of
Indian music.
Meanwhile, in India the violin and clarinet
have long been conspicuous in classical, semi-
classical and even some folk music. Although
Western classical music has not made any notice¬
able impact on Indian music, pop and rock have
had a strong influence on film music, most of
which lacks any authentic identity or organic link
with the classical mode.
Although Indian music has assimilated many
influences in the past, the mixing process has been
gradual, an attempt to find the new without
losing the essential characteristics of the old.
However, the last two decades have been a heady
time for successful Indian performers, who have
earned big money and popularity abroad. Wel¬
come though it is that Indian music has borne
such a variety of fruits in the West, great care
must be taken to maintain an environment in
which it can flourish at home.
The Caribbean group
Kassav'
in concert,
Paris, 1986.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
w-~-
Exciting new sounds
and rhythms from
the Third World
are bursting onto
the Western pop scene
by Alain Gardinier
'World Music'
or sounds of the tunes
HE international success of musicians such as
Kassav', Ofra Haza, The Sabri Brothers, Mory
Kante, Johnny Clegg and The Gipsy Kings, who
hail from the Caribbean, Israel, Pakistan, South
Africa and France respectively, has turned them
into representatives of a new musical trend of
major importance, an audio revolution which has
been variously described as "World Music",
"sono mondiale" or "musique métisse".
In the developed countries, the standardiza¬
tion of sounds and musical trends and the extreme
harmonic simplification resulting from the fierce
competition to make hit records, has jaded the
public, which has turned to new kinds of music
as a source of unusual and original sensations. At
the same time, the spread of long-distance travel,
the attraction of new technology and the need
of artists everywhere to widen their horizons,
have paved the way for new musical textures.
Today, World Music knows no frontiers.
Some Third World performers have made records
that have achieved international success. "Yeke
Yeke", a song adapted by Mory Kante from the
traditional music of the Malinke people of West 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Africa, became a worldwide hit. The Senegalese
singer Youssou N'Dour joined international stars
Sting and Bruce Springsteen on a world tour in
support of Amnesty International.
There is nothing new about solo performers
and groups from Asia, Africa and Latin America
who win a reputation in the West. What is new
is the musical and technical collaboration which
has developed between them and Western per¬
formers and has enabled them to enrich their art
and to take advantage of modern recording and
production techniques. Naturally, what they
want most of all is access to distribution networks
which can bring their work to a wide public,
unlike traditional music labels which only reach
a limited audience.
This is not just a one-way exchange. Rock
groups have been taking an interest in traditional
forms of music ever since the 1960s, when the
Beatles visited India and became so enthusiastic
about Indian music that they tried to popularize
it in the West, incidentally bringing fame to the
sitarist Ravi Shankar. The Rolling Stones in their
turn helped to make known Moroccan musicians.
Around this time many other Western artists reis¬
sued adaptations of hits from other parts of the
world, notably Latin America.
The scope of the movement is wider today,
and is in many cases associated with a real desire
to learn from other cultures. Playing alongside
African, Indian and Latin American musicians,
artists such as Paul Simon and Peter Gabriel have
created a new dynamic. The success of Paul
Simon's Graceland album, based on traditional
South African rhythms, has helped a number
of South African artists to break into the inter¬
national market.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
It remains true that many more artists from
disadvantaged countries are flocking to the West
than vice versa, usually to their former colonial
metropolis. Indians tend to head for London,
French-speaking Africans for Paris. At the
moment this trend shows no signs of changing,
but perhaps the new movement towards World
Music will also encourage exchanges between
Asia and Latin America, and between Africa and
the Caribbean.
Specialized record labels
The decisive factor will probably be the big
record companies, which are making positive
moves in this direction. Multinational companies
have set up subsidiaries specializing in World
Music to stimulate encounters between musicians.
The hi-tech studios of Real World Records, for
example, founded by Peter Gabriel in Bath (UK),
produce a wide range of artists including The
Musicians of the Nile, Tabu Ley from Zaire,
Nusrat Fateh Ali Khan from Pakistan, The Guo
Brothers from China and Elio Revé from Cuba.
These musicians are also supported by WOMAD
(World of Music, Arts and Dance), an organiza¬
tion founded by Peter Gabriel in 1980 to promote
the arts of many different cultures through Euro¬
pean concert tours, since live shows play a deci¬
sive role in an artist's career.
In order to reach the widest possible
audience, is World Music being forced to "wester¬
nize" itself by the use of more modern instru¬
ments, rhythms or sounds? The answer is yes,
Opposite page: the South
African singer Johnny Clegg
(centre) and his group Savuka
at Angoulême (France) in
1987.
Above left: Cheb Khaled (left)
and The Gipsy Kings at the
"Gypsy Mosaic" festival held
at Nîmes (France) In 1990.
Above: the Ugandan singer
Geoffrey Oryema.
ALAIN GARDINIER
is a French journalist with a
special interest in World Music.
He contributes to a number of
music magazines and
television programmes.
judging from the great success of "mixed" forms
of music which have a foot in both the traditional
and the modern camps. But the answer is no
insofar as the listening public is becoming increas¬
ingly familiar with strikingly different sounds.
"The main thing is to offer artists the technology
they need for top-quality recording, without tam¬
pering with their art, unless they themselves
initiate an exchange," emphasizes Peter Gabriel.
In any case World Music is not always a
direct product of the Third World. Some Western
artists are also successful exponents of it. The
Israeli singer Ofra Haza had a hit with a tradi¬
tional Yemeni song. In France Caribbean groups
such as Kassav', and a Gypsy group from the
South of France, The Gipsy Kings, are increas¬
ingly popular. The Négresses Vertes, a French
group of second-generation immigrants, recently
provided the music for the American film Dick
Tracy.
A surprising success
For the record industry, which sees World Music
as a minor phenomenon although one with a
promising future, these breakthroughs seem
difficult to analyse. Why, for example, should the
South African singer Johnny Clegg and his mixed
band Savuka be so successful in Germany and
France, while he is virtually unknown in the rest
of the world? And since Clegg's music contains
an anti-apartheid message, should we conclude
that World Music is necessarily committed music?
By assimilating disparate rhythms might it not
lose its identity and become commonplace? Might
too many concessions not compromise its fresh¬
ness and innovative spirit?
For the moment, the communications society
in which we live seems bound to encourage the
development of World Music, and the confron¬
tation of cultures which it promotes must surely
help to discredit racism and intolerance. It
remains to be seen what support for World Music
will come from governments, the media, cultural
associations, concert promoters, radio and tele¬
vision programme planners, and multinational
record companies. Will World Music be the
sound of the twenty-first century? 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
ECENT RECORDS
listening
JAZZ
Shirley Horn.
You Won't Forget Me.
Horn (piano, vocals). Special guests:
Miles Davis, Buck Hill, Branford
Marsalis, Wynton Marsalis, Toots
Thielemans.
CD Verve Digital 847 482-4.
A superb selection of romantic
ballads interpreted by one of the
great jazz pianists and singers,
Shirley Horn, who was discovered
years ago by Miles Davis but is still
little-known outside the United
States. Here she accompanies
herself on piano with a consummate
sense of harmony, supported by
some brilliant jazzmen. One
remarkable feature, in view of the
rivalry between the two trumpeters,
is the presence of Miles Davis and
Wynton Marsalis.
Charlie Haden/Carlos Paredes.
Dialogues.
Haden (bass), Paredes (Portuguese
guitar).
CD Polydor 843 445-2.
On a recording which is hard to
categorize, American bassist Charlie
Haden, who is known for his
association with a number of avant-
garde jazz musicians such as
Omette Coleman, dialogues with
Portuguese guitarist Carlos Paredes,
who plays an instrument resembling
the 'ud or Arab lyre. What they
create is not so much jazz as a kind
of subtle and original chamber
music, with melodies evoking the
court music of the Golden Age of
the Iberian peninsula.
Jan Garbarek.
I Took Up the Runes.
Garbarek (soprano, tenor sax.),
Rainer Brüninghaus (piano), Eberhard
Weber (bass), Nana Vasconcelos
(percussion), Manu Katché (drums),
Bugge Wesseltoft (synthesizer), Ingor
Antte Ailu Qaup (vocal).
CD ECM 1419 843850-2.
In Europe all kinds of musical
influences are often found under the
jazz label. The Norwegian
saxophonist Jan Garbarek took to
jazz in the early 1960s when he
heard Coltrane's Giant Steps. But his
work has an entirely personal touch,
rooted In Scandinavian folklore,
despite the presence of the Brazilian
Vasconcelos and the West Indian
Katché. Atmosphere, not swing, Is
the keynote of this charming record
whose somewhat melancholy poetry
brings to mind Nordic landscapes.
Robert Cray.
Midnight Stroll.
Cray (vocal, guitar), Richard Cousins
(bass), Jimmy Pugh (keyboards),
Kevin Hayes (drums, percussion),
Ti Haihatsu (guitar), Wayne Jackson
(trumpet, trombone), Andrew Lowe
(tenor sax.)
CD Mercury 846652-2.
m I» Robert Cray, whose resonant voice
1U is rather like that of Otis Redding,
sings a modem blues mixed with
soul and funk. Yet the recurrent
themes in his compositions are
those of traditional blues: solitude,
unfaithful women, unrequited love.
The arrangements are pleasant,
flowing and well orchestrated. A fine
album from one of the most
promising young musicians in the
United States.
FOLKLORE
Gabon: Musique des Pygmés
Bibayak, Chantres de l'épopée
("Gabon: Music of the Bibayak
Pygmies, Epic Bards").
CD Ocora C 559 053.
With the griots of West Africa, the
Pygmies are certainly the most
extraordinary singers of the African
continent. This recording, dedicated
to the musicologist Pierre Sallée,
who spent many years studying the
music of Central Africa, enables us
to fully appreciate their polyphonic
talent and keen sense of rhythm.
Full accompanying notes give
detailed information on the context
in which this music is performed.
Laos: Lam Saravane, musique pour
le khène ("Laos: Lam Saravane,
Music for the Khen").
CD Ocora C 559 058.
Much less widely-known than other
forms of Asian music such as that of
China, Japan, India and Bali, Laotian
music has astonishing vitality. The
lam, an improvised alternating song,
is performed at community events in
Laosfamily gatherings, festivals,
religious ceremonies. Other tracks
feature the khen (a wind instrument
of reed pipes on a wooden support),
the flute and a small drum.
Grèce. Les grandes époques du
chant sacré byzantin, XIV'-XVIII« s.
("Greece. The Great Epochs of
Sacred Byzantine Chant,
14th-18th c").
CD Ocora C 559 075.
The Greek singer and musicologist
Theodore Vassilikos has compared
the original scores of these
Byzantine chants with their
transcriptions into the simplified
notation developed by Archbishop
Chrysanthos in 1818, and located
alterations and omissions. In this
collection his ensemble interprets
the most significant works in this
liturgical tradition. Of particular
interest is "From on high the
Prophets announced His coming",
written by the famous 14th-century
composer and chanter loannis
Koukouzelis. The polyphony
progressively unfolds to a sublime
climax like some shimmering Eastern
fabric.
POPULAR MUSIC
Intelligent Hoodlum.
CD A& M 395 311-2.
Rap music, which originated in the
1980s in the Bronx and other Black
and Latin American districts of New
York, is now known all over the
world. The title of this disc
encapsulates the biting irony of this
poetry of the streets. Powerful lyrics
and a driving rhythm defiantly evoke
racial and political tensions in
America. The militancy of such
tracks as "Arrest the President",
"No Justice, No Peace" and "Black
and Proud" hark back to late 1960s'
Afro-American music and poetry, the
Black Panthers and the Black
Muslims.
Zucchero Sugar Fornaciari.
Oro Incensó & Birra.
CD Polydor 841 125-2.
One of the most successful
examples of Italian pop music today,
an inventive cocktail of rock, funk,
rap and disco, more angular and
harsh than Afro-American funk and
rap but full of humour. Among the
American, British, African and Italian
musicians in the line-up is the Rufus
Thomas of "Funky Chicken" fame in
the 1970s.
CLASSICAL
Johannes Brahms.
Paganini-Variationen op. 35;
3 Intermezzi op. 117;
6 Klavierstücke op. 118
("Paganini Variations, Intermezzi,
Piano Pieces").
Lilya Zilberstein.
CD Deutsche Grammophon
431 123-2.
Brahms is magnificently
interpreted on this recording by the
clear and vibrant playing of the
young Russian pianist Lilya
Zilberstein. The set of 28 variations
on Paganlni's famous theme, op. 35,
was composed for the pianist Carl
Tausig, then aged 21 and a friend of
Liszt and Wagner.
Krzysztof Penderecki.
Polnisches Requiem
("Polish Requiem").
Ingrid Haubold (soprano), Grazyna
Winogrodska (mezzosoprano), Zachos
Terzakis (tenor), Malcolm Smith
(bass), NDR-Chor & Chor des
Bayerischen Runfunks,
NDR-Sinfonieorchester.
2 CDs. Deutsche Grammophon
429 720-2.
A magnificent recording of a
concert given with the North German
Radio Symphony Orchestra,
Hamburg. Composed between 1980
and 1984, This Requiem for four
soloists, two mixed choirs and
orchestra, draws its Inspiration from
both political and religious sources.
The "Lacrimosa" was written to
celebrate the unveiling of the
Solidarity monument at Gdansk, and
the "Agnus Dei" for the funeral of
Cardinal Wyszynski in 1981. The
sombre and majestic music, shot
through with flashes of brilliance,
reveals an admirable mastery of the
polyphonic idiom.
Isabelle Leymarie H
ethnomusicologist and journalist
Ernest Ansermet dirige
Frank Martin
("Ernest Ansermet conducts
Frank Martin").
Orchestra de la Suisse romande,
D. Fischer-Dieskau, P. Fournier.
CD Cascavelle VEL.2001.
The centenary of the birth of
Frank Martinsurely, with Arthur
Honegger, the greatest Swiss
composer of the 20th century-
was not celebrated widely
enough in 1990. The importance
he attached to literary
texts in his vocal works
(as in his version of Shakespeare's
Tempest), his dynamic sense of
rhythm (as in his famous Little
Sinfonía Concertante, which can be
heard conducted by its composer on
CD Jecklin JD 645-2), and the
sustained attention he pays to the
instruments, notably In his concertos
and ballads, are just a few reasons
why, almost 20 years after his
death, Frank Martin deserves to be
rediscovered.
Kurt Weill.
Die Dreigroschenoper
("The Threepenny Opera"),
Songs from Berlin 1930.
Lotte Lenya, Marlene Dietrich.
CD Teldec 9031-72025-2.
Kurt Weill, who with Bertolt Brecht
and a few others symbolizes the
Weimar years in Germany and the
turbulent artistic landscape of Berlin,
settled in the United States in 1935.
His American work is little known,
but his earlier music has remained
popular since 1945, largely because
of the talent of his wife and
favourite interpreter, Lotte Lenya.
All Weill fans will be delighted
that Teldec has reissued a selection
of songs from The Threepenny
Opera, recorded in 1930
by the cast of the first production,
as well as songs from the films
based on The Threepenny Opera
and from Mahagonny, plus two
extraordinary numbers by Marlene
Dietrich.
Pierre Boulez.
Le visage nuptial/Le soleil des
eaux/Figures, doubles, prismes.
Phyllis Bryn-Julson, Elizabeth
Laurence, BBC Singers & Symphony
Orchestra conducted by Pierre
Boulez.
CD Erato 2292-45492-2.
The latest Boulez release, the
umpteenth arrangement
of the vocal pieces "Le visage
nuptial" and "Le soleil des eaux" is
characterized by a sumptuous and
violent lyricism. The sound is equally
magical in the third piece, for
orchestra alone.
George Frideric Handel.
Alcina.
Joan Sutherland, Fritz Wunderlich,
conducted by Ferdinand Leitner.
2 CDs. Rodolphe RPC 3256364.
Handel had many ups and downs
during his long association with the
London theatre, and in 1735, when
he staged the opera Alcina (with a
libretto after the Italian Renaissance
poem Orlando Furioso), he was
looking for a popular success to
solve his financial problems. The
enchantress Alcina (Sutherland) falls
in love with Ruggiero (Wunderlich),
whom she takes into her power.
Happily, Bradamante (Norma Proctor)
hurries to the rescue of her fiancé.
The performance, recorded live in
May 1959, is a fine memento of
these celebrated voices in their
prime.
Claude dayman M
journalist and music critic
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
The Andalusian past
The largest Islamic necropolis
ever found in Europe has been
discovered at Granada, Spain,
by archaeologists working on
the site of an underground
carpark and on disused land
next to the 16th-century Royal
Hospital. Vestiges of some
2,000 burials, several hundred
tombs, two funerary
monuments, and a number of
ritual objects and pottery will
throw new light on Andalusian
history and on aspects of daily
life in Moorish Spain between
the 8th and the 12th
centuries.
Exploring the Universe
together...
The American National
Aeronautics and Space
Administration (NASA), the
European Space Agency, the
Soviet Space Research
Institute, and the Japanese
Institute of Science and
Astronautics are
co-ordinating a programme
of solar and terrestrial
studies which includes the
launching of several space
probes after 1992.
"We share the same planet,
the same solar system and
the same Universe: let's
explore them together," says
David Southwood, a British
member of the European
Space Agency's scientific
committee.
Inspiration for Guernica
Recent studies suggest that
Picasso's celebrated
painting Guernica may have
been inspired by a
15th-century fresco entitled
The Triumph of Death, which
depicts the figure of death on
horseback mowing down the
rich and powerful. The fresco,
at Palermo in Sicily, has
recently been restored. The
artist who painted it has not
yet been identified.
Fibre optics span the globe
In 1995, a trans-Siberian fibre
optics link will come into
service between Western
Europe and the Far East,
completing a worldwide
communications network.
Fibre-optics technology can
instantaneously transmit the
human voice, numerical
data and images. A link
between the United States
and Europe has been open
since 1988, and the United
States and Japan were
connected by a trans-Pacific
cable in 1989.
Spanish emigration
to the Americas
Twenty Spanish scholars from
universities in Europe and the
Americas are writing a history
of Spanish emigration to the
Americas. Although the study
is primarily concerned with
migratory movements from
Spain, it also covers other
European countries. It
analyses the consequences of
the transfer of manpower,
both for the receiving
countries and for the
countries of origin.
The 20 volumes of this
monumental work are
scheduled for publication in
1992, in time for the 500th
anniversary of the encounter
between the Old and New
Worlds.
Energy at sea
A number of windmills are to
be installed on platforms at
sea, 2 to 3 km from the
Danish island of Lolland. They
are expected to supply 60%
to 70% more energy than
windmills on land. Denmark
hopes that 10% of its
electricity will be supplied by
wind-power by the end of the
century.
A first for giant telescope
Astronomers building the
world's largest telescope, the
Keck telescope in Hawaii, have
taken the first photographs of
a spiral galaxy which
resembles the Milky Way, 65
million light-years from the
Earth. The telescope has a
10-m-diameter mirror
consisting of 36 hexagonal
sections, not a single piece of
glass. The position of the
sections can be adjusted by
computer to correct
distortions of the image.
Antwerp,
city of culture
The Cultural Capital
of Europe 1993 will be
Antwerp, Belgium. The city,
one of the most prosperous
river ports in Europe in the
16th century, was a major
centre of Flemish painting.
Although plans to transform
Antwerp have been mooted
since the Second World
War, work has only recently
begun on the rehabilitation
of the old quays to create a
residential area and a vast
cultural centre.
Sculpture by computer
A British company has
developed a computer-
controlled system which can
produce sculptures.
It consists of a laser camera
which records the thousands
of co-ordinates of a
3-dimensional object, animate
or inanimate, in a few
seconds, and a milling
machine which reproduces
the model according to this
data. Possible applications
include restoration
work and the production of
replicas of archaeological
finds. The technique may also
prove useful in plastic surgery
and orthopaedics.
Common past,
common future
An international symposium on
Arab-Spanish culture in
history, held recently in
Damascus (Syrian Arab
Republic), was attended by
eminent specialists from the
Arab countries and from
European countries, including
France, Germany, Portugal,
the Soviet Union and Spain.
On the agenda was the way to
a better understanding
between Arab countries and
the West through the study of
the special relationship
between the Arab world and
Spain.
New MAB biosphere
reserves
The creation of eight new
biosphere reserves was
approved by UNESCO's Man
and the Biosphere (MAB)
International Co-ordinating
Council in November 1990:
the coastal zone of
El-Kala (Algeria); the
Berchtesgaden Alps, the
Waddensea of Schleswig-
Holstein, and the moors of
Schorfheide-Chorin (Germany);
the mountain forests of
Shennongjia (China); Mont
Ventoux (France); the Maya
national parks (Guatemala);
and the Great Gobi desert
(Mongolia).
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
w o r l d h e r i t a g e
Ouro Prêto, city of black gold
by Augusto C. da Silva Telles
42
I he problems of reconciling the
traditional and the modern are raised
in particularly acute form at Ouro
Prêto, a historic city in Brazil's Minas
Gerais state which is today sur¬
rounded by an industrial zone and
lies on an important highway.
Ouro Prêto (Portuguese for "Black
Gold") grew out of a mining settle¬
ment which developed on the lower
slope of the Serra do Ouro Prêto in
the early eighteenth century when
miners flocked Into the region to
prospect for gold in the rivers and on
the mountain slopes. In 1711 it was
given the status of a city and the
name of Vila Rica. It is said that many
houses used the entrances to mine
shafts as their cellars.
In this rugged setting, narrow
crooked streets and alleys were built
along the mountain spur without any
overall plan. The central square,
today known as the Praça Tiradentes
after a hero of Brazil's independence
struggle, was not built until the mid-
eighteenth century. Around it stand
the old colonial governor's palace,
the town hall and the colonial
penitentiary.
The houses, of varying height, are
strung haphazardly along steep,
winding streets. Their picturesque
beauty charms visitors and leads
them from one surprise to another.
The diversity of the site and the out¬
standing views are accentuated by
the outlines of churches and chapels
silhouetted high on the slopes or
blending into the townscape. The
French specialist Michel Parent has
described how "This straggling
urban fabric reveals itself gradually
to the eye, which slowly comes to
dominate it, bringing together near
and far, narrow streets set deep in
the valley, a bell-tower atop a distant
hill.... It does not have the obvious
advantage of a magnificent site, its
beauty is at first hinted at, then
becomes elusive, before finally
yielding itself to the visitor."*
The mid-eighteenth century was
the period of Ouro Prêto's greatest
splendour, thanks to the abundance
of gold which brought it wealth. The
houses dating from that period were
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
aärtll
J ^J
built In dressed stone. Decorated
with a profusion of friezes and scroll¬
work, their architecture is more
elaborate than the others. Many of
these buildings are in Conde-
Bobadela street and on the Praça
Tiradentes, where the Casa dos
Contos, the governor's palace, and
the town hall are notable for the
elegance and force of their late
baroque style.
The religious architecture of Ouro
Prêto is also remarkable for its origi¬
nality, diversity and quality. Some of
the buildings are among the most
beautiful examples of baroque art
not only in Brazil but in the world.
On either side of the spur of rock
topped by the Praça Tiradentes are
the Carmelite church of Our Lady and
the church of St. Francis of Assisi.
The architect and sculptor of these
two churches was Antonio Francisco
Lisboa, better known as "0
Aleijadinho" ("the little cripple"). The
church of St. Francis, which dates
from 1764, was Aleijadinho's first
project and his masterwork. It is
remarkable for an ingenious combi¬
nation of curves and ellipses, as well
as the composition, of an astonishing
expressive force, of the frontispiece
carved in "pedra-sabâo" (a kind of
alabaster).
Problems of growth
Ouro Prêto was the seat of the mili¬
tary government and then the cap¬
ital of Minas Gerais until the state
administration was transferred to the
new city of Belo Horizonte in 1897.
As a result of this change in status
and the exhaustion of its gold
deposits, the city went into decline.
If Ouro Prêto today still has a certain
vitality, it is because of its position
as a university city. When it was clas¬
sified as a historic monument in
1938, it was living in the past. The
city had virtually ceased to grow, and
conservation activity was limited to
religious and civic buildings.
In the 1950s, an aluminium plant
was built at nearby Saramenha, and
the highway between Saramenha
and Bela Horizonte was metalled.
Population growth and economic
activity suddenly picked up again.
Road traffic also sharply increased,
largely because of the heavy trucks
serving the Saramenha complex.
Opposite page:
general view of Ouro Prêto,
former capital of Minas Gerais
state, Brazil.
Above: one of the steep and
winding streets that lend charm
to the old city.
Left: detail of the church
of St. Francis of Asslsl (1764),
a baroque masterpiece by the architect
and sculptor 0 Aleijadinho.
This development threatened one of
the finest jewels of Brazil's historical
and artistic heritage, and the institu¬
tion responsible for its safeguard
asked UNESCO to provide technical
support for Ouro Prêto.
In 1966 international specialists
carried out studies with a view to
defining possible zones of develop¬
ment, reducing demographic growth
and preserving the old city. Their
proposals were taken up and worked
out in greater detail by a team of
Brazilian technicians acting under
the auspices of the federal, provin¬
cial and municipal authorities. A
number of measures were adopted,
including the construction of a new
road around the site and a bus sta¬
tion outside the historic centre so
that buses and coaches do not need
to park on or near the Praça
Tiradentes. Trucks and other heavy-
duty vehicles are not allowed in the
city, where a new urbanization zone
is being created. Slopes subject to
landslides are being consolidated. In
1979 a geological map was made of
the whole urban area in order to indi¬
cate zones which can be built on
without risk.
In December 1980, Ouro Prêto
was included on UNESCO's World
Heritage List.
* Michel Parent, Protect/on et mise en
valeur du patrimoine culturel brésilien dans
le cadre du développement touristique et
économique, UNESCO, 1966-1967.
AUGUSTO C. DA SILVA TELLES,
Brazilian architect and historian, has
been involved in the safeguarding of
Ouro Prêto in his capacity as technical
consultant to Brazil's Institute of the
National Historical and Artistic Heritage.
The author of many studies on
Portuguese and Brazilian architecture,
he was chairman of UNESCO's World
Heritage Committee in 1988 and 1989. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
N N M T
Coping with uncertainty
by Michel Bâtisse
How far are science and scientists responsible
for solving environmental problems?
Ihe many environmental problems with
which our planet is faced stem from the capri¬
cious, unpredictable effects of "development",
that is to say, the increasingly large-scale
application of industrial, agricultural, medical
and other techniques in economic and social
life. Technology, the term we use to describe
techniques in their totality, is today
omnipresent, and upon it depends the func¬
tioning of the modern world. Technology is
sometimes referred to as the daughter of
science. Today, however, science and tech¬
nology are closely intertwined in so many con¬
tinuous lines of fundamental and applied
research that it has become very difficult to
distinguish disinterested research from
research whose sole object is development.
Should we, then, blame science for being
the source of those imperfect techniques that
are degrading the human environment and
squandering the natural resources of the
biosphere? Some do not hesitate to make this
criticism. They forget, however, that we cannot
put the clock back. Some applications of
science, especially in the fields of medicine and
public health, have led to a rapid proliferation
of the human species. Only through other appli¬
cations, particularly in agriculture, has it been
possible to feed these increased numbers.
Nevertheless, we have every right to ask
whether the science upon which our material
civilization is based does not bear some respon¬
sibility for the way in which we handle the
environment, through its fundamental approach
rather than through its applications, and to try
to find out how, and to what extent, it can help .
us to escape from the rut into which we have
fallen.
Science as a conceptual attempt to under¬
stand the universe dates back to the ancient
civilizations. The scientific method, which
44 ensured the astounding progress of science,
is a more recent development dating from the
seventeenth century and emerging from the
promptings of Bacon, Descartes and Galileo.
Depending primarily on reasoned analysis, it
attempts to break down seemingly complex
phenomena into simpler, more easily meas¬
urable elements.
Based on a deterministic confidence in the
order of nature, the analytical method rapidly
met with dazzling success, particularly in the
fields of mechanics, physics and chemistry. Its
achievements gave rise to the notion of
progress and opened the way to the great social
changes of the Enlightenment in Europe and
America. It led on triumphantly to the industrial
revolution of the nineteenth century which is
still going on today. There can be no question
now of abandoning a tool that has been such
an effective instrument in the advancement of
knowledge and action.
The convergence of
disciplines
The limitations of the analytical method become
evident, however, when applied to phenomena
of a higher degree of complexity where deter¬
minism no longer seems to operate and where
the whole seems to be greater than the sum
of its component parts. This is especially the
case when the method is applied to questions
concerning the life of living beings and of soci¬
eties whose constituent elements react
amongst themselves and with their environ¬
ment. The striking successes being achieved
in biology today are doubtless due to the fact
that the scientific method has begun to go
beyond its traditional, analytical and reduc¬
tionist approach and to search for a conver¬
gence of disciplines in an attempt to achieve
a better grasp of the complexity and unpredic¬
tability of living systems.
Environmental problems are by nature
complex precisely because they involve human
life and life in the biosphere. Because they are
the incidental result of an excessively linear
technology, they are linked together by a chain
of multiple, often harmful interactions between
factors that may not have been suspected.
Because they are unforeseen and often
menacing, they appear to demand urgent solu¬
tions. Although scientists have never been
afraid to tackle difficult problems in fields they
have chosen to explore, the environment sud¬
denly faces them with extremely complex
problems which are not of their choosing and
which have to be handled with tools which are
still basically imperfect. It is true that consider¬
able methodological progress has been made
in the study of complex phenomena and their
evolution. Against the necessary interdiscipli¬
nary background two broad streams of scien¬
tific research have taken their place at the heart
of environmental concerns: ecologywhich
involves the study of the totality of the inter¬
relationships of human beings with one another
and with their environmentand geography
which is today capable of tracing the links
between the physical, biological, economic and
social factors that clash and interact within a
given territorial area.
Does this mean that science in its present
state can provide the eagerly-awaited answers
to environmental problems and in some way
correct the errors engendered by its own appli¬
cations? The answer is not so simple. Scientific
research is not immune to the inertia of habit
that affects all human behaviour. The interdis¬
ciplinary approach, which alone can enable real
progress to be made in our understanding of
complex systems, is still far from being
accepted by the scientific community. This is
because many scientists feel lost without their
traditional landmarks and are afraid of being
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Cattle enclosure In the Mount Kulal biosphere
reserve (Kenya), where the capacity of the
environment to support livestock is being studied as
part of a project on arid lands within UNESCO's Man
and the Biosphere programme.
taken in by worthless research work in fields
they have not fully mastered. The long-awaited
marriage between the natural and the social
sciences has either not come about or has led
to conflict and as a result a great deal of tech¬
nically unimpeachable scientific research is
either not applied or leads to failure simply
because it is not adapted to sociological and
economic requirements. Under these circum¬
stances, the persistent development of the
classic disciplines, especially when there is a
possibility that they will lead to applications in
industry, is still the most reliable route for
researchers to follow in order to obtain honours
and funding. The very structure of research
institutions favours isolation between dis¬
ciplines rather than contact with the realities
of the outside world.
Truth and value
judgements
In the last twenty years, however, praiseworthy
efforts have been made to place the analysis
and management of environmental problems
on the soundest possible scientific basis,
whether the concern be with threats to human
health, with the deterioration of natural
resources or with threats on a planetary scale
to the climate, the oceans or the atmosphere.
UNESCO's Man and the Biosphere (MAB)
Programme is one example of a remarkable
attempt to explore, on an interdisciplinary basis,
possible sustainable use of terrestrial
ecosystems and to provide useful information
for those who have to make decisions con¬
cerning their management.
It is not up to scientists to make decisions.
Scientists can attempt to evaluate the risks
involved in using this or that technique and
shed light on ways of handling those risks, thus
helping to ensure the avoidance of accidents
or errors. Science attempts to distinguish what
is true, what is possible, probable or certain, but
it does not make value judgements. It would be
a serious misjudgement of the nature of
science to ask it to decide what is right and
what is wrong. Every decision, even when it is
based on all the knowledge available, implies
a judgement of value and of expediency. In the
environmental field, in which the interests of
individuals, businesses, local authorities, the
state, or even the whole of humanity are
involved, every decision is necessarily political
rather than scientific. The same is true of deci¬
sions in the economic spherein industry,
why the climate is getting warmer.. nor what level of biological diversity is
necessary to sustain ecosystems...
We do not know exactly...
nor why the ozone layer Is thinning. But we can't afford to wait until we
know everything. We must act!
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
agriculture and transport, and in the social
spherein housing, employment and security.
In none of these fields, however, is the scien¬
tist called upon to act as arbiter.
Why then do we turn so readily to the scien¬
tist when environmental questions come up?
Perhaps because, when faced with unexpected,
worrying, complex problems, which seem to
cast doubt on the very basis of our calm belief
in material progress and the benefits of tech¬
nology, the authorities feel an overwhelming
need to understand and to be reassured. We
appeal to the scientist as we would to a magi¬
cian or a judge. We want to know the truth
about all the alarming threats and all the poten¬
tial catastrophes we hear people talking about.
Governments and the general public look to
science to provide certainties upon which
action can be based.
The difficulty and it is a considerable one
that there are no certainties about many
environmental problems because of their
extreme complexity, their novelty and their
chaotic, unpredictable evolution, coupled with
the multiplicity of the interactions involved.
These are problems that have a profoundly dis¬
turbing effect on our ingrained habits, and yet
we may not even be sure that they really exist.
We do not know, for example, precisely what
level of biological diversity is necessary to sus¬
tain the functioning of ecosystems. We do not
really know why the ozone layer in the upper
atmosphere is thinning. There is no undisputed
certainty about the greenhouse effect, which
is thought to be caused by the accumulation of
MICHEL BATISSE, French engineer and physicist, is
internationally known for his work on the environment
and natural resources. Currently a consultant with
UNESCO and the United Nations Environment
Programme, he has headed the Blue Plan Regional
Activity Centre for the Mediterranean at Sophia
Antipolis, France, since it was created in 1985.
"The interdisciplinary approach Is still
far from being accepted
by the scientific community."
Reforestation at Namche
In Sagarmatha National Park (Nepal),
i site inscribed on UNESCO's World Heritage List.
carbon dioxide and other gases of industrial or
agricultural origin, and its consequences remain
largely unpredictable.
Yet at the same time, responsible scientists
are telling us that all these things are happening,
that the loss of species diversity related to the
felling of the tropical forests, the influx of ultra¬
violet rays related to the destruction of the
ozone layer, and the warming up of the climate
due to the oil and coal we so light-heartedly
burn, are all just around the corner, even though
we do not know what is really going on.
Hard decisions and
soft information
Faced with this problem of uncertainty, the con¬
servative reaction of certain leaders is simply
to say that more research must be done before
any action is taken. It would not be easy for a
government to decide that it had, for example,
to tax motorists on the gases emitted from their
exhaust pipes. Such an attitude, however, might
very quickly be seen as irresponsible, if not
criminal, with respect to future generations. It
is clearly necessary to continue and intensify
research in an effort to find out more about
these phenomena which are so complex that
they may never be fully mastered, but it would
be wrong to delay acting until the situation
worsens. Regardless of the uncertainties, action
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
must be taken if we have legitimate grounds
for thinking that time is not on our side.
This is what was done recently to limit the
production of the chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)
that are destroying the ozone layer. In this case
it was possible to draw up an international
agreement because a specific product with
clearly defined uses was involved, because
industry was ready to provide substitute
products and because compensation could be
made to developing countries that would be
handicapped by this technical change. The
important thing to remember, however, is that
this exemplary action was undertaken despite
uncertainties about a number of scientific
aspects of the problem, thus avoiding further
deterioration of the ozone layer while waiting
for absolute certainties to be obtained. Imper¬
fect scientific knowledge of environmental
problems should never be an excuse for inac¬
tion. As a British researcher once remarked,
governments today have to take hard decisions
on the basis of soft information.
To aid them in this formidable task, govern¬
ments naturally try to base their action as far
as possible on scientific opinion. They hope
thus to give a certain legitimacy to their deci¬
sions by basing them on accepted knowledge
and thus to shelter behind the objective façade
of science. The major economic leaders tend
to follow their example, as do associations for
the defence of the environment and of the con¬
sumer. Thus scientists find themselves torn
between various conflicting interests, each of
which seeks to make the scientist an advocate
of its own cause. Because of the divergent
interests of states the struggle is increasingly
coming into the open at the international level.
Various countries have laid down standards of
chemical quality for certain food products, on
the basis of so-called scientific norms, with the
sole aim of preventing the import of such
products. In these circumstances, what
becomes of scientific rigour and objectivity?
Experts and
the scientific ethic
The fact is that when they are asked to give
their opinion on these complex questions,
scientists no longer act as scientists, in accor¬
dance with the search for a consensus that is
part of the scientific approach itself, but as
experts called in to provide arguments in sup¬
port of one theory rather than another, so as
not to harm the interests of those who have
commissioned them. This is a thankless role
and one which some do not play, preferring to
remain within their ivory towers. However, if
scientists or independent engineers are not pre¬
pared to assume this role, who will play it?
Would it be better to have administrators,
jurists, or engineers employed by the great
state institutions undertaking this task on their
own, with the attendant danger of confounding
judge and plaintiff, as we have seen from time
to time in military, nuclear and even forestry
matters? It would be better to gather together
a sufficient number of competent scientists
from a variety of disciplines and to observe how
far they agree.
At all events, the important thing is for
scientists, in their role as experts, to retain the
same ethical standard by which they are guided
in their scientific work. The political choices
facing governments in environmental affairs will
never be easy, especially so long as ecology is
not fully integrated into the economy. But in the
end, given the uncertainties that will always per¬
sist, these choices must be guided by respect
for the scientific ethic.
The situation is somewhat similar with
regard to public opinion and to associations.
Here too there is a need for expert advice if
wrong or unrealistic paths are to be avoided.
Here too there must be an appeal to scientists,
even though they may not be inclined to put
their knowledge on display or may fear that, by
co-operating with the media, they may incur the
disdain of their colleagues. This descent into
the arena does not give scientists the right to
use the prestige of their scientific status to
express dogmatic opinions, but it should pro¬
vide public opinion, whether as partner or
privileged adversary of the government in
"The scientific culture
must become part of the daily
experience of each one of us."
democratic discussion about the environment,
with reliable information about the issues, thus
avoiding cacophonous arguments and arbitrary
judgements. It.means that scientists, who are
too often regarded as inaccessible, obscuran¬
tist or indecisive, retain the credibility earned
by their mastery of a difficult branch of
knowledge. They must emerge from their
habitual reserve and not hesitate to speak out
against policies they consider harmful or activi¬
ties they see as potentially dangerous for the
environment.
Public opinion may also fear that scientists
are accomplices of the government or of
powerful economic interests. Here, perhaps, is
an opportunity for scientists, in acting as
experts for the government on the one hand
and for movements for the defence of the
environment on the other, to place the scien¬
tific ethic at the high level it should maintain
in these difficult debates and thus to acquire
a more highly respected role and power within
modern society, just as Bacon recommended
over 350 years ago.
The rehabilitation of science in the environ¬
mental fieldwhere it has been rather too often
accused of being the prime cause of many
problems and of failing to provide solutions
depends not only upon scientists but also upon
the public at large. Although during the past
fifty years the applications of science have
become so widespread as to upset all our
behavioural and value systems, how many of
us have made the effort to understand the
impulsions and constraints of this technolog¬
ical universe now unfolding before our eyes?
How can we expect governments, the world
community and motivated public opinion to
stem the degradation of the planet while this
scientific culture, which influences our lives and
ensures our survival, is still not fully integrated
into the daily experience of each one of us?
There, perhaps, lies the real challenge we must
face if we are to achieve responsible manage¬
ment of our uncertain future. 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The
Silk
Rods
Threading through the past
by François-Bernard Huygbe
Scholars taking
part in UNESCO's
Maritime
Silk Roads
expedition highlight
the complexities
of exchanges along
the great trade
routes of long ago
48
FRANÇOIS-BERNARD HUYGHE,
French writer and journalist, is a
former member of UNESCO's
Division of Cultural Heritage.
rtFTER leaving Oman and calling at
Karachi, Goa, Colombo and Madras,
the Maritime Silk Roads expedition
embarked on the second half of Its
voyage at Phuket in Thailand.
Although they are following a route
which traces a single line across the
map, the participants realize that its
ramifications are labyrinthine in their
complexity. Each discovery of a new
site, each new lecture and sympo¬
sium, fits into a pattern and sets a
vast network of travel, trade and
communication in a new perspective.
The stop-off at Karachi was an
opportunity to reflect on the trading
civilization of the Indus, the Aryan
invasions of the Indian sub-continent,
and the relations between Sind and
Central Asia, Iran and China which go
back to the last millennium of the
pre-Christian era. At Goa we were in
the Portuguese world, with its
privileged links with Malacca and
Macao. Sri Lanka evoked thoughts of
the Greco-Roman world, of Arab
trade, and the spiritual influence of
an island which played a leading role
in the spread of Buddhism. In
Madras, the abundance of research
on relations with the Roman world
was only rivalled by that of studies
on the links between Tamil Nadu and
South and Southeast Asia. So many
threads to be unravelled from such
a tangled skein!
The general term "Silk Roads" is
also used to designate trade routes
in commodities such as porcelain,
spices and incense. But there are
other routes whose scattered traces
invite study. One of them is that
taken by Roman coins. It is not sur¬
prising that Roman coins should
have turned up all along our route,
but when two numismatists put for¬
ward some ingenious hypotheses at
a seminar held in Madras they
prompted a number of more general
historical questions. How important
was the heavy drain of coinage along
the trade-route with India which
caused the Roman emperor Tiberius
such alarm? What role did the
emperor's entourage play in this?
When were Roman coins prized at
their nominal value and when
according to their weight in metal,
and why? Tiny coins lost at the other
end of the world are evidence of
crises and conflicts that were
agitating a distant empire.
Another specialist on board the
Fulk al-Salamah, the Ship of Peace,
is studying even smaller objects, the
beads with which necklaces were
made. His field of research begins in
the third century BC, and is based on
the different shapes of rough glass
beads. From the region of what is
today Pondicherry it is possible to
trace the steps of Indian glassmakers
to Sri Lanka, Viet Nam, Thailand and
Malaysia and learn something about
the beliefs and hierarchies that
existed in those societies. Perhaps
we should think in terms of a "glass
bead road" or a "seashell road"?
After all some seashells, particularly
those from Oman, were used for cen¬
turies as a unit of exchange. The
type, location and quantity of shells
found along the Silk Roads warrant
scholarly investigation.
Even the simplest and most tan¬
gible vestiges of trade raise ques¬
tions with complex answers. Such
vestiges amply prove, as we might
expect, how ancient, regular and
intensive were the relations between
cultures and how rich was their
common heritage. But artefacts and
coins always have a value that is not
merely utilitarian. They indicate that
trade routes are also channels of
communication for technology,
ideas, art forms and beliefs.
A speaker at one seminar pointed
out that while many scholars have
abandoned the concept of cultural
"influences" on the grounds that it
is too simplistic, they have often
replaced it by the concept of "inter¬
actions" which is hardly more
illuminating. As they try to decipher
the clues left by their predecessors,
modern travellers along the Silk
Roads are constantly struck by the
irrelevance of some of the categories
we use. Stones, pottery, artefacts,
stories, maps and vestiges are the
external transcription of an inner
need that impels certain peoples
towards maritime adventure, each in
its own different way.
The mysterious Indus
civilization
The gaps in our knowledge often
whet our curiosity about the values
which lie behind rare vestiges from
the past. In Pakistan, for example,
our programme of seminars and
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Visits highlighted the importance of
the mysterious Indus Valley civiliza¬
tion which disappeared 3,500 years
ago. A visit to Moenjodaro, whose
discovery in 1921 was a milestone
in the history of archaeology,
prompted a host of questions. All
that survives of this great monument
to a civilization whose writing has still
not been deciphered, a metropolis
that was continuously occupied for
almost 2,000 years and may well
have had a population of some
45,000, are the ruins of a brick city
built on a remarkably regular grid
system of street layout.
The overall impression is one of
austerity. The houses, rebuilt one
above the other in the course of the
centuries, are virtually identical. The
drainage system and the public baths
are evidence of an important infra¬
structure. The discovery of stan¬
dardized weights and seals
throughout the area influenced by
the Indus civilization suggests the
existence of an efficient mechanism
of control and perhaps of a powerful
administrative framework. But the
few vestiges and works of art of this
great civilization transmit a laconic
message that is not fully understood.
We know next to nothing about the
myths and beliefs of one of the first
peoples who opened up the great
trade routes of the Eurasian con¬
tinent.
But whether we are faced with a
plethora of traces or, as in the case
of the Indus civilization, with very
few, we come up against the same
uncertainties. What type of dialogue
was established along the Silk Roads
over the centuries, and what did it
mean for those who lived in its orbit?
There is an urgent need for concep
tual guidelines to help us understand
the effects of this process whereby
so many peoples and forms of
expression came into contact with
each other. Perhaps we should exa¬
mine the spiritual as well as the phys¬
ical dimensions of the Silk Roads.
Gods and places
From Sri Lanka onwards the maritime
Silk Roads intersect with the route
along which Buddhism spread. If the
conversion of Sind to Islam and of
Goa to Christianity are major events,
the way in which this island once
known as Taprobane became the
centre from which the Buddhist doc¬
trine of Enlightenment was dissemi¬
nated illustrates the relationship
between gods and places.
Perhaps something predisposes
the island to play this role. The geog¬
raphy of the "lion kingdom" has an
imaginary and a spiritual, as well as
a physical, dimension. The car¬
tographers of Antiquity, following
Ptolemy, attributed to Taprobane a
size and a locationon the very edge
of the world in keeping with its sym¬
bolic importance. The mountain of
Samanakuta or "Adam's Peak" is a
famous place of pilgrimage. At its
summit is a hollow resembling a
human footprint which is venerated
by pilgrims of the "religions of the
Book" as that of Adam after he was
banished from the Garden of Eden.
The great Arab traveller Ibn Battuta
came to meditate at the foot of the
mountain, "forty leagues from Para¬
dise". Pliny's stories about the Isle
of Emeralds fed the Western imagi¬
nation until the Middle Ages and
Inspired extravagant depictions of
fields of precious stones and houses
inside the shells of giant snails.
; i \Jà 1
- 'A^-'f " -7
"^ M
V
T-
i Í
1 t \á ñ
r
j
f I mW*~~t
^BT ' 'títItí Wttc&f; í
*
1m
}
IV'y »,
But Buddhists believe that the
hollow is the footprint of Gautama
Buddha. Around 250 BC, the Indian
emperor Asoka sent his son Mahinda
to Sri Lanka to convert the sovereign
to Buddhism. Later, Mahinda's sister
followed him with a branch of the Bo
tree under which Gautama was sit¬
ting when he attained Enlightenment.
The sacred tree which grew from this
branch can still be seen at Anurad-
hapura, Sri Lanka's ancient capital.
From there the doctrine of Lesser
Vehicle Buddhism spread through
Burma, Thailand and Southeast Asia.
But the history of Anuradhapura, a
town noted for its many monasteries
and the world's tallest stupa, is en¬
twined with the fortunes of another
venerated relic, the Buddha's tooth,
which was sent there in the fourth
century. From then on the power of
the reigning dynasty was linked to
possession of the tooth-relic which,
together with the capital, was moved
from place to place under the pres¬
sure of invasions.
When, at the end of the fifth cen¬
tury, King Kasyapa built an extraor-
Opposite page, the Buddhist sanctuary
of Dalada Maligava (Temple of the
Tooth) at Kandy (Sri Lanka).
Above: a staircase hewn from the rock
leads to the ancient royal residence of
Slglriya (Sri Lanka).
Left: the Calangute church, Goa
(India).
dinary fortified palace and gardens
on a 200-metre high rocky outcrop
at Slglriya in the heart of the jungle,
his enemies talked of heresy. In the
eleventh century Anuradhapura was
sacked by the Cholas from southern
India. Polonnaruwa became the
island's capital, remaining so for
three centuries, and many Buddhist
monuments were built there. Finally
the relic was taken to Kandy, the cap¬
ital until the arrival of the British,
where it still remains.
Religion is omnipresent in Sri
Lanka. An order of Buddhist nuns
was founded there and spread
overseas. Men of faith and wisdom
travelled there in search of purity of
doctrine, among them the monk
Faxian who left China in the year 399
and stayed on the island for two
years. Missionaries and pilgrims set
out from Sri Lanka on journeys that
took them all over Asia. Travelling
and taking root, sea and landthese
two poles mark the history of Singha¬
lese Buddhism.
The participants in the maritime
expedition have come to realize that
the spread of Buddhism was the
result of factors such as geography,
maritime technology and trading net¬
works, as well as economic and polit¬
ical forces. But they have also
learned that these causes alone do
not explain the conversion of Sri
Lankaa mystery which exploration
of the Silk Roads does not unlock.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
50
The temple of the heart
As a regular reader of the UNESCO
Courier, I should like to express a
Protestant viewpoint about your
issue on "Sacred Places" (November
1990).
Protestants have never
sanctified places in the same way as
Catholic and Orthodox Christians.
They believe that the human heart is
the only repository of the sacred.
This explains why Protestant
architecture is less elaborate and
Protestant places of worship are
more functional. Many evangelical
Churches today hold their meetings
in marquees or cinemas.
In most cases this lack of
ornamentation is not due to lack of
taste or means. It is an affirmation
that the sacred does not have a
geographical location, since the
"only temple of God is the human
heart".
This comment may seem
irrelevant to the preoccupations of
UNESCO. This is not the case.
Current events show that many
recent conflicts are polarized around
sacred places.
As part of your mission to work
for peace through reflection on
cultures, you should have pointed
out that the sanctification of a place
all too often leads to contempt for
others and sometimes to hatred and
war, and that education for peace
should entail the difficult but
necessary task of desanctifying
objects and places. The Protestant
Churches have been pioneers in this
respect.
This letter is intended to bring
the efforts of the Protestant
Churches to your readers' attention.
It in no way reflects a desire that
everyone should become Protestant.
Michel Bourguet
Dunkirk
(France)
The geophysics of the sacred
It was extremely instructive to read
in your November 1990 issue about
the variety of the forms and places
through which different civilizations
and cultures express their search for
the sacred.
Some of the articles evoke the
role played by the siting of sacred
buildings and places of worship. My
profession of architect, and my
personal interests, have led me to
give some thought to these matters.
Religious buildings fulfill the
architectural purpose of enclosing
space, but in them it seems that our
senses are more strongly affected
than they are in secular buildings.
Our behaviour and reactions are
Influenced by various physical
factors whose impact on the
human body is still not fully
understood.
These physical phenomena
emanate from the environment and
have a cumulative effect. Applied
geophysics describes them as the
gravimetric field, which is not
uniform and depends on such
factors as local geological variations;
properties of the Earth's magnetic
field such as intensity, orientation,
declination; the ionization of the air,
which has a direct effect on health;
radioactivity; the speed of diffusion
of seismic waves; the electrotelluric
currents which run through land and
sea.
Through physical and sensory
experiments I have discovered that
religious buildings in FranceI am
particularly interested in
Romanesque churches of the 11th
to the 14th centuryare built on
sites with distinctive geophysical
characteristics. Thus I have noted
that there is almost always at least
one watercourse underneath these
monuments, as well as geological
faults.
Of course, the symbolism of
ancient buildings must also be
considered alongside these invisible
forces, and the art of the builders
and their understanding of
harmonious relationships also
contribute to the construction of a
building and to its echoes in a
receptive mind.
Bernard Arditti
Manosque
(France)
Middle Earth
I should like to point out that in your
excellent issue on "Sacred Places"
you state that the Great Stupa at
Sanchi is in northern India. In fact
the stupa is in the state of Madhya
Pradesh (which means "Middle
Earth") in central India, and is itself
right in the centre of the state.
Elisabeth Beaumont
La-Celle-Saint-Cloud
(France)
We apologize to readers for this error.
Editor
Rejecting poverty and shame
In 1991, thanks to the UNESCO
Courier, art, poetry and culture will
reach very needy people all over the
world and will help to alleviate the
shame, humiliation and dependence
which they refuse to accept. Thank
you for this excellent magazine.
Mouvement International ATD
(Aide à Toute Détresse) Quart Monde
107, avenue du Général Ledere
95480 Pierrelaye (France)
Quart Monde, the French-language
quarterly published by the Institut de
Recherche et de Formation aux
Relations Humaines du Mouvement
International ATD Quart Monde, seeks
to be "a means of exchange and
reflection for all those who reject
extreme poverty and exclusion. Each
issue presents a dossier on a social
question not only from the viewpoint of
specialists but of the needy and those
who support them." Editor
Addresses wanted
We humans who speak the same
language should communicate,
speak and write to one another,
share the convictions that motivate
us, in order to know others, to
discover new horizons, to force back
the many-headed Hydra of
ignorance, the source of all ills.
Let's exchange our addresses!
Bertrand Hue
46, rue August Moutié
78120 Rambouillet
(France)
H Timeless values
The photograph in chiaroscuro on
the cover of your December 1990
issue ("The Enigma of Beauty") is
one of the most beautiful and
moving cover illustrations I have
seen in the Courier. The silent
immobility of an anonymous couple
before Barnett Newman's vast
canvas Is a tribute to artists, those
creators of human values.
Barnett Newman, who died in
New York in 1970, wanted to refine
art to its most fundamental
significance. In so doing, he took
abstraction to the limits of
asceticism.
His immense, monochrome
canvases, devoid of any allusion to
reality except a few vertical bands,
are "fields of colour" offered for
contemplation. Through this
fascinating expanse of colour, the
artist invites us to meditate on
fundamental, timeless, metaphysical
values.
This photograph, quite apart
from its plastic qualities, delivers a
marvellous message of peace, a
pause for reflection in a world of
agitation and uncertainty.
Henry Christiaën
Grenoble
(France)
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, pages 3 (right), 9 (right), 12
(left), 29, 30 (left), 35 (below), 37
(right): © Bita Seyedi, Paris. Back
cover: © Artcurial, Paris. Page 2:
© Henri Landier, Atelier d'Art Lepic,
Paris. Pages 3 (left), 5, 6: AH Rights -
Reserved. Pages 4, 15 (above):
© Francis Vernhet/Birmapresse, Paris.
Pages 6-7, 10 (left), 23 (below), 26
(below), 32: © Christian Rose, Paris.
Pages 7 (right), 11 (right), 23
(above), 25, 35 (above), 37 (left), 38
(below): ©J.M. Birraux, Paris. Pages
8-9: © Rio Branco/Magnum, Paris.
Pages 10-11: Jeffrey Scales ©Virgin,
Paris. Page 12 (right): © Charles
Carrie, Paris. Pages 13: © DITE/IPS,
Paris. Page 14 (above): © Doc Stills,
Paris; (left): Denis Stock © Magnum,
Paris; (right): ©J.C. Simon, Paris.
Page 15 (below): D. Boutard © Stills,
Paris. Page 16: © Fernando Seixas,
with the permission of Globo
Records France. Page 17: De Wilde
© Hoa-Qui, Paris. Page 18:
Engravings from Grabados populares
del nordeste del Brasil, Servicio de
propaganda y expansión comercial de
la Embajada del Brasil, Madrid, 1963;
(right): © Globo Records France.
Page 19: © Charles Lénars, Paris.
Pages 20, 21: © Manuel Peña,
California. Page 24: Frank Driggs,
© Magnum, Paris. Pages 26-27:
M. Macintyre © ANA, Paris. Page
28: © Progress Publishers, Moscow.
Pages 30-31: Guy le Querrec
© Magnum, Paris. Page 33:
UNESCO/Auvidis Collection. Page
34: © Béatrice Lagarde. Page 36
(above): Picto-Press © Stills, Paris;
(below): © BMG, Paris. Page 38
(above): © C. Stoman/Mosa'ique
Gitane, Nîmes, 1990. Page 39: © Real
World/Virgin, Paris. Page 42:
UNESCO/A. Huzarska. Page 43
(above): TJNESCO/Lozouet-Fury;
(below): UNESCO/T. Fury. Page 45
(above): UNESCO/S. Schwartz.
Pages 45 (below), 46 (above), 47
(above): UNESCO/Yvette Fabri.
Pages 46-47 (below): UNESCO.
Pages .48, 49 (above): ©J.-L. Nou,
Paris. Page 49 (below): Raghubir
Singh © ANA, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
NESCO
COURIER
44th YEAR
Published monthly In 35 languages and in braille
by UNESCO, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin. 75015 Pans, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque. Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Russian edition: Georgi Zelemn
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, Carole Pajot-Font
(Tel.: 45.68.4690)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstem (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Beim (Tel.: 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68 47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Selection In braille In English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Mane-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkii (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanmi (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Mgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dares-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kossler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gu^utz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88),
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89).
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68 45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité. Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Din.
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk. Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Gmette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65).
Mail: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 139 French francs. 2 years: 259 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 108 French francs. 2 years: 194 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of UNESCO
individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may Oe reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the UNESCO Couner",
pus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
pi otos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
Se -eturned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Sigred anides express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
a' the editors of the UNESCO Couner Photo captions and headlines
are written by the UNESCO Courier staff The boundaries on maps
published m the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nat ons. The UNESCO Courier
is produced in microform {microfilm and/or microfiche) by (1) UNESCO.
7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox),
Ann Arbor. Michigan 48 100. U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York. U.S.A ; (4) Be!l and Howell
Co.. Old Mansfield Road. Wcoster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed >n France) DEPOT LEGAL CI MARS 1991.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP.
Photocomposition The UNESCO Courier
Photogravure-impression Maury Imprimeur S.A..
2.1 route d'Etampes, 45330 Malesherbes.
Will the benefits of the Green Revolution of the 1960s and
progress in food production meet the needs of the world
population at the end of this century?
Will the "biotechnical revolution" offer a solution to worldfood
problems?
How can agricultural development and self-sufficiency be
attained, particularly in developing countries?
FEEDING
TOMORROW'S WORLD
BY ALBERT SASSON
ISSN 0041-5278 N°3 1991 OPI-91 -3- 491 A
is an attempt to answer these and related questions through a
pluridisciplinary approach to human nutrition and food
production. The book, addressed to a wide readership, provides
a remarkable synthesis ofthe scientific, economic, socio-economic
and environmental aspects of nutrition throughout the world.
FEEDING TOMORROW'S WORLD (SEXTANT SERIES 3)
1990, 805 pages, ISBN 92-3-102083-8, FF225.00; US$56.25; £34.00.
Co-published by UNESCO
and the Technical Centre for Agriculture and Rural Co-operation (CT A), The Netherlands.
Orders may either be sent direct with payment enclosed, made out to the order of UNESCO, to the
UNESCO Press, Sales Division. 7 place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, France; or via the national distributor(s)
of UNESCO publications in your country.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
fe±
]]>
</page>
</document>
