<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="088610eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
* ni	ï m**^^
IIISII 1
MAY 199
,-
*W*
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Tomorrow,
another peace
On 25 January 1991, during the Gulf war, an article in which the
Director-General of UNESCO set forth his ideas on ways of
achieving world peace was published in the Paris daily Le Monde.
On this page we reproduce the article in its entirety. Its arguments
have lost none of their force or relevance.
BY FEDERICO MAYOR
DIRECTOR-GENERAL OF UNESCO
IN 1945, THE SURVIVORS OF A WAR IN WHICH THE
whole world had gradually become embroiled were convinced that
reason could only prevail over self-interest if a collective organization
were to take responsibility for universal security, which would be based
on intergovernmental co-operation, shared development and dialogue
between cultures. Peace would result from the emergence of a con¬
cerned and responsible world citizenship, transcending individual affili¬
ations to local, regional and national groups.
Human beings were to acquire this sense of citizenship by learning
tolerance, by learning to respect the dignity of individuals and the differ¬
ences between them. Between 1945 and 1990 every effort was made,
notwithstanding the persistence of wars, famines and acts of aggres¬
sion, to address the causes and consequences of those antagonisms
which were still causing people to rise against people, nation against
nation, state against state.
As a result of these individual and collective efforts, and the sacrifice
of many lives, for the first time since the collapse of a wall which had
become symbolic, a ray of hope appeared, accompanied by fears and
hesitations, calculations and ambitions, feelings of reluctance and resig¬
nation. The idea that all men and women share the same world, the
same earth, and the same humanity, gained ground, distilling a spirit of
joyfulness that was sometimes naive but brought with it a new
potential for peace.
However, within a few months, all kinds of economic, financial,
military and geopolitical interests, combined with personal ambitions,
had toppled a still fragile edifice. Yesterday's hopes are now beset with
uncertainty. Peace has again appeared to be slipping from our grasp.
Following this setback, and after the vain expenditure of so much effort,
would courage and clearsightedness inevitably succumb to lassitude
and resignation? Not at all. The obligation to work for peace is not
one that can be shrugged aside. This invasion, like those before it, this
war, like those that preceded it in other parts of the world, will not
make us abandon our efforts. We must start again. We must rebuild.
We must strive anew for peace, another peace. For if we are convinced
that it is through respect for international law and the resolutions
whereby it is given effect that the international community can
legitimaly express itself, then that international community must
wholeheartedly commit itself to the struggle against ignorance, poverty,
discrimination, oppression, and all forms of violence and humiliation
which erode freedom and compromise human dignity.
The new international order which could be glimpsed a few months
ago was based on undeniable achievementsthe emergence of new
democracies, the disappearance of the legacy of a tormented past, the
acceleration of the disarmament process, negotiated solutions to
local conflicts. It must be enriched with new prospects for human
development. For if it is to be just and lasting, the peace to which
we aspire must be global, andthrough dialogue," understanding, and
knowledge of the identities and specificities of othersmust take into
account those whom history has spurned, those who stand by help¬
lessly and see another world being builta world to which they
nevertheless fully belong.
The permanent peace which we hoped to build has turned out
to be unable to withstand the logic of war because it was not envisaged
in global terms. To achieve such a peace we must, in the short term,
patiently restore discussion, common sense, intelligence, sensitivity and
tolerance to their rightful place. These virtues and these values must
be the keynote of the post-war future. It also seems to me essential
that we should all learn to pay more attention to the psychology of
peoples, whose roots plunge deep into history and are not governed
by political rigidities.
In the longer term, we must insist on a change of direction in the
ways of thinking and practice of those responsible for world peace.
The standardization of lifestyles, values, mentalities and patterns of
behaviour has been too widely presented as the touchstone of moder¬
nity. By minimizing the importance of specific cultural, national, ethnic
and religious characteristics, this standardization has removed our
familiar landmarks. It has now gone far enough. The rediscovery of
our own identity should provide the most effective impulse towards
tolerance of others.
The spread of scientific knowledge and technological progress has
contributed to a fairer, albeit still inadequate, distribution of the benefits
of development. But quantitative growth must be guided by renewed
respect for the environment, limited natural resources and balanced
demographic development.
In all societies, ethical, philosophical and religious ideas should cir¬
culate freely. As much attention should be paid to the spiritual dimen¬
sion of development as to its sustainability.
If we again give precedence to these considerations, then perhaps
one day war will be eradicated from the human mind. This was the
hope of the founders of UNESCO, men and women who had wit¬
nessed and survived a war which was so close to them that its wounds
had still not healed.
War and peace are human, all too human. To discourage one and
encourage the other, we must first reinstate with tenacity and com¬
mitment that which is best in humanity, that which makes us human,
for therein lies the source of life, of work and creativity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
MAY 1991 CONTENTS
4
Interview with
SADRUDDIN AGA KHAN
ThellNESCO
^COURIER
44th YEAR
Published monthly In 35 languages and In Braille
"The Governments of the States
parties to this Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds
of men, it is In the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded, if It Is not to
fail, upon the intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect knowledge of
each other's lives..."
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of UNESCO,
London, 16 November 1945
PEOPLE AT PLAY
AN APPETITE FOR LIVING
by Martine Mauriras-Bousquet 13
BETWEEN ORDER AND CHAOS
by Graciela Schemes 19
DOING WHAT COMES NATURALLY
by Shalva Amonashvili 22
SMILE, SMILE, SMILE
by Marsi Paribatra 26
CHILD DEVELOPMENT THROUGH PLAY
by Raimundo Dinello 29
PLAY AND THE SACRED IN AFRICA
by Barthélémy Comoe-Krou 30
GAMES WITHOUT FUN
by Jean d'Ormesson 34
41
IN BRIER.
42
VSESCO IS ACTIOS
WORLD HERITAGE
The Dogon,
Mali's people of the cliffs
by Caroline Haardt
46
VSESCO IS ACTIOS
THE SILK ROADS
The fabulous land of Cathay
by François-Bernard Huyghe
49
LISTENING
Recent records
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
SPORT AND PLAY
by Georges Magnane 39
Cover: 18th-century Indian
miniature.
Back cover: The spring
festival, Tokyo (Japan)
Special consultant
for this issue:
MARTINE
MAURIRAS-BOUSQUET
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
I INTERVIEW
SADRUDDIN
AGA KHAN
Prince Sadruddin Aga Khan is the son of
Mohammed Shah, the Aga Khan III, religious
leader of the Nizari Ismailis, a Shiite Islamic
reformist movement which has many
followers in India, Pakistan, Central Asia, the
Islamic Republic of Iran, Syria and East Africa.
In 1958, at UNESCO, he embarked on a
brilliant international career, and in 1965
became United Nations High Commissioner
for Refugees, a position he held until 1977.
Still extremely active In the field of
humanitarian action, Sadruddin Aga Khan
created the Bellerive Foundation, Geneva,
which is concerned with development aid and
the protection of the environment, notably in
Africa. He is also vice-president of the World
Wide Fund for Nature.
You have been associated with the United
Nations system for many years. Did you feel
a vocation to serve the UN?
I think people are primarily influenced by
their family environment. Because of my
origins I belong both to the East and the West.
Iran is the cradle of our family, but we have
never lived there. I was born in Paris, and my
mother was French. Through my father, who
had a strong influence on me, I came into con¬
tact with Islam when I was very young. We
travelled widely in the Islamic countries and
often visited Egypt. My father was a pioneer in
international organizations: he played an active
part in the creation of the League of Nations,
was its president in 1937, and even inaugurated
the Palais des Nations in Geneva. My office
is only a few steps away from the one he
occupied. That makes for a kind of continuity.
As well as being a senior international civil
servant, you are also known as a man ofideas
and someone who is closely involved in grass¬
roots issues.
have tried to resist the forces of bureaucratic
inertia. In the corridors of diplomacy people
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Poster produced by
the Office of
the United Nations
High Commissioner
for Refugees (UIMHCR).
gradually tend to lose their capacity to distin¬
guish between what is important and what
isn't. A phrase or a comma in a draft resolu¬
tion suddenly come to assume dispropor¬
tionate importance. Negotiations go on for
hours, for nights on end, before agreement is
reached on what is generally the lowest
common denominator. You feel that you have
won a great victory. But no-one will read the
text which was so difficult to draft.
Don't you find this sort of thing futile?
History will judge. Perhaps we shall have
a more objective perspective on the United
Nations when we come to celebrate its fiftieth
anniversary. Certainly it is a good thing not
to always observe the world through United
Nations spectacles. That's why I have set so
much store by my independence.
While waitingfor the judgement ofhistory,
don't you see positive aspects in the work of
the United Nations?
Indeed. It is now widely and rightly
accepted that we live in a world which is more
interdependent than ever before, and that
problems are increasingly global in character.
At the risk of stating the obvious, I would say
that when governments realize that certain
problems are beyond their powers, it is clear
that the United Nations has an irreplaceable
role to play.
At the same time, the world is changing
considerably and the United Nations must
change too. It must become an instrument
which responds to the needs of the interna¬
tional community of the year 2000, which will
be quite different from that of 1945. This is
very far from the case. We should not delude
ourselves into thinking that the United
Nations is going to change because a certain
role has been restored to the Security Council.
The Security Council is an exclusive club with
a restricted membership, sensitive to the
moods of the moment. Its resolutions only
remotely affect the organs and institutions of
the United Nations which face the great
challenges of today.
To return to your own career, which has
always taken you towards the mostpractical
activities of international life. I believe you
started by taking an interest in the problem
of the Abu Simbel temples.
Yes, I took my first steps in international
life at UNESCO, which at that time was con¬
ducting an exciting campaign to save the
monuments of Nubia, a campaign which in
my opinion remains one of UNESCO's great
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
achievements. In the middle of the Cold War
it was quite remarkable to get East European
archaeologists to join archaeologists from the
United States and other Western countries in
order to save the treasures of ancient Egypt.
Not to mention that since 1956 Nasser had
not exactly been the most popular Arab figure
in the West.
Did the general feeling that Abu Simbel
should be saved crystallize at a precise
moment?
Not only Abu Simbel. There were other
monuments which were just as important: the
temples of Philae and Kalabsha, the Christian
churches of Nubia. The Upper Egypt of the
great pharaonic civilizations did not stop at
Aswan, it extended to Nubia, to Khartoum
in the Sudan. In order to develop, all these
regions needed the resources that tourism
could bring them.
From an entirely different point of view,
in face of the threat of the flooding of archaeo¬
logical sites by the construction of the Aswan
dam, all kinds of people from many countries,
independently of their political orientations,
were united in thinking that something should
be done. At that time I was executive secre¬
tary of UNESCO's international action com¬
mittee for the preservation of the Nubian sites
and monuments, and I was strongly aware of
this feeling.
So this was your first mission?
I was also Head of Mission and Advisor to
the United Nations High Commissioner for
Refugees (UNHCR). I was principally con¬
cerned with World Refugee Year (1959-1960).
Through a philatelic programme to which all
member states of the UN and the Universal
Postal Union contributed, we collected a large
sum of money and also gave pleasure to stamp
collectors.
Was this for the benefit of European
refugees alone?
No. World Refugee Year was very useful
for the Palestine refugees, since the United
Nations Relief and Works Agency
(UNRWA), which was responsible for
providing them with assistance, had been in
existence since 1949. But it is true that around
this time refugees began to appear in the Third
World who did not benefit from United
Nations aid. One such case was that of the
Vietnamese who had fled from the north of
their country after the battle of Dien Bien
Phu. In Africa, the first refugees from Angola
were entering Congo-Kinshasa and Congo-
Brazzaville. Refugees from Algeria were
flowing into Morocco and Tunisia. These
were new situations for UNHCR, which had
been originally created for refugees from
Eastern Europe and was a kind of European
club. Very early on, and perhaps this is the
best thing I have done in my career, I tried
to avoid all discrimination between European
and Third World refugees.
Why were there different categories of
refugees and what form did these differences
take?
They were the result of constraints that
were essentially legal. United Nations action
was subject to the 1951 UN Convention
relating to the Status of Refugees, an interna¬
tional instrument which was drawn up during
the Cold War and, as everyone now accepts,
made UNHCR a propaganda instrument
against the Eastern countries.
In order to benefit from UNHCR protec¬
tion, a refugee had to be able to prove that
he or she was persecuted for reasons of race,
religion, nationality or political opinions, was
outside his or her country of origin, and could
not enjoy that country's protection. At that
time refugees were pictured as people who
crossed the Iron Curtain and were fired on
from frontier watchtowers. But where did this
leave the African populations who were
victims of general instability, fleeing tribal
warfare on both sides of frontiers traced
arbitrarily by the colonial powers? In Hun¬
gary in 1956 and Czechoslovakia in 1968
people knew where the frontiers with Austria
were. But there was not a single frontier post
between Angola and what was then Congo-
Kinshasa!
I
/*
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Above, refugees on the border
of Cambodia and Thailand.
Left, at the Bellerlve
Foundation's centre In Nairobi
(Kenya), meals are prepared
on the low-fuel stoves which
the Foundation distributes In
Africa.
It was necessary to widen the UNHCR
mandate, and this was a long and legally com¬
plex process. The protection of the High
Commissioner was finally extended to new
categories of refugees by virtue of a Protocol
which was adopted in 1967 and which I myself
strongly supported. These same refugees were
also able to benefit from the so-called "good
offices" resolutions voted by the General
Assembly of the United Nations.
It looks as if Third World refugees were
a frightening prospect at that time...
People saw millions of men, women and
children who could not be integrated. They
feared the economic and financial conse¬
quences and the repercussions on the labour
market. It was already a North-South
problem. If it was easy to resettle Czechs, Rus¬
sians or Hungarians in countries like Australia,
New Zealand, the United States and even
South Africa, it was difficult to integrate in
those countries displaced people originating
from Africa or Asia. In any case, most of these
refugees did not wish to be resettled perma¬
nently. They looked forward to the day when
they could return home.
In the twelve years you spent as UNHigh
Commissionerfor Refugees, did you see any
major changes in the situation of refugees
worldwide?
Yes. First of all, the problem of European
refugees was virtually solved, except for cer¬
tain specific cases such as Polish emigration
to the Scandinavian countries or the case of
the Baltic countries today. In the Third World,
on the other hand, we had to face massive exo¬
duses. In the 1950s in Europe, there were
between 200,000 and 300,000 refugees to be
helped. In 1971, in Bangladesh alone, there
were 10 million overnight! And they were not
the only ones. Hundreds of thousands of
refugees from the Sudan, Mozambique,
Angola, Guinea-Bissau and Viet Nam, were
waiting to go home.
At present, my successors at the head of
UNHCR are faced with another problem:
that of the refugees who quit their country
and find themselves in camps which they
cannot leave on the borders of Cambodia and
Thailand, in Hong Kong or El Salvador. They
can neither return to their own countries nor
go to another. They cannot be integrated, for
political, economic or ethnic reasons, either
because they do not want to stay in the host
country or because the latter refuses to have
them. It is a terrible problem.
There is also a new category of refugees
which I will call "ecological" refugees. They
leave regions in which they can no longer sur¬
vive, because the food resources are exhausted,
the desert is advancing inexorably, and they
can no longer even find enough firewood to
cook their food. And so they leave. They are
not stopped by frontiers. In many cases they
cannot return for political reasons.
So you decided to do something about this
problem yourself...
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Afghan refugee camp In Dobha, Pakistan.
I have always been in favour of individual
initiatives. I also take a very close interest in
the environment, animals, plants, disappearing
species....And so I set up the Bellerive Foun¬
dation, which takes its name from that of the
Geneva commune where I live. It is a non¬
governmental organization (NGO) which
finances a certain number of studies and activi¬
ties in collaboration with international insti¬
tutions, British and Scandinavian bilateral aid
organizations, and other NGOs such as the
World Wide Fund for Nature.
Initially we were very closely involved,
along with UNICEF, the United Nations
Children's Fund, in the struggle against
deforestation. But we wanted above all to be
present in the field and to do things at the local
level. Rural populations in the Third World
suffer far less from the oil crisis than from a
very serious firewood shortage. With the help
of Swiss specialists we have developed cooking
stoves which use very little fuel, and use
renewable energy sources such as methane and
biogas. We have used these stoves to equip
communities, the armed forces, police stations,
schools, bush hospitals and many rural African
families. These low-priced stoves are today so
highly appreciated that we can no longer
satisfy the demand, notably in Kenya.
Our programmes are extremely decentral¬
ized, we have regional offices. The main one
is in Nairobideforestation has wreaked
havoc in Kenya, whose demographic growth
rate is one of the highest in the world. The
population doubles every seventeen years!
We are also interested in the risks from
nuclear energy. We are a many-sided group
whose members include scientists, churchmen,
university teachers and senior international
civil servants. We organize conferences and
inform the public about the possible different
options in this field. We are also helping to
strengthen the Treaty on' the Non-
proliferation of Nuclear Weapons.
Finally, we are helping to defend certain
threatened species such as the elephant, which
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
UNHCR has helped thousands of Namlblan
refugees to return to their homeland. Below, a
refugee group about to leave Lubango airport
(Angola), June 1989.
has almost been exterminated by ivory
poaching.
Is collaboration increasing between the
institutions ofthe UnitedNations system and
non-governmental organizations, which are
more flexible and closer to people?
Certainly. I noted this in Afghanistan, for
example, at a time when the UN could not
enter the country and when a number of
NGOs managed to operate there.
I have worked hard to bring together
NGOs and UN agencies, and I am happy to
see my efforts bearing fruit. Of course there
are still certain suspicions. The NGOs fear the
bureaucratic weight and political pressures to
which international organizations may be sub¬
jected. The international organizations, for
their part, fear the sometimes anti-
governmental inclinations of the NGOs.
Can any lesson be learned at this stagefrom
the co-operation between intergovernmental
institutions and NGOs?
When major infrastructure work such as
airport, dam or road construction is not
involved, the approach of the NGOs, which
intervene at grassroots level, is certainly prefer¬
able in development projects.
The success of any development project
is based on encouraging people to shoulder
their own responsibilities and become aware
of their own capacities, their rights too, rather
than providing them with ready-made solu¬
tions. Who knows better than a peasant
farmer the agricultural conditions in his
country or region? It is not always necessary
to send an FAO expert to tell him what crops
to grow or what seeds to use. Give him the
seeds he asks for, and he will do the rest. Don't
tell him how to renovate his irrigation system:
give him the necessary equipment and he will
do the job far better than us. He will know
how to make use of local raw materials. The
international expert will turn up with plastic
piping and reinforced concrete in a situation
where it is better to use beaten earth. As if
one could ask UNESCO experts to teach
Afghans how to weave carpets!
Let us show great humility towards the
peoples we wish to help, for we have very little
to teach them. I think we go wrong when we
insist, as some have done since 1945, on using
experts who are paid Western salaries, drive
beautiful cars and live in air-conditioned
houses to teach people in the Third World
how to improve their living conditions.
So what is the point of international aid?
It helps the experts themselves! Multilateral
aid should be continued all the same, for it is
impossible to remain unaffected by extreme
poverty. But to be effective, this aid should
enable the victims of poverty to achieve a cer
tain form of self-sufficiency, however modest. :
It is better to concentrate on less ambitious
projects in rural areas than to pursue, for
example, the mindless policy of industrializing
at all costs in countries where such a course
is impossible, in order to obtain currency with
which to buy imported mineral water and
Camembert!
Those responsible should be induced to
change their approachthere should be a kind
of peaceful revolution. Here I think that we
are starting to learn the lessons from natural
catastrophes provoked by man, such as
deforestation and drought. Of course the pes¬
simists will say that in any case the planet is
ruined, but there are also optimists who
believe that it is still possible to influence the
course of events.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
m
II
I
EDITORIAL
In the games of children and the pastimes of adults
alike, the capacity for play, for following one's fancy
with no thought of immediate gain, is central to the
human experience. Biologists and ethologists have
demonstrated that play, which is closely bound up
with the urge to explore and to satisfy one's curiosi¬
ty, is a springboard for learning and discovery among
human beings and indeed all the higher animals. Many
philosophers think that humankind is too pragmatic
and serious by half and that if we want to go back
to a more authentic, freer and more worthwhile form
of existence, we must rediscover the instinct for play.
ft is already common practice in industry, finance,
the armed forces and research to use simulation
games to understand complex situations and engage
in decision-making. Play is now even coming to be
regarded in some quarters as the method of commu¬
nication of the future. But at school, which has so
strong an influence on every society, has there always
been enough concern to preserve the role of play in
children's education?
The amount of importance attached to spontane¬
ous play can tell us much about the basic features
of a culture. In industrialized societies, for example,
playin the guise of sports, show business or toys-
is often at the mercy of the profit motive, with the
result that there is a gulf between paid profession¬
als and paying spectators, whose role is a passive
one.
Other societies have at times been more success¬
ful in preserving the innocence of play and have main¬
tained a judicious balance between play and more
serious matters. But how long can this last? If, as
some people think, the human species as we know
it could not have evolved without the spirit of play,
is it not essential to preserve or rekindle that spirit?
Today some people are trying to do this by seeking
to revive traditional games and sports.
History is full of games that are now shrouded
in mystery. Our future will depend on our ability to
create not only new techniques, but also new societies
and cultures; on our ability, in a word, to continue
playing freely.
Children's Games (1S60), a painting by Pleter Bruegel, the Elder.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
"All animals play, but
man is one of the few
species that carries its
youthful capacity for
play into adult life"
MrMMBHr^raM*
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
An appetite for living
by
"Man is only truly man when he is playing"
FRIEDRICH VON SCHILLER
MARTINE MAURIRAS-BOUSQUET,
a staff member of UNESCO's
Education Sector, is a
psychosociologist who has
taught in the Lao People's
Democratic Republic, in Côte
d'Ivoire and at the University
of Paris. Co-author of The
Child and Play (UNESCO, 1979)
and author of Théorie et
pratique ludiques (Paris, 1984),
she has also written many
articles on the applications of
play to communication and
training.
W' HEN placed in a maze, a well-fed rat with no
particular caufe for anxiety will start to explore
its new surroundings out of curiosity and a desire
to play. By doing so, it seems to become familiar
with the layout of the maze. If food is then put
in the maze and the rat is returned to it unfed,
it will soon find its way to the foodfar more
quickly at any rate than another rat which has
not previously played in the maze and has thus
had no opportunity to find out its plan.
The impulse to play which can also be called
the curiosity or exploration impulse, since for
ethologists (students of animal behaviour) the three
expressions are pretty well interchangeablegives
species and individuals an obvious advantage in
the process of natural selection. The individual
who is in the habit of gratuitously exploring his or
her environment will have many more opportu¬
nities to acquire knowledge and will consequently
be better prepared to face unexpected situations.
The most playful species are
the most adaptable
To some extent all animals play, explore and
move around to no apparent purpose. But only
a few species retain in adult life their youthful
capacity for play. They include certain birds such
as crows, rodents, the higher carnivores and pri¬
mates and, of course, man. The species with the
greatest aptitude for play are also the most "cos¬
mopolitan", in the sense that they have proved
able to adapt to very different climates and have
thereby improved their chances of survival.
What is true in biology is also true in socie¬
ties and cultures. In order to subsist in a specific
territory a society needs a considerable capacity
for hard work, organizing power and determi
nation to pursue its own interests. But these
serious qualitiesor faultsare not enough to
guarantee progress. Myths, social rituals and even
science are not based on seriousness but on play,
curiosity and gratuitous explorationfactors that
stimulate creativity and invention.
Some of the greatest scientistsone might
mention at random such names as Kepler,
Ampère, Darwin, Gauss, Pasteur, Maxwell,
Planck, Poincaré and Einsteinhave described
how, at the moment of discovery, they felt the
same pleasure and the same excitement that a
child feels when playing.1 If the research to
which these men made such notable contribu¬
tions is the basis of modern technology then we
must admit the truth of an idea that at first may
seem paradoxicalthat progress, like culture, is
born in play.
We are not of course talking about games
such as bridge or football. The problem is largely
semantic. The English language uses two words,
game and play, to denote concepts that in French,
German, Spanish and many other languages are
designated by a single word. This leads to end¬
less confusion. So before embarking on any dis¬
cussion of play we must agree that these two
words denote two very different things. "Games"
are social institutions that are the sediment of
play. Play itself is an existential attitude, a way
of approaching life which can be applied to every¬
thing but is not exclusively attached to anything
in particular.
Bridge, football, hide-and-seek, dice and
dancing are games. But playing cards or dancing
do not automatically involve the specific
approach to life that is play, nor lead to the par¬
ticular pleasure which accompanies play.
Everyone knows that it is perfectly possible to 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A Japanese kite enthusiast.
Kite-flying has long been
popular In Asia, especially In
Japan where It was
traditionally a sport for
adults.
take part in a bridge tournament or to go dancing
and be bored stiff. No institutionalized game is
ipso facto playful.
In contrast, a number of activities which are
not usually considered to be games may be
playful experiences. Travelling, conversation, the
creation or appreciation of a work of art, getting
to know another person, going for a stroll, even
work, can all be experienced from time to time
as play.
If we think back to childhood, we find that
our most vivid memories of the excitement of
play often have nothing to do with games as such,
but with intensely-felt moments linked to fortui¬
tous experiences such as exploring a house,
walking in a strange district, or discovering the
world of nature.
From Martin Heidegger to Georges Bataille,
from Johan Huizinga to Roger Caillois, from
14
Konrad Lorenz to Gregory Bateson, some of the
most eminent thinkers of our time have been
keenly interested in the phenomenon of play. A
fairly clear idea has gradually emerged in contem¬
porary thought as to the place of play in human
experience and in the overall world-picture.
Today most philosophers, anthropologists and
ethologists would agree on a definition of play
as an activity which is its own justification and
exists in its own right.
The more play is authenticas in the case of
an absorbing children's gamethe more the
player feels freed from contingencies of all kinds.
Play is totally gratuitous and, as the German
philosopher Eugen Fink has remarked, it is an
"oasis of happiness" in the desert of so-called
"serious" life.
Taking life as it comes
To play is, for a moment in time, not to ask life
to be anything but what it is, nor to have any
purpose other than itself.
Play is desire for that with which one plays,
not desire for something which one lacks and
feels one must obtain. It is desire for the here and
now, for the passing and the coming moment.
In other words, play is pure appetite for living,
not for this or that type of life made desirable
by fashion or habit, but for things as they are,
for life as it is.
Take the example of modern tourism. More
often than not tourists set themselves precise
targets. They want to visit outstanding sites and
monuments which, so they have been told, are
particularly beautiful. They are looking for curi¬
osities and a change of scene in the picturesque
and the exotic. What is supposed to be a pleasure
trip is actually subject to a number of imperatives.
It is an extremely serious unpaid activity, a kind
of holiday task.
Adventurous travellers do not plan every¬
thing. They go where their whim takes them.
They are not collecting souvenirs as lepidopterists
collect butterflies, but looking for an opportu¬
nity for self-renewal.
"Serious" desire is a desire for something that
one lacks. It is almost like an addict's desire for
a drug, a desire which is bound to lead to
suffering. It is a desire for something one does
not possess, a desire to consume. In our civiliza¬
tion it often focuses on a commodity (in the
widest sense of the term) and is therefore depen¬
dent on money. In contrast, desire linked to play
finds its satisfaction within itself and asks for
nothing from outside. It makes desirable
whatever it turns to. One might say that it creates
the desirability of its object.2
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Play, the enemy of materialism
The essentially materialistic civilization in which
we live today is dominated by desire for what is
lacking. It is focused on progress, which means
in effect on the continual invention of new needs.
For our civilization play is the enemy. It is
defined in negative terms as something that is not
serious. Play is thus marginalized in theory and
in practice. To neutralize it even further, it must
be restricted to exceptional occasions (celebra¬
tions) and to clearly defined activities (games).
Many authors agree with the American
anthropologist Marshall David Sahlins3 in
thinking that play has been continuously mar¬
ginalized and diverted to other ends ever since
neolithic times. Today games have a new market
value. With cinema, television, books, magazines,
records, sports and tourism, games of all kinds
may constitute the most important industry in
the industrially developed countries. But play is
not necessarily involved in these commodity-
games which present play as something that can
be bought and thus tend to exclude it. The
amount of genuine play diminishes as the number
of manufactured games proliferates.
The current fashion for educational games
An old Eskimo plays cat's
cradle and tells a story to a
rapt young listener. The trouble with our attitude to
play is that we necessarily refer to
very different realities by the same
name.... These pastimes, this golfing
and bowling and these package
tours, these soggy writings and
anaemic philosophies are the
measure of an immense abdication,
the reflection of this sad humanity
which has preferred work to death....
First ofall, the principle of the new
world must be affirmed: that which
is useful rules supreme and play is
only tolerated if it is of use.
Georges Bataille
from Critique No. 51-52, August-September 1951.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
and toys is a good example of this. The very con¬
cept of an educational toy is in many ways ques¬
tionable. It is true that children, like adults, can
learn, create and discover a new universe in the
free-ranging mental activity that is play. But this
does not mean that the uses of play in education
are boundless. An educational game, like any
other kind of game, does not automatically lead
to play. It all depends on the inclinations of the
person who is being induced to play.
Can play be taught?
So we either teach children or let them play
freely. But we cannot simultaneously let them
play freely and teach them multiplication tables,
the alphabet or the principles of hygiene. All
attempts to instruct, indoctrinate or inform by
means of play are doomed to failure because they
are contrary to the very nature of play. However,
the fact that play cannot teach ideas or values does
not mean that it cannot be educational. As we
said at the beginning of this articleand as St.
Augustine noted in the opening pages of his
Confessionsplay is eminently educational in that
it whets our curiosity about the world and about
life itself, and is the principle governing all dis¬
covery and all creation.
While it is a mistake to claim, as Montaigne
and Froebel did, that play can be a means of
It is clear that when birds and
higher mammals are at play, their
rapid succession of instinctive
behaviour patterns cannot derive
from the same sources as motivate
these patterns when the situation is
a serious one.... What is new in
exploratory behaviour is only that
the motivation is furnished by the
learning process itself, not by the
achievement of the final
consummatory state.
Konrad Lorenz
Behind the Mirror: A Search for a Natural History
of Human Knowledge,
translated by Ronald Taylor © Methuen & Co. Ltd., 1973.
"Our most vivid memories of
the excitement of play have
nothing to do with games as
such, but with Intensely-felt
moments."
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The birth and the development of
the universe is the playing ofa child
pushing pieces around a board.
Destiny is in the hands of a playing
child.
Heraclitus
Fragment 52.
Why does the child play to whom
Heraclitus attributes the Game of
the world? He plays because he
plays. The "because" disappears in
Play. Play has no "why". He plays
while playing.
Martin Heidegger
Der Satz vom Grund, 1957
instruction, it is extremely tempting to conceive
of education for playthe invention of ways of
developing or reawakening the capacity for play,
in adults as well as children. If there is something
that people today urgently need to learn, surely
it is how to use their leisure time.
What type of education could this be? Obvi¬
ously it would not, strictly speaking, involve
teaching. It is possible to tell other people about
play, but it is difficult to see how a playful attitude
could be instilled into them because such an atti¬
tude is essentially self-taught. Collective activities
should be strictly voluntary. There must be no
punishment, examinations, diplomas or financial
reward.
How can spontaneity and education be
reconciled? The French philosopher Mikel Louis
Dufrenne4 has shown that this question, which
Herbert Marcuse5 had already examined, was
central to the "cultural revolution" which shook
the student world in the 1960s and might well
occur again. Why wait for another student revolt
Koreans playing Paduk,
a variant of Go, a
popular board game In
the Far East.
before trying to introduce play into such fields as
aesthetics and philosophy, that have been unneces¬
sarily dominated by instruction? Play cannot
teach us about the history of literature, art or
philosophy or theories of sociology. On the other
hand, it is the best and perhaps even the only way
of introducing us to aesthetic pleasure and medi¬
tation, and, at a more modest level, teaching us
to question accepted ideas and opinions.
Initiation into aesthetic pleasure by means of
play would not be an attempt to form people's
tastes, to suggest what should or should not be
liked. It would aim to awaken their capacity to
find pleasure in beauty and help them to become
aware of this pleasure. Most important of all, it
would help them to extend this feeling of pleasure
to other objects of their choice, leaving aside any
value judgements. The aim of such an initiation
is clearly not to transmit academic or social skills,
but to encourage an aesthetic appreciation of the
world around usand this is, most definitely, a
game.
1. Arthur Koestler, The Act of
Creation, 1964.
2. J. Lacroix, Le désir et les
désirs, Paris, 1975.
3. Marshall David Sahlins,
Stone Age Economies, Aldine
Atherton, Chicago, 1972.
4. Mikel Louis Dufrenne, Art
et politique, Paris, 1974.
5. Herbert Marcuse, Eros and
Civilization, and
Counterrevolution and Revolt,
(1972). 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Between order and chaos
by Graciela Scheines
Like a game, society has rules. What happens when the players cheat?
'I
Left, the Queen's croquet
game: "the croquet balls were
live hedgehogs, and the
mallets live flamingoes, and
the soldiers had to double
themselves up and stand on
their hands and feet, to make
the arches". Illustration by
Gwynedd M. Hudson for a
1932 edition of Alice In
Wonderland.
don't think they play at all fairly, and they
all quarrel so dreadfully one can't hear oneself
speakand they don't seem to have any rules in
particular; at least, if there are, nobody attends
to them...."
The speaker is Alice, heroine of Lewis Car¬
roll's Alice in Wonderland, and she is describing
her confusion at a bizarre croquet game in which
all the normal rules have been abandoned. The
croquet ground is not the usual smooth lawn but
a wasteland of ridges and furrows. The hoops,
balls and mallets are all living creatures that liter¬
ally refuse to play the game. A bloodthirsty and
tyrannical Queen rules the proceedings by whim,
unilaterally deciding when play starts and finishes
and having the other players' heads cut off on the
slightest pretext. They too behave rather oddly,
fighting and insulting one another and playing
all at once without waiting their turn. Their fear
An institution operates partly like a
game, so that it too may be seen as
a game which had to be founded on
new principles and take the place of
an old game. This new game
responds to other needs, complies
with other norms and regulations,
calls for other virtues and aptitudes.
From this point of view, a
revolution can be said to represent a
change in the rules of the game.
Roger Caillots
Les jeux et les hommes © Gallimard, Paris, 1967.
of the Queen makes them suspicious and cruel
and encourages cheating. But then they are not
playing because they want to, but because they
have been ordered to do so.
Carroll's parody brilliantly illustrates the
links that bind play, power and society. Alice's
experience in the croquet game effectively lays
bare the irrational and sometimes dangerous
mechanisms of social life. Reading her account
of it, it is hard not to think of the game of
democracy, when it is disturbed by the arbitrary
decisions of a few unfair players who prevent
their adversaries from playing, treating them as
enemies rather than as equals worthy of respect.
The crazy hoops, balls and mallets are simply a
metaphor for bureaucratic institutions when they
impede decisions and projects undertaken in the
public interest.
In contrast with the Queen's croquet game,
any kind of genuine play seems to be a model
of conviviality and sociability, even including
those violently competitive games that worry
some teachers so much, for they too have an
educational function. From time immemorial
children in every country have played at samurai,
soldiers or cowboys and Indians, using sticks in
place of spears or rifles. Even if such games give
vent to aggressive instincts, they do not encourage
children to murder or promote a cult of violence.
On the contrary, playing at war serves a useful
purpose, even at the cost of occasional cuts or
bruises, for it prepares children for democratic
co-existence by teaching them to defend their
own beliefs without despising those of other
people. Always granted, of course, that the
players respect the rules, which set limits on the
degree of aggressiveness allowed and ensure
respect for adversaries.
When any social group turns its back on this
model, however, whether by forgetting it or
breaking its rules, the gates are opened for every
conceivable abuse of power. As soon as the rules
cease to apply equally to all citizens without dis¬
tinction, or when rivalry degenerates to the point
at which one group terrorizes another, then the 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
What is a game but an activity
which is originated by man, who
establishes its principles, and which
can have no consequences
inconsistent with those principles.
Once a man feels he is free and
wants to make use of his
freedom...his activity is coloured by
play: ...he himself sets value on his
acts and devises their rules, only
agreeing to pay according to the
rules which he himself has' set and
defined.
Jean-Paul Sartre
l'être et le néant © NRF, Paris, 1948.
whole concept of ordered and fair competition
disappears and the worst excesses become
possible.
There cannot be games without rules. The
act of playing involves creating order. The players
may make the rules up themselves or may choose
voluntarily and enjoyably to submit to existing
regulations, insofar as the order of the game both
hampers and encourages the freedom of the
player.
But the patterns of everyday life must be tem¬
porarily interrupted in order to create this order.
A kind of vacuum has to be created before play
can begin. That is why neither the Queen nor
her subjects can truly be said to be playing in
Alice's croquet game. Even in the game they are
still prisoners of the serious business of everyday
life, whose hierarchies, repressive order, punish¬
ments and fears they reproduce. The disorderli-
ness of life intrudes into the game and confuses
the players. The climate of terror that reigns in
Carroll's imaginary kingdom leaves no room for
the spirit of play because it leaves no place for
freedom.
It follows that there are two essential steps
in genuine play: a temporary relapse into chaos
followed by the creation of a new order. Chaos
and the void are not easy to accept, and this may
explain why old people and children are much Tug-of-war in Bangladesh.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
readier to play games than adults who are too tied
up with everyday responsibilities to abandon
their familiar routine.
Some people, however, never get beyond the
first step. For them, creating chaos is not a
preparatory stage but an end in itself which they
seek to perpetuate by systematic and purposeless
destruction. Chaos can be a necessary step on the
path to the founding of a new social order, but
if it goes on too long, the law of the jungle pre¬
vails and individuals become subject to the
despotic caprice of an autocrat or a ruling group.
Play requires a balance between order and
chaos, destruction and creation. If the balance is
upset, play ceases to be possible. On one side of
the coin, there are the forces that turn citizens
into mere cogs in a machine: fear of the unknown
or of a break with established ways, attachment
to a daily routine that leaves no room for freedom
or for change. On the other, the exaltation of
chaos and permanent destruction turns man into
a beast of prey and can only lead to violence and
absolutism.
The past forty years have been marked by
a growing infatuation with games, particularly
those invented by and for adults. We now have
games weekends, games courses, games mara¬
thons. There is also a growing market for busi¬
ness games aimed at decision-makers and
executives.
In such exercises, the materialism of the
modern world generally perverts the true spirit
of play. The game is no longer a gratuitous
activity indulged in for its own sake, but a
utilitarian pursuit aimed either, in the case of
work simulation, at preparing young people for
adult life and a career, or, in the role-playing type
of business game, at envisaging work scenarios
and practising decision-making with the aim of
improving commercial, political or diplomatic
acumen.
In these instances play is gradually being
deprived of its fundamental significance, not by
disequilibrium between the forces of chaos and
order but through the erosion of the line that
separates play from real life. When the only
reason for playing is to win (time, experience, or
money) then play ceases to be a pastime or leisure
activity. It is no longer the art of enjoying spare
time.
GRACIELA SCHEINES
¡s an Argentine philosopher and
writer with a special interest in
play and games. She has
organized many seminars on play
and literature and is the author of
several books In this field.
Gambling at
Las Vegas (USA).
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Doing what comes naturally
A child at play is the toy of nature
In a temple of Angkor
(Cambodia), children play with
coloured pebbles on a grid
pattern traced out on a flat
stone.
VJHILDREN reveal an instinct for freedom in
everything they do, but especially when they
play. Everyone knows how much they love to
play and how completely engrossed they become
in games. For them, playing is what life is all
about, and they give themselves up to it whole¬
heartedly. This is something adults find hard to
understand.
Children experience an immediate psycholog-
22
ical need which is expressed as "I want...", and
adults cannot always persuade them to suppress
it or at least to wait for a while. Children feel
the same kind of urge to play: "I want to
play.. ..let me go out to play!" A refusal will lead
to conflict. Children also protest when adults try
to get them to stop playing, even if only for a
moment, so difficult do they find it at such times
to give attention to anything else.
The need to play does not cease when children
go to school, but adults attempt to channel it
towards learning and homework. Parents know
only too well that they will never have to force
their children to play, although persuading them
to study is a daily chore. The time-honoured for¬
mula is, of course, "First do your homework, then
you can go and play!" This kind of bargain is
struck in virtually every family, but is it a good
thing?
There is no clear-cut answer to this question.
If children are subjected to authoritarian pressures
at school, then parents, unversed in the subtle¬
ties of child psychology, also have to use their
authority at home in order to influence them. But
the motivation to learn goes askew when children
study not to acquire knowledge and get ahead,
but to win the right to play, to engage in an
activity they prefer.
The impulse to play
In children the course of development is very
intense. Nature itself is expressed through them.
At any given moment, some function or other
becomes dominant, pushing the child towards a
form of activity that offers it the fullest scope.
The foremost of these activities is play.
Hence children have good reasons for
playing, which owe more to internal stimuli than
to the environment. It is not the ball that asks
the child to play with it, but the the child's inner
functions that are looking for something that will
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
It should be noted that the games
ofchildren are not games, and
must be judged as their most serious
acts.
From The Essays of Michel de Montaigne, translated by George
B. Ives © The Heritage Press. New York, 1946.
Whether he is keeping himself occupied
or amusing himself, it is all the same
to him; his games are his occupations,
he does not see any difference between
the two.
Jean-Jacques Rousseau
Emile ou l'éducation (1762), Gamier, Paris, 1961.
make it possible to satisfy an immediate develop¬
mental need.
The rules of the game
Children at play are free, even when there are rules
to be observed. Achild who does not abide by them
will soon be excluded by the other children: "Go
away", they'll say, "you're breaking the rules".
Children are thus free to choose whether or not to
play but, having joined in, they immediately lose
their freedom of action since they have to play
by the rules and not as they might have preferred.
In fact children are happy to comply with the
rules of a game and don't like to see them being
broken. They need rules and willingly submit to
them from the age of four or five. Their capaci¬
ties are pushed to the limit when they seek to
overcome the difficulties of a game. The tension
created gives the child a huge emotional pleasure
and is all part of the fun.
Game of skill (Afghanistan).
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
When the functions expressed through play
reach saturation point, they are switched off for
a while. Children stop playing and put aside their
toys. They stop as easily as they started. It is
usually a waste of time trying to persuade them
to continue. A moment ago they were fully
immersed in a game, now they're no longer
interested in it. Yet they may well go on directly
to another game or another kind of activity under
the influence of another set of functions.
When children want to play, the choice of
game is no small matter. They must choose the
game or toy themselves, and they will play until
the desire to do so has gone. An old and stub¬
born psychological theory has it that children
release surplus energy in the course of play. But
where do they find this surplus energy? And why
should it be released for no obvious reason? No,
24
The major error in wanting a child
to make an effort simply through
love of duty, simply through respect
for abstract discipline, is to forget
that the child is not a man, and for
him other values correspond to those
of the adult.... For the child, play is
work, the good, duty, the ideal of
life....
To ask of a child work based on
something other than play is to act
like a fool who shakes an apple tree
in springtime to get some apples:
instead ofgetting apples, by making
the flowers fall he denies himself the
fruits promised in autumn.
Edouard Claparède
Psychologie de l'enfant et pédagogie expérimentale ©
Delachaux et Niestlé, Neuchâtel, 1951.
nature does not create surplus energy, but just
what is needed to develop the functions which
will in turn sustain the individual's capacities for
work, creative endeavour and all the other activi¬
ties of adult life.
To forbid games and oppose the free expres¬
sion of the child's natural functions (and of his
or her potential abilities and skills) would be tan¬
tamount to interfering with the process of self-
realization, to opposing the play of nature itself.
Parents concerned about their child's progress
at school, or seeking to develop a special talent,
may succeed in excluding play from his or her
life. Is such a "far-sighted" policy conducive to
the formation of the child's personality and self-
fulfilment? The few known exceptions, such as
Mozart, whose father locked him in his room as
a child and made him study music for hours on
end, merely confirm the general rule. It will never
be known how many people have been irremedi¬
ably damaged through being thus prevented from
giving expression to the free play of nature during
their childhood.
A serious business
For children playing is not a way of shirking
difficulties or making things easier for themselves.
Adults should not assume that children play
games just for fun, as a means of avoiding
"serious" activities. We have all heard parents
complain: "All they think about is playing, they
never open a book, they don't want to learn any¬
thing!" Teachers sometimes complain to parents
that their children spend all their time playing
Below, miniature football in
Tombouctou (Mali).
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Top, Shanghai children mime
a fencing match with wooden
swords.
Above, children at play In
northern Russia.
SHALVA AMONASHVILI
is a Soviet pyschologist. The
author of a series of popular
works on child development,
he is an active member of the
Academy of Pedagogical
Sciences of the USSR and
Director-General of an
educational research
association.
in class, never listen, never do what they are told.
But all that parents can do to influence their chil¬
dren is tell them off, lay down the law or punish
them. It is open to question whether such
methods ever achieve anything from the educa¬
tional point of view.
Of course children should not be allowed to
spend all their time playing while adults stand by
waiting for them to have had enough. Yet it has
to be recognized that children have a natural
instinct to play and that is essential for their
balanced development that they do so.
Nature bequeaths to children not only abili¬
ties, skills and functions, but also a wise internal
"instructor" responsible for directing their
activity and their development. The fact is that
since man took his first steps a million years ago
until the present so-called civilized age, nature has
not entrusted, and will perhaps never be able to
entrust, human beings to the care of parents and
teachers alone. Adults responsible for bringing
up children need to understand the role of play
in development so that they can create the
material and spiritual conditions whereby the
natural abilities of children can be freely expressed
and they can find self-fulfilment.
If more adults knew how to play with chil¬
dren, all would be well. Unfortunately, children's
games tend to disturb us, distracting us from what
we are doing and demanding that we assume a
more active educational role. Children have an
innate curiosity for things and will not wait for
someone to come along and oblige them to learn.
They want to know everything, but for this they
need to have well-developed cognitive powers.
I always assess the educational process by the
extent to which it shapes the growing child's per¬
sonality. I am of course in favour of a humanist
education, a pedagogy of co-operation that can
be instrumental in moulding the personality. And
I have analysed the psychology of play in order
to identify those aspects crucial to the develop¬
ment of a child's internal functions: freedom to
choose an activity and scope for exercising the
will.
The pitfalls of education
through play
It is fashionable today to claim that play is the
chief means by which children learn. Perhaps this
is a reaction to authoritarian methods of teaching.
But we should be wary of the pitfalls of educa¬
tion through play, because the longer that chil¬
dren are kept from serious study, the more
difficult they will find it later on. The primary
goal of education should be to make serious
things interesting.
Play alone does not result in the full develop¬
ment of children. Allowing children freedom to
play does not mean that they should be cons¬
tantly entertained or their every whim gratified.
Admittedly, play serves as a foundation for the
development of individuals who are useful to
themselves and to society, but lessons should be
serious and it is their very seriousness that should
engross children. This kind of seriousness does
not thwart their desires, but forcing them to be
serious might do so.
In order to learn, children should have a
feeling of free choice and of self-respect. If this can
be achieved they will not have to be coaxed with
promises of games or amusements. A serious
approach, respectful of the developing personality,
will be most likely to engage their attention and
help them come to terms with the complex
problems of learning, morals and behaviour. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Smile, smile, smile
by Marsi Paribatra
In the Far East people always look on the bright side, even when life's no joke
SERENITY is one of the salient qualities of the
arts, religions and philosophies of the Far East.
Far more significantly, it is also characteristic of
the behaviour of people of all ages and social
classes as they face the trials and tribulations of
everyday life.
Visitors to Thailand often remark on the
smiling faces they see all around them. Air
hostesses, children in the streets, market traders,
wealthy businessmen everyone seems to be
smiling.
26
It can be irritating. How many European
visitors to Thailand feel exasperated when they
are smilingly informed that their car has broken
down, their flight has been cancelled or the hotel
where they are due to stay is booked up. They
think people are making fun of them, whereas
what the Thais are really trying to do is soften
the blow and get them to look on the bright side.
There is a large measure of conventional
courtesy in this smile. It is a mask. Yet how could
the Thai people keep smiling if the smile did not
reflect their true attitude to life? A visitor who
learns a few words of Thai is bound to notice that
a certain expression turns up over and over again
in conversation: maïpen araï... ("never mind").
This formula covers all life's minor troubles.
There's no need to get annoyed or fret over small
inconveniences, there's no point in turning life
into a drama. Maïpen araï. If people smile when
they announce the death of a loved one, it is not
through lack of feeling, but as if to say that what
has happened was inevitable, to spare others from
grieving and to avoid spoiling their enjoyment
of life. There's no need to make a fuss. Basically,
life is just a game.
This attitude, so characteristic of Thailand (in
the early twentieth century Siam was known as
the "land of smiles"), is found throughout the
Far East, from Sri Lanka to Laos and from Bali
to Japan. At the beginning of this century Laf¬
cadio Hearn, the writer who introduced Japanese
culture to the West, took Japanese nationality,
even wrote a short book about the Japanese smile.
Everything passes: youth, beauty, love, life,
happiness and unhappiness. Impermanence is the
backcloth to human existence and the great game
of the universe.
"In Far Eastern cultures the
art of living, and art itself, are
based on the subtle effects of
impermanence".
Above, cherry blossom time In
Okayama, Japan.
Left, a Japanese bonze
composes an Ikebana, a
flower arrangement with a
precise symbolic meaning.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
'.
ï " '
if *ß
'^'" ti? -
Xa
rm
wm
In Far Eastern cultures the art of living, and
art itself, are based on the subtle effects of imper¬
manence. Moments of happiness and beauty
should be enjoyed precisely because they are
fleeting, but people should not become too
attached to them. As a Japanese haiku poem says:
"The wave comes and goes/I wish to touch the
water/My sleeve is damp" (with tears, it is
implied). The poet thus suggests that those who
play with love may get hurt. The risk of suffering
a little or a lot is also part of the game.
Perhaps all aesthetic feelings are based on the
impermanence of things and lead to the
"desperate joyfulness" so typical, for example, of
Mozart's music. But this sense of impermanence
is nowhere so apparent and so systematic as in
the aesthetics of Zen Buddhism, whose influence
began to permeate Chinese and Japanese art in
the seventh century.
The cult of the passing impression was deeply
rooted among the wider population as well as
courtiers and intellectuals. Even today, at cherry
blossom time, thousands of young Japanese spend
the night in Tokyo and Kyoto parks watching
the first flowers unfold.
True play is only possible when too much
importance is not attached to the game. The
ability to achieve detachment, to divert one's
attention from oneself, is a source of wisdom and
a source of delight in play.
Detachment and play
If the East is compared with the West, in spite
of all the risks inherent in such sweeping gener¬
alizations, the stereotype of the Easterner as
someone who is less self-absorbed than the
Westerner is perhaps not entirely false. Outside
intellectual and cosmopolitan circles, it is quite
rare in the Far East to hear young people say that
they are trying to "fulfil themselves". The Budd¬
hist, for whom the self is an illusion, would not
dream of doing such a thing.
Of course the people of the Far East, like
people everywhere, assume all kinds of social
roles, but they never forget that they are only
roles. They probably act their parts with greater
aplomb because they know that they are artifi¬
cial. The less importance we attach to the reality
of the roles we impersonate, the readier we are 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
to accept the masks that etiquette prescribes
us to wear according to our sex, age or social
status.
Less self-centered than Europeans, the people
of the Far East do not draw a sharp distinction
between man and the rest of the world, particu¬
larly between man and animals. We consider that
we are different from other animals, but not to
the point of being separate from them. We are
not necessarily kinder to animals than Europeans,
in fact sometimes we may be even more cruel
than they are, but we are less distant, less haughty
and more "polite" to our fellow-creatures. To
A superficially miraculous
phenomenon is the invention ofplay
between members of contrasting
mammalian species. I have watched
this process in interaction between our
keeshond and our tame gibbon.... The
gibbon would come suddenly out of
the rafters of the porch roofand lightly
attack. The dog would give chase, the
gibbon would run away, and the
whole system would move from the
porch to our bedroom, which had a
ceiling instead of exposed rafters and
beams. Confined to the floor, the
retreating gibbon would turn on the
dog who would retreat, running out
onto the porch. The gibbon would then
go up into the roof, and the whole
sequence would start over again, to be
repeated many times and' evidently
enjoyed by both players....
To describe cross-species play as an
evolution of items of behaviour would
be incorrect because no new items of
behaviour are generated.... The dog is
still unchanged dog; the gibbon is still
gibbon...and yet, clearly something has
happened. Patterns of interaction have
been generated or discovered.
Gregory Bateson
Mind and Nature © 1979 by Gregory Bateson
Feeding time
in a Japanese park.
MARSI PARIBATRA
of Thailand has taught the
history of European art at
Chulalongkorn University,
Bangkok, and Far Eastern
culture at Complutense
University, Madrid. She has
published several books on
Western and Eastern art, in
Thai, French and Spanish, and
since 1961 has worked
exclusively as a painter.
realize this, one need only see how a child in a
Japanese park makes a little bow when feeding
bread to a deer.
Strict observance of the rituals of politeness
is the great parlour game of the Far East. The dis¬
tinguished anthropologist Gregory Bateson said
that play is the best form of communication
between different species such as dog and
monkey, man and dolphin, as well as the best
form of communication between people of
different generations, social classes and cultures.
When a child and a cat play together, the unity
of the universe, fragmented by human pride, is
renewed.
Thai people are by no means ascetic, but they
have in general assimilated the notion that life and
death, freedom and constraint, sadness and joy,
happiness and misfortune, go together and are
indissociable from each other. And so they take
life as it comes and enjoy the passing moment.
The Thai expression sanuk dee ("it's very
pleasant") is heard as frequently as maïpen araï
("never mind"), mentioned above. When some¬
thing pleasant happens, Thais will say sanuk dee
("that goes down nicely"); in adversity, maïpen
araï ("it's not so bad"). Aren't these the very prin¬
ciples of life as a game?
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
V-/REATED in Sweden, the United States and
Switzerland, the first toy libraries were institu¬
tions which lent out games and toys. Their coun¬
terparts in Latin America, known as ludotecas, are
something quite different in that their centre of
interest has shifted away from games and toys
towards the players, who are offered a range of
play activities.
In societies suffering from chronic economic
crisis, the creation of institutions for play may
seem like a luxury. In the name of this miscon¬
ception those children who most need to play are
often deprived of the opportunity to do so. With
its interaction between communication and cre¬
ative expression, freedom and self-discipline, play
is extremely valuable in child development and
in helping children to fully belong to their cul¬
ture and society.
Latin American ludotecas seek to do more than
fill the gaps in the formal education system. The
experience of the network of ludotecas extending
from Mexico to Tierra del Fuego which has been
set up under the auspices of the Federación Latino¬
americana de Ludotecas (FLALU), created in 1986
on the initiative of Argentina, Brazil, Colombia
and Uruguay, shows that they can also help to
solve some serious problems of the Third World,
such as dropping out of school, illiteracy, juvenile
delinquency and marginalization.
Making toys from scrap materials or using
local craft techniques, inventing disguises, games
of skill and competitions, discovering nature and
the environment, as well as introductory courses
in music, theatre and dance, are just a few of the
activities offered by these institutions which give
pride of place to imagination and initiative.
Most Latin American ludotecas are associated
with projects to combat marginalization. They
operate in conjunction with educators and socio-
cultural workers, but in most cases it is the com¬
munity associations that decide to set them up and
run them. Whether it forms part of an extracur¬
ricular education project, of the social develop¬
ment centre of a poor district, or of a children's
dispensary, each ludoteca has its own methods of
work and its own objectives. But they all have a
social and educational function, the idea being that
play will encourage the development of more cre¬
ative, self-reliant individuals, better equipped to
contribute to society.
One notable example is the ludoteca started in
the big top of a circus as part of an itinerant cul¬
tural programme in Brazil's mining district. The
creative and organizational abilities that both child
and adult participants discovered in themselves
thanks to the ludoteca led to the establishment of
an association to improve living conditions in the
neighbourhood.
RAIMUNDO DINELLO
is a Uruguayan professor of the
sociology of education. A
specialist in educational
guidance and training, and an
educational consultant with
several European and Latin
American universities, he has
written several works on his
speciality. 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Play and the sacred in Africa
by Barthélémy Comoe-Krou
30
IN 1817 Hegel wrote that "only man is capable
of being religious. An animal can no more be reli¬
gious than it can understand law or morality."
But, he added, where Africa is concerned, "What
we call religion, the state...none of that yet exists
for them.... In Africa all men are magicians". This
belief led the British ethnologists Edward Burnett
Tylor and James George Frazer to say that
"magic preceded religion",1 while the British
naturalist and prehistorian John Lubbock
declared that there were "races of men totally
lacking in religion".
It was demonstrated scientifically that "even
insects play",2 and at the same time it was said
that primitive peoples, including the Africans,
had no games.3 Lubbock did not know "any
children of savages who have played with a
rattle".4
However by around 1870 the law of the three
states or stages set forth by Auguste Comte in
1839 had been generally accepted. Comte held
that the evolution of human thought and
knowledge passes through three main stages: the
religious stage during which all phenomena are
explained by reference to supernatural agents, the
metaphysical stage, and the scientific stage. Tylor,
and after him Lewis Morgan, then set forth a law
of evolution by virtue of which societies
inevitably moved from savagery to barbarism,
and from barbarism to civilization. Savagery
naturally came to be associated with the religious
stage and civilization with the scientific stage.
Play and magic
As a result savages and primitive peoples suddenly
began to be considered more religious than civi¬
lized peoples. Their whole existence was suffused,
as it were, with religion. It was also discovered
that games did after all exist in these societies.
And since it continued to be held that primitive
peoples were incapable of invention, these games
were said to be derived from religious or magic
rites. Lubbock said that primitive peoples consi¬
dered the rattle to be a "sacred and mysterious
object."
In 1917, the Swedish anthropologist Yrjö
Hirn extended this thesis to all manifestations of
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Above, Bambara statuette
representing a female
ancestor figure (Mali).
Opposite page, a ritual white
wood statuette of the Ewe
people of Togo perpetuates
the memory of a dead twin
sister.
play by children in all societies. In 1938 the
French ethnologist Marcel Griaule used it in a
study of the games of the Dogon people in which
he wrote that "When adults are asked about the
significance of anthropomorphic statuettes with
religious or magical uses, they sometimes say that
the statuettes are children's dolls. Even at Yougo,
the sacred cliff-side city, a blacksmith...maintained
that he often carved them for children, but this
seems doubtful.... His claim is quite interesting
in itself, however, since it reveals the narrow gap
through which an object slips from religion to
play."5
Roger Caillois, another disciple of Hirn,
wrote in 1958 that "A number of games are based
on forgotten beliefs or reproduce the form but
not the content of rites no longer practised."6
He concluded that "A sense of play is essential
to culture but in history games and toys have
always been the residues of culture, misunder¬
stood survivals of bygone ways or borrowings
from foreign cultures which lose their meaning
when transposed, and never seem relevant to the
functioning of the society in which their presence
is recorded."7
Even in the nineteenth century there was
some hostility to the theses outlined above, but
its impact was limited. As far as I know, the
Taylor/Hirn theory was only refuted by Charles
Béart between 1950 and 1970 as part of what
might be called an epistemological purge. "What
more can be said," wrote Béart, "when we are
shown dressed, articulated dolls exactly like those
we know in the world's oldest hypogea?... Even
when the maidens of Attica fastened dolls to trees
at the festivals of Icaria, these were dolls and not
sacred statues. Antiquity no more confused a doll
with a statuette of Tanagra or a Mithraic ex-voto
than we would confuse a doll with a piece of
Sèvres porcelain or a plaster saint. In regions
where Christianity has lost much of its influence
and where many religious statuettes lie forgotten
in the attic, no little girl would ever dream of
using such a statuette as a doll... A little Dogon
girl would be no more likely to use as a doll a
statuette carved for the altar of her ancestors than
a little Parisian girl would do so with the plastic
statuette of the Virgin that once adorned her
grandmother's bedroom. Dolls inhabit their own
special world. There may be a temptation to link
this world to the sacred world, but there is no
historical justification for doing so."4
The creative impulse
In all human societies there are joke-words and
words that serve as prayers or blessings and
thus express the sacred. No-one could seriously
maintain that jokes are derived from words of
prayer. Yet this has been and still is done with
regard to play. Words, like all the material ele¬
ments used by a society, can be used for different
purposes. Wood can be used as firewood or to
make games, chairs and houses. It can also be
carved to make sacred statuettes representing
ancestors or spirits. These are different expres¬
sions of different ideas.
Like all ideas and thoughts, the sacred is made
manifest by physical expressionsa resonant flow
of words, pieces of vegetable or mineral matter,
living beings, people. These entities already
existed in nature in what might be called a neu¬
tral state before they were used to express the
sacred, themselves becoming sacred objects in the
process, or before being used in play, before
becoming toys or material for games. Sacred
objects and material for games are both products
of the human creative impulse. They are cultural
data that exist in society. What possible interre¬
lations could there possibly be between the social 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
"Dolls inhabit their own
special world. There may be a
temptation to link this world
to the sacred world, but there
Is no historical Justification for
doing so".
32
BARTHELEMY COMOE-KROU
of Côte d'Ivoire is director of a
play study programme at the
University of Abidjan. A former
Director of Cultural Heritage at
his country's Ministry of
Culture and Assistant Director
of the Ivorian Ethno-
sociological Institute, he is the
author of several studies on
culture and African games as
well as methodological guides
for students in higher
education.
expression of play and the social expression of
the sacred?
Play, outside of both
law and religion
If someone happens to break a leg during a chil¬
dren's or adolescents' game, people simply say:
"They were only playing", and the matter is
closed. There is no complaint or punishment. If
a boxer dies as a result of injuries received during
a match his opponent need not worry even
though he has in fact committed murder. What
happens if the sacred is involved?
In the villages of Africa children and teenagers
are not allowed to play violent or noisy games
in the main street. Such games are only allowed
in an area far from the dwellings which is offi¬
cially regarded as a playing field. If a woman
returning from the well with a jar on her head
ventures onto the playing field and is jostled so
that the jar falls to the ground and breaks, then
she is the one who will be blamed, since "he who
unrolls his mat on the public highway is more
guilty than he who tramples on it."
However, if a diviner wearing his emblems
of office sets foot on the field the adolescents will
stand aside to let him pass. If he is jostled, the
parents of the culprits will immediately go and
apologize and make the appropriate offerings to
ward off misfortune.
Sometimes a false diviner is unmasked. The
impostor is considered a liar, a cheat and a
blasphemer, and is publicly mocked. If, as often
happens, he is an outsider to the village, he will
be expelled from it. The children ridicule his
gestures, his dances, chants and utterances. Could
this be the "narrow gap" through which a piece
of behaviour "slips from religion to play"? Not
at all. The children are laughing at a liar, not
turning a religious act into a game. The false
diviner is not a religious man, he is a man who
has cheated at religion just as one can cheat at
games. The children would never dare to imitate
a real diviner. His "spirit" would hear their
chants and see their dances and would "fall upon
them" (put them into a trance), exposing them
to serious illness or even death.
A fetish is not a toy
Historians today unanimously accept that, long
before they came into contact with the
monotheistic religions, the peoples of black
Africa acknowledged the existence of an all-
powerful Supreme Being, who had created the
world and was morally pure and infinitely good.
Like African hospitality, to which it is directly
linked, the idea of a Supreme Being is unfor¬
tunately disappearing.
Out of respect, Africans will not address the
Supreme Being directly. They approach Him by
way of his subordinate spirits which may inhabit
natural elements such as mountains, forests and
rivers or via manufactured objects commonly
known as fetishes. If these fetishes are defined as
objects from which protection is expected, how
do they differ from the holy water, scapularies,
miraculous medals and relics to which Europeans
are so attached?
Whatever the truth of this, for Africans no
fetish is absolute. It can be "spoiled" and lose its
power. When the spirit has left it, the object is
no longer sacred and is discarded. Does this mean
that children can use it as a toy? Never! It is often
said that human beings are only afraid of what
they do not understand. Familiarity casts out fear.
When people knew that a good spirit dwelt in
an object and that they could expect protection
from it, they were at ease with the fetish. But
once the good spirit went away, whatever the
reason, there was no guarantee that a wicked
spirit had not taken up residence there.
A desacralized object can never return to the
neutral state which it possessed before it became
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
sacred. This is what Béart noted in the case of
the religious statuettes that lie forgotten in French
attics. Take the case of a priest who leaves the
priesthood or a nun who leaves her Order. People
are always whispering behind their backs: "He
used to be a priest, he's an unfrocked priest, she
used to be a nun..." Their religious life has left
indelible traces on them. This is the natural atti¬
tude of all human beingswhether primitive or
civilizedfaced with what is holy, even those
who claim they are no longer believers.
Although play and holiness both proceed
from the idea of divinity, they are mutually exclu¬
sive and can never be present together.
War games and peace games
Ethnologists have been led astray by constant
reference to Greco-Roman civilization as a model
for all other civilizations. Today we talk of chil¬
dren's games, athletic games and Olympic games.
But ancient Greek and Latin had no generic term
that covered all these meanings. Agon, from
which the verb agonizomai, meaning to fight,
combat or compete is derived, designates games
played in a stadium and exercises to prepare for
war that were closely linked to worship of a god
(Apollo at Delphi, Zeus at Olympia). The Latin
word ludi has a similar meaning. Agon and ludus
are the origin of modern sport, the different dis¬
ciplines of which are called games.
The French word jeu, which is derived not
from ludus but from jocusrevels, joking and
jestingis closer to the majority of African words
used to designate this phenomenon whose expres¬
sions have nothing to do with the sacred.
An old proverb says: "When the Moon rises
all Africa dances". In the past African children,
adolescents, young men and girls would dance
and play on days of rest and moonlit nights. This
intense and continuous exercise of play was the
reflexion of a social state. Those who took part
were well-fed, healthy and joyful, for this was a
time when even sub-Saharan Africa had enough
food. Another old proverb says: "If a child owns
a pool, we fish there for him, not for ourselves."
This principle acts as a guarantee of the social
peace which is a pre-condition of inner peace,
mutual confidence and the enjoyment of play.
We can thus conclude that, in African
society, and probably in all other societies too,
play is not derived from expressions of the sacred.
It would be more accurate to say that man's con¬
ception of divinity determines his overall
behaviour, of which play is only one element.
One might even say, "Tell me who your God
is and I will tell you who you are and what games
you play."
In a Senegalese village,
women make fun of men's
wrestling matches.
1. Robert H. Lowie, History of
Classical Ethnology.
2. Charles Darwin, The Descent
ofMan and Selection in
Relation to Sex.
3. Charles Béart, Jeux et jouets
de l'Ouest africain, Dakar,
IFAN 1955.
4. Charles Béart, "Histoire des
jeux" in Jeux et sports,
Encyclopédie de la Pléiade, vol.
XXIII, Paris, Gallimard, 1967.
5. Marcel Griaule, Jeux dogon,
Musée de l'Homme, Paris 1938.
6. Roger Caillois, Les jeux et les
hommes, Paris, Gallimard 1958.
7. Roger Caillois, "Nature et
jeux" in Jeux et sports,
Encyclopédie de la Pléiade, vol.
XXIII, Paris, Gallimard, 1967. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
by Jean d'Ormesson
Commercial and technological pressures are turning modem sport into a ruthlessly competitive industry
34
iJLT first sight games, sport and play seem so
similar as to be indistinguishable. People play
tennis, rugby and baseball. The loftiest expres¬
sion of competition in sport bears an illustrious
centuries-old name: the Olympic Games. Play is
a form of sport, and sport is a kind of play. But
on closer inspection the illusion of identity
between play and sport is soon shattered. Far
from being similar, they start to look like oppo-
sites. Play has something spontaneous and unor¬
ganized about it, whereas sport is governed by
rules. It is true that a game such as chess is also
codified by very strict rules; and that, conversely,
a sport such as walking has very few. The matter
becomes confusing. As so often, looking closely
at apparently simple, obvious ideas (which in fact
conceal a lurking element of linguistics and
philosophy) leads to mental confusion. But let us
try to be clear.
Play is so ancient that its origins are lost in
the earliest history of mankind. And it goes even
further back. Monkeys, cats, dolphinsmost
animals and their young ones play. Nobody is
going to maintain that animals engage in sports,
but it is obvious that they play. In a well-known
French ñ\m,.La Guerre du feu, we witness the
birth of laughter and speech in our most remote
forebears. Even in those distant times play
occupied an important place. Ontogeny repeats
phylogeny: i.e. the development of the individual
passes through the same stages as the development
of the species. From their earliest years children
play, alone or in groups, with things or with their
hands, without ever having had a single lesson.
They are not thinking of taking part in a sport,
developing their physique, competing with
others, or breaking records: but they play. People
in all cultures, latitudes and periods, however
serious their preoccupations and duties, will go
on playingtill their dying day. Indeed, it may be
that the loftier their functions the more important
play is for them. A head of state with his guard
of honour, his protocol and his personal style
perhaps does more playing than a tramp does.
All the world's a game,
with obscure rules
The multifarious activities we call play, appar¬
ently so simple yet actually so complex, have
interested philosophers, historians, psychologists,
sociologists and ethnologists. They have a bearing
on religion, war, science, technology, culture and
art. The whole world ends up looking rather like
a great big game, with obscure rules involving
every one of us.
Play is ubiquitous; and in one form or
another has probably been a feature of every suc¬
cessive civilization. Bull-running, still a feature of
Spanish culture, was practised in ancient Crete.
The ball games of the Aztecs, played on holy
pitches called tlatchi, combined the blood of their
defeated enemies and a highly-developed religious
symbolism. The famous buzkashi of the Afghans,
a kind of polo played with the carcass of a goat,
has inspired novels in many languages. Basque
pelota, Moroccan fantasia, Japanese martial arts,
aquatic processions such as those on the Grand
Canal at Venice, the famous palio at Siena, the
Carnival of Giants in Belgium and northern
Franceall these and many more are popular
regional manifestations of universal play.
UNESCO set out recently to preserve and make
known these valuable and varied features of
national identity. Like so many monuments in
Greece, Italy, Cambodia, India, China, Mexico
and elsewhere, they too are part of mankind's
cultural heritage.
Again, we cannot help being struck by the
enormous variety of games. Among the old
Above, javelin thrower
painted on a Greek drinking
cup (5th century BC).
Opposite page, a Chinese
gymnast at an international
tournament held at Corbeil
(France) in 1989.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
traditional types, some have to do with religion,
others with the collective memory, social dissent
and violence. Others again are obviously the fore¬
runners of sport. These are all group games,
imbued with history, religion and culture. But
then there are all the innumerable children's
games, card games, games of chance, chess, cha¬
rades, word games and helter-skelter. It is enough
to make one's head go round. To introduce a little
order into this medley, Roger Caillois, a French
sociologist who for many years held a post at
UNESCO, suggested a classification of games.
From competition to vertigo
Building on the foundations laid by Johan
Huizinga, Rector of the University of Leyden
between the wars and author of a seminal book
about games, Homo Ludens, published in 1938,
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
...Examined more closely,
however, the contrast between play
and seriousness proves to be neither
conclusive nor fixed. We can say:
play is non-seriousness. But apart
from the fact that this proposition
tells us nothing about the positive
qualities ofplay, it is
extraordinarily easy to refute.
...First and foremost, all play is a
voluntary activity. Play to order is
no longer play.
Johan Huizinga
Homo Ludens. A study of the play-element in culture
© Roy Publishers, 1950.
Caillois divided games into four main categories:
agon (the Greek word meaning competition); alea
(the Latin word for chance); mimicry; and ilinx
or vertigo. These main categories, according to
Caillois, were influenced to a greater or lesser
degree either by what Caillois called paidia (from
the Greek for childhood) or by what he called
ludus (Latin for play), that is, either by the
elemental force of improvisation and exhilaration
or by a taste for gratuitous regulated difficulty.
Sport obviously comes under the heading of
ludus (gratuitous regulation) rather than oípaidia
AGON ALEA
(competition) (chance)
MIMICRY ILINX
(vertigo)
PAIDIA
noise races
agitation wrestling
laughter etc.
nursery childish roundabouts
rhymes imitations swings
heads or tails
36
kites boxing betting
patience fencing roulette
crosswords football lottery
draughts
chess
LUDUS
(uncoordinated movement). Imitation plays little
part in sport: and chance certainly needs to be
kept out of it. Sport has a lot to do with vertigo,
and even more with competition: the ancient
Greeks taught us in the Olympic games that sport
is primarily competition, regulated as strictly as
possible.
Sport is born of play, in its infinite variety.
It satisfies the body's urge to surpass others, and
itself. Baron Pierre de Coubertin, who revived
the Olympic Games of ancient Greece, defined
it as going faster, further, higher and harder. It
is human to want to transcend others (and one¬
self) but in accordance with arbitrary rules. Thus
sport is a form of play, and also a peaceful imita¬
tion of war, and a set of moral standards into the
bargain.
Money invades sport
What is now happening is that under the
threefold influence of money, technology and
advertising, sport is being taken over by increas¬
ingly harsh and exclusive competition. Tech¬
nology is becoming more and more important
in what was once a matter of emulation between
amateurs. Money invaded sport in a big way some
years ago. Television, whilst helping to propagate
Right, buzkashl, a traditional
Afghan game played on
horseback.
Below, a football crowd In
Milan (Italy).
dressing up fairground
acting attractions
skiing
mountaineering I
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
and popularize sport, also serves to arouse pas¬
sions and turn games into shows. The chauvinism
involved in some football matches and tennis
tournaments, plus the atmosphere of violence sur¬
rounding some sporting occasions, means that
sport is no longer a game but a feverish ultra¬
modern industryand an industry dominated by
ruthless competition often involving huge finan¬
cial interests. When Baron de Coubertin revived
the Olympic Games, he naturally put the stress
on emulation, but he emphasized that what
matters is not winning but taking partthus
keeping them as games. Nowadays this aspect is
fast disappearing under the impact of big money,
the influence of advertising and the ruthless use
of high technology to defeat one's opponent.
Following the American historian and sociol¬
ogist E. Weber, who has carried out research into
traditional forms of play, Pierre Parlebas has
pointed out that with the advent of modern sport
traditional games have gradually disappeared. To
put it another way, the higher the stakes the less
important the game. The spontaneous and joyful
effervescence that Caillois called paidia is losing
ground to ludus, a system of arbitrary albeit con¬
stricting rules. Competition, which in games con¬
sisted of excelling oneself, now consists of setting
records and beating a rival who is often ridiculed
and even hated. The high stakes in modern sport
banish the fraternal and disinterested delight in
the game.
Sport is a fundamental activity in the modern
world, casting its spell over its many participants
and spectators. We must not allow it to be
swamped by money, debased by violence, or
cause hostility between nations, regions, cities and
clubs. It must remain exhilarating, pure, young
and dignified. It must become play once more.
UNESCO has done much, particularly in the
context of the World Decade for Cultural
Development (1988-1998), to propagate and
preserve traditional games. With active help from
the Intergovernmental Committee for Physical
Education and Sport and the International Fund
for the Development of Physical Education and
Sport (see page 38), it has also turned its atten¬
tion to the problems of sport that receives a very
high degree of media coverage and faces the threat
of violence. UNESCO has, for instance, stressed
the notion of fair play, the spirit of generosity
and impartiality in games played for their own
sake rather than to win. Instead of violence, the
appeal of financial gain at all costs, and
dehumanized technology, this means going back
to the idea of pleasure which is disappearing in the
harsh world of high technology, and to an ethic
in which an opponent is a human being to be
respected rather than an obstacle to be flattened. 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
A pelota player depicted In a
frieze from the ancient Maya
city of Chlchen Itza, Mexico.
38
JEAN D'ORMESSON,
French writer, is Secretary-
General of the International
Council for Philosophy and
Humanistic Studies and Editor
of the international journal of
human sciences, Diogenes. A
member of the French
Academy since 1973, he is the
author of many essays and
novels, a number of which
have been published in
English, including The Glory of
the Empire (New York, 1974)
and At God's Pleasure (New
York, 1977).
Sport must continue to combine enthusiasm and
regulation, exhilaration and effort, pleasure and
moral standards. It must remain a game in which
emulation is essentially a mark of harmony and
complicity.
Obviously not all games are sports. Poker,
the theatre, roulette, crossword puzzles and pun¬
ning hardly fall within the category. But all sports
must remain gamesgames calling for effort, per¬
sistence and courage, sometimes for heroism. The
great thing about sport is that physical pleasure
is transmogrified into moral standards. In a
freedom that accepts constraints, it makes rules
for itself in order the better to surpass itself. Vio¬
lence, cheating, self-interest and hatred are off¬
side. Sport is a matter of struggling, emulating,
competing and surpassing. It must also above all
be a matter of friendship, happiness and coming
to terms with oneself and othersfor it is above
all a game. Adultslike the children they once
wereshould play only to be happy. People only
ever play with their own kind. Sport, like play,
is a fraternity.
The International Fund
for the Development
of Physical Education
and Sport
(FIDEPS)
FIDEPS was set up in 1978 by UNESCO's General
Conference with the object of helping the most
disadvantaged of its Member States to implement
the International Charter of Physical Education
and Sport. According to the Charter, "Every
human being has a fundamental right of access
to physical education and sport, which are essen¬
tial for the full development of his personality (...)
Physical education and sport contribute to the
maintenance and improvement of health (and)
provide a wholesome leisure-time occupation (...)
At the community level, they enrich social rela¬
tions and develop fair play, which is essential not
only to sport itself but also to life in society".
In the industrialized countries between 80
and 85 per cent of children receive physical edu¬
cation at school, while in the developing coun¬
tries, where there are very few sports facilities
and personnel, almost the same proportion are
deprived of it. In Europe and North America there
is often one sportsground per 1,000 inhabitants,
whereas in many countries of Asia, Africa and
Latin America there are no more than a few dozen
poorly equipped sportsfields.
In so far as its resources allow, and thanks
to the contributions it receives from public and
private sources, FIDEPS helps countries and insti¬
tutions on request to train physical education
teachers and instructors and technical personnel,
to acquire basic facilities and equipment, to
organize sporting and cultural events and to pro¬
tect and develop traditional games and sports.
^/DEPS-
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
y tí í mi i
Sport and play
Have the critics of modern sport gone too far?
by Georges Magnane
MLodern sport has been criticized by many
writers who have expressed their disapproval of
those sporting activities that no longer contain
an element of play. They maintain that, whether
the element of play has been destroyed by too
serious an approach or has simply degenerated
into childishness, what is left is no longer a game
but what the Dutch historian Johan Huizinga
called its "grimace".
If competitive sport really did extinguish the
spirit of play, we should unhesitatingly suggest
that it be banned. But careful consideration sug¬
gests that training for sport, whatever the level,
does not deserve so severe a condemnation.
Even professional and amateur stars of such
particularly demanding sports as soccer, cycling
or boxing have not necessarily ceased to consider
themselves as people at play. One might even say
that those athletes who are the hardest on them¬
selves and approach their task with the zest of
an artist, only succeed if they keep the sense of
boundless freedom and audacity which alone can
produce the spark of geniusin artists we would
call it inspirationthat allows them to surpass
themselves. And that is precisely the attitude of
the adult or child who plays just for the fun of it.
Exceptional sporting achievementsrecords,
victories in international matches or the
Olympicsare to athletes what masterpieces are
to artists. The poet Guillaume Apollinaire once
wrote that "Artists are above all else men who
want to become inhuman". Adapting his for¬
mula, one might say that champions are men
trying to make themselves superhuman. In
attempting to achieve something extraordinary-
something that Huizinga, speaking of poetry,
described as "exorbitant"the champion is
demonstrating play's highest vocation, which is
to surmount human nature.
Never mind, then, if the faint-hearted or ill-
informed find training cruel or frightening. As
long as the athletes themselves fix the amount
of effort they put into it, they are free and can
be said to be playing....
Anyone who practises a competitive sport
voluntarily and conscientiously for a single
season has an opportunity to realize that training
has an element of play in it. However completely
athletes submit to the demands of their trainers,
they never forget that they have freely chosen
this apparent passivity. They know that they can
withdraw from the situation if they want to. But
the chances are that they won't. The humilia¬
tion of quitting would be too great, so a sense
of honour keeps them from giving in to dis¬
couragement or irritation.
Athletes thus voluntarily submit to an
apprenticeship that can justifiably be called work.
But it might just as accurately be described as
play, since it serves no useful purpose. It was not
the "serious" aspect of training that Huizinga
had in mind when he complained that the spirit
of play had virtually disappeared. He himself had
written, after all, that "Play can perfectly well
have a serious element". In fact it is only when
athletes lose their freedom that the element of
play disappears.
The French philosopher Alain (Emile
Chartier) defined the difference between work
and play thus: "If what matters is the action itself,
it is play; if the main thing is the purpose
achieved by the action, then it becomes work."
The entirely unproductive activity of the
sportsman or woman would be the best possible
illustration of his point, but the antithesis he
draws seems less than convincing.
Training is both a playful kind of work and
an industrious form of play. There is no clear
dividing line between work and play. Some
might argue that amateurs play whereas profes¬
sionals work, but that would be a gross oversim¬
plification. A few minutes' conversation with
Above, soccer on the beach, 120 km south of
Dakar (Senegal). 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
professional athletes is enough to show that their
attitudes are not necessarily different from those
of amateurs. Professionals only keep the quali¬
ties that have brought them success if they do
not lose the special kind of enthusiasm, akin to
a state of grace, which only exists in play.
Work becomes play if the worker does it for
its own sake, without considering the results.
When Aldous Huxley wrote "Work is fun, of
course", he was thinking of work which people
do willingly because it is the thing they do best.
He was talking about the work of a writer, which
he knew to be an end in itself. True writers put
pen to paper because they need to write, regard¬
less of whether they will get fabulous royalties
for their efforts or none at all. In the same way,
true sportsmen and sportswomen compete to
enjoy a sense of achievement, because the game
is their vocation.
So the distinction between amateur and
professional seems relatively unimportant, if not
actually a red herring. Instead of evaluating the
payments made to star players, we should exa¬
mine the conditions in which sports are practised.
When they take part in the sport they love, ath¬
letes give of their best without being paid. They
play for the sake of playing; and in so doing they
experience that sense of freedom and potential
that can transform people profoundly enough to
deserve the name of culture.
For sport, like any other form of play, is a
cultural activity. In Les jeux et les hommes, the
French thinker Roger Caillois recalls how when
he read Huizinga's book Homo Ludens, he began
to wonder whether "Everything might have
started with play". Although he goes on to reject
such an exclusive hypothesis, he still claims else¬
where in the book that "Culture and play are
consubstantial".
There is an obvious similarity between atti¬
tudes associated with play and attitudes associated
with culture. Both allow man to achieve spon¬
taneity. Never mind whether this spontaneity
is the result of a miracle or of long effort. The
discoveries of poets and scientists can be made
in either way, but the sublime moments of dis¬
covery are always accompanied by the burning
enthusiasm and the sense of doing something for
its own sake that characterize play.
Doubtless sport is not one of the major con¬
duits of culture. It is one of them, nevertheless,
and it is accessible to great numbers of people,
not just the tiny, gifted minority whose perfor¬
mances are celebrated as masterpieces. Those who
take part in sport at any level experience the same
emotions, the same moments of triumphant
freedom.
A love of accuracy and the search for balance
and control are essential preconditions for any
kind of cultural activity. Those who do not dis¬
cipline themselves firmly right from the start will
never travel far along the path of knowledge.
Spectators at sporting events want to know
every detail of the rules of the game they are
watching so that they miss nothing and under¬
stand everything that happens on the pitch. A
French factory worker explained his love of sport
in this way: "At least you're sure to see some¬
thing real. Everything happens before your
eyes."
Sporting events constitute a system of evalu¬
ation which is offered to the public. This explains
the extraordinary atmosphere on the terraces.
The cry of 100,000 spectators swelling up like
a sudden storm is the modern equivalent of the
catharsis the ancient Greeks expected from clas¬
sical drama. The sporting public is wildly
generous in its enthusiasms; it offers its applause
without reservations, because it has complete
confidence in what is happening on the pitch.
As the factory worker said, the spectator feels
he is taking part in something real....
Complaints about excessive publicity
accorded to some stars of sport, the persistence
of the old controversy about professionalism, the
disdain that many intellectuals still show for
physical exerciseall these factors suggest a
malaise, a feeling of guilt on the part of the
Tense moment in a basketball -
game at the Seoul Olympic
Games (Republic of Korea) In
1988.
community as it is forced to recognize the extent
of the social problems posed by sport. Everyone
seems to underestimate the importance of the ele¬
ment of play.
If sport loses touch with its origins and ceases
to be first and foremost a game, it may become
a kind of drug and stir up increasingly violent
emotions while also stripping them of all their
deeper significance.
Yet this malaise does not seem particularly
alarming. It is only a question of growing pains,
and if these sometimes seem to be catastrophic,
it is because the growth has been rapid, hasty and
disorganized. Modern sport is a colossal and
sometimes overwhelming phenomenon. For the
time being, however, the colossus is in pretty
good shape.
Encyclopédie de la Pléiade, vol. XXIII, Gallimard,
1967
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
WAR AND PEACE
The Madrid-based International
Institute of Mediterranean
Theatre is planning to stage a
series of plays on the theme
Mediterranean, Violence and
Peace, in order to illustrate the
treatment of war in the theatre.
Aeschylus's tragedy The
Persians, Aristophanes's comedy
The Peace, and an adaptation of
French novelist Marguerite
Yourcenar's Memoirs of Hadrian
ate among the works which will
be staged in France, Greece,
Italy and Spain between August
and November 1991.
FISHY ENGINEERING
Fish have become favourite
subjects for genetic engineering
because they lend themselves
to it more easily than mammals.
With a view to solving world
food problems, species have
been developed with a rapid
growth-rate or a high resistance
to heat, cold and disease. But
fears have been expressed that
a proliferation of new species of
fish, unless rigorously
controlled, may endanger the
equilibrium of aquatic
ecosystems.
THE SATELLITES OF
URANUS
In a study recently published in
the scientific journal Nature, two
astronomers from the University
of London report that Uranus
may have as many as 25 still
unobserved satellites or moons.
Their argument is based on
images of the rings of Uranus
taken by the interplanetary
probe Voyager 2 in 1986. The
sharp-edged structure of the
rings led them to deduce the
presence of these satellites,
estimated at some 20 km in
diameter, the gravitational force
of which would counteract the
tendency of the rings to spread.
...
HEALTHIER TREES
Scientists at the Aubonne Valley
Arboretum in Switzerland, which
seeks to save rare tree species
from extinction, have discovered
that sheets of a textured
polypropylene known as Plantex
laid around the base of trees
can protect them from weeds,
insects and plant diseases. The
material is porous and thus
allows air, water and fertilizer to
reach the roots.
WAR ON THE
SCREWWORM
A campaign in the Libyan Arab
Jamahiriya to eradicate the New
World screwworm Cochliomyia
hominivorax (literally, "devourer
of man"), a livestock pest which
recently arrived in the country,
has entered a decisive phase.
With technical and financial aid
from the United Nations
Development Programme
(UNDP), the Food and
Agriculture Organization of the
United Nations (FAO), the
International Atomic Energy
Agency (IAEA) and the
International Fund for
Agricultural Development (IFAD),
hundreds of millions of
laboratory-reared male
screwworm flies rendered sterile
through radiation have been
released into the Infested zones.
When these files mate with wild
females, the eggs fail to hatch
and the population soon dies
out. It is hoped that this
technique, which In the 1950s
was used to eliminate
screwworm from the USA, most
of Mexico and several Caribbean
islands, will yield rapid results
and stop the pest from
spreading to other countries.
SOLAR COOKING
A cooker which runs on solar
power has been developed by
American scientists. It consists
of a wooden box lined with
insulating material and fitted
with a glass door. Inside, a
metal plate covered with
aluminium foil captures the heat
of the sun. On a very sunny day,
the temperature in the cooker
can rise to over 150°C. In rural
areas of developing countries,
this type of apparatus could be
used to help reduce firewood
consumption and lower the
Incidence of respiratory and skin
infections caused by more
rudimentary cooking methods.
DANISH MUSEUM
OF SCIENCE
AND TECHNOLOGY
The Experimentarium, opened in
Copenhagen early this year, is a
museum where children and
adults alike can discover the
world of science and
technology. The largest
institution of its kind in Northern
Europe (4,000 m2), the
Experimentarium will not only
present exhibitions but also
encourage cultural and scientific
exchanges and entertaining,
hands-on learning.
THE ALHAMBRA LIONS
AT RISK
Gamma ray and ultrasonic
readings carried out over 2
years in the Court of the Lions
in the Alhambra, Granada
(Spain), by technicians from the
University of Seville, have
produced alarming data on the
condition of the columns and
the 12 white marble lions from
which the Court takes its name.
Experts are calling for urgent
restoration work to be carried
out on the Alhambra, which
features on UNESCO's World
Heritage List.
POLLUTED WATERS
The management of drinking
water reserves is becoming a
major ecological problem in
most Latin American countries.
For example, water from the
river Rocha, which runs through
the Bolivian city of
Cochabamba, cannot be used
for consumption or even
irrigation without prior
treatment. Uncontrolled
discharge of sewage and waste
water, environmental
degradation and scarce water
resources also plague the
Argentine capital of Buenos
Aires; while in Säo Paulo, Brazil,
the main source of water Is
becoming unfit for human
consumption as indiscriminate
dumping of sewage in the rivers
contaminates reservoirs.
MUSIC
FOR THE BLIND
Eleven countries of the
European Community were
represented at a Congress of
Braille Music Libraries held in
Amsterdam (Netherlands), last
January. The Congress decided
to compile an international
catalogue of the Braille music
scores published in the
participating countries.
HIGHER EDUCATION
CONFERENCE
UNESCO has organized an
international conference on new
roles for higher education, to be
held in Caracas (Venezuela) on 2
and 3 May 1991. The
conference, to be opened by the
Venezuelan President and the
Director-General of Unesco, will
be attended by a number of
Nobel Prizewinners and some
200 education experts from
Latin America and the
Caribbean, the United States,
Canada, Japan and Europe.
AN INDO-EUROPEAN
PROTOLANGUAGE?
The great Indo-European
linguistic family includes most
Indo-lranlan and European
languages. It was long thought
that these diverse languages all
grew from a single source a
people living in Central Europe
around 3000 BC. But, according
to two Soviet specialists, there
are certain linguistic clues
Indicating that long before this
period an Indo-European
protolanguage was spoken in
the southern Caucasus region.
Their hypothesis is supported by
the fact that in all Indo-
European languages there are
words for certain plants (beech,
oak) and animals (monkey,
leopard, lion) which did not exist
in 3000 BC in Northern Europe
but were widespread in the Near
East.
INFORMATICS
INTERNATIONAL
The International Colloquium on
Automata, Languages and
Programming (ICALP), which the
European Association for
Theoretical Computer Science
organizes annually in
conjunction with a European
university, will be held this year
(8 to 12 July) at the
Complutense University of
Madrid. The university will also
be the venue for the 12th
triennial World Computer
Congress In 1992 (7 to 11
September), organized by the
International Federation for
Information Processing.
IN BRIEF. . IN BRIEF. . . IN BRIEF. . .
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
The Dogon, Mdft people of the cliffs
by Caroline Haardt
Above, Dogon village at the
foot of the Bandlagara cliffs.
Wn
42
ITHIN the loop of the Niger River in Mali,
between the town of Mopti and the Burkina Faso
border, there is a place where steep cliffs at the edge
of an arid plateau dominate a sandy plain. Over 500
metres high in places, the escarpment is fissured with
deep ravines, where rain caught in the cracks of the
grey rock supports the growth of dense and varied
vegetation. This is the Land of the Dogon, whose
natural features alone would justify exceptional
measures of protection.
Against the rock face and on the scree slope
below, the Dogon have built villages which are
remarkable for their architecture and for the pro
foundly original culture of those who live in them,
described by the French ethnologist Marcel Griaule
as a "relic of a lost Africa". In 1989, an area of some
350,000 to 400,000 hectares along the Bandiagara
cliffs, including almost 250 traditional villages, was
placed on UNESCO's World Heritage List as a site
of outstanding natural and cultural importance.
The Dogon, who today number about 300,000,
are of Malinke (Mandingo) stock. Their ancestors
are thought to have fled from the Keita empire in
the fifteenth century and found refuge at the Ban¬
diagara cliffs, where they displaced another people,
the Tellern, who left behind abundant evidence of
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
their own cultural traditions in tombs set in caves
in the rock face.
Most of these caves can only be reached with
the aid of ropes and crampons. Some have been
explored in the past decade, and have revealed
interesting evidence of the highly developed tech¬
niques, especially for weaving, which had been
employed by the Tellern since the Iron Age.
On the cliffs themselves, aspects of Dogon ritual
and cosmogony are illustrated by cryptic signs and
paintings, the best-known of which adorn the
famous "Shelter of Masks", at the village of Songo
(fifteen kilometres from Bandiagara), which forms
part of the World Heritage site.
The Pale Fox, bringer of anarchy
According to Dogon cosmogony, from the union
of the supreme deity Amma and his creation, the
Earth, issued a being known as the Pale Fox. Unique
and imperfect, the Fox introduced the principle of
disorder into creation. It is associated with human
weakness and the anarchy inherent in the universe.
Amma also created Nommo, a hermaphroditic
creature who represents celestial harmony and is
linked symbolically to water and to fecundity. Then
Amma modelled a human couple from clay. They
gave birth to the eight ancestors of the Dogon,
whom Nommo taught to speak.
Every aspect of Dogon domestic, social and eco¬
nomic life is linked to this cosmogony. Villages are
designed in the image of the cosmos. Built on rock
in order to preserve scarce arable land, they are laid
out on a north-south axis in the form of a prone
human body, supposedly that of Nommo, the great
ancestor. The head is represented by the togu net
(literally, "big shelter"), a meeting-place reserved for
men. This open-sided structure is always the first
to be built in a new village. It consists of a platform
on which stand several rows of rough-hewn timber
pillars that support a roof of branches topped by
a thick mat of millet straw. The number of pillars
has symbolic significance. Decisions taken in the
togu m are solemn and irrevocable.
In each settlement there is also a large family
dwelling, or ginna, which is reserved for the spiritual
leader. Corresponding to Nommo's breast, this
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44
building has a raised living area reached by a ladder
carved from a tree trunk. The windowless facade
is decorated with eighty niches, representing the
eight original ancestors and their descendants. The
two doors are often carved with rows of male and
female figures which, like the niches, symbolize
earlier generations.
Ordinary homes, which are smaller and are
generally made of mud-brick, are grouped around
the ginna. They are built to a rectangular- design,
with flat-roofed rooms opening onto an inner court¬
yard. They are flanked by granaries with distinc¬
tive conical thatched roofs. These structures are used
for storing millet, seeds, rice, dried onions and var¬
ious other foodstuffs. Their narrow entrances are
protected by wooden doors, which are often carved
and secured by ornate locks.
Many of the granaries are circular, like the
houses at the edge of the village where menstruating
women are sequestered. The forge, and the homes
of members of various artisan castesblacksmiths,
wood and leather workers and griotsare also on
the outskirts. Those who farm the land are the
aristocrats of this patriarchal, agrarian society.
Almost all the villages, and certainly the oldest
ones, possess one or more shrines, whose walls are
decorated with totems or chessboard patterns. The
most venerated of these shrines, which are square
chambers in the rock containing altars, are protected
by the hogon, a spiritual leader who serves several
villages and who formerly dispensed justice and
presided over the council of elders that directed
public affairs. Today he still conducts major religious
ceremonies and transmits to posterity the people's
myths and beliefs.
A century and a half ago the influence of Islam
began to reach the Land of the Dogon from the
neighbouring Tukulor and Fulani (Peul) peoples,
nomadic pastoralists of the plain, and many of the
villages now have mosques. Whether modest or
imposing, the mosque is often built next to the
togu na, which even among the Islamicized Dogon
has kept the role of men's house and council
chamber.
Statues and masks:
a rich artistic heritage
Among the many different arts mastered by the
Dogon, the most sacred is weaving, held to be the
first art bestowed on humanity, at the same time
as speech. In fact the Dogon have a single word for
the two concepts, both of which are considered to
have a question-and-answer structure. Griaule sees
the act of weaving as a metaphor for culture itself:
the warp represents uncultivated land; the weft, life-
giving human activity.
But the aesthetic talents of the Dogon are prob¬
ably best illustrated by their sculpture, whose
primary purpose is ritualistic. Roughly carved or
highly elaborate figures represent ancestors or
mythical heroes. They are usually made by the vil¬
lage blacksmith, who also carves the wooden doors
and shutters, while his wife is responsible for making
pottery for ceremonial use.
Masks, associated with the spirits of the dead,
are used only in funeral rites or to mark the end
of a period of mourning, which may be celebrated
either by public dances and ceremonies or by secret
gatherings for initiates. The masks form part of a
costume made of fabric or plant fibres, complete
with trimmings and accessories. They may be
fashioned from wood, bark or braided fibres deco¬
rated with cowrie shells and painted designs, or
topped with high crests like the kanaga mask, whose
upper portion is shaped like a cross of Lorraine. Its
two branches represent the demiurge Amma
gesturing towards his creations, Earth and sky.
CAROLINE HAARDT, French journalist, was a staff
member of UNESCO's Division of Cultural
Heritage from 1983 to 1987. She is currently
preparing an exhibition as part of the UNESCO Silk
Roads project on the CroisièreJaune, a motor rally
from Beirut to Tibet held in 1931-1932.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
Above, sculptures
representing the ancestors
decorate the doorposts of
Dogon dwellings.
Middle photo this page,
typical Dogon rectangular
mud-brick houses and
granaries with conical roofs.
Top: a togu na, the men's
house where the elders meet
to take Important decisions.
The platform and the
supporting pillars are
decorated with symbols.
Top left, masked figures
enact a funeral rite. The
celebrant at right Is wearing a
kanaga mask topped with a
high crest In the shape of a
cross of Lorraine.
IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
A CULTURE IN DANGER
THE IMPACT
OF TOURISM
The greatest threat to the Dogon heritage
today is the gradual abandonment of the cliff
villages, a process accelerated by the drought
that has affected the Sahel region over the
past twenty years. Shortage of water, and the
hard labour involved in fetching it, have encou¬
raged many of the Dogon to settle on the plain.
Another threat is looming with the arrival
of large numbers of tourists. Some 5,000 visi¬
tors come to the Land of the Dogon every year.
Unless it is properly controlled, this influx may
lead to acculturation and social destabilization.
Art-dealers and souvenir-hunters are buying up
(often at ridiculously low prices) important
archaeological objects including ladders, locks
and carvings, thereby considerably impov¬
erishing the artistic heritage. Already a growing
number of masks are made for the tourist
trade. In addition, many cult objects and masks
are plundered. Once inaccessible, the cave
burial grounds are no longer safe from tomb-
robbers.
Every year the Land of the Dogon attracts
more and more tourists to Mali, one of the
world's poorest countries. In 1988 the govern¬
ment adopted a plan that took into account the
area's fragility as well as its spectacular beauty.
Measures have been taken to disperse tourist
facilities by installing small camp-sites and cul¬
tural information points on a marked itinerary
along the base of the cliffs. These facilities will
be able to receive some 10,000 visitors a year
while averting the problems that would arise
if they were sited too close to the villages. The
intention of the scheme is to minimize culture
shock while making known the villages of the
plain.
PRESERVING
THE ARCHITECTURE
Safeguarding the building techniques dis¬
played in the cliff villages, a living heritage
transmitted by word of mouth, must be pri¬
marily a task for the Dogon themselves. But this
will be pointless if the villages are uninhabited,
and living conditions in them will have to
improve if the exodus is to be staunched. New
amenities such as wells, schools and dispen¬
saries must be provided without delay.
The legal and constitutional measures
aimed at protecting the Land of the Dogon
should be reinforced. Laws protecting Mali's
national heritage are already proving useful in
this respect. At the international level, the
country has made its position clear by ratifying
the Convention Concerning the Protection of
the World Cultural and Natural Heritage in
1977, and, ten years later, the Convention on
the Means of Prohibiting and Preventing the
Illicit Import, Export and Transfer of Ownership
of Cultural Property.
FURTHER READING
ON THE DOGON
M. Griaule. Conversations with Ogotemmeli:
Introduction to Dogon Religious Ideas, Galaxy
Books, Oxford University Press, 1976.
M. Griaule and G. Dieterlen. Le renard pâle
("The Pale Fox"), Le mythe cosmogonique, Vol.
1, Paris, 1965.
D. Roberts. Mali's Dogon People. National
Geographic, Vol. 178, No. 4, October 1990.
General History of Africa, Vols. I and II,
Heinemann/UNESCO, 1981.
Films
A number of films by Jean Rouch and Ger¬
maine Dieterlen.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
After stopping off in Thailand and Indonesia, the Fulk al-Salamah, the Ship of Peace which is carrying UNESCO's
Maritime Silk Roads expedition, approaches the coast of China, one of the highlights of its long voyage
The fahubm Und of Cathay by François-Bernard Huyghe
Above, the silk and ginger
trade, a miniature from a
15th-century version of The
Travels of Marco Polo.
Opposite page left, the
minaret of the Amin mosque
(19th century), Turfan,
Western China. This former
trading-post on the Silk Road
was the capital of the Uighur
In the 8th-9th centuries.
Opposite page right, 18th-
century watercolour showing
porcelain being packed before
shipment to Europe.
0,
46
'n 8 February 1991, the Fulk al-Salamah set
sail from Manila in the Philippines for the Chinese
ports of Guangzhou and Quanzhou, formerly
known as Canton and Zayton. Since leaving Oman
we have been retracing the legendary voyage of
Sindbad the Sailor, just as navigator Tim Severin did
ten years ago at the helm of the Sohar, a replica of
a traditional dhow fitted out by Sultan Qabus of
Oman.
At lunchtime on that day the captain took the
ship several miles off course in order to identify a
curious immobile blip that had appeared on the
radar screen. The blip turned out to be a junka
vessel one could well imagine in an eighteenth-
century painting. On board the craft, which was
shipping water, were eight fishermen who, we later
discovered, were from the Fujian region. One of the
Chinese academics taking part in the expedition was
drafted in as an interpreter. From the bridge of the
Fulk al-Salamah, he called out to the hapless sailors
through a loudhailer in their own dialect. We took
them aboard and they told us that they had been
blown 245 nautical miles off course and had been
adrift for two weeks. Their engine and radio had
broken down. They had had nothing to eat for five
days, and no water for three. Soon they would have
been too weak to bail out. When we arrived on the
scene four sharks were already circling around the
junk. An hour later, after being rescued, fed,
showered, shaved and interviewed, the sailors were
sleeping aboard our ship.
The next day we dropped them off at the port
of Canton, and then made our way to the mouth
of the Pearl River and the temple of the god of
Nanhai, the South China Sea, who has protected
voyagers from the perils of the sea since the sixth
century. At the gate of the sanctuary is the statue
of a "foreigner", possibly Bodhidharma, who
introduced Great Vehicle Buddhism to China. When
we sailed from Quanzhou on 19 February we
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
devoted our last morning in China to another
divinity, thereby following the example of the for¬
eign sailors who asked the protection of Heaven
before embarking on their return journey. In the
palace of the celestial empire, our hosts prayed to
the wind and made a sacrifice to the sea-god, a rite
which had not been performed for 600 years.
Surrounded by a host of romantic and exqui¬
site things, how could we resist the fascination of
China?
Where the Silk Roads began
Everything seemed to have been leading up to this.
Throughout the voyage there had been constant
reminders of the fabulous country where the Silk
Roads began. Every museum contained objects
which, directly or indirectly, through Arab or Indian
intermediaries, the Middle Empire had despatched
to the then known world.
Ever since we had left Oman, we had discovered
traces of Zheng He, the admiral who at the begin¬
ning of the fifteenth century led a vast fleet to dis¬
play the power of the Ming dynasty. We had also
come across traces of the itinerant monks Faxian,
Xuanzang and Yjing who, between the fourth and
the seventh centuries, set out for India in search of
the purity of Buddhist doctrine.
Western travellers to China brought back tales
which had prepared us for all kinds of astonishing
things. Among their number were Ibn Battuta from
Tangiers, the Venetian Marco Polo, and many more
including the Arab merchant Soleyman whose
reminiscences inspired The relation of India and
IN ACTION
THE SILK ROADS
China (851). In Pratica della Mercator, a manual pub¬
lished in 1340, the Florentine merchant Francesco
Balduccio Pegolotti gave much judicious advice about
trading with China, where he had never set foot.
The Franciscan friars Joannes de Plano Carpini
and William of Rubruquis were commissioned, in
1245 and 1253 respectively by Pope Innocent IV and
St. Louis, to find out about the "Tartars" of whom
Europe was then so terrified. Giovanni di Monte
Corvino set out to convert the land of Cathay, then
under Mongolian domination. His fellow mis¬
sionary, Odoric of Pordenone, visited China around
13 16, and his writings provided the substance of the
fabulous traveller's guidebook generally known as
Mantkville's Travels.
As we continued our voyage, the presence of
China became increasingly strong. After leaving Sri
Lanka we found traces of ancient kingdoms which
at one time or another in their history paid tribute
to the Middle Empire and were included in the com¬
plex politicc-commercial system which was the basis
of Chinese power and wealth.
Brunei was one of these kingdoms. Before the
arrival of Magellan in 1521, next to nothing is
known of its history except through dynastic
chronicles. The very name of the sultanate may be
of Chinese origin. At least since the tenth century,
Brunei had paid tribute to China and traded with
the empire. As time went by and as the prosperity
of the sultanate, a great exporter of camphor, waxed
and waned, these links strengthened and weakened
by turns. But when Manajakelana, the first sover¬
eign of the present Brunei dynasty, came to power
at the beginning of the fifteenth century, he jour¬
neyed to Nankin where the emperor received him
warmly. This outward-looking diplomacy was neces¬
sary to Brunei, which depends entirely on maritime
traffic, and inaugurated a period of growing power
which lasted until the arrival of the Europeans.
Manajakelana was honoured by his protectors, and
died at Nankin where his tomb has been discovered.
As early as the ninth century, the Philippines
also entered the Chinese tribute system and the great
commercial network of the Silk Roads. Under the
Song (tenth-thirteenth centuries) and above all the
Yuan (1280-1368), the archipelago profited from its
strategic position and attracted the Chinese mer¬
chant fleet. But here European colonization played
a different role. In 1570 the Spaniards inaugurated
the transPacific route, and for three and a half cen¬
turies, Spanish vessels plied between Manila and
Acapulco, transporting Chinese products and
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
bringing silver from Mexico. Via Latin America this
itinerary led to Europe so that the Silk Roads girdled
the globe. The Hispanic world, whose cultural
presence is so strong in the Philippines, thus reached
China by different ways.
"The biggest port in the Universe"
It is impossible not to feel that you are approaching
the centre of the labyrinth as you sail towards
Canton and Zayton, the two ports which vied for
the title of capital of the Silk Roads. In the thirteenth
century Marco Polo wrote that the former was the
biggest city in the worldit was said to have a mil¬
lion inhabitants. He added that it was possible to
enjoy so many pleasures in Canton that a man might
think he was in paradise. A little later, Ibn Battuta
considered Zayton to be the biggest port in the
universe.
For centuries, under the Han dynasty (206
BC-220 AD), but above all under the Song and the
Yuan, and even under the Ming (1368-1644) and the
Qing (1644-1911) who were on occasion tempted
to prohibit trade, thousands of sailing ships followed
the itinerary which is being retraced by the Fulk al-
Salamah. 'They were laden with unguents and per¬
fumes, precious stones, spices, silver and ivory (not
forgetting the supposedly aphrodisiac rhinoceros
horn). Some of them sailed as far as the East African
coast, their holds laden with ceramics, silks and of
course satin (the word is derived from a deforma¬
tion of Zayton).
All the great trading cities we have sailed
through seem to be modelled on Canton and
Zayton, places where, more than elsewhere, trade
encouraged the meeting of cultures and the settle¬
ment of foreign minorities. Persians and Arabs,
whose communities Soleyman described in ninth-
century Canton, have doubtless left the most visible
traces.
At Chen Dai, near Quanzhou, we were wel¬
comed to the "village of the Hui". The 17,000
inhabitants, all of whom bear the patronymic Ding,
believe that a thirteenth-century Arab merchant is
their common ancestor, and claim their Islamic iden¬
tity. At Quanzhou, we were shown the tombs of
two of the four disciples of Muhammad who are
thought to have come to preach Islam in seventh-
century China.
Many other religions flourished in the Middle
Empire. Hinduism was brought to China by Tamil
merchants. Buddhism was also brought by mer¬
chants and has left many sanctuaries such as the
1,500-year-old temple of Guangxi in Canton, whose
monks offered us tea.
There is strong evidence of the presence of
Christianity in the thirteenth century, when Mon¬
golian tolerance enabled Giovanni di Monte Cor¬
vino, appointed archbishop of Beijing by Pope Cle-
48 ment V in 1307, to convert thousands of the dreaded
Virgin and Child In a procession at Malolos,
on the Island of Luzon (Philippines).
Tartars. At Zayton, the tombstones of bishop
Andrea Perugia, who died in 1332, and of other
Christians give some idea of the important Catholic
cemetery which archaeologists hope to find there.
Paradoxically, we never saw so many sanctuaries
nor breathed incense before the altars of so many
gods as we did in China, which is said to be attached
to atheistic materialism.
At Fangzhou, the Silk Roads team saw the
gigantic inscriptions dating from the Song dynasty
to the Qing dynasty, carved in the rock to "pray
for the wind". The return of the monsoon deter¬
mined the great annual voyage to the Indian Ocean.
With what religion was this wind-cult connected?
In another village, Su-Nei, we entered the last
known Manichaean convent and contemplated the
image of a solar divinity which popular belief
wrongly holds to be the Buddha. Some suggest that
Manichaeism may have been perpetuated into our
own day in this guise.
This syncretic doctrine which originated in Iran
incorporated elements of Zoroastrianism (which also
reached China), Buddhism and Christianity. It
reached China around the end of the seventh cen¬
tury, probably via the overland Silk Road. An
imperial edict of 732 declares that although this
religion is perverse, its followers should not be per
secuted. In due course Manichaeism became the
official religion of the Uighur of Turkestan until
they were crushed in 842 and their faith persecuted.
Other religions reached China by other routes,
such as Nestorianism, the heresy of bishop Nestor
who proclaimed the divine and human natures of
Christ and was condemned in 431 at the Council
of Ephesus. How did this abstract theological thesis
give rise to the religion which in 635 reached China,
where many Nestorian convents were founded and
where Nestorianism, after being proscribed in 845,
reappeared much later in the encourage of Genghis
Khan?
How can we explain the destiny of the Jews of
China, who lived in isolation from the Hebrew com¬
munity and whose existence the Jesuits rediscovered
in the sixteenth century?
One of the great mysteries of the Silk Roads is
how doctrines could survive the centuries and travel
for thousands of kilometres without changing. At
the same time, China and Europe lived in a state
of extreme mutual ignorance. In Rome, at the time
of the Yuan, it was believed that beyond Cathay
lay the Christian kingdom of Préster John, whose
troops would vanquish the Tartar hordes and deliver
Europe from their terrors.
FRANÇOIS-BERNARD HUYGHE, French writer
and journalist, is a former member of UNESCO's
Division of Cultural Heritage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
RECENT RECORDS
listening
FOLKLORE
&*r:
Haydée Alba.
Tango Argentin.
CD Ocora C 559091.
A superb rendering of tangos
and milongas, recorded with double
bassist Kicho Diaz and pianist
Osvaldo Berlinghieri, who once
accompanied the legendary Anibal
Troilo. The bandoneón player is José
Libertella. Haydée Alba has an
expressive voice, higher-pitched than
that of most tango singers. The
poetic lyrics conjure up the heady
and sometimes unsavoury
atmosphere of the Buenos Aires
slums: "Malena sings tangos like no-
one/ Putting her heart into each line/
The vulgar and the common/ Are
made fragrant by her voice/ For
Malena grieves/ With all the sorrow
of the bandoneón."
Malou.
CD Polydor 843 938-2.
Flamenco updated, with electric
guitar and percussion backing.
Malou, an excellent guitarist, has the
husky and passionate voice of the
Andalusian macho. The rumba, which
originated in Cuba, has for some
years been popular with the Gypsies.
If the rumbas in this collection are
rather weak rhythmically, the
bulerías, closer to Andalusian cante
y'ondo, are beautiful. A singer to look
out for.
JAZZ
Le cinéma muet par Martial Solal.
1990: Musique du film de Marcel
L'Herbier, Feu Mathlas Pascal,
1925.
("The Silent Cinema by Martial
Solal. 1990: Music from Marcel
L'Herbier's film Feu Mathias Pascal,
1925.")
CD Erato 2292-45504-2.
A master of harmony, the
French pianist Martial Solal here
improvises jazz at the frontiers of
contemporary music. Sometimes he
drifts into dreamy soliloquies,
sometimes, influenced by Art Tatum,
he lets the notes soar out in a
dazzling stream. The accent is more
on atmosphere than rhythm. A
collector's item for Solal fans.
Dave Valentin Live
at the Blue Note.
Valentin (flute), Bill O'Connell (piano),
Lincoln Goines (bass), Robert Ameen
(drums), Giovanni Hidalgo
(percussion).
CD GRP Records D-9568.
Dave Valentin is a young Puerto
Rican flautist from the South Bronx
whose career took off in the late
1970s. Accompanied here by Bill
O'Connell, former pianist with Mongo
Santamaría; Lincoln Goines, former
bassist with Tabia Maria; Robert
Ameen; and Giovanni Hidalgo,
currently with Dizzy Gillespie, he
offers a pleasant hybrid of Latin jazz.
There are particularly adroit versions
of Milton Nascimento's "Cinnamon
and Clove", Wayne Shorter's
"Footprints", and Santamaria's "Afro
Blues". Music for staying home and
dreaming of a tropical paradise.
POPULAR
Guidon!.
Aux tourniquets des grands cafés.
CD Musidisc 195582.
Typically French lyrics with a
caustic flavour reminiscent of the
early Juliette Greco. Jean Guidoni
sings of fleeting love, seedy cafés,
the brothels of Lisbon, to an
accompaniment that has echoes of
jazz and popular dance music. It's
easy to be carried away by Guidoni's
haunting, cracked voice and the
melancholy atmosphere.
Rachid Taha.
Barbes.
CD Nord Sud/Barclay 843 179-2.
Bilingual French-Arabic rock-rap
from the mysterious Taha, whose
voice is as rough as the boulders of
the Aurès mountains, far from the
monotonous rai that is often heard.
Hard rock recorded at Oran with a
cosmopolitan set of musicians-
Arabic, French and African proving
that Algerian popular music is
shaking off the rigid yoke of
tradition.
The Cure.
Mixed Up.
CD Fiction 847 099-2.
Disco rock from a British band
with simple but pleasant effects
from synthesizers. The group's
particular brand of humour comes
over in the titles of tracks such as
"Lullaby (extended mix)", "Close to
Me (closer mix)", "The Walk
(everything mix)", "A Forest (tree
mix)", Inbetween Days (shiver mix)",
etc., and in the quotation from Jules
Renard in the accompanying notes:
"Look for the ridiculous in everything
and you will find it."
Isabelle Leymarie M
Ethnomus/'co/og/st and journalist
CLASSICAL	
Hommage à
Paul Torteller.
Gabriel Fauré: Elegy Op. 24 - Two
Sonatas for cello and piano Op.
109-117. Claude Debussy: Sonata
for cello and piano.
Paul Tortelier/Jean Hubeau.
CD Erato 2292-45660-2.
Claude Debussy recommended
that "the pianist should never forget
not to fight the cello, but to
accompany it", thus advocating a
kind of fusion of the two
instruments, so evocative of a
corpus of French chamber music at
once post-Romantic and
Impressionist. Paul Tortelier, the
distinguished French cellist who died
recently, provides a marvellous
interpretation of these pieces. Nor
should we forget Jean Hubeau, a
remarkable pianist who is too little
known.
John McLaughlin.
Concerto for Orchestra and Guitar.
The Mediterranean.
London Symphony Orchestra
conducted by Michael Tilson
Thomas. Duos for guitar and piano,
Katia Labeque.
CD CBS MK 45578.
John McLaughlin introduces his
jazz guitar (he has played with such
great names of jazz as Chick Corea
and Miles Davis) into a new-style
classical world, thus helping to
perpetuate the breakdown of
divisions between musical categories
that was initiated by Stravinsky and
Ravel and continued by Gershwin
and Bernstein.
Claudia Muzlo.
Opera Arias and Songs
(Recordings from 1934-1935)
CD EMI Références, CDH 7697902.
Claudia Muzlo (Recordings from
1911, 1934 and 193S): CD Nimbus,
Prima Voce Collection, NI 7814.
The great Italian soprano
Claudia Muzio (1889-1936) can be
regarded as an immediate
predecessor of Maria Callas.
Nicknamed the "Divine", like Callas,
she created several new operatic
roles, worked with Toscanini, and
won fame in New York and Latin
America. Her lyricism, supported by
an extraordinary sense of theatre,
lives again in these remarkably well-
restored recordings, which are
valuable historical documents from
her extensive repertory, notably roles
of the school of verismo (Italian
opera dealing with "real-life"
subjects).
Russian music
Rlmsky-Korsakov.
Christmas Eve.
2 CDs LDC 288001-2.
Aleksandr Knaifel.
The Canterville Ghost.
CD LDC 288009.
Clurlionls.
Symphonic Poems, String Quartet.
CD LDC 288004.
A new record label. Saison
Russe, has recently been created in
the Soviet Union by the French
company Chant du Monde in
association with Harmonía Mundi. Its
first offering includes a rare
recording, conducted by
M. Yurovsky, of Rimsky-Korsakov's
opera Christmas Eve, which is based
on a story by Gogol. The same
conductor features on the second
disc. The Canterville Ghost, an opera
(after Oscar Wilde) by the avant-
garde Soviet composer Aleksandr
Knaifel which is undeniably
influenced by Shostakovich's The
Nose. The third disc features
Mikalojus K. Ciu/lionis (1875-1911),
founder of the Lithuanian National
School of Music, with narrative and
neo-Romantic pieces ("In the
Forest", "The Sea") followed by a
more complex string quartet.
Remembering
Leonard Bernstein
The Isaac Stern Collection.
Orchestra of the Air conducted by
Leonard Bernstein. Isaac Stern
(violin).
3 CDs Sony Classical SM3K 45956.
Guidon Kremer (violin),
Philharmonic Orchestra of Israel
conducted by Leonard Bernstein.
CD Deutsche Grammophon
423583-2.
Rodrigue Mllosl (violin),
Orchestra of Caen (France)
conducted by Jean-Louis Basset.
CD Adda 590033.
Leonard Bernstein, conductor,
pianist, composer and television
personality, died in October
1990.The great popular success of
West Side Story (1957) Invested the
reputation of his other work with a
certain ambiguity, but the ambitions
of the man who was sometimes
ironically called the "Offenbach of
Broadway" were not limited to light
music. His little-known "Serenade for
Violin and Orchestra", after Plato's
Symposium, was first performed in
1954 by Isaac Stern. In "The Isaac
Stern Collection" it is given an
intensely emotional Interpretation in
a recording made in 1957 with the
composer on the rostrum. The
"Phaedrus" and "Agathon"
sections are wonderfully poetic.
Of the other discs, Kremer's seems
the less committed, while
Milosi's clarity is attractive. Two
different ways of paying tribute
to a great man.
Claude dayman I A O
Journalist and music critic 'rü
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
50
BOOKS FOR BULGARIA
I teach English and French at a
foreign language school in the town
of Berkovitza. The French edition of
the UNESCO Courier, which my
students greatly enjoy reading, is
sent to me directly from your offices
in Paris, and I should also like to
subscribe to the English edition.
Unfortunately books and magazines
in languages other than German and
Russian are very hard to find in our
country, and my students, who have
twenty-two hours of English lessons
per week, do not even have
dictionaries. We should be very
grateful if you would allow us to
inform your readers that our school
is seeking new or second-hand
books and magazines in English.
Vladimir Gheorghiev
Preparatory English class
Dr. Ivan Panov School
3500 Berkovitza (Bulgaria)
AN INTERNATIONAL
CHARTER FOR
THE ENVIRONMENT
Although environmental questions
have been discussed in your
magazine on several occasions by
internationally known writers, none
of them has yet suggested that
there should be a United Nations
charter which would be comparable
to the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights and would provide a
philosophical, legal and moral basis
for handling such issues. A
document of this kind is today badly
needed.
André Michel
Saint-CIair-du-Rhône (France)
REASONS FOR LIVING
As the mother of five children and
the grandmother of thirteen, I should
like to see the UNESCO Courier help
young people to feel that life is
worth living. In L'appel du héros et
du saint, the French philosopher
Henri Bergson wrote of the
inspirational role played by
exceptional men and women whose
work and human qualities have
contributed to man's tortuous
journey towards universal fraternity.
Why not (as you once did in the
case of Gandhi and non-violence)
devote an issue from time to time to
figures such as Louis Pasteur, Marie
Curie, Nelson Mandela, Janusz
Korczak, and many others like them
from all continents and all
civilizations?
Young people today need to see
and hear something other than
praise of violence, money and
material success. They need to
discover the meaning of joy and
sustained effort and, as the French
writer Michel Serres said recently,
the necessity for a degree of
asceticism in order to do something
worthwhile and achieve fulfilment,
the source of true happiness.
M.A. Pleutln (France)
LITERACY IN LOW-RENT
HOUSING SCHEMES
On the "In brief..." page of your
January 1991 issue, I read that a
literacy prize has been awarded to
the Institute of the Brothers of the
Christian Schools. The Marists,
Lazarists and Carthusians of the
Lyons area of France provide an
excellent education, but to whom?
To middle-class children. My own
dream is that they should come and
teach in the low-rent housing
schemes of the suburbs.
Before moving closer to the centre
of Oullins, we lived for ten years
near to three high-rise blocks and
saw the poverty, despair and
illiteracy that was rife there. And yet
there was great human warmth. The
best part of my children's education
took place in that neighbourhood.
Marcelle Chalandon
Oullins (France)
ETHICS AND PROGRESS
I fear that the divorce between
human achievements in science, in
the arts and in other fields, and
mankind's lack of an ethical sense
will continue to be a feature of life
on earth. There are those who think
that we are progressing, and those,
including myself, who see history as
a kind of film with episodes in which
the dates, the décor and the actors
change, but not the patterns of
behaviour.
G. Négrln
Cloyes-sur-le-Loir (France)
THE FAMILY SPIRIT
I am taking the opportunity offered
by your reader survey (see the
UNESCO Courier, April 1991) to tell
you about my reaction on reading
Andrée Michel's article on the
European family which appeared in
your July 1989 issue on the family.
Families of the kind described in the
article certainly exist. But large,
balanced, solid families also exist
and nothing is ever said about them.
As the head of a closely-knit
household and the mother of five
children each of whom is married, I
feel that I do not count. What kind
of image does your magazine, which
is read throughout the world, wish to
give of the European family?
Mme de Buyer
Compiègne (France)
SEXISM
On reading your February 1990
issue, "The Art of Hospitality", I was
dismayed to find little or no female
authorship among the articles
presented. The article by Perla Petrich
may be a woman's contribution and
should have been acknowledged by
a "she" in the biographical note.
I have found a similar pattern in
some other recent issues. In
addition, women have seldom been
included in the subject matter. Last
September's issue of the American
magazine MS highlighted several
women who have been in the
forefront of recent political
developments in Eastern Europe.
Your "Winds of Freedom" issue
(June 1990) was less eclectic.
I have heard it said that the United
Nations, unexpectedly, offers a chilly
climate for women. While your list of
editors, many of whom are female,
would appear to negate that charge,
could the scarcity of female authors
in your columns possibly indicate
that articles by women are in short
supply. That seems unlikely,
considering the significant output of
scholarly and popular literature by
women in recent years. EMen Lee
Iowa City (USA)
AGAINST TOTALITARIANISM
For the last year you have quite
rightly been expressing delight about
the rediscovery of freedom in
Eastern Europe, but previously you
had kept quiet about a situation
which was nevertheless no more
acceptable than apartheid, against
which you fulminate.
Why keep quiet before the
powerful? Surely totalitarianism is
essentially the same everywhere.
B. Dominger
Nancy (France)
AN APPEAL FOR PEACE
An organization such as UNESCO
should increase human awareness of
the consequences of war. I should
welcome, for example, articles that
clearly explained subjects such as
the possible effects of
bacteriological warfare, the dangers
of local conflicts extending
worldwide, or the time it takes for
the passions and hatreds
engendered by war to cool down.
If every household in the world
displayed a peace-symbol on its door
on the same day, then for a few
hours at least humanity would be on
the same wavelength.
Let us hope that human
intelligence will prevail.
Sylvie Guyonvarc'h
Auray (France)
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, page 3 (right): © Roland and
Sabrina Michaud, Paris/Prince of
Wales Museum, Bombay. Back cover:
Marc Riboud © Magnum, Paris. Page
3 (left): Nick Rogers © The European,
Geneva. Page 4:
UNHCR/A.Hollmann. Page 5:
UNHCR, Geneva. Page 6: Bellerive
Foundation, Geneva. Page 7:
UNHCR/L. Taylor. Page 8
UNHCR/N. Van Praag. Page 9:
UNHCR/J. Crisp. Pages 10-11:
Nimetallah © Artephot, Paris. Page
12 (above): Waine Miller © Magnum,
Paris. Page 12 (below): ©Jacana,
Paris. Page 14: Marc S. Wexler
©Cosmos, Paris. Page 15: Burt
Glinn © Magnum, Paris. Page 16: A.
Moyse © FAO, Rome. Page 17:
© Roland and Sabrina Michaud, Paris.
Page 18: Mary Evans Picture Library
© Explorer, Paris. Page 20: E.
Kennedy © FAO, Rome. Page 21:
Harry Gruyaert © Magnum, Paris.
Pages 22, 25 and 47 (left): © Claude
Sauvageot, Paris. Page 23: Roland and
Sabrina Michaud © Rapho, Paris.
Page 24: Jean-Marie Lerat © Hoa-
Qui, Paris. Page 26: G. Aschendorf
© Vandystadt, Paris. Page 27: F. Le
Diascorn © Rapho, Paris. Page 28:
Dominique Buisson © Vandystadt,
Paris. Page 29: © Raimundo Dinello,
Montevideo. Page 30: Daniel Laine
© Hoa-Qui, Paris. Page 31: Georg
Gerster © Rapho, Paris. Page 32: Luc
Girard © Explorer, Paris. Page 33:
M. Renaudeau © Hoa-Qui, Paris.
Page 35 (above): Erich Lessing
© Magnum, Paris. Page 35 (below):
Gerard Vandystadt © Vandystadt,
Paris. Pages 36-37: Allsport/David
Cannon © Vandystadt, Paris. Page
37: Eve Arnold © Magnum, Paris.
Page 38: © Charles Lenars, Paris.
Page 39: Hervy © Explorer, Paris.
Page 40: Billy Stickland © Allsport/
Vandystadt, Paris. Page 42:
UNESCO/O. Konare. Page 43:
© Constance de Monbrison, Paris.
Pages 44, 44-45: S. Salgado
© Magnum, Paris. Page 45:
© Caroline Haardt, Paris. Pages 46
and 47 (right): © Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris. Page 48: Alain
Evrard © ANA, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
44th YEAR
Published monthly in 35 languages and In braille
by UNESCO, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévéque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbma
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, Carole Pajot-Font
(Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel.: 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Selection in Braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Biazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kessler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88),
Assistant: Mane-Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Mane-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diaktté. Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo. Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Dm.
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk. Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65),
Mall: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 139 French francs. 2 years: 259 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 108 French francs. 2 years: 194 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of UNESCO
ndividual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the UNESCO Courier".
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be suppl ed on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO Courier. Photo captions and headlines
are written by the UNESCO Courier staff. The boundaries on maps
oublished in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations. The UNESCO Courier
is produced m microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) Oy: ¡1) UNESCO,
7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox),
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. USA.. (3) N CR Microcard Edition. Indian
Head, inc.. 1 1 1 West 40th Street. New York, U.S.A ; (4) Bell and Howell
Co.. Old Mansfield Road. Wooster. Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) - DEPOT LEGAL : CI - MAI 1991.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - JlFFUSE PAR LES NMPP
Photocomposition: The UNESCO Courier
Photogravure-impression: Maury imprimeur S.A.,
2.1. route d'Etampes. 45330 Malesherbes.
Museums and sports:
Olympic and other dimensions
is the theme of the latest issue
(No. 2 1991) of UNESCO's quarterly magazine
Museum
This issue of Museum surveys the
successes and problems of the museum
treatment of sports internationally. It leads
off with a message from Juan Antonio
Samaranch, President of the International
Olympic Committee. Then comes the
question "Sports in a museum?", asked, and
answered, by the Director of France's
National Sports Museum. Other articles
include "Sports as history" in Prague's
Museum of Physical Training and Sports,
anthropological interpretations of sports by
an Italian specialist, and the sport museum
as a business, which looks at the case of
the Swiss Sports Museum in Basle.
For Courier readers, the Museums and Sports issue of Museum Is
offered at the special rate of 40 French francs (normal cover price,
F 48), or the equivalent in convertible currency. Please send a cheque
made out to UNESCO, with your name and address clearly printed, and
indicate which language version you wish to receive (Arabic, English,
French, Russian or Spanish) to:
Museum, UNESCO (UPP/V),
1 rue Miollis, 75015 Paris, France
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 5- 1991 -OPI 91 -3-492 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
sat
]]>
</page>
</document>
