<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="088837eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
*?e
va
m
ffi
v\
I
à
JULY 1991
M1205 18.00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters We Invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication In this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds In which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
Travel
Impressions
(1991)
crayons on paper, by
Hajja Fatima
Bakhcha
Hajja Fatima
Bakhcha is a
Moroccan who
visited France for the
first time this year,
at the age of sixty.
Before returning
home, she left her
hosts this drawing of
her impressions.
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JULY 1991 CONTENTS
4
Interview with Professor
LÉON SCHWARTZENBERG
The Unesco
44th tí 4«
ftlSSsMd monthly In 35 languag» *nd In Sr»ill*
"The Government» of the Stale»
partie* to th«» Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare.
"that since wars begin In the minds
of men. it Is In the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded, if It Is not to
fail, upon the Intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect knowledge of
each other's lives..."
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of UNESCO,
16 November 1945
* I
; -
V
«H
WS
.Hi "l 3rT^j3 I
¡v m v^U
í*-
Wm1
K
¡f. ::/jL> Vj
* -f»/^
r V
WÊMÂ!
11
MOZART AND THE ENLIGHTENMENT
THE MYSTERY OF GENIUS
A EUROPE OF TRAVELLERS
by Brigitte Massin ' 12
THE AGE OF GENIUS
by Jean Starobinski 18
MOZART AS A MAN
OF THE ENLIGHTENMENT
by Jean Lacouture 22
'EVERY ANGEL'S TERRIFYING'
by Olivier Messiaen 25
TWO KINDRED SPIRITS:
GOETHE AND MOZART
by Manfred Osten 26
A LONG JOURNEY FROM OBSCURITY
by Hugo García Robles 30
A COMPOSER IN HIS TIME 34
37
IN BRIEF...
38
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
The rock art
of Tassili N'Ajjer
by Caroline Haardt
42
UNESCO IN ACTION
ENVIRONMENT
From awareness
to action
by Charles Hopkins
44
UNESCO IN ACTION
THE SILK ROADS
The kingdom of Silla and
the treasures of Nara
by François-Bernard Huyghe
46
UNESCO IN ACTION
Freedom of the press:
an appeal by the Director-
General of UNESCO
THE AMAZON SYMPHONY 36
48
LISTENING
Recent records
50
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
Cover: Symphony (The
Seasons), 1942-1956, (detail),
oil on canvas (96 x 130 cm)
by the Hungarian-born
painter Ernest Klausz
(1898-1970).
Back cover: Requiem II
"Mozart", oil on canvas
(116 x 89 cm) by the
Guadeloupe painter
Marcellus.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
with Professor
LÉON
SCHWARTZENBERG
A leading French cancer
specialist who is also a
member of the European
Parliament and of the French
national watchdog committee
for the life sciences, explains
how cancers are formed and
describes current methods of
treatment. In a field where
misunderstandings are still all
too common, Professor
Schwartzenberg sums up
some of the lessons he has
learned from a lifetime's
experience.
Lots ofpeople talk about cancer, but not
many of them know what it really is. Could
you tell us?
A cancer consists of a colony of cells which
have escaped from control by the laws which
govern the organization of a living being. Each
of the cells in our organism has a specific role.
For reasons that we are now beginning to
understand, some of them suddenly change
into different cells. They cease to co-operate
with the other cells and work as it were for
themselves. They behave anarchically.
X.
This can happen to all living things. Plants
and birds can have cancer. When cells estab¬
lish themselves within a living being in order
to take it over and destroy its life, we talk of
a malignant tumour. A tumour is a group of
cells. Etymologically speaking, malignant
means "diabolical". It is as if the devil has set
up house within a living thing and will, if not
eliminated, systematically destroy it.
What can modern medicine do to eliminate
this "devil"?
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Culture of cancerous
cells of the breast.
Malignant or "diabolical" tumours must be
removed. But how? The simplest way has
always been the knife, or, to use a more high-
flown word, the scalpel. Early this century
radiation began to be used to prevent can¬
cerous cells from dividing. Then, around 1950,
chemical substances which poison cancerous
cells were discovered. But these substances can
also poison healthy cells, albeit to a lesser
degree, and so this form of treatment, known
as chemotherapy, is difficult.
Today a fourth and highly promising
form of therapy known as immunotherapy is
in its early stages. It may be described as
follows. Our immune system provides us with
natural defences against foreign agents such as
infectious bacteria or viruses, or transplanted
cells. In the case of organ transplants an
attempt is made to weaken the body's immune
defences so as to allow the recipient to accept
the transplanted organ, but where cancer is
concerned we try to stimulate these defences
so that the patient can reject the cancer. This
is a new attitude in medicine. Instead of acting
externally by means of surgery, radiation or
chemotherapy, we are trying to act from the
inside by helping patients to get rid of their
tumours by themselves.
Is genetic manipulation involved in this?
No that's something different. The manipu¬
lation of cells should not be confused with the
manipulation of genes. When a tumour
develops, the lymphocytes, the body's
infection-fighting white blood cells, try to
fight it. When the tumour becomes too big,
they lose the battle. Part of the tumour can
then be removed surgically and the lympho¬
cytes which are fighting it can be recovered
and cultivated in the laboratory so that their
number is multiplied a hundred-, a thousand-
'TO^bi
or ten thousand-fold. All these lymphocytes
are reinjected into the patient who then has
more cells with which to fight the tumour.
This is cell manipulation.
Genetic manipulation, as its name sug¬
gests, consists of modifying the hereditary
structure of certain cells, either by using a radi¬
oactive substance or by introducing a specific
gene. But cells manipulated in this way are not
reproductive cells.
Genetic manipulations of the human
ovum are not on the agenda, either scientifi¬
cally since they are still not feasible, or morally
since they are unacceptable to our society.
Could we replace the cells which are in
the body?
This is another possible approach to treat¬
ment. Each of the organism's normal cells has
a kind of organized brain. In the liver cell, for
example, there is a brain which tells it how
to stock sugar and how to secrete certain
enzymes. When the cell becomes cancerous,
its brain goes mad. This rogue cell has returned
to a wild state. A living creature, a human
being, is a being whose cells have become civi¬
lized in order to acquire maturity and phys¬
iological knowledge. The cancerous cells
which have returned to a wild state are totally
uncivilized. Is it possible to imagine
"recivilizing" these cells, making them
"normal" again? Some products give grounds
for hope.
Are some people more predisposed than
others to have sick cells?
Until 1975 we did not really understand
why some people develop cancers more easily
than others. Why, for instance, should some
heavy smokers develop cancer and not others?
Then a young scientist named Dominique
Stehelin, who was Working in the laboratory
of Doctors J. Michael Bishop and Harold E.
Varmus (who were later awarded the Nobel
Prize) discovered cancer-causing genes. Each
of us has tens of thousands of cells which are
"shadowed" by these genes, known as
oncogenes, from oncos the Greek word for
tumour. These cells can be "silent" or unex¬
pressed throughout our lives, in which case
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
we die of something else, or be activated and
trigger a sequence of events that leads to a
cancer. There are also cells known as "anti-
oncogenes", which afford protection against
cancer. When they weaken, they favour the
development of a tumour.
Do some people have a predisposition
towards cancer?
It is wrong to say that cancer is hereditary
except in very rare cases such as cancer of
the retina in children. What is usually called
heredity is a quasi-automatic induction
mechanism. Haemophilia, mucoviscidosis and
myopathia are hereditary. Cancer is not
hereditary because it is a multifactorial disease.
It requires the combined presence of external
causes, of oncogenes, a weakening of immune
defences, and perhaps too a specific kind of
psychological fragility.
Genetic fragility may constitute a
predisposition. A woman whose forebears,
sisters or aunts have had breast cancer is at
greater risk than someone else. In the same
way, there may be a family predisposition to
cancers of the colon or the rectum, the ovaries
or the prostate. In other words, people
belonging to such families, who are at risk,
should have systematic examinationsbreast
X-rays, endoscopy of the intestine
(colonoscopy)as well as systematic smear
tests for cancer of the womb.
Surely these ideas about genetic predispo¬
sition will cause alarm ifthey are notproperly
explained?
Let's take the example of cancers of the
colon or the rectum, which constitute a
quarter of all cancers. In 95 per cent of cases
these consist initially of a small benign
tumour, a polyp the removal of which will
prevent the appearance of a cancer.
Regular breast X-rays make it possible to
detect small breast tumours which are easier
to cure when detected in the early stages.
Some people believe that in fifteen years
cancer will be curable.
It is impossible to say. All we can do is
simply press on with research. Today, there
is less talk than there was ten years ago about
the curability of all cancers. But there is no
reason to give up hope. All the problems
facing humankind have eventually been
solved.
Do you tell yourpatients about the nature
of their illness?
Yes, provided that their general condition
is not too seriously affected. The essential
thing is to make patients understand that they
are not responsible for their illness. The ill¬
ness is not a punishment. As long as there is
no proof that a person's psychological make¬
up can bear any responsibility for the induc¬
tion of a cancer we have no right to use this
argument, for if we do we imply that patients
are responsible for their own cancers.
When you come into the world, you carry
within you the genes transmitted to you by
your parents who inherited them from the
long chain of life which preceded them. This
is the capital of risks and possibilities that is
available to us. This is how we are made. We
do not come from nowhere. We are not born
by immaculate conception. We are reposito¬
ries of all the adventures, possibilities and
defects of humanity.
Do you think that patients can do much
to cure themselves?
Yes. Studies carried out in the United
Kingdom on several hundred patients who had
been operated on for breast cancer showed
that those who were most highly motivated
lived longest. Unfortunately this should not
be considered a law. I have known admirable,
extremely courageous people, young mothers,
who have fought to be able to bring up their
children and havea terrible injusticebeen
unable to do so.
Some doctors do not tell theirpatients the
truth.
I think they are wrong. Human beings have
the right to know the truth about their ill¬
nesses, their destiny. Unless they expressly do
not wish to know. Whatever our convictions
or beliefs, we all feel that our earthly course
does not end on the day of our death. I am
not thinking about what lies beyond but about
what happens here on Earth. We are all
responsible for a human enterprise towards
which we feel certain responsibilities. Love,
family life, the arts, our profession	 Faced
with the possibility of death, we need to take
decisions about the the fate of those we love
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
or those for whom we feel responsible. If you
lie to a patient, he or she will die in ignorance.
Even more serious, lying falsifies human
relations. Perpetuating a lie has serious con¬
sequences. If you give dishonest answers to all
the questions asked by a patient, then you
create a kind of triangular relationship
between the patient who is going to die and
does not know, the person who shares the
patient's life and does know, and the cancer
itself, the third point of the triangle. Just think
of the bitterness the surviving member of such
a couple must feel. As long as his or her
partner was alive, that person agreed to live
a lie without measuring all its consequences.
Suddenly the loved one dies and the surviving
partner realizes that the moment when he or
she began to lie something in their intimate
relationship was broken.
I am not saying that I believe in truth at
all costs. Perhaps some things should be con¬
cealed. But if someone does have to keep a
secret then it should be the patient (since it
is the secret of his or her own body) rather
than the person who shares the patient's life.
We are all free to build our lives as we
think fit. That's why I ask patients who are
near to death whether they are believers, and
if so, whether they want to receive the sacra¬
ments. They all wish to do so, and contrary
to what is often thought, they are not over¬
whelmed by the experience.
Computer Image of a cancer
being treated by radiation therapy.
The green cone corresponds
to the path of the rays.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
An electron microscope
at the Léon Bérard
Research Centre,
Lyons (France).
You say that you are a defender of
euthanasia, ofdeath in dignity. You believe
that people who tolerate the sufferings of
others are torturers.
Doctors and nurses are there to cure. When
you have succeeded you feel yourself justified
intellectually and morally. Intellectually
because the knowledge you have acquired has
brought about this result. Morally, because the
patient who has been for a time handicapped
or infirm, has returned to a normal life, to his
or her family and profession.
In the case of chronic illnesses, such as cer¬
tain cancers and neurological diseases, you
know that you will manage to prolong the
patient's life without being able to effect a
cure. Morally you are ill at ease. But you can
make sure that patients benefit from the latest
advances in science, improve their conditions
and prolong their lives. And this is for you
an intellectual justification.
A situation may arise in which all forms
of therapy have ceased to be effective. Every¬
thing has been tried: surgery, radiation,
chemotherapy. You have shot your bolt. All
you have learned in order to cure a patient
is now useless. Intellectually, you have failed.
At this juncture you must change your whole
intellectual approach and rediscover what has
been the glory of medicine since Greek Antiq¬
uity. The battle against the illness is lost, but
the struggle for the patient can still be waged.
There is a moral justification for this attitude.
To give a complete answer to your ques¬
tion, one also comes across patients who are
demoralized by their illness. They even feel
degraded and want to leave this world with
dignity, so that those around them do not see
them disfigured by a facial tumour, say, or
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
afflicted with a spinal tumour or creeping
paralysis.
In the course of a difficult illness, the
patient may ask for help by saying to you, "I
accept all the treatment you give me, doctor,
but don't let me go too far. When the moment
comes don't strive too hard. If I come to the
end of my tether and I ask you to help me,
will you agree?" One says yes, hoping that the
moment will never come. But when it does
one must keep one's word. You administer a
palliative which eases the disorder caused by
the illness without affecting the illness itself.
One can say that the doctor has realized that
the illness is irreversible. Then we may face
the problem of euthanasia, a word coined in
the seventeenth century by the English
philosopher Francis Bacon. Euthanasia is more
than a gentle death, it is a death worthy of a
human being. Of course it only concerns
patients who are conscious and lucidthey're
the only ones I'm talking aboutpatients who
wish to keep their dignity and their freedom
to be human until the last moment.
From palliative care you have moved on
to euthanasia. . . .
What actually happens? It is possible to
fight against pain, thirst, and fear. But it some¬
times happens that a patient's condition deteri¬
orates, that the tumour, paralysis, handicap,
infirmity or whatever get worse, and the
patient asks for help to preserve his or her dig¬
nity. Now this request for help is insistent,
profound, and repeated; it is not simply made
during a moment of depression. In fact the
first thing we do in this situation is to
administer anti-depressants, and then we dis¬
cover that the patient continues to make a
request which rests on a certain conception
of existence. Make no mistake. All these
patients who out of respect for their dignity
ask for the opportunity to go to sleep forever
are people who love life intensely. As an old
peasant woman said one day: "I'm not tired
of life. It's life that's tired of me."
But surely doctors who help theirpatients
in this way face enormous problems if the
word gets out.
This is because of a medical bureaucracy
of which we should be suspicious. In
medicineand this is the glory of the
professionyou are always confronted with
a person who is different from everyone else.
Even if that person is suffering from an illness
which affects others, he or she remains unique.
A doctor confronted with a patient is one
person confronted with another. You cannot
ask a bureaucracy to define the relationship
between two individuals.
You see death every day. Does it tell you
anything about your own death?
Even if contact with the death of another
person is terrible, I don't think it brings you
any closer to your own death. It only increases
your solitude on Earth.
Have you gained anything from patients
who are at death's door?
Of course. When I began to write about
them I did so because some of them seemed
to me to be more heroic than soldiers. They
displayed courage, dignity, and serenity. This
attitude transcends the difference between
believers and non-believers. I have known anx¬
ious atheists and serene believers and vice
versa. An eminent priest whom I had the
honour to treat was anxious because he was
not sure whether anything lay beyond. That
day I understood that faith could be a matter
of will, not of certainty.
I have seen the extraordinary power of
maternal love. I know that it is total, a love
without equal, and that if fathers have the
same feelings then they too feel maternal love.
Maternal love is protective, giving and trusting
whatever the circumstances. Think of those
unfortunate mothers whose children are
addicted to drugs and sometimes steal from
them. They go on living in order to be able
to bring up their children and perhaps to save
them.
It is hard to understand that death is part
of life. One hears of children who say that
they don't want to die. How can they have
such ideas?
Children start to ask themselves the big
metaphysical question around the age of seven
or eight. These are the most intense thoughts
of our lives. For some people they remain
intense. For others they eventually lose their
force.
Spinoza was right when he wrote: "The
wise man thinks of nothing less than he does
of death, for all wisdom is wisdom of life and
not wisdom of death."
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
^V i
i
»V*
' ' 1 BE1'1 HI
* LaaaaT aW *»*
i^aaP*
11
J*" T^W " i . r
"
' . f t --
, *
-^¿\ - v
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
EDITORIAL
Of their time and at loggerheads with it, with one foot in their
century and another in eternity, rooted in a particular ge¬
ographical setting but also possessed of a universal dimen¬
sion, geniuses are impossible to pigeonhole. To what space-
time do they belong? Given that genius essentially defies all
explanation or definition, can we at least say something about
the context in which it has its being? This is the question to
which the present issue tries to find the beginnings of an
answer.
Our aim has not been to establish a typology of genius in
general or to draw a portrait of that exceptional genius whose
bicentenary is being celebrated this year. What we have tried
to do is to make our own modest contribution to the case¬
book by touching on some of the paradoxes that characterize
genius. The figure of Mozart, a composer whose genius was
long denied or at least underestimated before being universally
acclaimed, seemed to us to chime perfectly with our attempt
to throw a little light on what might be called the truthor
rather the mysteryof genius.
Mozart cannot be dissociated from the Europe of the En¬
lightenment whose best qualities he exemplifies. Whether in
respect of musical composition or of the movement of ideas,
he was a man in the vanguard of his time. What other genius
epitomized to such a degree, in his own creative field, all the
knowledge of his period? True, Mozart was singularly en¬
couraged by his family. At a very early age, in the course of
his travels, he mastered all the major European musical forms,
harvesting with amazing sureness whatever suited his pur¬
poses wherever he found it.
However, this faculty of assimilation, this power of creative
synthesis, rare as it is, cannot by itself provide an adequate
definition of genius. For an artist to be a genius, he also needs
to be in the forefront of all the intellectual currents of his time.
Mozart was not a revolutionary, but he was a fervent Free¬
mason. Philanthropic, philosophical, wedded to the idea of
progress and reform without violence, Freemasonry was a
cosmopolitan humanism whose ideals Mozart espoused
against the intolerance and injustices of his century.
That being said and no matter how aware he may be of con¬
temporary issues, a genius does not simply hold up a mirror
to the age. Unclassif ¡able, unforeseeable, genius spreads its
wings far and wide. A genius is one whose work finds an echo
in other, increasingly remote periods and cultures, meeting
a response in the minds and hearts of people who are more
and more at a remove from it. He then transcends the infinite
variety of the languages, customs and concerns of the peo¬
ples of the world and strikes the chord of their common hu¬
manity. Mysteriously, he achieves universality.
And in a sense his contemporaries make him pay dearly
for it. Mozart ended up by alienating Viennese audiences.
Those who, during his lifetime, were capable of appreciating
his works at their proper value were very few. In the
nineteenth century his star seemed to have set. Now at last
his true stature is recognized, but it has taken almost 200
years. ...
Concert beneath a portico (detail)
by the Italian painter Giovanni Paolo Pannini (1691-1765).
, m»
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
A Europe of travellers
by Brigitte Massin
Europe in Mozart's time was a patchwork of different cultures. The Enlightenment
provided it with a unifying principle and ushered in the modern age. Against this
background of cross-fertilization, Mozart's genius blossomed.
Wo
12
' OLFGANG Amadeus Mozart was born in Salz¬
burg on 27 January 1756 and died in Vienna on
5 December 1791. He was thus a European of the
second half of the eighteenth century.
The geopolitical landscape of eighteenth-
century Europe was very different from that we
know today. First of all, it would be a mistake,
historically speaking, to think of Mozart as an
Austrian, even if Austria can claim him as one
of her sons. When Mozart was born, Salzburg
was the capital of an independent principality
under the jurisdiction of a Prince-Archbishop. It
was an ecclesiastical principality, like the birth¬
place of another great composer, Beethoven, who
was born in 1770 in Bonn, the capital of the
ecclesiastical principality of Cologne.
Cologne and Salzburg were located on arteries
of communication that had been important since
very early times: in the case of Cologne the Rhine,
and in the case of Salzburg the north-south routes
leading from Germany to Italy via the Brenner
Pass. They were also close to the east-west routes
leading from Vienna towards France, England,
and the Austrian Netherlands (what is today
Belgium). These great axes of trade and commu¬
nication often follow the old Roman roads.
Mozart was not born an Austrian and never
claimed to be one. He always referred to himself
as a "German".
These ecclesiastical principalities, relatively
few in number, were part of the Germanic Holy
Roman Empire, which was founded in the tenth
century and survived, at least nominally, until the
upheavals due to the French Revolution and the
Napoleonic Wars eventually led to its disappear¬
ance in the nineteenth century. All the
ecclesiastical principalities were then secularized,
and after many vicissitudes the principality of
Salzburg was attached to Austria in 1816.
The Holy Roman Empire was an attempt
to perpetuate the thinking of Charlemagne. It
was to be a union of European states joined
politically and spiritually under the banner of
Roman Catholicism and ruled by an emperor.
By the eighteenth century it had long ceased
to consider itself Roman and was actually the
Holy Germanic Empire, an agglomeration of
some 400 states varying greatly in size and impor¬
tance (from the large kingdom of Bohemia to
the small princedom of Salzburg), with at its
head an emperor elected by a college of electors.
Since the fifteenth century Austrian Habsburg
princes (who were also kings of Bohemia) had
traditionally been elected emperors of Germany.
Map of Europe from an
18th-century atlas.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
-
I
*f>
v A; S\ > 4
In the eighteenth century, the emperor was
elected by the first college of the imperial diet,
which consisted of nine electorssix lay princes
(representing the Palatinate, Bohemia, Branden¬
burg, Saxony, Hanover and Bavaria) and three
ecclesiastical princes (representing the Rhineland
principalities of Mainz, Trier and Cologne). The
archbishop of Salzburg was not an elector, but
he was a prince of the Empire and belonged to
the second college of the diet. He also bore the
title of primate of Germany, which placed him
above his national colleagues in relation to papal
authority.
While this German empire was the
geographical heart of Europe, it did not represent
the whole of Europe. Beyond its borders to the
east were the Russias, Poland with its shifting
frontiers, Hungary and above all Prussia. To the
south lay Italy which was also divided into many
states, some of which were under Austrian
administration. The great kingdoms of Spain,
France and Great Britain to the west and the
northern kingdoms of Sweden and Denmark-
Norway also lay outside the Empire.
The Austrian Netherlands (what is today Bel¬
gium) belonged to the Empire, but the United
Provinces (today Holland) did not.
Some imperial princes and electors ruled
simultaneously over states which were not
integrated into the Empire. Thus the Habsburgs
of Austria and Bohemia were kings of Hungary,
the Guelfs of Hanover became the kings of
England, and the Hohenzollerns of Brandenburg
became the kings of Prussia.
A march towards progress
The European balance of power was determined
by five states: Great Britain, France, Austria,
Prussia and Russia. The prosperous regions of
Europe (Great Britain, France, Holland, Ger¬
many and northern Italy) embarked on a period
of economic growth which led to a demographic
explosion. The population of Europe rose from
115 million at the beginning of the century to
187 million on the eve of the nineteenth century.
Between 1750 and 1800, the population of Russia
rose from 19 million to 29 million; that of the
Habsburg dominions from 20 to 27 million; that
of France from 22 to 26 million; that of Italy from
15.5 to 18 million; and that of Great Britain from
10.5 to 15.5 million. The population of Prussia
virtually doubled, rising from 3.5 million to 6
million.
Scientific progress called political and social
structures into question. Europe began a march
towards progress. There emerged a critical spirit
towards institutions and the past which called for
the participation of all human beings and implied
a democratic process. The first thing that had to
be done in order to create the spirit of tolerance
necessary for the establishment of a pluralist
society was to reform the educational system and
make it accessible to all.
A reading of Voltaire's tragedy
"L'orphelin de la Chine" in
Madame Geoffrin's drawing
room in 1755 (1812) by the
French painter Gabriel
Lemonnier. Madame Geoffrin's
salon was a centre for the
Encyclopaedists and an
international meeting-place of
artists and men of letters.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
In its search for a new balance, Europe found
a unifying principle in a form of philosophical
reflection, a generalized attitude of thought,
which became known as the Enlightenment and
gave its name to the eighteenth century as a
wholethe age of the Enlightenment. It was a
century of receptiveness to modernity. Many of
the ideas which paved the way for this new mode
of thinking came from Great Britain, from the
Glorious Revolution of 1688 and the liberal con¬
stitution which ensued, from the experiments of
Isaac Newton and the philosophy of John Locke
(1632-1704), but it was in France that the new
philosophy was most fully and coherently
developed.
'Dare to reason!'
The spirit of the Enlightenment materialized on
the public stage around 1750. By that time the
Italian historian and philosopher Giambattista
Vico had already defended in his Scienza nuova
(1725 and 1744), the idea that all peoples pass
through three ages: the divine, the heroic, and the
human. In France Montesquieu published L'esprit
des lois (1748), and Voltaire his Essai sur les mlurs
et l'esprit des nations (1756), which familiarized
the public with the idea of the historical evolu¬
tion of human nature and with the possibility of
progress towards a greater maturity of conscience.
In 1750 the Encyclopédie was launched. Its publi¬
cation continued until 1772.
This Dictionnaire raisonné des sciences, des arts ^
14
England, land of freedom
This is what English legislation has finally achieved. It has succeeded in
restoring to all men those natural rights of which they are divested in nearly
every monarchy. These rights are: complete freedom to dispose of one's person
and property, to speak to the nation through the medium of one's pen, to he
tried for a criminal offence only by a jury composed of independent men, to be
tried in all cases only in accordance with the strict terms of the law and to
profess in peace the religion of one's choice.
These are called prerogatives. And it is indeed a very great and very happy
prerogative, and one that might be envied by many nations, to he certain when
going to to bed that you will wake up the next morning with the same fortune
as you had the night before, that you will not be snatched from the arms of
your wife and children in the middle of the night and led away to a dungeon
or to a wilderness, that, on emerging from your sleep, you will be able to
publish whatever you think, and that if you are accused of reprehensible
conduct, speech or writing you will be tried only in accordance with the law.
Voltaire (1694-1778)
French writer
article on "Government" in the Dictionnaire philosophique (1771)
The "philosopher-king"
Frederick the Great of Prussia
(1712-1786) with his guests
at the palace of Sans Souci.
The king Is shown seated at
right. At his right is the
French writer Voltaire, with
whom he corresponded.
19th-century engraving.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
et des métiers eventually comprised 60,000 articles
published in seventeen volumes, plus eleven
volumes of illustrations. Over 150 writers,
including d'Alembert, Voltaire and Rousseau,
contributed to the vast enterprise, which was
directed by Diderot. The Encyclopédie was based
on the idea that knowledge is the key to power.
This synthesis of knowledge took its place in the
vanguard of enlightened opinion, which insisted
on the primacy of reason in all research. The
Encyclopédie rejected all forms of prejudice and
embodied an attempt to develop a truly scientific
spirit which would lead to a better understanding
of the laws of nature and enable each individual
and humanity as a whole to attain a new state
of happiness.
In the Germanic world, the Enlightenment,
known as the Aufklärung, assumed a more con¬
structive significance in the work of Lessing
(1729-1781) and of Kant (1724-1804), both of
whom wished to make the individual fully adult
rather than to transform the world. Kant's
pamphlet "An answer to the question: what is
the Enlightenment?" (1784) is an achievement in
itseIf as well as a step towards the great German
philosophy of the nineteenth century. What is
the Aufklärung? The emergence of man from his
minority, for which he is himself responsible.
The word "minority" signifies an inability to use
his own understanding, since this state of mind
results not from a flaw in understanding but from
a lack of decision and courage to use it without
the guidance of others. Sapere audel (Dare to
reason!) is the motto of the Aufklärung.
European thinkers were united beneath the
banner of the Enlightenment. The Italian
economist and criminologist Cesare Bonesana,
Marquis of Beccaria (1738-1794), the author of a
famous treatise on Crimes and Punishments
(1764), was one of the most notable representa¬
tives of the spirit of reform which seized Enlight¬
enment Europe. Law reform, edicts of toleration,
the suppression of torture, the abolition of
slavery, the foundation of schools, universities,
national theatres and botanical gardens featured
in the government programmes of the most
enlightened rulers.
The new Europe became truly cosmopolitan.
There were exchanges between philosophers and
kings, and there were even philosopher-kings.
Frederick the Great of Prussia (1712-1788) invited
Voltaire to his court and corresponded with the
leading writers and philosophers of his time.
Catherine II of Russia (1728-1796) was a friend
of Diderot and the protector of French artists and
the philosophes. In Austria, Joseph II (1741-1790),
the son of Maria Theresa, was a strong advocate
of the new reforms and legislation, and almost
came to personify this principle of government.
"Josephism" was a word often used to describe
such policies.
Most Enlightenment sovereigns were not
swayed by these ideas so far as to relax their
authority, and hence came to be known as
"enlightened despots". "All for the people,
nothing through the people" [Allesfür das Volk,
Nichts durch das Volk), was the terse and eloquent
formula of Joseph II. The sovereign wished for
the happiness of all but he alone continued to be
in charge.
One characteristic figure of the century who
played a key role in the spread of knowledge was
the pedlar who, weighed down with books,
travelled from town to town, from town to
country, and in many cases from country to
country. Eighteenth-century Europe was a
Europe of travellers.
Ideas without frontiers
Sovereigns and princes dazzled by the glory of
Versailles commissioned their architects to create
palaces for them along similar lines. Architectural
Haydn (right), Gluck and the
young Mozart. Bas-relief
(detail) on a monument on
Maria Theresa Square, Vienna
(Austria).
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Europe was a mirror of Versailles. From Lisbon
to Madrid, from Naples to Rome, from Vienna
to Warsaw, from Berlin to St. Petersburg,
fabulous mansions rose from the ground. One of
the most notable of these itinerant architects was
François de Cuvilliés of Hainaut (Belgium), who
created wonderful examples of ornamental art.
Among the buildings he designed were the
summer home and the delightful Munich resi¬
dence of the Prince Elector of Bavaria.
Musicians have always been travellers, and
they were notably itinerant in the eighteenth cen¬
tury. Mozart's European travels began in child¬
hood. His contemporary Paisiello journeyed
from Naples to St. Petersburg. Late in life, Haydn
made long visits to England. Italy has always
attracted operatic composers. It was there that the
Saxon Hasse achieved fame and became "Il caro
Sassone". Johann Christian Bach, the son of
Johann Sebastian Bach, was known successively
as "Bach of Milan" and "Bach of London", after
the cities in which he established himself profes¬
sionally.
Italy, homeland of the arts, held a strong
attraction for painters, writers and art-lovers. The
figures are amazing. According to the historian
Edward Gibbon, no fewer than 40,000 English
people visited the peninsula in 1785. Travelling
in Europe, in France but above all in Italy,
inspired much writing by Stendhal, Goethe and
others.
Bigger and bigger publishing houses were
founded in Berlin and Leipzig, Geneva, Rome and
Florence, Paris and London. Newspapers and
Pedlar selling newspapers and
prints. Copper engraving by
the German artist Johann
Christoph Seekatz
(1719-1768).
16
BRIGITTE MASSIN,
French musicologist, writer and
journalist, is the author, jointly
with Jean Massin, of a seminal
study devoted to Mozart (1958
and 1990, new edition, Fayard,
Paris) and the editor of a
history of Western music
(1985, Fayard, Paris). She has
also written a book on
Schubert (1977, Fayard, Paris)
and an essay on Olivier
Messiaen (1990, Alinéa, Paris).
Mme Massin is responsible for
the co-ordination of the Mozart
bicentenary year in France.
Reason, tolerance, humanity
In England, Collins and Bolingbroke; in France, Bayle, Fontenelle, Montesquieu,
and the schools that grew up around these illustrious men, waged battles in defence
of truth, employing in turn all the weapons offered to reason by erudition,
philosophy, wit and the talent of writing; adopting every tone, using every form,
from pleasantry to pathos, from the most learned and most extensive compilation
to novels and topical tracts; lenient towards despotism when combatting religious
absurdities, and sparing religion when rising up against tyranny; attacking these
two evils at their roots, even when appearing to be directing their shafts exclusively
at the outrageous or ridiculous abuses to which they give rise; at one moment
teaching the enemies of liberty that superstition, which guards despotism with an
impenetrable shield, is the first chain they must break; at another moment, on the
contrary, denouncing it to despots as the true enemy of their authority, but
untiringly asserting the independence of reason and claiming freedom to express
one's ideas as a right, and as the salvation of the human species; rising up with
inexhaustible energy against all the crimes offanaticism and tyranny; and taking
as their war cry: reason, tolerance, humanity.
Condorcet (1743-1794)
French philosopher, mathematician and politician
Esquisse d'un tableau historique des progrès de l'esprit humain
(Sketch for a Historical Picture of the Progress of the Human Mind. 1795)
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Residenztheater, Munich,
a masterpiece of German
Rococo art designed by
François de Cuvilliés. It was
here that Mozart's opera
(domeneo, re di Creta was
first performed in 1781.
gazettes crossed frontiers. Baron Melchior
Grimm's Paris newsletter, Correspondance littér¬
aire, philosophique et critique, was read in all the
courts and made Mozart famous when he was still
a child.
The market for books was transformed, with
Frankfurt as its major centre. At Kehl, across the
Rhine from Strasbourg, the French writer Beau¬
marchais founded his own publishing house and
published the complete works of Voltaire for
German readers. He also took the opportunity
to print his own comedy Le manage de Figaro,
long banned in France, which caused a scandal
throughout Europe. Mozart was one of the pur¬
chasers of this first German translation and made
it the basis of his Italian opera The Marriage of
Figaro.
This great movement of cross-fertilization
which characterized the Enlightenment, deve¬
loped "understanding", encouraged individuals
to emerge from a Kantian "minority" which they
had hitherto accepted, and also led to the
awakening of German nationhood. The many
states, great and small, and writers such as Klop-
stock, Goethe, Schiller and Lessing, realized that
their union around a common language, German,
was legitimate, and claimed the right to make
German a cultural vehicle on a par with French
or Italian.
If life and thought in eighteenth-century
Europe had not been so open, dynamic and
optimistic, Mozart would probably never have
been able to write The Magic Flute, a work which
for him represented the fulfilment of a long
cherished dream, the flowering of German opera.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The age oí genius
by Jean Starobinski
The concept of genius in the modern sense dates from the eighteenth century. Already at
that time, when Mozart was still alive, the word was being applied to him.
%
18
HEN the seven-year-old Mozart first per¬
formed in Paris, Friedrich Grimm, whose cultural
newsletters were sent to the European courts,
spoke of him with enthusiasm and, reporting on
the event in December 1763, did not hesitate to
use the word genius: "What is incredible is to see
him playing by heart for an hour without inter¬
ruption and then give himself up to the inspira¬
tion of his genius and to a host of ravishing ideas
which he then goes on to develop one after
another with taste and without confusion".
Three years later, after a concert in Lausanne,
one critic spoke in praise of "this forcefulness
which is the hallmark oí genius, this variety which
bespeaks the fire of imagination, this charm
which reveals an unfailing taste". Later, in 1788,
just after the triumphal success that had greeted
Don Giovanni in Prague, Joseph Haydn, con
cerned about Mozart's precarious financial situ¬
ation, wrote in a letter: "The lives of great geniuses
are all too often marred by the thoughtless
ingratitude of their admirers".
The fact is that Mozart's genius was not
recognized by enough people nor indeed to a
sufficient extent to preserve him from want or
to protect him from the rivalry of lesser talents.
In the opinion of many, whose ears could not
be trusted, the precociousness of Mozart's gifts,
which made him a "prodigy", a "wunderkind",
a "miracle", was not a guarantee of genius. Some
people, after being dazzled by him, were con¬
vinced that his performance had been just a flash
in the pan. For educated audiences of the eight¬
eenth century, being a "genius" was, to say the
least, not the same as being a "prodigy".
After Mozart's death, when there was no
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
longer any doubt about his greatness, Count
Waldstein wrote to Beethoven, at the time of the
latter's visit to Vienna: "The Genius of Mozart
is still in mourning and laments the death of its
disciple". Allegorized in this way, genius becomes
an independent being, a kind of graveside statue,
examples of which abound in neoclassical art,
fond as it is of combining conceptualization with
shows of sentiment.
The voice of nature
What was understood by genius in the eighteenth
century, and particularly musical genius?
The meaning of the word had changed since
the previous century. Genius was thought of
primarily in neutral terms as intellectual ability.
One might speak of a "narrow genius" or a "fine
genius" or an "original genius". Each and every
language in the world had its own "genius". An
individual's "moral personality" was determined
by his or her character (passions and propensities)
and genius (gifts or talents). The word genius
could be given a favourable or unfavourable con¬
notation.
If we retrace the use of the word in the abun¬
dant English, French, German, Italian and
Spanish literature of the eighteenth century we
see it gradually losing its original neutrality. Its
meaning became strictly circumscribed, coming
to designate the higher activity and power of the
mind as revealed in certain exceptional
individuals. Genius was a mysterious gift of
nature. Thanks to this gift, man became a cre¬
ator in nature's image. Genius was nature at work
within the human imagination.
Genius thus became, in Diderot's words, "A
secret, indefinable quality of the soul without
which one cannot accomplish anything very great
or very beautiful". Genius made its own rules,
which were not the same as those governing the
common run of humanity. In the article on genius
in the Encyclopédie (written by Saint-Lambert, but
largely inspired or revised by Diderot) we find
the following: "The rules and laws of good taste
would set shackles on genius; genius puts them
asunder in order to soar to the heights of the sub¬
lime, of pathos, of grandeur. Love of that eternal
beauty which characterizes nature and a passion
for depicting scenes in accordance with some self-
created model from which he derives his ideas and
feelings of beautythese are the inclinations of
the man of genius. . . . Power and abundance, an
indefinable roughness, unevenness, sublimity,
pathossuch, in the arts, are the qualities of
genius; it does not affect in mild degree, it does
not give pleasure without causing surprise, it is
surprising even when it errs".
To Diderot, genius was "a kind of prophetic
cast of mind". Goethe, taking Shakespeare as his
example, was to say the same thing: through the
agency of genius, which is its interpreter, nature
engages in prophecy. But Goethe, who celebrated
genius and the independence of genius, as did
Kant, was all the more scathing about the triviali-
zation of the concept and the frauds perpetrated
in its name during the period when the "cult of
genius" reigned. "On the pretext that they have
genius or that they are geniuses, large numbers
of young people have indulged in every kind of
extravagance, going beyond all bounds: they have
lost their way	" This reproach, it hardly needs
pointing out, was in no way directed at Mozart,
all of whose works were considered by Goethe
to possess a "fertilizing power which remains
active from generation to generation and which
will not soon be exhausted. . . ."
Diderot, in his writings on the arts, did not
forget music. In his Leçons de clavecin ("Harp¬
sichord lessons", 1771) he has the pupil ask: "And
do you think that eventually one day I'll be able
to compose? Composing is the finest skill!" To
which the master replies: "And unfortunately it
is the only one that cannot be taught: it is the
Opposite page, Voltaire and
Rousseau being led by their
Genius to the temple of glory
and Immortality (French
engraving).
Below, frontispiece from
L'Encyclopédie ou Dictionnaire
raisonné des Sciences, des
Arts et des Métiers (1751) by
Diderot and d'Alembert.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
preserve of genius. ... If you have genius you
will find songs. . . . Any music which neither
paints nor speaks is bad, and you will produce
it without genius. . . : you will swell the ranks
of those I call the rag-and-bone men of music".
It will be remembered that Rameau's Nephew
opens with a debate on genius, turning around
Racine, Voltaire and Jean-Philippe Rameau. But,
concerning the latter, the Philosopher declares
that "it is not quite certain that he really is a man
of genius". Voltaire for his part was convinced
Lully and Rameau did have geniusand in this
his judgement was that of all his generation, for
which moreover genius was but the supreme
manifestation of talent and taste.
Diderot and especially Rousseau distanced
themselves from French tradition. To know the
views regarding genius of the men and women
who sided with the Italians on the occasion of
their dispute with the partisans of the French
theatrical style (the Guerre des Bouffons), one must
open Rousseau's Dictionnaire de Musique (1768)
and read in particular the article on prima inten-
zione: "A melody, a piece of music di prima
The library of the
Klementinum (1727), a Jesuit
college in Prague
(Czechoslovakia). Mozart
visited the library in 1787.
20
JEAN STAROBINSKI,
Swiss writer and essayist,
member of the Institut de
France, has written widely on
the eighteenth century. His
publications translated into
English include The Emblems of
Reason (1982, University of
Virginia Press), The Invention
of Liberty, 1 700 to 1 789
(1985, Rizzolo Intl.,), Jean-
Jacques Rousseau-
Transparency and Obstruction
(1988, University of Chicago
Press) and The Living Eye
(1989, Harvard University
Press).
intenzione, is one which has taken shape at a
single stroke and in its entirety in the composer's
mind, like Pallas emerging fully armed from
Jupiter's brain. Compositions diprima intenzione
are those rare strokes of genius in which all the
ideas are so closely linked as to form so to speak
one single idea. . . . This kind of operation of the
intellect, which can barely be explained, even ana¬
lytically, is a wonder to reason and can be con¬
ceived only by geniuses capable of producing it.
... In music, compositions di prima intenzione
are the only ones that can cause those ecstasies,
those raptures, those flights of the soul that trans¬
port listeners into another world".
Rousseau harks back here to a theory of
knowledge subscribed to by the neo-Platonic
philosophers of the Italian Renaissance who held
that ecstasy afforded a direct view of a supreme
reality, composed of pure ideas. This all-
embracing vision is offered only to the highest
faculty of the soulto its finest flowering. In the
eighteenth century, according to the accepted idea
of genius, the gaze ceased to be turned towards
the sky of existing truths and was directed
towards the future, instantaneously embracing
every aspect of an original composition, all the
parts and components of a work which the artist
then went on to construct.
Mozart, according to the account given of
him by his friend Rochlitz, claimed to hold the
whole of a work in his head before noting it on
paper. However, this totality did not present itself
to him at a single stroke: it gradually took shape
in his mind: "It grows; I develop it more and
more, ever more clearly. The work is then com¬
pleted in my head, or as good as, even if it is a
long piece, and I can view the whole at a single
glance like a painting or a statue. In my imagina¬
tion I do not hear the work as a flow or a succes¬
sion, but I hold it in its entirety so to speak, as
a single unit".
In the text quoted earlier, Rousseau attributes
to musical prima intenzione the privilege of that
systematic and organic unity which he claimed
to have experienced philosophically on the occa¬
sion of his famous "illumination" on the Vin-
cennes highway, when all the truths inherent in
his system became clear to him in one mind-
shattering moment. So numerous and so closely
interlinked were they that he was unable to seize
hold of each and every one. A piece of music is
of narrower compass, and that which has been
revealed "at a single stroke" to the composer's
mind can be preserved and transcribed. So it was
that Mozart proceeded, if we can believe
biographical tradition, during the night when he
noted down the overture to Don Giovanni.
An all-consuming fire
Rousseau was very proud of the article on genius
that he had included in his Dictionnaire de
Musique. Rightly so, for it is outstanding and
deserves to be more widely known. It should be
read in conjunction with the articles on prima
intenzione and composition. From it we learn that
genius is by essence indefinable; that it is recog¬
nizable by its extraordinary powers; that it draws
inspiration from contact with other geniuses, par¬
ticularly poetic genius; and that, even if it is a gift
of nature, it may be fully developed only by dint
of unremitting effort: "Young artist, seek not to
know what genius is. If you have it, you will find
it in yourself. If you do not have it, you will never
know it. The musician's genius subjects the entire
universe to his art; it paints every picture with
sounds; it makes the very silence speak; it renders
ideas by feelings, feelings by tone colours; and the
passions it expresses, it rouses them in the depths
of people's hearts: it gives fresh charms to sen¬
sual pleasure; the pain it portrays pierces each
breast; it burns steadily and is never consumed:
it evokes ice and frost by means of heat; even
when depicting the horrors of death, it is ani¬
mated by a feeling of life that never leaves it and
which it communicates to receptive hearts: but
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Jean-Jacques Rousseau in
Rochecardon park, a painting
(1795) by the French artist
Alexandre-Hyacinthe Dunouy.
alas it cannot speak to those in whom its seed has
not been sown, and its wonders are not percept¬
ible to those who are incapable of imitating them.
Do you wish to know then whether some spark
of this all-consuming fire glows in your breast?
Hasten to Naples and listen to the masterpieces
of Leo, Durante, Jomelli and Pergolesi. If your
eyes brim with tears, if you feel your heart
pounding inside you, if you are seized with shud¬
dering, if in your raptures you are stifled by a
sense of oppression, take up the lyrics of
Metastasio and work: his genius will fire your
own, you will create through his example; this
is how genius proceeds, and other eyes will soon
pay you back for the tears that the masters have
caused you to shed. ..."
Rousseau (born in 1712) urged his readers to
model themselves on the Neapolitan geniuses.
But Rousseau was simplifying matters: he seemed
not to be aware that the Italian style had gained
a foothold nearly everywhere in Europe. Mozart
became acquainted with the Italian taste in 1764
through Johann Christian Bach in London. Then,
in 1770, during his visit to Italy, he acquired fur¬
ther knowledge of an art that Rousseau abhorred:
counterpoint. In this technical field, the lessons
of Martini, in Bologna, were invaluable to the
young composer.
He nevertheless seems to have heeded Rous¬
seau's advice. He journeyed to Naples! But not
with undue haste. He met Jomelli (born in 1714)
and went several times to listen to his latest opera,
Armida abbandonata. But this did not produce
the effect foretold by Rousseau. In his first letter
on the subject, Mozart found the opera to be
"well-written". A few days later he declared it
to be "beautiful, but . . . too reasonable and too
antiquated for the theatre". No longer were there
any tears or raptures. The fire announced by
Rousseau had lost its warmth. It burned brightest
not in the old Neapolitan master, but in Mozart,
who had nothing more to learn from him.
It is hazardous to say that one place offers
a more fertile ground to musical genius than any¬
where else. This again implies an undue desire to
define genius. But genius is recognized by what
it produces, regardless of locality, provided that
men and women are willing to listen. This
capacity for listening, it is true, is not equally
present at all times, in all places, in all societies.
Is it merely by chance that those who theorized
about genius in the eighteenth century, and first
and foremost Rousseau, were the very ones who
theorized about education?
A model of perfection
What is the secret of an art that decks truth out in cheerful
colours while dimly preserving the real grimness of truth?
Music has the particular faculty, by inducing moods, of
accomplishing this curious feat of incorporating the worst into
the best, of achieving the paradox of harmonious dissociation.
And Mozart's music more than any other. Its real lyricism
distances it from reality. It contains the things that we are most
loathe to consider and which indeed our minds reject. It is
steeped in the ineluctable presence of death. Yet, so that we can
bear to recognize these things, it cloaks them in a magnificent,
limpid myth. We are not compromised by what we have
touched, our hopes remain intact. Mozart thus offers to Art a
model ofperfection.
Pierre Jean Jouve (1887-1976)
French writer
Le Don Juan de Mozart (1942)
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Mozart as a man of the Enlightenment
by Jean Lacouture
The philosophy of the Enlightenment is at the heart ofMozart's work.
A convinced Christian and Freemason, Mozart was also a rebel who proclaimed
a message of love and fellowship.
M<Lozart, idol of Versailles, London, Prague
and the Vienna court, did not seek disgrace, iso¬
lation and grinding poverty: he was too fond of
the good life. But he braved them and endured
them. He went boldly forward over open ground
on routes where the forces of the Ancien Régime,
daunted but still well-armed, lay in wait for the
enemyfreedom.
He went his own way, this young Wolfgang
son of Leopold, born in prudish Salzburg and
pampered by the great: at the age of thirty he
chose to set to musicand without toning it
Osmin, one of the
characters in Mozart's
opera Die Entführung aus
dem Serail (1782), as
staged by Giorgio Strehler
at the Paris Opera House
in 1984.
down!Beaumarchais's explosive Marriage of
Figaro, already censured by the imperial police.
This play, by an adventurer who busied himself
supplying arms to the American revolution (fore¬
runner of the French one), was nothing less than
an egalitarian, libertarian manifestoa tract
directed against all the privileges of the nobility,
starting with the droit du seigneur. It fore¬
shadowed the night of 4 August 1789, when the
last privileges of feudalism were abolished in
France.
The rebel
Anybody unfamiliar with Figaro's aria Se vuol
bellare, signor Contino can have no idea of the
social bravado and temerity needed to use such
language and such a tone of voice to a powdered
and bewigged Viennese audience. The message is
plain: the era of high-handedness, when wearing
knee-breeches and a sword was all that was
needed to be always in the right, is over, my lords.
Other human relationships are on the way.
Figaro proclaims as much, and so in her own way
does Suzanna to Figaro the manbarely freed
from the tyranny of the nobility and already
impatient to assert the authority of a husband.
In the following year Wolfgang was to go still
further, putting into the mouth of Masetto a
challenge to the wife-stealing Don Giovanni
which according to the great French poet Pierre
Jean Jouve "heralded the subversive movements
of the French Revolution. . . . The little aria .
. . seems related to the Ça ira of the coming days.
... A revolution is on the way, and it will settle
human difficulties by more drastic and more
impersonal methods."
Let us not, however, make Mozart out to be
a revolutionary militant, a sans-culotte, a Jacobin,
a Carbonaro or a forerunner of Sturm und Drang.
He would have loathed the "more drastic and
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
* V
more impersonal methods" that the 1793 revo¬
lution saw fit to adopt, just as Pamina loathes the
dagger handed to her by her mother, the Queen
of the Night, for the purpose of killing Sarastro,
who is the voice of wisdom and light.
More light
The key word is out. It was not revolution but
light that Mozart the rebel was after. His whole
life was a search for the light, more light, the
"mehr Licht" of Goethe on his death-bed. Others
saw it as a direction, a stage on the road, a means
to an end: for him it was an end in itself, and a
tremendous one.
The reason why this search accelerated and
intensified during his last ten years, which took
him from II Seraglio to The Magic Flute, was
because that was when he really entered his
"enlightened" Masonic period under the aegis of
that greatest of German initiates, Ignaz von Born,
regarded by Jean and Brigitte Massin as the model
for the wise Sarastro.
Whether von Born's influence was direct or
indirect, Mozart's support for freemasonry was
reflected in his membership of the Vienna lodge
known as "Hope Crowned". There he was to get
to know Schikaneder, later librettist and producer
of, as well as a performer in, The Magic Flute, in
which the Age of the Enlightenment came to
flower in 1791. This was the very moment when
in Paris the Constituent Assembly broke up
proclaiming that thenceforth "in France every
man is free", enfranchising the Jews, and
abolishing the "imaginary offences" of lese-
majesty and heresy.
Ten years before The Magic Flute, however,
Meeting of the Viennese
Masonic lodge Zur gekrönten
Hoffnung (Hope Crowned)
showing Prince Miklós
Esterházy officiating as
master of ceremonies. Mozart
can be seen in right
foreground talking to his
neighbour.
True nobility
It's the heart that makes man noble, and though I'm not a
count I have perhaps more honour lodged in my body than
many a count; and lackey or count, he who insults me is a
scoundrel!
Mozart
20 June 1781
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24
at the start of his life as a freemason, Wolfgang
Mozart had rebelled against the hegemony of the
Prince-Archbishop of Salzburg, Colloredo; and
he had fired the opening shots in his campaign
of enlightenment in // Seraglio, the highly
"philosophical" extravaganza in which the
wisdom of the East shines out through a mêlée
of turbans, fans and Turkish slippers.
Fraternal reason
Here it is no Westerner, guided by Christianity,
who lays down the precepts of reason: it is Sultan
Selim who transcends passions and intrigues to
enunciate the liberating judgement to a gaggle of
feather-brained Europeans. This must have been
embarrassing to the Viennese, still quaking from
the incursions of Turkish troops in the Danube
basin.
Lo and behold, Europe now begins to break
free from Manichaeism, distributing good and evil
on both sides of an imaginary linethe cross on
one side and the crescent on the other. The
Enlightenment informs each of Selim's utter¬
ances, an Enlightenment which is shown to be
be in no way the exclusive preserve of the West.
Nine years later, Sarastro grandly echoes
Selim's even-handedness. It is no longer a matter
of merely restoring physical liberty to a few
scatty Westerners who have gone astray in
Muslim lands, but of propounding to humankind
rules of conduct based on fraternal reason: a
reason which under the patronage of Isis and
Osiris poses no threat to religious observance.
Though his genius drew sustenance from
Christianity, Mozart had no links with the
Catholic Church. In a century in which Free¬
masonry came into being under the wing of
Christianity, intending not to destroy it but to
guide it and free it of clericalism, he appears as
the harbinger par excellence of this creative
enlightenment.
To return to Jouve: Mozart, "that religious,
almost irreligious genius . . . , cannot be fitted
into any ideal category. Like Shakespeare, he is
atheist and believer, man of religion and sorcerer
at one and the same time". He adds: "We no
longer have yardsticks to measure the stature of
such men: our beings have become too small."
Design for an 1879
production of The Magic Flute
(1791), Mozart's last opera,
at the théâtre de l'Opéra-
Comique in Paris.
Costume for Sarastro, a
character in The Magic Flute,
designed by the French
painter Roger Chapelain-Midy.
JEAN LACOUTURE,
French journalist and writer, is
the author of several major
biographies, including the
recent Champollion, une vie de
lumières (1988, Grasset,
Paris). Volume I of his
3-volume life of Charles de
Gaulle was published In English
in 1988 as Charles de Gaulle:
The Rebel by Holmes & Meier,
New York, who have also
published his biographies of
Léon Blum (1982) and Pierre
Mendès-France (1984).
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
'Every angel's terrifying'
by Olivier Messiaen
A great French musician pays tribute to Mozart
%»EAUTY'S nothing but the start of terror, and
we adore it because of the serene scorn it could
kill us with". These lines by Rainer Maria Rilke
apply very well to Mozart's music. It is a music
of purity and perfection, as befits this most
musical of musicians. No flaw can be found in it.
Accentuation in Mozart. In his feminine
rhythms (anacrusis, stress accents, pauses), the
stress is always in the right place. Melody in
Mozart. Melodic lines suffused with his own spe¬
cial poetry. What enchantment in Suzanna's aria
in Figaro, what gentle strains of birdsong in the
andante of the Haffner symphony!
Harmony in Mozart. Always light, always
perceptible, always appropriate. A soothing har¬
mony when it is tonal (listen to the "Ave Verum"
and the slow movement of the Jupiter symphony),
a heartrending harmony when it is chromatic
(listen to the symphony in G minor, the andante
of the concerto for piano in A major, K. 488, and
the slow movement of the concerto in E flat, K.
271). Sometimes it is an otherworldly harmony,
as in the amazing Statue scene at the end of Don
Giovanni, where we already find (underscored by
the trombones) two sonorities favoured by
Debussy: the chord of fifths and fourths, and an
altered chord belonging to the whole-tone scale.
Form in Mozart. It is always perfect and cons¬
tantly renewed (listen to the great symphonies
and the piano concertos).
Theatre in Mozart. A man of the theatre if
ever there was one, Mozart, at a single stroke, cap¬
tures with one aria the essence of a character
(listen to Cherubino, the Countess, Sarastro,
Papageno). His finales are masterpieces of the
stage. Pierre Jean Jouve said of the finale of Don
Giovanni that it was "an awesome piece of
music".
Mozart's orchestration carries the same force
of truth as his accentuation, his melodic line, his
harmonies and his form. Mozartbefore
Berliozhad a sense of specific timbre. First
example: the trio from the minuet of the sym¬
phony in E flat (K. 543) where the two clarinets
thread together low notes and high notes, echoed
by the flute, and where the chromaticism of the
violins gives way to the warm, mellow tones of
the horns returning to the theme. Second
example: the entreaties of the three masked
figures, before Don Giovanni's ball, where the
singing lines of the two female voices are backed
only by tenor voice, horns and woodwinds.
Third example: in The Magic Flute, the almost
modern effect of the high notes of the solo glock¬
enspiel, accompanied by the hushed tones of the
male choir. Fourth example: the ballroom scene
in Don Giovanni with, before Darius Milhaud,
its four superimposed levels of music: the large
orchestra, two small orchestras on stage and the
dialogue of the characters.
Mozart has been portrayed in a variety of
ways: the small boy playing the harpsichord for
the elegant ladies of the court; Leopold's
respectful son; the young man in love with all
the opera singers; the insulted servant giving his
notice to the unpleasant Prince-Archbishop; the
misunderstood composer of genius, dying of
hunger, cold and fatigue.
All these images are at once true and false.
The adjective "angelic" is perhaps the least inap¬
propriate. Angelic, yes, and, on that account, very
difficult to come to grips with. His apparent charm
hides a deep mystery. To quote Rainer Maria
Rilke once more: "Every angel's terrifying".
3
The language of genius
Here he is, the supreme master! He is neither an Italian
nor a German. He is of all times and all ages, like logic,
poetry and truth. He gives utterance to all passions, all
feelings, in their very own language.
George Sand (1804-1876)
French writer
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
by Manfred Osten
Two kindred
Contemporaries and geniuses both, the composer of The Magic Flute
and the author of Faust were ahead of their time and hold out a mirror to our own
26
VJoETHE had a very high opinion of The Magic
Flute (K. 620, 1791), Mozart's last opera, and
staged it almost a hundred times during the period
when he was director of the theatre at Weimar.
In 1795, four years after the composer's death,
he began to write a sequel to The Magic Flute, but
got no further than the beginning of the second
act. Goethe's project may be seen as a late tribute
from one creator who was not of his time to
another whom he perceived as a kindred spirit.
When in 1830 Goethe evoked the long-dead
Mozart, the image that came to his mind was that
of the child prodigy, the "little man with his wig
and sword" who at the age of seven had given
a concert at Cologne. Was he conjuring up a
nostalgic picture of a rococo past that had gone
for ever? How in that case can we explain the
explosions of violence in some of Mozart's work,
a vehemence which is in flagrant contradiction
with the musical and artistic conventions of his
time?
Autonomy and clemency
To answer this question we must go back as far
as Mozart's second visit to Paris in 1778. The
vaudevilles and comic operas performed in the
French capital at that time contained social criti¬
cism which foreshadowed the coming political
upheavals. Melchior Grimm, Mozart's German
mentor and protector in Paris, made no secret of
his political affiliations as a friend of Voltaire and
Diderot. Something of this must have rubbed off
onto Mozart. His wife Constance told the music
publisher Novello that one of her husband's
favourite books was a nine-volume work that was
on the Index. "A revolutionary French work",
Novello concluded, and may well have been
right.
This hypothesis is amply confirmed by
Mozart's seven great operas, which were com¬
posed in the decade leading up to the French
Revolution. These ten years saw a growing dis
trust of religious and secular absolutism, and a
growing demand, both from thinkers and oper¬
atic librettists, for the independence of the
individual. The hermetic world of the baroque
dissolved into the fascinating yet terrifying
prospect of the modern. It was in the Utopian
world of the opera that Mozart celebrated this
moment of hope in a humanity whose members
could live together on equal terms. In his tragedy
Iphigenia in Tauris (1787) Goethe also saluted this
historic moment by expressing his faith in utopia,
although he did so only in passing and his tone
was ironical.
Goethe's Iphigenia and Mozart's Pamina are
characters who herald a time when mankind will
throw off its shackles, both literally and
metaphorically. They dare to imagine the eman¬
cipation of humanity from above and from
below. Goethe, however, insists that the
individual can only achieve complete autonomy
if "external and completely unexpected factors
come to his aid". This intervention is a form of
grace, a pardon, an act of clemency. Pamina
expresses this link between the realm of grace (the
ultimate and already resigned act of a single
person who is the sovereign) and the realm of
autonomy (that of the individual freed and
revealed unto himself). Pamina, like Iphigenia,
calls down an unexpected intervention from on
high. She persuades and even forces the sovereign
to be merciful to her.
In 1985 the dramatist and theatre critic Ivan
Nagel noted in his reflections on Mozart's operas
that "Initially musical classicism aspires to an
overall improvement in the human condition.
Such an aspiration could only emerge during the
brief alliance between the nobility and the bour¬
geoisie which took place in Vienna and Weimar
under the protection of enlightened despotism."
This "protection", Nagel added, "soon stood
revealed as a political daydream". Pamina and
Iphigenia thus seem united in a fleeting Utopian
moment.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
spirits: Goethe and Mozart
The living present
Mozart is nothing if not elusive. He is, as Nagel
has pointed out, a truly protean spirit whose
genius oscillates between two poles: the Ancien
Regime's idea of pardon as an act of mercy
granted from above, and a belief in the autonomy
of the individual. For Mozart, the idea of pardon
is at the heart of eighteenth-century opera seria,
whereas autonomy is the guiding principle of the
great musical dramas which he composed
between 1781 and 1791 and which broke with
a form that had become ossified.
Was Mozart a traveller between different
worlds? During the summer of 1791, while in
France the people arrested the fleeing King and
Queen, he was composing for Emperor Leopold
II, who had been crowned King of Bohemia, an
opera celebrating a sovereign who is merciful to
all conspirators (La clemenza di Tito, K. 621).
If this was a step backward, it was cancelled
out by two steps forward. In Don Giovanni,
Mozart clearly anticipates the future, the rapid
and self-wrought eclipse of the Enlightenment by
ideology. In the person of Don Giovanni, an ego
of boundless autonomy is brought down by a
curse. The seducer's freedom is sacrificed in the
name of the same bourgeois morality as that rev¬
ealed in the second act of The Magic Flute. In the
masonic music it is possible to discern the out¬
line of a society which regards virtue as the only
universal value and shuns as evil any behaviour
that diverges from this norm.
Between these different worlds, Mozart has
a place of .his own, one that is simultaneously
visible and yet secretthe buffa movement at the
end of The Marriage ofFigaro (K. 492, 1786). Ivan
Nagel believes that this final movement reveals
with consummate perfection "a way of living in
the present unburdened by nostalgia, an
unprecedented freedom with regard to utopia
which is the culmination of the new musical art."
Why? Because here a sovereign incapable of an
act of pardon is graciously admitted into the
Knight of the opera. Above,
Mozart in the regalia of the
Order of the Golden Spur.
Anonymous painting (1777).
Left, Goethe in the
countryside near Rome (1787,
detail), by the German painter
Johann Heinrich Wilhelm
Tischbein (1751-1829).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
singers' stage fellowship, into the "non-
totalitarian whole" that they form, in the unity,
the long dreamed-of fusion between happiness
and society, reason and nature.
It is hardly surprising that Goethe should see
in the prodigious creator of this operatic grace
the repository of a metaphysicalor rather
"demoniac"natural grace. "To tease and trick
humanity, demons often use solitary creatures
they have endowed with an irresistible power of
seduction. . . . They have made Mozart an
untouchable musical figure."
It is precisely this inaccessible aspect of
Mozart, the miraculous state of grace that his exis¬
tence represented, which makes him seem a man
who did not belong to his time. This would also
be the fate of Goethe, of whom Nietzsche
observed in 1886 that "His existence has no con¬
nection with his nation. He livedand still
livesonly for a few. ... In the history of the
Germans, Goethe is an interlude without a
sequel."
The solitude of genius
Mozart's early biographers saw a connection
between the disfavour into which Mozart fell at
the end of his life and his celebrity as a child
prodigy. The young Mozart and his sister were
admired as phenomena that could be tested by
musicians, analysed by philosophers, and coaxed
and wheedled by European princesses. But that
was not all. Their very existence seemed a
manifestation of divine grace in keeping with the
concept of the miraculous which was still widely
current at that time. The general public was more
than ready to admire the image of the child
prodigy. Mozart's final years, and the ever-
widening gap between current musical conven¬
tions and his own style were unable to affect this
^wuui.u
DON JUAN
-" '-/4
CAMILLE SCHUBERT
Mozart for the ballroom.
Dance music based on
Mozart's Don Giovanni.
(19th-century French
engraving).
28
Method of composition
Mozart prefered to play at night and, as the work was often needed
in a hurry, the effect that this had on his frail constitution can
easily be imagined. He wrote everything with an ease and lightness
which could at first sight seem like haste. He never used a
harpsichord when composing. His imagination delivered the work
up to him in its entirety, clearly and vividly delineated, as soon as
it had been begun. His great knowledge of composition enabled him
to take in the whole harmonic structure at a stroke. His rough
scores rarely contain any passages that have been, crossed out or
deleted. This does not mean that he composed his works on the page
in the twinkling of an eye. The work was always completed in his
head before he put pen to paper. When he was given words to set to
music, he devoted a great deal of time and thought to them and
then gave free rein to his imagination. He went on develop his ideas
fully on the harpsichord, then began writing. For him, writing was
an easy task and while engaged in it he would often laugh and joke.
Franz Xaver Niemetschek (1766-1849)
Czech composer, author of a biography of Mozart published in Prague in 1798.
limited vision. When in the middle of his life
Mozart chose freedom of personal expression, he
experienced increasing solitude. What posterity
considers a prodigious step forward in quality was
greeted by his contemporaries with amazement
and incomprehension.
The operas and chamber music in particular
aroused hostility. Haydn, who had developed the
classical string quartet from galante music, was
seen as a conciliator. He knew how to make the
new musical genre acceptable to music-lovers and
connoisseurs. Mozart, whose composition of
string quartets was so close to Haydn, was fiercely
criticized. In 1782 in the "Musikalischen Kunst-
magasin", the influential Berlin composer Johann
Friedrich Reichardt openly criticized Mozart's
instrumental music for being "extremely
unnatural" since it is "first joyful then suddenly
sad and then, just as abruptly, joyful again."
According to Nissen, one of Mozart's first
biographers, when Mozart's friend and publisher,
the composer Anton Hoffmeister, handed over
to Mozart the royalties for the quartets for piano
and strings (K. 478 and K. 493) which were selling
poorly, he begged him not to compose the other
four quartets included in the contract and advised
him to "Write in the popular style, otherwise I
cannot pay for or print anything else for you."
To set against this lack of understanding there
is the famous verdict which Haydn sent to
Leopold Mozart in February 1785, just after he
had heard the last and most audacious of the
quartets Mozart had dedicated to him, the "Dis¬
sonances" (K. 465). "I tell you before God,"
Haydn wrote, "your son is the greatest composer
known to me in person or by name: he has taste,
and what is more the greatest knowledge of com¬
position." Between the demands of his art and
the expectations of the public, there was no place
for Mozart's genius in his own time. Goethe
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
suffered a similar fate. Why? A genius of equal
stature, he made a similar attempt to accept
historicity while also sapping it from within. This
conflict ended in an act of renunciation, both the¬
oretical and practical. The writer who did not
belong to his time decided not to publish part 2
of Faust even though it was completed. He
refused to allow his central preoccupation to be
set before his contemporaries in his lifetime.
Goethe's legacy to Mozart
This isolation culminated in the paradox of an
existence divided between representativity and
marginality. Goethe lived much longer than
Mozart. After his youthful successes with Götz
and Werther, Goethe gradually ascended to a
"sovereign height"though this is not apparent
if we look at the long sequence of crises and
failures, half-successes and disappointments which
he experienced, a disharmony between a man and
his age which several times led him to flight.
Iphigenia, sister-figure of Mozart's Pamina, is part
of this flightthe play was, incidentally, a literary
failure. The same phenomenon can be seen in
Goethe's designation, four years before his own
death and thirty-seven years after that of Mozart,
of the musician as testamentary executor of his
"central preoccupation", namely his Faust.
The solitary writer of the Restoration,
hemmed in by the champions of Germanity and
by liberals, caught between ancients and moderns,
chose Mozart as posthumous witness of his
untimeliness and entrusted to him his great work.
This drama which expresses a disconcerting
hostility towards his age, albeit tempered by
irony and symbolism, this tragi-comedy of
humanity and its errors, Goethe handed to the
creator of Don Giovanni. His faithful secretary
Eckermann noted on 12 February 1829 that
"Mozart should have composed the music for
Faust."
Goethe, citizen of the world and inhabitant
of Weimar, cosmopolitan and provincial, subject
of a kingdom located somewhere between "no
longer" and "not yet", could be sociologically
defined as a transitional phase between the pre- and
post-bourgeoisie. In a letter dated 3 November
1820 he noted "... There are still many . . . fan¬
tastic errors. Our friend Faust should pass that
way too." Perhaps only Mozart could have com¬
posed the music to accompany these "fantastic
errors", this Faustian story, immemorial yet ever
topical, in which man passes from illusion to dis¬
appointment, a tale of love and violence, of war
and economic intoxication, right up to the final
moments of grace and redemption.
Goethe was certain that only Mozart could
have managed this successfully. The music
appropriate to Faust must contain elements that
are "repugnant, frightful and repellent," he
wrote, "and that would displease my contem¬
poraries. The music should be in the spirit oí Don
Giovanni. " For Goethe, Mozart's opera also con¬
tained features that were repugnant, frightful and
repellent, and he situated it at the opposite pole
to that of the Apollonian, solar grace, which
would give the age an aura that Wagner called
a "Mozartian ethos of love and light".
Goethe's Faust also has repellent features. In
his Xenies, Goethe said that the hero of Faust was
a man-devil (Teufelskerl): "The devil should be a
world unto himself/To harbour such repellent
things." On 6 May 1827, he even suggested a
parallel between the destiny of this "Teufelskerl"
and Don Giovanni's journey to hell: "There are
those who ask what idea I sought to embody in
my Faust; as if I could know and say! From
heaven to hell, passing through the world, one
could formulate it thus. . . ."
Are Faust and Don Giovanni, two hell-bent
travellers, kindred spirits? And Mozart and
Goethe? Contemporaries not of their time,
yesterday and today? Perhaps this is the secret of
their eternal timelinessnot the superior, tran¬
scendent human nature it is so often claimed that
they possessed, but rather the energy with which
each of them opened the door to the modern era.
The water spaniel (seated
Faust), by the French artist
Jean-Paul Laurens
(1838-1921).
MANFRED OSTEN,
German writer and diplomat, is
cultural adviser at the German
Embassy in Tokyo (Japan). He
has written poems, and essays
on Goethe, Mozart, Schubert
and Hölderin, and has
published many articles in
leading German newspapers.
He is currently preparing a
collection of literary portraits
of Japanese writers. 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
A long journey from obscurity
by Hugo García Robles
LATIN AMERICA
Long ignored or considered to be a composer of the second rank,
Mozart has only recently been fully recognized as a genius. The pattern
of his fortunes in Latin America illustrates these whims ofposterity.
I
30
N 1791, the year of Mozart's death, a little-
known musician of Salamanca in Spain published
a pamphlet ranking the composers of his day in
order of merit. The hit parade he produced says
much about the tastes and prejudices of the time.
In it one can read: "If Apollo, noted among the
gods for the beautiful music of his lyre, was to
come down among us, what eulogies would he
not deliver for the celebrated Antonio Lolli,
Manuel Carreras, Melchor Ronci or Jaime
Roquillas? Let him hear the compositions and
concerti of the great Joseph Haydn and Ignaz
Pleyel, or of our own countryman Josef Castel
. . . not to mention the works of Paesiello and
Cimarosa for the theatre."
Antonio Lolli often toured Spain as a
standard-bearer for Italian violin music, which no
doubt explains his presence on the list. Josef
Castel was a Spaniard who belonged to the world
of the theatre, of the musical interludes known as
tonadillas and of the opera, where Paesiello and
Cimarosa were also noted figures. Haydn and
Pleyel, great names both, represented instrumental
music.
Mozart's name, however, is conspicuous by
its absence. And the same neglect is evident in
another contemporary source, Tomás de Iriarte's
poem La Música, in which Haydn is frequently
praised.
There are indications of the same attitude in
paintings of the time. When Goya portrayed the
Duke of Alba, he chose to exalt his patron's
musical talents by showing him leaning on a
piano on which rests a violin, an instrument the
Duke played with a virtuoso's skill. In his hand he
holds a composition bearing the name of Haydn.
The passion for Haydn was shared by those
well-informed music-lovers the Dukes of
Benavente, who were also at the time supporting
Luigi Boccherini, without doubt the most impor¬
tant composer resident in the country. In
October 1783 they signed a contract at the palace
of Esterhazy that entitled them to take to Madrid
all the works of the master that were not already
covered by copyright.
Yet it was not only in the Spanish capital that
Haydn was glorified and Mozart ignored. When
Haydn died in 1809, he was accorded the honour
of a state funeral, and Napoleon's army escorted
him to his final resting-place. The composer of
The Marriage ofFigaro, however, ended up in a
pauper's grave.
Yet tastes were already starting to change.
Notwithstanding the profound admiration felt by
the aristocracy for such masters as Haydn and
Boccherini, whose music graced many a stately
home, a new vogue was emerging. Romanticism
was about to explode on the world, and the
theatre was to be the place where the new sensi¬
bility would find its fullest expression.
At the time no one realized that the struggles
of Victor Hugo and Berlioz, the battle of Her-
nani and the scandal caused by the Symphonie
Fantastique, were signs of a revolution whose
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
roots could be traced back to such works of
Mozart as Don Giovanni, The Magic Flute, and
the last symphonies of 1788.
Rossinimania
In Latin America in the closing years of the eight¬
eenth century, just before the struggle for
independence began, theatrical fashion followed
that of Madrid. Tonadillas were still in vogue.
These Spanish equivalents of the operetta featured
overtures, duets, choruses, and ballets. Their
libretti had literary pretensions, but the inspira¬
tion was clearly popular, as indeed was the music.
It was the vogue for Italian opera that spelled
the end for the tonadillas. Initially, from around
1810 to 1820, the new form was introduced
piecemeal. Arias and duets, sometimes even
whole scenes, were played on the Latin American
stage, but rarely entire works. The situation
changed after 1825, the year when the great
Spanish singer and teacher Manuel Garcia arrived
with his company in New York. This was an
important date in the development of attitudes
to opera throughout the American continent.
Garcia's production of The Barber of Seville
sparked off a movement, best described as
Rossinimania, that would only subside a quarter
of a century later when the work of the young
Verdi came into fashion.
After two successful years in New York,
Garcia moved to Mexico City, where he per¬
formed the same repertoire. Meanwhile further
south two Italian singers, the Tanni brothers,
were staging the first Italian opera ever performed
in Buenos Aires, doubtless Rossini's Barber. In
The Austrian conductor
Erich Kleiber and his
orchestra in front of the
Colón theatre, Buenos Aires
(Argentina), in 1926.
Understanding genius
Mozart's greatness shines out for all time. Even if one generation
or another refused to pay any attention to him, what would it
matter? The laws of beauty remain for ever the same and current
fashion may cast a veil over them for only a short while. Is our
age capable of appreciating Mozart? Does the world of today have
the fineness ofperception and the healthy simplicity needed to
acquire an intimate understanding ofMozart?
Edvard Grieg (1843-1907)
Norwegian composer
article on Mozart und seine Bedeutung für die musikalische Gegenwart,
published on 21 January 1906 in the Neue Freie Presse in Vienna.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
1830, three years later, Teresa Schieroni and Mar¬
garita Caravaglia took the new mode to Chile.
Their only innovation was to substitute another
Rossini opera, L'inganno felice, for the ubiquitous
Barber.
In Lima, Caracas and Rio de Janeiro the same
tunes were being playedthe roles and trills of
the ever-popular Rossini. Mozart in no way
benefited from this growing enthusiasm for
Italian opera.
In spite of the omnipresence of Italian bel
canto Mozart's music was occasionally performed.
Jose Mauricio Nunes Garcia (1767-1830), a native
of Rio de Janeiro, performed Mozart's Requiem
there as early as 1819. Introduced to music by his
mother, Nunes Garcia had been ordained a priest
in 1792 and became choirmaster of Rio's
cathedral six years later. Given the overwhelming
preference for Italian works shown by both the
city and the court, the knowledge of German
music displayed in his work is truly surprising.
Above, portrait of the Duke of
Alba by the Spanish painter
Francisco de Goya y Lucientes
(1746-1828).
Right, portrait of Peter I, King
of Portugal and Emperor of
Brazil, by Henrique J. Da Silva
(1771-1834).
Another early champion of Mozart in Latin
America was the Milanese baritone Michèle Vac-
cani. Born in 1770, his American career was to
take him the length of the continent, following
the standard itinerary later taken by the young
Toscanini. He made his debut in Rio in 1822, at
a time when the presence of the Portuguese court
lent great cultural prestige to the city, still basking
in the glory of the Braganza dynasty's baroque
heritage. In 1827, he and his wife Maria Candida
played Leporello and Zerlina in Don Giovanni
in Buenos Aires. In February of that year,
Angelita Tanni sang the role of Donna Anna.
These isolated performances were too excep¬
tional to threaten Rossini's operatic primacy. But
tastes were to change. It was a sign of the times
that, when the San Felipe theatre opened in Mon¬
tevideo in 1880, there was a place on the façade
for Mozart's name.
Towards the end of the nineteenth century,
instrumental music began to play an increasingly
important part in Latin American cultural life,
on a par with opera and the theatre. As in
Europe, musical societies and enthusiastic
amateurs were active in taking instrumental
music out of the constricting world of the salons
and into the concert hall. At first the two genres
were juxtaposed, with instrumental works and
arias often featuring on the same programme.
One sign of this change in taste can be traced
as far back as 1850, when Camilo Sivori, a vir¬
tuoso trained by Paganini, gave a recital in Mon¬
tevideo which was interrupted to allow the
orchestra of the Casa de Comedias to play the
overture to The Magic Flute. And in Santiago de
Chile in 1869, the band of the local philharmonic
society played a Mozart symphony in C, perhaps
the Linz (K. 425) or the Jupiter (K. 551).
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Design executed in Italy in
1830 for a production of Dido
(1794), an opera by the
Italian composer Giovanni
Paisiello.
HUGO GARCIA ROBLES,
Uruguayan musicologist, is a
music critic in his country and
also works with Italian Radio
and Television in the fields of
music and literature. His
publications include El cantar
opinando (1969), an essay on
songs with a social and
political message in Uruguay.
The half century from 1880 to 1930 saw an
increase in the number of concerts and the
appearance of the first philharmonic societies in
Latin America. The growing interest in classical
music was also served by new means of commu¬
nication, notably the radio and the gramophone.
Europe remained the great provider, both of
the musical compositions themselves and of the
means of appreciating them. Yet even Europe
took time to rediscover Mozart. Otto Jahn's great
biographythe first to really do justice to the
composer's geniusdid not appear until almost
a hundred years after his death, and it was not
until 1912 that the initial tomes were published
of the monumental five-volume critical and
biographical study by Theodore de Wyzewa and
Georges de Saint-Foix. Alfred Einstein's repub¬
lication of Köchel's thematic catalogue dates from
1937. All of which suggests that the belated appe¬
tite for Mozart in Latin America merely reflected
his gradual rediscovery in Europe.
Mozart in the twentieth century
In musical terms, the dark years of the 1930s and
the catastrophe of the Second World War were
beneficial for Latin America. Among the artists
who fled from racial and political persecution in
Europe to find a haven across the Atlantic were
many musicians seeking a place of exile where
they could exercise their profession. Such was the
case of the distinguished German conductors
Fritz Busch and Erich Kleiber, both eminent
Mozartians, and also of Bruno Walter, who chose
to settle in the United States for similar reasons.
Busch is particularly associated with the
Glyndebourne Festival in England, where he
made recordings of Don Giovanni, The Marriage
of Figaro and Cosi fan tutte which are sublime
examples of Mozart interpretation. But, like
Kleiber, he also directed brilliant performances
of the composer's works at the Colón Theatre
in Buenos Aires.
Both Busch (from 1935 to 1948) and Kleiber
(from 1938 to 1951) chose to pursue their careers
in Latin America. Chile, Brazil and Argentina all
benefited from their refined art, dedicated notably
to the service of Mozart. The two masters
bequeathed their passion to many Latin
American disciples, thereby doubly enriching the
cultural life of the continent.
At first Mozart's music encountered the same
indifference in Latin America as it had in late
eighteenth-century Europe. The wheel turned full
circle with the arrival of these illustrious represen¬
tatives of the culture of the old continent who
went on to put down new and vigorous roots for
Mozart's music in the New World. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
S?*"T
HI
%
rW
/%i ^ ¿M
B^ô.*- ^B* AW3Ssâ
A composer in his time
34
Johann Christian Bach (1735-1782).
Friedrich von Schiller (1759-1805).
Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1712-1778).
Georg Friedrich Handel (1685-1759).
Joseph Haydn (1732-1809).
Maria Theresa (1717-1780).
Christoph Willibald von Gluck (1714-1787).
Gotthold Ephraim Lessing (1729-1781).
9. Catherine the Great (1729-1796).
10. Carlo Goldoni (1707-1793).
11. Giovanni Paisiello (1740-1816).
12. Pierre Augustin Caron de Beaumarchais (1732-1799).
13. Immanuel Kant (1724-1804).
14. Metastasio (1698-1782).
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
BACH
Johann Sebastian Bach, the father of German
music, died in 1750. As a child Mozart studied
the work of one of Bach's sons, Carl Philipp
Emmanuel, and later met his youngest son
Johann Christian in London.
SCHILLER
Born in 1759, Johann Christoph Friedrich
Schiller, one of the greatest figures of eighteenth-
century German literature, was Mozart's exact
contemporary. Both shared the same desire for
a renaissance of German theatre.
GOETHE
Johann Wolfgang von Goethe was a great
admirer of Mozart, whom he met when Mozart
was a child. "I was about fourteen years old, and
I have a perfect recollection of this little man with
his wig and his sword." Goethe even thought
of writing a sequel to The Magic Flute.
ROUSSEAU
Bastien und Bastienne, the short German opera
Mozart composed in 1768, would never have
existed if Jean-Jacques Rousseau had not com¬
posed his opera Le Devin du village, which had
enjoyed a huge success since 1752.
RAMEAU
The French composer Jean-Philippe Rameau died
on 12 September 1764, when the Mozart family
was en route from Paris to London. His name
does not appear in the letters Leopold Mozart
wrote from Paris. By that time Rameau's star
had set.
HANDEL
During his long stay in London in 1765 the
young Mozart became aware of the importance
of the work of Georg Friedrich Handel. There¬
after his admiration for Handel never waned.
LONGHI
The Venetian painter Pietro Longhi painted
scenes from Italian life of the kind Mozart would
have seen on his first visit to Italy in 1770.
HAYDN
On a visit to Vienna in 1773 Wolfgang discovered
Joseph Haydn's series of "Sun" quartets. He too
immediately began to compose a series of string
quartets, the six "Viennese" quartets.
DIDEROT
In 1778 Leopold Mozart advised his son to make
contact in Paris with the philosopher Denis
Diderot, the chief editor of the Encydopédie.
FRANKLIN
In 1778 Benjamin Franklin was in France to
negotiate a treaty of friendship between France
and the United States. An inventor as well as a
politician, he constructed a glass harmonica for
which Mozart composed several works.
FRAGONARD
In many of his works Jean-Honoré Fragonard
portrayed scenes from eighteenth-century high
life. His reputation was at its height when Mozart
was in Paris in 1778. His famous painting The
Music Lesson was executed some ten years before.
VOLTAIRE
Mozart made these harsh comments when he
heard of the death of Voltaire in 1778: "The
Unbeliever, the two-faced master Voltaire has
died like a dog, like a brute." (3 July). A few
months later, however, he was thinking of
writing an opera based on Voltaire's spectacle
Semiramis.
MARIA THERESA
In 1780 the death of the Empress Maria Theresa,
who had so warmly welcomed Mozart the child
prodigy and then advised one of her sons against
taking him into his service, took the composer
by surprise when he was at Munich preparing
his opera Idomeneo. The reign of Joseph II began.
Mozart had a real affection for this "enlightened"
sovereign.
GLUCK
Of all Mozart's works, the opera Idomeneo, re di
Creta, first performed in Munich on 29 January
1781, is the most clearly influenced by the great
German composer Christoph Willibald von
Gluck, a key figure in the history of eighteenth-
century opera.
LESSING
Mozart's opera Die Entführing aus dem Serail,
first performed in Vienna in July 1782, cannot
be understood without reference to the German
writer Ephraim Lessing's Nathan der Weise,
which had appeared not long before. In this work
Lessing, one of the most outstanding represen¬
tatives of the German Enlightenment, develops
the principles of tolerance and reconciliation
which are those of Enlightenment philosophy.
CATHERINE
Catherine the Great of Russia was a friend of Vol¬
taire and the Encyclopaedists. She was a model
sovereign of the age of enlightened despotism.
On 8 October 1782 Mozart himself directed a
performance of Die Entführung aus dem Serail
in honour of her son who was then visiting
Vienna.
MONTGOLFIER
In 1783 the Montgolfier brothers made their first
experiments with hot-air balloons, one of which
would later be used to observe the movements
of the enemy at the battle of Fleurus.
GOLDONI
Mozart often wrote arias to texts by the Italian
playwright Carlo Goldoni and in 1783 even
thought of composing a German opera based on
one of his plays, Il servitore di due Padroni.
PAESIELLO
The Italian composer Giovanni Paesiello was one
of Mozart's true friends. They met in Vienna in
1784 when Paesiello, who had left the service of
Catherine the Great in St. Petersburg, was en
route for Naples. "It was wonderful to see how
happy they were to meet one another; their
mutual esteem was well known", said someone
who was present at the meeting.
BEAUMARCHAIS
On 27 April 1784, a play entitled La FolleJournée
ou le Mariage de Figaro was performed in Paris.
It was acclaimed by the whole of Europe, and
two years later Mozart transformed it into his
opera The Marriage of Figaro.
KANT
In 1784 the German philosopher Immanuel Kant
defined the Aufklärung, the German Enlighten¬
ment, in these terms: "It is the age of the mind
which has attained its majority and its motto is:
dare to use your reason."
FREDERICK II
Frederick the Great of Prussia was an excellent
flautist. He died in 1786. As a result of his love
of literature and the arts he became a friend of
most of the leading European intellectuals.
GAINSBOROUGH
The favourite painter of English society for
almost half a century, Thomas Gainsborough
painted portraits of many musicians. The couple
in his painting The Morning Walk could well be
the heroes of The Marriage ofFigaro, Count and
Countess Almaviva.
BEETHOVEN
In April 1787 a young musician by the name of
Ludwig van Beethoven travelled from Bonn to
Vienna in order to study with Mozart. His visit
was cut short when, after only two months, he
received the news of his mother's death.
METASTASIO
The Italian poet Pietro Antonio Metastasio was
the most prolific and celebrated librettist of
Mozart's time. He had already been dead for ten
years when Mozart composed La demenza di
Tito. The libretto by Metastasio was a classic
which had already been set to music forty-odd
times by as many composers. For his opera,
Mozart used an adaptation by Mazzola. 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
The Amazon
symphony
How music can remove
the barriers between peoples
JLn 1950 the explorer Alain Gheerbrant set off
on an expedition into the forests of the Orinoco
and Amazon Basins. He carried with him a few
records of music, among which was a Mozart
symphony, which he intended to play to the
Indian tribes he was hoping to discover there. In
his book recounting the expedition1 he describes
the meeting between Mozart and the Makiritares:
"Diego having reached the end of his song,
we put on our precious Mozart symphony. This
record really exercises a magical power over all
Indians. Despite all their hesitations, even the
young women cannnot resist: they come out of
the hut one after the other and sit down to listen.
. . . The music of Mozart possesses an indefinable
charm, in the truest sense, acting like a mysterious
potion to which no Indian is immune. On them
as on us this record has a soothing effect: one's
body relaxes and one's very soul seems to breathe.
. . . This is not the kind of music that forces
people to sit stock-still with a frozen look on their
faces. It unlocks all the most secret recesses of
one's being, it is a balm. ...
"I don't know whether music is really the
universal language it is said to be, but never will
I forget that it was thanks to a Mozart symphony
that we were able, on rare occasions, to bridge
almost entirely the gulf created between the
Indians and ourselves by centuries of 'civiliza¬
tion'	"
Mozart was by far the Indians' favourite,
much preferred to Rameau or to military music.
Alain Gheerbrant later informed the musicolo¬
gist Jean-Victor Hocquard2 that the Mozart
symphony in question was the symphony in F
major, K. 184 (composed in Salzburg in 1774).
He al~o told him how a tribal chieftain, after
hearing Mozart, suddenly said to him out of the
blue: "Since you too possess a sacred music, I can
reveal secrets to you. . . ." The explorer was thus
able to hear a story recounting the origin and des¬
cent of the gods which would not otherwise have
been divulged to him. Brigitte Massin
1. L'expédition Orénoque-
Amazone by Alain
Gheerbrant, collection
"Folio", Gallimard, Paris
1980.
2. Mozart, l'amour, la mort
by Jean-Victor Hocquard,
Librairie
Séguier/Archimbaud, Paris.
ALL
MOZART
JLNJPAPERBACK
ANTL
ON VIDEODISC
Exciting news for Mozart-lovers: all the great com¬
poser's scores are now available in paperback, at a
reasonable price in a handy format. This compila¬
tion is based on the "New Mozart edition" ("Neue
Mozart Ausgabe", NMA), a monumental edition
of the composer's entire work on scientific prin¬
ciples, representing the culmination of fifty years'
efforts by the greatest Mozart specialists and com¬
pleted only this year.
This 32,000-page edition, published in twenty
volumes, provides those who can read music with
an opportunity to familiarize themselves with all
of Mozart's works, from the most famous to the
least well-known. Readers of the new publication
will be on equal terms with those who have access
to one of the world's few major music libraries that
boast a copy of the NMA.*
Another milestone in Mozart studies is the
forthcoming general release of a videodisc, the fruits
of ten years work by Austrian film-maker Titus
Leber, which presents everything that is known
about Mozart. The videodisc has already been fea¬
tured in the great Vienna and Salzburg exhibitions
devoted to Mozart on the occasion of the two-
hundredth anniversary of his death. It contains over
6,000 still photos and excerpts from films based on
eighteenth-century sources. The method of use is
as follows: starting from a first given image and
through a series of choices made by simply pressing
on the screen, users can decide on their own line
of approach, entering Mozart's world at their own
pace, moving around in it and plunging at will into
his biography, his travels and his works.
Titus Leber has made a number of highly
acclaimed films dealing with the work of such com¬
posers as Mahler, Schubert and Berlioz. He also took
part in UNESCO's Silk Roads expedition (see page
44). His videodisc will be released to the public in
autumn 1991. Brigitte Massin M
* Wolfgang Amaäeus Mozart, Neue Ausgabe Sàmliîcher Werke (New
complete edition of Mozart's work), Bärenreiter, Kassel, Basel,
London, 1991.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF..
THE AMERICA-ANTARCTICA
CONNECTION
Recent research by American
geologists suggests that Antarctica
and North America might once
have been joined together. If
proven, this surprising connection
could explain the birth of the
Pacific Ocean, which would have
been created when North America
broke away from eastern
Antarctica, leaving a gap to be
filled with water. Geologists have
long known that the western half
of North America was separated
from another land mass some 550
million years ago. But which one?
Previously, the most commonly
held view was that it was Siberia.
EUROPE'S CELTIC PAST
A major exhibition at the Palazzo
Grassi in Venice is bringing back
to life the mysterious world of the
ancient Celts. Regarded by some
archaeologists as the first
Europeans, the Celts lived 1,400
years ago in the area between the
Upper Danube, the Rhineland,
Switzerland and the Lyons region
of France. A thousand years later
their descendants could be found
in places as far afield as Turkey
and Brittany. These peoples, who
straddled the Bronze Age and the
Iron Age, developed a distinctive
culture based on metal work. The
Venice show, "The Celts,
The First Europe", presents
outstanding pieces from the
collections of 250 museums,
including sculptures, gold and
bronze vases, pottery, tools,
weapons and jewellery.
SEA URCHINS
KANGAROO-FASHION
Researchers have discovered that
sea urchins in the Antarctic keep 4
or 5 eggs in a protective pouch
and expel them into the sea when
they are ready to hatch. This
particular mode of reproduction
must have developed in the hostile
environment of the South pole.
Sea urchins in Europe lay
thousands of eggs directly in the
surrounding water.
GAMMA RAY ASTRONOMY
A satellite called the Gamma Ray
Observatory (GRO), put into orbit
by the space shuttle Atlantis, is to
survey the gamma rays in the
universe. These powerful radiations
are a source of knowledge about
compact galaxies known as
quasars and so-called active
galaxies which may contain black
holes. Gamma ray astronomy could
not be effectively developed on
Earth as the gases in our
atmosphere act as a screen
against high-energy rays. The
17-ton Observatory is the largest
scientific satellite ever developed
by the US National Aeronautics
and Space Administration (NASA)
and the second of four "great
observatories" to be launched by
the Agency.
TOBACCO OR HEALTH
"Public places and transport:
better be tobacco-free" was the
slogan chosen for World No-
Tobacco Day, which was
celebrated on 31 May 1991 on the
initiative of the World Health
Organization (WHO). The aim was
to encourage governments,
communities, groups and
individuals to be aware
of the need for tobacco-free
public places and public transport
and of the necessity to take
action to move towards a
tobacco-free society. In many
countries laws and regulations
have already been promulgated to
this effect.
MOZART AND THE PIANISTS
OF ASIA
To commemorate the 200th
anniversary of the death of Mozart,
a competition open to young Asian
pianists will be held in Hong Kong
from 20 to 28 December 1991.
Competitors should be under the
age of 28 and citizens of one of
the following territories: China,
Hong Kong, Indonesia, Japan,
Korea, Macau, Malaysia,
Philippines, Singapore, Taiwan and
Thailand. The final concert of the
competition will be televised in
Hong Kong and via satellite to
countries in the Asian Pacific
region.
Deadline for applications:
15 August 1991
For all inquiries and
correspondence:
Mozart Bicentenary Piano
Competition of Asia
Radio 4, RTHK (Radio
Television Hong Kong)
30 Broadcast Drive
Kowloon
Hong Kong
Tel: 852-339 6455
Fax: 852-338 0279
THE REFUGEE PROBLEM
According to figures issued in April
1991 by the Office of the UN High
Commissioner for Refugees
(UNHCR), there are more than 15
million displaced persons in the
world. Some migratory movements
are on the increase, especially in
black Africa where there are
already more than 4.5 million
refugees. In Asia the situation
appears somewhat more stable. In
Latin America, according to the
latest statistics from UNHCR, there
are 1,200,000 refugees. In the
case of Europe a distinction has to
be drawn between "true"
refugees, who fear for their safety
in their own countries, and those
who are lured by the mirage of the
consumer society. According to
figures supplied by UNHCR, the
number of persons seeking asylum
in the industrialized countries of
Europe and North America at the
end of 1990 was 1,687,200, as
against 222,320 ¡n 1986.
IT'S NO JOKE BEING
LEFT-HANDED
According to a study published in
the New England Journal of
Medicine, left-handed people have
statistically a smaller chance of
living to an advanced age than
right-handed people. In the United
States 13% of those under 20 are
left-handed, and less than 1% of
those over 80. Right-handed
people live on average 9 years
more than the left-handed, who
are 6 times more likely than others
to die accidentally, most often in a
traffic accident. The authors of the
study believe that this is because
left-handed people live in a world
designed for the right-handed. In a
study published in 1989, a
Canadian psychologist specializing
in laterality had already reached
much the same conclusions, with
some qualifications. Napoleon,
Charlie Chaplin and Albert Einstein
have been among the world's
noted left-handers.
THE SECRETS OF SMELL
Scientists are beginning to
understand the mechanism of
smell, the most mysterious of our
senses Two biologists at Columbia
University, New York, have recently
identified a family of "smell
genes" which produce the
thousand or so smell receptors in
the nose, enabling us to recognize
nearly 10,000 different smells.
When recognizing colours, the
human eye uses only three types
of photoreceptors which pass on
signals for interpretation by the
brain. Smells on the other hand
are perceived directly in the nose,
with very small use being made of
our mental capacities. The sense
of smell developed at a very early
stage in human evolution, long
before hearing and sight.
GREAT BALLS OF FIRE
Two Japanese scientists have
succeeded in creating under
laboratory conditions the
mysterious balls of fire that are
often observed during
thunderstorms. The red, orange,
blue or white spheres sometimes
pass through closed windows and
burn everything they touch. In
other cases they do not give out
heat and vanish with a muffled
thud or with a terrifying bang. The
Soviet scientist Pyotr Kapltsa, who
won the Nobel prize for physics in
1978, thought that they might
consist of plasma, which is
sometimes referred to as the 4th
state of matter, distinct from the
solid, liquid and gaseous states.
The Japanese experiment,
described in the British scientific
journal Nature, confirms his
theory.
THE LEFTOVERS FROM
POMPEII
Fruit, vegetables and seeds
carbonized as a result of the
eruption of Mt. Vesuvius, which
buried the city of Pompeii under
ashes in 79 AD, have been
identified and itemized at the
instigation of two American
researchers. This inventory
enables us to form a picture of
the agricultural life and food
resources of the region
in the first century AD. The
cereals include a variety of wheat
still used by plant-breeders
because of its resistance to
disease. For dessert, the
Pompeiians preferred dates, bitter
cherries, hazelnuts,
almonds and chestnuts to
walnuts and pears (probably
baked), while pine kernels were a
prized delicacy. Other finds were
wild apples, which can be seen on
mural paintings, and a large
quantity of pomegranates. The
bulk of cultivated products
originated from outside Italy, but
dates were the only fruit that was
totally imported.
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
¿j
- -
--».
»_ . . .
Tk roa ¿oí o
by Caroline Haardt
38
U^or¿s in italics are explained
in box on page 41
JLAMED for its thousands of prehistoric rock
paintings and engravings, Tassili N'Ajjer is
also one of the last bastions of the Tuareg
Berber pastoralists. A 1,200-metre-high plateau
shaded by cypress trees, some of which are
over a thousand years old, it rises from the
desert like a gigantic natural fortress. Its
natural and archaeological wonders are spread
over a vast areathe Tassili National Park
covers more than 80,000 square kilometres.
The first thing you notice about the high
plateau is the extraordinary verticality of the
landscape. Then, once you have got over your
initial surprise, your attention is captured by
the odd contours of the place. Curiously
eroded sandstone blocks, vertiginous canyons
and rock columns 20 to 30 metres high all bear
witness to an eventful geological past. It is
these remarkable rocks, some as massive as
buildings, others as delicate as wax tapers, that
give the region what one historian, F. Soleil-
havoup, has described as "the look of another
planet, unique, mysterious, sometimes
unnerving".
Human activity, changes in climate and
the wear and tear of time have all played a part
in radically altering the heart of Africa. It is
less than 4,000 years since the Sahara became
a desert. The valleys, canyons and stacks worn
away by erosion are the last vestiges of an
earlier, humid time. The fossil record even
indicates that, several hundred million years
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
A "forest of stone", Tassili N'Ajjer.
ago, the area formed part of the vast Silurian
sea.
Then wind took over from water, shaping
and polishing the rocks like a sculptor. What
vegetation now survives the rigours of the
desert climate does so thanks to the gueltas and
wadis. Here the tarout, the ancient cypress
unique to the Sahara, still adds a touch of
green. Olive and myrtle, lavender and
oleander, call to mind the softness of the
Mediterranean climate. Along the Iherir and
Edarène wadis, luxuriant reed-beds have sur¬
vived. Other plants such as the date palm and
the acacia play a primordial role in the Tas¬
sili ecosystem.
We are accustomed to think of the desert
as a hostile, lifeless place, so the ways in which
the surviving animal and plant species have
adapted to it seem all the more marvellous.
Most of the mammals, including the mouflon
and the gazelles, have sand-coloured coats, the
better to resist the heat and camouflage them¬
selves in its vastness. In even the most arid
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
areas rodents and reptiles survive. There are
fish in the gueltas, which also serve as staging
posts for birds migrating southwards towards
black Africa.
An open-air museum
The Tassili National Park is also one of the
world's finest open-air museums of prehistory.
The Neolithic civilization of the Sahara was
closely linked to the prevailing geological and
ecological conditions. Once the desert started
to advance, the people gradually lost much of
their nomadic character.
The region's rock paintings illustrate the
animals that were crucial to the survival of the
inhabitants of Tassili at different periods in
their history. It is possible to distinguish four
separate eras via the prevailing fauna, though
historians have not established a unanimously
accepted chronology for them.
The first is that of the bubal or great
buffalo, which is depicted in rock art from
about 7000 to 4000 BC. Elephants,
rhinoceroses and various savannah antelopes
are all typical of this period. Oxen appear
around 4000 BC. They are depicted without
humps, and with hprns that are short or splen¬
didly lyre-like. After 1500 BC horses make
their appearance, and finally, around 1500 AD,
camels. About this time the first written
characters in the Tuareg tifmagh script can also
be observed.
Three main styles
There are three principal modes in Tassili's
rock art. Size and symbolism are characteristic
of the first, archaic manner. The animals are
gigantic and are often represented in isolation;
only magic seems to have been capable of
coping with their terrible force. Simply drawn
in the bubal style, they are depicted with an
acute sense of observation. Along Wadi Djerat
4,000 separate figures have been itemized. One
bestiary stretching over 120 square metres fea¬
tures giraffes 8 metres high: it is the largest
complex of prehistoric engravings in the
world.
The appearance of antelopes and mouflons
marks the start of a second sub-period within
the archaic style. The beasts are more often
painted than engraved, and they are pursued
by hunters with round heads. One can sense
the presence of totem animals, masked men
and ritual dances. As well as single figures,
groups are depicted in frescoes whose splen¬
dours can be admired at Iharen or Séfar.
The second style, best typified at the Jab-
baren site, is naturalistic. The images are
Round-headed figure (Séfar).
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
smaller and more brightly coloured, reflecting
a more sedentary lifestyle. Humankind is now
in charge, dominating the surrounding
animals.
The final mode is schematic or even
abstract. The engravings are less finely
executed, but the paintings are more elegant
and skilful. There are wonderfully stylized
horses, chariots andlaterdromedaries. The
use of a wash technique allows for delicate por¬
trayals such as the tender scene at Iharen in
which a young antelope is shown being
suckled by its mother.
The sites
Where are these works of rock art? Hardly
any of them are to be found in the so-called
"forests of stone". The strangest paintings are
in the heart of the "towns" of Tassili, such
as Séfar and Jabbaren. F. Soleilhavoup has even
suggested that there may have been a sanctuary
where rituals were practised by Neolithic men
in the archaic period.
The naturalistic works on the other hand,
showing everyday scenes from the life of the
shepherds and their flocks, are most often situ¬
ated in isolated spots outside the towns, while
the third, schematic style is best represented
on standing stones in the regs, or stony deserts,
where late works depicting camels point to the
degeneration of rock art.
The wall paintings of Tassili provide
glimpses of a whole society, its everyday life
and the animals that were essential to it. The
works indicate that a revolution took place
in the region sometime in the Neolithic
period, linked to the change from a hunter-
gatherer lifestyle to one based on agriculture.
Nevertheless, many mysteries still remain.
Among them are:
The techniques used in rock art. The
engravings generally seem to predate the
paintings, yet at Tissoukai the existence of
carved sketches suggests that the stone may
have been engraved before the paintings were
executed. Sculpture is rare in Tassili; the only
examples are miniatures like the resting
ruminant at Wadi Amazzar.
The lack ofhomogeneity within each style.
The archaic manner, for instance, is very
diverse. There is nothing to link the bull at
Séfar with the masked figures also depicted
there.
The secret world of magic and religion.
What do the two-headed bulls at Wadi Djerat
signify? What is the meaning of the magnifi¬
cent spiral engraved on the great buffalo at the
same site? Is it a symbol of the continuity of
life? Or did it form part of a spell cast on the
40 animal, as in hunting rites elsewhere?
Three fine examples
of Tassili rock art.
From top:
deer; an archer; animal in the bubal style.
Problems ofdating. It was once thought that
the Neolithic civilization of the Sahara was
later than those of North Africa, Egypt and
the Middle East. Now scholars tend to believe
the opposite, maintaining that the Saharan cul¬
ture was independent of and even earlier than
the artistic flowering of Egypt. André Malraux
considered the zoomorphic heads of Wadi
Djerat to be "préfigurations of Egyptian zool-
atry". If this is the case, Saharan representa¬
tions of cattle with discs between their horns
may be earlier than Egyptian images of the
cow-goddess Hathor. As for the war-chariots
of Tassili and Fezzan, their origins are still
swathed in mystery.
The spectacle of this rock art, executed by
generations of Tuareg and handed down
almost intact to the present day, arouses strong
emotions in the viewer. Despite their image
as "lords of the desert", warriors living in a
hierarchical society, the Tuareg were in fact
primarily herdsmen. According to one
historian, J.D. Clark, they appeared less than
5,000 years ago, and led their flocks through
the Sahara until the time when increasing
desiccation drove them out.
Of all African peoples, it was the Tuareg,
together with the Peul and the Masai, who
remained most strongly committed to the
pastoral life, which they refused to combine
with arable farming. They also tamed and
herded the biggest flocks. The sparse Tuareg
population commuted seasonally between the
desert regions of the Sahara and the high
plateaux, the Hoggar and Tibesti as well as
Tassili. Pastoral skills were passed on from
father to son. The herders learned how to find
their bearings in the desert, how to read the
stars and recognize plants.
Now a growing population and changing
ways have created new pressures. Djanet, with
between 5,000 and 6,000 inhabitants, Illizi and
other centres have become the focus of a rela¬
tively sedentary lifestyle that the former
nomads do not always handle well.
Knowledge of skills is no longer being trans¬
mitted from generation to generation. And on
top of these problems, the arrival of tourists
has forced the Tuareg to come to terms with
a radical change in their way of life.
Why the heritage is in danger
The cliff walls themselves are at risk. Exposed
to the desert winds and eroding particles of
sand, they are showing signs of age. As the
sandstone base starts to break up, rock
crumbles, paintings lose their colour and
engravings the sharpness of their line. The
ageing of the rock is also leading to flaking,
discolouration, encrustation, Assuring,
blotching, and the growth of lichens. Other
problems include oxydization and rainwater
run-off on the walls themselves, and the
damage caused by nests of flies.
Now, however, a new danger has been
added to the wear and tear of time. The Sahara
has become fashionable, and anarchic forms
of tourism are developing, bringing in their
wake a host of threats to Tassili's natural and
cultural environment. Vandalism is one
problemsome supposed lovers of the past do
not scruple to break off pieces of rock as sou¬
venirs. One person was arrested at Djanet air¬
port with more than 800 archaeological
specimens. Paintings and engravings are
harshly treated. Photographers have been
known to scratch or dampen the rock to bring
out line or colour, or even to touch up the
images. Sometimes graffiti are added as a joke.
The pristine desert is being polluted.
Camps have no lavatories, rubbish is left
behind, scant water resources are abused,
gueltas are fouled. The natural pastures of Tas¬
sili, used for grazing since the Neolithic era,
are today menaced by the gathering of fuel for
cooking and by the comings and goings of
vehicles off the recognized trails. It is hard to
judge how much damage is being done by
unauthorized hunting, but certainly there is
a great demand for mouflon and gazelle, as
well as for the flesh of some reptiles.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
What can be done
to preserve Tassili?
The idea is to preserve the heritage while also
opening it up to visitors in a way that will not
threaten its natural and cultural riches. For
some years now, UNESCO has been working
with the Algerian government and, locally,
with the Tassili National Park authorities to
promote acceptable forms of tourism. The
accent is on stricter supervision of the park
and on the training of guides.
Yet some local agencies seem completely
unaware of the importance of Tassili's
inheritance. Instead of protecting it, they drum
up business by promising to take clients to off-
limits sites and encouraging them to swim in
the watercourses, and even to take away rock
fragments as souvenirs. Sometimes they fail
to bury the rubbish from their camps; and
they permit long evenings round the camp-
fire when it is vital to economize on firewood.
These unscrupulous operators should not be
allowed to cash in on the attraction of
unspoiled sites, and clandestine archaeological
excavations should be discouraged.
The preservation of the cultural heritage
will require clearly thought-out conservation
and security measures. All the rock art will
need to be inventoried, and a guttering system
will have to be installed to protect the works
from rainwater run-off. Sand barriers will have
to be constructed to ensure that visitors keep
their distance.
Various ways of preserving the paintings
and engravings are being tested. Since 1982
UNESCO has operated a solar-powered
laboratory in the area and is working on
samples from the worst-affected sites. The
International Centre for Conservation
(ICCROM) is experimenting with the appli¬
cation of silicone to preserve the paintings.
Another crucial problem is that of con¬
serving Tassili's extraordinary natural environ¬
ment. As part of a solution, tourists must be
persuaded not to pollute the desert. Clear
instructions must be given about the gathering
of wood, and visitors must be made to under¬
stand that the maintenance of water resources
is crucial to the ecosystem.
The Tuareg will need help to adjust to the
new conditions. A pilot scheme that could
serve as a model has already been set up at
Ihérir, a magnificent site that has been at risk
since it was opened up to visitors by the
Djanet-Illisi road. The local people are being
encouraged to develop their crafts, diversify
their occupations, improve livestock raising,
and above all to protect and develop the
existing watercourses. Housing also affects the
quality of life, and a special effort will have
to be made to ensure that new buildings fit
in with the local architecture and conform to
the aesthetic imperatives of this exceptional
region.
CAROLINE HAARDT, French journalist, was a staff
member of UNESCO's Division of Cultural
Heritage from 1983 to 1987. She is currently
preparing an exhibition as part of the UNESCO Silk
Roads project on the Croisière Jaune, a motor rally
from Beirut to Tibet held in 1931-1932.
A guelta in Tassili.
GLOSSARY
Bubal: great buffalo
Erg: a desert region of shifting sand
Gara: sandstone butte isolated from the
plateau by erosion
Guelta: a spring in rocky terrain
Méharée: a journey by camel
Reg: stony terrain
Tarout: the Duprez cypress, of which some
300 have survived, almost all a thousand
years old
Tassili: plateau
Tif'magh: writing used by the Tuareg
FURTHER READING
General History of Africa. Vol. II. Ancient
Civilizations ofAfrica edited by G. Mokhtar.
UNESCO, Heinemann Educational Books,
London, and the University of California
Press, 1981.
The Prehistory of Africa by J.D. Clark.
Thames & Hudson, London 1970.
»Ala découverte du Parc national du Tassili
N'Ajjer by B. Bousquet. UNESCO 1989
Les rupestres sahariennes sont-
elles menacées? by F. Soleilhavoup, Algiers
1978.
Eating in Tassili
The traditional dish is tadjela, a wheatflour
pancake cooked in ashes and mixed with
chorba, a soup based on flour paste and
tomato sauce.
Legislation
1972: creation of the Tassili National Park
and the OPNT (Office du Parc National du
Tassili)
1982: inscription on the World Heritage List
as an outstanding cultural and natural
property
1986: classification of the park as a
biosphere reserve (UNESCO's Man and the
Biosphere programme)
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
hm mmttm to action by Charles Hopkins
it is in the minds of men that the strongest
defences of the environment can be con¬
structed. Environmental education is an essen¬
tial element in these defences and one with
great potential to provide assistance in the
quest to save the planet. Its aim is to raise the
awareness and understanding of all people,
from their childhood onwards, of the physical
and biological systems that support life on
Earth, to which they belong and upon which
they can act positively or negatively.
In 1977, an international conference was
organized by UNESCO and the United
Nations Environment Programme (UNEP) in
Tbilisi (USSR) to provide ideas and leadership
for an international programme in environ¬
mental education. While this was a major
global launch and implied recognition of the
importance of the subject, it was not the begin¬
ning of the concept. Before then educators had
recognized the need for environmental edu¬
cation and had begun a number of small
programmes tailored to local needs and con¬
ditions.
In the industrialized countries, such estab¬
lished activities as nature study, conservation
education and outdoor education, which had
focussed largely on education in the outdoors
and about nature, began educating/or the out¬
doors and/or the conservation of nature. Non
governmental organizations also launched
activities which highlighted the plight of the
environment and developed advocacy
programmes to protect it. By the mid-1970s,
a few urban environmental studies projects
had even emerged, as a response to the
growing impact of cities on the natural
"The aim of environmental education
is to raise people's awareness
and understanding of the physical and
biological systems to which they belong."
environment. Several universities began to
include environmental education in teacher
training. Classroom materials aimed at
addressing this new concern of students,
parents and educators were produced by a
number of countries and organizations.
In the developing world, environmental
education programmes were particularly
aimed at the workplace and at decision-makers
in government and industry. To take but one
example, agricultural workers handling and
applying fertilizers and pesticides, often for the
first time as part of local "green revolutions",
needed vocationally-oriented environmental
education. Environmental education and
training were sought to assist professionals in
such diverse fields as wildlife management and
urban planning.
In all regions of the world, educators
working in this new field were and are ham¬
pered by a host of similar problems. Most have
no environmental education training them¬
selves, the topic being barely twenty years old.
There is often no overall conceptual frame¬
work within which to organize programmes
or curricula. Equipment for "hands-on" dis¬
covery approaches is scarce, and the media,
advertising, and non-governmental organiza¬
tions provide an abundance of contradictory
information about environmental issues.
"Educators working in this new field are hampered by the fact that most
have no environmental education training themselves."
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Educating the consumer
While too many people live in total poverty
or in regions where consumer choice is a
luxury, there are still several billion who can
make a difference through their purchases.
Today enough of them are crossing the
environmental apathy line and changing their
life styles and purchasing habits to encourage
corporations and governments to address the
"green" marketing issue. Ecomark in Japan,
Eco-logo in Canada and the Blue Angel
programme in Germany are but the begin¬
nings. While these programmes are founded
on scientific research, much of the informa¬
tion upon which people are basing their new
"eco-actions" is fragmented and in some cases
totally erroneous. Society's actions must be
based on environmental literacyaccess to
information and the competence to understand
the overall significance of that information.
The consequences of an environmentally
illiterate society are incalculable, but enough
of them have become apparent to persuade
governments and leaders of industry to address
the situation. It is costly to repair ecological
damage caused unintentionally by the general
public, such as the disposal of toxic or
hazardous waste into domestic sewer systems
or the cavalier use of non-renewable commodi¬
ties. It is often said that environmental damage
costs about ten times as much to correct as
to prevent.
In a similar vein, ecological damage caused
unintentionally by employees not only costs
their employers money in fines, restoration,
restitution and lost raw material, it also has
an impact on their firm's image and eventu¬
ally on its sales. This type of damage may
trigger off emotional campaigns against the
firms in question by citizen activist groups and
thus actually jeopardize large-scale corporate
investment. It is both difficult and expensive
to overcome a negative image of this kind.
A desperate need for the jobs created by
industry may pressure an environmentally
illiterate community to accept an ecologically
inappropriate enterprise. Ironically, the com¬
munity may find that by allowing its ground¬
water or other resources to become polluted
it is jeopardizing its possibilities of attracting
"Decision-makers are
in particular need
of environmental education
programmes."
i 	
UNESCO IN ACTION
ENVIRONMENT
ecologically sound projects in the future. Even¬
tually, the community may find that the costs
of remedying environmental damage caused
to the site may outweigh any benefits from
the operation.
Environmental education must be re¬
examined in this new perspective of interac¬
tions between the public, industry, govern¬
mental and non-governmental action. The
early diagnosis is not encouraging. No country
has achieved the goals set forth at Tbilisi
fifteen years ago. It is not that the goals were
unattainable or insufficiently important, but
rather that the available resources in the tradi¬
tional spheres of education have been insuffi¬
cient. Environmental education has been
approached in a traditional way, and tradi¬
tional sectors have tried to cope using existing
resources. This effort is totally inadequate.
Breaking down the barriers
between business, government
and education
It is time to explore new partnerships in
environmental education. All those involved
must learn to work synergistically. The com¬
bined energies of a multi-sectoral, multi
national and interdisciplinary approach must
be sought and mobilized. The forthcoming
UN Conference on Environment and
Development which will take place in Brazil
in 1992 will provide an opportunity to pro¬
mote this new approach at the highest level.
Advertising and public relations can
indirectly support teacher training, and the
media and publishing can produce learning
materials that highlight areas of environmental
consensus and areas of disagreement. Let us
teach the citizens of the future basic
philosophical principles to follow, the ques¬
tions to ask, and methods of interpreting data.
Let the communications industry explore
ways of using new technologiesespecially in
the developing worldto help all nations and
cultures share their environmental knowledge.
We all have much to learn regarding such
issues as development, biodiversity, environ¬
mental accounting and global trade.
Educators themselves must learn to work
with the community and ensure that curricula
are relevant both locally and internationally.
This will be difficult in some countries, where
years of mistrust have built up between busi¬
ness, government and education. The task
ahead for educators, for the media, for
industry and for governments alike, is formid¬
able. It is also urgent if we are to reconcile our
technological world with our environment
and with our traditional values and cultures.
CHARLES HOPKINS, Canadian educator, is a School
Superintendent for the Toronto Board of Education.
He is a former director of several field study centres
in environmental education and is currently assisting
in the preparation of the United Nations Conference
on Environment and Development in the area of edu¬
cation and training.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Ik %k ojÄ ad tk Mm ofAto
by François-Bernard Huyghe
lis UNESCO's Maritime Silk Roads expe¬
dition set sail from the Chinese port of Quan¬
zhou on 19 February 1991, crowds of school¬
children gave us a rousing send-off from the
quayside, waving flowers, streamers, and card¬
board lions and dragons. Our ship the Fulk
al-Salamah's two visits to China had taken
place in an atmosphere of constant festivity.
In addition to our scholarly work, the mara¬
thon seminars and visits to historic sites, many
less serious moments were still fresh in our
memory. Whole villages had turned out to
greet us. We had been entertained with fire¬
work displays (our arrival had coincided with
the Chinese New Year) and acrobats. There
had been many colourful scenes and much
laughter.
Our hosts had spared no efforts to give
the expedition a spectacular welcome. They
had deepened a harbour so that the Fulk al-
Salamah could enter, built a museum, and
brought forward by several weeks the spring
parade in which thousands of people take part.
In addition to this generosity we would not
soon forget the infectious joy and vitality of
the Chinese.
Thus we began the last part of our
journey. We were about to follow a branch
of the maritime silk route that would lead to
its easternmost extremity.
Before making for Japan, our ship sailed
for Korea, where the links between China and
Japan were forged in the ancient kingdom of
Silla, once a meeting place for the peoples of
central Asia and the Far East, for the mari¬
time route and the land route across the
steppes. Our port of call was Kyongju, which
was the capital of Silla for a thousand years.
In the last century of the pre-Christian era,
this region was settled by the Si-Ro, one of
many tribes of obscure, possibly Ural-Altaic
origins, which occupied the Korean peninsula.
After a conflict which lasted several centuries
and was often arbitrated by the Chinese, Silla
conquered and subjugated the rival kingdoms
44 of Paekche in 660 and Koguryo in 668, before
Above, one of the statues guarding
the burial mound of King Kwaenung in the
Korean city of Kyongju, formerly the capital of
the kingdom of Silla.
Top, Chinese children welcoming
the Silk Roads expedition.
driving out Chinese troops. This kingdom,
known as "Unified Silla", lasted until 935.
Silla or the age of friendship
The golden age of Silla, from the seventh to
the ninth centuries, coincided in China with
the consolidation of the political power of the
T'ang, who reunified the empire, and in Japan
with the victory of the central government
over the clans. This period of political stability
was also a period of intensive political, com¬
mercial and cultural exchanges which estab
lished via the Silk Roads what a speaker at one
seminar in Japan was to call "the age of friend¬
ship" between the three nations.
The Unified Silla kingdom sent a hundred-
odd ambassadors to the court of the T'ang,
who were in theory sovereign rulers. China
sent ambassadors in return. As a result of these
diplomatic missions Silla came into possession
of Chinese writings such as the Taoist classic
the Tao-te Ching and important Confucian
texts, and sent students to study in China,
whence they returned with more treasures for
Korean scholars.
Korean envoys also journeyed to
Maracanda (present-day Samarkand), the cap¬
ital of Sogdiana. Late-seventh-century wall
paintings discovered in Samarkand show
figures dressed in the Korean style among the
delegations received by the ruler of Sogdiana.
Perhaps, as a Korean scholar suggested during
a seminar held at Pusan, they were envoys of
the Koguryo kingdom who were in
Maracanda to negotiate an alliance to coun¬
terbalance that which the rival Silla kingdom
was working out with China.
By way of trade or tribute, Silla sent to
China horses, artefacts produced by its excel¬
lent jewellers and metalworkers, silk, which
had been cultivated ever since the first tribes
had settled in Korea, and medicinal plants. To
Japan it exported its own products and mer¬
chandise which passed through its ports,
including, oddly enough, horses and camels,
whose presence in seventh-century Japan is
mentioned in the "Written Chronicles of
Japan".
But Silla was also in contact with the Per¬
sian and Arab world, and traded with the
Muslim merchants who travelled through
China, where some of them eventually settled.
As early as the middle of the ninth century,
the writings of Arab travellers and geographers
tell of a fabulous kingdom, described by Ibn
Kurdadbih who wrote that "Beyond China
is a land where gold abounds and which is
named Silla. The Muslims who have gone
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
THE SILK ROADS
there have been charmed by the country and
tend to settle there and abandon all idea of
leaving."
Later, the Arab geographer al-Mas'udi also
penned a description of Silla, which he located
behind the Great Wall which protected men
from the demoniac hordes of Gog and Magog.
He wrote that the kingdom had been founded
by Alexander the Great, whose myth (which
kept cropping up throughout the maritime
Silk Roads expedition) here makes a surprising
appearance. Other texts describe, with greater
credibility, how Shiites sought refuge in Korea
during the Umayyad period. Many objects
discovered in Korean tombs were certainly
brought to Korea by Muslim traders.
The physical type and dress of two of the
statues we saw guarding the tumulus of King
Kwaenung at Kyongju suggest that Persian
mercenaries may have served the Silla court.
Kyongju, a city which attracted many
foreigners, enjoyed great prosperity. The court
was reputed for its luxurious way of life, and
especially for its finery. The clothes people
wore were determined by their rank, and the
common people were forbidden to wear silk
clothes or gold and silver jewelry. "The houses
of the leading ministers possessed boundless
resources", says the Chinese chronicle. "Some
of them had as many as 3,000 slaves." A Korean
historical document, the Samguk yusa (1285;
"Memorabilia of the Three Kingdoms"), says
of Kyongju that "There is not a single cottage.
The houses touch, wall follows wall. Singing
and music fill the streets without ceasing day
and night."
The Buddhist ferment
Two of the three Koreans on the Fulk al-
Salamah were musicologists, and the spotlight
was on music during our visit to Korea. On
board ship they accompanied their demonstra¬
tions, one instrumentally, the other with a fine
baritone voice, and ashore took care that the
pieces we heard were authentic. They revealed
to us a little-known musical culture, showing
the extent to which it influenced court music
in Japan and describing its origins in China,
central Asia, and in Buddhist songs. Music
gradually came to symbolize for us the cul¬
tural flowering of the Silla kingdom.
Buddhism, one of the major sources of
Korean music, was brought to Korea largely
by Chinese monks. But soon Korean monks
Above, the drum pavilion
in Toshodaiji temple, Nara (Japan).
Middle, lantern on mount Jiu-Ri, Korea.
Top, the Chumsungdae (7th century),
one of the earliest known astronomical
observatories, In Kyongju.
in their turn were setting out along the Silk
Roads to study the Buddhist canon.
One of them, Hye-cho, who travelled as far
as India at the beginning of the eighth century,
wrote a "Diary of a journey to the five coun¬
tries of India" a fragment of which was dis
covered in 1908 in the famous grottos of Dun-
Huang in western China. Writing in Chinese,
the Korean monk described various stages of
his initiatory journey, and gave details of the
different Buddhist sects and their monasteries,
the regions through which he had travelled
and the customs of the people who lived there.
The journey, which was to take him to
Kashmir and a number of central Asian coun¬
tries, provided him with opportunities to
engage in historical and political reflection,
and to observe Arab incursions into India.
Like the great Chinese pilgrims who preceded
him, Hye-cho was a witness of the great move¬
ment of intercultural contact generated by
Buddhism.
This movement is also reflected in the
flowering of Buddhist architecture and sculp¬
ture, strongly influenced by T'ang China, and
by more distant India. The Korean chronicle
even reports the Indian emperor Asoka, a
major figure in the spread of Buddhism, as
having sent a model of the image of the
Buddha directly to Korea and describes the
installation of a reproduction of it in the
temple of Hwangyong-sa. But the influence
of Buddhist art in Korea was exercised on a
culture profoundly influenced by shamanism
and the art of the steppes.
Our visit to Korea brought us into con¬
tact with another silk route, part of which
would be explored by an expedition through
the Islamic republics of the USSR between 18
April and 18 June. During a seminar in Pusan
Korean specialists described to us Korean
weapons similar to weapons discovered in
Kazakhstan and Turkestan, a Korean animal
art close to that of the Scythians, and the
presence of Uighurs in Silla.
This affinity with central Asia is nowhere
more evident than in the many royal burial
mounds at Kyongju. The wall paintings and
jewelry such as the famous Silla gold crown
with shamanistic symbols, as well as the
weapons found there, testify to a heritage that
China would not supplant.
The Shoso-in treasures
The ocean routes extend much further, and
lead firstly towards Hakata, on the island of
Kyushu, Japan. It was via this port, at once
an administrative, military and trading centre,
that relations with China and Korea were
established at a very early period. Our first 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
visit was to the remains of the Korokan, an
important guest-house where ambassadors
from Silla and China were lodged between the
seventh and the eleventh centuries. Diplo¬
matic, commercial and cultural missions set
out from Hakata, and in the eighth century,
the imperial court sent monks and students
to Chan'an, present-day Xian, in China. There
is evidence that relations with China existed as
early as the first century of the Christian era.
The maritime expedition ended at another
symbolic place, the Shoso-in repository of
imperial treasures at Nara, which was built
after the death of emperor Shomu in 756 and
is often referred to as the eastern terminus of
the silk roads. Most of the treasures were gifts
made to the Todaiji, the temple of the imperial
family, in whose precincts the Shoso-in stands,
and objects relating to an important moment
in the history of Buddhism in Japan, the con¬
secration of a giant statue known as the
Daibutsu, or Great Buddha. The immense log
building was thus a storehouse of art which
reached Japan from China along the Silk
Roads.
For thirteen centuries the Shoso-in has
preserved these treasures in a state comparable
to that which modern technology could be
expected to achieve. The building is only open
to the public once a year, and even then only
a small part of it can be visited. It is a mys¬
terious and, for scientists who would like to
understand its secrets, a somewhat frustrating
place. Scholars who have studied the collec¬
tions have identified many works produced
by T'ang craftsmen with materials brought to
China from across the sea: ivory and
rhinoceros horn from India, tropical timber,
pearls and tortoiseshell, wood from Indochina,
metal artefacts from Persia and Sogdiana.
The objects in the emperor Shomu's col¬
lection had a considerable impact on Japanese
society, introducing a new taste for foreign arts
and thus contributing to the opening of Japan
to the outside world.
The treasures of Shoso-in possess a sym¬
bolism which is perhaps even more powerful
than their outstanding aesthetic qualities. They
remind us that the silk roads were not only
a conduit for trade in everyday commodities,
and that the travellers who for centuries
braved great risks as they wended their way
in caravans, across steppe and desert or plied
the oceans in their fragile craft were also
serving an inexhaustible appetite for beauty.
FRANÇOIS-BERNARD HUYGHE, French writer
and journalist, is a former member of UNESCO's
46 Division of Cultural Heritage.
Freedom of the press:
an appeal by the Director-
General of UNESCO
On the occasion of the International Day for Freedom of the Press, 20 April
1991, the Director-General of UNESCO launched a worldwide appeal.
Throughout the world, it becomes daily more apparent that
freedom of the press ¡s a constituent of democracy and develop¬
ment. It is a constituent of democracy inasmuch as the pluralistic
expression of opinion necessarily favours openness, dialogue
and mutual respect among individuals, peoples and cultures;
a constituent of development inasmuch as the exchange of
know-how, technical information and ideas contributes to the
training of human resources, to the spread of knowledge and
to economic progress.
Unfortunately, freedom of the press is still flouted in all too
many countries. In 1990 some forty journalists were killed in the
exercise of their profession; 200 or so were imprisoned; while
others have been held hostage for years, and may already have
abandoned hope.
In addition to these breaches of the most elementary human
rights, many news organizations have been subject to censor¬
ship. For there are still those who think that by reducing people
to silence they can cover up the facts, prevent the spread of
ideas and shackle freedom of the spirit. This is gravely to
underestimate the force of the mind, the fertility of ideas and
the eloquence of facts.
Today, I call on people everywhere to defend this form of
freedom. Let each and every one of us, through individual or
collective action, demand or facilitate the release of those jour¬
nalists taken hostage or imprisoned and the lifting of politically
or economically motivated curbs on the press. Let governments
become aware of the wider implications of freedom of the press.
We shall then have won a guarantee of greater balance in the
future.
Federico Mayor
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO ISSUES
MOZART MEDAL
On the occasion of the two-
hundredth anniversary of Mozart's
death, UNESCO has issued a
medal bearing the great
composer's image. Struck by the
Paris Mint, designed and engraved
by Raymond Joly, the medal is
available in gold, silver or bronze.
Order forms may be obtained
from the UNESCO Philatelic and
Numismatic Programme,
7 Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris, France.
THE WORLD'S LITTLE SINGERS
On 21 July 1989 a unique
international children's choir was
launched when 45 youngsters
from 15 countries gave a concert
in Autun Cathedral (France) on the
occasion of the bicentenary of the
Declaration of the Rights of Man
and the Citizen. The choir, the
World's Little Singers, not only
provides children from different
cultures and backgrounds with an
opportunity to sing together, it is
also creating an extensive record
library of choral music, a
collection of musical scores and a
documentation centre. The
World's Little Singers enjoy the
support of the French Committee
for UNICEF and the official
patronage of UNESCO, which has
included them among its projects
for the World Decade for Cultural
Development. A recording of the
concert given in Autun cathedral
is available as a compact disc:
"The World's Little Singers,
inaugural concert, Cathedral of
Autun, 21 July 1989", SOCD 73
CYD 85, distributed by Solstice,
147 Rue de Bercy F-75012 Paris,
France. Tel: (1) 43 45 64 81.
THE INTERNATIONAL MUSIC
COUNCIL
The International Music Council is
a non-governmental organization
which was founded in 1949,
shortly after UNESCO, to provide
the Organization with support for
its programmes in music. The IMC
receives part of its financial
support from UNESCO and is the
principal musical organization
associated with it. Through its 65
national committees and some 20
international organizations, the
IMC is active in every continent
and reflects many aspects of
musical culture throughout the
world, ranging from Mozart to
Bolivian folk music, and from
Stockhausen to the Hat Cheo
(theatre with dance and song) of
Viet Nam.
For the last 30 years, the IMC
has been performing one of its
functions, the preservation and
promotion of forms of traditional
music which are in danger of
dying out, through the UNESCO
Collection of Traditional Music,
now available on CD and cassette
from Audivis. Every two years the
IMC organizes radio rostrums in
every continent, and an annual
International Rostrum of
Composers is held in Paris with
the participation of more than 30
national broadcasting
organizations. Over the years, this
Rostrum has revealed major works
by present-day composers like
Berio, Dutilleux, Hans Werner
Henze, Penderecki, Takemitsu and
others.
For some years now a large
International team has been
working, under the auspices of
the IMC, on the preparation of a
world encyclopaedia of music,
which will be the first work of its
kind to be produced by authors
originating from the different
world regions.
The world-wide membership
of the IMC is closely associated
with such UNESCO projects as the
Five-Hundredth Anniversary of the
Encounter between Two Worlds,
the Integral Study of the Silk
Roads, and study of the Baroque
World, for which it organizes
concerts and symposia. In this
Mozart bicentenary year, the IMC
is planning to organize in October,
through its Musicians'
International Mutual Aid Fund, a
Mozart concert for the
delegations of the 165 countries
participating in the UNESCO
General Conference.
During the IMC's 1991
General Assembly in Bonn and on
the occasion of International
Music Day, on 1 October, the
UNESCO-IMC Music Prize, already
awarded to Ephraim Amu, Munir
Bashir, Nadia Boulanger, Alberto
Ginastera, Benny Goodman,
Yehudi Menuhin and Ravi Shankar
among others, will be presented
to the winners, who will have
been selected for their standing
contribution to music and to
UNESCO's objectives.
The latest issues in the
UNESCO Collection of Traditional
Music (UNESCO/Audivis) include
"North Indian Folk Music" (D
8033) and "Tibetan Ritual" (D
8034). They are available from
UNESCO, 7 Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris, France, from record
shops, and from AUVIDIS,
12 Avenue Maurice Thorez,
F-94200 Ivry-sur-Seine, France.
UNESCO INFORMATION
SERVICES
A 70-page brochure has been
produced by UNESCO in English
and French to provide an overview
of the Organization's information
services. The Directory of
UNESCO Information Services
covers the documentation centres
and information units of UNESCO
and some non-governmental
organizations, and describes the
resources of UNESCO's main
library and the holdings of its
archives.
STUDY ABROAD
The 27th (1991) edition of
UNESCO's international guide
Study Abroad contains 2,846
entries relating to post-secondary
education and training. The
information provided, collected
from 124 countries and valid for
the academic years 1991-92,
1992-93 and 1993-94, covers
offers of scholarships and
financial assistance, university-
level courses, special preparatory
courses for admission to higher
education, short courses,
vocational training schemes,
continuing education
programmes, job opportunities for
students and information
regarding facilities for the
handicapped.
Study Abroad, 92 French
francs (including packing and
shipping costs). Copies may be
obtained from the UNESCO Press,
Sales Division, 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, France, or
from the national distributor of
UNESCO publications in your
country.
STOLEN STATUETTE
The Turkish authorities have
informed UNESCO that a precious
objectan ancient Egyptian
statuettewas stolen in July 1987
from the site where it was
originally discovered, the village of
Kale-Denizli. They also report that
the statuette was subsequently
seen in Germany, but that since
then there has been no trace of it.
The cubical (21 cm x 21 cm)
basalt sculpture (below) depicts a
human being, with the head
missing. The figure is seated, arms
folded on knees, and bears in front
and behind an inscription in Greek
containing a reference to the
Egyptian king "Psommetikhos".
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
RECENT RECORDS
listening
JAZZ
48
Stan Getz. Serenity.
Getz (tenor sax.); Kenny Barron
(piano), Rufus Reid (bass), Victor
Lewis (drums).
CD Emarcy 838770-2
In this CD, recorded at the Café
Montmartre in Copenhagen in 1987,
the late, great Stan Getz treats us
to a few standards "On Green
Dolphin Street", "I remember you"
and "I love you"and offers us
two new tunes: "Voyage" by his
pianist Kenny Barron, and "Falling in
Love" by Victor Feldman. Getz, as
lyrical as ever, is flanked by ideal
sidemen. Kenny Barron, whom I
have long considered to be one of
the best pianists around, is an
admirable accompanist whose
playing grows steadily more subtle.
He never hits a dud note and his
chord work provides the soloists
with a perfect backing. Rufus Reid,
a musician with perfect pitch, plays
a bouncing, swinging bass,
wonderfully matched by the
dazzling rhythms of Victor Lewis on
drums. Reid, Barron and Lewis have
often worked together, and the
results are there for everyone to
hear in the shape of a very tight
rhythm section which must have
been a joy to Getz. The playing of
Barron, in particular, is sometimes
even more subtle and imaginative
than that of Getz. At the Antibes
festival two years ago, he was the
star of Getz's group.
Wynton Marsalis. The Original
Soundtrack from Tune in Tomorrow.
Wes Anderson (alto sax.), Wynton
Marsalis (trumpet), Herlin Riley
(drums), Marcus Roberts (piano),
Reginald Veal (bass), Todd Williams
(alto and soprano sax. and clarinet)
with others.
CD CBS 467785-2.
Marsalis, hailed by journalists as
the "new Miles Davis" when he
appeared on the scene five or six
years ago, continues tc go his own
way, returning now to his musical
sources in New Orleans. His current
model is not so much Miles Davis
I960s-vintage as Louis Armstrong
and the contrapuntal style of the
1920s, updated and with new
harmonies. Increasingly called on
for soundtrack music, he has
proved more than capable of
meeting the challenge, as is
demonstrated by this recording. All
the compositions are by him except
for one, "I can't get started". Some
of the tracks also feature the
clarinet of Alvin Batiste and the
voice of Shirley Horn, whose latest
record has Wynton as guest
performer. Mario Vargas Llosa, the
author of Aunt Julia and the
Scriptwriter, on which the film is
based, must surely have
appreciated this catchy music, so
close to the Latin American spirit.
Miles Davis. E.S.P.
Davis (trumpet), Wayne Shorter
(tenor sax.L Tony Williams (drums),
Ron Carter (bass), Herbie Hancock
(piano).
CD Columbia 467899 2.
This is a reissue in CD of a
landmark in the history of jazz,
featuring Miles at the head of one
of his greatest groups, which still
inspires many imitations. Seldom
has there been such a degree of
complicity among musicians,
performing here a restrained,
understated music ringed around
with silences. Hancock's note
clusters anticipate developments in
contemporary jazz, while his piano
runs, which opened up the way to
polytonality, have proved spellbinders
for many a present-day pianist. As
Miles would say to Hancock in his
shorthand jive at the time, "Don't
play the butter notes", meaning
that he should skip the expected
harmonies and find what was
essential, always making it new.
Hancock learned the lesson
wonderfully well. The drummer, Tony
Williams, does not lay down a beat
but suggests it intelligently, rapping
on an equal footing with each of
the other musicians. As for Wayne
Shorter, whose sinuous
compositions are full of invention,
his tenor saxophone soars to
soulful heights. The waltz "Little
One", "Iris" and "Mood" are
absolute masterpieces. This is
music that will never date.
Hank Jones, Dave Holland, Billy
Higgins. The Oracle.
Jones (piano), Holland (bass),
Higgins (drums).
CD Emarcy 846 376-2
Hank Jones, one of the great
heirs of bebop, belongs to a
musical family in which his famous
brothers, the cornetist Thad and
the drummer Elvin, have particularly
excelled. His is a deceptively simple
music. Hank, a smart and seasoned
jazzplayer, possesses a strict inner
logic and has an extremely subtle
way of phrasing between the beats,
defying imitation or transcription.
Solid backing is provided by Dave
Holland, who is particularly
appreciated by his fellow jazzmen
for his ability to fit in with a wide
range of musicians, from exponents
of free jazz like Anthony Braxton to
performers of mainstream. Higgins
is every jazzman's Tdeal drummer,
always good-humoured, always on
the ball. Each and every one of his
notes falls pat and his solos verge '
on perfection. All the tracks on this
CD "Beautiful Love", "Maya's
Dance" and "Jacob's Ladder" are
pure gems.
Dee Dee Bridgewater. In Montreux.
Bridgewater (vocals), Bert van den
Brink (piano), Hein van de Geyn
(bass), André Caccarelli (drums).
CD Polydor 847 913-2
The performances of the
charismatic Dee Dee Bridgewater,
who for a number of years now has
made Paris her home, are a regular
highlight of international jazz
festivals. Besides having a warm,
deep-throated voice, she is
particularly well-endowed with
physical charms which she deploys
for the greater pleasure of her
male audiences. But Bridgewater,
who sang for a long time in New
York alongside her ex-husband, the
trumpeter Cecil Bridgewater (now
with Max Roach), is not a mere
entertainer, one of those fly-by-nlght
performers who fill the hot spots of
Hollywood or Las Vegas, but a real
musician with a sure instinct.
Displaying her legendary swing, she
offers us here a vibrant, direct,
communicative jazz of which one
never tires.
POPULAR	
Mezcla. Frontera de Sueños.
Pablo Menéndez, Sonia Cornuchet,
Lucia Huergo, José Antonio Acosta,
Juan Carlos Abreu, Octavio Rodriguez
(miscellaneous instruments).
CD Intuition Records INT 3047 2
Mezcla which means "mixture"
in Spanish is a perfect example of
musical crossbreeding. This Latin
American group, which was
previously unknown to me, has
created an attractive blend of song,
synthesizer, guitar, percussion and
other instruments at the confines of
pop, nueva trova, rock and salsa.
Influences also include the music of
the Yoruba ("Ikiri Ada") and Dominica
("Ando buscando un amor"). The
last track features a guest
performance on güiro by the only
one of the musicians previously
known to methe salsa and Latin
jazz percussionist Nicky Marrero.
The music, recorded in Cologne
and mixed in New York, reminds me
at times of the Moliendo Vidrio
group, which enjoyed some success
in Puerto Rico in the 1970s.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Mustrtfiof S*y ftfnoíf
Kid Frost. Hispanic Causing Panic.
CD Virgin Records America
CDVUS 22
"Kid Frost", alias Arturo Molina
Jr., is currently the best known
name in Latin rap music. A
Chicano living in Los Angeles, he
raps in "Spanglish", a slangy
mixture of Spanish and English
spoken, in variant forms, by
young Latin Americans in United
States cities. Kid Frost pulls out
all the stops here, giving voice to
the violence of the ghettoes,
expressing his pride at belonging
to "La raza" (the Latin "race"),
and asserting his virility and
identity. This is music in the
tradition of the desafíothat
challenging stance characteristic
of Latin American and Afro-West
Indian cultures which also marks
other types of music such as jongo
in Brazil, dozens in the south of
the USA, and rumba brava in Cuba.
Frost displays an excellent sense
of rhythm and intelligent phrasing,
often lacking in European rap
performers. This is high-quality
rap with a bite to it.
Isabelle Leymarie I
CLASSICAL	'
Joseph Kosma.
Chansons + Baptiste.
J.-C. Benoit (baritone),
B. Ringeissen (piano), Orchestra of
the Paris Opera, conducted by
Serge Baudo.
CD ADES 13.292.2
In France there is a tradition of
songs with a literary flavour. One
of its main founders was Joseph
Kosma, who was born in Budapest,
spent some time in Berlin where
he worked with Brecht, and then
came to France in the early
1930s. A prolific composer of film
music this record includes the
famous pantomime written for
Baptiste, the celebrated mime
played by Jean-Louis Barrault in
Marcel Carné's Immortal film Les
enfants du paradis he has often
worked with poets, especially in
the period following the Second
World War, and notably with
Prévert, Queneau, Desnos and
Aragon. The popular success of
such songs as "La pêche à la
baleine", "Les enfants qui
s'aiment", "Les feuilles mortes"
and "Barbara", in the versions of
Les Frères Jacques, Yves Montand,
Juliette Gréco and others, should
not obscure the filiation that
exists between this kind of
songwriting, midway between high
and popular culture, and the
melodies of Fauré, Duparc,
Debussy and Ravel, as revealed
here in this distinctive version by
the baritone J.-C. Benoît.
György Kurtag. Works.
CD Hungaroton HCD 31290
György Kurtag counts as one of
the recent great revelations of
contemporary music worldwide.
Born in 1926, this very withdrawn
Hungarian composed a great deal
in the 1960s, as attested by the
two books of "piano pieces"
featured on this CD, together with
"Duos for piano and cymbalum"
and numerous "pieces for voice"
inspired by poets. Kurtag's style
can be described as a happy blend
of simplicity and complexity.
Considered against the background
of Hungarian folk music and the
edicts of the communist regime
at the time, his compositions
create the impression of having
found a way out of the
"intellectuality" of Western
research towards an unexpected
freshness, curiously generating an
unsuspected sense of density and
gravity. The works from the 1980s
are exceptionally brief, as though
expressing the quintessence of
Kurtag's original art.
The Waltz.
Nikita Magaloff, piano.
CD ADES 14.179.2
In nineteenth-century Venezuela,
the wealthy middle classes were
crazy about Chopin and his
waltzes, which later were a source
of inspiration to Venezuelan folk
guitarists. The exact origins of this
traditional music in triple time
remain unclear but we do know
that the Church was long opposed
to it. The great pianist Nikita
Magaloff offers us here a
panorama of the waltz in Europe,
based on Schubert, Weber and
those who, so to speak, gave it a
pedigree as a serious form. The
Strauss dynasty is featured, along
with the innovations of Liszt and
Scriabin, but also the French
contribution, with Chabrier and
Debussy, and the German and
Russian, with Moszkowski,
Levitsky and others. A panorama
of a musical form that changed
the history of music.
Einojuhani Rautavaara. Vincent.
Choirs and orchestra of the
Finnish National Opera Company,
conductor Fuat Manchurov.
Box of 2 CDs. CD Ondine ODE
750, distributed by Harmonie.
Einojuhani Rautavaara, born in
1928, is one of the main Finnish
composers of the present day. He
has to date written four operas,
drawing inspiration from the
national epic Ka/eva/a for Thorns,
his last work but one, issued on
the same label. The opera Vincent,
which is built around his vision of
the painter Van Gogh, was
successfully staged by the Finnish
National Opera Company in 1990.
It is not easy to form a good idea
of the work from a recording
because of the ambitious
technique employed, which
combines serialism and
synthesizer. However, the three
acts, organized around three of
the tormented artist's major
paintings, with Gauguin cast in a
clearly satanic role, give the
impression of a kind of vocal
hysteria which rings true with the
image we now have of Van Gogh.
Sergei Prokofiev.
Early Works.
Abdel Rahman El Bacha, piano.
CD UCD 16596
The hundredth anniversary this
year of the birth of one of the
greatest twentieth-century Russian
composers is in danger of being
somewhat eclipsed by the Mozart
bicentenary celebrations. Himself
a brilliant pianist, Prokofiev was
described by Neuhaus, the Soviet
master, as being possessed of a
determination and power combined
with a prodigious lyricism, devoid
of sentimentality. This description
is also valid, mutatis mutandis, for
this record of the composer's
earliest works (with the exception
of the first piano and violin sonata,
which dates from 1948). The
soloist here is a Lebanese-born
pianist with many prizes to his
name, including the Queen
Elisabeth of Belgium prize (1978).
His highly developed technique
goes hand in hand with a sensitive
approach which augurs well for the
recording of the complete sonatas
of Beethoven which Abdel Rahman
El Bacha is currently making for
the same label. A pianist to look
out for.
John Adams. Harmonielehre/
The Chairman Dances.
San Francisco Symphony Orchestra,
conducted by Edo de Vaart.
Box of 2 CDs. Nonesuch
7559-79115-2/979144-2
The enfant terrible of new
American music, whose Death of
Doctor Klindhoffer was recently
premiered in Brussels, after the
Houston Opera had put on the
famous Nixon in China (box of 3
CDs, Nonesuch 979177-2), is
represented here by strictly
orchestral pieces. These reveal a
highly personal style of repetitive
music, punctuated by unexpected
events which help to sustain the
listener's interest in the manner
of variations. A playful, bucolic
atmosphere is imparted by this
music, which can be said to
exemplify a worldwide trend
towards a new orchestral
romanticism, steeped in nostalgia,
which has made itself felt in film
music. However, a question
arises. This apparent simplicity
seems at one stroke to have
written off decades of
experimentation. This makes for a
more easily accessible music, but
is it not also one which is formally
less inventive?
Claude dayman I 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
What about steel bands?
As a constant reader and collector
of the UNESCO Courier, I was
delighted with the cover story "A
world of music", in the March
1991 issue. However, I am
surprised that a publication which
has gained worldwide admiration
for its coverage of cultural topics
should have omitted to make any
reference to steel bands. These
groups which play on steel drums
form part of the musical culture
of Trinidad and Tobago where
they first appeared in 1941-1942.
They have now spread all over the
world, from Brazil to China. The
quality and sound of these
instruments and the dexterity of
the players have earned them an
international reputation, with their
renditions of classical pieces from
Handel to Bach.
Derrick John Jeffrey
United Nations Secretariat
New York
Art Nouveau and the
Russian soul
For a very long time in my
country Art Nouveau, to which
you devoted your August 1990
issue of which 1 bought four
copieswas banned (buildings
pulled down, books burnt). It was
regarded, in the definition of the
Soviet Encyclopaedia, as "a
decadent bourgeois trend in
art".
For me Art Nouveau is not only
a source of inspiration but also a'
way of life and a philosophy. My
friends and I have formed an art
group which is called "Iris". It's
not an official body, but we have
already held three art exhibitions,
launched several activities and
carried out a number of projects.
We have encountered many
obstacles, but we believe in
culture and belong to a
generation that is searching for
its roots. For us there is no future
without our past.
It was during my studies at art
college that I discovered by
myself, through love of natural
forms, the principles of Art
50 Nouveau which, incidentally, was
not represented and which I was
told I should forget about.
Learning that what I was looking
for In nature did exist as Art
Nouveau style, I rediscovered
Moscow for myself by going in
search of Art Nouveau buildings
and design. But whenever I tried
to talk about it I met with the
same scornful attitude or, at best,
condescension.
And then your magazine arrived.
For me it's extraordinary. Where
before I had been told that Art
Nouveau was "superficial",
"vulgar" and "sterile", I now read
about its subtle, expressive
qualities and about what was
referred to as "architecture with a
smile". I couldn't believe my eyes.
Although I'm Russian, every stone
in Europe is very dear to me. I
admire Tiffany, Mackintosh and
Guimard as much as Shehtel,
Kekuschev, Bakst, Lidval, Korovin,
Borisov-Musatov, Vrubel and
others.
I believe that Art Nouveau did
not fully exhaust itself and that
the future belongs to it. My
country must go back to its roots
in order to rediscover its true
identity.
This is why I am appealing to
you, hoping that you can succeed
where I have failed in alerting
certain Soviet organizations to
this problem and in encouraging
them to protect the vestiges of
Art Nouveau in this country. It
would also be great to have a
museum of Art Nouveau here,
especially since, through its
cosmic inspiration, this style
admirably reflects the Russian
soul.
Solml, an artist
Moscow (USSR)
My friend the Courier
A secondary school pupil, I am
always very happy to find the
UNESCO Courier in my mail.
No other publication has such
an appeal for me. I am of course
more interested in some topics
than in others, but when
I read the magazine I feel that I
am widening my educational,
scientific and cultural horizons.
So I regard the UNESCO Courier
as a friend who brings me
knowledge and learning.
A subscriber since February
1989, I hope that this friend will
find its way into other people's
homes. It doesn't contain any
advertising singing the praises of
a perfume or vaunting the
mildness of a cigarette and it's
not too expensive.
Thank you for this book, and I
use the term advisedly as the
word "magazine" doesn't do
justice to this fine collection
of photos and texts brought
every month by my friend the
Courier.
Séverine Marotin
(aged 15)
Le Grand Baignerault
03360 Saint-Bonnet-Tronçais
(France)
Food for thought
Several of your recent issues have
focussed on important and topical
subjects. I am thinking of "The
Media, Ways to Freedom" (Sept.
1990), "Sacred Places" (Nov.
1990), "The Enigma of Beauty"
(Dec. 1990), "Cities under Stress"
(Jan. 1991), 'Somewhere,
nowhere... The Quest for Utopia"
(Feb. 1991) and "A World of
Music" (March 1991).
There are other questions,
again of central importance in our
everday lives, which to my mind
need urgently to be raised in a
magazine such as yours,
profoundly concerned with moral
issues as it is. For instance, is
nationality in itself a source of
conflict or does politics make it
so? Why is there no mutual
respect between cultures? Is this
again the' fault of politics? Is the
division between peoples due to
economic problems or is it the
result of culture?
I should be very glad to read
the answers that might be given
to these questions by a writer,
an economist, a politician and
others.
Victor H. Gutierrez
Tbilisi, Georgia (USSR)
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, page 3 (right): © Galerie
Drouart, Paris. Back cover:
© Galerie d'Art Noir
Contemporain, Paris. Page 2:
© Hajja Fatima Bakhcha,
Casablanca. Pages 4, 6, 9: AU
rights reserved. Page 5: Cecil
Fox/Science Source © Explorer,
Paris. Page 7: David
Grossman/Science Source
© Explorer, Paris. Page 8: Rauzier-
Rivière ©ARC, Paris. Pages 10-11:
© Réunion des Musées nationaux,
Paris-Musée du Louvre. Pages 12,
14, 28: ©Jean-Loup Charmet,
Paris. Page 13: © Edimedia, Paris-
Musée des châteaux de Malmaison
et Bois-Préau. Pages 15, 17:
© Jérôme da Cunha/Perrin. From
Sur les pas de Mozart, Librairie
Académique Perrin, Paris 1991.
Pages 16, 34 no. 4: © Archiv für
Kunst und Geschichte, Berlin.
Pages 18, 34 no. 12: © Edimedia,
Paris-Bibliothèque nationale, Paris.
Page 19: © Nicolas Bruant, Paris.
Page 21: © Edimedia, Paris-Musée
Marmottan, Paris. Page 22: Jacques
Moatti © Explorer, Paris. Page 23:
© Edimedia, Paris-City Museum,
Vienna. Page 24: © Edimedia,
Paris-Bibliothèque de l'Opéra,
Paris. Page 27 (left): © Giraudon,
Paris-Goethe Museum, Rome. Page
27 (right): © Luisa Ricciarini,
Milan-Museo Cívico, Bologna.
Page 29: © Roger-Viollet, Paris-
Musée d'art moderne de la ville de
Paris. Page 31: ©Colón Theatre,
Buenos Aires. Page 32 (above):
Oroñoz © Artephot, Paris-Prado
Museum, Madrid. Page 32 (below):
© Dagli Orti, Paris-Museo histórico
nacional, Rio de Janeiro. Pages 33,
34 nos.2, 6, 8, 14: Emilio-F.
Simion © Luisa Ricciarini, Milan-
Civica Racolta Bertarelli, Milan.
Page 34 no.l: © Roger-Viollet,
Patis-Museo cívico, Bologna. Page
34 no.3: FPG International
© Explorer Archives, Paris. Page
34 no.5: © Edimedia, Paris-Haydn .
Museum, Eisenstadt. OPage 34
no.7:F001 ©Jean-Loup Charmet,
Paris-Bibliothèque de l'Opéra,
Paris. Page 34 nos.9, 13:
© Explorer Archives, Paris. Page
34 no.10: © Luisa Ricciarini,
Milan-Museo del Burkado, Rome.
Page 34 no.ll: © Luisa Ricciarini,
Milan-Conservatorio di Música S.
Pietro a Maiella, Naples. Page 36:
© Hervé Bernard, Paris. Pages 38,
40 (middle), 47 (left), 47 (right):
UNESCO. Pages 39, 40 (top), 40
(bottom): UNESCO/OPNT. Page
41: UNESCO/Bousquet. Pages 42,
43: UNESCO/Ivette Fabri. Pages
44, 45: ©J.J. Boucher, Paris. Page
51: © Volvox/Vloo, Paris."
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
Published monthly In 35 languages and in braille
by UNESCO, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Michael Fmeberg
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, Carole Pajot-Font
(Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel.: 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15).
Mouna Chatta
Administrative assistant: Prithi Perera
Selection in Braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Mane-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Metra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuafa Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dares-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Slnhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kessler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88),
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65),
Joceiyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo. Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk, Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65).
Mall: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 139 French francs. 2 years: 259 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 108 French francs. 2 years: 194 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of UNESCO
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the UNESCO Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bea' author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO Courier Photo captions and headlines
are written by the UNESCO Couner staff. The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations. The UNESCO Courier
is produced in m.croform (microfilm ard/or microfiche) by: (1) UNESCO,
7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 3aris. (2) University Microfilms (Xerox),
Ann Arbor Michigan 48100, U.S.A. (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head. Inc . 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A. (4) Bell and Howell
Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) DEPOT LEGAL : Cl - JUILLET 1991.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE NO 71844 - DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP.
Photocomposition The UNESCO Courier
ahotogravure-tmpression: Maury Imprimeur S.A.,
Z.I route d'Etamaes, 45330 Malesrerbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 7 1991 -0PI-91 3 494 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Sfu
n
Élil
lili
]]>
</page>
</document>
