<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="088998eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY 1991
-"
il'liirriy
O
«
m
5
ZI
B
z
II
I'll 1 1 II
H JIl k
LL *
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
-I
encounters We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
I a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
DIALOGUE
OF CULTURES
1986, oil paintings on canvas
(50 x 60 cm)
by Helena Delgado Rufino
Inspired by the contact
between civilizations which
followed the maritime
discoveries of her
countrymen, this Portuguese
artist conveys "the enigmatic
relations between individuals
and between peoples".
Different cultures meet in her
work through the
intermingling of their myths,
heroes, gods and demons.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY 1991 CONTENTS
4
c
Interview with
DANIEL J. BOORSTIN
TheljNESCO
m ^COURIER
wíh
M»ll monthl) In II
"Th« Governments o( the States
parties to this Constitution on benalt
of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds
of men, it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments would
not be a peace which could secure
the unanimous, lasting and sincere
support of the peoples of the world.
and that the peace must therefore
be founded, if it is not to fail, upon
the intellectual and moral solidarity
of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and determined
to develop and to increase the
means of communication between
their peoples and to employ these
means for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer and more
perfect knowledge of each other's
lives..."
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of Unesco,
London. 16 November 1945
JL JL
CITIES UNDER STRESS
THE URBAN EXPERIENCE
by Wolf Tochtermann 12
CITIZENS WHO HELP THEMSELVES
by Jorge E. Hardoy and David Satterthwaite 1 7
What future for the urban past?
A NEW HEART FOR OLD CITIES
by Stefano Bianca 22
THE MUTILATION OF BUCHAREST
by Matei Lykiardopol 26
CAN LENINGRAD BE SAVED?
by Olga Nosareva 29
Planned and 'spontaneous' cities
Chandigarh
A PLANNER'S DREAM
by Roger Aujame 30
Berlin
A TESTING GROUND FOR URBANISM
by Hardt-Waltherr Hämer 33
THE SQUATTER-BUILDERS OF LIMA
41
IN BRIEF...
42
c
WORLD HERITAGE
The Jesuit missions
to the Guarani
by Caroline Haardt
44
LISTENING
Recent records
by Isabelle Leymarie and
Claude Glayman
45
ENVIRONMENT
Reviewing the accounts
by Michel Bâtisse
48
mw'r¿>-<*-<rrrrsn
THE SILK ROADS
In the wake of Marco Polo
by François-Bernard Huyghe
50
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
by Anna Wagner de Reyna
Cover: Detail of a wall
painting by Jan A. T.
Erkrich, Milwaukee,
Wisconsin (USA), 1981.
Back cover: Montage by the
Yugoslavian photographer
37 D. Stamenkovich.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
N W
Daniel T. Boorstin
The distinguished American historian
Daniel J. Boorstin directed the
Library of Congress in Washington
D.C. for twelve years and is now
Librarian of Congress Emeritus. Here
he talks about the American past
and its influence on the development
of his country's institutions.
Professor Boorstin's many books include a trilogy, The Americans (Random
House, New York, 1958-1973/Cardinal, London, 1988); The Image, A Guide
to Pseudo-Events in America (Atheneum, New York, 1988); and The Dis¬
coverers, a history of man's search to know the world and himself (Random
House, 1983/Dent, London, 1984, Penguin Books, London, 1986). He is now
at work on The Creators, a companion volume on the history of the arts.
With the movement towards democracy in Eastern
Europe, the idea that we are seeing the "end of history"
is gaining currency. As a historian, what do you think of
this?
I don't think history has any end. Moreover, I think of
history as a cautionary science, one of the purposes of which
is to warn us against just such generalizations. Historians
should not play the role of prophets. It's difficult enough
to be a historian. I think that among the excesses which
historians should caution us against are prophecies of Utopia
or Armageddon, or the beginning, or the end. These prophe¬
cies have been made again and again, more often by reli¬
gious fanatics and by people frustrated with their own lives
than by serious students of history.
The events in Europe suggest that we may have been
a little hasty in assumptions about the impossibility of
change, or the necessity of change only in one direction.
In the United States, we are a nation of immigrant people
who procured democracy simply by becoming democratic,
simply by coming to our country. We assume that it's very
easy for people to change their political attitudes without
reference to the history that they inherit.
Is it very easy? Or is this specific to pioneer countries?
It depends on what you mean by a pioneer country, but
I think that one of the characteristics of people living in
many pioneering situations in the United States, for example
in the movement westwards, is that they were not conscious
that they were building political institutions. The wagon
trains that moved West formed their own constitutions, and
they had to have rules of conduct, a way of trying people
for crimes they had committed. I don't think they ever
thought of it as creating a political life, it was a matter of
convenience when crossing the prairies together. One of the
consequences of the American experience of moving across
a sparsely-populated continent was that people became polit¬
ical through force of circumstance. When they found them¬
selves in Wyoming or one of the Dakotas, they had to make
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
legislation to protect their property and their families,
whereas in Europe they would have left that to the people
who had always had the job of protecting others.
People became political through force of circumstance,
but did they become democratic?
One of the characteristics of the movement West is that
people were forming new communities, which led to a very
vivid sense of solidarity. They knew that they had to co¬
operate with their fellows. Another feature of American
society, perhaps one of the most important, has been the
lack of ideology. In more settled communities, such as
England, where there was a long inheritance of established
law and institutions reaching back to the Middle Ages, if
you wanted to change those institutions, you had to develop
a theoretical argument, and so you find a succession of polit¬
ical theoristsLocke, Hobbes and othersrationalizing
institutional changes. For Americans, who came out to a
continent that had been barren, there was no history, you
might say there was only geography. This meant that people
had to invent institutions to serve their convenience. They
were not living near their ancestors, in fact there were no
ancestors, once in the West. And of course the same story
was repeated in a different, urban, landscape in late-
nineteenth-century New York.
My grandparents came to America from the ghettoes
of Poland and Russia, they came to start a new life.... One
of my grandfathers went to a country town in the state of
Georgia and opened a store. His brother then came and
settled in the same town, and they had shops on opposite
sides of the same street under different names, because the
immigration officer hadn't been able to pronounce the name
that he'd been given. It was very puzzling, but it was a
symbol of the way in which the movement to America sepa¬
rated people from the kind of necessary and self-evident affili¬
ations which a long life in the same village would have
created in Europe.
As I wrote many years ago in The Genius ofAmerican
Politics,1 one of the paradoxes of American political life
is that we have been relatively successful in the United States
in building political institutions empirically, and yet con¬
spicuously unsuccessful in producing great political
philosophy. I suggested that those two facts are not
unrelated. In the United States we have been willing to work
out a political society without always knowing what we were
doing or worrying about the long-term end. The great debate
in American political life is of course about our Constitu¬
tion, which I call a piece of political technology, not a polit¬
ical philosophy. It was the product of an effort to find ways
for people who had come from different countries, different
cultures, different religions, to live together by forming their
own communities. This is what the federal system is, an
interaction of communities, and it was not necessary to agree
upon a political philosophy.
Jefferson, whom we sometimes think of as our great
political philosopher, was not really a philosopher, he was
a student of law and English institutions. His A Summary
View of the Rights of British America, the book he wrote
The signing of the United States Constitution,
by American artist Howard Chandler Christy (late 19th century).
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Above, Black slaves on a tobacco
plantation In one of the southern states.
Italian engraving, c. 1820.
Opposite page, Gary Cooper plays the role
of a heroic town marshal In the classic
Western High Noon (1952).
Below right, pioneers cross the Arkansas
river In the early 1880s.
in 1774 which became the legal raison d'être of the American
Revolution, was really a description of the way in which
the old Anglo-Saxon customs preserved people's rights; and
the Declaration of Independence, which he drafted, is really
a list of rights. Most of what is a long legal document con¬
cerns the way in which the traditional legal privileges of
Englishmen had been violated in America, and the Preamble,
the part most often quoted, is a way of inviting the sym¬
pathy of people all over the world. So the American Revo¬
lution was really an affirmation of traditional rights, and
in that sense it's very different from the French Revolution
of 1789, which talked about the rights of man. The Decla¬
ration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen is a list of
abstract rights which didn't exist anywhere in the world.
We still have many problems and many injustices in our
country, but I am amazed when I come back to the United
States from any other country and see how many different
races of people and different ways of life have been brought
together. It's relatively peacefulwe've never had a religious
war, for example. The only other country in the world of
which that's true is probably Japan. We had a terrible Civil
War, the bloodiest war of the nineteenth century, but it was
not a religious war.
.¡4s regards the reasons for the Civil War, why didn't
Jefferson abolish slavery when drafting the Declaration of
Independence?
Jefferson didn't live in the air, he lived in a particular
community in Virginia, and there were institutions of which
he was part. It would have taken a great deal of boldness
at that time to insist on the abolition of slavery, but in his
original draft he had included a clearer statement against
slavery, and there is still a shadow of that in the Declara¬
tion. But slavery was an established institution and a basis
of the economy in itself.
Isn't it striking that American political and democratic
institutions evolved parallel with the fight against the
Indians, and later, with the repression of the slaves?
Slavery was a regional institution, which only existed in
the south and certain other parts of the United States.
Yes, but didn't the existence of slavery give rise to the
fear of an enemy within?
No, I don't think so. There were some slave uprisings,
but these were relatively few. I don't think that the planta¬
tion owners in the south considered their slaves as enemies,
but rather as part of the family. I'm not saying it wasn't
unjust, but at the same time the plantation wives played a
very positive role in delivering babies and looking after the
health of people in the slave quarters. They considered that
they had a duty to do so. It was like a feudal community
in Europe where the lord didn't consider that he was
oppressing his vassals or his peasants, he saw himself as their
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
protector. For many people, too, the belief in the inferi¬
ority of the Black race was very strong. They thought that
they were protecting people who were helpless or feckless.
That was the way they looked at it. You and I may find
that immoral but nevertheless that was how they saw things.
They didn't feel that they were living in a fortress, that their
plantation houses would be besieged by the slaves. This did
happen, but very rarely.
To come back to history, or the end of historyisn't
there a certain logic in the idea that the history ofmankind
passes through several stages ofdevelopment which, in the
way that Marx imagined it, lead to communism?
To say that there's no history because there isn't the kind
of history that Karl Marx described is to commit the Marxist
sin doubly: first to accept it, then to become the prisoner
of it. I've already suggested that history is a cautionary
science. I also think it's the science of uniqueness, a way
of discovering how everything differs from everything else.
I don't believe in cycles, I'm not a millenarian. I don't believe
that we can ever come to the end of change because I think
that man's possibilities are infinite in all directions. One of
the many mistakes or over-simplifications of Marxism is to
give an excessive importance to political and economic insti¬
tutions. There are many other kinds of institutions that Marx
discounted, religious ones for examplelook at the charisma
that people attach to certain kinds of leaders. Or look at
the way in which the art of Proust or Joyce transforms
people's consciousness, which seems to me to have no visible
relation to the infrastructure of society. That's history.
Shakespeare was history, Chaucer was history, Homer was
history, and to say that we've come to the end of history
is to deny our humanity, because our humanity consists in
a need to pursue the unknown and the new, to be prepared
for the unexpected. We cannot stop creating new kinds of
art, we cannot stop research into microgenetics and atomic
physics. That's the penalty and the glory of being human,
that's the meaning I attach to having eaten the apple in the
Garden of Eden. We can't stop knowing.
There's another aspect to this question. Sometimes
people, especially historians, talk about the difficulty of
remembering, as if history is the product of memory. Our
problem is not so much that we can't remember, but that
wè can't forget. It's much more difficult to forget than to
remember, and that is one of the consequences that the
world has to face when any nation has committed crimes.
The massacre of millions of people by the Nazis, for
example, is unforgettable, and it will affect attitudes towards
Germany for ever.
Do you think so?
I think so, unfortunately for those who happen to be born
in Germany, because it's not their fault. They're just as
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Above, taking the oath in a naturalization ceremony on Ellis Island,
the former immigration station in New York Harbor.
8
virtuous as anyone else, but that is their inheritance and the
price of memory. If we're going to have peace in the world,
our problem is to find ways of remembering without being
overwhelmed by it.
If we're going to have peace in the world, do you think
democracy will have to grow? Do you think the whole
world is ripe for it?
I don't believe in that kind of generalization, or that any
country can prescribe institutions for other countries. I think
that fulfilment, the apple that I referred to, is that every
nation should seek its own way. I don't believe it's the des¬
tiny of the world to become American, for instance. It would
be very dreary if that were the case.
There have been Americans who thought that we should
try and enforce our will on the world. But the same thing
has happened in the Soviet Union, and in many other coun¬
tries. The ancient Greeks and Romans were perhaps more
tolerant in that respect. I think it's futile to try to assimi¬
late the world, our object ought to be to find the means
to allow people to pursue their own ways.
You mean that you don't accept the idea that there
may be universal laws which govern humanity?
I'm not saying there are none, but I don't know any.
Coming back to what I said earlier, one of the purposes of
history as a cautionary science is to make us wary of people
who pretend to know the ideal laws of the world. The
United States does in my opinion have a mission in the
world, and that is to be an example of the possibility of
people living together without political ideology, even
without the same religion. We see in the Soviet Union now
the consequences of not having found a way for allowing
people to live together, with their different religions and
different traditions.
In so many places there have been wars over language,
but in the United States we've had the curious and, until
now at least, instructive experience of people coming to
another country and learning another language without
losing their dignity. My grandparents spoke Yiddish. They
learned to speak English and they didn't feel that their life
had been ruined or that they had been deprived of their per¬
sonality. On the contrary, people here have discovered that
it's possible to learn another language and still be fulfilled.
This sense of openness, of starting anew, is illustrated
in my recent book, The Discoverers, one of the leitmotifs
of which is that the enemy of progress is not ignorance but
the illusion of knowledge. This is applicable to political life.
People who always have doubts, who have the courage to
doubt, are those least likely to impose their ways on others.
People who acquire a sense of rectitude and believe that they
know best are the enemies of decent society.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Do you feel that people in the United States have found
the best way for them to live in harmony?
Possibly...but I think that if you travel, you discover that
other people's way of life is just as valid. In this respect,
one of my great experiences was living in Japan, where I
taught a number of years ago. I discovered that almost all
the categories of history that I was accustomed to didn't exist
in Japan. It was possible for people to be human, to treat
one another decently, without anything that Westerners
would call religion, for example. So much else is entirely
different. The architect in the West tries to build something
that will last for ever, like the Parthenon or the Pyramids,
while traditional Japanese architecture is in wood. You
expect it to disintegrate, and you rebuild it. The architect
is not fighting a battle against time, he's co-operating with
time, accepting it. In Japanese wrestling, you try to over¬
come your opponent by yielding to him, not by aggression.
That's how you bring him down. There is a temptation to
believe that our way of doing everything is right, and it's
discomforting to discover that there's another way of doing
it. That's what it means to be human, to accept that price,
to fulfil ourselves by acquiring the capacity to doubt and
a willingness to have the new displace the old.
The same is true of the progress of science. We see scien¬
tific ideas as great additions to our knowledge, but every
advance of scientific knowledge is also a kind of subtrac¬
tion. When Copernicus persuaded people that the Sun didn't
go round the Earth, he caused a lot of trouble. The idea was
wonderful, it was a step forward, but it also destroyed a
whole world of folklore and theology. The most explosive
thing in the world today is the atom, which for most of
history people thought of as unbreakable by definitiona
good example of the advance of science subtracting from
our sense of security.
When Apollo sent back the first pictures of the Earth
seen from the Moon, surely that created new myths about
our planet?
Science is not always subtractivewe can still learn some¬
thing from Aristotlewhereas the arts, it seems to me, are
always additive. There's no work of art that subtracts from
another work of art. Michelangelo doesn't subtract from
Phidias, Picasso doesn't subtract from other modern
artists.. .if anything each work adds to our understanding
because it creates a new contrast. That's one of the reasons
why the arts become increasingly important with the
advance of technology, which tends to reduce cultural diver¬
sity. With television, for example, there is obviously much
less difference between being there and being here, and the
same applies to advances in transportation and communi¬
cation. But the arts encourage cultural specificity. The artist
creates a difference between now and then, and here and
there, and me and you, and this and that. So there is a mis¬
sion for the arts which is increasingly urgent.
1. The Genius ofAmerican Politics, Phoenix Books, University of
Chicago Press, 1953.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
R
o
N the eve of the twenty-first century over half the world's
population will be living in cities. Urbanization is proceeding at a pace
that would have been unimaginable a few decades ago.
In the developing countries, rapid population growth and the
concentration of economic activity around big cities have swelled a
massive influx of urban migrants which governments can no longer
reverse or even slow down. Rampant urbanization has gone hand in hand
with inner city decline, proliferating squatter settlements, and the
construction of illegal dwellings in mushrooming slums and shanty towns.
The industrialized countries, where around 80 per cent of the population
already lives in urban areas, are also facing problems. Where they have
survived the ravages of war or the Utopian dreams of planners, many
historic city centres are a prey to speculation and pollution, while soulless
suburban development testifies to the failure of ill-thought-out approaches
to urban planning.
Cities everywhere present increasingly striking contrasts. Though they
may produce much of a country's wealth, they also bear the brunt of
its poverty.
It is high time to mobilize this wealth to create urban centres fit for
people to live in, to return the city to those who live in it. Many city-
dwellers deploy indomitable forces of ingenuity, tenacity and solidarity
Mexico aty, by the Mexican in a struggle for survival. These energies must be tapped if we are to
architect and muralist Juan 1 1 - 1 1 1 r
0-Gorman (1905-1982). avert tragedy and create a bright urban future.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
CITIES UNDER STRESS
The urban experience
by Wolf Tochtermann
Are urban decay
and a declining
quality of life
the inevitable
consequences of
rampant growth
in the world's
burgeoning cities?
A,. town or city is essentially a place where men
and women work, move about, meet one
another, improve their minds and amuse them¬
selves. Obviously the range of opportunities it
offers is proportional to its size, the number of
its institutions, and the intensity of its economic,
commercial, social and cultural life.
But the inhabitants of cities all have different
perceptions of the urban environment in which
they live, depending on their origins, their edu¬
cation, their professional concerns and their ambi¬
tions. For many people the city is simply
somewhere to live, a place of work, and the
journey between the two; while others regard it
as a far more complex environment offering
much greater scope.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Opposite page, the
mountainous site of La Paz
(Bolivia).
Left, the spiralling streets of
Pérouges, a village north-east
of Lyon (France) which dates
from the Middle Ages.
Below, Toronto (Canada), an
example of the urban grid
pattern.
For the mayor and the municipal councillors
a city is primarily a political entity posing
management problems that need to be solved in
the interests of its population. It is also a place
that calls for leadership, in the sense of putting
forward or encouraging projects likely to give it
a character of its own and differentiate it from
other cities.
Urban planners see the city as a sphere of
operation that makes demands on their
knowledge and experience in the organization of
built-up areas. They seek to bring order to chaos
and give shape to the urban fabric, and they are
usually convinced that their work responds to
users' aspirations. Historians of urban planning,
on the other hand, see cities in terms of a process
of continuous development through periods
characterized by successive architectural styles.
Each period has its own conception of develop¬
ment, its own ways of exercising power, and its
own modes of production, all of which may
explain the prosperity of a conurbation or its
decline.
Intellectuals, research workers, philosophers
and artists find in towns and cities the rivalries
and confrontations conducive to creative work
and the interplay of ideas they need to stimulate
their imagination. One scholar even worked out
that he needed a city with a population of at least
one million in order to find the five or ten people
essential to the progress of his research.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
For people who live in the countryside, cities
are magnets. With their opportunities for
material gain and entertainment they hold out a
promiseor a mirageof a better life, and so have
led to an exodus from the land whose scale has
varied at different times. This migration was par¬
ticularly substantial in the nineteenth century,
when it was justified in the sense that jobs and
pay were more attractive in the towns than in
the country. Today, especially in developing
countries, towns and above all the major conur¬
bations still attract rural people even though there
is no longer any work, at any rate in the formal
sectors of the economy. Yet even though they
do not enjoy the privileges of city life, migrants
still hope that by settling in an urban area they
will manage to move a step or two up the social
scale.
Why some cities grow
and others lag behind
It is usually hard to ascertain the origins of a
conurbation, and the factors that have helped or
hindered its development down the centuries are
often obscure. Why should one city have become
prominent while another with the same advan
tages have lagged behind and developed less exten¬
sively or less quickly? The reasons may not be
exclusively economic, although many towns did
start from a favourable situation at the junction
of trade routes, along a river or at the site of a
natural harbour. But a town or city might also
be founded by the decision of a temporal or
spiritual ruler, or as a result of the discovery and
working of natural resources or the setting up of
an industrial plant. These factors often coincide
and generate a dynamic conducive to urban
development.
Many urban planners make a distinction
between the "traditional" towns and cities, which
developed organically, and "planned" towns and
cities created by the decision of a ruler or govern¬
ment, but this distinction is not as clear-cut as is
claimed. Medieval cities were unplanned, but this
did not prevent them from being thoroughly
organized; and twentieth-century new towns,
though planned, are usually not truly urban in
character.
Traditional cities, which have developed
organically over the centuries, have a certain
homogeneity as a result of their structure, the
uniformity of their building materials, and the
human scale of their narrow streets and open
A covered street in Ghadamis
(Libyan Arab Jamahiriya).
Opposite page, detail of the
recently built Institute of the
Arab World, Paris.
WOLF TOCHTERMANN
is in charge of Unesco's
human settlements
programme. A specialist in
urban problems and town
planning, he is currently
concerned with a project
entitled "The future of cities in
the face of social and cultural
challenges: ways of organizing
and improving the living
conditions of disadvantaged
population groups". He is
writing a book on this project,
which will be published by
Unesco in 1992.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
spaces. Some people think that such growth owes
nothing to urban planners or administrators, for¬
getting that these towns conformed to the stan¬
dards of their time and that cathedrals, castles,
fortresses, ramparts and other monuments were
the result of a collective effort. It is true that many
of their inhabitants were fated to live in penury
and without any kind of comfort. Noise, dirt,
insecurity, difficulty in obtaining supplies and the
threat of epidemics were the normal conditions
of urban life for centuries.
Planned towns and cities have existed in most
parts of the world. The ideal cities of the Italian
Renaissance, Baroque cities, the Spanish cities of
Latin America, Beijing in China and Jaipur in
India all stemmed from steps deliberately taken
by rulers who wanted to control not only the
shape but also the destiny of their cities.
Many cities were remade in the eighteenth
and nineteenth centuries because of explosive
population growth and the migrations brought
about by the Industrial Revolution. Regular and
often rectangular layouts were juxtaposed with
traditional urban ground plans. The extensions
of Barcelona and Berlin, and the street plans of
Washington, New York, Chicago and Canberra
strikingly demonstrate the difference between an
organic urban fabric and a city whose shape and
functions have been determined from the outset
by rigorous planning.
Many architects and urban planners, con¬
vinced that they could solve the social as well as
the architectural problems of cities, have drawn
inspiration from the industrial towns and cities
that are so characteristic of the twentieth century.
Under the dictatorships the monumental had to
make way for the colossal, and a disturbing var¬
iant of the planned city made its appearance. The
Berlin development plan drawn up by Albert
Speer at Hitler's request in 1937, and the Bucharest
plan put forward by Ceausescu in 1981 in the
name of "urban systematization" entailed ruth¬
lessly gutting the existing cities and implanting
in them urban structures that were alien to their
original character and revolved around the centres
of power.
Many countries, especially since the 1950s,
have embarked on plans for new towns in order
to relieve congestion in cities and focus growth
on particular points. In some cases capitals have
been built to give a country or a region a new
identity. Two of them, Brasilia and Chandigarh,
are world famous, notably for their spectacular
architecture. Other countries such as Nigeria and '
the United Republic of Tanzania have also begun
to build new capitals. It will be interesting to see
how they turn out, for makeshift dwellings are
already proliferating around them.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Urban decay
In industrialized countries urban decay is leading
to a disintegration of the urban fabric, especially
in those cities that are witnessing the disappear¬
ance of once-important economic activities.
Several mining and industrial areas in Europe
and the United States have been affected by
this phenomenon, the signs of which are patches
of waste ground, derelict industrial estates,
and disused buildingsa breeding ground for
social problems such as unemployment and
delinquency.
In developing countries the rural exodus and
vigorous population growth are leading to the
accelerated urbanization deplored by demo¬
graphers, by urban planners and especially by
local administrators. No arrangements are made
to receive the people who flock in from the
country, attracted by the possibilities of city life.
towns) are generally regarded as a blight on the
face of a city, and their inhabitants as delinquents,
intruders or undesirables. What tends to be over¬
looked is that in many cities they now represent
the bulk of the population.
Municipal authorities usually accept that it
is no longer feasible to evict these people from
the sites they have illegally taken overespecially
since the construction of subsidized housing does
not solve the problem of the influx of new¬
comers. Moreover the public purse can no longer
afford operations of such magnitude.
The quality of life is declining in all great
conurbations. Pollution, noise, the constant
threat of epidemics or starvation, rising crime
rates and a chronic shortage of public facilities
are the price to be paid for rampant urban
growth. The situation seems unlikely to improve
lOIJ I'»«"
, ¡Em wcMta« i
America Mm
-Profil
MAY 20, I**»
Helping America' Hungry
75 CENTS
I
*>>
SA
PUBLIC
HOUSING:
JATale of Two Cities
BROKEN «UT OF
DREAMS THE
i ^AJamUtba^x .
Stark urban contrasts In a
residential district of Bangkok
(Thailand).
Street News,
a New York newspaper
for homeless people launched In
November 1989. Published fortnightly,
It Is sold In the streets by the homeless themselves.
16
They are unfortunately obliged to look after
themselves as well as they can on the outskirts
of the cities, on insalubrious pieces of land or dan¬
gerous slopes, where they gradually erect
makeshift accommodation in districts that are not
without cohesion but are desperately short of
infrastructure, facilities and services.
Their presence is resented by the city authori¬
ties and the rest of the urban population. Squatter
settlements, barrios, favelas and bidonvilles (shanty
in the next few years. In a world that will become
increasingly urbanized, the role played by
architects, urban planners and designers will,
sadly, continue to be insignificant.
Towns and cities, especially in developing
countries, are becoming the end product of
"informal" planning, the process whereby people
take possession of a piece of land, settle on it and
build modest shelters there. Some sociologists
regard this as the beginning of a new urban cul¬
ture, born of the traditions of historic towns and
cities and of a so-called "vernacular"
architecturean architecture without architects.
We do not yet know whether this new urban
culture will take root, but we do already know
that towns and cities in poor countries will con¬
tinue to grow without any overall urban planning.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
U~¿
TW
mr
ffîaS
Citizens who
help themselves
by Jorge E. Hardoy and David Satterthwaite
To provide
themselves with
shelter, low-
income families
in Third World
cities often have
to take the law
into their own
hands
SOME 1,300 million people today live in the
cities of the Third World, an urban population
larger than that of Europe, North America and
Japan combined. Over the next ten years this
figure is likely to grow by around 500 million.
While governments and aid agencies discuss
strategies, the population of cities such as Karachi
and Bombay will grow by over 300,000 a year,
that of Sâo Paulo by over 400,000 a year, and that
of Mexico City Metropolitan Area by over
500,000 a year. Tens of thousands of small urban
centres will also experience rapid population
growth.
Despite enormous differences between the
societies, cultures and economies which build and
shape them, these cities are becoming more
similar in appearance today than they were
during colonial times when they were founded
although in many of them life is still shaped by
a strong colonial legacy in the form of legal
systems, institutions, land ownership patterns,
tenancy systems and poorly developed structures
of local government. Since the 1950s, a combi¬
nation of a rapidly growing low-income popula¬
tion and a scarcity of government investment in 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Below, SuperBarrio, the
masked defender of victims of
the 1985 earthquake that left
over 300,000 people
homeless In Mexico City. This
colourful character, a self-
appointed champion of
popular causes, leads
demonstrations and
campaigns In support of the
homeless who are fighting to
obtain housing credits from
the authorities.
construction and maintenance has produced
urban forms that look increasingly alike. Third
World cities in different continents have many
common features, Including the intensity of their
street life and the dense use of space in their cen¬
tral districts and in most residential areas.
Most people who live in Third World cities
cannot afford a conventional house or apartment.
They buy, build or rent housing in the illegal set¬
tlements which surround the pockets of official,
legal architecture and are spreading to ever
growing distances from city centres. Many of the
things they do contravene laws or regulations
relating to shelter, work and even the food and
water they consume and the medical services they
use. They cannot afford to obtain these facilities
legally.
Most illegal settlements are built by the
people who live in them. Virtually all of them
are dusty, densely populated, without trees,
lacking paved roads, adequate supplies of water,
drains, and even schools and rudimentary health
centres. Dwellings which outside observers may
call a shanty town provide a home for between
CUITO
iE
18
a third and two-thirds of the inhabitants of most
Third World cities.
Government strategies
and people's needs
Until relatively recently, the transformation of
cities has usually been determined by powerful
men and technocrats whose actions were sup¬
ported by only a small minority of society. Many
of the assumptions used to justify the decisions
of these rulers have been unrelated to society's
needs, disguised under pretensions of a long-range
view of future national and urban development.
Rulers have been known to reshape cities and
order the eviction of tens of thousands of fami¬
lies to "beautify" the more visible districts. Such
examples of the divorce between the basic needs
of a society and the grand strategies of a ruler
abound in the history of urbanism.
Many "new cities" in the Third World have
been planned according to Western norms and
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Above, modern apartment
blocks overlook makeshift
shelters In Bombay (India).
fashions and built parallel to existing indigenous
cities with long histories. They have drawn little
from the culture and society in which they were
implanted, and their avowed purpose of
separating the rich and powerful from the poor
majority reveals the elitist principles on which
they were based.
Poor people's needs have too often been
ignoredwhether in planned or unplanned cities,
new cities or projects to expand old cities.
Although it is often suggested that the policies
and expenditures of governments and aid agen¬
cies have an "urban bias", very few of the urban
poor benefit from it. Burglaries, muggings and
the ransacking of supermarkets and pharmacies
have become more common, as the price of food
and medicine rises far more rapidly than incomes.
Recession and economic crisis are the reasons
usually cited to justify neglect of the basic needs
of the poor. In earlier decades too it was said that
meeting this goal should be postponed until the
economy was performing more successfully.
Why urban problems deserve
s more attention
If current trends continue, the majority of Third
World city-dwellers will go on leading lives of
privation, millions will die prematurely every
year, and hundreds of millions will continue to
suffer from ill health or disablement, most of
which could be prevented with a very modest
outlay. Hundreds of millions will be deprived of
dignity if they are unable to obtain the credits
and resources to allow them to acquire a home
and enhance their own living conditions and, in
so doing, encourage their incorporation into the
social and economic life of each nation as full
citizens.
Urban problems also deserve more attention
because city-dwellers will play a vital role in the
political future of Third World nations.
Hundreds of millions of urban people want to
participate fully in the political lives of their coun¬
tries. The alternative between democracy and 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
dictatorship will be largely determined in the
cities.
Urban centres have important economic
functions, although these are often misunder¬
stood. Urban workforces and enterprises make a
substantial contribution to nations' Gross
Domestic Product (GDP)usually a far higher
share than the proportion of the population living
in cities. Much of this economic dynamism draws
heavily on what outsiders have labelled the
"informal" or "black" economy. Informal activi¬
ties constitute the sole source of income for tens
of millions of urban households in Africa, Asia
and Latin America.
One reason why government policies for
managing urban growth and improving living
conditions have achieved such poor results is that
governments do not properly understand how
cities function, how needy individuals and house¬
holds earn an income, how different social groups
use their time, and how the family and commu¬
nity organizations can play a role. Human lives
will not be saved and health will not be improved
if most government funds are spent on expanding
bureaucracies while leaving hospitals and health
centres without basic equipment and supplies.
If governments were to adopt new
approaches, basic needs could be met at relatively
low cost. Water supplies, provision for sanitation,
drainage and garbage collection, street paving,
health care systems and the like can be provided
cheaply and effectively if local knowledge, skills
and resources are used, and municipal govern¬
ments work in partnership with low-income
groups and their community organizations. The
channelling of more resources to meet the needs
of poorer groups does not necessarily imply a
diversion of funds from rural to urban areas but
rather a better use of existing resources.
The city of the future
The future cities of the Third World will be very
different from those we have known and thought
we understood. They will be different not only
in size but also in cultural values, codes of con¬
duct and in age and labour structures. There will
be massive numbers of children and adolescents
in virtually all of them, at least in the next two
decades. This will bring to urban life a mixture of
aggressiveness and solidarity, of expectations and
frustrations which only a new style of leadership
and governance can channel towards the develop¬
ment of more equitable places for all to live.
There is clearly a need to develop new forms
of local government within new processes of
decentralization and democratization. Metropo¬
litan governments or new types of city-region
governments are also needed for the larger
Right, In the shanty town of
Mezquital, 13 km from
Guatemala City, 25,000
peasant families are crowded
Into corrugated Iron and
cardboard shacks. Above,
election of delegates to the
neighbourhood association
responsible for seeking legal
title to land occupied at
Colonia de La Nueva
Esperanza, the most heavily
populated district of
Mezquital.
JORGE E. HARDOY,
Argentine architect and urban
planner, is president of the
International Institute for
Environment and Development
in Buenos Aires (IIED-AL) and
of the National Commission for
Historic Monuments in
Argentina. He has written
widely on both historical and
contemporary urban issues.
DAVID SATTERTHWAITE,
British historian and
development planner, is a
researcher who works with
NED in Buenos Aires and in
London. He has published
several books with Jorge E.
Hardoy, including Squatter
Citizen: Life in the Urban Third
World (Earthscan Publications,
London, 1989) and The Poor
Die Young: Housing and Health
in Third World Cities (edited
with Sandy Cairncross,
Earthscan, forthcoming).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
agglomerations. One priority is to redefine the
scope of current legislation which at present
deems illegal hundreds of millions of squatters,
informal workers and traders.
Decision-makers must accept that their
projects should be guided by the priorities of low-
income citizens and implemented under their
supervision. Power, resources and trained per¬
sonnel should be decentralized in a new collabora¬
tive framework so that local government can
respond directly to demands from low-income
neighbourhoods. Of course city and national
governments must provide a broad planning
framework. Such a framework does not imply
a diminution in the role of government, but a
different rolemore developmental, more
activist, more decentralized and more represen¬
tative. The unco-ordinated efforts of dozens of
local governments and hundreds of community
organizations would produce chaos in any city
for transport planning and major infrastructure
investments.
The 1990s are beginning with global discus¬
sions of common causes. Sustainable development
with a priority to protecting the global commons
is receiving most attention. These discussions are
encouraged by the ending of the Cold War and
detailed discussions about nuclear disarmament.
But how long will peace be possible and how can
environmental degradation be avoided in regions
where there is mass poverty? Let us hope that the
1990s will concentrate on saving human lives,
eliminating easily preventable suffering and dis¬
ease and restoring dignity to the lives of the many
millions who live in poverty. This should be the
first goal of sustainable development.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
WH U RE FOR HE URBAN
The threats to
historic city
centres range
from war to
ideological
dogma, property
speculation and
the pressure of
demographic
growth
PAST?
A new heart for old cities
by Stefano Bianca
I
22
N the pre-industrial era the development of
towns and cities was a slow process governed by
enduring cultural values and only slightly in¬
fluenced by the very limited technology then
available.
Some absolute rulers completely remodelled
their cities; others built entirely new ones. But
such cases were few. Cities were sometimes trans
formed for religious reasons, and as a result ac¬
quired a special significance which was recognized
by everyone. But in spite of apparently radical
changes in architecture and the use of space, there
was always a thread of cultural continuity.
The advent of the industrial era in the early
nineteenth century created an entirely new situ¬
ation. As a result of technological progress,
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
A highway under construction
(now completed), In central
Cairo.
human creativity and the innovatory spirit ac¬
quired new scope for expression in building and
urban planning. New means of communication
and production and new ways of living made an
indirect but powerful contribution to these
processes. Built-up areas expanded to an extent
that would once have been inconceivable. Tech¬
nology became a driving force and began to play
a role that had once belonged to culture and
religion. Change became explosive, coupled as it
was with new economic mechanisms which were
themselves at odds with traditional cultural values
and obeyed only the laws of profit or speculation.
European cities suddenly began to grow
under the impetus of new forces, the rise of new
social classes and hierarchies. With the expansion
of the suburbs, the levelling of old city walls and
fortifications and the construction of wide
boulevards, a new concept of the city began to
emerge. It differed sharply from the traditional
concept of the city, where development had often
been haphazard.
The old districts of towns and cities were then
regarded not as places of historic value but as the
insalubrious areas in which the poorest members
of society, the early industrial proletariat, found
refuge. The prosperous middle class lived in
buildings which lined the new boulevards and in
residential areas on the outskirts.
The ravages of war
and Utopian ideas
This polarization, and the class divisions that
went with it, existed all over Europe until the
mid-twentieth century. In the 1920s and 1930s
many modernist architects argued for the destruc¬
tion of the old districts. The most important of
them was probably Le Corbusier, whose "Radiant
City" plan for Paris would, if executed, have
sacrificed much of the existing city in favour of
a series of skyscrapers laid out in a geometrical
pattern.
These radical proposals came to nothing, but
the ideology behind them contributed largely to
the obliteration of many historic urban districts
in Europe. Then the Second World War came
along and flattened some central European cities
more effectively than the boldest Utopian projects
of modern architects could have done.
Following these losses, planned and un¬
planned, some new thinking began to emerge in
the late 1960s. On featureless housing estates
whose residents had no reason to identify them¬
selves with their man-made environment, the
standardized "machine for living" revealed all its
defects. Moreover, a growing awareness of eco¬
logical issues gradually led to a revision of the 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
dominant concepts in architecture and urban
planning. Meanwhile, the increasing scarcity of
"historic resources" in big cities obliged local
authorities and architects to treat the surviving
historic fabric with greater consideration.
As often happens in such cases, the pendulum
swung to the opposite extreme. Legitimate con¬
cern for conservation was accompanied by exces¬
sive zeal for the protection of ancient monuments,
Left, book sellers In the suq
at Damascus (Syrian Arab
Republic).
Below, a dangerous tangle of
electricity and telephone
cables In a corner of the old
city of Peshawar (Pakistan).
wake. Only a few cities, such as Bologna in Italy,
have managed to preserve and gradually rehabili¬
tate their old centres without the original inhabi¬
tants being driven out by property speculation.
The historic districts
of Third World cities
The problem of old towns and cities is even more
acute in developing countries, where the great
wave of modernization came not in the nineteenth
century but in the 1950s and 1960s, usually
around the time when political independence was
achieved. The colonial cities of the nineteenth
century were the points at which modern civili¬
zation gained access to these countries, but they
also formed a closed social system, which had vir¬
tually no contact with the indigenous communi¬
ties. This social dualism only collapsed with the
ending of colonial rule, when a rising indigenous
class began to settle in the abandoned colonial
cities.
. In societies eager for progress, the modern
"European" areas of these cities are regarded as
the most desirable urban environment. The old
urban districts, like those of nineteenth-century
European cities, decayed and turned into slums.
Population movements in recent decades, largely
the result of a massive rural exodus, have acceler¬
ated this process. The prosperous classes have
moved to the newer parts of the city, and a flood
of rural migrants has descended on the old dis¬
tricts, which (together with the shanty towns on.
24
and this hindered any creative approach to the
renovation of even the most ordinary buildings.
Strict rules were applied, especially to the resto¬
ration of façades. When the interiors of buildings
were completely restored, the old frontages
were meticulously preserved for the sake of
appearances.
A good example is the old city of Berne (Swit¬
zerland), where the façades of older buildings pro¬
vide the frontage of modern department stores.
Such changes of function are encouraged by the
rapidly growing trend for inner city renewal.
Pedestrian areas in historic districts, once shunned
by traders because of their inaccessibility to
motor traffic, have become gold-mines overnight.
Thus run-down urban areas began to be gen-
trified in a rehabilitation process that has some
positive features but, like the former process of
slum-formation, brings new social problems in i«--
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
y v
	 _ <^B
i
k i^^_ P*È>^
,
"^
^ P
H-
.¿Mf^^MI ¡M -
VI Wt
^
-^K
¡L!fr üfi
»CTir
} *5" ^>^i'Ti
JT^£ !
: 1
' 1* i^K
Bttài^ia H^^^^^^^^^H ï ' j 1 Wfe
i ;l' ^ = Mllf 1
i l^-'r^ r- -
* i
>
fi
>
y
Wooden scaffolding prevents
these buildings In Algiers from
collapsing.
STEFANO BIANCA,
Swiss architect and urban
planner, has directed many
restoration projects in the
historic districts of Arab cities
such as Aleppo, Fez, Baghdad
and Riyadh, and has worked
with Unesco at Fez, Cairo,
Damascus and Sana'a. He is
the author of a number of
books on Islamic architecture,
the most recent of which is
Hofhaus und Paradiesgarten
("Courtyard and Garden of
Paradise", Beck Verlag,
Munich, 1991).
the outskirts) were the only sources of cheap ac¬
commodation and job opportunities in the so-
called informal (i.e. pre-industrial) sector of the
economy.
The historic districts of Third World cities
have thus survived to a large extent as _ isolated
pockets of pre-industrial traditions and customs
in the midst of a rapidly modernizing world.
Rural migrants have found in them ways of life
resembling those they knew. The threat to these
districts is that the influx of people leads to over¬
crowding, with several families often living in one
house, and sometimes in a single room. Many old
houses, stables and even cellars, abandoned by
their owners, are used for unauthorized small bus¬
inesses and as craft workshops, supplying the
local market at a very low cost but in deplorably
unhygienic conditions.
Historic buildings used in this way soon fall
into ruin. In the maze of narrow streets of the
old districts, houses are often difficult to locate,
and from outside it is sometimes even impossible
to suspect their existence. This hinders any sur¬
veillance of undesirable or illegal activities. Sani¬
tary arrangements are also inadequate. The water
supply and sewerage networks generally no
longer meet current needs, and traditional
systems (where they still exist) are dilapidated or
obsolete.
This situation must be remedied if living stan¬
dards are to be improved and a responsible middle
class brought back into the old districts. For
whereas major monuments can be restored only
by the authorities, the upkeep of a city as a whole
needs support from private initiative. Here
another problem arises: material improvements
call for substantial investment, usually beyond the
available resources, which in any case tend to be
allocated to "modern" districts.
Projects for the renovation of historic urban
areas should not be governed by the same criteria
as those applied to modern citiesto do so would
be to deprive historic areas of the very quality
which justifies big investments. Renewal schemes
must scrupulously respect the morphology of the
old districts. Unfortunately there have been many
ill-considered redevelopment operations which
have defeated their own object. Major roads have,
for example, been driven into a number of old
city centres. Some of these schemes have been
well-intentioned, but they have ignored the vital
needs of the traditional city life and paid little
heed to the manifold social, economic and aes¬
thetic consequences of purely technical solutions.
Those responsible for the renovation of
historic neighbourhoods must ask themselves
whether imported methods of modern urban
planning are appropriate, and devise solutions
suited to local situations. Such solutions can only
be based on a thorough knowledge of traditional
urban structures and their interna] economy.
The conservation and revival of historic dis¬
tricts must likewise be considered in the overall
context of the city. While a single notable historic
building can be treated like a museum and
preserved, an old city that may be inhabited by
hundreds of thousands of people cannot. Human
dynamism must be mobilized to revitalize the ar¬
chitectural shell and save it from decay. A
planner's first task must therefore be to strike a
balance between meticulously restoring buildings
and gradually adapting them to current needs.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The mutilation of Bucharest
by Matei Lykiardopol
MATEI LYKIARDOPOL,
Romanian architect, teaches at
the Bucharest Institute of
Architecture. He has published
a number of articles and
papers on urban settlements.
B
26
UCHAREST, a city of contrasts at the cross¬
roads of Byzantine and Western European civili¬
zation, is no stranger to destruction. It has seen
invasions by the Ottoman empire, by Russians and
by Germans, as well as natural disasters such as
earthquake and fire. A small number of churches,
monasteries, aristocratic residences and other
monuments survived these perils. A network of
streets in the centre of the old city, lined with
buildings dating from the seventeenth and eight¬
eenth centuries, also lasted until 1977.
These monuments, whose historic and cul¬
tural value was enhanced by their rarity, were
concentrated in the Uranus and Vacáresti districts
of Bucharest. They bore the brunt of the cam
paign of destruction unleashed by the dictator¬
ship in order to make room for a monstrous
"House of the People" which would be the new
seat of government. This vast edifice was to
dominate a new triumphal way symbolically
dubbed "The Victory of Socialism", although to
the horrified citizens it signified a victory over
Bucharest.
Why should this district have been chosen
rather than a vacant site? The Romanian historian
Nicolae Iorga (1871-1940) answered this question
when he wrote that "The first thing that every
conqueror of a city does is to annihilate the
ancient symbolic centre and to replace it with
another, in a different style."
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
In deciding to destroy this part of Bucharest,
Nicolae Ceausescu was probably driven by the
natural propensity of dictators to appropriate
their country's history and rewrite it to their own
advantage, to sweep away all traces of a glorious
past in order to vaunt their own power and
encourage a personality cult.
First of all over 40,000 people were evacu¬
ated by the armed forces, sometimes within
twenty-four hours and with no compensation
(the very small sums they were given later barely
covered their removal expenses). They were
rehoused in unfinished apartment blocks on the
fringes of the city. Many deaths and suicides
ensued.
The construction of Bucharest's new "civic
centre" also entailed the demolition of the
Ypsilanti palace, built in 1776, and the eighteenth-
century Brincovenesc hospital. Eighteen churches
and monasteries were destroyed. Eight others,
including the Mihai-Voda church dating from the
sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, were disman¬
tled and moved to restricted areas behind rows
of tenements.
Similar operations were carried out elsewhere
in Bucharest as part of grandiose construction
schemes. Much of the Stirbey-Vodä district was
sacrificed to make way for a history museum on
a highway intended for parades and ceremonies,
and a new law court and a congress hall (to
accommodate 30,000!) were erected or. che site
of the Väcäresti monastery, an ensemble of
seventeenth-century architecture that was unique
in southeast Europe.
Under the pretext of solving tram, subway
and automobile circulation problems, wide
swathes of central Bucharest were razed to the
ground, creating worse traffic jams and diverting
vehicles into streets that lead nowhere and inter¬
sections that it is impossible to cross.
The construction of the "civic centre" finally
confirmed the bankruptcy of the new city
project. Launched forty years ago, this project has
spawned acres of barrack-like blocks in dormi¬
tory suburbs where the public transport system
is hopelessly inadequate and there is a woeful lack
of health, cultural and sporting facilities. To cap
it all, the development of the new city led to the
process known as "systematization"a euphe¬
mism employed to describe the destruction of
nearby villages.
What can be done to remedy so many errors?
Where should we begin? Who can help us?
Unfortunately, equally serious mistakesall
fraught with human and material consequences-
have been made in the economic, social, cultural
and political fields. The task that lies ahead is
immense.
One thing is beyond question. Any tempta¬
tions towards totalitarianism must be resisted and
everything possible must be done to strengthen
democratic institutions.
Opposite page, the "House of
the People" towers over the
ruins of old Bucharest.
Below, the Domnlta Balasa
church, surrounded by
apartment blocks, Is one of
the few historic buildings still
standing in the city centre. .
5\3S'S''X' ^ü¡
il iPnr ;
^^H
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Can Leningrad be saved?
by Olga Nosareva
IN 1703, Peter the Great founded the city of St.
Petersburg at the mouth of the Neva river. In
1914, the city was renamed Petrograd, and since
1924 it has been known as Leningrad.
The Tsar wanted his city to be an ideal cap¬
ital, a Venice of the North. For two centuries,
successive generations of architects worked to
translate his dream into reality. They built a city
of extraordinary beauty and fantasy, rich in
architectural detail, palaces and museums. Its
layout is clear and logical, its streets and squares
are elegant. Majestic waterfront quays were con¬
structed, and the streams and canals were bor¬
dered with whimsically designed ornamental
railings. The city centre, where half the houses
are listed as historic monuments, covers 46 square
kilometres.
But today Leningrad is dying. Within ten or
fifteen years its historic centre will have entirely
disappeared. Over 30 per cent of the public
buildings and private residences built by both
European and Russian architects are or soon will
be in ruins.
This once glittering capital is today a
wretched sight. Houses are on the point of col¬
lapse. Pavements are full of potholes and strewn
with debris from broken cornices and railings.
There is a general air of dereliction. Scaffolding
and wire netting protect passers-by from falling
bricks and masonry. Some deserted streets look
sinister even in broad daylight, with their doors
boarded up and their windows broken. No one
lives in them any more.
There are many reasons for this decline. In
the 1917 Revolution the city's palaces were
besieged. Hundreds of buildings of outstanding
value were converted into communal apartments.
In 1918 the civil war took its toll, and in the 1930s
Stalin ordered the demolition of many religious
buildings. Then came the Second World War, the
blockade of the city and the destruction of entire
streets which the occupants took decades to
rebuild. In the 1960s a campaign against "architec¬
tural superfluity" disfigured many original
buildings and transformed them into square
boxes.
The years of the Soviet regime ended with
the destruction of half the habitable surface area
and the disappearance of hundreds of historic and
religious buildings. In addition, current restora¬
tion work is not managing to curtail the natural
ageing process.
Unfortunately many old buildings were given
over to administrative use, which rapidly led to
their deterioration. Thus the splendid cathedral
of St. Vladimir until recently housed a research
department, the church of the Assumption was
turned into a skating rink, and the Armenian
church was used as a warehouse.
The construction of the Leningrad subway
system in the 1940s and 1950s did not help
matters. For each stationand in Leningrad they
are palatiala row of houses had to be
demolished or a green space sacrificed. Several sta¬
tions were built on sites where churches had
simply been dynamited. An obsolete technique
which involved freezing the ground was used to
build the tunnels. During the work the layers of
subsoil expanded and the subsequent irregular
subsidence affected the buildings above.
One of the characteristics of Leningrad is that
70 per cent of the buildings of some architectural,
cultural or artistic value are. inhabited. How can
the integrity of their often lavishly-decorated
interiors be preserved when they are divided up
into the tiny rooms of communal apartments?
Most of these conversions are now in an appalling
state.
Rather than demolish a building, restoration
teams usually prefer to sacrifice the interior by
knocking down partition walls and converting
the space into small modern apartments. Twenty
years of this kind of "restoration" has meant the
loss of 150 private residences, of which only the
. façades remain.
The city also has a major ecological problem.
The concentration of pollutant gases pumped out
by industry and transport is very much higher
than average. Untreated effluent from hundreds
of factories pours into the Neva, which provides
water for the whole of Leningrad, as well as into
the other urban waterways. Not only is the river
water undrinkable as a result, but swimming in
it has been banned for some time. Controls on
the toxic emissions into the atmosphere and the
water are virtually non-existent.
Leningrad is perhaps the only city in Europe
not to have been provided with a ring road' or
a bypass. An enormous volume of heavy goods
traffic passes through the centre, causing consider¬
able damage. It would be difficult to say which
is the worst problem, the traffic vibrations and
exhaust fumes, or the indifference of the popula¬
tion to them.
It is not just the city of St. Petersburg (there
is some talk of reverting to the original name)
which is disappearing before our eyes, but an
architectural, cultural and historical witness to the
splendour of Russia. Is there still time to save it?
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
PLANNED AND 'SPONTANEOUS' CITIES
Chandigarh in India
is a classic example
of a "pre-planned"
modern city.
Elsewhere, when
conventional forms
of urban planning
have been
ineffective, popular
forms of urbanism
have arisen.
Residents have
sought participation
in urban renewal
projects and in
some cities of the
developing world
have organized
themselves in self-
help communities
of squatter-builders
(see* page 37).
CHANDIGARH
A planner's dream
by Roger Aujame
30
ROGER AUJAME,
of France, is a former
colleague of Le Corbusier. In
1948 he worked on the United
Nations Secretariat building
project in New York, before
joining the UN as an expert in
the Housing, Building and
Planning Section. He later
became a Unesco staff
member in his capacity as a
specialist in educational
buildings.
IN November 1950, the government of the new
Indian state of the Punjab sent a mission to
Europe to choose a team of leading architects and
urban planners which could design a state capital.
As a result of their efforts, the Swiss-born French
architect Charles-Edouard Jeanneret, known as
Le Corbusier, was commissioned to draw up a
master plan and design the official buildings.
The site of the city was a vast plateau
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The university auditorium,
Chandigarh (India).
extending over 500 hectares (half the area of cen¬
tral Paris). It was bounded to the north by the
foothills of the Himalayas, and to the east and
south by the beds of two rivers, the Sukhna and
the Patiali, which swelled to a torrent during the
monsoon. At the centre of the site, a band of
greenery ran from north to south. The land
sloped gently downwards towards the south to
large clusters of mango trees which formed
natural landmarks and to the village of Chandi,
from which the city would take its name.
The new city was destined to be the «eat of
the government and parliament of the Punjab and
also a university centre. In the first phase of con¬
struction, official buildings, dwellings and facili¬
ties for 150,000 inhabitants (including 10,000 civil
servants and their families) would be built. In
addition to the services sector, an industrial
development area with road and rail facilities
would be created. During the second phase the
population was to rise to 500,000.
The apostle of mechanization
Le Corbusier, who was known as the "apostle
of mechanization", applied his ideas about
modern city planning to a historic region which
had been" inhabited for thousands of years and
where people still travelled by donkey or camel,
or in carts drawn by horses or oxen. He proposed
an urban highway network linked at certain
points to a secondary network for motor traffic
which would move more slowly. The Punjabi
authorities accepted this approach although it
called for substantial investment at a time when
motor traffic was still virtually non-existent. The
capital of a developing state needed an infrastruc¬
ture which could underpin the country's spec¬
tacular development. Chandigarh would be able
to face this challenge since its planned road net¬
work would keep traffic flowing smoothly.
To define the character of Chandigarh, Le
Corbusier grouped together all the government
buildings in one vast area, the Capitol, at the
highest point of the city, with a marvellous view
towards the mountains. Between 1951 and 1963,
he designed and built most of these buildings
the High Court, the Secretariat, and the Legisla¬
tive Assemblywhich are today considered the
keystone of his work as an architect. At the foot
of the Capitol, the city slopes gently between the
two rivers, its plan defined by a simple, logical
network of arterial roads which meet at right
angles, like the streets and avenues of New York.
But similarities with New York end there.
Instead of New York's dense fabric of residen¬
tial blocks Chandigarh has neighbourhood units
where the housing is no more than five storeys
high, and where there are as many green spaces
as residential zones. There is also a much more
extensive network of roads, divided into categories
with different capacities and speed limits. None
of the main arterial roads is directly linked to
housing.
The neighbourhood units, each of which has
a specific purpose according to its location, are
mainly residential, with population densities 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
varying from 80 to 280 inhabitants per hectare.
Villages within the city, they have their own
shopping centres, schools and health centres.
They are served by an east-west transversal road,
a shopping street where the speed of traffic is
limited. This road provides a sense of continuity
and community between the different neighbour¬
hoods. It takes no more than a quarter of an hour
to walk through each one.
In addition to the Master Plan, Le Corbusier
drew up a tree planting scheme designed to create
micro-climates in particularly exposed areas, to
prevent drivers from being dazzled by headlights
on the main roads, and to provide shady areas
for car parks, cycle tracks and pedestrian paths
as well as wind-protection screens.
Le Corbusier and his team did not want to
impose Western ethics and aesthetics on the
Indian people but, through buildings rationally
designed to provide optimal conditions of com¬
fort, to respond to the aspirations of a people
living through a period of rapid change.
Chandigarh today
What is Chandigarh like today, a quarter of a cen¬
tury after Le Corbusier's death?
The city has developed slowly and not
entirely smoothly. It was clear right from the
start that demand for water would far exceed
available reserves, especially during the dry
season, and as a result a four-kilometre-long dam
was built across the Sukhna in record time to
store the monsoon rains and to provide irriga¬
tion for market gardens within the city limits.
This reservoir, now known as Lake Sukhna, has
also become the centre of a park and a leisure
complex.
The construction of the residential zones,
offices and business premises as part of the first
phase was slow and sporadic. Isolated groups of
buildings stood out in a kind of no-man's-land
without community facilities. Mobile market
stalls proliferated at the junctions of the access
roads until they were gradually pushed out by
the construction of shopping centres, as Le Cor¬
busier had planned.
Chandigarh today is changing rapidly. As a
result of the development on its boundaries of
the capital of the new state of Hariana, created
by the division of the Punjab, the population of
the conurbation as a whole is now a million.
The city has also become a major university
centre, which takes substantial numbers of stu¬
dents from the region and from neighbouring
countries. In 1976 it hosted a Unesco symposium
on urban problems and the education of town
planners. It is regarded by its inhabitants as an
ordered city, unlike the eastern suburb which is
developing chaotically with large numbers of
poor squatters in insanitary areas exposed to pol¬
luting industries and lacking community facilities.
Thirty years after the foundation of Chan¬
digarh, motor traffic still flows easily through the
city. The number of vehicles is increasing very
slowly, and the main form of transport is the
bicycle. Unfortunately, the proliferation of
motor scooters, motor cycles and above all of
motorized rickshaws, is gradually transforming
the almost rural calm of Chandigarh into a
deafening roar.
The slowest district to come to life was the
civic centre. Planned to house official bodies and
cultural and commercial institutions, it long
remained a building site. With the opening of
shops and the big cinemas loved by young Indians,
the heartbeat of the city became more lively.
The second phase is under way, and the
development of the Capitol according to Le Cor¬
busier's designs has continued with the construc¬
tion of a "Pit of Consideration", a "Tower of
Shadows", and traditional "tanks" in front of the
Legislative Assembly, and the erection of the
"Open Hand" monument, a symbol dear to Le
Corbusier which was inaugurated in 1987 on the
centenary of his birth.
Sketch of Chandigarh
by Le Corbusier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
BERLIN A testing ground for
urbanism
by Hardt-Waltherr Hämer
I
Sculpture by the "Tonteufel"
group of artists In Berlin's
Admiralstrasse, 1985.
F you want to get to know Berlin you are
bound to visit the Kreuzberg district at some time
or other. There you will find an audacious mix
of architectural styles in a crowded city environ¬
ment. Modern buildings stand next to run-down
tenements. There are workshops in upper storeys
and sheds in the courtyards of recently restored
apartment blocks. In the streets, the squares and
the few open spaces, native Kreuzbergers rub
shoulders with punks, Turks wearing headscarves
as if in Anatolia, and urbane figures sporting the
typical Berlin look. There are many dogs and
even more youngsters. Kreuzberg must house
more children than any other neighbourhood in
Europe. You may also, however, notice a burned-
out supermarket on a street corner; for in Kreuz-
berg, they will tell you, something goes up in
flames every May Dayif not a supermarket,
then at least a car or two. You will hear of a grim
tradition of disturbances and street fighting.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A building erected In 1984
near the Landwehr Canal,
Berlin.
34
HARDT-WALTHERR HAMER,
German architect, is vice-
president of the Berlin
Academy of Sciences. From
1979 to 1985, he was head of
urban renewal in the follow-up
to the Internationale
Bauausstellung, an
international architectural
exhibition held in Berlin in
1978. He has published a .
number of books, notably on
theatre construction and urban
renewal.
For the story of Kreuzberg is first and fore¬
most that of the conflicts and controversies that
punctuate social change in our society. It is a dis¬
trict where extremes clash head-on and urban
chaos reaches its peak. In a city that is constantly
trying to learn the secrets of peaceful coexistence,
Kreuzberg has for generations been a testing
ground for urban development.
Lenné's green city
The district's history began with a plan for an
ideal garden city drawn up by an architect named
Peter Joseph Lenné in 1841, shortly after the
revolution brought by the coming of the railway.
In Lenné's project, the district was to be called
Südliche Luisenstadt.
After 1850, however, Berlin spread out
beyond the ring of boulevards that surrounded
the old city to accommodate an influx of new¬
comers from the provinces. The first expansion
was so rapid that before long dwellings were
being built even in gardens in the courtyards
of apartment blocks. This was when Berlin's
Mietskasernen (literally, barrack dwellings) were
born. Tenements with tiny courtyards, they were
popular with property speculators at a time when
housing was in short supply.
The masses flocking to the city crowded into
ever-smaller dwellings that often served in addi¬
tion as cottage-industry workplaces. Then
manufacturing industry moved in, and factories
went up next door to the tenements. The district
that in Lenné's mind had been crisscrossed with
broad avenues, canals, promenades and gardens
was now overbuilt and overpopulated. It had
become a working-class slum.
Eventually conditions became bad enough to
stir up an outcry, directed not just against the city
authorities but also against the whole develop¬
ment process that had created the slum. Property
speculation fell into ill repute and the concept of
the garden city was revived. The modern homes
of the 1920s were a reaction to the social misery
of the old, stone Berlin.
The aftermath of war
Almost a quarter of the city was destroyed during
the Second World War. Only ruins remained of
the streets in the neighbourhood of the ministry
buildings and the Ritterstrasse, where the arms
factories had been located. But the working-class
district, including Kreuzberg, between the River
Spree and the Landwehr Canal escaped relatively
unscathed.
Some years later, in 1961, the Cold War
resulted in the construction of the Berlin wall,
which split the city from north to south and cut
Kreuzberg off from the old city centre and tradi¬
tional leisure areas such as Treptow park, which
were situated in the eastern sector of the city.
Once a central district, Kreuzberg became
peripheral, a dead end.
Yet the damage caused by the war and the
Berlin wall pales into insignificance in compar¬
ison with that caused by redevelopment
programmes between the 1950s and the 1970s. An
urban planning competition held in 1957, billed
as Berlin, Capital City, launched the idea of a mas¬
sive motorway network. A four-lane ring road
was to serve the business centre, and expressways
with stacked interchanges replacing junctions
would separate residential islands from commer¬
cial areas.
The problem was that the existing urban
fabric stood in the way of this planner's dream.
For more than two decades entire streets were
expropriated and torn down. The buildings put
up in the 1960s and 1970s still bear witness to the
damage done. For those who had to suffer its
effects, urban renewal became synonymous with
destruction.
Kreuzberg's revolt
Kreuzberg's inhabitants were transferredwhole
neighbourhoods at a timeinto new apartment
blocks. But the apartments they vacated were
filled, even before they could be demolished, by
immigrant workers and by tenants driven from
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Above, a Kreuzberg façade
decorated with ceramic
figures by the Turkish artist
Hanefl Yeter.
Below, mural on an
Admiralstrasse apartment
block, painted In 1985-1986.
their previous homes by development
programmes elsewhere in the city. The evictions
left thousands of apartments empty at a time
when some 80,000 people were urgently looking
for accommodation. Some of these people ended
up by occupying and refurbishing the empty
buildings, as the property companies that had
bought them up were no longer maintaining
them.
The squatter movement grew too fast for the
police to hold it in check. By May 1981 there
were 168 illegally-occupied buildings in Berlin,
86 of them in Kreuzberg. The new residents lived
with the threat of eviction and demolition
hanging permanently over their heads. But they
also had some popular backing. Demonstrations
in their support drew tens of thousands of people.
The politicians were thus confronted by the con¬
sequences of their own planning decisions.
In combination with increasing construction
costs and a reduction in housing subsidies,
popular resistance eventually paralysed the
renewal programme around 1978. Faced with
growing unrest and the indignation both of those
who upheld property rights and those who
attacked them, the municipal authorities decided
to try to get the city's development back on
course.
An international architectural exhibition held
in 1978, the Internationale Bauausstellung (IBA),
provided an opportunity for returning the city
centre to residential use. A company was founded
to rebuild on sites left derelict since the war. It
also led to the renovation of the district between
the Spree, the Landwehr Canal and the old
Luisenstadt Canal, in other words the very dis¬
trict that had sparked off the opposition to the
original redevelopment programme.
A fresh mistake
The city council outlined a plan of action: 1,600
new homes were to be built and 1,500 existing
ones restored at the heart of the Kreuzberg
redevelopment zone, on both sides of the Mari¬
annestrasse. More than 12,000 people and several
hundred businesses would be directly affected, as
their homes and workplaces would be expropri¬
ated and in 80 per cent of cases demolished. '
During the winter of 1979, Kreuzberg 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
residents complained that draughts and snow
were coming in through gaps in their roofs, doors
and windows. The buildings needed urgent
repairs but the authorities were not in a position
to carry them out and the property companies
wanted to put off work until the following year,
to the anger of the residents. At a public meeting,
the latter decided to give up their weekends to
restore four houses in Manteuffelstrasse that had
already been partially cleared of their occupants
and were awaiting demolition. The houses, which
are still standing today, are now the property of
the Instandebesetzung-the squatter-renovators,
organized into co-operatives.
For Kreuzberg residents, the experience of
working together in the cold and damp changed
many things. They were no longer prepared to
let themselves be evicted, and wanted to be
involved in all decision-making that affected their
neighbourhood. Their representatives drew up a
list of demands and complaints to be presented
at the IBA.
At first the authorities were hostile to their
pleas for participation. It was feared that the
redevelopment programme would become
bogged down in interminable discussions, or that
unreasonable demands would make its cost
excessive.
To soften their opposition, the residents drew
up, with the help of experts from Rotterdam,
Hamburg and Vienna, a list of guidelines for "rea¬
soned renewal". It was the action of the squatter-
renovators, though, that brought things to a head.
Although some Berliners considered them justi¬
fied in taking the law into their own hands, most
of them considered their action to be intolerable.
Together with a series of housing scandals, the
unresolved problem of urban renewal led to the
fall of the government a year before elections
were due. Now at last it became imperative to
find realistic solutions.
It was not until March 1983, however, that
the residents' guidelines finally received official
approval. They specified that plans for redevelop¬
ment should be drawn up in consultation with
the people directly affected by them, and that
their views should be taken into account when
any decision was made. The inhabitants of a
building were to have a right to vote before any
work was done on it. Disagreements could be
taken to a redevelopment commission or a neigh¬
bourhood committee.
Although this programme has not yet been
formally accepted by the authorities, it has
proved its worth on many occasions. In any case,
critics have been silenced by the results achieved.
Far from slowing things down, the assent of those
concerned, for instance in matters affecting home
maintenance or temporary removal while repairs
are carried out, has actually made for faster
progress. As for the cost of the operation, the
adaptation of renewal measures to the wishes and
pockets of the residents has saved money, both
by reducing construction costs and avoiding rent
increasesand consequently rent allowances. It
has been estimated that, partly as a result of the
consensus approach, the redevelopment has cost
about 58 per cent less in public subsidies than the
1978 programme would have done.
The 1978 plan has in fact been profoundly
altered. Only 360 new dwellings have been built
in place of the 1,600 originally specified, but
7,000, not 1,500, have been restored. Ten schools
are to be expanded and improved, and 24 creches
will be provided to receive 1,640 children. The
courtyards of 320 buildings have been turned into
small parks orwith the approval of the
residentsinto private gardens. Streets and
squares have been landscaped in over 170 places,
and many facilities have been provided for cul¬
ture, sport and young people.
There is still squalor in Kreuzberg, but
working with the victims of that squalor has
provided 7,360 decent rented properties and has
improved schools, creches and the general
environment. The demolition has been stopped,
and living conditions have become more bearable.
Everyone involved now knows that it is possible
save a cityeven when it has been largely
destroyed.
A children's farm beside the Berlin wall, Kreuzberg district.
4>1
X 1
W
vr
r t
ra
Ä;
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The squatter-builders
of Lima s
by Anna Wagner de Reyna
Aerial view of Villa Maria del
Triunfo, a working-class
suburb south of Lima (Peru).
QUATTER settlementsthe so-called "spon¬
taneous" districtsbegan to proliferate in Lima
shortly after the Second World War. They were
the result of an influx of population brought
about by internal migrations, a shortage of
dwellings for the poorer classes, and the lack of
any coherent social housing policy.
What distinguishes these settlements from
other residential districts of the Peruvian capital
m
37
&
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
is the fact that they were built by their own resi¬
dents, without any external financial support and
in contravention of existing property laws and
urban housing standards. The land on which they
are constructed was usually acquired illegally,
sometimes simply by occupation, and the normal
sequence of urban planning was reversed: people
moved onto the site before the buildings went
up, and only later were the dwellings provided
with services and legally acquired by their
occupants.
It is a very special kind of urban develop¬
ment. Whole neighbourhoods, built by the poor
themselves, spring up suddenly, sometimes
within hours, and then remain unfinished for
years on end. They are precariously built and
inadequately equippedcharacteristics that won
the name "spontaneous" for this new form of
urbanization.
According to the dictionary definition, the
term "spontaneous" implies something impulsive
and uncalculated, instinctive and unconstrained.
However, none of these epithets applies to the
squatter-built settlements of Lima, which have a
rigour and a coherence that sit uneasily with any
suggestion of unconscious or unconsidered
activity. Nor are the districts spontaneous in the
sense of following the dictates of nature rather
than culture, for they fit into a historical and cul¬
tural context. They are, in fact, a response by the
needy to the failings of public and private housing
policy.
The roots of popular urbanism
Even a hasty glance reveals that the districts
follow a methodical plan, usually a grid pattern.
Roads meet at right angles, and are often grouped
around a central square known as the plaza de
-the parade-ground.armas-
38
Left, most new
structures In Villa El
Salvador, on the
outskirts of Lima, are
built by community
volunteers.
On the level ground on the city's outskirts,
this chessboard model is systematically applied.
Wide, straight roads delineate squares and rec¬
tangles. A similar pattern is repeated on the hill¬
sides wherever the lie of the land permits. The
square at the centre of the grid is the site of the
principal public buildings such as the church, the
school, and the town hall. Land set aside at the
start of the project allows room for the settlement
to grow and provides some green spaces, although
in time these often disappear to make more room
for housing.
The urban grid pattern with a central square
has great symbolic significance in South America,
. since it was used by the Spaniards in the sixteenth
century as part of their efforts to organize and
pacify their newly-conquered territories. With
the exception of a few ports and mining centres,
the ground plans of almost all the towns and cities
founded by the Spaniards were as regular as
chessboards. There was nothing spontaneous
about this form of urbanism. It was the result of
careful calculation that found its clearest expres¬
sion in 1681, during the reign of the Spanish
King Charles II, in a widely-circulated compen¬
dium of laws relating to the Indies,1 in which
the chessboard model was prescribed as the only
conceivable form of urban layout. Earlier direc¬
tives, including one promulgated by Philip II
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Newcomers to Villa El
Salvador often use straw as a
material when building their
first home.
ANNA WAGNER DE REYNA,
Peruvian architect, is currently
preparing a doctorate on land
use management at the
University of Paris I. She is the
author of a study entitled Lima,
quartiers spontanés: formes
urbaines et facteurs
d'évolutionLe cas de Villa
María del Triunfo, which was
published in 1986 as part of
Unesco's "Human Settlements
and Socio-Cultural
Environment" series
(in French only).
in 1573,2 had already recommended this arrange¬
ment as a model both for Spanish and Indian
communities.
At that time the grid pattern was a response
to important strategic imperatives. With its cen¬
tral plaza de armas, it seemed in the first place
almost a replica of the military camps to which
the Spaniards were accustomed to withdraw
when trouble threatened. Besides having purely
military uses, however, the grid was part of an
attempt to instil in the overseas territories a
rigorous social organization of which the under¬
lying assumptions were order, unity and cohe¬
sion. In spite of their vast numerical inferiority,
the Spaniards would succeed through this urban
model in imposing on the indigenous peoples the
image of a people strong in its discipline, organi¬
zation and efficiency.
Today the same simple ideas have re-emerged,
inspiring a similar solution to the problems of
development. The motives are, after all, analo¬
gous: the need to bring order to a piece of land.
Bending the rules
The communities of squatter-builders contravene
the law, not only because the land they build on
has not been legally acquired but also because
they flout the planning regulations by which a
district has to be equipped with basic services
before it can be settled. The would-be residents
have to organize themselves to circumvent the
rules.
A typical group of squatter-builders consists
of a nucleus of families which either come from
the same part of Lima or from the same part of
the country. The first problem is to choose a site.
To minimize the risks, they usually choose vacant
land in public ownership, since the state is more
likely to tolerate an occupation than private land¬
owners, who generally fight vigorously to defend
their property. The squatters normally need the
backing of a well-placed politician or civil servant,
who can suggest possible sites to them. The fami¬
lies then choose leaders to take charge of the oper¬
ation, for occupying the land involves
co-ordinated collective action. Moving in is not
an initiative for individuals but a communal task
demanding concerted action by all the members
of the group.
The next stage is to draw up a plan outlining
residential zones and public spaces, shared ameni¬
ties and land reserved for future extensions. The
families are given advance notice of the timing
of the occupation, and each has specific jobs
assigned to it. An advance guard, most of which
are men, moves in to take possession of the land,
with the women and children providing back-up. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The group must then stay put, both to prevent
other families coveting the same site from moving
in and to resist any reprisals by the forces of
order.
The blueprint for the district is immediately
traced out on the ground. Individual lots are
assigned, and temporary shelters made out of rush
matting are erected on each one. The whole oper¬
ation must be carried out quickly, simply and in
good order, for an immediate, visible occupation
of the district reduces the risks of subsequent
expulsion.
Life soon begins to get organized in the
precarious encampments. Those in charge arrange
for trucks to deliver water, and do their best to
see that public transport starts to serve the new
district. The residents set about constructing
housing units and public amenities. At best it
takes ten to fifteen years before the infrastruc¬
ture of a new residential district is completed. The
risk of eviction slows the process even more.
Districts where people lack security of tenure
develop two or three times more slowly than
those where they enjoy such tenure. Conse¬
quently, the organizers go to great lengths to win
recognition of their title to the annexed land.
Below, a Bangladeshi family
works together to make a
home.
Bottom, at Popotlán (Republic
of El Salvador) low-income
families are building their own
homes with the help of small
loans for materials and on
land provided by FUNDASAL,
the Salvadorian Development
and Low-Cost Housing
Foundation.
school are not allowed to send their children to
that school. Local tribunals deal with thefts, mug¬
gings and other crimes.
A new urban model?
Right from the start, the state passively
encouraged the growth of the squatter settle¬
ments, firstly by failing to provide any effective
alternative social housing policy and subsequently
by tolerating and eventually legalizing them.
The first legal attempt to deal with them dates
from 1961, fifteen years after the earliest commu¬
nities had sprung up. That law was inspired more
by political and electoral considerations than by
any considered policy of resolving the housing
problems of the poor. Its authors sought
primarily either to win votes or to bring some
order to the question of land ownership in the
capital. In 1984, however, the city authorities
made an attempt to adopt the squatters' methods
in developing its own social housing programme.
The mayor decided to make land available to a
group of families that was already organized to
take advantage of it. Realizing the impossibility
of handing over the land through accepted legal
channels, he simply allowed them to go ahead and
occupy it.
So perhaps the word "spontaneous" is no
longer really appropriate for these settlements.
Drawing on the traditions of the Spanish con¬
quest and with a social organization comparable
to that of conventional society, Lima's squatter
communities have proved efficient enough to
challenge traditional assumptions of urban
development, and finally have forced the powers-
that-be to accept their methods as a viable solu¬
tion to the problems of popular housing.
1. Recopilación de las leyes de los reinos de las Indias ("Compen¬
dium of Laws of the Kingdoms of the Indies"), published by
Cultura Hispánica, 1973.
2. Ordonanzas de descubrimiento, nueva población y pacifica¬
ción de las Indias ("Ordinances Concerning the Discovery,
Colonization and Pacification of the Indies"), Archives of the
Indies, Seville, Spain. Editor
40
Usually they form alliances with political parties
that promise them legal right to the land in return
for votes.
The social organization that enabled the land
to be occupied and divided up and allowed houses
to be built and services to be provided, evolves
to cope with the new problems facing the com¬
munity. The organizers' job is no longer just to
defend land illegally acquired; now they must also
handle the day-to-day administration of the dis¬
trict. Their goal is to raise the living standards
of the residents, for example by sorting out
problems caused by the division of the land, as
well as to maintain order and see that the rules
that guarantee the solidarity and cohesion of the
community are respected. Transgressors are
severely punished. Families that refuse to partic¬
ipate in a collective endeavour like building a
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
BRIEF
Spanish-Muslim art
An exhibition of some 150
important works of art produced
during the centuries of Arab
presence in Spain will be held at
the Alhambra palace in Granada
on the occasion of the Seville
Universal Exhibition in 1992.
Organized by the Andalusian
authorities and the Metropolitan
Museum of New York, the
exhibition will feature works
loaned by major world museums
such as the Louvre in Paris and
the Hermitage in Leningrad.
Power from plants
"The energy sources available
today, such as oil, gas and coal,
will not last forever. Oil will be
exhausted in 50 years. This is
why we must direct research
towards the discovery of
renewable sources," said Nobel
Laureate Sir George Porter at a
recent meeting at the Ramon
Areces Foundation in Madrid. Sir
George, president of The Royal
Society and joint winner of the
1967 Nobel Prize for Chemistry,
believes that plants will provide
one of the main energy sources
of the future, particularly
through the process of
photosynthesis.
The year of Rembrandt
In 1991, the Rijksmuseum,
Amsterdam, the Gemäldegalerie
and the Kupferstichkabinett,
Berlin, and the National Gallery,
London, are jointly organizing a
major exhibition of the works of
the Dutch painter Rembrandt
(1606-1669) and his most gifted
pupils. Canvases have been
loaned from private and public
collections in the United States,
France, the Soviet Union, Austria
and Australia. 700,000 tickets
will be on sale from 1 August
1991, following the advance-
sales system which was
successfully tested during last
year's Van Gogh exhibition held
in Amsterdam.
Children's rights on film
An international group of film¬
makers (Jerry Lewis, Jean-Luc
Godard, Euzhan Palcy, Rolan
Bykov, Lino Brocka, and Ciro
Duran) have written and directed
six short features which
together make up a 60-minute
programme entitled How are the
Kids?. The English version of
the films (with subtitles where
appropriate), each of which
illustrates an aspect of the
children's rights proclaimed by
the United Nations, will be
shown on BBC television later
this year.
Saving the Black Sea
The Black Sea is on the verge
of catastrophe, says Prof.
Georgi Dechev, head of the
Bulgarian Institute of Ecology in
Sofia. He warns that the
situation is so serious that all
living organisms in the Sea are
threatened with extinction, and
that toxic in the water
could begin to pollute the
atmosphere, spelling ecological
disaster for over 150 million
people living on the coast and in
the Danube river basin. With the
support of the United Nations
Development Programme, the
World Health Organization and
the United Nations Environment
Programme, the countries on the
Black Sea coast are drawing up
a convention to assess the
extent of the environmental
problems and how to deal with
them.
'Cosmic popcorn'
In a recent issue of the British
scientific weekly Nature, the
British mathematician and
astronomer Sir Fred Hoyle and
other astrophysicists discuss
evidence to show that the
generally accepted view of the
Big Bang model for the origin of
the universe is unsatisfactory.
They propose an alternative
model which suggests a series
of small creation events in
which new matter is ejected, a
process which has been
described as a kind of "cosmic
popcorn". This hypothesis,
consistent with Prof. Hoyle's
long held steady-state theory
(that the universe is expanding
and that matter is being
constantly created), may help to
explain phenomena such as
microwave background radiation
and quasars.
5,000 years
of European history
A history of Europe has recently
been published simultaneously
in 11 European countries and In
8 languages. Written by eminent
French scholar Jean-Baptiste
Duroselle with the assistance of
historical advisers from
Germany, Italy, Spain and the
United Kingdom, the work aims
to contribute to a better
understanding of 5,000 years of
European history seen in overall
European as opposed to
national perspective. The
English translation by British
historian Richard Mayne, entitled
Europe: A History of its Peoples,
is published by Viking Penguin
Books, London and New York.
Bees against bacteria
Scientists from the National
Heart and Lung Institute,
London, have discovered that
propolis, a resinous substance
collected by bees from the buds
of trees for use in the
construction of their hives,
appears to contain antibiotics
capable of killing certain
bacteria and which may form a
future basis for medicines.
A second Noah's Ark
An unprecedented ecological
experiment known as Biosphere
2 was launched in December
1990 in the Arizona desert,
USA. The Biosphere consists
of a series of airtight
greenhouse-like structures in
glass and steel covering over a
hectare and aiming to be a
self-contained microcosm of the
world's ecosystems, including
selected animals and plants.
For the next two years
it will be home for 4 men and 4
women, whose only contact with
the outside world will be
electronic. The project has been
developed by a private company
to test the feasibility of space
colonies.
Tactile art for the blind
An exhibition entitled "Tactile
Graphic Art" is being held at
Unesco Headquarters in Paris
from 4 to 15 January 1991. It
has been organized by the
Belgian Permanent Delegation
to Unesco as part of the United
Nations World Decade for
Cultural Development
(1988-1997). Some hundred
works by over 70 Belgian artists
are being shown, each
accompanied by a relief version
for blind or partially sighted
visitors. To produce the
"tactile" pictures, a special
paper is used which swells when
heated, particularly in the inked
areas.
Literacy prize
One of the 5 international
literacy prizes awarded by
Unesco on 8 September 1990
in Geneva, the Noma Prize
offered by Japanese
publisher Shoichi Noma went
to the Institute of the Brothers
of the Christian Schools.
This teaching organization
of religious and lay members
has built up a network
of 1,200 educational institutions
in 81 countries, and
concentrates on literacy training
and education for deprived and
marginalized people in both
Third World and industrialized
countries.
Einstein's dream
The biggest particle accelerator
in the world, the large
electron-positron collider (LEP)
which became operational in
1989 at the Geneva-based
European Laboratory for
Particle Physics (CERN),
is the centre of a research
programme on subnuclear
particles and forces of
matter. Before the end of the '
century, the team of scientists
involved in one of the CERN
experiments, DELPHI
("Detector for Lepton Photon
Hadron Identification"),
hopes to find a new class of
matter called supersymmetric
particles. The existence of such
particles is predicted in the
"grand unified theories" now
being explored by physicists
and which if verified would
fulfil Einstein's dream of
discovering the common laws
governing the behaviour of
everything in the universe.
IN BRIEF. . . IN BRIEF. . BRIEF
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
world heritage
The Jesuit missions to the Guarani
by Caroline Haardt
42
In the seventeenth century the
Jesuits organized a remarkable ex¬
periment in community living in the
homeland of the Guarani Indians, on
the borders of what are today Argen¬
tina, Brazil and Paraguay. The experi¬
ment, which was compared at the
time to Thomas More's Utopia, to the
design for a Utopian commonwealth
set forth by the Italian philosopher
Tommaso Campanella in his book
The City of the Sun, and even to
Plato's Republic, lasted for over a
century. It provoked admiration in
some quarters and indignation in
others, but no one who knew any¬
thing about the matter was in¬
different to it.
Attempts had been made to con¬
vert the Guarani to Christianity during
the sixteenth century, when the area
was being colonized by the Spaniards
and the Portuguese. The Society of
Jesus and other religious orders had
sent itinerant missionaries into the
Indian villages, where they preached
the Gospel before hastily retreating
back to the relative comfort of their
colleges. These attempts to convert
the Indians were a failure. Collective
baptisms and other sacramental rites
made no lasting change in their reli¬
gious beliefs. Idolatry continued to
be practised. The missions eventu¬
ally led to disguised forms of slavery
and encouraged abuses by European
colonists and rich creóles who ex¬
ploited the captive labour force.
The exploitation of the Indians,
combined with the weakness of the
religious orders, led to a crisis which
Francisco de Toledo, the Spanish
Viceroy of Peru, and the Jesuit
fathers determined to resolve.
In 1602, the Jesuits began to
replace the Itinerant missions by
founding villages in which the Indians
could be concentrated and taught
CAROLINE HAARDT,
French journalist, was a member of
Unesco's Division of Cultural Heritage
from 1983 to 1987. She is currently
preparing an exhibition as part of the
Unesco Silk Roads project on the
Croisière Jaune, a motor rally from
Beirut to Tibet held in 1931-1932.
Christian doctrine in a stable environ¬
ment. These villages became known
as reduccionesreductionssince
in them ad ecclesiam et vitam civilem
esse reducti ("people were to be led
to the church and to civic life"). The
first of them were established by the
Jesuits of the province of Paraguay.
It was no easy task to persuade the
Indians, who were strongly attached
to their homelands, to settle In the
reductions. The Jesuits realized that
they would have to create an environ¬
ment in which Guarani tribes from
different places could feel a sense of
ethnic and cultural unity. They chose
sites which could be easily defended,
with forests, streams and land that
could be farmed.
To the Indians, the missions
The Jesuit missions of San Ignacio Mini, Argentina (below);
Trinidad, Paraguay (opposite page above);
and Säo Miguel, Brazil (opposite page below).
offered a number of attractions-
dwellings, the opportunity to practise
trades and crafts, plenty of food
(above all the beef they loved) and
the beverage known as "Jesuit tea",
which was made from the maté plant
and which also served as currency.
Dances, theatre, music, processions
and military manoeuvres were other
blandishments that contributed to
the success of the Jesuit missions.
Each reduction was self-governing,
under the spiritual supervision of a
priest. The Jesuit fathers maintained
the powers of the traditional chiefs
or caciques, and each village also
had a calbido or council of notables.
Agricultural produce and objects
produced by craftsmen belonged to
the community. Each family received
the necessities of life. Any surplus
went to widows, to the sick, to the
church, or as taxes to the Spanish
Crown.
Each reduction specialized in a
particular activity, which was deter¬
mined by the resources available to
it. Some practised animal husbandry,
others cultivated maté or cotton, or
devoted themselves to carpentry or
working in precious metals.
"Right from the start, the Guarani
missions provoked envy. They were
violently attacked by bándeirantes,
adventurers and gold prospectors
from the Säo Paulo region of Brazil.
The most severe attacks took place
between 1628 and 1630, when
groups of Indians were captured and
taken into slavery. Eventually the in¬
cursions became so numerous that
the Jesuits moved the reductions
and established them between the
Uruguay and Paraná rivers (in what
is now Paraguay).
Furious to see the Indians slip out
of their grasp, the Spanish colonists,
and above all the encomenderos* of
Asunción, were also extremely
hostile to the missionary villages. In
the mid-seventeenth century, the
Jesuits asked the King of Spain for
permission to arm the reductions so
that they could defend themselves
against attack. Thus armed, they es¬
tablished thirty missions definitively:
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
WORK IN PROGRESS
In Argentina, to save the missions of Mártires, San Javier, Corpus,
San José and Candelaria, encroaching vegetation must be cleared,
stonework must be cleaned, and an infrastructure must be estab¬
lished to protect the ruins and prevent looting.
The other missions in Argentina are in a better condition, but
restoration and consolidation work is still necessary. The most
extensive work has been done at San Ignacio Mini, which has been
a major tourist attraction for the past 25 years, and is particularly
representative of the architecture of the missions (ornately deco¬
rated church walls and portals, high-walled Indian houses, a col¬
lege with ceramic flooring). Between 1978 and 1980, museums were
created in most of the missionary villages.
In Brazil excavation and restoration work is under way at the
three main sites: Sào Miguel, Sào Nicolau and Sào Lourenço. The
Brazilian government is trying to persuade the Sào Lourenço
authorities to close the road that runs through the mission and to
clear the vegetation that infests it. Excavations have led to impor¬
tant discoveries. At Säo Nicolau a remarkable wooden capital has
been unearthed.
Since the creation of a Historic, Artistic and National Heritage
Service, new impetus has been given to operations at Säo Miguel,
where there is an unusual church notable for its baroque façade
and porch, and its dressed stone structure supported by masonry
pillars. Only its timber roof is typical of the traditional architec¬
ture of the missions. The collapse of the porch led to subsidence
which has affected the façade and the tower. The latter has been
dismantled and rebuilt. Urgent measures are necessary to prevent
the rest of the church from collapsing.
In Paraguay, work began in 1976. The college of the San Ignacio
Guazú mission, which is still inhabited by Jesuit fathers, houses
a museum of sacred art. The magnificent collections of wood
carvings and engravings at San Ignacio and Santa Maria de Fe have
been meticulously restored. The chapel at Santa Rosa, with its
murals, carved doors and panels, is unique in Guarani missionary
art. The murals are currently being repaired.
At San Cosme y San Damián, which includes the only group
of buildings among the mission villages which has been continu¬
ously inhabited since the seventeenth century, the original wooden
structure of the chapel has been restored.
At Trinidad, major efforts have been made to clean the stone¬
work of the presbytery, repair the roof of the sacristy and consoli¬
date the structure of the college and the church. With its three naves,
tower, cupola covered with varnished tiles, and frieze of angelic
musicians which adorns the crossing of the transept and the choir,
the Trinidad church is doubtless the architectural masterwork of
the Jesuit missions. .
fifteen in Argentina, seven in Brazil,
and eight in what is now Paraguay.
They flourished, and some of them
comprised more than 6,000 Indians.
Architecturally speaking, the mis¬
sions differed from the Hispano-
American towns whose forms had
been defined by the Laws of the In¬
dies. They were designed for com¬
munity life. At the heart of the village
was a large square dominated by the
church, which was big enough to ac¬
commodate the entire population.
The priests' house, the college and
other ecclesiastical buildings stood
on one side of the square. On the
other was the cemetery. The Indians'
houses were built in rows around the
square.
The experiment came to a sudden
end in the second half of the eight¬
eenth century, partly as a result of
the new frontiers drawn by colonial
treaties between Spain and Portugal,
but above all because of the expul¬
sion of the Jesuits from the Spanish
and Portuguese dominions. The po¬
litical and religious autonomy of the
missions was seen as a threat to
Spanish imperial power, and the
Jesuits were replaced by lay adminis¬
trators and priests belonging to other
religious orders. The Indians were
dispersed. The reductions were
abandoned and fell into ruin.
* The encomienda was a colonial institution
whereby the Indians were divided into groups
and enlisted into the service of an encomen¬
dero, to whom they paid a tax and who was
obliged to protect them and convert them to
'Christianity. Editor
SAFEGUARDING SITES
IN 3 COUNTRIES
There are 15 missions in Argentina, 7 in Brazil, and 8 in Paraguay.
In recognition of the common origin of this cultural heritage, the
3 countries have decided to combine their efforts to restore it. The
missions were already partially protected by law in each country,
and the first task was to improve and extend this legislation.
Since 1972, Argentina, Brazil and Paraguay have been engaged,
in collaboration with Unesco, in a joint effort to establish a cul¬
tural tourist circuit and to restore the architecture of the missions.
In 1977, the Inter-American Development Bank financed a tourist
plan for the Iguaçu Falls region and the Jesuit missions. Thanks
to support from private bodies and international organizations such
as Unesco and the Organization of American States, restoration
and conservation work began in the 3 countries.
In 1978, in response to a request from the Argentine government,
supported by Brazil and Paraguay, a plan of action was drawjn up
for an international campaign to safeguard the missions.
In 1983, the Brazilian mission of Säo Miguel and the Argentine
missions of San Ignacio Mini, Santa Ana, Santa Maria la Mayor
and Nuestra Señora de Loreto were inscribed on Unesco's World
Heritage List.
On 3 November 1988, the Director-General of Unesco launched
an appeal to the international community on behalf of the Jesuit
missions to the Guarani. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
ECEN
JAZZ
listening
X-
»
^
*****£,*<*
«^u^
Frank Morgan. Mood Indigo.
CD Island 260678. Morgan (alto
sax.), George Cables and Ronnie
Mathews (piano), Buster Williams'
(bass), Wynton Marsalis (trumpet),
Al Foster (drums).
Frank Morgan is one of the
great saxophonists of bebop as
well as one of the least-known. In
this album of admirable vigour
and smoothness, he makes a
comeback with Wynton Marsalis.
Beautifully served by an
outstanding rhythm section,
Morgan plays classics such as
"Mood Indigo" and "Polka Dots
and Moonbeams" as well as
original compositions such as
"Gratitude" and "Lullaby".
Art Blakey and the Jazz
Messengers. Not Yet.
CD Soul Note 121 105-2. Blakey
(drums), Philip Harper (trumpet),
Robin Eubanks (trombone), Javon
Jackson (tenor sax.), Peter
Washington (bass), Benny Green
(piano).
Another excellent disc from
the late great Art Blakey and a
talented team of young musicians.
One highlight is the playing of
Benny Green, who provides a
superb piano introduction for "I'll
Never Be the Same".
Abbey Lincoln. The World is
Falling Down.
CD Verve 843 476-2.
The first time I heard the
"Freedom Now Suite" in the late
1960s was an unforgettable
emotional experience. Abbey
Lincoln, as spell-binding as ever,
is accompanied by some first-rate
musicians including Jackie
McLean, Clark Terry, Billy Higgins
and Ron Carter.
FOLK
44
Chinese Turkestan/Xinjiang/
Uyghur Music.
Box of 2 CDs. Ocora
C 559092-93.
The Uyghur live with other
Turko-Mongolian populations in
Xinjiang in northwestern China,
and in the Soviet Union. Turkestan
has been a crossroads of
civilizations and a meeting point
of Orient and Occident.
Contemporary Uyghur music,
based on muqam (modal
categories), reflects Arab
influence. Among the much-used
string instruments are the satar,
tanbur, and rawap, variants of
which are found in India, Iran,
Afghanistan and the Middle East.
Memory of the Peoples/Mémoire
des Peuples.
CD Auvidis/Unesco D 8200.
A compilation of folk music
from the major world regions. For
armchair travellers, a fabulous
journey which takes In Corsica,
Bielorussia, Kurdistan, Viet Nam,
Morocco, and Brazil.
POP	
Daniel Ponce. Arawe.
CD Antilles 90631-2.
One of the best Cuban
percussionists in the. United
States, Ponce arrived in New York
in 1980 after escaping from
Havana by boat. Yoruba by origin,
he grew up in the atmosphere of
carnival and rumba. Here he
recreates his country's music in
all its vigour, mingled with
elements taken from soul music.
An intelligent and lively example
of cross-fertilization.
Selif Keita. Ko-Yan.
CD Island 842 454-2.
Keita mixes, with varylngly
successful results, the African
tradition and funk, notably by
using synthesizers. I think
"Prlmpin" is the most successful
track. "Tenin" is an attempt to
recreate the atmosphere
associated with the kora, the
harp-lute played by the Mandingo
people of West Africa. The lyrics,
as in most African songs, contain
a moral message: "It's better to
do good today for God/ Than to
wait for gratitude tomorrow."
African pop music is feeling Its
way, and this recording by Keita is
one of the most successful
efforts to date.
Isabelle Leymarie
err)nomus/co/oá/st and Journalist
CLASSICAL	
George Frideric Handel. Susanna.
The Chamber Chorus of the
University of California, Berkeley/
Philharmonia Baroque Orchestra.
Box of 2 CDs. Harmonía Mundi
907030.32.
This superb oratorio is rarely
performed because of its length.
Texts in English, French and
German outline the history of the
work and provide a detailed
synopsis of it. The story is set In
Babylon, where the beautiful
Susanna, during the absence of
her husband Joacim, is accused
of adultery by two elders whose
advances she has rejected.
Condemned to death, she Is
saved by Daniel and is reunited
with her husband. The counter¬
tenor Drew Minter sings the role
of Joacim, and soprano Lorraine
Hunt sings that of Susanna.
Gregorio Paniagua. Villancicos.
Atrium Musicae of Madrid.
CD Harmonía Mundi 1901025.
The villancico tradition of
Spanish folk songs from the 15th
and 16th centuries, which has .
survived in Puerto Rico, originated
in Arab-Andalusian poetry. During
the Renaissance, these short
polyphonic pieces were inspired
by sacred or profane subjects.
Traditional instruments such as
the chirimía, the psaltery, the
dulcimer and the crumhorn can.
be heard on this recording,
creating an atmosphere of court
festivities.
Franz Schubert. Works for Piano.
Alfred Brendel.
Box of 7 CDs. Philips 426 128-2.
Here, performed by one of
the greatest living pianists, are
the pieces for solo piano
composed by Schubert between
1822 and his death in 1828. The
idea of death haunts this music
and invests it with tragic force.
Schubert's work shows a growing
consistency, especially in the
pieces composed after the death
of Beethoven. The "Wanderer"
Fantasy is a very modem piece
which enchanted Liszt. The "6
Momens musicals" and the late
"Impromptus" are redolent of
poetry and dance. The authority
of Brendel's performance is
exceptional. A monumental
achievement!
Yoshira Taira.
Hommage à Noguchi.
CD Auvidis/Unesco D 8302.
Born in 1937, Taira is one of
the dominant figures of
contemporary Japanese classical
music. He draws inspiration from
the West, just as European
composers such as Debussy and
Messiaen borrowed ideas from
Asia, and here pays tribute to the
sculptor Isamu Noguchi. A
felicitous blend of shakuhachi
(bamboo flute), flute, harp, cello
and tape recordings in
compositions which exalt the
sanctity of nature.
Martinu. The Greek Passion.
Brno Philharmonic Orchestra
conducted by Charles Mackerras.
Box of 2 CDs.
Supraphon 10 3611-2 632.
The great Czech composer
Bohaslav Martinu, who died in
1959, has still not received the
recognition he deserves. Sung in
English, this work completed in
the year of his death and inspired
by Nikos Kazantzakis's novel
Christ Recrucified, provides an
arresting social and mythical
vision of the world. The music is
timeless. It possesses, in the
words of Martinu's biographer,
Guy Erismann, "the force of the
supernatural and of emotion".
Claude Glayman I
journalist and music critic
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
N I
Current systems of measuring economic performance often conceal
widespread human deprivation and degradation of the environment
Reviewing the accounts
by Michel Bâtisse
nu environmental problems today
can be analysed as assaults on the
biosphere by modern Industrial
civilizationthe technosphere.*
Without this profusion of industrial,
agricultural, medical and other inven¬
tions, we should not be able to feed,
clothe and shelter (with varying
degrees of success) the present
world population of some six billion
people, still less to provide a fraction
of them with the comfort and abun¬
dance which are the hallmarks of the
so-called developed countries.
We have cast in our lot with
technology. But technology is not
neutral, as the science of which it is
an offshoot seeks to be. It is marked
by the choices of what has been
called the sociosphere* and notably
by the principal motor of the so¬
ciosphere, the economy.
Does this mean that the
economists are responsible for the
current environmental crisis? And
that no share of the blame attaches
to engineers, agronomists, architects
and consumers? It would be far too
MICHEL BATISSE,
French engineer and physicist, is
internationally known for his work on
the environment and natural
resources. A former Unesco staff
member, he was instrumental in
launching the International
Hydrological Decade (1965-1974)
and Unesco's interdisciplinary Man
and the Biosphere (MAB)
programme. Currently a consultant
with Unesco and with the United
Nations Environment Programme, he
has headed the Blue Plan Regional
Activity Centre for the Mediterranean
at Sophia Antipolls, France, since it
was created in 1985.
simplistic to look for a single
scapegoat In this way, but it cannot
be denied that there is something
wrong with our economic models and
that they are not entirely blameless.
The most widespread economic
thinking today is still dominated by
the Keynesian macro-economic
model, which combines consump
tion, savings, investment and public
expenditure and is concerned with
attaining, as far as possible, full em¬
ployment.
Keynesian economics takes no ac¬
count of the role of natural resources
In production, perhaps because it
was elaborated during the colonial
era, after the great depression of
Soil erosion In Amazonia due to deforestation.
1929, at a time when natural
resources still seemed Inexhaustible
and It was not generally realized that
they constitute the prime source of
wealth of almost all developing coun¬
tries. Perhaps also because the im¬
pact of economic activity on the
biosphere was then still at a tolerable
level. With a world population of only
two billion people, annual production
was equivalent to today's monthly
output.
The more a country
pollutes,
the richer it seems
to be...
The spectacular rise in industrial
output after the Second World War
whetted a growing appetite for all
kinds of material goods, of which the
automobile Is perhaps the most
striking symbol. Countries wanted to
have statistical records for meas¬
uring their progress and their posi¬
tion in relation to others. Income
levels were considered to be the best
Indicators of wealth.
Since then, governments have
set annual growth of national income
as their major target. Accounting
systems for measuring economic ac¬
tivity were established and the notion
of Gross National Product (GNP) was
invented, as well as its more sophisti¬
cated variants such as Gross
Domestic Product (GDP). There was
a great temptation to measure a
country's standard of living exclu¬
sively in terms of per capita GDP and
to establish a pecking order of coun¬
tries on this basis.
This is still current practice and the 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
criteria associated with it divide the
world into developed and developing
countries. However, it has long been
accepted that GDP is a rough and
ready indicator. One example of its
Inadequacy is the way in which it to¬
tally ignores unpaid work such as
that done by the countless numbers
of women in the Third World who
fetch and carry water and firewood.
Regarding the environment, GDP
makes no distinction between
productive work and palliative
measures. Thus the production costs
of a factory which causes pollution
are added to the costs of combating
that pollution. According to this
system of accountancy, the more a
country pollutes, the richer It seems
to be!
Even more serious and contrary to
the practice of businesses, which
keep a capital account from which
they deduct the depreciation of their
capital goods over time, states cal¬
culating their GDP take no account
of the depreciation of the capital
comprised by their natural resources
and their environment. Generally
speaking, in the exploitation of non¬
renewable natural resources such as
oil and fossil groundwater, and also in
that of so-called renewable resources
such as tropical forests or soils, which
are actually only partially renewable,
current economic calculations simply
consider what is taken from capital
as income. Here too, the more a
country exhausts its potential in
terms of resources, the more its GDP
increases and the richer it seems.
In the national accounting system
adopted by almost all countries
under the auspices of the United Na¬
tions, there is currently no means of
taking into account the cost of the
degradation of resources and en¬
vironmental factors which do not
form part of market mechanisms.
There is no generally accepted
method of calculating the value of
pure air, clean water, wild animals or
the beauty of sites. Everything which
cannot be considered as property or
which cannot be expressed in terms
of a price is considered as a gift of
Providence, set.at our disposal to be
used or abused. This inadequacy of
economics and this attitude of
modern society are bound to en¬
courage the waste of resources and
the sack of the environment.
This being so, it is not surprising
that advertising should urge us to
use more electricity or detergent,
that there should be overt or hidden
subsidies to encourage the use of
more fertilizer and pesticides, and
that there should be bulk-user price
concessions to encourage us to con¬
sume more water, cement or energy.
Until relatively recently, for example,
extensive deforestation in Brazilian
Amazonia was encouraged by tax
relief and subsidies in favour of en¬
terprises which embarked on risky'
animal husbandry projects.
Sustainable human
development
In spite of all its inadequacies, the
concept of GDP is unlikely to disap¬
pear immediately. It is an economic
instrument for quantifying market ac¬
tivity in the short term. We should
simply not read more into GDP than
it really means. It grows as a result
of technological progress, but its
growth cannot be limitless. In any
case growth cannot be based on
constantly increasing consumption
of natural resources, which is physi¬
cally impossible. Did not Aristotle be¬
lieve that the accumulation of
"wealth" is not an end in itself? The
purpose of life is rather to achieve
sustainable human development
through optimizing the material and
spiritual possibilities available to
every human being, while not com¬
promising the capacity to satisfy the
needs of future generations.
The United Nations Development
Programme (UNDP) took a first step
in this direction recently when it
created a composite human develop-
ment index (HDI) which integrates
into GDP the adult literacy rate, life
expectancy and the purchasing
power to buy commodities for satis¬
fying basic needs. It is interesting to
note that the United States, which
has the world's second highest per
capita GDP (after Switzerland), is only
in nineteenth position on the HDI. It
is also comforting to note that some
developing countries with low per
capita income, such as China, Costa
Rica, Jamaica and Sri Lanka (or coun¬
tries with a very low income such as
the United Republic of Tanzania)
score comparatively well in this
evaluation of human development.
The HDI is not much better than
GDP as a reflection of the environ¬
mental situation, but it shows that
GDP can be improved as an ac¬
counting system. In fact various at¬
tempts have been made in the last
two decades to take account of the
quality of the environment and
natural resources in economic anal¬
ysis. Mineral reserves, forests, water
and soil have been taken into ac¬
count. France has evaluated its
natural heritage and Norway is en¬
gaged on a similar exercise.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Above, a small boat applying a non¬
toxic dispersant chemical cuts a clean
swathe through an oil slick at sea.
Right, "states calculating their Gross
Domestic Product take no account of
the depreciation of the capital
comprised by their natural resources
and their environment".
Opposite page below, "efforts are
being made to apply more widely the
principle that the polluter should pay".
An attempt can also be made to
set a monetary value on those com¬
modities which do not figure in
market exchanges and to establish
"satellite accounts" relating to the
main operations which have an im¬
pact on the environment. When this
is done the result is a downward cor¬
rection of GDP which may be ex¬
tremely instructive. An in-depth study
of this kind on Indonesia shows that
the country's GDP increased by 7 per
cent annually between 1970 and
1984, but that if account Is taken of
losses In terms of soils, forests and
oil, the increase was actually only 4
per cent per year. Similar calcula¬
tions carried out for other countries
could even show a gradual reduction
in national wealth.
Perhaps more important than
these adjustments, at the somewhat
abstract national scale, is the inclu¬
sion of environmental impacts in the
cost-benefit analysis of major de¬
velopment programmes such as road
and dam construction, forestry and
mining. Natural resources and the
environment have so far hardly
figured in methods of calculation, for
the reasons given above. However,
thanks notably to the work of the
World Bank and UNDP, attempts are
today being made to modify cost-
benefit analysis procedures and to
respect a certain number of
minimum safety norms relating to en¬
vironmental impacts.
Efforts are also being made to
apply more widely the principle that
the polluter should pay, that those
who cause pollution should be made
to pay for the damage they cause.
The principle is relatively easy to
apply in the case of an oil company
responsible for an oil spill that has to
be cleaned up or an industrialist who
discharges chemical products into a
river and can be taxed accordingly.
The situation is more complicated
when all the farmers in a region pol¬
lute water with pesticides but cannot
be identified individually. And what
can be done when the air polluter is
simply the average motorist?
An ecological economy
It must be admitted that the accounts
of the difficult marriage between
economics and ecology have not yet
been fully put in order. The debate
is far from academic, since develop¬
ment decisions are still largely based
on Keynesian economic analysis, and
no country or place is unaffected by
these decisions.
The fact is that the globalization
of markets is ineluctably bringing rich
and poor countries together and im¬
posing on them a system of trade,
prices and regulations which, by
glorifying GDP and Ignoring capital
resources, is dangerously ag¬
gravating pressures on the environ¬
ment thousands of kilometres from
the place where the decisions are
taken.
Thus poor accounting in one
country may lead to wrong decisions
for itself and for others. Some trop¬
ical monocultures for export would
doubtless not have been cultivated
if it had been possible to calculate
their ecological and social disadvan¬
tages. Conversely, it would be In¬
teresting to explore other paths of
development than those prompted
by excessively simple forms of eco¬
nomic calculation. It has, for example,
been shown that the sustainable ex¬
ploitation of fruit and other small
products of the Peruvian forest could
bring in two or three times more than
felling for timber, and would have the
obvious advantage of leaving the
forest intact.
These methods of sustainable de¬
velopment, which help to conserve
ecosystems and benefit the local
populations which take part in them,
are encouraged in the biosphere
reserves supported by Unesco. Cer¬
tain precautions clearly have to be
taken, especially that the crops
chosen should be marketable, for if
economics must take account of
ecology, the opposite is also true.
Classical economists such as Adam
Smith, David Ricardo and Robert
Malthus, and even Karl Marx, took
account of the value of agricultural
land, but until very recent times the
economy has simply ignored ecology
and development has paid no heed
to the environment. At present the
economy is trying with more or less
good grace to mitigate the most
visible forms of ecological damage.
Pollution is combated, national parks
are created, policies for the environ¬
ment are announced. These are
steps in the right direction but they
are not enough. We must move more
resolutely and more swiftly towards
a new stage which will effectively
integrate economic systems with
ecological systems and will lead the
world as a whole to the sustainable
development which hitherto has been
talked about rather than effected.
We may feel that there is little we
can do about the issues raised here.
This is not so. Our dally choices and
behaviour define the forms of de¬
velopment adopted in different parts
of the world. The protection of the
environment begins on our own door¬
step. It is not only a matter for other
people, for businesses and govern¬
ments. Are we, for example, ready to
reduce pollution and economize on
oil consumption by using our cars
only when we really need them? Are
we ready to buy only "environment-
friendly" products? To take a stand
against building up coastlines and
green spaces? To avoid despoiling
nature and wasting resources? Are
we ready to support new ethical stan¬
dards for the relationship between
economic activity and ecology? Or do
we wish to remain accomplices of the
world environment crisis? We should
all re-examine our accounts.
* See the article by Michel Bâtisse in the
November 1990 Issue of the Unesco Courier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The
Silk
Roads
were channels of trade
and dialogue between
East and West at least
2,000 years ago. Today
Unesco is seeking to
renew this dialogue
through a far-reaching
project to investigate
these historic arteries of
communication.
An overland expedition
has already been
completed, and on
23 October 1990 a
\tn w v mi i * r
maritime expedition set
sail from Venice en route
for Osaka in Japan,
where it is scheduled to
arrive in March 1991.
French writer
François-Bernard Huyghe,
on board ée expedition's
"Ship of Peace", fills in
the background to this
unique voyage of
discovery.
mm Qnimiiz
In the wake of Marco Polo
by François-Bernard Huyghe
'A
48
FRANÇOIS-BERNARD HUYGHE
is a former member of Unesco's
Division of Cultural Heritage.
crowd of people gathered on
the canal, standing on vessels. Silk
parasols were everywhere to be
seen. The boats themselves were ad¬
mirably painted." In these words the
great Arab traveller Ibn Battuta, who
spent thirty years journeying through
the Islamic world of his time,
described the great city of Hangzhou
in southern China, in the mid-
fourteenth century.
On 23 October 1990, there was a
similarly colourful scene at St. Mark's
Basin In Venice, terminus of one of
the routes along which the Chinese
silk noted by Ibn Battuta was for
centuries brought to Europe. While
crowds watched from the quayside,
a flotilla of historic boats gathered
to celebrate the departure of the
Omani ship Fulkal-Salamah, or "Ship
of Peace", on a journey that will
retrace the ancient maritime silk
route from Europe to the Far East.
The vessel has been loaned by
Sultan Qabus of Oman as the flag¬
ship of an international scientific
expedition that marks a high point in
Unesco's Integral Study of the Silk
Roads: Roads of Dialogue project.
The Venetian rowers raised their oars
in salute as we prepared to set sail
to a fanfare of trumpets anda roll of
drums.
Also moored in St. Mark's Basin for
the send-off was the Sultan's
54-metre three-masted dhow Z/nat
al-Bihaar ("Beauty of the Seas").
Although It is only three years old,
the traditional lateen-rigged wooden
dhow and the traditional costume of
the envoys from Oman who mingled
with the international delegations
were reminders of the historic Venice
depicted by Carpaccio and other
Venetian painters, of the days when
ambassadors, travellers and mer¬
chandise from the whole of the then
known world converged on "the
most serene city" and took part in
ceremonies presided over by the
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
The city of Venice as depicted In a
manuscript copy of The Travels of
Marco Polo, 1298-1299.
Right, Zheng He (1371-1435), a
Chinese navigator and diplomat
selected by the Ming emperor to be
commander In chief of the missions to
the "Western Oceans".
Below, the "Ship of Peace" In Venice
harbour.
Doge in his magnificent state barge,
the Bucintoro.
Flying the flag of the United Na¬
tions, the Fulk al-Salamah will carry
the Unesco expedition from Venice
to Osaka in Japan, where it is sched¬
uled to arrive on 3 March 1991. Over
fifty scientists and journalists on
board will be calling at some twenty-
one ports in sixteen countries, where
symposia, visits and other events will
be held as part of the research
programme.
The aim of the Unesco project is
to study the ancient channels of
communication between Orient and
Occident from different viewpoints
and disciplines. The term "Silk
Roads" Seidenstrassen was
coined by the German geographer
Ferdinand von Richthofen, himself a
great traveller in the nineteenth-
century tradition, to designate the
vast network of exchanges and in¬
fluences which stretched across Asia
as early as the second century BC
and helped to shape its spiritual and
material history. Many scientific
disciplines above all the human
sciences are represented on the
"Ship of Peace". Among them are
economics, archaeology, the history
of technology, the history of
religions, sociology, linguistics, ge¬
ography and philosophy. The very
name of the ship is a symbol of a
desire to understand and recreate
the dialogue between Orient and
Occident of which Venice is the
incarnation.
The quest of Marco Polo
The most celebrated Venetian of all
time was Marco Polo, the traveller
and merchant whose account of his
adventures in central Asia and China
in the late thirteenth century first set
Europe dreaming exotic dreams
about the Orient. "I think it pleased
God that we should come back, so
that people should know the things
that are in the world.... Never has
man, neither Christian, nor Saracen,
nor Tartar, nor pagan, made such a
quest across the earth as that of
Messer Marco, nephew of Messer
Nicolö Polo, noble and great citizen
of the city of Venice." These are the
last lines of the Tuscan version of his
book The Travels of Marco Polo,
which he dictated to his fellow-
captive, Rusticiano of Pisa, after he
had been made prisoner by the
Genoese in 1298.
There began an episode without
precedent in the history of literature.
Marco Polo's story of his adventures,
variously titled Le Livre des Merveilles
du Monde, Imago Mundi, Divisament
dou monde, and translated into
several romance languages, spread
throughout Europe. It inspired many
armchair explorers and some real
ones, the most famous of the latter
being Christopher Columbus who,
when he sighted the coast of Cuba
in 1492, thought he had reached
Marco Polo's Cathay. It has been said
that Marco Polo discovered China in
his lifetime and America after his
death. This is historically false, but
poetically true.
It had long been known in Europe
that there was a country in the East
which manufactured sericum (Latin
for "silk" from si, the Chinese word
for silk). When this mysterious and
prestigious fabric reached Rome In
the second century BC, little was
known about it except that it came
from the country of the Seres, a
fabulous place where, according to
the Greek satirist Lucian, people lived
to be 300 years old.
The many routes along which silk
was brought westwards varied over
the centuries, creating a network of
contacts some of whose traces can
still be followed in space and time.
Few men crossed the vast Eurasian
continent from end to end. It was not
until 98 AD that the first Chinese em¬
bassy arrived in the West, and in 166
AD what is known as the embassy of
the emperor Antoninus reached
China. In point of fact the "ambas¬
sador" was an adventurous mer¬
chant and not a representative of
imperial Rome.
Several centuries would pass be¬
fore the Far East came into more fre¬
quent contact with western Europe.
The first European explorers set out
for China in the Middle Ages, most
of them by overland routes, some by
sea. The majority were missionaries
such as Jean de Montcorvin, who
sailed from Venice in 1288 and ten
years later built the first Christian
church at Kanbalik (Beijing). Some,
such as Giovanni Loredan, entered
the service of the Mongols. The
Vilioni family, who may also have
been Venetians, were also great
travellers who left traces of their
presence in the Far East. One
member of the family is known to
have made his will at Tabriz in 1264,
and at Hangzhou is the tomb of a
Catherine Vilioni who died on 2 June
1342.
Who knows how many other Euro¬
peans set out for the East and
travelled at least part of the way
along the Silk Roads? The first stage
of the journey from Europe was most
likely to be a sea voyage. The classic
route was from Genoa, Brindisi or
Venice to the east coast of the
Mediterranean, where an adven¬
turous overland journey would begin
at Alexandria, St. Jean d'Acre or
Istanbul. In 1340 the Florentine Fran¬
cesco Balducci Pegolotti wrote in his
Pratica della Mercatura, the first
travel guide for European merchants,
that it took more than seven months
to travel from the Sea of Azov to
Hangzhou. The journey by sea took
even longer.
Venice occupied a key position in
the Western approaches to this Silk
Road. It was known, after all, as the
gateway to the East. Marco Polo was
the first Venetian to reach China, but
the city of the Doges had long held
sway over the Mediterranean basin.
Fortified by its political system (a
Republic which lasted eleven centu¬
ries without a break), its navy, its
colonies, its diplomats and mer¬
chants, Venice became the in¬
dispensable intermediary between
Orient and Occident. Until the six¬
teenth century, it was the European
port famed for precious Eastern mer
chandise such as silk, spices, carpets
and porcelain.
The secrets of paper
Oriental communities driven from
their homeland by war found asylum
In Venice, and in the fifteenth and six¬
teenth centuries the city was
thronged with foreigners who
brought with them their customs,
crafts and trading enterprises. Jews,
Armenians and Greeks had their own
neighbourhoods. And there is a fun¬
damenta oí the Ormesini in Venice,
a street of the people of Hormuz.
The foreign colonies which be¬
came established in Venice enriched
the Republic with new technologies.
In addition to their mastery of silk and
velvet weaving, the Chinese held the
secrets of paper manufacturing,
which also reached the West by
stages. When printing was in¬
troduced to Venice, it spread rapidly,
its development boosted by the city's
heterogeneous community. Many
Greek, Hebrew and Arabic texts were
printed. 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
Back numbers wanted
A long-standing subscriber to the
French edition of the Unesco Courier,
I am trying to complete my collection.
After a fruitless search in bookshops,
I am writing to you directly. I would be
prepared to buy the following back
numbers if anyone would like to part
with them: the years 1948 to 1968;
January to October 1969; February,
November and December 1970; March,
July 1971; May 1972; March, August,
September 1975; July, November,
December 1977; the year 1978;
November 1983. Bertrand Ferro
3 rue de la Meuse
54520 Laxou (France)
For sale
I'm looking for a buyer for 46 copies of
the Unesco Courier, in French, dating
from March 1962 to March 1974.
Emile Granger
33 rue des Baconnets
92160 Antony (France)
Plan of action for survival
Readers should be grateful to the
Unesco Courier for publishing, even a
year late, the text, of the Vancouver
Declaration of September 1989 which
sets out the appalling problems facing
humanity and outlines some alternative
visions of the future.
As a concerned inhabitant of our
common planet, it seems to me that we
have reached the stage where mere
declarations are no longer adequate. It
is possible that the present transition
from competition to co-operation
between the world powers may herald
the dawn of a new era. Perhaps we are
heading towards the realization of the
old dream of a world federation, as
expounded by Albert Einstein, H.G.
Wells and Bertrand Russell.
But it is also possible that the formid¬
able political and economic forces
In the wake
ofMarco Polo (CONTINUED)
50
In general, intellectual influences
travelled only short distances along
the Silk Roads. No Chinese poet be¬
came known in the West, no Greek
or Latin author crossed the Great
Wall. Buddhism long remained
unknown in the West, and the Chris¬
tian missionaries who set out for the
Far East never really implanted their
doctrine. Only after the Jesuit mis¬
sions began in the sixteenth century
did Western Christianity become es¬
tablished in some parts of the Orient.
Islam alone expanded in the East. It
which rule us are opposed to change,
and that they are in fact anxious to per¬
petuate the present system, whether
for selfish reasons or through Ignor¬
ance of the true magnitude of what is
at stake. A collective and determined
effort by leading scientists and intellec¬
tuals may thus be required to prepare
a practical plan of action, and to bring
the full facts of the tragedy that
threatens us to the attention of world
leaders and the public at Jarge. At the
same time, an organization like Unesco
is clearly in a position to play a leading
role in shaking the public out of its
indifference. Zeev Raphae|
Haifa (Israel)
Old obsessions
I read with great interest the article on
"Rethinking scientific progress", by
Marc Chapdelaine and Jacques
Richardson, in your September 1990
issue. The eminent names quoted in the
text compel respect and may even
encourage more profound reflection on
the human condition. It seems that we
are all cogs in the wheels of an age
racked by multiple problems and that
we have to suffer the consequences of
an imbalance between developments In
science and culture on the one hand,
and approaches to economics and
communication between peoples on
the other.
At the heart of this universal dilemma
lies the regrettable tendency,
unmitigated by time, to give in to old
obsessions which could at any moment
plunge us back into horror and hatred.
Professor Yujiro Nakamura, in his
warning to the Vancouver conference,
seems to have summed up the
phenomenon very well. He states:
"Contact between different peoples
and nations has not brought mutual
respect, but often violent opposition...."
Lack of understanding between cul¬
tures can only in the long term
was not until the late seventeenth
century, and even more in the eight¬
eenth, that the West really became
interested in what others thought
and in studying their history.
Once the concept of the Silk Roads
had been established by von
Richthofen, attempts were made to
locate them with precision. Routes
followed since the second century
BC were retraced. Explorers visited
towns which had been staging posts
on routes through steppe and desert.
They journeyed from Calcutta to
Balkh and followed the paths
whereby Buddhism had spread. They
sailed from Alexandria and through
the Red Sea, the Gulf of Aden, the
Sea of Oman, the Indian Ocean and
encourage those who are so distracted
by blind obedience to the principles of
another age that they do not see a fun¬
damental truththe only way to put an
end to suffering is a thorough under¬
standing of its causes.
At the dawn of the third millennium,
as you are attempting to show in your
invaluable magazine, it is vital that
among the dangers that threaten us all
this particular problem should be recog¬
nized as a major element in human
society. Otherwise blood and tears will
flow again and the fine spirit of
generosity and humanism expressed by
some of the greatest figures of our time
will be rendered meaningless.
Judging by the extremely serious and
alarming events taking place today, we
may be in danger of taking the chaotic
road to decline, to general xenophobia
and rejection of our fellows.
That would be the end of the human
race and its fragile little world, for to
make a mistake where mankind is con¬
cerned is, ultimately, to condemn the
whole of humanity.
Francis Hervé Charlssoux
Lyon (France)
Correction
I am glad to be among the thousands
of readers who will write to you in order
to tell you that the painting on the cover
of the December 1990 issue of the
Unesco Courier is nota Rothko but a
Newman, the title of which is Vir
Heroicus Sublimus. In order to help you
for future identifications among
abstract expressionists, please
remember this very humorous resume
by Ad Reinhardt:
mm m
Newman Reinhardt
Jessica Bolssel
Paris
Full marks! We apologize to readers for the
error. Editor
the China Sea to Osaka. Great interest
was taken in the trading centres
caravanserais, post systems, Venetian
trading houses. A mass of informa¬
tion about the Silk Roads began to be
accumulated. The experts involved
in the Unesco project are seeking to
bring together and make sense of all
this scattered knowledge.
But let us not forget that there are
also imaginary journeys, evoked in
myths and fabulous stories. From
travellers' tales to major works of
literature, the Silk Roads still weave
a magic spell.
As we set sail in the Fulk al-
Salamah, the thoughts of many of us
on board turned irresistibly back to
Marco Polo.
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, page 3 (right): © Moira F.
Harris, Minnesota. Back cover: © D.
Stamenkovich, Paris. Page 2:
© Helena Delgado Rufino, Lisbon.
Pages 3 (left), 4: © Collections of the
Library of Congress, Washington,
D.C. Page 5: © DITE/IPS, Paris-
House of the Representatives Wing of
the US Capitol Building. Pages 6-7,
7, 8, 46: © DITE/IPS, Paris. Page 6
(above): © J.L. Charmet,
Paris/Bibliothèque des Arts
Décoratifs, Paris. Page 9: Eric L.
Wheater © The Image Bank, Paris.
Page 10: © Dagli Orti, Paris/Museum
of Modern Art, Mexico. Page 12:
Unesco/A. Jonquières. Page 13
(above): © Eric Guillemot, Paris.
Pages 13 (below), 14, 25: © Wolf
Tochtermann, Paris. Page l5:
©Hervé Bernard, Paris. Page 17:
© Andrea Brizzi/UNDP, New York.
Page 18: © Bruno Puevo, Paris.
Pages 18-19: © G. Ducret, Paris.
Pages 20, 20-21: Serge Sibert
© Odyssey, Paris. Pages 22-23: Pascal
Maitre © Odyssey, Paris. Page 24
(above): © Gérard Degeorge, Paris.
Pages 24 (below), 40 (below):
© Studio Azzurro/UNDP, New
York. Page 26: © Collection Viollet,
Paris. Page 27: © Benoît Rajau, Paris.
Pages 28 (inset), 49 (below):
Unesco/Dominique Roger. Page 28
(right): Russian edition of the Unesco
Courier, Moscow. Pages 30-31:
Raghubir Singh © ANA, Paris. Page
32: © with the permission of the
Fondation Le Corbusier,
Paris/SPADEM. Pages 33, 34, 35
(below): © Gunnar Nagel, Hamburg.
Page 35 (above): © STERN-Archiv,
Berlin. Page 36: Stadtgrün © STERN,
Berlin. Page 37: © Foto Servicio
Aerofotografico Nacional, Peru.
Pages 38, 39: © Lois Jensen/UNDP,
New York. Page 40 (above):
Unesco/Kazi Mizanur Rahman. Page
42: François Gohier © Explorer,
Paris. Page 43 (above): José Mayans
© Ciric, Paris; (below): © ICOMOS,
Paris. Page 45: Abril © Gamma,
Paris. Page 47: © Ivette Fabri, Paris.
Page 48: © Roger-Viollet,
Paris/Musée Correr, Venice. Page 49
(right): © Roger-Viollet, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
44th YEAR
Published monthly in 35 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31. rue François Bonvin. 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkm, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Russian edition: Georgi Zelenin
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, Carole Paiot
(Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15).
Mouna Chatta
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: SJ. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kossler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A, M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Stovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88),
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie. Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk. Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64).
Accounts: (45.68.45.65).
Mall: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 139 French francs. 2 years: 259 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 108 French francs. 2 years: 194 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear authors name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published
in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by
Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform {microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Pans; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (3) NCR. Microcard Edition. Indian Head.
Inc.. 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York. U.S.A. ;T4) Bell and Howell Co..
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) - DEPOT LEGAL CI - JANVIER 1991.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE NO 71844 DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP.
Photocomposition: The Unesco Courier
Photogravure-impression: Maury imprimeur S.A.,
Z.I. route d'Etampes. 45330 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 1 - 1991 -OPI-90- 3-489 A
Each month it explores
the astonishing diversity of
world culture and knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's
mission offurthering "universal respect for
justice, for the rule of law and for human rights
and fundamental freedoms...without distinction
of race, sex, language or religion..."
..- ËaVJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJ]
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
