<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="089116eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
*
â ''
*
AUGUST-SEPTEMBER 1991
-
#*
M 1205- 9109 36,00 F
?up
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
_l
encounters We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
Untitled
1989, tapestry cartoon (50 x 50 cm) by Raymond Pichaud
In Western art a cartoon was originally a full-sized drawing done on pasteboard and used as a model
for a tapestry, a fresco painting, a mosaic or a stained glass design. In its purity of line
and geometric tension, this cartoon by the contemporary French artist Raymond Pichaud seems
to be the fruit of an encounter between this Western tradition and the spirit of African art.
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
AUGUST-SEPTEMBER 1991 CONTENTS
4
Interview with
TAHARBENJELLOUN
Thel Inesco
^COURIER
44th YEAR
Published monthly In 35 languages end in Braille
"The Governments of the States
parties to this Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds
of men, It Is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded, If It Is not to
fail, upon the Intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
Increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect knowledge of
each other's lives..."
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of UNESCO,
London, 16 November 1945
11
SEA FEVER
Fragments for a private iconography
of the sea
by Edouard J. Maunick 12
TIME AND TIDE
The wondrous deep
by Rachid Sabbaghi
The legacy of Confucius
by W. E. Cheong
16
20
In the wake of Ulysses
by André Kédros
Pacific pioneers
by Tipene O'Regan
24
28
VOICES FROM THE SEA
Music of the waves
by Georges Moustaki
Yemanja, goddess of the sea
by Mario de Aratanha
Night watch, alone
by Arthur Gillette
32
34
37
STORIES AND SYMBOLS
The shipwrecked sailor's story 40
ta Taro
43
The strange destiny of Urashim r
by Ninomiya Masayuki
Moby Dick, monster of the forbidden seas
by A. Robert Lee 46
Reflections on the ocean
by Elisabeth Mann Borgese 50
Sailor beware!
by Pier Giovanni d'Ayala 54
71
IN BRIEF...
72
UNESCO IN ACTION
ENVIRONMENT
The Blue Plan
for the Mediterranean
by Michel Bâtisse
75
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
An ecological Eldorado:
Peru's Manu
National Park
by José Serra- Vega
78
UNESCO IN ACTION
THE SILK ROADS
The return
of the Fulk al-Salamah
by François-Bernard Huyghe
81
UNESCO IN ACTION
News from UNESCO
82
LISTENING
Recent records
Cover:
sea-wave and sunset.
THE LAST FRONTIER Back cover:
A scientist looks at the sea
early 16th-century miniature
by Don Walsh 5«
The ghost ship of the Arctic
by David Gunston 63 Special consultant
The four pillars of Neptune's temple for this issue:
by Jacques Ferrier 66 LUC CUYVERS
The diver's lonely world 7Z
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TAH AR
BEN JELLOUN
Tahar Ben Jelloun is a Moroccan poet and
novelist who spans two cultures, Arab and
French. In 1987 he became the first Arab
writer to win France's most prestigious
literary prize when his novel La Nuit sacrée
was awarded the Prix Goncourt.
An English translation of La Nuit sacrée
appeared in 1989 under the title The
Sacred Night, and several of his other
works have been published in English,
including The Sand Child (1987) and Silent
Day in Tangier (1991).
Alert to the hopes and sufferings of Arab
men and women and to the stirrings of
freedom in the world at large, Tahar Ben
Jelloun here talks about his work and the
commitment to truth and justice from
which it springs.
Let's start at the beginning. You are an
Arab writer who writes in French. Why?
I belong to a specific category of writers,
those who speak and write in a language
different from that of their parents. I am a
Moroccan, an Arab. My culture is Arab,
Islamic, but it was in French, the language of
the former colonial power, that I spontane¬
ously expressed myself when I began to write.
This is a paradox which stems from a histor¬
ical situation. Morocco, which was a French
Protectorate from 1912 to 1956, managed to
be receptive to French culture without losing
any part of its identity. I don't feel guilty
about expressing myself in French; nor do I
feel that I am continuing the work of the
colonizers. Actually, what I express in French
could very well be expressed in any other
language.
All the same, the fact that I do not use the
language of my people perhaps means that I
can take liberties with certain themes which
the Arabic language, the language of the
Qur'anwhich naturally intimidates me
would not allow me to take. On the one hand
there are taboos and prohibitions; on the other
there is my own sense of propriety. It is
difficult for us to ill-treat the Arabic language.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
For me poetry is a situationa state of being,
a way offacing life and facing history.
Do you mean that the language of tradi¬
tion, of unchanging values, is your mother
tongue, whereas to break new ground and
explore other directions, you need to express
yourself in a foreign language?
Yes, it helps and liberates the imagination.
For many people, poetry is working with
words, with language. It is hard to imagine a
poet who expresses himself in a language other
than that of his people. But there is another
conception of poetry, which is, for me, a
broader and more accommodating one. For
me poetry is a situationa state of being, a
way of facing life and facing history. Poetry
is not only a set of words which are chosen
to relate to each other, it is something which
goes much further than that to provide a
glimpse of our vision of the world. It does this
through images, through a musical universe.
And this universe can very well be expressed
in words and syllables which are not those of
one's mother tongue.
I am a guest of the French language. My
poems in French are born of my interaction
with the French language, which is not the
same as that of a French poet.
Precisely. What kind of adaptation has
there been between the French language and
your universe and between your universe and
the French language?
There has been no adaptation, but rather
a marriage, a kind of cohabitation that I have
entered into with French and which means
that I give this rather Cartesian language
another feel, another memory. I introduce it
into a world to which it could never other¬
wise have been admitted. If you send a French
sociologist, researcher or journalist to
Morocco, he will not see the kind of things
that I see as a result of my deep involvement
as an Arab and a Moroccan. The French
investigator will not see these things or be able
to express them.
In a sense, we Arab writers who write in
French are the ones who offer hospitality to
the French language! Not only do we adopt
it, we invite it home, we transform it, we take
it to places where it is not accustomed to go.
Sometimes it gets lost, but so much the better
since it's a language which is somewhat too
rigid except when it is taken in hand by great
poets like Mallarmé, Baudelaire or Rimbaud.
Jean Genet transformed Freneh4nto a beau¬
tiful rebel princess. But few French poets have
done with the language what poets like Kateb
Yacine or Aimé Césaire, two great franco¬
phone poets, have done. These are writers
who have gone very far creatively, experimen¬
tally, and as craftsmen of the language.
Different images? Different sounds?
Above all a different manner. Poetry is a
form of mathematics, a highly rigorous rela¬
tionship with words. The genius of an Aimé
Césaire is to know how to choose words with
fantastic precision and to marry them in such
a way that they produce unexpected images.
By doing this he creates new insights into
meaning which are surprising and sublime.
This is beauty, something that cannot be
explained away technically. Beauty is first and
foremost an emotion. When I read Aimé
Césaire's Cahiers d'un retour au pays natal for
the first time, I was spellbound. The same
thing when I discovered Kateb Yacine's
Nedjma. Perhaps my sensibility steers me
towards these writers who are out on their
own.
For writers like you and them, has writing
in French madefor a bigger or smaller reader¬
ship in the countries where you were born?
It may seem odd, but writing and pub
lishing in France has enabled me to commu¬
nicate with a pretty wide public, even in the
Maghreb. And this public reads me just as well
in French as in Arabic. Those who read me
in French are more numerous, perhaps
because they want to go to the original. But
I must say that Arab publishing is in such a
mess today that so far I haven't found my
public in the Arab world. Piracy or unautho¬
rized reproduction is doing terrible harm. The
pirates not only steal translations, they tamper
with them so that your work is distorted and
your relationship with the public is perverted.
Not to mention countries where books are
purely and simply banned because of an occa¬
sional erotic or political allusion, for example.
I think that on the whole publishing in
the Arab world is in a bad way. What is pub¬
lished there is not always subjected to serious
standards of criticism. Vast quantities of stuff
get into print. Some of it is good, but much
of it is bad. There is a confusion which reflects
a general situation.
In what sense?
The Arab world as a whole has been in the
grip of a serious crisis for forty-odd years. I
say "grip" because the crisis has become a state
of being which takes hold of people and steri¬
lizes them, paralyzing their creative impulse.
As if the Arab world had not experienced
sufficient pain to produce great writers such
as Dostoevsky or Kafka, who were born of
suffering and humiliation. Perhaps we have
not yet reached the bottom of the pit.
We do not have many intellectuals who
can speak out for us internationally. We have
no writers who are recognized, respected and
loved outside the Arab world. The rest of the
world only seems to have become aware of
the existence of Naguib Mahfouz since he won
the Nobel Prize two years ago. Basically
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
people are only interested in the Arab world I
when there is trouble. Who in Europe knows I
the work of Yusuf Idris, Edouard Kharrat and I
Chaker Essayab? Mahmoud Darwish is only I
known in Europe to supporters of the Pales- ]
tinian cause, and not even to all of them.
You are not sticking to the point. . . .
If we have no Arab intellectuals of interna- 1
tional stature, it is because, on the one hand, j
we live in a state of generalized mediocrity, I
we are suspended in the pit without touching '
the bottom, as I said just now, and on the
other because the world does not look to us
out of a healthy desire for knowledge. The
two reasons are complementary, I think.
Let's examine the first reason a little more
closely. What stands in the way of creative
thinking? The position occupied by the
intellectual?
For me the intellectual, the man of thought,
doubt and analysis, should by definition give
the best of himself. He may find himself in
one of two distinct situations: he lives either
in a country where freedom prevailsreal
freedom not sham freedomor in a country
where repression provokes him to make some
kind of an outburst because he can no longer
endure humiliation, fear and silence. In each
of these two cases, he can create.
But the intellectual may also find himself
in a nebulous, ill-defined, equivocal situation.
This is often our case. What have we achieved
since the end of the Second World War? We
have established, or more exactly we have
allowed to be established, petty bourgeois
regimes in which everything is average, medi¬
ocre. In this situation of "averageness", which
I would prefer to call mediocrity, intellectuals
try to keep going. But their situation is very
difficult. Those who have had the courage to
voice their opposition have often paid a very
high price. We should pay tribute to them.
Is there not also a habit of "thinking
together", a fear ofbeing noticed, ofstanding
out from the community at large? People feel
safer, finally, in this average situation.
There is a constant, something which you
find everywhere. The individual, as a unique
entity, as a singular human being, is not really,
fully recognized. What is recognized, even
today, and whatever people may say, is what
lies behind the individual: the clan, the family,
the tribe, the district or the village, but not
the expression of the individual's uniqueness.
However, a modern civilization is only pos¬
sible when it is accepted that singular beings
exist and express themselves freely.
In our societies, when a person expresses
disagreement with the general consensus,
when he or she is no longer at one with the
rest of the tribe, then that person is rejected.
An individual voice can be heard in a choir
that otherwise sings in unison. This is some¬
thing that is not excused.
Of course, there are also degrees, nuances,
and steps forward. Egypt, for instance, seems
to me to be in process of breaking up this pat¬
tern, perhaps because it is a country steeped
in history and because its experience of
modern democracy goes back to 1923. . . .
Egypt has a head start, historically speaking,
it has had the time to train minds for the exer¬
cise of citizenship. It is the country which has
suffered more ordeals than the others to get
where it is. . . .
To be fair, we should cite particular break¬
throughs in other Arab countries. But what
is certain is that a long road lies ahead. Sub¬
jectivity is still generally frowned on. People
do not understand that a writer or a film¬
maker explores his subjectivity and expresses
it in public.
Take the great Egyptian singer Urn
Kalsum. When she sang she tugged at the
heartstrings of tens of millions of Arabs. . .
Is that subjectivity or not?
It is somewhere between subjectivity and
widely shared values. She played on a key¬
board of emotions, but these emotions were
attuned to archetypes, rather conventional sty¬
lized sentiments. We are rarely shown any¬
thing of a private world. Her songs are rooted
much more in what you might call a "collec¬
tive subjectivity".
You naturally compare Western societies
with Arab societies. If intellectuals aren't
often portrayed in a good light in the Arab
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
world, why is this so and what can be done
about it? Intellectuals and writers have
played a big part in bringing change to the
West.
For the moment I don't see change coming
about through the intellectuals, for the simple,
terrible reason that there is a gulf between the
Arab peoples and Arab intellectuals.
Were the ties all that close between Voltaire
and the French peasantry in the eighteenth
century?
There has always been, everywhere, a
polemical, sometimes even violent relationship
between intellectuals and the people. But the
important thing is that there should be a rela¬
tionship of some kind. In the Arab world,
since the cultural disruptions caused by coloni¬
zation, there is no longer a link between the
cultural habits of peoples and the ways of
thinking and creating of modern intellectuals.
They are two separate worlds. The only
example which comes to mind, in recent years,
of a marked congruence between the people
and the intellectuals, is the case of the musi¬
cian Sheikh Imam and the performer-poet
Fuad Nagm in Egypt. And even then, their
message was transmitted through the medium
of popular song on cassettes. If they had been
writers in an ivory tower that symbiosis
would not have existed.
I would add that although they were very
popular, it was popularity within an intellec¬
tual, militant stream of opinion. They got
through not to the peasant masses but to the
intelligentsia in the broadest sense of the term.
Not only the intellectuals, the thinkers, but
the hundreds of thousands of people who can
read a newspaper, who watch the television,
who live in the cities, who travel perhaps . . .
who are, in any case, influenced by the cinema,
the radio, and television.
There has always
been, everywhere, a
polemical, sometimes
even violent
relationship between
intellectuals and the
people. But the
important thing is that
there should be a
relationship of some
kind.
If the circumstances are propitious,
writers, painters, sculptors and poets can make
an impact on those groups. But they cannot
reach the masses, above all the peasants.
Perhaps they could do so gradually, if the
media tried to make them known and helped
them to get their message across to the greatest
number. But as a rule the media are open to
those whose material is undemanding,
inoffensiveactors and singers.
All day long they broadcast soap operas
which propagate a lowbrow ideology. Today
people watch only this kind of stuff. As a
result, most intellectuals worth their salt have
no option but to get quietly on with their
work, far from the limelight. Myself, I don't
think there's anything wrong in taking that
decision, hoping that future generations will
discover one's work and like it.
Ifyou think that little can be expected of
the intellectuals for the moment, where will
change come from?
Let's take the example of Europe. Until
very recently there were three powerful dic¬
tatorships in Europe: Spain, Portugal and
Greece. The future for these countries seemed
totally blocked, it was impossible to see what
they could do. And yet they have been reborn,
initially because of a new-found political
legitimacy. Finally they accepted the very
simple idea that to lead a country, you must
periodically hold a national consultation in
which people representing different
programmes can make a bid for power.
It all starts when power is desacralized and
politicians become vested with it, not because
they have bought the best machine-guns or
chosen the best moment to overthrow their
comrades, but because they have a vision of
the future, a programme for which they have
obtained a majority which trusts them.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
But aren't you putting the cart before the
horse?
Yes of course. That's what intellectuals do.
It's a long hard job, and it's not by producing
committed, ideological literature that you can
get the message across. There are two levels:
specifically political work and creative work.
In general the two are quite distinct, otherwise
you have art or literature which is disem¬
bodied, sterile.
How can intellectuals prepare the ground
for progress?
They must get people used to the existence
of doubt, of criticism, of disagreement, praise
the courage involved in opposition, insist on
the right to say no, to be alone, to stand out
from the herd. Creative artists can say all this
in their own way and in their own field, by
hard, rigorous work.
Two attitudes are possible. Creative artists
can do their own thing, try to satisfy them¬
selves without bothering whether their coun¬
trymen understand them or not. Or else
they can try to invest the strongholds of mass
culture. Unfortunately it is impossible to
disregard such an important medium as
television, for example. We should know
how to use it, learn to work in it and express
new values in it. And of course we must
fight for that. New ideas should confront
old ideas, as they do everywhere. We must
refer again to the example of Europe. People
have fought to make Europe what it is today.
Freedom is not something that is served up
on a plate, like breakfast. It has to be earned.
Be vigilant, for nothing one achieves lasts
for ever.
But how should an intellectual approach
this task?
Freedom is not
something that is
served up on a plate,
like breakfast.
It has to be earned.
Be vigilant, for
nothing one achieves
lasts forever.
First and foremost through self-expression.
But what is happening today? There seems to
be a kind of sound-proof barrier. The intellec¬
tuals cannot be heard. Are they expressing
themselves but we can't hear them? Perhaps.
Perhaps they are shouting their heads off and
we can't hear them.
Isn't one big problem that of being able
to communicate freely with the rest of the
world? Keeping abreast of what's going on
elsewhere, ofwhat otherpeople are thinking?
Yes, there isn't enough information and no
attempt is made to encourage people to know
what's going on. But there is always rumour,
the weapon of the poor. Rumour, humour,
ironythey can be very effective but of course
they're not enough.
Who in your opinion, in the novel, art or
literature, have prepared or are preparing a
way to the future? You mentioned Naguib
Mahfouz.
Yes, Mahfouz is our national monument.
But don't forget Taha Hussein before him. Or
the Iraqi writer Al Sayyab, who died in
Kuweit in 1962. To my mind he is a very great
poet. Modern, ahead of his time, he broke new
ground in Arab poetry. He had a vision of the
world that was universalist and at the same
time deeply rooted in his native country. And
great rigour in the use of Arabic.
Adonis has brought new life to Arabic,
but in a way which does not seem to me
entirely successful. His poetry is highly tech¬
nical, highly cerebral. Mahmoud Darwish is
quite the opposite. He is a poet of verbal
generosity, who has a sense of imagery, a
broad perception, and writes for a mass
audience. The ideal would be a mixture of
Adonis and Darwish. A poet like that would
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
be the greatest poet of the Arab world. . . .
But we don't have such a poet. . . . There are
very few great poets in the world anyway.
What about short story writers?
Some of them have produced very good
work. First of all there is Yusuf Idris, a very
fine writer whom I would rank with William
Faulkner. In a few pages he can express the
preoccupations of a whole society. By
describing a seemingly trivial incident or
character, he leaves traces which endure. Idris
is a great writer.
Painters?
The painters I like are abstract painters. For
me the greatest of them is the Moroccan
painter Ahmed Charkawi, who died in 1967
at the age of thirty-six. He is a painter who
inspires strong feelings. He uses the basic
colours and signs of our conscious or uncons¬
cious universe, our universe as Arabs and
Africans.
Working in depth with language, signs and
images is one way ofpreparing the ground
for modernity, preparing peoplefor detached
thinking, for freedom. Does it lead to disin¬
tegration or to synthesis? Is it a search for com¬
promise between what is inside and what is
outside, between old and new, or is it a source
of great tension which destroys all sense of
continuity?
Initially, to my mind, we have to talk in
terms of making a clean break. We must do
this to shock people and make them think.
Later we must try to look for common
ground. Above all we must stop posing as
victims of the West and behaving negatively
towards the West. We must participate with
the West on an equal footing in the reconstruc-
^
/
tion of the world. We must have our say, not
through violence, aggression or fear. We must
speak out calmly and forcefully. We shall only
be able to enter the new world era if we agree
to engage in dialogue with the other side. It
is through accepting other people in our own
countries that we shall come to respect our
neighbours and be respected in our turn. Then
we shall be able to imagine our common
future together. If we want the state to respect
and guarantee human rights, we must respect
one another first. The newborn child must see
men showing respect for women, for example,
and vice versa.
Is your own work an attempt to break
things apart or to see things whole?
I came to poetry through the urgent need
to denounce injustice, exploitation, humilia¬
tion. I know that's not enough to change the
world. But to remain silent would have been
a kind of intolerable complicity.
The break is there: a break with the litany
of silences. Uttering in poetry the desire for
a more human world, while recognizing the
limits of literature. And yet one must write,
even and above all if human beings are not
particularly good or decent.
Which characters and which themes in
your work are most representative of your
attitude?
My characters are often driven by a pas¬
sionate desire for justice. They are rebellious
and incorruptible. I would cite two of them,
a woman, Harrouda, and a man, Moha. Each
of them, in different books, bears witness to
the wounds of the peoples of the Maghreb.
Perhaps they are marginal, but they forcefully
express a passion for truth and dignity. When
I think about my work with a certain detach¬
ment, I realize that I have written about the
dispossessed, the condition of immigrants, the
condition of women who do not enjoy the
same legal rights as men, the Palestinians who
are deprived of their land and condemned to
exile and despair. Even in the short book I
wrote about the sculptor Giacometti I deve¬
loped these main themes, themes of solitude
and anguish.
I who love life in spite of all that mars it,
I who love friendship, jokes and laughter, actu¬
ally write about wounds, the eternal treasons
of life. It's not very funny but it's sincere. My
commitment is to sincerity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Dutch ships In a Chinese harbour. Detail from a Chinese Coromandel lacquer screen (18th century).
SEA FEVER
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
'IF they but knew, almost all men in their degree, some time sea increased rapidly. New and valuable mineral and energy
or other, cherish very nearly the same feeling toward the ocean resources were discovered, and later recovered, from the sea
with me," says Ishmael, the narrator of Herman Melville's great floor. Marine transportation methods were revolutionized. New
novel Moby Dick. Melville was alluding to a universal bond uses of the ocean were proposed and studied: obtaining clean
between people and their ocean, though he readily admitted energy from the difference in temperature between warm sur-
many of his contemporaries were unaware of it. face layers and cold deep waters, for instance, or from tides and
What are the reasons for this bond? Some scientists believe waves; recovering new and promising drugs from a variety of
that our reactions may have something to do with the sound marine organisms; or disposing of certain wastes, safely and
waves emitted by water. Others feel there is a connection with effectively, in the ocean environment,
the visual appeal of water. Water is playful and refreshing. For But soon this sense of optimism was marred by a number
most of us it is an essential ingredient of natural beauty. of incidents. Just over thirty years ago the Minamata incident
Our feelings for the sea seem to reflect intuitively the impor- shocked the world. People living in or near the Japanese town
tance of water to life. Water made life possible on Earth, of that name were poisoned, killed or crippled for life by indus-
Without it there would have been no atmosphere, and condi- trial pollutants discharged into the sea and returned to them
tions on the planet would have been too extreme to make life through the marine food chain. Shortly thereafter, other inci-
possible. Life probably originated in water, and we still carry dents occurred, seemingly with increasing frequency. There was
traces of these origins. The blood that runs through our veins concern over radioactive contamination caused by the fallout
is similar in the composition of its salts to sea water. So is the from nuclear tests. Pesticides such as DDT began to affect the
amniotic fluid in which the human embryo floats for the dura- coastal environment. Valuable fish stocks disappeared, fished
tion of its gestation period. No wonder then that babies appear to near-ruin by increasingly effective fishing methods. Massive
to thoroughly enjoy a warm bath, as though it were a return oil spills, from platforms as well as vessel accidents, smothered
to the maternal womb. beaches and birds, causing a public outcry and providing visible
Some scientists believe that there may even have been an evidence for the first time that there were limits to human
aquatic phase in our evolution. In their view, our ancestors may domination of the sea. No matter how much we may think
have spent a good deal of their time in the balmy waters of we control the sea, it has many ways of reminding us that it
tropical seas rather than in trees or on grass flats. The theory will always have the last word.
is by no means universally accepted, but it would help explain The development of mass communications, especially of
our attraction to the sea and our kinship with dolphins and television, has greatly affected our perception of the sea to the
whales, mammals that joined the migration to the sea but stayed extent that we no longer need to be at sea, or even see it in
there and readapted to fish-like forms and habits. person, to experience its mysteries. As a result of television
If any of the above is true, our feelings toward the ocean today's generation knows more about the sea than any before,
should be universal. And that is what this issue of the UNESCO although the information is not necessarily based on first-hand
Courier seeks to explore. By examining the role of the ocean experience; nor is it always of high quality,
in the human imagination, it looks for similarities in the ways Today the ocean is perceived less as a place of danger and
in which people in different parts of the world have sought to menace than as a beautiful, romantic place where it is possible
express their feelings about the sea. Are there themes common to live and relax. In it live creatures not like Moby Dick, the
to sea stories of the distant past and their modern equivalents? threatening monster that sank Captain Ahab's ship, but gentle,
What about cultural divisions? Are there, for instance, similar- singing whales. In an age when sea travel has become far safer
ities between the attitudes towards the sea of the Polynesians, than it once was, we relive the fear of shipwreck in the com-
who have always been surrounded by water, and the Chinese? fort of our living rooms. We feel more comfortable and familiar
In the last few decades there have been dramatic changes with the sea, and yet at the same time we want it to remain
in our uses of the sea. Driven by a need for more space and mysterious. What lurks beneath the surface, in the eternal
resources, we built machinery to explore and exploit the sea, darkness of the abyss? L.C.
even to its deepest reaches. We apportioned and reapportioned	
it, and SOUght tO live or relax along its shores in ever growing LUC CUYVERS is a Belgian writer and film producer who specializes in marine
numbers. And finally we acquired the ability to affect and even and maritime affairs. He is president of the Mare Nostrum Foundation, a non-
i profit educational organization created to inform the general public about ocean
resource issues. He is the author of 4 books and numerous articles on the ocean,
Much Of this was, at least initially, accompanied by a Sense and recendy completed an 8.pan international television series on man's rela-
of optimism. During the 1960s, the annual food yield from the tionship with the sea, entitled The Blue Revolution. 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Fragments for a private
by Edouard /. Maunick
JL RAGMENTS and not extracts. Identifiable bits and pieces, not
necessarily regular. Spaces of the imagination rather than tidy
parcellings. Here the sea broke against the land of the living
and the dead in accordance with the unchanging law of the tides.
But it receded and did not carry off all that it had brought. In
the live salt and the dead seaweed, it left fragments, odds and
ends, flotsam and jetsam, over which the tides no longer have
any power or rights. On the rocks and along the shorelines they
came to rest; and there, wishing to use them in various ways,
maybe for the purposes of some mysterious spell, coasters and
inlanders out on a stroll picked them up, these remnants afloat
in the stream of time, these shreds like impalpable scrolls.
Iconography and not album. Images on the loose and not
portraits confined to a page. A tale told by the sea, but not
in writing. The other side of the ephemeral. No longer the fas¬
cinating yet oh so fleeting calligraphy of foam, but instead the
indelible imprints of the memorable: events, mere circum¬
stances, occurrences. All that the sea utters, all that it murmurs
and mouths in its unending ebb and flow.
A private iconography, like a private collection. It belongs
to J.M.D. Solitude, sixty years old, hailing from an island in
the Indian Ocean, in love with words. It was in his house with
its back turned to the sea, open on the dirt tracks and wounded
grasses, that I found, the morning after a terrible cyclone, a
handsome notebook with stitched, clothbound pages of the kind
that can be bought in stationers' shops in London, Melbourne
EDOUARD J. MAUNICK, Mauritian poet and writer, is the author of a number
of books including Ensoleillé vif (Apollinaire Prize, 1976), Anthologies
* _ personnelles (1984) and Paroles pour solder la mer (1989). He is currently
1 a¿ director of the UNESCO Collection of Representative Works.
j<^
Jg*
íH^r
and Vancouver; a thing of such beauty it seemed that wind and
rain had not dared damage it. For years I refrained from opening
it, from cutting the thick paper band around it, girding it like
a precious wad, frightened that I might be betraying a friend¬
ship so close that it had made us alike, J.M.D. Solitude and
myself, and so much so that we might have issued from the
same womb.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
iconography of the sea An islander dreams
of distant shores
When I told my friend, who like myself was always travel¬
ling, that I had only just managed to rescue his diary from the
storm, he answered that I should keep it, "as one more secret
between us". But recently a letter from him was forwarded to
me in which he mysteriously announced that he was "going
away for ever". "Not dead", he explained, "just somewhere
else". Further on he added: "I am counting on you and on all
that lies between us not to let anyone try to find out where
I am. Let's say that my exile is now total. . . . I'm no longer
the same man. ... It has gone on too long. . . . Leave me to
my wanderings. ..." A postscript mentioned the rescued note¬
book, giving me leave to do whatever I liked with it.
I opened it with the feeling that I was going to find in it
things I already knew. I repeat, J.M.D. Solitude and I have 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
the same past and the same present. What I found in the note¬
book resembled my own memory: a leitmotiv of the sea as set
down in a private iconography. From it I reproduce three
fragments at random.
14
III. Looking at the sea . . .
When one is seventeen years old and comes from the Masca-
rene Islands, strewn like pieces of rock or lava off the southeast
coast of Africa, one fast feels all but cursed, as though doomed
to go round in circles for ever. Distances are not distances but
a number of spans. After closing books and magazines, and espe¬
cially the big illustrated encyclopaedia with reproductions,
maps, names of countries and words never seen beforeat ship
alone: binnacle and bobstay, crossjack and garboard, jibboom
and sheer strake, spanker gaff, stanchion on coming out of
the cinema, after seeing Gerónimo, Mutiny on the Bounty, Pepe
leMoko and The Count ofMonte-Cristo and a ragbag of westerns,
both silents and talkies, Indian films and Egyptian films, which
carry you off to worlds and lands and great ports open to every
fantasy, where you are attacked by the most malignant form
of inanition there isthat hungering after departure which
pounds in your head, in your heart, in your gutsyou end up
inventing "solitudes crowded with loneliness", to quote the
poignant title of a book by the Black American beat poet, Bob
Kaufman.
And so, to ward off ill fortune, you go down to the sea.
You choose twilight because of the sun dipping behind the
horizon to drink, leaving behind it long minutes of a light so
special that, in describing it, one is unsure whether to compare
it with flames or ambers. Then, when evening rises from the
calm waters of the harbour, the merchant ships and the occa¬
sional ocean liners, berthed or anchored off shore, light up one
after the other. The world catches fire. Fascination increases.
Imagination runs wild. Dreams become a kind of madness. You
go on board; you embark for Genoa, Marseilles, Lisbon,
Southampton, Amsterdam. ... At last you're going to know
the big ports. You'll be Christopher Columbus, Magellan,
Vasco da Gama, Amerigo Vespucci, Diego Cao	 On deck,
you look back to give a last wave to your friends left behind
on the pier. Once in your cabin, you touch the bulkheads with
the flat of your hands and the iron rivets with your fingers to
make sure that you're really on your way and you take one
last look through the porthole: how small the island is! You
tell yourself that you're no longer cursed because you're going
to see what's on the other side of the water. . . . You repeat
it to yourself in creóle: lote koté dilo. . . .
But this is how it is: at each twilight, the other side of the
water is a sheer sky wall against which the ship runs aground.
Now is still not time to leave. You'll have to come back
tomorrow . . . and come back again . . . and yet again.
One day I, J.M.D. Solitude, will no longer go back to look
at the sea; the boot will be on the other foot. The curse will
no longer spring from the cramped feeling of the island but
from the gigantism of metropolises visited all too many times,
from an immensity in which something vital will be lacking:
a patch of land, a garden at the end of the ocean. . . .
VII. Golgotha amid the waves
I see the Sacred Hill as the crest of an Atlantic wave. The cross
carried by a man crowned with thorns is a slave ship advancing
beneath the exertions of men chained naked to their oars. The
cries of the crowd are beats struck on a huge bilge drum to
set the stroke. Flagellation is matched by whipping. That one
was sold for thirty pieces of silver, this one for thirty pennies,
perhaps less. One was crucified, the other flayed or burned alive.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Christ was called Jesus, the slave was called nobody. One was
denied, the other was negation in person. And more than one
Pontius Pilate still washes his hands today before other Passions.
Whenever I think of this, my mind goes back to those lines
by René-Guy Cadou, dead at the age of thirty and buried in
the humble cemetery of Louisfert, in Brittany:
"If they could do that to the King of the Jews
What wouldn't they do to a poor nigger. . . ."
and it occurs to me that those who most desecrated the seaways
were not pirates and that Gorée isn't so far from Gethsemane.
IX. The bird from the sea
At noon, on the Senegalese coast, at Cayar, near Dakar, I walk
side by side with Jacques Howlett. We have deserted a talking
shop on négritude, organized on the occasion of the First World
Festival of Negro Arts. Wrongly or rightly, we thought it more
profitable to come and listen to the sea than to have our minds
plugged with critical comment. He tells me about the latest
manuscripts received at Présence Africaine of which he has long
been a pillar. But very soon we realize how beside the point
it is to be talking about literature when the sea is there in all
its splendour beneath the raw sun.
Silence! . . .
We walk, dazzled by the glare from the white sand. Only
the sight of the worm-eaten wood of a few abandoned boats,
too old to be any use, their colours high and dry, offers some
relief to our eyes. It'll be a long time yet before the return of
those that went out at first light to cast their nets offshore.
They'll be back at the end of the day. To our great regret, we
shan't be witnessing their noisy, turbulent ritual as they come
through the channel. A fight with the waves just a few yards
away from the shore. Each time, the blessed insolence of the
boatmen, cocking a snook at the swell. No, we shan't be seeing
any of that.
But a strange voice interrupts the silence. A sort of muted
chanting. Jacques and I start searching between the skeletons
of the boats and discover an old man sitting on a stone, a chisel
in his hand, working away at a piece of wood clamped between
his knobbly knees. He accompanies each of his movements,
each incision in the wood, with a guttural threnody, mournful,
slow or animated according to how gently or violently the tool
penetrates the heart of the wood.
He goes on working for a few moments as though not
aware that we are watching him. Then, slowly, he lifts his head
and with a movement of the chin acknowledges our presence.
He then goes back to his sculpture. Our attention is focused
mainly on his chant, trying to understand its meaning. It grows
in intensity as, beneath his carvings, a bird's head emerges from
the block of wood. We no longer care about time slipping by,
transported as we are by the rite unfolding before our eyes.
Now the hornbill's features can clearly be seen. The old
man puts down his tool in order to take a closer look at his
work. His eyes dwell on every angle. Then with his skinny
fingers he strokes every detail, staring straight ahead now at
the sea. He seems elsewhere. ... He gets up, about to leave.
I can no longer restrain myself. I call him:
"Tell me, grandad, what were those words you were
chanting just now?"
"I was just calling to the bird hidden in the piece of wood.
Without words, son, you can dig away as much as you like
with the chisel. Nothing will come if you don't call, especially
when you're working before the sea. . . ."
Saying this, he went off, carrying with him at arm's length
the bird's head, surely destined to become the first piece of a
weather vane fixed on the prow of a boat to indicate the direc¬
tion of the wind.
I didn't like to ask him why "especially before the sea".
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
AND TIDE
The wonirws deep
The sea has always inspired a sense
of awe. Some peoples have
responded eagerly to its call, while
others have remained firmly attached
to the land. For desert peoples like
the Arabs it was a source of fear and
wonder; the Chinese, for all the
glorious chapters in their maritime
history, pursued their destiny
essentially on land. Many of the
world's cultures have risen from the
waves: Polynesian civilization was
propagated by some of the most
intrepid and skilful seafarers ever
known. The Greek sailors who ply
the seven seas today continue a
tradition which can be traced back to
Homeric times.
In classical times the seas of Islam represented
another world and, for the Arabs, who were the
sons of nomads and had lived on the land since
time immemorial, it was a dual world. At once
close and familiar when seen from the shore, it
became an object of terror when on all sides there
was nothing but water extending to the horizon.
Subject to laws beyond good and evil, the marine
world was considered to be situated at the very
edge of the habitable universe. There members
of the same species and indeed of the same family
tore one another to pieces and pursued each other
mercilessly. The Dadjal (the Antichrist) beat his
drums in the suffocating heat of bewitched
islands. Satan was not far. Perhaps, when all was
said and done, it was he who ruled beneath the
waters.
The earliest references to the sea in Arab
poetry reflect this hostile world, beyond the
compass of the human mind. The poet Al
Muhalhil issued a warning which was to become
the leitmotiv of relations between the Arab imagi¬
nation and the sea: "Setting sail on the sea
without taking care/Is a sure way of courting
disaster."
For the early Arab poets the sea was also the
supreme symbol of strength and power. The pre-
Islamic poet Malik Ibn Nuweyra describes an
attack made by his tribe against an enemy camp
in the following terms: "They saw us arrive with
the first dawn rays/More ruinous yet than the
foaming seas". And Antara Ibn Shaddad
recounting a battle enjoins: "Question them as
to my valour/When the tribes of Kalb, of Ghaniy
and Amir/Came crashing down like waves. . . ."
The advent of Islam hardly affected the Arab
image of the sea. It is often described in the
Qur'an as an emblem of divine power or benevo¬
lence and the sea in fury is seen as denoting the
Apocalypse: "When heaven is split open, when
the stars are scattered, when the seas swarm
over. . . ." (Surat 82, verses 1 to 3); "When the
sun shall be darkened, when the stars shall be
thrown down . . . when the seas shall be set
boiling. . . ." (Surat 81, verses 1, 2 and 5).
The waves (Mawdj, Amwadj) are an image
of extreme danger. The Arabic root "M.W.DJ."
covers a semantic field dominated by ideas of
imbalance, upheaval, agitation, turmoil and
storm. The term crops up many times in the
Qur'an: "And when waves cover them like
shadows, they call upon God . . ." (Surat 31, verse
32); "And waves come on them from every side,
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
by Rachid kbbaghi
Detail from a map by the
Persian scholar al-lstakhrl.
and they think they are encompassed; they call
upon God ... : 'If Thou deliverest us from these,
surely we shall be among the thankful' " (Surat
10, verse 22).
The Hadith (the words of the Prophet) sound
the same note: "He who takes to the sea in
stormy weather has only himself to blame".
TRAVELLERS AND
STORYTELLERS
The Arabs were not seafarers, even though their
early traditions reveal some familiarity with the
world of the sea and the Qur'an evokes the
dangers and riches of the ocean to illustrate the
power and bounteousness of God. The Prophet's
tribe, the Quraysh, no doubt already had sea links
with Abyssinia via the Red Sea. But, as scholars
such as W. Barthold and G. Hourani have shown,
there appears to be little doubt that they did not
have any ships of their own. They were, for
example, incapable of going after fugitives who
took to the sea. When the Empire was founded,
the Arabs had to rely on the knowledge of the
Egyptian Copts to establish their first naval fleet
in the Mediterranean.
However, until the Ottomans came to power
the Mediterranean was considered to be of only
marginal interest and held by the Caliphate to
be not directly relevant to its ambitions. The
Arabs had their first real experience of the sea
in the Great Eastern Sea (AI Bahr Sharqui Al
Kabir), that part of the Indian Ocean which
extends from the coast of India to East Africa,
including its two branches formed by the Gulf
and the Red Sea. The most notable contribution
made by Arab navigators and geographers related
to knowledge of this sea.
The Arabs had from very early times acted
as middlemen in the far-flung trade between the
East (India, China, Ceylon, Java) and the West
(Egypt, Syria, Rome). However, after Baghdad
had been founded (762 AD) and the ports of Basra
and Siraf had been developed, they started to
trade on their own account, from Hang-chou in
the Far East to Sofala on the east coast of Africa.
Those who first taught the Arabs seamanship
were doubtless the Persians who under the
Sasanids had formed a true maritime aristocracy
all around the western part of that same Great
Eastern Sea.
By the ninth century, when the Abbasids
were at the height of their power, the Arabs had
fully mastered and perhaps progressed beyond the
available stock of knowledge about the sea. Their
navigators had by then acquired a fairly rigorous
understanding of monsoons and winds. They no
longer made do with plying up and down the
coast but sailed directly from the Arabian coast
to the confines of the Indian peninsula; the straits
lying between the Gulf and the China Sea were
well known to them. Similarly, black Africa was
no longer altogether a terra incognita; their ships
sailed from Aden in East Africa all the way to
Sofala (or Sofalat al Zindj as it was known to
Arab geographers). They also plied the Red Sea,
the Mediterranean, the Caspian Sea, the Black Sea
and a number of navigable rivers like the Nile
and the Indus. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The Roc bird saves a
shipwrecked sailor.
Illustration from a
16th-century manuscript of
the Booh of Wonders, by the
great 13th-century Islamic
scholar al-Tusl.
18
The widespread use of nautical charts (Rah-
manis) and manuals (Dafatirs) dates from this
period. In his The Meadows ofGold and Mines of
Gems, Mas'udi, the great tenth-century ency¬
clopaedist and traveller, gives the names of a large
number of Nakhuda (ship captains) and specialists
on the Indian Ocean with whom he was per¬
sonally acquainted. It was also a golden age for
sea literature, travellers' tales and descriptions of
wondrous things ("Mirabilia") in which the sea
had a central part. Few have survived. One of the
earliest travellers' tales is that attributed to the
merchant Suleyman, who made several journeys
to India and China and described his impressions
of the countries he visited and the peoples he
encountered in his Akhbar Al-Sin wa Al Hind
(Account of China and India).
Another interesting author of that period is
Buzurg ibn Shahriyar. Himself a ship captain, in
around 953 AD he compiled an anthology of tales
of the sea entitled Kitab Adja'ib Al Hind which
contains several curious stories about the adven¬
tures of sailors in the East Indies and other parts
of the Indian Ocean. Intended for the common
reader, mingling actual experience and fiction,
Buzurg's tales largely belong to the genre known
as "Adj'aib" ("Mirabilia") which was much in
vogue at the time.
The Thousand and One Nights, the first com¬
pilations of which, according to the specialists,
date from the ninth century, contain a number
of tales centring on the sea, including the famous
"Adventures of Sindbad the Sailor". The Egyp¬
tian oceanographer and man of letters Hussein
Fawzi has shown, in a splendidly erudite book
(Le discours de Sindbad l'ancien, 1942), the distinc¬
tively Arab qualities of this story and its inter-
textual references to contemporary Arab mari¬
time literature, making it a kind of bible of nau¬
tical knowledge for that period.
THE WAY OF WONDERS
What were Muslim Arab navigators and traders
looking for in such far-off lands as Japan and
Madagascar? The "wondrous" merchandise with
which, according to travellers and geographers,
those countries abounded, ranging from silk in
China to ebony in the Wak-Wak islands (Borneo, .
the Philippines), from topazes and rubies in
Sirandib (Ceylon) to tin in the peninsula of
Malacca. As commonplace as such goods may
seem today, for travellers at that time they were
fabulous treasures, full of enchantment and magic.
Many passages in the Thousand and One
Nights bear witness to this. But Sindbad also
travels in quest of knowledge, roused by the call
of distant lands, the lure of the unknown, the
mystery of otherness.
The Indian Ocean which was the doorway
to these lands of plenty was also swarming with
Bawaridj, the pirate ships that plied its waters,
and its islands were inhabited by cannibals. We
are told by the author of the Summary of Wonders
that "To the right of the island of Kalah lies the
island of Balus. Its inhabitants eat human flesh",
while in the words of al-Idrisi, "The denizens of
this island (Bakus) are black and go naked. . . .
Should a foreigner chance upon them, they hang
him up by the feet, cut him into pieces and eat
him. . . . Their speech is incomprehensible".
The skies above this sea are sometimes dar¬
kened by the open wings of huge birds known
as Rukh or Anka (Pheng to the Chinese and
Simorg to the Persians). According to al-Kazwini,
"The Anka is the largest bird there is. It hunts
elephants, whales and dragons. When it flies, its
wings make a noise like a torrent. When it spreads
its wings, the sun is hidden and the sky is
darkened".
Travellers of the period tell us of other sea
monsters that infested the depths of the Great
Eastern Sea. Some were so big that "from head
to tail is a four-month voyage". From afar the
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
giant turtles resembled islands. A merchant left
the following eye-witness account: "We found in
the middle of the sea an island on which grass
grew protruding from the water. We landed and
prepared to eat. The island started to move. The
sailors shouted 'Back to the ship! Back to the ship!
It's a turtle, awakened by the fire for the meal.
. . . Back to the ship before it plunges beneath
the water!'
On the Wak-Wak islands strange trees were
said to grow whose fruit took the form of women
which died a few hours after being picked but
not before providing the famished traveller with
intense and mysterious pleasures: "On these
islands there are trees which bear as their fruit
The talking tree on the
enchanted Island. Miniature
from a manuscript of the
Shah-Nama ("Book of Kings"),
a masterpiece of Persian
literature.
women hanging by the hair. . . . Some travellers
have seen very beautiful ones. If they are picked
by cutting properly the roots of their hair
attaching them to the tree, they can live for
several days. The travellers experienced in their
arms a happiness that can be compared with no
other". Such is the description given of the Wak-
Wak islands by Ibn al Wardi in his Book of
Wonders. Other strange phenomena were reported
by travellers and geographers of the period:
dwarfs that would come out of the sea, climb on
board ships, spend the night there and then go
off without saying or doing anything, which for
sailors at the time meant that the most terrible
of the sea winds, the Khub, was impending: the
RACHID SABBAGHI,
Moroccan writer and journalist,
is the author of an essay on
20th-century French
philosophy which will shortly
be published in Arabic. He is
also preparing a study on
French travellers in Morocco,
which will appear (in French) in
1992.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
famous white cloud which, on coming into con¬
tact with the waves, caused them to boil and roar
like a tornado; the hole in the sea, known as
Durdur, which carried ships away into the abyss;
and magnetic mountains that drew boats towards'
them and broke them to pieces. . . .
A source of profit and of fear, able to pro¬
vide man with fabulous riches and to inspire in
him unspeakable terror, dispensing life and death,
the sea is unfathomable. Man barely scratches its
immeasurable surface. But, like everything that
exists, it is subject to divine lawthe ultimate
guarantee that the world has a meaning, and it
was this law that travellers, geographers and cos-
mographers always thought they were obeying
when they embarked on their journeys. In so
doing, they were bringing their intelligence to
bear on the visible signs of creation, trusting in
the benevolence of God to take care of everything
that exceeded the bounds set by Him upon that
intelligence.
20
Sindbad's maiden voyage
One day when we were under sail we found
ourselves becalmed before a small island lying
just above the water and covered with
verdure like a meadow. The captain had the
sails lowered and informed the members of
the crew that those who wished to go ashore
could do so. I was one of those who availed
themselves of the opportunity. However, just
as we were pleasantly engaged in eating and
drinking and resting our weary limbs, the
island suddenly shook all over and made us
reel. . . .
. . . The shudder that passed through the
island was not unnoticed on the boat; from it
cries arose telling us to go back on board at
once lest we perish; that what we had taken
for an island was the back of a whale. The
quickest on their feet made off in the rowing
boat, others went swimming away. I for my
part was still on the island, or rather on the
whale, when it plunged into the sea, and I
just had time to seize hold of a piece of wood
that been brought from the boat to make a
fire. However, the captain, after taking on
board those who were in the rowing boat and
rescuing some of those who were swimming,
wanted to take advantage of the favourable
fresh wind that had started up; he had the
sails raised and in so doing robbed me of
any hope ofgetting back to the boat.
So I remained at the mercy of the waves,
driven first one way then another; I fought
with them for my life for the rest of the day
and the following night. The next day I no
longer had any strength and was giving up
all hope of avoiding death when happily a
wave cast me upon an island.
The Thousand and One Nights
The legacy of
i ~
&
rtlMClENT China was a landlocked state and its
expansion to the coast opened a new chapter in
Chinese history. Rule of the sea was achieved
under the T'ang dynasty (618-906 AD) and mar¬
itime expansion continued under the Sung
(960-1279 AD). Sung seamanship became a
byword for excellence in the Asian maritime
world, but Chinese technological superiority
endured many challenges both on land and at sea,
and the Mongol conquest of the Southern Sung
ushered in the Yuan dynasty and brought the first
hint of a naval threat that eventually reduced
China to almost semi-colonial status.
During the early Ming dynasty (1368-1644
AD), the Chinese state sponsored epic maritime
expeditions which took hundreds of ships and
tens of thousands of men to countries as far away
as East Africa. Chinese emissaries played the role
of arbitrators in Ceylon and Sumatra, and in
return over sixty embassies visited China within
a short space of time, many bearing gifts of
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Confucius tyKöw?
- -
strange animals, plants and jewels. This grand
design, which depended so heavily on state
patronage, leadership and finance, lost its staun-
chest and most energetic patron when the Yung-
lo emperor died in 1423, although voyages con¬
tinued under Hsiian-te. No royal patron, court
official or private adventurer ever emerged to
resume or indeed to finance such expeditions
again.
Instead of going on to develop the maritime
empire that had seemed to lie within its reach,
China now turned its back to the sea. The reasons
for this were historical, ideological and perhaps
even temperamental. One reason may have been
an intrinsic lack of interest in the sea on the part
of the Chinese, for never again in Chinese his¬
tory were such proclivities for maritime expan¬
sion to be revealed. Another may be found in the
Confucian ethos which held trade and mercan¬
tile concerns in low esteem. The Chinese never
considered trade to be a source of the state's
**?*«
domestic power, and merchants were never
thought worthy of a leading role in state-building.
A partnership between the state and the mer¬
chants in an overseas adventure for national glory
or profit would have meant turning the whole
Chinese social order and value system upside
down.
A COUNTRY WITH ITS BACK
TO THE SEA
As it turned away from the sea and concentrated
on the defence of its land frontiers and the reor¬
ganization of its finances, China lost the initia¬
tive in the East Asian maritime world. In the six¬
teenth and seventeenth centuries, a new maritime
order developed in the region. Led by the
Japanese and closely followed by the Europeans,
it was driven by the profit motive. The new Euro¬
pean masters of the Asian seas were soon
clamouring for concessions at the gates of China.
Above, Confucius
(C.552-C.479 BC) as depicted
on a stele in Xi'an, the capital
of Shaanxi.
Above left, junks in the bay of
Macao.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
The Ming government, already predisposed
towards a defensive maritime policy, closed the
major ports and evacuated the coastal population
inland.
For the next 200 years, the coast of China
became a shady world, peopled by fidalgos (Por¬
tuguese noblemen), burghers, Wakoes (Japanese
pirates), marauders and conniving merchants and
officials, with in their midst perhaps a few honest
traders and people earning a living from the sea.
It was a world of romancé, terror, treachery and
illicit gain, dominated by the so-called "merchant
princes" who amassed fortunes from the inter-
Asian carrying trade, thereby building up polit¬
ical power and becoming virtually the paymasters
of local officials.
The new rulers of China after 1644, the
Manchus at the head of the Ch'ing dynasty, were
without experience of the sea and had inherited
a maritime world which the late Ming had aban¬
doned to private trade and local autonomy. They
took forty years to pacify the south, but when
this was done they returned the people to the
coast and repealed the prohibition against
overseas navigation. At the same time they
adopted an open-door policy by opening four
ports to foreign trade.
THE CHINA TRADE
By the late seventeenth century, the Dutch and
Spanish had been driven from the trading stations
they had established on the China coast and their
places taken by the English (from the 1670s) and
the French (after 1699). In the 1720s came the
Ostenders, who were later followed by Dutch,
Danes, Swedes and others, under the flags of their
East India Companies. As European trade with
China developed, it was brought under semi¬
official management by a system of controls and
regulations, the most intense period of legislation
being from 1740 to 1760.
European trade with China between 1684 and
the First Opium War in 1839 marked a revolu¬
tion in the maritime history of China. After a
break of 250 years the Chinese state was again
turning its attention to the sea. This was the great
era of trade in China tea, which displaced spices,
pepper and Chinese silk as Europe's leading
import from East Asia. A distinctive hybrid
between "official trade" and "private trade" was
devised by the Ch'ing to meet importunate
Western demands, to safeguard the livelihood of
Chinese coastal peoples and to maintain the secu¬
rity of the coast. The relationship between
Above, Europeans welcoming
a Chinese ship in a Dutch or
Portuguese settlement on the
Chinese coast. 18th-century
painting on paper.
Right, a "tower boat" of the
Sul dynasty (6th-7th century).
This article is based on
material contained in a longer
study by W.E. CHEONG,
Reader in history at the
University of Hong Kong. Dr.
Cheong is the author of
articles and two books on the
history of East-West trade in
Asia. One of the books, Opium
Agencies in China in the
1820s, won the Imperial
History prize of the Royal
Commonwealth Society. His
forthcoming The Hong
Merchants of Canton,
1684-1798, is a history of
official Chinese merchants in
the European trade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Chinese merchants and the Europeans during this
long period was generally peaceful for, despite
their diametrically opposed views about the place
of trade and merchants in society, both European
mercantilism and Chinese Confucianism advo¬
cated active state intervention and a monopolistic
system as the means of attaining their ends.
From the beginning, the Ch'ing correctly
judged the maritime frontier to be the most likely
source of their major domestic and foreign policy
difficulties and acted accordingly. But as time
went by they found security in a conservative
orthodoxy, and when China was exposed by sea
to all that was new and changing in the late eight¬
eenth century, they failed to respond to the
stimulus and missed the chance to join the new
world order.
The traditional world order was challenged
by the new. After 1826 a rapid increase in imports
into China, first cotton and opium and later
..
industrial goods and equipment and, most damag-
ingly, consumer goods, served to highlight the
importance of merchants, industry and trade to
the national wealth of Western countries, whereas
industrial development was a concept that did not
exist in the Ch'ing official vocabulary. Finally,
China had not realized that it was necessary to
maintain her technologyshe was humiliated in
the nineteenth century by a few gunboats
despatched to her shores by "barbarians" from
outside.
The dockyard at Foochow that produced out¬
dated warships, some of which sank on going
down the slipway, the fleet that remained idle at
one port while another fleet was being destroyed
elsewhere on the coast, and several unsuccessful
major industrial enterprises symbolized the failure
of a country that had once been technologically
advanced to make up for more than five centuries
of neglect. Foreign warships, merchant ships, pas¬
senger and freight steamers frequented Chinese
ports and sailed upriver at will. Finally, the total
defeat of China at sea in the Sino-Japanese War of
1894-1895 raised the key question of whether eco¬
nomic and military reforms can be achieved
without political and institutional reforms.
How merchants travel
Upon a vessel four decks are built. The vessel
is fitted out with rooms, cabins and saloons
for merchants. Several of the cabins contain
private rooms and conveniences. There are
keys for the cabins, which are locked by their
owners. The merchants bring their
concubines and wives along with them.
Often there will be one person in his cabin
without any other person on board knowing
that he is there, and it is not until they
arrive at their destination that people find
that they have been voyaging together.
The sailors have their children living in
these cabins; they plant pot herbs, vegetables
and ginger in wooden tubs. The ship's
steward has the appearance of a great emir;
when he goes ashore, archers and Abyssinians
walk before him with javelins, swords,
kettledrums, horns and trumpets. Upon his
arriving at the inn where he is to be lodged,
they plant their lances on either side of the
door and continue to behave in this manner
throughout his stay. Among the inhabitants
of China there are some who own many
ships on which they send their message-
bearers abroad. The Chinese are the richest
people in the world.
Ibn Battuta (1304-1368/1377)
Arab traveller
{The travels of Ibn Battuta)
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
In the wak of Ulysses
by André ledros
The ship of the Argonauts.
Detail from the Ficoronl urn, a
richly engraved cylindrical
container from Praeneste
(4th-3rd century BC), Italy.
I HERE are some 2,000 Greek islands. Most of
them are barren rocks. Some lack fresh water and
are uninhabited. But ever since the earliest times
Greeks have lived in the largest and most beau¬
tiful of them and Greek civilization has flourished
there. A people with so many islands is bound
to have special links with the sea.
The Greeks were bold seafarers long before
the Phoenicians came on the scene. Like the wan¬
derings of Ulysses, the mythical expedition of
Jason and the Argonauts, the heroes who sailed
aboard the Argo to recover the Golden Fleece,
is inspired by early Greek exploration of the
Mediterranean. We owe a late account of this
expedition to Apollonius of Rhodes, who was
born around 295 BC. We can be sure that Homer,
who is thought to have lived five centuries before,
knew an earlier version of the exploits of the
Argonauts. The sorceress Circe living on the
island of Aeaea, the dangerous strait of Scylla and
Charybdis, and the Sirens, all feature in the
Odyssey but also appear in the voyage of the
Argonauts, which was recorded long before.
24
The small sailboats of Antiquity and rowing
vessels like the longship Argo were sturdily built.
Greek sailors trusted them implicitly. They knew
all about the dominant winds and currents, but
Poseidon the sea-god was given to sudden terrible
rages. As they plied the seas far from their
homeland, Jason, Ulysses and their companions
faced terrible dangers. It took far more courage
to set out on a long voyage without maps or
compass and brave violent storms than it did to
fight against the King of Colchis or the Trojans.
These journeys were plagued by hunger, thirst,
fatigue and stress. . . . How else can we explain
the fact that Ulysses weeps so often?
When storms blew up, the Greeks depended
on skilful seamanship to save them. Without a
steady hand on the tiller all was lost. The Greeks
have never been good swimmers and shipwreck
would almost invariably be fatal. Ulysses himself
barely escapes drowning on two occasions.
Ulysses has angered Zeus. The god hurls a
thunderbolt at his ship, which is shattered to
pieces. Billowing waves sweep the crew into the
sea. Ulysses, the only survivor, clings to a piece
of wreckage. A gust of wind blows him towards
the strait guarded by Scylla and the whirlpool
Charybdis, who swallows up the debris of the
ship. Ulysses just manages to grasp a fig-tree
growing on the rocks above the waves. Then
Charybdis spits back the mast and the keel, and
Ulysses continues his adventurous wanderings.
But before long the son of Laertes falls victim
to the anger of another god, Poseidon, who has
long been persecuting him.
Aboard the raft which the nymph Calypso has
unwillingly allowed him to build, Ulysses comes
in sight of the land of the Phaeacians. Suddenly
a violent gust of wind breaks up his fragile craft.
Ulysses manages to haul himself on to a plank but
he is battered by the waves and is soon overcome
by exhaustion. Leucothea, the white goddess,
saves him in the nick of time. She gives him her
veil to tie around his waist, and he manages to
swim through the stormy sea to Phaeacia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Ulysses and the sirens,
detail from a Sth-century-BC
Greek vase.
Many Greek sailors over the centuries in
similar perilous situations to those described in
the Odyssey have lost their lives because they did
not know how to swim. This failing, which I
have often noticed among fishermen and sailors
serving in one of the world's biggest fleets of mer¬
chant ships, is particularly surprising since the
Greeks are outstanding divers.
SPONGE DIVERS
In ancient times, sponge diving was practised in
Greece more widely than it is today. Sponges
were used for various, and sometimes unusual,
purposes. Soldiers drank from them when they
had no goblets and made them into protective
cushions which they wore beneath their armour.
Today synthetic sponges compete with natural
sponges. Nevertheless, beautiful women still
prefer real sponges, as do painters, craftsmen,
polishers, cabinet-makers and surgeons.
Sponge divers can still be found on some
Greek islands such as Kalymnos and Skyros,
where their marvellous but arduous skills are
handed down from father to son. The only differ¬
ence is that they have to sail further and further
away, near to the coast of Cyprus or Libya. And
they must dive deeper and deeper. The old men
remember the time when they used to skin-dive
to find sponges 30 metres underwater. Today
their successors have to dive more than 60 metres,
wearing diving suits and other equipment. Their
outfits are often the worse for wear, and accidents
are frequent. The men's health suffers. On the
quayside of the port of Kalymnos, old men of
forty can often be seen.
THE ANGER
OF POSEIDON
Thousands of Greek sailors serve in the merchant
navy. Many of them accept low wages to work in
old tubs which often sail under flags of con¬
venience and which they describe among them¬
selves as floating coffins.
When one of these decrepit hulks runs into
a storm the crew need all the courage they can
find. Heavy seas pound the deck murderously. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Neptune's Horses (1892) by
the English painter and
illustrator Walter Crane.
Summer solstice
The sea they call calm
ships and white sails
sea breeze from the pines, and the mountain
ofAegina
breathlessly,
your skin glided over the sea's skin
warm and welcoming
a thought almost formed was immediately
forgotten
But in the shallow waters
a harpooned octopus discharged its ink
and in the depths
if you but knew where these lovely islands
take root
I looked at you with all the light and
darkness that I possess
George Seferls (1900-1971)
Greek poet
In the dark night stars topple into the waves like
a shower of meteorites, then rush back heaven¬
wards in a cosmic firework display. Roiling
breakers race from the distant horizon and crash
over the ship, which pitches and rolls. Their
white foam rushes to the top of the mainmast,
making whirlpools of spray. The wallowing old
tub is buffeted hither and thither.
The crewmen race around, complaining but
putting their backs into their work, stemming the
inflow of water with packing and cement, stowing
away overturned sacks and boxes before the ship
begins to list, keeping the ship's electrical system
working. They never let up, driven by their sense
of danger and their matchless experience of the
sea, rather than by their officers. This is why their
reputation for seamanship is second to none.
PIRATES AND SHIPOWNERS
Greek sailors are not superstitious. Children of
the Sun and the Mediterranean, they have never
been obsessed by the appearance of the dreaded
m
Ŵ
M
m
- aaàaV
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Flying Dutchman which haunts the imagination
of northern seamen. It's not ghost captains that
they fear but real ones who let themselves be cor¬
rupted by cynical shipowners and deliberately
sink their ships on desert island reefs. Barratry,
the fraudulent breach of duty by the master of
a ship, which often endangers the life of the crew,
is still relatively frequent. The older the ship, the
greater the temptation to barratry. The sailors
know this and are secretly afraid.
Of course not all shipowners are so
unscrupulous. Many of them have combined
their maritime instinct with a genius for business
and have become very rich without infringing the
laws of trade.
A VISION OF THE SEA
Greek shipowners, sailors and fishermen make
their living from the sea. But the Greek people
as a whole also lives from the sea, albeit indirectly.
Greece has profited from the tourist boom
more than most countries. Hundreds of thou¬
sands of foreigners spend their holidays there each
year. What are they looking for? Archaeological
sites such as Delphi, Mycenae and Delos are still
a magnet for visitors. The beautiful marble of
ancient temples, theatres and statues bears wit¬
ness to the cult of beauty in a distant past and
glows in the soft light of the present. But more
and more tourists are flocking to Greece to realize
an ideal vision of the sea. They head for the Greek
islands to escape from oil-polluted beaches and
the dirt of the big city, hoping to bathe in trans¬
parent waters and make friends with the Greeks
who live in close contact with the sea. (Even if
they do not bathe in it, for the good reason that
they cannot swim).
One myth that symbolizes perhaps more
than any other the extraordinary symbiosis of the
Greeks with the sea, as well as their inadequacy
as swimmers, it is that of Orion, son of Hyrieus
king of Boeotia. Orion was a giant who walked
across the sea from island to island without ever
getting out of his depth. One day when Apollo
was engaged in an archery contest on the beach
with his sister Artemis, the goddess and huntress
whose arrows never missed their target, he
pointed to an object floating far out to sea.
"I bet you can't reach it," he said.
Artemis strung her bow and her arrow sped
unerringly to its distant target, which was, alas,
the head of Orion who was walking as usual in
the water far from the shore.
When she saw that she had killed the good
giant by mistake, Artemis was so distressed that
she bore Orion to heaven and transformed him
into a constellation.
-P-x^.-jtV.
"Shellfishing". Painting on
silk by the Japanese painter
and printmaker Hokusai
(1760-1849).
ANDRE KEDROS,
a Greek author who writes in
French, is the author of 13
novels which have been widely
translated. He has also
published several historical
essays including a History of
the Greek Resistance
1940-1944 (Robert Laffont
publishers, Paris).
The Coloured Beach
It was again a fine day on the sixteenth. I
went to the Coloured Beach to pick up some
pink shells. I sailed the distance of seven
miles in a boat and arrived at the beach in
no time, aided by a favourable wind. A man
by the name of Tenya accompanied me, with
servants, food, drinks and everything else he
could think of that we might need for our
excursion. The beach was dotted with a
number offishermen's cottages and a tiny
temple. As I sat in the temple, drinking
warm tea and sake, / was overwhelmed by
the loneliness of the evening scene.
Lonelier I thought
Than the Suma beach
The closing of autumn
On the sea before me.
Mingled with tiny shells
I saw scattered petals
Of bush-clovers
Rolling with the waves.
I asked Tosai to make a summary of the
day's happenings and leave it at the temple
as a souvenir.
Basho (1644-1694)
Japanese poet
(The Narrow Road to the Deep North,
translated by Nobuyuki Yuasa, in The Narrow Road
to the Deep North and Other Travel Sketches,
Penguin Books 1966).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
In Polynesian myth, the primal spiritual force
is Tangaroa, the atua, or god, of the ocean. The
sky, Raki, is his parent, and Hinemoana, the
woman of the sea, is his partner. Tangaroa
appears in different forms within the diverse but
connected cultures of Polynesia as a figure who
cannot be escaped and must always be accom¬
modated.
The Polynesians inhabit a world which con¬
sists almost entirely of ocean. Apart from New
Zealand, the land area they know consists of small
islands, some of them volcanic outcrops and
many others mere coral atolls. Habitable land
constitutes no more than 1.5 per cent of
Polynesia.
In Polynesian mythology the land comes
from the sea, from which it has been drawn by
the demi-god Maui. Islands are great fish dragged
from the depths, or waka (canoes) from which
Maui brought lesser islands to the surface.
The indigenous people of Polynesia share a
high level of linguistic, ethnic and cultural unity,
tempered by a diversity resulting largely from
adaptation to the specific island worlds where
they have made their homes. They live within
the vast area of the Pacific which is known as the
Polynesian Triangle and is divided into two
closely related yet culturally distinct areas,
Western Polynesia and Eastern Polynesia. The
former comprises Tonga, Samoa, Tuvalu and,
historically, part of Fiji. The latter consists of
Hawaii, the Tahiti group of islands, the Cook
Islands, the Marquesas, Rapanui (Easter Island)
and Aotearoa (New Zealand).
THE PEOPLING OF POLYNESIA
Who were these people and where did they come
from? Modern scholarship concludes that their
ancestors were Austronesian seafarers who
worked their way from a starting point some¬
where in Southeast Asia down the island chains
to what is now the western Polynesian Triangle.
Archaeological evidence based on the remains of
their distinctive pottery suggests that these people
were capable of sailing over vast areas of ocean
from one group of islands to another.
What was to become Polynesian culture
began to appear about 6,000 years ago in the
Tonga-Samoa triangle. Then, some 2,000 years
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
later, some of these proto-Polynesians broke out
into Eastern Polynesia. It is widely believed that
this great leap into oceanic space took them to
the Marquesas Islands, from which they then dis¬
persed to Hawaii, the Tahiti group and from
there to Aotearoa. This last major movement
seems to have occurred about a thousand years
ago. A glance at the Polynesian triangle on a map
of the Pacific is enough to give some idea of the
extraordinary distances involved.
Were these migrations purposeful or were
they accidental "drift" voyages? The scholarly
consensus, based on computer simulation of
ancient weather conditions and other evidence,
such as the distribution of plants and animals, sug¬
gests that although some accidental voyages may
have occurred there was intended and purposeful
migration.
One argument against the drift thesis is that
the known pattern of migration conflicts with
the prevailing easterly winds of the Triangle. In
fact the wind shifts to the west at more or less
regular times, and waiting for this west wind
became an important element in Polynesian reli¬
gious beliefs. Tawhiri-a-matea, the god of winds,
Padfic
pioneers
Tipene O'Regan
Tahitlan war canoes are
shown In painting, left,
executed by William
Hodges during Captain
Cook's second voyage to
the Pacific (1772-1775).
Right, a figurehead from
Rarotonga, Cook Islands,
carved In the form of a
fisherman's god known as
"Great Ears".
is almost as important in Polynesian traditions
as Tangaroa, and in the whakapapa (genealogy)
of creation, he is the elder brother with whom
Tangaroa most closely interacts. This relationship
was activé and constant, and when the Polyne¬
sians put out to sea it was into the hands of these
two atua that they entrusted themselves.
THE CANOE, SYMBOL OF PRESTIGE
The dominating cultural object in migration tra¬
dition was the waka or canoe, which was a
symbol of mana, tribal authority, chiefly pres¬
tige and, most of all, wealth. Building a great 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
canoe was a major exercise which required the
full commitment of the skilled members of the
tribe and called for resources that only a few of
the high island cultures of Polynesia could afford.
The decoration of the waka and the ritual
associated with it became a major focus of reli¬
gious life.
Far from being a frail and inadequate vessel,
the traditional Polynesian canoe was, for its time,
at the leading edge of maritime technology. We
know from historical evidence and more recent
From the sea to children
The seaa soaring mountain-
Lashes and crushes mighty cliffs of rock.
These flimsy things, what are they to me?
"Know ye my power?" The sea lashes
Threateningly, it breaks, it crushes.
No fear assaults, no terror
Masters me. Earth's power and pride
Are tedious toys to me. All that the earth
Imagines mighty is to me no more
Than a mere feather floating by.
Ch'oe Nam-son (1890-1957)
Korean writer
simulated research that its double hulls, lashed
together with sennit, were capable of sailing at
great speed. The heavy stresses experienced in
modern twin-hulled catamarans were avoided by
keeping the canoe hulls quite close together so
that they did not create too much resistance to
the pressure of the sails on the hulls. The latter
were able to "give" to the pressure of wind and
to flex and "work" with the movement of the
waves.
The distinctive Polynesian sprit sail which
drove these canoes was woven from pandanus
fibre. Recent simulated studies suggest that it had
more driving force than even the fore and aft rig
of modern vessels. It was, however, more difficult
to control. A remarkable modern reconstruction
of a Polynesian voyaging canoe, the Hawaiian-
built Hokule'a, has made swift voyages between
Hawaii and Tahiti, Tahiti and Raratonga, and
Raratonga and New Zealand.
PRODIGIOUS FEATS OF MEMORY
But the waka by itself was not enough. The great
voyages would have been impossible without
mastery of a developed and sophisticated system
of navigation. Considerable astronomical
knowledge was required, and an intimate under¬
standing of oceanic wind patterns and other
natural and seasonal phenomena. A navigator
would, for example, need to know the rising and
setting positions of roughly 1,000 azimuth stars.
Right, carved post from a
Maori meeting house In
Rotorua (New Zealand).
Below, replicas of Hawaiian
canoes off the island of Maui.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
1
As well as performing that prodigious feat of
memory, the priestly navigator would have to
make and master "memory maps" of island
groups and know much about wind patterns and
wave systems. The absorption and retention of
this huge volume of knowledge, transmitted
without notebooks or instruments, were a part
of religious practice. We know that these naviga¬
tional systems were workable because they have
been tested extensively in the Hokule'a
experience.
Why did these people undertake their
remarkable travels? There is much historical evi¬
dence of inter-island trading in canoes between
Samoa and Tonga, Tahiti and other islands of
eastern Polynesia. But what of the migration
voyages over hundreds of miles of ocean? Poly¬
nesian traditions speak of competition on over¬
crowded islands, defeat in war, and chiefly con¬
flicts of family and prestige. Much voyaging,
however, seems to have been driven by that most
human of all needsthe lure of the far horizon
and the desire to know and to explore. Whatever
the motive, it is clear that these remarkable
seafarers were supremely confident in their
ability, in the capacity of their craft and in the
goodwill of their atua.
The high and ornately carved stern posts and
low-slung prows of the Maori and Tahitian waka
are examples of a blending of art and belief. Art,
knowledge, and the pride of the community all
focused on the canoe. The smaller, more
IB
TIPENE O'REGAN,
a New Zealander of Ngai Tahu
Maori descent, is chairman of
the Ngai Tahu Maori Trust
Board and chairman of the
Maori Fisheries Commission. A
member of the New Zealand
Geographic Board and a
trustee of the National
Museum of New Zealand, he
has written widely on Maori
and Polynesian history and
cultural affairs in the Pacific.
utilitarian waka for fishing and coastal travel were
less adorned, but there was always some
decoration carving, inlaid shellwork or the geo¬
metric design of the lashings holding the craft
together.
There is art in both the structural design and
the decoration of these canoes. To the Polyne¬
sians, art is inseparable from function. The carved
prow of a Maori war canoe is a defiant figure
flying over Tangaroa towards the enemy. The
small carved figures carried aboard fishing and
voyaging canoes were not works of art taken
along as prized possessions, but symbols and
residing places of the protective atua of the Poly¬
nesians.
Everything to do with Tangaroa was
decoratedfish-hooks, sinkers, spears. Art was
necessary to evoke from the atua a good catch.
Even today the custom of returning the first fish
to Tangaroa remains an important one. Art and
custom decree that the god of the ocean must be
appeased.
The sea of courage
Perhaps the encyclopaedist who would prove
most instructive for us would be Hegel when
he ascribed man's finest qualities to the sea.
In describing this sea, he spontaneously
lit upon the expression he had used to
characterize the logic of History: the cunning
ofReason (die List der Vernunftj; nor is it
inappropriate to hark back to the Iliad and
to cunning Odysseus. Let us consider the
passage devoted to the sea. The seafarer is a
man who, better than any other, symbolizes
human grandeur, courage and endeavour:
"The sea arouses courage" (Das Meer
erweckt den Mut).
Here courage is bound up with
intelligence and must also involve cunning
as it is directed against an element which is
the most cunning, the least trustworthy and
the most deceptive: "This infinite expanse is
perfectly malleable for there is no pressure it
resists, not even a breath; it seems infinitely
innocent, submissive, good-natured and
docile and it is precisely this pliability that
transforms the sea into the most dangerous
and the most powerful element.
"Against such deceitfulnesss and such
violence man pits no more than a simple
piece of wood, relies solely on his courage
and ingenuity and moves from what is firm
to what is unsupported, bringing with the
floor that he has set beneath his feet
himself."
Yvon Belaval
French philosopher
{La mer au siècle des encyclopédies,
1987, collective work,
Champion, Paris, Slatkine, Geneva, 1987)
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
From siren song to shanty, the sea
has always been associated with
music. For songwriter Georges
Moustaki it was a formative
influence as he grew up in the
cosmopolitan port of Alexandria. On
the Atlantic shores of Brazil it has
brought inspiration to the "saltwater
poets" who have created explosive
forms of popular music from a
multicultural tradition. The sea is
also a cradle where, alone beneath
the stars, the sailor can find solace,
away from the pressures of modern
life ashore.
Mask 0/ the f«
1 HE sea, a source of sustenance to those who live on her
shores, the homeland of travellers, of those who span worlds;
the sea, which rises and falls with all the majesty of a symphonic
poem. The sea, fountainhead of sounds and rhythms. The sea
wind plucks the strings of guitars, harps and lutes, and makes
the tom-tom skin vibrate. It fills the bellows of the accordion.
Great music and light music, Debussy and Trenet, live and
breathe the cadence of the waves as they endlessly advance and
retreat.
I am a son of Alexandria, and my vocation as a musician
grew in a port city, a seaside city where from childhood my
rovings were accompanied by the tang of algae, by glittering
cascades of spray, by the splashing of waves against the stone
blocks of the jetty and their discreet murmuring as they died
on the sand, by the sirens of liners, by the lapping of water
around the hulls of the caiques, and the cries of seagulls.
As I walked along the seashore to school, I would hear the
first songs of the day being intoned by the fishermen as they
drew in their nets, hauled their boats ashore or serenaded an
early morning bather.
After the war, a film entitled Fièvre was shown in Alexandria
in which Tino Rossi, alone in the middle of the Mediterranean,
sang Schubert's Ave Maria unaccompanied. As I spent most of
my time on the Maiscaizone, the cockleshell my father had given
me, I identified spontaneously with the hero of the film and
sang away as I pulled on the oars. Later, I learned that the writer-
sailor Gérard d'Aboville sang my songs during a solo voyage,
to break the silence, fight exhaustion or simply to amuse
himself.
When I wrote the music of Milord for Edith Piaf, I tried
to remember the sounds I had heard in the sailors' dives I knew
when I was a teenager, with the disturbing beauties of the port
and the songs the seamen bawled out to the accompaniment
of a honky-tonk piano.
Songs of the sea, of love, of death.
Songs of the deep or the shore. . .
. . . My memory is steeped in them, and my verses some¬
times hymn the urge to travel. It was on the Greek island of
Spetsai that the sea whispered my first notes to me.
GEORGES MOUSTAKI, French singer and composer, was born in Alexandria
(Egypt) of Greek parents. He wrote songs for a number of well-known French
singers before becoming a successful singer himself. He is the author of two
books, Questions à la Chanson and tes filles de la mémoire (with a preface by
Jorge Amado).
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
by Georges Moustài
Wherever there is sea, songs are born to reduce tensions,
ease partings, salute arrivals, win the girls waiting on the jetty
or console the wives dressed in black who have learned that
the sea, their rival, has kept their husbands.
The songs of Dorival Caymmi, a poet, singer and musician
from the north of Brazil, describe the daily odyssey of the
fishermen of Bahia, lovers of the ocean, victims of its fury, cap¬
tivated by its sorcery and by Yemanja, goddess of the waves,
who sometimes takes them to her underwater kingdom.
Before Hertzian waves, the waves of the sea transmitted
music between people, countries and continents, mingling with
other forms of music to give rise to new melodies and new
rhythms.
The bandoneón, a portable harmonium invented by the
German musician Heinrich Band to accompany religious
processions, was introduced by the sailors of Hamburg to the
porteños of Buenos Aires, where it became indissociable from
the tango.
At Tananarive I bought a kind of musical bow and a drum
whose notes could be modulated by a stick fixed on to its skin.
Some time later I came across almost identical instruments in
Brazil where they were known as the "berimbau" and the
cuica .
Andalusian music, which originated in Pakistan or Byzan¬
tium, was brought to north Africa and southern Spain by
nomads who travelled by land and sea.
The meeting of European folklore and emigrants to the New
World with the pulsating songs of the African slaves, all borne
by sea, created the musical expression of the two Americas. This
intermingling brought universality to American music.
The World of Silence is the title of a great film about the
sea. Silence, too, is music.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Yemanja, godàss of the sea
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
by Mario de AraUnha
Boats laden with offerings are
launched In Rio de Janeiro on
New Year's Eve during a
fiesta In honour of Yemanja,
goddess of the sea and of
fertility.
I HE musical tradition of the Brazilian littoral
began with the arrival of the first Portuguese navi¬
gators and developed during the 300 years or
more which saw the forced migration of slaves
from Africa. This century it has achieved nation¬
wide popularity and recognition through the
talents of Dorival Caymmi, a mulatto of Afro-
Italian origin who drew inspiration from the
songs of Portuguese sailors, mestizo fishermen
and worshippers of the three black divinities of
the sea.
THE AFRO TRADITION
The coastline of Brazil is almost 8,500 kilometres
longlonger than that of almost any other
country in the world. Along it the early sixteenth-
century colonists first settled. Only later did
colonization spread to the hinterland with the
gold rush to Minas Gerais in the eighteenth cen¬
tury, the rubber boom which attracted settlers
up the Amazon, and the development of coffee-
growing inland from Sào Paulo. The inaugura¬
tion of a new capital, Brasilia, in 1960 constituted
an official challenge to the Brazilian's passion for
the sea.
Maritime culture is important in the big
northeastern cities such as Recife and Fortaleza,
and throughout the region as a whole. But it is
primarily in Bahia that the ripple of waves turns
most easily to music. Early Portuguese influences
such as that of the majurada ("Sailor, it's the fish
in the sea/ that taught me to swim, that taught
me to swim. . . .") were followed by African Can-
domblé chants which established a tradition of
sea songs, whose musical form and religious
power attested doubly to their black origins. The
people of Salvador de Bahia, the most African of
Brazilian cities, sing for all the Orixás, the saints
of their syncretic religion, but they keep their
best offerings for Yemanja, the goddess of the
deep sea more beloved than her fellow-divinities,
Oxum god of the shore and Ayoka goddess of
the deep.
"On the second day of February, festival day
at sea,
I want to be the first to celebrate Yemanja.
J)
Thus sang young Dorival Caymmi, who left
Bahia in 1938 to seek fame and fortune in Rio
de Janeiro, where he was a fantastic success with
his big guitar and his serious way of singing about
gods, fish, fishermen, and the sea off Bahia.
"The raft set sail with Chico Ferreira and
Bento,
the raft returned alone. ..."
"How many have lost
husbands and sons in the waters of the sea."
While Caymmi sang of dramatic events from
the lives of the fishermen of northeastern Brazil
and their familiesdisconsolate widows, weeping 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
fiancées waiting for their men to return, offerings
begging Yemanja to provide fish Admiral Paulo
Moreiro da Silva, the architect of modern Brazil's
fishing policy, said jokingly that "The hunger
problem of the northeast would be solved if we
turned the map of Brazil upside down and sent
the great shoals of fish from the south to the
north". In rich, cold, southern Brazil, where the
economy is based largely on industry and agricul¬
ture and where the coast is sparsely populated,
sardines are plentiful and fishing is practised on
a large scale with modern vessels.
In the northeast, where fishing has always
been a source of subsistence, the fish are bigger
and finer, but they are caught individually on the
line, from rudimentary craft such as the saveiros
of Bahia or even from rafts. The recent industri¬
alization of fishing in the region has largely
brought profits to a handful of companies from
the south.
POETIC INSPIRATION
Solitary adventures like that immortalized by
Hemingway in The Old Man and the Sea are
common in the warm waters off Bahia, Ceará and
Pernambuco. They have inspired many poems,
including one written by Caymmi and his great
friend Jorge Amado, which contains the words:
"It is sweet to die at sea, in the green waves
of the sea. . . . The siren has seduced the hand¬
some sailor. . . ."
Caymmi's influence on Brazilian popular
music has been far-reaching. Many other com¬
posers inspired by folklore have followed his
example, and have brought the music of distant
regions to Rio, the cultural centre of the Brazilian
sub-continent. As a composer and guitarist
Caymmi has been a great innovator in the field
of harmony. Already a veteran, he wrote four of
the early songs of Joào Gilberto, the creator of
the bossa nova. His musical heirs are countless.
Caymmi was still very popular when the
bossa nova appeared on the scene. He shared its
glory on the record in which he and Gilberto,
accompanied by Cuarteto em Cy, sing a bossa
nova classic, "The fishermen's suite":
"My raft is off out to sea. . ./ when I come
home from the sea a fine fish I shall bring/ my
friends will come back too/and we shall give
thanks to God in heaven. . . ."
"Farewell, farewell fisherman, do not forget
me/I am praying for fair weather/that the
weather won't be foul. . . .
"With weather like that we stay in port/He
who goes to sea does not come back. . . ."
A NEW CULT
From the historic encounter between Caymmi
36 and the bossa nova a new cult was born on the
shores of a sea that had become symbolic, an
urban sea edged by the concrete buildings south
of Rio from which people can greet the summer
from their windows:
"Day of light, festival of the Sun, and the
little boat glides on the tender blue of the sea"
(O Barquinho by Mensecal and Boscoli, recorded
by Joào Gilberto in 1961).
This is the cult of health, beauty and passion.
From Tereza de Praia, in which Dick Farney and
Lucio Alvez sang "She belongs to nobody, she
can't be mine, she can't be his", to Tom Jobim
and Vinicius de Moraes's great hit The girl from
Ipanema, the shapely beauty of the girls (and
boys) of Rio who congregate on the beaches and
in the bars of Ipanema, Copacabana and Leblon
has become the great source of inspiration for the
poets of salt water and ice-cold beer.
Most of the movements that have changed
the life of the Carioca and of Brazilians in general
have come into being and found expression in
song on the beaches of Rio: cultural resistance
to the dictatorship, the liberalization of morals,
and now the prevention of AIDS.
As the urban population increases, the
problem of seawater pollution gets worse in spite
of all that has been done to extend sewage pipes
further from the shore. The ecological balance
is precarious. A great effort is being made to
restore beauty to the beaches and purity to the
water.
Perhaps this is a response to the dearest
wishes of Yemanja, whose cult is gaining ground
in Rio not only among the traditional practi¬
tioners of Candomblé, the country's second
religion after Roman Catholicism, but also
among the general public. New Year's Eve has
become a great festival in honour of the sea
goddess. That night, southern Rio comes to a halt
as hundreds of thousands of worshippers throw
flowers into the sea while cascading fireworks
illuminate the scene.
The moment symbolizes what is expected of
the sea throughout the year. When it is not a
receptacle for the city's wastes it is the recipient
of requests for good luck and happiness, money,
health and love. It is almost as if the sea can
absorb all the negative energies of humankind and
return them in the form of food and fortune.
Perhaps the Bahia song-writers Gerónimo
and Vevé Calasans were seeking to placate the sea
divinities of Brazil when they wrote:
"A dozen roses ... I wanted to give,
but without asking a thing, I threw them in
the sea,
embracing the sea, but without asking a thing
I just gave thanks. ..."
MARIO DE ARATANHA is a Brazilian journalist, record
producer, and organizer of cultural events.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Night waé, ahne
A M I T I É is a 7.60-metre cutter with
L\ a blue hull and white sails. We
JL Jl. named her for friendship
ours, that of the people we hoped to meet
on our two-year cruiseand for a song
well known to international volunteer
workcampers. We only discovered much
later the other Amitié which appears,
dragged up on the beach, in a painting by
Van Gogh.
One late April afternoon, our Amitié
nosed out of the harbour of Las Palmas,
capital of the Canary Islands, and turned
west. Objective? Bridgetown, Barbados,
some 2,700 sea and tradewind miles
toward sunset. On board were Nicole
(France), Glyn (UK) and I (USA). Glyn's
first son had just been born back in
England. In a paternal gesture (and
perhaps to ward off storms and evil
spiritssailors still tend to worry about
both), he streamed astern, on a short line,
a rubber duck borrowed from the new
baby. "There," announced Glyn, making
sure the line was tied fast to a cleat, "by
the time he gets back to England, that
duck's going to be a very salty bluewater
sailor!"
The first night and day were har¬
rowing as we crossed a heavily-travelled 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
north-south shipping lane. We were not
much bigger than a single lifeboat on the
deck of one of the monster craft that
loomed on all sides. Our radar reflector
probably graced their screens with a blip
not much bigger than that of a seagull.
Then the shipping lane was behind us.
And before us? Nothing. We would
not see another human being for over a
month.
Nothingness. . . . Sea, sky, wind,
waves: huge rollers towering above our
stern, raising us to their crests in slow-
motion roller-coaster style, and depositing
us (not always gently) in the following
trough. A nothingness made the more
impressive by the fact that, as we settled
into a routine, each of us spent several
hours out of every twenty-four on watch
alone.
Nothingness, the sea? Beneath our
keel were something like two kilometres
of salt and waterelemental substances
that make up some 70 per cent of you and
me. The surface of this ever-heaving,
often-roiling liquid was about one metre
beneath the seat of the slicker trousers-
then, as the weather warmed, swimsuit
of whoever was on watch.
Close enough to observe the dolphin
fish that followed us, the dolphins that
preceded us, and the flying fish chased by
some ominous icthyomorphous cousins
off the crests of waves and practically into
the open jaws of frigates and other sea
birds that wheeled and waited for a
winged snack.
SOLITUDE
Nothingness, the sky? Sun and stars gave
us our bearings; the sight of a bird trying
to light on the wildly gyrating masthead
gave us mirth; and the Moon and Jupiter
joined forcesI enjoyed night watch-
to light up whatever reading matter I
wanted, even an old copy of Le Monde (a
newspaper not renowned for large type).
Not nothingness, then; but solitude
for certain. A solitude made the more
present by the disappearance of Glyn's
son's ducky. A sharp tooth had been at
work: the line was severed, not
unravelled.
Solitude, then, although humankind
wasn't far: strewn along the whole trans¬
atlantic crossing were bobbing oil drums,
38 petroleum-coated plastic containers of
The sea's hand
/ lost my way.
And I found the sea's hand,
its ever open route,
the glittering green waves.
I walked beside it,
oh gentle lull of evening.
Oh drunken rapture of dawn.
And the monster of the tempest
took me in his arms.
Elmer Diktonius (1896-1961)
Finnish writer
many shapes and sizes and other flotsam
and jetsam of our "civilization". One
plastic box wheedled to nobody but us
and the birds: "Drink Coca-Cola!" "Like
hell I will!" I shouted after it as it drifted
astern, already on the lookout for another
yachtsman-client, improbable before a
few days ... or months.
Other news that came, via the BBC,
included civil war in Africa, student dis¬
turbances in Europe, and twice-daily time
checks for our navigation. We also heard
May Day in Red Square: thank you,
Radio Moscow; the bands came in loud
and clear and we cavorted in the
1.5-square-metre cockpit.
"IT'S RAINING IN RIO"
About two a.m. one night I craned my
neck as two planes approached each other
in opposite directions overhead. At first
mesmerized by their warning flashes, I
then jumped for the radio and heard two
British Airways pilots chat offhandedly:
"Hope you've brought your mac, friend;
it's raining in Rio. Over." Crackle.
"Roger, friend. And /advise you to take
the Underground in from Heathrow.
They've got the motorway dug up a treat
again. Over."
For me, there was nobody to talk to,
but I was speechless anyway. And then I
started laughing out loud. Those fellows
were each doing about 800 knots and
would reach their respective destinations
in scant hours. We were churning out
about four knots and had several weeks
to go yet.
Little by little, night solitude turned
one's thoughts inwards. Fear? I honestly
searched for it, and knew there were
objective reasons to find it. A Swedish
sailboat had recently been becalmed in
mid-Atlantic and turned up in the West
Indies with no more drinking water and
only one tiny pot of jam left to eat for
the five-person crew. We ourselves had
had a dicey moment when one of the
crosstrees started to crawl down the port
staythat could have been catastrophe.
Luckily, Glyn was on deck at the same
time as I and, standing on my joined hands
(a prayerful stepping stool they made),
managed to jury-rig a repair. In Las Palmas
we had met Poland's first single-handed
round-the-world sailor, Leonid Telega.
He showed us his logbook in which the
Soviet poet Yevgeny Yevtushenko, whom
he had met in Tahiti, had written that his
boat's name, Opty, made him "half an
optimist". No, there was not much fear,
however. (No superman, I'm scared of
high places.)
On the other hand there was some
(pardonable?) satisfaction. Contrary to
friends' predictions, I had managed to
learn to use a sextantwe were, in fact,
only about five sea miles off course when
we arrived "on the other side"; not bad for
a bunch of amateurs. And I had managed
to rig a twin headsails arrangementFred
and Jim we called them following the
example of a pre-war French solo sailor
and seascape painter, Marin-Marie. They
enabled Amitié to steer herself most of
the time. (Giving time to think.)
I felt only a distant relative of the
Tabarly-type racers. Amitié was a friendly
donkey, not a sleek racehorse; our only
competitor was danger, not the chronom¬
eter; and minus an obsession with speed,
we were able to savour the slow passing
of time.
THE CALL OF THE DEEP
But if the racers were distant relatives,
they were kin all the same and I thought
often of them. Other nocturnal kindred
visitors included some of our hardy
predecessors, who managed with wood,
hemp and canvas (compared with our
fibreglass hull and synthetic running rig¬
ging and sails), who had no radios, no self-
inflating life-rafts, and were often months
on a single crossing.
Grandad among the solo artists was
probably Yankee Capt. Joshua Slocum,
who built his boats with his own hands
and may well have beenas early as the
nineteenth century the first singlehander
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
to circumnavigate the globe. There was
also Vito Dumas, an Argentine relative
of writer Alexandre, who had to operate
on himself with a penknife at sea when
an abcess threatened his life. Then there
was painter Marin-Marie, just mentioned.
In 1933, he crossed the Atlantic from east
to westa real "first"alone but in rela¬
tive comfort and with a modicum of rest.
Of sixty-five days at sea, he only spent
twenty-three at the helm. The twin-
headsails system he invented obligingly
steered his eleven-metre cutter Winibelle
II the rest of the time.
Why did they do it? Why were we
doing it? "To get away from it all"at
least for a whileand literally to rub
shoulders with Nature in her many
moods, to be in and of and completely
dependent on Nature, and to learn not
to try to dominate her, but to co-operate
with her. To test ourselves, too, since we
were fairly young at the time. For the
sheer joy of the days when the Sun shone
and the wind sped us along leaving a
straight bubbling, glistening wake astern;
for the thrill of facing nasty blows (that
had been in the winter Mediterranean a
few months earlierand we'd had quite
enough of that particular kind of thrill!).
And, finally, because one hot summer
evening years before, sitting on
Geneviève, a hulk where we lived under
the Pont de la Concorde in Paris sniffing
The sea
Before our human dream (or terror) wove
Mythologies, cosmogonies and love,
Before time coined its substance into days,
The sea, the always sea, existed: was.
is the sea? Who is that violent being,
Violent and ancient, who gnaws the
foundations
Of earth? He is both one and many oceans;
He is abyss and splendour, chance and wind.
Who looks on the sea, sees it the first time,
Every time, with the wonder distilled
From elementary thingsfrom beautiful
Evenings, the moon, the leap of a bonfire.
Who is the sea, and who am I? The day
That follows my last agony shall say.
Jorge Luis Borges (1899-1986)
Argentine writer
Translated by John Updike in Jorge Luis Borges.
Selected Poems 1923-1967. ©Penguin Books 1985.
at the gracelessly perfumed Seine, with
auto exhaust fumes wafting down on us
from the bridge above, Glyn and I had
suddenly decided that the open sea was
for us.
Despite a strict prohibition on
alcohol, my thirty-first birthday was
celebrated with the merest thimble of
medicinal rum. It came as a reminder of
temporal realityby then, after three
weeks at sea, firmly in inverted commas:
"reality". But I was never bored. The
racers have no time to be bored; I had
time not to be bored. Not too many Deep
Thoughts crossed my mind, but it was
ready to receive and nurture those that
happened its way, doubtless a bit ruffled
by the tradewind that pushed us inex¬
orably towards the New World.
THE RHYTHMS OF NATURE
Day thirty-five dawned with Barbados'
eastern shore beginning to rise before us
from the flat bed of the western horizon.
As Amitié drew closer, I was first
bemused, then astonished, then (a little)
frightened by repeated rapid glintings of
light. Closer still, and the glintings proved
to come from the windscreens and
windows of cars zipping along the shore
roads of Barbados, reflecting back to us
the light of the Sun rising at our stern.
"Zipping" is too weak a word: the drivers
seemed to have been maddened to dizzy-
ingly, fantastically dangerous speeds along
those winding narrow roads: now I did
feel fear, fear for the drivers' lives!
Later, I realized that the cars had been
moving at a careful leisurely pace, that I
in fact had slowed down, that in one-
month-plus at sea my own biorhythm
had relaxed, to match the rhythms of the
elements of Nature: the slow, relatively
regular respiration of the waves, wind and
stars.
My night watches alone left me with
many questions and perplexities, but also
with one secure conviction (on which I
have certainly not acted sufficiently
since): "faster" is not necessarily "better".
Thank you, Amitié.
ARTHUR GILLETTE was formerly editor-in-chief of
UNESCO's international quarterly Museum, and is
now a member of the Organization's Division of
Youth and Sport Activities. He has published a
number of articles on maritime questions in
specialist magazines. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
A wealth of legends, fables,
poems and allegorical writings
illustrate the fascination that
the sea has exercised on
the creative imagination ever
since ancient times. For modern
seafarers who observe age-old
superstitions and taboos the
symbolism associated with the sea
is still as potent as ever.
However, with increasing
pollution and uncontrolled
tapping of its riches, the sea
may be losing its sacred aura.
A ' ' ¡I » ; v-
,*:?»'
Extracted from Romans et contes
égyptiens, translated into French with
an introduction and commentary by
Gustave Lefebure © Adrien Maisonneuve,
Paris 1976.
IN this story from ancient Egypt, an
Egyptian describes the extraordinary
adventures that befell him when he
sailedfrom a Red Sea port to the mines of
Sinai. He tells how he was shipwrecked
and then landed on a marvellous island
whose master, a serpent, made him welcome
and sent him home laden with gifts. Back in
Egypt he was received by the king, who
bestowed on him the honour ofCompanion.
The island on whose shores the sailor
was cast by a wave of the "Very Green"
(the Red Sea) is called "the island o/ka."
The ka was originally regarded as an
invisible power which is born with man,
accompanies him during his life and,
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
mMÍMm
. Tí
sah's story
leaving him at his death, continues
nevertheless to represent the personality of
the being with which it coexisted on Earth.
It corresponds approximately to the
Western concept of the soul. The ka is also
the life force, the principle oflife, and then
all that keeps a person alive, from food to
royal favour.
The island o/ka would thus be a place
where there is an abundance ofall the good
things which help to keep life going. Given
the early meaning o/ka, it might also be
thought of as the island of the spirit, the
island of the ghostthe enchanted island.
It lay in the "land of Punt", a place-
name which seems to have designated
primarily the western coast ofthe Red Sea
and later came to include the coast of
Arabia opposite and notably the Yemen
(where the land of the famous Queen of
Sheba was located).
As early as the old empire, the Egyp¬
tians sent expeditions to the land of Punt
in search ofaromatic essences and incense.
Sometimes accidents happened, for the
coast is dotted with many reefs and islands.
These voyages were laborious and often
dangerous, and those who returned embroi¬
dered the stories of their adventures with
extraordinary details to charm and astonish
their listeners. This must have been the
origin ofthe story ofthe shipwrecked sailor.
An ancient Egyptian vessel
is shown In this detail from the burial
vault of Nefer, a dignitary of
the fifth dynasty (c. 2500-2400 BC),
at Sakkara.
I am going to tell you something . . .
that happened . . . while I was going
to the mines of the sovereign and had
gone down on the Very Green aboard a
ship 120 cubits long and forty cubits
wide.1 Aboard were 120 sailors, the
flower of Egypt. Whether they kept
watch on the sky or the land, their hearts
were more steadfast than that of a lion.
They could announce a storm before it
happened.
THE STORM AND THE SHIPWRECK
A storm had broken when we were on
the Very Green and before we had
reached land. We carried on sailing, but
the storm redoubled its violence, raising
a wave of eight cubits. . . . Then the ship
sank without any survivors. And I was
cast away on an island by a wave of the
Very Green. I spent three days alone,
with only my heart for companionship.
Lying inert beneath the shelter of a tree
(?), I embraced the tree. Then I stretched
my legs and went in search of something
to eat. I found figs and grapes, magnifi¬
cent vegetables of all kinds, the fruits of
the sycamore . . . and cucumbers as if they
had been cultivated. There too were fish
and birds. Everything imaginable was
there. I took a grip of myself and threw
down on to the ground (some of these
foodstuffs), for I had too much to carry.
Then, when I had taken a fire-stick I
made a fire and a burnt offering to the
gods.
A BEARDED SERPENT APPEARS
Then I heard the sound of thunder. I sup¬
posed that it was a wave of the Very
Green. The trees cracked and the earth
trembled. When I uncovered my face, I
saw that a serpent was coming: he meas¬
ured thirty cubits and his beard exceeded
two cubits; his limbs were plated with
gold, his eyebrows (?) were in real lapis
lazuli. He came forward cautiously (?).
He opened his mouth to me while I
was on my belly before him, saying:
"Who has brought you [here], who has
brought you, little one? Who has brought
you? If you tarry before telling me who
has brought you to this island, I shall
make sure that you see that, after being
reduced to cinders, you have become 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
something that is no longer visible." [I
replied:] "You speak to me and I do not
grasp [what you say]: I am before you and
I have lost my senses."
Then he put me in his mouth, car¬
ried me to his lair and put me down
gently so that I was safe and sound,
without anything having been taken
from me. He opened his mouth to me
while I was on my belly before him, and
then said to me: "Who has brought you
[here], who has brought you, little one?
Who has brought you onto this island of
the Very Green whose two shores are in
the waves?"
[The Egyptian tells the story of the
shipwreck]
THE SERPENT
MAKES A PROMISE
Then he said to me: "Fear not, little one;
don't look so tormented now that you
have come to me. God has certainly
allowed you to live, since he has brought
you to this island of ka where everything
can be found and which is filled with all
kinds of good things. Here you will pass
month after month until you have spent
four months on this island. Then a boat
will come from the country, manned by
sailors whom you know. You will return
with them to your country and you will
die in your city.2 Happy are they who
can tell what they have experienced, once
the painful moments have passed!
"I shall tell you a similar story, which
happened on this island where I was with
my fellows, among whom there were
children. There were seventy-five of us
serpents in all, including my children and
my fellows. Not to mention a very young
girl whom I had obtained by prayer. A
star fell, and set them ablaze. This hap¬
pened when I was not with [them]; they
burned while I was not in their midst. I
nearly died because of them when I found
them in a single heap of bodies.
"If you are strong, master your heart:
you will clasp your children to your
breast, you will embrace your wife, you
will see your house again, and that will
be worth more than anything. You will
return to the country where you lived in
the midst of your brothers."
THE PRINCE
OF THE LAND OF PUNT
Then, prostrate on my belly, I touched
the earth before the Serpent with my
forehead and said: "I shall tell the Sover¬
eign of your power and will see that he
42 is informed of your greatness. I shall have
[perfumes] brought to youibi, hekenou,
iudeneb, khesayt, and the temple incense
in which each god rejoices. I shall thus
tell what has happened [on this island],
mindful of what I have seen by virtue of
[your] power. You will be thanked in the
city, before the notables of all the
country. I shall sacrifice bulls for you as
a burnt offering, I shall twist the necks
of game birds for you. I shall have ships
laden with all the precious products of
Egypt brought to you, as is meet for a god
who loves men, in a distant country that
men do not know."
Sea and darkness
At first I thought it impossible to
remain alone at sea for three hours.
But at five o'clockfive hours after
my shipwreckI found it natural to
be waiting still. The sun was going
down. . . . Suddenly the sky grew
crimson and I continued to scan the
horizon. Then it turned dark purple
and I continued to look at it. On
one side of the raft, the first star
came out, set like a yellow diamond
in the wine-red sky. And all at once
pitch-black night descended upon the
sea.
My first impression, on realizing
that I was so completely immersed in
darkness that I could no longer see
my hand before my eyes, was that I
would not be able to surmount my
terror. The sound of the water
lapping against my raft was my only
way of knowing that, slowly but
surely, I was continuing to advance.
Plunged in the gloom, I realized that
never during the daytime had I been
so alone. The darkness added to my
feeling of loneliness on this raft
which I could not see but which I
felt gliding beneath me on a viscous
sea inhabited by strange animals. To
feel less lonely, I started looking at
my watch. Ten to seven. Much
latertwo or three hours later, so it
seemed to me!I looked again: five
to seven. When the big hand reached
the figure twelve, it was seven o'clock
precisely and the sky was streaming
with stars. I had the impression that
so much time had gone by that dawn
was about to break.
Gabriel García Márquez
Colombian writer
(Relato de un naufrago)
Then he laughed at me,3 [or rather]
at what I had said and which he thought
crazy, and said: "You do not have much
frankincense, while you were born pos¬
sessing resin of the turpentine tree. But
frankincense belongs to me, the prince of
[the land] of Punt. As for this hekenou
perfume which you thought of bringing,
it is the main product of this island. It will
come to pass, when you have left this
place, that you will never again see this
island, which will be transformed into
waves."
THE RETURN HOME
This ship came as the Serpent had
predicted. I went and perched high in a
tree and recognized the people who were
aboard. Then I went to announce this
piece of news [to the Serpent], but I found
that he [already] knew. And he said to
me: "[Go back] healthy, healthy, little
one, to your homemay you see your
children again! Make sure that my repu¬
tation is good in your city. That is all I
ask of you." Then I prostrated myself on
my belly, arms outstretched before the
Serpent. And he gave me a cargo of
frankincense, hekenou, iudeneb, khesayt,
tichepes, chaasekh perfumes, black eye
wash, giraffes' tails, much resin of the tur¬
pentine tree, ivory tusks, hunting dogs,
monkeys, baboons, and all kinds of pre¬
cious goods.4 1 loaded it all on the ship.
Then, when I prostrated myself to thank
him, he said to me: "You will reach your
country in two months, you will clasp
your children to your breast, you will
become young again, you will be buried
there." Thereupon I went down to the
shore to the ship and hailed the crew. I
gave thanks, on the shore, to the master
of this island and also [to] those who were
on board.
Then we set sail northwards, towards
the court of the Sovereign and we reached
our country two months later, exactly as
the Serpent had said. I was taken to the
Sovereign and I gave him the presents I
had brought back from the island. He
thanked me in the presence of notables
from the whole country, then I was raised
to the rank of Companion and rewarded
with serfs belonging to him.
1. Around sixty metres by twenty metres. It was a
large ship.
2. The greater misfortune that could befall an
Egyptian was to die far from Egypt.
3. The Serpent laughs because he has no need to
receive from Egypt the very things that Egyptians
came to his country to procure.
4. This list includes everything that the Egyptians
found in the land of Punt.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The strange èstiny of Urdiim Taro
F.ROM the deep waters of my childhood rose a
fantastic edifice called the Ryugu, the palace of
the Dragon. Contrary to what this rather fright¬
ening name might suggest, a soft, feminine
atmosphere prevailed there. The dragon was
rarely to be seen and a very beautiful young
woman, Otohime, lived in this underwater palace
whose walls were decorated with enamels and
corals. She wore an exotic dress. Was she the
daughter of the dragon king or some other animal
which had undergone metamorphosis? My pic¬
ture book did not say.
A man named Urashima Taro lived with her
as her guest. These two charming figures spent
days and months together in an atmosphere of
continual joy. They lacked for nothing. Count¬
less multicoloured fishessea bream, sole and
thousands of othersdanced a fantastic ballet to
the sound of exquisite music. Their table was
laden with delicious dishes. Do they eat fish and
shellfish even at the bottom of the sea, I often
wondered naively. But as to the nature of the link
that bound this extraordinary couple, I never gave
it a thought. Were they lovers, or were they mar¬
ried? My old book of stories said only that the
young man was happy. That was enough for me.
I knew why Urashima Taro lived at the
bottom of the sea. The young fisherman had gone
to the help of a giant turtle who was being
attacked by some naughty children on the beach.
Grateful for his aid, the sea creature transported
its saviour to this wonderful place.
Being such a bookworm as a child, I also
knew the end of the story. After a few years had
gone by, the hero tired of an existence given over
to games and amusements. Nostalgia took him
back to his home country, where he found to his
amazement no trace of either his home or his
mother. Nobody recognized him. . . . That was
why I was in no hurry to turn the page and leave
behind the pictures of the dragon's palace.
The last illustration to the story was dis¬
tressing for a child. On a deserted beach a piti¬
fully thin old man with a long white beard could
be seen. He seemed overwhelmed by his strange
destiny. Beside him was a small, precious-looking
box from which a plume of white smoke spiralled
upwards. Though forbidden to do so, the
fisherman had opened the present Otohime had
given him as a souvenir of their life together. The
j^HHl
by Uinomiya Masayuh
Urashima returns to his
village. Illustration from a
17th-century manuscript.
three years he thought he had spent with her were
the equivalent of 700 years on Earth! The
fisherman's death, which was clearly imminent,
seemed to me enigmatic. What offence had he
committed to deserve such a terrible punishment?
LATER on, I learnt that the legendary figure
of Urashima Taro had lived for centuries in the
collective memory of my fellow-countrymen,
symbolizing for them the sea that surrounds their
small islands.
This figure appears for the first time in
written form in the Nihon-shoki (the "Written
Chronicles of Japan", compiled in 720) which
describe mythical and historical events from the 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
The song of the Ocean
Old ocean, great solitary. . . .
Voluptuously rocked by the myriad
vapours of your majestic slowness, which is
the greatest of the qualities vested in you
by sovereign might, in the midst of a dark
mystery you unfurl over all your sublime
surface your incomparable waves, with a
calm sense of your eternal power. They roll
by in parallel lines one after the other,
with short intervals between them. Scarcely
has one begun to ebb than another rears
up towards it, accompanied by the
melancholic sound of the dissolving foam,
telling us that all is foam. (Thus human
beings, those living waves, die one after
the other, in monotonous fashion, but
without the sound of the foam).
Lautréamont (1846-1870)
French poet
(Les Chants de Maldoror)
44
beginning of the world to the seventh century.
The Chronicles describe the physical nature of
the love between Urashima and Otohime, unlike
the story I read when I was a child.
Subsequently the legend reappears in many
works belonging to different genres. The
Manyoshu (759?), the oldest anthology of Japanese
poetry, contains several poems which tell the
story of Urashima. A folk tale dating from
medieval times (otogi-zoshi) gives a particularly
detailed version which reflects a Buddhist desire
to edify and, through the theme of the quest for
immortality, the influence of Chinese literature.
After aging in the twinkling of an eye, Urashima
is transformed into a crane by a feather in one
of the three boxes given to him by Otohime, who
returns to him in the form of a turtle. Thus the
story ends with the uniting of two creatures that
symbolize longevitya thousand years of life for
the crane, ten thousand for the tortoise. A no play
tells the same story. The legend also crops up in
several tales from oral folklore. Several modern
Japanese writers have also produced variants of it.
I HE story I read in my storybook as a child
was a simplified, perhaps over-simplified, version.
But even today I love it, with its pitiless ending,
more than any other. Urashima's mysterious
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
. " . . * . . '
adventure is still deeply rooted in my memory
where, paradoxically, it is inseparable from the
sound of a military march. Like all Japanese chil¬
dren who grew up during the Second World War,
I often sang in those days a song called "Urashima
Taro" which was put out by the Ministry of Edu¬
cation. Its words gave an even simpler version of
the fisherman's story. Its rhythmical music is by
no means exceptional. This tune linked to a
specific moment in history has often come back
to me when in my imagination I have plunged
to the bottom of the sea.
M,luST I today explain, as an adult, why I prefer
the version of the story that I do? Would this not
be an act as fatal as the opening of the little box?
By way of explanation, I shall describe another
legendary image of the underwater world which
is also engraved in the memory of the Japanese
people.
In an episode of the Kojiki ("Records of
ancient matters"), a seminal text of Japanese liter¬
ature compiled in AD 712, two mythical figures
find themselves in a similar situation to that of
Urashima and Otohime, but their lives are quite
different. Toyotamabime no mikoto, the
daughter of the sea god, welcomes to the palace
of her father Watatshumi an earth divinity,
Yamasachibiko. She marries her guest and, unlike
Otohime, becomes pregnant. Thus, for the
individual, the cycle of time is renewed by procre¬
ation. As far as I know, Urashima Taro and Oto¬
hime did not have any children, although they
lived together for three yearsor 700 according
to our earthly measurement. To my mind, this
universe under the sea can only exist outside
human time.
Now we can understand that what breaks the
spell is affection, linked to a personal concept of
time. Urashima's first mistake is to wish to return
to his mother and his village. Then, by clinging
to the memory of the underwater palace which
perhaps still lingers on in the box, he irrevocably
breaks the rules of the game. Then, inevitably,
everything goes up in smoke. The bewitched
fisherman will return to human time to face his
destiny. In my children's picture book the story
ended there. When Pandora opened the box she
did at least find Hope inside it, unlike Urashima
Taro. This children's version of the story is more
cruel but it is also more authentic. If the sea of
Eternal Life exists, so do the life and death of
individual human beings. The imagination must
accept the reality of human life.
With this smoke, which is in the end far too
explanatory, it only remains for me to disappear
in my turn.
Urashima arrives in the
Dragon's palace. Illustration
from a 17th-century scroll.
NINOMIYA MASAYUKI,
Japanese university teacher
and essayist, is a lecturer at
the Institut des Langues et
Civilisations Orientales in Paris
and executive secretary
general of the association for
the construction of the
Japanese Cultural Centre in
Paris. His Watashi no naka no
Sharutoru ("Chartres in the
heart of memory", Tokyo
1990) was awarded the prize
of the essayists' club of Japan. 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Moby Dick, monster
oftheforbiäen
seas
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
IN 1839 eighteen-year-old Herman Melville, the
son of a prominent but impoverished American
family, sailed as a deckhand from New York to
Liverpool and back aboard the packet ship Si.
Lawrence. This was his first taste of the sea. Less
than two years later, after a short and unsuccessful
spell as a teacher, he returned. Signing on this
time as a lowly whalerman, despite his genteel
origins, he embarked upon the Acushnet, which
took him from Fairhaven, Massachusetts, round
Cape Horn, to the Pacific. There, after deserting
the Acushnet and becoming involved in a mutiny
on another whaling ship, he became variously a
harpooner and beachcomber on islands from the
Galápagoswhere just a few years earlier Charles
Darwin had preceded him on board the Beagle-
to Tahiti. In 1844 he returned to Boston from
Honolulu as an enlisted seaman aboard the man-
of-war United States.
It was then that his writing career truly
began, informed by his first-hand experience of
the sea, its calms and tempests, its exhilarations
and tribulations. For Melville, the sea was both
massively actual, alive with observable creation,
yet at the same time a kind of cosmic key or
cipher. Within its ebbs and flows, its moving sur¬
faces and mysterious depths, its plenitude of life-
forms from plankton to leviathans, was to be
found the very riddle of existence. "You must
have plenty of sea-room to tell the truth in", he
proclaimed.
He could hardly have better indicated the
ocean dimensions of the epic tale then taking
shape in his imagination, one which would take
its hero, Captain Ahab and his ship-of-all-nations,
the Pequod, backwards and forwards across the
great Atlantic and Pacific fishing lanes in pursuit
of that most sumptuous of aquatic creatures, the
white whale, Moby Dick, which would give its
name to his novel.
A LONGSTANDING TRADITION
Yet in speaking of "sea-room" Melville was also
aligning himself with a very longstanding tradition
in Western culture. The Book of Jonah, to take
one starting-point, explicitly alluded to in Chapter
9 of Moby Dick, relates a parable of would-be
flight and guilt in which the sea is portrayed as
the tempestuous domicile of a "great fish" that
swallows and later spews forth the recalcitrant
prophet. Then there is Homer who, with the
Iliad and the Odyssey, composed epics that became
founding stories in the Graeco-Roman legacy. In
the latter, especially, which recounts Odysseus's
journey homeward to his faithful wife Penelope
after the Trojan war, we have one of the classic
expressions of the sea as both actual and figurative
domain.
Other landmarks in Western literature, the
anonymous Beowulf znà the Nordic sea sagas,
delineate the sea as a place of northern dark and
cold. Sebastian Brant's Narrenschiff, a fifteenth-
by A. Robert Lee
century German satiric masterpiece, bequeaths us
the image of a Ship of Fools afloat on a sea of
illusion and false hopes. The European Renais¬
sance, an age of boundless discovery, yields
images of the sea as at once a site for battles and
piracy, for the unknown, and for possible routes
to Utopia, reflected in Shakespeare's The Tempest
or Camöes's Os Lusíadas (The Lusiads), the
national epic of Portugal. Camôes, not inciden¬
tally, was favourite reading for Melville. Other
poetry of the sea ranges from Coleridge's ghostly
The Ancient Mariner to Rimbaud's intensely
imagined Le bateau ivre, with the lyrics of a Fer¬
nando Pessoa, a Hart Crane or a Rafael Alberti
there to enrich the list.
But it has perhaps been in the modern novel
that the sea has found its most striking literary
expression. Who has not relished the voyaging
and the shipwrecks of Defoe's Robinson Crusoe,
Swift's Gulliver's Travels or Stevenson's Treasure
Island? Do not Antarctic fantasias like Poe's The
Narrative ofArthur Gordon Pym or Jules Verne's
underwater empire of Captain Nemo in Twenty
Thousand Leagues Under The Sea weave a spell
which extends well beyond childhood? Nor has
the sea lost any of its fascination for our century,
though it does have a growing rival in the immen¬
sities of outer space. In Joseph Conrad, Polish-
born and also an ex-mariner, one can turn to a
tale of the Malaysian Straits like Lord Jim or of
ocean journeying from the Thames to the River
Congo in Heart ofDarkness. English fiction also
Opposite page, Captain Ahab
struggles with the great white
whale in John Huston's film
Moby Dick (1956).
Below, Jonah and the whale.
Mosaic from the Basilica
Teodoriana (4th century),
Aquileia, Italy.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The Ship of Fools.
16th-century German
engraving.
supplies Virginia Woolf's The Waves, a "moder¬
nist" classic in which the sea acts as a metaphor
of human consciousness, and, as recently as the
1980s, William Golding's Rites ofPassage, the fic¬
tionalized log of a late-eighteenth-century crossing
to Australia. In these too, the sea goes beyond
mere theme: its rhythms and cadences get drawn
into the very story-telling itself.
Herman Melville thus joins distinguished
company, and not only on account oí Moby Dick.
The sea marks much of his other fiction. Still,
it is Melville's "whale-book", as he liked to call it,
which remains central. Perhaps this is because
Moby Dick so dazzlingly combines high adven¬
ture with philosophy, authentic sea lore with a
taste for metaphysics. "I have written a wicked
book", Melville told his fellow writer, Nathaniel
Hawthorne, "and feel as spotless as the lamb".
How, then, does Melville's epic picture the sea?
Firstly, there is the sea as a physical power,
Melville's ability to render the smack of wind and
current. Nowhere more dramatically does he do
so than when Ahab and his men confront the
breaching of the white whale:
"Moby Dick bodily burst into view! For not
by any calm and indolent spoutings; not by the
peaceable gush of that mystic fountain in his head,
did the White Whale now reveal his vicinity;
but by the far more wondrous phenomenon of
48
breaching. Rising with his utmost velocity from
the furthest depths, the Sperm Whale thus booms
his entire bulk into the pure element of air, and
piling up a mountain of dazzling foam, shows his
pace to the distance of seven miles or more. In
those moments, the torn, enraged waves he
shakes off, seem his mane. . . ."
Here, sea and whale become one, the ocean
as a kingdom with leviathan as one of its ruling
presences. Few of Nature's dramas, for Melville,
ever matched the sight of a Sperm Whale rising
from out of the sea's very depths.
But Melville knew the sea to have a myriad
of quite other incarnations. It could also be a place
of rapacity, of warring and predatory species and
none more so than the shark. With just the right
touch of gallows humour, he describes how
sharks will rip into the flesh of a captured whale:
". . . thousands of sharks, swarming around
the dead leviathan, smackingly feasted on its fat¬
ness. The few sleepers below in their bunks were
often startled by the sharp slapping of their tails
against the hull, within a few inches of the
sleepers' hearts. Peering over the side you could
just see them (as before you heard them) wal¬
lowing in the sullen, black waters, and turning
over on their backs as they scooped out huge
globular pieces of the whale of the bigness of a
human head. . . ."
In contrast, in a chapter appropriately called
"The Grand Armada", Melville depicts the sea
as wonderfully feminine and maternal, an arena
for birth as much as death. He describes a whale-
boat which inadvertently has steered into a school
of newly born whales and their mothers:
"But far between this wondrous world upon
the surface, another and still stranger world met
our eyes as we gazed over the side. For, suspended
in those watery vaults, floated the forms of the
nursing mothers of the whales, and those that by
their enormous girth seemed shortly to become
mothers. The lake, as I have hinted, was to a con¬
siderable depth exceedingly transparent; and as
human infants while suckling will calmly and fix¬
edly gaze away from the breast, as if leading two
different lives at the time . . . even so did the
young of these whales seem looking up towards
us, but not at us. . . ."
At the heart of the engaging peace and beauty
of this scene is Melville's recognition that
however we may view the sea, it always retains
its own way of being. Hence the infant whales
look towards, but not at, their human observers.
FORBIDDEN SEAS
As, too, the Pequod travels ever closer towards
destruction, Melville undertakes an extensive
survey of every aspect of whale life. He takes a
positive pleasure in playing the self-appointed role
of cetologist, supplying lists, systems of categori¬
zation, quotations and fables from a multitude
of sourcesand not least from legendary explorers '
like Thomas Cook and Charles Darwin. He
proves just as alert in describing dolphins, por¬
poises, walruses, brit, crustácea, seabirds, and the
huge floating colonies of algae and seaweed. It is
almost as if he wants to drive home the vital,
incalculable abundance of the seas and their func¬
tion as repositories, places of rebirth and con¬
tinuity. What is more, if ever a book cautioned
against ecological arrogance, it is Moby Dick. In
our own nuclear age, in which global warming
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
and pollution have become everyday facts,
Melville's story of Ahab's monomania and of a
technology which seeks to maim or even destroy
one of creation's supreme creatures could not
offer a timelier warning.
Yet rooted in fact as they are, Melville's
accounts of the sea and its creatures are also inter¬
spersed with flights of speculation and
philosophy. From the outset, Ishmael, the nar¬
rator, makes no secret of the matter. Contem¬
plating his own going to sea, he declares "Yes,
as every one knows, meditation and water are
wedded for ever". He speaks of the great seas as
"watery prairies" which arouse nothing less than
"mystical vibrations". "Noah's flood", he muses
at a later point, "is not yet subsided; two thirds
of the world it still covers". And with an eye to
the sea as a source of endlessly proliferating myth
and ritual, he invokes two of the most ancient
of world cultures:
"Why did the old Persians hold the sea holy?
Why did the Greeks give it a separate deity, and
make him the own brother of Jove? Surely all
this is not without meaning. And still deeper the
meaning of that story of Narcissus, who because
he could not grasp the tormenting, mild image
he saw in the fountain, plunged into it and was
drowned. But that same image, we ourselves see
in all rivers and oceans. It is the image of the
ungraspable phantom of life; and this is the key
to it all."
In passages like this, Moby Dick confirms how
Melville writes both a sea-story, one of the
greatest, yet also something infinitely more ambi¬
tious. The Pequod's "voyage-out", in another of
his phrases, may well take us literally, exhilarat-
ingly, into an Atlantic or Pacific. But it also takes
us into matching other seas, "forbidden seas" as
Ishmael calls them. These are the seas which exist
within us and where the very first and last of all
meanings might be encountered.
The Wreck of the Minotaur,
by the English painter J.M.W.
Turner (1775-1851).
The Tempest
Ariel's song
Full fathom five thy father lies,
Of his bones are coral made:
Those are pearls that were his eyes.
Nothing of him that doth fade,
But doth suffer a sea-change
Into something rich and strange. . .
Sea-nymphs hourly ring his knell.
BURTHEN
Ding-dong.
ARIEL
Hark! now I hear them
Ding-dong bell.
William Shakespeare (1564-1616)
English dramatist and poet
The Tempest
A. ROBERT LEE,
of the United Kingdom,
teaches American Literature at
the University of Kent at
Canterbury. He is editor of an
edition of Moby Dick
(Everyman Library, 1975) and
of 12 volumes in a "Critical
Studies" series published by
Vision Press (London), the
most recent of which are
devoted to Herman Melville
(1984), Edgar Allan Poe (1986)
and William Faulkner (1990). 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
étions on the ocean
by Bisabeth Mam Borgese
50
SOME human attitudes towards the
ocean are universal and timeless
almost like the ocean itself. Whether
they originated in one place and spread
from there into all cultures, or whether
they were born identical, in different
places, settings, and times, we do not
know.
However this may be, human beings
have always regarded the sea as the origin
of all things. In virtually all mythologies
of the world, water is given primacy over
the other elements. It was the first thing,
after which came all others. To the
Greeks as to the Aztecs, even the gods
were "born of water". Myths of creation,
from Peru and Mexico to North
America, India and Scandinavia, depict
the Earth as being created from the sea,
and life as evolving from the sea.
A second univeral perception of the
sea is the perception of ambiguity. The sea
is seen as a giver of life and a taker of life:
an element of calm and beauty, of physical
and spiritual nourishment, a conveyor of
wealth and power, a road to new lands, to
new knowledge, a medium of communi¬
cation. At the same time, however, it
separates lands and their peoples. It
remains mysterious, unfathomable and
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
irrational. In its wrath, with its storms and
floods, it destroys wealth and power. It
drowns and kills life. It is horrible to
behold, generating fear, bereavement and
mourning. The Great Flood, exter¬
minating a humankind at odds with
nature and its laws, is a universally recur¬
rent myth of doom and damnation.
Other perceptions, though rooted in
these universal ones, are more closely
linked to specific cultures. In the
northern, terrestrial hemisphere, for
instance, we tend to think of the oceans,
and especially the seabed, as an extension
of the landmass. In the southern, aquatic
hemisphere, people living in island states
think of the land as a continuation of the
water mass, the most important part of
their environment. The Western image
of the oceans is as complex as the Western
self-image. The souls of Westerners are
mirrored in the ocean, in its very
ambiguity between creation and destruc¬
tion, good and evil.
'HE WHO RULES THE SEA,
RULES THE LAND'
The role the world ocean has played in
the evolution of Western culture is indeed
enormous.
Since the Stone Age fisheries have
constituted the basis of the economies of
coastal communities. For fisheries to be
successful, ships had to be built, and this
encouraged the development of science,
technology, exploration, trade and naval
power. The power and influence of the
Hanseatic League, the medieval federa¬
tion of north German cities, was based
on their maritime skills. With its variants
in many other languages, the expression
"He who rules the sea, rules the land"
has been conventional wisdom, and naval
battles have decided peoples' destinies
from Greek Antiquity to modern times.
Western culture thrived on its
overseas discoveries and conquests, based
on sea power. It has seen the ocean as a
great educator, nursing a love for freedom
in seafaring people. Republics are the cre¬
ation of maritime peoples; tyranny was
born inland. In his Philosophie des Rechts
(Philosophy of Law), the philosopher
Hegel compares the role of the seas in
industrial societies with the role of the
Opposite page above, Rooms by the sea
(1951), oil on canvas bv the American painter
Edward Hopper.
Right, Noah's Ark (1731), an engraving
by the German artist Johan Andreas Pfeffel
the Younger.
earth in agricultural, less developed,
societies.
Oceans, storms and waves; ships and
sailors; fishermen, mermaids and sea
monsters have filled the pages of our liter¬
ature, the canvasses of our painters, and
the scores of our music. Occidental music
is indeed the art form most suited to cap¬
ture the essence of the sea, the playing of
silvery ripples and the crashing of surf.
The swelling of storms and their exhaus¬
tion find expression in crescendo and
decrescendo. The rolling of waves and
their eternal cadences are readily trans¬
lated into the measures of musical time.
The multiple layers of ocean space, from
the mysterious seafloor through sub¬
merged waves and submarine rivers to the
bobbing, scintillating surface can be cap¬
tured in harmony and counterpoint, its
flux in time reflected in the duration of
horizontal, melodic development.
FARMING THE SEA
Today the ocean has become our "last
frontier". Penetrated ever deeper by the
industrial revolution, its immensity is
shrinking, yielding to ever more rapid
and efficient means of communication. Its
wilderness, where humans used to hunt
and gather at their own risk, is being
transformed into farms and mines, just as
terrestrial wilderness has been trans¬
formed over the past 10,000 years.
Fishing from the wild is being over-
I \i) I. M
< «I Mm,i|i\IIIy » -
Corvu» c\ ol.nis
I ";>tuIiT\Mn|i'>(.,.iiviii i...:
jpirr iinr-Mii-nniiV i*lrtBr!
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
52
taken by sea farming and aquaculture,
which introduce human intervention
and, potentially, genetic engineering, into
the life cycle of every commercially
fished species. Chemicals, pharmaceu¬
ticals, energy, metals and minerals are
extracted and produced from the seas,
while the marine sciences are trans¬
forming concepts of the genesis of our
planet. They have demonstrated that con¬
tinents are drifting, and oceans are born,
made and remade through volcanic
masses welling up from mid-ocean rifts,
expanding the seafloor and forcing con¬
tinents apart, while other oceans die, their
floors devoured by deep trenches, and
continents clash, their landmasses forced
up into mountains.
Strange creatures have been disco¬
vered in recent years, deep down on the
seafloor where all this activity takes place,
where volcanoes spew matter from the
core of the Earth and the water reaches
temperatures too high to support life as
we know it. There colonies of red-
crowned tubeworms, white crabs and
giant clams are thriving, not on the basis
of photosynthesis like all other known
forms of life on Earth, but through
chemosynthesis in a symbiotic relation¬
ship with bacteria capable of converting
volcanic sulphur into energy and body
mass. Life on other planets may sustain
itself in this way, and it may possibly
have been the first life system on our
planet, the one from which all other
systems evolved.
THE MIRROR OF THE OCEAN
What do contemporary Westerners
project onto the mirror of this new kind
of ocean? What do they discover about
themselves?
Perhaps: that science and mystery are
not zero-sum values, such that one
decreases as the other grows. Western
science may be the greatest of all sciences,
but while spaces are indeed shrinking, the
mystery of the sea remains as deep as it
ever was. The more we know, the more
we know how little we know. And some
of our science, at least, may make us
relive old myths in new clothes: universal
myths of genesis and Leviathans and
Great Floods.
Perhaps: that we still feel awe and
love and fear faced by the power and the
beauty of the sea, just as we always did;
that we yearn for its healing and dan¬
gerous elementariness, for its purity as an
escape from the sophistication and cor¬
ruption of industrial city life, just as we
yearn for the awesomeness and purity of
Leviathan (1908)
by the English artist
Arthur Rackham.
ELISABETH MANN BORGESE,
of Canada, is professor of
political science at Dalhousie
University, Halifax, Nova
Scotia, and chairman of the
Planning Council of the
International Ocean Institute,
Malta. She has written many
articles on the law of the sea
and on ocean management
and several books, including
The Mines of Neptune (1983).
Her Ocean Frontiers (with a
preface by Federico Mayor)
and Chairworm and
Supershark, a book about the
oceans "for children aged 8 to
80", will be published in 1992.
the high mountains and their eternal
snowsfrozen waves; that we yearn to
encompass it in our art, our music; that
we long for its integrity, the unity of all
life in nature, in the cyclic rhythm of
becoming, being and passing.
And then, perhaps, a cloud moves
across the Sun and the water darkens,
reflecting a different image of ourselves:
harvesters of fish, of oil measured in
tonnes. We see wave and tide power
translated into dollars and cents; ports
and harbours and trading ships; satellite
guided fleets and navies; the scum and
foulness from outfall pipes and river
mouths continually streaming in.
We feel greed, but we feel shame and
fear: fear of our own destructive power
as much as the ocean's. Greed and love,
the irrationally rational, are clashing in
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
our minds. Do we want Development, or
do we want Environment?
Western culture has been programmed
with an Either-Or writ large. Good or
evil. Ego or other. Egotism or altruism.
Mine or yours. Nationalism or interna¬
tionalism. It is easy to say but hard to see
that these might be mutually dependent,
be considered as a whole.
In the case of the oceans we will have
to learn to see it. For there, beneath our
eyes, everything flows, everything
interacts with everything else; boundaries
are fictitious, and neither sovereignty nor
ownership holds solutions. What is mine
is dependent on you; what is yours is
dependent on me. If we want to get things
done, we have to do them together, across
sectoral uses, across fictitious geographic
boundaries, or we cannot do them at all.
Development depends on conservation.
Without conservation it simply cannot
happen. Economics becomes part of
ecology; culture, part of nature; the
human being, part of the animal family.
The flowing ocean environment reveals
these facts, while the apparently solid
state of terra firma could maintain in us
the illusion of separateness and indepen¬
dence, superiority and domination.
Other cultures have stayed closer to
a unitary world-view. In the West we had
to return to the sea to regain it, and thus
it is no accident that, in the evolution of
Western culture, the search for a new
world order starts from the Law of the
Sea, a term which in itself symbolizes the
unity between culture (Law) and Nature
(Sea) and all that flows from it.
A metaphysical dream
Infinity! My love for the sea, whose
enormous simplicity I have always
preferred to the pretentious
multifariousness of the mountains
my love for the sea is as old as my
love for sleep, and I am fully aware
of the common root of these two
sympathies.
I have within myself much that
is Indian: a great deal of inert and
heavy longing for that form of
perfection, called "Nirvana", or
nothingness, and even though I am
an artist, I have a rather unartistic
inclination towards eternity. . . .
The sea is not landscape. It is the
experience of eternity, of nothingness
and death: a metaphysical dream.
Thomas Mann (1875-1955)
German writer
The United Nations Convention
on the Law of the Sea
The adoption in 1982 of the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea was
a milestone in the history of international relations. The Convention contains the first
comprehensive, binding, enforceable international environmental law. It is the first legal
instrument effectively to integrate environment and development within the concept
of sustainable development. It is also the first instrument to provide for a system of
mandatory, binding settlement of disputes arising not only from environmental issues
but from all other issues relating to the uses of seas and oceans.
The Convention is based on two fundamental concepts: the concept of the Common
Heritage of Mankind and the idea that the problems of ocean space are closely
interelated and need to be considered as a whole.
The concept of the Common Heritage of Mankind, applicable to areas (such as
the deep seabed or outer space), to resources (such as minerals and metals), and to
abstractions (such as science and technology) subsumes four other fundamental
concepts:
Development: The Common Heritage of Mankind must be developed for the benefit
of mankind as a whole.
Equity: In the distribution of benefits, particular consideration must be given to
the poor and disadvantaged.
Environment: The Common Heritage of Mankind must be developed with due
consideration for the conservation of the environment and its resources. Mankind
includes present and future generations, which have an equal right to share in the
common heritage.
Security: The Common Heritage of Mankind is reserved for exclusively peaceful
purposes.
The incorporation of the Common Heritage concept in the UN Convention is of
such far-reaching cultural importance that we have not even begun to fathom all its
implications.
The Common Heritage of Mankind implies a new economic theory, based on a
new concept of ownership, or rather non-ownership, which may provide a point of
convergence in a common effort to meet the environmental challenge.
The economics and philosophy of the common heritage provide a logical basis
for common and comprehensive security. Common, since in the contemporary world
the security of one can no longer be founded on the insecurity of the other and the
security of each must be the security of all. Comprehensive, since in the contemporary
world, security comprises economic and environmental security as well as military
security.
The idea that the problems of ocean space are closely interrelated and should
be considered as a whole has important consequences. For while the problems arising
from the different uses of the oceans interact, the uses of the sea in turn interact
with terrestrial activities. Much of the world's food comes from the sea; seabed metals
and minerals are bought and sold on the world commodity market; offshore oil is used
for the same purposes as onshore oil; the marine environment is part of the biosphere;
the naval arms race cannot be dissociated from the general question of the arms race
and disarmament.
An integrated approach to other world problems is just as necessary as it is for
the management of ocean affairs. Land boundaries are becoming porous, as production
systems, financial systems, communication and information systems move unhindered
across them.
In the case of the oceans this interrelationship was more obvious. This is why the
Law of the Sea is the most advanced legal instrument and institutional framework for
the integration of Environment and Development. Let us try to learn the lessons the
ocean has taught us and apply them to wider global concerns. E.M.B.
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
54
A rouná-np of nautical
supentitions and rituals
Vn the bridge of yachts bobbing at berth in
their harbours a common sight is a no entry sign
with the picture of a shoe placed over it. The mes¬
sage is clear and is always heeded by those who
are lucky enough to board one of these graceful
craft: first remove your shoes. If you are so
curious as to ask questions about this form of
courtesy, you tend to receive vague replies to the
effect that the high heels worn by women would
damage the deck or that the dust picked up from
the quay would make the boat dirty.
But apart from the fact that the decks of these
noble vessels are made of teak, which is one of
the hardest woods there is, we can be sure that
their owners would not take the same precautions
to protect the sitting-room floors of their houses.
Even stranger, this prohibition does not concern
working shoes but only town shoes. One's
Sunday best in fact.
One of my friends, a Sicilian fisherman, was
talking to me one day about an uncle of his, who
was a great believer in traditions. "It was a cold
February morning", he said, "and we had gone
off to fish. It was still dark. In the first glow of
dawn my uncle saw that I had kept my shoes on
my feet. Furious, he ordered me to take them off
and, after attaching them to a rope, threw them
into the water where they remained in tow". He
was a kind man and, knowing that his thought¬
less nephew possessed only one pair, this was his
compromise solution'.
This prohibition is widespread in the North
Sea, among the deep-sea fishermen of England and
Scotlandbut the Malay fishermen of Penang
take the same curious precaution. Where yachting
circles are concerned, it may have originated in
England along with the practice of sailing as a
sport, assuming along the Mediterranean coast
and probably elsewhere this pseudo-rational
veneer that we have seen.
What is the link between shoes and boats?
To understand, we perhaps need to refer to
another superstition, associated this time with a
particular accident of birth.
Some babies are born with the amnion or
inner membrane which enclosed the foetus before
birthknown as a caulcovering their heads. All
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
A symbolic sheepskin
on the prow of a Portuguese
fishing boat.
over the world numerous beliefs have been
attached to this. Generally, the caul is thought
to possess extraordinary qualities and it is not by
chance that, in northern Europe and Sicily alike,
it is reputed to be a preservative against drowning.
Being born with a caul on one's head is a sign
of good luck.
"Good" births are traditionally thought to
be those where the child passes through the
amniotic waters head first. "Bad" ones are those
known as breech births, where the feet appear
first, making for a difficult delivery which, in
former times, was likely to result in the death of
the mother or the child.
While birth is a voyage through the salt
waters of the maternal womb, death is thought
of in mythological and religious belief as a
journey to the, beyond. In both cases, there are
certain rules. It is the custom for the dead to leave
"feet first" and, in keeping with the solemnity
of the occasion, they depart from from the world
of the living in their best clothesand in their
best shoes.
This then is the explanation. He who,
wearing such shoes, undertakes a sea voyage in
a boat will be accompanied by the spectre of
death, in a world where danger looms on every
side.
THE NECESSARY SACRILEGE
Since earliest times in many civilizations, water
and the sea have been linked to the nether world
of death, the abyss and the primal chaos to which
all creatures return before being reborn to other
lives.
Crossing the water by means of a man-made
device (a bridge or boat) involves a direct con¬
tact with the element that separates life from
death, which also serves as a bridge into the
beyond. This journey into the next life is depicted
in many myths, from that of the Greeks' ferryman
Charon to the Mesopotamian, Egyptian or Scan¬
dinavian legends. In order to commit the
sacrilegealbeit a necessary oneof crossing the
water, one is required to take a number of sym¬
bolic precautions.
For the Romans, the pontifex maximus, the
"bridgemaker", represented the supreme religious
authority, vested in Julius Caesar when he com¬
manded a bridge to be built over the Rhine. The
annual ceremony of casting a doll into the Tiber
from the Sublicius bridge, the oldest bridge in
Rome, served to remind the ancients of the
human sacrifices needed to build it.
In more recent times, the cross thrown by
the Greek Orthodox bishop into the sea on 55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
Above, boat in Syracuse
(Italy).
Top, fishing boats In Bangkok
(Thailand).
56
Twelfth Night in order to bless it and the act per¬
formed by the Doge of Venice in marrying the
sea with his city and casting a ring into the waters
may be understood as a ritualized means of
obtaining redemption.
This sheds an interesting light on Christ's
walking on the water and on the feat accom¬
plished by Moses, for whom the Red Sea divided,
enabling him and his people to cross it on foot.
Many are the heroes and saints who have thus
shown sacrilege to be necessary and reparation
possible.
THE BAPTISM OF BLOOD
The ritual often involves a blood sacrifice,
whether real or symbolicthat of Iphigenia, who
in Greek mythology has to be sacrificed by her
father Agamemnon so that the Greek fleet can
sail to Troy, or that of the young Persian who
has his throat cut in the bows of the Greek flag¬
ship before the battle of Salamis.
From the the Anatolian coast all the way to
Alexandria in Egypt, a sheep is always sacrificed
in the bows of a boat, thus perpetuating the
ancient Mediterranean ritual and the symbolic
substitution, dating back to Abraham, of a lamb
for a human being. This is indirectly testified to
by Homer's crimson-cheeked ships and the sheep¬
skins hanging from the stems of fishermen's
boats, from the eastern Mediterranean to
Portugal.
Even today, ships are "baptised", from the
smallest boat to the giant oil tanker. Why is this?
A Sicilian fisherman told me one day: "Do you
not baptise your son and give him a name? It's
the same for boats. They are Christian creatures"
(In Sicily, "Christian" and "man" are syn¬
onymous).
There are many practices connected with the
building and launching of boats. All reflect sym¬
bolically the idea that a ceremony is necessary
to give life to and purify the inert matter, and
to protect the seafarer and the members of his
family. Greek and Italian shipowners often call
their ships after one of their nearest and dearest
or after a saint or a hero, thereby suggesting that
the vessel is part of a larger spiritual family.
BOATS WITH EYES
Whether blood is shed or is replaced by wine-
champagne at modern launching ceremonies
the sacrificial rite is always performed in order
to give life to the ship.
In Laos, "eyes" are given to boats in a
ceremony which involves the feigned sacrifice of
a maiden and the fixing of her eyes on the prow.
The prows of dugout canoes in Bali depict the
head of Makara, the mythical elephant-fish.
Viking drakkars displayed a dragon's head and
Greek and Roman ships looked at the waves
through the eyes of boars or dolphins. The figure¬
heads of the great Western sailing ships fixed their
hieratic gaze on the waters, and even today junks
on the China Sea have eyes.
Considering then that ships are living, almost
human things, it is natural that they should be
threatened by the same dangers as members of
the crew. They have to be protected from mis¬
fortune by means of various symbolic signs which
might appear to be fulfilling no more than a
decorative function.
In the archipelagoes of Melanesia, as in the
Trobriand Islands for instance, the pirogues that
participate in gift exchange ceremonies (kula) bear
elaborate sculptures on their prows representing
the mythical hero Manikiniki in the form of the
life-giving Serpent. The serpent-hero and the-
pirogue become a single creature. In order to
acquire the powers needed to achieve this union,
the sculptor has to serve an apprenticeship that
may last for more than twenty years.
On the Mediterranean shore, when the boats
belonging to a particular village are painted in
green or red monochrome, one can be sure that
the effigy of that village's patron saint in the
church will be dressed in the same colour. In
another village, where blue predominates, the
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
Above, the head of the
mythical elephant-fish Makara
adorns the prow of a Balinese
canoe.
Left above, a boat In
mourning; below, prow of a
boat In Ghana.
PIER GIOVANNI D'AYALA,
a staff member of UNESCO's
Division of Ecological Sciences
and a former researcher at the
Ecole des Hautes Etudes en
Sciences Sociales in Paris has
long been interested in the
lore and symbolic beliefs of
Mediterranean fishermen.
Among his recent publications
are Carnavals et Mascarades
(with Martine Boiteux. 1988
Paris).
local boats will be placed under the protection
of the Virgin who is venerated here and who
wears a blue wrap. A boat may also be painted
in honour of a more personal and familiar saint.
If someone has made a vow to St. Francesco di
Paola, his boat will have a brown stripe added
to it, the same colour as the cowl worn by the
hermit saint, who according to legend crossed the
Strait of Messina on his coat. St. Francesco,
incidentally, is the patron saint of the Italian mer¬
chant navy.
IN SEARCH OF SALVATION
The sailor who at the risk of his life has embarked
upon the sacrilegious voyage is required to give
thanks when he again sets foot on dry land. All
Greek schoolchildren are familiar with the story
of the prophet Elijah, whom seafarers, both
Christian and Muslim, hold in undying devotion.
Legend has it that the holy prophet was a sailor.
"One day, tired of confronting the danger of the
waves, he took an oar on his shoulder and walked
so far up into the mountains, so far away from
the sea, that a peasant who knew nothing of boats
mistook the oar for a flail. There the holy
prophet planted his oar, on which the green
leaves of an oak tree grew, and made his abode."
A white chapel graces many of the Greek
islands, built on the highest point and dedicated
to the prophet Elijah by some sailor grateful for
having survived the perils of the sea. Even if this
custom seems to bear Homeric echoes, it is a fact
that holy shrines dedicated to the sea are very fre¬
quently situated on a hill inland. Notre-Dame de
la Garde in Marseilles and Genoa, Our Lady of
Montserrat in Barcelona, Our Lady of Guadalupe
in Mexico City and other ancient or recent sanc¬
tuaries thus bear witness to the seafarer's secret
need to remove himself from the source of
danger, the sea. He accordingly sets out, often
barefoot, on a pilgrimage to the place of salva¬
tion, the landmore precisely to the moun¬
tainous heartland.
There the salt water becomes the fresh water
of a well or of a miraculous fountain where the
survivor of a shipwreck washes off the bitter
danger, as is the custom in the Sicilian sanctuary
of the Black Virgin of Tindari, which overlooks
the blue expanse of the Tyrrhenian Sea. There
the votive offeringpicture, model, candle, part
of the riggingis laid at the foot of the holy
effigy. Here lies salvation, in this place away from
the dangers of the everyday world. Here time is
eternal; the time of horror and the night of the
storm are no more.
This journey into the symbolic universe of
humankind must perforce remain incomplete. But
it is only by not rejecting all these beliefs out of
hand on the grounds that they are childish
leftovers from a benighted past that we shall get
any closer to understanding the secret world of
seafarers and to recognizing how much courage
and dignity they need to ply their hard trade.
The "Bag-Noz" {The ghost ship)
Whenever some disaster is about to occur in
the vicinity of the He de Sein, an island off
the coast of Brittany, a ghost ship is seen. . . .
It is called a "bag-noz" (night boat)
because it usually heaves in sight at nightfall
without it being possible to say where it is
coming from nor where it is going. For it
suddenly vanishes just when one is looking at
it, then reappears a moment later somewhere
else on the horizon. Onward it plies in full
sail, Jolly Roger at half-mast. . . .
Its crewwhich must be largewail and
shout as though calling for help, with piteous,
heart-rending cries. But as soon as anyone
seems to want to draw near, the vision fades,
and the voices themselves become so distant
that one can no longer tell whether they are
calling from the depths of the sea or from the
depths of the sky.
It is related however that one night a
pilot from the island managed to sail
sufficiently close to the ghost ship to see that
there was nobody on board except a
helmsman at the stem. The pilot called out
to the man:
"Can I do anything for you? Do you
want a tow?"
Instead of answering, the man swung the
tiller round and the boat disappeared.
If the pilot had had the presence of mind
to say "Requiescant in pace""', he would
have saved the whole boatful of dead sailors.
*"May they rest in peace", a Christian formula on
behalf of the dead.
Anatole Le Braz (1859-1926)
French writer
La legende de la mort en Basse-Bretagne (1893)
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
ä«i£
"-"Vi.-.;
-
i&S&r.
av: '
; '
v.v
. -Jt '«.fTS.
... -Î,Fi
The sea is a treasure-house which
belongs to all mankind. The marine
sciences have revealed the crucial role
played by the oceans in regulating
the Earth's climate and have unlocked
many secrets of the deep. A source of
wealth and perhaps potentially
habitable, the marine environment is
fragile and must be protected if it is
to continue to sustain human life
and inspire the imagination.
A sántist
Building a boat, Japanese
print of the late Kano school
(15th- 19th century).
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
has at the sea
MANKIND lives beside the sea.
Over 145 of the world's nations
are coastal or island states, and
the majority of the world's population
lives within 200 kilometres of a coastline.
Today the use of coastal space for living,
trade, resources development and recre¬
ation is increasingly intensive. In the
United States, for example, even though
there is abundant space inland, it is fore¬
cast that 80 per cent of the population
will be living within 80 kilometres of the
sea by the year 2000.
In addition to this migration to
coastal areas, many works of literature
and music testify to mankind's emotional
link to the sea. Intellectually, however,
the tie is much weaker. Although since
the beginning of recorded history the sea
has been used as a highway between
different lands, this vast region has never
been explored with the same urgency or
thoroughness as the land. The world
ocean is truly the last geographic frontier
on Earth.
Why should this be so? Perhaps one
reason is that until the twentieth century
there was little demand for scientific
studies on the sea, and in any case the
means did not exist for putting man into
the sea to make direct observations. Even
today, marine exploration does not arouse
as much public interest as the exploration
of space. The rhythm of events tends to
be slow, the events themselves are not of
great visual interest, and they do not
receive wide publicity. And yet the world
ocean has a major influence on our lives.
THE EARLY DAYS OF OCEANOGRAPHY
It is widely agreed that oceanography
began as an interdisciplinary science 115
years ago, when the British HMS
Challenger expedition (1872-1876) left 59
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
England on a round-the-world scientific
voyage. The team that wrote up the
results of the three-and-a-half-year expe¬
dition formed the first international net¬
work of marine scientists. The fifty-
volume set of reports and the extensive
sample collections taken by the expedi¬
tion are still being studied by marine
scientists today.
It was also during the 1870s that the
first marine laboratory was established,
at Naples, Italy. The Marine Biological
Laboratory was founded at Woods Hole,
Massachusetts, in 1893, and by the turn
of the century océanographie studies were
being conducted in many places
throughout the world. In 1902 the Inter¬
national Council for the Exploration of
the Seas, the first intergovernmental
organization concerned with marine
science, was founded in Denmark.
Most maritime research before the
beginning of World War I was in marine
biology relating to fisheries development.
Before then, few samples of marine
minerals were taken from the sea, and the
study of ocean currents and water depths
was mostly confined to improving the
safety of navigation in shallow coastal
waters. However, the tragic loss of the
steamship Titanic in 1912 set in motion
60
Where do the seas
come from?
Some think that the sea is a vestige
of the primal humidity of which the
most substantial and most essential
part evaporated under the effect of
the heat, while the rest changed into
the sea. Others maintain that, all the
original humidity having been
subjected to the fire of the Sun's
revolutions, which removed
therefrom all that was pure, the
residue became salinity and
bitterness. . . . Yet others believe that
the sea is that which escaped, through
the density of its constitution, from
the Earth's filtering of the aqueous
humidity, exactly like fresh water
which, mixed with ash then filtered,
ceases to be fresh and becomes salty.
. . It is sometimes reckoned that
the sea is a sweat which the Earth
secretes beneath the action of the Sun,
which heats it by turning constantly
around it. . . .
Al Mas'udi (C.900-C.965 AD)
Arab traveller and encyclopaedist
(The Meadows of Gold and Mines of Gems)
studies of icebergs, their formation and
drift trajectories. These studies still con¬
tinue, though Earth-orbiting satellites
make the tracking safer and more
accurate.
World War I stimulated the need for
more information about the oceans, espe¬
cially to aid the detection and destruction
of enemy submarines. Since the primary
means of submarine detection was sound
propagation through the water, this need
promoted the advancement of physical
oceanography and the field of marine
acoustics was born. During World War
II more research was carried out in this
field and by the end of the war effective
sonar (sound navigation and ranging)
systems were installed on both subma¬
rines and surface ships. The scene was set
for a major expansion in the field of
oceanography in the postwar years.
PREDICTIVE INFORMATION,
THE KEY TO EFFECTIVE USE
OF THE SEA
The primary product of marine scientific
research is predictive information that
will eventually enable the sea to be used
in ways that are beneficial to mankind.
Without the supporting foundations of
excellent science and technology, exploi¬
tation of the ocean's resources is wasteful,
economically inefficient and potentially
harmful to the marine environment. Lack
of scientific information is bound to con¬
tribute to misuse of the world ocean in
such areas as overfishing, waste disposal,
and coastal and open ocean pollution.
Many of the uses of the ocean are
commercial, but not all. Public safety is
also important. For example, accurate
advanced warning and movement predic¬
tion of marine weather systems such as
typhoons and hurricanes can save thou¬
sands of lives and billions of dollars.
Today the world community is con¬
cerned about the complex issue of global
warming and a consequent gradual rise of
sea level. We need to know more about
how the oceans interact with and
influence the Earth's atmosphere and its
quality. At present we may not be com¬
pletely certain that accelerated burning of
fossil fuels since the Industrial Revolution
has caused these problems. But we cannot
afford not to do the necessary science that
will enable us to know for sure. This
work will require an unprecedented inter¬
national pooling of scientists and research
assets. No one nation can do it alone.
THE TOOLS
OF THE MARINE SCIENTIST
In seeking the answers to these and other
questions, modern oceanographers use a
3-tier family of macroscale, mesoscale and
microscale "platforms" and techniques to
study the oceans. Macroscale platforms
are remote-sensing systems such as air¬
craft, balloons and Earth-orbiting
spacecraft which provide the "big pic¬
ture", permitting scientists to observe
large areas of the ocean surface. Satellites
in particular provide the only means of
measuring air-sea interaction processes in
real time.
The principal mesoscale platform is
the ship, which is the primary and gener-
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
ally the cheapest means of obtaining data
at sea by means of long-term research
programmes using relatively large teams
of scientists and large quantities of
instrumentation. In recent years, sophisti¬
cated ship designs, high-powered on¬
board computer capabilities and new
sensor technologies have made the
modern research ship several times more
productive than the vessels of only
twenty years ago. Ship platforms are also
remote sensing systems. They work at the
air-ocean interface and make observations
and take samples through the use of
lowered mechanical "eyes and hands".
The last, microscale category of plat¬
forms puts the trained mind and eye of
the scientist into the sea. For about $1,000
a scientist diver can be fully equipped
with the self-contained underwater
breathing apparatus (SCUBA) and ena¬
bled to operate at depths of about 40
metres. This research technique is today
used by marine scientists throughout the
world, including under ice in polar
regions. At depths greater than 40 metres,
the marine scientist will use a submer¬
sible. Using manned submersibles,
oceanographers can descend to depths of
up to 6,000 metres to make direct, in situ
observations and measurements.
Since they were first developed in the
1950s, over 150 manned submersibles
have been built. Today about twenty-
four are being used for marine science
support in eleven countries. Currently
discussions are going on in several coun¬
tries about building a new generation of
manned submersibles capable of diving
into the deepest parts of the oceans. A
Above, the submarine Caya, with Its
three-person crew, can dive as deep
as 300 m. It is used for Industrial or
scientific purposes.
Left, a Soviet océanographie vessel In
the port of Istanbul (Turkey).
Right, satellite Images enable
scientists to track the Gulf Stream
with precision.
DON WALSH,
of the United States, is a specialist in
oceanography, marine «ngineeiing and
underwater technology. He served in
the U.S. Navy for 24 years and is the
author of many articles and books on
marine subjects. 61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
Harvesting salt from Lake Rose (Senegal).
Canadian company has also proposed
building a commercial, nuclear-powered
submarine which would be capable of
missions of up to eighty days at depths
up to 1,000 metres.
Unmanned submersibles have also
been developed for submerged scientific
operations. The most common type is the
remotely operated vehicle (ROV), which
is controlled from the surface through a
long tether cable. ROVs can be fitted
with television and still cameras, mechan¬
ical arms for work tasks, and a variety of
instrumentation sensors depending on the
scientific mission.
The vehicle is controlled from a sur
face vessel using television pictures from
the ROV as well as instrument readings
for depth and compass heading. Almost
a thousand ROVs have been built since
their introduction in the late 1960s, but
only a few have been used for marine
science. In the past five years, however,
several have been acquired by marine
research organizations.
FUTURE EXPECTATIONS
The distance between scientific investiga¬
tion of the ocean and commercial prac¬
tice is great. At every step of the way
there are major problems which need to
be addressed to ensure that the people of
our planet can enjoy maximum use of the
resources of the ocean. One of these
problems is lack of public interest and
thus investment in marine science and
technology. Because marine science
produces results over the long term, it is
difficult for short-term governments to be
concerned about it. Since modern marine
science calls for international co¬
operation, the political difficulties
become even more complex. Can ocean
science prevail in this context? Clearly,
the answer is that it must.
Some facts and figures
The ocean covers nearly two-thirds of the
Earth's surface, an area of 361,000,000 square
kilometres. The Pacific Ocean alone covers
more of the Earth's surface than all the land
masses put together.
Two-thirds of the Earth's land masses are
north of the equator. The southern hemisphere
is often called "the ocean hemisphere".
The average depth of the ocean is 3,730
metres. Its greatest depth is nearly 11,000
metres, but only 2 per cent of the sea floor is
deeper than 6,000 metres.
A specimen of Zooplankton. -
The total volume of the sea is over 1.5 bil¬
lion cubic kilometres. The oceans contain over
86 per cent of all the water on our planet.
The water in the oceans has been there for
about 3 billion years. It has been thoroughly
mixed more than a million times. As a result,
this well-mixed "chemical solution" contains
the same relative proportion of chemical ele¬
ments (salts) no matter where a sample is taken.
Only six elements make up 99 per cent of
the salts in seawater: sodium, calcium, chlorine,
magnesium, potassium and sulphur. The
amount of these elements in a given volume
of seawater may vary from place to place. This
is called "salinity". The average for the world
ocean is 35 grams per kilogram of seawater.
It is estimated that if all salts in the world ocean
were extracted and put on land, the layer would
be 150 metres thick.
Life in the sea begins with photosynthesis
when solar energy is captured by microscopic
plants in the sea, phytoplankton, which are the
first step in the marine food chain. Like terres¬
trial plants, phytoplankton absorb carbon diox¬
ide and release oxygen to the sea. A large por¬
tion of our planet's oxygen is produced from
the sea.
Because seawater rapidly filters out the
penetration of solar energy, most marine life
is found in relatively shallow, upper layers of the
sea. In fact, about 90 per cent of the life in the
sea can be found in the upper 30 metres. The
highest biological productivity exists near coast
lines, where river and other runoff from land
provides a steady supply of nutrients. Even
though these coastal areas represent only
about 15 per cent of the ocean's area, they are
the primary areas for marine life. Essentially,
the rest of the world ocean is thinly populated
and more of a biological desert.
The principal current system of the oceans
is called "wind-driven circulation". Its engine
is the wind that blows across the ocean surface
at a constant velocity and from the same direc¬
tion season after season and year after year.
The motion of the surface waters due to wind
forces is modified by the shape of the ocean
basins and the Earth's rotational motion. This
results in a generalized circulation pattern con¬
sisting of giant circular water movements in
each major ocean. These circulations are called
"gyres". Direction of circulation is clockwise in
the northern hemisphere and counterclockwise
in the southern hemisphere. Major surface cur¬
rents such as the Gulf Stream in the Atlantic
and the Kuroshio in the Pacific are examples
of wind-driven circulation and each is part of
a larger gyre in that ocean basin. These mas¬
sive movements of seawater act as part of our
planet's "air conditioning system". Excess heat
is transported from the tropical regions to the
higher latitudes where there is a heat deficit.
This process helps to keep the average regional
temperatures throughout the planet constant
from year to year.
D.W.
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
The ghost ship
of the Arctic
4M n*
WNE of the world's strangest sea stories is still
unfinished, and looks like remaining so for a long
time, perhaps for ever. This is the story of the
Baychimo, the deserted ghost ship that refuses to
die and still haunts human memory and curiosity.
A fine, trim, solid steel 1,322-ton cargo
steamer owned by the Hudson's Bay Company,
the Baychimo was built in Sweden in 1914. She
was originally used to collect furs from Eskimo
trappers along the Victoria Island coast of
Canada's North-West Territory. With her single
tall funnel, curved bridge and long high prow,
the Baychimo was sturdily built to withstand the
floes and pack-ice of the dangerous northern
waters in which she operated.
She actually pioneered fur trading with the
Eskimo settlements around the Beaufort Sea,
forging her way many times on her 3,200-
David Gunston
kilometre round trip through some of the most
treacherous shipping lanes in the world. Each
year she set out on a regular voyage, always a
tough and difficult one, delivering food, fuel and
other supplies to, and loading pelts from, eight
of the Hudson Bay Company's lonely outposts.
On 6 July 193 1 she left Vancouver, British
Columbia, on such a journey, with skipper John
Cornwell and his crew of thirty-six men. They
On the morning of 22
September 1931 members of
the Baych/mo's crew make a
vain attempt to help their ship
break through ice floes to
open water.
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
expected a hard trip, for all their runs were hard,
but what they did not know was that this was
to be the Baychimo's last manned voyage.
PRISONERS
OF THE PACK-ICE
Day and night, under the misty glow of the never-
setting sun, the Baychimo steamed on eastward.
Eventually they reached the end of their normal
eastward run by the shores of Victoria Island.
With the hold crammed with cargo, the relieved
captain turned the Baychimo about for Van¬
couver.
Unfortunately winter came early that year
to this bleak northern wasteland. Ferocious winds
and deep-freezing conditions brought the dreaded
pack-ice south much quicker than usual. By 30
September only a narrow stretch of open water
remained for the ship to steam through, and on
1 October the ice closed in.
Her engines at stop, she could only move as
the creaking ice willed. She was not far from the
Alaskan village of Barrow, where the company
had permanent huts built ashore. Seeing that a
terrible blizzard was imminent, Cornwell ordered
his men to trudge across the kilometre or so of
ice to shelter in these huts, where they remained
for two days, half-frozen and unable to venture
out.
Then the first extraordinary thing in the Bay¬
chimo's strange story happened. Without warning
the pack-ice loosened and moved away from the
Baychimo's sides, leaving her free to move again.
The crew rushed aboard and for three solid hours
the ship steamed away to the west at full speed.
Disaster seemed to have been narrowly averted.
But once more the ice gripped the little cargo
steamer, and on 8 October a sickening crack her¬
alded the sudden appearance of a deadly black
fault-line in the ice. It actually cracked right across
the patch where some of the crew were playing
football.
Now the ice that had held the ship had
broken away, it began to move slowly but surely
towards the shore. To Cornwell it seemed only
a matter of hours before his rugged little vessel
would be crushed like an empty eggshell. Radio
SOS messages were sent out but these doughty
men hung on in the hope that they and their ship
might be saved. By 15 October their plight
seemed so desperate that the Hudson Bay Com¬
pany sent two aircraft from the base at Nome,
almost 700 kilometres away. Twenty-two of the
Baychimo's crew were rescued, and her skipper
and fourteen men were left behind to wait until
the melting ice released the ship and its precious
64 cargo. They knew they might have to wait as long
as a year, so they built a small shelter on the pack-
ice a short distance from the shore.
Their sojourn proved to be short and
startling, for on the pitch black night of 24
November a hellish blizzard descended, trapping
the men inside their wooden shelter. When at
last the storm abated, they emerged into the
wintry gloom to find that the Baychimo had com¬
pletely vanished beneath mountains of ice over
20 metres high. They searched around as much
as they could, but on failing to find their doomed
ship they came to the conclusion that she had
been broken to pieces in the blizzard and had
sunk.
A GHOST SHIP
They reached the safety of the mainland and pre¬
pared to return home. In a few days, however,
an Eskimo seal-hunter brought the astonishing
news that he had seen their ship some 70
kilometres away to the south-west. Already the
Baychimo had been turned into a ghost ship, a
polar puppet pushed this way and that by the
power of ice, wind and water. The fifteen men
trudged to where the Eskimo led them and, sure
enough, there was the ship.
It was obvious to the captain that the chances
of salvaging his vessel were nil. The ice was not
going to allow it. So the men rescued the more
valuable furs from the hold and reluctantly left
the Baychimo for ever. In due course they were
flown back home.
American planes rescue
the crew of the Ice-locked
Baychimo.
DAVID GUNSTON
is a British free-lance writer
and journalist whose work has
been published in over 40
countries. He has written
widely on the natural world and
is the author of biographies of
Marconi and Faraday.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
Wfi. mt u
As the months went by, the Company's base
in Vancouver received strange reports from
Eskimo sources that their ship had again been
sighted, this time hundreds of kilometres to the
east. On 12 March 1932, a young trapper and
explorer named Leslie Melvin discovered her
while on a journey from Herschel Island to
Nome by dog-team. She was floating inshore
peacefully enough. He managed to board her and
found that many of the furs were still intact in
the hold. Unfortunately, as he was alone and
without much equipment, far from his base in
Alaska, he could do nothing.
Some months went by and a group of wan¬
dering prospectors saw the ship and also managed
to board her. They reported that everything was
in perfect order. In March 1933 the Baychimo
apparently drifted back to roughly the point
where her captain had abandoned her. A group
of some thirty Eskimos saw her floating idly in
the freezing waters and went out in their kayaks,
but no sooner had they clambered aboard than
a terrific storm blew up. They were trapped on
the ghost ship without food for ten days before
they could get away.
ADRIFT IN THE ARCTIC
By August 1933 the Hudson Bay Company knew
that the Baychimo was moving calmly in a north¬
erly direction, but she was still much too far from
civilization to make salvage operations a possi¬
bility. The next visitors were an exploring party
on a schooner. They came across her in July 1934,
and boarded her for a few hours.
By now the legend of the little grey tall-
funnelled ghost ship was well known among the
Arctic Eskimos, many of whom sighted her from
time to time on their travels. By September 1935
she had reached the Alaskan coast, always
managing to avoid the crushing grip of the pack-
ice, always surviving the worst polar storms.
Nature seemed unable to destroy her, but man
was unable to rescue her.
After 1939 the Baychimo was seen scores of
times, mostly by Eskimos but occasionally by
explorers, traders and pilots. Each time she eluded
whatever pursuit was possible, and over the inter¬
vening years she has sailed on crewless and alone.
In March 1962 a small party of Eskimos dis¬
covered the ship again while fishing from their
kayaks. This time she was floating serenely in the
Beaufort Sea near a desolate strip of coastline.
Once again there was no means of capturing her,
so they left the desolate, rusting, but still
uncrushed hulk to drift away into the unknown
once more. The last recorded sighting, again by
Eskimos, was in 1969thirty-eight years after she
was abandoned. But this time she was once more
fast in the pack-ice of the Beaufort Sea between
Icy Cape and Point Barrow.
A representative of the Hudson Bay Com¬
pany told me, at their headquarters in Winnipeg,
that even now they cannot say definitely whether
or not the Baychimo is still afloat.
It is often forgotten
that the sea is ageless;
therein lies its
strength.
Mohamed Dib
Algerian writer
(Qui se souvient de la mer,
Seuil, Paris 1959)
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
The four pilkrs of Neptune's
temple by ¡acques Ferrkr
His breast must have been protected all round with oak and
bronze, who first launched his frail boat on the rough sea. . . .
(Horace, Odes, I, III, 9)
Xhe ocean is the largest expanse on Earth and
the vastest resource available to humankind. It
contains in abundance, in a state of continual
regeneration, the source of life from which the
human race emerged. It inspires the industry of
Homofaber and whets the imagination of Homo
sapiens, stimulating his creative genius and
challenging his spirit of adventure and courage.
The scientific, technological, industrial, economic
and social responses to the ocean's hold on the
human imagination may be grouped under four
headings, each of which corresponds to a dream:
the achievements of the maritime genius (walking
on the sea); the conquest of the abyss (penetrating
the ocean depths); the exploitation of the oceans
(harvesting food from the sea); the new Atlantis
(inhabiting the sea). These are the four great
pillars of Neptune's temple.
The achievements of the
maritime genius
Free man, you will always cherish the sea
(Charles Baudelaire)
The sea has inspired human genius to invent a
host of navigational devices. The Greeks, the
Chinese, the Arabs, the Portuguese, the
Spaniards, the British, the Italians, and the
French, among other peoples, may claim to have
invented the astrolabe, the compass, portulans
and sea charts, the chronometer for calculating
longitudes, the anchor and rigging, the keel and
66 the rudder. The polders of Holland and the
embankments promised for Bangladesh, the artifi¬
cial harbour of Arromanches and the Channel
Tunnel rank with with the lighthouse of Alex¬
andria as Wonders of the World. The Statue of
Liberty in New York harbour and the Colossus
of Rhodes were born of the same spirit of inven¬
tion. Dictionaries in every language abound in
words that designate things and events
experienced, dreamed of and created under the
sway of the sea. However, the ship remains the
most beautiful of these creations.
Many peoples have left the mark of their
genius on the design of ships which have been
the witnesses and often the agents of their des¬
tiny. The history of science and technology,
which forms the infrastructure of the history of
civilizations, is a fresco in which naval pomp and
circumstance play as big a part as they do on the
Bayeux Tapestry. The English poet John Masefield
wrote of a "Quinquireme of Nineveh from dis¬
tant Ophir/Rowing home to haven in sunny
Palestine/With a cargo of ivory". Today, twenty-
seven centuries later, giant oil tankers ply in their
wake.
The strands of legend and history, dream and
reality, have been woven into a rich tapestry of
images by poets, novelists and historians: the
longship of the Argonauts; the barques of Ulysses
and Aeneas; the triremes of Salamis; Polynesian
rafts; the drakkars of Ragnar Lodbrok and Leif
Erikson; the ships of the crusaders; the Santa
Maria of Christopher Columbus; Chinese war
junks; the praus of Malayaancestors of today's
"Sfc
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
Cartoon, below, shows
Jules Verne, the author of
Twenty Thousand Leagues
Under the Sea, investigating
the seafloor (1883).
multi-hulled ocean racers; the storm-battered
invincible Spanish Armada; Mongol fleets dis¬
persed by the kamikaze wind; the galleys of
Lepanto; the dhows of Sindbad and Henri de
Monfried; tea clippers; the Victory of Hood and
Nelson; the Queen Elizabeth and the France, great
liners in the tradition of the Great Eastern immor¬
talized by Jules Verne in Une Ville Flottante, and
the Titanic, recently rediscovered on the ocean
bed.
~^£5:
The conquest of the deep
that ye . . . May be able to comprehend with
all saints what is the breadth, and length,
and depth, and height.
(St. Paul, Ephesians III, 17, 18)
In 1868, Jules Verne described for the enchant¬
ment of generations of "children in love with
maps and prints", how Professor Aronnax and
his two companions discovered beneath the
pounding waves Captain Nemo's electrically-
powered steel monster the Nautilus, as vainly pur¬
sued and harpooned by Ned Land as the white
whale Moby Dick had been in 1851 by Captain
Ahab in Melville's novel.
Less than a century after Jules Verne, the
American nuclear submarine Nautilus became the
first vessel to sail beneath the polar ice-cap and
took only a few years to cover more than ten
times "Twenty Thousand Leagues under the
Sea". Also in our own time, the divers of the
French vessel Calypso descended to the most
secret corners of the "World of Silence"; the
"Extraordinary Voyages" ofJules Verne's imagi¬
nation were emulated in real life by Comman¬
dant Jacques-Yves Cousteau; while the French
marine engineer Camille Rougeron amused him¬
self by designing a submarine supertanker which
could carry several million tonnes of crude from
one deepwater terminal to another. May God
preserve us!
All these feats, both mental and physical,
were performed a few cables beneath the surface,
in the blue sea that is penetrated, caressed and
brought to life by the not totally absorbed rays
of the Sun. However, no one ventured into the
ocean depths until the early 1930s when William
Beebe and Otis Barton made the first dives in the
bathysphere, a steel sphere suspended on a cable
attached to a boat. By 1934 these courageous men
had reached a depth of just under 1,000 metres.
It was not until 1954, twenty years after
Beebe and Barton's exploit, which was without
practical consequences but had a catalytic effect
on the collective imagination, that psychological
taboos and technological obstacles to deep-sea
exploration were finally overcome when Georges
Houot and Pierre Willm in the bathyscaphe
FNRS 3 reached a depth of more than 4,500
metres off Dakar. The spherical cabin of the
bathyscaphe, which was made of high-quality
steel, had to resist pressures of over 400 kg per
cm2. Its success was due to the scientific imagi¬
nation of professor Auguste Piccard, the
engineering skills of French submarine con¬
structors, and the courage of the two pioneer
divers.
The hidden depths of the ocean have been
visited and observed at close quarters on several 67
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
A 16th-century Korean
"turtle-boat".
occasionsto a depth of 9,050 metres in the
Kouriles trench by Houot and Willm in 1958
aboard the Archimede, and frequently in recent
years at the mid-Atlantic ridge, where the con¬
tinental plates supporting Europe and America
meet and fray. Although no sea monster has yet
appeared, this does not necessarily mean that such
monsters do not exist. Neither have the stocks
of living creatures which accumulate at certain
depths according to the hypothesis proposed by
the Danish oceanographer Hans Petterson1 ever
yet been seen beneath the arc lights (which
perhaps drive them away).
The exploitation of the oceans
The sea is the forest
(Victor Hugo, Les pauvres gens)
The most imaginative and universal poet of the
nineteenth century, exiled at the age of fifty on
a cliff overlooking the sea, regarded the sea as a
sterile and frightening immensity, a cemetery of
wrecks, a hostile power, a source of uncontroll¬
able energy ready to crush and bury the coastal
poor who were condemned to forage for their
meagre food supplies using ways and means that
had hardly changed since biblical times.
-fs } * Jk * À M
68
Within less than two generations, this night¬
mare situation had changed into a far more
hopeful one. Lone fishermen were replaced by
industrial fisheries. Then came the development
of aquaculture. Soon it will be possible to order
robots by remote control to shovel up the man¬
ganese nodules which carpet the seabed. If ther¬
monuclear fusion of hydrogen in confined con¬
ditions is successfully developed, the seawhich
contains inexhaustible supplies of hydrogenwill
become the reservoir of a virtually free and non-
polluting energy source, which could satisfy all
our energy needs in a new golden age. Perhaps
we shall see a happy ending to the wonderful Per¬
sian story of the poor fisherman who cast his net
after imploring Allah and invoking Moses and
caught a bottle which he was unwise enough to
uncork after breaking the seal of Solomon to do
so. A genie emerged from the bottle "in the form
of smoke which rose to the clouds, billowing over
the sea . . . before solidifying into a monstrous
giant". The genie would have wiped out the over-
curious fisherman if the latter had not persuaded
it to get back into the bottle. For us the genie
was the cataclysmic mushroom cloud which rose
above the Pacific Ocean off the island of Bikini
on 26 May 1956 after the testing of a ther¬
monuclear bomb. Today there are grounds for
hoping that scientists working on nuclear fusion
may return this particular genie to its bottle, pos¬
sibly in the form of a Tokamak2 or some other
form of apparatus serving this fourth and last
pillar of Neptune's temple.
The new Atlantis
The sea begins and ceases and then again begins
And when after thought I long rest my gaze
On the calm of the gods, I have here my reward. . . .
But the wind is rising! . . . I must try to live!
(Paul Valéry, Le Cimetière Marin)
The imagination and the sea have been closely
linked ever since the legend of Atlantis. But is
it really a legend?3 Whatever the case, it may be
converted (or restored) to reality. More and more
people dream of lotus-eating on tropical islands,
and holiday clubs and leisure centres of all kinds
are proliferating. Offshore oil platforms could
already serve as models or embryos for earthly
paradises.
We must aim higher and settle in ever more
remote locations. Today it is possible to build off¬
shore and even way out to sea, far from the dirt
and noise of cities, islands dedicated to the higher
pursuits of humanity. Habitations can be built
above the deep blue waters, looking out over a
vast expanse, the inviolate horizon and "the calm
of the gods", but above all in the freedom of the
open sea, subject only to international law. The
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
"serene temples of the sages" which Lucretius
imagined in the marine environment (Suave mare
magno), the ideal scientific city which Francis
Bacon called the "New Atlantis", could thus
emerge from the limbo of the mind.
Philippe Tailliez, another pioneer of under-
The Rime of the Ancient Mariner
All in a hot and copper sky,
The bloody Sun, at noon,
Right up above the mast did stand,
No bigger than the Moon.
Day after day, day after day,
We stuck, nor breath, nor motion;
As idle as a painted ship
Upon a painted ocean.
Water, water, everywhere,
And all the boards did shrink;
Water, water, everywhere,
Nor any drop to drink.
Samuel Taylor Coleridge (1772-1834)
English poet and philosopher
The Rime of the Ancient Mariner
water exploration, has been cherishing this idea
ever since his first dives in 1937 with Jacques-Yves
Cousteau. He has worked out an outline
Archipelaego Project and in 1981 founded an
association whose aim is "the design, construc¬
tion, and experimentation of a floating inhabited
archipelago extending from the heights to the
depths, by means of spatial and underwater struc¬
tures. Such an archipelago, dynamically anchored
to the seabed, is being planned for the Pacific
Ocean, outside those areas which have already
been or are being appropriated by the nations of
the planet for economic exploitation."
Described as "a symbol and affirmation of
the common marine and spatial future of the
human race, in line with the concept of the
common heritage of humanity", the Archipelaego
Project was favourably received by leading divers
and astronauts who met at Miami in 1985, in
Tunis in 1986 and in Japan in 1990, under the
auspices of the World Confederation of Under¬
water Activities (CMAS). It is still no more than
a project, perhaps even a pipe-dream. But it is not
too late, nor perhaps too soon, to start to build
this "last shore".
Summer holidaymakers on the
Atlantic coast of France.
1. La croisière aux abîmes, cited by Georges Houot and Pierre
Willm in Le bathyscaphe, Les Editions de Paris, 1954.
2. Tokamak: an apparatus for the magnetic confinement of the
reacting matter (plasma) involved in nuclear fusion.
3. One recent study suggests that an Atlantis civilization may have
existed in the North Sea 10,000 years ago. Jean Dequelle, De la
préhistoire à l'Atlantide des mégalithes, France-Empire publishers,
Paris 1990.
JACQUES FERRIER,
Commissioner General in the
French Navy, is honorary
president of the Academy of
the Var département in France
and a member of the French
Academy of Commercial
Sciences. He is the author of
many scientific papers, and
recently published a study on
the French Revolution and the
Var (Académie du Var, Toulon
1990). 69
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
M ÙMS LONELY M)
70
I he pearls described in sixth-century-BC Sin¬
ghalese and Indian literature and the sponges
mentioned by Homer and Hippocrates must have
been fished by divers. The oldest unequivocal
reference to diving is in book sixteen of the
Iliad, in which Patroclus gives the following
description of the Trojan Cebhones whom he
has just hit with a stone and knocked from his
chariot: "Ha! Quite an acrobat, I see, judging
by that graceful dive! The man who takes so neat
a header from a chariot on land could dive for
oysters from a ship at sea in any weather and
fetch up plenty for a feast. I did not know the
Trojans had such divers." Thucydides and other
historians of Antiquity also describe how divers
managed to take enemy fleets by surprise.
The first skin divers certainly lived in parts
of the world such as the east Mediterranean and
Polynesia and on the shores of the Yellow Sea
in southeast Asia where there was a combina¬
tion of several favourable factors for diving,
including relatively calm seas, Clearwater, and
a temperature enabling divers to stay in the
water for a reasonable time.
Until the end of the Renaissance diving was
limited in time (by lung capacity) and depth (by
visibility). From the time of the Roman author
Vegetius in the fifth century to that of Leonardo
da Vinci in the fifteenth, people thought of con¬
necting the diver to the surface by means of
an air tube, but attempts to do so came to
nothing since certain principles of hydrostatics
(the branch of mechanics which deals with the
equilibrium of fluids) were only established by
Pascal in the seventeenth century. It then
became known that an underwater swimmer
breathing through a tube linked to the surface
needs to exert a force greater than the water
pressure in order to inhale. The human respira¬
tory muscles are weak. Two metres underwater
the effort to inhale is very tiring, and impossible
any deeper.
Nevertheless, experiments with diving bells
were carried out during this period. These bell-
shaped hulls open to the water at the bottom
were modelled on saucepans or on the urns
containing air which Roman divers placed on
the seabed, with the mouth facing downwards,
and used to supply themselves with air.
BELLS AND CAISSONS
In 1690, Edmond Halley invented a method of
renewing the air inside the diving bell from
barrels lowered to the seabed.
Taking up an idea formulated a hundred
years before by Denis Papin, the English
engineer John Smeaton (1 724- 1 792) went one
step further when he fitted a pump to the bell
in order to provide it with fresh air from a ship
on the surface.
But diving bells were heavy, unwieldy, and
difficult to use. A diver has to breathe air at the
surrounding water pressure, the inflow of air
must be sufficient to keep him or her supplied
with oxygen, and carbon dioxide must be elimi¬
nated so that it is not reinhaled.
Early in the nineteenth century, the German
engineer Augustus Siebe took the decisive step
of providing the diver with a "bell" tailored to
his own sizea diving suit in which the diver
was equipped with a copper helmet with port¬
holes, and supplied with compressed air
pumped from the surface. The supply of air was
continuous, and excess air escaped through the
edge of the helmet below the chin. By 1837
Siebe had developed an improved model with
a valve which let air out without letting water in.
Inventers next tried to make an autono¬
mous diving suit which would free divers from
the need to be in contact with the surface and
enable them to move about more easily.
Borelli (1680), Fréminet (1776), Forfait
(1783), Klingberg (1796) and de Drieberg with
the Triton (1811) had already tried to construct
apparatus of this kind, in which the diver
breathed through the mouth by means of a tube
connected to a container carried on his back
and caused the air to circulate by activating a
bellows with movements of the head.
Further improvements were added by W.H.
James (1825-1828) and then by Condert, who
designed a system for adjusting the supply of
compressed air, a primitive regulator and a free
escape system for surplus air. Cabirol improved
this apparatus even further in 1885.
SCUBA DIVING
In 1860, a French mining engineer, Benoît Rou-
quayrol, and a naval officer, Auguste Denay-
rouze, made a decisive improvement to the
diving suit when they invented a regulator, a
valve which provides air at a pressure equal to
the prevailing water pressure.
In 1864, a swimmer equipped with a gas
regulator supplied by a pump on the surface
could thus easily move around up to 40 metres
down.
In the following year, these brilliant
inventors devised a system for providing the air
supply directly from a container carried on the
diver's back. This was the birth of modern
SCUBA (self-contained underwater breathing
apparatus) diving.
Divers could now operate for up to half an
hour at a depth of ten metres without any link
with the surface. The apparatus was outstand¬
ingly successful. Jules Verne understood its
potential immediately and equipped Captain
Nemo and his men with it in Twenty Thousand
Leagues under the Sea.
Source: Revue de la Fondation Océanographique
Ricard, No. 7, 1984.
Right, "Got a spanner?"
Mechanics adjust a diver's
helmet (1927). Middle,
Halley's diving bell (17th
century). Top, diving hood
designed by the Roman writer
Vegetius (5th century AD).
A*à Jï
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF..
Mozart's unfinished
symphony
At the request of the
prestigious Internationale
Stiftung Mozarteum
foundation, the Japanese
composer Shigeaki Saegusa
has recently completed the
score of an unfinished
orchestral work by Mozart, the
Symphonia Concertante KV
320. The new version of the
symphony, which lasts 20
minutes, will be played in
Salzburg, Mozart's birthplace,
on 5 December, the
bicentenary of the great
composer's death.
Spain's Islamic art
An exhibition on "Al-Andalus,
Islamic Art in Spain", will open
in March 1992 in the
Alhambra Palace, Granada.
The exhibition is being
organized by the Metropolitan
Museum, New York, under the
patronage of the Bank of
Bilbao-Vizcaya. On display will
be 125 objects produced
during the 8-century Islamic
period of Spanish history, on
loan from museums and
private collections in Spain,
Berlin, London, Leningrad,
New York and Paris.
EEC acts on exhaust fumes
Environment Ministers of the
European Economic
Community (EEC) have agreed
on a new directive to limit
exhaust fumes from diesel
lorries. The directive, which
will come into force on 1 July
1992, will cut the maximum
permitted emission of carbon
monoxide, hydrocarbons and
nitrogen oxide.
Brain drain earlier for men
After studying the brains of
34 men and 35 women aged
18 to 80, scientists at
Pennsylvania University have
concluded that men's brains
deteriorate three times faster
than women's. The results of
their research, published in
the Proceedings of the
National Academy of Sciences,
show that men's brain cells
die earlier than women's and
that much of the loss is
concentrated in the parts of
the brain responsible for
reasoning, calculating,
planning and conceptualizing.
Family planning spreads but
world population still rising
More than half of all couples
in developing countries now
use some kind of
contraception, as against less
than 10 per cent in the
1960s, according to the latest
annual report of the United
Nations Population Fund. The
report also says that without
family planning programmes
carried out in the last 20
years, world population would
be 412 million higher than it
is today. In spite of this
progress, United Nations
specialists estimate that world
population will rise from 5.4
billion in 1991 to 6.4 billion in
2001 and 8.5 billion in 2025.
an increase which will be
overwhelmingly concentrated
in the developing countries.
The right to a clean planet
The French ocean explorer
Commandant Jacques-Yves
Cousteau has launched a
campaign for the United
Nations to proclaim the right
of future generations to
inherit a planet where life will
not be seriously threatened by
pollution and overpopulation.
He suggests that a 5-article
Declaration of Rights should
be added to the United
Nations Charter. Commandant
Cousteau has drafted the
Declaration in co-operation
with French and American
scientists and philosophers.
Amnesty International at 30
The humanitarian organization
Amnesty International, which
this year celebrates its 30th
anniversary, has published a
pessimistic report which says
that 2 out of 3 people live in
countries that torture and kill
their citizens. Amnesty
International is appealing to
decision-makers and citizens
to reject all attempts to justify
violations of human rights.
...
Fighting drug abuse
In accordance with a United
Nations resolution, 26 June is
observed each year as
International Day against Drug
Abuse and Illicit Trafficking.
This year the Day, whose
theme was "Preventing Drug
Abuse: all together against a
common threat", coincided with
the launching of the
International Decade against
Drug Abuse (1991-2000), which
is designed to strengthen and
support national, regional and
international efforts in this
field.
Waste not...
To remedy defects in the 3
widely-used methods of
treating household wastes
(incineration, tipping and use
as raw material for the
manufacture of fertilizer), a
Swiss company has invented a
high-speed fossilization
process which produces
neither fumes nor residues.
The waste is subjected to heat
and light radiation in a
reactor, and petrified within 8
minutes. The end product is a
kind of gravel which can be
used in industries ranging
from construction to
mechanical engineering.
Nausicaa, the magic
of the sea
Nausicaa, a marine centre
designed to present to the
general public the spectacle
of the marine world and its
riches opened in May at
Boulogne-sur-Mer (France).
With 15,000 square metres of
exhibition space, 1,400 square
metres of aquarium, a library
containing 5,000 titles and
4,000 references to works
about the sea, a video library
with 5,000 images and 300
films, Nausicaa is also a data
bank providing researchers,
journalists and lovers of the
sea with a matchless source
of information.
A woman's world
Some 4,000 craters, plains
and mountains have been
identified on Venus as a result
of topographical
measurements made by the
Magellan space probe. The
nomenclature commission of
the International Astronomical
Union has decided to name
these sites for famous women
who died more than three
years ago. The only exception
is the planet's highest point,
which already bears the name
of the physicist James Clerk
Maxwell.
From the Chunnel,
a 95-million-year-old
fossil
During work on the Channel
Tunnel between the United
Kingdom and France, 16 km
from the coast of Kent in
southeast England, a
surveyor has made the first
major palaeontological
discovery of these gigantic
excavations: a perfectly
preserved fossil, that of an
octopus-like mollusc which is
believed to have lived 95
million years ago. This
species, says British geologist
Stuart Warren, has not
changed in appearance for
500 million years.
The Jeu de Paume reopens
in Paris
In June the old Paris museum
of the Jeu de Paume
reopened after renovation.
Built in 1862 by Napoleon III,
transformed into a museum in
1947, it housed until 1986 a
splendid collection of
immpressionist paintings
which were later transferred
to the new Orsay Museum.
The new Jeu de Paume will be
a national gallery without a
permanent collection. The
inaugural exhibition, a
retrospective of the last years
of the French painter Jean
Dubuffet, will be followed by
exhibitions of work by
contemporary artists who are
little known outside their own
countries.
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
71
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
ENVIRONMENT
The Blue Plan for the Mediterranean
by Michel Bâtisse
X or us human beings the ocean is an alien
environment where there are no familiar fea¬
tures to help us get our bearings, a place of
which we still know little. Sometimes we over¬
estimate its wealth, sometimes we neglect its
importance. We behave as if the oceans can
absorb anything, and do not suspect that they
play a crucial role in the regulation of climate.
We think that there are unlimited stocks of
fish, whereas in reality world fishing has
already reached saturation point. Where the
sea is concerned, we seem to find it hard to
distinguish myth from reality. . . .
These contradictions between what we
believe and what is true, between what we
want and what is possible, are nowhere more
apparent than in the Mediterranean, that "sea
in the midst of land", the cradle and crossroads
of ancient civilizations, which is today pointed
to as an example of pollution and degradation.
What are the facts, and what does the future
hold for these shores "where the orange tree
blossoms"?
Since 1976, political and economic differ¬
ences notwithstanding, all the Mediterranean
countries have been co-operating within the
framework of the Barcelona Convention to
protect their common sea from pollution. The
Mediterranean is a closed sea, without big
tides, and accidents like those involving the
Amoco Cadiz off Brittany in 1978 or the Exxon
Valdez off Alaska in 1989 could have disas¬
trous consequences for the historic cities on
its shores, for its beaches, for its tourist and
port facilities, and for the fragile economy of
its coastal regions. A small oil slick which
recently appeared off Genoa caused conster¬
nation on the Italian and French rivieras.
"Integrated coastal management comes up against
administrative compartmentalizatlon."
72
Naturally enough, co-operation between
the Mediterranean countries focused initially
on risks of oil spills and the discharge of toxic
wastes and other pollutants. However it soon
became clear that the harm being done to the
sea originated mainly from the landfrom the
coast, from rivers, and from the atmosphere.
Contrary to what is often said, the main
sources of offshore pollution in the Mediter¬
ranean are plastic bags, lumps of tar and occa¬
sional algae blooms produced by nutrient-rich
agricultural fertilizer. On the coast, however,
the situation varies widely. On the one hand
there are sparsely populated areas which are
still very clean; on the other there are zones
where considerable chemical and bacteriolog¬
ical pollution is caused by urban, industrial
and agricultural wastes. It is on the coastal
regions of the Mediterranean countries that
human activities are focused and where all
kinds of pressures are created.
The Mediterranean basin, whether consi¬
dered in its totality or in terms of individual
countries, provinces and sites, behaves as a
"system" whose components act and react
together. Any attempt to understand the
present and possible future situation of the
Mediterranean has to be based on an analysis
of the system and its possible futures. Any
action which affects only one or another of
the components of the system and ignores the
overt or covert links between them runs the
risk of failure. It may, for instance, be futile
to try to attract more tourists to a stretch of
coast where the necessary water resources are
not available, or if a polluting industry is
created nearby.
The Mediterranean countries decided to
produce a system-based and future-oriented
study which would help them to understand
the nature and extent of current developments
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
and to make sound policy decisions. This tool
is the Blue Plan. In it population is regarded
as the primary component in the Mediterra¬
nean system, for it is people who, by their
number, age, needs, aspirations and move¬
ments, are the dominant factor of change since
they act directly, both quantitatively and
qualitatively, on all the other components of
the systemagriculture, industry, energy,
tourism, transport, soils, forests, continental
waters, the coastal areas and the sea itself.
Scenarios for the future
In the Blue Plan, a number of scenarios have
been constructed for the Mediterranean
system until the year 2025. They are based on
coherent sets of hypotheses relating to demo¬
graphic change, to types of development and
the growth rates that result from them, to
environmental policies, and to levels of co¬
operation between the northern and southern
Mediterranean countries.
Of course these scenarios do not claim to
predict the future, which will doubtless emerge
from the course of history as erratically as it
always has. But they aim to show what may
happen in the logic of things, depending on
Fishermen are depicted
on this mosaic from the ancient city of Utica,
Tunisia (4th century AD).
whether or not certain conditions exist. Two
types of scenario have been constructed: so-
called "trend" scenarios which, to a greater
or lesser degree, prolong observable current
developments in different parts of the system;
and "alternative" scenarios which depart con¬
siderably from current developments, pay
more attention to the environment, and are
based on far more effective economic and tech¬
nical co-operation between the countries of
the northern shores of the Mediterranean and
those of the south and east. The latter coun¬
tries are and will be in a far more difficult posi¬
tion than those of the north. The population
of their Mediterranean coastal regions may rise
from 60 million today to somewhere between
100 and 130 million in the year 2025, whereas
population in the northern countries may
only rise from 80 to 90 million at most. Popu¬
lation growth alone would create a parallel
growth in needs, with major socio-economic
and environmental consequences.
The results of the different scenarios of the
Blue Plan are too complex to be summarized
in a few lines. It is clear however that the trend
scenarios describe situations which it is hard
to accept from either an ecological or an eco¬
nomic point of view. They suggest the whole¬
sale destruction of coastal landscapes by ram¬
pant urbanization, increased pollution,
damage to the terrestrial and marine environ¬
ment, and a marked deterioration in living
conditions in the countries of the south. The
figures are alarming. To take but one example,
between now and 2025, an average of one
power station would have to be built every
twenty kilometres from the coast of Morocco
to that of Turkey.
The alternative scenarios are of course
more acceptable, even if they are based on the
supposition that major difficulties will have
been overcome. The most obvious of these
difficulties concerns the radical change in poli¬
cies implicit in the channelling of massive aid
from north to south. At the same time there
would have to be a real change in attitudes,
both in the north and in the south, towards
the environment and the consumption of
resources. Perhaps the rarest of these resources
is fresh water, whose scarcity imposes con¬
siderable limitations on development in many
Mediterranean countries, and which will have
to be economically and rigorously managed. 73
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
74
The most threatened resource, however,
is the coastline itself. It is there that the most
serious conflicts arise about land use. I would
cite one example to illustrate the importance
of the choices which will have to be made. By
the beginning of the next century, almost all
the Mediterranean countries will have to
import much of their food. To obtain the
necessary foreign currency, their most pre¬
cious capital will in many cases be a natural
and cultural heritage which is concentrated on
the coast. Depending on the scenario, these
areas may be visited by between 125 and 190
million foreign tourists each year from Europe
or elsewhere. But the coast will not attract
tourists if it is blighted by anarchic building
and infrastructure development and by all
kinds of pollution on land, on the beaches and
at sea. There are other places where tourists
can go.
Priority to the coast
If the idea of "saving" the Mediterranean is
to make any sense at all, it is essential that the
coastline be properly managed. All the com¬
ponents of the "coastal system" must be taken
into account, both on land (controlled urban
development, wastewater treatment, agricul¬
ture without excessive discharge of fertilizers
and pesticides, respect for productive land,
appropriately sited industries and clean tech¬
nologies, the control of air and water-polluting
emissions at source, the development of
highways and airports in the hinterland, the
conservation of forests and humid zones) and
at sea (the development of ports with debal-
lasting facilities for ships, control of dredging
and waste disposal, the disposal of wastewater
offshore, limitations on marina development,
the protection of aquatic plant life and the
seabed, regulation of fishing).
Unfortunately, there is no tradition of
integrated coastal management of this kind.
In most countries matters concerning the land
and those concerning the sea are handled by
different parts of the administrative system.
MICHEL BATISSE,
French engineer and physicist, is internationally
known for his work on the environment and
natural resources. Currently a consultant with
UNESCO and the United Nations Environment
Programme (UNEP), he has headed the Blue Plan
Regional Activity Centre for the Mediterranean at
Sophia Antipolis, France, since it was created
in 1985.
Integrated management conflicts with cor¬
poratism, private interests and administrative
compartmentalization. However, there is
reason to react, and all those of us who are
interested in the sea or go to the seaside can
do something to help.
The Blue Plan for the Mediterranean
shows both the limits and the possibilities of
protecting the shoreline. It also shows that
other blue plans could be useful for the future
of other regions. By the very nature of the
problems that exist therebetween north and
south, between the environment and develop¬
ment, between land and seathe Mediterra¬
nean basin is a truly representative microcosm
of the planet as a whole.
This region has seen a succession of rich
and varied civilizations: Egyptians and Phoe¬
nicians, Greeks and Hittites, Romans and Car¬
thaginians, Arabs and Franks, the Italian
Renaissance, the rise of the modern world. It
was doubtless right and proper that it should
break new ground in reflecting on the future.
But now it must vigorously continue the
action it has begun so that its future will be
worthy of its past. Time is running out if we
are to modify or reverse the degradation of
the coastline. If Venus, goddess of beauty,
daughter of the Mediterranean, ever rises from
the waves again, let us make sure that she is
not covered with red algae, plastic and tar.
^«**.
*
*"<**,
*«<£«
The Blue Plan has been
published in English under
the title Futures for the
Mediterranean Basin {Oxford
University Press, 1990).
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
An ecological Eldorado: Peru's Manu
National
Park
by José Serra-Vega
ELanu National Park in south-east Peru
rises from the sweltering fastnesses of the
Amazonian forest up through a labyrinth of
giddying scarps to an altitude of 4,000 metres
on the eastern slopes of the Andes. The two
great rivers that flow through the region, the
Manu and the Madre de Dios, rush down from
the high plateaux to the plain where, slack¬
ening their course, they meander along
through a succession of different ecosystems
and climates, joining up to flow together into
the Amazon.
In the west, flocks of vicunas, the occa¬
sional guemal (a small American deer) and
fearsome mountain lions roam across the
frozen peaks and the cold, wind-swept
plateaux dotted with black lakes where all that
grows is a coarse yellow grass known as ichu.
From time to time a spectacled bear can be
seen, a species found nowhere else in South
America. The mountain forest stretches out
further down between altitudes of 3,800 and
2,500 metres, shrouded in thick mist. Lower
down the temperature rises and rainfall
increases, making for a proliferation of plant
and animal life. Manu National Park consists
mainly of tropical rainforest whose tangle of
giant trees, creepers, plant parasites and
orchids, climbing plants and epiphytes, pro¬
vides a habitat for a huge variety of wildlife.
In the vast Amazonian plain down below, the
river Manu winds its way through a valley
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
The ai or
three-toed sloth,
a tree-dwelling
vegetarian.
made well-nigh impenetrable by the density
of the vegetation, forming in places oxbow
lakescochaswhich teem with aquatic life.
The lure of the unknown
For centuries people have been drawn to the
Amazon by the lure of the unknown, a thirst
for adventure and the prospect of fortune. The
Incas of Cuzco sought to expand their empire
in this region and found themselves with no
choice but to trade with the warlike tribes of
the region in order to obtain the colourful
feathers with which they decorated their
ceremonial costumes and the hallucinogenic
and medicinal plants on which they relied.
Legend has it that Paititi, the lost city
where the Incas are believed to have hidden
enormous quantities of gold and silver after
learning of the murder of their ruler Atahu-
alpa at the hands of the Spanish conqueror
Francisco Pizarro, was located in the Manu
region. The Spanish armies, in their search for
this Eldorado and its fabulous treasures,
penetrated deep into the jungle where they
were decimated by disease and hostile Indians.
They too ended up by abandoning all attempts
to settle there.
For three more centuries it was not
known whether the rivers in the Madre de
Dios basin flowed northwards or westwards.
Some geographers of the time, who embel¬
lished their maps with mythical creatures and
monstrous caimans, thought that the
Amazon's source lay somewhere within it.
The rubber boom in the late nineteenth
century attracted thousands of adventurers to
the area. For twenty-odd years the tapping of
trees for latex was a thriving industry and
Amazonia edged its way into the world
market, but competition from the British
plantations in Asia brought this activity to a
sudden end.
Lethargy again descended on the region, 75
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[
only to be shaken off in the 1960s with the
development of the trade in fursocelot,
jaguar, otter, black lizardand exotic wood-
manly mahogany and cedar. Around the same
time people started taking an interest in the
exceptional biological resources to be found
there. In 1968 the Peruvian authorities
organized an expedition into the basin of the
river Manu and its tributary the Sotileja. On
the basis of the information collected, they
declared Manu a national park in June 1973.
In 1977 UNESCO recognized it as a biosphere
reserve and since 1987 it has been on the
World Heritage List.
The core of the biosphere reserve is Manu
National Park, which has an area of 15,328
km2 from which all economic or touristic
activities are barred. It is bounded in the east
by a buffer zone measuring some 2,500 km2
where the aim is to preserve the forest while
allowing limited tourism and scientific
research. Further south is a transitional zone
covering 900 km2 inhabited by a few settlers
and by Indian communities which continue
to practise their traditional activities, within
set bounds.
The Cocha Cashu biological observatory
was established in 1969 beside a cutoff of the
river Manu. Its laboratories and research facil¬
ities can accommodate about twenty
researchers. The work done there has helped
to provide a fuller picture of the forms of life
present in the reserve and of tropical forest
ecosystems in general. Another observatory
is being built outside the national park so that
certain studies can be carried out which are
not allowed in the park itself. But there is a
huge amount to be done. The forest harbours
countless mysteries. We know little about its
aquatic forms of life and virtually nothing
about the tropical montane rainforest or the
grasslands of the high plateaux or punas.
In a sense, then, the legendary treasures
of Eldorado do exist in the form of the sixteen
ecosystems present within the 18,800 km2 of
the reserve, which have remained practically
intact since the dawn of time.
Parrots, monkeys, and turtles
The most characteristic feature of the tropical
rainforest is doubtless its fabulous diversity.
It would be impossible here to list even the
main forest species in the reserve. To give
some idea of its biological resources,
researchers have identified 1,200 vascular
plants within an area of 4 km2 around the
76 Cocha Cashu observatory. One tenth of the
Macaws, members of
the parrot family which often
live in groups.
plants in the reserve have not yet been identi¬
fied and may belong to species hitherto
unknown to scientists. When an inventory
was made of canopy insects within one hec¬
tare of rainforest, 41,000 species of inver¬
tebrates were found, including 12,000 kinds
of beetle. In one single tree there were 43 types
of ant belonging to 26 different genera, prac¬
tically as many as in the whole of the British
Isles.
No less than fifteen per cent of the world's
bird species are found in Manu park, whose
denizens include majestic condors, tiny hum¬
mingbirds, and noisy black and yellow
icteridae whose hanging nests look like great
purses made of straw. There are twenty-eight
species of macaws and parrots, including the
very rare blue-headed parrot.
From beneath the trees these birds are
easier to hear than to see, but they can some¬
times be glimpsed in the open spaces along the
river. At sunrise a squawking, multicoloured
flight of parrots can sometimes be seen
swooping down on the furrowed banks of the
Manu to gobble up the clay which is rich in
mineral salts. Herons, wild geese and ducks,
delicate spoonbills and other gangling waders
mingle on the shores with sleepy caimans that
can move into action with devastating speed.
Kingfishers, large-billed toucans and stiletto-
billed snakebirds also live by the river, feeding
on its plentiful supply of aquatic animals.
Perhaps the strangest bird of all is the hoatzin,
which nests at the riverside. Its young have
claws on their wings which they use to
clamber about in the trees before they learn
to fly. Its digestive system resembles that of
ruminants.
The forest is also the habitat of monkeys,
thirteen species of which have so far been
identified, including the tiny pygmy marmoset,
the smallest in the world, which weighs barely
120 grams, the restless emperor tamarin,
which owes its name to its superb white
moustaches, worthy of emperor Franz-Josef
of Austria, the spider monkey and the howling
monkey whose roars, imitating those of the
jaguar, have curdled the blood of more than
one tourist.
The jaguar itself, like the puma and the
ocelot, is mainly nocturnal but can be seen
prowling along the river bank at the time of
the year when turtles come there to lay their
eggs. Tapirs, peccaries and wild dogs come to
the water during the daytime to drink. There
are also many other mammalssmall bats
which sleep head downwards, hanging from
the branches over the cochas, vampire bats
which live exclusively on blood, giant
anteaters and armadillos, some of which weigh
as much as fifty kilograms.
There are also large numbers of giant
otters. Much sought after for their valuable
furs, these carnivorous mammals once came
near to extinction in the Amazon basin.
Insatiably curious and extremely fast-moving
in the water, otters hunt and fish in groups.
Endowed with powerful teeth, they do not
hesitate to attack one-and-a-half-metre-long
caimans in order to defend their young or
obtain food.
Many dangers lurk in this spellbindingly
beautiful world, vibrant with sounds and
colours. In the forests and swamps there are
]]>
</page>
<page number="77">
<![CDATA[
poisonous snakes and other dangerous crea¬
tures. The most fearsome and aggressive of the
snakes is the deadly bushmaster [Lachesis
muta), which can be more than three metres
long and is reputed to pursue people who are
foolhardy enough to cross its path. The most
common reptiles are pit vipers of the genus
Bothrops, which are capable of detecting
sources of heat from a distance and can thus
hunt in the dark, and the brightly-coloured
coral snakes of the genus Micrurus, which are
distant cousins of the Asian and African
cobras. The rivers and lakes are the home of
the anaconda and the gigantic aquatic boa
which can be as much as nine metres long. By
the riverside or on drifting trunks it is not
uncommon to see river turtles basking in the
sun in the company of black lizards. The largest
reptile in the reserve, which has been observed
at Cocha Cashu, is a black female lizard nearly
five metres long and over 500 kilos in weight.
The forest hunters
The most mysterious area in the reserve is the
Pusharo gorge, a colossal gateway through
which the river Palotoa finds its way out of
the mountains. On one side of the gorge, con¬
cealed by the vegetation, is a thirty-metre-long
frieze of rock carvings which display solar
symbols, snakes, women's heads, spirals and
crisscross patterns. Behind, a ramp, which is
probably artificial, leads to a stone terrace.
Like many other examples of rock art scat¬
tered through Amazonia, they have been
neither studied nor interpreted. They are the
remains of a forgotten Amazonian culture
probably dating back to the earliest settlers in
America.
Today very few people live in this com¬
plex and wonderful setting. A few Amahuaca
and Yaminahua Indians live in the valleys of
the Panahua and Pinquén rivers and in the
northeastern part of the reserve. In the rainy
season, the Neolithic Amahuaca hunters,
fishermen and farmers return to the sources
of the two rivers to tend their crops. During
the dry season, from July to December, they
go back to the banks of the Manu where they
harvest the river turtle eggs which are the main
source of protein in their diet. The indigenous
peoples have permission to live on the
resources of the reserve, and care is taken not
to disturb their traditional way of life, which
is the result of thousands of years of adapta¬
tion to the harsh forest environment.
Even more mysterious are the Kugapákori,
who lead a nomadic existence between the
basins of the Madre de Dios and the Uru-
bamba. They jealously defend their territory
and shoot arrows at anyone who crosses the
invisible frontier that runs around it.
The Machiguenga people are very
different. Converted to the ways of the
modern world, some have settled in the vil¬
lage of Tayakome, a distance of five hours by
canoe upstream from Cocha Cashu, where
missionaries brought them from their home
territory in the upper reaches of the Uru-
bamba valley. The rest live in small scattered
groups consisting of a few households,
provided by the government with rudimen¬
tary schools and with teachers, many of whom
speak their language.
Few people come from the high plateaux
The jaguar is the largest species
of the cat family in the western hémisphère.
and settle on the edge of the park and hence
they present no threat to the forest. The poor
state of the road from Cuzco makes transport
expensive, and this discourages people from
settling in the area.
A threatened world
But the park is being increasingly exposed to
danger. There is a risk that certain industri¬
alization projects may jeopardize the integrity
of the reserve and the survival of its inhabi¬
tants. If these schemes come to fruition, the
extraordinary natural heritage of Manu will
soon be no more than a memory.
In the region of Madre de Dios, which is
one of the last unspoiled areas of Peru, and
especially near the Brazilian border, linked to
Sao Paulo by a tarmacked road, the forest is
being burnt away, sometimes illegally, to
make space for big stock-raising farms.
A multinational oil company has disco¬
vered an enormous deposit of natural gas at
the north-east edge of the Manu Park, which
is believed to extend beneath the actual
reserve. A camp set up for the prospectors has
already caused incalculable harm. Wild
animals have been exterminated, rivers have
been polluted with oil and chemical products
and indigenous groups have been driven from
their traditional hunting grounds.
But this is nothing in comparison with the
ecological and human disaster that would be
triggered by the installation of a pipeline to
transport gas to Cuzco, along with a power
station which would produce electricity
exported to Brazil via a 350-km-long high-
voltage cable, 120 km of which would pass
though the reserve. Almost 300 km of a road
planned to run from Puerto Bermúdez, in the
centre of Peru, to the frontier of Bolivia would
cross the northern part of the reserve.
If these projects are carried out, the forests
of Manu will cease to be.
JOSÉ SERRA-VEGA,
of Peru, is a former staff member of the United
Nations Environment Programme in Nairobi
(Kenya). He helped to set up a new scientific
research station in the Manu biosphere reserve
and contributed to a plan for a biosphere reserve
at Beni in Bolivia. 77
]]>
</page>
<page number="78">
<![CDATA[
The return of the RA al-Safamaft
by François-Bernard Huyghe
Or'n 25 April 1991 the Fulk al-Salamah, the
"Ship of Peace", dropped anchor in the port
of Mina Qabus in Muscat. Six weeks had
already gone by since the ship, which had been
loaned by Sultan Qabus of Oman to
UNESCO's Maritime Silk Roads expedition,
had left its passengers at Hakata, Japan. But
the festivities to celebrate the return of the cap¬
tain and his crew had been postponed until
the end of Ramadan. Like the celebrations on
17 November last that had marked the start
of the voyage, these were in traditional Omani
style and featured hundreds of dancers.
It would be an understatement to say that
the expedition received a royal welcome. Her¬
alded by fireboats spouting great jets of water
and with a helicopter whirring above our
heads, escorted by launches and patrol ships
and encircled by a flotilla of white boats
decked out in the national colours, our ship
pulled into port. There we were greeted by
floating rigs adorned with the United Nations
flag, the Sultan's portrait and a mysterious
flower that several of usclearly no great
shakes as botaniststook for a lotus, seeing
it as a possible symbol of East-West relations.
Later we were told that the flower thus
depicted was a new variety of rose, the "Sultan
Qabus".
But it was the noises that made the strong¬
est impression: drumbeat, chanting and
whooping sounds punctuated the dances per¬
formed by hundreds of dancers on board boats
crammed with people. They brandished sticks,
swords and kandjarsthe traditional dagger
sported by Omani men on solemn occasions.
Meanwhile, on land, ministers, members of
the royal family, an escort, other dances, and
a procession of official cars awaited us. . . .
Our arrival in Muscat coincided with the
twentieth anniversary of the Sultan's accession
to power. In actual fact, what was being
celebrated in the city, transformed into a daz¬
zling tricolour array by thousands of light
bulbs in the national coloursgreen, red and
whitewas the amazing leap in time that had
78 been made in less than a generation, and the
change that had occurred in people's minds.
It was the transition, effected through dynastic
succession and with the help of petrodollars,
from an Oman immersed in its history, where
electricity and sunglasses were suspected of
bringing the evils of modernism, to the most
up-to-date form of civilization. And yet, here
more than anywhere else, there was clearly a
concern to maintain spiritual values, and evi¬
dence of a discipline that seemed to be freely
accepted.
The stereotype image is of an "Arabian
Switzerland", of a place where camels and
computers exist side by side, but what I actu¬
ally saw was: a city rebuilt in accordance with
aesthetic standards which endow it with unity;
a military parade ended with a tribal march-
past featuring ancient rites of war; sheiks from
Dofar visiting an ultra-modern cultural centre
in Salalàh, amazed to see objects from their
everyday lives being displayed in showcases;
hundreds of youngsters moving together in
unison to create an electronic tableau vivant
reminiscent of the opening of the Olympic
Games, and in the stands every single man
without exception dressed in the traditional
Omani costume. Few places present such
striking contrasts.
I leave it to better-informed observers than
I to explain how the people can experience
such a culture shock while remaining seem¬
ingly unperturbed. I would also ask them to
make allowances for what may be no more
than a superficial impression.
Losing our bearings
But for us passengers of the Fulk al-Salamah
the culture shock had been even greater. We
had left behind us the agricultural and urban
Mediterranean world with its layer cake of
different cultures, and found ourselves face to
face with something radically other. The Euro¬
pean writer of these lines, who had been
taught to see the succession of Egyptian,
Greek, Roman, Byzantine and Islamic civili¬
zations as a harmonious continuum within
which "influences" could be identified and
studied, was gradually losing his bearings.
From kafenion to fonduk, from Memphis to
Ephesus, from the archaeological museum in
Athens to the one in Cairo, a line of develop¬
ment could be discerned, or interactions could
be seen. Now there was no longer any per¬
ceptible pattern.
At the seminars which we attended ashore
and during the twice-daily working meetings
on board we were supposed to be adding to
our knowledge. Inundated with new informa¬
tion, faced with the impossible task of sum¬
ming up that which constitutes the fabric of
all the different cultures, namely exchange,
]]>
</page>
<page number="79">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
THE SILK ROADS
1
13
how could we know which clue to follow? We
could at least try to remember what our points
of reference were, for they seemed to have
gone astray somewhere in the Red Sea.
In Athens, we hadn't yet lost the thread.
It wasexcuse the play on wordssilk. We
knew that the introduction of this precious
fibre in ancient Rome had triggered a riot of
indulgence and a craze for imported fabrics,
leading finally to a debt of such proportions
that the English historian Edward Gibbon
considered it to be one of the causes of the
fall of the Roman Empire. The case of Byzan¬
tium is no less striking. In the time of the late
empire silk clothes were highly prized and
passed on from generation to generation, so
it is not surprising that the introduction into
Byzantium of the modest silk-worm in the
mid-sixth century caused a total upheaval.
Trade in this precious commodity and its sub¬
sequent manufacture were strictly controlled
by the state. Silk was also the source of con¬
siderable economic activity in some parts of
Greece up to the nineteenth century.
At a seminar in Izmir in Turkey we like¬
wise discovered the role of ancient Smyrna in
the silk trade and the relationship of the city's
periods of prosperity and decline with fluc¬
tuations of the international market. The links
between the maritime silk route and the
caravan trails helped to reassure us that we
were indeed finding similarities and exploring
a unifying network which was a cause of strife
among the powerful but which was usually
kept open in the interests of a deep-rooted
need for security.
Little by little, we turned from silk to
other commodities. The spice road increas¬
ingly attracted our attention, and this was per¬
fectly logical. The expression "silk roads" was
to be understood not in geographical and eco¬
nomic terms but, to quote one of our fellow
passengers, as a "metaphor of dialogue".
A sense of identity
To return to Oman, what we found bewil¬
dering there was not the absence of such links
but their profusion. Archaeological studies
have only recently been undertaken in the
country, but they already reveal links that
reach far back into pre-Islamic times. As early
as the third millennium BC and right up to
the beginning of the following millennium,
Oman, the land of Magan, exported copper
and diorite to Mesopotamia. At the same time
pottery from Mesopotamia appeared in
Omani tombs. Similarly, relations between
Magan culture and the Indus Civilization can
apparently be traced back to about 2,300 BC.
A number of stories from later times
provided us with other examples of cultural
exchanges between Oman and other countries.
One of the specialists on board recounted
to us the tale of an Omani merchant of Indian
Left, the Fulk al-Salamah in
the port of Venice. In
foreground is the Zlnat al-
Bihar, a traditional Omani
ship.
Above, three-coloured
enamelled statuette of a
bearded camel driver. It was
found in an 8th-century tomb
near Xi'an (China).
79
]]>
</page>
<page number="80">
<![CDATA[
origin, Sayyid, who lived in the thirteenth cen¬
tury. Not only did he have frequent and cor¬
dial commercial dealings with the Chinese
navigators who came to Oman but, when
Prince Ma'abar took exception to these friend¬
ships, Sayyid fled to the court of Kubla Khan,
who showered him with gifts and wedded him
to a Korean princess. He died a rich man in
Beijing in 1299.
A story from the early fifteenth century
concerns the famous Chinese navigator Zheng
He, a Muslim, who travelled several times to
El Balidid, present-day Salalah, in the south
of Oman. Zheng He was provided with inter¬
preters who were trained in a special school;
their writings are the source of our information
about his visits to Oman.
These cases are striking not only because
they suggest vast areas for study. The first two
examples take us back several thousand years,
and far from the regions which the expedition
had studied. The second two show that rela¬
tions between China and Oman were by no
The Fulk al-Salamah is welcomed
in style on its arrival in Muscat, capital
of the Sultanate of Oman.
means confined to trade but had a cultural
dimension.
The history of Oman, until relatively
recent times, seems to consist only of accounts
by foreign observers and of the records of
trade. For a people which has taken as its
national heroes Sindbad the Sailor and Vasco
da Gama's helmsman, Ahmed bin Majud,
travel and discovery led not to self-enrichment
but to identity.
Coming into port
With hindsight, our magnificent welcome in
Muscat came to assume a significance that it
had not possessed at the moment when we
landed there. Several times during our voyage
we had talked about how we had gained
another sense of time and had come to see
travelling in another light. We had slipped our
moorings, both physically and metaphorically,
forgotten our everyday lives for several
months and formed a community. We had dis¬
covered that coming into port is an event, that
it has nothing in common with the triviality
of modern travel which blots out distances and
differences. The distant noise of war reached
us but was somehow muffled. And this helped
to remind us of the strangeness of our adven¬
ture, causing us to look at the world with new
eyes.
One specialist pointed out that the
presiding geniuses of our journey, Marco Polo
and Ibn Batuta, had been able to roam freely
through the then known world without being
arrested or murdered. What was their secret?
What signs of peace did they use, what code
of salutation? Our voyage could be an occa¬
sion for meditating upon the rituals that defuse
aggression in different cultures.
If the longest journeys are in the mind,
the flood of sounds and colours that greeted
us in Muscat or celebrated the homecoming
of the Fulk al-Salamah perhaps showed that
the traveller is someone for whom novelty can
be a source of inner change. Far from the
world of total and instantaneous media
coverage, we had come to see things in a
different way.
FRANÇOIS-BERNARD HUYGHE,
French writer and journalist, is a former member
of UNESCO's Division of Cultural Heritage.
80
]]>
</page>
<page number="81">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
UNESCO launches
AIDS appeal
An appeal for international
solidarity with the victims of AIDS
was launched by a group of
leading personalities meeting
under UNESCO auspices in Venice
on 8 June. The signatories of the
Venice Appeal, which is intended
to further the Global Programme
on AIDS co-ordinated by the World
Health Organization (WHO), call on
all those who wish to fight this
terrible pandemic to contribute to
national programmes to combat
AIDS in the countries that are
most stricken in Africa, in order to
strengthen preventive education,
training and scientific research,
and to support those orphaned by
AIDS, especially by covering their
educational expenses. A bank
account has been opened for this
purpose: UNESCO Sidaids World,
compte 77666, Chase Manhattan
Bank, N.A. Chips Uids 019719,
18 bd Malesherbes,
BP 450 Paris Cedex 80.
Germany supports
educational projects in
Sahel
Under an agreement signed in
December 1990, Germany is
contributing 1.5 million dollars to
a basic education project to be
carried out by UNESCO in six
countries of the African Sahel:
Burkina Faso, Chad, Mali,
Mauritania, Niger and Senegal.
The first stage of the project will
last 3 years and is designed to
enable each of these countries to
produce 100,000 textbooks for
use in literacy and post-literacy
work.
An ethics of development
The importance of an ethical code
of development as a factor in
lasting peace was emphasized by
Mr Federico Mayor, Director-
General of UNESCO, in a recent
interview with the French daily
newspaper Le Monde. "Together
we must work out a moral code
for development", Mr. Mayor said,
"which, over and above interest
rates, technology transfers, the
price of raw materials, financial
flows, tariff and non-tariff barriers,
etc., helps us to devise forms of
development of which we can all
be proud, because they
incorporate universal and eternal
values, in particular those of law
and justice."
"How", he went on, "can we
devise forms of human
development that do not give rise
to these huge migratory
movementsresulting in a
diasporized humanity these
inequalities in respect of food,
health, education and access to
scientific and technological
knowledge that affect hundreds of
millions of people, the threats
hanging over the biosphere and
the environment in general, the
scourge of ever less cultural and
biological diversity, loss of values,
a diminishing sense of solidarity,
loneliness and drugs? The answer
that is given to these questions
will largely determine how we
reshape international relations."
The Arabia Plan
Within the framework of the World
Decade for Cultural Development
(1988-1997), UNESCO has
launched a plan for the promotion
of contemporary Arab culture,
known as the "Arabia Plan".
Among the projects proposed as
part of the Plan are the creation
of training fellowships, the setting
up of a data bank on Arab culture,
action to provide financial support
for the international distribution of
Arab films and to increase public
awareness of the major
achievements of Arab art in such
fields as architecture, miniatures
and the graphic arts.
The media and the cultural
heritage
A major international conference
and festival entitled "Media Save
Art 91" took place in Rome from
17 to 22 June under the joint
patronage of UNESCO and the
Italian Government. The aim was
to alert public opinion to the
dangers threatening the cultural
heritage and to seek closer co¬
operation between the media and
institutions responsible for
protecting the heritage.
Highlights of the occasion
included an exhibition on the
restoration of works of art, the
projection of films and audio¬
visual documents on art and
culture, and discussions among
leading specialists on the role of
the mass media in safeguarding
the cultural heritage.
Mandela and De Klerk
awarded Houphouët-Boigny
Peace Prize
Nelson Mandela and Frederik
de Klerk, of South Africa, were
named on 27 June first winners
of the Houphouët-Boigny
Peace Prize by an international
jury of eleven distinguished
figures nominated by the Director-
General of UNESCO. The president
of the jury, Mr Henry Kissinger,
said that the two prizewinners
had been chosen for their
contribution to international
peace, to encourage them to
continue their efforts, and as a
tribute to what they had done to
educate their peoples towards
understanding and towards
overcoming prejudices that many
considered to be insurmountable
only a few years ago.
The prize, worth 800,000
French francs, will be presented
later this year. It is intended to
honour persons, institutions or
associations that have made a
significant contribution to the
promotion, maintenance or
restoration of peace.
IDAMS,
an integrated international
software package
UNESCO has developed an
integrated data management and
statistical analysis software
package (IDAMS) for large and
small IBM and IBM-compatible
computers. Designed for
professionals who have to process
numerical data for scientific or
administrative purposes, IDAMS
may be interfaced with other
UNESCO-produced CDS/ISIS
software for the management of
textual data bases.
Users will find in IDAMS the
standard range of univariate and
bivariate statistics, and
multivariate statistical techniques,
plus some recent advanced
techniques. IDAMS also provides
a series of data management
programs, and a powerful
language for transformation
of data. The version of
IDAMS for micro-computers is
equipped with highly efficient
word-processing functions,
graphic facilities and on-line help
messages.
The software can be used
without programming know-how
and is distributed to institutions
free-of-charge on request to:
IDAMSCII/PGI, UNESCO,
7, Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris, France.
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Page 3: Denarnaud © Sipa Press, Paris. Pages 3 (right),
14-15, 21 (right), 31 (above), 39, 73: © Charles Lenars,
Paris. Pages 4, 6, 9: U. Andersen © Gamma, Paris.
Pages 10-11, 22: © Rijksmuseum, Amsterdam. Pages 12-13,
16, 32, 40, 58: © Monique Pietri, Paris. Pages 17, 18, 19, 68,
back cover: © Roland Michaud, Paris. Pages 20-21: Roland
Michaud © Rapho, Paris. Page 23: by permission of Institut
Chine-Europe, Louvain, taken from Chine, ciel et terre (1988).
Pages 24, 27, 47, 49, 58-59: © G. Dagli Orti, Paris.
Pages 25, 29: © Trustees of the British Museum, London.
Pages 26, 48, 51, 52, 66-67: ©Jean-Loup Charmet, Paris.
Pages 28-29: © National Maritime Museum, London.
Pages 30-31, 61 (below): © Luc Cuyvers, Maryland.
Page 33: © Charles Carrie, Paris. Pages 34-35: Claus Meyer
© Rapho, Paris. Pages 36-37: UNESCO-Arthur Gillette.
Pages 40-41: Brian Brake © Rapho, Paris. Pages 43, 44-45:
© Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris. Page 46: © DITE/IPS,
Paris. Page 50: © Yale University Art Gallery, Stephen
Carlton Clark donation. Pages 54-55, 56, 57: UNESCO-
Ayala. Pages 60, 70 (middle and below): © Viollet
Collection, Paris. Page 61 (above): © CNM Nausicaa,
Boulogne-sur-Mer. Page 62 (below): © C. Carré, Nausicaa,
Boulogne-sur-Mer. Page 62 (above): © Claude Sauvageot,
Paris. Pages 63, 64, 65: © Hudson's Bay Company,
Winnipeg. Page 69: © Muñoz de Pablos, Paris.
Page 70 (top): © Boyer Viollet, Paris, Bibliothèque de
l'Arsenal. Pages 72, 74: UNESCO-Ivette Fabri.
Pages 75, 76, 77: UNESCO-Peru Tourist Office.
Pages 78-79, 80: Delegation of Oman to UNESCO.
Page 79: © Robert Harding Picture Library, London.
81
]]>
</page>
<page number="82">
<![CDATA[
RECENT RECORDS
listening
FOLK
Les nouvelles polyphonies corses.
CD Philips 81885-2
This CD is an example of the
worldwide trend to update and
revitalize folk music. It features
Corsican vocal music traditionally
performed a capella but here
accompanied by Manu Dibango,
Ryuichi Sakamoto and other
musicians mainly associated with
pop music. It might seem sacrilege
to provide instrumental backing, but
this in no way detracts from the
superb voices of the Bonifacio
church singers. A rough poetry
("Onda", "Terra Brusgiata"), true to
the spirit of Corsica, is distilled by
this music whose beauty matches
that of Bulgarian music, better
known internationally.
Radio Bratislava.
CD Philips 848 207-2
This is an anthology of the finest
examples of folk music broadcast
on the radio stations of Eastern
Europe (Prague, Budapest, Sofia,
Thessalonica, Skopje, Warsaw,
Helsinki, etc.) that have taken part
in the Bratislava Radio contest over
the past twenty-odd years. The
pieces, which are seldom
performed on the radio, range from
the fiery to the melancholic.
Especially noteworthy are an epic
song from western Bulgaria and a
wistful melody performed by
herdsmen of central Slovakia. The
instruments played include the
cymbalum, associated with gypsy
music, and the domra. At a time
when things are moving in Eastern
Europe, this welcome recording
serves to remind us how rich and
varied is its musical heritage.
POPULAR
Gerardo Nuñez.
Flamencos en Nueva York
CD VeraBra No. 28
The new German label VeraBra
seems to go in for eclectic musical
forms, as reflected in the title of
this CD. The title song, described
as a "rumba", ¡s a successful
marriage of flamenco and salsa.
"Mi patio" is a tango, but
modernized and adapted to the
tastes of young people in Argentina
Q¿. today. "A Gill Evans" (presumably
a misspelling of Gil Evans, who
worked with Miles Davis), has a
jazzy flavour, while most of the
other compositions are closer to
traditional bulerías, alegrías and
sevillanas. The guitar playing is
quite dazzling.
JAZZ	
Tom Harrell. Forms.
Harrell (trumpet, flugelhorn), Joe
Lovano (tenor sax.), Danilo Pérez
(piano), Charlie Haden (bass), Paul
Motian (drums).
CD Contemporary/Carrère
9031-73600-2
Harrell is a young trumpeter who
is increasingly in demand, both for
the quality of his playing and for
his compositions. The title of this
CD is "Forms", which is very
appropriate to this dense, lyrical
and highly structured music, which
is also of a consistently high
quality. Harrell is the leader on this
session, but Danilo Pérez arouses
the most admiration. Pérez, a
23-year-old from Panama whose
first recording this is, is Dizzy
Gillespie's current pianist and has to
be heard to be believed. An
exponent of a polytonal, polymodal,
"modern" style of jazz, he is an
attentive accompanist and virtuoso
soloist who has well and truly
assimilated the lessons of the
pianists who came before him. But
his rhythmic inventions are most
fully brought into play in Latin jazz
and I hope that it won't be too
long before he is given an
opportunity to record in this vein,
which is perfectly suited to his
temperament.
The Branford Marsalis Quartet
featuring Terence Blanchard.
Mo Better Blues.
Marsalis (sax.), Kenny Kirkland
(piano), Robert Hurst (bass), Jeff
Watts (drums), Terence Blanchard
(trumpet), Cynda Williams (vocals).
CD CBS 467160 2
The best thing about Spike Lee's
latest film "Mo Better Blues" was
Its soundtrack. Marsalis, Blanchard
and their rhythm sectionall
seasoned musicians despite
their youthare producing
some of the best jazz around,
tightly scored and, on some
tracks, full of bounce, in the
good old Dixieland tradition.
A special word of praise for
Cynda Williams, who also acts in
the film and who gives a vibrant
rendering of the old W.C. Handy
number "Harlem Blues" In a
sparkling new arrangement for
strings by pianist Claire Fisher.
Isabelle Leymarie
Ethnomusicologist and Journalist
CLASSICAL
Maximilien Koibe. Opera by
Dominique Probst, libretto by
Eugène Ionesco.
Andréa Snarski, Paul Gerimon,
Pierre Danais, Vicenzo Sanso.
Conductor Olivier Holt.
CD Cybelia CY 879
The Cybelia record company is
trying to make French music better
known, and particularly the music
of living composers. Dominique
Probst was born in 1954 in a family
of musicians. A percussionist, he
has composed a great deal for the
theatre and it was therefore natural
that, after many changes of
direction, he should try his hand at
opera when seeking to forge his
own style. The libretto by the writer
Eugène Ionesco is based on the
martyrdom of Father Kolbe, who in
1941 gave his life to save a
prisoner at Auschwitz. After
Shostakovich, Schoenberg, Britten,
Penderecki and a few other lesser
composers, Probst in his turn
denounces the horrors of Nazism.
First performed in Italy in 1988, this
ambitious work was originally
commissioned by the Paris Opera
House. Although in live
performance the work is not always
entirely convincing, on record it
comes over with an impressive
simplicity and authenticity.
A NEW EMI COLLECTION:
"L'ESPRIT FRANÇAIS"
Gounod.
Symphonies Nos. 1 and 2.
Orchestre du Capitole de Toulouse,
conducted by Michel Plasson.
CD EMI 7639492
Vincent d'lndy.
Symphonie sur un chant
montagnard cévenol/
Symphony No. 2.
Orchestre de Paris et du Capitole,
conducted by Serge Baudo and
Michel Plasson.
CD EMI 7639522
Ishtar/Wallenstein/La forêt
enchantée.
Orchestre philharmonique des Pays
de Loire, conducted by Pierre
Dervaux.
CD EMI 7639532
Henri Dutilleux.
Le Loup.
Orchestre symphonique des
Concerts du Conservatoire,
conducted by Georges Prêtre.
CD EMI 7639452 (with Poulenc and
Milhaud)
The famous label EMI/HMV is
reissuing its treasures of
nineteenth- and twentieth-century
French music. As we know all too
well, everybody loves French music
except the French. This people,
particularly sensitive when its sense
of national pride is at stake, seems
however to be changing its attitude.
Gounod is not just the composer of
"Faust"; he wrote two symphonies
under the influence of the classical
composers, particularly
Mendelssohn. A far cry from
Berlioz, Gounod was true to a
tradition and contributed to it. As
for Vincent d'lndy, he seemed to
have sunk without a trace. However,
the work of this nationalist
composer marked by Wagner
reveals a refined lyricism. His
second symphony is to be
savoured, especially for its mystery.
Also to be rediscovered are the
symphonic fragments from Henri
Dutilleux's ballet "Le Loup", which
enjoyed great success when first
performed by Roland Petit In 1953.
This appealing work sheds valuable
light on the development of one of
the great twentieth-century masters.
Other CDs in this collection are
devoted to Castillon and Rabaud,
Poulenc and Pierné, Koechline and
Messiaen. It will be interesting to
see what other treasures lie in
store. . . .
Beethoven. Symphony No. 2.
Brahms. Variations on a theme of
Haydn.
Marlboro Festival Orchestra,
conducted by Pablo Casals.
CD Sony Classical SMK 46247
Schubert. Quintet D. 956. The
shepherd on the rock.
Benita Valente, Harold Wright,
Rudolf Serkin.
CD Sony Classical SMK 45901
Schoenberg. Serenade op. 24
Chamber symphony No. 1 op. 9
Marlboro Festival soloists.
CD Sony Classical SMK 45894
In 1954 a group of musicians
including Adolf Busch, Marcel
Moyse and Rudolf Serkin founded
the Marlboro Festival in Vermont
(U.S.A.). The aim was to provide a
place where musicians, whether
recognized masters or promising
young talents, world famous or
unknown, could come together and
play purely for the pleasure of it,
without there being any kind of
pecking order. The celebrated
cellist Pablo Casals honoured the
Festival with his presence from
1960 to 1973. He is featured as
conductor on the first of
these CDs where he reveals a
luminous poetry which also
pervades the other recordings.
Each one is a gem that does full
justice to the composer
represented and brilliantly illustrates
one of the most marvellous musical
events of our time.
Claude dayman
Journalist and music critic
]]>
</page>
<page number="83">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
Theme of the next issue:
Published monthly In 35 languages and In braille
by UNESCO, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-ln-chlef: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Pari!)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin. Michael Fineberg
French edition: Alain Lévéque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, (Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel.: 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Administrative assistant: Prithi Perera
Selection In Braille In English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Metra ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Slnhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88),
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo. Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk, Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65),
Mall: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 139 French francs. 2 years: 259 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 108 French francs. 2 years: 194 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of UNESCO
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the UNESCO Courier".
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name Non-copyright
Photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply ceupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinipns pf the authors
and dp not necessarily represent the opinipns pf UNESCO pr those
of the editors of the UNESCO Courier Photo captipns and headlines
are written by the UNESCO Courier staff. The boundaries on maps |
published m the magazine dp npt imply official endorsement or
acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations. The UNESCO Courier
is produced in microform (microfilm and'or microfiche) by: (1) UNESCO,
7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris: (2) University Microfilms (Xerox),
Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100. U.S.A : (3)N.C.R. Microcard Edition. Indian
Head. Inc.. 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell
Co.. Old Mansfield Road, Wooster. Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) - DEPOT LEGAL : Cl - AOÛT/SEPTEMBRE 1991
COMMISSION PARITAIRE NP 71844 DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP.
Photocomposition The UNESCO Courier
Photogravure-impression: Maury Imprimeur S.A.
Z.I. route d'Etampes. 45330 Malesherbes.
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 8/9 1991 -0PI-91 -3-495/496 A
plus an interview with Colombian writer
GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ
Nobel laureate for literature (1982)
g by Anamlka Pual (aged 5, India). © The International Museum of Children's Art, Oslo.
]]>
</page>
<page number="84">
<![CDATA[
Wii
/
m
f ^fcr'
]]>
</page>
</document>
