<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="090699eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for pubiication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two worl<s from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some stril<ing connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
Textiles at Monte Aibán
1991, gouache on paper (11 x 7.5 cm)
by Cliristian Olivé
At Monte Albán, a pre-Columbian site in iVlexico's
Oaxaca valley, Indians spread out on the ground
colourful clothes w/hich they weave to sell to
tourists. A visit to the site inspired the French
painter Christian Olivé to paint this gouache on
grainy paper which evokes the weave of Indian
cloth.
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
FEBRUARY 1992 CON NTS
Interview with
JOSEPH KI-ZERBO
The Unesco
¿-^COURIER
45th YEAR
Published monthly In 36 languages and In Braille
"The Governments of the States
parties to this Constitution on behaif
of their peopies deciare,
"that since wars begin in the minds
of men, it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded, if it is not to
fall, upon the intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect l<nowledge of
each other's lives...".
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of UNESCO,
London, 16 November 1945
APARTHEID
THE BEGINNING OF THE END
UNESCO'S FIRST
45 YEARS (Part V)
!/)> Michel Conil Lacoste
THE MAKING OF A TRAGEDY
//)' Macadou Ndiaye
A RETURN TO SOUTH AFRICA
hy Ruth Lazarus
WHICH MODEL OF DEMOCRACY?
by Alhic Sachs
STATE OF TRANSITION
hy Gerald Gordori and Dennis Davis
THE FUTURE OF WOMEN
by I-'atima Mcer
RACIAL DISCRIMINATION
IN CULTURAL LIFE
by Sipho Sepamla
PEOPLE'S LITERATURE
Iry Nadine Gordimcr
THE UN'S LONG CAMPAIGN
AGAINST APARTHEID
UNESCO AND THE ELIMINATION
OF APARTHEID
/zy ¡rancine ¡'ournia'
16
20
23
28
30
33
35
40
44
Cover:
A multi-racial school in South
Africa.
Back cover:
An anti-apartheid poster
commissioned by the United
Nations calls for a new South
Africa.
The Editors
wish to thank
Ms. Carrie Marias, of
UNESCO's Division
of Human Rights and
Peace, and Ms. Ruth
Lazarus for their help
in the preparation
of this issue.
A CHRONOLOGY OF REPRESSION
AND RESISTANCE 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S FIRST 45 YEARS (M \l)
by Michel Conil Lacoste
The impact of the Experiment!
World Literacy Programme
im
General policy
The United Nations University is established
in Tokyo under the joint auspices of the United
Nations and UNESCO.
A conference is held in Pans on the educational
problems of the 25 least developed countries.
A group of experts commissioned to evaluate
funttional literacy work carried out in 11 Member
States since 1967 presents its report, which is pub¬
lished the following year by UNESCO and the
United Nations Development Programme
(UNDP). Its conclusion: the Experimental World
Literacy Programme has had mixed results, but
has yielded important lessons for the future.
Exact and natural sciences
The Intergovernmental Co-ordinating Council
of the international Hydrological Programme
(IHP) meets for the first time. The IHP follows up
the work of the International Hydrological
Decade, putting emphasis on methodology and
training in the rational management of water
resources.
A World Network of JVIicro biological Resource
Centres (MIRCENs) is established, with branches
in Bangkok, Brisbane, Dakar, Guatemala City,
Cairo, Nairobi and Porto Alegre (Brazil).
A meeting of experts on the ethical problems
posed by recent advances in biology is held at
Varna in Bulgaria. Btology and Ethws, a publication
based on the proceedings of the meeting, marks
a notable advance in thinking on the subject.
Culture
An Advisory Committee for the Study of
Oceanic Cultures is set up to promote research
into the cultures of the Pacific.
sconces «t»«"*^
m
General policy
The General Conference, held in Nairobi, is
opened by Jomo Kenyatta, President of the
Republic of Kenya. It decides to create a Drafting
and Negotiating Group to seek consensus solu¬
tions to sensitive questions.
The Conference adopts a Medium-Term Plan
for 1977-1982.
A General Information Programme is inau¬
gurated to regroup activities relating to the
exchange of scientific and technological informa¬
tion, covered by UNISIST, and those dealing
with the planning of national library, archive and
documentation infrastructures, covered by
NATIS (National Information Systems).
Education
The General Conference adopts a Recommen¬
dation on the development of adult education
that enshrines the concept of lifelong education,
defined as follows, that UNESCO has helped to
propagate: "Education and learning, far from
being limited to the period of attendance at
school, should extend throughout life, include
all skills and branches of knowledge, use all pos¬
sible means, and give the opportunity to all
people for full development of the personality."
The first international conference of ministers
and senior civil servants responsible for physical
education and sport in the training of young
people is held in Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Exact and natural sciences
After 12 years' work, UNESCO completes
publication of the Geological World Atlas, pre¬
pared in collaboration with the International
Geological Congress's Commission for the Geo¬
logical Map of the World.
Social sciences
A meeting of experts on inter-regional co¬
operation in the social sciences is held in Paris.
Culture
In Nairobi, the General Conference adopts a
Recommendation concerning popular participa¬
tion in cultural life.
An advisory committee for Arab culture is
established.
Communication
San José, the capital of Costa Rica, hosts the
first in a series of regional intergovernmental con¬
ferences on communications policies. Others will
later be held m Kuala Lumpur (1979), Yaounde
(1980), and Khartoum (1987).
UNESCO contributes to the establishment in
Nairobi of the African Council on Communi¬
cation Education. Initially grouping 19 institu¬
tions, the Council now has 65 members.
UNESCO uses a communications satellite for
the first time during a session of the General
Conference.
Events
Two Nobel Peace Prize winners, Willy Brandt
and Philip Noel-Baker, and Alfred Kastler, Nobel
laureate for physics, take part in a Round Table
organized by UNESCO on the theme of "Cul¬
tural and Intellectual Co-operation and the New
International Economic Order". Other par¬
ticipants included Nancy Reeves, Tewfik al-
Hakim, P.-M. Henry, Samir Amin, Jean d'Or-
messon, Yannis Xenakis, Buckminster Fuller and
Peter Ustinov.
Opposite page, from top:
Mauritania's Zravié dam Is one of
several that liave been repaired by
the iViauritanian rurai engineering
service with the aid of a joint
OPEC/UNESCO project; French edition
of a worl< published by UNESCO on
the techniques of information and
documentation (2nd edition, revised
and expanded, 1990); a poster of the
International Fund for Physical
Education and Sport (1985).
This page, from top:
Han Suyin, writer; Willy Brandt,
politician; Iannis Xenal<is, composer.
Wl
Education
An Intergovernmental Conference on
Environmental Education is held in Tbilisi,
USSR, under the joint auspices of UNESCO and
the United Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP).
Culture
UNESCO contributes to the Festival of
African Arts (FESTAC) in Lagos.
Communication
The Asia-Pacific Institute for Broadcasting
Development is established in Kuala Lumpur
(Malaysia) to train broadcasters.
The International Commission for the Study
of Communication Problems starts work under
the presidency of Ireland's Sean MacBride. Its
report. Many Voices, One World (1980), will be
published in 17 languages.
Events
A Round Table on "The Challenge of the
Year 2000" is attended by Han Suyin, Michel
Jobert, André Fontaine, Prem Kirpal, Alicia
Penalba and others.
im
General policy
UNESCO has 145 Member States, 129 of
them with National Commissions.
The first World Congress of UNESCO Clubs
is held at UNESCO's Paris headquarters.
Education
A Regional Centre for Higher Education in
Latin America and the Caribbean is established
in Caracas.
The General Conference sets up an Inter¬
governmental Committee for Physical Education
and Sport to orient and supervise UNESCO acti¬
vités in this field. The Committee adopts an inter¬
national Charter and creates a fund to promote
the development of sport and physical educatiim.
Working in collaboration with the International
Council of Sport Science and Physical Education
and the International Council for Health, Phys¬
ical Education and Recreation, UNESCO focuses
on the role of sport in education and the role
of education in sport.
Exact and natural sciences
UNESCO completes publication of the Soil
Map ofthe World, the fruit of 17 years' work in
collaboration with the Food and Agriculture
Organization of the United Nations.
An Intergovernmental Conference on Strate¬
gics and Policies for Informatics is held at Tor-
rcmolinos (Spain).
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
L* eft, a drawing
"^ommissioned from the
""tomanian-born French
"''rtist André François for
U^INESC0 poster on the
""licit transfer of cultural
P"iroperty.
'"llight, the Egyptian socia
><=cientist Aziza Hussein.
Teaching Human Rights
Social sciences
To mark the 30th anniversary of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights, an international
congress on the the teaching of human rights is
held in Vienna. Panels of experts meeting in Í979
and 1982 work with the International Institute
for Human Rights, based at Strasbourg (France),
to develop a programme. The plan eventually
adopted by UNESCO includes a section on
women's rights.
Culture
The General Conference approves the statutes
of the Intergovernmental Committee for
Promoting the Return of Cultural Property to
its Countries of Origin or its Restitution in Case
of Illicit Appropriation.
A meeting of scholars is held in Port-au-Prince
(Haïti) on the African slave trade from the 15th
to the 19th century.
The General Conference decides on the prepa¬
ration of a History ofthe Civilizations ofCentral
Asia.
Communication
After several years of difficuh discussions, the
General Conference adopts the Declaration on
Fundamental Principles concerning the Contri¬
bution of the Mass Media to Strengthening Peace
and International Understanding, to the Promo¬
tion of Human Rights and to Countering
Racialism, Apartheid and Incitement to War.
A UNESCO-UNDP Programme leads to the
creation of an Institute of Mass Communications
at the University of Nigeria, Lagos.
Events
A Round Table is held at UNESCO head¬
quarters in Paris to commemorate the 23rd cente¬
nary of the death of Aristotle. Participants include
Helene Ahrweiler, M. Arkoun, J. Beaufret, J.
Berque, J. Dausset, D. Dubarle, J. Merleau-Ponty,
E. Moutsopoulos, R. Thorn. A notable contri¬
bution is made by Jacques Lacan.
im
Exact and natural sciences
Two reports summarizing the existing state of
knowledge about tropical forest ecosystems and
tropical grazing-land ecosystems are published
under the joint auspices of UNESCO, the United
Nations Environment Programme and the Food
and Agriculture Organization of the United
Nations.
The International Soil Museum (now the
International Soil Reference and Information
Centre) is officially opened at Wageningen in the
Netherlands. It was established as a result of co¬
operation between UNESCO, the Netherlands
government and the FAO.
Socta) sciences
A meeting of experts held in Quito (Ecuador)
to study "Research on the Idea of Integrated
Development" leads to the publication of A new
concept ofdevelopment: basic tenets, by Francois
Perroux, in 1981.
Culture
The editorial committee of a series on studies
on Different Aspects ofIslamic Culture, financed
by a donation from the Islamic Call Society,
holds its first meeting.
The consultative committee for the study of
Malay cultures is enlarged to address the cultures
of Southeast Asia.
Communication
UNESCO and the International Telecommu¬
nications Union (ITU) set up a working party
to examine international telecommunications
charges, a common obstacle to the exchange of
information.
Events
A Peace Forum organized by UNESCO and
the International Council for Philosophy and
Humanistic Studies brings together Yevgeny
Yevtushenko, Aziza Hussein, Yuri Zhukov, Sean
MacBride, Daniel Oduber, Edgar Faure, Philip
Noel-Baker, M.L. Mehrotra, Helen Vlachos and
others.
Within the framework of International Anti-
Apartheid Year, Miriam Makeba sings in
UNESCO's main conference hall.
General policy
At the 21st session of the General Conference,
held in Belgrade, Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
becomes the fir.si Director-General to be re¬
elected unanimously.
For 1980, UNESCO spends $61,510,230 of
UNDP funds to the benefit of its Member States.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The General Conference examines the case of
a staff member prevented from returning to his
post at UNESCO on political grounds, and
adopts a resolution on the independence of the
international civil service.
Education
The International Panel on the Future
Development of Education holds its first meeting
in Paris. Participating bodies include the Inter¬
national Association of Universities and the
World Confederation of Organizations of the
Teaching Profession.
Exact and natural sciences
Eight major regional scientific projects are
launched on: applied biotechnology and microbi¬
ology (Africa and the Arab states); technological
research, training and development (South-east
Asia); geology for development (Africa); the
management of water resources in rural areas
(Latin America; the Arab States); the integrated
management of humid tropical zones (inter¬
regional); arid and semi-arid regions (inter¬
regional) and coastal ecosystems (inter-regional).
Social sciences
A World Congress on Disarmament Educa¬
tion is held in Paris.
A symposium is held in Paris on Human
Rights in Urban Areas (the same theme will be
discussed again in Cairo in 1982).
A meeting of experts on Teaching and
Research in Philosophy in Africa is held in
Nairobi (similar meetings will be held for Asia
in 1983 and for Latin America in 19851.
Culture
The General Conference adopts the Recom¬
mendation concerning the Status of the Artist.
The Nubian campaign comes to an end with
the inauguration of the temples of the island of
Philae on their new site on the nearby island of
Agilkia.
The first volumes of the. General History of
Africa are published: Methodology and African
Prehistory and Ancient Civilizations ofAfrica. Six
further volumes are planned.
Controversy over Communication
Communication
Following the series of regional intergovern¬
mental conferences on communications policies,
and in line with the directives of the 20th ses¬
sion of the General Conference, UNESCO con¬
venes a special meeting of Member States, the
International Conference for Communication
Development (DEVCOM), in Paris.
Taking up a DEVCOM recommendation, the
21st session of the General Conference decides
to launch an International Programme for the
Development of Communication (IPDC), the
goal of which is to correct the imbalances, above
all between North and South, in communication
infrastructures and capacities.
The General Conference invites the Director
General to carry out studies relating to the estab¬
lishment of a new world information and com¬
munication order. Two Round Tables on this
theme, jointly organized by UNESCO and the
United Nations, will be held at Igls (Austria) in
1983 and in Copenhagen three years later. A long
and stormy public controversy, partly rooted in
misunderstandings, will ensue until the General
Conference proposes a new communications
policy based on a broader consensus in 1989.
Events
Pope John Paul II visits UNESCO head¬
quarters in Pans. In his address he says, "Yes,
the future of mankind depends on culture! Yes,
world peace depends on Ûie primacy ofthe Spirit!
Yes, the peaceful future of mankind depends on
love! Your contribution ... is vital. It consists
in adopting the correct approach to the problems
with which you have to wrestle. My final word
is this: Do not abandon the struggle! Continue
thout ceasing
A series of conferences on Islam, philosophy
and the sciences are held in Paris.
Left, inauguration of the monuments of the island
of Philae (Egypt) after they had been transferred
to a new site.
Above: Bhutan's radio service, which went on the
air in the 1970s, has received aid from UNESCO
in the framework of the international Programme
for the Development of Communication (IPDC).
TO BE CONTINUED
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
JOSEPH KI-ZERBO
talks to Bahgat EInadi and Adel Rifaat
A former member of UNESCO's Executive Board artd a member
of the Council of the United Nations University, Joseph Ki-Zerbo has an international
reputation as a historian of Africa. He Is the author of many articles and books,
including a history of black Africa (1972) that has been translated
into eight languages, and was editor of volume 1 of UNESCO's
General History of Africa (1981)*. In 1990 he published Educate or Perish
(UNESCO/UNICEF, L'Harmattan, París,). In this interview he corrects some
widespread misconceptions about African history.
* Co-published with Heinemann Educational Books Ltd., United Kingdom, and
the University of California Press, Berkeley, U.S.A.
You have been one of the architects of
UNESCO's monumental General History of
Africa project. How does writing the history
of Africa differ from writing the history of
other continents?
Historians all over the world perform vir¬
tually the same social function. Their mental
processes and methods are generally similar.
But insofar as the subject being studied is
somewhat different in Africa, then the logic
they follow and the methodological principles
they employ must be adapted. Some principles
and criteria have to be redefined to fit into the
African context.
We also have to take into account the
methods developed by those who performed
the historian's function in our precolonial
societies. One can't just forget them and say,
as has been done in the past, that "there is no
African philosophy since there were no
philosophers before the ones who were tramed
at the Sorbonne." That is the wrong way of
looking at the problem.
Precolonial African historians at least tried
to situate man in time, even if they did not
always succeed in domg so. On the other hand
we should not go to the other extreme of
claiming we are so different from the rest of
the world that we must adopt different mathe¬
matical or scientific principles from theirs! The
fact is that it is impossible to grasp our situa¬
tion simply by importing knowledge as it has
been developed in the West.
Let me give you two examples of what I
mean. The first concerns the oral tradition as
a historical source. During work sessions
organized at UNESCO in connection with
the History of Africa project, we had an
opportunity to give due regard to this source
which Europeans had tended to consider as
irrational. We showed that it could be a
rational tool with which to study history. In
return this has also influenced historical
research in the European countries themselves.
A proof that the intellectual flow is not just
one-way. . . .
The second example concerns traditional
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
A àmcracj kd on tk mátutimd diàritj oftk Africm ijM mid niâk
Africa a crdèk mmkr ofd new pknetarj pârtn&éip,
African medicines, which are also a subject of
historical research. African medicine has
stressed the importance of some principles,
such as the psychosomatic effects of certain
substances, which Western countries have
tended to neglect. In other words African
countries contain reserves of rationality, of
logical principles, which might well open up
new horizons in various fields of knowledge.
That, in my opinion, is the right approach.
Let's take from Europe but let's give some¬
thing back in return. To say that we must start
from scratch would be to accept a kind of
mental apartheid.
Let's get back to the oral tradition. Ham-
pâté Bâ used to say that when an old man
dies in Africa, a library disappears. What is
the precise value of the oral tradition as a
historical source?
There are a substantial number of oral texts,
but they have been neglected because the his¬
tory of Africa was for centuries viewed exclu¬
sively from the outside. And yet they are
extremely valuable because they come from
within Africa. Of course they need to be care¬
fully sifted and subjected to critical analysis
before they can be considered as credible
evidence.
The oral tradition takes different forms.
The most sophisticated form, and the one
closest to written documents, is what is
known as the institutionahzed or formalized
text. In some cases, monarchical and dynastic
structures have existed in Africa for 500 or a
thousand years. In these cases, a body of State
functionaries -^yith the responsibility of
administering the collective memory gradually
came to be established. Sometimes they were
known as griots; in Mali they were called dyeli;
elsewhere they had other names. But these
griots had nothing in common with the
"griots" who pander to the modern tourists'
appetite for the exotic. They were State func¬
tionaries.
Thus, among the Moose, in Burkina Faso,
in Mali, or in the kingdom of Abomey, what
is now Benin, there were organized corpora¬
tions which were responsible for managing the
collective memory. The members of these cor¬
porations were trained in specific places, each
of which had its own traditions. In these places
masters taught their pupils a curriculum that
took several years to complete. This process
had to be followed before the student could
become a full member of the corps of griots.
All this is well described in Djibril Tamsir
Niane's book about the western Sudan.
In these cases, we can be sure that the
process of transmission was correct. Even so,
the content must be subjected to a series of
internal and external analyses to check its con¬
sistency. If, for example, two warring peoples
give the same version of the same battle, there
is a strong likehhood that the version is
accurate. If a vanquished people admits in its
oral tradition that it has been defeated, there
are also good grounds for believing that such
a defeat actually took place. On the other
hand, conflicts between rival princes jockeying
for power within the same society may give
rise to different versions, special oral tradi¬
tions. In such a case the different accounts can
be compared in the same way as written docu¬
ments. Comparison makes it possible to reach
a hypothesis that can be labelled "certain",
"probable" or "possible", as the case may be.
The oral tradition is subjected to precisely this
kind of eminently rational criticism.
To give you an idea of just how reliable
these texts may be, in the land of the Moose,
in Burkina Faso, the head griot had to recite
the genealogical list of the "Mogho-Naaba"
every day! It was out of the question that he
should forget it. This knowledge was passed
on, for the head griot practiced his craft until
he died or was removed from office. Each day
he had to make this connection with the past.
And he trembled as he did so, for the slightest
error could cost him his life. If he forgot a
name or wrongly attributed an act to someone
who had not performed it, he was immedi¬
ately taken to task by his audience, who acted
as a vigilant jury and guaranteed the accuracy
of what he said. Exactly the same thing hap¬
pened at the court of the king of Abomey.
Other traditions were less explicit, less
stereotyped. One example is the "Sundiata
fasa"the history or eulogy of Sundiata, a
hero from the early history of Mali in the thir¬
teenth century. We know about him from
other, Arab sources, especially from Ibn Bat-
tuta, who visited Mali in the fourteenth cen¬
tury. The cycle describes a cluster of events
that evoke certain economic, social, political
and religious structures. The stories are
chanted to the accompaniment of instruments
kept specially for the purpose. They may seem
epic and purely legendary, but in some cases
they are corroborated by the written docu¬
ments. In fact sometimes they flesh out or
even correct the written record.
What was the relationship with time? Was
there a single notion of time, or several? One
gets the impression that tribal time is cyclical,
made up of endless renewals, all linked to a
cosmogonie overview. Yet you have been
talking ofdynasties and successions. How are
these two concepts of time linked?
I think that in the African system the two
are combined. The cyclical aspect is very
important, especially in agrarian societies. Not
that these societies lacked either leaders or
State structures. Each one had a government
and its own administrative conventions.
Nevertheless, these were peasant societies sub¬
jected to a cyclical rhythm. But even in them,
there is reason to believe that people were not
enmeshed in a process of eternal recurrence
which is implicit in certain philosophies that
accept the idea of reincarnation.
Take this episode from an African cos¬
mogony, which was quoted by the late Ham-
pâté Bâ: "God created man in order to have
an interlocutor, a companion with whom to
speak." These words, and the status they
accord to mankind, imply that our role is not
merely to go on repeating the same actions.
That is the message of the African version of
the Prometheus myth, according to which
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
A murai decoration by
the South African artist Johanna iVIkwebani
in the KwaNdebeie bantustan.
God invented fire to warm his mother, then
man discovered the fire and carried it off. Thus
began an epic chase between God and man,
which lasted until the day God stopped and
saw in man his equal and his brother. Such
is the grandeur of the human condition.
To return to the conception of time,
Africans say that tomorrow must be better
than today and claim that those who have
lived longer possess more wisdom and
knowledge. In medicine, for example, anyone
who inherits knowledge is expected to add
something new himself. So the idea of an
accumulation of knowledge is to some extent
accepted, but it serves the common good and
not just the individualthis is very important.
This was both a great strength and a weak¬
ness of the African system.
The idea ofaccumulation as a community-
based concept brings us to the idea ofchange.
How was change regarded? Was it controlled?
Despised? Feared?
It has often been said that the African only
repeats what his ancestors did. This is one
principle, but it is not the only one. It is reduc¬
tionist to limit Africans to this dimension. In
Africa there has been change as well as con¬
tinuity.
The first thing to remember is that all
Africans do not have the same social situation.
Some people maintain that there were no
social classes in Africa, others say that even
if there were, they did not radically call social
structures in question. This is to some extent
true, for we have not reached the stage of
industrial capitalismeven though we helped
it to become estabHshed in Europe! Neverthe¬
less, differences of status have existed, and con¬
sequently conflicts which could generate cer¬
tain kinds of change.
Let me give you two examples from
African history. The first is that of Biton
Kulubali, king of Segou. He owes his impor¬
tance to the fact that he introduced a personal
tax. He also created a professional army,
which had not existed before, and a collégial
system of leadership. This is a specific case of
a transition due to the inventiveness and
creativity of a leader who was literally an initi¬
ator of history.
The other example, that of Shaka, is better
known. The rise of Shaka was an amazing
phenomenon that changed the destiny of
entire peoples in southern Africa, by amal¬
gamating them into the Zulu nation. There
was a concept of nationhood. Some people
have talked in terms of a "pre-nation", but
there were real nations, even if they did not
have all the attributes or external signs of
nationhood that existed in Western
countriesalthough even in the West nation¬
hood developed at different times in different
countries and regions.
Shaka gave a common name to all those
who had been brought together by war and
conquest. He transformed the army by
changing its weapons, turning it into a body
equipped only with hand-arms for hand-to-
hand fighting. Later he introduced a strategic
system based on age. The youngest soldiers
were posted in the vanguard and on the flanks
so that they could attack and envelop the
enemy. Behind them were the men of mature
years who bore the brunt of the main shock.
The oldest waited in the rear, ready to carry
out other missions if necessary. This was the
"buffalo-head" order of battle whereby Shaka
revolutionized the art of war. Unfortunately,
he ended up as a dictator.
Even so, Africans felt an almost visceral
attachment to the past, and this was linked to
the oral tradition. In countries where history
is a matter of books, written documents and
archives, there is a kind of distance, a detach¬
ment from the past. In Africa, however,
people remained so closely bound to the
spoken tradition with its cargo of familiar
names that history tended to be transmuted
into common property, proclaimed and
reproclaimed from generation to generation.
Is it possible to pinpoint a moment that saw
the emergence of an African consciousness,
transcending not only the consciousness of
tribes and clans but that of States and
empires? Was the shock caused hy the slave
trade a moment of this type?
Objectively, yes. I would say that there was
a continent-wide dawning of awareness, in the
sense that almost all African societies at the
time of the slave trade shared a feeling of alie¬
nation, of self-deprivation. But how can one
talk of a subjective pan-African conscience?
How could It be propagated and diffused? You
must bear in mind the immensity of the con¬
tinent and the natural obstacles within it. The
miraculous thing is that truly pan-African ele¬
ments did eventually emerge and coalesce in
spite of these barriers.
When I first went to Northern Rhodesia,
what is now Zambia, one evening I heard
through the window of my hotel room a tom¬
tom rhythm from a distant part of the city
that was exactly the same as that of my home
villageso much so that I started dancing!
There definitely are elements of unity.
But let me get back to the natural
obstacles, which were for long virtually
impassable. The great equatorial forest, for
example, might have been a melting pot of
social innovations and technologies, but it was
an obstacle all the same. The Sahara too was
a barrier that filtered and slowed down com¬
munication. All of which meant that the
dawning of pan-African awareness was bound
to be a slow process. In other words, even if
all Africans felt the same thing at the same
time, this common sentiment could not be
transformed into a collective desire to take
action. Not to mention the internal
contradictionsthat some Africans were set
against others, by encouraging ethnic conflicts
and in other ways.
m Asa historian ofAfrica, what is your aim
today? Is it just to carry out research and then
to analyse what happened in the past? Or do
you want to draw conclusions, find lessons for
the future?
The answer to this question is immense. On
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
the one hand there is the problem of the
historian's craft. On the other, the idea that
peoples have of history. And thirdly, the dis¬
tinction to be made between real history as
it unfolded and the history we try to recon¬
stitute: the representation of history as
fashioned by historians.
First of all I should like to make a distinc¬
tion between the journalist and the historian.
I'm thinking of what is called instant history.
Communications today are so rapid that
historians feel swept along by the demand and
the need to describe immediately events that
have just happened. Popular works of instant
history appear a matter of months, sometimes
just weeks, after the events they describe. This
kind of history is next door to journalism. But
the historian should be distinguished from the
journalist by a concern for the long term, by
the fact that he takes into consideration a spell
of time sufficient to indicate sustained con
tinuities and trends in events or structures
in short, a landscape beyond the present.
This concept of extent in time, not to say
in space, is one of the distinguishing elements.
There is also the matter of whether one is con¬
fined to the surface of events, to the waves
splashing before one's eyes, or whether one
is examining the deeper currents, the substruc¬
tures that explain the waves. This is the well-
known distinction between the Annales
school of historians and others concerned with
the history of events.
But it is also important to emphasize that
the historian is not independent of his or her
society. He responds to its needs, and even if
the latter seem subjective or personal they still
have a social dimension. The historian has not
dropped from the clouds. He belongs to a
many-faceted social context that leaves its
imprint on him, if only through his genetic
inheritance. The historian is not a kind of
independent judge dealing in abstractions. He
is more or less impHcated, if not committed,
in what he describes.
There was a time when historians had to
fulfill social obligations, such as passing on the
genealogy of kings or teaching princes ethics
via examples from the past, which is why
royal tutors in Europe at a certain period were
usually historians. Then came the develop¬
ment of nationhood, which produced
historians who primarily stressed the events
or the men that created the nation-state.
Now we are living in a period that con¬
cerns itself with structures, sometimes on their
own, some'times in combination with ideolo¬
gies. It was the Annales school, and my teacher
Fernand Braudel, that really opened up this
new space, this intellectual galaxy, to history.
I must say that the African historian can
really spread his wings here because of the
durability of the structures in our civilizations.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
One finds things which have not changed for
centuries, or which repeat themselves as they
were a hundred years ago. Over twenty years
ago I attended the enthronement of the moro
naaba. His grandson was enthroned recently,
and the sacred ritual was the same. But please
note that durability is not the same as immo¬
bility. The structures are never entirely fixed.
Things move, eventually. The important thing
is to analyse African realities in depth, to X-
ray the combination of factors which
introduces a process of mutation into a per¬
manent structure.
You have talked throughout this interview
ofpermanence and enduring structures, but
also ofnew departures and changes. African
society seems to be a mixture of the two. But
it is also clear that in the modern world, with
colonization and what has followed, the
processes of change have been accelerating.
In your opinion, what is the most important
change?^What is happening to communities
that were once based^ on permanence but have
been profoundly shaken in the last century?
How has the perception of African society
been transformed?
There have been at the same time
astonishing elements of continuity and also
rapid movements forward. Sometimes the
latter have been purposeless, mere aimless
avalanches, what's more, because they have
A reconstruction
of Ethiopia's Lower Omo
valley as it might have
appeared 2 million years
ago, based on
palaeontological research.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
been non-indigenous, brought in from the out¬
side. I think the period of the slave trade can
be considered as a haemorrhage which under¬
mined and exhausted the biological and social
forces of Africa.
But the fundamental change was coloni¬
zation. Colonizadon was a major amputation.
It was a brutal separation that cut its victims
off from many essential things, ft was an
enforced divorce from their own history, the
social structure they knew, their organized
civic identity: their society's particular way of
organizing space, the use of its language in the
main public places ... in short an ethnocide
punctuated by occasional genocides.
But out of this change, new things deve¬
loped: colonization, through a kind of
dialectic, made it possible to accomplish cer¬
tain things in Africa. For example, it created
large spaces containing numbers of commu¬
nities and established, sometimes by means of
massacres, a peace within them that recalled
the ancient "Pax Romana". But Africans did
not lose their creativity under colonization,
whatever some colonial historians might have
claimedhence the importance of an African
history viewed from within. In reality, many
supposedly "static" and passive societies kept
alive, developing processes that often led to
protest or even insurrection, until the Second
World War.
But this creativity, since the end of coloni¬
zation, hasn't merely sought to rediscover the
rhythm of the past. It also inevitably seeks to
innovate, to invent a future that isn't just a
repetition of what's gone before. . . .
Actually, the strategies of resistance have
often been similar in the colonial and the post-
colonial periods, for example in what is now
known as the "informal" sector of the
economy. The struggle for identity and
autonomy, which must not be confused with
a pig-headed rejection of change, has taken a
multitude of forms, the most obvious being
armed resistance. But even reputedly docile
leaders, called on to send their children to the
white man's school, often preferred to substi¬
tute the sons of their servants in order to cut
off their children from the foreign system.
Young people called up for mihtary service
or forced labour got out of it by migrating or
even by mutilating themselves.
As for religion, even in our own day it
is a bastion of resistance to the powers-that-
be. Africans have shown an audacious willing¬
ness to reinterpret faiths, to blend elements
of Christianity or Islam with traditional beliefs
and customs. Some marabouts, under cover
of inculcating a work-mystique in their pupils,
have become successful producers of cash
crops. African traders have used their own
methods and connections to seize market
share in the trade in colonial products. Tradi¬
tional healers have modernized the packaging
of their products, even the preparations they
sell. Rejecting imported legal codes, peasant
cadres have revived working groups based on
the old tribal age-groups. Herdsmen who have
always worked more or less without the idea
of profit have sold their animals on the
market.
But overall, in comparison with Asians
for example, the Africans adapt little and
adopt much. And for good reason. When you
have no autonomous industrial sector, the
creative imagination has Hmited room for
manoeuvre. . . .
The last few years have seen young people
rising in the name of liberty and democracy,
and some have been willing to die for these
ideas. Who are they? Where do they come
from?
These splendid young people are the fruit
of a long-standing system of disagregation.
They have been doubly trapped. Uprooted by
the potent influence of an exogenous school
system and by radio and television series
pouring out from the North, they have
become cut off from the African system of
rights and responsibilities. They are simultane¬
ously free and slaves; for they are entering the
modern market-place with tiny purchasing
power but an enormous appetite, whetted by
the media. Confronting them are dictators
who are often far less educated than they are,
but who have power and possessions 	 For
these young people, the past is blind, the
present is dumb and the future is deafi
In these conditions, the youth bomb is
bound to explode. The dictatorships don't
create jobs, except for policemen or torturers,
whose targets are these same young people.
But democracy is a delusion, a placebo, if
it is only a matter of outward forms. A multi¬
party system is a necessary but not a sufficient
condition. If other structural conditions are
not met, democracy is reduced to a skeleton,
a text without a context. Without the flesh of
a certain amount of development and the
blood of a minimum level of democratic cul¬
ture, there is a risk of falling into the bitter
disappointments that followed independence
and the blind race for economic growth.
Where are the programmes and social
projects of the hundreds of poHtical parties
that have mushroomed in Africa in the last
few years? Now that communism, which was
humanistic in theory but in fact crushed the
populations who came under its sway, is on
the way out, and capitalism is reveaHng its
many structural weaknesses, has the African
system really got nothing to offer? To take
one example, by what kind of social securky
system have Africans hitherto managed to
look after their children, their sick and their
old?
That is a form of constitutional solidarity
that may be a new boundary of civilization,
if civilization hopes to advance beyond today's
barbarian and suicidal selfishness. A
democracy based on that spirit of solidarity
could make Africa a credible member of a new
planetary partnership 	 On condition that
another equally essential precondition is met:
the integration of Africa, which alone can give
us access to major industries, that is the
capacity to harness our economy to a new set
of values marrying the best from elsewhere to
the flnest fruits of our own history.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
L
'' All human beings are horn free and equal in dignity and rights. They
EDITORiAL are endowed with reason and conscience and should act towards one
AHB another in a spirit of brotherhood.
Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
Article 1.
R.kACiSM has deep roots in human history. It emerges wherever
groups of people in situations of conflict defend their freedom and
their culture without respecting those of others, set themselves apart,
isolate themselves and attack one another in the name of ethnic
criteria. It speaks a language of exclusion, which leads naturally to
contempt and even hatred.
Institutionalized racism is a variant which is particularly odious
because it attempts to justify the business of enslavement in terms
of a philosophical and legal terminology which pretends to be "civi¬
lized". I am thinking here of the slave trade, which bled Africa so
that the cotton fields of the Americas could bloom; and also of
Nazism, which brought devastation to Europe for the greater glory
of the purported Aryan race.
During the Second World War, racism was unleashed in all its
murderous folly. The conflict was brought to an end thanks to the
mobihzation of the forces of freedom throughout the world and to
a growing realization of the danger this new form of barbarism
represented for humanity. The United Nations system was itself an
offspring of this new awareness. As the preamble to UNESCO's con¬
stitution declares, "the great and terrible war which has now ended
was a war made possible by the denial of the democratic principles
of the dignity, equality and mutual respect of men, and by the propa¬
gation, in their place, ... of the doctrine of the inequality of men
and races".
However, this doctrine was soon to reappear in the shape of apart¬
heid. A challenge to the universal values of human rights, it was able
to survive for almost half a century with the help of external com¬
plicities and reprehensible self-serving. But now the pillars of apart¬
heid are crumbling in their turn, beneath the blows of those who
have fought and are fighting for freedom in South Africa, in a world
14 context in which democratic values are finally coming into their own.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
For all those who, since the Second World War, have fought
unceasingly against racism, this represents a great victory for freedom.
It is also a clarion-call to pursue with increased confidence the struggle
against insidious new forms of racism that appear in the everyday
life of societies in the North and the South ahke whenever people
find it impossible to resolve their differences in a spirit of mutual
respect.
Only education brings freedom. It alone nourishes the roots of
behaviour and shapes attitudes of tolerance and solidarity. Only edu¬
cation in the love of others will one day lead to dialogue between
cultures and enable all the people of the Earth to live together in
peace. May that day come soon.
Federico Mayor
Director-General of UNESCO
A paper cut-out illustration by
the Brazilian artist Kinkas,
specially commissioned for
this issue of the UNESCO
Courier. 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
r Tfte flí^fcíng of a tragedy by Mâcadou Ndiaye
From the arrival of the first Dutch settlers to the be^nninès of apartheid
0,
16
MACADOU NDIAYE,
Senegalese journalist and
university teacher, is vice-
president of the Ligue
Africaine des droits de
l'homme et des peuples An
International consultant on
geopolitical problems, he has
produced many documentaries
for French television
N 6 April 1652, after an exhausting voyage,
about one hundred men disembarked from
Dutch ships in Table Bay, the old name for the
area around the Cape of Good Hope. Their leader
was one Jan van Riebeeck, who had been
instructed by the Dutch East India Company to
establish a revictualling base for Company boats
en route for India.
Five years earlier, one such vessel had come
to grief in the same bay. The crew survived the
wreck, and it was they who had suggested that
a port of call be set up at the Cape. They were
encouraged to do so by th'e reputed hospitality
of the Khoi, skilled herdsmen who inhabited the
region.
Portuguese navigators had landed on the
southern shores of the African continent two cen¬
turies earlier. In 1487 Bartolomeu Dias had
rounded the Cape and reached as far as Mossel
Bay. Ten years later, Vasco da Gama disembarked
on the coast of Natal, which received its name
from him.
Unlike the Spanish guilds and the chartered
companies that financed the Habsburgs' wars
during the reigns of Charles V and Philip II, the
East India Company was a truly capitalist insti¬
tution. It was less interested in people than in the
profits it could extract from its operations. From
1656 on, it granted certificates of free enterprise,
while retaining for itself a monopoly on purchase
and the right to fix the price of wheat, cattle and
vegerables.
Meanwhile, the numbers of the small Dutch
colony were swollen by the arrival of French
Fluguenots, driven from their home country by
the Revocation of the FMict of Nantes. Van Rie-
becck's own wife was a French Protestant,
For these Crusaders of another age, fleeing
religious persecution in Europe, the fertile
African lands were manna from f-leaven, a gift
of Providence, a promised land. Even their atti¬
tude tf)wards the Company began to change.
With the granting of independent estates, they
gradually distanced themselves from it.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The colonists called themselves burghers or
citizens, but were to go down in history as boers,
Dutch for "peasants". Their dealings with the
indigenous peoples initially centred on cattle-
trading, but as their numbers grew they soon
came into conflict with the fiottentots. They
organized offensive and defensive raids, in the
course of which they seized rich pasturelands.
The struggle against the African tribes gradu¬
ally bound this little colony of uprooted
individuals into a separate ethnic community,
linked by a common, Calvinist creed. The Boers
also developed their own language, Afrikaans,
derived from Dutch.
The Boers became tough, hard-working
crusaders, firmly convinced that they were a
chosen people superior to the "godless"
indigenous peoples they called Kaffirs. They
based their faith on three pillars: the Bible, the
wagon and the whip. From 1657 on, they gradu¬
ally reduced the Khoi to servitude, despite fierce
resistance, notably under Chief Austshumayo.
The East India Company ceased to exist
in 1795. The Boers, who by then numbered
16,000, saw themselves as a race apart. But they
were soon to come into conflict with two ene¬
mies: the British, who had recently bought Cape
Colony from the Dutch for £6 million, and the
Africans, in particular the redoubtable Zulus,
with whom they were soon to come into contact.
Relations with the Hottentots degenerated,
with disputes over cattle thefts escalating sporad¬
ically into open confrontation. Travelling in ox-
drawn wagons that they used to form defensive
circles, the Boers launched expeditions against the
Africans, some of whom were reduced to slavery
after being defeated in battle.
Boer nationalism
versus
British imperialism
A community of Moravian Brothers settled at
Genadenstad in 1792, and from then on there was
a British presence on the Cape. The London Mis¬
sionary Society also sent envoys. Under the
influence of the missionaries, the British governor
at the Cape promulgated laws from 1806 on that
enabled black people to take their Boer masters
to court.
These measures aroused the opposition of the
Boer colonists, who saw them as acts of hostility
that both damaged their interests and offended
against their sense of superiority with regard to
the Africans. However, the British grip on the
colony tightened, and in 1828 English became the
official language of Cape Colony. Six years later,
slavery was abolished and raids against the Hot¬
tentots were prohibited.
Opposite page: in the late
15th century, the Portuguese
navigator Bartolomeu Dias
became the first European to,
round the tip of Africa and
sail up the continent's eastern
coast. To commemorate
Dias's expedition, his arrival
at Mossel Bay (South Africa)
was re-enacted in 1988.
Below: a scene from a South
African television series
entitled Shaka Zufu (1986),
which told the story of the
19th-century warrior king who
was the founding father of the
Zulu nation.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
To escape British domination, the Boers
began in 1835 an arduous )ourney through the
and interior of the country that took them from
the Cape to the lands of the Transvaal and the
Orange River. For these Protestant farmers,
steeped in the Bible and brought up on memories
of persecution in Europe, the Great Trek through
lands inhabited by people they considered savage
and hostile recalled the Exodus of the Old Testa¬
ment Hebrews, which the Boers were to evoke
as a veritable national foundation myth. The
Trek indelibly marked the image and the destiny
of the Afrikaners.
One claim often made by the apologists of
apartheid is that those who took part in the Great
Trek the Voortrekkers found unoccupied,
virgin land on their arrival. In fact in the course
of their migration they came up against the
Xhosa, who barred their route. They were then
obliged to divert northwards, where they found
themselves confronted by the Zulus, a formid¬
able warrior race, under their chief Dingaan,
brother of the celebrated Shaka.
At first the Boers were received in peace; Din¬
gaan declared that there was enough land for
everybody. The Boer settlers thus had free run
of the pastures. But they immediately set up
fences and barbed wire to mark off "their" land,
thereby denying the indigenous herdsmen the
right of free passage that had been customary for
generations. For the proud Zulu warriors, who
had no sense of private property, this was a
betrayal of the spirit of hospitality that lay behind
the agreement between the two peoples. Dingaan
subsequently lured the Boer colonists to his
kraal ihn Afrikaans word for an indigenous
village and in 1838 massacred many of them.
This episode, regarded by the Boers as an act
of treachery, left them with an enduring hatred
and fear of the Zulus. Dingaan was defeated later
in 1838 at the Battle of Blood River, commemo¬
rated as a day of celebration by the Boers but
regarded as a tragedy by the Africans. Even so
the Zulus continued the struggle, especially
against the British who now arrived in their thou¬
sands, France's Prince Imperial, the son of
Napoleon III and the Empress Eugénie, was killed
while serving with the British Army in the course
of one such battle.
The Boers then founded two small republics,
the Transvaal and the Orange Free State, in which
they first reduced the indigenous peoples to
slavery and then established the principles of
apartheid, the rigorous separation of races. The
northern Sotho peoples under Moshoeshoe and
their southern counterparts under Sekhukhum
rose en masse against the Boers, and never sub¬
mitted to their domination.
The discovery of diamonds at Kimberley in
1867 and of gold in the Transvaal attracted thou¬
sands of European adventurers, many of them
British, who stirred up trouble for the Boers.
Cecil Rhodes, the founder of Rhodesia, was
among them. Financial interests underlay the
noble, humanitarian motives put forward by the
British as reasons for liberating their compatriots
and the Africans from the Boer yoke.
The British concentrated around the Boer
republics a formidable expeditionary force of
some 20,000 men, including many Africans, who
had been promised recognition of their rights.
The Boers were defeated, and signed the Peace
Above left: Paul Kruger
(1989), a sculpture of velvet
corkwood, enamel paint and
nails by South African artist
Phuthuma Seoka that evokes
the famous Boer leader.
This work, and those
reproduced on pages 23, 28,
33 and 38, featured in Art
from South Africa, a travelling
exhibition organized by the
Museum of IVIodern Art,
Oxford (UK), in association
with the Zabaiaza Festival,
London.
Left, beneath a more
conventional statue of Kruger
in the centre of Pretoria,
Afrikaners demonstrate in
February 1990 against ttte
liberation of Nelson Mandela.
Opposite page: an Afrikaner
and a Bantu photographed in
the 1940s.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
of Vereeniging in 1902. Their republics were
henceforth subject to the British crown.
The birth of the Afrikaner nation
In Europe, the course of the Boer War was fol¬
lowed with great interest, and the defeat of the
Afrikaners aroused a certain amount of pity. Paul
Kruger, the President of the Transvaal, took
refuge in Switzerland and strove to sensitize Euro¬
pean public opinion to the misfortunes of what
he depicted as a brave and hardy race of pioneers
that had developed savage lands where the spirit
of darkness reigned. The Boers began to build up
a store of public sympathy, as the unfortunate
victims of persecution at the hands of perfidious
Albion, that has survived in the collective uncons¬
cious of Western public opinion to our own day.
In fact the Afrikaners of the late nineteenth
century had little in common with the early
colonists of East India Company days. Living in
Africa had changed their mentality. They had
remained isolated from the great currents of
thought favouring liberty, social justice and the
sovereignty of peoples that, in the wake of the
French Revolution, had illuminated the history
of nineteenth-century Europe. They were hostile
to any Idea of progress. Their economy was rural
and backward, and they regarded Africans as
inferior beings, to be kept at all costs in ignorance.
For the British, who stood for capitalism
based on salaried work, the system of racial segre¬
gation practiced by the Boers belonged to the
economy of another age. Britain, in full economic
expansion, looked primarily to the formidable,
undeveloped industrial potential of South
Africa "a veritable geological scandal". The
British Empire was then at its peak, and it was
less preoccupied with humanitarian considera¬
tions than with economic interests.
So the British reneged on the promise of
political rights for Africans made at the time of
the Boer War. On the other hand, they accepted
the Afrikaners as British subjects.
Far from putting an end to the injustices of
which the Africans were the victims, British
domination only made them worse. Rampant
segregation between blacks and whites was estab¬
lished, first of all in economic matters; by a series
of iniquitous laws and directives, the whites took
the best lands and introduced increasingly draco-
nian legislation to permit the compulsory exploi¬
tation of the black workforce.
Finally, the victory of the Nationalist Party
in the 1949 elections and the end of political
dominance by groups depending largely for their
support on English-speaking voters brought to
power the hard-core champions of the system of
racial segregation known as apartheid.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
%J return to South Africa by Ruth Lazarus
An expatriate's eyewitness account of a country in the throes of change
Below, the Khayeiitsha
township outside Cape Town,
to which black South African
families were sent after the
demolition of squatter camps.
Below right: a house in a
residential district of Cape
Town.
IjLn absence of twenty-five years from one's
country of origin is a long time: and on returning
to it on a visit, as I did recently, one would natur¬
ally expect to find changes. But to return to South
Africa at this point in time is to witness a country
that is undergoing particularly profound and dra¬
matic changes.
The dismantling of apartheid has begun and
the process is, I believe, irreversible. The last few
years have seen a new willingness on the part of
the Government to review many of the apartheid
laws and to work together with the national
movements towards a new democratic constitu¬
tion and full franchise for everyone regardless of
ethnic origin. This process began in 1982 and
accelerated when President de Klerk took office
in 1989. "One person one vote", long the dream
of all non-whites, is now a possibility in the fore¬
seeable future.
Talk of the "new South Africa" is on
everyone's lips, but the expression often means
different things to different people, depending on
their origins, colour and political bias.
Some changes are very noticeable to the
visitor. Petty apartheid is disappearing, people of
different ethnic origins are now seen together,
and there are no separate queues in shops, at bus
stops or in banks. Schools (in theory at least) are
now desegregated. But the vast majority of blacks
cannot afford to send their children to the better
schools, and they are still dependent on "Bantu
Education", an inferior and inadequate primary
school system. Many of the blacks are, in fact,
not in school at all.
More important, all political parties, national
movements and black trade unions are now legal,
and many although not all political prisoners
have been released. The old and hated "Pass
system", controlling freedom of movement for
blacks, has been abolished.
There is, in general, a greater recognition
among the white population of the legitimate
rights of blacks and other oppressed groups to
equality in social and political life. Television and
radio programmes are much freer. However, at
least one third of the whites (the conservative
Afrikaners) rigorously oppose these changes, and
some have already formed a "state within a state"
Jh.-^' wmnmmm
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
RUTH LAZARUS
was born in South Africa and
left the country m 1946. A
former head of UNESCO's
Literacy Activities Section, she
IS the author of many articles
and studies on adult education
and literacy.
called Orangia in the Western Cape, to maintain
their segregated lives. I also suspect that the
majority of whites would still wish, and expect,
to maintain their economic supremacy.
During the last twenty years there has also
been an unprecedented exodus of highly skilled
and professional whites (doctors, lawyers, accoun¬
tants, etc.), most of whom have settled in Canada,
the United Kingdom and Australia. This exodus
still continues, and might well grow during what
many of them consider to be the uncertain years
of the future. The motivation varies, but manv
oppose the new wave of change and fear for their
privileged economic position.
Many of the oW structures
still remain
Yet despite these changes, the apartheid structures
are at present still very much in place. The right
to vote is still the privilege of the whites. Residen¬
tial apartheid is still entrenched. A high propor¬
tion of the whites live in beautiful homes with
swimming pools and large gardens in the richer
residential suburbs of the cities, fortified and
bolted inside with their luxury possessions.
Meanwhile, the majority of blacks are still
living in segregated, desolate towmships, in the
urban areas on the edges of the big cities, in very
inferior houses or shacks, in overcrowded homes
often lacking elementary urban amenities, such
as sanitation or electricity. Rural conditions are
even worse. These inhuman surroundings are
often a breeding ground for destabilizing ele-
¿i^iiîUMMÎIMMIIMMII^MIlMa.
ments, especially among the young. Law-abiding
residents live in constant fear of having their few
possessions stolen by marauding bands of delin¬
quents and socially deprived gangs. In fact, the
fear of being robbed or assaulted is felt in both
the white and non-white communities, especially
in Johannesburg (the largest city).
Economic apartheid is still perhaps the most
blatant hangover from the past. Even though
jobs arc no longer exclusively reserved for
whites, and trade unions for black workers are
now legal, a very high proportion of office
jobs and industrial jobs requiring technical
skills are still held by whites and the
overwhelming majority of unskilled, poorly paid
jobs by the blacks. With unemployment on the
increase, it is the black labour force which is most
badly hit.
The present recession is, in fact, of such con¬
cern that the Governor of the Reserve Bank,
Chris Stals, has stated that "poor economic
growth, if continued at its present performance,
wfll make the country ungovernable by 1995".
He gave three reasons for this stagnation: "polit¬
ical uncertainties, social unrest and industrial
action,"
One of the biggest obstacles to change still
lies in the distribution and ownership of land. In
spite of the abolition in 1991 of the Group Areas
Act, which dictated where people could live
depending on their ethnic origin, and of the Land
Acts (1919-1939), which reserved 87 per cent of
the country's land for whites (although they cur¬
rently make up less than 14 per cent of the popu¬
lation) there is as yet very little expectation that
change will come soon and the problem remains
grave. I saw little evidence of change, except in
the city of Johannesburg, where the centre of
town and adjoining residential districts have in
recent years, despite these laws, become mixed
areas. However, the overwhelming majority of
the black population is still confined to the
townships.
Despite the repealing of the land laws, land
formerly expropriated from the blacks by forcible
evacuation has not been returned, nor is its return
included in any new legislation, and there are stili
7 million squatters in temporary homes, mostly
without sanitation or water.
The Reverend Frank Chikane, a well-known
anti-apartheid activist, gives an example of what
happened to his own family: "My mother who
has owned land, and my father, now passed away,
have been removed twice since the 1950s. The
plot of land from which she was originally
removed is still there. It is not owned privately
by anybody: she has not been compensated for
being removed , . . and when they say that the
Land Act is going to be repealed, but is put under
the free market system, everyone else can come
and buy it, it rteans nothing to my mother. . . ."
Christopher S. Wren of the New York Times
recently gave a vivid description of a shanty town:
"In Sowcto-by-the-Sea, near Port Elizabeth, the 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ukuhlelelek (the marginal ones) live jammed into
about 14,000 shacks built from corrugated metal,
wooden packing cases, and whatever else can be
scavenged. They overflow a squalid city without
schools, hospitals, community centres, parks,
sidewalks, or street lights. . . . Electricity,
drainage, sewage systems and paved streets do not
exist." And all this within a few kilometres of
the luxurious houses of the rich.
Another area in which there is still discrimi¬
nation IS that of pensions and Government
benefits for the disabled. These are still very
inferior for blacks. Unemployment benefits for
them hardly exist. Thus the sharp difference
between the rich and the poor, broadly speaking
between the whites and the blacks, is still very
evident.
A sense of isolation
Another impression is of South Africa's con¬
tinuing isolation from the rest of the world, both
economically, culturally and in the domain of
sport. The economic sanctions have been widely
felt, although this is often denied by the authori¬
ties. The Government has not yet, despite the
ongoing reforms, succeeded in attracting suffi¬
cient foreign capital to bolster a flagging
economy. The cultural and sport boycott has also
had a deep effect. Well-known artists have refused
to perform in South Africa, and are still doing
so. However, books and films which were cen¬
sored in the past are now easily available.
The boycott that until recent months
prevented South African sportsmen and women
from participating in international sports events,
notably the Olympics, and that discouraged
internationally-known competitors from coming
to South Africa, has had a devastating effect on
South African sport. This has been deeply
resented in white sporting circles. But changes are
now in progress and slowdy new sporting con¬
tacts with the outside world are taking place. The
International Olympic Committee has, for
instance, invited South Africa to the Barcelona
Olympics.
The future
I came away with the feeling that "the new South
Africa" IS still for the overwhelming majority a
hope rather than a reality. Nevertheless, in the
coming months negotiations between the
Government and the ANC and other national
movements could lead to the creation of a con¬
stituent assembly, the drafting of a new consti¬
tution based on universal adult suffrage, and even¬
tually the election of a fully democratic parlia¬
ment based on a non-racial voters' roll.
South Africa's future is thus still in the
balance. But the new freedoms gained will be
rigorously defended, and there are hopeful signs
that, if reason prevails over force, a new nation
will emerge that could rightfully and proudly
take its legitimate place among the other nations
of the world.
New Year's Eve revelry on the
streets of Hiilbrow, in central
Johannesburg.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Which model of democracy? by klbie Sacfis
A distinèuished lawyer and anti-apartheid campaigner reflects on the democratic choices
facing a non-racial South Africa
lYAoDELS are enticing. Simplicity is difficult.
Democracy grows and withers in all conti¬
nents, and nothing is gained by giving it a
geographical genesis. We fight for it where we are,
because it embodies the values we wish for our¬
selves, and not because we want to prove to
anyone how good or civilized we are, or how
worthy of aid.
It is for this reason that we in the South
African anti-apartheid struggle resist the lure to
say that we wish to install Western democracy in
our country. We acknowledge without difficulty
that the very word democracy has a Western
origin, and that many of the institutions of
democracy, such as periodic elections and the
multi-party system, and much of its theorization,
first emerged in Western countries. We are also
not unaware of the fact that the West is so rich,
well-armed and confident that prudence, if not
opportunism, would suggest that we engage in
the closest mimicry possible.
Yet much as we may like an idea, we may
reject the wrapping within which it is presented.
It is not a question of complexes or shallow pride,
but of principle, of what is meant by democracy
and how it is achieved in any part of the world.
The relationship of the West with our conti¬
nent has in fact been far from democratic. First,
African people were denied their physical
autonomy through the slave trade and then had
their legal personality negated by colonialism.
More recently in South Africa the whole
panoply of racist laws which made up the system
of apartheid emanated from a certain type of
Western institution. The West might have trans¬
ported railroads and the ballot to South Africa. It
also brought hanging, the pass laws. States of
Emergency and detention without trial, all sanc¬
tioned by Parliament and enforced by courts. At
the international level, with the honourable
exception of the Nordic countries, the Western
countries traded with apartheid and largely turned
their backs on those fighting for democracy.
In my lifetime, white-on-white violence in
Europe has exceeded by far both in scope and
savagery anything practiced by Africans against
Africans in Africa; only four European countries
have escaped military dictatorship or military
occupation in the past half century. South Africa
also has a long history of white on white violence,
including the Anglo-Boer War, the 1922 miners'
strike, the actions of pro-fascist groups in the 1930s,
during the Second World War, and recently again.
The ideas of democracy, peace and respect for
human rights thus do not belong to any conti¬
nent, and certainly not to any racial group. In
South Africa, it was not people from Europe who
fought most consistently for what is called
Western Democracy, but people of African and
Leapin' to People's Culture, a
print by the South African
artist Tiki Phungula.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24
Asian origin. While the notion of racial dictator¬
ship in more or less benign form was being
extolled by white South Africans, the idea of non-
racial democracy was kept alive in the prisons,
the underground and exile by blacks. In the light
of our history, nothing is gained by affixing the
label Western to the word Democracy.
Does rejection of use of the term Western
Democracy mean that we favour the formulation
African Democracy? Not at all. We oppose
Eurocentrism with universalism, rather than with
any concept of African exceptionalism. On the
whole, African democrats are not comfortable
with the term African democracy. It is, of course,
always necessary to emphasize that our country
is South Africa and not South Europe. The sup¬
pression or marginalization of African languages,
culture and history permeates every aspect of
public and private life. In that sense, we have to
Africanize, or better still, to South Africanize our
society and its institutions.
Yet the term African democracy has been
used to deny African people their individual
rights as citizens and their fundamental freedoms
as human beings. The eminently good African
tradition of talking a matter through courteously
and reasonably until consensus binding upon all
is reached, has very often been turned around to
justify the imposed consensus of one-person rule.
Trade unions, political parties and other non¬
governmental organizations set up to advance the
interests of the ordinary working people of Africa
are outlawed on the grounds that they are sup¬
posedly un-African. Persons declare themselves
to be President for life, on the model of an
African king, though their rule has been legiti¬
mated neither by traditional royal lineage, nor
by elections.
Any departure from internationally accepted
standards of fair treatment is justified on the
grounds that Africa is different and there is no
shortage of Europeans and North Americans
willing to back dictators arguing that democracy
is not for our part of the world. In our country,
the greatest believers in special systems of African
democracy have not been the African people,
who overwhelmingly demanded universally
accepted rights and freedoms, but the whites, who
used the notion to impose corrupt Bantustan
leaders on the majority.
Millions of victims
of State neglect
The model of liberal democracy, on the other
hand, has the virtue of being based on a concept
rather than a continent. It emphasizes the aspects
of personal freedom and political pluralism that
are fundamental to democracy in any land, and
places heavy emphasis on secure legal mechanisms
to prevent abuses by the State. Yet in South
Africa oppression takes the form not just of State
interference but of State neglect. Millions die of
malnutrition and tuberculosis, and go without
homes and schools, because in the eyes of the
"The South Africans":
portraits of a people by
photographer Guy Hobbs.
Government as blacks they simply do not count.
Political freedoms are empty and precarious if not
associated with a dignified existence for all.
It is for this reason that we say we do not
want freedom without bread, nor do we want
bread without freedom, but rather, we want
freedom, and we want bread.
Our fear is that many people who have either
been bitterly anti-liberal all their lives, or who
at best were only timidly liberal when it really
mattered, will now seize upon liberal notions as
a justification for what will amount to the privati¬
zation of misery. It is one thing to say that the
State should not try to do what it does badly,
namely produce and market goods, or to declare
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
that It should not attempt to monopolize com¬
pletely the provision of public utilities and social
services. It is quite another to imply that the State
has no role at all to play in achieving equity and
fairness in South Africa.
Social democracyfor and against
It is in this connection that social democracy has
special appeal. Our understanding of social
democracy is that it combines personal freedom
and an active role for the market, with the
guaranteeing of minimum rights of humane exis¬
tence for all. Public authorities have an impor¬
tant responsibility for ensuring generalized access
to health, education and housing. At the same
time there are legal and public-opinion
mechanisms for seeing to it that the State does
not become too intrusive.
Yet impressive though the record of countries
regarded as social-democratic might be, they
simply do not provide ctmstitutional models
which respond to all the many problems facing
us in South Africa. Most o\ these countries have
an ancient history of nationhood, if not of state¬
hood; we in South Africa have an insecure 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
history of statehood, and none at all of nation¬
hood. Many of these countries happen to have
monarchs as Heads of State, and Prime Ministers
as Heads of Government; and, though we are
undoubtedly not short of would-be Prime
Ministers, we do not, as far as I am aware, even
have pretenders to a throne.
Thus we need to make provision for the elec¬
tion of a President as Head of State, and, possibly,
as Head of Government. For this technical
reason, but for more substantive motives as well,
we are moving away from a parliamentary-based
concept of democracy to a constitutionally-based
one. Parliament will continue to function as the
central expression of the popular will, but it will
exercise its powers within the framework of a
nationally-agreed compact of fundamental rights
and freedoms embodied in a judicially-supervised
Bill of Rights.
None of this is incompatible with social
democracy, yet the reality is that constitutions
tend to play a relatively small role in the public
life oí the Social Democratic countries. In South
Africa, the constitution will be a central docu¬
ment, serving both as a symbol and as a guarantor
of freedom and security. Attractive though social
democracy will continue to be as a political
programme, its value as the foundation of a new
constitution will be more limited.
Religious movements
and the State
There are many countries in Europe and Latin
America where Christian Democracy has
received considerable support. In South Africa the
concept is so remote that we do not even know
what it is. Three-quarters of all South Africans
regard themselves as Christians. Christianity is
more than a religion, it has influenced the whole
culture of our country. Yet important though
Christianity is both to public and private life, any
opportunistic attempt at this stage to establish
exclusively Christian parties, and certainly any
move to create constitutional privileges for Chris¬
tianity, would be strongly resisted, and most
vigorously by Christians themselves.
The fact is that there is no predominant
Christian church, nor any distinctive political
allegiance of Christians. The Dutch Reformed
Church has long had an important role because
of its association with the National Pany Govern¬
ment, but it is divided, and is a minority church
in the country as a whole. There are millions of
Anglicans, Catholics and Methodists, an even
larger number of members of independent
African churches, and a growing body of pen-
tecostals and evangelicals, all with divided polit¬
ical loyalties. Equally important, there are
hundreds of thousands of Muslims, Jews and
Hindus who would expect the same religious
rights and freedoms as Christians.
Attempts made in previous years to run edu-
- cation on what were called Christian National
^O lines have brought the notion of Chrrstian domi
nation of public life into disrepute. What is likely
is a phase of active co-operation between the reli¬
gious organizations and the State to achieve the
objectives of the new Constitution, with the reli¬
gious bodies retaining their right to bear witness
and criticize the actions of the State. In the mean¬
while Christians will be found in all the parties,
as will non-Christians.
Until fairly recently, there was extensive
backing amongst large sections of the anti-
apartheid forces for the model of People's
Democracy, The argument was twofold. In the
first place it was contended that racist power was
so intransigent and authoritarian that the only wav
to destroy it and guarantee rights to the people
was through opposing it with the massed forces
of people's power. Secondly, it was felt by many
that liberal or social democracy converted the
general population into passive recipients of rights
who only became active in quinquennial bursts
of electoral activity; representative democrac}'
was important, it was argued, but it had to be
supplemented by participatory democracy.
Today the notion of popular empowerment
places less emphasis on the coercive capacity of
the community, and more on the acquisition of
skills, self-confidence and material means to
enable communities to make effective decisions
and take charge of their own destinies. More is
said about people's rights and less about people's
power.
The concept of democracy in itself involves
government of the people, for the people, by the
people. It is not necessary to say we want people's
government of the people's people, for the
people's people, of the people's people.
A plant nurtured by the sufferings
and struggles of people everywhere
Accordingly, without identifying ourselves solely
with any of the proffered models of democracy,
we draw in different ways on each one of them,
and prefer to speak simply not of Western, or
African, or Liberal, or Christian, or Social or
People's Democracy, but simply of . . .
democracy.
Democracy in South Africa will look at the
rich and varied experience of Western countries
in overcoming the rich and varied forms of
absolutism and tyranny which Western countries
have thrown up over the centuries. It will pay
special attention to the institutional mechanisms
which have been created to guarantee basic rights,
as well as to ways and means of encouraging a
rights culture in society as a whole.
It will seek to ensure that in terms of lan¬
guage, symbols and personality it has a character
that roots it in Africa, The fact that religion plays
a big role in South African life will find
appropriate acknowledgment in the Constitution,
without creating a State religion or giving anv
religion preference t)ver others; the hymn Nknsi
Sikclcle lAjrika, God Bless Africa, has airead)'
become a major force for national unity.
ALBIE SACHS,
South African lawyer and
writer, is a member of the
Constitutional Committee of
the African National Congress
He IS a professor at the
University of the Western Cape
and at the University of Cape
Town, and Director of the
South African Constitution
Studies Centre of the Institute
for Commonwealth Studies at
the University of London
Notable among his published
works are The Jail Diary of
Albie Sachs and Protecting
Human Rights in a New South
Africa This text was prepared
as a contribution to a
Workshop on issues of human
rights for a post-apartheid
South Africa which was
organized at Banjul, The
Gambia (18-21 June 1991),
UNESCO and the African
Commission on Human and
People's Rights
by
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The institutional arrangements of the
democratic State will owe much to the tenets of
Liberal Democracy, while mechanisms to ensure
basic rights of nutrition, housing, health and edu¬
cation will be influenced by Social Democracy.
People's Democrac}' will live on not as a form
of institutionalized power but as active civic
involvement in the processes of transformation.
Above all, democracy in South Africa has to
be anti-apartheid in character. It is for this reason
that we speak of non-racial democracy. Our hope
IS that much as we draw on the experience of
other countries in building democracy, so we
make our own special contribution.
The first shall be the last, and the last shall
be the first. We in Si^uth Africa are attempting
three great historical and constitutional processes
in one:
collective self-determination, in overcoming the
effects of colonial-type domination, and creating
a single multi-lingual, multi-faith and pluri-
political nation;
individual self-determination, in guaranteeing
personal rights and freed(mis to all who live m
our country;
minimum rights of social welfare and a decent
existence for all.
Where do these ideas come from? They come
from ourselves and our own struggles.
People establish the concept of justice in their
imaginations and their hearts when they fight
against injustice. The laws and the constitution
then seek tt) confirm and institutionalize
the rights which have been gained in battle.
But in fighting for dem'ocracy in South Africa,
we gladly take inspiration and learn from
the experience of other persons who have fought
for freedom in other continents and at other
times.
Perhaps the most significant political accom¬
plishment of our epoch at an international level
has been the universalization of the ideas of
democracy and human rights. Democracy does
not belong to any part of the world, even less
to any race. We all draw on it, we all contribute
towards it. It may be likened to a single giant
plant with roots in all the regions of the world,
nurtured by the sufferings of people everywhere.
The world has helped the anti-apartheid struggle;
the anti-apartheid struggle helps the world.
Black South Africans singing
the anthem "God Bless
Africa".
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
LStâte of transition
Framing a new constitution for a new South Africa
by GeraW Gordon end Dennis Davis J
'G
Towards Emancipation (1988).
, a iinocut by the South African
artist Sydney Seiepe.
lo back; look at the baby in his mother's
arms; . . . listen to the first words which awaken
his dormant powers of thought; and take notice
of the first struggles he has to endure. Only then
will you understand the origin of the prejudices,
habits, and passions which are to dominate his
life. The whole man is there, if one may put it
so, in the cradle,
"Something analogous happens with nations.
People always bear some marks of their origin.
Circumstances of birth and growth alfect all the
rest of their careers,
"If we could go right back to the elements
of societies and examine the very first records of
their histories, we should there find the first cause
of their prejudices, habits, dominating passions
and all that comes to be called the national
character,"
Alexis de Tocqueville's words, in his classic
Democracy in America (1835), can aid in an under¬
standing of South Africa's enormous problems
in its present hoped-for transition from a semi-
28
authoritarian State to a democracy. When Presi¬
dent de Klerk on 2 February 1990 unbanned the
African National Congress (ANC) and other
organizations of opposition to his Government's
apartheid ideology, he was releasing passions that
had been born in the preceding three centuries.
In the light of South Africa's history and the
"prejudices, habits, passions and national
character" to which de Tocqucville referred, the
country is far from being ripe for democracy.
There is hardly a common national character; the
disparity of wealth between the richest 10 per
cent and the poorest 50 per cent is one of the
highest in the world and at least half the popula¬
tion is illiterate.
What makes the situation even more difficult
is that a sovereign country like South Africa has
no big brother to lend it a helping hand in its
aim to substitute a wholesome democracy for the
apartheid régime. Rhodesia went through its tran¬
sition to independence as Zimbabwe v.'ith Lan¬
caster House to turn to. Likewise Namibia had
a big brother in the United Nations, But South
Africa has no such State or body to supervise the
processing and adoption of a new constitution.
The price of so\'erelgntv is solitude.
In cases where there is no supervising
authority, forces competing for control of the
processing and adoption of a new constitution
have two alternatives. Thev must either fight
their opponents in order to gain control f;f the
machinery of the future government or negotiate
with them to share or divide that control. Bv
agreement thev may use the existing constitu¬
tional structure. If agreement is not attainable
they have to sweep the old constitution aside.
Understandably, in this context, organiza¬
tions like the ANC are not prepared to allow the
existing South African Parliament to legislate a
new constitution into existence. If this Parliament
were allowed to do so, it would be continuing
the long legal line back to the establishment of
the Union of South Airica in 1910. There is one
reas(m why it mav be argued that the long line
mu.st be broken. An unbroken line would be legal
but It -would lack legitimacy: it would not be
based on the norms and values of a desirable
society. It IS thus contended that the question of
a new constitution must be approached in a
vacuum.
T'here is also another reason. It involves the
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A march organized in Cape
Town on 1 February 1991
against the exclusion of black
South Africans from
Parliament, in centre, Walter
Sisuiu, a leading figure in the
anti-apartheid struggle.
GERALD GORDON QC,
of South Africa, is a former
leader of the Cape Bar.
President of South African PEN
and patron of the South
African League for Civil Rights,
he IS the author of a number
of legal works and of three
novéis.
DENNIS DAVIS,
of South Africa, is professor in
the School of Law of the
University of the
Witwatersrand. Director of the
Centre of Applied Legal
Studies and of the Society for
the Abolition of the Death
Penalty, he is the author of a
number of legal worl<s.
question of how far the opposition parties feel
they can trust the Nationalist Government. And
this turns on the question of the motivation for
the now famous unbanning on 2 February 1990
of the ANC and the other opposition bodies such
as the Pan African Congress and the Communist
Party. Critics of the Nationalist Party (NP) claim
that the true reason for the unbanning was that
political and economic pressures on the interna¬
tional front had become too severe more than
the South African Government could face any
longer. At last it realized its enormous depen¬
dence on the financial and technological resources
of the international community.
The purported aim of the present great move
towards democracy for South Africa is to be seen
against the world background of an international
cc:>mmitment to democracy after the fall of Euro¬
pean communism.
All in all, therefore, the way seemed open
for the Nationalist C}overnment to meet its old
opponents at the negotiating table. Short of
revolution and civil war which has been the
lot of man)' countries in Africa recently it
was and is the only way. And negotiation in
turn revolves around the question of power.
While all the political parties (including
organizations like the ANC which do not as yet
regard themselves as "parties") are bargaining
their way to a new South Africa and a new con¬
stitution, there has to be an interim constitution
in control of law, order and peace. The drafting
of the new constitution and its ultimate adoption
are part of the negotiations and so the various par¬
ties have to come together to decide on the
logistics of control.
The questions posed are: is the present
government to be allowed to control the transi¬
tion process.' And to continue to hold the instru¬
ments of power? Is there to be some interim set¬
up to displace the government? If so, how is it
to be constituted? By elections? Who will con¬
trol these? And what voters' roll will be used?
The existing ones which exclude the 20 million
Africans? And who is to set the timing, pace and
placing of the elections?
Apart, however, from disputes concerning
the mechanism for transition, the principal par¬
ties involved will doubtless focus their attention
on the drafting of a new constitution. 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
The major parties, in particular the NP and
the ANC, have published constitutional
proposals. There is a surprising measure of agree¬
ment in respect of important aspects of the con¬
stitution. Both agree on the need for an electoral
system based on proportional representation.
Both agree that the lower house in parliament
should be elected by universal suffrage. There is
consensus regarding the need to incorporate a
justiciable Bill of Rights into a new constitutitm.
After much dispute, there now seems to be little
doubt that a constitutional court will be created
to supervise the operation of the Bill of Rights.
There remain, however, important points of
difference. The ANC believes in a unitary svstem
of government with strong central powers, which
It considers necessary if the social and economic
legacies of apartheid are to be addressed. The NP
IS particularly keen that power should be diffused
and therefore it insists on federalism.
It also proposes a presidential troika in which
the leaders of the three largest parties would form
a collective presidency with the chair rotating
annually, and the establishment of a second house
of parliament in which each of nine regions
would elect an equal number of representatives.
Each party gaining a specified number of votes
in a region would have an equal number of seats
of that region's allocation.
In short, the ANC proposes a system of
government oí which voluntary association is the
central pillar, while the NP has based its
proposals on the principle of an imposed coali¬
tion. This constitutes the NP's concept of "par¬
ticipatory democracy" and "power sharing".
There are also fundamental disagreements
concerning the contents of the Bill of Rights. The
NP wishes to entrench the right to own private
property which can only be expropriated in
exchange for just compensation. The ANC con¬
siders that such a clause would prevent a future
government from restoring land rights to millions
of South Africans from whom they were taken
by the policy of forced removals.
The ANC has included a range of social, eco¬
nomic and environmental provisions in its Bill
of Rights. It contends that within the context of
South Africa such a measure must make provi¬
sion for the equal distribution of fundamental
social and economic goods throughout society.
The South African Law Commission, appointed
by the Minister of Justice, accuses the ANC of
Utopian thinking because of the wide range of
social and economic rights included in the latter's
document.
In conclusion, there does seem to be a sur¬
prising degree of consensus regarding the major
elements for a new constitution, particularly now
that the NP has jettisoned its insistence upon the
need to include protection of group rights. For
this reason there is some ground to hope that
agreement can be reached on the broad principles
for a new constitution.
He future for mml
The difficult path to a non-sexist
as well as a non-racial democracy
vJender discrimination, inherent in South
African society, is rooted in the ethnic traditions
of the multi-cultural communities, largely
through the compliance of women themselves.
Each cultural and ethnic group is grooved in
systems of values that perceive women as subor¬
dinate to men. The apartheid State simply con¬
firmed these values and in some cases incorpo¬
rated them into its legal system.
Radical feminists m South Africa see the
family as the foundation of women's oppression,
Flowever, the vast majority of women in South
Africa, in particular black African women,
experience the family as a source of emotional
strength and the theatre of their self-realization,
and value their roles as mothers and home
workers. Their separatum from the sphere of cap¬
ital and power tends to make them relatively
unambitious, far mc)re value-centred than men
and far more dependent on the famil\' for their
well-being.
Black South African women have waged the
liberator)' struggle from within the family, in
response to oppression experienced by the
family less-than-subsistence wages, schooling,
housing and medical .services that were inadequate
or non-existent, and so on. During that struggle,
they have come to understand their own pt)ten-
tial and have laid claim to their own freedoms.
Far from experiencing the family as an insti-
tutitm of oppression, they trace the subjugation
of the African people to the violation of the
African familv and to the ways in which family
members have been treated as commodities and
turned into labour units for the convenience of
the job market.
Most women in South Airica and this is
confirmed in interviews conducted by the Insti¬
tute of Black Research with almost a thousand
Indian, African and Cxiloured women working
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
by fatíma Meer
A home in Soweto, the
sprawling black ghetto
outside Johannesburg.
FATIMA IVIEER,
South African sociologist, is
director of the Institute for
Black Research at the
department of sociology of the
University of Natal, Durban
She IS the author of many
published works, including
Higher than Hope, a biography
of Nelson Mandela (1990).
in factories in Durban accept their subordina¬
tion and do not feel a sense of oppression. Nor
do they feel alienated from their men, whom they
see as the most immediate victims of white domi¬
nation. It IS after all their men who fought and
lost to the colonizer, who have made up by far
the greatest number of casualties in political pro¬
test, and who have suffered most extensively from
the brutal exploitations of capitalism.
This does not imply a blindness to gender
oppression, but an inbred understanding that the
major conflict in the country is racial and that
the people need to be galvanized to resolve that
conflict. Any deflection to subordinate conflicts
like class and gender can only weaken the
struggle,
African women, who comprise over 70 per
cent of all women in South Africa, are generally
the most oppressed group in the country.
suffering the cumulative effects of racial and
gender-based discrimination. Untrained in every
sphere, under-educated and largely confined to
the rural areas, the vast majority remain excluded
from the job market. Those who are employed
find employment in the lowest paid rungs. Of
African women in gainful employment, 57 per
cent are employed as domestic servants or agricul¬
tural labourers, and as such remain outside
unionization and are subjected to the whims of
their employers with regard to wages and condi¬
tions of work.
The problem of agricultural land affects
African women most crucially, since the vast
majority of them live in rural areas and are almost
wholly responsible for any cultivation that exists
in the homelands, to which African land rights
are still restricted, despite the recent abolition of
the Group Areas and the Native Land Acts,
Twenty-five per cent of rural African families are
entirely dependent for their subsistence on the
land, worked largely by women, who are forced
to farm using primitive techniques.
Industrialization in South Africa, for the
African people who constitute 75 per cent of the
population, is based on the principle of migrant
labour. This has deprived the African family of
its male head and destroyed the economic base
of the African family.
Simultaneously, it has placed greater curbs on
the entry of African women into the urban areas,
subjecting them to authorization from male
magistrates and male guardians. Thus while
African men remain dangling on the margins of
urbanization, the vast majority of African women
remain unurbanized and impoverished, and
poverty is their greatest oppressor.
These are some of the oppressive conditions
from which South African women need urgent
relief. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Until 1943, women were excluded from
membership of the African National Congress,
although the Bantu Women's League was active
in it as early as 1913. Today the ANC slogan
IS "Forward to a non-racial, non-sexist demo¬
cracy", and Its Draft Bill of Rights provides for
a minimum of social and economic rights and for
affirmative action to redress disadvantages faced
by women. This recognition of a double oppres¬
sion in need of correction is significant for the
South African future, since it comes from the
political party popularly tipped to constitute the
post-apartheid Government. Proposals from
other parties speak of a women's ministry, of
women's desks in government departments, and
of affirmative action in as many public areas as
possible until equality is achieved between the
sexes.
However, a policy approach is one thing: its
implementation another. The post-apartheid
government, to justify itself, will have to redress
imbalances that have accumulated over more than
300 years, and these include gender imbalances.
The post-apartheid societ)' will be under
serious constraints to give priority to the full
employmenr of young men. Women themselves
can be expected to support such a policy, as is
evident from the Durban survey, in which 69 per
cent of the women held that men needed jobs
more than women. Young black males ctm.stitute
the most volatile sector of the South African
population. They have played the crucial role in
toppling apartheid, and they are eager to collect
their dues. There is no matching expectation
among young women.
While the post-apartheid State will be under
enormous pressure to develop local black skills,
it will find It easier to ctmcentrate <m the black
male sector, and it will probablv do so at the
expense of women. Very probably, it will do so
with their co-operation.
The integration of women into the public
sector in South Africa, at a rate and under condi¬
tions equivalent to that of men, will thus depend
on economic development, industrial need and
industrial policy. The Durban survey revealed
that while employers were satisfied with the per¬
formance of women in the workplace, women
constituted the most vulnerable sector of the
work force during depressions. The South
African cconom)' is in a slump, and while some
recovery is expected in the post-apartheid era, this
will hardly result in full employment for some
time to come. Since industry will not need to
draw massively on their labour, the State can be
expected to spend no more than the minimum
on child-care services, thereby confining women
to the home and placing low priority on their
skill training. Women will thus be in danger of
remaining gripped in a vicious circle no skills,
unskilled low-wage occupations, high birth rate,
inadequate child-care services and so risk remai¬
ning confined to domestic and child-minding
chores, Women at work in Soweto.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
líaciai discrimination in culturai life]]
by Sipiio SepmlB
Hostel for Migrant Worker
(1978), a composite sculpture
by the South African artist
Michael Goldberg that
incorporates three alarm-
clocks as well as steel, wood,
fibre and horns.
SIPHO SEPAMLA,
South African novelist and
poet, IS the director of FUBA
Academy, a school of fine arts,
music, drama, dance and
writing, which he established
fifteen years ago for black
children The present article is
based on his contribution to
the Workshop on issues of
human rights for a post-
apartheid South Africa,
organized at Banjul, The
Gambia (18-21 June 1991), by
UNESCO and the African
Commission on Human and
People's Rights
T.HtRf, is no cultural life for most of the people
of South Africa today. Nc5 more writing is being
produced by Africans living in the country. The
origins of this situation can be traced to the Land
Act of 1913, which took away the right of black
people to own land. The population was
arbitrarily separated into locations for blacks,
Indians, coloureds and whites. Halls and other
facilities were built for weddings, funerals and
football matches, but not for plays, concerts and
other cultural events. The black population had
to adapt these halls for all-purpose use. Develop¬
ment of the arts has thus been controlled in the
African townships ever since 1913. Things
became even worse in the 1970s.
In the 1950s there were many cultural activi¬
ties in the townships, with famous singers like
Miriam Makeba, an active literary scene, and the
emergence of political leaders like Mandela and
Tambo, Some people have referred to this period
as a golden cultural age.
This creative activity died out in the 1970s
as a result of a number of government measures.
The Entertainment and Publications Act in 1963
led to a large number of African writers being
banned, even if they were not involved in policies.
Many left the country. Censorship was tightened
even further by the Publications Act of 1974,
which prohibits access to literature from abroad.
Censorship operates on two levels. Officially it
functiims through a Censorship Board. On the
other level, superintendents in the townships,
ostensibly officials whose functions are to collect
rent and repair street lights and potholed streets,
are also censors. A play cannot be performed
unless the superintendent considers it suitable.
The Censorship Board is discriminatory. The
publicatitm of books by white writers is autho¬
rized, even if they are politically critical, whereas
anything written by a black writer, especially in
English, is banned. It was only when writers like
Nadine Cíordimer or André Brink weri; banned 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
that public outcry and protests occurred. By that
time black creative activity had come to a
standstill.
Because of the Group Areas Act, even when
you went to a library, you could not borrow a
book, but only consult it there. The depressed
state of the cultural scene fs aggravated by the
kind of education received by Africans. Other
groups are allowed to study arts at school, but
black children have few alternatives and no
opportunity for training in the fine arts, music,
museums, theatre, etc.
So far the Government has done very little,
and real change can only be expected when a
representative Government takes over. In the
meantime assistance and donations from the
international community would be welcomed.
Qualified teachers, arts equipment and the con¬
struction of new premises are all needed. As far
as pressure on apartheid structures is concerned,
the cultural boycott is being maintained.
However, relevant assistance to the majoritv
population should be stepped up, in keeping with
the recommendations of the United Nations.!
34
Left, a scene from IVoza
Albert!, a South African
musical by Percy Mtwa,
Mbongeni Ngema and Barney
Simon that was staged In
Paris in December 1989 in
the framework of the Year of
Human Rights and Liberties.
Written for the black
townships and carrying a
political message, the play
was a major international
success that gave a new
impetus to black South
African theatre.
Above, a young poet recites
"freedom poetry" at the
funeral of a victim of social
unrest at Bethal in the
northeast of South Africa.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
People's Sterdim by Nadine Goräitner 1
Copyright '- Felix Licensing BV
A testament of faith in the untapped creative resources of
South Africa's excluded masses
AliOPLi'S literature as a particular mode
appropriate to the present is something most
developed countries have no call for. Their con¬
temporary literature is confidently middle-class
which is to say it may assume an educated reader
with whom the writer shares terms of reference.
The demand for a People's Literature seems to
have been answered once and for all, and the need
apparently satisfied, by the comic book, with the
people's hero as an extra-terrestrial, and by oral
folk poets the wise-cracking commentators, disc
jockeys and presenters of television and radio.
Thus the semi-literate and illiterate appear to be
uncomplainingly provided for.
But in developing countries the situation is
different. The Irish poet Seamus Heaney's "govern¬
ment of the tongue" does not have the same c<m-
stituency. In the post-ctikmial world in general,
and m South Africa specifically, the illiterate and
semi-literate now .surround the cultural convention. 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
They have been called up by history.
They have been called up by justice. For over
300 years, not only were they excluded from any
role in defining cultural norms; it was denied that
they had any need of these let alone anything to
contribute. If they could read, there were virtu¬
ally no common references, no givens, between
them and white writers, and few between them
and black writers, the latter already upwardly
alienated by education and the white-collar style
of life it has implied. Now, beyond the opportu¬
nities to acquire knowledge of modern science,
technology and administration, there is asserted
the masses' right to enjoy the self-realization of
literature. Here, where the responsibility of
educationists is seen as exceeded, it is the writers
themselves who are expected to take over.
The demand is for a particular fictional mode:
subjects, narrative form, vocabulary to express
ethics, mores and relationships that arise from the
daily lives of peasants and industrial labourers
where there has never been a mode stemming
from their own level of consciousness. It means
finding a format and distribution process that will
bring books arising directly out of that conscious¬
ness into the ghettoes and squatter camps where
there are no libraries, and into the farm huts
where there is no money to buy books in the
form of consumer luxuries.
It is formulated as a call for a People's
Literature.
How does People's Literature differ from
plain old social realism?
There is a basic distinction of the greatest con¬
sequence. Any writer may become a social realist
by choosing a worker as his or her protagonist
or hero. It is subject and treatment of subject
which defines social realism, not the class of the
writer.
But in South Africa, People's Literature is
conceived as that written by, not about, the
people. Thus it seems the responsibility for
creating it is not even that of any progressive
literary establishment.
Who are "the people"?
Virtually all blacks and so-called coloureds,
who comprise the overwhelming majority of the
population, qualify under the blunt definition of
workers as those who, if they don't get up in the
morning and go to work, won't eat: blacks don't
have unearned income. But the image of "the
people" has come to be symbolized more specif¬
ically in the features of farm workers, miners and
construction workers: the rural people and the
manpower they export under the migratory
labour system to single-sex hostels in the indus¬
trial areas.
The image is appropriate. These workers
stand, historically, at either end of that system
established by the conflation of capitalism and
racism; in between is the whole span of black
labour yoked by the white man factory
workers, street cleaners, domestic servants. The
agricultural workers cm white farms are the
lowest paid, having no statutory minimum wage;
the miners and industrial workers are the freest
on the way to economic emancipatum, having
organized themselves m powerful trade unions
which will one day end the migratory labour
system that brought them from country to town
without the right to be accompanied by their
families.
A People's Literature therefore means to
paraphrase Walter Benjamin literature con¬
ceived as the people's "ability to relate" their own
lives.
But Benjamin was speaking of the storyteller
among the people a title which in itself sets the
relater aside as si')meone who has emerged from
those with whom he shares the conditions of
li\'ing. The object of People's Literature, m the
context of which I am speaking, is to do away
with the title, to reject its 1 unction of singling-
out, with attendant connotations of a particular
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
gift or talent others do not have, A year or two
ago a South African literary journal featured
"Worker Poets" as a special category of poet, as
one might speak of the lyricist or symbolist. The
poems were written, in their spare time, by
people who labour with their hands. But the vali¬
dation of their status as poets was that they were
workers. The syllogism follows; writing poetry
IS not work; any workers can write poetry; there¬
fore poets are not workers.
The "worker" poet or playmaker or prose
ficticm writer does not wish to emancipate him
or herself from the condition of worker; not at
all. He is asserting not a desire to opt out of the
labour class, but his right, as a worker, to the
making of poetry, of literature his right to tran¬
scendence not as a quality that will exalt him
above the dirt of toil, but which is integral to it.
He is asserting his right to the ecstasy of creation
while doing piece-work eight h(jurs a day.
South African road-workers.
This has been a deep subconscious desire,
beyond material justice, in most workers' move¬
ments; it is present in the determination of the
liberation movements to establish a workers'
democracy in South Africa.
The "worker poets" are the balladeers of
strikes, wage disputes, the perils of industrial acci¬
dents, the violence experienced in clashes with
the police sent in by the bosses or the State to
break strikes. The balladeer is himself one of the
striking workers; he is himself miles underground
with his fellow miners when the rock-fall occurs.
It IS the experience that makes him a poet, it is
the rhetoric of union meetings and the liberation
movements' manifestos that gives him the Word.
To those of us who look for an intensely
transformed experience in reading poetry, not
experience as poetry, generalized doggerel put
together mainly out of slogans stirs little response.
But People's Literature, it can be argued, is not
for the reader who is looking for experience
intensified by the writer; it is for those whose
own experience exceeds the intensity of words.
Therefore the most banal of verbal signals will
set off identification. People's Literature is not
meant to enlarge the reader's understanding
beyond his familiar work, but to concentrate his
understanding on the worth and dignity of that
world, give it its rightful place in the national
consciousness as the class-alienated storyteller is
believed not to be able to do.
How IS this to be achieved?
The cover of a recent number of Cultural
Worker, the journal of the Congress of South
African Trade Unions, quotes the Angolan writer
Jorge Rebello: ". . . forge simple words/that even
children can understand/words which will enter
every house/like the wind,"
Nothing IS more difficult. Some with the
vocabulary of genius at their command have
spent a lifetime striving for the words that will
enter every house.
In the context of a People's Literature it is
either a glorious demand, based on faith in the
untapped creative resources of the masses, or a
total misunderstanding of the labour that writing
IS, to believe this achievement could come from
the spare-time occupation of anybody who has the
appropriate life experience. Handling the
unfamiliar tool of the written word, what the
"worker poet" fashions is likely to be what
Njabulo Ndebele has termed the "interaction of
the surface symbols of South African reality"
no more.
So far, drama is the literary form which best
shows positive signs of realizing the concept of
a People's Literature. Some reasons may be iden¬
tified. The worker-actor-playmakers are in total,
immediate interaction with the roles they play
in real life. There is unity of experience in the
actuality of dramatized events "set" cm the fac¬
tory floor, for the workers' plots are contem¬
porary autobiography the clashes between
themselves and the bosses, the relation between 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38
the workers' own differing personalities and states
of awareness. Any inadequacy of dialogue is over¬
come by song and mime. Humour and the phys¬
ical individuality of performance break the bonds
of rhetoric in which the "worker poets" bind
themselves.
In a recent play, Mrs. Thatcher, represented
by a worker wearing a huge, toothy papier-mâché
blonde head, takes a coffee break with the bosses
as a metaphor for collusion between British
capitalism and South African industry. The mode
so happily hit upon is something between Grand
Guignol and Brecht an observation using refer¬
ences that might mean nothing to the players, and
of which, indeed, they prove they have no need,
having of themselves arrived at a successful means
of relating their own lives among their own
people.
For the professional writer the ultimate
problem in the creation of a People's Literature
is not so much, in the case of the black writer,
that he has been removed from the common lot.
It is not so much, in the case of the white writer,
that no matter how involved he or she may be
in the cause of black liberation, he or she has
never shared the general experience of living on
the dark side of the colour bar.
The problem is that generations of the most
appalling cultural deprivation inevitably have
produced in the masses a deep resentment of the
"republic of letters". In South Africa this
"republic", like all other pretensions to
democracy, has been a mockery of the name. It
has discounted the masses entirely, whether as
creators or consumers of literature. Blacks have
felt that the only way to belong, in literature,
except as other people's material, was to cease to
be one of the people. And that, in this revolu¬
tionary era, is to cease to be yourself: your black
self taking your own liberation and life in your
own hands.
The desperate determination to claim the
worth of that life in the lasting form of art is in
conflict with any acceptance that the writer does
what the worker cannot do that the practice of
writing is a craft, a trade in itself. Why be sur¬
prised? The resentment engendered by this con¬
flict has led other revolutions to send their writers
to cut cane. In capitalist societies it has jealously
led to sending writers to perform in chat shows
anything rather than have the masses recognize
that the writer labours at a vocation whose con¬
dition IS not open to the public, even if anyone
may become President. . . .
But the concept of a People's Literature not
only assumes everyone can write. It also assumes ,
everyone reads or will read. Alas, we know this
has not proved to be the case in most countries
where the majority has become literate and books
are available in all communities, through libraries.
Certainly not in the Western world. Comic-book
literacy is not book-literacy.
With desk-top publishing and modest new
forms of distribution through trade union and
A series of iinocuts by the
South African artist
Vuyiie C. Voylya. From top:
Rhythm in 3/4 time I,
Rhythm in 3/4 time II,
Rhythm in 3/4 time IV, and
In the coffin of my skin.
community organizations m South Africa's black
ghettoes, journals and books are beginning, in a
very small way, to be part of the iurmshing of
places where people gather, and as such may
begin to be used as essentials.
It is early to judge, perhaps, but 1 believe it
significant that Ravan Press, which publishes a
series of "simple" books, written in a limited
vocabulary by blacks who, if not always "worker
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Rows upon rows of "bachelor
quarters" in which black
South African workers are
obliged to live cut off from
their families.
NADINE GORDIMER,
South African writer, was
awarded the 1991 Nobel prize
for literature. Her fictional
works and essays chronicle the
experience of a society torn
apart by apartheid, against
which she has always fought,
actively supporting blacl< South
African writers. She is the
author of ten novels and more
than 200 short stories, the
most recent a collection
entitled Jump (1991) and a
novel, My Son's Story (1990).
writers" in the strict sense, are at the remove only
of a rural schoolteacher from that category, found
a surprising demand for an expensive scholarly
work, far remioved from the rhetoric of political
pamphlets as from any assumed naivety of
"people's" fiction. This was Tom Lodge's Black
Politics in South Africa since 1945. Skotaville Pub¬
lishers had a similar experience with Mokgethi
Motlhabi's Black Resistance to Apartheid.
Of course, these are not works of the imagi¬
nation; but the effort of comprehension may stir
.something that leads to works of the imagination.
For, in Benjamin's beautiful aphorism, literature's
great offering is its "creation of a demand which
could be satisfied only later". And that is surely
a perfect definition and defence of literature's
revolutionary function. Literature calls up the
effort to formulate and analyse vague yearnings,
to resolve frustration and resentment through
grasping their causes and acting upon them at a
level of roused being the learning-by-maxim of
political education cannot reach. Here stands the
writer's real justification for his existence in the
revolutionary situation, and the claim for the
practice of literature as a category of work
demanding special aptitudes and skills.
It has to be accepted that talent is not a
right alas, no.
But every means of giving talent a chance to
discover itself, to grow within political, economic
and social structures conducive to this, is a right.
None of these structures has ever existed for the
black masses in South Africa, in a succession of
racist régimes. Writing talent has been stifled,
wasted, distorted by exile within as well as
without the country. But this talent will not be
freed to create a People's Literature, in the true
sense that literature shall embody the conscious¬
ness of the masses instead of that only of an élite,
if writing is regarded as a kind of therapy for
industrial alienation.
By law and lack of education, by lack of
libraries which are the writer's continuing
educationby lack of a corner to themselves with
a table to write at, the potential writers among
the people have been cast as miners, street
cleaners, ditch diggers. If there is to be a People's
Literature it will come about because these
writers will now do, instead, the work they are
gifted and fitted for. If there is to be a People's
Literature it will come about only if there is no
State interference, and if social conditions ensure
that cofnic book literacy, disseminated through
the long-established colonial agencies which con¬
tinue to monopolize distributitm of publications
in the entire African sub-continent, does not
become the people's literary culture, as it has in
so many parts of the world.
Only then could the contradictions oí a
"People's Literature" begin to be resolved. Only
then, when asked "Who writes?", those of us
who work to create a post-colonial, post-
apartheid culture in South Africa might be able
to answer: all who have the ability. And when
asked, "Who reads?", might be able to answer:
the people. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
I^Tlie UN's lon¿ campaign against apartliéi
T
40
.HE United Nations has been in the forefront
of the struggle against apartheid for over four
decades. The General Assembly has condemned
apartheid as a crime against humanity, and the
Security Council, which has considered the ques¬
tion since 1960, has termed apartheid a crime
against the conscience and dignity of mankind.
The United Nations has sought to help bring
about a peaceful solution of the conflict by
promoting concerted international action,
including the isolation of South Africa diplomat¬
ically, economically and militarily, the develop¬
ment of international norms against apartheid and
the provision of assistance to the victims of apart¬
heid and their liberation movements.
The racial policies of South Africa were dis¬
cussed at the very first United Nations General
Assembly session in 1946, when India complained
that the Government had enacted legislation
which discriminated against South Africans of
Indian origin. During the 1950s, as South Africa
persisted in and intensified its policies of racial
segregation, numerous resolutions concerning
apartheid were adopted.
The Sharpeville massacre
In March 1960, sixty-nine people were killed and
180 wounded at Sharpeville, when South African
police opened fire on peaceful, unarmed demon¬
strators protesting against the "pass laws". The
"pass laws" required that all Africans carry
"reference documents" which served as identifi¬
cation and as work and travel permits. The inci¬
dent and its aftermath, which rocked South
Africa, aroused world opinion and marked a
turning point in deliberations on apartheid at the
United Nations.
For the first time the matter was taken up
by the Security Council, which on 1 April 1960
adopted a resolution stating that a continuation
of South Africa's racial policies might endanger
international peace and security and calling upon
the South African Government to abandon its
policies of apartheid and racial discrimination.
The General Assembly asked Member States to
break off diplomatic relations with South Africa,
boycott South African goods and refrain from all
exports to South Africa, including the export of
armaments. In 1962, it established a special body,
known since 1974 as the Special Committee
against Apartheid. The mandate of the Com¬
mittee is to review all aspects of South Africa's
policies of apartheid and the international reper¬
cussions of these policies.
The Committee quickly assumed an activist
role in what the General Assembly in 1966 would
formally designate as the "international campaign
against apartheid". It has promoted sports, cul¬
tural, consumer and other boycotts and, with the
Centre against Apartheid, established in 1976, has
co-operated with Governments, intergovern¬
mental t^rgamzations, religious leaders, student
and youth movements and anti-apartheid groups
in mobilizing international public opinion in sup¬
port of United Nations resolutions against
apartheid.
In a move to provide assistance to the victims
of apanheid, the General Assembly in 1965 estab¬
lished the United Nations Trust Fund for South
Africa. The Fund is based on voluntar)' contri¬
butions from which grants are made to organi¬
zations for legal aid to persons persecuted under
South Africa's repressive and discriminatory laws,
relief to such persons and their dependents, and
relief for refugees from South Africa. Two years
later, the United Nations Educational and
Training Programme for Southern Africa
(UNETPSA) was set up. One of its functions is
to provide scholarships for higher education to
disadvantaged students from South Africa and
Namibia.
During the 1970s, continued efforts by the
United Nations to persuade South Africa to
abandon the system of apartheid were intensified.
In 1973, the General AssembK' adopted the Inter¬
national Convention on the SuppressK:)n and
Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid, which
came into force in 1976. The following year, the
General Assembly barred the delegation of South
Africa from participating in its work, and recom¬
mended the exclusion of South Africa from par¬
ticipation in all international organizations and
conferences under United Nations auspices as
long as the authorities continued to practice apart¬
heid. Since then. South Africa has not participated
in the proceedings of the General Assembly.
In 1974, the UN invited the national libera¬
tion movements recognized by the Organization
of African Unity the African National Congress
and the Pan Africanist Ctmgress of Azania to
participate as (observers in its debates on the ques¬
tion of apartheid, and later recognized the move¬
ments as "the authentic representatives of the
overwhelming majority of the South African
people". They attend United Nations meetings
and conferences, and are consulted on decisions
concerning South Africa.
In 1976 and subsequently, the Cjcneral
Assembly denounced South Africa's declaration.s
of "independence" for the so-called homelands
«A6A1h
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
pkUÍ7^LM^^/*¤í^
Untitled (1982), a collage by the American artist Robert Rauschenberg. This poster and that
shown on page 44 were produced for an exhibition entitled "Fifteen Artists against
Apartheid", organized on the occasion of the International Day for the Elimination of Racial
Discrimination, 21 March 1983.
or bantustans, none of which has consequently
gained any diplomatic recogniticm bv the inter¬
national community,
A historic step the mandatory
arms embargo
The Security Council took a historic step in
November 1977, making mandatory the volun¬
tary arms embargo against South Africa which
It had called for in 1963. This marked the first
time that the United Nations had taken action
against a Member State under Chapter VII of the
Charter, which provides for enforcement actiem
with respect to threats to the peace.
In 1982, the South African Government began
to introduce measures which it claimed were
reforms of the system, among them the establish¬
ment of a raciall)' segregated tricameral parlia¬
ment, including Asians and Coloureds but
excluding Africans. The General Assembly con¬
demned these measures since they maintained
power exclusively in the hands of the white
majority and failed to offer any political rights
to blacks.
Efforts by the United Nations in the first half
of the 1980s were directed mainly towards gaining
support for the implementation of comprehen¬
sive mandatory sanctions against South Africa in
order to isolate the country from the interna¬
tional community and force it to abandon its
apartheid policies.
In 1985, the level of violence and unrest
increased in South Africa, and the Government
declared a nation-wide state of emergency, ban¬
ning many opponents of apartheid or detaining
them without trial. Acting in response to the
imposition of these repressive policies, the
General Assembly stepped up its anti-apartheid
activities. In February 1986, the Security Council
adopted a sweeping resolution including a
demand for the lifting of the state of emergency,
the release of all political prisoners and detainees
and the eradication of apartheid. However, efforts
in the Security Council in July 1986 and several
subsequent attempts as well to make economic
sanctions mandatory were not successful.
Sport and cuhural boycotts
win world-wide support
The sports, cultural and academic boycotts of
South Africa, whose implementation has been
monitored by the United Nations, have been
important means of exerting pressure on the
South African authorities. By involving millions
of people worldwide they became a particularly
effective way to educate public opinion, demon¬
strate international abhorrence of the apartheid
system and press for reforms.
The ban on sporting contacts with individuals
or organizations from either inside or outside
South Africa was legalized when the International
Convention against Apartheid in Sports, adopted
by the General Assembly in 1985, came into
effect in April 1988. The Commission against
Apartheid in Sports has since 1989 mcmitorcd the
sports boycott. Since 1981, at the request of the
Special Committee against Apartheid, the Centre 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
against Apartheid has published a periodic register
containing the names of athletes who ignored the
ban.
Under the cultural boycott, first called for by
the United Nations in 1968, entertainers, actors
and other artists were requested to work towards
the cultural isolation of South Africa. From 1988
onwards, the guidelines for the boycott, which
were elaborated by prominent entertainers and
artists at a Symposium held in Athens, Greece,
placed outside its scope those cultural and aca¬
demic activities which had the intent and effect
of opposing apartheid, enriching the culture of
the oppressed people of South Africa and fur¬
thering the liberation struggle. Since the early
1980s, and at the request of the Special Com¬
mittee against Apartheid, the Centre has pub¬
lished a Register of entertainers, actors and others
who have performed in South Africa.
On 13 December 1991, in recognition of the
progress that had been made towards abolishing
apartheid, the General Assembly called unani¬
mously for nations to start restoring sports, cul¬
tural, scientific and academic ties with South
Africa. It recommended that sports links be
resumed with unified, non-racial sporting organi¬
zations within South Africa and that assistance
be given to disadvantaged athletes in the country.
It also called for a resumption of links with
democratic anti-apartheid organizations and
individuals in the cultural, academic and scien¬
tific fields.
Many United Nations bodies and specialized
agencies such as UNESCO and the International
Labour Organisation have played an important
part in the campaign against apartheid. The Com¬
mission on Human Rights has kept apartheid
under close review and oversees the implemen¬
tation of the conventions against racial discrimi¬
nation and apartheid. The United Nations Centre
on Transnational Corporations has focused on
the role of foreign investment, trade and loans
through the transnational corporations in sus¬
taining apartheid.
The Declaration on
Apartheida milestone in UN action
In the late 1980s, world developments and events
in South Africa contributed to an important
breakthrough at the General Assembly. In 1989,
through the efforts of the Special Committee and
the Centre Against Apartheid, consensus was
achieved for the first time on substantive resolu¬
tions on apartheid. In December 1989, at a Spe¬
cial Session, the General Assembly aJDproved
specific guidelines for the peaceful dismantling of
apartheid in South Africa. The guidelines were,
contained in the Declaration on Apartheid and
its Destructive Consequences in Southern Africa.
The adoption of the Declaration by consensus
was unprecedented, and clearly demonstrated the
unity of the world community on the South
African question and its resolution.
The Declaration encouraged the people of
South Africa to join together to negotiate an end
to apartheid and to agree on all the measures
necessary to transform South Africa into a non-
racial democracy. It indicated the fundamental
principles for a new constitutional order;
measures to be taken by the South African
authorities to create a climate conducive to
negotiations and free political activity; guidelines
to the process of negotiation; and a programme
of action that called for sustained international
action until there was clear evidence of profound
and irreversible changes, bearing in mind the
objectives of the Declaration, namely the eradi¬
cation of apartheid and the establishment of a
united, non-racial, democratic South Africa.
Nelson Mandela at the UN
In February 1990, in a speech at the opening of
parliament two months after the Special Session,
South African President F,W. de Klerk
announced a lifting of the ban on the African
National Congress and other anti-apartheid
movements together wdth a number of other
reform measures, and stated that his final aim was
a totally new and just constitutional dispensatitm
Two posters issued in 1988
by the United Nations Centre
against Apartheid.
This article has been specially
prepared forth'e UNESCO
Courier by the United Nations
Centre against Apartheid
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
for South Africa. On 11 February 1990, Nelson
Mandela was released after twenty-seven years of
imprisonment, and in June 1990 he addressed a
special meeting of the Special Committee against
Apartheid at United Nations Headquarters.
The Secretary-General sent a mission to
South Africa in June 1990 to report on progress
that had been made in the implementation of the
UN Declaration towards the dismantling of apar¬
theid. The General Assembly took careful note
of the ensuing Secretary-General's report, and in
September 1990 adopted a resolution which called
upon the South African Government to take a
number of steps and the international commu¬
nity to maintain the pressure on South Africa,
in order to bring about a speedy end to apartheid
through negotiations.
Despite certain setbacks, considerable pro¬
gress was made during 1990 and 1991 towards the
resolution of the conflict in South Africa. A
number of steps specified in the United Nations
Declaration as necessary for establishing a climate
conducive to negotiations were implemented,
including the repeal of the major apartheid laws.
the ending of the state of emergency and the lif¬
ting of bans on political organizations. Also,
many political prisoners were released.
As noted by the Secretary-General in his
second progress report, released in September
1991 and covering the period from June 1990, the
process towards the ending of apartheid in South
Africa, although halting, has remained on course.
As he pointed out, the convening of a meeting
of all parties concerned to discuss and draft a new
constitution based on non-racial, universal suf¬
frage tops the political agenda.
A continuing struggle
One of the major obstacles to the beginning of
the talks was removed when an agreement was
reached in August between the United Nations
High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) and
the South African authorities, which cleared the
way for UNHCR to begin to provide assistance
in the voluntary repatriation of an estimated
30,000-40,000 political exiles and refugees, who
will now be able to return home, free from the
threat of persecution.
Although the end of the road may be in sight,
the long struggle against apartheid is certainly not
over yet. An array of discriminatory laws are still
on South Africa's statute books, political trials
continue, and a number of political prisoners are
still in jad. Outbreaks of the violence which has
wracked the country continue. Furthermore, the
apartheid system has generated widespread
poverty and grave crises in the economy, parti¬
cularly in the education, employment, health and
housing sectors. Unless concerted efforts to
redress these issues are made, the social and eco¬
nomic problems they cause could jeopardize the
ongoing process towards negotiations, the success
of a constitutional settlement and the future sta¬
bility of the country.
Through its concerted efforts over the years,
the United Nations has played a vital role in for¬
ging an international consensus on action for the
elimination of apartheid. The Organization will
continue to work to maintain that consensus
throughout the transitional period. It will con¬
tinue to promote the maintenance of the pres¬
sure needed for the early establishment of transi¬
tional arrangements, the agreement on a n-.-w
constitution, and the installation of a democratic
government.
The United Nations will also provide assis¬
tance to the opponents of apartheid and the disad¬
vantaged sectors of South African society in a
concerted and co-ordinated manner, as well as
encourage the international community to assist
in addressing the glaring socio-economic inequa¬
lities in the country. By this two-track approach,
the United Nations alms at reinforcing the
momentum towards the establishment of a
united, democratic and non-racial South Africa.
Only when this has been achieved can it be said
that the international community has fulfilled its
moral and political obligations to remove a
system from the world that affronted the sense
of dignity and humanity of mankind. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
r UKCO and k élimination of apartlieiíf^lif;;^^
u.
44
'nescx") drew up a programme for the elimi¬
nation of apartheid in the 1950s. In fact, it was
in reaction to studies carried out within this
programme, which were being circulated by the
Institute of Race Relations in South Africa, that
South Africa decided to withdraw from
UNESCO in 1955,
In 1965, at the request of the UN Special
Committee against Apartheid, UNESCO
initiated a programme of social science research
to elucidate the effects of apartheid and to
produce reliable and objective information on
what was actually happening in South Africa. The
publication Apartheid, Its Effects on Education,
Science, Culture and Information (1967, revised
edition 1972) was the first in a series of works
that UNESCO has produced over the years on
the problems of apartheid in South Africa and
Namibia. Other studies deal inter alia with the
impact of apartheid on social science research, the
falsification of history, the influence of apartheid
policies on news repiorting, anti-developmcnt in
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
the so-called bantustans, the effects of emergency
rule on education, information and culture, and
the dynamics of race and class in an apartheid
society.
UNESCO has also undertaken to mobilize
the intellectual and academic community, artists,
creators, media professionals and educationalists
in various countries.
A UNESCO International Meeting of
University Researchers held in Beijing, China,
from 1 to 4 September 1986 drew up a Five-Year
Research Plan on Apartheid. As a follow-up to
the recommendations of this meeting, several
international working groups of scholars were
convened to reflect on problems of apartheid: one
on the economy and apartheid in co-operation
with the University of the West Indies (in King¬
ston, Jamaica, 21 to 28 April 1989); one on
women, apartheid and options for a post-
apartheid society (in Caracas, Venezuela, 19 to
21 September 1989); and one on apartheid and
culture (in Dakar, Senegal, 27 to 30 November
1989). Problems encountered by the Front-Line
States were examined during a sub-regional work¬
shop organized under contract with the Zim¬
babwe Institute of Development Studies on the
effects of destabihzation policies of South Africa'
m the fields of education, science and culture
(in Harare, Zimbabwe, 20 to 24 February 1989).
Over the years, UNESCO has likewise
provided technical and material assistance,
through the African National Congress and the
Pan Africanist Congress, to the development of
educational structures and programmes for
refugees in asylum countries and for training key
personnel.
In 1989, UNESCO adopted a Special Project
which, while continuing to focus on the eradica¬
tion of apartheid, also has the longer-term objec¬
tive of reflecting on and helping the people of
South Africa to prepare the foundations for a
future apartheid-free, democratic society. In order
to contribute to reflection on the needs and pri¬
orities of an apartheid-free society, three major
meetings were convened during 1991.
1. A Workshop on Human Rights Issues for
a Post-Apartheid South Africa was organized
jointly by UNESCO and the African Commis¬
sion for Human and Peoples' Rights in Banjul,
The Gambia, from 18 to 21 June 1991.
Participants at the Workshop, while noting
certain positive developments, pointed out the
shortcomings of on-going législative reforms. Cer¬
tain apartheid structures remained intact
notably the "bantustans", the tri-cameral racially
defined parliament, the police and the security
Opposite page: Apartheid No,
a poster created by the Italian
painter Leonardo Cremonini in
1983. Above, a class of black
pupils in the so-called Bantu
system of primary education.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Frederik de Klerk and Nelson
Mandela at the signing of the
National Peace Accord in
Johannesburg on 14
September 1991.
46
FRANCINE FOURNIER
IS UNESCO's Assistant
Director-General for Social and
Human Sciences. A former
professor of political science
at the University of Montreal
and at the University of
Quebec (Montreal), she has
served as director of research
and later president of the
Quebec Human Rights
Commission and as president
of the Canadian Equality Rights
Panel. She is the author of
several books and articles
related to human rights
forces. Affirmative action, including for women,
was required to tackle the legacies of apartheid
and institutionalized racism.
2. An International Conference on Educa¬
tional Needs of the Victims of Apartheid was
organized by the UN Special Committee against
Apartheid and UNESCO, in co-operation with
the Advisory Committee of the United Nations
Educational and Training Programme for
Southern Africa, at UNESCO Headquarters in
Paris from 25 to 27 June 1991.
The Conference called for a radical restruc¬
turing of the entire educational system and inter¬
national support for urgent training of the black
population. Universities and other educational
institutions which were promoting educational
and training programmes for the black majority
population deserved particular support from the
international community. The role played by
anti-apartheid organizations during the transition
period was recognized, and the Conference
endorsed the convening of a national meeting of
non-racial educational organizations and
specialists, to take place in South Africa at an
early date, in order to further work out national
priorities and strategies in education and training.
3. UNESCO convened a Working Group on
Problems of Access of Africans to Science and
Technology, with particular reference to South
Africa, in Lusaka, Zambia, from 17 to 20 Sep¬
tember 1991, in which African specialists in
science and technology participated, as well as
representatives of ANC, PAC and UN special¬
ized agencies. This workshop examined various
obstacles to the involvement of the black popu¬
lation in science and technology, with particular
reference to tertiary-level education and possibil¬
ities for future assistance in preparing a non¬
discriminatory science and technology policy for
a free South Africa.
In the immediate future, UNESCO plans to
contribute actively to the Conference on the
Future Role of the United Nations System in
Efforts to Redress the Socio-Economic Inequali¬
ties in South Africa being organized under the
auspices of the UN Centre against Apartheid and
the Special Committee against Apartheid in
Windhoek in February 1992, as well as a joint
UN system study on this topic. A workshop on
problems of nation-building and of promoting a
culture of peace and democracy will be convened
in co-operation with the OAU in southern Africa
in 1992.
UNESCO will provide assistance in the
training of leaders and planners in key nation-
building areas, including applied social sciences,
science and technology, social communication
and education.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Ck chronology of repression and resistance
1652
The Dutch East India
Company sets up a trading
station at the Cape.
1659
First battles by the Khoi in
defence of their land against
the settlers,
1702
First major military clash
between settlers and Xhosa
people near the banks of the
Fish River,
1806
Britain takes over the Cape
from the Dutch.
1845-1875
Svstem of segregation
introduced throughout Natal
under British colonial rule.
1860
Indentured labourers begin
to be brought from India to
Natal to work m the sugar
plantations.
1867
Discovery of major diamond
deposits.
1886
Discovery of gold on the
Witwatersrand,
1899-1902
Anglo-Boer War,
1906
Suppression of the Bambata
rebellion marks the end of the
first phase of armed resistance
to colonial conquest.
1910
Britain formally transfers
power to the white minority
in South Africa, and the Union
of South Africa is established.
1912
January 8. Founding of the
African National Congress
(ANC).
1913
Land Act prevents Africans
from acquiring land outside
"reserves", amounting to 7 per
cent of the total land area of
the country, as a "temporary"
measure.
1936
Native Trust and- Land Act
increases the land set aside for
Africans to 13 per cent of the
total area of the country,
fixing "once and for all" the
distribution of land. The
increase in land is presented as
compensation for the
elimination of African
parliamentary voting rights,
1945
A strike by 100,000 African
miners closes many mines. The
strike is broken by armed
police: at least 12 mmers are
killed, 1,200 injured and many
trade unionists arrested,
1949
ANC adopts Programme of
Action, ushering in a period of
mass campaigns,
1950
Group Areas Act passed as a
powerful measure for the
continuation and extension of
racial segregation.
June 26, On this day,
subsequently known as
Freedom Dav, demonstrations
and strikes are held in
opposition to the Suppression
of Communism Bill,
1951
Bantu Authorities Act
provides for setting up
bantustan structures,
1952
June 26, Launch of Defiance
Campaign against Unjust Laws
by the ANC and the South
African Indian Congress,
1953
Public Safety Act enacted,
giving the executive the power
Natal Indian Women's
delegation to the Congress of the
People, 1955.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
to declare a State of
Emergency,
Segregation of trade unions
made a condition of
registration. Exclusion of
Africans from official
negotiating machinery, and
consequent outlawing of strikes
by African workers,
1955
Formation of the South
Alrican Congress of Trade
Unions (SACTU), the first
non-racial trade union
federation, and a subsequent
member of the Congress
Alliance,
June 26. Freedom Charter
adopted by the Congress of the
People, jointly organized by
the components of the
Congress Alliance under the
leadership of the ANC,
1956
August 9. In protest at the
extension of passes to African
women, 20,000 women march
to the Union Buildings in
Pretoria.
1956-1961
Treason Trial in which 156
leaders of the Congress
movement are eventually
acquitted of High Treason,
1959
Pan Africanist Congress (PAC)
formed,
1960
March 21. Police kill 69
people in the Sharpeville
massacre, during a peaceful
demonstration against the pass
laws called by the PAC.
March 30. State of
Emergency: 22,000 people
detained or arrested. The
Unlawful Organizations Act is
passed and used to ban the
ANC and the PAC,
May 31, Foundation of the
apartheid republic, with a
military mobilization to
prevent protests and
demonstrations. Eight to ten
thousand people arrested and
many detained under the
"12-day law", the first law
allowing detention without
trial.
December 31, First
operation of Umkhonto we
Sizwe ("Spear of the Nation"),
formed by leaders of the ANC
and allied organizations to
undertake armed resistance,
1962
Nelson Mandela secretly
visits .several countries to seek
facilities for military training
and returns to St:)Uth Africa to
continue working
underground.
1963
"Rivonia Trial" of
Umkhonto We Sizwe leaders,
including Nelson Mandela,
1967-1968
Joint actions by ANC and
the Zimbabwe African People's
Union against the Smith
régime in Rhodesia.
1969
South African Students
Organization (SASO) formed,
1973
Wave of strikes by black
workers.
1976
Internal Security Act passed,
to introduce even harsher
repressive measures,
June 16, Soweto massacre as
police shoot at schoolchildren
protesting against apartheid
education. The protests
develop into a general uprising,
1977
September 12, Death in
detention of Steve Biko.
October 19. Banning of 18
Above, demonstrators burn their
pass books (1959).
Below, from left to right: a 1961
protest against the Group Areas
Act of 1950, which had
intensified residential
segregation; police action against
a white student demonstration in
Cape Town (1972); young blacks
march in the streets of Soweto to
commemorate the massacre of 16
June 1976.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
organizations, including most
of the black consciousness
organizations, and two
newspapers with a black
readership (the World and
Weekend World).
1979
April 6. Solomon Mahlangu,
ANC combatant, executed.
1980
March 21. Launch of
campaign for the release of
Nelson Mandela by the Sunday
Post newspaper (successor to
the banned Weekend World).
Countrywide boycotts
against apartheid education, a
wave of industrial militancy,
protests against rent increases
and bus boycotts combine in a
period of sustained popular
resistance. In June ANC
guerrillas sabotage the Sasol oil-
from-coal complex. Over 900
people detained during the
year.
1981
January 30. The South
African Defence Force attacks
houses in Maputo, killing 13
ANC and SACTU members,
May 31, The apartheid
régime celebrates the 20th
anniversary of the founding of
the apartheid republic, m the
faee of a countrywide
campaign of protest and
boycott of the celebrations,
November 4, Successful
boycott of the elections to the
South African Indian Council.
1983
Regional United Democratic
Front (UDF) structures
established in first half of year,
August 20. National launch
of UDF,
November. White
referendum approves
government's constitutional
plans: boycott of elections to
African local authorities.
1984
Widespread rent and
transport boycotts,
August, Over 80 per cent of
voters boycott elections to new
Coloured and Indian chambers
of parliament.
September 14, New-
parliament opened. Police
violence against rent protests m
Vaal area sparks protests across
the country,
October, Troops move into
townships in strength.
1985
Mass resistance continues;
consumer boycotts and stay-
aways spread,
February. Nelson Mandela
rejects offer of conditional
release from prison, requiring
him to renounce armed
struggle,
June, ANC National
Consultative Conference in
Zambia calls for "people's
war",
July 20, Partial State of
Emergency declared.
November 30. Congress of
South African Trade Unions
(COSATU) formed.
1986
Mass resistance continues;
large-scale protest stay-awavs;
extensive detentions and
repression; public calls to
unban ANC.
June 12, National State of
Emergency declared,
1987
Strikes in mines and m
public sector; violent conflict
involving Inkatha escalates m
Natal.
June 16, One and a half
million workers stay away
from work to commemorate
Soweto uprising.
July, Meeting in Dakar,
Senegal, between Afrikaner
intellectuals and ANC.
November 5, Govan Mbeki
released from prison.
December. Commander of
Transkei military force takes
over bantustan administration.
1988
February, Mutiny by
Bophuthatswana bantustan
forces suppressed by the South
African Defence Force (SADF),
February 24, 18 anti-
apartheid organizations
prohibited from engaging m
any political activities,
June 6-8. Three million
workers stav awa\' from work
in protest against Labour
Relations Amendment Act,
October 26, Boycott of
municipal elections, -
1989
Mass defiance campaign,
including hunger strike bv
detainees, grows during year,
accompanied by trade union
protests against Labour
Relations Amendment Act,
January, Beginning of
hunger strike by emergency
detainees,
June, Number of emergency
detainees released since
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
beginning of hunger strike-
reaches 800.
August. Organization of
African Unity adopts ANC
proposals tor negotiations
process (Harare Declaration).
September. F.W. De Klerk
replaces P.W. Botha as State
President: large demonstrations
in major cities as part of
defiance campaign.
October 15. Release of eight
leading political prisoners;
subsequent mass rallies mark
virtual unbanning of ANC.
December 9-10. Conference
for a Democratic Future unites
2,100 organizations.
1990
Unbanning of ANC and
release of political prisoners
leads to talks between ANC
and government, but police
continue to break up
demonstrations. Violence in
Natal escalates and spreads to
other areas.
February 2. De Klerk
declares that ANC and other
restricted organizations will be
unbanned; massive rallies
follow. Moratorium on
executions at the time there
are over 60 political prisoners
on Death Row,
February 11. Nelson
Mandela released from prison;
he tours the country addressing
mass meetings.
March 3. With popular
support, bantustan army
officers take over
administration of Ciskei
bantustan-.
April 5. Bantustan army
commander takes over Venda
bantustan administration after
mass protests.
May 2-4. Talks in Cape
Town between ANC and
government on removal of
obstacles to a climate for
negotiations result in
declaration of a common
commitment to peaceful
negotiations.
June. State of Emergency
lifted except in Natal province.
July 2. Nationwide stayaway
protests against violence in
Natal,
August 6. ANC-Government
meeting in Pretoria results in
agreement on definition of
political prisoners and detainees
to be released according to
agreed schedule; ANC suspends
armed struggle.
August/September. Violent
conflict involving Inkatha
spreads to Transvaal; police
given increased powers.
October 8. Government
declares that guidelines for
release of political prisoners
have been agreed, and exiles
and others who have carried
out political offences can apply
for indemnities.
October 18: The state of
emergency is lifted in the
province of Natal.
November 7: The
Rustenberg Declaration,
adopted at a meeting of 230
delegates representing 81
churches, "unequivocally
rejects apartheid as a sin".
Source: International Defence and
Aid Fund, London.
50
1991
January 8: ANC calls for the
convening of an all-party
congress while reiterating its
demand for an elected
constituent assembly and an
interim government.
February 1: President de
Klerk announces in Parliament
that the Fand Act and Group
Areas Act, as well as the
Population Registration Act,
will be repealed. He issues a
"Manifesto for a new South
Africa".
February 14: The Labour
Relations Amendment Bill is
adopted by Parliament,
Invalidating amendments to
labour legislation introduced
by the authorities in 1988.
April 5: ANC addresses an
open letter to President de
Klerk demanding that the
authorities undertake specific
measures to end the violence
and stating that, otherwise,
ANC will suspend any further
discussion with Pretoria on
negotiations towards a new
constitution.
April 29: More than 50
persons are killed and 176 are
injured in the townships of
Soweto and Alexandra.
June 5: Parliament votes to
repeal the Group Areas Act
and the Land Act.
June 17: Parliament votes to
repeal the Population
Registration Act. The
population register is to be
maintained until a new
constitution is negotiated.
July 2-6: The National
Conference of ANC elects
Nelson Mandela as its new
President and Walter Sisuiu as
its Deputy President. Cyril
Ramaphosa becomes Secretary
General.
July 9: The International
Olympic Committee recognizes
the National Olympic
Committee of South Africa,
thus paving the way for the
country's participation in the
next Olympic Games.
September 4: The National
Party issues its proposals for a
new constitution. ANC
criticizes them as "an attempt
to disguise an effective
minority veto".
September 14: Some 23
political parties and
organizations, including the
South African Government,
ANC and the Inkatha
Freedom Party (IFP) sign a
National Peace Accord in
Johannesburg.
October 25-27: Some 90
organizations, including ANC
and the Pan-Africanist
Congress of Azania (PAC),
attend the Patriotic/United
Front Conference in Durban
and adopt a Declaration calling
for a constituent assembly and
a sovereign Interim
Government/Transitional
Authority.
November 4-5: Sixty
delegates representing 19
parties hold a preparatory
meeting to outline the future
main tasks of the Convention
for a Democratic South Africa
(CODESA). They agree on a
nine-point agenda for the
Convention and on the
establishment of a steering
committee to facilitate its
convening.
December 20-21: Nineteen
political groups participate in
CODESA in Johannesburg.
Seventeen of them (including
the South African Government
and ANC but excluding the
IFP) sign a "Declaration of
Intent".
United Nations action
in 1991
June 25-27: An International
Conference on Educational
Needs of the Victims of
Apartheid in South Africa is
held in Paris by the Special
Committee against Apartheid
and UNESCO, in co-operation
with the United Nations
Educational and Training
Programme for Southern
Africa. Participants adopt the
Paris Statement, which calls on
Pretoria to address urgently the
education crisis in South Africa
and on the international
community to provide
assistance in this field.
August 16; The United
Nations High Commissioner
for Refugees (UNHCR) and
the South African Government
initial a Memorandum of
Understanding on the
voluntary repatriation and
reintegration of an estimated
40,000 South African returnees.
December 13: The General
Assembly calls upon the
international community to
resume academic, scientific and
cultural links with democratic
anti-apartheid organizations
and sports links with unified
non-racial sporting
organizations, and to review
existing restrictive measures as
warranted by positive
developments.
Source: United Nations Centre
against Apartheid.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheljNESCO
Published monthly in 36 languages and In braille
by UNESCO, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31. rue François Bonvin, 75015 Pans, France
Director: Bahgat EInadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévéque. Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Anane Bailey, (Tel.' 45.68.46,90)
Documentation: Violette Rmgelstein (Tel 45.68,46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel.. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.. 45.68.47.15),
Ivlouna Chatta
Administrative assistant: Prithi Perera
Selection in Braille In English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Mane-Domimque Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Meinikov {Moscow)
German: Werner Merkff (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Metra ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wad Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok {Seoul}
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Saiaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,^
Slovene: Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou {Athens}
Sinhaia: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larranaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong {Hanoi)
Pashto: Ghoti Khaweri (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangia: Abdullah A M. Sharafuddm (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Miian Syrucek (Prague)
Galiclan: Xabier Senin Fernández
(Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45 68 45,89),
Subscriptions: Mane-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakíté, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Dm,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk, Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65),
Mail: Martial Amegee (45.68,45 70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval {45.68,47,50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel : 45.68.45.65
1 vear; 211 French francs. 2 years' 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year 132 French francs. 2 years- 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of UNESCO
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providirifi the credil line reads "Reprinted from the UNESCO Courier",
plus dato of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor
Signed dfticles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request, Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returripd unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering pfjstage Signed articles express thé opinions of the authors
cind do not necessanfy represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors oí the UNESCO Courier. Photo captions and headlines
are written by the UNESCO Courier staff, The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
.icLRptance by UNESCO or the United Nations, The UNESCO Courier
1=: produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UNESCO,
f Place de I ontenoy. 75700 Pans, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox),
Ann Arbor Michigan 48100, U S A,: (3) N.C R MicrocarO Edition. Indian
Head, inc , Hi West ¿íOth Street, f^ew York, U S A , (4) Bell and Howeti
Oo , Ola ^^1<lnsfleld Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S A,
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) - DEPOT LEGAL CI FEVRIER 1992.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE NO 71844 - DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP
Photocomposition The UNESCO Courier
Photogravure-impression Maury Imprimeur SA,,
7 I route d'Etampes, 45330 Malesherbes,
ISSN 004 1-^j2/8 NO 2- 1992 OPI - 92 - 3 - 501 A
ïhme
ojîknatiim
(Mmh ¡m):
Also featuring:
an interview with Indian physicist
Vandana Shiva
Cover, page 3 (right): H. MaraLs-Barrit © Gamma, Paris. Back cover: United Nations. Page 2: (£) Christian
Olivé, Paris. Page 3 (left): Unesco/Michel Claude. Page 4 (top): UNESCO/Alicia Aureli. Page 4 (middle and
bottom): UNESCO. Pages 5, 7 (left): UNESCO/Dominique Roger. Page 6 (left): UNESCO © SPADEM,
1992. Page 6 (right): UNESCO. Page 7 (right): UNESCO/Arnaldo. Page 8: All Rights Reserved, Page 11:
M. Courtney-Clarke © Explorer. Paris. Page 12: J.Oster © Musée de Tflomme, Paris. Drawing by M.
Bertoncini and M. Gaillard under the scientific supervision of Y. Coppens. Page 15: © Kinkas. Paris. Page 16:
Littleton © Sygma, Paris. Pages 17, 20 (left), 24-25: Guy Hobbs © Gamma, Paris. Pages 18 (above), 23, 28,
33, 38: © The artists and the Museum of Modern Art, Oxford. Page 18 (below): Patrick Zachmann
© Magnum, Paris. Page 19: © Rogor-VioUct, Paris. Pages 20-21: J.N. de Soye © Rapho, Paris. Pages 22, 26-27,
35, 49: Gideon Mandel ,© Magnum, Paris. Pages 40-41, 44: ©World Artists agains" Apartheid. Page 29: Bahc
© Sygma, Paris. Page 31: Lily Erancy © Rapho, Paris. Page 32: Martine Franck © Magnum, Paris. Page 34:
© Gilles Abegg, Paris. Page 36-37: Chris Steele-Perkins © Magnum, Paris. Page S9: Alberto Venzago
©Magnum, Paris. Pages 42, 43: United Nations Center against Apartheid, New York. Page 45: A. Nogues
© Sygma, Paris. Page 46: Louise Gubb © Rapho, Paris. Pages 47, 48 (above): Eli Weinberg (ë International
Defence and Aid Fund for South Africa. Pages 48, 48-49: © International Defence and Aid Fund for South
Africa. Page 50: Eric Bouvet feJ Gamma, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
FOR A UNITED, NON-RACIAL
AND DEMOCRATIC SOUTH AFRICA
]]>
</page>
</document>
