<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="092021eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
: .i I r±
%
DOUBLE ISSUE JULY/AUGUST 1992
^a^p»9S»^
#3«
bíseb
UNIVERSALITY:
A EUROPEAN VISION?
1205 -9208 -40.00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered for
publication in this feature. Your
photo should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of architecture or
any other subject which seems to
be an example of cross-
fertilization between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send us
pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds in
which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all
photographs.
Timeless cities
1992, acrylic, ink, collage
(38 by 27 cm.)
by Henry Christiaën
"Where are these strange
city walls? In what
forgotten Acropolis? In
what unlikely Manhattan?
In what undreamed of
Babylon, buried beneath
the layers of the ages?" In
this imaginary urban
landscape, the French
artist Henry Christiaën
has juxtaposed a variety
of architectural styles and
elements, including some
that evoke the electronic
circuitry of modern
technology. He thus
reveals affinities of
structure and rhythm
between civilizations and
cultures which transcend
time and place.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 INTERVIEW
Mikis Theodorakis
describes a Greek childhood
onten
JULY/AUGUST 1992
68 Unesco m Acr/ow
NEWSBRIEFS
fU Unesco in action
WORLD HERITAGE
A dream city built on salt
by Roy Malkin
I J Anniversary
Stefan Zweig
by Gertraud Steiner
Reflections
Ziryab, master of Andalusian music
by Mahmoud Guettât
Reflections
One sky, One world
by Tom Krol
f Recent records
by Isabelle Leymaríe
and Claude Glayman
82 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
9 Universality:
a European vision?
Editorial by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
10 AN IDEA WHOSE TIME HAS COME
11 The two faces of Europe
by Enrique Barón Crespo
13 The moral imperative
by Karl Otto Apel
18 Louder than words
by Sami Naïr
20 The common ground of humanity
by Mahmoud Hussein
26 CHANGING PERSPECTIVES
27
31
47
52
56
57
61
67
Cover:
Complete (1989), mixed
media, by the Turkish artist
Akyavas Erol.
Back cover:
Volcano/Trees (1989),
a photo-collage by
the US artist Pat Horner.
Between two worlds
by Tahar Ben Jelloun
Africa's long march
byAhmadou Kourouma
Eastern Europe: an uphill road to freedom
by Antonin Liehm
Latin America: a different way forward?
by Ernesto Sábato
THE WHOLE AND THE PARTS
A golden age of dialogue
by Vassilis Vassilikos
Two great traditions
by Wang Bin
The face of a stranger
by Emmanuel Lévinas
35
Greenwatch
69
Commentary
by Federico Mayor
TheïÎNESCO
îffi^COURIER
45th year Published monthly
in 33 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure
the unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail,
upon the Intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between
their peoples and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each
other's lives	»
Extract from the Preamble to the Constitution of Unesco, London, 16 November 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
T E R V I E W
MIKIS THEODORAKIS
describes A GREEK CHILDHOOD
No one who has heard the
wonderful bouzouki melodies
written by the Greek composer
Mikis Theodorakis for Zorba
the Greek or his theme music
for two other noted films, Z
and État de Siège, will ever
forget them. Theodorakis has
infused the soul and spirit of
the Greek people into all his
musical works. He is also a
militant who today, as a
member of his country's
parliament, continues a
struggle for freedom and
justice which began when he
joined the wartime resistance
as a teenager and has taken
him more than once to prison
or into exile. Here he looks
back on the circumstances
that gave rise to his musical
vocation and his political
commitment.
Tell us something about your early life.
I was born on 29 July 1925 on the island
of Chios, opposite the native village of my
mother on the mainland of Asia Minor, in
what is now Turkey. My father was from
Crete. He had volunteered to serve in the
first Balkan War, in which he was wounded,
and had then entered the civil service. When
the Greek army occupied Smyrna, he was
posted to the small town of Bourla, where he
met my mother. She came from a very poor
family. Her father was a farmer during the
winter and went out fishing in the summer.
Her brother, who had had an education,
later became a Director in the Ministry of
Economic Affairs. My family therefore came
from the lower middle class of government
officials who instilled a sense of discipline in
their children.
I was born after the military defeat
which Greece suffered following the Turkish
revolution of Kemal Ataturk. It was a real
tragedy for the country. I think that Greece
lost its soul when it lost Ionia. Greece and
Turkey have been in conflict with one ano¬
ther over long periods of their history. The
first Greek nationalist revolution was
directed against the Ottomans, in 1821. And
Crete remained under Turkish domination
until 1912.
Many of our relatives, on both my
father's and my mother's sides, were victims
of these confrontations and made great
sacrifices. My father used to say that our two
families had shed a river of blood. I therefore
grew up in an atmosphere of patriotic stories
and the stirring revolutionary songs known
as Rizitika, which had a very great influence
on me.
Even so, you have memories of a happy
childhood.
Yes. We had a country house, where we
were surrounded by aunts and uncles form¬
ing one big family. This house had also been
:''&4£5
the home and source of inspiration of a
famous naive painter, Theophilos. It was a
wonderful experience to live there in the
middle of the olive groves, the orange trees
and the flowers, overlooking the sea. I
remember that there was a boat which used
to sail past twice a week. The impression
which that white boat on the blue sea has left
on me is like a wound, like the mark of a scar
left by a moment of exhilaration. I really
believe that I have tried, in everything I have
composed, to recreate that beauty and redis¬
cover those images engraved in my memory
like a childhood dream.
I also remember evenings we spent with
my father, stretched out on the ground
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
gazing at the stars. He knew a lot about the
stars and he explained them to me and made
me follow them, telling me their names and
their history.
Another of those childhood memories
that leave an indelible mark on you came
from my uncle. Just before he was posted to
Alexandria as consul, he came back to the
village to get married and brought me a gram¬
ophone as a present, together with records of
Greek classical and popular music and of
jazz, which was then at its height. I was only
four years old and there I was discovering
music! We used to hold social evenings at
which young people danced the Charleston
and the foxtrot and I was put in charge of
the gramophone. Moments like those have
meant a lot to me throughout my life!
My uncle also gave me a set of record¬
ings of operatic arias, which for a long time
made me afraid of opera. I think that this
was probably because, for a child of my age,
there was something frightening about the
voices of those famous tenors and prima
donnas. I was sixty before I made up my
mind to tackle opera. The music I heard on
that gramophone in my childhood certainly
contributed to developing my tastes for a
long time to come.
What sort ofchild were youf
I had some crazy ideas. I wanted to fly
like a bird. I climbed a tree and flung myself
into the air and almost broke my neck. Then
I did it again, because I was sure that I would
be able to fly. One day, I wanted to take off
from the top of a three-metre-high wall,
because I thought that I would be able to fly
down to the beach below. I was just about to
jump when my grandfather suddenly came
out of nowhere and tried to catch me and
stop me from hurting myself. I fell on top of
him and he lost his balance. I broke my
wrist, but the old man broke his leg. There
was utter panic all around me. Everybody
was obsessed with my wrist, but nobody
bothered about my grandfather. He was very
embittered, and started to refuse his food. It
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
was this, coupled with the after-effects of his
broken leg, that eventually ruined his health.
He died not long afterwards. That was the
first time I had seen a dead person and I
didn't realize what it was all about.
How did your musical vocation come to
youf
The period from 1928 to 1930 was a very
stormy one in Greece. There was one
government after another, which meant that
civil servants didn't have a very easy time of
it. My father was from Crete and was there¬
fore a liberal and a supporter of Venizelos.
He was not only my father's idol, but was
actually a relative. When he became prime
minister, my father was appointed Vice-
Governor of Epirus. It was a very poor and
backward region, where the children were
dirty and went barefoot. I was the only child
to have a pair of shoes, but I was so ashamed
that I used to take them off. Then Venizelos
was deposed and my father was transferred
to a less highly rated and above all less well
paid post in Cephalonia, which was very
hard for us.
The cultural atmosphere in Cephalonia
was completely different from that in
Epirus. The island had never been occupied
by the Ottomans and the influence of the
Venetians, and later of the British, could still
be perceived, even in the way people spoke.
The music played on the island was more
Western in style. It was there that I heard a
philharmonic orchestra for the first time. It
used to play on the main square and when¬
ever I went by I was transfixed, spellbound
with admiration. I was very impressed with
the conductor. When I asked my mother
what he was doing, her reply was: "That
man is suffering". For me too that music
meant suffering.
I was still at primary school when the
Metropolitan of Cephalonia came to inspect
my class and asked the other children and
me to sing the national anthem, so that he
could judge what our voices were like. After
that, twenty of us were chosen to sing can¬
ticles in a small local church on Good
Friday. The tunes were very old and beau¬
tiful two of them were in modal form and
one was tonal. I joined the church choir just
to be able to keep on hearing them. About
ten years ago, I used those three canticles in
my third symphony, in memory of those
times I shall never forget.
After Cephalonia, we were sent to
Patras, which was a more affluent middle-
class town, although it was not such a pretty
place. It was there, when I was buying some
books, that I found out what a musical
score was. My father explained to me that
that was how music was written, and gave
me my first lesson. There was a very good
choir at school, conducted by a teacher
who was also a violinist. Every morning
we used to sing a hymn by Haydn, with a
solo part which I must have sung well,
since the teacher regularly invited people
to come and listen to it. One day, he
offered me a violin, which I bought from
him. I then went to the academy of music
square. I was already very tall and thin and
people tended to look at me, with my lanky
frame, as if I was a bit of an oddity. In the
end, I shut myself up in the house and, as a
result, I made considerable progress with my
music. In the house opposite, there was a
beautiful girl with green eyes and I fell
madly in love with her. All alone in my
room, I watched the girl, who couldn't see
me, and composed a large number of songs
on my violin. I taught them to my mother,
who had a beautiful voice and sang well. In
Opposite page,
Anthony Quinn dancing a
sirtakl in a famous scene
from the film
Zorba the Greek, based on
the novel by Nikos
Kazantzakis, with music by
Mikis Theodorakis (left).
in Patras, but the violin teacher there used to
hit me every time I played a false note. Even¬
tually I left and went on studying by myself.
As a result, when I was about twelve, I
wrote my first songs to the words of classical
poems I took from my schoolbooks. The
melodies are beautiful, perhaps the most
beautiful I have ever written. There are
about seventy of them altogether and I plan
to publish them. I shall dedicate them to
schoolchildren, since they were written
when I was a schoolchild myself.
We left Patras for a poorer town further
south. It was summer and in the afternoons
everybody strolled about on the main
the evenings, after supper, when my father
asked us what we had been doing during the
day, we used to sing our songs for him. He
in turn started singing and later on my
brother joined in, so that we formed a family
quartet which I accompanied on the guitar
or violin, while also singing myself. My
father began to invite his friends, along with
the prefects and sub-prefects and a whole
small world of civil servants, to come and
listen to us. It was like having a job, since I
had to prepare a concert every evening for
my father's guests.
The following year, we changed towns
yet again. I was more and more on my own
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
and I spent a lot of time reading. My father
had a library of more than 1,600 books,
which followed us wherever we went.
Later on, in Tripolis, I started to learn
the piano and harmony. We couldn't afford
to buy a piano and there were only three in
the entire town. I practised the scales on the
piano of a rich American, who allowed me
to study at his house on Sunday mornings
when people were at mass. But I had to stop
playing as soon as he got back. For the first
time in my life, I felt a sense of hatred for
rich people who could afford a piano but
who didn't use it, whereas I really needed a
piano but was deprived of the opportunity.
If I became a Marxist, it was because of that
piano, which to my eyes was the embodi¬
ment of social injustice. I eventually hired a
harmonium, which I found very useful. But
all these setbacks taught me to write music
from memory, without any instruments, and
I was therefore later able to go on com¬
posing in exile and prison
Where and when didyou decide to devote
yourself to musicf
At Tripolis, in the Péloponnèse, which
was a poor region where life was very hard.
Many people emigrated to the United States
or went to seek their fortunes in Athens. I
decided to become a musician, although I
was fairly good at mathematics and liked
handling abstractions. My parents and my
maths teacher hoped that I would go in for a
glamorous profession, like architecture.
However, I went on studying classical music
and composing. I started writing piano
pieces at a time when I knew a girl who had
a piano and played Schumann and Bee¬
thoven. We used to give concerts to which
we invited the town's leading citizens. This
was during the occupation, when our only
diversions were poetry and philosophy. We
translated classical authors such as Aristotle,
Plato and Homer into modern Greek. There
was also the cinema, which only showed
German films, although we sometimes got to
see splendid musical films instead of military
propaganda. For example, I saw German
films which ended with the finale from Bee¬
thoven's ninth symphony, which had an
absolutely stunning effect on me. I was so
shaken that I actually fell ill and ran a high
temperature. In the end, I told my father and
the maths teacher that all I was interested in
was music.
In 1942, my father went to see the
director of the Athens conservatory with my
music. The director asked to meet me and I
went to his home, where we had a talk and
he listened to me play the piano. The upshot
was that he offered me a scholarship to the
conservatory, which I was due to enter in
1943. But I am jumping the gun. Before that,
there was another important stage in my life,
when I joined the resistance and discovered
Marxism.
It was wartime. We were deeply reli¬
gious and fervent worshippers. The love of
Christ, Christian charity and religious feel¬
ing catered for a real need when we had to
face up to the violence surrounding us and
«*-^
image of a hideous monster for me. But
when I started talking to these people and
learnt that they had been the first to rise
against the occupying forces, it made me
think. When I came out of prison, I joined
the resistance.
I was entrusted with the first resistance
cell at school. I had to explain my ideas and
justify the proposals I put forward. I there¬
fore had to read about Marxism and brief
myself on the ideology with which we were
going to fight the enemy.
the ugliness of the world at that time. Read¬
ing the Gospel was itself a form of resis¬
tance, but it was not enough. We had to do
something. We had to react. On 25 March
1942, we organized a demonstration against
the Italians in Tripolis. The National Libera¬
tion Front, which had been set up in Athens
and was communist-inspired, sent represen¬
tatives to help us. During the demonstra¬
tion, we were surrounded by the Italians. I
got into a fight and apparently struck an Ita¬
lian officer. Along with other demonstra¬
tors, I was arrested and beaten and was
taken to a barracks, where we were tortured
in an attempt to force us to reveal the names
of our leaders. I was then thrown into
prison, where I met the first resistance
fighters, who were communists. I was then a
member of the nationalist youth movement
formed by Metaxas and we abhorred com¬
munism. The very word conjured up the
Was this a sudden change of attitude of
yours? By that time, your only interest was
music, yet there you were becoming a
member of thepolitical resistance.
No, the change was not all that sudden. It
is true that I was still interested in music, but
we were spurred on by deeply held patriotic
feelings. We suffered terribly during the
occupation. The country was divided bet¬
ween the Germans, the Italians and the Bul¬
garians. There was talk of torture and the
population was reduced to famine. The Ger¬
mans surrounded Athens for four months
and 300,000 people died of hunger. My
family had always been very nationalistic
and it was only natural, therefore, that I
should join the resistance.
At that period, I gave a public concert,
attended by Italian officers, who were sur¬
prised to find a young musician and com¬
poser in front of them. From then onwards,
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Thera, Greece.
I became something of a celebrity among the
occupation authorities, since Tripolis was a
small town where everybody knew every¬
body else. The head of the Italian garrison
was a terrifying colonel whose excesses put
the fear of death in us. One evening, when
people were taking their evening stroll on
the main square, he suddenly came up to me,
took me by the shoulder and started singing
La donna è mobile! People looked at us in
amazement. Then, all of a sudden, his mood
changed and he pushed me all the way to the
hospital that was requisitioned for Italian
soldiers and had me searched. Since they
found nothing on me, he ordered me to
report to his office the next morning. When
I entered, he got up, gave a military salute
and said: "I hail the patriot and hate the
communist!" He then told me that the
Italians were due to withdraw from the town
on the following day and hand it over to the
Germans, who had demanded a list of
twenty resistance fighters to be executed. So
in order to save my life he had to arrest me
and send me to Athens! That's how I came
to leave for Athens. Only a few days later,
the colonel was killed in battle.
In 1944, 1 was arrested by the Gestapo.
Then the Germans pulled out and there was a
breathing-space which the communist
patriotic front used to its advantage. After
that, the British arrived and were at one time
in favour of the formation of a government of
national unity under Papandreou, but soon
urged confrontation with the communists.
Papandreou was caught between two
fires and eventually resigned, whereupon we
organized a demonstration against the Bri¬
tish in Athens, in the course of which the
police killed seventy demontrators in
Constitution Square. The partisans then rose
up in mass against the British, who had come
with heavy weapons and warships. The com¬
munist party was reluctant to put its most
seasoned fighters in the front line and with¬
drew them from Athens. Instead, we reserv¬
ists, who were students in the daytime and
soldiers after lectures had ended, were sent
into action. Even so, we managed to resist
for thirty-three days, after which the British
occupied the country.
The party, which was still quite strong,
continued to organize demonstrations for
two more years. Then the communists fell
into the trap of reacting to provocation and
civil war broke out. A fresh army composed
of 70,000 militants, including 15,000 women,
was mobilized. This was a well-trained army
set up with the help of the countries of Eas¬
tern Europe. Its strength surprised the natio¬
nalists and it managed to take control of
almost the whole of Greece! Then the Amer¬
icans landed with a full-scale battle-fleet,
rebuilt the national army and supplied it
with an exceptional array of equipment and
facilities. They hunted down the partisans,
made massive arrests and deported whole
villages to unpopulated islands, whereupon
Yugoslavia closed its borders to the fleeing
partisans, who took refuge in Albania, Cze¬
choslovakia, Bulgaria, Romania and even the
Soviet Union.
I was arrested for the first time in 1947.
Then there was a change of government and
I was granted an amnesty. I returned to
Athens, but had immediately to go into
hiding. I was arrested again and sent into
exile on the island of Ikaria, interned on
Macronisos with other political prisoners,
taken to a military unit and tortured for
several days before being sent to hospital,
and then brought back to Macronisos. At
the end of the war, I was just like a ghost,
walking on crutches.
Even so, you continued to compose during
this turbulentperiod?
I think that it was during these difficult
years that I wrote my most important
works. I also recopied the scores of the great
classical composers and studied them from
beginning to end. This was how I analysed
Beethoven's nine symphonies. I don't think
that anybody has ever composed anything
quite so all-encompassing. My own compo¬
sitions were confiscated at Macronisos, but I
had committed them to memory and was
able to reconstitute them afterwards.
In 1949, I was able to return to my
father's village in Crete. It was a horrifying
experience: all my cousins who had been in
the national army were there and they, like
me, had been wounded. Some of them had
had arms or legs amputated. We belonged to
the same family, yet we had torn each other
apart and had all lost out in the end. It was a
lesson I would never forget. In a sense, it
marked the end of my childhood. O
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
*
i
I he quest for universality is a response to a long-standing
human aspiration. It may have begun long ago with the sages,
prophets and mystics who sought a single divine principle which
would release the sacred from confinement within purely local,
tribal or national boundaries and make it accessible to people
everywhere. In so doing, they created a potential link between
each individual conscience and humanity as a whole.
The philosophers of the Enlightenment gave another meaning
to the quest when they removed its sacred dimension. They
regarded the principle of universality as inherent in human
nature and applicable to all people, whatever their religion or
community, by virtue of their status as members of the species.
This attitude, which seems unexceptionable today, was actually
a radical new departure at that time.
How far has Europe served ornotably through the slave
trade and colonialismbetrayed this vision of universality in the
last few centuries? Now that all other societies have been
confronted with it through European influence, how and at what
cost can they incorporate it into their mental and cultural
landscape?
These are some of the questions raised in this issue, which
has been inspired by an international meeting that was
organized by the European Parliament at Strasbourg on 21 and
22 November 1991 on the theme of "Universal culture and
Europea dialogue of civilizations". The authors of the articles
published on the following pages all took part in the meeting. In
our choice of contributions we have tried to give an idea of the
wide range of responses aroused by this important question. We
only regret that for reasons of space we have been unable to
publish texts by the other participants at the Strasbourg
meeting, who all contributed to a debate of high intellectual
calibre.
Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
" -
10
The double-faced
head of the Roman
god Janus
on a terracotta
votive stele
(Rome, 1st century
BC).
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The two faces of Europe
by Enrique Barón Crespo
European imperialism has
led many peoples to look
askance at the universal
values proclaimed by
Europe. But it is on this
heritage that the future
must be built
WHY should we be concerned with the
universal? For one thing surely
because the future of humanity on our
planet is the day-to-day responsibility of all of
us, everywhere. For another because the uphea¬
vals of the past few years have often triggered
reactions that oblige us to ask where we stand in
relation to the universal. What do we see around
us? A retreat into self-absorption, a resurgence of
aggressive sectarianism, a rising tide of nationa¬
lism, communities turning to fundamentalism.
We are witnessing a collective identity crisis
accompanied in some cases by a crumbling of the
forces that hold societies together.
In spite of this perhaps even because of
it the context in which these shifts in identity
are taking place is one of an irresistible march
towards globalization. Societies everywhere are
involved in the same processes of wealth-cre¬
ation and exchange. All societies, at least those
that are free, have access to much the same
information and, for better or for worse, the
same television mythology, the same games, the
same tragedies and the same hopes. But this
globalizing trend is egalitarian only in appear¬
ance, since it reproduces inequalities, imbalances
and tensions across the planet. To see that this is
so, one need only consider the current state of
North-South relations.
Yet out of this contradictory situation, with
its convergences and divergences, a completely
new historical configuration is emerging. We
may be entering an era of global immediacy.
Universality is ceasing to be an abstraction, as
part of a natural process shaped by the qualities
of each and every one of us. We cannot join in
this chorus of many voices unless we accept its
diversity. People today are no longer only
asking themselves about their place in their
families, their towns and cities, their regions
and their countries, but also about the role they
should play in the future of our planet, and
what they must do to remedy the harm caused
by pollution, technology and progress. 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Both for societies and for individuals the
word universality has many different meanings,
coloured by a host of historical, cultural and
religious connotations. It would be wrong to
attach priority to one of these meanings and try
to impose it on everybody. Modern anthropo¬
logy and ethnology have taught us that no civili¬
zation is superior to any other, that there is no
such thing as "advanced" or "primitive" intelli¬
gence, only collective mental images that must
be judged on their own terms. Yet we must
beware of falling into the trap of all-comprehen¬
sive relativism. When widely differing cultures
come into contact, some values remain inviolate,
and we must try to preserve them and ensure
that they are respected, not so much because
they serve our own particular interests as
because, through each and every one of us, they
reach out to embrace the whole of humanity.
Have we not entered a historico-cultural
period in which it will be possible to win uni¬
versal support for certain fundamental values?
A twofold demand for freedom and human
dignity is evident in social relations every-
Tofem (1991),
mixed media on batik by the
Slovenian artist
Anièce J. Novak. In the
words of its creator, this
work inspired by the sand-
paintings of the Navajo
Indians of North America is
an attempt to express a
"vision of one world in which
each element has its place
in a harmonious whole, thus
linking us to the universal."
where. This fundamental imperative is at the
heart of all questions relating to human rights.
Having contributed to the downfall of more
than one monolithic empire, it now requires
those of us who rightly defend equality of
opportunity and living conditions to reflect on
the best way to equate living well with living
freely. This equation is becoming a funda¬
mental and, when it is solved, a universal value.
Like Janus, Europe has two faces, a dual
identity oscillating between good and evil. As
the French historian Fernand Braudel once put
it, Europe is both hell and paradise. The past
two centuries have seen modernization and
progress but also war, revolution, colonization
and totalitarianism. Paradoxically, it is through
this duality that Europe has, since the sixteenth
century, made its mark on the world. Its great¬
est sin, perhaps, has been to fashion that world
in its own image. For the most part the rest of
the globe has paid it back by assimilating
its humanitarian ideals while rejecting its urge
to dominate. This is a lesson we must never
forget.
LA /'"NN / ,
12
Enrique Barón Crespo,
former Spanish
government minister,
was president of the
European Parliament at
the time when the
seminar on "Universal
culture and Europe" was
held. He is the author of
El rapto de Europa
(1990).
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The moral
imperative
by Karl Otto Apel
Contrary to the view
of some modern thinkers,
a universal ethic complements
and even guarantees the right
to be different
EUROPEAN universalist philosophy and
I am thinking particularly of moral phi¬
losophy and the philosophy of law has
always shown itself ultimately to be, in its poli¬
tical and economic implications, the ideological
expression of Eurocentric power. That, at any
rate, is how it appears even now to the peoples
of the Third World, who find the framework it
provides inappropriate for the expression of
their aspirations. Excluded from the debate
about themselves, strangers to European ideas
about universality, which to them smack of
colonialism, they are not permitted, for
example, to participate in the deliberations of
the World Bank or to attend the great interna¬
tional summits so as to adequately defend their
interests.
Even when their élites are accorded a
worldwide audience, they remain prisoners, at
least in economic terms, of the perspective
imposed by the interests of the wealthy coun¬
tries. This view tends to accord a priori uni¬
versal validity to the decisions of the great arbi¬
ters of international economic life, including 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Multi-image (1991),
by the Indian artist Naresh
Singh, who wished to evoke
in this portrait of a woman
with a fathomless gaze "the
age-old serenity of ancient
civilizations".
14
those relating to the reduction or cancellation
of Third World debt.
Even if one believes that the inequalities of a
market economy based on capitalism represent
an irreversible achievement of the cultural his¬
tory of humankind and I personally do not
it in no way follows that the socio-political fac¬
tors that underlie the economic power
structure linking rich and poor countries are
naturally pre-ordained.
On the other hand, no one would dispute
that it is the rich countries of Europe and
North America, and one must also add Japan,
that are primarily responsible for the current
world ecological crisis, both directly through
their uncontrolled waste of energy and toxic
emissions and indirectly where the destruction
of tropical forests by Third World agricultura¬
lists is concerned. At a time when the threat of
nuclear conflict seems to have been largely
lifted, the world ecological crisis constitutes the
best argument for a strict, universally appli¬
cable moral code.
That said, I would like to put forward an
argument which seems to me to confirm the link
between the European intellectual tradition and
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
e components of culture
Egyptian culture may be clearly analysed into the ancient Egyptian artistic component, the Arab-Islamic legacy, and the borrowings
from the best of modern European life. These elements are strongly antipathetic to each other. As they clash, the un-Egyptian
qualities are rejected and a purified blend emerges which is then transmitted from father to son and from teacher to pupil.
I realize that many prominent European thinkers are opposed to national cultures because they want mankind to have but a
single culture. I feel that this, however, is contrary to nature. While certain things, of course, are the common property of all men,
for example, many branches of science, others are individual and limited to a given nation, as in fact are many kinds of art. Human
life is so constituted that people are afforded the opportunity of particularizing the general and stamping their own imprint upon it.
Science has no homeland of its own, but when it settles in a country it becomes influenced by the prevailing atmosphere, physical
and social, and is thus able to reach the souls of its inhabitants. Art, on the other hand, is personal, portraying as it does the soul
and temperament of its producer. It scarcely appears when by the very fact of existence it acquires an indefinable quality that
brings the artist closer to his fellow men everywhere. An Egyptian statue is purely national in that it embodies the Egyptian nature
and taste; yet as soon as cultivated people glimpse it, they are moved by admiration. Similarly, a piece of typically German or
French music, say by Wagner or Berlioz, will touch the hearts of all sensitive listeners.
Culture is neither exclusively national nor international; it is both, often individual as well. Who can separate Beethoven from
the music of Beethoven or Racine from the poetry of Racine?
Taha Hussein
Egyptian writer (1889-1973)
Mustaqbal al-thaqàfah fi Misr (1938; The Future of Culture in Egypt,
translated from Arabic by Sidney Glazer, Octagon Books, New York, 1975)
its claims to universality. It is a historical fact
that ever since the start of the conquest of the
world by Europe, the repeated and constant
condemnations of such tragic manifestations of
this imperialism as the extermination of the
Indians or the African slave trade have them¬
selves proceeded from the universalist thinking
of European philosophers. This is as true of
Latin-American "liberation" theology and phi¬
losophy as it is of "dependence theory". It
holds true to the point that in the fields of
morality or legal theory it is hard to imagine
any philosophy with universalist pretensions
that could attract consensus support around the
world starting from premises other than those
of the tradition of European thought. This
seems to confirm the universalist vocation of
Europe, even if at present it amounts to no
more than pious intentions.
For and against a universal
morality
It is a remarkable and irritating fact that all the
names that count in the world of thought
today are critical of the idea of a universal
morality, which they consider to be useless,
superfluous or even impossible. So-called
"post-modern" philosophers such as Jean-
François Lyotard or the late Michel Foucault
also consider it undesirable, on the grounds
that universalism could stifle the variety of
individual forms of life. American neo-prag-
matists such as Richard Rorty and British
neo-Aristotelians such as Alasdair Maclntyre
go further, rejecting the very possibility of a
universal morality on the grounds that all
moral values, in Rorty's view, rest on a
consensual basis contingent on a specific cul¬
tural tradition. In Germany too, the view of
the conservative, neo-Aristotelian current
represented by such writers as H. Liibbe and
Otto Marquard is that a universal morality
transcending local differences is not only
impossible but undesirable. They hold that the
desire to assess the values attached to the
conventions and institutions of each cultural
tradition would do more harm than good.
It is worth noting that accepting the accuracy 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
of all these critiques would implicitly confirm
the view of Third World intellectuals that uni¬
versalisai is merely Eurocentric imperialism in
another guise. So Europe's universalist mission
arouses hostility both inside and outside the
continent. Basically its critics tend to deny the
very possibility of achieving a macroethic of
universal law recognized by all the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights, for example or
of a concerted approach to resolving the great
problems confronting humanity such as the
world ecological crisis.
Commenting on his great unfinished His¬
tory of Sexuality, the French thinker Michel
Foucault deplored the fact that classical Greek
morality based on "care for oneself", whose
goal was for each individual to find self-
fulfilment through a personal lifestyle, was sup¬
planted by the Christian Stoicism of Kant and
"a universal law imposed in the same way on
every reasonable being". He went on to reject
the very idea of a universal morality in the fol¬
lowing terms: "The quest for a moral formula
that would be acceptable to everyone in the
sense that everyone would have to submit to it
seems to me to be catastrophic". It is true that
shortly afterwards, when he was asked whether
human rights have a universal value, he felt
obliged, as the progressive militant he also was,
to reply in the affirmative. This internal contra¬
diction seems to me to result from the incom¬
patibility between Foucault's critique of power
and his post-Nietzschean conviction that all
discourse, including his own, is nothing other
than an act of power, the expression of a will to
power.
Currently critics of Eurocentrism look to
post-modern attacks on rationality, universa¬
lisai and the theory of consensus, and Sao
Paulo and Mexico City affirm as ardently as
Paris and the International College of Philo¬
sophy the right to plurality and to variety in
face of the ubiquitous tyranny of universal
reason. But what theoretical interest is there in
such a polarization?
If it were only a matter of demonstrating
the limits of certain types of rationality tech-
nico-instrumental, strategic or systemic-func¬
tional or establishing a distinction between
forms of reasoning centred on theory, morality
and aesthetic expression, this critique of the
homogeneity of rational expressions would be
doing no more than pushing at an open door.
But when the critique of rationality calls
into question the fundamental identity and
unity of reason in the name of difference and
plurality, it overshoots the mark and threatens
the very diversity that it aims to protect from
the reductionist tendencies of European
thought. For if this prodigious diversity really
exists and the ultimate goal of human commu¬
nication is to develop an awareness of it, does
the stress put exclusively on basic "difference"
and "otherness" not risk encouraging be¬
haviour similar to that of the first colonists who,
when confronted with beings very different
from themselves, considered them as not
human and so saw nothing wrong in massa¬
cring them or transforming them into beasts of
burden?
The consensus
ETHIC
It will be objected that that is not what the
postmodern critiques of the unity of reason
seek to demonstrate. What they try to do,
rather, is to win acceptance for the idea that the
essential differences with regard to the funda¬
mentals of morality and value judgements are
Minerve écrivant les droits
de l'homme
(1790, "Minerva Inscribing
the Rights of Man"), an
allegorical work by the
French historical painter
Jean-Baptiste Baron.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
irreducible and irrational. Max Weber used to
say that humanity practised moral "poly¬
theism", and one simply had to accept the fact.
I believe that the task now facing us is not
to set the particularism and self-concern of
individual existences against universal value-
structures, but rather to seek an accommoda¬
tion between an exacting universal morality
and the values of neo-Aristotelian individua¬
lism. As Kant realized, this would imply that
the ethics of great universal principles should
take precedence over a value-system founded
on self-fulfilment. In fact such an approach
would benefit individual aspirations, for ever
since the promulgation of Roman law inspired
by Stoicism, moral and legal progress in the
field of human rights , has always brought
advances with respect to individual particular¬
ism. It is in their inability to understand this
that the postmodern philosophers who set par
ticularisms against the unity of normative
reason have failed.
The consensus ethic, on the other hand,
allows for two-way communication, and concil¬
iation between the universal norms of an exact¬
ing morality and the burgeoning demands of
self-fulfilment in all its multiple manifestations.
This exercise in conciliation must involve the
search for a rational consensus rather than inti¬
midation or manipulation, which rely for their
effect on force.
To end on a personal note, I would
conclude that even in the domain of morality,
Europe's universal vocation is both an impossi¬
bility and a goal to strive for. As for knowing
whether it will be achieved and whether
Europe will succeed in dissociating itself
sufficiently from a manifestly Eurocentric ideo¬
logy of power, only time will tell.
Karl Otto Apel is a German
philosopher who has been
Professor Emeritus at the
University of Frankfurt since
1990. A specialist in
hermeneutics, he is the
author of an important body
of work covering in particular
the philosophy of language
and communication. His 2-
volume Transformation der
Philosophie (1973) has been
translated into eight
languages.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
How far is Europe meeting the
standards it sets itself?
Louder than words
by Sami Naïr
At a crossroads of cultures.
18
THE universal can no longer be regarded as
an abstraction. The process of unification
resulting from membership of a single trad¬
ing nexus, the worldwide domination of media
and information networks, and the sharing of
mythologies at the planetary level all imply that
any discussion of the universal is meaningless if
it does not take account of the individual cul¬
tures of which it consists. We shall not be
awarded a diploma for proficiency in universal¬
ity merely because we affirm our belief in the
fundamental values of humanism, freedom,
equality, tolerance, progress and human rights.
Societies are now judged by the world at large,
and the events that take place in them are
matched against the account they give of them¬
selves and the values they claim to epitomize.
For example, what the West says about uni¬
versality seems to be extremely constructive
when looked at in abstract terms, but much of
the shine rubs off when it is set against the
facts. In the past, colonization went forward in
the name of progress and civilization. Today,
although democracy may ensure that freedoms
are protected, in Western Europe it also finds
expression in the return of racism and xeno¬
phobia and the resurgence of exclusive local
allegiances.
The fact is that we are living in a zone of tur¬
bulence created by the revolution in world eco¬
nomic structures which took place in the 1970s
and 1980s. That revolution turned everything
upside down, including the chessboard of world
politics, relations between North and South and
between East and West, and even the forces of
social cohesion within the democratic societies
of Europe and America. The nature of the tradi¬
tional social classes is changing this is particu¬
larly true of the traditional middle and working
classes and new classes, with different values
and attitudes to life, are emerging. The rise of
new middle classes all over the world makes it
very difficult to define universal values rooted
in solidarity and progress, because these middle
classes are confronted with influxes of new
migrants in Europe from the developing
countries of the South and from Eastern
Europe, and in North America from Spanish-
speaking America. This encounter prompts
people in the host societies to reassert their own
identities and in many cases leads to attitudes of
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
refusal and rejection. It will not be easy to give
tangible form to a universal vision of the world.
Thought must also be given to the scope and
limitations of the European social and political
model. Although democracy and the economic
system subtending it seem to be here to stay,
they are far from perfect. It would be worth¬
while investigating the relationships between
different forms of power cultural, political and
economic. The media can in some cases be of
decisive importance in encouraging emancipa¬
tion and freedom, but they can also be extremely
dangerous by leading to new forms of alienation
(especially television) and by manipulating indi¬
viduals. Democratic access to the media is now
becoming a key issue, and the modern concept
of freedom of opinion clearly hinges on it. The
concept of democracy should also be refined,
since in these closing years of the twentieth cen¬
tury democracy cannot be considered simply as
an institutional form. It must be given a content
that will make it possible for social communica¬
tion to flourish and, in its wake, for society itself
to take responsibility for its problems.
Europe is, in the words of Enrique Barón
Crespo, former President of the European
Parliament, "easy to describe but difficult to
build". It cannot be defined in terms of an
ethnic, denominational or even narrowly cul¬
tural identity. In reality, Europe is both an
idea the idea of a dialogue and a universal
humanist outlook and a combat against ten¬
dencies which within Europe itself wish to
pervert this idea. Seen from the outside, Europe
must be both of these things simultaneously.
This is now the only way it can exert its power
of attraction.
European universality no longer depends
on the force of arms or even on the power of
words to convince. It faces a much more
difficult test in which success or failure will be
measured by the account which European
society will be seen to give of itself, day in day
out. Europe is no longer a source of fascina¬
tion, and that is all for the good. It will be
judged on its acts. It no longer holds the mono¬
poly on universality, but the Universal will be
recognized as the foundation stone of its iden¬
tity if and only if it provides itself with
appropriate democratic facilities; if it extends
democracy to all the people of whom it is
constituted; and if it supports the emergence
and strengthening of democracy the world
over. O
Opéra cosmique
(1991, "Cosmic Opera").
Composition by the French
artist Hélène Mugot.
Sami Nair, French
philosopher, is Professor of
Political Science at the
University of Paris-VIII. His
books include Machiavel et
Marx (1984), Le Caire, la
Victorieuse (1986) and Le
regard des vainqueurs
(1992).
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
If North and South are to meet,
both must make an effort-the
North to stop thinking it has a
monopoly on universal values,
the South to incorporate the
principle of universality within its
own value systems
An allegorical,
revolutionary
representation of Equality
and Liberty. 18th-century
French engraving.
Opposite page,
Metaphorical Salute to
Europe 1992, by the
French artist Marc Pio
Maximilien Salvelli.
The common ground
of humanity
by Mahmoud Hussein
20
THE European Enlightenment ushered in a
new conception of humanity, based on
the idea that certain fundamental charac¬
teristics the need for individual autonomy and
freedom, the ability to think for oneself by
exercising the power of reason, the aspiration to
progress are common to all human beings.
Over and above all differences of race, nationa¬
lity, region or class, the individual was acknowl¬
edged as belonging first and foremost to uni¬
versal humanity.
This truly modern view of the individual
seen independently of all his or her religious
and social affiliations was developed in the West
from the time of the Renaissance onwards and
assumed its final form in the eighteenth century.
Since then, however, the West has betrayed it.
No sooner had the bastions of feudalism and
absolutism in Europe been rocked to their foun¬
dations or toppled than the principles of huma¬
nism, which had hitherto been articulated with
crystal clarity, gradually came to be swamped by
the demands of financial and industrial capital¬
ism, for which the French Revolution had
opened up great prospects. A scheme for exer¬
cising world domination began to take shape,
boosted by the astonishing achievements of
industrialization. From then on, Europe would
export to other societies not the unabridged
message of a universal humanity but rather a
piecemeal collection of universal characteristics,
chosen to cater for the requirements of coloni¬
zation in those societies. Generations of emi¬
nent European thinkers did their utmost to
resist this betrayal of the principles of 1789. By
doing so, they saved their honour, but they did
not change the course of history.
The clash between universalist ideas and the
urge to dominate continues to this day. The
prime concern of the ruling political and eco¬
nomic classes is to hang on to their positions of
strength and sources of wealth in what used to
be called the Third World. The profits they
reap from a trading system based on inequality,
the exceptional sums they make from the sale
of arms, the pressures they can bring to bear as
a result of the indebtedness of the poorest
nations all these are arguments strong
enough, in the eyes of many governments and
private companies, to ensure that their interests
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
prevail over vague and half-hearted talk of
worldwide solidarity.
These interests are being defended all the
more fiercely today because their future seems
less assured than it once did, because of the
general instability of the world economy and
because of the growing frustration and unrest
which they arouse. In some extreme cases, their
defenders justify their actions by aggressive
ideologies based on claims of national, cultural
or even racial superiority.
In the countries of the South, where the
choice between fundamentalism and demo¬
cracy is starting to be posed, such attitudes are
grist to the mill of fundamentalism. Confronted
with a West whose power is so manifestly
geared to safeguarding its own privileges, those
who subscribe to the universal principles of
freedom and equality which came from the
West in the first place find themselves on the
defensive against opponents who are intent on
dismissing all such universalist pretensions as
mere camouflage to cover up injustice and
inequality on a global scale. Fundamentalism 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
North-South
^
22
uses the selfishness of the rich as a pretext for
giving an aura of respectability to the
selfishness of the poor and insisting that com¬
munities should keep themselves to themselves.
Some leading intellectuals and a handful of
statesmen in the West are trying to grasp these
home truths from the developing world and to
develop a strategy which is receptive to the uni¬
versal hopes of freedom heralded by the wide¬
spread emergence of people as individuals in
their own right. But the stakes involved in such a
change are too high for the burden to be shoul¬
dered by a handful of thinkers alone. It demands
a drastic shake-up in people's attitudes generally,
and a radical transformation of the very nature
of the ties binding the North and the South.
An immense moral privilege
Apart from the self-interest of the major powers
and the calculations of international financiers,
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Some have claimed that European culture has a universal mission. This, essentially, is supposed to distinguish it from all the
others. Its essence is at the same time defined as a creative activity of superior dynamism. Its expansion is considered as the
natural consequence of this superiority. European culture still seems to spread throughout the world, whereas the other cultures
remain purely local and hold their ground with difficulty.
Universality and superioritythese are comforting conclusions for Europeans. But there is a fallacy here. That European civili¬
zation created the entity of a modern world unified by the streamlined wing of the aircraft and by the radio wave is a historical
fact. This, however, was not the work of jurists, theologians, politicians or writers, but of engineers and scientists. So what we
should ask is which parts of "European" world civilization are truly universal and which are of purely local importance. As soon as
the question is clearly put, the reply is clear. The true universal factors are modern science and modern technology, with the philo¬
sophies that have made them possible. . . .
Furthermore, it is wrong to assert that science, whether pure or applied, was entirely shaped by the European Renaissance.
There were long centuries of preparation during which we see Europe assimilating Arab learning, Indian thought and Chinese tech¬
nology. It is hard to represent the physico-mathematical hypotheses of Galileo without the aid of Indian numerical notation. The
Arsenal, in which Galileo set the scene of one of his Dialogues which changed the world, could hardly have functioned without mas¬
tery of a typically Chinese technique, that of casting. Likewise, the first phases of science in Europe were neither so laborious nor
so fraught with difficulty as has been claimed. On the contrary, there were periods when great discoveries could be made just by
lifting a scalpel, once the basic technology of the discovery had come to light. It is thus impossible and even absurd for Europeans
to think that science is their private property. It is not something they can protect by an everlasting patent. Science has always
belonged to the world community.
Joseph Needham
British historian of science
The Dialogue of Europe and Asia, 1955
so far-reaching a change comes up against a fun¬
damental feature of Western consciousness. It
would entail making a sacrifice whose psycholo¬
gical consequences would be incalculable. It
would mean that the West would have to face
the loss of the immense moral privilege it has
enjoyed for the past five hundred years that of
being the motive force of universal history.
Throughout the period marked successively
by the Renaissance, the age of the great inven¬
tions, the intercontinental voyages, the Reforma¬
tion, the Enlightenment, the Industrial Revolu¬
tion and finally colonialism, European society
gradually forced everyone else to dance to its
tune. Other parts of the world had to adjust
their ways of thinking, acting and producing in
order to fit in with European demands; they
even had to take lessons from Europe when they
came to resist European domination. The West
felt it was justified in considering itself to be the
heartbeat of the world and in assuming that its
own new ideas and discoveries, not to mention
its own spiritual, moral and aesthetic expe¬
riences, had an immediate and universal validity.
Now it faces the threat of losing the power
to speak for others and to create in the name of
all. The graft of individualism that it has
implanted all over the world is beginning to
take in the most varied soils. It is giving rise to
modern democratic movements which are
rooted in desires, fears and dreams that are dif¬
ferent from its own, and through which a host
of rapidly changing societies are trying to assert
themselves, forge their own identities and set
their own stamp on the future.
The West is thus called upon to adapt to a
contemporary world that will move in increas¬
ingly unpredictable directions, and whose inner
resources and secret workings will often tend to
slip from its control, for they will draw on
memories and loyalties that are not its own. As
the West is forced to take on board intellectual
landmarks and constructs which it has had no
part in making and which will be transmitted and
given universal relevance by citizens from other
shores, it will have to think in terms of a future
which it is no longer alone in desiring or shaping.
It will have to learn how to become once more
one element in human society among others.
The West already realizes that although its
historical reign still continues, it is no longer
absolute; that although it may have invented
Mahmoud Hussein is the
joint pen-name of Bahgat
Elnadi and Adel Rifaat,
respectively the director and
editor-in-chief of the Unesco
Courier. Egyptian-born
political scientists, they have
lived for 25 years in France,
studying the problems of the
Arab world and, more
generally, of the societies of
the South. Their most recent
work is Versant sud de la
liberté: essai sur l'émergence
de l'individu dans le tiers
monde (1989; "The Southern
Slope of Liberty: an essay on
the emergence of the
individual in the Third
World").
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Project (1938).
Painting on newsprint by
Paul Klee.
the concept of the modern individual, it no
longer holds exclusive rights to its invention;
and that other possible models for man are
emerging. But the West has not yet come to
terms with this change nor agreed to pay the
price for it. To do so would mean abandoning
the benefits it has reaped from a historical
situation in which it has for so long been able
to identify the promotion of its own cultural
landmarks with the forward march of civiliza¬
tion and the furtherance of its own interests
with the welfare of humanity.
From the specific to the universal
In these closing years of a millennium that has
seen the peoples of the world emerge one after
the other from tribal, national or regional isola¬
tion, become caught up in the maelstrom of a
common history and feel that they share a
single destiny, it is becoming clear that this des¬
tiny will be democratic only if two conditions
are met. The peoples of the West and the
peoples of the South will have to find a new
way of relating their own specific values to the
values they have in common. Let the former
stop thinking that what is good for the West is
good for the world, and let the latter start to
incorporate a modern, universal dimension into
their own particular value systems.
In taking it for granted that it held the key
to universality because it had invented the
concept of the modern individual, the West not
only overestimated its own genius but also
depreciated its own achievement. It forgot that
other cultures and civilizations have, especially
in art and religion, reached out to values tran¬
scending space and time in a bid to encompass
the human condition in all its mystery; that
they have produced accomplished expressions
of universal preoccupations in metaphysics,
ethics, aesthetics and rational thought; and that
the West drew on all these sources before creat¬
ing in its turn a new vision of modern Man.
This new vision is destined to unite the
whole of humanity, for several reasons. It is the
culmination of so much that has gone before; it
draws inspiration from so many sources; it
marks the completion of so many initiatives
and experiments cut short by the vagaries of
history. It responds to the potential which is
latent within all people but was previously
confined within the straitjacket of their many
local allegiances. Now, without denying any of
these allegiances, it can illuminate them all.
The idea that modern Man is a creation of
the West that people elsewhere in the world
can only emulate by adopting Western ways
and surrendering their own identity is a mis¬
representation of the West's essential contri¬
bution to humanity. That is the mentality that
underpinned colonialism, corrupting the minds
of the colonialists and tormenting those of the
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
peoples they colonized. This double misun¬
derstanding can now be avoided.
THE FRAGILE FLOWERS OF FREEDOM
It is not for the West to export to others a value
which belongs naturally to it but would be alien
to them. Instead, the West should help others to
adopt, of their own free will and in their own
way, a value that is needed by all. That value was
first formulated by the West and long monopo¬
lized by the West for its own ends. Now the
West must serve the value it created. Let the
West protect the first, timid shoots of freedom
that need the universal nourishment provided by
human rights if they are to take root in very dif¬
ferent political and cultural soils.
Until now, the only way in which the
peoples of the South could try to protect their
personality was through confronting their iden¬
tity with that of others and rejecting out of hand
everything they regarded as specifically Western.
It is true that they have come to acknowledge
modern science and technology as necessary
aspects of the universal, but they have remained
convinced that these could easily be superim¬
posed on their own, unchanged identity. Now
Ntshak, raffia cloth
decorated
with divinatory symbols
by an artist of the Kuba
people (Zaire).
they are starting to realize that the concept of the
individual human being is the driving principle
behind modern universalism. They will have to
come to terms with this realization by volun¬
tarily doing violence to a part of their innermost
selves, by reappraising the core of values in
which the tyranny of the community, the habit
of despotism and the temptations of fatalism and
superstition are all closely intertwined. The
democratic imperative requires, in short, that
they must accept, a mutation and regeneration of
their very identity.
For intellectuals in the South who support
democracy, the time has come to accept this chal¬
lenge. They must do so if they are to follow the
same path" as their counterparts in the West and
the East and are to embark on the road to mem¬
bership of a global community experienced as an
intrinsic part of their own individuality. And
they must do so in order that all" those societies
which, in five hundred years of disorder and vio¬
lence, have moved from the stage at which their
identity was defined by community and religion
to the stage at which it is defined by the nation
can together, in a spirit of solidarity, embark on
the era of planetary identity. O 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
:
I
Ui
The Restaurant Window I
(1967),
by US artist George Segal.
Life-size plaster mouldings
reflect the distance between
people and the barriers to
communication.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Between two
worlds
by Tahar Ben Jelloun
The uncomfortably acute
perceptions of the intellectual
who is an intermediary between
two cultures
IN 1967, the Moroccan historian Abdallah
Laraoui published in Paris a book called
L'Idéologie arabe contemporaine ("Arab
Ideology Today"). In it he formulated the
problem of the Arab quest for identity in these
terms: "For three-quarters of a century, one
question has absorbed the Arabs: 'Who are the
others and who am I?'. . . Who are the non-
Arabs? They long went by the names of Chris¬
tianity and Europe. Their new title is at once
vague and precise: the West".
Twenty-five years on, the question is still as
topical as ever. It was brutally. restated by the 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
Gulf crisis and the subsequent war. Some have
answered it by rejecting everything associated
with the non-Arab world, and have gone so far
as to blame all the ills of the Arab world on the
West. Others have known the attraction and
fascination of the West but also its capacity to
repress, and to cultivate indifference and even
ignorance.
Those who are considered as links or inter¬
mediaries between the Arab world and the
West are in an unenviable position. They do
not stand between the two camps but rather
have one foot in each, casting a critical eye in
both directions.
The uneasy world of the Arab
intellectual
The days when Arab intellectuals were fasci¬
nated by Europe are over. Now the relation¬
ship is more complex. They are preoccupied
with Europe's future, with its weaknesses. As
for the Arab world, they feel a responsibility
towards it, but live in uncomfortable isolation
from it.
Arab intellectuals living in Europe today
feel uneasy. Perhaps this is a necessary stage in
developing a clearer sense of their own identity.
For many of the values born of the French
Revolution have become universal, as part of a
process that is making ever greater headway.
Now people around the world take to the
streets to fight for freedom and democracy as
well as for bread. Europe no longer has a
monopoly of values to which much of the
world now stakes a claim.
These intellectuals must constantly rectify
their vision of the world if they are not to be
abandoned by their own folk while at the same
time feeling alienated from a Europe that they
find disturbing. It is not a comfortable situation
to be in. But the tension it creates is interesting
insofar as it obliges thinkers constantly to take
stock, like photographers recording their sur¬
roundings.
In Europe Arab intellectuals have an oppor¬
tunity to express their individuality, to test
their subjectivity and affirm their uniqueness,
for the individual, both as a unique entity and
as a value, enjoys an unchallenged status there
that is linked to the rule of law. Until the coun¬
tries of the southern Mediterranean arrive at
the same situation, the individual will not
achieve recognition there.
Yet at the very time when the emergence of
the individual is a rallying cry in the Third
World, the individual is being increasingly
demeaned as a value in the West. A selfish indi¬
vidualism is gaining ground. A chill wind is
blowing as people become more and more self-
absorbed and unresponsive. This tendency can
be seen in the way in which the industrially
developed countries of Europe have reacted
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Basta Game Over
(1991).
A print made by Mélik
Ouzani to promote peace and
understanding between
peoples.
recently to the phenomenon of immigration.
Europe on those terms has not just lost its fas¬
cination, it provokes anger. Arab intellectuals
won over to Western values have good reason
to be concerned by the ways things are going in
such a Europe, which apparently seeks to
rekindle the spirit of colonialism and revive
ethnocentric attitudes.
The paradox is that these intellectuals some¬
times accept the achievements of liberal devel¬
oped societies without adopting certain aspects
of the cultures of those societies that are not
compatible with their own backgrounds. On
the other side of the Mediterranean there is a
similar paradox: Europe has such a splendid
image there that the picture sometimes verges
on caricature, since everything that comes from
the West is regarded as being good.
Everything? Well, not quite. In some non-
democratic countries, for example, the import
of large quantities of material goods is per¬
mitted, but the frontier is firmly closed to cer¬
tain ideas and principles. We have all heard
politicians claim that democracy, multi-party
elections and universal suffrage are "foreign
products" whose "consumption" would be
harmful for a traditional society. Even so, these
principles are now accepted as valid for all
countries and all peoples.
Prejudices
and suspicions
Is Europe equally fascinated by the Arab
world? Various clichés distort the picture,
resisting rational analysis as firmly as prejudices
always do. To begin with, the Arab world is
often confused with the Muslim world; people
hardly bother to distinguish between Arabs
and, say, Berbers. There is a passion for the
desert, but it is often viewed as a kind of
country retreat. Harems still haunt the popular
imagination, even though they have long since
ceased to exist. Polygamy is generally consid¬
ered to be widespread, despite the fact that it is
forbidden in many Arab and Muslim countries.
People think that the wearing of veils by
women is prescribed by Qur'anic law, when in
fact it is merely a matter of tradition (though
women do have to wear a veil when praying).
How can the picture be set right?
This is one of the duties of those intellec¬
tuals who wish to serve as intermediaries be¬
tween the two cultures. It is no easy task, for
politically the Arab world in general is held in
low esteem, its image tarnished by régimes that
can claim no democratic legitimacy. But there
is more to the Arab world than these un¬
popular systems. How can one set about
adjusting the image?
The Israelo-Palestinian conflict has only
reinforced European prejudices, while also
constituting an obstacle to the progress of 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
democracy in the Arab lands. Sometimes it
serves as a litmus test for attitudes towards the
Arabs and their role in history. Arabs do not
understand why Europe defends some causes
more than others. All this clouds relations be¬
tween the Arab world and Europe with mutual
suspicion. When a misunderstanding arises, it is
allowed to fester. Frank dialogue and healthy
curiosity free of all hypocrisy are in short
supply.
Time for
co-operation
If the era of fascination with the West is over,
let us hope that a new age of co-operation on
equal terms will not be slow in replacing it,
when specific projects can be tackled together.
It ..is time, for example, for the West to recon¬
sider the status of immigrants and to stop bran¬
dishing them as a threat at election time.
Consideration must be given to those
North African countries that want closer rela¬
tions with the European Economic Commu¬
nity. At the very least their demand to be
treated as fully-fledged partners and interlocu¬
tors should be taken seriously.
It is time, too, to highlight the originality of
the Mediterranean countries, whether they lie
north or south of the sea. In order to bring
them closer together for want of being able to
unite them, which is another matter what is
needed is a great moral force capable of over¬
coming suspicion, fear and unhealthy stereo¬
typed opinions.
Jean Monnet said that "people only accept
change out of necessity; and it takes a crisis to
make them recognize the necessity". Imagina¬
tion is needed as well as a sense of urgency, for
as Monnet also said, without imagination
peoples die.
Misunderstandings poison relations be¬
tween peoples, in defiance of all logic. That is
why it is so important to nip them in the bud.
Even when they have flowered, should we not
have the courage to try to clear the ground so
as to allow new co-operation to grow, free of
malice and suspicion?
In a time of exceptional historical upheaval
will an Arab voice be heard, so that its unique,
authentic tones, its own special contribution to
the universal heritage, can again join in the
chorus of history? O
Tahar Ben Jelloun is a
Moroccan-born novelist and
poet whose La Nuit sacrée
(The Sacred Night) won the
Prix Goncourt, France's most
prestigious literary prize, in
1987. Among his other works
published in English are The
Sand Child (1987) and Silent
Day in Tangier (1991). He is
also the author of a number
of essays, including
Hospitalité française: racisme
et immigration maghrébine
("French Hospitality: Racism
and Immigration from the
Maghrib", 1984).
Les Princes du désert
("Princes of the Desert").
Wash-drawing by the French
artist Claude Quiesse.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
There is much for the West to
learn from the original art,
religion and society of black
Africa. But first of all Africa must
learn to believe in itself
Africa's long march
by Ahmadou Kourouma
"When your friends do not tell you the truth, ask your
enemy andpay him to tellyou"
Malinke proverb
FOR an African, taking a view of European
civilization poses two problems at the
outset. The first stems from the extent to
which he or she is imbued with European cul¬
ture. For myself, I went to a European school
and I write in a European language. Each day I
live, function, and (thanks to the European
media) think like a European. How can I stand
back far enough to take a genuinely African
view of this civilization? Europe's economic,
political, military, technological and intellectual
strength nowadays allows it to make its culture
universal. Nothing totally escapes its influence
or the ideas behind it. As they say in my village,
I shall have to dance and watch myself dancing
at the same time. And that is no easy matter.
The second problem is how to define 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Marble head of Athene
(460 BC)
from Aegina, Greece.
32
African culture. That vast continent contains
several Áfricas and hundreds of cultures: hence
a myriad possible views of European civiliza¬
tion. For the sake of simplicity I shall divide
Africa into two, a Muslim Arab area and black
Africa, and confine myself to presenting the
black African view of European civilization.
For this purpose we need to examine the main
features of European cosmogony and religion,
and compare them with their traditional
African counterparts.
Starting with Gods, the European God and
the black African God have one feature in
common: each of them is a single God who
created the world. It was only after they had
completed this tremendous fundamental task
that their functions became differentiated. The
European God is a God revealed to humankind
by prophets, and those who have heard the
Gospel have a duty to spread it to the world.
This God ascended into heaven, but before
doing so He left humankind in sole charge here
on Earth. He granted human beings a soul, and
put the whole universe at their disposal. He can
use them as he wishes, even if it means des¬
troying them. Humankind is free and at the
same time a prisoner, since it is God who
governs everything here below: it is God who
marks out the path everyone must tread. When
a person dies that person disappears for good,
is recalled by God forever.
So much, in brief, for the essential features
of European culture. They still exist, although
after the Renaissance Western thought tended
to become secularized and decided to separate
itself from religion. But the axiology, the
system of moral values and the ontology,
remained linked to Judaeo-Christian ideas.
This Judaeo-Christian conception of the deity
is common both to Europe and to the Muslim
world.
IN THE BEGINNING
WAS POWER. . . .
The black African God is a natural God. He
has revealed himself to no one. He sent no one
to preach the good word, did not become flesh,
and asks no one to make him known. He will
not sit in judgement after death. He ascended
into heaven, like the European God, but will
stay there for good. He no longer concerns
himself with the world or takes an interest in
what happens here below. Less unjust, he gave
all his creatures (things, plants, animals and
men) souls, or "Powers" as black Africans say.
Life is essentially a constant struggle between
these powers. As an animist priest from Casa-
mance explained to us: "In the beginning was
Power. God, the supreme power, created all
power by infinitely diversifying his own. God
created all energies at one stroke, and life on
Earth is now no more than an interchange of
powers, willed and planned by God. Man
intervenes in the structure of the world by
words and sacrifices, since in this way he can
ask God to move powers about. This is why
the world is at the same time both completed
and inchoate."
For black Africans language is not merely
an instrument of communication: it is the
expression par excellence of the power of
Being, the release of life forces. The words of
the ancients are sacred, and the dead are not
dead: they never went away, but exist in things,
beings and plants. Above all, it must not be
thought that traditional African religion is a
thing of the past: that is not true. Even when
converted to one of the great world religions,
Africans retain part of their religious heritage.
When we analyse the value systems and onto¬
logies of black Africans, we find that they are
still rooted in the concepts of traditional reli¬
gion. Thus their views about Western civiliza¬
tion are mainly derived from what are called
animism, naturism, vitalism and even fetishism.
For Europeans, nature and the environment
are there to be dominated. The environment was
created by God for humankind. For black Afri¬
cans, however, people live not merely off nature
but with nature. They are not its exploiters but
its allies, and they survive and reproduce only
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
by knowing how to come to terms with the
other powers that animate it. There is no super¬
natural world separated from nature. Religion
is not independent of a given setting or a given
Earth or heaven, any more than it is of a given
society: it is closely linked to them. Proselyti-
zation and conversion are meaningless: a reli¬
gion is not something people belong to. Thus
there is no place for intolerance.
ART AS THE MYSTIFICATION
OF THE SENSES
In the field of art, artists drawing inspiration
from a civilization born of Christianity and
Graeco-Roman culture seek to define the out¬
lines of their subject in order to take it and pos-
Kaolin-palnted wooden
mask of the Fang people,
Gabon.
sess it, use it and subjugate it. They do so in
order to demystify the subject, to ensure that it
is dissociated from themselves and is no more
than what they see. Black African artists take
the opposite approach. They take the subject
from within and make it implode, in order to
express its complexity. They strive to erase or
blur its outlines in order to heighten its mys¬
tery. Whilst European artists aim to please,
African artists aim to frighten, to make you
doubt the evidence of your senses, to make you
believe that what you are seeing has other
dimensions, meanings and languages which are
beyond you.
In the field of law, a European is an indivi¬
dual. Europeans are solely responsible for what
they do: they act and the consequences of their
actions do not jeopardize or bring shame on
their community. They can do what they like:
create, innovate and change, or alternatively
blaspheme, lie, contradict themselves, be unjust
and destructive, without any aftermath or
punishment here below. The victims of their
actions and. turpitudes carry within themselves
no immanent powers to constrain their ways of
thinking and behaving. Black Africans, wher¬
ever they are and whatever they do, never
forget that they belong to a community which
is held to account for their every action. Res¬
ponsibility is collective. There is an immanent
power which can avenge the victims of injustice
and untruths. Things destroyed needlessly and
for no reason react. Black Africans grow up in
a world marked out with signs to be inter¬
preted and powers to come to terms with.
The basic cultural features of European civi¬
lization have turned out to be much more
efficient and much more favourable to man's
social, technological and economic develop¬
ment than those of black African culture. They
made Europe the hub of the universe and
master of the world, and enabled it to dominate
the black African peoples, directly or indi¬
rectly, for 600 years. This domination has taken
various forms. At every stage European culture
has managed to secrete an ideology, a utopia, a
doctrine or a mirage sufficiently uplifting and
motivating to persuade Europeans to launch
out on the adventure of conquest without
second thoughts. The efficacy of a culture may
also be gauged by this ability to turn out new
myths and doctrines.
The colonial utopia, or the quest
for Paradise Lost
Let us consider the stages in the history of
Europe's domination of Africa and the Afri¬
cans. European civilization has produced
various ideologies, utopias and doctrines to
motivate the adventurers who set out in search
of the point "where the Sun falls into the sea".
The Judaeo-Christian religion describes this 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Allegory of Peace
(1929-1930),
a fresco by the French artist
Ducos de la Haille.
It is now in the Museum
of African and Oceanian Arts
in Paris.
34
Ahmadou Kourouma, a
writer from Côte d'Ivoire,
currently lives in Togo. His
novels, Les soleils des
independences (1970) and
Monnè, outrages et défis
(1990), have won several
prizes.
lost Paradise, which only the chosen will attain
after the Last Judgement. Europeans have
always dreamed of such a Paradise, and when
in the Middle Ages they found themselves tor¬
mented by hunger they hoped to find it else¬
where, in distant lands. This was the colonial
utopia: "Somewhere where life is deliciously
warm, easy and sparkling, where all Nature's
generous juices set out to produce good things,
so easily come by" (Maurice Lencellé).
The quest for this idyllic land took Euro¬
pean seafarers to the coasts of Africa in the
mid-fifteenth century, and the Africans wel¬
comed them as spirits from the sea. The Euro¬
peans traded with the black Africans on terms
greatly to their advantage: gold and silver in
exchange for shoddy baubles. They continued
for a century and a half, with ever-renewed
enthusiasm and obstinacy, to explore the coasts
of Africa. Their religion turned trade into a spi¬
ritual mission: they were the soldiers of Christ,
spreading the good word among the savages.
Europe next discovered America, and mas¬
sacred the Indians there. Then shortage of man¬
power for the planting of sugar-cane and coffee
led them to institutionalize the slave trade. The
Renaissance, one of the most brilliant periods
in human history, coexisted with slavery. Here
again, European religion found the myths
needed to salve people's consciences: negroes
had no souls, and were descended from Cain.
Hence they could be tortured or killed with a
clear conscience.
We must of course pay tribute to the aboli¬
tionists who, Bible in hand, fought coura¬
geously against slavery and denounced the
imposture of its advocates. Towards the middle
of the seventeenth century they were joined in
their struggle by the churches and by intellec¬
tuals and governments. On every sea and in
every port slavers were pursued and slaves set
free. This struggle was carried through in the
name of humanism as well as of Christian
morality, but the moment slave labour turned
out to be less profitable than hired labour,
things changed. Immediately after the abolition
of slavery, European civilization launched out
into colonization.
A dialogue
OPEN TO ALL
People tend to mention only the drawbacks of
colonialism, but it must be said that it also had
its advantages, and not only for the colonists. It
contributed to the advent of the Industrial
Revolution; it opened up many lands to social
and economic progress, and made possible the
creation of the frontierless world that is at last
taking shape. The questions we need to ask
ourselves are the following: did Africa not pay
too high a price to be thus opened up? Without
the colonial powers, would Africa, left to itself,
not have found the way to economic and social
development and receptiveness to the world by
itself?
The universal civilization that is taking
shape will be a civilization that has incorpo¬
rated all cultures, with none barred. The West,
which is the master of the world by virtue of
its weapons, its economic power, its means of
communication and its spirit of enterprise, has
the duty to enter into genuine dialogue
with other civilizations in order to understand
others and accept them along with their
differences.
Africa for its part must realize that a man at
the bottom of a well cannot be pulled up unless
he makes the effort to grasp the rope that is
lowered to him. The failure of Africa is perhaps
due to cultural reasons. Africa and only Africa
must recognize this and reform itself. Europe
can go along too, but Africa must make the
journey by itself. C
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO COURIER JULY/ AUGUST 1992
EDITORIAL
The roadfromRio
byAlcino Da Costa
Attended by more than a hundred heads ofState and
government, with over 170 countries represented and
with a total of 40,000 participants, including 14,000
representatives ofNon-Governmental Organizations
(NGOs), under the eyes ofsome 10,000 accreditedjournalists,
Rio 92 has been acclaimed as the biggest world conference ever
held.
But looking beyond these impressivefigures, what did this
mega-summit achieve? The list includes adoption ofthe Rio
Declaration, ofAgenda 21 and ofa resolution on the conser¬
vation offorests and the signing by a majority ofthe partici¬
pating countries of international conventions on climate
and on biodiversity.
In some quarters, however, it wasfelt thatall these laudable
declarations ofprinciple might well remain mere words.
Disappointment was expressed about the lack ofprecise,
enforceable measuresfor the control ofcarbon dioxide emis¬
sions and the absence of any binding financial provisions
for the implementation ofAgenda 21, the action plan for
litorial
36 World
38 Dossier
Antarctica,
continent of science
and peace?
by France Bequette
40 Interview
with
Francesco di Castri
42 Ecology
A worldwide synergy
byRenéLefort
43 Biodiversity
Of cockroaches
and roses
44 Climate
The return of El Niño
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
y protection ofthe environment coupled with
sustainable development. Many were
alarmed by the absence ofany reference to
that important source of pollution, the
armaments industry.
Nevertheless, Rio 92 succeeded in obtain¬
ing unequivocal, worldwide recognition of
one incontrovertiblefact there is only one
Earth, itbelongs to both the rich and thepoor
and its protection is the responsibility ofall.
The Conference had the additional merit of
reinforcing awareness that all nations are
interdependentand that no individual coun¬
try could hope to escape the ecological catas¬
trophe towards which progressive degrada¬
tion of the environment, due both to
* consistent over-consumption in the North
andgrowingpoverty in the South, is leading.
There was general agreement that the dis¬
equilibrium caused by the unequal dis¬
tribution ofthe riches ofthe world had to be
corrected by a decisive actofsolidarity. The
fight against poverty has become an ecolo¬
gical imperative. This is what underlies the
concept ofsustainable development, the
multiple aspects ofwhich layat the heart of
the debates initiated by the NGOs within
theframework oftheir "Global Forum".
The extraordinary vitality of the Non-
Governmental Organizations was one of
the revelations ofRio 92. Present in force,
dynamic, even aggressive at times, and with
the confidence that comesfrom their wide
geographical representativity, they demon¬
strated their ability to analyse, to look ahead,
to mobilize, to animate and to take action.
The NGOs made a vital contribution to the
discussion on development and the envi¬
ronment. Strong in the support they enjoy in
society at large, the NGOs wield real power
and their voice will be increasingly heard in
thefield ofinternational negotiations.
Rio 92 has triggered a new dynamic. In
the words ofthe United Nations Secretary-
General, the time has comefor "a new moral
and political contract with nature". Collec¬
tively and individually we must undertake
to change our way oflife, to better our man-
gement ofthe Earth's resources and to seek
a form ofdevelopment that incorporates
the cultural dimension. Only thus will we be
able to bequeath to future generations a
world in which it willbegood to be alive.
ALCINO DA COSTA, Senegalese journalist,
is an information officer with Unesco's Office of
Public Information. He wasformerly director of
the weeklyAfrique Nouvelle.
World
KH
The great barrier reef of Belize,
the world's second largest after that
off the coast ofAustralia, has found
a guardian angel. A jury meeting at
Unesco Headquarters in March
awarded the first International
Marine Environment Prize set up
by the World Confederation of
UnderwaterActivities to Coral Cay
Conservation (CCC), a UK civic
group that has been working since
1986 with the Belize Government
on managing the country's coastal
areas and largest marine reserve.
In 1991, more than 300 volunteers
engaged in diving expeditions and
helped in computerizing all kinds of
data of value to the programme.
CCC has also provided Belize natio¬
nals with 24 fellowships a year, in a
bid to encourage the population to
look after its natural heritage.
A WAY WITH WASTE
Véronique Gnanih is undoubted¬
ly the prettiest refuse collector in
West Africa. She lives in Tohoue, not
far from Porto Novo, the historical
capital of Benin, where, draped in a
green dress with an embroidered
neckline, she takes pride in showing
people round the domestic refuse
sorting and reprocessingplant which
she set up in February 1989 with the
assistance ofEmmaus International
and the United Nations Develop¬
ment Programme (UNDP). With
diplomas in rural development and
community organization, Véronique
had the idea of doing something
about a waste tip the height ofa two-
storey building, which had been an
eyesore in the town ever since colo
nial times. She recruited a number of
jobless youngpeople, who are paid a
good wage and are given a meal and
free medical care. She has also
bought a tractor and trailer. Organic
waste is dumped in a heap and is
watered until it has completely
decomposed. The resulting compost
is then sold or spread inVéronique's
organic vegetable garden. Glass
bottles and metal scrap are also sold.
Plastic objects are stockpiled until a
use can be found for them, as are the
shells ofacatines, a type oflarge snail
which Véronique rears. This is a
prime example ofa small-scale pro¬
ject that is working perfecdy, thanks
to a renewable energy source in the
person ofVéronique herself.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
At a meeting of CITES, the
Convention on International Trade
in Endangered Species of Wild
Fauna and Flora, held in Kyoto
(Japan) in March, Mostafa Kamal
Tolba, the Egyptian-born biologist
who has been head of the United
Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP) for the past sixteen years,
said that CITES was itself endan¬
gered by North-South divergences.
Zimbabwe, Namibia, Botswana and
Malawi are demanding the resump¬
tion of trade in ivory, which has
been banned since the Lausanne
Conference in 1989. At that time
the international community had
voiced concern about the threat¬
ened disappearance of the African
elephant. By cutting off the supply
at source, it thought it could, by the
same stroke, do awaywith demand.
Yet poaching did not stop, and the
profit that states could have de¬
rived from the sale ofelephant tusks
disappeared. "Powerful groups,
chiefly in the rich, industrialized
countries, consider that the out¬
lawing of trade in elephant products
is the answer," Mr. Tolba stated,
before adding that "There are also
thousands of millions of people
whose voices will not be heard, who
use a minute part of the planet's
resources and who receive a pathe¬
tic part of its revenues. . . . These
people cannot be refused the right
to use their natural heritage."
Prompted by an idea that came to a solitary yachts¬
man appalled by the sorry state of the high seas, Aus¬
tralia has instituted a clean-up day for beaches, rivers
and parks. On the 1991 Cleaning Up Australia Day,
more than 350,000 volunteers collected some 30,000
tons ofwaste from 4,452 locations, twice the amount of
the previous year. In all, a quarter of a million garbage
bags were distributed to military personnel, local auth¬
orities and associations ofvolunteers. All kinds ofrubbish
were collected, including bottles, cartons, syringes,
wrecked cars, rubble, industrial waste, animal car¬
casses and household refuse. Plastic, glass, paper and
aluminium were recycled. Although Australia is the
only country to have officially designated a special
clean-up Day, volunteers on the Hawaiian island of
Oahu, where Honolulu is located, gather every Saturday
morning to clean up villages and remove wrecked
vehicles from the roadsides.
Since 1 December 1989, trucks have been prohibited
from travelling by night on some ofAustria's highways,
including the main route across the Alps through the
Brenner Pass and the valley of the River Inn. This high¬
wayaccounts for 75% ofthe road traffic transiting through
the country.People living along the road had to put up
with noise pollution ofmore than 67 decibels, two deci¬
bels above the officially acceptable limit. Consequendy,
trucks weighing more than 7.5 tons have been banned
from using the road between 10 o'clock at night and 5 in
the morning, except for vehicles carrying perishable
produce and livestock. Since the prohibition went into
effect, traffic on the road has dropped by two-thirds,
while unaccompanied rail-road transport has risen by
1 1 5% and accompanied transport by 250%. The "piggy¬
back" system is an excellent substitute for road traffic, in
that it is better suited to rapid trade flows and is less
expensive over distances ofmore than 500 kilometres.
Of all the republics to emerge from the former Soviet
Union, only Russia and Turkmenistan are energy export¬
ers. Russia has abundant resources and is widely ack¬
nowledged to have 20% ofthe world's oil and 40% of its
natural gas reserves. However, the current crisis in the
country is affecting the production and transportation
of this wealth, especially since the oil and gas fields
are in isolated regions to which access is difficult.
Drilling equipment is old and poorly serviced, and the
wells have been poorly managed. Vladimir Kozlov, the
head of the International Fuels and Energy Associa¬
tion, a specialized non-governmental organization,
said at a meeting in Paris last February that he was
pinning his hopes on the development of natural gas,
which could be easily transported by pipeline.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Dossier
nu m
38
by France Bequette
continent in its own right,
covering an area larger than
Europe, Antarctica has long
been shrouded in mystery.
From the early years of the
last century, national flags
gradually came to be planted
-all over it, although it has
never been the scene of armed
conflict. Since then, eighteen States
have laid claim to varying portions
of the continent, which in 1940 was
divided into cake-like slices extend¬
ing outwards from the South Pole to
the surrounding ocean. However it
was not until 1958, thanks to the
combined efforts of explorers, air¬
craft and satellites, that Antarctica
was completely mapped.
This enormous landmass is cov¬
ered by an ice cap which is estimated
to be 2,500 metres thick and
accounts for roughly one-third of
the planet's freshwater reserves. In
1983, at the Soviet Vostok base in
the interior, a temperature of -89.6°C
was recorded, setting an all-time low
in an environment where cold is
constant, with temperatures ranging
from -36°C in January to -72°C in
July. The most extreme conditions
are associated with blizzards, fierce
'A few months from now we shall know
whether the international community has
the good sense to respecta continent where
the dawn is more beautiful than any¬
where else in the worldbut one which
already has a hole in its ozone layer'.
bitingwinds accompanied by snow¬
falls, which reduce visibility to zero
and make the cold unbearable.
Yet Antarctica has exerted great
fascination over people ever since
the American navigator John Davis
first set foot on the continent in
1821. Scientists and explorers of
extreme conditions followed in each
other's footsteps. International
Geophysical Year in 1957-1958 pro¬
vided the occasion for setting up
the first permanent scientific sta¬
tions. Some 2,000 people now occu¬
py all the year round forty-two bases
located on the continent or on the
offshore islands, while twenty-six
other bases are only occupied
during the southern summer.
Research being carried out covers
such broad subject areas as glacio-
logy, meteorology, the Earth's
magnetic field and the upper
atmosphere, but even so the conti¬
nent has by no means yielded all
its secrets.
About 140 million years ago, the
east of Antarctica was still at the
heart of an enormous continent,
known as Gondwanaland, formed
ofwhat are nowAfrica, South Amer¬
ica, India, Australia and New Zea¬
land. Gondwanaland had a tem¬
perate climate and was covered
with forests and inhabited by rep¬
tiles and amphibians, vestiges of
which dating back 200 million years
have been found. In 1982, American
scientists unearthed the fossil
remains ofa small, 40-million-year-
old marsupial that was an ancestor
of those now found in Australia,
thus showing that these territories
once formed a single landmass.
However, through the action of
what is known as plate tectonics,
rift faults started to appear and
these were gradually widened by
movements of the Earth's crust.
Antarctica came to be isolated from
the rest in the ice-bound ocean of
the South Pole, where its tempera¬
ture fell and its forests gave way to
everlasting snow. It is still not
known exactly when the different
parts of Gondwanaland started to
break away or what the shape of the
continents was at that time.
HEAT UNDER THE ICE
In the south of Antarctica, Mt.
Erebus, on Ross Island, is the conti¬
nent's only still active volcano. Not
far from Erebus, there are "oases",
or dry valleys, which have been
given that name because there has
not been a single drop ofprecipita¬
tion for at least two million years.
The ice has retreated and the snow
is melted by the the heat of the Sun's
rays. These rock-strewn deserts
have been used by the US National
Aeronatics and Space Administra¬
tion (NASA) to test equipment for
the exploration ofMars, whose sur¬
face features are similar. Lake
Vanda, which is situated in the
middle ofone of these desert areas
and which, in the everlasting cold, is
almost always covered by a thick
layer of ice, displays one peculiar
feature, in that the temperature of
the water at its lower levels may rise
to as high as 25°C. This is because
the ice crystals act like optical fibres
and transmit the sunlight to the bot¬
tom of the lake, heating up the
motionless water.
What we know aboutAntarctica is
based on information gathered by
some fifty expeditions that have
explored the continent in the last
150 years or so. The actual name
Antarctica was coined by the Greek
philosopherAristotle, who held the
view that, in order to offset the
known mass of the northern hemi¬
sphere under the constellation of
the Great Bear (Arktos), there was
bound to be an equivalent mass in
the south, whence Antarktikos.
When one of Magellan's ships was
returning from its circumnaviga¬
tion of the world, demonstrating
that the Earth was round, its crew
thought that they had caught sight
of an unknown land, which was
thereafter shown on maps as terra
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
australis incognita, although its
contours were a matter of conjec¬
ture. Explorers like Kerguelen, Cook,
Weddell, Dumont d'Urville, Ross,
Charcot, Amundsen, Scott, Shack-
leton and Byrd endured untold suf¬
fering, and sometimes even went
ficient quantity for their exploitation
to be a profitable proposition.
Ever since the beginning ofthe cen¬
tury, the extreme fragility of the
Antarctic environment has given rise
to a series of Commissions, Treaties
and Conventions, such as the
for the development of mineral
resources to be prohibited and for a
Conference to be held in fifty years'
time, with a view to making, ifneces¬
sary, changes to the status ofthe conti¬
nent or even abolishing that special
status. A few months from now, we
Left, a huge tabular iceberg
off the Coast of Adélie Land,
Antarctica.
Below, acting like optical fibres,
surface ice crystals transmit
sunlight to the bottom of Lake
Vanda.
to their deaths, in order to find out
more about the continent.
A PRECIOUS NATURAL
RESERVE
Plant life on the continent consists
only of lichens, mosses and a few
flowering species, and terrestrial ani¬
mal life oftiny invertebrates, but there
is an intensive marine life. Plankton
and krill provide food for 120 fish spe¬
cies, which are particularlyabundant
during the summermonths, and also
for seals and whales. Nineteen sea-
bird species live in harmony with
seven species offlightless swimming
birds belonging to the large penguin
family. However, the source of
wealth posing the greatest threat to
the ecology ofAntarctica lies beneath
the surface ofland and sea. Although
less than 1 per cent of the continent
has been prospected, deposits ofcoal,
iron, copper, gold, titanium, uranium
and cobalt have been identified. Off¬
shore drilling has also revealed the
existence ofhydrocarbons. However,
it is impossible to state with certainty
that these minerals are present in suf-
Washington Treaty, the Wellington
Convention and the Madrid Proto¬
col. Their purpose is to protect plant
life, as well as whales, which are threat¬
enedwith extinction, and seals, which
are hunted for their fur. But they are
also designed to prevent overfishing.
From the environmental standpoint,
the scientific bases are not entirely
free from blame. All kinds ofwaste, of
varying toxicity, are beginning to pile
up. The firstAmerican nuclear power
station installed on the continent
developed faults andhad to be trans¬
ported back to the United States,
along with tons of contaminated
earth. Aircraft landing strips disturb
the habitat of the Antarctic fauna.
Tourism, the "smokeless industry",
is increasing and is attracting 9,000
visitors a year.
In 1991, the Madrid Protocol, which
has already been signed by thirty-
nine States, was left open for signature
for a period ofone year. The Protocol
forms an additional instrument to the
Washington Treaty. Its originality lies
in the fact that it includes a morato¬
rium providing forAntarctica to be a
natural reserve ofscience and peace,
shall knowwhether the international
communityhas the good sense to res¬
pect a continent where the dawn is
more beautiful than anywhere else
in the world but one which already
has a hole in its ozone layer.
; *S
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American journalist specializing in
environmental questions. Since 1985 she has been associated with the
WANAD-UNESCO training programmeforAfrican news agency
journalists. She has played a leadingpart in the preparation ofthis
Greenwatch section.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Interview
The second instalment ofan interview
with the co-ordinator ofUnesco's
environment programmes
Villagers gather
round a solar
powered
television
receiver in the
Tuareg village of
Air (Niger), in a
part of the Sahara
that is one of the
largest protected
areas in Africa.
40
The world'sforests have been called
"the lungs of the planet". Is this an
accurate metaphor?
The metaphor arises from the
continuous exchange of carbon
dioxide and oxygen that takes place
between living organisms and the
environment. Living plants take up
carbon dioxide and give offoxygen.
When they are dead, the reverse
occurs and they take up oxygen and
give off carbon dioxide. If all the
forests were wiped off the face of
the Earth, the amount of oxygen in
the atmosphere would diminish and
the amount ofcarbon dioxide would
increase. However, the change in
the amount of oxygen in the atmo¬
sphere that this would entail would
be only temporary furthermore, the
concentration of oxygen in the
atmosphere is such that, as far as
humans are concerned, the change
would be imperceptible.
In fact, the prime role played by
forests, in particular the tropical
forests, in the atmospheric balance
and the Earth's climate relates to
the part they play in the water cycle.
Deforestation has serious reper¬
cussions on the process of evapo¬
ration and the rainfall régime. When
forests are destroyed, the water
balance of the atmosphere is upset
and this has a direct influence on
the climate. Massive deforestation
would also entail a serious reduc
tion in biodiversity, a subject that I
shall not go into more deeply here.
How can the poorest countries
achieve a level ofgrowth and welfare
compatible with the protection ofthe
environment?
That problem is more than just
circumstantial, which is to say it
cannot simply be solved, in a rather
paternalistic way, by the rich coun¬
tries providing money. The roots of
the problem are structural. The
developing countries need and
Unesco plays a central role here to
acquire know-how: without educa¬
tion, awareness, management train¬
ing, they will not be able to resolve
their difficulties. Meanwhile, as a
result of the prevailing monetary
system and the market economy,
the terms oftrade are against them
and give them no room for
manoeuvre.
To escape from this impasse, it
will be necessary to change the rules
of the international marketplace.
Otherwise developing countries will
be forced to destroy forests, impov¬
erish the soil, and only cultivate
cocoa, coffee or other export crops,
thereby aggravating the degradation
of their environment. The relation¬
ship between the North and the
South should be modified struc¬
turally. Instead of talking about aid
for the Third World, we should be
talking about justice and equity for it.
Energy consumption per head of
population is often used as an index
ofdevelopment. Yet theproduction of
energy under present conditions is a
major cause ofpollution. Isn't there
a contradiction between economic
growth and the protection of the
environment?
Yes, there is a conflict between
development as it is presently
understood and the environment.
The objective of the Rio conference
was to prove that environment and
development are two sides of the
same problem. As long as we refuse
to admit that the two issues are
complementary, we will continue
to experience setbacks in both
domains. Despite growing aware¬
ness among governments and
peoples, in spite of the efforts made
and programmes set up here and
there, environmental policy over
the past twenty years has been an
almost total failure. As a result, we
have also lost out where develop¬
ment is concerned.
There is undeniably a link be¬
tween development and energy
consumption, but it is less direct
than it is often thought to be. Let's
take an example: the United States
consumes much more energy than
the European countries, but should
one conclude from that that it is
more developed than Germany? No.
The United States could maintain
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
the same level ofdevelopment while
using maybe 20 to 30 per cent less
energy. To sum up, considerable
energy savings can be made without
slowing down development. But a
minimum of energy is of course
necessary	
Will the so-called "clean", renewable
energy sourcessolar energy, tidal
powerandso on one dayproduce suf¬
ficientlysatisfactory results to be wide¬
ly used? Whatare their realprospects ?
The priority for the time being
is to conserve and economize on
existing energy sources rather than
to produce new ones, however
necessary they may seem to be.
Both in the developed countries
and elsewhere, there is an urgent
need to reduce energy consump¬
tion without slowing down devel¬
opment two perfectly compatible
objectives. The new energy sources
are already producing results, but
on a limited scale providing heat¬
ing in villages, or working wells in
the desert but the main thing is
that they are notyet sufficiently pro¬
ductive. It is a fantasy to think they
could replace existing energy
sources in ten or even fifteen years.
It will certainly take much longer
than that. They still cost too much.
And a lot more progress will have to
be made on the scientific and tech¬
nical fronts before these new ener¬
gy sources replace the older ones
everywhere.
Protecting the environment is every¬
one's business. Don't you think that
Ministries ofEducation in every coun¬
try ofthe globe should be made aware
of this point, so that every child can
learn from a very early age how to
respond to the situation? What is being
done about this?
This is a very important point.
The role of education at both the
primary and the secondary level is
crucial. But there's more to it than
that. The people responsible for
development should also be train¬
ed in ecology; they must be fully
aware of the repercussions of the
economic model they choose. We
must make ecology seem a force for
action, a broadly-based movement.
People who have become aware of
the problems of the environment
can put pressure on their govern¬
ments which tend to act in the
short term, within the narrow time¬
frame of their mandates to take a
longer-term view of things. Well-
informed people could bring about
policy changes byusing their power
as voters. Direct action of this kind
must rest on a solid scientific foun¬
dation if it is to be effective, not just
on emotional reactions as is still too
often the case.
I repeat, whether in the Third
World or in the developed coun¬
tries, the problem of the environ¬
ment will remain unsolved as long
as the norms of development
remain unchanged. The two crises
cannot be separated, which is why
the Rio conference has marked a
turning-point: to think one can
resolve them independentiy is Uto¬
pian. The only chance for a solu¬
tion rests in a joint approach. The
problem of the environment is in
realityjust a consequence, an aspect
of the type ofdevelopment we know
today. No country is unaffected, for
the world economy is completely
interdependent and the environ¬
ment ignores frontiers. No country
is so great or powerful that it can
afford to say, "No, I don't want to
change, and what happens else¬
where doesn't matter tome. ..", for
the scale of these problems is global,
and none of them can be resolved
without a sense of global solidarity.
To be continued m
Rain Forest Wall
(1967), sculpture
in black wood and
mirrors by US
sculptor Louise
Nevelson.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Ecology
imm mÈ,
by René Lefort
Monitoring
pollution in the
Baltic Sea,
offshore from
Kiel, Germany.
"We're not doing any research ourselves, but we help
with research atan international level. We don't have any
laboratories ofour own, yet we work with the best labs in
the world. We don't teach, but thanks to us knowledgegets
awmd- ndras Szollosi-Nagy, head
of Unesco's International
Hydrological Programme
(IHP), wants to avoid any
misunderstanding: even
though he is trained as a
scientist and his work deals
.with science, he is first and
foremost a "scientific manager". A
term that applies as well to his col¬
leagues working for the other three
international scientific programmes
at Unesco: the Man and the Bio¬
sphere Programme (MAB), the
Intergovernmental Océanographie
Commission (IOC), and the Inter¬
national Geological Correlation Pro¬
gramme (IGCP).
"We achieve a worldwide synergy
of local research," says MAB Direc¬
tor Berndt Von Droste. Synergy is
the key word in the role played by
Unesco with these programmes.
They offer (but do not impose) pro¬
cedures on which scientists in dis¬
tant labs can rely to work effectively
as a global team. These procedures
thus help researchers in prioritizing
their activities on a worldwide scale,
in dividing up tasks according to
each team's strengths, and in co¬
ordinating the projects, making
information and results available
to all. In diplomatic jargon, this is
"international intellectual co-oper¬
ation." For Szollosi-Nagy, it is more
simply a way to "put together all
the pieces of the puzzle and get a
global picture."
Going global
With the worldwide impact of
environmental problems such as
pollution, the greenhouse effect,
climatic changes, and urbanization,
the concept ofworking together on
a global scale seems obvious today.
At the time when Unesco's interna¬
tional programmes got under way,
however, this idea had little weight.
In particular, the South was then
kept out of major developments,
most of the research capacity being
concentrated in the North. One of
the great merits of Unesco's pro¬
grammes lies in links built between
North and South and, little bylittle,
between South and South by
adding Third World scientists to
their endeavours, by helping in the
development of science in the
South, and especially by making
significant efforts in local training.
Innovating in new fields went
along with this extended geo¬
graphical reach: MAB, the IOC, the
IHP and the IGCP have been pio¬
neers in the study of tropical eco¬
systems, which were previously
little known even though three-
quarters of the world's population
live in the tropics. Similar ground¬
breaking studies are carried out in
desert areas, and on the relation¬
ships between the environment and
cities swollen by rural migration.
Indeed, Unesco's four major scien¬
tific programmes do not conduct
research for its own sake, be it on
the biosphere (MAB), the ocean
(IOC), fresh waters (IHP), or the
Earth's crust (IGCP), but rather with
the aim of improving humanity's
condition. Their interdisciplinary
42
character is emphasized further by
Unesco's mandate, integrating
science, education and culture.
Thus Unesco has played a leading
role in putting the concept of sus¬
tainable development forward in
international forums. -
The programmes have proved
successful. For example, more than
four out of five laboratories
throughout the world dealing with
issues concerning water co-opera¬
te with IHP, and the ratio is one out
of two in cases involving MAB or
IOC. But should this success be
taken for granted? Revolutionary as
such programmes may have been
twenty or thirty years ago, might
they not become outdated, even
superfluous?
Their budgets are extremely
modest compared to what is at
stake: Unesco provides them with
about $5 million a year, to which is
added about $25 million in volun¬
tary contributions from other orga¬
nizations and Member States. Yet
their worldwide scope is an asset
that no other network holds.
For the programme Directors, as
with the International Council
of Scientific Unions the largest
non-governmental body in this
field their intergovernmental char¬
acter is their "main strength", an
irreplaceable feature that "connects
the scientific engine with the poli¬
tical machine." But intergovern¬
mental means heavy bureaucracy,
making it at the same time an
obvious weakness.
The fact that many others have
now followed the lead set by
Unesco's programmes is a welcome
development. Faced with today's
environmental crisis, should inter¬
national networks not forge new eco¬
logical alliances, each focussing on
what they can do best, and
thereby ensuring greater efficiency?
Are interdisciplinary methods suf¬
ficiently established and validated
within and among these pro¬
grammes, or adequately tied to social
sciences, culture, and education?
Now that the Earth Summit is over,
the question is how these pro¬
grammes should evolve to embrace
the "revolution" needed in all our
institutions to confront the deg¬
radation ofour environment.
RENÉ LEFORT is Editor-in-chiefof the
monthly magazine Unesco Sources.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Biodiversity
-
oF fil[|IMlu
1 uUuJ[VI\m\)[\iL
iiDl1IS ES
LL living species whales
and cockroaches, roses and
the AIDS virus, pandas and
people make up the bio¬
logical diversity of the
Earth. All biological entities
and systems are intercon-
-nected and interdepen¬
dent, from a DNA molecule to an
ecosystem to the biosphere. Bio¬
diversity is important because it
provides basic services: it protects
and maintains soils, regulates the
climate and ensures photosynthe¬
sis, thus furnishing the oxygen we
breathe. It provides the basic mate¬
rial for our food, clothing, medi¬
cines and housing.
It is time to think about the conse¬
quences of the current changes in
biodiversity. Although there have
always been extinctions (such as
the disappearance of dinosaurs),
never have there been so many
losses of species and alteration of
natural areas as today. In order to
feed, lodge and transport the
world's millions, ecosystems are
being cut up, fragmented and com¬
pletely modified. Additions of ferti¬
lizers, domestic and industrial
wastes, or simply salty water are
degrading and poisoning natural
systems with a resulting die-off of
the animals, plants and fishes that
depend on them.
The resulting destruction affects
not only the area directly concern¬
ed: wind and river and sea currents
can transmit pollutants far from the
source ofcontamination. Thus pen¬
guins in the Antarctic have DDT
residues in their tissues. There are
cases of malaria in people living
near airports far away from infected
countries.
Intensive agriculture has brought
about a deliberate loss of biodiver¬
sity, which is a mixed blessing.
Farmers traditionally used many
varieties ofcrops and domesticated
animals to accommodate the local
differences in soil and climate.
Today, of 145 local sorts ofbeast in
the Mediterranean basin, all but
thirty are in serious danger of
extinction. In order to achieve maxi¬
mum yields, farmers are using only
a limited number of varieties of
cattle and crops, the latter very often
needing heavy inputs of fertilizers
and pesticides.
Our dwindling
biological capital
Only now are we beginning to
assess the threat that the loss ofbio¬
diversity can have on environmen¬
tal development. But such an assess¬
ment is difficult because we know
very little about biodiversity. While
some 1.4 million species have been
identified and described by scien¬
tists, there is a great deal of dis¬
agreement on the total number of
species on Earth. Estimates vary
from 5 to some 80 million, taking
account ofall the insects, microbes
and marine life-forms to be dis¬
covered. With so few data, the losses
in terms ofgenes, species and ecosys¬
tems are not easy to calculate. Some
biologists have hazarded a guess that
perhaps one-quarter of the world's
total biodiversity is at serious risk of
extinction over the next twenty to
thirty years. This figure may be
contested, but it does call attention to
the urgency of the matter.
Scientists are only now question¬
ing why there is so much biodiver¬
sity and how it is generated and lost.
They are also asking whether bio¬
diversity has a role in the function¬
ing of ecosystems. It has been
shown that there is some redun¬
dancy in ecosystems, for example,
different species performing the
same ecological tasks such as eating
the same fruits and occupying the
same space. This implies that we
may be able to do without some
species. But which ones? And is this
morally acceptable to society?
In the face of so many unknowns,
different countries have different
ideas and priorities. In order to
conserve a maximum of biodiver¬
sity, efforts need to be made to pro¬
tect natural areas as reserves, to set
up repositories in zoos, botanical
gardens and gene banks. Care
should be given to preserve biodi¬
versity in all types of natural sys¬
tems, from deserts and grasslands
to estuaries and coral reefs. However,
the most effective and difficult
measure of all is to use natural
resources sustainably, at least above
the threshold at which the processes
of evolution, of speciation and
adaptation can continue.
A mountain
gorilla. The small
surviving groups
of this
endangered
species are
mainly found in
Rwanda.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Biodiversity Climate
44
ThirdWorld countries, usually rich
in biodiversity, will and must exploit
their natural resources for their de¬
velopment. The industrialized coun¬
tries feel that more should be done to
protect biodiversity and save the last
wild natural areas of the planet.
Some countries thus decided to
negotiate an international conven¬
tion on biodiversity.
Unesco has an important role to
play in this effort. First, as the Uni¬
ted Nations scientific organization,
it will promote research and inven¬
tories to improve our understand¬
ing of the world's flora and fauna
and the role of biodiversity in the
functioning of ecosystems.
The 'Diversitas' project
Together with the non-govern¬
mental scientific community,
through the International Union of
Biological Sciences (IUBS) and the
Scientific Committee on Problems
ofthe Environment (SCOPE), a new
initiative called "Diversitas" has
been launched to mobilize a major
global co-ordinated effort in this
field. Unesco will also tackle the
educational aspects, sensitizing the
public and policy-makers to the
implications of losses of biodiver¬
sity, based on the results of Diver¬
sitas. Training activities, for example
ofmuch-needed taxonomists (spe¬
cialists in the classification ofplants
and animals) in developing coun¬
tries, will also be conducted.
One of Unesco's unique contri¬
butions is the international bio¬
sphere reserve networkunderwhich
representative ecosystems are pro¬
tected in 300 sites in 75 countries
around the world. The biosphere
reserve system makes it possible to
find solutions to land management
problems and to share the informa¬
tion through a co-operative net¬
work. They are field laboratories for
finding out more about biodiversi¬
ty and how it can be both protec¬
ted and sustainably used for the
benefit ofhumankind in all parts of
the world.
Extractedfrom an article byJane Robertson, a
Unesco specialist, and Nancy Mathews, a
journalist specializing in environmental
questions. Umsco-Office ofPublic Information.
ROUGHTS and floods in
1987 in India, Africa, Aus¬
tralia, Indonesia, North
and SouthAmerica and the
Philippines were caused by
the El Niño effect. El Niño
is the name given to the
recurring tropical pheno¬
menon that brings a warm current
to the west coast of South America
every three to five years. It begins to
appear around Christmas-time, as
befits its name (EI Niño means the
Christ-child in Spanish).
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
During El Niño periods the warm
ocean surface temperatures, nor¬
mally found only in the western
Pacific, move east toward the cen¬
tral Pacific and the western coast
of South America. The results are
unusual weather and short-term
climatic changes. There have been
crop losses and famines as well as
major changes in fisheries such as
severe reductions in the Peruvian
anchovy catches, and tropical crus¬
taceans have moved far north of
their normal habitats.
Oceans cover 70 per cent of the
Earth's surface, and contain 97 per
cent of the world's water. They have
long been understood to influence
weather patterns, including hurri¬
canes, typhoons and tropical
storms. Only recently, however, has
their very large influence on clima¬
tic variability and climatic change
become accepted. The interaction
between oceans, atmospheric acti¬
vity, weather and climate are be¬
coming better understood.
Oceans absorb and retain heat,
as well as carbon dioxide (which
could theoretically help to mitigate
the effects ofglobal warming). The
top two metres ofocean contain as
much heat as the atmosphere, but
the average ocean temperature
ranges from 2°C (its freezing tem¬
perature) to 30°C, in contrast to
mid-continent variations of up to
100 degrees of difference.
Changes in ocean temperatures
and currents and in salinity levels
can affect weather and climate,
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Climate
which in turn determine which
crops will (or will not) grow in a
given season and which fish will
be found (or not found) in a
given marine, coastal or estuarine
environment.
Raised sea water temperatures
already have affected coastal zones
in many regions. Changes in
nutrient levels and water tempera¬
ture have caused mass mortality of
corals; decreases in sediment inputs
lead to the retreat of mangroves.
While these incidents occur as a
result of locally or regionally im¬
posed burdens, they suggest what
might occur with global influences.
Although oceans might reduce the
effects of global climatic change,
they also could make matters worse;
increases in ocean surface water
temperature can cause a release of
carbon dioxide into the atmosphere.
Moreover, as oceans absorb carbon
dioxide their acidity increases, which
in turn lowers their ability to take
up further carbon dioxide.
If climatic change or other phe¬
nomena were to cause a rise in sea-
level ofbetween 20 centimetres and
a metre, a number of problems
might result. There are thousands of
populated islands at low altitude in
the world's oceans, and many major
cities are located in low-lying areas
ofcontinental coastlines; they could
suffer flooding or inundation. Glob¬
al sea levels have already risen in
some areas, by approximately 15
centimetres, over the past century.
Among the reasons given are land
movements and tectonic plate acti¬
vity, local océanographie and
meteorological conditions and
numerous human activities on land.
In some cases, however, land has
actually risen.
To improve human understanding
of the oceans requires the applica¬
tion ofmany disciplines and many
technologies. Satellite imaging is
identifying currents and tempera¬
ture gradients. The International
Mussel Watch being conducted
A coral formation
(Belize).
throughout the world by Unesco's
Intergovernmental Océanographie
Commission (IOC), the United
Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP) and the U.S. National
Oceanic and Atmospheric Admi¬
nistration, is gathering extremely
useful data. Mussels are, in effect, an
"indicator" species capable of
revealing everything from the level
of pesticides applied on upland
agricultural lands to the presence of
other toxins.
A new international effort has
begun to monitor, describe and
understand the physical and bio-
geochemical properties that deter¬
mine ocean circulation and the sea¬
sonal-to-decadal climatic changes
in the ocean and to provide the
extensive observations which will
be needed for any climatic predic¬
tions. Known as the Global Ocean
Observing System (GOOS), it is
jointly sponsored by IOC, the World
Meteorological Organization
(WMO), UNEP and the states
concerned.
In the past dozen years, intensive
scientific research jointly sponsored
by IOC, WMO, the International
Council ofScientific Unions (ICSU)
and the Scientific Committee on
Oceanic Research (SCOR) has great¬
ly increased the understanding ofEl
Niño. Known as the Study ofTropi¬
cal Oceans and Global Atmosphere
(TOGA), its observers- have begun
to piece together enough informa¬
tion to begin anticipating El Nino's
arrival and its expected effects.
El Niño is, of course, only one
phenomenon among many in the
highly complex and poorly under¬
stood system ofoceans, atmosphere,
weather and climate. To compre¬
hend potential global climatic
change, much more information
than now existswill be needed.
Extractedfrom an article by
Nancy Mathews, a journalistspecializingin
environmental questions.
UNESCO-Office ofPublielnformation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
EclS irape: an uphill road to freedom
by Antonin Liehm
Dialogue (1989),
wood and oxidized iron
sculpture by the Slovak
artist Juraj Melis.
Post-communist societies face
many pitfalls as they seek to
modernize themselves
LESS than three years have gone by since
the collapse of communism in central
Europe, and we are only beginning to
realize the extent of the fall-out and to come to
terms with the problems its heirs and by
extension all Europe will have to resolve.
Central Europe had been subjected to total¬
itarian régimes first nazi, then communist
for more than fifty years, leaving two genera¬
tions with no experience of any other system,
least of all democracy or a market economy,
which were not even a distant memory. Such
systems survived only as dreams, fleeting
images whose shape changed according to
whatever scraps of rhetoric or other informa¬
tion people had gleaned at random, mainly
from hearsay.
Like all dictatorships, the communist
régimes were profoundly conservative in their 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
structures and manner of operation. Despite
the resolutely forward-looking beginnings of
communism, its ethics and even its aesthetics
remained firmly rooted in the nineteenth cen¬
tury. In its turn, it provoked anti-communist
trends that also took their cue from the past,
whether in the form of rampant economic lib¬
eralism, a certain form of nationalism or an aes¬
thetic of rejection. So when exponents of these
trends came to power two years ago, they gra¬
dually transformed the anti-communist revolu¬
tion into a restoration of the ancien régime.
Only in Germany was there any kind of cor¬
rective counterweight.
A DISMAL LEGACY
We knew that the fall of communism would
reveal the depths of the ideological and political
Athletes
(1928-1930),
oil on canvas by the
Russian artist
Kazimir Malevich.
pit the communist movement had dug, in
flagrant contradiction with its own doctrines.
Nevertheless, many of us thought that the
vacuum would soon be filled, first by a return
to religion and then by a restoration of demo¬
cracy, tolerance and political ecumenism, at
least in those countries that had a democratic
tradition. It was clear, of course, that commu¬
nism had done nothing to solve the problems
of nationalities, which it had merely glossed
over or concealed. Even so, few of us foresaw
that the nationality issue would erupt as sud¬
denly as it did. In some countries, nation¬
alism with the backing of the churches filled
almost the entire ideological vacuum left by the
collapse of communism.
Half a century of totalitarianism had also
left other dismal legacies, among them the
myth of social equality, which was for the most
part achieved by a levelling downwards, and the
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Repairmen
(1960),
by the Azerbaijani artist
Tahir Salakhov.
illusion of full employment. The very idea of a
society made up of the rich, the poor and the
unemployed is a difficult one for most people
to accept. A sense of responsibility (except for
one's own destiny) and the spirit of individual
initiative have also both disappeared. The
middle class hardly exists except in a form
inherited from communism, namely a mass of
state employees and functionaries on the one
hand and a class of small or big-time specula¬
tors, crooks and parasites on the other. The
latter group is best placed to benefit from the
new situation. One interesting development is
the growing esteem in which the old titled nobi¬
lity is held, echoing the respect once enjoyed by
the party élite, the nomenklatura. One last
factor we have to bear in mind is the complete
absence of structures governing labour rela¬
tions, as well as the lack of trade unions and
employers' and business organizations.
A PRECARIOUS BALANCE
In politics, the organized successors of the
communist party, which, surprisingly, remain
relatively strong, have been boycotted by all
the other formations, thus upsetting the normal
democratic process of alternation in power.
Confronting them is a liberal right intent
on putting the clock back, flanked by a chauvin¬
istic and often racist extreme right wing. In
between lies a fragile centre-left and various
timid social democratic groupings that hardly
dare mention the words "social" or "left" for
fear of being tarred with the communist brush.
This virtual deadlock will continue until the
market economy and all that goes with it have
been restored, for these are indispensable to the
proper functioning of democratic politics.
In the meantime, there may be and in some
cases already have been political explosions
and recklessness that could have dangerous
consequences.
Economic reforms aimed at restoring earlier
market structures were of course already under
way well before the collapse of the old régimes.
In its death throes, the communist state sought
with a kind of desperate energy to find a way
out of the impasse in which it found itself by
creating a mixed system, inspired on the one
hand by the parallel economy (which was par¬
ticularly developed in Hungary) and on the
other by Polish experiments in associating the
unions with the running of the economy and
attracting massive foreign aid. In Czechoslo¬
vakia, because of the panic fear of liberalization
shown by the communist régime installed after
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
About Love
(1990),
oil on canvas by Alex
Belyakov, a young Moscow
artist. The work is inspired
by the Yin and the Yang, the
two opposing but
complementary principles of
Chinese philosophy on
whose interplay the universal
order is based.
50
Antonin Liehm, a Prague
journalist, left Czechoslovakia
in 1969 and took up
university teaching. In 1984
he founded Lettre
Internationale, a periodical
published in nine European
countries. His publications
include Trois générations:
Entretiens sur le phénomène
culturel tchécoslovaque
(1970), Socialisme à visage
humain (1974), Le passé
présent (1979) and Le
cinéma de l'Est (1979).
the 1968 invasion, the reform programme was
prepared almost surreptitiously. Its proponents
were a handful of reformist communists run¬
ning the Institute of Economic Planning and a
group centred on the Prime Minister, Vaclav
Klaus. The former were basically Keynesian in
their approach, seeking a "third way", a gradual
transformation of the economy based on large-
scale state participation. The second group,
drawing its inspiration uncompromisingly
from F.A. Hayek and Milton Friedman, aimed
at a restoration of the situation before commu¬
nism. They sought the dismantling of the exist-
' ing system, then a return to classic liberalism
via a more or less uncontrolled privatization, as
well as by opening up the economy almost
unconditionally to foreign capital. By and large
this latter view prevailed in the three main
countries of central Europe, Hungary, Poland
and Czechoslovakia.
In view of the fact that the European
Community is not in a position to open its
doors to the central European nations in the
immediate future, or to finance their transfor¬
mation in the meantime, decision-makers in
these countries are looking increasingly to the
United States as a last hope. The Americans are
fully aware of this situation, and they view
central Europe as a not unimportant area for
their long-term influence and a significant
factor in their policy towards the European
Community. This seems natural to the extent
that current economic doctrine in the United
States closely matches that of central Europe
another factor promoting the belief that central
Europe will long remain one of the corner¬
stones of European conservatism.
It remains to be seen whether such conser¬
vatism will speed up or slow down the process
known as the "return to the European fold".
Will the urge to return to an earlier status quo
move central Europe closer to or away from
Western Europe as it is today?
The American model
The same questions arise in the field of culture,
taken in its widest sense. In cultural terms, the
situation in central Europe is coming to
resemble American practice more than the
Western European norm, with the arts be¬
coming an object of speculation, a speedy route
to riches. Yet this is the field in which the
American model is in fact least applicable. In
Czechoslovakia, for example, there are about
3,000 publishing houses but no law protecting
them or defining their financial position.
Attempts are being made to propagate the idea
that privately-owned television is synonymous
with independent television. Meanwhile, local
film production is coming to a halt as its pro¬
ducts lose access to distribution networks satu¬
rated with American B-movies. Cuts in subsi¬
dies to public libraries, museums and similar
institutions are being contemplated.
Such, in brief, are some of the pitfalls and
dangers confronting post-communist societies
in the throes of change. The much-touted risk
of a return to communism seems to me per¬
sonally to be one of the least of them.
Every communist nation had an opposition
of sorts, whose strength and visibility varied
from country to country. The "dissidents", as
they were known in the West, only enjoyed
solid popular support in Poland. Elsewhere
they represented protest movements of nation¬
alists or intellectuals, drawing their strength
only from the contrast between the moral sense
of individual citizens and the immorality of the
ruling class. In this way the very concept of
morality was identified with the anti-commu¬
nist cause.
This association was largely illusory, as the
first years of the post-communist era have
demonstrated. In a recent essay entitled Summer
Meditations, Vaclav Havel writes: "The return of
freedom to a world in moral decomposition
inevitably involved a phenomenon that was
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
wholly predictable in the nature of things but
that nonetheless turned out to be much graver
than might have been expected. This was the
extraordinary and almost blindingly blatant
explosion of every imaginable base human ins¬
tinct. It was as if a whole range of shady or at
the very least ambiguous inclinations, which
had insidiously festered within society for
years (while also being requisitioned into daily
use by the totalitarian system), were suddenly
released from their straitjacket and granted
complete freedom to express themselves and
spread. their wings. A certain discipline, if one
may use the term, that had been imposed by
the authoritarian régime (which, in doing so,
had also 'legalized' these base instincts), had
been shattered, while a new one based on
freely-accepted collective responsibilities,
which would have smothered them rather than
giving them rein, had not yet grown up. Nor
could it have, for it takes many years for such a
development to mature.
"So we find ourselves confronted with a
bizarre situation in which societies that have
indubitably become freer in many ways behave
worse than in the days when they lacked
freedom. Criminality of every kind has
increased rapidly, and the sensational press has
unleashed the nauseating flood that always
seems to spurt out of some dark corner of the
collective memory in times of great historical
change. Worse still, even more disturbing phe¬
nomena are beginning to become apparent: sus¬
picion and rancour between nationalities,
racism, even manifestations of fascism, brazen
demagogy, intrigues and deliberate lies, poli¬
tical chicanery, shameless and unrestrained
promotion of vested interests, naked ambition
and the thirst for power, fanaticism of every
variety, new kinds of confidence trickery,
Mafia-style venality and a general absence of
tolerance, mutual comprehension, good taste,
reflection or a sense of proportion	"
The communist countries have gained their
freedom, but they are far from achieving a
healthy democracy or economy. They will only
attain these objectives if political leaders do not
confuse ends and means and choose suitable
paths to reach the desired goals. O
In Our Fathers' Footsteps
(1988),
polyester and concrete
sculpture, painted
in acrylic, by the Slovak
artist Josef Jankovic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Latin America:
a different
way forward?
by Ernesto Sábato
52
Robotized industrial nations
can learn a salutary
lesson from the supposedly "less
advanced" societies
THE problem of the relationship between
cultures is subtly linked to that of
national or regional identity. For proof
one need only look to Latin America, where
the movement of opposition to the Spanish
conquest, five centuries after the fact, has made
the "return to tradition" a rallying cry without
specifying to which tradition we are supposed
to return. Am I, as an Argentinian of Italian
parentage, expected to write in Quechua or in
Araucanian? Or to reject the influence of
Greek and Latin culture and then that of the
European nations?
World history is a story of invasions, con¬
quests and the intermingling of peoples. Con¬
sider, for instance, a nation like Spain. What is
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
its "real" identity? If we go far enough back into
the past, we reach the mysterious Iberians
about whom almost nothing is known. In their
footsteps came Phoenicians, Celts, Romans,
Germanic peoples, Greeks and Arabs. What
could the "real" language of such a nation be?
Castilian Spanish with all its Teutonic, Arab,
Greek, Latin, Italian, English and now Amer¬
ican derivations expunged? Purity is a concept
that only has meaning in the world of Platonic
ideals. Nothing in the human world is pure
nor on Mount Olympus either, contaminated
as its denizens were by Egyptian and Babylo¬
nian divinities.
In 1978 I was told that we were celebrating
the millennium of the Spanish language. Sur¬
prised by such precision, I requested further
information. What I learned was that in the
year 978 a monk of the monastery of San
Millán jotted notes in a grotesque Roman dia¬
lect in the margins of a Latin manuscript. He
can hardly have imagined that he was inventing
Castilian Spanish. This is no joke on my part. I
am simply paraphrasing the arguments put for¬
ward to justify the anniversary.
Since Spanish is a living language, not an
invented one, we must refuse the good monk
the honour of having invented it. All he did was
to put into writing some words of a dialect that
had developed over the centuries in the clumsy
and poorly articulated utterances of illiterate
peasants who had no need to read Cicero in
order to raise their pigs, shout for food, scold
their wives or berate their children. It is impos¬
sible to know how long it took to "corrupt
Latin", as one purist has put it but then Latin
had already been corrupted by the Roman sol¬
diery, and would continue to be so through the
development of other tongues. The same point
could be made about the languages of other
nations once invaded by so-called "barbarians"
and now celebrated for their culture.
I am perfectly well aware of the atrocities
committed by the Spaniards in the course of
the conquest, and I am in no way condoning
them. The Spanish conquest of the Americas
was, like all such events, abominable. But if the
descriptions of the "black legend" and all its
attendant horrors were the whole story, it is
hard to see why the defenders of the indige¬
nous peoples' cause do not make their case in
Mayan or the Aztec language. Come to that, it
is also difficult to see why Rubén Dario and
César Vallejo, two of the greatest poets of the
Spanish language and both of mixed race, not
only felt no rancour towards Spain but even
hymned it in memorable poems. Nor is it easy
to explain how, in those circumstances, the cul¬
ture of Hispanic America, having undergone
the influence of the great European intellectual
currents, could not merely have produced one
of the great literatures of the contemporary
Opposite page,
a Mayan stucco sculpture
of a man's head
(classic period, 600-900),
Chiapas, Mexico.
Below, Mask
(pastel and coconut fibre, on
wood), by the Hungarian
artist Blaise Simon (1990).
world but also have influenced European
writers in its turn. Finally one could adduce the
subversive and paradoxical argument that the
colonies owed their liberation to the doctrines
of the Enlightenment and of Romanticism,
both of which originated in Europe.
I am not for a moment denying the element
of snobbery that has characterized Hispanic
America's passing imitations of the great Euro¬
pean intellectual movements. But snobbery is
not limited to new nations: it was not us, to the
best of my knowledge, who invented the word
"snob". True, a great Argentinian intellectual
of the last century discovered the beauty of one
of our own trees by reading a European
Romantic. But just as illustrious, and even
more ridiculous, examples of similar behaviour
can be found in Europe itself. Although Frede¬
rick the Great spoke German as his native
tongue, he only read Wolff's metaphysical
works after they had been translated into
French. The story is frightening as well as
comical, rather as if nineteenth-century Greeks
had had to read Goethe to appreciate the
beauty of the Parthenon.
But that is how culture works, in strange
and roundabout ways. We should not be so
hard on our feeling of awe in face of European
culture, for thanks to it we have in turn been
able to dazzle the Europeans themselves
those same Europeans who once turned to
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
Left and opposite page,
wood sculptures from a
Sakalava royal tomb at
Tsianihy, Madagascar
(c. 1897).
The influence of Indonesian
art has been turned to
original effect in these
imposing figures (height
159.1 and 180.5 cm).
Ernesto Sábato, Argentinian
writer, philosopher and
essayist, is the author of a
number of novels that have
had a great influence on
Latin-American literature.
Among the best-known are El
túnel (1948; The Outsider,
1950) Alejandra (1967) and
Abaddon el exterminador
(1974; "Abaddon the
Exterminator").
Spanish-American novels only for picturesque
effects and local colour, as though solitude, suf¬
fering and death, the ultimate attributes of the
human condition, were not common to all
peoples. I mention this because one American
critic has written, with reference to Borges, that
the Argentinians have no "national" art, doubt¬
less because our culture lacks that quality of
local colour that tourists so admire. What
would this critic make of Moby Dick? Would
he consider Melville stateless on the grounds
that in American territorial waters metaphy¬
sical whales are in short supply?
A THREATENED
WORLDVIEW
Great artists seek the absolute, for art comes,
mysteriously, not just from the conscious mind
but also, and perhaps to a greater extent, from
the submerged layers of the unconscious, the
domain of the life urge and the death wish. Yet
although this visionary form of art is essentially
subjective, its subject-matter does not exist in
isolation, but has a specific society and a given
culture as its context. And every artist, however
magisterial, reflects the influence of others, just
as Beethoven came out of Mozart. In the same
way, our art has European antecedents, but the
link in no way diminishes its (relative) origina¬
lity, for those forms of artistic expression that
are not collective endeavours, like the building
of the cathedrals, are individual and unique.
The basic difference between science and art
lies in the fact that scientists strip away the self
from their view of the world, while artists do
not aspire to such abstraction. The originality
of art lies precisely in this apparent incapacity,
which explains why art has style while science
does not: it would be meaningless to look for
the "style" of Pythagoras in his celebrated
theorem. The language of science is ultimately
no more than a sequence of abstract and imper¬
sonal symbols, while a work of art is a unique
and original mark left on the world, the
concrete expression, enigmatic and uncertain,
of a creature of flesh and blood.
Although this difference between science
and artistic creation has always existed, it has
now attained critical importance. By overval¬
uing science and technology, the thinking of
the philosophers of the European Enlighten¬
ment and their positivist successors has
involved the human race in an accelerating pro¬
cess of abstraction and rationalization. The
resulting crisis is not just that of capitalism or
of socialist dictatorships, but also that of a cer¬
tain view of the world that has ended by forc¬
ing both opposing camps into the same mould
and establishing the reign of mass man. Under
both systems for scientific knowledge knows
no politics the sciences are all the more
powerful because they are abstract. Humanity
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
has been led off towards a mathematical
Olympus, leaving flesh-and-blood humans
increasingly alone and confused. Steel and the
triangle, logarithms and nuclear energy have all
come together with the most abstract forms of
economic power to create a diabolical machine
in which human beings have become anony¬
mous and powerless cogs.
It is already possible to measure the terrible
price we have had to pay for having. banished
the archaic powers of the unconscious mind.
The hidden gods have had their revenge in the
form of collective hysteria, widespread anxiety,
the devastation of whole peoples by technol¬
ogy, sadistic violence and drug abuse, which is
not, as is often wrongly claimed, a problem of
delinquency.
The true
realists
So what does the dialectic of cultures amount
to? What role is there for the poor nations
that huge majority of peoples oppressed by the
myopia and mad avarice of the world banking
system and the rich countries in a world in
which social injustice prevails and where mil¬
lions of children are dying of hunger?
Some countries, including my own, have
already advanced halfway along the path sepa¬
rating us from the great industrial powers and
it is important that we should not make the
same mistakes as they have. Progress must be
welcomed, but only if it is illuminated by the
light of the great philosophies of life and by the
wisdom and foresight of those thinkers who in
the nineteenth century were already looking
for ways of restoring a sacred dimension to
nature and to humankind. Let us avoid at all
costs the alienation of the individual by exces¬
sive state power, the world of mass man, the
spread of megalopolises built for robots, the
destruction of ancient cultures, centralization,
and contempt for small nations, however small
they may be above all if they are very small.
All of this may sound Utopian and may
draw smiles from so-called realists. But if "re¬
alists" are those who are destroying all forms of
reality, from nature in all its nobility to the
souls of children and adolescents, it seems wise
to turn instead for inspiration to those who
believe it is impossible to live without these
ideals. We are all aware of the crisis of ideolo¬
gies, but that does not mean that we must give
up the great ideals of freedom, justice and a
belief in the sacred nature of the human being.
In this respect, the so-called "backward" coun¬
tries, in which people have not been trans¬
formed into robots, have a salutary lesson to
teach us all. As Schopenhauer put it in a phrase
later quoted by Nietzsche, "There are periods
of history in which progress is reactionary and
reaction is progressive". O 55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
I
THE PARTS
ÉoT>
/*
4"
Above,
Endless Ribbon, a sculpture
in granite by the Swiss artist
Max Bill.
56
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
A golden age of dialogue
Mixing reason and intuition, the
pre-Socratic philosophers of
ancient Greece reached some
surprisingly modern conclusions
and developed a spirit of
intellectual tolerance that still
has much to teach us
by Yassilis Vassilikos
AT the wellspring of universalist thought,
the pleiad of philosophers known as the
pre-Socratics belong not just to their
homelands the Greek and Sicilian coasts of
ancient Ionia but to the world. They deserve
to be known as philosophers of the Universe,
or philosophers of the four corners of the
Earth, or philosophers of the infinite.
To start alphabetically, Alcmaeon was the
first philosopher to discuss the importance of
the human brain, that most perfect of com¬
puters, which he described as a primordial ele¬
ment. A little later, another pre-Socratic,
Democritus, put forward ideas prefiguring the
first electronic brain and atomic fission. But
Alcmaeon, a pupil of Pythagoras in his later
years, has the honour of having introduced to
Western thought the Chinese concepts of yin
and yang when he spoke of humankind's essen¬
tial duality and claimed that the unitary state,
with no counter-balance, is a cause of sickness.
Duality was, of course, subsequently to prove
fundamental to the development of computers,
through the concepts of "input" and "output".
Democritus, with Leucippus (often des¬
cribed as his twin), developed the original
atomic theory. He was the first thinker to
affirm that nothing exists other than atoms
and the void. His dialectical materialism,
which presented nature as a single entity
whose parts were all linked, has been borne
out by the scientific discoveries of our 57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
Mercury (Roman equivalent
of the Greek god Hermes)
with his caduceus, or staff,
adorns the façade of a house
at Melk, Austria.
58
Vassilis Vassilikos, a writer
and essayist who was exiled
from his native Greece during
the dictatorship of the
colonels, is the author of
several novels, the best-
known of which, Z, was
filmed by Costa Gavras. He
was in charge of Greek
television from 1981 to
1985, and now lives in Paris,
where he has recently
published a novel,
L'Hélicoptère (1991).
century, the century of the atom, of the theory
of relativity and of quantum mechanics. In the
1920s and 1930s in Copenhagen, Born, Schrö-
dinger, Kramers and Dirac conducted experi¬
ments on quantum mechanics and on the
uncertainty principle, the law of physics that
most directly rebuts Plato's social ideas and the
logic of Aristotle.
Heraclitus introduced the concept of psy¬
chosomatic influences on health, which has
been considerably developed in our time. One
of his fundamental beliefs was that antithesis
and antagonism are the causes of progress and
development. "War is the mother of all things,"
he claimed. Everything decays and is changed,
except for the law of change itself. Another of
his ideas, which appeared paradoxical at the
time but which anticipated many modern
scientific discoveries, was that the universe dies
and comes to life in alternating epochs, having
neither a Creator, a beginning nor an end in
time. Is the physicist's law of the conservation
of energy not the clearest possible confirmation
that the Universe is infinite and immortal?
Some years later, Empedocles foretokened
the eternal nature of matter. "Foolish men," he
wrote, "how could it be possible that anything
should come from nothing? Movement and
immobility, life and death are merely two faces
of the same reality." Yet it was not until 2,500
years later, in the eighteenth century, that
Leibniz and Lavoisier discovered the law of the
indestructibility of matter. And contemporary
atomic science has calculated that, while the
lifespan of certain atomic particles is extremely
short, every electron, proton or neutron has
always been in existence. The universe is made
up of these basic building-blocks, and it is cer¬
tain that nothing is born of nothing. "Nothing
is born of nothing and whatever is has always
been and always will be. There is neither begin¬
ning nor end. Nothing departs, for nothing has
ever arrived." So claimed Melissos, one of the
least known of the pre-Socratics, but none the
less important for that. Others of his fellows
would add precision to the concept of con¬
tinual creation: Pherecydes of Syros said that
"Water is born of time".
The beginnings
of pluralism
At the beginning of the sixth century BC,
Thaïes travelled by boat from Miletus to Egypt
with the intention of studying in the temples of
Thoth or Hermes, god of learning. On his
return, he amazed his compatriots by declaring:
"The Sun and stars are only spheres of fire of
colossal dimensions." His disciple Anaxi-
mander thought that the world originated as an
undifferentiated mass of primitive and arid
matter. He explained that this mass had grad¬
ually condensed from a gas to a liquid before
solidifying, and he stressed the role that tem¬
perature played in the birth of the world. Other
thinkers sought a comprehensive explanation in
mathematics. Philolaos, for example, con¬
sidered that "everything is numbers. Without
numbers there is neither knowledge nor
thought." And the essential power of numbers
for him lay in a decimal system.
Modern physicists have similar concerns.
Werner Heisenberg wrote that "It is perhaps
interesting to note that the problem of determi¬
ning whether the original matter is one known
to us, or something different placed above it,
re-emerges in a different form in contemporary
physics. Physicists today are trying to establish
a fundamental law of the movement of matter,
just as the pre-Socratics did in their day, a law
that would explain all the elementary particles
and their singularities." "Consequently," Hei¬
senberg noted, "in the last analysis mathe¬
matical forms replace regular bodies according
to a process that is virtually identical to that of
the Pythagoreans, whereby harmonic vibrations
can be obtained by differently arranging the
tension of strings." For Pythagoras, numbers
were "the principal elements of nature".
Thaïes, "the first astronomer to predict
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
Left,
bronze statuette
(7th-6th century BC) of the
ancient Egyptian Moon-god
Thoth, whom the Greeks
identified with Hermes.
eclipses of the Sun and explain the solstices",
was the founder of a new tradition of freedom
of thought, according to the British philoso¬
pher Karl Popper. The critical attitude dis¬
played by disciples towards the teaching of
their masters was a feature of the philosophy of
the Ionian school. Thaïes could tolerate criti¬
cism, and even encouraged it. That was some¬
thing new. It marked a break with the previous
tradition whereby each school had a single doc¬
trine. Acceptance of a plurality of doctrines led
inevitably to an awareness that our attempts to
understand and explain the truth are not final
but open to improvement, and that knowledge
and ideology are influenced by circumstances.
Popper believes that one of the most important
lessons to be learned from the pre-Socratic phi¬
losophers is that all of them, with the exception
of the Pythagoreans, accepted a critical attitude
and even open disagreement without ostraci¬
zing dissenters.
The path
of dialogue
Parmenides was not only the physicist who
said "Everything comes from Necessity; Earth
and Sun and Moon and air that is common to
all and the Milky Way and the glowing stars".
He was also a poet who wrote that "Every¬
where Eros encourages base procreation and
parturition, driving the female to the male to
join in union." Anaxagoras showed the same
concern for unity: "The visible is the aspect of
The Greek philosopher
and sage Heraclitus of
Ephesus (c. 576-480 BC).
Engraving by an unknown
artist (17th-18th century).
59
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
The Greek philosopher Empedocles (c. 490-c. 435 BC). 17th-century engraving.
60
the invisible", he wrote; "the spirit rules every¬
thing" and "what had to be, what was and is no
longer, what is now and what will be all this
the spirit has known and has disposed in good
order by its rotation." So did Xenophanes, who
wrote that "The vast sea engendered the waters,
the winds and the rivers," and Anaximander,
who claimed that "Heat separated from cold at
the creation of the world and formed a burning
sphere around the atmosphere of the planet like
bark around a tree-trunk. And the sphere split
in two to form two spheres, that of cold and
that of heat, born of the matrix at the birth of
the world."
The ideas of the pre-Socratics can therefore
be seen as astonishing intuitions of modern
experimental science. After the pre-Socratics,
according to Popper, humanity sank into the
wintry torpor of the Middle Ages until our own
time, when Einstein, with his discoveries with
regard to movement, mass, energy and time,
offered a new image of the old universe.
Popper's views may be summarized as follows:
pre-Socratic philosophy shows us the way of
debate, from which truth can emerge, whereas
dogmatic religions and rigid ideologies are
monologues delivered by a single speaker who
thinks he has a monopoly of the truth. No such
monopoly can exist. The notion of complemen¬
tarity that characterizes atomic structure and
the quanta presupposes an awareness that two
different descriptions of an experience can be
equally valuable, and are both indispensable
even though they remain irreconcilable. I would
add, myself, that the law of indeterminacy re¬
inforces this message.
The pre-Socratic philosophers investigated
not just the Earth but the universe. Today they
would be involved in star-wars research. As one
American researcher has put it, "The psycho¬
logy of the common man in the twentieth cen¬
tury is hardly different in its outlines from that
of a sixteenth-century merchant or a four¬
teenth-century peasant, even if modern man has
a car and a television set. Future historians will
be astonished by the gap between the scientific
discoveries of our time and the anachronistic
attitudes we have inherited from the Middle
Ages. This chasm is one of the causes of our
present material and psychological crisis. For a
good example of right thinking and judgement,
we could turn to the golden century of the
Greek pre-Socratics, at a time when philosophy
was synonymous with scientific thought."
And, I would add, at a time when tech¬
nology was not limited to the capacities of the
computer. Humankind cannot live without
intuition. All the great thinkers, like all the
astronauts, have turned to poetry to describe
the miracle they saw. And poetry, along with
scientific knowledge, is what we find in pre-
Socratic philosophy. O
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
Two great
traditions
by Wang Bin
Attempting to understand the
European Christian tradition of
thought is a complex and
challenging experience for the
Chinese mind
Above, Confucius
(c. 551-479 BC).
18th-century Chinese
water-colour.
Above right, the birth of
Eve, as depicted in The Book
of Birds, a 12th-century
illuminated manuscript.
THIS article endeavours to answer a
difficult question: How does Christianity
differ (beyond purely religious differ¬
ences) from the Chinese tradition? Focusing
on collective thought patterns, I shall attempt
to explore a number of non-religious pheno¬
mena that are deeply rooted in Christian doc¬
trines but are notably absent from Chinese
intellectual life. It is these phenomena, the
article will argue, that not only differentiate
Western culture from Chinese culture, but also
illuminate the contributions Christianity has
made historically to the general development of
the human mind.
A transcendent deity emerges when the
potential believer separates himself or herself 61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
St. Francis, detail of a fresco
by CImabue (1240) in the
church of St. Francis at
Assisi, Italy
mentally from the external world and attempts
to establish a system of interpretation capable
of affording a final answer to all the mysteries
represented by nature. What impresses a Chi¬
nese reader of the Bible is not so much the
image of God as His relationship to human¬
kind. The notion of "covenant" is particularly
difficult for the Chinese mind to grasp. Ac¬
cording to Genesis, man, created by God, sepa¬
rates himself from God through the Fall and
devotes life-long strivings to an attempt to be
reunited with God in another world. The cove-
62
Wang Bin, Professor of
Language and Culture at the
University of Canton, has
published several
comparative analytical
studies of Chinese, Japanese
and European culture. His
recent works include Italian
Cappuccino and a Chinese
Tea Drinker: An Encounter of
Two Imaginations (1990).
nant between God and man not only holds out
the hope of achieving that ambition but pre¬
supposes a separation of man mentally from
the Truth, the Good and Beauty, the whole
external world pertaining to or created by God.
As for visible cosmic nature, God encourages
man to subjugate it by exercising "dominion
over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the
air, and over every living thing that moves
upon the Earth" (Genesis 1:28).
Stripped of its doctrinal content, the cove¬
nant reveals a deep-rooted thought pattern
whose archetype can be traced back to ancient
Greece and serves as a unique link between the
pagan tradition and contemporary intellectual
life. The characteristic features of this pattern
are, on the one hand, the detachment of man
(the observer) from the external world (the
observed), and on the other a constant effort to
achieve the final yet impossible recombination.
Ultimately, man is separated from himself as an
object of study. No revolution in the West has
ever altered this basic thought pattern.
The Chinese counterpart to this thought pat¬
tern is its precise opposite. In defining man's
relationship to the universe, Confucius, Lao
Tzu and his modern critics share a single frame¬
work: that of man in the universe. The term
"universe" refers mainly to cosmic nature in
Taoism and to society in Confucianism. (The
former finds its fullest expression in artistic
creation while the latter has its roots in Chinese
political-moral doctrines.) The man-in-the-uni-
verse thought pattern has survived many gen¬
erations of revolutionary change. The overlap¬
ping shadows of Confucius and Lao Tzu still
guide the thought processes of the Chinese
intelligentsia and circumscribe their imagination.
Transcendency
versus immanency
When the Chinese and the Western traditions
meet, the Chinese mind tends to appreciate the
Greeks and to reject Christianity, disregarding
the intellectual process which made the transi¬
tion from paganism to Christianity possible.
To the modern Chinese, passages in the Bible
that encourage the conquest of nature might be
acceptable. But the results of the separation
described above go much further than the
exploitation of cosmic nature and do not form
part of the Chinese mental landscape. They
include: a persistent quest for the ontological
meaning of human existence; a way of veri¬
fying the truth, divine or scientific, which in
the historical continuum encompasses not
merely modern individualism but a deep
Christian sense of the individual's soul
identified only with God; man's challenge to
the Almighty (as in the story of Job); the for¬
mula "I think, therefore I am"; the progress
from equality before God to equality before
the law; a contractual tradition that binds two
separate parts: God and man, a King and his
subjects, a state and its citizens; and so on. To
understand these ideas, the Chinese mind has
to adapt to a new perspective.
In addition to a mental state preoccupied
with the separation of man from God, a sense
of transcendency is indispensable to Christian
faith. Without it, it would be impossible to
conceive of reunion in the other world.
As a concept imported from the West, trans¬
cendency is frequently used by Chinese scholars
as well as Western sinologists to describe Taoism.
This conceptual misplacement, a common phe¬
nomenon in contemporary Chinese intellectual
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
r
"An Ascetic in Meditation".
Painting on silk of the Yuan
period (13th century).
:*St.
life, neglects the basic fact that Chinese "trans¬
cendency", restricted as it is to the "man-in-
the-universe" framework, is totally different
from what is meant by transcendency in its
strict Western sense.
Christian transcendency takes the indivi¬
dual (his soul) as the point of departure as well
as the final goal of fulfilment. It rises above
objects which reveal themselves to experience
and moves towards God or the absolute truth
in the other world. It focuses on the fulfilment
of the individual and points to the infinite. Chi¬
nese "transcendency", on the other hand,
requires the individual to transcend himself so
as to merge into nature or society. When there
is perfect harmony between man' and the uni¬
verse, the absolute truth can be grasped
through sense-perception and intuitive reason.
To the Chinese mind, the truth is here and to
the Christian mind, the truth is there. The two
truths are incommensurable, though they may
agree on some specific points.
The most obvious manifestation of this dif¬
ference is to be found in theoretical reflection
on artistic creation. From Plato on, classical
theories of art and literature attribute the
source of inspiration to the divine or the super¬
natural. In modern times some theorists have
seen inspiration as originating in the irrational
self (the emotions or the subconscious) as
opposed to the rational self, thus postulating a
microcosm within human nature of the separa¬
tion of man from God. Both these ideas involve
a transcendent movement from one opposite
towards the other. Modernism seeks pure truth
in life, a truth which, it maintains, has been pol¬
luted and distorted by civilized society. But it
remains a truth which is always there, not here.
All this contrasts sharply with the way in
which the Chinese understand inspiration. In
ancient Chinese, there is no such term as inspi¬
ration because such an idea is totally absent
from Chinese spiritual and intellectual life.
However, classical Chinese theories of art and
literature do describe a mental state in which
the artist suddenly finds himself confronted
with a spiritual spark triggered off as a result of
the inexplicable harmonization between the
artist and his object to be expressed.
Scholars of comparative literature who lack
philosophical insight have simplified this situa¬
tion and wrongly described it by attaching to it
another Western label, "expressionism" or
"empathy". Chinese expressionism, if we must
adopt this term, emphasizes a constant reci¬
procal movement and recognition between
subject and object within a shared space, the
universe. It is two in one. As for the source of
inspiration, the difference might be summa¬
rized as inspiration out of ontological transcen¬
dency versus inspiration out of cosmological
immanence.
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
64
To illustrate this difference, let us imagine
two classical pictures: a Western figure painting
and a Chinese wash painting. In the latter, the
landscape often occupies almost the whole
space with one or several figures relegated into
obscurity. A Western connoisseur might
misunderstand the overall arrangement as a
suppression of individuality. On the other
hand, the nimbus around the head of a beau¬
tiful medieval or Renaissance figure often
puzzles the Chinese mind. The setting is beau¬
tiful, so is the figure. But what is the point of
that small halo, a visual cliché? A readily found
explanation is Western superstition. If only
both sides would understand that appreciation
of different mysteries demands different pers¬
pectives as well as different imaginations!
However, from the Chinese point of view, the
challenge of Christian transcendency is more
than an image of unfamiliar beauty.
The relevance of Christian transcendency to
the general orientation of Western philosophy
and modern intellectual life cannot be overesti¬
mated. Kant, in his Critique of Pure Reason,
where he is concerned with modern epistemo-
logy or scientific knowledge, denies transcen- .
dent knowledge, that is, knowledge which goes
beyond the limit of experience. Such know¬
ledge belongs to the noumenon, the thing-in-
itself, or, to use the Christian expression, God.
But in his Critique of Practical Reason, Kant
tells us that moral thought and in particular
considerations about human freedom demand
reference to a noumenal self. Hence a famous
Kantian principle of man as the end, never only
as the means. It is on this transcendent specula¬
tion that modern liberal thinkers have built
various arguments about the freedom of the
individual which constitute the starting point
of Western political philosophy. Can we
understand this Kantian "categorical impera¬
tive" without a sense of transcendency? Is it
not true that Christian transcendency has in the
past two thousand years cultivated an intellec¬
tual atmosphere whose impact upon modern
society transcends religion itself?
The relevance of transcendency to the
natural sciences is equally important. Always
pointing to the infinite, it acts as a force which
constantly drives human imagination and cre¬
ativity forward. It is said that the Chinese mind
is capable of creating or absorbing new tech¬
nology but is not so efficient in creating or
internalizing new science. I would not go as far
as that, but history has proved that the remark
is not without foundation. It takes transcen¬
dency as well as abstraction to make a scientific
mind. Unfortunately, in everyday Chinese
conversation and in the mass media, science
and technology are not differentiated. This
matches another confusion: the equation of
religion and superstition.
What is versus what-ought-to-be
When we discuss the Western tradition, we
Chinese are often confronted with a seemingly
inexplicable dichotomy between the moral man
and the intellectual man, a distinction first
made by Matthew Arnold who referred to the
two elements involved as, respectively, "the
forces of Hebraism and Hellenism". This gives
the misleading impression that the Greek mind
is concerned with "What-Is" while the Chris¬
tian mind, like that of Confucius, is oriented
towards "What-Ought-To-Be". I would argue
that What-Is is characteristic of both the Greek
and the Christian traditions.
Like Aristotle's "substance", God as a cate¬
gory is characterized by three priorities: know¬
ledge priority God is the Absolute truth or
the subject and purpose of understanding;
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
definition priority God is the definition or the
subject in terms of logic while all the others are
predicates; and time priority God is the Being
independent of and determinant of all other
beings. Without this combination of epistemo-
logy, logic and ontology as a prerequisite,
Christian love and good works are meaningless.
Modern Chinese intellectuals feel sympathy
for Christian charity and works but many of
them reject god as a term imagined through
superstition. In the past ten years or so many of
them have talked loudly about the importance
of "transforming the traditional thought pat¬
tern", but what they mean by "thought pattern"
has turned out to be economic, political or
moral ideas. While they have been busy intro¬
ducing Western ideas to replace Chinese ones,
they have actually paid little attention to the
Zen
(8 cm x 66 cm, 1991).
Mixed media on canvas by
the French artist
Jean-Pierre Bourquin.
thought pattern which supports those ideas.
Thus we have a coin with two sides: Cathayan
centricity on one side and wholesale Westerni¬
zation on the other. This is the inevitable result
of a three-thousand-year long tradition in which
epistemology has yet to come to maturity.
Doubtless, Christianity also experienced
domination by What-Ought-To-Be. For more
than a thousand years, the spirit of the Church
ruled the Western mind. It monopolized the
interpretation of the Bible and institutionalized
the Christian world into a hierarchy of terror.
The Reformation was of profound significance
in that it removed the Church as the mediator
between God and man. When man confronts
directly what he believes, he is free to pursue
What-Is. Without this spiritual and intellectual
liberation, the capitalist spirit and Protestant
ethics could not have made a new world. Max
Weber should have added two significant
points to his analysis of the rise of Protestan¬
tism. Firstly, that the re-establishment of What-
Is is predetermined by the separation of man
from God, which not only gives rise to a reli¬
gious revolution but nurtures modern episte¬
mology which, in turn, challenges that religion.
Secondly, that any faith or ideal, no matter how
perfect it is, will inevitably decline in popula¬
rity if it is institutionalized into an interpreta-
tional hierarchy in order to control freedom of
thought. The second point is more than a
matter of thought pattern. Its far-reaching
significance is a powerful challenge to any type
of authoritarian institution.
The universal
The above argument presents Christianity as a
challenge to the Chinese mind. It does not
imply that Christianity or the West are uni¬
versal. If they were it would be impossible to
explain Chinese prosperity in the past and its
predictable possibility in the future. What,
then, is the universal? It seems to be a mis¬
leading and even dangerous question, similar to
"What is God?" or "What is the absolute
truth?" A more acceptable formulation is that
of unity in diversity. Unity does not mean
conformity, nor does diversity mean the
coexistence of independent but discrete ele¬
ments. How can unity in diversity be achieved?
I see it as a kind of challenge. It is a mutual
exposure to new dimensions and perspectives, a
constant discovery of complementary factors in
otherness and, finally, a rediscovery of oneself.
It is a dialectical movement towards reciprocal
recognition of different traditions and thought
patterns. Even if there is no contact for the time
being, the challenge remains. Our task is to
turn potentiality into actuality. The process is
endless. It is in this sense that I take Christia¬
nity as a challenge to the Chinese mind. O 65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
66
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
The face of a
stranger
by Emmanuel Lévinas
A distinguished French
philosopher reflects on the
process of ethical
Self-portrait
(c. 1655),
oil on wood,
by Rembrandt
THE process of reflection stirred by the
face of another individual is not a thought
about a representation but at once a
thought for, a non-indifference towards the
other which upsets the equilibrium of the calm
and impassive soul of pure knowledge. It is an
awakening to a uniqueness in the other person
which cannot be grasped by knowledge, a step
towards the newcomer as someone who is both
unique and a fellow being. I am speaking of the
face itself, over and above any particular
expression it may bear, the face that exists
beneath every expression that crosses its coun¬
tenance and cloaks its nudity. To look at it in
this way is not so much an unveiling as a strip¬
ping bare of something exposed and un¬
defended, revealed as it is, naked as mortality
itself. The extreme precariousness of something
unique, the precariousness of the stranger. The
totality of the exposure lies in the fact that it is
not merely a new awareness of the familiar
revealed in its true light; it is a form of expres¬
sion, a primal language, a summons, an appeal.
The face is not the only vehicle of such an
exposure. In Vassili Grossman's Life and
Fate (part three, chapter 23) the author des¬
cribes a visit to the Lubianka prison in Moscow
by the families, wives and relatives of political
detainees, come for news. There is a queue at
the window, and those in it can only see the
backs of the people in front. A woman is wait¬
ing her turn. "She had never thought that the
human back could be so expressive and could
so vividly communicate a state of mind. As
people approached the window, they had a spe¬
cial way of stretching their backs and necks,
with their lifted shoulder-blades taut as if on
springs, as though the shoulders themselves
were shouting, crying and sobbing." What is
conveyed is the extreme precariousness of
those people, and a sense that peace lies in an
awareness of this.
For the absolute directness of this face and
its expression make demands on my deepest
self. Implicit in them is a right over me. What
concerns my selfhood is the specific circum-
awakening triggered by
scrutiny of the face of
another human being
stance in which that right has meaning. It is as
if the shadow of death the other face confronts
were my business, as if that death were my
concern. In this reminder of my responsibilities
by means of a face that has a claim on my self¬
hood, the stranger is my neighbour.
Of the directness of the stranger's gaze I
once wrote that its precariousness and defence-
lessness represent both the temptation to kill
and a cry for peace, a "Thou shalt not kill".
That face is already an accusation; there is sus¬
picion in it, but also a mute appeal. A human
right is there, in the frankness of that exposure,
invocation and command, a right more ancient
than any bestowal of honours or any question
of merit. In my closeness to my fellow beings,
and the promise of peace it brings, lies my res¬
ponsibility for someone else, the impossibility
of leaving that person to face the mystery of
death alone. In practical terms, this entails a
willingness to die for him. Living in peace with
others can demand that much. That is the
momentous implication of loving one's neigh¬
bour with a selfless love.
The peace attained by loving one's neigh¬
bour is not that of pure rest, which strengthens
us in our selfhood. Rather it represents a conti¬
nual challenge to selfhood, its limitless freedom
and its power.
Emmanuel Lévinas, of France, is a distinguished
modern philosopher, whose work, which combines
elements of German phenomenology and the Jewish
tradition, has had an important influence on
contemporary thought. He is the author of more than
twenty books, including Ethique et infini (1982),
Humanisme de l'autre homme (1975) and Entre-nous
Essais sur le penser-à-l 'autre (1991). Among his works
published in English is Totality and Infinity (1980).
67
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWS BRIEFS
BICYCLES AROUND THE
WORLD
Montreal will host the first world
conference on bicycling from 13
to 17 September this year. At
the Conférence Vélo Mondiale,
which is supported by Unesco
and the United Nations
Environment Programme, 700
participants from 30 countries,
among them planners, decision¬
makers and ordinary cyclists,
will spend 80 hours discussing
the current situation of cycling
around the world. The bicycle is
the world's most popular
personal vehicle, with more than
800 million machines in use.
Non-polluting, economical and
faster than cars, buses or even
the underground in urban
conditions, it might have been
designed with cities in mind,
though unfortunately cities are
rarely designed for it. At the
conference, the problems of
integrating bicycles into the
world's urban transport systems
will be considered in workshops,
discussion groups and round
tables. Given the stress,
pollution and difficulties of life
in cities today, the organizers
may be steering in the right
direction.
68
IN THE STEPS OF
GENGHIS KHAN
This July and August, Unesco's
fourth scientific expedition along
the Silk Roads of Asia will cross
one of the remotest parts of
Mongolia. Some 60 experts
from Mongolia and elsewhere,
including linguists,
ethnographers, anthropologists,
archaeologists and ethno-
musicologists, will cover 4,000
kilometres of dirt road by car or
bus or on horse or camel-back,
and will spend eight or nine
nights in yurts, the traditional
round felt tents of the nomads
of central Asia.
The expedition will set out
from Khobdo, in the heart of the
Altai mountain range in western
Mongolia, and will travel
eastwards along the former
trade route which once linked
the West to the Korean
peninsula and Japan. After
crossing the Gobi Desert and
visiting the former capital,
Khara-Khorin, it will come to an
end at Ulan Bator, where a
seminar on "The nomads of
Central Asia and the Silk Roads"
will be held from 3 to 5 August.
The Altai range, which is the
starting-point for the expedition,
is the heartland of the
Mongolian people and of the
Altaic family of languages, of
which there are more than forty,
including Turkish, Mongol and
Manchu-Tungus, spoken
altogether by over 90 million
people. The region has a
traditional music of great purity,
played on instruments of a kind
found nowhere else in the world.
FIRST NORTH-SOUTH
CONFERENCE ON THE
HUMAN GENOME
The developing countries must
be involved in the Human
Genome Project in order to
provide the majority of mankind
with a chance to share in its
benefits. To help to achieve this
goal, the first North-South
Human Genome Conference was
held at Caxambu (Brazil) from
12 to 15 May this year. Some
300 specialists from all over the
world attended the Conference,
which was organized by Unesco
and the Brazilian Biochemical
Society. The Project, one of the
most ambitious in the annals of
international scientific co¬
operation, aims to identify all
the DNA components of human
genes, and is likely to have far-
reaching effects, particularly in
the treatment of genetic
diseases. So far, all the work
has been done in industrialized
countries because of the
expense and complex
technology involved. Unesco
plans to organize similar
conferences in Asia and Africa.
SHIP WANTED
Does anybody have a spare
research vessel ready to set sail
for Antarctica? Oceanographers
and climatologists the world
over would be grateful for the
assistance which such a vessel
could provide for measuring the
Antarctic Circumpolar Current.
The lack of measurements
for the heat transfer patterns of
this current linking the Pacific,
Indian and Atlantic Oceans
represents one of the remaining
gaps in the research programme
for the World Ocean Circulation
Experiment (WOCE), the largest
scientific study ever undertaken
on the ocean and its influence
on climate. The study is being
carried out in connection with
the World Climate Research
Programme, which was launched
in 1979 by the World
Meteorological Organization and
the International Council of
Scientific Unions. More than 40
countries are taking part in the
work by providing research
vessels, drifting buoys,
satellites and other data-
collection aids. Merchant
vessels are also co-operating in
the measurement operations.
Unfortunately, scientific data
have not yet been gathered from
some of the ocean areas well
off regular shipping lanes.
WOCE will be of benefit to a
large number of maritime
activities, such as navigation,
fisheries and offshore oil
prospection and drilling. It will
also make it possible to obtain
a more accurate picture of the
impact which human activities
have on the climate and the
greenhouse effect caused by
the accumulation of gases in
the atmosphere. Its findings will
be used to set up the Global
Ocean Observing System
(GOOS), the studies for which
are being co-ordinated by
Unesco's Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission.
UNESCO REVIVES
DISAPPEARING CRAFTS
To prevent production-line
techniques from eliminating
traditional craftsmanship,
Unesco ¡s preparing a project to
improve the ¡mage of craft
professions in the eyes of
pupils, teachers and parents. In
six countries in Europe, Latin
America, the Caribbean, the
Arab states, Africa and Asia,
classes of children aged
between 10 and 12 will be
taught one of several crafts
such as glass-working, basket-
making, lace-making or
ceramics, chosen for their
cultural and historical interest
and their universal value. For
four months the children will
take part in weekly sessions of
practical work and visit craft
centres. They will keep a
notebook in which to describe
the history, techniques and
aesthetics of the craft they are
studying, and discuss its place
in modern life. The notebooks,
illustrated with drawings and
photographs and possibly
supplemented by short videos,
will be exchanged among the
participating countries, and then
with Unesco's assistance made
available around the world. O
This article is one of
a series in which the
Director-General of
Unesco sets out his
thinking on matters of
current concern.
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
AFTER R I O
A global partnership
i^^OURAGE is when you have choices," declared the
\#American journalist Terry Anderson emerging from
four years of terrible captivity. We have a choice. But do we
have the courage? This was the great underlying question at
the United Nations Conference on the Environment and
Development that took place at Rio de Janeiro (Brazil) from
3 to 14 June. Are we capable or not of establishing new prio¬
rities, of making arms reductions in favour of human devel¬
opment and aid to the most deprived countries, of pur¬
suing in the face of all obstacles and set patterns the path
from a civilization of war to a civilization of peace?
Five hundred years after the first encounter between
Two Worlds, we are finally discovering that the world and
humanity are one. We are realizing that the precious
resources of this Earth do not exist to be appropriated and
exploited without regard to the balance of nature or the
interests of others. Everywhere the understanding is dawn¬
ing that our common future depends on the establishment
of a new worldwide approach to development, on a new
relationship with the environment and our fellow human
beings. Our task is to translate this growing awareness into
a solemn compact of nations and into a personal commit¬
ment by all the inhabitants of the planet. No one can
remain a mere spectator; we must all become actors. Our
task is no longer to record history, but to write it. For it is
through our actual behaviour that history is written,
notably that of a more equitable future for humanity.
A CULTURE OF SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT
We must lay the foundations for a culture of sustainable
development rooted in a new ecological economics and for
a global partnership dedicated to ensuring the well-being of
all the world's inhabitants and safeguarding the future habi-
tability of our planet. Our generation bears a unique ethical
responsibility since its choices will determine the fate of all
future generations. As the main contractors of the environ¬
mental debt, the industrialized countries should be the chief
contributors to making good the damage to the environ¬
ment and should take measures to help the less well-
endowed countries achieve sustainable human develop¬
ment. In the face of potentially irreversible damage to
global life-support systems, we must act now in order not
to compromise the rights of generations to come. This is the
challenge that confronts us.
Such a challenge calls for an alliance between govern¬
ments, international organizations, non-governmental orga¬
nizations of all kinds, scientific and professional communi¬
ties and individual citizens. The United Nations will have a
vital role to play as co-ordinator and co-implementer of the
measures adopted at Rio. Within the overall United
Nations effort, UNESCO has a broad and substantial contri¬
bution to make as the specialized agency responsible for
education, science, culture and communication.
Education at all levels, formal and non-formal, will be
essential in moving, through increased knowledge and
improved capacity-building, towards sustainable develop¬
ment. Reducing population growth, improving urban and
rural living conditions and increasing economic growth all
depend on access to knowledge and on the transfer and
sharing of knowledge. Educational, informational and
awareness-building activities particularly at the grassroots
level will encompass such areas as environment and devel¬
opment, global issues, women's role in development, family
planning and child care.
Science, of course, will be of the essence. It is more vital
than ever that political leaders have access to hard scientific
data for decision-making and that scientists and politicians
should work closely together. The measures adopted at Rio
will have to go hand in hand with continuous scientific
assessment of problems, likely future developments and
possible solutions. Systematic long-term monitoring of the
state of the environment and the state of human develop¬
ment will be essential. UNESCO, with its constitutional res¬
ponsibility for mobilizing the scientific community and for
providing scientific and technical assistance to governments,
has a major role to play here.
Culture must not be neglected in this programme. Sus¬
tainable development means human development one
expressive of the rich diversity of cultures and individuals.
The activities of the World Decade for Cultural Develop¬
ment and the independent World Commission on Culture
and Development will have an important contribution to
make to the implementation of the conclusions of the Rio
Conference.
The complex, interrelated problems of environment and
development call for solutions based on interdisciplinary and
intersectoral approaches. UNESCO's wide mandate makes
it particularly well placed to test and promote integrated
approaches in this sphere. It is likewise called upon to lend
its voice to those that have no voice: the most deprived, the
most ignorant, the most isolated and above all the
unborn.
A MORAL CONTRACT
The Conference could not resolve the problems confront¬
ing us at one stroke. It has, however, marked the start of a
"global change" in attitudes to environment and develop¬
ment and to the related issues of poverty, illiteracy, disease
and overpopulation. It has fashioned a moral contract
strong enough to prevail against powerful economic inter¬
ests of many kinds, so as to enable present generations to
repair the harm that has been done and to ensure that future
generations enjoy the right of all human beings to be born
"free and equal". From now on we shall all be accountable
for our action or our failure to act; and this accountability
will rest on a new system of accountancy, transcending
economism.
Will we have the courage to open up a new path for the
future of the human species? Will we have the wisdom to
agree to pay the price of peace as we have been willing at
what cost! to pay the price of war? Yes, if the most devel¬
oped countries set about curbing their consumption, parti¬
cularly of the superfluous kind. Yes, if sharing takes place
particularly the sharing of knowledge. Yes, if the developing
countries fix their national priorities according to their own
criteria but in keeping with the principles of human devel¬
opment. Yes, above all, if it is understood on all sides that
external aid can do no more than initiate a process and that
all of us, rich and poor, will only become what we ourselves
have been capable of creating. Q
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
A DREAM CITY BUILT ON SALT
WORLD HERITAGE by Roy Malkin
70
Right, an engraving from Claude-Nicolas Ledoux's book L'Architecture (1804)
showing an overall view of Chaux, the ideal city Ledoux dreamed of building
around the nucleus of the royal saltworks at Arc-et-Senans.
Above, the saltworks as they are today.
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
DEEP in rural France, on a wide plain
beneath the foothills of a mountain
range, stands a group of massive
stone buildings arranged in a semi-circle and
surrounded by a high wall. They have vast
tiled roofs, neo-classical pillars, porticoes and
pediments which dwarf the modern village
houses around their precinct. There is some¬
thing strange and otherworldly about them,
perhaps because of their lack of context;
Who built them? What for? And why here in
the midst of fields? When one learns that
they harbour a centre for reflection on the
future, the mystery deepens, before being
resolved when one discovers that they are
actually a piece of futurology themselves: an
eighteenth-century French architect's vision,
partly realized in the twilight of the ancien
régime, of how a modern industrial society
should look and be organized.
The buildings in question are those of
the Royal Saltworks at Arc-et-Senans, a vil¬
lage not far from Besançon in the region of
Franche-Comté. They have a theatrical set¬
ting between the forest of Chaux to the west
and, to the east, the ramparts of the Jura
massif, which make a spectacular backcloth
as they rise in a series of plateaux towards
the Swiss border.
Salt is a universal necessity, and in the
days before refrigeration it was even more
necessary, to preserve perishable food, than
it is today. "Man can live without gold but
not without salt," wrote Julius Caesar, and in
ancient times this precious commodity was
actually known as "white gold". During the
ancien régime in France salt was particularly
indispensable as a source of revenue to the
crown, which held a monopoly on its distri¬
bution. A tax known as the gabelle was
levied on salt and collected by intermedia¬
ries, the Farmers-General, who each year
paid a lump sum to the king for the privilege.
The gabelle was a highly unpopular tax, and
salt became in the popular mind a hateful
symbol of royal absolutism.
Salt has been produced in the Jura ever
since the Iron Age. The town of Salins, some
twenty kilometres away from Arc-et-Senans
in a valley of the Jura foothills, had become
rich and powerful in medieval times because
of the brine that lay deep beneath its streets.
For many centuries Salins brine was evapo¬
rated into salt in vast cauldrons heated by
firewood from the surrounding hills (the
word Jura is a synonym for a wood or
forest). By the second half of the eighteenth
century, however, the saltworks of Salins
were in crisis. With the passing of the ages
the brine had become increasingly diluted,
so that more and more fuel already
scarce was needed to supply the furnaces.
In 1771 it was decided that a new royal salt¬
works was needed in the region. To design
and build it Louis XV called on a thirty-
eight-year-old architect and decorative de¬
signer, Claude-Nicolas Ledoux.
Ledoux had won a reputation as a de¬
signer of houses for members of fashionable
society, a profession he would follow until
the Revolution. He had written the article on
Architecture for the Encyclopaedia of
Diderot and D'Alembert. He built the
Pavillon de Louveciennes for Madame du
Barry, the king's favourite, and it was at her
instigation that in 1771 he was appointed by
the king Inspecteur Général des Salines de
Franche Comté. Now he had a commission
that any ambitious architect might dream of:
building an entire new industrial facility
from nothing.
Ledoux familiarized himself with the ter¬
rain of Franche-Comté, and by 1773 he had
found what seemed to be an ideal location: a
clearing in the middle of the royal forest of
Chaux between the two small villages (today
united into one) of Arc and Senans. The
forest offered a seemingly inexhaustible
supply of wood. Brine would be brought
from Salins at the rate of 135,000 litres a day
by means of a twenty-kilometre-long under¬
ground pipeline which would be made from
hollowed-out tree trunks and be guarded by
the military. Some idea of the size of the op¬
eration can be gauged from the fact that
15,000 fir trees would be felled for the pipe¬
line alone. Ledoux enthused over the site he
had chosen: "lying between two rivers, near a
forest 40,000 acres in extent, in the centre of
the continent; linked to the Mediterranean by
the Dole canal, and to the North Sea and the
port of Antwerp by the Rhine."
The plans that were drawn by Ledoux
and eventually accepted by the king made
provision for the buildings disposed in a
closed semi-circle that can still be seen today.
At the centre of the main axis was a
Director's Villa, flanked by other buildings
in which the brine would be evaporated. In
the interests of aesthetic uniformity the latter
would not have chimneys: the smoke would
be evacuated through dormer windows in
the roof. In the curve of the semi-circle were
the dwellings in which artisans carpenters,
smiths, coopers and so onand their fami¬
lies would live, some 240 people in all. There
would also be a prison, for the director of an
eighteenth-century royal saltworks in France
wielded absolute power; at Arc-et-Senans no
workman could leave his dwelling or work¬
place without being seen from the Director's
Villa. The semi-circular space enclosed by
the buildings would be used for stocking the
vast quantities of wood needed to evaporate
some 100,000 tons of brine each year.
Building work began in 1775 and four
;yt'. iií
Roy Malkin is editor
of the English-
language edition of
the Unesco Courier. 71
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
The villa of the
Director of the
saltworks flanked by
the salt-making
workshops.
72
WORLD HERITAGE
years later salt was being produced at Arc-
et-Senans. However, it soon became clear
that output would not live up to expecta¬
tions. It had been hoped to produce 60,000
quintals of salt annually, but production
hardly reached 35,000-45,000. There were
several reasons for this disappointing perfor¬
mance. The brine from Salins was less and
less salty, and in any case much of it seeped
out of the pipeline from leaks caused by As¬
suring of the wood and badly made joints.
Ledoux had built an immense 500-metre-
long wooden shed known as a bâtiment de
graduation, in which the brine was supposed
to evaporate naturally by exposure to wind
and Sun, thus becoming more concentrated
and requiring less fuelwood in the final
cooking process. The Jura climate proved
inimical to this system.
In 1806 the saltworks were sold to a
private company which exploited them
throughout the nineteenth century. The
hollow trunks were replaced by steel piping
and coal took the place of wood. But still the
saltworks were barely viable, and production
finally ceased in 1895. In the 1930s the buil¬
dings were bought by the local authorities,
restored and later classified as a historic
monument by the French Government.
Since 1972 they have been the Headquarters
of the Fondation Claude-Nicolas Ledoux as
a "Centre International de Réflexion sur le
Futur". In 1982 the monument was included
on UNESCO's World Heritage List.
Ledoux did not forget the Royal Salt¬
works. In fact they seem to have obsessed
him until the end of his life. During the
Revolution, when he was imprisoned for a
time and narrowly escaped the guillotine, he
dreamed of an Ideal City and drew plans for
it. The nucleus of the city, which he named
Chaux, was the saltworks he had built in
Franche-Comté years before.
Using the cubes, cylinders, pyramids,
spheres and other geometric shapes for which
he had a predilection, he set out to develop a
style of architecture to meet the needs of a
new classless society. The principles and ideas
on which the city of Chaux would be based
he set forth in a remarkable book, L'architec¬
ture considérée sous le rapport de l'art, des
mcurs, et de la législation, which he wrote
during the Revolution. "People!" he wrote in
the preface, "Unity so worthy of respect for
the importance of each individual of which
you are composed, you shall not be forgotten
in the constructions of art; at appropriate dis¬
tances from the cities, monuments rivalling
those of the palaces of the governors of the
globe will rise in your name."
Ledoux wished each building in Chaux
to be "an edifice marked by the function
accorded to it." The houses of craftsmen
would symbolize in their architecture the
trades of those who would live in them. The
cooper's house would have a hoop-like
shape; that of the woodcutter would
resemble a pile of logs. In Ledoux's draw¬
ings, the gunsmith's house looks like a group
of smoking pyramids. This would be what
Ledoux called "une architecture parlante"
whose overall effect would be that of "a kind
of visual encyclopaedia of the members of
society and of their respective duties." Some
buildings and their designs would also be
identified with moral values and contribute
to the education of the people who would
belong to the new society. There would be a
Temple of Reconciliation, an Asylum of
Happiness, a Temple of Memory.
None of Ledoux's Utopian plans for an
Ideal City ever came to fruition. Long for¬
gotten, they have fascinated many modern
architects and city planners. Perhaps for want
of a better label, the style of the nucleus of
buildings the visitor to Arc-et-Senans can still
see today has been described as "Revolutio¬
nary Architecture"although of course it
was built in the reign of Louis XVI.
And so these stone buildings, today
marooned incongruously in the middle of a
plain in Franche Comté, are both a begin¬
ning and an end, a memorial to a lost cause, a
signpost along a road that industrial society
might have taken but did not. O
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
ANNIVERSARY
1881-1942
Stefan
Zweig
by Gertraud Steiner
HE was a man of letters, a cosmopo¬
litan European in that period be¬
tween the World Wars when the old
world had been shaken but not destroyed by
the fall of the Austro-Hungarian monarchy.
It was Hitler who finally delivered the
death-blow. In his London exile, in 1940-41,
Stefan Zweig erected a lasting monument to
that period and to turn-of-the-century
Vienna in his memoir Die Welt von Gestern
(The World of Yesterday). He was himself an
embodiment of the bygone age that he so
matchlessly described.
Zweig, the son of a Jewish-Bohemian
textile manufacturer, was born in Vienna but
wrote most of his numerous biographies,
novellas and essays at his Salzburg villa. He
was attracted to Salzburg in part by its
baroque setting, but even more by its ideal
location as a jumping-off place for his exten¬
sive European travels. Here, in his "little
palace", he lived the story-book life of an
internationally famous author, receiving
visits from other leading European writers
such as Thomas Mann, Arthur Schnitzler,
H.G. Wells and James Joyce. Unlike most of
/*
I
his fellow authors, he did not have to live by
his pen. Yet his writing made him a wealthy
man. By the 1920s and 1930s his works had
been translated into almost forty languages.
A pacifist, Zweig was one of the most
prolific letter-writers of his age and spun
across Europe a web of correspondence that
included such figures as Romain Rolland,
Maxim Gorky and Rainer Maria Rilke. "I
felt I was living completely as a European,"
he wrote. "Borders were insignificant lines."
Looking back on his life, he admitted, "I stu¬
died philosophy. But my real studies began
only when I started travelling extensively
throughout Europe, America and India. My
inner education began through friendships
with some of the leading personalities of my
generation Verhaeren, Romain Rolland,
Freud and Rilke." His underlying pacifism
was based not least on this transcending of
international boundaries.
His rich and abundant output, which
includes biographies of Marie Antoinette,
Mary Stuart, Fouché, Erasmus and
Magellan, offers a tour d'horizon of Euro¬
pean culture. His most famous work is
Sternstunden der Menschheit (The Tide of
Fortune). In it he discussed certain "momen¬
tous occasions when a decision with lasting
consequences can be pinpointed to a single
date, a single hour." His profound know¬
ledge of the human soul and his ability to
recognize and portray the subtlest emotional
nuances clearly illustrated in his Schachno¬
velle (The Royal Game) led him to be
among the first to honour the founder of
psychoanalysis. In his essay "Sigmund
Freud" he exposed the nineteenth century as
an epoch of prudery.
A refugee from fascism, Zweig moved to
London in the 1930s and took British citi¬
zenship in 1940. In 1942 he moved to Brazil.
In exile he found new companionship with
his secretary, Lotte Altmann, who became
his second wife. Believing that his world was
lost forever and that Europe would be
plunged into eternal barbarism, he was
seized by despair. In a crisis of depression
and resignation, he committed suicide to¬
gether with his wife in Petropolis, a suburb
of Rio de Janeiro. He was sixty-one. In a
farewell letter he wrote: "Greetings to all my
friends. May they live to see the red sky of
morning, dawning after a long night. I am
too impatient and go before them." O
Gertraud Steiner, Austrian journalist, is
responsible for cultural information in her
country's Federal Chancellery. She has
published many articles and two books: Die
Heimat-macher (1987), a history of Austrian
cinema, and a study on the history of the
Marshall Plan in Austria, 25 Jahre ERP-Fonds
(1987).
73
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
Ziryab,
master of
Andalusian
music
by Mahmoud Guettât
74
"There never was a man of his profession,
either before or since, who was so unanimously
loved and admired. Even in the twilight years
of the kingdom of Granada, which fell in 1492,
poets were still finding in his glory a subject
for their songs."
THE man the historian al-Maqqari so
described in the Naß al-tib ("The
Perfumed Breath"), a celebrated lit¬
erary-historical compilation on the subject
of Muslim Spain, was Abu al-Hasan 'Ali ibn
Nan', known as Ziryab ("blackbird")
because of his dark skin, sweet tones, fluent
speech and pleasant character. Although we
have no record of the dates of either his birth
or death, the circumstances of his biography,
and in particular his passage from the Orient
to the Islamic West, suggest that he was born
about 787 and died in approximately 857.
Apprenticeship
in Baghdad
Ziryab was a fervent disciple of the cele¬
brated Ishaq al-Mawsili (767-850), the
uncontested master of the 'Udist' school of
music in Baghdad. He learned all he could
from the master without drawing attention
to himself, until the day came when Ishaq,
perceiving his talent, introduced him at the
court of Harun al-Rashid (786-809). The
? *J I Uli wivvt v
^y^ril^J
young singer made a great impression,
showing off an 'ud he had designed himself.
"Like many others I know how to sing," he
told the caliph, "but I also understand things
that other people don't. My art can only be
appreciated by a connoisseur such as your¬
self. If you will permit me, I shall sing you
something that no-one has ever heard
Then he disdainfully pushed aside
his master's lute, claiming that his own was
about a third lighter, even though it was
made of the same wood and was the same
size as a normal instrument. "The first two
strings are made of silk spun in cold water,"
he explained. "They are stretched tight, are
supple without being slack, and are stronger
than normal strings made from silk dam¬
pened in hot water before it is spun. The
third and fourth strings are made from the
gut of a lion's cub, which makes them melo¬
dious and gives them a clear, dense sonority.
They are harder-wearing and resist changes
in temperature better than strings made from
the intestines of other animals."
Then, with the caliph's permission,
Ziryab sang, to the accompaniment of his
special 'ud, an ode he had written glorifying
the Prince of the Faithful, who was duly
charmed, convinced that such a talent could
not fail to enhance the splendour of his
court. Ishaq, who had not suspected that the
haughty and insolent young musician har¬
boured such virtuosity, was less pleased.
"You have tricked me with your filthy dis¬
sembling," he shouted when they were alone
together again. "You were only out to do me
down in the eyes of the caliph! Now you
must choose: either you disappear, first
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
V UlUM
swearing that I shall never hear of you again,
in which case I shall give you the money you
need to go away; otherwise I won't answer
either for your possessions or your life."
From Kairouan
to Cordoba
Realizing that the odds against him were too
great, Ziryab decided to go into exile and
travelled first to Africa, where he entered the
service of the emir of Kairouan, Ziyadat
Allah I (816-837), the most illustrious ruler
of the Aghlabid dynasty, where he found
himself in the company of several other
renowned musicians. His reputation soon
grew, and his name was given to a bustling
district of the capital Al-hay-al-Ziryab
renowned for its artistic activity. The stay in
Kairouan, often underestimated in accounts
Moor and
Christian sing
together to their
lutes. Illustration
from Las Cantigas
de Santa Maria, a
book of poems
written by Alfonso
X, the Wise, king
of Castile and
León (13th
century).
of Ziryab's life, brought him wealth and
honour, until the day, sometime around the
year 821, when he was condemned to be
whipped and banished, after offending the
ruler with one of his songs.
Mansur al-Mughanni, an envoy of the
Umayyad emir al-Hakam I (796-822), wit¬
nessed the incident and invited Ziryab to
Córdoba. So the musician set off westward
again, crossing the Mediterranean and
disembarking at al-Jazira (Algeciras), only to
learn the unwelcome news that al-Hakam I
had died. He was preparing to set off on his
travels again when word reached him that
the dead ruler's successor, Abd al-Rahman
II (822-852), was as fond of music as his
father had been. The new emir received
Ziryab with the respect his great reputation
merited, and treated him with the greatest
consideration. Even before he had been
given a chance to demonstrate his talents,
Ziryab was granted a pension of 5,640
dinars, 300 measures of cereals and an estate
valued at 40,000 dinars. Ziryab wasted no
time in showing the sovereign that his lar¬
gesse had not been distributed in vain. His
incontestable musical abilities, along with his
fine manners, elegance and artistic tastes,
soon established him as one of the emir's
three favourites, along with sultan Tarub and
the poet Yahya al-Ghazal.
The emir's generosity towards Ziryab
attracted a great deal of attention in the
Muslim world, and a celebrated musician of
the Abbasid caliph of Baghdad, al-Mahdi,
complained to his master that he would end
up dying of hunger "while Ziryab, at the
court of the Umayyads of al-Andalus, had
30,000 dinars and a thousand slaves or
more". It was even rumoured that when the
treasury of al-Andalus jibbed at paying the
considerable sums allotted to Ziryab, "the
sultan made them up from his own privy
purse", thereby confirming his personal inti¬
macy with the singer.
Arbiter of taste
and fashion
Ziryab, whose reputation as a man of the
world spread throughout Muslim Spain,
quickly became the accepted arbiter of
fashion, taste and manners. He was respon¬
sible for various innovations, which are des¬
cribed in detail by al-Maqqari. Under his
influence, the people of al-Andalus altered
their domestic habits, the furnishing of their
homes and their cooking as well as their way
of dressing. The people of Córdoba, who
had been used to let their hair grow long and
separate it with a parting, now took to wear¬
ing it in a crown around their heads, follow¬
ing the style set by Ziryab. They learned to
dress seasonally, wearing light materials and
bright colours in spring, loose white gar¬
ments in summer, and cloaks and fur hats in
winter. Girls wore saffron-coloured dresses
and headscarfs with verses embroidered on
them. Ziryab even invented a kind of deodo¬
rant (al-martak) to replace the powdered
rose, basil and myrtle used until that time,
which had the disadvantage of leaving stains
on clothing though he also found a way of
removing these.
He invented new carpet designs, blan¬
kets that were softer than linen, and leather
tablecloths that efficiently protected wooden
surfaces and were also easy to wipe clean.
He took an interest in the way banquets
were organized and in table settings. He
advocated the use of fine glassware in place
of metal cups, and recommended that
flowers be arranged in gold and silver vases.
He radically changed culinary habits, intro¬
ducing many new and delicate foodstuffs, 75
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[
including asparagus (al-isfiraj) and the pas¬
tries known as naqaya', made of almond and
pistachio paste sprinkled with sugar and
coriander-flavoured water. The delicious zla-
biya, honeyed fritters that are popular in
North Africa to this day, even owe their
name to him: the word is a contraction of
ziryabiya.
A peerless musician
First and foremost, however, Ziryab was a
peerless musician who was universally
appreciated and admired. He had a prodi¬
gious memory, and knew more than ten
thousand songs (aghani) and their melodies
(alhan) by heart; furthermore, he knew how
to expound them as a teacher. As the
founder of the Andalusian musical tradition,
he carried on the work of the great classical
composers while also being an innovator
whose genius enabled him to combine the
art of an Ishaq and the science of an al-Kindi
(796-874).
In his teaching and through his pupils he
introduced reforms that profoundly affected
the art of his time. He continued to improve
the 'ud, adding a fifth string to the instru¬
ment and replacing the wooden plectrum
with an eagle's quill to obtain a richer sound
and a lighter touch.
As a singing instructor, he developed a
rational and progressive teaching method.
He worked step by step, always starting off
by testing a new pupil's voice. The candidate
was asked to sit up straight on a stool and
either to shout at the top of his voice Ya
hajjam ("Hey! Barber!") or else to sustain a
prolonged "aah" up and down the musical
scale. This test enabled him to judge the
power of the voice, to confirm that there was
nothing nasal about the tone and that the
singer had no breathing problems. If the
voice was perfect, he started teaching
without further ado. If it was not, he would
order the pupil to wrap a turban around his
stomach to compress the middle of his body
and facilitate correct voice projection. He
advised pupils who had difficulty opening
their mouths to the fullest extent to clench a
piece of wood three fingers wide between
their jaws for several nights running.
The lessons he gave ranged from the very
simple to the extremely complex. Poems
were recited to a tambourine accompani¬
ment, in an attempt to encourage apprecia¬
tion of different rhythms and especially the
place of accents. Pupils were introduced to
the rudiments of melody, before moving on
to the study of ornamentation, nuance and
the possibilities for improvisation that
constitute the charm of a work and the skill
of an interpretation.
Another of Ziryab 's innovations was
the development of the nawba, the perfor¬
mance of a suite of pieces composed in one
mode. "It is customary in Andalusia," al-
Maqqari wrote, "to start with a nashid
(recitative), then to continue with a basit
(full-throated song) and finish with muhar-
rakat and ahzaj (light, lively numbers), fol¬
lowing the rules laid down by Ziryab." One
characteristic of these songs is the primacy
of musical rhythm over poetic metre, giving
birth to new styles: an elaborate form of the
type of poem called the muwashshah and of
its popular version, the lyrical zajal, subdi-
This craftsman of Fez, Morocco, descends from a long line of famous lutemakers from Andalusia.
76
vided into stanzas (aqfal) that are them¬
selves composed of a variable number of
short lines (aghsan). Ziryab was thus the
architect of a veritable musical revolution
that shattered the rigid framework of the
old qasida poetry and opened the way for
new metrical combinations.
From Spanish lyrics to the
troubadours' songs
The musical tradition of the Islamic Orient
accorded to music mysterious properties
that were both magical and mystical, as well
as expressive and therapeutic powers linked
to its powerful effects on the human psyche.
Under Ziryab's influence, these conceptions,
which in the East were enmeshed in fruitless
speculation, acquired new vigour in the
Muslim West and came to constitute the very
foundation of the musical edifice. Twenty-
four imaginary nawba formed a symbolic
"tree of temperaments" (shajarat al-tubu),
each in its own tab' (mode). In addition,
close links were forged between music's
magical-religious origins and cosmology,
medicine, mathematics and ethics. The
strings of the 'ud were associated with
cosmic influences and the elements of
human physiology. In the direct line of mys¬
tical aspiration of the traditional Arab
school, the fifth string added by Ziryab to
the instrument's sonorous and living body
was described as "red, like blood" and
because of its central position was con¬
sidered to symbolize life and the soul.
The music Ziryab bequeathed to Anda¬
lusia profoundly influenced the music of
medieval Europe, both in theory for most
of the Arab musical treatises, of which some
250 were produced between the ninth and
fifteenth centuries, were studied if not pla¬
giarized in the great monasteries and in
practice, in the evolution of plainsong and
early Roman chant. It shaped important
aspects of the Spanish lyrical tradition, as
well as of the poetic and musical repertoire
of the Provençal troubadours. Under the
influence of Ziryab, several Arab instru¬
ments, including the 'ud and the rabab, came
to be widely used under their Arab names.
Ziryab's music had no need of a translator to
be understood, and it contributed more than
literature or philosophy to the extraordinary
influence of Andalusian civilization. O
1 The traditional school of Arab music, so called
because of the importance attached to its principal
instrument, the W, or short-necked lute.
Mahmoud Guettât, Tunisian musician and
musicologist, founded the Institut Supérieur de
Musique in Tunis and introduced musicology to
the syllabus of the Tunisian university system.
He has published many books and articles in
Arabic and in French, including La musique
classique du Maghreb (1980) and La tradition
musicale arabe (1986).
]]>
</page>
<page number="77">
<![CDATA[
One world
by Tom Krol
Above, a Chinese kite. The hobby of kite
flying, which probably originated in China,
spread rapidly throughout the world.
Aflash of colour rises swiftly into the
wind, dances softly, then comes to
rest as a meditation against a bright
blue sky. A tradition more than 2,000 years
old, the serene act of kite flying continues to
lift our spirits beyond the insistent gravity of
earth.
A universal symbol in art, literature and
folklore, the kite is an efficient and peaceful
aircraft. The earliest historic references date
to the fourth century BC, when Kungshu
Phan, a Chinese engineer, reportedly sent
aloft a "wooden bird". Accounts of kites are
also found in the annals of ancient Egypt and
Greece.
From Benjamin Franklin's experiments
with electricity to the Wright Brothers' first
flight, kites have played key roles in
scientific discovery and the study of weather.
But even for scientists, kite flying can repre¬
sent a way to relax and have fun. Alexander
Graham Bell, the inventor of the telephone,
designed a massive six-sided kite that could
carry a person into the air.
In the modern world, the venerable kite
is experiencing a renaissance that may carry
with it a new role as a symbol of global co¬
operation. The historic 1985 summit meeting
of Presidents Ronald Reagan of the United
States and Mikhail Gorbachev of the USSR
marked a significant step towards peace be¬
tween the super-powers. The spirit of that
meeting inspired American kite designer
Jane Parker-Ambrose to create a kite com¬
memorating this new promise of global har¬
mony. The flags of the US and the USSR are
joined on the face of the kite. Halley's
comet, which revisited the Earth in 1986 for
the first time in seventy-six years, is shown
as a portent of peace.
On a "people to people" visit to Moscow
in that year, Jane presented her kite, along
with a letter of friendship signed by some
300 kite flyers from the US, Canada, Japan
and the United Kingdom, to the Soviet
Women's Peace Committee. This gesture of
international goodwill gave birth to the idea
for One Sky, One World, an annual global
kite-fly held each year on the second Sunday
in October. A non-profit organization based 77
]]>
</page>
<page number="78">
<![CDATA[
in Denver, Colorado, its mission is to focus
the entire planet's attention on the need to
maintain peace and protect the environment.
'Painting
the sky' for peace
The first One Sky, One World kite-fly took
place in 1986, with more than 10,000 kites
and 40,000 participants at ninety locations in
fourteen countries. In just six years, the
event has grown to include more than
250,000 people in twenty-four countries. In
"bird" kites a few inches long, and "stun-
ters" with as many as 250 kites in train. They
appear as airborne dragons, centipedes,
hawks, bats and geometric shapes. Some are
rooted in centuries-old tradition, while
many incorporate high-tech design and
materials such as nylon, mylar, fibreglass and
carbon fibre. Kites have inspired colourful,
spinning wind socks and giant streamers in
the shapes of fish, cows, pigs and even chile
peppers.
Most likely originating in China, the kite
Right, kites and banners by the American
artist George Peters are displayed at the One
Sky, One World meeting in Denver, Colorado,
on 13 October 1991.
Below, a giant kite in Guatemala.
78
Tom Krol, of the United States, is a media
consultant and video producer with wide
experience in broadcast journalism. He
prepared the present article in collaboration
with Larry Ambrose.
October 1991, One Sky, One World events
were held in Moscow, Washington DC,
Bombay, Berlin, Sydney, Beijing and many
other major cities. Kite-flyers from Japan,
France, Colombia, Guam, Chile, England,
Hungary, Italy, The Netherlands, Scotland,
Spain, Hawaii, Alaska and many other US
locations joined in.
Jane Parker-Ambrose has travelled
around the world to promote her message.
In April 1991, Jane and a One Sky, One
World delegation visited the Weifang kite
festival in China, an annual event that draws
up to 30,000 people, and then went to Bei¬
jing's Tienanmen Square, where they flew
kites along with Chinese citizens.
The custom of "painting the sky" is
common to people around the globe. Like
their kites, flyers come in all shapes, sizes
and colours. The kites themselves display an
incredible diversity of design, flying
methods, colours and sizes. There are tiny
spread quickly throughout Asia, becoming a
sacred ceremonial object in some cultures.
Marco Polo wrote of man-carrying kites that
bore a passenger whose spirits were often
lifted beforehand by alcohol. A successful
flight indicated a prosperous outcome for a
. proposed sea voyage.
Japanese legend tells of an exiled samurai
who built a kite to carry his son Minamoto-
to-Tametomo from the island of Hachijo to
the Japanese mainland. Today, the kites of
Hachijo traditionally carry the likeness of
Tametomo. Many Japanese have become so
involved in kiting that they have been
labelled "tako kishi" or kite crazy.
In Guatemala, elaborate and colourful
patchwork kites are flown at cemeteries each
year to mark the "day of the dead". At day's
end, the Guatemalans burn their kites to
ashes in honour of their ancestors.
The highly manoeuvrable "fighter" kite,
developed in India, is now popular world-
]]>
</page>
<page number="79">
<![CDATA[
wide. In the "civilized" pursuit of kite
fighting, the object is to sever the line or
force down an opponent's kite.
The Malay kite, used in Malaysia, Indo¬
nesia and Java for centuries, was adapted in
the 1890s by the American photographer
William Eddy, who used it to carry his
cameras into the sky.
Kite technology began to accelerate in
the nineteenth century. In the 1870s, the
German engineer Otto Lilienthal studied the
shape of birds' wings in order to create a
manned glider. A few years later, the Austra¬
lian Lawrence Hargrave designed the highly
efficient three-dimensional box kite, which
soon led to the bi-wing aircraft of the Wright
brothers.
Francis Rogallo, an American aerospace
engineer, invented the first truly modern
kite, the delta-wing, in 1948. The delta is the
precursor of the hang-glider as well as the
most popular kite in use today, the stunt
kite. With two kite lines, and sometimes as
many as four, "stunters" are capable of pre¬
cise aerobatics. "Stacked" one behind the
other, they create a spectacular stream of
colour and speed.
Kiting's latest development is the para-
foil, invented by the late Domina C. Jalbert.
A wing-shaped aerofoil, it is now used
widely to make steerable parachutes that
allow for remarkable pin-point landings.
Kiting can be both simple and complex,
meditative or competitive. Spectators at
competitive events witness graceful and ela¬
borate air shows featuring synchronized
movements, aerobatics and music.
Attracted by the mixture of technology
and tradition, more and more people are
attending kite events and joining kite clubs.
New clubs and speciality stores are springing
up. Annual kite sales world-wide have
boomed to more than $216,000,000.
A One Sky, One World meeting held at Foligno,
Italy, in October 1989.
One Sky, One World
takes place each year on the
second Sunday in October.
For information about how to take
part, write to:
One Sky, One World,
Box 11149, Denver,
CO 80211, USA.
79
]]>
</page>
<page number="80">
<![CDATA[
JAZZ
80
Toots Thielemans with the
Shirley Horn Trio. For My Lady
Thielemans (harmonica, guitar,
whistle), Horn (piano, vocals),
Charles Abies (bass), Steve
Williams (drums).
CD Emarcy 510 133-2 Gitanes
Jazz
This is the second record
that Thielemansthe Belgian
master of the jazz
harmonica has made with
Shirley Horn, having
accompanied her on her last
disc. This time Horn repays
the compliment, limiting
herself to the unaccustomed
role of background pianist
except on "Someone to Watch
Over Me", the only vocal track,
in which her velvety voice
blends perfectly with
Thielemans' plaintive
instrumental. Thielemans
whistles to good effect on "I'm
Beginning to See the Light", in
which he also overdubs
himself on guitar. Horn, who
has long shown a feeling for
Brazilian rhythms, solos
economically and. inventively
on "Corcovado". On drums,
Steve Williams is effective and
precise, picking up all the
nuances of the music and the
changes of rhythm. This
beautiful, sometimes poignant
music loses something in the
transfer from the concert hall
to compact disc.
Donald "Duck" Harrison. Full
Circle
Harrison (alto sax, vocals),
Cyrus Chestnut (piano), Carl
Allen (drums), Dwayne Burno
(bass), Mark Whitfield (guitar).
CD Sweet Basil ALCR-64
Originally from New
Orleans, Harrison was
discovered a few years ago by
Roy Haynes during a New York
jam session, and after a spell
in Haynes's band worked with
Art Blakey. In Full Circle he
turns his hand to a mixed
bunch of original compositions
and standards in a warm,
classical style, with a Coltrane-
like version of "Nature Boy"
standing out. The musicians
accompanying him are young,
reliable and enthusiastic,
though they have yet to find
their own sounds. This is a
good record that brings the
mainstream tradition up to
date.
Bill Evans Live at Blue Note
Tokyo 2. The Gambler
Evans (tenor and soprano sax),
Victor Bailey (bass), Mitchel
Forman (keyboards and piano),
Richie Morales (drums).
CD Bellaphon 660.53-025
The Gambler offers
pleasant fusion jazz in the
spirit of Weather Report or the
Brecker Brothers, complete
with echoplex effects and
synthesizers. Evans not to
be confused with the pianist of
the same name, who died
some years ago is
technically a master of his
instrument. Forman, who has
worked with various groups
including Latin combos, shows
his capabilities as a soloist on
his own composition,
"Gorgeous", in a style close to
Keith Jarrett. There are no big
surprises here, just music to
relax to at home, preferably
late at night.
Bessie Smith. The Complete
Recordings Vol. 2
2 CDs Columbia 468767 2
This splendid re-issue of
tracks by the Empress of the
Blues features material
remastered from the original
78 r.p.m. recordings and
cleaned of all background
noise. If the first blues singers
to be recorded were men from
Mississippi, Texas and
Alabama such as Blind Lemon
Jefferson and Leadbelly,
Bessie Smith was one of the
earliest female stars, opening
the way for Mamie Smith and
later Alberta Hunter and Billie
Holliday. Bessie, who toured
with her musicians in her own
railway carriage to escape
racial discrimination, has lost
none of her majesty, her
powerful voice providing a kind
of female counterpart to Louis
Armstrong. These two compact
discs cover the greater part of
her career. Fletcher Henderson
plays on such tracks as "Work
House Blues" and "House
Rent Blues", while the young
Coleman Hawkins can be
heard on "Cake Walkln'
Babies" and "The Yellow Dog
Blues".
POPULAR MUSIC
Louise Feron
CD Virgin 30839
Feron, a pretty young rock
singer who hails from Le Havre
in France, sings about love in
all its forms in a very French
voice, less aggressive in its
tones than those of English
and American girl rockers. The
poetically-inclined texts
contrast with the tight
accompaniment typical of
rock.
Saliha. Unique
CD Virgin 30847
Saliha, who was born at
Bagneux in the Paris suburbs,
is one of the rare French solo
rap artists. Unlike most of her
European counterparts, whose
mechanically predictable
phrasing can be soporific, she
has an interesting sense of
rhythm, even if she lacks the
edge of American equivalents
like Salt 'n' Peppa or Queen
Latifah. She works in English
]]>
</page>
<page number="81">
<![CDATA[
as well as French, a language
whose less vigorous tones do
not easily lend themselves to
rap. Still, Saliha holds her own
with the help of the "fiery
temperament" referred to in
the title of one of the tracks.
As her opening song
proclaims, she knows how to
lay down "The Law" her law,
the law of rap.
Julian Lennon. Help Yourself
CD Virgin CDV 2668.
Julian Lennon's fourth
album, Help Yourself is acid
rock with an English accent,
despite the fact that it was
produced in Los Angeles. The
lyrics are sophisticated and
intellectual: in "Keep the
People Working", he sings:
"From the mines of Anatolia to
the isle of Mandalay/Along the
coast of sullen Africa, they're
queuing up to pay". Julian still
has his father's voice, and a
"feeling" similar to the
Beatles. Breeding will out.
Isabelle Leymarie
CLASSICAL
Anssi Karttunen
Karttunen (cello) plays
Hindemith, Merikanto,
Lindberg and Zimmermann
with the London Sinfonietta
conducted by Esa-Pekka
Salonen
CD Finlandia FACD 400.
Apart from the
Kammermusik no. 3, which
dates from 1925 and takes us
back to a bygone musical
context, the great Finnish
cellist Anssi Karttunen here
demonstrates his skills in
works from the second half of
the twentieth century. The
Konzertstuck by Aarre
Merikanto, Sibelius's
unfortunate rival who died in
1958, is particularly
impressive. Also featured is
Zona, a work by the young
Finnish composer Magnus
Lindberg, born in the year of
Merikanto's death. And there
is Zimmermann's extraordinary
Canto di Speranza, an
astonishingly concentrated
piece dating from 1957, when
the influence of Webern was
at its peak.
Clérambault. Cantates
Noémie Rime, Jean-Paul
Fouchécourt, Nicolas Rivenq,
and Les Ans Florissants,
conducted by William Christie
CD Harmonia Mundi HMC
301329
Straddling the seventeenth
and eighteenth centuries, the
work of Louis-Nicolas
Clérambault (1676-1749), a
contemporary of Rameau,
prolonged the musical
traditions of France's golden
age while subtly steering them
in the direction of baroque
refinement. Clérambault was a
famous organist, and the
change is most perceptible ¡n
his cantatas, a form of which
he was a master. La Muse de
l'Opéra (1716) explores the
complex relationship between
the cantata and opera, whilst
Orphée, performed at the
Concert: Spirituel in Paris in
1728, is quietly moving. Its
vocal flourishes and the
dialogue between voice and
flute almost seem to prefigure
Glück. Although it is now rarely
performed, Clérambault's work
is worth listening to, especially
when it is rendered, as here,
by artists familiar with his
style.
Philidor. Carmen Saculare
Ghylaine Raphanel, Sophie
Fournier, Donald Lltaker, Jean-
François Gardeil, the
Sagittarius vocal ensemble, La
Grande Ecurie and the
Chambre du Roy, conducted
by Jean-Claude Malgoire
CD Erato 2292-45609-2
Philidor was first and
foremost a famous chess¬
player, like the philosopher
Diderot, though music also ran
in the family. The Carmen
Slculare, a secular oratorio
drawn from works of the Latin
poet Horace, was presented at
Paris's annual Concert
Spirituel in 1780, two years
after Mozart had been invited
to perform, with not entirely
happy results. Philidor's music
in fact bears some
resemblance to the early
works of the Salzburg master.
But its majestic, even operatic
pretensions also prefigure the
vast pretensions of the music
of the French Revolution,
whose heroics declared an
affiliation to pagan Rome.
Berlioz reflects his influence,
as he does those of the
Revolutionary composers
Méhul and Gossec.
Berlioz. Mélodies
Montague, Robbin, Fournier,
Crook, Cachemaille, orchestre
de l'Opêïa de Lyon conducted
by John Eliot Gardiner -
CD ERATO 2292-45517-2
This disc is something of a
rarity, for it features some
little known material, including
the splendid Mort d'Orphée,
presented here in a synthesis
of the versions of 1842 and
1848. For the most part the
pieces are in the romantic
mode, touched here and there
by the Spanish influence that
was very much in fashion at
that time. The disc also
contains a version of the
incomparable Nuits d'Eté,
inspired by poems by
Théophile Gautier, that is
notable for the breadth of its
tessitura. Unfortunately, the
articulation of the singers is
sometimes stretched to the
limit, and this recording
cannot compare with the
sublime version by Régine
Crespin under Ernest
Ansermet's direction, recorded
by Decca in 1964 and now
available on compact disc with
works by Ravel, Debussy and
Poulenc.
Claude dayman 81
]]>
</page>
<page number="82">
<![CDATA[
Letters
to the editor
82
ANGKOR MUST BE
SAVED
As a former temporary
representative of the World
Health Organization in
Cambodia, where I was posted
for four years, I should like to
congratulate the Director-
General of Unesco on his
speech of 30 November last
year launching an international
appeal to save Angkor, as
reported in your Newsbriefs
column (April 1992).
Angkor is the apotheosis of
Khmer culture. The complex
includes not merely Angkor
Wat itself the most
celebrated temple in Asia and
the symbol of Cambodia but
also the charming Banteay
Srei, a jewel of classical
South-east Asian architecture,
Angkor Thorn and its
enigmatically smiling stone
heads, the imposing Giant's
Pathway and the splendid Ta
Prohm, lost in luxuriant jungle.
Angkor must be saved as
quickly as possible. . . .
France should be in the
forefront of the struggle. Let
us hope that thanks to Unesco,
the restoration of Angkor will
be taken in hand and brought
to a successful conclusion, as
at Borobudur.
Dr. Jacques Verdrager
Lyon (France)
BACK NUMBERS OF THE
COURIER WANTED
In a developing country like my
own, the Unesco Courier
provides access to information
that is otherwise
unobtainable. The magazine is
especially useful to those of
us working in education,
because it allows us to
expand our pupils' horizons
and provide them with
knowledge untainted by the
stereotypes that have long
reinforced intolerance and lack
of respect between cultures.
We should be pleased to
receive copies of the Courier
dating from before 1991,
especially (though not
exclusively) the Spanish-
language edition. We can
promise to make good use of
them, to the benefit of many
readers.
Claudio A. Vargas Arias
School of History and Geography
University of Costa Rica
San José (Costa Rica)
A MIRROR FOR Unesco
As Founder and President
Emeritus of the Unesco
Association of Colorado, I am
writing to commend you on
your issue entitled "Women
Speak Out on the
Environment" (March 1992).
It is so timely and exciting to
have such exceptional
coverage. I have already used
information from it for several
talks I have given recently.
The February issue,
"Apartheid The Beginning of
the End", is a fitting response
to those who continue abusing
human rights all over the
world. We are experiencing
some of it here. I plan to write
a letter to one of our daily
papers shortly and will use
some quotes from the editorial
by Federico Mayor, Director-
General of Unesco. The
chronology, "Unesco's First 45
Years", will be put in our
archives as well as those of
the Auraria library. It is
something we have needed for
a longtime.
Finally, the article on
Hampâté Bâ (January 1991)
impressed me deeply. Copies
will be shared with the Ford-
Ross Library and the Black
American West Museum. And I
love the colourful covers and
the photos which tell so much!
Genevieve N. Fiore,
Denver (U.S.A.)
SPEAKING UP FOR
TLEMCEN
I should like to draw your
attention to an unfortunate
error which appeared in the
box on page 30 of your issue
on al-Andalus (December
1991), and raised my
hackles as a citizen of
Tlemcen. You referred to
al-Maqqari, the author of the
Nafh al-Tib, as a "Tunisian
historian", when you should,
of course, have called him a
"Tlemcenian historian". It is a
pardonable mistake, and it
gives me the opportunity, in
the name of the Tlemcen
Ahbab Cheikh Larbi Ben Sari
Musical Association, to
congratulate you on the
quality of your articles and to
let you know how much
pleasure I have had in reading
them and getting others to do
likewise.
A. Ben Mansour
Tlemcen (Algeria)
WHAT ABOUT ASIA?
Asia is almost entirely missing
from the Courier, except for a
few words here and there
about "saving Angkor". Are
stones so important? An awful
lot of them must have been
lost that humanity will never
see again. It's people that I'm
interested in. Is this vast
continent so impenetrable
behind its ideological, political
and religious barriers? Could
you not try to establish closer
contact? It seems to me that
there must be many ways for
you to penetrate the human
maze. Do you use them all?
I accept the sincerity of your
efforts, which I follow with
great interest and sympathy.
Marie-Louise Lacoustille
Monpezat (France)
As a regular reader, you will
have noticed that we make a
point of opening our columns
to authors from all over the
world. In almost every issue
you will find an article or
illustrations that refer to Asia
or one of its many
civilizations. Even so, it is
always possible to do better.
Please believe that we try our
utmost to do so. Editor
]]>
</page>
<page number="83">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
45th YEAR
Published monthly in 33 languages and in Braille by Unesco. The
United Nations Educational. Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31. rue François Bonvin. 75C15 Pans. France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gi lian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Mallen
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel. 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin ;Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tei. 45.68.47.15), Mouna Chatta
Administrative Assistant: Prith Perera
Selection in Braille in English. French, Spanish and Korean:
Marie-Dominique Bourgeais (45 68 46 92)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner MerKli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidor.i (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vima: ¡Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Si va (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti : Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul;
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar es-Sa aam;
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofa)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens;
Sinhala: SJ. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Ghoti Khaweri (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddm (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
Galician: Xabier Senh Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (Tel. 45.68.45.89;
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45 68.45.65i,
Jocelyne Despouy, Aloha Diakité, Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo. Michel Ravassard, Michelle Robillard,
Mohamed Salan El Din, Sylvie Van Rijsewijk,
Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: G nette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Mall: Martial Amegee (Tel. 45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel : 45.68 45.65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year s issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
órete' of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier',
oius date of issue, and three voucier cooles are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be .eturned unless accompanied oy an international reply coupon
cove-mg postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
tne editors of the Oaiesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unescd Courier staff. The boundaries on maos
pub ished in the magazine do not imp'y official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. Trie Unesco Courier is
prod. iced in micoforn imicrofifm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 74700 Paris; 12) University Microfilms (Xerox),
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition,
Indian Head Inc., Ill West 40th Street. New York. U.S.A.; (4) Bell
one Howell Co., Old Mansfield Roac, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE [Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - JUILlET/AOÚT 1992
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N ' 71842 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Pnotocomposition: Le Courrier de ¡'Unesco.
Pnctogravure-impression: Maury-lmphmeur S.A..
Z.I., route d'Etampes. 45330 Malesherbes.
ISSN 0304-3118 N° 7/8-1992-0PI-92-506 A
Tnls issue comp'ises 84 pages anc a 4 page insert between pages
34-35 and 50-51.
Theme of the next issue
9
(September 1992):
9
9
Teachers, guides and mentors down the ages
Also featuring
an interview with the Argentine musician and poet
Atahualpa Yupanqui
Acknowledgements
Cover, page 3: © Galerie Castillo, Paris. Back cover: © Pat Horner, Paris. Page 2: © Henry Christiaën,
Grenoble. Pages 4-5: Bibal © Rapho, Paris. Page 6: Chris Chareton © Magnum, Paris. Page 7: © A.
Fahdcl Coll., Paris. Page 8: © Fotogram-Stone, Paris. Pages 10-11: Bapier © Artephot, Paris. Page 12: ©
Aniece J. Novak, United States. Page 13: Martine Franck © Magnum, Paris. Page 14: © Naresn Singh,
Paris. Pages 16-17: ©J-L Charmet, Paris. Page 18: Olivier Pasquicr © Le Bar Floréal, Paris. Page 19:
Isabelle Chanel © Hélène Mugot. Page 20: © J-L Charmet, Paris, Musée de l'Histoire vivante,
Montreuil, France. Page 21: © Marc Pio Maximilien Salvelli. Page 22: Elliott Erwin © Magnum, Paris.
Page 24: Peter Laurie © Paul Klee Stiftung, Kunstmuseum, Bern, 1992 VG Bild Kunst, Bonn. SPADEM,
Paris. Pages 25, 54, 55: © Dapper Foundation, Paris. Pages 26-27: © Rheinisches Bildarchiv, Cologne,
Ludwig Museum. Pages 28-29: Claude Gaspari © FDAC Conseil Général du Val de Marne, France.
Page 30: © Galerie Antoinette Jean, Paris. Page 31: © Y. Gellie/Odissey, Paris. Page 32: © R.M.N.,
Louvre Museum, Paris. Page 33: D. Ponsard © Musée de l'Homme, Paris. Page 34: © R.M.N., Musée
des Arts Africains et Océaniens, Paris. Pages 35, 40: © M. and A. Kirtley/ANA, Paris. Pages 36 (above),
46: © Coral Cay Conservation, London. Page 36 (below): UNDP-Ruth Massev. Page 37 (above): ©
Freeman/ANA, Paris. Page 37 (below): © N. Rakhmanov/ANA, Paris. Pages 38-39: Gilbert Gayrard ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 39 (below): C. Monteath/Auscape IN © Explorer, Paris. Page 41: © Luc and Lala
Joubcrt, Galerie Jeanne Bücher, Paris, All Rights Reserved. Page 42: UNESCO-Sinety. Page 43: © T.
Stringer/ANA, Paris. Pages 44-45: Alain Soldeville © ANA, Paris. Pages 47, 51: © ABCD, Paris. Page
48: © Musée Russe/MI/Le Bar Floréal, Paris. Page 49: © Mustafayev Art Museum, Baku. Page 50: All
Rights Reserved. Page 52: Jean Mazenod © Citadelles et Mazenod, Paris. Page 53: Naresh Singh © Blaise
Simon, Saint-Prix Coll., Martinique. Pages 56-57: © Musée National d'Art Moderne, SPADEM, Paris.
Pages 58, 73: © Roger-Viollet, Paris. Pages 59 (right), 60, 61 (left): © J-L Charmet, Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris. Page 59 (left): © Dagli Orti, Paris, Egyptian Museum, Turin. Page 61 (right): Louis
Yves Loira © Explorer, Paris, Torre de Tombe, Lisbon. Page 62: Toni Schneiders © Artephot, Paris. Page
63: Lavaud © Artephot, Musée Guimet, Paris. Pages 64-65: © Galerie Lise et Henri de Menthon, Paris.
Page 66: © Artephot/Nimatallah, Kunsthistorisches Museum, Vienna. Page 69: UNESCO-Dominique
Roger. Page 70: Marc Paygnard © Fondation Claude Nicolas Ledoux, Arc-et-Senans. Page 71: ©
Fondation Claude Nicolas Ledoux, Arc-et-Senans. Page 72: UNKSCO-F. Kronenbergcr. Pages 74-75:
Oronoz © Artephot, Paris. Page 76: © Roland and Sabrina Michaud, Paris. Page 77: Lavma Yann ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 78 (left): Wheeler © Rapho, Paris. Page 78 (right): © Leo C. Huelsmann. Page 79:
© One Sky, One World, Denver. Page 80, 81: All Rights Reserved.
]]>
</page>
<page number="84">
<![CDATA[
{
*&
rSS.
/
i**
yv
*vi
'."
1
ö
«
s>.*
]]>
</page>
</document>
