<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="095106eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
TheI JNESC
COUR1E
OCTOBER 1991
M 1205 9310 -22.00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send
us photographs to be
considered for publication in
this feature. Your photo
should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
HEAD OF IAO
1989,
construction in wrought
iron on a stone base
(57 x 20 x 28 cm)
by Ronaldo Pereira Rego
Rego is a Brazilian
painter, engraver and
sculptor whose work is
influenced by Umbanda,
a syncretic Afro-Brazilian
religion in which the
forces of nature are
worshipped. Rego sees
profound resemblances
between the divinities of
Umbanda and those of
other religions, and has
been inspired by these
unexpected analogies to
make constructions which
he calls mocans
(talismans). Shown here
is a head of laô, a
priestess of the
Umbanda goddess of air,
storms and flashes of
lightning, whom Rego
connects with
St. Barbara, a Christian
saint invoked in
thunderstorms, and with
Shu, the ancient Egyptian
god of air and light.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 INTERVIEW WH
James D. Watson
Contents
OCTOBER 1093
TINE TO
DISARM
8 Editorial
by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
Cover:
Beirut (Lebanon).
Ï UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
Ï UNESCO IN ACTION
ARCHIVES
Goethe« a mind for the
universal
by Thomas Mann, Georges Opresco and
Paul Valéry
ï UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
Portobelo, a bridge
between two oceans
by ¡osé Serro-Vega
00 RECENT RECORDS
by Isabelle Leymarie
00 BOOKS OF THE WORLD
by Calum Wise
9 Making disarmament work
by Dominique David
I 2 Wanted: a new philosophy
by Jean Klein
1 6 Europe after the Cold War
by Andrei Zagorski
1 9 An appeal for non-violence
by Federico Mayor
20 Investing in peace
by Jacques Fontanel
3 I The business of war
by Christophe Carle
35 The bomb or peace
byjasjit Singh
15
Greenwatch
41
COMMENTARY
by Federico Mayor
39 Glossary
Special consultant
for this issue:
Dominique David
Unesco
courier
46th year Published monthly
in 32 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements ot governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, / 6 NOVEMBER / 945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
James D. Watson
talks to
Serafín García Ibáñez
The American geneticist and biochemist
James Dewey Watson is one of the pioneers of research
into molecular biology. Keenly interested in
crystallography, his investigation of ribonucleic acid led
him to tackle the mystery of DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid),
whose double helix structure he unraveled, with Francis
Crick, in 1953. For this major scientific discovery of the
twentieth century James Watson, Francis Crick
and Maurice Wilkins were awarded the 1962 Nobel Prize
for Physiology or Medicine. In this interview with the
Unesco Courier, James Watson reveals his hopes and
fears for the future of research, and talks of the
complex and important question of bioethics. His
published works include Molecular Biology of the Gene
(1965), and The Double Helix (1968).
serafIn garcía ibáñez
is ;i journalist with
U'.e sco's Office of Public Information.
The DNA discovery was one ofthe cru¬
cial scientific breakthroughs of the post¬
war years, and it also made you and your
colleague Francis Crick famous world¬
wide. . . .
DNA, the molecule, made me famous. I
didn't make the molecule famous. It's the
most important molecule of all in the sense
that it carries our genetic instructions. The
fact that the answer was so simple partly
explains why we became so famous but
that was because the molecule was simple,
not because we had found a simple way of
interpreting it to people outside. So we
became famous because DNA had such a
likeable structure.
What led you into biology in the first
place?
I went into biology because I was inter¬
ested in what life was. Where did we come
from? Initially I was very excited by what
I had learned about Charles Darwin and
the theory of evolution, that we weren't
created as it was stated in the Bible and
there was no Ark or anything like that.
Instead there were several billion years of
evolution. But how did the whole thing
start? What was really the basis of the con¬
tinuity between one organism and another?
Why do some animals grow up to be cats
and some grow up to be human beings?
And the answer turned out to lie in our
genes. It's instructions which are carried in
our genes which make us a human being or
a bacterium or a monkey. And so if the
real uniqueness of a living form lies in the
set of instructions that is the genes, I
wanted to know what the gene was.
Initially I had thought I was going to be
a naturalist, with particular interest in
birds I had grown up on the south side of
Chicago not too far from the steel mills, so
my aim was not to live in a city but to
escape into nature and to study nature.
But then I got interested in what the gene
was, so I didn't go outside, I stayed inside,
in my little laboratory, at least to start with.
What was the immediate significance of
the discovery of DNA? What prospects
did it open up?
Its significance was that, since it was the'
genetic molecule, it was the most important
of all molecules inside cells. If you're asking
what did we plan to do with it, initially we
didn't know. We had to find out how it
worked. Many, many thousands of people
are now involved in that search. When we
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
found the structure, there were only a few
people interested in DNA. Now there are
hundreds of thousands.
Picasso once said, "I do not seek, Ifind".
Is that a statementyou could apply to your
own career? In other words, is scientific dis¬
covery in your experience the result of
carefulplanning, or does it have more to do
with luck?
I think in most cases it's a product of
both. You generally don't find gold unless
you're looking for it. You have to have an
objective. Whether you then reach it partly
depends on how many other people are
out there trying to prospect for gold.
Luckily, when we were there, almost no-
one else was prospecting. In fact there were
only three groups in the world trying to
find the gold that DNA turned out to be.
And we found it first.
I'd like to ask a question about the tech¬
nical background to discovery. Research
nowadays has extraordinary means at its
disposal laboratories, powerful com¬
puters, and so on. As a result, only a handful
of countries those that can afford these
tools are in a position to make scientific
discoveries. Does that fact alarm you? Is
there any way ofbalancing out the way in
which the fruits ofdiscovery are shared?
Depending on how expensive the
research is, it's going to be limited to those
people who can afford it. You cannot
imagine countries in central Africa having
the means to build super-colliders in the
form that they exist, say, at CERN, the
European Organization for Nuclear
Research. It takes a great deal of wealth to
do that.
On the other hand, I think it's very
important that the knowledge that comes
from discovery should be spread. In the old
days we used to say the most important
thing for UNESCO to do was to give books
out to people, so they could read and find
out what was up. Now of course there are
other forms of media; information goes
out on television and the radio and of
course on computers.
A free society the best societies
have a rapid flow of information. I think
that's probably the most important thing
that even those who don't have the best
teachers and are not in the best universities
can still get at the facts.
I was very privileged with my educa¬
tion. I went to one of the best universities
in the world, I had a very good teacher, so
I was told what was important, and if I
hadn't gone to that school, the name
Watson would not be well known. Today
I think it's possible to make high-quality
education much more widely available
through, particularly, TV and cable or satel¬
lite. There's really no reason why, in the
future, people in relatively primitive envi¬
ronments shouldn't be exposed to the very
best teaching, if people have the interest to
make it so. So if I had to say the most
important thing UNESCO could do now, I
think it would be getting information out to
people, providing them with information.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
You can't make them read and you can't
make them listen, but you can give them
that possibility.
In my own case, my family lived close
to a public library and my father used to
walk to the library with me once a week
when I was young. We got books out. The
knowledge was available. I didn't come
from a wealthy family, but there was a
library. It was the library that first opened
your eyes to worlds beyond your own
limited one.
Most people are born without great
aspirations, and they don't think they can
do great things. You've got to let them see
that there are still great things to be done,
and they can be done by many people. It's
not only privileged people who can do
things. In fact, I'm surprised how often
the people on top make mistakes, even
though they have all the advantages. So
it's opportunity that matters. I think you
really have to provide the opportunity of
a high-quality education. Other people
might point out you have to give people
health, because if they're sick they can't
learn. So let's say that health and education
are the most important things to give
people in underdeveloped regions.
The human genomeproject is seeking to
decode our genetic heritage, our genetic
book. Can you tell us about this greatpro¬
ject? What stage has it reached?
We've just started. But we have the tech¬
nical means to finish the project within
the next fifteen to twenty-five years. You
have to know when to say you're finished:
when you've got 90 per cent of the infor¬
mation, or 95 per cent or 98. It's slightly
arbitrary. We're never going to get 100 per
cent, because there's just so much infor
mation there. But we're going to know
most of it.
Finding a few new ways to reduce the
costs of the project would certainly help.
Even so, there's a realistic chance of fin¬
ishing it for the cost of three trips of the
Space Shuttle. I think if people were asked,
do you want the human genome or do you
want three trips from the Space Shuttle,
almost everyone would say that they'd
rather have the human genome. But we've
got the Space Shuttle!
You 'd agree that the human genome is a
bigproject in every way. It's "big science"
like, in thepast, nuclearpower. . . .
But it's not big science in the way that
the super-colliders are in the world of
physics. The super-collider in Texas might
take half the money for physics in the
United States. That's a lot. But the human
genome project would probably never take
more than two per cent of the money for
biomedical research. It doesn't have that
all-or-nothing element. There are many
physicists who feel, "Well, if we build this
machine, I'm out of a job because I'm not
part of that machine." But we're not going
to put any people out of work.
Despite appearances, the project really
isn't that big. It's really a sort of bubble, a
bubble on the surface. But I think it's prob¬
ably the most important bubble that exists
in biomedical research now, because it is so
important to the understanding of dis¬
eases.
Do you think that some scientists con¬
ceal, even ifonly for a little while, some of
their knowledge?
Oh, I think people are always going to
conceal, and I don't think you should get
too upset about it. If someone is
prospecting for gold and thinks he sees a
little bit of it, he wants to be sure before he
gets a thousand people in the same stream.
I think the question is how fast the infor¬
mation is released. You need fast publica¬
tion, and you have to have a fairly honest
system whereby the people who make the
discoveries get the credit for them.
Having competition is good. I would
hate to have only one team out there trying
to find the gene that, say, predisposes many
women to breast cancer. I'd rather have
quite a few, Each wants to make the dis¬
covery, not only because it's important sci¬
entifically but, well, if they make the dis¬
covery maybe they can develop a
diagnostic test. Then they might become
not only scientifically famous but might
also make some money, might be able to
buy a better car. That's a regular human
emotion, and I don't think we should try
and change it.
I think what you need to have are rules
by which those who make discoveries get
rewarded. We tend to find it's a pretty
good rule that people will exchange
information quite freely except when they
feel they're very close to a discovery. As
long as they think the discovery is probably
not going to be made tomorrow, then
they'll say "This is what I think". If they
think it's going to be made the next day,
they're not going to tell someone a fact
that would let them make it first. I think
that's just a fact of life. Otherwise, it would
be like playing tennis and not wanting to
win.
As to the general question, do we on
the whole exchange information fairly fast,
the answer is "Yes". And the chief reason
why is that it's much more fun to get
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
James Watson and Francis Crick (seated in
foreground) and other Nobel prizewinners at
Unesco's Paris Headquarters, where they
took part in a symposium entitled "From the
double helix to the human genome: 40 years
of molecular genetics" (21-23 April 1993).
someone excited about what you're doing.
If you just keep everything to yourself,
it's like having a very fine painting and not
showing it to anyone. You get pleasure in
being able to show nice things to other
people. And of course, I got a lot of plea¬
sure from being able to tell people about
the double helix.
What is your opinion on thepatenting of
discoveries in human genetics?
I think it's pretty much the custom that
if you find something useful say, you've
discovered a gene that people didn't know
about yet which would let you make an
important drug then that's going to be
patented. It's happened already. It fits in
with the way industry operates in the
world. If you make a discovery, you're
rewarded.
The controversy was not about
whether you could patent something
important. It was that you could patent
something before you understood what it
did. I strongly opposed the decision of the
National Institutes of Health to patent
DNA irrespective of whether the patenter
understood what it did or not. I had diffi¬
culties with the director of NIH and I was
asked to give up my job, because I thought
that the government's policy was irre¬
sponsible, to industry as well as to
everyone. It was just silly. Everyone I knew
agreed with me, so it wasn't as if there was
much controversy in the scientific world.
In fact there was no controversy we all
thought it was stupid. But it was done.
/s there any reason to feel afraid of the
uses to which genetics coidd beput?
Yes, there certainly is. I think we have to
develop laws so that genetic knowledge is
confidential. I wouldn't want anyone
having the right to look at my DNA. And
no-one should have to show their DNA
before they're employed.
There are going to be difficult situa¬
tions. If you know there's a genetic disease
in your family, do you have an obligation
to tell someone you might marry? That
problem already exists; people have kept
quiet when there was "madness" in the
family. You're going to have cases where
ethical behaviour would compel you to
reveal these things.
On the other hand, at the level of
employers I think we're going to have to
have laws. Just like with medical records.
I don't think someone's medical record
should be in the public domain. It gets
very difficult now that we're asking politi¬
cians to show their medical records. I think
that's a bad idea, and similarly I don't think
you should demand that political candi¬
dates have a genetic examination. And I
think it would be pretty dangerous if you
were expected to have a genetic examina¬
tion when you were married. I think we're
going to learn from experience, but my
own personal prejudice is that we should
only reveal when it's absolutely necessary.
What ethical code, whatprecautions or
laws could ensure that knowledge of the
human genome is used in a human way?
I don't think laws per se can do this. I
think you've also got to look to cultural
traditions. I mean, is it a failure of law that
is responsible for what's happening in
Bosnia now? It's what children learn in
their families, what they learn in their
schools, what examples they get from their
political leaders, that count.
All knowledge in some form or other
can have bad consequences. Personally I'm
against too many laws, because I think
they can be used to restrict activities. On
the other hand, I think it's pretty clear that
people are going to be very afraid of this
genetic information, and will possibly try
and stop the information being gathered
unless they feel they're protected against
real misuse of this knowledge.
When I became director at the National
Institutes of Health, I made an arbitrary
decision that we'd spend three per cent of
the available money on ethics. By the time
I left we were spending five per cent. I
think if I was still there the figure would be
going up, because this really is a very com¬
plicated issue.
Are there any otherpassions in your life
besides biology?
As I run an institution, I like to build
architecturally distinguished buildings. I
have a touch of megalomania. I like to
make the world more beautiful.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
EDITORIAL
/%ITER being for so long a Utopian dream, has disarmament now
become a practical proposition?
Wc remember how, some fifteen years ago, UNESCO invited Nobel
Peace Prize winner Lord Noel-Baker to a symposium at which one of his
fellow-participants was another Nobel Peace laureate, Sean MacBride. By
then over eighty, his eyesight failing, Lord Noel-Baker spoke without notes.
His voice was clear, his turns of phrase elegant, his reasoning firm, consistent
and irrefutable. He took his listeners back to the time of David Lloyd
George, whom he had known well and to whom, in the aftermath of the
First World War, he had already pressed the case for transferring the mas¬
sive resources invested in arms research and production to education,
health and other forms of welfare. Of course, such reasoning became
even more relevant and urgent after the Second World War, when East and
West spent colossal amounts of money to keep up with each other in the
arms race.
What was so moving about Lord Noel-Baker's speech that we still
remember it vividly many years later? Perhaps it was the contrast between
the physical signs of the orator's age and the subtlety, eloquence and
undimmed intellectual fire with which he spoke. Perhaps too it was the gap,
which suddenly seemed intolerable, between the dream of a world without
weapons and the absurd reality of an accelerating, seemingly unending arms
race.
Today the bipolar world is a thing of the past, and the balance of
terror can no longer serve as a pretext for a gadarene rush to the brink of
the abyss. Does this mean that humanity will start to prefer negotiation to
war? Can we expect to see nations making or buying fewer bombers and
building more schools and hospitals?
In exploring some aspects of this question, the present issue of the
UNESCO Courier reveals at the outset its complexity and its paradoxes.
While many moral, political and socio-economic arguments now plead in
favour of a "disarmament race", the context of the post-Cold War period
is also bringing to light contradictions, constraints and habits that will not
vanish overnight just because America and Russia are no longer clashing
on the ideological battlefield.
New ideas about disarmament are starting to take shape, but at the same
time new trends toward rearmament are emerging. From the following
pages it can be seen that this contradictory two-way movement reflects a
much older conflict between a mentality based on distrust, fear and the cult
of strength rather than the culture of law and a revolutionary state of mind
that looks forward to the challenge of a peaceful future in which freedom
and justice will be possible for all.
Fifty trillion watts of
electricity were produced by
the Saturn machine (above)
during tests to simulate
space attacks by radiation-
producing weapons at a
Strategic Defense Initiative
("Star Wars") test site at
Sandia (United States).
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Making disarmament work
by Dominique David
What can be done
to reduce swollen
arms budgets?
THE arguments in favour of disarmament
have always been based on three main
assumptions: that a) it is immoral to accu¬
mulate stocks of weapons; b) this build-up is a
threat to peace, and c) the economic cost is
reflected in artificial or misdirected development.
The moral argument has always been put for¬
ward strongly against chemical weapons and,
after Hiroshima and Nagasaki, also against
nuclear weapons. The industrial production of
arms has permitted long-drawn-out wars and
enabled unprecedented violence to be unleashed.
The cost of modern weaponry is hard to sustain
and has literally devastated the economies of
some countries.
However, these simple facts have not sufficed
to win full acceptance for the concept of general
disarmament. That idea was widely endorsed in the
1950s. It gave way in the 1960s to the more real¬
istic, but at the same time more limited, notion of
arms control. The major nuclear powers negoti¬
ated to reach agreement on certain rules of coex¬
istence and on the development of their respective
arsenals. The aim was no longer to disarm or even
to freeze the growth of arms stockpiles, but to
impose a framework on that growth in areas where
the powers were willing to engage in discussions
with each other. At no time did the American
and Soviet stockpiles of nuclear weapons grow
more rapidly than during the Strategic Arms Lim¬
itation Talks (SALT) in the 1970s.
The changes which took place in the late 1980s,
especially in the former USSR., enabled real agree¬
ments on the withdrawal and destruction of
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
IO
What justification
can there be for
the image of rich
countries which
believe nuclear
weapons are good
for themselves but
unacceptable for
others?
weapons to be negotiated and concluded. How¬
ever, the optimism soon faded. The 1987 US-
Soviet Treaty on the Elimination of Interme¬
diate-Range and Shorter-Range Missiles, the 1990
Treaty on Conventional Armed Forces in Europe
(CFE) and the 1991 START 1 Treaty1 on strategic
missiles only concerned limited quantities of
weaponry. Moreover, the application of these
treaties is fraught with uncertainty following the
break-up of the Eastern bloc. Last but not least,
the vast area of the South is not covered by any
global or regional disarmament process.
POLITICAL OBSTACLES
Hopes of disarmament are thwarted by countless
difficulties and objections, particularly of apolit¬
ical nature. The creation of armed forces and
industries to guarantee self-sufficiency in the pro¬
curement of military hardware and the adaptation
of these resources to technical progress, are priv¬
ileges of national independence. The period of
decolonization which began at the end of the
Second World War naturally led to considerable
growth in conventional arsenals belonging to the
new sovereign states. Agreements encompassing
the Third World might be viewed by some of
these countries as intolerable limitations on their
sovereignty. How can these countries be pre¬
vented from thinking that the Western nations
only discover the dangers of weaponry when they
have no prospect of effecting new sales? What
justification can there be for the image of rich
countries which believe nuclear weapons are good
for themselves, but unacceptable for others?
Moreover, translating the concept of disar¬
mament into law is a very complicated business.
Treaties leading to a general ban on weapons are
very difficult to draw up and even more difficult
to implement and enforce. Regional agreements
are more effective but presuppose the settlement
of existing conflicts and the opening of a sincere
political dialogue between the countries of a par¬
ticular region.
In Europe, one of the main obstacles to the
disarmament process at present resides in the
disappearance of the states that were to nego¬
tiate and apply these accords. The break-up of the
Warsaw Treaty Organization (WTO), the frag¬
mentation of the former USSR and the weakening
of certain countries, illustrate the scale of the
problems to be solved. What is more, no one
can predict what the situation will be in a few
years' time. To date, only one of the agreements
negotiated in recent years has been put into effect.
Despite the rapidity of political change in Europe,
the arms stockpiles there today are not much
different from those of a decade or so ago.
SOCIO-ECONOMIC HURDLES
In the past fifteen years, some Third World coun¬
tries have made a breakthrough into the arms
trade. Arms exports have now become an impor¬
tant sector of their economy. The proliferation of
local conflicts has broadened some markets, in
particular the market for light weapons requiring
medium level technology. The new exporting
countries are well placed to supply these markets.
The saturation of some traditional markets of the
Western countries therefore does not imply that a
global reduction has already taken place in world¬
wide arms production and in the arms trade or
even that such a reduction is now under way.
In Europe, countries like Russia and the former
Czechoslovakia soon realized that economic and
social considerations simply made it impossible for
them to close down their arms production facili¬
ties in Russia, this is the only sector of the
economy that seems able to remain self-financing
in convertible currency hence the sale of arms by
some countries of the former Warsaw Treaty on
the markets of the South at knockdown prices.
This is the key problem because it involves the rad¬
ical conversion of an economy structured around
military production. This trend seems impossible
to reverse in the short term.
DOMINIQUE DAVID,
of France, holds a post of
special responsibility under
the director of France's
Institute of International
Relations (IFRI), and is a
professor at the Saint-Cyr
Special Military School. He
is the author of Conflits,
puissances et stratégies en
Europe (Conflicts, Powers
and Strategies in Europe),
Brussels, 1992.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
In the countries of the North, the arms
industry is often a guarantee of their presence in
the race to develop high technology. The Strategic
Defense Initiative (the famous "Star Wars")
launched by the Reagan administration in 1983
was a striking example of this phenomenon. The
will to disarm, indissociable from a reduction of
exports, is therefore obstructed by the need to
safeguard systems of high value research which
cannot readily be transferred or converted to
other sectors. Some observers even fear that
stockpiling in quantitative terms may be replaced
by technological sophistication, which would of
course be a way of circumventing the very con¬
cept of disarmament.
RISKS AND OPPORTUNITIES
Although progress towards a world with smaller
arms stockpiles is politically, economically and
technically hard to achieve, there can be no doubt
that it is a strategic imperative. First of all, no the¬
oretical definition of an optimum quantity of arms
can be adduced. Neither the "militarist" theory
"the more weapons there arc, the safer things arc",
nor the "pacifist" theory, "the less weapons there
arc, the safer things are" holds water. Specific
cases must be examined. But the world situation
today gives cause for permanent anxiety.
In the North, the stocks of American and cx-
Sovict nuclear arms no longer reflect any logic of
strategic conflict. Although these weapons were
strictly controlled by the political powers of yes¬
terday and arc still under relatively firm control
today, we can have no certainty about the future.
The hypothesis of a rapid deterioration of the sit¬
uation also applies to conventional weapons. The
European arsenals are over-endowed: are they
now destined to be spread still more widely, to
follow the fragmentation of communities and so
nourish interminable conflicts? After escaping
from the gravitational pull which used to be
exerted on them by the East-West conflictual
system that has ceased to exist, these weapons
may well now be used in local conflicts or escape
beyond the frontiers of Europe to regions which
arc already overarmed.
In the South, the concept of proliferation is
often perceived as an idea of the North: in other
words, arms proliferation is seen as beginning
where its control by the rich countries ends. Be
that as it may, the quantities of weaponry and the
factors which make for destabilization arc
increasing in many places throughout the world.
In the aftermath of the Gulf War, technologies
whose effectiveness was demonstrated in this
theatre have been marketed widely. The great
post-Soviet sell-off has resulted in the rapid
transfer of vast amounts of weaponry. What is
more, these traditional suppliers have been joined
by many Third World manufacturers. Supply is
thus increasing, but so too is demand. Some latent
conflicts which had hitherto been held in check
by the Moscow-Washington relationship arc
now able to break out freely.
Even if it docs not at present reflect the true
situation, the image of a North united in
upholding its wealth and military might (an image
Details from War (1955,
opposite page) and Peace
(1956, above), two murals
by the Brazilian artist
Candido Portinari. They
adorn the delegates' lobby
of the General Assembly
building at United Nations
Headquarters in New York.
1. Strategic Arms Reduction
T.ilks (see glossary on page 39)
to which the Gulf War lent credibility) could
encourage some countries of the South to acquire
weapons in the face of what they perceive as at
best a system of exclusion and at worst a threat.
Unfortunately, this conjunction of factors seems
to point at one and the same time to a prolifera¬
tion of conflicts and to an increase in their level
of technological sophistication.
REGIONAL NEGOTIATIONS AND
AGREEMENTS
Disarmament is less than ever a spontaneous
process. In addition to the traditional economic
arguments after all, capital gains from arms
exports can never be anything other than tempo¬
rary and the moral and political arguments, there
are now pressing strategic and security consider¬
ations. The time has come for a global reduction of
stocks and the regulation of weapons transfers.
But a combination of many factors is needed
to bring about the success of bilateral or multi¬
lateral negotiations and the implementation of the
resulting treaties. The most important of these fac¬
tors, such as adequate political cohesion, do not
always exist today to a sufficient degree for pro¬
nouncements to be made about the future with
any certainty. Moreover, disarmament is not a
meaningful concept in isolation: it is the reflection
and the product of a thaw in relations and of
political trust. Conversely, arms stockpiling is
the expression of tension and closed attitudes.
Such attitudes are particularly redoubtable today.
The changes that have taken place in the past
five years are both an opportunity and a threat. Are
political leaders sufficiently aware of these risks to
place the need for disarmament in the forefront of
their preoccupations? If they are not, loose cannon
may soon pose a serious threat to our future. I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Wanted: a new philosophy
by Jean Klein
Despite all the
progress that has
been made, the
principle of
deterrence still
carries too much
weight in current
disarmament
negotiations
12
JEAN KLEIN,
of France, is a research
director at his country's
National Centre for Scientific
Research and professor of
law at the University of Paris
1. The author of many
articles in specialized
journals, he is attached to
France's Institute of
International Relations
(IFRI) where he is currently
studying problems of
international security and
disarmament.
SINCE the end of the Second World War,
the question of disarmament has been
permanently on the agenda of the United
Nations General Assembly, and the major mili¬
tary powers have engaged in endless debate about
it. Nevertheless, all the efforts of the interna¬
tional community towards this goal have pro¬
duced only modest results, and it is only in the
course of the last decade that the member states
of the two alliances that constituted the American
and the Soviet camps have embarked on the path
of authentic disarmament. This trend has been
confirmed since the collapse of the communist
regimes in the countries of central and eastern
Europe and the dissolution of the Warsaw Treaty
Organization (WTO) or Warsaw Pact, while the
Gulf War underlined the risks of an uncontrolled
spread of conventional and nuclear weapons in
various zones of conflict.
Speculation is thus rife as to the chances of,
and the suitable pace for, a disarmament process
that would at last make it possible to overcome
the divisions inherited from the past and reinforce
international security while "diverting to arma¬
ments only the minimum of the world's eco¬
nomic and human resources". For some, the
"disarmament race" is irreversible, and nuclear
weapons are doomed to wither away once secu¬
rity can be guaranteed at less risk within the
framework of a collective organization. Others
are more sceptical and believe that cutbacks in
military expenditure and the reduction of armed
forces and weaponry stem not so much from a
new political vision as from structural adjust¬
ments determined by economic and social factors
in the wealthy societies. The fact is that, apart
from the Washington Treaty of 1987, the other
disarmament agreements (CFE, START) are not
yet in force, and their implementation raises all
kinds of difficulties. So it is well to be prudent in
assessing the chances for disarmament in the new
international context.
AN IMMEDIATE ACTION
PROGRAMME
Today, the threat that the armies of the Warsaw
Pact represented for the West has vanished, tac¬
tical nuclear weapons have almost entirely dis¬
appeared from the European continent, and the
new strategic concept of the North Atlantic
Treaty Organization (NATO) gives pride of
place to arms control and disarmament within the
framework of "co-operative security". It is there¬
fore essential that the 1990 Treaty on Conven
tional Forces in Europe (CFE) should come into
effect as rapidly as possible. The arrangement
concluded in Tashkent in May 1992 on the
sharing of arms quotas between eight countries of
the former USSR that are directly concerned
augurs well for their willingness to make it work.
Building on what has been achieved, the partic¬
ipating states of the Conference on Security and
Co-operation in Europe (CSCE) will next try to
reinforce stability in Europe and in certain "fron¬
tier zones". The drive for stability will entail the
adoption of new measures intended both to
ensure greater transparency in military activities
and to reduce the level of armed forces to a min¬
imum corresponding to legitimate security needs
or maintain them at that level. A programme of
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
immediate action was approved at the end of the
Helsinki summit conference in Finland, on 10
July 1992.
Meanwhile, the momentum triggered by the
START (Strategic Arms Reduction Talks) Treaty
has been kept up and even accelerated. After the
withdrawal and even the destruction of a sizeable
number of tactical nuclear weapons, land-based
and deployed on surface ships or in submarines,
both Russians and Americans have put a stop to
the production of fissionable materials for mili¬
tary purposes. In June 1992 they also agreed in
principle to drastically reduce their strategic
weapons and to eliminate ground-to-ground
missiles with multiple warheads by the year 2003.
It should be noted that the control of nuclear
weapons is still the exclusive preserve of these two
protagonists and that they are pressing forward
rapidly to attain their goals with the least delay.
They have, for instance, harmonized unilateral
declarations on both sides relating to the with¬
drawal and destruction of tactical nuclear
weapons, and the additional protocol to the
START Treaty ofJune 1992 was negotiated in less
than six months.
All the same, political friction still raises some
doubts as regards the actual process of disarma¬
ment. It has to be admitted that the dismantling
of tactical nuclear weapons and the storage of
the resultant fissionable material from them pose
delicate technical problems which can only be
resolved with the help of the Western powers. The
same is true of the implementation of the START
agreement: in the best-case hypothesis, it will
take more than ten years before the level of arma¬
ments reaches the agreed final total of 3,000/3,500
nuclear warheads. In any case, it would be mis¬
leading to present these moves as the result of a
deliberate policy aimed at ending the old
dilemmas of deterrence and promoting a world
free from nuclear weapons. When the process
ends, Russians and Americans will still possess an
imposing strategic arsenal, and it is probable that
the logic of deterrence based on retaining "suffi¬
cient" if not minimal capability will continue to
govern their mutual relations.
MEASURES FOR
NON-PROLIFERATION
Disarmament implies global action, and it is essen¬
tial to reinforce the effectiveness of the United
Nations in this field. This was the conclusion
In Arkansas (United States)
workers dislodge equipment
in an underground
cableway while dismantling
a Titan II intercontinental
ballistic missile and
deactivating its silo.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Apart from the Washington
Treaty of 1987, the other
disarmament agreements
are not yet in force.
Untitled acrylic painting on
canvas by the Lebanese
artist Samir Khaddaje.
reached by members of the Security Council at a
meeting held on 31 January 1992 at the Heads of
State or Government level to examine current
aspects of "the maintenance of international peace
and security". On that occasion, stress was placed
on the need to prevent the proliferation of
weapons of mass destruction, to regulate the
transfer of conventional arms and to control by
peaceful means "any problems concerning these
matters threatening or disrupting the mainte¬
nance of regional and global stability."
Measures have already been taken to consol-
14
idate and extend beyond 1995 the system set up
by the Treaty on the Non-Poliferation of Nuclear
Weapons (NPT), and there are plans to make
more resources available to the International
Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) and enlarge its
fields of competence so that it can fulfil its mon¬
itoring role. Moreover, the export of sensitive
technology is being subjected to ever stricter sur¬
veillance, and an International Centre of Science
and Technology has been created, with the sup¬
port of the West, aimed at dissuading scientists
and engineers working in the arms industry of the
former USSR from lending their skills to "pro¬
liferating" states.
In the field of conventional weapons, the five
permanent members of the Security Council
have defined a code of conduct, but this seems to
have been scarcely respected, to judge by the
transfers of arms that have taken place in certain
sensitive areas. On the other hand, multilateral
negotiations aimed at banning the production
and stockpiling of chemical weapons and ulti¬
mately eliminating them altogether have entered
a decisive phase, and it is hoped that an agreement
will be concluded shortly.
A WORLD
PERSPECTIVE
While the end of the Cold War and the new rela¬
tionship that has emerged between the former
adversaries have called into question the tradi¬
tional approach to arms control, it is still regarded
as one of the best means of reducing interna¬
tional tension, preventing conflicts and facili¬
tating the peaceful settlement of differences.
Neither the Americans nor the Russians have
any intention of thus repudiating the gains made
during several decades of concerted action to
avert the perils of the nuclear age; on the contrary,
they are determined to keep on their present
course and even to aim for more ambitious objec¬
tives than those they have already set themselves.
It remains to be seen whether the nuclear dis¬
armament on which they have agreed can be sat¬
isfactorily implemented, given the current situa¬
tion in the states that resulted from the
dismemberment of the USSR and considering
the difficulties already encountered by those
bodies responsible for verifying precisely whether
the commitments entered into are being respected.
In Europe, the reduction of conventional
forces has been viewed from the start as an essen¬
tially political process. The aim was not so much
to perpetuate the status quo by adjusting the mil-
itary balance between NATO and the WTO as to
encourage the emergence of a new security system
based on dialogue, co-operation and the mainte¬
nance of a purely defensive capability. The situ¬
ation thus gradually changed from antagonism to
peaceful coexistence before shifting to co-oper¬
ation within the framework of the CSCE, and
now the way has been paved for true disarma¬
ment by the adoption of confidence-building
measures.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
A Kuwait oil well set ablaze
during the 1991 Gulf War.
Whilst this model cannot be replicated else¬
where as it stands, it should serve as an inspiration
for putting a stop to the conventional arms race
in unstable regions of the planet. Since the end of
the Gulf War, various proposals on comparable
lines have been put forward for bringing about
peace in the Middle East. However, the success of
such an enterprise presupposes that attempts to
achieve a balance of forces at the lowest level in
a regional framework will respect the right of
every state to security and will not be dictated by
outside powers.
Moreover, arms control has to be seen in a
world perspective, and it is vital to reaffirm the
specific role that the UN Security Council must
play in this respect. It may also be necessary to try
to work out a global disarmament programme
closely linked with a plan for collective security.
The tenth. special session of the UN General
Assembly made recommendations to this effect,
but they have not yielded results so far. Today,
such an exercise would help clarify just what is at
stake in disarmament, and would serve as a per¬
manent reminder to member states of the
supreme importance of the enterprise in which
they arc engaged. IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The transformation
of the European
landscape calls for
completely new
thinking about
disarmament
Europe after the Cold War
by Andrei Zagorski
16
ANDREI ZAGORSKI,
of Russia, is deputy director
of the Centre of International
Studies of the Moscow State
Institute of International
Relations (MGI MO).
DISARMAMENT issues remain high on the
European agenda despite and to some
extent because of the end of the Cold War.
Today decisions on reductions in both nuclear
and conventional arsenals are being taken at a
speed that could hardly have been imagined two
or three years ago.
The signing by the United States and the USSR
of the INF (Intermediate-range nuclear forces)
Treaty in 1987 paved the way for a new generation
of agreements concerning weapons in Europe.
The Treaty provided, for the first time in post-war
history, not for a limitation but for an actual reduc¬
tion in medium- and short-range weapons that
were already deployed. Since then, efforts have
ceased to be directed towards arms control, which
in practice underwrote a controlled arms race,
but towards real disarmament cuts in existing
weapons arsenals. This new approach has been
consolidated and strengthened by the dramatic
developments that have taken place in Europe
since 1 989, which have led in their turn to a series
of agreements concerning both nuclear and con¬
ventional weapons.
The START (Strategic Arms Reduction
Treaty) agreement of 1991, partially modified in
terms of its implementation in the Lisbon pro¬
tocol of May 1992 signed by Russia, the United
States, Belarus, Ukraine and Kazakhstan, provides
for cuts of around 50 per cent in strategic nuclear
weapons belonging to the United States and the
former USSR. When they met in June 1992 Pres¬
ident Boris Yeltsin and President George Bush
went even further along this path when they
made a commitment to the complete elimina¬
tion of ground-based heavy missiles as well as
deep cuts in US sea-launched strategic missiles.
The Treaty on Conventional Forces in Europe
(CFE1), signed on 19 November 1990, sought to
eliminate numerical imbalances in five categories
of weapons (battle tanks, armoured combat vehi¬
cles, artillery, combat aircraft and attack heli¬
copters) available to the North Atlantic Treaty
Organization (NATO) and the Warsaw Treaty
Organization (WTO) in the area stretching from
the Atlantic to the Urals, as well as to reduce their
numbers and limit their ability to carry out a sur¬
prise attack. A follow-up to this Treaty, the CFE1
A agreement, established limits for personnel
strength in the same arca. CFE1 A, which is not a
treaty but a politically binding document, was
signed by twenty-five states on 9 July 1992.
No less important than these multilateral
agreements arc deeper cuts resulting from uni¬
lateral reductions on both of the previously adver¬
sary sides East and West. They include cuts in
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Left, withdrawal of Soviet
forces stationed in Hungary
(1989). Above, American
troops evacuate the military
base at Bremerhaven
(Germany) In 1990.
tactical nuclear weapons in Europe providing
for a total withdrawal of US and former Soviet
ground-launched battlefield weapons (short-
range missiles and nuclear artillery). Unilateral
cuts are also being made in the nuclear forces of
both France and the United Kingdom, although
neither country has yet participated in formal
negotiations on these issues.
However, the spectacular developments that
have taken place in the field of European disar¬
mament since the end of the Cold War have been
accompanied by a wide range of new challenges
which make the task of managing this process
quite difficult. One indication of the difficulties
facing the European disarmament process today
is the fact that hardly any of the recent disarma¬
ment agreements, including the CFE1 Treaty,
have yet entered into force, because several states
have not yet ratified them. Another problem is
that the conceptual approach to European dis¬
armament is still largely based on attitudes that
were shaped during the years of East-West con¬
frontation and have not been adapted to current
needs. The disintegration of the Warsaw Treaty
Organization and the break-up of the Soviet
Union have totally changed not only the envi¬
ronment of disarmament negotiations and the
positions of the parties to them, but the very
functions of the negotiations.
The disappearance of the Warsaw Treaty
Organization, which happened de jure in 1991
but de facto in 1990, made the Treaty on Con¬
ventional Forces in Europe virtually obsolete,
since it had emerged from negotiations that began
as a bloc-to-bloc endeavour aimed at improving
the level of stability and predictability between
NATO and WTO. This general approach was to
a great extent outdated before the negotiations
were concluded. Early in 1990, Hungary
announced that its defence needs could not be
properly dealt with in a bloc-to-bloc arrange¬
ment and insisted that its quota of armaments
should not be established within the framework
of the WTO. Other East European countries
followed suit and by the time the CFE1 talks
came to an end the major problem was no longer
the achievement of an agreement between East
and West but the achievement of mutually accept¬
able quotas within the WTO, which still for¬
mally existed. In order to provide East Euro¬
pean countries with appropriate quotas for their
national forces, the limits on armaments within
the CFE1 Treaty were raised even higher than
those initially envisaged.
The break-up of the Soviet Union meant that
new tasks had to be carried out within the CFE
framework, especially after the division of former
Soviet military assets became one of the most
controversial issues among the members of the
Commonwealth of Independent States (CIS),
which was joined by eleven of the fifteen former
Soviet republics. The CFE1 Treaty thus became
a framework for discussions on the sharing of
Soviet military assets and for legitimizing Western
participation in these discussions. The succes¬
sors of the Soviet Union committed themselves
to respect obligations under the CFE1 Treaty
and were urged to negotiate rapidly and to reach
agreement before June 1992.
On 15 May 1992, at a CIS summit meeting in
Tashkent, an agreement on the implementation of
the CFE1 Treaty was reached, including provisions
for a share-out of the former Soviet quotas on
various categories of weapons. This agreement 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
All disarmament efforts in
Europe so far have been
based on the philosophy of
managing problems at the
level of East-West relations.
was then approved at a conference of the parties
to the CFE1 Treaty held in Oslo on 5 June and by
an extraordinary conference held on 10 July in
Helsinki in conjunction with the CSCE summit
meeting.
However, the issue cannot be regarded as set¬
tled since none of the CIS states except Russia had
ratified the CFE1 Treaty before the CSCE
summit as had been agreed previously. Prospects
for ratification can be regarded as high only in the
case of Belarus and are low in the case of the
Caucasian states that are engaged in military hos¬
tilities. That is why, instead of enacting the CFE1
Treaty, as was initially planned, the extraordi¬
nary conference of July 1992 only produced a
document on the "provisional application" of
the Treaty whereby all parties committed them¬
selves to "apply provisionally all of the provisions
of the Treaty, beginning on 17 July 1992" within
120 days, in the expectation that the Treaty would
be ratified within that time-frame. Armenia,
Azerbaijan, Georgia and Moldova have not yet
signed this document.
Disintegration problems at least partially sim¬
ilar to those within the former Soviet Union
might be expected to arise elsewhere, especially
in view of the division of Czechoslovakia into the
Czech Republic and Slovakia early in 1 993 .
All previous disarmament efforts in Europe so
far have been based on the philosophy of man¬
aging problems at the macro-level of East-West
relations. In formal terms this approach came to
an end in September 1992, when all fifty-two of
the CSCE countries sat down to begin new secu¬
rity negotiations in Vienna. Though this new
security forum is an important instrument for
permanent communication and discussions of
security issues, it has been launched without any
clear conception of where future efforts in this
field should be directed. It now has to work
towards agreements that will respond to the
growing number and diversity of problems at
the "micro" level.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Left, The chess game
(1943), oil on canvas by
Maria Elena Vieira da Silva.
Below, a meeting of the
Conference on Security and
Co-operation in Europe
(CSCE) in 1991.
An appeal for non-violence
In one part of the world the school year is beginning. In others it is already underway. But sadly,
for millions of children the school year docs not exist. It is this that I have in mind when I call upon
all those who arc responsible, in one way or another, for shaping young minds.
The role of educators, which has always been important for society and its development, is today
fundamental. The future evolution of the human community depends to a great extent on them and
their work with the young all over the world. Will the human community sink deeper into violence,
which is the expression of racism, xenophobia, intolerance, fanaticism and hate, and which in turn
engenders more violence? Or will it realize the danger of turning these tendencies into everyday
facts of life and react by taking advantage of every opportunity tor building a culture of peace,
including the important opportunity offered by children?
Children, young people in general, are the first victims of violence. Victims in the literal sense
because their bodies and hearts are hurt by the consequences of blind conflicts; victims in the fig¬
urative sense because their only entertainment is to be found in the violence universally pre¬
sented on screens of all kinds.
Many young people are vaguely aware of the destructive consequences of aggressive behaviour.
Many admire, if we know how to present them, the great world figures of non-violence and peace
Gandhi and Martin Luther King, to name but two. Manv (all in my opinion) are naturall v inclined
to be generous and open, and to share with others who are suffering or who are different if we explain
to them that suffering or that difference.
It would be irresponsible not to seize upon this awareness of danger, this capacity to identify
with heroes, this natural generosity. It would be irresponsible not to move quickly, for events are
providing us each week with a host of bad examples. Yes to difference, yes to firmness and perse¬
verance. No to violence. Yes to the force of reason. No to the reason of force.
That is why I invite all those in charge of educating and taking care of children parents, teachers,
youth leaders, those who design leisure activities for young people, organizers of youth movements
and activities to emphasize in their work the values of dialogue, sharing, respect for others and
solidarity in order to build in the minds of tomorrow's citizens the solid foundations of a culture
of peace.
Federico Mayor
Director-General of UNESCO
Paris, 8 September 1993
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Investing in peace
by Jacques Fontanel
Profitable yet non¬
productive, the
arms industry is
still a key sector
in the world
economy. Will it
be possible to
convert to
development the
resources freed
I© by
THE United Nations has sought to pro¬
mote disarmament ever since its founda¬
tion and has demonstrated that there is a
close link between disarmament and economic
and social development. A comprehensive UN
report on this relationship, issued in 1982, found
that more publicity should be given to military
spending, that it would be useful to convert
some of the resources freed by disarmament to
meet economic and social needs in developing
countries, and that consideration should be
given to establishing an "international disar¬
mament fund for development." However, the
report was not unanimously accepted, and a
special session of the UN General Assembly in
June 1982 merely confirmed the absence of any
real hope of progress. In fact, the subject
dropped out of the picture during the 1980s.
The political and economic upheavals that
have taken place in Eastern Europe, the disar¬
mament agreements that have been reached
(which, though limited in scope, are quite spe¬
cific in respect of intermediate-range missiles)
and the world economic crisis have, however, all
helped to bring the idea of disarmament for
development back into the limelight. On the
other hand, the first flush of optimism about the
expected results of disarmament has now faded
somewhat. Three questions arise:
"~ Does armament put a brake on develop¬
ment?
i*" Are the effects of disarmament on national
economies entirely beneficial?
'* Can disarmament easily be combined with
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
transfers of resources from the developed coun¬
tries to the developing ones?
A BRAKE ON DEVELOPMENT?
Economists regard military expenditure as non¬
productive spending, yet it amounts to nearly
$1,000 billion (or 5 per cent of the world's gross
national product), more than 50 million people
are employed in military activities, and research
and development in the arms industry employ
the skills of more than 20 per cent of the planet's
scientists and engineers.
The influence of military spending on eco¬
nomic growth has been the subject of many
studies, in some cases contradictory. Three prin¬
cipal ideas emerge from such studies:
*" Military spending has a powerful effect on
the shape of modern economies. According to
Marxist economists, market economies need
the growth of military expenditure in order to
combat the tendency of profit margins to decline.
J.K. Galbraith believes that the military budget
neutralizes part of the surplus of products that
results from an ever greater excess of supply
Left, Let us beat swords
into ploughshares (1959), a
bronze sculpture by Evgeniy
Vuchetich at UN
Headquarters in New York.
Right, a Soviet tank bought
by a British firm for
recycling into girders and
agricultural tools. It is one
of thousands that have been
scrapped as a result of
arms reduction agreements.
JACQUES FONTANEL,
of France, is director of
European studies and
professor at the Faculty of
Economic Sciences of the
Pierre Mendès-France
University in Grenoble. He
has written many articles on
the economic problems
connected with
disarmament.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
In the short run a slowdown
in the arms race often has
unfavourable economic
effects, but in the long run
disarmament encourages
development
over demand demand that is reduced by the
limitation of purchasing power. Free-market
economists challenge this idea and consider that
the market economy ought eventually to result
in both disarmament and development.
*" Military expenditure has a negative effect
on economic growth. According to Seymour
Melman, the militarization of the economy
undermines the strength of market economies by
encouraging inflationary tensions and reducing
the role of efficient units of production.
According to Michael Ward, while military
spending may have positive short-term effects on
growth in some countries such as India, the
United States or Brazil, these effects are less
important than those produced by other forms
of public expenditure. It is undeniable that,
compared with other public spending, military
expenditure does least to create jobs and to
stimulate economic activity.
*" Military spending slows down investment, so
that long-term economic development is threat¬
ened as well as short-term growth. A study by
Emile Benoit in 1978 suggesting that such-
spending encourages economic and social
progress in developing countries has been
strongly criticized for both its form and its con¬
tent.
The fact remains that such general analyses
are only valid on a world scale. In some coun¬
tries, arms production can have beneficial effects
on the economy: arms industries create jobs
while reducing imports, exports improve the
balance of trade, and military technology has a
positive spin-off in the civilian sector of pro¬
duction. Moreover, military strength protects
states against the ambitions of their neighbours
and provides the means for political domina¬
tion the same means deployed by the great
powers in trade and monetary negotiations to
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
the detriment of countries that are less well pro¬
tected.
THE ECONOMIC EFFECTS
OF DISARMAMENT
Disarmament is usually presented as being con¬
ducive to economic and social development. The
cost of an aircraft carrier is, for instance, often
compared with the number of schools and hos¬
pitals that could be built instead. A surplus of
armaments invariably provokes crisis situations.
Negotiated disarmament has nevertheless
to take into account the economic and statcgic
imperatives of international security. There are
several forms of disarmament, ranging from
cutbacks in military spending to the destruction
of arms stockpiles or the scrapping of specific
weapons, and they naturally have different eco¬
nomic consequences.
In general it may be said that while in the
short run a slowdown in the arms race often has
unfavourable economic effects, in the long run
disarmament encourages development.
Three practical observations show that "peace
dividends" are meagre in the short term:
*" Disarmament docs not necessarily in all cases
bring about an immediate reduction in military
spending. The destruction of arms stockpiles and
the verification of accords involve additional costs.
The destruction of arms stockpiles guaran¬
tees neither the limitation of strategic capabili¬
ties nor the reduction of military expenditure. It
generally leads countries to devise new weapons
that are much more sophisticated and costly
than those dealt with under the accords.
A cutback in military expenditure does not
necessarily result in an immediate improvement
in a country's economic situation. Even if the
actual expenditure can easily be switched to
other purposes, the factories, staff and equip¬
ment previously devoted to defence arc not so
easily converted. To be viable, the conversion of
existing materials and equipment will require
new investment, the development of new activ¬
ities and a search for new outlets in already
highly competitive civilian sectors.
LONG-TERM
PRODUCTIVITY
Disarmament must be general. While in the
short term it may have adverse economic effects
on the arms industries of exporting countries, in
the long term its economic consequences ought
to be positive if the economic downturn
resulting from reduced domestic arms procure¬
ment does not become irreversible. If the reduc¬
tion in military expenditure is well managed, it
would even be likely to produce benefits for M. ¡S
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
We don't agree (1993), oil
on canvas by the
Portuguese painter
Baptistantunes.
civilian research and development, for produc¬
tivity and for confidence in international trading
relations.
Indeed, the economic advantages to be
expected from lasting disarmament can in the
long run prove very substantial. Econometric
models highlight the positive effects, notably
if some at least of the resources thus released are
trasnferrcd to the countries of the Third World.
Considering the unproductive nature of military
spending, it is undeniable that, once the initial
problems of conversion have been overcome, the
new state of peace will have a positive impact on
worldwide economic development.
ROADS TO SUCCESS
Two fundamental conditions must be fulfilled if
disarmament for development is to succeed:
firstly, some of the resources saved by cutbacks
in arms production must be transferred to the
countries of the Third World; secondly, it is
essential to eliminate the basic causes that impel
states to enter into armed conflict.
For countries that have no arms industry of
24
their own, the effects of a reduction in military
spending arc beneficial in the short term, since
the resources hitherto spent on arms purchases
can be more usefully employed, but only if the
savings thus effected are not hijacked by social
groups intent on diverting them to other non¬
productive uses such as the export of capital or
the import of luxury goods. In other words, a
transfer of resources is economically worth¬
while only if they are channelled into highly
productive activity.
Such transfers may, moreover, sometimes
have a negative effect by aggravating inflationary
tensions. International aid too can have adverse
effects if it encourages poor countries to run
down their own industries and gradually become
more economically dependent, a situation con¬
ducive to pauperization. Furthermore, aid that
is not disinterested can misdirect development:
transfers of resources are often primarily influ¬
enced, as concerns the rich countries, by con¬
siderations other than the economic develop¬
ment needs of the beneficiary countries.
TOWARDS LASTING
DISARMAMENT
Disarmament calls for a series of decisions
relating in particular to the international eco¬
nomic order, the nature of development, the
direction taken by technological progress, and
the distribution of economic resources.
Although such matters only rarely figure on
the agenda of arms limitation negotiations, the
economic development of nations plays a role of
fundamental importance to international secu¬
rity. It is involved on at least three counts:
Firstly, in a world where there is scarcity
but there are no international conflicts, mili¬
tary expenditure is a form of waste. The recent
experience of the USSR shows that overspending
on the military gradually erodes the efficiency of
the economic system and in the end reduces a
nation's defence potential.
' Secondly, any disarmament dissociated from
the reasons that underlie the arms race could in
the end prove particularly dangerous for peace or
for democratic political systems. Since the great
powers can, directly or indirectly, take advantage
of their dominant position, any profound change
in the strategic balance of forces is liable to trans¬
form the international economic map too.
Finally, when human dignity is threatened, it
often happens that nations prefer warfare to inac¬
tion. International security cannot be lastingly
maintained within a framework of power politics
or of excessive economic and social inequalities.
Nor is peace in all cases necessarily preferable
to conflict, particularly when that peace is based
on tyranny, slavery or exploitation, and on dis¬
regard for human rights but in such cases can
it really be called peace?
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
THE U NES C O COURIER - O C T O B E R 1993
ES
BY MICHEL BATISSE
Just twenty-five years ago, in
September 1968, an important
conference organized by
Unksco was held in Paris. Its full
title, the "intergovernmental
conference of specialists to study
the ideas of modern science on the
rational use and conservation of the
resources of the biosphere", was
something of a mouthful, and for
the sake of simplicity it became
known as the "Biosphere Confer¬
ence". It was, incidentally, on this
occasion that the scientific term
"biosphere" (sphere of life), which
until then had been rarely used out¬
side the writings of the Russian geol
ogist Vernadsky and the French
philosopher Teilhard de Chardin,
began to be more widely used.
A few months before, notably in
France and the United States, stu¬
dent movements had challenged
the consumer society and heralded
the entrance of environmental
issues on to the political stage. Fully
four years before the big United
Nations Conference on the same
theme was held at Stockholm, the
biosphere conference was the first
occasion on which these issues were
considered scientifically at inter¬
governmental level and their world¬
wide dimension was recognized.
Above, grazing
animals in the
Serengeti-
Ngorongoro
Biosphere
Reserve
(Tanzania). The
reserve, and
sites shown in
photos on pages
26 and 27, form
part of the MAB
Biosphere
Reserve
network.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
IB ÁT
íISE
Above all, however, it showed for Urdaibai
the first time that there was a desire (Spain),
to reconcile the imperatives of the
use of natural resources with those
of their protection. In other words,
at that early date the biosphere con¬
ference launched the concept of
what is today known as "sustain¬
able development".
Under the dynamic presidency of
François Bourlière, former presi¬
dent of IUCN (World Alliance for
Nature) and the International Bio¬
logical Programme, over 300 dele¬
gates from some sixty countries and
international organizations (such
as FAO, WHO and WMO') assem¬
bled for the discussions. In the près- Isle of Rhum
ence of such great pioneers of the (UK)
environmental movement as Carlos
Chagas (Brazil), René Dubos
(United States), Viktor Kovda
(Russia), Théodore Monod (France)
and Barton Worthington (United
Kingdom), they thrashed out all the
issues, both practical and theoret¬
ical, concerning the relationships
between human activities and the
terrestrial and aquatic environ¬
ments of the planet.
PRACTICAL RECOMMENDATIONS
However, the conference did not
limit itself simply to debates. Since
the participants were official repre¬
sentatives ofgovernments, it was able
to adopt formal recommendations
26
on all the subjects dealt with. The
range and relevance of these recom¬
mendations are striking even today.
The first recommendation called
on Unesco to prepare "an interna¬
tional research programme on man
and the biosphere". This programme,
soon to be known worldwide by its
English acronym, "MAB", was natu¬
rally based on the work of the con¬
ference. It therefore adopted an
interdisciplinary approach, linking
the social sciences with the physical
and biological sciences, and it took
into account the specific problems of
developing countries. It would also
provide a practical follow-up and
give a worldwide dimension to the
International Biological Programme,
which had just entered its final stage.
Thus the biosphere conference gave
birth twenty- five years ago to the
research and training programme
that is still at the heart of Unesco's
activities relating to sustainable
development.
The Man and the Biosphere Pro¬
gramme is governed by an intergov.-
ernmental co-ordinating council
composed of representatives from
thirty countries, elected in rotation,
and from the international organi¬
zations concerned. Each country
participates in the programme
through a national committee whose
members are representatives ofoffi¬
cial bodies, universities and research
centres. During more than two
decades ofoperational activities, the
scientific content of the MAB pro¬
gramme has naturally evolved, but it
has retained its primary orientation,
namely to seek the most judicious
ways ofusing each country's natural
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
resources while ensuring their long-
term conservation.
A NEW IMPETUS
Whether it is concerned with
tropical forests or semi-desert
regions, mountain or coastal areas,
pastureland, islands or even urban
areas, the MAB programme seeks a
comprehensive understanding of
the processes triggered by the
impact of human activities on the
various elements of the biosphere,
and tries to minimize their harmful
effects. To a large extent, MAB's
operations in the field are concen¬
trated in some 300 "biosphere
reserves" established in over eighty
countries, where efforts are made
to combine the conservation of
biological diversity with sustain¬
able ways of using natural
resources that will benefit the local
populations. These biosphere
reserves provide the programme
with some of its most original and
important inputs.
At its most recent session, in Jan¬
uary 1993, MAB's co-ordinating
council stressed that the pro¬
gramme constituted a "pre-adapted
response" by Unesco to the recom¬
mendations set forth in Agenda 21 ,
the action plan adopted by the
United Nations Conference on Envi¬
ronment and Development held at
Rio de Janeiro (Brazil) in 1992. So, as
it celebrates its jubilee, MAB is more
necessary than ever and is being
asked to take out a fresh lease on
life, deploying its wealth of experi¬
ence and its considerable volume
Chang Bai Shan
(China).
Rio Plátano
(Honduras)
of results, only some ofwhich have
so far been analysed in depth.
One thing is very clear: the
sapling that was planted by the bios¬
phere conference with its key¬
words of globality, interdiscipli-
narity, systemic and prospective
approaches, problem-oriented
research, concern for the future and
for future generations will long
continue to bear fruit.
1 EAO: Food and Agriculture Organization
of the United Nations; WMO: World
Meteorological Organization; WIIO: World
Health Organization.
MICHEL BATISSE,
ofFrance, is currently Unisco's adviser
on environmental issues. He was
secretary-general ofthe biosphere
conference and organizer ofthe MAB
programme. 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
vv 0 R L
PROTECTING QUITO FROM POLLUTION
The capital of Ecuador has a big
problem. Dominated by the active
volcano Pichincha, Quito could soon
be suffering from the same kind of
pollution as Mexico City ifnothing is
done. At present some 80 per cent of
the city's air pollution is caused by
traffic, and the average lead level in
the blood of schoolchildren is three
times the maximum set by the World
Health Organization (WHO). Two
initiatives have been started under
the auspices of Fundación Natura
(FN), a World Wide Fund for Nature
(WWF) affiliate. First, it has devel¬
oped a plan for tree-planting in the
city previously only 20 per cent of
newly-planted trees survived,
because no study ofsuitable species
had been made. Second, since
engines do not run efficiently at
Quito's altitude of2,850 metres, espe¬
cially if they are old, FN has brought
together drivers and the municipal
authorities in an attempt to establish
and enforce new norms. It is also
training professional drivers and
seeking to improve fuel quality.
=******a5atiS3
i^V*^fKm J
A PRIZE FOR "CLEAN UP AUSTRALIA"
The United Nations Environment Programme (UNEP)
has awarded a prize to Ian Kierman, leader of a project
called "Clean up Australia." After tidying up the port of
Sydney, each year some 400,000 volunteers are removing
litter from roadsides, watercourses and parks throughout
Australia. Ian Kiernan has since embarked on an even
more ambitious project called "Clean up the World." He
intends to draw the attention of the international com¬
munity to waste disposal, which poses the same prob¬
lems all over the world.
FRAGILE ECOSYSTEMS
In the United States 4,200 out of
some 20,000 native plant species are
threatened with extinction, including
some 750 within the next ten years
because their habitats are being
destroyed or degraded. To save as
many as possible, conservationists
are sowing their seeds in places
where they have not hitherto grown.
However, these introductions are
proving surprisingly controversial.
What if an endangered species intro¬
duced into a new environment
begins to crowd out its neighbours,
threatening them in turn with extinc¬
tion? There is also the risk that a spe¬
cialist trying to save a specific plant
by introducing it into another
ecosystem may be tempted to see
its new environment as an adver¬
sary to be manipulated. The risks
and difficulties of reintroduction are
leading to a growing awareness that
more care should be taken to avoid
the destruction ofexisting habitats in
the first place.
LUCKY CRABS
The region ofAntsalova on the west coast ofMadagascar
(below) has been listed as a world heritage site by
UNESCO. A conservation and development project
aimed at making the most of the area's ecological
resources is already underway in this remote, sparsely
populated area, which is very rich in endemic flora and
fauna. Although swimming crabs {Scylla serrata) are
heavily fished and eaten locally, they have not so far
been exported to Europe because the fine skin which sur¬
rounds their flesh is brown and not pink like that of the
crabs that tickle the palates ofgourmets in that continent.
Because of this anatomical detail these plump man¬
grove crabs have so far escaped decimation by intensive
fishing.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A HAIRY NOSE
FOR STAMP-COLLECTORS
To mark its 45th anniversary this year, the United Nations
Postal Administration issued a series of stamps on 3
March showing endangered animal species, which the
Convention on International Trade in Endangered
Species of Wild Flora and Fauna (CITES) so far rati¬
fied by 1 15 nations is trying to protect. Twelve species
will be featured each year on superb stamps designed by
well-known animal painters. The star turn this year is the
hairy-nosed wombat of Queensland, Australia, a mar¬
supial rodent whose population is down to only about
one hundred. Others will include the snow leopard,
Grevy's zebra, the desert monitor, the Amazonian man¬
atee and the peregrine falcon. To obtain the stamps,
sold in three blocks of 16, contact the United Nations
Postal Administration, Palais des Nations, CH-Geneva 10,
Switzerland. Tel. 022 917 38 25. Fax022 917 00 24.
OECD
AND PESTICIDES
The theme of the April 1993 "Green¬
watch" dossier was pesticides. A Bel¬
gian reader has written to scold us for
not condemning these potentially
dangerous products more roundly.
Their use is often indispensable,
however, as when crops are invaded
by locusts, for instance. The Orga¬
nization for Economic Co-operation
and Development (OECD) is
preparing to launch in January 1994
a three-year programme whose aim
is to reduce risks by gradually
phasing out use of the most dan¬
gerous pesticides, to promote a gen¬
eral reduction in pesticide use, and to
encourage the wider use of other
methods of destroying pests.
SORTING OUT THE RUBBISH
Since June 1991, the population of
Colonia Valdense (Uruguay) has
been receiving leaflets explaining
why household waste is being col¬
lected on a selective basis, and a
timetable of dates throughout the
year when glass, metal, paper, plastic
and organic rubbish will be taken
away. Profits from selling these
wastes for recycling pay the costs of
spreading the message and manu¬
facturing containers, which are
strategically placed in public places.
Local schools are associated with
these activities, which feature regu¬
larly in the media. The initiative was
launched by DEMAVAL {Defensa
medio ambiente ValdenseValdense
Environment Protection), a non-gov¬
ernmental organization headed by
Unfsco Courierreader Omar Esteban
Pita, to whom we are indebted for
this information. To find out more,
write to Señor Pita at Avenida Artigas
s/n 70202, Colonia Valdense,
Uruguay.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
INITIATIVES
"Initiatives" ¡s a feature designed to highlight examples of environmental action
in different parts of the world. We invite readers to send us details of their own experiences
in this field for possible publication in the column.
6110D E FOE LIffl I
The Israeli
pavilion (Venice,
1993).
Tin-: Venice Biennale of Modern Art sprang a
surprise this year with the Israeli Pavilion,
which was designed by Avital Geva, an Israeli
artist who lives on the Ein Shemer kibbutz,
not far from Hadera. The pavilion took the
form ofa large experimental greenhouse covering
1,700 square metres. A pond stocked with five
species ofcarp and watered at regular intervals by
artificial rain was overhung by cucumber plants
growing in pots fixed on hollow pipes, and whose
flower- and fruit-laden stems cascaded to the
ground. Along a system of water-filled channels
grew a special variety of "spelt" or primeval wheat,
whose medicinal powers are currently being
studied. Suspended three metres above the ground,
these crops were watered by a dropper mecha¬
nism specially designed to economize on water. The
five carp species were not only an excellent source
ofproteins; they also ate any mosquito larvae they
found in the water, thus preventing the spread of
these insect pests.
After studying painting in Tel Aviv and exhibiting
at many shows, Avital Geva retired in 1978 from
the world of art, which, he felt, was incapable of
solving the problems of society. Under the
patronage of an educational institution, "Mevo'ot
Iron," he assembled dozens of youngsters from
other kibbutzim and set them to work on an equal
footing with leading specialists from agriculture
and industry. His ambition was to make the most
of the "hamama" the greenhouse. It was in this
spirit that he designed the greenhouse for the Ein
Shemer kibbutz, of which the Israeli Pavilion at
Venice was a replica.
It is a very special kind of greenhouse. Various
kinds of research are undertaken there, particu¬
larly on the simultaneous breeding of different
species of fish, the use of solar energy, the recy¬
cling of water, and finding alternative substrata
for crop-growing. The greenhouse is also intended
to be a place where team members can meet and
discuss their ideas: in an area kept cool by the arti¬
ficial rain, large armchairs in light-coloured wood
are arranged around low tables.
In this way Avital Geva seeks to redraw the fron¬
tier between art and life, between art and nature
and even to challenge the art world itself. There is
nothing Utopian about his work. On the contrary,
it proves that a place may be both beautiful and
socially useful, while at the same time offering
many possibilities for research into ways of
improving the environment.
IP
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
In spite of efforts
to impose
restrictions, the
international arms
trade is still
flourishing
The business of war
by Christophe Carle
Jet fighters on patrol. ARMS transfers from the industrialized
countries to the countries of the Third
World have long constituted the bulk of
the international arms trade. Although the end
of the Cold War and the Gulf-War have pro¬
foundly altered the dynamics ofthat trade, these
changes arc still too recent for us to be able to
clearly discern all the consequences. What is clear,
however, is that the principal arms producers are
facinsi a new and incrcasinelv acute dilemma: how
can the economic interests involved in the export
of military hardware be reconciled with the
requirements of non-proliferation and security?
Ever since the Iran-Iraq War and the Gulf
War, the problem of arms proliferation has been
at the forefront of international security issues.
It is a problem that encompasses the entire range
of ballistic, chemical or biological, and nuclear
weapons. These so-called non-conventional
devices arc already covered by a series of non-
proliferation measures. The question of con¬
ventional weapons, on the other hand, deserves >* 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
0 ^BENGE
31
closer consideration, the Gulf War having once
again underlined the importance of technolog¬
ical superiority in conventional weapons in the
air, on land and at sea. Yet attempts to limit the
trade in these weapons the most commonly
manufactured and sold throughout the world
are of very recent origin.
OTHER TIMES,
OTHER WARS
During the Cold War, the production of con¬
ventional weapons was stimulated by East-West
antagonism. The biggest manufacturers were
also the biggest exporters. For those countries,
providing the Third World with arms was all
part of the bipolar competition in which they
were engaged on a global scale. If one belligerent,
in any part of the world, received arms from one
of the two blocs, its adversary was practically
sure of obtaining support from the opposing
bloc. The superpowers thus competed for influ¬
ence on the periphery of their zones of direct
confrontation, a situation which also suited the
states engaged in regional confrontations.
That situation no longer exists, but the flow
of arms to the Third World has not dried up.
Tensions other than those fuelled by the former
East-West conflict still exist all over the world,
stimulating a demand for arms in certain devel¬
oping countries.
L'imprudence (1991),
acrylic on canvas by the
Zairian painter Cheik Ledy.
CHRISTOPHE CARLE,
a French specialist in
regional security questions,
is engaged in research at
France's Institute of
International Relations
(IFRI).
The Middle East is of special, though not
unique, importance in this respect. Two years
after the invasion of Kuwait by Iraq, most of the
nations in the Gulf region, conscious of the
inadequacy of their own armed forces, have
been buying arms on the international markets,
and the other countries of the region are also
restocking and reinforcing their arsenals.
ACODE
OF CONDUCT
The Gulf War did, however, inspire new
thinking and a series of political initiatives at the
highest level to try to curb the delivery of
weapons to the Middle East and avert the risk of
upsetting the balance of international security.
The example of Iraq, overarmed to a point where
it was emboldened to invade a neighbour state,
thus triggering a war in which the whole planet
was to some extent involved, speaks for itself.
Various proposals aimed at reducing the arms
trade have been drafted in recent years by a
number of Western prime ministers and heads of
state, and the European Community leaders
discussed these matters at their meeting in Maas¬
tricht in December 1991.
Following up these initiatives, two proce¬
dures have been adopted. In the first place, the
five permanent members of the United Nations
Security Council have agreed to meet periodi-
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The five permanent
members of the United
Nations Security Council
have agreed to meet
periodically in order to draw
up a common "code of
conduct" bearing on the
export of conventional
weapons.
cally in order to draw up a common "code of
conduct" bearing on the export of conventional
weapons. Together, these five states accounted
for over 80 per cent of the conventional weapons
exported to the Third World over the last five
years. This readiness to consider the question
from a new angle is a first encouraging sign.
As a second measure, on 9 December 1991
the UN General Assembly adopted a resolution
relating, among other things, to "transparency
in armaments" and a "Register of Conventional
Arms", whereby the member states of the UN
are henceforth required to provide an annual
inventory of all imports and exports of arms
during the previous twelve months.
Although several meetings of the Security
Council have been held to discuss this matter, the
five permanent members have not succeeded in
arriving at a clear, agreed definition of matériel
considered as "destabilizing" a decision which
would have made it possible to ban its export
nor have they managed to agree on mutual noti¬
fication procedures about their exports. In any
case, there is little likelihood of such information
being exchanged prior to the signature of pos¬
sible export orders, and this considerably limits
the scope of the negotiations.
A FREE MARKET
IN EXPORTS
The current outlook for an agreement among the
suppliers of conventional weapons to the coun¬
tries of the South is not bright, essentially
because of the economic and commercial con¬
ditions already mentioned.1 While it is true that
the case of the Iraqi weaponry that was turned
against some of its principal suppliers in the
battles of the Gulf War has underlined one of the
risks that can result from an arms race in the
Third World, it must be said that the arms-pro¬
ducing states are still irresistibly drawn towards
export markets to compensate for shrinking
domestic demand for military hardware.
In the East, the same commercial logic as in
the West works in favour of arms exports, pre¬
sent and future. In a situation of shrinking bud¬
gets, stagnant or sluggish economies, or pressing
need for convertible currency, such exports
seem to be the only means of guaranteeing the
security of jobs in high technology sectors and
A British missile base. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
World totals
Industrialized countries
Developing countries
of preserving the viability of the conventional
arms industries.
In short, despite their stated attitudes
towards non-proliferation, the principal arms
producers are engaged in an ever keener com¬
petition for export markets, which incidentally
means that they are willing to accord numerous
compensatory measures to purchasers, most
often in the form of transfers of technology and
licensing agreements.
Other, more ambitious states are still intent
on devising and producing their own
weaponry Taiwan, for instance, is pursuing
its project for a combat plane known as the
"Indigenous Defense Fighter" (IDF) but even
they remain dependent on inputs of foreign
technology. Moreover, certain countries of the
South that a few years ago seemed likely to
become important new arms producers have
been unable to stand up to the competition from
the countries of the industrialized North which
alone can hope to continue footing the massive
bills for designing and producing high-tech con¬
ventional weapons.
The future of the arms export business will
thus depend essentially on the policy of the
principal producers, who have declared their
intention to limit the international arms trade.
But since each export order signed is one more
incentive for escalating a spiral of free competi¬
tion, for the present one can but note the gap that
separates words and deeds.
As for the immediate future, only two factors
could help to restrain arms transfers: the lack of
financial resources among potential Third World
purchasers, and the desire of the main producers
to keep the market in the most sophisticated
weapons for themselves, at least for the time
being.
As for the new UN Register, its function at
present seems likely to be limited to recording
JT the continuation of existing trends.
1 See the article by
Jacques Fontanel on
page 20.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
To check the
spread of nuclear
weapons, we must
stop thinking that
they are
synonymous with
security
The bomb or peace
by Jasjit Singh
Above, Illumination of
Peace, papier collé by the
Indian artist V. Balu.
CHANGES in the global political architec¬
ture during the past few years have led to
a number of agreements to reduce nuclear
weapons. The threat of a nuclear war and global
holocaust has receded. On the other hand, the
unmasking of the nuclear weapon programme
pursued by Iraq for many years, unknown and
undetected in spite of regular inspections by
the International Atomic Energy Authority,
has generated renewed concern about nuclear
proliferation.
Proliferation means different things to dif¬
ferent people. The five acknowledged nuclear
weapon states the United States, the former
USSR, China, France and the United Kingdom,
sec the problem essentially as one arising out of 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Uniforms for sale in a
Moscow street.
the spread of nuclear weapons to other states: in
other words, "horizontal" proliferation. Most
other states sec the problem as far more com¬
plex, although no consensus view exists. The fact
that 1 57 states are now parties to the Treaty on the
Non-Prolifcration of Nuclear Weapons (NPT)
which was signed in 1968 is an indication of this
widespread concern. It also highlights the com¬
mitment of the five nuclear weapon states to total
nuclear disarmament and reflects the expecta¬
tions of the non-nuclear weapon states that this
commitment will be honoured at an early date.
The real problem is that for more than forty-
36
five years the world has been led to believe that
nuclear weapons have kept the peace in Europe.
The United States and NATO justified their
nuclear weapons strategy as necessary for their
security against the perceived threat of the Soviet
Union's massive conventional forces and, later, the
combination of nuclear and conventional forces.
There is no way of testing this proposition, but its
logic has appealed to many other states and their
decision-makers.
A very large number of states do not have the
means to acquire nuclear capability, or lack suf¬
ficiently strong security incentives to do so.
Others have been coupled in the past to the
nuclear weapons of the two superpowers. But a
powerful logic in favour of acquiring nuclear
weapons for their own security has been oper¬
ating in many states, which have been swayed by
the rationale of nuclear deterrence. In such situ¬
ations a "ripple effect" takes place as other, neigh¬
bouring countries feel obliged to acquire nuclear
weapons in their turn.
Besides the security incentive, nuclear
weapons have acquired a certain aura in the inter¬
national system. The five permanent members of
the United Nations Security Council are nuclear
weapon states, and there have been many inci¬
dents in which a state has used nuclear weapons
as an instrument of policy to coerce others. These
and other factors create incentives for prolifera¬
tion, which is a source of instability.
There is no intrinsic reason to suggest that
only the states of the North can act in a rcspon-
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
*&£&
War/Peace (1989), a
collage by the American
artist Pat Horner.
sible manner, although unfortunately the debate
normally implies this. China, a major state of
the South, has possessed nuclear weapons for
the past twenty-five years. But an increase in the
numbers of those who control nuclear weapons
inevitably carries serious risks, not least those
arising from miscalculation and accident. There
is thus no reason to disagree with the prevalent
view in the North that any increase in the number
of nuclear weapon states is destabilizing. How¬
ever the problem cannot be resolved by
addressing the question of horizontal prolifera¬
tion alone.
FLAWS IN THE
NON-PROLIFERATION TREATY
The NPT is the only non-proliferation regime
that has so far been established. The general view,
especially in the South, is that the Treaty is dis¬
criminatory, but this is only a small part of the
problem. NPT has failed to meet its own stated
objectives, especially when judged against three
critical yardsticks sound principles, efficiency,
and security interests. The number of warheads
proliferated from less than 12,000 in 1968 to
55,000 twenty years later. The twin objectives
of non-proliferation and disarmament set out in
the NPT have not been met. This makes it nec¬
essary to establish a more viable non-proliferation
regime for the twenty-first century.
The NPT has also given nuclear weapons a
certain legitimacy, while at the same time tending
to provide a false sense of security. States which
adhere to the Treaty as non-nuclear weapon states
are believed to be such, although the reality may
be different, as Iraq's example shows. South
Africa clandestinely built up a stockpile of at
least six nuclear weapons. It joined the NPT in
July 1991; its denuclearization will remain under
question. North Korea signed the NPT in 1985
but is pursuing a weapon-related programme.
Iran is a party to the Treaty but is suspected by
some of having a weapon-related programme.
THE COLLAPSE
OF THE USSR
The disintegration of the USSR has led to
unprecedented risks of nuclear proliferation,
opening three major areas of concern.
Firstly, there is widespread uncertainty about
the extent of control being exercised over nuclear
weapons. On 21 December 1991 the leaders of
eleven former Soviet republics signed the Alma
Ata Accord in which it was agreed that deci¬
sions about the use of the strategic nuclear forces
of the Commonwealth of Independent States
(CIS) would be made by the Russian president
"with the agreement" of the leaders of Ukraine,
Belarus and Kazakhstan and after "consulta¬
tion" with other Commonwealth leaders. Actual
control of the "nuclear button" is believed to
rest with Marshal E. Shaposhnikov, the com¬
mander of CIS Strategic Deterrence Forces, and
President Boris Yeltsin. The system docs not
have the reliability of NATO in the sense that
there arc no institutionalized political controls 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
It is becoming feasible to
construct a world without
chemical weapons, and
to go from there to a
nuclear-weapon-free world
is only a few steps down
the same path.
Soviet leader Mikhail
Gorbachev and President
George Bush of the United
States sign understandings
on nuclear arms cuts at the
White House on 1 June
1990.
between Russia, Ukraine, Belarus and Kaza¬
khstan. Nor can the stability of these states be
taken for granted. Russia has been resisting mul¬
tilateral controls even on the processes of dis¬
mantling nuclear weapons.
Secondly, it is hard to predict the effects of
Russia's domestic crisis on the mechanisms for
controlling nuclear weapons within the country.
In the former Soviet Union, control over nuclear
weapons was maintained through a balance of
tensions between three mutually reinforcing pil¬
lars of the power structure the Communist
Party, the KGB and the military. Today the Com-
munist Party is disbanded, and a stable political
framework has yet to be firmly established. The
KGB, which traditionally controlled the nuclear
warheads, has undergone a fundamental trans¬
formation. The military has been severely affected
by the dissolution of the USSR and the social and
economic problems this has caused. It was gen¬
erally believed that Soviet theatre military com¬
manders possessed delegated authority to use
nuclear weapons in their jurisdiction. There is
little to suggest that this has changed. In the West
concern has focussed essentially on the fate of
strategic weapons in the former Soviet Union, but
nearly 17,000 non-strategic nuclear warheads
constitute a more serious danger. Control over
these weapons has inevitably been far more dif¬
fused and uncertain.
Thirdly, the continuing social and economic
crisis in the former USSR has increased the risk
of leakage of nuclear weapon technology and
know-how. A nuclear brain drain could rein¬
force clandestine weapons programmes. New
trends in ethno-religious nationalism may provide
further incentives to nuclear proliferation.
THE DANGERS
OF PROLIFERATION
It was the transformation of political relations
between the United States and the Soviet Union
that made real progress possible in nuclear arms
reductions, rendering START itself obsolete even
before it was signed. Political relations, rather
than weapons per se, are the critical factor in
international security.
The biggest problem with nuclear weapons
may be described as one of asymmetry of capa¬
bilities. Asymmetry creates greater complexities
and uncertainties in multi-polar situations where
nuclear weapons of one state have implications for
a number of others. Inevitably asymmetry
increases with the increase in the number of
nuclear weapon states, creating instability and
providing a powerful incentive for proliferation.
Instability and proliferation, therefore, arc
closely linked. Broadly speaking, stability can
be enhanced only through one of two diametri¬
cally opposite methods global nuclearization by
extensive horizontal proliferation which could
keep the peace on the so-called European model
of nuclear deterrence, or denuclearization through
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Glossary
CFE Treaty: The Conventional Armed Forces
in Europe Treaty, signed on 19 November
1990, came into force on 9 November
1992. Sets ceilings on treaty-limited ("con¬
ventional" or non-nuclear) equipment in
the Atlantic-to-the-Urals zone. 29 states
parties, including the former Soviet republics
since 1992.
CSCE: Conference on Security and Co-oper¬
ation in Europe. Began to meet in 1973 as
a forum for matters relating to security,
human rights and economic and scientific
co-operation in Europe. 51 member states
(all the European states plus the United
States and Canada and the former Soviet
republics).
IAEA: International Atomic Energy Agency.
Established in 1957 by the UN to promote
the peaceful uses of atomic energy and to
ensure that nuclear activities are not used
to further any military purpose, it has 1 13
member states.
ICBM: Intercontinental ballistic missile
(range in excess of 5,500 km). IRBM: Inter¬
mediate-range ballistic missile (range of
from 1,000 up to and including 5,500 km).
NATO: North Atlantic Treaty Organization.
Established by a Treaty signed by 12 states
in Washington on 4 April 1949, it now has
16 members: Belgium, Canada, Denmark,
France, Germany, Greece, Iceland, Italy,
Luxembourg, the Netherlands, Norway, Por¬
tugal. Spain, Turkey, the United Kingdom
and the United States. (France and Spain
are not in the integrated military structures
of NATO).
NPT: Treaty on the non-proliferation of
nuclear weapons, signed on 1 July 1968;
came into force on 5 March 1970. It pro¬
hibits nuclear weapon states from trans¬
ferring to other states nuclear weapons or the
means of manufacturing or acquiring them.
156 states are parties to the Treaty.
SALT: Strategic Arms Limitation Talks. Nego¬
tiations between the United States and the
USSR which sought to limit the strategic
nuclear forces of both sides and resulted in
two treaties. The SALT I Agreements and the
ABM Treaty limiting the development,
testing and deployment of Anti-Ballistic
Missile Systems were signed in 1972. The
SALT II Treaty was signed in 1979 but never
ratified.
START: Strategic Arms Reduction Talks.
US-Soviet treaty, signed on 31 July 1991,
which reduces US and Soviet offensive
strategic nuclear weapons. In view of the
new political situation in Eastern Europe, a
protocol was signed at Lisbon on 23 May
1992 by the United States, Belarus, Kaza¬
khstan, Russia and Ukraine.
TNF: Theatre or tactical nuclear forces (also
called non-strategic nuclear forces). Nuclear
weapons with ranges of up to and including
5,500 km. The US-Soviet Intermediate-
range nuclear forces (INF) Treaty of 1987
obliged the United States and the USSR to
destroy all land-based missiles with a range
of 500-5,500 km (intermediate range and
shorter-range) and their launchers by June
1991.
UN: United Nations Organization. Interna¬
tional organization established in June 1945
by the San Francisco Treaty in succession to
the League of Nations, which was officially
dissolved in July 1947. It seeks to maintain
world security and peace and works on
behalf of international co-operation for eco¬
nomic and social progress and respect for
human rights. Its principal organs are the
General Assembly (where each of the 183
member states has one vote), the Security
Council (five permanent members: China,
France, Russia, the United Kingdom and the
United States, plus ten members elected for
two years), the Secretariat, the Economic
and Social Council (54 members elected by
the General Assembly for three years), and
the International Court of Justice.
WTO: The Warsaw Treaty Organization, or
Warsaw Pact, was established in 1955 by a
treaty of friendship and mutual assistance
between 8 countries: Albania, Bulgaria,
Czechoslovakia, the German Democratic
Republic, Hungary, Poland, Rumania and
the USSR. Dissolved on 1 July 1991.
Sources: United Nations, Stockholm
International Peace Research Institute (SIPRI)
JASJIT SINGH,
of India, is director of the
Institute for Defence Studies
and Analyses in New Delhi.
A member of India's
National Security Advisory
Board, he is the author of
several works on defence,
including Air Power in
Modern Warfare.
complete and global nuclear disarmament. It is
obvious which one would be the better option.
Denuclearization has traditionally been con¬
sidered too idealistic on the grounds that nuclear
weapons cannot be disinvented, and in theory the
problem of the rogue state and violations would
always remain. However, the Chemical Weapons
Convention now awaiting approval by the United
Nations General Assembly is quite relevant here
and could be taken as a model for dealing with the
threat of nuclear weapons. One of the most pos¬
itive results of the end of the Cold War, this Con¬
vention is based on the principles of universality
and comprehensiveness and includes provisions
for extensive verification and routine inspection.
This is particularly important since chemical
weapons arc easier to manufacture than nuclear
weapons, and even the less developed states of the
South have some access to technology and
resources to develop them because of the exten¬
sive and expanding chemical industry. Violations
of non-proliferation agreements concerning
nuclear weapons would thus be far easier to
check than those concerning chemical weapons.
It is becoming feasible to construct a world
without chemical weapons, and to go from there
to a nuclear-weapon-free world is only a few
steps down the same path. Denuclearization,
however, will have to be dealt with on the con¬
ceptual as well as the physical level. The problem
with nuclear weapons is that belief systems have
been built up to support the idea that they are
usable and indeed almost indispensable to inter¬
national security. If the dangers of proliferation
are to be addressed on a durable basis, steps must
be taken to counter these ideas. The real dan¬
gers of nuclear proliferation stem from nuclear
fundamentalism.
Nuclear fundamentalism needs to be tackled
at the conceptual level. This is why 138 states,
mostly of the South, have been regularly voting
at the UN since 1978 for a convention to outlaw
the use and threat of use of nuclear weapons.
This would be the most powerful method of
delegitimizing nuclear weapons and eroding
the concept of their utility. At the same time,
methods of maintaining national security need
re-examination.
In defence of their sovereignty nation-states
have traditionally sought to enhance their own
security at the cost of the security of other states.
Nuclear weapons, of course, represent an extreme
example of this process. The result is a competi¬
tive security framework that seeks to create and
exploit vulnerability in other states. This approach
should be replaced by a move towards a co-oper¬
ative security framework in which the security of
each side becomes of equal importance, the two
sides make allowances for each other's minimum
needs, and co-operate not to raise each other's
levels of insecurity. This would represent a com¬
prehensive model of collective security. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
TÏÏÏÏÎ
40
UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
JORGE CHANIHÉ SINCS FOR BOGOTÁ
STREET CHILDREN
The Spanish baritone Jorge Chaminé
will sing works by Joaquin Turina,
Claudio Carneyro, Joaquin Nin,
"Modinhas" Luso and Carlos
Guastavlno at a concert to be held at
Unesco Headquarters in Paris in aid of
the street children of Bogotá
(Colombia). All proceeds from the
concert will go to an association called
"La Bergerie", which has since 1987
been providing shelter, medical care and
training for abandoned children In a
number of centres in and around the
Colombian capital. The concert, on
behalf of an effort jointly supported by
Unesco and the United Nations
Children's Fund (UNICEF), will take
place on 12 October 1993. For further
information please call: 45 68 17 18 or
45 68 17 19.
AID TO CHERNOBYL VICTIMS
CONTINUES
On 28 April 1986, one of the reactors
at the Chernobyl nuclear power plant
exploded, contaminating hundreds of
thousands of hectares of forests, lakes,
rivers and arable land in the republics of
Ukraine and Belarus and in the
Federation of Russia and exposing many
thousands of people to potentially
harmful doses of radiation. In response
to the call of the three republics for
international assistance, a Unesco-
Chernobyl Programme was created in
1 990. Of 70 projects proposed as part
of the programme, 30 are now
underway, notably through the
establishment of nine pilot psychological
rehabilitation community centres, the
development of an Economic and Social
Development Area in Russia and of
facilities to build prefabricated housing.
UNESCO LITERACY AWARDS FOR 1993
On International Literacy Day (8
September), Indian President Dr.
Shankar Dayal Sharma presented
Unesco's literacy prizes for 1993 at a
ceremony in New Delhi attended by the
Director-General of Unesco, Mr.
Federico Mayor. Dr. Sharma, who noted
that "Literacy and National Integration"
was the theme chosen for this year's
Literacy Day in India, presented the
Noma Prize to the Indian National
Federation of Unesco Clubs and
Associations, the King Sejong Literacy
Prize to the Illiteracy Eradication and
Adult Education Project of Jordan's
Ministry of Education, and the
International Reading Association
Award to the Sebenta National Institute
of Swaziland. All three winners have
been actively promoting community
participation, distributing literacy
material and conducting adult literacy
classes in rural areas in their countries.
A UNESCO REPORT
ON EDUCATION FOR ALL
The first of a series, a new report by
Unesco entitled "Education for All:
Status and Trends" has been produced
as part of Unesco's responsibility to
monitor progress towards the goals
adopted by 1 55 countries at the World
Conference on Education for All held at
Jomtien (Thailand) in March 1990. The
report ranks developing countries
according to their net enrolment ratio
for primary schooling, defined as the
number of pupils in the primary-school
age group who are enrolled in school,
expressed as a percentage of the total
population of that age group. According
to the report, there are also an
estimated 948 million illiterate adults
worldwide. However, Unesco estimates
that if present trends continue, this
figure will drop during the 1990s to
about 935 million by the end of the
century. Published by Unesco for the
International Consultative Forum on
Education for All, the report gives an
overview of the situation of basic
education and the direction it is taking.
It is available on request from the Press
Room, Office of Public Information,
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy,
75352 Paris 07 SP, France.
Tel: (33- 1 ) 45 68 1 7 45 and 45 68 1 7 46;
Fax: (33-1) 44 49 06 92.
WORLD HERITAGE DESK
DIARY 1994
The 1994 Unesco World Heritage Desk
Diary, now on sale, contains superb full-
colour photos of monuments,
sanctuaries and national parks included
in the World Heritage List, with
explanatory texts in English, French and
Spanish. By offering this desk diary as a
gift you will also help to preserve the
artistic and natural heritage of mankind.
Format: 17 x 23.5 cm, 72 pages. Price:
92 French francs (including postage).
Orders should be sent to: Unesco,
Sales Division, 7 Place de Fontenoy,
75352 Paris 07 SP, France.
CORRECTION
In our September 1993 issue, Rhythm,
gesture and the sacred, information given
in the caption to the photos (pages 34-
35) of Indian symbolic hand gestures
(mudras) was erroneous. The caption
should have read as follows: "Clockwise
from photo below: peak; tortoise; open
lotus; half moon; a parrot's head, the
head of a deer." We apologize for this
error.
CONHENTUff
by
Federico
Mayor
This article is one
of a series in which
the Director-General
of Unesco sets out
his thinking on matters
of current concern
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
CULTURE FIRST AND LAST
THE fundamental role of culture in development, in the
building of peace and democracy, and in the preservation
of the environment is now starting to appear in large let¬
ters at the top of the international list of priorities.
Culture used to be a flower. Then it grew into a tree. Now it
has become a fruit. What was yesterday a mere ornament is
today the very centre and soul of the human adventure. We
used to look upon it as an adjunct; we are coming to sec that it
is the heart of the matter. And so there is a need for a new
approach to development that will at last recognize the decisive
role of culture.
With the support of the United Nations, UNESCO has
created a World Commission on Culture and Development,
thereby responding to one of the major challenges of the twen¬
tieth century. The Commission's task will be to look closely at
the links between culture and development, and to prepare a
report on the global situation. This is something quite without
precedent: never before has the relationship between culture and
development been the subject of comprehensive, coordinated
study on a world scale.
Sceptics will say "if you want to bury a problem, set up a
committee!" Unesco and the United Nations are doing the
opposite. What is more, they arc following the example set by
the Brundtland Commission, which proved the blase and the
cynics wrong. It is largely thanks to the Brundtland Commis¬
sion that the need for sustainable development has gradually
become accepted, that it was roundly endorsed at the Rio
Summit and that no leading politician can now afford to ignore
the problems of environment and development.
The work of the new Commission will also be action-
oriented. Its recommendations are intended to serve as guide¬
lines for policies in every area where development and culture
meet. The task will not be easy. As everyone knows, it is hard
to define culture, perhaps because culture defines us rather than
the other way round. A leading philosopher of our time,
Jacques Derrida, who is taking part in the public hearings of
the Commission, has said that culture is the name we give to
the unfathomable enigma confronting those who peer into its
depths.
The task of the Commission is nonetheless important, indis¬
pensable even, firstly because much of the world today is suf¬
fering from the development crisis that certain far-sighted
thinkers such as Edgar Morin forecast fifteen years ago. Old
dogmas and ideas that were taken for granted, the conventional
wisdom about stages of growth, the notion of importing off-the-
peg development models all that has flown out of the window.
What we need now is a radical rethinking of development if we
are not to find ourselves entering the twenty-first century in a
state of disarray.
Secondly, it is quite clear that the relationship between cul¬
ture and development lies at the heart of the problem, and
equally clearly it is at the point where culture and develop¬
ment interact that we will find the beginnings of a solution. If cul¬
ture and development pull in different directions, as in Plato's
image of the team of horses, each will cause the other to fail. If
development collapses, culture itself is doomed to decline, or
worse still may be tempted to withdraw into seclusion and sink
into mindless violence. It is only when each community is at ease
with a specific system of values inseparable from its culture
and heritage that the linkage between the economic and cultural
aspects of development can be re-established.
If, on the other hand, we deceive ourselves into believing that
culture is the be-all and end-all of development, many dangers
lie ahead: the danger of the trivialization of culture through
the commercialization of images; of cultural erosion under the
onslaught of standardized models of development; of a sev¬
ering of the dialogue and interaction between cultures and of their
giving way to hatred and violence; of the triumph of tribe over
nation, the Pyrrhic victory of fanaticism over co-operation; of
the danger that closed minds will triumph over open ones, and
that the dead hand of conformity will stifle the spirit of creativity
and innovation. Contemplating the bloody revolutions of his age,
Victor Hugo spoke of "this grim readiness to die."
Dostoyevsky believed that beauty would be the salvation of
the world. Culture no more offers salvation than do education
or beauty, but it contributes to it, and I have every confidence that
the World Commission on Culture and Development, working
in complete independence, will help to ensure that the power of
culture will enlighten us and suggest to us ways of creating a world
where it will be better to live, a world with a greater sense of sol¬
idarity, a world more receptive to all that is best.
PEACEFUL SOLUTIONS
Far from getting in the way of development, culture is its source,
as history abundantly confirms, from ancient China to the
European Renaissance and the Enlightenment, from the Islam
of medieval times to the Japan of the Tokugawa and Meiji eras.
Culture is not an obstacle to development, to be negotiated or
destroyed; it is its opportunity and its stimulus. It is the main¬
spring, the horizon and the goal of all human transformation.
Without culture as its foundation and its goal, development
will go the way of all ephemeral creations, like a ghost town aban¬
doned after a gold rush. Culture is not just development's
"accession of soul": it is its very heart and soul, the heart and soul
that both South and North need to rediscover together by
drawing up the "cultural contract" of solidarity and sharing
which Javier Pérez de Cucllar, President of the new Commission,
has so well described.
It would be hard to imagine anyone better endowed than he
with the necessary skill, natural authority, breadth of vision,
moral standing, impartiality and readiness for dialogue that are
indispensable for such a task.
History mostly records the names of generals who won
battles but seldom preserves the names of those who excelled in
avoiding them. Javier Pérez de Cuéllar is a fortunate exception
to that rule. During his two terms of office as Secretary-General
of the United Nations, he was successful whenever the cards
he held allowed him to do so in extinguishing the fires of war
and lighting the lamps of peace. A man of harmony, he gave deci¬
sive impetus to the peaceful solution of many conflicts.
If one day we decide to stop recording the history of wars
and massacres and to write the history of peace an account of
how generosity, love, modesty, wisdom and the silent virtues
overcome cruelty, hatred, unbridled lusts and fascination with
death I am convinced that one of its finest chapters will be
devoted to Javier Pérez de Cuéllar. And I trust that chapter
will include a memorable account of his work at the head of the
World Commission on Culture and Development. H
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
R H
Goethe, a mindfor the universal
The Committee on Arts and Letters ofthe
International Institute ofIntellectual Co¬
operation organized a symposium on
Goethe in Trankfurtfrom 12-14 May 1932
to mark the centenary ofthe German
poet's death.' The eighteen speakers,2 who
addressed topics as varied as the poet's
interests, all reached the same conclusion
in differing but consensual terms: the
versatile author o/Werther had a central
preoccupation which we have called a
concernfor universalitya continuing
urge to achieve harmony and reconcile
opposites, andjoy in the richness ofunity
in diversity.
Goethe visiting the Coliseum in Rome,
a painting by the German artist Jacob Philipp (1737-1807).
41
Texts selected and presented
by Edgardo Canton
(Í ^"^ [;iln from the summits of pure
reason," wrote Goethe, "the
whole of life seems to be a nasty
illness, and the world is like a madhouse."
That was a real writer's expression an
expression of pained impatience with
humanity, such as is often met with, more
often than is generally supposed, in
Goethe's works	
Goethe's works contain many passages
in which he complains of the pain inflicted
on him by nastiness and stupidity: there
are many more of these passages than
might be expected or than it would be fit¬
ting to quote, especially since we know
from the example of Goethe himself how
courtesy and kindliness can help in the
task of reconciliation. To use a stronger
and warmer word for this kindliness, we
may call it love. Goethe was aware that
intelligence and art without love amount
to very little, that they cannot exist without
it, and that intelligence cannot live with the
world or the world with it unless it pos¬
sesses love.
This love takes the form of consider-
ateness, tenderness, kindness and a desire
to treat others gently that is typical of
Goethe	
But here I want to mention a thought,
a tendency and an idea that make up the
main expression of the mind's love of life,
namely educational thought. Goethe was
a true educator, as witness the two great
monuments of his life, Faustand Wilhelm
Meister. The latter work in particular shows
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
V
by Thomas Mann, Georges Opresco andPaul Valéry
how the impulse that drove him to pen
his autobiography as a confession and
self-portrait became objective, was exter¬
nalized in the social and even the political
sphere, and so acquired educative value.
This impulse and this educative voca¬
tion were not, however, born of inner har¬
mony but were the result of the inner con¬
flicts that perturb the Ego, the discords it
contains, the difficulties it undergoes, and
the struggle with itself on which it has
embarked and which it needs to confess.
The poet-writer is an educator in the sense
that he expounds problems which are not
part of everyday life but which neverthe¬
less are apt to portray or express the ideas
of the human community. "When the par¬
ticular portrays the general", wrote Goethe,
"that is true symbolism." . . .
A writer may be defined as an edu¬
cator whose own education has followed
the strangest route; education in his or
Cover of a booklet containing the
proceedings of the symposium held by the
International Institute of Intellectual Co¬
operation in 1932 to mark the centenary of
Goethe's death.
EKTR£TI£SS
SUR GOETHE
i j'tOémm i« .-mentiré 4* t* m-rl
her case always goes hand in hand with the
fight against the self. The innermost being
and the outside world become confused in
this struggle against both the Ego and the
world, and a purely objective education by
a perfect teacher is but empty pedantry.
THOMAS MANN
Humanity looks at itself in [Goethe]
and knows no finer image of
itself. He is both a summit and a
frontier of the mind. And yet no-one was
as fond of the genius of the people, the
fresh, spontaneous work of humble peas¬
ants, as this god of the intellect	 He set
out to encompass the whole vast field of
folk literature, to make contact with the
most outstanding creations of the most
remote nations, those which history has
placed in exceptional circumstances or
which have lived far removed from all civ¬
ilizing influences	
The poet by no means commands all
the tongues from which he takes the
poems he translates; but even though he
does not know their exact meaning, his
instinct comes to his aid. Not under¬
standing a word of the original, and using
a translation sent him by a kind corre¬
spondent, he manages to render its
rhythm, its sonority and even its word
order in short, the essential shape of a
poem. It is for him an amusing and very
instructive game to see how ancient uni¬
versal themes are interpreted by the most
diverse nations	
For Goethe, folk poetry is only part of
a wider whole, and for all its beauty it has
no real value except insofar as it helps us
to understand this whole, establish its
laws and define its boundaries. . . . No-
one better than he has grasped its modest
beauty, the depth and force of its
emotion or the immediate freshness of its
feeling. . . But that was not the end of his
curiosity: he aimed to go further, to dis¬
cover in what sense a humble piece of
rustic verse is "poetry", in short, what
"poetry" consists ofand what the subject-
matter of poetry is	
For [Goethe] there is really only one
genuine, true poetry. It is exclusive nei¬
ther to the people nor to the nobility, no
more to kings than to peasants. Anyone
who feels himself a man in the full sense of
the word will practise it successfully. . . .
Imperceptibly, stage by stage, starting
with an interest in folk poetry, Goethe in
the last years of his life arrived at the
grandiose idea of humanity reconciled in
the worship of beauty, more mindful of
what unites the human family than ofwhat
divides it. Eckermann quotes a comment
by the poet dated 5 July 1827: "I cannot
think of a column or monument to the
memory of a remarkable man without
seeing it toppled and trampled under the
hooves of future warriors." This vision is
unforgettable, of regiments destroying and
dragging through the mire men's
reminders of the lofty deeds of the greatest
of them. Goethe the realist hated war. He
speaks of it not mawkishly, nor in its cruel,
distressing, blood-curdling aspect, but in
its absurdity. He sees only one cure: the
union of mankind through thought and
feeling, through learning and literature.
GEORGES OPRESCO
Some men give us an idea (or an illu¬
sion) of what the world, especially
Europe, could have become ifpolit¬
ical and intellectual power had intermin¬
gled, or at least had had less distinct rela¬
tionships	
I see some such men as appearing in 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
HIVES
44
the twelfth and thirteenth centuries.
Others gave rise to the fire and splendour
of the Renaissance. The most recent, born
in the eighteenth century, took with them
when they passed away the last hopes of a
certain civilization founded primarily on
the myths of Beauty and Knowledge
both created or invented by the ancient
Greeks.
Goethe was one of these. I say at once
that I can see none after him. ... I was
thinking of trying to build up, starting from
him, the general idea ofwhat I call a "uni¬
versal" man not to be confused with a
"great" man. There are plenty ofgreat men;
they are not all universal men, and perhaps
not all "universal men" are "great men" in
the sense in which we use these terms.
... I thought that universal men would
be principally those individuals seemingly
relatively free of chronological, ethnic or
national peculiarities. There are some per¬
sonalities whom we can imagine being at
home in any age and among any people
and only accidentally belonging to the
race that is their own	
So Goethe is an example perhaps the
last to my knowledge of those men
whose mind and even whose character in
A letter written by Bela
Bartók on 30 April 1932
to the director of the
International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation.
In it he declines an
invitation to speak on
"Goethe and music" at
Frankfurt on the grounds
that he has not "studied
the question".
a sense call for a much wider formula than
the usual one by which other individuals
are constituted. A Goethe molecule is extra¬
ordinarily more of a compound than a
Sc/n'Wermolecule or a Byron molecule	
Had I looked for other types of this kind, I
would perhaps have had difficulty finding
any as representative as the one that sug¬
gested to me this appellation. As I have
said elsewhere, it is obvious that Napoleon
belongs to the same species, and that
Caesar isanothermemberofit	
Goethe effortlessly takes his unique,
unrivalled and commanding place in the
world of the intellect; and he occupies it so
manifestly or rather creates it, pre¬
scribing the conditions for it by his very
existence and so much as a matter of
course that the 1808 summons to and
meeting with Napoleon were bound to
happen, as though pre-ordained by some
conjunction of heavenly bodies: a sum¬
mons and a meeting that were almost too
devoutly to be wished, too clearly intended
to be a wonder, too obviously obeying the
command of poetic destiny. . . .
Goethe never forgot this interview, cer¬
tainly his greatest memory and the jewel in
the crown of his pride	
The empire that was built on intellect
in action and the empire of the intellect in
freedom beheld each other and talked
together for A MOMEN . . . and what a
moment! ... A moment which of its own
accord spoke the fatal words of the
covenant to the Emperor: STOP ME ... I
AM SO BEAUTIFUL. . . .
They talked of literature. Werther and
French tragedy served to pass the appro¬
priate time. But something quite different
was at stake	 Coquetry is essential for
such an interview. Both men set out to
appear at ease and smile as they see fit.
Here were two enchanters seeking to
charm each other. Napoleon made himself
emperor of the Mind, even of Letters.
Goethe felt himself portraying Mind itself.
Perhaps the Emperor has a more precise
awareness of the real essence ofhis power
than Goethe imagines.
Napoleon knew better than anyone
else that his power, more than all the
world's powers, was a strictly magical
power a power of Mind over minds an
aura.
He said to Goethe: You are a Man (or he
said of Goethe: There is a Man) . . . that is
to say, a measure ofall things, that is to
say, a being next to whom the others are
but sketches, fragments of men, hardly
men, since they are not the measure of all
things as we are, YOU AND I. There is in us,
Monsieur Goethe, a strange virtue ofabun¬
dance, and a fury, a destiny to do, to
become, to change, to leave nothing in
the world the same as it was before.
Goethe (and this is no longer my imag¬
ination) pondered, and thought of his
strange idea of the diabolical.
What a splendid Faust Part III Bona¬
parte would make!
PAUL VALÉRY
1. The three texts published here have been
extracted from the proceedings of the
symposium, which appeared in Untreuem sur
Goethe ("Conversations about Goethe"), League
of Nations, International Institute of Intellectual
Co-operation, Paris, 1932.
2. Karel Capek, A. Costa du Reis, Jules Destrée,
Henri Focillon, Julien Luchaire, Salvador de
Madariaga, Thomas Mann, Gilbert Murray, Ugo
Ojetti, Georges Opresco, Kagnar Gistberg,
Roberto Paribeni, Gonzague de Reynold, N. Roll-
Anker, Josef Strzygowski, Hélène Vacaresco, Paul
Valcrv, A.W. Waetzoldt.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Portobelo, a bridge
between two oceans
byJosé Serra-Vega UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
Ramparts and watchtower
of the fort of San Lorenzo.
In November 1502, during his fourth
and last voyage in search ofgold and
a passage to the Empire of the Great
Khan, Christopher Columbus took refuge
from Caribbean storms in a bay in what is
now Panama. As he wrote to the Spanish
monarchs, it was with a fleet of "leaking
ships, tattered sails, lost anchors and rig¬
ging, and very sick crews" that he arrived
in this bay which he named Portobelo
(fine harbour) because of its beauty and its
naturally protected site.
However a century was to elapse before
its favoured geographical situation made
Portobelo one of the great trading centres
between the Spanish colonies and the
home country.
A mercantile Odyssey
The fabulous riches ofPeru were brought
by sea from El Callao, the port ofLima, as far
as the Pacific shore of Panama. They were
then unloaded and carried overland to
Nombre de Dios, on the Caribbean shore,
where they were embarked for the perilous
transatlantic voyage to Seville.
At the end of the sixteenth century, the
Spaniards abandoned Nombre de Dios
ruined by the incursions of the Indians
and of the English pirate Francis Drake
for the new settlement of San Felipe de
Portobelo, hidden in the bay discovered by
Columbus. Surrounded by mountains and
forests, the new port was both easy to
defend and blessed with a beach onto
which ships could be hauled for repair.
Sanitary conditions at Portobelo left
much to be desired. Many of the 400 or
500 men from each fleet of ships sent out
from Seville died of malaria or dysentery in
the months following their arrival, espe¬
cially when they encountered the stifling
humidity of July and August.
There were violent rainstorms from
May to June, then again from July to 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
Inside the ramparts of Portobelo.
November, interrupted by a brief fine spell,
"the little summer of St. John." The set¬
tlers complained of the intolerable din
made by millions of toads and countless
monkeys living in the surrounding forests.
Occasionally a jaguar ventured into the
streets of the town and killed a pig, a dog
or a child. Snakebites were an everp resent
hazard, but the inhabitants wore trusty
amulets with which to protect themselves.
Armadas and mules
Every year an armada of some three or
four big galleons and a few small sailing
ships left El Callao on the 1,340-mile
voyage to Panama city, loaded with mer¬
chandise that had reached Lima by way of
Arequipa and Arica.
The land journey ofabout 100 kilometres
between Panama and Portobelo was highly
dangerous. After two days on muleback,
the convoy would arrive at Venta las Cruces,
where it divided in two. The first team
would embark on the muddy waters of the
Chagres river, infested with mosquitoes
and other insects, sailing in flat-bottomed
boats rowed by about twenty black oarsmen
or in pirogues hollowed from the trunks of
giant trees, each ofwhich could carry up to
two tons. Part of the cargo would have to be
jettisoned, ruined by the sun or the torren¬
tial rains, before it reached the shark-
infested estuary, which was defended by
the great fort of San Lorenzo. The convoy
then continued its journey along the coast
to Portobelo.
The other part of the precious cargo,
particularly the gold and silver, went over¬
land. The steep and narrow trail some¬
times disappeared altogether under the
luxuriant tropical vegetation. The trav¬
ellers walked in Indian file, with the team
leader keeping a strict eye on the mule¬
teers, who were regarded as potential trai¬
tors. There was also danger from maroons,
fugitive blacks who lived in the forests and
lurked near the towns waiting to carry off
the womenfolk when they came to draw
water or wash their linen beside the river.
They also served as informers and guides
for the English who coveted the Spanish
gold.
On the other side of the Atlantic, the
fleet which at regular intervals left the
River Guadalquivir in Andalusia for South
America also divided into two parts. One
set course for the Spanish Main (present-
day Colombia and Panama) and the other
for New Spain (Mexico).
The flagships were heavy galleons
whose task was to bring back to Spain the
precious metals of America. They were
armed with powerful cannon to beat off
attacks, whether from officially declared
enemies such as the ships of the Dutch
West India Company or freebooters such
as the pirates of Jamaica or Tortuga Island.
Their first landfall was Cartagena, a strong¬
hold commanding the Caribbean, from
which a tender sailed away at once to the
isthmus of Panama, carrying mail for the
Viceroy of Peru.
The Atlantic squadron usually reached
Portobelo in July-August or in December-
January, after a voyage of some seventy-five
days, driven by the tradewinds. To avoid
the September hurricanes, they had to
leave Seville by 20 August at the latest.
The forts and the Fair
In the seventeenth century, Portobelo
was protected by three forts: San Felipe de
Todofierro, whose 100 men and twelve
cannon guarded the entrance to the bay;
Santiago de la Gloria, which had a garrison
of 200 men equipped with thirty-two pieces
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
of artillery; and San Jerónimo, which stood
on a promontory overlooking the sea and
the port. In fact these were defences in
name only, for the humidity spoiled both
gunpowder and fuses. The soldiers, few in
number and poorly trained, could put up
little opposition to pirate attacks.
The Duke of la Palata, Viceroy of Peru,
had had the forts built by a noted Italian
engineer, Gianbattista Antonelli. The phys¬
ical labour was provided by English pris¬
oners, who were subjected to the humili¬
ation of being treated as slaves.
The town of Portobelo itself consisted of
two squares, a parish church and two con¬
vents, one of which served at times as a
hospital, a big stone-built customs-house
and about 100 houses made ofwood. Out¬
side the town lay the "Guinea suburb," a
district reserved for blacks, slaves or
freedmen, but this did not prevent the Euro¬
peans from visiting them during the fair.
The Portobelo fair, a great annual event
lasting forty-five days, transformed the
town into a gigantic market which had no
equal at that time, where goods from met¬
ropolitan Spain were traded against the
riches of the New World.
The sailors who came to Portobelo for
the fair set up in the square a vast tent
made of sails stitched together, under
which they piled up their merchandise,
each item bearing the name of its owner.
The town filled with Lima merchants, the
"Peruvian uncles" (as the Spaniards who
had returned to Spain from Peru were
called), and the agents of Spanish busi¬
ness houses on their way to Lima.
Spain sent cloth, carpets, metal tools,
paper, wine, arms and ammunition; the
prices were fixed by a commission repre¬
senting the authorities and the traders.
America offered cacao, quinine wood,
emeralds, vicuña wool, copper and bezoar
stones. Silver ingots were piled up inside
the customs-house and even at the road¬
side. If the chroniclers are to be believed,
there were neither brawls nor thefts.
The Portobelo fair ceased to be held in
the middle of the seventeenth century,
but it was long remembered with nostalgia
by the Panamanian bourgeoisie for the
influx of wealth that it brought.
Capture and decline
This short-lived influx of wealth
inevitably aroused the envy of the Dutch,
the English and the French. As early as
January 1596, the famous Elizabethan buc¬
caneer Francis Drake had tried to seize
Nombre de Dios, but died from an attack
of dysentery and was buried at sea.
In 1668 Henry Morgan, a Welsh gen¬
tleman turned pirate, set his sights on Por¬
tobelo. As was the custom, a pact was con¬
cluded between the members of his
expedition. Each sailor would receive one
share of the booty, the craftsmen (car¬
penters, blacksmiths, the surgeon and so
on) a little more than one share each, the
cabin-boys a half share, the captains two
shares and the commander-in-chief
Morgan himselffive shares. There was
also a system of awards and fines for
courage or cowardice, and compensation
for the loss of an arm or a leg.
Besides Englishmen, the expedition
included Dutch, Italians, Portuguese,
French, Africans, mulattos, and even a
Spaniard from Córdoba. A mixed bag of
ruined planters and ruffians from the back-
streets of European cities, they were nev¬
ertheless well-armed with excellent French
muskets and well-sharpened cutlasses.
Portobelo was easily captured after a
night landing and less than half a day of
sporadic fighting. The fortifications, with
their faulty cannon and powderless mus¬
kets, proved useless. The pirates, who lost
only eighteen men, locked up the towns¬
folk in the church, and celebrated their
triumph with wine and with women who
were dragged to the festivities against their
will. Then they began roasting the resi¬
dents' feet to force them to disclose where
they had hidden their savings. Portobelo's
wealthy traders eventually had to pay
100,000 pesos to avoid having the forts
demolished as a reprisal because the royal
treasury was virtually empty.
In 1739, the English Admiral Edward
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
Vernon with just six ships in turn seized
the wretched town, and shortly afterwards
Spain terminated Portobelo's monopoly
of trade with the homeland as part of a
general move to liberalize colonial trade.
In any case, in order to avoid pirates, the
Spaniards now preferred the land route
from Lima to Buenos Aires or even the
long sea-voyage round Cape Horn. Por¬
tobelo slowly declined in importance and
became forgotten.
Today Portobelo is no more than a vil¬
lage with a few hundred inhabitants, slum¬
bering in the shadow of its ancient forts. Its
great pride is its miraculous statue of the
Black Christ, sculpted from a hardwood so
heavy that it does not float. Each year on 21
October, the statue is brought out from
the main church and carried in a religious
procession.
EZZE aHaaaHiB
JOSE SERRA-VEGA,
a Peruvian engineer and former staff member
of the United Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP), has worked in the Indian
subcontinent on technologies geared to
environmental conservation.
PHILATELY The French Post Office is issuing
these two stamps on the theme of the safeguard of the cultural heritage of huma¬
nity (2.80 francs: the archaeological park of Angkor, Cambodia; 3.70 francs: the
National Park of Tassili n'Ajjer, Algeria). The stamps will be on sale at a temporary
post office at Unesco Headquarters in Paris on 23 and 24 October. (They will be
generally available at French post offices as of 25
October.) Further information may be obtained from
Unesco's Philatelic Programme, tel: (33 1) 45 68 03 70.
4J
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
RECENT RECORDS
by Isabelle Leymarie
TRADITIONAL
MUSIC
INDONESIA.
Gong Kebyar de Sebatu.
Music and dances of Bali
Music from the World
Collection
CD Buda 9253 1 -2.
Afine recording of the
gamelan-gongorchestra of
Sebatu village made during a
performance at the Paris Opera
(Palais Gamier) in 1992. This
ensemble of metallic
xylophones and gongs, which
accompanies the ancient
sacred dances of Bali, is
conducted by I Wayan Susila. A
talented composer who draws
inspiration from birdsong and
other sounds of nature, I
Wayan Susila makes music that
reaches exultant climaxes
evoking the lushness of the
volcanic island of Bali.
NIGER/NORTH BENIN.
The Peuls
Music and Musicians of the
World
CD UNESCO/Auvidis D 8006.
Nomadic herdsmen
scattered across several
countries of West Africa, the
Peuls are rightly famed for their
spoken poetry, their love of
physical beauty and their
devotion to their animals. They
are also enthusiastic and
talented musicians. Their
music, more austere than that
of the forested regions of Africa,
belongs to the great Sahel
tradition, in which stringed
instruments and song often
predominate. Like most of the
world's shepherds and
herdsmen, the Peuls are
particularly fond of the flute,
which they play with great
ingenuity. The Peuls of Niger
are better known than those of
northern Benin, but in both
countries love and the
exaltation of courage and
beauty are recurrent themes of
their many songs.
JAZZ
RAY OBIEDO
Sticks and Stones
Ray Obiedo (guitar,
keyboards), Kenny
Kirkland/Rebeca Mauleon
(piano), Jeff Cressman
(trombone), Luis Conte
(percussion)
CD Windham Hill Records
01934 101422
Flowing and melodious
Californian music for a hot
summer's night, this attractive
West Coast Latin jazz is less
ebullient than its East Coast
counterpart. Besides Ray
Obiedo, both Kenny Kirkland, a
fine pianist who once played
with Wynton Marsalis, and the
Cuban pianist and arranger
Rebeca Mauleon, are
outstanding and deserve to be
more widely known.
OLIVER NELSON
Sound Pieces.
Oliver Nelson (saxophone),
Ray Brown (bass), Shelly
Manne (drums), Red
Callender (tuba)
CD Impulse GRP 11032
Recorded in New York in
1966, Sound Pieces is a classic
from the Impulse label, which
launched John Coltrane,
among others. It features the
inventive big band of composer
and arranger Oliver Nelson,
who has also written
authoritative theoretical works.
These arrangements are dense
and colourful, with a variety of
textures. Although less well
known as an instrumentalist,
Nelson is an expressive
saxophone player whose solos
display a powerful sense of
structure. "Patterns", a piece
taken from his book Patterns
for Saxophone which he used
when teaching composition at
Washington University, shows
just how the "thematic core"
concept developed in his
course lies at the heart of all
well-constructed
improvisation.
CLASSICAL MUSIC
HELENE BOSCHI
Vol I. Sonatas. Soler, Mozart,
Clementi
CD Musicae Fidelis ES 9306.
A pupil of Alfred Cortot and
Yvonne Lefébure, the pianist
Hélène Boschi (1917-1990) here
plays some little-known works
by the Spanish composers
Antonio Soler, who dominated
his country's musical life in the
eighteenth century, Rafael
Angles, Cantallos and Mateo
Pérez de Albeniz, as well as
sonatas by Mozart and
Clementi. Delightful music to
which Boschi's lively touch
adds further charm.
J.S. BACH
Suites for Violoncello Solo,
BWV 1007-1012
Anner Bylsma
Album of 2 CDs. Sony
Classical S2K 48 047.
These six Suites for cello,
here played on a magnificent
Stradivarius, are among the
greatest of Bach's works.
Composed while he was living
at the Court of the Margrave of
Brandenburg, they illustrate his
genius for fugue and
counterpoint. Questions of
technique apart, the simple
and sublime sound produced
by this instrument, which was
made in 1701 and belonged to
the Belgian cellist Adrien-
François Servais, transports the
soul to sacred spheres.
GLENN GOULD
The Glenn Gould edition.
Ludwig van Beethoven.
Symphony No. 6 in F, Opus 68.
"Pastoral." Transcribed for
piano by Franz Liszt
CD Sony Classical
SMK52 637.
It may seem surprising that
Glenn Gould, who expressed a
strong aversion to the
technique of Liszt's flamboyant
transcriptions of orchestral
works for piano, should have
chosen to record this
transcription of the "Pastoral
Symphony." I lis clear, slow
interpretation, with a tempo
that never loses its tension, is
sometimes disconcerting,
but as Michael Stegcmann
rightly comments "succeeds
in allowing the listener to hear
polyphonic textures . . . which
show the work in a completely
new light." An indispensable
recording for Gould's admirers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
BOOKS OF THE WORLD
by Calum Wise
JULIO CORTÁZAR,
A LITERARY ACUPUNCTURIST
"There was a time when I thought a lot
about axolotls. I went to see them in the
aquarium of the Botanical Garden and
spent hours just looking at them, watching
their immobility, their obscure move¬
ments. And now I am an axolotl." This
short paragraph, the opening passage of
one of Julio Cortázar's best-known short
stories, beautifully captures their narra¬
tive flow, in the course ofwhich a transition
occurs, concealed by subtle shifts of lan¬
guage, from one world to another.
From a starting point firmly set within
a familiar context, the reader is irresistibly
drawn, by a sequence of commonplace
details that accumulate until they gradually
change the original setting, towards some
completely different destination along an
apparently uneventful route. It is rather as
if, setting off from home in a precise direc¬
tion and with a particular goal in view, you
arrive in a totally unfamiliar place.
But to discuss Cortázar's work only in
terms of transgressing the rules of narra¬
tive and scrapping the conventions would
be to overlook this author's greatest
achievement: the creation of a multi¬
dimensional universe in which all the bar¬
riers are down, where there are only influ¬
ences and gentle transitions, from life to
death, from childhood to maturity, from
bachelorhood to marriage all of them
cleavages that, in our everyday world,
demand complex rites of passage but
which Cortázar condenses to a few gentle
and terribly intelligent words.
Born in Brussels in 1914, a school
teacher in Argentina, settled in Paris 1 952,
naturalized French 1981, translator for
Uni:sco, admirer of the French surrealist
writer Alfred Jarry, died 1984these are
the bald facts. The rest is literature in
other words, immersion in a universe
where the geometry of time and of the
way the world is organized obeys much
more complex, flexible and shifting laws
than those that govern our daily life.
This weighty 1,000-page volumein
which all Cortázar's stories are gathered
together between the same covers for the
first time includes, besides some novellas
hitherto unpublished in French from a
collection called Final del Juego, (1956;
1964), a collection of short stories unpub-
Julio Cortázar (1914-1984).
lished even in Spanish, In. otra orilla. These
twelve stories, written between the end of
the 1930s and 1945, are pure as the icy
peaks of the Andes and scalpel-sharp. A
few will remind some readers of certain
early episodes in the US television series
Twilight Zone, and all of them carry the
emotional overload that was to make all his
later writings so powerful.
Over time, Cortázar's texts became
more complex. The narrative structures
pile up and intermingle. Some could serve
as the literary embodiments of the Dutch
artist M.C. Escher's visual paradoxes
("Sobremesa" for example). Cortázar's
humour, present just below the surface,
fluctuates between irony, the absurd, and
a casual cynicism that he handles rather in
the manner of Dino Risi (in Historias de
cwnopios y defamas, 1962, for example).
Sometimes, however, it blows up into a
storm of frightening and devastating force,
like some wild scene carefully constructed
by Fellini and Pasolini together, as in Los
ménades, which describes a concert of
classical music where, in essence, nothing
happens beyond what the reader is
capable of imagining.
Demolishing reality
The French critic Jacqueline Outin has
written that "one of the problems that
most preoccupies Cortázar is that of time:
he wants to destroy conventional notions
about it. . . ." The best example of this
occurs in "The man who lies in wait," an
internalized account of the downfall of a
diabolically gifted cannabis-smoking jazz
saxophonist, who breaks off in the middle
of the best recording sessions to accuse
the other musicians of playing something
that he "has already played tomorrow."
More than merely exploring a theme or a
problem, Cortázar here shows his writer's
hand for an instant and half-admits that
his gigantic scheme is nothing less than
that of demolishing reality. With a nuanccd
style and sensitivity much more subtle
than the science-fiction of Philip Dick but
showing the same keen intelligence (born
of a hyper-acute awareness of the sur¬
rounding world) so keen that it can some¬
times transfix us without our noticing, he
pierces the flesh of the West at certain sen¬
sitive points in a kind of literary acupunc¬
ture of modern mythology, opening up
intriguing and dizzying perspectives on
the flaws in our universe.
In metaphysics as in syntax, in the
writing as in the subject matter, Cortázar
is an experimenter. This relationship
between author and text, which has the
effect of placing the reader on the stage
while the writer remains in the wings, is
neatly and precisely illustrated in a very
short story called "Continuidad de los par¬
ques", a flamboyant and, to the protag¬
onist, fatal demonstration of Cortázar's
ability to twist a story around on itself, to
wring the neck ofall logical reasoning and
to replace it by an apparent irrationality. In
this trompe-l'oeil of a tale the reader
passes at lightning speed from the story
proper into the story within the story,
which finally replaces the story and thus
becomes defacto the story itself.
This entire volume has about it a terrible
feeling of latent anguish, an elusive under¬
current running through every story the
muffled and ceaseless murmur of a nearby
river from which the damp can be felt rising
yet which remains always out of sight,
hidden by exuberant literary vegetation. In
"Relato con un fondo de agua," the vision
the narrator has of his own corpse drifting
gently by under the sparkling radiance of
tropical moonlight is very revealing of the
writer's fears ofan underlying despair that,
like the thinner used in tempera painting,
tinges all his work. Even more revealing is
his highly ambiguous way of dealing with
childhood, a recurrent theme in Cortázar
and one which, of all his themes, undoubt¬
edly benefits the most from his peerless
style. Mario Vargas Llosa has described that
style as follows: "A style which marvellously
imitates the spoken word, the fluid casual-
ness ofdaily conversation, the spontaneous
expression, without embellishment or pre¬
tension, of the man in the street. Of course,
it's all an illusion. . . . The language of
Cortázar is itself a fiction, magnificently
wrought, an artifice so effective that it seems
natural, a way of speaking that is drawn
from life	"
To enter the world of Cortázar is what
it must be like to travel weightless in space: 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
BOOKS OF THE WORLD
so radically are one's perceptions over¬
turned that one is left for a while disori¬
ented. He and James Joyce must be the
only writers who could spurn the struc¬
tural limits of language and thus convey to
the reader the vision ofa certain field of lit¬
erary and human expression where the
rational becomes no more than a special
aspect of the fantastic.
(This volume forms part of the Unesco
Collection of Representative Works).
Julio Cortázar: Nouvelles (1945-1982)
Edition intégrale. Translated into French
from Spanish by Laure Guille-Bataillon and
by Françoise Campo-Timal and Françoise
Rosset. Preface by Mario Vargas Llosa
(translated by Albert Bensoussan).
Gallimard, Paris, 1993. 1036 pp., 290 French
francs ISBN 2-07-072913-3.
RETRACING THE SILK AND
SPICE ROUTES
The general term Silk and Spice Routes
covers the many trade routes which, from
the first century B.C. onwards, linked the
Orient and the West by a chain of posts
where goods were bought, sold and
bartered.
Flexible and ever-changing, these itin¬
eraries were influenced by fluctuating
political circumstances as well as by the
terrain, in both cases taking the line of
least resistance. For more than fifteen cen¬
turies, empires rose and fell along their
way, causing only temporary and minor
detours. Thus from Changan (Xi'an), the
ancient capital of the Chinese Empire, as
far as Kashgar, the 8,000-kilometre Silk
Route passed south of the Gobi Desert;
then, after crossing the Pamir mountain
range ("the Roofof the World"), it divided
into two. Depending on the political and
trading situation at the time, it either
turned northwest towards the Aral Sea
then back down to eventually reach Con¬
stantinople (Istanbul) after crossing the
Black Sea; or it swung south of the Caspian
Sea and crossed Iran, Mesopotamia and
the Anatolian Plain on its way to Venice
and Genoa via Constantinople.
The Spice Route was even longer, a
sea-passage of more than 15,000 kilome¬
tres around the entire Asian continent.
Sailing south from P'anyu (Canton)
through the Yellow Sea, merchant ships
steered their winding way by Borneo,
Sumatra and Malaysia, then hugged the
Chola and Malabar coasts of India before
heading up the Gulf or rounding the Ara¬
bian Peninsula to the Red Sea in order to
gain access overland to the Silk Route and
the Mediterranean.
These long and often dangerous jour¬
neys through many lands and cultures can
be relived in the space ofsome fifty pages
in these two books, each abundantly illus¬
trated with maps, photographs, engrav¬
ings and drawings accompanying descrip¬
tions of the civilizations met with on the
way. Mainly intended for young people,
the stories they tell guide the reader
through the history and geography of the
subject. Each stage of the journey is
described in short instructive chapters in
which great events are skilfully blended
in with anecdotes, human touches that
bring the subject to life. Well furnished
with cross-references from one to the
other, the two books are written in a clear,
simple style and offer a broad overview of
these two great trade routes, so very dif¬
ferent yet so inseparable from each other,
which are still in use to this day, though
updated to modern requirements.
A preface by Federico Mayor, Director-
General of Unesco, begins by recounting
the Chinese legend ofthe discovery ofsilk,
and each book includes at the back a glos¬
sary of unfamiliar names and words as
well as a "Spice Routes time chart" and
an index. These attractive little volumes
form part of the "Integral Study of the Silk
Roads: Roads of Dialogue" project which
Unesco launched in 1987.
THE SILK AND SPICE ROUTES
Exploration by Land, by Paul Strathern.
Belitha Press/UNESCO, 1993, 50 pp.,
72 French francs. ISBN I 85561 160 0 or
(ISBN Unesco) 92 3 102761 I.
Exploration by Sea, by Struan Reid.
Belitha Press/UNESCO, 1993, 50 pp.,
72Frs. ISBN I 85561 161 9 or
(ISBN Unesco) 92 3 102762 X
SO
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, page 3: Abbas © Magnum, Paris. Page 2: © Ronaldo Rego, Rio de Janeiro. Page 5: Christian Vioujard
© Gamma, Paris. Page 7: Unesco-F. Dunouan. Page 9: Karen Kasmauski © Cosmos, Paris. Pages 10, 1 1 : ©
Leo Christiano Editorial, Rio de Janeiro. Page 13: Roger Ressmeyer © Cosmos, Paris. Page 14: © Samir
Khaddaje, Paris. Page 15: S. Compoint © Sygma, Paris. Page 16: M.T.I. © Sipa Press, Paris. Page 17: Stacy
Beker © Sipa Press, Paris. Page 1 8: © Musée National d'Art Moderne, Paris. ADAGP, 1 993. Page 1 9: Adenis ©
Sipa Press, Paris. Page 20: © Patrick Lages, Romainville. Page 21: Hayhow/Kevina © Sipa Press, Paris. Page 22:
© Pepe Diaz/Revista Española de Defensa, Madrid. Page 23: Paul Lowe © Network/Rapho, Paris. Page 24: ©
Joaquim Antunes, Saint Ouen. Page 25: Unesco-B. Von Droste. Page 26 (above): UNESCO-Amor Galarza.
Pages 26 (below), 28-29, 47: All rights reserved. Page 27 (above): Unesco-J. Jeffers. Page 27 (below):
Unesco-B. Houseal. Page 28 (below): UNESCO-Bousquet. Page 29 (below): © Clean Up the World, Sydney.
Page 30: © A. Geva, Israel. Pages 31, 33: Barry Lewis © Network/Rapho, Paris. Page 32: Claude Postel ©
Musée des Beaux Arts de Nantes. Page 34: Source S1PRI, Stockholm. Page 35: © Balu, Bangalore. Pages 36-
37: © Pat Horner, Seattle. Page 36 (below): Alfred © Sipa Press, Paris. Page 38: Laski © Sipa Press, Paris.
Page 40: UNESCO-Michel Claude. Page 42: © Lauros-Giraudon, Paris. Pages 43, 44: Unesco. Pages 45, 46:
L Bias Aritio © Incafo, Madrid. Page 49: Ulf Andersen © Gamma. Paris.
ThellNESCO
It COURIER
46th YEAR
Published monthly in 32 languages and in Braille by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31, rue Franco s Bonv.n. 75015 Par s. France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation:
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Beim (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15).
Administrative Assistant: Prithi Perera
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mano Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Serpil Gogen (Ankara)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Sidin Ahmac Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksaren (Helsink)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donastia)
Thai: Pornnipha Limpaphayom (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Ghoti Khaweri (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelrrakh (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernárdez (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard. Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Grette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45 68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel : 45 .68 .45 .65
I year: 2 1 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder £or one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 1 32 French francs. 2 years: 2 1 1 FF
Payment can De made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
lrd:vidua articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the UNESCO Courier", plus
date of ssue. and three voucher copies arc sent EC the editor. Signed arti¬
cles reprinted mi.st bear author's name. Non-oopyrght photos will be sup¬
pl ed on request. Unsolicited niaruscnpts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by in inte-nntioral reply coupon covc-mg postage. Signed arti¬
cles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of Unbco or those of the editors of the Unesco Courcr. Photo
captions nnd headlines arc written by the U'JESCO Courier staff. The bound¬
aries on r-inps pjblishec in the magazine do rot imply official endorsement
or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Un£SCO tourer is pro¬
duced in microform (microfm and/or m:crofic:ne) by: (I) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Par s; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann
A-bor. Michigan 48 1 0C U.S.A ; (3) NCR. Microca-d Edit on. Ind an Head
Inc.. 1 1 1 West 40th Street. New Yor<. U.S.A.: (4) Bell and Howell Co.. Old
Mansfield Road. Woostcr, Orno 4469 1 . U.S.A.
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France;
DEPOT LÉGAL CI - OCTOBRE 1993
COMMISSION PARITAIRE iV 71842 - DIFFUSÉ MR LES N.M.P.P.
P"otoco~iposit on. photogravure: Le Courrier de I'UnesCO.
Impression: IMAYE GRAPHIC.
Z.I. des ""ouches. Bd Henri-Becquerel. 53021 Lavai Cedex (France)
ISSN03C4-3IIS N'' I0-I993-OPI-93-5I9A
This issus comprises 57 page; and a 4-page insert between
pages 10-11 and 42-43.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
VU/AÜÍ _»#-,
¡53 ~siTsUIiU^i
Faites de vos élèves de vrais Européens !
L'EUROPE À PORTÉE DE L ÉCOLE !
De classes européennes en séjours culturels,
"Voyages scolaires en Europe" vous propose
une vaste gamme de déplacements avec vos
élèves ; vous choisisse/ voire destination et
nous aménageons ensemble un programme
sur mesure.
LA BASSE SAISON CHEZ VSE
VSE maintient ses prix jusqu'à la lin du
mois de décembre 93.
Les marchés de Noël à Nuremberg valables
jusqu'à la lin décembre 93.
A partir de maintenant jusqu'en mars 44. la
Hollande revit le Siècle d'Or : concerts de
carillon. Festival de musique, reconstitution
des plus beaux monuments disparus.
Le Futuroscope de Poitiers ouvre ses portes
entre le 15 décembre et le 2 janvier et à partir
de février 94. Le forfait 48 h est également
intéressant.
Deux voyages promotionnels vous sont
proposés en basse saison :
> un week-end à Londres du 24 au 27 février 94.
> le Carnaval de Venise du 1 2 au I Ci février 94.
Demandez nos programmes et nos
devis.
DEVENEZ MEMBRE
DE NOTRE ASSOCIATION CVS
La documentation pédagogique : à votre
disposition, un vaste choix de dossiers. Et si
vous avez préparé pendant un voyage scolaire
un dossier original, l'association souhaite
l'acquérir et financer ainsi une participation à
un futur voyage.
Les bourses pour travaux : pour permettre
aux élèves de partir malgré des problèmes d'ar¬
gent, l'association finance un ou deux travaux
réalisés par les élèves au cours d'un voyage,
s'ils peuvent être utiles aux futurs voyageurs.
Les voyages d'études : vous pourrez partici¬
per en priorité à nos voyages d'études réser¬
vés aux professeurs pour découvrir de nou¬
velles destinations :
>. Moscou/Si Petersbourg du 24 au 31 octobre 94
> Les villes romantiques du 2 1 au 25 octobre 94
> Prague tlu 26 au 3 1 octobre °4
> Tolède du 27 août au 2 septembre 94
Notre concours "reportage de voyage" :
une trame de recherche sur la destination
choisie vous est adressée. Vous nous envoyez
le meilleur dossier (récompensé) cl nous éli¬
sons les trois meilleurs parmi les meilleurs
dossiers (également récompensés).
-3~â
Je souhaite recevoir :
une documentation sur les voyages d'études
suivants
une documentation sur la destination
suivante
une documentation sur les voyages hasse
saison suivants	
la brochure générale \SE-93194
Nom
Prénom
Adresse personnelle
Code postal Mllll Ville
Téléphone
Discipline enseignée 	
b-lablisscnieni
Adresse
Code postal l l M I I Ville .
Téléphone
VOYAGES SCOLAIRES EN EUROPE - Le Trifide - Rue Claude Bloch - 14050 Caen Cedex. Tél. 31 06 07 89. Fax 31 43 81 31
LISEZ TOUS LES MOIS
ÉTVDES
Revue d'information, de réflexion et de culture
Dans les numéros de septembre et octobre :
Pourquoi la xénophobie en Allemagne ? Jörg Alt
Générations russes en conflit Boris Doubine
Japon : la fin des certitudes ? V. Shumizu-Niquet
Deuils et rites funéraires Maurice Abiven
La politique démonétisée Henri Madelin
La guerre d'Algérie dans la littérature Pierre Lepape
Choix de films, Chroniques de théâtre,
Revue des livres, Choix de disques
Le n° : (144 pages) 55 F, étr. 62 F
Abonnement : 11 nos / an : 450 F - étr. 550 F
Rédacteur en chef
Jcan-Yvcs Calvez
Pour recevoir un numéro ou vous abonner, envoyez vos nom,
adresse et règlement à l'ordre d'ETUDES à :
Assas Editions 14, rue d'Assas - 75006 PARIS - Tél. : (1) 44 39 48 48
Ou, sur Minitel, tapez 36 15 SJ'ETUDES
LANGUES & AFFAIRES
Diplômes de Langues
à vocation professionnelle
Pour rentabiliser vos connaissances
et votre compétence en langue(s) !
' Affaires, gestion, commerce
Chambres de commerce étrangères
anglais, allemand, espagnol, italien, russe
Certificat européen d'anglais des affaires
i Communication
Certificats européens de langues
anglais, allemand, espagnol, italien
Diplômes de l'Université de Cambridge anglais
TOEFL américain
COURS PERSONNALISÉS À DISTANCE, TOUS NIVEAUX,
À VOTRE RYTHME. INSCRIPTIONS TOUTE L'ANNÉE.
FORMATION PROFESSIONNELLE CONTINUE.
Documentation sur formations et diplômes
+ tests gratuits :
LANGUES & AFFAIRES
Service 5413, 35 rue Collange
92303 Paris-Levallois. Tél.: (1) 42.70.81.88
Fax : (1) 47.31.80.96 - Minitel : 36 15 LANGAF
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
EACH MONTH, ESSENTIAL
READING FOR AN
'J. Ml ¡>1 /:!>i
PROBLEMS OF TODAY AND
THE KMWLEDCE BEARERS ... TELEVISIONS
... THE CHALLENGE OF DEMOCRACY ...
THE COMPETITIVE WORLD OF SPORT ...
EXPLORING THE COSHOS ... VIOLENCE ...
PSYCHOANALYSIS: THE HIDDEN I ... A TINE
TO LOVE... WATER OF UFE ... MINORITIES...
WHAT IS MODERN?... RHYTHM, GESTURE AND
THE SACRED... TIME TO DISARM...
c.fH MONTH: AN INTERVIE
CULTURE.
iSONALITY
SCIENCE,
FRANCOIS MITTERRAND ... JORGE AMADO ...
RICHARD ATTENBOROVGH ... JEAN-CLAUDE
CARRIÈRE... JEAN LACOVTURE ... FEDERICO
MAYOR... NAGUIB MAHFOVZ ... SENBENE
OUSMANE ... ANDREI VOZNESENSKY ...
FRÉDÉRIC ROSSIF ... HINNERK BRVHNS ...
CAMILO JOSÉ CELA ... VACLAV HAVEL ...
SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV ... ERNESTO
SÁBATO ... GRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND ...
CLAUDE LÉVI-STRAUSS ... LEOPOLDO ZEA ...
PAULO FREIRÉ ... DANIEL J. BOORSTIH ...
FRANCOIS JACOB ... MANU DIBANGO ...
FAROUK HOSNY ... SADRUDDIN AGA KHAN ...
JORGE LAVELLI ... LÉON SCHWARTZENBER6 ...
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN ... GABRIEL GARCIA
NARGUEZ ... JACQUES-YVES COUSTEAU ...
"NA HERCOURI ... CARLOS FUENTES ...
"W KI-ZERBO ... VANDANA SHIVA ...
AH STYRON ... OSCAR NIEMEYER ...
THEODORAKIS... ATAHUALPA
NOUI ... HERVÉ BOURGES ... ABDEL
IAN EL BACHA ... SUSANA RINALDI ...
CT REEVES... JOSÉ CARRERAS ...
..TER FROM FREUD TO EINSTEIN ...
FERRY ... CHARLES MALAMOUD ...
'TO ECO... OLIVER STONE...
BRINK... JAMES D. WATSON...
IVITIES WORLD
THEME OF THE NEXT ISSUE
(NOVEMBER 1991):
THE
WORLD
OF
NUMBERS
ALSO FEATURING AN INTERVIEW
WITH THE ISRAELI NOVELIST
AMOS OZ
]]>
</page>
</document>
