<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="095141eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send
us photographs to be
considered for publication in
this feature. Your photo
should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
In which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
AND XOLOTL
( 1 99 1 ) sculpture in wood
and metal (height 1 .70 m)
by Georges Tardy
Quetzalcóatl, the Plumed
Serpent, one of the great
gods in the Aztec
pantheon, is here
depicted with his
companion, the
dog-headed god Xolotl.
They represent the forces
of life and creativity.
According to an Aztec
myth, the two of them
descended into hell to
gather the bones of the
ancient dead, anointing
them with blood and
thereby giving birth to
those who inhabit the
present universe. The
artist has covered the
wood of his sculpture
with pieces of metal from
motor oil cans in a
symbolic allusion to
industrialized societies in
need of regeneration.
<
¿^
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 INTERVIEW WITH
Amos Oz
F GREEHWATCH
HERITAGE
The valleys of the Miser
by jean Dévisse
ï UMESCO IH ACTION
ARCHIVES
Miguel Unamuno en the
future of culture
Special consultant
for this issue:
Tony Levy
THE STORY
OF NUMBERS
8
8 Editorial
by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
9 The origin of numbers
by Tony Levy
1 4 Sumerian sums
by James Ritter
1 8 The mathsticks of early China
by Du Shi-ran
22 The star system
by Berthold Riese
30 Making something out of nothing
by Pierre-Sylvain Filliozat
34 Hindu-Arab roots of medieval Europe
by André Allard
3 7 Words, gestures and symbols
by Paulus Gerdes and Marcos Cherinda
mContents
NOVEMBER 199]
Cover:
Figure 5 (I960) by the American
painter Jasper Johns.
UNESCO'S
GENERAL CONFERENCE
44
FedencoMayor:
UNITED
WE STAND.
The programme
fer 1994-1995:
SOLIDARITY
AND SHARING
TheUNESCO
jgpGOURIER
46th year Published monthly
in 32 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, I i NOVEMBER 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Amos Oz talks to
Edgar Reichmann
Amos Oz, who was born in
Jerusalem in 1939, is widely
acknowledged to be one of the
most gifted Israeli writers working
today. His novels and collections of
short fiction, which have been
translated into many languages,
include Elsewhere, Perhaps (1966),
My Michael (1968), Touch the Water,
Touch the Wind (1973) and
The Hill of Evil Counsel (1976). His
In the Land of Israel (1983) is a
book of reportage based on
interviews with Israelis from
different backgrounds. A committed
writer, Amos Oz has always worked
for a rapprochement between
Israelis and Palestinians. His latest
novel, Fima, has just been published
by Chatto & Windus, London.
EDGAR REICHMANN
is a novelist and literary critic.
You write in Hebrew, which is not a
widely read language. How do you explain
the fact that your work has an interna¬
tional readership f
My books have been translated into
twenty-six languages, including Japanese
and Catalan. I speak only Hebrew, which
is my mother tongue, and English. I've
always wondered what a reader on another
continent, steeped in a culture so different
from my own, might feel on reading my
books. I think reading a book in translation
is like making love to someone through a
window or playing a violin sonata on the
piano. However good the translation,
something is always lost. Granted, every¬
thing hinges on the translator's generosity
and intelligence. A translator should not
slavishly follow the syntax of the original
text but focus on the meaning and the
melody of words and transpose as well as
possible their music and scansion.
My parents, who were born in Russia,
spoke Russian and Polish to each other,
read German, English and French, which
opened the doors of Western culture to
them, and probably dreamed in Yiddish,
since they were Jewish. But when between
the wars they came and settled in what
was then the British mandate of Palestine,
they adopted Hebrew and decided to speak
to me only in Hebrew, if only to prevent
me, someone who was so drawn to the
"elsewhere" that had brought them so
much disappointment, from being tempted
to leave the country.
My father studied comparative litera¬
ture. It's because of him that I started to
read the great writers, the ones who ask the
fundamental questions that are asked by
men and women all over the world.
The concept of universalism may seem
vague and sometimes irrelevant. One might
well ask how an Australian or an Argentine
reader can have the same centres of interest
as an Egyptian or Pakistani reader, for
example. How can one find the secret way
from the particular to the universal? Great
Russian writers like Dostoyevsky or
Chekhov, Israeli ones like Agnon or
Brenner, and central European writers such
as Musil and Mann have managed to tran¬
scend historical and cultural differences
and religious and political commitments.
Your works are peopled by nostalgic,
uprooted characters at grips withpainful
inner conflicts and in search of an "else¬
where" that is hard, if not impossible, to
find. Are thesepersonal dramas metaphor-
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
ical expressions of those rocking your
country?
Authors from the world's trouble spots
are often suspected of using metaphor to
express their political commitments. To me,
political reality is a metaphor for personal or
family conflicts. The issue that preoccupies
me most is the durability of the family, the
most fantastic, the most mysterious and the
oldest of our social institutions. Man and
woman have not always been monogamous,
far from it! Their love never lasts forever,
whether it is carnal, based on pure affection
or has the form of a loving friendship. And
yet the family has survived throughout his¬
tory, indestructible in spite of many social
upheavals. Why? I have tried to answer this
question in all my novels.
As far as the links between novels and
politics arc concerned, I am amazed by
the importance some European readers
have attached in the last half-century to
"deciphering" all forms of literature in
terms of current events. If Melville had
written Moby Dick today, commentators
would sec Ahab as some kind of dictator
who wanted to destroy individual freedom
as embodied by the mythical whale. In the
West there is too much of a tendency to
read politics into writing that has nothing
to do with current events. Even in coun¬
tries and regions where the situation is
particularly tense, family life goes on, with
its joys and sorrows, births, unresolved
conflicts, divorces and reconciliations.
Although violent death is common in this
world that has gone astray, spring follows
winter and the trees blossom anew.
Some ofyour characters are fanatics,
lam thinking ofthefundamentalistMichel
Sommo and the intellectual Alex Gideon
in Black Box. What do you think of
fanaticismf
I am a son of Jerusalem, which is the
womb and home of all the monotheistic
religions, a city where the devout live side
by side with unbelievers and where very
different communities live a few streets
away from each other. And so I've seen
fanaticism erupt in all its horror. I have
also seen fanaticism elsewhere, in other
forms and in other guises. I think fanati¬
cism is the supreme fascination that death
exerts on some people, an urge that com¬
pels them to give it and receive it.
The true fanatic is not content to sac¬
rifice his own life. He must destroy his
opponent first. He does not exist as a pri¬
vate individual; he is always representing
something, ready to sacrifice his family as
well as himself for a cause that must come
first. But it is not the "cause" that triggers
the fanatic's murderous deeds, but fanati¬
cism itself, which is a kind of disease.
"Great causes" come and go, but fanaticism
remains.
Think of the incredible changes that
have happened in what used to be the
countries of the communist bloc. We see
the dyed-in-the-wool communists of yes¬
terday become today's ultra-nationalists,
former anti-clerical militants impose strict
religious observance and vice versa. A few
decades before, in central and eastern
Europe, we saw former Nazis turn into
communist torturers. And they were not
only driven by opportunism. No matter
which ideology they were defending, they
showed the same enthusiasm and loyalty.
They were true fanatics, driven as much by
temperament as by choice.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
I believe thatpeace and human happiness are more important than the
tragic options of the heroes ofAntiquity.
Alex Gideon, the hero of Black Box, is a
specialist in the human sciences who is doing
research into fanaticism at an American uni¬
versity institute. Like a researcher contam¬
inated by the virus he is trying to isolate
and fight in the laboratory, Gideon becomes
infected, in his relationship with his ex-wife,
with the virus he is working on. He becomes
self-absorbed, spiteful and vindictive.
In Knowing a Woman an Israeli secret
agent decides to retire after his wife mys¬
teriously dies and asks himselfpainful
questions about the meaning ofhis life. Is
this the work ofa moralist or an opportu¬
nity to say something about the human
condition?
In this novel I turned my attention to the
riddle in our fellow man, an enigma that is
not always where one might think it is. It
seems as if nothing is going on. I took the
spy out of the spy novel setting. My hero,
a secretive man and a loner, explores his
own past and that of his dead wife and
their daughter, an epileptic. Is he respon¬
sible for his wife's disappearance, his
daughter's affliction and the death of a col¬
league who took his place on a mission?
These questions are not answered, of
course. Death and loneliness are the main
characters in this book, which is a journey
of initiation towards self-knowledge. But
the ethical dimension is still there in the
form of theological questions about the
nature of good and evil, for example. Does
the Dostoyevskian framework of Crime
and Punishment still work? In real detec¬
tive novels the reader always ends up
finding out who the murderer and victim
are. In this one, the reader may be invited
to look into himself or herself.
These issues crop up again in Fima,
where the main character, whosepersonal
andsocial aspirations have been thwarted,
seeks refuge in the "thirdstate", the area in
which man comes face to face with eter¬
nity. Is this due to despair?
I conceived this book as a sort of theo¬
logical comedy. My character Fima is a
real schlemiel, the comic hero of Yiddish
folklore whose head is always in the clouds
and to whom the most incredible things
happen because he mixes up dreams and
reality. When Fima's father dies, bringing
to an end a long pdipal conflict, he takes
refuge in this third state. Like most people
who live in Jerusalem, Fima is also a kind
of minor prophet with his eyes on the stars,
in search of some mysterious revelation.
He is trying to find an improbable har¬
mony in which all the dissonances of real
life would melt into symphonic chords.
He would like to reconcile the irreconcil¬
able. Narcissistic, like so many intellec¬
tuals, he would like to be loved by every
woman and would like all women to love
each other through him. For Fima, the
third state is the place where there are no
more decisions to be made. He flees to a
distant, heavenly Jerusalem. He is a good
man who, alas, cannot manage to do any¬
thing good.
To him Jerusalem is burdened with a
guilt that he makes his own. Like Christ, he
takes on all the sins of the world. He feels
personally responsible for the intifada.
Like some of Chekhov's characters, he is
full of good intentions. If he can't manage
to translate them into deeds, it's because
circumstances are stronger than he is.
Your love forJerusalem is a recurrent
feature ofyour work. Areyou forJerusalem
what Svevo was for Trieste or Joyce for
Dublin?
I grew up in Jerusalem in a working-
class environment where each individual,
no matter how humble, was transformed
into a prophet or political scientist. Our
grocer rebutted Marx with arguments
taken from Hegel, and around the end of
the Second World War the milkman
wanted to put forward a detailed plan to
change the direction of British policy in
Palestine, which was then under the man¬
date. Later, my dentist, who came from
Russia and was a bit of a mythomaniac,
claimed to have known Stalin personally.
We kept open house and our neigh¬
bours came to talk to my parents about
Sartre and communism, America and our
chances of living in peace with our neigh¬
bours. Everyone argued in favour of his or
her positions and I, little more than a child,
thought they were all right, like Fima. I was
often driven to despair by the tragedies
caused by the fanaticism that repeatedly
caused bloodshed in our city. I was Fima,
but I was also the little guy with the
bicycle, the hero of my children's book
who rides through the city with his heart
full of bitterness and hope. "When you
can't cry any more, then laugh," my grand¬
mother used to tell me. That's why I have
faith in humour. When I was a child there
was one particular joke that I loved it
baffled me every time I heard it. Two men
arguing about which of them owns a piece
of goods ask a rabbi to say which of them
is the rightful owner. The rabbi listens to
the first man and then gives judgment in his
favour. Then he listens to the second man
and comes down on his side too. Back
home he tells the story to his wife, who
says, "How on earth could you have
decided that both of them were right?"
"Well, I guess you're right, too," he replies.
I think this story is still valid today.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Jerusalem has taught me about the
unfathomable depths of relativism, the
tragic dimensions of the human comedy
but also the comic aspects of that tragedy.
I have never seen a fanatic with a sense of
humour, and I have never seen anyone
with a sense of humour turn into a fanatic.
As a peace-loving Israeli novelist, the
highest reward I aspire to is the Nobel
Prize for medicine. I'll get it the day I
manage to put a sense of humour into cap¬
sules and administer it to people all over the
world so as to immunize them against
fanaticism. The elevator to the third state
will always be humour.
For decades you have been not only a
novelist but apeace activist as well. What
do you think of the latest developments?
With the mutual recognition of the
Israeli government and the PLO, and the
conclusion of the accords on the autonomy
of Gaza and Jericho, the illusion of a
"Greater Israel" has finally evaporated,
and so has the dream of those who wanted
to send the Jews back to their countries of
origin. However, in this historic autumn of
1 993 we have not yet reached the end of the
road. Let's say that today we are at the
"end of the beginning" together. Jew and
Arab, who are living on the same land, are
leaving behind them the memory of endless
suffering. After this beginning, punctu¬
ated by so many wars and so much suf¬
fering, we can see the first glimmer of hope.
But while the lucid, level-headed posi¬
tions of the Israeli and Arab peacemakers
are now inspiring the talks between the
Israeli government and PLO leaders, the
time for rejoicing has not yet come because
we are still steeped in mistrust and fear.
Waging war is difficult, but building peace
is just as arduous in a different way. Once
the foundations for understanding between
our two peoples are laid, mentalities must
change and peace must be made to reign in
these streets where the cries of extremists
can still be heard. It's possible. It has
already been done. The wars between
France and England went on for centuries,
not to mention the slaughter between the
Germans and the French. Today these peo¬
ples get along so well with each other that
they're building the European Community
together.
The mirage of total justice brings blind¬
ness, grief and death. I believe that peace
and human happiness are more important
than the tragic options of the heroes of
Antiquity. After turning our backs on fan¬
tasies that could never be achieved, we
have finally succeeded in talking to each
other face to face around the same table.
After all, the art of negotiation and com¬
promise is one of the great qualities of the
people of our region. Isn't it better to use
this art than to make war?
Today, at a time when the peace process
is under way, something paradoxical
between Israelis and Palestinians is
emerging the mistrust that stems from
love. Mistrust is the culmination of the
long struggle that has pitted our two peo¬
ples against one another because they both
love this blood- and tear-soaked land. Sev¬
eral decades of bitterness and frustration
have only made them more impatient and
heightened the temptation to say no. And
so we must make a tremendous effort to
clarify things in order to sow the seeds of
mutual acceptance and sharing in the minds
of everyone. The hostility that arises
between adversaries during the struggle
can be transformed into mutual respect
insofar as experience has taught them more
about each other and as long as the out¬
come safeguards the dignity of all.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
EDITORIAL
I HE interview which opens this issue has a symbolic
importance that will be evident to all our readers. Amos Oz is a
great Israeli novelist, deservedly taking his place among the
leading artists, scientists and writers from every corner of the
globe whom the UNESCO Courier welcomes to its pages month
by month. He has also been in the forefront of efforts to achieve
peace between Israelis and Palestinians, peace that has so
suddenly, so unexpectedly, ceased to be a dream and become an
ongoing political and economic process. Amos Oz has been in
the vanguard of those who have, at great risk to themselves,
reconnoitred the no-man's-land where dream and reality for so
long tried in vain to meet.
This issue also carries a dossier on UNESCO's General
Conference. The session that opened on 25 October, as well as
considering the Organization's programme and budget for the
next two years, will also see the election for the post of Director-
General. We have taken the opportunity to focus on some of the
issues and projects that are being discussed during the
Conference and to present Federico Mayor's views on this
turning point in the life of UNESCO.
Last but not least, the main theme of the issue is the origin of
numbers and the numeration systems that are among the great
intellectual inventions of humanity. The articles have been
written by specialists who were asked to explain in terms
accessible to those of us who may not be of a mathematical turn
of mind some of the latest findings of scientific research in their
field. We hope you will agree with us that they have successfully
risen to the challenge. I
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
vr ¡-i j ja» iiug
4MI -'
*?:J ... i MM^ í
'V'j.iYi
¿ire
^ ,
« . ü
F==}s
v~
The origin of numbers
The story of a great intellectual adventure
by Tony Levy
Above, detail of an ancient
Egyptian painted low-relief
depicting a table for
funerary gifts (2700 B.C.).
On it several numbers are
written in hieroglyphic
script (the hieroglyph for
1 000 appears four times,
bottom right).
IT is generally accepted that some animal species
are capable of perceiving quantitative differ¬
ences, such as a chick missing from the brood
or a more or less abundant food supply. The
human infant also shows a kind of quantitative per¬
ception in relation to familiar objects long before
it is able to speak. The development of language
and the use of words widen and refine this quan¬
titative perception, so that some cultures have
invented names for vast multiplicities such as the
stars in the sky or the sand on the seashore, and
have even attempted to quantify infinity.
D Counting and recounting
Of all the powers conferred by speech, that of
naming numbers certainly seems to be among the
oldest. After all, "numbering" means organizing
and putting in order the real world and our ideas
about it. This is apparent in the idiom of different
languages.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
English eighteen 8-10
French dix-huit 10-8
German acht-zehn 8-10
Ancient Greek
Modern Greek
okto-kai-deka 8 and 10
deka-okto 10-8
Latin
Latin
decern et octo 1 0 and 8
duo-de-viginti 2 from 20
Lithuanian ashtuno-lika 8 left over (from 1 0)
Breton tri-ouch 3-6
Welsh deu-naw 2-9
Mexican
Finnish
(from K. Menninger
caxtulli-om-mey
kah-deksan-toista
1 5 and 3
2 (from) 1 0 (in the) second (ten)
Number Words and Number Symbols)
IO
- In some European languages, for example,
there is a strong similarity or even an overlapping
between words meaning "count" and words
meaning "tell": compter/raconter in French,
contare/raccontare in Italian, contar/contar in
Spanish and Portuguese, and zählen/erzählen in
German. In modern English the word tale
denotes a story, but the word teller can be used
to designate a bank cashier as well as someone
who tells a story. So it is not surprising that this
similarity is found in older Indo-European lan¬
guages. Etymologically, the Sanskrit term for
number, sankhya, denotes a way of saying
things. The Greek word logos, denoting both
reckoning and also word or speech, derives
these different meanings from the old sense of
the verb lego, to collect, choose, gather, and
hence to reckon, count, enumerate, and then to
recount or say. Similarly the Greek word
arithmos means both number in the arithmetical
sense and also adjustment or disposition. This
ambivalence later shifted to the Latin numerus
and its derivatives. The adjective numerosus
means both numerous and harmonious.
Moving away from the Indo-European
languages, we find a similar situation in two
Semitic languages, Arabic and Hebrew. In
Arabic the word for account is hisab, from the
triliteral root h.s.b. The verb "to count" is
hasaba, which with one vowel change becomes
hasiba, to imagine, believe. Likewise with
Hebrew, which from one root, s.p.r., constructs
the words for book, sepher; number, mispar;
and story, sippur.
Words and numbers
Whatever numerical facility a given language
may have developed, the names it uses for num¬
bers seem to go back to a very early period in the
history of that language and have, moreover,
remained amazingly stable through the ages.
They are reminders of human strivings since
time immemorial to bestow names on the diver-
Different ways of forming
the number 18.
sity of the real world, and occasionally they
provide us with a glimpse of the process that pre¬
ceded and underlay the naming of the various
orders of quantity.
One example, that of the number 9, illus¬
trates the interest as well as the difficulty of
historical analysis. In many Indo-European lan¬
guages the word for this number is strikingly
close to the adjective conveying the idea of new¬
ness: Latin novem/novus, French neuf/neuf,
English nine/new, German neun/neu, Sanskrit
nava/navas. Combining the disciplines of the
linguist and the historian, one is tempted to
explain the phenomenon as follows: at the dawn
of counting, the number 9 was perceived as a
"new" level after 8. The word for 8 {octo, huit,
eight, acht, ashta in the five languages cited
above) could be derived in its turn from a gram¬
matical dual of the word for 4 (quattuor, quatre,
four, vier, tchatvara). In the light of many other
linguistic and cultural phenomena it turns out
that the number 4 really does represent a new
stage in our perception of numbers. We can
easily discern one, two, three or four objects
without needing to count them, but from five
A runic calendar (Finland,
mid- 1 6th century). Runic
writing, using an alphabet
of characters known as
runes, was used by the
Germanic peoples of
northern Europe between
the 3rd and 17th centuries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
A Phoenician inscription
on gold leaf in honour of
the goddess Astarte (early
Sth century B.C.).
onwards we have to count them before we can
say how many there are.
This is an attractive hypothesis, although in
such a field it is impossible to be dogmatic. If we
pursue our linguistic investigations a little fur¬
ther, we can even find new arguments to support
it. Most Semitic languages use phonetically
related terms to denote the number 9: Akkadian
uses tishu, Hebrew tesha', Syriac tscha', Arabic
tis'un, and Ethiopian tes'u. Arabic grammar
indicates that the word tis'un is derived from the
verbal root wasa'a, "to be or become wide".
Thus it is possible that the notion of "newness"
observed in the Indo-European languages recurs
in the Semitic ones.
Ordering, combining and
counting
Any number system, however elementary, pre¬
supposes the adoption of a small number of
symbols words, pictograms or graphic signs
structured according to two principles. A prin¬
ciple of order or arrangement distinguishes the
first symbol (one) from the second (two) and if
necessary from the third (three) etc., and a prin¬
ciple of grouping or combining interrupts the
series of distinct individual symbols by intro¬
ducing a symbol of a higher order of magnitude
which is then combined with the previous
symbol to continue the system. Thus "one, two,
three. . . , ten, ten-one, ten-two. . . , ten-ten or a
hundred, a hundred and one, a hundred and
two. . ." is called a base-10 system or decimal
system.
But other bases have been or still are used:
base two (the binary system), five (quinary),
twenty (vigesimal) and sixty (sexagesimal). It
seems likely that the bases 5, 10 and 20 were
originally chosen because of their relationship to
characteristics of the human body, and traces of
this remain in some oral counting systems. In
Api, the spoken language of the New Hebrides,
the word luna denotes a hand, and also the
number 5; the number 2 is lua, and 10 is of
course lualuna literally, two hands.
The variety of the rules governing the forma¬
tion of the names of numbers is a striking instance
of human cultural and linguistic diversity. The
table on the opposite page illustrates how the
number eighteen is formed in various languages.
We must recognize, however, that little is
known about the methods of reckoning used in
very ancient times. Certainly the numbers for
which words already existed had to be repre¬
sented symbolically. In addition to verbal
numeration manual gestures were used
(counting on the fingers) or physical devices
such as an abacus, a counting frame, a sand-
table or a knotted cord. To the historian, this rep¬
resentational numeration seems in some cases to
foreshadow certain forms of written numeration.
I Counting systems, writing systems
and alphabets
The advent of writing resulted in a fantastic
growth in numerical capacity. Written counting
systems or numerations may be divided into I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
,cx A 9 Y
1000 900 90
//
1 3 2? n n
4 50 300 400 5000
Figure /. Alphabetical number
systems
1993 in Greek alphabetical
numeration (left)
5754 in Hebrew
alphabetical numeration
.(right)
two main types: additive numeration, in which
a number is produced by directly adding
together the numerical value of its component
symbols, as in Ancient Egyptian hieroglyphic
numeration and in Roman numerals, and posi¬
tional or place-value numeration, in which the
value of a symbol (units, tens, hundreds, etc.) is
determined by the position it occupies. Thus
1034 (written from the left to the right, "one-
zero-three-four") represents one (thousand)
plus zero (hundreds) plus three (tens) plus four
(units). This system, which requires the use of a
zero (a blank space or a graphic sign) appeared
historically only in four civilizations with
written languages: in Mesopotamia, in China, in
ancient India and in the Maya civilization of
central America.
Though writing first appeared in Sumer
during the fourth millennium B.C., alphabetical
scripts were doubtless invented in the middle of
the second. The best-known and most influen¬
tial script was that developed by a trading and
seafaring people, the Phoenicians, who spoke a
Semitic language. It was adopted or adapted by
other languages in the same group (Hebrew,
Aramaic and later Arabic), as well as by other
languages less closely related to Phoenician.
The Phoenician alphabet only transcribed con¬
sonants, of which there were 22. The Greeks
later added vowels to it. The Latin alphabets,
descended directly from the Greek, retain the
order of the Phoenician alphabet almost
unchanged.
Mastery of this extraordinary tool led to the
development of a number of counting systems
12
S O
0ï
»
E91
y»
' HA- o 2.
figure 2. Use of the zero in
ancient China
Multiplication of 3069 by
45 (from a 1 4th-century
Chinese mathematical
treatise).
including the ancient Hebrew system, the so-
called "learned" Greek counting system, and
the Arabic counting system known as hisab al-
jummal or hisab abjadi. These were alphabetical
additive numerations, whose principle is
extremely simple provided the user knows the
order and numerical value of the letters of the
alphabet. The first nine letters correspond to
the nine digits (1,2,3,..., 9), and the next nine
to the nine tens (10, 20, 30 . . . 90). The remaining
letters are used to denote the hundreds. Thus
alphabetical numbers are written in descending
order of numerical value of their constituent
letters, in the direction of the script (figure 1).
Since the alphabet comprises only a small
number of different signs (22 in Hebrew, 28 in
Arabic and 27 in Greek), this counting system
initially only allowed the representation of num¬
bers below 10,000. Various expedients were
available for going further, but it became diffi¬
cult to handle large numbers. Consequently
scholars, particularly astronomers, had to adopt
the far more efficient Babylonian sexagesimal
positional number system and adapt it to their
script. In principle this numeration requires 59
different symbols plus a sign for zero. These
"sexagesimal digits" would often be expressed
in alphabetical numeration, thus combining the
power of positional notation with the conve¬
nience of alphabetical notation.
LI A legacy from India
The decimal positional numeration system with
a zero, as developed in India, gradually came to
supersede other written systems and is now in
virtually universal use. It spread slowly, however,
and in a complex fashion.
China, for instance, acquired a decimal posi¬
tional system of its own quite early on, inde¬
pendently of the Indian one, but one which did
not use a zero. It may even be supposed that the
Chinese could have designed a system like the
Indian positional system on their own. But the
introduction of the zero into the Chinese posi¬
tional notation seems to have been of Indian
origin (figure 2).
Nowadays schoolchildren in the West learn
to count with "Arabic numbers": but what
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
tint» iiipomii iuni'0 qnaan
io quiuqu» flew ín*ymíio
vH-ÍUÍlti Ol C 0 I I H, J
exactly are they? We owe our knowledge of the
principles of Indian arithmetic to Arab scholars
of the eighth century. In about 774 A.D. an
Indian scholar passing through Baghdad made
known a Sanskrit book on astronomy which
adopted the principles of "Indian arithmetic"
{hisab al-hind), and al-Fazzari's Arabic transla¬
tion of this book represented the first stage in the
history of "Indian arithmetic" in the Muslim-
Arab empire. The Arabic word sifr, "empti¬
ness", is a translation of the Sanskrit sunya. It
was chosen in the ninth century to represent
zero. Sifr gave rise to the Latin cifra in the thir¬
teenth century, the French chiffre in the four¬
teenth century and the German Ziffer in the
fifteenth century. It is also the forebear of the
English cipher. By a parallel development sifr
gave rise to the Latin zefirum in the thirteenth
century, the Italian zefi.ro/zevero in the fifteenth,
and finally the word zero. Western terminology
is unquestionably Hindu-Arabic.
We must, however, distinguish between the
spread of knowledge about the principles of
Indian numeration and the development of the
graphic signs used for its notation. The rela¬
tionship between the written forms recorded
from India and those that appeared in the Arab
world from the ninth century onwards is not
clear. Moreover there is a difference between
eastern and western Arabic numerals. While
the principles of Indian numeration spread in
Latin in the medieval West in the twelfth century,
the figures we call "Hindu-Arabic" spread
through intermediaries that have not all been
identified, sometimes borrowing from earlier
Roman or Visigothic forms in Spain.
A system for counting on
the fingers is shown in this
illustration from a 13th-
century Spanish
manuscript.
TONY LEVY,
of France, is a research
associate at his country's
National Centre for Scientific
Research (CNRS) and teaches
the history of science at the
University of Paris Vlll-Saint
Denis. His main centre of
academic interest is the
Hebraic mathematical tradition
in the Middle Ages and its
relationship to the Arab and
Latin traditions. He is the
author of a study on the
history of the idea of infinity
entitled Figures de l'infini. Les
mathématiques au miroir des
cultures, published by Editions
du Seuil, Paris, 1987. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Sumerian sums
byjomes Ritter
The origins of a positional system of numbering
in ancient Mesopotamia
Bronze head of king
Sargon, founder of the
Akkadian dynasty
(2400-2200 B.C.).
figure I. Three ways ofcounting
The arrows point from the
lower value to the higher
value unit. The number on
top of the arrow indicates
how many of the lower
value unit make up the
higher value unit, e.g. I
small circle = 6 small
notches in System S, 10
small notches in System S,
and 18 small notches in
system G.
System S (sexagesimal
for counting discrete
objects and measuring
lengths)
System G (surface
measures)
System S (capacity
measures)
WHEN, during the last one hundred years,
scholars began to understand the written
numerical system of the ancient
Mesopotamian world in the last two millennia
before our era, they discovered that it had two
highly distinctive features. First of all the
Mesopotamians used a unique system with the
base of 60. Secondly, they differed from the other
known ancient peoples by using a system of
place notation, as we do, to express their written
numbers. All kinds of explanations for the exis¬
tence of these two strange features were put for¬
ward. Some thought they might have had some¬
thing to do with the Sumerian calendar; others
that they were due to the convenience of the
number 60, so rich in divisors; others still that they
were the result of a psychological peculiarity of
the Sumerian people. We now know, however,
that the answer lies in the genesis and develop¬
ment of writing in Mesopotamia, or more pre¬
cisely in the relation between bookkeeping and
writing the fact that the original purpose of
writing was bookkeeping and was the outcome
of a process lasting a thousand years.
Since the Mesopotamians used artefacts made
of clay, a virtually indestructible medium, to
keep their accounts, we can follow the devel¬
opment of writing in Mesopotamia (and in
6 * . 10 3 _ ^ 6 _
neighbouring Susa) at the end of the fourth and
the beginning of the third millennium. Initially
bookkeeping was done using hollow clay balls
which contained small tokens of varying sizes
and shapes and whose surfaces bore the impres¬
sions of cylinder seals. The form and size of the
tokens represent the object and/or the counting
or measuring unit employed. The seal impres¬
sions on the outside indicate the owner or con¬
tracting parties, or the controlling official.
During the next several hundred years this
system evolved. First, the tokens were impressed
on the surface of the ball before being enclosed;
next, the tokens themselves were abandoned,
and only their impression on the surface of the
now flattened ball or tablet was retained; finally,
a reed was used instead of a token to create the
surface marks.
By around 3200 B.C., a writing system had
developed that consisted of a repertory of some
30 numeric and 800 non-numeric signs, used
to designate the items counted and geographical
and official names.
I A dozen different counting systems
A large number of different ways of counting
were used in Mesopotamia during this period
(3200-2800). These systems included one for
counting discrete objects and lengths, one for
measuring surfaces, another for determining vol¬
umes of grain (subdivided into a number of dif¬
ferent subsystems for different kinds of grain!), yet
another for measurements of time. There were
probably close to a dozen of these metrological
systems. Three of them are shown in figure 1.
To express a number in any of these sys¬
tems an additive technique was used; in other
words a number sign was used as many times as
there were units represented by that sign. This
can be seen in figure 2, a text showing the
number of sheep in a flock.
But despite the wealth of systems, the reper¬
tory of numeric signs was small. In fact, all the
signs were essentially built up from only four
different marks of the reed: a large and small
circle, and a large and small notch (figure 3).
Furthermore these signs were used only in cer-
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Mesopotamian clay tablet
used for bookkeeping
(c. 3000 B.C.).
Figure 2. Counting sheep
Explanation:
2x10 + 7x1=27 ewes
and
2x10 + 5x1= 25 rams,
a total of 5x10 + 2x1 =
52 sheep.
tain combinations: either separately (four signs)
or combined in the form circle + notch of the
same size or circle + circle of two different
sizes this yields seven signs in all.
These few signs were thus used differently in
different systems: the small circle is worth 10
small notches in the system used for discrete
measurements (system S), 6 small notches in that
used for measuring capacity (system S), and 1 8 in
that used for surface measurements (system G).
The "numeric signs", then, have no intrinsic
value, only that lent by the system in which they
appear. Furthermore the ratios between succes¬
sive signs their "relative values" vary from
one system to another. Thus there is no general
idea of number, only ways of counting.
For the 500 years starting around 3200 B.C.,
the range of texts produced in Mesopotamia is
very restricted. They are overwhelmingly
accounts, consisting of numbers drawn from
the various metrological systems with the addi¬
tion of signs representing the objects thus
counted, but also geographical names and offi¬
cial titles. There is also a handful of school texts,
lists of the signs and words, both numeric and
non-numeric, that the young apprentice scribe
had to master in acquiring his craft. The principal
role of scribal training was the training of a
corps of bookkeepers. The idea that writing can
be diverted from bookkeeping, and used to
record a spoken language the role of writing
which seems so natural to us was slow in
developing, taking over 500 years.
A dual evolution
Some time around 2600 B.C., the developing
city-states that constituted ancient Sumer
achieved sufficient size and wealth for writing,
hitherto found at only a few sites, to become
common all over southern Mesopotamia.
One of the reforms carried out during this
period of consolidation was that of the metro-
logical systems. The number of such systems
was reduced from a dozen to a mere handful,
one for discrete and length measures, one for
areas and one for capacity. To these three was
added a new system, to measure weight. Rather
than invent new numbers to indicate values in this
system, it was decided to use the numbers from
the system used to measure discrete objects, fol¬
lowing them with the names of the units of
weight. This system proved so practical that the
names of weight units and their relative values
were taken over into the surface metrological
system, and used there to express small areas. IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
This idea the naming of units was one
of the two major innovations of this period,
and was not restricted to the weight system and
its extensions. Even the larger units of length or
volume now began to carry names. The scribe
wrote a number-sign + "bur" for surface mea¬
surements, and a number-sign + "nindan" for
lengths. Of course once the names of units are
written, it becomes possible to see immediately
which form of measurement is being made. The
,, scribes of Mesopotamia were to make increasing
use of this new method.
The other important change in this period
relates to the writing of numbers. In the case of
areas, the sign [A] takes the place of the older [B]
(figure 4), the outer of the two concentric circles
being replaced by four crossed "cuneiform"
strokes (from Latin cuneus, "nail" or "wedge").
This is just one example of the growing
"cuneiformization" of the writing system
including number signs that is typical of this
period. To an increasing degree, the curvilinear,
incised lines of the older, semi-pictographic
form of the script, difficult to trace in clay, were
replaced by the faster and simpler method of
impression of the reed. This evolution of the
writing system, already timidly apparent during
the previous period, spread rapidly during this
Figure 4
* ©
A B
Q 0
C D
Figure 5
T ï
E F
Figure 6
TI n
61 2
period, and virtually squeezed out the older,
rounded numbers by the end of the millennium.
Speedy scribes
The period from 2350 to 2200 B.C. saw the
building of the first major empire in Mesopotamia,
that of the Akkadians, who spoke a Semitic lan¬
guage. Two of the innovations introduced by the
new centralized administration of the Akkadian
empire, which at the height of its power stretched
from the Gulf to Syria and Lebanon, also played
a crucial role in metrology and writing.
The systems of units inherited from the pre¬
vious period were rationalized and adjusted so that
simple correspondences would exist among them.
Although the complexity of the old ways of
counting was never totally banished, the ratios of
units tended to stabilize around fixed values. Fur¬
thermore the system of numbers used for mea¬
suring discrete objects now began to be widely
used for other kinds of measurements, coupled
with the use of names for different units.
At the same time the older numbers such as
[C] and [D] were replaced by [E] and [F] (figure
5). The long march of cuneiformization was
still under way. These changes, dictated by the
need for efficiency in performing the growing
number of bureaucratic tasks in the Akkadian
empire, have a double edge. Certainly it is sim¬
pler and faster to write the new cuneiform num¬
bers than the old rounded numbers, but the
speed is purchased at a price. The difference
between the small unit and the one sixty times
larger was quite small, a question of a slightly
larger "head" to the simple vertical stroke. The
Figure 7. The significant detail
1<4] 5<4I
2<9J 5 <6T 5<
i<7j 4<3I
3< 5<3
4<
2<
14 54 00
29 56 50
17 43 40
30 53 20
Figure 8. The sexagesimal system
In our decimal, positional system, we use the
nine digits I, 2, 3,....,9 plus 0; the value of a
digit in a number is determined by its position
in that number, each place representing a
power of ten. Thus, in the number 161, the
rightmost I is worth one unit, while the
leftmost I is worth one hundred and the 6 is
worth six tens, i.e.:
161 = 1 00 + 60 +1 = 1x1 00 + 6x10+1x1
x 10' + 6 x 10' + Ix 10°.
I
<= 10 = 1
16
Total: I 1/2 mana 3 1/2 gin minus 7 se silver
Column I (rightmost): 0 + 50 + 40 + 20 = 60 + 50 put down 50 and carry I
Column 2: 54 + 56 + 43 + 53 + I (carried) = 207 = 3 x 60 + 27 down 27 and carry 3
Column 3: 1 4 + 29 + 17 + 30 + 3 (carried) = 93 = 60 + 33 down 33 and carry I
Total: I 33 27 50
Since I mana = 60 gin = I 00 gin (base 60) and I le = 1/180) gin = 0;00 20 gin (base 60):
I 33 27 50 = I 33: 27 50 gin = I mana +33 gin + 83 se (rounded off, 83 se = 0; 27 40
gin) or, written more traditionally, I 1/2 mana (= I mana 30 gin) + 3 l/2g (= 3 gin 90
se ) 7 se.
In the sexagesimal, base sixty system, there
are 59 digits (zero is represented by a blank
space). Thus the number written by putting
side by side the three cuneiform digits
representing 29 56 50 can be translated into
our decimal system as:
29 x 601 + 56 x 60' + 50 x 60° = 29 x 3600 + 56 x
60 + 50 x I = 1 04400 + 3360 + 50 = 1 078 1 0
This is of course exactly the system we use for
reading time:
29 hours 56 minutes 50 seconds = 29 x 3600 +
56 x 60 + 50 = 1 078 1 0 seconds.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
JAMES RITTER,
of the United States, teaches
mathematics and the history of
science at the University of
Paris VIII. His research
interests centre on the history
of the general theory of
relativity as well as "rational
practices" in ancient Egypt and
Mesopotamia. He contributed
to a work edited by Michel
Serres entitled Eléments
d'histoire des sciences
(A Basic History of Science),
Paris, 1989.
figure 9. The Mesopotamian "zero"
There are two main uses of the zero in our modern
numerical notation:
as a number, for example one can add 0 to 5 with
the result 5;
as a place-holder in a number. The number 5020
indicates that there are 5 thousands, no hundreds,
2 tens and no ones.
The Mesopotamians never created the con¬
cept of a number zero. They did need to indicate
empty places in a number, however, and for this
they used two different methods.
The first method, used from the time of the
invention of a positional notation at the end of
the third millennium to the end of the first mil¬
lennium, was to a leave a blank in the writing of a
number to indicate that there were no units ofthat
particular power of 60. For example, the number
3 22 (3 sixties and 22 ones) was written as shown
in example Y (above), while 3 00 22 (3-thousand-
six-hundreds, no sixties and 22 ones) was written
as shown in example Y (below).
Very late in the life of the Mesopotamian civi¬
lization, in the Seleucid period (from the end of the
fourth century B.C.), one finds another method,
using a written zero place-holder, especially in astro¬
nomical texts. Thus the sexagesimal number 3 00
22 was noted at this period as shown in example Z.
«n
w «n
difficulty of distinguishing between the two
numbers 61 and 2, for example (figure 6), when
hastily written and read poses a critical
problem of ambiguity. The resolution of this
problem by the Mesopotamian scribes, probably
during the Akkadian period or in that just fol¬
lowing, was precisely to turn this ambiguity to
good use by creating a positional system.
I The birth of positional notation
After the period of disruption that followed the
end of the Akkadian empire, a newly central¬
ized state was founded in Mesopotamia; the city-
state of Ur successfully established a new empire,
which we call the Third Dynasty of Ur, or Ur III.
A single text (figure 7) among more than
100,000 from this period, has left us a trace of the
technical and conceptual revolution that took
place during the Ur III and the preceding Akka¬
dian epoch. A bookkeeping text dealing with a
delivery of silver, it is quite ordinary except for
one detail: the scribe has forgotten to erase the
mathematical calculations he made in drawing it
up. The writing of these calculations shows us
that, at least by Ur III times, the full positional
system in base 60 was in place. What the scribe
has done in the first four lines is to write down
the weight of four separate deliveries of silver in
positional, sexagesimal notation. In this system,
each place represents a power of 60, with the
numbers in each running from 1 to 59 (figure 8).
The signs used for writing these 59 numbers
are created by using the first two signs of the
now totally cuneiformized system for discrete
objects: the wedge for the value of 10 and the
stroke for 1. A blank space appearing in a
number represents the Mesopotamian "zero"
(figure 9). In the final line the scribe has trans¬
lated the sum of the four entries into the tradi¬
tional system for measuring weight.
As can be seen from this example, the ambi¬
guity mentioned above between 61 and 2 is
resolved simply by accepting it. There is no
longer any difference in the writing of the signs
that make up, say, 1 1 and 61 . Both use the same
sign twice. The difference is conveyed exclu¬
sively by the spacing between them, that is, by
giving a significance to the relativeposition of the
two signs (figure 10). The positional system of
Mesopotamian mathematics was born. And this
system was sexagesimal; the Mesopotamians
had chosen a sexagesimal system from the var¬
ious systems at their disposal.
So it was neither a psychological peculiarity
of the Sumerian and Akkadian peoples, nor mys¬
tical and religious ritual, nor again complicated
mathematical criteria of divisibility which led to
the sexagesimal, positional system of
Mesopotamia. Rather, pushed by the economic
and social needs of an increasingly centralized
state operating over a period of a millennium, two
simultaneous developments the increasing
reliance on numbers drawn from a single metro¬
logical system and the progressive cuneiformiza¬
tion and consequent risk of ambiguity in the
writing of numbers interacted to form the
number system that was to be used in
Mesopotamia for the following 2,000 years. As we
have seen, it was the increasing predominance of
one particular metrological system with its par¬
ticular choice of relative values which gave birth
to a sixty-based number system, and it was the
cuneiformization of writing that was respon¬
sible for the creation of a positional notation.
Most important of all was a possibly
unlooked-for result of these two developments.
The same number-signs could be and were
used to write the numbers involved in calculations
in all the metrological systems. The new system
was not attached to any of the traditional ways of
counting; numbers had become free-floating and
the detachment of number and measure was
complete. The end of the third millennium B.C.
saw the birth of the concept of number, abstracted
from any particular unit. ÎI
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The mathsticks of early China
by Du Shi-ran
The ancient Chinese devised an original
system of calculating using counting rods
Schoolchildren learn to use
the abacus in Nanking
(China).
18
THE origins of numeration in China go back
into the dim and distant past and since, as
in many other countries, no-one knows
precisely how it began, all sorts of legends and
myths sprang up. An ancient book called Shi
Ben ("The Book on Ancestries") tells how the
legendary Yellow Emperor, regarded as the first
emperor in China's history, ordered his sub¬
jects Xi He to observe the sun, Chang Yi to
observe the moon . . . and Li Shou to invent
arithmetic. The story of Li Shou became widely
known, and people imagined that he discov¬
ered the concept of numbers by himself.
But to credit the concept of numbers to one
man obviously does not accord with the his¬
torical facts; such a complex concept could not
have been worked out single-handed, even by a
genius. It is obvious that numbers gradually
evolved throughout the long history of
humanity in response to practical requirements.
Certain features in the evolution of Chinese
numeration can be inferred from legends and
myths, but more important clues can be drawn,
and more accurate deductions can be made,
from archaeological evidence.
Archaeologists discovered that some earth¬
enware from the 7,000-year-old Yangshao Cul¬
ture (excavated in Henan and Shanxi Provinces)
bore specially inscribed signs and marks. Most
of the marks were vertical lines, while others
were Z-shaped. These vertical lines are believed
to be the very earliest forms of numeration in
ancient China.
After tens of thousands of years of primitive
civilization, a society with a class structure
evolved in China. This was the slave society of
the Shang dynasty (circa sixteenth to eleventh
centuries B.C.). It is clear from archaeological
evidence that this culture was fairly well devel¬
oped, producing bronze weapons, household
utensils and sacrificial vessels. Around the four¬
teenth century B.C., the Shang Dynasty moved
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Detail of bronze bell
showing inscriptions,
Western Zhou period
(8th century B.C.).
DU SHI-RAN,
of China, is a professor at the
Institute of the History of
Natural Science of the
Academia Sinlca. Since 1 99 1 he
has been teaching at Bukkyo
University, Kyoto, Japan. His
main publications are The
History ofAncient Chinese
Mathematics ( 1 986, Clarendon
Press, Oxford) and A Draft
History of Chinese Science and
Technology (2 volumes, 1982,
Science Press, Beijing).
its capital to the neighbourhood of the present-
day Xiaotun, near Anyang in Henan province.
Culture and the economy took a further step
forward, and a form of calendar appeared.
I The oracle bone script
In the course of the present century, a large col¬
lection of plastrons the ventral part of tor-
toiseshells and animal bones inscribed with
characters have been excavated in the same area.
Research has shown that the nobles of the Shang
period worshipped the spirits of their ances
tors. In their prayers they put questions to these
spirits, inscribing the questions, the answers,
and sometimes the subsequent verifications on
the plastrons and on animal bones. The charac¬
ters used in the inscriptions are generally known
as "oracle bone script," and this is the earliest
form of Chinese writing so far discovered,
although isolated symbols have been found on
Yangshao pottery.
Among the 5,000 characters used by the
Shang people on the excavated oracle bones are
the earliest known Chinese numerals. The oracle 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
bones recorded how many prisoners were taken
in war or how many of the enemy were killed,
how many birds and animals the hunters caught
and how many domestic animals were sacri¬
ficed to the spirits. Days were also numbered.
Here are some examples:
"On the eighth day, namely the day of
Xinhai, two thousand six hundred and fifty-six
men were killed while crossing spears."
"Captured ten and six men."
"Ten dogs and five dogs."
"Ten cattle and five."
"Deer fifty and six."
"Five hundred four tens and seven days."
The largest number inscribed on the oracle
bones is 30,000 and the smallest is one. Units,
tens, hundreds, thousands and ten thousands
.. each have a specific character to represent them
(figure 1).
Ancient inscriptions on bronze have also
been found, in what is known as "bell vessel
script" or "bronze script," and research shows
that most of them date from the Zhou period
(around the eleventh century to 221 B.C.). The
numerals were written in a similar way to those
on the oracle bones. In the bronze script, how¬
ever, compound words are written quite dif¬
ferently from the oracle bone script. The modern
Chinese jo«, meaning "and" is used to separate
units, tens, hundreds and thousands. The
number 659, for instance, is written as 600 and
50 and 9.
In the Han Dynasty (206 B.C. to 220 A.D.)
the character used for separation in recording
(large) numbers was dropped and compound
numerals also disappeared. The shape of char¬
acter then used is almost exactly the same as in
present-day Chinese.
To show how the characters have evolved,
figure 2 compares the characters for one to ten
in oracle bone script, in bronze script, in the Han
Dynasty script, in present-day Chinese charac¬
ters and in modern Western (or Hindu-Arabic)
numerals.
M Counting rods
So far we have discussed decimal notation, but
in ancient China calculations did not directly
involve the manipulation of numerals. The
device used for calculations by the ancient Chi¬
nese was the counting rod.
The counting rods were small bamboo sticks
known as chou which Chinese mathematicians
arranged into different configurations to repre¬
sent numbers before performing calculations
with them. This was known as "chou suan"
(calculating with chou).
In August 1971, more than thirty rods dating
back to the time of Emperor Xuan Di (73-49
B.C.) of the Western Han Dynasty were found
in Qianyang County in Shanxi Province. Their
M. w length and width conform to the descriptions in
Oracle bone script:
= x n, A + X % 1
Modern Chinese: Z- ¿- C9 jl * -t /\ iL -l-
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
100 1 000 10 000
0© * *
s
4*
u Ui UJJ 2 ir -f >'(
-+ Z.-V V3~\- ¿+ *+ -t+
20 30 40 50 60 70 80
H B W ¥ fe* tf &
-'S" JLíT ES "g" Aï A"5" /VS" tes
200 300 400 500 600 800 900
É k * * V y
--Î- -H.-Í- E9"f- JL+ Af .=-#
2000 3000 4000 5000 8000 30 000
figure /. Two ways of writing
numbers
the History of the Han Dynasty, with the dif¬
ference that the Shanxi rods are made of bone.
A bundle of rods was unearthed in 1975 in Han
tomb No. 168 at Fenghuangshan in Jiangling,
Hubei Province. These are made of bamboo,
but are a little longer than the Shanxi rods. They
date from the reign of the Emperor Wen Di
(179-157 B.C.). In 1978, a quantity of earthen¬
ware with rod signs, dating from the Warring
States period (473-221 B.C.) of Eastern Zhou,
was found in Dengfeng County, Henan
province.
No reliable evidence has yet been found to
determine when counting rods began to be used,
but it is plausible that people were quite familiar
with this technique by no later than the Warring
States period. Texts relating to that period which
have survived to the present day use the
ideograms "chou" and "suan".
To represent numbers, counting rods could
be used either vertically or horizontally, as
shown in figure 3.
The rods are arranged in accordance with a
decimal place-value system, like the present
Western system. For units the vertical form is
used, for tens the horizontal form, for hundreds
the vertical form, for thousands the horizontal
form, and so on. A blank space is used for zero.
A number could thus be represented by
digits arranged in vertical and horizontal forms
alternately, working from right to left in the
usual order of units, tens, hundreds, thousands,
ten thousands, etc. This method of recording
numbers is explained in "Master Sun's Mathe¬
matical Manual" {Sunzi Suanjing, circa fifth
century A.D.) and in Xiahou Yang's "Mathe¬
matical Manual" {Xiahou Yang Suanjing, circa
eighth century A.D.). Master Sun says:
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Clay statuette of a
horseman, Han period
(late 3rd century A.D.).
Oracle bone:
	
_
= Z n, a T )C =\ 1
Bronze: = = = , 8 1. X fr t H A i
Han: = ' = <n> X 9* Í A- h t
Modern Chinese: ""
J"" va JL * -t A iL +
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
"Units arc vertical, tens are horizontal,
Hundreds stand, thousands lie down;
Thus thousands and tens look the same,
Ten thousands and hundreds look alike".
Xiahou Yang's "Mathematical Manual" says:
"Units stand vertical, tens are horizontal,
Hundreds stand, thousands lie down.
Thousands and tens look the same,
Ten thousands and hundreds look alike.
Once bigger than six,
Five is on top;
Six does not accumulate,
Five does not stand alone".
The last four lines mean that for digits equal
to or greater than six, the units from one to four
are used and a single counting rod standing for
five rods is placed on top of them. This is just the
same as in the Chinese abacus, where each bead
above the crossbar stands for five beads below.
The digit six is not represented by piling up
counting rods. "Five does not stand alone"
means that the digit five must not itself follow
the method described above, in which one
counting rod is used to represent five. This is to
avoid confusion with the representation of the
tens, thousands and so forth.
Written language in ancient China was
arranged in columns reading from top to bottom
and right to left, but when using counting rods
to record numbers, the characters were arranged
from left to right as in the present way of
recording numbers in both East and West.
The decimal place-value method of recording
numbers appeared in China at some point
during the Spring and Autumn period (770-476
B.C.) or the Warring States period (475-221
B.C.). From then on, various arithmetical oper¬
ations could thus be performed easily and con¬
veniently.
Figure 3
vertical:
horizontal:
Figure 2
I 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
1 II III llll mu T TT rrr im
	 = ==
= m J_ X 4 ¿
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The star system
by ñertholó Riese
In their quest to foretell the future, Mayan priests and
astronomers entered the realm of pure mathematics
Head of a priest emerging
from the mouth of a
serpent. Architectural
detail in the Mayan Puuc
style (7th to I Oth
centuries) from Uxmal
(Yucatán, Mexico).
22
BERTHOLD RIESE,
of Germany, is a specialist in
the field of Amerindian
civilizations. His work Maya-
Kalender und Astronomie (The
Mayan Calendar and
Astronomy) appeared In
Altamerikanistik (Early
American Studies), edited by
Ulrich Köhler and published by
Dietrich Reimer Verlag, Berlin,
1988.
SEVERAL million Indians living in Guatemala,
southern Mexico and Belize today still speak
one of the thirty or so Mayan languages,
including Mam, Quiche, Cakchiquel, Kekchi and
Myathan. A well-developed and broadly similar
numerical system exists in all of these tongues.
Centuries of colonization and, more impor¬
tantly, the introduction of the market economy
have led to the gradual replacement of vernac¬
ular names for numerals by words borrowed
from Spanish. Higher numerals have disap¬
peared from general use and today even the pri¬
mary numbers are being forgotten.
Numbers in everyday use
Archaeological excavations have yielded little
information on how numerals were used in the
economy of pre-Columbian America. We do
know, however, that the Mayas' numerical
system was initially based on counting on the
fingers and toes. In Quiche, for example, the
word for the number twenty, huvinak, literally
means "a whole person". This method of
counting is also reflected in the decimal divisions.
The word for 11 is hulahuh or hun (one) plus
lahuh (ten). These numbers were probably used
in much the same way as we use numbers for
counting today, with one difference. The Mayan
languages use words known as "classifiers" to
describe objects being counted, denoting
whether they are round, elongated, stackable,
solid or liquid food, etc. For example, a Yucatec
would not say, "Here is a cigarette", but "Here
is one {hun) long, cylindrical object {dzit) called
a cigarette {chamal)".
I Calendars
The conventional solar year
The Mayan calendar was based on the 365-day
solar year, which the Mayas had inherited from
the earlier civilizations of the Zapotees (at Monte
Alban) and the Olmecs (at La Venta and Tres
Zapotes). The length of this calendar year never
varied and was divided using the vigesimal
system of numeration into eighteen months of
twenty days each. The remaining five days were
added at the end of the year. Each month had a
name, which does not seem to have been related
to the seasons or to any particular festivals.
Most of them were handed down by tradition
and perhaps even borrowed from other lan¬
guages and cultures. They do not seem to have
had any meaning other than their calendar func¬
tion, not unlike our own months whose original
Roman meanings few people know today.
Each day was designated by a number from
0 to 1 9 which was placed in front of the name of
the month, and from 0 to 4 in the case of the
final, shorter month. It was therefore possible to
identify each day of the year, as in our own cal¬
endar. The years followed each other without
interruption and there were no leap years.
The diviner's
calendar
Guatemala's Quiche, Ixil and Mam Indians still
use a traditional 260-day calendar to predict
the future. Why 260 days? In interviews with
Guatemalan diviners in Chichicastenango and
Momstenango, German ethnologist Leonhard
Schultze Jena found that the number of days in
the year matches the length of human preg¬
nancy. Whatever its origin may be, the vigesimal
system made it possible for early Mayan math¬
ematicians to break this 260-day year down
into thirteen months of twenty days each. Each
calendar day was identified by attaching a
number from one to thirteen to one of the
twenty names of the vigesimal cycle, which
referred to animals, natural forces and tradi-
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
tional or abstract concepts whose meanings are
unknown today.
Like the solar calendar, the diviner's calendar is
cyclical. The last day of one cycle is automatically
followed by the first day of the next and so on.
The calendar round
Permutation of the 260-day calendar with the
365-day calendar gives a cycle of 52 years in
which each day bears a different name derived
from elements taken from the other two systems.
This major cycle of 1 8,980 days 52 solar years
of 365 days each or 73 divination years of 260
days each is known as the "calendar round"
and was the largest time-measuring unit for
most of the Mesoamerican peoples during late
pre-Columbian times. Unlike the Mixtees and
Aztecs, the Mayas were familiar with different
systems and used other units for measuring
longer periods of time, but they were an excep¬
tion among the great pre-Columbian cultures.
Hieroglyphics
As we have seen, the calendar days were identified
by names, some of which designated numbers.
That is how Indian diviners still express them in
their own languages. The pre-Hispanic Mayas
could also write all the days of the year, of the
divination calendar and the calendar round in
Carved glyphs and
calendar dates on a
7th-century Mayan
limestone stele at
Palenque (Mexico).
hieroglyphic script. Four hieroglyphic books or
codices from that time have survived, and are
today conserved in Paris, Dresden, Madrid and
Mexico City.
Countless stone inscriptions, a few wall paint¬
ings and many painted clay pots and sherds are
other sources of information about this highly
original writing system.
The simplest way of writing numbers
between 0 and 19 consisted of using dots for
units and lines for fives in an additive system
(figure 1). For higher numbers an additional
symbol for 20 was used. A positional system was
used to write numbers higher than 40, with an
extra symbol equivalent to our zero identifying
the unoccupied places (see photo page 24). Each
place represents a power of 20, until the third
place in which a factor of 18 is used. Thus, the
order of positional values was as follows: first
place, 20° (=1), second place, 20' (=20), third
place, 18 x 20' (=360), fourth place 18x202
(=7,200), fifth place 18x203 (=144,000) and so on.
Counting the days
At an early stage, certainly no later than the
beginning of the Christian era, the Central Amer¬
ican Indians invented a new way of calculating
time: the day number {"cuenta larga", or "long
count"). This system, which is independent of the
calendar cycles described above, consists of 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Below, detail from a Mayan
manuscript conserved in
Dresden (Germany). The
columns of numbers to left
and right of the female
figure designate the length
of lunar half-years. Above
the figure the sign for zero
(in red) appears twice.
numbering the days continuously from a more
or less mythical date far in the past. This
extremely accurate dating system has proved
to be of invaluable assistance to modern
researchers, ever since scholars in the early twen¬
tieth century succeeded in correlating it with our
own calendar. Its primary aim was to help the
Mayas codify major historic dates concerning
their rulers or deities.
Other calendar cycles
The Mayas of the classical period used other
cycles for historical, divinatory and speculative
purposes. For example, a cycle of days or nights
devoted to nine deities is known from hiero¬
glyphs G j -G9 Furthermore, the combination
of short 7, 9 and 13-day cycles, each of which
designated a category of gods, was used to come
up with a complex divination cycle of 819 days.
Astronomy
The astronomy of the Mayas was not limited to
observation of the stars and approximate pre¬
dictions of the movements of the heavenly
bodies. Using their sophisticated numerical sys¬
tems and various tabular calculations in con¬
junction with the hieroglyphic script, Mayan
astronomers were able to perform complex cal¬
culations with figures running into millions.
Their efforts were focused primarily on the
sun and the moon. Different year lengths were
used for different sorts of calculations. Nor¬
mally they took the conventional 3 65 -day year
as a basis. However, years with a length of 364
1 to© -cp.9tffiß$ü
* " ~ # 	,	 ""
:
I.
' iO-'HO-lCA
I <P:\IOUO\tena m
»' J^t&A 8. *t
¿¿.{¿à W*tS) « «« «r>
24 m
days are also encountered, as are years of 365 V4
days, similar to our own Julian calendar.
The moon played a prominent role in stone
inscriptions, which often begin with a day
number followed by the phase of the moon and
the day's position in a calendar of six lunar
months (see photo below left).
Mayan astronomers also calculated the syn¬
odic period of the planet Venus, and the figure
of 584 days at which they arrived is astonishingly
close to the modern astronomic value. But they
went still further. A set of tables in the Dresden
Maya codex cites correction factors to allow
for the fractional deviations from this value,
which can only be observed after decades and
even centuries. Researchers also suspect that
the Mayas were familiar with the synodic period
of other planets, such as Mars and Jupiter, but
this has not been proved conclusively.
A springboard into pure
mathemathics
For the Maya, all the calendar and astronomic
cycles and systems were ultimately used for div¬
ination and religious or speculative purposes.
Their calendar experts constantly strove to estab¬
lish a relationship between the cycles by permu¬
tation, using the lowest common multiple and
other methods, to predict the future and connect
the present with historical dates. In this way they
could also learn something about the destiny of
their clients the ruler and private individuals.
These practical goals often served as a spring¬
board for complex calculations and research
which transcended their original purpose. For
example, some of their calculations were pro¬
jected so far into the past or future that the pri¬
mary purpose must have been to quench the
calendar priests' own thirst for knowledge and
desire to explore the limits of their mathematical
system. It is therefore reasonable to assert that
the Mayas, like the Babylonians, Greeks, Arabs
and Indians before and after them, had entered
the realm of pure mathematics.
12
10 13
3 7 II
4 8
figure /
Mayan system of writing
numbers from I to 1 3
using dots and lines.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO COURIER -NOVEMBER 1993
U
I TO M
EAn.<
m
lii
BV FRANCE BEQUETTE
" "nesco regards the environment
as one of its top priorities, and
by virtue of its four fields of
competence education, sci-
v ence, culture and communi¬
cation it is involved in environ¬
mental issues on a wide range of
fronts.
"Unesco started doing in-depth
work in the aftermath of the major
United Nations Conference on the
Environment held in Stockholm in
1972," says Victor Kolybine, who is
in charge of the Organization's activ¬
ities in environmental education.
"In collaboration with the United
Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP), we launched an interna¬
tional programme on environ¬
mental education in which the con¬
cept of the natural environment was
widened to include socio-economic
and cultural dimensions. A key idea
was that environmental protection
is compatible with ecologically
sound development."
Today Unesco and UNEP are still
using a wide range of methods to
improve awareness of environ¬
mental issues. Twenty-seven young
people from various northern and
southern countries have designed
and illustrated a version ofAgenda
Women at the
well in Niger
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
FTP I TO SAVE TlEEART
Cover of a
Turkish
environmental
education
handbook for
teachers. The
book was
prepared with
assistance from
a Unesco
expert.
21, the action plan adopted at last
year's UN Conference on Environ¬
ment and Development, adapted
for 7- to 12-year olds. The book,
entitled Rescue Mission: Planet
Earth, will be published at the end
of the year by Kingfisher (UK).
Another innovative project is being
planned by the International
Humour Centre in Granada, Spain,
which in April 1994 will publish a
book of cartoons by famous artists
and informative texts in Spanish,
English and French.
To promote better under¬
standing of the the complex inter¬
relationships between human activ¬
ities and the environment, Unesco
makes a point ofbreaking down the
barriers between its various fields of
activity, with the social sciences
joining forces with the exact sci¬
ences and economics. University
chairs in sustainable development
will be established to provide mul-
USB*«*"»
ittnelirt*ri,teWt*.
Covers of the I
first two I
"People andj
Plants working
papers" issued I
by Unesco
(March and May
1 993). I
tidisciplinary education. Pro¬
gramme specialist Christine von
Furstenberg explains: "Training
nothing but overspecialized experts,
as is done everywhere today, pre¬
vents the co-operation between
researchers and practitioners that is
vital in many disciplines."
This pioneering multidiscipli-
nary approach is intended not only
for those with specialized qualifi¬
cations in the exact, natural and
social sciences but also for deci¬
sion-makers, civil servants, engi¬
neers, journalists and the interested
public. The holder of a Unesco chair
co-ordinates the teaching of sev¬
eral colleagues from different dis¬
ciplines, and offers sixteen courses
leading to a degree. Outlets include
national, international and non¬
governmental organizations. The
first chairs already exist. One is in
Granada (Spain), another in
Quebec, and a third is shared
between two universities in Aus¬
tralia and Thailand.
Since 1971 Unesco's "Man and
the Biosphere" (MAB) programme
has been an outstanding tool for
understanding and protecting ter¬
restrial ecosystems. Its purpose is
to study the impact ofhuman activ¬
ities on the biosphere and the
means that can be employed to pre¬
vent further damage. MAB has
established an international net¬
work of 300 "biosphere reserves"
covering a total of 164 million
hectares in 75 countries.
The reserves are not static, unpop¬
ulated ecological museums. They
have been created to conserve and
monitor representative samples of
the planet's major natural and semi-
natural ecosystems, offer research
opportunities and ensure that local
people benefit from the resources of
their area without exhausting them.
Examples include the Maya forest
reserve in Guatemala, the Central
Californian coast reserve in the
United States a complex terrestrial
and marine environment and the
National Park of Tassili N'Ajjer in
Algeria, which is famous for its cave
paintings.
Each reserve has a protected
"core" area which is surrounded by
a buffer zone. However, this system
of protection is only effective if the
government of the country in which
the reserve is located has the polit¬
ical will to respect it. In Africa
recently an oil company was given
permission to carry out extensive
drilling operations in a reserve,
wiping out conservation efforts.
Other, less well-known environ¬
mental programmes include
"Diversitas", which studies terres¬
trial and marine biodiversity, and
"People and Plants", which was
launched jointly with the World¬
wide Fund for Nature (WWF) and
the Royal Botanic Gardens in Kew
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
,.
"Unat
READIMC LIST:
The Environment and Development
Dossier (in French, English and Spanish)
presents clear, precise scientific
information and is available free to
governments, university teachers and
students and the media. Please contact
the Unesco Environmental Programme
Coordinating Office, 1 rue Miollis, 75732
Paris Cedex 15, France.
Tel: (33 1) 45 68 10 00, Fax: 45 66 90 96
"Unesco Sources": Rio One Year Later,
no. 47, May 1993 (English, French,
Spanish and Catalan).
Tsunami Warning, a cartoon book
produced by the Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission's
International Co-ordinating Group for
the Tsunami Warning System in the
Pacific. Available from the International
Hydrological Programme, Unesco, 1 rue
Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France.
African Medicinal Plants, by A.B.
Cunningham (in English). "People and
Plants", Division of Ecological Sciences,
Unesco, 7 place de Fontenoy, 75351 Paris
Cedex 07, France.
(UK) to promote the sustainable
and equitable use ofplant resources
by providing support to ethnob-
otanists from developing countries.
Nature can provide a cornucopia of
medicines for those who know how
to use it.
For over a year local people have
been helping ethnobotanists, forest
managers and traditional practi¬
tioners conduct an inventory of
plant life in particularly rich ecosys¬
tems in the Caribbean, Madagascar,
Bolivia, Brazil, Mexico, Cameroon
and Uganda. In Kinabalu Park,
Sabah (Malaysia) a three-year pro¬
gramme is cataloguing the many
uses of palm trees and medicinal
plants. A detailed manual describing
the plants and their chemical com¬
position, medicinal or toxic prop¬
erties and uses will be published.
The objective is to make traditional
plant resources, which poor and iso¬
lated populations rely on for most or
all of their medicine, available to the
greatest number of people.
The Intergovernmental Océano¬
graphie Commission (IOC) works
on a completely different scale. It
participates in international climate
and ocean observation research
programmes aimed at forecasting
natural disasters such as floods,
cyclones and tsunamis (seismic sea-
waves).
Unesco is also concerned with
the sustainable management of
coastal areas threatened by urban¬
ization, pollution, the spread of
tourism and transport systems and
the destruction of mangroves and
coral reefs. "Insula" and "Archipel"
are two programmes exclusively
concerned with promoting sus¬
tainable development of islands.
Their aim is to piece together a vast
network, which is already begin¬
ning to take shape between Oues-
sant (France), Estonia, Majorca
(Spain) and the Bijagos Islands
(Guinea-Bissau). The programme,
based on sharing experience and
solutions, has aroused interest in
the United States, Guadeloupe and
Finland, which are considering
taking part in it.
Insularity is also a concern of
Unesco's International Hydrolog¬
ical Programme (IHP), which seeks
to rationalize fresh water use and
management on tropical islands.
IHP's wide-ranging mandate
includes evaluating the link
between climatic change and water
resources and helping Member
States, especially those in arid or
semi-arid zones, to study the water
cycle and improve the management
of water resources degraded by
human activity.
This is only a selection of
Unesco's many environmental
activities. A forthcoming Green¬
watch will take a further look at the
Organization's work in this field.
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD-Unesco
training programmeforAfrican
news-agencyjournalists.
Cover of the
informational
cartoon book
Tsunami
warning! See
reading list
above.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
R L fi
GOURMET GARBAGE
Delicious mushrooms can be grown
on plant and agro-industrial waste.
This lucrative practice has eco¬
nomic potential for developing
countries, as Cameroon has dis¬
covered. This West African state is
currently growing varieties that are
not only tasty but also rich in pro¬
tein. Up to 1.25 kilos ofmushrooms
can be grown on one kilo of straw.
BANGKOK
GOES ORGANIC
A Thai company, Agro-Town Co.
Ltd., is beginning to market fruit
and vegetables grown in accordance
with the Codex organic farming
standards set by the World Health
Organization (WHO) and the UN
Food and Agriculture Organization
(FAO). Lettuce, tomatoes, cucum¬
bers, watermelons and asparagus
will be grown without pesticides or
chemical fertilizers. Despite prices
that are somewhat higher than
those paid for non-organic produce,
the company has found outlets not
only in Bangkok but in South Korea,
Singapore, Malaysia, lapan and the
United States.
TRANSFORMING ESTONIA INTO GREEN-LAND
Located on the Baltic coast in north¬
eastern Europe, Estonia today suf¬
fers from industrial pollution whose
impact extends beyond its borders,
notably contaminating the waters of
the GulfofFinland. Several Estonian
cities and many villages have no
waste water treatment facilities. And
yet Estonia was once an environ¬
mental pioneer. As early as 1910 a
bird sanctuary was created on the
islands off the country's west coast
which have since become a bio
sphere reserve. Before 1940 Estonia
boasted 47 nature reserves, 80 pro¬
tected parks and 40 protected
forests. Lahemaa national park, cre¬
ated in 1971, was the first of its kind
in the Soviet Union. One of the pre¬
sent government's priorities is to
save the country's natural areas,
which include islands, forests and
lakes that are home to an extraor¬
dinarily rich variety of nearly 9,000
plant and over 12,000 animal
species.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
"LITTLE GREEN LIES"
An American environmental policy
analyst, lonathan H. Adler, claims
that some children are being taught
on ecologically unsound principles
so that, for instance, they criticize
their parents for using objects made
ofplastic rather than natural mate¬
rials or for leaving the tap running
while brushing their teeth even
when there is no water shortage. He
also refers to a textbook which
claims that the world is hotter now
than it has ever been, without men¬
tioning that temperatures have only
been recorded scientifically for a
century. Mr. Adler's point is that
educators should base their
teaching on scientific facts and
beware of political indoctrination.
INDIAN FARMERS SAVE THEIR SOIL
trees had grown back, and today irri¬
gation has doubled the production
ofcereals, which are now harvested
three times a year instead ofonce, as
before. Buffaloes have replaced goats
and the village now sells over $10,000
worth ofmilk annually.
For years overgrazing and defor¬
estation devastated the mountain
slopes overlooking the village of
Sukhomajri, located in the Shivalik
foothills of the Himalayas. The ero¬
sion rate reached 900 tons ofsoil per
hectare, and fertile, river-borne mud
was gradually filling an artificial lake
downstream. In 1977 a soil conser¬
vation specialist unsuccessfully
attempted to change the villagers'
behaviour. Things only began to
change when a village elder sug¬
gested to the specialist that a small
dam of earth should be built to pro¬
vide the village with water. In return
for the water the village herdsmen
agreed to respect the hillside and to
pay a tax when they gathered fodder
there. Within five years the grass and
BACTERIA
GIVE BEANS
A BOOST
Beans are a major food resource in
the Andes. The International Center
for Tropical Agriculture in Cali,
Colombia, has announced the dis¬
covery of bacteria that enable bean
plants to draw the nitrogen essential
for their growth directly from the
air. Farmers can buy a bacteria-peat
mix called Rhizocaj for one-tenth
the price of industrially-manufac¬
tured nitrogen fertilizer. They mix
bean seeds with sugar and water,
add Rhizocaj, mix the seeds again
until they are coated with the blend
and plant them. The best results
have been achieved in the moun¬
tains, precisely where successful
farming has been most difficult.
Rhizocajhas already been tested in
Peru and Bolivia and, if funding per¬
mits, will be tested in the highlands
of Ecuador.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Making something out ofnothing
by Pierre-Sylvain Fiiliozot
By inventing the zero, India became the
birthplace of modern arithmetic
Kushan coin with
inscription in the ancient
Indian brâhmî script (first
century A.D.).
ÍN India mathematics has not always been
linked to writing. The earliest surviving
written document dates from the third cen¬
tury B.C., but India certainly had an advanced
civilization many centuries before that, and sci¬
entific knowledge formed part of it. Most
knowledge was transmitted orally. This ancient
learning preserved in human memory makes
up the corpus of the great religious texts known
as the Vedas, which incidentally contain evi¬
dence of mathematical knowledge. The Vedas
arc written in an archaic form of Sanskrit. Like
all Indo-European languages, Sanskrit has dec¬
imal numerals and individual names for the nine
units, as well as for ten, a hundred, a thousand
and higher powers of ten (figure 2, page 33).
30
figure /
Numeral signs and their
values as attested by the
Nâneghât inscriptions (first
century B.C.).
Numerals Value Numerals Value
Or - 12 - J
1 or - 1Z
Thi 1700 Tot Z1,000
"Mcd? 189 - 1.
ex q 17 TH 60,000
TcxT u,ooo "Rx- MOO/
T * 1,000 M- 101
oc r 1Z TrM 1,100
- 1 M 100
T°"r¥W 14,4-00 M- Jul
TV 6,00ti TcM- 1,101
I T7H- 1, 101
I M- JOl
1 T = jpoz
JH 100 T- 1001
The names of the tens are derived from those
of the units, somewhat modified and with the
addition of a suffix. Examples are vimqati 20,
trimcat 30, catvârimçat 40. The other numerals
are formed from these components. The names
for the hundreds, thousands and so on consist of
a unit name followed by çata or sahasra. Dve
gate (dual), for example, means 200, and trini-
sahasrani (plural), 3,000.
In Sanskrit grammar the qualifier in a com¬
pound word precedes the qualified. In the case
of compound numerals the number of the higher
order is regarded as qualified by the lower.
Eleven, for example, is ten qualified by the addi¬
tion of one, giving the compound ekâ-daça,
and similarly dvâ-daça is 12, trayas-trimgat 33
and so on. The number is divided into compo¬
nents, with the smallest coming first. Units are
followed by tens and so on.
si The advent of writing
We do not know when, how or by whom
writing was introduced into India. All we know
is that as early as the third century B.C. two
scripts were in use. One, called kharoshtî, was
derived from Aramaic. It was used in the
extreme northwest of the sub-continent, but
soon fell into disuse. The other, known as
brâhmî, seems to have originated in India itself.
It is the forerunner of all the scripts now in use
in the Indian sub-continent and in southeast
Asia. The earliest records (from between the.
third century B.C. and the third century A.D.)
of figures transcribed into this script reveal a
notation system that corresponds fairly closely
to the pronunciation system.
There is one sign for each digit, and so there
are nine signs for the nine units, an entirely dif¬
ferent sign for each of the tens (10, 20, etc.),
another sign for 100 and yet another for 1,000.
Compound numbers are represented by com-
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
An Indian merchant does
his accounts in Ajmer
(Rajasthan).
binations of symbols. The brâhmî script reads
from left to right, and combinations of signs
are written in that direction, starting with the
highest value. Here there is a difference between
the written and the spoken language. The scribe
starts with the highest component, whereas the
speaker starts with the lowest. For example, the
number 13 is pronounced trayo-daga, or "three-
ten", but is written "ten-three".
Combinations of components arc usually
produced by juxtaposing signs, in some cases by
ligatures. Whereas there are different signs for
each of the tens, for the hundreds there is just the
sign for 100 plus the sign for the number of
hundreds, and likewise with the thousands.
At this stage wc cannot yet speak of posi¬
tional notation. There is a juxtaposition of the
numeral signs which when added together give
the desired number. This is exactly in keeping
with the structure of the language (figure 1).
I The zero and positional
numeration
In the decimal positional system of numeration
the tens, hundreds and thousands arc not rep¬
resented by different signs but by the same digit
signs placed in different positions. Only then
docs position become significant. It alone shows
which are the tens, which the hundreds and
which the thousands. Such a system needs only
ten signs, the digits from 1 to 9 and a zero or
at least a blank space.
There is no satisfactory documentary evi¬
dence as to how and in what exact period this
system was discovered in India, and how it
developed. The earliest reference to a place-
value notation is a literary one. Vasumitra, a
Buddhist writer and leading figure at a great
religious council convened by King Kanishka
(who reigned over the whole of north and north¬
west India at the end of the first or the beginning
of the second century A.D.), maintained in a
book on Buddhist doctrine that if a substance
that exists in all three time dimensions (past,
present and future) is regarded as something
different every time it enters a new state, this
change is due to the alterity of the state, not to ¡J I
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
^$?M?k+.Wt^Jfyffis& é^Û
*&*
$$ R* *-* &*j i nA&M-y&KTg'y&i.«^ *
32
its own alterity. He illustrated this idea by
speaking of a marker which in the units position
counts as a unit but in the hundreds position
counts as a hundred. He did not specify the
nature of the marker.
This may be a reference to a kind of abacus.
The marker might have been an object that
could be placed in a column or square, where its
position gave it the value of a power of ten. Or
it could be a mark in the sand, in the case of sums
written on the ground. Indian accountants are
known to have liked the simplicity of this
method. In some parts of southern India village
astrologers can still be seen doing calculations by
placing cowrie shells in columns drawn in the
sand. Whatever the form of the abacus, Vasum-
itra's reference implies the existence of a notation
that took account of positional value.
The same is true of the zero, the use of which
in India is known from literary references pre¬
dating the earliest written examples. The zero
forms part of the positional system of numera¬
tion. Originally it seems to have been a gap in a
column resulting from the absence of a figure or
marker in the space reserved for an order of the
power of ten. This is shown by the use of one of
the words meaning empty, çûnya or kha. The
word kha occurs in a treatise on metrics by Pin-
gala, in which he sets forth a rule for turning
binary numbers into decimal numbers. Pin-
gala's dates are unknown, but quotations from
his works are found from the third century
Charter dating from 596
A.D. The last three signs
on the last line represent
the figures 346.
PIERRE-SYLVAIN
FILLIOZAT,
of France, is a specialist in
Indian studies. He is a director
of studies at the Ecole Pratique
des Hautes Etudes in Paris.
A.D. onwards, and so he must have lived earlier
than that.
That a dot came to be used to indicate an
empty space wc know from a Sanskrit story¬
teller, Subandhu, who probably lived in the
sixth century A.D. To denote the zero Subandhu
used the compound noun cûnya-bindu, literally
"empty point", in other words a dot indicating
an empty space in a column.
The zero itself appears in a deed of gift,
carved on copper plates, from King Deven-
dravarman of Kalinga (Orissa, in eastern India).
The document is dated in letters and figures :
"samvacchara-gatam trir-âgîte (100) 83 shra-
vane masi dine vimgati 20 utkîrnnam", liter¬
ally "carved a hundred and eighty-three years
(100) 83 (having passed) the twenty day 20 in the
month of Shravand"'. The number 183 is written
as three signs, the sign for a hundred and then the
figures 8 and 3. The number 20 is written with
the figure 2 and a zero in the form of a small
circle. The period specified in this document
began in 498 A.D., so that it dates from the year
681 A.D.
Positional notation, and the zero in the form
of a big dot or small circle, are found in inscrip¬
tions in southeast Asia, at Sambor (Cambodia)
and Kota Kapur (Malaysia), where the earliest
records go back to the seventh century A.D.
The scripts used in these countries are all derived
from Indian scripts, and their system of writing
numbers is undoubtedly the Indian system. All
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Below, numerals written in
devanâgarî (script used for
Sanskrit, Hindi and other
Indo-Aryan languages) in a
"magic square" painted on
a wall in Ujjain (Madhya
Pradesh, India).
these documents show that by the late seventh
century the positional system and the zero were
in general use not only in India but in all the
countries to which Indian civilization had spread
as well.
Notation using nine digits and a zero seems
to have quickly taken the lead for inscriptions,
but it never completely superseded the old
system, which survived until recently in manu¬
scripts, and in southern India even in early twen¬
tieth-century printed books.
Words standing for numerals
A mixed notation, in which features of the old
system are combined with or alternate with
characteristics of positional notation, was also
known and used in India. In this system number
names are replaced by words with numerical
connotations. For example, two is replaced by
"eyes", "arms", "wings" or "twins", four by
"oceans" (there being four oceans in Indian
geographical mythology), ten by "fingers",
thirty-two by "teeth", hundred by "human life¬
span", zero by "empty space", and so on. These
words are arranged as they would be in speech,
so that in a compound number the lowest
numerals come first. In other words, the order
is opposite to that used in writing. For instance,
the number 4,320,000 is pronounced khaca-
tushka-rada-arnavâh, which literally means
"tetrad of empty spaces-teeth-oceans", or 0
0
Figure 2. Number names in Sanskrit
çata
sahasra
ayuta
niyuta
prayuta
100
1 000
10 000
100 000
1 000 000
eka 1
dvi
tri
catur
pañca
2
3
4
5
shat 6 arbuda 10 000 000
sapta
ashtan
nava
7
8
nyarbuda
samudra
100 000 000
1 000 000 000
10 000 000 000
100 000 000 000
000 000 000 000
9 madhya
anta
parârdha
daça 10
This example is taken from the Sûrya-sid-
dhânta, an astronomical text which takes
account of data observable in the fourth century
A.D. It is one of the earliest records of this
mixed notation, which enjoyed great popularity
throughout the history of Sanskrit literature.
Even among mathematicians and astronomers it
seems to have been the preferred method of
expressing numbers. Its advantage was that it
allowed variation of vocabulary. Sanskrit has
ten or so common words for eyes, whereas there
is no synonym for the number 2. Sanskrit tech¬
nical and scientific literature was usually written
in verse, so that authors needed to command a
wide vocabulary in order to find words to fit the
requirements of prosody.
It would be a mistake to regard this mixed
notation as a transitional stage between the old
oral system and the pure positional system. It
was an artificial method adopted by authors
who were familiar with both systems and used
them in their writings.
Economy and lightness
In 662 A.D. a Syriac writer, Severus Sebokt,
wishing to show that the Greeks had no
monopoly on science, referred to the inven¬
tiveness of Indian scholars. The only one of
their mathematical skills that he mentioned was
their system of reckoning using nine digits.
Severus Sebokt's comment points to the greatest
advantage of this system, its economy. By
reducing the symbols needed for the notation of
all numbers to ten nine digits and a zero
the system achieves the ideal of economy and
efficiency. Indian intellectuals were well aware
of the advantages of economy. They had a tech¬
nical term for it laghava or "lightness" and
have cultivated it since Antiquity in various
fields of thought. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Hindu-Arab roots ofmedieval
Europe M by Anóré Moró
A written numeration system
transmitted to the West from India
via the Arab world
34
ANDRE ALLARD,
of Belgium, is research director
at his country's National Fund
for Scientific Research
(F.N.R.S.) and a professor at
the University of Louvain. He is
the author of many works on
ancient and medieval science.
A T the beginning of Molière 's last play, Le
t\ Malade Imaginaire (1673), the hypochon -
M ldriac Argan uses a counting-frame an
abacus to reckon up the cost of the remedies
prescribed by his apothecary. He eventually
arrives at a total cost of "three and sixty pounds,
four sous, six deniers."
This method of counting, which dates back
to Antiquity, was quite common in Molière's
time. Though written numeration had been
known in the Latin West for several centuries,
and paper was in general use, the abacus with
counters was still often used in the seventeenth
and even in the eighteenth centuries. Leibniz
used one, and Voltaire's famous correspondent
Frederick II of Prussia took it as the pretext for
a quatrain:
"Courtesans are counters
Whose value depends on their place :
In favour, millions,
Noughts in disgrace."
The counting-frames still used in the Far
East and parts of Eastern Europe (the Chinese
xuanban, the Japanese soroban and the Russian
schoty) are linear abaci based on the same prin¬
ciple as those of ancient Greece and Rome.
How did counting devices of this kind come
to be superseded in the West by figures?
Counters, fingers and Indian
numerals
During the early Middle Ages (from the fifth cen¬
tury, which saw the fall of the Roman Empire, to
the ninth) Western writers' scientific knowledge
was limited to a speculative arithmetic based
mainly on the Introduction to Arithmetic by the
second-century neo-Pythagorean Nicomachus
of Gerasa, and a practical method of calculation
using counters, not written figures. These coun¬
ters were remotely descended, via the calculi of the
Romans, from the pebbles used by the Greeks of
Pythagoras's time to represent numbers.
For a long time the only rival to the counter
system was reckoning on one's fingers, as described
in the seventh century by the Venerable Bede in his
brief treatise De Temporibus ("On Times"):
"When you say one, bend the little finger of
your left hand and dig it into the middle of your
palm. When you say two, do likewise with the
bent second finger from the little one	 When
you say five, likewise straighten the second
finger from the little one. . . . When you say
ten times a hundred thousand, clasp both hands
with the fingers interlocked	"
This method of using the hands for counting
remained current for a very long time. A detailed
description of it (figure 1) can be found as late
as 1494 in one of the most important mathe¬
matical works of the modern era, Summa de
Arithmetica by Luca Pacioli (Luca di Borgo)
which was published at Venice in that year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Portrait of the Italian
mathematician Luca
Pacioli(c.l44S-c.l5IO), by
Jacopo de' Barbari.
figure /. Numbering by band
Illustration showing a
method of using the hands
for counting taken from
Luca Pacioli's Summa de
Arithmetica, Geometría,
Proport/on/ e
Proport/ona/ità (1494), a
compendium of
mathematical knowledge.
Gerbert of Aurillac, who in 1003 became
Pope as Sylvester II, seems to have been one of
the first persons to propagate the use of Hindu-
Arabic numerals in Europe. He did so by bor¬
rowing from the Arabs of Spain the use of an
advanced type of abacus with twenty-seven
columns, on which counters made of horn could
be moved. The counters were usually marked
with the first nine numerals.
I From Baghdad to Toledo
In the early ninth century the Abbasid Caliph al-
Ma'mun founded at Baghdad an academy called
the House of Wisdom, which promoted cul¬
tural exchange with India, in particular transla¬
tions of manuscripts collected by his envoys.
The mathematician al-Khwarizmi, in addition to
his famous Kitab al jabr wa'l-muqabala, the
basic text of Arabic algebra, also wrote a "Book
of Addition and Subtraction" and a "Book of
Indian Arithmetic".
The latter work gave rise to two traditions.
One, exclusively Arabic and of the highest quality,
reached its peak in the ninth and tenth centuries.
The other, equally important, developed later. In
twelfth- and thirteenth-century Europe, and espe¬
cially at Toledo, translators and compilers of
Arabic books in Latin played a key role in the
development of mathematics in the West, com¬
parable to that played by the Baghdad scholars and
translators in the Islamic world.
Under the influence of the new mathematical
treatises they wrote towards the middle of the
twelfth century, reckoning by abacus, cither with
counters or in the sand (in which figures could
easily be written and erased), and on the fingers
gradually gave way to a system based on Indian
and Arabic methods. This was "algorism", a
word derived from al-Khwarizmi's name.
Based on the nine digits (figurae in Latin) and
the zero (sometimes called cifra in the Latin
texts, from the Arabic sifr, "emptiness", but
more often called circulus, "little circle"), algo¬
rism made it possible to perform traditional
operations on whole numbers (addition, sub¬
traction, duplication, multiplication, division 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
1 2th century
"Toledan" numbers
"Indian" numbers
Astronomical tables
13th century
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0
\ 3 3 S- 4 G ? S 7 0 / T
A, P r 7* fl V <r r
i, ï ¥ 9- °l ¿ 7 « ¿ û / f
Manuscript, Staatsbibliothek, Munich
123 4 56 7 89 0
1 P 3 JU/^ 4 £ V /7 S ? -^
i P >» /* ^ V 7 9 ?
Manuscr/pf, Biblioteca Apostólica, Vatican
15th century
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0
i X 3 4- r ¿ 7 S ; o
Book printed byJohann Widmann, Leipzig, 1489
This table shows how the
writing of numerals in the
West evolved from the two
series of figures originating
from the eastern and
western parts of the Arab
world (12th to 15th
centuries). The
manuscripts conserved in
Munich (12th century) and
in the Vatican (13th
century) show how the two
different forms continued
to exist side by side. The
numerals in Widmann's
book (late 1 5th century)
represent the culmination
of a process of evolution
that is still not fully
understood.
figure 2.
Turning the numbers 2 and
3 in their eastern Arabic
written form through
ninety degrees to the left
gives a fairly convincing
approximation to the
western Arabic forms and
shows how they may have
evolved into the forms
familiar to us today.
V
\>
and extraction of roots) faster and more reliably.
Contrary to a view widely held during the
Middle Ages and the Renaissance, numerals of
Indian origin brought to the West by the Arabs
owed nothing to the late Roman mathemati¬
cian of the sixth century, Boethius.
In the late thirteenth century most of these
treatises were eclipsed by the impressive "Book of
the Abacus" by the Pisan mathematician Leonardo
Fibonacci (Leonardo of Pisa). Contrary to what
its title might suggest, this work marked a final
break with the abacus tradition. Even more influ¬
ential were two highly successful works,
Alexandre de Villedieu's "Song on Algorism" and
Sacrobosco's "The Common Algorism".
For a long time Hindu-Arabic numerals were
written in Western manuscripts in a wide variety
of ways. From the outset translators were faced
with two series of figures, one from the eastern part
of the Arab world, the other from the western
Arab world. The latter seems to have developed as
a result of two factors the discovery of the prin¬
ciples of Indian arithmetic and the ways in which
the abacus was then used. This difference can
only be seen in a few Latin manuscripts (table at
top of page). In most cases Western copyists tran
scribed forms that were increasingly remote from
their originals. Obliged to write from left to right
(to which the Arabic shapes did not lend them¬
selves), they gave the figures only a symbolic
value and soon distorted their forms. This palaeo-
graphical evolution continued until the Renais¬
sance, and may have reflected Visigothic influ¬
ence. It is particularly striking in the cases of the
numbers 2 and 3 (figure 2).
I The triumph of algorism
By the tenth century if not before, the ease with
which calculations could be done with Indian
numerals led the Arabs to improve the technique.
Some methods spread in other ways than through
textbooks of arithmetic. Probably on one of his
many journeys, Leonardo of Pisa became familiar
with the Arabic method of calculating called
"houses", and used it to devise his own "checker¬
board" method a set of squares with all the
numerals written in them, on which diagonals
were drawn. This became very widespread.
At the dawn of the Renaissance a wood
engraving that was to become famous was made
at Freiburg-im-Breisgau. It showed the "Philo¬
sophical pearl" {Margarita Philosophica). On the
left a money-changer representing Boethius is
operating with Hindu-Arabic numerals and
looking cynically at one of his colleagues, who
with a shamefaced expression is working with
an abacus and counters according to the
Pythagorean tradition. Behind them, Dame Arith¬
metic shows clearly where her own preferences lie:
her dress is actually spangled with figures.
There could be no better illustration of the
triumph of figures in the medieval West, even
though the latter all too rarely acknowledged its
indebtedness to the Indian and Arabic civiliza¬
tions which bequeathed it, among other legacies,
this remarkable tool.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Words, gestures and symbols
by Pauius Gerdes and Marcos Cherinda
Africa has a rich variety of traditional
counting methods
A A ANY hundreds of well-structured
# 1#1 numeration systems were invented in
I M Africa south of the Sahara whose peo¬
ples, like those elsewhere in the world, learnt
through the ages that it is very difficult to count
and calculate if one uses a completely new, dif¬
ferent word or symbol for each quantity that
is, for each number. These systems include
spoken numeration systems, gesture counting
systems, and symbolic systems that use body
Above, Peul drovers ¡n parts or objects to represent numbers.
Mali. The most common way to avoid having to
invent completely new words for different num¬
bers has been to compose new number words
out of existing ones by using the arithmetical
relationships between the numbers concerned.
This principle can be seen in many African
spoken numeration systems.
In the Makhwa language spoken in northern
Mozambique, for example, the words thanu (5)
and nloko (10) are dominant in the composition of
number words, and constitute the bases of the
system of numeration. The expression for 6 is
thanu na moza (5 plus 1), and 7 is thanu napili, (5
plus 2). To express 20, people say miloko mili
(tens two or 10 times 2), and 30 is miloko miraru
(tens three).
The most common bases in Africa are 10, 5
and 20. Some languages such as Nyungwe,
which is spoken in Mozambique, use only base
10. Others like Balante in Guinea-Bissau use 5
and 20. Verbal numeration in the Bété language 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Ashanti weights used for
weighing gold dust.
38
PAULUS GERDES
is a Mozambican mathematician
who is rector of his country's
Higher Pedagogical Institute
and chairman of the
International Commission on
the History of Mathematics in
Africa (AMUCHMA). His
published works include
Ethnomathematics and Education
in Africa.
MARCOS CHERINDA,
Mozambican mathematician, is
a lecturer at Mozambique's
Higher Pedagogical Institute,
where he specializes in
ethnomathematics. He is the
co-author, with Paulus Gerdes,
of Famous Theorems of
Geometry.
of Côte d'Ivoire uses three bases: 5, 10 and 20.
Fifty-six, for instance, is expressed as golosso-ya-
kogbo-gbeplo, that is "20 times two plus 10
(and) 5 (and) 1". The Bambara of Mali and
Guinea have a 10-20 system in which the word
for 20, mugan, means "one person", while the
word for 40, debé, means "mat", referring to a
mat on which husband and wife sleep together
and jointly they have 40 digits.
The Bulanda (West Africa) use 6 as a base so
that 7 is expressed as 6 + 1, 8 as 6 + 2, and so on.
The Adclc count koro (6), koroke (6 + 1 = 7), nye
(8) and nyeki (8 + 1 = 9). Among the Huku of
Uganda the number words for 13, 14, 15 are
formed by the addition of 1, 2 or 3 to twelve.
Thirteen, for instance, is expressed as bakumba
igimo (12 plus 1). The decimal alternatives, 10 +
3, 10 + 4 and 10 + 5, were also known.
One advantage of using a low number such
as 5 as the basis of a spoken numeration system
is that it may facilitate oral or mental calculation
where the answer has not been memorized. For
instance, 7 + 8 would be (5 + 2) plus (5 + 3). As
2 + 3 = 5, one finds as answer 5 + 5 + 5, 10 + 5,
or 5 multiplied by 3.
The duplicative principle
A particular case of the use of addition to com¬
pose number words is the situation where both
numbers arc equal or where one of the two is
equal to the other plus one. For instance, the
Mbai count from 6 to 9 in the following way:
mutu muta (3 + 3), sa do muta (4 + 3), soso (4 +
4), and sa dio mi (4 + 5). The Sango of northern
Zaire express 7 as na na-thatu (4 + 3), 8 as mnana
(4 + 4) and 9 as sano na-na (5 + 4). One possible
reason for using the duplicative principle to
compose the number words between 6 and 9 is
that it may make it easier to do mental arith¬
metic, in particular duplication operations. For
instance, to obtain the double of 7, one has to
add, if one has not memorized the answer, 4 + 3
and 4 + 3. As 4 + 3 + 3 = 10, the answer becomes
10 + 4. In sub-Saharan Africa, there is a strong
tradition of mental calculation, and oral and
mental multiplication often were (and some¬
times still are) based on repeated duplication.
In several African languages subtraction, as
well as the additive and multiplicative principles,
has been used to form number words. In the
Yoruba language of Nigeria, for example, 16 is
expressed as eerin din logun meaning "four until
one arrives at twenty". The Luba-Hemba people
of Zaire express seven as habulwa mwanda
("lacking one until eight"), and nine as hab¬
ulwa likumi ("lacking one until ten").
Spoken numeration systems may vary
greatly within relatively small geographic
regions. In Guinea-Bissau, for example, the
Bijago have a pure decimal system; the Balante
use a five-twenty system; the Manjaco use a
decimal system with exceptional composite
number words such as 6 + 1 for 7 and 8 + 1 for
9; and the Felup use a ten-twenty system in
which the duplicative principle is also employed
in forms like 7 as 4 + 3 and 8 as 4 + 4.
Some number words are adjectives while
others are nouns. In this situation, number word
structures may appear that do not correspond
directly to an addition, multiplication or sub¬
traction. For instance, in the Tschwa language of
central Mozambique 60 is expressed as thlanu
wa makuma ni ginwe, that is "five times ten
plus one more (ten)".
To denote relatively large numbers, com¬
pletely new words are often used or words that
express a relationship with the base of the
numeration system. The Bangongo of Zaire say
kama (100), lobombo (1,000), njuku (10,000),
lukuli (100,000) and losenene (1,000,000), while
the Ziba of Tanzania say tsikumi (100), lukumi
(1,000), and kukumi (10,000), the three latter
terms being clearly related to kumi (10).
Counting by gestures
Gesture counting was common among many
African peoples. The Yao of Malawi and
Mozambique represent 1, 2, 3 and 4 by pointing
with the thumb of their right hand at 1, 2, 3 or
4 extended fingers of their left hand. Five is
indicated by making a fist with the left hand. Six,
7, 8 and 9 arc indicated by joining 1, 2, 3 or 4
extended fingers of the right hand to the left
fist. Ten is represented by raising the fingers of
both hands and joining the hands. The Makonde
of northern Mozambique start counting on their
right hand with the help of the index finger of the
left hand. Five is indicated by making a fist with
the right hand. For 6 to 9, the representation is
symmetrical to that of 1 to 4, that is, right and left
hands change roles, with the index finger of the
right hand pointing at the fingers of the left.
Ten is represented by joining two fists.
The Shambaa of Tanzania and Kenya prac¬
tise a method of gesture counting that uses the
duplicative principle. They indicate 6 by
extending the three outer fingers of each hand,
spread out; 7 by showing 4 on the right hand and
3 on the left, and 8 by showing 4 on each hand.
To express numbers greater than 10, the
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The number I as indicated
in gesture counting (from
top) by the Makonde, the
Yao and the Shambaa.
Sotho of Lesotho employ different individuals
to indicate the hundreds, tens and units. To rep¬
resent 368, for example, the first person raises 3
fingers of the left hand to represent 300, the
second one raises the thumb of the right hand to
express 6 tens, and the third one raises three
fingers of the right hand to express 8 units. This
is actually a positional system, since it depends
on the position of each man whether he indicates
units, tens, hundreds, thousands, and so on.
The use of fingers and hands to count may
explain the choice of five and ten as bases for
verbal numeration systems. The use of bases
may also have been stimulated by practices used
to accelerate counting. For instance, Makonde
basket makers count the plant strands of the
bottom of their likalala-baskcts by fours instead
of counting one by one.
I Tally devices
Tally devices were commonly used in Africa
south of the Sahara. In Mozambique Chuabo
boys use the following counting technique when
they are playing football. The two halves of the
leaf of a coconut tree obtained after taking off its
vein serve as a tally device for each team. The
halves are called mulobuo. When a team scores
a goal, a fold is made in its mulobuo, and at the
end of the match, the scorer compares the
lengths of each one or counts the folds, in order
to see who has won.
Among the Tswa, also from Mozambique,
trees are used to record the age of children.
After the birth of a child a cut is made on a
trunk of a tree, and each year a new cut is added
until the person is old enough to count for him
or herself. Cuts on tally sticks arc also used
The best general work is undoubtedly
Karl Menninger, Zahlwort und Ziffer.
Eine Kulturgeschichte der Zahl, Göttingen
(1958). English translation by P. Broneer,
Number Words and Number Symbols. A
Cultural History of Numbers (1977).
See also:
Georges Ifrah, Histoire universelle des
chiffres, (Paris, 1981).
"A mathematical mystery tour",
Unesco Courier, November 1 989.
when counting the number of animals in a herd,
each cut corresponding to one animal.
Among the Makonde, knotted strings were
used. A man who was setting out on an eleven-
day journey would tie eleven knots in a string
and would say to his wife, "This knot" (touching
the first) "is today, when I am starting;
tomorrow" (touching the second knot) "I shall
be on the road, and I shall be walking the whole
of the second and third days, but here" (seizing
the fifth knot) "I shall reach the end of the
journey. I shall stay there the sixth day, and
start for home on the seventh. Do not forget,
wife, to undo a knot every day, and on the tenth
day you will have to cook food for me; for see,
this is the eleventh day when I shall come back."
Pregnant women used to tie a knot in a string at
each full moon so that they would know when
they were due to give birth. In order to register
a person's age, two strings were used. A knot was
tied in the first string at each full moon. When
twelve knots were tied, a knot was tied in a
second string to mark the completion of the
first year, and so on.
Figures in the sand
A variety of numeration systems exist in Africa
that are "written" in one way or another. The
eastern Bushongo (Zaire) counted simultane¬
ously by threes and tens. For each three objects,
they marked in the sand three short parallel
strokes with three fingers of a hand. After com¬
pleting three groups of three strokes, a longer
stroke was marked for the next object to indicate
that ten more objects had been counted.
The Fulani or Fulbc, a scmi-nomadic pas¬
toral people of Niger and northern Nigeria, place
sticks in front of their houses to indicate the
number of cows or goats they possess. One hun¬
dred animals are represented by two short sticks
placed on the ground in the form of a V. Two
crossed sticks, X, symbolize 50 animals. Four
sticks in a "vertical" position represent 4. Two
sticks in a "horizontal" and three in a "vertical"
position indicate 23 animals. The following was
found in front of the house of a rich cattle owner:
WVWVXII, showing that he had 652 cows.
The Akan peoples (Côte d'Ivoire, Ghana,
Togo) used figurines in stone, metal or simply
vegetable seeds as coins. The weight of each fig¬
urine was agreed to represent the monetary value
that corresponded to a certain quantity of gold
dust of the same weight. The figurines show ani¬
mals, knots, stools, sandals, drums and in some
cases have diverse geometric forms such as step
pyramids, stars or cubes. Many display graphic
signs representing numbers. Although in the lan¬
guages spoken by the Akan peoples only base ten
is used, base five is also found on the money
weights. The Agni, one group belonging to the
Akan people, used a scries of units of money
weights with a binary structure, each new unit
being double the previous one. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
ThevalkySOftheNiger byJeanDevisse
Flowing some 4,200 kilometres
through a drainage basin which
covers over a million square kilome¬
tres and whose ramifications extend into
at least nine countries, the Niger is Africa's
third longest river. Although some of the
cultures that developed in this vast region
are as old as those of the Nile valley they
are undeservedlylittle-known. In recent
years, however, they have begun to be
studied scientifically, and archaeological
excavations have brought to light new infor¬
mation that has enabled scholars to recon
struct part of the rich past that slumbers
here in the earth ofAfrica.
The Africans of the Niger basin, like
people in many other parts of the world,
wanted to make sure their ancestors'
remains were respected. Like the tombs of
the Etruscans, the kurgans of Ukraine, the
mastabas ofEgypt and the vast cemeteries
ofNapata in the Sudan, these burial places
faithfully conserve the memory of the past.
The remains ofhouses of unbaked earth
that were built hundreds and in some cases
thousands of years ago also contain keys
40
that can help to unlock the past. Large
quantities of pottery, ceramics and metal
objects will provide eloquent testimony, as
long as they are treated carefully and sci¬
entifically.
Archaeological and historical research
is a late-comer to this part of the world.
Much has been achieved in the last twenty
years, but an enormous amount of work
still needs to be done. In addition to
funding, such research requires above all
boundless patience and respect on the part
of scholars. It is imperative that archaeo¬
logical investigation should not be jeopar¬
dized by wanton violation of the ancient
tombs and that the stratigraphy of village
and urban ruins should not be destroyed by
profit-seekers hunting for trophies or arte¬
facts to sell on the market.
This does not mean clamping down on
the trade in works of art by pitting
researchers against dealers, but trying to
make people understand, recognize and
respect the priorities of research. What is at
stake is the opportunity to discover intact
precious evidence of the Niger basin's past.
In the last three years, a team of French
andAfrican researchers has been preparing
a major travelling exhibition to present this
immensely rich heritage which is over 5,000
years old. The exhibition can be seen in
Paris, its first port of call, from October 1 993
until lanuary 1994.
It is divided into ten "sequences", the
themes ofwhich are described below. First of
all there is a brief visual introduction,
including maps and chronological tables, to
the countries concerned, and an explana¬
tion of the approach adopted by the orga¬
nizers. Then visitors are taken along the
course of the river, from its sources to its
delta.
1 - The valleys ofthe upper Niger were
the cradle of a great power that flourished
between the thirteenth and seventeenth cen¬
turies that ofMali and an areawhere kola,
gold and rice were produced in ancient times.
2 - Iron, which played a vital part in the
growth and hierarchical development of
societies in the Niger basin, appeared as
early as the second half of the last millen¬
nium of the pre-Christian era in Nigeria
and perhaps a thousand years earlier in
Large figure of a horseman
(between 3rd and 1 0th
centuries) originating from
Bura (Niger).
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Ténéré. It was produced and worked almost
everywhere by the beginning of the Chris¬
tian era.
3 - The inland delta is a vast area to
which floods bring an annual increment of
silt. lust as ancient Egypt was described as
"a gift of the Nile", this vast inundation is a
"gift of the Niger", but it did not give rise to
a centralizing power such as that which
developed in Egypt as early as the fifth mil¬
lennium B.C. On the contrary, the high
waters isolated groups of people who took
refuge on small islands known as togué. The
remains of an ancient settlement, lenné
leño, have been found and partially exca¬
vated on some of the most remarkable togué
near the city of lenné in Mali. Between eight
and nine centuries older than the existing
city, lenné leño has been included on
Unesco's World Heritage List. The delta has
been inhabited for at least 5,000 years, and
only a fraction of the vestiges of its past
have yet been unearthed. It is the area most
threatened by looting.
4 - It has often been thought and
written that Sudanese architecture, as dis¬
played in many mosques old and new, did
not appear until the fourteenth century.
However, its roots go back much further.
5 - Gold, which was produced, traded
and minted into coins "in the north", was
considered locally to be less precious than
copper.
6 - Northwards, beyond the ridge of
Wagadu (the ancient empire ofGhana), lay
the trade routes of Mauritania; to the west
was the basin of the Senegal River. Major
discoveries from Kumbi Saleh, the capital of
Wagadu, are presented, as well as a model
of the splendid mosque (10th-15th cen¬
turies).
7 - Some seven or eight thousand years
ago, a huge network of rivers flowed down
from the north to the left bank of the Niger
Bronze statuette of a
horseman (between
ISthand 18th
centuries) from the
ancient kingdom of
Benin (Nigeria).
between the Tropic ofCancer and the Niger
Bend. Today it no longer exists, but traces of
human activity have survived in what are
now dry valleys. One extraordinary example
is a tomb at Iwelen (Niger), which dates
from the middle of the eighth century A.D.
8 - Perhaps the most unexpected and
spectacular of the ten sequences is that
devoted tofunerary practices. It features var¬
ious forms of inhumation in earthenware
jars (Mali, Burkina Faso), funerary steles,
mass graves (Tellern du Mali) and a remark¬
able "village of the dead" unearthed in Niger.
9 - The coppersequence follows those
devoted to gold and iron. The quality and
complexity of copper-working techniques
as well as the ramifications of the copper
market are illustrated.
10 - Exceptional coverage is given to
the valleys ofthe lowerNigeria Nigeria, the
cradle of Nok art (remarkable both for its
Head of an
anthropomorphic
terra-cotta figure from
Jemaa (Nigeria).
JEAN DEVISSE,
of France, is professor
emeritus of African history
at the University of Paris I
and rapporteur of the
International Scientific
Committee for the
publication of Unesco's
General History ofAfrica.
He is commissioner-
general of the exhibition
on the Niger basin
described in the present
article.
longevity it was produced for more than a
thousand years and for its diversity) and
the sophisticated art of Ife and Benin. Also
displayed are treasures discovered during
excavations near Igbo Ukwu, which are
quite different from anything previously
discovered.
The exhibition ends in a music room
where visitors can admire the landscapes,
art and current activities of the Niger basin
while listening to African music.
The exhibition is co-organized by
Burkina Faso, France, Guinea, Mali, Mauri¬
tania, Niger and Nigeria, with an impor¬
tant contribution from the Netherlands. It
will travel from Paris to other cities begin¬
ning with Leiden (the Netherlands) and
probably Philadelphia (United States) in
spring and summer 1994. It will then be
shown in Bamako (Mali) from October to
December 1994, Ouagadougou (Burkina
Faso) from lanuary to March 1995, Lagos
(Nigeria) from April to June 1995, Niamey
(Niger) from July to September 1995, Nouak¬
chott (Mauritania) from October to
December 1995 and Conakry (Guinea) from
January to March 1996.
A richly illustrated book describes each
sequence of the exhibition and sets it in its
context, presents the findings of the past
twenty years of research, and outlines the
new directions being taken by current inves¬
tigations. The exhibition is to be presented
in condensed form on panels that will be
sent to each of the co-organizing countries,
so that it can reach schoolchildren and rural
populations far from the capitals where it
will be displayed.
In Paris the exhibition (entitled Vallées du
Niger) can be seen from 14 October 1993 to 10
January 1994 at the Musée National des Arts
d'Afrique et d'Océanie (National Museum of
African and Oceanic Arts), 293 Avenue
Daumesnil, 75012 (tel: 44 74 84 80). 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
H
Miguel de Unamuno on thefuture
4t
In 1933, the International Institute
ofIntellectual Co-operation
organized a series oftalles in Madrid
in which Miguel de Unamuno gave
his views on thefuture ofculture.
Professor ofGreek and later rector
ofSalamanca university,
philosopher, poet, playwright and a
lifelong opponent ofbigotry and
dogmatism, Unamuno was one of
the most influential Spanish
thinkers ofhis time. Wien he gave
the talks (betiveen 3 and 7May) he
was 68years old.
I must admit that after over forty years
as a teacher, I have reached the stage
where I don't know what culture is.
What I do know is that I find it rather bur¬
densome. Instead of making a series of
formal observations, I am going to treat
you to an outpouring ofpersonal impres¬
sions. I'm feeling a little tired and so, I
think, is most ofcivilized humanity at this
moment. What we need is not so much
peace as rest, because there is such a thing
as peace without rest and a dreadful thing
it is!
In economic terms, everyone knows
that there is a disparity between produc¬
tion and consumption. We have con¬
sumed for the sake of production rather
than produced for the sake of consump¬
tion, and the same thing can be said of
intellectual and spiritual life. Most people
cannot keep up with today's intellectual
output. People are thinking too fast. That
is a very serious matter. Pindar said that
Tantalus had been punished for not being
able to digest happiness and joy. Perhaps
many people suffer today because they
cannot digest truths and, even more
serious, cannot digest the truth. It is very
unpleasant to be incapable of digesting
happiness swallowing it is something
different. But it is even more serious not to
be able to digest and swallow the truth.
In this very place I met one of my
friends, a highly cultivated, well-read man
who has travelled widely but never writes
anything. When asked, "Why don't you
produce anything?" he answers, "I pro¬
duce consumption."
Of course, in consuming culture we
produce it as well. It is perhaps more dif¬
ficult to consume than to produce. It is
more difficult to listen than to speak, more
difficult to read than to write, far more dif¬
ficult. Most of the writers I know, unfortu¬
nately, cannot read. Digestion is very dif¬
ficult.
The question of the future of culture, its
goal and purpose, which will be, perhaps,
to achieve the spiritual unity ofhumanity,
has not been raised. Speaking for myself,
I never achieve my own unity. I always
carry within me a people fighting a civil
war. One of the things that makes me suffer
the most, when I am engaged in a discus¬
sion with another person, is to see that
person defend himself when he is unfa¬
miliar with the grounds for his argument
and I know them better than he does. At
present most people, here at any rate, are
living in anguish. But I do not want to talk
about current affairs because they are
above or below what we are dealing with
here.
Of course, the cultural point ofview in
my opinion is a matter of religion. I am
going to make a digression. In the past
Miguel de Unamuno y Jugo ( 1 864- 1 936).
people said, "Long live Christ the King"
to show that they were monarchists. The
other day I was talking aboutVelasquez, to
whom I dedicated a poem. His painting of
Christ says something, it tells you quite
clearly, "My republic is not of this world, it
is of another world."
Yes, education is a national issue, but it
is also a danger. When I look at all these
books about how to teach I have the
impression that children are being used as
fodder for testing, that the aim is not to
educate them but to bring them up as if
they were frogs or guinea pigs for psy¬
chologists. This is dreadful. Poor young
people! What they have to go through
because of these books! They are trained
like performing animals!
"Is teaching an unnatural function?"
Socrates was not a teacher, but a
vagabond. He wandered the streets of
Athens talking to everyone. That's what
culture is. Here in Spain there is a deep-
rooted popular culture forged by tradition
in what is the true people's university of
Spain, the cafés. This culture is more uni¬
versal than the other one. The other one is
international rather than universal, which
is not the same thing. What is most uni¬
versal is what is most individual, and the
people in our cafés and countryside are
profoundly individual.
I believe that to defend the universal
you have to stand up for the individual. Mr.
Severi has talked about the national char¬
acter that all the sciences have. Science is
naturally a language because even math¬
ematical formulas are written in Spanish,
French, English and German. Always. I
also believe that the mind makes language
and that words are what make us. Even
philosophy makes language. Hegel is the
German language. Cartesianism is the
French language speaking, scholasticism
is thinking in dead Latin. In Spain there is
also a kind of fluid philosophy. It is not
systematic. It is in the language of the
people. In Spain there have never, or
almost never, been philosophical systems.
That does not mean that there have never
been philosophers.
In the foreword to the Baedeker guide to
Spain it says that we Spaniards are touchy
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
ofculture
and easily offended. There's more to it
than that! In Spain, when we have the army
we are anti-militarist. When there was the
clergy, there was anti-clericalism. I have no
doubt that our children and grandchil¬
dren will be anti-teacher. People talk about
tyranny. Well that is a form of tyranny. I am
a teacher but I naturally resisted falling
into a professional rut because, instead
of working and having my students work
on other people's poems, I have a weak¬
ness I write poetry myself. It is myweak¬
ness to be a direct producer. A kind of civil
war goes on inside me. Anyone who
studies literature always ends up hating
what he studies, always. I've seen it
happen. Whenever people talk about indi¬
viduals or personalities I am accused of
being an individualist because I am an
anarchist. To me individuality is a kind of
container and personality is the content.
It is possible to have a strong individu¬
alitywithout much ofa personality. I know
people in Spain with a very strong indi¬
viduality, but they are almost all the same.
Their minds are skin and bone. They are
like crayfish and lobster. They have bones
on the outside and and flesh on the inside.
But there are other minds, even here on the
peninsula, who are more like octopuses
and invertebrates. Some of them have very
hard shells. They are very strong on the
outside. But there are also people who are
soft and swallow the lobster or crayfish
whole with its shell, digesting it without
chewing.
There is a nationalist international. This
is one of the most dangerous things in
existence, because it is not universal!
The most universal is the most indi¬
vidual. All my life I have fought to defend
my own individuality and I thought that in
doing so I was also standing up for the
freedom and the individuality of my
country, Spain, which I bear inside myself.
At times I have said, with the modesty so
typical of me [laughter], that not only am
I a son of Spain, I am one of its fathers as
well! Spain is also my mother, but it's my
daughter too. Sometimes one needs soli¬
tude. Here we are together and I shall look
back on this talk with pleasure. I have rec¬
ognized people, but I shall go back home
to see if I can still recognize myself. Let
me tell you a little anecdote. One day I
was in Barcelona, where I went to see the
director of the asylum, who is a friend of
mine.
He said to me, "One of my inmates
knows you're here. He wants to meet you".
I was introduced to the madman. He
was calm; he was perfectly all right.
"Mr. Unamuno?" he asked.
"The very same!"
"The real one? Not the one who lives on
paper and in the press?"
"Yes."
But afterwards I had second thoughts
and wondered if I was the real one. I won¬
dered if I was the person I knew or the one
other people knew, myself or the historic
man, who is not made of flesh and blood.
In Spain we've managed to turn a fic¬
tional character, Don Quixote, into a
national hero. Did he exist? He does exist.
We must be wary of education, and
especially of national education, of the
clerisy of the state. I, who am an educa¬
tional functionary, an administrator,
humble though I maybe as an adminis¬
trator, of course [laughter] I see the
danger ofwanting to train young people in
one way or another. What can be done
about it? We cannot let them teach them¬
selves. And yet they would do the job very
well if they were left to themselves. I repeat,
the danger of teaching is the fatigue I men¬
tioned earlier, and the fatigue is partly a
result of that. People's minds are over¬
loaded. Poor children! I have known chil¬
dren who were very clever until the age of
seven. After that their intelligence stopped
developing	
Let's get back to what I was saying about
the danger of fatigue. It stems from a cer¬
tain kind of education, from teaching.
There are two things I cannot stand: ped¬
agogy and sociology. The former must be
replaced by art and the latter by history.
Another time I shall have an opportu¬
nity to return to some of these ideas in
greater detail. For the moment we are here
to get to know each other. The Greek oracle
said, "Know thyself". Why? What I say is,
"Know others, not yourself". I do not think
anyone can know his or her self, fortu¬
nately. We are here to see each other and
get to know each other, to feel a certain
Text selected and presented
by Edgardo Canton
human warmth, to experience something
more than ideas, perhaps to see our dif¬
ferent ways of approaching life. Ifyou for¬
eigners leave here knowing a little more
about our Spain, this old Spain where
people, including myself, believe a renewal
is under way, we should thank you. I am
Spanish, and profoundly so. You are in a
country which, I think, has a great culture,
a profound culture. Those who cannot read
or write may be even more cultured than
the rest. They have long centuries in their
souls, not only thought and faith. Faith is
very difficult to define. Of course, if it is
defined it ceases to be faith. A god who is
defined is no longer a god. Faith is neces¬
sary. Faith in what? I don't know.
In the Basque country where I was born
there was a bigoted old woman who often
went to mass. Because of my interest in
these matters I once asked her:
"Tell me, madame, what do you believe
comes after death?"
"After death?" she replied. "I haven't
had time to think about that kind ofthing".
Please excuse me for rambling on; I do
believe these ideas can shed some light
on the subject. At the same time I think this
is a subject on which not too much light
should be shed. Too much light is not a
good thing. You solve one problem and
twenty or thirty new ones appear in its
place. You have to work. This quotation
from an old Italian poet comes to mind:
"Meglio optando obliar senza indagarlo
questo enorme misterde ¡'Universo" We
are better off trying to forget the great mys¬
tery of the universe. The trouble is that I
cannot resign myself to forgetting this
great mystery. To get back to culture: I
repeat that at the age of seventy and after
forty years of teaching I have reached the
point where I do not know what it is. I
hope my own people, your peoples, may
have a few years not only of peace, but of
rest, rest during which they will be able
to sleep and digest truths and the truth.
Perhaps that is the hardest lesson in the life
of the world. Tr ¡S
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S PROGRANNE FOR 1004-1005:
SOLIDARITY
Mounting intolerance
and inequality are
dividing the world. In
response, Federico
Mayor, Director-
General of Unesco,
calls for a sustainable
global approach,
based on the values of
solidarity and sharing.
It is in this direction
that the Organization
will be moving in
44 1994-1995.
UNITED WE STAND
ALTHOUGH huge threatening clouds
hang over the dawn of the third
millennium, humanity has at its dis¬
posal the means to make the changes
required. Though yearning for equality
encounters inexorably growing dispari¬
ties, and strivings towards fraternity
founder upon individual self-interest, we
can win through if only we are clear¬
sighted, resolute and bold enough to effect
a radical change of course.
More wars are being fought today than
at any time in the last fifty years. In the past
decade, people fleeing death, destruction,
and even deliberate policies of plunder and
extermination, have swollen the ranks of
the world's refugees from ten to twenty
million. At the same time, there have never
been so many negotiated solutions and
processes of reconciliation, under the aegis
of the United Nations in particular.
Although the danger of a nuclear holo¬
caust may have virtually disappeared, more
and more countries possess nuclear
weapons, and new tensions are developing
in a number of places. For all its harmful
effects, the polarization of international
relations brought about by the East-West
conflict did at least keep in check the war¬
like impulses of those who tried to escape
from its grip. The very subjection imposed
by the totalitarian regimes served to
restrain the hatreds and fanaticism that,
with the collapse of those regimes, are now
bursting their banks. Differences, cultural,
racial and ethnic, lead more and more often
to a hostility that may result in exclusion or
even, in extreme cases, extermination.
At the same time, the disparity in the
resources available to people to provide for
their needs is growing: superabundant for a
few, they are, for an ever greater number,
increasingly, pathetically inadequate. While
global figures may, for instance, show a
steady growth in living standards and school
attendance or a fall in mortality rates, such
overall improvements conceal a widening
gap between the extremes.
About 1 .3 billion people in the world
today live below the poverty line, with no
chance of feeding themselves adequately.
They include nearly all the 30,000 children
who die every day directly or indirectly
from malnutrition, most of the one billion
people who cannot read or write and almost
all the 300 million children who are deprived
of schooling. On the other hand, the income
of the richest fifth of the world's population
is 150 times greater than that of the poorest
fifth, and this disparity has actually doubled
in the last thirty years.
The present pattern of development is all
awry. Even as the North-South gap widens,
international trade is organized in such a
way that it deprives developing countries of
$500 billion a year ten times more than
they receive in foreign aid. Since the mid-
eighties, debt repayments by the poor coun¬
tries have exceeded the amounts they receive
from the rich lender-countries, and the dif¬
ference is increasing every year. Inequality
is growing in the developed countries too.
The existence of "two nations" within
almost every country is becoming as
inescapable a fact as the existence, in the
world as a whole, of "two-track" societies.
A further harmful effect of the present
pattern of development is that it depends
on overexploitation of natural resources
and at the same time causes damage to
those resources it does not exhaust. Defor¬
estation, the excessive depletion of the
ozone layer and the steady erosion of our
bio-genetic heritage prove that our ways of
living and producing have now brought
us up against a physical threshold.
WALLS OF ILLUSION
This threshold is all the more real in that
population growth is increasing our impact
on the environment. The world's popula-
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
AND SHARING
tion is growing by 254,000 a day. At this
rate, by the year 2030, it will have reached
at least ten billion, compared with just
under six billion today. About 95 per cent
of this increase could be in developing
countries, with the highest growth rates
in the poorest of them. Along with all their
other problems, these countries would
thus have to cope with increasing pressure
of population on an increasingly despoiled
environment. How could the population of
these countries agree to stay put?
No wall would be high enough to stop
them emigrating en masse to the sparsely
populated, fabulously rich countries whose
streets they imagine to be paved with gold.
UNESCO:
THE STRUCTURE
Unesco comprises three bodies: the Gen¬
eral Conference of Member States, the
Executive Board and the Secretariat.
The General Conference, which is
sovereign, "shall determine the policies
and main line of work of the Organiza¬
tion". Meeting usually in the latter half of
every second year, the representatives of
all Member States currently I 75 fol¬
lowing the principle of one vote per
country, finalize the Organization's pro¬
grammes and the amount and break¬
down of its "regular budget", decide on
Conventions and Recommendations,
elect members of the Executive Board
and, as is the case this year, appoint the
Director-General.
The Executive Board, representing
all the Member States between sessions
of the General Conference, has 5 I mem¬
bers who meet twice yearly to prepare
the agenda of the General Conference
and recommendations to be submitted to
it. The Board is, above all, responsible for
the execution of the programme adopted
by the Conference, and can take any mea¬
sures necessary to this effect.
The Secretariat is Unesco's execu¬
tive branch. Under the authority of the
Director-General, who is elected for a
period of six years, the staff implements
the adopted programme and provides
the General Conference and the Execu¬
tive Board with all necessary elements
for the successful accomplishment of their
work.
It is easy to sec how such influxes of immi¬
grants could fuel reactions of xenophobia
and exclusion, if those reactions persist.
I have used the words "would" and
"could" because I am convinced that wc
will act in time, using our immense talents
to prevent such developments and pro¬
vide each people with the means to become
the master of its fate.
Just as it is hard to sec the wood for the
trees, so the Berlin Wall concealed the real
priorities, the hidden threats, and the new
solutions. Before the Wall fell, the East-
West dichotomy hid many facts from sight,
brought to a standstill all thinking that did
not proceed therefrom, shaped patterns of
development and governance and exer¬
cised a disproportionate influence on inter¬
national relations. We lived in a sort of
blind tranquillity, where thought was
benumbed and action to face the great
challenges of our time was paralysed.
So there is no call for nostalgia. The
collapse of the totalitarian regimes has cre¬
ated openings for a freedom which, though
fragile, is at last attainable. With the increase
in the number, scale and speed of the flows
of people, goods, capital, ideas, knowl¬
edge and information, the unification of the
world (the famous "global village") seems
irreversible, yet the world is becoming
more and more divided as inequalities grow
and differencesalthough they contain
the answers to a good many of our prob¬
lems tend to be seen as threats. United
but not uniform. The irreversible process
of globalization now underway is incom¬
patible with a narrow attitude of self-
preservation. We have no choice but to
organize that process equitably.
A NEW ATTITUDE
It has to start with a new attitude towards
others. The differences between us must be
accepted, and we must show tolerance for
others and respect for their freedom and
dignity. In pursuance of new approaches to
development, poverty must be combattcd by
practising the virtues of solidarity, sharing
and the sense of fraternity which, according
to André Malraux, is alone capable of putting
an end to inequality. To think and act in the
short term and at the local, or national or
even regional levels is becoming ludicrous.
While action must continue to be adapted to
local situations, both its basis and its effects
must be seen in the context of a long-term,
general, global vision.
The transition from an age-old culture
of war to a culture of peace requires the
participation of all, their weapons being
common objectives and agreement on
essentials. The challenges of the past were
met with force; those of the future will be
met with intelligence. This transition calls
for a change of outlook, combining intel¬
lectual adventurousness with perseverance
in the way of sustainable action. How
many failures are the result of short-lived
convictions, of meeting violence with vio¬
lence! Whatever the affront, non-violence
must be the universal basis of response.
The complexity of reality must also be
accepted: simplification is neither rigorous
nor useful, and a pluridisciplinary approach
is the only way forward to precise under¬
standing and effective action.
With this in mind, the activities that
Unesco is to carry out in 1994-1995 will
have three main objectives: the promotion
of a culture of peace and tolerance; the
establishment of a type of development
that has human beings as both its agents
and its beneficiaries; and the preservation
of the environment and the rational man¬
agement of resources. These activities will
be particularly aimed at populations and
groups that arc in distress: women, the
least developed countries and Africa.
To achieve these aims, Unesco has nei¬
ther battalions nor substantial financial
resources at its disposal. The means it
employs are of a different kind: building up
the intellectual and moral solidarity of
mankind so as adapting the words of
UNESCO's Constitution to construct the
defences of peace in the minds of men. Its
purpose is indeed to combine and conjoin the
creative capacities of all the world's educators,
scientists, researchers, artists and journal¬
ists, to pave the way to a world where
everyone can at last learn to coexist and
share. TT^
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO PROGRANNE FOR
SOLIDARITY AND SHARING
EDUCATION
Access, quality and
relevance are the
key words in
Unesco's education
programmes for
the coming
biennium
46
REACHING THE
HISSING MILLIONS
by Cilla Ungerth Jolis
In Croatia, 200,000 children displaced
by civil strife have no access to
schooling. In Somalia, where war has
destroyed virtually all schools, 99 per cent
ofboys and girls are deprived ofeducation.
In Cambodia, most of the country's young
are ill prepared to help reconstruct their
country because they cannot even write
their names. In Mali, 68 per cent of men
and women are illiterate. In many other
countries, education is underfunded, ill-
equipped and given low priority.
When Victor Ordonez, Unesco's
director for basic education, prepared the
draft programme for 1994-1995, he faced
the following dilemma: on the one hand,
there are some 948 million illiterate adults
in the world and almost 130 million
children with no schooling; and on the
other, UNnsco's budget is lower than
that of a medium-sized university in an
industrialized country. Under such con
ditions, what can Unesco do to make a
real difference?
A CATALYST
The new programme, which concen¬
trates on a few large-impact actions, has
two main goals: to provide basic education
to those children and adults who have no
access to it, while at the same time
boosting its quality and relevance. One
approach is to act as a catalyst. Thus
Member States will be able to draw largely
on the report to be submitted at the end of
1995 by the International Commission on
Education for the 21st Century, headed
by Jacques Delors.
"Even if our budget is a drop in the
ocean, Unesco can maximize its impact by
helping governments to act," says Mr.
Ordonez. "They are, after all, responsible for
the education of their citizens." A third of
the budget (almost $200 million) has been
earmarked for advisory services and other
activities to help Member States frame poli¬
cies and programmes, especially to assist
eastern European and central Asian coun¬
tries rebuild their education systems.
Another emphasis is closer co-opera¬
tion with a range ofpartners in the follow-
up to the World Conference on Education
for All held in 1990. At this gathering of
governments, international agencies, pro¬
fessional bodies and non-governmental
organizations, 155 governments com¬
mitted themselves to education for all
before the year 2000.
One example of inter-agency collabo¬
ration is a new project focused on nine of
the world's most populous countries:
Bangladesh, Brazil, China, Egypt, Mexico,
India, Indonesia, Nigeria and Pakistan,
which account for half the world's popu¬
lation, 72 per cent of the world's illiterates
and over half of out-of-school young
people. "By targeting our action on these
countries," says Mr. Ordonez, "we can
make a spectacular change in the world
situation." As part of the project, a Summit
of leaders of these countries will be orga
nized by Unesco and other UN agencies in
December.
Other target groups are the least devel¬
oped countries in Africa, the Arab states
and east Asia. "We will take an especially
hard look at legislation, policies and pro¬
grammes which help or hinder education
for women and girls," says Mr. Ordonez.
For example, a task force ofwomen will be
set up to plot action in support of basic
education in this area. Other target groups
are young children among refugees or with
special learning needs, young people in
urban slums, and cultural minorities and
remote populations.
The new "Scheme of Humanitarian
Assistance for Refugee Education"
(SHARE) responds to the needs of the 88
per cent of refugee children who receive no
schooling. It goes beyond the urgent but
short-term goal of providing shelter, food
and medicines, to develop a coherent
policy of refugee education in co-opera¬
tion with local and national authorities.
After initial experiences in Cambodia,
Somalia andAfghanistan, SHARE activities
are now underway in Slovenia and Croatia.
But placing more children in school
and more adults in literacy classes does
little good ifwhat they learn there is irrel¬
evant to their lives. That is why Unesco is
also focusing on the content and process
ofbasic education, with stress on boosting
the effectiveness of teachers and instruc¬
tors, school management, the measure¬
ment of learning outcomes, and the devel¬
opment of a prototype curriculum for the
first four years of primary education.
"Because too few children get more than
four years' schooling," says Mr. Ordonez,
"it is crucial that they learn something
essential there to survive in life. The three
R's, yes, but also health, nutrition and the
preservation of the environment."
So despite the great need and limited
resources, Unesco is, in the words of
Director-General Federico Mayor, "deeply
committed to making the right to educa¬
tion an everyday reality, not a remote
promise."
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
10 0 4-1005
This dossier presents the draft programme and budget for 1 994- 1 995
that has been drawn up for submission to the 27th session of Unesco's General
Conference (IS October- 1 6 November 1993). It has been prepared by the staff of
the monthly magazine Unesco Sources, whose editor-in-chief ¡s René Lefort.
SCIENCE
The quest for
sustainable
development is
the mainspring
of Unesco's
scientific
activities
IN SEARCH
OF THE GRAIL
by Sue Williams
In the wake of the UN Conference on
Environment and Development held at
Rio de Janeiro in 1992, sustainable devel¬
opment has become a new Holy Grail,
and "capacity building" strengthening
human resources, particularly in devel¬
oping nations has been deemed one of
the keys to fulfilling the quest. It is also
the foundation ofUnesco's scientific pro¬
grammes for the 1994-1995 biennium.
"The human element is the most
important factor, both as a means of
achieving sustainable development and
as its main beneficiary," says Adnan
Badran, Unesco's Assistant Director-Gen¬
eral for science. "We therefore need to get
whole populations involved and provide
countries with the knowledge and exper¬
tise they require to carry out research and
implement projects that will bring about
such sustainable development."
Unesco's science programmes for 1994-
1995, which in manyways served as a fore
runner to the Earth Summit and which
were roundly endorsed by the participants
in the Rio meeting, have consequently put
the emphasis on education, specialist
training and research. Workshops, schol¬
arships, exchange programmes, research
grants and specially devised computer
modules will thus enable thousands of
biologists, chemists, geologists, hydrolo¬
gists, marine scientists, ecologists and
technicians to be trained.
At the same time the science pro¬
grammes have fine-tuned their research
to the goals and priorities of Agenda 21,
the plan ofaction adopted at Rio, for which
they are particularly well suited. The Man
and the Biosphere (MAB) programme's net¬
work of3 1 1 biosphere reserves in all types
of ecosystems around the world, for
example, provides a ready-made global lab¬
oratory for the study and monitoring of
biodiversity. The "Diversitas" programme
has been set up to this end, covering ter¬
restrial, freshwater, marine and coastal
environments and all living things, from
whales to microbes. The biosphere reserves
could also provide logistic support for
research by the International Hydrological
Programme (IHP) which seeks to improve
understanding of the water cycle and man¬
agement of the planet's precious water
resources. Those in coastal areas could pro¬
vide precious data for the work of the Inter¬
governmental Océanographie Commis¬
sion (IOC) in monitoring global change.
For its part the International Geological
Correlation Programme (IGCP) will be
geared towards better identification ofmin¬
eral resources.
Another characteristic of the workplan
for 1994-1995 is the emphasis on an inter¬
disciplinary and multi-sectoral approach.
"The environment must not be treated in
isolation," explains Gisbert Glaser, co-ordi-
nator of Unesco's environmental pro¬
grammes. "It is inextricably linked to a
range of other domains, and our work
must concentrate on these interrelations."
The "Environment and population edu¬
cation and information for human devel¬
opment" project is a good example of the
new direction being taken. "The overall
UNESCO IN ACTION
aim is to improve education and informa¬
tion on subjects which are too often treated
as separate issues," says Glaser. The $2.1
million project is a combined effort by the
science, social science and education sec¬
tors with other UN agencies, and will see the
development of scientifically sound
teaching materials as well as information for
decision-makers and the media, the
training of experts, and the provision of
technical support for reshaping education
systems and training programmes.
^^^^1«^^«ffig I III I III IIIIMIIIIIII
GREEK ENGINEERS
A major push will also be made in basic
and engineering sciences to improve
university teaching and promote research
in these fields. "It was said clearly in Rio
that engineering sciences should incor¬
porate environmentally friendly compo¬
nents," says Mr. Badran. "Engineers shape
our landscapes and thus have an impor¬
tant impact on the environment. In the
past, they have not been concerned about
this impact they have not been con¬
cerned about such details as the level of
carbon that their machines have spewed
into the atmosphere or the effect of chlo-
rofluorocarbons (CFCs) on the ozone
level and this must change." The Uni¬
versity-Industry-Science Partnership
(UNISPAR) project well illustrates Unesco's
aims in this direction.
Unesco will also reinforce its support for
renewable energy research and networks of
solar energy centres in the Mediterranean
countries, Africa, Asia and Latin America.
"Strength through union" is how new
MAB Director Pierre Lasserre describes
the programme's guiding principle for the
coming biennium. It would also serve well
as the leitmotiv for the rest of Unesco's
science sector. T" m
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO P R O G R A N FOR
SOLIDARITY AND SHARING
SOCIAL
SCIENCES
Ending the isolation
of researchers in
the human
sciences is the
goal of a new
programme
mounted by the
Social Science
Sector
by Nicolas Michaux
One major subject left off the agenda of
the Rio Summit on Environment and
Development was the extremely sensitive
issue of population. However the topic is
set to come storming back. Another big
world conference is to be held in Cairo in
1994 specifically on this question which
presents such a serious challenge to our
future.
Unesco starts off better prepared for it
perhaps than other international institu¬
tions since it is the only organization in the
United Nations system with a social sci¬
ence sector.
Over the next two years, studies that
have already been begun on international
migrations will be continued and others
including studies designed to improve
birth control policies will be launched. In
particular, fertility rates will be examined
in regions such as sub-Saharan Africa and
^O the Caribbean.
FAMILY AND EDUCATION
1994 will also be the International Year
of the Family (an important meeting is
scheduled to be held in Malta) during
which Unesco will offer states technical
assistance for drawing up family policies
following on from the studies that have
been carried out for several years with this
in mind. Unesco is particularly concerned
to develop studies on the family and edu¬
cation. In 1995 it will contribute to the
United Nations Year for Tolerance and to
the World Summit for Social Development.
It will also pursue a variety of other activ¬
ities ranging from youth to questions of
ethics in research on the human genome.
In all these fields, as one of the officials
responsible for the sector, Souleyman
Baldé, points out, "Unesco does not do,
but gets things done". In other words, in
close co-operation with non-govern¬
mental organizations, states, networks of
researchers and other bodies, it promotes
studies on topics which it considers crucial
and helps specialists to compare their
findings and to make the results known.
In response to the appeal for peace
launched by the Secretary- General of the
United Nations, Mr. Boutros Boutros-Ghali,
and to the requests of countries that are
struggling to emerge from war, Unesco is
also working for the consolidation ofpeace
and democracy. This involves a series of
activities including helping demobilized
soldiers to return to civilian life, the prepa¬
ration ofelections, and providing an intro¬
duction to parliamentary life and the con¬
cept of the public good in countries that
in some cases have no real experience of
democracy.
But the main objective of the Social Sci¬
ence Sector is "to give structural solidity to
its programme", in the words ofAli Kazan-
cigil, who is in charge ofUnesco's activities
to promote the international development
of social and human sciences, by estab¬
lishing international research programmes
on some of the major topics of the day.
However astonishing it may seem when it
is universally recognized that the major
challenges ofour time are global and inter¬
disciplinary by nature, specialists in the
human sciences and the research they
carry out are, according to him, "remark¬
ably isolated". The bipolarization of the
world was a great obstacle to joint research
under the auspices of an international
organization such as Unesco.
UPGRADING RESEARCH
The programme to foster social science
research and its applications, the title of
which is MOST (the Management of Social
Transformations) is to have an Intergovern¬
mental Council of thirty-three members
elected by Unesco's General Conference, half
ofwhom will be replaced every two years. It
is also to have a Scientific Committee ofnine
members, who will work to expand research
in the developing countries.
One of the principal underlying ideas
of the programme is that of bringing
researchers in the human sciences back
into the decision-making process. "All too
often they not only have no links with
other sectors or other countries, but have
no concern for the practical implications
of their research either. Decision-makers
too often complain that the only docu¬
ments they have are incomprehensible,"
says Kazancigil, who pleads for an
"upgrading of research".
A French researcher, Francis Godard, a
leader ofan interdisciplinary research pro¬
gramme on cities being carried out under
the auspices of the French National Centre
for Scientific Research (CNRS), stresses the
vital importance of this question ("it is in
cities that the future of human relations is
being decided") and the extent to which
the scientific community needs interna¬
tional programmes: "There is very little
contact between researchers," says Godard,
"and this leads to considerable wastage."
MOST is not only an English word. It
also means "bridge" in Russian.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
10 0 4-1005
CULTURE
Unesco works for
the integration of
culture into all
\
areas of human
activity
A SOURCE OF
INSPIRATION
by Sue Williams
In Canada, the traditional ecological
knowledge of the Indian populations is
being collected and documented as part of
the quest for sustainable development
models. In Indonesia, efforts are underway
to develop a style of tourism that high¬
lights the country's outstanding cultural
heritage without damaging it. Meanwhile,
in Africa a "Culture Train" is in the plan¬
ning, linking Nairobi to the Cape, to pro¬
mote the performing arts in the southern
part of the continent. Although these are
but three of a range of projects being
undertaken by Unesco's Culture Sector,
they well illustrate the direction being
taken for the 1994-1995 biennium, which
also marks the mid-point of the World
Decade for Cultural Development: to take
culture out of its "ghetto" and recognize the
role it plays in virtually all areas ofhuman
society.
"The objective of the Decade is to incor¬
porate culture into all domains of activity,
ranging from the economy to health and
the environment," says Unesco's Assistant
Director-General for Culture, Henri Lopes,
"and, in doing so, to encourage the active
participation ofpopulations in the devel¬
opment process."
One of the main vehicles for this will be
the World Commission on Culture and
Development, established at the end of
1992 and presided over by former UN Sec¬
retary-General Javier Pérez de Cuéllar.
Essentially, the Commission's task is to
formulate policies and practices that,
according to Mr. Pérez de Cuéllar, "will
lead to a more human, sustainable and
unifying form of development."
The move in this direction has also led
to a new emphasis on the intangible cul¬
tural heritage traditions, skills and lan¬
guages that in many places are dying out
but constitute a vital part of a people's cul¬
tural identity. "This is not only a way of
preserving a people's memory and knowl¬
edge," says Doudou Diene, who is in
charge of intercultural projects. "Tradi¬
tional crafts and forms of artistic expres¬
sion have always been shaped by outside
influences. Culture and cultural identity
are the result of constant movement, inter¬
action and exchange. This is a particularly
important message today, when the
defence ofcultural identity has become a
source of conflict."
Centres to study cultural identities and
foster intercultural co-operation are cur¬
rently being planned for the Mediter¬
ranean basin, southeast Europe, central
Asia and southern Africa.
RAPID RESPONSE TEAM
The second major pole ofaction in the
cultural domain for 1994-1995 is the
preservation of the world's sites, monu¬
ments and cultural property. Here, a major
reinforcement effort is underway to
encourage more Member States to accede
to the World Heritage Convention. The
World Heritage Centre, established in 1992
to "promote and mobilize", is also refo-
cusing its efforts to better ensure the pro¬
tection of the 378 sites on the World Her¬
itage List. "The mere listing of properties
is not sufficient" says the Centre's director,
Bernd von Droste. "We need more effective
site management. This means systematic
monitoring, which in turn means better
information and documentation on sites,
especially the fifteen now on the World
Heritage in Danger List." It has also been
decided to set up a team ofspecialists who
can move quickly into emergency situa¬
tions, such as natural disasters, and launch
safeguarding operations a sort of rapid
response team for the world's natural and
cultural treasures.
Given the surge in illicit art trafficking,
especially in eastern Europe, the coming
biennium will see the strengthening of the
Convention on the Means of Prohibiting
and Preventing the Illicit Import, Export
and Transfer of Ownership of Cultural
Property. "Many ofUnesco's new Member
States are not even aware ofhow the Con¬
vention works or how they can use it," says
Lyndel Prott, head of Unesco's Interna¬
tional Standards Section. "To correct this
situation, we are planning a series of sem¬
inars in West Africa, South America and
central Asia, not only to inform but also to
provoke some action and stem the tide of
smuggling from these regions."
Despite the belt tightening that has
marked the past fewyears, this biennium
will see the budget allocated to the Culture
Sector increased to $41.7 million. This
reflects the priority given to this area at a
time when, stresses Federico Mayor, "ten¬
sions and conflicts have a growing ten¬
dency to be cultural in origin [and] a gen¬
uine intercultural dialogue is becoming
an urgent necessity." 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
TO FIHD OUT MORE . .
ABOUT UNESCO
What ¡s Unesco? A 15-page brochure describing
the Organization, its history and objectives,
how it functions and what can be done to
support its action.
Unlsco publishes a wide range of information
material on its programme, including:
Education: Unlsco: Worldwide action in
education. An illustrated 56-page booklet
presents UiNiisco's strategy to meet the
challenge of Education for All (EFA). EFA2000 is
a quarterly bulletin reporting on activities of
inter-agency efforts to achieve EFA goals.
Science: Descriptive leaflets, newsletters and other
materials are available from the secretariats of
Unesco's major scientific programmes,
including the Man and the Biosphere
Programme (MAB) (notably InfoMAB); the
Intergovernmental Océanographie
Commission (IOC) (notably International
Marine Science (IMS) Newsletter), the
International Geological Correlation
Programme (IGCP) and the International
Hydrological Programme (IHP).
Culture: Culture +, newsletter of the World
Decade for Cultural Development; The World
Heritage Newsletter reports on the state of
conservation of sites on the WH list and on
activities of the WH Committee and the WH
Centre. The World Heritage, a map indicating the
location of sites (378 in 1993), with colour photos
and details on the WH Convention and Fund.
Ml this material is availablefrom the bookshop at
Unhsco Headquarters, 7 place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris, France.
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, page 3: Peter Willi © Explorer, Musée
National d'Art Moderne, ADAGP, 1993, Paris. Page
2: © Georges Tardy, France. Pages 4-5: Sara
Binovic © Gamma, Paris. Page 7: Zoom 77 ©
Gamma, Paris. Page 9: © RMN, touvre Museum,
Paris. Page 1 0: © Jean-Loup Charmet, Paris. Page
I I: Nimatallah © Artephot, Paris. Villa Giulia,
Rome. Pages 12, 14 and IS (below), 16, 17, 20,
21 (middle and below), 24 (right), 30 (below),
32-33, 33 (top right), 34, 36, 39: All rights
reserved. Page 13: © G. Dagli Orti, Paris.
Bibliothèque Nationale, Lisbon. Page 14 (above):
© Giraudon, Paris, Iraqi Museum, Baghdad. Page 15
(above): © G. Dagli Orti, Louvre Museum, Paris.
Page 1 8: © Marise Pell/Charles Lénars, Paris. Page
19: © RMN, Musée Guimet, Paris. Page 21
(above): © Lauros-Giraudon, Musée Cernuschi,
Paris. Page 22: © Dagli Orti, Paris. National
Museum of Anthropology, Mexico City. Page 23: ©
G. Dagli Orti, Paris. Page 24 (left): © Sachsische
Landesbibliothek, Dresden. Page 25: N. Thibaut ©
Explorer, Paris. Pages 26, 27 (above): Unesco.
Page 26 (below): © OCAK, Ankara. Page 27
(below): Illustration Joe Hunt © IOC, Paris. Pages
28-29: © Eliane Aboussouan, Beirut. Page 30
(above): Jean-Louis Nou © Van en Inde, Editions
Citadelles et Mazenod, Paris. Pages 31, 33
(below): © Roland Michaud, Paris. Page 35: © G.
Dagli Orti, Museum of Capodimonte, Italy. Page
37: © Eric Juillard, Paris. Page 38: M. Huet © Hoa
Qui, Paris. Page 40: © RMN, Institut des Sciences
Humaines, Niamey, Niger. Page 41 (above): ©
RMN, Paris. Musée National de Bénin City. Page 41
(below): © RMN, Paris. Page 42: © Viollet
Collection, Paris. Page 44: UNESCO-Michel Claude.
Unesco
courier
46th YEAR
Published monthly in 32 languages and in Braille by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
3), rue François Borwh. 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcornb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lèvèque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Migue! Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation:
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel, 45.68.46.87i
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Pritni Perera
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta 145.68.47.1 4)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Moncrioux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Serpil Gogen (Ankara)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-cs-Salaam)
Slovene: Alexandra Komhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shcn Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colomao)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donastia)
Thai: Pornnipha Limpnphayom (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Ghoti Khaweri (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernández {Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonckco, M'chel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motretf (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel : 45 .68.45 .65
I year: 21 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
B nder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line roads "Reprnted from the Uníí-íq Courier", plus
d.ite of ¡sine, and three voucher copies nee sent to the editor, Signed art -
des reprinted must bea-" author's name. Non-copyright photos wil be sup¬
plied on request-. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompan cdby r.n international reply coupon covering postage. Signed art¬
eles express the opinions of liic authors anc do not necessarily rcorcscnt
['re opin ons of UNESCO or those of the editors of the (JwCSCC Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the UNESCO Couriei stiff. The bound¬
aries on maps published n the magazine do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by Unesco or the United Natrons. The UNESCO Courier is pro¬
duced m microform (microfilm anc-'or microfiche) by: (I) UNESCO, 7
P;acc dc Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. (2) University M trofïlms (Xerox). Ann
Arbor. Michigan 48 1 00 J S.A. (3) NCR, M crocard Edition, Ind.an Head
Inc .III West 40th Street, New York. U.S.A ; (4) Be I and Howell Co., O d
Mansfield Road, Woostcr. Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: C I - NOVEMBRE 1 993
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N ' 71842 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Pnotocor" position, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'UnesCO.
Impression: IMAYE GRAPHIC
Z.I. des Touches. 8d Henn-ßecquerc!. 5302! Lava! Cedex (France)
ISSN 0304-3 1 18 N H-:993-ODl-93-520A
c'mémattièiiiiee
revue semestrielle d'esthétique
et d'histoire du cinéma
Tnis issue comp-ises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 10- Il and 42-43.
T r u f f a u t
D r e y e r
Disney
Panorama
Scénario
Parution du numéro 4
le 10 novembre
Vente en librairie : 135 F
et sur abonnement (2 numéros) : 200 F.
Publié par la Cinémathèque française
et YELLOW NOW, avec le concours du
Centre national des lettres et du
Centre national de la cinématographie
et le partenariat de
la Fondation Crédit Lyonnais.
Revue cinémathèque,
29 rue du Colisée, 75008 Paris.
Tél. : (1)45 53 21 86.
Photos : Pickup on South Street S. Fuller 1953.
8IFI Coll. Cinematheque française.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
293, avenue Daumesnil
75012 Paris
14 octobre 1993 - 10 janvier 1994
Le cavalier de Bura, Institut Uîi recherches en sciences humai nos. Ninmey. Nlge
Photo Denis Rouvre
FONDATION
elf
déc 93
M Mairie
de Montreuil C'est avec
une bonne pile
qu'on recharge
ses batteries
SALON DU LIVRE DE JEUNESSE
m beine baint-uenis
^ ^Conseil Général
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Unesco
^courier
EACH MONTH, ESSENTIAL
READING FOR AN
UNDERSTANDING OF THE
PROBLEMS OF TODAY AND
nti'f;
TELE...VISIONS ... THE CHALLENGE OF
DEMOCRACY ... THE COMPETITIVE WORLD OF
SPORT ... EXPLORING THE COSMOS ...
VIOLENCE ... PSYCHOANALYSIS:
THE HIDDEN I ... A TINE TO LOVE ...
WATER OF LIFE ... MINORITIES... WHAT IS
MODERN?... RHYTHM, GESTURE AND THE
SACRED... TINE TO DISARM... THE STORY OF
NUMBERS...
EACH MONTH: AN INT
FROM THE WORLD OF
ruLTURE.--
ND... JORGE AMADO ...
RICHARD ATTENBOROUGH ... JEAN-CLAUDE
CARRIÈRE... JEAN LACOUTURE ... FEDERICO
MAYOR... NAGUIB NAHFOUZ ... SEMBENE
OUSMANE ... ANDREI VOZNESENSKY ...
FREDERIC ROSSIF ... HINNERK BRUHNS ...
CAMILO JOSÉ CELA ... VACLAV HAVEL ...
SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV ... ERNESTO
SÁBATO... GRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND ...
CLAUDE LÉVI-STRAUSS ... LEOPOLDO ZEA ...
PAULO FREIRÉ ... DANIEL J. BOORSTIN ...
FRANCOIS JACOB ... MANU DIBANCO ...
FAROUK HOSNY ... SADRUDDIN AGA KHAN ...
JORGE LAVELLI ... LÉON SCHWARTZENBERG ...
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN ... GABRIEL GARCÍA
MARQUEZ ... JACOUES-YVES COUSTEAU ...
NELINA MERCOURI ... CARLOS FUENTES ...
JOSEPH KI-ZERBO ... VANDANA SHIVA ...
WILLIAM STYRON ... OSCAR NIEMEYER ...
NIKIS THEODORAKIS ... ATAHUALPA
YUPANQUI... HERVÉ BOURGES ... ABDEL
RAHMAN EL BACHA ... SUSANA RINALDI ...
HUBERT REEVES ... JOSÉ CARRERAS ...
A LETTER FROM FREUD TO EINSTEIN ...
LUC FERRY ... CHARLES MALAMOUD ...
UMBERTO ECO ... OLIVER STONE... ANDRÉ
BRINK... JANES D. WATSON... ANOS OZ...
EACH MO
HlBWORL»
THENE OF THE NEXT ISSUE
(DECEMBER 1991):
THE MEANING
OF PROGRESS;
A NORTH-SOUTH
DEBATE
ALSO FEATURING AN INTERVIEW
WITH THE FRENCH PHILOSOPHER
MICHEL SERRES
]]>
</page>
</document>
