<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="096065eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication m this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
exannple of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two worl<s from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resennblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
1980, wood and horse's
teeth (height 80 cm)
by Chico Tabibuia
"You ¡earn from books, 1
fearn from dreams," says
Chico Tabibuia, a former
wood-cutter who has
become one of the
masters of contemporary
Brazilian folk art. The
sculpture showrt here,
like his other works, first
appeared to him in a
dream. It depicts Exu, a
divinity of fertility and
the power of creation in
"umbanda", an Afro-
Brazilian cult. The
Brazilian museologist
Paulo Pardal, who
discovered Tabibuia and
has encouraged his work,
sees in his sculptures "the
unconscious presence of
age~old universal myths."
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 iNmmwwiTH
Yves Coppens r «iKents
FEBRHARY IM4
WORLPS
WITHIN WORDS
41 UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
44 UNESCO IN ACTION
- ARCHIVES
The way to coexistence
fc/ Arnold Toynbee
46 UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
The royal palaces
of Abemey
by]asmma Sopova
49 RECENT RECORDINGS
by kabelte Leymaríe
50 LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
i 0 The 9iH of tongues
by Stephet) Wurm
1 6 Babel revisited
by Peter Mühlhäusler
1 1 Nigeria's ciioice
by Ayo Bamgbose
3 1 Language death in Siberia
by Vladimir Belikov
3 1 The chicken and the banana
38 Of gifts and gaffes
byjia Tlan
Cover:
L'arc du verbe (1993), a computer-
generated image specially produced by
Ezéchiel Saad for this issue.
Languages are visualized as waves of
colour propagating thought through
the universe.
Greenwatch
41
COHHEMÏARY
by Federico Mayor
TÏÏÏÏT '^'
NESCO
OURIER
47th year Publahed monthly
in 32 lar\guages ond in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments »rould not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intelleaual and moral solidarity of manl<ind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each odicr's lives. . . ."
£XTfMaf/!0A1 7H£ PREAMBLE TO THE C0NS7ÍTUTÍ0N OF UNESCO, LONÛON, (6 NOVU^BER 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
YVES COPPENS
talks to
Francis Leary
A palaeontologist of international reputation, Yves Coppens
is professor of paleoanthropology and prehistory at the Collège de
France (Paris). He has carried out extensive fieldwork which has led to the
discovery of many fossil hominids and the oldest known manufactured
stone tools (over three million years old). He has also constructed
models to explain the origin of hominids (eight million years ago), and the
origins of Man (three million years ago), as well as a cultural
model to explain the evolution of thought
Among his recent publications are: Préambules, Les premiers pas de
l'Homme (1988); Le rêve de Lucy (1990, in collaboration with Pierre Pelot
and Tanino Liberatore); and "The Origin and Evolution of Man", which
appeared in From the Stars to Thought, no. 155 of DIOGENES, the
quarterly review of the International Council of Philosophy and Humanistic
Studies (published with Unesco support by Berg Publishers, Providence,
U.SA, and Oxford, U.K).
Gauguinpaintedafamous triptych that
depicted naked dream figures of Tahitian
women together with animals anda native
goddess. He made this brilliant fantasy of
colour and imagery a haunting symbol of
the human situation by entitling it: "Where
do we comefrom ? Who are wef Where are
we going?" Could we say that Gauguin's
questions summarize the goals of anthro¬
pological investigation ?
Absolutely. They were probably also
the first three questions that occurred to
man's earliest conscious mind, what some
recent philosophers have termed "existen¬
tial anguish". This triptych by Gauguin is
so symbolic of these basic questions in our
field that I used it on the cover of a volume
in the series of scientific publications
FRANCIS LEARY
is an American writer and journalist
entitled Les Cahiers de Paléoanthropologie,
which I have edited for fifteen years.
Dinosaurs are a subject ofgreatpopular
interest, these monsters that roamed the
Earth 220 million years ago, persisting
through theJurassic and Cretacious before
disappearing about 70 million years ago.
Various explanations have been advanced
for the extinction ofthe dinosaurs. What is
your viewf
The problem of massive extinction of
species is linked to the different episodes of
Earth's history, such as expansion and con¬
traction of the seas. During the last 500
million years, thirty-five such extinctions
have been known. This means that the
extinction of the dinosaurs, with that of
certain molluscs at the same time, is not an
exception. The meteorite theory of the
"Death Star" crashing into Earth is for me
a romance as big as some dinosaurs! For
cosmic reasons, the position of the Earth
on its parallax and consecutive alterations
of climate mean that the history of life
consists of successive periods of expan¬
sion alternating with periods of slow
decrease or even a quite rapid extinction of
species.
Is it not possible that the very size of
these monsters has influenced theories con¬
cerning their extinction? Afierce carnivore
such as Tyrannosaurus Rex, 15 metres
*L
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
long, couldn 'tjust quietlyfade away. Surely
some great catastrophe was neededfor its
exit?
I think that you are right. The extinction
of the invertebrates called trilobites 200
million years before, or the disappearance
of the beautiful molluscs, the ammonites,
at the same time as the dinosaurs, have not
inspired such romantic theories.
Are the birds we see today descended
from dinosaurs?
Definitely, yes. The earliest birds known,
the Archaeopteryx, of the UpperJurassic,
were very like dinosaurs, with anatomical
similarities, such as teeth and long savage
claws, to the small dinosaur, Deinonychus,
discovered by Dr. John Ostrom of Yale in
1964. Archaeopteryx, however, was also
warm-blooded, with feathers for insula¬
tion, like birds.
To get the time-scale ofMan 's origins
intofocus, true apes, the very remote ances¬
tors of Man, emerged about 20 million
years ago. Afterseveralmillion more years,
the line ofprimates split, giving rise to
apes such as chimps and gorillas on the
one handandhominids on the other. What
brought about this split, without which
we wouldneverhave existed, at least in our
presentform?
After fifteen years of digging in East
Africa between 1963 and 1978, 1 was sur¬
prised not to have collected any fossil rem¬
nants of chimps or pre-chimps and gorillas
or pre-gorillas among hundreds of thou- I
sands of fossil vertebrates distributed along 1
geological levels dating from eight to one j
million years. In contrast, I found in these j
sites hundreds of hominid remains. As i
molecular biologists and geneticists were j
then claiming that the African apes were j
obviously Man's closest relatives as far as \
the genetic card and proteins were con- Í
cerned, that is, chimps and gorillas were j
cousins and we shared with them common í
ancestors, I thought it interesting to try |
to solve this curious enigma. The African i
apes and ourselves were cousins, yet in the j
field were never found together. )
In 1982, 1 suggested at a conference in I
Rome and subsequently in other places j
and in many papers a model to explain this j
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
There is a good possibility
that Man had an Australopithecus as
progenitor. But which one? It's not yet
known for sure.
: apparent discrepancy, a model that I called
i "The East Side Story". Just before the split
occurred between apes and hominids, eight
million years ago, our common ancestors
: were living all across Equatorial Africa,
from the Atlantic to the Indian Ocean, in
very low-lying humid country, covered
with a dense forest and wooded areas.
A tectonic event intervened. The Rift
Valley sank 4,000 metres, while its
; périmètre thrust up 4,000 metres, forming
a barrier between west and east. This had
: important ecological consequences. Cut
off from the east, the western region
; between the Rift and the Atlantic remained
\ humid and wooded, while the eastern area
; between the Rift and the Indian Ocean
. became open country, much less humid
: and only seasonally watered by the new¬
born system of monsoons.
Our common ancestors, the apes, were
'- divided into a large western group and a
small eastern one. The western apes, in
; their forested niche, could have been ances-
\ tors of chimps and gorillas, while the
' eastern apes, having to adapt to the new
: open grasslands, could very well have been
the precursors of hominids, Australop-
; ithecus and Homo in succession.
: So that's how our ancestors got down
from the trees.
: They got down because they had to!
i With the trees disappearing, they had no
: choice.
Thefossil skeleton ofafemale was dis¬
covered in the Afar Valley ofEthiopia in
1974. Dating from about three million
years, this skeleton was more complete
than that of any previous find. She was
christened "Lucy", after the Beatles' song
Lucy in the Sky with Diamonds. Can
you discuss this Afar expedition and its
significance forpalaeontology?
The Afar palaeontological sites were
found by a French geologist, Maurice
Taieb, in the 1960s. As I knew him well, I
was the first to be consulted and I gave
him the approximate geological age of these
sites, according to the determination of
the fossil remains collected, which was
two to three million years.
In 1972, Taieb organized an expedi¬
tion under international leadership: two
French scientists, Taieb and myself, and
two Americans, Don Johanson and Jon
Kalb, which constituted the International
Afar Research Expedition. We conducted
five field campaigns over a period of six
years. The chief discovery was that of Lucy,
an Australopithecus about three million
years old. It was the first time that such a
complete skeleton from that epoch had
been found and we could as never before
get a good idea of the size of the specimen,
the proportions and how the joints
worked.
In my own lab, I had ten theses done on
this analysis, each one over three years; in
other words a total of thirty years trying to
understand Lucy's behaviour! We finally
created the extraordinary picture of a pre¬
human female, probably twenty years old,
between 1 metre and lm. 20 in height and
weighing 20-25 kilos, with long arms and
short legs. She ate fruit, roots and tubers
and may have had primitive stone tools.
She stood erect and walked as a biped but
with short steps, rolling her shoulders and
hips. With her flat feet and prehensile big
toe, the curved phalanges of her hands and
feet, she was still climbing trees.
Where would you place Lucy in our
family tree?
Lucy was probably a cousin but
descended anyway from one species of
Australopithecus to which we gave the sci¬
entific name Australopithecus afarensis,
which also became the genus Homo that
appeared in East Africa three million years
ago. This appearance was linked to another
environmental event that I had discovered
in 1970 in the sediment of the Omo River
Valley, in southern Ethiopia. That's why,
making a pun, I called it the (H)OMO
event.
Between 3.3 million and 2.4 million
years ago, an important climatic crisis
occurred a prolonged drought. The
number of trees drastically decreased, as we
know from fossils contained in geological
levels of three million to two million years.
The entire fauna altered, trying to adapt to
the changed environment. For hominids,
the genus Homo, with a much larger brain,
was the solution. Poor Lucy had a brain of
only 340 cc, while Homo's brain was 800
cc. Homo was also equipped with a denti¬
tion adapted to a much more varied diet
than that oí Australopithecus.
In 1972 the Kenyan anthropologist
RichardLeakey discovered on the shores of
Lake Turkana in Kenya some hominid
fossils datingfrom about two million years.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
These hominidshadwalkederect, "with an
easy striding gait like that of modern
humans." Homo habilis could have been
aprogenitor ofMan, with a brain capacity
of 800 cc, or more than half that ofMan
today.
As the earliest men had been found in
East Africa, where the earliest Australop¬
ithecus had also been found; as australop-
ithecines are the beings with the nearest
resemblance to Man; and as the earliest
australopithecines are older than the earliest
men, there is a good possibility that Man
had an Australopithecus as progenitor. But
which one? It's not yet known for sure.
Australopithecines were vegetarians
and only exceptionally carnivores out of
necessity. Because of the climatic crisis of
three million years ago, the Homo (Homo \
habilis) are both vegetarians and meat- \
eaters; thus, they could very well have been !
the first killers, sometimes scavengers but '
hunters as well.
Controversy over whetherMan inher¬
ited an instinct for killing from ancestors ;
millions ofyears agofirst began with Ray- :
mondDart. This South Africanprofessor of
Anatomy concluded that a skullfound in ;
1924 at Taung near the Kalahari Desert I
was that ofan Australopithecus, sixyears
oldandliving three millionyears ago. The
creature walked erect, with a brain the
size ofa gorilla's. The evidence ofthe teeth
convinced Dart that it had been a carni¬
vore. Was he right?
Dart's interpretation of some animal ;
bones that he associated with Australop- ;
ithecus as tools, called by some writers
"Danifacts", was perhaps partly correct. ;
But now it seems more likely that,
according to the analysis of marks on the
occusal surface of their teeth and the
analysis of the tooth morphology, the aus- -
tralopithecines were vegetarians, not car-
nivores.
One day in Antanarivo, Madagascar, I ;
had to give a lecture on the "Taung baby"
and the organizers of the event had the :
idea of making a large poster with the :
restored image of the Australopithecus
infant. Shortly before the lecture, I saw
two Malgache ladies looking at the poster
and one said to the other, "This lecturer
seems really very young!"
NeanderthalMan, whosefossil was dis¬
covered nearDusseldorfin 1856, was said \
to have descendedfrom Australopithecus
robustus, a slow-brained, heavy-jawed,
plant-eating hominid. Hefadedfrom the
picture, the pace a million years ago too
much for him, but was said to have sur- ,
vived in NeanderthalMan, who hadsome- \
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
what similar characteristics. Hegave way
in turn to Cro-Magnon Man. What hap¬
pened to NeanderthalMan?
Australopithecus robustus is one of the
answers of the hominid family to the
(H)OMO climatic crisis, that is, a new
Australopithecus, heavier, taller and
stronger, with a very peculiar dentition,
tiny front teeth and enormous molars for
a quite specialized tough vegetarian diet.
And it now seems to us urn robustus
became extinct one million years ago.
It seems also that the first Homo,
because a bigger brain had made it more
daring and because of an omnivorous diet,
which made it more mobile, was the first to
expand its territory. These adventurers soon
reached the Middle East from East Africa
and then went on to Europe and Asia, grad¬
ually transforming themselves into what
we used to call Homo erectus and Homo
sapiens, which are not in fact true species.
But the successive glaciations of the
quaternary period, covering the Alps and
Scandinavia as well as Germany and
Poland, isolated the first hominid popula¬
tion. In such a case, a genetic drift hap¬
pens to the population. In western Europe,
Homo habilis became Homo erectus as
elsewhere, but a particular Homo erectus,
already with some Neanderthal features,
and this Homo erectus became Homo
sapiens as elsewhere, but a very distinc¬
tive Homo sapiens that we call Homo
sapiens Neanderthalensis.
So Neanderthal Man is not the descen¬
dant of robustus but is what Homo became
in an island called western Europe. This
genetic drift only came to a stop between
30 and 40,000 years ago, when Homo
sapiens sapiens came from the Middle East
to Western Europe. Otherwise, the Nean¬
derthal phenomenon could have given
birth to a new Humanity, unable to inter¬
breed anymore with the other one, that is,
with Cro-Magnon Man.
Darwin 's thesis ofthe "survival ofthe
fittest" has often been used to justify a
claim to the superiority of white people
over others, blacks and Amerindians, for
example. What do you think about this?
Every scientist, in any discipline, has,
like any layman, more or less preconceived
ideas. Everything is all right as long as such
ideas are just working hypotheses. If these
hypotheses are confirmed, it's fine, but if
they are not, the true scientist must forget
them and change his thinking. That's the
way to recognize a good scientist.
Darwin was an outstanding scientist,
with particularly clear and synthesizing
concepts, but he was quite wrong when he
tried to apply, without any correction, his
conclusions obtained from plants or ani-
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
mais to Man and human societies. He
forgot that Culture interfered, bringing
liberty and responsibility while dramati¬
cally changing the rules.
On entering the Paris Musée de
l'Homme, ofwhich you wereformerly the
director, a large sign tells one to leave "Cul¬
ture" in the cloakroom and concentrate
on the universal biological affinity of
humankind. Yet, as we may see every day
on TV, people can be violently aroused by
bothphysicalandcultural differences, pro¬
ducing outbursts ofrage and hatred.
It's true that there are differences
between people and it's true that people are
often divided by economic, territorial and
religious rivalries, causing violent behav¬
iour. But it's also true that these differ¬
ences are essentially superficial. We are all
Homo sapiens sapiens and share the same
genetic characteristics, separating us from
the apes.
Somepeople have seized upon discov¬
eries in anthropology as demonstrations
ofdivine intervention, on thegrounds that
no scientist has been able to explain fully
the development ofthe human mind, with
all its complexities andachievements. How
does one accountforMan 's unique stature
in the animal kingdom?
The invention of the first stone tools
was an essential stage in Evolution, the
introduction of culture in Nature. My own
expedition in southern Ethiopia found the
earliest tools, 3.3 million years old. After
the natural environment has prevailed for
four billion years, suddenly, three million
years ago, a new environment is created by
a hominid. This changes everything
because Man will respond to the sollicita¬
tions of the natural environment faster
than Nature, adapting to them before
biology does. Thus, biological evolution
will decrease and finally stop.
Man is the only animal to have
"chosen" to develop his nervous system
at this level for his adaptation.
The quest for an explanation beyond
Evolution, born of consciousness and the
effort to reduce the "angoisse existentielle",
is outside the realm of science. The end of
our scientific research is to describe the
world through its history; to find an expla¬
nation of how it works. And the natural
explanation cannot solve the supernatural
question.
Every step in the history of life has
been extraordinary the origin of life itself,
only known for a brief hour in palaeonto-
logical time, the appearance of pericel¬
lular beings and of sexuality, the respiration
of air, the development of vision, of
thought, of speech, the invention of culture.
Thanks to prehistorical studies, we know
about the intermediate steps between the
first tool-maker and Cro-Magnon, as well
as, for example, those between Cro-
Magnon and the civilization of Sumer and
Akkad.
Man is the only animal to have
"chosen" to develop his nervous system at
this level for his adaptation. Other ani¬
mals have chosen the transformation of
their limbs in order to run faster or of their
teeth to improve their diet. A scientific
answer would be: confronted by such an
environmental event, it so happened that
Man adapted to the new conditions by the
development of a big brain, but it might
just as well have been the horse. A philo
sophical response would be: this event
occurred in this area and not elsewhere
and at that time and not at another time and
Man was the member of the animal
kingdom who developed his brain.
Can human nature be so modifiedas to
prevent the extinction ofour race by all-out
war, by the destruction ofourfragile envi¬
ronment, or by runaway demographic
problems?
I must say that I am optimistic. Since the
emergence of consciousness about three
million years ago, humanity has developed
knowledge of itself and of its environment,
losing its primeval instincts and gaining
its liberty. Though formidable individual or
collective problems remain, the way we
are organizing answers to these problems
is very impressive.
Overall, humanity is becoming a
thinking, rational and organized society,
aware of its responsibilities. But it is not
easy: over three million years we have had
to learn to deal with hundreds of thou¬
sands of people, then with millions. Now
we have to cope with billions. Education,
the acquisition of more knowledge, the
colonization of our solar system and, in the
distant future, of other systems will bring
us to a better understanding of our world,
better control of ourselves and of our
planet and an increase in freedom.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THE GIFT OF TONGUß
by Stephen Wurm
=SEr5=^^
lO
STEPHEN WURM,
of Australia, is Professor of
Linguistics in the Research
School of Pacific Studies of the
Australian National University
in Canberra. Among his 300
publications are Papuan
Languages of Oceania ( 1 982),
Language Atlas ofthe Pacific Area
(1981-1983) and Language At/as
of China (1987-1990).
N
ORE than 5,000 different languages are
currently spoken in the world, with a
very much larger number of dialects.
Many of them are mutually unintelligible or
virtually so, and are spoken by small groups of
people.
The need for communication across lin¬
guistic and cultural boundaries which has
become even more pressing and widespread in
recent decades as a result of dramatic increases
in the movements of people in many parts of the
world can be met in a number of different
ways. One common method is for speakers of
two different languages that are used adjacently
to each other to learn to speak, at least to some
extent, the language of their neighbours. This is
called active two-way bilingualism. If only one
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
of two groups that speak different languages
learns the language of its neighbours, this is
called active one-way bilingualism. For instance,
if two neighbouring groups live near the
seashore but only one of them has access to the
sea and possesses a commodity such as salt or
fish that the other group is eager to acquire, the
sellers of such commodities are in an economi¬
cally more powerful position than the potential
buyers, and their language takes precedence
over that of the inland tribe when contact occurs.
Ambassadors and negotiators
One interesting case of bilingualism has been
observed among certain traditionally hostile
tribes in Papua New Guinea who speak dif¬
ferent languages but need to communicate with
each other in order to settle disputes. These
tribes customarily exchange children who then
learn the language of the tribe that has adopted
them, in addition to their own. Afterwards,
they act as ambassadors and interpreters, helping
to negotiate settlements or other matters arising
from tribal disputes. Their safety is ensured by
strict laws on both sides.
Members of very small language communi¬
ties which are surrounded by larger linguistic
groups usually learn to speak several of their
neighbours' languages. Such people may play an
important cultural role as interpreters, nego¬
tiators and intermediaries.
Another solution to the intercommunication
problem occurs when the speakers of two or
several closely related neighbouring languages
Above, a dancer ofthe
Trobriand Islands (Papua
New Guinea) during a
festivity associated with
the kula, a ceremonial
form of economic
exchange.
Opposite page, the leader
of a village community at
Ccatca in the department
of Cuzco (Peru) holding his
silver-tipped staff of office.
I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
learn to understand, but not to speak, their
neighbours' languages. Participants in such sit¬
uations speak their own language and are under¬
stood by all their communication partners, and
vice versa. This is called passive bilingualism or
passive multilingualism. It is especially common
between speakers of different Turkic or Mon¬
golian languages in Central Asia, but is also
found in parts of Africa and New Guinea.
Lingua francas
The cases mentioned so far involve languages
that are native to at least one of the communi
cating groups. However, there are many situa¬
tions in which languages not native to any of the
speakers are used as a means of intercommuni¬
cation. They occur frequently between speakers
of European and non-European metropolitan
languages, such as when a Frenchman, a Nor¬
wegian, a Hungarian and a Japanese communi¬
cate with each other in English. Such a contact
language used for wider communication is called
a lingua franca.
There are many of these languages in the
world, and they achieve their status for a variety
of reasons, one of which may be that their
It
Left, sports day at a
school in a Paris suburb.
Opposite page, villagers
wall< to the fields on the
island of Java (Indonesia).
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
speakers possess some appealing cultural features
or achieve cultural or political supremacy, which
makes their language prestigious in the eyes of
speakers of other languages. Many of them
emerge as a result of trading relations in which
the speakers of a given language take their wares
far and wide for sale, and use only their own lan¬
guage, which their customers have to learn, at
least rudimentarily, in order to trade with them.
Examples of such traders' lingua francas are
Kiswahili in East Africa, Bazaar Malay in the
East Indies (though it is now receding before
Indonesian), and several trade languages in the
New Guinea area. In centuries past, Iranian lan¬
guages such as Sogdian and Middle Persian, and
later Modern Persian, were used as trade lingua
francas on the silk route across Asia.
ridgin languages
The majority of such trade lingua francas
become simplified when used as such, but they
continue in their original full form within the
communities that use them as their native
tongues. Some trade languages have become
pidgin languages, that is languages that are
sharply reduced in their grammatical complexity
and vocabulary. Examples include a Russian-
Chinese pidgin used in the Chinese-Russian
border areas in Siberia from the eighteenth to the
twentieth centuries, a number of pidgins devel¬
oped from local indigenous languages in parts of
New Guinea before the time of European con¬
tacts, and an Inuit pidgin used between Inuit and
Alaskan Indians in northern Alaska during the
nineteenth century.
A more common way for a pidgin language
to emerge is as a means of communication when
representatives of a metropolitan culture estab¬
lish a colonial-type rule over indigenous popu¬
lations. Quite often, however, such tongues
become lingua francas that permit wider inter¬
communication between speakers of different
local languages. This is especially true in areas in
which many different tongues are spoken, as is
the case in Papua New Guinea, and parts of
Africa, northern Siberia and South America.
The grammars and sound structures of these
pidgins reflect, in varying degrees, features ofthe
language or languages of the local indigenous
population, while their vocabularies are usu¬
ally, but not always, based on the metropolitan
language with an admixture of indigenous ele¬
ments. Most such pidgins, where they are still
spoken, have become the first language of com¬
munities, replacing their original native lan¬
guages. Such languages are called creóles. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
There are, however, some parts of the world
in which very prominent and widely-used
pidgin languages have not, or have only to a
very limited extent, replaced local languages.
These areas include New Guinea and regions
adjacent to it, where several large pidgin lan¬
guages play very important roles because of the
enormous multiplicity and diversity of the local
tongues. Nevertheless, the indigenous popula¬
tions adhere tenaciously to their native lan¬
guages, which are their most cherished sym¬
bols of cultural and ethnic identity.
Many pidgin languages that are in close con¬
tact with the metropolitan languages on which
much of their vocabulary is based tend to grad¬
ually approximate to that language in both
vocabulary and grammar and to move towards
that language via what is called the post-pidgin
(or post-creole) stage. Eventually they become
sub-standard forms of the metropolitan lan¬
guage concerned.
iVlessages of religion and power
The so-called mission languages, also known
as church languages, constitute another type of
language of wider intercommunication. These
are local languages originally adopted by Euro¬
pean mission organizations as the vehicle of
their activities. When the missions extended
their work beyond the boundaries of the indige¬
nous language they had adopted, they usually
continued to use the adopted local tongue in the
new areas, making it thereby an artificially-
introduced lingua franca. With the reduction
of missionary work in many parts of the world
and the nativization of religious activities intro¬
duced by Westerners, such languages have in
some cases turned into secular lingua francas.
A somewhat similar situation is that in which
a local language is adopted as the language of
administration by a colonial or conquering
powen The language chosen for this purpose is
usually fairly widely spoken in the area in ques¬
tion and enjoys some prestige. The Dutch intro¬
duced Standard Malay as the official adminis¬
trative language and general lingua franca in
what is now Indonesia. In the same way, the
post-colonial rulers of Indonesia adopted
Indonesian as the official language even before
the country became officially independent.
(Indonesian is based on Standard Malay, which
made its introduction fairly easy.)
An example of the introduction of a con¬
queror's language as the general language in the
invaded area was the compulsory introduction
of the Quechua language of the Incas in what is
today Peru in South America. This took place a
comparatively short time before the arrival of the
Spaniards.
The metropolitan languages of present or
past colonial or similar rulers constitute another
type of lingua franca in certain areas. Even after
most colonies become independent, the lan¬
guages remain lingua francas, usually among
members of elite groups. Their use is beginning
to spread in former colonial areas, especially
among members of the young generation, at
the expense of other lingua francas, in particular
of pidgin languages.
A procession of gods chanting ritual
words is depicted in this Zapotee painting
(c. 5th-7th centuries) which adorns
a tomb at Monte Albán, a pre-Columbian
site in Mexico.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
ÛéstBfn Maf^y
SíHílf}tfn M^ls-y
/\N
í^.iíiu
, ^ ^4, .^^^tfsU^^fJSjtíiBSt
languages
on the map
Peninsular Malaysia
tlHÜij\ /f
\.¿'\ ;L
mS
Thailand
3^^gT|¿ffT»^ >. - r^^^^ "^r.
k/C-k ! I
/f (:
> ^J
lese three mops are details from Language
Atlas ofthe Pacific Area* {1981) produced
under the general editorship of Stephen Wurm
and Shirô Hottori. The Atlas is one of o series
sponsored fay the Internotionol Council for
Philosophy and Humonistic Studies with the
financial assistance of UNESCO, which
encourages the safeguarding and
revitalization of endangered longuoges as port
of Its progromme for the preservation ofthe
culturel heritoge. Atlases on the longuoges of
China and Korea have aiready appeared, and
an Atlas of the World's Languages has just
been published by Routledge, London. Other
otloses are in preparation on languages of
Interculturo/ communicotion ¡n the Pacific,
African languages, and the indigenous
languages of South America.
* Published (in Canberra) by the Australian Academy ofthe
Humanities in colloborotion with the japan fltodemy.
Oirtributed by GEO CENTER, D-7000 Stuttgart 80,
Poitfoch 80 08 30, Germany (fox; 49111 1669354).
Sfek 7 _S*^Jt fBÀ S .1
«l^P**t V '^ ' Ifcmr	 , 1»
^H
Northern Borneo
mm^^.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
sÀbEl REmiTED
by Peter Mühhousler
Unguistíc diversity is a resource whose value has beer) widely
mderestimated
ÍO
IN the biblical story of the Tower of Babel, the
descendants of Noah tried to build a tower
leading to heaven, but God frowned on their
presumption and sabotaged the common lan¬
guage that enabled them to communicate. This
story, which portrays linguistic diversity as a
divine punishment, has dominated Western
thinking about languages for centuries and as a
result many people believe that a multiplicity of
languages is undesirable.
I believe, on the other hand, that linguistic
diversity should not be seen as a problem but as an
essential resource and that there is an urgent need
to reverse policies and practices that currently
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Left, The Tower of Babel
( 1 990), acrylic on canvas by
the French artist Robert
Combas.
Right, desert greeting
(Egypt).
threaten thousands of small languages. Unless
this is done, the chance to learn from the cumula¬
tive insights, successes and errors of a large pro¬
portion of the human species will be lost forever.
¡he attractions of a single language
There have been many attempts to replace the
diversity of human languages with a single lan¬
guage. This goal was vigorously pursued by the
philosophers of the European Enlightenment
and, in the latter half of the nineteenth century,
by the supporters of artificial languages such
as Volapuk and Esperanto which attracted mil¬
lions of followers around the globe. Many
Esperantists hoped not only that Esperanto
would one day become a universal auxiliary
language but that at a later stage it would be
the world's only language.
The idea of the modem nation-state also pro¬
vides a powerful inspiration for those who are
committed to reducing linguistic diversity: a
common language is often seen as a necessary
binding ingredient for new nations. Only 200
years ago, French was not the mother tongue of
the majority of people born in France, whereas
today, non-French-speakers living in France
belong to a small and shrinking minority. What
happened in Western Europe in the past is being
repeated nowadays in states such as Indonesia,
where Bahasa Indonesia developed from being a
small auxiliary language into the country's main
language and will soon be the mother tongue of
more Indonesians than any other language.
It would be no exaggeration to say that the
choice of a single national language is often
regarded as a precondition for all moderniza¬
tion. No matter what language is chosen an
introduced language such as English, French,
Mandarin or Russian, or a newly-developed lan¬
guage such as Filipino a basic requirement is
that it should be fully intertranslatable, that is,
capable of expressing the concepts and distinc¬
tions that are needed in the modem world. But the
. need for intertranslatable languages has an unfor¬
tunate side effect the destruction of small lan¬
guages as outmoded and irrelevant.
The processes of streamlining which are
taking place in the field of language can be com¬
pared to the streamlining of the world's plant
and animal species. Both developments have been
promoted by people acting with the best of inten¬
tions reducing the cost ofcommum'cation in the
first case and feeding the world's growing popu¬
lation in the second. Regrettably, those people had
only a very limited understanding of the nature
and function of diversity.
In recent years there has been a growing real¬
ization of the importance of biological diversity,
and even more recently the voices of those advo¬
cating linguistic and cultural diversity have
become louder. However, the importance of lin¬
guistic diversity has not yet aroused widespread
public concern; nor has the notion that "lin¬
guistic ecology" needs the same amount of care
as natural ecology. There are, however, a number
of parallels between the two. First, all present-day
diversity is the outcome of processes that took a
very long time: millions of years in the case of bio¬
diversity, at least 100,000 years in the case of lin¬
guistic diversity. And once genuine diversity is
lost, it cannot be easily restored, in spite of
progress in bioengineering and linguistic engi¬
neering. A second, equally important similarity
is that linguistic diversity and diversity in the
natural world are both functional. The 10,000
or so languages that exist today reflect necessary
adaptations to different social and natural con¬
ditions. They are the result of increasing special¬
ization and finely tuned adaptation to the
changing world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
yJne world or many?
To understand the nature of this fine-tuning,
we need to contrast two theories about the rela¬
tionship between language and the world. One
theory, known as the mapping or labeling view,
maintains that we live in one world that consists
of many parts and each language provides a dif¬
ferent set of labels for the same set of parts.
According to this theory, the differences
between languages are only superficial and all
languages are fully intertranslatable.
The second theory holds that most percep¬
tions of the world and parts of the world are
brought into being and sustained by languages.
Speakers of different languages, therefore, do
not perceive the same world. Instead, different
languages emphasize and filter various aspects
of a multi-faceted reality in a vast number of
ways.
If we accept this theory, each language may be
seen as a provisional interpretation of a world so
complex that the only hope for understanding it
is to approach it from as many different per¬
spectives as possible. If we regard each language
as the result of a long history of human endeavour
to gain knowledge ofthe world, we may begin to
see why linguistic diversity is an invaluable
resource rather than an obstacle to progress.
Different languages communicate different
perceptions of reality in a number of ways. These
include differences in vocabulary, differences in
the grammatical information that is expressed, and
differences in the boundary between what is
regarded as literal truth and what is regarded as
metaphorical.
Virtually all human knowledge depends on
having criteria with which to determine similar¬
ities and differences. Doctors need to know, for
instance, whether or not the red spots on the
foreheads of two patients are symptoms of the
same disease. Psychologists need to know
whether two forms of behaviour are manifesta¬
tions ofthe same psychological state, and biolo¬
gists need to know whether two animals are
members of the same species. In most instances,
reliable criteria for similarities and differences
are difficult to come by and decisions are usually
determined by the available lexical resources.
One well-known area is that of colour names.
The same area of the colour spectrum may have
one name in one language, two names in a second
language, and three names in a third. Not making
a lexical distinction between, say, green and blue
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Re/otiVity (1953),
a lithograph by
the Dutch graphic artist
Maurits Cornelis Escher
(1898-1972).
(as in the Welsh g¿ís), means not focusing on the
difference between the two colours in real life. In
the field of plants, there are again considerable dif¬
ferences. Where certain plants are central to a
culture, an amazing degree of lexical fine-tuning
can occur. Many New Guinea languages, for
example, make dozens of distinctions between
different types of cordilync leaves, according to
whether such leaves are used for dressmaking,
decoration, magic or other purposes. Similar
fine-tuning can also be observed in the sub-lan¬
guages spoken by specialist groups in Western
societies, for example, the sub-language of motor
mechanics, painters, doctors or bankers.
Suddenly to get rid of all these fine distinctions
developed by specialists over centuries would
greatly impoverish a language such as English,
making it incapable of referring to anything
except in general terms. Abandoning language
diversity could have similar consequences on a
global scale. Specialist vocabularies and specialist
knowledge about phenomena as diverse as types
of snow, useful plants, types of weather or ways
of dealing with children would suddenly be lost.
Language and the breakdown of
traditional societies
One area that offers many examples of differences
of this kind is kinship. Anthropological linguists
have accumulated a vast amount of evidence as to
how different languages focus in different ways
on the shared properties and differences among
family members. While in English, the word
"sister" refers to the female sibling of both males
and females, in Tok Pisin of Papua New Guinea,
a pidgin language that often reflects a Melanesian
interpretation of the world, the word "sister"
means sibling of the opposite sex. A brother calls
his sister "sister" and a girl calls her brother
"sister". In some Aboriginal languages in Aus¬
tralia and other languages in Melanesia, the same
word is used to refer to both grandfather and
grandchild. In these instances, having the same
label usually means getting the same treatment.
Such labels reinforce solidarity within the group.
For example, giving the same name to members
of different generations can be a way of reducing
generational conflict. The rather impoverished
inventory of words in most modern Western
languages may not be sufficient to sustain com¬
plex extended family networks, and the replace¬
ment of an indigenous language with more dis¬
tinctions by a Western language with fewer
distinctions could be a factor in the breakdown
of traditional societies.
Another area in which there are considerable
differences between languages is the naming of
parts of the body. In many languages, including
some spoken in West Africa, the term "hand"
covers either the whole arm or the arm up to the
elbow. The West African practice of gripping
another person's lower arm when "shaking" is a
reflection of a different linguistic organization. In
my own native Alemannic, the terms "foot" and
"leg" are not distinguished lexically, something
that caused me considerable confusion when
learning High German, where the distinction is
made. In Melanesia, dogs are said to have two
arms and two legs rather than four legs, and cen¬
tipedes are perceived as having many arms rather
than many legs.
Most of the examples given so far have dealt
with the different ways in which languages lexi¬
cally subdivide a fairly tangible reality the reality
of colour or the reality of plants and people.
There are other less tangible realities where per¬
ception is even more closely linked to language:
for example, the names of emotions or states of
mind. The German word Gemütlichkeit does
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
not compare neady with the English word "cosi¬
ness", nor is "depression" the same as the out¬
moded "melancholy". The absence of words for
depression or sadness in certain Polynesian lan¬
guages would seem to correspond to the absence
of the associated phenomena.
Language is even more direcdy involved in the
creation of philosophical and religious approaches
to the world. It sustains the meaningfulness of
ideas such as solipsism, "the view that self is all
that exists or can be known" or of elements in sys¬
tems used to explain the workings ofthe universe
such as "phoneme" in linguistics or "phlogiston"
in eighteenth-century science. Death in tradi¬
tional Polynesian languages is described by a
number of words, ranging from initial permanent
unconsciousness to the ultimate disintegration of
the body. The practice of "reburial" reflects this
linguistic distinction.
Another important difference between lan¬
guages relates to the ways in which they require
speakers to make important choices about the
people they are addressing. This is well known to
English speakers who find that when they learn
French the neutral English second person singular
pronoun "you" has to be translated into "tu" or
"vous", depending on the degree of politeness or
solidarity being shown towards the person
addressed. When using nouns, some languages do
not have number distinctions at all, while others
like Fijian need to express at all times whether the
speaker is talking about one, two, three, a few or
more than a few entities. In some New Guinea
Highland languages, a sentence such as, "The
pig broke the fence", cannot be said in this kind
of neutral manner. Using grammatical endings,
the speaker has to indicate whether this is a report
of what he or she has actually observed or
whether it is an inference from indirect evidence
such as pig droppings or hearsay.
iVletaphorically speaking
The expression of social distinctions, numbers or
the credibility of a piece of information can lead
to interesting quandaries. One wonders what
advertising is like in Aiwo, a language spoken in
the Solomon Islands in which all words referring
to useless objects have to be given a prefix indi¬
cating uselessness. How could one describe a
nuclear power station in Aiwo? Would one have
to use a prefix indicating the class of entities that
are dormant but liable to sudden change?
The influence of certain semantic distinctions
may be so strong that it leads languages to inter¬
pret reality in very different ways, that may be
described as either event-dominated or object-
dominated. Many standard European languages
can be regarded as object-dominated because of
their strong tendency to convert processual verbs
into abstract, object-like nouns. For example,
the subject matter of linguistics is not perceived
as the activity of speaking but as an object termed
"language". One of the consequences for this
area of enquiry is that, while speaking always
involves people, and a spatial, temporal situa¬
tion, the abstract term language suggests an object
that can be analysed as something self-contained.
Equally important in Western languages is
the very strong presence of causalit)'. Verbs such
as "to teach" or "to cure" can be paraphrased as
"to cause to leam" and "to cause to get better".
However, there is a very different, equally valid
way of looking at what goes on in the classroom
or in a doctor's practice, as seen in languages
such as Wintu, an American Indian language
spoken in California, which favours comitative,
or "being with" interpretations. In a Wintu's
perception, the doctor takes part in the patient's
recovery and the teacher shares the learner's
learning progression. It is not at all clear that a
causative view of these matters necessarily leads
to better teaching or healing practice.
Languages, finally, differ according to the
metaphors their speakers live by. Western life
tends to be dominated by a small number of
metaphors. The saying "time is money", for
instance, reinforces cultural practices such as
charging by the hour, trying to save money by
getting things done more quickly and the view
that there are more economical and less eco¬
nomical uses of time. Needless to say, such a
metaphor does not occur in non-monetary, tra¬
ditional societies where work and gain are mea¬
sured in terms other than quantity of time
"spent". Another prominent Western metaphor
is that of "rule", the idea that there is an abstract
ruler of the universe who has laid down the rules
of nature. So deeply entrenched is this metaphor
that scientists believe that it is literally true and are
convinced they can discover the rules of nature,
a belief that has only recendy begun to weaken as
a consequence of discoveries by chaos theoreti¬
cians. Researchers on neural networks are now
beginning to question the idea that language
Right, a dancer from the
Fine Arts University of
Phnom Penh (Cambodia).
Her dress consists of a
rectangle of cloth specially
fitted and sewn before
each performance.
Delow, a Tahitian woman
(French Polynesia).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
1 ^
f^^
wL,. J
yiÊ^Ê^j^j^^^ ^v
PETER MÜHLHÄUSLER,
of Germany, taught linguistics
at the Technical University of
Berlin and then at Oxford
University (United Kingdom).
Since 1 992 he has been
Foundation Professor of
Linguistics at the University of
Adelaide (Australia). He Is a
Fellow of LInacre College,
Oxford, and a Fellow of the
Academy of the Social Sciences
of Australia.
learning involves rules and mle systems, a dogma
of linguistics for many decades. It is quite likely
that metaphors of other cultures not dominated
by the idea that the world needs to be governed
by rules may produce future breakthroughs in
scientific thinking.
Environmental discourse provides a striking
example of why learning from different languages
may be very important. Western languages have
many gaps in their ability to express aspects of the
environment. The number of edible plants the
average Westerner can name contrasts very
unfavourably with the many hundreds of names
known to the average speaker of a South Amer¬
ican Indian language.
There is now a growing awareness of "green"
issues, and "green" vocabulary is on the increase.
We have words such as "biodiversity", "recy¬
cling" and "lead-free petrol" but not all of these
terms are equally suitable for environmental dis¬
course. For instance, the word "resource" sug¬
gests that the notion of regeneration is applicable
to both renewable and non-renewable resources
and the very term "environment" suggests a divi¬
sion between humans and what is around them,
an idea that is not widely found in the languages
of the world.
The combined propensity of Western lan¬
guages to emphasize human causativity and con¬
trol and their object-dominated character suggests
that the best course of action is one of estab¬
lishing control over a small bounded area and not,
as other languages would suggest, learning to
understand an undivided whole.
Note also the underdifferentiation between
different types of control in languages such as
English, where the possessive pronoun "my"
can be used to express three situations:
A controls B = my child (A's child)
B controls A = my father (A's father)
A and B reciprocally control one another =
my partner.
In Barrai, a language of Papua New Guinea,
these three categories are clearly distinguished by
different pronominal forms. Interestingly, to
express the notion of "my land" in Barrai, one uses
the pronoun for mutual control suggesting inter¬
dependence, the need for balance and co-operation
between people and the land. Western metaphors
of the land are dominated by the distinction
between human beings and the non-human world,
and the idea that human beings are a privileged
species, the rulers or controllers for whose benefit
the rest of the world was created. Recent
metaphors such as "Spaceship Earth" reinforce the
idea that the Earth exists predominandy for the
benefit of its human inhabitants, and the idea of
environmental management and eco audits is just
another version of the old picture of human beings
as rulers over the rest of creation.
I would suggest that Westerners are trapped
within the limitations imposed on them by their
languages and this is one of the principal rea¬
sons for the lack of genuine progress in the envi¬
ronmental sciences. This example of environ¬
mental discourse illuminates the dangers of
monolingualism and monoculturalism and shows
how many different interpretations and many
different languages are necessary to solve the
problems facing the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
NIGERIA'S CHOICE
by Ayo ßamgbose
^----^^-"dsrS:^^^
12
AYO BAMGBOSE,
formerly Professor of
Ungulstlcs at the University of
Ibadan (Nigeria), has been
involved in linguistic research
and language planning activities
In West Africa for almost 30
years. His publications include
A Grammar of Yoruba
(Cambridge University Press.
1 966), Mother Tongue EducoOon:
The West African Experience
(Hodder & Stoughton/UNESCO,
1 976), and Longuoge and the
Nation (Edinburgh University
Press, 1991).
D
EVELOPING nations, in general, rarely con¬
sider language questions a priority unless
problems arise in connection with the
implementation of controversial language policies.
Nigeria is no exception, and economic problems
are popularly perceived there as being more imme¬
diate and important than language problems.
However, social, economic and political
upheavals since independence have brought lan¬
guage into the spotlight as a crucial factor for
the country's social and political stability. As a
result, questions about language have featured in
the deliberations of two Constituent Assemblies
set up to create new constitutions, in the national
debate over the framework for political gover¬
nance, and in successive constitutions since 1960.
Like most African countries, Nigeria is mul¬
tilingual. There are about 400 languages not
dialects and three of these languages, Hausa,
Igbo and Yomba, are spoken by about half of the
88.5 million population of the country. In addi¬
tion, another 10 per cent of the population is
made up of speakers of other languages who
are nevertheless able to speak at least one of the
major languages as an additional language.
Although Nigerian languages are usually clas¬
sified as either major or minority languages, this
is grossly misleading because next in numbers and
importance to the three major languages are
about ten main languages that serve as the prin¬
cipal languages of some of the states. Such lan¬
guages include Kanuri, Ibibio, Efik, Tw, Ijo, Edo,
Fulfulde, Urhobo, Nupe and Igala. The other
languages should not be dismissed as "minority"
languages, since the combination of all those
who speak them adds up to a substantial pro¬
portion of the population. We may thus con¬
clude that there are three functional types of lan¬
guages in Nigeria: major languages that have a role
at the national level, main languages whose role
is at the state level, and small-group languages that
function mainly at the local level.
Uiversity and divisiveness
The fact that a country has several languages is
often seen as an intrinsic problem. Nigeria, with
its 400 languages, is deeply concerned with the
problems of divisiveness and tribalism, and the
need to achieve national integration. One of the
popular myths in multilingual countries is the
association of a multiplicity of languages with
divisiveness. In spite of the prevalence of this
myth, it is important to stress that it is not mul¬
tilingualism as such that causes divisiveness, but
the exploitation of ethnicity, by linking it with
language differences. In some countries the
myth of divisiveness has been used to oppress
speakers of small-group languages. Fortunately,
this has not happened in Nigeria.
A complementary myth to that of divisive¬
ness is the myth that a single language can unite.
In Nigeria, the English language, which was
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
TO KEEP
NIGERIA ONE
IIS A TASK THAT
MUST BE DON^
.T t .' t '
lÍHIüiltlíJtltMIIIIItilllItlIII HtllMlllliilll'^
,î^7&^ iifcv-j^
the official language in the colonial period, is
widely considered the best candidate for a uni¬
fying role. It is well-entrenched, having been
used as the language of government and educa¬
tion, thereby "uniting" elites from the different
ethnic groups. Furthermore, because it does
not belong to any ethnic group in Nigeria, it is
believed to be a "neutral" language. However, a
common language does not automatically induce
unity unless there are already unity-inducing
factors in the communities concerned, and it is
simply not true that a language can be neutral,
since it inevitably comes with the baggage of the
culture it represents.
Three major questions have dominated
Nigeria's language policy since independence:
What should be the country's official language?
Which ofthe languages should be accorded the
status of a national language? What language
should be used in education?
tingUsh: overwhelmingly dominant
For some, the question of an official language has
been predetermined. Given the colonial heritage
of the use of English for practically all official
purposes in the pre-independence era, the possi¬
bility for change in this practice is almost nil. The
dominance of the English language is truly over¬
whelming. It is the language of government and
administration, including the proceedings in the
National and State Assemblies, the language of
education at almost all levels, the main language of
the media, the language of science and technology,
and the language used by many Nigerian novelists
and poets. Even the debate on the desirability of
change has to be conducted in English!
Attempts to reduce the use of English as an
official language have been singularly unsuc¬
cessful. For example, the 1979 constitution pro¬
vides for the use of the three major languages as 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
additional languages in the National Assembly,
but only subject to adequate arrangements. Such
arrangements include the compilation of leg¬
islative terminology, the training of translators
and interpreters, the installation of simulta¬
neous interpretation facilities and printing equip¬
ment, and hiring personnel for the production
of the Hansard, the official record of the pro¬
ceedings ofthe Assembly. Of all these require¬
ments, only the first one has been completed to
date. Hence, no Nigerian language is used for the
proceedings of the National Assembly.
A much-discussed and recurrent language
question is that of the evolution of a lingua
franca as a national language for the country.
While nationalistic sentiments ensure majority
support for an indigenous national language,
that is where consensus ends. The real problem
is how to decide which of the 400 Nigerian lan¬
guages should be selected for this prestigious
role. Here is where the fear of domination crops
up again, with speakers of smaller languages
fearing that they may be overwhelmed politi¬
cally, economically and linguistically by speakers
ofthe major languages. Even among speakers of
the three major languages, there is no consensus
about which one should become the national
language. In frustration, some Nigerians have
offered solutions ranging from the absurd pro¬
posal to create an artificial language from a com-
14
Left, the market at
Calabar.
Right, election posters on
a wall in a Nigerian town.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
posite of elements of several to the deliberate
adoption of a small-group language in order to
marginalize speakers of larger group languages
and so put most people at an equal disadvantage.
While the difficulties of choosing an indige¬
nous national language have led others to propose
the adoption of a foreign African language such as
Kiswahili from Eastern Africa, or the promotion
of English from official language status to national
language status, the official government policy
has been to encourage the learning of the three
major languages in schools in the hope that one of
them may emerge in the future as an acceptable
national language. This, of course, means that
English, by default, will continue to perform the
functions expected of a national language, even
though it is not called by that name. It is this
unsatisfactory position that has led some other
observers to propose that Nigeria should opt for
three or more national languages in much the
same way as Switzerland operates nationally in
three official languages (German, French, Italian)
and one regional language (Romansh). Although
this may turn out to be very expensive in the
Nigerian context, it is at least a positive way of
resolving an impasse that effectively leaves the
country with English as a national language by
default.
education as the key to change
Changes in language habits are not easy to
enforce, but education provides a good oppor¬
tunity to modify language use. It is for this reason
that much of Nigeria's language policy is predi¬
cated on the educational system. The principles
on which the educational language policy are
based are: equal opportunity of access to the lan¬
guage of education; thorough grounding in the
child's own language; thorough mastery of Eng¬
lish; and bilingualism in two Nigerian languages.
Equality of access to the language of educa¬
tion is promoted by starting primary education
in a child's mother tongue or, failing this, the lan¬
guage of the immediate community. Adult lit¬
eracy is also taught in the local language of the
adult learners. Through this policy, a language
is not ignored simply because it is small. How¬
ever, there are practical constraints. Some lan¬
guages are not yet written languages, and some
have not been studied enough for literacy mate¬
rials to be produced in them. In such cases, edu¬
cation is conducted in the language of the imme¬
diate community. The situation is not static as
more and more languages are being analysed
by linguists and becoming written languages.
A thorough grounding in the child's mother
tongue is supposed to be ensured through an IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
A school class in the town
of Aba, in southern
Nigeria.
16
introduction to reading, writing and arithmetic
in the child's native language, and the use of
this language as a medium of instruction for
the first three years of primary education. Apart
from the constraints mentioned above, which
may militate against the realization of this objec¬
tive, the attitudes of parents and guardians often
run counter to the principle of mother tongue
education. This is because many children from
elite homes are sent to fee-paying schools where
they are taught in English.
Thorough mastery of English is promoted
through the introduction of English in the first
year of primary school and its later adoption as
the medium of instruction for the rest of the
child's education. In spite of the enormous
amount of time devoted to the study of English,
a frequently heard complaint is that the standard
of English in Nigeria is poor. Proof of this inad¬
equacy is the poor performance often recorded
in school certificate as well as university entrance
examinations. The underlying cause of this
problem appears to be the dissociation of mother
tongue teaching from the teaching of English. In
experiments where the two have been related,
significant success has been recorded. The point
is that it is not how long one learns English but
how well.
One drawback of the present practice is that
it assumes that every- primary school teacher
can teach English well. Yet this is not always
true: some primary school teachers have very
poor spoken and written English. An approach
that provides for specialist teachers of English
alongside teachers for other subjects taught in
the mother tongue has been shown to provide
excellent results in terms of mastery of both
English and the mother tongue.
The requirement that every Nigerian child
should leam one of the three major languages in
addition to his or her own language is meant to
facilitate the eventual emergence of a Nigerian
lingua franca. The policy is meant to be enforced
at the secondary school level, subject to avail¬
ability of teachers. Alany schools have sought
refuge in this escape clause and several state gov¬
ernments have not made any effort to produce
teachers for major Nigerian languages. Instead,
soft-option alternatives such as the use of
untrained native speakers to teach only spoken
forms of the language have been adopted, with dis¬
astrous results. There does not seem to be much
enthusiasm for the implementation of this policy,
which may well be connected with ambivalent
attitudes to the national language question.
In Nigeria, there is an acute awareness of
some of the most important language problems.
There are also spirited attempts to tackle them
through the formulation of appropriate lan¬
guage policies. What has been lacking is the will
to implement the policies. This may be due to a
lack of faith in the policies not only on the part
of the people, but also on the part of the policy¬
makers themselves.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO COURIER -FEBRUARY 1994
CM Mffli BE SAVED?
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
Restorers have decided to
leave some Angkor ruins in
the powerful hands of giant
trees. Here, the roots of a
kapok tree grip stonework of
the temple of Ta Prohm.
TV ENEATH the aircraft's wfing at
I I simset, the broad marshy moat
r\ dotted vdth white egrets, the
I I three rectangles ofcovered gal-
1/ leries, the terraces and the five
high, sculpted towers ofAngkor Wat
are all tinged pink. We are privileged
to be flying over the best-known
temple of the unique complex of
monuments that is Angkor in old
Khmer, the name means "the city"
or "the capital". Here, on a plain 200
square kilometres in extent in
north-eastern Cambodia, between
the Kulen plateau and the Tonle Sap
("Great Lake"), a dozen Khmer
rulers of the ninth to the twelfth
centuries built seven capitals con¬
taining many temples. Some are
hidden in the jimgle, where they are
even more inaccessible because of
the presence of the Khmer Rouge,
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
who after holding power from 1975
to 1978 and killing upwards ofa mil¬
lion Ciambodians, took refuge in this
region near the Thai border. The
temples are all that now remains of
the ancient capitals, for only the
gods had the right to stone or brick
buildings. The palaces and dwellings
were built of wood, and they have
since disappeared without trace.
RECONCILINC TOWRISN AND
CONSERVAnON
Nature, not human wrath, has
destroyed these marvellously rich
monuments. The heat and humidity
of the tropical climate encouraged
the unbridled growrth of kapok and
"strangler fig" trees, popularly asso¬
ciated with ruins because their roots
destroy monuments.
Today the principal temples have
been freed ofthe vegetation that held
them in its grip. Only the Ta Prohm
temple has deliberately been left in
the midst of the thickets in which
the French missionary Charles
Bouillevaux and, later, the naturalist
Henri Mouhot foimd it in the mid-
nineteenth centiu^'. Since 1898, the
year in which the French Far Eastem
School (the Ecole Française
d'Extrême-Orient, or EFEO) was
founded, a steady stream ofarchae¬
ologists have worked on the site.
They patiently cleared away the
undergrowth, dismantled and then
reassembled the monuments, and
in 1908 created the "Conservation
d'Angkor" to which the most threat¬
ened statues were taken.
According to Bernard Philippe
Groslier of the EFEO, a former
curator ofthe site, "There is hardly
anything in the world comparable
to the Angkor complex in terms of
the number, size and perfection of
its buildings." But this masterpiece
is in grave danger, and in 1989 the
four main Cambodian political par¬
ties asked Unesco to assume the co¬
ordination of international activi¬
ties for the preservation of the
monimients ofAngkor. In December
1992 Angkor was placed on the
World Heritage List.
In view of the scale of the conser¬
vation problems involved, Unesco's
World Heritage Committee placed
a number ofconditions onAngkor's
inclusion on the List, insisting that a
legal framework for conservation
work and a management plan
should be drawn up, and that an
authority should be established with
the resources to manage the entire
Angkor area. Unesco's first task was
to help the government to set up a
Cambodian Authority for the Pro¬
tection of the National Heritage,
which was formally approved in Feb-
mary 1993. Unesco has also worked
with the Cambodian government
and a group of international experts
on a Zoning and Environmental
Management Plan (ZEMP) for the
authorities, donors and local people
as well as visitors. This comprehen¬
sive document takes into account
Angkor's assets as well as the dangers
threatening the site.
The archaeological treasures are
particularly at risk from lichens,
microscopic algae and bacteria that
proliferate in the guano ofthe many
bats living in the ruins. The ZEMP
also cites the destructive effects of
monsoon rains, the vegetation, and
variations in the underground
aquifer that influence the stability of
the buildings. Other factors include
18
Sculptures
in the
conservation
area of Siem
Reap are
protected by
barbed wire to
prevent theft.
uncontrolled agricultural develop¬
ment after deforestation, the influx
of thousands of tourists and the
construction of hotels to replace
existing facilities that are not up to
international standards. The region
badly needs revenue from tourism,
but there is also a risk that it may
suffer from it. Angkor is a "new"
destination that travel agencies are
now adding to a circuit that includes
Thailand, Laos and Viet Nam.
Statistics show that in 1992 35,000
tourists visited Siem Reap, the base
for excursions to the temples. If
forecasts turn out to be accurate,
between 300,000 and 700,000 for¬
eigners and between 100,000 and
500,000 Cambodians will visit
Angkor in the next five years. The
figures represent a sizeable market,
and fourteen big hotel chains are
already hoping for a share of it.
There is growing concern since two
hotels had been built previously
beside the moat ofAngkor Wat with
litüe regard for the site. (They were
subsequentiy burned down by the
Khmer Rouge). Is it only a matter
of time before there are pleasure
boats, theme parks and neon signs?
To avoid this kind of desecration
while permitting sustainable devel¬
opment of the region, the ZEMP
suggests dividing the site into zones.
The Angkor Parks, comprising five
of the ancient capitals including
Angkor Wat, Angkor Thom and
Preah Khan, would be given max¬
imum protection. They would be
located within an Angkor Cultural
Reserve. On the other hand there
would be no restrictions on new
residents coming to join the 350,000
people already living in the area,
nor on their techniques of farming
or forest management.
A WAT THR0V6H THE
NINEFIELBS
Much remains to be done for the
management of water resources
before Angkor can reclaim the rep¬
utation it once had as a "hydraulic
capital". The prosperity of die early
Angkor empires was closely linked
to irrigation. A network of dykes and
canals served to control flooding
and to provide water in the dry
season from huge reservoirs called
"barays", all ofwhich are now aban¬
doned with the exception of the
Western Baray, which has been
restored in this century. The temple
moats were both sacred boundaries
and sources ofwater and of food in
the form of fish and lotus, whose
fruits contain a mealy substance
from which bread can be made.
Now, however, they have silted up
and are clogged with vegetation.
Other, more immediate dangers
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
also threaten the Angkor region.
There are estimated to be twelve mil¬
lion mines in northern Cambodia.
A French company, COPRAS, which
has trained Cambodian mine dis¬
posal squads, has been attempting to
clear the eight minefields identified
atAngkor. Three hundred and sixty
mines have already been removed.
The only way one can reach the
temple of Ta Nei and the eastern
entrance to Angkor Thom ^the so-
called Gate of Death is by following
a mine disposal squad. Countless
people adults and children have
been killed by the mines or have lost
limbs. In addition, armed and
trained Khmer Rouges are operating
in the vicinity, terrorizing the local
population by sporadic raiding.
In these circumstances, it is very
difficult to prevent the looting of
sculptures that every year causes the
sanctuaries to deteriorate further.
The thieves prize loose with chisels
the wonderM faces ofthe heavenly
dancers known as apsaras, cut the
heads offstatues, and in some cases
remove the statues wholesale, even
those weighing more than a ton. The
protests of the Cambodian govern¬
ment, of Unesco and ofthe Interna¬
tional CouncU of Museums (ICOM)
have no effect on the traffickers, who
know where they can get vast sums
ofmoney for the statues.
The task of co-ordinating inter¬
national aid that the Cambodian
government has entrusted to Unesco
is a difficult one. Only one archaeo¬
logical excavation is currenüy under
way, and that is the EFEO's investi¬
gation of the Terrace of the Leper
King. Without co-ordination and
political determination to protect
the site, Angkor could well fall into
the hands of unscrupulous busi¬
nessmen seeking quick profits from
the curiosity of tourists and the
poverty ofthe local population.
Angkor has a special place in
the memory of humanity. Let us
hope that the international com¬
munity wUl wake up to the fact soon
enough to take the urgent action
that is needed to save, protect and
rationally develop this irreplace¬
able treasure.
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD- Unesco
training programmefor African
news-agency journalists.
Aerial view of the temple of Angkor
Wat, masterwork of Khmer architecture
(early 1 2th century).
A traditional technique is used to
extract sap by fire. The sap is used as a
fuel for lighting or for caulking boats.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
WORLD
THE DANGERS OF MINERAL DUST
According to World Health Organization (WHO)
experts, the health of millions of workers around
the world involved in the extraction, refining and
use of minerals may be at risk. People who are
exposed to mineral dust over many years inhale par¬
ticles which stay in their lungs, where they can cause
serious illnesses such as the pneumoconioses (e.g.
silicosis and asbestosis), bronchitis, emphysema
and lung cancer. The degree of risk is related to the
duration of exposure. In Zimbabwe, 20 per cent of
workers were found to suffer from silicosis after 20
years or more of exposure in gold, copper and
chrome mines. In India, silicosis rates were higher
than 50 per cent among slate pencil workers, 35 per
cent among stonecutters and 30 per cent among
lead and zinc miners. WHO recommends closer
medical surveillance ofworkers, which is not always
easy to implement in poor countries. Perhaps a good
first step would be to take a hard look at mining
methods.
CARTOONS AGAINST
LOCUSTS
Boukari is a small farmer in the
Sahel. Tired of standing by help¬
lessly while his crops are
destroyed by clouds of locusts, he
takes a course that teaches him
how chemicals can be used to
fight these devastating insects.
When he has learned how to use
the insecticides, he returns to his
village and shares his knowledge
with the community. This story is
told in an unusual full-colour strip
cartoon book published for
France's Centre de Coopération
Internationale en Recherche
Agronomique pour le Déve¬
loppement (GIRAD), and aimed
at the countries in the Sahel and
on the coast ofthe Gulfof Guinea.
Fifty thousand copies have been
printed. There is no charge for the
book, which is published in
French. For further information,
please contact CIRAD/PRIFAS, BP
5035, 34032 Montpellier cedex 1,
France.
INTRODUCTION
TO THE
ENVIRONMENT
Unesco has contributed photo¬
graphic material to Manuel d'ini¬
tiation à l'environnement {"A First
Environmental Reader"), a new
book that presents major eviron-
mental issues to non-specialist
MANUEL
D'INITIATION
AÜÉNVIRONNEMT
FMWÇmS CAZAUS
readers. The book gives a plane¬
tary overview of environmental
problems followed by a series of
fact sheets on a range of subjects
including nuclear energy, biodi¬
versity, acid rain and the green¬
house effect. It also features a
multiple-choice quiz. Written by
François Cázalas, Manuel d'initi¬
ation à I'environnment is pub¬
lished by Les Editions de l'Envi¬
ronnement, Paris.
THREATS
TO MARINE LIFE
Two centuries ago a marine
mammal weighing up to 10 tons
known as the Steller's sea cow lived
peacefully in the icy waters of the
North Pacific. It took just 27 years
of harpooning to make this harm¬
less, edible species extinct. A new
study entitled Global Marine Bio¬
logical Diversity, published by the
Center for Marine Conservation
in Washington, D.C. (U.S.A.),
shows that the sea creatures of
today are increasingly endangered
and calls for action to protect the
whole chain of global marine life.
Pollution and overexploitation of
marine flora and fauna are respon¬
sible for the most visible damage,
but other factors also play a part
such as trawling and coastal con¬
struction, the introduction ofalien
species, and the addition to the
atmosphere of substances that
increase ultra-violet radiation and
cause climate change. Global
Marine Biological Diversity, A
Strategyfor Building Conservation
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
into Decision Making is partly
funded by the World Bank and
includes contributions from more
than 100 authors from 40 different
countries. It can be obtained from
the Center for Marine Conserva¬
tion, 1725 DeSales Stteet NW, Suite
500, Washington D.C. 20036, U.SA
(price $27.50).
BHUTAN'S LUCKY CRANES
Ever since the day in 1600 when a
Buddhist monk spotted two
black-necked cranes near a site
at lakar where a monastery was
being built, these birds have been
considered sacred in Bhutein. The
cranes, which arrive from Tibet
in October and stay till March, are
treated with reverence by the
inhabitants of the valleys where
they feed. But the tourists who
flock to see them often go too
close to their roosting places and
dazzle them with flashlights or
torches. Local people advise the
visitors not to disturb the birds,
and their efforts seem to be paying
off: 175 cranes were spotted last
year in the Phobjekha Valley, as
opposed to 139 in 1992.
A SANCTUARY FOR
WHALES?
At the 45th meeting of the Inter¬
national Whaling Commission in
Kyoto last year, Dominica,
Grenada, lapan, the Republic of
Korea, Norway, St. Lucia, St. Vin¬
cent and the Grenadines, and the
Solomon Islands voted against
continuing the international
moratorium on commercial
whaling. Norway subsequently
gave notice of its intention to kill
296 minke whales for scientific
purposes. (The North EastAflantic
mitike population is estimated to
be aroimd 80,000). There are hopes
that a proposal to establish a
Southern Ocean Whale Sanctuary
in the Antarctic will be adopted
prior to this year's IWC meeting in
Mexico. Meanwhile, the whale sit¬
uation remains critical.
An outdoor
green turtle
(Chelortia mydas)
hatchery on the
coast of
Pakistan near
Karachi.
Tuareg nomads
drawing water
from a well in
the Aïr massif
(Niger).
THE World Conservation Union
(lUCN) has its headquarters in
a light, airy building set amid
maize-fields near the shores of
Lake Geneva in Switzerland.
This influential body, set up jointiy
by Unesco and France in 1948,
brings together 62 sovereign states,
99 government agencies and 575
non-governmental organizations,
and is backed by the work of 6,000
specialist volunteers worldwide. It
spelled out its programme in Caring
for the Earth, prepared in partner¬
ship with the United Nations Envi¬
ronment Programme (UNEP) and
the World Wide Fund for Nature
(WWF) in 1 99 1 . This document out¬
lines a sttategy that, if implemented,
would bring our lifestyles and devel¬
opment paths within the limits of
what nature can sustain. But the
task is immense: "In less than 200
years the planet has lost six million
square küometres of forest. . .; water
withdrawals have grown from 100 to
3,600 cubic kilometres a year. . . .
Since the mid-eighteenth century,
human activities have more than
doubled the methane in the atmos¬
phere; increased the concentration
of carbon dioxide by 27 per cent;
and significantly damaged the
stratospheric ozone layer."
Confronted wdth this situation,
lUCN has prepared, in co-operation
with governments, national conser¬
vation strategies for some 50 coim-
tries. It is increasingly decentralizing
its operations in order to improve
efficiency: more than two-thirds of
lUCN's secretariat is now based in
regional and country offices around
the world. The regional emphasis
also helps to get local people more
involved the onlyway to reconcile
environmental protection and sus¬
tainable development. lUCN's pri¬
orities are saving species, main¬
taining biodiversity, managing
habitats and preserving wetiands,
national parks and protected areas.
In Congo, for instance, lUCN is
helping to plan the management of \
the Conkouati Faima Reserve and of ;
the immense wetiand forest of Lac
Télé. In Costa Rica, where the last
lowland tropical rainforest on the
Atlantic coast is being destroyed at
a rate of 8 per cent a year all round
the relatively small Tortuguero
national park, lUCN has worked
with the government and the Euro¬
pean Commission to persuade the
main local landowner to reduce the
spraying ofpesticides on his banana
plantation and to stop expanding
the plantation into the forest.
One of the biggest lUCN country
programmes is in Pakistan, where a
National Conservation Strategy was
adopted in March 1992. The policy
changes it advocates are being car¬
ried forward in the 8th Five Year Plan,
which has a section on the environ¬
ment for the first time. Since 1987,
lUCN has also been carrying out a
major programme in Africa's Sahel
region, where it is helping the gov¬
ernments ofBurkina Faso, Mali, Mau¬
ritania, Niger, Senegal and Chad to
prepare national conservation strate¬
gies and plans for the management of
wetlands, forests, semi-arid grass¬
lands and protected areas. The plans
stress the importance oferdisting the
support of local residents.
lUCN makes its experience avail¬
able not only to states but to non¬
governmental organizations, asso¬
ciations and individuals. It produces
a steady flow of documents, books,
brochures and bulletins, many of
them in several languages. For fur¬
ther information, contact the Infor¬
mation Office of lUCN at 28 rue
Mauvemey, CH-1196 Gland, Switzer¬
land (Tel: 41 22 999 00 01; fax: 41 22
999 0002.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
'language death in SIBERIA
- by Vladimir Belikov
"yf*e world's longuage. today face e*c^V,n.
WHILE cultural change in many parts of
the world is usually spontaneous, in
Russia it has been the direct result of
decisions made by the Communist Party.
Shortly after the communist revolution, a policy
of "cultural engineering" was announced, with
the aim of developing different national cul¬
tures, languages and traditions in order to build
a new type of culture that would be "national in
its form and communist in its content".
Some of the early achievements of this policy
were actually very impressive. A tiny village in
the Poltava district ofUkraine, populated mainly
by Swedes, used Swedish as the official lan¬
guage of the local administration; the first (and
perhaps the only) school primer in the Gypsy
language was published; the state financed peri¬
odicals in the native languages of small com¬
munities of Estonian and Latvian immigrants in
Siberia. Indeed, for a time, "the blossoming of
national cultures", became a common phrase
in official communist propaganda.
{cultural assimilation
Unfortunately, by the mid-1930s the blossoms
had begun to fade. The authorities had discov¬
ered that their policy did not accelerate the
development of communism and sometimes
even hindered it. Although it was never publicly
announced, a policy of cultural assimilation for
minority groups began to be encouraged.
In many parts of the country, especially
those traditionally influenced by the Russian
Orthodox Church, the cultural differences
between rural people of different ethnic origins
were not great, and the ethnic identities of var¬
ious minority groups were not very pronounced.
In these regions, acculturation was a slow but
steady process, and as the years went by lin¬
guistic and cultural boundaries disappeared.
For example, Russians had lived for cen-
J\ team of reindeer in the
Kamchatka peninsula.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
turies among the Komi, a Finno-Ugric people
who formed the majority of the local population
on the banks of the lower Pechora river in the
north of European Russia. Over time, the
number of Russians living in the area grew and
so did the influence of their language, until
Russian came to be used in the school system
and all the local Komi became bilingual.
Many years ago, I met a Komi fisherman
who told me a story which ended with a quite
extraordinary sentence. Although the speaker
didn't realize it, all the roots and auxiliary words
he used were Russian, though the grammar was
still Komi. It went something like this: Takeoff-
tim ring-ie and ñndout-tim that duck-js spend-
winter-íowíí France-;)'«. (In this anghcization
the Komi suffixes have been left as they were
used by my informant.)
I have not been in this part of Russia for
twenty-five years and do not know for sure
whether this dialect is still in use, but even if it
is, it has been so strongly influenced by Russian
that it is no longer an effective tool for main¬
taining Komi culture. This linguistic mixture
has no chance of competing with Russian even
as a basic means of communication, especially
since thousands of newcomers came to the
region in the 1970s to work in the oilfields and
many of the Komi fisherman became industrial
workers.
This story illustrates a typical process of lin¬
guistic change within the acculturation process.
However, it is not the only possible result of
cross-cultural contact. If two ethnic groups
come into sudden contact and a marked gap
exists between them, it is very likely that one of
the cultures will die quickly, especially if it is gen¬
erally perceived to have less prestige than the
other. Deculturation may have tragic conse¬
quences for the weaker ethnic group. It usu¬
ally leads to widespread distress within the com¬
munity, high crime rates, mass alcoholism,
declining life expectancy. A culturally unique
human group may even become extinct. This
threat now hangs over many small ethnic
minorities that are scattered in the depths of
the Siberian taiga forests and Arctic tundra of the
Far North. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
¡he threat of cultural extinction
In the late sixteenth and the seventeenth centuries,
the Russians took over the area known as Siberia
^vithout much fighting. They did not e\'en consider
the area to be foreign territorj'. For centuries
Russia had no eastem border and Russian pioneers
simply moved further and further eastward. Most
of them settled permanently on a narrow strip of
land in southern Siberia, where cultivation was
possible, and the few who settled further north
often lost their Russian language.
The local societies were highly stable until
the 1930s, when the importance of the timber
and mineral resources in the Far North was
realized. They had no special educational insti¬
tutions, but from early childhood girls learned
female skills from their mothers, and young
boys learned male roles from their fathers and
older brothers. The authority of grandparents
was undisputed and any serious problem
curing the sick, locating hidden things, sending
a dead soul to the upper world was solved
with the help of a shaman. (The word shaman
comes from theTungus language.)
The situation began to change in 1924 with
the formation of the Committee for Assisting
the Peoples ofthe Far North. This committee led
to the creation of administrative offices to help
different ethnic groups change their ways from
traditional to communist "in one step, during
the life of one generation".
The first Russian teachers came to remote
Siberian areas in the late 1920s. At that time, text¬
books for primary schools were written in at
least thirteen of the languages of the North, but
their content was the same: biographies of Lenin
and Stalin, the crimes of the predatory czarist
regime, the deeds of the heroes of the revolu¬
tion, the achievements of industrialization and
collectivization.
The books for Siberian minorities also had a
section dealing with local affairs. The essence of
it was that old people lack any true knowledge,
all their habits are wrong, traditional culture is
a silly jumble of ignorance and prejudices, and
shamans are servants of the counter-revolution
who deceive people to achieve their ignoble
goals and stop the development of communism.
Komnata
ausikci
tatusikci
jlUMKCl. JatuMKcl.
gagBini.
digasikci
guasikci
ÍDlgaMKCl. ITtlOAiHCl.
îa »,
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Right, a Komi story-teller.
Left, illustrations from a
primer in the Udihe
language showing boarding
school life. The book was
burned by the authorities
in 1938.
In those days, no-one even considered
whether or not communist concepts made sense
for traditional societies of hunters and gatherers.
It was assumed that collectivization and indus¬
trialization would form the economic foundation
of their new cultures, and traditional land tenure
and social organization were declared reactionary.
Thus people were deprived of their lands and
rivers, the very foundations of their life.
An enemy ofthe people
while traditional cultures were ruined, native
languages were sometimes still used, especially
in schools for a time. However, in 1938,
Eugene Schneider, the author and translator of
the first books in the Udihe language, was
denounced as "an enemy ofthe people", arrested
and shot. One of my informants remembers
how KGB agents came to his village, gathered all
the books from families and the school library
and took them into a courtyard, where they
were set on fire. The bonfire burned through the
night and in the morning my informant, who
was a young boy at the time, managed to steal a
half-burnt favourite book of folklore. The
written language of Udihe was banned.
For many other languages, misfortune
arrived soon afterwards as a result of a new
policy whereby children were sent away from
their families to study in boarding schools. At
first, the boarding schools were intended for
children from semi-nomadic groups in which
families were scattered across large stretches of
territory because they were shepherding Arctic 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
»'à -r f r .7 r
î;-;.».».t
V r* H ^ BB^ _:_T« ï » ff a
:5 ! ! »
R
	 It
hEït
A camp of Komi reindeer
farmers in the tundra
(above left).
/\ residential quarter in
Syktyvkar, capital of the
Komi Republic (above
right).
VLADIMIR BELIKOV
is the senior research fellow of
the Pacific Department at the
Institute of Oriental Studies of
the Russian Academy of
Sciences. Since 1989 he has
been working on a series of
textbool<s on the ethnic
language of the Udihe minority
of the Russian Far East
reindeer or hunting wild animals. But soon the
boarding schools were established even in large
villages and children were only allowed to spend
time with their relatives on Sundays.
Gradually, the only language of instruction
became Russian. Sometimes children were for¬
bidden to speak their mother tongue in the school
building. Parents did not protest, and even if
they had protested it might not have made much
difference because their children considered them
archaic because ties between the generations had
been broken. Even folk-tales, which were central
to traditional cultures, were lost.
Meanwhile, Russians became more numerous
in the remote parts of Siberia, and more influen¬
tial in local administration. Neither they nor the
Russian communist elite paid any attention to the
traditions and real needs of the people. Then, in
1957, the death sentence was imposed on many
Siberian languages by a Communist Party reso¬
lution, "On the Measures for Further Economic
and Cultural Development of the Peoples of the
North."
f\n irreversible process
A key measure within the resolution called for
combining the settlements of ethnic minorities
and transferring them, which meant closing
schools, shops and medical posts in small, old vil¬
lages and forcibly relocating Siberian minorities.
With this measure, people were deprived of their
traditional hunting and fishing grounds and scat¬
tered among large numbers of newcomers. As a
result, even those groups that used to have offi¬
cial territorial autonomy became small minorities
in the new settlements. The history of the ethnic
composition of the Chukchi Autonomous
Region serves as an example. Between 1926 and
1989, the total population of the region increased
elevenfold, from 15 thousand to 164 thousand. In
the same period, the Chukchi component sank
from 79 per cent to 2.4 per cent, while the per¬
centage of Russian and other newcomers rose
from 2 per cent to 95.3 per cent.
These days, the degree of knowledge of an
ethnic language depends on general ethno-
ecology in the region in which it is used; the
written status of ethnic languages isn't changing
very much. Extreme examples of this are pro¬
vided by the modern position of two Siberian
languages, Oroks and Nganasan, neither of
which have been used in schools or in print.
The homeland of the Oroks people lies on
the mainland opposite the island of Sakhalin. It
was heavily invaded by Russians in the 1930s,
when railroads, new towns and seaports were
built. In the new surroundings there was no
place for traditional culture and no reason for
young people to acquire any language except
Russian. As a result, by 1989 only 15 per cent of
the Oroks people had any knowledge of their
ethnic language at all.
On the other hand, the Nganasans, who
wander with their reindeer on the Taymyr penin¬
sula, managed until recently to preserve many of
their traditional habits and cultures. Their land is
characterized by an extremely severe Arctic cli¬
mate and has attracted hardly any immigrants.
Even the system of boarding schools didn't affect
them until the 1960s. The 1989 survey found
that 90 per cent of the population still had some
knowledge of their language.
In recent years, perestroika has prompted the
renewal of ethnic nationalism among many
groups in the former U.S.S.R., but not among
Siberian minorities. In the last few decades, tal¬
ented Siberian youths have been drawn to Russian
culture and left their villages. Some of them have
good jobs in the cities while others have come
back to the Far North as teachers and physi¬
cians. But they have lost their ethnic identity.
Efforts to revive local languages and cul¬
tures in Siberia are now doomed to failure.
People are ashamed to speak their ethnic lan¬
guages or to distinguish themselves from Rus¬
sians. Many consider Russians the best mar¬
riage partners. "Our children will be more
beautiful," they explain, "and more happy."
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
L..
THE CHICKEN AND THE BANANA
SOME ofthe world's most unusual languages
are spoken in the Santa Cruz Islands, a vol¬
canic archipelago located between the
Solomon Islands and the islands of Vanuatu (for¬
merly the New Hebrides) in the southwestern
Pacific. The languages, which belong to a small,
interrelated group, are spoken by a population
numbering about 5,000. They are remarkable for
the ways in which they subdivide and minutely cat¬
egorize the world into sets or classes some forty
of them in all, each indicated by a special prefix.
Some of these classes of words reflect complex
ways of thinking. In one of the languages, Ayiwo,
for example, the basic meaning of the v/orApaa
is "sliver", but it never occurs without a class
prefix. It may be combined with nyi-, the pointed
objects class prefix, to make nyi-paa, which means
"a chip", or, literally, "a pointed sliver". With
the prefix no-, which refers to indistinctly sepa¬
rated parts of a whole, it becomes no-paa, which
means "pieces of bark peeling off a tree trunk", or,
literally, "slivers indistinctly separated and still
attached to the thing to which they belong and of
which they form a part". When preceded by
nyo-, the class prefix for moving away into the
distance, it makes nyo-paa, which means "type of
arrow" or, more exactly, "sliver-type object that
moves away into the distance". With te-, the
class prefix for something foreign, particularly of
Polynesian provenance, it becomes te-paa,
meaning "a nail", literally a "sliver of foreign
metal, probably of Polynesian origin".
Another such word is -modyi, which means
"concept of the right hand and strength". It also
only occurs with prefixes of this kind, so that
when combined with lo-, the class prefix for
acquisition through labour and effort, it makes lo-
modyi, which means "small adze", literally
"something used for acquiring something else
through labour and effort by one's strong right
hand". Combined with mo-, the class prefix for
extending far, it becomes mo-modyi, meaning a
"small outrigger canoe", or, in the literal transla¬
tion, "something that goes far when using one's
strong right hand for paddling". And with oyä-,
the mangrove class prefix, oyä-modyi means "a
type of mangrove with very strong wood".
Another feature of this language is that many
of its nouns are descriptions based on verbs, with
a class prefix added. The verb va, for instance,
means "to be immature". When class prefixes
are added to it, the following words emerge. The
addition of the masculine human class prefix, gi-,
produces gi-va meaning "male baby". The addi¬
tion oí si-, the feminine human class prefix, pro¬
duces si-va meaning "female baby". Me-va means
"human babies" {me being the collective human
class prefix). Pi-va means "adolescent" (pi being
the prefix for the half-developed human class).
Va-, is the prefix for the chicken class so that
vä-va means "small chicken". And since h- is
the banana class prefix, u-va means "small, unde¬
veloped banana".
While such multiple class systems, though
with fewer classes, occur in other parts of the
world, the Santa Cruz Island languages add
another highly complicated, quite different class
system to indicate possession, with the object
possessed determining which of the numerous
possessive classes should appear in any given
case. For instance, if someone wants to say that
a chicken belongs to them, the word indicating
"my" would be different depending on whether
the chicken was thought of as food or as a pet.
What's more, the chicken class prefix would
also have to be added to the "my" word chosen.
Verbs are also put into classes indicated by
prefixes, according to whether the action
referred to is carried out using one's hand, a
tool, or a knife. For example, vä-gäte means
"to tear apart by hand", while tä-gäte means "to
tear apart with a tool" and lä-gäte means "to slit
with a knife". Other prefixes indicate other
activities carried out by exerting energy, or con¬
stituting a single violent action, etc.
There is also a system that uses verbs to pre¬
cisely indicate the location of an action in rela¬
tion to the speaker (i.e. near, at some distance,
behind, near the person addressed, or not close
to either the speaker or the person addressed,
etc.); the general direction of the speaker or the
person addressed (upwards or downwards); and
the direction ofthe action (towards the speaker,
or the person addressed, or a third person).
Vä-va (a small chicken) and
u-va (small bananas).
Elgeklrt
This text was compiled by
Stephen Wurm from
information supplied by
speakers of the languages of
the Santa Cruz Islands,
especially Patrick Bwakolo,
John Mealue and Ini Lapli. 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
For Chinese immigrants in Australia, overcoming cultural differences
can be ¡ust as nerve-wracking as learning a new language
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
OF GIFTS AND GAFFEj
byjia Tian "
A Chinese woman who has lived in Aus¬
tralia for more than twenty years recendy
told me the following storj'. Shortly after
she arrived in the country, already speaking
fluent English, she had a birthday and an Aus¬
tralian friend invited her over for dinner to cel¬
ebrate. When she turned up at the house, she was
presented with a gift wrapped in beautiful paper.
She thanked her friend profusely and put the
parcel away. Puzzled by her response, the Aus¬
tralian asked, "Don't you want to open it?"
The Chinese woman replied, "Oh, no, no! I
don't want to open it now! Certainly not!" It
was not unül much later that she realized that she
had unwittingly made a "cultural mistake".
While it is generally considered common cour¬
tesy in Chinese culture not to open gifts imme¬
diately in front of the giver, Anglo-Australian
culture takes the opposite point of view.
It is often said that one of the biggest chal¬
lenges for people who have emigrated to a new
country is learning a new language, and it is
true that many Asian immigrants to Australia
find it difficult to learn English. However, even
when they speak the language excellently, they
can still find themselves making social blunders
because of their lack of knowledge of different
cultural values and customs.
Language and ritual
Immigrants may encounter a variety of diffi¬
culties if they are not aware of these cultural dif¬
ferences. When two people brought up in the
Chinese culture meet in the street, they often ask:
"Where are you going?" {nishang narqua?") or
"Have you had your meal?" {"ni chi fan le
ma?'). Greetings such as these may be regarded
by people from English-speaking backgrounds
as intrusive, irritating and rather odd, because
respect for an individual's privacy is a widely-
accepted cultural concept in most English-
speaking countries.
Typical ways of greeting people in Australia
include "How are you?" and "How are you
doing?". Although phrased as questions
showing concern for the addressee's well-being,
they are actually not meant to be taken literally.
Left, street scene in Broome,
Western Australia.
Kight, welcome to Sydney's
Chinatown.
They are examples of the ritual phrases of
greeting which are a salient feature of most lan¬
guages. In general, speakers would expect a
ritual answer such as "Fine" or "Not bad", even
though the addressee may not actually feel well.
Many Chinese immigrants find it hard to
understand why their Anglo-Australian friends
and colleagues expect them to give a positive
reply to such questions instead of a truthful
one. Some have asked me, "If they don't really
want to know how I feel, then why ask me all
these questions? It's pure hypocrisy!" It may
take years before they realize that they are
making assumptions based on Chinese cultural
norms and codes of behaviour.
Sometimes an Anglo-Australian might greet
someone by saying: "Hello! You're looking
smart today!" Here the speaker may not be
referring to the addressee's dress sense but be
asking a tactful question such as: "Would you
please tell me whom you are going to see/where
you are going?" To which the response might be:
"Oh, I have to see my boss today" or "We're
having a party tonight."
In many Asian cultures, when friends or
acquaintances run into each other in the street,
they stop and exchange greetings, which are
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
followed by short or lengthy conversations,
depending on the closeness of their friendship.
It is considered rude to simply say "Hello",
and keep walking. Even if one of the parties
has urgent business, he or she is still expected to
stop and answer questions politely.
In Australia, however, where people are
more casual, it is quite acceptable for someone
to say, "Sorr)', mate, I have to hurry" or simply
"Hello!" and keep on walking. Chinese immi¬
grants who do not understand Australian casu-
alness and informality interpret such behaviour
as abrupt and unfriendly.
Eat! Eatl Eatl
Chinese immigrants often feel confused on social
occasions. The following scenario is typical. A
Chinese immigrant couple invite their Aus¬
tralian friends to dinner at their home. When the
Australian guests arrive, their host and hostess
point to the sofa and say, "Please! Mn and Mrs.
Smith. Sit! Sit! Sit!" Somewhat startled, the
Australian guests sit down without saying any¬
thing. After a few drinks, the guests are asked to
take their places at the dinner table. The hostess
brings food to the table and the host, pointing at
the food with his chopsticks, urges his guests
with great enthusiasm, "Please! Mr. and Mrs.
Smith. Eat! Eat! Eat!"
The guests, knowing little about Chinese
culture, appear ill at ease. The hosts, on the
other hand, repeat, "Please! Don't just sit there!
Eat! Eat! Eat!" Now the Australian guests look
even more uneasy, thinking to themselves that
their hosts' manners are rather odd. In the mean¬
time, the hosts are increasingly bewildered by
their guests' reticence. They do not realize that
they have just made a "cultural mistake".
Whereas in Australia, hosts often show their
hospitality by using phrases such as "Would you
like to sit down?" or "Please make yourself at
home", their Chinese equivalents say, "Zuo! Zuo!
Zuo!" and " Chi! Chi! Chi!" which literally means,
"Sit! Sit! Sit!" and "Eat! Eat! Eat!" The repetition
of the words "sit" and "eat" is an attempt to create
an informal, hospitable atmosphere.
What the immigrant host and hostess failed
to understand was that "Sit! Sit! Sit!" and "Eat!
Eat! Eat!" are imperatives that in English are
usually reserved for commands for young chil¬
dren and pet dogs. Because they transplanted
their original cultural scripts to the Australian
setting, they achieved the opposite of what they
had hoped for: they made their guests nervous
and uncomfortable.
N.lever say no
In many Asian cultures, gift-giving involves
reciprocity and mutual obligations. In the Chi¬
nese culture, for example, when someone is
given a gift, he or she is expected to give some¬
thing back of equal value. To do otherwise is a
breach of etiquette.
This give-and-take is an important aspect
of Chinese culture. It promotes friendship, cre¬
ates harmony and strengthens bonds among
family members, relatives, friends and col¬
leagues. Yet in the Anglo-Australian culture,
gift-giving is seen merely as a way of saying
thank-you or showing appreciation. Often the
recipient is under no obligation to give a present
in return. Instead, he or she might offer to do
something useful for the giver such as helping
them move house or looking after their pets
while they are on holiday. Because of these dif¬
ferences, many Chinese immigrants feel hurt
when their Anglo-Australian colleagues or
friends accept gifts with a mere thank-you .
'¡>< : . ':>!*:
Above, students at the
University of Sydney.
Left, in Sydney,
Australians of Chinese and
non-Chinese origin
perform a Chinese dragon
dance during the
celebration of Chun ¡ie, the
Spring Festival.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Declining and accepting invitations also
cause problems. In the Chinese culture, people
usually abide by the principle of reciprocity
when they receive a dinner invitation. In other
words, they are expected to return the hospi¬
tality soon afterwards. Under normal circum¬
stances, those invited try to attend the dinner, but
if they have other commitments or do not like
the host, they decline the invitation with an
excuse. The excuses are often "white lies", but
the host accepts them because he or she under¬
stands that they are a way of turning down an
invitation in a diplomatic, indirect and most
important of all, culturally acceptable way.
This is perhaps the area in which many Chi¬
nese immigrants in Australia experience the
greatest "culture shock". An important con¬
cept in the Chinese culture is "saving face" {gei
mian zi), which may be translated, depending on
the circumstances, as preserving someone's pride
or ego, respecting the dignity of others, not
hurting somebody's feelings or not putting
another person in an embarrassing position.
When declining an invitation, people from the
Chinese culture try their best to "save face" for
the other party by not using the word "no",
which is considered offensive.
Because of this, some Chinese immigrants
feel deeply offended by Australians who decline
invitadons in a straightforward way: "Sorry mate,
I can't come tonight. I have to fix my lawn-
mower." Such a reply is often interpreted by
Chinese immigrants as unpleasant or downright
rude. The misunderstandings here are not really
caused by the words but by the casual manner of
Anglo-Australians, which differs considerably
from the greater formality of the Chinese.
Language is a reflection of culture. It is just
as important for migrants to learn to under¬
stand a new culture as it is to master a new lan¬
guage. At present, the resources of language
teaching for migrants tend to be too narrowly
focused. Only when the dynamic relationship
between language and culture is fully under¬
stood can a language be learned properly and
used appropriately.
JIA TIAN
is an Australian journalist who
has published many essays,
reviews and features on the
arts, theatre and films in
various Chinese- and English-
language newspapers,
magazines and journals. She Is
currently preparing a study on
Asian immigrants in Australia
at the Australian National
University. 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
pi III HI I lyMIMILilBMIMiafciM^átiJ
ENEMY ON DISKEUE
The 3rd edition ofthe Unesco
International Directory of New and
Renewable Energy Information
Sources and Research Centres has
just been published by James &
James Science Publishers, London.
The volume, which contains 3,864
entries, is the printed version of
the ENERGY database, also
available on diskettes and CD-
ROM, which provides information
on governmental organizations,
research and information centres,
professional and trade associations,
networks, training and education
institutions, databanks, journals
and reference publications in 1 72
countries. Further information on
the database may be obtained
from: the Engineering and
Technology Division, Unesco, I,
rue Miollis, 7S732 Pans Cedex IS,
France. Tel: (33-1) 45 68 39 41;
fax: (33-1) 40 65 95 35.
EINSTEIN ON THE BEACH
The 1993 Unesco Einstein Gold
Medal, struck in 1979 to
commemorate the 1 00th
anniversary of the birth of the
great scientist, has been presented
by the Director-General to
Australia's Great Barrier Reef
Marine Park Authority. The award
recognizes the Authority's
outstanding contribution to the
conservation of World Heritage
and the advancement of
environmental education.
AWARDS FOR SAVINC THE SEAS
March 1st 1994 is the deadline for
the receipt of applications for the
International Marine Environment
Award established by the World
Underwater Federation (CMAS) to
honour a person, organization or
company whose work has made a
major contribution to the
protection of the marine
environment CMAS, which was
founded in 1959 by the French
underwater explorer Jacques-Yves
Cousteau, seeks to develop
underwater activities in fields
including sport, science, education
and archaeology. It currently has a
membership of several million
people from more than 80
countries. The prize, together with
the Prince Tomohito Mikasa
International Marine Award, will be
presented at a ceremony to be
held at Unesco's Paris
Headquarters in September.
Application forms are available
from Marine Awards, CMAS, Viale
Tiziano, 74-00 1 96 Rome, Italy.
OPEN DOORS AT UNESCO
Free guided tours of Unesco
Headquarters, including lectures
and filmshows, are available on
request during weekdays. Both
individual visitors and groups are
welcome. For further information,
please contact Visitors' Service, 7
place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07
SP (tel: 45 68 03 71). The nearest
Metro stations are Segur or
Cambronne.
UNESCO ISSUES 1 NEW MEDALS
What do the following have in
common: the Old Town of
Dubrovnik; the Jesuit Guaraní
republic; Pablo Picasso; Jawaharlal
Nehru; and the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights? The
answer is that they have all
featured on Unesco
commemorative medals. Since
1 974 Unesco has issued two medal
series, one illustrating threatened
monuments and sites, the other
devoted to anniversaries of
eminent people or historic events.
The most recent additions
celebrated respectively the 1 00th
anniversary of the birth of the
Catalan painter Joan Miró and the
inclusion of the city of Potosí
(Bolivia) on the World Heritage
List By purchasing the medals,
which are struck at the Paris Mint
in vermeil, silver and bronze,
people can contribute to Unesco's
efforts to preserve the cultural
heritage and to promote
understanding between peoples.
The medals may be obtained from
UNESCO's Philatelic and
Numismatic Service, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
CORRECTION
We apologise for an error in the
short article on the monuments of
Pagan (Myanmar) that appeared on
page 72 of the July-August 1993
issue of the Courier. In the second
paragraph, "the temple of Ananda"
should have read "the temple of
Nanpaya".
COHHENTABY
by
Federico
Mayor
This article is one
of aseries in wliicli
the Director-General of
Unesco sets out his
thinking on nnatters of
current concern
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
THE SPIRIT PF GRANADA
UNESCO is proud to have organized last December in
Granada (Spain), an international symposium at which
Israeli, Arab and European intellectuals met to discuss
the intellectual aspects of the Israeli-Palestinian reconciliation
process.
Among all the geopolitical, ideological and strategic changes
that mark the tumultuous closing years of this century, it is
inspiring to see the desire for reconciliation expressed by two
parties who have long been embroiled in conflicts so absolute
and so deep-rooted that many had given up all hope. At the
beginning of the 1 980s, anyone who had predicted such devel¬
opments as the ending of the Cold War, the dismantling of
apartheid in South Africa, or Israeli-Palestinian dialogue would
have been greeted with derision.
The process that has brought Israelis and Palestinians to the
negotiating table is also of enormous, and universal, moral
significance.
TRAMSFORMIMC DESTINY
A tribute is due to the architects of this reconciliation, those
responsible for the historic gesture made in Washington in
September 1993. Transcending the tragic scenario of resentment
and mistrust, they demonstrated courage, reason and vision.
They preferred the sweet promise of future innocence, however
fragile, to the bitterness of experience. In so doing, and in
accepting the risks they were running, they reflected what is
most noble in human nature, for, as Aimé Césaire has observed,
"man is distinguished by a special propensity to defy destiny
and transform it into history."
What they have done is truly a challenge to destiny. The idea
of peace, now miraculously illuminating the sky of the Middle
East, is very fragile. We must all join in the efforts of the peo¬
ples of that region to ensure that peace is strengthened. Polit¬
ical co-operation, economic development and the reduction of
military spending are certainly necessary for that. However, I
believe that the essential task is to let the idea of peace take root
and to consolidate the moral and intellectual solidarity of indi¬
viduals and peoples.
The ethical, cultural and human aspects of peace are of
paramount importance. Without them, no political or eco¬
nomic agreement can be viable. With them, the culture of peace
can be firmly grounded in all areas of the life of society; national
capacities can be built up and strengthened; knowledge and skills
can be mobilized, and the potential of each individual can be
developed for the common good.
Almost fifty years ago, UNESCO defined as its most impor¬
tant goal the combat against racism, antisemitism, prejudice and
stereotypes, and the defence of human rights and peace, hoping
to prevent any return of the hideous ideology of which the
Jewish people had been the victim. Later, in accordance with
those same aims, UNESCO undertook various activities designed
to help the Palestinian people, deprived of sovereignty and
forced into exile, in several Middle Eastern countries. For years
the Israeli-Arab conflict, with its many reverberations within
the international community, caused heart-rending divisions in
Unesco.
These rifts now belong to UNESCO's past. But the values set
forth in its Constitution notably the need to construct the
defences of peace in the minds of men and to strengthen the
moral and intellectual solidarity to which I alluded above shine
out with undiminished radiance and are more relevant than ever.
A NEW CHAPTER IN HISTORY
The past cannot be changed. The future, unlike the past, is not
yet written; it can be changed. It is the only part of our common
heritage that is still intact. The key to the relaxation of tension,
understanding, good neighbourliness, solidarity, conciliation
and reconciliation is the "memory of the future" rather than
memory of the past. However long the conflict lasts, there
always comes a moment when the adversaries shake hands. We
must strive to ensure that this moment comes as soon as pos¬
sible, so as to avoid immense suffering, so that people do not die
for causes that deserve to be lived for.
Of course, the memory of those who have been wounded
in their person or their dignity during the long years of con¬
frontation must be respected. Morality no less than practical
reason demands it since a common future cannot be built on the
flouting of memory. Yet while forgetting is impossible, deter¬
mination to open a new chapter in history can ensure that the
memory of the future prevails over that of the past. It is nec¬
essary to look beyond present realities. "Only those who can
see the invisible can achieve the impossible". Shortsightedness
in politics has already caused too much harm. We must now dis¬
cover new ways of seeing. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
R
Arnold Toynbee
The way to coexistence
In 1935, as the dictators were
tightening theirgrip on Europe, the
International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation organized
a conference in London on the theme
ofcollective security. One ofthe
participants was the English
historianArnold Toynbee (1889-
1975), author ofthe vast and
controversialA Study of History
(1934-1961), which seeks to elucidate
the laws governing the birth and
evolution ofcivilizations. Inface of
the dangers presented by the rise of
authoritarian nationalism, he
proposed as a route to peaceful
coexistence the creation ofa new
world order established by mutual
consent on supra-national
foundations.
44
Oim Rapporteur, Maurice Bourquin,
has explained the fundamental dif¬
ference between the notion of indi¬
vidual securityand that ofcollective security
in the following words:
"Nations have always sought to obtain
security, that is, to protect themselves
against external aggression. How have they
gone about it? In the first place, they have
tried to organize and to increase their own
forces; the natural, instinctive reaction,
under the circumstances, is to rely upon
oneself.
"The principal form that this reaction
takes is clearly the policy ofnational arma¬
ments. Then, by a logical consequence,
this policy of armaments gives rise to a
policy of alliances.
"There is already, in this policy of
alliances, a sort of collaboration; but this
collaboration is scarcely different in spirit
from the purely individualistic method.
What is it that distinguishes the collective
solution from this formula? The aim here
is not the special security of a few states,
Arnold Toynbee in 1975.
but the security ofall. A collective organi¬
zation of security is not directed against
one particular aggression, but against war
considered as a common danger. The
organization ofa system ofcollective secu¬
rity is a new experience which separates us
from tradition. Are there profound rea¬
sons for trying to induce the states to take
this path? Do this conception and this
system lie within the domain of practical
possibilities? Or have we here a Utopia,
an idea which is perhaps seductive but
which is unattainable?"
One very obvious difference between
the two notions lies in the fact that indi¬
vidual security is a considerably older
notion than collective security. As our Rap¬
porteur pointed out, collective security is
a very recent idea. Really it is only in our
own life-time that collective security has
begun to be seriously studied as a practical
possibility.
The idea of individual security is older.
I would like to say in passing that it is not
a very old idea. It hardly goes back more
than four hundred years, and four hun¬
dred years is a short period even in the
history of our Western World. The notion
of individual security would have been
quite antipathetic and alien to our
medieval forefathers, who would have
regarded it as a frankly immoral and anti-
Christian idea, in which I believe they
would have been right. At the moment I
will simply point out that this idea of indi¬
vidual security has held the field for about
four centuries.
Then, rather abruptly, in our genera¬
tion we find ourselves being compelled
to consider, and reconsider, and come
back to this new idea of collective security.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The question one asks oneself then is, why,
when individual security has apparently
more or less worked for a period of four
hundred years, we should suddenly find
that it no longer suffices.
I think the answer is that, while absolute
local sovereignty has been the theory of
our international life for four centuries, it
has by no means been the practice till
quite recently. During the greater part of
the modern age, the Western world has
been partíy insufficiently equipped, and
partly too wise and too much under the
influence of an older and a better tradition
to carry out the principle of local sover¬
eignty and the allied principle of indi¬
vidual security to their extreme logical
conclusion. It is only in our generation
that we have seen the absolute totalitarian
state a local totalitarian state emerge
from the theoretical handbooks of the
jurist or poliücal philosopher and become
a living reality in the actual world.
That is why the present situation is so
serious, because a development towards
absolute local sovereignty, which has been
implicit in our history for four centuries,
has in our generation suddenly become a
reality.
I hold it is controversial, but I throw it
dovm for discussion that this principle is
essentially imworkable, and that as soon as
the principle is really put into effect as it
is being put into effect in our generation
we are bound to seek a remedy for it. If
absolute local sovereignty and a complete
application of the principle of individual
security had been in actual operation
during the whole of the modern age, dis¬
aster would have overtaken us long ago.
Then let me make a further point from
that, that when once you have a world
consisting of sixty or seventy local states,
which are putting into practice complete
local sovereignty, then such a condition
of internatíonal affairs is by its very nature
transitory. One can prophesy with assur¬
ance that, a hundred years from now, or
fifty years from now, if states continue to
try to be absolute in their local sovereignty,
there will not be sixty or seventy separate
sovereign states in the world; there will be
far fewer of them perhaps only one!
Often in life, I think, one finds oneself in
a situation something like this: that one
can see that there is a certain goal ahead of
one which is inevitable, which one is
bound to travel to; and I think in our inter¬
national life the inevitable goal now ahead
ofus is the abolition ofabsolute local sov¬
ereignty but often in such a situation
one still has a choice of the roads by which
one may approach the single inevitable
goal; and, of course, it makes the whole dif¬
ference, very often, which ofthe roads we
choose. The single goal maybe inevitable;
the alternative roads offer us a choice; and
it is desperately important to make the
better choice rather than the worse choice
betweeen the alternative ways of reaching
the single goal which we must ultimately
arrive at.
If our goal is the disappearance of local
sovereignty and I think that, in a worid
armed with the powers of technique and
organization which we possess, it is hardly
a controversial thing to say that communi¬
ties armed with those powers cannot exist
side by side in the same world, for long,
without disaster overwhelming us all, if
they claim absolute local sovereignty if,
then, absolute local sovereignty is doomed
to disappear, is bound to disappear, what
are the two alternative roads by which we
may approach its disappearance?
I think that, as always, there are roughly
two ways. One of them is evolutionary a
way by agreement and forethought and
non-violence. That is the road ofcollective
security. If one wishes to solve this problem
of reaching some kind ofworld order in a
peaceful way, then collective security is
the road. It is because we rightly feel the
immense importance of travelling by that
road and not by the other that we are
brought back again and again to this insis¬
tent question of collective security now.
If we can achieve collective security, the
abolition of sovereignty will be qualified
and relative.
We must face the fact that collective
security means a diminution of local sov¬
ereignty, but along this road the diminu¬
tion will be gradual. The present local
states of the world will fit themselves by
voluntary agreement into a world order
in which they will each retain their local
culture, their traditional life, their local
administrative autonomy. If local sover¬
eignty is got rid of in that way, the process
Text selected and presented
by Edgardo Canton
will hardly be felt as a loss or a sacrifice.
So I would make an appeal to those pre¬
sent who stand for the view that nationality
and the local national life is the supreme
good. I would say to them that the people
who hold that view a view from which I
personally dissent ought, more than any
of us, to be eager to achieve collective
security, because collective security is the
way in which the necessary sacrifice of
local sovereignty will be exacted from us in
tlie least possible measure.
But if we fail to achieve collective secu¬
rity, there remains only the alternative
road, which is a very ancient road and a
very familiar one, and that is the road of
violence and conquest. These immensely
arrogant and highly armed totalitarian
states will in that case grind against each
other like icebergs in a stormy sea
clashing and grinding against each other
till they break each other to pieces and
the inevitable world order will come about
in an ancient and a most destructive form,
a form which will produce a totalitarian
world-state, the kind of super-state that
none of us desires to see, a world-state
produced by force and resulting in the
complete destruction of local life and local
autonomy.
If that does occur, perhaps there may be
one victorious survivor. I do not think that
the fate of the victorious surviving state will
be appreciably happier or more pros¬
perous than that ofthe other states which
it has destroyed. But if there is a survivor,
I feel very certain it will not be my own
country. I do not think it will be any Euro¬
pean country. It may not even be any
country ofEuropean origin. We might have
great surprises, in a forcible unification of
the world, in the matter ofthe actual state
or community which achieved the task in
the end. 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
The royalpakces ofAbomey
byjasmina Sopova
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
46
A lion, emblem of KingGlèlè (1858-1889).
"The sliark who does notfear the
cayman!
The king who saved Daiioitieyfrom
dishonour
Is theMasterofthe Universe who will
fulfill the country's hopes!"
EAQi day at dawn Panlingan, crier of
the court ofGezo, king ofDahomey
in the first half of the nineteenth
century; used to chant his sovereign's praises
in these words in the main courtj'ard ofthe
royal palace ofAbomey. He would then
prostrate himself and throw dust over his
head. The custom had originated two cen¬
turies earlier, when King Ouegbadja had
ordered his court crier never to address
anyone without having first proclaimed his
glory. It passed down from king to king until
the fall ofthe last ruler, Behanzin, a hundred
years ago.
Tlirough that same courtyard today, vis¬
itors enter one of Africa's largest ensem¬
bles of historical monuments, the royal
palaces ofAbomey, a site which in 1985
was placed on the List ofWorld Heritage in
Danger.
The site, which extends over forty
hectares, includes not just tlie main palace
complex, which now houses a museum
and craft centre, but also an archaeolog¬
ical zone containing the ruins ofother, ear¬
lier palaces. Each ofthe two sections has a
tale to tell ofthe great kingdom's history The
archaeological zone evokes its birth and
growth as a small city-state, while the main
palace complex recalls the golden age and
the decline of the kingdom, as well as its
enduring heritage.
A CENTRAUZED STATE
Located 1 60 kilometres north ofCotonou in
what is now Benin, the town ofAbomey
was for three centuries the capital of the
Eon kingdom that was created around 1 620
by Do Aklin, a prince of the royal Aliada
family. His son Dako was to become the
first king ofAbomey five years later, but it
was Dako's son Ouegbadja (1645-85) who
made the kingdom a powerful one.
Ouegbadja laid the foundations of a
social hierarchy whose pinnacle was the
court; local chiefs were appointed by the
central government Responsibility for ritual
matters was entrusted jointly to a priest
and to a minister appointed by the sover¬
eign. Having thereby distanced himself
from religious affairs, the king was free to
concentrate on problems ofstate. The priv
ileges granted to the royal wives were shared
out equitably, thereby removing, in prin¬
ciple at least, the risk ofjealousy or plots. In
terms of political influence, none ofthe
wives could rival the queen mother,
enthroned at the same time as her son and
invested with important administrative
functions. An ingenious system ofsucces¬
sion permitted the ruler to choose his own
heir, enabling him to distance his own sons,
if necessarj', from the throne. Brothers ofthe
reigning sovereign were often killed as a
preventive measure.
Thanks to its solid political, social and
religious organization, the tiny city-state
rapidly became the principal power in the
region. Sadly, only one ruined entryway
survives ofthe palace of Ouegbadja, who
was considered the father of his country.
In 1685 Ouegbadja was succeeded by
Akaba, vv+io continued the task ofenlarging
and enriching the kingdom. He built a
dwelling for himself that had more than
one storey, a rarityat the time (though other
rulers were later to follow his example);
one imposing wall still survives. Following
custom, he built a new palace for himself
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Above, thrones ofthe kings ofAbomey
(Benin) are displayed in the ceremonial
throne-room.
Left, detail ofthe tapestry in the throne-
room.
near that of his predecessor, constructing a
new precinct that was linked by passage¬
ways to its neighbours.
The walls sim'oimding these inner enclo¬
sures were dwarfed by the gigantic ram¬
parts, from five to eight metres high, that
surrounded the entire palace complex. The
fortress, which housed barracks for the
royal guard and was flanked by dwellings,
was further protected by a ditch and a huge
barricade of thorns. At the height of the
kingdom's prosperity, its outer walls
stretched for three kilometres. It is not hard
to understand why the place became
known as Abomey, which means "within
the walls".
Sadly, the complex was twice ravaged
by fire. In Akaba's reign, a conflagration
reduced much ofthe site to ashes. Two cen¬
turies later, when the palace had been fur¬
ther enriched with seven additional royal
residences, another fire this one started
deliberately, as we shall see was to cause
further damage.
The remains of Akaba's palace and of
the multi-storey cabin built by Agadja
(1708-1740), his successor, provide valu¬
able evidence of the time when the
kingdom began to increase its links with
the coast so as to monopolize the provi¬
sion ofslaves to European traders. The slave
trade had become the foundation of the
economy ofDahomey, and it sparked fierce
competition with the Yoruba of Oyo, who
took a share in the traffic and even man¬
aged, between 1728 and 1818, to force four
successive kings ofAbomey Tegbesu, Ken-
gala, Agongolo and Adandozan to pay
them an annual tribute.
THE GOLDEN AGE
Adandozan was notorious for his incom¬
petent handling of the economy, his
despotic temper and his contempt for tra¬
dition. He was deposed by Gezo (1818-
1858), Abomey's best-known ruler who,
according to an English commodore who
had dealings with him, bestrode the earth
as though it should be honoured to bear 4J
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
Above, the palaces ofthe 19th-century
King Gezo and his son Glèlè are today a
history and art museum. Among the
exhibits is this carving of a hornbill, one of
Gezo's emblems.
Below, the courtyard of a royal palace of
Abomey. The walls are adorned with
coloured low-relief carvings.
such a burden. Besides Gezo's personal dig¬
nity, there was much to impress foreign
visitors in the splendours ofhis court, which
was served by some 10,000 people
including an army of about 4,000 female
warriors.
Even today, despite the ravages of time,
an aiua ofnobility surrounds Gezo's palace.
Following the example set by his prede¬
cessors, he organized the area within the
ramparts into three separate, walled-off
courtyards. His multi-storey cabin opened
on one side onto the main square
(singbodji) and on the other onto the outer
courtyard (kpododji), which was used for
religious ceremonies and military parades.
The "seat of power", the throne-room, the
sanctuary and the royal residence were all
situated in the private courtyard.
To differentiate religious structures from
those with other uses, the formerwere cir-
ctdar while the latter were rectangular. In
either case, the roofwas an important fea¬
ture. Gezo's residence, which had a huge
verandah and seven doors, was covered by
a straw roof that in its original state was
twice the size of what could be seen ofthe
walls. There were good practical reasons
for the roof's imposing dimensions. It pro¬
tected the building from the torrential rains
ofthe wet season and provided insulation,
while also lending an air of majesty to the
entire courtyard. Furthermore, it came
down so low that visitors were forced to
stoop to enter the building, thereby showing
their respect for the monarch, and also
giving them an opportunity to admire the
magnificent polychrome low-reliefs deco¬
rating the foot ofthe walls. To enter some
tombs in the complex, people almost had to
get down on all fours.
The roofs, which were built on a frame of
branches, have not stood the test of time.
Now the straw is supported by corrugated
iron, which has substantially reduced its
volume. The famous low-reliefs, painted
with natural pigment, have also suffered
damage, particularly from tornadoes in
1975, 1977 and 1984.
Since the site has been included on the
list ofWorld Heritage in Danger, restoration
ofthe dwellings, the roofs, the bamboo ceil¬
ings, the low-reliefs, the sculpted doors and
windows and what is left ofthe fortifications
has been taken in hand.
The royal residence and throne -room
where you can see Gezo's throne, among
others, resting on the skulls of four enemy
chiefs now serve as galleries for the
Abomey museum, as do the jewel room
and the armoury in the private courtyard of
Glèlè, Gezo's son.
DECLINE AND SURVIVAL
The courtyards ofthe palace ofGlèlè (1858-
1889) were as rich and elaborate as those of
his father. He established two dwellings
and two roofed shelters for weavers, cop-
perworkers and sculptors, where present-
day craftsmen still practice Abomey's tra¬
ditional arts. The descendants ofthe royal
families continue to live within the walls
of the complex and are responsible for
maintaining the tombs and sanctuaries.
In Glèlè's reign, Dahomey underwent
radical political and economic change. On
the one hand the slave trade was declared
illegal, and agriculture was developed, as
was palm-oil trading. On the other, Glèlè's
conservatism in foreign affairs produced
a climate of tension in his relations with
Europe that soon turned to open hostility.
By the time Behanzin came to power in
1889, conflicts with France had escalated to
a dangerous level. The French complained
of "the insolence of the king ofAbomey",
who had once asked "Have I gone to France
to make war on the French?" The people of
Dahomey were not prepared to pay the
price demanded for peace: "flying the
French flag in Abomey and handing over
the arms of all the warriors". Both sides
took to arms. A series ofengagements over
a period of months ended with Behanzin
being forced into exile.
Abomey was made a French protec¬
torate, and in 1894 a brother of Behanzin
named Agoli-Agbo replaced him on the
throne. His succession can be seen as an act
of family treachery or as a colonial intrigue;
whichever the case may be, Behanzin is
regarded as the nation's last independent
king. Before leaving the palace complex,
he had just enough time to set it ablaze.
That desperate gesture, a final response
to the challenge issued by history to the
ancient kingdom, could stand as a symbol
ofthe decline ofa renowned civilization. But
vestiges still survive in spite of fire and the
violence of men. In preserving them from
destruction, Unesco has put this major site
back into the history books.
JASMINA SOPOVA
is a Macedonian essayist who has written many
articles and studies on the art and literature of
black Africa, the Indian Ocean region and the
West Indies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
RECENT REC0RDIN6S
by Isabelle Leymarie
TRADITIONAL
MUSIC
CHINA
ne Art of the Pipa
Lin Shicheng (pipa)
CD Ocora Radio France
560046
The pipa a wonderful
antique lute, originally from
central Asia was the favourite
instrument of Tang-dynasty
China and is still played by many
Chinese today. Shanghai-bom Lin
Shicheng is one of the
instrument's most accomplished
exponents, and is his generation's
sole representative ofthe Pudong
School, one of four historic
schools of pipa technique. Most
of the pieces on this disc are
taken from the so-called "literary
repertoire", one ofthe two main
categories into which pipa pieces
are grouped, while the
alternative, "martial" repertoire is
represented by one track, "The
King Takes Off His Armour". The
music, which draws on very
ancient poetic symbolism, can be
sedate or lively but is always
entrancing. The sublime art ofthe
pipa still works its magic today.
MADAGASCAR
Possession et poésie
CD Ocora Radio France
580046
Madagascan art is little
known, yet it has treasures in
store. This disc provides a
sampling of ritual music
recorded during spirit possession
sessions among the Vezo, a sea¬
faring people ofthe south-west
coast. There are cilso herdsmen's
songs that recall the chanted
poems ofthe Peul, and a fine
piece of improvisation by male
voices. The instmments include
bows, rattles, African zithers,
dmms and diatonic accordéons.
Although Madagascar lies at the
crossroads ofAfrica and Asia, it is
the African element that
predominates here, in the
rhythmic conception and in the
timbre ofthe voices. The disc is
exciting evidence ofthe island's
many delights.
GUADELOUPE
Le gwoka. Soíré léwoz à ¡abrun.
CD Ocora Radio France
560030
Gwoka, the traditional music
ofthe Guadeloupe countryside,
is currently experiencing a
comeback both in the Caribbean
and in France, symbolizing the
vitality ofthe island's black
culture. The name gwoka, which
is derived from a type of drum,
the ka, that is played in various
parts ofthe Caribbean and in
New Orleans, covers a variety of
rhythms, including the
toumblack and the léwoz, a word
that has become almost
synonymous with gwoka.
Dancing is accompanied by two
kinds of drum, the boula and the
make, and by songs whose lyrics
often evoke local incidents.
Recordings ofthe oldest forms of
black music in the West Indies
are hard to come by in Europe,
which makes this disc, recorded
in the Baie Mahault district on
one of Guadeloupe's last
surviving plantations, all the
more precious.
JAZZ
BRANFORD MARSALIS
TRIO
Bloomington
Branford Marsalis (tenor and
soprano sax), Robert Hurt
(bass), Jeff "Tain" Watts
(drums)
Branford Marsalis is enjoying
a career just as successful as that
of his elder brother Wynton
whose band he used to play in-
even though their styles are very
different. Branford's lyricism,
inventiveness and technical skills
have made him one of today's
most popular and admired
saxophone players. On this
outing he opts for the austere
sound of a pianoless trio, thus
taking a difficult route on which
Sonny Rollins was one of the
leading pioneers in the 1960s. In
these profoundly spiritual
compositions the musicians
juxtapose different rhythms and
dispense with the usual
structural guidelines without
falling into amorphous free jazz.
Hurst and Watts are familiar with
the techniques and the pitfalls of
the music, and they share
Marsalis's escapades on this
unfamiliar musical journey.
TRAVIS SHOOK
Travis Shook (piano), Bunky
Green (alto sax), Ira Coleman
(bass), Tony Williams (drums)
CD Columbia 473770 2
This is the first recording by
Shook, a young pianist born in
Washington state (U.SA) who
reached thefinalsofthe
Jacksonville jazz festival piano
contest. Backing him are Miles
Davis's old dmmmer, Tony
Williams, and Ira Coleman, a
rising star among the bass-
players of Shock's generation.
Shook is a craftsman who works
in delicate shades, creating a
subtle music that sometimes
brings Bill Evans to mind in the
handling of the chords while
recalling Ahmad Jamal in its
swing and phrasing. Shook
reworks standards like "Love for
Sale" and "My Foolish Heart"
with intelligence and a fine sense
of pitch, a quality often lacking in
European music that gives the
notes extra sonority.
CLASSICAL
MUSIC
SARAH CHANG
Tchaikovsky: Violin Concerto,
Brahms: Hungarian Dances
Sarah Chang (violin), with the
London Symphony Orchestra
conducted by Sir Colin Davis
CD EMI Classics 7 54753 2
Violinist Sarah Chang, barely
twelve years old, is the new
prodigy everyone is talking
about. On this disc she interprets
Brahms's Hungarian Dances and
Tchaikovsky's beautiful
concerto something of a
showpiece for young violinists
with passion and a keen and
wholly individual sense of
rhythm, making light work of the
most demanding technical
problems. Her phrasing, agility
and sense of contrast are
astonishing.
LOUIS SPOHR
Octet/Sextet/Quintet
L'Archibudelli & Smithsonian
Chamber Players
CD Sony Classical 53370
Louis ("Ludwig") Spohr, who
was born in Brunswick in 1784
and lived at the court of the Duke
of Saxe-Gotha, in Vienna and in
Frankfurt before moving to
Cassel where he died in 1 859,
was a remarkable violinist,
conductor and composer. An
admirer of both Bach and the
young Wagner, he is a
representative figure ofthe
period of transition between
classicism and romandcism. His
intensely lyrical Octet, Sextet and
Quintet for string instmments
are performed on this disc on
violins, violas and cellos from the
Smithsonian Institution's
Stradivarius collection.
Describing the Sextet for The
Musical World, a reviewer in 1853
called it "a work which, while
showing all the experience of
age, displays in an astonishing
degree that freshness and
spontaneity which are supposed
to belong only to youth. One of
the last chamber compositions of
Dr. Spohr, this sestet is equally
one ofthe finest and most
captivating of them all."
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR TheljNESCO
OURIER
WHY I NO LONGER BELIEVE
IN THE UNITED NATIONS
A Unesco Coi/ríer subscriber for many years,
I have long admired the magazine and have
introduced others to it.
I am still interested in culture, science
and education. For a long time I thought
they could help humanity to advance by fos¬
tering greater understanding beUveen peo¬
ples, improved living conditions, a more
highly developed spirit of civic responsibility
and personal morality, and so on.
At the age of fifty-eight I have reached
the bitter conclusion that the noble edifice I
dreamed of is at best a façade, of which
Unesco, admittedly, is the most beautiful
part. But that's no longer enough for me! I
prefer organizations that are smaller and
closer to the grassroots.
You are part of the United Nations, an
organization which is mandated by the
world's great nations. WTiat are these coun¬
tries actually doing? While their diplomats
work to maintain or restore peace, their
armaments industries are flourishing and
delivering weapons to those who will one
day ignite conflicts and massacre popula¬
tions. The danger is now ubiquitous because
international gangsters can get their hands
on highly sophisticated and destructive
weapons.
There are too many unscrupulous, cow¬
ardly and greedy countries. To salve their
conscience they engage in activities with
cultural and humanitarian goals or create
organizations to achieve these goals.
GuySchoenhauer
Rambouillet, France
A HUNAN CHAIN
In response to my offer to exchange back
issues ofthe Unesco Coi/ríerwhich appeared
on the letters page of your June 1992 issue, I
have received letters from people in many
countries.
The response from the Netherlands
Unesco Centre was particularly rapid and
efficient. This dynamic, active centre
deser\'es praise for helping to promote the
ideals promoted by the Unesco Courier,
ideals inspired by a humanitarian, philan¬
thropic spirit, a thirst for knowledge and,
above all, a desire for peace.
I should like to thank Unesco for making
this human chain possible.
Harold M. LaBesse
12 AVENUE BENOIST LÉVT,
94160 Saint-Mandé, France
RS. If anyone has available copies ofthe July-
August 1956 and January 1982 issues ofthe
French edition, I'll be happy to take them!
WILL ART LOSE ITS SOUL?
For those who think about the future of art,
Sonia Youman's remarkable article in your
July-August 1993 issue provided plenty of
food for thought. Perhaps it would be useful
to redefine the word "image", which has
assumed a much broader meaning in the
world of contemporary art. It is undeniable
that art has developed to a prodigious degree
as a result of techniques for the transmis¬
sion and mass production of images. But
these techniques (photography, the cinema,
information science) have gradually come
to replace the human touch in the creation of
images as vehicles for an artisric message.
This is an alarming development.
In view of the extraordinary potential of
technology, is it not possible that "hand¬
made" images, so rich in emotional content,
will fade into insignificance and eventually
disappear altogether? Will they gradually be
replaced by the soulless products of super-
robots, as George Orwell grimly predicted?
Will the artists of the future have any
desire to learn the traditional gestures ofthe
painter and the sculptor, or will they simply
have to choose between the computer key¬
board and kinds of formula art increasingly
bereft of sensibility?
As we prepare to assess the achievements
and failures of this century, let us hope that
the balance will be redressed and that art
will be rehumanized. If this hope turns out to
be vain, we must be prepared for the worst:
infantile art without soul or structure, mind¬
lessly flickering on and off our screens.
Henry Christiaen
Grenoble (France)
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, page 3: © Ezéchiel Saad, Paris. Pages 5, 7, 8: Ulf AntJersen © Gamma, Paris. Page 1 0: Marco ©
Ask Images, Paris. Pages II, 14, 20: © Charles Lénars. Paris. Page 1 2: © Muñoz de Pablos, Paris. Page 1 3:
Bordes © Explorer, Paris. Page IS: © The Australian Academy of the Humanities. Page 16: © Miss
International, Galerie Beaubourg, Paris. Page 17: Sabine Weiss © Rapho, Paris. Pages 18, 19: © 1953 M. C.
Escher/Cordon Art-Baarn-The Netherlands. Pages 21, 27, 28, 29: © Yves Gellie, Paris. Pages 22-23, 24,
26: Bruno Barbey © Magnum, Paris. Page 25: James Morris © Panos Pictures. London. Page 30 (above):
David Reed © Panos Pictures. London. Page 30 (middle): © CIRAD/GERDAT/ PRIFAS 93. Page 30
(below): © Editions de l'Environnement. Paris. Page 3 1 (above): Mauri Rautkari © WWF, Gland. Page 3 1
(below/): Peter Tunley © WWF, Gland. Pages 32-33: Chistyakov © Novosti, Paris. Page 34: All Rights
Reserved. Page 3S: Matytsin © Novosti. Paris. Page 36 (left): Zagumeny © Novosti, Paris. Page 36
(right): S. Gukski © Novosti, Paris. Page 37 (left): Jim Pickerell © Rapho, Paris. Page 37 (right): Jean
Hosking © Rapho, Paris. Pages 38-39: Stan Fautré © Ask Images, Paris. Page 39 (right): R Rivière © Miss
International, Paris. Page 40: ©Jia Tian. Pages 40-41: Michel Baret © Rapho, Paris. Page 42: Unesco-
Michel Claude. Page 44: © Keystone. Pages 46, 47, 48: J.A. Fernandez © Incafo, Madrid.
47th VE&R
PubEFsFied munthly In 3Í Itnguagtï and in Btallf« by Umeïco,
TPi« United Nations EducitlonaF, Scientific und Cultunl
Or^ïiiFlAtion.
3F.rvefrir*çoisBOfmnr7»F5 F*ans, Ff^nce.
Director: Bahgat Etnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition; Alain Lèvéque. Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition; F^igu^F Labarca, Araceli Ortii de Uriiina
Art Unit^Producdon; Georges Servat
Illustrations; Ariane Bail^ (Tel ii.6B46.%)
Documentation:
Liaison with non- Headquarters editions and press:
Solange BelFn (TeF. 15.6«,«,8 7)
Secretariat Annie Brächet (Tel, 45,68,47, 1 S),
Administrative Assistant;
Selection in Braille in English, Frwich, Spanish and
Korean: F^ouni Chacta (45,68,47,14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander MelnFFtov (Moscow)
German: DominiqFie AndeF^s (Beme)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian; Mario Guidocti (Rome)
Hindi; Ginga Prasad Viniai (Delhi)
Tamil: f^. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
^rsian; H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrleux (Antwerp)
Portuguese; Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Serpil Gogen (Ankara)
Urdu; WaN Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan; Joan Carreras I Marti [Barcdona)
Malaysian; SldFn Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpiw)
Korean: Yi Tong.ok (Seoul)
SwahiM: Leonard J. Shuma (Danes-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Komhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek; Sophie Cosiopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Meville Pi^digama (Colormtio)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque; JuKto Egana (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surlntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese; Do F^uong [Hanois
Pashto: Naier Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib AJhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian; Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Galician; Xabler Senin Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions; Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy. Jacqueline Louise-Julie. Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard. Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginecre Mocreff (Tel, 45,68,45,64)
Accounts; (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.66.47,50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel : 45 68 45 65
1 year: 21 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF
Binder for one ^r's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries;
I year: 1 32 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF
Pa)^ment can be FTiade with any convenible currency to die
order of UNESCO
FfldividuaF articles ar\ii pFictDgraplis rxjt Enpyrrghted may b^ re^rinwd
prOMdmg ctie çftdiï Fine reaih 'fiip.'FiiKd fiWi tht OFwEKO Courttf", plirt
àULo ïTfiïiuEiandtFrrep va^KÍ^er copiesar^senttad^eBdicar, S^ed arn-
dBS repnrKexl miAi bear auEhor'ï name. NofxcpyngFit p^4I0t YnFi bt tup-
pli«d on retquHt. LFntoFJCitc^ nviflulcnpts <:a^nnt bë returned unless
accDrnpanjed by an ¡rHErraüonal nçfy coupon cxjvertng poï^^ SFpvd v>
cFh eupt'eu ïFvc oplniwit oF th« authö.? a[>d<lür>otnfita&sar¡Frr^r«SEnt
ti« opjntoru of Unesco er thcua gf the editors otf The C^ snï Cwief F^w
captiOfVS 3M F)«adFHne$ ar« written bytiie t^Mtsco {lomEr ïtafF. TFh btiund-
sriaon mspj pubüíFied in Che ntigutfie dfl not irripFy cfficiaF ndors*ni*m
or acceptance by L^JESCO or the LJnited F^bdons. TFie Ltficc C^ouncf if pr^
tjticed in mkroi*m» (rrtFcrofllm and/or micrüTrch*) bjr (F) Unesco. 7
Place dE Fnntenofy. 7S700 Paris: (2) Univetiity Microftirn (Xerox), Ann
Arbw, F*FicF>¡¿an^8IOOiJ.SAi(3)N.C.F^,MicTOca^dEdFt^t>^,lntfeí^Head
Fnc, I F I West .«ih Saeet New To*. UW: (H) BeH ind HowelF Co. OU
Fianîfield Riad, Wmster, Ohio 444? F . U.SA.
FMPRFMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Print«! in FjiHmFwrg)
DÉPÔT FJGAI; Cl - FÈVRFER FW4
COMMFSSFON PARFTAFUE N" 7Fftll - DIFRJSÉ PAFl LÉS NMPÍ,
Phqtocompoïition, photpgnivure: Le Courrier de IUnesco.
Fmpresiion: IMPFÎIMEF(FE SAFNT.PAUL, 1, rue Chrnioptie.pFandn
L-1S6B Liitenibour^
FSSN0îtM-3IF8 N^2-F«4-OPI-M-533A
This iiiue ctxnpriies SI piges and a ^f^ Fnierx benveen
pa|« ID-IF and 424}
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
LISEZ TOUS LES MOIS
ETVDES
Revue d'information, de réflexion et de culture
Dans les prochains numéros :
L'Afrique du sud va voter Maggie Paterson
Palestine - Israël : les étapes ultérieures L.-J. Duclos
L'homme de mer Guy Labouérie
Pour une définition de l'art Jean-Claude Lemagny
Figures du « siècle des reformations » Th. Wanegffelen
Mallarmé et Saint-John Perse André David
Choix de films, Chroniques de théâtre,
Revue des livres, Choix de disques
Le n° : (144 pages) 55 F, étr. 62 F
Abonnement : 11 nM / an : 450 F - étr. 550 F
Rédacteur en chef
Jean-Yves Calvez
Pour recevoir un numéro ou vous abonner, envoyez vos nom,
adresse et règlement à l'ordre d'ETUDES à :
Assas Editions 14, rue d'Assas - 75006 PARIS - Tél. : (1 ) 44 39 48 48
Ou, sur Minitel, tapez 36 15 SJ* ETUDES
EUROLANGUES
Les stages de langues...
Réputés depuis de nombreuses années pour :
L'excellence et la spécificité de ¡a pédagogie,
La parfaite adéquation avec les exigences
du système éducatiffrançais,
L'efficacité et lafiabilité de l'encadrement.
Collégiens Lycéens Prépas Etudiants
182, rue Lecourbe
75015 Paris
tél. : (1)42 50 0817
fax ': (1)45 33 70 74
Vivre et étudier dans un
autre pays ... w^
... L'expérience de-^B^
toute une vie ! F ~~
Contactez-nous au : (1) 48 00 06 00
ou retournez le coupon ci-dessous pour recevoir nos brochures gratuites :
Cours de langues, 8 pay's 16anset +
9 mois d'étude d'anglais, USA, GB 16-28 ans
Programme d'année scolaire, USA 15-2 1 ans
Etudes en université, 6 pays 1 8 ans et +
FoTnations professionnelles, Europe, USA 1 8 ans et +
Q Séjours en famille d'accueil, USA 14-25 ans
Q Séjoursjuniors, GB 8-15 ans
Nom/Prénom 	
Adresse 	
CP/Ville 	 .'.	
Tel 	 Age 	 3702
Inscription dès à présent à :
ASPECT- 53, rue du %Poissonnière -75009 PARIS
& ASPECT
Organisme adhérent à la charte de qualité UNSE
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
TVie
r deseï^^
uâ
-nu
ut»'
^tfttüsBL
three good
reasons for
offeríngyour
friends a gift
subscription:
The Unesco Courier is the only internotionol mogoiine
published in 32 languages and reod by hundreds of thousonds of
people in 120 countries
Eoch month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture ond
knowledge
ft ossociotes ill reoden with UNESCO's mission of furthering "universal respect
forjustice, for the ruk of low ond for humon rights and fundomentol
freedoms,. . without distinrtion of roce, sex, longuoge or religion..."
NONTH, ESSENTIAL READING F
OF TODAY
M UNDERSTANDING
TONORROW
PROBLENS
VIOL£NC£ ... PSYCHOANALYSIS: THE HIDDEN I ... A TIHE TO LOVE ,.. WATER OF LIFE .,, MINORITIES,,, WHAT
iS MODERN?,,, RHYTHM, GESTURE AND THE SACRED,,, TIHE TO DISARM... THE STORY OF NUMBERS...
KORTH-SOUTH DEBATE: THE MEANINfi OF PROGRESS,,, DESERTS,,, WORLDS WITHIN WORDS,,.
,TURESONTHE
»HERITAGE,
FRANCOIS MITTERRAND... JORGE AHADO... RICHARD ATTENBOROUCH.,, JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIERE... JEAN
LACOVTURE... FEDERICO MAYOR... NAGUIB MAHFOUZ... SEHBENE OUSHANE,,, ANDREI VOZNESENSKY...
FREDERIC ROSSIF... HtNNERK BRUHNS... CAMILO JOSE CELA... VACLAV HAVEL... SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV...
ERNESTO SABATO,,. «RO HARLEM BRUNDTLANO... CLAUDE LEVI-STRAUSS,,. LEOPOLDO ZEA... PAULO
FREIRÉ... DANIEL J, BOORSTIN... FRANCOIS JACOB... RANU DIBAHGO,,, FAROUK HOSNY... SADRUDDIN AGA
KHAN.,, JORGE LAVELLI,,, LEON SCHWARTZENBERG.,, TAHAR BEN JELLOUN... GABRIEL GARCIA MÁROUEZ..,
JACflUES-YVES COUSTEAU,,, HELINA HERCOURI.., CARLOS FUENTES... JOSEPH KIZERBO... VARDANA SHIVA,..
WILLIAM STYRON,.. OSCAR NIEMEYER... MIKIS THEODflRAKlS,,, ATAHUALPA YUPANflUI.., HERVE BOURGES,,.
AB9EL RAHMAN EL BACHA... SUSANA RINALDI... HUBERT REEVES.,, JOSE CARRERAS... A LETTER FROM
FREUD TO EINSTEIN... LUC FERRY .. CHARLES HALAMOUD,,, UHBEBTO ECO.,, OLIVER STONE... ANDRE
BRINK... JAHES D. WATSON... AMOS OZ... HICHEL SERRES... THEODORE HONOD,.. YVES COPPENS...
HUNAN RIGHTS
FEATVHH6 AN IRTEHVIEW : NAIIUTIAH
EDOUARD J. NAUNICK
]]>
</page>
</document>
