<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="096120eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
mwPmff'
The I Inesco
- ^courulURIER
MARCH 1994
HUMAN
RIGHTS
i \ &
ifHE
V UNFINISHED
TASI
m
INTERVIEW WITH
I EDOUARD J. HAUNICK
ENVIRONMENT
SMALL ISLANDS:
DREAMS AND REALITIES
HERITAGE
THE FABULOUS WORKS
OF HENRY CHRISTOPHE
\
*1
H
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
THE LIGHT
1989, stoneware
Agnès Andrée Legrand
Returning from a visit to
Morocco, French
ceramist Agnès-Andrée
Legrand brought back
from the mountains of
the High Atlas some
statuettes whose facial
expressions reminded her
of the mysterious stone
statues of Easter Island.
Inspired by this intriguing
similarity, she created
these three "silent heads
turning towards the
light" an intermingling
of influences from the
South Pacific and North
Africa on the soil of
France and in its clay.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 INTERVIEW MH
Edouard J. Maunick
Contents
MARCH 1994
HUNAN RIGHTS
THE UNFINISHED IASK
8 The birthright of humanity
by Federico Mayor
9 The U-word
by Ibrahima Fall
UNESCO IN ACTION
11 NGOs: the fight to be heard
by Sophie Bessis
46
HERITAGE 15 One and indivisible
Haiti: King Henry's
fabulous works by Antoine Bernard
by Francis Leary
18 Free speechdemocracy's m
49 by Helen Darbishire
ARCHIVES
Venice: a picture of
harmony
by Le Corbusier
18 States of bondage
by Manfred Nowak
Cover:
Crowd XV, a watercolour by the
American artist Diana Ong.
11
Greenwatch
Small Islands:
dreams and realities
by France Bequette
Special consultant for this issue:
Ehsan Naraghi
with a contribution from
Diana Ayton Shenkcr
I Seedplot for the future
by Stéphane Hessel
' Unesco: the rights of all
by Francine Fournier
I A new departure
by Alois Mock
The Vienna Conference
what was at stake
The
Mi
Unesco
courier
47th year Published montWy
in 32 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO. LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER (945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
EDOUARD J. MAUNICK talks to Jasmina Sopova
Among authors writing in French
today, the Mauritian poet Edouard J.
Maunick is one of those who most
strikingly embodies and champions
the values of a mixed racial
background. He has written more
than a dozen books, one of which,
Ensoleillé vif, won the 1977 Prix
Apollinaire, a leading French poetry
prize. All his works are centred on
the encounter between the self and
that which is outside the self. They
are filled with the wonder of a
childhood and adolescence spent
on his native island, where he
experienced the plurality of cultures
as a living reality. After nearly ten
years as director of the Unesco
Collection of Representative Works,
he is now associate editor of the
Paris-based magazine Jeune Afrique.
JASMINA SOPOVA
is a Macedonian essayist
You like to describe yourselfas not just
an "insulaire" an islander but an
"insulé" someone who has as it were
become an island unto himself. What do
you mean by this?
I use that word because I believe the con¬
dition of being an islander is determined
both by the place of birth and by the person
born there. Let me explain. Those who are
born on an island and live there for years
imperceptibly adopt the "attitudes" spe¬
cific to it. When I use the term insulé, I refer
to that natural chacteristic of the islander. I
invented it because I felt the need to be
more precise. It is a better way of expressing
the metamorphosis from person to island:
one is born an islander but one becomes
insulé.
At the same timeyoupresent the island
as a confined space, penned in by the sea.
Mauritius is a very small island, a rock cast
out in the vast ocean, so that when one
reaches the age of awareness and begins to
try to find oneself, one is inevitably over¬
come by a feeling of constriction, both
physical and mental. The island hems you
in, clasps you to it. At times you even feel
cramped within your own body, your own
skin. That at least was the well defined and
painfully sharp impression I had, especially
on the seashore. The littoral was the place
where the revelation came to me.
In yourpoemsyou compare the sea to a
prison's bars. Is being surrounded by the
sea such a cursef
An island is an enclosed space and the sea
a way out, into the wide world beyond,
but an island also has another dimension. It
is fertile in more than one sense. What I
mean is that when your eyes are drawn
upwards by the hills and the trees, from
the foothills and roots to the treetops and
summits, your gaze emerges into the wide
open sky in all its immensity. In the same
way, the branches draw your eyes outwards
and away, beyond the outermost leaves.
This constant toing-and-froing of the eye in
the end conditions what many would call
the soul but for which I have no name. No
matter, everything overflows and reaches
out.
When you have been raised in the school
of sun, rain and wind, of the red soil of the
tropics, the clouds and the stars, all these
supposedly inanimate things, the constric¬
tion that at first felt like a curse, a sentence
passed at birth, soon elicits a reaction that is
both awesome and sweet, an irreverence
that sets things in motion. One does an
about-turn; one's eyes are no longer fixed on
the island's centre but look out to sea and the
horizon becomes another country, other
countries. That is when the dream begins,
the urge to leave	
That is also when exile begins. You were
barely thirty when you left your islandfor
Paris. You were later to write that exile is
hard, even when it is self-imposed.
Exile becomes hard when loneliness sets
in, a loneliness that has more to do with the
memory of something essential rooted
within oneself than with ordinary recol¬
lections. Otherwise I do not regard exile as
painful, because it not only means leaving
home to go somewhere else, it also means
stepping forward towards yourself,
deciding to get to know yourself and to live
in and with yourself. After living through
your own tribulations and moments of
wonderment, you need to find out about
others, but the first essential is self-knowl¬
edge. Exile then becomes a quest, an expe¬
dition into the inner space of others, in
the course of which one must above all
never give in to the temptation of wanting
to portray others in one's own likeness,
on the pretext of aligning certain details.
That would be simply subjecting others
to the appetite for power that gnaws at all
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
of us. Sharing is something else. Exile then
becomes an opportunity for getting to
know, a fabulous voyage of discovery.
It appears from yourpoems that wher¬
ever in the worldyour travels takeyou you
discover something ofyour native island.
Exile is fraught with a sense of loss, to
make up for which some part of that which
one encounters transforms itself into that
which is missing. It is true that wherever I
go I find scraps of my childhood, when
everything was a source of wonder to me.
My desire no longer to regard my island as
a self-contained place, an outcast from the
world, goes together with a desire, expressed
through my verse, to bring rr country
closer to other countries.
Often by means of certain leitmotifs
like the "sega", the music ofAfrican origin
foundonly in the Mascarenhas Islands in the
Indian Ocean	
The sega is for me not just a type of music
peculiar to the Mascarenhas but a vibra¬
tion, a throbbing in the guts. Another reason
why I bring in the sega is for this throbbing
rhythm to merge with the rhythm of the
world. In much the same way, although I am
a man in search of himself, I am nothing
without the crowds that fill the world. That
is why I believe the world should be as one,
that the true name of the world is solidarity,
togetherness, sharing. Unless we share, listen
to one another, speak to one another, empti¬
ness and silence ensue.
Living means being surrounded by the
hum of life, of which the sega is part. All
human beings need vibrations, need to
express that busy hum of living in sounds
and harmonies, to find an accompaniment.
They need their own small tune to play in
the great orchestral score of the world. I
am not being a dreamer when I talk in this
way. It is from a refusal to talk in this way
that wars come about.
Is that why poets need to link this
"vibration", by means of their words, to
the whole human condition?
Words are more universal than people
think. They are not the exclusive property
of a particular person. Writing in French, I
often give the words a different meaning, a
different echo, a different ring, no doubt
because I bend the language or try to join it
in lawful or unlawful wedlock with my
own Creole speech. To admit this is not to
detract from French. On the contrary, it is
to enrich it, to show the love of an insulé for
the language, to spice up the words not so
much so as to give them local colour as
because you can't help it, because it comes
naturally.
As far as I am concerned at least, it is
not the words alone that give a poem its
meaning but also the way they are chosen
and used. When I use a word, I give it a
cadence of my own. Using a word affects
its meaning, its harmonics, its music and
movement.
You see the poet then as a sort of
alchemist?
To some extent the poet creates language.
He draws speech out of silence and the
unspoken, and in the southern hemisphere
all poetry is speech; but although poetry is
my way of reaching out to myself and the
world, it is also the most essential and at the
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
same time most pointless act I perform.
Here we enter deep into the realm of
paradox for better or worse.
The fact is that life is made up of
paradox. Poetry is essential in that it enables
me to say what I see, not just what is before
my eyes, and what I hear, not just what I
listen to. I have been given the stewardship
of a talent for which I cannot take the credit,
and I realized from the outset that I must use
it in a serious and responsible, not a facile,
way. Poems are my weapon, the voice that
speaks to me, the music I dance to, the fire
that warms me and burns me, the light by
which I see things more clearly. .
I have made use of poetry and I still do,
but you will understand that it also verges
on pointlessness. I am not saying that I am
not happy to write I dare to believe that
my poems are not of use to me alone but
face to face with the ignominy of death the
eternal question recurs why? Perhaps,
after all, that is what life is, asking ques¬
tions.
Are you casting doubt on poets?
Yes and no. I do not see the poet as a
mere adjunct of the nation, a decorative
flourish, quite the contrary. This is not to
plead my own cause: poets can claim some
of the credit for the fact that peoples have
survived and civilizations have not disap¬
peared. Memory is enshrined first in their
spoken words, then in writing and now in
images. The greatest film-makers, photog¬
raphers, painters and sculptors are primarily
poets. To grasp the inner meaning, the emo¬
tion in things not the explanation but the
emotion is to attain to the epic, the
memory that must endure. Dictators, the
murderers who always condemn poets first,
before soldiers and politicians, know what
they are about. Poets lug memory around
with them, they make trouble!
One ofyourpoems, "As far as Yoruba
land", clearly illustrates the disagreement
you have often expressedwith Paul Valéry 's
idea that civilizations are mortal.
You are quite right. As long as a single
closely or distantly related heir to a civi¬
lization survives, that civilization cannot
die, and even should that individual disap¬
pear, his or her civilization would still be
there, because it would have nourished
others. That is the way the world's great
heritage is shared out: it is enough for traces,
only traces, to remain for everything to
begin again.
One day I happened to be in Oshogbo,
in Yoruba country, with my friend Wole
Soyinka. We were in a sanctuary, richly
adorned with stone carvings and with tra¬
ditional paintings on the surrounding walls.
He explained that it was a shrine to Oshun,
the Yoruba goddess of fertility, and he told
me the ancient story that comes into the
poem you mentioned. I revisited that vestige
of an immemorial civilization in the 1960s.
The place was deserted but I, someone born
thousands of miles away, had come back
there and I instantaneously and with great
intensity relived that memory.
I believe that even in more ordinary,
humdrum circumstances we can experience
other civilizations, of whatever age.
In the samepoem we come across your
holy trinity: Oshogbo, Benares and Geth-
semane.
I was fortunate enough to be born in a
country where all the great religions are pre¬
sent. I was christened and I read the Gospel
and then the whole Bible, but I also read
the Vedas, the Ramayana and the Egyptian
Book of the Dead. The Bible made me want
to discuss things with my school friend
Aziz I was aware that he attended a dif¬
ferent place of worship from me and
observed different rites. I wanted to find
out, I read the Qur'an. My father Daniel
Maximilien taught me one should always
try to get to the origin of things, and that was
how my search for my identity led me to dis¬
cover my Hindu roots. I had the good for¬
tune to have a great master, Ram Prakash,
who introduced me to Indian culture and got
me to read the Mahabharatra, the Bha-
gavad Gita and the Tripitakas as well. When
I later met Miguel-Angel Asturias, he opened
my mind to the Aztec Bible, the Popol Vuh.
All this is rewarding but at the same
time makes the questioning more intense.
The discovery that places are different but
not people is no doubt due to to my deep
personal experience of Mauritius' plu¬
rality the triune divinity Oshun/Shiva/
Jesus is the trinity that has run in my veins
from birth. Be that as it may, in spite of all
vicissitudes I am still a close friend of Christ.
I often speak to him because I am convinced
that he too must have asked himself many
questions about the human condition, and
the answers he found concern me still.
You have often said you do not accept
ready-made answers.
There are so many questions to ask. It's
not that I take pleasure in it, but what else
can one do? I began to ask questions and to
put questions to myself very early, perhaps
too early, which may be why I have found
answers but not the answer, and when I
realized I was too soon with my questions
I rebelled. Rebellion is my way of surviving
while thinking I am living. Whether or not
I shall one day find the ideal, the complete
and final answer I don't know. In the mean¬
time I must reply. Somewhere I find
answers. I do not rebel for rebellion's sake.
There have been victories, but however
uplifting they may be, this loneliness that
creeps up on me belies everything.
How did this rebellion start?
In several situations, great and small. For
instance, when I witnessed the contempt
shown by someone of a supposedly superior
race towards my father, simply because he
was a descendant of coolies and slaves, had
a black skin and bore an Indian name, my
blood boiled. That was when I began to
rebel, when I was still a child, not ten years
old. That was the day I went to war and told
myself, clenching my fists and gritting my
teeth: this is not going to happen ever again,
not to me nor to others, and especially not
to my father.
Sol felt this pressing need for justice at
a very early age. The Bible says that after
death we shall live in a kingdom where jus¬
tice reigns. I didn't understand then and I
still do not understand. I am an impatient
person, I'm incapable of waiting. I say to
myself that death always comes too soon.
History is forever blowing up in your face
South Africa, apartheid, the concentration
camps of the Second World War, Hiroshima,
Viet Nam, Biafra, Lebanon, more recently
Sarajevo, Somalia, Algeria and the rest.
All these things make me want to rebel
even more. History is a dangerous place
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
and travelling through history is hard going;
one would sometimes prefer not to know,
not to understand but just to pass by but
that would be a form of cowardice. I am not
laying down my arms. This rebellion can be
developed and expressed through poetry. As
Aimé Césaire said, poetry brings me to the
heart of myself and of the world; after
quoting that all-time giant of poetry I need
say no more. The poet is by nature more of
a rebel than a dreamer, or else his dream is
reality in a cruder form.
To quote you one last time, the poet
fights his war alone and in his own way.
That is true in a sense, because his whole
life is solitude. In coming back to solitude I
bring the wheel full circle, because this little
world is alone, because when you love a
woman you are alone, because you live
your life and experience death alone, because
when the feeling of loss comes upon you,
you endure it alone. But perhaps solitude is,
after all, the natural human condition. There
is said to be something called a herd instinct:
I am glad to have travelled and above all to
have met people.
What is important is that the road we
travel passes among other people. Although
they raise weighty questions within you,
other people at the same time provide you
with fragmentary answers. Perhaps I am
asking too much! I cannot say whether I
have found the island, the woman, the land,
but I cannot deny that I have come upon
serendipitous fragments and experienced
ineffable instants of all that I was in search
of, which leads me to wonder whether the
human adventure does not in fact consist in
gathering up these fragments and instants as
one gathers sticks to make a bundle of fire¬
wood. Human beings have this genius for
fending off loneliness, exile and death by
dressing up the passing moment as a miracle,
as we did in childhood.
Is this, ultimately, what we should be
looking for in yourpoetry?
Yes, but with a strong dose of caution.
Let us not delude ourselves: everything
begins and ends with death, and in order
to "try to live", to disregard the only cer¬
tainty that death will come I confront
death with my words. It's not much, but at
the same time it's a great deal, for we of the
South know that words never decay. Death
is a curse that comes upon us I know not
how, and since I shall never know the
answer I have chosen to turn it aside. In
my latest poem, not yet published, I say
that as a child I used to build a memory to
nourish my sleep, and who could deny
that sleep is a kind of death? Even then I
refused to accept the state of non-being, of
non-presence.
Since then I have talked a lot and peo¬
pled my own life and other people's lives
with my sounds, sometimes coherent and
sometimes incoherent. No matter. I did so
and still do so to defer death, to confuse it.
I disguise it so that it is no longer an absence.
That is the source of my poetry.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
THE BIRTHRIGHT
OF HUMANITY
IN order to protect and implement human rights, we have a prac¬
tical task to perform, that of securing wider acceptance of the inter¬
national instruments adopted in this field by the United Nations,
the International Labour Organisation, UNESCO and other institu¬
tions, so that the whole of humanity is covered by them.
This practical, effective universality that we are striving to achieve
is the reflection and corollary of another kind of universality that
underpins it, the universality of the values enshrined in the Uni¬
versal Declaration of Human Rights, the landmark text whose forty-
fifth anniversary we celebrated in 1993. The universality of human
rights: the words say so much and yet so little. Are we fully aware of
the ethical truth summed up therein, that each and every human
being has the same rights? Do we truly understand that each individual
is both a unique being and the epitome of the species ? Do we recog¬
nize, in our way of life and behaviour, the implications of the fact that
human rights belong within the common heritage of humanity?
These rights are common to all because they belong to each and
every one of us, universal because they transcend cultural differences.
One may argue against their being uniformly applied to all cultures,
to the extent that such an objection is part of a larger struggle to resist
the creeping uniformity threatening to engulf the world. However,
the values in whose name these rights are invoked correspond to aspi¬
rations inherent in human nature and are therefore indeed universal.
These rights have a collective dimension, in the sense that they may
be claimed by individuals as members of a group, or when their
enjoyment presupposes a social framework. In this connection, on the
eve of the International Decade of the World's Indigenous People, the
voice of those people must be given a hearing, must be heeded, and
must bear its part in the democratic polyphony.
At the dawn of the third millennium, the concept of human
rights interactive, inseparable and indivisible has broadened to
encompass economic, social and cultural rights, civil and political
rights, the right to a healthy environment, the right to human and sus¬
tainable development, and even the rights of future generations. We
should welcome this continuing process of expansion, which is nec¬
essary for the full realization of these rights.
Federico Mayor
Director-General of Unesco
8
msmm&mm®
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
This issue of the
Unesco Courier,
devoted to human
rights, focuses on the
proceedings and
outcome of the World
Conference on Human
Rights convened by the
United Nations and
held in Vienna (Austria)
from 14 to 25 June 1993.
The Conference was
attended by more than
7,000 people, including
delegates from over 170
states and 800 non¬
governmental
organizations. In the
article below, its
Secretary-General
explains how, in spite of
many differences of
viewpoint, the principle
of the universality of
human rights was
endorsed.
The U-word by Ibrahima Fall
Above, Iridescent
copenetration ( 1 9 1 2- 1 9 1 3),
drawing on paper
by the Italian painter
Giacomo Baila
WHEN the United Nations World Con¬
ference on Human Rights adopted the
Vienna Declaration and Programme of
Action on 25 June 1993, it marked the culmi¬
nation of a process that had lasted over two
years, in the course of which the international
community had woven a network of activity
embracing all regions of the world and an
impressive range of sectors of society.
The genesis of the Conference can be traced
to the end of the Cold War when, in the new
spirit of optimism and renewed confidence in the
United Nations, the international community
considered that the time was appropriate to
hold a world meeting that would review and
assess the progress made in the field of human
rights since the adoption of the Universal Dec¬
laration in 1948, and identify obstacles and ways
in which they could be overcome to facilitate
progress in this area.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
During the May 1993
election in Cambodia,
held under United Nations
supervision, a crowd
in Phnom Penh follows
the results as they are
posted up.
The World Conference on Human Rights
thus marked a watershed in the consideration of
human rights. It helped to soften the antagonistic
overtones of the North-South divide, as well as
narrow the gap between what initially appeared
to be two mutually irreconcilable positions.
The process of reconciliation was not easy.
The North-South differences which replaced
the East-West confrontation ranged from such
diverse questions as universality versus regional
particularity, the interlinkage and indivisibility
of all human rights, the interdependence
between the right to development and civil and
political rights, and the threat of terrorism to the
enjoyment of civil and political rights. Other
controversial areas included implementation
machinery, monitoring, prevention and the
strengthening of United Nations mechanisms in
the field of human rights.
Among the more important achievements of
the Conference was the reinforcement of the
universality of human rights. The Universal Dec-
IO
IBRAHIMA FALL,
of Senegal, is the United
Nations Assistant Secretary-
General for Human Rights and
head of the UN Centre for
Human Rights, which is based
at the United Nations Office in
Geneva. He was Secretary-
General of the World
Conference on Human Rights
in Vienna.
laration adopted by the General Assembly of
the United Nations in 1948 was globally recog¬
nized as "a common standard of achievements for
all peoples and all nations". During the 1960s,
however, with the collapse of colonialism in Asia
and Africa, this notion was challenged by many
Afro-Asian thinkers and philosophers on the
grounds that since the Universal Declaration had
been adopted before the onset of decoloniza¬
tion, universally recognized human rights stan¬
dards needed modification in order to take into
account differing religious, historical and cul¬
tural values. However, human rights activists
and thinkers feared that any such modification,
if accepted, and based on differing religious and
cultural norms, would undermine internationally
recognized human rights norms and standards. In
other words, the post-colonial period witnessed
a deadlock. There was an avoidance of debate
on this question by metropolitan scholars and
intellectuals, and consequent suspicion on the
part of formerly colonized peoples.
The preparatory process of the World Con¬
ference, including the regional meetings for
Africa, Latin America and the Caribbean, and
Asia, adopted different formulations on this
question. The most interesting formulation, and
certainly the most far-reaching, was contained in
the Bangkok Declaration (see page 44), which
states that while human rights are universal in
nature, they must be considered in the context
of a dynamic and evolving process of interna¬
tional norm-setting, "bearing in mind the sig¬
nificance of national and regional particularities
and various historical, cultural and religious
backgrounds."
A spirit ofcompromise
The Tunis Declaration, on the other hand (see
page 42), was more positively worded when
it stated that "The universal nature of human
rights is beyond question; their protection
and promotion are the duty of all States, regard¬
less of their political, economic or cultural
systems."
The San José Declaration (see page 43) fol¬
lowed a middle path when it stated: "Reaf¬
firming that our countries represent a broad
grouping of nations sharing common roots
within a rich cultural heritage based on a com¬
bination of various peoples, religions and races,
and that our roots unite us in the search for col¬
lective solutions to present problems	"
The Declaration of Asian non-governmental
organizations, also made at Bangkok, put for¬
ward another possibility of reconciliation: "We
can learn from different cultures in a pluralistic
perspective and draw lessons from the humanity
of these cultures to deepen respect for human
rights. . . . Universal human rights standards
are rooted in many cultures. . . . While advo¬
cating cultural pluralism, those cultural practices
which derogate from universally accepted
human rights, including women's rights, must
not be tolerated	"
Right through the preparatory process, this
question dominated the debate, both of Member
States and non-governmental organizations.
Notably the Western European and Others Group
hoped for a strong reaffirmation of universal
values as enshrined in the Universal Declaration.
Failure to reaffirm these values would have implied
that the World Conference had not succeeded in
one of its primary objectives to enhance and
strengthen the United Nations human rights pro¬
gramme, and to move human rights to the centre
stage of all United Nations activities.
I was convinced that a satisfactory negotiated
outcome of the paragraph on universality would
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
" IS" ^-r^w^U^MB
!
W«
..>>>
V->~»<lrvlT.
¡BÏRM
ï-r" -, '-.--.- ri
1 i '
facilitate a breakthrough in the final document
of the Conference (see page 40). Accordingly, in
the working paper prepared by the Secretariat
containing elements for inclusion in the draft
final document, a compromise formulation was
included as follows: "All human rights are uni¬
versal, indivisible and interdependent. The uni¬
versality of civil, cultural, economic, political and
social rights requires that every state throughout
the world recognize, protect, respect and pro¬
mote internationally recognized human rights
standards, whatever the state's level of economic
or political development. Regional and national
specificities must contribute to the strength¬
ening of the universality of human rights. The
exercise of any human right must not be denied
because the full enjoyment of other rights has
not been achieved. It is the duty of states, regard¬
less of their political, economic and cultural
systems, to promote and protect all human
rights and fundamental freedoms."
However, despite many informal consulta¬
tions, the paragraph remained in square brackets.
The principal difficulties experienced by the
Western Group was the insistence by the Asian
Group that all human rights are interrelated
and interdependent and that regional and
national specificities must be taken into account
to strengthen the universality of human rights.
For this reason, as Secretary-General of the
World Conference, I convened consultations
at ambassadorial level to consider, inter alia,
consensual language on this question.
This was, in fact, one of the first paragraphs
to be adopted by consensus in the Drafting
Committee in Vienna. The formulation con¬
tained in paragraph 5 of the Vienna Declara¬
tion is positive and forward-looking. It reads as
Ina Zimbabwe village, a
member of an itinerant
volunteer team of human
rights campaigners
explains to farmers their
basic rights.
Ina remote village of
Yunnan, southern China, a
woman belonging to the
Hani minority is an object
of curiosity to the Han-
majority villagers.
follows: "All human rights are universal, indi¬
visible and interdependent and interrelated. The
international community must treat human
rights globally in a fair and equal manner, on the
same footing, and with the same emphasis. While
the significance of national and regional par¬
ticularities and various historical, cultural and
religious backgrounds must be borne in mind,
it is the duty of States, regardless of their polit¬
ical, economic and cultural systems, to promote
and protect all human rights and fundamental
freedoms."
The relative ease with which this formulation
was accepted in a spirit of compromise demon¬
strates once again my conviction that all issues
of human rights, when addressed with compas¬
sion and understanding ultimately result in a
global consensus.
I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
NGOs: thefight to be heard
by Sophie Bessis
The non-governmental organizations were a force to be reckoned with at Vienna
12
SOPHIE BESSIS,
who has Tunisian and French
nationality, is a historian and
journalist. A contributor to
several French newspapers and
magazines, she has written
mainly on the economic
problems of the Third World,
development problems and
the Maghreb. Among her
recent publications are
Les enfants du Sahel
(L'Harmattan, Paris, 1 992) and,
with Souhayr Belhassen,
Femmes du Maghreb, l'enjeu
0--C. Lattes, Paris, 1992).
INTERNATIONAL conferences are not what
they used to be. The atmosphere in which
they once used to meet, with diplomats
coming together to settle the affairs of the world
away from prying eyes, is a thing of the past. The
veterans of past UN jamborees who met at the
World Conference on Human Rights had to
reconcile themselves to rubbing shoulders with
new players they were not used to consorting
with.
Dishevelled demonstrators carrying plac¬
ards daily crowded the forecourt of the Austria
Center, venue of the conference, to defend the
rights of those we never hear about: yellow-
robed Buddhist priests demanding the right to
practise their religion; American Indians in
colourful headdresses proclaiming their exis¬
tence to the world; women from every land
demanding at last to be treated like human
beings; associations of street-children; peasants,
Kurds, Bosnians the whole of humanity in its
richness and variety had foregathered for the
occasion in the Austrian capital.
The presence en masse of all kinds of non¬
governmental organizations (NGOs) on the
very spot where an official conference was taking
place not only lent colour to the occasion but
marked a new era in the history of the United
Nations and international relations. For non¬
governmental organizations to take part in meet¬
ings of this kind is of course nothing new: they
had earlier made their voices heard loud and
clear at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro in
June 1992. There, however, nearly twenty-five
miles separated the official conference from the
NGOs' forum. In Vienna, government repre¬
sentatives and the spokespersons of ordinary
citizens worked in the same building. This jux¬
taposition is surely more than just a coinci¬
dence: it may even mean that from now on
nothing can be done without the latter.
Never before' had organizations representing
civil society been so closely associated with the
preparations for a world conference. They were
present at all the preliminary regional sessions,
and managed to voice the views of the walk-on
players who are all too often muzzled. On the tra¬
ditional "Prepcoms", the preparatory commis¬
sions set up to compile the working papers, they
fought tooth and nail for their existence to be rec¬
ognized and for the right to speak. At Vienna they
at last showed their determination to stop being
bit-part players and to have real speaking parts in
discussions with government representatives.
A voice for civil society
The theme of human rights certainly lent itself
thereto better than any other, given that for
decades the only protests against the high-hand¬
edness of dictatorial regimes and the hypocrisy
of the old democracies, always ready to point the
finger at their enemies and connive at the turpi¬
tude of their allies, had come from associations
such as national human rights leagues and inter¬
national organizations campaigning against the
systematic violation of human rights.
If they had decided to exclude them, the
organizers would have disqualified themselves
in the eyes of world public opinion at the outset.
They therefore opted to let them join in their
proceedings, over the objections of those most
strongly opposed to their participation.
This massive presence of NGOs at Vienna
was certainly not the outcome of a consensus
among the UN Member States, many of whom
clashed with all comers in an attempt to deny the
podium to those who had come to denounce
dictatorships and massacres, pinpoint those
responsible and secure a hearing for their myriad
victims. So there were battles first in the "Prep¬
coms" and then at Vienna itself, where much of
the discussion consisted of wrangling about the
place to be allotted to the NGOs. Between their
demands and the obstacles erected by certain
states that carry weight in the South, the Con¬
ference secretariat sought tirelessly to reach
compromises in their favour.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
End of the century (1993),
sculpture in Carrara
marble by the Argentine
artist Eugenia Wolfowicz.
Disregarding all the commotion at the Con¬
ference about the propriety of their attending the
drafting committee for the final declaration, or
how many seats they should have in the main
conference room, we can now gauge the size of
their achievement and the extent of their influ¬
ence on the document that came out of the
Vienna meeting.
They certainly did not get all they were after,
and some of them, such as Amnesty Interna¬
tional, justifiably criticized the vagueness of the
UN discussions, the absence of forthright con¬
demnations, and the lack of concrete decisions
such as would help the champions of human
rights to campaign more effectively.
The new international landscape
Their presence nevertheless had a considerable
impact. By pulling the official delegates up every
time the discussions showed signs of drifting off
into party-political byways, they reduced
though they could not eliminate the danger of
the human rights theme being used as a means
for other ends. By attacking dictatorships and
refusing to underwrite authoritarian regimes 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Femme (1992),
mixed media. Sculpture by
Anne Delfieu.
on the pretext of development needs, the NGOs
of the South showed that the South is anything
but monolithic.
This was perhaps one of the most striking
revelations to come out of Vienna. It had of
course been known for some years that the so-
called Third World had changed, but it is now
clear for all to see that it is split two ways
between the champions of authoritarianism
who defend their respective regimes on grounds
of religious or cultural identity or economic
constraints and the proponents of the idea of
democracy, which for them is a universal.
Many discussions were of course coloured
by the North-South divisions, but contrary to
expectations they did not set the agenda of a con¬
ference that had other issues on its mind. The
most dictatorial states of the South had to con¬
tend not only with the old democracies of the
North but also with the representatives of their
own societies, who came to tell the world that,
to put it mildly, they did not share their rulers'
hostility to the idea of human rights.
Having by their continual presence com¬
pelled the participating states to take sides with
or against them, the NGOs also showed that
ways of exercising power are tending to diver¬
sify in the South. While most representatives
from Asia and the Arab Muslim world sought to
justify the old authoritarian attitudes, the bulk
of African and South American states seem to
have swung over, at least in words, to the side of
the champions of democracy.
The NGOs thus emerged as both the agents
and the exponents of the new divisions that are
redrawing the international political landscape.
Their fierce struggle for unequivocal acceptance
of the proposition that human rights are uni¬
versal and indivisible overcame the resistance of
those defending special interests, and the col¬
lective pressure exerted in the drafting com¬
mittee ensured that on this point at least the
final document was clear enough.
14
A watchdog role
As to their role, this document mentions their
contribution to the discussion, acclaims their
courage and their work on the ground, and calls
on governments to collaborate with them more
closely. Some people sneered at what they saw
here as a belated tribute paid by vice to virtue, but
behind the careful wording, calculated, in accor¬
dance with UN practice, to offend no-one, may
be seen an implicit recognition that citizens' orga¬
nizations have a right to exercise a watchdog role
in regard to the behaviour of governments.
This is a crucial matter, and the NGOs are
quite determined to fight in future for this right
to be explicitly recognized, for their entrance
upon the UN scene albeit for the moment
only in a modest capacity also means that gov¬
ernments have begun to lose their monopoly of
the right to lay down the law, and that having
half-opened the door to them the UN will have
difficulty in shutting it again. Although at Vienna
the NGOs did not take part directly in the
drafting of the final declaration, there seems
little doubt that at future international confer¬
ences they will try, and probably succeed, in
storming other bastions.
One last and not inconsiderable result of
their presence in hundreds in the Austrian cap¬
ital is that the international community, having
resigned itself to granting observer status at the
UN Economic and Social Council to some 20D
of the major transnational NGOs such as the
International Commission ofJurists, the Inter¬
national Human Rights Federation and
Amnesty International, can no longer ignore
the existence and the energy of thousands of
regional, national and local associations deter¬
mined to press their case.
The representatives of oppressed minori¬
ties, of women, and of all those living on the
fringes of society played an active part in the
NGOs' Forum which met for three days before
the opening of the official conference, and by
main force gained the right to be present thereat.
The Conference thus brought to light the extra¬
ordinary variety of citizens' movements, and
the diversity of their campaigns. The word
"cacophony" was applied to them, and it is true
that the Forum was the scene of some Homeric
battles, but this actually represents an emerging
realignment in the world of the NGOs. Their
success in bursting on to the international stage
is leading to a distribution of tasks among them¬
selves, a development that some NGOs have
already taken into account.
Many NGOs were disappointed at the
meagre results of a conference that went no fur¬
ther than restating a few principles, without
providing the necessary clout to implement
them. They all proclaimed that their struggles
would not slacken until the rule of law pre¬
vailed over brute force. They are under no illu¬
sions: they know that hard battles have still to be
fought. In gradually taking by storm the UN
fortress, some bastions of which they managed
to conquer at Vienna, they hope above all that
their members will no longer suffer in silence,
and that the United Nations will respond to
their demands less timidly than in the past.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
One and indivisible
The dangers ofan à la carte approach to human rights by Antoine Bernard
/Xbove, meeting of
women in Ghana to discuss
the development of their
village.
SINCE the adoption in 1948 of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights, the principle
of the indivisibility of the rights of the indi¬
vidual has become, along with the principle of
universality, the pivot of the present interna¬
tional system for the protection of such rights.
Indivisibility means that the corpus of inter¬
national standards forms a coherent whole, of
which the different parts are indissociable in
their conception and their application.
Its raison d'être is, as set forth in Article 28
of the Declaration, that: "Everyone is entitled to
a social and international order in which the
rights and freedoms set forth in this Declaration
can be fully realized".
Indivisibility means first and foremost a
refusal to accept the view that certain rights
should take precedence over others, a view that
would allow the most pernicious ideologies,
whether spiritual or temporal, to go about their
abject business. It also insists that there can be
neither development without democracy nor
democracy without development. It is a way
of preventing human rights from becoming an
empty shell, leaving people without the eco¬
nomic, social, cultural, civil and political means
to enable them to live in dignity.
Although the principle of indivisibility has
been constantly reaffirmed by the successive
resolutions and other international instruments
adopted by UN bodies over a period of decades,
it has never been given a more precise definition
in international law.
The obvious explanation for this lack of pre¬
cision is to be found in the divergences, within
a pluralistic, imbalanced and even profoundly
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
antagonistic international society, in the political,
economic and cultural interests for which the
principle of indivisibility is both the instrument
and the point at issue.
The World Conference on Human Rights
confirmed that this is the case, since conflicts of
interests arose both during the two years of its
preparation and over its final declaration, which
turned out to be a lukewarm document. The
principle of the indivisibility of individual rights
was reaffirmed, but in terms that leave scope for
the restrictive interpretations of those who
uphold so-called "religious and cultural rela¬
tivism". On the other hand, the sanction given
to the right to development provides grounds for
hoping that the United Nations family will take
a greater interest in the protection of economic
and social rights.
A single human community
Some governments launched an out-and-out
offensive against the indivisibility principle,
seeing the opening of Pandora's box in Vienna
as an excellent opportunity to justify supposedly
divinely inspired practices and to release them¬
selves from the obligation to respect interna¬
tional principles that are decidedly too much of
a hindrance to their repressive activities.
On the opening day of the conference, UN
Secretary-General Boutros Boutros Ghali in fact
presented the double issue of indivisibility and
cultural diversity as being the guest of honour at
the conference and tried, with a diplomatic nod
in that direction, to get round the obstacle. "While
human rights are common to all members of the
international community," he explained, "and
each member of that community recognizes him¬
self in them, each cultural epoch has its own spe¬
cial way of helping to implement them."
In any case, he continued, "human rights ... are
not the lowest common denominator among all
nations, but rather what I should like to describe
as the 'irreducible human element', in other words,
the quintessential values through which we affirm
together that we are a single human community."
This was not a view shared by some gov¬
ernments of the South, which were unenthusi-
astic about accepting the existence of universal
standards for the protection of human rights.
These governments had some success at Vienna,
starting with the reservations expressed
regarding the principles of the indivisibility and
universality of human rights. The elimination of
the condemnation of religious extremism that
had featured in the draft of the final declaration
was another victory for them.
Although consensus was finally reached on
the reaffirmation of the principle of indivisi¬
bility, its ambiguity threatens to legitimize atti¬
tudes that are sometimes far removed from the
universal culture of human rights, and in par-
Workers on a Rwanda
tea plantation wait to
receive their pay.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
ticular to give surreptitious endorsement to so-
called "cultural relativism".
Development
and solidarity
Respect for economic and social rights was
another subject at the heart of the debate on
the indivisibility of human rights.
Three years after the fall of the Berlin Wall,
the Conference provided the countries of the
South with an opportunity to raise their voices
in some cases not without ulterior motives to
demand that the international system direct its
attention first and foremost to economic and
social rights.
The reticence displayed by many Western
countries in this regard in the run-up to the
Conference suggested that a North-South con¬
frontation might be on the cards. The demand
made by some countries of the North for the
indivisible application of human rights indeed
appears hypocritical to the nations of the South,
so long as the North remains indifferent to the
huge problems caused by the pauperization of
80 per cent of the planet.
By insisting on the indivisibility of human
rights without practising solidarity as a veri¬
table duty, the Western powers ultimately make
themselves accomplices of austerity policies that
have dramatic social consequences and result
in repressive regimes remaining in power.
Furthermore, the emergence of counter¬
vailing forces such as the many human rights
organizations that have sprung up in the South
in recent years is often like the precipitate
introduction of a multi-party system no more
than window dressing hiding rampant corrup¬
tion among the political authorities.
In this context, the confirmation at Vienna of
the right to development as a "universal and
inalienable" human right (paragraph 10 of Sec¬
tion I of the Declaration) is evidence of a new
awareness on the part of the Western countries,
the United States in particular, since this was the
first time they had recognized such a right. It in
any case represents a step forward that must
now be given substance.
To that end, it is imperative that several con¬
ditions be met: the rights of the individual must
be scrupulously respected in the context of mul¬
tilateral and bilateral aid; the debt crisis must be
resolved; the right to a healthy environment
must be respected; and a struggle must be waged
against corruption and the fraudulent self-
enrichment of those in power. In other words,
the human being must be put back at the centre
of the development process.
On the level of principles, the Vienna Dec¬
laration proclaims democracy, development and
respect for human rights to be "interdependent
and mutually reinforcing" (paragraph 8). It also
stipulates that, in this context, "the lack of devel¬
opment may not be invoked to justify the
abridgement of internationally recognized
human rights" (paragraph 10).
At the same time the Declaration calls upon
the international community "to help alleviate the
external debt burden of developing countries"
(paragraph 12). It also reaffirms that "the least
developed countries committed to the process of
democratization and economic reforms, many of
which are in Africa, should be supported" (para¬
graph 9), and it comes down against strings-
attached development aid (". . . the promotion and
protection of human rights . . . should be universal
and conducted without conditions attached",
paragraph 8).
Everyone was pleased that a consensus was
reached on all these points and that the Vienna
Conference therefore did not give rise to the
North-South clash that the run-up had sug¬
gested might happen. .
Let us not delude ourselves, however: each
interest group got what it wanted out of the Con¬
ference, and only the exhaustive application of
itsin fact very modest Programme of Action
will make it possible to tell whether it marks the
start of a convergence of political wills in favour
of respect for the right to development as a human
right indissociable from the rest.
Street scene in Portugal,
1 974, when the "Junta of
National Salvation"
came to power and put an
end to the regime founded
by Antonio de Oliveira
Salazar.
ANTOINE BERNARD,
of France, is executive
secretary of the International
Federation of Human Rights,
an international non¬
governmental organization
which has consultative status
with the United Nations,
Unesco and the Council of
Europe, and observer status
with the African Commission
on Human and Peoples' Rights.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
lortrait of Niccolo
Machiavelli (detail) by
Santidi Tito (1536-1603).
Free speechdemocracy 's
by Helen Darbishire
Censorship as a threat to human rights
18
THE ancients, especially the Greeks and the
Romans of the early Republic, wrote
choice phrases in defence of the right to
freedom of expression. Demosthenes, for
example, declared that no greater calamity could
befall a people than "the privation of free
speech". But there is no evidence that, in even
Greece's most libertarian periods, opinions
could be expressed verbally or written with
impunity. Plato relates how Socrates was pun¬
ished by the freedom-loving Athenians for the
crime of subversive utterances. And Plato him¬
self was an exponent of censorship. "The poet
shall compose nothing contrary to the ideas of
the lawful, or just, or beautiful, or good, which
are allowed in the state," he wrote. "Nor shall he
be permitted to show his compositions to any
private individual, until he shall have shown
them to the appointed censors and guardians of
the law, and they are satisfied with them."
Nevertheless, the fundamental nature of
freedom of expression has been recognized by
many societies throughout the ages. For
instance, a fifteenth-century Kazakh law of the
Steppes stated that you may chop off a man's
head but you may not cut out his tongue. Such
a philosophy is perhaps not so far removed
from an English pamphleteer's cri de coeur of
1721 that "Where a man cannot call his tongue
his own, he can scarce call anything his own."
Censorship, including self-censorship, was
often regarded as an acceptable part of the
process of free speech rather than its enemy.
Machiavelli epitomized the attitudes of the
Renaissance when he qualified the right of every
man to "think all things, speak all things, write
all things", by asserting that Princes should be
talked of with "reserve and respect". And even
John Milton, who in 1644 thundered in his
acclaimed Areopagitica, "Give me liberty to
know, to utter and to argue freely according to
conscience, above all liberties", became
Cromwell's official censor.
It was in the Enlightenment of the eigh¬
teenth century that tolerance, based on the idea
that there is no such thing as an absolute truth,
began to take hold. This gave rise to a belief in
liberty and is best embodied in Voltaire's famous
statement "I disapprove of what you say but I
will defend to the death your right to say it."
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Constitutional changes introducing new
ideas of personal liberty often followed histor¬
ical discontinuities such as civil wars or revolu¬
tions. In 1688, the year of the "glorious" revo¬
lution, the British parliament had enacted a "Bill
of Rights" and the process reached its climax at
the end of the eighteenth century, with the rebel¬
lion of Britain's American colonies and the
French Revolution. In each case, the successful
rebels saw merit in enshrining in one or more
great texts the Declaration of Independence
and the Bill of Rights in America, the Declara¬
tion of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen in
France values which had inspired them in the
struggle against their respective anciens régimes.
These texts showed a significant evolution in
political philosophy. For the first time they set
forth principles recognizable today as proposi¬
tions of modern human rights law. The rights,
including that of expression, were described as
freedoms: they fell beyond the scope of regula¬
tion or interference by the state, whether
through the enactment of law or otherwise.
Many subsequent constitutions were modelled
on these principles.
The role of technology
The battle for freedom of expression and infor¬
mation, unlike that for other rights, has been as
closely tied to technological developments as to
cultural changes developments which pro-
Young resistance
fighters in Prague at the
time of the invasion of
Czechoslovakia by
Warsaw Pact troops in
August 1968.
voked censorship as often as they advanced the
cause of freedom. The invention of the printing
press by Johann Gutenberg in Germany in 1440
immediately brought restrictions on dissemina¬
tion of ideas in written form. In the English-
speaking world it was not until about 1700 that
the concept of a right to print had been estab¬
lished, and newspaper editors fought for another
century to gain acceptance of the right to criticize.
A second revolution in communications began
in the mid-nineteenth century with the invention
of the telegraph and the electrification of com¬
munications which greatly increased the flow of
information and within a few years spawned the
first news agency (Associated Press in the United
States). This revolution has continued during the
twentieth century with the spread of radio and
television, facsimile machines, computers and
satellites. Through the airwaves and down tele¬
phone lines, individuals now have greater freedom
than ever before to send and receive ideas and
information. But at the same time there are greater
possibilities for sophisticated control and manip¬
ulation of information.
State control of the mass media for war-mon-
gering and racial propagandizing was a feature of
the genocide and other massive human rights vio¬
lations committed during the Second World War.
In the aftermath of the war, freedom of expression
was recognized by the countries represented at the
founding of the United Nations as one of the
fundamental democratic values necessary for the
peaceful coexistence of nations. Thus it was given
the highest status in the 1948 Universal Declara¬
tion of Human Rights by being included in the
preamble as one of the four essential freedoms:
"human beings shall enjoy freedom of speech and
belief and freedom from fear and want." It is also
set forth in Article 19 of the Declaration which
states: "Everyone has the right to freedom of
opinion and expression; this right includes freedom
to hold opinions without interference and to seek,
receive and impart information and ideas through
any media regardless of frontiers."
Expression:
indivisible from other rights
Freedom of expression is a fundamental right
which is indivisible from other human rights. In
other words it is a right which is necessary for
the enjoyment and protection of other rights.
Without freedom of expression and access to
information one cannot participate in national
debate about government economic policies or
gain the information vital to protect one's health;
without free speech one cannot speak out against 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
violations such as torture, disappearances and
extra-judicial executions.
At its most extreme, censorship threatens the
right to life. Sometimes this is a direct threat when
murder is used as a sanction against those who
express their opinions. But there are many other
ways in which censorship can kill. Millions of
deaths from starvation have been linked to delib¬
erate concealment of information. Denied a voice
by repressive governments, the starving could
not cry out to the world; deprived of information,
the international community could not respond to
their plight in adequate time to save lives. By con¬
trast, in countries where a relatively free press
regularly addresses the issue of food shortages,
major famines have not arisen in recent years.
The right to health is also jeopardized by
censorship. In some countries government inter¬
ference with information about Aids, other sex¬
ually transmitted diseases and the benefits of
using condoms is contributing to the sickness
and early deaths of millions.
Protection of the environment is equally
dependent on freedom of information and expres¬
sion. Without information about environmental
damage, such as the scale of rainforest depletion
or toxic waste deposits, it is impossible to mount
effective campaigns in defence of our natural
heritage. Environmental protesters are often
silenced, censored or even murdered.
There is now a widespread recognition that
respect for civil and political rights is crucial to sus¬
tainable development and the advance of eco¬
nomic, social and cultural rights. Arguments by
some governments that freedom of expression is
'THE COMMUNALITY OF FREEDOM'
It is freedom of expression that guarantees the rights of individuals,
minorities, the collective and the community. Any suggestion that
freedom of expression is a luxury of the West insults the historic
struggles of individuals and communities all over the world for the dig¬
nity and well-being of their kind, for social fulfilment, equality of
opportunity, equitable sharing of resources, access to shelter, nour¬
ishment and health. Such claims are an attempt to diminish our
humanity, to reduce us to marginal existence even within our own
societies. It is a clear vote for the party of Power against the com-
munality of Freedom.
Wole Soyinka
Nigerian writer
Nobel laureate in literature
a luxury to be granted once development has been
achieved have been exposed for what they are:
pretexts for retaining power and denying democ¬
racy. This recognition has yet to be translated
into real support for the development of infor¬
mation systems: the development aid budgets of
industrialized countries give no more than 0.4
per cent to information and communication.
Duties and responsibilities
Freedom of expression is a universal right. Uni¬
versality is often challenged by countries whose
system of government is based on adherence
Opposite page,
aborigines demonstrating
on the occasion of the
bicentenary ( 1 988) of the
British presence in
Australia.
Below, Sandinistas
demonstrating in Managua
(Nicaragua) after their
party's defeat at the polls.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
to one particular religion or ideology, or which
prefer to govern without having to take into
account the will of the people. In such countries
free speech, particularly for those whose opin¬
ions run counter to the dominant ideology, is the
first right to be curtailed.
Indivisible, universal and fundamental,
freedom of expression is not, however, an absolute
right. This means that unlike the rights to be
free from torture, summary execution or pro¬
longed arbitrary detention the right to freedom
of expression may be subjected to restrictions in
certain narrowly defined circumstances. The Inter¬
national Covenant on Civil and Political Rights
states that freedom of opinion is absolute and
may not be interfered with, but freedom of expres¬
sion and information "carries with it special duties
and responsibilities. It may therefore be subject to
certain restrictions, but these shall only be such as
are provided by law and are necessary:
a) For respect of the rights of others;
b) For the protection of national security
or of public order {ordre public), or of public
health or morals."
These conditions may appear to be suitably
narrow, but in the words of a 1992 UN report on
freedom of opinion and expression: "History
teaches that restrictions have an unfortunate
tendency to spread beyond the limits within
which they were originally conceived." The
task of defending individuals against govern¬
ments who overstep the mark, or who flout
international law completely, falls largely upon
non-governmental organizations (NGOs).
In 1986 a new international NGO was
founded with a mandate to defend victims of
censorship and to promote freedom of expres¬
sion. Taking its name from the relevant article of
the Universal Declaration, ARTICLE 19, the
International Centre Against Censorship, works
to oppose both the practice of censorship and the
laws which allow it to be imposed. One can
campaign for the release of an individual or for
the unbanning of a newspaper, but the threat of
future censorship remains as long as the laws
which allowed these actions to take place remain.
New trends in censorship
Campaigning for freedom of expression requires
alertness to new forms of censorship, new trends
in government repression. A recent example of this
is the rise in sedition cases in several countries of
HELEN DARBISHIRE,
of the United Kingdom, is
Campaigns Officer for
ARTICLE 19, the International
Centre against Censorship,
based in London. She is
responsible for designing and
implementing campaigns
against violations of the right
to freedom of expression at a
national and international level. 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
the South which, often under international pres¬
sure, have been forced towards multi-party sys¬
tems of government and to respect the rule of
law. Increased use of criminal law to restrict
freedom of expression, such as by charging jour¬
nalists and opposition politicians with sedition, is
a clear indication of the lack of commitment of
many entrenched regimes to permit true democ¬
racy to take root. This trend is often paralleled by
informal measures, including the use of hit squads
to attack and intimidate government critics.
Another area which poses complex problems
for anti-censorship organizations is the continuing
rise of fundamentalism in many religions. The
threat which fundamentalism poses to freedom of
expression takes many forms, from political
expression to the rights of women, including the
right of access to jobs, to participate in the cultural
and political life of their societies and to dress as
they choose. But at the same time this threat must
not be used to justify censorship in the name of the
war against fundamentalism.
Gathering information about abuses of
freedom of expression has been greatly aided by
the creation in 1992 of an electronic network
linking freedom of expression groups around
the world. The International Freedom of Expres¬
sion eXchange (IFEX), based in Toronto (Canada),
uses electronic mail to disseminate information
about censorship incidents often within hours,
enabling rapid and co-ordinated protest actions.
It is a clear example of information technology
being used as a tool for for good in the fight
against censorship.
Two recent developments demonstrate an
increasing recognition of the importance of the
UNESCO AND THE DEFENCE
OF FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION
UNESCO is closely involved in programmes to promote the growth of
communication systems in developing countries. In 1991 it held a
conference in Namibia which brought together journalists from across
the continent to discuss the legal and economic conditions necessary
for an independent and pluralistic press. The "Windhoek Declara¬
tion" adopted by this conference has rapidly become a standard text for
identifying the needs of media in developing countries.
A follow-up conference in Kazakhstan in 1992 brought together
print and broadcast journalists from across Asia from Turkey to
Fiji. The "Alma Ata Declaration" resoundingly endorsed the principles
of Windhoek and restated the belief that the development of free and
independent means of expression is vital to the building of democracy.
The United Nations has declared 3 May the anniversary of the
Windhoek Declaration as International Press Freedom Day. It is an
annual reminder of the central role the media play in promoting and
protecting other human rights.
right to freedom of expression. One is the
appointment by the UN in 1993 of a Special
Rapporteur on Freedom of Expression whose
mandate includes receiving complaints about
violations from individuals and NGOs and
raising these with the governments involved. The
other is the declaration by the UN of 3 May each
year as International Press Freedom Day.
22
Recording studio of Radio
Pachamama, an Aymara
broadcasting station in La
Paz (Bolivia).
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
mm
THE UNESCO COURIER -MARCH 1994
v > BSí¡u^5g^
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
In Chinese mythology, heaven is
represented as a group of rocky
islands where the immortals lead
a blissful existence, and in many
other traditions in India, Cam¬
bodia, lapan, Ireland and Britain,
among the Celts and the ancient
Greeks islands were regarded as
paradise. In his Works and Days,
Hesiod wrote: "There, on the Islands
of the Blessed, by the edge of the tur
bulent depths of the Ocean, with
carefree hearts live the heroes
favoured by fortune, for whom the
fertile earth thrice yearlybrings forth
sweet and abundant harvests."
Although islands are still thought
of as ideal places to spend a holiday,
the reality is often less idyllic. In 1920,
the League of Nations refused to
accept as members what it referred
to as the "Lilliputian" states, most of
Above, phosphate mining
on the island of Nauru
in the Pacific.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
SMALL ISLANDS: DREAMS Al REALIT
Windmills at
Algaida in
Majorca, the
largest of the
Balearic Islands
(Spain).
which were islands. Seventy-two
years later, at the United Nations
World Conference on Environment
and Development in Rio de laneiro,
islands were in the forefront of atten¬
tion and were the subject of many
studies, meetings and development
projects. As early as 1973, Unesco
organized its first meeting ofexperts
on island ecosystems, in the frame¬
work of its Man and the Biosphere
(MAB) programme. In 1989, it helped
to set up a nongovernmental orga¬
nization, the International Scientific
Council for Island Development
(INSULA), whose aim is to promote
the sustainable development of
small islands all over the world.
WHAT IS A "SMALL" ISLAND?
Various attempts have been made
to answer the question, byno means
an easy one, as to what "small"
means in this context. MAB con¬
siders an island small when its area
is less than 10,000 sq. km. and its
population less than 500,000, but all
small islands, wherever they may be
and whether they are independent or
linked in some form of association
with larger countries, have to deal
with the same issues: water, energy,
fisheries, agriculture, the manage¬
ment of coastal zones, waste dis¬
posal, forestry, wildlife and tourism.
Their very isolation is at the root of
24
their problems limited sources of
revenue, insufficient exports or
shortage of raw materials. While
technological progress may bring
prosperity, it can also contribute to
their marginalization. Mauritius, for
instance, which was an ideal port of
call for sailing ships plying between
Europe and Asia until the nineteenth
century, lost its privileged status with
the opening of the Suez Canal and
more especially with the advent ofair
travel, although it was later able to
find alternative sources of develop¬
ment. When landing strips are not
big enough for jet aircraft and there
are no deepwater harbours for
today's cargo vessels, it becomes
impossible for small islands to pro¬
cure the heavy capital goods needed
for the major infrastructure projects
that will draw in business. Some
islands are so small that they lack
the institutions to train their work
force, the materials needed by
industry, the possibility of negoti¬
ating political or trade agreements or
the means to send representatives
to defend their interests in interna¬
tional forums. On the other hand,
some isolated territories, overlooked
by the mass media, are managing to
preserve their cultural identity and
their natural environment. Island
status nevertheless calls for a spe¬
cific approach fully justifying the
attention now being given to it.
All the experts agree that the
major problem facing small islands,
especially those in the Mediter¬
ranean whose population may
double in the tourist season, is that of
fresh water supplies and waste dis¬
posal. Very few ofthem have lakes or
permanentwatercourses. Pockets of
fresh water (also known as Ghyben-
Herzberg lenses) provide only lim¬
ited resources. The Mediterranean
island ofMalta, to take one example,
consists of a slab of porous lime¬
stone and its groundwater runs off
into the sea. As the long dry season
coincides with the tourist season,
around ten million cubic metres of
sea water peryear have to be treated
by means of extremely expensive
desalination plants. The islands of
Elba (Italy) and Nueva Tabarca
(Spain) are linked to mainland water-
supply systems by undersea
pipelines (some offshore islands
receive electricity via underwater
power cables), while some of the
small Greek islands are supplied by
tankers. Louis Brigand, ofthe Institut
Français de Géo-architecture, writes
in Les îles en Méditerranée ("The
Mediterranean islands"), one of a
series of booklets covering various
aspects of the "Blue Plan" (a project
setting out different scenarios for
the future of the Mediterranean) that
the characteristics ofsmaller islands
are such that they call for an orig¬
inal energy policy, their small popu¬
lations and limited requirements
inclining them towards a varied mix
of alternative energy resources
wind power for pumping up
groundwater, solar energy, geo-
thermal energy in the case of vol¬
canic islands, imported fossil fuels,
wood or biogas and he adds that
ability to solve the problem ofwater
and power supplies will be a decisive
factor for the future in terms both of
development and of environment.
DISASTROUS DEFORESTATION
The policies adopted have not,
unfortunately, always been wise
ones. The overuse oftimber for fire¬
wood or for boat-building and wood¬
land clearance for farming has often
resulted in disastrous deforestation,
as has happened on Easter Island
and in Haiti and the Cape Verde
islands, leaving the denuded land a
prey to erosion. Western Samoa nev¬
ertheless recently took the risky step
ofselling off timber extraction rights
to foreign interests. Moreover,
though vegetation conserves water
and also protects the soil, some
deep-rooting crops such as the
coconut palm can exhaust ground¬
water, and that at a time when copra,
like cane sugar, is harder and harder
to sell. These two so-called cash
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Quayside scene
in Male, main
island and
capital of the
Maldives
archipelago
(Indian Ocean).
crops have often, in the tropics, taken
the place offood crops, to the detri¬
ment of the inhabitants' food sup¬
plies. An extreme case of this phe¬
nomenon is provided by Sào Tomé
and Principe, where it was long for¬
bidden to grow anything but cacao.
Meanwhile, the inhabitants of the
Pacific island ofNauru have literally
destroyed their island by the overex-
traction ofphosphate; having made
their fortunes, they now have to find
somewhere else to live, but where?
lamaicans spend a good part of their
income on buying their national
dish, cod a fish caught in cold
waters. There are rich fishing
grounds around Kiribati, but the gov¬
ernment has leased the fishing rights
to Russia, while the local fishermen
pay a fortune for tinned sardines!
KIRIBATI, A TV-FREE ZONE
This archipelago, one of the
islands ofwhich (Christmas Island)
was used by Britain and the United
States for nuclear tests from 1945
to 1948, was offered a complete tele¬
vision network in exchange for the
right to dump nuclear waste in its
territorial waters . . . but is still
luckily without television. The dis
posal of household garbage and
industrial waste, imported or oth¬
erwise, is a serious problem for
islands. Shortage of space means
that sewers and disposal sites are
often too near to drinking-water
reservoirs. Fertilizers, pesticides and
hydrocarbons infiltrate coral atolls
and limestone, and can also conta¬
minate coastal waters. The situa¬
tion is even worse when population
density is increased by an influx of
tourists. But who can resist the lure
of foreign-currency income from
holidaymakers looking for a change
of scenery? Many islands have suf¬
fered the consequences.
Is there any way of preventing
coastlines from being smothered in
concrete, ofsafeguarding the islands'
identities, of preserving the true
worth of local cultures and pre¬
venting the indigenous population
from being drawn into a master-ser¬
vant relationship with the tourists?
The solution entails the protection of
sites and the promotion of cultural
tourism and ecotourism. At its
Member States' request, Unesco has
given biosphere reserve status to a
number of islands, including Lan-
zarote (Canaries), the Colón (Gala¬
pagos) Archipelago, the Taiaro atoll
(French Polynesia), Hawaii, and
Yakushima (japan). The Galapagos
Islands have also been placed on the
World Heritage List. The Darwin
Foundation, which has been set up
there, is making efforts to protect
the islands' flora and fauna, and
tourism is strictly regulated so as not
to disturb the native wildlife.
Could all these positive measures
encouraged by Unesco nevertheless
be cancelled out by the global
warming that is forecast by some cli-
matologists? Will low-lying islands
be engulfed as the ice-caps melt?
Although the global warming
hypothesis is not without its critics,
the Government of the Maldives has
already taken preventive measures,
putting down concrete blocks and
building concrete sea walls to protect
the most exposed parts of the coast¬
line. Let us hope the international
communitywill rally to the defence
of islands, so that they may remain
the abode of the blessed.
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD-Unesco
training programmeforAfrican
news-agencyjournalists.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
0 R L
i
wttlMWMWmHf^ mm
A HAPPY MARRIAGE IN THE TILAPIA FAMILY
Tilapias, a species of freshwater fish orginating from
Africa, are now found all over the world. Nicknamed
"water chickens", they are easily fed, grow quickly, are dis¬
ease-resistant and good to eat. The International Centre
for LivingAquatic Resources Management, based in the
Philippines, has set up a genetic improvement pro¬
gramme for the species. As excessive inbreeding among
Asian Tilapia tends to cause degeneration, genetic mate¬
rial is being brought in from Africa for breeding pur¬
poses yet more proof of the need to preserve indige¬
nous breeds and the resources ofbiodiversity.
FLOWER POWER THREATENS
WATER SUPPLIES
The export flower industry has
invaded the agricultural plain
around Funza, a town west of
Bogotá, Colombia, drawing thou¬
sands of people in search of work.
The first flower company moved in
22 years ago, women workers were
hired and living standards improved,
but unfortunately the traditional
crops ofpotatoes, grains and beans
are no longer grown, and the school's
tap ran dry a year and a half ago all
the water is being used for growing
flowers. The authorities have been
promising to pipe water in from
Bogotá for three years, but Funza
has grown so much lately that people
are starting to get worried.
MOZAMBICAN
FARMERS PROTECT THEIR
SEED SUPPLIES
The war that has been raging in
Mozambique for years has pre¬
vented the farmers of the Niassa
province getting hold of imported
seeds. In 1980, a nongovernmental
organization, Crocevia, lent its sup¬
port to the establishment of the
Gabinete de produçao de sementes
do Niassa, which, with the aid of the
Bank ofMozambique, has provided
funding for the farmers. They have
developed local strains well adapted
to the region, some of them not pre¬
viously recorded, which give high
yields without requiring fertilizers. A
26
1 w " J)fl
WmLu ¡ i
P^r __
'
iVt- ** - * -
certification system has been set up
to keep a register of the characteris¬
tics of these strains and to protect
them. Seeds of corn (maize),
sorghum, wheat, manioc, ground¬
nuts, peas and other legumes are
now locally available, eliminating
the need to turn to international
seed suppliers and to use chemical
fertilizers.
OIL SPILLS ARE EXPENSIVE
IN THE UNITED STATES
Under the U.S. Oil Pollution Act of
1990, two oil companies responsible
for separate spills have agreed to
penalties totalling $14.7 million.
Texaco alone faces abill ofmore than
$9 million for the spillage of 5,000
barrels ofoil when a pump exploded
at a refinery near a bay in Wash¬
ington State, while the U.S. Oil and
Refining Company has acknowl¬
edged responsibility for a spill of
more than 14,000 barrels that
occurred during the unloading of a
tanker in Puget Sound, also inWash¬
ington State. The fines, of up to
$1,000 a barrel of oil spilled, go
towards the cost of cleaning-up
operations.
THREATENED BREEDS OF
FARM ANIMALS
A study by the United Nations Food
and Agriculture Organization (FAO)
shows that 1,000 of the 4,000 breeds
of farm animal that were recorded in
a list recently established by the orga¬
nization are under threat of extinc¬
tion. One reason for this erosion of
genetic diversity is that animal
farming is becoming increasingly
intensive and specialized, tending
to give priority to the more produc¬
tive breeds. More than a quarter ofall
breeds of cattle, sheep, pigs and
horses are found in Europe, and
many of them face extinction
because they are economically
uncompetitive. Does this mean
goodbye to the Reggina cattle of
northern Italy, the North Ronaldsay
sheep of the Orkneys and the Yakut
cattle ofSiberian Far North?
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
READERS INTERESTED IN
ISLANDS HAY FIND THE
FOLLOWING INFORMATION
USEFUL:
INSULA, the International Scien¬
tific Council for Island Development,
is an international nongovernmental
Organization bringing together
researchers working in many dif¬
ferent fields, decision-makers and
institutions wishing to contribute to
the economic, social and cultural
advancement of the world's islands.
INSULA encourages technical co¬
operation in everything to do with
the sustainable development of
islands, the exchange of informa¬
tion and pooling of experience
through the publication of a maga¬
zine, INSULA, the International
Journal of Island Affairs, and of
reports, and by organizing confer¬
ences and seminars. Further infor¬
mation may be obtained from Pier
d'Ayala, c/o MAB-Unesco, 1, rue
Miollis, 75015 Paris. Tel. 33 1 45 68 40
56; Fax. 33 140 65 98 97.
THE ARCHIPELAGO PROJECT is
a network of island biosphere
reserves. It is intended as an exten¬
sion of the work done and exchanges
carried out in relation to small
islands as part of Unesco's MAB (Man
and the Biosphere) programme. It
collects data on the reserves con¬
cerned and carries out comparative
studies, with a view to achieving sus¬
tainable development. The founder
members of the network are the
Balearic island of Minorca (Spain),
the Mer d'Iroise biosphere reserve
(France) and the Hiiumaa biosphere
reserve (Estonia). Other candidates
for membership of the network are
the Bijagos Archipelago (Guinea
Bissau), the Université des Antilles-
Guyane (France), the Archipelago
Sea (Finland), the central Californian
coastal biosphere reserve (United
States) and the Isles ofScilly (United
Kingdom) . The network publishes a
newsletter, Archipelago. The project
is headed by Louis Brigand, Univer¬
sité de Bretagne occidentale, 6,
avenue Le Gorgeu, 29275 Brest
CEDEX. Fax. 33 98 31 66 26.
VAKA MOANA"THE OCEAN
ROADS" is the name ofa project
proposed to the Director-General of
Unesco at a subregional consulta¬
tion ofUnesco Member States of the
Pacific in luly 1 99 1. It aims to define
and highlight the part played by the
ocean as a pathway linking the
islands and their cultures. Studies
will be carried out on the peopling of
the region and its history, archae¬
ology and languages, the interaction
between environment and popula¬
tion, tourism and the arts, and tra¬
ditional lore and modern societies.
"WOULD YOU LIKE TO ADOPT
AN ISLAND?": lohnRulmalisthe
Executive Director of the Office of
the Traditional Chiefs of the Ulithi
Falalop Atoll, Yap, Micronesia.
Addressing Unesco and other pos¬
sible partners in the Italian magazine
Airone and in Insula, he has put for¬
ward a proposal for an original form
of "adoption". The tiny state of Yap,
formerly administered by the United
States, will cease to receive any aid
as of the year 2000. Its thousand
inhabitants want to take responsi¬
bility for their own development
whilevigorously protecting their envi-
ronment and culture, and would like
to have access to some ofthe benefits
of progress, such as telecommuni¬
cations, modern medicine, books for
the library, and solar panels. Anyone
wishing to participate in this imagi¬
native operation should contact: Pier
d'Ayala, INSULA/ Unesco, 1, rue
Miollis, 75015 Paris.
A UNITED NATIONS CONFER¬
ENCE ON SMALL ISLANDS will
be held from 25 April to 6 May 1994
in Barbados. Further information
may be obtained from Mr Miles
Stoby at UN Headquarters in New
York. Fax. 212 963 59 35.
READING LIST:
« Sustainable development and
environmental management of |
small islands (in English only), by
William Beller, Pier d'Ayala and
Philippe Hein, with contributions
by 30 experts in economics, ecology,
geography, environmental sciences
and anthropology (MAB Series, No 5,
Unesco /Parthenon Publishing,
1990).
* Unesco Sources, No 42, November
1992: "The fragile world of islands"
(English, French, Spanish, Catalan).
« Les îles en Méditerranée, by Louis
Brigand, Les Fascicules du Plan Bleu
5, UNEP/Economica, 1991.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
StateS Ofbondage m by Manfred Nowak
28
TORTURE is one of the most barbaric acts of
state repression, and it constitutes a direct
and deliberate attack on the core of the
human personality. Like slavery, it is an expres¬
sion of the almost unlimited power of one indi¬
vidual over another. In the case of slavery, the
human being is degraded to the condition of a
non-human object deprived of legal personality.
Torture aims to destroy human dignity and
reduce the victim to the status of a passive tool in
the hands of the torturer.
In ancient and medieval times in Europe, tor¬
ture was employed to aggravate criminal pun
ishments usually the death penalty and to
extort confessions. Its use was an officially
accepted and legally regulated aspect of the crim¬
inal justice system.
Torture was officially abolished in all European
countries between 1750 and 1830. Like the aboli¬
tion of slavery, its suppression was the fruit of
the humanism and rationalism of the Enlighten¬
ment. Although torture continued to be applied
behind prison walls, there were comparably few
allegations of its systematic use in the late nine¬
teenth and early twentieth centuries. Whereas
slavery and the slave trade were explicitly pro-
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Torture is a crime in
international law but it
is widely practised.
What can he done to
bring the cidprits to
book?
Left, A scene of the
Inquisition,
by Francisco de Goya y
Lucientes (1746-1828).
Right, Slave (1948),
by the Mexican painter
José Clemente Orozco.
hibited by a number of bilateral and multilateral
treaties culminating in the 1926 Slavery Conven¬
tion, torture was so much regarded as a phenom¬
enon of the past that neither international human
rights law nor even most domestic bills of rights
of this period contained explicit prohibitions.
Under National Socialism in Germany and
Stalinism in the U.S.S.R. torture was again prac¬
tised in a systematic, albeit clandestine manner. It
acquired a new rationale as a means of state
repression against political, ethnic and religious
"enemies of the people". As well as being used as
a punishment and in obtaining confessions, tor¬
ture now served additional functions: the extor¬
tion of denunciations and other information
about third persons, intimidation and discour¬
agement of the victim, and the creation of a gen¬
eral atmosphere of fear as a violent means of
deterrence and repression.
Since these modern functions proved to be
fairly efficient in combatting criminality and ter¬
rorism as well as "subversion" and other oppo¬
sition tendencies, torture unfortunately began
to spread again after the Second World War, to
such an extent that it is now sometimes referred
to as "the plague of the twentieth century". It was,
for instance, systematically practised by European
colonial powers against decolonization move¬
ments in the 1950s and 1960s (well-documented
cases include those under French rule in Algeria
and under Portuguese rule in that nation's former
African colonies), under British anti-terrorist
legislation in Northern Ireland, by the Greek
colonels in the late 1960s, by many Latin Amer¬
ican military dictatorships based on the ideology
of "national security", by African dictators, by
communist regimes, and by many other govern¬
ments in many other regions.
What is torture?
The international movement against torture can
only rest on humanitarian grounds and on the
moral, political and legal force of human rights.
In contrast to their practice with regard to torture
in earlier centuries and to most other human
rights violations today, governments now prac¬
tically never admit that they order or even tolerate
its use. Condemnation of these barbaric acts is
universal, which might make the "mobilization of
shame" somewhat easier than, for instance, in
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
IT can be more clearly seen today that we shall solve none of the
world's profound and serious problems without the full
participation of indigenous people, ethnic minorities, the victims
of arbitrary acts and repression, women, widows, children,
displaced persons and other vulnerable elements, of all those who
comprise the vast majority of the poor of our societies and whose
experiences and demands must be taken into account.
It is essential, for the future of humanity, to envisage a new
type of education which conveys the message that indigenous
people and minorities in general demand co-operation from all sec¬
tors of society so as to avoid confrontations, racism and discrimi¬
nation and so that their struggle to achieve full respect for their
rights and their identity may be crowned with success.
Recognition and respect for cultural pluralism are key factors in
the construction of new relations based on equality and peaceful
coexistence between our peoples and the nations of the world.
Rigoberta Menchú
Nobel Peace Prize-winner
SO
MANFRED NOWAK,
Austrian specialist in
constitutional, administrative
and international law, is
director of the Ludwig-
Boltzmann Institute of Human
Rights in Vienna. He was co¬
ordinator of NGO-parallel
events during the World
Conference on Human Rights.
the case of the campaign against capital punish¬
ment. On the other hand, the same fact leads
governments to apply torture primarily in remote
and clandestine detention centres on prisoners
who are held incommunicado, which makes the
gathering of evidence about its use usually very
difficult. It also increases the risk of victims being
killed after having being subjected to torture.
Torture and other forms of cruel, inhuman
and degrading treatment or punishment are pro¬
hibited in various international treaties and
agreements generally considered to have the
force of law, among them the Geneva Conven¬
tions of 1949, the International Covenant on
Civil and Political Rights of 1966 (CCPR), the
1984 UN Convention against Torture (CAT),
the 1950 European Convention on Human
Rights, the American Convention on Human
Rights of 1969, and the African Charter on
Human and Peoples' Rights of 1981. In addition
article 5 of the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights of 1948 is generally regarded as part of
customary international law. The Vienna Dec¬
laration and Programme of Action again con¬
firmed in the strongest terms that freedom from
torture is a right that must be protected under all
circumstances.
Despite this impressive evidence regarding
the universality of the right to freedom from tor¬
ture, doubts remain as to whether this universal
standard can be applied equally to all political sys¬
tems, religious and cultural groups. The govern¬
ments of certain states claim that amputations
and similar forms of corporal punishment pro¬
vided for by Islamic law do not contravene the
right to freedom from torture. While feminist
groups around the world denounce female cir¬
cumcision as a form of torture prohibited under
international law, many Africans view the prac¬
tice as an expression of their traditional culture.
Similarly, the admissible minimum standard of
prison conditions is said to depend on the cultural
background as well as the socio-economic devel¬
opment of the respective country.
These examples show that even an absolute
right such as freedom from torture may be rela¬
tivized as a result of the different interpretations
given to the term in different cultures. Even in a
single cultural environment, opinions as to what
constitutes torture can differ considerably. In
the case of Northern Ireland, the European Com¬
mission of Human Rights considered the so-
called five techniques used by British security
forces during interrogation (hooding detainees,
subjecting them to constant and intense noise,
depriving them of sleep and sufficient food and
drink, and making them stand for long periods on
their toes against a wall in a painful posture) as
torture; but the European Court of Human
Rights viewed them only as inhuman treatment.
The drafters of the 1984 UN Convention
against Torture (CAT) aimed at solving the
problem of defining a universal minimum stan¬
dard of unacceptable behaviour by elaborating a
precise definition of torture. According to Article
1 of the Convention, torture is an act of public
officials that intentionally inflicts severe physical
or mental pain in order to fulfil a certain purpose,
such as the extortion of information or confes¬
sions. The concept of severe pain is itself of course
partly subjective.
The CAT definition further excludes "pain or
suffering arising only from, inherent in or inci¬
dental to lawful sanctions". This limitation has
been heavily criticized as an unacceptable loop¬
hole. Who is to decide whether a sanction such as
corporal punishment is lawful? If cultural diver¬
sity is to be taken into account, the obvious
answer would be the domestic legislature
involved. Yet to leave the question exclusively
with national authorities would strip the right to
freedom from torture of its regulatory function.
In the circumstances, it is hard not to agree with
the observation of the Special Rapporteur on
Torture, whose post was created by the UN
Commission on Human Rights in 1985, that "it
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
is international law and not domestic law which
ultimately determines whether a certain practice
may be regarded as lawful".
In defining torture and other forms of
inhuman treatment or punishment, one therefore
has to strike a careful balance between the need
for common universal minimum standards and
the requirement to take political, social, religious
and cultural particularities into account. This
can only be done on a case-by-case basis by the
competent international bodies. In cases involving
certain dictatorships such as that which formerly
existed in Uruguay, the Human Rights Com¬
mittee of the United Nations found that inter¬
rogation techniques that included systematic
beatings, electric shocks, burns, mock execu¬
tions, hanging prisoners for extended periods by
their arms or forcing their heads under water
constituted torture and violated Article 7 of the
International Covenant on Civil and Political
Rights.
By these universal standards, there can be no
doubt that the more severe forms of corporal
punishment practised under certain religious laws,
including amputation and stoning, would con¬
stitute inhuman or cruel punishment or even tor¬
ture. Whether states under present international
law are under a positive obligation to prohibit
female circumcision is more difficult to judge.
Since these traditional practices inflict severe phys¬
ical and mental pain on the girls and women con¬
cerned and are, moreover, discriminatory on the
ground of gender, states should at least try to pre¬
vent them by educational and similar means.
Torture and human rights
Since most cases of torture take place in detention
and/or are related to criminal proceedings, an
indivisible relationship exists between freedom
from torture, personal liberty and the right to a
fair trial. To strengthen the guarantees of these
other human rights may, therefore, have the indi¬
rect effect of preventing or reducing the occur¬
rence of torture. Consequently, states should
ensure the following minimum guarantees, which
are not dependent on the political, social or cul¬
tural background of the country concerned:
The absolute prohibition of incommunicado
detention;
The right of arrested persons to immediately
contact relatives, a lawyer and a doctor;
The right of arrested persons to be brought
promptly (within forty-eight hours of arrest) to
a judge and to have a medical examination by an
independent doctor;
Supervision of interrogations by an indepen¬
dent authority;
Prohibition of the use of statements obtained
by torture as evidence before courts.
Some of these standards can be derived from
present international law; others should be
added as a means to prevent torture. Another
provision that links freedom from torture with
personal liberty is the right of detained persons
under Article 10 of the Covenant on Civil and
Political Rights to be treated with humanity
and dignity. This right provides a guarantee
against harsh prison conditions that nonetheless
do not amount to inhuman or degrading treat¬
ment as defined by Article 7. Again, what is
considered inhuman will reflect a country's cul¬
tural background.
Nevertheless, the United Nations has adopted
standard minimum rules for the treatment of
prisoners. In one recent case, the UN Human
Rights Committee even found that allowances of
just five minutes a day for personal hygiene and
for open-air exercise constitute inhuman prison
conditions. Since it had already earlier expressed
the view that states must establish a minimum
standard of conditions of detention regardless
of economic difficulties, this comparatively high
standard will have to be applied equally in all
States Parties to the Covenant.
In view of the fact that, despite its unanimous,
runeral of the black
leader Steve Biko, who had
died in detention. (South
Africa, 1977).
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
absolute and universal condemnation, torture was
practised on such an unprecedented scale in the
1970s, Amnesty International, the International
Commission ofJurists and other NGOs called for
more efficient and innovative implementation
measures. In fact the traditional monitoring mech¬
anisms under the terms of the Covenant on Civil
and Political Rights and regional conventions
only apply retrospectively, usually years after the
actual violation has taken place, and offer little
relief to the victim. A person under imminent
threat of torture needs either immediate inter¬
vention or else international measures that effec¬
tively deter potential perpetrators.
A victim of repression by
the Securitate (secret
police) in 1 989, at the time
of the fall of the Ceausescu
regime in Romania.
Current trends
The main thrust of the Convention against Tor¬
ture is the punishment of torturers by means of
the criminal law. States Parties are obliged to
treat all acts of torture as criminal offences, and
to assign appropriate penalties for them. The
CAT provides for universal jurisdiction, which
means that torturers can be detained, prosecuted
and punished in all States Parties regardless of the
nationality of the torturer or his victims or the ter¬
ritory in which the act of torture was perpe¬
trated. In addition to the traditional monitoring
procedures, Article 20 of the CAT authorizes
the Committee against Torture in cases of alleged
systematic torture to carry out confidential
enquiries, including visits to the territory of the
state concerned if it gives its consent.
The experiences of the first six years of CAT s
implementation have not been particularly encour-
311
aging. States are extremely hesitant about applying
universal criminal jurisdiction against foreign
nationals, and the Committee against Torture
seems to be more occupied with its traditional
task of examining state reports than with adopting
a new and more efficient approach. However, in
November 1993 the Committee issued for the
first time a public statement in which it confirmed
the practice of torture in Turkey.
The Special Rapporteur on Torture has a
worldwide mandate to examine questions rele¬
vant to torture and to report on its occurrence and
on the extent to which it was practised in all
countries. His activities consist of communi¬
cating with governments on questions relating to
torture, launching urgent appeals when he
receives information that a person is at risk,
paying visits to countries which invite him for
consultation, analysing the phenomenon of tor¬
ture and the root causes conducive to it, and rec¬
ommending measures for improvement.
To permit more efficient action to prevent
torture, the Special Rapporteur time and again
stressed the need for a universal system of pre¬
ventive visits to places of detention. This system,
originally proposed byJean-Jacques Gautier and
the Swiss Committee against Torture, is based on
a very simple idea: states should give an interna¬
tional body the right to carry out visits to places
within their jurisdiction where persons are
deprived of their liberty by a public authority.
This international body would then draw up a
report on its findings and make the necessary
recommendations. The mere fact of an interna¬
tional body having the right to inspect places of
detention without giving previous notice would
presumably have a deterrent effect on those
responsible for torture.
Thus far, the fear that such a system would
interfere too much with states' internal affairs
has prevented its adoption at the universal level.
That is why the Council of Europe took up the
idea and adopted, in 1987, the European Con¬
vention for the Prevention of Torture, which fol¬
lows the lines described above, and entered into
force in 1989. The European Committee for the
Prevention of Torture has made a very dynamic
start by carrying out regular visits to all States Par¬
ties and by submitting very thorough and critical
reports with detailed recommendations, which are
taken seriously by governments.
On the basis of these encouraging experi¬
ences, efforts to establish a similar non-juridical
and non-bureaucratic system at the universal
level also have gained force in recent times. In
1992, the Commission on Human Rights setup
an open-ended intersessional working group in
order to elaborate a drafL Optional Protocol to the
UN Convention against Torture. InJune 1993 the
Vienna World Conference on Human Rights
reaffirmed that efforts to eradicate torture should,
first and foremost, be concentrated on prevention
and therefore called for the early adoption of
this draft. 0
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Justice (1 990), a sculpture
by the French artist Niki
de Saint-Phalle, was one of
a number of works by
contemporary artists sold
in aid of Amnesty
International, founded in
1 96 1 , to mark its thirtieth
anniversary.
Seedphtfor thefuture Iby Stéphane Hessel
The results of the Vienna
Conference will take
time to bearfruit
Hi
1 ow do the results of the Vienna Confer¬
ence look today, several months after the
.meeting ended?
The most disappointing thing about the Con¬
ference was that it failed to make a significant
impact on public opinion. At the time the media
were too absorbed by the Bosnian drama and the
inability of the international community to bring
it under control for them to give the speeches
made in Vienna the coverage they deserved.
The best efforts of the Austrian Govern¬
ment, thanks to which the Dalai Lama was in
attendance at the Conference, the strongly
expressed, and sometimes persuasive, opinions
voiced by the leading figures invited by the Sec¬
retary-General of the United Nations, including
Cory Aquino, Jimmy Carter, Rigoberta
Menchú, Wole Soyinka and others, and the tur¬
bulent scenes that occurred daily in the non-gov¬
ernmental organizations' Forum none of these
sufficed to arouse journalists' interest. Maybe
they would have liked to regale their audiences
with stories of confrontations between the
democracies and the dictatorships, but such
confrontations failed to materialize.
One needs to have followed the development
of international relations in the area of human
rights to be able to pick out, as I shall attempt to 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34
STEPHANE HESSEL,
French diplomat, was formerly
his country's permanent
representative at the United
Nations in Geneva. He headed
the French delegation at the
World Conference on Human
do here, the significant new elements that
emerged from the Conference.
The previous world conference on human
rights was held in Tehran in 1968, the year of
the short-lived "Prague spring", when East-West
antagonism was at its height. The Vienna Con¬
ference enjoyed the advantage of meeting in a
radically different context in which, with the col¬
lapse of the last of the great empires and the rap¬
prochement between its main successor state,
Russia, and the Western democracies, a whole
new perception of international co-operation is
taking shape.
One-party regimes have everywhere been
routed or at least challenged, as witness many
examples in eastern Europe and others in Latin
America and the Caribbean, Southeast Asia and
several African countries. The prosperity of those
countries where democracy is underpinned by the
rule of law and respect for individual liberties
stands in stark contrast to the impoverished con¬
dition that the peeling façades of the authori¬
tarian regimes can no longer disguise.
Rights.
The right to development
Two arguments have been rebutted: the one
claiming that "development" reduced to a mere
synonym of growth in the gross national
product could more readily be achieved by
constraint than by consent among the individual
interests involved and requires a centrally
directed distribution of resources; and the other
regarding "democracy" reduced to the pres¬
ence of a multiparty systemas a luxury only
rich countries can afford. In point of fact, a linkage
has been established, both in the East and in the
South, between the market economy and respect
for individual liberties, the challenging of the
leadership and accession to material well-being.
While there can be no question of taking the
regulatory mechanisms necessary for ensuring the
public good out of the hands of the state, only a
state wherein the rule of law, issuing from demo¬
cratic processes of consultation, prevails can per¬
form that role. Breaches of human rights and
oppression exerted by force of arms or by means
of the police arc seen for what they are, serious
obstacles to economic and social development.
Conversely, "underdevelopment", mani¬
festing itself in the form of drastic insufficiencies
in such vital areas as health, food and urban
development, and resulting in the exploitation of
children and corruption in the ranks of an under¬
paid civil service and a poorly trained magistracy,
provides a fertile breeding-ground for viola¬
tions of civil and political rights and at the same
time slows down the necessary process of raising
civic awareness and creating a civil society
capable of conducting a dialogue with the state.
Economic and social development clearly has a
crucial part to play in the establishment of insti¬
tutions for the safeguarding of human rights.
There thus exists, not only on paper but in
reality, a dialectical relationship between the
three themes of human rights, democracy and
development on which the Vienna Conference
was focused.
Each of these needed, however, to be inter¬
preted in the light of recent history: human
rights include not only civil and political rights
but also, inseparable from them, economic,
social and cultural rights. Democracy entails
not only the existence of constitutional guar¬
antees but also the establishment of the rule of
law, together with the system of justice and the
appeals procedures needed to enforce it for the
benefit of the citizen. Development means not
only the increased production and consumption
of material goods but also improved living con¬
ditions for the population as a whole in eco¬
nomic, social and cultural terms.
Development in this sense is an inalienable
right. The definition given in the Declaration
adopted by the Conference (see page 41, Article
10) deserves to be expounded in greater detail
and seen in the light of the many studies carried
out by all the specialized agencies of the United
Nations family. The industrial powers hitherto
regarded the "right to development" simply as
an impossible demand on the part of the poor
countries for ever-increasing aid from the rich
ones. They need to show a better understanding
of the place it occupies in a world strategy that
takes fuller account of the inescapable relation¬
ships of interdependence between civil and polit¬
ical rights and economic, social and cultural
rights.
It was on this level that the real breakthrough
came at the Conference. We managed to recon¬
cile the contrasting views of states belonging
to different cultures cultures all equally proud
of their fundamental values in a text wherein
they reached agreement on a common definition
of the universality of human dignity and the
imprescriptible nature of human rights: what
the United Nations Secretary-General, Boutros
Boutros Ghali, called the emergence of a "world
culture of human rights". The hope that this
culture will gradually spread to the whole of
the planet is replacing the former antagonistic
ideologies as a new Utopia to be striven for.
Despite the strong misgivings of certain states,
breakdown was avoided and the final document,
adopted by acclamation on 25 June, gives away
nothing essential in relation to that hope. Those
who feared a breakdown were reassured for the
time being, albeit on the understanding that they
must pursue their efforts unrelentingly. Those
who, on the other hand, hoped for a breakdown,
either because they wanted to smash what they
denounced as a hegemony of Western values or
because they wished to blacklist the countries
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
that were least co-operative and were guilty of the
most serious violations, were disappointed in
their hopes.
One of the most interesting speeches made in
this connection was that of the Indonesian For¬
eign Minister, Ali Alatas, whose country at pre¬
sent occupies the presidency of the non-aligned
movement. He denied the Western countries the
right to impose on others, in the name of human
rights, their system of values, which he denounced
as being flawed and rejected as being arrogant, at
the same time declaring that every effort should
be made, by means of a form of co-operation
that paid respect to cultural diversity, to achieve
the full flowering of the human being.
Aprogramme ofaction
An equally important speech was given by Sec¬
retary of State Warren Christopher, taking
United States diplomacy a decisive step for¬
ward in the direction of the countries of the
South. Acknowledging the right to develop¬
ment as an inalienable right means recognizing,
not that such a right takes precedence over
respect for civil and political rights, but that it
merits an effort of international solidarity to
enable all societies to become states where "the
rule of law" prevails, guaranteeing fundamental
freedoms and a peaceful world order.
By refusing to confine itself to a statement of
principles, as some delegations would have liked,
and adopting a substantial programme of action,
the Conference mapped out ways of strength¬
ening the many mechanisms devised by the
United Nations Commission on Human Rights
at its last three sessions. Above all, it called for
the promotion and protection of human rights
to be included among the concerns of the inter¬
national co-operation system as a whole.
Steps had already been taken in this direction.
In 1992, the Commission held two special ses¬
sions on the former Yugoslavia. At these sessions
new texts on minorities, enforced disappear¬
ances, indigenous peoples and arbitrary deten¬
tion were adopted, and bodies were set up for
the protection and promotion of human rights
in El Salvador, Cambodia and Haiti. Amnesty
International had no hesitation in calling the
progress made in that year "historic".
Where do the states concerned stand in rela¬
tion to this progress? Many of the states that
were represented at the Conference remain more
fearful of interference by an international insti¬
tution in their internal problems than appre¬
ciative of the help such an institution offers
them to solve those problems, and this despite
Uemonstration in .
Guatemala City, capital of
Guatemala, calling for
greater participation by
civil society in the peace
process.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
the great skill with which this offer was made by
the Conference's Secretary-General, Ibrahima
Fall, who heads the United Nations Centre for
Human Rights in Geneva.
The two key questions put before the United
Nations General Assembly by the final document
of the Conference were those of the human and
financial resources of the Geneva Centre, which
were to be substantially increased, and of the
status of the senior official in charge of it.
By resolution 141 adopted on 22 December
1993, as its forty-eighth session was drawing to
a close, the Assembly pronounced itself in favour
of creating a post of High Commissioner for
Human Rights. It decided that the Office of the
High Commissioner should be located in Geneva,
and that the High Commissioner should be
responsible for overall supervision of the Centre
for Human Rights.
The resolution gives the High Commis¬
sioner extensive, well defined terms of refer¬
ence, in keeping with the wishes expressed by
the Vienna Conference, thus representing an
undeniable success for those who defend human
rights throughout the world.
In the paragraph dealing with the Centre's
resources, on the other hand, the resolution,
without going into further detail, limits itself to
requesting the Secretary-General, "to provide
appropriate staff and resources from within the
existing and future regular budgets of the United
Nations, to enable the High Commissioner to
fulfil his/her mandate, without diverting
resources from the development programme
and activities of the United Nations".
In regard to these two key issues, it will be
for Mr Boutros Boutros Ghali to decide how
best to ensure that the impetus provided by the
Vienna meeting and indeed by the 1992 Rio
meeting is followed through in practice.
The pressure ofcivil society
The caution shown by states on human rights
questions should come as no surprise. It is, on the
other hand, encouraging to see how the activities
of the various associations, federations, commit¬
tees and commissions for the defence of human
rights, increasingly numerous in every part of
the world, are growing in strength.
The question as to how these bodies could
play an effective part in the deliberations of the
Vienna Conference was one of those most hotly
debated during the meeting of its Preparatory
Commission and was still giving rise to heated
controversy before and after the official opening
of the Conference itself.
The "voice of the peoples" was being given
free, often sharply controversial, expression at the
NGOs' Forum, but how was it to make itself
heard in the intergovernmental deliberations on
a document entailing commitments on the part of
the states represented? In the first instance, the
Women protesting in
Moscow (Russia) in 1992
against official silence over
the disappearances of
Russian servicemen.
two thousand or so Forum participants had to
reach agreement on the proposals put forward in
their name. Notwithstanding the conflicts,
moments of high drama and outbursts of passion,
the NGOs succeeded in doing so.
The Conference plenary heard what they had
to say without paying it too much heed. The
plenary commission accorded them plentiful
speaking time but the Drafting Committee closed
its doors to them. In fact, however, all the dele¬
gations kept in constant contact with them. It may
therefore be said that considerable progress was
made in the interpénétration between the official
and unofficial levels, the latter including not only
the non-governmental organizations, with or
without consultative status, but also the National
Commissions, the mediators, the authors of the
special reports and the experts from the bodies
responsible for monitoring the treaties and con¬
ventions, all of whom kept up constant pressure
on the Conference.
The most encouraging thing to report, now
that the Conference itself is over and done with,
is the existence and the strength of this pressure,
even if it is as yet exerted in too unco-ordinated
and sporadic a fashion. It is no longer a phenom¬
enon peculiar to the old democracies, as it was in
the early decades of the United Nations. The
preparatory conferences in Tunis, San José and
Bangkok attested to the fact that civil society in
Africa, Latin America and Asia is a force to be
reckoned with.
The peoples of the world will no longer
leave it to governments alone to realize their
common aspirations less injustice, less oppres¬
sion, greater accountability and less violence. As
the media now present it, this goal seems distant
and unreal; but looking back on the progress
already made, progress that it is up to all of us to
consolidate, we cannot help but believe that it
can, and therefore must, be attained.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
IN 1950 the United Nations Economic
and Social Council called on UNESCO
to encourage and facilitate education
relating to the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights, adopted two years earlier,
both in schools and among the adult pop¬
ulation and through the medium of the
press, radio and the cinema. Shortly after¬
wards, in 1951, the first of what was to
become an impressive number of
UNESCO publications on human rights
teaching appeared: The Universal Dec¬
laration ofHuman Rights: A Guide for
Teachers.
Human rights teaching entails more
than providing information about rights
and the channels through which they
may be put into effect. It must aim to
create a strong attachment to the princi¬
ples and values underlying them, such as
respect for human dignity and for the
rights of others, and to develop people's
capacity to organize themselves to stand
up for their rights and to combat igno¬
rance and indifference.
Information about human rights
therefore needs to be worked into all
types of education, beginning, naturally
enough, in schools. As long ago as 1953,
UNESCO launched its Associated Schools
Project, one of the aims of which is to
promote international understanding and
world peace. Over 3,000 primary and
secondary schools belonging to this
world-wide network are now teaching
respect for human rights and fundamental
freedoms.
This learning process should, how¬
ever, continue through every phase of
adult life, in the universities and through
the work of associations and profes¬
sional bodies, and should be made an
essential element in the education of the
most vulnerable sections of society, such
as refugees, minorities, women and the
disabled.
UNESCO built up this very broad con¬
ception of human rights teaching by
stages. A decisive step forward was taken
by the International Congress on
Teaching in Human Rights (Vienna,
1978), which brought together a hun¬
dred or so experts from around the
world teachers, educationists, human
rights activists and government officials
and gave particular emphasis to encour¬
aging attitudes of tolerance, respect and
solidarity.
THE
RIGHTS
OF ALL
BYFRANCINE
FOURNIER
Nine years later, the International
Congress on Human Rights Teaching,
Information and Documentation (Malta,
1987) added further depth and breadth to
the ideas discussed in Vienna, stressing the
diverse forms that such teaching should
take to bring it within the reach of all
and to extend it to all levels of education.
The International Congress on Edu¬
cation for Human Rights and Democ¬
racy (Montreal, March 1993), the latest
stage in this process, summing up all that
had gone before, culminated in the adop¬
tion of a "World Plan of Action on Edu¬
cation for Human Rights and Democ-
Learning how to vote in a Unesco
Associated School in Costa Rica.
racy". This plan is addressed to all those
involved in human rights teaching, in or
outside of the education system and espe¬
cially in difficult circumstances such as
conflicts, natural disasters or the transition
from an authoritarian to a democratic
system one of the new dimensions to
emerge at this congress being that democ¬
racy itself is inseparable from, and com¬
plementary to, true respect for human
rights.
This essential topic, learning democ¬
racy, has since been the subject of many
UNESCO activities. Some of the seminars
and other meetings UNESCO has orga¬
nized, in particular a meeting of experts
on "Human rights and human rights edu¬
cation in the process of transition to
democracy" (Prague, November 1992)
and an international workshop on "Edu¬
cation for human rights and democracy in
post-communist societies" (Warsaw, Sep¬
tember 1993), have made it possible to
identify the priorities and the steps to be
taken in support of human rights teaching
in eastern and central Europe.
UNESCO publishes a newsletter enti¬
tled The Human Rights Teaching Bul¬
letin and awards a "UNESCO Prize for
the Teaching of Human Rights" every
two years to institutions, organizations or
individuals who have distinguished them¬
selves in this area, most recently, in 1992,
to the Arab Institute for Human Rights.
The Organization also publishes a
number of directories and bibliographies,
such as Access to Human Rights Docu¬
mentation, and helps out with the estab¬
lishment or management of documenta¬
tion centres.
UNESCO has provided a forum in
which recommendations and conven¬
tions safeguarding such basic cultural
rights as the right to education, the right
to participate in cultural life or scientific
progress and the right to information
have been worked out and adopted.
Last but not least, UNESCO's Execu¬
tive Board has set up a "communica¬
tions" i.e. complaints procedure to
enable the Organization to help in solving
problems in relation to the observance
of cultural and educational rights sub¬
mitted by individuals or associations.
FRANCINE FOURNIER
is UNESCO's Assistant Director-General for Social
and Human Sciences. 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
A new departure by Alois Mock
38
ALOIS MOCK,
Austria's Minister of Foreign
Affairs and Chairperson of the
European Democratic Union,
was president of the World
Conference on Human Rights.
THE second World Conference on Human
Rights brought together all the parties con¬
cerned with the implementation of these
rights governments, United Nations agencies,
specialized and regional international bodies,
non-governmental organizations, national insti¬
tutions, parliamentarians, the media and pri¬
vate individuals.
The Conference was thus like a living mosaic,
reflecting the present situation of human rights
in the world: a lot of pieces need to be polished
and fined down and then put in their proper
places to form a meaningful whole. The Con¬
ference was likewise at pains to define, and often
to redefine and reaffirm, principles that have
existed for decades or even centuries. Some of
these principles may have given rise to contro¬
versy in the past; the Conference at last gave
them universal authority.
Guaranteeing all human beings fundamental
rights stemming from human nature is a long-
term undertaking that in the first place entails
reaching agreement among states. What is
needed is to establish the principles of human
rights first as political and then as legal obliga¬
tions, and finally to see to it that they are put into
practice.
The final document of the Conference, con¬
sisting of the Declaration and Programme of
Action"', paves the way for a dynamic develop¬
ment of the UN system to promote and protect
human rights in the following fields:
The universality ofhuman rights: the Dec¬
laration confirms that all human rights are uni¬
versal, indivisible and interdependent, even
emphasizing that the universal nature of these
rights and freedoms is beyond question. It was
clear from the preparatory proceedings, and
then from the discussions during the Confer¬
ence, that this principle needed restating.
Respect for human rights as a subject for
international discussion: the final document
stresses that the promotion and protection of all
human rights is a legitimate concern of the inter¬
national community. Raising questions about the
effective respect for these rights can thus no
longer be regarded as unwarranted interference
in the affairs of a state.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The relationship between democracy, devel¬
opment and human rights: the Conference
brought out clearly the interdependence
between respect for human rights, economic
and social development, and individuals' par¬
ticipation in public life.
Minority rights: the participating states rec¬
ognized the importance of the promotion and
protection of the rights of minorities to the
political and social stability of the states in which
they live, and accepted the obligation to ensure
that persons belonging to minorities may fully
and effectively exercise all human rights without
discrimination.
The position of women and vulnerable
groups: the final document attaches particular
importance to the rights of women and of various
vulnerable groups, including children, indige¬
nous people, migrant workers and the disabled.
It declares that the full and equal participation of
women in political, civil, economic, social and cul¬
tural life, at the national, regional and international
levels, and the eradication of all forms of gender-
based discrimination are priority objectives of the
international community.
It also reaffirms the commitment of the inter¬
national community to the economic, social
and cultural well-being of indigenous people,
and their enjoyment of the fruits of sustainable
development.
The Programme ofAction: unlike the first
World Conference, held at Tehran in 1968, the
declaration of the Vienna Conference is com¬
bined with a Programme of Action containing
guidelines for its implementation in future years.
The United Nations system is called upon
to take concrete measures for the practical appli¬
cation of the recommendations contained in the
final document. To this end the Conference asked
that the Geneva Centre for Human Rights be
strengthened and its financial resources and staff
be increased, and that existing machinery for
promoting and protecting human rights be made
more effective. The proposal that a post of High
Commissioner for Human Rights be created has
since been adopted by the General Assembly.
The realization of human rights is, however,
an undertaking that is far from complete. The dis¬
cussions at the Conference confirmed that the
modern world is in total disarray. Armed aggres¬
sion, flagrant and systematic violation of human
rights, and the denial of fundamental freedoms
continue in various parts of the world. As the
Nobel Peace prizewinners gathered at Vienna
emphasized during the Conference: "One of the
fundamental lessons of our time is that respect for
human rights is essential for peace. There can be
no real peace without justice, and any lasting
peace must be founded on universal devotion to
the human family. National interests must be
subordinated to international obligations	
"The only way of permanently settling the
conflicts still rife throughout the world is by
tackling the main causes of human rights viola¬
tions. Ethnic wars, growing militarism, racial,
religious, cultural and ideological hostility, and
the denial of social justice will come to an end if
all individuals are brought up, educated and
trained in a spirit of tolerance based on respect
for human rights in accordance with the various
instruments relating to human rights adopted by
the United Nations system." H * Sec extracts overleaf
I he Conference was like
a living mosaic. . . ."
Right and opposite page
above: details, at various
stages of preparation, of a
mosaic ( 1 99 1 ) by Slobodan
Bijeljac, an artist born in
Sarajevo.
T
t
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
/
The "Vienna Declaration and Programme ofAction, ", extractsfrom which are
published below, was adoptedat the World Conference on Human Rights by con¬
sensus, but only after long and often difficult negotiations. Thepreparatory meet¬
ings for the Conference revealed profound differences between the partici¬
pants, notably on the question ofthe universality ofhuman rights in a world of
different cultural traditions. In the dossier beginning on this page are long
extracts from the final declarations produced by some of these meetings. They
show where the different approaches to human rights issues coincide and where
theypart company.
The Vienna
Declaration and
Programme of
Action
Adopted 25 Tune 1993
by the
World Conference on
Human Rights
The World Conference on Human Rights,
Recognizing and affirming that all
human rights derive from the dignity and
worth inherent in the human person, and
that the human person is the central subject
of human rights and fundamental freedoms,
and consequently should be the principal
beneficiary and should participate actively in
the realization of these rights and freedoms,
Emphasizing the responsibilities of all
States, in conformity with the Charter of
the United Nations, to develop and
encourage respect for human rights and
fundamental freedoms for all, without dis¬
tinction as to race, sex, language or religion,
Considering the major changes taking
place on the international scene and the
aspirations of all the peoples for an inter¬
national order based on the principles
enshrined in the Charter of the United
Nations, including promoting and encour¬
aging respect for human rights and funda¬
mental freedoms for all and respect for
the principle of equal rights and self-deter-
mination of peoples, peace, democracy,
Tw justice, equality, rule of law, pluralism,
development, better standards of living
and solidarity,
Deeply concerned by various forms of
discrimination and violence, to which
women continue to be exposed all over
the world,
Solemnly adopts the Vienna Declara¬
tion and Programme of Action.
1. The World Conference on Human
Rights reaffirms the solemn commitment
of all States to fulfil their obligations to
promote universal respect for, and obser¬
vance and protection of, all human rights
and fundamental freedoms for all in accor¬
dance with the Charter of the United
Nations, other instruments relating to
human rights, and international law. The
universal nature of these rights and free¬
doms is beyond question.
2. All peoples have the right of self-deter¬
mination. By virtue of that right they freely
determine their political status, and freely
pursue their economic, social and cultural
development.
Taking into account the particular situ¬
ation of peoples under colonial or other
forms of alien domination or foreign occu¬
pation, the World Conference on Human
Rights recognizes the right of peoples to
take any legitimate action, in accordance
with the Charter of the United Nations, to
realize their inalienable right of self-deter¬
mination. The World Conference on
Human Rights considers the denial of the
right of self-determination as a violation of
human rights and underlines the impor¬
tance of the effective realization of this right.
5. All human rights are universal, indivis¬
ible and interdependent and interrelated.
The international community must treat
human rights globally in a fair and equal
manner, on the same footing, and with the
same emphasis. While the significance of
national and regional particularities and
various historical, cultural and religious
backgrounds must be borne in mind, it is
the duty of States, regardless of their polit¬
ical, economic and cultural systems, to
promote and protect all human rights and
fundamental freedoms.
6. The efforts of the United Nations
system towards the universal respect for,
and observance of, human rights and fun¬
damental freedoms for all, contribute to the
stability and well-being necessary for
peaceful and friendly relations among
nations, and to improved conditions for
peace and security as well as social and
economic development, in conformity
with the Charter of the United Nations.
8. Democracy, development and respect
for human rights and fundamental free¬
doms are interdependent and mutually
reinforcing. Democracy is based on the
freely expressed will of the people to deter¬
mine their own political, economic, social
and cultural systems and their full partic¬
ipation in all aspects of their lives. In the
context of the above, the promotion and
protection of human rights and funda¬
mental freedoms at the national and inter¬
national levels should be universal and
conducted without conditions attached.
The international community should sup¬
port the strengthening and promoting of
democracy, development and respect for
human rights and fundamental freedoms in
the entire world.
9. The World Conference on Human
Rights reaffirms that least developed coun¬
tries committed to the process of democ¬
ratization and economic reforms, many
of which are in Africa, should be sup¬
ported by the international community in
order to succeed in their transition to
democracy and economic development.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
10. The World Conference on Human
Rights reaffirms the right to development,
as established in the Declaration on the
Right to Development, as a universal and
inalienable right and an integral part of
fundamental human rights.
As stated in the Declaration on the
Right to Development, the human person
is the central subject of development.
While development facilitates the
enjoyment of all human rights, the lack
of development may not be invoked to
justify the abridgement of internationally
recognized human rights.
States should co-operate with each other
in ensuring development and eliminating
obstacles to development. The international
community should promote an effective
international co-operation for the realiza¬
tion of the right to development and the
elimination of obstacles to development.
Lasting progress towards the imple¬
mentation of the right to development
requires effective development policies at
the national level, as well as equitable eco¬
nomic relations and a favourable economic
environment at the international level.
11. The right to development should be
fulfilled so as to meet equitably the devel¬
opmental and environmental needs of pre¬
sent and future generations. The World
Conference on Human Rights recognizes
that illicit dumping of toxic and dangerous
substances and waste potentially consti¬
tutes a serious threat to the human rights
to life and health of everyone.
12. The World Conference on Human
Rights calls upon the international com¬
munity to make all efforts to help alleviate
the external debt burden of developing
countries, in order to supplement the efforts
of the Governments of such countries to
attain the full realization of the economic,
social and cultural rights of their people.
15. Respect for human rights and for fun¬
damental freedoms without distinction of
any kind is a fundamental rule of interna¬
tional human rights law. The speedy and
comprehensive elimination of all forms of
racism and racial discrimination, xeno¬
phobia and related intolerance is a pri¬
ority task for the international commu¬
nity. Governments should take effective
measures to prevent and combat them.
1 7. The acts, methods and practices of ter¬
rorism in all its forms and manifestations as
well as linkage in some countries to drug
trafficking are activities aimed at the
destruction of human rights, fundamental
freedoms and democracy, threatening ter¬
ritorial integrity, security of States and desta¬
bilizing legitimately constituted Govern¬
ments. The international community should
take the necessary steps to enhance co¬
operation to prevent and combat terrorism.
18. The human rights of women and of
the girl-child are an inalienable, integral
and indivisible part of universal human
rights. The full and equal participation of
women in political, civil, economic, social
and cultural life, at the national, regional
and international levels, and the eradication
of all forms of discrimination on grounds
of sex are priority objectives of the inter¬
national community.
Gender-based violence and all forms of
sexual harassment and exploitation,
including those resulting from cultural prej¬
udice and international trafficking, are
incompatible with the dignity and worth
of the human person, and must be elimi¬
nated. This can be achieved by legal mea¬
sures and through national action and inter¬
national co-operation in such fields as
economic and social development, educa¬
tion, safe maternity and health care, and
social support.
The human rights of women should
form an integral part of the United Nations
human rights activities, including the pro¬
motion of all human rights instruments
relating to women.
The World Conference on Human
. Rights urges Governments, institutions,
intergovernmental and non-governmental
organizations to intensify their efforts for
the protection and promotion of human
rights of women and the girl-child.
19	The World Conference on Human
Rights reaffirms the obligation of States to
ensure that persons belonging to minorities
may exercise fully and effectively all human
rights and fundamental freedoms without
any discrimination and in full equality
before the law in accordance with the Dec¬
laration on the Rights of Persons Belonging
to National or Ethnic, Religious and Lin¬
guistic Minorities.
The persons belonging to minorities
have the right to enjoy their own culture,
to profess and practise their own religion
and to use their own language in private
and in public, freely and without inter¬
ference or any form of discrimination.
20. The World Conference on Human
Rights recognizes the inherent dignity and
the unique contribution of indigenous
people to the development and plurality of
society and strongly reaffirms the com
mitment of the international community to
their economic, social and cultural well-
being and their enjoyment of the fruits of
sustainable development. States should
ensure the full and free participation of
indigenous people in all aspects of society,
in particular in matters of concern to them.
21	 National and international mech¬
anisms and programmes should be
strengthened for the defence and protec¬
tion of children, in particular, the girl-
child, abandoned children, street children,
economically and sexually exploited chil¬
dren, including through child pornog¬
raphy, child prostitution or sale of organs,
children victims of diseases including
acquired immunodeficiency syndrome,
refugee and displaced children, children
in detention, children in armed conflict, as
well as children victims of famine and
drought and other emergencies. Interna¬
tional co-operation and solidarity should
be promoted to support the implementa¬
tion of the Convention [on the Rights of
the Child] and the rights of the child
should be a priority in the United Nations
system-wide action on human rights.
22. Special attention needs to be paid to
ensuring non-discrimination, and the equal
enjoyment of all human rights and funda¬
mental freedoms by disabled persons,
including their active participation in all
aspects of society.
23. The World Conference on Human
Rights reaffirms that everyone, without
distinction of any kind, is entitled to the
right to seek and to enjoy in other coun¬
tries asylum from persecution, as well as
the right to return to one's own country.
36. The World Conference on Human
Rights reaffirms the important and con¬
structive role played by national institu-
tions for the promotion and protection of Tr I
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
;?
42
human rights, in particular in their advi¬
sory capacity to the competent authorities,
role in remedying human rights vio¬
lations, in the dissemination of human rights
information, and education in human rights.
37. Regional arrangements play a funda¬
mental role in promoting and protecting
human rights. They should reinforce uni¬
versal human rights standards, as contained
in international human rights instruments,
and their protection. The World Conference
on Human Rights endorses efforts under
way to strengthen these arrangements and
to increase their effectiveness, while at the
same time stressing the importance of co¬
operation with the United Nations human
rights activities.
The World Conference on Human
Rights reiterates the need to consider the
possibility of establishing regional and
sub-regional arrangements for the pro¬
motion and protection of human rights
where they do not already exist.
38. The World Conference on Human
Rights recognizes the important role of
non-governmental organizations in the
promotion of all human rights and in
humanitarian activities at national, regional
and international levels. The World Con¬
ference on Human Rights appreciates their
contribution to increasing public aware¬
ness of human rights issues, to the conduct
of education, training and research in this
field, and to the promotion and protec¬
tion of all human rights and fundamental
freedoms. While recognizing that the pri¬
mary responsibility for standard-setting
lies with States, the Conference also appre¬
ciates the contribution of non-govern¬
mental organizations to this process. In
this respect, the World Conference on
Human Rights emphasizes the importance
of continued dialogue and co-operation
between Governments and non-govern¬
mental organizations.
The Tunis
Declaration
Regional Meeting for
Africa
The Ministers and representatives of the
African States meeting at Tunis from 2 to 6
November 1992, in the context of prepa¬
rations for the World Conference on
Human Rights, and pursuant to General
Assembly resolution 46/116 of 17
December 1991... adopt the present dec¬
laration, to be known as the Tunis Decla¬
ration, which reflects both their convic¬
tions and their expectations:
1 . The African States reaffirm their com¬
mitment to the principles set forth in the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
the International Covenant on Economic,
Social and Cultural Rights, the Interna¬
tional Covenant on Civil and Political
Rights and the African Charter on Human
and People's Rights.
2. The universal nature of human rights is
beyond question; their protection and
promotion are the duty of all States,
regardless of their political, economic or
cultural systems.
3. The proper administration of justice
and an independent judiciary are crucial to
the full realization of human rights. The
attainment of these objectives is, however,
impossible without substantial investment
in the area of the administration of jus¬
tice. The African States and the interna¬
tional community are, therefore, called
upon to allocate more resources to this
area.
4. Responsibility for the implementation
and promotion of human rights devolves
primarily on Governments. The compo¬
nent institutions, organizations and struc¬
tures of society also play an important
role in safeguarding and disseminating
these rights; they should therefore be
strengthened and encouraged.
5. The observance and promotion of
human rights are undeniably a global con¬
cern and an objective to the realization of
which all States, without exception, are
called upon to contribute. However, no
ready-made model can be prescribed at
the universal level since the historical and
cultural realities of each nation and the
traditions, standards and values of each
people cannot be disregarded.
6. The principle of the indivisibility of
human rights is sacrosanct. Civil and polit¬
ical rights cannot be dissociated from eco¬
nomic, social and cultural rights. None of
these rights takes precedence over the
others.
7. Political freedom when not accompa¬
nied by respect for economic, social and
cultural rights is precarious. The right to
development is inalienable. Human rights,
development and international peace are
interdependent.
8. Lasting progress towards the imple¬
mentation of human rights implies, at the
national level, effective development poli¬
cies and, at the international level, more
equitable economic relations, as well as a
favourable economic environment.
9. Racism, particularly its new forms,
extremism and fanaticism, whether of reli¬
gious or other origin, pose a serious threat
to the protection and promotion of uni¬
versal human rights values. Governments,
individuals, groups, institutions and non¬
governmental organizations are called
upon to apply their efforts, take the nec¬
essary steps and co-operate in dealing with
this threat.
10. Africa, which has chosen the path of
democracy, economic reform and the pro¬
motion of human rights, in an
unfavourable economic environment, and
which finds itself particularly exposed to
internal tensions deriving from the failure
to meet the basic needs of populations and
from the rise of extremism, will neverthe¬
less remain committed to its choices and its
responsibilities, and calls upon the inter¬
national community to do likewise, in par¬
ticular through an intensification of inter¬
national solidarity, an adequate increase
in development assistance and an appro¬
priate settlement of the debt problem.
11. Africa, which remains committed to
respect for individual human rights, also
takes this opportunity to reaffirm the
importance that it attaches to respect for
the collective rights of peoples, particu¬
larly the right to determine their own
future and to control their own resources.
Accordingly, it condemns the persistence
of apartheid in South Africa and the gross
and systematic violations of human rights
due to foreign occupation, particularly in
Palestine and in the other occupied Arab
territories, including Jerusalem, the armed
conflicts in Somalia and the policy of ethnic
cleansing in Bosnia and Hcrcegovina, and
reaffirms the right of all peoples to self-
determination and free choice of their
political and economic systems and insti-
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
tutions, on the basis of respect for national
sovereignty and non-interference in the
internal affairs of States. B
The San José
Declaration
Regional Meeting for
Latin America and
the Caribbean
The representatives of the Latin-Amer¬
ican and Caribbean countries, meeting in
the city of San José, Costa Rica, from 1 8 to
22 January 1993, as part of the preparations
for the World Conference on Human
Rights, to be held in June 1993 in Vienna,
Austria,
1. We reaffirm our commitment to pro¬
moting and guaranteeing the full obser¬
vance of the human rights established in
the Universal Declaration and in universal
and regional human rights instruments,
through our own efforts and through
broad-based, non-selective and non-dis¬
criminatory international co-operation;
2. We reiterate that the World Conference
on Human Rights should be based on the
unconditional and indissoluble link
between human rights, democracy and
development;
3. We hold that the interdependence and
indivisibility of civil, political, economic,
social and cultural rights are the basis for
consideration of the question of human
rights, and therefore the exercise of some
cannot and must not be disallowed on the
pretext that full enjoyment of the others
has not yet been achieved;
4. We underline that respect for human
rights and fundamental freedoms, the
strengthening of development, democracy
and pluralism in international relations
with full respect for the sovereignty, terri¬
torial integrity and political independence
of States, and the sovereign equality and
self-determination of peoples are the pillars
of our regional system;
5. We consider that the defence and
strengthening of representative democ¬
racy constitute the best guarantee of the
effective enjoyment of all human rights,
and stress that the rupture of the democ
ratic order threatens human rights in the
country concerned and has negative reper¬
cussions on the countries of the region,
particularly neighbouring countries;
13. We draw attention to the urgent need
to establish mechanisms and programmes
for the defence and protection of children
and adolescents, in particular, in relation to
abandoned and street children, and for
Governments to set up national commis¬
sions for the monitoring and follow-up
of the Convention on the Rights of the
Child, made up of governmental and non¬
governmental organizations; we trust,
moreover, that the international concern
expressed at the situation of the children in
our region will translate into concrete
forms of co-operation with the pro¬
grammes and projects established at the
national level;
14. We reaffirm that Governments must
emphasize the implementation of actions
to recognize the rights of women, to pro¬
mote their participation in national life
with equality of opportunity, to eradicate
all forms of hidden or overt discrimination
on grounds of sex, race or social status
and, especially, to eliminate gender-based
violence, as well as all forms of sexual
exploitation. Wc recommend that the
World Conference promote the relevant
international instruments;
15. We welcome the celebration in 1993 of
the International Year of the World's
Indigenous People; we recognize the enor¬
mous contribution of indigenous peoples
to the development and plurality of our
societies and wc reaffirm our commitment
to their economic, social and cultural well-
being and our obligation to respect their
own initiatives and participation, recog¬
nizing the value and diversity of their cul¬
tures and their forms of social organiza¬
tion, without detriment to the unity of
the State;
16. We attach the utmost importance to the
observance of the human rights and fun¬
damental freedoms of vulnerable groups
and the elimination of all forms of dis¬
crimination against them, and to the devel¬
opment of norms which protect those
groups not yet covered by relevant instru¬
ments;
17. We attach the greatest importance to
consideration of the topic of disability and
human rights, and affirm that, in order to
ensure compliance with existing norms of
protection, there is a need to elaborate an
international convention that will provide,
on the basis of equality, for the full exercise
and enjoyment of the fundamental rights
of disabled persons, in order to incorporate
them fully into the active life of the com¬
munity, and to intensify efforts to prevent
disability;
18. We consider that efforts must be inten¬
sified to improve the situation of migrant
workers and their families according to
the principle of non-discrimination, and
we encourage Governments to adhere to
the International Convention on the Pro¬
tection of the Rights of All Migrant
Workers and Members of Their Families;
19. We express our commitment to pro¬
mote and protect all of the human rights
and fundamental freedoms of elderly per¬
sons, as established in national and inter¬
national instruments, and to guarantee the
full access of this vulnerable group to social
security benefits and to the specific pro¬
tection mechanisms recommended in the
Vienna International Plan of Action on
Ageing;
20. Wc recognize the need to respect the
princple of non-discrimination and to
guarantee the legal and social equality of
people infected with human immunodefi¬
ciency virus (HIV) and people with
acquired immunodeficiency syndrome
(Aids), as well as their right to receive the
necessary treatment, and the need to take
public health measures to prevent the pro¬
liferation of this illness;
21. Wc reiterate our concern about, and our
condemnation of, the various forms of ter¬
rorism, including the activities of armed
groups that sow terror in the population
and of drug traffickers, who threaten the
exercise of democracy and arc serious
obstacles to the full realization of all human
rights and fundamental freedoms in our
region;
29. We stress that the promotion and
defence of human rights must be given
priority within the United Nations, and _ _
that this must be reflected in the distribu- ^t ¡S
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
A
*
tion of the Organization's budgetary
resources;
30. We stress the importance of strength¬
ening the Centre for Human Rights by
providing it with the necessary resources
so that it may expeditiously and effec¬
tively provide a wide range of human rights
advisory services, taking into account the
current historical, political and social sit¬
uation of requesting Governments;
31. We reaffirm the importance of incor¬
porating the topic of human rights issues
into the education imparted by States, and
recommend that its dissemination, both
theoretical and practical, be established
as a priority objective of educational
policies.
The Bangkok
Declaration
Regional Meeting for Asia
The Ministers and representatives of Asian
States, meeting at Bangkok from 29 March
to 2 April 1993, pursuant to General
Assembly resolution 46/1 16 of 17 December
1991 in the context of preparations for the
World Conference on human rights,
Adopt this Declaration, to be known as
"The Bangkok Declaration", which con¬
tains the aspirations and commitments of
the Asian region:
1. Reaffirm their commitment to the prin¬
ciples contained in the Charter of the
United Nations and the Universal Decla¬
ration of Human Rights as well as the full
realization of all human rights throughout
the world;
_ _ 2. Underline the essential need to create
TT T" favourable conditions for effective enjoy
ment of human rights at both the national
and international levels;
3. Stress the urgent need to democratize the
United Nations system, eliminate selec¬
tivity and improve procedures and mech¬
anisms in order to strengthen international
co-operation, based on principles of
equality and mutual respect, and ensure a
positive, balanced and non-confrontational
approach in addressing and realizing all
aspects of human rights;
4. Discourage any attempt to use human
rights as a conditionality for extending
development assistance;
5. Emphasize the principles of respect for
national sovereignty and territorial
integrity as well as non-interference in the
internal affairs of States, and the non-use of
human rights as an instrument of polit¬
ical pressure;
6. Reiterate that all countries, large and
small, have the right to determine their
political systems, control and freely utilize
their resources, and freely pursue their eco¬
nomic, social and cultural development;
7. Stress the universality, objectivity and
non-selectivity of all human rights and the
need to avoid the application of double
standards in the implementation of human
rights and its politicization, and that no
violation of human rights can be justified;
8. Recognize that while human rights are
universal in nature, they must be consid¬
ered in the context of a dynamic and
evolving process of international norm-
setting, bearing in mind the significance of
national and regional particularities and
various historical, cultural and religious
backgrounds;
9. Recognize further that States have the
primary responsibility for the promotion
and protection of human rights through
appropriate infrastructure and mecha¬
nisms, and also recognize that remedies
must be sought and provided primarily
through such mechanisms and procedures;
10. Reaffirm the interdependence and indi¬
visibility of economic, social, cultural, civil
and political rights, and the need to give
equal emphasis to all categories of human
rights;
17. Reaffirm the right to development, as
established in the Declaration on the Right
to Development, as a universal and inalien¬
able right and an integral part of funda¬
mental human rights, which must be real¬
ized through international co-operation,
respect for fundamental human rights, the
establishment of a monitoring mechanism
and the creation of essential international
conditions for the realization of such right;
18. Recognize that the main obstacles to
the realization of the right to development
lie at the international macroeconomic level,
as reflected in the widening gap between the
North and the South, the rich and the poor;
1 9. Affirm that poverty is one of the major
obstacles hindering the full enjoyment of
human rights;
22. Reaffirm their strong commitment to
the promotion and protection of the rights
of women through the guarantee of equal
participation in the political, social, eco¬
nomic and cultural concerns of society,
and the eradication of all forms of dis¬
crimination and of gender-based violence
against women;
23. Recognize the rights of the child to
enjoy special protection and to be afforded
the opportunities and facilities to develop
physically, mentally, morally, spiritually
and socially in a healthy and normal manner
and in conditions of freedom and dignity;
29. Stress the importance of strengthening
the United Nations Centre for Human
Rights with the necessary resources to
enable it to provide a wide range of advi¬
sory services and technical assistance pro¬
grammes in the promotion of human rights
to requesting States in a timely and effec¬
tive manner, as well as to enable it to
finance adequately other activities in the
field of human rights authorized by com¬
petent bodies;
30. Call for increased representation of
the developing countries in the Centre for
Human Rights.
The Cairo
Declaration
on Human Rights
in Islam
The Member States of the Organization of
the Islamic Conference,
Reaffirming the civilizing and historical
role of the Islamic Ummah which God
made the best nation that has given
mankind a universal and well-balanced
civilization in which harmony is estab¬
lished between this life and the hereafter
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
and knowledge is combined with faith;
and the role that this Ummah should play
to guide a humanity confused by com¬
peting trends and ideologies and to provide
solutions to the chronic problems of this
materialistic civilization;
Wishing to contribute to the efforts of
mankind to assert human rights, to protect
man from exploitation and persecution,
and to affirm his freedom and right to a
dignified life in accordance with the Islamic
Shari'ah*;
Convinced that mankind which has
reached an advanced stage in materialistic
science is still, and shall remain, in dire
need of faith to support its civilization and
of a self motivating force to guard its rights;
Believing that fundamental rights and
universal freedoms in Islam are an integral
part of the Islamic religion and that no
one as a matter of principle has the right to
suspend them in whole or in part or violate
or ignore them in as much as they are
binding divine commandments, which are
contained in the Revealed Books of God
and were sent through the last of His
Prophets to complete the preceding divine
messages thereby making their observance
an act of worship and their neglect or vio¬
lation an abominable sin, and accordingly
every person is individually responsible
and the Ummah collectively responsible
for their safeguard.
Proceeding from the above-mentioned
principles,
Declare the following:
Article 1:
a) All human beings form one family
whose members are united by submission
to God and descent from Adam. All men
are equal in terms of basic human dignity
and basic obligations and responsibilities,
without any discrimination on the grounds
of race, colour, language, sex, religious
belief, political affiliation, social status or
other considerations. True faith is the guar¬
antee for enhancing such dignity along the
path to human perfection.
b) All human beings are God's sub¬
jects, and the most loved by Him are those
who are most useful to the rest of His sub¬
jects, and no one has superiority over
another except on the basis of piety and
good deeds.
Article 6:
a) Woman is equal to man in human
dignity, and has rights to enjoy as well as
duties to perform; she has her own civil
entity and financial independence, and the
right to retain her name and lineage.
b) The husband is responsible for the
support and welfare of the family.
Article 10:
Islam is the religion of unspoiled
nature. It is prohibited to exercise any
form of compulsion on man or to exploit
his poverty or ignorance in order to con¬
vert him to another religion or to atheism.
Article 11:
a) Human beings are born free, and
no one has the right to enslave, humiliate,
oppress or exploit them, and there can be
no subjugation but to God the Most-High.
b) Colonialism of all types being one of
the most evil forms of enslavement is
totally prohibited. Peoples suffering from
colonialism have the full right to freedom
and self-determination. It is the duty of all
States and peoples to support the struggle
of colonized peoples for the liquidation
of all forms of colonialism and occupa¬
tion, and all States and peoples have the
right to preserve their independent identity
and exercise control over their wealth and
natural resources.
Article 12:
Every man shall have the right, within
the framework of Shari'ah, to free move¬
ment and to select his place of residence
whether inside or outside his country, and
if persecuted is entitled to seek asylum in
another country. The country of refuge
shall ensure his protection until he reaches
safety, unless asylum is motivated by an act
which Shari'ah regards as a crime.
Article 16:
Everyone shall have the right to enjoy
the fruits of his scientific, literary, artistic
or technical production and the right to
protect the moral and material interests
stemming therefrom, provided that such
production is not contrary to the principles
of Shari'ah.
Article 19:
a) All individuals are equal before the
law, without distinction between the ruler
and the ruled.
b) The right to resort to justice is guar¬
anteed to everyone.
c) Liability is in essence personal.
d) There shall be no crime or punish¬
ment except as provided for in the Shari'ah.
e) A defendant is innocent until his
guilt is proven in a fair trial in which he
shall be given all the guarantees of defence.
Article 22:
a) Everyone shall have the right to
express his opinion freely in such manner
as would not be contrary to the princi¬
ples of the Shari'ah.
b) Everyone shall have the right to
advocate what is right, and propagate what
is good, and warn against what is wrong and
evil according to the norms of Islamic
Shari'ah.
c) Information is a vital necessity to
society. It may not be exploited or misused
in such a way as may violate sanctities and
the dignity of Prophets, undermine moral
and ethical values or disintegrate, corrupt
or harm society or weaken its faith.
d) It is not permitted to arouse nation¬
alistic or doctrinal hatred or to do any¬
thing that may be an incitement to any
form of racial discrimination.
Article 23:
a) Authority is a trust; and abuse or
malicious exploitation thereof is absolutely
prohibited, so that fundamental human
rights may be guaranteed.
b) Everyone shall have the right to par¬
ticipate, directly or indirectly in the admin¬
istration of his country's public affairs. He
shall also have the right to assume public
office in accordance with the provisions of
Shari'ah.
Article 24:
All the rights and freedoms stipulated
in this Declaration are subject to the
Islamic Shari'ah.
Article 25:
The Islamic Shari'ah is the only source of
reference for the explanation or clarifica¬
tion of any of the articles of this Declaration.
Cairo, 14 Muharram 1411H
5 August 1990
* Shari'ah: the Holy Law of Islam. Editor
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
HAITI
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
KingHenry'sfabulous
works
by Francis Leary
46
Inthe Caribbean lies an island known
as the "Pearl of the Antilles". Here
Christopher Columbus, westward
bound from Seville in 1492 to seek the
riches of the Indies, made his first
promising landfall in the New World. A
large, beautiful island, it was a green,
forested land with sparkling white beaches
and, in the interior, lofty mountains where
roamed the Arawak Indian tribe. He called
it "Hispaniola", after his Spanish sponsors.
Going ashore on the northwest coast,
Columbus set up the crimson and gold
standard of Spain, to found his first set¬
tlement in America. As it was December
26th, he baptised the post "La Navidad", for
the Nativity of Christ. When he departed,
he left a small company of thirty-nine men,
but the post was destroyed by the Indians
and only vestiges remained. But more
white men would arrive, well-armed, to
overpower and enslave the natives.
In 1697, Spain ceded to France the
western third of the island, which became
the colony of Saint-Domingue, now Haiti.
Near the site of La Navidad is the present
National Historical Park, comprising twenty-
five square kilometres. Here the visitor will
find, towering heavenwards, the huge
Citadel built by King Henry I, who ruled as
absolute monarch from 181 1 to 1820.
To reach this massive fortress, which
cost so much in toil and blood, one pro¬
ceeds on horseback along a narrow road
that snakes upward for 1,000 metres. As the
fierce tropical sun burns away the
shrouding mist, a gigantic shape emerges
like the prow of a great ship. It is the
citadel's Coidavid tower and battery,
named for Queen Marie-Louise Coidavid,
the king's wife. She was the daughter of
the innkeeper of the Auberge de la
Couronne, where Henry Christophe once
served as a waiter.
From the summit of the Queen's tower,
rising forty metres from the base, one gazes
at the distant roofs of Cap Haitien, far
below, and the wide curving bay where in
1778 the French Admiral d'Estaing
dropped anchor. He wanted 1,500 likely
lads, both slave and free, to aid the
colonists in the American Revolution
against British rule.
Young Henry Christophe was eager to
go. Born in Grenada, in the Windward
Islands, in 1767, he had worked his way up
from sugar mills to apprentice to a master
mason. At the age of twelve he ran away, to
be seized by the French captain of a slave
ship and taken to Saint-Domingue, where
he was sold to a naval officer with
d'Estaing's fleet.
His experience of the American Revo¬
lution inspired Christophe. He met other
freedom fighters from Saint-Domingue
and other islands of the French Antilles,
both black and mulatto, and he felt that
what the American colonists could do, the
slaves in their island might also achieve.
Such dreams became reality with the
tumult in France itself, when the ancient
monarchy was overthrown by men with a
passion for liberty and equality. In March
1792, the National Convention in Paris
enfranchised mulattos and black freedmen
in the Antilles, to the fury of the French
colonists. They broke with Paris, called on
the British to succour them, and executed
anyone who tried to claim his rights.
When in 1794 the Commissioners from
Paris abolished slavery, the blacks rallied
to the French Republic to drive out the
British who had occupied Port-au-Prince.
Finally, the liberated slaves turned on all
the whites who still barred their freedom.
Three brilliant black tacticians and former
slaves, Toussaint L'Ouverture, Jean-Iacques
Dessalines and Henry Christophe, out-
generalled the whites by their guerilla war¬
fare. The 40,000 colonists who had
enslaved a half million blacks were over¬
whelmed, slain or put to flight. It was the
first and only successful slave insurrec¬
tion of the New World.
AMERICA'S FIRST BLACK REPUBLIC
WINS INDEPENDENCE
The fatal imbalance in numbers, which
did not prevail elsewhere in the Caribbean,
was due to the greed of the French
planters, who craved riches by ever-
expanding production, especially of sugar
and coffee, with a great mass of slaves. In
two years only, 1787 and 1788, over 60,000
slaves were imported from Africa.
However, Napoleon Bonaparte, now
First Consul of France, sent an army of
26,000 veterans and a fleet of sixty war¬
ships to retake the "Pearl of the Antilles".
Under General Leclerc, Napoleon's brother-
in-law, the French broke the black resis¬
tance, while Toussaint was lured into a trap
and seized, to be despatched to die in a
French dungeon in the Jura hills. The brief
era of black freedom was apparently over.
Abruptly, an epidemic of yellow fever
struck the French a devastating blow. Vic¬
torious from February to June 1802, the
invading army was nowbarely able to main¬
tain control of Saint-Domingue. Leclerc
himself died in October, and Pauline, his
wife and Napoleon's sister, took his body
back to France. The blacks surged again
under Dessalines and Henry Christophe
and won the decisive battle of Vertieres,
near Cap Haitien, on 18 November 1803.
On 1 January 1804, at Gonaives on the
west coast, Dessalines proclaimed the
Republic ofHaiti, thus reviving the original
Indian name of "land ofmountains". Haiti
was the first black republic in America and
the second colony to win independence. In
October, Dessalines, following Napoleon's
lead, took the title of emperor. He first
conceived of building a mighty fortress
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Above, piles of cannonballs
on the western flank of the
Citadel.
Opposite page, Henry
Christophe (1767-1820).
Woodcarving by an unknown
artist.
on the mountain peak that the peasants
termed "the Bishop's Bonnet". When in
1806 the new emperor fell victim to an
angry mob incited byAlexandre Pétion, a
rival quadroon general, Henry Christophe
took over the project. Elected President, he
became King Henry I in 1811, reigning
over the north of Haiti.
SCANNING THE HORIZON FOR THE
TRICOLOUR OF FRANCE
In King Henry's golden days, the monarch
himselfwould stand for hours on the ram¬
parts of La Coidavid, elegantly attired in
blue swallow-tail coat with gold buttons,
white nankin breeches and black boots. On
his head perched a cocked hat, worn fore
and aft in British style. At his side stood his
trusty aide, the quadroon Pompée Vastey,
bearing the royal brass telescope through
which Henry surveyed his domain.
Below the Citadel, on the North Plain,
stretched the plantations tended by a mul
titude of black subjects, growing coffee,
sugar, rice and cotton. Hours ofworkwere
strict: "From dawn to 8 a.m., then one
hour for prayers and breakfast; from nine
to twelve, then two hours for dinner; from
2 p.m. until sundown."
Often the king scanned the horizon,
looking for tall ships and the tricolour of
France. He was obsessed. The French
would return, as they had years before, to
destroy the black realm, even though it
was protected to some extent by Henry's
friends the British. But if the French should
manage to land, Henry was ready for them.
Assisted by the Haitian engineer Henri
Barré, the monarch drove on his grand
project to build the Citadel with a hurri¬
cane of energy. Like pharaoh's slaves
building the pyramids under the lash,
thousands of men toiled upward bearing
bricks and mortar or dragging ponderous
cannons. Once apprentice to a mason,
Henry himself sometimes lent a hand.
Though men might lose their footing on
the vertiginous slope and fall screaming
into the abyss, nothing stopped the frantic
pace of construction.
The Citadel formed an irregular quad¬
rangle, with four great towers, protected by
eight batteries in tiered casements of
twenty cannon each. These cannon ofvar¬
ious calibres were sited on mobile gun
carriages to cover all angles of fire. Only the
west front, with its sheer drop, had no
defending battery. Within the walls, on
average 3.5 metres thick, was a central
court, the Place des Armes, around which
were the governor's palace, barracks for
2,000 men or 5,000 in an emergency, a
chapel, a powder magazine and wells for
cooling the guns. A huge cistern stored
drinking water, while a sewage system car¬
ried waste beyond the walls.
On the south, the approach to the
Citadel was guarded by the four redoubts
on the plateau of Les Ramiers, an out¬
cropping ofthe crest on which the Citadel
stood. At Les Ramiers were also living
quarters to supplement the Citadel's facil¬
ities. The ensemble of the King's great work
covered 10,000 square metres and could
accommodate the royal family, the court
and government in addition to the thou¬
sands of soldiers in the garrison.
After descending the winding treach¬
erous roadway from the Citadel, the visitor
arrives at the village of Milot, twenty kilo¬
metres from Cap Haitien. Here the
grandiose ruin of Henry's royal palace
looms, even its present blackened shell a
visionarywonder. Built by black men at the
direction of a black king, the palace was
intended to show that blacks, though
former slaves, could rival the magnificence
of white monarchs.
King Henry created the finest mansion
in America, rising four stories above a
broad open terrace where fountains 4J
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
played, with canals and basins in the gar¬
dens, as at Versailles. The terrace was
reached by a double marble staircase, rem¬
iniscent of Fontainebleau. With red-tiled
roof and peach-brick walls, this rose-
coloured palace was called "Sans-Souci" in
imitation ofFrederick the Great. Tall ogival
windows glittered in the sun, while the
rooms within were paved with polished
hardwood. On the great gilded carriage of
His Black Majesty could be seen the sun
motif of the Sun-King.
In the grand hall, hung with French
and Flemish tapestries, under the vigi¬
lance of the Royal Dahomey Guard, the
King held audience everyThursday. In the
morning, the peasants came with their
complaints, while the afternoon was
reserved for the nobility. Wearing their
prescribed attire ofwhite tunics, silk hose,
red shoes and swords with gilded hilts,
they sat on folding chairs before the
monarch on his golden throne.
All this finery had to be ordered from
abroad, as well as the decor of the palace,
which kept the elite busy on their planta¬
tions to pay for their costumes and their
mansions. Henry had excellent relations
with the British, with whom he traded the
produce of the plantations for gold, estab¬
lishing the kingdom's currency and paying
for imports. Noting the exhausting labour
of the peasants, a British admiral, Sir Home
Popham, warned Henry that he was going
too far, too fast. Alexandre Pétion, whose
lax rule in the south made him popular,
had an army ready to intervene should
Henry falter. To this warning, the King
One of the Citadel's many cannon
emplacements.
replied: "If we could lay our hands on
things we have made, monuments, towers,
palaces, we might find our self-respect.
While I live, I shall try to build that pride we
need and in terms that white men as well
as black can understand. I shall teach pride
if I break every back in my kingdom!"
Yet Henry had other plans for his
people besides endless toil. Most of his
170,000 subjects were illiterate, as was the
King himself. Importing teachers from
Britain and making use of educated
mulattos, he created free primary schools
and lycées, which soon had over 2,000
students.
A ruler of such energy and competence
might have governed for many years, but
inAugust 1820 a stroke left him paralysed.
He struggled to carry on but, unable to
walk, he could no longer control events. As
the ancient mystique of African voodoo,
which Henry had tried to banish, now
swept the kingdom, his subjects aban¬
doned the crippled monarch, while
Pétion's army invaded Port-au-Prince, as
the admiral had foretold. Realizing that
his reign was over, King Henry put a bullet
through his heart.
FRANCIS LEARY is an American writer, based
in Paris, who has written extensively on historical
subjects for European and American publications,
especially on the period from the fifteenth century
to the First World War.
RESTORING HENRY'S MONUMENTS
Long abandoned, King Henry's works presented a
formidable job of restoration. When he died, his
palace was pillaged, while the Citadel, already shat¬
tered by the explosion of the powder magazine in
1818, was also vandalized and the interior set
ablaze. In 1 842, further substantial damage was
done by an earthquake. Because access to the
Citadel was so difficult, however, the 1 8th-century
armament of 163 guns, considered a unique col¬
lection, was preserved. The roofs and north façade
of the palace had gone, while on the south façade
the walls were cracked and windowless. Frequent
flooding has undermined the foundations.
The programme of restoration of Henry's
monuments, sponsored by Unesco and the United
Nations Development Programme (UNDP), was
undertaken in 1 980. It was directed by the noted
Haitian architect Albert Mangones, with UNESCO's
technical adviser Giselle Hyvert, and employed
Haitian staff and workers. Since no original plans
exist, it was necessary to do extensive research.
Workshops in architectural design, masonry,
woodwork, ironwork and tiles were organized.
One workshop at Milot produced more than
150,000 tiles and bricks, while another at the
Citadel turned out hinges, hooks, locks and paint.
To stop flooding, drainage was essential for
both Citadel and palace. Retaining walls were
erected to shore up the battlements and to close
fissures caused by the explosion. Cannon were
positioned on their repaired gun carriages and the
vaults of the casements restored. This armament,
with 30,000 cannonballs and shells, should be a
major tourist attraction when the Citadel-Museum
is opened. Special rooms in the museum will be
devoted to Henry Christophe and to the Liberator,
Toussaint L'Ouverture. When work stopped in
1 99 1 , the basic tasks were completed, and Henry's
grandeur preserved for posterity. F. L.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Charles Edouard Jeanneret-Gris, known as
Le Corbusier (1 887- 1 965).
Tlie visionary architect and town-
planner Le Corbusier (Charles-
EdouardJeanneret; 1887-1965) was
one ofthe speakers at a symposium
organized by the Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation in Venice
in 1934. Published below are extracts
from the address in which explained
why, in his opinion, Venice is an
outstandingly successful city.
Le Corbusier
Venice: a picture ofharmony
Text selected and presented by
Edgardo Canton
Venice is a totality. In its present state
of conservation it is a unique phe¬
nomenon, a unique example of
total harmony, of utter purity and of the
unity of a civilization. It has come down to
us intact for one simple reason: it is built on
water. Since the water has not changed,
Venice could not change either! It has
remained entire. For those who seek to see
to what innumerable peaks ofperfection a
healthy system can lead humankind, Venice
is an extraordinary example.
Who was the genius who, at a certain
moment in time, had the idea of turning
what might have been just a small town
into a city with the potential for develop¬
ment? It was a great and strikingly insightful
conception of what a city can offer. The
first step was to create the necessary ameni¬
ties Venice is entirely made up of such
amenities. What came first? Transport. It
is central to all Venetian preoccupations, for
water is everywhere, a means of defence
but also an obstacle to movement. The
problem is how people can travel about
and live on the water, not just once in a
while but as they go about their daily busi¬
ness. So by a set of circumstances of great
interest from the point ofview ofart for art
is a way of putting things in order, in their
place, where they fit one thing leading
implacably to another, life gradually estab¬
lishes itself on the lagoon. A city is born
and people live in it, enjoying amenities so
excellent that they remain in perfectly good
working order to the present day, when no
other city in the world has been able to
resist the explosive incursion ofmachines.
It is not for the palaces ofVenice alone
that I reserve my admiration. I observe the
city from the moment I arrive at the railway
terminus, the steps that take me down to
the waterside; then the gondola that is
waiting for me. What strikes me first and
foremost is not the romantic appeal of the
gondola but the discovery ofwhat a mag¬
nificent device this intensely rational inven¬
tion is. To what miracle is it due that, ever
since people have been describing Venice
and painters have depicted the city, the
gondola has not changed its shape? How
has it escaped the whims ofchanging styles
and fashions? Except for a few unimportant
decorations, a few carvings that make it
neither more beautiful nor more ugly, some
little bronzes representing a chimaera or
the like, mere details, the biological state of
the gondola that of a marvellous, bal¬
ancing instrument, very like an aeroplane
in its mechanical reality has never
changed, has remained constant, proving
the existence of links of cause and effect
that are fundamental if a given object con¬
cerned has always served people's needs
and has been built to a human scale.
Let us move on from the gondolas to the
little harbours where they come alongside,
to the water gates opening into the houses,
to the bridges one crosses, built strictly on
a human scale and made proportional to
this means of transport. I am not speaking
here of the Rialto bridge, which mayor
may not be very beautiful, but rather of
the countless little bridges that are, as it
were, the setting for a precious object a
gondola with a gondolier standing upright
aboard. Complete unity reigns, the steps
where one disembarks are extraordinarily
ingenious in their design I could go on.
Venice's streets too are extraordinary:
streets where we go on foot, where we are
masters of terra firma, lords of the land;
where we are at peace, where our ears are
soothed, where we can safely stroll where
our footsteps take us streets without
traffic! In Rome the other day, I publicly
stated the case for the dignity of the pedes¬
trian. In the name of the world's cities, I
called for an end to the scandal ofmodern
streets slashed in two by cars, an end to the 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
R H I TheljNESCO
nSBXOURIER
threat of death in the streets. I said that it
was possible to separate pedestrians com¬
pletely from cars, that they could have the
cities at ground level entirely to themselves.
The Venetians are the undisputed masters
of their city's streets, the pedestrian is king.
Have you noticed how proud and cheerful
Venetians are, in the streets, in the squares,
on the great Riva degli Schiavoni?
The streets, the pedestrians, the water
are all part of a wonderful unity; we are
now ready to appreciate all the differences
of scale and all the subtlest nuances of this
ensemble. We appreciate them because
our eyes are 1.6 metres above the ground,
and they are the instruments with which we
measure things. What is the value of the
gigantic but out-of-place, the dispropor¬
tionate? In Venice nothing is out of pro¬
portion, thanks to its watery setting.
Streets on land and streets of water:
perfect measure. Now consider the houses,
another element of the art. Admittedly,
those who have tasted the bitter flavour of
modern life can no longer live in Venice,
which is built to suitwalking. Things move
too slowly there. Butwhen I try to see things
from the point ofview ofnormal times and
slower paces, I can see everywhere the care
that went into every gesture and every deci¬
sion when the houses were built. I am not
talking about the palaces; palaces don't
matter to me! House after house, dwelling
after dwellingwas built, with gardens wher¬
ever a little of the scarce soil could be set
aside. Here too all is measure and propor¬
tion and a human presence. Explore the
city to its innermost recesses and you will
appreciate that everywhere, in this superla¬
tive example ofan urban undertaking, there
is tenderness.
Here at last we come to the reason why
the whole world speaks of Venice and is
right to do so. The third factor influencing
the character of the place, more than prob¬
lems of transport and housing, is the outlook
that turned inert materials into a living,
breathing city civic spirit! It bursts forth
here as it does virtually nowhere else in
Western civilization. Civic spirit determined
everything inVenice. It inspired the builders,
it created the great public palazzi, the
statues, the paintings. It breathed a beauty
that is both palpable and omnipresent into
everyday items. I have shown you how far
this "decorative art" (what a pathetic term
that is!) can extend.
I should stress that this unanimous art is
not frivolous; on the contrary, it is found in
the implements ofdaily life, as when it cre¬
ated the gondola, that most purelyVenetian
object, and gives us the right to laugh offthe
complaints and lamentations we are always
hearing today about the standardization of
modem life. The gondola is a standardized
object a lot more standardized than a car.
It has not changed in centuries, and has thus
attained the perfection sometimes found in
Greek temples. There was only one kind of
temple, so the creative impulses could be
concentrated on the matter of quality. The
amenities of urban life transport and
housing plus civic spirit drew the entire
population into becoming part ofa totality
an enthusiastic and fruitful gesture that
amounted as it were to a mark of affection
bestowed on each object.
The result was the joy ofcreation and of
participating in a collective act, and the
happy outcome of the enterprise may be
seen today, five or ten centuries later, in
the proud and cheerful Venetian populace
crowding the city's streets, squares and
magnificent waterfront.
Let us now leave Venice and set foot
again in contemporary realities.
SO
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, page 3: © Superstock/Vloo, Paris. Page 2: © Agnès Andrée Legrand, Dammarie-sur-Loing, France.
Page S: All rights reserved. Page 7: Christian Sappa © Rapho, Paris. Page 8: © Fabian, Paris. Page 9: ©
Private collection. Pages 10, 1 1 : © Claude Sauvageot, Paris. Page 1 3: © Eugenia Wolfowicz, Paris. Page 1 4:
© Ariette Gimaray Gallery, Paris. Page 15: Bruce Patón © Panos Pictures, London. Page 16: Sebastiào
Salgado © Magnum, Paris. Page 17: G. Peress © Magnum. Paris. Page 18: © Alinari Giraudon, Paris. Page
19: Josef Koudelka © Magnum, Paris. Pages 20, 35: Paul Smith © Panos Pictures, London. Page 21: Penny
Tweedie © Panos Pictures, London. Page 22: Sean Sprague © Panos Pictures, London. Pages 23, 25: Frilet
© Sipa Press, Paris. Page 24: G. Carde © Explorer, Paris. Page 26 (top): Toni Comiti © Gamma, Paris.
Page 26 (middle): Charles Sattleberger © Gamma, Paris. Page 26 (below): Pierre Laboute ©Jacana, Paris.
Page 27: © Christophe Lepetit, Paris. Pages 28-29, 29: © Giraudon, Paris. Page 31: William Knosi ©
Gamma, Paris. Page 32: Frederic Reglain © Gamma, Paris. Page 33: © Artis, Paris. Page 36: Chris Stowers
© Panos Pictures, London. Page 37: Unesco. Pages 38, 39, 40, 41, 42 43, 44, 45: © Slobodan Bijeljac,
Paris. Page 46: Rémi Berli © Rapho, Paris. Page 47: Y. Gladu © Explorer, Paris. Page 48: M. Moisnard ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 49: R. Doisneau © Rapho, Paris.
47th YEAR
Published monthly in 32 languages and in Braille by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31. rue François Bonvin, 750IS Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation:
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin {Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant:
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Serpil Gogen (Ankara)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard]. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Sangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tei. 45.68.45.65),
jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
I year: 2 1 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies arc sent to the editor. Signed arti¬
cles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be sup¬
plied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed arti¬
cles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opin.ons of Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Umesco Courier staff. The bound¬
aries on maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is pro¬
duced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (I) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor. Michigan 48 1 00 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition. Indian Head
Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street. New York. USA; (4) Bell and Howell Co.. Old
Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Printed ¡n Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL: CI -MARS 1994
COMMISSION PARITAIRE Nc 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: IMPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL. 2, rue Christop he-Plantin
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN 004 1 -5278 N" 3- 1 994-OPI-94-524A
This issue comprises 52 pages, a 4-page insert between
pages 10-11 and 42-43 and an insert numbered UV.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
PROJET 237
L'HUMANITAIRE
SANS FRONTIÈRES
136 pages - 65 F - Etranger 70 F
Abonnement (4 nos/an) : 230 F - Etranger : 260 F
Pour recevoir ces numéros ou vous abonner, envoyez vos nom,
adresse et règlement à : Assas Editions
14, rue d'Assas - 75006 PARIS - Tél. : (1) 44 39 48 48
ETVDES
Questions
sur les droits de l'homme
H Force armée de l'ONU ou nouvelle ONU ?
Béatrice Pouligny (mars 1994)
Jugement des crimes contre l'humanité
en Yougoslavie
Marcel Merle (mai 1994)
Le numéro : 55 F - Etranger : 62 F
Abonnement (11 n°s/an) : 450 F - Etranger : 550 F
INSTITUT
CATHOLIQUE
DE PARIS
UNIVERSITAS
CATHOLICA
PARISIENSIS
40 ORGANISMES DE FORMATION
UNIVERSITAIRE ET SUPÉRIEURE
PLUS DE 16 000 ÉTUDIANTS
115 NATIONALITÉS REPRÉSENTÉES
Un Espace Universitaire Original qui
conjuque TRADITION du SAVOIR
et TALENT de L'INNOVATION
1
Association reconnue d'utilité publique
la Catho de Paris est habilitée à recevoir
DES DONS & LEGS
L'INSTITUT CATHOLIQUE DE PARIS,
c'estdécider de participer
à SON RÔLE dans la recherche et la
présentation des valeurs éthiques et
religieuses,
et à SON ACTION au service de la
FORMATION HUMAINE,
PROFESSIONNELLE
ET SPIRITUELLE,
21, RUE D'ASSAS 75270 PARIS CEDEX 06
TÉL. (1) 44 39 52 14 - FAX (1) 45 44 27 14
CCP 270 43 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
S;..':
^
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine
published in 32 languages and read by hundreds of thousands of
people in 120 countries
Each month it explora the astonishing diversity of world culture and
It associates its readers with UNESCO's mission of furthering "universal respect
for justice, for the ruie of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms.. .without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
MONTH, ESSENTIAL READING F
OF TODAY
UNDERSTANDING PROBLEMS
TOMORROW
PSYCHOANALYSIS: THE HIDDEN I ... A TIME TO LOVE ... WATER OF LIFE ... MINORITIES... WHAT IS
MODERN?... RHYTHM, GESTURE AND THE SACRED... TIME TO DISARM... THE STORY OF NUMBERS... A NORTH-
SOUTH DERATE: THE MEANINC OF PROGRESS. DESERTS... WORLDS WITHIN WORDS... HUMAN NICHTS, THE
UNFINISHED TASK...
FRANCOIS MITTERRAND.. JORRE AMADO... RICHARD ATTENBOROUCH... JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIÈRE... IEAN
LACOUTURE.,. FEDERICO HAYOR... NACUIB NAHFOiZ... SEHRENE OfSHANE... ANDREI VOZNESENSKY...
FREDERIC ROSSIF... HINNERK BRUHNS... CAMILO JOSE CELA... VACLAV HAVEL... SERCEI S. AVERINTSEV...
ERNESTO SABATO... CRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND... CLAUDE LEVI-STRAUSS... LEOPOLDO ZEA... PAULO FREIRÉ...
DANIEL I. BOORSTIN... FRAJCOIS JACOR... MANU DIBANCO... FAROVK HOSNY... SADRUDDIN ACÁ KHAN...
JORCE LAVELU ... LEON SCHWARTZENBERC... TAHAR BEN JELLOUN... CARRIEL CARCÍA MAROUEZ ... JACQUES-
YVES COUSTEAU... MELINA HERCOURI... CARLOS FUENTES... JOSEPH KI-ZERBO... YANDANA SHIVA... WILLIAM
STYRON... OSCAR NIEHEYER... MINIS THEODORAKIS... ATAHUALPA YUPANOUI... HERVÉ BOURGES... ABDEL
RAHHAN EL BACHA... SISARA RINALDI... HUBERT REEVES... JOSÉ CARRERAS... A LETTER FROH FREUD TO
EINSTEIN... LUC FERRY... CHARLES HALAMOUO... UMBERTO ECO... OLIVER STONE... ANDRÉ BRINK... JAMES D.
WATSON... AMOS OZ... HICHEL SERRES... THÉODORE HONOR.. YVES COPPERS... EDOUARD J. MAUNICK...
COMPANIES AND CULTURES
MODERN BUSINESS INTERACTS
0 FEATURING AH INTERVIEW WITH TH
ICAL TRADITIONS
ANTHROPOLOCIST
lALAURIt
]]>
</page>
</document>
