<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="097246eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
r^H
^F. TmWim TviK^lT^i
encounters with other ways of life
GHANA, TRINIDAD,
CHINA, SENEGAL,
SIBERIA, MEXICO...
PAVEL LOUNGUINE,
ALEKSANDAR PETROVIC
FACES OF TIBET
INTERVIEW WITH
JOSÉ DONOSO
ENVIRONMENT
CORAL: TAKING THE
PULSE OF THE PLANET
HERITAGE
LETTER FRON BOROBUDUR
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Af>rica anse
Rise up
from the sleep
that keeps you weak
and voiceless,
sing your song,
recite the verse
waiting on your lips.
Show the new sap
rising
from your deep roots
towards the ripenedfruit
ofyour tempered heart.
Take flight, Africa,
with your own wings.
Spread
your enormous strength
for centuries withheld
in your warm hands
now freed
for the embrace.
Today yourflight
is imperative,
it is essential
to reach
together
for the first time
the same side,
the shore
which is still
denied us.
Unchain yourself
from lenders
and misers,
and trace the road
you wish to follow,
the moment
ofmeeting,
ofmemory and oblivion.
Your diversity
which is your wealth
must unite
with only
the light of dawn
as helper
to guide you to the
shining horizon
we long for.
Africa:
Wake up!
and reveal
the immensity
ofyour dreaming soul.
Federico Mayor
Yamoussoukro, 7 February 1994
Signs and Swirls
(1992), oil on canvas
by the Senegalese artist
Souleymane Keita.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 INTERVIEW WITH
José Donoso
UNESCO IN ACTION
61 NEWSBRIEFS...
64 TESTIMONY
The rescue of the Bulgarian
Jews in 1943
by Emmanuel Vaillant
66 ANNIVERSARY
Olexander Dovzhenko, poet of
the seventh art
by Lubomir Hosejko
68 HERITAGE
The Dawn of Serenity: Letter
from Borobudur
by Eiji Hattori
74 ARCHIVES
The new obscurantism
by Thomas Mann
76 THE DELHI DECLARATION
Towards education for all
78 The U.N. goes to school
by Sally Swing Shelley
79 Letters to the Editor
80 BOOKS OF THE WORLD
Here comes the sun
by Raoul Silva-Cacérès
82 Recent recordings
by Isabelle Leymarie
SURPRISING
STRANGERS
8 Elvis the African by George Darley-Doran
13 Borshch and sympathy by N'Baah Santy
14 Lost illusions by Neil Bissoondath
18 The Indianization of the whites in North America
"Living like savages"
19 Interview with Pavel Lounguine
Inuit blues
21 The genius of peoples
22 The Fulbe and the Samurai code by Ryo Ogawa
24 The hornbill's quest by Kusni Sulang
26 Paulius Normantas:
A photographer in Tibet
30 Dreams of twenty young women
by Hélène Trouche Simon
33 'One turning planet' by David Harris
37 Mexico City: the shock of discovery
38 Interview with Aleksandar Petrovic
My friends the Gypsies
42 The son of Polish Jewish immigrants looks at
the Palestinians by Maurice Rajsfus
45 A European artist discovers the salt
of the earth by Jacques Leenhardt
48 We are Siamese if you please
by Morgan Sportes
50 Café society by Rifâ'ah Râfe' el-Tahtâwî
51 Getting to know Chief lamory
by Louis Gustave Binger
52 When the Mombuttu women cried hosanna
by Georg Schweinfurth
Contents
JULY/AUGUST 1994
Cover:
Meeting between a European
woman and an African in Olduvai Gorge
(United Republic of Tanzania).
53
Greenwatch
Coral: taking the pulse
of the planet
by France Bequette
63
Commentary by
Federico Mayor
Special consultant for this issue:
Myriam Smadja
IM "^
\ irr fm'f^\ "^e Governments of the Sates parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
J\J I -]»%,_,%,_/ "that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
S~\1 [nirn "tnat a Peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
\, J[ I IX I l" lv unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
Published monthly and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXT/WC7 FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, lb NOVEMBER (945
47th year
in 32 languages and in braille
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
talks to
Fernando Ainsa
The Chilean writer José Donoso is a
leading Latin American novelist. After
teaching English literature in the United
States and travelling in many countries,
he lived in Spain until 1980, when he
returned to Chile. His works have been
translated into many languages. Among
those translated into English are The
Obscene Bird of Night (1979), A House
in the Country (1984), and The Garden
Next Door (1992). Here he explains his
conception of the writer's role in
society.
FERNANDO AINSA,
Uruguayan writer, is director of the Unesco
Collection of Representative Works.
In the minds ofcritics and readers alike,
the Latin-American novel no longer occu¬
pies the dominantposition that it heldat the
time ofthe "explosion " ofnovel-writing in
the 1960s, although thegreat writers ofthat
period Gabriel Garcia Marques, Carlos
Fuentes, Mario Vargas Llosa andyourself
are still publishing regularly, and a new
generation ofwriters has emerged in every
one ofthe countries ofLatin America.
A clear distinction has to be drawn
between, on the one hand, the ballyhoo and
commercial exploitation surrounding the
1960s explosion, which I denounced in my
personal account of it (Historia personal
del "boom", 1972), and on the other the
grand ambitions that the writers of the
period entertained to write the "total" novel.
One thing that is certain is that, in the last ten
years, Latin-American novelists have aban¬
doned their dream of upholding, so to
speak, the great blueprints for society that
were a characteristic feature of the political
and cultural life of the 1960s and 1970s.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Those blueprints were an integral part of the
"cosmogonie ideologies" that proposed
universal, radical solutions and stemmed
from an unquestioning belief in the power
of the will.
In Latin America, that period was
marked by a "Bolivarian" dream of the con¬
tinent's literary unity. At the same time,
each novel aimed to be a literary "super-
production" by virtue of its encyclopaedic
accumulation of knowledge. Conversely,
during the 1980s and even more so in the
present decade, novels have ceased to offer
the sort of absolute and all-embracing vision
represented in the weighty tomes that many
authors of my generation perpetrated,
myself included. Our aim was not only to
interpret the world but to change it as well.
Yet you have never been one for cer¬
tainties. You deal rather in doubt, ambi¬
guity and contradictions.
Contradictions and doubts that never¬
theless formed part of an ambitious self-
appointed task, that of saying "everything"
in a novel that aimed to be representative of
a particular moment in history, a moment
whose special, unique nature seemed to us
to be beyond doubt. History is now per¬
ceived subjectively and deciphered through
the individual; what it has gained in relativity
it has lost in "certainty". Novelists today
present individual life-stories, which may be
more or less representative, but they no
longer have any pretensions to give lessons
to their readers. Their characters are helpless,
often loners and disoriented. We have no
place to go to get warm now as we used to
do, when ideology gave us a roof over our
heads: nowadays, and I think this is all to the
good, we are exposed to the elements, no
longer sheltered by revealed truths from
the storms of life.
That is truefor the characters, but what
about the authors? What are theirpoints of
reference now? People have to believe in
something, after all.
Literature and aesthetics have taken the
place of ideologies, and it's not the first
time this has happened. I am thinking, for
instance, of John Milton, the author of
Paradise Lost, tugged this way and that
by the forces of the Renaissance and those
of puritanism. His cultural references were
those of his time: the recently rediscov¬
ered Greek and Latin poets, the writings of
the Fathers of the Church, the Bible he
was writing for a readership steeped in the
Scriptures rather than for one that shared
his political beliefs. At times of crisis, it is
the gossamer threads spun by the authors
of the past that hold writers back from the
brink of the existential void. It is this cul¬
tural heritage that helps them to go on
living. The works of the past are our real
strength and stay: it is on them that we
lean to write new ones, especially when
all the other certainties totter and tremble.
But the crisis also means that individ¬
uals are tempted to withdraw into their
shells, to create a safe hideawayfor them¬
selves. Everythingpoints to thefact that we
are "cocooning" ourselves, to use a
favourite American expression, adopting a
mode of behaviour compounded of self¬
ishness and cosiness, isolation and an
absence ofsolidarity.
I don't know which is worse, individual
cocooning or the collective cocooning in
ideological certainties that used to provide
us with answers to every question. In any
case, it is a very healthy development that
certain barriers have come down and certain
definitions have been challenged. I am
thinking in particular of the little self-con¬
tained worlds created by the disciples of
the various "sects" that have had such an
influence on modern thought, from Freud
to Lacan or from Marx to Althusser, or the
jargon used by some critics, which is impen¬
etrable except to the initiates of their own lit¬
erary coterie! The shackles have all fallen
from us and it seems that nothing else has
yet come along to take their place. The pos
itive side to this, in my opinion, is that we
find ourselves in a new situation, beset with
questions we cannot answer.
Why shouldwriters have all the answers
anyway?
This is perhaps typical of Latin-American
intellectual life. Importuned by the realities
of the world around them, writers feel con¬
stantly obliged to make statements and take
stands. The worst of it is that many of them
feel it their "duty" to voice an opinion on
"Novelists today
present individual
life-stories that may
be more or less
representative, but
they no longer have
any pretensions to
give lessons to their
readers."
everything that happens in their country
and elsewhere in the world. Intellectuals in
our part of the world are "know-alls" who
feel free to hold forth from the pulpit on a
whole range of topics, from economics to
current political affairs, whereas European
writers tend rather to concentrate on the
work in hand, believing, quite rightly, that
the cobbler should stick to his last. So many
"prophets" have come a cropper by dis¬
cussing subjects they know nothing about!
Would it be true to say that the idea, so
fashionable not long ago in Latin America,
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
ofthe writergrappling with the realities of
"the here and now " is today in crisis ?
Every writer is obliged to live with the
uncertainties of his own times. It is some¬
thing inevitable but not specifically Latin-
American. The question "Who are we?" is
implicit in all literature. But it should be
remembered that writers must always be, at
least to some extent, outsiders. If they are
not so by nature, they must be able, albeit at
some personal cost, to distance themselves
from anything that would identify them
too closely with a particular group, ide¬
ology or class, or with their country. One
should be wary of the idea of belonging.
Outsiders see things differently. This is pre¬
cisely what the marginal characters in my
books, those who are "excluded from the
banquet of life", all say.
Chilean writers, in spite ofeverything
and even in the darkest hours of the
Pinochet dictatorship, have always main¬
tained strong emotional ties to their
country. The "garden next door" from
which one ofyour novels takes its title is
that of childhood and the homesickness
that is the backdrop to allyour books.
Chilean writers do, it is true, have a very
special relationship with their country.
Even those of us who have lived and
worked abroad and could be called
"transnational" writers cling to certain
images and memories a secret garden
where we find shelter from the inclement
weather of the real world. As you know, I
am now back living and working in my
own country. I am at present putting the
finishing touches to a novel, Sparrows sing
in Greek, set in the Lota coal-mining
region; the spare, taut language draws
inspiration from the way the miners talk.
Is that why you went back to Chile in
1980, when the dictatorship was in full
swing?
That was only part of the reason. It was
mainly because I felt that everything that
had to be done in Europe had already been
done, and people like me were not needed to
do what remains to be done. I am firmly
"Literature and
aesthetics have
taken the place of
ideologies, and it's
not the first time
this has happened."
convinced of this. I could leave no footsteps
behind me in the Old World, but in Chile
there is still so much to be done. Of course
there was the advantage that in Europe I
was anonymous, I could wear various masks
to "disguise" myself, I could hide and go
unnoticed. In Chile I cannot get away from
the image that people have formed of me.
Everything is preordained: I have to play
out my role as writer which is not easy
when, like me, one is a prey to doubt and
uncertainty. But to answer your question, the
primary reason why I returned to Chile was
homesickness, which gets worse as one gets
older and for which there is no remedy.
The theme ofexile ispainfullypresent
in The Garden Next Door,published [in
Spanish], it is worthpointing out, in 1981,
and the theme ofhomecoming appears in
Desesperanza ("Despair") published in
1986. Is there an autobiographical element
in this?
"Writers must
always be, at least
to some extent,
outsiders."
Many myths have been woven around the
theme of exile. Wherever people go, what¬
ever they do, they take their homeland,
their home town, with them, and there is no
way of going into voluntary exile from one's
own self, whatever some people may think
or claim to the contrary. Even the most cos¬
mopolitan traveller remains bound up with
his place of origin. As the Greek poet Con-
stantine Cavafy wrote, "You'll always end
up in this city". It is worth quoting the
whole poem:
You said: "I'll go to another country, go
to another shore,
find another city better than this one....
You won't find a new country, won't
find another shore.
The city will always pursue you.
You'll walk the same streets, grow old
in the same neighbourhoods, turn grey
in these same houses.
You'll always end up in this city. Don't
hopefor things elsewhere:
there's no shipforyou, there's no road/'
So in the end it's not such a bad thing
to have roots and a home!
I have never said it was, despite the fact that
Chileans, however deep their roots in the
South, of course also feel drawn back to
Europe, which, when all is said and done, is
a part of their background. The theme of
the voyage haunts the works and lives of
many Chilean novelists: take Criollos en
Paris by Joaquin Edwards Bello, Los
trasplantados by Alberto Blest Gana or the
tradition of the "initiatory voyage" to
Europe among nineteenth-century intellec¬
tuals. The great Chilean poets have always
been great travellers too Pablo Neruda,
Vicente Huidobro, even Gabriela Mistral,
despite her profound attachment to the real
life of her country! There's nothing like
having been out in all weathers to make you
appreciate the warmth of hearth and home.
That's why we are now in such a state of
happy uncertainty, torn between the urge
to leave and wanting to stay.
*"The city", from C.P. Cavafy, Collected
Poems, translated by Edmund Keeley & Philip
Sherrard, Chatto & Windus, London, 1975.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Societies have always allocated a special place to the stranger who comes to
them from elsewhere. In Antiquity he would have been a navigator, a merchant,
or an exile. In Athens, before the city-state made a distinction between "bar¬
barians" (foreigners) and "metics" (resident aliens) strangers were protected by
the gods, especially Apollo, himself a god in exile, and to enjoy the "inviolability
of supplicants" they had to carry in the crook of their left arm freshly cut olive
branches bound by narrow white strips of cloth. In those far-off times a Phoeni¬
cian who found himself in Athens, a Cypriot who sailed to Delos, was a man apart,
not necessarily regarded sympathetically. For Aristophanes, a false and rascally
individual was someone who "behaved like an Egyptian". One of the first great
heroes of mythology was Odysseus, an outsider who sailed from island to island,
blown far from home by the wind of fate.
Then the dimensions of the world grew wider. Great conquerors like Alexander
the Great, Julius Caesar, the Arab Muslim general Khaled Ibn al-Walid, Genghis
Khan and the Mogul emperor Akbar redrew the map of the earth. The quest for
URPRISING STRANGERS
the Indies took Marco Polo to China and Christopher Columbus to the Americas,
dreaming of the gold of Cipango. When in the present century the Malian sage
Amadou Hampâté Bâ said that "the whole universe is our planet", he was only
one small step ahead of today's media explosion in which image-hungry cameras
capture dramatic events as they happen and beam them instantly to the four cor-
bV Martin EVGII ners of the earth. Bui barriers aplenty still continue to exist... great walls, iron
Writer and journalist curtains, homeless peoples and travellers without papers.
This double issue of the Unesco Courier contains reports of encounters
between people from different lands and cultures. It explores the freshness and
spontaneity of their reactions as they find themselves at close quarters with unfa¬
miliar ways of life. A Siamese ambassador visits the court of the Sun King. A
member of Trinidad's Indian community feels at home in Canada. The Inuit are
seen through Russian eyes. A Dayak traveller from Borneo meets the Koreans of
China. In Paris, a group of young women from countries of the South talk among
themselves of love and marriage. . . .
Here are travellers intrigued by new ways that they try to translate into
their own terms, getting to know strangers through an effort of comprehension
that, however slightly, changes their own way of seeing the world. Jf
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Elvis
Chief.
visits a neighbouring
Elvis Johnson-ldan is a man with two lives. For eleven
months of the year, he works as the parks manager of a
London municipality, spending the weekends relaxing with
his wife Elizabeth and their three children. In December and
January, however, Elvis is usually to be found in his
birthplace, a little village in Ghana where he reigns supreme
as Nana Otumayin Kofi Idan I, Brahene ofJukwaa. George
Darley-Doran accompanied him on his most recent visit.
by George Darley-Doran Wß AfñCíM
8
Some time ago I came across a small
item in a London newspaper that went as
follows:
"King Gets Back to his Parkland
"Elvis Johnson-ldan, alias Nana Elvis ofJukwaa,
was back in his job as head of Brent Council's
parks department yesterday, after having been
made a chief of his native Fanti tribe in Ghana.
Tt was fascinating,' reported the 37-year-old
chief upon his return. T was absolutely spell¬
bound by it all. On one day I had to bathe in a
wooden tub filled with herbs to tone up my
muscles and skin to get me looking my best.'
Nana Elvis plans to continue with his job at
Brent Council, and visit his tribe once or twice
a year. Apart from that, he and his English-
born wife, Queen Elizabeth, do not expect their
lives to change dramatically. 'We still shop at
Sainsbury's', Queen Elizabeth admitted last
night."
I decided to track down this Anglo-African
chief. I called up the Council in the northwest
London suburb of Brent and was put through to
Mr. Johnson-ldan. He could not have been
friendlier when I told him of my wish to meet
him in order to discuss "a project". Several days
later, I found myself in a big, drab council
building.
Elvis Johnson-ldan welcomed me into his
office. He was of average height, on the portly
side, and his round face was characterized by a
pair of sharp but limpid eyes. His voice was
understated but musical and full of laughter.
He had the ability to make one feel entirely at
ease and we were soon on first-name terms.
Elvis told me his story. He had grown up in
a small town on the Ghanaian coast. Both his
mother and father were Fantis of "noble"
descent, but he had always been fairly oblivious
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
to this. Well into his adulthood, he left Ghana
(and an unsuccessful marriage) to study horti¬
culture in England. He and Elizabeth met at
agricultural college and were soon married. He
took her back to his country, where he was
second in charge at the National Department of
Parks and Gardens. After a couple of years in
Accra, they returned to England, and settled
down. Liz began having children, and their life
became more and more independent of his
Ghanaian origins. Then, one day, Elvis received
the news that his mother had died. Grief-
stricken, he returned to his family village,
Jukwaa, to attend her funeral. In the course of
that visit, he discovered to his amazement
that the "kingmakers" of his village had been
planning for years to make him a chief. This
was all the more surprising in that he was the
youngest of nine brothers. The situation was
thrust upon Elvis, without his being given much
say in the matter. Two months later, he went
back to Jukwaa with his family and was for¬
mally "enstooled" as Nana Otumayin Kofi Idan
I, Brahene of Jukwaa-Idankrom.
Elvis explained to me the meaning of his
formal name. "Nana" is the title preceding the
name of any Fanti, male or female, of noble
descent. "Otumayin" (breaker of men) is the
name of Elvis's father. "Kofi" means "Friday";
many Fantis are named after the day of their
birth. "Brahene" is a designation of chiefdom,
signifying that Elvis has special responsibilities
for the "youth" of his area. Jukwaa is the name
of Elvis's village, and "Idankrom" signifies that
the village is the traditional domain of the Idan
family; "-krom" can effectively be translated
into English as "-ville".
Elvis among his people.
Since the time of his enstoolment, Elvis's
life has been a balancing act between his roles as
head of Brent Council's Department of Parks
and Recreation, husband and father, and Fanti
chieftain. He now visits Ghana once or twice a
year, usually spending a good part of December
and January with his people. This coincides
with the anniversary of his enstoolment (27
December) and Jukwaa's usual end-of-year fes¬
tivities. The rest of Elvis's time is divided
between his job in Brent and his family home.
Elvis told us that he had been subject to a
considerable amount of media attention at the
time of his enstoolment. He had been appalled
at the degree of inaccuracy in the various articles
written about him. Every paper had its own
version of the story. One quality daily had
claimed that he was named after Elvis Presley,
which is clearly impossible if one considers that
Elvis (the chief) was born years before Elvis
(the Pelvis) had cut his first single. The most
common mistake was that Elvis had been made
king of the entire 1.5-million-strong Fanti tribe.
He had, in fact, only been made chief of some
20,000 souls.
Several film companies had expressed interest
in developing Elvis's story into a full-length
movie. With only a few exceptions, he had found
their ideas to be banal at best and at worst an
offence to his people. One studio had suggested
a plot in which his wife would be kidnapped by
another tribe and then rescued amid plenty
of jungle combat by a crack team from the
British army. This was not the kind of publicity
that Elvis wanted to attract. On the other hand,
he was open to anything that would give the
world a better idea of the realities of his people,
their way of life and the problems they faced.
It was arranged that later in the year I would
join Elvis and his family on their annual visit to
Jukwaa, where I would have the opportunity to
see a modern-day African chieftain at work.
Over the next couple of months I spent a
good deal of time piecing together some back¬
ground information about Ghana in general
and the Fantis in particular.
The "stool lands"
I discovered that the Fantis and the better-
known Asante (or Ashanti) are two branches of
a single tribe originally known as the Akan.
Hundreds of years ago, the Akan moved down
from the African interior towards the Gulf of
Guinea. One group went as far as the central
coast of what is now Ghana and evolved into the
Fanti tribe. The other group settled down fur¬
ther inland (in the region surrounding what is
now Kumasi) and developed into the Asante.
The languages of the two tribes became distinct
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
"After a couple of years in Accra, they returned to England,
got married and settled down. Then one day Elvis received
the news that his mother had died. Grief-stricken, he returned
to his family village, Jukwaa, to attend her funeral. In the
course of that visit he discoveredto his amazement
that the 'kingmakers' of his village had been planning for
years to make him a chief."
from one another but remained closely related,
rather like English and French. The turning
point in the history of both tribes came in the
late fifteenth century with the arrival of the
European traders, who came in search of gold
and slaves. From that point on, the Fantis were
under constant attack from the Asante, who
were intent on capturing a bigger slice of the
lucrative coastal trade.
Despite the almost perpetual state of war
between the Fantis and the Asantes, their tribal
institutions were not at all dissimilar. The bloody
conflicts gradually died away, but many of the
institutions have survived intact until today.
The most important one of all is the tradition of
the stool. This is more than just a seat of power,
in that the stool embodies the very spirit of the
people relating to it. Once a chief has been
enstooled, he maintains custody of the stool
and is therefore directly responsible for the spir¬
itual well-being of his subjects. Throughout the
Asante and Fanti tribes there are countless major
and minor stools, each one relating to an area of
land and the people living within that area.
These areas are known as "stool lands". The
C chief acts as custodian of these lands, as opposed
hildren in Elvis's village,
Jukwaa.
to owning them outright. It is, and has always
been, rare for a chief to "personalize" the stool
lands.
The power behind the stool
An important clan will often control more than
one stool. The "blue blood" tends to go back a
good many generations to the time when lands
were originally conquered and settled. Para¬
mount chiefs, chiefs and sub-chiefs are all
selected from eligible males of the "noble" clans.
Chieftains are not chosen according to their
age, but rather to their strength and political
skills. The power behind the stool resides with
the "kingmakers", the group of elders that
decides who is to be enstooled or in the rare
event of abuse, destooled. A Byzantine net¬
work of relationships usually exists between
the kingmakers, the various ranks of chiefs and
those aspiring to chiefdom. In the midst of all
this intrigue is the Queen Mother, who often
plays an influential role in deciding which of her
sons will be enstooled.
Fanti society is based upon kinship and
group solidarity. The isolated individual is con¬
sidered to be a lost and hopeless soul not just
for the course of this life, but for all eternity. This
is because the religious ceremonies of the Fanti
are directed towards their ancestors, who are
considered to exercise surveillance over the
living. There is no activity in life that lies outside
the scope of religion. It would be rare, for
example, to see a Fanti take an alcoholic drink
without first offering a libation to the spirits. The
Fantis have such a firm belief in the afterlife
that if you happened to be standing next to a
grave and a Fanti walked by, he would quite
IO
GEORGE DARLEY-DORAN
is a Turkish-born Englishman
who lives in London, where he
works as a television
correspondent.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
likely say, "Good day to you both." The exiled
Fanti therefore faces the horrifying prospect of
being "left out" for ever and ever.
The area occupied by today's Republic of
Ghana used to be known by Europeans as the
Gold Coast. From the late fifteenth century
onwards, the seafaring nations of Europe were in
fierce competition for the wealth of this region.
All of these powers Britain, Denmark, Sweden,
Prussia, the Netherlands and Portugal built
themselves coastal forts along the Gulf of Guinea.
(All twenty-nine of these forts, incidentally,
remain standing today.) By the mid-nineteenth
century, the Gold Coast had been formally assim¬
ilated into the British Empire. It was ruled by
colonial governors until 1957, at which point
Ghana became the first African nation to gain
independence from Britain. Ghana's first presi¬
dent was Kwame ("The Saviour") Nkrumah.
He, along with Egypt's Nasser, was perhaps the
most vocal Third World leader of his day. But
power went to Nkrumah's head. He eventually
died in exile in Romania. Ghana went into a
downwards spiral. One military junta replaced
another, and the country became more and more
embroiled in debt. Ghana has only achieved a
measure of stability over the last decade.
In December I flew to Accra ahead of Elvis
and his family, and stayed for a while with a
friend of Elvis named Nathan Austin. I was well
looked after. Nathan's wife Pauline introduced me
to African food. This usually consisted of yam (a
kind of enormous mutant potato), cassava (a
smaller root vegetable), plantain (long, savoury
green-skinned bananas) or some combination of
the three. Being comparatively well off, they
would often have some meat or fish on the side.
Various friends and relations would come and
spend time with them, and the atmosphere was
convivial. They all tried to teach me Fanti, and I
gave drawing lessons to the children. Pauline's
brother Emmanuel told mc about his plans to go
to America, work and save for five years and
then return to Ghana to build his own house.
A resilient, optimistic people
I soon came to like Ghana. I was struck by the
lively, joyful and humorous nature of the
Ghanaian people. Children would fall about
laughing at the sight of a white man in shorts and
countless stallholders would beckon me over to
say hello. Everywhere, all the time, music was
playing. Interspersed with "I'm dreaming of a
white Christmas" and "Jingle Bells" was the
indigenous music of West Africa, which itself is
Elvis presides at a traditional
gathering.
I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
"Fanti society is based upon kinship and group solidarity. The
isolated individual is considered to be a lost and hopeless
soulnot just for the course of this life, but for all eternity.
This is because the religious ceremonies of the Fanti are
directed towards their ancestors, who are considered to
exercise surveillance over the living."
influenced by a whole range of different styles:
pop, disco, gospel, even country & western.
The songs might be badly recorded, and
they might blast out from some tinny car stereo,
but the melody is invariably subtle and elegant.
The vocals are in English, French or any number
of tribal languages. The sound is unmistakably
African and it transforms an uncomfortable
minibus ride into a vivid and memorable expe¬
rience. West African music is fundamentally
positive and good-natured not angry like
American rap or depressive like Jamaican
reggae and says an awful lot for the resilient
optimism of the Ghanaians.
There are Muslims, Buddhists and animists
in Ghana but the dominant faith of all is evan¬
gelical Christianity. Every other building seems
to be the headquarters of some colourfully-
named denomination: The Church of Christ of
Zion; The Holy Gospel Movement of West
Africa; The Order of the Holy Trinity. The
Jukwaa market.
fronts and backs of all the trucks and minibuses
are emblazoned with holy slogans: "DON'T
GIVE UP, YOUR MIRACLE AWAITS" ... "I
CAN'T HELP YOU BUT MIGHTY JESUS
CAN" ... and the best of all, "IF YOUR GOD
IS DEAD . . . TRY MINE". Even business
names have been evangelized: King of Kings
Transport Ltd., Jesus Saves Chemical Store and
the Christmas in Egypt Chop Bar. It is not at all
uncommon, at any hour of the day or night, to
hear the singing and clapping of an outdoor
congregation, backed up by an electric organ,
guitar, bass, drums and a few tambourines.
Christmas was approaching day by day and the
religious fervour was reaching boiling point.
Nana Elvis arrives
On 24 December I heard that Elvis and his family
would be arriving that evening. I went out to
the airport to meet them. I walked into the VIP
lounge and there was Nana Elvis, as friendly,
smiling and understated as ever. Accompanying
him was Elizabeth and their children Theresa
(seven), Matthew (five) and Christopher (three).
There was also his daughter Eunice (sixteen)
from Elvis's previous marriage. Queen Eliza¬
beth in person was the epitome of an English
middle-class wife: maternal and unruffled. Eunice
was darker in complexion than the other three
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Elvis's akyempona or
sceptre.
due to the fact that Elvis's first wife was Ghanaian.
The younger ones are light coffee-coloured with
curly (as opposed to Afro) hair. The little children
were all lively, but it was clear from the start that
Christopher was definitely the ham of the family.
Elvis and Liz were very welcoming and told me
to just latch myself on to the family for the next
two weeks.
The next morning, after breakfast, we hauled
everything into the Peugeot station wagon that
Elvis had hired for the duration of their stay. We
all managed to squeeze in. I got the front seat,
which I shared with a suitcase, two overloaded
carrier bags and a ghetto blaster. Then we took
off for Jukwaa, which was an hour's drive away,
about fifteen kilometres inland from the fishing
port of Winneba.
Driving away from Accra, the monotonous
coastal plain gradually subsided into low, bushy
hills that were dotted with the occasional enor¬
mously tall baobab tree. The drive itself was quite
an experience. Our car weaved crazily down the
highway, avoiding the countless potholes. The
cars approaching us were doing the same. Some¬
times we would pass them on one side, some¬
times on the other. We stopped for petrol. The sta¬
tion had a 1920s manual pump with two large
glass cylinders that were filled with petrol before
being discharged into our tank. It was late morning
when we reached Jukwaa.
N'BAAH SANTY,
of Togo, studied medicine at
Kharkhov (Ukraine) during
the 1980s. He is currently
studying in France.
An African student
discovers Ukrainian hospitality
and vodka
orshch
and sympathy
by N'Baah Santy
My first contact with a Ukrainian family came as a
result of an invitation from my Russian teacher. She came
to fetch the ten of us who were in her study group at the
trolleybus station and took us to her home, a villa sur¬
rounded by apple-trees and a flower garden.
Her father greeted us on the verandah, where we
took off our jackets. Then he took us into a rather spa¬
cious and beautifully furnished living room. The usual
introductions were made. Her parents were retired
people. Her father had been an army officer, and her
mother a primary schoolteacher who had taught
Ukrainian. Their son, a professional soldier in Moscow,
was not present. Their daughter our Russian teacher
had invited a pastrycook woman friend of hers along for
the occasion.
We took it in turns to give our name and nationality.
Our hosts were delighted to have representatives of
every continent under their roof. They were interested
in knowing why we had chosen to study in Ukraine and
wanted to hear what we thought of the country. The
father could not resist offering us some vodka as an
aperitif, under the reproving gaze of his daughter, who
had clearly instructed him not to serve us alcoholic
drinks. He was happy when we drank to each other's
health. Our teacher kept an eye on the quantities he
served us.
The meal was quite different from what we had so far
experienced in canteens. The borshch with fresh cream
was so delicious I ate too much of it, which meant I could
not enjoy as much of the following dishes as I would have
liked. The mother urged us to have second helpings if we
wanted to. During the meal we discovered that her hus¬
band now spent a lot of his time doing carpentry. She
proudly showed us the furniture he had made with his
own hands. Her hobby was gardening, but she also
sang in a choir and played the piano.
A woman of about sixty, she radiated the content¬
ment of a life well spent. She was very unaffected in the
way she spoke to us, explaining how well she could
understand the worries of our parents, as she was also
worried about her absent son. Her husband was less
forthcoming, and content merely to approve or correct
his wife's and daughter's remarks.
After the meal, the two young women taught us a
sailor's dance and a few waltz steps. The mother said she
was sorry she had not been able to admire our traditional
dances. We said goodbye to our hosts after tea.
They gave us some cakes and apples to take away
with us. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
"We can change
homes. But we
cannot, indeed we
must not, forget
the homes of the
past, for they too
have shaped us."
ost illusions
by Neil Bissoondath
Above, a family of Hindus in
Trinidad.
14
As the twentieth century began, the
people who, fifty-five years later, would
become my ancestors, found themselves living
not in India, the place of their birth, but in a new
land, the Caribbean island of Trinidad, which
they were learning to call home. Driven by
poverty, they had chosen to seek a new life in
another part of the British empire thousands
of miles away.
As the twenty-first century approaches, I
too find myself living not in the land of my
birth, Trinidad, but in another new land, Canada,
which I have grown to call home. I was driven
not by poverty my family had found success,
both professional and financial, over the
decades but by dissatisfactions far less tan¬
gible and yet, in some ways, as virulent.
Trinidad is a small island off the coast of
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Venezuela. Geography has given it a hot cli¬
mate, rich soil, and oil. History made it a British
colony, then an independent nation under the
British crown, and finally a republic answerable
to none. History also gave it a diverse citizenry.
A 1 990 population of 1 .2 million was composed
of 43 per cent African and 40 per cent East
Indian, with the rest from a variety of racial
and cultural groups. And yet it was this very his¬
tory, stirred by racial passions, that made it a
complex and at times unsettling place.
On 31 August 1962, when Trinidad and
Tobago became an independent nation, I was
seven years old. My memories of that grand
time are few. I remember lying on a mattress at
night in my grandmother's house in the cap¬
ital, Port of Spain, and listening to a cacophony
of ships' horns mingling with the crash of
artillery from the newly-formed Defence Force.
I remember receiving at school a chocolate bar
and a little gilded medal. I remember the flag: a
red field, with a wide black band bordered in
narrow white stripes running diagonally from
upper left to lower right. And I remember too
that other flag, the old one, the Union Jack
which my grandfather used to fly outside his
store, furled and forgotten in a dusty corner,
history now.
I remember faces, too, frozen in adolescence:
black, white, Chinese, Indian, mulatto. There is
my namesake, Neil, always smiling; and Wayne,
a soccer player whose promise could have led to
a career in a bigger place; Brian, whose angers
would lead him to radical Marxism and Black
Power; Dave, whose talents would take him to
Oxford. There is Andrew, from England; Vivek,
from India; Reza, from Oman. There is Richard,
who would die of a drug overdose; and Frank,
who would die in a car accident. And so many
more.
We were friends and, in the rhetoric of the
time, future leaders of the new nation. Race,
religion, politics should not have mattered. But,
inevitably, they did.
"Together we aspire, together
we achieve"
On the verge of adolescence, Zaid and I were, for
a time, deskmates in primary school. We were
friends. We played together in the dusty school¬
yard and, even though we were not of the faith,
sang the Presbyterian hymns together at the
morning worship. Zaid was Muslim and I was
Hindu, but this meant only that our families
celebrated different religious festivals:
Mohammed and Krishna exercised no influ¬
ence on our friendship. Yet when his father sud¬
denly died a silence descended between us. Zaid
had no words to express his loss, and the lan¬
guage of condolence was foreign to me. I knew
that Hindus cremated their dead, and I won¬
dered what Muslims did. But my curiosity
seemed an intrusion. I could not bring myself to
ask, and our friendship ended in a wordless
ballet of pained glances.
In the years to come the new flag would be
reproduced dozens of times in my sketchbooks.
It would be drawn in pencil or in ink, crayon-
coloured or water-coloured, free and fluttering
or ruled stiffly to scale. Beneath it, within a
stylized ribbon, I would inscribe the island's
new motto, "Together We Aspire, Together We
Achieve". I liked the phrase;'it had a wonderful
resonance, and neatly captured the vision of
hope and optimism vital to the new era. At
school, the new anthem would be drilled into us,
and after more than thirty years, twenty of them
in a new country, the words remain as familiar
to me as the alphabet:
Forgedfrom the love of liberty
In the fires ofhope andprayer . . .
"Hindus should keep their noses out of
Muslim affairs"
On the verge of adulthood, Shafique and I were,
for a time, friends in high school. We talked
together during the hot lunch periods and,
because we were not of the faith, stood in
respectful silence while our classmates said the
"Hail Mary". Shafique was Muslim and I was
Hindu but, as with Zaid some years before, our
religions exercised no influence on our friend¬
ship. Until, that is, late in 1971, when war
erupted between Pakistan and India over the
breakaway state of East Pakistan, now
Bangladesh. The war and its merits were, like
Viet Nam, like Northern Ireland, a topic of vig¬
orous discussion at school. For me, though,
debate came to an abrupt end one morning
Trinidad and Tobago became an
independent nation and a
member of the Commonwealth
in 1962. Below, at a ceremony
during the independence
celebrations, the Princess
Royal, representing Queen
Elizabeth II, head of the
Commonwealth, reads the
speech from the throne during
the State Opening of
Parliament.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
w
16
NEIL BISSOONDATH,
Trinidad-born Canadian writer,
has published several novels,
including A Casual Brutality
(Bloomsbury, U.K., 1988) and
The Innocence of Age (Knops,
Canada, 1992).
when, as I expressed support for Indian inter¬
vention in the face of reported massacres by
the Pakistani army in the east, Shafique who
had been eavesdropping on the discussion
whipped around and with great indignation
declared that Hindus should keep their noses out
of Muslim affairs. This advent into the personal
stunned me into wordlessness, and once more a
friendship ended in a strained silence, but this
time with a vision of schism never anticipated.
Other schisms began to make themselves
apparent. It became clear as I grew older and
developed an interest in politics that those who, in
1962, had offered promises of aspiring and
achieving together had conceived of a narrowed
togetherness. They engaged readily in the politics
of race, the island dividing itself into two camps,
the People's National Movement, which was
largely the party for blacks, and the Democratic
Labour Party, which was largely the party for
Indians. We acquired a knowledge of racial unease.
In a place where truth was formless, where one
learnt to dismiss nothing and to distrust every¬
thing, even so simple an undertaking as a popu
lation census can lead to anxiety. Some years ago,
Indians whispered to each other that their num¬
bers had surpassed 50 per cent but that the black-
controlled government had, through fear of
numerical inferiority, suppressed the truth. There
was something tragic about that rumour. It was,
I felt, a sign of despair. We were, contrary to the
popular claims, no happy island in the sun. We
could not even play together without mutterings
of dissatisfaction. No selection of the Trinida-
dian or West Indian cricket team could be made
without a deserving Indian being left off the team
because so the whispers went of his race.
"She's nice, for a black"
But it was at the island's Carnival that notions of
play, of fun in the sun, became most explicit.
Many aspirations are invested in the Carnival,
many achievements pursued. It is spectacle on
the grand scale, a two-day street party that effec¬
tively shuts the island down. It is as brilliant as
Rio's, but less controlled. Anyone, local or
tourist, can join in and many do. So it was
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
A little girl dressed up for
Carnival in Port of Spain,
Trinidad.
"I remember receiving at school a chocolate bar and a
little gilded medal. I remember the flag: a red field with
a wide black band bordered in narrow white stripes run¬
ning diagonally from upper left to lower right. I remember
faces, too, frozen in adolescence: black, white, Chi¬
nese, Indian, mulatto. We were friends and, in the
rhetoric of the time, future leaders of the new nation.
Race, religion, politics should not have mattered. But,
inevitably, they did."
with a certain dismay that my ironic eye began
to discern divisions not immediately apparent:
that while every race participated, each did so in
little pockets of homogeneity, blacks with blacks,
Indians with Indians, whites with whites, etc.
Only the tourists, ignorant of indigenous ten¬
sions, felt free to mingle.
But as painful as social hypocrisy may be,
hypocrisy in private cuts more deeply; it slices
into the soul. There is no defence against it, no
shrug of C'est la vie, for there is in youth no
recognition of the personal hypocrisies acquired
through life and circumstance. How was I, as a
young boy with friends black, white and Indian,
to respond to one relative's disdain for people of
mixed (Indian/black) race? What to say when a
woman, speaking of a friend, says, "She's nice, for
a black"? How to intervene when social conver¬
sation includes fluid references to "nigs"? How
not to explode patience finally melting when
a New York business agent, hitherto well-liked,
makes a small mistake and becomes a "dirty
Jew"? When stern arguments were made that
blacks were incapable of running governments, I
would point to the undeniable chaos of India: I
have yet to meet an Indian willing to draw racial
conclusions from that nightmare.
No one ever said black school friends were not
welcome in our homes. They were, for the most
part. But it was also implicit that certain limits were
to be observed. A recent conversation with a rel¬
ative is revealing. Denying that her parents were
racist in any way, she pointed out that they wel¬
comed all her friends to their home. Her black
friends too? Yes, her black friends too. They just
made it clear she wasn't to marry any ofthem.
At the age of eighteen, I left Trinidad for
good. I went to a city, Toronto, in a country,
Canada, which quickly became my home. The
United Nations has recognized Toronto, with its
hundred-odd ethnic groups speaking some
eighty languages, as the most ethnically diverse
city in the world. It is a place where, as another
newcomer to the city once observed, one simply
becomes part of the difference.
Growing up in Trinidad was for me, on both
the social and personal levels, an exercise in dis¬
satisfaction. But it is not so for everyone.
My mother, born and educated in Port of
Spain, a woman widely read and travelled,
always swore that she would never leave
Trinidad, no matter how difficult life became.
Although she enjoyed London, New York,
Paris, Caracas and Rio de Janeiro, and despite
her particular fondness for Venice, Trinidad was
her home in ways I could not appreciate, a place
to which she was linked in ways that were to me
frustrating because they were inscrutable. She
felt herself linked to the place as I felt myself
alienated from it. The intimacy of her feeling was
not one I could engage.
I have for a long time been unable to refer to
Trinidad as "home". When I am travelling, when
I feel myself in need of comfort, security, famil¬
iarity, it is not Trinidad that I long for. "Home"
to me now is the ungraspable vastness of
Canada, its diversity of geography, climate and
people, its yet unformed face both a warning and
a possibility. We can grow attached to other
places, then. We can change homes. But we
cannot, indeed we must not, forget the homes of
the past, for they too have shaped us. The fact
remains that the Trinidad motto, "Together We
Aspire, Together We Achieve", humanitarian
in vision, universal in philosophy, betrayed by
so many people in so many ways, still speaks to
me in the land in which I pursue aspiration and
achievement. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
"LIVING LIKE SAVAGES"
CO
N
18 |-
The mission of the colonizers was not confined to the
occupation of land. They also had a wider social
purpose: spreading Christianity, educating "sav¬
ages", and civilizing what Montaigne called this
"child's world", a malleable world offered up to the
invaders in "a state of nature". This approach was
reinforced by first contacts, for the Indians regarded
the "newcomers" as supernatural beings.
But the time of surprises and gods was soon
over. The Indians understood that their relations
with the invaders had an ideological context. Ideo¬
logical conflict took root in colonial society as early
as the seventeenth century; but the fascination was
not where it should have been. Missionaries, gover¬
nors, merchants and army officers were dismayed to
see colonists frequent Indian women and "go native",
men freed from captivity prefer to stay with their
Indian captors, and frontiersmen "live like savages".
Thoroughgoing cultural assimilation seems to have
taken place, but not in the sense wished for by the
colonizers.
This is one of the strangest features of the dis¬
covery of the New World: European culture showed
itself to be more fragile than the cultures it wished
to dominate. Indian society exercised an attraction
that was disturbing. Of course it only affected a
minority, but it was an aspect of the colonization of
America that called into question many accepted
ideas.
In the seventeenth century, illiterate immigrants
from poor backgrounds brought with them an oral and
gestural culture and a vague feeling of egalitari-
anism. They felt close to the Indians. Communication
was established through modes of behaviour, ges¬
tures and certain values shared by the Indians and
the humblest colonists, even if the latter were some¬
times violently hostile to the "savages". There were
varying degrees of Indianization, ranging from
dressing like Indians to tattooing, from living with a
squaw in some remote fort to integrating into a
tribe, from frontiersmen living on the fringes of
society to hated half-castes.
CAPTIVATING CUSTOMS
From the Canadian Shield to Texas, Indian commu¬
nities constantly accepted whites who wanted to
settle with them. Only considerable hindsight makes
it possible to understand this phenomenon that so dis¬
turbed the colonial authorities, who in any case were
only interested in these Indianized colonists when they
needed guides, interpreters or go-betweens with a
tribe. In the eighteenth century groups of French
trappers, living with tribes around the Great Lakes,
gave birth to a sizeable mixed-blood community.
"There is something in their social system that
is singularly captivating, something superior to the
charm of our customs and traditions since thou¬
sands of Europeans have willingly gone native,"
wrote Guillaume Saint-Jean de Crèveceur in his Let¬
tres d'un cultivateur américain (1782; "Letters from
an American Farmer"). The charm that so surprised
him lay in the power to assimilate, the great tolerance
of Indian society and the adoption system that
existed in most tribes. The bonds created by adop¬
tion were indissoluble. During colonial conflicts cap¬
tured whites lived in Indian villages for months, even
years, on end. After undergoing the ritual of adoption,
they shared the Indians' daily lives and were treated
with affection by their new families.
Even after one of their prisoners had been freed,
his Indian relatives would come to enquire after his
health, meet his family and enjoy the pleasure of
being together again. A Delaware chief said to the
British in 1758, "We love you more than you love us,
for when we take a prisoner, we treat him like one of
our children."
Extracted from "L'indianisaiion des Blancs: Nous sommes tous
des sauvages. . . Regard sur une séduction oubliée", by
Philippe Jacquin in Destins Croisés, Cinq Siècles de Ren¬
contres avec les Amérindiens, © llNESco/Bibliothèque Albin
Michel Histoire. Paris, 1992.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Interview with Pavel Lounguine
** :*.^
Pavel Lounguine, director of Taxi Blues (1990), travelled to the polar regions to witness the
collective suicide of a culture. He returned with a documentary film, A People too Many (1994).
Above, Pavel Lounguine in
Chukotka, Siberia, while
shooting his fiim about the Inuit
in 1993.
B What gave you the idea of making a
film about the Inuit of eastern Siberia?
Pure chance. My eldest son spent a year
living with them as part of his history
studies. Like all young intellectuals, he
finds the taste for material values that cur¬
rently prevails in Russia quite repugnant.
The violence, the aggressivity, the constant
struggle to get ahead	 When he returned
from living with the Inuit, he told me,
"They are a people who refuse to live, who
are committing collective suicide." I was so
strongly moved by this idea of a people
refusing to live that I decided to go and see
for myself. And I found what he said was
true. I don't think it's an exaggeration to
speak of collective suicide.
The first impression one gets, the
moment one arrives in Inuit territory, is of
the great contrast between the beauty of
the surroundings and the dire situation of
the population. The magnificent moun¬
tains, the ocean, the majesty of nature. And,
in the midst of this, these appalling con¬
structions, horribly dirty. . . . Refuse is
strewn everywhere. Mountains of refuse,
broken-down shacks with tiny windows, a
rising stench	 This filth, the accumulation
of debris, is the tangible result of contact
between the Inuit and modern society!
U What happened on your first meeting?
When they meet an outsider, the first
thing the Inuit do is ask whether you have
any cigarettes or alcohol. Have you got
anything to sell or give away? They are a
people who have no desire to talk. Talking,
for them, is a waste of effort.
In our society conversation may some¬
times bring comfort. A trouble shared is a
trouble halved. But not for the Inuit.
It's only through seeing them at sea,
in their kayaks, that one can begin to
understand them. On board these tiny
boats, which are now equipped with out¬
board motors, these men go through a
complete transformation. It really is like
Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde, an astonishing
case of dual personality. Suddenly, their
eyes light up, their faces change completely,
and they live again as they were meant to
live and as they lived for thousands of
years. Handsome and strong, magnificent.
At sea, none of them would think of
drinking, even during rest periods.
M What is their daily life like?
I would almost say it is like a caricature
of paradise.
There are no taboos in their lives. They
have complete sexual freedom. Nobody
cares whose son or daughter they are; fam¬
ilies are more or less collective. Days are
spent drinking, eating, making love,
smoking, making love again, drinking	
No history, no memory. The whole lot of
them the old, the young, even the chil¬
dren drink and make love. No rules or 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
"Nobody cares whose son or daughter they
are: families are more or less collective. Days
are spent drinking, eating, making love.
smoking, making love again, drinking	 No
history, no memory. The whole lot of them
the old, the young, even the childrendrink
and make love. No rules or regulations.
Nothing is forbidden. But since ail this is wal¬
lowing in dirt, it is a filthy, squalid paradise."
Three stills from Pavel Lounguine's
documentary about the Inuit.
10
regulations. Nothing is forbidden. But
since all this is wallowing in dirt, it is a
filthy, squalid paradise.
Does the family exist in this restriction-
free society?
Of course, the family exists, but in a
very particular form. As almost all the
Inuit are of mixed race, the problem is not
so much one of knowing who one's father
is as of knowing to whom or to what one
belongs. Each of them, whether they
appear to us to be white, red-haired, blond,
Indian, oriental or black, is an Inuit. They
are all completely convinced of their Inuit
identity. They all share, in a sense, a phys¬
ical inability to live anywhere else.
They are extremely attached to their
land, their hills. Alaska is only thirty kilo¬
metres away. They could put their families
on board their kayaks and go and visit
their cousins, their relatives in North
America. The American and Canadian
Inuit live in a modern culture, with cars,
houses, and so on, on reservations where
white people are not allowed.
D Are the Russian Inuit allowed to go
there?
Today they are prohibited from going to
join those in America. But when they had
the right to go there not one of them chose
to stay. They went for day trips and then
came back.
D In your film you speak of 3,000 years of
civilization	
Under the communist regime, the chil¬
dren were forcibly educated in boarding
schools, where they were taught to speak
Russian. They lived in a Russian cultural
system. But the Inuit have nothing in
common with Russian farmers. Their psy¬
chological make-up is extremely subtle.
Half of them paint	 Their language and
their culture are rich and complex. They
are great readers and the library is a revered
place. They know an enormous amount
about culture and history.
At the same time the Russian adminis¬
trators are crying out for them to work.
There is practically no contact between
the two worlds.
O You say that the Inuit read a great deal.
Do they listen to the radio or to music?
Of course they do. You can see children
who sport the trappings of modern life.
They wear smart shoes like kids all over the
world, and listen to Michael Jackson on
their personal stereos!
O This is all a far cry from their tradi¬
tional culture.
The ancient Inuit created a thoroughly
original culture. As their land is very fragile,
their food supply is unreliable and the
winter is extremely cold, they developed a
way of life which is highly sensible and
ecologically sound. There never used to
be any waste. . . . They would capture a
walrus and cut it up. All the villagers would
share in the booty, eating the flesh, making
kayaks from the skin, tools from the bones
and fire from the fat. Even the intestines
were used. Every conceivable part of the
walrus served some purpose. The animal
was consumed in its entirety. Not a scrap
was thrown away!
The Inuit lived in harmony with nature,
before the arrival of caterpillar tracks,
which tore up the earth and brought waste,
packaged food, heating oil	 They had a
spiritual life, a mythology and a philos¬
ophy: they built one type of house for the
winter and another for the summer. They
proudly looked after plots of grass.
All so-called primitive peoples have an
"ecological" culture. The Inuit cannot
understand why the Russians take so many
fish out of the sea, only to throw half of
them back and leave them to rot. They
seem to find this deeply disturbing. Abhor¬
rent. It is soul-destroying for them.
Nowadays they dream of independence.
They want to set up a kind of national park
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
run by wise old sages, and live without
the whites, as before. But will they suc¬
ceed? It's doubtful whether they will be
able to maintain their houses, their heating
systems, their electricity supply. . . . They
are not sure themselves.
You say that there are as few as 1,500
Inuit in the area now, whereas there were
far more of them in the past. Is this due to
emigration?
I'd prefer to describe it as a disappear¬
ance. The Inuit are dying out and they are
not reproducing. They die very young of
disease, from drowning, of asphyxiation.
Basically because of alcohol. They are a
people born to live among nature, and now
nature is being destroyed. So what reason
is there to go on living?
PAVEL LOUNGUINE
is a Russian film-maker who wrote a dozen scenarios
for television and cinema before making his first
feature-length film, Taxi Blues (1990), which won him
the award for best director at the Cannes Film
Festival. Since then he has made another feature
film, Luna Park (1992), and several documentaries.
THE GENIUS OF
PEOPLES
The misdevelopment of small peoples with
traditional ways of life is the price to be paid
for insufficiently developed thinking by the
social sciences, those major sciences of the
twenty-first century that are "scientific" in
name only, lus gentium: the law, the genius
of peoples, was defined by Giambattista Vico
(1668-1744). Each people, however small,
has its own unique genius, and more techni¬
cally advanced nations should respect the
genius of these peoples, i.e. their religion, so
that they "develop" according to their own
dynamic. The desire to "convert" them to a
revealed religion or to Marxist atheism is a
form of interference that, five centuries on,
we know to be lethal. The state should
remain strictly neutral.
The Inuit and Indian peoples will be in a
position to seek positive solutions to their
existential problems if they act vigilantly
within the framework of truly autonomous
territories. Ignorance has never been syn¬
onymous with innocence. With their brothers
in the Third World, they must rearm them¬
selves inwardly and give new force to their
mythologies. All peoples need to be
respected on equal terms.
It is particularly urgent that decision¬
makers should be converted to cultural and
religious pluralism because we are discov¬
ering, on the eve of the year 2000, that we
need them. They are part of the second wind
of humanity which is coming to realize that
our technological and materialistic civiliza¬
tion, by deserting the thought of others, has
cut itself off from the universal.
Introduction, by Jean Malaurie, to "Les Inuit" ("The
Inuit") in Destins croisés, Cinq siècles de rencontres
avec les Amérindiens © UNESco/Bibliothèque Albin
Michel Histoire, Paris, 1992.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Ryo Ogawa
explains why a
Japanese can feel
at ease among
Africans
he Fulbe and the
Samurai code by Ryo Ogawa
»
RYO OGAWA
is a Japanese ethnologist who
worked until 1993 at the Osaka
Museum of Ethnology and now
teaches at Kyoto Seika
University. Since 1975 he has
carried out research on the
Fulbe of Senegal, about whom
he has written several studies
including (in Japanese) Life in
the Sahel Ethnographical Study
of a Fulbe Society in Senegal
(Japan Broadcasting Office
Publishers, 1987) and (in
English) "Bodilessness" and
Incongruity: Body Image and its
Social Dynamics among the
Fulbe of Senegal (1990).
When I was doing research among the
Fulbe of Dyolof, in Senegal, I had a
faithful assistant called Awdi, an evocative name
meaning "seed kept for the next sowing". He
was ten years my junior. The day of my depar¬
ture, instead of seeing me off from the village like
the other Fulbe, he hid himself away and did not
bid me farewell. It was his way of not showing
how sad he was.
As a Japanese taught at a very early age not
to show any emotions, I was always touched by
the way my Fulbe friends concealed their joys
and sorrows. It was the result of a code of behav¬
iour they call pulaagu.
Dignity, courage, patience and discernment
all form part oípulaagu. For me, its essential fea¬
ture is the notion of self-control. In Japan, too,
it is thought shameful to make an exhibition of
oneself or give in to physical needs, in accor¬
dance with the bushido tradition venerated by
the samurai of old.
It is true of hunger, for example.
I very rarely heard a Pullo* say, "I'm
hungry." To say so would be to betraypulaagu,
to demean oneself. I never saw children of four
or five complain when a meal was slow in
coming. If they went to market with their
mothers, they would not eat anything until they
got back home. At the beginning of my stay, I
myself was sharply criticized for wanting to
watch a sheep that had been killed in my honour
being cut up. My curiosity went beyond the
bounds ofpulaagu.
Yetpulaagu, devised by an African people of
herdsmen, and bushido, devised by Japanese
rice-growers, have the same function, which is
to train fighters who are capable of resisting
adversity and want to surpass themselves while
retaining their self-control.
We differ in so many ways that I am
delighted by such affinities. The brisk, almost
violent dances of Africans contrast with our
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Right, Ryo Ogawa with his Fulbe
friends.
Above, a young Pullo girl
photographed by the author.
Below, Fulbe women returning from
the well.
slow, undulating movements. Their eloquence
contrasts with our terseness there are few great
Japanese orators.
How can I explain why I always feel at ease
with Africans? Perhaps it has something to do
with our shared attitude to nature. The Japanese,
like the Africans, are careful to maintain har¬
monious links with nature, which is seen as the
manifestation of a many-faced deity. African
animism and Japanese Shintoism are closely
related.
Black Africans' dignity in their daily lives and
their mystical links with nature are such that
whenever I return to Africa I come into contact
again with the real Japan.
* Singular of Fulbe. 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
he hornbilñ quest
A Dayak writer from
Indonesia visits the
Koreans of northern
China
The author (circled) during his
visit to China.
I am a Dayak, one of the indigenous
people of Kalimantan (Borneo) in the
Indonesian archipelago. I was born in the heart
of the island, which we call Tanah Dayak (Dayak
Island), and ever since I was a little boy I have
always been conscious that I am an Indonesian
of Dayak origin.
When I left Tanah Dayak at the age of thir¬
teen to go to Java to continue my studies, my
family said, "Do not come back unless you can
make a substantial contribution to our suffering
people. We have fought the Dutch and the
Japanese, and we won independence. The task
facing your generation is to develop our people
and our region because we cannot believe that
anyone else will do so."
As "a young warrior" I knew that this was a
challenge that I could not refuse. I did not reply,
however, and went silently down to the ship
that took me a thousand miles away from my
dear forest and river, my childhood playground.
Since then I have travelled to many places with
a big question in my small head: "What can I do
to help my suffering minority people?" I have
24
**P^^^P
d'-T^
^K L £k _j^|M ^kltk
always asked this question throughout my
eventful life, and it was very much in my mind
during a visit I made to the People's Republic of
China about fifteen years ago.
After listening to my questions, my Chi¬
nese hosts in Beijing seemed to have under¬
stood what I was interested in and arranged for
me to visit many minority regions. I was able to
go almost everywhere except Tibet and Xin¬
jiang.
It was winter when Lao Wang, my Chinese
host in Beijing, organized my visit to the Korean
minority that lives in Heilongjiang in north¬
east China.
My Korean hosts were waiting to welcome me
as I stepped down from the train. Lao Wang spoke
to them in Mandarin and introduced me to them.
"So you speak Mandarin too"
"Mr. Kim is in charge of the ethnic Koreans
here," said Lao Wang. We shook hands warmly.
"I hope you are not too cold," said Mr. Kim.
"I think I have enough clothes, thanks to
the serious responsibility and full attention of
Lao Wang," I answered. "So you speak Man¬
darin too."
"Every Korean here speaks Mandarin
because we learn it at school," said Mr. Kim on
our way to the guest house. "In China there
are a lot of Korean translators. In our schools
Korean is used as the teaching language, but of
course we also have to learn Mandarin, our
national language, so that we can communicate
with other ethnic groups in our big country."
"I should like to know how you Koreans
here think of yourselves," I asked Mr. Kim. "Do
you regard yourselves primarily as Korean or
Chinese?"
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
by Kusni Sulang
"Our nationality is Chinese and our ethnic
group is Korean," said Mr. Kim. "I do not see a
contradiction between my nationality and my
ethnic origin."
"Contradictions conflicts even between
ethnic groups will come to the surface if you do
not have a correct ethnic policy," added Lao
Wang. "It will turn out badly if you neglect
their existence and their rights."
"Do you think you are the real masters of
your home region here?" I asked. "Don't you
have an idea of forming an independent state or
joining North or South Korea? I don't want to
cause offence. ..."
"Don't worry. Ask any questions you wish,"
said Lao Wang.
"I am sure that our Korean friends will show
you everything you need to see."
"Let's go and visit some Korean families,"
said Mr. Kim.
"I think it will be better to walk so that we
can enjoy the winter weather and appreciate
the beauty of the snow," Lao Wang added
smiling.
"It is too far," Mr. Kim said.
Special treatment
When we approached a family house, all the
members of the family were waiting in front of
the door and applauded us. After I had been
introduced to everyone, they showed me their
house, which consisted of a kitchen, a guest
room and sleeping rooms. It was small but tidy.
In their kitchen was a water pump.
"Every Korean family's house has a water
pump like this," Mr. Kim explained.
"Do Han families have them too?" asked
Lao Wang. (The Han are the majority ethnic
group in China, like the Kinh in Viet Nam and
the Javanese in Indonesia.)
"No," said Mr. Kim. "I am worried that the
Han will become jealous because of the special
treatment the Chinese government accords to
the ethnic Koreans."
"Jealous of the water pump?" I asked.
"No, not only the water pump. That is only
one form of our government's special attention
towards minorities. Here we have our own
schools with Korean as the teaching language.
We have our own factories manufacturing
clothes and footwear. As the majority popula¬
tion here we also control economic and political
power. Of course there are representatives of our
Han brothers and sisters among us."
"What can I do to help my suffering minority people? I try
to answer this question by going to see what is hap¬
pening in other countries. Wherever I go, I keep my
eyes and ears wide open. I am like the hornbill, the
beautiful bird that is the emblem of my people. I fly
from tree to tree in the thick forest of ideas."
"Are there any grounds for your fears? Have
you ever had any serious differences of opinion
or conflicts with the Han?" I asked Mr. Kim.
"I do not think we can avoid differences of
opinion as they arc part of life," said Mr. Kim.
"Contradictions even exist among the Koreans
here, and it is one of our tasks to solve them so
that they do not develop into serious conflict."
"What about your own experiences, Lao
Chung?" Lao Wang asked our host.
Lao Chung, the head of the family, answered
without hesitation. "Until now the Koreans
and the Han have lived together peacefully here
and wc always help each other in our daily activ¬
ities. The Han children study in the same schools
as our children. They learn Korean and we learn
Mandarin as our national language. We need
our Han brothers and sisters to develop our
region."
"The Koreans are in the majority here,"
said Mr. Kim, "and this creates a special situa¬
tion. As Chinese, the Koreans and the Han
enjoy the same rights in all fields. If we manu¬
facture our own clothes and shoes and keep
our culture alive, it is because our government
respects the cultures and traditions of minori¬
ties and regards them as the riches of our nation.
The Han, who are the minority among us here,
enjoy exactly the same rights as the ethnic
Koreans. Just as the central government gives us
special treatment, sc we give the Han minority
here special attention. Be patient, please, my
friend, we will visit our schools, factories, local
government offices, agriculture and art and lit¬
erature centres so that you can make an overall
evaluation of our development."
"It sounds like a propaganda speech," I
couldn't help thinking.
The village of Miao in
Heilongjiang, a vast province in
northeast China with a large
immigrant population.
KUSNI SULANG
is an Indonesian political
scientist and writer who has
published several plays and
collections of poetry, the best
known of which is Song of a
Dragon Son (1992). His articles
on political, cultural and social
questions have appeared in
several Indonesian newspapers
and magazines.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
ENCOUNTER WITH A PHOTOGRAPHER:
PAULIUS NORMANTAS
illllÉS
HI
-.
S$flJH¡lPÍÍ
.-, S
«£&
'.
-."' :- '" ';
in
EHhBS
m
ig
Tibet preserved in amber
11
riljHBHMiw
^^^^^MlJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJJl :
9H
:. -.ï '." :
Paulius Normantas ¡s a Lithuanian photographer
who lives in Hungary. He is particularly
interested in peoples whose traditional ways of
life he believes to be threatened. A beautiful
collection of his photos has appeared in a book
whose title, Vanishing Sources (1990),
encapsulates the spirit of his work. His quest
for sources has taken him to some sixty peoples
'
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
llfnllíT
B
. . : - .
:
S* .uKflUW ^HJ^KIJIJJJJKJIIJ^MIJJI^K vtfUt/SPK^kfJB
HJJJJJJJJJHJIJJJJJI
m
¡Mus
a&lsl h
JBHBvUUJIJJJJBiBí^lJDDJHr
> ^Bjjjh
gSflffl Znm'-'X&k
K a
BM lliliW
ssszstmm
w-¿a
BjjjjHIH
m
¡ÉSO»
ÍIsSMaS
!
¿íZ ^Vúft?;
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
i
s
m
whose lives he has shared and whose dying
traditions he has recorded with sober, powerful
images.
In eastern Tibet, where he followed in the
footsteps of the great Hungarian Tibetologist
Alexander Csoma of Koros (1784-1842),
Normantas tells how he came to win the trust of
the villagers of Shoni bo: "In the market I saw
two exceptionally beautiful girls who were
wearing diadems of Indian amber, each weighing
at least two kilos. I tried to photograph them
with my telephoto lens, but they ran off
immediately. So I put my camera away and
eventually managed to get near to them. I wear
an amber charm around my neck, but it is Baltic
amber, fossilized resin, whereas Indian amber is
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
mineral. After touching the amber of my good-
luck charmone of them even chewed it a
littlethe girls invited me to their village where
I spent the happiest part of my entire trip and
took my best photos."
The black and white photos on these four
pages were taken by Paulius Normantas during
his stay in Tibet. L
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Twenty women aged
between eighteen and
twenty-five. After not
very successful school
careers they are
attending the Active
Preparation Programme
for Qualification and
Employment (PAQUE) at
the Parismédica centre.
Set up by the French
government in 1992,
PAQUE aims to assist
young adults in the
eighteen to twenty-five
age group from all
cultural backgrounds.
The Parismédica Centre,
which was opened In
1987 and is located near
the Gare de l'Est in
Paris, trains them to
become paramedics. But
the teaching staff is also
prepared to listen to
their problems. . . .
reams oftwenty
30
One morning I told the young women on
my course: "Today it's your turn to do the
talking. Fire away."
There was a moment's hesitation, then the
well-behaved Fatma, with her large white collar,
overcame her shyness and said:
"Everyone here makes their clans!"
As I had decided not to intervene, I let gra¬
matical errors go by. Fatma's French is as shaky
as her colleagues'.
Martine, a Frenchwoman "born and bred",
chipped in: "It's simply that one likes to be with
people one prefers." Her categorical tone, round
glasses and slight plumpness accentuated her
air of being the little lady who knows everything.
Nelly from Martinique was surprised at the
odd way they had all decided where to sit. She
walked elegantly round the classroom, her high
heels tapping on the floor, and said:
"Could it be that we're sitting like coun¬
tries drawn on a map? Yes, that's it, we've
formed a map! The two Comorans are sitting at
the same table. On their right are the three
inseparable Sri Lankans, on their left the West
Indians. And who do we find in the middle?"
Her varnished nails flashed as she raised a
slender hand and pointed:
"The metropolitan French!"
Sabrina from Morocco rose to her feet:
"What about the Africans? If we're sitting
like a map, they should be occupying the whole
of the middle of the room."
But beautiful, smooth-haired Sirga from
Côte d'Ivoire, an imposing figure in her ample
boubou, said calmly, and with an authority
probably inherited from her father, who is a
judge in her native village:
"We African women never form groups.
Here we're mixing with the rest."
It is African women, though, who are the
most reluctant to give up their traditional cos¬
tumes, even when we advise them to try to reas¬
sure their future employers by dressing in a
more conventional fashion. Their brightly
coloured boubous contrast sharply with the
skirts and blouses of the other women, whose
style of dress, we explain, is more likely to
secure them the kind of jobs they are being
trained for by "Parismédica" as nursing aux¬
iliaries, assistant paediatric nurses or geriatrics
auxiliaries.
The people in my class come from a host of
countries Algeria, Comoros, Côte d'Ivoire,
Ethiopia, France, French West Indies, the
Gambia, Guinea, Haiti, Italy, Mali, Mauritania,
Morocco, Portugal, Senegal, Sri Lanka, Viet
Nam and Zaire, among others and theypersist
informing clans!
A certain intercultural resentment, which
can sometimes flare up into open conflict, is
the inevitable result of so many women being
cooped up in a little rectangular room and
wanting to stick up for their own traditions
rather than their neighbour's.
"Let's talk about the ideal husband."
There was a buzz of excitement in the room.
All the women were interested in my request.
Several were already married, others were
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Young women today. From left
to right: in France, Morocco
and Viet Nam.
young women
by Hélène Trouche Simon
engaged, though they had no say in the choice
of their future husbands. In many cases, their
fathers still had the right of veto.
"In Algeria we're regarded as French," said
the already married Fatma. "But my mother,
who is French, converted to Islam to marry my
father."
"But couldn't you have 'gone' with a
Frenchman?" asked Linda the Senegalese.
"No, I wasn't interested," Fatma replied
with a nervous laugh.
"What if he'd converted?"
"Oh in that case, yes."
"But he'd still have remained French."
"I'd have encouraged him to convert."
Fatma is an unquestioning believer in Islam:
whatever the "infidel's" colour or nationality, he
will be accepted as a brother by the Muslim
community as long as he recognizes the Qur'an.
"But a converted Frenchman is still a French¬
man," repeated Linda, who regards ethnic ties as
more important than religious denominations.
African men
who live with Frenchwomen
Martine got to her feet and took off her glasses.
A great believer in freedom of conscience, she
banged her fist on the table:
"It's outrageous to force someone to convert! "
Fatma stood up to her bravely:
"I can't see anything wrong in it it's my
mother who urges us to remain faithful to Islam.
Yes, my mother! "
She emphasized her affection for her mother,
which, she said, was why she had taken the
decisions she had. They were linked by a strong
and profound bond which had a whole tradition
behind it. Contrary to the suggestion of the
indignant "free thinker" and however goody-
goody she might seem to other people she
was not under the thumb of an intransigent
father.
"Wouldn't you like to be able to choose for
yourself?" Linda insisted, proud that she had
recently managed to shake off the yoke of tra¬
dition by marrying a man who, it would seem,
came from another milieu.
"My parents are demanding people. I would
be dishonouring them," Fatma replied quietly.
She was referring to horma, the honour
without which a Muslim is excluded from
society, the family honour which hinges largely
on the conduct of the daughter of the house.
Honour, for Fatma, was something vastly more
important than any other notion cherished in the
West, such as personal happiness, independence
or freedom of choice.
Martine unexpectedly took Fatma's side,
revealing that she was not such a great believer
in freedom after all:
"My family would never speak to me again
if I went off with a black!"
Calmly, and with a mysterious smile on her
lips, Sirga decided to intervene:
"There are African men who go with
Frenchwomen, and Frenchmen who go with
African women. In Senegal we women now do
the choosing. I met a young man in Corsica. His
"For Fatma,
whatever a
person's colour or
nationality, he will
be accepted as a
brother by the
Muslim community
as long as he
recognizes the
Qur'an. 'But a
converted
Frenchman is still
a Frenchman,'
retorted Linda,
who regards
ethnic ties as
more important
than religion."
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
"That day each of them stuck to their
guns, with a hint of condescension,
not to say contempt, for those who did
not share their vision of the 'ideal
husband'. In fact very little was said
about that putative husband. All that
counted was the attitude of the family,
that omnipresent and time-honoured
institution whose shadowy presence
hung over the lives of Sirga, Linda,
Jasmina and even Martine, who was
so proud of being a free spirit."
Young women today in Sri
Lanka (above) and Côte d'Ivoire
(below).
family doesn't like blacks, but he does. I won't
say anymore!"
Martine, the little Frenchwoman, put on her
glasses again and tried to justify her reaction:
"It has to do with my two brothers. They
like to know who I'm going out with. At their
school there were lots of immigrant children
who bullied them. That's where their hatred of
foreigners comes from."
The piping voice of Jasmina, the young Sri
Lankan who had arrived in France less than a
year ago, could be heard above the hubbub:
"My fiancé is Sri Lankan, like me. And he
was chosen by my parents. I have to wait three
years before getting married	".
Martine interrupted her:
"Three years? Good luck to you!"
Encouraged by the approving giggles her
quip had produced, she went on:
"In the meantime, what do you get up to
with him?"
"We just talk," murmured Jasmina, who
normally never says a word in class.
32
HÉLÈNE TROUCHE SIMON, a
French psychologist who was
born In Zaire, is an educational
advisor and consultant for
developing countries. She has
published a number of studies
on the Rorschach test, a
projective test widely used in
psychology.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
I he Beijing underground
turningplanet'
Australian writer
David Harris set
out to search for Li-
jien, a mysterious
city built in China
by Romans 1,300
years before Marco
Polo reached
Cathay. . . .
by David Harris
Beijing. There are sixty-two people
waiting at the stop for bus 375. As it
comes around the corner, I see the bus is already
full. I join the crowd that runs beside the double
doors, and when the bus stops I struggle up
against the flood of people pouring out. The
doors hiss shut, the bus lurches forward and I
grab a hand-rail.
"Hello." I twist around to see a young Chi¬
nese woman smiling at me. She asks, "What do
you think of China?"
"It teaches you to stand like a banana." All
those who smile know English. "What is your
name?"
"Wang Fei. I want to go to a university in the
West." She takes an envelope from the pocket of
her jacket. It is a long list of rules for overseas
study. Wang Fei's face becomes suddenly fright¬
ened as she asks, "What does it cost for an air fare
to America, or Australia?"
How precious and fragile is hope. I feel
guilty when I whisper, "More than a thousand
dollars."
Wang Fei turns her face aside. "Thank you,"
she says. We stand quietly, staring out of the
window at the four lanes of traffic, the crowded
markets, and the steel skeletons of high-rise
hotels.
The bus reaches Xishimen terminus. Wang
Fei shakes my hand and is soon lost among the
thousands of people. I walk towards the under¬
ground railway station.
The footpath is blocked by a boy, tied up
with ropes and lying on the concrete. He is per¬
haps ten years old. Naked to the waist he lies on
his side, knees tucked up. The ropes cut into his
arms that are bound tightly to his body. An old
man stands by the boy's head. He rattles a tin that
he holds out to the onlookers. When enough
coins have been dropped into the tin, the boy
begins to struggle. He kicks out his legs, gasps for
breath and cries out in pain. Then the ropes burst
apart and he leaps to his feet, triumphant.
The crowd sighs and applauds. His street
performance shows the power of Qi Gong, a
belief that we have an energy to control things
and even to heal the body. This is the China
that launches satellites, splits the atom and has
just opened its first Kentucky Fried Chicken
restaurant. One of the most popular pro¬
grammes on Chinese television is the Qi Gong
show. Like Western magicians, or faith healers, 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
"We have a pleasant time learning
words of each other's language.
Other Chinese visit us to sit on the
bunk and meet a stranger from the
West. Mr. Shui searches rapidly
from page to page in his book,
looks up words in the dictionary
and suddenly says, his eyes
gleaming with pride and happiness,
'We belong to one turning planet.'"
the Qi Gong experts delight millions by making
a watch pass through the sides of a drinking glass,
reading minds, or curing a person who has fits.
In the underground train I sit beside a Chi¬
nese woman dressed in high-fashion clothes,
with a beautiful lace collar. "My name is Fan Li
Su." She teases her crimped hair with her fin¬
gertips. "I work with an international finance
company. The hours are hard. Often we finish
after midnight. But the pay is good. My boss lets
me come to work late some days. Flexible time."
Fan Li Su is confident, with the relaxed way
of somebody who knows she has a good meal
waiting at home.
"You see, I belong to an elite in Beijing. The
common people call us nobles. We are unmar¬
ried, independent, well-educated, have travelled
to America, and earn ten times the salary of a
university professor. My boyfriend has a Toyota
car, and I have a maid at my apartment.
"In China," says Fan Li Su, pushing her hair
back with both hands, "We have much about the
sun and the moon. Male and female. Light and
darkness. China is changing. I will be the bright
sun.
A fast-food restaurant in
Beijing.
I leave the underground train and walk to the
34
Australian Embassy. There I will meet officials
who help me plan my search for the Lost City
of Rome. Far out to the north-west, where the
Great Wall crumbles into mounds of dust, may
be the ancient ruins that have brought me across
the world. Tomorrow I will catch the night train
from Beijing to Lanzhou, the Golden City of the
Silk Road.
Stranded in a train
The train is stranded. In hard sleeper carriage
number five I sit on a bottom bunk, a blanket
wrapped around my shoulders. My breath
steams in the air. Through the window I see a
leafless plane tree standing in the snow. Across
a wide flat land, scattered trees lose themselves
in low clouds. It is twenty hours since we
stopped here at a nameless railway siding in
central China, south of the Yellow River.
Opposite me, on the other bottom bunk,
sits a policeman, Mr. Zhou, with his wife and
their little boy, Jian Jun. Mr. Zhou hands me a
stick of purple sugar cane. I tear the husk off
with my teeth and munch the yellow pulp. We
grin at each other and gnaw the fibres.
With the help of a dictionary we learn that he
has hot noodles and beef for breakfast. I eat
toasted bread. The Zhou family lives in a three-
room apartment on the fourth floor of a concrete
high rise. They have a bedroom, a living room,
a shared kitchen and a laundry. Outside there is
no playground forJian Jun. No pets are allowed,
except goldfish or birds in cages. Jian Jun likes
playing with snails, and watching the Mickey
Mouse cartoons on television.
This is China the people. Although we are
stuck under a gloomy sky, there are no com¬
plaints, no demands for special privileges. People
chat, enjoy food, take out shopping to examine
their new shoes or new dress. Children are cud¬
dled; old people helped to the toilet outside on
the platform.
"Hello. Allow me to introduce myself." A shy
soldier stands near my bunk. He carries a BBC
book on how to speak English. He says, "My
name is Mr. Shui. I am pleased to meet you."
We have a pleasant time learning words of
each other's language. Other Chinese visit us to
sit on the bunk and meet a stranger from the
West. Mr. Shui searches rapidly from page to
page in his book, looks up words in the dictio¬
nary and suddenly says, his eyes gleaming with
pride and happiness, "We belong to one turning
planet."
Later, I go outside to walk for a while along
the platform. A man comes to me and holds
out a basket. Partly buried in straw are porcelain
horses. A voice behind me says, "Five yuan.
Tang Dynasty." It is a middle-aged man in a
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
suit. He hands me his business card, one side in
Chinese, the other in English. Professor Li
Deren, a specialist in making maps.
Maybe he will know something about the
location of my lost city. He asks, "Will you
have dinner with me in the buffet car?"
I follow him through his carriage soft
sleeper car 22. Soft sleepers arc for officials, for¬
eigners and wealthy Chinese. They have a wash¬
room beside the toilet. The buffet car is full of
cigarette smoke. Wc sit at a table by the window
and drink a can of Changlcsc lemonade. "It is
expensive," says Professor Li, "because we add
an education tax to luxury goods."
Hao Wen from Widow Town
Wc talk about his work. "There is a new age in
the world," Professor Li says. "The information
revolution. Now our computers design not just
a river canal, but the best ways to look after the
people and the environment. There is so much
to do. All day at university is very busy with
teaching, guests, research. When I come home at
night, I put on my overcoat, wrap blankets
around my legs and work on the ten pages I
must write each day of a textbook."
Then we begin to talk about the accuracy of
maps. While we discuss Li-jien, a young man
walks into the buffet car and looks at the empty
scat beside me. He sits and begins to talk with
Professor Li, who translates for me. Hao Wen is
the sales manager of a factory making fashion¬
able Western clothes for women. Professor Li
explains, "Hao Wen is from Widow Town. It has
a sad history. Husbands go abroad to make their
family fortune. Some see their wives only once
or twice in a lifetime."
"Will Hao Wen be a widow-maker?"
"Already he has bought two houses with
air-conditioning. One day he will choose a suit¬
able wife." Professor Li is proud of the young
man. "Hao Wen is the new China. He only
went to high school, but he owns a car. He pays
for his brother to be educated at university to
become a modern manager. That way, his chil¬
dren and mine can develop more factories."
"How large is your factory?" I ask Hao
Wen.
He smiles. "It is not all in one place. My
father sends sewing machines through Hong
Kong. I put these small machines in farms where
the families sew the clothes to the latest overseas
designs. Young women always want new fash¬
ions, so I have 700 machines working. My fac¬
tory is just a shed where I store the clothes
before selling them to big department stores.
Already I export to more than thirty countries,"
he grins. "Even Australia."
Whistles blow and the train jolts. I return to
A sleeping car in a Chinese
train.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
A train wends its way through
arid terrain near the city of
Jiayuguan in Gansu province at
the western end of the Great
Wall.
36
DAVID HARRIS
is an Australian historian and
writer who in 1989 discovered
ruins of the lost Roman city of
Li-jien, in China's Gansu
province, near the Gobi Desert.
The full story of his search for
Li-jien is told in his Black Horse
Odyssey: Search for the Lost
City of Rome in China (Wakefield
Press, Kent Town, South
Australia, 1991).
my bunk before the doors are locked that keep
apart the soft and hard sleeper carriages. Soon I
will sleep while the train takes me deeper into the
heart of China, and closer to the ancient city that
lies in wait for me out in the desert.
The invisible city
The desert reminds me of outback Australia.
Heat shimmers from the ground, making distant
mountains float and break apart in the mirage.
Beside me, in the Lanzhou University Toyota
Crown car, sits Mr. Zhang Hulaguang. He is a
blanket-maker, power-house technician and
nuclear physicist who has come with me as a
friend and interpreter.
On the horizon glimmer the eternal snows of
the Qilian Mountains. Where the mountains dis¬
appear over the curve of the earth is the area where
the city of Rome looked down on the Silk Road.
Mr. Zhang looks at the barren, stony soil.
"One drop of water is as precious as a drop of
oil. Some farmers go into the mountains and
carry out snow to water their crops." He sighs.
"Only 2,000 years ago this was good land. Now
it is desert. What has made the temperature rise
by 4 degrees in that time? It is the same right
across to the Caspian Sea. Perhaps we have cut
down too many trees. Now our children must
plant and care for the new trees we grow."
Ahead is the town of Yongchang. I sit for¬
ward eagerly. The documents in my bag show
Li-jien just south of this place. Yongchang is a
town of narrow streets, mud and pebble walls,
a market with the body of a pig hanging from a
hook, and in the centre of town a huge gate
with high arches to pass through and a green
roof on top with eaves like big curved wings.
Mr. Zhang takes me to the government head¬
quarters. I wait outside while he talks to officials.
High above, two jet fighter planes swoop and
roar in mock battle. Mr. Zhang returns with
two men.
Before long our shyness is lost as we talk
excitedly about Li-jien. We wave our arms about,
interrupt, dispute dates, swallow twigs and leaves
with our tea, and Mr. Zhang translates brilliantly
as we charge over old battle grounds and run
backwards and forwards through centuries.
"Come on," says Cultural Secretary Zhang
Yu. "We think we know where Li-jien is. Why
don't we go and look now?"
It is a race against the setting sun. We all
cram into the Toyota and speed out of town
and along a narrow dirt track. We drive straight
for the mountains as though all the devils of
hell are chasing us.
"Here," says Cultural Secretary Zhang Yu.
The car bounces along a dry river bed and stops
beside a village. I run up the river bank and see
mud brick walls of the village, a girl standing
among her cattle, smoke from kitchens, yellow
hay piled on roofs, television antennas. There is
no sign of Roman ruins.
I take photographs in many directions, aware
that my eye has seen something that escapes
my recognition.
"Li-jien is beneath this village," says the
Cultural Secretary.
With a thrill of excitement and anticipation
I know that what I failed to recognize today will
reveal itself in its own time. But now the sun is
setting, and we must return to Yongchang for an
official banquet.
I am happy. Li-jien is so close. I look out at
the beauty of the desert in the last soft light of the
day. The search for Li-jien has just begun. White
ice gleams on the roofs of Yongchang. The stars
of Orion, the Hunter, glow in the darkening
sky. In early Spring I will be back.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
MEXICO CITY: THE SHOCK OFDISCOVERY
The existence of Mexico City, the
world's largest city at that time, was
totally unsuspected. Its name had a
strange ring to it, like a place-name that
might have been conjured up in the imagi¬
nation or the garbling of the mysterious
sounds of an unknown language.
Long before Europeans discovered
Mexico City they had received their first
impressions of a great Amerindian city when
they came to Tlaxcala. There they were
struck with a mixture of astonishment and
admiration that did not impede their ability
to count and take stock, European cities
serving as references for measurement and
judgment. The Spanish conquistador Hernán
Cortés described it in the following terms:
"The city of Tlaxcala is so big and so
admirable that even if I do not say all I
could about it, the little I shall say is almost
incredible, for it is much bigger and
stronger than Granada, with buildings just
as beautiful and with many more citizens
than Granada had at the time it was cap-
IVlexico City stands on the site of the
ancient Aztec capital, Tenochtitlán, shown
here in a contemporary painting preserved
in the Mexico City Museum.
tured. And it is much better supplied with
local commodities	"
These splendid cities that the conquis¬
tadors found in Mexico disturbed their way
of looking at the world, its inhabitants and
the ultimate purposes of Creation. An
encounter with naked savages scattered
through inhospitable tropical jungles could
have fitted coherently into a catalogue of
what was then known about humanity. But
what could be made of these immense cities,
this dense urban fabric that provided the
framework of a nation of more than twenty
million people? It was a truly unexpected
world, perhaps because it could not have
been predicted in the context of what was
then known about the planet.
The sight of Mexico City on that fatal day
of 9 November 1519, when Cortés "discov¬
ered" it by marching into it, made America
even more difficult to understand. It was as
if a veil of opacity cast by the irreducible oth¬
erness of an unexpected world had been
added to the amazement and wonder of an
unexpected spectacle.
There is no doubt that the city made an
astonishing impression, leading the narrator
the conquistador and chronicler Bemal Díaz
del Castilloto make sense of it by looking
for comparisons in fantastic fiction and the
hazy world of dreams. "When we saw so many
cities and towns built on water and on firm
land and that road that ran so straight and
level towards Mexico City," he wrote, "we
were stunned, and we said that it looked like
the enchanted things described in the book of
Amadis, because of the lofty towers and tem¬
ples and the buildings they had in the water,
all in stone and whitewashed. Some of our sol¬
diers even wondered if what they were seeing
was not a dream	"
Excerpts from "Mexico, la cité que l'on n'attendait pas",
by Georges Baudot in Destins Croisés, Cinq Siècles de
Rencontres avec les Amérindiens © UNESco/Bibliothèque
Albin Michel Histoire, Paris, 1992.
3J
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Interview with Aleksandar Petrovic
the gypsies
Aleksandar Petrovic is a leading figure in Yugoslav cinema. His film / Even Met Happy Gypsies
won the Palme d'Or at the 1967 Cannes Film Festival.
D Why do you like Gypsies? How did you
get to know them in the first place?
As far back as I can remember, I've
always felt compassion for those little
raggamuffins you see in the street and those
young mothers with babies in their laps
and hands outstretched.
Today in Serbia there is unprecedented
privation. Some 30 per cent of Serbs are on
the edge of starvation. Because of shortages
of medical supplies, mental patients are
even being tied up in psychiatric hospi¬
tals, where they die of hunger.
And the Gypsies in Serbia are worse off
than everyone else. I have never seen so
many four- and five-year-old Gypsy chil-
My Lord, if you reincarnate me again after my death,
Let me be a Gypsy
Let me choose one of the ways
The way of joy that will make me a happy man
Or the way of death and a new encounter with you.
Aleksandar Petrovic
dren out on the street before. You see ten-
year-olds at crossroads, offering to wash
your car windows for a coin or two, always
ready to laugh and joke. In summer they go
barefoot, and they're not much better shod
in winter.
Because they are exposed to life's harsh
realities from infancy, they are far more
mature and quick-witted than children from
more privileged backgrounds. They soon
learn the ins and outs of the black market,
which is growing by leaps and bounds with
the economic chaos that Serbia is now in.
They sell anything: car fuel, old clothes,
toilet paper, cigarettes imported from
Romania. Now that it has replaced Trieste
as the source of supply, Romania has
become the poor man's El Dorado.
When I look into the great dark eyes of
these children of the wind and poverty, I
feel that I'm looking into the mystery of
their origins. No one knows where Gyp¬
sies come from, but they arc a people in
their own right. Their eternal sense of
freedom and music attracted me to them
and inspired me to make my film / Even
Met Happy Gypsies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Q What is the film's original title?
The title in Serbo-Croat was The Feather
Collectors, which is more evocative for us
since we're used to seeing Gypsies on our
roads carrying enormous bundles of goose
feathers that they sell in the villages.
Unlike the Gypsies of Bosnia and
Croatia, most Serbian Gypsies are seden¬
tary except those in the east near the
Romanian and Bulgarian borders, where
you can still meet nomads such as the last
bear-leaders from Pozarevac. In the spring
the whole family clambers into an old cart
drawn by a nag and does the rounds of
weddings and village fêtes.
O You say they are sedentary. Where do
they live?
Gypsy dwellings arc usually found on
the edges of small towns and villages. In
Belgrade they live in certain central neigh¬
bourhoods and like their forebears work
for the city on road maintenance. They
seem to lead a more human existence in
towns and villages than in cities, plying
their traditional trades and occupations as
collectors of scrap metal, goose-down mer¬
chants and more rarely these days as
blacksmiths or small traders. The interiors
of their little houses are simply white¬
washed whereas we Serbs like to decorate
our walls. The façades, on the other hand,
are painted in vivid colours and imaginative
designs. Their little houses look as if they
might be part of a fairy tale, but what with
alcohol, poverty and sometimes, unfortu¬
nately, petty crime, there is nothing
romantic about the life they lead.
The crime rate in Serbia today is rising by
leaps and bounds. And although the Gypsies
comprise only 2 per cent of the Serb popu¬
lation, one of four offenders is a Gypsy. Yet
the Gypsies are better accepted by the Serbs
than they are in many other places.
NOBODY THINKS OF HIM AS A
GYPSY ANY MORE, NOT EVEN
HIS OWN FAMILY
The ties of friendship between Serbs and
Gypsies are so strong that a Gypsy singer
appearing on Belgrade television recently
said jokingly, "You Serbs should put up a
monument to the Gypsies because we're
the only ones left who still love you!"
He was referring of course to this
awful, dirty war that is ravaging parts of the
former Yugoslavia.
Serbian goodwill towards the Gypsies
does nothing to improve the Gypsies' con¬
dition, because the word Gypsy also des¬
ignates someone who belongs to a certain
social level the lowest.
Whenever, through sheer grit, one of
them becomes a doctor or lawyer, no one
Scene from / Even Met Happy Gypsies (1967) 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The Gypsies did not arrive in the Balkans at the same time as the
Turks. They are already mentioned in Serb manuscripts of the
eleventh century, and the Turks did not occupy southeastern
Europe until 300 years later. About half a million Gypsies live in
the former Yugoslavia. But Gypsies do not declare themselves as
such at census time. They assume instead the nationality of
the people among whom they live. a.p.
thinks of him as a Gypsy any more, not
even his own family!
D How much of a barrier is the Gypsy
language?
For Gypsies the language problem is par¬
ticularly acute because on the one hand their
language has no alphabet and on the other
they express themselves poorly in their
adopted language. Some non-Gypsies go so
far as to claim Gypsies are incapable of
learning other languages, which is obviously
nonsense! First of all they speak their own
tongue although it has diversified into so
many different dialects that sometimes Gyp¬
sies from different parts of the world find it
very hard to understand each other. In fact,
all Gypsies are bilingual since they also use
the language of their host country.
D Do they get normal schooling?
In Serbian, Macedonian, Slovenian and
other schools, Gypsy children are taught in
a language that is not their own. So they are
already at a disadvantage in relation to the
other children. Moreover their mother
tongue is not a written language, but it is
the language they use at home. And some¬
times too, their teachers have a racist attitude
towards them.
PALM-READERS WHO CAN
RECREATE THE WORLD
Not long ago a sociologist tried to show, in
an article that appeared in Belgrade, that
Gypsy children are intellectually inferior
and that in a normal class they hold the
others back. He proposed that special classes
and programmes be adapted to Gypsy chil¬
dren's "intelligence levels". That's the kind
of nonsense you still hear about Gypsies!
It might be a good idea to give Gypsy
children special lessons, but without sepa¬
rating them from their class, so that they
can improve their skills in the national lan¬
guage. Otherwise how can they possibly
emerge from poverty?
How much is known about their cul¬
ture?
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Two scenes from / Even Met Happy
Gypsies (1967).
Gypsy mythology, which has been trans¬
mitted orally down the centuries, is sym¬
bolically very rich, and their poetry is unreal,
or rather surreal, woven from dreams.
Although there is no written history of
the Gypsy language (or rather languages)
and without written traces the life and his¬
tory of a people are shrouded in obscu¬
rity the oral tradition has kept alive in the
Gypsy mind the most dramatic episodes
of their past.
In Serbia there are whole families of
Gypsy musicians. One of the best known
are the Lakatoshes, one branch of which
lives in Hungary, the other in Serbia. I met
Mikhaflo Lakatosh in a remote village in
northern Serbia. He was singing one of his
songs, Djelem Djelem, which, after being
sung in my film, has become the Gypsy
national anthem. "I wandered endless by¬
ways/I even met happy Gypsies/Oh the
Gypsies, oh what men	"
In Gypsy language the word Rom also
means "man". All non-Gypsies are called
Gadjos, or "foreigners".
ETERNAL OUTSIDERS
If the true measure of humanity is the
amount of freedom that people manage to
win for themselves in this life, then Gypsies
are truly men Rom.
Like everyone else, Gypsies are fond of
money. But they'll never sacrifice an imme¬
diate pleasure a moment of intensity for
a few gold coins. Their attachment to
freedom is not a rational choice, it is part of
the natural order of things. They feel it in
their bones. It brings radiance to their
sombre lives of mingled joy and pain.
The euphoria generated by a sense of
boundless freedom can lead to atrocious
crimes. The Gypsy hero of my film, who
refuses to think about the consequences of
his acts, is a character out of Dostoyevsky.
He doesn't think about the consequences
before committing his crime. For example,
he doesn't say to himself, "I must not kill,
because if I do I'll go to prison for ten
years." He goes through with his mur¬
derous act, knowing full well that he is
bringing about his own ruin. A little later
in the film he is watching television with his
family when he suddenly kisses his chil¬
dren, takes his hat and leaves. And that's
that. He has moved into another world.
Compared with the fleeting sense of
power, by which he crosses over to "the
other side" of social morality, his personal
interest counts for little. He is ready to sac¬
rifice his life for absolute freedom, through
which he can affirm his personality.
Europe was recently horrified by mur¬
ders committed by two Gypsies who, while
under the influence of drugs, massacred an
entire family in northern Italy. One was
tried and found guilty, but the other chose
to kill himself. The police surrounded his
parents' house, and he agreed to surrender
but only after having a coffee and a cigarette
in the courtyard. When he had finished his
cigarette, he shot himself through the heart.
He had set off on a road without end, sig¬
nifying by his act the mysterious link that
exists between crime and freedom.
Less attached to their personal interests
than others, perhaps less "rational" because
they scorn to consider the long-term conse¬
quences of their acts, Gypsies seem to me
more sensitive than others to the world's
beauty and its suffering and more susceptible
to unhappiness, for they are more vulnerable
to the call of evil if that's what it has to be
called that we have in each of us.
ALEKSANDAR PETROVIC is a French film-maker of
Serbian origin. In addition to / Even Met Happy
Gypsies, he has directed The Master and Margaret
(1972), which won the CIDALC prize at the Venice Film
Festival, and Group Portrait with Lady (1977). His
latest film, Migrations, has not yet been released but
was shown at the Festival des étonnants voyageurs at
Saint-Malö (France) in May 1993.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
How a writer of Jewish origin, a defender of
human rights, came to know those he calls
"exiles in their own country"
Jewish
he son ofPolish
immigrants
looks at the
Palestinians
by Maurice Rajsfus
For as far back as I can remember I have
always pricked up my ears whenever I
heard someone talking about Palestine, a myth¬
ical, far-off land where my father lived and
worked hard as a young man. He used to tell
me that Palestine was a land of orange trees and
sunshine, and I thought it was a Jewish country.
In 1923, however, my father finally chose to settle
in France, which he saw as a haven of liberty.
In Russian Poland before the First World
War my father had been a Zionist. After he
moved to France, he ceased to be one. I never
knew the reason for this change of heart and I
never asked, because ideological problems had
not yet begun to torment me.
¿S-2
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
So I was not a Zionist by virtue of cultural
heritage. However, I accepted that other Jews
might think of going to settle in Palestine. I was
not yet aware of the colonial aspect of the
problem. I did not imagine that Jews might
behave as exploiters of other peoples.
It was not until 1984 that I was ready, phys¬
ically and morally, to make my first trip to the
region. I had to go and sec for myself what was
happening there. In the plane I felt anxious.
People all around me were impatient to see the
land of the Bible as tourists and became tremen¬
dously excited. These men and women, even
the children, suddenly seemed alien to me. I
was travelling to a country under permanent
siege, the army of which was occupying neigh¬
bouring territory in a less than kindly fashion.
And my fellow passengers were as joyful as if
they were on the way to Paradise. I was con¬
cerned. Their joy seemed dangerous to me.
A country in arms
On my first day in Israel I was more struck by the
difficulty of being with Israelis than drawn
towards Palestinians, whom I glimpsed from
afar they did their best to be inconspicuous. It is
true that very few real natives of the place ventured
into the white city. However, I could not help
but notice that Israeli labourers were strangely
absent from Jerusalem's many building-sites.
The sight of this country in arms at a time
when there was no threat to civil peace seemed
to me more than strange; it was fearsome. The
army was not in barracks but permanently out
on the streets, in public places and on the public
transport system. I could not bear these sol¬
diers, these boys and girls so full of life and
laughter who would bump into me on the buses
with their loaded Uzi machine-guns.
Who were they waging war against here in
Israel? The armed civilians strolling up Ben
Yehuda Street in their white shirts contrasted
oddly with the crowds of people jostling around
the ice-cream sellers and thronging the café ter¬
races. Was it a paranoid show of strength? An
attempt to inspire fear? Self-intoxication?
I soon thought I had found an answer to
these questions. On my second day, I was
making my way into the old city through the
Jaffa Gate when suddenly I came across an
odious sight. A group of children, apparently
from a town in the occupied territories, was
crossing the street under the watchful eye of a
woman monitor carrying the inevitable Uzi
machine-gun. At the same moment a Palestinian
boy pushing a heavy cart was coming from the
opposite direction. The cart was so heavy that
the boy was unable to stop, and the children had
to slow down. At that moment the monitor's
Left, passers-by at the
Damascus Gate, one of the
entrances to the Old City
of Jerusalem.
Opposite page, an Arab market
in Jerusalem.
"Israelis, Palestinians and Jordanians have started to talk
to each other. Will they create the kind of common economic
unit that will really make the desert blossom and transform
the region into a Switzerland of the Middle East?"
happily smiling face became contorted with
hatred. Giving vent to a stream of invective, the
charming young thing invited the delivery boy
to go around them. He had to give way.
Forty years before, it was a good average
Frenchman not a cop who had thrown me
out of a metro car that I had boarded by mistake,
brutally informing me that because I was
wearing a yellow star the only car I had the
right to use was at the rear of the train.
"I am from Palestine"
Right from the start I felt very uncomfortable
with these triumphant Israelis. But where were
the Palestinians? My first real contact with them
took place a few days after my arrival, when
my pal Michel Warshawski, formerly of Stras¬
bourg, suggested that we visit one of his friends
in Deheishe refugee camp near Bethlehem. That
day the camp entrance on the Hebron road was
barred with rolls of barbed wire and cement-
filled barrels. To get inside wc had to go all
round this grim settlement built on a hillside. In
the rocky alleyways between dwellings that
looked more like glorified hovels than low-
MAURICE RAJSFUS,
French journalist and writer, is
the author of some 15 works,
most of which deal with the
Second World War period. He
wrote Mon père l'Etranger
(1989) in memory of his father,
a Polish Jewish immigrant who
was deported to Auschwitz in
1942, and has published two
books on the Palestinian
problem, Retour de Jordanie.
Les réfugiés palestiniens dans
le royaume hachémite (1990)
and Palestine, Chronique des
événements courants (1990).
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
"The sight of this country in arms at a time when there was
no threat to civil peace seemed to me more than strange;
it was fearsome. I could not bear these soldiers, these
boys and girls so full of life and laughter who would bump into
me on the buses with their loaded Uzi machine-guns."
grade suburban housing, I suddenly felt that I
was walking through a ghetto.
Although profoundly shaken, I had not yet
made up my mind to feel active solidarity with
the Palestinians. But it was no longer possible for
me to regard the Israelis in the same way. I was
repelled by the behaviour of the Jewish
colonists their certainty that right was on their
side . . . and might as well!
I spoke to children who described their vil¬
lages, places where they had never set foot. Then
followed the disturbing refrain, "I am from
Palestine! " It did not sound as if they had learned
it by rote. The country that had been wiped off
the map was still alive.
My two subsequent visits in January 1986
and November 1987 only strengthened my
impression of being in a colonized country
whose inhabitants were submissive in appear-
Israeli soldiers on the West
Bank.
anee only. On 28 November 1987 Hamdi, a
journalist from Deheishe camp, told me: "We
don't intend to remain passive until the end of
time, but there's no doubt that if we lift a finger
they'll throw tanks at us, maybe even planes!"
He smiled sadly as he spoke. In the three
years since I had met Hamdi, his happy opti¬
mism had gradually faded away. He appeared
nervous, even feverish. His time in jail, followed
by a long period of house arrest, had done
nothing to boost his morale. He must have fore¬
seen darker days ahead.
The next day I left Israel, never to return
again. A week later the Intifada began.
"I have a dream! " said Martin Luther King,
a man who knew the value of words, when he
called for the fulfilment of an impossible dream.
Israelis, Palestinians and Jordanians had to talk
to each other some day. Now they have begun
to do so. Will they create the kind of common
economic unit that will really make the desert
blossom and transform the region into a
Switzerland of the Middle East? A confederation
where differences would not prevent the imple¬
mentation of a generous programme?
While waiting in hopes of such a conclu¬
sion, I do not forget that I have a standing invi¬
tation to visit my friend Anwar in Hebron as
soon as he gives up driving his Paris taxi and
I fully intend to honour it some day.
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
European artist
discovers the salt of the earth
by Jacques Leenhardt
Above, traces left by salt
gatherers on Lake Sayula in
Mexico (600 to 900 A.D.).
Countless are the representations of the
Other, and infinite the choice of ways that
lead to them.
The artist is like the traveller, always tuned
into a world that speaks the language of the body,
of space, of the wind that sweeps through space,
and also the language of vision and light. Before
coming into contact with ideas, an artist embraces
different kinds of matter and things, colours and
sounds.
Lake Sayula is in the Mexican state ofJalisco.
French artist Jean-Charles Pigeau had travelled
the length and breadth of Mexico. He had pitted
himself against El Tajin and the classical grandeur
of Chichén Itzá. He had combed the country
from the Atlantic to the Pacific in his quest for a 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
site where he could install his steel mirrors to
face the sun. He wanted a space that was totally
free of anecdote. Far from the monuments erected
by civilizations, he hoped to discover the very
foundations on which they are based.
He had chosen Mexico so that the light cap¬
tured by his polished parabolas would appear in
its primal, absolute brilliance, in a state somehow
prior to the forms in which man captures and
symbolizes light. Materialized as temples and
pyramids, the light of the Mexican plateau has
already lost what it must have given to monu-
mentality. Pigeau wanted to experience it as the
Indians had known it immemorial and pre¬
dating constructions erected to memory. To that
end he crossed the coast and the plateaux from
cast to west until he reached Jalisco state, where
he saw a lake that reflected the sky.
Gazing at the expanse of Lake Sayula and
the ring of green hills surrounding it, Pigeau
knew he would have to wait until the water fed
by winter rains had evaporated. This landscape,
which he had discovered the previous year, did
not seem to bear the emblematic marks of pre-
Columbian cultures. Yet it was those cultures
that he wished to encounter through his quest for
light. Since it had no pyramids or temples, Lake
Sayula, which dries out each year in the sun, was
the natural product of light. That is why he
returned there. He would have to wait.
Symbolizing the cycle of life,
water and sun
The lake gradually turned into a vast expanse of
silt. In places, the dried crust began to crack.
Soon it would be possible to walk over it without
getting one's feet wet. In a few days' time, Pigeau
would be able to arrange his concave mirrors,
focusing them on a hollow in the mountains bor¬
dering on the Lake Sayula site, very low on the
horizon.
The waters of Lake Sayula are brackish. Pigeau
had not yet realized, but he may have uncon¬
sciously chosen the lake because of that. No veg¬
etation interferes with the perfect plane the lake
waters offer the eye, or the plane formed by the silt
once they have disappeared. On the dried-out
lake, Pigeau was going to ressuscitate, by pointing
his mirrors skywards, the momentarily absent
reflective waters. Thus he would symbolize the
cycle of life, water and sun. He would bring light
and heat back down to earth. With a propitiatory
gesture, he would mimic the birth of our inhab¬
itable world, a thousand leagues from any inhab¬
ited land. Or at least that was what he thought.
But because artists create their ideas solely out
of matter, matter responds to them matter
which has always been informed with the
memory of the people who have worked, trans
formed and inhabited it. Human beings inhabit
matter just as matter inhabits human beings, and
a site is always the form taken by nature when
humans imprint their lives on it.
Meeting the men of salt
The surface of the lake was almost uniformly
cracked. The time to arrange the polished
parabolas on the hardened silt was approaching.
And yet something in the distance disrupted the
harmony. Pigeau moved closer and was clearly
able to make out circles on the ground of almost
exactly the same diameter as his mirrors slightly
concave circles in which the water was taking
longer to dry out. Their circumference was
marked by pottery shards.
Over a thousand years ago, at a time known
to archaeologists as the Sayula period, Indians in
the region had discovered how to exploit the
lake's brackish waters, as Antonio de Ciudad
Real described in his Tratado Curioso y Docto de
la Grandezas de la Nueva España ("A Curious
and Learned Treatise on the Grandeur of New
Spain"). After capturing the salt water in shallow
basins dug in the bottom of the lake, they speeded
up its evaporation by lighting fires and then gath¬
ered the salt.
The circles that Pigeau was looking at were
therefore aquatic hearths, traces of humans who
used nature by thwarting it, by pushing its logic
to extremes through ingenuity and artifice.
That was how Pigeau 's devices came into
contact with those of an ancient Indian civiliza¬
tion. All of a sudden he discovered that this out-
of-the-way expanse had been entirely occupied
by the labour of human beings. After going back
into the past beyond the cultures whose jade
objects and ball games, in full colour photographs,
now adorn coffee-table books, he thought he
had at last found the very origin of his own
. impetus. And now, after moving so far out of line
as to be on the verge of deculturation, he had
found human beings at work, human salt collec¬
tors. The people of Sayula did more than collect
salt, they shaped it. They made cakes of it and
modelled figures with it "men of salt", in
Antonio de Ciudad Real's words heads of salt,
busts of salt and thousands of other figures. That
was how the Indians created a world out of the
primal silt that had been doomed by the brackish
waters of the lake to remain barren.
Taking his time, because such encounters
encourage one to see everything in the context of
eternity, Pigeau laid out his parabolas next to the
Indian hearths. The sunlight allowed itself to be
captured with the same benevolence it has shown
in drying out the lake since the beginning of
time, so that the artist in each of us can make
statues of salt and light parabolas.
French artist Jean-Charles
Pigeau's parabolic mirrors on
the parched bed of Lake Sayula.
JACQUES LEENHARDT,
of France, is a professor at the
Ecole des Hautes Etudes en
Sciences Sociales in Paris and
president of the International
Association of Art Critics (AICA)
and of Crestet Art Centre
(Vaucluse, France). Among his
published works are Les
Amériques latines en France
(1992) and Dans les jardins de
Roberto Burle Marx (1994).
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
"On the dried-out
lake, the artist
would symbolize
the cycle of life,
water and sun. He
t=
-
i *
Í
would bring light
and heat back
down to earth."
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
e are Siamese
ifyou please
by Morgan Sportes
In his novel Persian Letters (1721), the French philosopher Montesquieu gave a satirical portrait of the society of his time, supposedly
seen through the eyes of two visitors from the East. Did he know that some fifty years before, three ambassadors from Siam (today Thai¬
land) had caused a sensation at the court of Louis XIV?
48
rThe three ambassadors sent by King Phra
Narai to the court of Louis XIV at the end
of the seventeenth century aroused widespread
curiosity. They inspired novels and farces. Their
likenesses were reproduced by the thousand in
gazettes and almanachs, especially their flat noses
and their pointed white ceremonial hats. Crowds
of people swarmed around the landing-stage to
greet them when they arrived. When they broke
their journey to Paris at Nantes, Blois, Chambord
and Vincennes, beautiful aristocratic ladies gave
them a warm welcome, plying them with teas-
ingly playful questions.
People were surprised that they washed
every day and even several times a day. They
wanted to know how the visitors managed to
satisfy the twenty-odd wives each one was sup¬
posed to have.
Siamese women are always half naked
The chief ambassador, Oc Khun Wisutra Sun-
thon (more commonly known as Kosapan)
knew perfectly well how to behave in such cir¬
cumstances and gave these ladies as good as he
got, always with the greatest courtesy.
A paparazzo of that time, one Jean Don-
neau de Vizé, a hack who wrote for a weekly rag
called the Mercure Galant, scrupulously noted
it all down, especially the ambassador's rejoin¬
ders, which delighted the court. This Siamese
gentleman was considered to be full of "hon¬
esty", "cool good sense" and "gallantry".
One day Madame de Seignelay, the very
pretty wife of the Minister of the Navy, visited
the château of Berny, where the ambassador
was staying for a month, and insisted on being
fVSOU NNU-IX AMIVASSAUi 1)1 lUrt IH SIAW M IKAI'Ol'KI.
\SM l h II ! 11 I D'OHKM I.K.I i I I" W>SII > 1)1 I \ I.I.I Mil I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
told whether he considered French or Siamese
women were more beautiful. Kosapan courte¬
ously replied that French women were more
beautiful, that Madame de Seignelay was the
most beautiful French woman he had ever seen,
and that she would undoubtedly be the most
beautiful woman in the world if only she would
dress like a Siamese woman. It was only after
much pressing that the interpreter, a well-trav¬
elled missionary who was blushing with con¬
fusion, was made to reveal exactly what Kosapan
meant, namely that, "Siamese women are always
half-naked." There was loud laughter, especially
at Madame de Seignelay's expense. The story
went all over Paris.
Kosapan was so intelligent and perceptive
that he could "enter into each nation's idiosyn¬
crasies, however different the nations may be."
He needed to have all his wits about him to
keep track of the intrigues that went on in the
wings of the great "theatre" of Versailles as he
was shunted from dinners to high masses, from
operas to light theatre. There was also plenty of
walking to the Orangerie at Versailles, for
example. "A very big house indeed for simply
sheltering trees," Kosapan noted.
Ambassador Kosapan becomes prime minister
The purpose of Ambassador Kosapan's mission to Versailles was to offer a trading post
to Louis XIV in Singor (now Songkhla) in southern Siam, where the Compagnie des Indes
Orientales and a handful of troops would establish themselves and provide a coun¬
terweight to the all-powerful Dutch.
Siam always played off one imperialist power against another: French against Dutch,
English against French, Japanese against English and French, with the result that the
country was never colonized.
France requested the right to build a fort outside Bangkok and sent a squadron of
five vessels with 700 heavily armed soldiers to back up her claim. Kosapan was one
of the main architects of the revolution that overthrew the prime minister, King Phra
Narai himself, and resulted in the expulsion of the French. After being besieged in
Bangkok for six months, the French surrendered and left the country in November 1688,
exactly a year after their arrival.
The monarch who then came to the throne of Siam showed little gratitude to Kos¬
apan. He appointed him prime minister, but a few years later began to distrust him, tor¬
tured him and had his nose cut off.
In 1700 Kosapan committed suicide. It seems that he always felt a certain nos¬
talgia for what he called the "great and good kingdom of France". A German traveller
who met him in Siam in 1690 saw several paintings of the Sun King and the most emi¬
nent members of his family hanging on the walls amidst the cobwebs.
Sic transit	 M. S.
The dark regions of idolatry
Kosapan soon formed an idea of the strange
religious passions that were swirling through
Louis XIV's kingdom, shaken by the anti-
Protestant persecutions that followed the revo¬
cation of the Edict of Nantes.
In the land of the Sun King there was "one"
truth, i.e. Catholic. Idolaters and heretics had to
submit ... or go into exile. Fortified by these
"Three ambassadors sent by the King
of Siam to the court of Louis XIV in
the late seventeenth century aroused
widespread curiosity. Their likenesses
were reproduced by the thousand in
gazettes and almanachs. especially
their flat noses and their pointed
white ceremonial hats. Beautiful aris¬
tocratic ladies gave them a warm
welcome. People were surprised that
they washed every day and wanted to
know how they managed to satisfy
the twenty-odd wives each one was
supposed to have."
religious certainties, many courtiers and great
noblemen asked Kosapan when he intended to
renounce the "dark regions of idolatry" and
discover the "true faith". To which Kosapan
would answer diplomatically, "What is said of an
unknown religion must seem ridiculous to
people who know nothing about it and who
believe in another, because it is natural to believe
that the religion one has adopted or into which
one is born is the best of all."
Sometimes he was more sharply questioned
and put in a tight spot, whereupon he would
make even more concessions. His reply to the
Bishop of Tournay was, "Please obtain from
the true God that I may know Him and that it
may please Him to save me from the darkness I
am in so that one day I may profess the true
faith."
This remark delighted the French prelate,
who thought that grace had already begun to
descend on this idolater full of goodwill. The
bishop would probably have been less inclined
to indulge in wishful thinking if he had read
the works of another bishop, Louis Laneau,
who had spent twenty years in Siam. Laneau
warned young missionaries who went to Siam to
beware of the "irony" of the Siamese who only
admit to us "that they are in darkness" in order
to get us to understand that "we are in darkness
Opposite page, the
ambassadors of the King of
Siam arrive at the château of
Versailles for an audience with
the French King, Louis XIV.
French engraving of 1687.
ourselves.
MORGAN SPORTES
is a French writer who has
published a dozen books,
including two novels about
Thailand, Siam (1982) and Pour
la plus grande gloire de Dieu
(1993), both published by Seuil
(Paris). He has also written a
historical essay, that will be
published shortly, on touis XIV's
attempt to seize control of Siam.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
afe society
by Rifâ'ah Râfe' el-Tahtâwî
In the nineteenth century a group of Egyptians in Marseilles discover European ways of life. One of them is Rifâ'ah Râfe' el-Tahtâwî (1801-1873),
a pioneer of modern Arabic literature. He lived in Europe between 1826 and 1831.
Above, The Port of Marseilles
(c. 1820) by Ambroise-Louis
Garneray.
SO
I On the very first day, funny things started to happen
I at meal time.
First of all they brought us about a hundred chairs to
sit on. In this country everybody is amazed when they see
people sitting on a carpet or simply on the ground. Then
they came back with high tables on which they put
white plates. In front of each of us they put a glass, a
knife, a fork and a spoon. On each table they put two bot¬
tles of water and two containers, one for salt and the
other for pepper.
AT TABLE
Then they brought the food on big platters that they
placed in ones and twos in the middle of each table. They
shared out the food among the people sitting down, with
each person receiving one portion. You then had to cut it
with a knife and lift little pieces to your mouth with a fork,
not your fingers. Here you don't use your fingers, or
someone else's fork or knife, and you don't drink from
someone else's glass. They claim it's healthier and cleaner
that way.
We have also noticed that the French never eat from
copper dishes even if they've been tin-plated. They only use
them for cooking. At table they use shiny plates, and
they eat in stages, beginning with soup, then meat, fol¬
lowed by all kinds of vegetables and pasta. Then they
eat salad. Sometimes the plates are the same colour as
the food. They are green for salad, for example.
They finish their meal with fruit and wine but don't drink
much. Then they take tea or coffee, but that depends on
how poor or rich they are. For each new dish they give you
a clean new plate.
The first time we walked round the town we saw
stores full of mirrors and pretty women. It was midday. The
women in this country don't cover their heads, necks,
throats, arms or shoulders or even lower down.
So you can imagine what fine sights we saw in shops,
cafés and the crowds.
MIRROR IMAGES
The first wonder we beheld was a magnificent café. We
went in and found it was organized in an extraordinary
fashion. The owner was a lady who sat on a tall chair
with an inkwell, feathers and a notebook in front of her.
They made the coffee far from the customers, in a back
room; the waiters stood between this room and the room
where the people were. The main room was filled with
chairs covered with velvet and fine wood tables, each
with a black or striped top.
This café served all kinds of drinks and cakes. When
someone ordered something, the waiters repeated the
order to the lady, who ordered them to fetch it and then
wrote down the order and its price on a page of her note¬
book. When a customer wanted to pay, she tore out the
page and sent the waiter with it to the customer.
If you ask for a coffee, they bring you the sugar with
it. They put the sugar in the cup and stir to mix it with the
coffee before they drink. We did the same. Their coffee
cups are big. One of theirs is as big as four of our cups in
Egypt.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
In this café they have all the newspapers, and you can
either leaf through them or read them carefully. When I
walked in, I thought it was an immense open restaurant full
of people, but in fact everyone who comes in and sits down
is reflected in all the mirrors, which is why you get the
impression that you are in a busy street.
I only really understood that when I saw our images in
the reflecting glass of the mirrors. In Egypt mirrors usually
deform the reflections. It made me think of certain verses
where our poets talk about mirrors and the images they
reflect.
Extracts from Takhliç al-lbriz Wâ talkhiç Bàriz ("The purification of gold,
or the brief glimpse of Paris").
A Paris café founded in 1832
and still doing business today.
mm-*T*'~AV
"Cafés in France are not meeting places for criminals. Respectable people go there. They are
decorated with magnificent, precious accessories that reflect extreme wealth. They are very
expensive. Only the well-off frequent them. The poorer folk go to cabarets to smoke and drink."
etting to know ChiefIamory
by Louis Gustave Binger
Louis Gustave Binger (1856-1936) was a French officer who explored the Niger bend
and the hinterland of Côte d'Ivoire in 1887-1889
I Thursday 9 February 1887
In the Sudan, the chiefs' power over their subjects is lim¬
itless. Since they are to some extent suspicious of
any white traveller, when they have not decided in
advance to let him through, they never broach a dis¬
cussion with him.
Here this was not the case, since Iamory would
allow me to see him. But would I get permission from
him to continue my journey? He had been described to
me as a despotic chief who held merchants to ransom
and made them endure all imaginable kinds of vexation.
Iamory is a tall fine-looking man who bears some
resemblance to our Wolof contacts. Unfortunately he is
slightly disfigured by the tattoos of the Mandé-Dtoula,
which consist of three long grooves that run from the
temples and the ear and spread out at the corners of the
mouth.
Uaptain Binger being received by Iamory
(seated at right), as shown in an illustration from
the Captain's account of his travels (1892).
SI
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
When you arrive in a village or come into the pres¬
ence of a chief of whom you have something to ask, you
must take care not to tell him immediately what you
want of him. However urgent your mission, you should
only talk about it after several interviews.
The first audiences are devoted to greetings and
expressions of welcome; then gifts are despatched
and other mutual courtesies are exchanged.
On the second or third day, people from the chief's
house come and skilfully sound you out. It is a good idea
only to unbutton yourself gradually and not to be too pre¬
cise about your intentions. As he gets to know about
your plans, the chief consults his entourage and enquires
about public opinion, which it is always advisable to pre¬
pare or to win over by cajoling a few powerful figures.
Only when he has worked out what he is going to do will
he ask to see you. Usually he will only question you as
a formality; he will have made his decision beforehand.
But Iamory is a very intelligent man, and there's no
point in beating about the bush with him. I explained to
him the purpose of my journey. He took a great interest
in everything I said, asked for more information about
France and our political situation in Europe and assured
me that I would be well received wherever I went.
Extracts from Du Niger au golfe de Guinée par le pays de Kong et le
Moss/ (1892).
The German botanist and traveller Georg August Schweinfurth (1836-1925) explored the reaches of the
upper Nile and was the first European to discover the Uele River in what is now Zaire.
hen the Momhuttu women
cried hosannaby Georg Schweinfurth
"IVlombuttu Woman" (above)
and "Details of the palace of
Moonza, king of the IVlombuttu"
(right). Two illustrations from
the French edition of
Schweinfurth's Heart of Africa
(1875).
SI
fl My relationship with the natives became closer
I with each passing day. There was always a con¬
siderable crowd around my dwelling, avidly watching my
slightest gesture. The well-born even had chairs brought
for them.
At first these visitors amused me.
I greeted them with welcoming gestures, combing
my hair and shaving in conspectu omnium.2
Moreover the astonishment was mutual. Each
instant brought me a new surprise. I spent a good deal
of the day sketching and taking notes.
Interesting though they may have been, these visits
soon became tiresome. The day after my arrival I had to
have a barrier of thorns put up around my tent. But that
didn't stop them. I threw water on the nuisances, I
exploded powder and fire-crackers. To no effect. My door
was guarded by soldiers, but no sooner was I outside it
than the crowd gathered round. The women were par¬
ticularly exasperating. They would follow in my foot¬
steps, preventing me from collecting plants and crushing
the few flowers I had taken the trouble to pick. I came
to despair. As I walked along streams and through val¬
leys there were a hundred In my wake. With each farm
and hamlet the avalanche swelled.
At other times I was in better temper and joked with
them. I had learned a few words of their language.
When I spoke one of these words, they repeated it
happily in chorus like an echo. "Hosanna", one of the
words I knew, meant "It isn't". One day, in the midst of
a group of women, I shouted it out in a stentorian
voice. "Hosanna!" they replied, and for the next quarter
of an hour, they repeated the same word with me and
continued this strange concert.
These Mombutu women, so cheeky when they are
in a group, tend to be shy when they are on their own.
I wanted to observe the details of their daily lives, but
whenever they saw me coming they would scamper into
their dwellings and shut the door in my face.
1. Now known as "Mangbetus", one of the peoples of Zaire.
2. In full view of everyone.
Extracts from Heart of Africa. Three Years' Travels and Adventures
in the Unexplored Regions of Central Africa from 1868 to 1871
(1873).
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
CORAL:
TAKING THE &
PULSE OF ík'H
THE PLANET i m_
1BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
Coral reefs are one ofthe won¬
ders of the world. And one of
its most useful. This is how
Professor Jean Jaubert,
director ofthe European Oceanolog-
ical Observatory (l'Observatoire
Océanologique Européen) at the
Monaco Museum, sees them: "Coral
reefs are the marine equivalent of
primeval forests and, as home to an
exceptionally dense and diversified
plant and animal life, help to main¬
tain the major balances of the
planet." Roughly 400 million years
ago they existed in almost every
ocean. Today they form the coast¬
lines of 105 (for the most part devel¬
oping) countries and reefs extending
from the surface down to 30 metres
cover some 600,000 km2.
iäö&
&*
ÊÊÊk.
They are mostly found in the
world's warm and temperate waters,
in the Indian Ocean, the Caribbean,
Polynesia, Australia, usually on the
eastern sides of continents which
protect them from the prevailing
west winds. There are three main
types of coral reef: fringing reefs,
near coasts; barrier reefs, separated
from the coast by a deep lagoon,
the best known example being
Yellow damsel,
Pacific Ocean
branching coral
(Australia).
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
CORAL: TAKING THE PULSE OF THE PLANET
54
Australia's Great Barrier Reef; and
atolls, rings ofreefs around lagoons,
a typical configuration of many
Pacific islands and the kind ofthing
holidaymakers dream of. As well as
being beautiful, coral is also an indi¬
cator ofmarine pollution and vari¬
ations in global climate. Scientists
have noticed that, just as the age of
a tree can be read in the concentric
circles ofa crosscut, coral shows its
age in its skeleton and also the
traces of any aggression ofwhich it
may have been a victim over the
years.
ANIMAL, VEGETABLE
OR MINERAL?
For many years researchers were
stumped as to whether coral was
animal, vegetable or mineral. The
mysterywas solved in the mid-eigh¬
teenth century by a French surgeon,
Jean-André Peysonnel, and an Eng¬
lishman, John Ellis, who declared
coral to be animal! Behind a rock¬
like appearance conferred by its
aragonite skeletons are hidden car¬
nivorous polyps of the coelenterate
taxon (in Greek, coelenteronmeans
"hollow tube"). There are from 2,500
to 2,600 species (not counting soft
corals without skeletons), 700 of
which are found in the Indo-Pacific
region alone.
Corals are small animals about a
centimetre long, consisting of a
cylindrical digestive tube with a
mouth at one end surrounded by
tentacles armed with stinging cells
for capturing plankton. During the
day these tentacles are folded inside
the digestive sac. Like the big car¬
nivores, they only hunt at night,
feeding on plankton, small shell¬
fish and larvae. They evacuate cal¬
cium carbonate which enables
them to produce the outer skeleton
within which they shelter. They live
symbiotically with microscopic
single-celled algae known as zoox-
anthellae, that lodge in their tissue
(up to 7,000 algae per mm2). The
algae process the nitrates, phos¬
phates and carbon dioxide (CO2)
produced in the coral polyp. As a
result of photosynthesis, which is
only possible as far down as sun¬
light can penetrate, i.e. some 50
metres, they generate oxygen and
organic compounds which the
polyps can use. They may also help
the polyp lay down calcium car¬
bonate. Thanks to its algae, living
coral is rainbow-coloured, yellow,
blue, purple, orange, brown or even
fluorescent (it should not be con¬
fused with red coral, used in jew¬
ellery, which is not within the scope
of this article). When the symbiotic
algae leave it, the coral dies and goes
white.
More than a century ago Charles
Darwin wondered why the Pacific
Ocean is almost a desert although
its atolls are luxuriant "oases" where
coral and fish abound. In 1974 three
oceanographers, Yves Magnier,
François Rougerie and Bruno
Wauthy working on behalf of the
French Polynesian Fisheries Service
under the aegis of Unesco's Man
and the Biosphere Programme
(MAB), studied the physical-chem¬
ical balance of the Takapoto atoll
lagoon in the Tuamotu Islands. The
food that sustained life in the lagoon
clearly came from deep water. But
how, since the deep water is cold
and does not mix with the warm
surface water? The three researchers
made the brilliant discovery that
the atoll works like an oil lamp. The
water warms up as it occupies the
reef's porous base (the wick),
causing nutrient salts (the fuel) to
rise with the warmer water towards
the surface where they are con¬
sumed (the flame). The phenom¬
enon was given the name geot-
hermal endo-upwelling and is now
gaining ground in the scientific
community.
Acropora coral
(New Caledonia).
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
Gorgonia and
snapnose puffer
(Baja California,
Mexico).
If they are well fed, the polyps
reproduce in two ways. In a single
night shortly after the full moon, the
polyps (which are both male and
female) spew out a cloud of sper¬
matozoa and ova that unite and give
birth to thousands of small larvae,
planula, which, if they are lucky
enough to escape their predators,
attach themselves to rocks. When
the polyp is firmly ensconced, it can
also reproduce asexually by simply
splitting. If it is to prosper, the polyp
must not be subjected to stress.
What it likes is warmth, between 25
and 29°C, but in the Gulf it may sup-
Û
port variations between 14 and 35 C.
It needs clear, salty, highly oxy¬
genated sunlit water. It detests sand
clouds that suffocate it, pesticides
and fertilizers leached by rain
through deforestation, oil, parrot-
fish that nibble its dps and, above all,
human beings who walk on it and
break off its branches for souvenirs.
Although tourism provides
income, the care that the Aus¬
tralians take of the 2,300 kilometres
and the 400,000 km2 of the Great
Barrier Reef should be emulated,
i.e. divers and pleasure boats should
be strictly monitored. But for poor
countries this is easier said than
done.
STRIKING REGENERATIVE POWERS
However, some optimistic news has
reached us from Unesco's Regional
Office in Jakarta, where Robin
Harger, a coral specialist, notes the
striking regenerative powers ofcoral
reefs. He challenges the accuracy
of a map but only the map that
has appeared in a booklet entitled
Reefs at Risk (see further reading
below). In an area of eastern
Indonesia where the map indicates
reefs with a life-expectancy of 10-20
years, he notes 80%-90% coral cover
in a reef in Banda Island that had
been badly damaged by lava flows.
He describes the reef in question as
"absolutely spectacular" with
"humphead parrotfish half the size
of a Volkswagen Beetle". His many
dives around the world enable him
to judge that this ecosystem is in
good health. To say that the reefs
are in a critical condition is to strike
a blow at eco-tourism, "which is
considered as a potential element of
economic salvation."
Coral reefs deserve respect
because they protect coasts and
mangroves from battering by waves
and provide a home for countless
fish and shellfish species. And yet for
centuries in islands like the Mal¬
dives itwas traditional practice, now
prohibited, to extract blocks ofcoral
for building temples and monas¬
teries, so that the fish virtually dis¬
appeared. In the Philippines fishing
with dynamite, although officially
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
CORAL: TAKING THE PULSE OF THE PLANET
Acropora coral
from the Indo-
Pacific region.
banned, is still practised, and more
generally, the often-criticized cap¬
ture ofexotic fish and the removal of
living coral for European and North
American aquariums are only mar¬
ginal activities.
HEAT WAVE
Another, more serious, threat to
coral is posed by the earth's
changing climate. Some scientists
claim that by the middle of next
century the amount of CO2 in the
earth's atmosphere will have dou¬
bled, there will be a general rise in
temperature, and climatic variation
will be greater than it has been in
the past 6,000 years. What effects
would this have on coral reefs and
the creatures that depend on them
for their survival?
A Global Task Team of experts
sponsored by the United Nations
Environment Programme (UNEP),
Unesco's Intergovernmental Océano¬
graphie Commission and the Asso¬
ciation of the South Pacific Environ
mental Institutions (ASPEI), in col¬
laboration with the World Meteoro¬
logical Organization (WMO) and
the World Conservation Union
(IUCN), asserts that people repre¬
sent the greatest threat to coral reefs.
Because of the constandy increasing
emissions ofgreenhouse gases and
gases that destroy the ozone layer,
we can expect: a rise in air and sea-
surface temperatures; changes in
weather patterns; more frequent
storms, droughts and floods; pos¬
sible alterations in ocean currents
and in the chemical composition
of sea water due to higher concen¬
trations of CO2. The hole in the
ozone layer again comes into it:
coral larvae have a very low toler¬
ance to ultra-violet rays. Freshwater
run-off, loaded with dissolved nutri¬
ents, promotes the development of
phytoplankton, the favourite food of
the larvae ofAcanthaster, an enor¬
mous starfish measuring 60 cen¬
timetres in diameter that can dev¬
astate coral reefs. It extracts its
stomach from its body and attaches
it to the rock, devouring and
digesting all the coral's living matter.
One of the most controversial
human activities in the Pacific
region is French nuclear testing on
the Mururoa Atoll. Yet some scien¬
tists are happy about this because
when testing takes place vertical
soundings to a depth of 1,200
metres and oblique soundings
towards the ocean have made it
possible to study the terrain ofvol¬
canic origin that constitutes the
base and sides of the atoll. Subsi¬
dence after the explosions has also
enabled scientists to study the
impact of the rise in sea-level on
this kind of island.
WHITE DEATH
In April 1991 and again recently
Polynesian fishermen and divers
observed a strange phenomenon
that intrigues researchers. The reefs
seemed to "flower" in gorgeous, flu¬
orescent colours or else to become
totally white. The eight high islands
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
Gorgonla
(Australia).
in the Society archipelago were
affected. Was the coral being deci¬
mated by the few degrees' rise in
the global temperature? According
to the findings of three tropical
oceanographers, Francis Rougerie,
Bernard Salvat and Miri Tatarata-
Couraud, "bleaching" seems to be
the result of a combination of fac¬
tors: "a heat wave in the tropical
ocean combined with an accentua¬
tion of the greenhouse effect, an
overdose of ultra-violet rays con¬
nected with the reduction of the
ozone layer, a shortage of nutrient
salts, disease or oxygen intoxication".
They conclude that "Whatever the
real cause, the threat to the algae-
coral ecosystem is serious and could
be linked to human activities. Are
we witnessing a veritable eco-geno-
cide?" Fortunately, according to Pro¬
fessor Jean Jaubert, the phenom¬
enon is not irreversible and under
certain conditions the symbiotic
algae return to the coral, and they
start life over again together.
The increase in CO2 for which
we are directly responsible now
exceeds the absorbent capacity of
the plant-life that feeds on it, espe¬
cially since we continue to destroy
forests. Yet it is probable that even if
the world were completely
replanted there would not be
enough vegetation to absorb the
751 gigatons of CO2 present in the
atmosphere. Can coral reefs help
us to get rid of it? "Although they
consume CO2 to make their skele¬
tons," Jean Jaubert remarks, "they
actually release more than they
absorb, i.e. about 2 per cent of the
CO2 released by human beings, but
that is a normal figure for the inter-
glacial period we are living in."
Even if they do not get rid of CO2
for us, corals deserve our fullest
attention. They are food-stores,
assuring the survival of all those
who live by fishing on the many
islands surrounded by reefs. The
Monaco Scientific Centre is at pre¬
sent the only place where coral is
grown in laboratory conditions.
Their oldest specimen is 16 years
old. "We take cuttings from it, and
they become our laboratory mice
for experimentation. So we don't
have to take samples from reefs. We
have a kind of nursery of seedlings
ready to help restore reefs that are in
bad shape!"
FURTHER READING:
'«" Coral ReefManagement
Handbook, R. A. Kenchington and
Brydget E. T Hudson, Unesco,
1988.
' Les coraux, B. Robin, C. Petron
and C. Rives, Les Editions du
Pacifique, 1988.
<* Coral Reefs, Unesco, 1990.
* Reefs at Risk, published by
UNEP, IOC, WMO, WWF and
IUCN, 1993.
<*- Monitoring Coral Reefsfor
Global Change, IUCN. 1993.
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD-Unesco
training programmeforAfrican
news agencyjournalists.
u
a:
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
w
IF TOADS HAD
FEATHERS. . .
This is no joke, but a thought
inspired by a serious study
published by the US National
Academy of Sciences and
sponsored by the National
Science Foundation, the
Forestry Service and the
National Geographic Society.
The frog and toad population
of every continent is
dwindling because these
hairless, featherless creatures
with gelatinous, shell-less
eggs are sensitive to
ultraviolet B rays that attack
their DNA. The intensity of
these rays is increasing with
the depletion of the ozone
layer.
KILLER HOUSES
The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) says
that 20,000 lung cancer deaths a year are caused by the
polluted air breathed in homes, offices and factories.
Certain pollutants such as radon, a colourless and
odourless radioactive gas, tobacco smoke and asbestos,
are well known. Others, such as dust, mould and
mildew in air ducts, fumes from cleaning solvents,
furniture polish and carpet shampoos, are less so. In
most industrialized countries attempts to cut energy
costs have reduced ventilation rates in buildings,
increasingly exposing their inhabitants to noxious
products. A bill approved by the U.S. Senate would
give the EPA the power to develop safe levels for a
range of pollutants. Before being enacted into law it
must be approved by the House of Representatives
and signed by the President.
31
ANTI-NOISE
TYRES
Used tyres cause pollution
when they are burned
because they emit a
dangerous gas with a high
sulphur dioxide content.
Dumps are few and far
between and cost money. Now
a French company4' has come
up with the bright idea of
using them to make anti-
noisè screens. The tyres are
cut in two along the
diameter, then pressed
together and stacked in a
fire-resistant metal container
with a perforated cover on
the side facing the road. They
absorb 85 per cent of noise
frequencies between 250 and
2,000 Hertz, a real feat since
heavy road traffic emits
between 250 and 700 Hertz.
The tyres are rot-proof and
act as shock-absorbers in the
case of accidents. About 10
million tyres would be needed
to equip 200 km of
motorway, but it appears to
be an excellent way of
recycling this cumbersome
form of wasteFrance alone
produces more than 20
million used tyres a year.
*Groupe ACIAL, Division
Acoustique, 62, rue Amelot,
75011 Paris,
Tel.: (33-1)4492-1818,
Fax: (33-1)4338-7010.
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
MOROCCO'S
FUELWOOD CRISIS
In southern Morocco, on the
edge of the Sahara Desert,
the gradual disappearance of
forests is forcing villagers in
search of fuel to burn scrub
and even leaves. In order to
light a small fire, not even
hot enough to cook meat,
women spend 6 hours a day
gathering from 30 to 35 kg of
this fuel. The soil is not
regenerating, posing a threat
to the survival of plant-life.
The meagre herds of cattle
and sheep are being forced to
migrate in order to survive.
Gérard Buttoud of the French
National Institute for
Agronomical Research (INRA)
suggests cultivating oasis
trees, with emphasis on fruit .
trees and acacias for fodder,
associating perennial plants
with annuals, and promoting
the biological regeneration of
the environment.
WILL CHILDREN SAVE THE BALTIC?
According to the ecological organization Greenpeace,
the Baltic Sea is becoming more and more polluted. Its
lifeless waters contain all kinds oforganic and chemical
wastes. Bordering countries, which are counting on
industrial development as a motor for economic growth,
are not ready to jeopardize growth for the sake of
ecology. With the aid of the University ofRiga in Latvia,
Greenpeace has thus launched an operation urging all
the children who live on the Baltic rim to write to their
governments asking them to save the sea.
PREVENTIVE MEDICINE FOR THE
ENVIRONMENT
New European regulations oblige industry to reassess
100,000 chemical substances. This represents an enor¬
mous market for ecotoxicology, the environment's "pre¬
ventive medicine" department. At a rate of 300 sub¬
stances per year, it will take no less than 300 years to
complete the job! The European Union's directive 92/32
stipulates that before being marketed all new chemical
substances must be reported to a competent authority
in a member State, which must also be given a dossier
evaluating their potential risks to health and the envi¬
ronment.
WASTE-EATING
ALGAE
Stephen Skill, of the London-
based company Biotechna, has
developed the "biocoil", a
machine that uses algae to
clean up sewage. In a 5-metre-
high coil of polyvinyl chloride
tubes, chlorella algae absorb
nutrients such as nitrogen and
phosphate from the effluent
and transform them into
protein. When it is working at
full capacity the biocoil will
detoxify 20 cubic metres of
sewage per hour. The well-fed
algae can be dried out and
used as animal feed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
INITIATIVES
U
H
<
JAPAN: NEW APPROACHES TO THE ENVIRONMENT
Fujiyama, a
dormant volcano
whose snow¬
capped cone is
perfectly
symmetrical.
Japan is an archipelago of more
than 3,900 islands stretching over
3,000 kms. to the east of the Asian
continent It is a largely moun¬
tainous country, two-thirds ofwhich
is covered with forests. Most of the
124 million Japanese live on the
coastal plains, and the average pop¬
ulation density of 330 persons per
square kilometre explains many of
the country's environmental prob¬
lems. The annual per capita income
of $27,000 indicates the degree of
economic development, based on
use ofultra-modern technology and
on a high standard ofeducation. The
environment has suffered as a result
of economic growth and high levels
ofmass consumption. Awareness of
growing problems appeared in the
1960s, and since then two novel ini¬
tiatives have been taken.
THE POLLUTER PAYS
After the Second World War the
numbers of city-dwellers rose to 77
per cent of the population. Tokyo
became a city of 20 million people.
Many industrial complexes were
built along the coasts, without much
regard for the environment. Irre¬
versible harm was inflicted on
nature, and serious health damage
from water and air pollution
occurred, such as methyl-mercury
poisoning (Minamata disease), cad¬
mium poisoning (Itai-Itai disease)
and chronic arsenic poisoning.
There was a public outcry against
these tragedies, and in 1971 the
Japanese government established
an Environment Agency to halt the
spread ofpollution. Action was taken
on several fronts: against air, water
and soil pollution, noise, vibration,
ground subsidence and offensive
odours.
A GREEN CENSUS
Anewprinciple ofjoint liabilitywas
introduced to make polluters pay.
By March 1993, the company
responsible for the Minamata dis¬
aster had compensated 2,255 suf¬
ferers from the disease, and over
2,300 claims for compensation
remained to be settled. In 1993 more
than 88,000 people certified as air-
pollution victims (e.g. asthmatics)
received compensation.
To monitor the state of its nat¬
ural environment Japan has enlisted
the aid of thousands of experts in
natural history, over 100,000 volun
teers and a number of non-govern¬
mental organizations to carry out a
comprehensive and periodically up¬
dated nationwide survey known as
the "Green Census". The first survey
was effected between 1973 and 1979.
The fifth has just begun. Vegetation
maps on a scale of 1:50,000 have
already appeared, as well as hun¬
dreds of volumes on animal life,
rivers, lakes and many other natural
elements. After studying threatened
plant and animal species, the Envi¬
ronment Agency also published a
"Red Data Book ofAnimals in Japan",
while the Nature Conservation
SocietyofJapan has produced a "Red
Data Book ofPlants in Japan". Many
species are under threat from pol¬
lution, the destruction oftheir habi¬
tats and excessive hunting. The
country's 28 national parks have only
one ranger per 17,500 hectares and
are not, strictly speaking, reserves.
In some zones within the parks there
are even golf courses, spas and ski
resorts.
Each year since 1968, Japan has
published a report entided "Quality
of the Environment in Japan", in
Japanese and English. It is drawn
up after consultation with the Envi¬
ronmentAgency and other relevant
institutions and ministries.
According to the Organization of
Economic Co-operation and Devel¬
opment (OECD), it should be seen
as a model for most other OECD
members.
FURTHER READING:
OECD Environmental Performance
Reviews. Japan. OECD, 2 rue André-
Pascal, 75775 Paris Cedex 16, France.
1994 (also in French).
The Environment Agency, 122
Kasunigaseseki Tokyo 100,
Fax: (81-3) 3504-1634.
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN
action
Gold masterworks from the Andes
The finest specimens of pre-Columbian jewellery ever seen in Europe
SOUTH AFRICA INVITED TO
RETURN TO UNESCO
After the first democratically held
elections in its history South Africa has
been invited to rejoin Unesco, which it
left in 1956. During the election,
Unesco supported several non¬
governmental organizations involved in
civic education activities, backing, for
example, an audiovisual voter education
programme intended for illiterate and
semi-literate citizens that provided
information in English, Zulu, Sotho and
Afrikaans. Unesco also supported
existing organizations to guarantee
press freedom during the election,
notably by working with the
International Press Institute in a
commission set up to deal with media
complaints. A Memorandum of Co¬
operation is being worked out with the
new South African government. Priority
will be given to a reform of the
educational system in order to create a
base for equitable development and
contribute to the building of a
democratic, non-racial society free
from apartheid.
COSMOPOLITAN CITIES OF THE
MEDITERRANEAN
Granada, Istanbul, Alexandria, Tunis,
Beirut and Sarajevo are just a few of the
cities around the Mediterranean that
have absorbed many different influences
and developed a way of life that blends
conviviality with tolerance. At a time
when some of them are the tragic
victims of violence and destruction it is
worth remembering that in their past
"They bartered everything they had
for a few glass beads and baubles. I
watched carefully and tried to find out
if there was any gold. Some of them
wore jewels. I used sign language to
question them and learned that by
going south and sailing around the
island one could reach a kingdom. Its
king possessed large gold jars, great
quantities of them," wrote Christopher
Columbus on 1 3 October 1 492, the day
after his discovery of America. Five
centuries later, a fabulous exhibition
of pre-Columbian gold is being held in
Metz in eastern France, on the initiative
of the Council of the Moselle depart¬
ment and within the framework of
Unesco's World Decade for Cultural
Development. More than 600 pre-
Columbian pieces of gold-work from
Peru, Colombia and Ecuador are being
shown. The finest specimens of their
kind ever seen in a European exhibi¬
tion, they include the ceremonial gold
jewellery of great Meso-American
priests and princes, and sacrificial knives
and masks, most of which have never
left their countries, where they are held
as part of central bank gold reserves.
The exhibition, entitled "L'Or des
Dieux, l'Or des Andes", is being held at
the Arsenal in Metz until 2 October
1 994. It provides an exceptional oppor¬
tunity to find out about Amerindian
civilizations that were victims of the
greed their riches inspired and
remained largely unknown until their
history was reconstructed from ves¬
tiges unearthed by archaeologists. In
Europe their treasures sent back to the
Spanish monarchs by the conquista¬
dors disappeared because they were
prized only for their weight in gold.
they have often provided a setting for
intelligent coexistence.
The quarterly review Confluences
Méditerranée has devoted a special
dossier to this theme, prepared by
Anissa Barrak. Its contents include the
proceedings of a symposium on the
The exhibition is divided into three
parts, one for each donor country. The
first is devoted to ancient Peru, where
gold and metalworking originated in
the Americas and where, before the
Incas, the Mochica (100 B.C. to 600
A.D.)andtheChimu(llthto 1 5th cen¬
turies A.D.) cultures held sway. Archae¬
ologists have recently unearthed the
extraordinary intact Mochica tomb of
the lord of Sipan, dating from the 2nd
or 3rd centuries. The tomb has been
reconstituted not far from the Arsenal
in the church of Saint-Pierre-aux-Non-
nains, a Roman basilica that proudly
claims to be the oldest church in
France, where the Mochica prince lies
as if in his tomb, arrayed in gold and sur-
rounded by copies of the precious
objects that accompanied him to the
next world.
From Colombia, the El Dorado of
the conquistadors, 151 objects in gold
and tumbaga (a copper and gold alloy)
are on show. They have been lent by the
Gold Museum of the central bank in
Bogota, whose collections are repre¬
sentative of all the pre-Hispanic cul¬
tures. Ecuador has sent some
extremely rare gold and platinum alloy
pieces. They date from the beginning of
the Christian era and display a level of
craftsmanship that European gold¬
smiths would only attain centuries later.
The exhibition also includes a sec¬
tion that traces the history of gold from
neolithic times to its use in space tech¬
nology.
Information and reservation by
phone at (33-1) 44 10 73 03 or by the
French electronic directory (Minitel)
36l5-Billetelor36l5FNAC.
Tunisian Jewish community organized in
May 1 993 by the Tunisian delegation to
Unesco. The first institutionalized
encounter between the Jewish and non-
Jewish communities since the country's
independence, the symposium was
attended by Jewish and Muslim Tunisian 61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
intellectuals and artists, including writer
Albert Memmi, historian Lucette
Valensi and film-maker Férid Boughédir.
Confluences Méditerranée, No. 1 0,
Spring 1994, 90 French francs.
77, rue Biomet, 75015 Paris, France,
Tel: (33-1) 48 42 47 44.
A RADIO SERIAL
FOR AFGHAN WOMEN
Later this year, Afghan women will be
able to listen to a radio serial that will
provide first class entertainment while
informing them about health, nutrition
and farming. Produced by the BBC
World Service in co-operation with
Unesco, UNICEF and the United
Nations Development Fund for Women
(UNIFEM), the serial is scheduled to be
broadcast in two 15-minute episodes
weekly in two Afghan languages, Pashto
and Dari. The main objective is to
educate a mass audience of women,
who are often hard to reach through
conventional development projects,
about issues necessary to improve their
lives.
AN ATLAS OF BAROQUE ART
Twenty European and Latin American
experts on Baroque art met in Havana
(Cuba) in March for a first inter¬
regional seminar devoted to the
preparation of a 5-volume international
Adas of Baroque Art. Part of UNESCO's
"Baroque World Project", the atlas will
present the art and culture of the 1 7th
and 18th centuries in 40 countries, not
only in Europe and Latin America but
also in Asia.
INNOV, A DATA BANK
ON BASIC EDUCATION
Some 80 innovative basic education
projects in developing countries feature
on INNOV, a new database created as
part of "Education for All, Making it
Work," Unesco's major international
project to collect, analyse and promote
such innovations. INNOV is intended
for grassroots project managers,
teacher training institutes, researchers
and planning personnel in ministries of
education. It appears in English and will
be regularly updated. For further
information please contact the Division
of Basic Education/CBE,
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75352
Paris 07, France,
Tel: (33 1)4568-2364/2126,
Fax: (33-1) 4065-9406.
THIS ARTICLE IS ONE
OF A SERIES IN WHICH
THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL OF
UNESCO SETS OUT HIS
THINKING ON MATTERS OF
CURRENT CONCERN
INTERNATIONAL ILLUSTRATION
COMPETITION FOR CHILDREN'S BOOKS
62
The winners of the Noma Concours
for Picture Book Illustrations will
be announced in December 1994 by
an international jury convened by
the Asia/Pacific Cultural Centre for
Unesco (ACCU) in Tokyo. The
Concours, a biennial competition
launched in 1978 thanks to a
donation made by Mr. Shoishi
Noma, former vice-president of the
Centre, is intended to encourage
children's book illustrators in
developing countries. It is open to
nationals of Unesco Member
States in Asia and the Pacific,
Africa, the Arab world, Latin
America and the Caribbean. The
winner of the Grand Prix will
receive a medal, a cheque for
US$3,000 and an invitation to
attend the award ceremony in
Tokyo. The closing date for entries
is 15 November 1994.
Asia/Pacific Cultural Centre for
Unesco (ACCU),
6 Fukuromachi, Shinjuku-ku,
Tokyo 1 62 Japan,
Tel: (81-3) 3269-4445/4435,
Fax: (8 1 3)3269-4510.
:
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
COMMEN TARY BY FEDERICO MAYOR
SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT AND
OUALITY OF LIFE
Fl HE World Summit for Social Development that will be
I held in Copenhagen early next year will be an opportu¬
nity for the international community to search for a new
approach to a very wide range of questions of fundamental
importance to all of us. These questions include the nature
of work and the concept of "active life" (including leisure),
mechanisms for the transfer of knowledge, systems for pro¬
viding assistance to developing countries, trade relation¬
ships, the form of higher education, and many others.
Development efforts in the past have given priority to
economic growth, but they have been unable to prevent
widespread poverty and provide full employment. Among
their consequences have been the marginalization and exclu¬
sion of large sections of the population, the acceleration of
the rural exodus, the deterioration of the urban habitat, the
ghettoization of the suburbs and the degradation of the nat¬
ural environment. Meanwhile, structural adjustment policies
have severely affected social sectors such as education and
health and in some countries have even compromised the
prospects for economic recovery. A world-wide "social
adjustment" must now be achieved.
Economic growth should serve the cause of social devel¬
opment and respect the environment. Machines should
replace people only to do work that cannot really be done
efficiently by men and women. Otherwise, there will be a
huge social price to be paid in terms of unemployment,
extremism and violence.
I believe that action to promote social development
should be taken on six major fronts:
1. Endogenous capacity building in each country.
*" Education and training should be given the highest pri¬
ority and investment in education should be increased so that
socially distant and geographically remote populations can
have access to knowledge. Intensive training courses should
be permanently available without regard to age or level of pre¬
vious studies.
' Education and empowerment of girls and women are key
factors in curbing population growth, promoting gender
equity and in developing the full potential of women.
*" A new role for higher education should be found in all
countries, incorporating lifelong higher-learning facilities.
*" Continuing efforts should be made to promote the
transfer and sharing of knowledge, particular in science and
technology.
** Development should be based on the will of each society
and should express its fundamental identity. Cultural factors
should be an integral part of all strategies designed to achieve
balanced development.
2. Promoting the development of rural areas. The problem
of emigration from rural areas should be tackled at its roots,
particularly through education, through promoting crafts¬
manship and cultural tourism, encouraging the develop¬
ment of indigenous cultures, ensuring that everyone has
access to shelter, and decentralizing education and social
services at municipal level.
3. Combatting marginalization and exclusion and pro¬
motingparticipation in community life. This is a key indi¬
cator of social development respect for human rights and
the forming of democratic attitudes must be promoted from
early childhood. Tolerance and non-violence should be
encouraged by all possible means, as should intercultural dia¬
logue and press freedom.
4. Protecting and safeguarding the environment. As a follow-
up to Agenda 21, the action plan adopted at the Rio Summit
in 1992, efforts should be redoubled to promote environ¬
mental awareness. One extremely important goal is to reduce
the impact of natural hazards (especially recurrent ones).
Research and training on the relationship between Man and
Nature in different parts of the world should be carried out
in an interdisciplinary framework.
5. Improving communication. To foster awareness and to
promote social integration, communication must be
improved world-wide through the use of new communica¬
tion and information technologies. Countries should draw
up overall information policies in these fields.
6. Establishing "observatories" and "early warning systems"
that will be able to detect potential social conflicts and unrest
and will be of great importance for monitoring implemen¬
tation of the work of the World Summit. UNESCO has
recently launched a programme called MOST (Management
of Social Transformations) to respond to the growing demand
from developing countries and countries-in-transition for
assistance in building their capacities in social sciences and in
monitoring social change and transition.
We must indeed be vigilant to all aspects of social change
and seek imaginative ways of dealing with any threats that
may be posed. I am thinking, for example, of opportunities
to promote "eco-jobs" in the field of environmental pro¬
tection concerning water supply and quality, industrial gases,
the use of fertilizers and other artificial compounds, as well
as the development of small-scale rural food transforma¬
tion industries, cultural tourism, the protection of handicrafts
and cultural property.
Development must have a human face. Sustainable social
development is only possible by way of improvements in the
quality of life: better education, better health, respect for
human rights, democracy, the rational use of resources
through the application of advances in science and tech¬
nology, and a commitment to the culture of peace and inter¬
national solidarity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
The rescue of the Bulgarian Jews in 1943
by Emmanuel Vaillant
On 8 March 1 994, a
ceremony was held at
Unesco Headquarters
in Paris under the
patronage of
M. François Mitterrand,
President of France, to
commemorate the
saving of the Bulgarian
Jews during the Second
World War. The
Bulgarians were one of
the few peoples In
Europe to protect their
Jewish community, even
though their country
was allied to Nazi
Germany. The following
article draws largely on
the testimony of Louis
Blum, who lived
through these events
and, Ike 47,000 ofhis
fellow citizens, escaped
deportation to the
death camps. Forty
years later history
honours the memory
of thousands of
Bulgarians who
rejected Intolerance. It
also records the
shameful story of the
1 1,363 Jews from
Thrace and Macedonia
who were sacrificed
because they did not
possess Bulgarian
nationality.
64
Bulgaria, ruled by King Boris III, had a
population of six million in 1939. The
regime had fascist leanings, but a number
of opposition political parties were tol¬
erated. The people were mostly Orthodox,
and the Jewish community was well inte¬
grated.
When war broke out, Bulgaria
leaned towards the cause of Nazi
Germany, on which it was economically
dependent. The government soon
drafted an anti-Semitic law, "for the pro¬
tection of the nation". A year later the
law was adopted in the teeth of fierce
opposition from many Bulgarian mem¬
bers of parliament and writers.
On 1 March 1941, the country offi¬
cially became an ally of the Third Reich
and was later permitted to administer
Thrace and Macedonia. At that time
12,000 Jews, considered to be stateless
persons, were living in Bulgaria's two
"new territories".
In August 1942 a Commission for
Jewish Questions was set up under the
anti-Semitic ideologist, Alexander Belev.
In the same month a decree expelling
Sofia's Jews to the provinces was pro¬
mulgated.
"We were given six months to leave
the capital," Louis Blum remembers.
"Those who did not leave voluntarily
faced deportation to a city arbitrarily
assigned to them by the authorities. Most
of Sofia's Jews preferred to stay, hoping
that things would sort themselves out. At
the end of May 1943, however, they were
all forced to leave.
"My family chose to leave Sofia in
November 1942. We settled in Pazardjil,
near Plovdiv, Bulgaria's second largest
city. There were about a thousand of us
Jews in a district of some 30,000 inhab¬
itants. A few months after our arrival,
alarming rumours began to go round.
There was talk about trains carrying
Jews from Greece and Thrace to Poland
in cattle wagons. On 9 March 1943, the
police arrested our community leaders
and their families.
"About thirty people were interned
in the Pazardjil Jewish school, which
was in the grounds of the synagogue.
No one was allowed to visit them,
although a crowd of their Jewish and
non-Jewish friends gathered nearby.
Protests spread like wildfire. Efforts
were made to influence the authorities.
We discovered that the detainees were to
join the trainloads of deported Greek
Jews and that other arrests were immi¬
nent. Schoolmates immediately offered
to let me stay the night at their homes,
just in case.
"The next day all the Jews who had
been arrested were released. The decree
for their deportation to Poland had been
rescinded. After their release, there was
a big demonstration at which people
cried 'Long live Bulgaria, homeland of all
its children'. It was not until later that we
learned what had really happened."
An indelible stain
On 22 February SS Sturmführer Theodor
Dannecker, a close colleague of Adolf Eich-
mann, met Alexander Belev in Sofia where
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
the two men drew up a plan to deport
20,000 Jews to Germany. The first target
was the Jewish community in the terri¬
tories of Thrace and Greece ceded to Bul¬
garia by Nazi Germany. At the beginning
of March, with the consent of Boris III and
his government, 1 1,363 "non-Bulgarian"
Jews were arrested. Packed into freight
trains, they crossed Bulgaria on their way
to Treblinka, from which they never
returned.
The agreement signed by the
I Nazis provided for the depor¬
tation of 20,000 Jews. More than 8,000
still had to be found. The Commission
for Jewish Questions drew up a list of
8,400 names. The deportations were
scheduled for 9 March. The day before,
an official of the town of Kiustendil dis¬
covered dozens of freight wagons
standing near the local station, ready to
transport Jews to Poland. He told one of
his friends, who was close to the deputy
speaker of the Bulgarian parliament,
Dimiter Pechev. Deeply distressed by
this piece of information, Pechev raised
the matter in parliament on the same
day. Before being dismissed from his
post, he had time to collect the signatures
of forty-three leading opposition fig-
"The next day, all the Jews who
had been arrested were
released. The decree for their
deportation to Poland had been
rescinded. After their release,
there was a big demonstration
at which people cried 'Long
live Bulgaria, homeland of all
its children.' It was not until
later that we learned what had
really happened."
ures. Elin Pclin, president of the Bul¬
garian Writers' Association and a friend
of the King, wrote that "The conscience
of the Bulgarian people hangs in the bal¬
ance. The stain cast on our people by
the expulsion of our Jewish fellow-citi¬
zens will not be erased for generations to
come."
Resistance began to take shape. Asso¬
ciations of doctors, shop-keepers,
lawyers, university professors and the
highest officials of the Orthodox Church
called for the annulment of the expulsion
decree. In Plovdiv, Patriarch Cyril told
the Jewish community, "Wherever you
go, I shall go too." The Red Cross and
foreign Jewish leaders also brought pres¬
sure to bear, as did the Allies, who
announced an offensive on the Russian
front. In a report commenting on the
reaction of the Bulgarian people, the
ambassador of Nazi Germany wrote:
"The Bulgarian efforts to save their Jews
are due to the mentality of this people
which lacks our clearmindedness and
our ideological vision. Raised with
Armenians, Greeks and Gypsies, the
Bulgarians have no trouble living with
Jews, so that in their eyes nothing justi¬
fies the measures we are taking regarding
them." On 10 March, after a big demon¬
stration in the streets of Sofia, Boris III
withdrew the expulsion decree and the
Bulgarian Jews arrested in the provinces
were freed.
A prayer for peace
However, the repeal of this decree was not
followed by the abrogation of the anti-
Jewish laws. In May and June 1943, almost
20,000 Sofia Jews were deported to
provincial cities. During the same period,
7,000 Jews were sent to forced labour
camps.
"After the events of March
1943," continues Louis Blum,
"my father decided to send my brother
and me to Palestine. It was hard enousrh
"The Commission for Jewish
Questions drew up a list of
8,400 names. The deportations
were scheduled for 9 March.
The day before, an official of
the town of Kiustendil discov¬
ered dozens of freight wagons
standing near to the local sta¬
tion, ready to transport Jews
to Poland. He told one of his
friends, who was close to the
deputy speaker of the Bulgarian
parliament."
to get a Bulgarian passport, but getting
a British visa for Palestine was even more
difficult. Meanwhile, I passed my school
certificate in June 1943. I was immedi¬
ately put into a Jewish group and sent to
a work camp. Conditions were very
hard, but no one died of mistreatment,
exhaustion or hunger."
Before the end of the war Louis
Blum, his brother and 2,000 other Jews
managed to obtain a British visa enabling
them to go to Palestine. In 1948 and
1949 35,000 more Bulgarian Jews fol¬
lowed them. Today there are no more
than 5,000 Jews in Bulgaria.
On the occasion of the commemo¬
ration of the events of 1943, Eddie
Schwartz, president of the Organiza¬
tion of Jews in Bulgaria, stated, "At a
time when children and women, men
and old people so near to us are suf¬
fering and dying, victims of an insane
inter-ethnic conflict in the Balkans, the
Bulgarian example assumes the dimen¬
sion of a prayer for humanity and for
peace."
EMMANUEL VAILLANT
is a French journalist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
la
EXANDER
poet ofthe seventh art
Uovzhenko
byLubomirHosejko
The pioneering film-maker once dubbed "the Homer of the cinema" dominated the
Ukrainian cinema for three decades
66
OLEXANDER Dovzhenko was one
of the giants of Ukrainian
cinema. He was born in the
town ofSosnytsia on 30 August 1894,
shortly before the invention of the
cinema. After teaching for a while at
a primary school, then studying eco¬
nomics at the Kiev Institute of Com¬
merce, he was caught up in the mael¬
strom of civil war in 1918.
Once the Soviet regime had been
established, Dovzhenko took up var¬
ious responsibilities in education and
the fine arts. In January 1920, he chose
his political camp by joining the
Borot'bisti, a Ukrainian peasant party
in favour of independence. When it
was dissolved he found himself,
almost reluctantly, a member of the
Ukrainian Communist Party.
After a spell with the People's Com¬
missariat of Foreign Affairs, which
took him to Warsaw and then Berlin,
where he took lessons from the
Expressionist painter Erich Heckel,
Dovzhenko settled in Kharkov, then
Ukraine's administrative capital, and
took up painting. He contributed illus¬
trations and cartoons to several news¬
papers, and designed film posters.
After half-heartedly toying with
the idea of a theatrical career,
Dovzhenko ended up joining the
Odessa film studios. He had earlier
decided to give himself ten years in
which to master the art of painting,
and nowassimilated cinematic tech¬
nique within a year. The next step was
to make his mark on the screen.
Dovzhenko's first film efforts in
1926 were minor works: a satirical
comedy, Vasya the Reformer, and a
burlesque short, Love's Berry. Then
he directed his first successful film, a
thriller called The Diplomatic Pouch
(1927), in which he himself played
the part of a stoker, his first and last
screen role.
A year later, Zvenyhora secured
Dovzhenko a place in the pantheon of
great directors. It is an eclectic but
spontaneously original work, a
sweeping poetic pageant that encom¬
passes ten centuries ofUkrainian his¬
tory. The linking thread of this visual
symphony in twelve cantos is the
figure of an old man who embodies
the patriarchal peasantry, and who is
attached to the values of the past and
indifferent to those of the Revolution.
The film marked the beginning of
Dovzhenko's own personal tragedy.
A deeply patriotic artist,
Dovzhenko ran up against the ideo¬
logical and aesthetic constraints of a
totalitarian regime throughout his
career. He was forced to make con¬
cessions to those in power and to
praise them in sometimes overblown
terms. He stated, for example, that
his aim in Arsenal (1929) was to
destroy nationalism and chauvinism
and glorify the working classes. The
film, which describes the workers'
uprising against the Rada (central
council) ofKiev, exaggerates the Bol¬
sheviks' achievements. Arsenal, which
bristles with didactic symbolism, is
the most expressionist work produced
by Ukrainian cinema.
That did not stop Dovzhenko
campaigning actively for the recog¬
nition of national minorities. He
championed above all the cause of
his native land. Earth (1930), made
at the watershed between two eras
and a harbinger ofgreat upheavals to
come, is a hymn to the glory ofnature
and its perpetual confrontation with
man. The shots showing the first
tractor flattening the boundary mark¬
ings in the fields and turning the peas¬
antry into a collectivist society were
much imitated in later Soviet films.
An epoch-making work that car¬
ries an extraordinarilypowerful emo¬
tional charge and produces an almost
physical effect of revelation, Earth
was violently criticized for its pan¬
theistic view of the world and its
excessive naturalism. It was also
denounced as nationalistic. Almost
thirty years later, a jury of 117 histo¬
rians meeting in Brussels in 1958 rated
Earth one ofthe twelve best films ofall
time.
Exiled in Moscow
Labelled a reactionary and banned
from lecturing at the Kiev Film Insti¬
tute, Dovzhenko was forced to stay
in Moscow and had to pay a high price
for his professional survival. His first
sound film, Ivan (1932), foreshadowed
Socialist Realism. It shows a radically
transformed Ukrainian landscape,
devastated by collectivization.
Starving peasants try to escape depor¬
tation and the effects ofan artificially
engineered famine. Those taken on
as navvies on the construction site of
the Dnieper dam project are the cen¬
tral characters of this film of great
pathos, which ambitiously tackles
such issues as the forced industrial¬
ization ofan agricultural community
and the social rehabilitation of the
peasantry through collective labour.
At a time when Russian directors were
becoming increasingly prosaic,
Dovzhenko steered the Ukrainian
Dovzhenko
(centre) during the
making of
Michurin, his first
colour film, which
was released in
1949.
Dovzhenko,
who had given
himself ten
years in which
to master the
art of painting,
assimilated
cinematic
technique within
a year. The next
step was to
make his mark
on the screen."
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
cinema towards more poetic hori¬
zons.
After the genocide of 1933,
Dovzhenko was forced to endure a
twofold exile: he was robbed of both
his native land and his creative uni¬
verse. Stalin sent him off to Siberia to
shoot Aerograd (1935), a film about
the construction of a Utopian city.
The mise-en-scène of this visionary
work shows Dovzhenko at his most
inspired. It was the first time he had
set eyes on the landscape of the taiga,
and he immediately spotted its pow¬
erful aesthetic potential. Aerograd,
which describes Japanese infiltration
into eastern Siberia, delivers an eco¬
logical message. But it was soon for¬
gotten.
Stalin wanted Dovzhenko to make
a "Ukrainian Chapayev". He therefore
authorized him to return to Kiev to
direct Shchors, a historic and revolu¬
tionary epic to which he was to devote
four years ofhis life. The film paints a
moving portrait of the commander
of the first Ukrainian Soviet division
during the civil war. Shooting was
long and difficult, as Dovzhenko was
kept under close surveillance during
the purges of 1936-37: the rushes were
systematically sent to Moscow and
checked by the Kremlin. Depending
on Stalin's mood and the political sit¬
uation at a particular moment,
Dovzhenko might be forced to rejig
whole sequences, sometimes even
five or six times. Shchors, who had
actually been killed by a stray bullet,
had to be shown as the hero of a Bol¬
shevik happy end. It is true that the
war clouds were gathering.
A new form of creation
After the signing of the Russo-German
pact in September 1939, western
Ukraine was reunited with the Soviet
Ukraine. The event was the subject
of Dovzhenko's first documentary,
Liberation (1940). He made two others
during the Second World War, The
Battlefor Our Soviet Ukraine (1943),
an extremely violent indictment of
war, and the more considered and tri¬
umphant Victory in the Ukraine
(1945). Towards the end of the war
Dovzhenko wrote and secretly edited
for the Yervan studios a documentary
about Armenia, Native Land (he is
not credited as editor).
Dovzhenko had earlier planned to
make a film called Ukraine in Flames.
But the publication in 1943 ofextracts
from the script caused a scandal. He
was summoned before the Politburo
by Beria, who controlled the Soviet
Union's internal security system, and
roundly admonished by Stalin, who
accused him of being a defeatist and
party to a nationalist plot. Such treat¬
ment only made Dovzhenko all the
more determined to look beyond the
Stalinist notion of the class struggle
and criticize the education of Soviet
youth and its ignorance of history,
which he saw as the reason for the Red
Army's defeat in 1941.
Dovzhenko was dismissed from
his post as artistic director of the Kiev
studios. He then embarked on a new
career as a war correspondent, writing
some thirty articles, pamphlets and
short stories while the war was still
on. The effervescence of his literary
inspiration can be judged from stories
like The Mother, On the Barbed Wire
and Before the Battle, plays like The
Descendants of the Zaporozhe Cos¬
sacks and Life in Bloom, and his novel
The Golden Gates.
Final indignities
After the war, Dovzhenko's filming
activity was severely cut back. The
personality cult was at its height, and
priority was given to biographical
films. It was in that noisome ideolog¬
ical climate that he made his first
colour film, Michurin (1949), a biog¬
raphy of the celebrated Russian
agronomist. But Dovzhenko refused
to produce a work of pure scientific
popularization, and his final cut was
turned down by the authorities. To
save his film from destruction, he
made a second version including var¬
ious rationalist and didactic episodes,
though he did manage to retain two of
the original sequences. A hybrid work,
Michurin is above all a tribute to
nature and to solitude a fate shared
by both the film-maker and his sub¬
ject. Michurin wanted to turn the
earth into an orchard. That was also
the secret dream of Dovzhenko, an
ecologist before his time.
Dovzhenko suffered one final
humiliation. When he had almost fin¬
ished shooting the interiors of
Goodbye America (1950), he was
locked out of the studios. He had
made the mistake of choosing a sen¬
sitive subject, taken from a short story
by the American Annabel Buckart.
The central character of the story,
Anna Bedford, who works at the
American embassy in Moscow, refuses
to become a spy and ends up going
over to the Soviet camp. As always,
Dovzhenko gave a poetic dimension
to the story, one of political brain¬
washing. Once again he was dis¬
avowed : the Cold War was at its height.
Stalin's death in 1953 completely
changed Dovzhenko's life. He lectured
at the State Film Institute in Moscow,
did some more writing, and devoted
After Dovzhenko's death his wife Yulia
Solntseva, who had worked closely with
him, made several films based on his
scenarios. Right, a scene from Poem of the
Sea, released in 1959.
anniversar
the last three years of his life to
preparing Poem ofthe Sea. But he died
on 25 November 1956, shortly before
shooting was due to start. He left six
unfilmed screenplays, including one
of Taras Bulba, which he had always
wanted to direct. His wife and collab¬
orator Yulia Solntseva loyally con¬
tinued his work and directed Poem of
the Sea (1958), The Flaming Years
(1961) and The Enchanted Desna
(1964) from his screenplays.
Dovzhenko was not only a tow¬
ering figure ofUkrainian cinema over
almost three decades, but one of the
most pioneering directors in the his¬
tory of film. The man dubbed "the
Homer of the cinema" by the Venice
Film Festival immortalized on film
an era that was at once productive
and tragic. The price he had to pay
was that although he miraculously
survived the system he was totally
ostracized by it.
His work, with its Gogolian under¬
tones, can be seen as a long lyrical
meditation on what it means to be
Ukrainian. His formal innovations,
such as the meditative pause, the
voice-over and an editing style that
breaks free from the spatio-temporal
restrictions of the image, established
a filmic syntax that was totally new
for the period. His brand ofrealism, at
once poetic, revolutionary, romantic
and socialist in form, was always
national in content. Although his mes¬
sage was occasionally obscured by
the philosophical digressions that
accompanied his lyrical outpourings,
his poetic language inspired many
film-makers. Kinugasa, Kurosawa and
Rossellini, to name but three, owed
much to Dovzhenko.
Worshipped abroad but all too
often detested by his own people,
Dovzhenko was a true poet who
always highlighted the purest aspects
of the beautiful. His work marks the
triumph ofbeauty over truth, of inner¬
most conviction over reason. B
"He was
summoned
before the
Politburo by
Beria and
roundly
admonished by
Stalin, who
accused him of
being a defeati
and party to a
nationalist plo'
LUBOMIR HOSEJKO
is a French cinema
critic of Ukrainian
origin. He is a
member of the
Ukrainian Film¬
makers' Union,
and, as a specialist
in films made by
expatriate
Ukrainians, works
for several
newspapers in the
Ukraine and
elsewhere. He is
currently engaged
in the creation of a
Ukrainian Film
Library and is
working on a history
of the Ukrainian
cinema.
67
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
The Dawn ofSerenity:
Letterfrom Borobudur
The Buddhist sanctuary of Borobudur (Indonesia) is one of the jewels of the world cultural heritage. Eiji
Hattori, a specialist in Buddhist art and thought, has long been fascinated by this great monument. Here
he suggests a new interpretation of its symbolism.
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
68
Dawn.The endless forest ofcoconut
trees is sleeping beneath white
mist, while to the east the elegant
silhouette of Mount Merapi stands out
against a background ofgolden light. Smoke
is rising gently from the volcano. Here and
there on the awakening plain below a cock
crows and breaks the silence. The lines of
stupas stand like süent shadows in the cool
of the early morning. Among them I can
see the statue ofa Buddha facing the rising
sun; the new day's light does not seem to dis¬
turb his meditation for an instant.
It is the dawn ofserenity.
In the half light I can make out a man
dressed in white sitting at the foot of the
central stupa. A strange vibration emanates
from him. I listen. He is murmuring a sutra.
Perhaps one of Java's few Buddhists,1 his
hands are joined as he calmly greets the
sun that by now is shining on Mount
Merapi. Then he goes silently away.
This is not my first visit to Borobudur.
The more I get to know this monument, the
more I am dazzled by its beauty. Some
twenty years ago Unesco launched an appeal
to the international community to save it.
Twenty-seven countries responded and
worked with Unesco and Indonesian experts
to move a million stones over a ten-year
period so that this chandi2 could live again
in its original form. Borobudur is an excep¬
tional place. It is not a temple it has no
place forworship nor for making offerings
but a huge Buddhist sanctuary that is both
a stupa3 and a mándala (a cosmic image) .
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
by Eiji Hattori
"I see the statue of a Buddha facing the rising
sun." At right of photo, the volcanic peak of Mt.
Merapi.
In eighth-century Java the rulers of the
prosperous Sailendra {saila indra: king of
the mountains) dynasty converted to
Mahayana4 Buddhism, a form ofBuddhism
that came into being around the same time
as the beginning of the Christian era. Using
the most advanced techniques available,
they built this brilliantly designed stone
mándala some time around the year 800.
Thousands of labourers, craftsmen and
artists worked on it. But how briefwas the
life-span of their masterpiece! Less than a
century after its completion Borobudur
had disappeared into oblivion, rather like
the earth mándala in ancient India that
returned to dust after seven days ofuse.
Why did the dynasty, which had built
other masterpieces in central Java, abandon
it in the tenth century and turn its attention
to the eastern part of the island? Could it
have been because ofan eruption ofMount
Merapi and the violent earthquake that
would have followed? Like Pompeii beneath
its shroud of ash, Borobudur fell into a
thousand-year sleep. It was not until 1814
that the legendary chandi, buried deep in
the jungle, was rediscovered by an agent
sent out by Sir Thomas Stamford Raffles, at
that time the British governor ofJava.
The three spheres
Let us take a closer look at Borobudur. On
the Kedu plain, formerly known as the
garden ofJava, the sanctuary stands on the
top of a decapitated hill and is built of
andésite, a bluish-greyvolcanic rock. It is a
colossal pyramid of superimposed tiers
that are crowned by an enormous bell-
shaped stupa. From a distance you can tell
that the whole construction is organized
around this stupa.
At closer range you can see a heavy stone
encasement around the base thatwas prob¬
ablybuilt to shore up the monument during
its construction. It hides the real base or
"hidden foot", which is decorated with 1 60
reliefs, all of which were photographed
shortly after they were discovered in the
late nineteenth century.
These "invisible" reliefs depict the
Sphere of the Desires that the human being
is bound to, the kâmadhâtu. I do not agree
with theories that claim this part of the
monument was deliberately covered up for
religious motives to prevent pilgrims from
"In eighth-century Java the
rulers of the prosperous
Sailendra dynasty
converted to Mahayana
Buddhism. Using the most
advanced techniques
available, they built this
brilliantly designed stone
mándala. Thousands of
labourers, craftsmen and
artists worked on it. But
how brief was the life-span
of their masterpiece!"
seeing it. On the one hand, the "hidden
foot" contains unfinished reliefs indicating
that work suddenly came to a halt due to
some unexpected event. On the other, as I
shall explain later, such an error seems
quite inconceivable in such a carefully
planned monument. This part of the mán¬
dala symbolizes "extreme exteriority": each
side has a stairway in the middle, leading up
to the monument's highest point.
The main structure of the sanctuary is
composed of this foundation and, standing
on top of it, five square terraces. The super¬
structure consists of three circular terraces.
This is the basic shape of the mándala: the
square, a symbol of the earth, and the circle,
symbolizing the sky, combine to produce
Borobudur's bas-reliefs are a vast picture-book in
stone illustrating the life of the historical Buddha
and the spiritual quest for Enlightenment of
Sudhana, the son of a rich merchant.
T - . 1
J
I ¿±d.
mt
P
B
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
"In Borobudur the transition from earth to sky, from
form to non-form, is made gently. I see it as an
intentional transition towards the circle. The
square form is not rigorously adhered to. Nor are
the first two terraces exactly circular. Only the
topmost terrace is a perfect circle." Left, aerial
view of Borobudur.
Opposite page, the "Mándala matrix" {Taizo-kal
mandara), an initiatory painting of Japanese Tantric
Buddhism. The height of the mándala, painted on
canvas from a Japanese temple, is 179 cm.
70
the number nine, the supreme figure of
Buddhism.
The galleries, which have to be visited
clockwise to respect the ritual circumam-
bulation, begin on the second terrace. They
are lined with 1,300 wonderful bas-reliefs
2,500 metres long. This is rûpadhatu, the
Sphere ofForms, in which the human being
gives up his thirst for desire but keeps his
Borobudur: from rediscovery to World Heritage listing
The site: a vast Mahayana Buddhist monument in the form of a pyramid-shaped mándala, built
in the heart of Java around 800 A.D. by the Sailendra dynasty and abandoned shortly after its com¬
pletion.
Size: the square base, with sides measuring some 120 metres, covers an area of almost one and
a half hectares; the central dome that crowns the monument is almost 35 metres above the base.
1814: rediscovery of the monument by Sir Thomas Stamford Raffles, who has the site cleared
of rubble and vegetation. Specialists compile documentation based on drawings.
1885: discovery of "the hidden foot"the original baseand its bas-reliefs concealed behind the
retaining wall needed to keep the structure from sliding.
1907-1911: Theodoor Van Erp carries out the first restoration work. He dismantles and rebuilds
the three circular terraces and the stupas.
1955: Indonesia seeks Unesco's advice on measures to prevent the monument's dilapidation.
1972: Unesco launches an international appeal to save Borobudur.
1975-1982: restoration work carried out.
23 February 1983: inaugural ceremony to mark the completion of restoration work. Total cost: $20
million, two-thirds from the Indonesian government, and $7 million from Unesco's international cam¬
paign, in which 27 countries took part.
1991: Borobudur included on Unesco's World Heritage list.
name and form. This immense stone book
relates Buddha's life as told in the sutras.
Nooks located on the outside of the
balustrades that surround the galleries each
contain a stone Buddha seated cross-legged
on a lotus cushion. There are 432 in all.
Next we come to the foot of the upper
part of the mándala. Here the view to the
outside, hitherto impeded by the balustrades,
suddenly opens up, so that one has a sense
of spritual breadth as one enters the arû-
padhâtu, the Sphere ofFormlessness.
In Borobudur the transition from earth
to sky, from form to non-form, is made
gently. The square form is not rigorously
adhered to: the edges around each square
terrace jut out and break up the hard right
angles, perhaps in an attempt to use archi¬
tecture to relieve the monotony of the pil¬
grim's perambulation. Personally I see an
intentional transition to the circle. Aerial
photos show that the first two terraces are
not exactly circular. A slight deformation
makes them more like squares! Only the
topmost terrace is a perfect circle.
Borobudur's three spheres mark the
spiral stages of an ascension that leads the
pilgrim up to the stupa of ultimate truth.
This central stupa, whose walls are not per¬
forated like those of the others, contains
nothing, the ultimate point is nothing but
emptiness {sûnyatâ). Buddha himself is
hidden. He is there yet not there; he is being
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
and non-being. Each of the seventy-two
small stupas with perforated walls that stand
on the three terraces contains a statue of
the Buddha. His face can only be imper¬
fectly made out through the gaps in the
stonework. These gaps are of different
shapes and become less numerous as one
approaches the central stupa, signifying the
Buddha's increasing invisibility. All these
Buddhas have the same hand position
[mudra): that of the perpetually-moving
wheel of the Law.
When we reach the summit, we sud¬
denly share the cosmic vision ofMahayana
Buddhism. Here the supreme reality is
unveiled, light is born! Yes, Borobudur, which
shimmers in a thousand colours from
morning to night, itself glistens like a huge
beacon. The sanctuary's 504 Buddhas face
the fourpoints ofthe compass and embrace
the world with merciful, shining eyes. Not
only these stupas, but the nooks in the wall-
parapets, the little towers, the smallest parts
ofthe edifice all reach skywards as if to seize
the breath ofpassing clouds.
The mándala of mándalas
According to this interpretation, Borobudur
is the lotus home of the "Great Buddha of
Light", who is depicted in a myriad ofsmall,
finely carved Buddhas. Dust itselfbecomes
light. As the doctrine of Mahayana Bud¬
dhism has it, the one resides in the many,
which is itself the manifestation of the one.
In the Gandhavyûha, the sacred text of
Mahayana Buddhism, light is not the enemy
ofshade: it is the light of the original empti¬
ness, which transcends the opposition
between being and nothingness.
Let us now look at the mándala this
esoteric image that aids active meditation of
the Buddhist cosmos formed by
Borobudur. Mándalas, whether painted or
sculpted, like the statues in the To-ji temple
in Kyoto, are always oriented in relation to a
central point. Borobudur, which looks out at
the four points of the compass while its
"heart" is empty, is a perfect illustration of
the mándala concept.
In 1930 the French archaeologist and
architect Henri Parmentier suggested that
Borobudur might have been originally con¬
ceived as an immense stupa resting on
square terraces but that problems of sta¬
bility forced the builders to rethink the plans
for the upper part. This theory was sup¬
ported by several participants in the inter¬
national symposium on Borobudur held in
Tokyo in 1980, but it seems unacceptable to
me. Even if Borobudur underwent minor
changes during its construction, the extreme
rigour of its design rules out the idea ofany
such architectural compromise.
A mysterious concordance
The mysterious concordance of the num¬
bers one sees at Borobudur is to my mind
sufficient proof. As I have said, there are
432 Buddhas on the square terraces and
72 others on the concentric terraces of the
upper part. These figures are not a mere
coincidence. Since the stairways divide
each of these groups of statues by four, in
each case their total number (432 and 72)
and the number of each group thus
obtained (108 and 18) can be divided by
three and nine. In other words, it is clear that
the entire structure was conceived as a
function of the number three, which sym¬
bolizes unity and the square of three, nine,
a sacred number in Buddhism.
Another researcher, J. G. De Casparis,
believed that the central stupa crowning
the structure was a tenth terrace, corre¬
sponding to the ten stages passed through
by the bodhisattva ("Buddha-to-be") before
reaching the state of Buddhahood. But
when Borobudur was built only six stages
were practised in lava. Surely they are rep¬
resented in the six square terraces. But how
can the transition from the square to the
circle be explained?
I had never been entirely happy with
any of these interpretations. Then one day
I read the Jûj'û shin ron (Treatise on the Ten
Stages of Thought) in which Kukai, the
Japanese Buddhist Grand Master who IÎ
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
72
founded the esoteric Shingon sect at the
beginning of the ninth century, expounds
his conception of the mándala.
In his eyes the "ascending transforma¬
tion of the spirit", for which the mándala is
the pictorial expression, is effected in nine
exoteric (apparent) stages, followed by a
final, esoteric (secret) stage. Could there
be any better definition of Borobudur's
architectural significance? Starting from
the sphere ofanimal desire, the monk even¬
tually reaches the "spirit laden with mys¬
tery" {Himitsu-shôgon-Shiri), the culmi¬
nating and hermetic point. The awakening
he experiences then transforms the world
into light. Was this not the secret that the
immense mándala was whispering to us
in the early light of dawn?
So is Borobudur a monument of eso¬
teric Mahayana Buddhism? I cannot say
so categorically, but I am profoundly con¬
vinced that it is.
Let 'there be no mistake. I am not
claiming that Kukai influenced the building
of Borobudur. I am only saying that
Borobudur and Kukai's teachings share a
common source. Kukai himself was initi¬
ated into the esoteric doctrine of Shingon
(True Word) in China and introduced the
first mándala to Japan.
In which year did he return to his
country? In 806, at the very time when the
Sailendra were building Borobudur on the
island ofJava. Let us not forget either that the
Todaiji, the temple of the Great Buddha in
Nara (Japan), the conception ofwhich was
based on the same Gandavyûhathat is illus¬
trated along most of Borobudur's square
terraces, was inaugurated in 751, the date
when work on the foundations of the
Javanese sanctuary is thought to have begun.
The sea route to China
This apparent coincidence is not confined
to Japan and Indonesia. In Ceylon at the
same time thousands of monks practised
the same doctrine ofMahayana Buddhism
in the monastery ofAbhayagiri, which was
in permanent contact with China. And to
reach China the Sinhalese monks did not
cross mountains but the sea!
This is where the maritime Silk Road
comes in. It played a decisive role in the
story of the meeting ofcivilizations. It was
a speedy route for the exchange of goods
and culture between the East and West,
perhaps even before there was an overland
Silk Road. It was used by many different
peoples: Indians, Chinese, Greeks, Romans
and Arabs, as well as Indonesians. Ceylon
was a port ofcall for those who crossed the
Indian Ocean, and once across the Malacca
Straits they either made a detour around
Singapore or sailed along the coasts of
Sumatra and Java before heading north¬
wards for Canton in southern China. The
maritime Silk Road eventually stretched
from Italy (Rome) to Japan (Nara), uniting
the Indian Ocean, the western Pacific, the
China Sea, the Red Sea and the Gulf.
Borobudur must be seen in the context
of this network ofextremely rich and varied
maritime exchanges. The seas of South¬
east Asia teemed with activity in the seventh
and eighth centuries. And when talking
about Indo-Javanese civilization, especially
a Buddhist monument, we should not
forget the part played by cultural influences
from nations other than India.
Look carefully at the meditating Bud¬
dhas ofBorobudur. Their expression differs
from that of Indian or Thai statues, and has
a greater affinity with those of China and
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
Japan. Did not the Sailendra have a large
fleet that travelled to China as well as to
India and Ceylon? Moreover the monks of
Abhayagiri often stopped in Java on their
way to China. They were even reported to
have founded a community in the eighth
century on a hill near Borobudur.
Could there be a link between the pres¬
ence of this monastic community and the
building of Borobudur? There is no defi¬
nite proof, but the shape of the stupas in
Borobudur is not unlike that of the stupas
in the lotus style ofAnuradhapura, Ceylon's
ancient capital. I also remember being
struck by the resemblance between two
statues ofBuddha discovered in the ruins of
Abhayagiri and the statues at Borobudur.
It is of course impossible to understand
the conception of Borobudur without
referring to the local culture. In Indonesia
"Not only these stupas, but the nooks in the wall-
parapets, the little towers, the smallest parts of
the edifice all reach skywards as if to seize the
breath of passing clouds." (Opposite page).
Below: "Each of the 72 small stupas with
perforated walls that stand on the three terraces
contains a statue of the Buddha. His face can only
be imperfectly made out through the gaps in the
stonework."
"Borobudur must be seen in the context of the network of extremely
rich and varied maritime exchanges formed by the maritime Silk Road.
The seas of Southeast Asia teemed with activity in the seventh and
eighth centuries."
THE MARITIME ROUTE TAKEN BY MAHAYANA BUDDHISM IN THE 8TH AND 9TH CENTURIES.
JAPAN
Dazaifu .... Nara
unang An \ Aian j 9 	
CHINA '.
Canton
INDIA
Pacific Ocean
Bay of
Bengal
SRI LANKA
Indian Ocean \ ' '
..- Borobudur
JAVA
UWWWmWÊÊÊÊÊÊÊÊÊIÊÊÊÊÊÊÊmWWWWWÊÊÊÊÊÊÊÊÊm.	wÊK
"Is Borobudur a monument
of esoteric Mahayana
Buddhism? I cannot say so
categorically, but I am
profoundly convinced that
it is."
EIJI HATTORI,
of Japan, is currently an advisor for
culture and science to the Director-
General of Unesco. A Unesco staff member
for many years, he initiated the
Organization's Integral Study of the Silk
Roads project.
there was a form of ancestor worship that
venerated the ancestors' spirits by building
tiered pyramids in their honour. Could
this great pyramid-shaped mándala have
been built without such a tradition? The
world owes this unique heritage to the
Indonesian people.
The sun has risen over Borobudur. My
thoughts turn to the outward-looking spirit
of the eighth century. There were no cultural
boundaries then. Peoples absorbed each
other's cultures like travellers slaking their
thirst together. Have those far-off times
gone forever? I cannot believe that they
have. Down in the water lotuses commu¬
nicate with one another through their roots.
Dew drops on petals reflect the same moon
that shines down on white flowers thou¬
sands of miles apart. And the sun that
shines on Mount Merapi now shone on pil¬
grims' faces at a time when beauty was the
splendour of truth.
1. The Javanese converted to Islam in the 15th
century.
2. A name given to Indonesia's oldest
monuments.
3. A reliquary or commemorative monument.
4. A sanskrit word meaning "a great means of
progression" or "Great Vehicle".
J3
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
R H
Thomas Mann
The new obscurantism
Tliis is the third andfinal instalment
ofThomas Mann's address to a
meeting organized in Nice in 1935 by
the International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation on the
theme of"the education ofmodern
man" (see our two previous issues).
Tins ardent defender ofEuropean
culture and civilization concludes
with a bitterly ironical commentary
on the rise ofirrationality in a
Germany delivered to Nazism.
Text selected and presented
"W ^L by Edgardo Canton
Necessity may indeed teach people
to think, but, one may wonder,
to think in what way? We have
seen for ourselves what happens when
the masses the middle and lower middle
classes, reduced to penury, dispossessed,
racked by distress and filled with resent¬
ment start to think and to indulge in
mystical speculation. The petty bour¬
geoisie had been taught that reason had
been done away with, that intelligence
was there to be insulted, and that those
bogeymen not unconnected with
socialism, internationalism and even the
Jewish mentality might in fact be to blame
for their plight; with this sanction from
above, they turned their thoughts against
reason and learned to get their tongues
around the difficult but reassuring term
"irrationalism". The spread of irrationalism
among the people at large during the
second and third decades of this century
is perhaps the most deplorable and ridicu¬
lous spectacle that history has to offer. It
was the petty bourgeois who had risen
from the ranks of the masses who them¬
selves, by dint of febrile mental effort,
came up with the term "intellectual mon¬
ster", a stupid expression but one that had,
to a certain extent, the blessing of the
higher echelons, where the anti-intellec¬
tual spirit reigned, and one that carried a
vulgar punch, a deadly turn ofphrase that
was primarily directed, in matters political
and social, against all reasonable, peaceful
aspirations and against all European sen¬
timents, but above and beyond that,
against all intellectual discipline and
morality.
A miasma of bad literature
Since, however, the mind, even when it is
anti-intellectual, cannot but remain mind,
its lowly offspring, the average man with a
few ideas in his head, cannot do without
either mind or thought. He talks, philoso¬
phizes and writes, but everything ema¬
nating from him is but a caricature ofmind,
low-powered intellectualism. The air is
heavy with thoughts spawned in the over¬
wrought brains of the populace. A stifling
miasma of bad literature hangs over the
country. Mass man, reasoning against
reason itself, has presumptuously claimed
for himself the exclusive right to think,
speak and write. He has silenced everyone
else and, confident that he will not be con¬
tradicted, avails himselfofhis privilege in a
way that takes one's breath away and
tempts one to curse the liberal democracy
that taught all and sundry to read and write.
Thought itselfand the written or spoken
word seem as if forever sullied by such
despicable misuse. Freed from all restraints,
a derisory culture, deplorablyworked up to
fever pitch, spreads far and wide its
pseudo-knowledge and its evil doctrines,
its farrago ofmystagogic nonsense and its
impudent decisions, with their thousand-
year pretensions; and learning, now intim¬
idated, now sheepishly sympathizing, dare
only feebly and fearfully raise some slight
objection. Some day soon, these "thinkers"
will be in a position to put their "ideas"
boldly into practice everywhere and write
them by main force into history. They will
get the history they deserve.
A philosophy of violence and
falsehood
Is there not, nevertheless, from the Chris¬
tian point of view, something moving
about the sight of this victorious uprising
by the poor in spirit, this overthrow of
learning, culture, intelligence and civi¬
lization and their replacement by the taste
and judgment of the lowly, the publicans
and sinners? One should, I believe, be very
careful about drawing such parallels. There
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
V
Thomas Mann in 1950.
are, between the Christian revolution and
the revolution of the masses, differences of
character, differences in regard to the feel¬
ings ofkindliness and humanity as I would
say to put it simply, that suffice to put us
seriously on our guard against misunder¬
standings and false comparisons.
Some might reply that the modern
movement is heroic in character, whereas
the Christian revolution and the French
Revolution were altruistic and humani¬
tarian. But much as I love and admire
heroism in its great spiritual manifesta¬
tions, I cannot bring myself to believe in
the heroism of the common people. Their
world is not heroic, it is a sensation-
seeking, detective-story-like world; it
strongly resembles the atmosphere of
dime novels and sensational films, but
there is nothing heroic about it.
One would hesitate to apply the word
heroic to the new methods of crime and
murder, the creations of a small-time
fanaticism, that are being followed in the
realm ofpolitics. Merely to be able to grasp
the meaning of heroism, one needs to
move on a higher moral plane than that of
a philosophy that takes violence and false¬
hood to be the fundamental principles of
life. This is in point of fact the philosophy
of the petty bourgeois who have been
infected by the urge to think. Apart from
violence, they believe only in falsehood,
and believe in it even more fervently than
in violence. Among the European ideas
that, since they have gone up in the world,
they hold to have been abolished for
good truth, freedom and justice it is
truth that they find most detestable and
impossible. They put "myth" in its place,
this term figuring as prominently in their
intellectual vocabulary as heroism.
The threat ofwar and the ruin of
civilization
Clearly, what we are dealing with here are,
again, a degenerate mind and a debased
literature. There are certain vital interests
to which the demands ofpure mind must
give way. Truth is an absolute, but life, the
realm of the permissive, is not; life requires
that truth which is useful and advanta¬
geous to it. So be it; but to acknowledge
falsehood as the only life-giving power,
the only power capable ofmaking history,
to elevate such a system to the status of a
philosophy in such a way that it becomes
impossible to distinguish truth from false¬
hood, to establish in Europe a disgraceful
pragmatism that repudiates mind itself in
favour of profit, that without compunc¬
tion commits or approves crimes so long
as they serve the cause of its ersatz
absolutes, that does not shrink from the
idea of falsity but values falsity as much as
truth as long as it finds it useful this is
what was in store for the type ofpeople to
whom I refer. I would not go so far as to
claim that they represent the "modern
man" we are supposed to be discussing,
but they are a common type; multitudes of
them exist, and when I say that they deter¬
mine the age in which they live, I am doing
no more than expressing their own con¬
viction, the conviction that provides the
devastating impetus with which they are
preparing to take on and conquer the
world a world whose moral scruples
hinder it from defending itself effectively
against them.
The outcome to which such a conflict
would lead is absolutely clear and certain:
it would be war, a disaster of immense
proportions, the ruin of civilization. I am
firmly convinced that this is the only pos¬
sible outcome ofsuch people's philosophy
in action. That was why I thought it my
duty to speak about them and about the
terrible threat they pose.
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[
From 13 to 16 December 1993,
the leaders of nine high-
population countries-
Bangladesh, Brazil, China, Egypt,
India, Indonesia, Mexico, Nigeria
and Pakistangathered in New
Delhi for the world's first Summit
on education for all. The goal of
the Summit, which was hosted by
the Government of India and
sponsored by Unesco, UNICEF
(the United Nations Children's
Fund) and the United Nations
Population Fund (UNFPA), was to
mobilize high-level political
support and financial and
technical resources for the
achievement of universal primary
education and adult literacy.
These countries, the home of
half the world's population, over
70 per cent of its adult illiterates
and more than half of its out-of-
school children, face major
obstacles as they seek to
achieve these goals. The size of
the challenge confronting them is
indicated by their population
numbers, rapid demographic
growth, vast distances, and
excessive urbanization combined
with the existence of
geographically remote and
scattered rural populations of
great cultural and linguistic
diversity.
At the same time, these
countries contain tremendous
potential for the future, given
their impressive scientific and
technological capabilities, the
rapid advances they have made
towards industrialization, their
large numbers of trained and
highly qualified personnel, and
the possibilities open to them of
benefiting from economies of
scale in education and other
fields.
Taking into account these
facts, the following Declaration
was adopted.
1 WE, the leaders of nine high-pop¬
ulation developing nations of the world,
hereby reaffirm our commitment to pursue
with utmost zeal and determination the
goals set in 1990 by the World Confer¬
ence on Education for All and the World
Summit on Children, to meet the basic
learning needs of all our people by making
primary education universal and expanding
learning opportunities for children, youth
and adults. We do so in full awareness that
our countries contain more than half of
the world's people and that the success of
our efforts is crucial to the achievement
of the global goal of education for all.
1 WE recognize that:
2.1 the aspirations and development goals
of our countries can be fulfilled only by
assuring education to all our people, a
right promised both in the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights and in the
constitutions and law of each of our
countries;
2.2 education is the pre-eminent means
for promoting universal human values,
the quality of human resources, and
respect for cultural diversity;
2.3 the education systems in our coun¬
tries have made great strides in offering
education to substantial numbers, and
yet have not fully succeeded in providing
quality education to all of our people,
indicating the need for developing cre¬
ative approaches, both within and outside
the formal systems;
2.4 the content and methods of education
]]>
</page>
<page number="77">
<![CDATA[
DECLARATION
must be developed to serve the basic
learning needs of individuals and soci¬
eties, to empower them to address their
most pressing problems combating
poverty, raising productivity, improving
living conditions, and protecting the
environment and to enable them to
play their rightful role in building demo¬
cratic societies and enriching the cultural
heritage;
2.5 successful education programmes
require complementary and convergent
actions on adequate nutrition, effective
health care and appropriate care and
development of the young child, in the
context of the role of the family and the
community;
2.6 the education and empowerment of
girls and women are important goals in
themselves and are key factors in con¬
tributing to social development, well-
being and education of present and future
generations, and the expansion of the
choices available to women for the devel¬
opment of their full potential;
2.7 the pressure of population growth has
seriously strained the capacity of educa¬
tion systems and impeded needed reforms
and improvements; moreover, given the
age structure of the populations in our
countries, it will continue to do so
throughout the coming decade; and
2.8 education is, and must be, a societal
responsibility, encompassing govern¬
ments, families, communities and non¬
governmental organizations alike; it
requires the commitment and participa¬
tion of all, in a grand alliance that tran¬
scends diverse opinions and political
positions.
3 CONSCIOUS of the vital role
that education must play in the devel¬
opment of our societies, we hereby
pledge that, by the year 2000 or at the
earliest possible moment:
3.1 we will ensure a place for every child
in a school or appropriate education pro¬
gramme according to his or her capabil¬
ities, in order that no child be deprived of
education for lack of a teacher, learning
materials, or adequate space; we pledge
this in fulfillment of our commitment
under the Convention on the Rights of
the Child, which we have ratified;
3.2 we will consolidate efforts towards
the basic education of youth and adults
from public and private sources,
improving and expanding our literacy
and adult education programmes within
the context of an integrated strategy of
basic education for all our people;
3.3 we will eliminate disparities of access
to basic education arising from gender,
age, income, family, cultural, ethnic and
linguistic differences, and geographic
remoteness;
3.4 we will improve the quality and rel¬
evance of basic education programmes
by intensifying efforts to improve the
status, training and conditions of
teachers, to improve learning contents
and materials and to carry out other nec¬
essary reforms of our education systems;
3.5 we will, in all of our actions, accord
to human development the highest pri¬
ority at national and other levels,
ensuring that a growing share of national
and community resources is dedicated to
basic education, and improving the man
agement of existing resources for educa¬
tion; and
3.6 we will rally all sectors of our society
towards education for all, as we hereby
endorse the Framework for Action
accompanying this Declaration and
undertake to review our progress at the
national level and to share our experi¬
ences among ourselves and with the
global community.
4 WE therefore call upon:
4.1 international collaborators to raise
substantially their support for our efforts
to expand our national capacities for
expanding and improving basic educa¬
tion services;
4.2 international financial institutions,
in the context of structural adjustments,
to recognize education as a critical invest¬
ment without imposing predetermined
ceilings on such investments, and to pro¬
mote an international environment to
enable countries to sustain their socio¬
economic development; and
4.3 the community of nations to join
with us in reaffirming the commitment to
the goal of education for all and in inten¬
sifying their efforts to achieve it by the
year 2000 or at the earliest possible
moment.
¥7
]]>
</page>
<page number="78">
<![CDATA[
THE U.N. GOES TO SCHOOL
T
i he Northeast International Magnet
School in Montclair, New Jersey
(U .SA.) , is a publicly funded school
with approximately 375 boys and girls aged
from four to eleven. About one-third of
the students come from forty different
countries, and altogether the children
speak twenty-seven different languages.
Northeast is one of a number of
"magnet schools" that were created several
years ago in order to encourage racial inte¬
gration. About one-third of the students at
Northeast are ofAfrican origin, reflecting
the fact that roughly one-fourth of the
population of Montclair itself are Ameri¬
cans ofAfrican origin. Each magnet school
focuses on one study area, international
affairs in the case of Northeast. Others
focus on the performing arts, science and
other special fields.
"With the population we had," says
Marty Miller, a teacher at the school, "and
with a principal who had the perspicacity
to see that we are very similar to the United
Nations in that we have children from all
over who really need to live with and
m O understand each other, it was not diffi-
>itt
cult to turn the school into a mini-United
Nations."
Children in each home room, the place
where the day's first class is held, invented
the name of a country, made a flag for it
and chose traits by which their country
should be known to the others. Thus one
home room is called "Afreemerica", while
others are called "Nigypt", "Angel Land"
and "Happlandia". The kindergarten chil¬
dren called their countries "Kinderfolk"
and "Kinderlund".
Each child who enters the school is
given a passport which is stamped as he or
she moves through the various grades.
When they leave school, students are
allowed to keep the passport as a souvenir.
The student body elected a Secretary-
General, eight-year-old Maya Berry, who is
in second grade. Her deputy is Under Sec¬
retary-General Brian Conroy, a fifth-grade
student.
A central part of the exercise is the
meeting of the Security Council, to which
all "nations" send ambassadors. The Secu¬
rity Council takes up complaints which
are brought to it for discipline.
Marty Miller tells of one complaint
that was brought to the effect that one
country was making too much noise for
by Sally Swing Shelley
An American school whose
pupils are drawn from many
countries has modelled itself
on the United Nations
the others to study. The children voted in
the Council to send an ambassador to ask
for the noise to stop, and to say that if it did
not then sanctions would be imposed in
this case the children in the offending
home room would not be allowed out to
play in the yard for a week. The offending
nation complied.
Marty Miller believes that one aspect of
the school particularly helps racial har¬
mony. "The children are all equal," she
says, "whether they are eleven or twelve
years old in the fifth grade, or seven or
eight years old in the second grade. The
little ones look after the big ones and the
big ones look after the little ones. It is
clearly understood that nobody has any
more power than anyone else. We have a
committee of peers that our Social and
Human Rights Council developed to help
boys and girls who have difficulty getting
along with others and say or do hurtful
things. The Council drafted a resolution
that was adopted by the General Assembly.
According to this resolution, if a citizen of
one country has a problem, the children
will counsel the child who caused it as
well as the victim (because they feel the
victim also needs to understand why
another child might have behaved in an
unacceptable way), thereby helping to
promote tolerance." M
. ._
SALLY SWING SHELLEY,
of the United States, ¡s a former information officer
in Unesco's liaison office with the United Nations in
New York. She is currently UN correspondent with
the German radio and television network Deutsche
Weile.
]]>
</page>
<page number="79">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
CHERCHEZ LA FEMME
As faithful readers of your magazine, which
opens new cultural horizons to us, we nonethe¬
less regret that it does not devote more space to
women in science and the arts or in intellectual
and social life. We are convinced that many
women are just waiting to be discovered (in
your monthly "Interview") or rediscovered (in
your "Archives" feature). Their outlook on the
world would definitely bolster your efforts to
make known Unesco's activities on behalfof the
"universal respect for justice, for the rule of
law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms for the peoples of the world, without
distinction of race, sex, language or religion."
Carolyn Medel Anonuevo,
Sofia Valdivieso, Uta Papen
Unesco Institute for Education
Hamburg, Germany
I THE WINGS OF HAPPINESS
I was surprised to see in your April 1993 issue
("A Time to Love. . .") a mistaken interpretation
by two authors, Henri Lopes and Jorge Enrique
Adoum) ofAragon's line "There is no such thing
as happiness in love".
The Second World War was the background
ofAragon's love for Elsa. The shadows of their
friends in the Resistance who had either been
deported or tortured to death hovered between
them. The context of their love clipped the
wings ofcareless rapture on which perfect hap¬
piness is borne.
Sylviane Schwer,
Paris, France
Ofcourse, this is one possible interpretation.
Editor
FRENCH WITH A CREOLE
TWIST
Working as a socio-linguist in the French-
speaking world, notably in Senegal, I would
like to qualify slightly some of Stephen Wurm's
remarks in his article "The Gift of Tongues"
(February 1994) on the expanding use of met¬
ropolitan languages by young people in former
colonial territories to the detriment of other
lingua francas.
The "vernacularization" of numerous
lingua francas in the capitals of the French-
speaking countries (Wolof in Dakar, Sango in
Bangui, Lingala in Kinshasa) leads to a radical
change in attitude in relation to the former
colonial language that has been maintained
as the official language and educational vector.
A language becomes a "vernacular" when it
becomes the first language of city children,
whatever their parents' origins. This language,
which becomes dominant and increasingly
complex, gradually acquires new functions in
daily life. The influence of French learned at
school is reflected in the appearance of "mixed"
idioms"Franlof" in Dakar, "Fransango" in
Bangui, "Kinya-French" in Rwanda and "Lin-
gala-French" in Kinshasathat are widely used
by young people and illustrate their accultur¬
ation and social status.
In rural areas the use ofFrench is still highly
regarded and French competes with the lan¬
guage that is tending to become the language
of urban, even national, integration for all
migrants.
This situation means that the prospects of
teaching in a single language, French, are
uncertain and that sooner or later problems
concerning« linguistic and educational policy
will arise in the countries concerned.
Caroline Juillard
Paris, France
HURA FOR ESPERANTO!
I wish to draw your attention to certain inac¬
curacies in the article entitled "Babel Revis¬
ited" by Peter Mühlhäusler in your February,
1994 issue. In the section of his article headed,
"The attractions of a single language", the
author makes two serious errors regarding
Esperanto.
Mr. Mühlhäusler puts Esperanto on the
same footing as abortive artificial-language
projects such as Volapuk. If he were better
informed, he would know that in 1994
Esperanto is alive and well with its own press
and literature, and that many persons use it
throughout the world for their professional
and personal relations.
Moreover, contrary to what Mr. Mühlhäusler
asserts, Esperanto has no intention of replacing
other languages. On the contrary, using Esperanto
as a transnational language is presently the best
way to protect the less widely used languages
against the ravages ofwidely used tongues such
as English. The author, though a linguist, seems
to ignore the fact that the working language ofthe
International Committee for Ethnic Liberties
(IKEL) is Esperanto and that an interesting mag¬
azine devoted exclusively to the defence of
minority cultures and languages is published in
Esperanto.
Jean-Claude Tiiumerelle
Warneton, Belgium
Volapuk, invented by a German cleric, Johann
Martin Schleyer, was first published in 1879. It
sought to be a synthesis of European mother
tongues, but the roots on which it was based
were so over-simplified that their origins were
virtually unrecognizable. The word Volapuk,
for instance, is based on two English words,
world and speak. Translated into Esperanto it
becomes mond-lingvo.
During the short-lived vogue for Volapuk at
the Paris Congress of 1889 it seemed momen¬
tarily that the problem of an international lan¬
guage had been solved. However, as many
Volapuk speakers realized, reforms were nec¬
essary, but these were systematically resisted by
Schleyer.
Esperanto appeared in 1887. Its inventor,
Dr. Louis Zamenhof, laid its foundations but left
its users to determine how the language would
develop, under the watchful eye of an academy.
Volapuk disappeared into oblivion.
Esperanto on the other hand is still used on
all five continents.
Lucien Bourgeois
President of the Esperanto
Federation of Northern France
Lille, France
I visited Lithuania in 1992. Thanks to my knowl¬
edge ofEsperanto I was welcomed into families
and was able to communicate with them. In
1993 1 spent some time in the Czech Republic.
Although I do not speak Czech, through
Esperanto I established contact with many
people and made new friends.
A. Legros
Bondy, France
Nearly all Esperantists are keen defenders of
their regional and national languages, and it is
because they want to defend their linguistic
and cultural heritage that they use a neutral
and supranational language, Esperanto, as their
lingua franca.
I am a Dutch speaker and active in the
movement to defend the sovereignty and sur¬
vival of the Dutch language within the Euro¬
pean Union, but for my numerous contacts
outside The Netherlands I use Esperanto
without encountering any problems or frus¬
trations. Nor does this prevent me from
speaking French, English or German when the
need arises.
Edward Symoens
Kalmthout, Belgium
The goal of any sensible Esperantist is to safe¬
guard and promote linguistic diversity.
Esperanto should simply be a linguistic lift that
can give people easy access to the different
storeys of the Tower of Babel.
Germain Pirlot _ ~
Ostend, Belgium * 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="80">
<![CDATA[
BOOKS OF THE WORLD by Raoul Silva-Cacérès
Here comes THE SUN
so
Although not many of those who watched
last February's Winter Olympics may have
been aware of it, the Olympic flame that
burned in Lillehammer (Norway) was a
legacy of an ancient solar cult.
The sun is an omnipresent symbol in
the history of civilization. It has been given
many names Helios, Ra, Shamash, Apollo,
Sûrya, Amaterasu are only a few and has
been deified since the dawn of time. The
fount of light and life, it came to symbolize
truth, the all-seeing eye of justice and
equality, and became associated with the
power to heal physical and mental ailments.
The illustrations ofsun-related objects in
The Sun: Eternal Flame of Creation, many
never before published, show how the sun
has been an endless source of inspiration
to the human imagination. They include
the chariot of the sun-god; the vampire
(destroyed by sunlight); sacred mir¬
rors; mountains that became solar
deities; the pyramids; various
animals (birds of prey, serpents,
lions and stags); the phoenix;
trees such as the cosmic fig-
tree, its roots upturned
towards the sky; gold; and fire.
Most religions, rites, social
functions, cultural events, fes¬
tivals and sports originate in
ancient solar cults, or can be asso¬
ciated with the "day star" through
ceremonies linked with agrarian and
fertility rites.
This book evokes solar cults all over the
world, focusing particularly on past cultures
and the cultures of indigenous peoples today.
An international team of twenty-four noted
scholars has written the texts which accom¬
pany a pictorial record ofoutstanding quality.
In a remarkably comprehensive intro¬
duction of some 130 pages, the book's com¬
piler and presenter, Madanjeet Singh art
historian, writer, painter and photographer
compares the different symbolic and artistic
representations of the sun, points to some
unexpected similarities between different
cultures, and outlines the central issues
underlying his research. "The comparison
which some scholars have made between
the Amerindian and Greco-Roman pan-
The Sun: Eternal Flame
of Creation
compiled and presented by Madanjeet Singh,
with a preface by Federico Mayor,
Director-General of Unesco,
UNESco/Thames & Hudson, London/Adams, New York,
1993.
This monumental 400-page volume with 550 colour
plates is being published simultaneously in six
languages, within the framework of the World Decade
for Cultural Development. It is the result of co-operation
between Unesco and seven of the world's largest
publishing houses (Thames & Hudson, London, and
Adams, New York, for the English edition; Bordas, Paris,
for the French; Plaza & Janes/Circulo de Lectores,
Barcelona, for the Spanish; Silvan, Milan, for the Italian;
Wasmuth, Tübingen, for the German; and Kodansha,
Tokyo, for the Japanese).
Price: 460 French francs
(or equivalent in other currencies)
theons," he writes, "shows how solar cul¬
tures and their mythologies in widely sepa¬
rated parts of the world seem to converge,
transcending both time and space, and man¬
ifest themselves continually in the global
totality of form and content. It is at the heart
of the controversy whether or not such sim¬
ilarities are coincidental or resulted from
interaction between cultures. Perhaps in this
inexplicable phenomenon lies the funda¬
mental character of the prehistoric myth-
making age and its cultural universality."
For the first time, here is a single work
which lists, discusses and draws compar¬
isons between symbolic and artistic repre¬
sentations of the sun from the earliest times
to the present day, both in works of art and
in the rituals of each of the major civiliza¬
tions. This thoroughly entertaining geo-
cultural travelogue takes the reader
from Mesopotamia to the Incas of
ancient Peru, via the medieval
French epic La chanson de
Roland.
Two examples may be
given. The chapter (by
French writer Jacques Lacar-
rière) devoted to represen¬
tations of the sun in popular
French culture is ofparticular
interest. Most of these repre¬
sentations originate in Celtic
folklore and an ancient animist
tradition which forms a symbiosis
between celestial phenomena and
human beings. This complicity is strongly
apparent in the popular legends of Brittany
]]>
</page>
<page number="81">
<![CDATA[
and in the torch festivals which take place on
the first Sunday in Lent in the Christian cal¬
endar. To revive the energy of the weakening
sun, flaming torches of straw were paraded
through village streets and nearby pathways
and orchards.
In the chapter dealing with the Aztecs of
ancient Mexico, Eduardo Matos Moctezuma
stresses the importance to this people oftheir
creation myth, the Leyenda de los Soles
(Legend of the Suns) . The Aztecs considered
themselves the chosen elite of the sun, and
according to this tradition, the history of
humanity was divided into four consecutive
eras or "Suns": "The Tiger Sun", "The Wind
Sun", "The Rain Sun" and "The Water Sun".
However, it was the fifth Sun, the "Sun of
Movement", which allowed humanity,
through the sacrifice of the gods, to become
integrated with the world:
The Sun is not moving!
How in truth shall we make people live?
Let the Sun gain strength through our
mediation,
Let us sacrifice ourselves, let us all die!
This demonstrates clearly the funda¬
mental role of sacrifice in Aztec religion and
society: man must offer up his life to the gods,
so that the sun may continue on its course and
cosmic harmony may be preserved.
In short, this book gives us a magnificent
lesson in comparative mythology. Consid
ered as a whole, this vast panorama reveals a
poetic vision of history and a record of the
hopes and frustrations of men and women
past and present. The story of the sun is the
story ofan eternal dream ofhumanity.
To complement this historical and cul¬
tural study of the world of imagery inspired
by the sun, UNESCO has decided to prepare
a second volume, devoted to solar energy
and the environment.
RAOUL SILVA-CACERES, of Chile, is a professor at
the university of the Sorbonne (Paris IV), where he
is in charge of doctoral studies in Latin American
literature. Among his published works are Elogio de
mi locura (1991; "In praise of my madness") and
L'arbre aux figures, Etude sur Julio Cortázar ("The
tree with faces, a study on Julio Cortázar").
81
]]>
</page>
<page number="82">
<![CDATA[
JAZZ
Tom Scott. Reed My Lips.
Scott (tenor sax), Eric
Gale (guitar), David
Witham (keyboards),
Larry Kimpel (bass), Ron
Aston (synth
drums/percussion), et al.
CD GRP 97592
On this Californian-
style techno-funk CD,
Scott gives a brilliant
demonstration of the
possibilities of electronic
music. "Every Day and
Every Minute" with vocals
by Carmen Twiley, and
"Saxapella" in which Scott
plays several saxophones
are especially interesting.
"G.B.U.", the only track
featuring an acoustic
piano, reminds us of the
atmosphere in some of the
Crusaders' recordings. This
is not intellectual music. It
is pleasant and well
performed, intended for
relaxation and
entertainment.
MUSIC FROM
AROUND THE
WORLD
The Slide Guitar. Bottles
Knives & Steel, vol. 2.
CD Columbia 472 1 92 1- 10.
In its "Roots n'Blues"
series Columbia continues
RECENT RECORDINGS
by Isabelle Leymarie
ïïnïï C(
to present the lesser known
sides of the blues. On this
CD are recordings made by
artists from the southern
United States in the 1920s
and 1930s. The
"bottleneck" style of
guitar-playing was
influenced by Hawaiian
music but has a strong
flavour of its own. This is
an opportunity to listen to
Salty Dog Sam and Tampa
Red and a number of
women performers
including the early Helen
Humes, and Nellie
Florence, who soon faded
from the limelight. These
blues from the early days
of recording tell of
incidents of daily life, the
problems of the
Depression and the joys
and frustrations of love.
They constitute a
wonderful chronicle of the
South.
CLASSICAL
Marcus Klinko with the
soloists and musicians of
the Orchestra of the
Paris-Bastille Opera
House. Debussy, Ravel,
Satie, Fauré and Ibert.
CD EMI Classics 7 54884 2.
Here are several pieces
from the early twentieth
century, the heyday of the
harp renaissance in
France. As insipid as this
instrument may sound in
inexpert hands, it has a
real presence here. All the
pieces are superb, notably
Ravel's flowing
Introduction and Allegro
for Harp, as light as if
suspended in mid-air,
Ibert's Entr'acte with its
Slavic tones, and Fauré's
romantic Berceuse Op. 16.
Satie's Deuxième
Gymnopédie, arranged for
flute and harp by Robin de
Smet, Ravel's Pavane pour
une infante défunte,
arranged for flute and harp
by Quinto Maganini and
Debussy's En bateau,
adapted for flute and harp
by Susanna Mildonian,
thoroughly deserve their
place in this harp
anthology.
Gil Shaham, Goran
Söllscher. Paganini for Two.
CD Deutsche
Grammophon 437 837-2
Some delightful works
by Paganini, especially the
Romance from the Grand
Sonata and the Cantabile,
performed on violin and
guitar, both instruments
that the maestro himself
played brilliantly. In the
Allegro vivace a movimento
perpetuo, Gil Shaham
demonstrates a blend of
dazzling technical
virtuosity and profound
sensitivity, in a piece in
which the guitar is limited
to a supporting role. In the
movements of the more
measured Sonata
concertata, however, the
two instruments join with
obvious relish in a dialogue
on equal terms.
81
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, pages 3, 37: © Charles Lenars, Paris. Page 2: Jean-Luc Mabit/Le Monde de l'An © Suleiman Keita, Gorée. Page 4: Sophie
Bassouls © Sygma, Paris. Pages 8, 9, 10, II, 12, 1 3: © G. Darley-Doran, London. Page 1 4: Popperfoto, London © Cosmos,
Paris. Page 1 5: © Hulton Deutsch, London. Page 1 6: Doug Armand © Fotogram-Stone, Paris. Page 1 9: © Pavel Lounguine,
Paris. Pages 20, 2 1 : © Arte, Paris. Pages 22, 23: © Ryo Ogawa, Kyoto. Page 24: © Kusni Sulang, Paris. Page 25: Wang Miao
© ANA, Paris. Pages 26, 27, 28, 29: © Paulius Normantas, Hungary. Page 30: A. de Andrade © ANA, Paris. Page 3 1 (left):
X. Richer © Hoa Qui. Paris. Page 3 1 (right): R Renault © Hoa Qui, Paris. Page 32 (above): D. Dorval © Explorer, Paris.
Page 32 (below): G. Boutin © Hoa Qui, Paris. Pages 33, 34, 35: © G. Azenstarck, Paris. Page 36: A. Bradshaw© Visions/
Cosmos, Paris. Pages 38, 4 1 , 66, 67: © Cahiers du Cinéma, Paris. Pages 39, 40: © Aleksandar Petrovic, Paris. Page 42: Le
Diascorn © Rapho, Paris. Page 43: Louis Goldman © Rapho, Paris. Page 44: Castelnuovo © Sipa Press, Paris. Page 45: ©Jean-
Charles Pigeau, Paris. Page 47: Carlos Diaz Corono © Jean-Charles Pigeau, Leonardo da Vinci scholarship-Ministry of For¬
eign Affairs, Paris. Page 48: © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris. Page 50: © Léonard de Selva-Tapabor, CCIP. Paris. Page 5 1 (above):
Raghubir Singh ©ANA, Paris. Pages 5 1 (below), 52: © Musée de l'Homme, Paris. Pages 53, 56: Sophie de Wilde ©Jacana,
Paris. Page 54: Pierre Laboute© Jacana. Paris. Page 55: Norbert Wu ©Jacana, Paris. Page 57: Alby Ziebell ©Jacana, Paris.
Page 58 (above): C. et M. Morton ©Jacana, Paris. Page 58 (below): © Groupe Acial, Paris. Page 59 (above): Renaudeau
© Hoa Qui, Paris. Page 59 (below): James King Holmes/ SPL© Cosmos, Paris. Page 60: © Fotogram-Stone, Paris. Page 62:
© Fabian. Page 68: © Eiji Hattori, Paris. Page 69: Huteau © ANA, Paris. Pages 70, 72, 73 (below): Michelangelo Durazzo
© ANA, Paris. Page 7 1 : J. Oster © Musée de l'Homme, Paris. Pages 73 (above), 8 1 : All rights reserved. Page 75: Fritz Eschen
©Archiv für Kunst u. Geschichte, Berlin. Page 78: © Northeast International Magnet School of Montclair, New Jersey.
The UNESCO
:ourier
47th YEAR
Published monthly in 32 languages and in Braille by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31, rue François ßonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Maikin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda Et Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servar.
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant:
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Serpil Gogen (Ankara)
Urdu: Wall Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de
Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohameo Salan El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
I year: 21 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be sup¬
plied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily rep¬
resent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco
Courier. Photo captions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff. The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offi¬
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche)
by: ( I ) UNESCO, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Micro¬
films (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48 1 00 USA; (3) N.C.R. Microcard
Edition. Indian Head Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York. U.S.A.; (4)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 4469 1 . U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Printed in Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL: CI -JUILLET/AOÛT 1994.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE Nn 71842 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: IMPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL, 2. rue Christophe-Plantin
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 7/8-I994-OPI-94-528A
This issue comprises 84 pages and two 4-page inserts between
pages 10-11 / 74-75 and 42-43.
]]>
</page>
<page number="83">
<![CDATA[
la mise en lumière du Louvre
par
Electricité de France
]]>
</page>
<page number="84">
<![CDATA[
KCMOlOCt
RESOURCEFUL GEN
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription;
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine
published in 32 languages and read by hundreds of thousands of
people in 110 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with UNESCO's mission of furthering "universal respect
for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms.. .without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
EACH MONTH, ESSENTIAL READING FOR AN UNDERSTANDING OF THE PROBLEMS
OF TODAY AND TOMORROW
INTERVIEW WITl
AMTOMI TAPIES
»EFEATI« DECIBELS
Û i
BUTRIKTI
REDISCOVERED
PIC OF UNIVERSAL
ACTIVITIES
WHAT IS MODERN?... RHYTHM. GESTURE ANB THE SACREB... TINE TO BISARN... THE STORY OF NUMBERS...
NORTH-SOUTH DEBATE: THE MEANING OF PROGRESS... DESERTS... WORLDS WITHIN WORDS... HUNAN RICH'
THE UNFINISHED TASK... NOBERN MANAGEMENT ANB LOCAL TRADITIONS... A NEW LOOK AT THE HISTORY 0
CONNUNISH... BIOTECHNOLOGY: THE RESOURCEFUL GENE... SURPRISING STRANGERS...
FRANCOIS HITTERRANB... JORGE ANABO... RICHARB ATTENBOROUCH... JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIÈRE... JEA
LACOUTURE... FEBERICO NAYOR... NAGUIB HAHFOUZ... SEHBENE OUSHANE... ANBREI VOZNESENSKY...
FREDERIC ROSSIF... HINNERK BRNHNS... CAMILO JOSÉ CELA... VACLAV HAVEL... SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV...
ERNESTO SABATO... GRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND... CLAUDE LÉVI-STRAUSS... LEOPOLDO ZEA... PAULO FREIRÉ...
DANIEL J. BOORSTIN... FRANCOIS JACOB... NANU BIBANGO... FAROUK HOSNY... SABRUBBIN AGA KHAN...
JORGE LAVELLI... LÉON SCHWARTZENBERG... TAHAR BEN JELLOUN... GABRIEL GARCIA MAROUEZ.., JACOUES-
YVES COUSTEAU... MELINA HERCOURI... CARLOS FUENTES... JOSEPH KI-ZERBO... VANBANA SHIVA... WILLIAM
STYRON... OSCAR NIENEYER... NIKIS THEOBORAKIS... ATAHUALPA YUPANOUI... HERVÉ BOURGES... ABBEL
RAHNAN EL BACHA... SUSANA RINALDI... HUBERT REEVES... JOSÉ CARRERAS... A LETTER FROH FREUD TO
EINSTEIN... LUC FERRY... CHARLES MALAMOUD... UMBERTO ECO... OLIVER STONE... ANDRE BRINK... JANES D.
WATSON... ANOS OZ... MICHEL SERRES... THÉOBORE NONOB... YVES COPPENS... EBOUARB J. NAUNICH...
JEAN MALAURIE.,. TRINH XUAN THUAN... ANTONI TAPIES... JOSÉ BONOSO...
THEHE OF THE NEXT ISSUE (SEPTEHBER 1004):
ETHICS AND GENETICS
ALSO FEATURING AN INTERVIEW WITH
NOËLLE LENOIR
PRESIBENT OF UNESCO'S INTERNATIONAL BIOETHICS COMMITTEE
]]>
</page>
</document>
