<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="098363eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
MYUNOWHUN CHUI
THE MONASTERY
RED ALERT FOR THEE/
GREEN BELT
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
Discs from the
"Floresta" series
(1991-1992)
Mixed media on wood, diameter 50 cm,
by Virginia Ryan Izzo
These painted discs form part of
a series entitled "Floresta". In
1 993 there were 36 of them.
The series was executed in
Belgrade and is intended as an
offering for the "dispossessed
and threatened". It is also the
"visual diary" of a widely-
travelled Australian-Italian
artist, who writes: "I hope the
discs reflect my fascination for,
and debt to, the Australia of the
Aborigines, Greco-Roman
Alexandria and Pharaonic
Upper Egypt, South America
and the Mediterranean, for
although I grew up in Australia, I
have spent significant time-
spans living in vastly different
cultures and civilizations."
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
NOVEMBER 1994
Cover: a group of Moken, a
nomadic sea-faring people who
live in the IVlergui archipelago,
Myanmar (formerly Burma).
Back cover: Tuareg of the Air
mountains of the southern Sahara
(Niger).
UNSETTLING
FREEDOM:
NOMADISM TODAY
5 Interview with Myung-Whun Chung
36 HERITAGE
The monastery of Alcobaça
par José Augusto Seabra
41 GREENWATCH
Red alert for the earth's green belt
by France Bequette
1 UNESCO IN ACTION
I GLOBAL VIEW
Literacy: How to reach the excluded
44 ANNIVERSARY
Rabelais: the ribald scholar
by Alain Frontier
I ARCHIVES
Marie Curie
The spirit of adventure
I LISTENING
Seeking the inner voice
Catherine Françaix talks to
Isabelle Leymarie
) LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Nomads and the modern state
An unsettling freedom
by André Bourgeot
Tuareg: silent lives
photos by Frances Dal Chele
Twixt land and sea
The myth of the Moken
by Jacques Ivanoff
The return of the Bedouin
by Riccardo Boceo and Ronald Jaubert
¡1 On the road
The European Odyssey of the Gypsies
by Patrick Williams
Forest rovers of the Amazon
by Howard Reid
The vanishing African herdsman
by John Galaty
Further reading on nomads
Consultant: André Bourgeot
35
Commentary by Federico Mayor
Th& UNESCO
COURIER
47th year
Published monthly in 30
languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding anda truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, lb NOVEMBER 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE. UNESCO
(PÜRIER
47th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
3 1 , rue François Bonvin. 750 1 S Paris. France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tei. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tei. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tei. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68 45.65
I year: 21 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of UNESCO
Individual articles and photographs no: copyrighted may be reprinted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copynght photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompa¬
nied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo cap¬
tions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Couner is produced
in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (I) Unesco. 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris: (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48100 U.SA: (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc..
1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York. U.SA; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road. Wooster. Ohio 4469 1 . U.SA
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Printed m Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL: CI - NOVEMBRE 1994
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de IUnesco.
Impression: IMPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL, 2. rue Christophe-Plantin
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN 004 1 -5278 Nc 1 1 - 1 994-OPI-94-53 1 A
onth by month
Nomads are misfits in the modern world. The state likes to see
them settled in one place, to "integrate" them and keep tabs on
them. The sedentary population is suspicious of them because it does
not understand their way of life. They have no place in a narrowminded
conception of modern civilization which only accepts what can be
pinned down, predicted and programmed.
They live on the outer edge of the economic system, usu¬
ally on unproductive land, practising a frugal and uncertain way of
life. They are shy of frontiers and avoid controls and supervision.
Everything about them is a challenge to modern society. They take
what it rejects and esteem values and codes it has abandoned. They
melt away into vast landscapesdeserts, forests, lakes, steppes
which the sedentary may regard as hostile but which for them mean
life, beauty, poetry and freedom.
This issue of the Courier records some of the things that
nomads have to tell us. In a more general way it may also stimulate
reflection about difference and the difficulty of being different today,
about the spread of intolerance, about the fears and anxieties that
lead people to reject what is at variance with themselves.
In any case, what sort of world would it be if everyone con¬
formed to the same pattern? In such a world we should not only die
of boredom, but of inability to adapt, to change, to renew ourselves
to meet life's unending challenges. For societies, as for living organ¬
isms, diversity is a necessary condition of survival. As the nomads,
with their thousands of years of history, remind us.
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 10-11 and 42-43. BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
N T E R V I E W
, ¡E MYUNG-WHUN
CHUNG
talks to
Claude Glayman
An immense ovation broke out at the Bastille Opera House in Paris on
19 September 1994 when the curtain went down at the end of the first
performance there of Verdi's Simon Boccanegra, conducted by Myung-
Whun Chung. The audience was giving a memorable salute to the last
work conducted by the young Korean conductor (except for a piece by
Olivier Messiaen, Concert à quatre, dedicated to Mr. Chung and conducted
by him on 26 September) as musical director of the Bastille Opera.
Myung-Whun Chung succeeded Daniel Barenboim as musical director
in 1989 and conducted the first opera to be performed there, Berlioz's
Les Troyens. In 1994, however, the situation at the Bastille Opera
changed when the decision was taken to appoint a director bearing
overall responsibility. Hugues Gall, manager of the Grand Theatre in
Geneva (Switzerland), has been appointed to this post to take effect from
August 1995.
To outside observers, a conflict seemed inevitable, and in March 1994
discussions began between the Opera management and Chung to take
led to the enforced departure of the Korean conductor.
Myung-Whun Chung was born in
Korea in 1951. He is reserved and seems
to have little time to spare for any¬
thing but music and the constant effort
to achieve perfection in it. Art is not
Myung-Whun Chung's only interest,
however:
"I was born a few months after the
outbreak of the Korean war. My par¬
ents my mother was born in North
Korea had had a pretty good idea of
what was going to happen. Even today,
forty years after the tragedy, I am still
strongly in favour of the reunification
of my country, although I feel that it will
be a longer and more difficult process
than the reunification of Germany.
"I ask myself, without being able
to answer, why there should be this
division and this antagonism between
members of the same people, who share
the same civilization, history and lan¬
guage. Politics is behind it all and the
effects of political mistakes last for a
very long time."
Chung was attracted to music at a
very early age, as a result of personal
inclination and family influence he
had strong backing from his parents,
and two older sisters became famous
instrumentalists. He trained simulta¬
neously as a pianist and a conductor.
After a first visit to the United States in
1968, he went to Moscow to take part
in the prestigious Tchaikovsky com¬
petition for pianists.
"It's not hard to imagine what this
competition meant to the authorities at
that time, and how important it was
for them that a Russian should win
the First Prize. This way-out patrio¬
tism, at variance with the universal,
cosmopolitan nature of music, came
as a shock."
How do you explain yourpassion for
European music?
I was immersed in classical music even
before I was born. For me it was a natural
language before it became a profession (in
addition to the piano I have also played
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
DISCOGRAPHY
Camille Saint-Saens: Samson et Dalila,
Placido Domingo, Waltraud Meier, Alain
Fondar, Samuel Ramey and others, Choir and
Orchestra of the Bastille Opera, conducted .
by Myung-Whun Chung.
lsetof2CDsEMI.
Camille Saint-Saens: Third Symphony with
Organ, and Olivier Messiaen: Ascension, the
Bastille Opera Orchestra conducted by
Myung-Whun Chung.
1 CD Deutsche Grammophon.
Olivier Messiaen: Turangalîla-Symphonie,
Yvonne Loriod (piano), Jeanne Loriod
(Ondes Martenot), the Bastille Opera
Orchestra conducted by Myung-Whun
Chung. 1 CD Deutsche Grammophon.
Olivier Messiaen: Eclairs sur l'au-delà, the
Bastille Opera Orchestra conducted by
Myung-Whun Chung,
1 CD Deutsche Grammophon.
Georges Bizet: Suite de Carmen, Suites n" 1
and 2 ofthe Arlésienne, Petite suite d'orchestre
(Jeux d'enfants), the Bastille Opera Orchestra
conducted by Myung-Whun Chung, 1 CD
Deutsche Grammophon.
Dimitri Shostakovitch: Lady Macbeth of
Mtzensk, Maria Ewing and others, the
Bastille Opera Orchestra conducted by
Myung-Whun Chung, 1 set of 2 CDs
Deutsche Grammophon (forthcoming).
Anton Dvorak: Trios n" 1 op. 21 and n° 3 op
65, The Chung Trio, Kyung Wha Chung
(violin), Myung Wha Chung ('cello), Myung-
Whun Chung (piano), 1 CD Decca.
Ludwig van Beethoven: Trios n°'4 and 7, The
Chung Trio, Kyung Wha Chung (violin),
Myung Wha Chung ('cello), Myung-Whun
Chung (piano), ICD EMI.
Rimsky-Korsakov: Scheherazade and
Stravinsky: The Firebird, the Bastille Opera
Orchestra conducted by Myung-Whun
Chung, ICD Deutsche Grammophon.
Serge Prokofiev: Romeo andJuliet (extracts),
Amsterdam Concertgebouw conducted by
Myung-Whun Chung, ICD Deutsche
Grammophon.
In preparation for Deutsche Grammophon:
Verdi's Otello, Berlioz's Symphonie
fantastique and Dutilleux's Métaboles,
Berlioz's Overtures and Airs d'Opéras
français with the soprano K. Battle.
The Chung trio: Myung-Whun Chung (piano) with
his two sisters, violinist Kyung-Wha (left) and
cellist Myung-Wha (right).
the violin and the kettledrums). Clas¬
sical music is truly universal. It is under¬
stood and shared by an infinitely greater
number of people than any form of tra¬
ditional music. For me traditional music
is, by and large, like the stalest kind of
Western folklore. It is a question of evo¬
lution. If you compare the two styles of
music over a sufficiently long period,
five centuries, say, you can reasonably
put forward the case that traditional
music has hardly changed.
So what do you think ofthe branch of
classical music that is usually described
as "contemporary"?
Technically difficult music has existed
since the baroque and Johann Sebastian
Bach. Modern experimental music is an
extremely advanced art-form which one
ought to keep up with and if possible
perform. But to make a contribution to
it requires an enormous amount of time.
It is in the forefront of a rapidly changing
field. It is a new dimension whose con¬
tours are not always clear to the com¬
posers themselves. Electronic music is
only one aspect of it. But the modular
hall at the Bastille Opera, for example,
should be useful for further exploration
of this type of music, which could pave
the way to the opera of the future.
Tell us something aboutyour meeting
with Olivier Messiaen.
I met him for the first time at Sar-
rebriick where I was conducting a pro¬
gramme of his music. He was a man of
very great talent and I was delighted that
he had come. Later I recorded some of
his music and we agreed to stage his
Saint-François d'Assise at the Bastille,
directed by Peter Sellars. That was in
1992, and alas, Messiaen died later in the
year.
What wereyour working methods at
the Bastille Opera?
When I was approached about the
post, I hesitated at first, knowing full
well that I would be involved in a great
deal of administrative work that would
prevent me from devoting all my time to
music. Everyone advised me against it,
but I finally accepted because I felt that
there was something to be constructed
there.
At the Opera, the musicians have
always felt that they were given short
shrift and of course that they were up
against the bureaucracy. My position
was simple. The purpose of the Opera as
a whole and of everybody who is
involved in it, should be to make it easier
for the musicians to do their job and to
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Myung-Whun Chung (left) after
conducting the first performance of
Concert à Quatre, a posthumous work by
the French composer Olivier Messiaen, at
the Bastille Opera in Paris on 26
September 1994. The work was performed
by the Orchestra and Choir of the Paris
Opera with pianist Yvonne Loriod (middle),
the composer's widow, and cellist Mstislav
Rostropovich (right).
help them fulfil themselves. The Bastille
Opera orchestra is, in my opinion, the
best in France, and I would like to see it
make more of an impact internationally.
Haveyou met many great conductors
during your career?
Yes, I had the honour to do two or
three days' work with Herbert von
Karajan, for example. But my most
important encounter was with Carlo
Maria Giulini, whose assistant I became
in Los Angeles in 1978 after I had fin¬
ished my studies. Paradoxically, he taught
me above all not to place art above
human qualities. A conductor should
strike the right balance between the pro¬
fessional approach and an ethical way
of life. It is important that profession¬
alism should not prevail over human
considerations. This is vital in an age
when the notion of professionalism has
become sacrosanct.
Giulini also strengthened my Chris¬
tian faith. My parents were Christian, but
I was not when I was very young. I came
to Christianity with difficulty, after much
questioning. Giulini was an example for
me. He is a man who has kept his purity
in a world of indifference.
I have also had the honour of being
received in private audience by His Holi¬
ness PopeJohn Paul II, whose message to
me was very clear: "You must do some¬
thing for humanity. You must take a
stand against drugs, against pollution,
against conflict and in favour of peace
and concord between people. That is
your mission."
He also said: "Even if there are all
kinds of talent, there is no fundamental
difference between people. Talent, of
whatever kind, is no exception to this
principle." Politics cannot solve all the
problems that beset the world, and I feel
that I and many others should do
what we can in a disinterested fashion. I
have, incidentally, been appointed a
United Nations goodwill ambassador.
I came to the same conclusion at the
Bastille Opera. Nothing is possible
without hard work and patience. Ready-
made solutions do not exist. But every¬
thing always has to be done on the spur
of the moment. We do not give ourselves
enough time to think carefully about
what we do, and personally I feel very
unhappy about all this haste. We achieve
far more if we are more tolerant and in
less of a hurry.
Constantly changing the people at the
top of institutions musical and other¬
wise will not lead to tangible and lasting
results. We must build with greater mod¬
esty and perseverance. Music and life are
not two separate compartments.
CLAUDE GLAYMAN
is a French journalist and music critic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
AN UNSETTLING FREEDOM
omads and the
modern state
by André Bourgeot
Nomadism is one of
the most balanced
relationships mankind
has made with
nature. But nomads
are misfits in the
modern state and
today their living
space and their
identity are under
growing threat.
8
j Nomadic societies have played an impor-
I tant part in history and have made an
undeniable contribution to the development of
different techniques and ways of using land.
Although their economic, political and religious
role is beyond doubt, for generation after gen¬
eration nomads have been looked down upon,
and regarded predominantly as rapacious
vagabonds and as parasites upon the body of
society.
In our own times, most of these societies
are suffering from the decline of their tradi¬
tional structures and deepening poverty. In these
circumstances, they become dependent on inter¬
national aid as and when they adopt a sedentary
way of life in urban environments.
Nomads are, however, to a considerable
extent self-sufficient in food production and
still have a contribution to make to countries'
economic balance. Pastoral nomadism, in par¬
ticular, remains the surest safeguard against
environmental degradation and desertification.
Diversified societies
Nomad societies in fact practise a very wide
range of productive activities in a great many dif¬
ferent environments. The best known of these
activities, which may thus be taken as the main
example, are those of nomad herders. Including
part-time pastoralists who also engage in agri¬
culture and stock-rearing, they number some
thirty million worldwide. Their chief occupation
is tending flocks and herds of domesticated her¬
bivores, and the territories over which they range
are ones where naturally-occurring resources
enable an annual cycle of production to be main¬
tained.
In nomadic as distinct from sedentary com¬
munities, man's relationship with nature is con¬
ducted via his livestock, which are both his
means of production and his consumer goods.
The nomadic community is concerned to pre¬
serve and regenerate the environment, and there¬
fore manages its territory in a rational manner.
Various other forms of nomadism are repre¬
sented by "travellers" (European Gypsies), dis¬
tinguishable by their attitude towards the dead
and towards language; the Moken fisher-gatherers
of Myanmar and the south-west coast of Thai¬
land, recognizable by the indentations in the
poop and prow of their boats and by the place of
the yam in their culture; the aborigène hunter-
gatherers of the Kimberleys (Australia), whose
identity is expressed in the symbiosis between the
sanctuary, the individual and the supernatural
being; or the Pygmy hunter-gatherers, scattered
over eight countries, who are ignorant of agri-
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
culture and metalworking and whose identity is
symbolized by the (mainly male) activity of
hunting with nets and the (mainly female)
activity of gathering.
Diverse as they are, all these communities
have certain common features, a combination of
mobility and flexibility that has enabled them to
face up both to domination by the societies
with which they are in permanent contact and to
the effects of colonial expansion, which repre¬
sented a crucial point in their history.
The fact is that colonial rule interfered with,
or in some cases obliterated, the internal
dynamics of these communities, as a result of the
introduction or expansion of new economic
activities, changes in the pattern of land owner¬
ship, the disruption of the established power
structure, the re-drawing of frontiers and
boundaries, and so on. The crisis in nomad
society that began then has gathered speed in the
context of the post-colonial states.
A comparison of the history of herding
The Tsaatan (in Mongolian,
"those who have reindeer") live
in northern Mongolia, where
they continue a tradition of
reindeer breeding that goes
back as far as the Bronze Age.
Above, in spring they move
down the wooded mountain
slopes to the place where the
reindeer give birth. The Tsaatan
live in yurts, tents similar to
the tepees of North American
Indians. Below right, striking
camp.
societies with that of other nomadic societies
shows that the former devised strategies of con¬
quest, with the aid of the camel in the case of the
Bedouin (Moors and Tuaregs) and with that of
the horse in the case of the Fulani and the Mon¬
gols; conversely, the nomadic societies of itin¬
erant merchants or of hunters and gatherers
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
IMomadic goat-breeders in the
Rif mountains, northern
Morocco.
A "Copper Eskimo"
photographed in 1916. Copper
Eskimos lived in the Northwest
Territories of Canada and made
weapons from the native copper
they found on the shores. Today
the Eskimos (or Inuit) only
follow their ancestors' nomadic
hunting and fishing way of life
in summer.
were in most instances reduced to a position of
subordination to societies of agriculturalists.
The fate of most of these communities was,
however, to be subjected to economic and polit¬
ical marginalization (e.g. the herders of the
Sahel) or to be parked in reservations or exter¬
minated (Amerindians, South African Bushmen,
Gypsies in Nazi-dominated Europe), or else to
undergo integration or indeed assimilation, a
policy inspired by an ideology aiming to achieve
cultural and economic uniformity.
Integration is imposed on nomads by
herding them together around centres of eco¬
nomic activity (as happened to the Moken
during World War II), by radically altering their
10
territorial organization with the aim of setting up
community stations and villages (the case of
the Australian Aborigènes), and by repressive
policies of expulsion, confiscation of flocks and
herds, and the destruction of crops grown on
state land.
The main way in which state policy affects
nomadic herders' way of life is via the intro¬
duction of technical innovations. Thus, the effect
on the environment of the sinking of public
wells overgrazing leading to erosion through
the disappearance of vegetation is to upset the
balance of the ecosystem and to disrupt the
management of grazing land and the control
exercised over it by the community, in the
absence of which such well-drilling operations
turn the adjacent area into a desert.
In the minoritynumerically or
politically?
As regards animal husbandry, the main innova¬
tions are in the field of veterinary medicine,
measures to combat livestock epidemics in par¬
ticular. These measures encourage livestock
growth but in so doing upset the balance
between the carrying capacity of the grazing
land, which itself varies in accordance with cli¬
matic factors, and the increasing size of flocks
and herds.
Lastly, the development of food or cash
crops such as rice and cotton takes up more
and more land to the detriment of nomad com¬
munities.
Except in those countries like Mauritania,
Djibouti or Somalia whose leaders themselves
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Whoever would think greatly must
stray greatly.
Martin Heidegger
German philosopher (1889-1976)
come from a nomad background, nomads find
themselves in one or other of the following
minority situations:
a) groups that move about on the frontiers of
one country but are of the same nationality,
religion and language as the populations of a
neighbouring country; such groups form a
restricted minority within a given national ter¬
ritory, e.g. the Algerian Tuareg of Tamcsna, in
Niger;
b) groups isolated within a given country
and surrounded by population groups of the
demographic majority, e.g. certain Arabic-
speaking groups in Niger and Mali;
c) groups scattered over the whole of a
country's territory the commonest case;
d) groups belonging to one and the same
cultural community spread across several nation-
states, e.g. Fulani, Toubou, Moorish, Arab and
Tuareg nomad herders.
When applied to these groups, the term
"minority" docs not necessarily imply that they
are fewer in number; it refers to a politically
dependent situation. Such minorities fall into
two categories, which may be labelled respec¬
tively:
a) the minority "in itself", consisting of
groups of nomads who are distinguished from
the rest of the population by ethnic, linguistic
and religious characteristics and by their cultural
links; the overall population of these groups is
small and they do not occupy a dominant polit¬
ical position;
b) the minority "for itself", i.e. one that has
woken up to its situation and is resolved to pre¬
serve its way of life and patterns of behaviour;
this state of awareness may lead to the group
voicing demands relating to its identity that arc
in effect political demands.
Frontiers and limits
The societies in which nomadic herders live are
mostly homogeneous cultural communities with
a territory scattered over several nation-states.
The intensive stock-rearing that they practise
cannot be contained within artificial, often arbi¬
trarily drawn frontiers; a cross-border territory
is a necessity for the purposes of a yearly pro¬
duction cycle the most striking feature of which
is transhumance, the seasonal migration of live¬
stock to different feeding grounds.
The strict delimitation of national frontiers
has in many cases had deleterious effects on the
structure of these societies. National sover¬
eignty, surveillance, and the principle of the
inviolability of frontiers, all matters of vital con¬
cern to the state, represent real difficulties for
nomadic herders and for some fishing commu¬
nities; they arc, however, less of a problem for
Pygmy hunter-gatherers since, owing to the
nature of their activities, the diversity of the
natural resources and the type of environment,
Pygmies do not need large swathes of territory.
A convention for nomads
The major international human rights conven¬
tions fail to take account of the particular case of
transnational minorities. Since these minorities
often have no wish to belong to any one nation,
they find themselves relegated, in terms of inter¬
national law, to a political and legal limbo.
The time has perhaps come to look into the
possibility of special conventions relating to
nomadism that would encourage the easing of
border-control measures, ensure a transnational
territorial basis for each community, and protect
its cultural homogeneity. These conventions
should lead on to the drafting of a charter on
transhumance, for which the requisites would be,
firstly, the simultaneous establishment in the coun¬
tries concerned of a body of land law governing
access to resources and, secondly, the recognition
of a system of landed property that at last responds
to the interests of nomadic herders.
The last Aka pygmy nomads
live deep In the equatorial
forest of central Africa, on the
border of the Central African
Republic and the Congo.
Hunters and gatherers, they live
In huts made of leaves and
branches (above).
ANDRE BOURGEOT,
a French anthropologist, is a
specialist In pastoral societies,
especially that of the Tuaregs,
with whom he lived for several
years. A researcher at his
country's National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS), he
is co-leader with Henri Guillaume
of a research team on "States
and Nomad Societies" (CNRS
and ORSTOM, the French
Institute of Scientific Research
for Development in
Co-operation).
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
t u a r e g
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
silent lives
"What has happened to
the Tuareg, the legendary
lords of the desert? How
have they adapted to
sedentary life? I wanted
to find out with my own
eyesin other words
with my cameraabout
the life they are living
today. During two visits,
in 1991 and 1993, 1 was
given a warm welcome by
sedentary Tuareg families
in the Hoggar (Algerian
Sahara). I shared their
daily lives. I saw the
meagre sustenance they
get from their vegetable
gardens and their goats,
and from the money
earned by the menfolk as
camel-drivers or guides
for tourists (when there
are any). My photos are
glimpses of the lives of
people who cling proudly
to their traditional way of
life."
Frances Dal Chele
Photographer and ethnologist
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Although they know
how to grow crops,
the Moken prefer to
live on the sea
through fidelity to
their foundation myth,
the story of Gaman
and Sibian.
THE MYTH OF THE MOKEN
wixt land and sea by Jacques ivanoff
14
I The Moken are a nomadic seafaring folk
I who, living to all appearances on the
fringes of human society, ply the waters of the
Mergui archipelago, off the Tenasserim coast
in the Bay of Bengal. No documentary evidence
subsists from the period before British colo¬
nial expansion into this region to throw light on
the mysterious past of these people who live
afloat on extraordinary craft, use the resources
of their environment in a curious way, and avoid
all contact with the outside world.
Employing so-called "archaic" technology
the harpoon and the adze being their main imple¬
ments and clad only in skimpy loin-cloths, the
Moken practise a purely symbolic type of agri¬
culture and refuse technical innovation in any
shape or form, including the use of more efficient
gear such as fish traps and nets that could increase
their catches; they have made a deliberate choice
to go on using only pointed or pronged harpoons.
A mistaken explanation was long put upon
this choice by observers who saw the Moken
only during the dry season and sent back a gar¬
bled account of their constant comings and
goings, their apparent lack of any system of
beliefs, and what seemed on the surface to be the
looseness of the nomadic structure, as evidenced
by the scattered and shifting dispositions of the
fishing fleets.
In fact, when the rains come the Moken go
ashore on the inhabited islands of the archi¬
pelago, where they grow rice, sorghum and
millet. They do not, however, eat the crops they
harvest. They use a few handfuls of rice for
ritual purposes, in particular at the festival of the
"Post of the Spirits", which occurs during the
fifth lunar month and represents a recapitulation
of the whole pre-Islamic and proto-Malay
period of Malay history. Since, moreover, the
only agricultural produce they do consume is
obtained by way of trade, they are thus demon¬
strating that, while they are familiar with agri¬
cultural practices, they at the same time reject
them.
During the rainy season, Moken society
again becomes strongly bonded, and the various
pieces of the nomadic jigsaw puzzle, with its dif¬
ferent levels of social integration by boat, fleet
and subgroup come together. This seasonal
transition to a sedentary way of life awakens
powerful unifying forces of which an upsurge of
religious activity is the most visible expression.
This alternation between the rainy season
and the dry season, between coming together
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Some 150 Moken boats are
still sailing today (above).
Poised for the kill: a Moken
fisherman hunts turtle. Living
between land and sea like the
Moken, turtles are prized as a
delicacy.
and dispersing, between a nomadic and a seden¬
tary mode of life, between fishing and farming
and between food-gathering and a self-imposed
food shortage the price the community pays
for infringing its own rule of keeping on the
move is not by any means determined by the
forces of nature alone: a logical explanation is to
be found in the mythical account of the Moken's
origins.
Gaman and Sibian
The key to the symbolic link between man, sea
and boat is provided by the epic of Gaman,
which sets forth the cultural motivations that
have enabled the Moken to keep their identity
intact throughout the changing fortunes of their
history, withstanding, one after another, Islam,
the agricultural way of life, missionaries, colo¬
nization, and the pressures exerted by expan¬
sionist nation-states that wanted to bring them
under their control and acculturatc them.
Gaman, a Muslim Malay, was the consort of
Queen Sibian but was enamoured of his young
sister-in-law Kèn and became her lover. By this
act Kèn transgressed society's taboo against
"mounting", i.e. taking the place of, one's elder.
Outraged, Queen Sibian decreed that thereafter
it would be forbidden to dwell on land, a ban
symbolized by her ordering Kèn to be cast into
the sea (lemo Kèn the "immersion of Kèn")
and that ever thereafter boats must be dugouts
hewn from a single balk of timber, with inden¬
tations fore and aft ("a mouth that eats and a rear
that defecates"), symbolizing the unending cycle
of ingestion, digestion and evacuation.
Thus it came about that the Moken were
QUEEN SIBIAN'S
DECREE
"Gaman, a Muslim Malay, was
the consort of Queen Sibian
but was enamoured of his
young sister-in-law, Kèn, and
became her lover. By this act,
Kèn transgressed society's
taboo against 'mounting', i.e.
taking the place of, one's
elder. Outraged, Queen Sibian
decreed that thereafter it
would be forbidden to dwell
on land 	"
condemned to a life at sea, cut off from their ter¬
restrial roots and from the royal bounty. The
golden age was over. Sibian's sentence was to
weigh heavily upon the subsequent fate of the
Moken and to provide the members of the new,
nomadic community with a common criterion
of identity: a Moken is anyone who accepts that
name and builds his boats in accordance with
Sibian's precepts.
This drama of forbidden love brings us to the
heart of the factors that determine the Moken's
sense of identity. By her immersion in the sea,
Kèn came to symbolize a community casting off
its terrestrial moorings, as embodied by Sibian.
This is why the Moken cannot return to terra
firma, which nonetheless remains symbolically
present in the community in the form of yams
and other traditional foods.
What's in a name?
The mythical account of the origins of the
Moken yields, upon analysis, an explanation of
certain features specific to them, such as their
self-imposed poverty and the fact that they do
not amass property, their rejection of technical
innovations and the fact that they do not con¬
sume their own agricultural produce, charac¬
teristics that, among these "sedentary nomads",
take on an ideological aspect rooted in the myth
itself: the Moken derive their nomad identity
from the judgment that sentenced them to a life
afloat, the symbolic immersion of Kèn "lemo
lolo nganyan Kèn", as commanded by Sibian.
The initial contact between Gaman and
Sibian represents the relations between the
Malays and the coastal civilization. The coming
of Gaman the Malay betokens the intrusion of
the rice-growing world into the Moken com¬
munity. The Moken did not adopt rice-growing
and were driven out by it. According to the
epic, there were at the time tens of thousands of
them, and they had reached a point where they
had to choose cither to extend their territory and 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The Moken respect their
ancestors and believe in spirits
and try to make contact with
them during rituals. Only the
shaman, however, can
communicate with the beyond
via the "Post of the Spirits".
take up farming or to stabilize their population
level and gather their food. Gaman acted as the
catalyst in this clash of opposing life-styles.
In the myth, Sibian and her people are shown
as an uncivilized sedentary society, while Gaman
appears as a civilized nomad. By taking rice with
them in the wanderings that followed the trans¬
gression committed by Kèn and Gaman, the
Moken were in effect bearing civilization with
them, thus redefining the terms and becoming, by
virtue of the rice, a society both nomadic and
civilized. By accompanying the Moken to the
islands of the Mergui archipelago, Gaman comes
to represent the rice borne away by a community
that rejects the sedentary agricultural way of life
but which, as a concession to the ascendancy of
a dominant people for whom rice represents civ¬
ilization, does not refuse to eat cultivated crops.
Sea and cereal thus became inseparably con¬
nected. Since the time when Gaman and rice, i.e.
Islam and rice-growing, appeared on the scene,
the Moken have been sea-going nomads, using
their catch as currency wherewith to obtain rice
for their own consumption. Only in the light of
this ambivalent attitude of the Moken to rice can
one understand their refusal to grow it for that
purpose and their acceptance of the economic
tyranny of the taukès, the Chinese traders and
middlemen from whom they obtain it.
From myth to reality
Furthermore, by leaving rice-growing to others,
the Moken are asserting their particular identity:
rice-growers, whether Muslim or Buddhist,
facilitate their self-awareness. Malays and Chi¬
nese are the middlemen preferred by the Moken
who, like Gaman, barter pearls and other prod¬
ucts of the sea for rice and other consumer
goods, such as clothing. By enfolding their com¬
mercial links within a system of kinship, the
middlemen secure the loyalty of the Moken,
though it would perhaps be more truthful to put
it the other way round. . . . The middlemen's
ships ride in the midst of the Moken fleets which
they exploit, and the Moken boats nuzzle up to
their huge bellies to take on supplies.
The hull of the Moken boat, with its analo¬
gies to the human body, carries hewn into its
flanks the history of the Moken people. The
"mouth that eats" (okang makan) and the "rear
that defecates" (butut maé) represent in visual
and technical terms the nomad belief that accu¬
mulation spells death. The "belly" (lake), i.e.
the hold, cannot take in food unless it also dis¬
charges itself. The middlemen's ship is thus
needed by the Moken, who accept as a necessary
compromise the resultant reduction in their
mobility.
I he Moken live on boats roofed
with palm-fronds.
16
JACQUES IVAN0FF,
a French historian and
sociologist, is a researcher at
France's National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS). He
is currently engaged on an
ethnological history of Moken
mythology as part of a project,
entitled "Grand Sud", that is
being carried out jointly by the
CNRS and the Prince of Songkla
University in Thailand.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Disregarded by most
approaches to
development in the
past fifty years, the
Bedouin pastoral
economy is coming
back into favour. But
for how long?
he return of the Bedouin
by Riccardo Boceo and Ronald Jaubert
Above, a falconer of the al-
Khrayshah tribe in Jordan. The
Bedouin train falcons and hunt
with them or sell them to the
emirs of the Gulf.
s' The term steppe (bâdia) is
used to describe regions
where the rate of
precipitation varies between
50 and 350 mm annually, as
opposed to the extremely arid
desert areas (sahra).
I The vast areas of land in arid and semi-
I arid regions known as the steppe make
up more than 70 per cent of the Arab Middle
East. For several centuries the main form of
human adaptation to this environment has been
pastoral nomadism. The Bedouin (badw) who
live in these regions take their name from the
Arabic word for steppe, bâdia/' The rhythm
of their lives has long been determined by the
seasonal movements of their herds from their
winter pastures in the arid regions to summer
encampments close to wetter areas or oases.
Today the steppe is no longer an ecological
unit, and the dangers of environmental degra¬
dation are great. In several regions natural plant
life has given way to large-scale cereal cultiva¬
tion. In others the spread of roads and the extrac¬
tion of hydrocarbons, phosphates and cement
have transformed the landscape. The introduc¬
tion of new technology and expanding national
and international markets have modified the
pastoral economy. Government policies in
favour of sedentarization have reduced the
autonomy of the tribes and led them to practise
new forms of mobility.
A changing tribal society
Traditionally the social counterpart of the pas¬
toral economy of the steppes has been the tribe,
an institution in which solidarity ('asabiya) and X I
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
"Once condemned
for their 'anti-
nationalist' and
'primitive'
attitudes, local
tribal organizations
are now seen as
virtue incarnate."
Above, in the Rub al-Khali
desert, in Saudi Arabia, a
Bedouin woman of the Yam
tribe prepares flour and water
paste to give to the camels as
a supplement to their meagre
forage.
Top, Bedouin tents in the
desert near the Gulf of Aqaba
(Jordan).
18
social bonds are based on blood ties (nasab).
Networks of blood relationships contribute to
the definition of tribal territories (dirah), within
whose moving frontiers members of the group
exercise the right to control resources, espe¬
cially water and grazing land.
Although in the Arab world the tribe is the
form of social organization typical of the people
of the steppes, it is not exclusive to Bedouin
societies. And just as pastoralism has never been
a self-sufficient economic system, Bedouin soci¬
eties have never been socially or politically iso¬
lated. Traditionally, the Bedouin economic
system has formed part of a context of comple¬
mentary and interdependent relationships with
crop-growing regions and urban centres through
trade in the products of herding, agriculture
and craftsmanship and also through caravan
transportation. Usually living on the fringes of
the empires that have succeeded one another in
the region, these societies have often been depen¬
dent on the interests and expansion strategies
pursued by sedentary governments.
Half a century of modernization
The nomadic herders were far less marginal¬
ized, demographically, economically and polit¬
ically, at the turn of the century than they are
today. The fall of the Ottoman Empire led to
great upheavals, and the emergence of new states
had far-reaching consequences.
First of all the creation of new frontiers lim¬
ited the herders' mobility and deprived them of
considerable economic space. New legislation on
landed property within the young states implied
the abolition of rights over the tribal dirah.
Between the two World Wars state inter¬
ests prevailed throughout the Middle East over
local arrangements, and the tribal policies of
the authorities (both Arab and colonial) set the
seal on the decline of the tribal order.
Although the European powers took charge
of military security in the steppes, they left the
problem of the political integration of the
Bedouin to the independent states. In the 1950s
most states adopted programmes of scdenta-
rization, which was considered the main if not
the best solution to the nomad "problem". These
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Sleep is light in the nomadic wastes. One's body, exhausted by
the space . . . remembers the long road. Mountain trails swarm
along one's backbone.
Ossip Mandelstam,
Russian poet (1892-1938)
programmes, supported and legitimized by
international organizations, were based on an
ideology of modernization subscribed to by
regimes whose political orientations were very
different. Most international experts and Arab
regimes stigmatized nomadism as a backward
social condition and condemned tribalism as a
hindrance to the ideal of a united nation.
Sedentarization policies allowed several states
to maintain tighter fiscal control over the former
nomads and enabled the latter to benefit from
public health and education services. However,
the transformation of herders into farmers rep¬
resented a denial of the importance of livestock-
raising and the abandonment of grazing-land
regeneration programmes in dry areas to the
benefit of intensive and extensive agriculture
that penalized the pastoral economy.
By the early 1970s, the effects of the policy
of sedentarization together with the direct and
indirect results of oil revenues were contributing
to a transformation of the Bedouin economies
into "multiple resource systems" in which live¬
stock-raising and farming had become one
option among a number of possibilities of
salaried employment, notably in the civil service,
the military and transportation.
Development out of control
Today rampant population growth and a
growing agricultural deficit in the Arab countries
of the Middle East are returning the arid regions
to centre stage in matters of food security. Tra¬
ditionally the main areas of sheep production,
Above, inside a Bedouin tent
of the Sba'a tribe at Wadi al-
Azib in Syria.
Top, Bedouin women milking
ewes near Palmyra (Syria).
Left, a meal prepared during a
religious festival by members of
Saudi Arabia's al-Murrah tribe.
Using his right hand, each
guest serves himself to kebssa,
the national dish of rice and
meat.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
RICCARDO BOCCO
is an Italian anthropologist and
political scientist who teaches at
the University Institute for
Development Studies (IUED) of
the University of Geneva. A
specialist in peoples of the arid
zones in the Middle East, he has
devoted particular attention to
the relationships between
Bedouin tribes and states.
RONALD JAUBERT
is a Franco-British economist
presently teaching at the
University Institute for
Development Studies (IUED) in
Geneva. A specialist in arid
regions, he has worked on
projects in Syria and Mexico.
Both authors have
published many articles in
specialist journals and are, with
F. Métrai, co-editors of Steppes
d'Arabie. Etats, pasteurs,
agriculteurs et commerçants: le
devenir des zones sèches
(Cahiers de l'IUED n" 23,
Geneva, and PUF, Paris, 1993).
Since 1993 they have jointly
directed the interdisciplinary
training and research
programme entitled Aridité et
Sociétés at the IUED in Geneva.
A typical village southwest of
Aleppo (Syria). Its inhabitants
are former nomad pastoralists
whose families settled there
permanently in the 1930s.
the arid and semi-arid regions are playing a
decreasing role in the supply of meat to regional
markets where demand has grown without
precedent partly as a result of urbanization and
revenue from oil.
In some countries of the Near East, such as
Syria, the explosion of regional markets has led to
a considerable increase in the number of sheep
and has tightened the pressure on the arid and
semi-arid zones, which until the 1960s were the
primary food source for herds but today supply
less than 20 per cent of their annual consumption.
On the regional level, government land and
economic policies have not only contributed to
breaking up the former management systems
but have also made for considerable expansion of
cultivated areas in the arid zones. At present the
Bedouin share the use of their former territories
with villagers in the farming areas, shop-keepers
and livestock-raising entrepreneurs from the city
whose interests often compete with those of the
formerly nomadic populations.
The increased fragility of the steppes due to
soil deterioration now appears to be one of the
most disturbing effects of the development poli¬
cies of the past thirty years. In spite of the modern
technological facilities at their disposal, states
have not been able to control the environment or
ensure the success of models drawn up by experts.
Full speed astern!
Since 1960 when the majority of studies sup¬
ported sedentarization and turning the steppe
into cropland, studies carried out in Saudi Arabia
have highlighted the need to develop systems for
regenerating grazing land and drawn planners'
attention to the existence of a traditional man¬
agement system known on the Arabian Penin-
20
sula as hima (plural ahmia, literally, "protection"
and, by analogy, "reserve").
Formerly used in the Near East as a means of
controlling the degradation of grazing land, the
hima system could also supply large reserves of
forage for herds. According to Omar Draz, an
FAO consultant, the reintroduction of such a
system might have changed the populations'
attitude to local resources by introducing a phi¬
losophy of protection and improvement and
not simply exploitation.
In the present international context of envi¬
ronmental awareness, the latest approach
favoured by social and natural scientists relies
heavily on the hima system as a means of com¬
bating desertification. The system enjoys an
Islamic seal of approval which may go back to
the Prophet, but so far no detailed analytical
study of its feasibility on the Near-Eastern
steppe has been made. Furthermore, according
to specialists in favour of hima programmes,
their implementation would depend on the
return of tribal land rights on the steppes, on a
participatory approach that would take account
of Bedouin tribal organization, and on govern¬
ments taking a back seat in project manage¬
ment. This about-turn from the policies fol¬
lowed in the 1950s and 1960s is in itself a form
of criticism of the sedentarization projects that
were carried out.
One steppe at a time
The consensus that is forming around the hima
programmes should not prevent us from asking
some basic questions about them. Once con¬
demned for their "anti-nationalist" and "prim¬
itive" attitudes, local tribal organizations are
now seen as virtue incarnate. Their rehabilitation
is based on an idyllic vision of the Bedouin
tribes that, before state intervention, were sup¬
posed to manage the resources of the arid regions
harmoniously by respecting ecological balances.
This perception, which sweeps away fifty
years of history and "development", points to a
useful alternative solution but it also raises many
questions. Is it realistic? How will it be inter¬
preted locally? What are the interests of those
newly involved? What is the political weight
of public administrative bodies and private
groups in this new approach?
Development programmes are always based
on ideas about the world that are the product of
their time, and it might be asked in this case
whether the presuppositions and knowledge of
specialists are not backing a new ideology that
may once again turn out to be short on analysis
of the real situation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
THE EUROPEAN ODYSSEY OF THE GYPSIES Uypsy caravans
in the Balkans, where
over five million Gypsies
live today.
n the road
Many Gypsy families
have lived for
generations in the
same part of Europe,
but they are still
regarded as transient
foreigners.
by Patrick Williams
The Gypsies originated in northwest
I India. Sometime around the tenth cen¬
tury A.D. they embarked on the migration that
scattered them all over the world. Paradoxi¬
cally, it is through the knowledge of non-
Gypsies (Gadje) that it has been possible to
retrace this migration, largely on the basis of his¬
torical linguistics.
The Gypsy language has the same relationship
to its mother tongue, Sanskrit, as Hindi, Gujarati
and Punjabi, except that it only exists in a range
of dialects that have been influenced by the lan¬
guages of the lands through which its speakers
travelled over the centuries. By studying the lan¬
guage spoken by a Gypsy today it is possible to
discover the routes taken by his ancestors. The
diversity of Gypsy dialects reflects the diversity
of the routes they have taken.
However, research has been unable to tell us
who they were during their time in India. Were
they already nomads, blacksmiths and musi¬
cians? Were they outcasts or Rajputs defeated
and dispossessed by Muslim invaders?
Whatever the truth may be, this uprooting
from a homeland and this mass movement west¬
ward are not etched in Gypsy memory, which
tends to indicate that they did not regard their
travels as an exodus. Certainly traces of India are
buried in their language and in some of their cus¬
toms and beliefs, but these traces are not part of
their conscious memory.
Moreover, Gypsy migration is linked to the
history of the peoples among whom they live.
They are not masters of their situation. The
decision whether to leave or to stay or where to
go is not for them to take. Perhaps this is why
they prefer to live in the border regions of their
adopted countries. 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
rVI embers of the Nicolich
family, above, have been
"mechkar" (bear-leaders) for
generations.
22
A study of the movements of groups of
Gypsies since their arrival in Europe shows
that, whether enforced or freely chosen, these
movements are always a response to a change in
the non-Gypsy environment. It would be a mis¬
take to think that their migrations are over, as is
shown by the arrival in western Europe of Gyp¬
sies fleeing political upheavals in the former
Yugoslavia and in Romania.
Moving to the rhythm of the seasons
While migration is a response to events over
which Gypsies have no control, nomadism is a
form of social organization in its own right.
Gypsy movements are clearly organized
according to the rhythms of the seasons, i.e.
sedentary life through the long winter months
and movement with the return of fine weather.
But the sacred must surely play a part, too. In
general it is the Christian holidays of Palm
Sunday and All Saints' Day that signal the dates
of departure and return, two dates when Gypsy
families are accustomed to visit their dead. The
cemetery in which the family graves are located
is often the pole around which the family terri¬
tory is organized.
Gypsies arc found in groups of varying sizes
that live or travel together. To describe these
units, the Kalderash Romanies one of the
main Gypsy groups use the word kumpania
(company). When stationary, these units may
gather in a neighbourhood or a "village" the
most frequent situation in central Europe or
live as scattered households among the
dwellings of the other Gadje inhabitants. On the
move, their composition may change at each
stopping place. The kumpania is a body whose
molecular structure changes according to cir¬
cumstances while remaining faithful to its
nature. Depending on whom they meet at each
halting place, people move from one kumpania
to another, taking with them expertise, stories
and ways of life.
The extended family (three generations) is
the stable nucleus of the nomadic kumpania. A
child who grows up in a kumpania feels that he
or she belongs to a permanent entity around
which the world revolves. The family unit seems
self-sufficient because of the distribution of
skills and the way in which its different com¬
ponents complement each other. The men work
at handicrafts, the women sell (the traditional
organizational model for basket-weaving fam¬
ilies), or else the adults sell some commodities
(clothes), and the children others (wild flowers
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
and fruit). Although some craftsmen, such as
blacksmiths, tinkers, silversmiths and basket-
weavers, specialize in a single field, versatility is
more highly prized than specialization. The
important thing is to be able to cope with unpre¬
dictable situations.
Moving from group to group
The movement of individuals and families among
the larger groups causes a constant reshaping of
the social landscape as well as intermixing all
parts of the society. A distinctive feature of Gypsy
"nomadism", this movement from group to
group is the result of several factors.
Through belonging to a kinship network,
people can be "placed" by those they meet. Per¬
sons arriving in a new community try to find
among their acquaintances those who will allow
them to "latch onto" a family. As soon as their
credentials are accepted, they become respon¬
sible members of their new community with
the same rights and duties as the others.
To make the decision, to cast off every
bond by which modern life and the
weakness ofour own hearts have
chained us, to arm ourselves with the
pilgrim's symbolic sack and staff, and
to depart.
Isabelle Eberhardt
French writer and adventurer (1877-1904)
Above and below, members of
a "kumpania" (extended group)
of Gypsies in their camp near
Sliven, an industrial town in
Bulgaria. They eke out a living
by collecting linden, camomile
and dogwood flowers for
Bulgarian pharmaceutical
companies.
The sharing of values and cultural charac¬
teristics, which create a sense of fraternity among
those who possess them, is another factor.
Once he is integrated into the community,
the new arrival can benefit from its technical
expertise. When out canvassing, a craftsman
never refuses to take on a repair job that he
cannot do himself, for he knows that among
his "brothers" he is bound to find one with the
necessary skills. The rule is that the profits are
shared out equally, no matter what kind of job
has been done. Co-operation is more highly
regarded than individual success.
However, it is not always possible to move
from one community to another. The itiner¬
aries of certain groups diverged from others so
early on that their members seem to have
nothing in common. In spite of the stereotyped
view that Gadje societies have of them, all Gyp¬
sies do not accept one another across the board.
How to be invisible
Gypsy nomadism takes place on land that is
already occupied. The relationship between
nomads and their environment is a struggle for
power material power, obviously, but even
more the power of legitimacy. Because they
come from elsewhere and live differently, Gyp¬
sies are universally seen as intruders, foreigners.
History has shown that the societies in which the
Gypsies live want to see the back of them.
But the history of the Gypsies is the history
of a people that does its best to play down this
power struggle. Nomads use strategies of invis¬
ibility and fluidity that enable them to slip into
the legislative, economic, geographical and other
nooks and crannies that sedentary societies leave
vacant.
Inside non-Gypsy territories therefore there
are Gypsy territories of various shapes and sizes. 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
LIVING IN COMPANY
"Gypsies are found in groups of varying sizes. To describe
these units the word 'kumpania' (company) is used. When
stationary, these groups may gather in a neighbourhood or a
'village', or live as scattered households among the other
inhabitants. On the move, their composition may change at
each stopping place. Depending on whom they meet, people
move from one "kumpania" to another, taking with them
expertise, stories and ways of life."
Composed of routes and poles, they overlap
and intermingle. They can be freely accessible or
forbidden. Relationships between Gypsy groups
present in the same region can vary between
solidarity and competition, ignorance of each
other's existence, and warfare.
The ways in which these territories are occu¬
pied and used differ according to the Gypsies'
activities and their relationships with non-
Gypsies. Gypsies' commercial activities require
a minimum of conformity to local administra¬
tive procedures and the possession of a min¬
imum of cultural skills. It is, for example, a good
idea to speak the language of the people you
wish to do business with. That is enough for
some Gypsies, but others have a deeper knowl¬
edge of local customs.
Yet observation shows that it is often those
communities that show the greatest cultural
dynamism in keeping alive their language, cus¬
toms (marriage is still usually within the Gypsy
community) and traditions (music, oral litera¬
ture, costumes), that are most at ease in non-
Gypsy environments.
The Gypsy pilgrimage to Les
Saintes-Marles-de-la-Mer in the
south of France. Legend has it
that Mary, sister of the Virgin,
and Mary, mother of James and
John, fled there to escape
persecution in Judaea. With
them was their black servant,
Sara, who became the
patroness of the Gypsies.
Below, Gypsies in procession
carrying statues of the two
saints.
Gypsies have not remained aloof from the
process of urbanization that has occurred in
many parts of Europe. Nor have they missed out
on technological progress. They have also under¬
stood how to get the most out of improvements
in individual transportation facilities. Ways of
moving about have changed. Families tend to
stay in the same place for longer and longer
periods, and the car is used for journeys occa¬
sioned by family events. If community life some¬
times suffers from these forms of progress, it can
also be enriched by making contact easier
between groups living far apart.
Changing patterns of movement
Recent political changes in Europe have affected
both migration and nomadism. Hundreds of
Gypsy families have left the former commu¬
nist countries to head for western Europe where
they hope to receive refugee status. But in these
countries increasing state intervention into the
lives of the citizen is also affecting nomads,
notably in the designation of places where they
can camp, the organization of their stay, and
the setting up of health care, schooling and voca¬
tional training programmes.
Gypsies have probably never had an easy
time, historically speaking, but they have always
managed to survive adversity and remain rela¬
tively independent. Movement in groups may
have decreased, but the other characteristics
that define Gypsy nomadism have been safe¬
guarded. As the essential dynamic of Gypsy
societies, individuals and families still continue
to move between larger groups, but between
fixed points rather than moving ones.
24
PATRICK WILLIAMS,
a French ethnologist, is a
member of the Urban
Anthropological Laboratory of
France's National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS). He
has been a student of Gypsy
culture and society for many
years. His recent publications
include Django (Limon, Paris,
1991) and "Nous, on n'en parle
pas". Les vivants et les morts
chez ¡es Manouches (Maison
des sciences de l'homme, Paris,
1993).
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
orest
rovers of
the Amazon
by Howard Reid
The Maku of Amazonia enjoy roaming
through the tropical forest and resist
efforts to settle them down
rVlaku village-life in Colombia. I The Maku are a highly mobile group of
; Amazonian indigenous peoples who live
in the rainforests of the northwest Amazon in
Colombia and Brazil. Their territories stretch
discontinuously from the northwest fringes of
the rainforest around the river Guaviare in
Colombia to the forests lying between the rivers
Japura and Negro in Brazil, a distance of about
1,000 kms from one end to the other. There are
six named sub-groups of the Maku, a word
which has been imposed by outsiders and can be
equated with the English term "Gypsy", each
speaking a dialect of the Maku language family.
All the Maku live in the rainforest itself,
away from the network of large rivers which
weave through this area. The riversides are
mostly occupied by ethnically distinct indige¬
nous peoples or by white colonists. Both these
latter groups live mainly by growing food crops
and by fishing, while the Maku of the forests rely
heavily on hunting, fishing and gathering. How¬
ever, they do also grow crops, albeit on a much
smaller scale than their riverside neighbours.
The Maku move around a great deal. Every
day the men or women of any group will take off
into the forest in search of game, fish, nuts,
fruit, insects or raw materials for making baskets,
weapons, houses in fact almost everything
they need to survive comes from the forest.
Most Maku groups have a "base" village or
longhouse with small gardens nearby from
which they make their daily sorties into the
forest, but everyone also spends weeks or
months each year living in camps inside the
forest proper. The location of these camps varies
according to seasonal rhythms and the ripening
of fruit and nuts, movements of game animals,
water levels in streams and so on.
Sometimes an entire group will go to camp in
the forest together, sometimes just a few families. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
"Freedom of
movement tends to
produce egalitarian
political systems
if there are no rules
saying that you
must remain under
the control of the
head of your group,
political life
remains in essence
voluntary. If a
leader abuses his
authority, he is very
likely to find
himself without a
group to lead."
Making curare, a substance
made from plants which
paralyses the motor nerves and
is used as an arrow poison by
the Maku.
When camps are going to be short only two or
three days then usually only men and older
boys go. On longer camps of a week or more the
people usually move camp-site every few days.
Forest camps are a time of intense work for
the men, who hunt and fish from before dawn
until dusk. Their aim is not just to get enough
food to feed everyone, but to build up a tem¬
porary surplus of meat and fish which will be
used for ritual purposes or traded to the river¬
side peoples. The choice of where people go
and for how long depends on many factors,
including the kind of food desired, the time of
year, and the state of rivers and streams. At any
one time any Maku man or family has a wide
range of choice in these matters, and it is quite
normal for each family in a residential group to
split up and go, all at the same time, to different
parts of the forest in search of different products.
For the women, forest camps are a welcome
change from the drudgery of the daily routine of
farming and the processing of food which fills
their days in the "base" village. In the cool of the
forest shade they collect vines to weave bas¬
kets, or gather ants, termites or caterpillars to eat,
and relax and play with their children at the
camp-site.
Working on the move is fun, working in
the same place is a bore
The Hupdu Maku, with whom I lived for two
years, have two contrasting words for the activ¬
ities they perform. "Bu'ui" means to work, that
is to clear gardens, build houses or make tools.
26
This is generally considered to be disagreeable.
The other word is "Get Ko'ai" which roughly
means "to cruise in the forest". You may be
fishing, hunting, foraging or just keeping an
eye on what's going on, but everyone agrees
that "Get Ko'ai" is a pleasant and valued way to
spend your time. So at a very basic level working
on the move is fun, while working in a fixed
place house or garden is irksome.
Besides moving around in pursuit of food the
Hupdu Maku also like to go and visit relatives.
They live in small dispersed groups (one to five
families, six to about forty individuals), and
there are always close kin in neighbouring
groups. The arrival of visitors is an exciting
moment. The sharp-eyed children are usually the
first to call out, "People are coming!" when vis¬
itors arrive, and then everyone in the house
rushes to see who it is. Once the guests have
entered the house, been shown where to sit and
been given something to eat and drink, every res¬
ident greets them by asking them, "Have you
arrived?" The reply is, "Yes, I have arrived, are
you here?". The hosts reply that they are here,
both parties thus affirming that it is indeed they
who are greeting each other and not some malig¬
nant spirits masquerading as people.
The Nukak Maku in Colombia are the most
mobile of all the Maku, and probably the most
mobile people in South America. Every three-
to-ten days they abandon their banana-leaf shel¬
ters and walk for a few kilometres through the
forest to a new camp-site. Although they have
small gardens in the forest, they do not use them
as "bases" with more permanent houses in them
as the other Maku do. We are not yet certain of
the reasons for this extremely high level of
mobility, but the Nukak were hostile to out¬
siders until very recently. For at least two cen¬
turies their region has been subjected to slave
raiding, and more recently rubber gatherers,
cattle ranchers and cocaine growers have tried to
penetrate their lands. This has resulted in several
massacres, isolated killings and outbreaks of
epidemics. I am sure that the Nayak realize that
it is much safer to keep on the move in these cir¬
cumstances.
The Maku not only move as individuals,
families or groups, they also very often move
between groups. For them, as for many other
nomads, people are free to choose where and
with whom they spend their time.
Searching for clues in a forest of dreams
The Maku love the world they live in. I have
often walked through the forest with old men
who would call to birds or monkeys just for the
pleasure of hearing them answer back. Talking
to the animals makes them laugh. A big game
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The base village or longhouse
of the Baras, a Maku group
living in Colombia.
kill, the discovery of honey or trees laden with
fruits or nuts are occasions of great joy. In their
dreams the Maku rove through the forest
searching for clues to dream of tobacco leaves
is to find wild pigs (peccary) as their noses are the
same shape as the leaves. A hunter will search for
and sometimes find peccary after such a dream.
The forest lives deep inside them and moving
around it is a way of keeping it alive within
them as well as deriving sustenance from it.
It is utterly wrong to say that nomads only
move around because they have to. It is even
more wrong to suggest that they would stop
doing so if they could find other ways to subsist.
The Maku, for example, have for decades had
sufficient tools to clear big gardens and live
more sedentary lives, but they do not want to.
The Tuareg speak of houses as "the tombs of the
city dwellers".
In the rainy season of 1975 there was a lot of
heavy rain and the streams overflowed their
banks, washing away the fish population and
making it difficult to get around in the forest.
There was little game and the hunters had no
luck. One morning a young man shot a yellow
agouti, a long-legged rodent, which weighed
about one kilo. Bringing it home he gave it to his
older brother, the leader of the group, who
pointedly did not offer any of it to the three fam¬
ilies who had been staying for the past month,
nor to his mother's brother, although he was a
resident member of the group.
Failing to share meat is the worst crime imag¬
inable to the Maku, so the offended parties
stormed out of the house, muttering about the
rudeness of the leader. A week later a drinking
party took place and when all were getting
drunk a scuffle broke out, there was a lot of
shouting and all those who had been denied the
agouti meat stormed out of the house, setting fire
to the shelter a guest family had been staying in
as a protest.
The guests returned to their own base village
and the mother's brother set up a base in an old
garden of his about three hours' walk away. A
year later all were on friendly terms again, but
the ex-resident never returned to live with that
group.
Being able to move is therefore an extremely
important mechanism in dispute settlement for
the Maku, and for most other nomad groups.
Freedom of movement also tends to produce
egalitarian political systems if there are no rules
saying that you must remain under the control of
the head of your group, political life remains in
essence voluntary. If a leader abuses his authority
he is very likely to find himself without a group
to lead. The Maku are extremely opposed to
other Maku giving them orders and will simply
leave if one person gets too bossy.
This is not a question of the absence of social
hierarchies or inability to develop them, as found
in property-based societies. It is a positive inten¬
tion not to let inequality develop in the first
place.
When the Maku stopped moving
In the 1970s Salcsian missionaries in the Upper
Rio Negro, Brazil, stepped up their pressure
on the Hupdu Maku to stop wandering in the
forest and build permanent settlements sur¬
rounded by large gardens, with a chapel and a
school. They "invited" six or more Maku local
HOWARD REID,
British film-maker, author and
anthropologist, is currently
Simon Fellow in Visual
Anthropology at the University of
Manchester. He lived with the
Maku between 1974 and 1976,
and revisited them in 1989 and
1992. He has also lived with
and made films on the Khazaks
(China), the Maasai (Kenya) and
the Tuareg in Niger.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
groups to come together in this task, at a stroke
creating villages of 120-150 people. The mis¬
sionaries' intermediaries in this policy were
local riverside people who effectively ordered
the Maku to comply. Several sites were selected,
with the eventual aim of concentrating all the
Maku there (they were then living in about
thirty-eight separate communities). As incentives
the missionaries offered them handouts of
clothes and manioc flour to tide them over until
their new gardens began to yield.
All the main concentration villages share a
very similar subsequent history which was
roughly as follows. For a few months the Maku
were interested. There was a lot of unpleasant
"Bu" (work) to do, and not enough "Get Koai"
(cruising or foraging), but there was free food,
clothes and the strange missionaries to watch.
Within months, however, tensions began to
mount. All the game for several hours' walk
around the concentration villages was hunted
out and the streams stripped of fish.
After six months the missionaries went away
for a break. The Maku then brewed a big batch
of manioc beer and a large-scale brawl ensued.
The people broke up into their old small groups
and dispersed throughout the forest. Hearing of
this, the missionaries sent out the riverside
teachers to round up the Maku and bring them
back to the concentration village. The mis¬
sionaries banned parties, dancing and the
brewing and drinking of alcohol. The Maku
remained, especially those who were keen for
their children to learn a little Portuguese,
28
reading, writing and basic arithmetic. But life
was not good there.
Pooh, a Maku friend, summed up the mis¬
sion experience in this way: "The priests come
here and they tell us to stop drinking beer and
dancing and playing our sacred trumpets. This
is like a man coming to us and taking all our food
away. What should we do? Without food,
without music there is no movement in the
world. People are sad, become sick and die."
How should we meet the needs of
nomads?
Countless other tales from all round the world
could be told of the sufferings of nomadic people
forced to stop travelling by outsiders of superior
military, political or economic strength. I have
never come across a case of nomads who want
to abandon their nomadism. Nomads not only
need to move, they like to move.
However, most governments feel that the
only way to protect nomads is to pin them to the
ground so they can be counted, taught, vacci¬
nated, taxed and the like. Yet, the few experi¬
ments which have been tried out in bringing
these services to nomads on the move have
proved highly successful. It is not difficult to
provide mobile medical aid and vaccination pro¬
grammes, even in tropical rainforests.
Education presents more problems, but it is
far from impossible, especially if the people
themselves are motivated and want to learn.
Once basic educational skills have been
implanted in the people themselves they will
be able to teach and travel with minimal support.
Many young Maku parents regret that they
cannot speak Portuguese or Spanish, do not
know how to handle money and are therefore
exploited. However, they do not wish to sacri¬
fice their way of life as the price to pay for being
able to understand what's being said on their
riverside neighbour's satellite TV set.
The last and perhaps most important factor
is land. The world's remaining nomads occupy
the most marginal lands on the planet deserts,
rainforests, tundra and steppe. These rugged
and beautiful wildernesses are, however, hardly
the most fertile places on Earth. For people to
survive without radically altering these envi¬
ronments they need a lot of space. It is essential
that nomads be granted proper title to their
lands and that this title should extend to the
subsoil. Extractive industries have caused hor¬
rendous suffering to nomadic peoples from the
Arctic to Australia. Only with secure land rights
can nomads both continue to move and choose
in what ways they wish to engage with the rest
of humanity.
Left, a hallucinogenic drug
used in rituals is being prepared
from plants.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Who is responsible
for the crisis of
Africa's nomadic
herders and their
traditional lands?
A group of Maasai burning
their village. They usually do
this to keep the area clean and
to kill parasites. Often they do
not burn their villages but leave
them empty when they move
away. he vanishing African
herdsman
by John Galaty
I Pastoralists make productive use of the
most inhospitable regions of Africa the
arid and semi-arid lands by raising livestock
for their own subsistence and to provide meat for
teeming cities and crowded farms. Today, most of
them live in a wide, curving band of savannah.
Specialized herders live in the drier regions with
up to 500 mm rainfall, agropastoralists who
tend livestock but depend on crop cultivation
for their livelihood in a larger zone with up to
750 mm of rainfall per year. Eastern Africa, a
region stretching from Ethiopia and the Sudan in
the north to Tanzania in the south and covering
20 per cent of the area of Africa, is populated by
half the continent's cattle and the vast majority of
its pastoralists.
The dry rangelands have fewer domestic
animals per land area than do the islands of
highlands, where both animals and people live
in high densities. In these areas of scanty rainfall 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Life is a bridge.
Cross over it, but
build no house
on it.
Indian proverb
¿y
&
,
IVIaasai goatherds of the
Samburu tribe (Kenya).
An encampment of the
pastoral Maasai, who live in
Kenya and the United Republic
of Tanzania, usually consists of
around fifty igloolike dwellings
(below and opposite page).
and sparse vegetation, where agriculture is gen¬
erally impossible or very risky, livestock require
relatively large areas of grazing to thrive. A
demographic explosion has resulted in a flow of
migrants from swollen highland communities
into the arid and semi-arid lands, which to them
appear relatively empty. However, people who
have lived for a long time in the drylands are well
aware that these areas have a low potential for
supporting human communities, and know that
all available sources are currently expended in
supporting them through animal husbandry
and dryland agriculture.
These facts do not, however, mitigate the
desire of land-hungry peasants to occupy neigh-
30
bouring rangeland, nor slow the steps they take
to do so. Many enclaves of relatively more fertile
land within the African rangelands are experi¬
encing piecemeal enclosure, whether in the oases
of the Sahara, the riverine valleys of western and
eastern Africa, the fringes of the Kalahari in
Botswana, or the mountains and swamps of east
Africa. The Maasai in the plains of southern
Kenya and northern Tanzania are noteworthy in
being subjected to more far-reaching threats to
their land than are perhaps members of any other
community on the continent.
In Kenya, corruption in land allocations
during privatization, sales by poor pastoralists
once they receive land titles, and appropriation
of rich rangeland for parks and reserves, all add
up to a massive haemorrhage of the land hold¬
ings of Maasai herders. In Tanzania, with its
new policy of leasing rural land to local and
foreign entrepreneurs, Maasai residents are being
dispossessed at an even greater pace. Circum¬
venting local villages, which theoretically serve
as land-holding bodies, leasehold titles for thou¬
sands and thousands of hectares of land are
being allocated to government officials, local
big men and foreign companies. Local pro¬
ducers wake up to find fences cutting them off
from land they have always used, or see tractors
clear-cut and plough fields that stretch to the
horizon where their pastures had lain. In the
idiom of enterprising Tanzanians today, the
Maasai districts represent the last frontier, and
they are the "cowboys" coming to seize land
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
from the "Indians", that is, their fellow Tan-
zanian citizens, the Maasai.
The discourse of dispossession
To understand this inexorable though not yet
inevitable process of dispossession, we must
look to the discourse, woven out of contradic¬
tory ideas, which motivates and justifies the
appropriation of pastoral land.
The first of these ideas suggests that the range
is o^mnilized by pastoralists, who degrade it
through overstocking. Pasture loss, erosion and
dust-filled valleys are seen to result from the
paradox of common property: since pastoralists
individually reap economic benefits while col¬
lectively sharing environmental costs, they lack
incentives to control the growth of their herds.
From this analysis it follows that common
resources can only be sustained if they are priva¬
tized or put under state control. But this argument
has been refuted on many grounds, and the poli¬
cies which follow from it have been subjected to
severe criticism.
Firstly, it ignores the role played by commu¬
nity institutions, legitimized by the authority of
tradition and by local participation, in managing
environmental resources. Secondly, it reflects the
view that individual producers are competitors
who make decisions independently of one another,
while herders form overlapping networks of com¬
munication through which strategies are co-ordi¬
nated. Thirdly, the argument assumes that the
most important determinant of grassland quality
is the number of animals using the range. However,
in most grazing systems in Africa, degradation
of the range environment is primarily correlated
with annual rainfall and local soil quality rather
than stocking levels.
The image of an Africa afflicted with erosion
and dust stems from the occurrence of lower than
average rainfall over the last thirty years. In the dry
season or during drought, the abundance of pas¬
ture depends more on the amount of rainfall
received than on the proportion of already dead
cellulose livestock do or do not eat. After a
drought, the seeds of annual grasses lie in the dust
ready to germinate, and the roots of perennial
grasses lie deep below ground ready to regen¬
erate when rains come. In fact, in many pastoral
areas, understocking is a more serious problem
than overstocking, since undergrazing leaves
unpalatable, woody and unproductive herbage
that harbours parasites and stifles the growth of
new grasses.
A second key idea, contradictory to the first,
suggests that under pastoral use rangeland
resources are underutilized. The same herders
"Many enclaves of
relatively more
fertile land are
experiencing
piecemeal
enclosure, whether
in the oases of the
Sahara, the riverine
valleys of western
and eastern Africa,
the fringes of the
Kalahari, or the
mountains and
swamps of east
Africa. The Maasai
are being subjected
to more far-reaching
threats to their land
than perhaps any
other community."
Maasai hut in Tanzania.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
who are accused of overexploiting the range are
also accused of underexploiting it! This myth
stems in part from the visual contrast between
crowded highland settlements and scattered pas¬
toral homesteads, between cultivated fields that
bear the imprint of human labour and regenerating
pastures that rest unused for much of the year.
It has also been argued that privatization
brings about more productive use of land, in this
case through moving pastoral land into farming
or through stimulating improved forms of
animal husbandry. However, privatization may
serve in the short run as a means of simply accu¬
mulating assets. Pastoral land may be sought
by speculators who covet land titles that can
be used as collateral for credit. Outsiders can buy
such land cheaply and invest elsewhere the loans
they procure on the basis of that land, which
they leave unused and often unoccupied. Under
these conditions, range productivityfalls because
of privatization. But even when land enclosures
and transfers do result in higher output, the
results must be balanced against capital invested.
Since politically powerful land-holders benefit
when the government subsidizes water improve¬
ments, the social costs of diverting public
resources to private gain must be weighed
against the output of the now irrigated land.
The tragedy of enclosure
In fact, the true tragedy of the rangelands occurs
at the moment of its enclosure, when it is in
everyone's interest to claim as much available
land as possible, independent of the common
good. The view that under private or state own¬
ership rural land tends to be better managed
must also be scrutinized. In countries where
rangelands have been declared state property,
community management has been undermined,
Arrayed in all their finery,
young Maasai head for the
Eunoto ceremony which marks
their transition from warriors to
mature men.
Below, the Maasai dwelling
consists of an armature of
branches covered with earth
mixed with cow dung and
chopped straw.
32
Wm^L^'
creating chaotic systems of "open access" to
the detriment of the range environment. Rarely
has the state had the means (or the will) to mon¬
itor range use with the knowledge and attention
of local herding communities.
After privatization, rangelands are often
both underutilized, as we have seen, and overuti-
lized, as when individual ranchers use private
land in conjunction with adjacent common
property for intensive commercial use. If we
seek to explain the disruption of local resource
management and time-tried techniques of food
production in these areas, we should seek it in
the erosion of indigenous rights over land rather
than in the erosion of the land itself.
There are good reasons to rely on small¬
holding herders and agropastoralists as agents of
conservation and development rather than on pri¬
vate entrepreneurs. When we realize that the ben¬
eficiaries of enclosure and privatization are often
not those who will dedicate their lives to the land,
we might also be discovering the roots of the twin
crises in Africa's arid and semi-arid lands, envi¬
ronmental decline and increasing poverty.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
,.*'
Ztfy
-*
?» û/fe> r;^
s^^n¡
*Sr*~
tm
JOHN GALATY
is an American anthropologist
who is currently associate
professor at McGill University,
Montreal, where he also serves
as director of the Centre for
Society, Technology and
Development. A specialist in
African pastoral nomadism, he is
currently engaged on research
into Maasai land tenure. He has
co-edited several volumes on
pastoralism, including The World
of Pastoralism: Herding Systems
in Comparative Perspective
(1990) and Herders, Warriors
and Traders: Pastoralism in
Africa (1991).
FURTHER READING
IN ENGLISH:
*- Adamu, Mahdi and Kirk-Greene, A. H. M., Pastoralists of the West African Savanna, Manchester, Manchester University Press,
1986, 359 pp.
*- Arhem, Kaj, Pastoral Man in the Garden of Eden: The Maasai of the Ngongoro Conservation Area, Tanzania, Uppsala, University
of Uppsala, Sweden, 1985, 123 pp.
Barth, Fredrik, Nomads of South Persia, Oslo, Oslo University Press, 1961, 159 pp.
* Black-Michaud, Jacob, Sheep and Land: The Economics of Power in a Tribal Society, Cambridge, Cambridge University Press,
1987, 231 pp.
* Clarke, Thurston, The Last Caravan, New York, G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1978, 286 pp.
» Lancaster, William, The Rwala Bedouin Today, Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 1981, 179 pp.
« Lewis, N., Nomads and Settlers in Syria and Jordan, 1880-1980, Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 1987.
* Liégois, Jean-Pierre, Gypsies. An Illustrated History, London, Saqi Books, 1986.
« Monod, Théodore (ed), Pastoralism in Tropical Africa, London, Oxford University Press, 1975, 502 pp
* Nelson, Cynthia, The Desert and the SownNomads in the Wider Society, Berkeley, University of California, 1973, 173 pp.
* Theslger, Wilfrid, Desert, Marsh and Mountain: the World of a Nomad, London, Collins, 1979, 280 pp.; Visions of a Nomad
(photographs), 1987.
IN FRENCH:
* Bernus, E. and Pouillon, F. (editors), Sociétés pastorales et développement (Cahiers des sciences humaines, vol. 26 nos 1-2),
Paris, ORSTOM, 1990.
* Boceo, R., Jaubert, R. and Metral F., Steppes d'Arabie. Etats, pasteurs, agriculteurs et commerçants: le devenir des zones
sèches (Cahiers de I'iued, n° 23), Geneva and Paris, iued and puf, (1993).
Denis, Pierre, Les Derniers nomades, Paris, L'Harmattan, 1989, 631 pp.
* Galaty, John, Aronson, Dan and Salzman, Philip Cari, L'Avenir des peuples pasteurs, Ottawa, Centre de Recherches pour le
Développement International, 1983, 432 pp.
Saintoir, Christian, Raison pastorale et politique de développementLes Peuls sénégalais face aux aménagements, Paris,
ORSTOM, 1983, 185 pp.
White, Kenneth, L'Esprit nomade, Paris, Grasset, 1987, 309 pp.
IN GERMAN:
Braukämper, U., Migration und ethnischer Wandel: Untersuchungen aus der östlichen Sudanzone, (Studien zur Kulturkunde, _ _
103), Stuttgart, Franz Steiner, 1992. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN
action *
34
A VIDEO CONFERENCE
ON LITERACY
There are currently more than 900
million illiterate adults worldwide, 65
per cent of whom are women. Of the
132 million children who have never
set foot in a classroom, two-thirds
are girls and one-third live in Africa
south of the Sahara. In developing
countries girls and minority groups
often have no opportunity to attend
school, and there is a crippling lack of
books, teachers and equipment. In
industrialized countries there are
relapses into functional illiteracy on
the part of adults who have attended
school and a decline in reading among
children addicted to television. The
technological revolution wrought by
computers, satellites, fibre optics and
cellular networks are changing the
notion of literacy. To highlight the
impact of these technologies on
education, Unesco celebrated
International Literacy Day on 8
September with a Paris-Washington
video conference that was
transmitted live over satellite to
audiences in North America, Europe
and North Africa. Educators, policy
makers and communications
experts from around the world
discussed literacy work, formal and
non-formal education and the
challenges they pose as the
2 1 st century approaches.
INTERNATIONAL FORUM
ON BIODIVERSITY
"Biodiversity: Science and
Development Towards a New
partnership" was the theme of an
international forum held at Unesco
Headquarters from 5 to 9 September.
Some 600 scientists, policy-makers,
economists, educators and business
leaders took part in the forum, the
largest gathering of its kind since the
United Nations Conference on
Environment and Development
(UNCED) in Rio de Janeiro in 1992
where delegates signed the
Convention on Biological Diversity.
Biodiversity, or biological diversity, is
a term that encompasses the variety
of all the earth's ecosystems, plants,
animals and micro-organisms. Themes
WORLD HERITAGE:
4 NEW SITES
At the 1 7th annual meeting of the
World Heritage Committee, held
in Cartagena (Colombia) 4 new
natural heritage sites were added
to the World Heritage List. Two of
them are in Japan. The Shirakami
mountains in northern Honshu
contain the last remnant of
undisturbed beech forest that once
covered the mountain slopes of
northern Japan. Yakushima, on
Yaku island, is famed for its ancient
Japanese cedars. The El Vizcaino
Whale Lagoons, in Mexico's Baja
peninsula, contain major breeding
and wintering sites for the grey
whale. The site also protects
several species of marine turtles,
sea lions, elephant seals and
wildfowl. Also selected was the
Tubbataha Reef Marine Park, in the
Philippines.
studied at the forum included:
approaching the unity of life through
biological diversity; biodiversity's
ecological functions; a global
inventory and monitoring system;
conservation of biodiversity including
our daily urban environment;
utilization of resources for agriculture
and industry; and biodiversity's ethical
and cultural dimensions.
BIOETHICS COMMITTEE
ACTION
Unesco's International Bioethics
Committee (IBC) was established in
September 1993. After consulting
with its correspondents throughout
the world, notably national ethics
committees, the IBC held its second
session in September 1994 and
embarked on its major task
preparing an international instrument
on the protection of the human
genome. The 3-day meeting examined
the ethical implications of genetic
advances. Among the subjects
discussed were genetic screening and
testing, gene therapy and the teaching
of bioethics. IBC president Noëlle
Lenoir spoke of the transformations
that took place last year in the
"international bioethical landscape",
referring to advances in French
legislation and the work of
international organizations including
the World Health Organization, the
Council of Europe and the European
Commission. The September 1994
issue of the Unesco Courier ("A Code
for Living: the Ethics of Human
Engineering") was devoted to this
major problem of our time.
THE KOMITAS QUARTET
On 15 November the Komitas
Quartet is giving a concert at Unesco
headquarters in Paris featuring music
by Brahms, Vartan, Schubert and
Komitas. Created in 1 924, the
Quartet has a worldwide reputation.
The concert is one of 14 being given
by the Quartet on a tour through
France, Germany and Switzerland to
celebrate the 125th anniversary of
the birth of Sogomon Sogomonian,
known as Komitas Vardapet ( 1 869-
1935), the ecclesiastic and composer
after whom the group is named. The
musicians play on instruments made
by Guarnerius (a famous Italian family
of stringed-instruments makers of the
17th and 18th centuries), which lends
a unique resonance to their music.
Their repertoire ranges from the
classical to the modern with a special
emphasis on Armenian music.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY BY FEDERICO MAYOR
programme on
Fthe arid zone, one of
A the first international sei
wL entific co-operation pro
A grammes to be set up
within the United Nations
system, was launched in
Algiers in April 1951. The
programme continued
until 1964 and contributed not only to the mobilization
of the scientific community concerned, but also to the
development of technical assistance programmes and
projects and to the opening and expansion of research,
training and development assistance institutions in
many countries. On the scientific level, it led to the
preparation of the "Map of the World's Arid and Semi-
Arid Zones" and the publication of some thirty volumes
in the "Arid Zone Research" series.
From 1964 onwards work continued within the
framework of a broader programme of "natural
resources research" and the International Hydrolog¬
ical Decade, which focused on the advancement of sci¬
entific knowledge and the preparation of methods
based on specific case-studies.
With the start of the Man and the Biosphere (MAB)
programme in 1971, arid and semi-arid zone activities
took a new turning based on an integrated multidisci-
plinary approach in this instance one in which the
social and the exact sciences were combined.
It was around this time that the ecological crisis
revealed by the drought in the Sahel reached its climax.
This crisis was one of the principal factors behind the con¬
vening of the United Nations Conference on Desertifi¬
cation, which was held in Nairobi in August-September
1977, and with which UNESCO was closely associated.
More recently, UNESCO vigorously supported the ini¬
tiative taken by France, with the support of several
A halt to advancing deserts
other countries, on the occasion of the Arche de la
Défense Summit in 1989, which resulted in the setting
up of the Observatory of the Sahara and Sahel (OSS).
We regarded this venture as a demonstration of concern
for the development problems and efforts to combat
desertification of the twenty countries in and around
the Sahara and as a political gesture designed to
encourage co-operation among and in favour of these
countries.
A COMBAT ON MANY FRONTS
Desertification is a global environmental problem, and
the solutions to it are bound up with those that must
be found in order to create conditions for sustainable
development that will meet the immediate needs of
the population and guarantee the long-term protection
of the environment. Unesco thus favours a global
approach in which the fight against poverty, literacy
work, the management of population dynamics and the
rational use of natural resources are all linked. Only
through an interdisciplinary effort conducted on sev¬
eral fronts by partners working in unison can the
living conditions of disadvantaged populations be last¬
ingly improved.
Efforts to combat desertification must not be con¬
sidered outside the social and human context in which
they are undertaken. They will never be effective if the
people who are to carry them out and benefit from
them are not convinced of the need for them and of the
advantages they will bring. The better informed local
populations are, the more motivated they will be to take
part in this work. Education for all is therefore clearly
essential. Given the requisite knowledge and know-
how, the populations of countries affected by deserti¬
fication will react with greater speed and effectiveness,
making sustainable development more likely to spread
throughout the world. OE
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
\
I
aft»
The monastery ofAlcobaça
From the spirit ofSt. Bernard to the idyll ofPedro and Ines
byJoséAugusto Seabra
36
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
Few monuments of outstanding
universal importance have been
so closely tied to the history of a
people than the Cistercian monastery of
Santa Maria in Alcobaça, a town in central
Portugal. It was founded in 1 153 the year
of the death of St. Bernard, one ofthe great
spiritual leaders of the Cistercian order,
on land granted to the Cistercians by
Afonso Henriques, the first king of Por¬
tugal, in gratitude for their contribution to
the reconquest of his country from the
Moors. The "white monks" so called
because of their white habits, symbolizing
the austerity and purity ofmonastic life
built one of the most beautiful monastic
houses in Europe on this site. It stands as
testimony to the distinguished religious,
cultural, political and social role they
played in the emergence ofa nation which
by virtue of its great maritime discoveries
would become a beacon of Christian civ¬
ilization throughout the world.
The Cistercians had arrived in Portugal
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Above, the monks'
dormitory.
Below right, the façade of
the church of Santa Maria
d'Alcobaça. Its Gothic
portal is flanked by statues
of St. Benedict and St.
Bernard.
ten years earlier, just after the kingdom
had been recognized by Castile. They took
an active part in strengthening the nation,
notably as organizers ofagriculture. These
"agronomist monks" maintained close ties
with the Portuguese sovereigns, who in
return granted them considerable powers,
including the right to create boroughs by
charter in order to clear and populate the
land around them. The monastery soon
began to prosper. In the thirteenth century
Alcobaça was a rich and influential com-
The vast Cistercian
monastery of
Alcobaça, founded
in 12th-century
Portugal, is a
masterpiece of
religious
architecture. Since
1989 it has been
inscribed on
UNESCO's World
Heritage List.
munity whose authority stretched over
vast fertile lands, thirteen boroughs, four
sea ports and two castles.
Later, these powers expanded and con¬
tracted according to the will of the crown.
Until the advent of the liberal monarchy,
the Cistercian order intermittently played
a significant role in Portugal's intellectual
and political life. While pursuing its edu¬
cational activities in the sixteenth cen¬
tury, the monastery became an important
cultural centre, distinguishing itself in
areas such as historiography and the
plastic arts, especially sculpture. It
endowed itselfwith a printing press and a
library that were to become famous.
An ideal of ascetic
simplicity
What makes the Monastery of Santa
Maria unique and justifies its place on
Unesco's World Heritage List is its archi¬
tectural beauty and harmony. Built in the
Gothic style characteristic of the old Cis¬
tercian abbeys, it embodies the ideal of
simplicity and asceticism that St. Bernard
preached, a simplicity that successive
transformations over the centuries have
not modified.
This spiritual vision is etched into the
smallest details of the monastery church,
which has a large, elegant façade com¬
posed of three sections. An early Gothic
portal with seven archivolts resting on
seven columns is flanked by statues of
St. Benedict on the left and St. Bernard on
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Opposite each other in the transept
of the church are the tombs of king
Pedro I and Ines de Castro
(late 14th century). Their tragic love affair
inspired a literary tradition.
38
The two lovers
"In the monastery are the
famous tombs ofKing
Pedro I ofPortugal and
his mistress, Inès de
Castro. The two lovers lie
infacing tombs, as if
ready to look each other
in the eyes again when
they risefrom the dead
on Judgment Day."
the right. Austere and hieratic, the nave
extends beneath a quadrangular vault of
pointed arches to the chancel, whose
sublime vertical upsweep creates an
impression of simple grandeur. The
transept, also under a ribbed vault, con¬
tains two chapels illuminated by rose win¬
dows and gives the church its symbolic
form of a Latin cross.
From Burgundian art to the
Manueline style
The tombs of the first Portuguese kings,
queens, princes and princesses in the
transept or royal pantheon attest to the
monarchy's attachment to this Cistercian
monastery. The most famous tombs are
those of King Pedro I and Ines de Castro,
whose tragic love affair spawned a literary
tradition stretching from Camoëns and
Velcz de Guevara to Henry de Monther-
lant's La Reine Morte. The two lovers lie
in facing tombs as if ready to look each
other in the eyes again when they rise from
the dead on Judgment Day. Ines, whom
Prince Pedro had secretly married, was
murdered in Coimbra in 1355 on the
orders of the prince's father, KingAfonso IV
When Pedro succeeded to the throne, he
had the remains of his beloved solemnly
brought to Alcobaça and ordered her mur¬
derers to be executed. Their ill-fated union
is depicted on the friezes that adorn the
sides of the tall sarcophagi in which they
lie, watched over by angels. Combining
secular and religious motifs, the decorative
carving is of a rare beauty.
In the sixteenth century, a sacristy in
the Manueline style was added to the
church, together with chapels decorated
with a profusion of sculptures. The most
famous chapel, that dedicated to "The
Death of St. Bernard", is considered to be
one of the finest works of the Alcobaça
sculptors. Several other buildings have
been added at different times to the original
Burgundian framework of the monastery.
Among them are the cloister ofDom Dinis,
the chapter-house, the dormitory, the
monks' hall, the kings' hall decorated with
azulejo panels, the refectory, and an eigh¬
teenth-century kitchen with a monumental
chimney and great basin.
But the entire complex preserves an
austerity and simplicity of which St.
Bernard would have approved. The
monastery ofAlcobaça remains the same
masterpiece of Gothic Cistercian art that
has impressed so many historians and vis¬
itors, including the English writer and trav¬
eller William Beckford, who penned unfor¬
gettable pages about it. And it still bears the
indelible imprint of a people whose genius
"gave new worlds to the world."
JOSÉ AUGUSTO SEABRA
is a Portuguese poet and essayist who was formerly
his country's ambassador to Unesco and is now a
member of the Organization's Executive Board. He is
the author of several volumes of poetry, essays and
criticism, including Fernando Pessoa ou le
Poétodrame (José Corti, Paris, 1988), and wrote the
preface to the bilingual (French-Portuguese) edition
of Pessoa's important work, Mensagem (José
Corti/UNESco, Unesco Collection of Representative
Works, Paris, 1988).
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
gl ew gl §
Literacy:
reach th
lew.
low
I Since International LiteracyYear
I in 1990, many things have hap¬
pened in the world of education. The
Declaration adopted in that year at
the conclusion of the World Confer¬
ence on Education for All held at Jom¬
tien (Thailand) to strengthen adult
education, promote universal primary
education and limit demographic
growth to cite just the main goals
has not gone unheeded. The World
Bank has doubled its lending to basic
education in the last three years,
Unesco has doubled its resources for
literacy and primary education since
1990, and the United Nations Devel¬
opment Programme (UNDP) doubled
its expenditure on basic education
between 1991 and 1992. Aid from
donor agencies has also increased.
Encouraging results have been
reported from Bangladesh, Egypt and
India, which alone account for a third
of the world's illiterate. After the Jom¬
tien Conference, Mauritius drew up a
Master Plan for Education which has
become a model for small island states.
But much still remains to be done
for some 948 million illiterate adults
and for the children 20 per cent ofall
children worldwide who are not
enrolled in school. And there are still
plenty ofproblems for those children
who are in school. In Africa south of
the Sahara, for example, it is not
exceptional to find classes with over
one hundred pupils, only a handful
ofwhom have desks and seats. In Latin
America and the Caribbean, where
school enrolment rates are rising,
barely half the pupils finish primary
school. Failure is inevitable when a
teacher has to work with six different
age groups at once and when children
live in conditions that make it diffi¬
cult ifnot impossible for them to learn
their lessons. No wonder they turn
their back on school and go out to try
to earn a living.
When it comes to the quality of
teaching, problems are not confined
to the Third World. A recent survey
carried out by the U.S. Department
of Education revealed that some 47
Sacred music of the
world
From 8 to 15 October, the historic
Moroccan city of Fez hosted the first fes¬
tival of the world's sacred music. The
aim of the festival was to encourage con¬
tact between major cultural and spiritual
traditions. The organizers adopted an orig¬
inal, pluridisciplinary approach the con¬
certs were accompanied by film shows
and exhibitions.
Aid for refugee children
Since 1981, "Enfants réfugiés du monde",
a French association that works with a
number of international organizations
including the Office of the United Nations
High Commissioner for Refugees, the
United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF),
the United Nations Relief and Works
Administration (UNRWA) and UNESCO,
has been helping child victims of war, vio¬
lence and exile. Its teams of doctors,
educators, relief workers and technicians
set up short- and long-term programmes
on behalf of young west Saharans, Pales¬
tinians, Bosnians, Brazilians, Mexicans,
Salvadorians, Guatemalans, Belizeans
and Lebanese. The children are provided
with food and material aid, medical care,
schooling and hospitality in crèches and
leisure centres.
For further information,
contact Enfants réfugiés du monde,
34 rue Gaston-Lauriau,
93100 Montreuil, France.
Tel: (33 1) 48 59 60 29;
Fax: (33 1) 48 59 64 88.
per cent of America's 191 million
adults have reading, writing and math¬
ematical skills so limited that they
cannot function effectively in the
workplace. Young adults (21 to 25
years old) showed literacy skills up to
14 per cent lower than those in the
same age group who took part in a
similar survey in 1985.
ONE POSSIBLE ANSWER:
NON-FORMAL EDUCATION
Because of deficiencies in "official"
schools, new "non-formal" pro¬
grammes, so called because they are
outside state-run school systems, have
been launched in many parts of the wSf
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
iew. . . global view
world. Taking advantage of decen¬
tralizing trends in education, they are
intended to fill the gaps of formal edu¬
cation. They have many advantages.
Lessons are adapted to local condi¬
tions and needs, timetables are flex¬
ible, modern teaching methods are
used and community participation is
encouraged.
In Bangladesh, to take one exam¬
ple, a non-governmental organization
called Saptagram Nari Swanivar
Parishad (The Seven Villages Women's
Self-Reliance Movement), now serving
900 villages, has designed a special
40
Africa's quest for
quality of life
The Amadou Hampâté Bâ Centre for Devel¬
opment and the Quality of Life recently
opened in Bamako. The Centre is named
for the great Malian writer who for 50
years collected and transcribed African
songs, tales and myths in order to retrace
the continent's history. It seeks to give
Africans an opportunity to work out their
future and to find solutions to their devel¬
opment problems by referring to their
own traditions as well as using the
resources of the modern world. Among
those participating in the work of the
new Centre are artists, bearers of tradi¬
tional knowledge, specialists in old and
new forms of communication, support
staff from the Malian administration and
members of community associations.
Further information
may be obtained from:
MISSIRAI, Rue 20x25, Bamako, Mali.
Tel and fax: (223) 22 30 82.
course for women. Taught by local
instructors, literacy and arithmetic
lessons are tailored to the require¬
ments of daily life. Women who were
once threatened with punishment,
even expulsion from their villages, if
they did anything but domestic
chores, now work the land or work in
factories and market their products
themselves. The immediate result of
literacy here has been the affirmation
ofwomen's identity.
In Rajasthan, a 7-million-dollar pro¬
gramme co -financed by Sweden's
International DevelopmentAuthority
and the Indian government, is offering
villagers a wide range of educational
possibilities, from popular theatre to
the electronic media. In Maharashtra
the PROPEL project (Promoting Pri¬
mary and Elementary Education) is
aimed at the 3,000 girls excluded from
official primary education. They learn
how to do book-keeping, read the
newspapers and become independent.
On the other side of the world
Mexico has revolutionized its educa¬
tional system, by decentralizing it,
increasing its budget by 86 per cent
and spending $100 million to improve
pre-school education in ten of its
poorest states.
Brazil is also looking for solutions to
the problems of its eight million chil¬
dren forced into work, crime or prosti¬
tution. The PRONAICA programme,
one of the major components of the
country's ten-year plan to promote
education for all, completely supports
children from underprivileged social
backgrounds while remaining open to
their families.
With support from UNICEF, the
The first world
conference on special
education
From 7 to 14 June, the representatives of
several United Nations agencies and spe¬
cialists and educators from some 60 coun¬
tries met in Salamanca (Spain) to study
ways of improving special education. This
form of education is not only intended for
physically handicapped children but for
those who experience various forms of
learning difficulty. The distinction between
institutions for so-called "normal" chil¬
dren and those for "handicapped" chil¬
dren is now regarded as an obstacle to the
social integration of these children. Spe¬
cial education thus needs to be rethought
and readapted. The Salamanca Confer¬
ence was an opportunity to exchange
ideas on this subject based on a wide
variety of experience.
World Bank and Unesco, the Escuela
nueva programme undertaken by the
Colombian government is seeking to
adapt education to the needs of rural
life, promote study in small groups and
provide each school with a library.
SOURCES:
«- EducationforAll: Status and Trends,
Unesco, 1993. A report published by the
International Consultative Forum on
Education for All.
* EFA 2000, quarterly information
bulletin published by Unesco for the
Secretariat of the International
Consultative Forum on Education for All.
For further information please contact
the Secretariat of the Forum on Education
for All, Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75352
Paris 07 SP, France. Tel: (33-1) 4568-0890,
Fax: (33-1) 4065-9406.
EducationforAll Making it Work,
published by the Basic Education Division,
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP,
France.27.9.94
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
GREENW
RED ALERT FOR THE
EARTH'S GREEN BELT
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
T
Right, felling trees
in the tropical
forest of the Indian
state of Sikkim in
the eastern
Himalayas.
íí^^ropical forest" is the
common name for what
specialists call "rainforest",
a term coined in 1898 by the
botanist Andreas Schimper to des¬
ignate forests that grow in a per¬
petually humid environment,
receiving more than 2,000 millime¬
tres of rain per year. In these condi¬
tions trees with smooth trunks can
grow to more than sixty metres high.
Their tops join together in what is
known as the canopy, a roof of thick
vegetation that keeps out the light.
Like a scarf girdling the equator,
rainforests cover about 9.5 million
square kilometres. The largest single
tropical forest zone is in South
America. Only five million square
kilometres ofrainforest now exist in
tropical Asia and central Africa. A
report published by Unesco in 1991
reveals that Côte d'Ivoire has lost 75
per cent of its forest since 1960, and
Ghana 80 per cent. In 25 years the
Philippines have lost 15 out of 16
million hectares. By the year 2000
the forests ofViet Nam may well be
no more than a fond memory. As
British ecologist Edward Goldsmith
noted in his Report on PlanetEarth,
published in 1990, the Food andAgri¬
culture Organization of the United
Nations (FAO) estimated in the early
1980s that 100,000 square kilome¬
tres ofrain forest were being lost each
year. TheAmerican Academy ofSci¬
ences was far more pessimistic,
deploring the loss of twice that area.
The situation in Brazil seems to sup¬
port the Academy's claim, since
Brazil lost 48,000 square kilometres in
1988 alone.
Lowland forests, by far the
biggest and the most easily acces¬
sible, have suffered most from
human exploitation. Although less
developed because of lower tem¬
peratures, rainfall variability and
poorer soil, highland forests still
play a very important role in pre¬
venting soil erosion and lowland
flooding. Mangroves are a kind of
rainforest growing in the salt-water
and silt-rich coastal regions and
along the banks of rivers flowing
through forests. The mangrove
forests in the Sundarbans region of
the Ganges delta are the world's
largest.
WHO IS TO BLAME?
Although they cover only 7 per cent
of the earth's surface, rainforests are
the home of more than half of the
planet's plant species. With massive
media support, international orga¬
nizations are rightly insisting on the
need to preserve biodiversity, which
is threatened from all sides, most
notably by competition from agri¬
culture. Again according to FAO,
some 250 million farmers live in rain¬
forests around the world. In search of
land for crop-growing and livestock-
raising, they occupy forest areas
owned by the state, which is often
unable to control access to it. These
farmers have no recognized right to
the areas they occupy. Alain Karsenty
and Henri-FélixMaître ofthe forestry
department of France's Centre for
International Co-operation in Agro¬
nomic Research for Development
(CIRAD) in a report to the Xlth Direc¬
torate of the Commission of the
European Communities published
in 1993 stress that "recognition of
property rights (not necessarily in
the Western sense of the term 'prop¬
erty') for local communities is one of
the necessary (but not sufficient)
conditions for joint management of
the forest with those who live in it."
Peoples who have lived for a long
period in these zones are well
adapted to their environment, but
this is not the case with the new
arrivals who grow cash crops such
as cocoa and coffee. They follow the
roads and trails gouged out by the
loggers, thereby infiltrating the
dense forest where, mainly by using
fire, they create "frontiers" which
push back the forest. "This inter¬
relationship between exploitation
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
THE DIMINISHING OZONE
LAYER
The World Meteorological Organiza¬
tion (WMO) reports that in 1 993 low
ozone levels were measured over most
of South America. Ozone concentra¬
tions fell by 7% above Sao Paulo and by
3 to 4% above Rio de Janeiro. In March
and April 1994 the depletion of the
ozone layer above Europe, Siberia and
the adjacent polar-ocean areas was
more than 1 0% below long-term mean
values.
FUEL FOR KANGWANE'S
FIRES
An American reader, Suzy Lieben¬
berg, former co-ordinator of Ecolink's
environmental community develop¬
ment programme, has written to tell
us about an interesting project in the
eastern Transvaal lowveld of South
Africa, where members of the rural
community of Kangwane are growing
Leucaena trees around their homes
and in their vegetable gardens. The
species grows quickly and produces
many stems from ground level rather
than a single trunk. This makes it ideal
for coppicing, which involves cutting
a few stems from each tree annually,
thus ensuring renewable supplies of
wood. Tree seedlings are provided at
a reasonable cost to the villagers and
are planted to act as windbreaks and
to provide shade and slow down
evaporation in vegetable gardens. Leu¬
caena is a legume, and its root nodules
contain bacteria that extract nitrogen
from the atmosphere and improve
soil fertility by producing nitrates.
Community members are encour¬
aged to plant 52 seedlings because in
a 3-to-5-year period, 52 trees would
supply enough fuel for a year. It also
relieves women of having to carry
heavy loads for great distances.
ON THE SCENT OF THE
MUSK DEER
The musk deer (Moschus moschiferus),
a small hornless ruminant that lives in
mountainous regions of Central Asia,
China, eastern Korea and Siberia, is
out of luck. The musk gland of the
male is coveted both by Asian medi¬
cine and the Western perfume
industry. Consisting of sexual hor¬
mones, cholesterol and a waxy sub¬
stance, musk gives out a strong odour.
Although musk can be collected from
farm-reared specimens without killing
the animal, as is done in China,
poachers do not hesitate to defy mea¬
sures to protect the musk deer.
According to World Wide Fund for
and agricultural colonization," says
Alain Karsenty, "makes it difficult
to apportion the responsibility
borne by each activity in deforesta¬
tion processes."
Edward Goldsmith has no time
for those who condemn farmers for
clearing land by fire, for this process
has always been used, even in
Europe. Its disadvantages become
apparent when the population
grows and the land is not left fallow
for long enough, thus preventing
the forest from regenerating itself
between two burnings.
Crops are greedy devourers of
forest. In Ethiopia vast plantations
have replaced trees: 60 per cent of
the land is now given over to cotton-
growing and 22 per cent to sugar
cane. CentralAmerica has seen two-
thirds of its forests sacrificed to live¬
stock-raising. Numerous devel¬
oping countries that once exported
timber Nigeria, for example, but
above all the Philippines, once a
major exporter now import it. Of
the last thirty exporters in the Third
World today, only ten will still be
exporting by the end of the century.
Another factor in deforestation is
the timber industry. Until now Suri¬
name on South America's north¬
eastern coast has been 90 per cent
covered by virgin rainforest. But the
government has just granted a con¬
cession of 150,000 hectares to an
Indonesian logging company and
is considering throwing in two mil¬
lion hectares more. Ernie Brunings,
a member of Suriname's National
Assembly, was quoted by Time mag¬
azine as saying bluntly, "We cannot
have these riches and keep them
for their beauty ifwe have children
dying of hunger, as we have here."
This is the crux of the matter. The
logging industry creates jobs, and
however low the wages may be, they
provide a basic minimum.
LAND-HUNGRY FARMERS
Sustainable management of rain¬
forests on a planetary scale is essen¬
tial. This is what the United Nations
Environment Programme (UNEP),
the World Bank and the World
Resources Institute (WRI) are trying
to achieve via an ongoing process
known as the Tropical Forestry
Action Plan (TFAP). This is not a
new plan but it is still relevant,
although there has been some crit¬
icism that state authorities and
sources of finance have a bigger say
in it than the populations directly
concerned.
"Is it possible," Alain Karsenty
wonders, "both to preserve vast
multifunctional forest ecosystems
(protectors of biodiversity, homes
to local communities, bulwarks
against erosion and regulators of
climate) and to allow logging activ¬
ities on an industrial scale?" He goes
on to ask, "How can we reconcile a
business rationale that thinks
largely in the short term with nat¬
ural forest regeneration, a process
that extends over dozens ofyears?"
Forest space is in high demand.
Not only by logging companies
but once the loggers have pulled
out by large-scale livestock-raisers
and cacao and rubber planters, who
are always ready to clear the land.
Forms of exploitation vary from
region to region. In Africa, where
highly-prized wood like mahogany
is found and logging is very selec¬
tive, only one tree per hectare is
felled on average. This may not be
much, but to reach logging sites,
trails have to be cut, sometimes as
much as one hundred kilometres
long, and this opens the way to
land-hungry farmers. In tropical
America, the opposite happens. The
farmers go in first and are followed
by loggers. Deforestation problems
in southeast Asia result from inten¬
sive, often devastating, clear-cut¬
ting. The pockets of remaining
forest are vulnerable to fires, as has
been seen in Borneo.
SUSTAINABLE POSSIBILITIES
Several proposals for preserving the
rainforest have been put forward.
One is to limit the time period of
concessions granted to logging com-
panies and making their renewal
dependent on "good behaviour".
Logging companies might aiso be
obliged by states to build on-site saw
Egrets in the
mangroves of
Florida (U.S.A.).
FRANCE
BEQUETTE
is a Franco-
American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
questions. Since
1985 she has
been associated
with the
WANAD-Unesco
training
programmefor
African news
agency
journalists.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
mills, as is done in Cameroon, to
prevent them from clearing out once
they have cut down all the valuable
trees. The value of concessions could
also be reassssed by taking account
of their true commercial value and
granting them on a competitive
basis. Skid trails must also be laid
down, for, according to the World
Bank, from 15 to 35 per cent of the
damage to forests is caused by trac¬
tors foraging randomly in search of
felled trees. Felling techniques could
also be improved so that falling trees
cause less damage to their neigh¬
bours. If their operating costs could
be brought down and their safety
ensured for both men and forest,
helicopters and blimps could even¬
tually lift timber vertically out of the
forest.
The preservation of the rain¬
forest depends above all on the
political determination of states.
Either states tolerate tree-felling
and impose taxes on it, or they
define regulations for using and
managing the forests that interna¬
tional organizations like the FAO
and the World Bank are prepared
to support.
Some states, such as Indonesia,
prohibit the exporting ofunprocessed
wood. In the process of industrial¬
izing, they have sought to add value
to their timber and create jobs. Is
this a solution? In Indonesia there
are 500,000 jobs in plywood mills
and about three million jobs in the
wood industry overall. To function,
the industry requires 50 million m3
of unprocessed wood per year, but
the country can no longer supply
this amount. Wood must be
obtained at any price thus encour¬
aging illicit practices or the mills
will have to be closed down, which
is politically impossible.
German, Dutch and American
ecologists have proposed that the
developed countries should boy¬
cott tropical wood unless it carries
Slash-and-burn
farming, or milpa,
in Mexico. In this
very ancient
system, the
vegetation that
grows during long
fallow periods is
destroyed by
burning.
The luxuriant
Zimbabwe forest
near the Victoria
Falls.
the "green label" awarded to wood
from forests that are exploited sus-
tainably. Even this plan is not
without drawbacks. What is to pre¬
vent timber companies from
reaping maximum profits before
the restriction becomes universal? It
might also speed up the conversion
of forests into huge cacao and coffee
farms that are supposedly more
profitable. Or states may simply
cease to manage and develop their
forests, inthebelieftheywillnotbe
able to make money out of them.
Preservation and exploitation
are not incompatible. In the tropics
as in Europe, a forest that is not
taken care of is a dying forest. But in
managing these renewable natural
resources, we must be satisfied with
reaping the interest without touching
the capital.
FURTHER READING:
* Tropical Forests, People and
Food, Man and the Biosphere
series, Unesco and Parthenon
Publishing Group, 1993.
* The Last Rain Forests, Mark
Collins, IUCN and Mitchell Beasley,
1990.
« Tropical Forest Ecosystems
(Unesco, UNEP and FAO), Unesco,
1979.
« The Disappearing Tropical
Forests, MAB and the International
Hydrological Programme, Unesco,
1991.
«- Etude des modalités
d'exploitation du bois en liaison
avec unegestion durable desforêts
tropicales humides, CIRAD-Forêts,
the Commission of the European
Communities, XI D.G.,1993.
«- Bois etforêts des tropiques, revue
n°240, CIRAD, Nogent-sur-Marne,
Francel994.
Si^OBT.
m
f^lî
mte-l- ffe* 'MRS» $
i
Á¥ '.
1 m ..
1 A ï ffifiKSffifîiffi
WORLD
Nature (WWF) estimates, there are
no more than 1 00,000 musk deer left
in the world.
SHRIMP IN CAGES
Since 1992, France's Research Insti¬
tute for Exploitation of the Sea
(IFREMER) has been co-operating
with Brazil on a pilot project for
farming shrimp in cages. The project
is designed to increase production
and to study the impact of aquaculture
on the environment. In Ecuador,
IFREMER is co-operating with the
National Centre for Aquaculture and
Marine Research (CENAIM) on the
immunology and pathology of shrimp
grown on farms. But while the cage
technique is simple, the high-tech
facilities being used in Ecuador have
been strongly criticized by the British
ecologist Edward Goldsmith on the
grounds that their products are too
expensive for the needy.
FIRE-LOVING FLOWERS
A rare flowering plant, the Peter's
Mountain mallow (lliamna core/), has
made a remarkable comeback thanks
to a prescribed burning programme in
a Nature Conservancy Preserve in
Virginia (U.S.A.). Only four such plants
were known to exist when scientists
discovered a large amount of dor¬
mant but viable seeds surrounding
the plants. The fire-dependent plant
was brought back from the brink of
extinction when over 500 seeds
sprouted after a controlled burn was
conducted in the preserve.
THE GREEN BUSES OF
BRUSSELS
Last March, Belgium's Ministry of
Public Works and Communications
and World Wildlife Fund (WWF) Bel¬
gium launched 20 new buses in Brus¬
sels that run on compressed natural
gas (CNG). Although they cost almost
$30,000 more than diesel buses to
buy, maintenance costs are halved
and a ministry subsidy keeps CNG
prices even with those of diesel fuel.
New York, Toronto and several other
European cities including Utrecht
(Netherlands) and Ravenna (Italy)
already power public transport vehi¬
cles with natural gas. WWF-Belgium
has sent education packs explaining
the link between transportation and
urban pollution to all secondary
schools in Brussels. While the world
waits for a miracle-fuel, CNG remains
the least polluting of all.
u
<
KD
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
the ribald scholar
byAlain Frontier
Thisyear marks the 500th anniversary ofthe birth of
the French writerFrançois Rabelais, hailed by his compatriot
Chateaubriand as "one ofthe nurturinggeniuses ofhumanity".
The earthy, exuberant universe that he created has lost none ofits
liberatingpower.
anniversary
44
Not even the French can get over the idea
that their literature should have spawned so
vast and overwhelming awriter as Rabelais.
They still regard him with a sort of bemused
incredulity.
The little that is known about his life is strange
enough as it is. We know that he was born near
Chinon in western France in the closingyears of the
fifteenth century and that he died in Paris around
1553. We also know that he was a monk. He must
have been an odd kind ofmonk, attracted more by
study than by monastic life, spending his days
devouring books, including some which the arbiters
of the intellectual and moral order of the time
regarded as suspect. Flis reading was not only in
Latin, the language of the clergy and the Church, but
also in Greek, a language dear to adepts of the new
thinking, and Hebrew, which made it possible to
read the Bible without having to go through Latin
translations and official commentaries. This rather
unorthodox monk seems to have been protected by
people in high places, where enthusiasm for new
ideas can sometimes be found. After his Greek
books had been confiscated on the orders of the
Sorbonne, he found a haven in a Benedictine
monastery, whose library was more congenial and
whose abbot was more accommodating. Eventually
he was authorized to shed his monk's habit and
was released from his vows.
All through his life, he corresponded and
debated with the leading intellectual lights of the
age, men such as Guillaume Budé, Erasmus and
Thomas More. Very much a man of his time, he
was deeply involved in the current ofrenewal which
ushered in more critical attitudes and a greater
sense of freedom, truth and beauty. He travelled. He
studied medicine at Montpellier, became a famous
doctor and was for several years head of the hospital
in Lyons. It was then that Rabelais, the man of sci¬
ence and culture, became known not for learned
treatises and scholastic works but for his folâtries,
the collections of fantastic and very funny tales
published under the titles of Horribles et épou¬
vantablesfaits et prouesses du très renommé Pan¬
tagruel (\52>2) orthe Vie inestimable du grand Gar¬
gantua, père de Pantagruel (1534). In these stories
erudition rubs shoulders with barefaced humour,
and folly and wisdom are to be found in equal mea¬
sure. Rabelais' characters are giants not only in
size but in wit. Their appetite for fleshmeat and
knowledge is boundless, and so is their thirst for
strong drink! Wise men or lunatics, scholars or
jokers, they spend all their time drinking and have
the uncanny power to provoke the same alcoholic
thirst in everybody they meet.
Even at their most serious, the tales are liable to
cause a great eruption ofbelly laughter. Everything
is good for a laugh Rabelais was never one to
dally over the daintier aspects of language or to
Francois Rabelais
(c.1494-1553). Drawing by an
unknown 16th-century artist.
Gargantua à Paris, an
illustration by the French artist
Albert Robida (1842-1926).
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
"Better to write of
laughter than
tears,
For laughter is
proper to man"
Rabelais
"Gargantua at his great board",
detail from an early-19th-
century engraving based on a
play inspired by Rabelais' work
and performed in the Tuileries
Gardens in Paris.
mince his words. He uses a staggeringly rich vocab¬
ulary, ranging from the recondite to the demotic,
from the most picturesque of evocations to the
crudest slang. Too bad ifchaste ears are offended by
crude jokes or obscene language. Rabelais' laughter
propels his sentences along at a breathtaking pace,
as the sounds collide with one another and set off
reverberations, to the extent that they sometimes
cloak the actual words he uses. The sentences go on
and on, before disappearing in a torrent of enu¬
merations that sweeps away both the words and the
music they make.
Rabelais is a laughing cavalier of philosophy.
This is the problem. What relationship can there be
between this booming laughter and this universal
intelligence? Rabelais was blessed with the mar¬
vellous gift ofbeing able to give expression to values
such as love of freedom, tolerance, thirst for knowl¬
edge, and faith in progress that are so precious and
essential to us. But through this laughter, he also
seems to be taking away with one hand what he
gives with the other. There may therefore be a great
temptation to cut the man in two, to look at the man
of laughter on one side and the man of ideas on the
other; on the one hand the verve of the writer, on the
other the ideas of the philosopher.
Even in the eyes ofhis contemporaries, Rabelais
was more than just a public jester. This can be
clearly seen from the attacks directed at him by
the Sorbonne. A clown would not have been so
unrelentingly pursued. Rabelais made people feel
ill at ease. They could not be indifferent to the crit¬
icism he levelled against the Church and the courts,
against ideas about education, against the insti¬
tutions ofofficial thinking. People could not coun¬
tenance his lack of respect for those whose function
is to be taken seriously.
In reality, the funny, crazy side ofhis books is not
merely an agreeable wrapping for the austere con¬
tent of the message. What Rabelais had to teach us
is that laughter is necessary in the quest for truth.
There is nothing more serious than laughter at
least Rabelais' sort of laughter. It is a weapon to be
used against people who take themselves too seri¬
ously. It makes fissures in the walls ofobscurantism.
It prevents thought from becoming set in certain¬
ties. It is what makes thought possible. Rabelais
always kept his eyes wide open and his ears to the
ground. He listened to all kinds ofvoices, languages,
cultures and worlds. He said, "I want to make sure
that there is no sea or river or fountain whose fish
you do not know. . ., all the birds of the air, all the
trees of the forest, all the blades of grass, all the
metals hidden deep in the bowels of the earth . . .
that there is nothing that you do not know".
There can be no thought without this freedom,
this feeling for movement, and open-mindedness.
The laughter of Rabelais makes them possible.
ALAIN FRONTIER,
a French poet and grammarian,
is the author of several
introductory works to classical
Greek and a dozen volumes of
poetry and fiction. Among his
most recent published works is
La Poésie (Belin publishers,
Paris, 1992).
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
R H
Marie Curie, the French physicist of
Polish origin who shared the Nobel
PrizeforPhysics in 1903 and won the
Prizefor Chemistry in 1911, was one
ofthe mostpopular members ofthe
scientific community ofher day.
Always a proponent ofinternational
intellectual co-operation, she was
one ofthe 12 members ofthefirst
committee set upfor this purpose by
the League ofNations, and until her
death played an active role in the
work ofthe International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation (IIIC).
Wien she chaired the IIIC
symposium on the Future ofCulture,
held in Madridfrom 3-7May 1933,
she spoke on all the topics that were
discussedthe definition ofculture,
the crisis ofculture and thefuture of
culture. Salient extractsfrom her
address are given below.
Marie Curie
The spirit ofadventure
Text selected and presented
by Edgardo Canton
46
Before throwing the discussion
open, I think it may be useful if
I summarize the contributions
of previous speakers and add a few
thoughts ofmy own.
We agree that there is a national ele¬
ment at the root of every culture; and we
also agree on the fundamental point
that a universal culture needs to be
superimposed on every national cul¬
ture, and that the development of the
individual is a duty in every national
and international culture.
What matters and here again we
are all in agreement is not so much
knowing how to strike a balance
between national and universal culture
as clearly recognizing the need to elim¬
inate whatever makes for hostility and
antagonism and to prefer co-operation
and reconciliation.
By way of example perhaps I may
quote the case of laboratories, since that
is what I know most about. A big scien¬
tific laboratory is an example of uni¬
versal culture sustained by input from
national cultures: mutual respect for
work done ensures a favourable envi¬
ronment for co-operation. It is a source
of great satisfaction to find that the
sharing of a common task is conducive
in the workers to a state of mind
favourable to universal culture.
Like some members of the Com¬
mittee, I am not convinced that a state of
crisis is particularly abnormal. It may
be a normal state, in the sense that evo¬
lution takes place not at an even pace
but through an alternation of what we
may call crises and what we may call
bursts ofspeed. This is an example of the
discontinuity found everywhere in the
field of science, and I believe it is the
natural way things work. If at the
moment we have an unusually serious
crisis, it is because of the dreadful cir¬
cumstances that have recently shaken
Europe, and also no doubt because of
the rapid pace of industrial and tech¬
nological development on which some
of us have insisted.
Features of the crisis include the spe¬
cialization and standardization that
rightly perturb the intellectual world.
Some of you hold that it is possible to
react against specialization, and that
the sciences can be better presented
and better taught.
I am one of those who believe that
science is a thing of great beauty. A sci¬
entist in his laboratory is not merely a
technician: he is also a child faced with
natural phenomena that impress him in
the same way as a fairy story. We must
have a way ofcommunicating this feeling
to outsiders; we must not let it be sup- .
posed that all scientific advance boils
down to a matter ofmachinery and appa¬
ratus not that machinery and appa¬
ratus do not also have a beauty of their
own. Like Professor Haldane, I believe
that we can remedy this state of affairs.
CURIOSITY AND THE SPIRIT OF
ADVENTURE
I also do not think that the spirit ofadven¬
ture is likely to die out in the world. The
one vital thing I see as I look around me
is the spirit ofadventure: it seems inerad¬
icable, and is related to curiosity. I am
inclined to think that it is a primitive
human instinct, for I cannot see how
humanity could have survived without it,
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
E
any more than a person could survive
with absolutely no memory. Curiosity
and the spirit ofadventure have certainly
not died out. What about the people who
go up in aircraft and cross the Atlantic?
There are plenty ofother examples: if I do
not quote them it is for lack of time. The
spirit ofadventure is found in children of
all ages and at all levels.
That leaves the problem of tiredness
and overdoing it. That is a real source of
danger. People who do intellectual work
do not have time to think about the
problems that crop up. They are obliged
to adopt at high speed ideas that can
only be assimilated gradually. Technical
advances force on us ways of living and
working that are perhaps beyond the
capacity of the human organism.
Thinking is a form of activity that
requires time. It is not certain that when
we considerably accelerate the speed
of such a phenomenon the human
organism can adapt to the change. If
experience showed that some of what
modern civilization demands of us is
actually dangerous, and cannot be made
harmless by reasonable adjustment,
then perhaps we ought to give up some
of the efforts that we ask of our organs
and are helping to destroy them. That is
a suggestion for the biologists: it is not
for me to judge.
As regards lack of drive and initia¬
tive, I am not pessimistic. Drive and
enterprise are, I believe, the attributes of
every person in good physical and
mental health, so I do not think they
will die out provided that the species
can resist physical decadence. The spirit
of enterprise doubtless needs to be
channelled and given worthwhile tasks
to perform, otherwise it will operate in
areas where it may have ill-effects.
Marie Curie (1867-1934)
in her laboratory.
It is hard to forecast the future. As
many ofus here have said, we can make
wishes, put forward solutions, and seek
to make dreams come true; but we
cannot say what the results will be. We
cannot, among other things, prevent
natural disasters, which can destroy
what we have achieved.
But just because we have this spirit of
enterprise, which we cannot do without,
we behave as though the future
belonged to us. This is part of the instinct
of self-preservation, and also of our
feeling of racial solidarity, which does for
us what our inner life does, namely gives
us responsibilities towards future gen¬
erations.
A UNIVERSAL GOAL
How are we to express our ambitions,
the goal of our dreams? This is a big
problem, which I shall not tackle for the
moment. Mr. Jules Romains has told us
that we must go to the limits of the capa¬
bilities of the human species. We cannot
imagine what these limits may be,
because we have no idea what the spirit
of invention and initiative, which shows
itself so strongly, has in store for us. But
ifwe agree to go to the limits, that is all
we can do. So I am happy to accept this
expression.
One thing we can do is to state here
and now the conditions in which dreams
can become possible and not be inex¬
orably destroyed by events. We can rec¬
ognize that our dream of the future
requires the synthesis of national cul¬
tures, and the subordination of largely
political differences to a universal aim,
that of culture and communication.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
LISTENING
A trained pianist
and actress,
Catherine
Français has
worked with
children for many
years and has
studied Tai-Chi
and other
oriental
I disciplines. She
teaches
musicians and
actors to look
further than
the written
word or musical score in order to
discover their own rhythms and, through
these, freedom of expression and their own
inner selves. The voice is the key element in
this type of training.
C You are specifically interested in the fun¬
damental role played by music and the human
voice in all religions.
very old sacred traditions, man is regarded as the
temple of the divine. At the same time, mantras,
prayers, sacred sounds, poems and chants have a
physical function: they facilitate the movement of the
diaphragm, and through their resonance and rhythm
awaken the harmonics of the body. The body, especially
the voice, is designed as a musical instrument. We
could, for instance, make an analogy with the violin. The
violin has different shapes, with curves that are
rounded, or more or less angular. If the "sound post",
the piece of wood that connects the back of the violin
to its front and maintains the correct distance between
them, is moved, the shape of the curves is modified
and the sound of the instrument changes, since the
vibratory phenomenon is a balance between form,
contained in the material, and the intangible which cir¬
culates inside the instrument.
The same is true of the human body: the
diaphragm which stretches and amplifies the
breathing through its constant spring-like motion,
corresponds in a way to the sound post of the violin.
It's the diaphragm that helps the body maintain its
proportions.
I* Since the inner world and the outer world
are inseparable, physical and mental changes
can bring about changes in the voice. Con¬
versely, a more judicious use of the voice should
help to restore harmony between the self and
the outer world when it has been disturbed.
in the Ancient World doctors used the voice and
sound in general to restore corporal harmony, and
Seeking the inner voice
Catherine Françaix talks to Isabelle Leymarie
incantatory magic would balance natural forces
through the power of sound. Working on the voice can
sometimes remove certain physiological or psycho¬
logical blocks. It restores tone to the organs, and,
since the voice is our essential tool of communication
with plants, animals, man and the gods, it encourages
receptivity to the outside world.
!i What steps can one take to improve one's
voice?
of all it is useful to bear in mind that the
voice is both subtle and adaptable. It is constantly
changing, at every stage in life and even over longer
periods of time. For instance, listening to voice
recordings of the 1920s and 1930s, one is struck by
the difference in colour between those voices and
those of today.
Training the voice means improving one's
breathing, sometimes by working on the form through
physical exercise, and sometimes by working on the
content, or internal energy (the Chinese chi, the
Japanese ki, and the Indian prana) and the channels
by which it circulates. One basic exercise consists in
warming up the diaphragm so as to be able to hear
the fullness, the elasticity of sound. Another consists
in awakening the face muscles. When we grow up, we
stop using some of our face muscles and lose some
of our expressiveness as a result. The remarkable
actors of commedia deli'arte who create "masks" by
using different face muscles also manage to produce
the right colour of voice to match the emotional res¬
onance of the mask. The basic mask is the "neutral"
one, where the face is relaxed and welcomes,
receives, imbues itself with sensations. In vibratory
terms, this corresponds to the position of non-
oscillation between two emissions of sound.
It is also necessary to discover the body's points
of equilibrium (without which the body establishes
compensatory mechanisms), its centre of gravity. This
awareness of the centre of gravity, on which certain Ori¬
ental disciplines lay great emphasis, provides a plea¬
surable feeling of stretching. Voice production is linked
to both the balance and the suppleness of the body.
The word "tone" comes from the Greek "tonos", which
means "tone", "tonus", "tonic", "ligament", "musical
mode" and "tone of voice". It is also necessary to
master the motor impulses which produce sound.
This implies harmony between gesture and thought. In
days gone by, everything to do with the intellect was
explained with the aid of metaphors and all that had to
do with the imagination or the divine with the aid of
mathematics and geometry.
', I After this necessary physical preparation,
should one work on elocution?
by seeking the right rhythm. In all languages,
the consonant represents the medium while the
vowel signifies the breath. It is the vowel that signi¬
fies the transition from one phoneme to another,
prolonging the impulse of the consonant. To carry out
this transition smoothly, without loss of balance,
one has to find a point of support. The sacred lan¬
guages, notably Hebrew, were conscious of this
notion of balance of speech. If the scansion is mis¬
placed, if we do not accentuate enough, we cannot
get our breath back. This involuntary apnoea brings
with it a break in rhythm and distorts the relationship
with the person to whom we are talking. Here again,
it is the elasticity of the diaphragm that allows you to
control the flow of breath.
¡u Is the lack of genuine communication
between human beings, which seems to be
exacerbated by the modern world, linked to the
loss of this rhythm and balance of speech?
art, certainly. It has been noted that in many lan¬
guages, except in regional speech which has remained
highly colourful, there is a loss of expressiveness, due
both to lack of time and to a fear of human relation¬
ships. We adults no longer live in the words we utter,
the body no longer takes part, while children on the
other hand, in a spontaneous way, physically live
out what they say. If we do not take the time either
to speak correctly or to listen to others, the breath no
longer circulates. We suffocate and we smother
those with whom we speak. This communication
problem also brings about a flattening of the melodic
curve of the language and an impoverishment of the
vocabulary.
\ In order to use one's voice correctly is it
necessary to know how to listen?
And listening can be purposeful or
receptive. In the second case, one allows oneself to
be bathed by the resonance, the emotional climate
evoked by the sound, thereby gaining access to
one's inner world. "Sentiré" in Italian means both to
listen and to hear. Polyphonic singing, in which one
hears one's own voice and the voice of others without
losing one's self, is a marvellous way of developing
the ability to listen and of learning to establish dia¬
logue. Bringing together East and West, it does away
with the need for long journeys in quest of exotic
teachings, because it helps us find what we are
seeking within ourselves.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-American musicologist,
is the author of La Salsa et le Latin Jazz (PUF, Paris,
1993). She is currently working on a study of black
music in Latin America and the Caribbean.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
^ LATENT MACHISMO
Congratulations on the high quality of
your magazine and your choice of
themes that are always interesting and
well documented. Sometimes, however,
I am annoyed by a latent macho atti¬
tude that flies in the face of Unesco's
humanistic message.
My annoyance bubbled over into
anger when in your March 1994 issue
on human rights, Manfred Nowak in an
article entitled "States ofbondage" (page
28) acknowledged that certain serious
forms ofcorporal punishment approved
by Islamic law constitute "cruel and
inhuman punishment or even torture"
but then went on to say that, "whether
states under present international law
are under a positive obligation to pro¬
hibit female circumcision is more diffi¬
cult to judge". He admitted that "these
traditional practices inflict severe phys¬
ical and mental pain on the girls and
women concerned", but limited him¬
self to exhorting the offending govern¬
ments to "at least try to prevent them by
educational and similar means". And to
feminists around the world who
denounce circumcision of young girls
"as a form of torture prohibited under
international law", the author merely
says that "manyAfricans view the prac¬
tice as an expression of their traditional
culture".
This so-called cultural practice has
never counted among its free and willing
supporters the majority 52 per cent
of the people concerned, i.e. women.
This act of aggression, which deprives
women of their inalienable right to
sexual pleasure, is a violation of their
lives and the lives of their children, and
condemns them to pain and humilia¬
tion, is no better, morally speaking, than
castrating young singers, deforming the
feet ofyoung Chinese women, the elim¬
ination of female foetuses in China and
India, the practice of suttee in India, the
immolation ofvirgins among the Mayas,
slavery, genocide, raping women in
cities and in times of war and many
other violent acts committed in the
name of God and good conscience. The
most immediately dissuasive measure
would be for the international commu¬
nity to show that it is no longer willing to
tolerate the torture ofwomen and other
vulnerable elements of society in this
way.
Maya Khankhoje
Montreal (Canada)
^ MONEY AND SPORT
I am interested in the traditional sports
and games of the Mediterranean region
and have been doing some research on
sport-related subjects. I came across
your highly interesting and useful pub¬
lication and was captivated by your
issues of May, 1991 ("People at Play")
and December, 1992 ("The Competitive
World of Sport").
What disturbs me most is the cur¬
rent trend to ignore traditional sports
and games in favour of popular spec¬
tator sports, namely, soccer, tennis and
cycling. It is no secret, in fact, that these
three disciplines are those most exten¬
sively covered by the media in Europe.
The ethical values associated with sport
are being lost and replaced by the desire
for success at any cost. Economic factors
have invaded sport and the educational
function that sport can play is being, to
say the least, obscured.
Developing countries are increas¬
ingly being lured into encouraging their
youth to practice the popular "western"
sports, hoping that this will ultimately
put them on the world map. This is a
serious danger and must not be ignored.
If it is, there is a risk that mankind will
not only leave behind an impoverished
cultural heritage to posterity but will
also be tempted to see sport as just a
money-making activity.
Stephen Caruana
Tarxien (Malta)
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, back cover, pages 3, 8-9, 9, 1 1
(above), 1 4- 1 5, 1 5, 1 6 (below), 2 1 , 22,
23: P. Perrin © G.L.M.R., Paris. Page
2: © Virginia Ryan Izzo, Edinburgh.
Pages 5, 6: Fabian © Sygma, Paris.
Page 7: Kleinefenn © Sipa, Paris. Page
10 (above): D. Guilloux © Ask
Images, Paris. Page 10 (below):
National Archives of Canada ©
G.L.M.R., Paris. Pages 12, 13:©
Frances Dal Chele, Paris. Page 1 6
(above): © Jacques Ivanoff, Patani.
Page 1 7: © R. Boceo, Geneva. Pages
1 8 (above), 1 9 (above), 24, 3 1 , 4 1 , 43: ©
Charles Lenars, Paris. Pages 18
(below), 1 9 (below): T. Mauger ©
MISS International, Paris. Pages 19
(middle), 20: © R. Jaubert, Geneva.
Pages 25, 26, 27, 28: Brian Moser ©
The Hutchinson Library, London.
Page 29: Sugar © Explorer, Paris.
Page 30 (above): Sistrez © Ask
Images, Paris. Page 30 (below):
F. Varin © Explorer, Paris. Pages 32-
33, 32 (below): Arthus Bertrand ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 35: Unesco-
Ines Forbes. Pages 36, 37: Gerard
Sioen © Rapho, Paris. Page 38: ©
Giraudon, Paris. Page 42: S. Cordier
© Explorer, Paris. Page 44 (above): ©
Jean Loup Charmet, Paris. Page 44
(below): © Jean-Loup Charmet,
Bibliothèque des Arts Décoratifs,
Paris. Page 45: © Jean-Loup
Charmet, Musée Carnavalet, Paris.
Page 47: © Harlingue Viollet, Paris.
Page 48: All Rights Reserved.
Correction: the credit for Frantz
Zéphirin's painting Makandal burned alive
reproduced on page 24 of the October
1 994 issue should have read: © Carte
SEGRETE, Rome. The painting
belongs to the "Afrique en Créations"
collection.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
cinematheque
revue semestrielle d *e s t li é t i cj u e
et d'il i s t o i r e du ci u é m :i
Stroheim
Bataille - Eisenstein
Aldrich
Capra
Parution du numéro 6
10 novembre 1994
Vente en librairie : 135 F
et sur abonnement (2 numéros) : 200 F
Publié par la Cinémathèque française
et YELLOW NOW, avec le concours du
Centre national des lettres et du
Centre national de la cinématographie
et le partenariat de
la Fondation Crédit Lyonnais.
Revue cinémathèque,
29, rue du Cotisée, 75008 Paris.
Tél. : (1)45 53 21 86.
Photogrammes : The Wedding March, E. Von Stroheim, 1926.
BIFI Coll. Cinémathèque française.
SALON
DE LA
TRADUCTION
ET DE
L'INTERPRETATION
CNIT - PARIS LA DEFENSE
17, 18 et 19 Novembre 1994
PARTICIPATION
- Associations Professionnelles françaises et étrangères
- Universités
- Grandes Ecoles
- Entreprises de Traduction
- Ministères
- Donneurs d'ordre
- Editeurs
- Librairies spécialisées
- Concepteurs et distributeurs de logiciels
- Concepteurs et distributeurs de matériel
pour l'interprétation simultanée
COLLOQUES, DEBATS, TABLES RONDES
- Promotion des métiers de traducteur
interprète, terminologue, chercheur.
COMMUNICATIONS
- les marchés et les perspectives nouvelles en traduction
- le rôle des interprètes au sein des conférences internationales
- la créatioh et la gestion des bases terminologiques
- la veille technologique
- problématique de l'indicible dans la traduction littéraire
- les communications internationales entre institutionnels
- la localisation
- rapports entre les entreprises de traduction et les traducteurs
- technologie des laboratoires d'interprétation
- le statut du traducteur, etc ...
SALON PROFESSIONNEL OUVERT AU PUBLIC
Pour réserver voire stand ou recevoir un dossier d'inscription,
contactez Brigitte PONSART
Commissaire General
tel: ( 1 )39 55 38 26 lax: ( 1 )39 66 02 20
52, rue dc Glatigny 78 1 50 Lli CHIiSNAY
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
10e SALON DU LIVRE DE JEUNESSE
M N
Seine Saint-Denis
Conseil Général
26 octobre 1994 - 9 janvier 1995
Le Tabouret foyal, Cameroun
Musée Barbier-Mueller,
Genève
En présentant plus de 1 50 sièges africains, cette exposition donne à
liesse et l'extraordinaire diversité de ce mobilier : tabourets
d'utilisation courante, sièges rituels richement décorés des chefs de
tribu, trônes, appuis-dos, chaises d'influence européenne réservées
aux patriarches, tabourets à cariatides, etc.
Musée des Arts d'Afrique et d'Océanie
Ouvert tous les jours, sauf le mardi, de 1 0h à 1 7h 1 5.
Catalogue de l'exposition .224 pages, 300F, coéd. Preste/RMN
Wuseum
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
/
»
I
THEME OF THE NEXT ISSUE
(DECEMBER 1994):
ALSO FEATURING AN INTERVIEW
WITH THE GERMAN HISTORIAN
WOLF LEPENNIES
]]>
</page>
</document>
