<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="098493eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
u
UNESC®
OURIER
200 YEARS AFTER IT WAS FIRST ABOUSHED
SLAVERY
a crime withoutpunishment
INTERVIEW WITH
YEHUDAH AMICHAI
HERITAGE
THE DANUBE DELTA
ENVIRONMENT
SAVING THE ARAL
2
X
E
z
s
i
U)
I
s
I
O
-1
* * * *
.
I
Ü
u
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
.-
¿á&*
w
^p '*'
ww.iV.4i »v9(
Untitled
1 991 , acrylic on canvas
(108x44 cm)
by Marie-France Michelin
With its blend of
realistic and visionary
elements, this painting
of the Pyrenees in
southwestern France
draws on the long
familiarity of the
artist a schoolteacher
from Brittany with
Oriental art and with
Chinese calligraphy in
particular. It is, as she
says, "a painting where
East and West come
together".
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
IContents
OCTOBER 1994
Cover:
A slave in the Congo
(19th-20th centuries).
200 YEARS AFTER IT WAS FIRST ABOLISHED ^^
SLAVERY fi
a crime without punishment
5 Interview with Yehudah Amichai
34 HERITAGE
The Danube delta
'A place the gods forgot' by Matei Cazacu
39 GREENWATCH
Saving the Aral: the drama of Central
Asia's great lake by France Bequette
32 UNESCO IN ACTION
38 ANNIVERSARY
Hermann von Helmholtz
Physiologist and physicist
by Reinald Schröder
A3 GLOBAL VIEW
The plight of the world's street children
45 BOOK REVIEW
Federico Mayor: keeping ahead of the future
by Edouard J. Maunick
46 ARCHIVES
The future of culture
by Gregorio Marañón
48 LISTENING
Strings down the centuries
by Isabelle Leymarie
49 REFLECTIONS
Elvis the African
3/ New Year's Eve in Jukwaa
by George Darley-Doran
8 Under the whiplash
by Oruno D. Lara
11 Who was responsible?
by Elikia M'Bokolo
A slave's story
A continent of fear
by M 'Baye Gueye
19 The Black Code
by Innocent Futcha
The long road to abolition
by Nelly Schmidt
1794: The French Convention
abolishes slavery
by Lluis Sala-Molins
Forced labour
by George Thullen
The slave route
Interview with Doudou Diène
Fact file: to find out more...
Consultant: Jasmina Sopova
33
Commentary by Federico Mayor
TH& UNESCO
(COURIER
4 7th year
Published monthly in 30
languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION Of UNESCO, LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER I94S
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
HL UNESCO
OURIERt<
47th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31. rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris. France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whttcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: E;-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard j. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala Neville Piyariigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45 68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel : 45.68.45.65
I year: 21 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 21 1. FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual anieles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unísco Courier", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies arc sent to the editor Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompa¬
nied by an International reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the Un£SCO Courier. Photo cap¬
tions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Couner is produced
in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (I) UNESCO, 7 Place de
Fontenoy. 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor.
Michigan 48100 USA: (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc..
I I I West 40th Street, New York. U.SA.; (4) Bell and Howeli Co.. Old Mans¬
field Road. Wooster. Ohio 4469 1 . U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Printed m Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL: CI - OCTOBRE 1994
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courner de I'Unesco
Impression: IMPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL, 2. rue Christophe-Planen
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN Û04I-S278 N: I0-I994-OPI-94-530A
lonth by month
Two hundred years ago revolutionary France abolished slavery, but then
a few years later, as if frightened by its own audacity, re-established
it. This brief spark of humanity would have to be re-ignited many
times in Europe and the Americas during the nineteenth century,
and revolts, bloody repression and civil wars (including the War of
Secession in the United States) would have to be endured before
slavery was at last proscribed on a worldwide basis. But this first vic¬
tory for freedom was far from complete. There arose other forms of con¬
tempt for human beings and other forms of exploitation of forced labour:
the colonization of most non-European societies, fascist and Nazi
repression, and Eastern Europe's descent into totalitarianism.
It took another centurymarked by revolutions, military expeditions
and two world warsbefore the colonial system finally ended, insti¬
tutionalized racism was defeated and the socialist gulag was dissolved.
Does this mean that today at long last respect for human dignity pre¬
vails everywhere? Unfortunately, new inequalities are arising as a result
of physical constraints and threats, because of terror imposed by indi¬
viduals or groups, and the exploitation by some of the weakness of
others. These inequalities exist where States are unable to prevent
them and where medieval customs survive; where the law can be
ignored with impunity, and isolation and secrecy permit terrible
abuses.
What is this dark side of man that has always led him to despise, sub¬
jugate and debase his fellows? Why is it that for thousands of years
inidividuals and in some cases entire peoples have been bought,
sold and treated like beasts? And how is it that such a crime against
humanity has remained unpunished even since the inception of Human
Rights?
There is probably no simple answer to these terrible questions. We
know, however, that we must never cease asking them.
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 10-11 and 42-43. BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
YEHUDAH
AMICHAI
talks to
Edgar Reichmann
Yehudah Amichai, one of Israel's most outstanding
writers, is mainly known as a poet, although he has
also written novels, short stories and radio plays. His
poetry, in which Biblical and contemporary allusions
are blended, is written in simple colloquial language.
In 1982 he was awarded his country's Israel Prize for
Literature for his work as a whole. Among his poetry
collections published in English are Selected Poems
(1986), Great Tranquillity (1983) and Love Poems (1981).
What is theplace ofpoetry in people 's
lives and can poetry contribute to their
happiness?
If you write about things that are hap¬
pening to people you can contribute to
happiness. My poetry helped me over¬
come my first encounter with adult life.
Between the ages of eighteen and twenty-
five, I was in two wars, the Second World
War and the Israeli war of independence. It
took me quite some time to overcome that,
to realize what it meant to start my adult
life with war. I needed my words to achieve
peace with myself.
I don't think that you should lie in
poetry and say that everything is fine and
beautiful. But you can write about things
as they are in a positive way. You can sing
them and by singing, even the bad things
become soothing and can heal you.
I think poetry is a part of the healing of
mankind, like all art. Think of Picasso's
painting Guernica. It is a great outcry
against the cruelty of the Spanish Civil
War. Or consider how a poem can be like
a lullaby. There's a Yiddish lullaby that
goes like this: "Sleep my child, sleep. Father
went to the war. The pound is falling, the
city's on fire, the enemy's coming, the
wolves are howling, but sleep my child,
sleep." The mother mentions all the bad
things in such a way that even the fire and
the enemy become soothing to the child.
She doesn't have to lie and talk about angels
and butterflies.
Your first collection of poems was
"Now and the other days", which the
critics saw as a sign ofradical change in the
Hebrew language and the birth ofa new
school ofHebrewpoetry.
Well, I'm reluctant to describe it as a
"new school". I started writing and I
thought that the generation before me was
not capable of expressing my experience.
It's like when you go to a restaurant and eat
very good food, and then go home and
say, "I really want to make it myself." So I
made it myself.
The change was that I wrote about
things that were on the edge of being for¬
bidden in poetry. Not totally forbidden,
but nearly. Consider Nathan Alterman, a
great writer of the generation before me.
He wrote war poems but he never used
the word "gun". He always spoke about
the sword and the arrow.
Wouldyou say that traditionalHebrew
poetry had a collective feeling and that
you needed to have a more individual
approach in your own poetry?
There is something in that. The genera¬
tion before mine wrote about "we" and
my generation writes more about "I".
Even in a war, when fate brings people
together, even in a very just war like the
Second World War or the Israeli war of
independence, every soldier has questions
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
about whether it's a good war or a bad
war, whether it is against good people or
bad people. Every soldier has his indi¬
vidual experience. In a similar vein, you
don't write love poems about love in gen¬
eral, you write poems about your own
experience in love.
I want to add, though, that I wasn't
making a conscious effort to change
Hebrew poetry. I just wanted to write my
poetry. I say this because there were other
poets of my generation who were very
conscious, very aware of what they were
doing. I think a real artist does what he
does because that's the only way he can
doit.
Why do we needpoetry?
I feel that poetry is the oldest form of lit¬
erary expression. Prayers are poetry and
they have not changed. Language and
images change but the basic things are
human events: love, death, sorrow, despair,
hope. Praise of women, praise of man,
praise of love. Weeping about them. So in
a way, poetry is actually the backbone, the
spine of the human language experience,
from the Bible on through to many other
great poems of the world.
It's the backbone because in a war
you're not going to take a book by Tolstoy
with you. It's too big to carry. But you
can take a few poems, even if they're just in
your head. That's why I think poetry will
survive. Novelists may have to adapt to
the demands of movies or television; they
constantly have to change. But poetry
remains the same.
I once said that poets are like the
infantry, the foot soldiers in an army.
They're out there in the war, all by them¬
selves with a few others. Novelists are
more like generals who sit in shelters plan¬
ning huge operations and don't really get
involved. Of course, literary academicians
are like war historians who write about
past wars because that way they have
nothing to fear from bullets.
Has Hebrew poetry gone through any
important metrical changes? Are you free
to use rhythm?
There's one style which is very strict,
where you have sonnets, couplets, poetry
with rhyme and metre. But you also have
another style, the style of the Bible and of
prayers, which is freer and has a kind of
internal rhythm. I've written in both styles.
I've also written some sixty rubaiyat, a
style of poetry from the Middle Ages that
is widely known through the Rubaiyat of
Omar Khayyam. It's a four-line poem,
very strict, with the same rhyme at the
end. It's like the sonnet in European lan¬
guages. I wrote rubaiyat poems under the
influence of one of our medieval poets,
Judah Halevi. He was one of the great
Jewish poets who lived alongside Muslim
culture in southern Spain until both cul¬
tures were driven out.
Through being translated into twenty
languages your work has reached a vast
number ofpeople.
Yes. That's a kind of compensation.
Because if you had an audience around
"I think poetry will
survive. Novelists may
have to adapt to the
demands of the movies
or television; they
constantly have to
change. But poetry
remains the same."
you in those times it was only fifty, a hun¬
dred, two hundred, four hundred people.
Nowadays poetry has another way of get¬
ting to people and I think it's very impor¬
tant. It's like when you start a fire with
little twigs at the edges. A big wind may
blow up later, but there always has to be a
fire burning. I was asked, when my poetry
was translated, "Do you think that your
poetry loses in translation?" I said, "Yes,
sure, but we lose things all the time. We lose
weight, but that can be a good thing." It's
okay if poetry loses a little something in
order to survive.
How do you explain that yourpoetry,
which is so deeply rooted in yourpersonal
experience and in a particular place and
time, can be understood and appreciated
by very differentpeople?
If you talk about your own life and feel¬
ings, then I think this gets through to other
people. What's happening now, all over
the world, is very interesting. Economically
people have been joining forces, but local
cultures and languages are again becoming
very important. The more a piece of art is
local, the truer it is. To my mind, there is no
such thing as universal art. I think that is
why Esperanto failed to catch on.
You have said that your roots extend
into thepast andpresent ofyour land and
yourpeople and that you never became a
chauvinistic nationalist. What's the dif¬
ference between realpatriotism andxeno¬
phobic nationalism ?
I think that's one of the main problems
of our time. If you love your culture, your
landscape, your climate and your history,
then that's fine. But if patriotism is based on
negating someone else's culture then it's a
bad patriotism. Patriotism also means
speaking out against your own people if
you think they are doing something wrong.
That's an even stronger patriotism. Real
patriotism has to be critical sometimes.
This brings us to the Palestinians	
That's important. We don't live in an
empty world. Only the feeble-minded
think that they're the only people in the
world. We have to see the others, even if we
think they are our adversaries and we think
they did a few things wrong. We have to try
and get them to understand our patrio¬
tism. And we have to understand them
and their patriotism.
Doyou think thatyou andaPalestinian
poet like Mahmoud Darwish could work
together anddo something to solveproblems
between Israelis and Palestinians?
In a way, yes. We are good friends. We
don't see each other very often, but he trans¬
lated a lot of my poems into Arabic and
published them in Syria and Egypt before
the Israel-Egyptian peace treaty. I may differ
with Mahmoud Darwish on certain points
but I regard him as a great poet.
We could do something that in a sense
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
I needed my words
to achieve peace with myself."
goes much deeper than what is done by pol¬
itics or journalism. Poetry is much slower,
but it's far more profound. The basic thing
in Mahmoud's poetry and in my poetry is
that it starts from human beings in their
own place. And that is where people meet.
Do you think the world is destinedfor
conflict, that it's doomed to explode or col¬
lapse?
In each generation people think the
world is going to collapse; it's one of our
basic feelings. My father thought that if
the world wasn't religious everything
would fall down. Some people feel that if
socialism collapses the world will fall apart.
But there are certain things like love that
can keep the world alive.
But now even youngpeople are begin¬
ning to have doubts about the world.
I remember as a fifteen-year-old in
Jerusalem in 1939, when the Second World
War broke out, that my parents and their
friends were fully aware of what was going
to happen. It was a big war, a big danger.
But I wasn't: when you are young you
have a totally different approach. When I
"If you love your
culture, your landscape,
your climate and your
history, then that's fine.
But patriotism also
means speaking out
against your own
people if you think they
are doing something
wrong."
was in my first two wars, I didn't have the
feeling that it was the end of the world. On
the contrary, I had the feeling that we were
fighting for a brave new world.
H Do you think, like many others, that
the great collective ideas of the past have
been shattered?
I'm quite sure that the next century will
find its own way to define itself positively.
After the First World War people thought,
because it was the first big war in which
millions were killed, that there was no
hope for the world. Then we had another
war. But even then mankind went on, even
after the holocaust. I think it was Theodor
Adorno who said that after Auschwitz it
was no longer possible to talk about God.
But people started talking about God again.
This could be foolish optimism, the
optimism of someone saying, "I have sur¬
vived so many wars that the world can't
be too bad." It's a very primitive and naive
optimism. But primitive in a sense that isn't
necessarily bad. It's also the lust for life,
for continuity, for not seeing all the dangers.
If you're always on the lookout for danger,
you stop living and just wait to die.
The developments in the Israeli-Arab
conflict have proved my optimisim to be
right. Without throwing caution to the
winds, there is still hope in our world for
even the most severe conflicts to be solved.
EDGAR REICHMANN is a writer and literary critic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
nder the whiplash
by Oruno D. Lara
Slavery existed in very early times, but it was in the Greek city-state that the
slave became what Aristotle called "apiece ofproperty which is animate"
8
Top, a Roman slave.
Lithograph by an unknown
artist.
Above, "Mandarin of Turan, In
Cochinchina, with his slave
pipe-bearer". Illustration from a
French edition (1804) of
"Journal of the Embassy to
China" by Earl Macartney, the
first British envoy to Peking
(Beijing).
Right, black slaves in Brazil
washing for precious stones
under the threat of the
supervisors' lash. Watercolour
by Carlos Juliao (circa 1775).
Forced labour existed in a variety of forms
throughout Antiquity in the Egypt of
the Pharaohs, the Middle East (Babylon and
Assyria), and Greece and Italy. However, slavery
as an institution, in which the slave became a
commodity or what Aristotle called "a piece of
property which is animate", was first devised by
the Greek city-states.
Slavery is essentially a relationship in which
one person dominates another. It is based on the
power of a master, who imposes his will by force
and threats. The slave system was created and
maintained by violence. Whipping slaves was
not only a means of inflicting punishment on
them but of dominating them, making an impres¬
sion on them and reminding them of their state of
servitude. Slaves were kept apart from one
another. The alternatives before them were "abject
submission", escape or rebellion.
This domination was justified by the "original
alienation" of the slaves and their status as "people
without honour". Stripped of any rights or title,
they no longer had any family history, ancestry
or issue. Completely isolated, they could not
receive or hand down any heritage. In their state
of rootless alienation, they were tools whose
owners could treat them as they saw fit. Masters
had a whole array of physical or symbolic instru¬
ments which they could use to control the bodies
of their slaves.
When did the slave system start to go into
decline, or rather to be replaced?1 In Italy, the first
imperial measures against the breaking-up of
slave families were promulgated in the year 325
of our era. According to some historians, how¬
ever, the ancient form of slavery is considered as
having ended under the reign of Charlemagne.
Even so, the Church at that time was still a con¬
siderable owner of slaves. The Anglo-Saxon the¬
ologian Alcuin, one of Charlemagne's closest
advisers, owned 20,000 slaves in the four abbeys
under his control. Almost 20 per cent of Europe's
population in Charlemagne's time consisted of
slaves. Some forms of medieval slavery continued
to exist from the ninth to the fifteenth centuries
and gradually faded out only when they were
superseded by the African and Asian slave trades.
Exploitation and torture
How many men, women and children left Africa
in the holds of the slave ships? How many
African and Malagasy captives were sold on the
slave markets of the Caribbean and mainland
America? The answer is that they were prob¬
ably tens of millions, but we shall never know the
exact figure because there are no reliable statistics.
In this respect, the stumbling-block historians
have to contend with lies in the conditions and
practices of the trade, both legal and illegal, which
went on from the mid-fifteenth century to the
closing decades of the nineteenth century.
The slaves of Antiquity, like those of modern
times, had to submit to the sexual demands of
their masters. Prostitution was only one feature of
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
	.¿¿^J.¿i**íu,
the relationship. Trimalchio, one of the characters
in the Satyricon of Petronius, the Roman author of
the 1st century A.D., says: "For fourteen years, I
was the light of my master's eyes. There is no
shame in doing what your master orders you to do.
In the meantime, I also kept my mistress happy".
A variety of methods, such as changing slaves'
names, inflicting corporal punishment on them or
torturing them, were used to dehumanize and
degrade them, deprive them of their personality
and make them different from other human
beings, who were not chattels. This was the sole
purpose of the practice whereby all male slaves,
regardless of their age, were called "boy" pais
in Greek, puer in Latin.
Attempts have been made to minimize, and
indeed conceal, the many acts of physical cruelty
meted out on slaves, and to deny the existence of
torture in Greece and Italy. Torture was practised
in Athens, however, and the instruments used
are well-known to specialists. As Demosthenes
noted, freedmen differed from slaves because the
latter had to answer for all their crimes with their
bodies. What we do not know, however, is
whether the slave-owners of Antiquity displayed
the same refinement as the planters of the Amer¬
icas in inflicting cruelty on their slaves. The atroc¬
ities perpetrated by the latter have provided mate¬
rial for a large number of books on the subject and
are borne out by irrefutable eyewitness accounts.
A totalitarian system based on racism
There were two ways of escaping from slavery:
emancipation or flight. Emancipation meant
that the slaves were no longer chattels. In Greece,
they became "metics", resident aliens who were
free but were debarred from discharging polit
ical obligations, whereas in Rome they auto¬
matically acquired Roman citizenship. Their
legal status changed from being that of an object
to that of a person recognised by law. The eman¬
cipated slaves of Antiquity were able to become
absorbed into the mass of the population within
the space of one or two generations. The poet
Horace, whose father was an emancipated slave,
complains in his Satires of having sometimes
been insulted about his origins.
This was by no means the case of the eman¬
cipated slaves of the Caribbean and the Amer¬
icas, for whom the colour of their skin was the
indelible mark of their slave origins. Writing in
1776, the colonist Hilliard d'Auberteuil noted
that "In San Domingo, for the sake of our own
interests and security, we show such contempt
for the black race that anybody descending from
it ... is marked with an indelible stain"2 In
Brazil, emancipation was regarded as a pow¬
erful form of pressure whereby slave-owners
were able to keep control over their slaves and
sow discord among them. In the Spanish
colonies of the Caribbean, a system of gradual
emancipation, known as coartación, under which
slaves could buy back their freedom in instal¬
ments, was introduced in the sixteenth century.
The emancipated slaves remained dependent
on their masters and were therefore obliged to
respect and honour them or work for them.
Slavery in the Caribbean was more than an
institution with its own laws and customs and
methods of keeping order. It was literally a "total¬
itarian" system of economic, political, social and
sexual exploitation based on force, violence and
the ideology of racism. The ceremonial in which
the slaves were integrated into the system was
SLAVERY
Above left, the slave market
at Zabid, in Yemen. Illustration
from the Maqamat
("The Assemblies"), short
anecdotes told in rhyming prose
by the Arab writer al-Hariri
(mid-13th century).
Below, the prison for
Christian slaves in Algiers.
Engraving by an unknown
18th-century artist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The same seed
Please reflect that the man you call your slave was born of the
same seed, has the same good sky above him, breathes as you
do, lives as you do, dies as you do! You may see him free, he
may see you a slavethe odds are level.
Seneca
Letters to Lucilius,
65-65 A. D.
meant to blot out their past and their culture, and
kill them as free men and members of society. It
was only by making a bid for freedom that the
black cimarrón, the runaway slave, could regain
his identity as a man (by again using his African
name) and his will to work.
In Greece and Italy, and also in Roman-
occupied Egypt, slave-owners had specially
designed instruments, in the shape of metal
chains and collars, to prevent the slaves from
escaping. If slaves did escape, the owners offered
rewards through public announcements or called
on the authorities or engaged professional slave-
hunters known as fugitivarii.
What fate lay in store for the runaway slaves?
They could flee into the bush and form small
bands living off robbery. One account from the
third century B.C. tells of a celebrated example on
the island of Chios, at some unknown date. A
band of runaway slaves had sought refuge in a
rugged, forest-covered mountain region, under
the leadership of a chief called Drimacos. They
successfully resisted several punitive expeditions
until Drimacos eventually concluded a formal
agreement with the authorities. He gave an under¬
taking to protect the property of Chios and only
to accept as members of his band those slaves who
had "suffered intolerably" and returned the others
to their masters. On his death, he was raised to the
dignity of "benevolent hero".
In the course of history, only four slave
revolts took on the proportions of actual war¬
fare, with thousands of armed men on either
side, pitched battles, sieges and the occupation
of towns. The first three took place in Sicily
and Italy over the period from 140 to 70 B.C.
The fourth was the major insurrection on the
island of San Domingo, which culminated in
the independence of Haiti in January 1 804.
1 "Slavery is not a moral category: it is an institution
which provides a large fraction of the labour force. As
long as that force is necessary, slavery cannot merely
go into decline, it has to be replaced". Moses I. Finley,
Ancient Slavery and Modern Ideology, New York,
Penguin, 1983.
2 Hilliard d'Aubertcuil, Considérations sur l'état
présent de la colonie française de Saint Domingue
(1776-1777).
"For the emancipated slaves of
the Caribbean and the
Americas, the colour of their
skin was the indelible sign of
their origins". Right, photo
taken in South Carolina (U.S.A.)
in 1899.
10
ORUNO D. LARA,
of Guadeloupe, is a historian
who heads the Caribbean-
America Research Centre at the
University of Paris X-Nanterre.
His published works include Les
Caraïbes (1986), Caraïbes en
construction: espace,
colonisation, résistance (2 vols,
1992) and, in collaboration with
Nelly Schmidt, Les abolitions de
l'esclavage, Une longue marche
(Centre national de
documentation pédagogique,
Paris, 1993).
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
a crime without punishment
ho was responsible?
by Elikia M'Bokolo
Africans were above all victims of the slave trade,
but some of them were partners in it
Above, "The slave trade in
Africa". Late 18th-century
engraving (artist unknown).
To judge from the number of countries
I taking part in it, the slave trade must have
been for Europeans both a profitable business
and, considering the number of years it lasted,
a familiar fact of life. Even so, in some of the
ports involved in the trade, like Nantes, the
slave-traders themselves were reluctant to call it
by its name and instead spoke of it in more
veiled terms as the "matter".
What about the Africans? Were they merely
its victims or were they conscious and con¬
senting partners in a business arrangement with
whose terms they were perfectly familiar?
A controversial question
There has always been heated debate over the
part played by Africans in the slave trade. For a
long time, the slave-traders took refuge behind
what they saw as the irrefutable argument that
the Africans made a regular practice of selling
their fellow Africans, and that if the Europeans
refused to buy slaves from them, other people
meaning the Arabs, who also used black slaves,
among others would hasten to do so. Nowa
days, African intellectuals and statesmen contend
that that these exchanges were always unequal
(in that human beings were bought with baubles)
and that the Europeans always resorted to vio¬
lence to get the Africans to co-operate against
their will.
For historians the story is not quite as simple
as that, in the first place because our criteria are not
the same as those of 500 or even 150 years ago. Wc
believe that if only one slave had been shipped
across the Atlantic, it would have been one too
many. But did Africans think like this in the past?
Secondly, the slave trade, which went on for almost
four centuries, was a very complex process
involving a very wide variety of power relation¬
ships and participants whose interests and
responses were bound to have changed with the
course of time. This has prompted the British his¬
torian Basil Davidson to say that the "notion that
Europe altogether imposed the slave trade on
Africa is without any foundation in history. . . . [it]
is as baseless as the European notion that
institutions of bondage were in some way pecu¬
liar to Africa.""' 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Thinking of the millions of my brothers
Each morning, when I wake up, I have the taste of death in my
mouth. . . . But, after doing a few physical exercises, I open the
windows of my bedroom. They overlook the sea and, away in the
distance, I can just make out the island of Gorée. And when I think
of the millions of my black brothers who were shipped from there
to destinations where misfortune and death awaited them, I am
compelled not to despair. Their story goads me on. . . .
Leopold Sédar Senghor
12
The European powers built
slaving forts in west Africa as
the bridgeheads of their military
presence and used them for
storing their merchandise and
holding their African captives
until they were shipped to the
Americas. From left to right:
Cape Coast Fort built by the
English in 1665 on the former
Gold Coast, in present-day
Ghana; the Portuguese fort of
Sao Jago (1482); Fort
Patience, a Dutch stronghold
(1697); the English fort of
Metal Cross (1693).
From slave-raiding to slave-trading
The first method by which the Europeans
acquired African slaves was through straight¬
forward abduction. Striking examples of this
can be found in the celebrated Crónica dos Feitos
da Guiñé (Chronicle ofthe Discovery and Con¬
quest of Guinea), written by the Portuguese
Gomes Eanes de Zurara in the mid-fifteenth
century. When the Europeans landed on the
coasts of Africa, they stopped at random at
places they thought might be suitable for their
purpose and set out on man-hunts. This was
not without its risks, however, as evidenced by
the massacre in 1446 of almost all the members
of the expedition led by Nuno Tristao near the
Cap Vert peninsula in present-day Senegal. This
was not the only such massacre, but it certainly
shows that the Africans were determined to
fight against enslavement.
The drawbacks of slave-raiding were that
its outcome was uncertain and it was incapable
of catering for the constantly growing demand,
when the plantations and mines of the Americas
had to be supplied with slave labour. The Por¬
tuguese were the first to switch from merely
seizing captives to actually trading in slaves,
following a suggestion made by Prince Henry
the Navigator in 1444 and subsequently fol¬
lowed by Portuguese sovereigns until the end of
the fifteenth century. However, even after this
v	 - " .. ' - -I
M" .. , V i ¿
trade had become a routine matter, raiding con¬
tinued to provide slave-traders with an addi¬
tional source of supply. The so-called "roving"
trade in which slaving ships sailed along the
coast and captured slaves at various places until
they had a full consignment often took the
form of armed incursions against villages situ¬
ated near to the coast. When countries engaged
in the slave trade, they often began by orga¬
nizing raiding expeditions, as did the first vessels
hailing from the "twelve colonies" (the future
United States of America) in the first half of
the seventeenth century.
By that time, however, the leading Euro¬
pean nations had imposed a code of ethics of a
kind on the slave trade. The English, Portuguese
and French agreed to make a joint declaration to
the effect that the slave trade was justified only
when it involved slaves duly sold by Africans.
Forts were built along the coastline in order to
organize the trade and at the same time to instill
a healthy sense of fear among the Africans. The
message they conveyed was perfectly clear: "Sell
us slaves and we shall leave it to you to choose
them as you see fit or else we shall take the
slaves we need at random."
The slave trade was therefore a one-sided
relationship, founded and maintained on the
threat of force. We once again have to agree
with Basil Davidson when he says, "Africa and
Europe were jointly involved	 Europe dom¬
inated the connection, shaped and promoted
the slave trade, and continually turned it to
European advantage and to African loss."
Affairs of state and lineage societies
At its height, the slave trade was regarded by
Africans as a kind of diabolical plot in which
they had to be accomplices or perish. Hence
almost all the lineage or state societies of the
African seaboard were compelled to become
involved in it. They did this in ways and under
conditions which differed significantly from one
region to another and from one period to another.
The social history of pre-colonial Africa
shows that slavery was a widespread institu¬
tion in states where, in some instances, a
domestic trade in slaves already existed for mil¬
itary or economic reasons. However, a distinc-
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
SLAVERY
tion has to be made between those states which
maintained relations with the outside world
and those which did not. The former were
quicker and more ready to join in the slave-
trade cycle. This was true of the states bor¬
dering the Sahel, which were already in the prac¬
tice of selling slaves, among other goods, to
their Arab and Berber partners, who actually
went on to sell some of them to the Europeans.
The chronicler Alvise de Ca' da Mosto, who
took part in a Portuguese expedition to
Senegambia in 1455-1456, reported that the
local sovereigns were skilled at taking advantage
of the new competition that was growing up
between the trans-Saharan trade and the Atlantic
trade by selling slaves to the Arabs and Berbers
in exchange for horses, and other slaves to the
Portuguese in exchange for European goods.
The situation was by no means the same in
those states which had no trading links with
the outside world. The part these played in the
slave trade is a pointer to the ambiguous and
contradictory attitudes they displayed and the
difficulties they faced when they came to take
decisions, often under duress. The kingdom of
Kongo, one of the most powerful in Africa at the
time of its encounter with the Portuguese at
the end of the fifteenth century, is a typical
example. In the view of contemporary histo¬
rians, its economic, political and social standing
was on a par with that of Portugal. From the
time of the very first contacts, the Kongo
nobility became converts to Christianity and
the king saw fit to address the Portuguese sov¬
ereign as "my brother". Yet the fact was that the
slave trade had already started, in violation of the
agreements, both tacit and formal, concluded
between the two states. A number of letters, in
which the king of Kongo protested against the
seizure of slaves, including members of noble
families, have survived to the present day. There
is still some controversy as to what was really the
motive behind these protestations. Some his¬
torians regard them as being an outburst of
nationalist sentiment, but others look upon
them more as a sign of the concern of the
country's aristocracy not to allow so lucrative a
business to slip through their hands. In any
event, the kingdom did not survive the impact of
the slave trade for very long. The same drama
blacks in the West
Indies", engraving from
La France maritime by
Amédée Gréhan, Paris, 1855
(artist unknown).
* Basil Davidson, Black
Mother, The Years of the
African Slave Trade,
Boston/Toronto, Little, a éy
Brown and Company, 1961. ¿O
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Uross-section of the slave ship
Brookes, showing how the
captives were crammed
together between decks.
Engraving from The History of
the Abolition of the Slave Trade,
by Thomas Clarkson (1808).
14
ELIKIA M'BOKOLO,
Zairean historian, is director of
studies at the Ecole des Hautes
Etudes en Sciences Sociales in
Paris. He is the author of many
works on African history,
cultures and development
problems, including L'Afrique au
20* siècle, le continent convoité
(1985) and Afrique noire,
Histoire et civilisations, 19-2C
siècles (1992).
was to be played out to varying degrees else¬
where in Africa.
The kingdom of Dahomey was also exposed
to the bitter experience of the slave trade. In
the mid-eighteenth century, it took over the
port of Ouidah, one of the main centres of the
trade in the Gulf of Guinea. The king of
Dahomey regarded the port where there was
a growing buildup of firearms as posing a
threat to the security of his possessions, since the
slave trade gave it a tactical advantage over its
neighbours. Once they took control of Ouidah,
the rulers of Dahomey were caught in a vicious
circle: in order to maintain a strong state, they
needed rifles and gunpowder, but to obtain
these they had to sell slaves to the Europeans.
The answer was really very straightforward:
since the sale of the kingdom's own subjects
was strictly forbidden, powerful armies were
raised to raid neighbouring peoples and make
war on them for the purpose of taking slaves.
Unlike states, lineage societies did not have
any means of obtaining slaves by force. In such
cases, servitude was based on complex prac¬
tices in which various categories of social out¬
casts, such as criminals, misfits, sorcerers and vic¬
tims of natural or economic disasters, were
relegated to being slaves. Even so, this would not
have been sufficient to turn the slave trade into
the vast and lasting business it became. Other
means were therefore found of meeting the
Europeans' demands. For example, in the city of
Arochukwu ("the voice of Chukwu", the
supreme deity), in the Niger delta, a celebrated
oracle whose authority was respected by all the
population was called on to designate those
who, for whatever reason, were condemned to
be sold into slavery. This practice continued
until the beginning of the nineteenth century.
In other regions, especially in central Africa,
trading networks were gradually established,
extending from the coast deep into the interior.
All the goods exported or imported via these
networks predominantly slaves transited
through the heads of the lineages. In Gabon
and Loango in particular, the coastal societies
forming the key links in these trading networks
had a highly developed ranking social order
based on the extent to which their members
were involved in the slave trade. Kinship rela
tions, which are fundamental in lineage soci¬
eties, gradually gave way to relations based on
fortunes made in the trade, which came to dic¬
tate people's standing in society.
Africans and the abolition
of the slave trade
On the African side, however, the basis of the
slave trade was very precariously balanced. The
part played by Africans in the trade cannot be
discussed without reference to the part they
played in its abolition. In a one-sided view of his¬
tory, the role of Europeans philosophers,
thinkers, men of religion and businessmen is
too often stressed, while that played by the
Africans is left in the shade. Some people have
even gone so far as to tax the Africans with
being the main impediment to the phasing-out
of the trade in the nineteenth century. Nothing
could be further from the truth.
Outside Africa, the resistance of the victims
of the slave trade which took a variety of
forms, including the "Back to Africa" move¬
ment, the founding of "Maroon" communities
and even armed insurrection, like that in San
Domingo in 1791 was primarily instrumental
in calling the whole institution of slavery into
question. Those who had managed to escape
its clutches took a very active but often unac¬
knowledged part in the campaign for abolition.
They included people like Ottobah Cuguano,
who had been born in Fantiland, in present-
day Ghana, had been a slave in the West Indies,
and published his Thoughts and Sentiments on
the Evil and Wicked Traffic ofSlavery in London
in 1787. In 1789, another African, Olaudah
Equiano, alias Gustavus Vassa, a native of
Iboland, in Nigeria, published, again in London,
The Interesting Narrative ofthe Life ofOlaudah
Equiano, or Gustavus Vassa the African, written
by himself. These books played a significant
role in the movement of opinion which led to the
abolition of the slave trade.
In Africa itself, all through the "years of trial"
of the slave trade, along with slaves, blacks con¬
tinued to sell the produce of their soil and subsoil,
such as timber, ivory, spices, gold, vegetable oils,
and others besides. Changing European demand
was sufficient for the Africans to turn to a more
"legal" form of commerce.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
A SLAVE'S STORY a crime without punishment
'My name is Moses Grandy'
Below, an advertisement
which appeared on 4 October
1775 in the Feu/7/e d'annonces,
Affiches et Avis divers des Isles
de France et de Bourbon, a
newspaper and advertising
gazette published in the islands
of Mauritius and Réunion, which
were then French possessions.
I was born in Camden County, North Car¬
olina. I believe I am fifty-six years old	
I remember four sisters and four brothers; my
mother had more children, but they were dead or
sold away before I can remember. I was the
youngest	
[The master's] wife, with much to be done,
prevailed on him not to sell me; but he sold my
brother, who was a little boy. My mother, frantic
with grief, resisted their taking her child away:
she was beaten and held down: she fainted; and
when she came to herself, her boy was gone. She
made much outcry, for which the master tied her
up to a peach tree in the yard and flogged her. . . .
My young master and I used to play together;
there was but two days' difference in our ages.
My old master always said that he would give me
to him. When he died ... I fell to young master: his
name was James Grandy. . . .
This continued till my master and myself were
twenty-one years old	 The first who hired me
was Mr. Kemp, who used me pretty well: he gave
me plenty to eat and sufficient clothing.
The next was old Jemmy Coates, a severe man.
Because I could not learn his way of hilling corn,
he flogged me naked with a severe whip made of a
very tough sapling; this lapped round me at each
stroke, the point of it at last entered my belly and
broke off, leaving an inch and a-half outside. I was
not aware of it until on going to work again it hurt
my side very much, when on looking down I saw
it sticking out of my body: I pulled it out and the
blood spouted after it. The wound festered, and dis¬
charged very much at the time, and hurt me for
years after. . . .
My brother Benjamin returned from the West
Indies	 While I was sitting with his wife and him,
his wife's master came and asked him to fetch a can
Foliad
famftuie.sUvefwaTe^ne^^
of water: he did so, and carried it into the store.
While I was waiting for him and wondering at his
being so long away, I heard the heavy blows of a
hammer: after a little while I was alarmed and went
to see what was going on. I looked into the store,
and saw my brother lying on his back on the floor,
and Mr. Williams, who had bought him, driving sta¬
ples over his wrists and ankles; an iron bar was
afterwards put across his breast, which was also
held down by staples. I asked what he had been
doing, and was told that he had done nothing
amiss, but that his master had failed, and he was
sold towards paying the debts. He lay in that state
all that night; next day he was taken to jail, and I
never saw him again. This is the usual treatment
under such circumstances.
Narrative of the Life of Moses Grandy; Late a Slave in
the United States ofAmerica, London, C. Gilpin, 5
Bishopsgate Street, 1843.
Slaves in Dahomey (present-
day Benin), photographed in the
second half of the 19th century.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
One hundred and
forty million
Africans died or
were sold into
slavery. For every
slave taken aboard
smp, six or seven
other Africans lost
their lives as
indirect victims of
the trade.
continent of fear
by M'Baye Gueye
16
One of the most patent consequences of
the slave trade was without any doubt its
effect on Africa's population. Although it is dif¬
ficult to put a precise figure on the numbers
involved, it may reasonably be estimated that 20
million slaves were taken to the New World
during the four centuries or so that the trade
existed.
When one remembers the kind of methods
used to obtain slaves, the losses suffered by
Africa take on appalling proportions. Natu¬
rally, thieves, criminals, witch doctors and all
kinds of misfits were unceremoniously sold to
traders. But most slaves were seized in the course
of wars and plundering forays. In such cases, in
addition to those who were exported as slaves,
there were direct and indirect victims of the
trade people who died fighting or as a result of
the famine, diseases and epidemics that followed
in the wake of destroyed harvests, burnt grain
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Opposite page,
"The rebellion of a slave on a
slave ship", oil on canvas
by the French painter
Edouard Renard (1802-1857).
Below, ivory pendant
probably representing an "oba",
or king, of Benin
(16th century). The heads of
bearded Portuguese are carved
on the tiara.
stores and the disruption of the population's
fragile equilibrium with its environment.
Such infamous acts were familiar events in
all regions of Africa involved in the Atlantic
trade. Oral literature is haunted by the sound of
groaning victims and the sight of burning vil¬
lages lighting up the horizon. That permanent
state of war, with its succession of massacres,
destruction, plundering and violence, made fear
"one of the dimensions of the African soul". It
may be estimated that for every prisoner taken
aboard the slave ships, six or seven Africans died
on the continent.
Yet these losses, which were spread over a
period of time, represented barely more than 1 per
cent of the black population. It may be won¬
dered why such a relatively small manpower
drain had such a paralysing effect on African
society. The reason is that slave-traders mainly
took young people. The massive deportation of
those sections of society that were able-bodied
and of an age to have children resulted in a pop¬
ulation shortfall which new births were increas¬
ingly unable to offset.
A political disaster
The political repercussions of the slave trade
were equally drastic. The former political struc¬
tures of northern Nigeria, Chad and the Congo
entered a period of decline, as they were unable
to adjust to the situation created by the slave
trade. The Congo, then at the height of its pros¬
perity, failed to resist the pressure of the Por¬
tuguese, who sallied forth from their base on the
island of Sào Tomé to seize Congolese slaves for
their colony in Brazil despite the fact that cer-
SLAVERY
tain members of the ruling aristocracy, who had
converted to Catholicism, were well disposed
towards them. The Portuguese furthered their
own interests by encouraging provincial chiefs to
rebel and by fomenting strife among the factions
that were struggling for power, with the result that
the country eventually lapsed into anarchy.
The same fate was suffered by the kingdoms
of Oyo and Benin, which had achieved a certain
degree of institutional stability until the Euro¬
peans arrived. They failed to withstand the con¬
tinual wars caused by the slave trade. Soon their
provinces set themselves up as independent
principalities. By the end of the eighteenth cen¬
tury, an outstanding culture over two centuries
old had been turned into a vast theatre of con¬
stant conflict which resulted in Benin being
grimly known as "bloody Benin".
However, the coastal states and those in their
vicinity managed to recast their institutional
structures and set up strong regimes. In the
Senegambian region, for example, traditional
political structures underwent far-reaching
The best hope of earth
In giving freedom to the slave, we assure freedom to the free-
honourable alike in what we give and what we preserve. We shall
nobly save, or meanly lose, the last, best hope of earth.
Abraham Lincoln
Annual Message to Congress, 1 December 1862
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
This plate made of bronze, a
. metal which the Europeans
traded for slaves, adorned a
wooden pillar in a royal palace
in Benin.
changes. A system of monarchy by divine right,
which set the king apart from his subjects and
put power in the hands of his representatives,
was replaced by a form of autocracy. Although
the latter system, which relied on a considerable
centralization of power, inevitably resulted in
abuses, it did make it possible to keep the slave
trade within "tolerable" bounds. The Futa, the
Waalo, the Kayor, the Banol, the Sine and the
Salum had succeeded in neutralizing each other,
so their respective kings felt little temptation to
venture on to their neighbours' territory.
The state of Akwamu, near the coast, took
advantage of its dealings with the slave traders
to assert its supremacy in the area. By control¬
ling roads to the hinterland, it was able to exert
pressure on commercial transactions. Towards
the end of the eighteenth century, it imposed
18
M'BAYE GUEYE,
of Senegal, is senior lecturer in
history in the Faculty of Letters
and Human Sciences at Cheikh
Anta Diop University in Dakar.
He has written a number of
books on the slave trade and
French colonization in West
Africa.
heavy levies on its neighbours. Akwamu s rise to
power was not an isolated case. The state of
Denkyira, in the western part of the "gold
coast", also expanded spectacularly as a result of
trade with Europeans. It secured substantial
revenues by acting as a broker, and built up a
powerful army that enabled it to impose levies
on the Ashanti confederation, whose various
districts decided to unite against their powerful
neighbour.
Ashanti achieved political and spiritual unity
towards the end of the seventeenth century.
Then, after a series of victorious campaigns
against Denkyira, it established its authority
over the main gold trade routes and opened up
a road to the coast. In order to administer its new
conquests, it set up a bureaucracy whose docility
only reinforced the central power.
Inadequate restrictions
Yet the Africans did not always take the slave
trade lying down. Many local chiefs reacted as
best they could to halt the practice. Slaves
rebelled on many occasions. Their uprisings in
Gorée in 1724 and 1749, in St. Louis in 1779 and
in Galam in 1786 ended in bloodbaths.
Several kings and religious leaders tried to
organize resistance against the slave trade.
Between 1673 and 1677, a Moor called Nasir al-
Din conquered the kingdoms of Futa, Waalo,
Jolof and Kayor by leading a veritable crusade
against local kings involved in the slave trade.
After repressive action was taken by the trading
post in St. Louis, the former regimes were
returned to power. In 1701, Lat Sukaabe, king of
Kayor and Bawol, kidnapped a slave-trader and
released him only after obtaining a tidy ransom.
Agaja, king of Dahomey, embarked on a
campaign that was as resolute in the resources it
marshalled as in the ambiguity of its aims. After
opening up a way to the sea, he took steps to
restrict the slave trade in his kingdom. Euro¬
peans were not allowed to put their merchandise
on board ship or to leave the territory without
his permission. He then posted a permanent
military unit on the coast and turned the slave
trade into a state monopoly.
But all such efforts, however commendable
they may have been, were incapable of putting
an end to the slave trade. African chiefs hostile
to the practice had no way of forming a united
front against it. The initiative shifted to the
marabouts, who urged the people to convert to
Islam on the grounds that it was their only
chance of salvation. In 1 725, the revolution of the
marabouts triumphed at Futa Jallon. In 1776, it
was Futa Toro 's turn. Between 1787 and 1817,
Uthman Dan Fodio founded the theocratic state
of Sokoto. But despite the efforts of various
parties to stop the slave trade, it continued until
the end of the nineteenth century.
By that time, all these political entities had
ended up losing their cohesion. As well as being
ill-defined geographically, they were handi¬
capped by having populations which were very
unevenly distributed and scarcely growing at all.
The oppressive authoritarianism of the ruling
aristocracies, combined with political exclu¬
sion, social discrimination and extreme tribal
idiosyncracies, resulted everywhere in a con¬
stant state of tension that did not favour the
emergence of peaceful societies. By the time
slavery was about to die out, those societies had
become profoundly weak and vulnerable to
colonialism, which was poised to take over
where the slave-traders had left off.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
by Innocent Futcha
In the France ofLouis XIVslaves
were legally regarded as chattels but were
also considered to have souls
I The Code Noir (Black Code) was one
I of the first attempts in the history of
slavery to codify a hitherto unregulated prac¬
tice. Published as an edict by Louis XIV in
March 1685, it included some sixty articles
aimed at regulating the way black slaves
lived and died in French possessions in
the West Indies and the Indian Ocean. In
1724, the same legislation was extended to
cover Louisiana.
The provisions of the Code Noir had
three aims: to Christianize slaves, to specify
the prohibitions imposed on them and the
punishments applicable to them, and to
define the conditions of their emancipation.
Described in these oversimplified terms, the
Code Noir might seem to have been designed
to facilitate the transition of blacks from
slavery to freedom via Catholicism.
APPARENT LENIENCY
Because it advocated the baptism of slaves and
stated the conditions under which they could
be emancipated, the Code Noir apparently
recognized blacks as belonging, to some extent,
to humankind. Some of its provisions granted
them explicit rights. They could, for example,
lodge a complaint against their masters if they
were not fed and clothed according to the law
(Article 26). Although they were required to
wed according to the rites of the Catholic
Church, a spouse could not be imposed on
them (Article 11), and if slaves were seized or
sold it was forbidden to separate husband,
wife and children (Article 47). Masters were
required to support disabled and sick slaves
(Article 27), and could emancipate slaves in
their service without the consent of their par¬
ents from the age of 20 (Article 55).
Taken separately, some articles of the
Code Noir were undeniably an improve¬
ment on the kind of practices endured by
slaves in other parts of the world until the
nineteenth century. However, it has to be
recognized that in its overall effect "the Code
Noir is the most monstrous legal text pro¬
duced in modern times"1. This might seem to
be a rather harsh judgment were it not for the
startling paradoxes that mar the spirit and
letter of that legislation.
The fact that the Code Noir emphasized
the need to Christianize slaves, a subject to
which thirteen articles are devoted, might
suggest that it at least recognizes them as
having their own soul and personality. Yet it
also proclaims: "We declare slaves to be
moveable property" (Article 44), and "Wc
declare that slaves may not possess anything
which docs not belong to their master . . .
people unfit to possess or contract in their
own right" (Article 28). This tendency to
see slaves as objects, which clearly under¬
lies the spirit of the Code Noir, is spelled
out in the two articles referred to, which
refuse to recognize them as human beings.
The nature of the slave changes, depending
on circumstances. While he is regarded as
"moveable property" in Article 44, he
becomes "immoveable property" in Article 48,
which sees him as an integral part of the "sugar
works, indigo factories and dwellings" where
he works. The legislator does exactly what
he likes with the slave, since he has first made
sure that the slave has no civil existence. Article
30, for example, states that the testimony of
slaves is null and void, and therefore cannot
count as evidence, while Article 31 stresses that
slaves may not take out proceedings before
cither a civil or a criminal court.
A CASE OF CATCH-22
What is the point of passing legislation on
individuals who are patently not regarded
as subjects of law? Yet Article 26, mentioned
above, allows slaves the right to lodge a com-
"I am a man: nothing human is alien to me": this
aphorism by Terence, the Latin poet of the 2nd
century A.D. and himself an emancipated slave,
was the caption to this 1791 engraving depicting
the supposedly more humane version of slavery
created by the Code Noir. The engraving was
produced by Louis Joseph Masquelier, from an
allegory painted by Jean-Michel Moreau.
plaint against their masters if the latter do not
reed them as laid down by the law. This is a
case of Catch-22: slaves are subject to the
law, yet their legal existence is denied by the
very same text which entitles them to seek
justice.
More generally, the Code Noir constantly
affirms one thing as well as its opposite, espe¬
cially where slaves' interests are concerned.
For slaves are above all regarded as prop¬
erty which can be disposed of by their owner
as he sees fit. Eleven articles regulate the
exchange of that property between buyers
and sellers, debtors and creditors.
The major part of the Code Noir is
devoted to the rules which should be imposed
on slaves to keep them under the control of
their masters. Every aspect of their relationship
is taken into account. Among other things, a
slave is not permitted to drink spirits, carry
arms, assault his master, hold meetings or
above all abscond. The first time he tries to run
away the slave loses an ear. If he tries again, he
is hamstrung. And if he is brave enough to try
yet again, he is beheaded. Even activities in the
Code Noir relating to the emancipation of
slaves comprise provisions which restrict their
liberties.
In this respect Article 58 is typical. It urges
emancipated slaves "topay especial respect to
their former masters, their widows and their
children; thus any disrespect they may show
towards them shall be punished more harshly
than if it had been shown towards another
person". The imposition of such conditions on
emancipated slaves was tantamount to
demanding that they behave submissively
towards whites in general, all of them actual or
potential owners of slaves. The distinction
between master and slave was compounded by
the henceforth insuperable divide between
black and white which at another time and
in another country came to be known as
apartheid. The enabling texts of the Code
Noir even went so far as to regulate the dress
of emancipated slaves in order to perpetuate
their differences from their former masters.
All in all, the Code Noir did not do much
to help slaves on their way to freedom. In it,
emancipation was seen as the transition from
one form of domination to another. But then
it could hardly have been otherwise in a
world where the economic interests of the
dominant class were more powerful than
any humanitarian considerations.
1 . Lluis Sala-Molins, Le Code Noir ou le calvaire
de Canaan, Paris, PUF, 1987.
INNOCENT FUTCHA, of Cameroon, teaches in the
department of African literature in the Faculty of
Arts, Letters and Human Sciences of the University
of Yaoundé-ll. His main field of interest is South
African literature.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
VOL» 1«1	 WILLIAM LLOYD GARRISON AHü ISAA' k\MI'P fCHLISHKKS.
Bowon, Massachusetts.) our cotMiBr is Tiir worn n huh countktmi-N are mankind.
	[NO. 11.
[Satuhdai Mai
he long road to abolition
by Nelly Schmidt
The eradication ofslavery in North America and the West Indies proceeded at
snail's pace. Even the leaders of the French Revolution dragged their feet.
Above, masthead of The
Liberator, the newspaper
published in Boston in 1831 by
the writer William Lloyd Garrison,
an ardent advocate of the
abolition of slavery in the United
States.
Some words are historically loaded. "The
abolition of slavery" is of course a con¬
venient phrase, but historical authenticity
requires us to choose terms more faithful to
reality. The process the Americas went through
in the nineteenth century and are still going
through today, may be more accurately
described as the destruction of the system of
slavery. It was a slow process, beginning with the
ending of slavery in San Domingo/Haiti in
August-September 1793.
The crucial importance of resistance move¬
ments by slaves themselves in triggering this
process is just beginning to be realized. The
case of San Domingo/Haiti is a typical example
20
Though Marster was a Mef'dis' preacher, he whip his slaves, an'
' den drap pitch an'tuppentine on dem from a bu'nin' to'ch.
Marster preach to de white folks Sunday mo'nin'. Den, at night, all de
marsters roun' dat country sen' dey slaves, an' he preach to us. He had
two fav'rit tex'es he uster preach from to de slaves. One was, "Serv'nts,
obey your marsters". He didn' say much 'bout de Marster in Hebben, but
alius tole us to obey our earthly marsters. De other tex' was "Thou shalt
not steal". He preach dat over an' over, to de niggers. Dey couldn' read
deir Bibles, so dey hatter bliebe jis' what he say.
Since I's got to readin' an' studyin', I see some of de chu'ches is
wrong, an' de preachers don' preach jis' like de Bible say.
Jack White
slave
of this: a slave revolt that turned out to be impos¬
sible to curb was what triggered the abolitionist
movement there in 1791.
In response to Spanish and British threats to
invade the island, Sonthonax, the civil commis¬
sioner assigned to the colony by the revolu¬
tionary government in Paris, decided on 29
August 1793 to end slavery in the north, and this
measure was extended to the west and south of
the colony in September and October of the
same year. The measure was confirmed on 4
February 1 794 (16 pluviôse of the year II) by the
Convention, which decreed that "all men
without distinction of colour domiciled in the
colonies are French citizens, and shall enjoy all
the rights guaranteed by the Constitution". The
1795 Constitution even specified that "the
French colonies are an integral part of the
Republic and are subject to the same constitu¬
tional law", and provided for their accession to
the status of departments.
This assimilationist legislation, however,
never came into force. In 1802, the legislative
body declared itself in favour of reintroducing
slavery. On 17 May the Consulate, taking the
view that "illusions of liberty and equality have
been spread to these remote lands" (i.e. France's
American colonies), where "the difference
between civilized and uncivilized men" was too
"striking", passed a decree providing that "In the
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
colonies restored to France under the Treaty of
Amiens dated the 6th germinal of the year X,
slavery shall be maintained in accordance with
pre-1798 laws and regulations".
The opposition aroused by the coming into
force of this decree obliged Napoleon Bona¬
parte to dispatch military expeditions to Guade¬
loupe and San Domingo. The colonial war that
raged in these two islands ended with the réin¬
troduction of slavery in Guadeloupe. In San
Domingo one of the great leaders of the insur¬
rection, Toussaint Louverture, was captured
and imprisoned in France, at Fort-de-Joux in the
Jura, where he died in April 1 803. But the French
troops sent to impose the reintroduction of
slavery were defeated, and the independence of
the colony (under its old Amerindian name of
Haiti) was finally proclaimed on 1 January 1 804.
The British practise "the right of search"
Emancipation in the British colonies which
followed thirty years later was likewise largely
the result of the long rebellion by the slaves of
Jamaica (1831-1832). As early as 1780 a human¬
itarian trend had emerged in England, one of its
supporters being a young M.P. of aristocratic
origin, William Wilberforcc: in 1807 he per¬
suaded the House of Commons to prohibit the
I When Dr. Cannon found out
dat his carriage driver had
larned to read and write while he was
takin' de doctor's chillun to and f'om
school, he had dat nigger's thumbs
cut off, and put another boy to doin'
de drivin' in his place.
Tom Hawkins
slave
transatlantic slave trade. From that date
onwards, and then after the 1815 Congress of
Vienna (which drew up a European agreement
on ending the slave trade), Britain was to lead a
campaign for the inspection of slave-ships,
which were pronounced illegal.
Well-established networks of illicit slave
trade had grown up from the coasts of Africa to
Brazil, the United States, Cuba and the French
colonies of Guadeloupe and Martinique. Pro¬
paganda against this trade though not against
the system of slavery itself developed partic¬
ularly in London, where numerous leaflets cir¬
culated in several languages. One of them enti¬
tled The cry of the Africans against their
SLAVERY
"The emancipation of slaves in
the United States", an engraving
published in the Illustrated
London News in 1864 (artist
unknown).
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Poster depicting Harriet Tubman
(1820-1913), a celebrated black
activist In the United States
before the Civil War. Herself a
fugitive from a Maryland
plantation, she helped more than
300 runaway slaves to reach the
northern states and Canada.
22
European oppressors, or a look at the murderous
commerce known as the slave trade, by Thomas
Clarkson, which appeared in 1822, contained the
famous cross-sections of the slave-ship Brookes.
The "right of search" practised by British
transatlantic vessels aroused lively controversy.
France and the United States in particular grudg¬
ingly accepted the role of policeman of the seas
first performed by the British.
A proliferation of petitions and the creation
of a society for the abolition of the slave trade
eventually brought about an investigation by the
Crown. But it was not until 1823 that an Anti-
Slavery Society was founded in London. In
1831 the Crown manumitted slaves within its
own lands, and on 28 August 1833 the King
approved an Act voted by Parliament emanci¬
pating slaves in the British West Indies, Guyana
and British Honduras (now Belize). This Act
No siree, I never did learn how to read and write. I just hold to
the end of the pencil so the white man can sign my name.
Eli Davison
slave
My moster would put slaves
in a calaboose at night to be
shipped de next morning. He always
limited de lashes to five hundred.
After whipping dem, he would rub
pepper and salt on deir backs, where
whipped, and lay dem before de fire
until blistered, and den take a cat,
and make him claw de blisters, to
burst dem.
Robert Burns
slave
Right, Victor Schoelcher
(1804-1893), one of the leading
architects of the abolition of
slavery in the French colonies
in 1848.
gave the planters generous compensation, and set
a time-limit of four-to-six years for the complete
liberation of slaves employed in farming and
domestic work. They were subject to compul¬
sory unpaid apprenticeship under their mas¬
ters, limited to four years because of the diffi¬
culty of enforcing such a system. Only children
under six and adults over sixty were declared free
in August 1834.
The new citizens of the Republic
Little attempt is usually made to situate the
beginnings and the acceleration of abolitionist
processes in the context of the resistance by
slaves themselves to the system of slavery. By
and large, European abolitionist movements
remained very timid. In Paris a decision to
abolish slavery was not on the agenda of the
Société française pour l'abolition de l'esclavage,
founded in 1834 and modelled on the British
Anti-Slavery Society. Nor did it form part of the
programme of the provisional government that
came to power after the revolutionary days of
February 1848. But Victor Schoelcher, who had
travelled in the French colonies and had set
himself up as the apostle of the abolition of
slavery, managed to persuade the Minister of
the Navy and the Colonies that a general
uprising was imminent if the status quo were
maintained; he got the government to accept
the principle of abolition in the French colonies.
It was only at this price that law and order, and
work on the sugar-cane plantations, could be
maintained. He was appointed Under-Secre¬
tary of State for the Colonies and Chairman of
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
the Commission for the Abolition of Slavery,
which on 27 April got the new government to
sign a decree providing for immediate emanci¬
pation. This instrument was modelled on the
British precedent, and granted slave-owning
colonists compensation; but its original feature
was that it made the "new freedmen" citizens
empowered to elect their representatives to
the National Assembly in Paris by universal
suffrage.
The introduction of this decree in the French
colonics where rebel slaves had already forced
the governors to proclaim liberty even before the
text arrived from Paris caused riots in the
Danish colonies of the Virgin Islands (St. Croix,
St. John and St. Thomas), where in July 1848
Governor Von Schölten had urgently to pro¬
mulgate an emancipation decree drawn up by
King Christian VIII's government. In 1863 a
similar decree was brought into force in the
Dutch colonies.
A different kind of emancipation of slaves
was to be seen in the United States and the
Spanish colonies, in the context of armed con¬
flicts. This was the case in Latin America in the
days of Bolivar, and also in Cuba starting with
the Ten Years' War, between 1868 and 1878.
Slaves were promised their freedom in return for
enlisting in the armies being raised against Spain.
The Moret law (from the name of the Spanish
Minister for the Colonies) was passed by the
Cortes in 1870 and brought into force in Puerto
Rico in 1873, and then progressively in Cuba in
1880 and 1886.
In the United States slavery was not so much
a colonial as a national problem. The northern
I Old Missus and young Missus told the
little slave children that the stork
brought the white babies to their mothers,
but that the slave children were all hatched
out from buzzards' eggs. And we believed it
was true.
Katie Sutton
slave
states, where industrialization had come rela¬
tively early and progressed relatively quickly,
were exposed to effective propaganda from the
Quakers and other Protestant sects. Indeed, the
Quakers were the only white group to plead the
cause of emancipation of the negroes in Eng¬
land's North American colonies before the War of
Independence. As early as 1688 the Quaker com¬
munity in Pennsylvania had protested against
"the business of buying and keeping blacks".
a crime without punishment
Toussaint Louverture,
below, as depicted in an
engraving published in the
Histoire du Consulat et de
l'Empire (1845-1862) by the
French historian and statesman
Louis Adolphe Thiers.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
I I recollect seein'
one biscuit crust,
one mornin'. Dey throwed
it out to de dogs, an' I
beat de dog to it.
Alex McCinney
slave
makandal burned alive (1991),
acrylic on canvas by the Haitian
painter Frantz Zéphirin. François
Makandal, a slave of Guiñean
origin, was known as the "Black
Spartacus". The instigator of an
uprising in Haiti, he held out with
his comrades-in-arms against the
French army, terrorizing the
plantations until he was caught
and burned at the stake in 1758
on the square in front of Cape
Haitien cathedral.
In 1775 the principles set forth in the Dec¬
laration of Independence were injected into the
debate on slavery. During the war the negro
slaves of New England intensified their anti-
slavery activities and produced a stream of peti¬
tions. They claimed to be following the example
of the oppressed colonists "in their present glo¬
rious struggles for freedom". Vermont, by pro¬
hibiting bondage in its 1777 Constitution, took
the lead among the northern states which pro¬
claimed the ending of slavery. The same step
was taken by Massachusetts and New Hamp¬
shire, while Pennsylvania, Rhode Island and
Connecticut opted for gradual emancipation.
Disappointed hopes
In 1830 the movement acquired fresh impetus.
William Lloyd Garrison founded the news¬
paper The Liberator. In 1845 Frederick Dou¬
glass, a fugitive arrived from the south, pub¬
lished his famous autobiography and settled in
Washington, where he made a career in jour¬
nalism and diplomacy. Harriet Tubman helped
to organize the clandestine departure of slaves
from the south to the north and Canada via the
"underground railroad". In 1848 the Free Soil
Society and then in 1854 the Republican Party
(whose candidate Abraham Lincoln was elected
President of the United States in 1 860) included
in their manifestoes the ending of slavery
throughout the country. The end of the War of
Secession in 1865 made it possible in any event
to enshrine abolition in the Thirteenth Amend¬
ment to the United States Constitution.
After Puerto Rico in 1873 and Cuba in 1886,
24
it remained for Brazil in 1888 to promulgate
the last slave emancipation decree in the Amer¬
icas having received the largest number of
captives from the illicit slave trade in the nine¬
teenth century.
Each decree was followed by an often
lengthy period of transition to other ways of reg¬
ulating labour and social relations. In the
Caribbean, agreements were very soon con¬
cluded between the European governments and
various agencies in Africa, India, Indonesia and
China for the importation of underpaid contract
(indentured) labour. With the arrival of several
hundred thousand of these coolies, recruited
from among the most deprived peoples, the
"new freedmen" inevitably found themselves
excluded from the labour market: the central
administrations had fixed their wages at four
times those of the new immigrants.
While the Second Republic in France gave
freedmen in its colonies citizenship rights, this
was not the case elsewhere. In the British West
Indies, for instance, decentralization of power
by the Colonial Office allowed the local
planters' assemblies to institute a means-tested
suffrage which disenfranchised the slaves
recently freed from their period of appren¬
ticeship. In the United States, when the Thir¬
teenth Amendment to the Constitution, offi¬
cially ending slavery in all the states of the
Union, was approved, the Ku Klux Klan came
into being in Tennessee in December 1865.
The southern states adopted a policy of dis¬
crimination and racial segregation similar to
apartheid, and it was to take another century to
bring this to an end. B
The quotations from
» the testimony of
slaves that accompany this
article are taken from
Bullwhip Days, edited by
James Mellon © 1988
Grove/Atlantic, New York.
NELLY SCHMIDT
is a French historian who is
engaged in research at France's
National Centre for Scientific
Research (CNRS). She is the
author of Victor Schoelcher and
La suppression de l'esclavage
aux Caraïbes, Une perspective
comparative, both published in
1994.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
if v*. ine rrenci
abolishes slaver
by Uuis Sala-Molins
I In 1783, a ten-year "boom" began for
I the slave trade. The price fetched by
slaves had never stood so high, and during
those ten years French ports dispatched more
than 1,100 slave ships to the coasts of Africa,
accounting for one-third of the entire turnover
of the slave trade in the eighteenth century.
From February 1788, when the Société des
Amis des Noirs (Society of Friends of the
Blacks) was founded, until 1793, 424 slave
ships one-eighth of the total trade set out
from French ports to take on board their car¬
goes of "black gold".
In 1791, the rallying cry of the insurgent
black leader Bouckman to the slaves gath¬
ered in the Bois Caiman forest was the signal
for a revolt that would not be relegated to
history like all its forerunners. The events
that were sparked off that night were to cul¬
minate in the eradication of slavery from San
Domingo and the forced removal of Haiti
from French domination.
It is true that, in pre-Revolutionary
France, the Société des Amis des Noirs had
worked to emancipate the mulattoes from
slavery and had advocated setting a series of
time-limits of up to as many as seventy years
for the gradual phasing-out of slavery after the
source of supply provided by the slave trade
had dried up. These time-limits were meant to
ensure that everything would proceed under
the orders of the whites, whose sovereignty
and ownership, which they regarded as sacro¬
sanct principles, would be respected. The fact
is that the "amis des Noirs", who were "Phys¬
iocrats" in politics and "enlightened" philoso¬
phers, were advocates of free labour in the
long run. They argued from time to time over
the prospective merits of setting up colonies
in Africa itself, where the whites would govern
the blacks infinitely better by engaging them
in "free labour" on their own continent rather
than by shipping them to the other side of the
Atlantic. Above all, however, they dilated
endlessly on the monstrous nature of slavery,
the intolerable human price of the slave trade,
the crime of seizing the blacks from their
homes, and the most appropriate length of
time that should be allowed to elapse between
the scheduled end of the slave trade and slavery
and the abolition of both practices once and
for all.
However, the slaves themselves in the
Bois Caiman laid down the absolutely non-
negotiable condition that there should be no
more slavery and no more paternalistic man¬
agement. In 1791, with gunpowder in their
belts, a machete in one hand and a torch in the
other, the slaves acted out the death sentence
of slavery. They had cast off their chains and
set themselves free. At last they were free!
The triumph of Toussaint Louverture
The authorities in Paris did not take kindly to
this unexpected outcome and pointed the
finger of guilt at the "amis des Noirs" who,
through their immoderate language and their
fiery rhetoric, were regarded as being respon¬
sible for the ransacking of the colony. The
"amis des Noirs" protested. They insisted
that they were in no way responsible and also
made it plain that they were only concerned
about the mulattoes. They had repeatedly
said that the blacks would have to wait in
calm, humility, patience and resignation, and
that they would be better off if they were
kept under control by the liberated mulat¬
toes who, in that capacity, would have inter¬
ests identical to those of the whites and would
seek to ensure peace and calm in the colony
and a profitable return on labour.
The Convention provided as best it could
for the defence of its island possessions in the
face of English and Spanish incursions, the
consequences of the slave revolt and the anti-
revolutionary and secessionist attitudes of the
local parliaments. It beat about the bush. It
held debates on the nature of the powers it
should delegate and ... on the colour of the
people to whom it would agree to delegate
them. Its immediate and constant aim lay in
trade and its colonial interests and in effectively
opposing the claims being made to its terri¬
tories by the other powers.
It was against this background that it sent
Sonthonax and Polverel to San Domingo to
inform those "who were not free" (since the
Convention, which was dragging its feet on
the "matter", deliberately refrained from men-
A French engraving dating from 1789
(artist unknown).
tioning the word "slave") that their recogni¬
tion as human beings would come more
quickly if they threw their weapons into the
rivers and went back to their picks and shovels.
No matter how well-disposed the envoys of
the Convention may have been to expediting
matters, the fact remains that it was the
"slaves" and Toussaint Louverture who
dragged the abolition decree out of them on 29
August 1793.
How could the people in Paris contend
with the threefold danger of secession, revolt
and seizure by the English which put such fear
into them? The only way of keeping the West
Indian possessions or what was left of
them was to arm the slaves so that, as free
men and citizens, they could serve as soldiers
and defend the land and the plantations with
their bodies still laced with the freshly inflicted
scars where the lash had bitten into them.
Then came the abolition decree of 1794
endorsing the uprising of Louverture in 1793.
Even people like the Abbé Grégoire were
taken aback by the suddenness of the events,
while others such as Robespierre were busy
with other matters. Danton expressed his sat¬
isfaction at the trick played on the English,
whose trade he predicted as coming to an end.
However, some very pretty phrases were also
heard that day: the least that could be done at
the height of the Enlightenment was to open
the floodgates of rhetoric and to congratulate
the Convention on having taken so imagina¬
tive a step. The event was even celebrated at a
splendid ceremony held at the Temple of
Reason.
LLUÍS SALA-MOLINS, a Catalan writer, is professor of
political philosophy at the University of Toulouse-ll Le
Mirail. He has recently published three books on the
legal arguments advanced to justify the enslavement
of blacks in the Americas and on the involvement of
Enlightenment thinkers in the history of the slave
trade. They are: Le Code Noir ou le calvaire de Canaan
(3rd edtion, 1993), L'Afrique aux Amériques, Le Code
Noir espagnol (1992) and Les misères des Lumières,
sous la raison l'outrage (1992).
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
From sub-Saharan Africa to southeast
Asia, ine iniernanonai Laoour urganisa*
tion is rooting out the last vestiges of
slavery. But it is easier to change laws
than to free children from exploitation in
factories and prostitution.
Forced labour
human bondage in today's world
by George Thullen
26
Slavery was a feature of many societies
until fairly recent times. For instance,
according to information brought to the atten¬
tion of the International Labour Organisation
(ILO) in 1992, it appears that slavery has not
been eradicated in Mauritania, despite being
outlawed by official decrees and constitutional
provisions. Lack of adequate and effective
inspection measures and of a mechanism to co¬
ordinate the struggle against slavery have ham¬
pered efforts to stamp out a practice deeply
rooted in the country's economy and culture.
Similarly, reports supplied to the United Nations
Working Group on Contemporary Forms of
Slavery showed that slavery and practices
analagous to slavery, such as certain forms of
serfdom, still exist throughout the country, and
that cases of kidnapping and sales of children and
their exploitation continue. Even where freed,
ex-slaves have been finding it very difficult to
support themselves away from their former
masters. The ILO's Committee of Experts has
asked the Government for information on spe¬
cific measures and policies which would lead to
a real abolition of slavery in Mauritania.
Traditional slavery also survives in modern-
day Sudan. Allegations of slavery in that country
reached the UN Working Group on Contem¬
porary Forms of Slavery for the first time in
1988 and were also discussed at the Interna¬
tional Labour Conference in 1989 and subse¬
quently. Indeed, as a result of that country's
civil war, slavery seems to be on the increase.
The Sudanese Government maintains that
the allegations are related to conflicts of a tribal
nature, such as disputes over pasture and water
resources in areas where there was an overlap of
tribes. As a result, each tribe involved in a dis¬
pute captures members of the other tribe or
tribes as hostages while waiting for the dispute
to be settled according to tribal traditions and
customs. However, the UN Special Rappor¬
teur on the situation of human rights in Sudan,
who visited the country in September and
December 1993, has concluded that reports and
eye-witness accounts reveal a great deal of con¬
sistency regarding the circumstances of abduc¬
tion, the locations of destination, the names of
locations where children and women are said to
be kept in special camps, and where people from
the northern Sudan, or even from abroad,
reportedly come to buy some of these people.
Debt bondage, a widespread evil
Sale or traffic of children, the Special Rapporteur
has noted, seems to be an organized and polit¬
ically motivated activity, of mass character.
Abductions of children have been repeatedly
reported, including the abduction in the summer
of 1993 of 217 children, mainly Dinka. The UN
Committee on the Rights of the Child, in a
report ofJanuary 1993, has also expressed con¬
cern regarding issues of forced labour and
slavery in Sudan. In the light of all this, the ILO
Committee of Experts has asked the Govern¬
ment to provide full information on measures
taken or envisaged to ensure that forced labour
practices are really eradicated.
Other forms of slavery, such as debt
bondage, or exploitation of or traffic in per¬
sons, particularly of women and children, are a
far more common occurrence. No region is
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
spared. Debt bondage is a mechanism whereby
an employer entraps a labourer by offering an
advance which he or she has to pay off from
future earnings. But because wages are generally
very low, and the employer frequently makes
deductions for accommodation or tools and
often levies fines for unsatisfactory work, the
worker is unable to repay. Instead, the debt
increases steadily and the employer may insist
that it be passed from parent to child or even
grandchild: there have been instances of people
slaving to pay off debts eight generations old.
Debt bondage is particularly widespread in
South Asia and in Latin America, and its victims
often tend to be the poorest, often tribal people,
who arc illiterate and relatively easy to deceive
and to keep in ignorance of their rights. If they
try to leave their employment they are usually
caught and returned by force, if not punished
severely or killed outright.
India and Pakistan have long faced some of
the most serious problems of bonded labour. In
India, the non-agricultural occupations in which
bonded labour has been identified include,
among others, stone quarrying, the brick-kiln
industry, fishing, building and construction,
forestry, carpet weaving and pottery-making,
with child labour found predominantly in carpet
weaving, glass-bead manufacturing and the
match and fireworks industries. Bonded labour
in Pakistan is very common in the brick-kiln
industry, but it is also found in other fields,
such as quarrying, shoemaking, carpet weaving
and in the making of bidis (cigarettes), as well as
in agriculture.
On paper, whether by Acts of Parliament or
by constitutional provisions, bonded labour
should have ceased to exist a long time ago. In
practice, however, enforcement of the legal texts
has been hampered by ingrained social, economic
and cultural patterns and practices. Action by
non-governmental organizations and trade
unions, combined with the effects of the media
and improved communications between various
parts of India is leading to growing public aware¬
ness of the existence of bonded labour and is
making it easier for the authorities to take the
requisite steps to stamp out the practice.
Pakistan officially abolished the bonded
labour system by an Act promulgated in March
1992 and there seems to be a strong commitment
in Government circles, up to the highest levels,
to make a clean break with past practices. The
Act provides that every bonded labourer stands
freed and discharged from any obligation to
render any bonded labour. One of Pakistan's
trade union federations, however, has alleged
that bonded labour continues to be practised in
many areas and industries, particularly in the
brick-kiln industry.
Forced labour of the bonded labour type
can also be found in other regions. The ILO
Committee of Experts has noted that in Peru, for
instance, as confirmed by a Government-
appointed committee, practices of debt bondage,
deceitful or violent recruitment of labour, sub¬
human conditions of work and the exploita¬
tion of children in the indigenous communi¬
ties of Atalaya are still current.
Exploitation of children
Unquestionably, as the ILO Committee of
Experts has put it "forced labour exploitation of
children, be it in forced child labour, child pros¬
titution, child pornography, be it in factories,
sweatshops, brothels, private houses or else¬
where, is one of the worst forms of forced
labour". This year the Committee has chosen to
condemn strongly the exploitation of children
for prostitution and pornography by tourists
and visitors from other countries. Eradication of
"these deplorable practices", it states, should
no longer be seen as a responsibility only of
the country in which it occurs, but as an inter¬
national responsibility. Yet child prostitution
for international tourist consumption is only
the tip of the iceberg recent studies show that
the largest share is for local consumption and
must be tackled there.
While child prostitution and pornography
may represent one of the worst forms of forced
child labour, millions of children are bonded
labourers, are kidnapped or otherwise lured
away from their families to be imprisoned in
sweatshops, to work "unseen" as domestic ser¬
vants or to be given or sold at a very young age
to another family. There they receive little or no
pay, arc stripped of any control over their own
lives, and arc often beaten, sexually abused,
starved and subjected to abnormal working hours
and hazardous working conditions. They are
deprived of the right to lead a normal childhood,
deprived of education, deprived of a future.
A direct contacts mission of the ILO to
Thailand in September 1993 reported that
SLAVERY
Men debased
The surest way of making people vile is to vilify them. Slavery debases
masters and slaves alike, hardens people's hearts, snuffs out morality and
paves the way for all manner of disasters. . . .
Abbé Grégoire
De la traite et de l'esclavage (1815)
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
despite existing laws for the protection of chil¬
dren, recruitment of children by force and
deception for work in factories, sweatshops or
brothels continued in Bangkok as well as in
the provinces. In a study of child labour con¬
ducted in 1986 by the National Youth Bureau
in the Prime Minister's Office, it was stated
that children lacked the opportunity to go home
for a visit, or even to get in touch with their
family, or were found to be confined, scolded
and physically and psychologically assaulted
by their employers. According to information
received by the ILO mission, such practices
continue to exist. One rescued boy, for instance,
who had been kidnapped at a railway station,
was forced with other children to work
extremely long hours, was beaten and was not
allowed to go out or look through the win¬
dows. As noted by the ILO's Committee of
Experts, another facet of forced labour in Thai¬
land is sexual exploitation of children. It is an
extremely serious problem there in terms of
both scale and complexity: it is hidden from
view, protected by gangs and mafias.
Effective policies to enhance social justice
and equity, says the ILO's Committee of
Experts, can go a long way to help children and
families left at the periphery of development
and contribute to the protection of children.
This is in essence the message of the Programme
of Action against Child Bondage adopted in
November 1992 by the Asian Regional Sem¬
inar on Children in Bondage, held in Islam¬
abad, Pakistan, and sponsored jointly by the
ILO and the UN Centre for Human Rights.
By subscribing to this Programme of Action,
the countries which participated Bangladesh,
India, Nepal, Pakistan, Sri Lanka and Thai¬
land have pledged themselves to "effective
and immediate abolition of child bondage" as a
priority goal of a national policy on children.
They have acknowledged that there must be a
firm political commitment, a clear and unam¬
biguous declaration against bondage, and a com¬
prehensive national policy and programme of
action covering legislative reforms, effective
enforcement systems, and a system of compul¬
sory and free education. All this would have to
be sustained by a vigorous media campaign
aimed at changing attitudes and values and at
engaging the public in the larger cause of
freedom and respect of human rights.
The ILO's Committee of Experts considers
that governments should redouble their efforts
in fighting forced child labour and punish those
guilty of it severely and in a manner commen¬
surate with the physical and moral harm done to
the children. To back governments in their fight
against forced labour exploitation of children,
the ILO launched at the end of 1991 an inter-
Indivisible freedom
Violence committed against the humblest member of the human race
affects the whole of humanity. We must all take an interest in oppressed
innocents, or else be victims in our turn, when somebody stronger
comes to enslave us. One man's freedom is part and parcel of universal
freedom. You cannot touch one without at the same time jeopardizing
the other.
Victor Schoelcher (1848)
national programme for the elimination of child
labour (known under the acronym "IPEC")
with a substantial financial contribution from the
Government of Germany. The elimination of
hazardous and bonded child labour is the pri¬
ority of this programme. In India, for example,
one of the first countries to participate, five
"action programmes" are being conducted in the
carpet industry of Uttar Pradesh and Bihar,
where the incidence of bonded child labour is
notoriously high; their aim is to rehabilitate
children who have been working in this industry,
and particularly those who have been liberated
from bondage.
Non-governmental bodies are a vital instru¬
ment in mobilizing public opinion and public
awareness. Thus, for example, at a meeting con¬
vened in The Hague in October 1993 at the ini¬
tiative of the Dutch economist and Nobel lau¬
reate Jan Tinbergen, he and four other Nobel
prizewinners, and representatives of non-gov¬
ernmental organizations and experts from dif¬
ferent parts of the world, laid down a strategy for
combating child exploitation around the world.
Since then, a further 104 Nobel prizewinners
have agreed to join in the campaign named
"Child Right Worldwide" to stop exploitation
of children.
GEORGE THULLEN,
of Ecuador, is the English-
language editor of the
International Labour
Organisation's annual World
Labour Report.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A NEW INTERNATIONAL PROJECT
THE SLAVE ROUTE
a crime without punishment
In September 1S34, at a meeting
held in Cotonou (Benin), Unesco
launched an international study
project on the slave trade which
will help to promote research and
other activities relating to this
major historical phenomenon.
Here Dotîdou Diene, the head of
Unesco's Division for Intercultural
Projects, talks about the new
Slave Route project.
How did the project come about?
The initiative came from Haiti and the
African countries, including Benin, which
is particularly concerned by the project. In
the days of slavery, its port of Ouidah, on
the west coast, was one of the leading cen¬
tres of the black slave trade. At the same
time, Benin was one of the few countries to
which slaves returned after they had been
set free, and even today many Beninese
families still have names of Brazilian origin.
It is doubtless this historical heritage that
prompted President Nicéphore Soglo to
give priority to the Slave Route and to
decide to host the Conference formally
launching the project in Cotonou.
What are the main features of the
project?
Its first objective is to re-examine a major
historical event over which, for a variety of
reasons, a veil has been cast by its European
perpetrators and African victims alike.
This will entail studying the slave trade
and its causes, and the manner and
sequence in which it proceeded. In other
words, it will mean retracing our steps
along the "middle passage". There is more
to the project than that, however. This
journey back in time is only one way of
understanding the events involved. The
most important thing is to analyse them
and shed light on their consequences. I
believe it is essential to take a closer look at
the paradox inherent in the fact that the ini¬
tial act of the black slave trade, barbaric as
it was, came strangely enough to be instru¬
mental in laying the foundations of a new
civilization. More than any other event in
history, the slave trade led, through bru¬
tality and coercion, to a far-reaching inter-
penetration of the African, European and
American continents. The massive dis¬
placement of slaves brought in its wake a
similar displacement of cultural values,
sensibilities and traditions.
Can you be more specific?
The slave trade had a cultural impact
first of all in Africa, where the violence
originated. But its consequences can also be
detected, in more or less disguised form,
among its European perpetrators. It influ¬
enced their ways of thinking, their forms of
artistic expession, and even their spiritual
lives. However, the cultural influences were
strongest in the Americas, the Caribbean
and the West Indies, where the actual phys¬
ical encounters took place. It is there that
cross-fertilization flourished. It began with
ethnic intermingling between blacks,
Indians and whites, despite the resistance
to it, as we well know. It was followed by
cultural intermingling, because the slaves'
ancestral traditions, which had become an
essential factor in their survival, were kept
alive and came to influence not only the
local cultures but also those imported from
Europe. Whether in music, poetry or other
areas, these encounters produced an extra-
The initial act of the black
slave trade, barbaric as it
was, came strangely
enough to be instrumental
in laying the foundations of
a new civilization.
ordinary mix that nobody could have pos¬
sibly foreseen. It created a whole give-and-
take relationship which still exists today
and is being projected into the future. Iden¬
tity is a process, the outcome of inter¬
mixing, of borrowing and appropriation.
So the Slave Route project is both
intercultural and interdisciplinary. Can
we expect it to give rise to activities
such as scientific debates, historical,
literary or musical research, cultural
events, exhibitions.and so on?
The Slave Route project had actually got
underway even before it was formally inau¬
gurated. When we asked the countries con¬
cerned for information on their projects, we
discovered that some of them had already
started work. This was the case, for instance,
of an exhibition entitled "Les anneaux de la
mémoire" which a group of intellectuals
from Nantes once one of France's largest
slave ports put together after several years'
work. A permanent exhibition is being pre¬
pared in Liverpool, once a British slave
port. In Africa, Senegal launched its Gorée-
Almadies Memorial project to create a his¬
torical monument on a small island in the
Atlantic from where millions of slaves were
shipped across the ocean. We have already
sponsored several exhibitions, including
one at Arc-et-Senans in eastern France on
art produced during the slave trade and
another at Nantes on the image of blacks in
advertising, and seminars. The proceedings
of one seminar on the abolition of slavery
held under the auspices of the University of
Paris VIII are being published jointly by
UNESCO and Paris VIII. We are aiming to
cover a very broad spectrum of activities,
situating them in a global context and pro¬
viding them with Unesco backing. The
Slave Route project sets out to bring people
together. 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Official abolition of slavery
SIGNIFICANT PAÏES
1793: San Domingo (Haiti).
1794: 4 February, the Convention, France's revolutionary
assembly, adopts a decree abolishing slavery in all the French
colonies.
1802: Napoleon Bonaparte restores the slave trade and slavery
in the French colonies.
1804: 1 January, San Domingo proclaims its independence as
Haiti.
1807: Great Britain and, later, Denmark prohibit vessels flying
under their national flags to participate in the slave trade.
1807: The United States of America abolishes the slave trade.
1815: The Congress of Vienna. The European nations
participating in the Congress ratify the decision to abolish the
slave trade but reserve the right to set a deadline for its
application. The illegal Atlantic slave trade still goes on.
1822: San Domingo
1823: Chile.
1826: Bolivia.
1829: Mexico.
1833-1838: British colonies.
1843: India. However, slaves are not emancipated.
1846: Tunisia.
1846-1848: The Danish Virgin Islands (St. Croix, St. John and St.
Thomas).
1847: The Ottoman Empire prohibits the slave trade in the Gulf
and closes public slave-markets in Constantinople.
1847: St. Barthélémy (then a Swedish colony).
1848: The French colonies.
1851: Colombia and Ecuador.
1853: Argentina.
1854: Venezuela.
1855: Peru.
1863: The Dutch Caribbean colonies of Curaçao, Bonaire, Aruba,
Saba, St. Eustatius, the Dutch part of St. Martin, and Dutch
Guiana (Suriname).
1865: The United States of America.
1869: Portugal.
1873: Puerto Rico. Application of the Moret law adopted by the
Spanish Cortes.
1880-1886: In Cuba, progressive application of the Moret law,
after a period of gradual emancipation following the Ten Years'
War of Independence (1868-1878).
1885: The Berlin Conference: Britain, France, Austria, Germany,
Russia, Spain, Portugal, Holland, Belgium, Italy, Sweden,
Denmark and the United States agree to "help in suppressing
slavery", although no direct measures are taken against the
slave trade in Africa.
1888: Brazil. Slaves in the country's provinces were gradually
emancipated during the second half of the 19th century.
1896: Sierra Leone.
1896: Madagascar.
1897: Zanzibar.
1900: Nigeria (in the British-occupied parts of the country).
1926: In Geneva, 44 countries ratify the Slavery Convention of
the League of Nations.
1928: Iran
1942: Ethiopia.
1952: Qatar
1962: Saudi Arabia.
1981: Mauritania.
20 books on slaver
The phenomenon of
slavery (philosophy,
anthropology, sociology)
The Problem ofSlavery in
Western Culture
David Brion Davis, Ithaca,
Cornell University Press,
1966, 505 pp. By the same
author: The Problem of
Slavery in the Age of
Revolution 1770-1823, Ithaca,
Cornell University Press,
1975,576 pp.
The Anthropology ofSlavery:
The Womb ofIron and Gold
Claude Meillassoux, Chicago,
University of Chicago Press,
1991,416 pp.
Ancient Slavery and Modern
Ideology
Moses Immanuel Finley, New
York, Viking Penguin, 1983,
208 pp.
The Arrogance ofRace:
historicalperspectives on
slavery, racism and social
inequality
George M. Frcdrickson,
Middletown, Conn.,
Wesleyan University Press,
1988,310 pp.
Slavery
Benjamin Whitaker (report
prepared by), Sub-
Commission on Prevention of
Discrimination and
Protection of Minorities, New
York, United Nations, 1984,
53 pp.
HISTORY OF THE SLAVE TRADE
Africa
Black Mother, the Years of the
African Slave Trade
Basil Davidson,
Boston/Toronto, Little,
Brown and Company, 1961,
311pp.
Transformations in Slavery, a
History ofSlavery in Africa
Paul E. Lovejoy, Cambridge,
Cambridge University Press,
1983, 348 pp.
At the Rendezvous of Victory
C.L.R. James, London,
Allison and Busby, 1984,
303 pp.
The African slave trade from
the fifteenth to the nineteenth
century
Paris, Unesco, 1979, 330 pp.
{General History ofAfrica:
Studies and documents 2).
Forced Migration: the Impact
of the Export Slave Trade on
African Societies
London, Hutchinson, 1982.
Equiano's Travels
ed. Paul Edwards,
London/Ibadan, Heinemann
Educational Books Ltd, 1967,
198 pp.
The Americas
Slavery and Social Death: A
Comparative Study
Orlando Patterson,
Cambridge Ma, Harvard
University Press, 1982, 528 pp.
From Slavery to Freedom: a
History ofNegro Americans
John Hope Franklin and
Alfred A. Moss Jr, New York,
Alfred A. Knopf Inc, 1987,
624 pp.
Africa in Latin America:
Essays in History, Culture
and Socialization
Manuel Moreno Fraginals,
New York, Holmes and Meier
Publishers, 1984, 342 pp.
West Indies and the
Caribbean
The Black Jacobins: Toussaint
Louverture and the Santo
Domingo Revolution
C.L.R. James, London,
Allison and Busby, 1980,
426 pp.
The Sociology ofSlavery
An analysis of the origins
development and structure of
Negro slave society in Jamaica
Orlando Patterson, London,
1967,310 pp.
African Slavery in Latin
America and the Caribbean
Oxford, Herbert Klein,
Oxford University Press, 1986.
The Arab World and the
Indian Ocean
Slavery in the Arab World
Murray Gordon, New York,
New Amsterdam Books,
1991,272 pp.
The Sulu Zone, 1768-1898: the
dynamics of external trade,
slavery and ethnicity in the
transformation ofa Southeast
Asian maritime state
James Francis Warren,
Singapore, Singapore
University Press, 1981, 390 pp.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
I
The international community against
slavery and forced labour
SLAVERY
1 The international community has
.. ~- proscribed slavery on a number of
occasions, one of the earliest being the
Congress of Vienna in 1815. The 1926
Slavery Convention of the League of
Nations was the first modern undertaking
to outlaw slavery and the slave trade, but
lacked formal procedures or institutions to
monitor violation. Forced labour the
usual purpose of slavery was targeted
by the International Labour Organisation
when it adopted the Forced Labour Con¬
vention (No. 29) in 1930.
Compliance by ratifying States with
its provisions is monitored, as with all the
ILO's Conventions, by the Committee of
Experts on the Application of Conven¬
tions and Recommendations. Set up to
supervise the application of ratified ILO
Conventions, this group of eminent jurists
from all over the world can also examine
allegations of violations submitted by
employers' or workers' organizations.
In 1957, the ILO went a step further
when it adopted the Abolition of Forced
Labour Convention (No. 105), which
banned forced labour altogether, whether
exacted, for example, as a means of polit¬
ical coercion or as punishment for striking
or other infringements of labour disci¬
pline.
The United Nations for its part
expanded the scope of the 1926 Slavery
Convention by adopting a Supplementary
Convention on the Abolition of Slavery,
the Slave Trade, and Institutions and Prac¬
tices Similar to Slavery in 1956. However,
it was not until 1974 that a monitoring
mechanism was established, a five-member
Working Group on Contemporary Forms
of Slavery.
The ILO is an active partner of the
Working Group and the two complement
one another in that each tends to acquire
information from different sources. The
ILO relies chiefly on governments,
employers' organizations and trade unions,
while most submissions to the Working
Group come from non-governmental
organizations.
Forced Labour Convention
(No.29), 1930
Article 1:
Each Member of the International Labour
Organisation which ratifies this Conven¬
tion undertakes to suppress the use of
forced or compulsory labour. . . .
Article 2:
For the purposes of this Convention the
term forced or compulsory labour shall
mean all work or service which is exacted
from any person under the menace of any
penalty and for which the said person has
not offered himself voluntarily. . . .
Article 25:
The illegal exaction of forced or compul¬
sory labour shall be punishable as a penal
offence, and it shall be an obligation on
any Member ratifying this Convention
to ensure that the penalties imposed by
law are really adequate and strictly
enforced.
Abolition of Forced Labour
Convention (No.105), 1957
Article 1:
Each Member of the International Labour
Organisation which ratifies this Conven¬
tion undertakes to suppress and not to
make use of any form of forced or com¬
pulsory labour:
(a) as a means of political coercion or
education or as a punishment for holding
or expressing political views or views ide¬
ologically opposed to the established polit¬
ical, social or economic system;
(b) as a method of mobilizing and using
labour for purposes of economic devel¬
opment;
(c) as a means of labour discipline;
(d) as a punishment for having partic¬
ipated in strikes;
(e) as a means of racial, social, national
and religious discrimination.
Article 2:
Each Member of the International
Labour Organisation which ratifies this
Convention undertakes to take effective
measures to secure the immediate and
complete abolition of forced or compul¬
sory labour as specified in Article 1 of this
Convention.
Ïprice of a living tool
r cost price
Purchase of slave
21 September r 4 service guns
,vears of age purchased Dy dinggun
Chiandvuba.
5 service guns
50 pounds gunpowder
10 bottles brandy
Left, an extract from the "Ledger of
extraordinary expenditure for the account
of the [French] King's trade in
Madagascar", 1767.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN
tion
PIRATED AFRICAN ART
More than $600 million in profits are
stolen each year from the African arts
as a result of international piracy, said
the president of the African Association
Against Pirating (ACOP) at a recent
conference held in Brazzaville (Congo)
to evaluate the implementation of
UNESCO's 1 980 "Recommendations
concerning the status of the artist".
More than 100 musicians, painters,
sculptors, writers, actors, scholars and
representatives of non-governmental
art associations from 30 African and
European countries attended the
conference, which was organized by
Unesco, ACOP and the Congolese
government. Participants noted sadly
that little has been done to implement
the Unesco Recommendations and that
artists are being increasingly
marginalized.
UNESCO AND CNRS
SIGN SCIENCE TRAINING
AGREEMENT
Unesco and the French National
Centre for Scientific Research (CNRS)
have signed an agreement on training
programmes in the natural sciences.
The agreement is the first of its kind to
help French-speaking researchers from
developing countries to train in France
and to enable French experts in
ecology, nutrition and certain diseases
such as Aids to travel to these
countries to meet local researchers and
share their expertise through lectures.
Unesco and CNRS will share the costs
equally. The programmes focus on
French-speaking Africa and countries
such as Egypt and Viet Nam where
French is spoken but is not the official
language. Unesco has signed similar
agreements with English-speaking
research institutes.
32
PEDALLING FOR THE PLANET
Two young Englishmen, environmental
consultant Steve Smith, 27, and
musician Jason Lewis, 26, have set off
on a round-the-world "Pedal for the
Planet" expedition on push-bikes as
part of a campaign to promote
environmental awareness and
international understanding. Using only
the strength of their leg muscles, they
will cover about 20,000 miles across
UNESCO'S DIRECTOR-GENERAL
CONDEMNS TERRORISM
AND INTOLERANCE
"Education is a fundamental
right," said Mr. Federico Mayor,
Director-General of Unesco, in
a statement condemning
terrorist threats to students and
teachers in Algeria, where a
fundamentalist group warned
students and teachers to stay
away from high schools and
universities and threatened to
blow up or burn any schools
that remained open. In recent
months some 30 teachers have
reportedly been murdered and
almost 20 schools and
universities have been damaged.
Mr. Mayor also spoke in the
spirit of the tolerance, non
violence and dialogue that
inform Unesco's activities when
he expressed concern about
another violation of a
fundamental right, that of
freedom of expression, and
called for steps to ensure the
freedom and safety of the
Bangladeshi writer, Taslima
Nasreen, who is under a death
threat because of her writings.
"It is deplorable," Mr. Mayor
said, "that religions, which are
based on compassion and love,
can be used to express
intolerance and contempt for
the lives of those who think
differently."
Europe, America and Asia, as well as
travelling 9,000 miles across the
Atlantic and Pacific Oceans in a unique
8-metre pedal-powered boat. During
the expedition they will be talking to
children and teachers in 40 Unesco
Associated Schools about how different
cultures can live together in harmony
with the environment. Unesco's
Associated Schools project is an
international network of some 3,000
educational institutions in 1 20
countries. It was created in 1953 to
encourage young people to work
together for a better future.
UNESCO HONOURS YOUNG
REPORTERS
On the outskirts of Lima, Peru, an old
man sifts through the ashes of giant pits
filled with burnt rubbish in the hopes
of finding metal scraps to sell at a local
market. His story is told in The King of
the Ashes, a video which was awarded
Unesco's Gold Medal at the Fourth
International Festival of Young
Reporters held last June in Port-de-
Bouc, France, by Unesco and the
World Federation of Unesco Clubs
and Associations (WFUCA). The
Festival, which centred on an
international competition of short
video news reports by young video
artists between the ages of 1 3 and 30,
attracted 1 20 students and reporters
from 26 countries. Workshops on the
practical and ethical dimensions of
audiovisual journalism were also held
as part of the Festival. Other prize-
winning videos included Invalid (Russia)
in which a man with severely deformed
limbs and an enormous head
remembers being once told by doctors
that he was better suited for scientific
experiment than a normal life and talks
proudly about his wife and job; Vettiyan,
the story of young Indian children who
work in factories, putting matches in
small boxes; and L'Aniste artisan, in
which children in a small Tunisian
village are enchanted by a would-be
magician who makes cartoons with an
old camera.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY BY FEDERICO MAYOR
The challenge ofculturalpluralism
i believe that the coming cen¬
tury will give increased
prominence to culture. On the
world map, the imprint of cul¬
ture is proving more perma¬
nent than the overprint of pol¬
itics. Culture is emerging as a
major factor in relations within
and between nations, and in
intercommunal living. In these
circumstances, we find our¬
selves confronted by an increas¬
ingly urgent question: what can and should be done to promote
genuine cultural pluralism locally and in the world at large?
The very concept of culture is notoriously difficult to
define a liquid in an age of solids, as it has been described.
However, we might not go far wrong if we were to describe it
as everything we create and preserve as a group or in a wider
context as a species. Such a definition has the advantage of
encompassing culture both in its restricted sense of the arts and
in its broader anthropological sense of a "whole way of life,
material, intellectual and spiritual". It makes the link between
artistic creation and the creativity of everyday life. It also
explains the characteristic diversity of cultures, since creativity
and diversity are synonymous. It points, finally, to the essen¬
tial problem posed by cultural difference, which relates to the
permanent tension between creation and preservation at the
heart of culture itself. Our behaviour is largely shaped by the
interplay of these contending forces within a given cultural
character.
Language, one of the main vehicles of culture, highlights the
problem inherent in cultural diversity. Languages do more
than map a given reality according to different codes. They
determine to some extent the way in which we view that
reality. The implications of such linguistic factors for our rela¬
tionships with each other and our environment are far-reaching
indeed. Linguistic diversity must be seen as an essential resource,
and its preservation assumes the same importance as the pro¬
tection of bio-diversity in general.
Yet language differences as the Tower of Babel myth
underlines can also give rise to cultural misunderstanding and
even conflict. The reason for this may well be as George
Steiner has argued that there is an inherent duality in our use
of language: it serves as a means of communication but also of
affirming our separateness. The continuous creation of private
sub-languages within language slang and jargon would
support this view. Language is to this extent a form of "shared
secrecy" as well as "shared expression".
What is true of language is true of culture. Our world
needs a diversity of cultural viewpoints, characterized by atti¬
tudes of openness and responsiveness rather than mistrust
and rejection. One of the most urgent tasks at the present
time in a world of ever closer cultural contacts is to
encourage recognition of the rights of others and to help those
whose cultural rights have been disregarded to maintain and
develop their identity. This is the challenge of cultural pluralism.
The achievement of such pluralism requires that a sense of
cultural difference be complemented by a recognition of wider
cultural affinities. The great masterworks of cultureand of
nature are of inestimable value since they are perceived
instinctively by most people as part of a common human her¬
itage. Unesco has embodied this concept of a common heritage
in its World Heritage Convention, under which over 400 cul¬
tural and natural sites in 95 countries have been inscribed on
the World Heritage List in recognition of their outstanding uni¬
versal value. The notion of universality enshrined in the world
heritage is a paradigm for the promotion of cultural pluralism.
A SHARED HERITAGE
The shared heritage transcends, of course, the sites and mon¬
uments that constitute the wonders of the modern world.
Our varied cultures have to a greater extent than is generally
realized a common history and have been mutually enriched
by their contacts down the ages. To promote awareness of
these links UNESCO is engaged in a series of major projects on
the historical interchanges between cultures and is supporting
the creation of networks of cultural institutions in different
world regions to promote intercultural exchanges.
To talk of cultural pluralism in today's world is to be con¬
stantly reminded of how far removed we are from our goal.
The reality in many parts of the globe is all too often one of cul¬
tural confrontation and conflict. The causes of such antago¬
nism are obviously inseparable to some degree from prob¬
lems such as poverty, overpopulation, environmental
degradation and global asymmetries of all kinds. However,
some tensions are inherent in cultural contacts themselves.
UNESCO is currently engaged in studying potential causes of
cultural conflict and is exploring in its Culture of Peace pro¬
gramme how cultural initiatives can be employed in confused
post-conflict situations.
I believe that action of this kind is inherently worthwhile
because of the catalytic effect it can have. Dropping a pebble in
a pond is a small gesture that can spread ripples far and wide.
We must never tire of making the gesture that helps to promote
cultural pluralism and the values of democracy, tolerance, jus¬
tice and peace that it implies.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
^^^m Mn4.;
The Danube delta
Ä place the gods forgot'
byMateiCazacu
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
I
34
t matters little whether scientists
consider the Danube delta as
being only 7,000 years old and
treat it as if it were born yesterday. In
the eyes of the traveller, the delta is a
place the gods forgot, where land and
water still merge imperceptibly into one
another, where everything river, sea,
silt, sand is tinted with ochre. Over its
entire expanse of 3,500 square kilome¬
tres ... it is impossible to tell where the
waves end and where the sand of the
river banks begins. And the same doubt
persists over a swathe 100 kilometres
wide right down to the Black Sea	
"Yet the solid mass carried down by
the Danube is encroaching on the sea at
a rate of ten metres every year. Vegeta¬
tion grows on it haphazardly, forming a
carpet ofwhite flowers. But ifyou try to
pick them, you fall into the water. You
may think you can see foam, but all you
are seeing is sand. One night we could
not moor our boat because the reeds
were drifting, forming an island several
kilometres long. Animals make the same
mistake and I have seen them drown in
the broad alluvial valley of the Balta.
"The delta is a world still in the
making, giving off the raw smell of fresh
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
A carpet of
whiteflowers.
Butifyoutryto
pick them,
youfall into the
water.
a
it collects on its 2,850-kilometre course,
with its average stream-flow of 6,500
cubic metres per second. Europe's
biggest river after the Volga, it has a
catchment area of more than 800,000
square kilometres, where the rivers of
central and southeastern Europe, Aus¬
tria, Germany and Hungary all come
together, as it flows through the former
Yugoslavia, Romania, Bulgaria and
Ukraine.
Sacred waters
For the people of Antiquity who lived
along its middle and lower reaches, the
Danube was a sacred river. Its waters
purified warriors before they set out to
do battle, and sacrifices were made to it,
in particular by the emperor Trajan, who
gave thanks to it for its benevolence to
the Roman army during its campaigns in
the 2nd centuryA.D. against the Dacians
living in the Danube plain and the
Carpathians. On Trajan's column in
Rome, the river is represented in the
shape of a bearded giant. Trajan was the
first person to cross the Danube on a
stone bridge, built by the architectApol-
lodorus of Damascus in 105 A.D.
The ancient Greeks looked upon the
delta as a self-contained country
bounded by seven, five or three arms of
the river, depending on the seasons. In
the course of time, at least four of the
river's outlets became silted up and gave
rise to innumerable freshwater channels
Above, aerial view of the
Danube delta.
Right, young Lipovan
women.
seaweed, moist earth, darting fish and
still warm caviar	
"There is no sign ofman having ever
lived here, no trace of history having
been written on the elements, which
continue on their unwavering course.
There is nothing for us to understand,
except that time and space are infinite."1
This description of the Danube delta,
which dates from 1936, is still true today
apart from the figures, which keep on
changing. The delta now covers an area
of more than 5,500 square kilometres,
since the Danube each year carries
down some 200 million tons ofsilt which 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Fishing is still one of the main
activities of the people of the
Danube delta.
and lakes separated from the sea by
floating or fixed islands covered in reeds
'and trees such as poplar, oak, willow and
alder.
The names ofthe three arms through
which the Danube empties into the
Black Sea are, from north to south,
Chilia, Sulina and Sfintu Gheorghe (St.
George). These hark back to the times of
the ancient Greeks (Chilia means
"monk's cell" and Sulina "channel" or
"tube") and to the presence there in the
Middle Ages of Italians, or rather
Genoans, whose patron was St. George.
Along with Istria, located further south,
they were the site of trading posts and
later of cities, from which ships loaded
with salted and smoked fish, cereals,
honey, furs and slaves set out for Greece
and Italy.
For the sailors of ancient times, the
Black Sea the Pontus Etudnus ofAntiqu¬
ity into which the Danube flows,
marked the limit of the known world.
They plied its inhospitable waters, buf-
fetted byviolent winds, until 6 December,
the feast-day of St. Nicholas, the patron
saint of sailors, when navigation came
to a halt by then the waters of the
Danube and even the sea had often
started to freeze over and only started
again at Easter.
Birdlife in danger
Legend has it that the island of Peuce
(the Greek for "poplar") in the heart of the
delta was once occupied by a mysterious
kingdom inhabited either by Amazons
or as would be more consistent with
historical fact by tribes of Germanic
origin. Off the mouth of the Danube lies
the island of Leuce (the Greek for
"white"), now known as Snake Island,
which belongs to Russia. According to
Greek mythology, it was the site of the
entrance to the Kingdom of the Dead
^^ . and also ofa cult to Achilles, who is sup-
wD posed to have taken refuge there.
As in ancient times, the Danube delta
today is a stopping-off point for birds
flying from central and northern Europe
on their annual migration to the
Mediterranean. More than 300 species
have been recorded, 176 ofwhich breed
there, including cormorants (3,000 pairs)
and pygmy cormorants (2,500 pairs,
comprising 61 per cent of the world's
population), while pelicans (2,500 pairs,
comprising 50 per cent ofthe Palaearctic
breeding population), 287,500 red-
breasted geese (a threatened species),
and hundreds of thousands of white-
fronted geese and ducks, egrets, herons
and a variety of birds of prey, including
a few pairs of rare white-tailed eagles.
The marsh tern colonies are particu¬
larly notable.
Otters, weasels and mink are to be
found on the floating islands. Fish are
another source ofwealth of the Danube
delta and lakes: more than sixty species
have been identified, including forty-
five native to the Danube and its tribu¬
taries, plus fifteen marine species. Some
of these, such as sturgeon, whose eggs
provide caviar, swim upriver to spawn,
while other species, such as the eel,
swim downstream into the sea.
However, for the past fifty years or
so, the fauna and flora of the Danube
the delta has the world's largest area of
reedbeds have been threatened by pol¬
lution, which has caused considerable
damage. The fish catch has plummeted.
Barely 20 tons of sturgeon were caught
in 1989, only 2 per cent of the amount
caught a century ago. In the last ten
years alone, five species of birds have
disappeared, eight have declined in
number, twenty-seven have become
rare and eighteen are on the verge of
extinction.
This critical situation is primarily due
to the growing imbalance caused to the
fragile ecosystem of the Danube delta by
such factors as the drying up and
dredging of lakes and canals such as
Braila lake and the Caraorman canal;
the introduction of agriculture, espe¬
cially maize-growing, on an area of 420
square kilometres, less than half of
which have proved productive; the
widening of canals to enable them to
take ocean-going vessels that are too
large for the Danube-Black Sea Canal
opened in 1984; and the intensive har¬
vesting of reeds with heavy-duty
machinery in order to provide feedstock
for paper and cellulose mills, such as
that at Calarasi upstream of the delta.
Increasing protection
In addition, there has been a dramatic
increase in the pollution of the waters of
the Danube. Many factories and agro-
industrial complexes are dumping phos¬
phates, nitrates, oil residues, mercury
and pesticides into the river and its trib¬
utaries. Urban sewers release their efflu¬
ents directly into the river without prior
treatment and waste water discharges
trigger off epidemics of diseases such
as swine fever, hepatitis B and cholera.
At the other end of the chain, the sit¬
uation in the Black Sea is just as disas¬
trous: 80 per cent of the fish species
caught in 1960 (twenty-one out of
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
twenty-six) have now disappeared and
the tendency for underwater life to be
destroyed still goes on.2
The reaction of the Romanian and
Ukrainian authorities (20 per cent of the
delta is on Ukrainian territory) to this
ecological catastrophe is still rather hes¬
itant, owing to lack of resources.
It is true that a promising start has
been made by halting drainage work in
1990, including the site as a biosphere
reserve on the World Heritage List in
1991, and setting up a Danube Delta
Institute at Tulcea to study and mon¬
itor the region. However, if the current
trend is to be reversed, assistance from
the international community will be
needed. In September 1990, a mission
from the World Conservation Union
(IUCN) consisting of experts from a
number of international organizations,
including Unesco and the Worldwide
Fund for Nature (WWF), visited the
delta. Its proposals and recommenda¬
tions have still by no means all been
implemented. However, Romania's
adoption in 1993 of a law aimed at
strengthening the protection ofthe delta
is a step in the right direction. Mecha¬
nized reed harvesting and reclamation
works to allow ocean-going vessels to
sail through the delta have been gradu¬
ally reduced and a policy has been
drawn up for the natural rehabilitation
ofthe polders and replanted forest areas.
The delta is also home to human set¬
tlements. It is inhabited by some 20,000
people, mainly fishermen. More than 80
per cent of them are Lipovans Russians
belonging to Orthodox sects which were
persecuted by the official Church and
the Czars and took refuge in the delta.
Their numbers have declined sharply,
from 30,000 some fifty years ago to only
about 12,000 at the present time.
1 Odette Arnaud, Pêcheurs de rêves,
Editions de la Nouvelle Revue Critique,
Paris, 1936, p. 22.
2 John Pomfret, "Communism's messiest
legacy is a gasping Black Sea", International
Herald Tribune, 21 June 1994.
MATEI CAZACU,
a Romanian-born historian, is a research assistant
at the French National Centre for Scientific Research
(CNRS). He has published a number of studies and
books including L'Histoire du prince Dracula en
Europe centrale et orientale au 15' siècle (1988)
and La Moldavie ex-soviétique: histoire et enjeux
actuels (1993).
80 per cent of
thefish species
caught in 1960
have now
disappeared
Below, fishing boats at Sfintu
Gheorghe, on the southern arm
of the delta.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
T T anniversary XX
nermann von îlelmholtz
Physiologist and physicist
38
TheGerman philosopher and scientist Hermann
von Helmholtz was born in Potsdam in 1821,
the eldest son ofa secondary school teacher. He
is remembered for his statement of the law of the
conservation of energy, which holds that the amount
of energy in the universe is always the same, and for
his major contributions to optics, physiology, elec¬
trodynamics and other branches of science.
<. Helmholtz showed a keen interest in nature from
an early age, and became consumed by a passion "for
discovering the causal relationship between natural
phenomena". At that time, however, physics offered
few career prospects, and since his father could not
afford to pay for him to study the subject, he opted for
medicine instead. He enlisted in the Prussian army as
a doctor, in exchange for which he received a medical
education in Berlin virtually free of charge.
Looking back as a man of seventy on his early
years, Helmholtz said: "Young people like to come to
grips with the most intractable problems from the
very beginning. I therefore turned my attention to the
enigmatic nature of the vital force". The problem
continued to intrigue him after he had taken up his
duties as an army doctor, and he started to examine
its implications for nature as a whole, not just for
living beings. The question he asked was: "What sort
of relationship must exist between the different forces
in nature if perpetual motion cannot provide an
explanation covering every eventuality?" (The pos¬
sibility of a perpetual motion machine had been
rejected by scientists in the late eighteenth century).
In his study of the conservation of energy, he
drew on his knowledge of mathematics, and in 1847
delivered an epoch-making paper on the subject to
the newly founded Berlin Physical Society. As a
"callow" young doctor, he had half-expected his find¬
ings to be received with amused tolerance by the
eminent physicists in the audience, only to discover
to his astonishment that they were determined to
"dispute the truth of the law and, in their diatribe
against Hegel's natural philosophy, to look upon my
own work as likewise being the rambling of an undis¬
ciplined mind". Fortunately, friends of his own age
present at the meeting thought differently and
greeted him with wild applause. His paper has been
described as "one of the first, and certainly the
clearest, statements of the principle of the conser¬
vation of energy." A few years later the theory of the
conservation of energy had become the most widely
accepted tenet of physics.
Thanks to his growing scientific reputation,
Helmholtz was released from his military obliga¬
tions and in 1848 went on to teach anatomy at the
Berlin Academy ofFine Arts. In 1850, he was made an
assistant professor of physiology at the University
of Königsberg. Subsequently, after a brief interlude at
the University ofBonn, in 1858 he became head of the
Institute ofPhysiology specially created for him at the
University of Heidelberg.
Although he was unable to devote all his time to
physics, his main interest, he made a virtue out of
by Reinald Schröder
necessity by applying physics to the study ofhuman
beings, thereby providing a modern basis for physi¬
ology as a natural science. This approach proved to be
particularly fruitful in the study of sensory organs in
which physical stimuli are converted into physiolog¬
ical signals.
While preparing his first lecture at Königsberg
Helmholtz hit on the idea of the ophthalmoscope, the
scientific accomplishment which brought him the
greatest fame. It was known that cats' eyes shine at
night because of the light reflected from the retina.
Helmholtz therefore designed an instrument which, by
focusing light on the retina, made it possible to examine
the eye through a magnifying lens. As a result of this dis¬
covery, a number of illnesses could be studied for the
first time through direct observation of the eye.
Helmholtz's theories ofcolour vision and musical
harmony were also instrumental in relating physics to
physiology and were to have far-reaching conse¬
quences for our knowledge of the mechanisms of
hearing and vision.
Despite these great successes in his specialized
field, Helmholtz wrote to his friend Emil Du Bois-
Reymond that "he had lost interest in physiology and
was only really interested in mathematical physics".
When Germany's most prestigious chair of physics
at the University ofBerlin became vacant, as Du Bois-
Reymond later put it, "the unthinkable happened: a
medical doctor and professor of physiology was
appointed".
The Berlin post was admirably suited to
Helmholtz's talents and temperament. From 1885
onwards, however, he began to suffer from poor
health. He was gratified to be appointed Chairman of
the new Imperial Institute of Physical Technology
responsible for supervising Germany's system of
weights and measures, a post which enabled him to
devote much ofhis energy to scientific research. Active
to the end, he died on 8 September 1894 of a brain
haemorrhage.
Hermann von Helmholtz
(1821-1894)
REINALD SCHRÖDER
is a German journalist and
publisher specializing in the
history of science and
technology. He is the author of a
number of books, including a
study of the industrialization of
the German printing industry in
the 19th century, published in
1993.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
SAYING THE ARAL:
THE DRAMA OF
CENTRAL ASIA'S
GREAT LAKE
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
In the wake oîperestroïka, banner
headlines such as "Aral Sea being
strangled to death" have brought
home to the world in the last few
years the scale of the ecological cat¬
astrophe caused by the gradual
drying-up ofthis vast lake wrongly
called a "sea" located in Central
Asia, in what used to be the Soviet
Union.
"For the first time in the history of
humanity", writes Professor Nikita
Glazovsky, First Deputy Director of
the Institute of Geography of the
Russian Academy ofSciences, "a lake
whose surface area is greater than
that of some countries is disap¬
pearing through human agency. The
deterioration of the environment is
responsible for declining health stan¬
dards among the population and the
growing child mortality rate. It is also
having a far-reaching impact on the
region's economic development."
Before 1960, theAral had a surface
area of66,000 square kilometres and
was the world's fourth largest lake,
but it has now slipped back to sixth
place. Following the collapse of the
Soviet Union, its catchment area is
now divided among five indepen¬
dent Republics Kazakhstan, Kyr-
gyzstan, Uzbekistan, Tajikistan and
Turkmenistan. In the early 1960s, the
lake's average depth was 53.4 metres
and had notvaried by more than one
metre since the beginning of the cen¬
tury. Today it is no more than 38
metres. Thousands ofworkers were
employed in the fishing industry
and in 1962, nearly 40,000 tons of
fish were delivered to the canning
plants in the surrounding region.
Stockraising was also a flourishing
activity. The lake shore was girdled
by native forests, known as tungai,
and marshes whose flora and fauna
had adapted to the salinity of the
water. Now, its two former ports of
Munyak and Aral'sk are situated
some 40 kilometres inland. Their
fishing fleets, stranded high and dry
and rusting away, bear all the signs
of a ships' graveyard.
Soviet scientists started to sound
the alarm at the beginning of the
1970s, but the Presidium of the
Supreme Soviet did not get around
to discussing the problem until
1986. It took twenty years for inter¬
national public opinion to get
moving. The geographer Monique
Mainguet, former head of the
Desertification Control Programme
Centre of the United Nations Envi¬
ronment Programme in Nairobi
(Kenya), has spent many years
studying the Aral. This is how she
describes the present situation:
"Because the water from the Aral's
two main tributaries, the Amu
Dar'ya and the Syr Dar'ya, has been
used for industrial-scale irrigated
cotton-growing, the lake's volume
has shrunk by 60 per cent and its
shoreline has receded by as much as
65 kilometres in some places. In
1942, its salinity level stood at 10
grams/litre, but it has now risen to
30 grams/litre and is responsible
for the disappearance of the original
flora and fauna. There is only one
remaining fish variety, and this is
unsuited to the once thriving fishing
All that remains of once thriving
fishing ports are rusting hulks
stranded on the sand.
and canning industries. As a result
of the emergence ofpart of the lake
bed above the water-line, salt par¬
ticles are picked up by the wind and
are carried for distances of hun¬
dreds of kilometres, polluting the
air and soil and both surface and
deep water deposits. The defects in
the irrigation systems responsible
for salt encroachment are com¬
pounded by the pollution caused
by the uncontrolled use of fertil¬
izers, herbicides, defoliants and pes¬
ticides. Drinking water and fruit and
vegetables have become toxic, par¬
ticularly for children".
A REGION INHABITED
SINCE THE OLD STONE AGE
Turania, the name by which geog¬
raphers often call Turkestan, is a
semi-desert plain covering an area
of 3.5 million square kilometres,
with a climate rather similar to that
of the sub-Saharan Sahel in Africa.
In their book on the Aral, Monique
Mainguet and the bio-geochemist
René Létolle explain the lake's role in
these terms: "Recent meteorolog¬
ical studies have shown that,
through evaporation from the lake
surface, the Aral created a sort of
mattress composed of moister air,
which varied with the seasons and
rose to an altitude of 9 kilometres.
The influence ofthis mattress used to
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
extend for distances ofseveral hun¬
dred kilometres southeast ofthe lake.
Through its local regulating effects,
Lake Aral gives rise to gende breezes
which are instrumental in creating a
milder climate well beyond the lake's
immediate shoreline". One of the
consequences of the drying-up of
the lake has accordingly been a
change in climate, which is gradually
growing harsher.
Even so, archaeological excava¬
tions have shown that the region
has been inhabited since the Lower
Palaeolithic era, in other words for
the past 100,000-300,000 years.
Although the arid plain is swept by
dust-laden winds, it forms a land
corridor in which a variety ofmodes
of production have been practised
at different periods. In the fifth mil¬
lennium B.C., agricultural settle¬
ments already existed in the
southern part ofpresent-day Turk¬
menistan. By the fourth millen¬
nium, cattle, sheep and goats were
being raised, and wheat, pome¬
granates and apricots were grown.
Irrigation was a very ancient prac¬
tice dating back to the eighth or
ninth millennia B.C., but owing to
its limited scale, it did not yet rep¬
resent a threat to the ecosystem.
COTTON-GROWING AND
AGRICULTURAL OVER-EXPLOITATION
The real danger came with mecha¬
nization. By 1843, there were already
more than thirty large canals and
an extensive secondary irrigation
network. "In 1918, during the
Russian Revolution," write Monique
Mainguet and René Létolle, "Lenin
signed a decree allocating 50 million
gold roubles to the development of
irrigation". In the agricultural sector,
priority was given to growing
cotton, for which there was a heavy
demand not only from the Soviet
textile industry but for use as gun-
cotton. Since a hot climate and
abundant amounts of water are
needed to grow cotton, the crop can
be said to be at the origin of the eco¬
logical disaster of the Aral.
In June 1993, Michael H. Glantz,
Alvin Z. Rubinstein and Igor Zonn
published a detailed study of theAral
in the magazine Global Environ¬
mental Change., inwhich theynoted:
"... in 1953 soil scientistViktorKovda
captured the spirit ofsocialist trans¬
formation when he wrote: 'the Party
. . . and the Soviet government are
doing everything possible to trans¬
form nature, to do awaywith deserts,
to attain a further big rise in agricul¬
tural productivity. . . . The grand pro¬
jects outlined by Stalin's genius . . .
will make it possible to master the
forces of nature in the U.S.S.R'.
Khruschev later reasserted a well-
known Soviet saying that his society
could not wait for nature to pro¬
duce benefits and that society must
extract those benefits from nature".
It was this short-sighted view of
things that was to cast such a blight
on the future.
It is true that, at the end of the
1980s, "modern" agriculture in
Turania supplied the former Soviet
Union with 95 per cent of its cotton,
40 per cent of its rice and 30 per
cent of its fruit. But at what a cost!
The figures for the agricultural
inputs responsible for pollution are
very impressive, ranging from 900
kilograms of fertilizer per hectare
for rice to 1,500 kilograms ofammo¬
nium sulphate, 100-200 kilograms
ofpotassium chlorate and 200-250
kilograms of superphosphate per
hectare for cotton and, to cap it all,
54 kilograms of pesticides per
hectare compared with only 3.5
kilograms in the rest of the Soviet
Union. Between 1960 and 1990,
118,000 tons of the highly toxic defo¬
liant known as "Agent Orange", used
by the Americans inViet Nam, were
sprayed in the Karakalpakstan
region south of the lake alone.
As a result of these practices,
there was a sharp decline in the
quality of the water in village wells
and ponds. People's health was
threatened: "the child mortality rate
of 51 per thousand is more than
double that for the former Soviet
Union, and 70 per cent of all adults
and 60 per cent of all children have
health problems". These figures
quoted by Monique Mainguet and
René Létolle are still increasing.
WHAT CAN BE DONE?
Professor Glazovsky ascribes the
drama of the Aral to the manage¬
ment errors made by Soviet officials,
who were paid according to the
number ofkilometres of canal they
built. Itwas therefore to their advan¬
tage to continue expanding an irri¬
gation network consuming vast
quantities ofwater. "One possibility
considered was to divert water to
theAral from Siberia or the Caspian
Sea. The same old mistakes should
not be made bypersisting in digging
more canals. The first step should
be to adopt legislation common to all
five Republics, but this will not be
easy because they do not necessarily
have the same interests."
Does the answer lie in action by
international organizations such as
the World Bank, the Global Envi¬
ronment Fund, or the United
Nations Development or Environ¬
ment Programmes? The Republics
concerned have appealed for inter¬
national assistance and nineteen
projects have already been put for¬
ward. The budget for the first stage
works out at some $50 million and
the second stage is expected to cost
$220 million. As the World Bank
acknowledges in its report of 26
April 1993: "Aside from the daunting
technical problems, the greatest risk
to the success of the proposed pro¬
grammes would be the failure of
the Republics to co-operate and
make the required sacrifices, in
terms of their financial contribu¬
tions and also in terms oftheir will¬
ingness to release a part of their
water allocations for improving the
environment of the deltas and the
Aral Sea disaster zone".
Will the appeal to save the chil¬
dren of the Aral region which a
group ofwomen scientists made in
October 1990 to the Presidents of
the Republics and the heads oforga¬
nizations of the United Nations
system be heard before it is too late?
FURTHER READING:
""Aral, by René Létolle and Monique
Mainguet, Springer-Verlag, Paris,
1993.
* Sécheresse, September 1992, No.3,
Vol.3, and Tune 1994, No.2, Vol.5, ed.
John Libbey
<* Aral Sea Programme, World Bank,
March 1994.
Contaminated by
pesticides, the
water supplying
village wells in
areas around the
Aral has become a
health hazard.
FRANCE
BEQUETTE
is a Franco-
American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
questions. Since
1985 she has
been associated
with the
WANAD-Unesco
training ,
programmefor
African news
agency
journalists.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
W O R
ENVIRONMENTAL
REPORTING: FINDING THE
RIGHT WORDS
The World Industry Council for the
Environment (WICE) has published
a short handbook, "Environmental
Reporting", setting out guidelines on
how industrial enterprises should
report on their environmental poli¬
cies, practices and performance. The
handbook encourages managers to
deal with controversial issues openly:
"Ifyour report is to be credible, publish
good and bad news. Be sure that you
can substantiate your data". The hand¬
book also points out that such
reporting can contribute to a dialogue
with even the severest critics of envi¬
ronmental damage caused by industry.
A useful course in transparency for
industrialists, who are so often accused
of polluting the planet.
COMMON SENSE
ABOUT
POLLUTION
Carol Browner, Administrator of the
United States Environmental Protec¬
tion Agency, has had an ingenious
idea. She has proposed that in future
the laws which have hitherto regu¬
lated industrial pollution on a pollu¬
tant-by-pollutant basis should take
account of the overall effect on the
environment. This would foil some
current practices, such as using water¬
ways for disposing ofpollutants which
it is forbidden to release into the air.
This "Common Sense Initiative" will
be initially tested on six major indus¬
tries disposing of345 million pounds
of toxic substances annually.
GIANT GALAPAGOS
TORTOISES IN DANGER
Isabela Island, in Ecuador's Galapagos
archipelago, has recently been victim
of a huge month-long fire, during
which rescue workers discovered the
remains of42 giant tortoises that had
been eaten by some of the island's
1,000-strong population or by people
from other islands. The giant tortoise
{Testudo elephantina) is in danger of
extinction and is an internationally
protected species.
When the fire broke out in mid-
April and destroyed 2,700 hectares of
woodland, trenches were dug to pro¬
tect the island's 6,000 tortoises. How¬
ever, according to Michael Bliem-
srieder, an official at the Galapagos
National Park, 400 of the tortoises had
to be moved to a special reserve not so
much because of the threat posed by
the fire as for fear of the appetites of
the inhabitants. Tortoise-hunting,
although illegal, is apparently a tra¬
ditional practice. The meat of the tor¬
toises, especially females, and their
blood are regarded as having medic¬
inal properties, apart from being par¬
ticularly succulent.
STEPPING
ON THE GAS
The big three American vehicle man¬
ufacturers Chrysler, Ford and Gen¬
eral Motors have reached an agree¬
ment on lowering the price ofnatural
gas-powered cars and trucks. Last
June, they decided to combine
research efforts to improve the gas
tank, the most expensive part of nat¬
ural gas-driven vehicles. Another
problem is that natural gas has only
one-quarter of the energy density of
gasoline, so that vehicles have to be
refuelled every 250 kilometres. As far
as pollution is concerned, gasoline-
powered engines give off carbon
dioxide, which is a greenhouse gas.
However, natural gas contains about
93% methane, which is released into
the air after the fuel has burned and
contributes just as much to the green¬
house effect. Is the project really
worthwhile?
THE DANGEROUS
DARDANELLES
Up to 1,500 ships a day sail through
the Bosphorus and the Dardanelles,
the two straits linking the Aegean and
Black Seas off the coast of Turkey. In
order to take the pressure off these
international waterways between
Europe and Asia, it would be neces¬
sary to build an oil pipeline linking
the Caucasus to the Mediterranean.
Last March, a Russian tanker carrying
100,000 tons of crude oil caught fire
u
<
following a collision. Existing regula¬
tions allow complete freedom ofpas¬
sage both day and night, regardless of
the nationality of the vessels or their
cargo. The assistance of a pilot or tug
continues to be discretionary,
although the strong current and the
large number of winding stretches
and shallow sections would warrant
their use. To respect new regulations
drawn up by the International Mar¬
itime Organization, notice of dan¬
gerous cargoes must now be given.
From November onwards, two navi¬
gation channels will separate ships
heading for the Black Sea from those
making the return voyage. A step in
the right direction.
THE VOICE
OF AFRICA
Over the past few months, the Pan-
African News Agency (PANA) based in
Dakar (Senegal) has set up an envi¬
ronment desk to put out information
that may have been overlooked by
other news agencies. On 27 June this
year, for example, it reported on the
dramatic spread ofsoil erosion in the
kingdom of Lesotho in a plateau
region of southern Africa, where some
18 to 20 tons of topsoil per hectare, or
2 per cent of the total, is being carried
away every year, an estimated loss of
some 40 million tons. At this rate,
there will be no arable land left in
Lesotho by the year 2040. The con¬
sequences are already startling: food
self-sufficiency is under threat and
there is an acute shortage of wood
fuels, while the population is
increasing. Owing to lack of fuelwood,
crop residues and manure are being
burned, thereby depriving the land
ofnatural fertilizers. Food yields and
the land's water retention capacity
are declining and erosion is contin¬
uing to spread. This situation is par¬
ticularly alarming, since only 9-10% of
the country's land is suitable for agri¬
culture.
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
u
INITIATIVES
NEW LESSONS ON THE ENVIRONMENT FOR PORTUGAL'S CHILDREN
o
42
Aprovision guaranteeing citizens
"a right to the environment" is
written into Portugal's 1976 Con¬
stitution, according to a report
produced for the Organization for
Economic Co-operation and
Development (OECD) in 1993.
Portugal first started to put
together an environmental policy
"in the early 1970s, but the real
turning-point came when it joined
the European Community in 1986.
In 1987, an outline law on the
environment was adopted, and
this was followed in 1990 by the
creation of a Ministry of the Envi¬
ronment and Natural Resources.
Agricultural land accounts for
45 per cent of the country's land
area. However, since the arable
topsoil layer is very shallow, ero¬
sion is a major problem and only
10 per cent of the land has an ade¬
quate level of fertility. Moreover, in
| coastal areas much of the land is
taken up by holiday villas, industry
and roads. More than three-quar¬
ters of the country's 10.6-million
population live less than 50 kilo¬
metres from the coast. On Por¬
tugal's 600,000 farms, fertilizer is
either not used at all or is applied
in enormous quantities as much
as 250 tons per square kilometre in
the case of greenhouse horticul¬
ture! The reafforestation pro¬
grammes set up by the Ministry of
Agriculture have not been entirely
successful in ensuring soil protec¬
tion: extensive forests of highly
combustible species such as euca¬
lyptus have been planted and a
t large number of forest fires have
been recorded.
Although the creation of31 pro¬
tected areas covering 5.6 per cent of
the country has had a positive
impact, the scheme has not enjoyed
full financial support. Between 1988
and 1991, its budget was cut back by
9 per cent (at a time when the cost
ofliving increased by 41 percent).
Another problem is the lack of
waste water treatment facilities.
Only 21 per cent of all effluents are
recycled before being released into
the natural environment. The
amount of inadequately treated
waste rose from 933,000 tons a
year in 1986 to 1,755,000 tons a
year in 1990. Three-quarters of all
hazardous industrial waste is
dumped without being treated.
According to an estimate made by
the Commission of the European
Communities, there are thought to
be more than 1,800 "blackspots"
in the shape of unregulated
dumps, industrial.wastelands and
casual refuse tips.
MOBILIZING THE PUBLIC
Over the past few years, the Min¬
istry of the Environment has
embarked on a policy of voluntary
agreements, or "programme con¬
tracts", with local authorities and
some branches of industry. Through
a new "environmental pact" proce¬
dure announced by the Govern¬
ment, industry will be required to
come progressively into line with
the environmental legislation. Gov¬
ernment expenditure under this
heading increased by 172 per cent
between 1988 and 1991.
The population must become
more involved in environmental
issues, and in this respect Portugal
is taking a number of remarkable
steps. A major reform of the edu¬
cation system in the 1980s made
protection of the environment a
cross-disciplinary subject at the
primary and secondary school
levels. Protection of the physical
environment, the cultural heritage
and the social environment now
forms part of courses in the nat¬
ural sciences, geography, history
and even foreign languages.
The Ministry of Education has
undertaken to train primary school
teachers and provide them with
teaching materials. Starting in 1990,
more than 1,000 primary school
teachers and 2,500 secondary school
teachers received environmental
training. In the same year, a school
for vocational training in environ¬
mental studies and development
was set up to train technical workers.
A dozen or so universities or equiv¬
alent institutions offer environ¬
mental courses to degree level and
beyond.
In addition, the National Insti¬
tute for the Environment is endeav¬
ouring to satisfy the public's "right to
know" about the environment. It
has set up data bases, from which
material is also published. The Min¬
istry of the Environment is not lag¬
ging behind either. It has set up an
Environmental Information and
Documentation Centre which sup¬
plies photocopies to the media and
the public. However, environmental
defence associations are still in their
infancy and their role and the
resources at their disposal need to
be strengthened at the earliest
opportunity.
SUGGESTED READING:
OECD Environmental Performance
Reviews, OECD, Paris, 1993.
The fishing town
of Nazaré, in
Portugal's
Estremadura
province.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
globa view. . . global view. .
The plight of the world s
street children
I Many people remember Pixote.
I Some may remember two Pixotes
the tragic little hero ofJosé Louzeiro's novel
about Brazilian street children,1 and Fer¬
nando Ramos da Silva, the squint-eyed
child who played his role in the film version
of the novel made by Hector Babenco in
1981 . Both of them were killed, the fictional
one in a cemetery, the boy actor on the
steps ofhis home, their deaths mirroring the
violence oftheir lives. The destiny of thou¬
sands ofBrazilian children is played out in
the streets. Alcohol, drugs, disease, prosti¬
tution, rape, kidnappings or remand centres
form the sum total of their childhood. Death
squads take care of the rest.
Fatherless, Fernando Ramos da Silva
was living in dire poverty with his mother
and his four brothers and sisters when he
was chosen to play the role of Pixote. The
film achieved worldwide success and the
life of his family was transformed. For the
budding actor the future would surelyhold
a home, work, drama lessons	 But it was
not to be. The street claimed him for good.
It was already too late. No one was able to
save him from the only too predictable end
that stalks a hundred million children gone
astray in streets, marketplaces and railway
stations all over the world.
"Dropouts", "urchins", "children of the
dust"the terms used to describe them
vary from continent to continent, but their
lives bear an aching similarity. Driven out by
unbearable poverty or the brutality of their
parents, sold or abandoned for those very
same reasons, they are orphans no one
wants to feed, let alone educate. Every¬
where they share a terrible plight. But the
laws that govern life in the street are not
the same everywhere.
In some of the world's sprawling mega-
cities, hundreds of thousands of children
live in the streets without the slightest pro¬
tection, prepared to do almost anything for
a few coins. Violence, however, is not
common. The street children are generally
looked upon as urchins who have learned
to survive on their wits.
Elsewhere, the story is one of forced
Combating sexual
violence
As part of preparations for the World
Conference on Women, which will be
held in Beijing in 1995, Unesco organized
a seminar on "Sexual exploitation and the
trafficking of women and children in Latin
America" in Caracas in March 1994. The
purpose of the seminar was to draw up
strategies for combating a reprehensible
practice which is particularly rife among
disadvantaged sectors of the population.
Unesco has also commissioned a group of
experts to prepare an exhaustive report
on the violence to which the women of
Bosnia are exposed, with a view to
drawing up a plan for the reintegration
into society of the victims and their chil¬
dren.
The cultural dimension
"Rethinking Development", a newly-
published booklet about the World Decade
for Cultural Development is available (in
English, French and Spanish versions) free
of charge from Unesco. Its contents include
articles on integrated rural development in
the Sahel, the Silk Roads project, the
Library of Alexandria, theatre and Aids
education, the Maya world, and pluralism
and the culture of democracy.
Copies may be obtained from:
Secretariat of the World Decade for
Cultural Development, Unesco, 1 rue
Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France.
labour and prostitution. Tourism tied to
child prostitution is on the rise and cor¬
ruption triumphs over legal sanctions. A
policeman who bought a twelve-year-old
Thai girl, Mii Chuu, from her stepfather
to sell her into prostitution paid less than
$200. Saved by an American missionary,
Mii Chuu now plans to become a teacher.
Her case is clearly an exception, as is the
fact that she did not contract Aids.
While many children spend their nights
in sleazy hotel rooms in the vain hope of
rejoining their parents after having paid
off the family debts with their bodies, others
bargain for their pavement beds with local
policemen and await the morning to go
scavenging for food. Still others expect
nothing at all. When hope has gone, why
make the effort? Suicide orwar on the adult
world are all that's left. They have nothing
to lose and they are afraid ofnothing. Even¬
tually, they get used to the tough ways of the
street, grow a thick hide against fear and
pain. Rage begets rage, and small-time go-
getters turn into hardened criminals. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
.global v
"Children take over the streets the way
pirates take over the sea," writes Jacques
Meunier,2 who was told by a Bogota child:
"At first I was ashamed. But not for long."
This is a journey from which there is no
return.
A Unesco priority
These children have become society's
open wound. For some, eradicating the
problem means eliminating the children
iew. . . global view
44
Learning about
solidarity
On the occasion of the launching of the
"Terre d'Avenir' Foundation, whose aim is
to alert public opinion to the main chal¬
lenges of the closing years of the century
and to the problems of the Third World, a
symposium on the subject of "Land of the
Future: training the citizens of a world of
solidarity" was held in Paris in September
1994. The purpose of the symposium,
which was organized by the Comité
Catholique contre la Faim et pour le
Développement, a leading French non¬
governmental organization, was to define
the subject areas on which the Founda¬
tion's action will be focused. The global¬
ization of social and economic processes
and the problems of development viewed
from the standpoint of different cultures
provided the starting-point for discussions
on economics, culture, world security and
peace, along with the contribution of the
media, associations and schools to edu¬
cation, development and solidarity.
Further information may be obtained
from: CCFD, 4 rue Jean-Lantier, 75001
Paris, France. Tel: (33-1) 44 82 80 00.
Fax: (33-1) 44 82 81 43.
themselves. In 1990 the press revealed that
492 children had been murdered in Rio
de Janeiro alone more than one child
per day. In July 1993, a mysterious group
killed eight Rio children in a single night.
Following this massacre, the Latin
American Faculty of Social Sciences,
France's Centre Unifié d'Enseignement et
de Recherche pour les Services de Sécurité,
UNICEF, and Unesco organized a seminar
on "Children and Adolescents in Conflict
with the Law" in Rio de Janeiro from 8-11
November 1993. This seminar, the first of
its kind, tied in with a project launched
by Unesco in 1989 in order to alert public
opinion, seek sources of funding, and,
through publications and seminars, pro¬
vide training for educators and social
workers working with street children. In
close collaboration with UNICEF, two
international meetings forAfrica were held
in Cotonou and Nairobi in 1990. As part of
the same project, an international work¬
shop of field specialists, held at Unesco
Headquarters in 1991, was devoted to
identifying the priority educational needs
of street children.
The purpose of the Rio seminar, which
was attended by 81 representatives from
the police and justice departments of six
Latin American countries, was to examine
ways and means of educating and
informing police and legal officials so that
the problem of violence perpetrated
against street children and child workers
can be tackled head-on.
The world in your
pocket
Following the publication of an overview
of the World Education Report, the "World
in Your Pocket" collection for young
people published by the World Federa¬
tion of Unesco Clubs, Centres and Asso¬
ciations has brought out a second booklet,
this time on the World Labour Report pre¬
pared by the International Labour Organ¬
isation. A short version of the World
Human Development Report 1994, drawn
up by the United Nations Development
Programme (see our feature "World View"
in the September issues of the Courier)
will appear shortly.
Further information from:
FMACU-WFUCA, Unesco house,
1 rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15,
France. Tel. (33-1) 45 68 28 18;
Fax: (33-1) 42 73 05 21.
1 José Louzeiro, Pixote, Karthala, Paris, 1990
(French only).
2 Jacques Meunier, Les Gamins de Bogota,
A.M. Métailié, Paris, 1989.
FURTHER READING:
Unesco Courier, "Children in Danger",
October 1991.
Survey on Street Children in Three
Urban Centres of Namibia, Peter Tacon,
Ministry of Local Government and Housing,
Windhoek, 1991. Study carried out with
UNICEF'S support.
Adolfo Pérez Esquivel, "Enfants des
rues" in La Ville partout, et partout en
crise, "Manière de Voir" series, Le Monde
diplomatique, 1991 (French only).
Protecting working children, ed. William
E. Myers, New York, UNICEF, 1992.
Street children of Madras, a situation
analysis, Joe Arimpoor, Noida, Uttar
Pradesh, India, National Labour Institute,
1992.
Blossoms in the dust: street children in
Africa, Jean-Pierre Velis, Paris, Unesco (in
preparation).
The State of the World's Children,
UNICEF, 1994.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Federico Mayor:
keeping ahead of
the future
byEdouardJ. Maunick
EDOUARD J. MAUNICK,
Mauritian poet and writer, is his
country's Ambassador to South
Africa. He has published many
books, including Ensoleillé vif,
which won the Apollinaire Prize
in 1976), Anthologies
personnelles (1984) and Paroles
pour solder la mer (1969).
I The publication, in French, of La Mémoire du
I Futur ("The Memory of the Future") offers a
fresh opportunity to share the thinking of Federico
Mayor, the author of Tomorrow is always too late.
The book is written with the same breadth of inspi¬
ration as its predecessor, the same determination
"to pave the way for the best possible future" and,
above all, the same lucidity and faith in human
beings qualities that go to make the Director-Gen¬
eral of Unesco a man of action who never gives way
to despair.
In this new work, Federico Mayor embarks on
an open-ended dialogue on the problems which he
knows "with the certainty of instinct that they will
beindeed, already are the vital challenges of the
coming millennium". These problems, doubts and
anxieties we can already read in the eyes of children
all over the world.
When he says that "the main thing is loving and
sharing", he cuts what he regards as the "Gordian
knots" that constrain the world today. For Federico
Mayor, the "main thing" is to feel a sense ofurgency,
and "loving and sharing" imply commitment. It is
urgent to break down the walls between the "haves"
and the "have-nots", to rethink the way we live our
lives, individually and in communities, and take a
fresh look at how we "control" nature. This means
pledging to eradicate illiteracy once and for all, calling
a halt to the brain drain, making scientific and tech¬
nical knowledge universally available, safeguarding
the memory ofhumanity, preserving the earth from
ecological disaster in short taking charge of our
future.
Writing in convincing and down-to-earth lan¬
guage, Federico Mayor recommends that we form a
conspiracy "conspiracy" in the etymological sense
of "breathing together". It should be the kind of con¬
spiracy that "transcends frontiers, nationalities, reli¬
gions and ethnic groups". It lies at the heart of any
solution to our problems, whether education for
international understanding, the preservation of the
cultural and natural heritage, development, the envi¬
ronment or the future ofhumanity.
All these issues are carefully discussed by an
author who is concerned but remains resolutely opti
mistic. After making a brief survey of their histor¬
ical background, he approaches the problems
directly, examines the facts, assesses the attempts
that have been made to solve them and charts the
future prospects.
Between a past for which we are not responsible
but which we must accept, and a future that we wish
to control, today's world, our lives our survival, as
Federico Mayor says must be taken care of. For
survival is the basic issue for so many people,
including the Cameroon villager who, after making
sure that he really was talking to the Director-General
of Unesco, asked him: "Why have you come to see us?
Is it to defend the elephants or to defend us?"
The answer to this question is to be found on
the page of "The Memory of the Future" where the
author says: "We should never lose sight of the fact
that the first thing we have to do is to protect the
human species".
In Federico Mayor there is a deeply-felt need to
look towards utopia. Has not the quest for a perfect
world given impetus to people's lives ever since the
world began? How can we dream of overcoming the
adverse circumstances of the present except by
assuming that the impossible is possible? Hence "The
Memory of the Future", a title spelling out a message
of faith, that tomorrow is alreadyanother day.
La mémoire de l'avenir,
BY FEDERICO MAYOR,
collection Défis, Editions Unesco, Paris, 1994,
216 pages (in French only)
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
R H
Gregorio Marañan
TJie Spanish polymath Gregorio
Marañan (1867-1970), one ofthe
pioneers ofendocrinology, was also a
historian, art critic and moral
philosopher. He was a prolific author
(a bibliography compiled towards
the end ofhis life listed more than
' 1,200 titles), notably ofhistorical
and literary works which reached a
wide public ofreaders attracted by
the clarity ofhis style and ideas. In
May 1 933, he tookpart in a
symposium on the "Future of
Culture" organized in Madrid by the
International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation. An extract
from the address he gave on that
occasion is reproduced below.
Regardless of how we define the
term, culture is the highest form of
expression of the human mind. It
exists and will continue to grow in parallel
with the development ofhumanity, which
is still only in its adolescence and whose
sins are the sins ofyouth. People today are
much the same as they always have been.
It is a mistake to think thatwe are at the very
hub of history. When we see everything
around us going from bad to worse, we
imagine that it is the world that is about to
disappear and change, not us.
In future, as new forms of culture
emerge, itwill be difficultfor us to associate
them with what we currently understand by
Thefuture ofculture
Text selected and presented
by Edgardo Canton
46
the term, and hence to predict their future
course. The same kind ofthing will happen
to the family of the future: it will differ from
the family as we know it but its existence
will not be jeopardized, as some people
nowadays are apt to think. Change, which
is synonymous with renewal, is all too often
confused with death.
The evolution of culture down the ages
has something in common with the evo¬
lution of living organisms. Both have var¬
ious growth centres, each with a cycle of its
own. The focus of evolution shifts as it
advances from one phase to the next. In
each of these phases, specific external fac¬
tors confer a different physiognomy on
organisms and culture alike. Yet the gen¬
eral course ofall these random events fol¬
lows a constant direction, at first upwards,
then to maturity, and eventually to the
stage of "involution", when the process
starts going into reverse. Suffice it to say
that human culture has barely reached
the mature stage and still has a long way to
go before it starts to regress.
MACHINE CIVILIZATION AND
THE ART OF LIVING
The culture of the future will accordingly
differ from our own in its forms and will
undoubtedly go deeper and be more effec¬
tive. The difficulty lies in predicting what
its fluctuating surface movements and
features will be in the phases immediately
following our own generation in that
future which we shall only just manage to
glimpse in the distance before we hand
over to the next generation.
However, there are a number of very
important factors which partly dictate the
shape that culture will take in future. These
are bound up with the way our human
instincts will develop a subject on which
we could hold forth at great length without
any danger of getting things wrong. One
such factor is the spread of the civiliza¬
tion of the machine. Another is the growing
influence of biological concerns, espe¬
cially as they pertain to the physical culture
of the body, the prevention of disease or
the precepts underlying eugenics. In the
generations coming after us, these con¬
cerns will become actual mandatory rules
ofconduct. Both factors are affecting and
will continue to affect the instincts of
human beings; they will, in the first
instance, have a direct influence on the
tone of culture.
People today often wonder whether
the advances that machines are bound to
make in the coming decades and they
will certainly be phenomenal will have a
decisive impact on culture. There can be
no doubt that they will. There is, however,
one point on which I cannot agree with
other people. I do not believe that the
impact of the progress they make will do
any harm to human culture. There can be
no doubt that at the present time per¬
haps only because the progress of
machines is still going through its honey¬
moon period we attach undue impor¬
tance to machine-minded people, people
who use their instincts, to the detriment of
cerebral people. But that fact should not be
regarded as being any more important
than the purely incidental and negligible
importance that it actually possesses. It
is unfortunate that somebody driving a
car should earn more than a poet and that
the winner of an automobile race should
be borne aloft in triumph by a crowd that
is unaware of the publication of a funda¬
mental work in the arts or sciences. But all
this, I repeat, is only of incidental impor¬
tance. The main thing is that the progress
made by machines spares humanity much
toil and trouble and therefore allows it
complete freedom to attend to its spiri¬
tual development. It also adds a happy
zest of precision and speed to the human
mind and culture, although we ourselves
do not realize this.
MAKING HASTE SLOWLY
Speed is a virtue, but at the same time it is
instrumental in spawning a vice, the vice
of precipitation. There can be no doubt
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
V E
that undue precipitation has had a harmful
effect on culture because it has forced
intelligent people to sacrifice the quality of
what they write to the need to spread the
word at great haste among the harried and
faceless mass of the population. We have
all stopped writing page after densely-
packed page ofslowly pondered thoughts
which came to us unobtrusively and which
may perhaps have made a deep impres¬
sion on people's minds. Instead, we have
all scattered our half-baked ideas and our
still inchoate emotions in the now yel¬
lowing pages of newspapers and in the
endless comings and goings of congresses
and conferences.
But there is an antidote to this poison.
The same progress of the machine that
indisposes and demeans us because of
our lust for speed at the same time helps to
bring us into direct and ready contact with
the timeless rules of the universe. As a
result of this progress, people nowadays
may perhaps not live in such close com¬
munion with nature, but they go out
increasingly in search of it and have a
better grasp of its inner meaning, which is
to synchronize our waking lives with the
variable rhythms of differing worlds.
RELIEVING PAIN
Living in communion with nature and
reading the humanities will automatically
compensate for the petty dangers to which
the present machine age exposes culture.
In short, the distorted image which it is
responsible for imprinting on our per¬
sonality has a significant effect on our out¬
ward demeanour but is less important in
terms ofour innermost being. It is like the
facial expressions which we unwittingly
copy from our cinema heroes and which,
in their outward forms and in those
forms alone make people nowadays so
different from those of forty years ago. For
example, it is surprising how slight an
impact the possibility of flight has on our
minds, although the fact that such a pos¬
sibility exists at all is in itself quite mind-
boggling. It has done little more than step
up the pace at which age-old sentiments
and ideas are handed down and make it
easier for us to gain a deeper knowledge of
them. If Leonardo da Vinci were to come
back to life, he would have to admit that
the pilot of an aeroplane is, by the act of
piloting, not really any different from the
helmsman of one of the galleys that sailed
the oceans of his time.
What is much more important for the
culture of the future is the whole range of
biological concerns to which we referred
earlier. Today lack of money or a fragile
digestion are the only things that stop
people from eating all they want. Future
generations will behave differently. They
will eat in accordance with a scientific
method imposed on them by the economy
of the future and the laws of nutrition.
They will not passively allow their bodies
to suffer the wear and tear ofmaturity and
old age, but will defend them by practising
sport and leading open-air lives. They will
not leave responsibility for their offspring
to the vagaries of physical passion or
fleeting love affairs but will turn love into
a reasoned emotion, separating simple
pleasure from the procreative function.
Yet, all these things and they are rem¬
iniscent of the sort ofpedantic statements
experts in hygiene are wont to make at
their gatherings are already a reality
being thrust on peoples furthest from the
mainstream ofcivilization. In the very near
future, these principles will be inviolable
rules governing our behaviour, and there¬
after they will become essential heredi¬
tary factors. I wonder how deep down into
people's souls this influence will pene
trate, and to what extent it will have an
effect on the way culture evolves.
To those who ask themselves what new
universal concern may come to replace the
fight for individual freedom, which set the
tone of culture for several centuries, the
answer may be that any such concern will
probably aim at relieving people ofphysical
pain, of the ordeal ofpain suffered by indi¬
viduals and the species alike. Naturally, I
believe in the need for pain as a fount of
progress. But the effectiveness ofsuffering
really lies in keeping alive the struggle to
prevent it from occurring, so that the soul
will remain thereafter alert and receptive to
all forms of struggle. People who do not
rebel against pain have no feeling for life or
for efficiency as the key to progress. As long
as progress keeps on being made, humanity
will suffer and will struggle in order not to
suffer. On the day people gain their
freedom, they can then be afraid and
rightly so of the coming of theAnti-Christ
and the end of the species, which will no
doubt come to pass when we enter the
reign of absolute happiness.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
- .
The story of the
guitar from the
Renaissance to
the age of jazz
and rock
LISTENING
"^^Ste-
Strings down the centuries
by Isabelle Leymarie
48
I The guitar, with its sensually curved body, is
I a favourite instrument of folklore and popular
music, the faithful companion of footloose trav¬
ellers, students and hippies. It can be heard not only
in classical compositions but in Spanish flamenco
and Portuguese fado, in folk music, blues, jazz and
rock, in the high-life music of Ghana and the soucous
of Zaire, and, in one form or another, in almost all
of Latin America and some of the countries of Asia.
Although the word "guitar" may have originally
been derived from kithara, the name of an ancient
Greek stringed instrument, it has been used to
describe instruments differing both in the tech¬
nique used to play them and in their shape.
A member of the lute family, the guitar as we
know it first made its appearance in Renaissance
Europe. However, instruments with similar names
already existed some 300 years earlier, and there are
references in medieval French literature to the
gitere and in fourteenth-century English literature
to the gitarer. Prototypes of the guitar may have
existed in ancient Mesopotamia, Anatolia and Egypt
and also in Central Asia at the beginning of the
Christian era.
As time went by, changes were made to the
shape of the instrument and to the layout of the
soundboard and fret. The guitar was initially smaller
than it Is today and had "courses" or sets of four and
later five or even seven strings, and eventually ten
individual strings. The modern classical guitar, on
which Andrés Segovia (d. 1987), and Alejandro
Lagoya are regarded as being among the foremost
virtuoso performers, was developed by nineteenth-
century Spanish instrument makers.
The guitar was first used as a solo or chamber
instrument, especially in Spain and Italy. The first
compositions for the instrument were published in
about the mid-sixteenth century. In Italy, the guitar
tended to be superseded by the lute and the vihuela,
but in France it became very popular, giving added
zest to courtly entertainments and providing the
accompaniment to the songs of troubadours and folk
dances. It reached the height of its popularity at the
end of the eighteenth century through the compo
sitions of Lulgi Boccherini (1743-1805), the Catalan
Fernando Sor (1778-1839) and Niccoló Paganini
(1782-1840).
FROM FLAMENCO TO BOSSA NOVA
In Europe, there are still a number of popular vari¬
ants on the guitar, like the vertically-held flamenco
guitar made of Spanish cypress wood, which weighs
less than the rosewood used in the classical guitar
and is fitted with a fingerboard for beating out the
rhythm. Other forms include the chitarra batiente of
Calabria, with its single-note bass string, and various
types of Portuguese guitar.
The American guitar, which usually has six to ten
metal strings mounted on a slender neck, first came
into prominence in the nineteenth century. It was later
to become the preferred instrument of blues musi¬
cians and singers like Big Bill Broonzy, Leadbelly
and Bukka White, who often played it using the "bot¬
tleneck" (or "slide") technique, where the strings are
stroked with the sharp edge of a knife, a broken-off
bottleneck or a brass ring fitting on the middle or
index finger of the left hand. It is widely used in
country and western music and is particularly popular
with folk singers like Joan Baez and Bob Dylan.
From the 1920s onwards, jazz bands and variety
orchestras also started using the crisp sound of the
non-amplified guitar, later followed by the electric
guitar, whose sound is amplified by a microphone and
whose strings are plucked with a plectrum. Freddie
Green, a member of the Count Basie orchestra, and
subsequently Charlie Christian, the pioneer of the
bebop guitar, along with Django Reinhardt in Europe,
were primarily responsible for the growing popularity
of the electric guitar, which gradually took on a
variety of forms. The ultimate in fantasy was reached
in rock music, in which the guitar is both a marvel of
technology and a sex symbol, while musicians like
Jimmy Hendrix have experimented with electronic
effects known as wa-wa, reverb or phaser. Acid rock
and heavy metal in particular are noted for their use
of outlandish distortion effects.
In the cooler bossa nova style, guitarists Joäo
Gilberto, Laurindo Almeida and Charlie Bird prefer to
use an acoustic guitar with nylon strings, and Joäo
Gilberto has invented a form of off-beat accompani¬
ment to produce a swinging effect known as the
balanço.
At the end of the nineteenth century, a type of
three-course metal-stringed guitar known as the
tres appeared in Cuba's Oriente province. Rudi¬
mentary tres were often made of old salt-cod cans.
From the 1920s onwards, the fres became the typ¬
ical instrument of the rhythm known as son. Arsenio
Rodriguez and Niño Rivera were among the best-
known treseros of the 1950s and 1960s.
The guitar was the preferred Instrument of
Cuban solo singers (trovadores), duos and trios.
Guitar trios, such as the famous "Trio Matamoros"
from Santiago de Cuba, also played in Puerto Rico
and Mexico. In Puerto Rico, a guitar with four pairs
of strings, the cuatro, was originally used in peasant
music, but was introduced into salsa in the 1970s.
In Mexico, people play the jarana, while the cha¬
rango, which is sometimes made from an armadillo
shell, is played in Bolivia, Peru, Chile and northern
Argentina. Musicians in Brazil play the samba and
other rhythms on the viola or the cavaquinho, while
Venezuela has its own type of cuatro, as well as the
quinto, with its five pairs of strings.
Throughout Latin America, and especially in
Peru, Argentina, Chile and Uruguay, the guitar con¬
tinues to be the preferred instrument of singers of
the folk song style known as nueva trova. In Hawaii,
the guitar, which may have been introduced by
Portuguese seamen, later gave rise to the four-
stringed ukelele. Java has its own five-stringed
guitar and the Philippines the tlape, a three-stringed
guitar which may have been named after the small
Latin American guitar known as the tiple. In Viet
Nam, sentimental songs are often sung to a guitar
accompaniment.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-American
musicologist, is the author of La Salsa et le Latín
Jazz (PUF, Paris, 1993). She is currently working on
a study of black music in Latin America and the
Caribbean.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
For eleven months of the
year, Elvis Johnson-ldan
lives in a London suburb
with his wife Elizabeth and
their three children.
However, in mid-December
every year, he goes back to
Jukwaa, his native village in
Ghana, where he reigns
supreme as Nana Otumayin
Kofi Idan I. In the two
previous issues, George
Darley-Doran accompanied
Elvis on his annual visit to
Jukwaa. In this third and
final episode, he discovers
the subtleties of tribal
organization and the role
Elvis plays in the village.
GEORGE DARLEY-DORAN
is a Turkish-born Englishman
who lives in London, where he
works as a television
correspondent.
I By 9:30 in the evening the whole village
was buzzing as a funeral rite got
underway, ft should be explained that a Fanti
funeral rite is not at all solemn and depressing,
but rather an occasion of celebration and joyful
remembrance of those who have passed away.
Tonight was no exception. There was an outdoor
disco for the children, where the music was
loud enough to . . . wake the dead. And once the
spirits had been fully aroused, they were sere¬
naded by the Wesleyan anthems belting out
from a largely female congregation in the Bethel
Chapel just a few steps up from the disco. A
good chunk of the male population was to be
found at Paoli's and Vic's, Jukwaa's two watering
holes, both of which are located directly outside
the Chapel. Vic's lovely barmaid Theresa a
devout Mormon and a strict teetotaller could
not keep the schnapps and akpeteshie* flowing
quickly enough. Up by the main road, young
women and girls were cooking and selling food
by the light of their hurricane lamps. The party
continued until the early hours, ft was almost
dawn when the men and women gathered into
a procession and swayed up and down the main
road, chanting praises to the spirits of the
deceased. Then everybody went to bed.
By now New Year's Eve was upon us. This
year, the usual celebrations would be coinciding
with the tenth anniversary of Ghana's December
31st Revolution. Those who bought newspapers
could read about it, and those with televisions
(perhaps two households in the village) could
watch all the speeches, but that was the extent to
which the village was affected. Ghana's revolution
(if that is the correct word for it) is to a large
extent an urban phenomenon. The central gov¬
ernment simply lacks the resources necessary
for effective local administration. Until that
changes, local chiefs will remain the practical
managers of the areas under their control.
The power of the chiefs in Ghana is officially
formalized in the National House of Chiefs. This
is situated in Accra. There are also regional houses
around the country. All the tribes of Ghana arc
represented the Fantis and Asantes, the Ga and
various others. The National House of Chiefs
convenes twice a year. All aspects of local gov-
the African
by George Darley-Doran
ernment issues are covered: education, transport,
communication, social policy and so on.
The concept of central government is rela¬
tively new to this part of the world. Modern
Ghana was born out of an arbitrary amalgamation
of many tribal elements. This national entity is still
very much in the gelling process. Even today,
for most of Ghana's population, the word of the
local chief is law. A villager might be tried for a
crime by the Supreme Court, and perhaps sent to
prison, but he will not feel that justice has been
done until he has been tried by his chief.
A noble lineage
The more 1 discovered about the nature of chief¬
taincy in Ghana, the clearer it became why Elvis
in particular had been targcttcd by the king¬
makers ofJukwaa. The village is in great need of
the managerial and diplomatic skills that Elvis has
picked up in the course of his career.
The Idan family to which Elvis belongs con¬
trols one of the five stools scats of power
relating to the area surrounding Jukwaa. Each
stool carries with it a specific area of responsibility.
Elvis, as Brahene, is responsible for harnessing
and developing the resources of the "abran" sec¬
tion of the population. The loose translation of
abran is "youth", but any able-bodied adult can be
classified as a member of this class in other
words, just about everybody between the ages of
fifteen and sixty. Most of Elvis's activities tend to
be in the economic area, trying to create incentives
for young people to stay in the village. He is
trying to improve farming techniques; promote
land-clearance for bigger and better-yielding farms;
experiment with new crops and seeds; and intro¬
duce small-scale technology such as charcoal-
making. A bakery and street-market have both
been established inJukwaa since he was enstooled.
Goats arc, as always, raised inprofusion but cattle-
raising is impossible due to the tsetse fly.
Elvis works in co-operation with the other
four chiefs of Jukwaa. One of these is the
"Odikro", Nana Kojo Idan VII. The direct trans¬
lation of Odikro is "village owner" but this title
is, in fact, a largely ceremonial one similar to that
of an English mayor. His sceptre features a golden
parrot, a symbol of intelligence in Fanti
mythology. Nana Kwesi Ansa the man who
had presided over sports day a few days earlier
is the "Omankrado" ofJukwaa. This title indicates
his role as the spiritual unifier of the village. His
responsibility is to keep the peace and to resolve
matters of civil dispute. The other two chiefs are
the "Tufuhene", who is in charge of the asafo mil¬
itary caste, and the "Gyasehen", who acts as a
kind of lieutenant to Elvis in his role as Brahene.
The role of chief is not necessarily one that 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50
"I used to come here when I was a
boy and find a canoe like this one. I'd
sit in it and look out over the sea."
Elvis would have chosen for himself. Indeed, his
mother (prior to her death in 1985) had been
adamant that he pursue his own life, independent
of the village. The kingmakers ofJukwaa were well
aware of this. But kingmakers take a long-term
view. They could see, even when Elvis was young,
that he had a potential capacity for decision¬
making and leadership. They waited until the
death of his mother before thrusting chiefdom
upon him.
Elvis is descended from "noble" lineages on
both sides. Most of the tribes under the Fanti
umbrella are matrilineal, in that men inherit
power via the senior females of each generation.
Elvis's mother Esi Nyarkoa Johnson was of
such a clan. Her family controlled (and still con¬
trols) an important stool situated in Ekumfi
Abaka, to the southwest ofJukwaa. She had been
groomed to be the "queen mother" of her people.
She never accepted the title as such but due to her
stock, as well as her personal strength of character,
she was a formidable woman. Elvis's father
Kobina Otumayin Idan was born into a divi¬
sion of the Fanti tribe that happens to be patri¬
lineal. The Idans are divided into two branches:
one controls an important stool in Winncba, and
the other controls the Jukwaa stool. Elvis's father
was directly descended from both of these
branches. Elvis is therefore the immediate product
of three families that are all-powerful in their
own right. The kingmakers see in Elvis a chance
to consolidate the power of the three families.
The schemes and manoeuvrings of the king¬
makers have implications not just for Elvis, but
for his offspring too. All four of his children
Eunice, Theresa, Matthew and Christopher
will grow up to occupy positions of considerable
influence. It is up to them to decide whether or
not they will exercise that influence. Each of the
children has a Fanti name in addition to his or her
Western one. These names were chosen by the
family elders, and each of them relates to a par¬
ticular stool or forebear. The relevance of the
name increases in proportion to the potential
status of the child in question. Christopher has a
particularly significant Fanti name: Nana Kwame
Akycn. This was the name of Elvis's paternal
great-grandfather, of whom Christopher is seen
to be a reincarnation. The original Nana Kwame
Akyen was the Idan family head before his
descendants separated into the Jukwaa and Win-
neba branches. The kingmakers see Christopher
as potentially being in a position to further con¬
solidate the two halves of a family that has been
divided for generations. But the kingmakers are
in no hurry. They bide their time, waiting entire
decades for their plans to come to fruition.
Liz, Elvis's English wife, has taken her hus¬
band's rise to chieftaincy in her stride and main¬
tains an active interest in the future development
of Jukwaa. She is particularily interested in the
development ofJukwaa's female population. The
lives of the village women consist of a great deal
more than just pounding away at fufu all day. The
men might have all the glory of chiefdom, but it
is the women who get most of the work done. All
the market traders are female. The bars and shops
ofJukwaa are all owned and run by women. It is
the women who run the households, often with
their own finances. They make all the important
decisions regarding the welfare of their children.
For the most part, the women of Jukwaa like
those all over Ghana do what they want, in
their own right, without seeking permission from
their husbands. The extended family solves the
child-care question at a stroke, leaving women to
lead their own lives. Birth out of wedlock is
accepted and not regarded as the stigma that it is
in the west. I could sense a great feeling of soli¬
darity among the women of the village. They
have a robust sense of humour, particularily
regarding men, and at the various festivities I
attended it was always the women who were the
life and soul of the party.
Beyond the horizon
The next day a whole crowd of us drove to Win-
neba together and visited the fishermen's neigh¬
bourhood to get what we needed for a barbecue
on the beach. The children were happy when
we got to the seaside, and immediately began
splashing about in the surf. Elvis climbed onto a
beached canoe and sat gazing out over the
horizon. I went over to join him. He was in
rather a philosophical mood. "That's where they
came from all those hundreds of years ago," he
said, "from beyond the horizon. They came and
turned our world upside-down. I can't say
whether it was for better or worse, but we have
to accept what happened and come to terms with
it. I used to comehere when I was a boy and find
a canoe like this one. I'd sit in it just as I'm sitting
here and look out over the sea. I'd wonder what
the world across the horizon could possibly be
like. I'd dream about going to that world one
day. I'd imagine myself taking what was best
from here and bringing back with me what was
best from over there."
1. A spirit derived from sugar cane. Editor
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, pages 3, 9 (top
right), 1 1 (top right), 1 3
(top right), 1 5 (top), 1 7
(top), 21 (top), 23 (top
right), 27,29,31,38:©
Harlingue-Viollet, Paris. Page
2: © B. Y Leglatin, France.
Pages S, 7: Ulf Andersen ©
Gamma, Paris. Pages 8 (top),
1 4: © Explorer, E.S. Collection,
Paris. Page 8 (middle): ©
Edimédia, Société de
Géographie, Paris. Pages 8
(below), 1 6: © Dagli Orti,
Paris. Page 9 (top left): ©
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris.
Page 9 (below): © Explorer,
Lausat Collection, Paris. Page
1 0: FPG International ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 1 1 (left):
J.-L Charmet © Explorer, Paris.
Pages 12, 13 (below): C.
Sappa © Rapho, Paris. Page 1 3
(top left): © Explorer, ADPC
Collection, Paris. Pages 1 5
(below), 23 (top left): ©
Léonard de Selva-Tapabor, Paris.
Pages 17 (below), 18:©
Charles Lénars, Paris. Page 1 9:
© Viollet Collection, Paris.
Pages 20, 2 1 (below): Mary
Evans Picture Library ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 22: ©
Edimédia, Paris. Page 23
(below): Soazig Collection ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 24: ©
Afrique en Création, Paris.
Page 25: © Edimédia,
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris.
Page 26: Lemzaouda © Musée
de l'Homme, Paris. Page 28:
Oster © Musée de l'Homme,
Paris. Page 33: UNESCO-lnes
Forbes. Pages 34-3S: Georg
Gerster © Rapho, Paris. Page
35: Laurent Sazy © Gamma,
Paris. Page 36: Aldo Pavan ©
Gamma, Paris. Page 37:
Gérard Sioen © Rapho, Paris.
Pages 39, 40: Gilles Saussier ©
Gamma, Paris. Page 4 1 (top):
Stephane Frances © Explorer,
Paris. Page 4 1 (below):
Raymond de Seynes © Rapho,
Paris. Page 42: J.-L Courtinat
© Rapho, Paris. Page 47: ©
Keystone, Paris. Page 48: ©
Giraudon, Musée Instrumental
de Paris. Pages 49, 50: ©
George Darley-Doran, London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
OLLECWNSYNTHESEl HISTOIRE
LA SOCIÉTÉ FRANÇAISE
aux XVIe- XVIIe- XVIIIe siècles
J.M. Constant 65 F
LA VIE RELIGIEUSE EN FRANCE
aux XVIe- XVIIe- XVIIIe siècles
G. Deregnaucourt et D. Poton 85 F
L'ÉCONOMIE FRANÇAISE
au XXe siècle
A. Broder 79 F
L'ÉCONOMIE FRANÇAISE
aux XVIe-XVIIe-XVI IIe siècles
F. Bayard et P. Guignet 79 F
LA FRANCE INDUSTRIELLE
aux XVIe-XVIIe-XVI IIe siècles
P. Delsalle 79 F
10 rue de Nesle 75006 PARIS. Tel 44 41 63 75
BP 87 05003 GAP Cedex. Tel 92 53 85 72
ET ILS SUIVIRENT LA GRANDE OURSE...
Jeanette Winter
*Et Us suivirent
Ca Cjrcmde Ourse. . .
H^ShM Jm I
Aux Etats-Unis, vers 1840, de nombreux esclaves noirs
cherchèrent à s'enfuir pour trouver la liberté. Des blancs
sympathisants formèrent avec les noirs un réseau
clandestin qui leur permit souvent de se sauver vers une
vie d'hommes libres.
Le texte permet d'aborder avec de jeunes enfants les
délicats et douloureux problèmes de l'esclavage et du
racisme.
Dès 5 ans 48 pages
ISBN 2-84083-010-8 70 FF
EDITIONS FRANÇOISE DEFLANDRE SOFEDIS / SODIS
LISEZ TOUS LES MOIS
ETVDES
Revue d'information, de réflexion et de culture
Dans ¡es numéros d'octobre et novembre
Identité et violence
dans les relations internationales
Nations, différences
Prison d'Afrique.
Enfer et damnation
Les enfants domestiques en Haïti
"Mariategui,
philosophe marxiste péruvien
Joseph Maïla
Jean-Yves Calvez
Alain Agboton
Christian Semur
Francis Guibal
Choix de films, Chroniques de théâtre,
Revue des livres, Choix de disques
Le n° : (144 pages] 55 F, étr. 62 F Rédacteur en chef
Abonnement : 11 nos / an : 460 F - étr. 560 F Jean-Yves Calvez
Pour recevoir un numéro ou vous abonner, envoyez vos nom,
adresse et règlement à l'ordre d'ETUDES à :
Assas Editions 14, rue d'Assas - 75006 PARIS - Tél. : (1) 44 39 48 48
Ou, sur Minitel, tapez 36 15 SJ* ETUDES
INSTITUTO CERVANTES
COURS D'ESPAGNOL
1994- 1995
PLACE SOUS LE HAUT PATRONAGE
DE SA MAJESTE LE ROI D'ESPAGNE
* CINQ NIVEAUX DE LANGUE
* COURS DE TRADUCTION FRANÇAIS-ESPAGNOL
* EXPRESSION ORALE
* LITTERATURE CONTEMPORAINE
* GRAMMAIRE
* CULTURE ET CIVILISATION HISPANIQUES
* PREPARATION AUX DIPLÔMES DU MINISTERE
DE L'EDUCATION NATIONALE D'ESPAGNE
COURS SEMI-EXTENSIFS, INTENSIFS ET EXTENSIFS
HORAIRES : MATIN, APRES-MIDI, SOIR
RENSEIGNEMENTS et INSCRIPTIONS
INSTITUTO CERVANTES
1 1 , Avenue Marceau
75116 PARIS
Tel: 47.20.70.79
Fax: 47.20.58.38
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
t UNESC®
OURIER
INTERVIEW WITH
NOËLLE LENOIR
A CODE FOR
LIVING
THE ETHICS OF HUMAN ENGINEERING
äca'ttcttaaaggtcaggc'tctacaaatonaaccca
ägaccctaatttgggttcacctcagtc <aatc
tatgtgagtaactggaagatactgatg icaa
ragctttgttgcgcaggtcaacatg-t?^ tgg
ättccaccaatattattataa-ttccta- ;tga
tctaccaagg-tcj*Boatcgagttcaga;<>. soc;
tgaa-tacttcctfflPJfegttaagtgg' tc¡
tg-tggactat-tajfj
:ctagcatttatäiT
tgggtcatcagccs
äaaactgttgctttstaggattt *
-ttnt+tggaaaccaatgcttacta. aas
tggtacatgctttaac-ttt#» .ygct
agaagaaaactagctaaagsjjg^, iaai
HERITAGE
THE TOWER OF LONDON
ENVIRONMENT
OF MEN AND MOUNTAINS
. M12<6.»M 22,00F
J J
Each month« essential
reading for an
understanding of the
problems of today and
tomorrow
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine published
in 32 languages and read by hundreds of thousands ofpeople in 1 10
countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission of furthering "universal respect
for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms.. .without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
u month- A TOPIC OF UNIVERSAL
eachmontkai"oUGHTHeeyesof m
INTEREST SEEN m D|FFERENT
'^SvARVlNG POINTS OFVIEW...
TINE TO DISARM... THE STORY OF NUNRERS... A NORTH-SOUTH DERATE: THE MEANING OF PROGRESS...
DESERTS... WORLDS WITHIN WORDS... HUMAN RIGHTS, THE UNFINISHED TASK... MODERN
MANAGEMENT AND LOCAL TRADITIONS... A NEW LOOK AT THE HISTORY OF COMMUNISM...
BIOTECHNOLOGY: THE RESOURCEFUL GENE... SURPRISING STRANGERS... A CODE FOR LIVING THE
ETHICS OF HUMAN ENGINEERING... SLAVERY: A CRIME WITHOUT PUNISHMENT...
FRANCOIS MITTERRAND... JORGE AMADO... RICHARD ATTENBOROUCH... JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIERE... JEAN
LACOUTURE... FEDERICO MAYOR... NAGUIR MAHFOUZ... SEMRENE OUSHANE... ANDREI VOZNESENSKY...
FRÉDÉRIC ROSSIF... HINNERK RRUHNS... CAMILO JOSÉ CELA... VACLAV HAVEL... SERGEI S.
AVERINTSEV... ERNESTO SABATO... GRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND... CLAUDE LÉVI-STRAUSS... LEOPOLDO
ZEA... PAULO FREIRÉ... DANIEL J. ROORSTIN... FRANCOIS JACOR... MANU DIRANGO... FAROUK HOSNY...
SADRUDDIN AGA KHAN... JORGE LAVELU... LÉON SCHWARTZENRERG... TAHAR REN JELLOUN... CARRIEL
GARCÍA MAROUEZ... JACOUES-YVES COUSTEAU... MELINA MERCOURI... CARLOS FUENTES... JOSEPH KI-
ZERBO... VANDANA SHIVA... WILLIAM STYRON... OSCAR NIEMEYER... NIKIS THEODORAKIS...
ATAHUALPA YUPANOUI... HERVÉ BOURGES... ARDEL RAHMAN EL RACHA... SUSANA RINALDI... HURERT
REEVES... JOSÉ CARRERAS... A LETTER FROM FREUD TO EINSTEIN... LUC FERRY... CHARLES MALAMOUD...
UMBERTO ECO... OLIVER STONE... ANDRÉ BRINK... JANES D. WATSON... AMOS OZ... MICHEL SERRES...
THÉODORE MONOD... YVES COPPERS... EDOUARD J. HAUNICK... JEAN MALAURIE... TRINH XUAN
THUAN... ANTONI TAPIES... JOSÉ DONOSO... NOËLLE LENOIR... YEHUDAH AMICHAI...
THEME 9F THE NEXT ISSUE (NOVEMBER 1994):
N O N A D S
ALSO FEATURING AN INTERVIEW WITH THE CONDUCTOR AND PIANIST
^^Ê^^^mSw^Ê wÊrnËÊÊm WÊBÈ
]]>
</page>
</document>
