<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="099696eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
UNBCè
OURIER
¥
r
HERITAGE
THE GREAT TEMPLE OF
THANJAVUR
ENVIRONMENT
CLEAN DRIVING: A GREEN DREAM?
* FRANCE: t%T1. - AUSTRALIA At? H KLGMJM WIM CANADA Ci» 7» U*A: ,t K »nTIEIILAMO: M*.** NtTMtRLA-IDS FI 10 DINMARU: ARU
Í.V
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
s /'
Mi
W
/
'I !
The Great
Manitou created
the sun, the moon
and the stars
1 994, oil on canvas
(92 x 73 cm)
by Danie Moulin
,:?
i ,
: r ' M
Í 4W Î f
\ à^l' 1 - '! V^_
ii
*,-.* mí r \
n «1 ?
1
rIf
1 .
V
v
; 1i '
"My painting is intended as a message of
universal love," says French artist Danie
Moulin. She uses signs and symbols from
different cultures in her work in order to
"remind people that others exist and to
encourage a sense of humility." This canvas
is part of an ensemble that will relate the
legend of an American Indian tribe through
its own visual language.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
FEBRUARY 1995
^ -**i*
Cover:
An integrated circuit
provides the background for a
computer-generated image
THE MULTIMEDIA
EXPLOSION
QUO VADIS I
?
5 Interview with Régis Debray
36 HERITAGE
The great temple of Thanjavur
byAppasamy Murugaiyan
41 GREENWATCH
Clean driving: a green dream?
by France Bequette
40 ANNIVERSARY
Fuzuli, poet of divine love
45 UNESCO IN ACTION
46 ARCHIVES
Intuition, intelligence and the making of
modern man
by Salvador de Madariaga
48 LISTENING
The heartbeat of jazz
by Isabelle Leymarie
49 1995: UNITED NATIONS YEAR
FOR TOLERANCE
The world turned upside down
by Lieh-tzu
50 Letters to the Editor
8
11
15
16
19
20
23
26
30
31
32
'New ways of being together'
by Daniel Bougnoux
Unequal voices
by Armand Mattelart
The media: a modern scapegoat?
by Eduardo Valverde
Interactivitya matter of give and take
by Michel Sénécal
The Internet: journey into cyberspace
by Denise Pelissier
From global village to global mind
by Derrick de Kerckhove
The shoals of freedom
by Marcin Frybes
Monopolies, minarets and videos
by Sadok Hammami
Unesco's strategy
interview with Henrikas Yushkiavitshus
From the Cold War
to the era of new technologies
by Alain Modoux
Fact file
Consultant: Daniel Bougnoux
Commentary by Federico Mayor
TU& UNESCO
QPURIER
48th year
Published monthly in 30
languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
Intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, 1 6 NOVEMBER 1 945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THL UNESCO
Courier
48th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
I. rue Miollis, 75732 Paris CEDEX i 5. France.
Fax: (33-1) 45.66.92.70
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque. Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel. 45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
.Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (Tel. 45.68.47. 1 4)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION. Fax: 45.68.45.89
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salan El Din {Tel.
45.68.49.19)
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel. 45 68.45.65
I year: 21 I French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: I year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 21 I FF.
Payment can be nade with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Repnnted from che Unesco Courier", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompa¬
nied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo cap¬
tions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced
in microform {microfilm and.or microfiche) by: (I) Unesco. 7 Place de
Fontenoy. 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor.
Michigan 48100 U.SA; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc..
1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York. U.SA: (4) Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooscer. Ohio 44691, U.SA.
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Printed in Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL CI - FÉVRIER 1995
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: IMPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL, 2. rue Christophe-Plantin
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN 0041-5278 N' 2-I995-OPI-9S-S34A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 2-3 and 50-51.
onth by month
Should we feel threatened by today's dramatic advances in com¬
munication or should we regard them as a source of hope? If many
leading thinkers hold different views on this question or hesitate to
state their position, it is because these advances are ambivalent,
because their present impact and likely future effects imply such
major changes in our ways of living and thinking that we are simul¬
taneously fascinated by the new perspectives they offer us and ner¬
vous about the unknown, unpredictable aspects of the world they
force us to accept.
This issue of the Courier has been prepared to help readers to see
the situation more clearly. It attempts first of all to show that
people's perception of the media and communication explosion
tends to be coloured by where they livein the West, the East or the
South; by whether they side with the powerful producers of state-
of-the-art technology, who transmit knowledge, information and
entertainment, or with those parts of the world that can only
receive what is sent their way by others. Viewpoints also vary
according to whether one favours freedom of expression or com¬
mercial freedom, responsible citizenship or passive consumption,
access to a global culture or the defence of a specific culture.
But after reading the contributions from many backgrounds that
try to come to grips with this issue, it is hard not to return to the
one question that seems to encompass all the others: are advances
in communications restricting and stifling our freedom, or are they
extending and deepening it?
We are inclined to believe that these advances are on the side of
freedom, and even that today's major world challenges are insepa¬
rable from the incredible explosion of freedom that has accompanied
the computer and media revolution of the past two decades.
In the East and in the South, new-found freedom has broadened indi¬
vidual horizons. It has extended people's opportunities to assess,
compare, judge, choose and take personal initiatives more than it
has consolidated their political and social rights. This is why it
often gives rise to doubt and anxiety; to desires, needs and hopes
that are far greater than the means of satisfying them; to the temp¬
tation felt by those left by the wayside to think nostalgically of par¬
adise lost, to reject freedom, progress and the rest of the world out
of hand.
Today's world does not measure up to the expectations to which
this new freedom has given rise. But surely there is nothing new in
this. The spirit of freedom always appears first. It challenges privi¬
lege and the forces of inertia, changes attitudes, breaks new
ground and opens new horizons, leading to solutions that only a short
time before were thought impossible. The next step is for the world
to adapt and change in order to accommodate the projects that will
spring from the imagination of people who are freer, more responsible
and more united.
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
RÉGIS
DEBRAY
talks to
Daniel Bougnoux
The French philosopher, essayist and novelist Régis Debray, who was
born in 1941, is one of the most brilliant thinkers of his generatioa A grad¬
uate of the prestigious Ecole Normale Supérieure, in 1967 he joined Che
Guevara's guerrilla movement in Latin America, which led to three
years' imprisonment in a Bolivian jail. Back in France, he worked on the
Committee for Studies on Freedom established by François Mitterrand
who, after being elected President of France in 1981, appointed him for¬
eign affairs adviser and later assigned him to a post with special
responsibilities for the Third World. Régis Debray's studies of the
world of images, carried out over the last ten years, have led to the devel¬
opment of a new discipline called mediology. His main works on this
theme are Cours de médiologie générale (1991), Vie et mort de l'image,
une histoire du regard en Occident (1992) and Manifestes médiologiques
(1994), all published by Gallimard, Paris.
You have proposed a new discipline
with a rather enigmatic namemediology.
What exactly is mediology?
Mediology is a discipline that is still on
the drawing board. It seeks to examine the
relationship between the higher social func¬
tions (religion, politics, ideology and mental
attitudes) and the technical structures used
for the transmission of information. It there¬
fore looks further than the media that actu¬
ally carry information. It is concerned first
and foremost with symbolic effectiveness:
how do symbols words, writing and fig¬
ures manage to produce specific effects
and become material forces in a given
society? Communication in the modern
sense of the term is a specific, if belated,
response to a much more difficult and per
manent issue, that of mediation. This is a
fundamental notion which has been at the
heart of Christian theology. After all, Christ
is the archetypal mediator: "And the word
was made flesh". The mcdiological assump¬
tion is that it is possible for each period in
history from the neolithic or the invention
of writing to the electronic era to establish
verifiable correlations between the sym¬
bolic activities of a human group, its forms
of political organization and its method of
recording, storing and disseminating
"traces" (ideograms, letters, characters,
sounds and images).
Could you define the field of mediology
and its neighbouring areas rather more
precisely?
The field of mediology? All the interac¬
tions between technology and culture, even
the most tenuous and minor such as
newsprint or radio waves but also trans¬
port networks, the organization charts of
churches and political parties, and so on. The
neighbouring areas of mediology? Semi¬
ology, but semiology does not take account
of material supports and historical discon¬
tinuities and is not interested in power, but
only in the meaning of signs. Sociology,
which does take account of the environ¬
ments in which ideas and images are
received, but disdains technical events and
the impact of all kinds of equipment. Per¬
haps our closest neighbour is the history of
mental attitudes, because a problem cannot
be analysed without looking at the period in
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
'Leading journalists, singers
and stars have become
strong competitors of
teachers as poles of
authority, and the small
screen is becoming a more
important centre of learning
than the traditional school.'
which it occurs. Mediology is built up from
a multitude of empirical works centring on
the materialities of culture.
In this context, what is the role of the
state?
The European nation-state is a child of the
printed word (without which mass education
was inconceivable). In France, the Revolu¬
tion created a state with a mission to educate,
the Republic, based on the ideas of Con-
dorcet. The cult of knowledge and reason,
subordination of the individual to the general
form of the law, order and progress all of
that presupposed control of images by
writing. This system continued to function
until around 1968 when it was destroyed
by the new video techniques the
videosphere. In the videosphere, the impor¬
tance of symbolic (written) and institutional
(parliament, political parties, trade unions)
mediations is diminished, and they are
replaced by the emotional immediacy of
images and sound. Direct broadcasts take
precedence over recordings, the short-term
over the long-term; visible personalities dom¬
inate invisible policies (which cannot be
shown on a screen).
This spells the end of party programmes
and official grand designs. The media state
is programmed by the broadcasting
machine, to whose ideology it subscribes.
Inherent in this ideology are the atomiza-
tion of the social body into categories to the
detriment of the general interest; the wor¬
ship of majorities and consensus; the ele¬
vation of usage to a norm (since the prin¬
cipal social use of the written word is
newspaper reading, let us teach school¬
children to read newspapers); the need to
fabricate events and create sensations. Pri¬
vatization of the state is accompanied by
market-oriented government: the customer
is king; government follows the vagaries
of social demand. The logic of demand
overturns the logic of supply. Each ministry
is guided by its "communicators".
Do these new technologies threaten or
enrich education today? How are our
memory and knowledge evolving in the
era of multi-channel TV, home computers,
CD-ROM and data banks?
Leading journalists, singers and stars
have become strong competitors of
teachers as poles of authority, and the small
screen is becoming a more important centre
of learning than the traditional school.
This is a very serious trend because knowl¬
edge cannot be reduced to knowing facts.
Knowledge is more than mere informa¬
tion; culture bears within it the memory of
meaning, it is more than today's news blot¬
ting out recollection of the past. The mes¬
sage recorded in a text has more content
than a live broadcast of images and sounds.
So it would be wrong to suppose that
an image culture can dispense with the
need for the rigours of discursive and
abstract thinking. At heart it presupposes
their existence. An aerial photograph will
be meaningless to an observer who does
not have some experience of archaeology.
Unless we teach children to read at least a
little, we cannot teach them to see. If we
place the broadcasting of messages above
the training of the human mind, we are
putting the cart before the horse.
The problem is that a basic course in
musical notation brings less credit to a
government leader today than the inau¬
guration of a new music festival which will
receive wide press coverage. But the former
is more essential to the development of
musical culture than the latter. It seems to
me that the traditional library of books is
the best path towards the video library,
whereas the reverse is not the case. Those
who replace history lessons by showing
historical films on video cassettes in the
classroom are merely helping to bring
supply and demand a little further into
line in the cultural sphere.
Having said that, the real problem, or
rather its pedagogical solution, is the com¬
puter. The computer should be capable of
enhancing the role of distance education at
university level, of providing continuing
education for adults and of offering greater
equality of access to knowledge.
What about the idea of the global vil¬
lage, of which so much has been made
since McLuhan?
The missing dimension of the McLuhan-
style global village is what I would call the
"jogging effect". With the invention of the
motor vehicle, the futurologists of 1910 said
that town-dwellers stuck in their little box
on wheels would soon be unable to use their
legs. But when urban man stopped walking,
he began to run instead. As the objects of our
planet become increasingly globalized, so its
subjects are more and more tribalized. Each
step forward towards the economic unifi¬
cation of the world is accompanied, through
a process of compensation, by a step back¬
wards in the cultural and political spheres.
Technology does of course oblige us to stan¬
dardize the media and so also to some extent
the messages carried by them. But the dif¬
ferences in mental outlooks and memory
rise up in opposition to that trend. Each
imbalance created by a new form of tech¬
nical progress is accompanied by a reshaping
of the ethnic balance. Hence the confusion
between the process of European unification
and a phenomenon of Balkanization,
between the progress of science and the
advance of superstition, between economic
imperatives and territorial aspirations.
Our village, which is both increasingly
global and narrow-mindedly patriotic
the one because of the other lives in an age
of nationalism, separatism, irredentism and
tribalism, the dark faces of which are called
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
segregation, war and xenophobia. The cen¬
trifugal forces which are threatening to frag¬
ment the great multinational states do not
spare the centralized countries of Europe
with their very old "civilizations".
What do you feel about what has been
called "the cultural exception", the idea
that cultural products should be given
some form of special protection from glob¬
alized free trade?
The purpose of the cultural exception is
to prevent the Spanish, Brazilian, Argen¬
tine, Canadian, Indian and other cinemas
from being relegated to a ghetto, turned
into folklore and confined to a small local
market of 10 per cent the sop given by the
imperial power to the cause of fringe enter¬
tainment. The survival of the people
without a voice and without images is at
stake here, whatever their language may be.
'The traditional library of
books is the best path
towards the video library,
whereas the reverse is not
the case.'
The real question is this: are we entitled
today to allow several different visions of
the world to circulate or just one? And if
we do want more than one, are we pre¬
pared to make the necessary resources
available with public aid for production, a
redistribution of profits and broadcasting
quotas?
Edison once said that "whoever con¬
trols the cinema industry will control the
most powerful means of influencing the
people." Today, he would have to say: all
peoples. The image governs our dreams and
dreams govern our actions. Political hege¬
mony always presupposes the destruction of
different outlooks. The cultural proletariza-
tion of three-quarters of all mankind is liable
to give rise in the twenty-first century to
even more resolute and numerous rebels
than the economic proletarians of the nine¬
teenth century. Is the whole planet to be
converted into a supermarket where the peo¬
ples will have no choice between the local
ayatollah and Coca-Cola? Natives versus
yuppies: this is a split that exists in all coun¬
tries. Let us heed the warning and see to it
that the soul of the minority cultures,
drowned under the waves of uniform images
and sounds and deprived of any outlet for
self-expression, does not look for a way out
in the worst forms of indigenist or funda¬
mentalist regression.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
'New ways of being together'
by Daniel Bougnoux
8
Communicating means sharing and establishing relationships. This
being so, the extraordinary growth of the contemporary media, which
is being accompanied by a transformation of cultures, identities and
modes of exercising power and authority, is leading to the invention
of new ways of being together.
j The history of civilization is intertwined
with the history of the gradual depar¬
ture from rural areas that had been occupied
for thousands of years, with the dematerializa-
tion of the instruments and products of human
work, with the promotion and rapid distribution
of signs (foremost among them being currency),
with growing desacralization and increasing
mobility as part of the phenomenon of urbani¬
zation. The peasantry no longer gives society its
direction; culture has ceased to be synonymous
with agriculture.
Communication, modernization and ratio¬
nalization advance hand in hand. By destroying
the rural base of society (by the year 2000, one
half of the world's population will be living in
cities), the modernization that began in Europe
in the late Middle Ages has taken people away
from the fields and brought them into the orbit
of historical time. According to Max Weber,
historical time is fashioned by three great
"machines": the market economy; activities
which require calculation and analysis (techno¬
science); and the bureaucratic nation-state.
This threefold opening may also be experi¬
enced as a loss of roots. Admittedly it has
enabled contemporary individualism to
blossom, but only at the cost of a radical revision
of old forms of identity. People no longer live on
stable ground. With the onset or progress of
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
"The history of civilization is
intertwined with urbanization.
The peasantry no longer gives
society its direction".
Opposite, New York City.
Below, Berber village women in
the High Atlas, Morocco.
communication technologies, we are witnessing
a transition:
- from the vertical to the horizontal: the media
which open up the world are irresistibly eroding
the old transcendent values. Hence the advance of
secularism; but after the Church, education and the
state are experiencing the same levelling process;
- from stock to flows: in banking, in companies
and in the knowledge-based economy, wealth is
now measured less in terms of fixed capital
assets than by the capacity of operators to mobi¬
lize those assets and bring them into circula¬
tion; currency itself has become increasingly
abstract and impalpable;
- from content to relationships: it is no longer
enough for a product to be good; it must also
find a buyer. On the market, the value of an
object is governed by its appearance; it is not
substance or content that count but attraction or
visibility. The public relations imperative extends
to all who take part in public life politicians,
show business or cultural stars, to wherever
"what you are is what you are seen to be";
- from heteronymy to autonomy: people who are
called upon to express themselves and be them¬
selves without fear or favour are ideal participants
in this slow process of detachment and analysis.
But this utopia of modern times cannot keep
its promises. People do not receive their identity
from themselves but from a place, a family or
some other symbolic upstream factor. People are
territorial beings who have everything to fear
from a culture which has lost contact with the
soil or is exposed to the onslaught of unbridled
communication.
Are we heading for cultural
standardization?
The more a message circulates, the more it is
liable to lose its particular savour or information
content. Thus the new imagery of communica¬
tion which has become a world of its own can
engender an indifferent and superficial cos¬
mopolitan subculture, whose emblem might be
the smiling face of Mickey Mouse. When we sit
in front of our television sets and play with the
globe as Chaplin did in The Great Dictator, we
get an overview of the life and death of others
that cannot be called knowledge. All television
viewers know something about Bosnia and
Rwanda, but that awareness does little to change
the course of history. In this case the commu¬
nication window merely engenders a feeling of
powerlessness and shame.
New fears are also emerging. Who will ben¬
efit from the information superhighways of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
'The peasant's field of olden times has been replaced by the
page, and ploughing has given way to a thousand different
forms of writing, to hardware and software and computer
screens which multiply our impressions and memories to an
extraordinary degree.'
future? How can we be sure that globalization,
or the "global village" of which we have heard
so much, will not amount to Americanization?
How can we safeguard our own identity or cul¬
tural "exception"?
While the waning of the idea of territori¬
ality may suit a few modern people who are
fully committed to nomadic cosmopolitanism,
for most it is frustrating their sense of identity
in many ways. Whereas people have tradition¬
ally been "placed" by their jobs and their
housing, the modern world will increasingly
require them to change their occupation and
place of residence in the course of their lives to
adjust to a rapidly changing world. Hence a
sense of meaninglessness and confusion. Faced
with growing mobility which inevitably spells
the end of old forms of solidarity and creates
exclusion, an immense need for identity is being
expressed through the come-back of religion, of
charismatic father-figures and "populist" politi¬
cians who promise tangible identifications and
warm organic relations.
However, it is by no means certain that the
modern media manufacture homogeneity. The
German philosopher Theodor Adorno saw
them as an instrument for the standardization of
culture; but the very notion of mass turns out
here to be misleading or otiose, and mass com¬
munications, like mass consumption, tend on the
contrary to become ramified and individual-
"When we sit in front of our
TV sets ... we get an overview
of the life and death of others
that cannot be called
knowledge." Below, a British
television crew in a Rwandan
refugee camp in Zaire.
10
ized, revealing what is specific, occasional or
distinctive.
Finally, at world level, it seems that the
mosaic of races, cultures, beliefs and histories is
far more opaque than the superficial imagery of
"communication" would have us believe. Surely
the best way to have something to communicate
is to acquire a deeper familiarity with one's own
culture.
Transmitting to unpredictable receivers
We must take care not to extrapolate from the
relative standardization of transmission and
conclude that the effects, or the messages that
viewers receive (and process) in their own
worlds, are themselves uniform. The standard¬
ization of mass communications may be a
worldwide phenomenon, but the fact remains
that we do not know how people watch and
we cannot foresee what they will remember.
Identity is neither a thing nor a deposit that
can be manipulated or exchanged at will, but an
active system of relationships and representa¬
tions. Each individual lives in his or her "own
world", entrenched behind a filter that may be
compared to an immunological barrier. That is
why the transmission of information is not a
linear process but circular (with feedback to
the transmitter and/or coproduction of the mes¬
sage by the receiver) and haphazard.
We moderns have no vertical roots in the
soil; nor are we confined to a particular piece of
territory. Our roots spread out horizontally;
they follow the network of signs and knowledge
that we are capable of processing. The peasant's
field of olden times has been replaced by the
page, and ploughing has given way to a thousand
different forms of writing, to hardware and
software and computer screens which multiply
our impressions and memories to an extraordi¬
nary degree.
The extension of these new machines there¬
fore announces the end of the (single, panoramic)
world. Under the onslaught of diversity, our
reality is receding or breaking up, to be replaced
by a plurality of worlds. Everywhere the com¬
munication of signs is outstripping the produc¬
tion of goods and services, and from their
coloured cloth each one of us cuts a Harlequin
suit which prefigures new norms of knowledge,
new frontiers and affinities, new ways of being
together and being onself.
DANIEL BOUGNOUX,
of France, is professor of communication at the Stendhal
University of Grenoble-3. His published works include La
Communication par la bande (La Découverte, Paris, 1991) and
Sciences de l'information et de la communication (Larousse,
Paris, 1993).
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Unequal voices by Armand Mattelart
Globalization of markets and exchanges is creating new disparities
between nations and may lead to a two-speed communication
system as well as a two-speed economy.
Above,
the Tokyo stock exchange.
Communication (not only through the
media, but also in the sense of exchanges
and the free movement of persons, goods and
messages of all kinds) has become a form of
world organization. Confronted with the ban¬
kruptcy of the old ideology of continuous, linear
progress, communication has now taken over. It
has become the yardstick by which the evolution
of humankind is judged at a time when people
have lost their bearings and are searching des¬
perately for the meaning of their future.
The English term "globalization" is often
used to describe this phase in the international
growth of exchanges through the development
of communications. Globalization has already
become a reality: increasingly, our societies are
linked up by information and communication
networks whose logic consists in operating in a
universal mode. But it is also an over-simplifying
notion a ready-made ideological approach
which conceals, instead of revealing, the com¬
plexity of this new world order.
Although the idea of the "global village"
was first mooted in the late 1960s by the Cana¬
dian university professor Marshall McLuhan1,
this view of our planet did not gain a firm
foothold until the 1980s, which witnessed the
globalization of markets, financial circuits, com¬
panies and all kinds of intangible exchanges.
This trend was made possible by a wave of
deregulation and privatization which turned
the market into the regulating factor of society.
This in turn resulted firstly in the weakening of
social forces, the decline of the welfare state
and of the public service philosophy and, sec¬
ondly, in the growing power of the corpora¬
tion, its values and private interests.
In the wake of this change, which encouraged
the deployment of technological networks and
big multimedia groups, the nature and status
of communication itself changed: it became 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
'Freedom of expression now has a competitor in the shape of
freedom of commercial expression, which some wish to elevate
into a new human right. This creates an ongoing tension between
the empirical law of the market and the rule of law, between the
sovereignty of the consumer and that of the citizen.'
increasingly professional and its areas of respon¬
sibility and activities proliferated. As to its
methods, which were presented as models for
the management of social relations, they fin¬
ished up by penetrating the whole of society.
Today, state institutions, intergovernmental
organizations, local and regional authorities,
and even such varied humanitarian associations
as Médecins Sans Frontières, Greenpeace and
Amnesty International have no hesitation in
using public relations expertise to establish
closer links with the general public.
Prom globalization to glocalization
The idea of globalization is therefore the stock-
in-trade of marketing and management experts.
In a sense it is the key to their world-view and
the foundation of the incipient new world order.
They see in it the demise of early-twentieth-
century scientific management techniques
because the hierarchy of authority and the spe¬
cialization of tasks created by those techniques
corresponded to a structure of the world that no
longer exists. In those days the local, national
and international levels were seen as a succession
of compartments which were impervious to
. each other. The new view of businesses and the
In Delhi (India), a group of world in wn;cn tney function as a "network"
young people use stereoscopes
to look at 3-D images.
establishes an association between these three
different levels. Any business strategy on the
globalized market must be at one and the same
time international and local; Japanese managers
use the English neologism "glocalize" to denote
this phenomenon. This new corporate logic is
governed by the keyword of integration: inte¬
gration of geographical scales, but also of design,
production and marketing or even of spheres of
activity which were previously separate. This
word does of course evoke a holistic or per¬
haps cybernetic vision of the organization of
the world into great economic units.
The widespread acceptance of the concept of
globalization in the strategic thinking of entre¬
preneurs has changed the rules of the interna¬
tional game, to say nothing of the course of
negotiations embarked upon in the sphere of
communication networks.
A first conceptual shift has taken place in the
very definition of freedom of expression, which
has now found a competitor in the shape of
"freedom of commercial expression"; attempts
are being made to elevate the latter into a new
human right. This creates an ongoing tension
between the empirical law of the market and
the rule of law, between the sovereignty of the
consumer and that of the citizen. Organiza¬
tions of communication professionals saw this
as a justification and legitimization of their lob¬
bying campaigns in favour of "television without
frontiers" in the second half of the 1980s.
As a principle for the organization of the
world, the concept of the freedom of commercial
expression is indissociable from the old prin¬
ciple of the "free flow of information" which
was invented at the start of the Cold War and has
always come to terms with the unequal distrib-
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
ution of information flows. The managerial doc¬
trine of the corporate undertaking has made this
principle popular once again; it equates freedom
to engage in trade with freedom as such.
Another shift, this time geographical, has
occurred in the assumptions underlying the
debate on the subject of communication. In the
1970s and until the early 1980s, UNESCO was one
of the main platforms chosen by the movement
of non-aligned nations to launch the idea of a
"new world information and communication
order". Since 1985, however, studies of this sub¬
ject have been entrusted to a more technical
agency, i.e. GATT (the General Agreement on
Tariffs and Trade). Communication is treated
here on the same footing as services and includes
the products of the cultural industries, together
with telecommunications, tourism and man¬
agement techniques.
A special case for culture
The recent GATT negotiations were the set¬
ting for a direct confrontation between the
European Union and the United States on the
subject of the "cultural exception". This con¬
frontation ended on 13 December 1993 in the
outright exclusion of audiovisual and cultural
productions from the scope of the free trade
agreements. On that occasion, the gulf could
be seen to widen between the defenders of cul¬
tural identity and the proponents of the intran¬
sigent application of the criterion of "goods" to
every form of production.
During the debate on the liberalization of
services, the latter advanced arguments of a pop¬
ulist kind. To justify their opposition to the
clause excluding cultural products from the
agreements, they put forward ideas of the fol¬
lowing kind: "Let people watch whatever they
like. Leave them to make their own judgment.
Trust in their common sense. The only judgment
of a cultural product must be its success or
failure on the market."
This argument is not entirely negative in
that it recognizes that the user plays an active
role, whereas the determinist theories of the
1960s and 1970s simply put him on the receiving
end of the communication machine. However,
by restoring the consumer's own discernment
and stressing his freedom to decide for himself,
the problem of the inequality of exchanges on
the world market for cultural products, and
that of the need to protect the diversity of cul¬
tures through appropriate national and regional
policies, are sidelined.
Should the freedom granted to televiewers
reduce them to wholesale consumption of the
Above, a demonstration of
virtual reality simulation
equipment at a show in
Monaco. The helmeted user is
"inside" a computer-generated
environment that closely '
resembles reality.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
In a shop window in Allahabad
(India) Shiva, the Vedic god of
fire, is used as an advertising
ploy for electric torches.
Below right, hot-air balloons
bearing advertising slogans lift
off from the grounds of a
French château.
14
ARMAND MATTELART,
of Belgium, is professor of
information and communications
at the University of Rennes-2
(France). He is the author of a
number of books on the history
and theories of communications,
which have been translated into
several languages. His most
recent published work in English
is Mapping World
Communication: War, Progress,
Culture (University of Minnesota
Press, Minneapolis/London,
1994). His The Invention of
Communication is scheduled for
publication later this year by the
University of Minnesota Press.
products of a hegemonic industry, or should
they on the contrary be helped to discover the
products of other cultures, starting with their
own? If we are not careful, the one-sided glori¬
fication of the consumer will lead to legit¬
imization of the subordination of certain peoples
and cultures. Until the late 1970s, this process
was known as "cultural imperialism" and eth¬
nologists continue to describe it as "ethnocide".
Unfortunately, when these matters are discussed,
there is often a slender margin between narrow-
minded chauvinism and defence of the right of
each culture to preserve its own access and spe¬
cific contribution to universal culture.
Ureolized cultures
It is disturbing to note the extent to which the
concepts inherent in the idea of globalization are
now taken for granted in any description of the
process of internationalization of cultural and
economic exchanges which is under way today.
If we are to do justice to the complexity of the
phenomena observed, it is imperative to define
a new conceptual framework.
I believe that it is preferable to regard the
current phase as that of the emergence of "world-
communication", a notion which explicitly refers
back to the idea of "world-economy" forged by
the historian Fernand Braudel to describe the
impact of macro-economic flows on the evolution
of national economies. As happened during the
gradual construction of the economic world,
progress towards a planetary "world-commu¬
nication" system is creating new disparities
between countries, regions and social groups. It
is giving rise to new forms of exclusion. By rel¬
egating a part of mankind to its periphery, it is
liable to drag our planet into a two-speed eco¬
nomic and communication system. In future, we
may have a world structured around a small
number of megalopolises situated for the most
The 1980s saw a quest for a global
culture but also the comeback of
individual cultures.
part in the North, but in some cases in the South,
from which all the principal flows of information
and communication radiate out and to which
they return. Globalization is not incompatible
with increasing disparities. These are two sides of
the same coin.
While the 1980s saw a quest for a levelling
global culture on the part of the great transna¬
tional corporations in search of "universals"
which were capable of facilitating the penetra¬
tion of their products onto the world market,
they were also a time when individual cultures
made a comeback. The tensions and disparities
between the plurality of cultures and the cen¬
trifugal forces of commercial cosmopolitanism
revealed the complexity of reactions to the emer¬
gence of a single worldwide market.
Today, greater attention is being paid to the
way in which each culture and each community
receives and adapts the messages carried on the
world communication networks. How do the
negotiations between the specific and the uni¬
versal, between the national and the interna¬
tional elements take place? Can individual cul¬
tures survive? Can they adapt? Or will they go
under? These new approaches have enabled the
terms "Americanization" and "dependence" to
be replaced by others such as "hybridization"
and "Creolization".
This new interest in fragmentation and inter¬
actions may prove ambivalent. It obliges us to
reflect on the process of globalization of
exchanges and on its relationship with everyday
democracy. But it can also cohabit readily with
nationalist and even chauvinist attitudes. A lucid
and critical observation of the former without
falling into the trap of the latter such is the
challenge that awaits us on the eve of the twenty-
first century.
1 In War and Peace in the Global Village (1968), a work
written jointly with Quentin Fiore.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Many people were shocked when the
1991 Gulf War was turned into a world
media event; they complained that by turning
the conflict into a giant video game, commu¬
nications had exceeded its mandate. They
forgot that the media have never been neutral
and that, like war, they heighten and make
visible our most diverse and contradictory
thoughts and actions.
And yet when I ask my students in Brazil
what effect the Gulf War had on them, they
seem surprised, as if that war were not a
part of their personal experience. Perhaps,
like their parents before them, they believe
that the notion of experience encompasses
only what happens near to home. All the
same they are forced to admit that media
events have an impact, however slight, on
their daily lives and, even though they may be
unaware of it, inevitably influence their ways
of acting and thinking.
The modern media are frightening because
they are correctlythought to be capable of
influencing people's judgment. Modern com¬
munication calls into question the autonomy
and freedom of the individual, the great myth
of our time. But is this really new? People's
judgment and the way in which they perceive
their experience have always been deter¬
mined by the group to which they belong.
With the globalization of communications,
however, this phenomenon has taken on
exceptional scope. In addition to the modes
of perception inherited from the "ancestral
homeland" come others which are shared by
people all over the world.
The modern media make us aware of the
limits of human freedom and of the relative
nature of the reality in which we have always
been immersed.
M isplaced fears
Theorists of communication are also afraid of
the media, often because they make a
methodological error. Using ideas applied to
exchanges between individuals, they can only
envisage exchange within the framework of a
single linguistic unit. Looked at in this way the
global communications media seem like an
immense sound and visual backdrop that
destroys dialogue and replaces it with a mono¬
logue that is listened to passively.
By using criteria of another age to assess
the modern media, these thinkers forget that
the media can have a civilizing effect and
can create a new balance in today's ways of
seeing, talking and acting.
To exist is to transcend one's condition.
And the human condition today includes the
media world whose existence we must
accept.
Standing beneath an open-air screen in Rio de
Janeiro, Brazilian soccer fans watch a World Cup
match transmitted live from the United States In
1994.
Let us take the soccer World Cup as an
example of the huge media events that inter¬
national sporting competitions have now
become. The 1994 World Cup was organized
and orchestrated by the United States, where
it was followed with a certain indifference. In
Brazil, however, a country which was simply
a receiver of the media coverage, it generated
tremendous enthusiasm. The intensity was
greater in Brazil than in the United States,
where the sport is not part of the national con¬
sciousness.
We must stop being afraid of losing our
identity. We must understand that modem
communication is flexible and that its mes¬
sages and images can be made ours just as
easily as our parents appropriated those
offered by television and the cinema, and
earlier, by the theatre, music, poetry and
painting.
MONCLAR EDUARDO GOES DE LIMA VALVERDE,
of Brazil, heads the programme for advanced studies
in contemporary communications and culture at the
Federal University of Bahia. The author of many
articles published in Brazilian journals, he is
presently preparing two books, one of which deals
with "the communication experience".
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Interactivity
a matter of give and take by Michel sénécai
A democratic communication system is inconceivable without fair
exchange, plurality of viewpoints, direct contact between
transmitters and receivers, decentralization and respect for privacy
and freedom of expression.
With each new wave of development in
media technology, hopes are raised that
communication in society will be rendered more
democratic. Unscrupulous operators invariably
step forth to promote technical equipment that
they claim will lead directly to fundamental
social change. The word interactive crops up
16
Right, a bundle of optical
fibres, glass filaments that are
increasingly being used for
long-distance transmission of
information in the form of
computer data, voice messages
and video.
ê
*aí^2. * jÈf ^^k
> _r t. i '' m!
^9*éj * 'jrW . .
;^PjA
/ M
f
:w7f
*<
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
again and again whenever businessmen and poli¬
ticians talk about the electronic information
superhighways of the future. Such metaphors
propagate a new technical and cultural myth,
that of a "communication society" on a global
scale.
Readiness to label all kinds of media tech¬
nology as "interactive" without the term ever
being precisely defined suggests that the word
is being used less to describe these technolo¬
gies than to make them commercially attrac¬
tive. However, there is not necessarily any cor¬
relation between the degree of interactivity
possessed by a piece of technical equipment
and the level of democracy attained by the
media. When a system is described as "uni¬
versal, bidirectional and interactive", we should
ask ourselves who is going to use it and with
whom, and what will be communicated?
Moreover, the fact that a system is universal
does not necessarily mean that it is interactive. It
may enable the suppliers of a service to deliver
directly to subscribers the information and goods
they ask for, but it does not mean that the system's
promoters have equipped it with the technical
facilities (interface, bandwidth, etc.) for commu¬
nication between users. In cable distribution
interactivity has so far been limited to a new way
of choosing goods and services, but one in which
the vertical exchange of data received and trans¬
mitted has remained inegalitarian.
If a communication system is to be used
democratically, it must meet a number of other
conditions as well as being interactive. These
conditions are: immediate and complete reci¬
procity in all exchanges; plurality of viewpoints;
the establishment of direct relations between
partners free both to transmit and receive mes¬
sages; decentralization of information circuits;
respect for freedom of expression and for privacy.
A challenge to civil society
New technical developments must be appraised
critically, taking into account the needs, interests
and values of users.
Regardless of the technological background
of any communications project, what matters
most is its accessibility. Only this can make mul¬
tiple exchanges possible, placing each user, as
often as he or she so wishes, in the position of a
supplier of information to the network.
No communication system can be consid¬
ered genuinely democratic if it causes exclu¬
sion, either because of its inaccessibility or
because of the images of society it creates. If its
architecture is closed and vertical, it may operate
exclusively to the benefit of a few authorized
suppliers.
Will the coming "information superhigh¬
ways" simply renew existing methods of
delivery and distribution of goods of all kinds:
catalogue retail sales, pay-per-view, electronic
entertainment, banking services, video games,
lotteries and so on? The new networks such as
teleshopping via cable TV will resemble elec¬
tronic home distribution centres over which
absolute control will be exercised by certain
private interests. Here interactivity will be lim¬
ited to sophisticated systems of selectivity,
allowing choices to be made among a number of
pre-programmed commercial options.
But it is also possible that information high¬
ways could provide the general public with
access to genuine information networks of the
kind that are already being offered by the
Internet. Combined with decentralized com¬
munication mechanisms, interactivity would
then encourage conversational-type reciprocal
exchanges. The roles of transmitter and receiver
would become interchangeable, allowing a very
Above, a computer exhibition
in Paris.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
An Afghan journalist being
trained in Peshawar, Pakistan.
At this home shopping centre
in the United States, 2,000
operators can take 20,000
calls a minute.
wide diversity of viewpoints to be expressed.
This socio-political definition of interactivity is
based on a participatory, egalitarian view of
communication, one that would offer all indi¬
viduals and social groups who are excluded
from the dominant models presented by the
media the means to compose and broadcast
messages that correspond to their real commu¬
nication needs.
The Internet is the product of a hybridization
process. Originally designed for military use,
then for institutional use, it finally underwent a
certain process of socialization to become what
it is today. Unfortunately, it is already being
eyed covetously by financial interests, and vir¬
tual shopping malls are appearing on it. This
development calls to mind the period during
which European radio and television stations
were "liberalized", particularly in France and
Italy in the late 1970s, leading to the creation of
private audiovisual companies. The challenge
to state monopolies by social movements mobi¬
lized to remove communication from the thrall
of the authorities and of market forces resulted,
paradoxically, in the commercialization of the
media via privatization.
I wo opposing concepts
Thus there are tensions between two opposing
concepts of interactivity selectivity and reci¬
procity reflecting two different views of the
democratization of the media. In one, viewers
are a captive audience in a commercial environ¬
ment provided to them on a turnkey basis, in
which the idea of interactivity remains frozen at
a purely instrumental stage, entirely oriented
towards consumption. The other calls for a crit¬
ical reappropriation of the media based on plu¬
rality and reciprocity of exchanges as well as
greater participation in the decision-making
process by those who are at the receiving end of
the communication process.
The predominance of the view focusing on
the technical and customer aspects of commu¬
nication is certainly linked to a specific concept
of democracy, subject to the logic of the market
and clearly oriented towards reduced public-
sector services. Interactive technologies will
thus continue to lend themselves to social par¬
ticipation in name only unless citizens mobilize
in support of a more accessible and egalitarian
form of media democratization.
18
MICHEL SÉNÉCAL,
of Quebec (Canada), is a
professor and researcher at the
Télé-université of the University
of Quebec. He is the author of
"The Alternative in Search of its
Identity", which appeared in
Video the Changing World, a
collective work edited by Nancy
Thede and Alain Ambrosi (Black
Rose Books, Montreal, 1991).
His latest book, Une démocratie
du paradoxe, Logiques d'acteurs
et démocratisation de l'espace
médiatique, is scheduled for
publication later this year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
WHAT IS IT?
It has become virtually impossible
to open a newspaper, a news¬
magazine or a professional journal
without finding something about the
Internet. This super-telematic net¬
work, the world's largest, is being
seen as a phenomenon unequalled
since the invention of the printing
press and a revolution in the pro¬
duction, circulation and exchange of
information. It consists of more than
13,000 interconnected computer net¬
works, and the number of its users
(high-school and university students,
researchers, engineers), already esti¬
mated to be some 30 million in 150
countries, is increasing every day.
Forerunner of the "information
superhighways" of the twenty-first
century, to use the expression coined
during the American presidential cam¬
paign of 1992 by vice-presidential
candidate AI Gore, the Internet was
set up in the United States in the
1960s. Originally intended only to
link up a few computers belonging to
research centres and universities
working on a defence project, the
network is today growing at the rate
of 20 per cent per month, and its
management is completely decen¬
tralized. Internet is not owned by
anyone. Each network pays for the
installation and operating costs as
well as its being connected up to the
other networks.
In short the Internet is both an
electronic village and an international
campus where all information is grad¬
ually organized into an immense vir¬
tual library. It is also a gigantic test
bench for developing open networks
covering the entire planet.
WHAT ARE ITS USES?
First of all it is used for communi¬
cating via electronic mail (e-mail).
This abolishes the notion of distance.
Users from the world over can chat
back and forth or take part in round-
table discussions at low cost. For
example, high-school students in San
Diego (U.S.A.) send and receive let¬
ters from students in a school in
Israel. During the attempted coup
d'état in Russia in August 1991,
THE INTERNET
JOURNEY INTO CYBERSPACE
by Denise Pelissier
People all over the world are taking their first steps on the information
superhighway by joining the Internet. Chatting about science,
sport or politics with someone on the other side of the globe; con¬
sulting the catalogue of the Library of Congress in Washington;
admiring the masterpieces in Florence's Uffizi Gallery; delving into
Unesco's data base in Paristhese are just a few of the myriad pos¬
sibilities open to Internet users.
RELCOM, a small network linked to
the Internet through Finland, was the
only means of communication
between Moscow and the outside
world.
The Internet mailbox hosts
debates and forums, serious and light-
hearted, on all kinds of subjects,
from science and politics to leisure,
sports and games. In order to receive
messages in your electronic mailbox
from other subscribers and to send
out replies all you have to do is sub¬
scribe. It is an unparalleled device for
finding the solution to a problem.
There is always someone along the
highway who knows the answer.
Images and sounds, as well as
computer data, travel around the
Internet, which makes it possible to
consult from a distance the cata¬
logues of the world's great libraries,
that of the Library of Congress, for
example, in the United States, visu¬
alize satellite photos taken by the
American national meteorological
service, admire the masterpieces on
display in Madrid's Prado, the Orsay
Museum in Paris or the Uffizi in Flo¬
rence. It is also possible to procure
softwarefree-of-charge if it is in
the public domain [freeware) and for
a nominal charge if it is shareware.
Books and newspapers can be pub¬
lished electronically on the Internet,
and international conferences can
even be organized through it.
WHO'S INTERESTED?
Most universities and a growing
number of research bodies are
already hooked up to the Internet.
Many United Nations agencies are
also on itthe United Nations itself,
the International Atomic Energy
Agency, the International Telecom¬
munication Union, the United Nations
Development Programme, the World
Health Organization, the World Bank,
the Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion, UNICEF (the United Nations
Children's Fund) and Unesco. It is
thereby possible to find out about
each agency's goals, activities, pro¬
grammes and publications, consult
each agency's data base and hop
from one server to another.
It is also possible for individuals
to hook up to the network through pri¬
vate companies such as CompuServe
and Delphi. All that's needed is a
computer, a modem (telephone con¬
verter) and communications soft¬
ware.
Benefit from the Internet explo¬
sion is not confined to the developed
countries; it is also a particularly
interesting tool for the developing
countries, although the situation
varies widely from region to region.
The Internet has great potential for
promoting exchanges and strength¬
ening North-South and South-South
co-operation, for it facilitates direct
contact between researchers and
helps those who feel cut off to get
into the mainstream.
GROWING PAINS
Originally free of charge and intended
to provide mutual help among
researchers from around the world,
the Internet is changing. In the United
States 60 per cent of the institutions
presently connected to it are private
companies, as against 40 per cent in
France. A number of pay-per-service
networks are appearing. Problems
are arising about security, information
reliability and copyright.
Anyone with a personal computer
can disseminate information. And it
is very easy to copy the electronic
version of a document or a data base
and rebroadcast it, with or without
modifications, under a different name.
To provide security on the net¬
work and prevent undesirable intru¬
sions, devices known as firewalls-
barriers that shut off parts of
computer systems have been devel¬
oped. Confidential information must
be encrypted before being sent.
The Internet is also a victim of its
success. Traffic jams are not
unknown. At certain times of the day
the networks are so crowded that it
is practically impossible to connect
with certain servers. In France, for
example, it is a good idea to take
advantage of the time difference by
working with American servers in the
morning.
Despite its growing pains,
Internet is already an exceptional
means of communication. Cross-
border transfers of Information have
become a daily reality for millions of
users the world over.
DENISE PELISSIER
is chief of the Clearing House of
Unesco's Bureau of Documentation,
Informatics Services and
Telecommunications.
FURTHER INFORMATION:
John R. Levine, Internet for Dummies, San Mateo, Ca., IDG Books,
1993, 352 pp.
Ed Krol, The Whole Internet: User's Guide and Catalogue, Sebastopol,
Ca., O'Reilly cop., 1994, 534 pp.
Recent Literature on Internet, Electronic Mail and Electronic Net¬
working, bibliography available from the Institute for the Development
of Research of the University of Tilburg, Holland. E.mail: ewoldt@kub.nl;
fax (31) 13 663 015.
Anne Sanouillet, L'Internet pour nous autres, Centre du 20e siècle.
Université de Nice/Sophia Antipolis, 81, rue de France, 06000 Nice,
France, ISBN 2-902311-86-9, 20 pp.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
From global village to global
mind by Derrick de Kerckhove
While television has turned the planet into a village in which we are all neighbours,
telematic networks abolish time and space and suppress traditional bearings of personal
and collective identity
If books, especially novels, fostered and
sustained the development of private
minds in public space, television has done the
reverse, bringing a public mind to private spaces.
Television screens are collective extensions of our
individual minds. Instead of information being
processed by a single person, namely me, the
television screen presents me with information
processed by a collective of which I am an inte¬
gral part.
"Live" TV, or "real-time" TV, is a kind of
collective eye which allows my eyes to look at
reality processed for me and for every other
person watching at the same time. Whenever
something happens that is internationally news¬
worthy, a huge thoughtwave made up of millions
of people grinding the same information at once
forms and reforms itself every evening and
sweeps over the nations from one time zone to
another. Even in its standard programming, TV
20
is a form of collective imagination, averaging
people's hopes and fears on the basis of a regular
public-pulse-taking through ratings.
Such thoughts may have occurred to Amer¬
ican journalist Bill Moyers when he called his
four ground-breaking shows on the workings of
television "TV, the Public Mind" (1989). Of
course, Moyers was really thinking about U.S.
television, and at that time Hollywood and the
Big Three U.S. channels still seemed to present
a united front and a coherent vision of the world.
Two questions are raised when the notion of
television as a form of public mind is examined
more closely. First, is the public mind uniquely
dependent on TV, and if it is, then what happens
when TV and TV audiences fragment as they are
doing today? Second, is TV generating a public
mind beyond the confines of the United States,
and if so, who is running the show? According
to French culturologist Augustin Berque, "If
the world said OK to the crusade against
Saddam [Hussein], it is not only because the
world drinks Coca Cola. It is because, to a large
extent, the meaning of today's world finds its
source, its creation and its distribution in the
United States."
There is no doubt in my mind that television
has done a lot to expand a sense of global destiny
beyond the confines of North America. Trips to
the moon, royal marriages and the Olympics,
among other world coverage shows, have served
to provide a common focus for the attention
of hundreds of millions of people of different
cultures. Cheap Hollywood movies and soaps
have proposed to do the same on a day-to-day
basis. Thus it is quite true that the public mind
of the world has been more or less grounded in
the country where the greatest expertise in tele¬
vision was found. But this may be changing
very quickly. Just as quickly, in fact, as the world
itself is "changing its mind".
With the U.S. military controlling all news
delivery via the American news channel CNN,
the Gulf War was perhaps the last occasion when
a single television channel was given full range,
albeit under duress, for the one-way production
Above, an impression of a trip
inside a computer.
Left, Madeleine Reading, a
portrait by the Flemish painter
Ambrosius Benson, who died in
Bruges in 1550.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
of meaning. The era of television as the principal
supporter of the mass creation of meaning may be
over. At least three new technological factors are
undermining the hegemony of television and
especially of American television: interactivity,
digitization and networks.
Interactivity, the recovery of
psychological autonomy from TV
Television had already begun to "disintegrate"
in the mid-1970s with the invention of the
zapper. Zapping in and out of a commercial was
the first step in giving power to the people over
the screen. The second step was the widespread
distribution of videorecording equipment. By
recording one programme while watching
another, or recording a programme while doing
something else, the private user was becoming
an informal "editor", taking revenge over the
content/time constraints of television broad¬
casting. The third step was the appearance and
fast distribution of personal computers.
Interactivity only became a concept after
people had begun to use a keyboard and a
mouse. They began to feel that they were taking
power over the screen. Another step, a sidestep
really, is the development and continuous refine¬
ment of videocameras. While in the 1960s and
1970s everybody was a consumer of television,
in the 1 990s we can expect to see more and more
producers taking advantage of lightweight and
efficient electronic pencils. After decades of
passive acceptance of their dictatorship, we have
learned to talk back to our screens.
universal digital culture
By 1991, personal computers had already stolen
the attention of a full generation from the seduc¬
tion of the television screen. Computers affect
culture in depth because they combine the char¬
acteristics of a mass-medium with those of a
private one. They allow universal access to indi¬
vidual input and vice-versa. The new universal¬
izing principle is that of the binary code. Thanks
to digitization, the binary code can translate
anything into anything else forms, textures,
sounds, feelings, even smell and why not taste
soon. This is the nature of multimedia.
The binary code is the new common sense,
the new common language which allows us to
DERRICK DE KERCKHOVE,
of Canada, has since 1983
directed the McLuhan Program
in Culture and Technology
(sponsored by Origin Technology
in Business), which is part of
the Faculty of Information
Studies at the University of
Toronto. Between 1968 and
1979 he worked with Marshall
McLuhan as a translator,
researcher and co-author. Among
his publications are The
Alphabet and the Brain: The
Lateralization of Writing
(collected essays edited in
collaboration with Charles
Lumsden, Springer-Verlag,
Heidelberg, 1988) and
Brainframes, Technology, the
Mind and Business (Bosch and
Keuning BSO, Utrecht, 1991).
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
'Computers combine the characteristics
of a mass-medium with those of a private one.'
recreate technically outside our minds the com¬
plex arrangements that we have learned to build
in our private imagination when we read novels.
It is much more powerful, spreads far wider,
and provides far more complex access to infor¬
mation-processing than television.
On the other hand, in spite of its universal
calling, the binary code does not present a par¬
ticular threat to local cultures and identities.
On the contrary, it may allow them to flourish
eventually because it is capable of supporting
competing representations in non-exclusive
fashion. The kind of collective mind produced
by computers is different from the public mind
of television. It is not only an object ofattention,
but also the subject of processing. It is an activity,
not a spectacle. Thus it includes the user in the
process. This is the reason why computers
depend on networks to fully realize their socio-
cultural potential.
N etworks and other highways
Delow, a tele-conference
in the United States.
Participants can talk to each
other from a distance, maintain
visual contact and exchange
documents.
By 1991, computers were already celebrating
what has become known as "convergence" with
the telephone (the most powerful of the unsung
technologies of communication) and television.
The networks of national telephone companies
today are vying for markets once reserved to a
few broadcasters and cable operators. Audiovi¬
sual information is becoming ubiquitous as mul¬
timedia. On the electronic data highway, tele¬
vision will eventually lose its status as a
broadcasting mass-medium and acquire that of
the telephone, the narrowcasting medium with
a billion interactive channels.
22
W^ ^ßß^^^^^E
^^fc^^. . -
.. ....M. JÊ r^i 1 1
wM
; ^B^^/"^ ^5
W, \*£
Am
The Internet, which is the earliest and as yet
the most complete expression of the electronic
data highway, comes as close as has ever been
possible to enabling a very large number of
people to process information simultaneously.
It is a technological expression of collective
consciousness. To be more precise, the Internet
is becoming a kind of global subconsciousness,
with myriads of points of immergence for indi¬
viduals into the collective, and points of emer¬
gence of the collective into the individual. Thus
digitization turns everything into information,
interactivity allows anyone to get into the pro¬
cessing, and networks connect every user to
every other.
Wr'here do we all fit in?
The idea of the "global village" was adequate for
the television era which made everybody a
neighbour to everybody else. It is quite inade¬
quate to describe the new conditions of net¬
worked communications. Indeed, if television
clearly supported the notion and even the per¬
ception of a common space, instant data net¬
works abolish both time and space. They thus
suppress the traditional bearings of identity,
both personal and collective. In fact, many
people seem to cultivate a new kind of
anonymity on the Net. It is also apparent that,
far from discouraging local initiative, the Net is
promoting all kinds of new associations based
not on political but on psychological boundaries.
Different cultures can surely coexist on the Net.
So we may be soon moving out of the global vil¬
lage, out of the public mind, into the "global
mind". The rules that operate that mind are still
unknown, but one absolutely essential crite¬
rion for guiding nations in their regulatory
process is that universal access and guaranteed
privacy be ensured.
While regulators are trying to resolve that
paradox, we are all fairly confused. The cre¬
ation of meaning is not homogeneous any more,
ideologies have been thoroughly trashed along
with the Berlin Wall, and television is henceforth
too decentralized to pretend to the status of a
public mind. Political and social strife find us
irresolute. We are now too conscious of local
sensibilities rather than insensitive to them. We
fear to tread where we once ran. The world's
record in Bosnia, Somalia and Rwanda is dismal
and yet, around the evidence of disaster, there are
signs of hope. Global thinking, evidenced by a
rising sense of ecological responsibility and
attendant environmental accounting, is finding
expression in local action. Multiculturalism and
political correctness are beginning to address
North-South concerns. All these are indicators
that in spite of hesitations about interfering in
local affairs, the general level of attention and
psychoplanetary pressure is rising.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The shoals of freedom by Marcin Frybes
In central Europe 1989 marked the end of the state-controlled
media. But after the first flush of excitement, the press is now
having to come to terms with market realities while avoiding
compromises and maintaining standards.
Above, Cracow, February
1990. Rock fans at a concert
inaugurating Radio Malopolska
Fun, the first free foreign radio
station in Poland.
Contrary to what some observers have
suggested, the process of transition from
communism in Eastern Europe involves more
than the introduction of free market mecha¬
nisms and democratic elections. The transition
to a modern society is first and foremost a cul¬
tural process which presupposes the recon¬
struction of areas of social communication. The
way in which the media landscape in these coun¬
tries is gradually taking shape has a vital bearing
on their future.
For five years, these countries have been
experiencing unprecedented economic, social
and political upheaval. The information sector
has witnessed spectacular changes, especially
in Hungary, Poland, the Czech Republic and
Slovakia, where radical reforms were adopted
from the outset. Only a few years ago, the media
in these countries were directed, controlled and
manipulated by the authorities, which enjoyed
a total monopoly, further consolidated by cen¬
sorship. They were able to fabricate a reality
which accorded with their interests of the
moment and to prohibit, discredit or sideline any
presentation of the situation that differed from
their own. Far from reflecting currents of
opinion and the wide diversity of social needs,
the media landscape did no more than repro¬
duce, at best, internal dissensions within the
party apparatus.
Today this scene is changing fast, but uncer¬
tainty still surrounds the audiovisual media.
Governments are reluctant to carry out the her¬
alded privatizations because they are afraid of
depriving themselves of a powerful lever to
influence public opinion. In Hungary, as in 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Poland and Slovakia, the fight for control of
television has been mobilizing the entire polit¬
ical class for several months now. And the suc¬
cesses of a few new private radio stations barely
scratches the surface of the hold on national
audiences enjoyed by public radio stations.
On the other hand, privatization of the
written press (which has traditionally been
important in these countries) is now almost
complete. The governments which controlled
most of the titles until 1989 found themselves so
lacking in support after only a few months that
some have since been trying (without notable
success) to create new organs that are more
favourably disposed towards them.
N ew markets
24
The emergence of the new press markets has
been marked by three main phases. At first, a
flood of pent-up words was released in an
atmosphere of fascination with freedom
regained. The fall of the communist regimes
and the end of censorship and cumbersome
bureaucracy sparked off a veritable explosion of
new publications. At this stage the creation of
new titles often reflected a quest for identity
and a need for social expression that had long
been held in check. The very fact of envisaging
the publication of a magazine (many projects
never reached fruition or were soon abandoned)
was a way of defining a new area of freedom to
be occupied by the writers concerned.
In the 1990s, the press has therefore played
a major role in the restructuring of the political
scene. By giving the different currents of opinion
a platform for expression, it eventually encour¬
aged the formation of new political parties
even though, with the passage of time, relations
between the press and the rising political elites
have become increasingly conflictual.
This first phase of euphoria with "speech
regained" only lasted for a few months. New
An editorial meeting at the
Polish daily Cazeta Wyborcza.
The Bucharest Press Centre,
below, was once the palace of
Romanian President Nicolae
Ceausescu.
'The leading newspapers are more
popular than the political parties and
must endeavour not only to gain the
loyalty of their readers but also to
measure the potential political
consequences of their editorial policy.'
problems made their appearance, associated with
the discovery of the realities of the market
economy. With the end of public subsidies, rising
paper and production costs, and the appearance
of competition, sometimes cutthroat, many pub¬
lications folded, while others abandoned their
original aims and were obliged to adapt rapidly
to the new demands of the public.
However, the laws of the market were
imposed with a vengeance with the arrival of the
major international press groups. This hap¬
pened relatively quickly in Hungary and some¬
what later in Poland and the Czech Republic,
while the process is still in its infancy in Slovakia.
Today, foreign investors control more than half
the press market in Central Europe: Hersant,
Springer, Bertelesmann and Marquard have
bought up the best titles of the former commu¬
nist press, in particular the major national dailies
and many regional newspapers. At the same
time, minor "national empires" have been estab¬
lished, usually at the instigation of former emi¬
gres who had made their fortune abroad and
decided to invest in their country of origin.
The unbridled diversification of the early
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
days has now given way to a phase of restruc¬
turing which is leading to new forms of domi¬
nance of the press market. Faced with foreign
competition, some titles famed for their clan¬
destine origins and their pride in their indepen¬
dence, nevertheless had to appeal to foreign
capital in 1993 in order to finance moderniza¬
tion. Two leading dailies are typical examples:
Gazeta Wyboreza in Poland and Lidove Noviny
in the Czech Republic.
Exorbitant power
Finally, the third phase in the formation of press
markets in central Europe corresponds to the
discovery by the political and economic élites of
the simple fact that the press wields enormous
power over public opinion. The leading news¬
papers are more popular than the political par¬
ties and must endeavour not only to gain the loy¬
alty of their readers but also to measure the
potential political consequences of their edito¬
rial policy. In a world which has lost its bearings
and from which the traditional authorities have
disappeared, the press often seems to wield dis¬
proportionately great power. Some observers
maintain that the victory of the former com¬
munist parties at the last elections in Poland
and Hungary is not attributable solely to the
frustrations engendered by the social cost of
economic reforms but also to the highly critical
attitude of the press to the first democratic gov¬
ernments in the transition period.
Although this is not a specific feature of cen¬
tral Europe, the media are increasingly tending
to act as "mediators" between divergent inter¬
ests, needs, programmes and points of view.
Sometimes the media tend to take the place of
the nascent political system. Hence the prolif¬
eration of conflicts between the media, which are
jealous guardians of their new-found indepen¬
dence, and an emerging world of politics. Hence
too the growing interest taken in the media by
the new centres of economic power private
enterprise and the banks which are endeav¬
ouring to win control or at least the sym¬
pathy of some major press organs.
A cultural revolution
In the last five years, the people of Central
Europe have not only discovered freedom of
speech but also products to which the public in
the West had long been accustomed but which
for them represented a veritable cultural revo¬
lution. In the print media alone, they were sud¬
denly offered a vast range of newspapers, colour
magazines for every taste and readership, aggres¬
sive new scandal sheets packed with human
interest stories, to say nothing of porn maga¬
zines all this with a print quality that was
unknown in the (dull and monotonous) com¬
munist press and with a profusion of adver¬
tising that did not exist before 1989.
Readers who used to go to great lengths to
get hold of their favourite newspapers some
were practically impossible to find are today
assailed by a host of new publications (in Poland
alone, half the titles have only been in existence
since 1989). They have lost their bearings and
often find it hard to make a choice. Under the
pressure of new economic constraints and
lacking competent journalists, the press for its
part easily lapses into sensationalism.
Although the press in Central Europe is for
the most part free and independent, it is still
searching for a role and the right language to
address societies that have become destructured
and are in a process of rapid change. Through its
very existence and plurality, it is making an
important contribution to the liberation of social
life from state control and to restoring the
autonomy of civil society. But does it not by the
same token run the risk of further amplifying
these phenomena of social disintegration and the
accompanying disarray?
Satellite dishes in Tirana,
Albania.
MARCIN FRYBES
is a Polish mathematician,
sociologist and journalist who is
engaged in research at the
Centre for Sociological Action
Analysis (CADIS) at the Ecole
des Hautes Etudes en Sciences
Sociales in Paris. A specialist in
the political and social problems
of Central Europe, he is
particularly interested in
changes in the media
landscape.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Monopolies, minarets and videos
by Sadok Hammami
Because of strict state monopolies and inadequate
programme output, the Arab public is looking elsewhere for
what it cannot find at home.
In the Arab world, where demands based
I on identity and religion are forcefully
pressed and where the present is continually
haunted by the past, the question of communi¬
cation is fraught with drama. All societies are
nowadays concerned by the link between cul-
Bturalidentity and the globalization of commu-
slow television
' . 	 nication, but it is a distinctive feature of the
on the move in Cairo s Imbaba
district, 1994.
26
Arab world that memories of the past intrude
into the very heart of modern life. This revival
of the past is particularly noticeable in the field
of communications.
The place of the media is closely linked to the
status of the "sanctuary" in the community. In
and around the mosque there grows up a culture
of resistance not only to modernization but also
to the authorities, thus reviving an old form of
territoriality in which the new media are always
faced with competition. There is an extraordi¬
nary competition nowadays between the sound
of the muezzin echoing from minarets and the
visual fascination of satellite dishes symbol¬
izing the contradiction of a world technologi¬
cally united but culturally fragmented.
But this paradox shows itself mainly in state
media monopolies and in the many forms of
resistance to which they lead. The communica¬
tion issue is a focus for all the cultural blockages
that have characterized the development of these
societies: state hegemony, the breakdown of
political bonds, a return to tradition	 Orig¬
inally required to be tools for development, the
media (notably television) have helped to inten¬
sify the authoritarian nature of the established
order. By consistently devoting itself to the glo¬
rification of charismatic leaders, television has in
general fostered the personality cult in politics.
In the Arab world radio and television, with
a few exceptions, are limbs of the state monopoly.
Access to them is strictly controlled. Economic
factors such as rising production costs, political
factors such as the restraining effect of censorship,
and social factors such as increased demand
resulting from the growth of the middle class, all
help to aggravate a creative crisis. Egypt, the only
Arab country with its own programme industry,
is the only exception. This situation drives people
to seek elsewhere what they cannot find at home,
and makes for increased cultural dependence on
the outside world.
I he saucepan strategy
Three different strategies tend to be adopted.
One is to plug surreptitiously into other net¬
works a common practice in North Africa,
because of the proximity of Europe. In Tunisia,
for example, some picturesque reception tech¬
niques were devised during the 1980s. By
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
"In Algeria six or eight million
people receive the European
channels by means of
improvised cable networks."
Left, a satellite dish in Algiers.
attaching a metallic item (usually a saucepan) to
their television aerials, people can usually
manage to pick up the Italian channels. In
Algeria six or eight million people receive the
European channels by means of improvised
cable networks. But the prime instrument for
cheating state monopolies is the video
recorder for Arab audiences still the best way
of getting programmes which are all the more
desirable for being forbidden.
Faced with this anarchy, and with calls for the
liberalization of cultural life, several states have
decided to relax their monopoly control of the
media, either by opening their radio networks to
public or private outside operators or by legal¬
izing the direct reception of foreign broadcasts
by dish aerials. This makes it possible to retain
a monopoly over national television whilst at the
same time monitoring the flow of programmes.
"All societies are nowadays
concerned by the link between
cultural identity and the
globalization of
communication". Below,
television in Yemen.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Algiers, 1992.
28
SADOK HAMMANII,
of Tunisia, is writing a doctoral
thesis on mediation and the
image in Arab-Islamic culture.
The third strategy is to reinstate places tra¬
ditionally devoted to communication this is
reflected in the emergence of mosques as centres
of political debate. By keeping television under
their thumbs, states have fostered the take-over
of mosques and their use in propagating the
ideologies of confrontation. The "informal"
appropriation of mosques brings out the ten¬
sions inherent in the emergence of public debate.
Treeing creative forces
Closed societies are today inconceivable. The
opening of national forums to outside media
does not necessarily result in cultural depen¬
dence, except when it is used to perpetuate
domestic ideas about social inequality. Calls for
"the defence of cultural identity against the
Western media" are primarily ideological argu¬
ments put forward by authoritarian states and
politicians to feed nostalgia for a non-existent
primeval purity.
To be free of real cultural dependence the first
essential is to liberate people's creative poten¬
tialities. The media system in the Arab world
needs to be built first and foremost around the
values of free discussion and free exchange of
views. Shibboleths about identity, the diabo-
lizing of technology, and paranoiac ideas about
other people will not help it to regain its cultural
sovereignty or make its creative presence felt in
the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S STRATEGY
Interview with Henrikas Yushkiavitshus
Unesco's Communication, Information and Informatics Sector,
created in 1990, plays a leading role in the Organization's activ¬
ities. The goals of its 1994-1995 programme, entitled "Com¬
munication, Information and Informatics in the Service of
Humanity", are to encourage the free flow of ideas, promote
the development of communication, safeguard the heritage of
archives and libraries, consolidate international co-operation
in the field of information and strengthen countries' infor¬
matics capacities. Here Henrikas Yushkiavitshus, the Assis¬
tant Director-General of Unesco who heads this sector, presents
the main features of this programme.
What is Unesco's strategy in the communication
field?
Our key words are media pluralism and indepen¬
dence. Since 1992, 30 per cent of the funds allocated by
the International Programme for the Development of
Communication (IPDC), the main operational arm of
UNESCO's new communication strategy, have gone to
private press projects. In order to ensure the free flow
of information and eliminate all restrictions on it, we
have concentrated our efforts on professional training
and know-how. In the present world situation, in which
an independent press is taking shape in countries whose
experience of democracy is still in its early days, it is
essential for journalists to understand exactly what a free
press means. Furthermore, while it is true that there can
be no democracy without a free press, it is equally true
that a free press cannot exist without democratic leg¬
islation. And so we have compiled basic information on
legislation in certain democratic countries in order to
help states which have asked for such data, and we
have proposed solutions to their problems.
In addition to the problem of democracy, the devel¬
oping countries are faced with severe financial con¬
straints. One of UNESCO's fundamental objectives is to
help them produce their own programmes and news¬
papers. There is a lot of talk today about "information
superhighways", but we forget that they can often be
littered with roadblocks. In partnership with the Inter¬
national Telecommunication Union UNESCO has devel¬
oped a study on telecommunication tariffs, an impor¬
tant factor in the flow of information.
What important projects are under way?
We recently approved forty-two new projects in
developing countries, and in a sense they are all impor¬
tant. There are several priority areas Africa and the
least developed countries, the situation of women
We have, for example, a project on the "Development
of the independent press in Africa", which has been co-
funded since 1993 by Denmark, France, Italy and the
United States, and an international symposium on
"Women and the Media" was held in Toronto (Canada)
in March 1994.
The media have an important part to play in peace-
building, and this is why we are giving support to
Oslobodjenje, a daily newspaper published in Sara¬
jevo, and to the humanitarian radio station Gatashya in
Rwanda. UNESCO has also contributed to plans to
restructure the audiovisual media in Cambodia, Haiti
and Mozambique. With the International Press Insti¬
tute we helped monitor the press situation before and
during the April 1994 elections in South Africa, and we
are currently supporting a new programme for training
journalists and strengthening media structures in a
post-apartheid society. We are also involved in setting
up a Palestinian broadcasting corporation and mod¬
ernizing the Palestinian news agency.
We attach great importance to the creation and
development of regional news agencies such as the
Caribbean News Agency (CANA), which is now
working independently, and the Pan African News
Agency (PANA), which has been completely restruc¬
tured.
Many of our projects are connected with local radio
stations, which are becoming increasingly popular
because they allow members of society to express
themselves freely. Here too, UNESCO is active in many
parts of the world the Philippines, Nepal, Mauri¬
tania, Gambia	
Your sector also handles questions relating to infor¬
mation and informatics.
Yes, communication and information cannot be dis¬
sociated. We have some very interesting projects in this
field. One of them, "Memory of the World", is designed
to introduce and facilitate the use of new technology for
the preservation of rare manuscripts. In conjunction
with the Czech National Library in Prague we have
brought out a CD-ROM reproducing highly precious
manuscripts. In Latin America we are helping to make
an inventory of nineteenth-century newspapers. We are
also working to safeguard manuscripts from the great
mosque of Sana'a in Yemen, some of which date from the
first century of the Hegira (A.D. 622).
UNESCO has helped set up the International
Freedom of Expression Exchange network (IFEX),
which enables network users to receive daily infor¬
mation on their computers about violations of press
freedom and about journalists in danger.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
FROM THE COLD WAR
TO THE ERA OF NEW TECHNOLOGIES
by Alain Modoux
LSome fifty years ago, the founders
of UNESCO singled out the "free
flow of ideas by word and image" as an
essential factor in the development of
collaboration among the nations. For
this fundamental principle to become
effective, however, it would have to be
practised by all states, and unfortunately
it was incompatible with the totalitarian
system existing in the countries of the
East. This incompatibility became one of
the key issues of the Cold War, which
was indeed partly a communication war.
In the 1970s and 1980s, therefore,
UNESCO became one of the hottest
arenas of East-West confrontation. As
the German philosopher Hannah
Arendt put it, "the force possessed by
totalitarian propaganda lies in its ability
to shut the masses off from the real
world".1 Arguing that there could not be
a totally free flow of information as long
as the dissemination of this information
was so strongly imbalanced in favour
of the North (i.e. the West), the Soviet
Union skilfully took advantage of the
understandable frustration of the devel¬
oping countries to impose within
Unesco its own interpretation of the
so-called "New World Information and
Communication Order" (NWICO). Its
objective was to limit, and if possible to
prevent, the penetration of the big
Western media into the territories it con¬
trolled. This was one reason, although
not the only one, why the United States
and the United Kingdom decided to
leave UNESCO respectively in 1984 and
1985.
The end of the Cold War gave
UNESCO a unique opportunity to work
out an approach to the communication
issue that was adapted to the needs of
both the emerging democracies in
Eastern and Central Europe and the
developing countries. In November
1989, UNESCO's General Conference
adopted by consensus at its twenty-fifth
session a "new communication strategy",
the objective of which is "to ensure a
free flow of information at international
as well as national levels, and its wider
and better balanced dissemination,
After being a hostage of the East-
West confrontation in the 1970s
and 1980s, Unesco can now
encourage a wider and better
balanced flow of information without
any obstacle to freedom of
expression.
without any obstacle to the freedom of
expression	"
Communication and democracy
The first objective of this "new commu¬
nication strategy" commits UNESCO to
promote freedom of expression, which is
the corner-stone of the human rights edi¬
fice, and freedom of the press, which is an
essential component of any democratic
society. UNESCO supports the action of
the intergovernmental and nongovern¬
mental organizations specialized in the
defence of these fundamental freedoms,
while preserving and developing its own
means of action. Furthermore, in a number
of countries it is helping to pave the way
for the creation and strengthening of plu¬
ralistic and independent media.
In certain contexts of ethnic and/or
sectarian conflicts, UNESCO, in liaison
with the United Nations and various
international media organizations, is also
supporting the local media that are inde¬
pendent of the parties to the conflicts, as
long as they provide non-partisan infor¬
mation and promote coexistence between
ethnic and/or sectarian groups.
Finally, UNESCO must react against
the growing use of violence in the mass
media cinema, television, video, comic
strips, electronic games which provide
people, in particular children, with a
vision of human relations which is in
total contradiction with the spirit of the
Organization. "Violence on the screen" is
one of UNESCO's priority concerns. There
is no doubt that it would be very difficult
to set up and enforce universal standards
in this area. Moreover, such an approach
might be used as a pretext to prejudice
freedom of expression. Hence UNESCO is
eager to foster dialogue with and among
those responsible for creating, publishing
and broadcasting, with a view to encour¬
aging them to determine themselves the
limits that should not be overstepped,
bearing in mind the cultural context and
the public these works and products are
addressing.
Communication and development
The second objective of UNESCO's new
strategy is to strengthen communica¬
tion capacities in the developing coun¬
tries, where the participation of the
people at grassroots level in the com¬
munication process remains in general
very low. Such causes as the struggle
against poverty, education for all, the
preservation of the environment, the
fight against Aids, the promotion of
human rights and of a culture of peace
will come to nothing if they are not
taken up by those directly concerned
people living in the rural areas and on the
edges of big cities. These people should
be given the means and the skills to voice
their opinions and aspirations. Devel¬
opment, participation and communica¬
tion form part of a continuum.
In February 1992, the International
Programme for the Development of
Communication (IPDC) decided to
modify its rules in order to accept projects
emanating from the private sector. In so
doing, it was following up a recommen¬
dation made a few months earlier by a
seminar held in Windhoek (Namibia),
which was attended by some sixty pub¬
lishers and journalists representing the
independent African media. Unfortu¬
nately this change did not bring about a
substantial increase in the financial con¬
tributions by the countries of the North
to the IPDC budgets. While more than 10
per cent of the national product in the
countries of the North is related in one
way or another to the communication
and information industry, it is hard to wl
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
accept that less than 1 per cent of the
programmes of national development
agencies is devoted to the development
of communication.
32
New issues
A third objective is related to the
emerging multimedia era, which is raising
fantastic expectations as to the sharing
of knowledge and the fostering of intel¬
lectual co-operation. Here the principle of
the free flow of ideas by word and image
has a boundless field of application.
UNESCO provides the international com¬
munity with a forum of reflexion where
the effects and possibilities of the new
applications of communication and infor¬
mation technology can be examined.
The prospects offered by these new
technologies, especially in the fields of
distance education and continuing edu¬
cation, are promising. But there is a great
risk that only a minority of humanity,
among and within nations, will take full
advantage of them. UNESCO should there¬
fore focus its efforts on countries which are
facing difficulties in this sphere. Situated in
both North and South, these countries
are in danger of becoming mere consumers
of the products and services provided by
the new technologies (transnational tele¬
vision programmes, audiovisual produc¬
tions, data banks, electronic games, etc.).
The stakes in terms of cultural and edu¬
cational values are extremely high, ranging
from the preservation of cultural diversity,
especially the survival of minority lan¬
guages, to education in non-violence, in
tolerance, in human rights and interna¬
tional understanding, and the achieve¬
ment of the necessary balance between
the education and the entertainment pro¬
grammes which the multimedia industry
will soon be able to offer.
Finally, UNESCO will do its utmost to
prevent the trend for cultural unifor¬
mity based on certain dominant models
from endangering the timeless values of
small and medium-sized nations in both
North and South. This will be a difficult
task but not an impossible one, to the
extent that dialogue, open-mindedness
and tolerance are the rule of conduct
within Unesco.
1 Hannah Arendt, The Origins of Totalitarianism
(Part 3), Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc., New
York and London, 1966.
ALAIN MODOUX
is the Director of Unesco's Communication Division.
A FEW TERMS
Interactive: allowing a continuous
two-way transfer of information
between a user and the central
point of a communication system,
such as a computer.
CD-ROM (Compact disk read¬
only memory): A digital-sound
laser disk that cannot be modified
but is able to store a large amount
of data in the form of text, images,
sounds and computerized data. A
12-cm disk can contain 2,500,000
pages of text or 70 minutes of
moving pictures. CD-ROM
appears to be the ideal medium not
only for providing access to data
banks, dictionaries and ency¬
clopaedias but also to more com¬
plex forms of information (e.g. the
contents of a museum).
Binary code: a notation system
consisting of only two digits, 0 and
1, which enables letters, numbers,
sounds and images to be coded. It
is used by computers to carry out
all their operations.
Digital imaging: digital recording
of an image by breaking it down
into lines and dots ("pixels", or
"picture elements") enables it to
be modified and to produce all
kinds of special effects. The
sequence of binary values (0 or 1)
that define the initial image can be
interpolated, modified or recalcu¬
lated. The same principle enables
the computer to generate images.
Information highways: Advances
in digital technology are erasing
the boundaries between the text,
sound and images that a single
communications system can
transmit. The media, telecommu¬
nications, electronics and com¬
puters can now converge in one
big digital, multimedia and inter¬
active network incorporating and
distributing services that have hith¬
erto been separate. On a single tele¬
vision or home computer screen it
is now possible (for a fee) to
receive, store, process and dialogue
with all sorts of data, e.g. access
library books without having to
borrow them, visit a museum from
the comfort of home, or "teleshop"
in a department store. The inte¬
gration of these high-yield infor¬
mation networks has become an
economic and political battlefield.
The Commission of the European
Union in Brussels has estimated
that it would cost 67 billion Ecus to
fund an information highway pro¬
ject in Europe over the next ten
years.
SOME UNESCO PUBLICATIONS ON COMMUNICATION
Books:
O World Communication Report
Paris, UNESCO, 1989, 576 pp.
O Many Voices, One World
Communication and Society Today and
Tomorrow (Abridged edition)
Sean MacBride et al., Paris, UNESCO, 1984,
244 pp.
A Richer Vision: The Development of
Ethnic Minority Media in Western
Democracies
Charles Husband (ed.), London/Paris, John
Libbey/UNESCO, 1994, 149 pp.
O Video World-wide: An International
Study
Manuel Alvarado (ed.), London/Paris, John
Libbey/UNESCO, 1988, 328 pp.
D Organizing Educational Broadcasting
David Hawkridge and John Robinson,
London/Paris, Croom Helm/UNESCO,
1982,302 pp.
Monographs on Communication Planning
series
O Communication Planning Revisited,
(No. 5)
Alan Hancock, Paris, UNESCO, 1992, 105 pp.
Reports and Papers on Mass
Communication series:
O Alternative Media: Linking Global and
Local, (No. 107)
Peter Lewis (ed.), Paris, UNESCO, 1993,
130 pp.
O Impact of Communication Technologies
on Women, (No. 108)
Silvia Pérez-Vitoria, Paris, UNESCO, 1994,
48pp.
TV Transnationalization Europe and
Asia, (No. 109)
Prcben Sepstrup and Anura Goonasckera
(ed.), Paris, UNESCO, 1994, 89 pp.
D The Vigilant Press: A Collection of Case
Studies, (No.103)
Paris, UNESCO, 1989, 116 pp.
D Violence and Terror in the Mass Media,
(No. 102)
George Gcrbncr, Paris, UNESCO, 1989,
45 pp.
Two issues of the Unesco Courler
O The Media, Ways to Freedom
(September 1990)
O Televisions (October 1992)
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
SOME KEY DATES
868: The first known book is produced in China.
1454: Gutenberg prints the Bible in Mainz.
1631: The first French newspaper, Théophraste Renaudot's La Gazette,
appears.
1790: Claude Chappe's semaphore visual telegraph.
1826: Nicéphore Nicpce's first photographs.
1837: Samuel Morse invents the electric telegraph.
1845: A rotary press patented.
1876: Alexander Graham Bell patents his telephone.
1878: Thomas Edison makes the first device for recording sound.
1895: Louis and Auguste Lumière screen the first motion picture in Paris.
1896: Marconi sends radio signals over three kilometres.
NUMBER OF RADIO RECEIVERS
Continents
World total
Africa
America
Asia
Europe (including
former U.S.S.R.)
Total (millions) Per 1,000 inhabitants
1970 1975 1980 1985 1992 1970 1975 1980 1985 1992
771 1,034 1,307 1,671 2,046 209 254 294 344 376
19 29 49 84 116 51 69 103 152 170
350 476 566 649 734 687 851 926 978 991
78 144 254 412 589 37 61 145 184
Oceania
314 368 418 502 580 446 506 558 653 736
10 17 20 24 27 526 816 865 964 990
Source: Statistical Yearbook 1994, UNKCO, 1994.
NUMBER OF TELEVISION RECEIVERS
Continents
World total
Africa
America
Asia
Europe (including
former U.S.S.R.)
Total (millions) Per 1,000 inhabitants
Oceania
1970 1975 1980 1985 1992 1970 1975 1980 1985 1992
298 407 558 689 873 81 100 125 142 160
1.6 2.7 8.2 15 26 4.5 6.6 17 26 38
108 153 202 260 302 211 273 331 392 408
41 54 98 137 235 20 23 38 48 73
144 192 243 268 300 205 264 324 349 381
3.8 5.6 6.8 8.6 10 187 264 296 348 375
1907: Edouard Belin invents the "Belino" system of telephoto
transmission.
1927: Vladimir Zworykin invents the iconoscope, a process for
analysing ¡mages electronically, a precursor of the video camera.
1928: First demonstration of television in the Bell laboratories in the
United States.
1930: The telex developed.
1932: Foundation of the International Telecommunication Union.
1940: Appearance of the tape-recorder.
1945: The ENIAC (Electronic Numerical Integrator and Calculator)
computer is built, using valves, at the University of Pennsylvania.
1947: The transistor invented.
1959: Second-generation computers appear, using transistors (a
thousand times faster).
1964: Third-generation computers appear with miniaturized elec¬
tronic components.
1965: Launch of the first geostationary satellite (Early Bird) in the
Intelsat system.
1981: IBM markets its first personal computer.
1985: CD-ROM brought out by Philips and Sony.
SOME FIGURES
The world telecommunication market (switching,
transmission and terminals) amounted to $82.1 billion in 1992.
Four news agencies (Agence France-Presse, the British
Reuters agency and two American agencies, Associated Press
and United Press International) collect, process and transmit 80
per cent of the information dispatched for newspaper readers
around the world.
Average expenditure on communication for a European
household in the 1980s broke down as follows:
telecommunications and postal services, 29%; the press, 23%;
TV and radio, 21%; books, 12%; photos, 7%; records, 3.5%;
computers, 2.5%; culture, 2%. (source: BIPE Conseil, Paris)
Despite these figures, it must be remembered that one person
out of two will never make or receive a telephone call in his or
her life.
D. B.
Source:
Figures and dates taken from:
*" Francis Balle, Introduction aux médias (PUF, Paris, 1994),
Armand Mattclart, Mapping World Communication: War, Progress, Culture,
University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis/London, 1994.
«" Bernard Miègc, La Société conquise par la communication (PUG, Grenoble,
1989).
Source: Statistical Yearbook 1994, Unksco, 1 994.
NUMBER OF BOOK TITLES PUBLISHED NUMBER AND CIRCULATION QF DAILY NEWSPAPERS
Continents Total Per million inhabitants
1970 1980 1990 1991 1970 1980 1990 1991
World total 521,000 715,500 842,000 863,000 182 161 159 160
Africa 8,000 12,000 13,000 13,000 22 25 20 20
America 105,000 142,000 148,000 144,000 206 232 206 198
Asia 75,000 138,000 228,000 215,000 59 54 73 70
Europe 246,000 330,500 364,000 403,000 515 682 726 802
Oceania 7,000 12,500 12,000 12,000 362 548 450 442
Former U.S.S.R. 80,000 80,500 77,000 76,000 329 303 266 261
Continents
World total
Africa
America
Asia
Europe (including
former U.S.S.R.)
Oceania
Number of dailies Estimated circulation
Per 1,000 inhabitants
1975 1992 1975 1992
7,780 9,279 110 113
170 204 12 15
2,950 2,965 158 144
2,190 3,750 55 64
2,350 2,247 304 364
120 113 299 213
33
Source: Statistical Yearbook 1994, Unesco, 1994. Source: Statistical Yearbook 1994, UNESCO, 1994.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY
Reinventing the press
34
Has the time come to rein¬
vent the press? This ques¬
tion becomes particularly rele¬
vant against the background of
two other prospective questions:
what does the future hold for
relations between the press (the
"fourth estate") and the world of
power, or rather the various cen¬
tres of power? And what are the
prospects for the written word
in an age of channel-hopping, the
multimedia revolution and infor¬
mation superhighways?
Has the press caught the power disease? Has it
been contaminated by power? "If the press did not
exist, it ought not to be invented. But the fact is
that it does exist," as Balzac put it. I would contrast
that vision with the ideal of Thomas Jefferson,
who declared that "The basis of our government
being the opinion of the people, the very first object
should be to keep that right. And were it left to me
to decide whether we should have a government
without newspapers or newspapers without gov¬
ernment, I should not hesitate a moment to prefer
the latter." In 1787, he added, "I mean that every
man should receive those papers and be capable of
reading them".
The end of the Cold War and the upsurge of
democracy all over the world are opening up new
continents to freedom of expression. The press will
have no future in these regions unless it builds
highways to lasting freedom, and this will require
a certain separation of powers. It is not enough to
win freedom: freedom must also be organized and
strengthened in face of established authority. How¬
ever, the press is first and foremost the reflection of
a society and of its readers. This is why Jefferson's
message of hope still has meaning for us since it
makes the link which is at the heart of UNESCO's
mission between the principle of press and media
freedom and its essential adjunct: literacy, education
for all and the freedom of scientific and academic
inquiry without which the concept of freedom can
only be an empty shell.
There can be no democracy without freedom of
the media and the free flow of ideas by word and
image. We therefore cannot accept the slightest
restriction on freedom of expression. However,
independent media can only exist to the extent
that the preconditions for freedom also exist. And
there can be no free and influential press or true
democracy without well-informed readers. Respon¬
sible and informed citizens are the best shield of
democracy.
The new faces offreedom
UNESCO is working to promote free, independent
and pluralist media in the public and private sector
alike. Two meetings held with this in view by
UNESCO, one in Windhoek, Namibia, in 1991, the
other in Almaty, Kazakhstan, in 1992, have been
major turning points and have opened up many
new perspectives. In these "march-lands" of democ¬
racy where everything needs to be rebuilt or
invented freedom of expression, a free press, pro¬
fessional ethics UNESCO is acting as a catalyst by
promoting public and private bilateral initiatives,
by encouraging the new print and audiovisual
media groups and non-governmental organiza¬
tions to work together, and by helping with the
establishment of training centres for journalists.
The Windhoek Declaration laid the groundwork
for the reinvention, or perhaps even the creation,
of a democratic press in the countries of the South
and East which had been deprived of it for so long.
These new media, these new and often heroic
journalists, many of whom have known impris¬
onment, are reinventing the press from day to day
and drawing the new shapes of freedom, some¬
times even laying down their lives in this cause.
The advent of a society of global communica¬
tions, a "programmed society" in which computers,
information and communication all converge, is
revolutionizing our outlook on culture, education
and development indeed on life itself.
The civilization of the written word may well be
replaced by a new empire of invisible and intangible
signs, forming the basis of a new commercial,
worldwide economy governed by what the Amer¬
ican political economist Robert Reich has called
"manipulators of symbols". And yet, the coming
change will also be a transition that is rich in
promise and will lead us to a civilization of knowl¬
edge and information. Some are alarmed by this
trend, just as in the past some people were wary of
the advent of the steam engine and the invention
of the telephone and the computer. Will we come to
regret the alienation of man enslaved to the
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
BY FEDERICO MAYO
assembly line, as immortalized by Charlie Chaplin
in Modern Times} We must now learn to navigate
on the seas of information and knowledge. Post¬
modern society is awash with culture, but it has at
one and the same time too much and too little cul¬
ture. A danger lies in store for us here. What if
technology is what the French writer Jean Bau-
drillard has called "a new artificial paradise of intel¬
ligence"? Will the human mind grow addicted to
virtual reality, to simulation?
The multimedia galaxy
Hence the urgent need to reinvent the press and
reinvigorate its critical function, its missions and its
instruments. This calls for a fresh look at the new
revolution in the media that transmit knowledge.
Consider the great technical and social transfor¬
mations of the past: they were closely linked to the
radical changes affecting the acquisition, preser¬
vation and, above all, the flow of knowledge. The
invention of writing led to historic changes.
Printing gave birth to countless extraordinary
developments and led to the industrial revolution.
To what new shores is the cognitive revolution
brought about by digital telematics leading us
today? How will it reshape the press? What cultural
changes will it bring in the long run?
The upheavals taking place today are signposts
to the press of the future. The merger of the cul¬
tural industries into a single multimedia galaxy
brings with it the risk of the hegemony of "edu¬
tainment", a mixture of education and commercial
entertainment. Knowledge and culture in its var¬
ious forms will indeed be available at home via a
single multi-purpose appliance. But what of those
who will not be able to afford the luxury of an
electronically equipped home? In the medium term,
the gap between the insiders and the outsiders will
widen. Moreover, the impact of such a revolution
is as yet ambiguous. Will it bring cultures closer
together or on the contrary hasten the erosion of
unique skills and forms of knowledge in a dazzling
world of simulation based on products of low cul¬
tural quality but high added value?
In his 1994 report to the Prime Minister of
France on information highways, Mr. Gérard
Théry notes that "the press, which is one of the
oldest and most important producers of informa¬
tion, will make growing use of the new networks"
once it has entirely digitalized its production pro¬
cedures, and that process will soon be completed in
the most advanced countries. While increasing
competition, which incidentally provides economic
stimulus and is in keeping with democracy, the
new electronic networks also provide a great
opportunity for the press: they offer new means of
dissemination to professionals with proven skills
and expertise in this area.
Creative tension
With the information superhighways, these ser¬
vices will be developed and enriched through a
considerable increase in the flow in communica¬
tions, through interactivity and the possibility of
combining text and images. The print media will
thus further diversify their content, and at the
same time develop new documentation and briefing
services. New audiences and new readers are thus
within reach of the press if it manages to act in time
and transform itself successfully.
There are other key issues, such as free access of
information to markets and networks; protection
of copyright, which will be the theme of a UNESCO
symposium in 1996; guarantees of independence
which many publishers of electronic services would
like to enjoy in relation to network operators this
raises the question of the control that is liable to be
exercised in practice over access to networks and
markets; the usefulness of clarifying the status of
networks in order to promote the dynamic growth
of new markets; and the types of support which
must be provided for the digitalization of press
archives, whose cultural implications and cost will
be enormous. I also believe that some barriers
against the excesses of competition, and the asso¬
ciation of the press with the process of reflexion and
experimentation on information highways, to take
up two of Mr. Théry's suggestions, might con¬
tribute to a positive start.
It is in situations of "human tension" that it is
possible to create, imagine, reinvent, give and con¬
tribute a part of oneself to the future. Changes
take place at positions which are far from the point
of equilibrium. Nothing can be expected of the
complacent who lack the resolve and the dynamism
to bring about change. They are too concerned
with their own future to think of the common
future. It is only through creative tension that
one can discover treasures, get to the essence of
things, and change direction.
More often than not, reinventing means
knowing how to get back to the source and
uncover the original seed; daring, with the sower's
determined and clear-minded gesture, to sow the
seed afresh in the field of our common future, to
which sharing alone can give meaning. JK
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
The great temple of Thanjavur
byAppasamy Murugaiyan
A magnificentsanctuary rich in murals, sculptures
andfriezes bears witness to daily life in southern India a
thousandyearsago.
36
The reign of Rajaraja I (985-1014),
the greatest king of the Chola
Tamil dynasty, marked a glorious
epoch in the history of southern India.
This exceptional figure, a fervent wor¬
shipper ofShiva, a great administrator and
a valiant warrior, is immortalized in many
inscriptions on the great temple ofThan¬
javur the most impressive of the fifty or
so sanctuaries which he built or restored.
The temple seeks to reconcile the spir¬
itual and profane worlds. It is a religious
edifice but at the same time a monument
to the history, literature, art and architec¬
ture of the Chola empire.
The venerable rules of sacred
architecture
The rules governing the architecture of the
temples ofsouthern India were particularly
rigorous. From the sixth century onwards,
stone was the only material used to build
temples. Wood and earth, being less durable,
were reserved for human dwellings. The
shape of a sanctuary, its layout and archi¬
tectural style, depended on the nature of
the objects which were to be venerated in it
and on the cult to which it was dedicated.
Priests and stapati (craftsmen-cum-tech-
nicians) together determined the con¬
struction principles which were codified in
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The temple's crowning glory,
left, is the vimana, a 66-metre-
high pyramid.
Above, in a recess of the
vimana, a divinity guards the
entrance to the holy of holies.
Below, an entrance gate seen
from inside the temple.
learned treatises, theAgama, the Vastu and
the Silpa. Once the site had been chosen, the
orientation ofthe temple was uppermost in
the minds of its builders. Thanjavur, which
was built in the year 1000 or thereabouts,
faces eastwards.
Three portals separate the visitor from
the inner courtyard. The first, of more
recent construction (fifteenth-seventeenth
centuries) differs from the next two which
give an immediate foretaste of Chola art
and architecture.
Inside the inner courtyard, the visitor is
welcomed by a statue (nearly 6 metres
long) of a recumbent bull. This is a fine
effigy of Nandi, the mount of the God
Shiva. Then, after crossing the three pavil¬
ions ofthe main sanctuary, the mandapas,
one reaches the holy of holies, which 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
houses the lingo, the phallic image ofShiva.
Above it towers an immense 66-metre-high,
13-storypyramid, the vimana. This hollow
edifice creates a void which unites the linga
with the cosmos. The delicacy of its deco¬
ration, its profusion ofniches and pilasters,
its friezes depicting the Hindu pantheon
surmounted by eight bulls make this a mas¬
terpiece ofChola art.
At the base, two rows of parallel walls
frame the holy ofholies and form a kind of
two-story vestibule. The lower floor is
famed for the beauty of its wall paintings,
while the upper floor houses magnificent
relief portraits of some eighty dance pos¬
tures described in the Natya Sastra, a trea¬
tise written in the first century A.D. on
which the principles of classical Indian
dance are based.
The main sanctuary is surrounded by a
constellation of small protective sanctu¬
aries. One of them is specially dedicated to
Karuvurar, the spiritual mentor of King
Rajaraja. On the day when the temple was
ready and the time came to install the
linga, the priests noticed that, despite all
their efforts, the special paste which was
supposed to fix the monolith to its pedestal
_ _ remained liquid instead ofsolidifying. The
wO god could not be placed in position. In
despair, the king had a sudden revelation:
the mystic Karuvurar must be present for
the proper accomplishment of the cere¬
monies. Conducted to the temple, Karu¬
vurar spat out what he was chewing a
mixture of betel leaves, areca nuts and
quicklime and used it to fix the linga] So
it was that saliva, a symbol of impurity in
Hinduism, was used here as a sacred
cement.
Inscriptions that tell the story
of everyday life
Thanks to the inscriptions engraved on
its interior walls, the temple ofThanjavur
is also rich in information on secular life:
society, history, military history, the
economy, administration, art and crafts.
Rajaraja seems to have been the first Tamil
king to have recorded the salient dates of
his reign in addition to the events associ¬
ated with the life of the temple. His suc¬
cessors were to do likewise.
On the walls of the main sanctuary is a
list ofgifts from the king and from his elder
sister; those from his wives, entourage and
officers are catalogued on the niches and
columns of the temple.
The king's gifts reveal untold prodigality:
utensils for ritual ceremonies and other ser
vices; goldenjewels setwith pearls and gem-
stones to ornament the statues; villages,
lands and money to supply the temple with
rice; camphor, cardamom and perfumes to
add fragrance to the waterused for the ablu¬
tions of the deities; cattle to supply the
temple with ghee (clarified butter used as a
fuel for the lamps) ; musicians and singers for
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Facing page, the inner courtyard of the
temple. At left is a 6-metre-long effigy of
Nandi, the sacred bull ridden by the god
Shiva. In background, the third entrance
gate. At right, a smaller statue of Shiva's
mount.
Facing page below, entrance gates to the
temple.
Below right, the gallery lining the northern
perimeter wall.
¡3	H	"	 	"	fvrr-M	n
A: the holy of holies. B. C and D: the three manàapa (pavilions) of the main
sanctuafy. E: the gopura (e "
added in the 12th century.
ntrance towers). F: the Subfahmanya shrine.
the liturgical chants; dancing girls; Brahmin
servants, accountants, treasurers, gold¬
smiths, carpenters, launderers, barbers,
astrologers, guardians. . . . The inscriptions
even detail the earnings and tasks of each
corporation.
Administration of the temple was
under the direct control of the king and his
army. Assemblies of different villages
administered the temple's assets and
public properties. Some received loans
from the temple, the interest being used to
finance rituals. The entire population was
therefore associated in one way or another
with the maintenance of the temple and
with its rituals and ceremonies.
The inscriptions also tell us about the
economic life of the period. We learn that
there was a system ofcurrency and that the
main resources of the state were derived
from income tax and land tax. We even
know that the rate of interest on all loans
was 12.5 per cent! No tax was levied on
communal properties such as the village
pool and the areas inhabited by craftsmen,
or on roads and wells. Urban space was
carefully distributed between the different
social and professional categories there
was a "street of the archers", as well as a
"street of the musicians" and a "district of
craftsmen and shopkeepers".
In short, King Rajaraja turned the
temple ofThanjavur into the focal point of
the urban and rural life ofhis age.
APPASAMY MURUGAIYAN
is an Indian linguist who teaches at the University of
Paris-VIII and at the Ecole Pratique des Hautes
Etudes. He is the author of many publications on
Tamil language and culture, notably Vanakkam =
bonjour, Initiation à la langue tamoule (BPI, Centre
Georges-Pompidou, 1986), the first oral-aural
method of learning Tamil from French. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
anniversary F U Z U L I
poet ofdivine love
FuzuLi, whose real name was
Muhammad ibn Süleyman, is thought
to have been born in 1495 in a small town
in the region of Baghdad, Karbala or per¬
haps Najaf, where he served in his youth as
keeper of the tomb of Caliph Ali. Later, he
moved to Baghdad which he only left in
his old age to make a pilgrimage to Kar¬
bala where he died, probably from the
plague. He never saw Tabriz, Anatolia or
India, which were so dear to his heart, just
as he was never to become poet to the Court
of Istanbul.
Although he won a high reputation
among his contemporaries, earning for
himself the tide "prince ofpoets", he spent
his life torn between impossible dreams of
travel and glory and a relatively mundane
daily routine. He wrote many odes in
honour of potential patrons, singing the
merits of Shah Ismail, founder of the Per¬
sian Safavid dynasty, who conquered
Baghdad in 1508, and then hymned the
brilliant exploits of the Ottoman Sultan
Süleyman the Magnificent, who became
lord ofBaghdad in 1534. But all these eulo¬
gies brought him little profit. Worldly
goods and honours were always to elude
this poet "whom God had destined for
misfortune". Only love was left for him.
_ "I have spoken of love and so it would
W be unfitting to complain," he wrote, sum-
The Ufe of Fuzuli (c. 1495-1556),
whom Arabs, Persians and
Turks alike acknowledge as one
of their greatest mystical poets,
is an enigma. Apart from a few
details contained in a
1 7th-century Turkish
biography (from which the
portrait, left, is taken) which
describes him as a jovial and
pleasant man, all we know
about him is what we can
deduce from his work.
marizing the essential features of his life
and work: an incessant quest for true love
whose paths are known only to poetry.
But what is the true nature ofsuch love
that is apparently capable of compen¬
sating for so much solitude and sorrow? In
the true mystic tradition, Fuzuli sees the
human being as a projection or "witness"
ofGod. His love for his fellow (whose name
and sex are never revealed) is so sublime
that it transcends physical love, whose
fleeting nature is constantly denounced
by the poet. Metaphorical love is seen as a
bridge towards true love, the love of God.
Fuzuli demonstrates this in one ofhis
major works, a verse novel inspired by the
old Arab legend ofLeyla and Mejnun. Fol¬
lowing a galaxy of Persian and Turkish
authors, he turned to the subject of this
lyrical epic and used it as an opportunity
to deploy his own ethic and philosophy
of sublime love.
The history of the two lovers lent itself
well to that purpose. Ever since his ear¬
liest childhood, Qaïs Ibn Mulawwah, nick¬
named Mejnun because he was possessed
by djinns, had loved Leyla, a daughter of
his tribe to whom he dedicated ardent
poems. But Leyla's parents refused to give
her to him as his wife. The poet lost his
mind and his beloved was married to
another man. The reasons for the parental
refusal and descriptions of the fate ofLeyla
differ from one author to another.1 But
everyone agrees that Mejnun, who was
smitten by this impossible love, went out
into the desert to die, with wild beasts as
his sole companions.
Fuzuli dramatizes the plot to an
extreme degree. He suggests that Leyla's
father saw the feverish verses of the young
suitor as an attack on his daughter's
honour. Mejnun is therefore condemned
to madness and death precisely for having
sung his love. Married to another man,
Leyla went on to die of sorrow.
In Fuzuli 's work, the love of these two
young people which would be termed
platonic in the West and "udhrit" in the
East (a reference to the Yemeni tribe of
the Banu Udhra whose poets are dedi¬
cated to this fatal form of love) embodies
the ideal of passion pushed beyond
human limits and rejecting all form of
physical fulfillment. Fuzuli also uses it to
illustrate the sacrifice which such a passion
calls for: instead of trying to forget his dis¬
tress, Mejnun implores God to make his
love grow stronger so that his suffering
may exceed the bounds ofanything that a
human being can bear. At the same time
Leyla deliberately succumbs to a fatal
sorrow and "melts like a candle held too
close to the fire".
Love, which haunted Fuzuli all his life,
did not prevent him from writing about
many other issues, ranging from theology
to medicine, ethics and astronomy. Set
out in a number of diwans (or collections),
some 700 ghazals (short lyrical poems)
and a hundred or so qasida (elegiac
poems) written in Azeri Turkish and in
Persian, and the dozen surviving qasida'm
Arabic all bear witness to a great wealth of
inspiration. A passionate lyricism, an acute
sense of humour, a profusion of images
and a dionysiac impulse provided a sen¬
sual counterpoint to his learned
researches. They also inspired him with a
power of evocation and an emotional
charge which have remained intact for
500 years.
	^S.
1 See "Why Ulysses?" by Mahmoud Hussein
in the Unesco Courier, April 1993, pp. 34-36.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
CLEAN DRIVING:
A GREEN DREAM?
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
It is all too easy for a motorist
enjoying a smooth drive along a
good road to forget that the road
and the vehicles that use it are far
from harmless to the environment.
In November 1989 the Council of
Ministers of the European Confer¬
ence of Ministers of Transport
(ECMT) adopted a Resolution
incorporating a wide range of rec¬
ommendations designed to curb
the impact of transport on the envi¬
ronment. The recommendations
are exacting and constitute a major
challenge for the nineties. -
Transportation unquestionably
contributes to the greenhouse effect
by producing carbon dioxide
(CO2)675 million tons in 1990 in
the member countries of the Orga¬
nization for Economic Co-opera¬
tion and Development (OECD)
methane (CH4), ozone precursors
such as hydrocarbons (HCs) and
nitrous oxide (N2O), as well as chlo-
rofluorocarbons (CFCs), tropos-
pheric ozone (03, from 0 to 15 km
above the earth) and water vapour.
These gases are emitted from fossil
fuel combustion within the manu¬
facture, operation and disposal of
transport systems and from the pro¬
duction and processing of fossil
fuels. Vehicles, especially private
cars, contribute 25% of the overall
CO2 emissions in most western
European countries.
Greenhouse gas emissions are
not the only forms of air pollution
caused by road transport. Diesel
engines (mainly lorries) emit oxides
of nitrogen (NOx), sulphur dioxide
(SO2) and microscopic particles
(especially of carbon) that cause
visible exhaust fumes and soil build¬
ings. Sulphur dioxide and nitric
oxide react in the atmosphere with
water to form sulphuric acid and
nitric acid, which can turn soil and
lakes acidic and eat away at building
stone. They may travel long dis¬
tances in the atmosphere. Gases
emitted by one country often cause
acid damage in another.
THE CARLESS MAJORITY
Motor vehicle production has expe¬
rienced spectacular growth since
the end of the Second World War,
rising from about 10 million vehicles
per year in 1950 to 50 million in
1990. Today there are more than 675
million vehicles worldwide
(including two-wheelers). Outside
the OECD countries, however, most
of the world's inhabitants do not
use motor transport. The countries
ofAfrica, Asia (excluding Japan) and
Latin America contain more than
four-fifths of the world's popula¬
tion, but only one-fifth of motor-
vehicle registrations. However, the
number of vehicles per head has
grown by 20% worldwide over the
past ten years.
As Laurie Michaelis of the Inter¬
national EnergyAgency (IEA) noted
in a report presented at a seminar
on Transport Policy and Global
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
FLOWER POWER
The city of Brest in northwestern France
has hit upon an attractive way of discour¬
aging unauthorized bill stickers. Its public
utilities division has covered some exposed
surfaces with metal trellises and clad them
with clematis, honeysuckle and other
climbing plants.
NO TEARS FOR CROCODILES
There are 23 species of crocodilians,
including crocodiles, alligators, caimans
and gavials, living in more than 70 coun¬
tries. By devouring a wide range of prey
considered of poor quality for human con¬
sumption and excreting into the aquatic
system nutrients for high-quality food
species, they contribute to the high pro¬
ductivity of fisheries in the tropical zones
where they live. They also create pools and
burrows that serve as refuges for many
species in low-water periods. Papua-New
Guinea, Venezuela, Zimbabwe and the
United States are countries that reconcile
the protection of crocodiles with water¬
fowl production, fisheries management
and ecotourism. In Florida and northern
Australia human-crocodile conflicts are
controlled by selective hunting of speci¬
mens recognized as dangerous. Crocodil¬
ians are not, however, particularly good
"indicator species", since they are robust,
long-lived and highly adaptable, even to
pollution.
MARINE POLLUTION: SOMETHING
TO DECLARE
In order to monitor ships that dump waste
in violation of the MARPOL international
convention on marine pollution signed in
London in 1973, the French customs have
acquired a second, twin-engine turbo-prop
POLMAR aircraft with a "ange of nearly
2,000 km. (They already own one
POLMAR plane, used for remote sensing.)
The aircraft's side-mounted radar can
detect hydrocarbon spills within a radius of
up to 35 kilometres. An infrared scanner
sweeps the area beneath the aircraft,
enabling it to "see" temperature varia¬
tions on the sea's surface that are linked to
the presence of hydrocarbons. An on¬
board computer is used for compiling data,
for mapping, and even for estimating the
extent of spills. A video camera records
the identity of the culprit and provides
proof of the violation.
Heading into Death
Valley, California
(U.S.A.).
Warming organized by ECMT in
1992, "It would be technically pos¬
sible, by reducing car size and per¬
formance, to reduce the energy con¬
sumption, and hence greenhouse
gas emissions, of petrol cars by a
factor of three. However the
resultingvehicles would not achieve
much market share under current
market conditions. Without com¬
promising marketable vehicle char¬
acteristics, vehicle energy efficiency
is unlikely to improve by much
more than 10% before 2005." In fact
the commercial success of a car,
based on power, speed, size, secu¬
rity and comfort, is usually at odds
with the goals of reducing energy
consumption.
In his report Laurie Michaelis
makes a comparative analysis of the
advantages and disadvantages of
the different kinds of fuel and the
environmental effects of their pro¬
duction and consumption. Diesel
emits 15% more CO2 than petrol.
Although the image of diesel-pow-
ered vehicles as dirty, noisy and
heavy is fading, their number is
restricted because they cost more to
buy. Liquid petroleum gases (LPG)
include propane and butane. Vehi¬
cles that run on LPG have a green¬
house gas emission rate 20% less
than that of petrol vehicles. The
major drawback ofLPG is that sup¬
plies are limited, since it constitutes
only about 5% of refinery output.
Compressed natural-gas engines
emit little CO2 but a lot ofmethane,
which makes them less enticing.
But the main unknown is how this
innovative fuel will be received by
the consumer. As far as alcohol fuels
are concerned, methanol and
ethanol are expensive to produce.
They are less energy-rich, and so
vehicles have to be fitted with larger
fuel tanks, or vehicle range is
reduced. They are also corrosive,
and if they were adopted as fuels,
some materials currently used in
engines would have to be replaced.
Hydrogen seems to be the ideal fuel,
since its combustion in air produces
water and certain nitrogen com¬
pounds. If it is obtained by elec¬
trolysis, however, with the current
average electricity generation mix in
OECD European countries, the
plants generating the necessary
electric power for this operation
produce twice as much carbon
dioxide per unit of energy as the
emission level from petrol. The
same problem arises with electric
cars. Although some car makers
believe that electric cars will
become increasingly popular, their
speed, limited to 100 km/h, their
autonomy, no more than about 100
km, and their relatively high price
are a handicap except when an anti¬
pollution law is enacted, as may
happen in Los Angeles, California
(U.S.A.). And of course, the elec¬
tricity that powers them must come
from renewable energy sources!
On the other hand the electric
car is the only one that is completely
silent. As we saw in the lune 1994
Greenwatch ("Defeating Decibels"),
noise is one of the great scourges
ofthe modern world, and automo¬
bile traffic is one of the major con¬
tributors to it. The noise heard by
people living near roads comes
from the engines, transmissions,
tyres, horns and the road surface.
Public-works contractors are trying
to improve the latter. A French com¬
pany has developed a system that
makes it possible to reduce traffic
noise by 3 to 5 decibels; this may
not sound like much, but it is actu¬
ally a breakthrough. Gravel is coated
in asphalt in such a way as to reduce
density. The result not only leads to
less noise but also enables rain to
drain away more quickly, making
the road less slippery.
OTHER KINDS OF POLLUTION
Indispensable though they are,
roads are the cause ofseveral kinds
of pollution. They contaminate
water by soil erosion, which may
generate between 1,000 and 10,000
tons of suspended matter per kilo¬
metre both during construction and
resurfacing. Chronic pollution is
caused by wear and tear on sur¬
facing, tyres, corrosion of protec¬
tion guards, road signs and rein-
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
.1-
p- M
' .- ¿4 *í&tet- _^|
..*
^ #^ »J^b
i
>
>*2¿7
^Wl ^
>
2;	 í
I
WORLD
forced concrete, not to mention
leaded fuel that spews heavy metals
into the air that are then ingested by
plants and mushrooms growing
nearby. In winter, to treat icy roads,
especially in the mountains, 20 to 30
grams of salts are spread per square
metre (sodium-, calcium- or mag¬
nesium-chloride) that are harmful
to rivers. Worst of all perhaps are
the dangerous products that are
spilled on the roads in accidents
involving tankers carrying hydro¬
carbons or other chemical products
that then filter into the earth and
pollute the groundwater.
As Jean-Pierre Orfeuil of the
French National Institute for
Research into Transport and Trans¬
port Safety (INRETS) writes, "The
shift of goods traffic away from the
railways has created an all-powerful
road-transport lobbywhich exploits
the intensified competition and its
corporate power to impose its views
on society." This shift is shown by
the statistics. From 1984 to 1989
road haulage traffic increased by
84% in the European Economic
Community, compared with only
13% for rail freight. "Because trans¬
port in developed countries helps
push up oil consumption," Jean-
Pierre Orfeuil notes, "there is per¬
sisting pressure on prices, and the
. Third World is deprived of the devel¬
opment opportunities flowing from
low-cost energy opportunities
which the developed world enjoyed
during the post-war years." More¬
over, the Third World is bogged
down in economic crisis and has a
hard time maintaining its roads and
motor vehicles, which are often in
poor shape and therefore even
worse polluters.
Although scientists sometimes
contest doomsday predictions of
global warming and its correlation
with the increased presence of
carbon dioxide, a sane precau¬
tionary principle would be to reduce
all. pollutants emitted by motor
vehicles in order to safeguard our
environment now and for genera¬
tions to come. A set of measures
currentlybeing studied provides for
an increase in fuel consumption
taxes, stricter enforcement of speed
limits, a reduction in the cost of rail
and public transport, the promo¬
tion of road-rail goods transport,
the reduction of traffic in towns and
cities and the development of cycle¬
ways. However, the users need to
be won over, and this is no mean
task. "Those without access to a car
(the young and some of the very
elderly)," writes Jean-Pierre Orfeuil,
"feel themselves outsiders in an
automobile-dependent society." We
cannot yet know whether informa¬
tion campaigns, however persua¬
sive, will convince people that
raising taxes and reducing speed
will guarantee cleaner air for
everyone.
FURTHER READING:
*~ Transport Policy and Global
Warming, The European Conference
of Ministers of Transport, ECMT-
OECD, 1993, 241 pp.
*- Freight Transport and the
Environment, ECMT-OECD, 1991,
172 pp.
* Innovations routières pour
l'environnement, French Ministry for
Equipment, Transportation and
Tourism (France), 1994.
L'Environnement Magazine,
number 1529, July-August 1994.
The Braus pass in
the South of
France.
FEANCE
BEQUETTE
is a Franco-
American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
questions.
GOLDEN PALM TO MOROCCO
A simple but effective technique has been
found for stabilizing sand dunes in southern
Morocco, where cropland has been
invaded by sand. In 1 980, as part of a joint
project carried out by the United Nations
Development Programme (UNDP) and
the Food and Agriculture Organization of
the United Nations (FAO), farmers were
advised to build enclosures of metre-high
palm-branches in adjacent 7-metre
squares. A considerable amount of land
was reclaimed in this way. When the pro¬
ject ended, local people continued using
this anti-desertification technique, which
is viable for all of North Africa and the
Near East.
THE RICEMAN COMETH
The International Rice Research Institute
(IRRI) in the Philippines has just announced
its discovery of a new rice variety, capable
of increasing harvests by 25%. Specialists at
the IRRI, one of 17 centres of the Inter¬
national Advisory Group on Agricultural
Research, studied 80 rice samples before
crossing selected plants to obtain an insect-
and disease-resistant variety that is also
tasty and a heavy cropper. If the new rice
strain lives up to expectations, it may even¬
tually provide 100 million additional tons
of rice a year. It will be put on the market
in about five years. For environmental rea¬
sons, the IRRI is currently trying to pro¬
duce a rice variety that will require 50%
less irrigation at present it takes some
1 ,900 litres of water to produce a kilo of
rice.
EVEN THE WORM . . .
The Bawalkar Earthworm Research Insti¬
tute in Pune is one of a number of Indian
organizations practising vermiculture, the
culture of earthworms, for use in agricul¬
ture. It is involved in the spread of vermi¬
culture technology for environmental pro¬
tection, sustainable agriculture and
wasteland development. Earthworms will
consume all kinds of organic waste from
factories, households and farms, and trans¬
form it into compost to maintain soil fer¬
tility. Extremely rich in protein, many earth¬
worm species also provide a source of
meal for use as livestock feed.
u
<
LU
Cd
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
NITIATIVE
U
I-
<
LU
O
THE CENTRE FOR OUR COMMON FUTURE
44
The phrase "Our Common
Future" became widely
known as the title of the
report of the World Commission
on Environment and Develop¬
ment, often referred to as the
Brundtland Report, after the
Commission's chairman, Gro
Harlem Brundtland, Prime Min¬
ister ofNorway. Widely acclaimed
on its publication in 1987, the
Report for the first time gave cur¬
rency to the term "sustainable
development" which became one
of the central issues of the 1992
Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro. In
1988, the Centre for Our Common
Future, a Geneva-based charitable
organization, was founded to
encourage efforts worldwide to
promote sustainable develop¬
ment and follow up other recom¬
mendations of the Brundtland
Report.
Helped by a network of more
than 200 Working Partner Insti¬
tutions in more than 70 countries,
the Centre collects information
on sustainable development and
distributes it to some 35,000 indi¬
viduals and organizations in over
170 countries. It publishes two
periodicals (free for subscribers
in developing countries), The
Network, an 8-page newsletter on
sustainable development initia¬
tives worldwide, and TheBulletin,
a 130-page quarterly which is
devoted to a main theme (e.g., the
Cairo Conference on Population
and Development in issue
number 24, October 1994) and
may also be obtained on diskette
in PC 3.5", PC 5.25" or Macintosh.
The Bulletinis a mine of informa¬
tion on environmental questions:
international conferences, pub¬
lications, videos and radio pro¬
grammes. Organizations and per¬
sons wishing to announce an
environment-related event or
reach a specific audience are
invited to contact The Bulletin
and be added to its mailing-list.
The Centre has also produced
a remarkable booklet which pre¬
sents a plain-language version of
Agenda 21 and the other agree¬
ments made at Rio de Janeiro.
Entitled The Earth Summit's
Agendafor Change, it is available
in English, French, Italian, Russian
and Spanish. Each topic discussed
is illustrated with figures and
tables showing, for example, the
volume ofhazardous waste world¬
wide, the percentage ofthe world's
population living in slums, and
the degree of soil degradation.
The Centre awards six-month
internships to young professionals
from countries of the South,
enabling them to visit Geneva, join
in the Centre's work, and increase
their knowledge about sustainable
development. It has also compiled
a catalogue of information pro¬
duced by the 1992 Rio non-gov¬
ernmental "People's Summit", the
Global Forum175 hours of TV
videotape, 5,000 photographs, 400
hours of audio tape, 350 meeting
documents, a 20,000-name data¬
base and hundreds of reports,,
books and declarations.
THE CENTRE FOR
OUR COMMON FUTURE
33, chemin Valavran, 1293 Bellevue,
Geneva (Switzerland).
Tel. (41-22) 774-4530;
Fax: (41-22) 774-45 36.
E-Mail: greenet:commonfuture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN M
tion '*
A NEW PUBLIC LIBRARY
MANIFESTO
Unesco, which is mandated by its
Constitution to "maintain, increase and
diffuse knowledge by assuring the
conservation and protection of the
world's inheritance of books", has always
taken a close interest in public libraries.
As long ago as 1 949 it issued a manifesto
in the form of a poster and a leaflet on
The Public Library a living force ofpopular
education, proclaiming the public library to
be a creation of modern democracy. As a
contribution to International Book Year in
1 972, the manifesto was revised to reflect
a broader concept of the purpose of
public libraries in the promotion of
information and culture. Twenty years
later, in 1992, a third version was
proposed by the International Federation
of Library Associations and Institutions
(IFLA). Encouraging national and local
governments to support public library
development, the new Manifesto reaffirms
that libraries should not be subject to any
form of ideological, political or religious
censorship or commercial pressures, and
that they should be free of charge and
open to everyone. It also invites libraries
to encourage the development of
information and computer literacy skills,
to make known their objectives, and to
establish networks to further co¬
operation at the national and international
levels. Adopted in November 1994 by the
representatives of 30 states belonging to
the Intergovernmental Council of
Unesco's General Information
Programme (GIP), the new manifesto
seeks to encourage the support of local
and national authorities, without which
the contribution of libraries to lifelong
learning and individual development may
be compromised.
Unesco mobilizes support
for Sarajevo Library
During the night of 25 August 1992
I the National and University Library
ofBosnia and Herzegovina was destroyed
by artillery fire from the hills surrounding
the city of Sarajevo. The shells ignited a
conflagration that completely destroyed
the handsome, moorish-style library
building and most of its collections from
1.5 to 2 million volumes, including 700
manuscripts and early primed books and
a unique collection of specialist publica¬
tions on Bosnia. Less than 10 per cent of
the precious collections were saved. The
greatest loss was the destruction of col¬
lections of some 600 Bosnian periodicals
published between the mid 19th century
and the present. The destruction of the
Library's central catalogues imposes a
severe handicap on the reconstitution of
the collections.
Unesco has set up an International
Assistance Programme to help in the
reconstruction of the Sarajevo Library. "At
a time when the force of arms and hatred
seems to be giving way to that of reason, it
is important that the intellectual and moral
solidarity ofhumanity for which Unesco is
working should express itselfvigorously,"
said Unesco's Director-General, Mr. Fed¬
erico Mayor, at a meeting held last April in
support of the Programme. Mr. Mayor
called on nations, international organi¬
zations, public and private institutions,
financial bodies, associations of librar¬
ians, archivists and documentalists, as
well as private individuals, to participate in
the reconstruction of the Sarajevo National
Library and the reconstitution of its col¬
lections through voluntary contributions
in the form of funds, materials or services.
"The intellectual isolation imposed on
Sarajevo is as dangerous as the shortages
of electricity, water or medicines from
which this shattered city is suffering," Mr.
Mayor continued. "What better symbol
to express solidarity and to break the iso¬
lation than a library in this case a
national and university institute? A place
of teaching and research, of culture, of
information and of intellectual exchange,
the library furthers access to knowledge
and helps to preserve cultural identity
while consecrating the local community's
participation in universal civilization."
The International Assistance Pro¬
gramme has so far enabled reading mate¬
rials and office equipment to be bought.
Despite the blockade, books have been
arriving in small, 20-kg parcels via the air¬
lift organized by the UN High Commis¬
sioner for Refugees and the UN Peace¬
keeping Forces. Librarians, archivists and
members of the university are being
helped to leave Sarajevo in order to attend
training courses and take part in interna¬
tional meetings devoted to the rebuilding
of the Library. Unesco has also sent several
missions to Sarajevo to establish a recon¬
struction programme and study the pos¬
sibility of extending humanitarian assis¬
tance to the acquisition of books and
scientific journals.
"I hope that contributions will be com¬
mensurate with the task involved," Mr.
Mayor concluded, "and that all those who
are concerned to see the universal docu¬
mentary heritage preserved and to pro¬
mote its widest possible utilization by
researchers and general public alike will
play their part in the reconstruction and
equipping of the National and University
Library of Bosnia and Herzegovina in
Sarajevo."
Donations to the Sarajevo Library
Assistance Programme will be
gratefully received. Cheques, made out
to Unesco, may be sent to:
The Director, Division of the General
Information Programme, I, rue
Miollis, F-7S732 Paris Cedex IS,
France. (Please cite ref. 416 BIH 60). 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
R H
Salvador de Madariaga
Intuition, intelligence and the makingofmodem man
The Spanish diplomat and writer
Salvador de Madariaga (1886-
1978) was a humanist and
democrat whofoughtagainst the
Franco dictatorship (he left
Spain in 1 936 and did not return
until 1976, afler Franco's death).
He was one ofthe originators of
the idea ofa united Europe. A
prolific author ofpoems, novels
and plays, he was a particularly
brilliant essayist and biographer
ofhistoricalfigures. In April 1935
he tookpart in a meeting on "Tlie
Education ofModern Man",
organized in Nice by the
International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation.
46
Text selected by Edgardo Canton
We need to strike a balance
between "intuitive brilliance"
and "intellectual
development"; we mustfoster
the intelligence that mobilizes
all thefacets ofa human being
(including the imagination)
rather than that which reflects
a compartmentalized,
technocratic approach.
If we think of an organized society
with a certain continuity, a certain
history and a certain tradition such
as a European nation we find that the
hierarchization that takes place
throughout its history arises from two
sources: firstly from practice or tradition,
based on heredity and transmitted social
privilege, and secondly from individual
worth, which is positive in those who make
their way gradually upwards and negative
in those who let themselves be carried
away by their natural instincts. By and
large I see little point in changing this
system, which has always existed and
seems to me to have all the advantages.
As to natural hierarchy, I think it is very
evidently characterized by a certain
number of faculties, or (in less vague
terms) non-physical qualities. First there
are the people of spiritual worth, who are
at the top of the human hierarchy. They are
not at the top of the social, i.e. mechanical,
hierarchy of the state, because that does
not interest them. They usually withdraw
from the public eye. They are the
dreamers, the loners, the hermits, even if
not officially.
Then there are the people I have here
called the elite, those who are at the head
of the state, who make up what (in a par¬
allel with the army which in political
terms I would not accept) I would call
the officers or generals of the state. They
are the people who stand out because of
their more highly developed intellectual
qualities.
Lastiy, there are the ordinary people, in
whom in general (I will say in a moment
what I think about this) we find above all
a great wealth of intuition. I said "in gen¬
eral". I think it is hard to generalize. For
instance, take a people like the French,
who are an intellectual people. Even when
a Frenchman is stupid, he is a stupid intel¬
lectual. This is very important; it is possible
to be an intellectual and completely
stupid. When a Frenchman is a genius he
is an intelligent intellectual, but an intel¬
lectual. Among ordinary French people
even the shopkeeper on the corner has
his centre ofgravity in the intellect. It is not
the same in Spain. Spanish people are
deeply intuitive, and this is something that
has greatly concerned me, since it makes
for great difficulty when it comes to dis¬
cussing a topic such as ours today. In Spain
I have often found that teaching a peasant
to read is almost certain to spoil him;
developing the intellectual faculties of
people who have very deeply intuitive
minds is a very dangerous operation. I
was a student when I met Miguel de Una¬
muno for the first time, and I heard him
say something whose wisdom has struck
me more and more ever since. He said to
me, "The difference between a Spanish
workman and a Spanish peasant is this: a
Spanish peasant has five hundred ideas
and five hundred words to express them in,
and every time he speaks he says some¬
thing. A Spanish workman also has five
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Salvador de
Madariaga
(1886-1978).
Photo taken in
1965.
hundred ideas, but because he reads the
newspapers he has five thousand words to
express them in, and he never says any¬
thing." Please ponder on this great diffi¬
culty; I do so all the more humbly because
I can offer you no solution.
So the distinctive feature of the elite
is intelligence. Are you sure that in opening
wide the door to intellectual development
you are not destroying a balance? For
myself, I do not know. I am not sure
whether a certain energy of perception
and synthesis found in human beings is
not generally impoverished when it
becomes intellectual and moves into an
environment that is not spontaneously
familiar to it. Nevertheless, despite this
risk, I believe that the state's need to create
an intellectual elite is such that in practice
it is essential to have as perfect or as little
imperfect a policy for primary educa¬
tion as possible, in order to enable all the
people to provide the state with the intel¬
lectual elite it needs.
There is another consideration. I am on
the side of the individual rather than the
state. Hence the interests of the state
would not, for me, suffice to justify the
development ofprimary education. There
are also the interests of the individual.
Among the mass of the people who in gen¬
eral except for some particularly intel¬
lectual peoples like the French stand out
for their intuitive ability, there are never¬
theless potentially many people whose
normal existence is in the sphere of the
intellect. We have no right to deprive these
individuals of a chance to achieve a level to
which they could naturally aspire in the
state, still less the level they ought to
occupy in their own lives, by denying them
access to schooling.
Hence I believe that for both these rea¬
sons we must very boldly and openly
adopt a primary education policy, even at
the risk, as I said just now, of a consequent
impoverishment of intuition.
Having said that, we must distinguish
very clearly between the culture of the
greatest number and the culture of the
group. These are two entirely different
things, but they interpenetrate because
the culture of the greatest number would
be impossible to achieve without the cul¬
ture of the group.
We must think of culture as an orga¬
nized whole. For instance, a family must
have a family culture; a state must have a
state culture, and the organized humanity
we are painfully trying to build must have
an organized human culture.
Can this group culture be ttansmitted to
the masses by intellectual means? I do not
think so, and I believe that modern states
have sorely neglected this aspect of the
transmission ofculture an aspect which
was never neglected during the periods of
richness and unity of culture, for instance
during the great periods ofdie Church. The
Church managed to propagate Catholic
culture, group culture, by the only means
that are effective in reaching the masses, i.e.
through mythology and symbolism. Now in
my opinion, however bad mythology and
bad symbolism are misused nowadays or
rather, however mythology and symbolism
are misused nowadays in order to propa¬
gate a bad culture (for there can be bad
culture) we must learn to formulate, or
rather to create, myths and symbols in such
a way as to propagate this group culture
among our peoples.
So far as I am concerned, I am con¬
vinced that if the League ofNations has so
far failed (as it obviously has) to create an
international atmosphere ofpeace and co¬
operation, it is because the efforts made in .
this direction have been directed towards
intelligence, because the realm ofsymbols
and myths has been abandoned.
These are the ideas I wanted to convey
to you, because the topic you have just
started to tackle is perhaps the trickiest and
most difficult part of our proceedings.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
listening
THE HEARTBEAT OF JAZZ
by Isabelle Leymarie
48
Drums, an indispensable ingredient
of popular music, are the only instru¬
ments "invented" by jazz. Resulting from the jux¬
taposition of various percussion instruments,
they have changed over the years and benefitted
from several technical improvements.
When jazz appeared at the beginning of
the century, the first drummers used instru¬
ments borrowed from circus orchestras, brass
bands and music-hall companies. With their
expressive swing styles, New Orleans drum¬
mers of today often evoke African or West
Indian music, yet the drums used by their col¬
leagues of yesteryear were not of African origin.
The bass drum and the snare drum came from
Europe, and other drums came from China.
They were used more to impress the audience
than for purely musical reasons. European- or
Asian-made drums were used in classical jazz
because in the United Statesin contrast to the
West Indies and certain Latin American coun¬
tries where small drums and hand-beaten drums
continued to be played despite repression-
plantation owners forbade their slaves to play
drums, and the instrument quickly disappeared
from popular black music.
Not counting the cymbals, a drum-set con¬
sists of three sorts of drum: the bass drum, the
snare drum and the tom-tom. The first bass
drums used in jazz were identical to those used
by brass bands, and the drummer's main task
was to keep a regular beat. The drum's powerful
sound enabled it to be heard over the blare of
the brass. The barrel-shaped tom-toms were cov¬
ered with thick pig-skin and were usually lac¬
quered in red. Drummers also used Chinese
cymbals and temple blocks (thick blocks of
wooda little like wooden gongsplayed in
groups of four to six). Until the First World War
tom-toms, cymbals and temple blocks were
imported from China and were extremely pop¬
ular because of their low price. It is very likely
that the immigration of large numbers of Chi¬
nese to the United States in the second half of
A jazz instrument
originally used to
keep the beat, the
drum gradually
became a solo
instrument in its
own right.
the nineteenth century influenced the drum¬
mers of the time as they sought new sounds.
At the end of the 1920s, with the advent of
nightclubs and show business in Harlem, drums
became more complicated. Sonny Greer, Duke
Ellington's drummer, and Jimmy Crawford, who
played for Jimmie Lunceford, added kettle¬
drums to their sets, more, it must be said, for
show than strictly musical reasons. Perched on
top of a small platform, they boomed away
with gusto. When Duke Ellington played the
Cotton Club, Sonny Greer used an extraordinary,
custom-made drum-set that contained temple
blocks, all kinds of cymbals, overhead gongs,
kettledrums, a vibraphone and chimes. His
mother-of-pearl drums sporting his initials were
the envy of rival drummers.
A SPLASH OF CYMBALS
In the 1930s in New Orleans many drummers
began decorating their drums, not only with
the band's name or initials but also with attrac¬
tive landscapes, the band-leader's portrait or
even erotic drawings.
Drum playing gradually changed with the
introduction of technological innovations and
improvements. At the end of the nineteenth
century Dee Dee Chandler, John Robichaux's
drummer, was probably the first to add a
pedala wooden mallet at the timeto his
bass drum, which enabled him to speed up
the beat. Metal pedals were soon being made
on a large scale and were enthusiastically
adopted by other drummers.
Cymbals, imported from Istanbul until
1929, were prized for their exotic value. They
were mainly used for keeping the beat, but
during the swing era musicians like Joe Jones,
Count Basie's drummer, began using the
Charleston (cymbals attached to the bass
drum) in a much more fluid way than before. At
the end of the 1960s Elvin Jones, John
Coltrane's drummer, produced a continuous
musical flow with his cymbals that enveloped
the other musicians.
Bebop, which had appeared some years
before, used bigger, heavier cymbals to help with
its dizzying beat. A pioneer of this kind of music,
Kenny Clarke moved the emphasis from the
bass drum to the "ride" cymbal, which he played
in masterly fashion using the so-called
"chabada" technique. Nicknamed "Klook"
because of the unpredictible rhythms he pro¬
duced, Clarke produced a far more modern
sound on what had become full-fledged solo
instruments rather than mere metronomes.
In the late 1940s in response to increasing
demand for drums, calf-skin membranes were
replaced with plastic "skins" that produced a
harder sound but could be produced on a large
scale.
While drumming in rock and pop has kept,
an essentially binary, rhythm-keeping beat,
drummers like Max Roach, Art Blakey, Philly Joe
Jones and Tony Williams have invented rich
and varied rhythms with countless accents and
heady syncopation.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE
is a Franco-American musicologist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
UNITED NATIONS YEAR FOR TOLERANCE
Lieh-tzu
The world turned upside down
Mr P'ang of Ch'in had a son who was clever as a child but suffered
from an abnormality when he grew up. When he heard singing he
thought it was weeping, when he saw white he thought it was black;
fragrant smells he thought noisome, sweet tastes he thought bitter,
wrong actions he thought right. Whatever came into his mind,
heaven and earth, the four cardinal points, water and fire, heat and
cold, he always turned upside down. A certain Mr Yang told his
father:
"The gentlemen of Lu* have many arts and skills, perhaps they
can cure him. Why not inquire among them?"
The father set out for Lu, but passing through Ch'en he came
across Lao-tzu, and took the opportunity to tell him about his son's
symptoms.
"How do you know that your son is abnormal?" said Lao-tzu.
"Nowadays everyone in the world is deluded about right and
wrong, and confused about benefit and harm; because so many
people share this sickness, no one perceives that it is a sickness.
Besides, one man's abnormality is not enough to overturn his
family, one family's to overturn the state, one state's to overturn the
world. If the whole world were abnormal, how could abnormality
overturn it? Supposing the minds of everyone in the world were like
your son's, then on the contrary it is you who would be abnormal.
Joy and sorrow, music and beauty, smells and tastes, right and
wrong, who can straighten them out? I am not even sure that these
words of mine are not abnormal, let alone those of the gentlemen
of Lu, who are the most abnormal of all; who are they to cure other
people's abnormality? You had better go straight home instead of
wasting your money."
The Book ofLieh-tzu
Translated by A.C. Graham
Unesco Collection of Representative Works
' The Confucians.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
rETTERS TO THE EDITOR
50
Stepping on the gas
In the Greenwatch section of your October
1994 issue (page 41), I was surprised to read
that cars powered by natural gas cause almost
as much pollution as cars that run on petrol.
It is true that the combustion of natural or
methane gas produces nitrogen oxide,
carbon monoxide and carbon dioxide, but it
does so in much smaller quantities than the
combustion of petrol. Moreover, by pro¬
ducing methane from the muck of sewage
treatment plants and from plant waste,
industrial waste and animal droppings, we
should be killing two birds with one stone
obtaining cleaner energy and eliminating
harmful waste.
Roger Paganet
Member, Friends of the Earth
Mesnil-Ie-Roi (France)
Reports prepared by the OrganizationforEco¬
nomic Co-operation and Development
(OECD) indicate that gas-fuelled cars emit
very little carbon monoxide, but that the
amounts of methane they release into the
atmosphere are not negligible. According to
ecologist Edward Goldsmith, 20% ofglobal
warming is due to methane. The concentra¬
tion levels of methane in the atmosphere,
which have doubled since pre-industrial
times, grow by about 1 % per annum. What's
more, natural gasforprivate cars is still hard
tofind.
France Bequette
A one-sided debate?
I am interested in debate and the exchange
of ideas, not in one-sided arguments. For
example in your September 1994 issue (page
29) I read in Federico Mayor's "Commen¬
tary" that "The cause of the serious prob¬
lems confronting so many of the countries of
eastern Europe today is not freedom, but
rather the burden of oppression which they
had to bear for so long". And in the October
1994 issue (page 4) Bahgat Elnadi and Adel
Rifaat write, "There arose other forms of con¬
tempt for human beings and other forms of
exploitation of forced labour: the coloniza¬
tion ofmost non-European societies, fascist
and Nazi repression, and eastern Europe's
descent into totalitarianism".
By abolishing the balance that existed
within international institutions, the liqui¬
dation of socialism in the former U.S.S.R.
and in eastern Europe has led to the replace¬
ment of a debate of ideas arising from dif¬
ferent viewpoints by a single way of thinking
based on the dogma of capitalist ideology.
M. Champaloux
St-Gratien (France)
Facts and figures about nomads
No country has made estimates of the size of
nomadic populations within their territo¬
ries. Such estimates may, however, be
obtained from specialists working in dif¬
ferent parts of the world. But even they often
face the problem of defining nomadism, a
way of life for many societies practising very
diverse forms ofsubsistence, e.g. animal hus¬
bandry, hunting, gathering, fishing, trade or
crafts, and whose itinerant life can be attrib¬
uted toa variety of ecological and economic
factors.
We have contacted several such special¬
ists and have been able to find the following
estimates. These data do not include any of
the thousands of groups who are nomadic
(such as, for example, sea nomads, whose
population is estimated at a minimum of
750,000) but do not exist on animal hus¬
bandry. Overall estimates of nomadic pas¬
toral populations range between 30 and 40
million, broken down as follows:
North and West Africa: 10-15 million
(1975)
Sudan: 2,157,302 (1983)
Somalia: 1 million (1980)
East Africa: 6 - 7 million (1975)
Jordan: 7,000 (1979)
Iraq: 250,000 (1947)
Afghanistan: 2.4 million (1960-1961)
3.04 million (1971-1972)
Iran: 1 million (1980)
Turkey: 750,000 (currently)
Mongolia: 3 million (currently)
Siberia: 400,000 (currently)
Northern Europe: 35,000 (1981)
South America: 2.5 million (currently)
It would indeed be very useful for gov¬
ernments, NGOs, international organiza¬
tions, policy planners and researchers to col¬
lect more such data and collate more
statistics and draw up maps. As far as we are
concerned, we have the trained staff for such
a task but unfortunately not the resources
with which to finance it.
Michael I. Casimir and Aparna Rao
Chairmen of the Commission on Nomadic
Peoples
International Union ofAnthropological and
Ethnological Sciences
Köln (Germany)
Tel.: (49-221) 470-2278
Fax: (49-221) 470-5117
E-Mail: alv04@rsi.rrz.unl-koeln.de
Respect rather than tolerance?
From a news item on page 43 of your Sep¬
tember 1994 issue I learn that 1995 has been
proclaimed Year for Tolerance by the United
Nations.
Here in India, the chain of events that
began in December 1992 with the mindless
demolition of the Babri Masjid Mosque gave
rise to unprecedented violence that reflected
the ill-will and hatred that lie so close to the
surface of human emotions.
The tradition and culture of this country
that learnt its first lessons oí Ahimsa (non¬
violence) from great masters such as Gau¬
tama Buddha, Vardhamana Mahavir and in
our own times Mahatma Gandhi went to
naught in the frenzy that followed the Babri
Masjid incident.
As an educator and history researcher, I
wonder whether the word "tolerance" indi
cates the correct approach to education for
peace. The word carries within it an inherent
sense of condescension by a dominant group
over another less privileged group. The hope
and the anxiety that go with the word would
be better conveyed by the idea of "respect"
given and received amongst individuals,
communities, neighbouring states and
nations. We should respect each other's way
of life by learning to accept what we do not
understand.
Let us declare 1995 the "Year of Respect",
or better still, "co-existence".
G. Venkateswar
Bombay (India)
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, page 3: L Bertrand © Explorer, Paris.
Page 2: © Danie Moulin, Le Bourget du Lac,
France. Pages 5, 7: © Delphine Warin, Paris.
Page 8: © Alain Guillou, Le Croisic, France.
Page 9: © Laure Vasconi, Paris. Page 10:
Jenny Matthews © Network/Rapho, Paris.
Page 1 1 : M. Bertinetti © Rapho, Paris. Pages
12, 14 (left), 40: © Roland Michaud, Paris.
Page 1 3: F. Pitchal © Sygma, Paris. Page 1 4
(right): © Guillou/Rahuchet, Le Croisic,
France. Page 15: Carlos Humberto/TDC ©
Contact Press Images, Paris. Page 1 6: Frank
Siteman © Viesti Associates/Ask Images, Paris.
Pages 1 7, 1 8 (above): Michel Baret© Rapho,
Paris. Page 18 (below): David Graham ©
Black Star/Rapho, Paris. Page 20: Peter Willi
© Explorer, Paris. Page 2 1 : Christian Zachari-
asen © Sygma, Paris. Page 22: Halaska ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 23: J.-M. Turpin © Sygma,
Paris. Page 24 (above): G. Atger © Editing,
Paris. Page 24 (below): Dumont © REA,
Paris. Page 25: Rhodri Jones © Panos Pictures,
London. Page 26: Reza © Sygma, Paris. Page
27 (above): Abbas © Magnum, Paris. Page 27
(below): Claudine Doury©Vu, Paris. Page
28 (left): Hugues de Wurstemberger © Vu,
Paris. Pages 28-29: Stephane Ragot © Vu,
Paris. Page 34: UNESCO-lnes Forbes. Pages
36-37, 37 (above), 37 (middle), 38
(below), 39 (below): © Monique Pietri,
Paris. Pages 37 (below), 38 (above): ©
Armand Emont, Paris. Page 39 (above): ©
taken from L'art en Inde by C. Sivaramamurti
© Editions Mazenod/Citadelles, Paris. Page
4 1 : Robert Doisneau © Rapho, Paris. Page
42: © Peter Tomlinson. Page 43: Charles ©
Rapho, Paris. Page 44: All rights reserved.
Page 47: © Keystone, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
LISEZ TOUS LES MOIS ^_
>
Llitece ^^. Propose depuis 1978
^^^^^» des stages d'anglais
TimT TTMIP Language ^^" pour scolaires,
ETV DES .. # universitaires et
College adultes, à Jersey,
-L/ X w JL-/JiLy Guernesey et Londres
Revue d'information, de réflexion et de culture Q Stages renforcés pour la
préparation aux examens
Dans les numéros de janvier et février : Q Cours pendant toute l'année
préparant aux examens de
Les guerres de l'eau au Moyen-Orient François Boëdec Cambridge et de la Chambre de
commerce de Londres
Environnement, agriculture
et développement Dominique Vermersch Q Stages intensifs suivis d'un
Le racisme subtil Maurice Olive
placement professionnel
Rwanda : l'Eglise
après le génocide Octave Ugira Shebuya
Stages "sur mesures" individuels
ou séminaires pour professionnels
(cadres, juristes, gestionnaires, etc.)
Miguel de Unamuno Pierre Sempé
Séjours linguistiques pour jeunes
et adultes de 2 à 6 semaines
Choix de films. Chroniques de théâtre, pendant les vacances scolaires
Revue des livres. Choix de disques (tous niveaux, classes de 8 élèves,
professeurs hautement qualifiés,
hébergement en famille, programme
sportif et excursions).
Le n° : (144 pages) 55 F, étr. 62 F Rédacteur en chef
Abonnement : 1 1 nos / an : 460 F - étr. 560 F Jean-Yves Calvez Pour obtenir dc plus amples renseignements :
Lutèee Language College
Pour recevoir un numéro ou vous abonner, envoyez vos nom, P.O. BOX 623 9 New street
adresse et règlement à l'ordre d'ETUDES à : St. Heller, JERSEY Channel Islands
Assas Editions 14, rue d'Assas - 75006 PARIS - Tél. : (1) 44 39 48 48 Tél. : (19.44)53459502
Ou, sur Minitel, tapez 36 15 SJ* ETUDES Fax: (19.44) 53469010 !
15th BOOK FAIR
17th to 22nd March 95
Parc des Expositions de Paris
Porte de Versailles
Morning opening
for booksellers
only Monday
March 20th
9h30 - 12h30
Free entrance
for booksellers,
librarians
teachers
and translators
Guest of honour :
Spain
5th Show
of the Review
Multimedia
Area
Book
professions
Meetings
(for professionals only)
The Salón du Livre is organized under the aegis of
Every day opening
10h-19h
Last opening
Tuesday
March 21st
10h - 22h
Grouped entrance
tickets with
SAGA and
MUSICORA
:30F
Events,
programme
of dedications
MM)K ai sm;dnai di
L'EDITION
information : Oil' / 62, rue de Miromesnil 75008 Paris - Trance
Tel : (33-1) 49 S3 27 00 - Tax : (33-1) 49 S3 27 88
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
SÜIsü
CONTACT
(bURIErl
ON
f I A THE
UNES VER
(address: UNESCO.ORG)
beginning in March
ANY COMMENTS ON THE MAGAZINE
AND ITS CONTENTS!
send your messages to our e.mail address:
UNESCO.COURIER@UNESCO.ORG
UNESC©
OURIER
THE SUN
ANCIKNT MYTHS
M « TI CHNOLOGIES
i te
<m #
wsí§&
Each month, essential
reading for an
understanding of the
problems of today and
tomorrow
THE THEME OF THE NEXT ISSUE,
PUBLISHED ON THE OCCASION OF THE
WORLD SUMMIT FOR SOCIAL
DEVELOPMENT, WILL BE:
THE HAVES AND
THE HAVE-NOTS
ALSO FEATURING A HITHERTO
UNPUBLISHED TEXT BY:
NOBEL PEACE PRIZE WINNER
AUNG SAN SUU KYI
HERITAGE:
BYBLOS, CROSSROADS OF
THE WORLD
BIOSPHERE RESERVE:
MONTSENY, A LABORATORY
OF HARMONY
SáSi®r®RS!
three good reasons
for offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
ü
IP PBpW
I
mm WÈÊ
The Unesco Courier is the onfy international magazine published in 30
languages and read by hundreds of thousands of people in 120 countries jJ
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with UNESCO's mission of furthering "umVersal respect
for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms.. .without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
]]>
</page>
</document>
