<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="100259eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
1& ::
¥rWm 1 *
W
m*»
WR
Ijt
INTERVIEW WITH
THE ABBE PIERRE
m
m*
h i
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We Invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to
all photographs.
Birth Sun
1993, coloured etching
(77.5 cm x 51 cm)
by Helen Hawley
In this image of the sun
and the earth the
artist, who originates
from western Canada,
has been inspired by
early Cree or Blackfoot
Indian paintings on
buffalo skins. "The
message I'm trying to
get across," she writes,
"is how much all of us
have in common, under
the universal light and
warmth of the sun."
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
MAY 1995
Cover:
pilgrims perform ritual
ablutions In Takao waterfall
on Mount Ontake (Japan).
THE PILGRIM'S WAY
Interview with The Abbé Pierre
40 HERITAGE
The mystery of Persepolis
by Charles-Emmanuel Doxuan
45 GREENWATCH
Mining: a clean bill of health?
by France Bequette
44 ARCHIVES
The Latin American intellect
by Alfonso Reyes
50 LISTENING
The eye and the ear
by Isabelle Leymarie
A mysterious journey
by François-Bernard Huyghe
The thrice-holy city
by Annie Laurent
Pathways to enlightenment
by Michael Pye
The road to Compostela
by Milien Bravo Lozano
Messengers of light:
Chinese Buddhist pilgrims in India
by Paul Magnin
Pilgrimages in Judaism
by Nicholas de Lange
il Where the rivers meet
by Rustom Bharucha
The heart's infinity
by Abdelwahab Meddeb
Consultant François-Bernard Huyghe
Commentary by Federico Mayor
Tri& UNESCO
QXIRIER
48ffi year
Published monthly In 30
languages and In Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their
peoples and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives	"
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THL UNESCO
Q)URIER
48th YEAR
Published monthly In 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational. Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31, rue François Bonvir. 75732 Paris CEDEX 15. France,
fax: (33-1) 45.66.92.70
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca. Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel. 45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (Tel. 45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Bernej
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Javaid Iqbal Syed (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dares-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sopnie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyaa:gama (Colombo)
Finnish: Kaul Himma (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Sudhasinee Vajrabul (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernández (Santiago de
Com postela)
SALES AND PROMOTION. Fax: 45.68.45.89
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel. 45.68.49.19)
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Te1. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: Daniel Meister (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 211 Frerch francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72. FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted pro¬
viding the credit line reads 'Reprinted from the Unesco Courier, plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyhgnt photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by
an International reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the opin¬
ions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco
or those of the editors of the U.\esco Couner. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Uhesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in the
magazine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations. The Unesco Courieris produced in microform (microfilm and/or
microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fcntenoy, 75700 Paris: (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100 U.S.A.: (3) N.CR. Microcard Edi¬
tion, Indian Head Inc.. Ill West 40th Street, New York. U.S.A.: (4) Bell and
Howell Co.. Old Mansfield Road. Wooster. Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
¡MPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Prnted in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - MAI 1995
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N' 71844 DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z.l. Route d'Étampes. 45331 Malserbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 5-1995-OPI-95-537A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 2-3 and 50-51.
onth by month
Pilgrimages began long ago. In most religions they are times of intense spiritual
feeling. They also have political implications.
They kindle the collective imagination around a holy place that is charged with
symbolism, a site associated with crucial moments in the life of a religion. The
act of pilgrimage intensifies the personal faith of believers and strengthens their
bonds of fidelity to their community.
By their very nature, therefore, places of pilgrimage ought to be outside the arena
of temporal ambitions and rivalries. But, as we know, this is not always the case.
Because those who control centres of pilgrimage are invested with prestige
and even moral legitimacy to an exceptional degree, these holy places have some¬
times become pawns in power struggles and triggers of confrontation.
Throughout history people of all sorts and conditions, inspired by authentic reli¬
gious fervour, have gone off to make war on others over a city or a mountain, a
cave or a valleya site which both sides considered to be sacred.
How could these men, who suffered the most gruelling hardships, in many cases
leading to mystical experiences, go so far as to kill each other in order to gain
possession of places there was every reason for them to share and honour
together?
This agonizing question, so often pondered in the past, is posed with renewed
force today. In our age of paradox and contradiction, horizons broaden for
everyone and yet solitude and insecurity increase. All over the world, opportunities
for meeting others, for self-expression and mutual understanding are so often
thwarted by impulses to ignore or reject others, even to risk mutual destruction.
The great centres of pilgrimage where the symbolic pathways of different reli¬
gious communities have overlapped since ancient times must cease to be flash¬
points of contention between these communities. They should provide the faithful
of all denominations with an opportunity to achieve reconciliation by rediscovering,
through their different forms of religious symbolism, the meaning of their common
attachment to the same holy site. In so doing they will provide the rest of the world
with new reasons to believe in the unity of humankind.
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
THE ABBE
PIERRE
talks to Martine Leca
Von. \\ lio thought yourself superfluous, aro needed.
The Abbé Pierre (a pseudonym
adopted in 1942 by Henri Grouès,
born in Lyons, France, in 1912)
has championed the cause of the
poor and dispossessed for almost
half a century. He is internationally
known for his work with Emmaus,
the charitable association which
he founded in 1949 and which now
has branches in many parts of the
world. In 1991 he was awarded
the Balzan prize for humanity,
peace and brotherhood between
peoples. Among his published
works are Emmaus ou venger
l'homme (conversations with
Bernard Lechevallier, Livre de
Poche, Paris, 1987), a liturgical
play, Le mystère de la joie (1985),
Mes images de bonheur, de
misère, d'amour (Text by Pierre
Lunel, photos by the Abbé Pierre,
Fixot, Paris, 1994) and Testament
(Bayard, Paris, 1994). Here he
looks back over his life and work.
You started out as a monk. How did you
come to be the spokesman of the poor,
travelling round the world and meeting
heads of state? How did you come to make
the change from contemplation to action?
When I was eighteen I told my parents I
wanted to become a novice in the
Capuchins, the strictest branch of the Fran¬
ciscan Order. I came from a wealthy family.
I made over my share of the estate to various
charities. My family background was deeply
Christian. My father, unbeknown even to
his close relatives and friends and although
he was in poor health, used to spend his
Sundays, with a small group of friends,
looking after vagrants. When I was fifteen
or so I went through a period of doubt that
lasted for about two years and the pangs of
which were aggravated by a long illness.
Illness has always brought me nearer to a
state of grace. The process of my transfor¬
mation came to a head with my discovery of
St. Francis of Assisi during a pilgrimage I
went on with a scout troop from my school.
Sensing what was to be the characteristic
feature of my whole existence, they gave
me the "jungle name" of "Thoughtful
Beaver" he who builds and meditates
and my life has indeed been one long ven¬
ture of thinking and building.
My encounter with St. Francis was a
defining moment. One night in Assisi,
during Easter week, feeling unwell and
unable to sleep I went out into the streets of
the old town and walked as far as the foot
of the ruined fortress. It was five in the
morning and it was wonderful. It was
springtime, the birds' dawn chorus was
beginning and all the bells of the town
started to ring out the angélus. As the sun
rose I jotted down on a piece of paper
which I still have the feelings that fdled
my heart: "Oh the bells! To die on a
morning of bells. To die on one of those
mornings when the whole earth confesses
the fullness of Love".
That afternoon, my friends and I went
on muleback to what are known as the
prisons, the caves where St. Francis used
to go to meditate. When we returned to
Assisi I knelt and kissed the ground because
back there two things had become power¬
fully evident to me: firstly, that worship
leads to universal communion with
humanity; and secondly, that it provides an
extraordinarily effective preparation for
action, as we can see from the life of St.
Francis, a life spent in contemplation and
at the same time in meeting with princes
and telling them the truths of the Gospel.
Those seven years in the cloister were the
key to my life. Providence was well aware
what lay ahead for me, and my Capuchin
training was to prepare me for it.
What is the life of a Capuchin monk
like?
The studies are rudimentary. In my
time it's not like that any longer we were
awake every night from midnight to two
o'clock. We spent the first hour chanting in
two choirs and the second in pure,
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW WITH THE ABBE PIERRE
The truc driving force, the
one that makes things
move forward, is striving
towards Unity, not greed.
unadorned worship, in the dark, without
even a reading to help us. Seven years of
.. such a ritual when you are a young man
leaves a mark upon you like that of a seal in
wax. Without experiencing that extreme,
almost excessive way of life, that training in
worship and in the love of one's neighbour,
I would not have had the strength required
to set up Emmaus and to wage a forty-year
combat. Echoing Archimedes' words, "Give
me but one firm spot on which to stand and
I will move the Earth", the Pope declared
that love is a lever that can move the Earth.
I owe that strength to my Capuchin
brothers. I had to leave in 1938 because of
illness and I was ordained a priest, but I
remained in touch with Franciscan spiri¬
tuality through what is known as the third
order of St. Francis of Assisi. Then war
broke out and I was called up.
You were thrown into active life and
joined the Resistance . . .
I started off as a non-commissioned
officer in the Alps and in Alsace, then, after
I had had diphtheria, I worked as a chap¬
lain in the Isère département. During the
years when the Resistance was under¬
ground, from 1942 to 1944, 1 helped to set
up maquis groups in the Chartreuse and
Vercors regions. While I was a chaplain in
the cathedral of Grenoble, a tragedy
occurred that triggered off everything I
have done since then: the round-up of Jews
at the Vélodrome d'hiver cycle track in
Paris. The French police and gendarmes, in
many cases shamefacedly and reluctantly of
course, carried out the order they received
from the minister responsible for Jewish
affairs in the Vichy government to round up
the Jewish families in the unoccupied zone.
One day some Jewish refugees came to me,
as a man of God, asking for shelter, and I
hid them. Then I learned how to forge iden¬
tity papers and finally, as the arrests became
more frequent, I smuggled Jews out of the
_ country, into Switzerland and Spain, with
O the help of mountain guides.
After the war, prompted by the Car¬
dinal Archbishop of Paris, I entered Par¬
liament so that a priest could speak out
for the poor, as canon law at that time still
permitted. This strengthened me in my
task. I had to plead the cause of society's
outcasts before the multitude and before
the authorities. I resigned my seat in 1951.
It was at that time you founded
Emmaus. Why did you choose that name?
It stands for hope. I rented a derelict
house in Neuilly-Plaisance, in the eastern
suburbs of Paris, and started "beavering"
away, doing up a building which soon
turned out to be too big. So I turned it into
a youth hostel. The young people who came
to it twenty-year-olds, English, Italian,
German, French, some of them orphans of
the war in which their fathers had killed
each other were sad, their disgust with
life increased by the recent discovery of the
horror of the concentration camps.
One day I was re-reading St. Luke's
Gospel, the part where, on the third day
after Jesus' death, the disciples were making
their way towards the village of Emmaus
you remember? They were discussing what
had happened. They were downcast, dis¬
appointed, because Jesus had been
announced as a prophet, come to set them
free, but nothing had happened. As they
walked, Jesus drew near and went with
them but they did not recognize him. It was
only when he was at table with them and
took bread, blessed it, broke it and gave it
to them that their eyes were opened. After¬
wards, they spoke those favourite words
of mine: "Did not our heart burn within
us, while he talked with us by the way?" So
I took a board, wrote "Emmaus" on it and
hung it on the door of the house, and I gave
all those young people this explanation:
"You must believe that a good, successful life
entails disillusion but also enthusiasm. It
first of all entails that honesty which can lose
its illusions with a good grace, for we come
into the world filled with illusions but we
shed them as we grow so as to arrive at the
truth, and we can only succeed by letting go
of them. The disciples, who had lost hope,
recovered their enthusiasm which does
not mean elation but, in the Greek,
becoming one with the Eternal, which is
Love and went off to proclaim the good
news to the apostles, saying that they had
seen the risen Christ."
That was how Emmaus became a move¬
ment giving refuge to those whom life has
treated roughly. One of the first was a man
called Georges who had tried to commit
suicide. He had served twenty years in a
penal colony for killing his father and had
been pardoned after saving someone in a
fire at the prison, but when he came back
he found his wife with another man and
other children. In desperation he tried to
kill himself. Somebody sent for me and I lis¬
tened to him, and I said to him, without
thinking, instinctively it was the Spirit
of God making me its instrument:
"Georges, you want to die, you say you
are going to try to commit suicide again.
Before you kill yourself, wouldn't you like
to come and give me a hand to finish these
houses for families in need?"
The question I asked Georges has now
become a general one You, who thought
you were superfluous, who thought there
was no place for you in society, not only
are you not superfluous, you are needed
and so those who were beggars become
givers. Since those days the movement has
gone on growing as poverty has spread.
Emmaus is still not sufficiently active in
Africa, however.
In fact, branches of Emmaus now exist
on five continents. This "uprising of good¬
ness" goes back to 1954, when you became
known in France as "God's rebel" and the
inventor of the "licence to live" . . .
In the winter of 1954, which was excep¬
tionally hard all over Europe, people were
dying of cold in the streets. No provision
had been made to help them. My friends
and I went out every night to rescue the
homeless, but the friends who helped me at
night had to work in the daytime as well, to
earn a living and to feed the poor. The
task was becoming superhuman, so I
wanted to make an appeal on the radio.
When a certain broadcaster was being eva¬
sive, one of my friends said to him: "Just
Anger is my way of
expressing my love. We
need to combat the
indifference of the
authorities. I shout out
loud to awaken the crowd.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
imagine yourself, in the warmth of your
home and with your family around you,
opening the paper at breakfast tomorrow
and learning that more people had been
picked up dead off the streets in the night
you must broadcast this appeal."
The broadcaster gave in, the unprece¬
dented call went out, and it had an extra¬
ordinary impact throughout France. Gifts
in cash and in kind, from rich and poor
alike, came in from all over the country,
and Parliament, which had previously
refused to allocate funds from the public
works budget for what I called "emergency
housing", accepted my request. That
appeal also brought to light the extent of
poverty in France. But having become
"God's rebel" I was a nuisance, as St.
Francis was for the prelates of the Holy
Mother Church. The Minister of the Inte¬
rior said they must strike at the head of the
movement, but the Chief of Police, who
was a secret sympathizer of ours, stood
his ground and said the Abbé Pierre should
be left alone. Why? Because I was a priest,
I had been a member of Parliament, I had
my wartime decorations and I had the
silent support of the underprivileged.
Emmaus now has branches in thirty-
five countries, and I have travelled all round
the world spreading the word. From 1958 to
1965, 1 made many journeys and gave many
lectures in support of the communities that
were coming into existence in Lebanon, in
Scandinavia, South America, Asia and
Africa. Emmaus divides the world into nine
regions, each ofwhich appoints a number of
officers who make up the Administrative
Committee, which in its turn appoints a
ten-member Executive Committee. The
presidency of the international movement is
based in the Paris suburb of Alfortville.
Another thing that has contributed greatly
to the spread of Emmaus are the interna¬
tional camps we have set up, where young
people from all over the world come and
work together for the poor. These volunteers
undertake to devote a major part of their
time, or even their whole Uves, to this cause.
Is Emmaus a specifically religious
movement?
No. Although it was founded by a
Catholic priest and takes its name from
the Gospel, it is non-denominational and
non-political.
Poverty is being constantly aggravated
by the population explosion, the misman¬
agement of resources and the growing
gap between North and South. What role
does Emmaus play in combating these
problems?
It plays not one but two roles. The first
is to stand up to the authorities and remind
them of their basic duties. We have to do
this in order to establish peace on earth and
to be of service, above all, to those who
suffer most, the weakest and the smallest;
and also in order to establish an order in
the world, in a context where the youth of
today are the first generation to have a
planet-wide awareness, where any event,
anywhere in the world, has repercussions
everywhere on account of the speed of
communication.
The second role derives from the fact
that living in the Emmaus communities are
4,000 people who have taken some hard
knocks in life and who are motivated by the
desire not to make more money, but to
work in order to give. They have not caught
the profit disease. How have we fed these
4,000 people, paid their social security
contributions and paid for holidays for
them? By using what the consumer society
throws away, saving things to save people.
We were ecologists before the letter. The
French town of Beaune, for example, asked
us to send a team to tackle the problem of
unauthorized rubbish dumping.
The Abbé Pierre in a Paris building occupied
by homeless squatters (1994).
The poor nowadays can be said to have
a certain power vis-à-vis the democracies.
They are a danger; you compare them to
human time-bombs.
There has been a turning point in human
history. I see the first sign of it in the guffaw
let out by Nasser, the head of a nation,
Egypt, that in the 1950s did not carry much
weight in the international arena. In 1956,
when he nationalized the Suez Canal and
blocked access to it, he brought the two
great nations Britain and France to their
knees. We have entered the age of the impo¬
tence of the strong and the power of the
weak, although the power of the latter is
only relative: it can make the mighty bow
down but can hardly manage the electrifi¬
cation of a country.
The numbers of the dispossessed in
the so-called developed countries are
growing. Does the fault lie with capitalism,
which, necessary though it may be, has
been led astray by the profit motive?
Capitalism may be said to be necessary, _
since even communism was no more than /
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW WITH THE ABBE PIERRE
state capitalism. A balance needs to be
struck between private capitalism and a
partially state-run capitalism, which
restores to citizens, in the form of social
security, family allowances and other safe¬
guards, what has been taken away from
them. This reminds me of the last conver¬
sation between Roosevelt and Stalin. The
American President said that their two
countries had got along pretty well in the
war but that the war would soon be over
and what would happen then? Stalin is
said to have replied: "The only problem is
whether our successors will be intelligent
enough to avoid the worst, I mean using
atomic weapons. But eventually the defects
of capitalism will get mixed up with those of
collectivism. People will no longer stand for
being deprived of their freedom, and the
time will come when your sons will marry
our daughters."
You have called for the establishment
of a world government. Isn't that Utopian?
Utopias are the carthorses that have
pulled history along. It's true that
humanity has seen a succession of crises,
wars and atrocities, but this negative side
is offset by advances in technology and
cultural exchanges. Despite atrocities such
as those in Rwanda, humanity is advancing
towards the One, towards Unity, as my
friend the French palaeontologist and
philosopher Pierre Teilhard de Chardin
predicted it would. The true driving force,
the one that makes things move forward, is
this striving towards Unity, not greed. The
One is not the uniformity into which all
individuality fades but that which brings
people together on the mountain top, what¬
ever different paths they take to reach it.
Together with the homeless, you take
over vacant properties, you go on hunger
strike, you camp out in front of government
offices. Is this your way of putting your faith
into practice?
Anger is my way of expressing my love.
We need to combat the indifference of the
authorities. I yell out loud to awaken the
crowd. It's not enough to attend church
and pray every Sunday; you have to act.
Many of the faithful devote themselves to
charitable work. Poverty is there on our
doorstep. That was why I invented the
"licence to live", emphasizing that it was
not a question of charity but of justice.
Because of all this, I have had to be a one-
0 man band lawyer, diplomat, counsellor,
Ö psychologist, trustee in short a man of
When they are assailed by
despair, young people
should let universal
concerns into their lives.
Then they will find their
place in society, where a
state of emergency has
been declared.
action and a darling of the media because
on a world-wide scale journalists have an
essential role of informing, warning and
querying, three vital functions in a society
that harbours exclusion, despair, disori¬
entation and hopelessness. People are
needed to take up the challenge, strong
people, who proclaim the truth, throw it in
people's faces, and do what they can with
their own two hands.
What's more, at the time when our
"illegal" activities were at their height, I
always pointed out that illegality is not
moving into empty premises that could
provide shelter for a woman and children.
What is illegal is the law itself when it fails
to provide everyone with the bare necessi¬
ties food, lodging, work and health
care as human rights, at present flouted,
require. The law in such cases is unjust,
and to observe it is unjust: it must be
changed.
There is also the grave problem of the
unemployed with time on their hands, time
that they should use creatively, not destruc¬
tively.
It is a characteristic of the times we live
in that we are a society foredoomed to
having time on our hands, a civilization
living in the concrete jungle, not the forest,
where the prospects for survival are dif¬
ferent and in the long term capable of
improvement. This is a new kind of time,
which should be made life-enhancing, not
degrading. The French socialist leader
Léon Blum was ridiculed when he pro¬
posed a "Ministry of Leisure", but he was
ahead of his time. There are three million
unemployed in France, not counting those
who have taken early retirement and are
fully able-bodied, in full possession of their
skills but unable to use them. There is an
imperative need to invent life-enhancing
ways of using this spare time, otherwise a
whole segment of our society is in danger of
sliding into drug abuse, drink and delin¬
quency time to help others, time for play
and sport, for instance, not to produce
champions earning fabulous sums of money
but for the joy of the game, of exercising the
body.
Do you have a message of hope for
young people?
Hope is not a matter of age. The main
thing is to be young at heart, to still feel
enthusiasm for great causes, even at eighty-
two. When they are assailed by despair,
young people should let universal concerns
into their lives. Then they will find their
place in our society, a society in which a
state of emergency has been declared. The
lack of a cause to fight for, the desire to live
in an artificial environment, being drawn
into the spiral of consumption, the way
people are forgetting how to be what I call
"extremists in the search for light" all
these things have created the present cli¬
mate of despondency. The coming genera¬
tion must escape from it: this, the first
planet-wide generation, must be mobilized
to fight the only worthwhile war, a counter¬
attack on poverty, which has declared war
on the whole world. These young people
have the good fortune to be mobilized for
the finest of all victories.
What I would say to the young men
and women who are beset by hopelessness
and doubt is that they should go and see
what is being done on the ground to fight
poverty, not like going to the zoo but to
take action, to open their hearts and their
consciences. After this kind of voluntary
service, they will find job openings in
humanitarian work. There is a combat to
be waged against the forces of evil, those
life-denying forces that prevent people
achieving fulfilment and pitch them into
suicidal behaviour. Young people must
remember three things: they are fore¬
doomed to know everything, foredoomed to
new ways of sharing and foredoomed to
have time on their hands, time they must
transform from idleness into creative
activity. It is in these three lines of force
that their hope lies.
MARTINE LECA
is a French writer and journalist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
A mysterious journey
by François-Bernard Huyghe
Pilgrimages are a feature of most of the world's religions
Above, Pilgrims going to
Mecca, a painting by the
French artist Léon Belly (1827-
1877). Mecca, In Saudi Arabia,
is the birthplace and heart of
Islam.
Between non-existent pillars, bathed in
unearthly light, a human clone advances
without moving. As he looks around or conti¬
nues on his imaginary way, the perspective
changes and different parts of the sanctuary
float into or out of his field of vision.
The scene thus described is real enough. By
means of virtual imaging technology, people
wearing headsets linked to computers can "visit"
the basilica of Cluny in France, "walk" around
the ambulatory, "turn" right or left, "gaze
upwards" at the vaulting and so forth, though
they may be hundreds of miles away.
Wearing a virtual reality headset, the believer
can theoretically "see" a place of worship, but
could he or she thereby be considered to make
a pilgrimage? The faithful of all religions would
answer "no" to this provocative question, and,
perhaps, condemn the very idea of such a pre¬
tence. There can be no pilgrimage without a
body of flesh and blood, no pilgrim's way
without a dusty road, no effective devotion
without real space. This is the first paradox
associated with pilgrimage. The body must grow
heavy for the soul to become light. Feet are
needed to go where the spirit breathes. That is
why, in the age of the instantaneous transmission
of images and of rapid transport, great multi¬
tudes surge around the Kaaba, on the banks of
the Ganges or on the plain of Chartres.
Far from being outmoded, pilgrimages are
highly topical. But what are they, exactly? The
concentration-camp survivor who revisits
Auschwitz and the old soldier who tours the
cemeteries along the Verdun road where the
bones of the fighting men of the First World War
lie mingled are commonly said to be making a
pilgrimage. On a less sombre note, we talk of
making a pilgrimage to the scenes of our youth
or to the place where we met a loved one. But
whether they are connected with death or love,
respect or nostalgia, such visits to the scenes of
the past are pilgrimages only by analogy, by
reference to a kind of journey that should not be
confused with any other.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Below, young penitents take
part in a pilgrimage to the
church of Our Lady of
Guadalupe, a few kilometres
away from the centre of Mexico
City. The church stands on the
spot where the Holy Virgin
appeared to an Indian in 1531.
About 10 million pilgrims visit
the shrine every year.
A pilgrimage is a quintessentially religious
act which creates a bond. It connects secular
places with the world above, the wayfarer with
the travelling community of the faithful, and the
flesh-and-blood pilgrim with his second self,
who will be reborn, healed or cleansed by making
the pilgrimage. These bonds or bridges between
orders of reality imply that there is a distinction
between pilgrimages and mere ceremonies, gath¬
erings, acts of worship, processions or devo-
10
tional visits, even though pilgrimages may include
all of these. They require at one and the same time
a sacred place, a sacred way and a sacred goal.
Few religions have been able to do without this
threefold mediation. Some have expressed mistrust
of a practice, often spontaneous and originating
among the rank and file, that can easily degenerate
into superstition, the fetishistic veneration of
relics, or the impious assessment of merits and
rewards. Many Christian theologians, for example,
see pilgrimages as an obstacle to contact with the
divine in the form of a pointless, or impure, detour
through the world of the senses. This was the
attitude of the Reformation towards Catholic
pilgrimages in the sixteenth century.
Buddhism is divided between its reservations
about the relics or representations of the Enlight¬
ened One (since he shows the way to liberation
from the cycle of reincarnation) on the one hand
and, on the other, the demands of the faithful
who, even in the lifetime of Gautama Buddha,
begged him for places, relics or signs to help
them express their fervent devotion to him after
his disappearance. Just as any religion may expe¬
rience a battle between iconolaters and iconoclasts
(is it possible to achieve knowledge of the divine
through the love of palpable representations?), so
theologians waver, where pilgrimages are con-
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Left, Hindu pilgrims make their
way to the Amamath caves,
over 4,500 metres high in the
Indian State of Jammu and
Kashmir.
cerned, between fear of degeneration into idolatry
or magic and acknowledgment of believers' per¬
manent needs.
We cannot say for certain that pilgrimages
have always existed, even though there is evidence
to suggest that travellers made their way to holy
places in prehistoric times. In the absence ofwritten
records to shed light on their significance, we shall
never know whether these hypothetical gatherings
met our definition. On the other hand, we have
well-attested written records ofpilgrimages dating
back to the Mesopotamian civilization, to the holy
places of Nippur and Babylon, and of sacred jour¬
neys made by the Egyptians and the Hittites.
Though we cannot be sure that pilgrimages
are a universal phenomenon, geographically
speaking, it should be remarked that very few reli¬
gions that have spread beyond the territorial con¬
fines of a single ethnic group have not given rise
to comparable gatherings in some form or other.
H
Below, pilgrims celebrate
appearances of the Virgin Mary
in the Senegalese village of
Popenguine, some 30
kilometres south of Dakar. The
pilgrimage takes place each
year at Whitsuntide.
oly places
Is the symbolism of the topography of the pil¬
grimage any less worthy to be considered uni¬
versal than the pilgrimage itself? What is the
constant goal? Holy places come in various
kinds. They may be mountains or rivers, grottoes
or lakes, trees or springs, but by the depths
The three essential components of
a pilgrimage are a sacred place, a
sacred way and a sacred goal.
from which they rise or the height that they
attain they suggest a transition to another dimen¬
sion than the horizontal and terrestrial where the
pilgrim lives, moves and has his being. This is the
first interpretation that comes to mind of the pil¬
grim's destination, be it the Ganges or Mount
Arafat, Athena's olive or the Bodhi tree, the
mountain top where the Taoist pilgrim climbs to
seek audience, or the springs of Lourdes where
the sick immerse themselves.
While most pilgrimages lead to a holy city or
building, one should also add the dimension of
time to that of space. The shrine, whether it con¬
tains the relics of a saint or the visible marks of a
past contact with the divine, a temple, a tablet of
the law, signs of a miracle or reminders of a
covenant, recalls some foundation event. The goal
of the pilgrimage, whether it is a place from which
the faith emanates, a centre on which it converges
or a commemorative representation, allows of
many different interpretations. The power at
work is often so great that one and the same site
1»
^ "irî'iB^TiL^^ 1 >p\-s
^** ^_c^*~j w^Bnter^^j "^BhB^Btm ' i» -.. a», ^fr^
L^^ >*v &'^ -o ¿f*Z*f~:^**apyte< - ' j
BL^.^?- ^^W
1 V ^5öSKK--^
Tw, 1 x* *"¿ÍB^i '" ï I
V BlH^^EflBBBAV M
B^L^T ^BV » * ** BH Bm i *^L wM^^" B^r"~JBl I 3
¿\y W* il BF 1 l\ BWfl Br fettBk ^B B
wi 1 i lYilnllMl
j 1
Br ^E ibBL I|^ R55^L Ij'.uH Hi^BBI Im
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
may be revered by various faiths, in succession or
simultaneously. Thus, we learn from medieval
travellers' tales that the same tracks at the top of
a mountain in present-day Sri Lanka were vari¬
ously revered as the footsteps of the Buddha and
as those of Adam, and drew Buddhists, Muslims ''
and Christians alike. Jerusalem, city of peace, is
sacred to the three major monotheistic religions.
Peace often lies more in the significance of such
places than in the logic of men.
A Brahman at prayer on the
banks of the Ganges in Benares
(Uttar Pradesh), a major
pilgrimage centre in India.
Homeward bound
12
The goal is, however, nothing without the way
to it. The pilgrim's progress is a journey through
space and time and within the self, a metaphor
of the secular life and something that endows it
with meaning. The pilgrim's way also estab¬
lishes a bond: it brings together and unites trav¬
ellers at the same high point in their existence, it
spreads ideas and models, and it forges an
alliance between peoples who share a faith and
a culture. It would be absurd to exclude Mecca,
Jerusalem, or the road to Compostela, Delphi or
Olympia from any explanation of the historical
unity of the civilizations to which they belong.
Such an explanation would lack an essential
component the idea that civilization implies
transmission and circulation.
FRANÇOIS-BERNARD HUYGHE,
French writer and journalist, is a
former member of Unesco's
Division of Cultural Heritage. His
most recent published works are
Les Coureurs d'êpices, Sur la
route Oes Indes fabuleuses
("The Spice Hunters, On the
Road to the Fabulous Indies",
J.-C. Lattes, Paris, 1995) and
(with Edith Huyghe) Les Empires
du mirage, Hommes, dieux et
mythes sur la route de la Soie
("Men, Gods and Myths on the
Silk Road", Robert Laffont,
Paris, 1993).
Mere specks borne along in a movement
that is greater than they are, pilgrims are also
transformed when they reach the end of their
personal journey. They may hope for a sick¬
ness to be cured, for the remission of a mis¬
deed, for a cleansing or even a mystical death and
symbolic rebirth, but whatever happens they
will end their pilgrimage different from when
they began it. Regenerated by an initiatory
journey, having cast off their old selves, they
often celebrate this regeneration in the joyous
explosion of festivities and celebrations that
mark the end of a cycle. Then the time of
remembrance begins.
From the Chinese Journey to the West
(Hiyouji) to Hermann Hesse's Journey to the
East and Lanza del Vasto 's Return to the Source,
literature has by no means exhausted the com¬
memoration or interpretation of pilgrimages.
This may be because pilgrimages obey two con¬
tradictory principles: that of otherness (going to
another place, experiencing a different time,
becoming another person) and repetition
(retracing a sacred route, repeating gestures,
returning to a point of departure . . .). Flesh-and-
blood pilgrims solved that mystery long ago.
When pilgrims reach journey's end they know
they have returned to their true home.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
o
o
cu
"Hail to our Sun father,
colour of fire, and to thee,
our Earth mother, our
beloved who has suffered
so much. We must pray for
those who do not grasp the
meaning of our Earth
mother and who have so
often bloodied her flesh. All
the violence we have
suffered ourselves, the
earth alone can share.
With these opening words
the first "Assembly of the
sages of the Americas"
began its proceedings on
12 March 1994 in
Guatemala. During the ten-
day meeting, held on the
Maya site of Iximche, once
the capital of the
Cakchiquel nation, Maya
priests held traditional
ceremonies around the
sacred fire and reaffirmed
the attachment of their
people to their spiritual,
social and cultural identity.
The meeting ended in the
impressive ruins of the
ancient Maya city of Tikal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
;--- . v
1} M"
^..;r-"; V* . *
: Jû ' ;.t.-fo t .: t- i*f. ' .'I
-J- » ¡ »
m
The thrice-holy city by Annie Laurent
Jerusalem is a magnet for Jewish, Christian and Muslim
pilgrims from all over the world
14
Jerusalem enjoys the unique privilege of
being holy three times over for Jews,
Christians and Muslims.
The Jews learn in the Torah (a Hebrew trans¬
lation of the Greek word "Pentateuch", desig¬
nating the first five books of the Bible) that at the
end of time the Messiah announced by the
prophets will appear on Mount Zion one of
the seven hills of Jerusalem, once the "City of
David" and that all peoples will become one.
In order to be as near to the fulfilment of this
prediction as possible, believing Jews the world
over dream of being buried in the cemetery on
the side of this sacred hill. Until then, it is written
that Jews must remain "a holy nation and a
people of priests", and not merge into other
nations. This is one of the underlying reasons for
the foundation of the state of Israel as both a
temporal and a spiritual kingdom with Jerusalem
as its "eternal" capital.
Christians refer to the Revelation of St. John
the Divine in the New Testament and believe
that the earthly Jerusalem will be transformed
into a heavenly city. Except for the short-lived
"Kingdom of Jerusalem" in the eleventh and
twelfth centuries, which was established after
the city was taken by the Crusaders, Chris¬
tians have never placed the city on a political
footing. They venerate Jerusalem only for its
role in the coming of Christianity and for the
memories associated with this. It is there that
Jesus Christ, the Son of God, took on human
form to redeem the world and experienced the
most painful and the most glorious moments of
his earthly existence, notably the crucifixion
and the resurrection.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
According to Muslim tradition, the faithful
await the coming of Muhammad on the Temple
esplanade, where he will meet Abraham, Moses
and Jesus (in the Qur'an Jesus is only referred to
as a prophet) and pray with them as a harbinger
of the last judgment and the resurrection. But
Jerusalem means something more to Muslims.
As Muhammad's destination on the night of
the mystic journey during which he was carried
to heaven on his mare, it is the third most holy
site in Islam after Mecca and Medina. Because it
is recorded in the Qur'an, this episode is
accepted as an absolute truth: "Glory be to
Him, who carried His servant by night from the
Holy Mosque to the Further Mosque the
precincts of which We have blessed, that We
might show him some of Our signs." (Surah
XVII).
Tens of thousands of faithful pilgrims
belonging to the three major monotheistic reli¬
gions flock to Jerusalem all the year round,
transforming the city into an astonishingly
colourful canvas of human diversity. The effect
is intensified by the fact that the main holy sites
are concentrated in the Old City, a relatively
small area surrounded by four kilometres of
ramparts. The Old City (East Jerusalem) has
four districts (Jewish, Muslim, Christian and
Armenian), and was under Jordanian rule
between 1948, when the state of Israel was cre¬
ated and the first Israelo-Arab war took place,
and 1967, when it was conquered by the Israelis
during the Six-Day War. Since 1967 the Israelis
have controlled the pilgrimage process.
The Wailing Wall
Temple Mount is a site of supreme importance
for the Jews. The famous edifice that protected
the Holy of Holies was rebuilt by Herod I the
Great in 37 B.C. on the ruins of the First Temple
built by Solomon. All that remains of Herod's
temple, which was destroyed by the Roman
legions of Titus in 70 A.D., is a twelve-metre-
high foundation wall familiarly known as the
"Wailing Wall", which the Israelites had sworn
never to abandon.
The dilapidated quarter in which the Wall
stood until 1967 has been torn down and replaced
by a broad paved esplanade. Pious Jews fer¬
vently wish for the Temple to be rebuilt, but
this is impossible since it would mean demol¬
ishing Muslim sanctuaries that have since been
built on the site. A synagogue and a rabbinical
Photos above, from left to
right.
The Wailing Wall (or "Western
Wall") in the Old City of
Jerusalem is a vestige of the
second Temple, built by Herod I
the Great (last century B.C.) on
the site of the Temple of
Solomon. It is the most
important of the Jewish holy
places in Jerusalem.
The Greek Orthodox chapel in
the church of the Holy
Sepulchre, which Is shared by
Christians of various
denominations.
The Dome of the Rock. Built
over a rock considered sacred
by Muslims, this shrine
constructed between 688 and
691 is considered to be the
oldest existing Islamic
monument.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
school have also been built near the foundations
of the Temple.
The Noble Holy Place
The raised platform once occupied by the Jewish
Temple became the Muslims' al-Haram ash-
Sharif ("The Noble Holy Place"). In 636
Jerusalem was captured by Caliph Umar, one of
whose successors, Abd al-Malik, built an octag¬
onal-shaped mosque on the site to house the
rock where Muhammad is reputed to have had
his dream. This is why the building is known as
the "Dome of the Rock". As the French writer
René de Chateaubriand noted in his Itinéraire de
Paris a Jérusalem ("Journey from Paris to
Jerusalem"), only Muslims were allowed access
to the platform, and if the nineteenth-century
French traveler Pierre Loti was privileged to
walk beneath the Dome of the Rock, it was
because he received a special dispensation from
the Pasha of Jerusalem.
Today the "Noble Holy Place" is open to
everyone except on Fridays, the Muslim day of
special congregational prayer, and on Islam's
great feast days (the Mawlid, which commem¬
orates Muhammad's birthday, and the Id-al-
Fitr, which marks the end of Ramadan). The
gatherings do not, however, take place at the
Dome but at the nearby al-Aqsa mosque, which
was built around the same time.
Al-Aqsa draws from all over the East a
growing number of the faithful, who mingle
with the early morning crowds of Palestinians
who ride in from the outlying villages of the
THE ROADS OF FAITH
As part of the World Decade for Cultural Development. Unesco has
launched a "Roads of Faith" project as a tribute to Jerusalem's
international, intercultural and inter-religious importance and to
make the city a centre of peace and understanding among people.
Launched in 1991. the project has acquired new significance
in the light of the peace talks between Israel and the Arab coun¬
tries. Mr. Doudou Diene. Unesco's Director for Intercultural Projects,
notes that it could open up new possibilities for Unesco to con¬
tribute to the peace process through an attempt to rediscover the
network of relationships woven in the past between the three
monotheistic religions.
16
West Bank and Gaza in hired coaches. On most
mornings the atmosphere is fairly relaxed, but on
Fridays it is tense because entrance into the
"Noble Holy Place" is carefully screened by
Israeli soldiers posted in front of the wooden
gate leading into it. Many of the faithful are not
admitted either because they are suspected of
being activists or because there are too many of
them. The excluded have to be content to pray
packed together in the nearby streets.
The Holy Sepulchre
Christian pilgrims flow into Jerusalem during
the main Christian festivals, Easter being the
most popular because of the importance of the
events remembered at that moment in the Chris¬
tian year. Their first destination is the Church of
the Holy Sepulchre which was begun by St.
Helena, the mother of the Emperor Constantine.
This huge, dark building covers Calvary, the
small outcrop where Christ was crucified, and
the tomb fifty paces away where he was buried
and from which he arose on the third day.
Chateaubriand noted that the church, "con¬
sisting of several churches built on uneven
ground and lit by a multitude of lamps, is par¬
ticularly mystical. A darkness reigns there that
fosters piety and inner reflection."
For centuries, the hierarchies of different
denominations have disputed the guardianship
of the Christian holy places. Unable to reach
agreement, they have made ad hoc arrangements
about the occupation of time and space. Fran¬
ciscan "Custodians of the Holy Land" rub
shoulders with Greek and Russian patriarchs,
Coptic and Abyssinian monks from Egypt and
Ethiopia, Maronites and Melchites from
Lebanon, Armenians and Nestorian priests from
Syria and Iraq. To add to this mosaic of Chris¬
tianity are Christians from the English-speaking
world, including Mormons, Anglicans and other
Protestants, who do not actually have any rights
over the holy places but possess a historical,
cultural and liturgical heritage in the Old City
which they jealously protect.
The Way of the Cross, a Good Friday pro¬
cession through narrow streets (the Via
Dolorosa) whose shops remain open, takes place
in an atmosphere of indescribable confusion.
In reaction to such difficulties a growing number
of Christian pilgrims prefer to visit Jerusalem
"out of season" when they can fully benefit
from the silence of the holy places that are so
dear to them.
ANNIE LAURENT
is a French writer and journalist
who specializes in the Middle
East. She Is the author (with
Antoine Basbous) of Guerres
secrètes au Liban ("Secret Wars
in Lebanon") published by
Gallimard, Paris, 1987.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Pathways to enlightenment
by Michael Pye
In Japan some pilgrimages involve a grand tour of almost a
hundred temples. Others take only a few minutes' walk.
Above, a pilgrim pathway lined
with sacred effigies at Tai Ryu
Ji temple at Anan, a city on the
east coast of Shikoku Island
(Tokushima prefecture).
Pilgrimages in Japan usually combine a
serious religious intention with a readi¬
ness to enjoy the journey as an excursion of
recreational value. This has been true at least
since the eighteenth century, when pilgrimage
became popular as one of the reasons for which
ordinary people could get permission to travel.
Since then it has usually been difficult to dis¬
tinguish between the touristic and the religious
aspects of pilgrimage. Or rather, we should say
that it is inappropriate to try. Leisure travel has
often simply been combined with religious
travel, with the more or less integrated pur
pose of maximizing individual and family wel¬
fare. It is therefore small wonder that nowadays
even the rather serious long-distance Buddhist
pilgrimages are performed with the help of a
comfortable coach and pre-booked hotel
accommodation.
In general two types of pilgrimage may be
distinguished in Japan. One is what may be
called "single-site" pilgrimage, that is, a reli¬
gious journey, for special reasons, to one specific
holy place. This is not different in principle
from pilgrimage the world over. The second is
only complete when a number of sites of equal
importance have been visited. In a strict sense
this type of pilgrimage appears to be special to
Japan.
Single-site pilgrimages in Japan arc important
in several religions. Historically significant was
the pilgrimage to Ise Jingu, the great Shinto 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
shrine to the sun-goddess Amaterasu. In the
eighteenth century this was immensely popular
and became something of a mass movement.
Today the visitors to Ise Jingu are again very
numerous, though they are relatively restrained,
being satisfied with a short prayer and a com¬
memorative photograph. The journey itself is
not difficult, though it is a little complicated
from major centres such as Tokyo or Osaka.
Other major Shinto shrines draw their own spe¬
cial public. Izumo is one of several shrines where
prayers for a good marriage are thought to be
specially effective.
Uawn on Mount Ontake
In some cases there is a kind of division of
labour according to region. Inari-sama, a divinity
of commerce, is visited at the Fushimi Inari
Shrine near Kyoto by residents of western Japan
and at Kasama Inari Shrine, north of Tokyo,
by those living on the eastern Kanto Plain. Since
visits to these shrines nevertheless involve con¬
siderable journeys they may be regarded as pil¬
grimages in a general sense. After all, it is usually
possible to say prayers to Inari-sama much
nearer to home, as many business areas or even
individual businesses have their own shrine to
this Shinto god or kami. Pilgrimage is the delib¬
erate traversing of a route to a sacred place
which lies outside one's normal habitat.
Buddhism in Japan is organized in several
different strands or denominations, and in most
cases it is the historic head temple which provides
the natural focus for pilgrimage. Some of these
temples are relatively difficult to reach. The
centre of Shingon Buddhism, for example, was
purposely set up by its founder Kukai on remote
Mount Koya. Nowadays the neighbourhood
can be reached by rail or road and there is a cable
car to master the difficult ascent to the top.
Other Buddhist denominations have cen¬
tres in urban areas. Shin Buddhist believers, for
example, flow regularly to the two great temples
in Kyoto, namely Higashi Honganji and Nishi
Honganji, which are both within walking dis¬
tance of the railway station. Visits to these tem¬
ples are not meant to be arduous. Rather they are
understood as an act of loyal devotion and grat¬
itude, for the believers rely on the saving power
of Amida Buddha rather than on any merit of
their own.
Another famous centre of Buddhist pil¬
grimage, an extensive temple area known as
Zenkoji, is jointly cared for by two Buddhist tra¬
ditions, the Tendai and the Jodo (Pure Land)
denominations. Situated high up at Nagano
City, the temple draws thousands of visitors
every year. Regardless of affiliation, many of
them descend into the dark space beneath the
main hall to circumambulate the huge base of the
Buddhist statue up above. Feeling their way
around the central pillars with their outstretched
right hands, they experience the total darkness
of death before being symbolically reborn when
they finally emerge into the light of day.
Some of the historic pilgrim sites ofJapan are
extremely mysterious and escape denomina¬
tional definition. A fine example of this is Mount
Ontake in Nagano Prefecture, a lightly active
volcano which tops 3,000 metres above sea level.
The local bus service stops well short of the
main part of the mountain, which is not served
by any mechanical transport at all.
Rearing up past the tree-line into the clouds,
the mountain itself is regarded as a kami, and
may therefore be worshipped "from afar", that is,
from a small shrine near the bottom. However,
many groups of religious believers prefer to make
the arduous climb to the top, where a Shinto-style
shrine is perched. This climb consists of a
scramble up a barely made up pathway, much of
which is simply a stream of irregular stones.
The horizontal distance is 3,000 metres, but
over this distance the pilgrim makes a steep
ascent of one thousand metres. A popular
approach is to climb up in the afternoon or
evening, stay overnight in a rough hostel and
worship the rising sun at crack of dawn. Many
of the pilgrims wear white clothing which is
similar to that worn on Buddhist pilgrim routes.
Those who climb Mount Ontake generally share
the idea that the arduousness of the climb, which
is undertaken by many people of quite advanced
age, will create merit and empower the rest of
one's life in a positive way.
The Saikoku 33 and the Shikoku 88
The second major type of pilgrimage in Japan is
the "circulatory" type. This is based on the idea
of visiting in sequence a series of, for example,
thirty-three different temples. The number
thirty-three arises because the compassionate
A pilgrim at prayer in Rei Zan
Ji Temple in the city of Naruto
(Tokushlma prefecture). In
foreground, a rosary and (right)
texts commemorating the
pilgrimage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
bodhisattva Kannon-sama (the equivalent of
Kuan Yin in Chinese and Avalokitesvara in San¬
skrit) is said to have appeared in thirty-three
different forms to bring salvation to living beings
in different states of karma.
The most famous group of thirty-three tem¬
ples dedicated to Kannon-sama is known as the
Saikoku Thirty-three. These are quite widely
spread out in westernJapan and require anything
up to two weeks to visit even using modern
transport. This pilgrimage is almost a thousand
years old and must have taken several weeks to
cover on foot in days gone by.
Imitations of the Saikoku pilgrimage have
been developed all over Japan. Well-known and
popular since the Edo period (1600-1868) are the
Bando pilgrimage, which is spread widely over
the Kanto plain around Tokyo, and the Chichibu
pilgrimage which is much more tightly arranged
around the little city of Chichibu to the north¬
west of Tokyo. Chichibu has thirty-four temples
to Kannon-sama, one more than usual, and this
means that a keen pilgrim may link the Saikoku,
Bando and Chichibu routes to complete a circuit
of one hundred in all.
The other dominant pilgrimage of this
second type is the Shikoku pilgrimage to eighty-
eight temples, Shikoku being Japan's fourth
largest island. At these temples the pilgrim first
visits the main hall, which may be dedicated to
any one of several different buddhas or bod-
hisattvas. A visit is then paid to a secondary
hall of worship devoted to Kobo Daishi, as the
founder of Shingon Buddhism, Kukai, was
posthumously named.
While the various regions of Japan are
known for their famous mountains and special
traditions, Shikoku is identified in people's
minds with this very ancient pilgrimage. It takes
about four weeks to complete visits to all the
temples, using modern transport. Since this is
arduous and costly, a number of much smaller
imitations have been set up.
The message on the pilgrim's straw hat
Some require one day's gentle walking. Others
require the circulation, usually clockwise, of a
series of eighty-eight stones or buddha-images,
each of which stands for one of the Shikoku
temples. This can be done in a few minutes.
Such miniatures are well understood, for the
abbreviation of long and difficult practices has
been an accepted principle of Japanese religion
for centuries. While the famous Buddhist saints
have often been known for their astonishing
ascetic feats, nobody is expected to do more
than they can manage.
In the Buddhist pilgrimages simple actions
are performed at each temple and are usually of
three kinds. First a slip of paper is deposited
which bears the pilgrim's name, address and
age, and states the prayers for which fulfilment
is sought. Such petitions include "safety at
home", "success in business" and "welfare of
ancestors". Second, brief prayer, or recitation of
a sutra a piece of scripture such as the Heart
Pilgrims make their way down
from the summit of Mount
Ontake, a holy place in Nagano
prefecture on Honshu island.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Feeling their way around the main hall of the
temple, the pilgrims experience the total darkness
of death before being symbolically reborn when
they finally emerge into the light of day.
Sutra or the Kannon Sutra is offered. In Shingon
Buddhism a mantra (shingon) a holy name or
word for inward meditation directed towards
the specific Buddha or bodishattva is often
included here. Third, a temple attendant sitting
patiently in a small office is requested to inscribe
the pilgrim's commemorative book, scroll or
shirt with red temple seals and fine calligraphy
in black ink.
This completed memento, for which a small
fee is paid at each temple, will ultimately be
proof that the pilgrimage has been completed as
a whole. It may be deposited at the last temple
as a final act of donation. In the case of a pilgrim's
shirt, an extra one bought for the purpose, it may
also be given to a sick or very old relative in
preparation for their deathbed. This dedication
shows that the pilgrimage mirrors in life our
ultimate passage through death, but in a manner
which opens this up to a Buddhist meaning.
Through pilgrimage, life comes to be under¬
stood as transitory, or as "empty", to use the
word which occurs in the Heart Sutra itself.
Circulatory Buddhist pilgrimage in Japan is
therefore full of different meanings. For some
The Shinto shrine of Fushimi who go round it is little more than a healthy
Inari, near Kyoto, is dedicated
to the goddess of rice.
leisure activity with simple participation in some
of the general forms ofJapanese religion. Trans¬
actions at the temples involve the payment of rel¬
atively small sums of money in exchange for
the expectation of benefits to oneself and one's
family in this life. These are known literally as
"this-worldly benefits" (genzeriyaku). For
others the meaning is more transformational.
Their experience is deepened as they reflect,
during the journey, on family hopes and grati¬
tude to ancestors, on the sequence of life and
death of which they themselves are a part.
In Buddhist understanding the ups and
downs of this life are put in a more relative per¬
spective. If travelling from one place to another
reflects the difficulties and efforts of life, the
completion of the pilgrimage makes the pas¬
sage through death seem possible. Paradoxi¬
cally this message is carried in a four-line verse
which appears on many a pilgrim's conical straw
hat. It runs in translation:
Through ignorance the three worlds are a
prison
Through enlightenment the ten directions
are empty
Originally there is neither east nor west
Where then shall be south and north?
In other words, the difficulty of finding the
pathways to a multitude of goals is a transient
matter indeed. The real goal is enlightenment,
beyond all thoughts of the points of the com¬
pass. Of this the pilgrim's own hat is a con¬
stant reminder.
20
MICHAEL PYE,
professor of religious studies at
Marburg University (Germany), is
a British specialist In Eastern
Asian Buddhism and
contemporary Japanese
religions. Among his published
works are The Macmillan
Dictionary of Religion
(Macmillan, London, 1993) and
Emerging from Meditation
(Duckworth, London, 1990).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
In medieval times
the pilgrimage to
Santiago de
Compostela in
Spain was a major
attraction for
western Christian
Europe
The road to Compostela
by Milien Bravo Lozano
Pilgrims gather in front of the
cathedral of Santiago de
Compostela on 25 July to
celebrate St. James's day.
! "Who can this great and powerful figure
be to whom Christians from both sides of
the Pyrenees throng to address their prayers? So
mighty are the multitudes journeying back and
forth on the road westward that there is hardly
any room to move on it. We have been told that
the person in question was 'St. James, the apostle
of our Lord and Saviour', whose body is buried
in Galicia, and who is venerated as patron and
protector of all the lands of Christendom:
France, England, Italy, Germany and, first and
foremost, Spain.""
Thus wrote the ambassadors of the Emir
Alf ben Yussuf (1 106-1 142), full of wonder as
they took the road leading to Santiago de Com¬
postela in northwestern Spain. ("Santiago" is
the Spanish for St. James). Where had they come
from, these crowds of pilgrims who obstructed
their way? When had this pilgrimage begun?
The pilgrimage to Santiago de Compostela
honours the apostle St. James the Great. The son
of Zebedee (a fisherman on the Sea of Galilee)
and Salome (one of the holy women who habit¬
ually accompanied Jesus), St. James was the 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
brother of St. John, another apostle and a key
figure in the New Testament.
After the death of Christ, St. James preached
the gospel in Palestine until he was beheaded on
the orders of Herod Agrippa I, nephew of the
notorious Herod the Great. He was probably
executed in 44 A.D., thus becoming the first
apostle to be martyred. According to legend, he
also preached in Spain, where his mortal remains
were taken and buried in Galicia.
The mythical Moor-slayer
In 71 1 A.D., a Muslim army from North Africa
landed on the Spanish coast near Gibraltar. The
Visigothic kingdom of Spain was in decline,
and within seven years the entire peninsula had
succumbed to these courageous and well-
trained invaders. For the next eight centuries,
throughout the Middle Ages, the history of
Spain was to be determined by the relation¬
ship between the opposing religious and cultural
powers of Islam and Christianity, a relationship
which was difficult but not always hostile.
St. James was to become the symbolic fig¬
urehead of the "reconquest" of Spain by the
forces of Christianity, and a knowledge of his
mythological role in this struggle is essential to
an understanding of medieval Spain. Known as
Santiago Matamoros ("St. James the slayer of
Moors"), he is traditionally depicted as a warrior
armed with a sword and sitting astride a white
horse.
An opportune discovery in the ninth century
revealed the legendary burial place of St. James
near the town of Iria Flavia, at the westernmost
tip of the Iberian peninsula.
For some time previously, the hermit
Pelagius and the natives of this area had been
troubled by strange and mysterious phenomena.
At night the air would be filled with supernat¬
ural light and the sound of sweet canticles, sung
as if by angels. Bishop Theodemir was informed
of these occurrences, and their source was imme¬
diately identified as a tomb, undoubtedly that of
St. James the Great. When news of this felicitous
discovery reached Alfonso II the Chaste (759-
842), ruler of the small kingdom of Asturias
and León, whose capital was Oviedo, the king
wrote, "... the presence has been revealed to us
of the most precious treasure of the blessed
apostle, namely his sanctified remains. Learning'
of this, my spirit filled with devotion and sup¬
plication, and with my court I immediately hur¬
ried to worship and venerate this precious relic,
and we paid homage with great shedding of
tears and prayers to the patron saint and pro¬
tector of Spain."
The origins and history
of the pilgrimage
In contemporary documents, this discovery is
described as an inventio, in the sense of an
encounter that was so unexpected and marvel¬
lous as to be considered supernatural. The king
made arrangements for a chapel to be erected on
the site of the tomb, and shortly afterwards this
was enlarged and transformed into a basilica.
The town of Santiago de Compostela grew up
around the tomb, which was to become so pow¬
erful a symbol of Christianity in Spain that the
victory of the Christian armies at Clavijo in 844
was attributed to the direct intervention of St.
James. The town was ransacked by Almanzor
STEPS TO KNOWLEDGE
22
The road to Compostela! Its unique influence gave Spain power in the medieval world, bringing back the spiritual richessci¬
ence, literature and artthat first flowed outward across the Pyrenees. It brought a number of illuminated manuscripts to the
south of France, including the Commentary on the Revelation to St. John by the monk Beatus of Llábana, whose strange and mar¬
vellous miniatures inspired the first examples of romanesque sculpture at Cluny, Moissac and Toulouse. It provided a channel
for the spread of the evocative themes of epic literature, taken up and moulded into French form in the Chanson de Roland, which
sings the praises of Charlemagne in his battles against the Moors. It was via pilgrimages that the metre and courtly ideal of Andalu¬
sian lyricism crossed the border into the songs of the troubadours in the French Languedoc, the trouvères and even the Minnesingers,
teaching them the flavour of oriental music.
The road to Compostela! It brought scholars from all over Europe to the school of translation in Toledo. They came from the
hills of Dalmatia, the cities of Italy, the banks of the Elbe, the canals of Bruges and the mists of Scotland, returning home with
Latin translations of the key works of the great philosophers and sages of Islamic Spain, but also of thoseChristian, Muslim
or Jewishwho had made Toledo a respected centre of knowledge to rival the archdeaconry of Segovia, still greatly admired by
men of knowledge.
The road to Compostela! It brought many new things to Spain from Western Europe: romanesque and gothic, the rites and
hierarchy of the Church, Roman institutions and French literature, Italian scholarship and the legal systems of the Bologna School.
Through its thousand pathways plied by pilgrims and villains, noble and rascally individuals, St. James the Great achieved the
most wondrous of miracles: to unite Spain closely with the West
CLAUDIO SÁNCHEZ ALBORNOZ
Españoles ante la Historia (1958, "The Spanish and their History")
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
(Al-Mansur) in 997 and rebuilt in the eleventh
century. The romanesque cathedral was built
between 1075 and 1188.
It is difficult to date precisely the first pil¬
grimages to Compostela. The above account
by Alfonso II is the first written evidence of
such a "pilgrimage", and not long afterwards the
faithful began to arrive in Compostela from all
the provinces of northern Spain, forming a con¬
stant stream of pilgrims which continues to this
day. According to the records, the first pilgrim
from outside Spain was Godescale, Bishop of Le
Puy in France, who travelled with his entourage
to pray at Compostela 100 years after the visit of
Alfonso II.
From this time on, most of the pilgrims were
foreigners. People began to travel from all cor¬
ners of Europe along the old Roman roads, and
very soon specific routes were established and
came to be known as the "road to Santiago".
The tenth, eleventh and twelfth centuries
were undoubtedly the Golden Age of the pil¬
grimage to Compostela, and a long line of dis¬
tinguished figures came to pay their respects
before the Saint's tomb. The pilgrimage of
Charlemagne, however, is probably apocryphal.
Similarly, accounts of a journey by St. Francis
(around 1213) may well be unfounded, although
numerous monasteries along the road to Com¬
postela claim to have been founded by the
"pauper from Assisi".
A long and hazardous journey
The pilgrims generally set off in groups from
their home towns, and their departure was the
occasion for much celebration, with the blessing
of their obligatory apparel: cloak, beggar's
bundle, staff, gourd and wide-brimmed hat. In
the early days, the pilgrims returned home with
a sea-shell to show that they had reached their
goal. In time, this became a distinctive emblem,
and pilgrims would even wear several shells,
earning themselves the nickname "shell-
wearers" from the Galicians.
Those who made the journey to Compostela
left their families, responsibilities and livelihoods
for between six months and two years, and faced
such hazards as sickness, accidents or attacks. It
has been estimated that at certain periods as
many as half of the pilgrims never returned.
Some simply decided to stop and settle down
somewhere on the road, especially once they
had reached Spanish territory. In many of the
towns on the road to Compostela, quarters
sprang up that were populated by foreigners
who had settled there to ply their trades . Most
of these settlers were French, and thus we find
"French quarters" in Pamplona, Burgos, León
and Compostela itself. Sometimes these "one
way" pilgrims would even set up their own towns
called "Villafranca". An anonymous chronicler
of the town of Sahagún described how "as the
King had decided that a town should be con¬
structed there, from all parts of the known uni¬
verse thronged townsfolk of many and various
trades, namely blacksmiths, carpenters, tailors
furriers, cobblers, armourers and learned men
from numerous and diverse provinces and realms,
namely Gascony, Brittany, Germany, England,
Burgundy, Normandy, Toulouse, Provence and
Lombardy, and many other tradesmen con¬
versing in various foreign tongues."
In the course of time, and principally in the
wake of the Reformation, Compostela lost some
of its importance. Nevertheless, a recent resur¬
gence of religious zeal has again peopled the
road to Compostela with thousands of pilgrims
from all over the world.
From a marble column in the main portico of
the cathedral of St. James of Compostela a mag¬
nificent statue by Master Matthew welcomes
pilgrims as they approach the goal of their
journey. According to an age-old tradition, vis¬
itors should place their right hand on the column
as a sign of devotion to obtain the favour of the
Saint. How many millions of hands have
touched this marble column for it to be worn to
a depth of a centimetre and a half?
* Historia Compostellana, written by the canons of the
cathedral of St. James of Compostela, Munio, Hugo and
Girardus (11th century).
A huge incense-burner is
swung during the high mass
held in the cathedral on St.
James's day.
MILLAN BRAVA LOZANO,
a Spanish university teacher and
specialist in Latin philology, is
the founder-director of the
"Centro de estudios del Camino
de Santiago" (The Santiago Way
Study Centre) at Valladolid
(Spain). Among his many
published works are A Practical
Guide for Pilgrims. The Road to
Santiago (Everest publishers,
León, 1994) and The
Unforgettable Pilgrims' Route to
Santiago (with 258 photos,
Everest publishers and The
Santiago Way Study Centre,
1994), which have also
appeared in Spanish, French and
German.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Messengers of light: Chinese Buddhist
pilgrims in India
by Paul Magnin
wmm
Chinese monks embarked on a long and arduous journey
when they sought instruction at the welisprings of Buddhism
24
I When Chinese Buddhist pilgrims set out
* for India on the "Western journey"
the title many of them gave to the record they
kept of their travels they could choose between
three overland routes and a sea-route. Two of the
overland routes passed through central Asia
and corresponded to what since the nineteenth
century has been widely known as the Silk
Road, a portmanteau term used to describe the
east-west trade routes that traversed the region.
After crossing part of the arid Gobi Desert, the
pilgrims had to choose between a northern and
a southern route in order to avoid crossing the
vast basin formed by the swampy regions of
Lobnor, the Tarim Basin and the Taklamakan
desert, which was notorious for its shifting
sands.
The northern route skirted the Celestial
Mountains (Tianshan) whose highest peaks were
some 7,000 metres above sea level. This route
took the pilgrims through staging-points and
oases as far as Kashgar, which controlled access
to the routes leading westwards to Ferghana
and thence to Samarkand or the southwest.
After leaving Kashgar, the pilgrims had to cross'
the Pamir mountains, the steep passes of the
Karakoram range, Gilgit and the high valley of
the Indus, before crossing the Burzil pass (over
4,000 metres high) on the road to what is now
Srinagar, or skirting the Indus gorges and the
Kagan valley to the city now known as Islam¬
abad. Next they travelled through Kashmir into
northern India and the central basin of the
Ganges where most of the great Buddhist sites
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Above, Lake Dal, near
Srinagar, capital of the Indian
state of Jammu and Kashmir. In
background, the rugged slopes
of the Himalayas.
Right, a 10th-century painting
on paper showing the famous
Chinese Buddhist pilgrim,
Huanzang (596-664). The
painting originated from the
Buddhist cave-temples of
Dunhuang, hewn out of the
cliffs in China's Gansu province.
associated with the life of the Buddha and the
first Buddhist communities are situated.
For the sake of simplicity, let us follow each
of the major routes through central Asia by
retracing the steps of a famous Chinese pilgrim:
Huanzang for the northern route, Faxian for the
southern route, and Yijing for the sea route.
Judging by their respective travel diaries, the
principal mission of the three monks was to col¬
lect all the written and oral traditions, canonical
or legendary, which could add to their knowledge
of the Buddha's teachings and Buddhist religious
practices, with a view to their use in China. This
primary concern did not prevent them from
observing the geography, the customs and behav¬
iour of the many kingdoms through which they
passed. Wishing to serve Buddha with the greatest
possible detachment, they also became histo¬
rians, geographers and sociologists.
raxian's fifteen-year journey
Faxian (334-420) made a journey that marked
the high point of the first wave of Chinese pil¬
grims in India. He left China in 399 and returned
in 414. At this time Chinese Buddhists were
searching for their identity. No longer satisfied
with the incomplete and ambiguous texts which
often came into their hands during the first cen¬
turies of the spreading of the "new religion",
they felt a growing need to set out in search of
texts that formed part of the Buddhist canon rec¬
ognized by monks living in the land of the
Buddha's birthplace.
Familiar with all the mysteries of the Bud¬
dhist doctrine, Faxian discovered that the texts
belonging to the monks and faithful scholars
had been scattered and mutilated as a result of
quarrels between the small kingdoms of central
Asia, the inevitable route which ideas circu¬
lating between the West and China had to take.
Most of Faxian's journal, entitled Foguoji ("An
account of Buddhist Kingdoms"), described
Buddhist rituals and ethics as he saw them. He
also interpreted the basic notions of Buddhist
teaching. Most of all Faxian wished to obtain a
complete set of the Buddhist rules of discipline,
or vinayas, which were sorely missing in China
when he began his journey.
Thanks to the efforts of Faxian and other for¬
eign pilgrims and monks who arrived in China
around the same time as he returned there, at
the beginning of the fifth century Chinese monks
had access to vinayas of all the main schools of
Indian Buddhism, to the founding sutras the
Lotus, Vimalakirti and Nirvana sutras and also
to the Amitabha Sutra, the fundamental scripture
of the Pure Land Buddhist faith, and the Perfec¬
tion of Wisdom sutra, from which the whole of
Chinese Buddhism would draw inspiration.
H uanzang, the prodigal monk
Huanzang (596-664), who went to India in 629
by the route running north of the Taklamakan
desert, is the best-known of all Chinese pil¬
grims. His fame is not only due to his great
record of his travels, which has been translated
into several Western languages, but also to Wu
Cheng'en's novel, published around 1570 in the
Ming Dynasty under the title Hiyouji ("Journey
to the West"), which recounted the imaginary
adventures of Huanzang and his strange com¬
panion, the monkey king Sun Wukong.
A native of Henan province, Huanzang took
the vows at a monastery in Luoyang when he
was thirteen years old. Famed for his erudition,
he was extremely aware of the ambiguities and
contradictions in the Buddhist texts used in the
monasteries. To solve the problems involved in
understanding these texts, he decided to go to
India. In 629, without a travel permit from the
Emperor, he left Chang'an by stealth and set out
on the longest route that a pilgrim had hitherto
taken.
Between 635 and 641, Huanzang travelled
through India, visiting all the great Buddhist
sanctuaries and teaching the doctrine of
Mahayana (or "Great Vehicle") Buddhism. In
643, he decided to return to China by way of the
Pamir mountains and the route running south of
the Taklamakan desert. In 645 he arrived at the
gates of Chang'an, the T'ang capital, where he
received a tumultuous welcome from the pop¬
ulation. With him was a twenty-horse caravan
laden with texts, relics and icons destined to
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
While almost a hundred
Chinese Buddhist pilgrims
travelled to India, a number of
Indian masters journeyed in the
opposite direction in order to
spread Buddhism In China. One
of the best known of them was
Bodhidharma (right), who
reached Canton around 526.
Here he Is seen crossing the
Yangtze on a reed.
26
enlighten the minds of his contemporaries and
to increase their faith.
Not only did Emperor Taizong of the Tang
Dynasty forgive Huanzang for having left the
country without a travel permit, he assigned him
a team of collaborators, including the prime min¬
ister and several high officials, with instructions to
translate the mass of Sanskrit Buddhist texts the
pilgrim had brought back. The emperor appointed
him Grand Master of the Temple of Benevolence
(Ci'en si), which was inaugurated in 648, and
organized a magnificent ceremony at court to cel¬
ebrate the event. It was on Huanzang's advice
that the famous Pagoda of the Wild Goose was
built in 652 to house all the Buddhist texts.
An influential figure in the history of Chi¬
nese Buddhism (he was responsible for around a
quarter of all the translations of Sanskrit texts
into Chinese), Huanzang was also the author of an
important book, "Memoirs on the western regions
during the period of the great Tang dynasty",
which presented a wealth of detailed and precise
data about the regions he had visited their phys¬
ical and human geography, their customs and eco¬
nomic life, and the situation of the Buddhist com¬
munities there. Huanzang also bequeathed to the
Chinese the manuscript of a fine metaphysical
and epistemological treatise, Yogacaryabhu-
misastra ("The Lands of the Yoga Masters").
Yijing's passage to India
The third great Chinese pilgrim to India was
Yijing (635-713), who travelled there by boat.
His journal is interesting for other reasons than
those of his eminent predecessors in that he
described the practical rules and institutions of
Buddhist communities not only in India
(although he went no further westward than
Benares), but above all in southeast Asia, part of
which was under the domination of the Sailendra
dynasty based at Srivijaya. It was this dynasty
which produced the magnificent sculptures of
Borobudur in Java.
Yijing recorded all his observations in his
Nanhai jigui neifa zhuan ("Account of Bud¬
dhism, sent from the South Seas"). This book
and his "Memoirs" (see box below) should not
make us forget that Yijing is also credited with
the translation of more than fifty texts and that
he introduced to the Chinese the longest and
most detailed of the codes of discipline, the
vinaya of the Mulasarvastivadin.
Yijing seems to have wanted to clear away
any ambiguities that may have surrounded the
pilgrims' intentions. "We are not looking for
personal gratification," he wrote, "nor are we
asking Heaven for posthumous glory. We have
sworn to sacrifice this body exposed to dan¬
gers in order to search for the victorious doc¬
trine. We all hope to satisfy our passion for
spreading the Light."
Indifferent to honours and high living
though they were, pilgrims still needed basic
provisions. They took with them objects and
PILGRIMS IN PERIL
In the time that elapsed between Faxian and Huanzang, there were pilgrims who passed through
the purple barrier (the Great Wall) and walked on alone; others crossed the great sea and trav¬
elled companionless. Not one of them failed to devote all his thoughts to the sacred vestiges of
the Buddha or to prostrate himself to pay the ritual honours. All were intent on returning to express
their gratitude to their father, their mother, the Tathagata (the Buddha) and their master in the
law by spreading hope.
However the triumphal Way was hedged with difficulties; the holy places were faraway and
vast. For the dozens who grew and flourished, and for several who dared, there was hardly one
who bore fruits and gave real results. And there were few who completed their task!
The real cause was the immensities of the rocky deserts [leading to] the Land of the Elephant
(Buddha and India), the great rivers and the brilliance of the sun which spits out its ardour; or the
mass of water of the waves raised by the makara, a gigantic fish; the enormous gulfs and the waves
which rise and swell up to the sky. Walking alone beyond the Iron Gates [a narrow path bordered
by steep cliffs between Samarkand and Balkh], they travelled among ten thousand mountains and
fell over precipices; navigating alone beyond the Copper Columns [erected by the Chinese Gen¬
eral Ma Yuan in the year 42 at the border of China and the former Tonkin], they crossed the thou¬
sand rivers [an allusion to what are now Thailand and Cambodia] and some lost their lives. Others
had no food for several days or ceased to drink for several mornings.
This is what it means to deny the principle of one's existence, to discard good health
because of pain and weariness. This is why those who left were more than fifty in number; only
a handful of men survived.
YIJING
Da Tang xiyu qiufa gaoseng zhuan (689-692. "Memoirs written at the time of the Great Tang
Dynasty on eminent religious men who went in search of the Law in the countries of the West").
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
food products that could be exchanged en route.
Many received substantial allowances from gen¬
erous donors. Once equipped, they had to be
prepared to face up to many natural hazards, dif¬
ficult situations arising from revolts and wars
between the different regions and kingdoms
through which they traveled, as well as sick¬
ness, which claimed the lives of many of them
and to which the youngest were not always the
most immune. All these difficulties and risks
were well known. The pressures on potential pil¬
grims were so great that some gave up at the last
minute before setting out, while others dropped
out before reaching their destination.
Places of worship and study
Chinese pilgrims stayed in India for a long
period because they had so much to do and so
many sites to visit as they followed in the
Buddha's footsteps. Four holy places held par¬
ticularly strong claims to their veneration.
They visited the Buddha's birthplace, in the
Lumbini Park at Kapilavastu, where the cele¬
bration of his birth took place on the eighth
day of the fourth month. Kapilavastu was also
associated with the memory of the departure of
the future Buddha when he stealthily left his
family in order to seek the Way, an event cele¬
brated on the eighth day of the second month.
The third celebration was held on the 15th of the
first month to venerate "Setting in Motion the
Wheel of the Truth" in the Deer Park, Mgr-
dava, northwest of Benares and now called Sar-
nath. It was there that the Buddha, shortly after
his Enlightenment at Uruvcla under the Bodhi
tree, presented the essence of his experience of
the Four Noble Truths to the five companions
who had followed him in his life as a wandering
ascetic. The fourth event, celebrated on the 15th
of the second month, marked the Buddha's
entry into complete extinction, parinirvana, in
the woods of Sala.
Many Chinese monks also visited Nalanda,
the chief centre for training in monastic life and
the study of Buddhist texts. Yijing gave the Chi¬
nese a detailed description of it and suggested
that they should build an imitation.
When they reached these sites associated
with so many historical and sacred events, the
pilgrims performed all kinds of rituals to express
their veneration. Yijing's own conduct was an
example of what the pilgrims achieved as they
followed in the Buddha's footsteps.
One highly important aspect of the pilgrimage
of Chinese monks to India that should not be for¬
gotten is their quest for instruction by the best
teachers, who could help them to achieve perfect
understanding of the texts of the different schools
of Buddhism. In order to derive as much benefit
as possible from this teaching, many of the pil¬
grims studied Sanskrit so successfully that they
won the acclaim of the Indian monks. After they
had been in India for a time, many Chinese pil¬
grims were invited to preach and expound the
great Buddhist texts in the local language. Kings,
princes and the superiors of large monasteries
organized important ceremonies at which the
pilgrims preached.
The temple at Budd Gaya in
India's Bihar state, one of the
holiest places in Buddhism. It
was there that Gautama
attained enlightenment and
became the Buddha after
meditating beneath a tree.
PAUL MAGNIN,
of France, is a research director
at his country's National Centre
for Scientific Research (CNRS) In
Paris. He is a specialist in
Chinese Buddhism and the
history of Chinese thought and
has published many studies and
articles in these fields.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Pilgrimages in Judaism
by Nicholas de Lange
The ancient Jewish tradition of pilgrimage has survived
many changes
Celebrations at the Wailing
Wall In Jerusalem during
Sukkot, a Jewish autumn
festival also called the Feast of
Tabernacles or Feast of Booths.
Pilgrimage was "a duty laid on Israel".
I This legal obligation (hoq) is stipulated
three times in the Torah, the foundation text of
Judaism: "Three times a year all your males
shall appear before the Lord your God" (Exodus
23,17; Exodus 34, 23; Deuteronomy 16, 16).
The three festive pilgrimages regulated the
year of the Jews living in their land so long as the
temple still stood inJerusalem. They were held at
key moments in the agricultural cycle, at the time
of the three harvests in late spring (the Passover),
midsummer (Pentecost) and early autumn (Taber¬
nacles). Of these pilgrimages the last, falling imme¬
diately after the most solemn moment of the
temple's year, the great expiatory gathering (kippur
or Day of Atonement), came to be considered the
most significant, and it was often known simply
as "the festival" (hag cf. Arabic hajj).
However, although strictly the duty to make
the pilgrimage three times each year had, for
male Jews, the status of adivine commandment,
in practice it was regarded as a non-obligatory
but highly meritorious act. While many Jews
living within relatively easy reach of Jerusalem
made the pilgrimage only occasionally, sources
from the early Roman period describe the holy
city as being thronged at each of the festivals
with countless pilgrims (numbering over a mil¬
lion according to some accounts), many of
whom had come from as far away as Babylonia
28
(Iraq), Persia, Ethiopia, Anatolia and Rome.
This phase of the religious history of the
Jewish people came to an abrupt end in the year
70 of the current era, when the temple was
destroyed by the Roman army. It may seem
extraordinary in retrospect that the Jewish reli¬
gion was able to survive the definitive loss of its
central institution. Presumably the destruction
was not at first perceived as final, and the survival
of Judaism was encouraged by the fact that an
earlier destruction, by the Babylonians in 586
BCE (before the current era), had been fol¬
lowed by the building of a new temple on the
same site some seventy years later. "Our holy
and splendid temple, where our ancestors
praised you, has been burned down, and our
most precious possession is now a ruin". These
ancient words of the prophet Isaiah were now
recited by pilgrims to the site of the destroyed
temple, whose joy was alloyed with bitterness.
Henceforth the dominant mood of the pilgrims
was one of grief and mourning.
I he destruction of the temple
Even more bitterly humiliating was the fact that
access to the holy city was not freely available:
it was now in the hands of alien rulers. Some¬
times the Jews were completely excluded from
the city; even when they were allowed access the
journey was difficult and dangerous, and there
were heavy taxes to pay.
Apparently, despite all the hardships and
humiliations, Jewish pilgrims kept on coming.
After the Arab conquest in 638 conditions
became much easier, and it seems that the num¬
bers of pilgrims increased; some came to settle
in Jerusalem, others just to visit. Those who
were able brought gold for the maintenance of
the Jewish community, for the relief of poverty
and the upkeep of the scholars.
For a long time the history of the Jews in the
Holy Land was shrouded in obscurity. Now,
thanks to the astonishingly rich haul of medieval
documents recovered from the Ben Ezra syna-
gogue in Old Cairo (the so-called Cairo
Genizah) many of the details have been filled in,
and it has become clear that pilgrimage was an
important facet of the religious life of the Jews.
As in temple times, the preferred time of the year
for pilgrimage was the autumn festival, and pil¬
grims came from far and wide: the Genizah
documents mention pilgrims from Khurusan,
Babylon, Egypt, Libya and the Maghrib, from
Byzantium and even from France. Some of them
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A model of the Old City of
Jerusalem as It was at the time
of the Second Temple (centre of
photo).
NICHOLAS DE LANGE,
of the United Kingdom, has been
a Fellow of Wolfson College,
Cambridge since 1985. Notable
among his published works are
Judaism (Oxford University
Press, 1986) and an Atlas of the
Jewish World (Oxford/New York,
1984)
went in fulfilment of a vow made at a time of dis¬
tress. They prayed particularly on the Mount of
Olives, outside the city to the east and facing the
site of the temple; they also prayed at the gates
of the city. At the end of the Festival of Taber¬
nacles, in particular, a great gathering was held
on the Mount of Olives.
The Wailing Wall
Jerusalem retained its sanctity throughout the
centuries, and it received many famous visitors.
Incidentally, it was under Ottoman rule that
the spot which is especially venerated today
acquired its status: the "Wailing Wall", or
western retaining wall of the temple precinct.
The wall itself is ancient, going back to Herod
the Great, a Jewish king who restored and
embellished the temple in the first century BCE;
but according to tradition it was one of the early
Ottoman sultans who cleared the area and
allowed the Jews to pray and lament there.
Though no formal rituals of pilgrimage are asso¬
ciated with it, this relic of the temple still attracts
Jews, both young and old, traditionalist and
more secularized: families come to celebrate the
bar mitzvah, the moment when a boy becomes
a man, and those in anxiety or distress thrust
little notes into crevices in the wall.
In each period of Jewish history the signifi¬
cance of the pilgrimage to Jerusalem has been
different. While the temple still stood, the pil¬
grimage was closely attached to the regular life
and sacrificial worship of that institution, and
to the belief that God was, in a real sense, present
in the building, which was referred to as his
"home". The pilgrim, in addition to offering his
personal devotions and participating in an estab¬
lished communal ritual, was obeying the divine
command to "sec the face of the Lord". After the
destruction of the temple, mourning and "sacred
nostalgia" took over: lamenting the present des¬
olation of the site, seemingly abandoned by God's
presence (the shekhina) "because of our sins", the
pilgrim cast his mind back to the past but also for¬
ward to the end of history, when the ram's horn
would sound out to proclaim the age of the Mes¬
siah, accompanied by the return of the people to
Jerusalem in a resumption of the mass pilgrimage,
the rebuilding of the temple, and the resump¬
tion of sacrifices.
At the present time, there is no doubt that the
vast majority ofJews throughout the world feel
a very strong sentimental attachment to the
Land of Israel and to the city of Jerusalem.
Every year large numbers of Jews visit
Jerusalem, and many of them take the oppor¬
tunity to pray at the Wailing Wall. On the other
hand, the term "pilgrimage" has gone out of
fashion. Indeed, most books about Judaism,
whether descriptive studies or manuals of reli¬
gious practice, omit all mention of pilgrimage or
refer to it briefly in connection with the three
festivals as a ritual belonging to times long past.
The tombs of the prophets
There is another aspect to the subject of pil¬
grimage in Judaism, that leads us even further A _
away from the official and universal forms of the ¿M
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Jewish pilgrims in the old
synagogue at La Ghariba on the
island of Djerba (Tunisia) take
part in the annual celebration
of Lag ba-Omer. The synagogue
attracts pilgrims from many
parts of the world.
religion. Within the holy city the site of the temple
can lay claim to a sanctity that is close to the heart
of millennial Judaism. But elsewhere in the holy
land, and in many countries where Jews have
lived since ancient times, there are lesser holy
places that have long been the object of pilgrimage.
Very often it is a tomb, associated with the name
of a prophet or holy man (occasionally a holy
woman); but sometimes it is a synagogue that is
the object of pilgrimage, and very occasionally a
movable object such as a scroll of the Torah.
Not far south ofJerusalem is the traditional
site of the tombs of Abraham and his family at
Hebron, which is also a Muslim shrine. Legend
holds that four couples are buried there:
Abraham and Sarah, Isaac and Rebecca, Jacob
and Leah, and also the first human couple, Adam
and Eve. Pilgrims to Jerusalem have tended to
include Hebron on their itinerary, and it is reck¬
oned as one of the four "holy cities" (with
Jerusalem, Tiberias and Safcd).
It is in the north of Israel, however, that most
of the holy sites are found. Indeed, parts of eastern
Galilee, particularly around the holy cities of
Tiberias and Safed, are dotted with tombs bearing
the names of the great rabbis of the Talmud.
Of the many Jewish shrines of the Middle
East, some of which are undoubtedly of very
great antiquity, the most famous were tradi¬
tionally the supposed tombs of the prophet
Ezekiel at el-Kifl and of Ezra the Scribe at
Kurna, both in Babylonia (modern Iraq). The
Jews of Iran, who used to frequent these sites,
also have their own shrines, many of which also
carry associations with biblical heroes, notably
Most of the holy sites are found in the north of Israel.
Parts of eastern Galilee, particularly around the holy
cities of Tiberia and Safed, are dotted with tombs bearing
30 the names of the great rabbis of the Talmud.
the tombs of Esther and Mordecai and the
prophet Zechariah at Hamadan, and the prophet
Habbakuk nearby at Tuserkan. The Jews of
Yezd, in response to dreams and vows, attend the
shrine of the prophet Elijah at Nasrabad; other
old shrines, such as the tombs of Daniel at
Shushtar, Isaiah at Isfahan and Zippora near
Qum, and of Abraham Ibn Ezra near Meshd, are
no longer practicable for Jewish pilgrimage.
Egypt once had many sites of local pilgrimage,
as we can see now from the documents of the
Cairo Genizah. Old synagogues were visited,
and by far the most popular sanctuary was the
sanctuary (miqdash) of Dumuh or Dammuh, an
abandoned site on the western bank of the Nile
south of Cairo. Many Genizah documents refer
to the pilgrimage (ziyara) to the "synagogue of
Moses" at Dammuh, particularly after the time of
Moses Maimonides and his son Abraham, who
were particularly concerned with its upkeep.
Besides synagogues and tombs, Egyptian Jews
also venerated ancient scrolls of the Torah (there
was one of these at Dammuh); this practice is
found as far afield as Syria and Morocco.
In conclusion, mention must be made of the
shrines of Morocco, where veneration of saints
is a very marked feature ofJudaism. Their shrines
are dispersed all over the country, mainly in the
Atlas Mountains but also along the coastal plain
and in the eastern regions. A recent study man¬
aged to gather information about no fewer than
571 Moroccan Jewish saints (of whom twenty-
one were women). More remarkable than this is
the fact that many of the sites are traditionally vis¬
ited by both Jewish and Muslim pilgrims; in
some cases Jews visited Muslim marabouts; more
commonly both visit Jewish shrines, or others
where the allegiance of the saint is disputed
between the two religions. With the resettlement
of many Moroccan Jews in Israel, new shrines
have sprung up there, to satisfy the religious
needs and customs of the immigrants.
It would be misleading to leave the topic of
Jewish pilgrimage here, with an impression of
the ubiquity and religious intensity of pilgrimage
rituals. It should be stressed that nowadays
Jewish pilgrimage is more or less confined within
the limits of the Land of Israel and the Muslim
world. As the Muslim countries have recently
been more or less emptied of their Jewish pop¬
ulations, the opportunities for pilgrimage have
been much reduced. (Some shrines, such as the
old synagogue on the island of Djerba in Tunisia,
still manage to attract back some expatriates for
the annual pilgrimage). In Europe, whatever
may have been the situation in earlier times,
pilgrimage is virtually non-existent, and most
European Jews, or Jews of European origin,
would not instinctively associate it with Judaism.
Modernist Jewish theology has tended to insist
that God is not to be understood as "present" in
one place more than in any other, and to reject
any need for the mediation of saints, or any
"superstitious reverence for sacred spots".
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Where the rivers meet by Rustom Bharucha
Ât the confluence of the Ganges and the Jamuna rivers,
millions of Indian pilgrims gather for the Kumbha Mela
festival
Below, massed pilgrims at the
confluence of the Ganges and
Jamuna at Allahabad during the
Kumbha Mela festival in 1989.
At the heart of any pilgrimage in India,
there is a confluence of waters. From the
trickle of underwater springs through the more
steady course of rivers and seas to the vista of the
ocean, pilgrimages derive their sanctity from
their proximity to water, and more specifically
to the mingling of waters. Tirtha the site of a
pilgrimage literally means a "ford" or a
"crossing place".
In the city of Allahabad in northern India, at
the sangam or confluence of the rivers Ganga and
Jamuna, subtly layered by the "invisible" waters
of the mythical river Saraswati, the holy city of
Prayag once stood. To bathe in these waters is said
to be one of the most cherished privileges for any
Hindu regardless of his or her caste, class or
community. More than an opportunity to wash
away sins or to earn merit, this immersion in
the waters offers the richest possibilities of reju¬
venation and self-realization.
Historically, Prayag has been associated with
bathing rituals and ceremonies which over the
centuries have evolved into the Magha Mela, a
religious festival which is celebrated every year
in the month of Magha between January and
February.
Underlying this festival is a myth which
refers to the beginnings of creation when the
gods and the demons were collectively involved
in churning the nectar of immortality from the
ocean. A fight ensued between these two parties
over a pitcher (kumbha) of nectar that emerged
from the primordial waters, along with other
treasures. As the demons chased one of the gods
in possession of the kumbha, we are told that a
few drops of nectar fell on four places in our
world: Hardvar, Ujjain, Nasik and Prayag. These
are the four tirthas in which a great festival
known as the Kumbha Mela takes place once
every three years in rotation over a twelve-year
cycle. Twelve years, we are told, because it took
twelve days for the gods to protect the kumbha
in their cosmic flight, and twelve divine days are
equivalent to twelve earthly years.
31
XL
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
RUSTOM BHARUCHA,
an Indian writer, director and
playwright, lives in Calcutta. He
has written extensively on
indigenous theatres and the
politics of interculturalism. His
most recent publications include
Theatre and the World:
Performance and the Politics of
Culture (Routledge, London,
1993) and The Question of Faith
(Orient Longman, 1993).
The mela or fair held at Prayag (or Tirtharaja
as it is often called, literally king of the tirthas) is
particularly dynamic. Here on the banks of the
Ganga and the Jamuna where the waters have
receded, millions of pilgrims congregate not only
to bathe but to engage in trade, witness religious
performances and dare-devil acts, and listen to
sermons and the sales-pitch of vendors and
mountebanks. This most concentrated of sacred
spaces also accommodates a great celebration of
everyday life, so much so that one is tempted to
view the Kumbha Mela in Prayag as a transcen¬
dence of ordinariness rather than a summation of
the extraordinary. Here we find "India" in all its
multiple dimensions and heterogeneous identities,
where the richest of the rich and the poorest of the
poor can share the same consecrated ground with
an unselfconscious solidarity.
Oacred and profane
Before the first glimmers of dawn, the pilgrims
arrive in droves, entire families and communi¬
ties from the far corners of India with pots and
pans, earthenware stoves, buckets and bedding,
all piled one on top of the other, balanced in pre¬
carious equilibrium. As the pilgrims enter the
camping grounds of the mela, they circumam¬
bulate labyrinths of dusty, triangular, canvas
tents thousands of makeshift edifices silhou¬
etted in an omnipresence of dust. As these chil¬
dren of Ganga move purposefully towards the
confluence of waters they know where they
are going with an almost intuitive knowledge
they become part of a vast sea of humanity
seemingly without beginning or end.
From a distance, you see these eddies of
people moving in circuitous lines (as always in
India, you realize emphatically that lines are
never straight but a continuous series of dots).
As the eddies flow and separate and merge rather
like tributaries in a river, you are almost afraid
to enter their devious currents. But even before
you have completed your thought, you find
yourself wading into the depths where you
become part of a surging humanity in which
strangely and inexplicably you are free to
be yourself.
Despite the rules and regulations enshrined
by the shastras (religious texts) concerning the
rules of pilgrimage fasting, offering ceremonial
rites orpuja, maintaining celibacy and purity of
mind and thought there is always space in this
sacred order for blessings and intimations
received in solitude. No one was more painfully
denied this condition than Mahatma Gandhi
who, on his visit to the Kumbha Mela in
Hardvarin 1915, was so besieged by seekers of
darsan the opportunity to see a holy person
that he found no time for his inner self. No
wonder then that he complained almost like a
foreigner about the oppressiveness of the mela-,
the "absentmindedness, hypocrisy and sloven¬
liness" of the pilgrims, the venal sadhus (holy
men), and the barbarity of such grotesque sights
as a five-legged cow.
If the pilgrimage does not induce an inner
state of being, it can easily become chaos, a
living inferno, or it can degenerate (as it so often
does) into a mere spectacle, a theatrical extrav¬
aganza. As much as one is compelled to respond
to the hyper-reality of the mela the sheer
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
A multitude of meetings with millions of people and
one's self
dynamics of millions of people sharing a specific
place and time the raison d'être of the pil¬
grimage is not to see (as in a spectacle) but to
simply be. The topography and panorama of
Prayag can be dissolved into an inner state of
being. More elusively, it can be concentrated in
the body and being of another pilgrim, who
can be worshipped as a tirtha, as Prayag itself.
A recurring enigma in sacred geography is its
transference of space, so that Prayag is also to be
found in many other tirthas the foothills of the
Himalayas, Benares, a shrine on a street. In
other words, the tirtha is capable of travelling,
not unlike the mela which can filter into
everyday life long after its auspicious time¬
frame has ceased. It is this fluidity that prevents
the mela from being centralized, homogenized,
bureaucratized, despite recent attempts by the
state to regiment its space.
"Before the first glimmers of
dawn, the pilgrims arrive in
droves, entire families and
communities from the far
corners of India." Left, the
Kumbha Mela festival at
Hardvar (Uttar Pradesh).
Above right, purification in the
waters of the Ganges at Nasik
(Maharashtra), one of the four
places where the Kumbha Mela
festival is held. For Hindus, the
Ganges is a sacred river in
which every believer must
bathe at least once in his or her
life.
A Brahman, a member of the
Hindu priestly class, reads the
sacred scriptures on the banks
of the Ganges.
A celebration of life
What needs to be emphasized, however, is that
the mela is not a carnival. Instead of reversing
the existing social order (and thereby rein¬
forcing the status quo), the mela enhances the
existing order and then transcends it. What is
being celebrated in the mela, therefore, is not
anti-structure but the structure of life itself
with all its hierarchies, disparities and distinc¬
tions, which are allowed to coexist on the same
ground. Far from being an officially sanctioned
deviation from the rules of everyday life, it is an
expansion of life's possibilities.
Yet fear infiltrates one's very desire to enter
the time-space of the mela at very bourgeois
levels. One has to rebuke these fears of disease
and theft, go beyond them, almost laugh at the
rumours of stampedes and terrorist attacks that
hang in the air. Melas are anti-bourgeois sites of
experience. They are not for the timorous or
faint-hearted. Even with all the amenities of
"cultural tourism" which have made pilgrimages
more comfortable, the mela challenges bour¬
geois notions of security.
Despite the need to protect the mammoth
environment of the mela in Prayag, the secu¬
rity provided by the police and the military is
increasingly visible there is something faintly
ridiculous in attempting to "discipline" the
tumultuous energies of the pilgrims. Their min¬
gling of social, cultural and human identities
functions on such a vast scale that it is not one
community that is being celebrated, but a mul¬
titude of meetings with millions of people and
one's self. So epic are the contours of the mela
that they are almost impossible to frame; so pri¬
vate is the privilege of immersing one's self in the
waters of Prayag that the moment defies repre¬
sentation. In the harmonious cacophony of this
largest religious gathering in the world the
loudspeakers blare through the night
announcing children lost who will almost invari¬
ably be found there is silence.
One needs to remember the inner myth of
Prayag in order to counter the recent attempts
by fundamentalists and communalist parties to
appropriate its sacred space in the name of Hin-
dutva. The mela, one should keep in mind, has
its own indigenous hierarchies and modes of
socialization that are not likely to accept the
strictures of a new administration advocating a
centralized view of Hinduism. Somehow one is
compelled to accept that the confluence of ener¬
gies, symbolized by the intermingling of the
Ganga, Jamuna and Saraswati, has the power to
absorb any political ideology attempting to rule
in the name of religion.
Centuries of faith cannot be removed
overnight. Or more precisely, the sheer hetero¬
geneity of faiths that have evolved over the years
cannot be reduced to a uniform code of conduct
and belief. Prayag teaches us more than tolerance
or a passive faith in coexistence. From its multi¬
tudinous configurations and interactions, we can
learn the vitality of living with difference. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
'
*c '* ...
Jf >; ' l^
v.J. t -* « *' » .. ~. K
; *.. :* 3
-	99R^ ^^ - - ** * *^^ - 	i la JB^ ' *	. t#< * _** -^^ 	
The heart's infinity
by Abdelwahab Meddeb
The visit to the Kaaba is the crowning moment of
the great pilgrimage to iecca, one of the three
holy cities of Islam. In the mystic tradition it is
identified with the heart. Here a modern pilgrim
describes his innermost feelings.
34
I A mere speck in the crowd, I follow the
* human tide and enter the sacred domain.
The Kaaba looms up, a cube in a black dress with
eye-catching fringes and a headband of callig¬
raphy in gold letters.
It is a great shock. I come closer to the black
Kaaba, making my way through the dense white-
robed crowd that throngs the vast courtyard.
I realize that I am in the spot where sense of
direction disappears. Wherever I was in the
world, from east to west and north to south, I
directed my gaze towards the qibla, the target of'
prayers: here, wherever I stand, the Kaaba is in
plain view, and from every side it makes this
qibla visible. No need to find the right direction:
it is for the pilgrim to make for himself the
square that will receive his prostrate form, and
his prayer will be accepted.
Such is the Kaaba, a black-robed cube peti¬
tioned by requests since ancient times, by a
myriad entreaties renewed down the centuries,
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
"*.''
r* ,**. ig
|i >*., , «1.1*1 «*>.*
*
V
In Mecca (Saudi Arabia),
pilgrims gather round the
Kaaba, the cubical shrine that
stands in the vast courtyard of
the Great Mosque and has the
famous Black Stone of Mecca
embedded in Its masonry. The
Kaaba Is the point towards
which Muslims all over the
world orient themselves to pray.
Wearing sacred garments, the
pilgrims circumambulate the
shrine seven times.
Kight, pilgrims exhausted by
the heat refresh themselves
with a little shade and water.
bombarded by all the world's mihrabs, apses
pointing their blind walls towards it blind,
yet opened by the pilgrims' eyes. O Kaaba, so
ancient and yet daily rejuvenated by the eyes that
converge on you from every side! How many
words in every tongue have saturated your black
dress and nourished your walls and stone foun¬
dations! You are made of stone, you grow out of
the bedrock that is rooted in your foundations,
always adopting a humble posture, only suf¬
fering to be raised up when driven by a will
that is alien to it.
Rabi'a, the great eighth-century woman Sufi,
said: "O Kaaba, idol worshipped on earth, never
has He entered into it, yet never has He left it."
Obsessed by this paradox, I go towards this
cube, which embodies belief in a God at once
present and absent, visible and unportrayable,
palpable and transcendent, near and remote.
This is why His vocation is to be solicited in the
third person, which is how Rabi'a, like all Sufis,
speaks to Him.
I know that by my movement I revive the
myth. Under the burning sun I make my way
through the white throng. I know that I am
ncaring the Temple, the Abode: I am a pilgrim,
I direct my steps towards it. All my energy is
absorbed by such a target.
I draw nearer still. I enter the circles of the
Kaaba. I wish to hurry during the first three
circumambulations, as the ritual prescribes, and
so as to escape the destiny of the marks inscribed
within me, to efface them and to hasten my
entry into a new beginning.
An inner thought sprouts within me, and
directs me towards the solution of the paradox
propounded by the great Rabi'a. The Kaaba
cannot contain Him as much as the human heart.
Faced with this revelation, I exult. Half laughing,
half crying, I feel that I am nearing the cube. On
one side I receive its shade. I honour my cir¬
cumambulations, whilst continuing to hearken
to my inner conversation. The human heart is an
inner temple far greater than the heavens and the
earth. Nothing equals the heart's infinity. The
thoughts that now come to me melt and spread
as they orbit my heart: they are like the people
who circle the Temple with me.
A gold tablet in an unknown script
God deposited a treasure in the Kaaba. The
Prophet wanted to get hold of it and spend it.
Then he repented and left it where it was hidden.
The second caliph, 'Umar, also tried to dig it out,
but turned away from this plan and remained
true to his imitation of the Prophet. This treasure
is still lodged within the Kaaba: I can see tiny
gleams from it. I recall an anecdote told by the
Andalusian theosophist Ibn 'Arabi. When Ibn
'Arabi was in my dear city of Tunis in the year
1201, he received a cracked gold plate out of
this treasure, one finger thick, one span wide and
a little bit longer, containing a script unknown
to him. But Ibn 'Arabi refused to accept this
sample, and asked for it to be put back in its
place. He too wanted to comply with the
Prophet's example, as was fitting. He knew that
it was no accident that the Prophet had decided
not to touch it. He reckoned that if he had used
it, blind sedition would have ravaged the uni¬
verse. Only the Mahdi who was to herald the
end of time could possess it.
Bit by bit the parallel between the Kaaba as
the human heart and as the Throne of God
grows stronger. In this sense the Kaaba is like a
double display screen: on the one hand it dis¬
plays man's interior and everything recorded
or inscribed thereon, on the other the next
world, metaphysical space. The Kaaba represents
this twofold extension into the unseen: it is the
link between the inwardness of the initiate and
the celestial theatre.
It is very hot. The sun holds sway. The white
of the vestments and the marble under foot
make the light more dazzling, more glaring. I am
still circling the Kaaba. I am elated. I think of
what awaits me for my pilgrimage to be com¬
plete and for myself to be born again. I observe
the heroism such a visit demands. And I cannot
repress the image of Hallaj that comes to me
from long ago in the ninth century, when the
martyr-to-be was discovered at Mecca, not far
from the Temple precinct, sitting on a boulder
in full sun, with sweat streaming down him so
that the rock was wet. A witness who saw him
thus noted his proud, heroic emulation of the
Absolute, and predicted to this Sufi the fate that
*1.
ff i ¿n
1
" ^ 1% ^
*W*> '
, * »* T***1
V' ~ >A
t -:WaS*¡F¿
.
-
^m~ ^^^-^^jf, jQ
1 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
I know that I am nearing the Temple, the Abode: I am a
pilgrim, and I direct my steps towards it. All my energy
is absorbed by such a target.
would be his: such a path can lead only to death.
The door of excess unlocks the house of sacri¬
fice. Challenging excess is fatal. I ask myself: am
I going to melt in this sun? No, I am protected
by whiteness, ally of the angelic host.
I want it to be night, not only because night
would provide a respite, a rest, but also because
it would confirm the very name of the Temple.
It was not by a whim that it was named "the
Abode". In order to confirm the correctness of
this name you feel a compelling urge to abide
there by night, to sleep in the sacred precinct, so
as to view the truthful visions on the stage of
your dreams: also so as to be introduced,
through the analogy of sleep, on to that other
stage that creaks under your ghostly feet the
stage of the other world. Should we not be ready
to decipher whatever presents itself to our minds
and feelings through the manifestation of the
occult? Great spiritual experiences have often
come about in pitch darkness. Darkness is
favourable to perception and clairvoyance. The
Prophet's celestial journey, his ascension into the
heavens, his scaling of the ladder all that hap¬
pened by night. It was in the middle of the night
that he was enabled to go to the limits of per¬
ception, to the lotus-tree of the end. It is said also
that God comes down from His throne at night.
Waiting for nightfall
36
ABDELWAHAB MEDDEB,
of Tunisia, is a writer and
associate professor at Yale
University (United States) and at
Geneva University (Switzerland).
Notable among his pbulished
works are Tombeau d'lbn 'Arabi
("The Tomb of Ibn Arabi"; 1990)
and, to accompany his
translation of Suhrawardi's "The
Western Exile's Story", L'Autre
exil ("The Other Exile") with
calligraphy by Hassan Massoudy
(Fata Morgana, Montpellier,
1993).
Waiting for nightfall, I try to perfect my knowl¬
edge of the Temple by following the ritual. I
realize that when I know the Temple I shall
know my true self. How many return journeys
there are between the Temple and the heart!
The stations of the pilgrimage correspond to
the effort to be made on oneself, to introspec¬
tion, to the exercise that probes a person's inner
discourse.
I know that in putting off my clothes I put
off all possessions; in ridding myself of sewn gar¬
ments I disencumber myself. I feel at home in a
setting of simplicity, and turn away from com¬
plexity; I wash and purify myself. To do this I go
into the bath-house: and there I find the dark¬
ness in which mysteries are revealed. There I
achieve the experience of death; I have a
forestaste of the other world: collective nudity
puts me in a sort of rehearsal for the Resurrec¬
tion and the Day of Judgment. In this hot and
humid place I shall from the outset and in
advance have known the two features that struc¬
ture a living person.
Like the ground plan of the Temple, the pil¬
grimage rests on four foundations: circumam-
bulation of the Kaaba, preceded by consecration
(resulting, I repeat, from purification and the
wearing of a white sheet, a living person's
shroud), then the halt at Arafat and the race
between Safa and Marwa.
Kevolve around me!
The halt at Arafat brings perfection of knowl¬
edge (as its name indicates: arafa means "to
know"). The halt is in the profane part: it is
outside the area covered by the domain of the
forbidden. The pilgrimage, in its various stages,
takes place via the dialectic between the sacred
and the profane, between the prolongation of a
prohibition and its cancellation. In this profane
area communal prayer takes place: the pilgrims
find each other in disarray, their hair dishev¬
elled, covered with dust, stripped of all sewn
garments, bare-headed, standing until their heels
are sore, bereft before Him. Their reading will
be secret, internal, whispered: it is spoken from
self to self, in silence, in the crowd, so that He
may speak to each one personally, intimately,
secretly, on the journey of the inner voice,
within.
Between Safa and Marwa I hurry from one
state to another: from sadness (caused by
remorse) to the gift of self. At the bottom of the
valley I go fast, I run, so as to stay as short a time
as possible in this low-lying place, the abode of
Satan. Here, where stone reigns supreme, the
twofold truth of stone is revealed to me: on the
one hand it is from between the stones that the
spring gushes out (and water is the life prin¬
ciple), on the other hand stone is the only being
that always seeks out the low point, i.e. bondage
and refusal to emulate God's plans: Stone does
not rise up of itself, and if it is lifted up an irre¬
sistible force drags it downwards. These two
truths I adopt in the heart's refuge.
With a heart ready for the invention of my
Lord, I shall proceed to the seven circumam-
bulations (on arrival, in the middle of my stay,
and to complete my farewell) for the first three
circuits I shall walk fast; for the last four I shall
go at a normal steady gait. As I circumambulate
I shall liken myself to the barefoot angels that
revolve around the Throne.
I also recall that the Kaaba spoke to Ibn
'Arabi in articulate speech. It said to him:
"Revolve around me!" Centuries later, it repeats
these same words to me. Water from the spring
Zemzem (which gushed out before Hagar and
Ishmael in the middle of the desert) spoke also
to me in audible words. It said to me: "Drink,
slake thy thirst, refresh thyself, take thy fill of my
water!"
I recall to mind the long sequence that made
up the special link between Ibn 'Arabi and the
Kaaba. One cold night with a full moon the
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Sufi got up: beset by a state of great perplexity,
he could not sleep. He made his ablutions and
went out. The night was damp, and the fine
moon was lightly veiled by a sort of curtain of
dew. Ibn 'Arabi made for the precinct, and went
into the courtyard where the Kaaba stands.
Only one person was there, and a strange tension
vibrated in the air; the Sufi felt highly uneasy, and
decided to place himself in the path of the cir-
cumambulations.
Let us strain our ears and listen.
"That night I came down, kissed the Stone
and began to circumambulate. When I was
opposite the drain-pipe, behind the Stone, the
Kaaba lifted its dress, rose up above its base, and
then pushed me away. It would not allow me to
circle around it, and spoke to me in a sharp
voice. I was afraid, nay more: I was seized with
great terror. To take refuge and avoid its aggres¬
siveness, I sheltered behind the stone as behind
a shield, for it was hitting me fierce blows. In the
end it shouted angrily: 'Take one step forward
if thou durst, and thou wilt see what thou wilt
see. So dost thou prefer initiates and famous
men? Dost thou prefer them to me? By God,
never will I allow thee to circle around me!'
"Gradually I lost the fear that had paralysed
me. I calmed down. The Kaaba had torn itself up
from the ground, and had lifted its dress as a
person does when trying to get up from a sitting
position. So it appeared to me. It had lifted its
dress in order to pounce on me. I quickly impro¬
vised some lines of verse, I talked to it, I recited
my celebration, my eulogy. My rhymed, rhyth¬
mical words placated its wrath; my panegyric
made it subside on to its foundations again. It
was happy with the words I heard. It returned
to its place and gave me its trust once more. It
gave me the order to resume my circumambu-
lations.
"Then I threw myself on the Stone and
kissed it again; I was moved, and trembled in all
my limbs. I was dumbfounded, and had to make
a great effort to impart to it the declaration of
Oneness: 'There is no God but God.' These
words came out of my mouth in the form of a
thread. The Black Stone opened like a wardrobe,
and I saw the bottom of it. Its depth measured
one cubit, and my testimony rolled itself up
into a ball and ensconced itself at the bottom of
the Stone, which closed up again. Then the
Kaaba said to me: 'This is a forfeit: I will give it
back to you on the Day of Judgment.' Since
then, peace has been concluded between us."
All this ecstasy, all these hallucinations and
sublimations unfolded in my head, and delighted
me. What pictures, what thoughts taken from
the memory and the corpus of all those who
down the centuries have borne witness and
bequeathed their evidence to posterity, so that
we might have them to enjoy in our beliefs and
unbeliefs!
r ilgrims on Mount Arafat near
Mecca.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY
Unfettered freedom
B Y
I The exercise of the right to
freedom of expression fully
demonstrates the two dimensions
of freedom: the absence of arbi¬
trary power, and the ability to
express oneself.
The first dimension the
absence of despotic pressure or
physical or intellectual coercion
should be seen in terms of the "real
limits of freedom". In this sense,
freedom is the area of autonomy every human being
enjoys within the various kinds of limits structural,
institutional, social, cultural, economic and polit¬
ical that define his or her existence and impose con¬
straints on it.
But it would be wrong to regard freedom as a
negative concept, as an absence of constraints, as
what is left when oppression ceases. Freedom is, or
should be, the capacity to, thepower to do something.
The Spanish thinker Julián Marías summed the
matter up splendidly when he wrote that "true
freedom is not ... an absence of restrictions but a real
opportunity to make projects and to carry out those
projects in one's life. ... In English, the expressions
freedomfrom and freedom to accurately describe these
two aspects of freedom.
In many world regions the breaking of the chains
of tyranny and removal of oppressive structures are not
enough to ensure that citizens fulfil their desire for gen¬
uine freedom and a dignified life. This combination of
freedom and capacity is implicit in the debate about
formal freedom and real freedom. On the threshold of
a new millennium, and after the immense changes of
the past few years, we can more clearly appreciate that
one of the major challenges of the coming century
will be to ensure that it will be really possible for formal
rights to be exercised; in other words that unfettered
freedom will be accompanied by the capacity to make
full and effective use of it.
Perhaps in no other field of human activity is this
truth more obvious than in that of freedom of expres¬
sion, especially freedom of the press. In journalism,
something more than the absence of censorship or
threats is needed if professionals are to do good work.
Material resources and the right social conditions
are also required for the exercise of the right to free
speech.
Above all, the mass media must function inde¬
pendently and objectively; otherwise they will lose the
reason for their existence. Here there is no place for
ambiguities or appearances: facts are the only things
that count. And the context is a highly complex one
in which it is sometimes virtually impossible to see the
pattern of cause and effect. We are talking about
freedom to write and to describe. When we write, we
put our own freedom on the line; when we describe,
other people's freedom is at stake. The reader, the
person at the receiving end, is both a mirror and a ref¬
erence point. The media cannot use technological
and financial reasons as an excuse for consigning to
irrelevance or anonymity the unique protagonist:
the human being, the journalist, the person writing
his or her thoughts or describing an event.
Access to ideas
Even when the mass media succeed in preserving
independent judgment, the latter is not in itself a
guarantee of "objectivity", which is the result of a
complex set of geographical, ideological, historical
and cultural factors. The very act of choosing which
news and opinions are or are not worth publishing is
highly subjective. This can be clearly seen by com¬
paring the space currently devoted to victims of the
war in Bosnia because it is a wound in the very
heart of Europe with the scant coverage being given
to events in Angola and Afghanistan, where the
number of victims may be far higher. Distance and
spectacular events condition editorial choice, which
is not always made on the grounds of what might be
called "global equity", even in the most independent
media. Another example is the attention devoted by
the mass media to two of the major problems of our
time, the Middle East and South Africa.
Freedom, capacity, independence and objectivity
are but a few of the many different issues today at
stake in the world of the press. This complexity is
inextricably linked to the scientific and technological
development of our civilization and to the extension
of civil rights to the great majority of our citizens, in
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
FEDERICO MAYOR
short to democracy. On the one hand, the tools of
transmission are becoming more varied and sophis¬
ticated (from printing to satellite television and infor¬
mation superhighways) as a result of scientific and
technological progress. On the other, the moral con¬
science of our time leads us to attach indisputable
value to the idea that this development should be
shared, that it is only justified if more and more
people benefit from it. We have to be aware that,
alongside the superhighway, there is a "small way", a
"downway" that plays an extremely important part
in shaping the world's awareness of what is hap¬
pening and, above all, why it is happening.
One of the great contradictions of our time is the
fact that, whereas the world's most prosperous regions
are entering the era of interactive television, faxes and
satellite communication, there are still 600,000 villages
without electricity and over 800 million illiterate people
in the world. Our moral sense stimulated by, among
other things, the very development of the mass
media prevents us from becoming resigned to this
monstrous situation. What the French sociologist
Raymond Aron called "the Promethean ambition" of
our time is this very desire to reconcile political free¬
doms with equitable and sustained development that
will provide all citizens with the economic and social
resources necessary for self-fulfilment. Freedom of
expression, like the mass media, cannot be the privilege
of a few: they must be accessible to all.
The Preamble to UNESCO's Constitution states
that the promotion of peace and mutual under¬
standing between peoples calls for "full and equal
opportunities for education for all, in the unrestricted
pursuit of objective truth, and in the free exchange of
ideas and knowledge". For almost half a century
UNESCO has endeavoured to promote those ideals,
convinced that to do so is to build bridges of under¬
standing and solidarity and to help "construct the
defences of peace in the minds of men". Article I of
UNESCO's Constitution refers to communication as
the principal instrument for carrying out this task,
when it says that UNESCO will "promote the free
flow of ideas by word and image". This is a crucial mis¬
sion and a difficult one it was especially so at the time
when we lived in the shadow of two superpowers
and the nuclear arms race. As a result its fulfilment
has been marked by side-tracking, setbacks and mis¬
understandings.
In the 1970s and until the mid-1980s UNESCO, in
the light of the work carried out by the Commis¬
sion chaired by Sean MacBride, discussed the require
ments of what was known as the New World Infor¬
mation and Communication Order. That policy
which some countries thought interventionist and
inimical to freedom led to a full-scale crisis in
UNESCO and was a key factor in the withdrawal, in
1985, of the United States and, shortly afterwards, of
the United Kingdom. UNESCO solved the problem
definitively in 1989 by adopting a "new strategy"
which adheres unreservedly to Article 1. Freedom is
like the sea: neither doors nor fences can withstand it.
There should be no restrictions on freedom. But at the
same time, through an international programme to
develop all aspects of communication (IPDC), action
was taken to develop the capacity to exercise this
freedom to the full.
'Technological minority3
Some of the countries then opposed to UNESCO's pro¬
ject, which they considered to be "interventionist", are
now feeling the impact of violence, including cul¬
tural violence, from the ubiquitous media and are
exploring the possibility that UNESCO could protect
them against "electronic interference" from their
neighbours. I am not only thinking of the Third
World. Some governments in Europe are extremely
anxious about neighbouring countries transmitting
television programmes that offend the feelings of
their inhabitants.
To my mind, a new concept is emerging the con¬
cept of "technological minority". A large country
with hundreds of millions of inhabitants can be a
minority from the technological point of view, if its
space the third frontier can be dominated by
instruments that vehicle, beyond its control, other
ways of living, thinking and behaving, other con¬
cepts and models. The reaction as we have seen in
the case of GATT is usually one of protectionism
a retreat into the fortress instead of openness, com¬
petition, association, interaction and harmony. This
is what happens to all minorities when they forget
that endogamy is synonymous with decline.
Our position has been and will continue to be
that this matter falls strictly within the competence of
national parliaments and that UNESCO as an insti¬
tution belonging to the United Nations system
respects the sovereign decisions concerning it taken by
each state. The "great march towards democracy"
which to my mind is the most important process of our
time is a guarantee that, in the name of the peoples,
measures will gradually be adopted that are best suited
to the diversity and unity of each of them.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The mystery of Persepolis
by Charles-Emmanuel Doxuan
40
Tust as Persepolis had surpassed
other cities in prosperity, so too
it surpassed them in misfor¬
tune!" With these words the Greek his¬
torian Diodorus Siculus commented on
the destruction of the Achaemenid holy
city in 330 B.C., two centuries after its
foundation by Darius the Great. The
fall of Persepolis symbolized the end of
the immense Persian empire that Cyrus
the Great and his successors had carved
out from the Nile to the Indus.
The city fell without a fight to
Alexander the Great's cavalry, who
found there an amazing treasure trove:
40,000 silver talents and such a profu¬
sion of riches that, according the Greek
historian Plutarch, at least 10,000 pairs
of mules and 5,000 camels were needed
to carry them away. Darius III, the last
Achaemenid king, had taken refuge in
Ecbatana after suffering a bloody defeat
at Alexander's hands at Gaugamela,
close by the ruins of the ancient Nin
eveh. At least for the time being Ms forces
presented no serious threat to the con¬
querors. So why did Alexander raze
Persepolis?
Had not Babylon, which had also
opened its gates to the young emperor,
been spared? And at Susa Alexander
had sat on Darius's throne without
spilling a drop of blood. . . .
FIRE AND SWOKD
It is true that Alexander's army had had
to fight a hard battle at the pass of the
Persian Gates, which was defended by
40,000 men under the command of Ari-
obarzanes, the satrap of Persia. Later, as
the troops marched across the plain,
they saw straggling towards them a
raggamuffin band of 800 old Greek pris¬
oners, most of them horribly mutilated.
They had been left with only their
"useful" limbs, i.e. those needed to carry
out the tasks assigned to them. Feelings
had run high in the Greek ranks.
When most of the army joined
Alexander in Persepolis, a council of
war was held at which the conqueror
came out in favour of looting the city
and destroying it. Parmenio, one of his
lieutenants, tried to dissuade him. Why
should he destroy something that now
belonged to him? And why run the risk of
rekindling local resistance by a wanton
act of cruelty? Alexander rejected his
arguments but agreed to spare the royal
buildings. Thus the residential part of
the city was abandoned to the ferocity of
the Greek soldiers. The Roman histo-
rian Quintius Curtius Rufus, author of
The History ofAlexander, tells how the
Persian leaders, dressed in their finest
robes, threw themselves from the tops of
their walls or burned themselves alive in
their houses rather than fall into the
hands of their enemies. Bands of sol¬
diers ran in every direction, slitting the
throats of their prisoners or killing one
another when they fought over the
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Royal residence and spiritual capital of the Persian empire, Persepolis (Takht-e
Jamshid in present-day Iran) came to a tragic end when it ivas destroyed by
Alexander the Great. Excavations on the site, which ivas abandoned for many
centuries, have yielded a mass of information about Achaemenid Persia. Persepolis
was placed on UïiESCO's World Heritage List in 1979,
Above, the Hall of a Hundred
Columns occupies a large part of
the northeastern terrace at
Persepolis.
Above right, the king is shown
fighting a lion in this detail from a
door in the Hall of a Hundred
Columns.
plunder. The carnage lasted several
days.
Persepolis 's misfortunes were not yet
over, however. Back in the city after a
swift expedition against a mountain
people, the Mardi, Alexander decided
to march against the remnants of the
Persian army. Before sending his pha¬
lanxes onto the road to the northwest, he
offered his entourage a magnificent ban¬
quet. It was held on the very spot where
the Great Kings of Persia had enter¬
tained their guests, on the vast stone ter¬
race where stood the palaces and gardens
that had been saved by Parmenio's sup¬
plications. Wine flowed in rivers, and it
was not long before everyone was drunk.
Suddenly Thaïs, an Athenian courtesan
famed for her beauty and quick wit,
began to harangue the crowd, urging
them to burn the palace of Xerxes, who
had once destroyed her native city, and
thus avenge Greece. Her words were
greeted with a roar of approval, and
Alexander, swept along in the general
enthusiasm, grabbed a torch and led the
crowd on its way. The revellers made
their way to all the palaces of the royal
city and, to the sound of flutes and pipes,
set fire to anything that would burn.
It is a moot point whether or not
Alexander really intended to go so far.
Although Plutarch seems to suggest that
an outburst of orgiastic madness took
place, he does not say so categorically.
The historians of antiquity each give
their own version. What is certain is that
on the following day Alexander ordered
the fires to be put out and, when a few
days later the body of Darius was dis¬
covered where he had been left to die
by traitors, ordered that the Persian
leader be buried with due honours.
The flames of a single night did not
destroy the whole of royal Persepolis.
Only the superstructures of the buildings,
mostly made of cedarwood, perished
immediately. What fire began, however, 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
time and neglect concluded. The walls of
Persepolis, like those of Mesopotamian
cities, were of mud brick, and the cen¬
turies eventually got the better of them.
Persepolis (meaning the "city in ruin" in
Greek) sank into oblivion. Its destiny had
been both short-lived and improbable.
A MONUMENTAL BLEND
Darius I, the city's founder, was probably
not of royal blood. His seizure of the
throne marked a break in the dynasty
and was fraught with dangers for his
future reign. In order to highlight the
refoundation of the empire he ordered
two new capitals to be built, one at Susa,
the other at Parsâ, the site of an impor¬
tant temple in the heart of Persis, 80 kilo¬
metres from present-day Shiraz (Iran).
At Parsa, against the side of Kuh-i
Rahmat, the Mount of Mercy, Darius laid
the foundations of a vast terrace 18
metres high, 530 metres long and 330
metres wide, and then began to build on
it. First he built a monumental double
stairway leading up to it, and then, on
another terrace, a grand audience hall
whose cedarwood ceiling was supported
by 36 columns almost 20 metres high.
This state chamber, which could hold
thousands of people, was known as the
Apadana. It opened out onto three por¬
ticoes, one of which looked out over the
plain below. Behind the Apadana Darius
built a smaller palace, the Tachara, which
was used for state banquets. His succes¬
sors, especially his son Xerxes (486-465
B.C.) and his grandson Artaxerxes (465-
424 B.C.) continued the construction
work. Persepolis never entirely ceased
to be a building site. The terrace was
gradually covered by buildings: porti¬
coes, a council hall, and a throne room,
a harem and a treasury. The Achaemenid
kings intended Persepolis to be an archi¬
tectural expression of their greatness.
They brought in workmen and
foremen from all the provinces of their
empire: Achaemenid royal art borrowed
styles from the different peoples under
Persian domination. These influences,
which are clearly visible, produce an
overall effect that is undeniably orig¬
inal. A striking example of this blending
is to be found in the columns which, with
the plant motifs at their base, their tall
shafts and their zoomorphic capitals,
simultaneously recall Egypt, Ionian
42
The Apadana, the royal audience
chamber, was flanked by two
monumental staircases. Above, part
of the eastern staircase, adorned with
magnificent low-relief sculptures. On
the lower retaining wall a lion is
shown fighting a bull in a setting of
cypress-trees. Lines of guards adorn
the upper wall.
Below, a stairway in the Tachara, or
small palace, of Darius I. A combat
between a lion and a bull is depicted
on wall in foreground. The wall beyond
is adorned with carvings of vassals
bearing tribute.
Greece and Assyria, while remaining
typically Persian.
The blend owes much, it is true, to
the personality of the first master-builder.
After Darius, Achaemenid art veered
towards the colossal. At the head of the
great staircase Xerxes built a massive
portal defended by two huge human-
headed bulls. In the recesses of his hall of
a hundred columns, he had himself
depicted as a giant killing equally gigantic
monsters. Artaxerxes, on the other hand,
did not follow his father's example and
opted for greater refinement. This was the
time when Phidias was supervising the
construction of the Parthenon in Athens,
and the flowering of Greek art probably
had an influence in the Great King's
court. The successors ofArtaxerxes, with
the exception of Artaxerxes III, who
added a building to the terrace, simply
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
embellished buildings, that existed
already.
What did Persepolis stand for in the
Persian empire? It was neither a political
capital nor a centre of economic activity.
Nor did it have any great strategic impor¬
tance. The king spent only a small part
of the year there. In autumn and winter
he was usually in residence at Susa; when
the warm weather returned, he and his
retinue went up to Ecbatana. These were
the two cities from which the Achaemenid
sovereigns promulgated their decrees,
dispensed justice and conducted diplo¬
macy. Persepolis became a kind of spir¬
itual capital of Persia.
A SPIRITUAL CAPITAL
Each spring, at the vernal equinox, the
King presided over a great celebration to
mark the New Year, the Noruz. No for¬
eign envoys were ever invited, which
probably explains why neither the fes¬
tival nor the city where it was held are
ever mentioned in western sources. The
perpetuation of an ancient Persian feast,
Noruz was a religious celebration held
under the auspices ofAhura Mazda, the
supreme god of the empire, whose winged
symbol was everywhere to be seen, but it
was also a great political communion to
which the King of Kings invited his sub¬
jects. Everything in Persepolis seems to
have been designed to celebrate Noruz,
and the ruling dynasty visited the city
each year to re-establish its power sym¬
bolically by receiving tribute from the
Persian and Mede nobility and submis¬
sion from the empire's twenty-three
nations. The ceremony ended with a
magnificent banquet at which guests were
offered all kinds of meat, from camel to
ostrich, before leaving with the silver
dishes from which they had eaten.
Today, twenty-five centuries later,
only the barest of bones remain of Perse¬
polis. A strange army of ruins, of empty
door frames and the bases of stone
columns, seems to gaze out over the
immense plain, eternally expectant.
These vestiges provoke speculation, as
they have done for centuries. Since the
1930s, excavations at Persepolis have
yielded a mass of precious data about the
civilization of ancient Persia. But the
city's mystery remains. It is not hard to
imagine Darius emerging from his tomb
in Naqsh-e Rustam a few kilometres
away to review the Immortal Ten Thou¬
sand of his praetorian guard.
CHARLES-EMMANUEL DOXUAN
is a French dramatist and screenwriter with a special
interest in ancient history.
Above, a detail of the eastern staircase of the Apadana showing two groups of tribute-bearers bringing their
countries' finest products to the Persian king. Above, the Babylonians. Below, the Lydlans.
TRIBUTE FIT FOR A KING
On the monumental staircases of the Apadana, the royal audience chamber, splendid bas-reliefs depict a
procession of astonishing diversity.
Delegations of the tributary nations of the vast Persian empire come forward laden with gifts. The Baby¬
lonians are about to offer the King a zebu, fine woollen scarves and beautifully crafted vessels. The
Scythians have brought a stallion, jewels and furs. Here are Cappadocians, and there Cilicians, leading two
magnificent rams.
A royal audience is taking place. The Great King Is on his throne with his golden sceptre in one hand
and a lotus in the other. He is receiving tribute from a figure, apparently a Mede, who is bowing slightly and
kissing his hand to the monarch. This is Oriental proskynesis, a form of homage that provoked great indig¬
nation among the Macedonians when Alexander demanded it from his own men. The crown prince and two
dignitaries stand behind the throne.
It is late in the day. The tribute-bearers are probably in a hurry to join the king's guests who have already
begun to gather in the gardens of the Tachara, the smaller palace. One group can be seen passing in front
of a row of Susan guards. Persians wearing long pleated robes with broad sleeves, and Medes with their
horsemen's cloaks thrown casually over their shoulders, are talking and laughing as they wait to be
admitted. In the background a whole army of servants are at work. Their task is to bring hundreds of chickens,
goats and sheep into the palace.
And here is the king coming out of his audience chamber. His diminutive parasol bearer and fly¬
catcher follow as close behind him as they can.
C-E.D.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Alfonso Reyes
The Latin American intellect
The Mexican miter Alfonso Reyes, a
passionate humanist, historian, poet
and critic, was one of the leading
«Latin American thinkers of the first
half of the twentieth century. He was
among the first intellectuals ofLatin
America to take an active interest in
the International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation. The text
published below consists of extracts
from Reyes' opening address al a
meeting entitled "Europe-Latin
America" that was organized by the
Institute and held in Buenos Aires
from 11 to 16 September 1936. In it
he brilliantly defines the distinctive
nature ofLatin American culture and
its place in the world.
44
Text selected by Edgardo Canton
This is not the place to talk about
Latin American civilization: that
L would lead us off into the field of
archaeology, which is outside our sub¬
ject. To speak of Latin American culture
would be somewhat ambiguous: it would
make us think only of one of the branches
of the European tree, transplanted into
the soil of the Americas. We may, how¬
ever, speak of a Latin American intel¬
lect, its outlook on life and its impact on
Ufe. This will enable us to define, albeit
tentatively, the subtle gradation that is
specifically Latin American.
A DIFFERENT TEMPO
Our drama has a stage, a chorus and a
protagonist.
By stage I mean not a space but
rather a time, in the almost musical sense
of tempo or rhythm. A latecomer at the
banquet of European civilization, Latin
America made up for lost time by cutting
corners, quickening the pace, hurrying
from one form to another without giving
the previous form time enough to
mature. The leap is sometimes a bold
one, and the new form comes out, as it
were, half-baked. Tradition weighed less
heavily, which explains the boldness.
But the question needs to be asked as to
whether the European rhythm, which
we try to follow by making great
strides being incapable of the mea¬
sured steps with which one should prop¬
erly keep up with it is the only histor¬
ical "tempo" possible, and there is
nothing to show that it is unnatural to
speed up the process somewhat. Therein
lies the secret of our history, of our pol¬
itics and of our life, one of the watch¬
words of which is improvisation.
As to the chorus, the Latin American
population is drawn mainly from the old
indigenous elements, the massive influx
of Spanish conquistadors, missionaries
and settlers, and the subsequent immi¬
grations from Europe as a whole. Clashes
between the different bloodlines, prob¬
lems of interbreeding and attempts at
adaptation and absorption have all
ensued. Depending on the region, it is
sometimes the Indian and sometimes the
Iberian element that predominates; the
intermediate colour of the mestizo, the
white of the European immigrants and
the vast patches of African colour intro¬
duced into our land by the former colo¬
nial administrations in centuries gone
by every shade is included. Gradually,
and not without effort, this heteroge¬
neous substance has been absorbed and
mixed in the bowels of Latin America,
and now there already exists a Latin
American humanity characteristic of
this Latin American spirit.
This is where our actor, our protag¬
onist comes in: the intellect.
AMERICANISTS VERSUS
1IISPANTSTS
The Latin American intellect operates
on a series of alternatives. Fifty years
after the Spanish conquest, in other
words as early as the second generation,
a Latin American identity was to be found
in Mexico: under the combined influ¬
ences of the new environment, the dif¬
ferent economic system, the contact with
the Indian sensibility, and the propri¬
etorial instinct originating from the pre¬
vious occupation period, the Mexican
Spaniards developed a colonial-aristo¬
cratic attitude that was at odds with the
arriviste inclinations of the Spaniards
coming straight off the boats. Literary
criticism has picked out as central to this
phenomenon, like a light source, the
person of the Mexican dramatist Juan
Ruiz de Alarcón who, via Corneille, influ¬
enced Molière, and the French theatre of
manners. The same could, however,
apply in varying degrees to any of the
countries of our part of the Americas.
Within this as yet inchoate unease, the
age-long desire of the Americas for inde¬
pendence was already throbbing.
This brings us to the second alterna¬
tive: no sooner had independence been
achieved than the inevitable conflict arose
between the Americanists, who accentu¬
ated the new reality, and the Hispanists,
who accentuated the old tradition.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 48
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
MINING: A CLEAN
BILL OF HEALTH?
by France Bequette
Right, gold
prospectors in a
village on the
island of Mindanao
(Philippines).
O
ur needs for the earth's min¬
eral resources are constantly
increasing, but it is no secret
that mineral extraction can cause
damage to the environment. How
high are these environmental costs?
"The industrial sector," writes
Mostafa K. Tolba, former executive
director of the United Nations Envi¬
ronment Programme, in Saving Our
Planet (1992), "is an important user
of natural resources and is the major
contributor to the world's pollution
loads. The use of metals has
increased over the past two decades,
although regional consumption pat¬
terns vary. The developing countries
have most of the world's proven
reserves of important minerals such
as bauxite, copper, tin, cobalt and
phosphates, but they consume only
about 12 per cent, exporting most
of their production to developed
countries."
In a study written in 1994 for the
Organization for Economic Co-oper¬
ation and Development (OECD)
Alyson Warhurst confirms this
analysis. "Many developing coun¬
tries depend on the production of
minerals to finance their develop¬
ment efforts," she writes. "In cases
such as Zambia, Zaire, Bolivia,
Peru, Chile and Papua New Guinea,
more than 40 per cent of their for¬
eign exchange earnings have come
from mineral exports in recent
years. In other countries including
Zimbabwe, Botswana, Colombia,
Venezuela and to a lesser extent
Brazil, mineral production accounts
for important portions of GNP."
Many industrialized nations are not
far behind. Canada, for example,
is one of the world's major mineral
exporters.
In both the developing and the
industrial countries, the extraction of
this wealth takes a toll. Every stage of
mining and mineral processing
prospecting, building access roads
to the site, ore extraction, smelting
and refining can have harmful
effects on nature. All rock is com¬
posed of minerals, but they are only
described as ores when their con¬
centration is high enough to make
exploitation commercially worth¬
while. Most ores consist of several
different minerals or metals, and in
order to obtain them in pure form
they have to be separated via a series
of physical and chemical processes
that are potentially polluting.
GOLD, MERCURY AND CYANIDE
Even at the exploration stage,
drilling and earth-moving can
damage the environment, but these
operations are usually limited in
scope. Environmental degradation
really begins when a mine starts to
be exploited. Six to eight years usu¬
ally elapse between the discovery of
a lode and its commercial exploita¬
tion. In the meantime roads and
buildings have to be constructed,
wells must be dug and the topsoil
has to be removed. Large-scale exca¬
vation is required. Open-cast mines
cause the greatest damage, pro¬
ducing about eight times more waste
per ton of ore than underground
mines. Although such waste material
may remain chemically inert, it can
block watercourses, cause clouds of
dust and even, if it contains sulphur,
dangerously pollute runoff water.
Animal and plant life, forests, agri¬
culture and recreation areas may
also be damaged.
The State ofCanadas Environ¬
ment (1991) describes how enor¬
mous amounts of rock must be exca¬
vated to obtain a relatively small
amount of minerals or metals: ore
with 2 per cent copper content yields
20 kg of metal per ton of processed
rock. According to another example
cited in the OECD report, in the
United States, in the case of a lower
copper content, about 0.9 per cent,
an estimated 990 million tons of ore
must be mined to obtain 9 million
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
tons of copper. The figures are even
more dramatic for gold mining. A
company in the United States, Gold-
strike, had to excavate 325,000 tons
of ore and waste to produce 50 kg of
gold metal. This gives some idea of
the environmental degradation
caused by this kind of activity.
Because of the volumes involved
and the reagents required to obtain
pure ore, there is good reason to
feel anxious about water quality in
mining regions. Mercury and sodium
cyanide are commonly used in gold
mining, for example. The gold amal¬
gamates with mercury and is then
heated to 300-400°C when the mer¬
cury vaporizes, leaving the gold.
The mercury can be recondensed
for future use, but it can also escape
from jerry-built mining installations
belonging to small-scale prospectors
and turn up in the river mud. Gold
miners frequently move from place
to place and pay little attention to
the environmental impact of what
they do. Mercury not only poses a
direct threat to their health, it also
works its way into the food chain so
that fish from the river are dan¬
gerous to eat. "With an estimated
usage rate of 4 kg of mercury per kg
of gold produced," the OECD report
continues, "the total environmental
loading of mercury from such
sources is roughly 400-500 tons per
year." Two recent case-studies on a
river in Mindanao (Philippines) and
An opencast gold
mine in Serra
Pelada (Brazil).
the Madeira River in the Amazon
region of Brazil have shown that
mercury toxicity in alluvial mud and
fish was six times higher than the
rates accepted by the World Health
Organization. Several cases of acute
mercury poisoning and related
deaths have been reported from
both the Philippines and Brazil.
IT COSTS MORE TO POLLUTE
THAN PROTECT
A humorist once wrote that cities
ought to be built in the countryside.
In much the same vein an economist
recently suggested that the low-
income countries were ready to
accept environmental degradation
in return for industrial expansion.
And surely nobody lives in deserts
and jungles, anyway. It is hard to
46
-FÏ'Mk
Prospecting for
gold in the
highlands of Papua
New Guinea.
share this viewpoint, for the fact is
that jungles and deserts are rarely
uninhabited. As Alyson Warhurst
points out, ". . . mineral projects . . .
due to their remoteness, often
require agricultural and fishery pro¬
jects to be established nearby. Pre¬
cisely by being so remote, communi¬
ties that do suffer environmental
degradation of their resources are
less likely to have it recorded and
less able to respond." And in any
case who would be ready to listen to
their claims? Warhurst cites "the
enforced removal of two aboriginal
communities from their land during
the construction of the North
Queensland (Australia) bauxite strip-
mine at Weipa in the early 1960s,"
and notes that the Bougainville
copper mine in Papua New Guinea
has ravaged vast areas of Nasiosi
and Rorovana farmland and forest.
Contrary to what one might
expect, it costs mining companies
more to pollute than to respect the
environment. First of all because
they can be held responsible for the
harmful effects of their activities on
people. The OECD study cites as a
recent example that of "Colquiri
where the Bolivian State Mining
Company, COMIBOL, was respon¬
sible for both the mine and the wel¬
fare of the mining community.
Through mismanagement it allowed
chemical effluent from the concen¬
tration plant to flow directly into
the natural drainage supplying
water to the community, resulting
in high mortality and illness, par-
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
0 R L D
ticularly amongst infants, the eco¬
nomic burden of which fell on the
company." Moreover, while the dust
and vapour that escape from
smelters are highly toxic and can
contribute to acid rain (an estimated
6 million tons of sulphur dioxide are
released into the atmosphere each
year by the smelting of copper and
other non-ferrous metals), they also
contain valuable metals such as gold,
or expensive reagents such as mer¬
cury and cyanide. Producing
cleanly, i.e. reducing emissions and
recovering metal losses, is not only
environmentally indispensable but
also makes economic good sense.
For many years mines were
opened, worked, then closed and
abandoned as landfill sites. Mostafa
Tolba notes that "Thousands of
landfill sites and surface impound¬
ments used for dumping hazardous
wastes have been found to be unsat¬
isfactory. Corrosive acids, persis¬
tent organic compounds and toxic
metals have accumulated in these
sites for decades. In the Clark Fork
Mining Complex in western Mon¬
tana the largest site identified in
the United States, and considered
the largest hazardous waste dump in
the world ponds of wastes from
copper and silver mining and
smelting activities have been accu¬
mulating for 125 years." Cleaning up
abandoned sites is expensive. The
United States legislation known as
FURTHER READING
Environmental Degradation from
Mining and Mineral Processing
in Developing Countries:
Corporate Responses and
National Policies,
Alyson Warhurst, OECD, 1994
(in English and French).
Saving our Planet, Challenges
and Hopes,
Mostafa K. Tolba, UNEP-Chapman
& Hall, London, 1992
(in English, French and Spanish)
The State of Canada's
Environment,
the Government of Canada,
Ottawa, 1991
(in English and French)
the "Superfund" is based on the
principle that "the polluter pays"
and obliges mining companies to
spend millions of dollars on site
rehabilitation.
The most responsible and
dynamic mining companies in the
North may well be heeding the new
"ecological imperative", but it will
be less easy to apply in the South.
What the South needs, far more
than repressive and virtually unen¬
forceable laws, is technology trans¬
fers, training programmes and the
enhancement of its engineering and
managerial skills. But perhaps the
first step of all should be for the
North to respect the South, espe¬
cially in this field. I
FRANCE
BEQUETTE
is a Franco-
American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
questions.
Large diamond
deposits lie
beneath the Namib
Desert in the
coastal region of
Namibia.
PRETTY BIT DEADLY
Thousands of clumps of densely packed leaves
sporting purple flowersotherwise known as
water hyacinthfloat on the surface of Lake
Victoria, the world's second largest fresh¬
water lake, which lies between Uganda, the
United Republic of Tanzania and Kenya. Water
hyacinth may look beautiful but Its effects
are disastrous. It propagates at an alarming
rate, and Is carpeting the lake with thick green
leaves that prevent boats from plying through
the water or tying up at docks, threatening the
fishing Industry and blocking the pipes of
water treatment plants. Spraying herbicides on
the lake is out of the question, but Beninese
entomologists have discovered a species of
hyacinth-munching beetle, 1,000 of which
have been released experimentally in hyacinth-
infested Lake Kyoga in central Uganda. Results
of the trial will not be known for several
months. Kenya and Tanzania are worried that
the beetles may attack crops. Meanwhile, the
half million Ugandans who depend on fishing
for a livelihood are extremely concerned, as
well as those for whom fish from Lake Victoria
provide their only protein source.
SUNDAY, CHILLY SL^DAY
The scientific journal Nature has recently con¬
firmed what many people knew all along, i.e.
that it is colder on Saturdays and Sundays than
on the other days of the week, in the northern
hemisphere at any rate. Adrian Gordon, a spe¬
cialist at the Flinders Institute for Atmospheric
and Marine Sciences in Adelaide (Australia),
examined data obtained by satellite on global
temperatures from 1979 to 1992 and found
an average spread of four hundredths of a
degree Fahrenheit between Wednesday, the
warmest day of the week, and Sunday, the
coldest. The discrepancy may exist because
at weekends there are fewer cars on the road
and most factories close down.
MAB GOES
MLSHBOOMING
As a result of growing competition for mush¬
rooms in the forests of the Pacific northwest
of the United States by both commercial and
recreational mushroomers, a study on mush¬
rooming funded by UNESCO's Man and the
Biosphere project (MAB) began in the summer
of 1994 on the Olympic Peninsula of Wash¬
ington State, where chanterelle mushrooms
are particularly abundant. Volunteers from
local mushroom societies, supervised by spe¬
cialists from the Forest Sciences Laboratory
in Corvallis (Oregon), are monitoring mush¬
rooms' fruiting times, abundance, grade,
weights and location. They are also noting
relationships between different fungi, the
effects of mushroom picking on nearby vege¬
tation and the impact of human activity on the
ecosystem. The MAB study hopes to develop
some management guidelines for preserving
and enhancing a resource that depends upon
a variety of environmental factors.
O
I-
<
OC
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
ARCHIVES
48
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 44
Sarmiento1 was primarily an Americanist,
Bello2 a Hispanist. This clash has
expressed itself many times in history as a
duel between liberals and conservatives.
Emancipation was so recent that neither
fathers nor sons could easily come to terms
with it. In the fullness of time, all the dif¬
ferent metals melted, as in the great fire of
Corinth, into one flowing stream ofmetal.
Shod with our seven-league boots, we
now come to the third alternative: one of
our poles is in Europe, the other in the
United States. Both influence us and we
draw inspiration from both; but it seems
-that our Latin American intellect encoun¬
ters in Europe a view of the human con¬
dition that is more universal, more essen¬
tial, and more in conformity with its own
sensitivity (which is not to deny our affini¬
ties with the elite of the other America,
and disregarding certain historical mis¬
understandings, for which there is now,
happily, less and less justification and
which are irrelevant here). We dislike
the tendency towards separation of the
races. We do not like to consider a given
human type as a mere curiosity or an
exotic, amusing case, for such a view is
not a basis for genuine spiritual fellow
feeling. The conquistador Cortés himself
pierced the secret of his conquest while
pillowed on the breast of Doña Marina':
it was maybe there that he learned to
love his prey, where other, colder-hearted
commanders, like Caesar in Gaul, were
never able to do so, and began to nurture
in his bosom certain ambitions towards
autonomy that, in the privacy of the
family, he was to pass on to his sons, later
to be tortured for plotting against the
Spanish motherland.
SYNTHESIS AM» ACTION
Such is the stage, such are the chorus
and the protagonist. I have outlined the
main choices open to the latter. I must
now explain what I meant by the watch¬
word of improvisation.
The Latin American intellect is of
necessity less specialized than the Euro¬
pean. Our social structure makes it so.
The writer has more tics, he usually holds
several posts and seldom manages to be
only a writer. He is nearly always a writer
plus something, or some things, else.
There are not, there could not be, any
ivory towers in our part of the world.
This further antithesis of advantages and
disadvantages finds its synthesis, its bal¬
ance, in a particular way of under¬
standing intellectual work as a public
service and a civilizing duty. This con¬
ception fortunately does not rule out the
possibility of interludes, pure literary
self-indulgence, fountains to which one
must frequently return to bathe in the
health-giving waters. In Europe, such
interludes may be the writer's normal
state. It is as if the European writer was
born on the top platform of the Eiffel
Tower: just a few metres' effort and there
he is, lording it on the spiritual summits.
The Latin American writer, on the
other hand, starts fife in the fiery central
regions. By dint of colossal effort,
exhibiting a vitality carried to so high a
pitch as to resemble genius, he barely
manages to raise himself a little above
the earth's crust. I do not believe that
this subtly characteristic feature of Latin
American culture is fraught with any
danger of detachment, quite the con¬
trary. I have a presentiment that the
Latin American intellect is destined for
the noblest complementary function, that
of establishing syntheses, tentative though
they may be and hasty though they may
prove; of putting the outcome of thought
rapidly into practice, testing the value
of theory on the living flesh of action.
SOLLS WITHOUT PASSPORTS
The Latin American spirit yields with
singular pliancy to the purpose of
achieving that magnificent harmony to
which I look forward. The fact is that
our spirit, however deeply rooted it may
be in our soil, is internationalist. This is
not only because our part of the Americas
fulfils all the requirements to be a melting
pot for the future "cosmic race" dreamed
of by Vasconcelos,4 but also because we
have had to fetch our cultural instru¬
ments from the great European centres.
We have grown accustomed to treating
others' concepts as our own business.
This internationalism, inseparable from
our nature and strengthened by the his¬
torical ties of brotherhood that bind us to
so many republics, is the cause of an
undeniable pacifist tendency within the
Latin American intellect.
The generation immediately pre¬
ceding ours still felt that it had been
born in the prison cell of several con¬
centric circles of fatality, experienced
by the most pessimistic members ofthat
generation in the following order.
The first great fatality was of course
that of being human, in accordance with
old Sileno's maxim as recorded by
Calderón: "For the greatest crime/ Of
man is to be born." Inside that first circle
was the second, that of coming too late
into a world too old. The echoes of
romanticism could still be heard, dis¬
tilled by the Cuban poet Juan Clemente
Zenea into two lines: "My time is that of
ancient Rome/And my brothers died with
Greece." In our literary world this sense
of being born at the wrong time domi¬
nated the average mentality.
There was a third circle: in addition
to the misfortune of being human and
living in the modern age, there was the
specific misfortune of being Latin Amer¬
ican, being born on and rooted into a soil
that was not the present seat of civiliza¬
tion but a branch office of the world. To
quote Victoria Ocampo,5 our grandpar¬
ents felt they were in possession of souls
without passports.
Of all these ghosts that are gone with
the wind, that the dawning light of day has
illuminated with a new meaning to the
point of making them at least acceptable
realities, something yet remains in the
nooks and crannies of Latin America,
something that has to be driven out by
flinging wide the windows and by calling
superstition by its name, which is the best
way of exorcising it. In the main, however,
all that has already been put right.
Having laid down these premises and
having examined the case, I shall make
bold to employ the style of a speech for the
defence. Between Spain and ourselves
there has long existed a feeling of levelling
out and of equality. Now, addressing the
court of thinkers of all nations, I say,
acknowledge the rights we have won, as
citizens of the universal homeland. We
have come of age. You can no longer delay
taking account of us. I
1 Domino Faustino Sarmiento (1811-1888),
Argentinian statesman and writer. His works
include Facundo (1845), in which his liking and
regard for the gauchos are evident. Editor
2 Andrés Bello (1781-1865), Chilean writer and
politician of Venezuelan origin. Poet,
philologist, grammarian and critic, he had a
considerable influence throughout Latin
America, where he is regarded as one of the
makers of the region's cultural consciousness.
Editor
3 Marina, also known as Malinalli or Malinche,
an Indian noble of Náhuatl origin who was
Hernán Cortés' consort, counsellor and
interpreter. Editor
4 José Vasconcelos (1822-1959), Mexican
politician, writer and philosopher whose works
include La Raza Cósmica (1925). Editor
5 Victoria Ocampo (1882-1970), Argentinian
woman of letters, founded and directed the
review Sur (1931-1970), contributing to the
dissemination of world literature in her
country. Editor.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
listening
The eye and the ear
by Isabelle Leymarie
: -
Should music be
seen and not
heard?
I Music exists in every society, but the dif-
I ferent worlds of music seem divided
from one another by aesthetic standards, by
behaviour and by rules that are sometimes
antagonistic if not irreconcilable. Because of
these differences people sometimes tend to
make value judgements that are invalid because
they are based on a mistaken understanding of
what music is. The gap between western clas¬
sical music and black music is particularly
wide, and in these two cases perception, exe¬
cution and appreciation seem governed by dif¬
ferent criteria.
All human beingsand every civilization-
give precedence to one sense or combination
of senses in their perception of the world.
Whereas people in the West tend to attach
most importance to the eye, black societies
tend to give priority to the ear, leading to
emphasis on the physical and instinctive. Nicole
Ricaille, a French specialist in ear research,
notes that doctors can save some patients
from deep depression by treating the ear, which
is linked to the parasympathetic nervous
system. At night, while we sleep, the ear
recharges the body like a battery, and disorders
of the ear can lead to loss of energy. Auditory
curves based on tests and indicating the fre¬
quencies we hear and the balance between
our left and right ears can reveal details about
our psychological profile, certain physiological
malfunctions, and even, in some cases, about
our family background. During childhood we
may refuse to hear a scolding parent or an
unpleasant teacher by involuntarily "switching
off" the frequencies that correspond to these
disagreeable voices. These missing frequencies,
which played a protective role in childhood,
may lead in adult life to various kinds of disor¬
ders, even depression and suicidal tenden¬
cies. Nicole Ricaille suggests that in general low
frequencies may correspond to earthiness and
high frequencies to spirituality.
A cerebral approach
The West, which has a high regard for the plastic
arts and the written word (both of which are
eye-oriented), tends to approach music cere-
A traditional dance during a
festival in Cameroon.
brally, through the written score and by assessing
the performance, interpretation or "reading" of
a work in accordance with relatively strict, non-
physical conventions. It also promotes the devel¬
opment of discursive disciplines such as musi-
cology and the sociology and philosophy of music.
With their abundance of graphic symbols, some
contemporary musical scores increasingly
resemble works of visual art, and for some
modern composers the conceptualization of a
piece of music takes precedence over its musical
content and even over its emotional charge. The
West also makes a very strong distinction
between classical music (including religious
music), which is considered "serious", and pop
and folk music, which are not.
It also cuts off music from dance and the
spoken word. These are intermingled in black
societies, which are particularly partial to sung
stories (especially the Cameroonian mvet), sto¬
ries told by dance (the kont of Saint Lucia and 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
' < « '
Suriname), danced and sung sketches (the mum¬
ming of biblical or Shakespearean stories to an
instrumental, danced or sung accompaniment
that is found all over the English-speaking West
Indies) and transitions between spoken lan¬
guage and song (soul music and gospel).
The polyrhythmic body
While the West insists on fidelity to a fixed pat¬
tern, Africa and black America highlight the imag¬
ination and the unexpected in oratory, music
and dance. A West Indian choreographer told me
recently that some classical European dancers
A scene from a Salzburg production of
Rossini's comic opera La scala di seta
{The Silken Ladder, 1812).
with whom he had worked knew their steps by
heart and had impeccable technique but did not
dance with the music. It was, he explained, as if
dance and music were two separate areas and
that the dancers had to superimpose them, to
make one fit with the other.
Dancers to black music do not blindly follow
the beat. By dissociating different parts of
their bodies, they create their own polyrhythms,
rather like a musical instrument (tap dancing is
a famous example of the dancer's rhythmic
creativity). Sometimes, as with the Cuban rumba
brava or the Puerto Rican bomba, they impose
their own rhythms on the drummers, who tailor
their playing to the dancers. Billy Bergman, a
specialist in Caribbean music, writes as fol¬
lows about the Haitian voodoo dance known as
yanvalu: "The tempo, which overlays a slow
beat, gives a false impression of speed. It dic¬
tates a fluid dance in which the feet move fast,
the head slowly and the torso even more slowly.
This polyrhythmic dancing ¡s a key to all Latin-
Caribbean dancing. The dancers in these
regions never try to copy exactly the intrica¬
cies of the tempo. Their movements make their
own counterpoint to the texture of the rhythms.
People unaccustomed to African rhythms often
move their feet wildly to the complex beat of a
talking drum, as if they are in a western and an
outlaw is shooting at their feet. The Haitians, on
the other hand, know that fluid, contrasting
movements are more appropriate."
The ritual surrounding the performance of
western musica raised stage separating the
audience from the musicians, an imposing
baton-wielding conductor "interpreting" the
work, ceremonial clothing (tail coat, evening
gowns), the audience's reverent silence and
immobility during the concert, the salvos of
applause which end ithighlights its separation
from the listeners, who take no physical part in
the music and are not allowed to dance to it or
even externalize their feelings too visibly. This
alienation is accentuated by the glorification of
soloists and the adulation showered on opera
singers, show-biz personalities and classical
dancers, who live in a world beyond the reach
of ordinary mortals, a phenomenon that paral¬
lels the cult of the ego in the West.
(To be continued)
ISABELLE LEYMARIE
is a Franco-American musicologist.
50
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, pages 3, 19: Bertolasi © Anzenberger/Cosmos, Paris. Page 2: © Helen Hawley, United Kingdom Pages 5, 12: Martine Voyeux ©
Métis, Paris. Page 7: Gilles Favier © Vu, Paris. Page 9: © Dagli Orti, Orsay Museum, Paris. Pages 10 (above), 24-25: © Monique Pietri, Paris.
Pages 10 (below), 14, 15, 20: © Charles Lénars, Paris. Page 11: François Perri © Cosmos, Paris. Page 13: Miquel Dewever © Anako, Paris.
Pages 16-17, 18: © Hideo Haga, Tokyo. Page 21: Bruno Barbey © Magnum, Paris. Page 23: Xavier Lambours © Métis, Paris. Pages 25 (below),
26, 27, 31: Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris. Page 28: Mayer © Magnum, Paris. Page 29: © Muñoz de Pablos, Diancey. Page 30: Thomas
Pflaum © Cosmos, Paris. Page 32: © Claude Sauvageot, Paris. Page 33 (above): Ly © Anako, Paris. Page 33 (below): © Béatrice Petit, Brus¬
sels. Pages 34, 35, 37: Abbas © Magnum, Paris. Page 38: UNESCO-Ines Forbes. Pages 40, 41: © Rémi Tournus, Paris. Pages 42 (above), 43:
© Dagli Orti, Paris. Page 42 (below): Mortimer © Rapho, Paris. Page 45: Jean Guy Jules © ANA, Paris. Page 46 (above): M. Macintyre ©
ANA, Paris. Page 46 (below): Arne Hodalic © GLMR Paris. Page 47: Eric Robert © GLMR, Paris. Page 49: Boireau © Rapho, Paris. Page
50: H. Gritschcr © Rapho, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
I
Jeu
Chr
Le r
Con
Le c
en i
LISEZ TOUS LES MOIS
.SKA
RME
AÏDI
OUX
)LVY
ETVDES
Revue d'information, de réflexion et de culture
Jans les numéros de mai et juin 1995
de balance post-communiste Malgorzata Kowa
étiens et musulmans en France Christian Delo
îouveau « monde » Zaki L
îmunication et vérité Daniel Bougn
hristianisme aujourd'hui
Arménie Gérard Chc
Choix de films, Chroniques de théâtre,
Revue des livres, Choix de disques
Le n° : (144 pages) 55 F, étr. 62 F Rédacteur en chef
Abonnement : 1 1 nos / an : 460 F - étr. 560 F Jean-Yves Calvez
Pour recevoir un numéro ou vous abonner, envoyez vos nom,
adresse et règlement à l'ordre d'ETUDES à :
Assas Editions 14, rue d'Assas - 75006 PARIS - Tél. : (1) 44 39 48 48
Ou, sur Minitel, tapez 36 15 SJ* ETUDES
©sus (GmOitas i> «xtupOTtair «aa ¡pàltairuasigis
ALLEZ VERS LE SEIGNEUR
Guide biblique et liturgique de Terre Sainte
par Didier MOUQUE franciscain
Préface de Mgr Jean-Ch. THOMAS, évêque de Versailles
Un ouvrage de 336 pages 110 x 175 - 90 F
Guide spirituel qui fait découvrir par les textes le pays
de Jésus-Christ. Il contient tous les passages bibliques sur
chaque Lieu saint visité : plus besoin sur le terrain de
chercher dans la bible où se trouve une citation. Et toutes
les messes particulières à un pèlerinage y sont incluses.
*
ASSISE ET LES ERMITAGES
SUR LES.PAS DE SAINT FRANÇOIS
par Théophile Desbonnets franciscain, et coll.
Un ouvrage de 160 pages 120 x 210,
avec de nombreux plans et une grande carte - 87 F
Guide spirituel très pratique, destiné aux voyageurs et
pèlerins voulant découvrir en Assise la source d'où saint
François a fait jaillir un esprit nouveau qui attire toujours
les cnurs avides de simplicité, de joie et de paix.
Réductions pour commandes de groupes et pèlerinages
LIS KlMTIONS FRANCISCAIMOS
9, Rue Marie-Rose - 75014 PARIS
Tel : ( 1 ) 45 4« 73 5 1 - 1 ax : ( ! ) 40 44 75 04
390 F
^&*
395 F
173, BD SAINT GERMAIN
75006 PARIS.
TEL: 40 65 75 32.
VENTE EN LIBRAIRIE. CATALOGUE COMPLET SUR DEMANDE. DIFFUSION: AFPU DIFFUSION. DISTRIBUTION:DISTIQUE.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
THEME OF THE NEXT ISSUE
(JUNE 1995):
AIDS: A WORLDWIDE EMERGENCY
INTERVIEW WITH ROMANIAN WRITER
NICOLAE BREBAN
HERITAGE:
SUSAH, THE PEARL OF THE SAHEL
ENVIRONMENT:
TURKEY, LAND OF DIVERSITY
Tb* UNESCO
Courier
The origins ofwriting
INTERVIEW WITH
ERNEST J. GAINES
HERITAGE
QUITO, A CITY
NEAR TO HEAVEN
ENVIRONMENT
OMAN'S GREEN
STRATEGY
, M 1205 !: 22 00 F
ill il
Each month, essential
reading for an
understanding of the
problems of today and
tomorrow
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine published in 30
languages and read by hundreds of thousands of people in 120 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission of furthering "universal
respect for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms...without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
]]>
</page>
</document>
