<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="101488eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW WITH
YEHUDI
iWdUl 17
Ktf'
Unesco prizewinners
GIFT POSTER
THE UNIVERSAL
DECLARATION OF
HUMAN RIGHTS
EIGHT-PAGE SUPPLEMENT
50 YEARS OF UNESCO
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to
all photographs.
^r
*»u
v;
Achilles'
heel
1994, Smoke darkened
Entraigues clay and raku
by Martine Cazin
This group of ceramic
sculptures evoking the
death of Achilles, the
legendary warrior and
leading character in
Homer's Iliad, belongs
to a series entitled
Armures d'argile (clay
armour). During a
recent visit to Japan,
the French painter and
potter Martine Cazin
was fascinated by the
sculptural possibilities
of Japanese armour,
and has since explored
the theme in sculptures
inhabited by "our
ambitions and fears".
"Empty armour," she
writes, "illustrates the
vanity of weapons.'
te
' 'ëê
«
r.
;^m-
E >V
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
CONTENTS
NOVEMBER 1995
a new beginning
46
Interview with
Yehudi Menuhin
35
Greenwatch
Fishfarming:
a 4,000-year-old growth
industry
by France Bequette
-6-
A new beginning by Federico Mayor
-8-
Our common home by Edgar Morin
-li-
The road to 1945 by Chikh Bekri
-14-
Unesco's programme for peace by Ahmed Saleh Sayyad
-17-
Demilitarizing military service by Anne Baer
39
Global view
40
UNESCO IN ACTION
Heritage
The Iguaçu Falls,
cascading wonder of the
subtropical forest
by Edouard Bailby
44
LISTENING
The birth of the blues
by Isabelle Leymarie
50
1995, UNITED NATIONS YEAR
FOR TOLERANCE
The watchful eye of
democracy
by Richard Hoggart
-19-
PEACEMAKERS
HONOURED BY UNESCO
Nelson Mandela by Tahar Ben Jelloun
Frederik Willem de Klerk by Anthony Johnson
The Hague Academy of International Law
Shimon Peres by Charles Enderlin
Yitzhak Rabin by Luc Beyer de Ryke
Yasser Arafat by Lotfi El-Kholy
Jimmy Carter by Flora Lewis
Juan Carlos I by Ramón Luis Acuña
THE UNESCO foURIER
48 th year ^^^
Published monthly In 30 languages and in Braille
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TB£ UNESCO
COURIER
48th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational. Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin. 75732 Pans CEDEX 15. France.
Fax:(331)45.66.92.70
Internet: unesco.cour;er@unesco.org
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tei. 45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15).
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French. Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (Tel. 45.68.47.14)
Artwork Consultant: Eric Frogé
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Moacyr A. Fioravante (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Javaid Iqbal Syed (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: KangWoo-hyon (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: DragomirPetrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Katri Himma (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Sudhasinee Vajrabul (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Voiodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION. Fax: 42.73.24.29
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard. Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel. 45.68.49.19)
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: Daniel Meister (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
lyear: 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
lyear: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be repnnted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the U\esco Courier", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must hear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot t>e returned unless accompa¬
nied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the Uhlsco Courier. Photo
captions and heaalines are written by the c/MESCO Counerstaff. The bound¬
aries on maps published m the magazine do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is pro¬
duced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7 Place de
Fontenoy. 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48100 U.S.A.; 13) NCR. Microcard Edition. Indian Head lite.. Ill
West 40tr Street. New York. U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mansfield
Road. Wooster. Ohio 44591, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - NOVEMBRE 1995
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier do I'Unesco.
Impression: MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z.I. Route d'Étampes. 45331 Maisherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 11-1995-0PI-95-542 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 2-3 and 50-51.
Preamble to
unesco's constitution
The Governments of the States parties to this Con¬
stitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in
the minds of men that the defences of peace must
be constructed;
that ignorance of each other's ways and lives has
been a common cause, throughout the history
of mankind, of that suspicion and mistrust
between the peoples of the world through which
their differences have all too often broken into
war;
that the great and terrible war which has now ended
was a war made possible by the denial of the
democratic principles of the dignity, equality
and mutual respect of men, and by the propaga¬
tion, in their place, through ignorance and prej¬
udice, of the doctrine of the inequality of men
and races; that the wide diffusion of culture, and
the education of humanity for justice and lib¬
erty and peace are indispensable to the dignity
of man and constitute a sacred duty which all
the nations must fulfil in a spirit of mutual
assistance and concern;
that a peace based exclusively upon the political and
economic arrangements of governments would
not be a peace which could secure the unani¬
mous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples
of the world, and that the peace must therefore
be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the intellec¬
tual and moral solidarity of mankind.
For these reasons, the States parties to this Consti¬
tution, believing in full and equal opportuni¬
ties for education for all, in the unrestricted pur¬
suit of objective truth, and in the free exchange
of ideas and knowledge, are agreed and deter¬
mined to develop and to increase the means of
communication between their peoples and to
employ these means for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer and more perfect
knowledge of each other's lives.
In consequence whereof they do hereby create the
United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization for the purpose of
advancing, through the educational and scien¬
tific and cultural relations of the peoples of the
world, the objectives of international peace and
of the common welfare of mankind for which
the United Nations Organization was estab¬
lished and which its Charter proclaims.
Adopted in London on 16 November 1945 and amended by the
General Conference at later sessions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
onth by month
On 16 November 1945, UNESCO's Constitution was signed by forty-one states. It came into
force a year later, on 4 November 1946, after being officially ratified by the first twenty
signatories.
The mission of the new organization was, in a word, to construct the defences of peace
so as to make war redundant. As well as being a matter for international agreements, peace
was to be instilled into people's hearts and minds, into their private and public ambitions
and their daily lives.
This idea had been formulated by Kant in the eighteenth century, but until the immediate
aftermath of the Second World War its expression was compromised by the almost total
supremacy of national self-interest. It was not until 1945, when the world contemplated the
monstrous consequences to which this had led, that the victorious democracies proclaimed
the principle of an intellectual and moral solidarity that included all humanity.
In this respect UNESCO's Constitution broke new ground. It stressed "that a peace
based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not
be a peace which could secure the unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of
the world." A more ambitious kind of peace was called for. States should seek to "develop
and to increase the means of communication between their peoples for the purposes of
mutual understanding".
But another half century was to elapse before any real progress was made on this peace
agenda. It took timethe years between 1945 and 1989for the East-West confrontation
between communism and capitalism to come to an end, and for the colonized peoples to
attain political sovereignty and full membership of the international community.
The world scene has been transformed. The inegalitarian integration of economies and
capital movements in a single market and the aggressive unification of technological stan¬
dards and media networks have led to the development of paradoxical and explosive situa¬
tions: growing cultural standardization at the same time as the exacerbation of tribal,
ethnic and confessional reflexes; the rise of democratic ideals as well as the recrudescence of
despotism.
In this general climate of instability in which countries large and small are tempted by
introspection and isolationism, the struggle for peace is a far less straightforward process
than it was. New dangers have appeared, but so too have new hopes.
The prospect of a global nuclear conflagration has receded. But while the threat of war
has become less intensive it has become more extensive, in the form of internal conflicts
within regions, countries, cities and even neighbourhoods. The great powers are less and less
inclined to take action outside their own turf, but while this may encourage adventurism by
petty local tyrants it may also foster self-expression on the part of peoples which are now
freed from tutelage, as well as experiments in democracy and the invention of many new
approaches to peace.
In such an open-ended context, the initiative of inspired and courageous leaders may
bring an end injust situations that have existed for centuries. The imagination and civic
spirit of private citizens now count for much more than they did. Many things that once
seemed inevitable, including war, have ceased to be so.
The world outlook has radically changed, bringing new fears and new promises. It is
time for a new departure on the road to peace.
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A new beginning
by Federico Mayor
FEDERICO MAYOR
is Director-General of Unesco.
For many years world events moved slowly
because the two super-powers took all the
decisions, and it seemed that the rest of the
world had been side-tracked away from deci¬
sion-making. Now, suddenly, we realize that
we are facing new threats for which we are
unprepared overpopulation, poverty, intol¬
erance, the knowledge gap and the inability of
different ethnic groups and cultures to live
together.
The Secretary-General of the United
Nations recently offered some ideas for con¬
sideration in his Agenda for Peace. The
Agenda for Peace has two main facets: peace¬
keeping and peace-building.
PEACE-KEEPING AND
PEACE-BUILDING
Peace-keeping is at the very core of the UN
mandate. It is implemented by the Security
Council. Peace-building, on the other hand,
is a more complex and long-term preventive
activity to which all UN institutions and spe¬
cialized agencies must contribute. We are
sometimes successful at peace-keeping, but
as yet we arc unprepared for peace-building.
We are used to relying on force, and our
budgets make provisions for the armed forces
and their weaponry. Our war machines exist
because we think that the hawkish inclinations
of others can only be discouraged by our own
capacity for destruction.
Some of today's peace-keeping operations
require an investment of 1.5 billion dollars.
Meanwhile, it is impossible to raise even 30
million dollars for peace-building operations
because the latter do not yet fit into our order
of priorities and therefore do not form part of
our budgets.
This is not a new situation. To take one
example, we are willing to provide 526 million
dollars in food aid to fight the effects of
drought in Africa, but all this money remains
in the North because that is where the indus¬
tries that provide the food are located and so
are the aircraft and ships that transfer it. But
when we ask for a million dollars for endoge¬
nous capacity-building, to provide stricken
countries with intensive learning pro¬
grammes so that they can be better prepared
for future droughts, we get a flat refusal.
Why? Because we are not ready to provide
that kind of peace-building operation.
Peace-building means taking preventive
action. Not only must we be prepared to act
when a conflict has broken out; we must also
be able to detect warning signals early enough
to nip conflicts in the bud. Just as we have
smoke detectors in buildings, so we should
have an early-warning system that would
enable us to act in time, before conflagrations
occur.
The problem is that preventive activities
attract neither recognition nor thanks. If a
conflict does not break out, nobody is going
to congratulate you for having prevented it.
The same thing happens in medicine. If you
prevent an epidemic or stop a disease from
spreading, parents are not going to come
along and thank you for protecting their chil¬
dren, for the simple reason that there has
been no outbreak of disease. If a surgeon
removes a tumour, the operation is
applauded as an achievement of modern
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
medicine. But if you manage to avoid surgery,
no one will congratulate you. Decorations go
to generals who win minor battles, not to
those who avoid major wars. Preventive
action produces intangible results; and we
have not yet learned to invest in intangibles.
We are only used to tangible results that
can be splashed across newspapers or televi¬
sion screens. If nothing happens and this is
exactly what we want no one will accept
that we are in any way responsible. We must
be prepared to use the media to inform
public opinion about how important it is to
take preventive- measures to stop problems
from degenerating into conflict. In other
words to establish peace in hearts and minds.
In culture.
EVERYBODY'S BUSINESS
With the growing power of civil society, the
situation has rarely been more propitious.
Every action, even the most trivial, counts.
Creating a culture of peace is now every¬
body's business. Peace can no longer be
regarded as an agreement between the pow¬
erful, as a state of grace that sometimes
descends on a lucky country. It is a social
condition to which every citizen can con¬
tribute at every moment.
It would of course be ridiculous to deny
that this condition depends largely on deci¬
sions that only politicians can take. But the
opportunities for individual and collective
action on behalf of peace are certainly greater
than is usually thought. The cause of peace
must be defended in everyday life at home,
at school, in the workplace, in parliaments
and cafés. Independent actions can interact
and strengthen one another. In this way we
shall gradually move from a culture condi¬
tioned by centuries of war to a culture
existing in the name of peace.
The supreme expression of a society's cul¬
ture is the behaviour of its members in their
everyday lives. The framework of justice,
dignity, equality and solidarity which is what I
mean by the term "culture of peace" will be
built, day in day out, by way of such behav¬
iour, at last free from all interference and con¬
straint.
Constructing
the defences of
peace is not an
exercise in damage
limitation but a
preventive effort
to which every
citizen can
contribute
Left, The dream of an angel,
by 8-year-old Gao Yan (China).
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Our common home
by Edgar Morin
We should abandon the Promethean dream of
dominating the universe and aspire instead to live
together on earth
The preamble to UNESCO's Constitution makes
the correct diagnosis that, "since wars begin in
the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that
the defences of peace must be constructed".
Today, although the illusions and enthusi¬
asms of 1945 are gone, we are again confronted,
in an acute form, with the same fundamental
problems that led to the establishment of
UNESCO, the problems of peace and war, the
problems of material, technological and eco¬
nomic underdevelopment facing the countries
of the South and the East and the problem of
psychological, moral and intellectual underde¬
velopment, which is universal.
As we look back over our millennium, the
three questions raised by Kant two centuries ago
come again to mind: "What can I know? What
must I do? What can I hope for?"
A WORLD IN DISARRAY
The planet is in turmoil: the crisis of progress
affects all of mankind, everywhere creating dis¬
array, causing old bonds to break and communi¬
ties to turn in upon themselves; the fires of war
are again being stoked; and the world is losing
hold of the global outlook and the sense of the
common good. Faith in science, technology and
industry is everywhere running up against the
problems that science, technology and industry
are themselves causing. Science is not only a
source of enlightenment, it is itself blind as to
where the scientific adventure is leading, an
adventure that is slipping beyond its control and
beyond the reach of its conscience. Like the bib¬
lical tree of life, science is a tree of knowledge
whose fruit contains both good and evil.
The vast apparatus we call science and tech¬
nology produces not only knowledge and
insight but also ignorance and blindness.
Progress in the various branches of science has
produced advantages arising from the division
8
of labour but also the drawbacks of over-spe¬
cialization, compartmentalization and the frag¬
mentation of knowledge.
With so many dramatically interrelated
problems, the world would seem to be not just
in crisis but on its last legs, in that violent condi¬
tion where the forces of death grapple with
those of life. Despite all our common interests,
we are still one another's enemies, and the
unleashing of racial, religious and ideological
antagonisms continues to generate wars, mas¬
sacres, torture, and humiliation. Humanity
cannot overcome man's inhumanity to man.
What we do not know yet is whether this is
merely the death rattle of an old world,
heralding a new birth, or whether these are
really the world's death throes.
We had already lost sight of the principles
that anchored us in the past; now we have lost
sight of the certainties that guided our steps into
the future. There is no law of history that auto¬
matically guarantees progress.
We are simultaneously experiencing the crisis
of the past, the crisis of the future, and the crisis
of transition. Contained within these crises are
the crisis of development and the crisis of our era
of planet-wide consciousness, comprising such
increasingly grave problems as the urbanization
of the world, economic and demographic dis¬
order, lack of progress or reverses in the devel¬
opment of democracy, and the uncontrolled
onward march of science and technology.
Inherent in all this is the danger that civilization
will become homogenized and cultural diversity
will be destroyed, a risk inseparable from the
equal and opposite danger that the nations will
split up into small, conflicting communities, ren¬
dering a shared human civilization impossible.
Our planet is indeed, in keeping with the
etymology of the word, a "wandering star". We
are embarked upon a great adventure into the
unknown.
LIVING TOGETHER
ON EARTH
The earth itself has lost its old familiar universe:
the sun has shrunk to the size of a Lilliputian star
among billions of others in an expanding uni-
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
verse; the earth is lost in the cosmos, its surface
a small, tepid patch of living mould in a glacial
expanse where stars and black holes devour one
another with incredible violence. As far as we
know at present, this small planet is the only
place where life and consciousness exist. It is
the common home of all human beings. We
need to acknowledge our consubstantial link
with it, relinquish the Promethean dream of
becoming masters of the universe and aspire
instead to living together on earth.
Instead of seeing "the universal" and our
various "homelands" as opposites, we should
link our homelands family, region, nation
into a concentric pattern and integrate them
into the concrete reality of our earthly home¬
land. We must stop contrasting a radiant future
with a past of servitude and superstition. All
cultures have their own virtues, their own store
of experience and their own wisdom, as well as
their shortcomings and areas of ignorance. It is
in its past that a community finds the energy to
confront its present and prepare for its future.
Since all humans are children of life and of the
earth, "rootless cosmopolitanism", which is
something abstract, must be discarded in favour
of "carthling cosmopolitanism", citizenship of
our extraordinary little planet. The re-establish¬
ment of ethnic or national roots is justifiable as
long as it goes hand-in-hand with a deeper re-
rooting in our human identity as citizens of earth.
The distinguishing feature of mankind is
unitas multiplex, unity in diversity, the genetic,
cerebral, intellectual and affective unity of our
species, whose numberless potentialities find
expression through the diversity of cultures.
Diversity is the jewel in the crown of human
unity and, conversely, unity is the jewel in the
crown of human diversity.
Just as living, ongoing communication
needs to be established between past, present
and future, so living, ongoing communication
needs to be established between distinctive cul¬
tural, ethnic and national characteristics on the
one hand, and, on the other, the concrete reality
of one world, the homeland of all humanity.
CIVILIZING THE EARTH
And so we must civilize the earth. This means not
only creating a confederation of humanity, while
respecting existing cultures and homelands, but
also promoting democracy and solidarity.
Democracy presupposes and also fosters
Love, by 11-year-old Nadia El
Saqed (Egypt).
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
diversity of social interests and groups and diver¬
sity of ideas. In other words it must not only
cause the will of the majority to prevail but it
must also acknowledge the right of minorities
and protest movements to exist and express
themselves, and allow heretical and deviationist
ideas to be expressed. It requires consensus
about respect for democratic institutions and
rules, but also needs conflicts of ideas and opin¬
ions to make it lively and fruitful. Conflicts can,
however, only fulfil that function if they comply
with the democratic rules of conduct, which
keep antagonisms in check by substituting the
combat of ideas for physical combat and which
decide the provisional victor among the contes¬
tants by means of debates and elections.
As to solidarity, a society cannot increase in
complexity without an accompanying increase
in solidarity, since more complexity means
more freedoms, more opportunities for initia¬
tive and more possibilities of disorder, which
can be both fruitful and destructive. Carried to
extremes, disorder ceases to be fruitful and
becomes mainly destructive; carried to
extremes, complexity deteriorates into disinte¬
gration, the breakdown of a whole into its con¬
stituent parts. The cohesion of the whole can, of
course, be maintained by reverting to coercion,
but to the detriment of complexity; an integra¬
tive solution conducive to complexity can only
be achieved by developing true solidarity, a sol¬
idarity that is not imposed upon people but that
they feel within themselves and experience as
fraternity. What is valid for any homeland, is
now valid for the whole human community.
This brings us to the problem of reforming
our thinking and of rethinking education.
Awareness of all these issues can only be
achieved when our thinking is capable of recon¬
necting concepts that have become discon¬
nected and areas of knowledge that have been
compartmentalized. The new areas of knowl¬
edge whereby we discover the place in the
cosmos of the earth as humanity's homeland are
meaningless as long as they remain separated
from one another. The earth is not the sum of
the planet, the biosphere and humanity. It is a
complex physical, biological and anthropolog¬
ical totality wherein life springs forth from the
history of the planet and humanity springs forth
from the history of life on earth.
Piecemeal ways of thinking that split what is
global into fragments naturally ignore the
anthropological complex and the planet-wide
context. But waving the global flag is not
enough; the component parts of the global
whole must be joined together in a complex,
organized system of linkages, and the global
whole itself must be put in context. The reform
of thinking that is required is one which will
generate attitudes that take account of the con¬
text and of complexity.
A MULTIDIMENSIONAL
WAY OF THINKING
As regards the context, we need to think in
planet-wide terms when considering politics,
economics, population questions, ecology, the
preservation of biological and cultural diversities.
It is not enough, however, to set all objects and
events within a planet-wide "framework". What
is needed is always to seek out the relationship of
inseparability, interaction and feedback between
any phenomenon and its context, and between
any context and the planet-wide context.
As to complexity, there is a need for a way of
thinking that brings together again that which has
been put asunder and compartmentalized, that
respects diversity whilst recognizing individu¬
ality, and that tries to discern interdependences.
In other words, wc need a multidimensional way
of thinking, an organizing approach that takes
account of the two-way relationship between the
whole and its constituent parts, an approach that,
instead of studying an object in isolation, exam¬
ines it in and through its self-organizing relation¬
ship with its cultural, social, economic, political
and natural environment, a way of thinking that
acknowledges its own incompleteness and
knows how to deal with uncertainty, particularly
where action is involved, since action can only
take place where there is uncertainty.
In the course of history we have often seen
the possible become impossible, but we have also
seen hopeless dreams come true and improbable
events occur.
We now know that the potential of the
human brain is still very largely under-exploited.
Since the possibilities of social development are
related to the brain's potential, no-one can say for
certain that our societies' capacities for improve¬
ment and change are exhausted and that wc have
reached the end of history.
The anthropological and sociological possi¬
bility of progress re-establishes the principle of
hope for the future, but without "scientific"
certainty and without "historical" promises. It
is an unsure possibility, greatly reliant upon
raised awareness, willpower, courage and luck;
the raising of awareness is therefore an urgent
task.
We are engaged, on a world-wide scale, in
life's essential undertaking, that of resisting
death. Civilizing the earth and promoting soli¬
darity, converting the human race to humanity,
such is the basic, all-embracing aim of any pro¬
ject that aspires not only to progress for
mankind but to its very survival. An awareness
of our common mortality should lead us
towards solidarity and reciprocal commisera¬
tion one with another, by all and for all.
EDGAR MORIN
is a French sociologist who is emeritus director of research
with the French National Centre for Scientific Research
(CNRS). His most recent work published in English is Towards
a Study of Humankind. Vol 1: The Nature of nature (1992).
)0 v è
ö°oooocoo
ÄVAAMM
n wonder tree,
by 7-year-old
Ulrike Terpetschnig
(Austria).
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The road to 1945
by Chikh Bekri
mjmmamÊmm
The long-cherished idea ofcreatingpeace in the minds of
men took form in the watershedyear of1945
UNESCO did not spring forth fully armed, like
Athene from the head of Zeus, out of the
smoking ruins of London one foggy day in
November 1945. As British Prime Minister
Clement Attlee said at the opening session of
the London conference for the establishment
of UNESCO, the idea of an intellectual organiza¬
tion to promote co-operation among the
nations and serve the cause of mutual under¬
standing between the peoples had been around
since the French Revolution or even earlier.
The relationship between culture and peace
has not always been obvious, however. It was
only with the gradual establishment of democ¬
racy in the nineteenth century and the assump¬
tion of responsibility for public education by
the state that the new concepts of the right to
knowledge, equality of opportunity and educa¬
tion for all emerged.
THE PIONEERS
In the late nineteenth century the Dutch educa¬
tionist Herman Molkenboer wrote, with
touching naivety, that "School is therefore the
power to which the future belongs and teachers
are the factors whose joint action should bring
the fruits of the moral order in the universe to
maturity", and the German educator Kurnig
drew up a plan for peace through education.
These forerunners often found themselves
swimming against the tide, without resources
or supporters. At the beginning of the twen¬
tieth century they were drawn largely from
associations of intellectuals and feminists. They
learned to frequent the corridors of power and
to lobby politicians. After the First World War,
the Belgians Henri Lafontaine and Paul Otlet,
fjrjboo oa
¡OOOoOO o o Afj^
who had founded the Union of International
Organisations in 1910, tried without success to
persuade the politicians to create an interna¬
tional organization of intellectual workers.
Fannie Fern Andrews, who established the
American School Peace League in 1908, later
worked on a project for an "International Edu¬
cation Bureau".
But these pioneers of culture for the sake of
peace could not make themselves heard. Prepa¬
ration for war was part of the training of the cit¬
izen, i.e. of culture, which, like education,
remained the exclusive preserve of the state.
The victors of the war made the vanquished
pay dearly for their defeat, while the latter
dreamed only of revenge, and thus the rise of
nationalism was exacerbated by the confidence
that comes from victory and the resentments
that rise from defeat. The maxim "Let him who
desires peace prepare for war" was quoted as a
self-evident truth.
At that time, few countries paid any attention
to intellectual co-operation, which was not
regarded as an important, or even a useful, factor
in international relations. Some governments
even regarded this form of international co¬
operation as suspect. The Covenant of the
League of Nations is silent on the subject of cul¬
ture. Peace remained the preserve of politicians,
diplomats and, in the last resort, the military.
PEACE IN THE MINDS
OF MEN
The Second World War was to change this situ¬
ation and to win acceptance for the idea, set
forth in UNESCO's constitution, that "since wars
begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of
men that the defences of peace must be con¬
structed", that "a peace based exclusively upon
the political and economic arrangements of
governments would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and sincere sup¬
port of the peoples of the world", and that "the
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to
fail, upon the intellectual and moral solidarity of
mankind."
Most of the speeches made at UNESCO's
founding conference took up this theme. The
general atmosphere in London was neither one
of rejoicing in victory over the forces of evil
nor even one of relief at awakening from a
nightmare but rather reflective and subdued.
As Jaime Torres Bodet, who headed the Mex¬
ican delegation and was later to become
UNESCO's second Director-General, put it, "the
gratification of triumph would be madness if we
were to neglect the immediate need of finding
some guarantee against the recurrence of such
perils". The fear of a war that would annihilate
human life on earth was in everyone's mind,
and Archibald MacLeish, the leader of the
United States delegation gave direct expression
to it when he told the delegates: "We must
choose to live together or we must choose,
quite literally, not to live."
CULTURE FOR PEACE
Tribute was also unanimously paid to the
courage shown and the sacrifices made by intel¬
lectuals and to their decisive contribution to the
triumph of democracy. In her opening address,
British Minister of Education Ellen Wilkinson,
who was President of the Conference, referred
to the part intellectuals had played in these
words: "In every land which the totalitarians
overran, it was the intellectual who was picked
out first to face the firing squad teacher,
priest, professor. The men who meant to rule
the world knew that first they must kill those
who tried to keep thought free".
The founding fathers also knew that culture
in itself was not enough to guarantee peace. The
totalitarian ideologies had been thought out by
philosophers before being put into practice by
politicians, and the deadliest weapons whose
devastating effects conference delegates could
see for themselves, in London had been
devised and developed by scientists before
being used by the military.
Knowledge cannot do without morality.
War, even more than a matter of armies, is a
matter of ideologies. As Léon Blum, Associate
President of the Conference, said, the war "has
shown us how education, culture (in the strict
sense) and science itself may be distorted
against the common interests of humanity. . . .
Expansion and perfecting [them] are therefore
not enough. These institutions must be steered
in the direction of that 'ideology' of democracy
and progress which is the psychological condi¬
tion and psychological basis of international sol¬
idarity and peace."
FROM UTOPIA TO
THE CULTURE OF PEACE
The British scientist Julian Huxley, who in 1946
became UNESCO's first Director-General, was
asked to draft a document on the new organiza¬
tion, to which he gave the title UNESCO, its pur¬
pose and its philosophy. The goal that Huxley set
for UNESCO was not only that of près erving the
peace, which is obviously the ultimate aim of
the whole United Nations system, but of con¬
tributing thereby to the fulfilment of humanity,
of those unique beings who have still to explore
and exploit all their possibilities but who are hin¬
dered in so doing by the obstacles they have
themselves raised, in the form of beliefs, ideolo¬
gies, cultures and so forth, which Huxley
regarded as the root cause of the divergences
between them, of conflicts and of wars.
Arguing from the viewpoint of an agnostic
biologist, Huxley was convinced that it was not
by integrating all cultures and all beliefs, with
their differences and contradictions, that
UNESCO could help to usher in peace as
humanity's natural state, since it would be lacking
that which he considered essential, a coherent
overall philosophy in conformity with its ideal.
No philosophical, religious, social, political or
economic system in the world could of itself sat¬
isfy the ultimate purposes of the new organiza¬
tion. The dream of this scientist, whose view of
humanity was both optimistic and Utopian, was
to lay the foundations of an organization that
would "help the peoples of the world to mutual
understanding and to a realisation of the
common humanity and common tasks which
they share, as opposed to the nationalisms which
too often tend to isolate and separate them."
But Huxley's ideas were rejected. Most of
the delegates to the London conference wanted
UNESCO to preserve the diversity of identities
and cultures. As the French jurist René Cassin,
the guiding spirit behind UNESCO's Constitu¬
tion, was to say, summing up the founders'
viewpoint, the new organization should not
"affirm any uniform philosophy, which would
strike a blow at the diversity of thinking, not
only of nations but even of individuals".
NO SCIENCE WITHOUT
CONSCIENCE
What sets UNESCO apart within the United
Nations system is not only its intellectual nature
but above all its moral basis. For the founding
fathers in London, it was above all an ethical
organization operating in a technical field: the
conscience of the world, as Jaime Torres Bodet
liked to call it. Its main task along the hard road to
peace is to contribute to the qualitative improve-
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
i/ream,
by 7-year-old Xiao Han
Qiu (China).
ment of humanity through education, science
and culture, to put the relations between individ¬
uals and peoples on a moral footing, and to help
to establish greater justice, fraternity, under¬
standing and solidarity among them.
Paulo de Berrêdo Carneiro, another emi¬
nent figure in UNESCO's history, insisted that
"We cannot regulate the human forces con¬
ducive to peace save by establishing above
purely political authority a spiritual force
common to all peoples".
NO PEACE WITHOUT
DEVELOPMENT
UNESCO's founders specified in its Constitution
the paths it should follow in order to reach out
towards the peoples, not over the heads of the
states but through those in government. These
paths are followed by educators, scientists,
writers and artists, working under the aegis of
UNESCO National Commissions and their com¬
mittees, within non-governmental organizations,
among the general population, young and old,
within UNESCO Clubs and Associated Schools, in
short, in the whole of civil society and among its
elites a vast field of operations in which to sow
the fragile seed of peace in the minds of men.
But culture alone is not enough, for the
hungry have no ears to hear, and nothing is more
terrible than culture when it makes educated
people aware of their unjust situation as those
whom fate has forgotten. The founding fathers
knew and said these things. Torres Bodet ended
his remarks with the following words: "The
world is waiting for something more than the
delimitation of frontiers and zones of influence,
something more than a system of agreements for
the exploitation and marketing of its products,
something more, in short, than an interim system
of security. It is looking for the establishment of a
new kind of relationship between nations and
between men. Hence the urgency of assigning a
common denominator to its development. And
that common denominator can be supplied only
by the moral solidarity of mankind acting through
knowledge and on the basis of education.
CHIKH BEKRI,
of Algeria, was an Assistant Director-General of Unesco
from 1976 to 1987. He is the author of L'Unesco: 'une
entreprise erronée '? (Publisud, Paris, 1991).
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO's programme for peace
by Ahmed Saleh Sayyad
A strategy to influence attitudes and act on the root causes
ofconßct
Peace-keeping is a function of the United
Nations Organization. Peace-building, an
activity concerning the human conscience and
the moral and intellectual foundations of human
behaviour, is a task which is incumbent on
UNESCO. The level on which UNESCO exercises
these responsibilities is that of culture as it is
expressed in everyday life. Culture must be
inspired and informed by the ideal of peace.
The American poet Archibald MacLeish,
who played a leading part in the drafting of
UNESCO's Constitution, described what the idea
of peace meant to him and to UNESCO's
founders in the following words. "Peace ... is
a process and a condition," he wrote, "not a
static objective periodically achieved and lost. It
is a condition of mutual confidence, harmony
of purpose, and co-ordination of activities in
which free men and women can live a satisfac¬
tory life ... in which war is affirmatively pre¬
vented by the dynamic and purposeful creation
of a human and social order between the people
of the world, in which the incentives to war are
neutralized by the human and spiritual advances
created and achieved."
Alfredo Cristiani, the President of El Sal¬
vador, believes that the culture of peace is
simply the "culture of life", while UNESCO's
Director-General, Federico Mayor, regards it as
"a way of living one's everyday life".
A NEW PERSPECTIVE
In the Medium-Term Strategy (1996-2001)
being submitted to UNESCO's General Confer-
14
ence the culture of peace is defined as "all the
values, attitudes and forms of behaviour, ways
of life and of acting that reflect, and are inspired
by, respect for life and for human beings and
their dignity and rights, the rejection of violence
and commitment to the principles of freedom,
justice, solidarity, tolerance and understanding
among peoples and between groups and indi¬
viduals."
These are tasks that must be performed by
all categories of civil society. But it is quite nat¬
ural that teachers and intellectuals (poets,
writers and creative artists) should play a leading
role in developing the ideas and values under¬
lying this process. They can also use their
knowledge and creative powers to inform the
rest of society and infuse these values into the
lives of their contemporaries.
Peace, like war, makes its own demands. It
implies a new way of looking at traditional
modes of thought which still abound in warlike
references epic tales that extoll the courage of
warriors, monuments commemorating battles,
school books that teach children the illustrious
exploits of soldiers, history books describing
world wars, civil wars and holy wars.
A LONG-TERM
JOB
Peace also calls for a large-scale programme to
eradicate the poverty, inequality and discrimi¬
nation that give rise to the violence which fuels
the conflicts of today. Many peoples and soci¬
eties are familiar with a state of political and
social instability that could lead to terrible racial,
ethnic or religious confrontations. The gap is
widening between the haves and the have-nots.
Human rights and fundamental freedoms are
too often scorned. These trends have led
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO to take the initiative by contributing to
national and international projects that promote
the search for common ground and bases for
compromise. These projects involve steps that
UNESCO can take to isolate conflicts before they
degenerate into violence, and in cases where
they have already done so, to help contain them
and to cope with their consequences.
This means creating an environment of jus¬
tice and social harmony, building confidence
between states and peoples, reflecting on the
remote or immediate causes of conflicts and
seeking solutions that short-circuit temptation
to violence, by means of cultural activities, edu¬
cation, communication and legislation.
IN THE FIELD
"A culture of peace cannot be imposed from
outside. It must be a process that grows out of
the people themselves and develops differently
in each country depending on its history, cul¬
tures and traditions." This statement from
UNESCO's Action programme to promote a cul¬
ture of peace, launched in 1993, reveals the
dynamics of a concept which is beginning to
take practical shape.
UNESCO's first steps in this field took place
in El Salvador, where the "First International
Forum on the Culture of Peace" was held in
San Salvador in February 1994. The previous
year a "Forum for Education and Culture of
Peace" organized in the same country had led
to a nation-wide programme the goal of which
was to contribute to the "country's economic,
social and cultural renewal".
In Mozambique a "Peace consolidation pro¬
gramme" has been organized with the authori¬
ties, non-governmental organizations and local
community associations. It covers a wide range
of activities including adult literacy work, the
social reintegration of demobilized soldiers, the
promotion of folk culture, radio programmes
and cultural exchanges between young people.
In Burundi a "National Symposium on the
Culture of Peace" gave an opportunity for a
broad spectrum of socio-professional groups,
political organizations and associations to reflect
on "problems connected with the interdepen¬
dence of democracy, human rights, peace and
development in the Burundi cultural context".
Other experiences in the Congo and
Somalia have enabled UNESCO to develop var¬
ious steps by which bellicose attitudes can grad¬
ually give way to a spirit of compromise and
reconciliation.
A RECONCILIATION
PLAN IN
THE CONGO
A forum on the theme "Intercommunity dia¬
logue for peace, democracy and sustainable
development" was held in Brazzaville in
December 1994. It was organized jointly by the
government of the Republic of the Congo and
UNESCO. Discussions focused on the questions
of how to integrate the mechanisms for
I he earth weeps,
by 14-year-old Rita Yamashita
(Japan)
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S CULTURE
OF PEACE
PROGRAMME
In response to the challenge of peace-building
contained in the UN Secretary-General's Agenda for
Peace, Unesco's Culture of Peace Programme is
playing a dynamic role in three priority areas: conflict
prevention, emergency assistance, and
strengthening the process of post-conflict
reconciliation.
For further information, please contact:
Director, Culture of Peace Programme, Unesco, 7 Place
de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France. Tel.: (33-1)
45 68 08 77; Fax: (33-1) 47 83 68 67.
conflict-settlement that exist in traditional soci¬
eties into the new democratic process, the role
of democratic institutions in peace-building
between ethnic groups and the ways in which
political parties can support social integration.
The action plan "for promoting a culture of
peace" that was devised after the Forum sug¬
gests a series of measures that could be adopted
either to prevent conflicts or to encourage rec¬
onciliation. The plan is based on the mobiliza¬
tion of intellectuals, artists, educators and jour¬
nalists. Among the measures it proposes are
providing support for research programmes on
pre-conflict situations and on the traditions of
dialogue and past experience in solving con¬
flicts; monitoring the ways in which different
communities respect cultural, social and polit¬
ical rights; and upgrading road, rural radio and
telephone systems to improve communica¬
tions between rural and urban areas.
Steps are also to be taken to improve the
status of women, who have often acted as con¬
ciliators in traditional African societies, and to
educate young people by developing and dis¬
tributing teaching aids and aiding schools and
universities.
There are also plans to encourage disarma¬
ment and the disbanding of private militias, and
to speed up the reintegration of young militia
recruits into civilian life and the integration of
unemployed young people and disaster victims
into society.
RECONCILIATION IN
SOMALIA
A Symposium on the Culture of Peace in
Somalia, organized on UNESCO's initiative, was
held from 17 to 20 April 1995 in Sana'a (Yemen).
It was attended by about seventy Somali intel¬
lectuals and professional people (some living in
Somalia, others belonging to the Somali dias¬
pora), representatives of the Organisation of
African Unity, the Arab League, a number of
UN bodies, international organizations and
donor countries. There were three main items
on the agenda: rebuilding Somali society, reha¬
bilitating the state and reintegrating the country
into the international community.
The Symposium was part of a broader
framework of activities deployed in Somalia by
UNESCO, which in the last two years has orga¬
nized 55 teacher training workshops (in many
parts of Somalia and in refugee camps in neigh¬
bouring countries), printed 850,000 school
books and handbooks for teachers, and distrib¬
uted emergency teaching materials.
However, the war has caused incalculable
damage. Hundreds of thousands of people
were killed; families were destroyed; people
displaced and children orphaned. All the tradi¬
tional values of African civilization have been
overthrown. The only schooling for young
people was training in handling weapons. The
elders who had settled conflicts in the past were
no longer listened to. Many people sought pro¬
tection in a clan. Despite the efforts of many vil¬
lages, violent tribalism replaced the traditional
mechanisms of peaceful dialogue between
ethnic groups.
The participants in the Sana'a Symposium
emphasized the need to combine tradition with
modernity in order to build a new way of living
together. Political pluralism, power sharing and
a developing democratic system should find a
source of ideas in certain kinds of traditional vil¬
lage democracy that still exist today.
As in the Congo and in any other country
seeking the path of reconciliation, steps must be
taken towards disarmament, administrative
restructuring and educational reform. In short,
Somalis must learn again how to live in peace. M
AHMED SALEH SAYYAD
is the permanent delegate to Unesco of the Republic of
Yemen and president of Unesco's General Conference.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Demilitarizing military service
by Anne Baer
Community service as a humanitarian alternative to
military conscription
Ehe good life on earth,
by 11-year-old Prajird
Sangthong (Thailand).
In many countries the army is an organized and
efficient structure and can play an important
role in development. Both in the North and the
South, young people who are called up to do
military service have often done civilian jobs.
They have built roads in Ethiopia and Yemen
and bridges in Guatemala. In the United States
they have joined in the war on drug abuse and
taken part in inner city resettlement pro¬
grammes. In Venezuela, Colombia and some
other Latin American countries, they have
taken part in literacy schemes. They have
worked on environmental projects in the
t-m3A
>*
Ld c*^ *"ä?Jl x5V. X »
Il I-SJ/J ITT
M U
N
¡Il ' J
Bfcfe, *A. 1 ^^^ .¿fl w\. *"* îv
Himalayas and reforestation projects in the
Algerian Sahara.
In most developed countries where com¬
pulsory military service still exists it is
becoming increasingly unpopular. Each year
more and more young people register as con¬
scientious objectors. These countries are
reducing troop numbers, partly because the
Cold War is over and partly because their
public finances are in a critical situation. They
are also reducing the length of military service.
The notion of security has changed. It has
assumed new dimensions. The main threats to
security now come from within, in the shape of
unemployment, poverty, environmental degra¬
dation and social exclusion. People are starting
to hope for a form of security that would be
guaranteed by sustainable human development
and rooted in tolerance and solidarity and not in
a balance of terror.
Exclusively military service could and
should now be replaced by a form of civilian
service which is not based on national defence
but extends to social life, to the environment
and the development of disadvantaged coun¬
tries. Although the principle of compulsory
military service would be maintained, its con¬
ception and practice would be rethought. The
proposed range of activities would be so wide
that it would stimulate young people's interest
in national service and community life. Com¬
munity service could be acceptable to the hun¬
dreds of thousands of young people who object
to carrying weapons and refuse to perform mil¬
itary duties.
There are many solid social and economic
arguments in favour of community service.
The time spent by a conscript in the army costs
money. This is why lack of financial resources is
leading some armies to discharge more and
more young people of military age and in some
cases to abolish conscription outright. A con¬
script who does community service costs less
than one who serves in the armed forces.
,'177
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Un
War machines used
for peace
In the last few months Unesco has been helping young
people and athletes in poor countries to benefit from
contributions in kind and from services offered by the
armed forces of the industrialized nations.
Tens of thousands of balls, shoes, shorts and
shirts given to Unesco by sportswear manufacturers
like Nike and Adidas have been delivered free of charge
by the French Navy and Air Force to Madagascar and
Guinea, where they were handed over to children
taking part in school-based and extracurricular "Sport
for all" programmes. Unesco and the International Mil¬
itary Sports Council are co-operating to extend the
scope and range of operations of this type.
Meanwhile, the Swiss Army, via Unesco's Special
Fund for Youth, has made a gift of 31 jeeps and
minibuses (worth $160,000) that had been taken out
of active service. These vehicles have been adapted for
use in socio-educative projects in Madagascar, Uzbek¬
istan and Romania.
Re-utilizing military equipment for peaceful ends
is one highly practical contribution to a culture of
peace.
Division of Youth and Sports Activities
Unesco
Intitled,
by 16-year-old
Destin Rolex (Haiti)
Another advantage of community service is
that it offers young people useful openings that
may guide them towards a career. Before
embarking on an expensive course of studies
that would perhaps lead nowhere, a conscript
who opts for community service can acquire
experience and skills that may be useful in a job.
Community service, whether at home or
abroad, is useful in itself and may lead to some¬
thing.
The conventional type of military service, in
which all conscripts are supposed to be on an
equal footing, itself provides an exceptional
opportunity for young people of different back¬
grounds to meet. Community service is an even
stronger encouragement to become a full
member of society, as well as being a catalyst for
democratic mixing. The young conscript who
opts for community service will come into con¬
tact with elderly people, delinquents, drug
addicts and problem children. He will learn to
cope with new situations, and will make plenty
of useful contacts. Independent of environ¬
mental or development considerations, the
demilitarization of compulsory national service
may be a first tentative step towards a solution of
such contemporary social and human problems
as the crisis of solidarity, racism, exclusion, urban
malaise, youth unemployment and drug abuse.
Conscripts who choose to perform com¬
munity service in a developing country of the
South must be thoroughly prepared before¬
hand. But this form of service is worthwhile
because young people may become closely
attached to the host environment and become a
major asset to another kind of co-operation,
involving more modest resources but bolder
objectives, with local populations.
The provision of new forms of national ser¬
vice is certainly not risk-free. The availability of
"free" human resources may lead to abuses. In
various parts of the world large-scale public
works projects supposedly of national interest
have sometimes been carried out by dra¬
gooning people in an arbitrary fashion. Other
risks may appear on a smaller scale. A conscript
attached to the civil service, a business firm or
an association may be required to do jobs that
are useful to an elected local politician and not to'
the community at large. Nor should young
conscripts be asked to do work that prevents
young people in the host country from doing
the same type of job. In other words, there
must be rigorous controls.
ANNEBAER,
of Israel, is a Unesco consultant who is currently preparing
a doctorate in development economics.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
PEACE
MAKERS
HONOURED BY UNESCO
1 991
NELSON MANDELA AND FREDERIK WILLEM DE KLERK
í 992
THE HAGUE ACADEMY OF INTERNATIONAL LAW
í 993
YITZHAK RABIN, SHIMON PERES AND YASSER ARAFAT
Í 994
JIMMY CARTER AND JUAN CARLOS I
The collapse of the two-bloc world system
brought to an end a long period of immobility.
However uneasy and unpredictable the
current situation may be, it is more open to
individual human effort, especially on the part of
remarkable personalities who, through their
commitment to peace, have given new
momentum to situations that seemed
to be at a standstill. On the following pages are
thumbnail sketches of some of these
peacemakers who have been awarded
Unesco's Félix Houphouët-Boigny Peace Prize.
il IS
1
1
Nelson Mandela, a giant of our time
by Tahar Ben Jelloun
Frederik Willem de Klerk, a conservative
revolutionary
by Anthony Johnson
Shimon Peres, passion and patience
by Charles Enderlln
Yitzhak Rabin, a hawk with the wings of a
dove
by Luc Beyer de Ryke
Yasser Arafat, the father of Palestine
by Lotfl El-Kholy
Jimmy Carter, the pilgrim-president
by Flora Lewis
Juan Carlos I, the democratic king
by Ramón Luis Acuña
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
NELSON MANDELA
a giant of our time
In 1994, the year in
which he was
elected President of
the Republic of
South Africa,
Nelson Mandela
visited Robben
Island where he had
been imprisoned for
many years.
I
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN
is a Moroccan-born
novelist and poet
who writes in French.
Several of his works
have been published
in English
translation, including
The Sacred Night
(1989), which won
the 1987 Goncourt
Prize, Silent Day in
7ang/'er(1991) and
The Sand Child
(1987).
It requires great humility to write about someone
who has spent his whole life on a long march in the
name of dignity. First, there is the dignity of his
people, which was fated to live under the laws of
apartheid, one of the most barbaric systems this cen¬
tury has known. Then there is the dignity of the man
himself, whose whole being is informed by passion and
by the daily fight for freedom. Everything about him is
redolent of the land, love of the land and love of jus¬
tice. He is a tree as old as the sea; he is a forest as
dense and as demanding as the urge for eternity. The
blood that runs in his veins is neither black nor white
but red, reminding us that there is no such thing as
race, that it was invented by racists.
THE DILEMMA OF THE ARMED STRUGGLE
Nelson Mandela has left his stamp on the twentieth cen¬
tury. More than that, he has given it a meaning. Human
but not all too human, and obsessive in his respect for
law and justice, he has succeeded in being a unique indi¬
vidual at the same time as the symbol of a people who
recognized themselves in him before they had even
chosen him through the democratic channel of the
ballot box. In Africa and beyond, in the memory of those
who suffer, those whose voices still carry the echo of a
wound that has never healed, the voices of those tossed
into the mass grave of ordinary massacres or suffocated
in a jute sack thrown from an express train, Mandela
exemplifies a determination that nothing could crush, a
passion that nothing could discourage.
Prison, humiliation, petty harassment and attempts
to undermine his morale did not succeed in shaking his
conviction that freedom could not be achieved without
a struggle. And he had a particular kind of freedom in .
mind, not one that is deceptively packaged to look
attractive, yet is actually full of illusions. Tn his eyes,
freedom is a non-negotiable value inseparable from dig¬
nity and pregnant with responsibility.
That unshakeable conviction prompted Mandela, at a
meeting in June 1961, after the half-failure of the stay-at-
home strike, to address the question of armed struggle.
He felt like a man attacked by a wild beast in a forest,
and used an old African expression: "The attacks of the
wild beast cannot be averted only by bare hands".
At that time he realized that a policy aimed at cre¬
ating a non-racial state by non-violent means had failed,
that his comrades were beginning to lose confidence,
and that they were flirting alarmingly with the idea of
terrorism. Mandela, who has been compared to Gandhi,
yielded to the reality principle; he preferred to forego
the non-violence which he would have preferred, but
which had proved inadequate in the context of a state
founded on total racial segregation and great brutality.
Yet he did not wish an extension of violence. He
knew that "with civil war racial peace would be more
difficult than ever to achieve. . . . How much longer
would it take to eradicate the scars of inter-racial war,
which could not be fought without a great loss of life
on both sides?"
WESTMINSTER IN SOUTH AFRICA
At the time when he accepted the need for armed resis¬
tance, Mandela was already thinking about later devel¬
opments the need for reconciliation and the possible
shape of South African democracy. He opted unequivo¬
cally for a Western parliamentary system: "I regard the
British Parliament as the most democratic institution in
the world," he said, "and the independence and impar¬
tiality of its judiciary never fail to arouse my admira¬
tion." He disagreed unbendingly with those who thought
that system could not be adapted to Africa, who pre¬
ferred a one-party, totalitarian regime on the grounds
that it was what Africans needed, and who rejected the
universality of such values as freedom and the rule of
law in order better to impose forms of apartheid that
suited them. Soon after he had been released from jail,
Mandela reportedly said to a journalist: "Yes, I want
Westminster here in my country!"
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
by Tahar Ben Jelloun
Mandela has never allowed the demands of the col¬
lective struggle to take precedence over the need to
respect the rights of the individual. Individuals are sin¬
gular entities, whether they live in London, Paris, Cairo
or Soweto. They need freedom in order to exist. It may
be a commonplace to say so, but that simple fact is not
to everyone's taste. In the past, people took to the
streets because they were hungry. Today, they demon¬
strate and risk their lives for principles. The notion of
the individual is a value that is beginning to take shape
in many countries where clans or tribes have so far had it
their own way, and where people's rights are trampled on
and violated in the name of the community. The emer¬
gence of the individual heralds the beginning of self-ful¬
filment for the peoples of those countries: they will
increasingly endow themselves with sound political
structures and reject those providential "fathers of the
nation" who are very soon intoxicated and corrupted by
absolute power and have an unfortunate tendency to
regard the coffers of state as their personal property.
Mandela realized very early on that the best way to
neutralize the political parasites who are so quick to rob
peoples of the fruits of their struggle was to make the
system universally democratic. What holds for whites
naturally also holds for blacks. It is a simple equation,
yet it took decades of fighting and tens of thousands of
deaths for that notion of equality between human beings
to carry conviction with the South African leadership.
That Mandela never doubted that it would, even at he
height of a relentless struggle, even in the loneliness of
his prison cell, is the most miraculous thing of all. The
South African people were doubly fortunate in having
Mandela to guide them during that struggle and Fred-
erik de Klerk to play for the very high stakes of recon¬
ciliation within an equal society.
A MAN FOR ALL SEASONS
The fact that mammoth tasks remain to be carried out
does not in any way diminish the magnitude of the two
men's achievement. The decisive step came with the abo¬
lition of apartheid and the arrival in power of a former
prisoner who was capable of showing his jailers the road
to freedom. By way of conclusion to his autobiography,
Mandela writes: "It was during those long and lonely years
that my hunger for the freedom of my own people
became a hunger for the freedom of all people, white and
A jubilant Nelson
Mandela on 2 May
1994 after the
announcement of
the victory of the
African National
Congress (ANC) in
South Africa's first
all-party democratic
elections.
black. ... A man who takes away another man's freedom
is a prisoner of hatred, he is locked behind the bars of
prejudice and narrow-mindedness. . . . The oppressed and
the oppressor alike are robbed of their humanity." What
a prodigious reversal of the situation, where a man who
emerges from the long night of imprisonment decides
that those who held him prisoner should also be freed.
Mandela is an awe-inspiring historic figure. He has
become so strongly identified with his people that any¬
thing he experiences personally, whether it be victory,
honours or happiness, is immediately passed on to his
people as though they were its natural recipients to
those faces which have escaped attempts to enslave
them, to those hands which have thrown off the
shackles of unhappiness, to those anonymous bodies
that run through the streets of shanty towns in search of
work and self-respect. Mandela is a very unusual
statesman in the extent to which he is a man of his
people; he has both emerged from his people and sym¬
bolizes them. That is why he is one of the giants of the
twentieth century. He would probably reject the
description, but it is no exaggeration.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
FREDERIK WILLEM DE KLERK
a conservative revolutionary
by Anthony Johnson
Frederik Willem de Klerk must be one of the few
leaders in the world of politics to have voluntarily
set in motion events resulting in the inevitable sur¬
render of his personal power and the demise of his gov¬
ernment. Just a few short months after he became
leader of the then ruling National Party (NP) in South
Africa in 1979, he embarked on a bold gamble which
ushered in an era of rapid transformation which saw
the nation reinventing itself after more than three
decades of apartheid rule.
The decision of the former State President in early
1990 to unban political parties representing the
majority of unenfranchised South Africans, release
Nelson Mandela and hundreds of other political pris¬
oners and follow the route of peaceful negotiation, vir¬
tually ensured that he would become South Africa's
last white president.
By playing a pivotal role in breaking the mould of
race-based politics, De Klerk paved the way for South
Africa's peaceful revolution at the very time when
many observers believed the country was headed for a
period of unparalleled strife and inter-racial conflict.
The fifty-eight-year-old politician now deputy
executive president in South Africa's government of
national unity is still confronted with the fears and
grumbles of NP supporters grown used to the security
and patronage that comes from having forty-five years
of virtually untrammelled power.
Despite his demotion as a result of the sweeping
election victory won by the African National Congress
(ANC) in the country's first democratic elections, in
April 1994, De Klerk maintains that his job satisfac¬
tion is as high as ever. He emphasizes that he does not
lie awake at night worrying about whether he has
chosen the correct course.
To this day, however, many political observers and
even colleagues find it hard to explain how a man with
the political background and track record of F.W. de
Klerk was capable of the momentous changes which
transformed the very fabric of South African society.
LIKE FATHER, LIKE SON?
De Klerk comes from a family environment in which the
conservatism of traditional white South African poli¬
tics is deeply ingrained. His great-grandfather was a
,'22~"
Vice-President
Frederik de Klerk and
newly-elected
President Nelson
Mandela on 10 May
1994.
ANTHONY JOHNSON,
a South African
journalist and
university teacher, is
the political
correspondent of
the Cape Times
newspaper in Cape
Town.
Senator, his grandfather stood twice for the white par¬
liament unsuccessfully, and his aunt was married to NP
Prime Minister J. G. Strydom. In 1948, the year when
the NP swept to power in whites-only elections on an
apartheid ticket, F. W. de Klerk's father, Jan de Klerk,
became secretary of the NP in the Transvaal province
and later rose to the positions of cabinet minister and
President of the Senate.
After receiving his early political training in the
youth section of the NP, De Klerk became a Member of
Parliament in 1972 and was appointed to the first of
his many cabinet portfolios in 1978. Significantly, he
became leader of the NP in the politically conservative
Transvaal province in 1982 the year when a split in
the ruling party resulted in the formation of the far
right-wing Conservative Party.
During his eleven years in the cabinet before
becoming NP leader, De Klerk demonstrated that he'
was a highly effective politician but showed few signs
of being a great reformer-in-the-making. When polit¬
ical scientists and analysts categorized cabinet minis¬
ters during the 1980s into those who were hardline or
enlightened in their thinking on racial matters, De
Klerk was rarely placed in the latter grouping.
In Parliament De Klerk assumed the mantle of the
champion of "own affairs" a euphemism for
apartheid and he betrayed very few liberal tenden-
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
cies in his handling of the many portfolios with which
he was entrusted. But his colleagues recall that De
Klerk was a wily political operator who refused to
become too closely identified with the ideological
camps that emerged during the frequent debates over
the future of the country. This no doubt gave him
greater room to manoeuvre when he took over the lead¬
ership of the NP at the end of the past decade from an
ailing P. W Botha.
A BURST OF REFORM
The courage and speed with which De Klerk as new NP
leader and State President went about transforming the
apartheid state left many observers wondering whether
he had undergone some sort of religious, Damascus-
Road-type of experience. De Klerk has always denied
that the burst of reform that he ushered in culmi¬
nating in his opening address to Parliament on 2 Feb¬
ruary 1990 in which he summarily ended the thirty-year
ban on political movements representing the unenfran¬
chised black majority was the result of a sudden reve¬
lation. He has endeavoured instead to spread the credit
for the changes, insisting that the new NP was really
born in 1986 when a special federal congress of the
party approved, in broad principle, the concept of polit¬
ical power-sharing between whites and non-whites.
However, De Klerk confidants and party insiders say
the NP leader realized when given the responsibility
of office that the white minority and its surrogates
could wage an eighty-year war in a bid to stave off
black majority rule but would eventually lose.
A series of other momentous events on the interna¬
tional scene the demise of the Soviet Union, the end of
the Cold War, and also the withdrawal of Cuban troops
from Angola no doubt created a climate in which
reform in South Africa was seen by the NP hierarchy as
less threatening. Whatever the complex dynamics which
spurred De Klerk and other political leaders in South
Africa to opt for peaceful negotiations instead of naked
confrontation, the international community was anxious
to assist the process and acknowledge those leaders who
had the courage to choose the peaceful options.
WHAT PRICE PEACE?
De Klerk lists the receipt of the Nobel Peace Prize
(jointly with Nelson Mandela) as one of the important
milestones of his political career. Nevertheless, he is
adamant that the fateful day in 1989 when he became
the leader of the NP was the proudest moment in his
public life. He notes that none of the dramatic changes
which followed in the ruling party would have taken
place when they did had he not been entrusted with
the leadership of the NP. He certainly could not have
had a better foil than the hard-nosed and authoritarian
P. W. Botha, who ran the party with an iron hand.
During his steady rise in the NP, De Klerk was even
regarded as something of a fence-sitter. On the other
hand, his undoubted intellectual ability as well as his
logical and relatively unemotional approach to prob¬
lems was highly regarded in party circles. Colleagues
are fond of recounting how after hours of often divisive
and heated discussion De Klerk would be invited to
summarize the feelings of the meeting in a few crisp
sentences or a resolution. This he was almost invariably
able to do, leaving colleagues wondering what they had
been arguing about for so long.
These skills in finding compromise solutions and
maintaining a clear head during the heat of debate stood
De Klerk in good stead during the years of multi-party
constitutional negotiations and bilateral talks with the
ANC that preceded the April 1994 elections. At a time
when a number of his colleagues were suffering burn-out
under the intense pressure of rapid change and his sup¬
porters were voicing grave reservations about the course
of the talks, De Klerk remained unflappable and main¬
tained his faith in the negotiation process.
A number of the four million voters who backed De
Klerk and his party in the April 1994 elections are uncom¬
fortable with the comparatively low profile he has
adopted since becoming one of the two executive deputy
presidents in South Africa's government of national unity
(the other being Thabo Mbeki). They would also like him
to be more strident in his criticism of the ANC, which
many have been brought up to regard as "the enemy".
Because of the hectic schedules of President Man¬
dela and Thabo Mbeki, De Klerk is often required to
chair cabinet committee meetings and is also the chair¬
person of the hugely influential cabinet security com¬
mittee. He dismisses criticism that he is a spent political
force or has lost interest in politics since surrendering
office to Nelson Mandela. He insists that he has as great
a role to play in forging the new South Africa as ever, and
remains upbeat about the course the country is fol¬
lowing. He told Parliament recently that despite a
number of problems confronting South Africa, the
country remained well placed to develop its "rainbow
nation" into a successful co-operative society. I
Frederik de Klerk,
then President of
the Republic of
South Africa, during
a visit to Paris in
1990.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE HAGUE
ACADEMY OF
INTERNATIONAL
LAW
One of the world's most prestigious centres for the
study and teaching of public and private interna¬
tional law, The Hague Academy of Intenational Law is
distinguished by a spirit of freedom and respect for
others which is very close to that of the great interna¬
tional organizations and especially to the United
Nations and its judicial organ, the International Court
of Justice.
Founded in 1913 in Paris, it began its work in 1923
in The Hague, at the Peace Palace, which is also the
seat of the International Court of Justice. Its aim is to
spread and deepen knowledge of international law in
order to promote peace and goodwill between peoples
and to help to ensure that disputes between states are
solved through negotiation and not through violence.
Lectures are given at the Peace Palace by well-
known lawyers from all regions of the world and cover
the theory and practice of international law as well as
international legislation and jurisprudence.
The Collected Courses of the Academy, amounting
to over 230 volumes, form a unique collection which
enjoys very high prestige. In co-operation with the
United Nations University (UNU), the Academy has
organized workshops on major themes of concern to
governments all over the world.
The Academy's external programme enables it to
extend its promotional activities in international law in
support of peace and human rights to Africa, Latin
America and Asia.
The working languages of the Academy are French
and English.
Shimon Peres,
Prime Minister
of Israel's
government of
national unity
in 1984.
In February 1981, a few months before the general
election, Shimon Peres, then head of the Israeli
Labour Party, was optimistic. At last all the polls put
him in the lead. Secretly, with a few advisors, he began
preparing his programme. His first hundred days as
prime minister would transform Israel and the Middle
East. He left for London where a secret meeting had
been arranged with Jordan's King Hussein.
The two men already knew each other. They had
met several times since the end of the October War1.
But the chances of a real breakthrough now seemed
much more likely.
After the London meeting, Shimon Peres left for
Casablanca via Paris where the French authorities had
arranged a secret meeting with King Hassan II of
Morocco. The Israeli Labour leader told Hassan II that
if elected he would propose placing Jerusalem's holy
mosques under the joint responsibility of Saudi Arabia
and Morocco. When he returned to Israel, Peres
believed that at last things were going to change.
But the election campaign proved to be one of the
hardest ever fought in Israel. The right threw waves of
turbulent supporters into the midst of election rallies
for Peres, who more than once had to beat a retreat
under a hail of tomatoes. He lost the elections. Demor¬
alized, he went through a dark period that was made
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
SHIMON PERES
passion and patience
by Charles Enderlin
worse by the war in Lebanon2. He emerged from his
depression only in 1984 on the eve of a new general
election.
A STATE OF GRACE
When the campaign opened, opinion polls gave the
Labour Party a twenty-four-seat lead. But once again
Peres's enemies were unrelenting in their attacks, and
each day the polls showed that Labour's lead was slip¬
ping away. The final result was a draw between the
coalition of rightist parties the Likud and Labour.
They decided to share power. Peres would be Prime
Minister for just over two years, and Yitzhak Shamir
would be his Minister of Foreign Affairs. Then they
would swap places until the next elections.
At long last, Peres became prime minister.
Although his hands were tied by his deal with Likud,
he could still prove his worth. Within a few weeks he
had launched an economic programme that drastically
reduced inflation. His Minister of Defence, Yitzhak
Rabin, directed the Israeli retreat from Lebanon that
had begun in July 1983. The army redeployed in a
security zone ten kilometres deep along the Israeli
border in Lebanese territory. Things quietened down.
This was a period of grace for Peres with Israeli public
opinion.
He next tried to get peace negotiations going again.
He made secret contact with the Palestine Liberation
Organization (PLO). A senior Israeli official was sent to
Tunis to sound out Yasser Arafat's intentions, but the
PLO was not ready and so Peres turned to his old idea
of a compromise with Jordan. To King Hussein he pro¬
posed setting up a joint Jordanian-Palestinian delega¬
tion that would negotiate within the framework of an
international conference. But neither the king of
Jordan nor the king of Morocco could commit them¬
selves to negotiations with Israel with only a few
months remaining before Yitzhak Shamir took over the
Israeli leadership. Another opportunity was lost.
Applauded for his management and feted by the
Israeli public and many foreign friends, Peres left the
premiership to become Minister of Foreign Affairs.
Furthering the peace process remained his main objec¬
tive, but he had to pursue it by more devious means.
On 11 April 1987 he had another secret meeting in
London with Hussein of Jordan. The two men reached a
three-part agreement on the calling of an international
conference on the Middle East, the creation of bilateral
regional commissions, and the procedure for talks. The
London accord was submitted to the Reagan adminis¬
tration, which sent it to the Israeli and Jordanian gov¬
ernments as if it were an American initiative. But Likud
rejected the proposals out of hand.
TIME TO THINK
A few months later, in December 1987, the Intifada3
the Palestinian uprising in the occupied territories
began. Shamir was in favour of letting the storm blow
over, but Peres was convinced that only peace negotia¬
tions would bring a return to calm. He began preparing
for the next elections, due to be held in 1988. Labour
presented a plan for a partial retreat from Lebanon.
Likud accused Peres of wanting a sell-out.
Events were not on the Labour Party's side. Forty-
eight hours before the election, a Jewish family died in
an attack in Jericho. There was a backlash. Shamir's
party won forty seats; while Labour captured only
thirty-nine. Once again a coalition government was
formed, but this time on Likud's conditions. Shamir
would not share the premiership. Peres tried to bring
down the government with a no-confidence motion in
parliament but in the ensuing crisis proved unable to
Shimon Peres with
Yasser Arafat in
Brussels in
November 1994.
CHARLES ENDERLIN
is a French journalist
who reports from
Jerusalem for the
French television
channel France 2. He
is the author of
Shamir (Olivier Orban
publishers, Paris,
1991).
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
form a new government. On 11 June a right-wing gov¬
ernment was presented to the Knesset4, and the Labour
Party went back into opposition.
They remained in opposition for another two
years time enough to think, and time enough for the
situation in the Middle East to change, after the Gulf
War, and the Madrid Peace Conference which opened
in October 1991. In the meantime Shimon Peres was
challenged by his long-time rival Yitzhak Rabin, who
supported his bid for the Labour Party leadership
with the argument that three failures at the polls were
more than enough. The party activists opted for Rabin,
and Peres became the party's second in command.
In 1992 Labour based its election campaign almost
uniquely on Rabin's personality, emphasizing that he
had been the victorious general in the Six Day War5 and
the Defence Minister who had contained the Intifada.
For the first time in fourteen years Likud went into
opposition. Peres again became Minister of Foreign
Affairs, and most important of all relaunched peace
negotiations.
On 16 November he went on an official visit to
Egypt. He asked his hosts to let the PLO know that he
was ready for a new dialogue. Even Prime Minister
Rabin did not know of this. On 1 December the
Knesset repealed a law that forbade all contact with
the PLO. Three days later Yaïr Hirschfeld, a left-wing
Israeli university professor, met a PLO official, Abu
Ala', in London. The two men decided to begin secret
discussions in Oslo, Norway. The meeting began on 20
January 1993. Peres was informed a few days later. He
in turn informed Rabin, who decided to let the discus¬
sions go ahead, although at first he did not think they
had much chance of success.
THE BREAKTHROUGH
The big moment came on 19 August, and Peres
savoured it to the full. Late at night without the pres¬
ence of reporters and recorded on film only by Norwe¬
gian security guards with a home-video camera, he was
present at the first signing of the Oslo Agreements, by
Uri Savir and Abu Ala'. Shimon Peres's obstinacy had
brought about a fundamental change in the Middle
East. Less than a month later the breakthrough was
officialized in Washington, this time with the cameras
turned on Yasser Arafat and Yitzhak Rabin. H
1. On 6 October 1973 Israeli positions were attacked by Egyptian
forces in the Suez Canal sector and by Syrian forces in the Golan
Heights. Ed.
2. The Israeli invasion of Lebanon on 6 June 1982, known as
Operation "Peace in Galilee". Ed.
3. Arabic for "uprising". Ed.
4. Israel's parliament. Ed.
5. From 5 to 10 June 1967, Israel occupied Sinai, the Gaza Strip,
the West Bank of the Jordan, the eastern sector of Jerusalem and
part of the Syrian Golan Heights. Ed.
Yitzhak Rabin
in 1985.
Close friends of Yitzhak Rabin say mischievously:
"When he was a teenager Yitzhak was ginger-
haired. There's a slang word in Hebrew to describe the
temperament of people with ginger hair: gingi, which
means inflammable. Gingi people flare up like tinder."
When still only a young man, Rabin was quite pre¬
pared to clash with Ben Gurion, He cut his teeth in the
Palmach, the commando troops secretly formed during
the British mandate. Once Israel had gained indepen¬
dence, Ben Gurion disbanded the Palmach and Rabin
became a "regular" soldier. But he kept in touch with
his former comrades more so than Ben Gurion would
have liked. As a result, Israel's patriarch felt a mixture
of resentment and esteem. He found himself dealing
with a sabra1 who stood up to him and used familiar
forms of language when addressing him. It was enough to
irritate Ben Gurion, but no more than that.
It may seem surprising that someone like Rabin,
whose responsibility when he was Defence Minister was
to put down the intifada, should subsequently be the
man who made peace with the Palestine Liberation
Organization (PLO) particularly since the intifada
eventually ran out of steam. But Rabin realized that
running out of steam is not the same thing as disap¬
pearing entirely. When he recognized the PLO, Rabin
was not renouncing his belief in Zionism. On the con¬
trary, the man who, after Ben Gurion and Begin2, can
lay claim to the title of king of Israel, is determined to
hang on to what he has achieved. If the war continues,
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
YITZHAK RABIN
a hawk with the wings of a dove
by Luc Beyer de Ryke
it will prove an ever-increasing drain on resources. More
seriously, if it is hard to keep law and order in the
streets of the Occupied Territories, it is impossible to
prevent children from being born: the Palestinian
birth-rate will eventually threaten Zionism.
During the First World War, the French socialist
Marcel Sembat proclaimed: "Make war or make a king."
The French did both: in Georges Clemenceau, known as
"the Tiger", they found a republican king who waged
war and won it. Rabin is just as tough as "the Tiger".
But making war does not preclude hard thinking. Rabin
may be quick-tempered, but he also has a methodical
and well-ordered mind. Indeed, he is sometimes criti¬
cized for being almost too rational. If you go to war and
lasting victory eludes you, it is as if you had lost the war.
The important thing for Rabin is to be able to guarantee
Israel's security and, as a result, the survival of Zionism.
The journey from the icy waters of Oslo Fjord to the
White House was a psychological ordeal for him. But it
was necessary and he made it.
HARD BARGAINING
Rabin is familiar with Washington. He spent years
there as ambassador and knows the workings of Amer¬
ican politics inside out. He has had to deal with people
like Presidents Nixon, Ford and Carter and Secretary
of State Henry A. Kissinger. His main interlocutor was
probably Kissinger. Relations between the two men
were marked by a combination of mutual under¬
standing, disagreement, friendship and complicity as
each fought to defend the interests at once conver¬
gent and divergent of his country. One of the reasons
why Rabin's political rival, Yitzhak Shamir, lost the
1992 elections was probably that he and the White
House were no longer on the same wavelength. Begin
had gradually loosened the traditional ties between
Israel and the United States. Shamir soured relations
even further. In the end, while Israel expected much of
Rabin, so did the United States.
But did the Israelis realize, when they elected
Rabin, that the hawk would sprout the wings of a dove?
It remains to be seen just how far Rabin is now pre¬
pared to go. The peace accords are being implemented
with only lukewarm determination. The letter and the
spirit of the law arc two different things. The tram¬
mels of occupation have been eased in Gaza and
Jericho, but they remain firmly in place in the rest of
the Territories. To be sure, the Palestinians are now in
charge of education, health and tourism in those areas,
and that is already something. But, as an Israeli jour¬
nalist has pointed out: "In the Territories, you open
your newspaper and read reassuring headlines; then
you open your window and see an Israeli patrol driving
past." As for Palestinian prisoners, many are being
released, but even more remain behind bars.
It is hard to decide what degree of generosity
should be shown when it forms an integral part of polit¬
ical bargaining. It is a difficult game to play, and there
are many players. There are Palestinians, Jordanians
and Syrians, not to mention Israeli public opinion,
which probably approves Rabin's policies, though
nowadays only halfheartedly.
For the time being, Rabin wants to stick to the
Accord, whether it ends up being called the Oslo,
Washington or Cairo Accord. The agreement implies, in
his eyes, a refusal to accept a Palestinian "state". But
Rabin-watchers think he may shift his ground if the
peace process works. If this turns out to be the case, a
Palestinian "state" would no longer have the explosive
repercussions which the Israelis fear today.
Fresh elections are due a year from now, and for the
first time the Prime Minister will be elected by universal
su ffrage. It is thought that Rabin intends to stand. Were
he to win, Israel would get a taste of a republican
monarchy of the kind experienced by the French under
Charles de Gaulle and François Mitterrand.
If Yahweh and the electorate smile on him, that
election will mark the official consecration of Yitzhak
Rabin as king of Israel and, perhaps, a new stage in the
long road towards peace. I
1. The name given by Israelis to those born in the region of the
modern state of Israel. Ed.
2. Menachem Begin, Prime Minister of Israel from 1977 to 1983.
Joint winner, with President Anwar El Sadat of Egypt, of the 1978
iNobel Peace Prize. Ed.
LUC BEYER DE RYKE,
of Belgium, isa
journalist with his
country's French-
language radio and
television service
(RTBF). He is the
author of several
books on political
subjects, Including
two about Africa,
and an
autobiography.
h5
nn>3V;>3
ryoa
In September 1993 ET 'V
demonstrators in Tel u^Bvftl
Aviv-Jaffa show their jnri > ('
support for the ^ ' :	
policy of seeking
agreement with the ffifi IF
PLO.
.
oprt
I ,U1|
oyrt]
FT
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
YASSER ARAFAT
by Lotfi El-Kholy
aiestine
"rWlhis is the most difficult situation that we've
-M. ever had to face," Yasser Arafat told me one
day in 1982. We were in his little hotel room over¬
looking the sea, a few kilometres outside Tunis, where
the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) had
recently gone into exile after the war in Lebanon. "And
yet," he went on, "there is a glimmer of hope because
we now know that we must choose between existing or
not existing."
Suddenly he broke into a smile and said, "Have you
heard the latest one about Abu Ammar1?" Sometimes
he talks about himself in the third person. "They say
that one day he made the pilgrimage to Mecca. When
it came to his turn to stone the devil by throwing the
customary seven rocks at him, Abu Ammar only threw
six. When somebody asked him why he hadn't thrown
the seventh rock, Abu Ammar answered, 'Do you think
I'm crazy enough to cut off all my links with the
devil?'" And he burst out laughing.
I said I was surprised to see him laugh at a joke
that made him look like a common opportunist. Still
laughing, he answered, "It's a long time since I was
upset by accusations of opportunism. Because of the
secrecy that surrounds them, some of our decisions can
only be understood by a small number of leaders. But
that's not the most important thing. What counts is
whether or not a leader can face up to his conscience
every night before he goes to sleep when he has the
opportunity to sleep!"
I think that this is one of the keys to Yasser
Arafat's personality. The revolutionary rushes impetu¬
ously to the edge of the precipice and then at the last
minute stops himself from tumbling into adventurism
and, political animal that he is, gets ready to take one
or two steps backwards, open up an escape route and
then return to the logic of revolution by another route,
or else open up a new avenue for political action to har¬
vest the fruit of revolutionary action.
FROM REVOLUTIONARY...
In the early days of his combat he believed in the total
liberation of Palestine, from the Mediterranean to the
Jordan, by force of arms. He talked in terms of perma¬
nent revolution, and his watchword was that Palestine
could only be recovered at gunpoint. With experience,
more direct contact with reality and growing awareness of
the real power struggles between Arabs, between Arabs
and Israelis, and between Arabs and the rest of the world,
the political animal began to mature, merge with the rev¬
olutionary activist, keep an eye on him and calculate
what the revolution could accomplish in material terms.
His goal shifted from the liberation of the whole of Pales¬
tine to establishing a Palestinian state on the West Bank
and in Gaza, with East Jerusalem as its capital.
Yasser Arafat
(centre) at Unesco
Headquarters in
Paris during the
ceremony at which
he received the
Houphouët-Boigny
Peace Prize. Beside
him is Federico
Mayor. At left and
right, the two other
prize-winners,
Shimon Peres and
Yitzhak Rabin.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
He stopped defending the hijacking of aircraft and
terrorist operations against Israeli civilians, and
focused armed operations exclusively on Israeli mili¬
tary targets. Later, he refused to let the Intifada use
weapons, insisting on the use of civil disobedience,
strikes and stone-throwing against the Israeli security
forces. After being admitted to the United Nations, he
made it increasingly clear that he was determined to
recognize Israel within its pre-June 1967 borders in
exchange for recognition of the Palestinian people and
the PLO.
He also refined the strategy of harassment and
political cat and mouse with the Arab regimes without
ever going so far as to break with them. He has often
said that "Breaking off ties with an Arab country is a
luxury that beleaguered Palestine can ill afford, no
matter what insults or personal grief are involved."
He has survived ten or more assassination attempts
and has always found out for himself who was behind
them. He has always stopped short of throwing the sev¬
enth rock at the devil, be he Arab, Israeli or Palestinian.
He is constantly meditating on the lessons of his
experience and records all his thoughts and conversa¬
tions in small notebooks that are never far away. No
matter who he is talking to, he never hesitates to pull
out a notebook and jot down anything he thinks is
important. By now he must possess more than four
thousand of these notebooks, numbered in chronolog¬
ical order.
The late Abu Iyad2 often told me about Arafat as
he was in the late 1940s when they were both members
Oni July 1994
Yasser Arafat
returned to Gaza
after a long exile.
LOTFI EL-KHOLY
is an Egyptian
author and political
essayist. Since
1988 he has been
Secretary-General of
the Afro-Asian
Writers' Association.
of the Palestinian Students' Union; of which Arafat
was the president. "He was full of vitality. We mem¬
bers of the executive board would meet and divide up
our activities for the week. Two days later, we would
be called in to see that Yasser Arafat had done all our
jobs by himself. He would ask us to discuss what he
had done and give our approval. We would accuse him
of trespassing on our territory. But he would say,
'Why? What harm have I done? Go on. I'm ready to be
judged.' We would ask him why he had acted on his
own. 'The opportunity presented itself,' he would say,
'and I didn't want to let it slip by. I assumed my
responsibilities as president.'"
Something of this activism survived in Abu Ammar
when he became chairman of the PLO. "It's true that
Abu Ammar sticks to the collectively decided policy
line," Abu Iyad told me. "But just as he did when he
was president of the Palestinian Students' Union,
whenever he can he takes the initiative to put the col¬
lective policy line into action. He can never wait. He
moves faster than other people."
...TO POLITICIAN
As a result, he has often been accused of exercising
personal power. This charge has even been made
against him before the Palestinian leadership, and
frank, sometimes stormy, exchanges have taken place,
with Arafat by turns silent and combative. But these
meetings have always ended with almost unanimous
renewal of confidence in him. The man who has given
everything to the revolution his life, his time and his
personal wealth has become the symbol of the Pales¬
tinian cause.
One day in 1993, at a time when he was the target of
considerable criticism, it was reported that he had been
killed in a plane crash. At once Palestinians everywhere
began to mourn, and when it transpired that Abu Ammar
had survived the crash unharmed, the mourning sponta¬
neously changed into a tidal wave of joy.
Abu Ammar is not the only name given him by his
companions and the children of his people. They also
call him the "father", the "master" and the "khtiare"
(wise old man). After the landmark agreement between
Israelis and Palestinians had been reached, Professor
Edward Said, who had been one of Arafat's closest
friends, made a violent attack on him in the press.
When he read Said's article, Arafat immediately dic¬
tated a telegram which read: "My dear Edward, I have
read your article. I want to tell you that I'll be
returning to Palestine in February 1994. Come and join
us and help build it on the ground. Your brother,
Yasser Arafat." M
1. Abu Ammar is Yasser Arafat's nom de guerre. Ed.
2. Abu Iyad, a leading PLO member, was killed in 1991. Ed.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
JIMMY CARTER
by Flora Lewis
the pilgrim-presi¡dent
When Jimmy Carter left the White House in 1981
after one term as president of the United
States, he was not popular with Americans. Since then,
more and more of his compatriots have come to say,
"Carter is the best ex-President we've ever had." He
had chosen neither to retire in sour resentment at the
electorate's ingratitude nor in fading but leisurely emi¬
nence, but to dedicate himself with undiminished
energy to the causes that grip him. They cover a broad
spectrum, and usually he pursues them quietly. But
now and then there are spectacular, news-making
bursts.
His trips to North Korea, to Haiti and to Bosnia in
rapid succession in 1994 were so startling that cartoon¬
ists were inspired to draw a desolate, hopeless war
scene or even a furiously quarreling husband and wife
over a caption that said some version of "Send for
Jimmy Carter." A miracle worker? A meddler? A right¬
eous, naive moralizer? He was accused of all, and he
didn't seem to care.
In those three mediations, he brought spectacular
results in one case Haiti where he persuaded the
governing military junta to depart peacefully, permit¬
ting the elected president, Jean-Bertrand Aristide, to
return under protection of an American invasion force
without a shot being fired. In North Korea, he also
defused an imminent threat of war, on terms accept¬
able to the U.S. government but criticized by its
domestic opponents as giving insufficient guarantees
that Pyongyang was abandoning its ambition to build
nuclear weapons, the issue of the crisis. In Bosnia, he
achieved no more than a tenuous four-month cease-fire,
less than fully observed but still bringing more respite
Managua
(Nicaragua), 1990.
Jimmy Carter heads
an international
observer mission
during the
presidential election.
than dozens of previous cease-fires and providing
breathing space for more negotiations which may or
may not get anywhere. This is a mixed score, but in all
cases lives, perhaps a great many lives, were saved.
Problems were left, of course, but he had achieved the
purpose of giving peace a chance.
Mr. Carter has been embarking on such missions for
quite a while, and he brings to them not only his
stature and prestige but an accumulation of tech¬
niques and attitudes developed by hard, and some¬
times negative, experience. He explained some of them
in an interview in the New York Times magazine with
Jim Wooten, an American journalist who had written
his biography.
For one thing, he isn't afraid of failure. This was
critical in Pale, where he made clear to the Bosnian
Serb leader Radovan Karadzic that he would just walk
away empty-handed if minimum terms weren't
accepted. He had no personal stake in the appearance
of success. Further, he was aware that Karadzic had
already lied to him, as so often to others. That
encounter had begun when a delegation of American
Serbs called on him in his home town of Plains,
Georgia, with an invitation from Karadzic to take part
in peace efforts. "I knew he wanted to use me," Carter
told Wooten, "so I told them I'd consider it only if the
Serbs would agree to a cease-fire."
DOING THE RIGHT THING
Word came back that Karadzic would go much fur¬
ther. He would end the war, free all UN hostages,
reopen Sarajevo airport, allow free movement for
peace-keepers, release all Muslim prisoners under nine¬
teen, respect human rights, and accept a cease-fire in
Sarajevo before Carter's arrival. None of that hap¬
pened by the time he got to Bosnia, shortly before
Christmas, as many had warned Carter to expect. Hé
wasn't optimistic, but he went to Karadzic's head¬
quarters at Pale with his proposals nonetheless.
There, he took care to observe another of his nego¬
tiating precepts. No recriminations, suspension of
judgment, allowing enough time for interlocutors "to
understand that there's nothing on the table except a
mutual effort to reach some sort of agreement. Of
course, there has to be a table. People in conflict have
to be willing to talk about ending it, or at least
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
FLORA LEWIS,
a noted American
journalist
specializing in
foreign affairs, is the
author of several
books, including
Europe: Road to
Unity (1992).
Jimmy Carter acted
as an observer
during the
presidential election
in Haiti (1990).
changing it, and there has to be someone willing to talk
to them, however odious they are and that's where I
come in."
Carter is a deeply religious man, a "born again
Christian", which means an adult rededication to the
ideals and principles of his faith. It has brought a rec¬
titude and austerity to his own behaviour and a confi¬
dence that he knows precisely what is right that can
seem chilling at a distance. But he can also muster a
tolerance and indulgence for others, whatever despi¬
cable things they've done, that give him an apparent
belief that no one is beyond redemption, everyone
should be given the chance to be humane and resolve
conflict.
His words of kindness and sympathy for the Haitian
leaders who had such a murderous record shocked
many. But he thought it worthwhile and wasn't
ashamed to tell what he called "a little white lie"
about President Clinton's acceptance of the Haitian
pseudo-President's signature on their departure agree¬
ment if that's what it took to get them out of the way
without war. He isn't interested in retribution, but in
solutions. He's after getting something done, and he is
remarkably resistant to personal attack. Nothing said
about him seems to irritate him more than the sugges¬
tion that his motivation is personal enchancement, that
his goal is the Nobel Peace Prize.
"I do what I do because I think it's the right thing
to do," he told Wooten. "Most of the time, believe it or
not, I enjoy myself. Sometimes I even have fun doing
my duty. Imagine that," he said with a chuckle.
All recent American presidents have set up libraries
and sometimes foundations, but unlike the others
which are essentially devoted to history, the Carter
Center at Emory University and the adjoining Carter
Library, in Atlanta, are action-oriented. They run lots
of conferences, the modern version of monastic convivi¬
ality, but also a surprising variety of programmes that
deal with regional problems, health scourges, agricul¬
tural innovation, human rights and, of course, conflict
resolution.
Carter has established a Council of Freely Elected
Heads of Government, which sends teams to monitor
elections in Latin America and has on occasion made the
difference between rigged and reasonably honest votes
that actually brought a democratic transfer of power.
Nicaragua and Guyana are examples. He has been per¬
sonally involved in peace negotiations in Liberia, between
Ethiopia and the Eritrean rebels, and in Sudan. Some¬
times there is a long preparation, many trips establishing
personal contacts, before he gets results. Sometimes
there are no results. He shows no discouragement, as he
shows no triumphalism when he succeeds.
FORCE OF CONVICTION
There are aspects to his personality that were abrasive
and hurt him with the American public when he was in
office. He ran against Washington, as an outsider, one of
the folks, and it got him elected. To prove he hadn't
become pompous and self-inflated, he was pho¬
tographed carrying his own suitcase on official trips,
even revealing anguished exhaustion while jogging.
Many Americans weren't comfortable with that much
show of being "just like us"; they weren't sure they
wanted that un-presidential looking a president. His
toothy smile was taut, and he spoke earnestly of
national "malaise," put in sharp contrast by his suc¬
cessor Bonald Beagan, who always assured Americans
they were "Number One" in the world and looked
relaxed and cheerful whatever happened. It may be a
flaw of human nature, but it shouldn't be surprising
that people found Dr. Feel-good more appealing than
Dr. Do-right.
Even Carter's name somehow set him apart, instead
of giving him the aura of friendly familiarity he seemed
to suppose. His proper name is James Earl Carter, Jr.,
and when he became president many thought it
unseemly to call him by the nickname Jimmy. But he
had grown up and governed Georgia as Jimmy, and he
insisted that he hadn't changed and neither should the
name he went by.
To look at, he is a medium sort of man, neither
large nor small, overwhelming nor reclusive, impressive
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
nor indistinguishable, not the type that immediately
draws the eye of strangers. His force lies not in person¬
ality but in conviction. He eschews florid rhetoric and
sets himself clear and narrowly defined objectives,
wiping out the plague of guinea worm in Africa, getting
a cease-fire in Bosnia. He wants to change the world,
but accepts that it can best be done in specific, modest
steps, and his persistence in pressing them is relentless.
No doubt historians will give his presidency better
marks than did his contemporaries. His contributions
to America's relations with the world were lasting: the
Panama Canal treaty, the Camp David peace treaty
between Egypt and Israel, the nuclear arms reduction
treaty with the U.S.S.R., establishment of diplomatic
relations with China, and perhaps most important of
all and undoubtedly of great personal satisfaction to
him, the establishment of human rights as a functional,
significant part of the international agenda. The
Helsinki accords, which made the way a government
treats its own citizens a legitimate international con¬
cern and not an exclusive sovereign matter, were signed
by his predecessor, Gerald Ford. But it was Jimmy
Carter who gave substance to the paper promises.
AN ITINERANT PRIVATE CITIZEN
Somehow, it has turned out that the 39th president of
the United States has won more affection and admira¬
tion as an itinerant private citizen, sticking his nose into
other people's quarrels, than he did as the head of a
super-power. At a time when U.S. involvement in the
world seems to be shrinking and others worry more
about the country's indifference than what they used
to consider a will to dominate, Jimmy Carter's almost
ubiquitous efforts have a special value. He admits he
shares the common human pleasure at being appreci¬
ated, but he isn't much moved by criticism or reward
because he has his own sense of fulfilment in doing.
When interviewer Wooten insisted that he must
really want the Nobel peace prize, saying, "But you
wouldn't reject it, would you? I mean, you'd like to be
chosen, right?" Carter replied, "Of course, but I'm
telling you that isn't what this is all about. Doesn't even
come close. My goodness, what if it were? What if the
Nobel were the be-all and end-all of my existence? And
what if it never happened? . . . Well, what sort of dried-
up, shriveled-up, disappointed old prune of a man
would I be then?"
That he isn't. He is still running to see to the things
he sees a need to do. And then he goes home, to his
modest house in Plains, Georgia, a modest country
town, and walks the land that gives his sense of place
and permanence. It is a 2,000-acre spread, some of it in
the family for 150 years, and on parts of it he farms
the lowly peanut. Nothing grandiose, but his earth, his
feeling of having a purpose and serving it to his utmost
capacity.
Juanearlos I In
Madrid in 1988.
Juan Carlos I of Spain is a king for our times. Not
for him ermine robes, crown, sceptre, or throne
although he was well and truly on the throne when he
brought about the collapse of an attempted military
coup in February 1981. On that occasion he revealed
his moral stature to his fellow citizens and showed the
world his democratic convictions.
"The Crown cannot tolerate the slightest act or
behaviour that seeks to disrupt by force the democ¬
ratic process enshrined in the constitution that has
been approved by the Spanish people by refer¬
endum." With these words the King ended his short
and solemn television address on the night of 23-24
February 1981, when the government, the parliament
and a group of journalists were being held inside the
Cortes by a clique of officers nostalgic for the old
regime.
Juan Carlos's action served to inject an anti-putsch
vaccine into the fragile, youthful body of Spanish
democracy. Ever since, no Spaniard has ever had to
ask what the king is there for.
His opposition to the putsch, which marked a final
break with the previous regime, endorsed the legitimacy
of a monarch who from that moment could rightfully be
called the "democratic King of Spain". His democratic
purpose had, of course, already been clearly shown
during the difficult transition period, but here suddenly
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
JUAN CARLOS I
the democratic king
by Ramón Luis Acuña
it was expressed in a founding act that confirmed the
shift from dictatorship to democracy.
After inheriting from General Franco full powers
over the army, the Council of Ministers, the Cortes and
the legislative system, the King thus rendered to the
people a sovereignty that was a political hot potato
since it was based on a military victory won in the
Spanish Civil War of 1936 to 1939. He returned Spain,
according to a widely used phrase, "to the hands of the
Spanish people" and, with the agreement of all democ¬
ratic forces, applied the Constitution approved in
1978. This Constitution is in many respects one of the
most advanced in Europe, particularly concerning
regional political freedoms and the defence of the
rights of cultural minorities.
Juan Carlos's actions met the expectations of
Spanish civil society which had entered the post-
Franco era long before Franco's death and wished to
get into step with the civil societies of the other devel¬
oped countries of Europe. At first, some politicians
wrongly saw Juan Carlos as the successor of the pre¬
vious regime, even going so far as to nickname him
"Juan Carlos the Short". They could not have been
more mistaken. Juan Carlos soon came to embody the
Spanish people's aspirations for change one of the
profoundest collective feelings expressed in Europe in
the second half of the twentieth century.
The King always insists that "the protagonist of the
transition was the people" and that he has done
nothing more than his duty in assuming the responsi¬
bility that history and the demands of the moment
imposed on him.
He was in fact the catalyst of a decisive political
change that astonished other democratic societies and
gave hope to those still subject to dictatorship. The
transfer of power in Spain was a model, a source of
inspiration for guiding democratic changes not only in a
number of Latin American countries but also, and
despite a very different political situation, in the
Eastern bloc countries, including Russia.
Juan Carlos started out from a simple, solid prin¬
ciple: he wished to be "the King of all the Spaniards"
that he was proclaimed to be in the posters waved by
his supporters on coronation day, 22 November 1975.
During the
attempted putsch
of 23 February
1981, 200 Civil
Guards invaded the
Spanish Parliament.
He would not only be the king of those who had won
the Civil War; he would also be the King of those who
had lost it. He would not only be the king of the Castil¬
lans and the Aragonese; he would also be the king of
the Basques, the Catalans, the Galicians and the other
inhabitants of Spanish territory. His attitude coincided
with the widespread opinion in the political parties in
favour of national reconciliation, the feeling that the
Civil War was a thing of the past: Spaniards realized
that while change was inevitable, a brutal break with
the immediate past could lead to serious confronta¬
tions. In consequence most of them chose the middle
way of reason, and their king, like them, preferred to
build the future rather than dwell on the past.
HISTORIC RECONCILIATIONS
And so he obeyed a second principle: that the rank of
monarch is not conferred by divine right or exclusively
by inheritance. It must be earned by doing the job well.
A monarchy only makes sense if it shows itself to be
useful to the nation. If it does not, it may become
redundant or even harmful, as happens when it falls
into discredit. Because of this approach, a two-thou¬
sand year-old institution provided what the king called
"a propulsive stimulus" to the modernization of Spain.
The king's third goal was harder to implement. He
wished to effect without violence or trauma the transi¬
tion from a dictatorial government to a constitutional
monarchy. The former regime was anachronistic and
lifeless, held together until the end by nothing more
than its autocratic figurehead. The ship had to be
scuttled. On his own and caught in a cross-fire between
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
RAMON LUIS
ACUÑA,
of Spain, is
assistant general
manager of the
Spanish news
agency EFE and
special advisor for
communications to
UNESCO. His most
recent published
work is Las Tribus de
Europa (1994, "The
tribes of Europe").
King Juan Carlos
(centre) out walking.
the hostility of the hardline Franco supporters and the
initial mistrust of the democrats, Juan Carlos used the
wide powers he had received with skill and determina¬
tion. "Everyone was against me," he said later. But he
succeeded in influencing the course of events. The
authoritarian structure was methodically dismantled
without bloodshed, and democracy built on its ruins.
The facts speak for themselves. This is the "democ¬
ratic king's" contribution to the history of Spain.
His powers are defined by the constitution. As
arbiter and guarantor of the institutions, the king is
the head of the armed forces and his country's highest-
ranking representative abroad. However, he appoints
the head of government in strict conformity with elec¬
tion results and can only dissolve parliament if
requested to do so by the head of the executive. His
authority is primarily of a moral nature.
Juan Carlos has a high reputation in Spain. More
than 80 per cent of Spaniards questioned in polls over
the years have given a favourable opinion of him. He
has become the most popular king in Europe. This is
largely due to his warm personality and joviality. He
has a straightforward manner which immediately puts
people at their ease. He likes laughter and jokes. Once
when I was interviewing him, some small change
slipped out of my pocket and onto the armchair where
I was sitting. When I was leaving, a member of his staff
caught me up on the staircase, handed me the coins,
and said, "His Majesty has asked me to tell you that for
the moment he makes no charge for interviews."
But this relaxed manner should not be misinter¬
preted. Juan Carlos is thoughtful and well-informed,
an avid reader of books, reports and newspapers. In pri¬
vate he is extremely spontaneous; in public and in the
performance of his duties he detests improvisation.
He loves family life and spends as much time as he
can with his children. He takes advice from his wife,
Queen Sophia, whose "inestimable support and under¬
standing" he readily acknowledges. A sports enthu¬
siast, he runs every day, rides off on his motorbike
whenever he can, sails in summer and skis in winter. For
a fifty-eight-year-old, his physical activity is intense.
When I last visited Cartagena in Colombia, the
guide who showed me around that beautiful colonial
town kept saying, "and here, when the king came. . . ."
After a while I asked him which king he was referring
to. "Our king, of course! Who else?" he answered
without hesitation. Just as he has managed to trans¬
form the Spanish into "Juancarlistas", if not outright
royalists, Juan Carlos has succeeded in being sponta¬
neously dubbed "the king" by Latin Americans.
Reconciliation within Spain has also led to historic
reconciliations with the world outside. Regarded in
Latin America as a symbol of the new democratic
Spain, Juan Carlos has to a large degree contributed to
reestablishing links with Spanish-speaking nations on
the other side of the Atlantic. In 1991 he was the
prime mover for an annual Latin-American summit and
himself attends these meetings of heads of state
designed to reinforce the community of Spanish- and
Portugese-speaking countries. In Madrid in 1992, com¬
memorating the 500th anniversary of the discovery of
America, Juan Carlos spoke in full awareness of criti¬
cism of Spanish and Portuguese colonization when he
declared, "We must assume our part in the history of
peoples with dignity and responsibility in order to
make a better future." He often points out that Spain
promulgated the "Law of the Indies", the social
aspects of which were extremely progressive and that
the first universities in the Americas were founded in
Lima and Santo Domingo in the sixteenth century at a
time when many European cities had none.
A MODERNIZING MONARCHY
Also in 1992, 500 years after the expulsion of the Jews
from Spain, Juan Carlos paid tribute in the Madrid syn¬
agogue to the "Spanish Jews who had to leave Spain
because the state saw religious uniformity as the basis
of its unity". He went on to express the wish that
"never again should hatred or intolerance provoke grief
or exile".
The 500th anniversary of the fall of the last Muslim
bastion in Spain, the Kingdom of Granada, also
occurred in 1992. On that occasion Juan Carlos paid
tribute to Arab Andalusia, Al-Andalus, as a place
where "several peoples formed the habit of sharing
over the centuries and where each of them maintained
their respective identities without losing respect for
difference". This history shared between the Jews and
Arabs for centuries "left a cultural heritage in Spain of
supreme importance," said the king, "and contributed
to the definition of Spanish national identity." These
thoughts also harmonize with current Spanish thinking
that is trying to recover the culturally rich roots the
country is so proud of.
During one of my interviews with King Juan Carlos I
asked him what was left for him to do in Spain since, if
one looked at his list of achievements, his task seemed
to be complete. "You must be joking," he said with his
usual candour. "There is much to be done. Nothing less
than the modernization and renovation of Spain. And in
this field too, I'd like the crown to be a spur."
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
FISH FARMING:
A 4,000-YEAR-OLD
GROWTH INDUSTRY
by France Bequette
Right, skimming
floating weeds
from fish ponds
in Bangladesh.
FRANCE
BEQUETTE
is a Franco-
American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
questions.
Four thousand years ago the
Egyptians were already
successfully farming Tilapia
or "Nile carp" (Oreochromis
niloticus). It is still a highly
regarded species: about 500,000
tonnes of it are produced world¬
wide today. Carp-raising has been
a part of Chinese and Vietnamese
traditions for centuries.
Aquaculture, which was
rediscovered in the 1960s as a
weapon in the fight against
hunger, is the raising of fish, mol¬
luscs, crustaceans and plants
either in salt or fresh water. By
1990 fish were providing about
15 per cent of the protein con¬
sumed worldwide. The United
Nations Food and Agriculture
Organization (FAO) estimates
that by the turn of the century
fish produced by aquaculture
will comprise up to 20 per cent
of the world supply of fish and
will be the major source of pro¬
tein in developing nations.
While the world harvest from
capture fisheries has barely
increased since 1988 (rising 0.5
per cent between 1990 and
1991), aquaculture production
has grown steadily since 1984
(doubling between 1984 and
1992) with an annual growth rate
of 9 per cent. Global fish produc
tion reached 98.1 million tonnes
in 1992, 13.9 million tonnes (9.4
million tonnes offish and 4.5 mil¬
lion tonnes of molluscs and crus¬
taceans) of which came from
aquaculture.
To maintain the current level
of world fish consumption, i.e. an
average of 13 kg per head per
year, until the year 2010, 91 mil¬
lion tonnes of edible fish will have
to be produced to feed the
earth's projected population of 7
billion. In other words the pre¬
sent level of aquaculture produc¬
tion will have to be doubled. This
is an attainable goal. Yet contrary
to what might be thought, fish¬
farming is not easy, especially if
the need to protect the environ¬
ment is taken into account.
CAPTIVE CATFISH
The advantages of expanding
aquaculture are obvious. At the
same time, the different systems
used, ranging from small-scale
fish farming to high-yield indus¬
trial plants, pose numerous prob¬
lems. A 1989 report produced by
the Organization of Economic Co¬
operation and Development
(OECD) asked a number of
important questions. Is there a
risk that fish farming will modify
natural populations and reduce
biological diversity? Is it wise to
introduce exotic species? Might
not fish farming cause the spread
of disease? What effects might
waste deposited in lakes, rivers
and coastal zones have in the long
term? What happens to chemical
products such as antibiotics that
are used in aquaculture? Are fish
farming zones wisely chosen? Is it
possible to predict the impact of
aquaculture on the environment
by using computer-generated
models?
Let us look at the example of
Viet Nam, where fish are farmed
in ponds (64 per cent), rice pad¬
dies (21 per cent) and floating
cages in rivers (15 per cent) and
the exploitation of water
resources makes a major contribu¬
tion to the economy. The continent
of which Viet Nam forms part is,
moreover, the runaway champion
in aquaculture. Asia supplies 84
per cent of world production, fol¬
lowed by Europe (8.5 per cent),
North America (3.7 per cent),
South America (2.3 per cent), the
former Soviet Union (0.9 per cent)
and Africa (0.5 per cent).
A single species of catfish
(Pangasius bocourti, ca ba sa in
Vietnamese) constitutes almost
three-quarters of floating-pen
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
production in Viet Nam, where
most fish farming is concentrated
in the Mekong Delta region. Until
recently supplying the farms with
young fish meant taking ten to fif¬
teen million young fish from their
natural hatcheries in the Tonle
Sap ("great lake") of Cambodia
during the rainy season (July to
November). The disadvantages of
this system are obvious. A natural
habitat is depopulated and the
source of supply depends on the
political relations between two
countries. Last May scientists
from the Continental, Mediter¬
ranean and Tropical Aquaculture
Group (GAMET) in Montpellier
(France) succeeded in getting the
catfish to reproduce in captivity.
This is a momentous development
for Vietnamese fish-farming,
especially since the price of
young fish fluctuates widely.
The fish are raised in pens
that float under houses. They are
fed with a paste made of rice-
bran and fresh fish, and are also
given human and animal refuse.
Aquaculture is a profitable way
of using wastes.
CULTURE AND AQUACULTURE
Surprisingly, in both Viet Nam
and China, where this technique
began, ponds used as latrines or
fertilized with manure prove to
be excellent for fish-farming.
Jerome Lazard, head of the
"Aquaculture and Fish Pro¬
gramme" in the department of
farming and veterinary medicine
at France's Centre for Interna¬
tional Co-operation in Agronomic
Research for Development
(CIRAD) says that there is no risk
of fish transmitting disease-
bearing germs to people if the
fish are left to swim freely in
clean water for a few days in
order to cleanse themselves both
inside and out. Lazard regrets
that this process is not practised
widely enough. Although con¬
sumers say they do not want to
eat these "dirty fish", the
130,000 tonnes (minimum) pro¬
duced in this fashion find buyers
nevertheless.
"Wherever ponds can be cre¬
ated," says Jerome Lazard, "they
constitute wonderful fish produc¬
tion facilities, since they blend
perfectly into agricultural produc¬
tion systems by helping to improve
water quality and by using various
by-products and wastes." The
ideal thing is to dig ponds just
downsteam from stables, pigsties
Hauling up a
wicker fish-pen in
a floating village
on Tonlé Sap, a
lake in
northwestern
Cambodia.
FURTHER READING:
The State of World Fisheries and
Aquaculture, FAO, Rome, 1995
Aquatic Biotechnology and Food
Safety, OECD, Paris, 1994
Ceres, FAO review, no. 131,
September 1991
Aquaculture continentale.
Initiatives rurales, the French Ministry
of Agriculture and Forests, no. 9,
1990
AquacultureDeveloping a Hew
Industry, OECD, Paris, 1989
and chicken coops or even to raise
these structures onto piles, which
solves the problem of effluents.
The droppings are nutritious to
the plankton that the fish feed on.
Fish canneries provide
another propitious environment,
for fish are very fond of fish! It
takes one kilo of fish in the form
of meal or oil to produce a kilo of
edible fish. The fish-meal is made
from less appetizing species and
is also used to feed pigs and fowl
and for making surimi, a kind of
fish paste. But since it takes at
least five kilos of fish to make a
kilo of fish meal, supplies of this
food source may eventually
dwindle and thus encourage over¬
fishing.
In order to be viable, the use
of ponds for fish farming must be
culturally acceptable. Writing in
the FAO review, Ceres, Peggy
Polk pointed out that in Africa,
"when experts suggested that
farmers raise fish in the small
ponds used to water cattle and
supply household water needs,
many local people rejected the
A tank of young
fish on a fish farm
in Andalusia
(Spain).
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
idea, insisting the fish would
muddy the water and make it
unsuitable for drinking". In India
it is standard practice to add fer¬
tilizer to water tanks being used
for aquaculture except in
Madhya Pradesh State where
people refuse to allow the fertil¬
ization of water tanks because
they use the same water for
cooking and bathing.
The farmed species also must
be acceptable to prospective con¬
sumers. In some parts of
Colombia, for example, people
traditionally do not eat dorado.
HOOKED ON PROFIT
Profit is probably the most dan¬
gerous bait for the fish-farmer
who is indifferent to the equilib¬
rium of ecosystems. In the 1980s
there was a boom in demand for
the Penaeus monodon shrimp in
the Gulf of Thailand. It was easy
to make a fortune. All it took was
the cash to buy a piece of man¬
grove swamp or to build a grow-
out pond in the estuary of a river.
People said there was more
money in shrimp farming than in
illicit drugs! Between 1983 and
1988 aquaculture in Asia grew at
the rate of 40 per cent a year.
Then, in 1989, 80 per cent of the
farms located near Bangkok,
where most of the activity was
concentrated, went bankrupt.
There were several reasons for
this, including a drop in demand
on the world market, reduced
profit margins and polluted water
due to poor effluent management.
(Dumping too much organic
matter reduces its oxygen con¬
tent, and untreated urban efflu¬
ents carry diseases and promote
the proliferation of algae that are
toxic to fish and humans alike). A
similar collapse had taken place
for similar reasons in Taiwan two
years before. Epidemics had
been caused by over-stocking the
ponds and there had been "mis¬
management of the pond
ecosystem", indiscriminate use of
antibiotics and chemicals and the
use of polluted water. The
results have been disastrous.
Vast areas of mangroves have
been destroyed in Indonesia, the
Philippines and Thailand.
A NEW KIND OF LIVESTOCK
In Europe, especially in Norway,
future candidates for aquacul¬
ture are cod, halibut, turbot,
catfish, lobster and scallops
raised in pens, tanks and, for
certain species like cod and
salmon, by sea-ranching.
Fish fanners use techniques
comparable to those that have
been used for years in animal hus¬
bandry. The salmonids are being
used as guinea-pigs for aquatic
biotechnology, which was the
subject of an OECD report in
1994. ' The fish are not only oper¬
ated on and vaccinated but also
fertilized, sterilized, made to
grow and even change sex. Scien¬
tists are trying to develop salmon
capable of living in the cold polar
waters by implanting the genes
that code for the anti-freeze pro¬
tein into its genome. They have
also injected the growth hormone
gene from the rat into trout, carp
and salmon. In other words, trans¬
genic fish now exist. What will
happen if they escape from their
pens and mingle with their kind
in nature? Fortunately the
greater the genetic difference
between organisms, the less
capable they are of fertilizing
each other.
Another way of obtaining
monosex or male fish (which grow
twice as fast as females) is by
administering "masculinizing"
steroids. "This technique, which
is forbidden in Europe, is widely
used in Asia (Taiwan and the
Philippines) and in Israel," notes
Jerome Lazard with some con¬
cern. "It releases some thirty by¬
products into the water, and we
don't really know its ecological
consequences." Nonetheless,
research is continuing to make
great strides and some concrete
results have already been
obtained. A natural hormone that
is as effective as the artificial
hormone but much easier for fish
to absorb is now available. It is
possible by using heat treatment
to change the sex of young fish
without harming the environ¬
ment. These are some of the
avenues that tomorrow's fish
farmers will be exploring.
1 . Aquatic Biotechnology and Food
Safety, OECD, Paris, 1994
LEADING THE VINE MOTH
ASTRAY
After 20 years of research and experimenta¬
tion, the French National Institute of Agro¬
nomic Research (INRA) has developed an
original way of protecting southern Euro¬
pean vineyards from the European vine
moth (Polychrosis botrana). The new method
consists of disrupting olfactory communi¬
cation between male and female moths, the
latter of which emit a chemical substance
(known as a pherome) to attract males at
mating time. By diffusing a synthetic
pherome in the vineyard it is possible to pre¬
vent the males from detecting the signals
emitted by the females, so that fertilization
does not take place. Only one application is
required, instead of the four or five applica¬
tions of chemical insecticide that are usually
needed in campaigns against the vine moth.
The treatment can be applied in any weather
conditions, leaves no residue and only
affects the moth. It costs slightly more
than the chemical method but is more envi¬
ronment-friendly.
THE IKON OE MOUNT NIMBA
Although mining activities were not dis¬
cussed at the Rio Earth Summit in 1992,
awareness of their impact on the environ¬
ment seems to be growing. It has been
known for years that the Nimba Mountains
in Guinea contain a deposit of about 350 mil¬
lion tonnes of high-grade iron ore (65 per
cent pure iron) which a consortium of mining
companies is eager to develop. But the
range, whose highest point is 1,742-metre-
high Mount Nimba, is also covered by a rain
forest that harbours a number of unique
species. A nature reserve since 1944, it was
accepted as a biosphere reserve by Unesco
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
w
in 1980 and registered on the World Heritage
List in 1981. Environmentalists wonder
whether the world's need for iron ore is so
great that mining Mount Nimba should take
precedence over ecological considerations.
China, the former Soviet Union and Brazil
alone supply 450 million tonnes of iron ore
annually; while Nimba would only produce 9
million, i.e. 1 per cent of world production.
Unesco has recently agreed to modify the
World Heritage site to exclude the proposed
mine, but it is to be feared that the influx of
people caused by mining would be harmful
to the natural environment.
ALL THEIR EGGS
IN ONE BASKET
The New Zealand section of the World Wide
Fund for Nature (WWF) has discovered
that, contrary to a widely held belief, the
survival of a species is not threatened if
the gene pool becomes too small. It cites
the example of the Chatham Island Black
Robin, only 5 of which remained in the early
1980s and whose numbers have now risen
to 150, all descendants of the same
breeding pair. They live on two tiny islands
in the Chatham chain, located to the east
of New Zealand.
A MARINE PARK
FOR MAFIA ISLAND
In April this year Tanzania passed legislation
to establish Mafia Island Marine Park, 120
kilometres south of Dar es-Salaam. Mafia
belongs to the Rufiji Delta ecosystem, is
surrounded by a chain of islets and
abounds in coral reefs and seagrass beds.
The environment has been damaged by
dynamite and seine-net fishing, and shell
and coral collection for building-stone and
lime production. The park has been estab¬
lished after a World Wide Fund for Nature
workshop in 1991 and a national campaign.
Most of the park will be a "regulated-use
zone" where sustainable resource use and
development will be promoted. H
SPHINX BITES MOTORWAY
The Egyptian government has agreed to a
Unesco proposal that the planned new
eight-lane motorway that was to cross the
INITIATIVES I
protected site of the plateau of pyramids
to the south of Cairo should be rerouted.
The Glza Plateau is on the World Heritage
List, and the pyramids and the Sphinx,
already suffering from erosion due to cli¬
mate, traffic and air pollution, would have
been exposed to an added threat caused
by car exhaust and vibrations.
PHOSPHATES,
HOW DO
YOU PLEAD?
The water companies that manage France's
drinking-water resources have called for a
ban on the polyphosphates found in deter¬
gents, which, they believe, are largely
responsible for water eutrophication (lack
of oxygen, green or brown colouring and the
spread of microscopic algae). Although
large-scale water purification plants can
dephosphatize urban waste water, much
waste water outside urban areas is
returned to nature without any processing.
A convention signed in 1991 between the
ministry of the environment and the deter¬
gent manufacturers seeks to limit the
phosphate level in detergents to 20 per
cent. France, however, is one of the major
consumers of detergents as well as the
foremost phosphate producer in Europe.
Phosphates have been banned in Switzer¬
land, Canada and Norway
AMERICA'S NEW BREED
OF RANCHER
In the last century when Wendy and Warner Glenn's
great grand-parents settled in the far southwest corner
of Arizona near the New Mexico and Mexican borders,
nobody thought about the environment. By 1960 when
the couple took over the family ranch, things had
become much more complicated. Environmentalists
were criticizing ranchers and complaining about the
degradation of pastureland. Moreover, about half of
the region's half-million hectares of near-desert
belonged to the state. The few people living there felt
victimized by administrative harassment. Burning the
prairie, for example, had been outlawed for nearly
eighty years although it had been practised for thou¬
sands of years in order to ensure the renewal and the
quality of grazing land by preventing the growth of
woody species like mesquite (Prosopis juliflora).
The ranchers soon realized that if they wanted to
get anything done they would have to join forces. In
1993 thirty-five cattle ranchers founded a non-profit
organization called the Malpai Borderlands Group.
"Our goal," they write in their manifesto, "is to restore
and maintain the natural processes that create and
protect a healthy, unfragmented landscape to support
a diverse, flourishing community of human, plant and
animal life in our Borderlands Region." Prairie fires
are no longer systematically opposed, and the first ones
have already taken place, resulting in the growth of
grass and wildflowers.
The Malpai Group also has a programme for the
protection of endangered species. The first beneficiary
has been the Chiricahuan Leopard Frog. During a long
drought last year, one member of the group and his
family hauled 4,000 litres of water each week to a
stock pond to keep some of these frogs alive. The
Malpai Group then began raising funds to sink wells
and install pumps to keep the frogs supplied with
water. Group members also keep their cattle con¬
stantly on the move in order to prevent over-grazing.
They can also benefit from a "Grass Bank", a system
whereby some ranchers make grazing land available to
others who don't have enough. This helps to prevent
over-grazing and division of the land, and gives the
grass time to grow back.
The Malpai Group also works with a botanist from
Tucson, Ray Turner, who has been studying the
region's plant-life for forty years and is able to assess
modifications by means of photographs taken a cen¬
tury ago. And if some ranchers are tempted to sell
their land because the life is too hard, the Malpai
Group vets new buyers to ensure that they protect the
environment by preventing wildcat development of the
beautiful wild valleys by profit-hungry developers,
sub-division of the land, massive incursions of tourists
and cars, industrialization and pollution. I
Malpai Borderlands Group, 6226 Gerónimo Trail Road,
P. O. Drawer 3536, Douglas, AZ 85608 United States.
Tel.: (1-602) 558-2470; Fax: (1-602) 558-2314.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
CHILDREN FOR PEACE
Between May and October 1995, Unesco's Cul¬
ture of Peace Programme and Associated
Schools Project jointly organized 7 festivals for
children in Costa Rica, the Cook Islands, Greece,
Grenada, Jordan, Thailand and Zimbabwe. In each
country children aged from 11 to 13 and their
teachers met to discuss the best ways to pro¬
mote a culture of peace in their immediate envi¬
ronment. The results will provide the basis for a
multimedia teaching kit for international use in
primary and secondary schools. The "Seven
Appeals" written by the children and the material
they made to depict the festivals' most signifi¬
cant moments will be exhibited at Unesco's Paris
Headquarters from 25 October to 16 November
during the 28th session of the Organization's
General Conference. The title of the exhibition will
be "Around the Planet, Children in Quest of a
Peaceful World".
WORLD SUMMIT FOR EDUCATION
THROUGH ART
The International Society for Education through
Art (INSEA) is a UNESCO-affiliated non-govern¬
mental organization which has championed the
role of art in education since 1951. It will be
holding its 29th World Conference, under the
auspices of Unesco, from 8 to 14 July 1996 at the
Lille Conference Centre (France). The general theme
of the conference will be "Art, Science and Envi¬
ronment in the 3rd Millennium: Divorce and Rec¬
onciliation". Hundreds of teachers, research stu¬
dents, artists, philosophers and art historians
are expected to attend some 350 lectures, dis¬
cussions, round-tables and workshops, at which
they will assess the current state of art educa¬
tion and chart guidelines for the future.
For further information contact
Bureau Organisateur du 29e Congrès mondial, INSEA,
Université de Lille III, Maison de la Recherche, BP 149,
59653 Villeneuve d'Ascq, France. Tel.: (33) 20 33-65 08;
Fax: (33) 20 33-64 60; E-mail: insea@univ-Ulle3.Fr
CARACAS, THEATRE CAPITAL OF THE
WORLD, 1995
Under the auspices of Unesco's World Decade
for Cultural Development the International The
atre Institute (ITI) held its 26th World Congress
in Caracas (Venezuela) from 24 to 30 June 1995.
Leading playwrights Including Nobel Laureate
Wole Soyinka (Nigeria), Emilio Carballido (Mexico),
Enrique Buenaventura (Colombia) and Isaac
Chocron (Venezuela) took part in a symposium
on the theme of the Congress, "The Fall of
Utopias and the New Millennium". Hundreds of
actors and actresses from the 93 ITI member-
countries took part in numerous artistic events,
including the first session in Latin America of the
Albert Botbol University of the Theatre of
Nations.
For further information contact
International Theatre Institute, Unesco, 1, rue Miollis,
75732 Paris Cedex 15 (France). Tel.: (33-1) 45 68-26 50;
Fax: (33-1) 45 66-50 40. Cable: INTHEAT.
PEACE EXHIBITION
TRAVELS THE WORLD
To celebrate the end of the Second World War
and the fiftieth anniversary of the United
Nations and to commemorate the bombing of
Hiroshima and Nagasaki, a French association,
"Le Mouvement de la paix", has organized a
multi-disciplinary exhibition in Montluçon
(France) entitled "1995: For a culture of peace".
More than 250 works by artists from some 20
countries were shown. They were divided into
three sections: "Banners of peace" (painting
and poetry), "Images of peace" (photography
and poetry) and "1945-1995 Hiroshima, an
image for peace" (posters). A travelling exhibition
of copies made from the original exhibits will tour
the world until the end of 1996. It has already
visited Locarno (Switzerland) and Hiroshima
(Japan).
For further information contact
"Le Mouvement de la paix", 139, boulevard Victor Hugo,
93400 Saint-Ouen, France.
Tel.: (33-1) 40 12-21 21; Fax: (33-1) 40 11-57 87.
CONTEMPORARY ART
AT THE PALAIS DES NATIONS
An international open-air exhibition of contempo¬
rary art entitled " Dialogues of Peace" was held at
the Palais des Nations in Geneva (Switzerland)
from 2 July to 26 October 1995. The exhibition,
organized by France's Association Française
d'Action Artistique (AFAA) on the occasion of
the 50th anniversary of the United Nations, fea¬
tured paintings, sculptures, installations, pho¬
tographs and videos specially produced for the
occasion by more than fifty up-and-coming or
internationally known artists from five conti¬
nents. A catalogue of the exhibition has been
published by AFAA with a preface by the Secre¬
tary-General of the UN, Mr. Boutros Boutros-
Ghali.
For further information contact
AFAA, Rue du Môle 38 bis, CH-120, Geneva, Switzerland.
SWISS FILM PRIZE
MARKS UNESCO AND UN
ANNIVERSARIES
At the Locarno International Film Festival
(Switzerland) in August 1995 the Swiss National
Commission for Unesco awarded a prize to mark
the 50th anniversary of Unesco and the UN to
Chen Yu-Hsun, a 33-year-old director from Taipeh,
for his film Redai Yu (Tropical Fish). The prize-win¬
ning film shows with a blend of humour and fan¬
tasy how tolerance and respect for human dig¬
nity are possible even in difficult circumstances.
Chen Yu-Hsun also received Unesco's Fellini
Medal commemorating the cinema's one-hun¬
dredth anniversary.
SPOTLIGHT ON ETHICS:
A NEW UNESCO PUBLICATION
The first issue of Spotlight on Ethics, the
newsletter of Unesco's International Bioethics
Committee (IBC), was published earlier this year.
The purpose of the new publication, as defined
by Unesco Director-General Federico Mayor, is to
be "a place for debate and exchange, . . . open to
all committees on ethics and similar bodies all
over the world that are busy developing pro¬
grammes of research, education and informa¬
tion". By publishing background articles as well
as practical Information about international
meetings, publications and institutions con¬
cerned with bioethics, the bilingual (English/
French) newsletter will contribute to efforts by
IBC to define ethical guidelines to accompany
advances in genetics.
For further information contact
Spotlight on Ethics, the Bioethics Unit,
Unesco, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France.
Tel.: (33-1) 45 68-38 03; Fax: (33-1) 45 67-39 15.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The Iguaçu falls
cascading wonder
of the subtropical
forest
by Edouard Bailby
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
On the border between
Argentina and Brazil, the
Iguaçu Falls are one of
the natural wonders of
the world and the main
attraction of the Iguaçu
National Park (Iguazu in
Spanish) which is
registered on UNESCO's
World Heritage List.
The 275 cataracts formed by
the waters of the Iguaçu River,
on the border between Brazil and
Argentina, create a permanent cloud
of spray above the surrounding area.
The breathtakingly spectacular
falls occur above the point where, the
1,320-kilometrc-long Iguaçu, which
rises in southern Brazil, joins the
Paraná, the country's second-largest
river after the Amazon. Twenty-eight
kilometres before the confluence, the
1.2-kilometre-wide Iguaçu suddenly
plunges into an 80-metre-deep
canyon. Its raging waters form an
immense succession of brilliant white
cataracts, forming a horse-shoe
shaped front of 2.7 kilometres. It is
an awesome sight: the mighty roar of
the river as it crashes down to the
bottom of the canyon at an average
rate of 1,700 cubic metres of water
per second, with peaks of nearly four
times that quantity, can be heard for
several kilometres around.
Long before the arrival of the
Spanish, then the Portuguese, in the
sixteenth century, the area belonged
to the Guarani people. Iguaçu means
"great waters" in Guarani. The story
goes that a tribe forming part of a
powerful people known as the
Caiguangue worshipped Tupâ, the
Supreme God, and his son JM'Boi, the
Serpent God. On learning that Tarobá,
a young warrior from a neighbouring
tribe, had fallen in love with the
Indian Naipi and fled with her in a
pirogue, M'Boi flew into a rage. Sum¬
moning up all his strength, he parted
the earth and created the gorges of
the Iguaçu. The pirogue was swept
over the waterfall and vanished into
the raging waters. Tarobá turned into
a palm tree and Naipi became a rock
at the foot of the falls. M'Boi buried
himself upright up to his neck in one
of the caves in the canyon so that he
could keep an eye on the two lovers
and ensure they would never be able
to embrace each other.
A IIAIK-K \ISI\G Tllll»
UPSTltliAM
The river waters flow relentlessly and
at terrific speed through the green
jungle. The surrounding trees harbour
toucans, parrots (in particular the
glaucus macaw, which is an endan¬
gered species) and budgerigars.
Singing birds of every possible hue flit
from branch to branch. Other
denizens of the forest include monkeys
and silently fluttering blue butterflies
of impressive proportions. There are
few large cats, which shun the pres¬
ence of man. But the paths trodden by
visitors are sometimes crossed by deer,
wild pigs and other tropical mammals.
Iguaçu National Park, which was
included on UNESCO's World Heritage
List on 28 November 1986, consists
of two sections, one in Brazil, covering
an area of 1,750 square kilometres,
and the other in Argentina, on the
left bank of the river, covering an area
of 550 square kilometres. The two
sections were connected a few years
ago, when a bridge was built across
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
the Iguaçu downstream from the
Falls. No visitor should fail to visit
both sections, which are very dif¬
ferent in appearance. While the most
impressive spot is the Garganta do
Diabo (Devil's Gorge) in Brazil, it is
only from the Argentinian side that it
is possible to get a panoramic view.
The canyon can be admired in all its
splendour from various forest paths
and from a 117-metre-long footbridge
over the waters. Last year, 970,000
tourists paid the $2 entrance fee to
get into Iguaçu National Park
(Iguazú in Spanish).
Visitors can take a dirt road down
through the forest on the Brazilian
side to a small landing stage on the
Iguaçu River. There, a specially
designed inflatable dinghy waits to
take them on an extraordinary forty-
minute trip. It can accommodate
batches of ten seated passengers at a
EDOUARD BAILBY
is a French journalist who has been a correspondent
with the weekly L'Express and a press officer in
Unesco's Office of Public Information. He is the author
of guides to Cuba (4th edition, 1993) and Hungary
(1991) published by Arthaud, Paris.
time equipped with lifebelts. The
boat takes off at spectacular speed.
Firmly fastened to his seat, the pilot
is forced to drive upstream at a speed
of 80-100 kmh in order to overcome
the force of the current and to wend
his way between whirlpools and
rocks. As it is swept along by its own
momentum, the dinghy sometimes
rears almost vertically out of the
water, before falling back and contin¬
uing on its difficult way upriver, even¬
tually gliding gently along the
Macuco falls, whose countless
droplets form a translucent haze.
Till] DANGERS OF TOUKISM
Can tourism harm this spectacular
site? Until now, it has not done so,
since both Brazil and Argentina have
taken the necessary steps to protect
wildlife. But the fragile balance of
the forest could be jeopardized if
either country were to take a wrong
decision. Controversy has already
been caused by the helicopters
which carry tourists on trips above
the falls every day.
The fact is that the Brazilians and
Argentinians are chiefly interested in
protecting the Park from poaching
and the illegal felling of palm trees.
At night, groups of men creep
secretly into the forest to hunt game
and fish for salmon in the Iguaçu.
Others trade in palm hearts, which
they gather in Brazil and sell in
Argentina, where they fetch a higher
price. Contraband has declined
thanks to the presence of the forest
rangers, but there are only about fifty
of them, which is not enough to
guard an area of 2,300 square kilo¬
metres. It is all the easier for
poachers to trespass on the Park
because it is not surrounded by a
buffer zone. When it was created in
1939, says José Carlos Ramos,
director of the Brazilian Park, the
notion that nature reserves needed to
be protected did not yet exist.
The Brazilian journalist and envi¬
ronmentalist Jackson Lima, with the
support of his Argentine colleagues,
has denounced various plans hatched
by private companies with an eye to
profit. One multinational woidd like
to illuminate the falls at night. The
cost of the installation would be Si.4
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
million. "What do they want to do?
Frazzle birds with the heat of their
lamps?" asks Lima. "We get a full
moon every month it's much more
beautiful!" Another company has
plans for a seventy-metre-high tower
with a revolving restaurant at the lop,
from which diners would be able to
admire the falls. A third linn has
come up with the idea of building a
miniature Disneyland-type railway
that would run around the cataracts.
In the last twenty years, 85 per
cent of the rainforest cover on the
banks of the Paraná River has been
destroyed to make way for fields of
wheat and soya. Straddling the Iguaçu
as it does, the National Park has
ended up becoming a veritable island
that has preserved most of its flora and
fauna. But Ramos is particularly con¬
cerned by a new development project.
To reduce the road distance between
two small Brazilian towns, Capanema
and Mediancira, by 140 kilometres,
there have been moves to drive an
asphalted road straight through the
middle of the Park from the southeast
to the northwest. "1 shall continue to
oppose that plan as hard as 1 can.
Iguaçu is sacrosanct," he says. Unfor¬
tunately, he simply does not have the
human and financial resources he
needs to keep the site in good shape.
A ISOL» YIÎIMlJISi:
The need to improve the Iguaçu
National Park's protection system is
all the more urgent because the Park
is located at the meeting point of
three countries, Argentina, Brazil and
Paraguay. The population of the
Brazilian town of Foz do Iguaçu,
which is only thirty kilometres from
the falls, has risen from 30,000 at
the beginning of the 1960s (when
work started on the world's most
powerful hydro-electric power sta¬
tion at Itaipu, twenty kilometres to
the north on the Paraná River) to over
200,000 today. Koz do Iguaçu is now
Brazil's third biggest tourist attrac¬
tion, after Rio de Janeiro and Sao
Paulo, and boasts 160 hotels of every
class. Yet two-thirds of their rooms
are taken not by tourists who have
come to admire the falls, but by
sacoleiros, people who drive across
the Bridge of Friendship, a few kilo¬
metres away, to go shopping in the
thousands of duty-free shops in the
border town of Ciudad del Fste in
Paraguay. On some days, especially
Wednesday and Saturday, cars wait
four hours to cross the Paraná River.
In 1994, 4.1 million people crossed
the bridge.
It is very tempting for Foz do
Iguaçu in Brazil and Puerto Iguazii
in Argentina to take advantage of this
more or less clandestine trade, while
at the same time preserving the nat¬
ural environment of the National
Park. It will be a tricky enterprise
that will require continual co-opera¬
tion between the authorities of the
two countries. Last June, 270 travel
agents from all over the world met for
four days in Foz do Iguaçu to look at
ways of attracting more tourists to
the region, which lies at the heart of
Mercosur, the common market of four
South American countries (Argentina,
Brazil, Paraguay and Uruguay) cre¬
ated in January 1995. The question
is: what, in addition to the falls, can
tourists be offered to induce them to
stay more than forty-eight hours on
the banks of the Iguaçu River?
This is an issue that is likely to
provoke heated debate between
defenders of the environment and
champions of growth. "We shall need
UlNKSCO's help," says Ramos.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
The birth of
the blues
by Isabelle Leymarie
After emerging from the field songs of
the cotton plantations in the Deep
South at the end of the 19th century,
the blues became a fount of inspiration
for jazz and later rock ï roll, Here
Isabelle Leymarie reviews La rouie du
blues ("The Blues Road"), a new book
that journeys along the Mississippi to
the source of this Afro-American
musical form that has fans all over the
world,
The origin of the blues, one of the
most original and powerful
musical forms to develop in the
New World, can be traced back to field
hollers, the modulated cries made by
slaves as they laboured in the cotton
fields of the Deep South. When LeRoi
Jones wrote a book on black Americans,
later to become a classic of Afro-Amer¬
ican literature, he gave it the evocative
title The Blues People.
The blues and its urban reincarna¬
tion, boogie-woogie, are the ancestors of
rock 'n' roll. Elvis Presley, Vincc Taylor,
the Rolling Stones and Eric Clapton
could never have existed without the
blues. Jazz is constantly going back to
its roots in the fertile soil of the blues
44
and gospel music, which has always had
close links with the blues. The cele¬
brated blues scale, which is so typical
of Afro-American music and gives it its
specific "mashed note" tone, provided
the uprooted slaves with a means of
reproducing untempered African scales
on instruments different from those
they had known. The first blues singers
were "loners" unattached men living
in rural areas who accompanied them¬
selves on the guitar. Later the blues
became urbanized when it was taken
up by vaudeville artistes and recording
companies. With the massive migration
of blacks to the northern stales, the
blues became more stylized and eventu¬
ally came to be played by bands and
orchestras.
Standard blues contains twelve bars
with a typical modulation on the fifth
bar. But rather than a particular struc¬
tural or harmonic pattern, the blues is
above all a "sound", a way of life, an
emotion. Musicians say that you have to
have lived the blues before you can play
it, you have to have suffered, toiled
away, wandered from place to place,
been in love and paid your dues.
From New Orleans to Chicago
La route du blues ("The Blues Road")
traces the wanderings of the bluesmen
along the Mississippi from New Orleans,
Baton Rouge and the Louisiana coun¬
tryside to Chicago, the end of the road
for the huge wave of migrants and still
capital of the blues today. This lively,
well-designed and beautifully illus¬
trated book reveals the multifaceted
world of the blues and its different
regional styles. It takes us along the
majestic Mississippi and explores its
curious hidden by-ways, as the musi¬
cians themselves once did. After the
haunting bayous and the monotonous
plain stretching from Lake Pontchar-
train to Baton Rouge, wc enter the
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
state of Mississippi with its impressive
delta swollen by the waters of the
Yazoo River. We move on through
Natchez, Greenville, Greenwood and
other towns and villages where some of
the famous blues performers lived. We
visit Tndianola, Ilta Bena, Tutwiler,
Clarksdalc, and Memphis, with its ever-
present memories of Elvis Presley,
Martin Luther King Jr., Bcalc Street's
famous blues clubs, and "Stax", the
great soul music record label, and then
on to Saint Louis, Detroit and Chicago.
We discover the urban and rural
landscapes, and taste the atmosphere of
bars, saloons and gambling dens, often
run-down but still "jumping", brightly
coloured churches, heat-oppressed resi¬
dential neighourhoods built along the
roadside or amidst luxuriant vegetation.
Vivid descriptions of places arc inter¬
spersed with portraits and interviews
with musicians, record producers and
other figures associated with the history
of the blues people like the prize¬
fighter and pianist Champion Jack
A scene in the French
quarter of New Orleans,
Louisiana (U.S.A.).
Dupree, Fats Domino, Professor Long¬
hair, Slim Ilarpo, the legendary Lead-
belly, who was discovered in the Angola,
Louisiana, penitentiary by the musicolo¬
gist John Hammond and was one of the
first jazz musicians to use the twelve-
string guitar, Lightnin' Hopkins, "Blind"
Lemon Jefferson, Willie Dixon, Charley
Patton, Robert Johnson, B. B. King,
Sonny Boy Williamson, Elvis Presley, Al
Green, Muddy Waters. We meet a cast
of characters who are by turns ecstatic,
disillusioned, thoughtful, jovial, kindly,
LA ROUTE
DU BLUES
("THE BLUES ROAD")
by David Ausseil and
Charles-Henry Contamine
with photos by Denis Chapoullié
Preface by Ahmet Ertegun
Ediciones de Arte J. P. Barthélémy
Besançon (France) 1995
383 pages
ISBN 2-909 413-17-9
jubilant, ironic and stylish, but all fig¬
ures of great humanity. And, of course,
there is the music, everywhere defying
adversity and discrimination, erupting in
Chicago's vacant lots or in the middle of
its crowded streets.
Touring the world
The hook also gives a detailed history of
the first blues recordings, such as Mamie
Smith's Crazy Blues on the "Okeh"
label, which was marketed only to
blacks and sold 75,000 copies in a
month, the hits of Bessie Smith, the
"Queen of the Blues", and the emer¬
gence of the minstrel shows. Some pages
tell the story of the alcohol, women and
gambling that fuelled the droll, tor¬
mented imagination of the bluesmen.
Others show trains with nicknames like
"The Southern" or "The Dog" which
carried migrants and hobos to faraway
places and occupy a key place in blues
lyrics. Other parts of the book are
devoted to such important themes as
cotton, the Mississippi, voodoo (known as
mojo in the Deep South), migration, reli¬
gion and its place in everyday life, and
Chess Records, one of the first impor¬
tant urban blues recording labels.
The saga of the blues did not end on
the shores of Lake Michigan. Its lan¬
guage has become international. In his
preface Ahmet Ertegun describes the
feelings that gripped him in Bodrum,
Turkey, when he heard an unknown gui¬
tarist launch into an impassioned version
of a Muddy Waters blues standard. The
book's authors report that "hack from a
European tour with Ilowlin' Wolf during
the Blues Revival, the ever-inspired
Hubert Sumlin had been fascinated by
the hero-worship with which they had
been received by British guitarists,
'When we got there, I couldn't believe
it. They knew more about us than we
know ourselves, or almost!'". M
ISABELLE LEYMARIE
¡s a Franco-American musicologist.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
YEHUDI
talks to Martine Leca
A former child prodigy, one of the
great violinists of the century,
Yehudi Menuhin has also
conducted, directed several music
festivals and founded a music
school in England. A man of peace,
he played for the Red Cross during
the Second World War and
continues to be a staunch defender
of human rights. From 1969 to 1975
he was president of Unesco's
International Music Council and is
presently a Unesco Goodwill
Ambassador. He recently created
the "Muse" project which seeks to
provide European children with
education for peace through music.
MARTINE LECA
is a French writer and journalist.
You gave your first concert at the
age of seven. How did you come to
terms with the gift that has taken you
so far?
I accepted it naturally. Later on,
daily practice of yoga in which the
body is like a root shooting simultane¬
ously skyward and into the earth
along with my fundamentally robust
nature, has kept me from going astray.
I was also certain that my music
helped to make the world a better
place. That was my first and most
abiding wish. My ambition was not to
become a virtuoso, a music-making
machine, but an intermediary who
could reveal the joy that exists in all
of us and lie receptive to others. My
soul has never been imprisoned by
the straitjacket of technique. On the
contrary, it is my Slav soul, with its
age-old wealth of instinct, that has
made me play naturally.
You have been called "the Mozart of
the violin". Has being a virtuoso
imposed constraints on you?
My father set himself the task of
helping me and looking after my
career. He had nothing in common
with Mozart's father, who was over¬
bearing and vain and presented his
genius of a son to the courts of France
and other European countries. My
court was and still is the public,
the people who come to uplift their
minds and souls so that they can
forget their everyday troubles. No,
learning to play the violin was never
an imposition for me.
The route from the head to the
heart must always be direct. When, at
the age of seven, I held my first violin,
this route was already mapped out
within me. I owe this rigour, these stan¬
dards that governed my childhood, to
my upbringing and to my nature. Later
I discovered a more carefree attitude
to life, because my teacher
Eneseu1 taught me to play unsystem-
atically, intuitively. I became known as
a young virtuoso. I went from concert
to concert, pursued by the desire to
float like a balloon and discover the
marvellous lightness of being.
However, the lightness I was
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
looking for was concealed by a sensa¬
tion of heaviness. It took me twenty
years to feel the weight of one finger
and to understand the relationship of
music which comes from the soul
to the muscles. I then realized that
technique must take a spiritual
course which involves the body. The
body is a noble thing: it should be
given life through dance, singing and
music, and not be crucified. Some
civilizations have understood this,
others not.
Art develops the intellectual,
physical, imaginative and sensory
spheres, and hence all human poten¬
tial. We use only part of our capabili¬
ties because education does not go to
the source. As a source of equilib¬
rium and tolerance, music should be
brought into the schools as a form of
self-fulfilment, a new philosophy,
especially in primary schools, with the
participation of monitors, musicians,
specialists and composers. Musical
education, which has hitherto been
regarded as an optional subject, can
change people's social behaviour.
Why in primary schools rather than
at other levels?
Music encourages revelation, a
sense of union with others and with
our environment. It enables us to
interpret our relationship with the
earth's rhythms and express emotions
like joy and pain. In remedying the
evils of a society blighted by con¬
sumerism and the excesses of materi¬
alism, children are in a way our
teachers and redeemers. Because
they are so genuine, they react imme¬
diately to encouragement and atten¬
tion. Schools nowadays often bring
together children from different
ethnic backgrounds. An exchange of
memories, cultures and sensibilities is
encouraged by this diversity because
children, by nature, do not succumb
to the temptation of rejecting others
on ethnic grounds.
They succumb to it when they are
adults, depending on how narrow-
minded they become or on the cre¬
dence they give to false information
for xenophobia is a falsehood and is
based on myths. The adult in us kills
the child. Now the child must teach
Sharing is the best
guarantee of peace. We
must encourage
everythingsuchas
music and the artsthat
encourages sharing and
exclude everything that
destroys or harms the
growth of harmony
between people.
the adult. Musicians, composers and
well-intentioned teachers must iden¬
tify with children, respect them, and
not deceive them by giving false
answers, by evasiveness or silence. A
driver must know that the road is his
guide and that he must adapt his driv¬
ing to the road, not to his idea of it.
There can be no mistaking a straight
stretch for a bend in the road.
You say that you have retained a
childlike naivety and freshness. What is
your recipe for this?
Quite simply, I have never let
myself give in to negative ideas, the
lugubriousness and hand-wringing
which poison our society. I prefer
happiness. And so, I have no diffi¬
culty in projecting myself into the
feelings of hundreds of millions of
children, into their games and into
their suffering. Since these children
are the continuity of humanity, they
should be given a hearing. They are a
living source that will help us to
recreate ourselves. In a sense, this
infanticidal adult world of ours
deserves the punishment it inflicts on
itself, like the scorpion that dies from
its own sting. In periods of so-called
peace a word that to my mind no
longer corresponds to reality the
world spends its energy preparing for
future wars.
Do you think that music is capable
of changing human relations, of
turning people towards peace?
Sharing is the best guarantee of
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
peace. We must encourage every¬
thing such as music and the arts
that encourages sharing and exclude
everything that destroys or harms the
growth of harmony between people.
During the Second World War, I
often played for the troops: it was my
form of resistance. The faces of those
men who had stared death in the face
and who would perhaps die the next
day, shone with a kind of ecstasy, the
ecstasy that is within our reach, if
only we want to grasp it and pass it
on. Music is the antidote to crimi¬
nality. Musicians will never be crimi¬
nals, nor will those who practise the
martial arts, because they purge
themselves of all their negative
impulses. The energy that flows into
them amplifies and enriches their
relationship with the world and with
other people.
Our times don't teach the higher,
transcendent things. But music and
singing can do so. Singing brings
people together; it harmonizes body
and mind. It unites people with others
We all have considerable
reserves of energy which
remain untapped or are
repressed or even
spoiled, in particular
because of the very
Western obsession with
material things. Our worst
actions are dictated to us
by a desire for security
and by fear.
and creates a symbiosis. Everybody has
to adapt to the rhythm and the notes.
This produces a collective effect on
the emotions and the intellect. Music
and singing have nothing to do with
consumerism; they are part of life.
Are you set apart from the world by
the ecstasy and sublimation you experi¬
ence when you play?
Any work of art, or any interpreta¬
tion of a work of art, is bound to be
executed outside real life and time.
Twentieth-century theatre seeks to
render the world's tragedy expres-
sionistically, to show us real blood
being shed and people's real-life
occupations. Even if it wishes to be
close to the real world, art cannot
coincide with it. Hence the need for
sublimation.
Emotions must be distilled. Mozart
could make people hear and see ter¬
rible events which, through the filter
of art, they could listen to in their
drawing-rooms and be profoundly
moved. If art gets involved in repro¬
ducing reality on stage, it becomes a
kind of television news broadcast. Art
has better things to do. It performs a
redeeming function. The artist's role
is to guide human beings, who arc too
wrapped up in material things,
towards ecstasy. In other words, to
take social beings out of themselves
and unite them to the work of art,
which expresses the intense experi¬
ence of the artist. This is the nature of
the link with the public: a shared
ecstasy created in a spirit of abnega¬
tion. You want to enwrap the audi¬
ence in the the beauty and calm of the
detachment that takes hold of you. It
is the joy of feeling a natural sense of
ecstasy at a time when artificial forms
of ecstasy are so fashionable.
I have always liked to experience
this sublime feeling and spread it
round me. It is a paradoxical state
which is at the same time very real
and yet detached from the present.
The Russians experience this state in
their everyday lives it is how they
transcend themselves. They have a
gift for drama. Their daily lives have
always been so steeped in sadness
and horror that they escape from it
into the world of art, which lifts them
out of distress and gives them life.
When they sing, dance and play they
draw on the drama of their daily lives
which they transmute with incredible
intensity and force.
I travelled with Russians during
the war. Singing and reciting poems
was their form of resistance. It was the
expression of a spontaneous culture
which had nothing to do with school;
it was born of pain but also of
indomitable hope. The survivors of
the concentration camps have set us
the same example: considering their
physical and mental exhaustion, it is
impossible to explain how some of
them went on living. These people
struggled and survived. My parents,
who were Russian Jews, personified
this blend of deep melancholy and
dogged hope.
Is this mystery, which seems such
an important part of your make-up, reli¬
gious in origin?
No. I feel its presence above all in
the space we call reality, but which is
to some extent beyond us. We do not
know what existed before we were
born or what will come to pass after
we die. So we look for ways of cre¬
ating ecstasy that are capable of liber¬
ating the mind from the body. But the
body is not an impediment to the soul.
On the contrary, everything hinges on
mastering its rhythms and its breath.
I have achieved my relationship
with the world without religion,
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Yehudi Menuhin and the young
violinist Sarah Chang at an award-
giving ceremony at the Palais des
Congrès in Paris in 1993.
through a sort of cosmic complicity
with the world that weaves its web
around me and in me and which I
weave like everyone else. Religions
create bonds between those who
practise them, but I dread the
excesses of adoration to which they
give rise. Human beings in search of
an existential support have the keys
of their freedom within them. Individ¬
uals are the threads of this cosmic
web, which is of divine essence. This
attitude seems to me to be truer,
closer to the human scheme of things
than any form of religious worship.
We all have considerable reserves
of energy which remain untapped or
are repressed or even spoiled, in par¬
ticular because of the very Western
obsession with material things. Our
worst actions are dictated to us by a
desire for security and by fear. Ide¬
ally, we should root out these evils,
which are within us. If we cannot
manage to do so, we might at least
adopt a conciliatory attitude, which
would not necessarily mean giving up
our resistance and determination. It is
a question of striking a balance.
There's no point in trying to smash a
brick wall by knocking your head
against it. Thought and mental energy
can do the job.
So, as I grow older, I get pleasure
from feeling light, freed from the
burden of having to take sides. The
only thing that interests me is a harmo¬
nious centre that is flexible and strong,
stronger than the sum of the parts.
This very simple arithmetic ought to
suit societies whose centre is yielding
under the pressure of extremes.
You are a fervent adept of yoga.
What part does it play in your attitude
to the world?
Yoga is a source of balance
between earth, heaven and the self, a
source of fusion not only with human
beings but with animals, plants and
the cosmos as a whole. It enables me
to play by introducing the heartbeat
of life and to understand intuitively
The adult in us kills
the child.
Now the child must
teach the adult.
what a composer is trying to say. For
instance, Bach's "Chaconne", which I
regard as the finest piece ever written
for solo violin, admits neither gratu¬
itous ornamentation nor aggressive¬
ness. It is a work that demands nerves
of steel. Human beings are like
Bach's "Chaconne". They have to be
capable of settling their own differ¬
ences, balancing their opposites and
negotiating their transformations, all
the deaths and rebirths which are
constantly changing them.
Do you have a political philosophy?
Politics captivates crowds which
are taken in by the illusion of speech.
I believe that all politicians should
have a job outside politics. Politicians
who were also cobblers, cooks or gar¬
deners, who had direct experience of
their country at every level, would
be head and shoulders above today's
politicians. They would be really
useful to their fellow citizens. I
1 Georges Enescu, Rumanian composer and
violinist (1881-195.)).Ed.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
The watchful eye of democracy
by Richard Hoggart
The task of encouraging tolerance may seem complex
at any time, but we live today in a particularly sombre
era. Our capacity to destroy each other, if we let intolerance
take its course, has never been greater from massive state-
organized destruction to do-it-yourself horrors engineered by
small fanatical groups.
Rabid intolerance is widespread and growing. Religious
intolerance stalks several large nations. Those who exhibit
ethnic intolerance have so far lost any sense of shame as to
flaunt an appalling phrase such as "ethnic cleansing". Nazism
and other intolerant creeds arc increasing, even in the most
"developed" parts of the world. The situation could hardly
be worse, but it worsens yearly.
When a real disagreement surfaces between individuals
and peoples, there is sometimes a tendency to say: "It's only a
failure in communication" as though to go further and fur¬
ther so as to communicate more and more would incluctably
lead to the sunny uplands of mutual respect. Not necessarily
so. As one former British Prime Minister answered when a
member of his Cabinet who was being dismissed said there
seemed to be a failure in communication: "There is no
failure. I understand you very well. You are not up to the
job". We will get nowhere without such frank speaking.
Many of us are congenital joiners of clubs, societies,
neighbourhoods, nations. We like to feel wc belong. That
sense of belonging is umbilically linked to its opposite: the
assumption that other people do not belong, are outsiders
and are to be kept in that condition. Those of us in nations
which arc comfortable and little threatened can keep such
nasty attitudes more or less at bay though if someone out¬
side the pale asked to marry our daughter it might well flare
into life.
These are hard and unpalatable thoughts. What hope is
there? The first hope is in the spread of democratic institu¬
tions. They are not a panacea, only the least bad social system
so far devised. For the idea of democracy is founded pre¬
cisely on the assumption of tolerance, rather than on any type
of authoritarianism, lay or religious: because those take away
the subject's freedom, and that loss is the essence of state
intolerance.
However, democracies only work well when they do better
in some important issues than the majority of their citizens
would wish or would vote for in a referendum. Thus, in 1995,
75 per cent of the population of Britain are in favour of a
return to capital punishment. Probably a majority have ele¬
ments of racism in their altitudes. But parliament has passed
anti-capital punishment and anti-racist laws.
That parliament should have to force its citizens to be
more virtuous than their natural instincts even in a democ¬
racy is a pity but unavoidable. One may look forward to a
time when citizens do not have to be "screwed into virtue" by
their elected representatives. Meanwhile we have to be
thankful for those instances where parliament does better
than the majority of us would collectively do.
So we are quite well on in the debate before we come to
what most well-meaning people put first: the power of edu¬
cation as a force towards tolerance. It is a critical force;
but not easy; not a matter of warm injunctions. In an early
poem the English poet W.U. Auden wrote: "We must love
one another or die". That was a call to a sort of calculated
tolerance. Later he altered it, because he thought it was
phoney, sentimental, face-saving, to: "We must love one
another and die".
We must in teaching (and in its best adjunct, broadcasting,
if it is properly used, and not made the agent either of com¬
merce or of state propaganda) be challenging and firm. We
can arrange, school exchanges, pen friends and all the rest,
but we must not expect too much from them even though wc
prepare most carefully and unsentimentally.
Above all, wc must educate our pupils and students in the
art of critical literacy in a democracy. This means, among
much else, training them both to understand and value their
particular culture but also to stand outside it and be able
and willing to judge it. M
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover (from left to right and top to bottom): Antoine Gyori © Sygma, Paris; Ian Berry © Magnum, Paris. Benami Neumann © Magnum, Paris; S. Nackstrand ©
Gamma, Paris; Photo news © Gamma, Paris. Carlos Angel © Gamma, Paris; T. Graham © Sygma, Paris. Page 6: llNESCo/lnes Forbes. Pages 7, 10-11, 13, 15,
16-17, 18: © International Museum of Children's Art, Oslo. Page 9: S.O.S. Children's Villages-International Museum of Children's Art, Oslo. Page 20: ©
Gamma, Paris. Page 21: Ian Berry © Magnum, Paris. Page 22: © Juda Ngwenya/Reuter/Max PPP, Paris. Page 23: Antoine Gyori © Sygma, Paris. Page 24:
Benami Neumann © Gamma, Paris. Page 25: Photo News © Gamma, Paris. Page 26: S. Nackstrand © Gamma, Paris. Page 27: S. Nackstrand © AFP, Paris. Page
28: J.F. Campos © Vu, Paris. Page 29: M. Deghati © AFP, Paris. Page 30: Halesian-Liaison © Gamma, Paris. Page 31: Carlos Angel © Gamma, Paris. Page 32: T.
Graham © Sygma, Paris. Page 33: © AFP photo/Europapress, Paris. Page 34: Omega © Sygma, Paris. Page 35: Marc Beziat © Cosmos, Paris. Page 36 (above):
© Yves Gellie/lcône, Paris. Page 36 (below): Pierre Boulât © Cosmos, Paris. Page 37 (above): Voegele © INRA, Paris. Page 37 (below): M. Renaudeau © Hoa Qui,
Paris. Page 38 (above): H. Silvester © Rapho, Paris. Page 38 (below): © Esther/Ask Images, Paris. Pages 40, 41: François Gohier © Explorer, Paris. Page 42: ©
E. Bailby, Paris. Page 43: 0. Franken © Explorer, Paris. Pages 44-45: Gérard Sioen © Rapho, Paris. Pages 46, 49: James Andanson © Sygma, Paris.
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
ó
Ce Salon,
ça me donne une
faim de loup !
SALON DU
LIVRE DE
JEUNESSE
EN SEINE
SAINT-DENIS
29 NOV. -4 DEC.
MONTREUIL
METRO MAIRIE
DE MONTREUIL
Seine Saint-Denis
^ f Conseil Général
NESco on line via Internet
gopher.unesco.org
or
http://www.unesco.org
Currently on-line are: an index of the contents of the last 22 issues of the Unesco Courier, Unesco
press releases, addresses, fax, telex and electronic mail numbers of Unesco's regional offices,
National Commissions and Unesco Clubs, the directory of Unesco databases and information
services, colour images of the Japanese Garden and other architectural sites at Unesco
Headquarters, as well as works of art such as Henry Moore's reclining sculpture.
To contact
THE UNESCO (OURIER
directly with suggestions and comments, type:
unesco.couher@unesco.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
t 4 - *t i
*
h
20 November 1946. The first General Conference opens at the Sorbonne In Paris. Uscsco/Edair mondial
the early years
1951. The arid zone research programme. umsco/G. Böhm
1948.
Translations from
world literature feature In
\ the Unesco Collection of
\ Representative Works
Uttsco Archives
1956. Radio Forum pilot project for literacy and development in India.
Imsco/J. Bhownagary
THE | JnESCO COURIER
^^Ä S'jcp'ewn: to the November 1995 issue.
1950. The joint Unesco-Unrw* education programme on behalf of Palestinian refugee children.
Unesco/D. Roger
i uppJeme '. ti
Not to De solo separately
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
he sixties
1965. The SITE satellite brings television to many Indian villages. Uutsco/Aimasy 1961. The Unesco Collection of recordings of traditional music. Uvscs/Aimasy
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
1963. A women's education project In Africa. unesoq/M. Caiiiarú
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
1976. Arid land research in the Mount Kulal biosphere reserve (Kenya).
© Yann Ar'MsBertrand/Earth from Above/UNESCO
1975. The International Hydrological Programme.
C Fnnco Zecchin. Paris
1976. The Geological World Atlas, scgmw/unescc 1972. Studying African oral traditions and promoting African languages. u*î$co/m. Claude
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
World Heritage: Meidan-Emam, Isfahan (Iran).
Koch © Rapho. Paris
1973. A world study of marine pollution Is launched under the auspices of the Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission (IOC).
OHI/COI/SHC © Minister of Supply and Services Canada
Bialowieza national park biosphere reserve (Poland). S. Cordier © Explorer, Paris World Heritage: the amphitheatre of El DJem (Tunisia), f. Le Diascom O Panho. Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
eighties
World Heritage: Humayun's Tomb in Delhi (India)
© Y. Layma. Heritage 2001/'La Caixa" Foundation
World Heritage: Hawaii Volcanoes National Park (U.S.A.).
M. Friedet © Rapio. Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
1985-1987. Communication courses for women
in developing countries. U'-csco/Banga Radio
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
t h e i n e t i e s
Bookmark biosphere reserve (Australia)
© R. Thwaites
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
IN THE NEXT ISSUE:
CAVE DWELLERS
AND THEIR WORLD
T
INTERVIEW WITH JEAN DANIEL
HERITAGE: THE CITY OF LUXEMBURG
ENVIRONMENT: PROTECTING WILD PLANTS
Each month, essential
reading for an
understanding of the
problems of today and
tomorrow
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine published in 30
languages and read by hundreds of thousands of people in 120 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission of furthering "universal
respect for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms... without distinction of race, sex, language or religion...''
]]>
</page>
</document>
