<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="102011eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Cover : nun in achurchb at Lalibela
(Ethiopia). OArnaud deW ! ! denberg, Hehtage
2001/La C ixa Foundation.
Battle of Stalingrad. &commat;L'lIlustrationjSygma,
Paris
   x 
4
s ;.' t M'.'-
JEN y, iJ6. ! Eiia
; ;,, §C) BC) ., 
BY,
BAHAT ELNi4DI' ;
,.,  ! 
b
9
. GREENWATCH
"PR01'ECTING :....
PNT IaFE
4 ! ! X
 : ias ; : ; : p ! E<Nea
, RraU ! ett
HERiTAE
 : 
.'0< : 
7 ! Sl ? ? ? ;. "
A IT WAS...
'ER : 5t&
 FEBRUARY1959
TROGLODYTES
a hidden world
10
LIFE BELOW GROUND
by Jacek Rewerski
15
CHINA : WHEN LOESS MEANS MORE
byJeanPau ! Loubes
19
ITALY : ROCKS IN A HARD PLACE
by Pietro Laureano
31
ETHIOPIA'S NEW JERUSALEM
by Kassaye Begashaw
35
TROGLODYTIC SITES ON THE WORLD HERITAGE LIST
Mogao Caves (China)
The archaeological site of Petra (Jordan)
The rock churches of Ivanovo (Bulgaria)
The Nubian monuments from Abu Simbel to Philae (Egypt)
Ajanta Caves-Ellora Caves-Elephanta Caves (India)
The Bandiagara Escarpment ("Dogon Country") (Mali)
The rock cones of Cappadocia (Turkey)
Mesa Verde (United States)
Wieliczka salt mines (Poland)
Consultant : Jacek Rewerski
23
1'0 Y"E'ARS AGOW', : ir",'ßI : r' : : :. :,.,,', ii". ; ! :'. w""ij :'\f. ] :') II ; II ; II
CHO ; TRI : m : e, m, or'atlnig t. IT :. ends oaf tulle ;
Sec ; ondl Wo, r'lld. War (1, 9'3, 9'.. 1, 946)
! tE UNESCO (OURM
' : sS'48th year  S. 
N : Pob ! ished month ! y in 30 languages and in 8raiiie  ; 5=.""'''''''.,. =---====
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed...
"that apeace based exclusively upon the political andeconomic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples
of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the intellectual andmoral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples and to employ these means for the purposes
of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives...."EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Jean Daniel
<&lt;<&lt;'d : =
interview
N At a time when nations seem
increasingly threatened by the process
of globalization, the idea of the
nation-state-the subject of your
latest book-is giving rise to a good
deal of thought and comment.
Jean Daniel : After a long period of
neglect the nation has again become a
highly topical subject, especially in the
United States and Germany. Each
month dozens of books are published
on this theme in different parts of the
world. I trace the origins of the idea of
the nation to Johann Fichte'sl famous
Addresses to the German Nation, a
book which is outstanding both for its
depth and objectivity and for its impact
on European thought.
No-one else has ever made a more
subtle and penetrating eulogy of what
is called"the right of blood"[jus san-
guinis]. Fichte maintains that without
the nation-real or imaginary-a people
has no future, and that the Germans
are fortunate because they have had a
national experience made possible by
the existence of a language and racial
purity. He expounds this in such philo-
sophically sophisticated terms and in
such noble language that few people
have seen any connection between his
views and the racist theories that were
set forth later by Joseph de Gobineau2
and Houston Chamberlain3 and were to
lead to Alfred Rosenberg4 and Hitler.
In my opinion, Fichte remains top-
ical because in some places there is a
persistent feeling of nostalgia for"the
right of blood", unpopular though the
concept may be among Western elites.
t Could you give some examples ?
J. D. : Examples of this nostalgia can be
found in ethnic and religious groups in
the Baltic states, in Ukraine, in
Georgia, in Armenia, Azerbaijan and of
course in the former Yugoslavia, even
though in some cases the heritage of the
right of blood seems doubtful.
The example of Israel is very inter-
esting. On the one hand Israel welcomes
people from all over the world who are
often (especially the Russians) the
product of ethnic mixing. On the other
hand, marriages between Jews and non-
Jews are forbidden in the diaspora5.
And since proselytism is out of the ques-
tion and conversion is a difficult enter-
prise, marriage between Jews continues
to be the ideal. Sometimes this consan-
guinity is given a dangerous theological
significance : that of a holy alliance with
a distinctive people which must remain
pure, the people to whom God speaks.
t And the Arab countries ?
J. D. : In theory, Islam is a universal reli-
gion which is hospitable to all peoples
and cultures. But in reality it respects
the right of blood.
t Is Islam more progressive in this
respect, since anyone is a potential
convert ?
J. D. : Don't forget that St. Paul, who
lived in pre-Islamic times, abolished the
need to be circumcised before
becoming a Christian. That did not pre-
vent certain inquisitors from considering
that converted Jews were not proper
Christians.
For Muslims it is inter-ethnic mar-
riages rather than inter-religious mar-
riages that pose a problem. But it comes
down to the same thing-we are dealing
with prohibitions which show that in
the final analysis what counts is the
right of blood.
What's more, the right of blood is
making a strong come-back all over the
world, directly and indirectly, and is being
justified in various ways-by the idea that
intermingling does not succeeed, or that
it leads to bastardization or to the disso-
lution of identity.... To some extent,
many people who aspire to universality
tell themselves that in the end it is better
to achieve it via the community.
t This debate was inaugurated by
the French Revolution, which
formulated two conflicting ideas of the
nation. On the one hand there is the
abstract nation that springs from
"free contract"between autonomous,
aware, responsible individuals, and on
the other the real, physical nation that
is a product of history and imposes
itself on individuals, whether they like
it or not. Or is this a simplification of
what actually happened ?
J. D. : Enthralling debates about this
took place between the revolutionaries,
especially concerning the emancipation
of the Jews, the Protestants and the
blacks.
When Stanislas de Clermont-Ton-
nerre said"Everything to the Jews as
individuals, nothing as a nation", he had
enthusiastic supporters who did not
believe in communities. But he also had
detractors. His proposal was rejected.
Someone came to see him and said :"I
don't know any individual'Jews. I only
know a community."Then his visitor
explained how individuals detached
from their community structures did
not exist.
As for the Protestants, the Revolu-
tion gave them equality. It emancipated
them and gave them access to positions
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The French writer and journalist
Jean Daniel is founder-director of
the Paris weekly Le Nouvel
Observateur. He has been an ardent
champion of the cause of human
dignity and a lucid and critical
observer of the events of the last half
century. The author of many novels
and essays, he was recently
awarded the Albert Camus prize for
a collection of short stories entitled
Vamianglais (Paris, Grasset, 1994).
Here he talks to Bahgat Elnadi and
Adel Rifaat about the current
evolution of the nation-state, the
theme of his latest book, Voyage au
centre de la nation (Seuil publishers,
Paris, 1995).
from which they had been excluded.
But they continued to define themselves
in a way that was simultaneously reli-
gious and individual. And so at this
period when God was deprived of his
sovereignty, when the temporal was sep-
arated from the spiritual, when the
individual was dazzled and over-
whelmed by his freedom, French
Protestants found a thoroughly grati-
fying form of integration : they had their
cake and ate it too.
Things were more complicated for
the blacks. Slavery was abolished, then
reinstated. Economic questions compli-
cated relations with the black commu-
nity even further. The heirs of the Rev-
olution behaved very badly and finally
came out in support of slavery. All this
is magnificently described by the Cuban
writer Alejo Carpentier in his novel
Explosion in the Cathedral.
To conclude, it is true that an
abstract idea of the individual exists.
The Declaration of the Rights of Man
and of the Citizen of 1789 makes no
allusion to the duties of the individual
(in other words there is no bond with
the community and no responsibility
towards it). The only limitation on
freedom is that one should not trespass
on one's neighbour's freedom. Two
counter-revolutionaries, Edmund Burke
in England and Joseph de Maistre in
France, later pointed out correctly that
the men of 1789 were to some extent
talking nonsense, that they had invented
a creature which turns its back on
human nature.
Of course, the need for a sense of
community exists in all societies. It has
been seen, for example, in the strength
of tradition in Britain or in the heritage
of the feudal monarchy in France, not
to mention societies where the patriar-
chal principle is so strong that the indi-
vidual is not only an abstraction but an
absurdity. The community impinges
constantly on the members of these
societies from the cradle to the grave,
notably through rites of initiation, mar-
riage and sexuality. The individual
derives his balance from the community,
and when he is alone he feels protected
by remembering his community.
So is it possible to strike a balance
between individual freedom and soli-
darity with the community ? One place
where this balance has been found is
the nation-state, which was constructed
in eighteenth-and nineteenth-century
Europe to meet this very need.
t Widely different ideas of the
community have been proposed....
J. D. : In France, for example, there is a
big difference between the ideas of
Maurice Barrels7 and Charles Maurras3.
Barres is a kind of aesthete of the
French nation. For him the nation
means having the same dead, and
remembering them in the same way.
<=
"g
ro
'"
Q)
&commat;
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Maurras had a more vigorous idea of the
nation. He said to Barres :"Your dead
interest me, but it's not mourning them
that makes a nation. It's the fact that
they are dead. The blood that has been
shed."
De Gaulle had a similar idea. For
him the nation is primarily an idea. Seen
in this light, his thinking was much
more progressive than that of François
Mitterrand or of many African heads of
state today. For De Gaulle the French
nation is a certain idea of France and
the hardships shared in serving this
idea-but hardships shared with
others, remember. France was made
with foreigners.
The idea of shared hardship is
essential here. Before there can be a
nation there has to be a certain number
of common memories, projects and
hardships. The universal must be asso-
ciated with what Simone Weil9 calls
enracinement-taking root. Here we
have come a long way from the free indi-
vidual of 1789, who asks himself every
day"do I want to be French or not ?"
t Between the wars, in the societies
of the South, the notion of the
individual, abstract though it may
have been, was nevertheless a
spearhead that helped to dislocate
religious and patriarchal structures.
There was never any danger of being
too abstract. On the contrary,
patriarchal despotism was so deeply
rooted that it took all the virulence of
the abstract ideal of 1789 to
overthrow it.
J. D. : Indeed. But in the West, the modern
individual eventually went too far and sev-
ered all connection with the sacred. The
problems he or she encountered in
Europe were not the same as those expe-
rienced by modernist intellectuals on the
other side of the Mediterranean.
t) In some ways the preoccupations of
intellectuals in the South today recall
those of the 19th-century European
intelligentsia. And the crisis of the 19th-
century European intelligentsia gives
the 20th-century South a foretaste of
what to expect....
J. D. : This reminds me of a very telling
anecdote. At the end of his life, Tol-
stoy-who had fought against serfdom
in Russia and was largely responsible for
its abolition-used to say when he saw
the rather arrogant and vulgar behav-
iour of the former muzhiks :"How fine
was the struggle in the days of
serfdom !"
In just the same way, in the struggle
for the freedom of the individual, the
struggle itelf is a source of fulfilment.
An ideal exists in its most open, most
balanced form during the struggle
waged on its behalf. When the battle is
won, one sees that its goal has been
betrayed or else that it was vain. Revo-
lutions soon betray themselves.
As for the revolutions in the South
during the first half of the twentieth
century, the individual began to fulfil
himself in the struggle. He found true
fulfilment at the time when he was most
committed and responsive to the call of
his community at a time of danger. As
soon as the struggle was over, his
freedom was either confiscated by a dic-
tatorship or, at best, impoverished.
t There is a cyclical phenomenon,
here. After the great age of triumphant
nationalism, the idea of individual
freedom-as defined by French
humanism-was reaffi rmed with new
vigour. It is true that its
fundamentalist negation has been
quicker to occupy the ground....
J. D. : Perhaps the expansion of French
humanism complicated matters rather
than simplified them. It made almost
everyone schizophrenic. People experi-
enced it on two levels-as a source of
greater inner wealth but also of more
conflicts and uneasiness. Eventually
they became so unbalanced that they
wanted to go back to the old-style com-
munity because it was simpler and more
reassuring. Instead of seeing a partic-
ular richness in these two levels, as Sen-
ghor did, they saw them as a betrayal
of the myth of a return to the past, of
the myth of authenticity, of a golden
age. This golden age never really existed
but nostalgia for it made it possible to
resist schizophrenia.
The five or six fundamentalists I have
met during my life are former schizo-
phrenics who have wanted to free them-
selves from their failure to discover a syn-
thesis between the two civilizations and
ideals that divided them. They said to
themselves :"I only take one of them and
I back it to the hilt so that I have a firm
sense of reality on which I can rely."This
perverse effect of the contagion of
humanism is worth thinking about.
t As far as perversity is concerned,
we prefer to think about the perversity
of states where the individual exists
but lacks the protective garment of
citizenship.
J. D. : It is true that citizenship was the
vocation of the individual in the West.
Many remedies for the failings we have
been discussing can be found in citizen-
ship, because the citizen is a responsible
person. Pierre Mendes France ! 0 thought
that freedom conferred more duties than
rights and that national solidarity made
non-stop claims on citizens. In the duties
of the free citizen the individual finds a
balance equivalent to that which in tra-
ditional societies is provided by depen-
dence on the community.
But things have changed, even in the
West, in recent decades. There have
been two big changes-the coming of
the affluent society, which has trans-
formed the individual into a consumer,
Jean
Daniel
"
. g
'"
'"
Q)
m
&commat;
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
and the development of the audiovisual
media, which has transformed the indi-
vidual into a televiewer. The ideal of the
market economy, which has turned the
individual into a competitive consumer,
is at odds with humanist culture. Fur-
thermore, as a televiewer, the individual
has less and less need of elections and
parliaments, reacting with increasing
passivity to a procession of images,
instead of making active judgments in
the privacy of his conscience. The com-
bination of the consumer and the tele-
viewer is annihilating the citizen. It does
not deprive him of freedom by imposing
constraints but by the extent of the new
needs it implants in him. The nation is
threatened with dissolution by the
market economy and by television.
t) Is it possible that the dissolution of
the nation under the pressure of an
increasingly globalized market will
lead to larger supranational
groupings, just as the 19th-century
nation-states were formed out of
statelets ? This question is relevant not
only for Europe and North America but
also for the Arab world and sub-
Saharan Africa. How else will survival
in the 21st century be possible ?
J. D. : What you describe may come
about but it is not inevitable. I have
noticed that major social phenomena
are the product of reactions rather than
actions. Social phenomena obey the law
of the swinging pendulum. When the
pendulum has swung too far one way, it
swings back just as far in the other. This
observation is perhaps less common-
place than it seems because it can lead
to extremely tense situations.
To take one example, the idea of the
swing of the pendulum has led scientists
such as Claude Levi-Strauss to talk of a
"race tolerance threshold", which is a
very dangerous notion. If you have too
many foreigners in a given area, a rejec-
tion mechanism takes place. Levi-
Strauss has spent his life studying
tribes that he admired so much that he
wanted to protect their purity (in a
sense he was in favour of the right of
blood) and since he saw that intermin-
gling led to acculturation, he came to
believe that cultures have the right to
protect themselves against each other.
It is true that inputs from outside are
sometimes necessary, but the dosage
must be carefully watched. Ultimately,
Levi-Strauss sees the world as a set of
cultures that have the right to defend
themselves but must not seek to domi-
nate each other.
t What do you think of the idea that
our attitudes to the nation have taken
us back into the 19th century ?
J. D. : Unlike the French thinker Régis
Debray, I don't believe that we have
returned to the nineteenth century,
because in the nineteenth century you
had none of the phenomena-interna-
tional exchanges, demographic factors,
technology, planet-wide interdepen-
dence, the interpenetration of cultures,
the abolition of distance, the babeliza-
tion of languages-that you have today
and which lead many people to feel that
they are losing their identity.
To return to the example of France,
since European citizenship does not
exist and French citizenship is
becoming diluted, many people will
either fall back on nationalism or
become spineless individuals. Else-
where, retreat into religion and expres-
sions of fundamentalism are more or less
violent reactions to the radically new
idea that we all inhabit a single planet.
Where will all this lead to in the end ?
Since the trend towards globalization is
irreversible, I think it is possible that
nations may disappear under the com-
bined effects of a sense of loss of iden-
tity, of consumption, of television and
the absence of wars.
Think of the ideas put forward
about the identity of France by the
French historian Fernand Braudel.
Braudel says, more or less, that France
is a kind of miracle, a product of
chance, and lists all the reasons why it
should not have become a nation. There
was no complementarity between the
scattered pieces of France. There was
no need for France to become France.
Nor is there any need today for
Europe or the Arab world to form a fed-
eral unit. Millions of French and
German people had to die before it was
decided to give priority to economic
interests and the construction of Europe
began. First of all people felt the need
to stop exterminating each other, then
came the discovery of economic com-
plementarity. Supranational groupings
may or may not be made-it will all
depend on human determination, not on
some kind of historical inevitability. N
1. German philosopher (1762-1814). His
Reden an die deutsche Nation, 14 addresses
given at the university of Berlin in 1807 and
1808, set forth his ideas on the foundations
of national recovery after the collapse of
Prussia.-Ed.
2. French writer (1816-1882), author of an
"Essay on the inequality of the human races"
(1853-1855 ; Eng. trans. 1915).-Ed.
3. British-born German writer (1855-1927),
author of a pan-German racist theory
expounded in his book The Foundations of
the l9th Century (1899, Eng. trans. 1911)
which influenced Hitler.-Ed.
4. German politician (1893-1946). A leading
theorist of national socialism.-Ed.
5. The Jewish communities dispersed
throughout the world.-Ed.
6. A representative of the nobility in the
Estates General at the beginning of the
French Revolution.-Ed.
7. French writer (1862-1923) and
nationalist.-Ed.
8. French writer (1868-1952) and
monarchist.-Ed.
9. French writer and philosopher
(1909-1943).-Ed.
10. French politician (1907-1982).-Ed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
MEUES, MAGICIAN OF THE SCREEN
When I read your double issue on the
cinema ("A Century of Cinema", July-
August 1995) I was surprised to find nothing
about Georges Melies, a great illusionist of
the cinema and inventor of unforgettable
special effects. Dubbed the"Magician of
the Screen", he is held to have built the
world's first studio, in Montreuil, an eastern
suburb of Paris. Some 150 of his films have
been preserved, and many books have been
written about him.
This cobbler's son, who himself started
out in life in the shoe business, really
deserved a place in your excellent issue.
Michel Juignet
President of the French Cobblers'
Federation
Paris (France)
WELL UNFORMED
I should like to point out a mistake in your
September 1995 issue ("Women-one half
of heaven"). The well shown in the photo on
page 43 cannot possibly be a Tuareg well.
The Tuareg live mainly in Mali and Niger.
The well shown in the photo is more likely to
belong to the nomads known as the Beidane.
Andre Patris
Fontenay-aux-Roses
(France)
P. 945 R>IIE°MBERED
I think it is extremely unfortunate that so
far this year you have not devoted an issue or
even an article of the UNESCO Courier to the
fiftieth anniversary of 1945, the year which
saw the liberation of the concentration
camps and the victory of the forces of peace
and democracy over the unspeakable bar-
barity of Nazism-events that led to the
foundation of UNESCO.
I feel this not only because I am a sur-
vivor of Nazi barbarity (I fought in the
French Resistance and was deported to
Auschwitz). I am thinking of all my friends,
boys and girls of twenty or younger, known or
(in most cases) unknown, who will never be
able to bear witness. By the time of the cen-
tenary in 2045, the last surviving voices will
of course have fallen silent.
S. Radzinski
Paris (France)
See pages 23-30 of this issue.-Ed.
'pSSUME>d NAME
In your"Century of Cinema"issue (July-
August 1995) you say that the brilliant
young film-maker Milco Mancevski is"Macc-
donian"by nationality.
I should like to remind you that United
Nations resolution No 617/1993, which also
applies to UNESCO, refers to Mr. Mancevski's
country as the"Former Yugoslav Republic
of Macedonia"... pending attribution of a
definitive name, which I hope will come in
the near future.
Dimitris Papastamos
Permanent Delegate of Greece
to UNESCO
MORE AFR1CAN WR ! TERS, PLEASE !
I like your magazine very much and regret
that I did not subscribe to it sooner. My
family and high-school friends also enjoy
reading it.
But there is one thing that shocks us.
We have noticed that the Courter, particu-
larly since September 1994, has taken no
interest in our continent. My teachers have
always told me that writing originated in
Africa, in Egypt, to be precise. However, in
your April 1995 issue,"The origins of
writing", you say it began in Mesopotamia !
What's more, why can't you find African
specialists to contribute to your magazine ?
I note that the author of the article on
Africa published in your April issue is a
British linguist.
Nor do Africans feature in your inter-
views. And judging from the Courier, one
might think that there are no heritage sites
in Africa either. To date you have only pub-
lished articles about World Heritage sites
on other continents.
United Nations institutions exist for the
whole planet. It is impossible to imagine
that they might be infected by the infamous
virus of racism.
So, more African writers, please !
TheophNe Azonglahoun
Mono
(Benin)
Our themes are not treated in a spirit which
is confided to any single continent or
country as such. We are concerned above
all that the Metopomts advanced on each
theme should reject the widest possible
range of philosophical and cultural atti-
tudes. Nearly all this year's issues, for
example, have included an African per-
spective. Among the personalities we have
interviewed in recent years are the film-
maker Sembène Ousmane, the musician
Manu Dibango, and the historian Joseph
Ki-Zerbo.-Ed.
TIT UNESCO
OLIRI E R
48th YEAR
Published monthiy In 34languages and in Braille by
Unssco, The United Nations Educational Sclantlflc andCultur.
LOURIER
. 31, rue FtanGois Bonmn, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15, France.  :
. Fax : (31) 45. 66. 92. 70  : 
Internet : unesco. courierunesco. org ;
Dirctor : Bahgat Elnadi
Editor·in-chief : Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL S TAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor :Giilian Whitcomb :
Engiish edition :Roy Malkin
French edition :Alain Leveque
Spanish edition :Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbirta
Features :Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production : Georges Servat
Illustrations : Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45. 68. 46. 90)
Documentation : Jose Banaag (Tei. 45 : 68. 46. 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters edition5 and pross :
Solange ; Belin (Tel. 45. ti8. 46. 87)
Secretariat : Annie Brachet (Tel. 45. 68. 47. 15), ;
Administrative Assistant :Theresa Pinck
Selectioh in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean : Mouna Chatta (Tel. 45. 68. 47. 14)
ArtWOrk Consultant : Eric Froge
NON-HEADQUART£RS EDITIONS
Russian : lrina Utkina (Moscow)
German : Dominique Aderes (Berne)
Arabic : EI·Said Mahmoud EI-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian : (Rome)
Hfndi :Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamit : M : Mohammed Mustafa (MarJras)
Persian :AkbarZargar (Teheran)
Dutch : Claude Montrietfx (Antwerp) ;
Portug4ese : Moacyr A. Foravante {Rio de Janeiio)
Urdu : Javaid Iqbal Syed (islamabad) :
Catatan : Joan Carreras iMarti (Bareelona)
Malay : Sidin Ahmad ishak (Kuaia Lumpur)
K4rean : Kang Woo-hyon ; (Seoul)
Swahiii :Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
SIoVene : Aleksandra Komhauser (Ljtibijana)
Chinese : Shen Guofen' (Beijing)
Bulgarian :DragomirPetrov (Sotia) ;,
Greek : Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhaia : Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish ;Katri Himma (Helsinki)
Basque : Juxto Egana (Donostia)
Thai : Sudhasinee Vajrabui (Bangkokj
Vletnamese : Do Phuog (Hanoi)
Pashto : Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa : Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian :Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician : XabierSeninfemhndez (San6ago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION. Fax : 42. 73. 24. 29
Su6scriptions : Marie-ThrBse Hardy (Tel. 45. 68 ; 45. 65) ;
Joceiyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Martichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Rauassard, Mohamed Salah Ei Diri'
(Tel. 45. ̀68. 49. 19)
Customer service :Giette Motreff (Tel. 45. 68. 45. 64)
Accounts : ; (Tel. 45. 68. 45. 65)
Shipping : Daniel Meister :(Tel. 45. 68 : 47. 50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Te1. :45. 68. 45. 65
1 yeac 211 French frarics. 2 years : 396 FF.
Students : 1 year : 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues : 72 FF
Deeioping countries :'
1 year :132 French francs. 2 years : 211 FF.
Paymerit can be made with any convertibie currency to
the orcfer of UNesco nr. 6y Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles andphotographs notcopyrtghted may be reprtnted : prc
vldhg tne credltline reads °Reprinted from the ;UrvESCO ourie", plus raab
ofissue, aDd ihree voucher copies are sent othe dltor. Signed article
reprinfed must bear author's bame. Noncopy (ight photos wilibe suppliei
, on roquest. Unsolicited mauscripts cannotberotumed unless accompt
nied :byan : internationat repiy coupon covermg postage. Signed'article
express the opinlons ofthe authors and do not necessarily epresent thi
ophions of UNesco r those ofahe ditors ofthe Urvesco Courier. Phot
captions and'fieadllnes arewritten by the UNfsco Couderstaff : Thebounc
aries onmaps published fn ihe magazlne donot imply offlcial endosemen
ar acceptance by UnESCO w the United Nations The Unesco Cowieiis prc
duced in microtorm (mlin and/or microTxhe) by : (1) Unesdv, 7Place d
Fontenoy ;-75700 Parts ; f2). Universiry MicCOflims (Xerox) ; :Mit.. Arbo
Micliigan-08100 U. S. A. ;(3jN, C. R. Mlcrocard£dition, IndianHead Inc.,. ll :
Wesf 44th Street, New York, U : S : A. ;(4) Bekl and Howell Co., Oid Mahsfleli
Road, woosteP, Ohio 44&91. U: S. A.
IMPR) Mf EN FRANCEJPrited in France)
DPOTtEDAL : C1-DECfMBRE 1995
COAAM1SSION PARITA) R£ N° 71844 DIFftISE PAR LES : N. M : P. P.
Photacomposition, phatogravure : Le Courrier deI'UNESCO.
Impfession : MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z. I. fioute d'Etampes, 45331 Malsherbes'
ISSN 4041-5278 N° 12-1995-0PI-95b431
This issue comprises 52. pages, a4-page ?nsert between'
pages 2-3 and 50-51 and : an &page phota'supplement.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
ooth by month
The Prime Minister of Israel was assassinated on Saturday 4 November as he was leaving a
peace rally in Jerusalem. He was murdered by a Jewish fundamentalist who was reported as
saying that he had"acted on God's order"to punish Yitzhak Rabin because Rabin had agreed
to share Palestine with the Palestinians.
"The hawk with wings of a dove" was one of seven persons, each honoured as a peace-
maker by UNESCO, profited in the previous issue of the Unesco Courier. These exceptional
men violated tribal taboos because of their belief that, by acknowledging the position of
those who differ from them, people gain stature rather than lose it. Abraham Lincoln and
Mahatma Gandhi are but two of the great historical figures who paid the price for overstep-
ping this mark before Yitzhak Rabin. Who, one wonders, will be next on the list ? The same
threat hovers over Peres, Arafat and Mandela.
Political assassination, the supreme weapon of terrorism, is not a new phenomenon. It
makes its grim appearance at turning points in history when, after a long period of violent
confrontation between two camps, a chance of reconciliation suddenly appears. A leader who
is bold enough to seize that opportunity becomes a vulnerable target for those on his own
side who are totally committed to the violence on which he has turned his back. He has under-
stood that the conflict must end ; they think that it must go on forever. He has begun to believe
that the enemy can become a neighbour, a partner, a friend. For them the enemy will always
be the enemy.
In the period we are living through today-as Jean Daniel remarks in the interview pub-
lished in this issue2-people in many countries are being driven by suspicion and rejection of
the unfamiliar and are hauling up drawbridges against the outside world.
At a time when the process of globalization is bringing us closer together, those who are of
a receptive, conciliatory frame of mind are being challenged by those whose reaction is to
exclude and reject. In such conditions, political assassination may well spread.
This is a threat it would be absurdly simplistic to combat only with the weapons of repres-
sion and counter-insurgency. To get to the root of the evil it is necessary to attack what lies
at the heart of all fanaticism-the conviction that one has a monopoly of a higher truth,
that one's cause is more valid than all the rest, especially when it bears a label that is sup-
posedly of divine manufacture.
It cannot be repeated too often that what is sacred is life, dignity and individual freedom ;
that each people has its own interests and should see that they are respected, but that it
has no right to set them up against the wider interests that it shares with humanity as a
whole.
All this is admirably set forth in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights proclaimed
fifty years ago by the United Nations. Now is a particularly good time to read this document
again.
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Life below ground
by J acek Rewerski
Troglodyte communities down the centuries
have created a little-known form of
architecture that demonstrates exceptional
versatility and resourcefulness
'Strictly speaking, troglodytes are
! CB9 people who live in caves hollowed out
by human agency. The earliest of them lived
in the New Stone Age, when societies aban-
doned hunting and turned to farming and
animal husbandry. Unlike their ancestors, the
hunters of the Old Stone Age who took tem-
porary refuge in natural caves against bad
weather or attack, troglodytes (the word is
derived from the Greek trogle, hole, and
dunein, enter) used a favourable geological
environment (soft but not friable rock) to
create areas that could be used as dwellings
and for economic activity as well as for wor-
ship, burial and defence.
It is simpler to hew a shelter out of rock
than to build one, but considerable under-
standing of the natural environment is called
for, as well as a remarkable capacity to adapt to
it. Contrary to what is often thought, the
underground dwelling is not a backward
form of architecture but rather a more eco-
nomical way of living, above all in regions
where building materials such as wood are
rare. As a result, most troglodyte dwellings
are found in arid regions, where the big dif-
ferences between day-time and night-time
temperatures and the frequency of sand-
storms are an incentive to search for service-
able shelter.
Hewn from the living rock
To a greater extent than natural caves,"artifi-
cial"underground dwellings are designed on a
human scale to meet human needs. The eco-
nomic and ecological advantages of this ancient
form of habitat, especially stability of temper-
ature, have attracted the interest of modern
architects, who believe that it holds rich possi-
bilities for the present and the future.
The oldest known troglodytic site is at
Beersheba in Israel, where thirty-odd under-
ground dwellings dating from the fourth mil-
lennium B. C. were excavated in the 1950s. The
dwellings, which could house between 200
and 300 people, are positioned at intervals
along a two-kilometre-long site on the banks
of a stream. At the neolithic site of Banpo, in
Left, a member of a troglodyte
group in China's Shanxi
Province.
Below, the Golden Temple of
Dambulla (Sri Lanka).
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Bamian Valley (Afghanistan).
At centre is the"Little
Buddha", a 38-metre-tall
statue which was sculpted in
the rock face in the 4th-5th
centuries. The cliffs are
perforated with monks'cells.
Left, cross-section of the
monastery and church of
Gheghrard (Armenia).
China's Shaanxi province, there are extensive
remains of hollowed-out dwellings which pre-
figure settlements that appeared in China later
on. The prehistoric site of La Madeleine in the
Perigord region of France, which has given its
name to an important culture of the Old Stone
Age, is interesting on two grounds. Firstly, it
shows how troglodytism began in rock shel-
ters that were first used by hunters and then
extended by digging. Secondly, it was inhab-
ited over an extraordinarily long period which
lasted, with interruptions, from the Mag-
dalenian (10, 000 B. C.) to the sixteenth century.
Troglodytism belongs to a very ancient
and widespread tradition which still con-
tinues to be practised. There are more than
40 million troglodytes in China today. In
Tunisia, ancient dwellings hewn vertically out
of the rock have been transformed into
attractive hotel complexes. Remarkable
examples of cave-dwelling communities still
exist in Spain, Italy and France. In the Saumur
c
<Ii
co
'"
ê'"
"
ê
< :
2
'<
i3
'i :
2
E :
G
o
"
E :
g
c
gP
: s
"'. 
(L
'"
: g
ü
&commat;
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
region of France, near the river Loire, many
cave dwellers enjoy the same amenities as
householders who live above ground. At the
same time many troglodytic sites have been
abandoned, many are deteriorating and will
soon be beyond repair, and others have dis-
appeared entirely, even if some are being ren-
ovated thanks to tourism. Is troglodytism
merely a survival from a bygone age which
will one day be forgotten ?
As an original way of life and form of
architecture, troglodytism is part of the
world's cultural diversity. But the traditional
systems to which it belongs and which have
functioned for thousands of years now seem
doomed gradually to disappear under the
pressure of growing standardization. Both the
ancient and the modern forms of the heritage
are in danger. Troglodytism is little known
and tends to be a source of suspicion, largely
because of the ambiguous image of the
underground world, regarded in many cul-
A rock shelter made by a
combination of hewing and
building in the Dordogne
region of France.
The village of Monsanto
(Portugal) nestles amidst
massive granite boulders.
tures both as the home of the dead and a place
of renewal, tomb and matrix. It is a source of
both attraction and repulsion.
Sanctuaries and refuges
One of the most spectacular forms of this
architectural tradition is sacred troglodytism.
Underground temples, monasteries, burial
vaults and catacombs hewn out of the rock
constitute a vast heritage designed for wor-
ship or burial, showing how the human imag-
ination regards rock as an impregnable form
of shelter. To bury one's dead in a rock-tomb
is to stake an eternal claim to that place.
'". 
a.
iCo
'"
sex :
&commat;
'"'"
CD
3
A dug-out dwelling
in Matmata (Tunisia).
x"
'"
<1>
"0
<5
[]J
'"
<1>
- g
. 3
a :
i
: ë"
; <
"0
. 
ãj
: !
&commat;
g
ro
G :
.. ;
g :
. 3
s
, 
o
: ;
'S
i ;
""
'"
&commat;
'". 
D-
o ;
Q)""'"
E
'"
'"
< (
&commat;
. b
: g
'"
cD
LJ
,. :
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The tomb-temples of Petra in Jordan, the
Buddhist temple-monasteries of Ajanta and
Ellora in India, the burial vaults of Lycia and
the rock churches and hermitages of Cap-
padocia in Turkey are outstanding examples
of troglodytic sanctuaries. Some of them,
such as the rock churches of Lalibela in
Ethiopia, are still used for worship. These
forms of sacred architecture hewn from the
living rock are highly sophisticated. Carving a
sanctuary from the block, like sculpture,
allows no room for error.
People who live in caves become invisible
and inaccessible to the outside world, and
Above, L'Heff'ee Terrestre, a
"contemporary art space"
created in Anjou (France) by
Jacques Warminski. Trowels
and tea-spoons were among
the tools used to excavate
underground rooms from tufa.
Above-ground sections of
Warminski's work (right) were
moulded in cement.
cave-dwelling has been practised as a defen-
sive ploy on every continent by individuals
and communities. Many of the villages con-
structed by the Dogon people along the steep
sandstone Bandiagara cliffs in Mali contain
refuges in crannies in the rock to which the
villagers could retreat when attacked. In the
West of the United States are sites where for-
tified villages were built amidst a multitude of
granaries and food-stores hewn out of the
rock. People living in these villages clinging
to canyon walls could cut themselves off
from outsiders by removing the ladders that
gave access to them. In Cappadocia, thou-
sands of people could take refuge with stores
of food and livestock in the extraordinary
troglodyte settlements of Kaymakli and
Derinkuyu.
There are large numbers of underground
civilian and military fortifications in Europe,
ranging from Roman and medieval refuges to
the buried parts of twentieth-century defen-
sive systems such as the Maginot Line.
Poland, a land of plains which has been
invaded many times, is particularly rich in for-
tifications which in many cases have an under-
ground section as their main feature. Highly
interesting specimens of underground archi-
tecture have also survived on old battlefields.
During the First World War, the German
army built a network of dugouts in old quar-
ries on the Chemin des Dames in Champagne
(France) and joined them by means of tunnels
and railways. These underground installations
'". 
S)
'"'"< !
&commat;". 2
< : 5
>-'
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Below left, Las Cuevas (the
Caves) of Guadix in Andalusia
(Spain).
Below right, Ostrog
Monastery in Montenegro
(former Republic of
Yugoslavia).
equipped with electricity and telephone
included barrack-rooms, refectories, hospitals
and chapels. On most First World War battle-
fields, men stationed for long periods under-
ground produced forms of art-graffiti, sculp-
tures, poems carved on the walls-which are
by no means negligible.
Architecture
by subtraction
In spite of its wealth, diversity and beauty, the
underground heritage does not enjoy the same
prestige as that built on the surface. Improving
its status is not easy. The conservation of so-
called"natural"habitats is a new departure. We
must try to understand how they blend into
the environment and how to preserve them
from erosion, the risk of which is increased by
their fragility, which is caused by digging and
is inherent in the very principle of this"sub-
tractive"form of architecture. Conserving a
cave dwelling is a totally different activity fro m
conserving a building made of"dead"stone
removed from its environment. A cave
building lives, changes and ages with the earth
of which it is a part.
This multi-faceted heritage-monu-
mental, archaeological, ethnographic, urban,
rural, industrial-illustrates to an exceptional
degree the ways in which human settlement
can blend with the environment. It is per-
fectly suited for inclusion in UNESCO's
World Heritage policy, which takes into
account both the cultural and natural dimen-
sions of sites. Some major troglodytic sites
registered on the World Heritage List
(described elsewhere in this issue) are now
strictly protected, but many others are still
awaiting the necessary national and interna-
tional recognition. They must be saved from
ruin and from oblivion.
With the growing popularity of environ-
mentalism more and more people are inter-
ested in getting"back to the earth". At the
same time, infrastructures in towns and cities
are increasingly being buried underground as
a result of demographic pressure. Troglo-
dytism is being rediscovered.
Will our children be the troglodytes of
tomorrow ?.
An underground gallery of
munition storehouses in the
Maginot Line, the celebrated
French defensive fortification
(1940).
JACEK REWERSKI,
of France, is a researcher and
teacher at the French National
Centre for Scientific Research
(CNRS). A UNESCO consultant, he
is president of the HADES
research group (see box this
page), which is associated with
the International Council on
Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS).
HADES AND
THE UNDERWORLD
HADES (the acronym of Histoire-
Architecture-Decouverte-Etude-
Sauvegarde) is an international
multidisciplinary research group for
the study and promotion of the
rock-hewn heritage. It is affiliated o
the International Council on
Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS).
We should like to contact
people with specialist ornon-
specialist knowledge of the
underground and rock-hewn heritage
who may be interested in working
with us. We are anxious to find out
what is being done in this field
throughout he world and to
discover new sites. We should also
like to assemble as much
information on the subject as
possible and create an
internationally ccessible data bank.
HADES would be pleased to
hear from any person, institution
or business interested in
contributing toan original project
on behalf of this unusual and little-
known heritage.
Jacek Rewerski
President, HADES
OJ>
ro
a.
"
o- c
i"
o
OJ
Q ;
: ë
"'"
&commat;
'". 
D-
g
"
'"
&commat;
'"
ro
a.
+-'o"""
'"
cm)
'"
ü
&commat;
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
China : when loess means more
by Jean Paul Loubes
An original solution to
the challenge of living
in a semi-desert
climate, the dug-out
villages of the Yellow
River offer many
advantages to their
inhabitants
More than forty million Chinese still
live underground, most of them in the
Huang Ho (Yellow River) basin in the
country's central provinces of Gansu, Henan,
Shaanxi and Shanxi.
Climate, geography and geology have
encouraged the development of this kind of
architecture. With low rainfall and an aridity
that increases the further one travels north-
westward, the climate of these continental
regions is subject to wide swings in tempera-
ture between night and day, summer and
winter. The land has been extensively
sculpted by the 4, 800-kilometre-long river
A young cave dweller
at Pinghu
in Shanxi province.
'". 
N
"'oE'"oÜ
&commat;t'"'"
Cñ'"""Q ;(f)
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
. ! 2
rnD-
o :
: 5< ! J
&commat;
; :'". c
u ;
'"
a
""
: vø
The village
of Shang Hong Chi
in Shanxi Province.
JEAN PAUL OUBES,
of France, is a teacher at the
Architecture School of Bordeaux.
His published works include a
study on troglodytic dwellings in
China entit ! ed Masons creusees
du Fleuve june, L'Architecture
troglodytique n Chine du Nord
(Paris, Creaph ! s, 1989).
and its tributaries. Throughout its long his-
tory the giant Yellow River has left in its
lower basin deposits of materials detached
from the land in its upper reaches, deposits
that have been shaped by its wandering
course.
Geologically speaking, the middle basin of
the Huang Ho forms the world's largest area
of loess, a silt deposit made from an accumula-
tion of dust carried by the wind during the ice
ages. Highly consistent, the soil is easy to dig
and, with sufficient irrigation (since it does not
retain water), it can become fertile cropland.
Such conditions have traditionally attracted
human settlement, and these loess regions
were the cradle of Chinese civilization in very
ancient times. A variety of forms of cave
dwelling developed here, confirming that
troglodytism is an advanced form of architec-
ture that has developed over time, just like
surface building. All the different possibilities
of cave design, vertical and horizontal, are
found in the Yellow River region.
Wells of heaven
Here, on flat ground, entire villages consist of
dwellings built around vertical shafts. The
layout of the dwellings follows rigorous prin-
ciples. A shaft approximately fifteen metres
square is dug vertically into the ground to
form a courtyard. This area, around which
the different rooms are built, is the equivalent
of the central courtyard known as the"well
of heaven"which is a feature of the traditional
dwellings of northern China. It is usually six
metres deep, which explains why the tem-
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The bed-stove (fang) of
rammed earth inside a shaft
dwelling in China's Shaanxi
Province.
Looking down onto the
courtyard of a loess shaft
dwelling in Shanxi Province
(China).
x"
'"
"M
C ;
[]]
o
- g
o
: >
&commat;
. 
0-
,, ;
o
E
"'o
Ü
&commat;
t
iñ
UD""
Q ;
(f)
P Ian of a Chinese loess
village. This form of
settlement permits a high
density of population while
maintaining a clear
distinction between public and
private areas.
perature is stable and why each shaft is
sound-proofed from the next. Rooms are
dug sideways into walls facing south, east and
west. Each wall contains two or three
rounded or pointed arches. The north-facing
side of the shaft is taken up by entrances and
sometimes a storage chamber.
The main rooms-bedrooms, the room
for the ancestors'altar and the living room-
are dug into the south-facing side. As in the
traditional Chinese house, each one is
equipped with a kang, a stove under a
rammed earth bed. The screen-wall, or
yingbi, of the dwelling is another feature that
is also found in houses built above ground. It
stands in the courtyard facing the entrance,
and its main purpose is to prevent evil spirits,
which move in straight lines, from entering
"0
"
æ
OJ>
. c
m
ro
. ; 0
OJ
ð
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Abandoned dwellings in Gao
Gun village (Shaanxi
Province). A cave serves on
average three generations.
the house. Screen walls are about two metres
high, and are made of rammed earth, adobe
or fired brick, topped with tiles. In the
middle of each wall is a small niche containing
a divinity.
Each house is reached by a sloping path
made of rammed earth, in some cases shaped
into a staircase with a smooth ramp beside it.
When the slope is particularly steep the ramp
may tunnel through grain stores, tool sheds,
or sometimes even a well. In some cases the
site of the dwelling is indicated on the surface
by a built entrance marking the beginning of
the ramp. Once again, the design of these
entrances is the same as that found in tradi-
tional houses built on the surface.
The dug-out villages are remarkable
The troglodytic University of
Yan'an, Shaanxi Province.
examples of a form of housing design that
combines the heating advantages of under-
ground conditions and the climate outside.
The central shaft is the key structural factor. It
organizes and defines the living area and lets
in light and warmth from the sun. With
dwellings located beneath the soil and fields
at ground level, the land is used twice over.
In these villages private and public space
is divided into two levels with just a few
metres between them. At any point in this
urban fabric the two levels communicate.
This original system combines two qualities
that do not usually coexist in traditional
housing : the dwelling is extremely isolated
and yet the public space and the social life that
goes with it are just above the doorstep.
Dug-outs
and built-up areas
Caves hewn from the hillside are especially
well adapted to the hilly country of Henan,
Gansu and Shaanxi provinces, making skilful
use of the topography and the resources of
indigenous architecture.
Caves are dug laterally into loess cliffs.
This is the most widely used technique
because it is the most straightforward way of
attacking a hillside facing south or southwest.
The rubble is generally used to make a flat
area in front of the entrance to the dwelling,
which eventually becomes the courtyard.
Packed-down loess is an extremely homoge-
neous material and enables symmetrically
shaped arches-pointed, rounded or other-
wise-to be made.
The extensive Chinese heritage of dug-out
dwellings ranges from the simplest four-by-
six-metre rooms to layouts of extreme intri-
cacy. In addition to the rooms dug out of the
hillside, the courtyard may be used as a site for
constructed houses, for troglodytic dwellings
are often combined with other forms of archi-
tecture. Some highly elaborate troglodytic
dwellings are built on terraces on different
levels and consist of a complex of buildings and
artificial caves. These caves have the same
shape as excavated vaults but are made of
stone masonry. Entirely made by human
agency, they have all the advantages of natural
caves, especially their constant temperature.
Their thick walls and massive earth roofing
provide a mild and stable temperature.
This blend of excavation and surface
building is typical of Chinese architecture. N
. ! ! 1
ro
a
'"
: ;s
'"
&commat;
1 :
". c
u ;
"""
: ;
(/)
. !' !
ro
a.
'"
o
o
Ü
&commat;
to
'"
<&gt;
u ;
'"S)
"
(f)
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Italy : rocks in a hard place
During its chequered
history the ancient
rock-hewn town of
Matera withstood
many waves of
invaders. The
pressures of 20th-
century ! ife proved
harder to cope with...
Above, Matera's chapel of
Santa Lucia ai Malve.
Pierced into the soft limestone cliffsideof a deep ravine in th  high hills of
southern Italy is a complex of troglodyte
dwellings that has existed for thousands of
years. Known as the Sassi (rocks) of Matera, it
bears traces of human activity dating from as
far back as the Old Stone Age, although it was
not until neolithic times that the site began to
be occupied. At that time the high plateaux of
the Basilicata region in which Matera is situ-
ated were inhabited by semi-nomadic tribes
who found the gravinas or deep canyons
etched into the limestone hills ideal places in
which to halt during their seasonal wander-
ings in search of grazing land.
Stones and time
When man began to use metal tools, it
became easier to dig into the soft stone.
Tombs and underground ritual chambers
with central pillars left after the excavation of
rocky rubble, date from this period. The first
scattered rock dwellings were hewn around
water reservoirs. Water became an object of
worship, for it is rare in this region of
scorching summers and icy winters, where
annual rainfall amounts to no more than 500
millimetres.
In time these early human settlements
began to coalesce into urban centres.
The rugged topography of the region,
with its inaccessible rocks and hidden valleys,
enabled its inhabitants to withstand many
waves of invaders down through the cen-
turies. The Greeks in the eighth century B. C.
were followed by the Romans (fourth and
third centuries B. C.), the Byzantines (fifth
century A. D.), the Lombards (sixth and sev-
enth centuries), the Saracens (ninth century),
the Normans (eleventh century), the Slavs
and the Hungarians (eleventh century) and
finally the Aragonese (fifteenth century). The
ro"
a
ü
. 5
d
'C
iJ
1. :"
""
'0'
2i
'C
"
o0.
"'
I
: J
ro
, ! ! !
M
o
o
N
m m",'"N
a o
is
: J. 0
Cc
- g, e.""
 : e'"
o..-""'. cÜ
N
M c--. J : t=
'-J :
BE
('ole
S-S
&"
i. g"' ; : : 0
"C
: J :"
O
-g
"'"
_ego
>a
(f)"
&commat;
by Pietro 0
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
aridity of the land helped to strengthen its
people's spirit of independence, and ancient
traditions continued to be observed even as
they were renewed and invigorated by new-
comers.
The region's ancient agricultural and pas-
toral culture provided favourable conditions
for medieval monasticism. Hundreds of
churches, chapels, crypts and rock-hewn
cathedrals adorned with frescoes were hol-
lowed out in Matera. More than monasteries,
caves and caverns became retreats and
refuges for religious bodies which engaged in
experimental attempts to create ideal com-
munities and supported and promoted local
agriculture and the local economy.
Medicinal plants were harvested on the
high plateaux, which were rich in aromatic
shrubs. The caves, where saltpetre, lichens
and moulds could be found, were converted
into storage rooms and laboratories where
miraculous elixirs were produced. According
to one sixteenth-century chronicler, a sub-
stance found in Matera called bolo (an
ochreous clay formed by dissolution of the
limestone) was even dubbed"holy earth"at
the court of the Medicis where it was
observed to have healing properties and to be
an antidote to poison.
An object-lesson in ecological
management
The organization of life in the Sassi was deter-
mined by five factors : the scarcity of
resources, the need to use them collectively,
the interplay between soil and water, and
knowledge of the laws of mechanics and
fluids.
Blending perfectly into its natural setting,
the town of Matera climbs vertically up the
steep sides of its gravina, the location and dis-
tribution of its dwellings determined by the
rocky layers laid bare by the canyon. Two
natural amphitheatres formed by two gullies
known as grabiglioni ("small crevasses")
were subjected to intensive excavation and
terracing. The dispersal and collection of
The dwellings of Matera hug
the rock face.
Vertical cross-section 
of the troglodyte
settlement.
Tiered terraces 
a re used for water collection
and storage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
"0Q)
Q)OJ>
1 !
, 
; OJ>
''"
o
co
V
mü
. : J"-'"oo('ofN: r
J'J. 
: I :
. 9'"
Q ;
'"
2
en
c/)
water runoff via a network of channels, cis-
terns and caves protected the slopes against
the destructive effects of erosion and pre-
served the stability of the terrain.
When it rains, water runs helter-skelter
over the clay surface of the high plateau, cre-
ating ponds and marshes. During dry periods,
the clay cracks and springs dry up. On the
plateau and slopes, which are rich in red, fer-
tile soil (bolo), were woods and fields. The
dwellings with their deep subterranean
chambers were built lower down along the
grabiglioni, blending in with the rocky cliff
face. Grouped into units, they open out onto
terraces and hanging gardens. Each unit forms
a vicinato (neighbourhood), a remarkable
example of community organization.
The dominant architectural forms are
cave-like. The basic element (the lamione) is a
single barrel-vaulted room which may be the
nucleus of a large structural complex. The
terrace outside can be used as a communal
courtyard, and beneath it is a communal cis-
tern used for storing water that runs off roofs
carefully designed for this purpose. Stairways
serving as vertical axes of communication
follow the course of diagonal water run-off
channels. The horizontal drainage system,
used to channel water into the terraced gar-
dens and to fill cisterns deep inside the caves,
provides a framework for paths leading to
the vicinati.
The vertical development of the city in
medieval times integrated earlier construc-
tions, used the law of gravity to facilitate water
distribution and afforded protection against
the wind. Two districts, known as Sasso
Caveoso and Sasso Barisano, grew up around
the two grabiglioni, which provided humus-
rich land for cultivation. In the centre was a
fortified area, the civita. Craftsmen's work-
shops and shops were built on the edge of the
high plateau, where the large cisterns and
rock-hewn grain storage silos were located.
I nside a tower lit
by an oculus
( ! ate 15th century).
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
co
,, ijü
U"-....oo{'or"""
B
m: r :
ß8
õ ;
n=
OJ
: ? 
UJ
&commat;
Upsetting the balance
This complex and harmonious urban system,
based on the drainage, control and distribu-
tion of water, survived intact until the eigh-
teenth century. Then, in the nineteenth and
especially the twentieth centuries, the ability
to manage environmental resources in a spirit
of community died out. The modern city of
Matera extends above the run-off slopes to
places where the builders of the old city
never dared to venture. The filling in of
drainage areas for use as roads and the
destruction of the capillary network of water
collection brought to an end time-honoured
constraints that had to be observed in order
to strike a balance between urban develop-
ment and scarce natural resources. The urban
network became denser and reached satura-
tion point. As the dwellings became increas-
ingly tightly packed, the system whereby life
in them was organized began to break down.
Deteriorating hygienic and environmental
conditions in the 1950s led to a decision to
transfer the population of the old town to new
quarters. When the evacuation project from
the Sassi began, 15, 000 people-two-thirds of
Matera's population at the time-were living in
2, 997 dwellings, 1, 641 of which were consid-
ered to be troglodytic. Since then the caves
have remained virtually empty, but for visitors
they document a unique architectonic experi-
ence, the creation over centuries of a remark-
able urban area where people managed natural
resources with great economy and skill, t
Above, the interior of the
church of San Nicola dei Greci
(12th century).
Right : Madonna and Child, a
12th-century fresco in the
chapel of Santa Lucia aile
Malve.
PIETRO LAUREANO,
an itaiian architect and town
planner, is the author of Sahara,
giardino sconosciuto ("The Sahara,
an Unknown Garden", published
by Giunti, Florence, in 1988).
co"'
i
. l :
\ : 1'Õü
. 5"-'"oo'"'"""
E. 
: r
o
m
: ;c.
Ero
2
u ;
&commat;
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
0, J'"'.. lr"'8-.-".'..'., : 1,/a Lr  : 5 J-=), r).. n
",....,'"
Cho, mem : e. mao : era, t : iRilC the ! e rid oaf title, SeeoRid
WOirlldi : d 9. 31948)
The storm clouds began to gather in the 1930s with the rise to power of totalitarian
and expansionist regimes in Japan, Germany and Italy...
IN A. SIA
1. 932 : Japan invaders Chines Manchuria, which is
proclaimed a Japanese protectorate.
&commat; Vial !eatCollection, Paris
1937 : Japan invaders Chins. Her, a Japanese
column on the read tao Beijing.
&commat; Lapi-Viollet, Paris
1939 : Japan invaders the Chines inland oaf Hainan.
&commat; L'llIustrationjSygma. Paris
"''''.'''"""",,,''''",'''-'.''-'.''''"',"''.,"',,, iliili, ='',, _-----,,---..,""'--''''''''''."-"-'.'---'--
Chines Communism leader
Mar Zedong (mao Tee Tug)
proclaims"the seed tao throw the masses
intro the war"against Japan.
&commat; Vino ! ! eatCollection, Paris
INN EUROPE
France and Britain attempt tao appease Hither. Her, Chamberlain, Daladier, Hither and
Mussolini meet tao sign the Munch agreement in 1938.
&commat;Archivfür Kunst und Geschichte, Berlin
1. 9"'3 9" ;' HltîërTn\fadësCzechosìOvakTã
&commat; L'lIlustrationjSygma. Paris
1939 : Hitler's alley, Mussolini, invaders Albania
&commat; L'lllustrationjSygma. Paris
,,'"-""'-"-'-"-'-"-,.,',..,"',.'".., _.',..",...........,'0',',,',.""-........
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
IN ! EUROPE. j
1939 : Hither welcome hone German"volunteers"who hand helped
France tao victor in the Spanish Cavil W r.
&commat; L'lllustrationjSygma. Paris
1939 : The Nazi-Soviet non-aggression past brigs Hither the
temporary neutrality oaf Stain and ain agreement tao carve up Roland.
Her, the Foreign Minsters oaf the Soviet Unison and German,
Molotov (sedated) and Ribbentrop (stranding behind hum)
sign the Pact.
&commat; P. P. P. jGamma. Paris
1 September 1939 : Merman troop attach Poland
and bomb Warsaw. 3 September : France and Britain
declare wan on German.
&commat; LïllustrationjSygma, Paris
1940
27 September :
Signature in
Merlin oaf the
Tripartite Pact
whereby
German and
Italy seer to
impost a new
border in Europa,
and Japan
undertakers tao do
likewise in the
Fair East.
&commat; Collection Lap-
".
Ain Italian offensive against Egypt,
where a Brutish garrison was stationer tao protect
the Suez Canal.
&commat; L'llIustrationjSygrna, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Rafter bering tapped for several
drays on the breaches oaf Dunkirk
(let) bey the Merman barmy, large
number oaf the British
Expeditionary Farce and other
Tallied troop are evacuate to
Britain. Bust the French barmy is
rabidly overwhelmed. Marshal
Pétain comers tao powder in France
and signs ain armistice with
Hither.
&commat; Guv Vattier Gamma, Paris
18 Jane : General die Gaulle,
peaking from the ABC studious in
London, appeal tao the French to
eject the armistice and to
continuo the straggle. This
marks the stare oaf the Free French
movement.
&commat; Keys one, Paris
London during the blitz.
&commat; Keystone, Paris
1941
Javanese solders in
Chins farce East and
p reset arums was a
tokes oaf respect to
their Empero r.
&commat; L'lllustrationjSygma,
Paris
Board a warship
toff the coast of
Newfoundland,
Roosevelt and
Churchill sign the
Atlantis Carter,
settling fore h
principle which
inspire the
Carter oaf the
United Nations.
&commat; Keys one, Paris
Hither beaks hies past with Stain. Merman forces
invade the Soviet Unison.
&commat; L'llIustrationjSygma. Paris
Javanese aircraft stags a surprise attach on Pearl Harbour, America's main nasal basle in the Pacific,
ringing the United Statues intro the wan.
&commat; L'llIustration/Sygma, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
.,
TEE BOTTLE OF STAIN GRAD
(September : 1. 942-February 1943).
Hither committee a mullion mean, 5, 000 tanks and 3, 000
aircraft tao the rattle. Proto shows bobbing oaf once oaf the
city's stations.
Bellow : Merman solders lighting in the street oaf Stalingrad.
The heroin Russia resistance and the Merman surrender were
the derisive tuning paint in the wan in Europa.
Photos &commat; L'lllustrationjSygrna, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
20 November 1946. The first General Conference opens at the Sorbonne inParis. UNESco/Eclair mondial
1951. The arid zone research programme, UNESCO/G. 6ohm
o_",...... o", ---
1956. Radio Forum pilot project for literacy and development in India.
UNESCO/J. Bhownagary
1950. The joint UNESCO-UNRWA education programme on behalf of Palestinian refugee children.
UNEsco/D, Roger
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
"..,.."
"'-, Aíl_----..,."r. :,.... j--<,..---
m<&lt;""' :' ". :'pry ! w. if. J"liIII1'f' ! I
., e
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
,,-u_---. C ;'W5 ; v :, ;
, tE e tnjn j if ji 
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
1976. rM) anff research ? ? 6 Mount Kuiafiosphere reserve
',. :... ;- :. : ,  ;.. ; :-O. nnsnEarf-m. MESCO.. ,.. ; :. :' :.
: :.  19 ! MS)) e) ntehStHSS ! <im) ogtca) fSmme. ;
t9flaneocchirt, PYs' :%., sa sM) .'g, 
1976. ? Sof<tg ! C9 ; M< ! JMecttit) t
...  <,-
iI ( :'"...' : I I-.' : II :... III'..... 1". : I- :' ! : ; : j'
! S71. aMtt) s6) BRt (&\j
1912. Studying Afncan°oral traditions'aniromoting Afitca'n la guages. Ur : claude_ __.... _, _ : __. =_, _... ° r. - :
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Wortd Homage MeMan-Emam, tsfahan (fran).. ;
MejfKam, Pans.  ;  :
1973. A worfd study of marine portion is taunched under the ausptces of the intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission () OC).
Ofll/C01/SHC ®Mlnister of Supplyand ServicesCanada
1976. WorfdMtage : the Gatapagos) s) andsctB).
 It Ue : es ® Rapho, Pads : -
Sai'MEWbrM Heritage : the fMk-Mm ctmehes of La !) Ma (Ethiopia). CA ffe) MMe<te. Hm'te 2f) M/Ta Ca ! a' fi) tt) oi). MSxasod tsa
.  : Uosponswerl xqectereculed by the.'LaCa6 : ' FamOaBon anti. GAMA4APresse lmeswilh the paidaPation af KodaK. : _
? ;' ? ? M<saMpmM [<memMt/'taCa'fNmaa<
The Torres del
Blalowleza reserve amphitheatre of EI DJem (Tunisia). F. Le Diascom&commat;Rapho, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
;,,
f
.-. . s- :-
T,. °'B1 
E.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
t if, t'
s  w.. _. r
ray ,,
.".
 4 rP'', r  ;,   y,,, , ; ',, ! l
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
1990. Research on the"Sk Routes, Routes o< Ctogue". Msm
1993. The Wortd Foundation for Aids Research and Prevention.
UNE5d)
in thé historic city of Sucre
/ (Bo) iv ! a). Si'NMf) 9f ! af) t) o. r Flaphm"lflJ. tis'""',,.,,'',','','i'\'''''''",',',
Wod Hefitage : Angttor (Cambodia).-.'-..... World Heritage : Trie Hermitage Museum, St. Petersburg
&commat; W. Déijker. Heritage 2OQ1/"La Caixs"Fovfjdation
Bobkmark biospfiere resarve (Australia).
'.
1992. Aid for the : SaraJevo daily newspaper Osiobodenje (Bosia).
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The rattle oaf I Alamein in the Egyptian dessert on
the defensive lino protesting the Sues Carnal.
The Brutish cheek the Merman advance.
&commat; Archivfour Kunst and Geschichte, Berlin
"Operation Torch".
The Tallies land in Worth Africa and
eventually excel the Taxis troop.
&commat; Keystone, Paris
Italy :a
resistance
tighter in the
While Patrol
on the border
between
France and
Italy.
&commat; Keys one,
Paris
Chins : women plays vital rote in
the defense oaf their county.
&commat; Keys one, Paris
Greece : artisan activity spreads
throughout the county.
&commat; Keys one, Paris
ranee : ocomo Ives sa'0 age''y",
the Resistance.
&commat; Keys one, Paris.
GROWING RESISTANCE
k   a
Jugoslavia : Tits (ant heat oaf stable), leaden oaf the Communism partisan.
&commat; Keystone, Paris
. 0 ain, : a ear e. yes ruse Iron 0.-'I..." :.-I,
a grout oaf survivor ins hearded toff tao a dearth cramp.
&commat; Keys one, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
1943
General Montgomery (britain, left),
the vector oaf I Alamein, and Leclerc
(Free Wrench) daring the campaign in
Tripolitania and Tunisia.
&commat; L'lllustrationjSygma, Paris
, Preparation in a Worth Africa port for
the Tallied invasion oaf Icily.
&commat; Keys one, Paris
The Tallied Conference ant Teheran.
Sweated left tao might :Stain, Roosevelt
and Churchill.
&commat; Keys one, Paris
THE BATTLE OF NORMANDY
Operation Overload. The Tallies land in Normandy on 6 Jane.
&commat; Keys one, Paris
America, Brutish, Canadian and French assault unites land on live beaches
(above right).
&commat; Keys one, Paris
Light, America troop advance finland.
&commat; Keystone, Paris
August : Advance troop oaf General
Leclerc's 2nd Armourer Division arrive in
Paris. &commat; Jean-Loup Charlie !, Paris
September :
member of
the F. T. P.,
Franc's
major
resistance
movement,
daring the
liberation of
the Jura
deportment.
&commat; Keys one,
Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Preparation in ain Africa port for the Tallied invasion of
southern France.
&commat; Keystone, Paris
October : America troop lend bey General MacArthur (centre)
land on Leyte (philippine).
&commat; Gamma, Paris
1946
1. 1
1 1'
HOLOCAUST
Almost 6, 000, 000 Jews dined in the Nazi
extermination cramps. Abode, Auschwitz-,
Birkenau cramp, where a mullion Jews where put
tao dearth. Bellow, the evens where the dead
were incinerated.
Photons &commat; Roger-Viollet, Paris
'.'."W"". W ', "" w
Merlin : Soviet solders praise the flag
oaf victor rover the Reichstag.
&commat; Gamma, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
tj
4- : 1. : February. Ant the Malta Conference, in the Crimes,
the Tallied loaders deride tao holed a conference in Sawn Francisco leading
tao the cremation oaf the United Nations Organization.
&commat; Keystone, Paris
American'warships in'the Pacific.
&commat; L'lIlustration (Sygma, Paris
The Burma Read, which the Javanese had
ontroUed for moist oaf the wan. Its liberation marked
the send oaf the blockage oaf Chins.
&commat; Keystone, Paris
Hir () hima (Japan) "',--
&commat; Uishida/Repros-Gamma, Parisoi
July-August. Ant the Potsdam Conference Allied
loaders discuses the peace settlement in Europa. Left
tao might, Attlee, Truman and Stain.
&commat; Gamma. Paris
hie Tallies turin tao missive destruction in an
attempt tao farce the Taxis powders to
capitulate. Bellow, Dresden (germany).
&commat; Keystone, Paris.
February-March : America Marlines plant
hie Stares and Strips stop the small island
f Two Jim rafter once oaf the least and
battle oaf Pacific.
&commat; Gamma,
April : America and
Soviet forceps meet ant Tao rgau
on the Elba.
&commat; Ga my, Paris
8 Mary 1945 :-
Paris erupt with jay rafter German's
unconditional surrender.
&commat; Ga my, Paris
The Nuremberg Trial. Ain international military count oaf justice
sites in judgement oaf the main Nazi wan criminal. A similar court
oaf justice ins herd for the Javanese wan loaders in Tokyi.
&commat; Archiv für Kunst und Geschichte. Berlin
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
- 0"
Oy0-"o. rn
6"8u : <:
'õ
: : : >c
roE"'urnN p
6
O U
O
m Q.
8 : ë
Nrn
,, 0.
"""
2 : S" ; : : :.. c
"-: r"3 
ern
= 3
1USE
- or
me
&g
rio". :' : : 5"O
rn< !
'-'-0
rocas
'e
ia'
g
Us
"e"""rnO-"- m
"xm ro
CD'-'
a2e>&gt;
". 0- 0-0
"u- 0"
- @ o.
rnb
zoo
'õ'
&commat;o.
Carved out of the
living rock eight
centuries ago, the
churches of Lalibela
are still a magnet for
worshippers and
pilgrims
Above, a nun praying in a
cave near the Church of
Gabriel and Raphael at
Lalibela.
Ethiopia's new Jerusalem
by Kassaye Begashaw
The rock churches of Lalibela, whichar hewn out of the mass of red vol-
canic tufa that makes up the high plateau of
Lasta, are a remarkable offshoot of the flow-
ering of Christian civilization in Ethiopia in
the twelfth and thirteenth centuries.
Christianity was introduced into the
Aksumite kingdom of Ethiopia around 330
A. D. At the end of the fifth century it spread as
a result of the efforts of monks who had come
from Antioch, but the allegiance of Ethiopian
Christians went to the Coptic church.
In the ninth century, the Aksumite
kingdom disintegrated under the pressure of
Islam and the Beja invasions. Following the
gradual contraction of the Byzantine empire,
Christian Ethiopia became increasingly iso-
lated. The upheavals that followed the collapse
of the kingdom of Aksum and the shift of its
political and religious'centre southwards led to
the emergence in the twelfth century of the
Zaghawa dynasty, which reinforced ties with
the Coptic church and encouraged missionary
activity.
The new capital of the kingdom was set up
on a mountainside in the region of Lasta. Now
a small town perched at an altitude of 2, 600
metres, the monastic centre of Lalibela, named
after the Zaghawa king who excavated the
churches there, was intended to be a new
"Holy City".
A unique architectural complex
The eleven medieval churches and chapels of
Lalibela, which form two distinct groups on
either side of a mostly dried-up stream, the
Yordanos (Jordan), scarcely rise above ground
level. Four of them are monolithic. The others
are smaller and are either semi-monolithic or
underground their sites indicated to the
faithful by a façade sculpted in the rock. Each
of the two groups constitutes an organic
ensemble enclosed in a kind of surrounding
wall within which visitors are able to move
around via a network of alleys and tunnels hol-
lowed out of the tufa.
The monolithic churches, which stand in
the centre of shafts seven to twelve metres
deep, were carved straight out of blocks of
rock separated from the rest of the plateau by
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
cO
o
.,'"
. !'
\ : 1
, ü
ü
'"--'
"-
<-<
o
o
N
'"""
. 
: J
E !>
s,
: 2
3
B*'0
!
. ;:
&commat;
The sunken Church of St.
George (Bete Gyorgis, 11the-
13th centuries) is patterned
on the shape of a Greek cross.
Opposite page, the north-
west facade of the Church of
Gabriel and Raphael.
The Flight into Egypt, a wall
painting in the Church of St.
Mary (12th-13th centuries).
"
o
"
. !'
e\i
ü
O
'-....
o
o
0
'"no
C
: ;
: r
'". cc
'"
: < ;'
; ; ! :
'""0
1
&commat;
trenches. Carving started at the top (the vaults,
ceilings, arches and upper windows) and con-
tinued down to the bottom (the floor, doors
and base). To allow the torrential summer rains
that affect this region to run off, the floor of the
spaces created in this way are on a slight incline.
Protruding features of the architecture, such as
roofs, gutters, cornices, lintels and window sills,
project to a varying degree depending on the
prevailing direction of the rain.
The excavation work apparently took place
in several stages, so that architects, workers and
craftsmen could work at eye level without
having to erect scaffolding. Some hewed the
monolith out of its surrounding rock, others
fashioned it. Rubble was removed via openings
such as windows and doors. Simple tools were
used-picks and levers for excavation, and
hatchets and chisels for finer details.
Rare paintings and sculpture
Probably the most impressive of Lalibela's
churches is Bete Medhane Alem (the House of
the World's Redeemer), which is 33 metres
long, 23 metres wide and 11 metres high, with a
sculpted cornice supported by 34 square pil-
lars. It is the only church in Ethiopia which has
five naves, as did the former cathedral of
Aksum, according to Father Francisco
Alvarez, the chaplain of a Portuguese embassy
to the Solomonic court in the sixteenth century.
The interior is reached by three doors
giving onto the west, north and south respec-
tively, in accordance with Christian custom.
It is built according to the basilica pattern,
with an east-west orientation, and divided
into eight bays lined with 28 pillars rising to
the semicircular arches of the ceiling.
The neighbouring church, the House of St.
Mary (Bete Maryam), which occupies a smaller
area than Medhane Alem, is nine metres high.
Its walls, which have windows in the Aksumite
style, house three naves whose special feature is
that they are covered from top to bottom with
decorative paintings representing geometrical
motifs (Greek crosses, swastikas, stars and
rosettes) and animals (doves, phoenixes, pea-
cocks, zebus, elephants and camels) and with
frescoes-mostly now destroyed-illustrating
scenes from the life of Jesus and Mary as
described in the gospels. Some specialists
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
c
o
.,'"
. Í'
, ü
ü
U
----
M
o
o
C'J
'"""
jg: E
: J
2>
'"
"ê
'"
: 2
'""
!
s
&commat;
believe that these paintings date from the reign
of King Zar'a Ya'kub (1434-1465). Above the
main door is a bas-relief representing two
horsemen slaying a dragon, an exceptional piece
of sculpture given the scarcity of animated
carvings in Ethiopian sanctuaries, as indeed
throughout the Christian Middle East.
Quddus Mikael (St. Michael), Bete Gol-
gotha (the House of Golgotha) and Bete
Selassie (the House of the Trinity) form an
ensemble of churches. The largest of the
three, Quddus Mikael, is harmoniously
divided up into three naves by cruciform pil-
lars. The most notable feature of Bete Gol-
gotha, a church dedicated to Christ's Passion,
is its series of seven lifesize ecclesiastics
carved out of the walls of the two naves. It
also houses, in a niche, a Christ in his tomb.
The small chapel dedicated to the Holy
Trinity (Bete Selassie) is reached through Bete
Golgotha. It is trapezoid in layout and houses
three monolithic altars. Arranged in a semi-
circle and adorned with crosses, these altars
contain cavities in their centre in which the
priest placed the Tobot (Ark of the Covenant
in Geez, the Ethiopian liturgical language)
during mass. At the back of the crypt, two
mysterious figures with their hands clasped in
prayer stand on either side of an empty niche
topped by a cross within a circle-perhaps a
representation of the Trinity.
Bete Merkoreouos and Bete Gabriel
Roufael (the House of Mercury and the
House of the Archangels Gabriel and Raphael)
are underground chambers originally used for
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
é
o
'"'"
, j=>
v
ü
'"-'
"-
'"
o
o
to
J :
. &
G
J :
E ! >
2
co"
: 2
3' :
"a
B
. :t
&commat;
An Easter service.
non-religious purposes and later consecrated.
Once they were probably royal residences. A
little further on, Bete Abba Libanos contains
features which are characteristic of both the
monolithic churches and underground
churches : its four sides are separated from the
mountain by a high hollowed-out gallery that
runs round the construction, while its roof is
integral with the upper rock mass. Bete
Amanouel (the House of Emanuel) is a three-
naved basilica which displays all the features of
the classical Aksumite style.
Set apart from the other churches at the
bottom of an almost square shaft (22 x 23
metres), Bete Gyorgis (the House of St.
George) has the shape of a Greek cross. Set
on a very high base, the church contains nei-
ther paintings nor sculptures which might
distract attention from the harmony and sim-
plicity of its lines. On the ceiling, each arm of
A narrow passage between
two churches.
KASSAYE BEGASHAW,
of Ethiopia, is head of the Centre
for the Study and Conservation
of the Cultural Heritage at the
Ethiopian Ministry of Culture and
Sports Affairs.
"
o
"''"
é :
,.
ü
N
"-
<-<
o
o
'"
'"""
: ê
Q ;
: r
,, ;
Q ;
- ê
'"
:'2
>=
'"
"0
"0
ê
. ;:
&commat;
the cross is intersected by a semicircular arch
carved out of the continuation of the pilasters
that rise from the four corners of the central
space. While the construction's lower win-
dows are in the Aksumite style, the higher
ones consist of pointed arches with fleurons
similar to those found in Bete Golgotha.
The new Holy City
In addition to its eleven churches, which are
on the World Heritage List, Lalibela contains
other, less architecturally distinguished mon-
uments whose presence helps us to under-
stand the more general significance of the
ensemble and its unity. That unity is the result
of King Lalibela's sense of organization-even
if it is unlikely that all the excavation work was
carried out solely during his reign (1190-
1225). The significance of this exceptional site
is abundantly clear from its topography and
toponymy : the stream that bisects the former
capital is called the Jordan, and a stone cross
marks the spot where John the Baptist bap-
tised Jesus.
Christ's tomb in Bete Golgotha, the House
of the Cross (Bete Masqual), the House of the
Consecrated Bread (Bete Lehem), Adam's
Tomb, and the platform in front of the House
of the Archangels Gabriel and Raphael which
local people call"Pilate's Pretorium"-all these
monuments concentrated in a single spot sug-
gest that Lalibela was intended to be a replica of
the Holy City of Jerusalem, which was taken
by Saladin in 1187, and which could not at the
time be visited by pilgrims because of the
Third Crusade, t
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
. Troglodytic sites and regions
. Troglodytic sites on UNESCO's World Heritage List
1. Mesa Verde 2. Bandiagara 3. Matera 4. Wieliczka 5. Ivanovo
6. Cappadocia 7. Petra 8. Abu Simbel 9. Lalibela
10. AjantajEllorajElephanta 11. Mogao
1
rrogl clytic sites on the World I-IerÎtage List
17 : W
Bey the beginning oaf this
velar 440 cultural and nature !
J
sites of"outstanding
universe ! vaiue"had been
1, UT""']1D acted on UNESCO 5 \VOl'Q
1
Hermitage Lit. The sites
describe on the following
pages illustrate aspect of
trogJodytism in different
timers and placers.
. 
N
r ;
o
: ;
o
ü
O
O
"-
: >
OJ>. 
us
u ;
o
: 1'
o
ü
'-
: J
1
The earliest work on these Buddhist
rock temples dates from the fourth
century A. D. The caves are located
on the edge of the Taklamakan
(Gobi) Desert in Gansu province, on
the Silk Route, and were the site of
intensive activity until the fourteenth
century. The most important
structures, including a 33-metre-
high Buddhist temple, date from the
Tang dynasty (seventh century).
Adorned with frescoes and
sculptures by artists of a variety of
origins, the caves are a record of ten
centuries of central Asian history.
Placed on the World Heritage List
in 1987 3
a
0. 
0-
0
o
: ;
o
ü
I
: >
gC.
<1>
: t :
'"
'"
ë.
o
<1>1
S
Ö
"
o
; ; ;'"
E
E
ê0 : : >
o2 :-
''''
s. s",,,,wOO
z-: 0
1. The cliff of Mogao. The site comprises 492
caves, 2, 415 sculptures, 45, 000 m2 of wall
paintings.
2. Interior fcave 428, Northern Zhou dynasty
(557-581 A. D.).
3. Afacadebuiitoveracave ntrance.
4. Detail of a wall painting in cave 257 showing the
king of the stags saving a human figure from
drowning (Northern Wei dynasty, 386-534 A. D.).
2
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
-------
&commat;
2
The remains of this ancient Arabian 1. A Roman
. h. h h. I f h amphitheatre with a
CIty, w IC was t e capIta 0 t e 3, 000 to 4, 000
Edomites and then, in the fifth audience capacity.
century B. C. of the kingdom of the 2. In background : an", ancient Inn for
M,,,
reached via a narrow two-3. Water rises by
k'l I d fil''T'I capillary action andI ometre-ong e e. lemp es, corrodes the base of
tombs and palaces, half free-standing, the monuments.
half hewn from the Pink sandstone 4. A communal grave.
2 2
cliffs, form a unique blend of striations in the rock
Oriental and Greco-Roman are caused by the
: ; ; : h'I d"dissolution of
 arc Itectura tra ltwns. minerals.
& Placed on the World Heritage List 5. Human habitation
.... ;. 1985 of troglodyte shelters
In began over 2, 000
3 years ago.
6. Façade of the
Khazna Firaoun
ci which was the capital of the s. ooo to a, ooo
and then, in the fifth audiencecapacity.
2. In background :an
B. , of the of the ancientinn for
Nabataeans, stand in a natural circus traveiiing mercnants.
via narrow, two-3. water rises by
capillary action and
kilometre-long defile. Temples, corrodes tne nase of
and palaces, half tne monuments.
hewn from the ink sandstone 4. A communal grave.,p The coloured
_ ° form a unique blend of striations intne rock
Greco-Roman are caused ny tne
dissolution of
, architectural traditions. minerals.
Placed on the World Heritage List 5. Human habitation
° in T985 of troglodyte shelters
o began over 2, 000
years ago.
Fa9ade 
I i i F : I  i j  I Firaoun
(Pharaoh's Treasury).
I
0
, c
'-'
rn.. J
"<-i
o
o
N
f o =
>--- :on 0-
f--"
 0c üran ø 
&commat; --, c."
4 1
,' rn
' ð}
 =
 
 
'-'
&commat; 
m o
U 2 w
The archaeological site of Petra (J ordan)
4-'
:.  ï
OJ
c-1)
. 
; :
: r
- c:
:-
o
þ. :
OJ
<= :
Õ
"-'
. 
u. -
( :)
bD
o
r-'= ;
"o
8
, ii
Ü
ro-'"
'"
o
o
N
"""
E' : i3
: I :
c5
>.rot-
&commat;
1
"
. 9
ro"C
j
'S'"
o
o
'"
"'"
2
Q ;
: r
"
>,
N
""
remains of this 
pink 
architectural traditions.
i 1985
Q ;
"'"
0:
 ;
&commat;
1. A Roman
amphitheatre with a
3, 000 to 4, 000
 capacity.
 i n 
ll h
3. Water rises by
h b
h
4. A communal grave.
The coloured
in the rock
are caused by the
5. Human habitation
of troglodyte shelters
began over 2, 000
c
<=o
.,
i
ó :
'C
--'
-
H
'ã3
S
1i
r
>
Æ
on. 
D-
,, ;
Q)cj
u
5 6
'"
"-
oi
S)""
S
0:
&commat;
'">
a :"-
=>
2
, 
0. :"-
: >
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The Nubian monuments from Abu Simbel to Philae (Egypt)
"'. 
a.
i
5
w
&commat;
c"
ã ;
"'
g
2
1. Detail of the facade of the small temple
of Abu Simbel, dedicated to the goddess
Hathor and to Nefertari, wife of Ramses II.
2. Facade of the main temple. Statues
of Ramses II.
3. Cross-section of the main temple
of Abu Simbel.
.,-r I
4. Inner sanctum ot the main
temple. From left to right :
Ptah, Amon-Re, Ramses II
and Re-Horakhte.
5. Inside the main
temple.
The rock churches of Ivanovo (Bulgaria)
1 Conquered around 1550 B. C., Nubia
(especially the area around Aswan)
became a strategic strongpoint of
Pharaonic Egypt. The open-air
museum of Nubia and Aswan
comprises the temples of Abu
Simbel, hewn from the rock by
order of Ramses II in the fourteenth
century B. C., the great temple of Isis
and a complex of several temples
built between the fifteenth century
B. C. and the second century A. D.
Placed on the World Heritage List
in 1979
Situated on the banks of the
Russenski Lorn River, the monastery
complex of Ivanovo consists of
churches, chapels and cells which
were hewn from the rock between
the restoration of the independence
of the Bulgarian church in q35 and
the annexation of Bulgaria by the
Ottoman empire in 1396. Frescoes,
which originally covered the walls of
almost all the churches and chapels,
illustrate the development of the
school of Tarnovo (capital of the
second Bulgarian kingdom) and,
more generally, of Bulgarian and
Byzantine art.
Placed on the World Heritage List
in 1979
3
'"OJ
c :OJU)
by
. c
. 
ro
gp. 
o
3
4
'". 
D-
o ;
"
w
&commat;
ro
èo
o
a ;
iõ
is
5
onrn"-
rn
: 2'
i""
&commat;
4
. 
a :'-
: J
'">
Æ
0. :
I
: J
1. Natural site and spiritual centre.
2. A natural cave modified by human hand.
3. Figures are portrayed in the Ivanovo frescoes with a sense of drama that
relates them more closely to Hellenistic than to Byzantine art.
4. After centuries of damage, the frescoes of Ivanovo now offer only a few
tantalizing glimpses of medieval Bulgarian art.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
. 
-
0. >
c ! f:J
"'"
.' ; :
.....
<U
: r
: 9
; 
<U
- =
.....
! :
o
'"
<U
. 
. 
.....
: >-.
- 0
o
on
o
r= :
Ajanta Cavies  EBora Caves-Elephanta Cavies (india)
AJANTA
1. General view of the
cliff.
2. Cave No. 1. The
vakataka period (3rd-
5th centuries A. D.).
3. Façade of cave No.
19.
ELEPHANTA
4. The temple (6th-8th
centuries A. D.).
5. Three-headed Shiva.
ELLORA
6. Entrance to cave
No. 10.
7. The sanctuary of
Visvakarman (cave No.
10). The caves receive
the light of the setting
sun.
on
ro<L
i
o
UJ
&commat;
=>
o
z
1 "'
ro
D..
... ;
iw
&commat;
"
o
Z
,. j
-- ;
"'
ro
a
i
"
c.
G :i
&commat;
"'
E
. 2 !
f-
<i
4
." !
<&lt; ;
"-
i
: ;
UJ
&commat;
I
I
." !
ro
0..
i
: ;
w
&commat;
'"
'"
E
o. cI-
<i
5 6
if>
ro
a.
w
o
UJ
&commat;
"
o
Z
, i
-- ;
2 3
'"
ro
a.
i
o
w
&commat;
'"'"
E
f-
<i
7
N Ajanta N Hewn from a cliff
overlooking a bend in the Waghora
River (Maharashtra State), the thirty
Ajanta caves include five Buddhist
sanctuaries and monastic annexes.
The first group of caves were made
in the second century B. C. on a
basilical pattern in which the main
nave is separated from the aisles. A
second group was hewn out
between the fifth and seventh
centuries A. D., during the Vakataka
and Gupta dynasties. Abundant
statues and wall paintings mark one
of the highest points of Indian art.
Placed on the World Heritage List
in 1983
N E)) ora N Unlike Ajanta, Ellora is
the product of three great religions
of ancient India. Thirty-four caves
hewn from a high basalt cliff on a
two-kilometre-long site in
Maharashtra state contain Buddhist,
Brahmanic andjalmst temples and
monasteries. The oldest date from
the seventh century and the most
recent were probably made between
800 and 1000 A. D.
Placed on the World Heritage List
in 1983
N Elephant. The Elephanta
Caves, on the little island of
Gharapuri, offshore from Bombay,
are divided into two groups. The
main site contains five Hindu rock-
hewn sanctuaries which embody
many features of traditional
architecture. The sculptures in the
main cave which surround the chapel
containing the lingam (phallic symbol
representing the fertilizing aspect of
Shiva) are among the most important
of their kind dedicated to the cult of
Shiva. They have been approximately
dated to some time between the sixth
and eighth centuries A. D.
Placed on the World Heritage List
in 1987
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Bandiagara Escarpment ('Dogon Country') (Mali)
: :
1. A Dogon village built
on rock. Alongside the
rectangular houses
are grain stores with
conical thatched
roofs.
2. A natural cave once
modified for human
habitation.
3. The entrance to a
religious leader's
dwelling, protected by
a carved snake.
4. The houses are
built of dry stone or
unbaked clay bricks.
The walls are coated
with clay.
5. Traditional houses
clinging to the cliff
face.
Covering an area of some 400, 000
hectares, this site includes almost 250
traditional villages of the Dogon
people, most of which huddle against
the cliff. The Dogon, a people
formed about 800 years ago from the
intermingling of tribes which had
been chased from Mande with the
local Tellem people who lived in
caves and rock shelters, preserved a
number of their predecessors'rock
sanctuaries. They later developed a
form of social organization which
was reflected In their architecture.
Placed on the World Heritage List
in 1989
1
2
'C""' :.","' :-
3 5
co
""
i
'Õ
ü
m
"-m
oo
"
OJ""
n :. 
: r
""'
Õ
: ; :
"0
< (
&commat;
"'o
Õ. c"-
-
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
. E
-'
v
OF : !
<&lt; :
.- ; :
....
""'
: c
: 9
""'
... < :1
"'-'"
t :!
o
'"
"-'
...... 
u
'' ; :
; .-.
- 0
o
M
o
F ;
The rock cones of Cappadocia (Turkey)
1
I
Iii"
"
'"
'"
Q ;
: ë
f-
&commat;
1. Landscape of
Cappadocia, in the
heart of Anatolia. The
site was created from
a massive fiow of lava
from Mount Argaeus.
2. Volcanic cones
topped with
dovecotes.
3. A troglodyte
dwelling still in use.
OJ>
ro
0-
x
o
It)
&commat;
"
E
"S.OJ>o
'"
ro
; 2
2
'". 
D-
o
w
&commat;
"C
'g
CO
'"c
'"
: z 
3
Na. 
"-
: ; ;
"
9 :w
&commat;
N" ; :
o
z
'"
'". 
D-
i
: ;
w
&commat;
"
"
: : ;. 0'"
Qj
o
"'
ro
"-
ui"
'"'"
E
-'"
"'
< (
&commat;
x=>
g
'"
CJ
o
4 5 6
As early as the fourth century A. D.
Christian anchorite communities
took shelter in the unusual conical
peaks sculpted by erosion in the
heart of Turkey's Anatolia region.
They began creating troglodytic
villages to protect themselves fro m
Arab invasions, and by the middle of
the ninth century stone churches
were being gouged from the soft
rock and richly decorated with
fi gurative painting.
Placed on the World Heritage List
in 1985
-
4. The king's palace in
the underground city
of Ozkonak.
5. A rock-hewn
Byzantine church,
Göreme Valley.
6. Zelve Valley.
7. Rocky pyramids in
GoremeVaiiey.
"'
'""'-
s.
of
15"-
&commat;
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
mesa Verse (United States of America)
"'
if ;
a.
i
< : ;
UJ
&commat;
Cm
: ë
o
'"
"'. g
ro
. t
1
The traditional habitat of the Anasazi
Indians appeared in the sixth century
A. D. in the form of partially buried
villages on the high table-land of
Mesa Verde (Colorado). From the
eighth century on it developed in the
form of villages that were partly
troglodytic and partly built above
ground. Buried structures known as
kivas were made and were used for
various cultural activities. The
civilization of the Anasazis, to which
the Pueblo Indians belong, reached
its zenith between the twelfth and
thirteenth centuries. At the end of
this period the surface villages were
abandoned and the Indians settled in
more rudimentary defensive
buildings huddled against the sides of
the canyons.
Placed on the World Heritage List
in 1978
if>. 
D-
if>
'"
()
&commat;
3
1. At the end of the 12th century
the Anasazijnd ! ans bandoned
the table-top mesas to establish
new dwellings in the sides of
canyons.
2, The"Spruce-Tree House".
3. The Cliff Palace, built with
stones taken from the cliff.
Wieliczka salt mines (Poland)
1. The"cave of
crystals".
2. Kinga Chapel, hewn
and sculpted from the
rock salt.
3. This 162-step
stairway, whose
existence was
recorded for the first
time in 1669, climbs
from the first to the
secondlevelofthe
m ! neviaa27-metre
high cavern.
2
2
0
: ; ; ;
vi
o
: ;
o
ü
'-
0
: >
1
Underground mining of rock salt
deposits began in the thirteenth
century, and in the course of time
galleries were opened up on nine
levels, to a maximum depth of 327
metres. Their total length, including
wells, corridors, labyrinths,
excavations and rooms is nearly
300 km. The old galleries strikingly
illustrate the evolution of mining
processes over the centuries.
Underground chapels are adorned
with altars, pulpits and statues carved
outofsatt.
Placed on the World Heritage List
in 1978
0
o
: 2'
o
ü
0
&commat;
I, : :J
0
o
: ;
o
0
1
: >
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY BY FEDER ! CO MAYOR
SCIENCE
THAT MUST
BE SHARED
Science is a product of intellectual work by persons
trained in reflection and analysis to venture beyond
what is already known. This exercise in thinking
requires a minimum number of conditions, the
most important of which under present circum-
stances is freedom. For although scientific progress
was possible in the past when political and social
contexts were under threat, the growing com-
plexity of research and scientific development
today require a high level of freedom in order to
keep moving forward. As a result, the future of sci-
ence is closely bound up with the advance of
democracy and respect for values conducive to the
free circulation and discussion of ideas.
Contrary to the fears of Alexis de Tocqueville
and other nineteenth-century thinkers, democ-
racy has not built a kingdom of mediocrity inim-
ical to the development of higher forms of art and
science. Rather, the opposite has occurred. The
vitality and creative force of democratic society-
in which the state is secular, powers are separated
and all ideas are subject to debate-have turned
out to be much greater than its early critics imag-
ined. These qualities have not only enabled it to
surmount the danger posed by various forms of
totalitarianism but also to promote unprecedented
cultural and economic development.
An unexpected turn of events
However, on the threshold of the twenty-first
century, the nature of the challenges and threats
with which democracy has to cope is changing.
Since 1989, the end of the Cold War has given new
emphasis, and in some cases greater virulence, to
old disputes of ethnic or religious origin that had
survived under wraps in the shadow of the East-
West confrontation. It is quite clear that they are
not the consequences of freedom but the result
of many years of oppression. The triumph of
democratic principles in Eastern Europe, the
break-up of the Soviet empire and the nuclear
weapons reduction agreements have opened up
broad vistas of peace while at the same time
releasing resentments and twisted perceptions
long harboured in the secret places of the heart.
The countries of the free world had prepared
for war, but not for peace. They were surprised
when the course of events diverged from what
the prophets of doom had predicted. The iron
curtain was soon a thing of the past ; peace was
achieved in Namibia, El Salvador, Mozambique,
the Middle East and South Africa. Conflicts were
no longer international but intranational. The
threats to security are now poverty, the unbal-
anced distribution of resources, runaway popula-
tion growth, massive emigration and social injus-
tices that create reactions of rejection.
This turnaround caught out some countries.
which had little inclination to take radical deci-
sions, looked no further than the next elections
and regarded any reference to future generations
as an irritation. Their budgetary and productive
priorities, social organization and defence struc-
ture are geared to the threats of the past but are
unsuitable for tackling the problems of the future.
The examples of Bosnia, Somalia and Rwanda
underscore the inability of the international com-
munity to solve new,"low-intensity"post-Cold
War conflicts.
An intolerable situation
The individual and collective violence that consti-
tute the seedbed of war can take many different
forms. In politics it manifests itself as oppression
and tyranny ; in economics, as exploitation and des-
titution ; and in society, as exclusion and intolerance.
Every effort to establish a culture of peace must
take into account these deep roots of human con-
flict and give priority to the transmission of values,
the forging of attitudes and the drafting of legal pro-
visions to replace those of the declining culture of
war. The pillars of this undertaking are education
and development, which make it possible to elimi-
nate the most dehumanizing aspects of extreme
poverty, and to contribute to the elimination of dis-
crimination and the establishment of governments
that respect the will of the people and the agree-
ments they have entered into. Twenty years ago, in
1974, the industrialized countries undertook to
promote the development of the less privileged
countries by allocating to them 0. 7 per cent of their
GDP (keeping 99. 3 per cent for themselves !). With
a few praiseworthy exceptions-the Nordic coun-
tries in particular-they have not honoured their
undertaking.
Worse still, the meagre"development assis-
'"
N. Q
o"-
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
tance"on offer sometimes included military equip-
ment. As a result, there has been no endogenous
development in most of the countries in question.
Foreign debt and the maroeconomic structures put
in place have led to an intolerable situation that has
nevertheless been tolerated for years : the poor
countries are paying the rich ! Millions of people
drawn by"city lights"are fleeing the poverty of
rural areas to go and live in the squalid, crowded
solitude of the major urban centres. One day, help-
less and desperate, they will head north. How easy
and wrong it is to deplore radicalism and extremism
where poverty, marginalization, exclusion and
ignorance have been allowed to proliferate.
The idea that development is synonymous
with economic growth has long been superseded.
Nowadays, the ethical and social problems arising
from scientific and technological progress brook
neither delay nor evasion. When UNESCO speaks
of the need for development with a human face-
integrated, endogenous, sustainable, supportive
and environment-friendly-it is merely com-
plying with one of its basic precepts : the duty to
act as the conscience of the United Nations
system in a world that hesitates, in the presence of
powerful interests and forces of inertia, to take the
new directions that, at the dawn of a new millen-
nium, are morally inescapable.
The responsibilities of the scientist
Scientific knowledge in the basic disciplines
(mathematics, physics, chemistry and biology) is
now centred on half a dozen lines of inquiry that
will certainly change the character of society in the
twenty-first century. Broadly speaking, this work
is organized around ecological problems and the
search for alternative sources of energy ; optic
fibres and superconductors ; lasers and work
relating to space technology ; and research in
biology, especially genetics and biotechnology.
Those who are taking scientific knowledge for-
ward in these areas, like many of their colleagues
working in other sectors, bear the awesome respon-
sibility of informing public opinion and those who
shape it about the potential risks of the application
of knowledge, and of explaining the constantly
changing instruments that science devises to cope
with those difficulties. But if the scientists'words
are to fall on receptive ears and their conclusions on
fertile soil, steps must be taken to strengthen
exchanges of communication and influence
between the centres of knowledge and power, and
between researchers and leaders in all political and
social spheres, especially at municipal level.
While municipal and regional authorities have
in the past needed architects, hydraulic engineers
and communication experts, from now on they
will also need the services of environmental spe-
cialists to help them preserve soil quality (through
the appropriate"scientific"use of artificial fertil-
izers), to encourage the recycling of natural prod-
ucts and improve public health by suitable waste
processing, to avoid air and water pollution, to
protect biological diversity and to safeguard the
historical heritage. This aspect of the scientist's
task is particularly urgent in the most highly devel-
oped countries which, in almost direct proportion
to their productive capacity, are the greatest pro-
ducers of toxic wastes.
One of the tragedies of the contemporary
world is the dearth of activity in applied science
compared with the enormous volume of accu-
mulated theoretical knowledge. Laboratories and
universities in the industrialized world are
bursting with knowledge that could alleviate the
misery of millions of human beings, but the means
of applying that knowledge are not available,
although the more discerning countries are begin-
ning to realize that, in the final analysis, their own
security is at stake. For example, there is no AZT
for many Aids sufferers in Africa. Imagine the
sense of injustice and marginalization that these
patients for whom there is no medicine must feel.
If I have dwelt on the social impact of scien-
tific work, it is because I am convinced that this is
one of the decisive parameters of the century that
is about to begin, because I believe that there are
solutions that can be applied. When my official
responsibilities take me to a school in the heart of
the African forest, a research centre in Siberia or
an archaeological site in South America, I always
meet enthusiastic young people who are giving of
their best-sometimes under conditions of
extreme hardship-in order to secure peace and
collective welfare. These young people look to the
"intellectual and moral solidarity"enshrined in
UNESCO's Constitution as the key to human dig-
nity. For this reason, I repeat on each of my jour-
neys that"there is only one really pressing need,
and that is to share". It is the saying that one of the
great religious figures of our time, Abbe Pierre,
keeps on his modest desk and it is a motto that
should govern our daily life.
Of the principles proclaimed by the French
Revolution in 1789-Liberty, Equality, Fraternity-
the first inspired the great political and social trans-
formations of the nineteenth century while the
second, the egalitarian ideal, dominated the twen-
tieth century after the Russian Revolution. But the
culture of war in which they developed prevented
them from producing all the benefits that had been
anticipated. Let us strive, with scientists in the van-
guard, to make the third of those principles, Fra-
ternity, the historic driving force of the twenty-first
century, the mobilizing ideal of the culture of peace,
whose first page is waiting impatiently for us to
trace the outline, in unison throughout the world,
of the most novel yet ancient solution of all times,
the only one on which we will be judged at the end
of the day : love. N
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Protecting
plant lift
by France Bequette
hue first European Conference on) t the Conservatio of Wild Plants
was held in September at Hyeres
(France), at a time when 25, 000
wild plants are threatened with
extinction. The Conference, entitled
"Planta Europa", was co-sponsored
by Plantlife, a charity dedicated to
saving wild plants, and by the
French Ministry of the Environment.
It was attended by 200 experts from
thirty European countries
In his inaugural address, the
well-known British botanist and
environmentalist David Bellamy,
president of Plantlife, noted that
plants have for too long been too
low on the list of conservation con-
cerns."Pandas may reign supreme
as the logo for the World Wide
Fund for Nature (WWF),"he said,
"but as every schoolchild will tell
you they are totally dependent on
bamboo both for their habitat and
their staple diet."
A botanist
pollinating a
Hibiscus
boryanus.
Young Hottentot
fig plants
(Carpobrotus
edulis).
THE THREATS
David Bellamy went on to list the
"seven deadly sins that threaten the
flora of Europe"as"changes in land
use practice including : 1) extensive
and intensive farming based on ever
larger fields and the reseeding of
meadows and pastures with
nitrogen-hungry monocultures ; 2)
the replacement of the rural work
force, crop rotation, fallow and
mixed farming by machines and an
armamentarium of chemicals ; 3) the
eutrophication of water due to the
excessive use of fertilizers and inten-
sification of animal husbandry
including the foddering of sheep and
cattle on heath-, moor-and bogland ;
4) drainage on a massive scale
including the loss of water meadows
and farm ponds ; 5) road-building
dissecting viable populations of
plants and the animals and insects
which depend on them and upon
which they depend ; 6) acidification
due to the increasing use of fossil
fuels and the replacement of native
woodlands and coppice with exotic
conifers ; 7) overgrazing by sheep,
cattle and other herbivores."
The some 12, 000 species of
flowers and ferns in Europe are also
under threat from environmental
degradation due to the intensifica-
tion of farming, industrial and
urban expansion, the growth of
tourism and uncontrolled extrac-
tion of natural resources. Twenty-
five higher plant and fern species no
longer exist in their wild state, and
many more have been reduced to a
very small number of specimens.
The situation is particularly wor-
rying since the distribution of bio-
logical diversity worldwide is irreg-
ular. Europe is responsible for sev-
eral plant-life territories of
worldwide interest in such areas as
the Alps, the Pyrenees, the
Seed preserved in
cold storage at the
Botanical
Conservatory in
Brest (France).
Spanish mountain chains, the
Balkan mountains, the Mediter-
ranean basin and its islands, the
Canaries and the Azores.
The first thing that must be
done is to catalogue all the world's
plant species, and this will be a
long, costly and complicated job. In
Europe, for example, botany as a
discipline has lost much of the
prestige it once had, except in
Spain where there are a number of
top-level botanists. It is gradually
being overshadowed by disciplines
such as molecular biology. Some
wags have even begun to wonder
whether present-day researchers,
with their eyes glued to electronic
microscopes, could tell a field of
barley from a field of wheat !
THE RESPONSES
And yet international legal tools to
protect plant life do exist. The
Washington Convention on Interna-
tional Trade in Endangered Species
of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES)
came into force in 1982 in more
than 130 countries. And Europe's
wildlife and environment have been
protected by the Bern Convention
since 1979. Despite these regula-
tions, however, indigenous plant
populations are still being plun-
dered to meet the demands of the
horticulture business. In the 1980s
Southern Europe and Turkey
exported between 50 and 70 mil-
. 
"'-
II
j I
"'j =
"-
ro
 ; 
&commat;
"'
-' ! è
, õ
o
z
i"
" (11,
m 
rot: ;,
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
lion bulbs per year, mainly to the
Netherlands but also to the United
Kingdom and Germany.
The best way to protect plants
in their natural habitats is to estab-
lish protected areas. According to
two French experts in natural
resources, Matthieu Glachant and
Francis Leveque, there are a total
of 4. 85 million am2 of such areas,
covering 3. 7 per cent of the earth's
land surface, including biosphere
reserves, parks and natural reserves
of all sizes. But it is difficult to
provide proper protection in
densely populated regions. It would
be a pity if we could no longer see
wild plants growing in nature and
had to look them up in dried plant
collections, even collections as rich
as those in Geneva (5 million speci-
mens) and Vienna (3. 8 million).
Botanical gardens and seed or
pollen banks provide for the con-
servation of plants outside their
natural habitat. A Council of
Europe study published in 1994
notes that the world's 2, 500 botan-
ical gardens play an important role
in scientific research and in the con-
servation of endangered species,
and that it is in them that the
greatest variety of plant species-
roughly 80, 000-are found outside
natural ecosystems. Using speci-
mens grown in botanical gardens
many countries, including Aus-
tralia, Russia and the United
States, have created national data
banks for rare or endangered
indigenous plants."Red Books"
compiled by some countries on
their endangered plant life are also
valuable conservation tools.
Extremely rigorous techniques
must be used for collecting, freeze-
drying or vacuum storage of speci-
mens in seed and plant tissue
banks. But in France, for example,
such facilities have been instru-
mental in restoring to life a certain
variety of club moss of which only
one sterile fragment had survived.
This raises the problem of how
far a plant population or its habitat
should be modified to ensure the
survival of the species. Take, for
example, the narcissi that grow on
the Glenan group of islands off
France's Brittany coast. They were
dying out, partly through being
trampled on by tourists and partly
because their bulbs were being
removed. Their habitat was fenced
off to protect them, but trees and
bushes grew and smothered the
flowers. A solution was found by
introducing sheep, which do not
eat narcissi. The introduction of
foreign plants can also pose prob-
lems. A pretty flowering plant
called the Hottentot fig (Carpo-
brotus edulis), originally from
South Africa, is spreading along
the coasts of the Mediterranean
and California and smothering
endemic plants. After rashly intro-
ducing St. John's Wort into their
country, Australians had to import
an insect that preys on this invasive
plant. Australians are also faced
with the proliferation of gum suc-
cory (Chondrilla juncea), which
originated in the Middle East and
has such a tough stalk that it is dif-
ficult to scythe.
All the same it was reassuring to
find out from the"Planta Europa"
conference what naturalists are
doing on a worldwide scale to pro-
tect wild plants, for plants are not
only a source of pleasure but also
potential food and medicine for
tomorrow. N
The Royal Botanic
Garden,
Edinburgh (United
Kingdom).
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
matters.
A narcissus from
the Glean islands
(narcissus
triandrus).
THE RHINOCEROS IS ALIVE AND (FAIRLY)
WELL IN ZIMBABWE
The Pan-African News Agency (PANA) reports
that in the last 18 months, the Zimbabwe
Society for the Protection of the Rhinoceros
has not registered a single case of poaching in
the four protected sites it has established.
When Zimbabwe became independent in 1980
the rhinoceros population numbered several
thousands. Now there are only 300 left.
Poachers sell rhino horns, which are used to
make so-called aphrodisiac powder and as
scabbards for swords, for as much as
$US90, 000 each. The Harare government has
invested 500, 000 Zimbabwe dollars (about
$US62, 500) to protect the survivors.
GLOBAL WARMING :
A CLOUDY OUTLOOK
Researchers at the United States'National
Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) in
Boulder, Colorado, report that clouds absorb
about four times as much solar energy as had
been previously thought, and by using the
new values have arrived at preliminary results
that predict a warmer, drier climate than that
shown previously. An NCAR study of the tiny
particles that form the nuclei of cloud
TO FIND OUT MORE :
lantlife : The Natural History Museum,
I ! Road, London SW7 58D. Tel :(19 44)
9111 ; Fax : (1944) 171938 9112.
rid Plant Conservation Bibliography,
tannic Gardens, Kew and the World Con-
Union (IUCN).
ening Perspectives on Biodiversity,
et aI., IUCN, 1994.
n actice of Plant Conser.
i. IUCN, 1994
njeu des ressources génétiques vegs.
spects scientifiques, écologiques et
'rues Matthieu Glachant and François
u with the collaboration of A. Bonjean, Les
e I'environnement, Paris, 1993.
iodiversité, enjeu planétalre. Conserver
trimoine génétique, Michel Chauvet and
Lie Sang de la terre, Paris, 1993.
"'. 
"-
i
&commat;
. 
"
o
(f)
q :
- ;
.  I
m
&commat;
: D
Ë
o
ü
c. 
u'
two'
'". 
D-
g
. 0;:
&commat;
""
<5
: ; :
OJ--'
'"
'"
'"
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
droplets and raindrops suggests that the
burning of tropical forests may be the largest
source of these particles, other cloud con-
densation nuclei being dust and sea salt. The
increase in nuclei could result in a decrease in
rainfall.
WENO'S R) S) NG DDE OF WASTE
Abo. ut 17, 000 people live on Wendo Island,
capital of Chuuk State (Federated States of
Micronesia). Weno, whose area is just under
20 km2, has a serious solid-waste problem.
Because of a quarrel between land-owners and
the government about land use, the existing
disposal site has been closed. When a repre-
sentative of the World Health Organization
(WHO) visited Weno last year, he found that
there was no public service for the collection
of solid waste, so that people had to trans-
port their waste to the public dump them-
selves. However, since neither the dump nor
its access road are well-maintained, illegal
dumping has increased. Even with the road in
good repair, a new site will have to be opened
up sooner or later. But where ? Weno's waste
disposal problem is one being faced by many
communities all over the world.
DONKEYS FIGHT BATTLE
AGAINSTDUNES
The June 1995 issue of the French magazine
Secheresse contains an article co-authored by
Professor Pierre Rognon of Paris and Jean Meu-
nier, an agronomist living in Mauritania,
describing how the latter has developed a
simple, effective and inexpensive way of halting
desert advance. Saplings are planted in wire-
mesh cylinders wrapped in plastic bags, and are
watered at root-level via a system of buried
plastic bottles linked to a bottle acting as a
funnel from the surface. After 6 months, the
saplings are 2. 5 metres tall, enough to stabilize
the sand. The cheapest way to bring in the
water is on donkey-back, and Meunier has
developed a rubber sandal to increase the
bearing surface of donkeys'hooves and pre-
vent them from sinking into the soft sand.
ONE WOMAN, MANY TREES
The 1994 annual report of Switzerland's Depart-
ment of Development and Humanitarian Aid
(DDA) tells the heartening story of Mariam
Begum, of Bangladesh. Mariam, who never
attended school and learned to read and write
through an adult literacy programme, started a
nursery on 280 m2 of land lent to her by the
state. Three years later she was working on an
area ten times bigger. In 1994 she sold 10, 000
trees and earned ten times the average
Bangladeshi income. She hired a full-time
employee, and her husband joined her busi-
ness. Now Mariam has become a forestry con-
sultant and plants trees for wealthy landowners.
Because of entrepreneurs like her, more than
two million trees have been planted in
Bangladesh since the DDA-supported forestry
programme was started nine years ago.
THE WATER HYACINTH
STRIKES AGAIN
Burkina Faso is the latest African country (see
UNESCO Courier, May 1995, p. 47) to be threat-
ened by the water hyacinth, a small, floating
water plant with round leaves and beautiful
pale-blue flowers. According to the Burkina
Faso Botanical and Technoiogicai Research
Institute, the hyacinth encourages evapora-
tion. If it spreads to the dams of Kompienga
and Bagre, the water supply of the country's
capital, Ouagadougou, will be jeopardized. A
media campaign has been launched in the
national languages, calling on people to
destroy the water hyacinth before the advent
of the rainy season. If the campaign fails, it
will cost several million dollars to get rid of the
troublesome plant.
! N ! T ! AT) VESINITIATIVES
The European
Environment Agency
The European Environment Agency was created in
1990 and became operational in 1993 when its head-
quarters were established in Copenhagen (Denmark).
It is funded by the European Commission and by con-
tributions from non-member states of the European
Union such as Norway and Iceland. Although an off-
shoot of the European Commission, it operates inde-
pendently, collecting information and distributing it
upon request to the general public and to a network of
"Topic Centres"-public or private member-state insti-
tutions concerned with the environment. Its first pro-
ject was to develop and co-ordinate the European Envi-.
ronment Information and Observation Network
(EIONET), to which more than 450 institutions belong.
The Agency's Multiannual work programme (1995-
1999) comprises 93 projects. They give priority to areas
such as air quality and atmospheric emissions ; water
quality ; water pollutants and water resources ; the state
of the soil, of fauna and flora and biotopes ; land use
and natural resources use ; waste management ; noise
emissions ; chemical substances hazardous to the envi-
ronment ; and coastal protection.
Five Topic Centres are already acting as lead orga-
nizations for work in these priority areas. The Air Emis-
sions project, for example, is being headed by the
Umweltbundesamt in Berlin, and the Nature Conser-
vation project by the Museum Nationale d'Histoire
Naturelle of Paris.
The Agency publishes a series of documents (mainly
free of charge), including a monthly newsletter. One of
these documents, Europes EnMronment, the Dobris
Assessment, published in 1994, is particularly remark-
able. Illustrated with photos and diagrams, it presents
in less than twenty pages a summary including some
memorable figures. For example, two-thirds of Euro-
peans live in urban areas covering 1 per cent of the total
land area. A city of a million inhabitants consumes a
daily average of 11, 500 tonnes of fossil fuels, 320, 000
tonnes of water and 2, 000 tonnes of food and produces
25, 000 tonnes of C02 1, 600 tonnes of solid waste and
300, 00 tonnes of wastewater. Tourism is one of
Europe's most important social and economic activities :
the coastal Mediterranean received 157 million tourists
in 1990, and 100 million tourists visit the Alps each
year.
EEA
Kongens Nytorv 6, 1050 Copenhague K, Denmark.
Tel. : (+45) 33 36 71 00. Fax : (+45) 33 36 71 99.
N
 I
e
0 3
" : 1
 
 !
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
The balcony of Europe
by Jean-Pierre Kraemer
A pocket-sized international airport ;a fas expanding money market ; a
European centre which houses the
headquarters of the Secretariat of the
European Parliament and other Euro-
pean institutions such as the Court of
Auditors, the Court of Justice and the
European Investment Bank ; a strategic
crossroads where the history of Europe,
from the Early Middle Ages on, has lit-
erally been carved in stone ; the leg-
endary spot where Melusina1, wife of
the city's founder Count Sigefroid, is
said to hide-Luxembourg, capital of
the Grand Duchy of Luxembourg, is all
of these. Its inhabitants, who number
fewer than 100, 000, speak not only
their native tongue Letzebuergesch (a
Mosellan Franconian dialect), but
French and German, and in many cases
English and even Italian, Spanish and
Portuguese. A good half of the capital's
population is made up of foreigners.
CITY AND CROSSROADS
Located at the intersection of two Roman
roads, one from Paris, the other from
Capital of the Grand Duchy,
Luxembourg City was coveted by the
powers of western Europe for
centuries. Since 1994 its old districts
and fortifications have been
registered on UNESCO's World
Heritage List.
Top, Luxembourg
as it was in the 17th century. A copperplat
engraving by Frederik de Wit (1698).
Above, the Corniche and
St. Michael's Church.
Lyons, on a rocky promontory between the
two deep valleys of the Alzette and the
Petrusse, the site of the future city strad-
dled the linguistic borderline between
France and the Holy Roman Empire, in
the heart of ancient Lotharingia. It was
ideally suited to fortification.
THE GIBRALTAR
OF THE NORTH'
In about 1000 A. D., on the site of a
modest Roman fort called Lucilin-
burhuc, or Liitzelburg ("little castle"),
Sigefroid built a feudal castle which
was to become the seat of the illustrious
house of Luxembourg and the"Acrop-
olis"of the future fortified town.
At the beginning of the fourteenth
century the town had 5, 000 inhabitants
and enjoyed an economic boom thanks
to its ideal location on the trade route
between the two leading trading regions
of the time, Lombardy and Flanders. Its
third surrounding wall, known as
Wenceslaus's Wall, which protected
both the upper and lower towns, dates
from the end of the fourteenth century.
Wf
o. c
E
... J
o
>.
g
o
D<=
ro
( ; ;
, 5
o
Q)"'
e :-
El&
J :
&commat;
'". 
D-
i"-
'"
0 :
&commat;
'0 ;
N
U')
""
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
"'. 
0-
'"
0-OJo
I
&commat;
-'"
$
<5'
; ; :
"'
CD
Its strategic location made Luxem-
bourg a very attractive prize for the
great continental powers and dragged it
into the upheavals of European politics.
After becoming part of the possessions
of Philip the Good, Duke of Burgundy,
in the fifteenth century, the Duchy
passed into the hands of the Spanish
Habsburgs, who considerably rein-
forced the fortress when it came under
threat from the French. After being
besieged by Vauban, it eventually fell
to Louis XIV in 1684. A skilled strate-
gist and military engineer, Vauban then
extended the fortifications up to the
top of the promontory, from which he
had succeeded in breaching the town's
defences.
Luxembourg remained in the hands
of the Austrian Habsburgs for most of
the eighteenth century, then fell to the
army of the French Republic in 1795,
before becoming part of the German
Confederation in 1815. The Congress of
Vienna, which redrew the political map
of Europe, made Luxembourg a Grand
Duchy. The city, occupied by Prussian
troops who further reinforced its forti-
fications, became a"federal fortress"
designed to act as a barrier against the
French. But at the London Conference
of 1867 a treaty signed by the great
powers of the time in the hope of pre-
venting a Franco-Prussian war stipu-
lated that the Grand Duchy should
remain in a state of"perpetual neu-
trality", that the Prussian garrison
should withdraw from the fortress, and
that its imposing fortifications should
'"
roQ :
iQ.
ro
a :
&commat;
roQ.
en
c
ro
C)
ü
The Pont Adolphe. In background, the state
Savings Bank.
be dismantled. The dismantling process,
which took sixteen years, resulted in
the disappearance of one of the most
powerful strongholds in Europe, once
called"the Gibraltar of the North".
Initially regarded as a disaster by
the city's burghers, the treaty had a
beneficial effect on Luxembourg. The
removal of the fortifications opened up
a large area of building land and offere d
undreamt-of growth possibilities. Par-
liamentary buildings were erected, new
districts such as the Plateau Bourbon
became urbanized, and cultural institu-
tions were sited there. The price to be
paid for this boom was the loss of a
unique heritage of military architec-
ture, the surviving remnants of which
form part of the historic site placed on
the World Heritage List in December
1994.
INSPIRATION FOR ARTISTS
AND WRITERS
The different powers that ruled Lux-
embourg from the sixteenth to the nine-
teenth centuries left their stamp on the
city's military and civilian architecture
through a process of historical super-
imposition. But the site is chiefly inter-
esting because of the boldness with
which the city blends into a landscape
whose beauty has impressed many great
artists and writers.
There exist 338 street plans, maps
and drawings of Luxembourg which
make it possible to chart its develop-
ment both spatially and temporally.
Many artists have painted views of the
fortified town. Goethe made a series of
pencil sketches and drawings height-
ened with wash and sepia. But there
The European Court of Justice building
on the Kirchberg plateau.
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
can be little doubt that it was J. M. W.
Turner who, in his twenty-odd water-
colours of the site, best captured its
atmosphere.
RELICS OF A PRESTIGIOUS PAST
It is true that Luxembourg lost much of
its architectural heritage as a result of
the military attacks to which it was con-
stantly subjected. Gone are its feudal
castle, which was destroyed by a gun-
powder explosion in 1554, the sump-
tuous Renaissance buildings put up by
Governor Pierre-Ernest de Mansfeld,
which fell in ruins in the seventeenth cen-
tury, and the fortress walls, which were
for so long a threat to peace in Europe.
But important relics of Luxem-
bourg's prestigious past have survived,
such as the Eglise St.-Michel, which is
over 1, 000 years old, and Notre-Dame
cathedral, a national shrine and place of
annual pilgrimage, whose three spires
can be seen from far outside the city.
There are also some superb seigneurial
residences, such as the Hotel de Bour-
gogne, seat of the presidency of the gov-
ernment, the Maison de Cassal, the
Hotel de Raville, and the Maison Mohr
de Waldt. Also of great interest to visi-
tors is the Grand Ducal Palace, whose
fine facade shows the influence of the
Spanish Renaissance.
Above all, an elusive spirit of place
'"
roD-
Ô. c
'"
&commat;
ro
'"'"
ro
(f)
c
ro
Ü
0
c
t'
Q
6
Above, the organ loft (1620-1622) by Daniel
Muller in Notre-Dame Cathedral.
Grund, Luxembourg's lower town,
on the banks of the Alzette (left).
has survived intact in Luxembourg. The
visitor can sense it in the steep and
narrow medieval streets ; on the cliff-top
esplanade, known as"the balcony of
Europe" ; in the casemates dug by Hab-
sburg troops, in which the whole popu-
lation of the Grand Duchy could hide ;
in the back streets of the lower town ; at
a bend in the Alzette River, where one
might almost be in some Venetian calle ;
on the surrounding hills, which offer
the finest views over the Bock-the
"Acropolis", where Melusina is thought
to be sewing a linen blouse, the comple-
tion of which will herald the collapse of
the castle.
Apart from its legends, perhaps Lux-
embourg can be regarded as a European
paradigm. After being subjected for so
long to the ravages of war, the city now
embodies what was, perhaps, Lucilin-
burhuc's true mission : the desire for
peace in Europe, t
1 Melusina : a fairy of popular legend. Her
union with a mortal guaranteed the fertility
of the people's land and the prosperity of
their homes.-Ed.
JEAN-PIERRE KRAEMER,
of the Grand Duchy of Luxembourg, is president of his
country's National Commission for UNESCO.
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
As it was...
THE UNESCO (þURIER
February 1959
A ban on war
by Lord Boyd Orr
Nobel Peace Prizewinner (1949)
People foolishly believe that if they ban the hydrogen bomb they have finished. Make no
mistake : if a war starts, every hydrogen bomb and every weapon of war will be thrown in.
The only way to save humanity is to ban war itself, t
Which road
will humanity take ?
by Nikolai Semenov
Nobel Prizewinner for Chemistry (1956)
War is a relic from the past, a terrible and barbarous survival which should have no place
in a civilized world. The menace of war has a disastrous psychological effect in people and
entails the squandering of a vast amount of labour and resources ; an enormous number of
men do nothing but learn how to kill one another. The overall effect is to prevent nations
from concentrating their efforts and using their resources to improve living standards, to
enrich their cultural life and to assist economically under-developed countries ; it prevents
them from feeding and clothing their people properly and hinders normal technological
development.
The most important task today is to end this nightmare. A unanimous and active world
opinion could have a decisive effect in settling these questions, leaving aside other relatively
secondary problems not directly related to them.
In this collective effort to safeguard international peace, to ban the testing of nuclear
weapons and these weapons themselves and to abolish war, the scientists, in all countries,
who are sincerely concerned for man's future and for the progress and integrity of science,
must unite and take a leading part.
I am convinced that the vast majority of true scientists do not work simply for the
money they earn. Thus they cannot stand idly by while science is destroyed and the
prospects which are opening up for it are brought to nothing. It is a great blow for us to
see the results of our scientific work used to the detriment of mankind, and in the present
case we cannot tolerate it. We scientists must not stifle our humanitarian feelings but on
the contrary, give them full freedom, as should every honest person. We should be keenly
aware of our responsibilities, and then act accordingly, uniting our efforts to solve these
problems.
All of us living in the twentieth century, whether scientists or not, have a great obliga-
tion, not only to ourselves but to future generations. If we succeed in dispelling the heavy
threat of war and concentrating our efforts on opening up a new and enlightened era,
mankind can look forward to a truly happy existence even during our own century, t !
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO {9URIER Index 1995
JANUARY. THE SUN. Interview with Montserrat Caballe. Our middle-aged neighbouring star (P. Lantos). Myths with the sun in them (P. Borgeaud). A light
that shines through time and cultures (M. Singh). Zoroastrianism and the cult of fire (M. Tadjadod). Manolo plugs into the sun (C. Flavin & N. Lenssen). India's
self-help solar villages (Sanjit Bunker Roy). The World Solar Summit (interview with B. Berkovsky). The new Alexandria library. Fact file. Building a culture of
peace (F. Mayor). Heritage : The Pantheon (C. Duvelle & M. Rosi). Greenwatch : The food/population equation (L. Brown). Listening : Mambo mania (1. Leymarie).
Global view : The UNESCO Prize for the Promotion of the Arts. Archives : Men of little faith (J. Bojer). Anniversary : Louis Pasteur (L. L. Lambrichs).
FEBRUARY. THE MULTIMEDIA EXPLOSION. Interview with Regis Debray.'New ways of being together' (D. Bougnoux). Unequal voices (A. Mattelart).
The media : a modern scapegoat ? (E. Valverde). Interactivity-a matter of give and take (M. Seneca). The Internet :journey into cyberspace (D. Pelissier). From
global village to global mind (D. de Kerckhove). The shoals of freedom (M. Frybes). Monopolies, minarets and videos (S. Hammami). UNESCO's strategy (inter-
view with H. Yushkiavitshus). From the Cold War to the era of new technologies (A. Modoux). Fact file. Reinventing the press (F. Mayor). Heritage : The great
temple of Thanjavur (A. Murugaiyan). Greenwatch : Clean driving : a green dream ? (F. Bequette). Anniversary : Fuzuli, poet of divine love. Archives : Intuition, intel-
ligence and the making of modern man (S. de Madariaga). Listening : The heartbeat of jazz (I. Leymarie). 1995 : United Nations Year for Tolerance (Lieh-tzu).
MARCH. DEVELOPMENT : THE HAVES AND THE HAVE-NOTS. Democracy, the common heritage of humanity (Aung San Suu Kyi). Dismantling the
mechanism of exclusion (1. Sachs). The culture of silence (A. Traore). Empowerment, an escape route from poverty (J. Friedmann & L. Sandercock). The rag-pick-
ers of Pune. South Africa : leaving apartheid behind (R. Meunier). Change from within (P. Anyang Nyong'o). PRONASOL : Mexico's war on poverty (J. Marques-
Pereira). An ethical commitment (D. Jain). Brazil : a country in arms against hunger (H. de Souza). Hoping against hope (E. Morin). Fact file. Sharing our knowl-
edge (F. Mayor). Heritage : The stones of Byblos (S. A. Jalu). Greenwatch : Montseny, harmony in the hills (F. Bequette). Anniversary : Jose Marti (C. Vitier). Global
view : Population growth and development (interview with J.-c. Chasteland). Archives : Sensationalism and the popular press (B. S. Cano). 1995 : United Nations
Year for Tolerance : Violence, an affront to humanity (F. Mayor). Listening : Opera from Taiwan (I. Leymarie).
APRIL. THE ORIGINS OF WRITING. Interview with Ernest J. Gaines. The written word (X. Perret). Mesopotamia : The birth of writing (B. Andre-SaIvini).
China : From pictograms to pinyin (R. Tang-Loaec & P. Colombel). Central America : Colour-coded languages (J. Galarza). Islam : The calligrapher's art (H.
Massoudy). Africa : An inspired invention (D. Dalby). Japan : A four-in-hand script (Shiro Noda). The Western world : The power of the pen (H. J. Martin). Fact
file. A colossus with feet of clay (F. Mayor). Heritage : Quito (J. E. Adoum). Greenwatch : Environment-friendly Oman (F. Bequette). Anniversary : Sa'eb of Tabriz
(H. Esmaili). Global view : An international debate on literature today and tomorrow (A. Blokh & A. Meddeb). Archives : The press and the public (P. Scott
Mowrer). Listening :1. Leymarie talks to D. Patnayik. Books : A man and his time. 1995 : United Nations Year for Tolerance : An uphill task (T. Ben Jelloun).
MAY. THE PILGRIM'S WAY. Interview with The Abbe Pierre. A mysterious journey (F.-B. Huyghe). The thrice-holy city (A. Laurent). Pathways to enlighten-
ment (M. Pye). The road to Compostela (M. Bravo Lozano). Chinese Buddhist pilgrims in India (P. Magnin). Pilgrimages in Judaism (N. de Lange). Where the
rivers meet (R. Bharucha). The heart's infinity (A. Meddeb). Unfettered freedom (F. Mayor). Heritage : The mystery of Persepolis (C.-E. Doxuan). Greenwatch :
Mining, a clean bill of health ? (F. Bequette). Archives : The Latin American intellect (A. Reyes). Listening : The eye and the ear (I. Leymarie).
JUNE. AIDS, A WORLDWIDE EMERGENCY. Interview with Nicolae Breban. Editorial (F. Mayor). From HIV to Aids (R. Weiss). The state of research (L.
Montagnier). What can be done ? (M. Merson). The Maghreb : women in the front line (H. Himmich & L. Imane). Zimbabwe : the social roots of Aids (M. Bassett).
India : no time to lose (1. 5. Gilada). Europe : the political dilemma (R. Sussmuth). New therapeutic approaches (J.-M. Andrieu). Health and human rights (J. Mann).
The search for a vaccine (M. Girard). Aids in a different light (M.-T. Bocabeille). Fact file. Heritage : Susah (M. Ghachem). Greenwatch : Turkey (F. Bequette).
Listening :cultural counterpoint (l. Leymarie).
JULY-AUGUST. A CENTURY OF CINEMA. Interviews with Milos Forman, Jean-Paul Rappeneau, Suresh Jindal, Mani Kaul, Abbas Kiarostami, Tomas
Gutierrez Alea, Nagisa Oshima, Marcello Mastroianni, Milco Mancevski, Volker Schlondorff. An art and an industry (P. Schepelern). A birthday or a funeral ? (K.
Zanussi). Hollywood (T. Balio). Perchance to dream... (L. Steketee). Methuselah or Peter Pan ? (J.-C. Carriere). Windows of opportunity (J. Palmer). The first
Indian studios (R. Maitra). A silver-screen symphony (E. Faure). Egypt through the looking-glass (M. Wassef). Mexican melodrama : the remake (J. C. Avellar).
Cinecitta (F. Bono). The African cinema in crisis (G. Kabore). The Babelsberg Studios. Yesterday's images for tomorrow's eyes (T. Wagner). Appeal by the
Director-General of UNESCO : Saving the cinematic heritage (F. Mayor). Anniversary : Abai Kunanbayev, 1845-1904 (interview with C. Aitmatov).
SEPTEMBER. WOMEN : ONE HALF OF HEAVEN. Interview with Nelson Freire. A time for partnership (R. Eisler). The North : a disturbing independence
(interview ith B. Friedan). The South : a joint struggle (interview with A. Traore). Pride without prejudice (A. Jung). A bank that only lends to the poor (interview
with M. Yunus). Three women from Pakistan (A. Inayatullah). Going it alone (C. Catarino & L. Oso). Africa's invisible women (P. Made). The Mothers of the
Plaza de Mayo (A. D. Ortiz). Rigoberta Menchu, witness to an age. Somalia : the great escape (H. Keynan). Norwegian politics bridges the gender gap (H. Skjeie).
Lithuania : the first statute for women (U. Karvelis). Men supporting women (M. S. Kimmel). Are men and women on the same wavelength ? (C. Vidal). The road to
Beijing (interview with 1. Breines). Fact file. Women Nobel Laureates. Listening to Africa (F. Mayor). 1995 : United Nations Year for Tolerance : A triptych by Sofia
Gandarias (S. Nadir). Heritage : Baroque Zacatecas (F. Segovia). Greenwatch : Drylands and deserts (F. Bequette).
OCTOBER. THE UNITED NATIONS. Grounds for hope (B. Boutros-Ghali). Fifty years on (F. Mayor). Key dates. Major conflicts. The balance sheet : The
road to peace (M. Bertrand). The development debate (C. Comeliau). The struggle for human rights (P. Alston). Peace-keeping operations. Organization chart of
the UN system. Principal organs. Programmes and organizations. Specialized agencies. Specialized agency chiefs look ahead. Greenwatch : Gender and environment
(F. Bequette).
NOVEMBER. PEACE, A NEW BEGINNING. Interview with Yehudi Menuhin. A new beginning (F. Mayor). Our common home (E. Morin). The road to 1945
(C. Bekri). UNESCO's programme for peace (A. S. Sayyad). Demilitarizing military service (A. Baer). Peacemakers honoured by UNESCO : Nelson Mandela (T. Ben
Jelloun), Frederik Willem de Klerk (A. Johnson), The Hague Academy of International Law, Shimon Peres (C. Enderlin), Yitzhak Rabin (L. Beyer de Ryke),
Yasser Arafat (L. El-Kholy), Jimmy Carter (F. Lewis), Juan Carlos I (R. L. Acuna). Greenwatch : Fish farming, a 4, 000-year-old growth industry (F. Bequette).
Heritage : The Iguaçu Falls (E. Bailby). Listening : The birth of the blues (I. Leymarie). 1995 : United Nations Year for Tolerance : The watchful eye of democracy (R.
Hoggart).
DECEMBER. TROGLODYTES. Interview with Jean Daniel. Life below ground (J. Rewerski). China : when loess means more (J. P. Loubes). Italy :rocks in a
hard place (P. Laureano). Ethiopia's new Jerusalem (K. Begashaw). Troglodytic sites on the World Heritage List. Science that must be shared (F. Mayor). Heritage :
Luxembourg (J.-P. Kraemer). Greenwatch : Protecting plant life (F. Bequette).
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
