<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="102554eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
EDGAR MORIN:
A NEW WAY OF
THINKING
INTERVIEW WITK
GABRIEL GARCI
MARQUEZ
M 1205 -9602 -22.00 F
UNITED KINGDOM: £3 FRANCE: 22F, F. AUSTRALIA: AS7.90 BELGIUM: BF1M CANADA: CSS TS TJ»: S4.S0 . SWITZERLAND: SFS.SO NETHERLANDS: Fl 10 - DENMARK: KRM
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to
all photographs.
The dance of life
1993, paper cutout by Lesya Bespalova
The art of making paper cutouts, practised in both East and
West, is particularly popular among the Slav peoples. Artist
Lesya Bespalova was born In Ukraine, where paper cutouts are
known as vitinanka. In this sample of her work fantastic
dancing creatures evoke the joys and mysteries of life.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
CONTENTS
FEBRUARY 1996
4
INTERVIEW WITH
Gabriel Garcia
Márquez
MONTH BY MONTH
by
Bahgat Elnadi and
Adel Rifaat
36
COMMENTARY by
Federico Mayor
38 HERITAGE
Olinda
The sleeping beauty ofnortheastern
Brazil
by Joel Franz Rose//
43 GREENWATCH
Mauritius
Paradise lost or Paradise regained'
by France Bequette
47 LISTENING
Isabelle Leymarie talks to
Chico O'Fcirrill
48 REFLECTIONS
Children and violence
on the screen
by Nils Gunnar Nilsson
50 AS IT WAS...
The Unesco Courier
FEBRUARY 1958
secrets of
complexity
A NEW WAY OF THINKING 10
by Edgar Morin
A FAMILY TREE WITH ROOTS IN EAST AND WEST 15
by Yi-zhuang Chen
CUTTING THE GORDIAN KNOT 20
by Ivar Ekeland
FRONTIERS OF PSYCHOTHERAPY 23
by Saúl Fuks
THE CASE OF THE DISAPPEARING DINOSAURS 26
by Gianluca Bocchi and Mauro Ceruti
LOGIC, CULTURES AND INDIVIDUALS 31
by Magoroh Maruyama
Cover:
A computer-generated image based
on a fractal geometry formula.
© Index Stoch/Vloo, Paris
consultant Edgar Morin
the unesco Courier
49th year ^^"^
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin ¡n the minds of men, It is ¡n the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples
of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples and to employ these means for the purposes
of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . . ajRMJ fRQM JHE pREmBLE n JHE C0NSmuTI0N 0F UNESC0: L0ND0Ni u N0KmER 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Inte r v i e w
Gabriel García Márquez
The writer's craft
Is it possible to protect culture?
Gabriel García Márquez: The major ques¬
tion that governments and people inter¬
ested in culture should ask is what kind
of protection the state can offer to cul¬
ture without interfering in it and manipu¬
lating it or, most important of all, without
making it subservient to the government's
political philosophy. The trouble with
culture ministries in Latin America is their
subordination to the vicissitudes of
national politics. A cabinet crisis has
repercussions on cultural activity. Power
struggles within the government result in
the appointment of a culture minister who
has no interest in culture or is opposed to
the previous minister's policies. Conse¬
quently culture depends on a series of
comings and goings that have nothing to
do with culture but everything to do with
politics, and worst of all, with partisan
politics.
Culture should be helped by estab¬
lishing the conditions in which it can
develop freely. But in practice this cre¬
ates big problems. It's impossible to pre¬
dict the workings of creativity or to plan
anything creative. What's more, how can
you do anything about culture without
defining what you mean by culture?
According to UNESCO, culture is what
people add to nature, everything that is
produced specifically by human beings. I
believe that culture is the social use of
human intelligence. Deep down we all
know what the term "culture" means,
but we have a hard time summing it up in
a few words. Culture may be I think it
was France's former Minister of Culture,
Jack Lang, who said this all kinds of
things cooking, a way of being, of
makinglovc, of living, and mixed up in all
this, the arts. Every act has cultural over¬
tones. The danger is that the wider the
concept of culture, the harder it is to
know how to protect it.
Can culture be taught?
6. G. M.: At the moment I'm wondering
how the arts, literature, journalism
(which, to my mind, is a form of litera¬
ture) and the cinema (which is most cer¬
tainly an art) should be taught. Educa¬
tion of this kind must be a one-off, it
must be informal.
At the cinema school in San Antonio
de Los Baños in Cuba I have a workshop
called "How to tell a story", where I sit
a maximum of about a dozen young men
with scenario experience round a table.
We try to see if it is possible to create
stories collectively, to see if the miracle
of creation is possible round a table.
Sometimes we've brought it off. I start
off by asking one of them about the
most recent film he's seen. "Tell me
what it's about," I say. Some of them
know how to tell a story, others don't.
One might answer, "It's the story of a
country girl faced with the contradic¬
tions of modern city life." Then his
neighbour will say, "A country girl is
bored with her family, so one day she
hops onto the first bus that goes by. She
runs off with the driver and meets. ..."
And he starts to tell the girl's story
episode by episode.
The first young man is gifted, but
he'll never know how to tell a story. He
hasn't been born with the gift of story¬
telling. The other fellow, who knows
how to tell a story, still has a long way to
go before becoming a writer; he's got to
acquire the technique and something
that's extremely important basic cul¬
ture. I cannot imagine how anyone could
even think of writing a novel without
having at least a vague idea of the ten
thousand years of literature that have
gone before, if only to know his or her
own standpoint. And then the writer
must settle down to a daily routine of
work because inspiration doesn't fall
from the sky. You have to work at every
word, every day of the week.
Writing is a craft, a difficult craft
that requires a lot of concentration and
discipline, as do painting and com¬
posing. By working at it, someone who
knows how to tell a story will become a
writer; someone else, however hard he
or she works, will never make it. It's the
same with music. If you teach your chil¬
dren a melody, some will be able to
repeat it exactly; others will never learn.
Do you regard yourself as an
intellectual?
G. G. M.:Not entirely. An intellectual, it
seems to me, is someone with more or
less preconceived ideas that he or she is
constantly trying to compare with
'It's impossible to predict the workings of creativity
or to plan anything creative'
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
A master of modern letters,
immer of the 1982 Nobel Prize
for Literature, the noted
Colombian writer talks to Bahgat
Elnadi, Adel Rifaat and Miguel
Labarca about creativity and his
conception of the writer's craft.
reality. In fact the intellectual tries to
interpret reality through his or her pre¬
conceived ideas. I live off anecdotes, off
the happenings of everyday life. I try to
interpret the world and create art
through experience of everyday life and
the knowledge of the world that I grad¬
ually acquire, without preconceived
ideas of any kind. That's why interviews,
where the questions oblige me to give
abstract answers, are very hard for me.
My starting point has to be a real fact.
That's how I function as a writer. I think
I could prove that every line in my books
has been inspired by a real fact, some¬
thing that I was either told, or that I
experienced or knew about.
In your world, knowledge
encompasses many things. . . .
G. G. M.: That's true. People have said
that my novel One Hundred Years of
Solitude contains incredible things that
could never have happened. But for me
these things correspond to real-life
experiences. Some of my reading has
marked me for life, for example, a
bound volume I once found in a trunk, a
book I had never even heard of. It was
The Thousand and One Nights. I spent
the early years of my life haunted by a
vision of flying carpets and génies pop¬
ping out of lamps. It was wonderful . . .
and for me, completely true.
Moreover, one of the episodes that
excited me most and seemed the most
fantastic was perfectly plausible the
story of the fisherman who asks his
neighbour to lend him some lead for his
net and promises to give her in exchange
the first fish he catches. She lends him
the lead and he keeps his promise. She
cuts open the fish and discovers a dia¬
mond inside. Life is full of natural
things that ordinary mortals fail to see.
The intelligence of poets is to see the
extraordinary in the ordinary.
So this is the question I ask myself.
Why shouldn't the people who believed
in the flying carpets of The Thousand
and One Nights believe that flying was
done in my own village? In my village
there are no carpets but there are mats.
So people fly mats, and do other won¬
drous things, among which we grew up
and lived. I think I made up my mind
not to invent or create a new reality but
to find the reality with which I identi¬
fied and which I knew. That's the kind
of writer I am.
What did you do after One Hundred
Years of Solitude'}
G. G. NI.: I began to mistrust myself. I
have to make an effort not to repeat or
plagiarize myself. I have to go deeper
and deeper into reality, by paying spe¬
cial attention to words. Without real¬
izing it, I have a tendency to repeat
things and put the same adjectives with
the same nouns.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
interview
Gabriel
García
Márquez
llie w
craft
People often talk about the influ¬
ence that some authors have had on
others. For myself, I've never tried to
imitate authors I've admired. On the
contrary, I've done all I could not to imi¬
tate them. But in wanting to be personal
there is a danger of falling into the
opposite trap, and the problem is how
to avoid imitating oneself.
In my latest novel, Del amor y otros
demonios ("Of Love and Other
Demons") a story that takes place in
Cartagena de Indias in the eighteenth
century I tried to recreate the culture,
the mentality and the intolerance of the
period, but the hardest thing of all was
to make sure that the novel was different
from its predecessors. The first people
who read it thought it had a kind of
sobriety that wasn't my style. I was
delighted because that's what I'd been
aiming at, to distance it not from myself
but from my other books. It had to be
mine; all books resemble their authors.
In one way or another every book is auto¬
biographical. And every fictional char¬
acter is an alter ego or a collage made
from this or that aspect of the author,
his memories and his knowledge. It seems
to me that a writer's work develops as a
result of digging down inside oneself to
see what is there, for the key to what one
is looking for and the mystery of death.
We know that the mystery of life will
never be deciphered.
Is this preoccupation unique to
Latin American literature?
G. G. M.: It's a fact that Latin America
was born out of a very specific litera
ture, the literature of chivalry. This was
no accident since novels of chivalry were
banned in the Spanish colonies. They
liberated the imagination! Because of
these novels, the chroniclers of the con¬
quest were ready to believe what they
saw. But what they saw went beyond
what they were capable of believing.
This led to the birth of the fantastic
world which later came to be called
"magic realism" and which is a hallmark
of Latin American culture.
When you think of your public now,
do you think in terms of Latin America,
the Spanish-speaking world or the
world at large?
G. G. M.: First of all we have to win over
our own public. If we manage to do that,
it means we have said something valid,
and only then will we interest the rest of
the world. One doesn't acquire a public
by chance. First there has to be an iden¬
tification with reality that interests this
public. Then the identification spreads,
and it interests the entire world.
Above all we must do and continue
to do what we think we should do. Then
things start to happen. When I began
writing, I never imagined I would have
any readers, not to mention large num¬
bers of them. One Hundred Years of
Solitude was my fifth book. It was five
years before my first one was published.
It went from publisher to publisher,
from press to press. It finally came out,
but it was a long time before it began to
sell. You have to do your own work, then
wait and see. To be able to live from
one's writing is a stroke of luck. It can't
be a goal.
For you as a writer, have there been
new departures, moments of doubt,
changes of direction?
G. G. M.: I have made two big leaps in
the dark. The first was to stop smoking
cigarettes. Or perhaps I should say that
cigarettes stopped smoking me. I was
totally hooked and smoked four packs a
day. I never had bronchitis, and the
doctor never ordered me to stop. But
one day I put out a cigarette and never
smoked again. Then, when I sat down to
write, I realized that I had never written
a line without smoking a cigarette.
"Now what?" I wondered. Should I wait
and get used to writing without smoking
or sit down immediately and start to
write? The need to write proved
stronger, and I sat down in front of my
typewriter. But then another problem
cropped up: my hands. They got in the
way now that they had no cigarette to
hold. Fortunately my mind wasn't
affected. It got on with the job as
before.
The second leap in the dark hap¬
pened when I woke up one day and real¬
ized I had only one thing to do, and that
was to write. Before that I either had
to write or work for television, adver¬
tising or the radio. My wife, Mercedes,
once put it like this, "What are you
doing today, working or writing?" We
had separated "work", which had a
financial purpose, from "writing", which
was an unproductive pleasure. Then,
one day I woke up and said to myself,
"From now on I don't have to 'work' any
more. I can write or not write." But I
soon understood the danger this
freedom brought. If I didn't write that
day, perhaps I wouldn't write tomorrow,
or the day after. I kept on writing.
Then I was confronted by another
problem. I had always been a newspa¬
perman, and at that time papers were
put together at night. It was a bohemian
life: finish at the paper at one in the
morning, then write a poem or a short
story until about three, then go out to
play skittles or have a beer. When you
got home at dawn, ladies who were
a difficult craft that requires a lot of concentration
and discipline'
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
going to mass would cross to the other
side of the street for fear that you were
either drunk or intending to mug or rape
them. Shifting from night to day in
order to write wasn't easy.
With'my newfound freedom, I made
myself keep banker's hours, or rather a
bank clerk's hours, as if I had to turn in
on time every day. Starting at one spe¬
cific time and finishing at another. This
is important. If you get involved and
don't stop in time, the later pages are
written by a tired man. The big problem
for most writers who don't earn enough
to be able to write full time is that they
write in their spare time, in other words
when they are tired. This is literature
produced by tired men. When I get car¬
ried away and continue beyond the time
when I should stop, I end up by writing
tired. You need strict discipline,
starting and stopping at specific times.
My children's school started at 8
a.m. I was the one who took them. Then
I would sit down and write until two
when I brought them back home again.
I felt that in all good conscience I had
earned my day and my lunch. In the
afternoon I'd go to the cinema or see
friends or do various odd jobs. Without
feeling guilty.
I felt guilty between books. When I
finished one book, I wouldn't write for a
while; then I had to learn how to do it
all over again. The arm goes cold;
there's a learning process you have to go
through again before you rediscover the
warmth that comes over you when you
are writing. So I really had to find some¬
thing that would keep me writing
between books. I solved the problem by
writing my memoirs. Since then, I
haven't left my desk for a single day.
When I travel I'm a little less strict, but
I always jot down notes in the morning.
All of which means there is a lot of
truth in the saying that writing is one
per cent inspiration and 99 per cent per¬
spiration.
I also defend inspiration, but not in
the sense given to it by the romantics,
for whom it was a sort of divine illumi¬
nation. When you are working hard on
something, trying to make sense of it,
worrying at it, fanning it into a blaze,
you reach a point where you control it
and identify with it so completely that
you feel that a divine wind is dictating it
to you. That state of inspiration exists,
yes, and when you experience it,
although it may not last very long, it is
the greatest happiness that anyone
could possibly experience. I
'When you are working hard on something,
trying to make sense of it, worrying at it, fanning it into
a blaze, you reach a point where you feel that a divine
wind is dictating it to you'
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
TBE. UNESCO
Courier
49th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational. Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15, France.
Fax:(331)45.66.92.70
internet: unesco.courier@unesco.org
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition: Miguei Labarca. Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José BanaagiTel. 45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (Tel. 45.68.47.14)
Artwork Consultant: Eric Frogé
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Ir na Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: E!-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Moacyr A. Fioravante (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Javaid Iqbal Syed (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay: S'dm Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: KangWoo-hyon (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Snen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Soohie Costopoulos (Athens)
Slnhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Katri Himma (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Sudhasinee Vajrabul (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: \azer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: VolodymyrVasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION. Fax: 42.73.24.29
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jacqueline Leulse-Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel
Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel. 45.68.49.19)
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: Daniel Meister (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
UNESCO m ACTION... UNESCO IN ACT!
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
lyear: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa. Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. No" -copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompa¬
nied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The bound¬
aries on maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by Usesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is pro¬
duced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc.. Ill
West 40th Street, New York. U.S.A.; (4} Beil and Howell Co.. Old Mansfield
Road. Wooster. Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl FÉVRIER 1996
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de r Unesco.
Impression; MAURY IMPRIMEUR.
Z.l. Route d'Étampes. 45331 Malsherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 2-1996-0PI-96-545 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 2-3 and 50-51.
SATELLITE NEWS EXCHANGE IN
FORMER YUGOSLAVIA
The first exchange of news by satellite
between three television stations in former
Yugoslavia began on 6 October 1995.
Each week since then NTV 99 (Sarajevo),
Studio B (Belgrade) and Kanal Al
(Skopje) have been sending their news bul¬
letins to the Worldwide Television Net¬
work (WTN) in London, where they are
compiled into a thirty-minute copyright-
free report (10 minutes per channel).
WTN transmits the report every Friday at
16:50 GMT on its Eutelsat II Fl satellite
channel, which broadcasts to Scandinavia,
Eastern Europe, Syria, Turkey and North
Africa. The exchange programme, which
has financial support from UNESCO, is the
latest in a series of UNESCO moves to
encourage media independence in former
Yugoslavia. I
PALMYRA AND CONFUCIUS
The archaeological site of Palmyra (Syria)
and the Chinese philosopher Confucius
are featured on two new medals from
UNESCO's Philatelic and Numismatic Pro¬
gramme. Struck in gold, silver and bronze
at the Paris Mint, the medals have been
issued respectively within the framework
of UNESCO's programme to preserve the
world's cultural and natural heritage and
on the occasion of the fourth World Con¬
ference on Women held in Beijing (China)
in September 1995. I
UNESCO PRIZES FOR SCIENCE AND
THE ENVIRONMENT
UNESCO prizes for science and the envi¬
ronment were awarded at a ceremony held
on 6 November 1995 at the Organization's
Paris Headquarters. The 1995 UNESCO
Science Prize went to Chinese computer
expert Xuan Wang, who created the Chi¬
nese automatic composition system cur¬
rently being used in the production of 95
per cent of the books and 99 per cent of
the newspapers in China. The 1995
Kalinga Prize for the Popularization of
Science was awarded to the Mexican
astrophysicist Julieta Norma Fierro
Gossman. The Carlos J. Finlay Prize was
presented jointly to French biologist Pas¬
cale Cossart for her research into liste
riosis, and to Belgian biochemist Jan
Balzarini for his research into cancer and
Aids. The 1995 Javed Husain Prize for
Young Scientists went to Mexican chemist
Tessy Maria Lopez Goerne. The Sultan
Qaboos Prize for Environmental Preserva¬
tion was awarded to the National Park of
Lake Malawi (Malawi). I
EDUCATION FOR ALL IN VIDEO
A database featuring 151 video tapes
devoted to educational projects from 58
countries has been set up as part of a joint
UNESCO-UNICEF project entitled "Edu¬
cation for All, Making it Work". The tapes
may be screened upon request at UNESCO
Headquarters. A printout of the data¬
base, entitled VIDED, is also available
upon request. I
\/ Education Sector Documentation and
Information Service of the Basic Educa¬
tion Division, UNESCO, 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France.
Tel.: (33-1)45 68 10 13.
CORRECTION
In the chronology entitled "Key dates"
published in the October 1995 issue of
the UNESCO Courier (The United
Nations: Why it matters), the following
entry appeared on page 9: "1950, 21
October: The General Assembly con¬
demns the invasion of Tibet by China."
This information was taken from a
book entitled L'ONUpour quoifaire? by
André Lewin (formerly Deputy Director
of the Press and Publications Division of
the United Nations), published by Gal¬
limard, Paris, 1995. On page 132 of Mr.
Lewin's book, in a chapter entitled
"Chronology", the following entry
appears: "1950, 21 October: the Chi¬
nese army enters Tibet. The Assembly
condemns China."
In point of fact, the General
Assembly adopted its first Resolution
on Tibet on 21 October 1959 (not
1950). Furthermore, this Resolution
does not include any explicit condem¬
nation.
In our previous issue, Dance, the
sacred fire, Maurice Béjart was
interviewed by Martine Leca.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
ionth by month
It is the most natural thing in the world to want to simplify things and see
them in schematic form, and to break complex phenomena down into their
component parts. Surely, before starting to look for order in a chaotic world
we should make an effort to set our own minds in order. But though this may
be a necessary first step, it can be misleading. If we go no further, if we
regard the point of departure as the destination, if we consider as certainties
what are at best only approximations, if we mix up the parts with the whole,
we adopt a reductionist outlook on the world. And sooner or later a price
must be paid.
In politics freedom is one casualty of a reductionist outlook, as twentieth-
century totalitarianism has shown on many occasions. Whether it is right-
wing or left-wing, religious or secular, rooted in ideology or the expression of
an identity, totalitarianism regards one human groupa race, a nation, a
class, or a religious denominationmore favourably than all others and sys¬
tematically highlights the virtues of the former and the defects of the latter.
By so doing, it glorifies the collective destiny of the group and denigrates the
individual experience of its members. Those who have such a biased, hémi¬
plégie perception of themselves and of others not only end up by doing harm
to others but by mutilating themselves.
What can be seen in the social arena also occurs in all the other spheres
in which human intelligence is exercised. Oversimplification is always infertile
because it imposes a straitjacket of rigidity on what is constantly changing,
because it compartmentalizes what is naturally interlinked, and because it is
suspicious of the chaotic, contradictory and random elements that are
intrinsic to nature.
This approach leads to a dead end and must be superseded by an effort
to move from the simple to the more complex, to turn from the study of
simple units and examine the complexities of their interactions. For much of
the time, most people manage to ignore the science of complexity and rely
instead on plain common sense. Now, however, as Edgar Morin says in this
issue, non-specialists cannot afford to leave the privilege of complex thought
to scientists. We must learn to fathom the mysteries of complexity because
the substance of daily life has itself become so complex.
This is a challenge that life in the late twentieth century compels us to
accept. If we refuse to do so we may lose the thread of reality and find our¬
selves victims of new forms of totalitarianism.
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
A new way of
thinking
by Edgar Morin
EDGAR MORIN
is a French sociologist who is
emeritus director of research at
France's National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS). He is
the author of many published
works, including Introduction à la
pensée comp/exe("lntroduction
to Complex Thought", ESF, Paris,
1990) and recently published a
selection of writings entitled La
complexité humaine ("Human
Complexity", Flammarion, Paris,
1994). His most recent work
published In English is Towards a
Study of Humankind. Voll: The,
Nature of Nature (1992).
Complexity represents a shift away
from the simplifying, reductionist
approach that has traditionally
shaped scientific enquiry
Until the mid-twentieth century, most
sciences based their method on spe¬
cialization and abstraction, i.e. reducing
knowledge of a whole to knowledge of its
constituent parts (as though the organization
of a whole did not generate new properties in
relation to those of its separate parts). Their
key concept was determinism, in other
words the denial of random factors and new
factors and the application of the mechanical
logic of artificial machines to the problems of
living beings and social life.
Knowledge must make use of abstraction,
but it must also be constructed by reference
to context and hence must mobilize what the
enquirer knows about the world. Individual
facts can only be fully understood by those
who maintain and cultivate their general intel¬
ligence and mobilize their overall knowledge.
Admittedly, it is impossible to know every¬
thing about the world or to grasp its many
and varied transformations. But no matter
how difficult this may be, an attempt must be
made to understand the key problems of the
world, for otherwise we would be cognitive
idiots. This is particularly true today because
the context of all political, economic, anthro¬
pological and ecological knowledge has
become global. As a result of globalization,
everything must be situated in the planetary
*£HPB?. ^*Ui
context. Knowledge of the world as such is
necessary both for intellectual satisfaction and
for life itself. Every citizen faces the problem
of gaining access to information about the
world, and then of piecing it together and
organizing it. To do this, a new form of
thinking is needed.
In the first place, the kind of thinking that
separates must be supplemented with a kind
of thinking that makes connections. Com-
plexus means "that which is woven together".
Complex thought is a kind of thought that
unites distinction with conjunction. Secondly,
it is necessary to come to grips with uncer¬
tainty. The dogma of universal determinism
has collapsed. The universe is not subject to
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
the absolute sovereignty of order; it is the
outcome of a "dialogical" relationship (a rela¬
tionship that is both antagonistic, concurrent
and complementary) between order, dis¬
order and organization.
Complexity thus connects (contextualizes
and globalizes) and also comes to grips with
the challenge of uncertainty. How does it do
this?
A computer-generated
image created from a fractal
geometry formula.
The three theories
One approach to complexity is provided by
three theories information theory, cyber¬
netics and systems theory. These theories,
which are closely related and indeed insepa¬
rable, emerged in the early 1940s and have
had a far-reaching cross-fertilizing effect on
one another.
Information theory gives access to a uni¬
verse where there are both order (redun¬
dancy) and disorder (noise) and derives
something new from it, i.e. information itself,
which then becomes the organizing (pro¬
gramming) instrument of a cybernetic
machine. For example, information that gives
the name of the victor of a battle resolves an
uncertainty. Information that announces the
sudden death of a tyrant introduces an unex¬
pected new element into a situation.
Cybernetics is a theory of self-controlling
machines. The idea of feedback, introduced
by the U.S. mathematician Norbert Wiener,
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
IVl odel of the double stranded
helix of DNA (deoxyribonucleic
acid), the main constituent of
the genetic material of living
cells.
'Complexity connects (contextuallzes
and globalizes) and also comes to grips
with the challenge of uncertainty. '
breaks with the idea of linear causality and
introduces that of the causal loop. The cause
acts on the effect and the effect on the cause,
as in a heating system where a thermostat
controls the operation of a boiler. This regula¬
tory mechanism makes the system
autonomous, in this case ensuring that an
apartment has thermic autonomy from the
colder temperature outside. The feed-back
loop may act as an amplifying mechanism, e.g.
in a situation where an armed conflict reaches
a critical stage. The violence of one adversary
triggers off a violent reaction which in turn
triggers off another, even more violent reac¬
tion. Very many instances of this sort of infla¬
tionary or stabilizing feedback can be found
in economic, social, political or psychological
phenomena.
Systems theory provides the basis of a
way of thinking about organization. The first
lesson of systems analysis is that "the whole is
more than the sum of its parts". This means
that properties emerge from the organization
of a whole and may have a retroactive effect
on the parts. For instance, water is an emer¬
gent property of the hydrogen and oxygen of
12
which it is composed. The whole is also less
than the sum of its parts, since the parts may
have properties that are inhibited by the orga¬
nization of the whole.
Self-organization
In addition to these three theories are a
number of conceptual developments related
to the idea of self-organization. Four names
that must be mentioned in this context are
those of John von Neumann, Heinz von
Foerster, Henri Atlan and Ilya Prigogine.
In his theory of automata, von Neumann
considered the difference between artificial
automata and "living machines". He pointed
to the paradox whereby the components of
artificial machines, although very well
designed and engineered, deteriorate as soon
as the machine starts to operate. Living
machines, on the other hand, are made of
extremely unreliable components, such as
proteins, which are constantly subject to dete-
rioriation. However, these machines have the
unusual property of being able to develop and
reproduce themselves; they regenerate them¬
selves through replacing damaged molecules
by new molecules, and dead cells by new cells.
An artificial machine cannot repair itself,
whereas a living machine constantly regener¬
ates when its cells die. It is, as Heraclitus put it,
"life from death and death from life".
Von Foerster's contribution is his dis¬
covery of the principle of "order from
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
'Order, disorder and
organization are
constantly
interacting in the
physical, biological
and human worlds. '
Left, "Complexas means 'that
which is woven together'."
Below, "The universe is the
interplay of an antagonistic
and complementary
relationship between order,
disorder and organization."
noise". If a box containing a haphazardly
arranged collection of cubes, each magne¬
tized on two faces, is shaken, the cubes spon¬
taneously form themselves into a coherent
whole. A principle of order (magnetization)
plus disordered energy have created an
ordered organization. In this way, order is
created from disorder.
Henri Atlan has developed the theory of
"random organization". At the birth of the
universe there was an order/disorder/organi¬
zation dialogic triggered off by calorific turbu¬
lence (disorder), in which, under certain con¬
ditions (random encounters) organizing prin¬
ciples made possible the creation of nuclei,
atoms, galaxies and stars. This dialogic recurred
when life emerged via encounters between
macro-molecules within a kind of self-pro¬
ductive loop which eventually became a living
self-organization. The dialogic between order,
disorder and organization exists in a wide
variety of forms, and via countless feedback
processes is constantly in action in the phys¬
ical, biological and human worlds.
Prigogine introduced the idea of self-orga¬
nization from disorder in a different way. In
so-called Rayleigh-Bénard convection cells,
coherent structures are formed and main-
tened between two temperature levels when a
thin layer of silicone oil is carefully heated. In
order to be sustainable, these structures need
supplies of energy which they consume and
dissipate. Living beings have sufficient
autonomy to draw energy from their envi¬
ronment and even extract information from it
and absorb its organization. I have called this
process auto-eco-organization.
The study of complex phenomena can thus
be seen as a building with several floors. The
ground floor consists of the three theories
(information, cybernetics and systems) and
contains the tools needed to develop a theory
of organization. On the second floor are the
ideas of von Neumann, von Foerster, Atlan
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Springtime (1573)
by the Italian painter
Giuseppe Arcimboldo. and Prigogine on self-organization. I have
added some other features to the building,
notably the dialogical principle, the recursion
principle and the hologrammatic principle.
'Complex thought
incorporates
uncertainty and is
capable of
conceiving
organization.'
The three principles
The dialogical principle brings together two
antagonistic principles or notions which on
the face of things should repel one another
but are in fact indissociable and essential for
understanding a single reality. The physicist
Niels Bohr believed that physical particles
should be regarded as both corpuscles and
waves. Blaise Pascal said that the "the oppo¬
site of a truth is not an error but a contrary
truth." Bohr put this in the following terms:
"The opposite of a trivial truth is a stupid
error, but the opposite of a profound truth is
always another profound truth". The
problem is that of combining antagonistic
notions in order to envisage the organiza¬
tional and creative processes in the complex
world of human life and history.
The principle of organizational recur¬
sion goes further than the feedback principle;
it goes beyond the idea of regulation to that
of self-production and self-organization. It is
a generating loop in which products and
effects themselves produce and cause what
produces them. Thus we, as individuals, are
the products of an age-old system of repro¬
duction, but this system can reproduce itself
only if we ourselves become its producers by
procreating. Individual human beings pro¬
duce society in and through their interac¬
tions, but society, as an emerging whole, pro¬
duces the humanity of individuals by confer¬
ring language and culture on them.
The "hologrammatic" principle high¬
lights the apparent paradox of certain systems
where not only is the part present in the
whole, but the whole is present in the part:
the totality of the genetic heritage is present in
each individual cell. In the same way, the indi¬
vidual is part of society but society is present
in every individual, through his or her lan¬
guage, culture and standards.
Conclusion
Thinking in terms of complexity is clearly not a
mode of thought that replaces certainty with
uncertainty, separation with inseparability, and
logic with all kinds of special exceptions. On the
contrary, it involves a constant toing and froing
between certainty and uncertainty, between
the elementary and the global, between the
separable and the inseparable. The aim is not to
abandon the principles of classical science
order, separability and logic but to absorb
them into a broader and richer scheme of
things. The aim is not to set a vacuous all-pur¬
pose holism against systematic reductionism,
but to attach the concreteness of the parts to
the totality. Linkage must be made between the
principles of order and disorder, separation and
connection, autonomy and dependence, which
are at one and the same time complementary,
concurrent and antagonistic.
In short, complex thought is not the oppo¬
site of simplifying thought; it incorporates sim¬
plifying thought. As Hegel might have put it, it
unites simplicity and complexity and ulti¬
mately reveals its own simplicity. In fact, the
paradigm of complexity can be described just
as simply as that of simplicity. Whereas the'
latter requires us to dissociate and reduce, the
paradigm of complexity requires us to connect
as well as to distinguish.
Complex thought is essentially thought
which incorporates uncertainty and is capable
of conceiving organization. It is capable of
linking, contextualizing and globalizing but
can at the same time acknowledge what is sin¬
gular and concrete.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
A family tree with roots in
East and West
by Yi-zhuang Chen
From Lao-tzu
to Hegel,
thinkers from
different
cultural
horizons point
the way to
complex
thought
Complex thought has a long history,
which can be traced in both Western
and Chinese philosophies.
From Heraclitus to Lao-tzu
Some philosophers of Western Antiquity
argued that reality is complex but thought is
simple, and that if people did not realize this,
the essence of reality would escape them
altogether. For instance, the properties of
being, which are contradictory and incom¬
patible according to the categorizations of
human thought, may be in harmony and
simultaneous in real life. This was the key idea
of the Greek philosopher Heraclitus (535-480
B.C.), who taught people "to listen to nature"
in order to find its "invisible harmony".
"Union consists of bringing together and
tending apart, agreement and disagreement;
the One comes out of all things and all things
out of the one."
" By virtue of its dynamism,
the mind, like the self-
organizing being, resists
natural tendencies to chaos
and degradation." Above,
Labyrinth (1993), Indian ink
drawing by the Argentine
artist Christina Martinez.
© Jacqueline Hyde/Maison de l'Amérique Latine,
Pans
According to Heraclitus, the underlying
connection of opposites the transformation
of a thing into its opposite is the principle of
the logos, the universal formula in accordance
with which all natural events occur. But this
concept is difficult to grasp owing to the fixed,
one-sided nature of human intelligence.
Similar ideas appeared at a very early stage in
Chinese philosophy. In the / Cbing ("Classic
of Changes") dating from the eleventh-
twelfth centuries B.C., yin and yang consti¬
tute the two opposite poles of a single reality,
its fundamental duality. In its original sense,
yang meant the brightness of the sun or a
sun-bathed slope, while yin meant lack of
brightness, or a shady slope. Later, all phe¬
nomena came to be classified in terms oí yang
znàyin and to be regarded as comprising two
opposing aspects. As efficient causes, yin and
yang co-operate to produce the universe and
all its constituent parts and to regulate their
1£.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
'In proposing a many-
sided version of the
truth, Protagoras
points to the
dimension of thought
that cannot be
simplified.'
The 4th-century-B.C.
Chinese philosopher Lao-tzu,
the father of Taoism.
movement. As the / Ching puts it, "Yang is
the principle that makes things commence,
while yin is that which completes them".
The ancient Chinese believed that the
cosmos is governed by a bipolar principle and
cannot be reduced to a single ultimate prin¬
ciple. Thought is governed by the proposi¬
tion that opposites are exclusive and incom¬
patible, but real life is governed by the com¬
plementarity of opposites. In the Tao-te
Ching (the "Classic of the Way of Power"),
Lao-tzu (fourth century B.C.) explains that
"the movement of tao, " which is at the origin
of the universe and causes order to reign
within it, is "to act in the opposite direction".
The tao encourages what is underdevel¬
oped and represses what is overdeveloped.
This leads to the implacable law whereby
everything that has developed to its extreme
turns into its opposite. "People who have
grown robust, age", for example. This law
maintains the harmony of the world as an
organic whole, but it often goes against the will
and the spontaneous intelligence of human
beings. By claiming that the successful com¬
pletion of an enterprise means starting out
from its opposite, Lao-tzu brings to light a mul¬
titude of paradoxical phenomena and criticizes
the linear nature of human understanding.
Protagoras and Chuang-tzu
Philosophical relativism, which in the West
was introduced by the Greek sophist Pro¬
tagoras (485-441 B.C.), takes account of the
multiplicity of approaches which are the basis
of knowledge. While "matter" is the common
source of human sensations, the images
human beings have of matter are determined
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
by their senses, which change with age and the
constitution of their bodies, so that each of us
sees matter in a different way. However, no
one representation of the true physiognomy
of matter is superior to any other. There are as
many yardsticks for measuring things as there
are people to measure them.
Plutarch tells the story of an athlete who
died of a wound inflicted by a javelin during a
sporting contest. After the accident, the
Athenian statesman Pericles and Protagoras
spent a whole day discussing who or what was
responsible for it, the javelin, the javelin
thrower or the organizers of the event. The
philosopher maintained that it was necessary to
distinguish several different viewpoints: for a
doctor, the javelin was the direct cause of death;
for a judge, the javelin-thrower was respon¬
sible; from the viewpoint of a magistrate, the
organizers of the contest should be charged.
In proposing a many-sided version of the
truth, Protagoras is advocating that diversity
and contradiction should be tolerated and
even legitimized in the process of knowledge.
He points to the unsimplifiable, irreducible
dimension of thought.
These ideas also have an equivalent in Chi¬
nese thought. In the view of Chuang-tzu (c.
369-268 B.C.), people apprehend different
aspects of the same object, depending on
their standpoint. This observation prompted
him to relativize the truth. "The male
monkey seeks the female," he wrote. "The
stag seeks the hind. Moaqiang and Liji are
beautiful creatures whom all men adore, but
when they approach, fish dive deep into the
water and birds fly quickly away. Who
knows true beauty?" Human knowledge is
conditioned and is therefore uncertain.
Kant and Hegel
In modern times, philosophers began to
realize that the human mind is capable of both
simple thought, which abides by the rules of
3 The Greek philosopher
Heraclitus of Ephesus
(6th-5th centuries B.C.).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
'The roof, which is
at the origin of the
tree, comes from
the seed, which is
itself born of the
tree.'
Fang Yizhi
The circle of yin and yang
(in centre), two
complementary principles of
Chinese philosophy.
'Moaqiang and Liji are beautiful creatures whom all men adore,
but when they approach, fish dive deep into the water and birds
fly away. Who knows true beauty?'
Chuang-tzu
formal logic, and complex thought, which goes
beyond those rules and criticizes, corrects and
improves simple thought. The mind has the
power to criticize itself and improve itself. It
is capable of knowing the complexity of reality,
and also of knowing itself.
Immanuel Kant (1724-1804) held the view
that understanding is concerned with
knowing the relative (or the finite) and reason
with knowing the absolute (or the infinite).
However, the distinction he makes between
these two cognitive faculties prevents him
from arriving at a true paradigm of com¬
plexity. G.W.F. Hegel (1770-1831) combined
the two by making a distinction between
three levels in the human mind: under¬
standing, which is responsible for analytical
knowledge and separates concepts; negative
or dialectic reason, which is concerned with
synthetic knowledge and unites all concepts
by removing the difference that divides
them; and positive reason, which unites ana¬
lytical and synthetic knowledge and grasps
that all concepts are distinctive yet linked, and
certain by virtue of their mobility. These
three cognitive levels are also essential and are
organically welded into a single process. We
thus have a perfect process, capable of self-
perfection.
In Hegel's view, the movement of the
mind follows an ascending loop. It emerges
from its usual form of operation (under-,
standing) in order to reveal the limits of that
form and remedy its failing, and then returns
with all the results of its criticism and correc¬
tion (dialectic) to its usual form of operation,
but at a higher level.
The active nature of the mind brings it
closer to the self-organizing being which, by
virtue of its dynamism, resists natural ten¬
dencies towards chaos and degradation. The
paradigm of complexity thus unveils the
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
©SuperStock, Pans
J apáñese snow monkeys.
essential way in which our mind functions,
while providing us with the means of under¬
standing the workings of reality, of the self-
organizing and self-producing being.
Fang Yizhi
A century and a half before Hegel, the Chi¬
nese philosopher Fang Yizhi (1611-1671) had
formulated very similar ideas. Deeply influ¬
enced by the dialectic arising from Chinese
philosophical tradition and Indian Buddhism,
Fang Yizhi argued that two fundamental
methods of knowledge existed simultane¬
ously: the "investigation of qualities" (identi¬
fying the specific determinants of different
things) and the "embracing of the essence"
(finding the common cause that determines
different things).
According to Fang Yizhi, only through
the fusion of these two methods (analytic and
synthetic) is it possible to know dynamic
reality. The essence of the real is to be found
in self-determination and self-creation. He
takes the example of the tree. The root, which
is at the origin of the tree, comes from the
seed, which is itself born of the tree. Once the
tree has flowered, the seed is no longer its
substance {ti) but its mode of operation
(yong). The functioning of a thing has a
causality that is not linear but recursive.
Fang Yizhi's methodology is based on the
theory of the threefold truth which he took
from Buddhism. He believed in the para¬
mount need to affirm the existence of two
opposing extremes (Heaven and Earth, for
example) and of all the distinctive things of
the world of phenomena. The next step is to
deny the existence of all this in order to grasp
the unitary value of the noumenal world as
nothingness. The synthesis of these two
forms of knowledge leads to complete and
perfect knowledge. In other words, Fang
Yizhi first of all observes the principle of non¬
contradiction and then subjects it to the prin¬
ciple of the unity of opposites, before going
on to comply with both principles at the same
time, each to its relevant degree. Here once
again are Hegel's three cognitive levels:
understanding, dialectical reasoning and pos-
YI-ZHUANGCHEN,
of the People's Republic of China,
is engaged on research into
comparative Sino-Occidental
Philosophy at the Centre for East
Asian Studies at the University of
Montreal (Canada).
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Cutting the
Gordian knot
by Ivar Ekeland
Since we can
never base our
decisions on
complete
knowledge, we
have to live with
uncertainty
lYIel Gibson in the title role of
Franco Zeffi relli's film Hamlet
(1991).
IVAR EKELAND,
of France, is honorary president
of trie University of Parls-
Dauphine and director of the
Institut Finance Dauphine, where
he teaches mathematics. His
works published in English include
The Broken Dice, and Other
Mathematical Tales of Chance
(Chicago University Press, 1993)
and Mathematics and the
Unexpected (Chicago University
Press, 1988). His most recent
publication Is Lechaos
(Flammarion, Paris, 1994).
Human existence is fraught with
uncertainty. Who knows what
tomorrow may bring? But this does not pre¬
vent us from taking daily decisions, in our
private and public lives, which hold implica¬
tions for our future, for the future of our fam¬
ilies, our country or even in certain dra¬
matic situations, such as war the future of
humanity as a whole. These decisions, be
they good or bad, are taken on the basis of the
information available at the time.
This raises the question of whether bad
decisions may not be the result of inaccurate or
incomplete information. Would complete
knowledge of a particular situation allow a fully-
informed decision to be taken and its conse¬
quences to be predicted with virtual certainty?
The climatological model
The complexity of both natural systems and
those of human design means that the ideal
scenario a clear-cut situation leading to a
good decision, the effects of which can be
simply deduced is not only unattainable but
inconceivable.
An example of such a complex system is
provided by that increasingly disturbing cli¬
matic conundrum, the greenhouse effect.
Does human activity increase the level of
carbon dioxide in the atmosphere and, if so,
what are the consequences for the earth's cli¬
mate? From a purely scientific viewpoint, the
problem consists in studying the long-term
evolution of a complex system (the earth's
atmosphere) which is subject to a variety of
external influences (cosmic and solar radia¬
tion, interactions between the oceans and the
land masses, influence of human activity and
other life-forms, etc.). The difficulty is
twofold: one must first acquire knowledge of
the present state of the system and, once this
has been thoroughly established, one must
then predict its future evolution.
Let us start by examining the apparently
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
"A butterfly flapping
its wings . . . can unleash a
storm. . . "
'In order to predict
next year's weather
at a given spot one
would need a
network of
information from all
over the surface of
the globe.'
© SuperStock. Paris
simple notion of "the atmospheric level of
C02". Does this mean determining the level
of C02 at a particular point in the atmosphere ?
This requires a statistical analysis which reveals
certain major seasonal trends but leaves a sub¬
stantial margin of error, due to the uncertainty
of various meteorological variables. Or does it
rather mean, less arbitrarily, the total mass of
C02 present in the atmosphere at a given
point in time? There is no way of measuring
this directly and, in any case, there is no indi¬
cation that this approach would be any less
uncertain than the previous interpretation.
The only precise definition of this para¬
meter would be "the level of C02 at every
point in the atmosphere at any given
moment". For this definition to be opera¬
tional, it would have to be supplemented by a
mass of data on the direction and strength of
the wind, the temperature and humidity of
the air, and on the oceans. Only then could
we determine, more or less precisely, the
near future of the climatic system.
A definition which requires such a volume
of information is barely feasible in economic
terms. It is therefore right to wonder whether
we should not abandon the attempt to produce
a single figure to denote this persistently elu¬
sive quantity, the "atmospheric level of C02".
Would it not be sufficient to work on the basis
of typical figures, for example, from points at
intervals of 100 km across the earth's surface,
and at 5,000 m intervals of altitude?
The answer naturally depends on pre¬
cisely what we are looking for. In meteo¬
rology, this kind of precision would enable
forecasts to be made from one day to the
next. To forecast the weather two days ahead,
data must be gathered on a finer scale; and the
farther ahead we wish to see, the more sensi¬
tive and extensive the data base must be. The
American meteorologist Edward Lorenz has
remarked that a meteorological disturbance
which is allowed to develop unhindered may
double in magnitude within three days. In the
now famous image, a butterfly flapping its
wings in the Amazon basin can, if atmos¬
pheric conditions are favourable, unleash a
storm on the coast of Brittany a year later.
In other words, in order to predict next
year's weather at a given spot one would need
a network of information on the scale of the
butterfly, stretching all over the surface of the
globe.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
'Modern societies have become so complex that their situation can
no longer be encapsulated in a handful of figures. '
Let us now leave the domain of meteo¬
rology, with its short-term quantitative pre¬
dictions, and return to climatology, where
these phenomena are analysed qualitatively
over a much longer time-scale. Can we
achieve results using composite data, by con¬
sidering the "atmospheric level of C02" as a
mean annual value adjusted to take account of
random fluctuations? This is possible, but it
will not guarantee a significant improvement
in the degree of certainty of our predictions.
One can, of course, imagine large-scale
assessments of the thermodynamics of the
M an in the World, oil on atmosphere, which would enable definite
canvas by the Russian painter
Pavel Filonov (1883-1941).
conclusions to be drawn. The dynamics of
the earth's atmosphere are subject to great
variation from one year to the next, but a sta¬
tistical analysis over a longer period a cen¬
tury, say would reveal certain trends
However, the relatively short history of
climatology means that such analyses are not
available to us at present. In any case, it could
be that the atmospheric level of C02 in 100 or
200 years time may crucially depend on phe¬
nomena that are too subtle or too obscure to
have yet entered our calculations (for example,
the disappearance of certain animal species).
A stitch in time
The question of the accumulation of large
amounts of data crops up in most human sys¬
tems (economics, politics, the social sphere,
etc.). It was long believed that the state of the
economy, and public opinion, were dependent
on several major variables (including the rate of
inflation, unemployment, taxation and the bal¬
ance of trade) and that the art of government
consisted in maintaining these few indicators
within acceptable limits, or bringing them back
into line if they strayed beyond these limits.
In recent years, however, some industri¬
alized countries have been unable to reduce
their unemployment figures; and a President
of the United States suffered a severe elec¬
toral defeat during a period of economic
growth. It may therefore be wondered
whether we tend to represent problems in an
over-simplistic manner, and whether statis¬
tical data still have any value at all. Perhaps
modern societies have become so complex
that the reality of a given situation can no
longer be encapsulated in a handful of figures,
still less be controlled on such a basis.
In any event, we can be certain of one thing
in human affairs: that nothing is certain. One
might even wonder whether certainty is desir¬
able. To want to know everything about a given
subject is futile, an endless escalation into com¬
plexity. As Shakespeare's Hamlet knew, any
decision involves slicing through a Gordian
knot. Complete information will never be
available, and total certainty is impossible. But
there always comes a moment when one must
decide, when the search for further informa¬
tion is more of a hindrance than a help. Cer¬
tainty will not be forthcoming, either sooner or .
later, and we will never know for sure whether
we have made the right decision: a world in
which a different decision had been taken, a
world in which Chancellor Helmut Kohl, for
example, had not gone ahead with the reunifi¬
cation of Germany, would be so different from
the world we know that any comparison
between the two is meaningless.
One could almost say that the most
important skill in decision-making is knowing
when to decide.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Dragon Fly (1993-1994),
a watercolour by Diana Ong.
Frontiers of psychotherapy
by Saul FuksPsychotherapy has invented new forms of dialogue
SAUL FUKS,
an Argentine psychologist, is
director of the research
institute of the faculty of
psychology at the University of
Rosarlo, where he teaches a
specialist course in clinical
psychology for postgraduate
students.
I Psychotherapy that takes account of
I complexity must be based on a form of
dialogue that enables those involved to ques¬
tion their convictions and dare to explore
new approaches to reality.
This means that the psychotherapist must
agree to come down from his or her pedestal.
If psychotherapists really want their patients
to rediscover the capacity to assume respon
sibility for their lives, they must reject the
position of power their patients attribute to
them at the outset.
The therapeutic relationship tends to func¬
tion according to a socio-cultural pattern in
which the psychotherapist is regarded as the
heir of the shaman, the healer or the sage as a
person with special powers associated with a
vast and diffuse corpus of knowledge.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
'Psychotherapists have had to become explorers of the unknown
territories of existence.'
The state of desperation and extreme vul¬
nerability that induces people to consult a
psychotherapist makes them extremely
receptive to the image of the therapist as an
omniscient person with unlimited powers to
cure mental suffering.
Because people who suffer in this way feel
weak, they tend to entrust themselves fully to
the psychotherapist, who is regarded as
someone who can answer all their questions
(and thus, they hope, solve all their problems).
The only way to modify the balance of
power between the person who has all the
knowledge and the person who has none is to
redefine psychotherapy and first of all what
society expects from the psychotherapist.
A co-operative
relationship
Long before psychotherapy became a pro¬
fession, a variety of practices existed to put
right those who "deviated" from the social
norm, either by going too far (agitation, manic
states, madness) or not far enough (loss of
contact, unsociability, inertia).
"Madness" and "delinquency" are the
terms society uses to describe these devia¬
tions from the line it considers to be
"normal" at a given moment in its history. A
penal system and a security apparatus exist to
take steps against delinquency; machinery for
control and isolation exists to deal with mad¬
ness. On the other hand, society makes
allowances for those it regards as "visionary"
or "inspired" people whose ways of life are
accompanied by certain deviant forms of
behaviour.
In the 1960s questions began to be asked
about the power relationships that exist in
psychotherapy, paving the way for explo¬
ration of other aspects of the therapeutic rela¬
tionship.
This relationship gradually ceased to be
considered as a contract between a profes¬
sional possessing a specific body of knowl¬
edge and a patient ready to accept and absorb
that knowledge, but rather as the confronta¬
tion of two different, but equally valid, types
of knowledge. These forms of knowledge
may or may not coincide, but their degree of
convergence or divergence does not affect
the idea that the therapeutic relationship is by
nature co-operative.
This approach has led to a transformation
of the roles, identities, practices, context and
forms that exist in this type of relationship.
Today, those involved in psychotherapy are
no longer simply people telling a story, true
or false as the case may be, but have become
architects of their own lives.
Medicine Man (1994),
an acrylic painting by the
American artist Gayle Ray.
The complexities
of psychotherapy
This new approach to the alleviation of psy¬
chological distress has naturally transformed
the possibilities and the operational capacity
of psychotherapy.
Crises, troubles and disorders are no
longer considered as "risk situations" but as
"fields of possibility". This being so, a rich
array of intensely felt choices, decisions, and
hesitations between "future and possible"
worlds comes into play and obliges psy¬
chotherapists to invent new forms of dialogue.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
'The idea that each of us is the sum
of multiple identities makes it
possible for both therapists and their
patients to use all the
multidimensional aspects of their
personalities.'
When their inherent complexities are
taken into account, deviant symptoms and
forms of behaviour become part of a contex¬
tual dynamic based on language. Verbal
exchanges bring into play factors large and
small, subjectivity and intersubjectivity, and
all the building blocks of reality available to
the protagonist and to the person who is
seemingly a mere observer.
Before it began to explore these different
ways of being and their contexts, psy¬
chotherapy first had to re-examine the func¬
tion of "social control". This meant that ther¬
apists had to abandon the role whereby they
made a diagnosis based on a system of theo¬
retical knowledge and become explorers of
the unknown territories of existence. They
had to use their ignorance and their capacity
for surprise, in order to explore the mysteries
of what seems "obvious", "natural", and
"common knowledge".
This joint construction of a shared reality
involved the creation of new mechanisms: a
form of dialogue in which the questions are
more important than the answers; an atmos¬
phere of co-operation conducive to the
"Two equally legitimate forms
of knowledge, which may or
may not coincide". Above, Two
Men (1993-1994), a
watercolour by Diana Ong.
" Verbal exchanges bring into
play the building blocks of
reality. . . ." Below, a
computer-generated ¡mage
(1994) by Frank Collyer.
exploration of possible futures and ways
leading to them.
The "essentialist" approach whereby per¬
sons are considered as possessors of an iden¬
tity was based on the coherence and perma¬
nence of a uniform "mode of existing". The
idea that each of us is the sum of multiple
identities, on the other hand, makes it pos¬
sible for both therapists and their patients to
use all these complex and multidimensional
aspects of their personality.
This is not a purely theoretical question:
multiple identities also define our possibilities
and limits in the worlds of the emotions, the
intellect and action. What people allow or
refuse to allow themselves to think, feel and
do is closely linked to the structure of their
identities and to the degree of flexibility, cre¬
ativity and reflection that it allows, and to
their possibilities of further development.
Psychotherapy has become a field in
which all those involved can explore and dis¬
cover their resources in order to redefine
their lives.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The case of the disappearing
dinosaurs
" I s evolution the result of a
pre-established scenario or a
chain of fortuitous events?"
by Gianluca Bocchi
and Mauro Ceruti
The earth's natural history has known many a chapter
of accidents
GIANLUCA BOCCHI,
of Italy, is a member of the
Association for Research into
Knowledge and Learning (ARCA),
Milan. He Is the co-author (with
Mauro Ceruti) of Origin! di storie
(1993; The Origins of the Future,
Adamantine, London, 1994).
MAURO CERUTI,
of Italy, is professor of genetic
eplstemology at the University of
Palermo. His works published In
English include Constraints and
Possibilities, The Evolution of
Knowledge and Knowledge of
Evolution (Gordon and Breach,
New York, 1994). He is the co¬
author (with Gianluca Bocchi and
Edgar Morin) of Un nouveau
commencement (Seuil publishers,
Paris, 1991).
26
Why did the dinosaurs disappear? This
question has intrigued human imagina¬
tion ever since the first fossils of these enor¬
mous prehistoric animals related to the rep¬
tiles were discovered nearly two centuries
ago.
Until now natural historians have tried
above all to marshal arguments to show the
inevitability of the story of the dinosaurs, or
at least of its major turning points and
episodes. In this scenario the disappearance
of the dinosaurs to make. room for the long
chain of mammals from which we emerged
was a natural development.
In terms of Darwin's theory of the sur¬
vival of the fittest, whereby rival organisms
are pitted against each other in an environ¬
ment containing limited resources, there was
a conflict between the dinosaurs and the
mammals. The latter won the day because,
despite the terrifying power of their adver¬
saries, the future was on their side. As warm¬
blooded creatures, mammals were more
adaptable to changing climate, and since they
were smaller, they were more agile and had a
greater capacity for brain development. Thus
the laws of evolution gradually tipped the bal¬
ance in favour of the mammals and con¬
demned the dinosaurs to extinction.
Current research into the extinction of
species has demolished this theory. We now
know that mammals probably had hardly
anything to do with the disappearance of the
dinosaurs, which may have been caused by a
planet-wide crisis in the biosphere. The
mammals inherited a biosphere brutally
impoverished by a great catastrophe, due
perhaps to the impact of an enormous
asteroid, or fragment of a comet, that crashed
into the earth. The history of evolution
would have been quite different without this
unforeseen event, which did not amplify
existing trends but overturned everything
that had gone before and created new rules.
An unforeseen disaster
Mammals did not appear after the dinosaurs
but at the same time as them, at the beginning
of the Mesozoic period (after another major
crisis in the history of the biosphere). In fact
mammals and dinosaurs lived together on
earth for about 150 million years, and there is
no indication that during this very long
period there was any gradual extension of the
ecobiological territory of the mammals into
that of the giant reptiles. On the contrary, it
was the mammals who lived what might be
called a clandestine existence, preferably at
night on the edge of areas occupied and cov¬
eted by the dinosaurs. In the vivid words of
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Contrary to what was once
thought, "mammals probably
had hardly anything to do
with the disappearance of the
dinosaurs."
the American palaeontologist Alfred S.
Romer, they were "the rats of the Mesozoic".
Ten million years elapsed after the extinc¬
tion of the dinosaurs before the mammals dif¬
ferentiated into forms as varied as bats and
whales. By that time the emergence of the
primates, which would eventually give rise to
the human species, was not very far away.
Without this turn of catastrophic and
unusual events some 65 million years ago, the
rules of coexistence between mammals and
dinosaurs might have continued indefinitely.
Of course, a catastrophe of the same kind
might have happened later, but there is no
reason to say that it would have occurred in
the millions of years that have gone by since.
So it is easy to imagine other worlds just as
plausible as ours, in which the continuing
domination of the giant reptiles would have
blocked the evolution of mammals, hindered
the multiplication of species and certainly
prevented the appearance of primates and
hominids. This latter event is of major impor¬
tance in natural history, but it is in no way a
foregone conclusion programmed in the bio¬
logical and structural characteristics of mam¬
mals and dinosaurs.
Yehuda Elkana contrasts two kinds of
interpretation of history that he calls respec¬
tively the tragic and the epic. The tragic
interpretation regards the unfolding of his¬
torical events as inevitable. This being so, the
question that historians must answer is
"How did what was due to happen actually
happen?"' They must find the necessary and
sufficient conditions that explain how the
inevitable came about. In relation to the pre¬
sent, history must be rewritten by linking
the facts, the stages and the stops and starts in
a smooth linear progression which ends
coherently and logically in the present
moment. In this connection, the French
philosopher Henri Bergson spoke of truth
moving backwards.
The epic interpretation, on the other hand,
is based on the principle that everything that
has happened might have happened differ¬
ently. In this view, the necessary conditions
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
are not as such sufficient, and the question
asked by historians is: "Why did it happen in
that way, given that the events could have
taken an entirely different turn?"2 With a sce¬
nario like this, "even the past evolves," as Aldo
G. Garganti has rightly pointed out. The past,
but even more the present and the future as
they connect with the past.
The Time Traveller (1993),
acrylic on canvas
by the Brazilian painter
Fernando Barata.
Chance and necessity
These two scenarios for explaining the evolu¬
tion of mammals are good illustrations of the
contrast between a tragic scenario and an epic
scenario. Many other important events and
decisive changes that occurred in the history
of the biosphere before and after the disap¬
pearance of the dinosaurs lend themselves just
as well to this double explanation: from the
extinction of certain species and the appear-
'It is easy to imagine other worlds
just as plausible as ours, in which the
continuing domination of the giant
reptiles would have blocked the
evolution of mammals and prevented
the appearance of primates and
hominids.'
anee of eucaryote cells (those of higher animal
and plant organisms) from simpler and more
"primitive" cells (bacteria), on up to those of
Homo sapiens, endowed with an articulate lan¬
guage that even his most advanced hominid
cousins probably did not possess.
Is the present state of the biosphere the
result of chance or necessity? Is its evolution
the result of a complex project that follows a
rigorously pre-established scenario which it
is up to us to analyse and describe? Or is it the
result of a chain of fortuitous events that can
be described in detail but do not form part of
the framework of logical reasoning that we
have become used to through classical
physics? If we could go back through the his¬
tory of life step by step, revisiting all the crit¬
ical stages of evolution, disregarding what has
really come to pass, and going through all the
decisive turning points again, would we
always end up in worlds with more or less the
same characteristics as our own, or in dissim¬
ilar, even radically different, worlds? That is
the great and decisive question that specialists
in evolution are asking themselves today.
When we consider a turning point in nat¬
ural history that led to a certain result, we can
certainly explain why the change took one
form rather than another. But in most cases
there are not sufficient reasons, at best the tip
of an iceberg atop an invisible mass of facts
whose contingent nature cannot be reduced
to the laws of determinist logic and the calcu¬
lation of probabilities, yet which play an
essential role in the creation of the forms,
structures and laws of our biosphere.
There have been two great revolutions in
our intellectual tradition. The first was the
exploration of space begun when, as a result
of the work of Galileo, Copernicus and
Newton, we turned away from the idea that
the earth is at the centre of the universe. The
second, associated with the work of Darwin,
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
"Ten million years elapsed
after the extinction of the
dinosaurs before mammals
differentiated into forms as
varied as bats and whales."
was the challenge to the anthropocentric
view of the world. Only now are we begin¬
ning to see that these revolutions opened up
two worlds to human thought, the first of
which did not necessarily lead to the second.
The Copernican revolution and the
advances of seventeenth-century science
imposed a rigorous approach. The subject of
scientific research had to be disencumbered
of anything that might lead to a mistaken or
ambiguous interpretation of the results.
Isabelle Stengers has made a good analysis of
the kind of rationality and logic associated
with this process. It is the rationality of the
experimenter, which leads to the creation of
laboratory conditions that eliminate all para¬
sitic elements so that the facts "can immedi¬
ately and non-theoretically impose their own
reading as long as no prejudice clouds the
observer's mind."3
From this point of view the only facts
worth the name are those obtained in perfectly
controlled experimental conditions. The ability
to repeat the experiment is an indispensable
condition. Science can only be based on the
repeatable, and, therefore, on generality.
'The appearance of new life structures
and dimensions is linked to a succession
of unique and non-repeatable events. '
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Darwinian revolution and the ques¬
tioning of our traditional conception of time
are not just a follow-on of the "disanthro-
pocentrism" of the universe begun by
Copernicus, Galileo and Newton, any more
than they are mere temporal extensions of
the history of the universe. At a deeper level
they constitute a revolution in our relation¬
ship to knowledge which necessitates a dif¬
ferent approach to the idea of rationality. The
naturalist sees that in world history the
appearance of new life structures and dimen¬
sions is also linked to a succession of unique
and non-repeatable events. For the naturalist,
"facts are positive in the sense that they pose
and impose problems. They cannot be
accepted as such; they must be examined in
the conditions in which they occur."4
In the rarefied atmosphere of the labora¬
tory it is impossible to go back to the dawn of
time and reconstitute the impact of the
asteroid which doubtless led to the extinction
of the dinosaurs. Naturalists must patiently
decipher the chain of events that led to the
present state of the biosphere and at the same
time construct plausible alternative scenarios.
By exploring these possible worlds, they can
hope to reconstitute the complex tangle of
the causes of our universe, the result of both
chance and necessity.
1. Antropología della conoscenza, Yehuda Elkana,
Romc-Bari, 1989, p. 9.
2. ibid., p. 9.
3. Le coeur et la raison, L. Chertok, I. Stengers; Payot,
Paris.
4. ibid.
I n the 16th century, the Copernican system demonstrated
that the earth is not the centre of the universe but revolves
around the sun with the other planets.
»>J3jwii;
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Logic, cultures
and individuals
by Magoro h
Maruyama
a u
I narmony,
1 a collage on the theme of
| peace by the contemporary
3 Indian artist V. Balu.
I The second half of the twentieth cen-
I tury has been characterized by polit¬
ical, social and cultural movements toward
heterogeneity and fragmentation. After the
Second World War, many new independent
nations won freedom from colonial subjuga¬
tion. In the 1960s ethnic movements
appeared in the U.S.A. More recently there
have been subnational separation movements
in Czechoslovakia, Yugoslavia and several
other countries.
All these movements sought a national,
ethnic or cultural identity which had been
suppressed or threatened. These reactions
were necessary and good, but they created
their own unexpected trap: they tended to be
separatist; and they tried to standardize and
homogenize individuals within their group.
But newer trends have appeared. Massive
migrations for political or economic reasons
have increased, and professionals and experts
cross national borders for other reasons.
Most major countries now contain a large
percentage of immigrants and resident for¬
eigners. Heterogeneity has become inter¬
woven and interactive within each society.
Furthermore, foreign foods, dress and music
have become accessible to those who do not
travel to foreign countries. The individual's
"ego identity" no longer consists in being one
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
thing, but in a unique pattern of combination
consistent with his or her mind pattern.
Below, Dancing Maenads, a
fresco by the Italian painter
Giulio Romano (1499-1546) in
the Palazzo del Te in Mantua.
Opposite page, Chinese
polychrome terra-cotta
statuettes of dancers (Tang
dynasty, 7th-10th centuries).
Fallacious assumptions
Some assumptions of the social sciences
today are becoming obsolete. Examples of
these fallacious assumptions are:
1) each culture is perfect and it is better
not to change it;
2) all "normal" individuals in a given cul¬
ture are homogeneously acculturated;
3) babies are born with a blank mind, to be
filled with culture;
4) a culture is a mentally healthy environ¬
ment for all its normal members;
5) social change is traumatic to all persons;
6) cross-national migration increases anx¬
iety;
7) contact with many cultures makes the
individual lose his or her identity.
These fallacies stem from the belief that
there is only one true logic.
However, heterogeneity is necessary and
desirable in biological, ecological and social
processes. This applies also to logical types.
Some social scientists who have looked into
the question have found that: there are many
logical types which vary from individual to
individual within each culture or social group;
any logical type found in one culture can be
found in other cultures, i.e., these logical types
exist across cultures; cultural differences con¬
sist in the way in which some type becomes
dominant and influences, transforms, sup¬
presses, utilizes or exploits non-dominant
types; it is possible for babies to be born with
individually different logical types; individuals
whose logical types are non-dominant cope
with the dominant type in various ways:
finding a niche to avoid the dominant main¬
stream; camouflaging their own type; con¬
sciously switching back and forth between
their own type and the dominant type;
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
repressing their own type into the uncon- Even though there can be as many logical
scious and reactivating it under favourable cir- types as there are individuals, the following four
cumstances; repressing it irreversibly; types and their combinations account for about
becoming a rebel or reformer; emigrating. two-thirds of the individuals in most countries.
H-type l-type S-type G-type
homogenist heterogenist heterogenist heterogenist
hierarchical isolationist interactive interactive
classifying randomizing stabilizing change-generating
opposition independence absorption exploration
one truth subjective poly-objective poly-objective
competitive uniquing co-operative cogeneratlve
'The individual's "ego-identity" no longer consists
in being one thing but in a unique pattern of combination
consistent with his or her mind pattern. '
H-type individuals try to standardize
everything, seek universal principles, rank-
order things, put things in neat categories,
look for opposites, place things between two
opposite poles, believe in one truth, compete
with others, and think that one's gain is
someone else's loss, and therefore in order to
win one must make someone else lose.
I-type individuals rebel against homo¬
geneity, look for freedom from interference,
seek self-sufficiency, caprice, uniqueness and
subjectivity, and believe that if many people
work together their efficiency decreases.
Pollution is a result of many people living
together, and if everyone went to the moun¬
tain and grew his or her potatoes, there would
be no problem.
For S-type individuals, things cause one
another in cause-effect loops, that is to say,
the effect comes back to the cause directly or
indirectly through other elements. Individual
differences make co-operation possible,
while sameness breeds competition and war.
Heterogeneous elements interact to maintain
a pattern, and interaction is mutually benefi¬
cial. In binocular vision, the differences
between two images enable the brain to com¬
pute depth. Likewise, different points of view
among many people are useful in computing
invisible dimensions.
G-type individuals are similar to S-type
individuals, except for their belief that inter¬
action generates new patterns.
People in different logical types do not
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
necessarily disagree. They may agree, but
their point of agreement may be based on dif¬
ferent assumptions, and therefore they may
face problems later. For example, several
people may agree that decentralization is
good. H-type persons may agree because the
whole country is seen as homogeneous or
standardized, and nothing is lost by dividing
it. I-type persons may agree because they see
each part of the country as independent, and
it makes sense to decentralize. S-type and G-
type persons may agree because they see het¬
erogeneity, but with the assumption that dif-
"ferent parts would naturally interact for
mutual benefit.
Thus agreement does not necessarily
mean that the same logic is used. One must
be aware of different logical types in order to
avoid later problems. Illusory agreement is
dangerous because later disagreement makes
one think that the other person was insincere
or lying. Consequently it is important to be
aware of the differences in logical types.
Unawareness of differences in logical
types may make people doubt one another's
personal integrity. For H-type persons, per¬
sonal integrity consists in adhering to absolute
principles regardless of situations. I-type per¬
sons stick to their own principles regardless
of what other people say. The way in which
persons of S-type and G-type logics act
depends on the situation. Persons of different
logical types may thus consider one another
to be unethical.
Cultures and logical types
In each culture, a certain logical type
becomes dominant and influences, trans¬
forms, suppresses, utilizes or exploits non-
dominant types. But all logical types exist in
each culture, even though some of them may
be hidden, camouflaged or repressed. For
example, during the period when Germany
and France were dominated by H-type
Gothic architecture or Baroque music, indi¬
viduals with S-type or G-type logics found
their niche and outlet in painting.
When we compare cultures, we do so in
terms of the dominant type. For example, H-
type dominates in Sweden, while a mixture of
MAGOROH MARUYAMA
is an American epistemologist who
is a professor at the School of
International Politics, Economics
and Business of Aoyama Gakuln
University In Tokyo. Among his
published works are Mindscapes
In Management: Use of Individual
Differences in Multicultural
Management (Dartmouth
Publishing Co., 1994).
S-type and I-type is dominant in Denmark.
In Asia, Koreans show strong H-type char¬
acteristics, while Indonesia is strongly of S-
type. In Japan, SH type is dominant, while in
the United States, HI type is dominant. In this
sense, Danes are closer to Indonesians than
to Swedes, and Koreans are closer to Ger¬
mans than to Indonesians. The popular
notion of East/West contrast does not hold.
Each profession has a dominant type
regardless of countries. Accountants tend to
be of H-type, and painters tend to be of I, S
or G-type.
Which logical type is more
scientific?
Newtonian astronomy was of H-type. Nine¬
teenth-century thermodynamics, based on
independent movements of molecules, was
of I-type; early cybernetics in the 1940s was
based on the S-type; the cybernetics of the
1960s on a combination of types G and S.
Archaeological research in Japan has
showed that the Jômon culture, which began
11,000 years ago, had G-type characteristics,
and that the S-type was dominant in the Yayoi
culture which arose 2,300 years ago. The H-
type Yamato culture reached Japan via Korea
1,500 years ago, and this logic eventually
became the official dominant logic of the
ruling class, even though farmers still use S-
type logic and the merchant class which
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
emerged during the seventeenth century
practised G-type logic.
In pre-colonial African cultures, G-type
logics were practised. Oral traditions explic¬
itly stated that heterogeneity made co-opera¬
tion possible while homogeneity bred wars.
Communication
It is extremely difficult, if not impossible, for
persons who think using I, S or G-type logics
to communicate with those who use H-type
logic, because the H-type believes in its "uni¬
versal truth" and tries to reduce everything
into the limited dimensions of its thought
structure. As long as the result of the dimen¬
sion reduction is internally consistent, the H-
type person is convinced that it is the correct
interpretation even though it may miss the
point completely.
The dominance of the H-type logic in
many societies hampers a heterogenistic view
of cultures. This fact has many implications:
«"" many policies of standardization are based
'The suppression or non-utilization of
non-dominant logical types is a waste of
precious human resources. '
on the incorrect assumption that sameness is
necessary for peace and differences are the
cause of conflicts. Policies should be formu¬
lated to encourage heterogeneity and mutually
beneficial interaction between individuals;
'*" the suppression or non-utilization of non-
dominant logical types is a waste of precious
human resources;
'*~ current educational and vocational sys¬
tems are based on H-type logics. Individuals
of other logical types are disadvantaged or
excluded. This is a violation of equal opportu¬
nity in education and in employment;
w it is currently fashionable to compare cul¬
tures as if each culture is homogeneous.
However, non-dominant logical types exist
under the surface. The key to successful mul¬
ticultural management is to discover individ¬
uals of non-dominant types.
« until now, cross-national population
movements were interpreted in terms of
labour demand and supply, or professional
skill matching. However, many people
migrate for the purpose of logical type
matching. We can expect increased migration
for this reason.
¡*~ many people are unaware that their own
logical types are non-dominant and therefore
they are disadvantaged in education and
employment. More importantly, they may
feel uncomfortable, unhappy or frustrated
without being aware of the reason. It is
important for them to become aware of their
own logical types.
The American painter Jackson
Pollock (1912-1956)
demonstrates his "drip
technique"controlled
dribbling and spattering of
paint on canvas.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY BY FEDERICO MAYOR
'THE VOICE OF THOSE
WHO NEVER SPOKE'
The suffering of the indigenous communi¬
ties that were subjugated and deprived of
their most elementary rights the right to
cultural identity, to the land of their ancestors, to
their language, freedom and beliefs is one of the
disasters of recent centuries that must be etched
in the collective consciousness alongside slavery
and other affronts to humanity. It happened slowly
and silently and it has lasted to the present day in
the form of social prejudice and economic struc¬
tures, of education systems and political power
machines that perpetuate discrimination and
neglect.
The Indigenous Initiative for Peace inspired
and guided by Nobel Peace prize-winner Rigob¬
erta Menchú is a sign of how far the situation of
indigenous people has changed in recent years.
The concept of "initiative" implies that these
peoples have decided to make a dynamic response
to the many problems, old and new, that beset
them; that they have the will to identify, study and
seek solutions to them that are consonant with the
times; that they are prepared to undertake this task
without falling back on imported models that dis¬
tort their cultural heritage and without repeating
the mistakes of the past; that they are resolved to
shape their own destiny.
This attitude is in itself a revolution, one of dia¬
logue and indocility after the centuries of silence
and submission that these communities have suf
fered. It is a creative and peaceful revolution,
which presupposes a huge effort to achieve edu¬
cational renewal and social transformation, access
to full citizenship and participation in decisions
great and small, and which will henceforth make a
difference to their shared lives. Rigoberta Menchú
has summed up that hope in these lines:
A long darkness obscured my face;
long are my dreams, immense my hopes.
But the dawn will come, brightness will come.
To the utmost height of the azure vault shall
soar
the voice of those who never spoke.
Joining the two hemispheres
In many countries, particularly those of Latin
America, the lot of the indigenous peoples is a lin¬
gering blight on the progress of democracy. On
the one hand, there is the continuing problem of
their incorporation into the life of the nation,
under conditions of full and effective citizenship.
On the other, these peoples, after falling prey to
historical iniquities (such as those that occurred in
America in the sixteenth century) went on to
suffer at first hand from political strife and civil or
international wars whose effects were added to
those of exclusion and marginalization.
So it is important to highlight the peace-
seeking ingredient of this Initiative because
without peace the political, social and economic
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
goals that these communities have set themselves
cannot be realized.
The construction of peace involves more than
efforts to prevent the outbreak of armed conflict.
It means removing the causes of individual and
collective violence that spark off wars in the first
place. Such violence may take many forms: at the
political level it emerges as oppression and
tyranny; in economic life, as exploitation and
poverty; in the social sphere, as exclusion and
intolerance. Any effort to establish a culture of
peace must be targeted at the roots of violence and
make a priority of communicating values, forging
attitudes and devising institutions that will extir¬
pate violence from human minds.
Industrial civilization and indigenous cultures
must engage in a dialogue that cannot fail to be of
mutual benefit to them. The former is the reposi¬
tory of a great deal of knowledge, particularly
technical know-how, but is short on wisdom; it
has lost a sense of human fulfilment. Peoples living
in precarious conditions of material development
still possess this wisdom and contact with nature,
but they lack the technological expertise that
abounds in the industrialized countries. To join
these two hemispheres of humanity is tantamount
to curing humanity of its hemiplegia. Still, these
material comforts and facilities do not suffice to
make us respect the natural environment and do
away with the most glaring injustices of our
society.
In the Pópol Vuh, the sacred book of the
Mayas, there are some verses laden with sym¬
bolism that tell how the first human beings were
annihilated as retribution because "they did not
think, did not speak with their Creator". Those
men and women, made of wood, had abused their
immediate surroundings and upset the natural bal¬
ance that united them with the cosmos. As a pun
ishment, the gods allowed the earth, the animals
and even household objects to rebel against them
and destroy them.
The revenge exacted by animals and even by
objects on the human beings who dominate
them a feature that exists in one form or another
in almost all cosmogonies is an allegory of the
woes that human beings may bring on themselves
through the misuse of power, especially the
Promethean might of the intellect. A noted leader
of the North American Indians, Chief Seattle, put
it like this in 1855:
"The earth does not belong to man, but man
belongs to the earth. Man has not woven the fabric
of life; he is but a strand of it. Everything he does to
the fabric he will do to himself. What befalls the
earth will befall the children of the earth."
A wealth of difference
We thought we had magic formulae to suit all situa¬
tions. As if all countries were uniform, and as if their
histories, their natural resources, their traditions,
their beliefs, their forms and styles of living were of
no account. As if it were possible to ignore the infi¬
nite diversity of individual lives, of the social, eco¬
nomic and cultural contexts in which people grow
up, of the ideas imparted to them, of their thoughts
and impressions, their states of mind, and so on. We
have forgotten the cultural dimension of personal
and collective development. Instead of believing
that wealth lay in diversity, we imagined that it was
uniformity which, at least in economic terms, ought
to prevail, forgetting that difference is wealth as
long as it unites us.
Knowledge of and respect for difference, full
receptiveness to others. May the diversity of cul¬
tures long continue, of those "hybrid and wandering
cultures", which, as Carlos Fuentes put it, are our
greatest our ultimate source of wealth.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Kirchgessner/Schuste © Explorer, Paris
f\J TIV T\ A the sleeping beauty of northeastern
V/Jjlll 1/lX Brazil by Joel Franz Rosell
Above, Olinda, with the city of Recife in the
distance.
Opposite page, traditional handicraft shops line
the Mercado da Ribeira, the former slave market.
JOEL FRANZ ROSELL,
of Cuba, is a journalist with the French radio station
Radio France Internationale. He also teaches Spanish-
American literature at the University of Marne-la-Vallée,
near Paris, and is the author of many children's stories.
38
The city of Olinda in north¬
eastern Brazil once wore its heart
on its sleeve. It owes its name to the
exclamation uttered by its Portuguese
founder when he saw its site for the first
time: "Oh linda situaçâo para se fundar
huma villa!" ("Oh what a beautiful
place for a city!"). Today it does not
reveal its charms so quickly. Visitors
who set out from Recife, the capital of
Pernambuco state, and drive through
seven kilometres of built-up area, will
not see on the skyline the eight unin¬
habited hills sweeping down to the sea
which so enchanted the sixteenth-cen¬
tury Portuguese colonizers of Brazil.
Only when they discover Olinda's
"high town" will they be able to appre¬
ciate this haven of peace on the doorstep
of bustling Recife. Then they will savour
the dialogue of palm trees, roofs and bel¬
fries, the admirable contrast between old
walls and luxuriant nature, between a
glorious sun and the pure blue sea. Only
then will they exclaim, like the Por¬
tuguese explorer of old: "Oh, what a
beautiful place. . . ."
SWEET AMI SOUK
Olinda was founded in 1537. It soon
became a magnet for the rich slave-
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Some of South America's finest colonial architecture
has survived in a city
that was once the capital of Brazil's sugar trade
owners of the plantations, who built on
the hillsides magnificent houses where
they could take refuge from the stifling,
insalubrious heat of the inland plains.
Churches and monasteries were built,
and the commercial infrastructures
required by the flourishing sugar and
slave trade began to be developed.
In 1612, when Brazil was the world's
leading sugar exporter, there were a
hundred-odd sugar refineries in
Olinda twice as many as there were in
Salvador, the capital. But the pros¬
perity of the northeast kindled envious
appetites, and the Dutch captured the
future province (capitanía) of Pcrnam-
buco. It was (luring the brief period of
Dutch occupation (1630-1654) that the
fate of Olinda was sealed.
First of all, the new arrivals set out
to modernize Olinda and turn it into a
port that could compete with Recife.
When the population rebelled they
were forced to abandon their plans. In
reprisal they put Olinda to lire and the
sword in 1631. A large number of six¬
teenth-century houses, churches and
monastic buildings, the fine flower of
colonial architecture, disappeared in
the flames.
The return of the Portuguese in
1654 coincided with the expansion of
Recife as a trading centre and a city,
and encouraged the rich land-owners of
Olinda to rebuild their city. They vied
with each other in building luxurious
houses, giving rise to a saying which
became proverbial: "People live better
in Olinda than at the king's court." But
rivalry between the merchants of Recife
and the Olinda sugar magnates led in
1710-1711 to a civil war which was won
by Recife.
This political blow took place at a
time when most of Olinda's architec¬
tural heritage had already been built.
Fortunately, the city's economic decline
was slow enough to enable the magnates
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
to complete the buildings they had
begun.
Although Olinda lost temporal
power, it became an important religious
centre. Between 1678 and 1823 it was
the seat of an archbishopric whose sem¬
inary, monasteries and schools became
the mainspring of religious activity in
northern Brazil. Two important events
(the modernization of religious educa¬
tion begun by Bishop Azeredo Coutinho
in the late eighteenth century and the
creation of a law faculty a few years
later) had such a great impact that
Olinda became known, with a certain
amount of exaggeration, as the
"Brazilian Coimbra".
GOXE WITH THE W I IN II
The visitor to Olinda who looks in the
city's churches and monasteries for
treasures accumulated over the cen¬
turies will look in vain. A handful of ves¬
tiges of these treasures can be seen in
the city's museums, but most of them
have mysteriously disappeared, possibly
40
recovered by their owners (to compen¬
sate for the lack of banks, rich families
entrusted their precious objects to the
protection of the churches).
The history of Olinda was also punc¬
tuated by a series of crises which opened
the door to the systematic pillage of pre¬
cious jewellery, paintings, furniture,
books and even ceramic tiles (azulejos).
Between the expulsion of the Jesuits in
1760 and the collapse into ruins of the
Carmelite monastery in this century as a
result of neglect, examples of vandalism
were legion. One prior removed a statue
of Our Lady of Mercy from its pedestal
and sold it to make money for himself.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
BRAZIL
OLINDA
Above, a house with a façade of enamelled tiles
[azulejos).
Opposite page above, the cathedral, the oldest
church in Olinda, was built around 1540.
Opposite page below, the Monastery of Sao Bento
(St. Benedict), entirely rebuilt in the 18th
century.
All the same, Olinda has suffered
less from the infidelity of its elites, the
negligence of its clergy, piracy and the
hand of time than it has from slapdash
restoration work carried out at the
beginning of this century, including
"improvements" made to the cathedral
in 1911 and the demolition of vestiges
of the Carmelite monastery by order of
the prefect in 1907.
A ¡NEW ACE
OE PROSPERITY
Fortunately, it was not yet too late when
the Brazilian government stepped in and
took the first steps to save Olinda's her¬
itage in 1937. The implementation of a
battery of judicious protection and
restoration measures in 1962, 1973,
1975 and 1980 was crowned on 21
March 1983, when the site and city of
Olinda were included on UNESCO's
World Heritage List. This marked the
start of a new age of prosperity for
northeastern Brazil's sleeping beauty.
There is much to admire in Olinda
OLINDA
LOCATION:
Olinda occupies a hilly coastal site, 7 kilome¬
tres from Recife, capital of Pernambuco State
in northeastern Brazil.
DESCRIPTION:
The city's 17th- and 18th-century layout has
survived almost intact, and many civil and reli¬
gious buildings are, by virtue of their architec¬
ture and rich decoration (wood carvings,
azulejos, silver work), remarkable examples of
Portuguese baroque art. A short distance from
the factories and skyscrapers of Recife, Olinda
still has the charm and enchantment of a city
of the colonial period.
LANDMARKS:
1537: Olinda is founded by Duarte Coelho
Pereira.
1631: The town is sacked by the Dutch.
1654: The Portuguese return and a long period
of reconstruction begins.
1678-1823: Olinda is the seat of an archbish¬
opric.
1800: A seminary is founded.
1811: A botanical garden is planted.
1828: The Academy of Legal Sciences is
founded.
1980: Olinda is declared a national monument.
1983: Olinda's historic centre is included on
Unesco's World Heritage List.
MAIN BUILDINGS:
Cathedral
Church of the Mother of Divine Grace
Carmelite convent and church
St. Benedict's monastery and church
Monastery of St. Francis and the church of
St. Mary of the Snows
Church of the Misericord
Church of St. John the Baptist
Church and monastery of Our Lady of
the Immaculate Conception
Archbishop's palace
Pernambuco Museum of Contemporary Art
(the former prison)
Many houses and other buildings decorated
with azulejos
Ribeira Market
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
today: the imposing façade of the
Carmelite church, the rustic grace of
the houses with their pastel-coloured
walls and Moorish balconies, the
restrained baroque of the monasteries
of St. Benedict and St. Francis, with
their magnificent interiors, their pre¬
cious wood furnishings, their frescoes
and their azulejos decorated with
designs that unexpectedly blend sacred
and profane themes. No visit to the city
is complete without a stroll through the
Ribeira market, where wood and clay
statues and paintings depict men who
were once sold there as slaves. And
Olinda would not be Olinda without its
tropical vegetation, its eternal garden of
trees palm and coconut, mango and
spondias, cinnamon and bread-fruit,
flame trees and banana trees.
Sometimes too the sleeping beauty
awakens and emerges from her tropical
torpor. There are explosions of joy at
carnival time, feast days and Christmas;
processions in honour of St. Antony, St.
Francis and the Sacred Heart take
place with time-honoured splendour,
memorable for African drumbeat and
spangled costumes.
In Brazil there is a tendency to con¬
trast Olinda and Ouro Preto, two jewels
of "classical" architecture that feature
on the World Heritage List. Ouro Preto,
the capital of the "gold cycle" in the
eighteenth century, is isolated in the
mountains of the hinterland. It is an aus¬
tere and imposing jewel, which seems to
have been hewn from an inhospitable
mountain-top. By way of contrast,
Olinda, capital of the "sugar cycle" is
the flower of the northeast, whose
corolla, as if modelled in clay soaked in
the juice of sugar-cane, straggles over
sunny hillsides rocked by the rhythm of
the sea.
If Olinda needed a patron saint, the
"Virgin of the Siesta" would be a good
choice. Not so much because of the
sleepiness encouraged by its peaceful
Above, Matriz church.
Right, traditional folk
dancing in an Olinda street.
streets barely disturbed even by bird-
song, its quiet gardens and the shadows
cast by its buildings, but because the
long sleep that for a century preserved it
from the sound and the fury of the world
also preserved it from the property spec¬
ulation and rampant urban growth that
have turned neighbouring Recife and
many old colonial towns into soulless
modern cities oblivious of their past.
Several suitors have tried to awaken
the sleeping beauty: students at the
beginning of the last century, holiday-
makers attracted by its deserted
beaches, geologists who dreamed of
turning it into a phosphate centre. They
all failed because they did not under¬
stand that only a kiss of love for its past
could work this miracle.
If Olinda lives from its heritage
today, it is not a dead or immobile city.
Craftsmanship, culture and tourism are
the main sources of income for its
youthful population of over 200,000.
Olinda could take as its motto an anony¬
mous graffiti drawn on an old wall on
Carmel Square: "Saudade do futuro",
nostalgia for the future. I
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
View of southeast
Mauritius, with
the town of
Mahébourgin the
distance.
MAURITIUS
by France Bequette
Paradise lost or
Paradise regained?
M
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
questions.
auritius emerged from the
Indian Ocean some eight mil¬
lion years ago, and since then many
animal and plant species some of
them unique developed there in
extreme geographical isolation.
The island lies some 800 kilo¬
metres southeast of Madagascar,
and, with Rodrigues, the Sey¬
chelles and Reunion, belongs to
the Mascarene group of islands.
Inland from a fringe of sandy
beaches, peaceful lagoon and coral
reefs, is rugged and mountainous
terrain. On this volcanic island of
idyllic greenery and flowers,
people of a variety of origins and
religions live on good terms. The
climate is temperate, although
between December and April
there may be occasional violent
cyclones.
Meteoric economic growth
based on sugar cane, tea and
tourism has brought full employ¬
ment to Mauritius and turned it
into what its people like to call the
"tiger of the Indian Ocean".
Although the government has been
concerned about the environment
since the 1970s, it took a demon¬
stration of international solidarity
by conservationists before part of
the island's animal and plant her¬
itage could be saved. Today it is
fair to say that Mauritius has
become a veritable laboratory for
the restoration of endangered
species.
PREDATORS AND HEALERS
When people arrived in Mauritius
in the 16th century the stage was
set for an ecological disaster. The
dodo (Raphus cucullatus) and the
solitaire (Pezophaps solitaria), two
big flightless birds, were soon
exterminated, and subsequent
changes in habitats, deforestation
for arable land, reforestation with
non-endemic trees and the intro¬
duction of certain animals from
outside led to the disappearance
of several species of birds , of giant
lizards, snakes, tortoises and
countless insects and plants.
Until Mauritius became inde¬
pendent in 1968 it was visited or
ruled in turn by the Portuguese,
the Dutch, the French and the
British, each of whom introduced
animals which in some cases
became pests and preyed on
endemic species. Examples
include the Timor deer (Cervus
timorensis) and the wild boar (Sus
scrofa), which damage the forest
and hence the island's birdlife
the deer eat the indigenous
plantlife, and the boars uproot
young plants. Monkeys (Macaca
fascicularis) and brown rats
{Rattus norvegicus) raid nests and
eat birds' eggs and nestlings, mon¬
gooses {Herpestes auropunctatus)
and feral cats (Felis cattus) eat
birds at all stages of development.
The Mauritius kestrel (Falco
punctatus), the island's only
endemic bird of prey, has been
almost wiped out, partly because
its recently fledged young are easy
prey since they spend much time
on the ground in the first few days
after leaving the nest, and partly
because the birds have been vic¬
tims of the pesticides which are
widely used on the island. Only
two pairs were known to survive in
the 1970s and attempts were
made to get them to breed in cap¬
tivity. Between 1984 and 1991
235 young kestrels were released
in the wild, and the goal of around
a hundred nesting pairs should
now be within reach. The pink
pigeon (Columba mayeri) was also
threatened with extinction.
Pigeons sent to the Island of
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Lime kilns in
Mahébourg.
;&
Jersey and monitored by special¬
ists with support from the Jersey
Wildlife Preservation Trust
(founded by the British naturalist
Gerald Durrell) reproduced and
were reintroduced in Mauritius. A
site for raising threatened birds
has since been established in
Black River Gorges National
Park. The large echo parakeet
{Psittacula eques echo) has also
been saved in the nick of time.
Only a dozen of these birds were
left in 1986.
BLACK RIVER GORGES
NATIONAL PARK
The creation of Black River
Gorges National Park was an
important step in nature conserva¬
tion. Proposed by the World Con¬
servation Union (IUCN) in 1973,
the project finally came to
fruition in 1994. The Park covers
6,574 hectares in the southwest
of Mauritius, where the land rises
to an altitude of 817 metres. Here
too endemic plantlife is being sti¬
fled by exotic plants such as the
Chinese guava (Psidium cat-
tleianum), a bush imported from
Brazil that monopolizes space and
light in the undergrowth, privet
(Ligustrum robustum) from Sri
Lanka, the Madagascar traveller's-
tree {Ravenala madagascariensis)
and "Framboise marron" (Rubus
alceifolius) a thorny bramble that
forms dense thickets and clambers
up host trees, often several metres
high.
In a carefully fenced-off corner
of the park workers have pulled
out all the exotic plants by hand.
This is a frustrating job because
the weeds will grow back if only a
small fragment of the plant is left
in the ground. This was an urgent
job, however, for 80 per cent of the
island's 900 plants, 300 of which
are endemic to Mauritius, are
threatened, and only about a dozen
specimens survive of 51 of them.
The Ministry of Agriculture
has received financial aid from the
World Bank and technical assis¬
tance from the Mauritian Wildlife
Appeal Fund (MWAF), a non-gov¬
ernmental organization that in
1986 took in hand the islet of Ile-
Aux-Aigrettes, which lies offshore
from the town of Mahébourg.
IUCN botanist Wendy Strahm
drew up a plan to eliminate all
animal and plant intruders, while
endemic plants were grown in
nurseries. The extraordinary
"Café Marron" (Ramosmania het-
erophylla), a single specimen of
which survived, was propagated
from cuttings at the Royal Botanic
Gardens at Kew in the United
Kingdom.
THE DARK SIDE
OF PARADISE
Despite these spectacular suc¬
cesses, Mauritius has not avoided
the problems caused by rapid
development and a big increase in
tourism. The island's 426 indus¬
tries consume large quantities of
water (up to 5,000 m3 per day)
and discharge effluent often
untreated into the rivers. Some
60,000 tonnes of fertilizer a
season, or 600 kilos per hectare,
are used in sugar cane production,
which occupies about 90 per cent
of the arable land. More than
1,000 tonnes of pesticides are sold
each year to farmers, and
Alice and the
dodo, an
illustration from
Alice's Adventures
in Wonderland
(1865) by Lewis
Carroll. A
flightless bird
native to
Mauritius, the
dodo was hunted
for its flesh and
became extinct
around 1560.
according to a report on the "State
of the Environment in Mauritius"
prepared for the Rio Earth
Summit, these products threaten
the quality of drinking water and
the lagoon. Measures taken by the
government include renovating and
extending the sewer system (which
in 1994 collected only 18 per cent
of all effluent) and building treat¬
ment plants and outfalls into the
sea.
More than 300,000 tourists
swell the million-strong population
of Mauritius every year. In 1990
tourism represented 3.1 per cent
of GDP. It has been estimated
that the island's maximum poten¬
tial for tourist reception is about
one tourist per three inhabitants.
The figure of 400,000 tourists
projected for the year 2000 will
require a 15 to 40 per cent growth
in the island's hotel capacity. This
is an incentive for promoters
attracted by the temptation of
easy money to cover the northern
and western coasts with concrete,
without waiting for the results of
"Environmental Impact Assess¬
ments" carried out by the author¬
ities. Each year a million tonnes of
sand are scooped from the lagoon.
At Pomponette, for example, the
coast has retreated by five metres
in the last five years. The authori¬
ties have restricted sand mining to
specific sites, and a project to
restore the beach is underway.
Although 800 tonnes of solid
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
YOUTHFUL HANDS TURN
WASTE TO GOOD USE
household and industrial wastes
are collected every day, they are
disposed of in open dumps, and
plastic bags and bottles litter the
countryside and the shore.
Another problem is that of waste
borne to the coast by winds and
currents. In 1992 there were only
two recycling plants for glass,
paper and cardboard. In the last
few years eight official dumps
have been or are being rehabili¬
tated, and the construction of two
sanitary landfill sites is planned.
In Mauritius, as elsewhere, pro¬
tection of the environment means
that everyone must give a hand.
Some forty environmental organi¬
zations registered with and sup¬
ported by the Ministry of the Envi¬
ronment are working hard to
inform and educate the popula¬
tion, particularly children. There
are many environmental clubs,
sponsored by a wide range of
bodies including village councils,
and young people's and women's
associations. Hopefully, the
younger generation will remember
that they live in a corner of par¬
adise and will do what their elders
have left undone.
FOR FURTHER
INFORMATION
contact the Department of the
Environment, Ministry of the
Environment and Quality of Life,
Ken Lee Tower, Line Barracks
Street, Port Louis, Mauritius.
Tel.:(230)212 60 80;
fax:(230)212 66 71.
A pink pigeon
{Columba
mayeri), a bird
native to
Mauritius.
UNESCO's Division of Youth and
Sports Activities recently com¬
missioned a survey of 120 youth and
student organizations around the
world to find out if they were par¬
ticipating in waste recycling activi¬
ties. Twenty responses were received
from Europe, 17 from Africa, 7
from Asia, 6 from Australasia and
the Pacific and 6 from North and
South America. They described a
raft of original projects and should
provide ideas for anyone interested
in working for the environment.
The Packwach Tools Production
Centre in Uganda has formed several
groups of unemployed young men
and women. The women collect
material and twine to make carrier
bags and fishing nets, while the men
collect steel scrap and learn black-
smithing skills. The experience and
training can help the young people
obtain professional credentials in
construction, mctalwork and joinery.
A little further to the south, in
the Republic of Tanzania, many
youth groups have also organized
metal-working shops. The Tanzanian
Railways and abandoned sisal plan¬
tation factories are important sup¬
pliers of scrap metal. A British orga¬
nization, Tools for Self Reliance
U.K., is helping the young metal¬
workers by providing refurbished
second-hand equipment. From 1990
to 1993, 25 blacksmith units pro¬
duced some 300,000 tools and
implements.
The Gecco Environmental Centre
in Namibia has both educational
and cultural aims. Working with
local schools, the Centre gathers
scrap and litter of all kinds and
makes large sculptures of animals
such as rhinos. The sculptures have
a metal rod structure wired together
with mesh stuffed with non-perish¬
able materials and decorated with
sea shells and coloured glass. The
children learn to avoid waste and
enjoy the creative art work.
In Papua New Guinea members
of the 'Tumi Tugetha" (You and me
together) Youth Group collect and
export non-ferrous scrap metal.
With the proceeds from their first
shipment they bought a mini-alu¬
minium crusher-bailer from Aus¬
tralia to process aluminium drinks
cans, and now they would like to
acquire a furnace to smelt the alu¬
minium and make castings. Group
members receive a small allowance,
which strengthens motivation.
On the Japanese island of
Shikoku the attitude to recycling is
more philosophical hut no less real¬
istic. Taiyo To Midori No Kai (The
Sun and Green Association) works
with mentally handicapped people
on the principle that "in order to
save the future of mankind, we must
drastically change our attitude to
life. To know how to be contented
and to give thanks for what we
have that's why we chose recycling
goods as our project".
FOR FURTHER
INFORMATION
contact Arthur Gillette,
Division of Youth and Sports
Activities, Unesco,
1, rue Miollis, 75015 Paris, France.
Fax: (33-1) 45 67 14 99
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
WHEAT PIPS RICE
The Consultative Group on International
Agricultural Research (CGIAR) reports
that wheat is on the way to becoming the
number one food crop in developing
countries, surpassing rice. Formerly con¬
fined to the temperate and subtropical
zones, wheat can now be grown as a
winter crop in warmer climates. Asia har¬
vested 217 million tonnes in 1994, or
eight million tonnes more than Canada,
the U.S.A., Europe and Mexico combined
(209 million tonnes). A grain whose
advantages include resistance to disease
and pests, low cost, rapid growth,
genetic diversity and flexibility, wheat is
making a major contribution to increased
food security.
COUNTDOWN
FOR THE INDOCHINA TIGER
The World Wide Fund for Nature (WWF)
reports that the Tiger of Indochina is the
most threatened of the five remaining
sub-species of tiger. One animal is being
killed each week by poachers, and if the
current rate of destruction continues
the Tiger of Indochina will be extinct in
ten years' time.
FRANCE SETS ITS SITES FOR EUROPE
By its "Habitats" directive of 21 May
1992 the European Union is seeking to
preserve biodiversity in Europe by estab
lishing a network of sites containing nat¬
ural habitats and plant and animal species
of interest to member countries. In France
1,700 sites have been identified, covering
a surface area of 7 million hectares. After
evaluation by the National Museum of
Natural History, a group of the sites will
be selected and submitted to the Euro¬
pean Commission for inclusion in the net¬
work, known as "Natura 2000".
ENVIRONMENTAL EDUCATION
FOR THE 21ST CENTURY
In November 1995 the Organization for
Economic Co-operation and Development
(OECD) published a report on "Environ¬
mental learning for the 21st century"
which describes how a network of edu¬
cators, researchers and policy-makers in
OECD countries have co-operated in local
initiatives to resolve environmental prob¬
lems and develop attitudes and skills to
manage future developments. It cites
three main challenges that lie ahead:
making environmental education a main¬
stream activity, providing teachers with
the skills and competence to teach and
develop environmental education, and
finding a place for environmental educa¬
tion in the core curriculum.
"Environmental Learning for the 21st
Century", OECD, Paris, 1995. 115 French
francs, ISBN 92-64-24478-6. By post:
VPC OECD, 2, rue André-Pascal, 75775
Paris Cedex 16. Tel.: (33-1) 45 24 82 00;
fax: (33-1) 49 10 42 76.
SCIENCE DISCOVERS THE SAOLA
The Vu Quang ox (Pseudoryx nghet-
inhensis), an animal previously unknown
to science, was discovered in the Vu
Quang (Viet Nam) Nature Reserve in June
1994. Local people had long known of the
animal, which they call the Saola, and kept
its horns as trophies. While gathering data
on the Saola a few months earlier, a
research team sponsored by WWF, IUCN
and Viet Nam's Forest Ministry came
across another undescn'bed animal, the
giant muntjac (Megamantiacus vuquan-
gensis), a large ruminant. Since these dis¬
coveries, the Vietnamese government has
enlarged the Vu Quang reserve from
16,000 to 60,000 hectares and imposed
logging and hunting bans.
PLANTS THAT CLEAN TAINTED SOIL
The salts of selenium, a metalloid present
in certain kinds of soil, can pose a threat
to aquatic wildlife if they infiltrate into
water courses. When California (U.S.A.)
horticulturist Delbert Herschback
noticed that his irrigation water was
leaching this toxic substance from the
soil he came up with the idea of growing
plants such as mustard, which absorb
the salts into their tissue. Other plant
species consume metals such as mer¬
cury, zinc, lead, copper and cobalt.
Euphorbiaceae, which absorb nickel, and
other metal-scavenging plants are cur¬
rently being studied by researchers in the
U.S.A. and the United Kingdom in the
hope that plants will prove easier and
cheaper to use than current excavation
and reburial techniques used for dealing
with tainted soils. What's more, the
nickel can be recovered by harvesting and
burning the plants.
OLD PROBLEM, NEW COOKER
Fuelwood is an increasingly scarce com¬
modity in Zimbabwe. To help the many
households that use this energy source,
the government has launched a pro¬
gramme to promote a cooker widely
known as the "chingwa" (bread) which
needs only a single log to prepare three
meals, bake bread and heat water to bath
the children. Women, who were at first
reluctant to use the cookers, have been
associated with the project. While they
provide the raw materials for the cooker
and its chimney (bricks and earth from
ant-hills), the Energy Ministry provides
the hot-plate, the grill and other acces¬
sories. All that has to be done is
assemble and decorate the cooker.
,J- j'y». HhiiW ' .\ V *-' W
mmEñwmi
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
r
^
fi> Isabelle Leymarie talks to
V
With his rich tonal range, "Chico" (Arturo)
O'Farrill is the most famous composer-
arranger of Cuban and Latin jazz. He began
working with the leading Havana bands in
the 1940s and later worked in New York with
the Afro-Cubans ("The Afro-Cuban Suite",
recorded with Charlie Parker, Flip Phillips and
Buddy Rich), Dizzy Gillespie ("Manteca
Suite"), Benny Goodman ("Undercurrent
Blues"), Stan Kenton ("Cuban Episode"),
Glenn Miller, Count Basie, Clark Terry, David
Bowie and Gato Barbieri. He has also
composed film music and classical works,
including "Three Cuban Dances" and
"Symphony No. 1".
He was born in Havana to a Cuban
mother and an Irish father and spent a few
years in an American military academy ("my
father thought it would keep me out of
trouble") where he played trumpet in the
school band and took his first steps In jazz.
Back in Cuba, he studied law for a year, but
music won the day. In 1943 he joined
Armando Romeu's Orquesta Bellamar and at
the same time led an experimental band with
a friend of his, guitarist Isidro Pérez.
In 1947 he moved to New York where he
composed scores for a host of musicians, and
in the early 1950s toured the United States
with his own band. He then spent two years in
Havana and went to Mexico in 195S where he
composed "Aztec Suite" and married the
Mexican singer Guadalupe Valero. By 1965
he was back in New York.
Recently he formed a big band with which
he has recorded Pure Emotion, one of his
most accomplished records, and composed a
piece for trumpeter Wynton Marsalis, which
was premiered on 30 November 1995 at New
York's Lincoln Center.
CHICO O'FARRILL,
one of the great figures of Latin Jazz
ISABELLE LEYMARIE
is a Franco-American musicologist.
How did you get started in music?
Even when I was a child I was fascinated
by Cuban rhythms, although mine wasn't a
very musical family. At military school I fell
in love with the recordings of Tommy Dorsey,
Artie Shaw and Glenn Miller. But it was
when I began to study Bunny Berigan's
trumpet solos and transcribe arrangements
that I found my real calling, writing music,
not playing because I had decided that I
couldn't do both at the same time.
But back in Havana, I still played with
René Touzet, then with the Armando
Romeu Jr. Bellamar band, the best Cuban
jazz band at that time. We played the clubs
until 1915, and I was lucky, thanks to the
encouragement of more experienced musi¬
cians, to be able to do more and more com¬
posing. I also studied harmony and orches¬
tration with Felix Guerrero.
Was a lot of jazz being played in
Cuba at that time?
Yes, probably because of the American
tourists. Clubs would usually hire two
bands, a big band with dancers, singers and
comics that accompanied the revues, and a
"b"-band that played Cuban music. The
brass sections were smaller than in the
United States, and bands used stock
arrangements that they bought ready-made.
The musicians' phrasing wasn't good. There
wasn't much exchange with American
jazzmen, and jazz records were scarce.
A few of us got together and formed a
small band and gave free rein to experimen¬
tation. When bebop took off in the United
States, I was immediately struck by Charlie
Parker and Dizzy Gillespie. I spent hours
studying their phrasing and trying to find
harmonies on the piano. Cuban music
seemed simplistic in comparison.
Were you able to turn your knowledge
of bebop to good use in a big Cuban
band?
Yes. The Montmartre Club asked Isidro
Pérez to form a band. We got together a
fabulous big band, the Isidro Pérez
Orchestra, with the best of Cuba's musi¬
cians. We did all our own arrangements just
the way we wanted. But our modern ideas
were often too much for the audience, who
had a hard time dancing to the music. A
year later, the Montmartre closed its doors,
and I was out on the street.
So I made up my mind to try New York,
where I carried on studying harmony with
Bernard Wagenaar, Stephan Wolpe and Hal
Overton. Then, after a hard spell financially,
Benny Goodman took me on as an arranger.
Does Latin jazz call for any special
know-how?
first have to know the jazz rhythms
and Caribbean rhythms a guaguancó is
different from a guajira or a bolero and
avoid discordance. Cuban music tends to
phrase farther behind the beat than jazz.
But it's a question of ear and experience
and instinct, of course. I remember when we
recorded the "Afro-Cuban Jazz Suite" with
the Machito band in 1948, the producer,
Norman Granz, hired the trumpeter, Harry
Edison. But Edison was an honest guy and
realized in rehearsals that he wasn't used to
that kind of phrasing. He decided to bow
out, so Granz called Charlie Parker, who,
extraordinary musician that he was, got the
idea right away.
É What do you think of Latin jazz today?
There's a lot of new talent. When I made
Pure Emotion, my son Arturo Jr. , who is a
pianist, recruited the musicians. They were
all incredibly talented! The media encourage
cultural mixing and the spread of Latin-Amer¬
ican rhythms, but I'm not expert enough to
get involved with kinds of music I don't know.
My roots are still in Cuban music. There, and
in jazz, I know what sounds good.
You hadn't made a record for years.
Why did you make Pure Emotion?
I've spent a lot of time writing music for
the market, which gives me a decent living,
but a producer talked me into making this
record. Pure Emotion, the title piece, is a
slow ballad that's got hardly anything Latin
in it. Variations on a Well-known Theme is
based on the theme of Cucaracha and has a
very advanced arrangement with complex
harmonies and a number of transformations.
I wrote it in Mexico in 1965 and I've played
it in Los Angeles and elsewhere. I put Get
me to the Church on Time a Broadway
standard to a mambo beat. There's a lot of
variety on the record.
Has Latin jazz got a future?
-Yes. It's music that's constantly regener¬
ated by new input. If Latin jazz died out, it
would mean that American jazz was also
dying, and the Western world would be in
trouble!
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
on
children
and violence
the screen
by Nils Gunnar Nilsson
NILS GUNNAR NILSSON,
a Swedish publishing and media
specialist, is a member of
Unesco's Executive Board.
Agrowing number of countries are con¬
cerned about violence on the screen
on television or in computer games
and a number of meetings have been held on
the subject in different parts of the world. In
March 1995 a world summit on children and
television was held in Melbourne (Australia),
and an international conference in Lund
(Sweden) in September was totally devoted
to violence on the screen and the rights of the
child.
At Melbourne more than 500 producers,
researchers, media executives and other
experts took part in a number of panels. A
projjosal by Anna Home, Head of BBC Tele¬
vision Children's Programmes, for a "chil¬
dren's television charter" led to a wide-
ranging debate. The proposal suggested cer¬
tain minimum requirements such as balanced
programming, broadcasting in regular slots
when children are able to watch, a wide
diversity of content, and sufficient funds.
After heated discussion, the charter was
revised into a new seven-point version which is
now considered official. The first point
stresses that children have the right to high-
quality programmes which are specifically
made for them and "which do not exploit
them". This is a reference to the fact that
children have become a steadily growing con¬
sumer group in the expanding world of chil¬
dren's television. This was highlighted by
Ellen Wartella, professor of communication
at the University of Texas, who pointed out
that we have learned that children are a
"special" audience, with "special psycholog¬
ical needs and social interests, requiring us to
tailor media production to them". There has
been "a virtual explosion of research studies
on children's reactions to television," she
added, "and we know how to make pro¬
grammes that both entertain and educate
children."
Professor Wartella went on to discuss an
alarming phenomenon, "the increasing com¬
mercialization of children's lives." "The past
twenty-five years have seen media industries
move their target downwards," she noted,
"first to pre-adolescents, then to children in
primary school and younger, and the vehicles
for this have been television and videos.
Today young children all over the world, even
pre-schoolers, are increasingly the target of
commercial messages. Young children's cul¬
ture is a culture dominated by television and
toys." With the rise of privatized commer¬
cial television all over the world, thanks to
satellite and cable, a "remarkably commer¬
cialized media culture for children" is being
created, at a time when public broadcasting
is under attack and declining.
At the Lund conference, more than 140
delegates from twenty-five countries took
part in or listened to the five panel discus¬
sions, ranging from "reports from the
research front line" to artistic depictions of
violence "From Shakespeare to Stephen
King". In one session representatives from
the media were confronted with defenders
of children's rights; another session focused
on the Convention and its implementation,
and the final panel asked the question:
Where do we go from here?
One panelist, ambassador Thomas Ham-
marberg (co-chairman of the United Nations
Commission which is monitoring the imple¬
mentation of the Convention), argued strongly
for a joint UlNESCO-UNICEF commission
which would organize a clearing house where
research and other information could be col-
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
VVS4WSW-
lectcd and distributed, and possibly publish
an annual blacklist of the names of the media
companies with the worst record of violence
on the screen. The Swedish Minister of Cul¬
ture, Ms Margot Wallström, who chaired the
summing up panel, supported the idea of a
clearing-house and was willing to give finan¬
cial support at the outset.
UNESCO will be publishing a full report of
the Lund Conference later this spring. The
ideas that were put forward there are also
reflected in the conclusions of an interna¬
tional survey, Violence in Broadcasting
Worldivide, prepared for UNESCO by the
Broadcasting Standards Council in Britain,
which will also be published in the near
future.
It was clearly stated in Lund that the
answer to the problem of growing violence on
the screen is not censorship. This conclusion
is repeated in UNESCO's recent far-reaching
World Report on Culture and Development.
Freedom of expression is a fundamental
freedom. The best way to cope with excesses
in violence, and even pornography is to use
the power of the consumer. In a free market
economy, where most media are commer¬
cially based, the viewer-consumer actually
has the last word, at least theoretically. You
can push the button and say "no thank you.
We don't buy products which are advertised
in too violent a media environment". If there's
anything big companies are scared of, it's a
bad image.
Ultimately, it's a matter of consciousness
raising. Twenty or thirty years ago, most
people did not know the word "ecology".
Today it's on everybody's lips. Jo Groebel,
professor of mass communication at the Uni¬
versity of Utrecht (Netherlands), and a world
authority on research into violence in the
media, has made the following comparison.
"In the 1960s and 1970s we thought we had
got rid of toxic substances when we dumped
them out of sight in rivers and oceans. Later
on, we learned the hard way that poisonous
waste does not disappear; it reappears just
where wc never expected it."
Perhaps the time has come to start
thinking in terms of "media ecology". fl
Drawing by Terry Sirrell.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
As it was... ^-*
THE UNESCO COURIER
February 1958
The divorce between science and 'culture'
by Bertrand Russell
There was a time when scientists looked askance at
attempts to make their work widely intelligible. But,
in the world of the present day, such an attitude is no
longer possible. The discoveries of modern science
have put into the hands of governments unprecedented
powers both for good and for evil. Unless the
statesmen who wield these powers have at least an ele¬
mentary understanding of their nature, it is scarcely
likely that they will use them wisely. And, in democ¬
ratic countries, it is not only statesmen, but the gen¬
eral public, to whom some degree of scientific under¬
standing is necessary.
To insure wide diffusion of such understanding is
by no means easy. Those who can act effectively as
liaison officers between technical scientists and the
public perform a work which is necessary, not only for
human welfare, but even for bare survival of the
human race. I think that a great deal more ought to be
done in this direction in the education of those who
do not intend to become scientific specialists. The
Kalinga Prize is doing a great public service in encour¬
aging those who attempt this difficult task.
In my own country, and to a lesser degree in other
countries of the West, "culture" is viewed mainly, by
an unfortunate impoverishment of the Renaissance
tradition, as something concerned primarily with lit¬
erature, history and art. A man is not considered une¬
ducated if he knows nothing of the contributions of
Galileo, Descartes and their successors. I am convinced
that all higher education should involve a course in the
history of science from the seventeenth century to the
present day and a survey of modern scientific knowl¬
edge in so far as this can be conveyed without techni¬
calities. While such knowledge remains confined to
specialists, it is scarcely possible nowadays for nations
to conduct their affairs with wisdom.
There are two very different ways of estimating any
human achievement: you may estimate it by what you
consider its intrinsic excellence; or you may estimate it
by its causal efficiency in transforming human life and
human institutions. I am not suggesting that one of
these ways of estimating is preferable to the other. I
am only concerned to point out that they give very dif¬
ferent scales of importance. If Homer and Aeschylus
If^z
had not existed, if Dante and Shakespeare had not
written a line, if Bach and Beethoven had been silent,
the daily life of most people in the present day would
have been much what it is. But if Pythagoras and
Galileo and James Watt had not existed, the daily life,
not only of Western Europeans and Americans but of
Indian, Russian and Chinese peasants, would be pro¬
foundly different from what it is. And these profound
changes are still only beginning. They must affect the
future even more than they have already affected the
present.
At present, scientific technique advances like an
army of tanks that have lost their drivers, blindly,
ruthlessly, without goal or purpose. This is largely
because the men who are concerned with human
values and with making life worthy to be lived, are still
living in imagination in the old pre-industrial world,
the world that has been made familiar and comfort¬
able by the literature of Greece and the pre-indus¬
trial achievements of the poets and artists and com¬
posers whose work we rightly admire.
The separation of science from "culture" is a
modern phenomenon. Plato and Aristotle had a pro¬
found respect for what was known of science in their
day. The Renaissance was as much concerned with the
revival of science as with art and literature. Leonardo da
Vinci devoted more of his energies to science than to
painting. The Renaissance artists developed the geo¬
metrical theory of perspective. Throughout the eigh¬
teenth century a very great deal was done to diffuse
understanding of the work of Newton and his contem¬
poraries. But, from the early nineteenth century
onwards, scientific concepts and scientific methods
became increasingly abstruse and the attempt to make
them generally intelligible came more and more to be
regarded as hopeless. The modern theory and practice
of nuclear physicists has made evident with dramatic
suddenness that complete ignorance of the world of sci¬
ence is no longer compatible with survival. M
The above is the text of an address delivered by Bertand Russell,
on receiving the Kalinga Prize for the Popularization of Science,
at UNESCO Headquarters on 28 January 1958.
J
511
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
ij j i «««x^m i : i **j r.
INTERNET
gopher.unesco.org
or
http://www.unesco.org
press releases, addresses, fax, telex and electronic mail numbers of Unesco's regional offices,
National Commissions and Unesco Clubs, the directory of Unesco databases and information
services, colour images of the Japanese Garden and other architectural sites at Unesco
Headquarters, as well as works of art such as Henry Moore's reclining sculpture.
To contact
THE UNESCO (pURIER
directly with suggestions and comments, type:
unesco/courier@unesco.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
IN THE NEXT ISSUE
WHAT IS RACISM?
T
INTERVIEW WITH HENRI ATLAN
HERITAGE: THE GOLDEN CITY OF SALAMANCA
ENVIRONMENT: CLEAN TECHNOLOGIES FOR TOMORROW
i UNESCO
OUR1ER
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
be sacred tire
lieraeu uitb
MAURICE BEJART
M 1205 - 22,00f
Each month, essential
reading for an
understanding of the
problems of today and
tomorrow
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine published in 30
languages and read by hundreds of thousands of people in 120 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission of furthering "universal
respect for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms. ..without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
]]>
</page>
</document>
