<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="104975eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ART
M 1205 -9612- 22,00 F
HERITAGE: TAI NATIONAL PARK
ENVIRONMENT: LAKE FERTÖ:
A WILDLIFE HAVEN IN CENTRAL EUROPE
UNIir 0 MHSOOHh IJ FRANCE Uff «U1IRALI» UT.M MLQ1UM »1« UHMM: CSV 7b -
ui« M.*o swiramju» *«.» «rutkuhh; n 10 «HUM: «RM
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ENCOUNTERS
To our readers
Since our regular "Encounters" feature first appeared,
on the inside front cover of the July 1989 issue, your tal¬
ented and imaginative contributions have abundantly
illustrated the range of the creative cross-fertiliza¬
tion that the feature is intended to encourage.
The invitation we issued then is still open to all our
readers: "Send us a photo (of a painting, a sculpture,
or a piece of architecture) which you regard as a good
example of cultural cross-fertilization. Alternatively,
send us pictures of two works from different cultural
backgrounds in which you see a striking connection
or resemblance. Please send a short caption with your
photos. Each month we will publish one of your
contributions."
In anticipation of many more rewarding encounters.
THE EDITORS
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (ÔURIER COI"^^
DECEMBER 1996
^M 1 ^^B H f **i
i^MÉ
¡^t--^	" ~-
'Átíít
!fu
S.(TßP^^ m* yfa}
I ^B flr^ -
WW - ^*^*^i? ¡
From traditional ceremonies to modem
performance art and happenings, from body
painting to virtual reality, the ephemeral
is a recurrent feature ofsacred and
profane art (pp. 6-37).
EPHEMERAL ART
Month by month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
Swimming against the tide byEzio Manzini
Sculptures in snow and Ice
A moment of grace by Stephen P. Huyler
Africa's women muralists
Navajo paintings in sand
Dancing with masks by Margaret A. Stott
A bridge to the creative past by Luke Taylor
Cosmetics and culture by Viviane Baeke
Art's back-to-the-land movement by Gilles A. Tlberghien
Theatre and performance art
Modern murals
Working notes byNils-Udo
Installation art by Michael Archer
Eventful happenings
Apocalypse now by Michel Conil-Lacoste
From ¡mage to environment by Florian Rotzer
Consultants: Jacques and Katel Lélut
Tai' National Park (Côte d'Ivoire).
A bastion ofthe equatorialforest rich in
biological diversity (p. 44).
6
9
10
14
15
16
18
19
22
26
27
28
30
34
35
36
Commentary Federico Mayor 38
GREENWATCH
LakeFertö by France Bequette
HERITAGE 44
Tai National Park byNimrod Bena Djangrang
PORTRAIT
Bohdan Khmelnytsky bylaroslavlsaievych 47
LISTENING
Isabelle Leymarie talks to Bernard Maury 48
ANNIVERSARY
1100 years ago: Hungary's appointment with Europe by Péter Deme 50
Cover: Pleats Please (1996), a creation by Japanese couturier Issey Miyake presented at the Pitti
Palace during this year's "Time and Fashion" Biennale in Florence (Italy).
© Marcello Bertonl. Florence (Italy)
THE UNESCO Q>URIER DECEMBER I99Ô
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
tb& unesco
Courier
^*^49thYEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15,
France.
Fax: (01) 45.68.57.45
Internet: unesco.courier@unesco.org
DIRECTOR
Bahgat Elnadi
EDITOR-IN-CHIEF
Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition: Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 01.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: (Tel. 01.45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Beim (Tel. 01.45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 01.45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: (Tel. 01.45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian: Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kang Woo-hyon (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxian (Beijing)
Bulgarian: DragomirPetrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Katrl Himma (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Aliyu Muhammad Bunza (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax: 01.42.73.24.29
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. 01.45.68.45.65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel. 01.45.68.49.19)
Customer service: Michel Ravassard,
(Tel. 01.45.68.45.91)
Accounts: (Tel. 01.45.68.45.65)
Shipping: Daniel Meister (Tel. 01.45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel.: 01.45.68.45.65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request, Unsolicited manuscripts can¬
not be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco
or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on
maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier
is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco,
7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox),
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition.
Indian Head Inc., Ill West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell
and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - DÉCEMBRE 1996
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844- DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure:
Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z.I. Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malsherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 12-1996-0PI-96-554 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 50-51.
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
An endleSS quest by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
Readers of this issue may well be struck by a paradox: an obsession with
the ephemeral has been a permanentfeature of human history.
Death has always been there to remind us of the unchanging order of
things: that whatever has a beginning must sooner or later come to an
end. Whence the urge to look beyond temporary things and seek the
eternalthrough religion, philosophy, and art. Some cultures have been
built on the aspiration to transcend time, to construct enduring
monuments and give tangible shape to the absolute. The temples of
ancient Egypt, Greece and Rome bear witness to this ambition, as do
the cathedrals of Christianity and the mosques of Islam.
Animism, Hinduism and Buddhism have a diametrically opposite
approach. For them, acceptance of life's impermanence is a way of
bringing eternity into betterfocus. Mural paintings, ceremonial masks
and mándalas have meaning only because the ephemeral is a pathway to
the timeless. In a sense, therefore, an ancient temple and a sacred dance
are two routes leading towards the same destination: achievement of
the absolute via experience of the transitory.
Modernity has wrought a disturbing change in representations of the
ephemeral. By shutting its eyes to transcendence, it consigns the
ephemeral to the void.
Imagine (March 1990)
a 6-metre-high ice sculpture by
Christian Claudel, Francis Cuny
and Lionel Muntrez at Fairbanks,
Alaska (U.S.A.).
THE UNESCO QjURIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
SWIMMING AGAINST THE TIDE
BY EZ10 MANZINI A quest for duration in societies whose only
permanent feature is change
Design is inseparable from its age.
I But its role may also be to break
away from the spirit of the age and
herald a new era.
Two hundred years ago, the seemingly sta¬
tic pre-industrial world began to stir. Slowly
at first, and then with growing speed, it
embarked on an unstoppable quest for nov¬
elty. Right from the start, industrial design
was one of the main driving forces behind this
process of acceleration, for reasons that were
both ethical (the new versus the old in the
name of progress) and mercantile (the new
replacing the old in the name of commerce).
Design was both a product and a component
of its time. How do things stand today?
It is often said that acceleration and tran¬
sience are the defining features of our age. But
today we wonder where all this speed is tak¬
ing us. Perhaps design should swim against
the tide and contribute to this questioning.
Perhaps it should promote profundity and
duration in what seems to be an increasingly
superficial and constantly changing world. In
other words, perhaps design should emphasize
the "solid side" of a changing world.
Language pollution
Freed from its inertia, matter lends itself to
unlimited transformation. The physical world
no longer seems to be a solid vehicle for per¬
manent meanings, but a constantly changing
fluid. At the same time, progress in informa¬
tion technology and communications opens
up a new dimension of human experience that
is liberated not only from matter, but from
the constraints of space and time. Even the
certainties of memory are called into question
by the greater possibilities of "fiction", of
juggling with information and images to cre
ate a potentially infinite variety of "virtually
real" pasts, presents and futures.
These developments are both fascinating
and disturbing. We cannot yet fully gauge their
human and social implications. The only thing
we can really be sure of is that the changes
underway are of far-reaching importance. New
cultural instruments must be created to con- Andy Warhol-Robot
(1994), by Korean artist
Nam June Paik.
THE UNESCO ^JURIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
.«-<_
kbove, The "Ara" halogen
lamp designed in 1988 by
Philippe Starck (France) and
produced by Flos.
lop, Ecriture de feu ("Writing
with fire", 1996) by the French
sculptor Yann. Oil burners
float on the surface of Lac de
Nariay, a lake in France's Jura
department.
front a phenomenon whose consequences will
be mainly negative unless it is kept under con¬
trol. We can already see this today. What ought
to be communication, and therefore exchange,
has led to a new form of isolation, and what
ought to be information has become no more
than background noise. We discover that
words and images are products that are "con¬
sumed" and produce rubbish that eventually
pollutes our language.
But matter that seemed to have dissolved in
the ever-changing flow of information reap¬
pears elsewhere in our experience. The rubbish
accumulated by our societies is matter that
has again become dense and inert, trapped in its
own heaviness and duration. It is used matter,
stripped of its original meaning, that invades
our space and our time as tangible evidence of
the irreducible physicality of our environ¬
ment. We discover that the fluid world of
information and "fiction" needs powerful
stage machinery in order to function, that all
this machinery consumes and is consumed,
and that it all forms a huge entropie system
which uses resources and creates waste.
Nobody today would deny this obvious
fact. We talk anxiously about "the environ¬
ment problem", and ask ourselves questions
about how to promote "sustainability", in
other words about how to put an end to the
war that the human race has more or less
unwittingly declared on its environment. We
cast around for solutions. Some turn to an
idealized past that will never return; others
look just as naively to an increasingly tech¬
nological and dematerialized future. As we
have just seen, in the current economic and
cultural context, dematerialization is more
than offset by the increase in consumer goods.
The solution to the problem the creation of
a more harmonious relationship between
humans and their environment is not and
cannot be purely technical.
And so we move between two contrasting
worlds: a virtual world without substance or
history, and an environment in which cum¬
bersome and durable rubbish is accumulating.
Living matter
Of course it is very tempting to turn away
from the problems of the environment and
take refuge in the virtual world. But to do so
is to forget that between the immaterial world
of information and the world of "dead mat¬
ter", or rubbish, there is a world of bodies,
things and images which change in ways and at
a pace determined by our innermost nature as
human beings biological beings who live in an
ecosystem, and cultural beings who constantly
try to make sense of things. And this world of
THE UNESCO QïURIERB DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
matter which is "living" in both a biological
and a semiotic sense is a world which needs
permanence as well as change, repetition as well
as novelty, and solidity as well as fluidity.
The world of living matter consists of
change and permanence. It could be thought of
as a fluid with a solid component. Today we
should fix our attention on the solid compo¬
nent. It is being eroded by change, but it
remains the basis of our search for meaning
and by its very nature it curbs consumption
and reduces waste (both physical and semi-
otic). It is here that we shall find the answer to
the basic questions concerning our cultural
future (the construction of meaning) and our
existential future (the preservation of living
conditions).
Permanence in change
In the past, the idea of solidity was based on
the permanence of things, on a duration of
forms and relationships which seemed intrin¬
sic to them (the inertia of matter and social
conventions). Today that solid world, which
was the basis of our models for interpreting
reality, has ceased to exist.
i creation by Belgian
fashion-designer Fred Sathal.
Otars in stripes. Hervé
Léger's ready-to-wear
collection, presented in Paris
in October 1996.
It has been superseded by a fluid world, in
which the permanence we so much need can no
longer be taken for granted but must be
acquired by a deliberate act of the will. "Solid¬
ity", when it exists, is the result of a project.
Some may feel that there is not much point
in seeking solidity in a world fascinated by
promises of immateriality. For myself I prefer
to think that the best way to make sense of
things is to rediscover and revalue their core of
solidity. In doing this we should reject nos¬
talgia and naivety, and remember that the solid
world of the past can now be no more than a
memory. The kind of solidity (of products,
relationships, ideas) that we can seek today is
that of forms stabilized in a context of per¬
petual change.
Since this solidity is no longer an intrinsic
quality of things, it must be the result of a
deliberate endeavour to define what must
endure so that everything else can change with¬
out losing meaning and without destroying
the planet. If it takes that course, design will
belong to its time, and the meaning it acquires
will help to shape the future.
8
THE UNESCO IpURIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
I
ft ' '
ü
'
mom
. .
raP
Symphonie pour une aurore boréale
(Symphony for an Aurora Borealis,
March 1992), an Ice sculpture measuring
4 metres high and 6 metres long by
Christian Claudel and G. Pazzola,
Fairbanks, Alaska (U.S.A.).
Sculptures in snow and ice
Above, French sculptors Christian Claudel
and Francis Cuny prepare blocks of ice for
Banquise (Ice Floe, March 1991) in
Fairbanks, Alaska (U.S.A.). Right, Francis
Cuny smoothes down Future Migration
(1995), also in Alaska. With Brigitte
Herbetz, these two artists from the
Vosges region of eastern France run an
association named Ephémère, which
seeks "to enhance the present moment"
via snow and ice sculptures that are also
shaped by the elementscold, rain and
sun. Since January 1988 they have won
many sculpture competitions throughout
the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
A MOMENT OF GRACE
BY STEPHEN P. HUYLER
Millions of Indian women decorate their houses with sacred
paintings that fade within hours
I n nature around us, beauty is fleet¬
ing; it has no permanence. Droplets of
rriorning dew on a leaf, the billowing
I shapes of clouds, the dancing move¬
ments of a bird, the soft eyes of a calf, the smile
of a young child these all change quickly. They
are not frozen in time. Why should art be
frozen, be still? So much of our art here is made
only for the moment. It is beautiful right now.
The artist knows it, and the gods surely know
it. The earth just for this moment is more beau¬
tiful because of it. What more is needed? It
changes as we change, as the day changes, until
again we make something of beauty."
These words, spoken many years ago by
the famous Indian dancer Rukmini Devi, give
insight into one of the fundaments of Indian
creativity: the ephemeral. In India all existence
is believed to be in constant transition. Every¬
thing is in a cyclical state of creation and
destruction, of birth, death, and rebirth. There
is no permanence all is thought to be in bal¬
ance with its opposite. In a country where the
present is layered and infused with untold
generations of the past, history is viewed by
most as irrelevant.
Aside from the Indian concern for social
and cultural traditions, the documentation and
preservation of the ancient is primarily a West¬
ern invention. Even the most substantial of
structures, temples and palaces built and carved
of stone were deserted in the centuries before
the modern era when their original purposes
were no longer deemed pertinent. Tradition is
important only as a means for coping with the
present, not as a way to canonize the past. The
maintenance of inherited traditions enables the
observer to ensure balance and harmony in his
or her life.
Most traditional art is in some way tied to
ritual. The central motivation of many Hindu
rituals is darshan, literally translated as "view¬
ing" or "eye contact". Darshan is that sacred
moment in which the devotee experiences direct
contact with the deity. In Hinduism, darshan
is achieved through the spiritual presence of a
god or goddess who is believed to manifest
materially within a natural or man-made object.
Divine spirit may be invoked to enter any puri¬
fied container a sacred tree or rock, a sculpture
of stone or bronze, or even, in some cases, the
body of a priest or supplicant. To facilitate this
process, both object and devotee must undergo
preparation.
An ornately carved sculpture that has been
in worship for a thousand years will be
adorned each day with fresh milk and butter,
honey, sandal paste and ash and dressed anew
in clean garments and strings of heady-scented
blossoms. The store rooms and treasuries of
major temples are filled with magnificent tex¬
tiles and jewellery in order to provide the
appropriate change of appearance to fit each
day. In this way even the most permanent of
objects is inseparably tied to the transitory.
Each time it is viewed, its presence is different.
Left, walls in Orissa State
are generally painted in rice
paste, a pigment that is clear
when applied but turns white
as it dries.
10 3 Q>WTHE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
vv
The very material of many sacred sculptures
is ephemeral. The most basic of elements, clay,
is considered sacred in India. Hindu legends
abound with descriptions of the magical prop¬
erties of clay (mitti). From earth all creation is
fashioned and to earth it eventually returns.
Mittiis the body of the Mother Goddess, the
Sustainer of Life. It is easily procured and
sculpted and, when purified by fire or other
sacred elements, it becomes an appropriate ves¬
sel for facilitating darshan with the gods.
Once each year for special festivals in eastern
India, potters apply clay to structures of straw
and sticks to create large and elaborate sculp¬
tures of the gods that become the principal
images in community shrines. On festival day
all the sculptures are carried in procession to a
nearby river and allowed to dissolve in the cur¬
rent. The deity has been honoured, the devotees
have received their darshan, the god is requested
to return to the heavens, and the sculptures no
longer have any value. Ephemeral images of the
day of the year this
woman paints a different
design on the brick surface in
front of her home in Tamil
Nadu state, southern India.
Usually the painting only lasts
an hour or two before being
erased underfoot.
gods are created for specific festivals and rituals
throughout India.
Protection
from evil spirits
Most Indian society and ritual is centred on
the home. The deity that protects the home
and all of its inhabitants is generally viewed as
feminine, most often the Goddess Lakshmi,
who governs household activities and ensures
the health and welfare of each family member.
Her worship, usually conducted by women,
is considered essential to the maintenance of
harmony and prosperity. Throughout India
women regularly paint their homes with dec¬
orative designs sacred to the goddess. They
begin by covering the surface with a new layer
of wet clay mixed with cow dung. Upon this
"canvas", they paint designs handed down
from mother to daughter through countless
generations. Almost all of them create a sacred
THE UNESCO ^>URIER DECEMBER I99Ó
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
In Patna (Bihar) a potter
sculpts a clay image of the
sun-god Surya that will be
worshipped for two weeks at a
temporary shrine before being
immersed and dissolved in the
nearby Ganges River.
Berelow, women in Madurai
(Tamil Nadu) make auspicious
rice-paste drawings on their
doorsteps during Pongal, the
Tamil New Year festival
celebrated by cooking new rice.
decoration at least once a year, but some paint
a new one every single day!
The style and form of decoration is gov¬
erned by the traditions of each subculture. In
most areas the painting is applied to the front
of the house on or around the main entrance.
The door is considered the means of entry
into the home for good and evil spirits as well
as household members. Consequently, the
front door must be protected with symbols
auspicious to Lakshmi and prohibitive to
negative energy. The women of some areas
paint only their doors; others just the thresh¬
old; some paint the exterior walls facing the
street; while elsewhere they paint the ground
in front of the house. Each painting is a private
invocation by a woman to her deity. Although
often very beautiful, its artistic merit is usu¬
ally considered of secondary importance. Cer¬
tainly it would never be signed. It is a form of
personal communication, valuable only for
the moment of its creation. After that, it is
left to crumble or to be rubbed away, its full
function complete.
Exquisite rice-flour
designs
In the foothills of the Himalayas, women
paint their homes only once or twice each year:
for Deepavali, the annual festival honouring
Lakshmi, and for special birthdays or wed¬
dings in the family. They usually use organic
pigments such as rice flour for white, mineral
ochre for yellow and rust for red, vermilion
for bright red, and henna for green. The pow¬
ders are applied directly to the ground for
floor designs, or mixed with water to decorate
windows and doors.
They generally employ floral motifs sim¬
ilar to those that embellish their colourful
shawls. In the extremely dry desert of western
Rajasthan bordering Pakistan, the wives of
camel and goat herders decorate their homes
only once each year for Deepavali. They cover
the entire front walls of their homes in bold
geometric designs reminiscent of (but not
influenced by) mid-twentieth century West¬
ern geometric abstraction. A village which for
most of the year is barely distinguishable fro m
the drab landscape of the surrounding desert
is transformed into a powerful visual invoca¬
tion to the goddess on this important occa¬
sion. The colour will last only a few weeks
until it is bleached out by the incessant sun.
In contrast, the women living in the eastern
section of the same state repaint their homes
often. They resurface their walls and floors with
locally-mined red ochre for every important
occasion (religious festivals and important fam¬
ily events, such as conception, birth, reaching
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
puberty, betrothal and marriage). They then
cover both surfaces with decorations specific to
the event using pigment made from white lime.
Every single day of the year in more than
a million houses in the south Indian state of
Tamil Nadu women paint decorations on the
ground outside their front doors. On regular
days they use rice flour or ground white stone
powder applied to the dampened surface of
dirt or pavement. Some first mark out a grid
of dots which they connect in fluid designs,
while others work entirely freehand. On fes¬
tival days or during auspicious months, bril¬
liant commercial coloured powders are used
to fill in the complex patterns.
The women pride themselves on never
repeating a design and the streets are trans¬
formed into endless galleries of colourful
artistry. Most paintings are completed before
sunrise, at which time the artist usually walks
past her neighbours to compare their produc¬
tions and to gather inspiration for the follow¬
ing days' paintings. Within an hour or two all
the paintings are gone blown away or kicked
into dust by the ongoing traffic of the day.
In the eastern state of Orissa women grind
parboiled rice into a paste which they apply to
the mud walls of their houses using many dif¬
ferent techniques (by hand, rag and brush).
Many festivals herald the repainting of walls;
but the most important paintings are created
In a village in the western
desert of Rajasthan, women
cover the walls of their houses
with bold geometric patterns
dedicated to the goddess
Lakshmi.
during the two months from mid-December
until mid-February dedicated to the special
worship of Lakshmi. Both walls and floors
are covered with exquisite floral and animal
motifs on the most important day.
Among other symbolic designs, a tempo¬
rary shrine is painted on the floor inside and
a wooden altar set upon it. A terracotta pot
filled with freshly harvested rice is then placed
upon the altar. Encouraged by high-pitched
ululations, the Goddess is invited to invest
her spirit in the pot, thereby blessing the home
and its inhabitants. At the moment when con¬
tact (darshan) with the deity is experienced
by the women, the ceremony is complete, the
Goddess is requested to leave, and the paint¬
ings no longer have any value.
Throughout India women's sacred paint¬
ings are personal expressions within a tradi¬
tional medium, the voice of the feminine in a
male-dominated culture. They are a means of
communication between the soul of a devotee
and her duty, painted prayer which brings bal¬
ance to a woman's life and which creates a bond
to other women throughout the subconti¬
nent. Communion with the Divine, as per¬
ceived in many Hindu rituals, is usually fleet¬
ing: both the work of art and the experience it
produces are ephemeral. They create a moment
of grace and harmony within a cosmos of con¬
stant change.
the unesco »Courier December i99&
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Africa's women muralists Wall painting, like body decoration, cloth
dyeing and pottery, is primarily a
woman's art in Africa.
It is as necessary and as incorporated
in the lifestyle of these people as walk¬
ing, eating and sleeping. First and fore¬
most, this art form is a means of beau¬
tifying the space in which the women and
their fami lies spend a great deal of time,
of enhancing an otherwise harsh envi¬
ronment. Itis also a magicalform of cre¬
ativity, the magic coming not from its
meaning or intent but from the act of
applying the paint to the wall.
Before painting begins, the women
must restore and replaster the walls with
a mixture of mud and cow dung. The sur-
i
jfe'
Wall paintings
in South Africa
(left and above
right) and Ghana
(above left).
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Navajo paintings in sand
The sand paintings of the Navajo Indians
of the southwestern United States play an
important part in traditional healing
ceremonies. The paintings are executed
on the floor of the hogan, the Navajo
earth-covered wooden dwelling, by the
singer or hatááli. The singing of the
hatááli and the figures he draws attract
the Holy People. During the ceremony,
the patient sits on the sand painting.
The singer then takes sand from figures
in the painting and applies them to the
patient, to whom the healing and pro¬
tective power of the Holy People is
thereby transferred. After the ceremony,
the sand painting is erased.
eCM-lesWats.Pa-ls
faces are smoothed by hand, using a brew
of dung and urine, in itself creating a
subtle pattern. Organic materials are
used for both the paintsin the form of
indigenous pigmentsand the tools,
made from plants or feathers. Flat colours
or relief work, or a combination of the
two, are applied to the wall in a variety
of patterns and motifs.
The most common practice is to use
earth pigments painted onto a freshly
plastered surface, often layer upon layer.
This layering slows the drying process of
the paints, as well as cracking, thus cre¬
ating a smudged effect, an "indistinct¬
ness" between pattern and surface.
The lifespan of painted wallssub¬
ject to disintegrationis not intended
to be permanent. Rather, the walls are
recreated each year to celebrate or
announce new events and to permit
women to partake in a communal or social
activity.
Margaret Courtney-Clarke, African Canvas,
The art of WestAfrican women.
Rizzoli International, New York, 1990.
The Navajo
Indians make sand
paintings as part
of healing rituals.
Top, a hatááli or
"medicine man"
traces a sun
symbol (above),
which he erases at
the end of the
ceremony (left).
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
DANCING WITH
MASKS
BY MARGARET A. STOTT
In echo mask of the Bella
Coola (Nuxalkmc) Indians of
British Columbia (Canada).
| he ceremonial art of the northwest
coast of North America has long
inspired admiration. In the past, huge
carved and painted totem poles,
masks, head-dresses and rattles as well as carved
or painted chests, boxes and bowls figured
prominently in elaborate feasts and potlatches
(ceremonial occasions on which gifts were dis¬
tributed to affirm social status), and continue
to be important to contemporary northwest
coast communities.
Important aspects of this art are not per¬
manent or tangible, for while some objects
exist for short periods of time and deterio-
KvLwakiutl artist Fah Ambers
puts the finishing touches to a
carefully crafted hamat'sa
mask that will be used in many
potlatches.
rate, others are created and/or destroyed as
part of ceremonial events.
Even during their "lifetimes", these cere¬
monial objects do not necessarily remain
unchanged. Study of the paint on northwest
coast masks has revealed that some of them
have been repainted in dramatically different
designs and colours since their creation. Some¬
times elements such as pieces of copper or
abalone have been added to areas which origi¬
nally were only painted.
Along with this evolution in the appearance,
form and life of objects, there has always been an
emphasis on producing new ones to replace
those which have grown old. Part of every pot-
latch has been the revelation of fine new masks
and other objects commissioned by proud hosts
to be presented for the admiration of their
assembled guests. The concept of the mask or fig¬
ure remains permanent, but it is recreated and re¬
presented in the ceremonial context.
The destruction of masks created for cere¬
monial purposes occurs in another context
amongst the Heiltsuk of Bella Bella, British
Columbia. It is their tradition to burn masks
and other ceremonial objects representing the
crests and privileges of a deceased person. In
1990, following the memorial potlatch held
to honour Hereditary Chief Wigvilba Wakas
(Leslie Humchitt), masks and other objects
created by Nuxalk artist Glenn Tallio (Chief
Wakas's son-in-law) were burned "as a gesture
of love and respect".
Dance and theatre
In 1 967 1 went to the Bella Coola Valley armed
with photographs of masks, head-dresses and
rattles known to have been part of Nuxalk
winter ceremonies. The people were excited to
see the photographs and loved to discuss them.
The conversation usually focused upon who
THE UNESCO (jïUR'EI I DECEMBER I 09Û
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
i hamat'sa ceremony at a
potlatch given by Chief
T'lakwagila (W. T. Cranmer) at
Alert Bay (Canada) in 1983.
had once owned and used the object in ques¬
tion, and when it had last been publicly dis¬
played in the community.
In some households I was shown masks
or other carvings. I was enthralled with these
objects which were currently held in the com¬
munity. But frequently I detected some puz¬
zlement on the part of my hosts as to why I
was so interested in them. Comments like,
"But you really ought to see it danced. . ."
began to impress me, as I could see that the
Nuxalkmc were not as reverent towards these
ceremonial objects as I was. The most impor¬
tant thing is not merely a carved mask or rat¬
tle, but the role it plays within the integrated
ritual complex in which it is involved.
Each part of a costume contributes to the
creation of a particular personage or character
and that character is unmistakably linked with
a song and a dance. When a man brings out a
carved and painted mask, and shows it proudly,
he says "I dance that". Little is said about the
merits of the mask, while long descriptions of
the dramatic movements of the masked dancer
are readily offered.
In fact, this art, while involving some very
fine tangible elements, is essentially an
ephemeral art of dance and theatre. This was
apparent in seven Kwakwaka'wakw masked
dances performed in March 1996, in the north¬
ern coastal community of Alert Bay. In prepa¬
ration for these dances, as much attention was
paid to instructing the dancer in correct body
movements and hand gestures as was lent to
fitting on his mask and other costume items.
These movements were presented in careful
synchronization with particular drum beats,
song passages and choruses provided by the
accompanying singers. When the Grizzly Bear
danced, the fierce mask worked in concert with
the snarls, song and rhythmic drum beating
that filled the air, and with the lumbering
movements around the dance floor and the
clawing gestures of the dancer.
Living memory
Part of the ephemeral nature of northwest coast
ceremonial art is the vast historical knowledge
and understanding that the creators and the
witnesses of the art traditionally bring to their
experience. Through the oral histories of the
northwest coast peoples, the iconography of
the objects and dramatic content of the art can
be explained. Most figures represented in the
plastic arts and events which are presented in
dance or dramatic form are derived from the
elaborate family histories of those involved.
Through speeches, those witnessing the cere¬
mony are reminded of that history, and hence
they are able to fully appreciate and understand
what they are witnessing.
Once objects are removed from the com¬
munity or are beyond living memory, their
meaning may be lost.
r 17
the Unesco Courier« December i 996
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ABRIDGE
TO THE
CREATIVE
PAST
BY LUKE TAYLOR
The religious life of the Aborigines of
Central Australia focuses upon the
activities of the original creator beings,
who instituted the first ceremonies
and produced the first sacred objects and
designs used in them. Today, Aboriginal peo¬
ple say they "follow up" these ancestors in
their own activities and care for the sites which
contain their powerful essence. They hold cer¬
emonies to honour the creative activities of
the original beings and to release a measure of
ancestral power in order to maintain the
world's fertility. The production of art forms
a very important part of these events.
At various stages in the performances, cer¬
emonial leaders paint powerful graphic designs
on the dancers' bodies in red and yellow ochre,
white pipe clay and charcoal. Coloured bird
down or vegetable flu ff may be attached to add
texture or fixed around an enveloping frame¬
work that temporarily transforms the dancer
into a representation of the ancestral being.
More elaborate designs, sometimes extend¬
ing over considerable distances, are made on the
ceremonial ground. They may include sculp¬
tural elements such as mounds or hollows.
Alternatively, decorated wooden poles strung
Mn Aborigine from Elcho
Island, Arnhem Land, In
Australia's far north.
Mboriglnes wearing feathers
stuck to the skin with a paste
made of beeswax and honey.
with sacred objects may be inserted into the
ground at certain points. The designs depict
schematically the features of landscape made
by the ancestral beings, whom the dancers imi¬
tate as they make their way across them.
The designs are destroyed during the cere¬
mony, having served their purpose of pro¬
viding a temporary bridge between the cre¬
ative past and the world of the Aborigines
today. The aesthetic aim is not to construct a
permanent monument but to produce a pow¬
erful effect, thus maintaining knowledge about
the nature of the ancestral world and trans¬
mitting it to the younger generation.
The motifs often consist of concentric cir¬
cles joined by parallel lines or incorporate
other features such as animal tracks, arcs and
straight lines often representing the shelters
or tools used by the Ancestral beings.
The concentric circles are symbolic of
female generative power and the straight line
joining motifs suggest male procreative power.
The conjunction of these elements in a cere¬
monial context is considered by performers
to release procreative energy and thus maintain
the life cycle.
THE UNESCO C3URILR DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
COSMETICS AND CULTURE
BY VIVIANE BAEKE
The cultural
significance of
body painting
ody painting and scarification are,
like jewelry and costume, ways of
covering, disguising and trans¬
forming the body. But although
the aim is almost without exception to beau¬
tify the body, aesthetic considerations are usu¬
ally ancillary to social, religious or political
preoccupations. However different the motives
of the societies that engage in these practices,
the common denominator is an attempt to
dissociate the human body from its purely
biological condition and endow it with a cul¬
tural dimension.
Body painting lies somewhere between
scarification, which leaves lasting marks, and
accessories that can be put on, taken off and
replaced at a moment's notice. Unlike jewelry
or clothing, it alters the appearance of the skin;
unlike the effects of scarification, the alter¬
ation is only superficial and temporary.
At one end of the spectrum between per¬
manent and temporary markings are the
I hese two Angolan tundanji
(newly circumcised youths)
have been dressed in finery
and painted with ritual red
and white patterns on their
return to the village after a
period of seclusion prescribed
by tradition.
THE UNESCO lOURIER« DECEMBER 1996 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
eft, a member of the
scarifications made by theBobodcof Mali and (Papua New Guinea).
Burkina Faso on the heads of babies when they D. Ui ,
J flight, a Tuareg woman
are a few days old. The scarifications are etched from Niger,
on to the still malleable skull tissue as well as the
skin and last until the subjects die, enabling
the corpse to be identified by the dead person's
ancestors. At the other end of the spectrum is
the ritual during which married women of the
Mfumte-Wuli people of western Cameroon
wrap the red leaves of an ornamental plant
around their hips once a year, on the day when
a great annual feast is held to celebrate the mar¬
riages that have taken place during the year.
Some body paint can last for a very long
time. When the Mfumte-Wuli rub their skin
with the leaves of a plant they call mahiyeru,
they obtain a black pigmentation that lasts
for two years. Penetrating deep into the sub¬
cutaneous tissue, this technique bears some
resemblance to tattooing, although unlike tat¬
tooing it is not permanent. Among the young
. women and children it is replacing scarifica¬
tion, which has fallen into disuse.
At the great annual feast marking the tran¬
sition from the maize season to the sorghum
THE UNESCO fpuR'ER DECEMBER 1996
season, the Mfumte-Wuli decorate their bod¬
ies with a black pigment made from the juice
of a local fruit mixed with ash. It lasts for sev¬
eral days, sometimes even several weeks, like the
henna used in North Africa. The effects of
charcoal make-up, which can be as easily effaced
as watercolour, are more transient.
Appearance
and reality
The Kayapo Indians of the Xingu region of
Amazonia (Brazil) arc inveterate body-
painters. Not to wear body paint seems out of
the question, except in such exceptional cir¬
cumstances as an illness during which the sick
and their kinsfolk withdraw from commu¬
nity life. Like scarification in sub-Saharan
Africa, body painting is here an emblem of
the group's cultural and ethnic identity. It is as
if the Kayapo have chosen to indicate a person's
membership of the group by using ephemeral
signs which are painted again and again,
whereas in Africa permanent, ineradicable
markings are used for this purpose.
The Kayapo distinguish between body
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Fulah woman from Niger.
painting for everyday use and body painting
for specific rituals. The former, which can be
likened to clothing, consists mainly of black
designs, covering almost the entire body, traced
with genipapo, a dye extracted from the fruit
of Genipa americana which remains visible
for several days. Only the extremities (feet,
ankles and head) are painted in red or rucu (a
dye extracted from the seed oiBixa orellana),
a colour associated with energy and vitality.
When called for by particular circumstances
or certain rites, the everyday designs arc replaced
(or painted over) by special patterns drawn with
charcoal or genipapo. Although these two forms
oí genipapo painting (daily patterns and ritual¬
istic patterns) use the same techniques and look
very much alike, only the everyday painting is
specifically described as "fine painting".
The designs used on special occasions are
almost always drawn with the fingers and sym¬
bolize transient, preliminary, in some cases
dangerous situations, such as mourning, birth,
hunting or war. As ephemeral as charcoal, rucu
is associated with certain precise situations.
Returning warriors, for example, smear it all
over their bodies and remain slightly apart
from the rest of the community before enter¬
ing the men's house in the centre of the village.
Among the Kayapo, as ethnologist Claudine
Vidal reports, to be is primarily to appear m a
culturally appropriate way.
M Kayapo Indian
from the Mato Grosso
Plateau of Brazil.
THE UNESCO (jïURIERB DECEMBER 1996 fl
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
BY GILLES A. TIBERGHIENART'S
BACK-TO-THE-LAND MOVEMENT
By intervening
in the
environment,
land art creates
anew
relationship
between space,
time and the
spectator
Atthe end of the 1 960s, a number of
artists, most of them American,
challenged the notion that galleries
and museums are the most suit¬
able places in which to exhibit art. They pre¬
ferred natural sites, derelict industrial zones,
quarries and mines, where they produced
works out of natural materials, sometimes on
a massive scale, thus creating a new tendency
known as "earth art" or "land art".
At the end of the 1950s, interest in the
human body, the "events" staged by the Fluxus
movement that flourished in New York and
Germany, Allan Kaprow's "happenings" and
productions by the Living Theater and other
street theatre companies focused attention on
the importance of movement and improvisa¬
tion, and created a cultural environment which
also provided a context for music, painting and
sculpture. At a time when the consumer soci¬
ety was riding high, artists started creating
works that appealed to the active conscience of
individuals and encouraged them to redefine
their position as spectators.
Body art, in which the body becomes a vehi¬
cle for experimentation, was the logical outcome
Oun Tunnels (1976) by
American artist Nancy Holt,
Great Basin Desert, Utah
(U.S.A.). The four "sun
tunnels" are specially
constructed pipes each
measuring 6 metres long and
2.5 metres in diameter. They
are aligned with the solstice
and their sides are pierced
with holes corresponding to
the constellations. They act as
observatories and a mirror of
the day and night skies.
Shown here, the setting sun at
the summer solstice as seen
through two of the tunnels.
> GuTHE UNESCO tpURIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
>
Uissipate (1968) by the
American artist Michael
Heizer. Wood-lined gashes in
the Black Rock desert,
Nevada (U.S.A.).
\ ife
- »
of these practices. But some artists preferred to
make a mark on the natural world. In One Hour
Run (1968), for example, Dennis Oppenheim
scarified a snow-covered dune with a motorcy¬
cle, and in Foot Kick Gesture (1968) Michael
Heizer marked the ground with his heels. One
of Richard Long's first works, Line Made by .
Walking (1 967), was the result of his walking to
and fro in a straight line over a stretch of grass,
leaving behind an ephemeral trace of his passage.
From then on, two trends emerged which
either combined or were mutually exclusive.
The first, found chiefly in Europe, focused on
the body (Gilbert and George) or body move¬
ment (Richard Long, Hamish Fulton). The sec-
ond, more particularly American, trend sought
to create a new relationship between the body
and space by intervening in the natural world,
which it used both as an inscriptive vehicle and
as a material. From 1 968 on, for example, Heizer
created a series of works in the deserts of the
American West, in some cases drawing inspira¬
tion from Indian pictograms, as in Primitive
Dye Painting (1969), in others seeking to pro¬
duce simple geometrical forms with "nega¬
tive" in other words hollowed-out sculp¬
tures, such as Rift or Dissipate (1968).
But earth is also used for building, some¬
times on a very large scale. For the Sonsbeek 71
exhibition in Emmen (Netherlands), Robert
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEM8ERI996
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Morris made an Observatory, subsequently
destroyed then reconstructed in 1977, which
consisted of two concentric, circular earth¬
works with a diameter of 91 and 24 metres
respectively. He was returning to the primitive
architectural forms that inspire certain land-art
artists. Such imposingly large works have to be
explored by spectators, who arc prompted by
their movement in space to look afresh at how
sculpture relates to the movements of their
own bodies.
The distinctive feature of land art is this
use of earth (or sand, rock, or wood) on nat¬
ural sites, which then become components of
the sculpture, or even the sculpture itself, as in
Heizer's Double Negative (1969). This work
consists of two colossal gashes ten metres
wide, 17 metres deep and almost 500 metres
long, gouged out of the side of a plateau, pro¬
longed by two platforms consisting of 240,000
tonnes of excavated rubble.
Involving the spectator
This form of art should be distinguished from
arte povera, which appeared in Italy around
the same time. Examples of it, made out of
natural materials, were mostly exhibited in
galleries. A distinction should also be made
between land art and other forms of inter¬
vention in the natural world, many of them
more recent, such as the work of Nils-Udo,
Bob Verschueren and Andy Goldsworthy,
who practise what might be called vegetable
art in that they often work with flowers, bark
and leaves. A similar case is the work of Michael
Singer, who erects large ephemeral structures of
wood and bamboo in the open air (First Glade
Ritual Series 4, 1979).
Whether they are ephemeral or not, land art
works are not easily accessible, either because
they no longer exist, or because they are located
in remote spots. In a sense, the effort needed
to reach them contributes to the pleasure expe¬
rienced in looking at them. The journey and
the crossing of the landscape rather than the
landscape itself are in some respects a constituent
part of these works. For example, Richard
Long who denies any affiliation with land art
even if it may fairly be asserted that he had a
hand in its beginnings shows, in galleries where
he exhibits, not only captioned photographs
and maps that indicate a date, a place and some¬
times the duration of the journey, but also
stones arranged in a circle or row, which he did
not bring back from his travels but extracted
from quarries, and whose purpose is to pro¬
vide the spectator with a kind of perceptible
equivalent of the essence of his art: walking.
Other related art forms display some of
the concerns of the exponents of land art. Cer-
Briroken Circle (1971), a
curved jetty by American artist
Robert Smithson in Emmen
(Netherlands), is one of several
works executed in an
abandoned quarry. Although
intended to be temporary, it
was preserved on the request
of local inhabitants.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
tain artists consider the most important ele¬
ment to be "the process". One of them is Peter
Hutchinson, who used a rope to tie together
five floating calabashes and waited for them
to rot (Threaded Calabash, 1969). Others
focus on "the environment", such as Christo
and Jeanne-Claude, who unfurled a 40-km-
long cloth fence across Sonoma and Marin
counties in California and left it there for two
weeks (Running Fence, 1972-76). Others are
more interested in light, in our relationship
with the sun and the stars, or in landscapes.
Others again find inspiration in the notion
of the garden, whether traditional or pic¬
turesque, or make allusions to sanctuaries and
fortresses.
Photography, although not essential, often
plays a central role in this form of art because
turrounded Islands
(1980-83), an installation
by American artists Christo
and Jeanne-Claude, Biscayne
Bay, Florida (U.S.A.). Eleven
islands located in Miami
were surrounded with
603,850 m2 of pink woven
polypropylene fabric.
By using natural sites and
man-made monuments,
Christo and Jeanne-Claude
induce people to see their
environment in a different
light.
it keeps a record of the act of creation. Its func¬
tion is twofold: it can be cither a perceptible
equivalent of a singular artistic experience, in
which case it is presented as secondary for both
artist and spectator, or a document about a
work which it is up to the spectator to go and
experience on the spot. For even in the case of
certain monumental creations, which can only
be fully appreciated from the air, photography
cannot replace direct contact with the work
itself. It is only through such contact that we
can experience the human condition and the
p recariousness of the world, and become aware
of such notions as duration and transience
which is indeed the purpose of this kind of
art, just as it was of seventeenth-century Van-
itas still-life paintings of objects symbolizing
the vanity of earthly achievements.
THE UNESCO lOURIER« DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Theatre
Theatre only exists at the precise moment
when two worldsthat of the actors and
that of the audiencemeet: a society in
miniature, a microcosm brought together
every evening within a space. Theatre's
role is to give this microcosm a burning
and fleeting taste of another world, in
which our present world is integrated and
transformed.
Peter Brook,
The Shifting Point
Harper & Row Publishers, 1987
Below, Nightsea Crossing (1982),
performance art by Marina Abramovic,
presented at the Stedelijk Museum in
Amsterdam (Netherlands). Two people sit
across a table from each other from 10
a.m. to 5 p.m. for twelve days without
speaking, eating or drinking. The
performance was put on in two other
places and lasted a total of 90 days.
A scene from Fuoco centrale
(1996) staged by the Valdoca Dance
Company in Bari (Italy).
Performance Art
In Performance Art the "work" consists of acts or gestures
within a certain situation. It is of limited duration and is
defined by a given time and place. Among its manifestations
are body art, happenings and events.
"Performance practically died in the 1980s but is reviving
now because awareness of the body is coming back. I think that
this automatically leads to performance, because performance
is the most direct way of communicating energy, and the artist's
work in the future is going to be direct energy, communica¬
tion without the object. Performance fixes the moment, the here
and now, and it is something ephemeral and untouchable."!
Marina Abramovic
in Art and Design, vol. 9, no. 9-10, Sept.-Oct. 1994
THE UNESCO IpURIER DECEMBEF
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Modern
murals
Palisades in Paris...
These improvised, vulnerable works are
ephemeral. Soon they will disappear, and
we should not regret their passing. Their
making was more important than their
conservation. On palisades painting
invents newways of being. It is wedded to
a moment: as soon as it appears, it must
reach its audience, then disappear for-
Denys Riout.
From Le livre du graffiti, by Denys Riout,
Dominique Gurdjian, and Jean-Pierre Leroux
(Editions Alternatives, Paris, 1990)
...and Amsterdam
The ephemeral nature of wall paintings is also a
sign of their modernity. Of course, paintings that
have been long discussed, and long in the prepara¬
tion and execution, are regarded by their authors
and the public as finished works. Although executed
in extremely durable colours or in some cases in
ceramics or mosaic, they are by virtue of their
themes, their mode of production and even their
physical location (e.g. on the walls of condemned
buildings), part of an ideology of ephemera li ty that
parts company with the time-honoured idea of the
work of art as precious and indestructible.
Frank Popper,
L'art public, Peintures murales contemporaines.
Peintures populaires traditionnelles,
Jacques Damase publishers, Paris
i m
Ji* Jf SP*
p<4 >/^^i
tâéM \ ik
ï - -'>= .'..1
>' 'IsW<
s *i
at C
T: ;r:T; J . HTîïiilT: i ¡^r-g* £&J4\
\.....'r .-:Y,r; í -JS4 Vf' ..
tf \/' r
P %é kP
O*'*$ a 4 ë $ ,
&i:&&v<jàP p ;¿
I DECEMBER I 99G
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
flowers as raw
material
WORKING NOTES
BY NILS-UDO raw with flowers. Paint with clouds. Write
with water. Record the May wind, the flutter
of a falling leaf. Work for a storm. Anticipate
a glacier. Curve the wind. Give direction to
water and light. The cuckoo's verdant call, the
invisible trajectory of its flight. Space. An ani¬
mal's whimper. The bitter taste of bay. Bury
the pond and the dragonfly. Illuminate the
fog and the scent of yellow barberry. Combine
sounds, colours and odours. The green grass.
Count a forest and a meadow.
pen the tangible, living, three-dimensional
space of nature. With the slightest possible
intervention, switch on and transform this
space of nature into a space of art.
tI atural space should be perceived by sight,
hearing, smell, taste and touch: like a kind of
total work of art, a utopia, born of nature
and returning to it.
short-lived reorganization, of course: one
day the operation will be effaced by nature.
I wrote these lines about making my first big
nest, constructed of birches, earth and stones:
"Perched on the high wall of the nest, my gaze
followed the forest floor, crossed the branches
of trees, the sky. I thought: The nest is not yet'
finished; I am building myself a house. Silently
descending, crossing the tree-tops, it rests on
the forest floor. Open to the cold night sky,
yet warm and soft, buried in the dark earth."
I he archetypal nature of the nest. An image to
try to overcome at long last, as in a magnify¬
ing glass, all the categories and painful separa-
28 THE UNESCO Q)URIER DECEMBER 1196
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
tions in the ardour of an act in which every¬
thing is fused.
^nly in its final refuges is nature still intact,
inexhaustible. Only there is enchantment still
real, at every moment, at every season, in all
weathers, in great and small alike.
otential utopias sit under every stone, on
every leaf and behind every tree, in clouds and
in wind. Sensations are ubiquitous. As a real¬
ist, all I have to do is gather them. Deliver
them from their anonymity. With an idiotic
and ineradicable faith in utopia. Inject poetry
into the inhuman river of time.
#ne basic objective of this work was to
aspire to absolute purity. In a sense, nature
should represent itself. Anything alien to
nature was excluded because of its impurity.
This means that only materials found in the
chosen natural space have been used and shaped.
In view of the overwhelming profusion of
natural phenomena, it appeared that they
could only be worked on in small or very
small fragments, detached from their context.
\J pposite page, Sunflowers
(1993) by Nils-Udo. "The river,
sunflowers, snowball berries,
the berries and seeds of the
spindle tree, and mountain
ash berries." Executed in
Donauried, Bavaria
(Germany).
flight, Entering the ground
(1993) by Nils-Udo. "Chestnut
leaves, pine needles, palm
fronds." Executed in Borgo
Valsugana (Italy).
B elow, /Vest (1995) by Nils-
Udo. "River, branches, rushes,
hay." Executed at Real World
studios, Box (United
Kingdom), for a CD-Rom by
musician Peter Gabriel.
oday, I often content myself with collect¬
ing plants, picking, spreading out and dis¬
playing.
1 1 is true that many people claim to love nature
Just as everyone wants peace. But the fact is
they lost nature long ago. They do not even
see it any more. Still less do they hear, smell,
taste and touch it. And even if they look, they
do not see: long ago they lost the faculties nec¬
essary for a vaster overview in time and space.
.I y work does not escape the basic fatality
of our existence, cither. It wounds what it
touches: the virginity of nature.
ather the specific potentialities of a land¬
scape in a given season, condense and blend
them into a unique apogee, an apotheosis of
that season in that landscape. One second of
life is enough. The event has taken place. I have
awakened it and made it visible.
n this narrow fringe, where is the fron¬
tier between nature and art? This debate does
not concern me. I am not interested in art but
in the Utopian character of my actions which
blend life and art.
\ n image. A leaf laden with flowers flows
down a river. Life.
THE UNESCO f^JURI ER. DECEMBER 1996
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
INSTALLATION ART BY MICHAEL ARCHER
Provocative artworks designed for spectator involvement
Once upon a time there was paint¬
ing and there was sculpture. But
that was a long time ago. The tech¬
nologies employed by artists now
include film, video, slide projection, sound
and computers, and there is no limit placed
upon the materials that may be used. The pre¬
sent-day visitor to a gallery or museum of
contemporary art can expect to be met by
almost anything.
At the Dia Foundation in New York there
is a room filled to waist height with earth. Wal¬
ter de Maria's 50m3 Earth, made at a time in the
late 1960s when artists were beginning to exam¬
ine the relationship between the industrial and
natural landscapes of the world and the ways
in which they were represented in the gallery,
has to be carefully tended and watered to keep
it looking and smelling fresh. Although one can
only stand at the doorway and look in, the
physical presence of the work is impressive.
At the Saatchi Gallery in London there is
a room filled to waist height with used car oil.
A channel let into the tank allows one to enter
the gallery which, because of the perfect reflec¬
tive qualities of the still, black liquid seems
to dissolve as the strong illumination from
the skylight also appears below one's feet.
However opposed their ultimate effects,
these examples of what has come to be known
as installation art share the idea that an art¬
work is not an object in the gallery but some¬
thing that extends throughout, thoroughly
occupies and is to some extent congruent with
its space.
It has been more than a quarter of a century
since art some art at least required its spec¬
tators to experience it differently. The term
"installation" covers a huge variety of art¬
works, a variety of form, materials, content
and effect so broad that there seems little that
could justify giving them all the same generic
name. However, it is possible to identify a
number of factors, principally concerning a
new perception of the space and time within
which the relationship between spectator and
30
» THE UNESCO Q_OURIER DECEMBER 1996
orte-chapeaux(1917), a
ready-made by French artist
Marcel Duchamp. work of art takes place, which go some way to
explaining why this word has become so com¬
monplace in recent years.
Ready-made art
If we needed a historical precedent we could
look to Marcel Duchamp who, in the early
years of the century, offered a series of mass-
produced artefacts a bicycle wheel mounted
on a stool, a urinal, a snow shovel, and oth-
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
ers as "ready-made" works of art. These
defied the idea that the artist's touch, as the
sign of a unique expressive act, was essential to
art. They also demonstrated that it is the con¬
text in which we encounter things that largely
determines how we behave towards them. If
we come across something in an art gallery,
whatever it is, we are predisposed to treat it as
if it were art. By extension, to talk about the
meaning of the work is to speak of what arises
out of this encounter and not to refer to
something that lives in the work waiting to be
unlocked and released. Contrary to conven¬
tional wisdom, this is not merely the justifi¬
cation that the charlatan seeks in order to pass
off just anything as art, but an opportunity
to reflect upon the particular qualities of one's
experience here, now.
A good illustration of this is given by Gary
Hill's Tall Ships. As the viewer walks down a
broad, darkened corridor, other figures appear
to close in from left and right. Whenever the
spectator pauses to take a closer look, they
too stop and stare back, making one feel
extremely self-conscious, before turning and
walking away. The figures are video projec¬
tions triggered by the presence of the specta¬
tor: in other words, there is only something
there to look at because you are looking.
However varied installations are, the thing
they have in common is the fact that their mean¬
ings depend upon a relationship between the
objects and images of which they are consti¬
tuted and the space that contains them. This
space is also the space inhabited by the spectator,
and as such it is an environment subject to the
r light (1SS5) by German
artist Joseph Beuys.
"The silent piano with its
closed lid emphasizes a
synaesthetic equivalence
between the stifling of sound
and the containment of heat
in a room lined with thick
rolls of felt."
vagaries and contingencies of daily existence.
Things occur in our lives over which we exercise
little or no control. Chance plays a large part in
what happens to us, and the same is true to a
greater or lesser extent in installation. Even some¬
thing as simple as stipulating that a work must
be viewed in natural light, as the Welsh artist
Bethan Huws does with her painstakingly pre¬
pared but apparently empty interiors, is suffi¬
cient to place one's endeavours in the hands of
fate. The gallery environment is not stable, but
prone to change according to the season, the
time of day and the amount of cloud cover.
One is not exactly seeing a different room when
the sun comes out or goes in, but one is expe¬
riencing an environment whose full potential
cannot be revealed in one instant.
Reled on Green (1992) by Anya
Gallaccio. A carpet of 10,000
red roses in an area measuring
six metres by four.
THE UNESCO (¿URIERB DECEMBER 1996 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Another contrasting example of the way in
which chance acts within the structure set up
by the artist to make the work could be seen
in Zurich's Shcdhalle in the late 1980s when
Christian Marclay carpeted the floor with
blank-grooved records. Visitors could only
"see" the installation by walking on the discs,
an eventuality which inevitably led to their
becoming scuffed and scratched. The very act
of viewing leaves its trace.
Perishable materials
Installations unfold in time, their significance
develops out of the spectator's being with and
in them. It is as much in this the importance
of duration that their unfixable, ephemeral
quality lies as in the fact that they may physi¬
cally change or degrade. Of course, some do
change. Anya Gallacio's use of perishable mate¬
rials such as flowers, fruit, chocolate or ice,
means not only that her work will change from
day to day, but also that she can never be certain
how those changes will affect the way the work
looks. Flowers fade, dry out and shrivel, ice
melts, oranges rot. Painting the gallery walls
bove left, German artist
Wolfgang Laib collects
dandelion pollen as the first
step towards creating a work
of art. Above right, Laib works
on Sifting Hazelnut Pollen
(1986) at the CAPC-Museum of
Modern Art in Bordeaux
(France).
Were are leaving here forever
(1991) by Russian artist llya
Kabakov represents a school
that its students, teachers and
administrative staff had to
leave without warning and
without hope of return.
with chocolate, as she first did in Vienna in
1 993, created an ambience that could be smelled
as well as seen: sweet-smelling chocolate box
art for a world that prefers as far as possible to
avoid confronting unpleasantness. (Those who
were not too squeamish could lick and taste
the surfaces too.)
One can also sec this mixing together of
input from different senses at work in the
German artist Joseph Bcuys's Plight, now part
of the collection at the Pompidou Centre in
Paris. The work comprises a blackboard and a
thermometer lying on top of a grand piano in
a room entirely lined with thick rolls of felt.
It is impossible to consider the various refer¬
ences suggested by this work without taking
account of the full range of its sensory impact.
The cosy, insulating warmth of the felt
quickly becomes suffocating, a point made
both by the presence of the thermometer and
the closed lid of the piano. The silence of the
instrument emphasizes a synaesthetic equiva¬
lence between the stifling of sound and the
containment of heat, just as the work's Eng¬
lish title indicates the somewhat contradic¬
tory notions of a pledge and a predicament.
With installation, then, the experience of art is
inflected with sensorily rich, tactile elements.
It is still visual art, but the eye that appre¬
hends is unequivocally and inescapably housed
in a body.
Duchamp explained his works as being
things that interested or amused him, and it is
this quality of being interested in or fasci¬
nated by things rather than struck or absorbed
by their beauty that characterizes installation.
Many installations are, of course, beautiful,
but the manner in which they are viewed is
akin to the way in which we watch television,
go for a drive, or fill a supermarket trolley.
Our involvement in these activities is distracted
in the full sense implied by the critic Walter
THE UNESCO IpURIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
\Jermania (1993)
by German artist Hans Haacke
is a work containing
allusions to 20th-century
German history.
Benjamin, a sense that includes the polarities
of being fully attentive and thoroughly
diverted, as well as everything in between. This
is a far cry from the ideal, detached position of
the contemplative, dispassionate viewer of the
more traditional art forms.
Awkward questions
Beuys's ambiguity and Marclay's chance appear
in other situations as uncertainty. The kind of
reflection we are triggered into by installation
can as well be broadly social and political as
poetic or spiritual. At the Venice Biennale of
1993, the U.S.-based German artist Hans Haacke
broke up the stone floor of the German pavil¬
ion. A photograph of Hitler making a pre-war
visit to the Biennale was mounted at the door
while on the gallery's back wall the word "Ger¬
mania" was written up in a Fascist typeface.
Picking one's way across the fractured, loose
and uneven floor was a precarious venture,
appropriately symbolic of the difficulties inher¬
ent in the country's own task of economic and
social integration after reunification.
In a comparable vein, the Russian Ilya
Kabakov has, since the break-up of the Soviet
Union, made a series of profoundly affecting
environments that pose awkward questions
about the transition to a new model of social
organization. For the 1991 Carnegie Interna¬
tional he created an entire "school" complete
with pupils' work and meticulously kept
attendance and academic records. The pupils
and staff had been told they had to abandon
these fruits of their earlier endeavours and
move to another establishment. There was,
though, no information on exactly where they
were to go or what to expect when they
arrived. Why, Kabakov asks, need so much of
our former lives be jettisoned? It has been and
remains of value in making us what we are and
without it our sense of self-worth and our
very identity as people is profoundly under¬
mined. And here we recognize that what, in
installation, might strike us as transient, con¬
tingent, diffuse or unresolved is itself expres¬
sive of the character and qualities of contem¬
porary life.
THE UNESCO r^iURl ERB DECEMBER 1996
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Eventful happenings
Théâtre Total ( Total Theatre) by the French artist Ben was
put on at the Théâtre de la Chimère during the Third
Festival of Free Expression, Paris, 1965. Seated from left to
right: Daniel Pommereulle. Ben, Eric Dietman, Jean-Jacques
Lebel and Noël Arnaud.
Bon Marché (1963). a happening staged by American artist Allan
Kaprow for the Théâtre des Nations at the Récamier Theatre and the
Bon Marché department store in Paris (France).
L'enterrement de la Chose de Tinguely (The Burial of Tinguely's Thing)
in a Venetian canal on 14 July 1960, a happening staged by French
artist Jean-Jacques Lebel. The Thing in question was a work by Jean
Tinguely that the artist no longer wanted. Among the participants
were Harold Acton, Peggy Guggenheim, Frank Amey and Jean-Jacques
Lebel. This was the first European happening.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Ever since the beginning of the century
artists have been demanding an active
role in society and moving towards a more
direct and physical relationship with the
public. In this context the happening
the term was first used by the American
artist Allan Kaprowis a logical step in
a search for communication between "art
and life". In the early days, in the United
States in the 1950s, happenings were
spontaneous events among friends,
staged with very limited means in all
kinds of places (in apartments or
garages, or on the street) and never
reproduced, for they are by definition,
according to Allan Kaprow, untranspos-
able in space and unreproducible in time.
This art closely linked to life and the
present is direct, transient and gratu-
Claude Gintz,
Groupes, mouvements, tendances de l'art
contemporain depuis 1945. Editions de
l'Ecole Nationale Supérieure des Beaux-
Arts, Paris, 1989)
A happening is not an unchanging cere¬
mony; it is more a state of mind, clair¬
voyance, a poem onto which anyone can
engraft movement or paralysis, an
expressed or repressed impulse, a sense
of celebration or despair.
Jean-Jacques Lebel,
Le happening, Denoël, Paris, 1966
APOCALYPSE NOW
A self-destroying
Tinguely machine
by Michel Conil Lacoste
Homage to New York, by the Swiss artist Jean Tinguely
(1925-1991), noted for his machine-like kinetic sculptures, was
presented at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on
17 March 1960.
The event consisted of the self-destruction, in a hellish noise
punctuated by detonations, of an enormous scrap metal con¬
struction into which as usual a number of miscellaneous objects
had been incorporated: bicycle wheels, pram wheels, a coin-
throwing contraption made by Robert Rauschenberg, wireless
sets, shopping trolleys, a piano. The sense of smell was also
involved, asinMétamaric37theyear before: as if to satisfy all the
senses, the commotion was completed by an emission of mal¬
odorous fumes. The stage-by-stage eruption was punctuated by
bangs, crashes, smoke, fiery explosions and mechanical break¬
downs, which took Tinguely himself by surprise, and eventually
the firemen were called in. After half an hour, the whole thing
or what was left of itwas destroyed by remote control. The
museum, the curators and the small group of assistants escaped
unharmed from this auto da fé of metal, whose disorganizer con¬
fessed later thatthere had been moments when he had "pressed on
regardless".
What was the point of this suicidal fury? The "sculptor's"
answerto this question is worth quoting: "Homageto NewYork
was a simulacrum of catastrophe. As I saw it, the apocalypse was
to be a plastic event. I wanted to create the end of civilization in
plastic terms. It was 'an ironicalsuiride', to use Duchamp's expres¬
sion. Everything went up in flames, as at the end of a civilization.
In reality, we are at the beginning of a civilization, at the begin¬
ning of the era of automatization. Butweare not like the Egyptians
who were convinced that the world they had invented would con¬
tinue to exist. We no longer believe in eternity. We are like any
human being who grows old and thinks he is going to die. All the
ancient civilizations believed in finality, but for us finality is move¬
ment. Finality is transformation." (Art Press)
Michel Conil Lacoste, Tinguely, L'énergétique de l'insolence.
© Editions de La Différence, Paris, 1989
THE UNESCO ^URIER DECEMBER t99û 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
FROM IMAGE TO ENVIRONMENT
BY FLORIAN ROTZER
fingertips
m* m
irtual reality is computer
technology enabling a person
to "live" interactively in a
world of computer-generated
images. Wearing a head-
mounted display and a data
glove, this man can "touch"
the table which is
simultaneously being back-
projected onto a giant screen.
n the galaxy of three-dimensional virtual
images into which we have entered,
paintings and the handful of sculptures
still produced using traditional methods
have become a marginal phenomenon. Art pro¬
duced using simulation techniques is moving
towards the conquest of a three-dimensional
world of space and objects which we can enter
and where we can move about freely.
Art is breaking away from the straitjacket
of convention and quitting the museum. Real¬
ity is no longer a matter of appearance but is
becoming increasingly artificial and staged.
The replacement of traditional paintings
and sculptures by ready-made objects is a reac¬
tion to the impact of photography. The intro¬
duction of raw reality into art is a response to
the opportunity which the photographic
image offers of dissociating the representation
of an object from its physical presence. The
microphone and recording technology have
brought the same phenomenon to music,
where a composer like John Cage introduces
into his scores unusual or simple sounds which
are the musical equivalent of ready-mades.
Artists are proposing a new relationship with
reality. Today, faced with the advent of virtual
reality, we find ourselves cherishing the tangible.
We are starting to attach an ethical value to the
reality with which we come into violent contact
at the same time as it eludes us. Now that we
can conjure up all manner of images on our
magic screens and reconstitute all kinds of things
in virtual space, we are rediscovering a taste for
risk in a world where images are analysed to
death. Many people regard the computer as a
machine that disembodies, but in fact the oppo¬
site is the case. The whole body becomes a com¬
mand post that is drawn into cyberspace and
hooked up to a multitude of sensorial and track¬
ing systems.
A gateway
to another world
The traditional warnings against the dangers
of confusing image and reality are no longer
36 THEUNESCO ^>URIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
relevant. We have ceased to believe in the power
of images; they have become too lightweight
and insubstantial. They do not live up to our
expectations. Even when they excite or move us,
we act like an onlooker during a storm who
impassively watches a shipwreck from the shore.
When images began to move, the first audi¬
ence of the Lumière brothers' short film
L'Arrivée d'un train en gare de La Ciotat (1895)
were apparently terrified that the locomotive
drawing into the station would come out of
the screen into the cinema. Today we no longer
jump out of our seats when we see such images,
but many people wish we did. Virtual reality
has created a desire to use simulation techniques
to transcend simulation and achieve the mental
state of the man who became so involved in a
play that he was ready to leap onstage to rescue
the hero. Today we use a joystick or a mouse
to create on our computer screens the creatures
and images of our choice, but the time will come
when monsters and fighter-bombers in elec¬
tronic games will be capable of transporting our
virtual being into their virtual universe.
We no longer want to look through win¬
dows. We want to step through doors into
other worlds and come and go between them.
We want reality, and so we ask for images that
not only act on us but can react to our inter¬
ventions, in some cases unpredictably. Illusion
and utopia are becoming less alluring, while
reality is becoming more attractive, even as an
unsophisticated form of entertainment. Wc
want to get closer to reality and even touch it.
Interactive art
In the words "telephone", "television",
"telecommunication" and "teleconference" the
prefix "tele" not only designates the juxtapo¬
sition in the same virtual space of two distant
events, it also designates the equipment and
technologies that seek to overcome this dis¬
tance and create proximity. Teletechnologies
open doors as well as windows. Soon channel-
hopping will no longer offer usa simple choice
in the quest for thrills, fascinating scenes and
out-of-the-way information; it will give us
access to worlds that will remove us body and
soul from the here and now, as if from a prison.
Reality is not a visual image, nor does it
only involve one or two of our senses, calling
U pposite page, 77ie Legible
City (Karlsruhe version, 1991),
an interactive installation by
Australian artist Jeffrey Shaw
in assocation with Dirk
Groeneveld and Gideon May.
Sitting on a stationary bicycle,
visitors "ride" through a
computer-simulation of
Karlsruhe streets where the
buildings are replaced by giant
letters. These compose a text,
written by Dirk Groeneveld,
that the cyclist deciphers while
riding. The Legible City exists
in two other versions:
Manhattan (1989) and
Amsterdam (1990).
We' earing a special outfit and
a head-set, this man is on a
virtual trip in the middle of a
real street.
on the imagination to do the rest. It involves
all forms of sensations, emotions and actions.
With so-called virtual reality, which offers us
not images but sensory environments enabling
us to explore three-dimensional space, the
transition from contemplation of the pho¬
tographic image to entry into the world of
that image has become technically feasible.
This is what is involved in the creation of
new interactive works of art which would
leave the public with considerable freedom.
Visitors to cyberspace can travel as they wish
in this virtual world, since they arc no longer
perceiving an image transmitted by the single
eye of the camera lens but feeling impressions
comparable to those that we receive in our
usual environment. This multiplicity of sen¬
sory perspectives opens a whole network of
possible interactions that escape linear per¬
spective. One of the attractions of this virtual
world is that those who have access to it can
meet in it other "explorers". Thus we have a
new, theoretically open and extremely mal¬
leable environment. What should we do or
want to do and experience in it?
Artists face an exciting challenge as they
seek to extract dramatic effects from these new
possibilities. The notion of the finished work
has given way to that of performance by those
at the receiving end, who use the work of art
as an instrument whose possibilities they can
exploit.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
com m entary Federico Mayor
I igher education
and new technologies
New information and communication technologies, espe¬
cially the Internet, are offering researchers, educators,
artists and administrators all over the world an opportunity
to form the most cultivated, specialized, versatile and active
intellectual community that the world has ever known a
kind of global university.
The emergence of these technologies has revolution¬
ized our ways of thinking and living in recent years and
opened up heady prospects for creating worldwide links
between universities, institutes of higher education and
research, libraries, laboratories and hospitals, disseminat¬
ing knowledge, promoting personalized teaching, educa¬
tion tailored to the needs of individuals and groups, the
exchange of ideas and data and the implementation of col¬
lective projects.
It soon became clear that among the many fields where
the new technologies may be applied especially the high-
capacity networks known as information superhighways
that can carry data, sound and images higher education,
research and the promotion and dissemination of knowl¬
edge are those with the richest potential.
But we should not let our hopes run away with us. In
the wealthy nations privatization and deregulation are pro¬
ducing mixed and sometimes even disastrous results in
human and ethical terms, notwithstanding some undeni¬
able advantages in terms of freedom of initiative and job
creation. In the poorer countries they usually lead to highly
aggressive and dehumanized market competition.
Looking no further than the production, exchange and
dissemination of knowledge, we can see that the technology
explosion is increasing the enormous disparities between
North and South. Within the countries of the North, it is
widening the gap between the insiders (engineers, intellectuals
and the cultured, well-off classes) and the outsiders who do
not have the means to buy access to telecommunications.
The poor countries are under no illusions. They know that
the global village and the electronic village are not the same
thing. Is new information technology really the tool for devel¬
opment it is claimed to be? The cyberspace eldorado may be
THE UNESCO r^)URIEI I DECEMBER 1990
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
creating as many dangerous illusions as fruitful achieve¬
ments. And what about the cost? Infrastructure, hardware,
software and training costs are already exorbitant for Europe,
as it tries to catch up with the American lead. They are crip¬
pling for the less-well-off countries, and a fortiori for the
developing world, whose aspirations to modernity are already
undermined by the struggle for survival. If we want the
poor countries to have a minimum of new information tech¬
nology, they will have to be helped.
Cyberspace has no frontiers, limits or rules. Theoretically
it belongs to everyone. A supremely efficient vector of com¬
munication and a place where freedom of thought may be
exercised, it welcomes all who use it. But it is only acces¬
sible to those who have the requisite electricity, computers,
telephone hookups and know-how. This paradox recalls
the ambivalence of the word "sharing", which denotes both
conjunction, as in the breaking and distribution of bread,
and division, as in "time-sharing". A whole must be divided
before the parts can be distributed.
Sharing, dialogue, exchange and interactivity are
extremely ambiguous words. Often enough a person is only
interactive with the screen, or at best with data placed at his
or her disposal by the provider or, on the Internet, with a peer
group of researchers and specialists. Where is the relational
interactivity, the give-and-take that encourages social cohe¬
sion and creates human warmth? The university has always
been a place where people of flesh and blood can meet and
live the life of the mind and share each other's company.
Where can students of the global university of electronic
knowledge get together for convivial talk? The new tech¬
nologies have created a new kind of communication that
tends to promote dialogue between person and machine and
threatens to supersede human communication.
The paradox of cyberspace
One consequence of the rise of the audiovisual communi¬
cations media is the passivity of human behaviour in front
of the screen. The citizen of the twenty-first century is a tele¬
viewer rather than a "teleactor", and is usually regarded
as a consumer of images, information, entertainment and
knowledge. Only students who have learned to master
interactive machines and processes since childhood and
know how to extract from the electronic media exactly what
they need for their own growth can resist the powerful fas¬
cination of multimedia. For those who are less familiar with
the technology, the discovery of the medium takes prece¬
dence over the message. Another paradox of the new situ¬
ation is that content is the poor relation in a revolution
based on hardware, technology and processes.
One reason for drawing attention to the dangers associated
with these changes is to improve our capacity to cope with
them. We must welcome and exploit the possibilities opened
up by the new information technology, especially in view of
current trends in higher education: increasing diversification
of the student population and student demand (in terms of
age, expectations and training programmes), financial diffi¬
culties in many cases due to cuts in government expenditure
on higher education and the need to make training courses
more flexible in order to follow market requirements.
We must keep pace with change and, if possible, keep
ahead of it. In order to present a synthesis of the main trends
in higher education and set forth guidelines for its future
policies in this field, UiNESCO recently published a policy
paper entitled Change and Development in Higher Edu¬
cation. It is to be expected that the new information tech¬
nologies will broaden access to higher education in all its
diversity, and that the role of open universities and dis¬
tance-education systems will continue to expand.
Learning without frontiers
Steps must be taken to use the mobility, flexibility, leanness
and speed of the new information technologies to bring about
real sharing of knowledge. Actions speak louder than words:
UiNESCO did not wait until all the promise of these technolo¬
gies was fulfilled before launching its "Learning without
Frontiers" programme. Its Member States decided that in
1996-97 special attention would be paid to the use of tech¬
nology in education. In higher education, the UNITWIN/
UNESCO Chairs Programme is continuing to promote solidar¬
ity and co-operation between universities. An effort is being
made to support university chairs and networks using new
technology for education in general and distance education
in particular. To promote diversification in ways and means
of transmitting knowledge, the number of distance-education
centres and open universities must be increased.
The poor countries must be helped to acquire new tech¬
nologies and equipment, to train their people and enter
existing networks, in short to modernize along with the oth¬
ers. Is a global information society really conceivable in a
world where the overwhelming majority of citizens would be
starved of training and information? In this massive effort of
active solidarity, we must also carefully weigh up the power
factors associated with the new information technology and
make sure that "aid" does not lead toneo-colonialism. If we
are not careful, aid donors will try to provide training tai¬
lored to their own needs, to advise setting up networks
corresponding to demands they have defined for their own
situation, and to back up training with programmes that
they regard as relevant (and/or profitable?) for themselves.
Each country should define its own needs, make its own
requests, set up its own structures and constitute the
regional network it desires to match its own aspirations.
Solidarity, co-operation and aid: nothing is more demand¬
ing than real generosity, which puts recipients first and
seeks to give them the means to choose without influencing
their choice. The information revolution is too rich in edu¬
cational and human potential to he left to market forces or
those who use market forces for their own exclusive profit.
Perhaps the greatest challenge of the twenty-first century
will be to ally progress with fairness. I
the Unesco Courier» December i996 %
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
greenwatch
ke Fertö: hallow
waters steeped in wildlife
by France Bequette
From each side of the grassy
causeway dominating the vast
expanse of water a gaggle of wading
hirds a white heron, several grey
herons, two purple herons slowly
took off, their long legs dangling
beneath their bodies. Ahead, the
horizon was blocked by a thick cur¬
tain of windswept reeds. A boat was
drawn up on a tiny beach beside a
canal. Surprisingly, it had a petrol
engine and belonged to a fisherman.
Surprisingly, because we were on the
shore of Lake Fertö, in Hungary, a
UNESCO biosphere reserve which is
also a National Park where fishing
and all motorboats except those with
electric, engines are banned. But this
particular fisherman was a very old
man who only fished in the summer
and used mercifully inefficient tra¬
ditional methods. lie would die if
suddenly ordered to give up his
hobby.
The lake was concealed by the
reeds. To get a good view of it we had
This watchtower, a
vestige of the iron
curtain, is now
used for bird-
watching.
to clamber up a 16-metre-high
watchtower, a remnant of the iron
curtain that was dismantled in 1990.
This grim frontier between the com¬
munist world and the West, which
claimed the lives of thousands of vic¬
tims, here consisted of two electric
fences enclosing a tract of land from
3 to 5 km wide. But as Hungarian
forestry expert Attila Fersch told
me, "This no-man's-land was very
good for wildlife, which flourished."
Nowadays projects for airports, golf
courses and leisure centres abound
and are not always compatible with
nature conservation. The lake is a
major attraction for holiday-makers.
An ornithologist's paradise
It is an amazing lake. It has two
nationalities. The northern four-
fifths (the Neusiedler See) are Aus¬
trian, the southern fifth (Fertö To)
Hungarian. ] t is 35 km long and from
7 to 15 km wide with an average
depth of 60 em. Nowhere deeper
than 1.80 m, it is fed only by two
streams and rainwater. The water
has a high mineral salt content and is
opalescent, except at the edges
where it is dark brown because of
decomposing aquatic plants. Lake
Fertö was formed at the end of the
ice age. The Romans called it Lacus
peiso, and in the first century A.D.
Pliny the Elder already noted that it
periodically dried up an occur¬
rence which happened most recently
in 1865. The surrounding landscape
is a blend of eleared forest, pas-
tureland and a network of drainage
canals some 250 kilometres long.
The canals are used to flood the land
when necessary and to provide access
to the lake. Without them, at least
on the Hungarian side, it would be
impossible to get through the reeds,
which grow in a belt up to 5 or 6
kilometres wide.
The Park was declared a Ramsar
Convention1 zone in 1989. Its reeds,
muddy ponds and open water are a
paradise for birds; 260 species have
been recorded. Large numbers of
egrets, herons, geese and grebe nest
there, and it is a stopping off point
for thousands of migrating geese, as
well as storks and peregrine falcons.
Thirty-six species offish live in the
lake. Frogs, toads, reptiles and
insects abound. There are 1,513
recorded species of plants, some of
whieh grow only on alkaline soil, like
the dwarf aster (Aster tripolium),
which covers the ground with a
mauve carpet.
The Park has five functions: nature
conservation, land management,
research, environmental education and
eeotourism. However, its managers are
having a hard time coping with fund¬
ing problems. As a result of cuts in
public expenditure researchers can
no longer count on state funding and
have had to look for other sources. All
the same, the Ministry ofAgriculture
is providing the reserve with financial
aid in order to save three species of
domestic animal from extinction: the
water buffalo, the Hungarian grey
cow whose number has risen from
282 in 1960 to 2,500 todayand
the Racka sheep. To tend the mead-
THE UNESCO QlURIER B DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
ows the reserve employs men from
neighbouring villages to scythe the
grass, which is then closely cropped
by cattle. Short grass is essential for
the survival of small mammals like
the suslik (Citellus citellus), a ground
squirrel, without which the
extremely rare Saker falcon (Falco
cherrug) would have disappeared.
This is a good example of a conserva¬
tion chain at work. Permission to har¬
vest the reeds (Phragmites australis)
for roofing thatch is granted to pri¬
vate companies from December to
February. The reeds attract birds,
some of which prefer the young
shoots, others the older plants.
Surely poaching must be a prob¬
lem in this natural aviary? Apparently
Lake Fertö
straddles the
border between
Hungary and
Austria, where it is
called the
Neusiedler See. Its
logo (above right)
of two red geese
facing a green
goose on a white
background
symbolizes the
two countries'
flags.
not. "Hunting is not a tradition here,"
Attila told us. "We've got only two
rangers for a patchwork ofprotected
areas: a core zone of 3,300 hectares,
a buffer zone with the same area and
a 5,913-hectare transitional zone."
The reception centre for visitors
and researchers on the Fertö reserve
is an extraordinarily beautiful
thatched building of wood and con¬
crete with residential and study
facilities. Its design, by two Hun¬
garian architects, is inspired by the
feather of the great egret viewed
through a microscope. Photos of the
reserve's plant and animal life are
displayed in galleries. Schools and
groups of teachers come to the cen¬
tre for training courses.
A few kilometres away, the Aus-
trians have also recently built a
reception centre on the shore with a
tall observation tower. Here the bios¬
phere reserve is known as the
Neusiedler See-Seewinkel. In con¬
trast to what we saw on our visit to
the reserve on the Arizona (U.S.A. )-
Mexican border (see the UNESCO
Courier, September 1996), there is
hardly any sign of a frontier between
the two countries that share the
lake.
Joint management
Hungarian and Austrian representa¬
tives on the management committee
meet every month and work together.
Aloys Lang, who is responsible for
communications, explained that the
problems are different. "All the land
here is privately owned," he said.
"We have to rent it from 1,200 own¬
ers after assessing how much they
might earn from farming. It costs us
28 million schillings a year."
The Austrian side of the bios¬
phere reserve consists of three zones,
two along the Neusiedler See and
the third in Lange Lacke, a swampy
7f
w
: m
* i
"o "'- '/
Rare ferns In the
swamps of Lake
Fertö.
The Saker
(Falco cherrug) is
an extremely rare
falcon.
[Unesco Kurier b December i
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
' . I > The great egret or
white heron
[Egretta alba),
left, is one of Lake
Fertö's many
visitors.
area to the south-west covering a
total of 7,600 hectares. There is no
industry around the lake, but farm¬
ing and grape-growing both prosper.
In summer the lakeside villages are
visited by thousands of holiday-
makers who love fishing and (non-
motorized!) aquatic sports. It is eas¬
ier to reach the lake on the Austrian
side because there are not so many
reeds, and the water is cleaner
because sewage pipes have been
widely installed. Because the sur¬
rounding land is fiat, no pesticide
run-off reaches the lake. There are
no rangers. Guides accompany visi¬
tors, who are only admitted to the
Park on weekdays for lengthy hikes
on asphalted roads built for that
purpose. People in the vicinity
receive a quarterly newsletter from
Aloys Lang entitled Geshnatter
("Cackle"), of which 6,000 copies
are printed. It is a mine of informa¬
tion on nature and local life.
On one of the roads we came
upon a strange sight. A man was sit¬
ting in his car pointing a shotgun sky¬
wards. "Here hunting is still legal
until 1999," Aloys Lang explained,
"when a contract made prior to the
creation of the reserve expires, but
only for local people with hunting
licences." When he heard this story,
Attila Fresch burst out laughing,
"The geese aren't crazy. They know
they've got nothing to worry about on
the Hungarian side!" A single logo
unites the two park reserves: two
red geese facing a green goose on a
white background symbolize the
Austrian and Hungarian flags and a
shared determination to preserve the
region's wildlife. I
1 The Ramsar Convention on Wetlands of
International Importance especially as
Waterfowl Habitat was adopted in 1971.
The suslik
(Citellus citellus),
right, is a small
herbivorous
ground squirrel.
The dwarf aster
(4sfer tripolium),
right, grows only
in alkaline soils.
initiatives RECTO THE RESCUE!
When Bulgaria has problems protecting bears, when the Poles are developing ecotourism,
the Czechs want to create a cycle track in Moravia, and the Romanians are trying to encour¬
age public involvement in environmental legislation, where do they all go for help? The
answer is the Regional Environmental Center for Central and Eastern Europe (REC). Set
up in 1990 by the United States, the European Community and Hungary, the Center ini¬
tially confined its activities to Hungary, but in 1995 became an international foundation
designed to help the people of the new democracies of Eastern Europe participate in envi¬
ronmental decision-making. The countries concerned include Albania. Bulgaria, Croatia,
Estonia, Hungary. Latvia, Lithuania, Poland, the Czech Republic, Romania, Slovakia,
Slovenia, the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia, the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia,
and Bosnia and Herzegovina.
REC does not finance large-scale projects, but grants funds collected in the West to a
large number of projects put forward by accredited non-governmental organizations. Its pro¬
grammes encourage experience sharing and the promotion of regional co-operation, e.g. by
protecting the Danube, which flows through eight countries. A REC-organized seminar on
this subject enabled officials from the Danube countries to meet and work together, in some
cases for the first time.
The Center works with non-governmental organizations engaged in fieldwork, with local
authorities, governments, academic institutions, the media and the private sector.
Recently it moved to new premises in a Budapest suburb that contain a library and a
sophisticated electronic information exchange system. REC organizes a wide range of
training courses open not only to the fifteen beneficiary countries but also to participants
from Armenia. Azerbaijan, Belarus, Georgia, Kazakhstan, Moldova, Russia and Ukraine.
As well as disseminating information, the courses strengthen East-East co-operation by
bringing people together from all over the region.
REC, Ady Endre ut. 9-11, 2000 Szentendre, Hungary.
Tel: (36 26) 311 199; Fax: (36 26) 311 294
42
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
PESTICIDE-FREE RICE
Two Filipino farming couples were
recently invited to Thailand to
describe their rice-growing tech¬
niques, which use no chemical pes¬
ticides. They have not treated their
crops chemically since one of the
couples lost a son to insecticide
poisoning. Not only do they har¬
vest 10,000 kilos of rice per
hectare, they are able to sell it at
an above-average price because it is
grown organically. I
TOMORROW'S CITIES
At the United Nations Conference
on Human Settlements (Habitat
II), held in Istanbul (Turkey) in
June 1996, it was noted that by
the year 2000 an estimated 75%
of the population of the industri¬
alized nations and 45% of the pop¬
ulation of the developing nations
will be living in cities. By the year
2025, the figures will have
increased to 83% in the North and
61% in the South. By 2025 as
"fy j
i a JÉ
many as 80% of the planet's city-
dwellers could be living in the
developing countries. UNESCO is
helping to shape the future of the
world's cities via its programmes
on the Management of Social Trans¬
formations (MOST), Man and the
Biosphere (MAB), the International
Hydrological Programme (IHP), its
World Heritage Towns Network,
its programme on Street Children
and its programme to mobilize
young people for the recycling of
urban waste. M
WORLD BANK JOINS IN
LAKE VICTORIA CLEAN-UP
Lake Victoria, Africa's largest
freshwater body, is faring badly as
overfishing and oxygen depletion
are threatening fish stocks and bio¬
diversity. More than 200 indige¬
nous species face extinction, and
fisheries, an important economic
resource, face potential collapse.
Algae, especially the potentially
toxic blue-green variety, are
spreading rapidly, and the water
hyacinth has begun choking impor¬
tant waterways. Water-borne dis¬
eases, too, are on the rise. To help
fight the Lake's degradation the
World Bank has contributed fund¬
ing to a programme run by the
three riparian countries (Kenya,
Tanzania, Uganda) to help them to
manage fisheries, reduce pollution
and improve water quality. I
NEW PRIMATE SPECIES
DISCOVERED IN BRAZIL
Six previously unknown primate
species have been scientifically iden¬
tified in the Brazilian forest since
1990. The most recent is a small
white-headed marmoset (Callithrix
saterei), the size of a squirrel. The
marmosets swing their way through
the trees with great agility but
unlike other primates do not use
their long tails to hang from the
branches. The females mate with
several males, and the father car¬
ries the new-born offspring on his
back. M
A GREEN ISLAND
IN THE BALTIC
Bornholm, a 30-km-long Danish
island off the Swedish coast, relies
heavily on income from tourism
based on the island's cleanliness and
natural beauty. The island, which
has 45,000 inhabitants, adopted a
green energy programme in the
1980s, harnessing solar, wind and
waste resources. Bottles usually
carry a 1 krone deposit, and a high
proportion are recovered. Paper is
recycled or used as animal bedding.
Used batteries are returned to the
shops. One hundred families volun¬
teered to try home composting with
the result that their waste volume
went down by 24%. To discourage
ships from dumping oil and oily
water at sea, the island places a free
cleaning facility at their disposal.
Bornholm would like to swap expe¬
riences and information with other
islands and comparable regions. M
Contact Jannik Stenberg,
County of Bornliolm, Ullasvej 23
DK-3700 Ronne, Denmark.
Fax: 45 56 95 73 97.
THE HOTTEST YEAR
According to the World Meteoro¬
logical Organization 1995's global
mean surface temperature over
land and marine areas was the
warmest since records began, more
than 0.4°C higher than the mean
for 1961 to 1990. Certain parts of
Siberia in 1995 had mean temper¬
atures more than 3°C higher than
their 1961-90 figure, and heat
claimed many victims in India and
the U.S.A. In 1995 there were also
many significant climate anomalies
and major weather events such as
hurricanes, torrential rains and
droughts. After the Antarctic
spring of 1995 the surface covered
by the ozone hole phenomenon
exceeded 20 million km and the
event began earlier and lasted
longer than in any previous year on
record. M
VERSATILE HEMP
Although Indian hemp (Cannabis
sativa indica), in the form of a mind-
altering drug, often makes the head¬
lines, much less is heard about its
cousin (Cannabis sativa), once used
in sail-, rope- and cloth-making. A
French non-governmental organiza¬
tion, Terre Vivante, is keen on
redeeming this plant whose stalk is
used for making cloth, paper, insu¬
lation, building materials and ani¬
mal bedding. Its seed (hempseed)
can be converted to oil, food, soap or
detergent. Hemp is also environ¬
ment-friendly, since it needs little
fertilizer and no pesticides. Some
6,000 hectares of it are grown in
France, but the main producers are
China and Hungary. M
Terre Vivante, BP 20, 38711 Mens,
France. Tel: (33) (0) 4 76 34 80 80;
Fax: (33) (0)4 76 34 84 02
3 G>uTHE UNESCO lOURIERB DECEMBER 1996
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
H E RITAG E Both a Unesco Biosphere
Reserve and a World
Heritage site, Côte d'Ivoire's
Taï National Park is an area
of remarkable biological
diversity and home to one of
the last representative
sa m p les of fo rest wi Id life i n
West Africa.
aï National Park
byNimrod Bena Djangrang
Cape buffaloes
[Syncerus caffer).
The African landscape reveals
itself in all its splendour from
the air. As you fly over Tai" National
Park in southwest Côte d'Ivoire, near
the border with Liberia, a palette of
many shades of green stretches
beneath you, mingling with blueish
vapour trails. From the summit of
Mount Niénokoué (396 metres), in
the south of the Park, there is an
equally stunning view of the sombre
beauty of the virgin forest and its
wheeling flocks of birds.
A more down-to-earth look at the
Park tells us that it was given national
park status by government decree on
28 August 1972 in an area which had
been a "forest and wildlife refuge"
originally created by the French
administration in 1926. In 1978 the
Park was accepted as a biosphere
reserve and in 1982 it became a
World Heritage site.
Straddling the borders of the
departments of Guiglo and Sassan-
dra, the Park comprises some
454,000 hectares of dense evergreen
rain forest, to which 96,000
hectares of the N'zo Animal Reserve
were added in 1993. It is in a sloping
granitic area which flattens out near
the coast where the granite gives
way to schist. The soil in the north is
fragile although protected from ero¬
sion by dense vegetation. Further
south the soil is far more fertile, ben-
efiting from the influence of the
Hana and Meno rivers as well as
heavy rainfall (more than 1900 mil¬
limetres annually). It is around these
rivers that the 230 bird species, and
47 of the 54 species of large mam¬
mals known to occur in Guiñean rain
forest are most in evidence, as well as
primates, ungulates and carnivores.
ECOLOGICAL ELEPHANTS
The African elephant (Loxodonta
africana), ofwhich only about a hun-
THE UNESCO ÇoURIER B DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
déeih****
Ut
.*-**
m
dred specimens were left in 1994
(there were 1,800 in 1979), makes a
big contribution to the perpetuation
of the ecosystem, as secondary forest
grows largely from the dung it leaves
in clearings and fallow areas. Seeds
that have passed through the ele¬
phant's intestines seem to germinate
more easily, and in this way it sows
species that are unknown in certain
One of the many
rivers that flow
through the forest.
White-chested
guinea fowl
(Agelastes
meleagridis).
regions. Cape buffaloes (Syncerus
caffer) Uve in couples or in herds of up
to ten. They live in marshland around
the liana and the Meno in the south of
the Park and also along long-estab¬
lished trails that run through the sec¬
ondary forest. But they have a strong
preference for dense undergrowth.
Pygmy hippopotamus (Choerop-
sis liberiensis), once found in Nigeria
and today occasionally spotted in
Sierra Leone, can also be seen in the
Park. They live in couples and much
prefer conditions on land, where
they find food and refuge in case of
danger, to an aquatic environment.
They venture into open country, usu¬
ally at dusk. Researchers at a sci¬
entific station near the village of Tai
have come across them disporting
themselves on Mount Niénokoué.
Scientists are particularly inter¬
ested in the population of chim¬
panzees (Pan troglogytes verus) of
I which there are from 2,000 to
| 3,000 specimens in the Park. The
¡ chimps use tools to crack nuts, orga-
I nize hunting and food sharing and
| practise division of labour accord
ing to sex. They are elusive crea¬
tures, however, since the presence
of humans disturbs them and their
sexual cycle. Their reproduction
rate gives little grounds to predict a
population explosion.
Tai National Park is home to 230
bird species, 28 of which are
endemic to the Guiñean zone. Eight
of them are threatened, including
the white-breasted guinea fowl (Age¬
lastes meleagridis).
Of the 1,300 higher plant
species identified in Southwest
Africa, at least 870 are found in the
Park: 80 per cent of them are
endemic to the Guinea-Congo sec¬
tor and 10 per cent to the south¬
western part of Côte d'Ivoire. The
northern part of the humid primary
forest consists largely of climbing
palms with spiny blistered leaves
(Eremospatha macrocarpa), and of
Diospyros mannii, small trees
belonging to the family that includes
ebony and niangons (Tarietia utilis).
From the observation trails that run
through the Park visitors can see
the Y-shaped silhouette of these
dÇJhjithe Unesco Courier b December 1996
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
trees whose trunks soar towards the
light like a simplified human form
joyfully thrusting out a multitude
of arms. There is a greater variety
of endemic plants in the south of
the Park because of its more fertile
soil and heavier rainfall. One of the
region's rarities is also found there,
Armorphophallus staudtii, a species
that was thought to have disap¬
peared until it was rediscovered in
1977.
Ant-hills built on dead tree
trunks are found on the edge of the
trails which wind around the virgin
forest in the south and lead to the
Park's ecological station.
A BARRIER AGAINST CLIMATIC
DETERIORATION
Tai National Park faces a number
of threats . In addition to those orig¬
inating in the usual economic activ¬
ities found in forests, the arrival
since 1989 of hundreds of thousands
of Liberian refugees fleeing civil war
in their country has considerably
increased demographic pressure on
the environment. Cropland (coffee,
cacao, palms, hevea) may expand
and make inroads on the reserve's
peripheral areas. Poaching and
unsupervised panning for gold must
also be reckoned with, although
development programmes set up in
recent years (especially under the
auspices of the Dutch Tropenbos
Foundation, UNESCO's Man and the
FURTHER READING
Yaya Sangaré, "Le Parc National de Taï, Un maillon
essentiel du programme de conservation de la nature",
Working Document no. 5 (1995), South-South Co¬
operation Programme for socio-economic development that
respects the environment in the humid tropics,
Unesco, Paris, France.
Pygmy
hippopotamuses
[Choeropsis
liberiensis).
Biosphere Programme, and German
technical co-operation schemes) have
closely involved people living in the
Tai' forest.
Since 1988, a Park Development
Unit, known since 1993 as the
Autonomous Project for the conser¬
vation of the Park, has been respon
sible for drawing up and imple¬
menting an agreed management pol¬
icy. Many village committees, co¬
operative groups and local non¬
governmental organizations have
been set up and are trying to make
young people and women more aware
of conservation problems. Themain
purpose of this educational project
is to draw attention to the impor¬
tance of the forest as a means of pro¬
tection against the deterioration of
climatic conditions.
Evergreen trees in
the tropical forest.
46
THE UNESCO ^>UMER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
by Iaroslav Isaievych
hmelnytsky
(1595-1657)
In the first half of the seventeenth cen¬
tury the territory known nowadays as
the Ukraine was embroiled in the rebel¬
lion of the Cossacks, military settlers who organized commu¬
nities in the vast steppe area between the territories controlled
by the Polish government and those controlled by the Crimean
Khanate. The leading figure of this rebellion, Bohdan Khmel-
nytsky, was to leave a profound and enduring mark on the polit¬
ical landscape of this part of Europe.
Ukrainian lands were the core of the medieval Kiev state
known to historians as Kievan Rus', a commercial crossroads
between Western Europe, the East and the Byzantine Empire.
Under pressure from nomadic invasions and internal rivalries,
it split into a dozen or so smaller principalities at the beginning
of the thirteenth century. The largest of these principalities,
Galicia-Volhynia , came under the domination of the kingdom
of Poland after a period of relative independence and resis¬
tance to the Mongol conquests. Some of the others were con¬
trolled by the expanding Grand Duchy of Lithuania, before
being joined to Poland after the Union of Lublin in 1569. Early
in the seventeenth century, increasing oppression of the Ortho¬
dox peasants of the Ukraine by the Catholic Polish nobility led
to social, ethnic and religious tensions that sparked off rebel¬
lions in which the Cossacks played a leading role.
Ardent defenders of their "ancient freedoms" and champions
of the Orthodox faith, the Cossacks organized themselves behind
the Dnepr rapids into the so-called Zaporozhian Sich ("fortifi¬
cation behind the rapids") and chose Bohdan Khmelnytsky, an
officer belonging to the Ukrainian minor nobility, as their hetmán
(commander in chief) . He led a number of Cossack risings .
A good tactician, an excellent politician and an astute diplo¬
mat, Bohdan Khmelnytsky concluded an important alliance
with the Crimean Tatars that enabled him to win decisive vic¬
tories over Poland. He then began peace negotiations. As the
leader of a force that sought only to uphold its autonomous sta¬
tus, he did not at first seek territorial expansion or political dom¬
ination. As time went by, however, the Cossacks' position hard¬
ened, and a series of campaigns were waged to wrest a number
of territories from Polish dominion. A Ukrainian government was
established, led by Khmelnytsky, who proved to be a remark¬
able political leader and administrator.
A Ukrainian state was created as the continuation of Kievan
Rus'. Power was delegated by the central government to local
authorities, and Khmelnytsky introduced to Ukrainian towns
the system of autonomous municipal administration known as
A Cossack leader
whose exploits
are celebrated
in many epic
poems,
Bohdan
Khmelnytsky
was the
architect of
the first
Ukrainian state
the Magdeburg law, from the German city where it was first
established. Self-governing bodies were established in cities,
boroughs and villages, where civilian administrators co-operated
with the military authorities.
Although these were troubled times, Khmelnytsky paid
much attention to cultural development in his country, espe¬
cially by granting financial support and privileges to the monas¬
teries, which at that time were centres of education and print¬
ing. Bulos ofAleppo, who accompanied the Patriarch of Antioch,
Macarius III, through the Ukraine on his way to Moscow,
recorded his amazement when he discovered that, "All the [Cos¬
sacks], including their women and daughters, with very few
exceptions know how to read and are familiar with the Church's
liturgy and hymns. What is more, the priests instruct orphans and
do not let them wander through the streets in ignorance."
Nevertheless, the new state's prospects were not favourable.
The Ukraine was surrounded by powerful countries, and after
a major defeat the Crimean Tatars went over to the Polish side
and Khmelnytsky had to look for new allies. In 1654 he obtained
Muscovite military aid in exchange for recognizing the Tsar's
sovereignty over the Ukraine, but when he realized that Muscovy
intended to curtail Ukrainian rights, he concluded a treaty with
Sweden, which was then at war with Poland and Russia. When
Khmelnytsky died in 1657, he had not succeeded in redressing
the balance of power in the Ukraine's favour. No later hetmán
proved able to achieve this goal. M
THE UNESCO ÇpURIERB DECEMBER 1996
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Listening
Isabelle Leymarie talks to BERNARD MAURY
A talented pianist and a fine teacher, Bernard Maury is a spiritual son and
disciple of the American jazz pianist Bill Evans1. He hails from southwestern
France, where he grew up in a music-loving family.
You have often said that if rhythm is the
body of music, then harmony is its soul.
Could you enlarge on this?
Bernard Maury: When I first became inter¬
ested in jazz, as a teenager, it was
almost impossible to get hold of scores .
I'd trained as a classical pianist, but
since I hadn't studied harmony, I was
incapable of playing jazz without a
score. Sure, I could always retran-
scribe certain melodies by ear, but I
also had to find the accompaniment,
and my rough and ready chords didn't
sound anything like those I heard on
records by Erroll Garner or Oscar
Peterson, pianists whose tone colours
I admired a lot.
After a bit of practice I managed to
make sense of certain solos, butlearn-
ing chords out of their context wasn't
good enough. I wanted to know the
reason for certain harmonic configu¬
rations. For me a chord is not an iso¬
lated thing but the result of a pro¬
gression. I became interested in
counterpoint as well as harmony
because it deals with the movement of
voices. As Debussy knew, a chord has
its own intrinsic colour, which creates
a particular climate, and I wanted to
construct chords in my own way, by
controlling their tonal colour.
When I was twenty I had a few ele¬
mentary harmonics lessons , but mostly
I studied alone, soaking up textbooks,
following my own lines of research and
analysing classical works. It's very
rewarding to find out basic principles
by yourself. Playing jazz taught me to
see harmony in a different way from
that usually taught in music schools.
Harmony is a matter of logic and ear,
but it shouldn't be made too abstract.
It must live.
How did you come to jazz?
B. M.: When I was around twelve or
thirteen, I went to a lecture given by
the musicologist Hugues Panassié. It
was an eye-opener. I'd already heard
about jazz, but until then no one had
told me anything about its history
and it's part of a very different cul¬
ture from my own. In Toulouse, where
I went to study later on, jazz bands
always played at university dances. I
began to paraphrase around themes,
then I took the plunge. I've got a fairly
analytical mind, and I tried to under¬
stand how the phrases were built; I
imitated the great musicians, and I
chose my masters.
How did you meet Bill Evans?
B. M.: In 1972 he came to Paris for a
concert with his bass player Eddy
Gomez and his drummer Marty Morell .
Bill had been my idol for several years,
and I was dying to meet him. At the
time I was playing in a Paris club with
the saxophonist Johnny Griffin. One
night after our set, a couple of Amer¬
icans who'd been sitting at the bar
came over and started chatting. Pretty
soon I realized they were Gomez and
Morell. The next day a friend invited
me to have lunch with Bill Evans him¬
self! And we hit it off right away.
I had some great times with him.
When he sat down at the piano I never
missed a note. He was one of the great
names of jazz, try as he might to deny
it he was a very modest man. "It didn't
come at all naturally," he told me. "I
had to work darned hard." He would
play certain sequences again and again
so I could really understand them. He
never gave lessons, but if he felt some¬
one was receptive to his music and
could see what he was up to, he would
48 THE UNESCO QsURIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
go out of his way to explain. I had
already been trying to analyse his music
for quite a while. Two years before, I'm
not sure I would have had the faintest
idea about what he was doing.
You spent two years in Brazil. Have you
been influenced by Brazilian music?
B. M.: I loved Brazilian music before I
went to live in Rio de Janeiro the
samba, of course, but above all the
jazzy bossa nova because of its har¬
monic wealth and its poetry. Its unob¬
trusive rhythm brings out the melody
and the harmony, and the different ele¬
ments balance beautifully. Brazil has
produced extremely talented musicians
and lyricists such as Antonio Carlos
Jobim. While I was there I accompa¬
nied the singer Maria Creuza, and when
I was playing in a club in Copacabana
I teamed up with the great pianist
Johnny Alf, one of the precursors of
bossa nova.
What qualities does a student of jazz
need to have?
B. M.: You've got to be highly motivated.
It's fringe music and rarely brings fame
or riches. It's more like evangelism than
a profession. You need to be stubborn
and take the hard knocks in your stride.
You need a musical ear and sensibility,
although it's true that the ear can be
trained. You've got to be rigorous, but
you've also got to know how to let your
imagination take flight, be logical at cer¬
tain times and not at others, and know
how to forget the academic side of jazz
and let creativity take over.
What about teaching jazz?
B. M.: Most of all you have to love
music. It's a bit like religious faith,
which often goes with evangelism; you
want to share something you love. You
learn a lot from teaching because you
have to dismantle mechanisms that are
sometimes unconscious. You can play
interesting ideas intuitively, but you
need to analyse them in order to pass
them on to others, and this opens up
new horizons. Teaching is very reward¬
ing, but it's primarily a matter of giving.
I think if I hadn't taught, there are
pieces I'd have been quite incapable of
playing because I wouldn't have
understood them.
What are your current plans?
B. M.: As a tribute to Bill Evans, I've
just founded the Bill Evans Piano Acad¬
emy in Paris. We don't only teach the
piano. Bill was one of the most important
jazz pianists of the second half of the
century, up there with Bud Powell and
Thelonious Monk. Modern jazz musi¬
cians owe him an enormous debt. In the
world of jazz he's also a direct descen¬
dent of the French school of Fauré,
Ravel, Debussy, Lili Boulanger and
Henri Dutilleux. The Bill Evans Piano
Academy aside, I've got two recording
proj ects : one solo and the other playing
unpublished compositions by Bill Evans
that I'll be choosing with the help of
his family. I
1. Bill Evans (1929-1980) was a member of
the Charlie Mingus band and later recorded
solo albums, e.g. Everybody digs Bill Evans
(1938).Editor
Bill Evans Piano Academy
6, rue Damiens
92100 Boulogne Billancourt, France
Tel.: (33) (0)1 46 21 40 95.
THE UNESCO lOURIER« DECEMBER 1996
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Anniversary
1100 years ago
Hungary's appointment
with Europe
by Péter Déme
This year Hungarians have been celebrating the 1100th
anniversary of the settlement of the Carpathian Basin by
their ancestors. According to historical sources the process
actually began in 895*, when the main mass of migrants
under their leader, Arpad, crossed the Verecke Pass in
the eastern Carpathians and descended to the plain in
response to an appeal for help by Arnulf, the Holy Roman
Emperor, who was seeking to assert his authority over the
Moravians.
The Magyars were a federation of semi-nomadic, semi-
agrarian tribes which came from the East. In their new
homeland they gradually abandoned raiding and military
expeditions, and developed new social and political stru c-
tures appropriate to a more settled way of life. Arpád's
great-grandson, Geza, played a prominent role in this
process, but it was above all Geza's son Stephen (997-
1038), the first Hungarian King, who laid the foundations
of the new Hungarian state. For his coronation, which took
place according to tradition on Christmas Day, in the year
1000, he asked the Pope to send him a crown, thereby
committing himself and his country to the Western European
world. In recognition of the long process whereby the Mag¬
yars and other peoples in the region became a European
nation in the Carpathian Basin, Hungarians are already
preparing to celebrate in the year 2000 the millenary of the
birth of the Hungarian state.
* The anniversary is being celebrated in 1996 because the Hungarian Parliament
decided that the thousandth anniversary of settlement in the Carpathian Basin
should be commemorated in 1896 instead of 1895, because many of the arrange¬
ments for the commemorative celebrations were delayed. Author's note
The royal crown of
Hungary. The lower
part of the crown Is the
original sent by Pope
Sylvester II to King
Stephen I. The upper
part was added in
1175.
© National Museum of Hungary.
Budapest
AUTHORS
EZI0 MANZINI, an Italian engineer and architect,
teaches environmental design at the Milan
Polytechnic (Italy). He is the author of many articles
and (In collaboration with S. Pizzocaro) of Ecología
industríale ("Industrial Ecology", Edlzioni Istituto
per I'Ambiente, Milan, 1995).
STEPHEN P. HUYLER, an American cultural
anthropologist, writer and photographer, is curator
of an exhibition of Hindu ritual art entitled "Puja:
Expressions of Hindu Devotion', being held at the
Smithsonian Institution's Arthur M. Sackler Gallery
(Washington, D.C.) His published works Include
Painted Prayers: Women's Art in Village India (New
York, Rizzoli; London, Thames and Hudson, 1994).
MARGARET A. ST0TT, of Canada, is a specialist in
the social and cultural history of British Columbia's
First Nations. She Is author of Bella Coola
Ceremony and Art (Ottawa, 1975).
LUKE TAYLOR, of Australia, is Senior Curator at the
National Museum of Australia. Notable among his
published works Is Seeing the "Inside": Western
Arnhem Land Bark Painting (Oxford, Clarendon
Press, 1996).
VIVIANE BAEKE is a Belgian ethnologist and
curator at the Royal Museum of Central Africa in
Tervuren (Belgium).
GILLES A. TIBERGHIEN, of France, teaches the
history of modern art at the University of Paris I.
Among his published works is Land Art (Princeton
Architectural Press, New York, 1995) and Land Art
Travelling (Erba, collection 222, Paris, 1996).
NILS-UDO is a German artist who uses the fruits of
nature to create ephemeral and permanent
installations in the natural and built environment.
He recently published (In French and German) Corps-
Nature (Alain Buyse publishers, Lille, France, 1996).
MICHAEL ARCHER is a British art historian and
critic who contributes regularly to the journals Art
Monthly (London) and Artforum (New York). His
works Include Installation Art (Thames and
Hudson, London/Smithsonian Institution,
Washington, D.C, 1994) and the forthcoming Art
Since 1960 (scheduled for publication in 1997).
MICHEL CONIL LACOSTE, a French art historian
and critic, is the author of Kandinsky (Flammarlon,
Paris, 1979) and The Story of a Grand Design:
Unesco 1946-1993 (Unesco Publishing, Paris,
1993), in addition to his study of Tinguely.
FLORIAN ROTZER, of Germany, is an editor with the
German Internet journal Telepolis, Das Magazin der
Netzkultur. He is the author of Die Telepolis.
Urbanität im digitalen Zeltalter ("The City In the
Digital Age", Bollmann Verlag, Mannhelm, 1995).
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American Journalist.
NIMROD BENA DJANGRANG is a Chadian poet,
short-story writer and novelist who formerly taught
philosophy in Côte d'Ivoire.
IAR0SLAV ISAIEVYCH, of Ukraine, is head of the
history, philosophy and law section of the Ukraine
Academy of Sciences.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE is a Franco-American
musicologist.
PÉTER DÉME is director of public relations at the
Hungarian National Museum and is presently
working for Hungary's Millenary Commemorative
Anniversary Commission.
CORRECTION
The photo credit for the cover of our November 1996
issue was incomplete. It should have read: Thierry
Nectoux © Ask Images, Paris
50 THE UNESCO ^lURIER DECEMBER 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1996
JANUARY DANCE: THE SACRED FIRE
Interview with Maurice Béjart. An impulse
from within (D. Dupuy). The language of body
and soul (W. Lambersy). Drama's hidden
depths (E. Barba). Nijinsky's requiem (M.
Leca). Post-modern dance (J. Schmidt). Rein¬
venting the body (A. Amagasaki). Steps to
emancipation (W. Buonavcntura). A living
museum (A. Raftis). The dancer's dilemma (R.
Maitra). A new outlook for humanity (F.
Mayor). Heritage: The temple of Apollo the
Helper. Greenwatch: Green Cross Interna¬
tional (F. Bequette). Interview with Huang
Hai-Tai, master puppeteer (I. Leymarie). From
the UNESCO Courier. How the gift idea started
(C. Lévi-Strauss, December 1955).
FEBRUARY SECRETS OF
COMPLEXITY
Interview with Gabriel García Márquez. A new
way of thinking (E. Morin). A family tree with
roots in East and West (Yi-zhuang Chen). Cut¬
ting the Gordian knot (I. Ekeland). Frontiers of
psychotherapy (S. Fuks). The case of the dis¬
appearing dinosaurs (G. Bocchi & M. Ceruti).
Logic, cultures and individuals (M. Maruyama).
'The voice of those who never spoke' (F.
Mayor). Heritage: Olinda, sleeping beauty of
northeastern Brazil (J. F. Rosell). Greenwatch:
Mauritius (F. Bequette). Listening: Interview
with Chico O'Farrill (I. Leymarie). Reflec¬
tions: Children and violence on the screen (N.
G. Nilsson). From the UNESCO Courier. The
divorce between science and 'culture' (B. Rus¬
sell, February 1958).
MARCH THE ROOTS OF RACISM
Interview with Henri Atlan. The seeds of hate
(M. Wieviorka). Racism and anti-racism (E.
Balibar). The affirmative action debate (S. Stein¬
berg). An unscientific notion (A. Jacquard).
'Beneath the dark sun of racism' (E. Canetti).
Race, history and culture (C. Lévi-Strauss).
Dossier: A plea for tolerance; Race and racial
prejudice. The rights of future generations (F.
Mayor). Heritage: The golden stones of Sala¬
manca (J.M.G. Holguera). Greenwatch: Waste-
free manufacturing (F. Bequette). Listening:
Interview with Teresa Laredo (I. Leymarie).
From the UNESCO Courier. The image and the
word (A. Moravia, January 1972).
APRIL EDUCATION FOR THE 21ST
CENTURY
Education for tomorrow (J. Delors). 'Learning
to be' in retrospect (A. Deleon). The education
of prisoners (S. Duguid). Opening new doors in
science education (F. Gros). Sharing knowledge
(P. Lena). Science made simple (J. V. Narlikar).
The hands-on approach (G. Delacôte). Schools
at the crossroads (R. Bisaillon). The prospects for
teachers (B. Ratteree). Distance education: inter¬
view with Mcnahem Yaari. Africa: a fresh start
(F. Chung). The children of Confucius (Zhou
Nanzhao). Fact file: UNESCO's worldwide action
for education. 1996: International year for the
eradication of poverty (F. Mayor). Heritage:
Talamanca-La Amistad (F. E. Gonzalez). Green¬
watch: Chernobyl today (F. Bequette). Listening:
Interview with Jocelyne Béroard (I. Leymarie).
From the Unesco Courier. The rarest, most
precious vital force (M. Curie, October 1967).
MAY SILENCE
Interview with Hervé Bazin (M. Leca). Men
of few words (Interview with C. Wondji).
Between two worlds (M. Smadja). The last
refuge (M. Benasayag). The height of silence
(Interview with H. Nisic). A mystic journey (K.
Erguner). Music, time, eternity (E. Sombart).
Painting the void (Interview with Kumi Sugai).
A moment of fulfilment (C. Louis-Combet). An
inner experience (J. Castcrmane). The city, envi¬
ronment and culture (F. Mayor). Heritage: The
rune-stones of Jelling (J. Boel). Greenwatch:
World tourism: where next? (F. Bequette). Lis¬
tening: Interview with Marcel Khalife (I. Ley¬
marie). From the UNESCO Courier. Looking
at life with the eyes of a child (H. Matisse,
October 1953).
JUNE CORRUPTION
Interview with Ismail Serageldin. Roots of a
long tradition (B. Fontana). The underside of
globalization (F. Lewis). Corruption and
democracy (D. della Porta). A hidden enemy
(M. Germaniangue-Debare). Easy come, easy
go (R. Andriambelomiadana). Glasnost and
after (L. Pliushch). The virus of power (E. R.
Zaffaroni). What can be done? (R. Klitgaard).
The press for peace (F. Mayor). UNESCO past
and present (J. Sopova). Heritage: A monastery
in the mountains (C. Chiclet). Greenwatch:
Waterworlds (F. Bequette). Listening:- Inter¬
view with Galina Gorchakova (I. Leymarie).
From the UNESCO Courier. 'Culture must be
one of the foundations for world understanding'
(A. Einstein, December 1951).
JULY AUGUST M UNESCO THROUGH THE
LOOKING-GLASS
(comic strip special)
Preface (F. Mayor). J.-C. Mézières. L.
Cornillon. J.-C. Denis. E. Point/J. Vertigo.
Narès. Fred. Delius. Vals. Juillard. Loustal.
Terpant. Truong. D. Sire. Caro. Petit Roulet/
Martiny. Aloys. Jano. A. Goetzinger. Druillet.
Mocbius.
SEPTEMBER CULTURE AND
DEVELOPMENT
Interview with Javier Pérez de Cuéllar. A
matter of choice (A. Sen). Back to the drawing
board (L. Arizpc). The age of the migrant artist
(M. Haerdter). The resurgence of religion
(Interview with J. L. Esposito). A recipe for dis
possession (Interview with S. Kothari). A
vicious circle (T. Heath). Unequal partners
(N. G. Canclini). Culture in the city (J. M.
Schuster). Living in tomorrow's cities (F.
Mayor). Heritage: The last days of Chan Chán
(A. Pita). Greenwatch: Sonora, a living desert
(F. Bequette). Listening: Interview with
Doudou N'Diaye Rose (I. Leymarie).
OCTOBER EXILES
Interview with Werner Arber. A land of no
return (A. Sayad). The coolies' odyssey (K.
Torabully). A journey' of self-discovery (B.
Nedelcovici). Travellers from a far country (I.
Kadaré). The roots of the banyan tree (R.
Dcpestre). The brain drain (C. G. Guadilla).
Refugees: the rising tide (R. Brauman).
Restricted entry. The struggle for peace (F.
Mayor). Heritage: The medina of Fez (G. Darles
& N. Lagrange). Greenwatch: Palawan, the
Philippines' last frontier (F. Bequette). UNESCO
philosophy forum (G. Schimmel). Reflections:
Culture first (C. Fabrizio). Listening: Inter¬
view with Juan Carlos Cáceres (I. Leymarie).
From the UNESCO Courier. A tiny bubble in the
silence of the infinite (R. Tagore, August 1957).
NOVEMBER THE MARKETPLACE
Interview with Hervé Télémaque. The birth of
Homo Economicus (A. Caillé). Tlatelolco, shop
window of the Aztec empire (M. R. Yoma
Medina & L. A. Martos López). The merchants
of Venice (D. Calabi). Open market or closed
shop? (M.-F. Garcia-Parpet). A tradition of
cross-border trade (A. S. Afouda). Friday in
Carpentras (M. de la Pradclle). A puzzling trans¬
ition (Y. Levada). Company capitalism (H. Oku-
mura). Market globalization (M.-F. Baud). The
rise of the stock market (E. Vaillant). Poetry, an
education in freedom (F. Mayor). Greenwatch:
Hawaii Volcanoes National Park (F. Bequette).
Heritage: Baroque churches of the Philippines
(A. F. Villalón). Listening: The hidden voice of
Frederic Mompou (I. Leymarie). Anniversary:
Jean Piaget, a foundational thinker (R. Schu-
maker). From the UNESCO Courier. The psy¬
chology of marbles (J. Piaget, November 1980).
DECEMBER EPHEMERAL ART
Swimming against the tide (E. Manzini). A
moment of grace (S.P. Huyler). Dancing with
masks (M.A. Stott). A bridge to the past (L.
Taylor). Cosmetics and culture (V. Backe). Land
art (G.A. Tiberghien). Working notes (Nils-
Udo). Installation art (M. Archer). From image
to environment (F. Rotzer). Higher education
and new technologies (F. Mayor). Greenwatch:
Lake Fertö (F. Bequette). Heritage: Tai National
Park (N. Bena Djangrang). Portrait: B. Khmel¬
nytsky (I. Isaievych). Anniversary: Hungary's
appointment with Europe. Listening: Interview
with Bernard Maury (I. Leymarie).
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
