<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="105001eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
MICROFINANCE
HELPING THE POOR
TO HELP THEMSE \ k
INTERVIEW WITH
JOHAN
GALTUNG
HERITAGE:
COLONIA DEL
SACRAMENTO
(URUGUAY)
ENVIRONMENT:
PEOPLE AND
PLANTS
M 1205-9701 -22,00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ENCOUNTERS
To our readers
Since our regular "Encounters" feature first appeared,
on the inside front cover of the July 1989 issue, your tal¬
ented and imaginative contributions have abundantly
illustrated the range of the creative cross-fertiliza¬
tion that the feature is intended to encourage.
The invitation we issued then is still open to all our
readers: "Send us a photo (of a painting, a sculpture,
or a piece of architecture) which you regard as a good
example of cultural cross-fertilization. Alternatively,
send us pictures of two works from different cultural
backgrounds in which you see a striking connection
or resemblance. Please send a short caption with your
photos. Each month we will publish one of your
contributions."
In anticipation of many more rewarding encounters.
THE EDITORS
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (OURIER
Johan Galtung,
one of the founders ofmodern peace studies,
proposes apracticed approach to conflict
resolution (p. 4).
rnntpntç
JANUARY 1997
I C R 0 F I N A N C E
HELPING THE POOR
TO HELP THEMSELVES
Month by month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rífaat 8
Reaching the unreached by Sayeeda Rahman 10
A new weapon in the war on poverty by José Garson 12
Three golden rules by María Otero 16
Where credit is due... by Robert Peck Christen 18
A bank for the poor by Muhammad Yunus 20
Microfinance in Indonesia by Marguerite S. Robinson 24
Latin America: acción speaks louder than words by Maria Otero 28
Enterprise in Africa by Kimanthi Mutua 30
Village banking: a report from 5 countries by Rupert Scofieid 32
Three microcredit schemes in Europe by Maria Nowak 36
Fact file 39
Consultant: Sayeeda Rahman
Colonia del Sacramento (Uruguay),
The majestic architectural legacy
ofa historic town on the estuary of the Rio
delà Plata (p. 46).
Commentary Federico Mayor
GREENWATCH
People and plants by France Bequette
HERITAGE
Colonia del Sacramento remembers Its turbulent past by Edouard Bailby
LISTENING
David Sanchez talks to Isabelle Leymarie
AUTHORS
Cover: A transaction in a loan and savings bank run by and for women in Burkina Faso.
© M. Dorigny/UNFPA/REA. Paris
40
42
48
50
THE UNESCO ^ÏURIER JANUARY I
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
meó
Johan Galtung
Professor Johan Galtung, of Norway, is one of What is the educational purpose of peace
the founders of modern peace studies. He studies?
established the International Peace Johan Galtun9: A maJ"r Wl,s «r.H-aee education
is to enable and empower people to handle con-
Research Institute, Oslo (PRIO), in January
1959 and the Journal of Peace Research in
diets more creatively and less violently. This is
what I mean hy peace; education, and a lot of
1964. He has published Over 70 books, the knowledge and skills, theory and practice are
most recent Of Which is Peace by Peaceful required for it. Peace studies is an applied social
Means: Peace and Conflict, Development and science, just as medicine is applied anatomy,
Civilization (Sage Publications/PRIO, 1996). Vty and pathology. It is only meaningful
if it leads to action. The goal is not more hooks,
hut more peace.
Here Johan Galtung talks to the Courier
about the guiding principles of his career as
a peace theorist anda peace field-worker. How are Peace stud1es structured?
Interview by Natascha Batic J.G.: To understand peace and violence we need
to consider hasic human needs for survival,
well-being, freedom and identity. Development
aims to promote those needs: violence insults
them: peace preserves them.
As I see it there are three types of violence
and hence three types of peace: direct, struc¬
tural and cultural. Direct violence insults human
needs with the deliberate, intention to hurt and
harm; structural violence does so more indirectly.
Cultural violence is symbolic, and refers to those
aspects of our cultures that are used to legit¬
imize direct or structural violence.
These three notions can be taught dialecti-
cally, with their negations direct peace, struc¬
tural peace, cultural peace. It makes no sense to
focus on only one of them. Conflict is part of a
double, yin/yang totality: both Creator and
Destroyer. Deep inside a conflict there are one or
THE UNESCO IpURIER« |ANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
© Lenzenwenger, Schlaining, Austria
more contradictions or incompatibilities. When
handled creatively they can be the driving force
of human social and moral development. Gandhi
is a rich source of creative and non-violent inspi¬
ration for the theory and practice of both sides
of conflict.
When did peace studies become a university
discipline?
J.G.: Sometime around the late 1960s and the
early 1970s. Today the subject exists in some
form in at least 500 universities and colleges
around the world, but mainly as a theoretical, lit¬
erature-oriented subject.
Two leading centres for peace studies arc the
European University Centre for Peace Studies
(EPU) and particularly the courses in civilian
peace-keeping at the Austrian Study Centre for
Peace and Conflict Resolution in Schlaining
south of Vienna (which won the U.MiSCO prize
for peace education in 1995), and the Institute
for Conflict Analyses and Resolution at George
Mason University in Fairfax, Virginia (U.S.A.).
Theory and practice go hand in hand in each of
these institutions. Rut many other places are
coming up. We need at least 1,000 of them with
at least 10,000 graduates a year.
What teaching methods are used?
J.G.: They are not so different from those used in
medicine. Theoretical work has to be combined
with case studies and practice, but students
should only go into the field when they are ready.
Many do this too early, as amateurs or dilettantes,
sometimes causing harm. Most never get closer to
reality than some university library. (There is
room for those, too.)
Rut it cannot be said too strongly that peace
studies must be action-oriented and empowering
for ordinary people in civil societies.
What do you think of the idea that conflicts
should not necessarily be avoided or suppressed, but
that violence and destructiveness call for positive
intervention?
J.G.: This is a truism. In a sense it's a bit like say¬
ing "weather should not necessarily be avoided
or suppressed, but destructive, violent weather
calls for some protection". It makes me think of
politicians and diplomats who talk about "con¬
flict" when they actually mean "violence", and
"peace" when they mean "cease-fire". Such sloppy
talk makes people fail to see a conflict before it
erupts into direct violence and then they only see
its negative, destructive aspect. There is also a
common failure to see that the situation after a
cease-fire is usually worse than before the vio¬
lence because of the invisible damage of violence,
for instance to structure and culture.
Is there a difference between 'positive
intervention' and peacekeeping, peacemaking or
peacebuilding?
J.G.: There certainly is! I would prefer people
to be empowered for self-intervention rather
than some managerial top-down intervention by
others. Positive intervention should be creative,
non-violent and empathie. People should know
how to do it.
What do you feel about peace enforcement?
3.G.: This is a very last resort, like a surgeon car¬
rying out an amputation. The term stands for
violence, and in my experience violence breeds vio¬
lence, regardless of how many Security Council
THE UNESCO COURIER JANUARY 1997 %
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
n t e rvi e w
f
Johan Gattung
resolutions and "advanced democracies" stand
behind it.
One definition of conflict resolution is to use
conflicts non-destructively and creatively 'to
promote needed social change'. Is social change an
inherent part of human experience?
J.G.: To me daoism gives the answer to this ques¬
tion. Contradiction is inherent in all life, and
hence conflict is ubiquitous. Human needs and
wishes are enormously complex. Society is sim¬
pler, structured in response to formulas deep in
the culture, and incapable of catering to all these
needs and wishes. Some of them will be repressed
and hence contradictions will germinate. Sooner
or later they will surface in attitudes and behav¬
iour and lead to social conflict. Social change will
be demanded to solve some problems, at the
expense of creating others. And so on. That
process is called history.
When is social change necessary?
J.G.: When the basic needs of human life and life
in general have been insulted or there is a threat
thereof, and when this is a structural/cultural
process, i.e. not just the result of the whims of
some ruler or ruling group. Democracies handle
this better than non-democracies. That is why we
need human rights, the whole repertory of the
International Bill of Human Rights, to intervene
at the bottom of societies and protect minori¬
ties. The problem is that so far we have only
heard from the West; we also need the contri¬
butions of other civilizations.
What is your own theory of social change?
J.G.: I could never be the slave of only one theory;
I try to be eclectic. Peace studies take you along
all kinds of highways and byways. Ars longa,
vita brevis. My theories are relatively complex,
and in any concrete situation I would use as many
of them and others eclectically, as I would
find necessary.
In the late 1950s and early 1960s I worked on
rank-concordant, feudal and -discordant systems
in order to locate sources of social change and on
ways in which concordant world structures com¬
bine into highly rigid, imperialist structures.
Since then I have been working on various
forms of violence, visible and invisible, and their
peace counterparts; and on the theory and prac
tice of reconciliation after violence. And also on
deep cultures in various civilizations or social
cosmologies as I call them, in an attempt to trace
their impact on macro-history, particularly for
peace and conflict and development, including
the destruction of the social fabric, values and
norms which is so rampant today. I have also
been concerned with pathological cosmologies
and possible therapies; with the collective sub¬
conscious of various nations, and with hard-soft
and transcendent-immanent aspects of religions
and other cultural manifestations.
In philosophy I have been concerned with apo-
dictic thinking in the Occident and its role in
utopianism and fundamentalism; especially as
this is expressed in the leading ideology of the
West today, economism based on egocentric cost-
benefit analysis. In political science I have worked
on the origin of the state system from feudal times
and its pathologies. In economics I have been par¬
ticularly concerned with externalities and how
they can be internalized in an equitable manner,
both within and between countries in new trade
theories. As a futurist I have been concerned with
better, less violent social and world systems. All of
these are or can be read as theories of peace and
social change.
As a peace and conflict worker 1 have also been
concerned with the fascinating steps involved in
putting theory into practice; including my own
efforts in twenty-five conflicts. So far.
Can social change arise from a natural,
spontaneous movement rather than force?
J.G.: Sometimes it is natural, spontaneous; some¬
times it is very deliberate. Sometimes it is non¬
violent, sometimes violent. I believe in deliberate
change to reduce dukkha (suffering) and bring
about sukha (happiness, enlightenment) as a
Ruddhist would say. It does not come by itself.
Working for this is itself sukha.
Is humankind doomed to live in a perpetual
state of crisis?
J.G.: No. Problems yes, crises no. There is no rea¬
son to be apocalyptic. Some problems, even
crises, are solved; others arise, hopefully at a
higher level, although I am far from sure of that.
How should we learn to discard the old and live
with the new peacefully?
6 THE UNESCO ÇlURIERi JANUARY I
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
3.G.: I don't think we should. The point is not
old/new but dukkha/sukha. Monks in a monastery
often know more about this than people sur¬
rounded by possessions. And yet I do not think
their truth is universal. I am a strong believer in
pluralism, not only in ideas but in social forma¬
tions, as long as they are nonviolent. The basic
problem is not to do things that cannot be undone.
Our action should be reversible. We may be wrong.
If we do something irreversible that is also wrong,
we create violence for those who come after us.
Reversibility is for me a much better guide than
universalizability. Non-violence follows from this
principle since we cannot recreate life.
When traditionally determined role
relationships are disrupted, what is the role of
culture as a means of understanding and
communication?
J.G.: That kind of disruption happens all the
time, and the result is what Durkheim called
anomie, an absence of compelling values and
norms. People then seek old or new sources of
meaning, and many find them in what others call
sects and try to discredit as "fundamentalism".
We shall get much, much more of this as we go
on destroying not only cultures hut old social
fabrics in the name of globalization, creating a
society of empty monads, what 1 call "atomic".
What role should international organizations
play in this situation?
J.G.: I see more possibilities for non-governmen¬
tal organizations (NGOs) than for inter-govern¬
mental organizations, given the pathologies of
the state-system, particularly the narcissistic
and paranoid behaviour of certain "big powers".
I think it was an act of genius on the part of the
United Nations to give NGOs a voice during major
UN conferences. This is our world civil society,
our world public space. The NGOs will have to
come to grips with the devastating impact of
what passes for free markets, including labour
flexibility on a global scale. The system is now
creating mass unemployment and misery on a
hitherto inconceivable scale, trying to destroy
all alternatives. On the other hand, as I pointed
out above, the alternatives will themselves bring
in their wake new problems that will also have to
be taken seriously. Such is life.
B
Johan Galtung conducts
a seminar.
What can be done to make education for justice
and peace efficient at grassroots level?
J.G.: I think most of this education is invisible.
The major teachers are still the mothers, the
kindergarten workers, the millions teaching in
elementary and other schools, the religious peo¬
ple in their churches, mosques and temples, peo¬
ple running organizations in a participatory man¬
ner, and many others. Rut often their messages
are harsh, exclusive, filled with hatred.
What is the impact of a worldwide form of
communication to which there is no equal access?
J.G.: There never has been a form of communication
with perfectly equal access. The range, speed and
volume were always unequally distributed. Rut, if
other social goods like education and money are
reasonably distributed, then communication will
follow, like the red telephones that dot the Japan¬
ese land- and city-scapes and are accessible to
almost everyone. I am more worried about one-way
communication like TV, and the enormous amount
of disinformation traveling on those famous high¬
ways, all the virtual realities we are encouraged
to confuse with the reality where real people meet
their real dukkha andsukha. That is the world we
live in and peace studies try to come to grips with
one bundle of problems: violence. Communication
is one of the tools. Education, formal and infor¬
mal, is another. I see that as a source of light in our
dark century. M
THE UNESCO Q^^R" JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
TBfe UNESCO
Courier
^^50lhYEAR
Published monthly in 29 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31. rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15,
France.
Fax: (33) (0)1 45.68.57.45
e-mail: unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet: http://www.unesco.org
bridging the
Director: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition: Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Film duplication: Daniel Meister
Secretariat: Annie Brächet
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian: Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Steven Van de Rijt (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mmgxian (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Katri Himma (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Aliyu Muhammad Bunza (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax: (33) (0)1.42.73.24.29
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68.45.65). Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salan El Dm
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45.68.49.19)
Customer service: Michel Ravassard,
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45.68.45.91)
Accounts: (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68.45.65)
Shipping: Daniel Meister (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel.: (33) (0)1.45.68.45.65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier',
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts can¬
not be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco
or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on
maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier
is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco,
7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox),
Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition.
Indian Head Inc., Ill West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.: (4) Bell
and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - JANVIER 1997
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N.M. P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure:
Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z.l. Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malsherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N' 1-1997-0PI-97-555 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 50-51.
8
) ÇowTHE UNESCO ^_OURIER JANUARY 1Q07
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
pOVerty gap by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
For most of us the words finance, credit, savings and investment call to mind
the world of big business and banking activities on a very large scale.
The idea that these major financial circuits could somehow be miniatur¬
ized might seem to fly in the face of reason. For some time, however, this
is what has been happening.
Finance and poverty no longer inhabit two different worlds. On every
continent tens of millions of families who once lived on the margins of soci¬
ety now have access to facilities for credit, savings and investment on a
very small scale. The term microfinance has been coined to describe their
transactions. So important has microfinance become that a world summit
is being devoted to it this coming February in Washington, D.C.
What has happened to bring about this departure from traditional
banking practice? What are the real conditions that underlie this change?
What can be expected from it, especially as a weapon in the war on
poverty? This issue of the Unesco Couríerattempts to answer these and other
important questions about microfinance.
No one imagines that microfinance is a panacea for poverty. But it can
indubitably bring hope to men and especially to women, many of them illit¬
erate, whose economic activities have hitherto been so precarious and spo¬
radic that they have never been statistically recorded. The hope is that they
can break out of the vicious circle of destitution and escape from the
humiliations of lifelong rejection by society.
But what is really new is not that these people are beginning to feel
the stirrings of hope, but that certain banks are starting to take them
seriously and are responding by reviewing their goals and methods and
adjusting to the demands of small-scale economic activity.
Perhaps this is because poverty in many countries has reached such pro¬
portions that it is threatening to throttle economic activity, destroy social
cohesion and sabotage development. When the gap between poverty and
prosperity becomes so flagrantly wide, when the numbers of the unem¬
ployed, of society's outsiders and rejects become so high, there comes a
moment when the only question worth asking is what can be done to
bring them back into the community .
THE UNESCO ^>URIER1 JANUARY 1907 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
REACHING
THE UNREACHED
BY SAYEEDA RAHMAN
vcr the past two decades, local
I institutions in different parts of
the world have developed innov¬
ative mechanisms to provide credit
and savings facilities for those who were tra¬
ditionally excluded from the formal financial
sector. These "microfinance institutions"
(MFIs) have devised original financial services
delivery systems for the very poor and have
succeeded in reaching segments of the popu¬
lation previously unreached by such facilities.
They have demonstrated that, contrary to
conventional wisdom, the poor are good credit
risks and have high savings propensity.
MFIs are now operating in rural and urban
areas of Asia, Latin America and Africa within
a wide range of social, cultural and economic
environments. They use different methodolo¬
gies, have a number of institutional arrange¬
ments and exist in a variety of policy settings,
but share a common concern: the alleviation of
poverty.
The methodology most frequently used
by the leading MFIs is that of "group lending"
to units ranging in size from small thrce-to-
tcn member "solidarity groups" to village
banks composed of approximately thirty to
fifty members. Group members collectively
guarantee loan repayment, and access to sub¬
sequent loans is dependent on successful
repayment by all of them. Risks and admin¬
istrative costs per borrower are thus reduced
and the group guarantee serves as a substitute
for collateral requirements.
Growing demand
MFIs provide very small short-term loans,
usually for twelve months. The prospect of
subsequent larger loans is a strong motivation
for repayment. Although most MFIs charge a
relatively high rate of interest, the repayment
rate is notable and demand is increasing, sug¬
gesting that it is not the cost but the timely
and continual availability of microfinancc
which is important for poor clients.
The initial focus was on micro-credit facil-
10 THE UNESCO ^)URIER JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
itics, and it tended to be forgotten that pro¬
vision for saving can be as important as credit
if not more so, for poor rural households. In
more recent programmes, however, increased
attention is being paid to mobilizing volun¬
tary savings in order to make loans more
widely available.
MFIs are based on the principle that provi¬
sion of financial services for the poor must be sit¬
uated in localities close to the clients, and func¬
tion as a set of small local units linked by a
central body. Several of them have made a specific
policy decision to target poor women, first
because access to resources and services is even
more difficult for them than it is for men, and
second because of their stronger repayment per¬
formance and willingness to form groups.
Although successful MFIs in different parts
of the world have removed conventional mis¬
conceptions about the "bankability" of the
poor, it must not be forgotten that their ser¬
vices do not reach the majority of the world's
poor. Having overcome the initial obstacles to
M loan from the Grameen
Bank enabled this family in
Dhaka (Bangladesh) to build a
new house.
obtaining funds and authorization to set up
their programmes, the MFIs thus face the chal¬
lenge of expanding their operations. With this
in view they are trying to reach a stage where,
independent of external funds or subsidies, all
their costs arc met from interest charges, and
loan capital requirements are met by borrow¬
ing from local commercial sources.
So far, only a handful of commercial banks
have shown interest in taking on the microfi¬
nance client group. This is because the legal
and regulatory framework within which the
formal financial institutions operate is not
favourable to microfinance practices. Policies
which maintain interest rates artificially low,
especially for credit to the poor, do not allow
the banks to cover their costs and so they have
remained outside this field. A fresh approach
to this question would encourage the formal
banks to extend their reach to sections of the
population they have hitherto ignored.
Social and cultural
support programmes
Non-governmental organizations (NGOs)
have played a vital role in channelling credit
and other services to the poor, and growing
numbers of them arc moving towards trans¬
forming themselves into full-fledged institu¬
tions specializing in finance. NGOs working
at the grassroots level can help commercial
banks to reach the poorest clients in remote
areas and, where required, monitor, supervise
and collect loans.
But in order to alleviate poverty for more
than a billion people today, progress in the
field of microfinance will have to be comple¬
mented with supporting programmes and ser¬
vices, notably taking into account the social
and cultural dimensions of development. The
responsibility for devising mechanisms to
ensure that these additional services also reach
a maximum number of poor households
resides not with the MFIs but with other
development partners.
UNESCO is exceptionally well placed to take
up this challenge. It can contribute to the cam¬
paign to explore ways and means of increasing
access to microfinancc for the poor on a com¬
mercially viable basis and to develop new tech¬
niques for providing appropriate services to
this difficult-to-reach population. With this
in view, UNESCO has entered into a co-operation
agreement with the Grameen Bank (see page
23). It envisages similar forms of collaboration
designed to support the clients of other suc¬
cessful MFIs with complementary programmes
in the fields of education, science and technol¬
ogy, and culture and communication.
THL UNESCO f3>URILRB JANUARY 1097
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
A NEW WEAPON IN THE WAR ON POVERTY
BY JOSE GARSON To be fully effective, microfinance must slot
into a broad strategy for cultural, educational
and social development
V¡liage women in Burkina
Faso learn the basics of
accountancy.
It all began with a simple question. What
operational definition can governments
or co-operation agencies use for poverty,
I independently of the sufferings of the
needy? In other words, what should anti-
poverty programmes try to do and how
should their success be measured?
After some hesitation, economists came up
with a practical definition that incorporated
scales ofpoverty and measured progress in alle
viating it. A person who has a much lower
income than that of the rest of the population
and who is deprived of any real access to basic
services (health, lodging and education) is
regarded as living in poverty. In a given popu¬
lation, the poor are those whose incomes are
lowest and who therefore consume least. They
are those who have the worst quality of life,
since they are excluded from the public services
which the state provides for its citizens. Poverty
alleviation, in this context, means focusing on
a precise target those sections of the popula¬
tion with a much lower income than the rest
via these two parameters. A poverty alleviation
programme achieves its goal if it produces a
sustainable increase in the income of the poor¬
est segments of the population.
Self-help projects
Of course formulating an operational defini¬
tion does not mean that we have the financial
muscle to get rid of poverty. Developing coun¬
try governments and co-operation agencies
do not possess sufficient resources to grant
subsidies that would sustainably increase the
income of each person defined as poor. Any
large-scale increase in the income of needy peo¬
ple must come from elsewhere.
Very early on, some developing countries
mainly in Asia realized that this "elsewhere"
could be the poor themselves, on condition
that they were associated with poverty allevi¬
ation policies. After all, they reasoned, many
needy people have sufficient initiative and
energy to devise small projects or activities
that, once underway, could increase their
income. By providing successive increases in
income, such projects could gradually lift these
people out of poverty without direct and mas¬
sive state intervention.
Before this could happen, obstacles to the
creation of small projects had to be identified,
and the poor who so wished had to be pro-
THE UNESCO INJURIER« |ANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
vidcd with the wherewithal to get round them.
One of the chief obstacles was credit, which
banks do not usually channel to small-scale
projects, especially those undertaken by the
poor, who are by definition not very credit¬
worthy. By granting credit selectively to the
enterprising poor, governments and co-oper¬
ation agencies hoped to initiate a sequence of
events that would lead to the creation of
income-generating economic activities, thereby
kbove, a training centre in
Ghana where women learn
craft skills and receive loans to
help them start up small
businesses.
" I he main challenge for
microfinance will soon be
cultural, educational and
social." Below, an outdoor
lesson in Nepal.
alleviating poverty. Here was the first link
between credit and poverty.
From credit to savings
But generating additional income by granting
credit to the working poor only alleviates
poverty among a small part of the population.
What about the rest, the overwhelming major¬
ity? Credit is of no use to this majority, but sav¬
ings certainly are.
To understand this, it is necessary to analyse
what actually happens in the poorest and most
isolated parts of developing countries. In these
regions all monetary transactions are made in
cash. Since there are no banks, people have to
keep all their possessions with them. A trans¬
action can only be completed if each party to
it has a wad of notes, with the concomitant
risk of loss and theft. At best, someone who
wants to "invest" his savings can do so by
purchasing an animal. In these circumstances it
is difficult for the very poor to accumulate
sufficient resources to escape from poverty.
The absence of institutions that make it pos¬
sible to transform cash into a deposit and then
into savings is a hidden but genuine reason
why poverty is so intractable and persistent.
THE UNESCO (^OURICR JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Mt a centre in Daghestan, a
Chechen refugee woman
The poor cannot save effectively and trans- makes duvets t0 seM on the
actions between them involve countless diff i- market,
culties because there arc no on-the-spot financial
intermediaries to provide the basic financial ser¬
vices that would permit the emergence of eco¬
nomic activities to lift their region from poverty.
In addition to credit, then, microfinance
the process which encourages the development
of financial intermediation at the local level
is one of the most powerful weapons in the
M cotton spinner in Laos.
struggle against poverty and economic isola¬
tion. Banks, specialized non-governmental
organizations (NGOs) or a combination of
the two are the architects of this development.
The next steps
In the traditional method of doing business or
saving, a poor person needs common sense
but docs not need to know how to read or
write. On the other hand, in a relationship
with a financial intermediary and in the
world that the financial intermediary gradually
creates around itself people must become lit¬
erate; they must participate culturally in the
world of reading and writing. Traditional busi¬
nessmen carrying their money in their pock¬
ets transact business which is their own affair
and no one else's. When they open a bank
account, however, they must understand that
the money they deposit is also going to serve
others the people to whom the bank issues
credit. They must understand that this money
is both theirs and other people's. They must
recognize and accept a fact of life of which
they were ignorant.
This explains why the arrival of microfi¬
nance is profoundly disturbing for some soci-
TME UNESCO QiURIERB |ANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
eties. The mechanisms of traditional relation¬
ships with self, others and the community
are shaken. The very structure of language can
become an obstacle, as in some southern
African languages where the same verb desig¬
nates the act of borrowing and lending. Co¬
operation agencies must therefore be cautious
and avoid prejudice. A credit scheme in which
40 per cent of borrowers do not repay their
loans is not necessarily a bad scheme in itself.
If four borrowers out of ten have not kept
their end of the bargain, it is because repay¬
ment of a loan within a given time frame is
behaviour that is not innate but is acquired
culturally in societies where borrowing is
widely practised. A good scheme must take
these factors into account in its initial analy¬
sis of the local population's needs.
The challenge
Microfinance's main challenge will soon cease
to be financial and become cultural, educa¬
tional and social. Bilateral and multilateral co¬
operation agencies working with the World
Bank and the leading microfinance networks
have met to examine all the financial questions
that microfinance can raise. In two or three
years' time, the different methods of imple¬
menting microfinancc systems will all have
been tested.
The next step will be to build on the far-
reaching revolution begun by the Asian pio¬
neers, Grameen and Bank Rakyat Indonesia
(BRI), continued by others such as BancoSol
in Latin America and taken further by African
initiatives such as the Kenya Rural Enterprise
Programme (K-Rep).
Microfinance opens doors by creating sol¬
idarity groups, by insisting on the need for
personal repayment disciplines and by think¬
ing of individual activities in social terms. If it
is to develop, action must be taken to pro¬
mote literacy, education, craft learning and
health care among the populations it is aimed
at and via the social structures it has set up.
Only this cultural, educational and social
development will keep microfinance in sight of
its original purpose and ensure that it remains
a weapon in the war on poverty.
fishermen's huts on the
banks of the Mekong River.
K^^l^^
THE UNESCO Q>URIER> JANUAR'
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
. ' ,** íT\..:a£*ji¿'¡
THREE GOLDEN RULES BY MARIA OTERO
Mbove, women tea pickers on
a plantation in central Sri
Lanka.
iny economic units operating at the
margin of the "modern" sector or
outside it are the major source of
employment in urban areas through¬
out the developing world. In some cities, more
than half of the economically active popula¬
tion are employed in these "microenter-
prises"as carpenters, shoemakers, street ven¬
dors, trash recyclers, and in innumerable other
businesses of varying sizes and sophistication.
Microenterprises operate outside the laws
and regulations that govern formal business
activity. They are not licensed as businesses,
generally do not fulfil the legal labour require¬
ments (social security, benefits, taxation), and
operate informally, often employing non-
paid family members. Other characteristics
include a lack of division of labour or special¬
ization in the workplace, lack of accounting
procedures, serious limitations in accessing
capital, the prevalence of businesses located in
the owner's home, and more important, the
lack of access to information, technology,
training and bank credit.
Although some microenterprises belong
to relatively well-to-do individuals, the vast
majority of their owners come from the poor¬
est sectors of the population and have seldom
completed secondary education. Most
microentrepreneurs live in the slums of large
cities and therefore lack access to public services
and to adequate housing.
The technology for lending to microen¬
terprises has improved greatly in the last few
years through the work of such institutions
as Bank Rakyat Indonesia (see page 24), the
Grameen Bank (see page 20) and ACCIÓN
International (see page 28). The lending
16 THE UNESCO ^URIER JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
schemes run by these institutions share the
following core characteristics that make them
highly effective:
* Familiarity with the market. Microenter-
prise institutions know that the poor are will¬
ing to pay for access and convenience. Their
major need is for small short-term loans to
cover working capital needs and liquidity con¬
straints.
Microentrepreneurs need these loans
quickly with little paperwork or other time-
consuming requirements. Microenterprise
institutions locate branches near the client,
provide simple application procedures and
disburse funds quickly. The institutions charge
interest rates that are higher than commercial
banks, but much lower than the moneylenders
who are the major source of credit for the
poor.
* Techniques to cut administrative costs.
Successful microcnterprise institutions use
the simplest procedures to distribute very
small loans. Loan applications often fit onto
one page, and approval processes are decen¬
tralized. Most institutions use group lending
techniques in which borrowers guarantee each
others' loans and also assume part of the loan
processing burden. These groups are often
comprised of three to five individual microen¬
trepreneurs and are modeled on the informal
savings and loans groups that exist through¬
out the world. The group known as a soli¬
darity group or peer group receives a loan
via one transaction, divides it among its mem¬
bers and assumes responsibility for managing
the loan.
*" Techniques to motivate repayment.
Microenterprise institutions also use small
groups as mechanisms to assure repayment by
everyone in the group. The promise of repeat
loans in increasing amounts is available to
those whether in individual or group lend¬
ing schemes who pay back on time. This
assurance of continued access to credit is a
powerful incentive that has enabled effective
microcnterprise institutions to maintain very
low loan loss rates, often below 2 per cent.
The application of these lending principles
enables microenterprisc institutions to accom¬
plish two key goals: to expand their outreach
so they can reach tens or hundreds of thou¬
sands of borrowers; and to cover their costs
through the income earned, thereby becoming
self-sufficient in the long term. The most
advanced institutions have demonstrated that
they can cover their operational and financial
costs and therefore are able to make the tran¬
sition from donor money to borrowed funds
from commercial lending institutions.
FINANCE
FOR THE NEEDY
The Grameen Bank (Bangladesh) is probably the best-known micro-
finance institution in the world. It started asan action research pro¬
gramme in 1976 and was transformed into an independent bank by
government ordinance in 1983. Operating throughout rural
Bangladesh, the Grameen Bank mainly serves very poor women. (See
page 20)
The Bank Rakyat Indonesia (BRI) is a state-owned commer¬
cial bank. BRI's Unit Desa (banking) System is an extensive network
of unit-banks operating throughout Indonesia as an independent
profit centre. The voluntary savings scheme which it designed mobi¬
lizes considerable amounts of savings, and loans are fully financed
by these deposits. The Unit Desa is a significant source of profit for
BRI. (See page 24).
The Kenya Rural Enterprise Programme (K-Rep) was established
in 1984, and in 1987 became a non-governmental organization
(NGO) working in both ruraland urban areas. Initially K-Rep promoted
Kenyan NGOs' credit programmes by providing grants, training and
technical assistance and later developed its own direct lending pro¬
gramme. (See page 30).
The Foundation for International Community Assistance
(FINCA) is a U.S.-based nonprofit organization that specializes in
rural credit. FINCA developed the village banking methodology and
administers programmes using this methodology in different parts
oftheworld.(Seepage32).
Banco Solidario, S.A. (BancoSol) started operations in 1992
as the first private commercial bank devoted solely to microenterprises.
It operates in major cities throughout BoLivia. BancoSol grew out of
PRODEM, an NGO affiliated with ACCIÓN International, a U.S.-based
non-profit organization. (See page 28).
Sayeeda Rahman
THE UNESCO ^)URiERl JANUARY1997 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
WHERE CREDIT IS DUE...
BY ROBERT PECK CHRISTEN
M<I embers of a
craftswomen's savings and
credit group meet in Sumatra
(Indonesia).
ave you ever tried to sell half a goat
without killing it because you only
needed ten dollars? The question
may seem absurd but it sums up a
dilemma that faces many poor people in the
developing world. Saving and lending are part
of their everyday lives, as they are for the rich.
However, economists would say, they have
fewer options than the rich for managing their
liquidity through financial instruments and
they save in inferior stores of value such as
goats and construction materials.
For the privilege of having more money up
front (loans), you pay. This is because the lender
cannot be totally certain that you will be able
to fully repay the amount advanced against
your future cash flow and probably has other
opportunities in which to invest the money
advanced to you. The borrower's greatest con¬
cern is not what interest rate I am going to
charge him or how profitable the venture will
be that he undertakes with my resources, but
rather, when and how much will he have to
repay. Avery profitable business opportunity
or a great personal need may have motivated
him to borrow a certain amount in the first
place. Maybe the quality of my credit service
made him choose me over my competitor. But
ultimately, his decision to enter into a credit
agreement with me has much more to do with
whether I can offer him repayment terms that
coincide with his projected cash flow so he can
meet his payments safely.
Going the whole hog
To use a common example from microlending.
Many village banking programmes lend tiny
amounts of money to very poor women so
that they can initiate an economic activity such
as fattening a hog. Most of these lending
methodologies require repayment on a weekly
or monthly instalment basis since this tech¬
nique seems to reduce the levels of default
among borrowers. In fact, repayment levels
among women who fatten hogs they buy on
credit is very high.
But where do they get the money to repay
the loan? Clearly it can't come from the hog.
It must come from some other income source.
In fact, we often see careful microentrepre¬
neurs setting the amount of their instalment
loan payment to the value of sources of income
they receive on a steady basis such as rent fro m
property they own or salaries someone in the
household receives, irrespective of the cash
flow they expect to receive from the invest¬
ment activity carried out with the loan.
When does a microloan generate economic
"development", if it essentially fulfils a cash
flow management function?
It can do so in a number of ways. When the
up-front nature of a credit relationship allows
microentrepreneurs and small farmers to take
advantage of a specific economic opportunity,
they can increase their incomes. When, through
access to credit, borrowers reduce their costs by
purchasing in larger volumes, take advantage of
sales of discounted merchandise, and replace an
THE UNESCO COURIER« JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
*
i ,
f*
VV-W
+,* >>
Trié
r
informal moneylender, they can generate an
immediate increase in income. Microentrepre¬
neurs may also use a loan to increase their sales
by financing their clients to allow them to
pay in instalments for the goods they have
purchased. Credit may allow borrowers to
increase their productive or commercial capac¬
ity through the purchase of major assets more
rapidly than would be possible through the
simple reinvesting of the proceeds of their
businesses. Credit may allow them to under¬
take activities which they would otherwise
not have the resources to finance.
An enormous number of microentrepreneurs,
Mbove, a baby sleeps in a
hammock strung above a bed
of apples in the Xinjiang
region of western China. Many
microenterprises are home-
based family businesses.
I his Togolese hairdresser
joined a small enterprise
development loan programme
in order to take part in its
savings scheme.
small farmers and fishermen, and others who
earn their living independently could benefit
from the efficient provision of microcredit ser¬
vices on the part of specialized financial insti¬
tutions. They cannot take advantage of eco¬
nomic opportunities that they sec out there,
because they do not have access to rapid and
appropriate sources of finance at reasonable rates
of interest. This fact has led many to enthusi¬
astically endorse the idea that "credit creates
economic opportunity, hence development".
A dangerous illusion
This simplistic belief lies at the heart of the
failure of many microcredit schemes to achieve
high repayment rates. The sponsors and
administrators of these failed programmes
forget that it is economic opportunity that
creates greater income potential and, eventually,
prosperity. Only when credit allows individ¬
uals to take advantage of economic opportu¬
nity can it contribute to prosperity.
No amount of credit to small farmers who
produce traditional staple crops has allowed
them to leave poverty behind, as long as farm
gate prices remain depressed to favour urban
consumers, rural marketing and physical infra¬
structure remain undeveloped, and rural tech¬
nology remains inappropriately simple. Rather,
rural credit programmes to traditional farmers
with strict repayment enforcement could very
easily wind up removing peasants from their
THE UNESCO Q>URIERB JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
land once their indebtedness reached unaccept¬
able levels.
Successful microcnterprise credit initiatives
over the past twenty-five years have focused
their loans on target groups who, through
credit, could gain access to real economic
opportunity. Concretely, most concentrated
their lending in non-farm enterprises that had
been in existence for at least one year prior to
the loan, and that demonstrated a clear repay¬
ment capacity.
These programmes have funded individu¬
als and the cash flow of their ongoing business
activities. By considerably shortening average
loan terms, they opened the opportunity to
re-lend to the same clients greater amounts if
their business had prospered with the original
loan. If, on the other hand, as frequently hap¬
pens, the projected increase in sales failed to
materialize, the loan repayment was not nec¬
essarily jeopardized since it was based on the
cash flow stream of the original level of busi¬
ness activity.
Encouraging results
An intuitive grasp of the essentially fungible
nature of loan funds led the organizers of these
programmes to the conclusion that it was
fruitless to spend great effort tracking the end
use of funds, once disbursed. Instead, they
saw the merit of developing a long-term rela¬
tionship with clients and found that by get¬
ting to know them over a scries of financial
transactions the credit risk would be consid¬
erably reduced. They developed community or
peer group based lending technologies that
generated information about potential par¬
ticipants' willingness to repay and generated
incentives to do so.
These approaches produced results. Better
programmes were routinely able to produce and
sustain repayment levels above 98 per cent. Since
the loans went to low-income individuals who,
through credit, gained access to real economic
opportunity, it was possible to charge suffi¬
ciently high rates of interest to fully cover oper¬
ating costs. When programmes recover 98 per
cent of their loans and more than cover their
operating costs, they can grow exponentially
and serve ever greater markets. Furthermore, the
history of economic development has clearly
shown that a well functioning financial system
will make a big contribution to overall local
prosperity as confidence in financial systems
increases the pool of local savings and the avail¬
ability of resources for investment.
) r
W THE UNESCO (^pURIERB JANUARY 1997
Heleads held high,
a group of Grameen Bank
members in a village near
Dhaka, the capital of
Bangladesh, give a
purposeful salute that
symbolizes their refusal to
accept poverty and
submission.
I n 1972, the year after Bangladesh became
I independent, I began to teach economics
I at one of the country's universities. Two
I years later the country was hit by a dev¬
astating famine. On the campus I was teaching
complicated theories of development while
outside people were dying in hundreds. Con¬
ventional economics suddenly seemed hollow.
The classroom was a world apart from the real¬
ity of poverty and struggle outside. I left it
and stepped out into the villages of Bangladesh.
I started talking to people for whom life
was an endless struggle for survival and learned
things that I had never encountered in text¬
books. I met a woman who worked hard mak¬
ing bamboo stools. At the end of each day she
had made only two pennies, hardly enough
to buy two decent meals. I could not under¬
stand how anyone could work so hard for so
long and receive so little. I found out that to
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
small amounts of money to the poor. They
did not think it was possible to hand out
money without collateral. Since poor people
by definition had no collateral, the banks
refused to deal with them. I went from one
bank to another. They all said the same. I
offered to act as guarantor for the loans. This
was acceptable to them for a few more loans,
amounting to a few hundred dollars.
All the poor people who contracted these
loans repaid the money. I went back to the
banks, showing this as proof that poor peo¬
ple repay their debts and that there was no
need to insist on collateral. The bankers said,
it may work in this one village but it wouldn't
work in many. I tried the same scheme in many
villages. All the poor people who borrowed
paid back. I went back to the banks. They said
it may work in a few villages but it won't
work in an entire district. So I extended the
scheme to an entire district. It worked. The
banks remained unpersuaded.
I said to myself, why am I running after the
bankers? Why don't I solve the problem by
setting up my own bank? And so I asked the
Central Bank and the Government for per¬
mission to set up a special bank for poor peo¬
ple. It took a long time but the Government
finally gave permission in 1983. Grameen Bank
was born as an independent bank, a bank for
the
A BANK FOR THE POOR
poor
BY MUHAMMAD YUNUS
M weekly meeting of Grameen
Bank members in a
Bangladesh village.
Banks that lend only
to the rich
The conventional banking system has been
deliberately designed to be anti-poor, gender
biased, and anti-illiterate.
The idea of "collateral", which bankers
regard as sacred, is to push the poor away fro m
banks. But any good banker who looked at
buy her raw material she had to borrow from
a trader, who took most of the money and left
the woman with very little. I realized that if
the money she needed were available at normal
interest rates the woman would earn enough to
reinvest and make higher profits. She could earn
a decent living and escape from poverty.
I spoke to forty-two other people in the
village who were trapped in poverty because
they were dependent on loans from traders
and money-lenders. Their total credit require¬
ment was only thirty dollars. I lent them the
money out of my own pocket. I thought that
if normal banking institutions would do like¬
wise, these people could leave poverty behind.
However, conventional banking institutions
do not make loans to the poor, especially to
rural women.
The bankers I met laughed at me. They did
not think it was their business to hand out
HE UNESCO ÇïURIERB JANUARY 1997 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
our banking system in Bangladesh would be
horrified. Millions of dollars are lent to very
rich people who never bother to pay back. The
repayment rate of our industrial banks, which
lend money to rich people in the name of
industrialization, has been less than 10 per
cent over the past fifteen years. "Why call your¬
self a bank?" I ask them. "Why not take your
signboard down and put up a new one saying
something like 'Charity Organization for the
Rich'?"
Banks do not like women. They do not
want to lend money to women. There are
"Ladies' Branches" all over Dhaka city designed
to serve women only i.e., designed to get their
money. Lending to them is a very different
story. In a Bangladeshi bank, if a woman wants
to borrow money, she is asked whether she has
discussed it with her husband. If she says "Yes"
she is asked, "Is he supportive of your pro¬
posal?" If the answer is still "Yes", she is asked
to bring him along to talk the matter over. No
male borrower is asked whether he has dis¬
cussed the idea with his wife, or whether she is
supportive of it, or whether he would like to
bring her along to discuss the proposal. I would
think that less than 1 per cent of borrowers in
Bangladesh are women. There must be some¬
thing wrong with the system.
Banks demand that clients write everything
down. In Bangladesh, where 75 per cent of the
people cannot read and write, this is a ridicu¬
lous situation. Even when people bring money
to deposit in the bank, they have to write
down every detail on paper. I asked why banks
cannot simply take money and issue a receipt
saying "received such and such an amount of
money from such and such a person?" Why
must the depositor have to do all this writing?
When I first challenged this notion, bankers
asked me how records could be kept without
reading and writing. My reply was that banks
could issue receipts for amounts received or
disbursed, and that all the necessary account¬
ing could be done by the bank. Why punish
the illiterate person?
The Grameen system
Grameen Bank now operates in over half the
villages of Bangladesh. It has over two million
members, 94 per cent of whom are women. Over
$1.7 billion have been disbursed so far, and more
than 300,000 houses have been built with
Grameen housing loans. Depositors, saving only
one or two taka per week, have managed to save
over $120 million. This has been achieved because
Grameen Bank is pro-poor, pro-women and
supportive of the illiterate.
Grameen Bank rejected collateral-based
banking as a structural impediment to the par¬
ticipation of the poor, and introduced instead
group-based lending and peer monitoring to
ensure both the selection of needy clients and
2?
the maintenance of high repayments. Groups
of five are formed with members from homo¬
geneous backgrounds who know and trust
each other. Six to eight groups are integrated in
one centre. Each village will generally have one
or two centres. Instead of making people come
to the bank, Grameen goes to the people. All
financial transactions take place at weekly cen¬
tre meetings. This lowers transaction costs as .
well as making the banking institution sub¬
ordinate to people's needs.
Ninety four per cent of Grameen mem¬
bers are women. This emphasis on women is
based on the fact that women arc the most
oppressed within the ranks of the poor and,
more importantly, because giving credit to
poor women translates into greater welfare
within the household. Unlike men, women
in rural Bangladesh spend almost all their earn¬
ings on the family and plan for the family's
future. There is also a social dimension to the
emphasis on women group members. Women
who had earlier rarely ventured out of their
houses now come to group meetings; women
who had previously never handled cash now
keep accounts and engage in financial transac¬
tions; women who had never been visible in
public now become assertive and confident.
Most Grameen members have no formal
schooling. At Grameen they are taught to sign
their names, to count and keep accounts. Bank¬
ing procedures are simple and transparent.
Members discuss among themselves and learn
to keep track of their money without having
to use difficult forms. Simple receipts arc
issued so that record keeping is simplified.
With her fourth loan from
the Grameen Bank this
Bangladeshi woman bought a
dairy cow.
THE UNESCO QjURIIER JANUAR1 ]<>97
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
I hanks to a loan from the
Grameen Bank, Angurl (above)
is no lorigar dependent on
middlemen for the bamboo she
uses to weave baskets.
Grameen has led to a virtual transforma¬
tion of rural society. Numerous studies on the
Bank have shown that it has increased the eco¬
nomic well-being of its members. Grameen
loans have contributed to the building of
sturdy houses, to better health and sanita¬
tion, and to higher school attendance. Studies
have also pointed to the increasing power of
women, to their challenging of conventional
norms discriminating against them, and to
their greater political participation. While
much remains to be done to alleviate poverty
UNESCO AND THE GRAMEEN BANK
In September 1995, Unesco signed a memorandum of understanding with the Grameen Bank in which
the two organizations pledged to combat poverty by joining forces in their specific areas of com¬
petence. Unesco's participation in the co-operation scheme has so farinvolved:
« designing a basic education programmefor Grameen borrowers and their families directly
related to their economic activities;
<* providing the Bank with technical assistance in setting up a company which now brings
cellular telephones to needy rural women in Bangladesh;
'expert advice on the exploitation of solar power and other renewable energy
sources;
training programmes and workshops for Member States interested in adopting
theGrameen Bank model. A workshop forCentral Asian countries was held at Bishkek (Kyrgyzstan)
in March 1996 and has been followed up by a study visit of the Grameen banking mechanism in
Bangladesh.
*" producing an information kit explaining theGrameen Bank's philosophy, mechanism and
success (published in English, French and Spanish).
and end inequality and gender discrimina¬
tion, microcredit in Bangladesh, as practised by
the Grameen Bank, has provided one simple
strategy that works.
Poverty alleviation
initiatives
We at Grameen, however, are not content to
stop here. We dare to dream of microcredit
paving the way for poverty alleviation once
and for all. The Grameen family is thus work¬
ing on expanding agricultural productivity
through environment-friendly integrated agri¬
cultural methods. We arc promoting the devel¬
opment of fisheries. We are expanding local
markets by linking weavers from the heart¬
land of Bangladesh to retail outlets in the
United States and Europe through the export
of "Grameen check" clothing.
We strongly believe that the most advanced
technology should be appropriated by the poor.
We are thus working on harnessing solar and
wind energy, and on providing telecommuni¬
cation facilities to every village in Bangladesh.
This will not be organized by wealthy corpo¬
rations. Access to credit will ensure that poor
rural men and women arc both the owners and
users of such products and services.
1 Muhammad Yunus talked about the Grameen Bank
in an interview published in the September 1995 issue
of the Unesco Courier. Editor
THE UNESCO ^_OURIERB JANUARY l<)97
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
MICROFINANCE IN INDONESIA
BY MARGUERITE S. ROBINSON A nation-wide banking netw
: " '
A branch of the Bank Rakyat
Indonesia.
Wn ithin the last two decades, the
Bank Rakyat Indonesia
(BRI), a large state-owned
commercial bank, has shown
via its "unit desa" or local banking system
that the demand for microfinance can be met
sustainably on a large scale.
BRI has traditionally been specially
assigned by the government to provide bank¬
ing services to the rural areas of Indonesia with
particular emphasis on agricultural credit. In
the early 1970s it developed its unit desa sys¬
tem in order to provide subsidized govern¬
ment credit to rice farmers. More than 3,600
local bank units were established, function¬
ing primarily as channelling agents for subsi¬
dized rural lending programmes.
The long-term results were similar to those
found in many other developing countries.
First, the low-interest, and therefore desir¬
able, loans tended to reach local elites who had
the influence to obtain them. Secondly, lower-
income people typically did without credit
or borrowed on the informal commercial mar
ket for much higher interest rates. Thirdly,
both arrears and losses were high.
Savings accounts began to be offered in the
unit banks in the mid-1970s. However, annual
interest rates were set by the government at
12 per cent for loans and 15 per cent for most
deposits; given this negative spread the bank
could not cover the operating and other costs
required to attract voluntary savings. By 1983
the unit banking system had reached a point
at which it would have to be either closed
down or converted into a fundamentally dif¬
ferent system.
Wrong assumptions
During the 1970s, the unit banking system
had mobilized deposits of only about $17
million nation-wide. This was widely attrib¬
uted within the government and the formal
financial sector to the lack of local demand for
financial services, absence of "bank-minded-
ness" and mistrust of banks that were assumed
to characterize Indonesia's rural population.
These assumptions were wrong.
In June 1983 the first of a series of major
financial reforms was announced. Government
banks were now permitted to set their own
interest rates on most loans and deposits.
Among its other purposes, this deregulation
served to provide an enabling environment
for the transformation of BRI's local banking
system. Following the reforms, the govern¬
ment decided that the subsidized unit banks
would be converted into a sustainable system
of commercial banking at the local level, and
that a programme of general rural credit at
commercial interest rates would be imple¬
mented through the unit banking system.
After an initial period, the loan programme
would be financed by locally mobilized sav¬
ings. Commercial microfinance in the unit
THE UNESCO QïURlCRB |ANUARY1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
«* m <gimi « n
" It is estimated that
institutionalized finance is
unavailable to over 80 per cent
of all households in developing
countries."
banks began in 1984 in the rural areas. In 1989
the unit banking system was extended to
urban areas as well.
In January 1984 BRI began its new pro¬
gramme of general rural credit, called
KUPEDES', offered throughout its unit
banking network, and by 1986 a new set of
savings instruments had been introduced pro¬
viding, for the first time at local level, the much-
in-demand combination of security, conve¬
nience, confidentiality, liquidity, and returns.
These instruments, along with the KUPEDES
credit programme, were offered in BRI's unit
banks throughout the country. The spread
between loan and deposit interest rates was set
to cover all costs and to return a profit.
Since 1984, BRI's unit banking system has
performed spectacularly. As of the end of 1995,
it held deposits of about $2.7 billion in about
14.5 million deposit accounts, and there was
about $1.4 billion in KUPEDES credit out¬
standing to about 2.3 million borrowers. The
KUPEDES long-term loss ratio was 2.3 per
cent. In 1995 return on assets for the unit
banking system was 6.5 per cent. Unit bank
deposits, a highly stable source of funds,
finance all KUPEDES loans.
A 1996 report by the World Bank states
clearly the reasons for the success of BRI's
unit banks:
"The programme succeeded because the
banks loaned at market rates, used income to
finance their operations, kept operating costs
» low and devised appropriate savings instru-
I ments to attract depositors. By mobilizing
£ rural savings, [the unit banking system] was
A MASSIVE GAP BETWEEN
SUPPLY AND DEMAND
Despite widespread demand, it is estimated that institu-
tionalfinance is unavailable to over 80 per cent of all house¬
holds in developing countries. This, of course, includes
the vast majority of the poor peoplein the developing world.
The massive gap between supply and demand occurs for two
primary reasons. Those who hold the power do not see the
ubiquitous microfinance demand; those who see the demand
do not hold the power.
In the former case, local demand for microfinance is
eitherinvisibletoitspotentialinstitutionalsuppliers, orthe
latter believe that it would be unprofitable for them to meet
this demand. Misunderstandings about local financial mar¬
kets are widespread on the part of many governments, finan-
cial institutions and donor agencies. It is generally
assumedwronglyboth thatthe cost of delivering finan¬
cial services at the local level is too high for non-subsi¬
dized institutions, and thatthe informal market satisfies
demand.
Since there is little incentive to meet an unrecognized
demand, or one that is considered unprofitable, the level of
institutionalcommercial microfinance globally has remained
very low. M.R.
THE UNESCO Q51"11"" JANUARY 1907 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
\J raftswomen hand-paint
cloth in a Balinese (Indonesia)
workshop.
not only provided with a stable source of
funds, it also kept financial savings in rural
areas, thus helping development growth in
the countryside. Other reasons for success
included: the simplicity of loan designs, which
enabled the banks to keep costs down, effec¬
tive management at the unit level, backed by
close supervision and monitoring by the cen¬
tre; and appropriate staff training and perfor¬
mance incentives."2
There are three main reasons why BRI's
experience is important.
First, it has shown that the high cost of
small loans can be substantially reduced and
that financial institutions can profitably pro¬
vide microcredit to large numbers of bor¬
rowers, delivered locally with low client trans¬
action costs, at much lower interest rates than
those normally paid by lower-income bor¬
rowers for informal commercial credit.
Informal commercial lenders in many
developing countries typically charge lower-
income borrowers a "flat" monthly interest
CREDIT IS NOT
A PANACEA
Poverty alleviation requires a toolbox. Credit is a powerful
tool, but it cannot be the only one. It is used effectively
when it is made widely available to the working poor.
Among the poor, the hungry, the destitute, the aged and the
ill, those who live in regions severely deprived of resources,
and those escaping from natural or man-made catastro¬
phes have prior needs: food, medicine, shelter, employment.
M.R.
A small textile business
funded with a loan from the
Bank Rakyat Indonesia.
rate ranging from about 5 per cent to over 40
per cent on the original loan balance. Money¬
lenders may offer lower rates to better-off and
more influential borrowers, but in general the
higher rates are charged to the poorer bor¬
rowers who have the fewest alternatives. In
contrast BRI's local banking system offers a
flat monthly interest rate that is at or below 1.5
per cent on the original balance of the loan.
No additional fees arc charged to borrowers
who pay on time.
A self-sufficient institution providing
microfinance must, of course, charge higher
interest on loans than those charged in the
same country by large urban banks provid¬
ing commercial and corporate loans. This is
necessary because it is much more expensive
to deliver financial services locally to many
customers in thousands of locations than it is
to deliver these services to relatively few clients
with much larger loans and deposit accounts
in large urban branches. However, sustainable
microfinance institutions provide loans at far
lower interest rates than lower-income bor¬
rowers can normally receive otherwise.
Secondly, BRI has made credit widely avail¬
able. Various institutions in developing coun¬
tries supply credit at the local level in the form
of subsidized loans, but since subsidies are
capital constrained by government or donor
budgets, this form of credit can meet only a
small fraction of demand. Being cheap and
desirable, it tends to reach local elites, not the
26 THE UNESCO ^)URIER« JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
that on-going subsidies are required for micro-
finance in developing countries. The institu¬
tions that on-lend donor funds at subsidized
interest rates, that combine social and financial
services and that do not mobilize voluntary
savings effectively have not (and cannot)
become self-sufficient. Some arc highly effec¬
tive at providing credit to large numbers of
poor people and in recovering loans. How¬
ever, institutions of this type have been depen¬
dent on large amounts of continuing donor or
government injections of low-cost funds. The
demand for institutional microfinance is too
large for this approach on a global scale.
1 KUPEDES is an acronym for Kredit Uraura
Pcdcnnan, or general rural credit. Editor
2 World Bank News (1996).
poor. From the borrower's point of view, the
key words in microcredit arc access and cost.
Subsidized loan programmes do not provide
wide access, and while moneylenders provide
access it is generally at a cost that precludes
microcnterprise growth.
The third lesson to be learned from BRI's
experience is that voluntary savings promote
institutional viability. Institutions that pro¬
vide microcredit on a commercial basis have
an incentive to make arrangements that are
appropriate for small saver demand. These
institutions can meet a high demand for sav¬
ings services. They set a spread between loan
and deposit interest rates that is adequate to
cover all costs, including the non-subsidized
cost of funds, and to enable institutional pro f-
itability and growth in equity. Such institu¬
tions can become fully self-sufficient. There is
much evidence to show that they can mobilize
massive local savings, in amounts that are small
on average, but large and stable in aggregate.
The necessary although not sufficient
conditions are an enabling macro-economic
environment, a reasonable level of political
stability, an appropriate legal and regulatory
framework, an adequate degree of monetiza-
tion and infrastructure development, and suit¬
able demographic conditions. Given these con¬
ditions, institutional microfinancc can achieve
both profitability and wide coverage.
The new institutional commercial micro-
finance challenges the widespread assumption
he owner of this grocery
shop took out a loan from the
Bank Rakyat Indonesia (BRI).
'THE BANK IS A SERVANT,
NOTA KING'
The relationship between microfinance and socialand eco¬
nomic development is best understood-and best
expressedby the clients of commercial microfinance insti¬
tutions. The comments below were made to the author by
microfinance clients of two banks.
Savings services are the subject of many comments by
clients. As this comment by a BRI client living in rural
Java, shows:
"Before, we did not have so many employment oppor¬
tunities. We kept our savings in animals or gold, and we kept
cash in the house. Now, except for a small amount, we do
not like to keep money and gold in the house. Because we
are working, there is not always someone at home. There is
a security problem, and we cannot sleep peacefully at night
if we keep money and gold in the house. We can keep sav¬
ings in up to eight goats. After that there is too much
work to care for the goats, and the shepherds are all in
school. But we have more savings than eight goats. We
could buy a cow, which is less work than eight goats. But
we cannot cut off the ear of the cow when we have to pay
the school fees. We preferto put our savings in banks."
One long-term client of Indonesia's oldest microfi¬
nance bank, the Bank Dagang Bali, said:
"I grew up poor and without education. I learned,
though, that I could improve myself, and thatthe bank
would help me. The president of Bank Dagang Bali is a
great man. Why do I say that? Not because he is a bank
president; thereare many bank presidents. Because he knew
that poor people fear banks, and he taught us not to be
afraid. BDB taught us something important that we never
knew before. BDB taught us thatthe bank is nota king. It
is a servant." M. R.
THE UNESCO QjUR'ER« |ANUABYI997 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
LATIN AMERICA: ACCIÓN SPEAKS
Alain Pinoges/CIRIC. Paris © Alain Pinoges/ClRIC, Paris
The story of
BancoSol, the
first private
vUll iiCívIdl
bank for micro
WoIforkmen trim wood in a
Bolivian sawmill whose owner
took out six loans from
BancoSol in a year in order to
buy machines and hire more
hands.
ÄCCION International is a U.S.-
based private non-profit organiza-
i tion that currently provides tech-
*nical assistance to a network of
institutions in thirteen countries in Latin
America and six cities in the United States. Its
network of eighteen independent organiza¬
tions in Latin America has lent over $1 bil¬
lion to microenterprises in the last five years,
in loans averaging less than $500.
Three of the most advanced institutions
in the ACCIÓN network started their pro¬
grammes as non-profit organizations and have,
in the last five years, converted into regulated
28
financial institutions that are part of the finan¬
cial system in their countries but specialize in
serving the microenterprise sector. One of the
most successful of these institutions is Ban¬
coSol in Bolivia.
Solidarity groups
Banco Solidario, S.A., or Bancosol, grew out
of a non-profit joint venture created in 1986
by prominent members of the Bolivian busi¬
ness community and ACCIÓN International.
The latter brought with them leadership and
seed capital, while the former provided tech¬
nology and methodology. PRODEM, as the
programme was named, provided credit and
training to broaden employment opportuni¬
ties for the very poor self-employed, encour¬
age investment in microbusinesses, and increase
the income generated by this sector. PRODEM
used the group lending technique of "solidar¬
ity groups" and began making small working
capital loans.
In its first five years of operation, PRO¬
DEM financed loans to over 13,300 microen¬
trepreneurs, 77 per cent of whom were
women, disbursing over $27 million in loans
averaging $273. The default rate remained close
to zero during this time. In five years, PRO¬
DEM was unable to recover only about $2,000
of the $27 million it lent.
Many factors contributed to PRODEM's
success. The most important were the orga¬
nization's commitment to total quality,
including 100 per cent repayment; investment
in training employees; and a powerful man¬
agement information system. By the end of
1991, PRODEM had a portfolio of $4 million
THE UNESCO 0>u RIERB JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
LOUDER THAN WORDS BY MARIA OTERO
Local branches of BancoSol
in La Paz (Bolivia). Centre, the
information desk of the Garita
district branch. In background
is a poster which says, "I've
got to make a repayment every
Monday." Left, customers
inside the El Alto district
branch. Far left, the entrance
to the branch.
© Alain Pinoges/CIRIC, Paris
and realized that despite its success, it was only
reaching a small percentage of the market that
needed its services. .
The enormous demand, coupled with
PRODEM's desire to provide savings services
to its borrowers and to access capital markets
for funds, moved PRODEM's leadership
towards the transformation of this non-profit
institution into a fully chartered private com¬
mercial bank specializing in microfinancc
the first in the world.
The transition required two years' work
which began in 1989. The process included
raising the equity capital required by Bolivian
Be> elow, a fruit and vegetable
vendor In the El Alto district of
La Paz. She took out eight
loans from BancoSol over a 4-
year period. The last loan was
50 times bigger than the first.
law before it would charter a bank; designing
the bank's financial structure, as well as its
projection for profitability; training staff;
and meeting the requirements of the Bolivian
Superintendency of Banks.
BancoSol opened its doors in 1992. PRO¬
DEM transferred to BancoSol its $4 million
portfolio in exchange for shares, making PRO¬
DEM the largest shareholder of this newly
formed bank. Other shareholders included
ACCIÓN, Calmeadow from Canada, which
had been very instrumental in the formation
of the bank, Fundes from Switzerland and
ICC, the Inter-American Development Bank's
private arm.
Small is profitable
After four years of operation, BancoSol is
currently serving nearly 70,000 clients through
twenty-nine offices. This clientele constitutes
about 40 per cent of all the banking clients in
the Bolivian banking system. It is interesting
that while BancoSol's loan loss remains very
low and in 1994 it registered the highest return
on assets in the Bolivian banking system, its
clients very low income people of indige¬
nous background, mostly women requiring
very small loans are not considered bank¬
able clients by other banks. Currently, Ban¬
coSol lends approximately $80 million a year,
in short-term loans averaging below $600. Ban¬
coSol's outstanding portfolio is some $35 mil¬
lion, about one fourth of which is funded
through savings deposits. Its plans are to con¬
tinue expanding its coverage in Bolivia, to
increase its mobilization of savings, and to
maintain itself as a profitable bank that ser¬
vices a population that has never had access to
financial services.
BancoSol's success is helping reshape
Bolivia's financial system. In 1994 the Super¬
intendency of Banks created a new type of
regulated financial institution to enable other
financially strong non-profit organizations
to become regulated and thereby expand the
availability of financial services to this sector.
Institutions in other countries are also learn¬
ing from the experience of BancoSol and adapt¬
ing it to their own settings. K-Rep in Kenya,
Acción Comunitaria del Peru, and Genesis in
Guatemala, for example, are following Ban¬
coSol's lead and in the next two years plan to
become regulated financial institutions spe¬
cialized in microfinancc. H
THE UNESCO COURIER« JANUARY 1997 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ENTERPRISE IN AFRICA
BY KIMANTHI MUTUA
Mm
and s
lega
rar from empty-handed.
Members of a women's tontine
in Cameroon, above, put their
notes on the table. They use
the tontine banking system,
based on mutual confidence
among its participants, as a
springboard into the business
world.
^pSäk
I he Kenya Rural Enterprise Pro¬
gramme (K-Rep) is one of the
largest microfinancc institutions
(MFIs) in Africa. Since it was
founded in 1984, it has made available over
50,000 loans worth $17 million and is now
financially sustainable. It is currently trans¬
forming itself into a regulated financial insti¬
tution, just as MFIs in other African countries
are doing in order to tap their financial markets
for funds, and thus minimize or eliminate
dependency on donors.
A new strategy
At first microfinance in Africa was usually
handled by institutions that ran social wel¬
fare projects, and little attention was paid to
promoting financial sustainability. The pro¬
jects did not reach large numbers of people
and were criticized for not being cost effec¬
tive. There was no clear strategy.
Next, many African MFIs looked to the
experience of other continents, notably Asia
and Latin America. There was a major change
of method, whereby training and technical
assistance were hived off from the delivery of
financial services. This "financial systems
approach" is now widely followed by MFIs in
Africa, including K-Rep.
In its early years K-Rep supported credit
p rogrammes that were tacked on to social wel¬
fare programmes, providing them with grants,
training and technical assistance. Over time it
became clear that welfare and relief institu¬
tions found it difficult to adapt to the finan¬
cial systems approach and that the mix of
credit delivery and training of entrepreneurs
was having a limited impact.
K-Rep therefore adopted a new strategy
in 1989, notably by changing the form of its
financial support from grants to loans. Finally
it started its own direct lending scheme,
Juhudi Chikola.
30
HE UNESCO COURIER JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Abundant choice
When it decided to establish a bank, K-Rep
considered the question of whether or not to
continue with its other development activi¬
ties, and whether these goals could be achieved
by a bank. Its response was to go on with
these activities because it believes that micro¬
financc is not a panacea to development prob¬
lems. Microcnterprise development, for exam¬
ple, has limitations in terms of reaching the
poorest of the poor. To remain relevant to the
constituency of the poorest, it is necessary to
develop new instruments and products. A
microfinance bank can provide many of these
services, such as loans for domestic, health and
education purposes, but it cannot provide
other services such as affordable housing mort¬
gages and health insurance. K-Rep thus does
not intend to become a conventional bank
but to use the banking framework to fill an
important gap that commercial banks have
been unable or unwilling to fill.
The choices made by K-Rep take their place
within the wide diversity of approaches and
systems being developed by MFIs in Africa
today. Apart from solidarity groups and credit
unions, many rotating savings and credit asso¬
ciations (Tontines in West Africa, Chikolas
in Kenya and Stockvel in South Africa) have a
proven track record as efficient sources of
microfinancc. In Egypt the Alexandria Busi¬
nessmen's Association has created a microcre¬
dit system which takes advantage of the strict
law and cultural stigma on defaulters of
promissory notes. In West, Central and East¬
ern Africa the village banking system, com¬
munity managed credit and associations have
proved to be very effective.
New microfinancc institutions, such as The
Centennial Bank in Uganda, The Commu¬
nity Bank in South Africa, City Savings in
Ghana and The People's Bank in Nigeria are
being or already have been established as reg¬
ulated financial institutions. A number of
countries, including the Gambia and several
French-speaking West African countries, are
in the process of formulating new legislation
for MFIs. In South Africa, MFIs have taken the
initiative of establishing a self-regulating body
to oversee the conduct of its members.
This legislation is extremely important.
Apart from providing a conducive regulatory
environment for MFIs, it provides legitimacy
for a practice still considered by many to be a
short-term donor-dependent intervention.
The sector has also attracted many "gct-rich-
quick" quacks, who must not be allowed to
hijack the industry. M
4 n women's self-help group i
Soweto (South Africa).
1/ameroonian fashion
designer Joséphine Bertrano
employs 12 men in her dress¬
making workshop.
.A grain mill owned by a
women's co-operative in Mali.
Bought on credit, it was
gradually paid for with money
charged for milling.
M meeting to discuss
microfinance projects
in Kenya.
THE UNESCO ÇiURlERl JANUARY 1997 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
VILLAGE BANKING: A REPORT
FROM 5 COUNTRIES BY RUPERT SCOFIELD
HONDURAS
For as long as anyone can remember, the
women of Siguatepeque, a rural pueblo in cen¬
tral Honduras, have produced ceramics. You
can see them for sale on the side of the high¬
way that runs between the capital city of Tegu¬
cigalpa and the northern city of San Pedro
Sula: great stacks of flower pots, urns, plates
and ornamental pieces in the shapes of roost¬
ers, parrots, dogs, cats and caimans.
Six years ago, most of the women worked
for a man let's call him Don Alejandro
who purchased the pottery the women made,
and resold them to a wholesaler who trucked
them to retail markets in Tegucigalpa. The
women of Siguatepeque were poor, and dis¬
organized. Most of them sold the pieces as
fast as they made them, for a fraction of what
Don Alejandro and the retailers earned on
them. They had no choice: they needed the
money to buy their daily food.
Kaabong women of Uganda
make bricks with which to
build a Women's Enterprise
Centre, assisted by the World
Food Programme's Food for
Work programme.
32
m THE UlNESCO ^_OURIERB JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
In 1990, when I was looking for a suitable
place for the first village bank to be organized
by the Foundation for International Com¬
munity Assistance (FINCA) in Honduras, a
friend of mine suggested I go to Siguatepeque.
The organizational meeting took place with
about thirty women, in Don Alejandro's
house. Our host was quite chagrined when,
halfway through the meeting, I explained that
the bank was for women only. Still, Don Ale¬
jandro was a good sport, and supported the
idea that FINCA would make $50 loans to
the assembled women to invest however they
felt best, and that, four months later, they
would repay the loan with interest of 3 per
cent per month. Another condition of the
loan, I explained, was that they would save at
least 20 per cent of it, or $10.
I kept waiting for some of the women to
drift away, or to be scared off by the interest
or the savings requirement, but they all
remained, nodding solemnly, as if they under¬
stood and were in complete agreement. I didn't
tell them it was only the second time I had
organized a village bank. But as I was to learn
from this and subsequent organizing meet¬
ings, they all go this way. It was as if the
women already knew how the system worked.
It was that simple.
In those days, FINCA had few resources,
and I was unable to return to Siguatepeque to
conduct the follow-up meetings with the
women. Fortunately, the village banking man¬
ual I had left behind with the women fell into
the hands of an enterprising Peace Corps vol¬
unteer, and one month after I had left I received
a letter from the women of Siguatepeque which
read: "Dear Mr. Scofield: Carolina, the volun¬
teer, has helped us organize our village bank,
which we have named "Pinos del Porvenir"
("Pines of the Future"). We have had our four
meetings, and we all understand how the bank
works. Please send us a check for $1,500."
It was almost four months before I could
return to Siguatepeque. I watched as the Pres¬
ident, Graciela, ran the meeting. The first thing
I noticed was the palpable change in attitude.
In sharp contrast to my first meeting with
the women, today they were all smiles. Check¬
ing the books, I saw that all the loans were
current, and that the group had savings of
almost $1,000, after only three months.
I asked the women what they had done with
the loans. "I spent it on food for my family,"
woman after woman said. I was appalled. "But
how can you be paying off the loans?" Graciela
explained to me that the FINCA loans had
enabled them to purchase a month's supply of
food, which had taken the pressure off them to
sell their ceramics as fast as they produced them.
Instead, they produced a month's stock, with¬
holding it from Don Alejandro and the other
middlemen until the price was more favourable.
The village bank loans had given them power in
the marketplace.
Another satisfied customer!
A lender receives a loan at a
village bank in Uganda. Today, "Pinos del Porvenir" is independent
of FINCA, and has several thousands of dol¬
lars in savings, which capitalize the bank's loans
to its members. The women no longer sell to
middlemen, but have their own retail store.
FINCA Honduras, meanwhile, has grown
from a shoestring operation to a financially
self-sufficient lending institution servicing
1 3,000 low-income borrowers in several regions
of the country. The experience of the women of
Siguatepeque has been repeated many times.
Some of the village banks in Siguatepeque, in
fact, went on to "graduate" and become clients
of the local commercial bank.
FINCA has derived a number of lessons
from the Siguatepeque experience. Most impor¬
tant, perhaps, is the fact that a mere $50 loan can
catalyze a process of individual and commu¬
nity development, which appears to be self-
sustaining. Second, is the idea that the bor¬
rowers, in possession of far more information
regarding local conditions than we outside
"experts", arc better prepared to determine how
to invest that loan. Finally, there is the evidence
that village banking can create a three-tiered self-
sufficiency: at the borrower, community, and
even national levels. If this kind of result can be
replicated on a massive, worldwide scale, then
rescuing many of the over one billion people
living in poverty today may not be as daunting
a challenge as we imagined.
IPERUI
The village bank "Union y Progreso" ("Union
and Progress") is located in a crime-ridden
shanty town on the southern border of Lima
(Peru). Like many other "pueblos jóvenes"
("young towns") surrounding the Peruvian
capital, this one was established by squatters
fleeing the violence of the "Shining Path" Guer¬
rillas, and the impossibility of scratching out
THE UNESCO ^>UR1ER |ANUARY 1997 ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
a living from agriculture on the rapidly eroding,
parched soils of the Andean highlands. From
the outside, the village bank President's house
bears little resemblance to a bank. The walls are
a conglomeration of scavenged lumber, card¬
board, and corrugated metal, and the roof is a
patchwork of the same, weighted by stones to
prevent the strong winds from blowing them
away. As a deterrent to housebreakers, the top
of the wall is crested with an intimidating glaze
of broken glass, barbed wire and nails.
Inside, the eighteen members of "Union
and Progress" are holding their meeting. The
Treasurer and President are giving the financial
report, with the aid of two large sheets of
paper, upon which the bank's "vital signs"
have been recorded with a pink magic marker.
After two years, the eighteen members of
"Union and Progress" have saved a total
$12,322, or almost $700 apiece. An examination
of the bank's records reveals that, through
active relending of their savings, the members
have generated an additional $55,278 in loans
over the past four months. This dwarfs the
mere $7,200 which FINCA Peru has lent to
the group. The interest income from these
"internal account" loans is $1,100.
Other income has been generated from fines
on borrowers whose payments were made late.
A late payment on cither an internal account
loan or external account carries a fine of 10 soles
(about $4.50). This goes into a pot shared by
only those who had perfect payment records.
The women of "Union and Progress" came up
with this carrot-stick system themselves. It
strikes me as ingenious. An institutional
approach would be to focus exclusively on the
punitive side, the fines. I intend to sec that this
idea gets disseminated to the other 3,000 village
banks in the FINCA network. Most of the
good ideas incorporated into village banking
methodology have arisen in this way, from the
borrowers themselves. The concept of the
"internal account" the relending of the bor¬
rowers' savings, among themselves and to the
community at large came from a village bank
in the border town of Sasabc, Mexico.
Now it is the turn of the borrowers, to
ask questions or to make comments. I listen to
the testimony of Maria Ponte, aged sixty-five,
who is leaving the bank, returning to the
mountain town of Puno to live with her son.
She thanks FINCA Peru for bringing the vil¬
lage bank to their community, and the mem¬
bers for trusting and supporting her. "I used
to be thin as a stick. Now, thanks to FINCA,
I have meat on my bones (she holds up her
biceps and squeezes her flesh). I can afford to
take vitamins. I have $683 in savings. I used to
be afraid to borrow money. When I got my
first loan from FINCA, I was shaking. This
cycle, I borrowed and repaid $1,867 from the
internal account in four months. We used to
be afraid of dollars. In FINCA, I learned to
save and borrow."
V THEUNESCO QiURIER« JANUARY 1997
M grocery shop in Honduras
funded by a loan from FINCA.
The Honduran affiliate of
FINCA is the foundation's
second largest.
With an average savings rate of $281 .57 per
member, Peru has the largest savings-to-loans
ratio in the FINCA network. In all, FINCA's
68,000 borrowers have saved $3.6 million over
the past ten years, up 80 per cent from just
two years ago. This money has not been fun-
neled off to commercial banks in the capital,
or sent offshore to Miami or Switzerland. It
remains in the poorest communities of the
world, working to create jobs and income on
the bottom floor of the economy. Clearly,
microcnterprise has great potential for what
my economics professor used to call "capital
formation: the engine of development."
EL SALVADOR
In 1991, Maribel Escobar Avalos' situation
seemed desperate. Having witnessed the destruc¬
tion of her first home in an earthquake in 1 985,
and her second in a guerrilla offensive in 1 989,
she had few possessions other than the clothes
on her back. At the same time, she was sup¬
porting a family of nine, including an unem¬
ployed male companion, her scventy-three-
year-old father, an invalid brother, two
daughters, a son, a son-in-law, and a niece. But
Maribel had learned from her mother in the
markets of El Salvador how to sell. In a bold
gamble, she sold what little she had left to make
the down payment on a corner house lot in
the western El Salvador town of El Sunsa.
The first year in El Sunsa was one of sacri¬
fice and struggle. Totally decapitalized, the Esco¬
bar family spent the year in a makeshift shack
of cardboard, with palm fronds for a roof.
Their food budget was so small that often their
only nutrition came from a concoction Mari¬
bel calls sopa de monte ("weed soup").
It was in these conditions that Maribel dis-
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
covered the FINCA Micro-Enterprise Sup¬
port Center. The MSC made Maribel the first
loan of her life, $50, which she invested in the
purchase and sale of used clothing. Over the
next two years, through her skill in selling,
and access to ever-larger loans, Maribel began
to diversify. First she established a small gro¬
cery store. Then a restaurant. Finally, she began
to supply fruit and vegetables to other traders
in El Sunsa. Eventually, these activities pro¬
vided employment for the entire family. Along
the way, Maribel accumulated $805 in cash sav¬
ings in her village bank. Today, on the corner
lot which used to host a ramshackle choza of
cardboard and palm fronds, a comfortable
four bedroom brick house stands. The store
front room houses the store and restaurant,
with an electrified "Orange Crush" sign fea¬
turing the name "Restaurante y Pupuseria El
Canalito."
As she sends her children off to high school
(she herself never progressed beyond third
grade), Maribel explains her formula for suc¬
cess. "My whole life, I've worked hard, getting
up at 5 a.m. and going to bed at 9 p.m. But
the difference is, now we are saving. The more
we save, the more we can borrow. The more we
borrow, the more we can sell. The more we
can sell, the greater our income."
UGANDA!
Prior to 1992, the women of Kimantu village
in southeastern Uganda, near the sources of the
Nile, had never managed their own money or
run a business, let alone received credit. What
little money did pass through their hands had
to be begged from their husbands, even to
buy food for their children. When I first
described how the village bank would work,
one of the women in the village asked me how
much money FINCA would lend them.
"Fifty thousand shillings," I replied, which
was the equivalent of $50. This was a tense
moment for me: I had been assured by the
Executive Director of another non-govern¬
mental organization working in Uganda that
the women would turn up their noses at such
a paltry sum.
The woman gasped and nearly fainted. She
assured me that 50,000 shillings was too much;
she could never take responsibility for paying
back such a princely sum. In the end, at the
urging of her neighbours, she agreed to accept
half that amount, splitting the loan with
another woman in the bank.
When I returned to Kimantu, four months
later, I found the women, and the village,
transformed. They had repaid their loans, 100
per cent. They had saved in excess of the
required 20 per cent. "The thing I like best
about the village bank," one woman told me,
"is that I have learned to start a business and to
manage money." The woman who had been
too timid to borrow 50,000 shillings now
told me she intended to borrow 100,000.
I he treasurer of a village
bank in Kyrgyzstan in central
Asia records repayments. The men in the village, who had initially
viewed the village bank with suspicion, now
welcomed it. As the Kimantu village chief told
me: "When the women first started to hold
their meetings, we men were concerned. We
thought they were talking about divorcing
us. But then, when we saw them earning
money, and they no longer came to us for
money to buy salt, and pay school fees, we
saw that the village bank was a good thing.
But Mr. Scoficld, I have one question." "And
what is that?" I asked. The chief grinned. "Can
you create a village bank for us men?"
In many communities of Uganda, Aids
has left its brutal imprint, sweeping away hus¬
bands, wives, and sometimes entire families. In
most cases, however, the children survive, to be
raised by the village as a whole. Many Ugandan
village bankers are supporting not only their
own children, but those orphaned by deceased
relatives and neighbours. It is an intensely sad,
but at the same time inspiring experience to
meet these selfless, struggling mothers.
"Women who are in village banks are seen as the
most responsible members of the commu¬
nity," was the way one observer put it. "It is
natural that people look to them, when they
THE UNESCO ^URIERB |ANUARY1997 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
want a secure future for the children they leave
behind."
IKYRGYZSTAN
Can microcnterprise succeed in a country
where, until recently, private enterprise was
officially discouraged, considered immoral,
and, in some cases, even outlawed? In 1994,
FINCA established the first village banks in
the newly independent state of Kyrgyzstan,
Central Asia, in the capital city of Bishkek.
With the snow-capped Himalayas as a back¬
drop, Bishkek is a city just coming to life,
economically, after years of surviving on sub¬
sidies from mother Russia. Today, an esti¬
mated 15 per cent of the population is unem¬
ployed, and more expected as state-run
enterprises are privatized or closed altogether.
Increasingly, the population is moving to self-
employment as an alternative to the meagre
wages of the public sector.
Today, the village bank Bereke ("Bless¬
ing") is receiving its first loan. Village banks are
smaller in Kyrgyzstan than in other countries
in the FINCA network, reflecting an added
cautiousness on the part of the members
towards their neighbours, the vast majority of
whom have never operated a business. FINCA
has learned to respect the members' apprecia¬
tion of local conditions as being far superior
to its own, and seldom intervenes in decisions
regarding the selection of the bank's mem¬
bers, or in the loan approval process. In this
case, most of the fifteen borrowers will be
investing their loans in consumer goods, to be
sold in the local market. A great feast for the
visitors was laid out on a gorgeous, hand-
woven rug in the village bank president's liv¬
ing room. Other rugs, of equally dazzling pat¬
terns, adorned the walls. These rugs, which
sell domestically for less than $10, can com¬
mand over $100 in export markets. Though
it was only mid morning, glasses of brandy
were offered and accepted.
The meeting began, presided over by a
democratically elected President, Treasurer and
Secretary. The President followed the standard
village bank agenda: financial report, approval
and disbursement of loans, and collection of
obligatory and voluntary savings. Besides the
small size of the village banks, the methodol¬
ogy has suffered little modification in its adap¬
tation to the Kyrgyz context. Contrary to
initial warnings that no one would be inter¬
ested in small loans in Kyrgyzstan, FINCA has
found the demand to be strong. To date,
FINCA Kyrgyzstan has reached 2,300 bor¬
rowers, and, in a country of five million, the
word is just beginning to spread.
THREE MICROCREDIT
36
age-earning is the most wide¬
spread form of employment in
the industrialized countries.
However, in a context of eco¬
nomic crisis and high unemployment, the pro¬
portion of self-employed workers has risen
steadily since the early 1980s. Microcredit is one
tool of development for this sector.
The Association for the Right to Eco¬
nomic Initiative (ADIE) was set up in France
in 1990, and was supported from its incep¬
tion by a number of private foundations, the
French state and the European Union. To date
THE UNESCO QîURIERB JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
In rural Albania, left, there is
an expanding network of
village credit funds managed
by locally elected committees.
SCHEMES IN EUROPE
BY MARIA NÓWAK
ADIE has funded more than 2,500 micro-
enterprises started by the unemployed and
people receiving the minimum social wage
(RMD). It has branches in fourteen French
regions and works in tandem with authorized
savings and loan banks such as Credit Mutuel
and Crédit Municipal.
Nearly 40 per cent of ADIE's customers
have not completed a vocational training
l.The RMI ("revenu minimum d'insertion")
is an allowance paid by the French state to people over
25 who have no other source of income.
Author's note
course, and about 10 per cent can barely read
or write. But in life's hard school they have
acquired entrepreneurial capacities and energy
that no formal schooling could have taught
them. Some of them pursue occupations tra¬
ditionally associated with poverty such as
street vending and scrap-metal dealing; oth¬
ers are astutely exploiting the possibilities of
modern technology, e.g. by teleworking pro¬
viding secretarial services from home.
What most differentiates them from their
counterparts in the countries of the South,
however, are the administrative complexities
and the social charges they have to cope with.
Social security coverage for the most vulnera¬
ble groups tends to discourage potential entre¬
preneurs from starting new businesses.
But helping unemployed people create
their own jobs on a permanent basis costs the
THE UNESCO Q>URIERB |ANUARYI997 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
state three times less than supporting them
for a year while they are out of work. In France
microcredit is used as a tool to help people on
the fringe of society to help themselves.
The dismantling of Albania's co-operatives
and state farms that began in 1992 has put
farmers in charge of individual holdings aver¬
aging 1.4 hectares but with no farm imple¬
ments or input.
As part of the Rural Poverty Alleviation
Project financed by the World Bank and Aide
International, village credit funds have been
set up to inject resources into rural areas and
rebuild village community life destroyed
under communist rule.
Managed by farmer-elected committees,
these village funds grant loans and collect
repayment instalments with support from
the Albanian Rural Development Fund. To
date they have granted 8,000 loans, the average
amount of which has gradually risen from
$200 to $400 with a 99.5 per cent repayment
rate.
This network so far covers only some 5
per cent of Albanian villages but is expanding
rapidly. A law was passed in April 1996 allow¬
ing credit funds to collect savings as well. The
success of microcredit in rural areas has led the
government to extend the programme to the
towns, where loans average $2,000 and are
granted on an individual basis.
As well as providing finance, microcredit
enables formerly communist countries to
decentralize decision-making by privatizing
the grassroots economy, promoting the emer¬
gence of new entrepreneurs and facilitating the
transition to a market economy.
A project in Tuzla
The Republic of Bosnia and Herccgovina is
facing the combined difficulties arising from
a transition economy and a war-torn econ¬
omy. Unemployment among people of work¬
ing age is running at 64 per cent, and nearly 80
per cent of the population lives on humani¬
tarian aid.
To case the passage from humanitarian aid
to economic activity the World Bank has
launched a pilot project in Tuzla to support
local initiatives. With support from the non¬
governmental organizations that endeavoured
to help the civilian population during the war,
the project is focused on displaced persons,
demobilized soldiers, small farmers and the
unemployed.
Loans range from $300 to $600 depending
on the projects and the borrowers' capacities.
In refugee centres the loans give single women
with children a chance to rent plots of land
to plant potatoes, buy a cow or goat, knit or
embroider. In the villages, they usually fund
crafts and businesses that supplement income
from farming, which is inadequate. In cities,
where the market is larger, they enable people
to start or relaunch microenterprises by job
creation. Microcredit is helping a country
emerging from war to turn to the future.
BEelowleft, a craftsman
from Bordeaux (France) makes
imitation antique armour for
theatre companies. He set up
his own business after
receiving a loan from the
French Association for the
Right to Economic Enterprise
(ADIE).
B elow, a refugee who lost
all her possessions during
the war in the former
Yugoslavia. After receiving a
loan from a World Bank pilot
project to support local
initiative, she bought goats
and now sells their milk to
support her family.
V THE UNESCO COURIER |ANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
FACT FILE What is poverty?
Microcredit Summit
Washington D.C., February 2-4, 1997
The purpose of the Microcredit Summit
is to adopt a plan of action and launch a
global campaign to reach 100 million of
the world's poorest families, especially
the women of those families, with credit
for self-employment by the year 2005.
The Summit will bring together all
sectors of global society public, private
and non-profit to affirm this goal and
to help develop the specific steps each
institution will take to contribute to its
fulfillment.
For further information contact
Microcredit Summit,
236 Massachusetts Avenue, NE, Suite 300,
Washington, DC 20002 USA.
Tel: (1-202) 546 1900
Fax: (1-202) 546 3228
E-mail: microcredit@igc.apc.org
Further reading
Maximizing the Outreach of
Microenterprise Finance. An Analysis
ofSuccessful Microfinance Programs,
by Robert Peck Christen, Elisabeth
Rhyne, Robert C. Vogel and Cressida
McKean. Center for Development
Information and Evaluation, U.S.
Agency for International
Development (USAID), 1995.
The New World ofMicroenterprise
Finance: Building Healthy Financial
Institutionsfor the Poor.
Edited by Maria Otero and Elisabeth
Rhyne. Kumarian Press, Inc.,
Connecticut, U.S.A., 1994.
The Sustainable Banking for the Poor
Initiative, a group within the World
Bank, has created a database of
microfinance institutions worldwide,
entitled
A Worldwide Inventory of
Microfinance Institutions.
It can be obtained by contacting
Ms. Laura Gomez:
Pax: (1-202) 522-1662.
E-mail: lgomez@worldbank.org.
FOCUS:. Aseries of notes which is
CGAP's primary vehicle for presenting
to governments, donors and private
financial institutions the best practices
in microenterprise finance.
FOCUS: 1818 H Street, N.W,
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.
Tel: (1-202) 473-9594
Fax: (1-202) 522-3744
E-mail: cproject@worldbank.org.
Poverty is usually thought of as a lack of income The CPM considers the lack of three basic
because it is income that is largely assumed to capabilities. The first is the capability to be well
determine a person's material standard of well- nourished and healthy represented by the pro-
being. Thus, if $1 a day is taken as the poverty line, portion of children under five who are mder-
33% of the developing world's population, or 1.3 weight. The second is the capability for healthy
billion people, are poor. Nearly half of them reproduction proxied by the proportion of
more than 550 million live in South Asia, 215 births unattended by trained health personnel,
million in sub-Saharan Africa and 150 million The third is the capability to be educated and
in Latin America. knowledgeable represented by female illiter-
But "income poverty" is only part of the pic- acy. The index is noteworthy for its emphasis on
ture. Just as human development encompasses the deprivation of women, which is severe in
aspects of life much broader than income, so some countries. It is now well known that depri-
poverty should be seen as having many dimen- vation of women adversely affects the human
sions. development of families and society.
A new, multidimensional measure of human According to national income poverty lines,
deprivation, the capability poverty measure 21% of the people in developing countries live
(CPM), was introduced in the United Nations below the poverty line. The corresponding figure
Development Programme's Human Develop¬
ment Report 1996. Intended to complement
income measures of poverty, it focuses on human
capabilities, as UNDP's human development
index1 does. But rather than examining the aver¬
age state of people's capabilities, it reflects the per¬
centage of people who lack basic, or minimally
essential, human capabilities.
for capability poverty is 37% . In other words, 900
million people in developing countries are income
poor, but 1 .6 billion people are capability poor.
1 Since 1990 the Human Development Report has
presented the human development index to capture as
many aspects of human development as possible in one
simple composite index and to produce a ranking of
human development achievements.
Source: Human Development Report 1996. Published for the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP),
by Oxford University Press, New York and Oxford (UK), 1996.
Facts and figures
It is estimated that less than 10 million
of the few hundred million people who
run micro and small enterprises have
access to financial services. (FOCUS no.
1, published by the Consultative Group
to Assist the Poorest [CGAP])
If 10% of all low income entrepre¬
neurs are to gain access to institutional
finance by the year 2005, financial sys¬
tems will need to be transformed. Finan¬
cial intermediaries' total portfolios in
microloans, now about $2.5 billion,
would need to be about $12.5 billion by
2005. These rapid increases in lending
levels are reasonable and reflect growth
rates that are lower than actual growth
rates in the last five years. The main chal¬
lenges will be in expanding the capacity
ana resources of those retail intermedi¬
aries committed to providing financial
services to low income entrepreneurs.
(FOCUS No 3)
Of the world's total labour force of 2.8
billion, around 30% arc not productively
employed, according to the International
Labour Organisation. This includes
more than 120 million people who are
unemployed, and 700 million who arc
underemployed. These people constitute
the bulk of the world's absolute poor.
(UNDP)
Sources: FOCUS, CGAP, UNDP.
Fashion for development
While hand-loom weavers from Bangladesh demon¬
strated their skills, some fifty designs made from their fab¬
rics were modelled at a show held at UNESCO's Paris
HQ early last year. The event, which formed part of co¬
operation between Unesco and the Grameen Bank,
showed how cultural wealth can be linked to social and
economic development.
"Unesco is not planning to get into the fashion busi¬
ness," said UNESCO's Director General, Federico Mayor.
" We only want to su ggest how the crafts of the weavers of
Bangladesh could find an outlet in international markets."
Many weavers in rural Bangladesh, where high-qual¬
ity textile production was once the mainstay of the econ¬
omy, have been forced to abandon their looms because
of lack of working capital and raw materials, and com¬
petition from machine-made products. Grameen Bank
is helping them to produce and promote their fabrics,
thereby contributing to preservation of the cultural her¬
itage as well as preventing these skilled craftspeople from
falling into poverty.
The potential of microfinance to help the world's
poor can only be fulfilled if their products find outlets. In
its strategy for the weavers' survival Grameen is linking
traditional handlooms with a product policy responsive
to fashion trends and aimed at winning new markets
both locally and internationally.
The fashion show, at which one of the creations was
designed by a Paris fashion house, demonstrated the
linkages that can be established between local crafts and
the international market.
THE UNESCO Ç0URIU I JANUARY 1997
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
ducat
Tomorrow's world will l)e shaped by our children's vision
of it. What kind of vision will it he, and how can educa¬
tion help to shape it? These questions raise two sets of
issues. One has to do with the contribution that educa¬
tion must make to society; the other relates to the expan¬
sion and reform of the education system itself so that it can
meet the hopes and expectations that society has vested
in it.
While the challenges to education are universal, the
responses to them must come from the heart of the cul¬
tures of each region. Education must reflect all that is best
and most distinctive within ourselves and our societies.
Only thus will it help to unite people everywhere around
shared values in defence of their common interests.
Everywhere and from every standpoint, education is
crucial to peace. For peace, as we all know, is more than
the absence of conflict. Peace is a culture based upon tol¬
erance and respect for others; it is a spirit of active soli¬
darity amongindividuals, built upon expectations of jus¬
tice and tranquillity. Sustaining and promoting these
values must be one of the foremost duties of education.
Our schools must be revered places of learning and their
most valuable lessons are those that teach the wisdom of
peace and the folly of war.
The promotion of democracy and human rights is an
essential part of the peace-building process. So too is
THE UNESCO G?URJERB JANUARY 1097
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
the promotion of the rights of women. If we really believe With this in mind, UNESCO and its partners in the
in human rights, how can discrimination against women United Nations system are actively engaged in promoting
be tolerated? In practical terms, the cost to development worldwide improvements qualitative and quantitative
of neglecting the unique talents of women is enormous. in the pro vision of basic education. Particular stress is
Morally, it seems to ine inadmissible that, at the dawn of placed on providing quality education for girls and
the twenty-first century, limitations should be placed on women. Another of our preoccupations is to improve the
women's fundamental freedoms. The problem of women's status and qualifications of teachers. Teachers are the
rights clearly transcends education, but it is one with front-line workers in the struggle to achieve a literate
which education systems, especially in the countries of world. Their job is a challenging and difficult one; their
the South, should be closely concerned. salaries and conditions of service are often poor. Yet the
A growing body of research highlights the importance vast majority of teachers are sclflessly doing all they can
of the education of women and girls in accelerating devel- to educate the citizens of tomorrow. They know how
opment. To educate a mother is not only to educate a vitally important their task is. We must remember this and
family, but also to replace a potential inheritance of illit- ()iTcr teachers the appreciation, honour and respect due
eracy with a tradition of education that will be passed from to them.
generation to generation. The education of women also In a worl(1 in which progress is increasingly dependent
has a very powerful impact upon fertility rates. on l,,e products of the mind, education is increasingly rec¬
ognized as the force of the future. This has in turn rein¬
forced the importance of international co-operation, which
A NEW ETHIC OF SHARING AND CARING , PTT T . . TT ,
is the vocation of UNESCO. I will not review UNESCO s
I must also stress the importance of the population ques- many activities in this field, but I would mention two
tion, which is of concern to us all. It is essential that we programmes especially designed to encourage the rapid
moderate population growth, but this can only be done transfer of knowledge and technology to developing
if women have the power of choice, the capacity to shape countries. The first of these is UNITWIN, which links uni-
their own destiny. It is not through the imposition of exter- versities in developing countries with those in industri-
nal models that the solution to the problem will be found. alized nations. The second is the UNESCO Chairs pro-
Education giving people the means to decide for them- gramme, which places high-level specialists at the disposal
selves once more provides the key. An increase in edu- of universities in developing countries,
cation is directly correlated with a decrease in fertility. As Our duty as educators is to use education to focus the
well as reducing demographic growth, we must provide energy and idealism of young people on building a soci-
properly for all those already on board spaceship earth ety of peace, progress and prosperity. We must strengthen
and those destined to join itincluding street children, the function of peace-building in all cultures. We must
those exposed to hunger, disease and neglect. We must infuse into the minds of young people everywhere a new
be ready to invest in education what we have in the past ethic of sharing and caring. We must prepare the ground
been prepared to invest in war. We must be ready to pay for a new civilization in which the word and not the sword
the price of peace. will prevail.
41
THE UNESCO COURIER JANUARY 1997 ~
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
greenwatch
eoole
by France Bequette
In India, between the Ganges
I and the foothills of the
Himalayas, grows a shrub with pale
pink flowers, smooth leaves and
milky saj). In Hindi it is railed
chotachund. According to a local
legend mongooses use to feed on the
plant before fighting cobras, and its
root is still administered as an anti¬
dote to snakebite. Its use gradually
spread to the neighbouring provinces
and then to the whole country. In
Miliar province, for example, it has
been used to treat insanity, epilepsy
and insomnia. In the eighteenth Cen¬
tury European botanists named the
shrub llauvolfia serpentina. It was
studied and analysed, and today it is
one of the most effective drugs used
to treat high blood pressure.
An interdisciplinary science
Elhnobotany, the study of the rela¬
tionship between plants and people,
is a marriage ol several disciplines
anthropology, botany, chemistry, ecol¬
ogy, linguistics and pharmacology, lis
field ranges from the use made of
¡liants by local populations to the
environmental and cultural impact
that the disappearance of a plant can
have on its environment. This inter-
A traditional
chemist's shop in
Suwon (Republic
of Korea).
Han-Kang, a
Chinese botanist
of the 2nd century
A.D. as depicted in
a 17th-century
painting.
disciplinary science is mainly prac¬
tised in developing countries and with
indigenous populations because in
that context the link between pro¬
duction and consumption is far more
direct than it is in the industrialized
world. An Amazonian Indian will go
out and pick the leaf he needs to
treat a burn, whereas in developed
countries not many people know that
the pretty foxglove (Digitalis pur¬
purea) growing in the garden is the
basis of the medicine they take for
their heart condition.
Some of the reasons for today's
growing interest in ethnobotany are
psychological (a revival of interest
in nature and "natural" products, a
sense of urgency that has arisen
because the knowledge and tradi¬
tions of indigenous peoples are dying
out), while others are more prag¬
matic (people in the poorest coun¬
tries often cannot get hold of and
above all cannot afford modern
drugs).
The World Health Organization
(WHO) is trying to restore respect
for traditional medicine, and many
other international organizations and
non-governmental organizations have
followed suit. In 1992 the World
Wide Fund for Nature (WWF),
UiMESCO and the Royal Botanic Car-
dens, Kew (UK) launched a joint
programme called "People and
Plants" "to promote the conserva¬
tion of biodiversity and the sustain¬
able and equitable use of plant
resources by providing support to
ethnobotanists from developing
countries".
As part of the programme, on-the-
ground activities are organized in
biosphere reserves, World Heritage
sites and other protected areas.
Their goal is to record useful plants
and knowledge, solve the on-going
dilemma between conservation and
exploitation in protected zones,
invent non-destructive ways of har¬
vesting wild plants, and ensure that
conservation and the sound exploita¬
tion of plant resources really do ben¬
efit local communities. Local people,
park and reserve staff, researchers
and university students are taking
part in the programme, to which
American cthnobotanist Gary J. Mar¬
tin has written a clear and practical
guide entitled Ethnobotany, A Meth¬
ods Manual, which sums up what
has been learned during the first four
years.
THE UNESCO COURIER! JANUARY
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
-!.ï
TV.
Learning from shamans
An ethnobotanist working in the field
must have received a rigorous scien¬
tific training. He or she also needs
to be physically tough, adaptable
and a good listener. In his hook Tales
of a Shaman's Apprentice, Ameri¬
can ethnobotanist Mark J. Plotkin,
who spent more than ten years in
Amazonia, describes how he learned
the local language, followed the
shamans, collected samples, made
a herbarium and noted the uses that
were made of plants, lie analysed
medicines, the vegetal poison on the
lips of arrows and the hallucinogenic,
substances used during initiation
ceremonies.
He recorded the words of an old
Amazonian shaman who said: "It is
true the youngsters do not want to
learn. One day the medicines that
the missionaries send from the city
will no longer arrive. The people here
will come to me to relieve, their pains,
to conquer the evil spirits that kill
their children. But I will be gone,
and I will have taken my plants with
me." Unlike modern doctors,
shamans, medicine men and
fetishists treat the mind and the
body. They also help to maintain the
group's cultural identity.
Shamans cannot practise their
skills without preparation. They
must be initiated, often using hal¬
lucinogenic substances like
ayahuasca (Uanisteriopsis caapi),
Group meditation
in the open air
(Republic of
Korea).
A Jivaro Indian
shaman treats a
patient In
Amazonia.
or "vine of the soul", which are a
passport to the spirit world. It is not
surprising that missionaries try to
eradicate these practices and beliefs
and discourage shamans from tak¬
ing disciples. It is just as easy to
understand why Mark Plotkin has
launched a training programme for
apprentice shamans in several coun¬
tries, with support from a non-gov¬
ernmental organization, Conserva¬
tion International.
Friends of humanity
Plants have always been part of
human history. "Thatch for huts,
timbers for boats, fibers for cordage
and textiles and dyes to colour them,
and a plethora of medicinal plants all
appear at early stages of human pre
history," write Michael Balick and
Paul Alan Cox in their remarkable
book, Plants, People and Culture.
Plants provide food, clothing, shel¬
ter, building materials, medication
and ingredients of ritual. Unlike ani¬
mals that have to eat either ¡liants or
other animals, plants live on sun, car¬
bon dioxide from the air, a few min¬
eral salts and a little water. From
these basic elements they produce
molecules that are sometimes so
complex that no laboratory can syn¬
thesize them.
Humanity has recorded some
250,000 flowering plants, but this is
not necessarily an exhaustive figure.
There is no great hook of nature
where botanists can record their dis¬
coveries and cross out species that
L UNESCO COURIER« JANUARY I 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
have ceased to exist, yet we know
that plants are victims of deforesta¬
tion, soil erosion, pollution, herbi¬
cides, urban expansion and even over-
harvesting. The United Nations
Food and Agriculture Organization
defines biodiversity as "the diversity
of life on earth: it includes all life
forms and the ecosystems of which
they are a part". Its reduction
results in the loss of irreplaceable
genetic materials that are the essen¬
tial components of the plant and ani¬
mal life that agriculture and other
human activities depend on.
The poor countries and their tra¬
ditional pharmacopeia face another
threat, however. Pharmaceutical
and other laboratories that use the
observations of cthnobotanists are
taking part in a "plant rush" to take
samples from nature, then large
quantities of primary plant matter in
order to produce drugs and cosmet¬
ics. To illustrate the problem, the
People and Plants Programme com¬
missioned Australian Tony Cunning¬
ham and Cameroonian Fonki
Mbenkum to study the sustainabil-
ity of harvesting the bark of the
Prunus africana tree in Cameroon.
TO FIND OUT MORE:
People and Plants Programme, Ecological
Sciences Division, UNESCO,
7, Place de Fontenoy,
75352 Paris Cedex 07 SP, France.
Fax: (33) (0)1 40 65 98 97;
e-mail: 100427.1260@Compuserve.com
FURTHER READING:
* Plants, People and Culture, The Science of
Ethnobotany, Michael J. Balick and Paul Alan
Cox, Scientific American Library, 1996
'* Ethnobotany, A Methods Manual, Gary J.
Martin, Chapman and Hall, 1995.
Tales ofa Shaman's Apprentice, Mark J.
Plotkin, Penguin Books, 1993.
Preparing a
manioc-based
beverage In a
Jívaro village.
A patent problem
This is a tree that grows especially
well in the cool, volcanic soil of
Africa's mountainous regions. It is a
wild-growing cousin of the peach,
apricot and almond trees and is
found in Kenya, Uganda and Zaire,
and also in Madagascar and the
Comoros Islands. It is especially
abundant in the southwest and
northwest regions of Cameroon. Its
bark is known in much of Africa as a
treatment for malaria, stomach ache
and fever. In 1966, a French labo¬
ratory discovered that it is an active
agent in the treatment of prostate
swelling, and applied for a patent,
followed by three other European
laboratories. In a single place 424
tonnes of bark were gathered from
7,717 Prunus trees between Decem¬
ber 1984 and December 1985.
Unfortunately, instead of simply tak¬
ing bands of bark, harvesters often
strip the tree bare so that it dies,
thus depriving traditional medicine
of one of its resources.
In this way the increased life
expectancy of western Europeans
has an impact on the Cameroonian
forest, since one European male out
of two over the age of 80 has a nine
out of ten chance of suffering from
this prostate affliction.
It is increasingly imperative to
adopt an ethical approach to
exploitation of the resources of
developing countries, and this is one
of the goals of the People and Plants
Programme. An ethical code is
urgently needed. Greedy for new
products, the pharmaceutical com¬
panies "buy" or "borrow" plant
species and file patents on them. The
neem (Azirdiruchtu indica), a tree
used for as long as anyone can
remember as a pesticide in India,
has been patented by an American
company. Stranger still, a vine grow¬
ing in the Amazonian jungle, known
to shamans for its hallucinogenic
qualities and used in initiation cer¬
emonies, has been patented by an
American and marketed via the
Internet.
But who can stop a villager from
"selling" a plant from his garden or
a traveller from quietly pocketing
it? Who can p revent a laboratory
from borrowing a specimen from a
botanical garden? If and when an
ethical code is promulgated, ways
of implementing it will still have to
he found.
i nitiatives EXPLORING THE EARTH
WITH EARTHWATCH
Russian geochemist Igor Taganov once led a 3-man Earthwatch expedition in Siberia that
became more than just a scientific outing. He tells how their food supply was destroyed by a hun¬
gry bear when they still had 300 kilometres to cover on their return journey to home base. Two
days later iheir dogs discovered a huge piece of meat, the flesh of a young mammoth that had
been perfectly preserved in a block of ice. During the next two weeks they cooked and ate a lot
of the meat, and later sent some samples of it to Moscow for laboratory tests. Carbon-14 analy¬
sis revealed that the steaks they'd been eating were 30,000 years old!
This unusual episode happened on a serious scientific expedition organized by Earthwatch,
a non-profit membership organization that was founded in the U.S.A. in 1972 and is one of the
world's largest private sponsors of scientific field research projects. Earthwatch offers amateurs
the opportunity to take part in projects and expeditions all over the world and thus contribute
to scientific progress. It brings a touch of adventure to observation of the planet in such fields
as agriculture, archaeology, the arts, botany, cultural anthropology, ecology, geology, palaeon¬
tology, volcanology and zoology.
Every year Earthwatch publishes a roundup of its teams' accomplishments. In 1996 for
example, four new species of snakes, two species of lizards and a frog unknown to science were
discovered on the islands off Hong Kong; the Wardaman aborigines of Australia were helped to
record and preserve more than 14,000 paintings and pelroglyphs made by their Ancestors; and
Costa Rican sea turtles were tagged with satellite transmitters making it possible to keep tabs
on their migrations and protect them.
To date Earthwatch has mobilized 1,882 projects in 111 countries. More than 40,000 of its
EarthCorps volunteers have contributed over $30 million and 5,230,000 hours to the search for
solutions to important problems. It already has 70,000 members from all walks of life, and
anyone can join.
EARTHWATCH HEADQUARTERS: 680 Ml. Auburn Street, P.O. Iiox403, Walertown, MA
02272, U.S.A. Tel: (1-617) 926-8200; Fax: (1-617) 926-8532; e-mail: info@earlhwalcli.org
EARTHWATCH EUROPE: Belsyre Courl, 57 Woodstock Road, Oxford OX2 7IIU
United Kingdom. Tel: (44) (0) 865 311-600; Fax: (44) (0) 865 311-383.
44 THE UNESCO Q)URIER JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
w o
WHERE HAVE ALL
THE FLOWERS GONE?
Fewer and fewer of the poppies, cornflowers and other wild
plants that once dotted the grain fields of Western Europe
are to he seen these days. They are being destroyed by selec¬
tive herbicides, and some of them are even threatened with
extinction. Generally hardier than cultivated plants, they com¬
pete with cereal crops for water, fertilizer, air and light. Some
of them have extraordinary root systems. The roots of a single
wild oat plant can measure almost 6,000 metres when put end
to end. In many ways these wild plants are very useful. The pres¬
ence of small concentrations of certain substances given off
by cornflower roots (Centaurea cyanus) helps flax to grow,
and poppies can have the same effect on wheat. I
THE CAR FREE CITIES NETWORK
In Amsterdam in 1994 the European Union created a "Car Free
Cities Club", which has today become a 60-nieinher Car Free
Cities Network. The aim is not for cities to outlaw private cars
hut rather to propose alternative solutions and develop effi¬
cient urban transport systems. In Copenhagen (Denmark), for
example, there are 125 coin-operated "cycle points" where
people can hire hikes. Since 1970 the closing of many Copen¬
hagen streets to motor traffic and a reduction in the number of
parkingplares (1 to 3% per year) have brought down the num¬
ber of kilometres covered by private ears by 10%. It has to he
said that Copenhagen is an exceptional rase in Europe. I
Eurorilirs, 18 Squarr <le Mcriis, 1030 Brussels, Belgium.
Tel: (32) 2 332 08 88; Fax: (32) 2 532 08 89.
i
A NATURAL FERTILIZER
FOR RICE
Rice feeds nearly half of the people who
live on planet earth. At the present pop¬
ulation growth rate, 300 million more
tonnes of the cereal will have to he pro¬
duced to meet demand in the year 2020.
This means using more fertilizer and pes¬
ticides, which are in the long run harmful
to the environment and soil productivity.
For the past few years, the French Sci¬
entific Research Institute for Develop¬
ment through Co-operation (ORSTOM)
and the International Rice Research Insti¬
tute (1 Kill) of the Philippines have been
studying the possibility of using micro¬
scopic algae known as cyanobactcria as a
biological fertilizer in ricofields. Cyanobac¬
tcria are naturally present in the soil of
rice paddies and arc able to fix from the air
5 to 30 kg of nitrogen per hectare. When
the algae decompose, the freed nitrogen
is reabsorbed by the rice. Cyanobactcria
thus act as natural fertilizer. Their other
advantages are that they enrich the soil
with organic matter and prevent the pro¬
liferation of mosquito larvae, vectors of
numerous diseases such as malaria. I
BRIGHT IDEA
A Creek household spends roughly 10%
of its budget on electricity. In an attempt
to help their compatriots save energy, stu¬
dents from Alimos High School suggest
that consumers should simply change
light bulbs. They write as follows in Bleu
Diane Vert, the magazine produced by
the Young Reporters Programme of the
Paris-based Foundation for Environmen¬
tal Education in Europe (FEEE): "If we
exchange 1 100-watt incandescent lamp
for one fluorescent lamp of equal light
power (20W), we reduce emissions of CO.,
by 650 kg for the w hole 'life' of the bulb
(8.000 hours)."
FEEE
U.MTKI) KINGDOM: Graham Hasliwoilh,
Tidv lirilain Group, The Pier, Wiiran,
WiN3 IEX. Tel: (11) 19 12 72 46 20;
Fax: (1 1)19 12 82 17 78
IliKl.VM): Ms. Patricia Oliver or Ms. Jo
Cooke, An Taisce, The Tailors' Hall, Back
Lane, Dublin 8. Tel: (333) 1 13 1 17 86;
Fax: (333) 1 153 32 55.
THE PROMISE OF
AGRO FORESTRY
Some 15.4 million hectares of the world's
2 billion hectares of tropical forests dis¬
appear annually, including 10 million to
slash-and-burn farming. In order to resist
this trend, the Consultative Group on
International Agricultural Research
(CG1AR), an international consortium
sponsored by the World Rank, FAO, the
United Nations Development Programme
and the Ui\ Environment Programme, is
supporting research into sustainable farm¬
ing practices. Agroforestry, one such
method, consists of integrating trees into
farming in order to reduce the pressure on
forests by providing farmers with timber
and fuelwood, as well as fruit, oils, resins,
medicines and fodder. This would eon-
tribute to the earnings of rural households
and increase food security. I
CASTOR OIL TREATMENT FOR
THE0Z0NE LAYER
Poly-Urcthanc Industria e Comercio Ltda,
a Rrazilian company based in Relo Hori¬
zonte, has perfected a new technology
that uses castor oil as the expanding agent
in the manufacture of insulating foam.
This original idea should lead to a notable
reduction in the use of Chlorofluorocar-
bons (CFCs), gases that destroy the earth's
protective ozone shield, and also encour¬
age castor-oil production in lirazil, where
the plant from which it is made grows wild
even in the big cities. I
THE UNESCO QïURIER JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
H ERITAGE
olonia del Sacramento
remembers its turbulent past
by Edouard Bailby
Colonial monuments with an eventful history grace the old
quarter of the Uruguayan port of Colonia
The Street of Sighs
( Calle de los
Suspiros), with the
swirling waters of
the Río de la Plata in
the background.
The Río de la Plata estuary,
which is 280 km wide at its
mouth, sticks like a wedge into the
continent of South America
between Argentina and Uruguay.
Well inland, where the Paraná and
Uruguay Rivers meet, its two banks
are still 50 km apart. It is there, on
a peninsula at Uruguay's southern¬
most tip, on the edge of the pam¬
pas, that Colonia del Sacramento
was founded in 1680. This small
town was spawned by rivalries
between two colonial powers, Spain
and Portugal, and its turbulent past
is reflected in its unusual blend of
two architectural styles. It was on
those grounds that the site was put
on UNESCO's World heritage List in
December 1995.
Present-day Colonia del Sacra¬
mento, which is visited by tens of
thousands of tourists every year, is a
sleepy town untouched by the hurly-
burly of modern life. From its upper
district, it is possible at night to see
the twinkling lights of Buenos Aires,
the town from which, in 1680, the
first Spanish expedition set out to
take Colonia del Sacramento, then a
Portuguese stronghold.
A coveted prize
For almost a century the Por¬
tuguese and Spanish fought for con¬
trol of the Río de la Plata, which
was of strategic importance. It was
through that estuary, after a voy¬
age of several thousand kilometres
along the Paraná and Uruguay
Rivers, that precious stones and
hides from Bolivia, as well as pre¬
cious metals from Peru, passed on
their way to Europe. It was through
that same channel, butin the other
direction, that the Spanish and Por¬
tuguese transported and often
smuggled goods to the heart of
the continent.
It is generally agreed that the
first Spanish navigator to have
entered the Rio dc la Plata was Juan
Díaz de Solis in 1516. Later on,
Spanish, English, French and Dutch
privateers and pirates ventured into
the estuary and unloaded cattle on
to unknown land, hoping they would
quickly proliferate and become a
source of trade. But there were soon
clashes with the Portuguese, who
were seeking to extend their terri¬
tory to the south of Brazil. In 1680,
the Prince Regent of Portugal, Don
Pedro, ordered Colonia del Sacra¬
mento to be founded.
But the Spanish were in no mood
to accept that, and the same year
the newly-founded town fell into
their hands, despite the heroism of
Joana Galväo: after the death of
her husband, who had been given
the task of defending the fortress,
she took over command of his
troops. Colonia del Sacramento
URIERI JANUARY I9"7
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
.<?» @
The late 17th-century
Church of the Most
Holy Sacrament in
Colonia del
Sacramento is the
oldest in Uruguay.
Remains of the
St. Francis Xavier
convent adjoin the
Colonia lighthouse.
later changed hands several times as
a result of treaties or battles, and
was destroyed and rebuilt almost
as many times. It was not until the
first half of the eighteenth century
that Colonia enjoyed twenty-seven
years of uninterrupted rule by a sin¬
gle Portuguese governor, Antonio
Pedro de Vasconcelos. During that
time (1722-1749), the town was
graced with many fine examples of
civilian and military architecture
(the surviving examples of which
can be admired today). It also
reached its cultural and commer¬
cial zenith, and boasted twice as
many inhabitants as Montevideo,
which was founded by the Spanish
in about 1726.
'Don't let's tamper with the past'
In the early 1960s a small group of
Uruguayan history enthusiasts man¬
aged to persuade the government
and the town council to come up
with the financial and material
resources needed to preserve Colo¬
nia 's old quarter. Some house-own¬
ers agreed to sell their homes and
restoration work started.
In January 1991, a team of
archaeologists identified the pre¬
cise location of governor Vasconce-
los's palace. The discovery and sub¬
sequent work on the site resulted in
Uruguay's first laboratory of his¬
torical archaeology being set up in
Montevideo. Nelsys Fusco Zambe-
togliris, an anthropologist and
archaeologist at the National Her¬
itage Department, is opposed to any
plans for reconstruction. "Let's
keep the old stones just as they
are," she says, "and don't let's tam¬
per with the past, except to show it
to good advantage."
The historic quarter, which is
sandwiched between the remains of
the ramparts and the modern city,
covers the area of the former Por¬
tuguese town of Nova Colonia do
Santissimo Sacramento. It contains
almost 16 hectares of buildings in a
great diversity of styles. Its layout
is unusual. Unlike many other Span¬
ish and Portuguese colonial towns,
which were built on a grid pattern,
this stronghold was given a jigsaw-
puzzle design, partly because of the
site's topography, and partly to act
asa windbreak the Río de la Plata
is subject to fierce gales.
Plaza Mayor, which was adorned
with five royal palms and two cedars
at the beginning of this century,
gives on to the Río de la Plata. With
its public gardens and lovingly pre¬
served eighteenth-century man¬
sions, it has retained some of its
erstwhile bucolic charm. No. 180,
a modest building with thick stone
walls, houses the Portuguese
Museum. Its azulejos (enamelled
tiles), furniture made of Jacaranda
(a precious South American wood),
clothes and kitchen utensils stand
as a reminder that Colonia del
Sacramento long had connections
with the Portuguese crown. A
stone's throw away, a small street
called Calle de los Suspiros (Street
of Sighs) runs gently down to the
estuary. It has a central gutter that
drains rainwater off its uneven cob¬
bles, and is lined with early eigh¬
teenth-century peasant houses. Less
centrally located is the Spanish
Museum, the home of exhibits and
documents relating to the Spanish
presence in the town.
Probably the most interesting of
Colonia's seven museums is the
Municipal Museum, once the resi¬
dence of the Irish Admiral William
Brown, who played a heroic role in
Uruguay's independence. It offers
THE UNESCO ^ÏURIERB JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
HERITAGE
the most comprehensive collection
of exhibits connected with the town's
history. On top of 50,000-odd docu¬
ments in Spanish and Portuguese and
wide-ranging collections of colonial
furniture, cannon-balls and stuffed
animals, there are a number of uten¬
sils and weapons used by Charrúa
Indians, the former hunter-gather¬
ers of the region who were massacred
and dispersed by colonization.
The governor's palace
The Church of the Most Holy Sacra¬
ment (Iglesia Matriz del Santísimo
Sacramento) is Uruguay's oldest
church. It has been partly destroyed
several times since its foundation in
the late seventeenth century. The
greatest damage was caused in 1823
when the sacristy, which was being
used as an explosives depot, blew
up. Despite restoration work, the
building has since, lost its original
architectural unity. The nave does
however contain some admirable
works of art, including a sixteenth-
century altar-piece, a seventeenth-
century painting of the Holy Family
and a sculpture of St. Francis of
Assisi made out of Paraguayan caoba
wood. The only elements of the orig¬
inal church that have survived are
its pillars, which date from 1695.
It is between this church and
Plaza Mayor that archaeologists
have succeeded in pinpointing the
site of the palace of the Portuguese
governor Vasconcelos. Nothing
remains of the building itself, but
by collating several ground-plans
dating from the colonial period it
is possible to delimit its outer walls
and reconstitute at ground level the
layout of each wall and partition
over a surface of 1,000 sq. m.
Despite extensive research and
excavations, the turbulent past of
Colonia del Sacramento's old town
has not by any means yielded all its
secrets, and much remains for
archaeologists yet to discover. I
LISTENING
ISABELLE LEYMARIE TALKS TO
DAVID SANCHEZ
Puerto Rico has a strong musical tradition dating back to the
early colonial period. At the beginning of this century, the
island had such a talented pool of instrumentalists that Afro-
American band leader and jazz pioneer James Reese Europe
recruited musicians for his wind section among them, in San
Juan, the capital.
Until the late 1960s Puerto Rican music was relatively
unknown outside the island, but since then a new generation of
musicians has emerged. Theyoung saxophonist David Sanchez,
one of the most expressive of present-day jazz composers and
performers, is a star in this constellation which also includes
drummer Giovanni Hidalgo and bass-player John Benitez, with
whom he has often played.
Isabelle Leymarie: Black influence is
very strong in popular Puerto Rican
musicboth traditional music and dance
music like salsa. This comes out very
clearly in your playing and your
compositions. Bomba Blues on your last
record, Sketches ofDreams, blended the
blues with bomba, an Ashanti- and Bantu-
inspired genre created in Puerto Rico.
David Sanchez: In Puerto Rico, 90 per
cent of the music has black roots. I'm
thinking of bomba, of course, but also
the more hybrid plena, which is played
with tambourines and appeared after
the First World War, and danza, which
is orchestrated for European instru¬
ments. Danza comes from old courtly
dances like the minuet, and when it
arrived in the Caribbean in the eigh¬
teenth century, it picked up African
syncopation. These black roots are per-
48 THE. UNESCO ÇjURIERB JANUARY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
vasive. Although we have our own
indigenous rhythms, which are our
hallmark, we've also left our mark on
Cuban music. Unfortunately, black
music in Puerto Rico is often over¬
shadowed by black American music
and is still far less widely played than
it deserves.
I. L.: Were you brought up in a musical
family?
D. S.: I grew up in Guaynabo, near San
Juan, in an atmosphere steeped in music.
At home I heard local performers such
as the drummer Rafael Cotijo, the singer
Ismael Rivera and El Gran Combo, a
famous band, all forerunners of Puerto
Rican salsa. My father used to listen to
the Mexican singer Toña la Negra and
Cuban musicians such as the Orquesta
Aragón and the singer Vicentico Valdés.
My sister, who was studying literature,
introduced me to Brazilian and Haitian
records and nueva trova, politically com¬
mitted Latin American songs of the late
1960s. I started playing on my brother's
drum set and the conga. I had a partic¬
ular liking for Cuban drummers such
as Mongo Santamaria, Patato Valdés,
Los Papines and El Niño, and jazzier
groups such as Irakere. I especially
remember Misa Negra, a composition
by their piano player, Chucho Valdés.
I. L.: How did you move from "Latino"
music to jazz?
D. S.: Again it was my sister who taught
me to appreciate jazz with records like
Miles Davis's Basic Miles and Billie
Holiday's Lady in Satin. When I was
twelve I moved onto the tenor saxo¬
phone. I studied classical technique
and then went on to the Escuela Libre
de Música in San Juan, where some of
our best musicians have studied. Then
I analysed the styles of the great jazz
saxophonists: Pen Webster, John
Coltrane, Dexter Gordon and Sonny
Rollins, whom 1 particularly admire.
I. L: Although you're known as a jazz
musician, you've never lost your affection
for Latin rhythms.
D. S.: Yes, I like playing what is known
today as "Latin jazz". It's a hybrid style
that came from the United States in the
late 1940s with musicians like Dizzy
Gillespie, Charlie Parker, Mario Bauza
and Chano Pozo, who realized that jazz
and Afro-Latino music flowed from the
same sources and that they could get
along very nicely. Some critics occa¬
sionally ask the question whether jazz
will last. I'm convinced that the future
of jazz is in Latin jazz. At a time when
jazz often returns to a certain kind of
classicism, Latin jazz has created new
forms of expression. Its popularity
keeps growing, and we Latin Ameri¬
can jazzmen are in top form.
I. L.: There seem to be two musical
trends in Latin America and the Caribbean
right now: a return to roots and fusion
between different musical genres.
D. S.: The whole of Latin America, and
Puerto Rico in particular, is multicul¬
tural, and has been from the start of its
history. This is where we get our inspi¬
ration. This is what shapes our per¬
sonality. If more people understood
the enrichment that comes from cohab¬
itation with other ethnic groups, there
wouldn't be so many conflicts!
rTHE UNLSCO (^OURIERB JANUARY 1997 ~
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
L I T E N N
I.L.: The Cuban flautist Alberto
Socarras used to describe how, when he
moved to Harlem in 1929, American
musicians couldn't believe that someone
with a Spanish accent could play their
music as well as they did. Is it still hard for
a Puerto Rican instrumentalist to be fully
accepted in the American jazz world?
D. S.: Sometimes there are tensions , but
the joy of making music usually wins
out over racial, language or cultural
differences. As in any art form, what
counts first and foremost is an open
heart.
I. L.: How do you compose your music?
D. S.: The first thing I usually dois set
the beat and the melody. Forme, these
are the two most important factors.
Rather than structure, I create themes
and melodies that bring about the form.
In my last recording, Street Scenes, I
wanted to reproduce the different kinds
of atmosphere in big cities like Paris
and New York. Street life and everyday
scenes were my sources of inspiration.
Except for Four in One by Thclonious
Monk, all my compositions were sug¬
gested to me by my band. Sometimes
it's the way my musicians play that gives
me ideas, and after a performance I
sometimes sit down and transcribe into
music what I've felt. I
DISCOGRAPHY
THE DEPARTURE
COLUMBIA 476507 2
SKETCHES OF DREAMS
COLUMBIA 67021
STREET SCENES
COLUMBIA 485137 2
Courier
EXPOLANGUES 1997
THE UNESCO (oURIERand its 29 language editions are taking part
in EXPOLANGUES 1997, the 15th International Salon of Languages, Cul¬
tures and Travel, which is being held in the Grande Halle de la Villette,
Paris, from 29 January to 2 February 1997. Visitors to the Salon will dis¬
cover a range of language-teaching methods (from traditional teach¬
ing to CD-Roms) and explore opportunities for learning languages on vis¬
its to the countries where they are spoken. Also on the agenda are
lectures and an international festival of world cultures and music,
designed as an initiation into the cultural pluralism of which linguis¬
tic diversity forms part. Canada is the guest of honour of this year's
EXPOLANGUES.
Forfurtherinformation, contact
REED-0IP, 11 rue du Colonel Pierre Avia,
Boîte postale 571, 75726 Paris Cedex 15, France.
Tel: (33) (0)141 90 47 47; Fax: (33) (0)1419047 00.
AUTHORS
N ATASCHA BATIÓ, a graduate of the Vienna
Academy of Diplomacy, is an Austrian journalist
specializing in international relations.
SAYEEDA RAHMAN, of Bangladesh, Is in charge of
the co-ordination of Unesco's activities related to
microfinance, in particular collaboration with the
Grameen Bank.
JOSÉ GARSON, of France, is Senior Technical
Adviser for microfinance with the United Nations
Capital Development Fund (UiMCDF) at the United
Nations Development Programme (UNDP), New York.
He also teaches at the College of Europe in Bruges
(Belgium).
MARÍA OTERO, of the U.S.A., is Executive Vice-
President of ACCIÓN International. She is co-editor
of The New World of Microenterprise Finance
(Kumarian Press, 1994) and has written several
studies and articles on microenterprise and related
issues.
ROBERT PECK CHRISTEN, an American economist,
is Director of the Microfinance Training Program at
the Economic Institute, U.S.A. He is the author of
many published works, including Financial
Management of Microcredit Programs: a Guidebook
for NGOs (Cambridge, MA, ACCIÓN International,
1990).
MUHAMMAD YUNUS, of Bangladesh, is Managing
Director of the Grameen Bank, which he founded in
1983. He was formerly Professor of Economics at
the University of Chittagong (Bangladesh) and has
written widely on poverty alleviation and
development. In 1996 he received the International
Simon Bolivar Prize, awarded by Unesco.
MARGUERITE S. ROBINSON, of the U.S.A., is a
social anthropologist and Institute Fellow at the
Harvard Institute for International Development
(HIID). She is the author of many books and
articles on economic development, including the
forthcoming The Microfinance Revolution:
Sustainable Finance for the Poor.
KIMANTHI MUTUA, of Kenya, is the Managing
Director of Kenya Rural Enterprise Programme (K-
Rep). He has published many articles on
microfinance.
RUPERT SCOFIELD, a U.S. economist, is Executive
Director of the Foundation for International
Community Assistance (FINCA International), which
he co-founded in 1984.
MARIA NOWAK, a French economist, is founder
and president of the Association for the Right to
Economic Initiative (ADIE). She works for the World
Bank in eastern Europe, where she has set up
several poverty-alleviation programmes. Her
published works include La banquière de l'espoir
("The Banker of Hope", Albin Michel, Paris, 1994).
EDOUARD BAILBY is a French journalist who was
formerly a correspondent with the Paris weekly
L'Express and a press officer in Unesco's Office of
Public Information. He is the author of guides to
Cuba and Hungary, published by Arthaud, Paris.
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in the environment.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE is a Franco-American
musicologist and has recently published Du tango
au reggae, Musiques noires d'Amérique latine et des
Caraïbes (From Tango to Reggae, Black Music of
Latin America and the Caribbean, Flammarion, Paris,
1996) and Musiques Caraïbes (Caribbean Music,
Actes Sud, Arles, 1996).
HE UNESCO ÇiURIlR JANUARY 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
NEsco on line via Internet
gopher.unesco.org
o
http://www.unesco.org
Currently on-line are: an index of the contents of the last 22 issues of the Unesco Courier,
Unesco press releases, addresses, fax, telex and electronic mail numbers of Unesco's re¬
gional offices, National Commissions and Unesco Clubs, the directory of Unesco databases
and information services, colour images of the Japanese Garden and other architectural
sites at Unesco Headquarters, as well as works of art such as Henry Moore's reclining
sculpture.
directly with suggestions and comments, type:
unesco/courier@unesco.or
Pour recevoir un dossier d'inscription
exposant, renvoyez ce coupon à :
Reed OIP
11, rue du Colonel Pierre Avia
75015 Paris- France
Tel. : (33) 01 41 90 47 60
Fax : (33) 01 41 90 47 69
	xt
Nom	
Prénom .
Société.
Adresse..
Téléphone..
Activité..
Courrier de ¡Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
IWlFir lîMKiFîrïï MWÜsSk*nffli WÊ
THEME OF THE NEXT ISSUE:
HE WORLD OF
RADIO
NTERVIEW WITH
LAIN DE LIBERA
HERITAGE:
MR. JEFFERSON'S
DREAM HOUSE
ENVIRONMENT:
EARTHWATCHING
SATELLITES
llllslS BKS
]]>
</page>
</document>
