<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="105695eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
V
ENCOUNTERS
We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered for publication in this feature. Your photo should show a painting, a sculpture, piece
of architecture or any other subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send us pictures of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which you see some striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a short caption to all photographs.
RUINS OF THE EAST 1995, photos by Luc Maréchaux
In a series of photos taken in Lebanon and Syria, Luc Maréchaux compares the time-worn
ruins of majestic Palmyra (left) with the devastation wrought in Beirut by fifteen years
of civil war. "We can forgive slow destruction by time," he notes, "but what should we
think of destruction by human action?"
© Luc Maréchaux. Montreuil
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
URIER
Two writers from former Yugoslavia,
Predrag Matvejevic ¿mf Vidosav Stevanovic
talk about their anomalous status 'between
asylum and exile.' (p. 4).
Amiens cathedral (France),
a classic example of Gothic art (p. 40).
contents
MARCH 1997
PLURAL CITIES
Month by month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat	9
TANGIER: myths and memories	10
byTaharBenJelloun
NEW YORK blues 14
by Jerome Charyn
BOMBAY: one and many	19
by Lajpat Rai Jagga
MARSEILLES: port of call and recall	23
by Emile Temime
LA PAZ: a tale of two cities 28
by Luz Pacheco
VANCOUVER, or the spirit of place	32
by Hadani Ditmars
The spirit of diversity 36
byAnissa Barrak
Fact file	37
Consultant: Anissa Barrak
Commentai}' Federico Mayor 38
HERITAGE 40
Notre-Dame d'Amiens, a Bible in stone by Cécile Romane
GREENWATCH Large dams by France Bequette	44
REFLECTIONS The world is a sanctuary by Henryk Skolimowski	48
LISTENING Rediscovering Lili Boulanger by Isabelle Leymaríe	49
AUTHORS	50
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR 50
Cover: Didier Dorval © Explorer, Pans, S Fautre © Ask Images, Pans, Bruno Barbey © Magnum, Pans,
Luc Girard © Explorer, Pans; Georg Gerster © Rapho, Pans; Alain Evrard © Globe Press/Hoaqui, Pans
î ÇïURIITHE UNESCO lO IERB MARCH 1007
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
interview
Interviewed byJastnina Sopova, two leading writers from formerYugoslavia, a Bosnian Croatand a Serb,
testify in the light of their experience of the war that tore their country apart. Looking beyond eastern Europe,
they draw some general conclusions from what they have learned, about the role of the writer and the
psychology of nationalist conflicts.
Predrag Matvejevic
Predrag Matvejevic was born in Mostar (Bosnia and Herzegovina). His father was a Russian from
Odessa, his mother a Bosnian Croatian. He taught atthe University of Zagreb before settling in Rome
where he teaches Slavonic literature atthe University of Sapienza. A staunch champion of human rights
who defended many persecuted east European intellectuals under the communist system, he now spends
much of his time trying to healthe wounds of thefratricidalwarthat tore his country apart. The works
of this brilliant essayist have been translated into ten orso languages. His The Mediterraneana Cul¬
tural Landscape will be published laterthis year by the California University Press.
"Between asylum and exile" is the
formula you use to define your situation as
an intellectual "who came in from the East".
Predrag Matvejevic: I am not really an exile.
No one exiled me from Croatia and the
former Yugoslavia. I left Croatia because
I realized that I could express myself
more openly and freely elsewhere. But
when I had left, I saw that this was a
trap. This is what I meant when I talked
about being between "asylum and exile".
Asylum neutralizes your message and
exile distances it from its goal.
But intellectuals from the East are
not the only people in this situation. So
too are intellectuals in the Western world.
The relatively comfortable position they
enjoy in their own countries is a kind of
"born" asylum. At the same time they
are exiles because they cannot take part
in decision-making and have no say in
social projects. They are exiles in their
own homeland.
"Between treason and outrage" is
another phrase you often use.
P. M.: Yes. Every word I utter against the
atmosphere I live in, or against the
national group to which I belong, is
regarded as treasonable. Any criticism I
make of others is regarded as a calumny
and an outrage. This position "between
treason and outrage" exists in many cul
tures and destroys critical thought. You
are caught in a vice which prevents you
from expressing yourself freely.
The main reason foryourvoluntary exile
is to enjoy freedom of expression. Do those
who stayed behind have to keep their
mouths shut?
P. M.: I would say that they stand
"between silence and obedience". Silence
about mistakes that are made here too
I'm not only talking about former
Yugoslavia silence because you're
afraid to talk, because the media are
controlled, etc. Obedience, because by
obeying the authorities you keep your
privileges.
So are silence and obedience both forms
of self-betrayal?
P. M.: Not necessarily. Silence can mean a
lot of things. There are eloquent silences.
The silence of Boris Pasternak and Anna
Akhmatova under Stalinism meant "We
reject Zhdanovist social realism, wc
reject terror in the arts and letters." But
there is also a silence which is a sign of
conformity, of acceptance of an existing
state of affairs. I think this is the position
of the nationalist intelligentsia. Its silence
about what happened in Vukovar and
Sarajevo means: "Let's keep quiet. We
are not guilty."
CONTINUED ON PAGE 6
THE UNESCO ^U^RB MARCH I
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Between asylum and exile
Vidosav Stevanovic
Vidosav Stevanovic, a leading contemporary Serb writer, lived for thirty years in Belgrade, before going
into exile in 1991. Since 1995 he has been living quietly in a house outside the town of Kragujevac,
where he was born. Although his voice is not heard in his own country, he is well known internationally.
His works have been published in some twenty languages.
In 1995, after your period of self-
imposed exile, you returned to your home
country. But you still travel a lot	
Vidosav Stevanovic: I travel from time to
time. I often go to Paris. Soon I shall be
visiting Prague and the United States,
on the occasion of a film which is being
made based on The Island of the
Balkans, the second book of my trilogy
The Snow and the Dogs. The director is
a Croatian in exile. We are on the same
wavelength in our attitudes to our respec¬
tive countries. The Czech Republic is
ihc only country that has been willing to
give a nationality to this film. And so a
Croatian and a Serb are making a Czech
film for the European market, probably
in English. . . .
Isn't there a risk that this collaboration
will cause you problems? Predrag Matvejevic
describes a situation "between treason and
outrage".
V. S.: I agree with this idea. It is true to
our experience. The only way of avoid¬
ing the traps that are set for you is to
write what you feel and what you think,
whatever the cost, now or in the future,
when it may well be even higher. At least
you will have acted according to your
conscience; you won't have been sullied
by the evil that rages in the Balkans.
Is keeping silent a form of self-
preservation from this evil? Some writers
have chosen silence in the current situation.
V. S.: Most of my country's writers today
live in silence. An eloquent silence, some
people say. I don't agree with them.
There are moments in history when peo¬
ple should come out of their corner and
fight for specific values, in this case the
values of humanism (however old-fash¬
ioned that may seem), the values of a civ¬
ilization that does not know how to defend
itself. I'm talking about European civi¬
lization. We must fight for these ideals,
just as we must fight against those intel¬
lectuals who have engineered war pro¬
grammes and war propaganda, and
fomented hatred. Let's not be too indul¬
gent towards those who keep quiet. Can
we accept that a country's literature
should be reduced to a handful of people
who speak out in the midst of a general
silence?
When a war ends, people are affected
by collective amnesia. "There was no war,
we didn't take part in it; there were no
crimes, it's got nothing to do with us."
They remember nothing. Those of us who
speak out belong to the awkward squad,
because we remember what has hap¬
pened. "Undesirable" though we may
be, we shall continue to bear witness.
A people cannot get over its funda¬
mental problems without making an in-
depth analysis of itself, just as some
patients cannot be cured without being
psychoanalysed. Nationalism is a sick¬
ness. A people must settle accounts wilh
itself, face up to its phantasms and its
myths that are the source of everything
that has happened. Until it has come to
terms with its own conscience not other
people's the lull will he short-lived. The
phantasms will sink to the bottom and
CONTINUED ON PAGE 7
i (JulTHE UNESCO lOURIERB MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
interview
Predrag Matvejevic
I refused to adopt that position. That
is one of the reasons why I left.
This attitude is comparable to one that
appears in your recent books"between
refusal and praise".
P. M.: Yes. Some people don't only obey,
they sing the praises of the authorities.
Others don't take refuge in silence but
openly express their hostility to the
authorities. The gap between these two
positions is growing wider. Very few peo¬
ple stay in their country and express their
revolt.
Your latest book, The "Ex" World,
Confessions, contains some hard thinking
about the war in former Yugoslavia. You
write: "In this war there are neither victors
norvanquished. Everywhere there are
victims. . . ."
P. M.: And I go on to add: "There is no
just partition of Bosnia; the only act of
justice would be not to partition it." The
first victim is Bosnia itself. I have always
been on the side of the victims. At the
time of the aggression against Croatia
and against Vukovar, I was on the side
of the Croatian victims. But when Croa¬
tian soldiers destroyed the bridge at
Mostar which had survived all kinds of
barbaric acts since it was built in 1566,
and then the part of Mostar where the
Muslim majority lived, my sympathy
again went to the victims.
You also write: "Losing is part of our
destiny. But it is rare to lose a country. It
has happened to me." Is mourning an
appropriate word to use here?
P. M.: I think that former Yugoslavia's pol¬
icy of non-alignment in a deeply divided
world had merits that deserved a better
fate. Even if this people wanted to split
up, I would have preferred them to do so
without war. Perhaps I am alone in this,
but I like Yugoslavia as a whole. Wherever
I go in Yugoslavia I feel at home. At the
same time I don't think I usurp the iden¬
tity of its different constituent peoples
in any way. You might call this, wrongly,
"unitarist Yugoslavism" or talk of
" Yugonostalgia", but it's nostalgia for the
peace and well-being of all these peoples.
I am without prejudice. I just feel very
suspicious of those who are guilty, even if
they are guilty to different degrees.
What do you think of the emergence of
national cultures from Yugoslav culture?
P. M.: We all fight for the right to a
national culture. That is an undeniable
right. But some areas of a national cul¬
ture often turn into nationalist ideology,
as happened under fascism. The fascist
regimes included cultured people who
helped to shape their ideologies. We saw
this in Italy, Germany and Spain. We also
saw it in Stalinist Bussia. It is necessary
to be more critical and vigilant where
national culture is concerned. This is a
danger we're not always aware of.
In your recent books you sound the
alarm against another danger: considering
each characteristic of a people as an
intrinsic value.
P. M.: Yes, this mistake is often made.
Particularity is not necessarily a value.
Cannibalism is a particularity. Does that
make it a value? If you don't make a dis¬
tinction between these two notions, then
you can slip from particularity to par¬
ticularism.
Your book The Mediterraneana Cultural
Landscape, first published before the war,
was a reflection on the Mediterranean which
was not confined to current events. In The
"Ex" World, Confessions, however, which
appeared in 1996, you return to the same
theme but treat it quite differently. Is this
change of perspective a result of the war?
P. M.: Yes, the war sharpened some of my
attitudes. The earlier book ignored cur¬
rent events and said nothing about the
hard realities of the Mediterranean today,
whereas the chapter devoted to this in
my latest book is an indictment in which
I emphasize the complete difference
between the Mediterranean and the usual
image of it. This "land of myths" has suf¬
fered from the mythologies it has given
rise to. Decisions about its fate are taken
elsewhere.
What does it mean to be an "ex"?
P. M.: You are not born an "ex"; it is some¬
thing you become. From one day to the
next you discover that you are an ex-
Yugoslav or you declare that you are an ex-
communist. For some this is a happy expe¬
rience, for others a traumatic one. It is a
situation that is regrettable to varying
degrees (one does not miss the ex-Soviet
Union in the same way as one misses ex-
Bosnia and Herzegovina). In individual
experience, the word "ex" does not have
the same meaning. At the end of the last
century, Nietzsche said that he wanted to
be "untopical", i.e. "ex" in relation to the
present, but he had the future in mind.
The untopicality of certain "exes" today
looks towards a past that is over.
There seem to be a lot of "exes" in
Europe as the century draws to a close.
What has happened to the myth of
progress?
P. M.: The idea of progress and other
Utopian ideas were seriously compromised
by Stalinism and by what happened in the
former Soviet Union. The idea of emanci¬
pation has been pushed into the shadows,
whereas it should he held before us as a
guideline, without reference to any kind
of ideology. The absence of this idea, at
the end of the century, is tantamount to an
absence of humanism. It is here, outside
ideological paradigms, that I am trying
to find my way.
THE UNESCO lOURIERB MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Between asylum and exile
Vidosav Stevanovic
float back to the surface when the next
shock occurs; then we shall see a modern
version of last century's war in the
Balkans.
This recurring war is the leitmotiv of
your book recently published in French as
Prélude à la guerre (Prelude to War). In the
first edition, published in Serbian ten years
ago under the title Testament, you wrote:
"Today or tomorrow we shall lose freedom.
All that my ancestors have accumulated will
be taken away from us. Everything will be
destroyed, devastated, looted; people will
be torn to pieces, women raped, churches
desecrated. Nothing will be left . . . ." Those
were prophetic words.
V. S.: Critics have drawn attention to the
"prophetic" element in this book, but you
don't have to lie a genius to foresee war!
Wars usually break out for the same rea¬
sons, happen in the same way and are fol¬
lowed by the same amnesia. It's not hard
to be a prophet when you prophesy evil.
I don't want to be either a prophet or
a people's guide. That is not the writer's
job. At most he can be the voice of con¬
science, the voice of art, the voice of an
individual.
When I wrote that book, I was trying
to get down to the roots of the history
of Serbia and its people and trace how
myths had originated and been trans¬
formed into evil, into collapse. "Look
where your myths are leading you", I
wanted to tell people. Take them for
what they are: stories and nothing more.
Don't let them turn into monstrosities. I
tried to warn them. I failed.
In the same book, you also write: "Evil
is not in the world but in man; he alone
invented it and he alone uses it."
V. S.: Evil is just as much part of human
nature as good. Before launching out into
a crusade against other people's evil, one
should campaign within oneself. Though
evil is inherent in human nature, it is not
a dominant component of our world. The
proof is that the world continues to exist,
whereas the ultimate aim of all evil is to
destroy it.
Can the writer exorcise this evil, this
destructive instinct?
V. S.: The writer says: don't let yourself be
carried away by myths of death. He
writes a poem about death which is a
poem about life, about the beauty of liv¬
ing. The writer writes an endless poem
about an ephemeral world.
Is "Prelude to War" not also a quest for
this endless poem? "Is there some story
that will be never-ending . . . always ready
to admit me into it and to rescue me from
time, in which it would be impossible to
know which sentence, page or chapter will
come next?" you write, calling to mind
Jorge Luis Borges's Book ofSand.
V. S.: I am not a Borgesian, but perhaps
you are right. All the same, don't forget
that the hero of my novel asks this ques¬
tion but does not give an answer. Doesn't
a writer write the same story in many
books, in an attempt to save himself from
time, from the ephemeral?
Yourimaginary world seems close to
that of Julio Cortázar.
V. S.: Throughout my writing life I have
used a literary form that I called, before
Gabriel García Márquez, "fantastic real¬
ism". It consists of lifting from reality
images that can be transformed into fan¬
tasy and the surreal. Perhaps this
explains why you see a parallel between
my work and that of Latin American
authors. I am a great admirer of Latin
American literature. In the last thirty
years, it has brought something really
new to what we call world literature.
Do you believe in the existence of a
world literature?
V. S.: Yes, in the sense of a literature that
embodies receptiveness between cul¬
tures. On the other hand, I am very scep¬
tical about the idea of "national litera¬
ture", which is based ultimately on a
certain isolation. If you add to that the
various kinds of political climate that
prevail in our part of the world, for exam
ple political exclusivity, largely inca¬
pable leaders, intellectuals ready to lord
it on their own dunghill you get some¬
thing that is simply not viable: a closed
culture.
The political fragmentation of
Yugoslavia has led to the disintegration of
its culture. What are the consequences of
this?
V. S.: I feel no nostalgia for what was
called Yugoslavia. If it broke up it's
because disintegration was inevitable.
But I deeply regret that we have lost
what was called the Yugoslav cultural
area. None of the now-proclaimed
"national" literatures from that area
would be what it is without years of con¬
stant interpénétration with the others. I
have learned a lot from Croatian, Slovene
and Macedonian writers who belonged,
in my opinion, to one and the same cul¬
ture. That culture drew great profit from
its very diversity. It is very important to
have the opportunity to choose. If you
lock yourself up in your little enclosure,
you cease to have any choice. I think that
before establishing relations between the
new Balkan states, something that will
not depend on writers, it is vitally impor¬
tant that artists should continue to col¬
laborate, to learn from each other and
even why not? to quarrel if their quar¬
rels are creative.
The main ideological thesis of all
nationalism in the Balkans is that a com¬
mon life is impossible. That is what led to
war, to the creation of nation-states, to
ethnic cleansing, to crime. But each war
shows those people that their thesis is
crazy and without foundation. Each war
shows that in the Balkans, an area which
has, often wrongly, attracted many nega¬
tive connotations, a common life is not only
possible but absolutely indispensable.
This is why I think that culture or cul¬
tures should be the precursors of reuni¬
fication, not in some state or other, but
intellectually. There are enough links
between us to give rise to a single culture
and enough differences for that culture to
be strong. And that is the best thing the
Balkans can offer to the world.
> C°uTHE UNESCO ÍOURIERB MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Th*. UNESCO
Courier
^^' 50th YEAR
Published monthly in 29 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15. France
Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45
e-mai!. unesco couner@unesco org
Internet: http://www.unesco org
crossroads cities
Director: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition: Araceh Ortiz de Urbma
Features: Jasmma Sopova
Art Unit/Production Georges Servat
Illustrations Ariane Bailey (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press.
Solange Beim (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 87)
Film duplication: Daniel Meister
Secretariat" Annie Brächet
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45.68 47.15),
Administrative Assistant. Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean (Tel (33) (0)1.45 68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian Irma Utkina (Moscow)
German Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian: Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian. Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch Bart Chnstiaens (Antwerp)
Portuguese Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidm Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene. Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxian (Beijing)
Bulgarian. DragomirPetrov (Sofia)
Greek Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala* Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish Riitta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: DuangtipSunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto. Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa Aliyu Muhammad Bunza (Sokoto)
Ukrainian* Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Gahcian- Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax. (33) (0)1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions Mane-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Dm
(Tel. (33) (0)1 45 68 49 19}
Customer service: Michel Ravassard,
(Tel. (33) (0)1 45 68 45 91)
Accounts: (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 45 65)
Shipping' Daniel Meister (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel.: (33) (0)1.45.68.45.65
1 year" 211 French francs 2 years: 396 FF.
Students. 1 year 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues 72 FF
Developing countries
1 year" 132 French francs 2 years 211 FF.
Payment can te made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads 'Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor Signed
articles reprinted must bear author s name Non-copyright photos will
be supplied on request, Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage,
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not nee
essanly represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of
the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are written by the
Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by U.esco or the
United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in microtorm (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Pans. (2) University Microtilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100
U S.A , (3) N C R Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc . Ill West 40th
Street. New York, U S A ; (4) Bell and Howell Co , Old Mansfield Road,
Wooster, Ohio 44691, USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL. Cl - MARS 1997
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N M PP
Photocomposition, photogravure.
Le Courrier de TUnesco
Impression: MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z I. Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041 5278 N' 3-1997-OPI-97-557 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2 3 and 50-51.
Thomas Höpker © Magnum, Pans
8
THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
New York, Tangier, Bombay and the other cities profiled in this
issue, have been dubbed "crossroads cities", a term which calls
for some explanation. They are cities where life is particularly
rich and variegated because their history has been punctuated
by the arrival of successive waves of immigrants who settled in
them side by sidein some cases packed closely together.
Prosperity wove the different strands of this urban popula¬
tion together and crisis unravelled them, but as hopes gradually
mingled and memories intertwined, a sense of belonging devel¬
oped, albeit one that fluctuated between solidarity and con¬
flict. The pulse of these cities beats more intensely and more
unpredictably than that of many others, but each one has
acquired the knack of handling its spasms of violence and even
of drawing vitality from them.
At first sight, these unusual socio-cultural excrescences
seem to tell us nothing about the countries in which they are
located. A closer look shows that this is not so. They have been
grafted onto their nation's tissue and the graft has taken. They
have grown and prospered within the nation because through a
mysterious alchemy they have responded to some of its unspo¬
ken aspirations and unavowed desires.
What is more, these cities have often been pacemakers of
their country's modernization, sometimes in the teeth of strong
opposition. It is due to themalthough the debt is not always
acknowledgedthat their country is geared to major trading
flows and to the non-stop movement of people, ideas, capital and
merchandise. In a word that it keeps pace with the changing
world.
They contribute to their country something far more than
resources and knowledge. They instilinto it the creative energy
generated by the combustion of a very broad spectrum of think¬
ing and imagination, by myriad sources of inspiration and by
the revitalization of beliefs and powers of invention. And this
energy seeps through hidden channels into the surrounding
country, bearing much-needed antidotes to uniformity and con-
formism.
By virtue of the contradictions they harbour and the con¬
flicts they foment, crossroads cities are laboratories of the
future for their respective countries as they face the challenges
of globalization.
> CouTHE UNESCO OURIER! MARCH 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
13nsíig \ my^s m^ mem°r^es
© Roger-Viollet, Pans
BY TAHAR BEN JELLOUN
Tangier a gateway to Africa, and a
window on Europe still draws sus¬
tenance from its myths and legends,
even though the city has expanded,
looks different and no longer recognizes its
children. This is the fate of places marked by
transience, the crossroads of history and
rumour. A point of departure (of escape) and
arrival, a port for easy dreams and uncertain
journeys, Tangier no longer knows what to do
with its reputation. The deeds and misdeeds
ascribed to it are legion; so too are the clichés
and fiendish images it has given rise to, and
the fractured prose and obscure poetry it has
inspired. It has been painted in every possible
colour, and evoked in salons and galleries so
often that it has become a ghost dressed in
shabby silk, a crumpled postcard not fit to
be sent to a friend waiting in the faraway cold.
A year after the death of Marco Polo, Ibn
Batuta, who was known as "the prince of trav¬
ellers", left Tangier on 14 June 1325 (he was
born there in 1304) on the journeys that
would take him several times round the then
known world. He did not often feel homesick
for the city, but he was haunted by its image.
Its perfumes and smells followed him every¬
where, conjuring up the memory of a peaceful
community where nothing untoward ever
occurred. He wrote that Morocco, "the land
where I wore the amulets of childhood and
where the dust first touched my skin", was
the best of all countries. In the travel note¬
books (Rihla) which he dictated, there were
few references to Tangier, which had not yet
become a crossroads. It was above all a port
from which people set out to explore the
world or seek adventure.
G Thepainter's eye
In 1832, Eugene Delacroix stayed in Tangier
before going on to Meknès, Fez and other
places. He was welcomed everywhere and did
not conceal his surprise or his sense of won¬
der. "I have now arrived in Tangier," he noted.
"I have just made a tour of the city and I am
full of astonishment at all I have seen. I would
need twenty arms, and days forty-eight hours
10
THE UNESCO QjURlElRH "MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Left, Avenue d'Espagne
in the 1930s.
Jewish Wedding in Morocco
(1839), oil on canvas by
Eugène Delacroix.
long, to give an account of it all. ... At the
moment, I am like a man in a dream who sees
things which he fears will escape his grasp	"
Through the good offices of Abraham
Benchimol, an interpreter at the French Con¬
sulate, he was able to obtain an introduction
to Jewish society in Tangier which gave him the
opportunity to paint his celebrated Jewish
Wedding. In a letter to his friend Pierret dated
25 January 1832, he wrote: "The Jewish
women arc admirable. I am afraid that it would
be difficult to do anything but paint them:
they are pearls of Eden".
Later on, another French painter, Henri
Matisse, came to Tangier, where he stayed at the
Hôtel Villa de France. At first, torrential rain¬
fall kept him confined to his room. Since he
had come for the sun and the light, he almost
gave in to disappointment and thought of
returning to France. Fortunately, he decided to
stay until the weather turned fine. That year,
1912, marked a new direction and dimension
in his work. The light of Tangier was a revela¬
tion to him.
Other painters have spent time in Tangier.
Today the Chilean Claudio Bravo lives and
works there. He seldom emerges from his
beautiful house at the foot of the "Vieille
Montagne" and he paints the people and
objects of Tangier in a hyper-realistic manner
which cannot be reduced to orientalism or
exoticism. Claudio Bravo paints the meeting of
two civilizations. He turns this place into a
crossroads where different ways of seeing and
being, different visions of the world and sen¬
sibilities, and a mix of different temperaments
all confront each other. In fact, his attraction
and respect for Moroccan popular culture have
made it virtually the main subject of his work.
I An international city
For some forty years, until 1957, Tangier had
the status of an international city. What did
that mean for its inhabitants? Although it had
a representative of the royal authority, the city
was administered by several different countries.
However, the most widely spoken language,
apart from Arabic, was Spanish, and the most
widely used currency was the peseta. Other cur¬
rencies could be exchanged in booths on the
rue Siaghinc, between the jewellers and the
bazaar stall-holders. There were as many schools
as there were countries represented in the city.
Young Moroccans had the choice between the
Spanish Institute and the Italian school, the
E Unesco Kurier march 1997 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
in the past compose nostalgic laments for a
Tangier which no longer exists.
American school and the French lycée. At this
time cosmopolitanism was a lifestyle, multi-
lingualism was not encumbered by the problem
of identity, and the Muslims of Tangier lived in
the same neighbourhoods as the Christians and
the Jews. The Calle Sevilla was known as the
Spaniards' street, but Muslims lived in the same
buildings sidc-by-side with the Spaniards and
there was no feeling of mistrust between the
two. It was a time when Moroccans wondered
how nearby Spain, a fairly poor country, could
be capable of colonizing them. They did not ask
this question about the French, who did not
mix with the others and often behaved in an
overbearing manner.
This period when the city had an interna¬
tional status witnessed the arrival of more
traffickers, gangsters, forgers and insolvent
or ruined businessmen than artists. Yet the
1 950s were prolific years for the group of Beat
Generation poets who discovered Tangier and
turned it into a centre for writing, pick-ups
and a total change of scene. Allen Ginsberg,
William Burroughs, Jack Kerouac, Lawrence
Ferlinghetti, Paul Bowles and Tennessee
Williams all came together to smoke hash,
party and improvise poetry performances.
Jean Genet did not mix with this set, even
though he knew most of the poets. He did not
like Tangier, which he compared to the French
Riviera And yet he wrote in The Thief'sJour¬
nal: "This city (Tangier) represented Betrayal
for me so well and so magnificently that I felt
I had no option but to come ashore here".
How did a gathering place of travellers,
traders, diplomats, gangsters and exiles come
to symbolize what Jean Genet called
"Betrayal"? It is probably because this port
opening on the West, washed by two seas, the
Atlantic and the Mediterranean, this myth
which still preserves some Roman remains,
this route to other places, is a stage where life
and death are played out, where old actors
take refuge in retirement, where writers fixed
eneral view of Tangier.
i café in the Socco
district.
M,larketscene
in the casbah, the high
part of town.
¡Fading romance
This memory of a city with its special status
still finds a refuge among people of another
age, outlasting the dampness of the tired walls,
the gusts of the East wind and the eternal
spirit of hope which one day will save Tang¬
ier from decay. It is in this sense that the city
is romantic, destined to appear in works of
fiction or fantasies stalked by mystery.
Over the past thirty years, until a major
clean-up campaign was launched early in 1 996, a
parallel clandestine economy linked to "mint"
(kif) trafficking was concentrated in Tangier.
Traffickers, smugglers and even government
officials were arrested and tried. At the same
time, a relentless struggle began against the smug¬
glers of human beings: people trying to emi¬
grate. Tangier had become the last stage for those
who hoped to cross the straits of Gibraltar and
find work in Spain or elsewhere. People came
Bit
THE UNESCO ÍOURIERB MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
from all over, from southern Morocco and even
from certain African countries, to embark at
night on boats belonging to unscrupulous
fishermen.
The city has grown. So-called "popular and
spontaneous" new districts have mushroomed
on the outskirts. Beni Makada, which was a
huge shantytown, has become an almost new
M scene in the medina,
the old town.
Ihe port
seen from the medina.
and respectable quarter, where the buildings are
now all solidly built. Casabarata is no longer
a shantytown, either. Tangier is no longer con¬
fined to the old city, the Casbah, Marshan and
the cattle market the residential area along
the road to the "Grande Montagne". Tangier
is spreading in length and breadth. The city's
old families arc isolated and in a minority. Per¬
haps that is why they arc not managing to
make their voices heard and to fight for the
future of their city.
Tangier is starting to lose its identity as a
crossroads, a place of trade and cross-fertil¬
ization, and is coming to resemble any other
modern Moroccan city. Fortunately, there arc
artists, most of them foreign, who still have
a passion for the city. Some of them live there
permanently, others come several times a year.
Neither they nor the people of the city can
understand or explain the attraction for this
port which can often seem shabby or com¬
monplace. Someone encapsulated this feeling
in the phrase: "I can't explain why I love this
city, but I know why I don't love it! " Appar¬
ently, love wins over everything else and peo¬
ple keep coming in spite of the wind and the
decay, the annoyances of everyday life and the
spectacle of a city adrift.
THE UNESCO Ç)URltR1 MARCH 1097 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
newyork
BY JEROME CHARYN
N
ew York is a city that breathes
fairness and barks against
inequality. It's this that has
made it the marvel of the twen¬
tieth century, not its skyscrapers or its bil¬
lionaires. New York's skyscrapers have lost
their lyrical line, and no billionaire has ever
really made a dent in the city's chaotic heart.
New York is the only city on the planet where
the lower depths fought against the rich, estab¬
lished order and won.
These lower depths arrived in the form of
the Irish, who tossed the Protestant majority
out of city government and became the boss of
Manhattan right after the Civil War, around
1 865. The Irish were never bankers or brokers,
and they rarely built mansions on Fifth Avenue
or anywhere else, but they were firemen and
cops and schoolteachers, mechanics, gangsters,
and politicians, who practised their own rude
Hn ocean liner arriving in
New York harbour circa 1925.
;:'r
' Il
I...
ill»
mi!
Mil
;¡i;i
¡ ' ii
i
, i
il !!
i ;,
i i i
M 'I
democracy, stealing from the city and also edu¬
cating and feeding the poor. And when the first
immigrants from Eastern Europe arrived in
the 1 870s, the Irish enlisted them in their own
anarchic political machine. The greenhorns voted
for Irish mayors and aldermen before they
could even spell their own names.
Wave after wave of immigrants soon fol¬
lowed the same example Italians, Ukraini¬
ans, Greeks, Polish, Russian, and Romanian-
Jews, Magyars, Albanians, Slovaks, Serbs, who
helped create their own turbulent tribal orches¬
tra until the National Origins Act of 1 924 cut
off the flow of "mongrels" from Eastern
Europe. But not even the anti-immigrant hys¬
teria of the United States Congress could really
change the complexion of the vitality of immi¬
grant New York. The "mongrels" had learnt
THE UNESCO QíURlíRM MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
.' 	 " »'Ulli) il "il
. . . - , [i ; -ir.- .
i . ., . , , r
. i r ' . .
*-= -
I
III"
r«¿- i jiij) ' i Min ir
niiiniimi i ii dab-"il|.i i
' i"iv ''ViL'ii , ,
;.;;;. ¡i:l.i. ;:.,.;l....
i!:::)!!:!!i!!!'!î!i!îii!Ji-ii!i!i!i!i'u.ii
r^i.*.*..i.(*( *	.»
"i!niMÍliii!iii¡iiiil¡iiii"i'i'i;i|iÍí';ii!Í¡i¡;
.....
i
ff ]]¡l¡ll¡l!i;l!i!v,..i	i:i;l
fifiSlilüilm ! IÎ1!!?!J! I!]!lii.|!!!]!lil ! IÎ1I
I he southern tip of
Manhattan.
English, could interpret all the complex signs
and signals of the metropolis, could gather
capital for their own enterprises, could buy
their own seats on the New York Stock
Exchange. Even more important, they helped
school their own and other people's children
without rancour or a sense of exclusion.
New York in the 1930s, in the midst of
the Great Depression, was still the most
democratic place on earth. It encouraged the
very idea of rebellion, the sacredness of indi¬
vidual rights, the belief that any government
which did not serve these rights should and
could be driven out of office. Even Holly¬
wood understood this ethos and capitalized
on it. In film after film The Bowery (1934),
Dead End (1937), Angels with Dirty Faces
(1938), Cityfor Conquest (1940)New York
ers are depicted as an unruly lot, women, chil¬
dren, and old men who provide their own
liberty and law. This ethos even reached as far
as Rick's Cafe (Casablanca, 1943), where Rick
Blaine (Humphrey Bogart) warns a German
major (Conrad Veidt) that if the Nazis ever got
near Rick's old neighbourhood of Hell's
Kitchen, they had better run for their lives.
But there are no Rick Blaines today. Is the
City becoming a kind of behemoth as it
approaches a new century? Its public schools are
dying. It cannot seem to educate its young,
teach them the most basic skills, or convince
them that the city is there for them. New
York's crisis of faith has become the crisis of
every large American city. The poor have lost
their place. They cannot negotiate for them¬
selves in this labyrinth. Since 1965, three million
THE UNESCO Q>IIRI ERB MARCH 1097
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
t immigrants have arrived in New York, most
of them non-white: Jamaicans, Dominicans,
Mexicans, Koreans, Pakistanis, Indians, Chi¬
nese, who have formed their own tribes and
entered into the fabric of New York, but it's
not the same democratic family. Blacks and
whites are further apart than they ever were, in
spite of "integration." Young black males have
become an endangered species in New York.
They cannot survive the system's shabby pub¬
lic housing and shitty public schools.
No one, not even the most passionate New
Yorker, seems capable of dealing with that
heartless dividing line between whites and
blacks. Poor blacks (and Latinos) have fallen
lop, immigrants take the oath of allegiance during a
naturalization ceremony in New York City.
Mbove, a meeting of "Guardian Angels", volunteers who
patrol the New York subway.
Left, street scene in New York City's Chinatown.
outside America's vocabulary. They arc, as nov¬
elist Ralph Ellison described over forty years
ago, invisible women and men. It doesn't really
matter that some blacks have escaped the
ghetto to have fabulous careers as rap singers,
generals, actors and actresses, comedians, box¬
ers, basketball and baseball players. The others
have been left woefully behind. And the
despair, paranoia, and depression get worse
and worse. The overwhelming majority of all
prisoners in New York State come from the
poorest black and Latino neighbourhoods in
New York City. These neighbourhoods, like
Harlem and Brownsville and the South Bronx,
arc the ghastliest sort of ghettos, where crime
THE UNESCO lOURIERl MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
begets crime, where the walls of every block are
filled with painted elegies to fallen black and
Latino warriors. This is the fastest-growing
art coming out of the ghettos. And the young
artists who are painting these testimonials are
sought out everywhere. It's ironic and sad that
their only real capital is death.
The South Bronx has become the worst of
the little laboratories of crime. The police are
quite proud that they have been able to use
the same federal statutes that trapped Mafia
chieftains like John Gotti to go after the black
and Latino gangs of the South Bronx and toss
them into jail. The exploits of these crusading
cops were written up in The New Yorker's
Above, New York's Indian community celebrates Indian
Independence day (15 August) on Fifth Avenue.
Kight, a city playground.
Qelow, a Chinatown grocery store.
"Talk of the Town" column, which praised
Walter Arscnault, chief of the Homicide Inves-
tigationUnit, "a small team of detectives and
prosecutors which specializes in large gang
busts and has not lost a single case in its ten-
year history." Arscnault, whose uniform is a
pair of blue jeans and a white oxford shirt, is
like a wizard who can rattle off the nicknames
of every defendant in a particular case
"Chicken, Foodhead, Pacqualito, Popcorn,
Dominican David." But is the South Bronx or
Ç Brownsville in better shape without "Pop-
Is corn" and "Dominican David"? I doubt it.
| As soon as one gang is pulled off the street,
| another gang forms. It's all part of the same
> Q>uTHE UNESCO ÍOURIERB MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
^ implacable beast, that Hydra's head of depra¬
vation that keeps fattening itself on other peo¬
ple. The police can only solve problems in a
community by being part of that commu¬
nity, by living in it, by sharing its despair,
bathing in its stink. But the cops never live in
the communities they patrol and rarely have a
stake in them. They are often part of the cor¬
ruption that helps destroy a community, in
spite of Walter Arsenault's heroics.
The South Bronx always had its gangs, even
sixty years ago, when the gangs were mostly
white, and the cops who dealt with them often
came out of the very same gangs. Then and
* now, the poor had to have their colours, their
territories, their little flags, declaring that they
were outlaws in a world that was largely indif¬
ferent to them and their designs. To some
degree, it was an educative process, a means
whereby a gang could talk to itself and other
gangs, find a common language. I'm not dis¬
missing the plunder and mayhem of any gang,
past or present. But most often, the gangs fed
off their own entrails and still do. Their com¬
mon language still unites them; it's the only
schooling many of them will ever have either
the old Fordham Baldies or today's La Com¬
pañía, Wild Cowboys, and Jheri Curls.
The police had better learn to understand
the dynamics of the gangs and their will to
survive, or they themselves and the city of
New York will not survive the gangs, which
are already taking over and "educating" the
jailhouses they are in.
New York itself has become an enormous
jailhouse, where the rich have their isolated
"free" zones, and the poor are tucked away in
ghettos that are growing larger every day. Cap¬
tured gangs will not make the problems disap¬
pear, only the deepest compassion and a com¬
mitment to overcome white and black paranoia
can possibly change things. New York is like
any other nation involved in internecine war¬
fare, and that warfare has to be stopped. It.will
not come with crime statistics which claim that
homicide is going up or down. Statistics always
lie. They're the baldest, crudest propaganda.
Crime will go down when New Yorkers feel
themselves to be a family again. It might start
to happen right now, as young artists, white
and black, invade bombed-out areas in search of
cheaper rent. But will they involve themselves
with the poor? Or will they recreate "fashion¬
able" neighbourhoods that will only drive up
the rent and oblige the poor to plunge into yet
another ghetto? No one really knows.
But I'm always the optimist. Like any
Depression baby (I was born in 1937), I still
believe in fairness. And no magical policeman
in blue jeans will ever take that away.
flight, film stars parade
through crowded Bombay
streets in a fund-raising
campaign for hurricane
victims.
Ounbathing during
lunch break in the business
district.
W THE UNESCO ÍOURIERB MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Bruno Barbey © Magnum, Pans
BOMBAY
BY LAJPAT RAI JAGGA
Bombay, the gateway to India, is a city
of contrasts. On the one hand, the
dazzling interiors of its five star
deluxe hotels; on the other the
poverty and squalor of its slums. The capital
of Indian finance and films, it is a city of hope
and despair, evoking desire and promising a
future, however illusory, to all who come to
its shores. The rags to riches stories that
abound in Bombay films recreate the myths of
its dream world.
I The European connection
Legend has it that Bombay, or "Mumbai",
derives its name from Mumbadevi, the goddess
worshipped by the Kolis, the earliest inhabi¬
tants of the archipelago on which the city is
situated. It is probable, however, that the city
one and many
derived its modern name from the Portuguese,
to whom it was ceded in 1534 by the Sultan of
Gujarat, and who called it "Bom Bahia", the
beautiful bay. In 1661, it was given as a marriage
gift to Charles II, the king of England, by his
queen, Catherine of Portugal. Its territories
then consisted of seven islands, interspersed by
swampy, low-lying areas, eighteen kilometres
long and seven wide, with Malabar Hill rising
to sixty metres above the sea, and the island of
Colaba as a narrow jutting headland. A nine¬
teenth-century traveller wrote that, "Bom¬
bay harbour presents one of the most splen¬
did landscapes imaginable", with "its gemlike
islands reflected in the broad blue waters" of
the Arabian Sea.
Evidence of human activity in the archipel¬
ago goes back a long way. The early Buddhist
19THE UNESCO COURIER MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
grottoes of Kanheri date from the second cen¬
tury A.D. Hindu grottoes and the sixth-eighth-
century caves of Elephanta testify to a rich cul¬
tural heritage. However, the region owes its
early economic development to the coming of
the Parsis, who arrived there from Iran in the
eighth century.
Starting in the seventeenth century, Euro¬
pean settlement on the west coast of India
the French in Cochin and Mahe, the Por¬
tuguese in Goa, Dieu and Daman, and the
English in Bombay, Baroda and Surat trans¬
formed the landscape, architecture, economy
and life-style of the inhabitants. The English
presence was the main catalyst of cultural and
economic transition in the Bombay region.
Rich merchant communities that had been
settled for centuries in the hinterland moved
to the ports, and Bombay became the focus of
this movement of indigenous culture and
wealth. The opening of the Suez Canal in 1 869
greatly enhanced Bombay's status as a port on
the Arabian Sea, and its rail links with the hin¬
terland made it the hub of all India.
Since the 1860s the Bombay economy has
been based on cotton its export and the man¬
ufacture of cloth. With the outbreak of the
American Civil War in 1861, and the conse- Victoria Station. "Mogul"
features complement the
Victorian neo-Gothic style.
quent "cotton famine", Bombay suddenly
emerged with a virtual monopoly of the world
cotton trade. Its merchants acquired wealth,
land and prosperity surpassing that possessed
by the colonial masters. Here in Bombay,
amongst its culturally diverse merchant com¬
munities and its modern cosmopolitan intel¬
ligentsia, was born the idea of freedom.
A blend ofarchitectural styles
While the growth of indigenous business and
finance made Bombay a hub of trade, the avant
garde movement in nationalist ideas, films and .
architecture made it the cultural capital of
India. In the course of the nineteenth century
Bombay evolved a typically Indian style in
architecture, and later in films and in the devel¬
opment of a composite culture that no other
city of the British Empire could boast of. In
architecture the Raj tried to impose its heavy
Gothic style, as can be seen in the gigantic
façades of the Victoria terminus and the city
hall. The merchant communities, mainly the
Parsis, tried to blend modern European and
traditional forms. The American historian of
urbanism Norma Evenson has pointed out
that a striking feature of nineteenth-century
20 THE UNESCO COURIER > MARCH 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
&Wfl
private building in Bombay was "its decorative
carving, a quality that linked it with the tra¬
ditional Gujarati architecture", while its fivc-
or six-storied buildings reproduced "the char¬
acter and charm of older centres of popula¬
tion" such as Amritsar, Lahore or old Delhi.
The creativity of this style is illustrated by
"airy balconies enriched with graceful carvings
and painted in all colours of the rainbow".
The façade style of older houses, with tradi¬
tional woodwork, has been "compared to that
of the Ionian Greeks"."" This blending of archi¬
tectural styles in nineteenth-century Bombay
was a part of the modern movement and the
city has continued to be an open window to
the outside world.
bove, the Hindu market
near Victoria Station.
light, a Bombay street
scene.
For over a century, Bombay has attracted
people from all over India, from all walks of
life to come to live and share the gentle sooth¬
ing winds of the Arabian Sea and the melodies
of the Hindi film song. Bombay today has a
population of nearly twelve million inhabi¬
tants, but it has always been a city of crowds,
a mix of many communities, cultures and lan¬
guages. Land was always scarce, and as early as
the 1 890s the Back Bay reclamation was started;
it still continues today. Reclamation and the
intermixture of socio-cultural groups may
sum up a century of Bombay's social history.
Apole ofattraction
Each social group has brought to the city its
richness and diversity, creating an environ¬
ment of tolerance and sharing. A person may
come from anywhere in India or the world,
here he or she is a Bombaywala, and speaks a
mixture of many languages. Whether people
sleep on the pavement, live in the slums or
reside in a Bungalow (big house) in Bandra,
they all share the city, its dreamy films, its
walks such as the Marine Drive, and its
beaches the Chaupati and Juhu. Over the
years, however, differences of community,
religion and social class have begun to plague
Bombay, as much as they have other cities of
northern India.
Nearly 70 per cent of the people of Bom¬
bay arc Hindus of diverse castes, sects and
beliefs. In recent years, however, the Maharathi-
speaking 45 per cent have begun to dominate
s "
HE UNESCO ÇiURIER MARCH 1997 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
the city's political life. Nevertheless, the
Gujarati, Sindhi, Punjabi or Marwari Hindu
merchant communities play an important role
in the city's economy. Nearly 1 5 per cent of the
population is Muslim. The Bohras and Kho-
jas are the more important business groups,
and their leader, Prince Aga Khan, is an inter¬
national figure. The Parsis, once Bombay's
most important community, are now in
decline, but still have a national presence in
the Tatas, India's most powerful industrial-
financial group. There are large numbers of
Christians, mainly Catholics, and there is also
a small Jewish community. Although the Jains
and Sikhs intermarry with the Hindus, they
have a separate cultural identity and exercise
considerable influence. Bombay's population
also includes oil-rich Arab sheikhs, Buddhists,
Armenians, Chinese and Europeans, who have
made the city their home and contribute to its
cultural texture
Bombay is not only a city of the rich or the
middle classes. It has attracted millions of
aspiring young people from all over the sub¬
continent. They speak different languages,
Konkani, Tamil, Kanard, Behari, Punjabi and
the beautiful tribal dialects. They all come to
Bombay in search of a livelihood, to live close
to the sea, and be a part of the dance, drama and
colour of its film world.
Necessary contradictions?
Each socio-cultural group has brought to the
city its place of worship, lifestyle, social cus¬
toms and habits, and has left historical monu¬
ments as a testimony of a composite culture.
The Hindus Marathi and Gujarati mer¬
chants gather at the ancient temple of
Walkeshwar (god of sand) on Malabar Hill, or
the temple of Mahalakshmi (goddess of
wealth), near which there is a mosque built in
the memory of Haji Ali, a Muslim saint. In
Worli is a Buddhist temple and the basilica of
Mount Mary, one of Bombay's twenty
Catholic churches. On the Back Bay, near the
Dhabi Hat, is the principal temple of the Jains.
In another part of Malabar Hill are the
Dakhmas, "towers of Silence", the place of dis¬
posal of the dead of the Parsis. Bombay also
has many Gurudwaras, Sikh places of worship.
Each community celebrates its religious fes¬
tivals: the Hindu Diwali, the festival of light
and Ganesh Chaturthi; the Muslim Muharram;
the Catholics' annual festival of Mount May.
For over a century these communities have lived
a shared life of mutual respect for each other's
religion and belief, but cracks have begun to
appear in this tightly woven social fabric.
The partition of India in 1947 left
wounds riots, internecine killings of Hindus
and Muslims which the passage of time has not
healed. Communal tensions elsewhere in India,
as in the case of the demolition of the Babri
Mosque in Ayodhya in December 1992, have
sparked off sectarian religious emotions and
riots. But more alarming is the growth of a sec¬
tarian organization, the Shiv Sena, which has
used political rhetoric Bombay only for the
Maharashtrians to win votes. A narrow
regionalism, coupled with sectarian religious
sentiments, could destroy the healthy mix of
cultures that Bombay has come to represent
for the rest of India. Bombay, a recent Hindi
film directed by Mani Ratnam, shows the
predicament of this city of cultural intermix¬
ture. It depicts the love story of a Muslim boy
and a Hindu girl, a saga of the reconciliation
of cultures of which Bombay is a living sym¬
bol.
* Norma Evenson, Indian Metropolis, A View Towards
the West, Yale University Press, 1989.
i improvised ball game
in the Panier district during
a day off school.
M<lodern buildings in
Bombay's waterfront
business district.
THE UNESCO f^URIERB MARCH 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
MARSEILLES
BY EMILE TEMIME
It is the destiny of Marseilles to be a cross¬
roads, a place of transit and a refuge. Mer¬
chants, travellers, migrants and merchan¬
dise meet in this city whose hinterland
spreads out along rivers and roads, this mythic
place that opens its arms to the Mediterranean
world. Once a colonial port, it has lived pri¬
marily from the passage of people and goods
whose diversity has shaped its long and event¬
ful history.
In the nineteenth century, a revival of com¬
mercial and industrial activity attracted busi¬
nessmen from northern Europe to Marseilles,
in accordance with a process that already existed
before the French Revolution, when the city
enjoyed privileges that made it a meeting point
between traders particularly Germanic
traders and ships that brought silk and spices
from the East or were engaged in the lucrative
West Indian traffic. This economic revival also
attracted Piedmontese, migrants from the
French Alps, and Ligurian sailors who found
temporary work in Marseilles and in due
course settled down there.
Later, after 1870, the Mediterranean was
the theatre of the great westward migration
THE UNESCO IpURIERB MARCH 1997
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Ihe Old Port in the late
nineteenth century.
of Italians, Greeks, Armenians and Levantines
towards the American Eldorado. For many
of these migrants, Marseilles was merely a
stopover, albeit a lengthy one in some cases. Its
population remained predominantly Euro¬
pean, but it was a cosmopolitan city, and after
the completion of the Suez Canal it became
more receptive than ever to all kinds of outside
trends and influences.
The following decades saw the arrival of
newcomers who gradually gave shape to the
Marseilles mosaic as we know it today. The
great influx of Armenians in the 1920s was
triggered by the violence and revolutions that
shook eastern Europe and the Middle East.
The use of "colonial" labour, starting early in
the twentieth century, brought to the Old
Port workers from the Far East, the shores
of the Indian Ocean (Somalis and Malagasy),
black Africa and, above all, from North Africa.
Marseilles industrialists were the first in France
to use Algerian workers. This flow of North
African workers was slowed neither by colo¬
nial wars nor by decolonization, after which
large numbers of "repatriated" French made
their way to Marseilles.
As a result of colonialism Algerians,
Tunisians and Moroccans came to constitute
the majority of "foreigners". In the 1970s
Comorians joined the Senegalese and Malians
who had long been settled in the city. There
have been sporadic inflows of Vietnamese,
Laotians and Cambodians. The decline in ocean
shipping and passenger traffic since 1 960 does
not seem to have had any immediate impact on
the city's multi-faceted identity.
m the Unesco Courier B march 1997
But an idyllic portrait of Marseilles would
be inappropriate. Terms like diversity, toler¬
ance, and acceptance of others should be han¬
dled with care. There is a longstanding mis¬
trust of newcomers. Divisions have always
existed, and sometimes minority groups have
been treated as outsiders.
Living together
Two centuries ago, many Catalonian fisher¬
men left Marseilles as a result of legal pro¬
ceedings. Anti-Italian demonstrations at the
end of the nineteenth century provoked a tem¬
porary exodus of Italians. More recently, vio¬
lence in 1 973 against Algerians spread fear and
caused some departu res. But all these episodes
were short-lived and did not jeopardize an
accepted and on-going cohabitation.
Coexistence is not always synonymous
with community. Crossroads arc not neces¬
sarily places where people really meet. One rea¬
son for this, in the case of Marseilles, is that
many people do not stay long in what is above
all a place of transit. All that many newcom¬
ers have known of Marseilles is life in fur¬
nished accommodation or transit camps, their
presence hardly noticed by the city's perma¬
nent population. I am thinking of the colonial
workers housed for years in the Lyautey and
Vict Nam camps of south Marseilles, of Jews
from North Africa and the survivors of the
concentration camps and ghettos of central
Europe after the Second World War, many of
whom lived in the "Grand Arenas".
MiI arket scene in
the Old Port, today a pleasure
boat marina.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
But even people who settle permanently in
the city do not always become part of the com¬
munity. Barriers remain. Ethnicity persists not
only because of rejection but because of the
bonds created by a common origin and a com¬
mon language and because of a basic need for
security and communication. The people of
Marseilles long dubbed "Belle-de-Mai" and
"Saint-Henri" in the northern part of town,
and "Menpenti" and "La Capelette" in the east,
as "Italian neighbourhoods". Later, Armeni¬
ans settled on the edge of the city at "Beau¬
mont" and "Saint-Antoine". They did not con¬
stitute the entire population of these areas, but
there were quite a few of them, and their sense
of solidarity was strong enough to identify
them with the neighbourhoods they lived in.
Such identification may last longer than the
demographic situation really warrants.
Divisions sometimes even persist when the
reasons for them have disappeared. In the inter-
| war years, for instance, Italians and Corsicans
| lived side by side in the "Panier" neighbour-
| hood, in the old town overlooking the sea.
1 They understood each other; their cultural
rado Beach.
>
E UNESCO ^JURIER MARCH 1 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
backgrounds were fairly similar; and they lived
in more less the same conditions. Many of
them did the same kind of work. Yet a closer
look reveals that for twenty years there were
Corsican streets and Neapolitan streets, Cor-
sican cafés and Italian cafés.
The many places of worship, often in the
same neighbourhood, demonstrate a de facto
tolerance and mutual acceptance that are actively
encouraged by the authorities. Their number is
synonymous with coexistence but not neces¬
sarily with dialogue. The longstanding diversity
of Christian churches is now matched by that
ofJewish and Muslim places of worship, with
their distinctive congregations and rites.
So it is not in the city's nature to erase cul¬
tural differences, and the steady turnover of its
population probably helps to maintain and
even strengthen traditions that might even¬
tually have disappeared with the appearance
of new allegiances.
Multiple allegiances
These allegiances, which transcend national
and religious boundaries, are largely based on
the jobs people do. This is true for all levels of
society.
Trade is the mainstay of the city's wealth
and has from very early times encouraged peo¬
ple of different origins and beliefs to com¬
bine their efforts and work together. The very
small French Protestant middle-class com¬
munity has played a role quite dispropor¬
tionate to its size. Some surprising alliances
have been made. In the nineteenth century, for
example, the Altaras, a devout Jewish family,
combined with a militant Catholic family, the
Caunes, to found an arms company.
At about the same time, Greek merchants
Belottom, Spanish immigrants
on the Canebière, the famous
Marseilles boulevard that leads
into the city from the Old Port.
Belelow, an American sailor
joins in a carnival organized by
Marseillais of West Indian
origin.
achieved notable status among the leading cit¬
izens of Marseilles, although at the outset
they did not take French nationality. Tech¬
nicians and engineers from Britain, Germany
and Switzerland also provided their expertise
and made a contribution to the city's mod¬
ernization.
More recently, fortunes of another kind
have been built on new networks and busi¬
nesses arising from North African initiatives.
In Belsunce, the business district of central
Marseilles, the fabric of commerce has been
woven, unravelled and woven again by Arme¬
nians, and Jews and Muslims from North
Africa. Competition is no obstacle to a
sense of community transcending national
and religious boundaries, although it may
give rise to mistrust and occasional misun¬
derstandings.
- M IE £
ilk- r 3 til!
For the most part immigrants have pro¬
vided the pool of unskilled labour needed to
run the port and the factories. This poorly
paid and exploited workforce included men
and women from all over the world. At first
Italians provided the bulk of the port work¬
ers, then Algerians, their ranks swelled until
the 1960s by Spanish, Greeks and Armenians,
in short all those who were forced to do'
unpleasant jobs in order to survive. Here, com¬
petition led to confrontation, but in the long
run awareness of common interests brought
these workers closer together and helped them
overcome longstanding grievances. The real
gaps are social, not national.
In the twentieth century, the middle classes
have concentrated in the southern districts,
continuing a process that began much earlier.
26
THE UNESCO (OURIERB MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The north-south polarity grew more marked
in the 1960s and 1970s when working-class
housing was built, mainly in the northern
neighbourhoods, for a population that was
growing in a context of full employment, a sit¬
uation that has changed since then.
Social integration
This cleavage naturally exists in daily life, start¬
ing at school. The school still does the "inte¬
grationist" job described by the long-standing
residents of working-class neighbourhoods
who look back to the time when children of
all backgrounds rubbed shoulders in the class-
An anti-racist demonstration
in a Marseilles street.
Marseilles worker gives a
colleague a friendly hand.
room, speaking a common, sometimes
invented language, a variant of French full
of foreign sounds and local jargon. But it is
true that social discrimination is growing
more marked and that schools are sometimes
closed because there are not enough pupils.
Working-class housing abandoned by its
more affluent residents is demolished.
But there are other places where the dif¬
ferent segments of the population come
together. They meet at places of recreation,
first and foremost at the soccer stadium,
where many of them probably identify most
strongly with the city. Gathering places less
well-known to non-residents of Marseilles
are the recently rehabilitated "beaches" along
the fringes of the southern neighbourhoods
and cultural centres (such as the "Maison de
l'Etranger") where different cultures can
express themselves. The "Fiesta des docks",
held in abandoned warehouses on the water¬
front, is another recent success in this field.
It attracted thousands of mostly young peo¬
ple from the city's new frontiers.
These new frontiers stretch to the Etang
de Berre and Aix-en-Provence. However, the
odds are that the city will only truly solve its
problems of unemployment, economic effi¬
ciency and harmonious coexistence by play¬
ing its traditional role as a bridge between
Europe and the Mediterranean. The big dan¬
ger would be for Marseilles to turn inwards
to its hinterland and break the bond between
the two shores of the Mediterranean.
THE UNESCO f3)LJR,ER" MARCH 1997
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
NuestraSeñora de La Paz (Our Lady
of Peace) was founded by the
Spaniards on 20 October 1548 in
the valley of the torrential river
Chuqueyapu. Located in the area where the high
plateaux of the Andes (the Altiplano) give way
to the slopes leading down to the Amazonian
side of the cordillera, it became an important
station on the route connecting the Potosi sil¬
ver mines to Cuzco and the Pacific coast.
At first La Paz consisted of two settle¬
ments, one for the "Indians" on the right bank
of the Chuqueyapu, near what is today Plaza
Alonzo de Mendoza; the other for the
Spaniards and their descendants, on the left
bank around Plaza Murillo. Although the
indigenous-mestizo and Spanish-creole pop¬
ulations lived in close proximity, in practice
they were divided by all kinds of physical and
symbolic barriers. The torrents and ravines ¡
that scar the hill-slopes around the historic |
town separated the different neighbourhoods, |
and after an uprising of the Aymara Indians of I
the Altiplano in 1780 a wall was even built to I
protect the white population. In« lk
r r r L. a Paz from the air.
M A social Babel
La Paz is the only city in Spanish-speaking
America that still has two names. In addition
to its official name it is known to the Aymara
Indians of the Altiplano as Chuquigo or
Chukiwayu Marka. In spite of the changes
wrought by the centuries, the shifting of the
neighbourhoods occupied by the different
populations, and ethnic intermixture, La Paz
still consists to a large extent of an Indian city
and a white city.
28 r
W THE UNESCO V__OURIER MARCH 1993
3i!»>tl- i "
&ê
'f *
-» ^ \,
This polarity is etched into its majestic
site, dominated by Mount Illimani, whose
peak towers over 6,400 metres high. The
world's highest capital, and the different social
strata that live in it, extends in tiers between the
altitudes of 4,200 and 3,200 metres. On the
heights, slopes and edges of the Altiplano live
Aymara Indians who have migrated from the
countryside. The middle classes live in the
heart of the city, at around 3,600 metres, near
the administrative and commercial centre (La
Paz became the seat of the Bolivian govern-
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
-*~"~
ment in 1900). Below 3,500 metres are resi¬
dential districts where an affluent and largely
white population lives in expensive houses
surrounded by gardens whose upkeep is
favoured by a more temperate climate.
The 1,000 metres between the "top" and
"bottom" layers, between the Indian settle¬
ments of El Alto and the elegant districts of
Calacoto, la Florida and Achumani, contain a
welter of climatic, ethnic, economic and social
contrasts.
M Interdependence
The whites were long haunted by the fear that
they would be encircled by the indigenous
people, as they were by Tupaq Katari in 1781.
However, the conquest (or reconquest) of the
city by the Indians has taken other, more
peaceful and irreversible forms. Between the
sixteenth century and the beginning of the
twentieth, whites and mestizos made constant
inroads on the territory of the indigenous
population. Deprived of their land and no
longer able to farm or raise animals, the Indi¬
ans began to specialize in crafts and trade and
came to constitute a partly urbanized group
known as cholos, "town Indians" or mesti¬
zos (see box page 31).
After the revolution of 1952, agrarian
reform, universal suffrage, education for all
and other measures were introduced, trans¬
forming Bolivia's social and economic struc¬
tures and encouraging a far-reaching process
of national integration. An internal market
grew, the rural world turned increasingly
towards towns and cities like La Paz,
Cochabamba and Santa Cruz, and new poles of
development emerged in the eastern lowlands.
Attracted by better-paid jobs with higher
status to leave their small plots of infertile land,
Indian immigrants and Aymara peasants set¬
tled in the hills around La Paz and on the
plateau, where the gigantic settlement of El
Alto grew up. The city's population, 321,000 in
1950, had almost quadrupled by 1992, with
nearly one third living in El Alto, where infra¬
structure and services are often dismally lacking.
Today, the two cities arc closely interde¬
pendent. The "white" and mestizo city cannot
exist without the labour of immigrants who
work in the lower echelons of the urban econ¬
omy (in the clothing, transport and con¬
struction industries, in small businesses, and
as domestic servants) but have rarely cut them¬
selves off from their home villages.
I The birth of the "Indian"
When the Spaniards arrived in this part of the
Andes it was inhabited by a number of
Aymara groups such as the Pacajes, the Lupacas
and the Collas. These traditional ethnic and
territorial units were dismantled by the colo¬
nizers and the generic term "Indian" was used
to designate all indigenous people. This view
of the Indians as a uniform mass still prevails
today, even though each region and rural com¬
munity has a specific identity that can be rec¬
ognized by its styles of clothing and music,
and by the spoken dialect. The term "Indian"
is rejected by most of the indigenous peoples,
who regard it as an insult and associate it with
exploitation and discrimination, but at the
M passer-by is dwarfed
by a wall painting in El Alto,
the Indian district.
THE UNESCO i3)URIERB MARCH I 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
same time it is accepted by Indian rights move¬
ments which in the last twenty years or so
have been trying to end discrimination against
all the Indians.
Whatever the rights and wrongs of this
debate, it is indisputable that the immigrants
brought cultural models that have given La
Paz its special flavour. La Paz differs from
other Latin American capitals, which are sur¬
rounded by poverty belts, in that its needy
districts display many features of the rural
communities from which their inhabitants
have come. For economic and cultural reasons,
newcomers first build adobe (sun-dried brick)
houses with corrugated iron roofs like those
in the villages they have left behind, consist¬
ing of a kitchen and a huge common living
room for all the family. Later they add new
rooms built of industrially manufactured
bricks which are often left ungarnished by
plaster or whitewash, partly because of the
30 r
W THE UNESCO L^OURIERB MARCH 1997
ancers shaking rattles
celebrate the Christian feast
of the Assumption.
cost but also because new migrants regard these
bricks as a status symbol.
External signs and codes physical appear¬
ance, clothing, food and language are
imposed, maintained and even sought-after.
They reveal the extreme ethnic diversity of
these Indian groups, and also highlight the
contrast between them and the economic and
political elites who favour a "Western" lifestyle.
La Paz has always been shaped by a two-
track process of integration and discrimination.
Although the existence of racism is denied it
can be seen in the day-to-day relations between .
people from different social strata. Immigrants
of peasant origin do the dirtiest jobs, earn the
lowest wages, are excluded from the social secu¬
rity system and have only limited access to
schooling and health care.
I Festive union
The different classes of society mingle during
the fiestas that punctuate the year. In the pre¬
dominantly indigenous neighbourhoods, as in
the villages, patron saints are the object of
colourful celebrations organized and financed
by volunteers who want to show their devo¬
tion and also acquire prestige corresponding to
the money they spend on food and drink for
the participants, dancers' costumes, bands,
and so on.
In recent decades, several events of Andean
and rural origin have spread to other sections
n street scene
in the city centre.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
of the population. The alasitas fiesta dedicated
to Ekeko, an ancient divinity of plenty, is
now celebrated throughout the city each year
on 24 January. On that day, at midday, every¬
body in the city stampedes to buy miniature
models of houses, cars, banknotes and other
good luck charms.
The fiesta of Señor del Gran Poder, which
takes place inJune, was once celebrated only by
the people who live in the parish of that name.
In the last twenty-odd years it has been an occa¬
sion when dozens of costumed groups dance to
rhythms from mestizo, indigenous and chola
cultures as they parade through the city's main
avenues. Recently, people from classes which
would once have looked down on such events
as vulgar and "Indian" have joined in.
Another common practice is to organize a
ch'alla good-luck ceremony at house-warm¬
ing parties, political meetings and all kinds of
other occasions. During the ceremony Andean
divinities (Pacha Mama or achachilas, the
sacred mountains) are invoked and presented
with offerings bought in the "Street of
Witches". Sometimes indigenous shamans are
called on to use their expertise as negotiators
with the Aymara divinities.
ruit sellers in an Indian
market.
HALF-WAY HOUSE
In La Paz the term cholo describes people who are socially and
ethnically in a halfway house. Forthose who regard themselves
as "whites", a choloU the son of an Indian who no longer dresses
in a traditional way like his father and has received a more
highly rated education. For others, a cholo is the mestizo son of
a marriage between a white and an Indian, or else the son of a
cholo. To be considered as such, two conditions must be met. A
cholo must have migrated to the city and have a job whose sta¬
tus is sufficiently high for him no longer to be defined as an
"Indian". For exa mple, a mason or a plumber who has migrated
from the countryside will be treated as an Indian, but an incomer
whohasajob with higher status (e.g. as a driver or butcher), will
be regarded as a cholo.
In white people's minds, the intermediate status occu¬
pied by the cholos in La Paz society seems bound up with a set
of qualities and defects (rebelliousness, submission, neurosis).
A passport from cholo status to that of a "señor" is possession
of a certain amount of wealth and an educationpreferably
gained abroad. For many "whites", however, those who have
"made it" in this way, i.e. become "señores", remain half-rio-
fos. "He acts like a cholo," is an insulting way of saving that a
person has no manners and reprehensible habits.
In La Paz, there are no very marked differences in men's
dress, which is mainly determined by economic factors, but
women's dress s quite a different matter. In everyday language,
a distinction is made between "a dressed-up woman ", who
wears Western-style clothes, and a chola who wears the pollera
(a capacious dress with a pleat in the middle) .
Cholas who control the sale of food in the markets are a
feared and respected group. They react with firmness and pride
when the term chola is applied to them pejoratively by those who
do not belong to their social and cultural world. L. P.
Events of this kind show how practices
and beliefs that not so long ago were generally
inaccessible or despised are spreading and that
the different classes and cultures of La Paz are
intermingling. It is still too early to say
whether these borrowings merely indicate that
the "haves" are taking over the cultural forms
of a tamed and neutralized class of "have-
nots", or whether they mark the start of a
process that will eventually lead to genuine
recognition of these cultures.
r *"
- - --MiJa Li» '
Left, a house in the Calacoto
residential district.
Par left, a shanty town on the
heights of La Paz.
THE UNESCO I^URIERB MARCH 1997 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
VANCOUVER
or the spirit ofplace
BY HADANI DITMARS
M mask by Bob Dempsey
inspired by Native American
tradition. It depicts a human
face with a raven and a frog.
Vancouver, pretty little Pacific town
of my youth. Cedar trees and blue
water. Snow-capped mountains and
Indian legends. I returned to you
after years away and found a city transformed.
Whole neighbourhoods had changed lan¬
guages from English to Chinese, Punjabi
and Spanish. Street signs spoke Cantonese and
all the taxi drivers were refugees. Vancouver
had made that grand voyage from small town
to big city, and even more dramatically, it had
leapt into the realm of displacement. It had
become a town full of people who were fro m
somewhere else.
Canada is known for its multiculturalism,
but Vancouver, which is separated from the
rest of the country by the Rocky Mountains
and spiritually connected to Asia by the Pacific
Ocean, is unique even within the Canadian
experience.
Only one hundred years old, Vancouver
was built on the bones of ancient native cul¬
tures by mainly British Europeans and inden¬
tured Chinese and Japanese labour.
Native Indian children were routinely taken
from their parents and put into "residential
schools" where their culture, language and tra¬
ditions were replaced by white English, Chris¬
tian values.
Since the introduction of Canadian Prime
Minister Pierre Elliott Trudeau 's policy of mul-
M bentwood box with a mask
inside by Ken Mowatt, a
contemporary Canadian
artist.
OéC THE UNESCO lOURIERl MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
ticulturalism, Canadians have been encouraged
to forget the past and embrace each others' dif¬
ferences. But the road to harmonious cultural
pluralism has not been easy. Japanese Canadian
groups have sought and in many places gained
acknowledgement for their unjust internment
during the Second World War as enemy aliens,
but compensation for the full extent of their
emotional and financial suffering has not been
forthcoming.
Native groups have been engaged in a series
of on-going and controversial land claims, and
English-Canadians have had to adjust to the
cultural changes brought by the influx of
Hong Kong immigrants.
But Vancouver's unique position in the
Canadian cultural context, its dramatic geog¬
raphy and indeed its very newness, create a
special atmosphere, where cultural métissage is
not only possible but inevitable. For in a city
less than a century old, tradition is something
that must be created rather than referred to.
I The beauty ofemptiness
As a student, I always complained that Van¬
couver lacked culture and dreamed of escape to
Paris or Rome older cities with richer tra¬
ditions. Now, coming back to the city of my
birth after years in many "older" places, I real¬
ize that the very newness of Vancouver is its
richness. Its emptiness is its beauty. Without
the cultural baggage both good and bad
of more established cities, Vancouver becomes
I he inner port of Vancouver,
Canada's third largest city.
a place where anything is possible, a place where
the new cultures arriving here can easily take
root.
Vancouver is not a "melting pot" like the
American multicultural model, where inte¬
gration usually means assimilation. It is a place
where cultures can continue to flourish and
grow, often keeping their language and tradi¬
tions, transplanting them into new soil. The
end result is a kind of cross pollination where
cultures rub against each other in new and cre¬
ative ways.
Evidence of this is found in Vancouver's
many ethnically distinct neighbourhoods,
districts that have their own colour and
flavour, but manage to transcend "ghettoiza-
tion" through cross-cultural connection.
s There is Vancouver's "Chinatown", for
5 instance one of the largest in North Amer-
| ica where the street signs are bilingual (Chi-
| nese/English). Although most residents are ori-
| ental, there is a growing link with the non-Asian
| community, just as Chinese speaking Vancou-
I vérités are making inroads into traditionally
n totem pole
in Stanley Park.
THE UNESCO lOURrERB MARCH 1997 ¿3
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Anglo-Canadian enclaves (especially in the busi¬
ness sector). A small but significant Anglo-
Canadian community of artists, inspired by
the sounds and colours of the lively market¬
place, chooses to live and work there. In addi¬
tion, in a city whose culinary palate is becom¬
ing more and more Asian (most Vancouverites
feel comfortable using chopsticks, and have dim
sum and sushi'm their nutritional vernacular), an
increasing number of non-Chinese Vancou¬
verites go to Chinatown to shop for food.
And as alternative medicine currently
enjoys great popularity in Vancouver, many
non-Asians go to Chinatown to consult Chi¬
nese herbal doctors or acupuncturists. Some
non-Chinese Vancouverites are even adopting
Chinese geomancy orfeng shui the ancient
Taoist art of designing houses and interiors
so that energy and harmony emanate and "bad
spirits" are not "trapped" in "blocked" or
poorly designed spaces, and come to China¬
town to consult withfeng shui masters.
Others come to Chinatown to sit and con¬
template in the Sun-Yat-Sen classical Chinese IVI usicians of different ethnic
origins form the Vancouver-
based "Asza" group.
gardens, where blue herons perch near bamboo
plants and pools of goldfish. (The only other
public garden in Vancouver that matches this
one in serenity is perhaps the Nitobe memo¬
rial Japanese Garden, which stays true to the
Shinto spirit thousands of miles from Kyoto,
while springing effortlessly out of West Coast
forest that is eerily Japanese).
The gateway to Asia
While Vancouver is becoming known as the
"gateway to Asia" and 25 per cent of our pop¬
ulation are Chinese speaking, this is only part
of the cross-cultural picture.
The Commercial Drive area, on the East
side of the city, is another example of an inte¬
grated ethnic neighbourhood. Originally a
very Italian area, Commercial Drive has now
become the great boulevard of multicultural
café society. Bohemian Anglo-Canadians, new
Portuguese and South American immigrants
as well as the original Italian community, all sit
together at the numerous terrazzo cafes, sip¬
ping caffe latte. Commercial Drive has become
the place for displaced Mediterraneans of all
nationalities, as local clubs feature nights of
Spanish flamenco music and Portuguese/ac/o
attended enthusiastically by both southern
Europeans and WASPs with gypsy hearts.
A stroll through the area around 49th and
Main Street, popularly known as Indiatown,
is a fantastic voyage in itself. It's like finding a
Delhi market magically transported to the
West Coast. I remember shopping there one
day in the midst of a small blizzard, with two
feet of snow piled up on the sidewalks. The
full fury of a Canadian winter could not stop
the sari merchants from selling silk, or keep the
sweetshop owner from his brisk trade in
coconut délectables. The streets were full of
women in colourful scarves and pantaloons
wearing snowboots, and young, turbanned
men dressed in the latest urban chic leather
jackets and mobile phones off to the CD
shop to buy the latest hhangra (Indian pop
music) tunes. After a few blocks, the faces
became paler, the music duller, the aromas less
intense, and I looked back at Indiatown like a
small urban jewel, glittering in the distance.
Similarly transporting is a walk down West
Broadway in the "Greek area". Within a five-
block radius, there are scores of Greek restau¬
rants, cafes and night-clubs. A special base¬
ment taverna known simply as "The Greek
Club" offers after hours bouzouki music,
great ouzo and wild folk dancing, as well as
heart-felt ballads of lost love belted out by a
beautiful, dark-eyed singer. It's enough to
make you homesick for Athens, until, bleary-
eyed from the late night and the Greek ciga-
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
to raise funds for refugee relief a simple,
compassionate gesture that might not have
been possible in another cultural and geo¬
graphical context.
Spiritually, too, Vancouver offers a wealth
of cross-cultural experience. It is a city where
you can find Christians who go on native
"visionqucsts", Jews who have become whirling
dervishes, and Scandinavian Lutherans who
have transformed into Tibetan Buddhists.
I know of an Iranian Sufi teacher who leads
weekly discussions of Persian esoteric poetry
I from his East Vancouver apartment. He reads
| and analyses excerpts from Saadi, Hafez and
I Rumi for a group of faithful students from all
Î corners of the globe. Among them are Jews,
| Muslims and Christians, Asians and Anglo-
I Canadians all Vancouverites. The sense of
-
mmJBt'l II 18-
lop, an Italian restaurant on
Water Street.
Mbove, left to right: Fruit and
vegetable stalls in Vancouver's
Chinatown. A street near the
waterfront. Street scene in the
city centre.
rette smoke, you emerge from below only to
find some unmistakable sign of North Amer¬
ica a McDonalds restaurant or a Seven-Eleven
chain-store.
And while Vancouver's colonial history is
not unblemished, different cultures do co¬
exist here in relative peace and harmony. Indeed,
more and more immigrants are attracted to
Vancouver precisely because it is, relatively
speaking, a sanctuary.
Not long ago, a group of gypsies arrived
here from central Europe, fleeing the recent
increase in violence and persecution from skin¬
heads and neo-nazis. They were helped by a
group of local gypsies and other supporters to
find housing and winter clothes. Some of the
gypsies who were musicians were able to find
work at a café where a multicultural group (an
Indian guitarist, a Rom gypsy dancer from
England, and a French Basque singer) perform
flamenco music every week. To them, Van¬
couver is paradise. It is a place where they can
have a chance to live normal, healthy lives, rel¬
atively free from racism.
During the violent shelling in South
Lebanon in the spring of 1996, a local group
of humanitarian Jews and Arabs joined forces
displacement somehow complements the Sufi
message that we are all spiritual exiles in the
material world, as well as the idea that unity is
achieved through transcending opposites.
I also know a Cree healer who runs weekly
native "healing circles" where people from all
kinds of backgrounds participate. When I first
attended one such "circle", where participants
sing, chant and drum native prayers while
passing an eagle feather around, I found a truly
international group. Among them were a Pol¬
ish secretary, an African teacher, a Swiss natu¬
ralist and a French artist. The Cree Shaman
told us that we were all connected by a com¬
mon experience of the spirit of the land.
It was a spiritual homecoming for me to
realize that, although my ancestors came fro m
many different lands from Lebanon, from
Denmark, France, England and Ireland they
and I were bonded by, as D. H. Lawrence put
it, the spirit of place.
Vancouver's green forests, blue waters and
majestic mountains are a common heritage for
us all to share. As the American Indians say, no
one "owns" the land because it "belongs" to
everyone. As long as everyone in turn belongs
a little to the land.
r 35
THE UNESCO ÍOURIER MARCH 1997 ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
THE SPIRIT OF DIVERSITY
^ ^^^^% rossroads cities" took shape
M down the ages as a result of
^L » population movements and
^^taiB^ voluntary or enforced migra¬
tions that brought together a wide spectrum
of cultures and ethnic groups. Located in the
heart of economically strategic regions, these
composite cities have drawn sustenance fro m
multifarious contributions made by those
who have settled in them. Their societies pos¬
sess a creative dynamism which is the main¬
spring of their constantly renewed diversity.
But successful handling of the difficulties
inherent in these plural societies with their
multitude of ethnic groups, languages and
religions means facing up to the problems
of adversity, exclusion, ghettoization and rejec¬
tion. Crossroads cities harbour striking con¬
trasts and fierce conflicts sometimes erupt
within them.
Religious, national and ethnic minorities,
of varying numbers and degrees of influence,
provide the pluralistic flavour of crossroads
cities. The place they occupy in the city is often
reflected in its spatial organization. To live in
one of the ghetto areas into which minorities
are shunted is generally a sign of discrimina¬
is THE UNESCO f^UR'^' M\RCH 1997
BY ANISSA
BARRAK
lop, a street festival
on Ninth Avenue in Manhattan
(New York). The stalls offer
ethnic gastronomic
specialities.
tion, of legal inequality or social and economic
marginalization. When minorities are more
evenly spread throughout a city it is often the
sign of a more tolerant and egalitarian regime.
Cities and towns that have managed to
develop and prosper in a spirit of cultural and
human diversity have done so by officially
protecting minorities. This kind of protec¬
tion is the guarantee of peaceful cohabitation,
even if cohabitation is not always synony¬
mous with fair and equal treatment, still less
with cordial relations between the different
communities. In one city ethnic and cultural
intermixture succeeds because it is an accepted
practice; in another, communities arc sepa¬
rated; elsewhere, fidelity to specific traditions
goes hand in hand with allegiance to a nation.
Some regard ethnic and cultural intermin¬
gling as a source of cultural impoverishment
through a fusion that leads to uniformity and
levelling down; others see it is a source of
mutual enrichment, the fruit of mutual
exchange. But this dilemma reveals the paradox
that is at the heart of all crossroads cities: is the
pursuit of cultural intermixture as an ideal in
plural cities anathema to their very pluralism?
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
FACT FILE
RAMPANT
URBANIZATION
The world's population is becoming more and
more urban. In 1950 only 30% of humanity
lived in towns and cities, and 45% in 1995. By
the year 2000, every second human being is
expected to live in an urban area. Most of this
growth will take place in small and medium-
sized towns and cities. The world's mega-cities
of more than 10 million inhabitants currently
hold only 4% of the world's people.
Source: United Nations, 1996
UNESCO
AND CITIES
Unesco has established an action-oriented pro¬
ject entitled "Cities: management of social and
environmental transformations" for the six-
year period 1996-2001. The first four years will
be spent designing and implementing a small
number of pilot activities. During the final two
years (2000-2001), a comparative evaluation
of these experiments will be carried out, and
proposals will be designed to improve policies
for cities, mainly in respect of support for local
communities.
This project, which will be carried out as
part of Unesco's MOST (Management of Social
Transformations) and MAB (Man and the Bios
phere) Programmes, will be implemented in
partnership with local authorities, non-gov¬
ernmental organizations and local voluntary
associations. Co-operation with international
organizations and scientific communities is
actively sought.
MOST AND THE
SOCIAL
SUSTAINABILITY OF
CITIES
Successful city management policies must be
conducive to "social sustamability"this is the
central premise of a MOST project entitled
"towards socially sustainable cities: building
a knowledge base for urban management".
By policy-relevant research, the MOST pro¬
gramme seeks to foster an environment con¬
ducive to the participation of culturally and
socially diverse groups while at the same time
promoting social integration through improve¬
ments in the quality of life of all segments of the
population.
Its international research projects cover a
broad spectrum, including industrialization and
decentralization in medium-sized towns in
India, the socio-economic problems of mega-
cities, and cities, environment and social rela¬
tions between men and women.
UNESCO, MOST Secretariat
1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 37 99
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 57 24
Internet home page: www.unesco.org/most
For the theme "Cities as places for social
transformation":
e-mail: g.so linis@unesco.org
METROPOLIS
"Metropolis" is an international research pro¬
ject that seeks to stimulate multidisciplinar
research on the effects of international migra¬
tion on urban centres.
The project has two overriding objectives:
*- to provide policy makers at all levels of gov¬
ernment, as well as community and business
leaders, with solid information on which to
anchor their policies;
* to develop an inventory of "best interna¬
tional practices", i.e. the most effective
approaches adopted in all countries that have
significant numbers of foreign-born persons in
their large urban centres.
Metropolis is a loose partnership involv¬
ing governments, research institutes and inter¬
national agencies. Its members include
Canada, the United States, Argentina, New
Zealand, Israel, Italy, the United Kingdom,
France, Germany, the Netherlands, Sweden,
Norway, Denmark, Switzerland, Austria, the
Organization for Economic Co-operation and
Development (OECD), Unesco and the European
Union.
The project features a series of major
annual international conferences hosted by
"partner countries". The first was organized
in 1996 by Italy. The next will be held in Copen¬
hagen (Denmark) from 25 to 28 September
1997.
For further information, contact:
Department of Citizenship and Immigration
Canada-Metropolis Project.
Tel: (1) (613) 957 59 70;
Fax: (1) (613) 957 59 68.
REGIONAL TRENDS IN URBANIZATION 1970-2025
%
100
Percent of Population Residing in Urban Areas % Average Annual Urban Growth Rates
6
Africa Europe
America America
1970 1995 2025
Source' United Nations Population Division, 1995
1970-1975 1995-2000 2020-2025
HEUNtSCO ^lURIERB MARCH I 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY Federico Mayor
cience and society (1)
>>
Scientists, politicians and
scientific research
The Second World War marked a turning point in the rela¬
tions between science and government. It was then, for
example, that the first science adviser to the White House
was recruited. This kind of assignment was something quite
new to those who had hitherto earned their living mainly by
research or the teaching of science.
While scientific research and government were becom¬
ing indispensable to each other, traditional policy-making
procedures were becoming obsolete.
A dangerous shift
Science has come to impinge more and more on society, to
some extent vindicating faith in the scientific enterprise,
but giving rise to doubts about human capacity for the wise
management of its applications. Increasingly science has
had to respond to many different and not always convergent
interests in society and enter into a relationship with many
different groups, including industry, government depart¬
ments, the academic community and tax-payers. The tradi¬
tional boundary between scientific practice and science
policy has become blurred. The issues, though still scien¬
tific in nature, are also economic, political, social and cul¬
tural. It is increasingly apparent that the traditional model
of science-and-technology decision-making, in which experts
in their various fields offer advice in confidence to decision-
THE UNESCO QïURIERB MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
makers whose interests and reflexes are often more political
than scientific, will no longer serve.
Where a ministry or an equivalent body lays down pol¬
icy guidelines for scientific research, it is often not suffi¬
ciently separate from day-to-day politics to maintain the
long-term perspective required in this sphere. Further¬
more, responsibility for science and technology policy is
often sectorally divided, which is not conducive to the
development of an integrated policy or the promotion of
research in frontier areas cutting across traditional fields.
There is also an unfortunate tendency for the interests of
science to be sacrificed to expediency for example, to
short-term economic considerations or the government's
need to achieve immediate results in order to stay in power.
Decisions and disagreements
Matters are not helped by the fact that science invariably
speaks with many voices. Despite their commitment to objec¬
tivity, technical advisers rarely agree once they stray out¬
side the realm of hard science. "When issues related to sci¬
ence and technology having strong political content . . .
come to the fore," Frederick Seitz, a past president of the
American National Academy of Sciences, has said, "it is
always relatively easy to find individuals with good pro¬
fessional qualifications to argue, even vehemently, in sup¬
port of either side." This accords undue power to decision¬
makers who then make choices based on their interests
and/or biases, using so-called scientific evidence in sup¬
port of what is in effect a foregone conclusion.
The lack of agreement among scientists reflects the com¬
plexity of the issues, which invariably involve a complex
combination of fields and require a holistic approach for
their solution. Scientists by themselves cannot be expected
to provide a complete answer to such questions. It is impor¬
tant that the spectrum of expert advice should be extended
to ensure inputs from all relevant fields.
Afresh approach
What is required is to move away from what has been termed
"decisionist action" whereby government decrees policy
based almost exclusively on expertise provided by the sci
entific and technological community to an approach
whereby the government takes into consideration the views
of the different protagonists with their diverse values and
standpoints. An effort should also be made to raise the gen¬
eral level of scientific and technological culture to opti¬
mize societal participation and support.
But this would require some fundamental changes of
attitude on the part of scientists and politicians alike. Sci¬
entists would have to develop a greater sensitivity to the
social and political impact of the advice they proffer. Politi¬
cians, for their part, would have to cede some of their deci¬
sion-making power to the experts, while learning to accept
the inevitable quota of uncertainty and instability in the
advice received.
The role of expert advice must, therefore, be redefined
in such a way as to emphasize the importance of scientifi¬
cally based decision-making while excluding any idealized
vision of enlightenment through scientific rationality. The
goal should be to arrive, through the marshalling and con¬
frontation of advice in all relevant fields, at the choices best
adapted to each situation. The diagnosis on which policy is
based should be as complete as possible, but it must also be
made in time. If we wait too long, "the patient may die", or irre¬
versible damage may be caused. Irreversibility is a key cri¬
terion. Postponement could lead to a point of no return.
Thought also needs to be given to the increasing
unwieldiness of scientific and technological institutions
with their multitude of decision-making centres. They should
be trimmed down to manageable proportions so that respon¬
sibilities can be more readily pinpointed and the risks of
duplication lessened. That being said, the hubris of over-
planning must be avoided. Scientific creativity cannot be
regulated. Policy decisions in certain areas of fundamental
research must remain with the scientists concerned such
autonomy being the very condition of those qualitative
advances in understanding that are ultimately as crucial to
the applied as they are to the basic sciences. In the words
of Bernardo Houssay, "there are no applied sciences if
there is no science to apply".
THE UNESCO ^_OURIERB MARCH 1097 ^b
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
H E RITAG E
Notre-Dame d' miens
by Cécile Romane
The cathedral of Amiens in France is a masterpiece
of Gothic architecture celebrated for the stone
carvings on its Western portals. It was placed on
the World Heritage List in 1981.
In foreground, a
sculpture by an
anonymous 16th-
century artist depicts
Salome holding the
head of John the
Baptist.
Notre-Dame d'Amiens, the
largest cathedral in France
and a masterpiece of the Rayon¬
nant style of Gothic architecture,
is twice the size of Notre-Dame
in Paris. Yet it does not give any
impression of being overpowering
or disproportionately huge. On
the contrary, harmony, elegance
and rhythm are the words
brought to mind by the thrust of
the pillars, the daring of the high
windows and the proportions of
the rib vaults. Inside, the visitor is
struck by the airiness, and looking
upwards is charmed by the alter¬
nating vivid pinks and greens
which cover the expanses of the
vaults. Even though other French
cathedrals elicit widespread
admiration (Chartres or Rheims,
for example), many people regard
Notre-Dame d'Amiens as the
Gothic cathedral par excellence.
A PASSION FOR BUILDING
The first Gothic church ofAmiens,
consecrated in 1152, burned down
in 121ÎÏ. Another church had to
be built. Like most of their con¬
temporaries, the people of Amiens
wanted to improve on what had
already been done and they had
the resources to do so. Thanks to
its weavers, its spinners and its
dyers, who used plants to produce
the highly popular Amiens "blue",
the city was prosperous. The chap-
THE UNESCO COURIER B MA-<CH 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
The Face of Saint John the Baptist,
a relic from the cathedral treasury.
teds, Thomas de Cormont and his
son Renaud, succeeded Robert de
Liizarches. The success of the
cathedral was due as much to
Robert's plans and methods as to
the innovations introduced by his
two successors. Amiens was the
first cathedral to be built to small-
scale plans and also the first where
the stone-cutting work was ratio¬
nalized. Shelters were built in the
quarry so that work could continue
during bad weather, and the pre¬
fabricated elements the masons
produced wen; then stored, ready
for use when the weather improved.
Work on a church usually
starts witli the choir, the centre of
worship. However, since the area
where the choir was to be located
was occupied, work at Amiens
started with the nave and the high
windows were placed on a blind
triforium, the normal practice at
that time. However, after the
death of Robert de Liizarches in
about 1223, when the choir and
the apse were being added, the
ter was also growing rich from the
influx of pilgrims. Bishop Evrard
de Fouilloy lost no time in asking
the architect Robert de Liizarches
to build a cathedral in the Gothic
style, which had begun to be used
in the previous century and was
then flourishing construction
work was already underway on the
cathedrals of Chartres, Bourges
and Paris.
The passion for building in the
Middle Ages which some people
at the time described as morbus
aedificandi (the building sick¬
ness) covered France with mon¬
uments of which half, some 1,300
buildings, still exist today. Amiens
cathedral (1220-1280) was built
during this productive period
when an aspiration towards splen¬
dour and novelty fostered techni¬
cal prowess.
In due course, two other archi-
The west façade of
Amiens Cathedral
(13th century). The
two towers were
completed in the 14th
and 15th centuries.
The cathedral was
extensively restored
in the 19th century by
the French architect
Viollet-le-Duc.
Detail of the carved
wooden choir stalls
(early 16th century).
> C°uiTHE UNESCO tOURIERB MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
HERITAGE
techniques for building an open¬
work triforium were known. This
is why, at Amiens, light flows in
abundantly at the back, confer¬
ring on the cathedral a grace
which is felt by everyone who vis¬
its it, Christian and non-Christian
alike.
From the twelfth century
onwards, the Gothic conception
of architecture attached more
importance to emptiness than full¬
ness, and soared skywards in
search of beauty. This concern for
clarity and for unity of space dic¬
tated certain features which con¬
tribute to the originality of
Amiens.
LIVES OF THE SAINTS
On the West facade, the vast Beau
Dieu porch is flanked by the
smaller porches of the Mother of
God and St. Firmin. The profu¬
sion of sculptures recounting
sacred history has earned the
cathedral the description of "a
Bible in stone" The fifty-five main
statues are placed in a hierarchical
order with, in the centre, the
twelve Apostles surrounding Christ
giving his blessing, while the tym¬
panum shows details of the Last
Judgement. The right porch dis¬
plays the history of the Virgin
Mary, and the left the lives of St.
Firmin, who came from Pamplona
in the third century to preach in
Amiens, and of other local saints.
In the past, the porches were
used as shelters as well as
entrances and justice was dis¬
pensed there. Beneath each
statue, at head height, are two
lines of quatrefoils, a typical
French Gothic motif. The vices
and virtues are represented at the
feet of the Apostles. They are
read vertically with courage
standing higher than fear and
symmetrically. Each virtue refers
to its symmetrical counterpart on
the other side of the porch so
that love faces chastity. Charity is
represented by the gift of a cloak
to a naked beggar. This allegory
reminds us that it was at Amiens
that St. Martin divided his cloak
in two with a stroke of his sword
and gave half of it to a poor man.
&5n
One of the great west
portals, decorated
with 13th-century
sculptures including
the "Beau Dieu" and
the Last Judgement
(detail).
A masterpiece
from the cathedral's
treasury:
the casket of
St. Firmin, the first
bishop of Amiens
(13th century).
St. Firmin's portal shows the work
of the different seasons of the
year and the signs of the Zodiac.
Very high up, above the Gallery
of the Kings, which is found in all
Gothic cathedrals in France;, shines
a rose window whose fine stone and
glass tracery extends over a circle
with a diameter of almost 13
metres. This colossal circle is as big
as a circus ring with room for twelve
galloping horses. On either side rise
two towers of different heights, one
completed at the end of the four¬
teenth century, the other in the fif¬
teen th. When it was built, the inte¬
rior of Amiens cathedral was the
highest in the world, the central
vault rising to more than 42 metres ,
the equivalent of fifteen storeys.
But the cathedral's architec¬
ture is not its only interesting fea¬
ture. The 110 oak choir stalls,
carved with breathtaking virtuosity,
constitute the finest masterpiece
in wood to be found in France.
They were executed over a period
of fourteen years (1508-1522) by
three local artists. On the seats, the
arm rests and the pendentives,
thousands of small figures, all dif¬
ferent and dressed in the style of
the early sixteenth century, mime
biblical and secular scenes.
Round the choir and the
transept, four series ofpolychrome
stone high-reliefs show dozens óf
figures, as lifelike as portraits, act¬
ing out the Bible stories and the
life of St. Firmin in fifteenth- and
sixteenth-century costume.
In addition to a polychrome
wooden Madonna and Child dating
from the fifteenth century, the
cathedral Treasury contains the sil¬
ver casket of St. Firmin, a marvel of
thirteenth-century art from the
Meuse region, and the Face of St.
John the Baptist, brought back
from Constantinople around 1206.
This impressive relic, protected by
a large hollowed-out rock crystal, is
presented on a gold plate with an
enamelled cover adorned with a
striking face of St. John.
NON-STOP RESTORATION
Restoration work is always going
on in Notre-Dame d'Amiens. In
1880, John Ruskin, the English
art lover and critic, expressed the
view that the French could not
leave their cathedrals alone for
ten minutes!
4* THE UNESCO Q^URIER MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The nineteenth century saw a
succession of restoration projects,
the most extensive of which lasted
from 1849 to 1874 and was
directed by Viollet-le-Duc. The
current operation is similar in scale,
but the comparison stops there.
No architect nowadays would go
so far as to create, as he did, a
gallery on the façade or add his
own portrait even concealed
behind an altar. Current practices
respect everything, even the alter¬
ations made by Viollet-le-Duc. The
statues of the Kings of France dec¬
orating the façade are smiling,
whereas those dating from the
time of Viollet-le-Duc are more
austere and will remain that way.
Umcsco placed Amiens Cathe¬
dral on the World Heritage List
in 1981. France is financing the
restoration work. The most sig¬
nificant effort is currently focus¬
ing on the West façade, the aim
being to ensure that it will enter
the third millennium without
scaffolding. The rose window,
which was dismantled at the end
of 1996, will be back in place in
the spring of 1997. The sculp¬
tures are being cleaned by laser
(the first time this has been done
in France) and this has revealed
minute traces of the early paint¬
work under the dirt, and has given
some idea of the original vivid
hues of red, green, white and gold.
The galleries and pinnacles are
being cleaned up by a micro rub¬
bing technique (with a 29 micron-
calibre abrasive!). In order to pro¬
tect certain stones from being
blackened by the sulphur in the
urban atmosphere, some of them
have been coated with a mineral¬
izing agent and others with water
repellents. Those that are too
badly damaged are replaced by
good-quality new stones of similar
colour. None of Amiens' master¬
pieces, produced with such mar¬
vellous skill, have been lost. Unfor¬
tunately, however talented the
restorers and hovvev er much fund-
ing is provided, pollution works
very quickly. It is discouraging to J
note that the cathedral became ¡
dirtier in the last decade than dur- |
ing the previous half-century. H 5
The cathedral measures 133 metres |
in length and 42.30 metres from floor to %
vault. Right, the nave. %
) ÇouTHE UNESCO lOURIERB MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
The Tucurui
hydroelectric dam
on the Tocantins
River in Para state
(Brazil).
"When the garden is full of
fruit, it's time to bottle some
for the winter," says Jacques Lecornu,
managing director of the International
Commission on Large Dams (ICOLD).
"In the same way, dams retain water
reserves for use in the dry season."
Floods claim some 100,000 vic¬
tims per year, and according to
ICOLD's 1995 Position Paper on
Dams and Environment, flood con¬
trol "has always been a particularly
significant motive for dam construc¬
tion." Dams also "mitigate droughts,
adjust natural runoff with its sea¬
sonal variations and climatic irresu-
L Darge uams
by France Bequette
- -",*- -
larities to meet the pattern of
demand for irrigated agriculture,
power generation, domestic and
industrial supply and navigation.
They provide recreation, attract
tourism, promote aquaculture and
fisheries, and can enhance environ¬
mental conditions." Swiss engineer
Nicholas Schnitter, author ofA His¬
tory ofDams (1994), adds that they
also protect estuaries against the
ravages of flood tides.
This positive view is increasingly
being questioned, however, by envi¬
ronmentalists and scientists who
advance strong arguments in support
of their case. Concern was expressed
as early as 1973 at an ICOLD con¬
gress in Madrid in the following
terms: "The real problem to be
solved is the question whether dams
are useful or detrimental, whether
they improve our environment as a
whole and man's well-being or
whether they spoil it, and appreci¬
ating in each case whether they
should be built and according to
what characteristics".
Past and present
The first dam for which there is reli¬
able evidence was built in Jordan
5,000 years ago to supply the city of
Jawa with drinking water. Around
1800 B. C, during the reign of the
Pharaoh Amenemhet III, the Egyp¬
tians constructed a reservoir with
the amazing storage capacity of 275
million m'i in Al Fayyum Valley,
some 90 km southwest of Cairo.
Known as Lake Moeris (today Lake
Qarun), it was used for 3,600 years.
According to Jacques Lecornu,
more than half of ICOLD's nearly
40,000 registered large dams
(higher than 15 metres) have been
built in the last 35 years.
Dams can be divided into two
broad categories according to their
use: those designed to regulate river
flow in the interests of navigability,
and those which confine and check
the flow ofwater for a variety of other
needs. Each type has a specific
design. Most water storage dams
(83%) are embankment (earth fill)
dams, a less costly technique than
masonry. The materials used may he
rock (Egypt's Aswan High Dam), earth
(the Nurek dam in Tajikistan) or a
mixture. There are various types of
concrete or masonry dams: gravity-
dams consisting of a massive triangu¬
lar wall (the Grande-Dixence dam,
Switzerland), arch dams built in a
convex arch facing the reservoir (Zim¬
babwe's Kariba dam), and buttress
dams (e.g. the Alcantara II dam in
44
THE UNESCO lOURIER» MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Spain). More than 52% of the world's
dams are located in China, 16% in
the United States, and 6% in Japan.
Costly savings
Reservoir-dams are mainly used for
irrigation and drinking-water sup¬
ply. Although waterfalls have been
used for centuries to generate
energy, hydroelectric production has
increased over the past thirty years
and now meets about 20% of world
electricity demand (hut only 7% of
global energy demand). By econo¬
mizing on coal and oil, hydroelectric-
ity limits the air pollution caused by
fossil fuel combustion. Hydroelectric
power could be developed to great
advantage if only it were not so often
associated with dams that have dire
consequences on the environment,
especially in dry ecosystems.
The effects that dams can have
on the environment are described in
Freshwater Resources, a booklet
produced by UNESCO and the United
Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP). They include changes in
the ecosystem, loss of agricultural
land, the spread of water-related
diseases (especially bilharzia and
malaria), regulation of river flow,
change in water quality and sedi¬
ment regime, flood risks, changed
conditions for fisheries, agriculture,
transport and other economic activ¬
ities, population displacements, loss
of recreational areas and increases
in the area's seismic potential
because of the reservoir's weight.
There may also be effects on climate
as well as the disappearance of some¬
times rare plant- and wildlife that
originally lived in the flooded areas.
These social and environmental
impacts assumed considerable pro¬
portions in the 1970s, when it
became impossible to ignore the fate
of the populations that were
Above, the dam
at Marib, the
former capital of
the Saba kingdom
(Yemen). One of the
world's oldest, it
was operational
from the 5th
century B. C. to the
6th century A. D.
Above right, an
irrigation dam
near Jogjakarta in
Java (Indonesia).
The Glen Canyon
dam in Utah
(United States)
with Lake Powell
behind.
affected by dam construction and
in some cases summarily displaced
without compensation.
According to the World Bank,
the construction of 50 dams has
uprooted about 830,000 people,
only half of whom were resettled in
a satisfactory manner. The Kiambere
hydroelectric project in Kenya, for
example, has supplied 30% of
Kenya's energy needs since 1990,
resulting in fuel oil savings of $25
million. When dam construction
began it was estimated that 1,778
people would be affected, but even¬
tually 7,500 people were displaced
or dispossessed, receiving financial
compensation which many spent on
marriages or debt repayment, hut
which was too small for them to buy
land equivalent to their original hold¬
ings. Resettlement reduced them to
poverty. Lubuge hydroelectric plant
in China supplies 21% of the energy
demand of Yunnan province, yet the
2,320 people displaced were satis¬
factorily resettled under a plan that
offered them a choice between con¬
tinuing to farm on new land irrigated
under the project or being retrained
for new jobs. The project brought
resettled families access to drink¬
ing water, electricity and communi¬
cation facilities.
Side effects
The World Bank has adopted guide¬
lines for integrating social and envi¬
ronmental concerns into analysis of
dam construction projects and avoid¬
ing or mitigating adverse conse¬
quences. ICOLD is producing publi¬
cations and organizing symposia to
highlight lessons learned from the
past and to present technology for the
future. But we are still paying the
price today for structures built in the
past by engineers who did not fore¬
see all the consequences of their work.
Monique Mainguet, Professor of
Geography at the University of
Rheims (France), recently published
a book, L'homme et la sécheresse
(Man and Drought, 1995), in which
she assesses the impact of the Sélin-
gué dam, built in 1981 on one of the
major tributaries of the Niger,
upstream of Bamako (Mali). The dam
deprived farmers ofnatural seasonal
flooding that irrigated 100,000
hectares of land and made it possible
to grow rice, and the fishing indus¬
try collapsed three years later. She
reports that two other dams in west
Africa, the Diama dam on the Sene¬
gal River and the Manantali dam on
the Bafing River (a tributary of the
Senegal), are not living up to expec¬
tations. Diama is not preventing sea
water from moving 200 km upriver
in the dry season. The Manantali "is
responsible for the destruction of
10,000 hectares of woodland; it is
accelerating erosion and sanding up of
THE UNESCO Q>URIERB MARCH 1997 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
the valley and holding hack fertile
silt from the delta".
The Aswan High Dam in Egypt
is fulfilling its initial purpose (regu¬
lation of flooding and the produc¬
tion of hydroelectricity), but it too
has drawbacks. Its 500-kiIometre-
long artificial lake receives some 100
million tonnes of fertile silt that used
to be carried and deposited by the
Nile (luring its annual flood. "This
silt was once used to manufacture
bricks and natural fertilizers that
now have to be replaced by costly
artificial materials and chemical fer¬
tilizers." Without the protective
layer that the silt forms on sandy
soil, the land is eroded by the wind.
What's more, the reservoir loses
more than 10 billion m3 of water
annually to evaporation, and a lot of
water percolates down into the sub¬
soil, resulting in increased ground¬
water salination in a richly evaporite
soil. But the dam has enabled Egypt
to cope with the large-scale
droughts that have struck the Sahel
in recent decades.
Big but not beautiful
In 1918 Sun Yat-sen, father of the
Chinese Republic, had the idea of
building the Three Gorges dam on
the Yangtze Jiang River in Hubei
province in central China. Over 75
years later, the first stone of what
will eventually be the world's largest
dam was laid in 1994. Although it
promises to supply 10% of the coun¬
try's electricity and regulate river
levels for nearly 300 kilometres, the
dam is a controversial project. For
thousands of years poets and
painters have sung the rare beauty of
its chosen site. Its 175-metre-high
concrete wall will create a lake
between 500 and 650 kilometres
long that will drown a magnificent
landscape, completely or partially
The Atatùrk dam
on the Euphrates
(Turkey)
submerging a dozen towns. About
1.5 million people will have to be
resettled. There are also risks of
massive pollution and silting up due
to the reduction in water flow sed¬
iment and effluent carried by the
Blue River will accumulate in the
lake. According to some estimates,
the total cost of the project could
well reach $32 billion. UiMiSCO and
UNEP have asked whether Three
Gorges dam should he built.
The estimated cost of the Bakun
dam project in Sarawak (Malaysia)
is in the region of $6 billion. Located
in the mountains on the island of Bor¬
neo, it will submerge some 70 to
80,000 hectares of tropical forest
and uproot around 10,000 people.
Preliminary work has already begun,
despite vigorous protests from local
environmental organizations. But
Malaysia is a member of the Inter¬
national Commission on Large Dams,
and is sticking to the terms of the
Commission's Position Paper, which
states that "Attention to the social
and environmental aspects of dams
and reservoirs must be a dominating
concern pervading all our activities in
the same way as the concern for
safety. We aim to balance the need
for the development of water
resources with the conservation of
the environment in a way which will
not compromise future generations."
Despite their controversial
aspects and increasing reservations
in scientific and financial circles,
large-scale projects are still popular.
Since 1986 the World Bank has
approved 39 dam projects and lent
$7.4 billion (3% of total World Bank
lending in the past ten years) to build
them. Wouldn't it be better to chan¬
nel the enormous investments they
require into more numerous smaller
projects that would be more accept¬
able to local people and the environ¬
ment? According to Jacques Lecornu
between 1 ,200 and 1 ,400 such dams
are begun every year.
FURTHER READING:
/ The Impact of Large Water Projects on the
Environment, proceedings of an international
symposium held at Unesco in 1986,
Unesco-UNEP, 1990
/ Freshwater resources,
UNEP-Unesco, 1995.
/ L'homme et la sécheresse,
Monique Mainguet, Paris, 1995
/ ¡COLD Position Paper on Dams
and the Environment, 1995.
(ICOLD, 151, Bd. Haussmann, 75008 Paris, France.
Tel: (33) (0)1 40 42 68 24;
Fax: (33) (0)1 40 42 60 71
/ L'Egypte et le haut-barrage d'Assouan,
M. Bakre, J. Bethemont, Presses de l'Université
de Saint-Etienne, Saint-Etienne, France, 1980
i ni ti a ti ves
CREM, a leader in urbistíes
The town of Martigny in Switzerland (15,000 inhabitants) is just the right size to serve as a real-
life laboratory for the Centre for Energy and Municipal Research (CREM). CREM's guiding prin¬
ciple is urbistics, or computerized town management.
CREM seeks to reconcile concern for the environment with development in an urban context.
This means bringing together town planners, engineers, builders and transportation, water,
energy and telecommunications utilities, which do not always see eye to eye. In partnership with
the Lausanne Federal Polytechnic, CREM's small pluridisciplinary and highly motivated team
collects data on everything to do with towns and how they work. This information is used as a
basis for developing, testing and making available tools and methods for planning, managing and
maintaining municipal infrastructures. The goal is to limit investment, reduce effluent, mini¬
mize environmental damage and make good use of resources by implementing a range of com¬
puterized measures.
Using this approach, CREM has launched a programme to clean up the heating systems of
public buildings. It has also shown that the centralized supply of liquefied petroleum gas
(LPG) to towns cut off from existing natural gas networks reduces energy costs and environmental
impacts. In 1995 it completed development of its SyCREM® (version 4.0) personal computer
software for monitoring energy resource use. The software is being used by several companies
in the Martigny region.
CREM also organizes courses and seminars on which it publishes reports and a newsletter,
Fecfeitr. I
FOR FURTHER INFORMATION CONTACT:
CREM, Rue des Morasses 5, case postale 256, 1920 Martigny, Valais, Switzerland.
Tel: (41) 027 721 25 40; Fax: (41) 027 722 99 77; E-mail: crem@pingiiet.ch
46
THE UNESCO QîURII1ER MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
MONEY GROWS ON TREES
Farmers in the centre of Côte d'Ivoire have high hopes
that gum arabic trees may prow: to be a profitable crop. The
gum arabic or gum acacia is a small tree (from 4 to 6 metres)
that produces a resin that can fetch from $2,000 to §4,000
per ton. It is used as an ingredient in chemical products,
medicines and some kinds of tyre. The Inter-African Agency
for Development and the Environment, a non-go\ emmental
organization created by young people in Katiola province,
has already planted 60 hectares of the trees. Easy to grow
and already well entrenched in Mali, Niger, Nigeria and
Sudan, the gum acacia should help to improve the living
standards of Ivorian farmers.
SUMMIT MEETING
Colombia's Sierra Nevada de Santa
Malta mountain chain, which rises to a
height of 5,775 metres, contains the
world's highest coastal peak. It is also a
UNESCO lîiosphere Reserve covering over
17,000 km- and including the sources
of 36 rivers that supply 1.5 million peo¬
ple with water. By the early 1980s mar¬
ijuana cultivation had destroyed
100,000 hectares of forest and endan¬
gered a whole range of ecosystems,
indigenous farming and water supplies
for the plains below. In 1986 the Foun¬
dation for the Protection of the Sierra
Nevada de Santa Marta got down to
work on the problem and a conservation
strategy began to be implemented in
1992. The creation of an association of
Sierra Nevada towns has been one mile¬
stone in the development of co-opera¬
tion. Its existence is a remarkable
achievement in view of the spectrum of
groups that had to be brought
together guerrilla fighters, the army,
drug producers, big landowners, small
farmers, government officials and local
people and convinced that they share
a common interest in safeguarding the
environment. M
TURKEY HOSTS WORLD
FORESTRY CONGRESS
Forests cover about a quarter of
Turkey's land area (some 20.2 million
hectares). 98% of them are state-
owned and managed. There are 30
national parks, and several nature
parks and wildlife reserves have been
created since 1958. Moreover 9,000
of Europe's 11,000 plant species are
found in Turkey, a botanist's paradise.
All these are good reasons why Turkey
will be hosting the 11th World
Forestry Congress in the town of
Antalya from 13 to 22 October 1997.
The event will he sponsored by the
Ministry of Forests and the Food and
Agriculture Organization
United Nations (FAO).
of tin
WATER IN THE
MEDITERRANEAN REGION
"Water in the Mediterranean region, sit¬
uations, perspectives and strategies for
sustainable water resources manage¬
ment" is the theme of a useful bilingual
(English-French) document published
by the Regional Activity Centre of the
Blue Plan, an arm of the United Nations
Environment Programme's Mediter¬
ranean Action Plan. The document was
prepared on the occasion of the Euro-
Mediterranean Conference on local
water management held in Marseilles
(France) in November 1996. Address¬
ing the Conference, Michel Bâtisse,
President of the Blue Plan, called for
"improvement in management capaci¬
ties on the economic, social and envi¬
ronmental fronts, strengthening of the
relevant legal and financial institutions,
greater participation by users, espe¬
cially farmers, and more intensiv e train¬
ing in water-related fields."
For further information, contad: lïlue
Plan Regional Activity Centre (lil'/R \C),
Place Sophie-Laffillo, Sophia Anlipolis,
06560 Yaibonne, France. Tel: (33) (0) I
9.1 65 39 59; Fax.: (33) (0) I 93 65 35 28;
F-niail: planl>lcii@iw av.fr
TRADITION VERSUS EROSION
In mountainous and semi-arid Ethiopia some 1.5 billion
tons of soil are degraded each year by erosion. In an attempt
to solve the problem, scientists have turned to traditional
farming techniques used by the Konso people who live near
Lake Turkana (Lake Rudolf) in the south of the country.
The Konso manage to farm steep arid slopes by terracing
and alternating crops, digging small basins where they
deposit plant waste, controlling cattle grazing and prac¬
tising agroforestry. They even manufacture straw and
sorghum pipes to drain water run-off which would other¬
wise carry away the thin fertile layer of lopsoil. H
DEADLY HOOKS
Since high-seas drift nets have theoretically been banned
because of their destrurtiveness to marine life, another
deadly effective fishing method lias appeared: fishing lines
tip to 130 kilometres long that can carry as many as 3,000
hooks. Thousands of boats are equipped with them. The
long lines are more selective than the drift nets and present
less of a danger to marine mammals, but they are so effec¬
tive that some species which take a hook easily, like sword-
fish, are endangered. In view of the small size of the sword-
fish now found in American markets, some biologists claim
that we are "eating the babies". Among other innocent vic¬
tims of long lines are albatross, which take the bait and
then drown after being hooked. H
THE UNESCO ^>URIERB MARCH 1997 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
REFLECTIONS
THE WORLD IS A SANCTUARY
BY HENRYK SKOLIMOWSKI
The time has come to abandon the metaphor which
has for so long dominated our perception of the
world and to reject the damaging assumption that
the world is a clock-like mechanism within which we
are little cogs and wheels. It has led us to reduce
everything, including human life, to the status of
components of this great machine. The consequences
have been disastrous. Only when we find a new
metaphor and invent a new conception of the world
shall we be able to stand up to the senseless, destruc¬
tive forces that have swept over our lives.
According to one tenet of ecological thought
the world is a sanctuary and we should treat it as
such. This assumption is the basis of a completely
different outlook on the universe and our place
within it. If we live in a sanctuary, then we must
treat it with reverence and care. We must be the
earth's custodians and shepherds. The idea of stew¬
ardship naturally follows from the assumption that
the world is a sanctuary.
These are the basic components of what I call
the ecological metanoia: simultaneously changing
our metaphor of the world, our attitude to it, and
our thinking about it. This can and is being done.
Of course it is a large and difficult project, and
this is why it is progressing slowly, haltingly, some¬
times grudgingly. For psychological and historical
reasons, we are reluctant to change, but deep down,
we know that we must do so. This is not the end of
the story, however. Other important changes must
occur before we arrive at a sane, sustainable and ful¬
filling world.
This quest for meaning leads us on to the ques¬
tion of the purpose of human life and to those ulti¬
mate concerns upon which our humanity is based.
One characteristic of our times is the atrophy of
meaning. Both religious people and secularists are
aware that there is a desperate search for meaning
in modern society. We do not find a meaning in con¬
sumption, entertainment and ordinary jobs. We
look for a larger purpose and we do not find it. For
this larger purpose requires a transcendent dimen¬
sion to our life.
This is where eschatology comes in. Eschatology
is the sphere of human thinking which is concerned
with the ultimate ends of human life and thus with
the meaning of human life, and with the question
of what gives meaning to meaning. Eschatology has
traditionally been the discipline which envisages
transcendent goals as the purpose of our life. These
goals are often, hut not always, religious. Tran¬
scendent goals and purposes must not be mistaken
for a religious agenda or religious beliefs.
Why do we need a new eschatology? Why do
we need a new transcendent purpose to give mean¬
ing to human life? The answer is that secular escha
tology, promising fulfilment here on earth in mate¬
rialist and secular terms alone has failed dismally.
Instead of bringing happiness and fulfilment, it has
robbed us of the deeper dimensions of human life.
Some secular humanists are aware of this and have
attempted to devise a new scheme, whereby a new
transcendent purpose is grafted on to secularism.
They postulate a task of continual self-improve¬
ment in the pursuit of perfectibility and freedom.
But these are only words. If perfectibility and self-
improvement are to mean anything, they must be
rooted in a deeper sense of transcendence which
goes beyond secularism.
It is thus time to abandon our linear modes of
thinking and an exploitative attitude toward nature
in favour of an ecological perspective and a new
form of spirituality.
Let us very briefly state some of the main con¬
tentions of the new ecological world-view, which
are also components of the new eschatology. The
universe is on a meaningful journey of self-realiza¬
tion. We are a part of this journey. The universe is
not a haphazard heap of matter and we meaning-
lessly drifting particles in it. The new Astrophysics,
the New Physics and the Anthropic Principle all
converge to inform us that we live in an intelligent
universe, self-actualizing itself. There is a won¬
derful coherence in this process of continuous self-
transcendence. Nowadays this is well supported
by science. I am not saying it is "proved" by sci¬
ence, for science cannot prove such things. A lead¬
ing contemporary physicist, Freeman Dyson, has
said: "Looking at all the 'coincidences' which have
occurred in the evolution of the cosmos, we cannot
escape the conclusion that the cosmos behaves as
if it had known that we were coming". A leading
American physicist, John Archibald Wheeler, main¬
tains that when we look at the universe, it is the uni¬
verse itself which is looking at itself, through our
eyes and minds. For we live in a curiously partici¬
patory universe, and we are profoundly woven in
this stupendous participatory process.
We are the eyes through which the universe
looks at itself. We are the minds through which
the universe contemplates itself. We have an incur¬
able urge to transcend because the will of the uni¬
verse to continually self-transcend itself is built
into us. We are cosmic, beings. We share with the
entire universe the dimension of transcendence and
the urge to self-realization. This has been the basis
of all enduring forms of spirituality.
A wonderful journey lies ahead of us as we seek
to actualize the cosmic meaning which resides in us,
to help the universe and all its creatures in the
journey of self-actualization and in the process of
healing the earth and making it blossom again. I
48 THE UNESCO COURIER« MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
LISTENING ,,/x... ah
REDISCOVERING LILI BOULANGER
BY ISABELLE LEYMARIE
A brilliantly
precocious French
composer who dazzled
the world of European
music at the beginning
of the 20th century.
r'The works of Lili Boulanger,"
the composer and conductor Igor
l Markevitch has written, "impress
me with their solitude. They are indifferent
to fashion and seem oblivious ofwhat is writ¬
ten about them. I think that this is why
they endure, and it may even explain the
strange delay before their true worth was
recognized."
This long "delay" is seemingly not yet
over. Yet Lili Boulanger, who died at the
age of twenty-four, left us music that is both
expressive and luminous, moving and
enchanting. She revealed her genius and ful¬
filled her vocation with an urgency that was
sharpened by the imminence of death.
"Lili" (Juliette Marie Olga) Boulanger
was born in Paris on 21 August 1893 of a
Russian mother and a French father. The
family had a musical tradition going back
several generations. Lili's mother was an opera
singer and her father, a composer (especially
of comic opera) and teacher of voice at the
Paris Conservatory, had won the Grand Prix
de Rome for composition for his cantata
Achille. Her sister Nadia six years her
senior was one of the twentieth century's
most influential teachers of composition, and
trained many singers, instrumentalists and
composers, includingAaron Copland, Virgil
Thomson, Astor Piazzolla, Quincy Jones and
the trumpeter Donald Byrd.
Lili showed her exceptional musical gifts
at a very early age. When she was six she
sang songs by Fauré, who accompanied her
on the piano. Despite indifferent health,
she learned to play the organ and began
composing at twelve when she wrote Valse
en mi majeur (Waltz in E Major) and La let¬
tre de mort (The Letter of Death) in 1905.
She was attracted to sacred music, and
impressed her family and friends by her
contemplative nature, maturity and spiri¬
tuality. "It is a finished monument," wrote
French composer Henri Barraud of her
work, "firmly established in its fullness, its
sobre style and a classicism which owes noth¬
ing to schooling and everything to natural
balance, a blend of knowledge and ability.
There is no trace of weakness in her think¬
ing or inexperience in her composition, no
youthful squandering of resources or vital¬
ity, no blaze of ill-contained passion if pas¬
sion there be, it has lost all carnality and
become a radiant beam of light."
Nadia, who was herself an organist and
had been a pupil of Fauré, taught Lili har¬
mony and counterpoint. Lili also received
advice from Roger Ducasse, a family friend
and another of Fame's pupils. She studied
the piano with Raoul Pugno, a cultivated
neighbour of the Boulangers' at Hanneu-
court-Gargenville in the greater Paris region
where she composed prolifically. Under the
guidance of Georges Caussade, a teacher
of fugue and counterpoint at the Paris Con¬
servatory and a celebrated harmonist, she
soon became adept at composition. In 1911
and 1912 she composed choral music and
cantatas, including Hymne au soleil ("Hymn
to the Sun").
She entered the Conservatory the fol¬
lowing year and studied with Paul Vidal,
an old friend of Debussy and Liszt, and Mau¬
rice Emmanuel, an enthusiast for modal
music. She practised for the Prix de Rome
with the cantata Pour les funérailles d'un
soldat ("For the Burial of a Soldier") with
words from a play by Alfred de Musset. She
was particularly fond of Debussy, especially
Pelléas et Mélisande and Prélude à l'après-
midi d'un faune, which influenced several
of her works. But she was ahead of her time,
and gradually moved away from impres¬
sionism and found her own voice. In 1913, at
the age of nineteen, she became the first
woman to win the Grand Prix de Rome,
awarded for her cantata Faust et Hélène.
Her works now began to be published, and
Faust et Hélène was performed by the cel¬
ebrated Concerts Colonne in November of
the same year.
In 1914, despite declining health, she
made a trip to Italy that was a revelation to
her, composed in Rome, then returned to
Nice in the South of France where she
began her cycle for voice, Clairières dans le
ciel ("Clearings in the Sky") based on a poem
by Francis Jammes, instrumental pieces and
the Psalms. During the First World War,
Lili and Nadia founded a Franco-American
support committee to send letters and food
parcels to the fighting men. Despite rest,
and an operation in 1917, Lili's health con¬
tinued to decline; she faced adversity with
exemplary courage and serenity. In the last
two years of her life she completed the three
Psaumes ("Psalms") and Vieille prière boud¬
dhique ("Old Buddhist Prayer") for voice
and orchestra, Un matin de printemps ("A
Spring Morning"), for violin (or flute) and
piano, and her masterpiece, Pie Jesu (for
voice, organ, string quartet and harps),
which she was too weak to write herself and
dictated to Nadia from her bed. She died in
Mézy near Paris on 15 March 1918.
Lili always remained an example for
Nadia, who praised her sister's "moral and
spiritual superiority" and "purity".
Throughout her life Nadia steadfastly kept
her sister's memory alive by propagating
her work and infusing into her students the
sacred fire that had burned in Lili. I
THE UNESCO ^)URIERB MARCH 1997 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
AUTHORS LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN ¡s a Moroccan-born
novelist and poet who writes in French. Several
of his works have been published in English
translation, including The Sacred /V/^ht (1989),
which won the Goncourt Prize in 1987, Silent
Day in Tangers (1991) and The Sand Child
(1987). His latest novel, La nuit de l'erreur, has
just been published by Editions du Seuil, Paris.
JEROME CHARYN, of the United States,
teaches film history at the American University
of Paris. He has written many novels and several
works of non-fiction, including New York,
chronique d'une ville sauvage (Gallimard, Paris,
1993). His most recent published work in
English is El Bronx (Warner Books, 1997). His
novel The Dark Lady from Belorusse will be
published in the U.S. later this year by St.
Martin's Press.
LAJPAT RAI JAGGA, of India, is a professor of
History at Jawaharlal Nehru University in New
Delhi (India).
EMILE TEMIME is a French historian who has
spent many years studying international
migratory movements. He has co-authored
several works on Spain and published a 4-
volume study on Marseilles, Migrance, Histoire
des migrations à Marseille (Edisud, Aix-en-
Provence, 1989-91) and Marseille transit. Les
passagers de Belsunce (Autrement, Paris, 1995).
LUZ PACHECO, of Bolivia, is a social
anthropologist specializing in the rural world of
the Andes.
HADANI DITMARS, of Canada, is ajournalist
specializing in intercultural relations.
ANISSA BARRAK, a Tunisian journalist, is
cultural attaché with her country's delegation to
Unesco. She is managing editor of the magazine
Confluences Méditerranée and author of Villes
exemplaires, Villes déchirées (L'Harmattan, Pans,
1994).
CÉCILE ROMANE is a Franco-British writer
whose published work includes a novel, La
Népalaise, (Orban/Plon, Paris, 1987) and a
story, Les téméraires (Flammarion, Paris, 1993).
FRANCE BEQUETTE ¡s a Franco-American
journalist specializing in environmental
questions.
HENRYK SKOLIMOWSKI, of Poland, is
professor of ecological philosophy at the
Technical University of Lodz. He Is the author of
many books and articles.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-American
musicologist, has recently published Du tango
au reggae, Musiques noires d'Amérique latine et
des Caraïbes (From Tango to Reggae, Black Music
of Latin American and the Caribbean, Flammarion,
Pans, 1996) and Musiques caraïbes ("Caribbean
Music", Actes Sud, Arles, 1996).
A TARNISHED
HERO
In y our December 1996 issue ("Ephemeral Art")
you published a very interesting article by
laroslav Isaievych on Holidan Khmelnytsky, a
historical figure who is little known in many
countries despite the very important role lie
played in the history of the Ukraine.
But nothing was said about one aspect of his
career. In the history of the Jewish people
Khmelnytsky is known as the archetypal orga¬
nizer of pogroms, a wholesale murderer of Jews.
The English historian Paul Johnson's well doc¬
umented and objcrtiveA History of the Jews
(1987) which the author of your article unfor¬
tunately seems not to have read, shows that his
exploits were surpassed only by the person v\ ho
has been dubbed the "Khmelnytsky of the 20lh
century". The Nazis clearly possessed infinitely
greater resources to carry out their murderous
plans.
Objectivity in analysing notable historical
figures is also a way of teaching tolerance and
mutual respect.
Congratulations on your magazine's excel¬
lent quality,
G. Finkelstein
Jerusalem (Israel)
When the Ukrainian peasants and Cossacks
rebelled against the Poles and set up an inde¬
pendent Ukraine, Bohdan Khmelnytsky's troops
perpetrated acts of unspeakable savagery and
cruelty on the Jews.
Most of the massacres were committed
between May and November 1618. The Jewish
communities on the east bank of the Dnepr were
exterminated in ihe early days of the revolt.
During the summer, persecutions extended to
the river's west bank. liy mid-June no Jews were
left in the villages and towns of Volhynia (these
details are taken from the Encyclopedia
Judaica, \ol. 5, Jerusalem, pp. 4ÎÎ0--4 iïl).
It is impossible to say precisely how many
died in these pogroms, which went on into 1619.
Jewish chronicles record that there were
100,000 deaths and that 300 communities were
exterminated.
Emmanuel Moses
Paris (France)
OUR COMMON
ANCESTOR
Is the mind-set that causes us to practise intol¬
erance and prejudice the fault of educational
systems in use around.the world?
We know that we are descended from a com¬
mon ancestor, Homo erectus, who evolved into
Homo sapiens, and began to migrate from Africa
to all parts of the world. We are all descended
from the same African ancestor.
Should the schools and universities of the
world each day instil this knowledge into the
minds of the world's students? If they did, per¬
haps they would dispel the mind-set that leans
toward intolerance and prejudice.
Martin J. O'Malley, Jr.
Passaic, New Jersey (U.S.A.)
PROGRESS AND EQUITY
"The poor countries must he helped to acquire
new technologies and equipment, to train their
people and enter existing networks, in short to
modernize along with the others,'" writes Fed¬
erico May or in his Commentary column on page
39 of your December 1996 issue.
To my mind, this is quite a challenge. Dev cl¬
opinent aid from the wealthy countries has dw in-
died in the past few years.
The day when we manage to "ally progress
with fairness" men and women will be living in
the best of worlds.
Abdou Tini Kano
Tibiri (Niger)
CITIZENS OF THE WORLD
In his interview on peace education in your Jaiij
nary 1997 issue, Professor Johan Gaining dis¬
cusses a number of interesting ideas to which I
subscribe.
lint to my mind he fails to grasp the fact
that conflict is sterile whereas peace is fertile.
There is a risk that his peace studies will not
get "to grips with . . . violence" (even though he
realizes that communication and education are
essential tools for doing this), because what must
be done is shoulder the noble task of developing
a system to promote peaceful collaboration.
The days when we were Chinese, French,
Indians or Chileans are over. Now we are all cit¬
izens of the world with responsibility for the
planet.
Claudia Merazzi
Bienne (Switzerland)
CARTOON ISSUE:
AN ORDER OF MERIT
I am used to the line illustrations that you usu¬
ally publish and thought that the aesthetic
quality of the cartoons in your July-August 1996
double issue (U\ESCO Through the Looking-
G/ass) was uneven.
This is my order of preference:
1) Egypt
2) Military dictatorship
3) World Heritage (pp. 46-55)
4)U1\T.SC()intheyear3000
5) A Lone Fortune adventure
I would have thought more highly of the
"Nomads" story if the characters had not been
depicted with like dog-like faces. The Tuareg,
Masai and other nomadic peoples deserve some¬
thing better than caricature.
Guy Barreré
Tamanrasset (Algeria)
Thank youforfor your appreciation ofour car¬
toon issue. Juno, the author of'Momads",
always draws the characters ofhis comicstrips,
whatever their theme, with ihefeatures ofani¬
mals. Editor
AUTHOR!
Why have you stopped giving biographical
details, even just a line or two, about your con¬
tributors? It would be interesting at least to
know their profession and nationality.
Yolande Briffa
Houilles (France)
lîriefbiographical notes on contributors ore now
published at the end ofeach issue. See this page.
Editor
50
THE UNESCO IpllltlERl MARCH 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
NEsco on line via Internet
http://www.unesco.org
Currently on-line are: an index of the contents of the last 22
issues of the Unesco Courier, Unesco press releases, addresses,
fax, telex and electronic mail numbers of Unesco's regional
offices, National Commissions and Unesco Clubs, the directory of
Unesco databases and information services, colour images of the
Japanese Garden and other architectural sites at Unesco
Headquarters, as well as works of art such as Henry Moore's
reclining sculpture.
To contact
THE UNESCO I OUR1ER
directly with suggestions and comments, type:
mesco.courier@unesco.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Sa ~'"'-í' H£n
THEME OF THE NEXT ISSUE:
INTERPRETING
THE HUMAN BODY
¥
INTERVIEW WITH:
MARIO LUZI
HERITAGE:
TE WAHIPOUNAMU
(SOUTH WEST NEW ZEALAND)
ENVIRONMENT:
GARDENS THROUGH
THE AGES
]]>
</page>
</document>
