<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="105951eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
I
INTERVIEW
MARIO LUZI
HERITAGE
TE WAHIPOUNAMU
(NEW ZEALAND)
ENVIRONMENT
GARDENS: A CULTURAL
FLOWERING
M 1205-9704-22,00 F
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ENCOUNTERS?̂*
We invite readers to send
us photographs to be
considered for publication
in this feature. Your photo
should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be
an example of cultural
cross-fertilization.
Alternatively, you could
send us pictures of two
works from different
cultural backgrounds in
which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption
to all photographs.
"PLUVIOMAGICAL PRAYER" 1996, serigraphy and collage (40 x 30 cm) by Eduardo Gabriel Pepe
This design by an Argentine artist features a two-headed serpent, a typical motif of the pre-Columbian
Yocavil culture (850-1480 A. D.) of northeastern Argentina. A good omen associated with rain and
prosperity, the serpent symbolizes lightning and water. The darker part of the design, extending over the
edge of the rectangle, evokes past and future and the slow advance of humankind with its attendant fears
and desires. chumo Gaonapepe
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Mario Luzi.
The life and art ofa major Italian poet (p. 4).
Te Wahipounamu (New Zealand).
One of the world's most beautiful wildplaces
(p. 40).
contents
APRIL 1997
THE BODY AND THE SELF
Month by month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat	9
Face values	10
by David Le Breton
An invisible river 15
by Shlgenori Nagatomo
The Body and the Book	21
by David Biale
A language of its own 25
by Manga Bekombo Priso
From selfhood to salvation	28
by Romain Maitra
The garden of delights 32
by Abdelwahab Meddeb
Dossier: Body language	35
Consultant: Romain Maitra
Commentary Federico Mayor 38
HERITAGE 40
Te Wahipounamu, New Zealand's pristine wilderness
by Ann-Marie Johnson
GREENWATCH Gardens: a cultural flowering by France Bequette 	44
LISTENING Isabelle Leymarie talks to Rido Bayonne . 48
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR	49
AUTHORS 50
Cover: A depiction of the "subtle body" with its network of wheels [cakras) and fibres
{nadls}, illustrating pranayama, the discipline of breathing in yoga, which is indispensable for
spiritual development. O Romain Maitra, Pans
> ^>URiiTHE UNESCO lO IERl APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
interview
vv
Mano Luzi
Mario Luzi is an essayist, playwright and translator, but above all he is one of the greatest living
Italian poets. His works have been translated into some thirty languages. Among those which
have appeared in English are For the baptism ofour fragments (Guernica, Montreal, 1992) and
After manyyears: selected poems (Dedalus Press, Dublin, 1990). Here, Mario Luzi talks to Mauro
Rosi about his life and work and the role of poetry today.
You wrote your first poem at the age of nine.
What do you remember about that time in your life?
Mario Luzi: I was an ordinary child, and I took
part wholeheartedly in the life of the community,
even if I sometimes had interests that were not
shared hy all my chums. One day, when I was
playing in the open air with the others, I felt the
need to leave them and go home, so I could write
that celebrated first poem to which you refer,
and which I have since lost. That was how I expe¬
rienced an almost physical need a need to trans¬
fer the living element of the grass and the park
where I was playing on to paper, into writing. I
can still remember the theme of that first piece
of poetic creation. At the timo 1 was very
impressed hy Dante's Divine Comedy, which of
course I hadn't read, but which I knew about
through a series of illustrated booklets (strip
cartoons didn't yet exist). I was intrigued by the
character of Dante and his journey that mys¬
terious adventure to forbidden places, where he
judged and was judged and wondered whether
he had really deserved his fate.
And after that initial experience?
M. L.: I remember a poem I wrote about a volcano
when I was about twelve. I must have heard
about an eruption in Italy or somewhere, and
my youthful imagination had been fired by that
wondrous element which blazed forth from its
hiding-place in the earth.
And then. ..?
M. L.: I wasn't very interested in the poems we
were given to read. My teachers gave pride of
place to moralistic poetry, chosen for didactic
purposes, like Giusti's not of course his ironi¬
cal poems, but his "devout" and less brilliant
work. I was far more drawn to the poetry of
D'Annunzio and Paseoli, which was modern for
its time. I couldn't really understand it but I
was interested in the way it broke away from
the set models we were given at school. It was
only later, when I was at high school, that I felt
a real need to express myself in words. I wrote a
great deal, mainly letters, almost all of which I
have lost. I then gradually decided that I was
going to devote my life to writing.
You later became a university specialist in
French poetry. How did your interest in that and in
European poetry in general begin?
M. L.: That was much later. First I became inter¬
ested in philosophy and spent a long time study¬
ing it, almost to the point where it began to com¬
pete with poetry. I was around eighteen or twenty
years old. Yet when I approached philosophy as
a spécifie discipline, I got the feeling it was all
rather how shall I put it? a will-o'-the-wisp. I
was probably more interested in the myth of phi¬
losophy than in philosophy itself: 1 loved the wis¬
dom of the Pre-Socraties, Plato and other philoso¬
phers of Antiquity. In other words, I preferred
philosophy that established a relationship with
truth and the human element to philosophy which
saw itself as a process of self-correction. I5y that
I mean the kind of finicky philosophy that
restricts itself to what Leopardi ironically called
"ramme/ir/i" "darning"' or "mending". At that
time, Italian philosophy was above all orientated
towards the latest manifestations of idealism, and
that didn't suit me at all.
THE UNESCO lOURIERB APRIE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Poetry is an especially important way of
approaching truth.
M;I ario Luzi
in December 1996
Do you think that in a different cultural context
you might have ended up as a philosopher rather
than a poet?
M. L.: I don't know. Put I would certainly have
been more responsive to philosophy. I think that
in this respect my career is similar to Leopardi's.
Although he was best known as a poet, he con¬
sidered himself a philosopher hut didn't like
the philosophy of his time.
It was only late in life that I rediscovered
philosophy, when I was asked by a magazine to
take part in a discussion with Gianni Vattimo
and Massimo Gacciari, philosophers who belong
to what is known as the "weak thought" {il pen-
siero debole) school. This school, which was
inspired by Martin Heidegger and Hans Georg
Gadamer, regards language as the "house of
being" and believes it plays an essential role in the
process of the formation and recognition of truth.
It recognizes the emotional roots of experience
and therefore its own emotional and poetic
sources. It holds that poetry, as a radical cre¬
ation in and through language, is an especially
important way of approaching truth.
i fM\\ â
Ik 1 1 t 1 i \
r ^m f 1 »
v
r
This relationship with philosophy, especially with
Heideggerian philosophy, is at one with the religious
urge, with religious faith, which is a constant
feature of your poetry.
M. L.: Heidegger's philosophy does indeed attach
great importance to the sacred. It constantly
asks questions of theology and of poetry too,
notably Hilke's and Hölderlin's. . . .
A hallmark of your generation was its belief in
the ideal of the committed intellectual. For some,
that involved a very direct form of commitment, and
sometimes even activism in political parties. What
was your experience ofthat eventful period, and
what do you think of it with hindsight?
L. M.: By way of an answer, I will refer you to a
poem I wrote some thirty-four years ago, l*resso il
Besenzio. In it I describe a kind of meeting with
the "committed", to whom I reply, poetically, by
defining my own position. I tell them that although
we are moving in the same direction my itinerary
is less direct and longer than theirs; that I also
have to heed values which transcend current
events and are in a sense timeless; that my watch
is regulated by more complicated mechanisms,
which means that my time is not the same as
theirs. You mentioned earlier the faith that dri¬
ves my creation. I would simply add that the rela¬
tionship and confrontation between time and the
timeless is a constant element of my poetry.
Having said that, I approve of political com¬
mitment when it is ethically inspired and deeply
motivated, not purely polemical. I've never liked
the barricades, but even though I have not
committed myself to any political movement
I've always been very aware of the sufferings of
people victimized by injustice and mindful of
the relationship between power and freedom.
The universality of poetry is nowadays taken for
granted. But when one looks closely at the question
of translation, it seems clear that the language
barrier can sometimes be an insuperable obstacle to
the wide circulation of a piece of writing. What's
your position on this?
M. L.: The language barrier complicates matters
and is certainly a limitation. I realize that any
THE UNESCO lOURIERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
k translation is debatable, that the legitimacy of
the choices made can always be questioned, and
that translation is always to some extent inade¬
quate or unfaithful. But no one, I'm glad to say,
has ever been able to prevent translation from
going on. And, anyway, surely the whole point of
poetry is that it transcends its original context,
overcomes the language barrier, and carries its
message beyond the source from which it sprang.
Without that potential, poetry cannot exist. It is
also true that people have always needed to wel¬
come poetry, to receive it as a gift, to be recep¬
tive to it. Despite the imperfections arising from
the way it is given concrete expression, there is
something vital and irrevocable in poetry: words
that are uttered in it are uttered forever and
can never be annulled. This holds true even if
they sometimes reach their audience in an "adul¬
terated" form.
When all's said and done, translation is about
human communication in the broadest sense. It
is in the nature of human beings to recognize
and be recognized, to seek and to be sought. In
Translation is about human
communication in the broadest sense.
other words, translation is an intrinsic part of
the human mind. In the biblical episode of Pen¬
tecost, the Word is heard and understood by
all though no one quite understands how. For
me, that is the "first translation".
Yourwerebornin Florence, you were educated
there, you have always lived there, and even if your
duties have taken you elsewhere, you have always
returned there. Didn'tyou everfeelthe need to cast
off your moorings and get away from your origins?
M. L.: No. My origins have not been an obstacle to
my poetry, because Florence has always been,
apart from one or two moments of eclipse, a pole
of universal attraction. Florence's culture is noth¬
ing if not universal. Far from being local or
parochial, it is open to all that is human, and
has been at least since the thirteenth century.
In the 1930s Florence was a hotbed of poetic
creativity. Literary historians refer to "Florentine
hermeticism" as an extremelyfruitful movement.
M. L.: The poets to whom the "hermetic" label
was attached were not all Florentines, but it is
true that at that time Eugenio Móntale, Carlo
Emilio Gadda, Alfonso Gatto, Tommaso Lan-
dolfi, Elio Vittorini and others all congregated in
Florence. The literary tradition of Dante's city
was not the only reason why they were there.
During the Fascist period Florence was an
"oasis", a place "apart" in Italian life. Because
of its marginal relationship with the country's
main political and economic centres, it enjoyed
a degree of cultural freedom that encouraged
the emergence of innovative movements. This
was an important factor which, on top of the
prestige of its centuries-old literary and artistic
tradition, enabled Florence to continue to play
a leading role despite the political situation in
Italy. Moreover, our movement was underpinned
by no specific doctrine or aesthetics. The poetic
renaissance of the 1930s was driven solely by
the need to lend poetic language a new, more
profound and more human credibility. Her¬
meticism inspired two or three generations of
poets. Even such already mature and established
poets as Móntale and Ungaretti underwent a cer¬
tain renewal thanks to the interest and support
of younger poets.
What were your sources of inspiration and points
of reference in international poetry at that time?
M. L.: We wanted to pursue the discourse of the
Symbolists while at the same time adapting it to
our environment and our motivations. Our inspi¬
ration was Mallarmé, and also Rimbaud. Our
movement brought about an important change in
Italian literary language, which opened up to
other traditions, especially those of other Euro¬
pean countries, thanks to great translators like
Giovanni Russo, Renato Poggioli and, for Span¬
ish, Carlo Bo. As for myself, I am sure that living
and working in that environment left a lasting
mark on the way I express myself.
In their desire to avoid retreating into a self-
contained environment, intellectuals today,
particularly those in the developing countries, are in
danger of being waylaid by shallow
cosmopolitanism, commercial culture and a
superficial lingua francaall of them examples of
the decay triggered by globalization. What do you
feel about this?
M. L.: I think it's a very real problem, and I share
the concern of intellectuals who have looked into
the question, such as the Egyptian Nobel Prize
winner, Naguib Mahfouz. Today's universalist
trend, encouraged hy historical events, brings
> rjoiTHE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 19^7
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
with it a risk of homogcnization and consequently
a loss of roots and identities. Certain writers,
notably those belonging to dominant cultures
that grew out of colonial civilizations, are perhaps
less sensitive to this problem. Others however
and I'm thinking of certain forms of literary
expression in the Caribbean have come up with
original and remarkably brilliant solutions
through very powerful writing which has
remained faithful to its roots while at the same
time being virtually "global". But the dilemma
of having to choose between regionalism and cos¬
mopolitanism remains a very real problem in every
country, including Italy.
Ever since Hegel, intellectuals have periodically
predicted the demise of art. While it is true that
poetry has blithely ignored such predictions, the fact
remains that it now leads a shadowy and marginal
existence.
M. L.: That's true. The myth of poetry has come
to an end. Poetry was more vigorous and more
important in the past than it is now. Take the
Renaissance court, the medieval city, Dante,
Petrarch. Poets had no power, but they could
celebrate power and help define its form. And
take, on the other hand, the antithetical power
of poetry: I'm thinking here of Baudelaire and
the key moment in the rift between power and
poetry. It was by opposing those in power that
poetry, in a way, demonstrated its force and its
virtues.
After alliance, and then opposition, came
divorce. And divorce led to indifference, the
great enemy of poetry. So it was that poetry and
sometimes even great poetry began to flourish
in a marginal way. Poetry accepted that mar-
ginality.
Some poets experienced marginality not as an
ordeal but almost as a privilege.
M. L.: Yes, as a sense ofbelonging, an essential fea¬
ture of their identity. But while the myth of the
poet has completely disappeared today, the
poet's discourse is perhaps more alive than ever.
In times as muddled and chaotic as ours, all soci¬
ety's players are called to account. We're all in
the same boat. The poet is no longer someone
special, but he is listened to like the rest of us.
Of course, you can dodge him or give him a wide
berth, but if you cross his path, and he is a true
poet, you cannot turn a deaf car to him. Per¬
haps his symbolic role is outmoded, but he is
still there, and he is more necessary than ever. We
Perhaps thepoeù symbolic role is
outmoded^ but he is still there, more
necessary than ever.
all feel the lack of something essential. And when
something is lacking we go looking for it in a
place where we have a chance of finding it. Well,
poetry is one of those places where the overall
quest for meaning manifests itself.
Is there a poem which you would have liked to
write but have never written?
M. L.: I believe that all poems exclude. Any poem,
even the greatest and most perfect, leaves some¬
thing unsaid. That is inherent in the symbolic
power of poetic language and in its force. It is a
limitation I perhaps feel more keenly than oth¬
ers. It is greater than I would have liked. It's
true I sometimes think I could have expressed
more directly something I have said. Whereas
we think we mean one thing and set out to
develo]) an idea, that idea may suddenly seem to
us to be an external object. We sometimes get the
feeling it has escaped us, even if that is not
strictly speaking true. In fact, this idea is part of
us. Without realizing it, we carry it within us
and we work on it, and at the same time its pres¬
ence influences our behaviour and everything we
say or do. By externalizingit, we transform it, and
there is sometimes a lingering regret that we
have not expressed it straightforwardly.
Perhaps, on the other hand, the spirit of our
age deserved a greater degree of dramatization.
One of my plays, Rosales, is about terrorism.
Terrorism and . . . eroticism, because, oddly
enough, the two were closely connected at one
time. One of themain characters is a kind of Don
Juan, who gets caught up in a terrorist operation
against his will. When I had finished the play, I
realized there was more to be said on the subject,
especially about the lurking, stifled yearning for
liberation and salvation which drives us all, and
which sometimes manifests itself in violence.
I could have said more about this highly elu¬
sive dimension which some people find in tra¬
ditional religion, while others deny its existence
that "something" which perhaps exists, but
which we do not know how to look for. I believe
that, while we assert that there is nothing, some¬
thing exists, but we cannot manage to give it a
name. I
THE UNESCO Q)URI ERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
TBfe UNESCO
Courier
^*^ 50th YEAR
Published monthly in 29 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15, France.
Fax. (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45
e-mail unesco couner@unesco org
Internet http //www unesco org
The body and the self
CO
Director- Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor Gillian Whitcomb
English edition RoyMalkm
French edition: Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production Georges Servat
Illustrations. Ariane Bailey (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 46 90)
Documentation José Banaag
(Tel (33) (0)1.45 68. 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Beim (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 87)
Film duplication: Daniel Meister
Secretariat. Annie Brächet
(Tel (33) (0)1 45 68 47 15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pmck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 47 14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian" Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian AkbarZargar (Teheran)
Dutch' BartChnstiaens (Antwerp)
Portuguese Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili Leonard J Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese Feng Mmgxian (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish Rntta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque JuxtoEgaña(Donostia)
Thai" Duangtip Sunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa Aliyu Muhammad Bunza (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasihuk (Kiev)
Galician Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Composlela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68.57.45
Subscriptions Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 45 65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Customer service: Michel Ravassard,
(Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91)
Accounts (Tel (33) (0) 1.45 68 45 65)
Shipping Daniel Meister (Tel (33) (0)1 45 68 47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel '(33) (0)1 45 68 45 65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years 396 FF
Students 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues 72 FF
Developing countries.
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 years 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles ant' photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent lo the editor Signed
articles reprinted must bear author's name Non copyright photos will
be supplied on request, Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not nec¬
essarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of
the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are written by the
Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps published in the maga
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in microtorm (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700
Pans, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100
U S A , (3) N C R Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc , 111 West 40th
Street. New York. U S A . (4) Bell and Howell Co , Old Mansfield Road.
Wooster. Ohio 44691, USA.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL Cl -AVRIL 1997
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N M PP.
Photocomposition, photogravure.
Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z I. Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 4-1997-OPI-97-558 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 50-51.
by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
8
THE UNESCO lOURIERB APRIL 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
_;- .
* Í
« =
»Vi t *' ; > *
*.
-
> *
\ ** .^ '
. *
*
-
. ' ""* \
»
r
V
In the normal way of things most healthy adults hardly think twice about their bodies until
some kind of accident, breakdown or illness suddenly reminds them that they have one. Then
they send in the artillerydoctors, analysts, medicationwith orders to put things right.
When the machine has been patched up, they forget about it again.
Yet when they really think about it, they realize that life and body are inseparable,
bound together in a singular partnership. The body is inhabited by consciousness, but this
consciousness does not exist outside its physical envelope. Life is a marriage, for better or
for worse, between the two. Divorce is out of the question.
People who know that this is so and yet continue to pay no attention to their body or treat
it badly, undermine the body's integrity and in so doing disturb the subtle rhythms and
necessary harmonies between mind and body. They are the victims of a self-inflicted wound.
How can people achieve a creative unity based on harmonious relations between body and
consciousness, matter and mind? These questions have intrigued philosophers and the¬
ologians for thousands of years and are of growing concern for doctors, psychologists and
psychotherapists today.
This issue of the UNESCO Counerattempts to give some idea of the variety and complexity
of the answers that have been offered, particularly highlighting their strong cultural, philo¬
sophical and religious overtones. Differences in approach arise largely from what is meant
by the notion of consciousness in different traditions of thought.
For some monists, consciousness is simply the highest, most refined form of the orga¬
nization of matter. They would define the relations between physical and mental phe¬
nomena experimentally and rationally, using methods of scientific analysis.
Dualists, on the other hand, believe that there is an irreducible distinction between
mind and matter. There is a difference in kind between the physical, perishable body and
the immortal soul, which, though joined to the individual, is part of a transcendent reality
and is accountable to a divine authority. To contribute to the soul's salvation the body must
submit to God's commandments, which may, depending on the scriptures and the way they
are interpreted, sometimes exalt sensual experience and sometimes disparage it.
A person can also be seen as a triad: a "gross body", a "subtle body" (or mind) and a
cosmic substance, the Spirit. The Spirit, the ultimate level of reality, can be metaphori¬
cally compared to a single, infinite and eternal Energy. The gross body and the subtle body
are provisional forms that partake of this Energy. Like ocean waves, they are born, grow and
fade away without ever ceasing to be part of the ocean. The meaning of life is accom¬
plished insofar as everyone, crossing the gross and subtle body's successive frontiers,
returns to their infinite nature, rejoining the ocean's reality.
Mind and body have much to say to each other. As long as they stay on speaking terms.
THE UNESCO ^lURIER APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Is there more
to the human
face than meets
the eye?
ace values
BY DAVID LE BRETON
The American artist George Catlin
was once painting the portrait of a
Sioux chieftain, Little Bear, and as
the portrait was in semi-profile,
part of the sitter's face was obscured. There
was consternation when one of the
bystanders called out roughly: "Little Bear
is only half a man". Little Bear asked who
it was that had spoken and the man gave his
name, adding: "Ask the painter, he knows
you are only half a man. He has painted
only half your face. He knows the other
half is no good."
A conflict that had been simmering
beneath the surface of relations between
the two men had erupted into the open
over the interpretation, in moral terms, of
a portrait, a painting wherein the sitter's
worth is symbolically represented by the
face he or she presents to other people.
Shon-Ka, Little Bear's adversary, urged him
to make the painter show him "full face".
10
THE UNESCO lOURlERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
I he face gives living,
mysterious expression to the
absolute nature of the
differences between
individuals."
Little Bear rejected the suggestion, but soon
the two men were again at loggerheads.
Shon-Ka challenged Little Bear, shouting:
"If he is a whole man, let him show it". To
save face in the eyes of the others, the two
men had to fight it out to the finish. Unfor¬
tunately, Little Bear's wife, knowing her
husband's short temper, had taken the pre¬
caution of unloading his rifle, so that when
the men fired at each other Shon-Ka was
unhurt but his shot hit Little Bear full in the
face, lacerating the "no good" part as if sym¬
bolically confirming Shon-Ka's accusations.
Shon-Ka did not benefit by his deed. He
hightailed it out into the prairie pursued by
his fellow-tribesmen, while Catlin hastily
packed up his belongings.
A mirror of individuality
Refusal to allow people the dignity of hav¬
ing a face of their own is a prime example
of how to deny their status as human
beings. There are a variety of metaphori¬
cal expressions losing face, putting a bold
face on things, being discountenanced, and
so forth that show how important the
face is to an individual's sense of identity
within the social context. Saving face and
being able to look others in the face are
considered serious issues in very many
societies. In the symbology of racism, the
suppression of all that is human in people
requires that the sign denoting their mem¬
bership of the human race be destroyed.
In racist taunts they are treated as animals
THE UNESCO ^JURIERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
and degraded. To be stripped of their
human rank they have to be symbolically
deprived of their faces, the more easily to
be despised or destroyed.
In everyday life, it is by our faces that
we recognize one another. By going about
with our hands and faces uncovered we
are exposing those features by which we
may be immediately differentiated. While
the body forms the line of demarcation
between the self and the external world or
other people, it is in the face that the iden¬
tity which gives social and cultural mean¬
ing to the individual is displayed. It is the
" Physiognomy endeavours
to dispel the mystery of other
people, to reduce it to a few
simple features and a specific
character, which entails an
illusion of control that
becomes a fearsome
weapon in the hands of those
who practice it as if it were a
science."
face that gives living, mysterious expres¬
sion to the absolute nature of what are in
fact only minute differences between indi¬
viduals. Faces work an infinite range of
variations on the same simple theme, cre¬
ating billions of shapes and expressions
out of the most basic of symbols eyes,
nose, forehead, and so on. Facial features
and expressions relate individuals to the
community and at the same time allow
them full scope to assert their differences
and their uniqueness.
Of all parts of the body, it is in the face,
that the highest values are concentrated. It
is there that the sense of identity is mir¬
rored, there that attractiveness and all the
gradations of beauty and ugliness are
recorded. So high a value is placed on it
that any disfigurement becomes a trau¬
matic experience, almost resulting in a loss
of identity. The more importance a society
attaches to individuality, the greater is the
face's value. Portrait painting appeared in
Europe at the time of the Renaissance, that
is, at the same time as the individualism
which characterizes Western societies.
The Florentine painters of the quattro¬
cento, Masaccio, Paolo Uccello and Piero
della Francesca, were at pains to render
the facial features of their sitters with
meticulous accuracy, as were Flemish
painters, especially Van Eyck, in his Virgin
with Chancellor Rolin (1435), for example.
I First impressions
As there seems to be a disturbing corre¬
spondence between personality and facial
form, there was a strong temptation to
make the face a kind of stand-in for the
individual, the outward and visible sign of
the character within. In religious art, the
inexpressible and singular nature of the
face was already reflected in the idea of it
as the place wherein the soul chooses to
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
make its dwelling, where the spiritual takes
corporeal form.
The importance of the face to the sense
of identity is clear from the attention that
lovers pay to it in their relationships, a theme
plentifully illustrated in literature. "One of
the signs of love", says Anne Philippe, "is the
passion with which the lover looks at the
loved one's face; the initial emotion, instead
of dwindling, continues and swells, and the
look in their eyes becomes Ariadne's thread,
leading each to the other's heart."1 The
French novelist Michel Tournier sees the
face as the focus of desire: "There is one
sure way of knowing whether you love
somebody," he writes. "It is when their face
inspires more physical desire than any other
part of their body."2
The lover's gaze seems permanently
on the verge of experiencing some reve¬
lation and feeds upon that anticipation. The
face always seems to be the place where
the truth is at any moment about to be
unveiled. Inexhaustible in its store of new
or undiscovered meanings, it is like a ter¬
ritory waiting to be explored afresh every
day, and the end of a love-relationship no
doubt comes when the lovers find each
other's faces ordinary and no longer seek
out the mystery in them.
It is only a step from perceiving, as peo¬
ple often do, a close correspondence
between the "soul" and the face, and
believing that a thorough acquaintance
with other people's minds can be obtained
from studying their features. Although,
as Montaigne says, "The face is a feeble
surety", faces nevertheless exert a very
strong influence when people meet.
Other people's faces create a "first impres¬
sion" of liking or mistrust, curiosity or
fear that is not always easily dispelled.
This emotional reaction, which is felt at
first glance and in which imagination plays
a very large part, to some extent directs
"In love the face always seems
to be the place where the truth
is at any moment about to be
unveiled."
the course of future encounters. What the
Swiss writer Johann Kaspar Lavater (1741-
1801), the founder of physiognomies,
called this "physiognomical feeling",
though lacking in discernment, is one of
the things that facilitate or hamper contact
with others.
The fallacy ofphysiognomy
Physiognomy therefore set itself the task
of obliging faces to yield up their secrets.
It claimed that individuals' external features
faithfully reflect their inner characters and
that their moral qualities can be immedi¬
ately ascertained from the study of those
> CpuiTHE UNESCO IOURIERB APRIL 1097
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
features. Those who can read the signs of
the inter-relationship between soul and
body, whereby the face becomes as it were
the individual's moral signature, hold mas¬
tery of their relations with other people.
Physiognomy endeavours to dispel the
mystery of other people, to reduce it to a
few simple features and a specific character,
and also to reveal, to expose the soul behind
the body's disguise a dubious enterprise
entailing an illusion of control that becomes
a fearsome weapon in the hands of those
who practice it as if it were a science.
The vocabulary of physiognomy
changes from place to place and period to
period but the illusion of total control over
others remains constant. It was in the nine¬
teenth century that this pseudo-science
" I he Florentine painters of
the quattrocento were at pains
to render the facial features of
their sitters with meticulous
accuracy." Below, a portrait of
Battista Sforza by the Tuscan
painter Piero della Francesca
(1416-1492).
flourished in Europe. Lavater and to an
even greater extent his followers reduced
human individuality to a small number of
visual clues tied in with a typology of per¬
sonality that psychology has since dis¬
carded. They were in fact interested not in
the face as a whole but in sets of facial fea¬
tures: merely from the shape of a forehead,
the curl of a lip, the set of a nose or the look
in the subjects' eyes, assumptions could be
made about their psychological make-up;
and their moral essence, their tempera¬
ments, hidden vices, qualities or faults and,
their as yet uncommitted acts of faithless¬
ness could be unambiguously brought to
light. For the physiognomists, the arrange¬
ment of the features unlocked the secret
of the individual's identity.
The ambivalence and the element of sur¬
prise present in human beings' relationship
with their own faces should in fact be
enough to discourage anyone from trying to
map out the personality on the basis of facial
characteristics. The great painters of self-
portraits such as Rembrandt painted them¬
selves over and over again with different
faces. "The physiognomy," wrote the sev¬
enteenth-century French moralist Jean de
La Bruyère, "though it may serve for the
purpose of conjecture, is not a measure
whereby we may judge men."3 Faces give
only indications of other people's person¬
alities, not full descriptions. It is only possi¬
ble to get to know others by meeting them,
speaking to them and seeing them in action.
Faces are not pretty geometrical figures or
sets of tell-tale features. Only when
approached delicately, with a special kind
of gentleness, does a face reveal its innu¬
merable facets.
l. Miroirs; autoportraits, an anthology edited by Michel
Tournier. Denoel, Paris, 1973.
2. Michel Tournier, La goutted'or, Gallimard, Paris, 1986.
3. Jean de La Bruyère, Les caractères ou lesmde ce
siècle, 1688 (first edition).
!* THE UNESCO COURIER« APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
n invisible river
BY SHIGENORI NAGATOMO
[n the Oriental
tradition,
meditation can
detect the elusive
energy-flows
that sustain the
bodv
Tl 'MiJA' .^
IYI onks meditating before the
ruins of Ayutthaya, the capital
of ancient Slam (now
Thailand), north of Bangkok.
I
n order to understand the East Asian also recognizes a dimension of being that
idea of the body, particularly that of the escapes our everyday understanding. This
Chinese and Japanese, we must imag- is important, because our perception of our
ine that instead of having a body, we body influences the method of healing we
are our body and more importantly, that think to be appropriate and effective for it.
our body lives us. The East Asian tradition Without a clear understanding of the body,
rthe unesco Courier« april 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
In April, Laotian women
celebrate the start of the new
year in a Luang Prabang
temple.
we cannot understand how the body can be
healed.
The idea of the body which has been
cherished in the East Asian tradition is
based on the philosophy of self-cultiva¬
tion and is derived mainly from experi¬
ence obtained through meditation. In Bud¬
dhism, Daoism and Shintoism, meditation
is a technique for observing and becoming
attuned to the intricate workings of the
life-supporting energy system that exists
beyond or beneath the psycho-physio¬
logical activity of the living human body.
i The flowing body
A characteristic image of the East Asian
meditational perspective is that of the
"flowing body". The body is likened to a
river whose water is, ideally, in pristine
condition and transparent but cannot be
seen by the naked eye or be detected
anatomically as blood vessels and nerve
fibres can. The body that flows is a "sub¬
tle-body" and since it is invisible to the
senses in everyday life, most of us are rel¬
atively unconscious of it.
It can, however, be detected through
heightened awareness during meditation.
When the threshold of self-consciousness
is lowered in conjunction with the reduc¬
tion of respiration, an advanced medita¬
tor can become aware of a subtle flow of
energy throughout his or her body. This
energy, which is called & ¿in Japanese (Chi¬
nese, qi), is the source from which both,
the psychological and the physiological
emerge.
Ki- energy flows through a network of
16 > CouruTHE UNESCO IpUftlER" APRIL 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
I he 12th-century Bengali poet
Jayadeva, author of the
Gitagovinda ("Song of the
Cowherd") bows in respect to
the Hindu god Vishnu. Indian
miniature from the Pahari
school (1730).
circuits, or "^¿-meridians", beneath the
skin. According to psychologist Motoyama
Hiroshi this network is located in the water-
rich area of the connective tissues of the
dermis, the deep inner layer of the skin,
where such chemical substances as sodium,
potassium, calcium, chloride and collagen
are found. Since these substances exist as
ions in the bodily fluids, the flow is electro-
physiologically detectable, so that the flow¬
ing body is more than just a metaphor. Ki-
energy literally flows beneath the
psycho-physiological body of which we
are ordinarily aware.
The flowing body knows no bound¬
ary between the interior and the exterior,
between mind and matter. For this rea¬
son acupuncture medicine maintains that
absorption and release of ^¿-energy
occur though for most of us, uncon¬
sciously between the flowing body and
its surroundings, and between one flow¬
ing body and another.
The second idea of the body which is
relevant for religious healing within the
East Asian tradition is that of the spirit-
body, a concept which brings us into the
domain of religion proper. Each human
spirit-body has a certain form which is dif¬
ferent from that of the individual's physi¬
cal body and also from other spirit bodies.
It is defined primarily by the pattern of
emotions such as love, hate and anger, and
their existential repercussions. Whereas
the flowing body is confined to the imme¬
diate ambience of its physical body (the
exernal emission of ^/-energy having a
four- to five-metre range), the spirit body
is believed to possess relative freedom
from spatial and temporal confinement.
In addition to the hierarchy of spirit-
bodies, however, Buddhists believe that
there is a hierarchy of divine spirits, whose
nature and attributes vary, their experien¬
tial correlates depending on the colour of
their light, which ranges from the primary
colours such as red and blue, to complete
transparency. They arc deified and wor¬
shipped under different names in different
belief systems.
The most significant point about these
different ideas of the body is that the "vis¬
ible" and the "invisible" are, in principle,
reversible. Without this reversibility no
religious healing is possible.
1 Religious healing
The crucial difference between religious
healing and other kinds of treatment is in
their respective goals. The former
addresses a pathological condition and
seeks to achieve higher religious cogni¬
tion; the latter are content to restore the
body to its normal everyday state.
Another significant difference between
17) ÇlURI ERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
religious and other forms of healing is that
the pathological condition that calls for
religious healing is functional in nature,
and not an organic disorder.
In religious healing, a pathological con¬
dition is regarded as a necessary step on
the way to spiritual growth. It strength¬
ens the living psycho-physiological body
and prepares it for encounters with spirit
bodies and spiritual beings, and eventu¬
ally for emancipation from this world.
Acupuncture
Acupuncture medicine is particularly
effective in treating both functional and
^chronic disease. It considers that a patho¬
logical condition is engendered by the stag¬
nation of &z-energy flowing in the merid¬
ians. The "water" in the flowing body
becomes polluted, accumulates debris,
and departs from its ideal pristine condi¬
tion and transparency. This stagnation
causes an excess or lack of ^¿-energy and
an inversion of complementary forces
(yin-yang phases). There is a departure
from the harmonious, natural distribution
of ^¿-energy between the right and left
sides of the body, and between its upper
and lower parts.
Three interrelated kinds of factor may
contribute to this stagnation.
The first is a psychological condition
brought about by emotional instability.
People process emotional stimuli differ¬
ently in accordance with "likes" and "dis¬
likes" that originate in their unconscious.
In their interpersonal relationships and in
dealing with things around them, this LV*.WVVy
\
1
> if
1. m
M Korean shaman or
mudang. Early 20th-century
painting on paper.
I he head of a bronze statue
used for teaching acupuncture
(Korea, 15th century).
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
unconscious propensity unknowingly
creates emotional distortion and instabil¬
ity, affecting, for example, the proper func¬
tion of the autonomic nervous system.
The theory of stress and adaptation devel¬
oped by the Canadian scientist Hans Selye,
when interpreted physiologically, captures
the significance of this condition.
Secondly, environmental conditions,
especially climatic conditions, may help
to cause stagnation. Acupuncture medi¬
cine warns against the inadaptation of the
human body to its surrounding "climatic"
ambience, although in the modern world
the environment is becoming less and less
appropriate for the living human body.
The third factor is our attitude towards
our health, including such factors as irreg¬
ular lifestyle, negligence, and exhaustion, all
of which are rooted in the ethical orienta¬
tion of our lives.
I Curative images
Another category of healing involves
manipulation of the flowing body and the
spirit-body by means of an image-experi¬
ence. Religious healing in Daoism, Bud¬
dhism, and to some extent in Shintoism
uses visualization techniques of this sort.
This psychological approach, based on the
curative effect an image can have on the
body, is employed because a religious
image carries transformative power. Jung's
"active imagination" is an application of
this method.
A general feature of visualization is to
learn to experience a "sacred" image, ini¬
tially by creating it within one's psyche.
THE UNESCO COURIER" APRIL 1997 J
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
But as one advances in this practice, one
relies on the spontaneous generation of
the luminous form within one's psyche
and beyond, until one comes to the free
generation of any kind of image one
wishes. Using this method, self-healing
occurs in the course of a spiritual journey.
However, since this is difficult for the inex¬
perienced to achieve, a healer is called in to
help. For instance, if possession by a
malevolent spirit is deemed to be the cause
of a pathological condition, the healer will
negotiate with the spirit and try to per¬
suade it to awaken from its fixation on the
sufferer's spirit-body and leave it alone.
In Buddhism, emptiness-meditation
may be employed in order to counter pos¬
session by a malevolent spirit by bringing
about its non-substantiality. Significantly,
possession by either a benevolent or
malevolent spirit is closely connected with
spiritual development or lack thereof.
I Enlightenment
A third kind of religious healing in the East
Asian tradition is the Kharmic reconfigu¬
ration of the ripe, kharmic body. This idea
is predicated on an Indian belief that a
human being comes into this world in
virtue of his/her own kharma, and dies in
virtue of the same, i.e., the human as a con¬
tingent being. This kind of healing, how¬
ever, is reserved only for the few who
have become "god-men," or who have
achieved the highest satori (enlighten¬
ment), by transcending the temporal
demarcation. Healing of this type is linked
with the creative power to effect a change
in the psycho-physical world, something
which is still a mystery for most of us.
What is prescribed to a sufferer in such a
case, as is true with all religious suffering,
is daily prayer and/or meditation, along
with the strengthening of faith, in order
to nurture spiritual growth.
The philosophical background to the
idea of the body and healing in the East
Asian tradition is that human beings cohabit
the world of nature with other living beings.
By transforming their everyday mode of
consciousness they can become one with
the creative activity of nature and awaken
in themselves a natural healing power.
Sometimes affirmed, sometimes
denied, the body has always occupied a
central place in Jewish thought
hudying the Talmud in a f
synagogue in Israel. ®
THE UNESCO lOURIERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
ODYANDTHEUOOK
BY DAVID BIALE
In the Bible, the foundational text of
Judaism, the body is treated primarily
in the context of the cultic laws of
j purity. These laws dictate who is pure
enough to enter a sacred site and offer a
sacrifice. Anyone who has touched a dead
human body, for example, is considered
impure. Similarly, certain diseases, such as
some skin disorders, cause impurity. Most
normal body functions, such as urination or
defecation, do not create impurity, while
those related to the sexual organs, such as
seminal ejaculation, menstruation and
pathological bleeding from the genitals, do
render a person and his or her sexual part¬
ner impure.
The impurity related to genital dis¬
charges, both normal and abnormal, is puz¬
zling, since the priestly laws, in which we
find these prohibitions, regard sexuality
very positively. The biblical priests appear
to have been quite preoccupied with ques¬
tions of fertility and it is they who authore d
the divine blessings "be fruitful and multi¬
ply." Why did such authors regard sexual
fluids as impure, if they wished to affirm
sexuality? The answer seems to be that such
fluids were seen as divine substances whose
very power created impurity when they
left the body.
Another aspect of the body regarded as
divine was blood, although normal bleed¬
ing did not create impurity. The biblical
authors believed that blood is the life-force
and that spilling blood was a violation of
the divine order. The blood of animals was
not to be eaten, but instead returned to
God in a ceremony expiating the sin of
THE UNESCO ÇlURIER» APRIL 1997 M
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
killing the animal. Spilling human blood
could not, however, be expiated in the
same way. Instead, the only atonement
for killing a human being was to execute
the murderer. The Bible's very severe law
of capital punishment was a product of
this holy status of human blood.
The Jewish religion is not based only
on the Bible. In the first centuries of the
Common Era, a parallel body of law, called
the "Oral Law" or "rabbinic law," was for¬
mulated and set in writing byJewish schol¬
ars called rabbis. Although rabbinic law
had some of its foundations in the Bible,
much of it reflected the prevailing issues
of Greco-Roman culture, which was the
^culture in which the rabbis lived. Thus,
the attitude towards the body in rabbinic
literature can best be understood in the
context of late antiquity.
For Greco-Roman thinkers, such as
the Stoic philosophers, the body itself
posed less of a problem than did the pas¬
sions, which could overpower one's rea¬
son. The rabbis were also preoccupied
with the passions, which they called the
yetzer ha-ra (the "evil impulse"). They
held that the law is designed to restrain
and channel the passions into construc¬
tive activities. But the body itself they gen¬
erally viewed as a neutral vessel. There
are, to be sure, negative statements about
women's bodies in rabbinic literature, but
they are typically in the context of the anx¬
iety of the rabbis, who were all men, about
women distracting them from the holy
duty to study.
The vehiclefor the soul
The rabbis did not believe in a division
between the body and the soul. One rab¬
binic saying held that the soul is like a lame
man riding on the back of a blind man.
Thus the body provides the necessary
vehicle for the soul, although, by itself, it is
morally blind. The soul is always embod¬
ied and, in messianic times, the body will
be resurrected with the soul. However,
at least one rabbi held that in messianic
times "there will be no eating, drinking or
procreation." For this particular school of
thought, the body in a "perfected" world
would not have the same drives and needs
as bodies in this world.
This last point brings up the question of
the rabbinic attitude towards sexuality. In
general, the rabbis affirmed sexuality and
held that all men must marry and father
children (the law in this case is only directed
towards men). Men also have an additional
obligation to give sexual pleasure to their
wives. At the same time, the rabbis had
ambivalent feelings about male sexuality.
Their position seemed to be that the sexual
desires of the body are legitimate and even
holy, but only if the sexual act is performed
with the proper restraint. Sex must be
potentially procreative, so that, for example,
masturbation is labeled a capital crime,
something unknown to the Bible. While
the rabbis never endorsed celibacy, as did
the Christian Church fathers, there is strong
evidence that they were also attracted by
scholarly abstinence. In some texts, the
study of Torah (biblical and rabbinic law) is
invested with eroticism, suggesting that
intellectual activity might compete with
the desires of the body.
Rabbinic law extended biblical law into
virtually every area of life. As such, it gov-
erned almost every aspect and function
of the body, from eating to sex. Although
rabbinic literature is generally motivated
by interpretation of the law, which the rab¬
bis believed was revealed at Mt. Sinai, it
also contains a great deal of medical spec¬
ulation. For example, the rabbis devoted
considerable attention to trying to under¬
stand female reproductive physiology and
their theories often owed much to late
antique medicine. They were particularly
concerned with the details of women's
menstrual cycle, since the law prohibited
sexual relations during menstruation. They
developed a whole science of menstrual
blood to distinguish between healthy and
pathological female bleeding. Reading rab¬
binic literature confirms the observation
(meant to be derogatory) of the first-cen¬
tury Christian, Paul, that Judaism is truly
"Israel of the flesh."
Proper intention
In the Middle Ages, the rabbinic insistence
on the unity of body and soul began to
break down under the influence of Greek
philosophers such as Aristotle and Ploti-
nus, who became known to Jewish
thinkers through the Arabs. Jewish
philosophers, such as Moses Maimonides
(1 135-1204), often denigrated the body as
representing the purely material. It is the
soul that gives form to matter and there¬
fore invests it with holiness. Maimonides
was particularly harsh in denouncing sex¬
uality as a negative impulse of the material
i Jewish marriage in Paris
(France).
THE UNESCO I OURIERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
body. He condemned the sense of touch
as the lowest of all human faculties. Yet
Maimonides was also a physician and
expounder of Jewish law. Both of these
disciplines taught him the importance of
cultivating the body and attending to its
needs and desires. Maimonides therefore
tried to strike a middle ground between
his philosophical asceticism and the bod¬
ily affirmations of medicine and Jewish
law. His doctrine with respect to the body
emphasized moderation and self-control.
A different school of thought in the
Jewish Middle Ages was the mystical
(often called "Kabbalah"). The mystics or
Kabbalists sometimes began their specu¬
lations in explicit rejection of Maimonides.
An important thirteenth-century text
called the Iggeret ha-Kodesh ("Letter of
Holiness") starts off by criticizing Mai¬
monides' stand on the body. How could
the sense of touch be evil, since God had
created the body and called it "good"? In
particular, the text insists that Adam and
Eve had had sexual relations in the Gar¬
den of Eden and had done so without any
sinful pleasure (this was a theme that could
be found in both early rabbinic and Chris¬
tian literature). But, as much as the "Letter
of Holiness" sought to affirm the body, it
also placed severe limitations on it. If men
and women engaged in sexual relations
without the proper intention, then the
purely physical act became a form of idol¬
atry.
"The Letter of Holiness" placed such
enormous importance on correct inten-
tionality because of the Kabbalistic theol¬
ogy which underlay it. According to this
mystical tradition, God himself consists
of male and female elements, which are
engaged in a kind of spiritual intercourse.
Proper human sexuality can be directed
towards God by the correct thoughts. In
this way, human sexual relations actually
cause the male and female elements in God
to unite sexually. Improper sexuality or
improper thoughts cause these elements
to break apart. Thus, human sexuality has
cosmic consequences.
In a similar way, all human activities can
magically influence God. The Kabbalists
describe God in anthropomorphic terms,
that is, as having a body just like a human
body. This divine body lacks materiality:
we might call it a "spiritual" body. But since
God's body is the model for human bod¬
ies, the way in which human beings use
their bodies can affect God's body. If
human beings remain trapped in their
material, bodily desires, then they subvert
the spirituality of God's body. The task of
humans is to spiritualize their material bod¬
ies and bring them into harmony with the
divine body.
I The resurrection of the body
This doctrine from the thirteenth century
was to have tremendous implications for
Jewish thought in the subsequent cen¬
turies. In the eighteenth century, a pietis-
tic Jewish movement in Poland, called
Hasidism, created a popular theology
based on the earlier Kabbalah. The
Hasidim held that every action of the body
might be turned into a spiritual act since
ev erything in the material world contains
a spark of the divine.
Some Hasidic doctrines celebrated the
material world and spoke of worshipping
God through the material. A common
Hasidic teaching held, for example, that
even the simple act of eating or drinking
could be transformed into the worship of
God with the proper intentionality. Oth¬
ers, on the other hand, saw the purpose of
the worship of God as emptying the mate¬
rial of its divinity. This latter approach,
sometimes termed "the annihilation of the
material," led to a much more ascetic
THE UNESCO COLIRIERB APRIL 1997 M
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
approach to the body, particularly in the
realm of sexuality. For these Hasidic mas¬
ters, any sexual act that involved pleasure
was sinful.
The eighteenth century also witnessed
the emergence of a movement of Jewish
enlightenment which challenged the world
of rabbinic and medieval Judaism. Part of
the critique of the Jewish enlighteners
focused on the treatment of the body in
traditional Judaism. For example, they
argued that the practice of early marriage,
which was common among the Jews of
eastern Europe, led to disease and bodily
weakness. They also wished to reform the
way Jews dressed to make them look
more "European". And they sought to
transform traditional attitudes towards
sexuality into something like emerging
bourgeois values.
A much more radical critique of tradi¬
tional attitudes towards the body devel¬
oped at the end of the nineteenth century
among the inheritors of the Jewish enlight¬
enment. With the rise of European anti-
semitism and the perceived failure of Jew¬
ish emancipation, secular Jewish thinkers
turned towards nationalist solutions of the
Jewish question. These nationalists adopted
and extended the earlier Enlightenment
critique of traditional Judaism. Traditional
Judaism, they argued, had denigrated the
body in favour of pure spirituality and, as a
result, Jews had become physically weak
and politically impotent. They wished to
return bodily vigour to the Jews by creat
ing what the Zionist ideologue Max Nordau
called "muscular Judaism." Following the
fashionable medical diagnosis of the time,
Jews were considered "neurasthenics"
(victims of a disorder of the nerves). The
only way to cure this nervous disease was
to strengthen the muscles. Consequently,
a whole movement of Jewish gymnastic
and sporting clubs developed to transform
the Jewish body.
The Zionists took this critique one step
further by insisting that the only real way
to transform the Jewish body was to trans¬
plant it to the soil of Palestine. Only in a
Jewish society based on agriculture rather
than petty commerce (the typical occu¬
pation of the European Jews) could Jews
become physically strong. This nationalist
ideal was based on a mythic vision of the
healthy Jews of the Bible, as opposed to
the weak and diseased Jews of the Dias¬
pora, but it was equally inspired by other
European nationalisms, which also
engaged in a cult of the body.
One might say that, far from negating
Jewish tradition, this secular nationalism
unconsciously continued a persistent motif
in historical Judaism: the centrality of the
body. From the Bible, to rabbinic litera¬
ture, medieval philosophy and mysticism,
the body in all of its facets has played a cru¬
cial role in Jewish thought, at times affirmed
and at others denied, but never ignored. In
the final analysis, the "people of the book"
can never be divorced from the "people
of the body."
In Cameroon, right, as in
other parts of Africa, masks,
costumes and symbolic
objects are widely used in
traditional ceremonies.
rt traditional Friday evening
Jewish family meal In Hadera
(Israel).
W THE UNESCO LAURIER« APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
language ofits own
BY MANGA BEKOMBOPRISO
The body is itself
a medium of
expression in
African societies
based on the oral
tradition
Africans regard the body (nyólo,
nyama) as a "full" object because
of the organs and substances it
J envelops and of which it is the
overall expression. The idea of the "body-
in-itself", externalized and observed from
the outside, appears in certain linguistic
expressions: a person who watches his or
her body in action sees it tremble {nyólo e
ma sówá mbá: body trembles in me), forces
it to sustain an effort {swè nyólo: force
body), sacrifices it through suicide {bwd
nyólo: kill body), preserves it from danger
{sunga nyólo: save body). To communicate
with his or her body, a person puts it to the
test {senga nyólo: feel body) and gets it to
relax {bôbisè nyólo, relax, loosen body).
Despite the importance of its media¬
tion function, this externalized body is a
precarious secondary organism which is
consigned to oblivion when it ceases to
be driven by the forces around it. It is not
the body that thinks but the I (Na); nor
does it dream, that is the function of the
r 25THE UNESCO COURIER» APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Self {Mbâ), for which the body is merely
a physical envelope. In African societies
where the oral tradition predominates, the
body is a product of the spoken word, and
as such it is itself a medium of expression.
This is particularly evident in African
sculpture, which largely consists of depic¬
tions of the body, sometimes wearing a
mask, sometimes without. These sculp¬
tures always have a meaning. Whereas the
body is never represented in order to
serve as a cult object or to demonstrate a
particular aesthetic, in African masks and
statuary it expresses an idea, a desire, a des¬
tiny. It reveals a phenomenon, designates
a thing, issues an instruction or a taboo.
As a cultural construct, the body is seen
in terms of its constituent parts, which are
*,
clearly differentiated from each other. Each
part has a place and a function whose impor¬
tance varies depending on the context in
which it is perceived and the value attached
to the objects with which it is associated.
I Good and bad blood
The body's symbolism is organized round
its external parts, which occupy space, and
its internal parts the hard, soft or fluid
substances whose continual interaction
generates life-giving energy. In some parts
of Africa, quality of blood reflects the
body's amount of efficient energy. In order
to maximize this energy the blood is
"washed" by absorbing medicines, and if
it has been rashly tainted some of it is
extracted from the body. Blood brings
26
M fertility statuette from
northern Cameroon.
G DagliOrli, Pans
THE UNESCO ^ÎURIIERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
good or bad luck depending on whether it
is "good" or "bad". It is the "breath of life",
the "life force", which may be attacked,
topped up and strengthened by the med¬
icine man, his opponent, the soothsayer
and the healer. Blood also has a unifying
quality that comes into play when oath-
takers exchange a little of their blood and
absorb it under the watchful supervision
of ancestors who are keepers of the law. In
this instance, blood-sharing is more
important than verbal promises, for
although promises are binding, the
exchange of blood guarantees that they
will be kept. At weddings, joint con¬
sumption of the blood of a sacrificed ani¬
mal sets the seal on lasting solidarity
between bride and bridegroom.
Head andfoot
During a chief's consecration ritual in
southern Cameroon a woman over child-
bearing age squirts purifying water on the
chief's feet at regular intervals, while mak¬
ing a recitation in which the words sángó
(father, master), nginya (strength) and
bolódí (power and fullness) are many
times repeated. This is because feet are in
almost constant contact with the earth of
the village, which is as "pure" as the water
and the plants that grow from it, as well as
being the home of the omniscient ances¬
tors who want everything in society to be
as it should be. Feet symbolize putting
down roots, the time-honoured presence
of ancestors and the power that springs
from the action of a chief.
As the location of the intellect, the head
is regarded as a microcosm, as a body-and-
soul reproduction of the person and the
"tool" that connects him or her to the cos
mos. Because of this, the head is used in
separation rituals. When members of the
lineage leave the village to make their for¬
tune far away, they are like a baby being
weaned from its mother's breast. Both
migrants and babies are bathed and their
skulls are ritually anointed.
M double-faced helmet mask
from western Cameroon. It Is
designed to regulate the social
order.
> CpuTHE UNESCO lOURIERB APRIL 1997
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
FROM PELFHOOD
TO P ALVATION
BY ROMAIN MAITRA In Hindu thought the body is a finely
tuned instrument always threatened with disharmony
Mn 18th-century Indian miniature from Rajasthan
showing the subtle body.
9JHI, ..¿tit* -,#...,*
Tun i^Mhi^wMmw diMí^ín,
r n the Indian tradition, the human body
is viewed as integrating a complex vari¬
ety of mental and physical processes.
L It is part of a body-mind continuum
that is regarded as the instrument of a Self
(Atman) or Soul that is essentially transcen¬
dent and free of its embodied condition.
The ancient Hindu scriptures, the Upan-
ishads, contain many passages on the body-
mind complex and its relation to the Atman.
The body-mind complex arises from the
ultimate Atman from which the universe
came into being: "from Him are born life,
mind, the sense organs and also ether, wind,
fire, water and earth." In the Upanishadis
the body is also described as "foul-smelling
and insubstantial", but another sacred
Hindu text, the Bhagavad Gita, describes
it as the chosen vehicle of "the perpetual,
imperishable and incomprehensible body-
dweller" in which the Atman breathes and
from which it radiates.
Later systems of Hindu philosophy
assign to each person two bodies an exte¬
rior or "gross body" and an interior or
"subtle body". Perhaps Indian philoso¬
phers conceived of the existence of a sub¬
tle body in order to make intelligible the
process of metempsychosis or transmi¬
gration of the soul after death. The Vedanta,
one of the main philosophical schools of
28 > GuTHE UNESCO lOURIERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
In the Himalayas, a yogi and a
young Buddhist monk practise
concentration. Hinduism, regards this subtle body as
incorporating the senses of the body
both perceptive and active and of mind,
intellect and sensation.
In this Hindu conception, the subtle
body links together physiological and psy¬
chological processes. It is believed to be
made up of a web of numerous arteries
{nadis) through which the vital energy cir¬
culates, and of a few centres called wheels
{cakras), receptacles {adharas) and knots
{granthis), where the arteries converge
and meet the nerves of the gross body.
The three principal arteries ida,pingala
and susumna extend along the spinal col¬
umn between the spot next to the anus,
the muladhar cakra, and the spot on top of
the skull, the brahmarandhra, where a
thousand-petaled white lotus blossoms.
However, the cakra patterns between
these two spots vary according to differ¬
ent theological systems and usually cor¬
respond to psychosomatic sites experi¬
enced during yogic practices.
I A microcosm ofthe universe
A vital goal of Tantra, basically a Hindu
(also Buddhist) system of esoteric prac¬
tices for attaining spiritual experiences and
the fulfilment of worldly desires, is to spir¬
itualize the human body which is consid¬
ered to be a microcosm of the universe.
Tantric discipline enables us to discover a
mystical geography in the subtle body.
The spinal cord represents the fictitious
Mount Meru. The three principal arteries
running along the left, the right and the
middle of the spine represent the three
sacred rivers, Ganga, Yamuna and Saras-
vati. The breathing process represents the
span of time. By awakening the female
force Sakti, lying dormant like a coiled ser¬
pent in the muladhar, and making it move
upward along the spinal cord to be united
with the male force Siva at the brah¬
marandhra, the yogi realizes the supreme
non-duality of the Self.
r 29
THE UNESCO ^_OURIER APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
In the theoretical construct of
Ayurveda "the science of long life"
life {ayus) arises due to association of body,
sensory capacities, mind and Self. The
gross, physical body is an arrangement of
the five elements which are present in
nature and are genetically transmitted
through the semen of the father and the
ovum and blood of the mother. They are
earth, water, fire, wind and space.
Wind {vayu), fire {tejas) and water {ap)
are fundamental to Ayurvedic biological
theory for they are considered as the prin¬
cipal components of life and movement.
Taken together, these elements generate a
nutrient fluid {rasa) that nourishes the
body as a whole.
Mn 18th-century Indian
miniature depicting kundallni
(from the Sanskrit kundala,
"coil" of rope), latent energy
colled like a serpent at the
base of the trunk in the subtle
body. The energy Is
"awakened" by certain yogic
disciplines.
i The three humours
Wind {vayu) is dry, light and soft, and indi¬
cates motion. It manifests itself as the
motor system of the organism which
includes respiration, swallowing, speak¬
ing, digestion, excretion, ejaculation, the
labour of childbirth and so on. Fire man¬
ifests itself as the energy system of the
organism, including bilious secretion
{pitta) of the liver and the "cooking"
process of the digestion, the colouring in
blood and complexion, and the energiz¬
ing of desire. Pitta is hot, bitter, oily fluid
of bluish colour. Water manifests itself as
the integrating system of the body, includ¬
ing phlegm {kaph), mucus, plasma and so
forth and holds together the limbs and tis¬
sues. Kaph is heavy, moist, unctuous and
white and is conveyed by air through the
vessels. According to the biological prin¬
ciple of Ayurveda, therefore, vayu, pitta
and kaph are the overall respiratory, diges¬
tive and integrative components of the
gross body, its three essential humours.
When these components are in balance
and harmony, they contribute to the health
of the organism, and when they are not,
they cause illnesses. Thus, the human
body exists in a state of precarious and
constantly threatened equilibrium, and
the task of the physician is to diagnose the
imbalances that occur in the person and
restore balance through treatment.
Ayurveda defines a healthy person as one
in whom there is equilibrium of the
humours and where the body substances
perform normal digestive and excretory
functions as well as gratifying the senses,
mind and soul as a result of living a pure life.
Impurity and bodily pollution are not
only the ultimate cause of much organic
illness, but also expose people to diabolic
affliction and cut them off from divine pro¬
tection. The state of the body, gross as well
as subtle, thus provides an index of the state
of the soul, the Self. The wealth of the yogi
is his two-fold body and it is by an absolute
mastery of it that he can achieve salvation.
The gross body is said to have three
possible fates: it can be eaten as carrion
"* THE UNESCO ^)UR.ER« APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
and reduced to excrement; it can be buried
and turned into maggots; or it can be burnt
and reduced to ashes. The putrefaction of
the body is regarded as particularly repel¬
lent by Hindus, and incineration is viewed
as the most acceptable fate since it is the
swiftest way of recycling the five elements
of which the body is composed. The body
particles of the dead return to be shared
with their kinsfolk and the soul is reborn.
A Hindu is never entirely new when born
and never entirely lost when dead.
religious cremation on the
banks of the Ganges near
Patna In northeastern India.
THE UNESCO ÇniRilERB APRIL 1997
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Some Islamic thinkers believe that cultivation of the
senses can lead to God
he garden ofdelights
BY ABDELWAHAB MEDDEB
According to the Book of the Lad¬
der of Mahomet, as the Prophet
was beginning his "night journey"
_ from Mecca to Jerusalem, a very
beautiful woman "clad in raiment of every
imaginable colour" called out to him. He
stopped and allowed her to draw near to
him, then went disdainfully on his way.
Whereupon his guide, the angel Gabriel,
told him that the woman with her garments
of many colours represented the world with
its manifold delights, and that "because you
waited for her, your people shall be granted
more solace and more delights than any
other people that has been or shall be."
This anecdote, taken from a medieval
work of fiction that was translated from
Arabic into Latin, Spanish and French in
the thirteenth century, has more to tell us
than any of the standard works of law or
theology. Islam had the reputation of being
the religion of enjoyment, a religion that
called upon its followers not to spurn
earthly pleasures but to delight in them as
God's blessed gift to humankind.
The promise held out by Islam to
believers seems to be that of a garden
overflowing with everything to gratify the
senses. This was the charge laid against
Islam in the inter-religious disputes that
raged in the Middle Ages, especially in Al-
Andalus (Muslim Spain). The late thir¬
teenth-century Catalan theologian Ramon
Llull, for instance, makes such charges in
his Book of the Three Sages, in which a
Jew, a Christian and a Muslim take turns in
vaunting the merits of their respective reli¬
gions to apagan.
Such enjoyment of earthly delights in
the name of God was, on the other hand,
much appreciated by nineteenth-century
Western writers and artists who visited
the East. This experience took them out¬
side of their Judaeo-Christian education,
which seemed either to repudiate the plea¬
sures of the flesh or to regard them as base
instincts that ought to be eliminated.
Reacting against the prudery prevailing in
their own countries, they saw in Islam an
alternative life-style, around which grew
the myth of an Orient where nihilism and
denial of the flesh were unknown.
In Ecce Homo, Nietzsche, who
acclaimed this worship of the body,
recalled that the first thing the Christians
did after recapturing Córdoba was to brick
up the city's 700 hammams. These bath¬
houses, which were the latter-day equiv¬
alent of the public baths of Roman Antiq¬
uity and which reflected the central place
accorded in Islam to the care of the body,
were seen by a Christian morality based on
asceticism, abstinence and penitence as
places of debauchery and depravity.
For their part, many writers succumbed
to the charms of Arab erotic literature. The
Thousand and One Nights had been well
known since the late seventeenth century,
but the French translation by Antoine Gal-
land had been expurgated, the crude or
downright pornographic passages being
toned down in keeping with the classical '
principle of decorum. The fact is that Arab
and Muslim authors were not afraid to write
about wild sexual abandon and the trans¬
ports of delight, which was why at the
beginning of the twentieth century Mardrus
thought it necessary to retranslate these
tales, in so doing even exaggerating their
sexual rhetoric.
32
THE UNESCO (OURIIERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
" I he Lovers", a detail from
a 19th-century Iranian
edition of the Thousand and
One Nights.
<$^*ij/</*hf^
y~f.u¿ ¡uiujti/ '^/^/^JW^^'
y¿C~*4tf,ü>f'ó¿/1 'Ci^ôûi o ¿(f¿s/W¿>)l
_ '
iL.S/. rS.
I * - - i. m
I
THEUNESCO ^)URIERB APRIL 1997 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Such exaggeration is a measure of the
spell cast by this different world, where
prudery was unknown and people made
love in the name of God. The fin-de-siè¬
cle aesthetes' ideas of the sensualism of
the East and of Islam was confirmed by
their discovery of The Perfumed Garden,
an erotic treatise that was written in the
fourteenth century by a theologian born in
southern Tunisia, the famous Shaykh
Nefzawi, and the anonymous nineteenth-
century French translation of which is
reputed to have been reworked by Guy
de Maupassant.
Their ideas were in fact scarcely exag¬
gerated: the Murcia-born Andalusian
M.lusic and dancing. An
illustration from a 17th-
century anthology of Persian
poetry.
theosopher Ibn al-Arabi (1165-1240)
believed that those of a perspicacious mind
could discern revelations behind all forms
of beauty and derive enjoyment from
them, and that such was the secret of spir¬
itual experience. Did not the Hadith pro¬
claim that "God is beautiful and He loves
beauty"? Within each thing of beauty there
lies concealed an image of God that the
individual may perceive through a lovely
woman, a handsome youth, a garment of
well-matched colours, a harmoniously
proportioned object, a stirring song, a well-
seasoned dish, architecture that creates a
musical interplay of light and shadow, a
courtyard where a tinkling fountain over-,
flows into its basin, or a bed of flowers in
a shady garden fragrant with the scents of
spring.
In short, the presence of God is to be
sought through the senses: all things that
appeal to the senses are ways whereby
God may be glimpsed and the mental
image of God may be formed. This con¬
ception may explain how it is that the prin¬
ciple of beauty finds its way into the most
prosaic objects in use in the most mun¬
dane circumstances, and it is perhaps
because of this belief in the immanence of
beauty that the decorative arts and crafts
flourished at that time.
Again according to Ibn al-Arabi, how¬
ever, it is in the carnal act itself that the
supreme revelation is granted. Through
the mystery of the female orgasm, through
its very excess, the individual is immersed
in the image of God. In the love-making of
two people, man and woman, the pres¬
ence of a third, God Himself, is thus made
manifest. This accounts for the extreme
importance Ibn al-Arabi attaches to phys¬
ical love: it is through physical love that
spiritual love is achieved, it is through the
sexual act, by the transmission of the elixir
of carnal pleasure, that humans rise to the
height of divine love. Ibn al-Arabi quotes
another tradition from the Hadith in sup¬
port of his interpretation: the Prophet said
"Three things have I loved in this world:
perfume, women and prayer". The shape
of things conducive to the gratification of
the senses and the call to fulfil the obliga¬
tion of worship are thus set forth side by
side in Holy Writ.
THE
UNESCO lOURIERl APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
DOSSIER Body language
Often more eloquent than words, gestures constitute a rich medium of
expression that varies from culture to culture
Greeting
WIGGLING THE THUMB AND
	LITTLE FINGER	
Meaning: Friendly greeting.
Description: The arm is raised, and then the
hand ¡s wiggled gently with the thumb and
little finger extended and the other fingers
curled.
Locality: The Hawaiian Islands
RUBBING NOSES
Meaning: Friendly greeting.
Description: The nose-tip is brought into
contact with the nose-tip of another
person or with another part of his/her
head.
Locality: New Zealand (Maoris), Finland
(Lapps) and North Africa and the Middle
East (Bedouin). Also among Malays,
Polynesians, Melanesians and Inuit.
SLAP ON THE SHOULDER
Meaning: Greeting
Description: When two people meet, they
slap each other playfully on the shoulder.
Locality: Inuit communities.
HANDS TOGETHER
Meaning: Greeting
Description: Palms joined, fingers pointing
upwards, in front of the chest. Usually
accompanied with a slight bow of the head.
Locality: Asia.
RISING HANDSHAKE
Meaning: Greeting.
Description: After a traditional handshake
the clasped right hands are raised high in the
air where they are disengaged.
Locality: Africa, especially among the Bantu.
BLOWING A KISS WITH THE
FINGERTIPS	
Meaning: Greeting
Description: The fingertips brush the lips,
and the hand is then moved away from the
mouth as the bunched fingers are spread.
Locality: Especially widespread on the
Mediterranean islands of Malta, Sicily,
Sardinia and Corfu. Also common in Portugal
(but not Spain) and in Sweden (but not
Denmark).
THE UNESCO tOURIER ACRIL 1997
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Directional signals
BECKONING HAND (1)
Meaning: Come here!
Description: Upward movements
of the hand with the palm up.
Locality: British Isles, Scandinavia,
Netherlands, Belgium, Germany,
Austria, France and the former
Yugoslavia.
BECKONING HAND (2)
Meaning: Come here!
Description: Downward
movements of the hand, with the
palm down.
Locality: Spain, Portugal, Italy,
Malta, Tunisia, Greece and Turkey.
BECKONING FINGERS
Meaning: Come here!
Description: The arm is extended towards the person being called
palm downwards, the wrist slightly bent. Then the fingers are
fluttered. ^~>
Locality: Japan
BECKONING HEAD
Meaning: Come here!
Description: The head is jerked
backwards.
Locality: Widespread.
POINTING LIPS
Meaning: To indicate a direction.
Description: The lips are protruded
in a certain direction, the head often
being slightly turned in the same
direction.
Locality: The Philippines, parts of
South and Central America, certain
African tribes and among the
Amerindians.
POINTING CHIN
Meaning: Over there.
Description: The chin is thrust briefly in a
particular direction.
Locality: Widespread.
Source: Bodytalk, The Meaning of Human
Gestures, Desmond Morris, Crown Trade
Paperbacks, New York, 1994.
More than 600 gestures are illustrated,
described and explained in this remarkable guide
to human gestures from all around the world.
36 THE UNESCO ^)URIER« APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
"No*signé
HAND FAN
Meaning: No.
Description: The open right hand, palm turned to
the left, is moved back and forth in front of the
face, like a fan.
Locality: Japan.
EYEBROW MOVEMENT
Meaning: No!
Description: The eyebrows are raised and
lowered rapidly once. The facial expression
is usually serious or annoyed.
Locality: Greece
FLICKING
THE CHIN
Meaning: No!
Description: The fingers brush the
chin several times, and the head is
tilted backwards.
Locality: Italy south of Naples,
Sicily and Sardinia. Also common In
Malta and Corfu.
HEAD TOSSING (1)
Meaning: No!
Description: The head ¡stilted
vigorously backwards.
Locality: Most Arab cultures.
Known in Europe as the "Greek
no", it is widespread in Turkey,
Corfu, Malta, Sicily and southern
Italy.
HEAD TOSSING (2)
Meaning: Yes!
Description: As no. 1, left.
Locality: Ethiopia.
NOSE SCREW (1)
Meaning: Drunk.
Description: The thumb and the
index finger circle the nose, and the
hand is then screwed round through
an arc.
\ Locality. France.
NOSE^CREW (2)
Meaning: Nevermind!
Description: As no. 1, left.
Locality: East Africa.
FOREFINGERS
TOGETHER (1)
Meaning: Agreement.
Description: The two index fingers
are placed side by side.
Locality: Middle East.
INDEX FINGERS
TOGETHER (2)
Meaning: Close friendship.
Description: As no. 1, left.
Locality: North Africa
) ^OURI!ER« APRIL 1997
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
commentary Federico Mayor
cience
and society (2)
During the Cold War years, the value of science and
technology tended to be construed in terms of its mili¬
tary and economic applications. While this enabled research in
many specialities to enjoy a golden age of generous funding in
some countries, it tended to widen the gap between the rich and
the poor nations. The ending of this chapter of history has
brought an opportunity to base civilization on peace, not on war.
The question is whether we are as ready to pay the price of
peace as we were to 2>ay the price of war.
The close co-operation between science and government
that is needed can flourish only in free societies, so it is encour¬
aging to observe the growth of democracy in recent years in
all parts of the world. The twentieth century has so far shown
us both the apogee and the demise of the totalitarian state. It
was Erich Fromm who described totalitarianism as "the escape
from freedom". Totalitarianism promised in exchange for the
surrender of personal freedom a guaranteed utopia that
would justify the sufferings of the present. In the march
towards this Utopia, science and technology were given a van¬
guard role.
For a while, and so long as technology remained predictable,
centrally planned economies demonstrated a brutal ability to
ape the successes achieved elsewhere, and even exceed them.
Many Western intellectuals who visited the Soviet Union in the
1930s compared the purposive activity there with the apathy
of the democracies and made no secret of their preference. In
a world dominated by coal and steel, the command economy did
achieve some successes, at the cost of great human misery.
But when the focus of development shifted to industries based
on new knowledge in electronics, biology and biotechnology,
the price of suppressing free thought and action had to be
paid. The centrally planned economies, for all their claims to
be "scientific", lost the battle because they used science as an
instrument, obscuring its true nature. The lesson is that nobody,
38
however powerful or well informed, can know for certain which
scientific ideas will shape the world of tomorrow. Only by allow¬
ing scientists the freedom of action logo where their curiosity
leads can we be sure that science will flourish and our economies
will flourish with it.
Beyond the market
The problems faced by societies in transition from oppression
cannot be solved simply by appeals to the free market, effec¬
tive as it has so often proved to be. The free market the so-
called Invisible Hand is no guarantee of meeting long-term
needs or of ensuring the best use of human resources. The
question is whether we possess adequate knowledge to devise
sound methods of moving from centrally planned economies to
a freer but nonetheless humane market. A longer-term view,
based on investing now to prevent future catastrophes, is
required, both for practical and ethical reasons. This is in my
view most important, for those who have been suffering under
the shadow of oppression or extreme poverty will be very dis¬
appointed if we offer them only the rules of the free market.
The success of science is based upon shared knowledge.
Only by open publication of results and the mutual testing of
ideas can we be sure that we are moving along the right lines.
The extent to which knowledge is shared, both within nations
and between nations, will determine our ultimate success. And
yet the community at large, all too often including its leaders, '
remains years behind in its understanding of the directions in
which science is moving.
Scientific illiteracy is one of the key issues we face. Elected
leaders have neither the time nor the resources to grasp biolog¬
ical or environmental complexity, although they may be required
to make decisions that will determine the educational, scien¬
tific and ecological priorities for years to come. Voters are unable
to make rational decisions on issues that require basic scien-
THE UNESCO ^>URI1ER« ARR1L 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
tifie knowledge, because all too often they have never been pro¬
vided with that knowledge. An unprepared community cannot
truly govern itself or plan for its children's future.
We live in a society that depends on science and technology
without really understanding it. When basic scientific knowl¬
edge was tested in one survey, it was found that less than a
third of Britons and 43 per cent of Americans knew that elec¬
trons are smaller than atoms. Almost a third of the British
respondents, and a quarter of the American ones, believed that
antibiotics kill viruses as well as bacteria. I am not seeking
here to be critical of any particular nation: there is no reason
to suppose that these results would be any different if the
surveys had been conducted elsewhere.
Achieving scientific literacy
Nor is there anything new about antipathy to and ignorance of
science and technology. We tend to think of the nineteenth cen¬
tury as a period of confident expansion, ruled by engineers. But
even then a strong undercurrent of opposition thrived. It is easy
to laugh at the Duke of Wellington, who opposed the develop¬
ment of railways because, he said, "they would enable the lower
orders to go uselessly wandering about the country". But he
wasn't alone. The French novelist Gustave Haubert listed the
four greatest misdeeds of modern civilization as "railways, fac¬
tories, chemists and mathematicians". Yet he happily used the
railway as a convenient way of meeting his friend Louise Colet,
who lived in Paris, while he lived near Bouen.
Many of us harbour the same double standard: we enjoy
the benefits of technology while remaining largely ignorant of
its inner workings. We have a society where, in Martin Wciner's
words, there is outward acceptance of modernity without inner
conviction. Few people know, or very much care, what goes on
under the bonnets of their cars, or at the other end of the
high-tension cables that supply their houses with electricity.
To them it is all a bit of a conjuring trick.
It is clearly impossible to provide every person with a pro¬
found understanding of all the important and controversial
areas of science and technology; impossible because even sci¬
entists themselves do not possess it. A cell biologist does not
understand particle physics; a metallurgist is unlikely to have
more than a limited grasp of genetics; and hardly anybody
understands the wonderful world of high mathematics. What
singles out scientists and engineers is not their knowledge of
fields other than their own, but the conviction that they could
understand these other subjects if they wanted to, a confi¬
dence that is not generally shared by non-scientists.
This is the confidence we must try to spread more widely. The
evidence is that when scientific ideas address people's concerns
and interests, they show an impressive ability to locate infor¬
mation and translate it into forms they find useful. An interest¬
ing example of this is the annual Aids conferences, ten of which
have now been held since the disease first challenged the scien¬
tific community to find an answer in the mid-1980s. While osten¬
sibly gatherings to discuss research in progress, the conferences
also involve many people who are HIV-positive, or who care for
Aids sufferers. These people are not scientists, but because of
the immediacy of the issues for them, they rapidly become
familiar with all the latest research in the fields of virology and
immunology, two of the most difficult of scientific disciplines.
Aids activists make life very difficult for scientists, with their
sometimes unreasonable demands for faster progress. But they
also make the whole field more stimulating, and help to ensure
that research is focused on the real problems.
This gap between what scientists know and what the public
understands is one of the greatest threats to clear-sighted science
and public policy. In 1931 Albert Einstein said, "Concern for man
himself and his fate must always form the chief interest for all
technical endeavour . . . in order that the creations of our minds
shall be a blessing and not a curse to mankind. Never forget th is
is the midst of your diagrams and equations."
On the scientific side we in the laboratories and classrooms
must share in the blame for the lack of diffusion of our findings
and concerns through the communities in which we live. On the
other side of it, however, the political leadership local, national
and international must also bear the responsibility of leaving sci¬
ence in a ghetto of narrow specialities, despite its central impor¬
tance in the world around us. The responsibility for scientific illit¬
eracy is shared and the solution to a continued state of chronic
ignorance or misplaced sensationalism must be found at the
meeting point between scientists and community leaders.
Three 'musts'
There are no easy answers, but it is clear that scientific liter¬
acy must try to provide at least three things.
First, a whole picture of the. different issues. Only a holis¬
tic approach can help us evaluate the different options open to
us. One example is that of energy sources: the costs and risks
of a power station are evaluated by most economists as if coal
were a renewable resource, picked from the tree like an orange.
Coal, however, is not renewable. Here are two more examjdes.
Can we seriously address the problems of developi ng countries
without taking into account the terms of an equitable inter¬
national trade? Can we try to improve the education of rural
women without providing the villages with wells and drills for
obtaining a pure water supply?
Secondly, it also means a far-sighted vision, bearingin mind
that in all the most important questions the most fragile and
ephemeral factor biologically, at least is the decision-maker.
Mortality is part of human existence, but we must learn to
think ahead for the intergenerational human rights of our chil¬
dren and their children.
Thirdly, we need a historical and global perspective, in
order not to forget that there is a past which has forged our own
behaviour and which, when consciously understood, can be
used to changed our ways of being. Nothing is determined by
some mechanical "logic" of history: everything depends on
what we do in the here and now. This is the legacy we can give
to our descendants.
THE UNESCO lOURIERB APRIL 1997
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
HERITAGE
AHIPOUNAMU
by Ann-Marie Johnson
Extraordinary flora and fauna flourish in Southwest New Zealand, one of the
world's most spectacular wilderness areas, which was placed on the World
Heritage List in 1990.
The Fox glacier, on
the western slopes of
the Southern Alps.
Maori people see more than
I a mountain when they look
at the snow-covered heights of
New Zealand's highest peak.
Members of the Ngai Tahu tribe
see their ancestor, Aoraki, first
born son of Raid, the Sky Parent.
In mythical times, Aoraki was
shipwrecked after his canoe over¬
turned as he sailed in the South
Pacific. Trying to save themselves,
he and bis crew clambered to the
high side of the hull . . . and
remained there for eternity.
Today, the canoe forms the South
Island of New Zealand, while
Aoraki and his crew, still clinging
to the hull, have become the great
mountain chain known as the
Southern Alps.
In due course, Aoraki's son,
Tuterakiwhanoa, came searching
for his father. Finding the remains
of the shipwreck had turned to
stone, he began to reshape it into
a suitable home for his human
descendants. Other atua (demi¬
gods) with skills in landscaping,
fisheries, birds and horticulture
helped him, creating the South
Island eventually inhabited by the
Ngai Tahu.
The results of their ancestors'
labours can be seen today in one of
the world's most spectacular and
pristine wilderness areas, south¬
west New Zealand, known in
Maori as Te Wahipounamu. Since
the atua created this vast region,
man has had virtually no impact on
it. In fact, no humans at all lived
there until about 1,000 years ago.
For millennia, the only sounds to
be beard were the rustling of
leaves, the rushing water of moun¬
tain streams and birdsong echo¬
ing through the densely luxuriant
dark-green bush. In the absence
of predatory mammals, plants did
not need to develop defence mech¬
anisms, some birds lost the power
to fly and did not develop the
bright plumage seen in the birds
of more dangerous countries.
Unique species evolved, their
development hindered only by the
effects of the climate.
THE PLACE OFTHE GREENSTONE
When the Maori arrived, they
found a land rich in resources they
could use to sustain their exis¬
tence and around which they
could build their culture. Abun¬
dant birds and fish provided food,
the bush gave them timber. But
the most valuable prize was hewn
from the rock of Aoraki's mythical
canoe and was reflected in the
name the Maori gave the region:
Te Wahipounamu, or the place of
the greenstone.
Creenstone (nephrite) was the
most precious of all stone to the
Maori. It was used for tools,
weapons and ornaments, and in
some forms is believed to hav e spir-
itual force. It was certainly the
most important item the Ngai
40 THE UNESCO ^>URIER APRIL
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Tahu had to trade with other The Te Wahipounamu
, -i i .i r rr. w i wilderness includes
tribes, and the stone i rom Je Wahi-
several national
pounamu was spread throughout parks and nature
New Zealand. reserves. Above, Mt.
T i^j.-i .i i Cook National Park.
In 1642 the Dutch navigator
Abel Tasman became the first
European to sight Te Wahi¬
pounamu, but no one landed there
until the arrival of the English
explorer James Cook in 1773. He
and his crew spent six weeks in
Dusky Sound, clearing a small
part of the native forest to make
way for an astronomical observa¬
tory. The tree stumps left behind
can still be seen today.
But the first real effects of
<wm
European settlement were not felt
until more than twenty years later,
after sealers began to harvest the
fur seals found along the coast.
By 1820 the seal population had
been almost wiped out. Fortu¬
nately they were given legal pro¬
tection in 1ÎÎ75, and the popula¬
tion has since recovered to the
point where there are now thou¬
sands spread along the coastline.
Europeans were also largely
responsible for perhaps the most
devastating impact on the wilder¬
ness of Te Wahipounamu. The
introduction of browsing and
predatory mammals such as red
deer, the Australian brush-tailed
possum, rabbits and rodents
wrought havoc in an ecosystem ill-
equipped to defend itself against
such creatures. Several bird
species have become extinct,
while others are among the world's
most endangered. Some palatable
plants were eliminated from
accessible areas and severe dam¬
age occurred in many ¡daces.
But the untrained eye does not
notice such things. Te Wahi-
pounamu's remoteness and isola¬
tion have saved it from the worst
encroachments of human civiliza¬
tion, and there are still areas where
The kea {Nestor
notabllis), a parrot
endemic to New
Zealand, Is found in
the mountains of the
South Island.
A waterfall on one
of the many rivers
that run through
the forest.
THE UNESCO (^OURIERB APRIL I 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
H A G E
WPi?
human beings have never set foot.
The first major land-based explo¬
rations were carried out in the sec¬
ond half of the nineteenth century,
but a number of the remote valleys
were still considered to be unex¬
plored as late as the 1970s.
ALONE IN THE WILDERNESS
Today experienced trampers can
find huge expanses which offer
neither tracks nor huts nor any
other sign of human inhabitation,
giving them the opportunity to
i*evel in the rare and sometimes
frightening sense of complete soli¬
tude. With no roads, houses, traf¬
fic or noise, walkers easily find
themselves overwhelmed by their
insignificance in the midst of the
magnificent mountain and forest
scenery that surrounds them.
They are left to depend on their
own resources in the knowledge
that they are hours away from
outside help.
But less hardy or more gre¬
garious visitors can enjoy Te
Wahipounamu's wonders in a little
The kiwi (Aptéryx
australis), a
flightless bird with
rudimentary wings,
lives in New
Zealand's dense
forests. It nests on
the ground and lays
enormous eggs.
The rare and
endangered takahe
(Notornis Mantelli),
a flightless bird
living in the forests
of New Zealand's
South Island.
.'>*
more comfort. The world-famous
Milford Track offers guided or
independent walks of two to five
days through spectacular scenery,
as do several other less well-known
trails, such as the Routeburn,
Greenstone or Ilolyford tracks.
Numerous shorter walks, ranging
from thirty minutes to a full day,
are spread along the length of Te
Wahipounamu, giving safe and
easy access to the wilderness. Sev¬
eral of these walks have been
equipped with informative dis¬
plays to help explorers under¬
stand the surroundinglandforms,
wildlife or vegetation.
But such displays cannot tell
all there is to know about Te
Wahipounamu. The region's 2.6
million hectares are breathtaking
in the extent and variety of their
natural beauty. Forming fully a
tenth of New Zealand's entire
landmass, the area is united only
by its diversity. Changes in vege¬
tation and scenery which span
thousands of kilometres on the
continents are compressed into an
area only about 450 km long and
between 40 to 90 km wide.
The area contains New
Zealand's highest mountains,
longest glaciers, tallest forests,
wildest rivers and gorges, most
rugged coastline, deepest fjords
and lakes, and largest populations
of forest birds. It is home to the
world's largest buttercup, the Alt.
Cook Buttercup; possibly the
highest sea cliff, Mitre Peak; the
world's only alpine parrot, the
friendly but mischievous kea; and
the total wild population of the
rare takahe.
There are dozens ofbird species
in Te Wahipounamu, including
many found only in New Zealand.
Among the best known is the kea,
which shows no fear of intruders,
and in fact often seems to actively
seek contact with humans often
to their discomfort. Willi its strong
hooked beak, this inquisitive bird
can destroy sneakers left outside
overnight, canvas or vinyl bags and
anything else it decides to take an
interest in.
New Zealand's smallest bird,
the rifleman, lives in the region's
mountain forests, and the tiny
rock wren can be spotted in alpine
areas. One of New Zealand's few
alpine birds, the rock wren sur¬
vives the harsh mountain winters
by sheltering in openings within
the rock debris beneath the snow.
Further down the mountains, the
beautifully echoing song of the
aptly named bellbird, or kori-
mako, is commonly heard, and
careful observers can also see the
tui,bush robin, flocks of screech-'
ing kaka (forest parrot) and
kakariki (parakeet). Tawaki or
Fjordland crested penguins
inhabit parts of the coastline,
while about 50 pairs of the beau¬
tiful kotuku (white heron) regu¬
larly nest at the northern end of
the region. Although common in
other countries, the kotuku is
rare in New Zealand and has great
spiritual significance for the
Maori, who see it as a symbol of all
that is beautiful and rare.
SURVIVORS FROM A LOST CONTINENT
Scientists tell us that Te Wahi¬
pounamu is the best modern rep¬
resentation of the ancient flora and
fauna of Gondwanaland, the south¬
ern super-continent that broke up
to form New Zealand, South Amer¬
ica, India, Africa, Antarctica and
Australia. New Zealand broke off
80 to 100 million years ago before
the appearance of marsupials and
other mammals, and the country's
subsequent long isolation enabled
ancient life forms to survive to a
far greater extent than elsewhere.
The great forests of rimu, southern
beech and kahikatea are the clos¬
est links with Gondwanaland, as
are unique birds like the flightless
kiwi, which New Zealanders have
adopted as their national symbol.
The magnificent chain of the
Southern Alps lies along the
boundary of the Pacific and Indo-
Australian plates, two of the six
42
THE UNESCO tpURIER APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
gigantic ¡liâtes making up the
earth's crust. This is one of only
three places in the world where
a major tectonic plate boundary
can be found on land. Earth¬
quakes caused by the collision of
these two plates have helped New
Zealand gain its reputation as the
"Shaky isles", but the fault line
has also given rise to a dramatic
landscape of deep fjords and high
mountains.
The glaciers of Te Wahi¬
pounamu are also evidence of the
movements under the earth's sur¬
face. These glaciers, particularly
those named Fox and Franz-Josef,
were among New Zealand's first
tourist attractions for those
wealthy enough to undertake the
arduous trip into the wilderness.
But the movement of the glaciers ¡
is so rapid that visitors a century g
ago saw a different sight to those ü
we see today as both glaciers are |
2 to 3 km shorter than when they g
were first surveyed in the 1890s.
Fox Glacier is 13 km long, while
Franz-Josef is 10 km, and both
flow very quickly, averaging as
much as 1.5 metres a day,
although rates of up to 8 in a day
have been recorded. Nearby, the
28 km Tasman Glacier, which
flows from Alt. Cook (Aoraki), is
one of the longest glaciers in the
southern hemisphere.
The glaciers are very sensitive
to climatic changes, advancing
during periods of heavy snowfalls
and receding under less severe
Pancake Rocks,
Punakaiki.
A brush-tailed
opossum
[Trichosurus T.
Vulpécula).
weather conditions. However, Te
Wahipounamu's weather is rarely
extreme, even though the region
lies across one of the world's
windiest latitudes, the Roaring
Forties. The large amounts of
ocean surrounding New Zealand
moderate temperatures, so the
climate is temperate and avoids
major seasonal changes. The
Southern Alps form a barrier to
the prevailing moisture-laden
westerly winds coming off the Tas¬
man Sea, with the result that the
West Coast is subject to heavy and
sometimes violent rainstorms at
any time of the year. The coastal
lowlands receive 3,000 to 5,000
mm of rain a year and this level
rises with the terrain, so that the
western flank of the Southern
Alps can receive more than
10,000 mm a year, although
much of it falls as snow.
Today, the Ngai Tahu are not
the only people who have reason to
be grateful that Aoraki was ship¬
wrecked in an isolated part of the
South Pacific. Visitors from
around the world, as well as New
Zealaudcrs themselves, are increas¬
ingly discovering the magnificenc e
of this untouched ¡tart of the
world. Even in this age of easy
travel, Te Wahipounamu's remote¬
ness means that tourist operators
and administrators have had time
to benefit from the lessons learned
from the effects of uncontrolled
tourist development elsewhere.
Although recreational use of the
region is generally encouraged,
the activities that are available,
such as boating, fishing, hunting
and mountaineering, have little
impact on the environment.
Growing awareness of the
importance of conserving the
world's few remaining areas of
untouched wilderness ensures
that Te Wahipounamu will con¬
tinue to be preserved as far as pos¬
sible in its pristine state. If Tuter-
akiwhonoa ever returns to survey
his handiwork, he will not find Te
Wahipounamu very different from
the way he left it. I
> C?u RIERB APRIL 1997
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
GREEN WATCH
by France Bequette
"As the expression of the
direct affinity between civi¬
lization and nature, and as a place of
enjoyment suited to meditation or
repose, the garden thus acquires the
cosmic significance of an idealized
image of the world, a 'paradise' in the
etymological sense of the term, and
yet a testimony to a culture, a style,
an age, and often to the originality of
a creative artist." So says the Charter
of Florence, which was drawn up in
1981 by the International Commit¬
tee on Historic Gardens and Sites, a
specialist organ of ICOMOS, the Inter¬
national Council on Monuments and
Sites (see ¡tage 46).
Gardening is a universal art. In
the Bible the Garden of Eden was
created by God and tended by
Adam, a place of delight to which he
longed to return after he had been
expelled from it. In the Qur'an, par¬
adise is a garden rich in pastures,
fountains, trees and delicious fruit.
In the arid desert, verdant oases are
watering places that make life pos-
sihle. In China, the fabulous K'un-
lun mountains of the west, the gate¬
way to heaven, were festooned with
hanging gardens.
Unlike agriculture, which has a
utilitarian purpose, gardening imposes
a certain order on turbulent and
unpredictable nature. This is what
the park at Versailles has in common
with a Japanese garden. "A garden,"
writes Belgian horticultural specialist
René Pcchère, "is a composition. It is
always artificial. . . ."It is a mirror of
the society which creates it.
Places of power and holiness
History offers many examples of
rulers who wanted a magnificent
park to provide a setting for their
palaces and express their power. The
The gardens of the Alhambra,
Granada (Spain).
Greek historian and philosopher
Xenophon wrote admiringly of the
paradise garden designed and culti¬
vated by Cyrus the Younger (in
about 420 B.C.), king of Persia. Lo\e
of gardens was at the core of the
Persian world-view. Not only was gar¬
dening a part of the education of
princes, it was taught to all school¬
boys. Two hundred years earlier, one
of the seven wonders of the world,
the hanging gardens of Babylon,
were planted on stepped terraces by
Nebuchadrezzar II for his Persian-
born wife, who missed the gardens of
her native land.
Greece's rocky soil, warm climate
and lack of water were not very pro¬
pitious for gardening, and in any case
luxuriant pleasure gardens associated
with ¡lower and personal prestige
would probably not have gone down
well with a people enamoured of
democracy. Gymnasia (schools) were
established in Athenian parks for the
common good. Plato shared a garden
with his students and established the
Academy there. The sacred groves
familiar to the Greeks of Antiquity
were wildernesses where divinities
took refuge, and as a result were left
untouched by human hand.
THE UNESCO IpURIERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The gardens of
Versailles Palace
(France).
Egyptian gardens blended plea¬
sure with productivity (wine, fruit,
vegetables and papyrus). Exotic
trees and flowers were imported very
early on and enriched the country's
natural plantlife. Gardens were laid
out in geometric patterns imposed
by the presence of irrigation ditches.
A scale model of a garden with abun¬
dant plantlife, found in the tomb of
Meket-Re in Thebes (1700 B.C.),
shows a garden with a rectangular
layout, surrounded by high walls
that protected it from the desert
sands and the Nile flood.
In ancient Rome gardens were
made within the confines of villas.
This example was followed in
Europe during the Middle Ages. In
those troubled times city dwellers
planted their gardens inside rather
than outside the town walls, and
lords made gardens in the courtyards
of their castles, where women grew
vegetables and medicinal herbs, as
did monks in monastery gardens.
These enclosed places contrasted
with cemeteries, which at that time
were public meeting places where
behaviour was free and easy, if not
licentious. Located as they were next
to churches, cemeteries continued
until the 18th century lo enjoy their
medieval status as extra-territorial
zones where the right of asylum asso¬
ciated with the church building was
still enjoyed.
The Islamic heritage
In Spain, the Arabs began to create
pleasure gardens in the 8th century.
Thousands of them appeared in
Andalusia. The Moorish gardens of
Granada the Alhambra and the
Generalife are still among the most
beautiful in the world. In compli¬
ance with strict geometric patterns,
they were divided into four quar-
An entrant in a
contest for flower-
decorated
courtyards in
Córdoba (Spain).
ters, representing the four elements.
This pattern, often symbolically fea¬
tured on carpets, was also found
among the Moguls of India. In the
15th century the Muslim sultan
Tamberlaine (Timur-Lang) used it in
Samarkand. The vast extent of their
gardens gave his successors real con¬
trol of the land, and were invested
with divine power by making the
desert bloom.
In Italy during the same period
gardens acquired a reputation for
sensuality. They were places for cel¬
ebrations, friendly meetings and
intellectual and sexual freedom.
They provided an image of a well
tempered, well ordered universe in
an eternal spring. Water played the
major role in these Renaissance gar¬
dens. Carefully trimmed evergreen
shrubs were sometimes used as
mazes. Marble statuary from Antiq¬
uity had still not been dethroned by
flowers.
The triumph of geometry
Italian artists who travelled through
Europe inspired "French" gardens
where architecture took pride of
¡dace over nature. Very strict geo¬
metric perspectives were used to
show buildings to their best advan¬
tage. The gardens at Versailles,
designed by André Le Nôtre, were
inspired by the sun-symbol chosen
by King Louis XIV, the main axes
corresponding to the points of the
compass. Flower beds edged with
trimmed box hedges were planted.
Garden specialist Gabrielle van
Zuylen sees the influence of Ver¬
sailles at Blenheim Palace in Eng¬
land, in St. Petersburg (Russia), at
La Granja near Segovia (Spain) and in
Caserta near Naples (Italy). Le
> GuiTHE UNESCO loURiER APRIL 1997
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
rri Tmynww ftpmt mnM
irmono nct'i fli pu*i\ dlM l filo.»twnm.
Nôtre 's radiating garden jiaths even
served as inspiration for the town
plan of Washington D. C.
Towards the end of the 18th cen¬
tury, the French garden came to be
seen as too artificial and gave way to
the English landscaped park style.
Lovers of poetry and painting for¬
sook straight lines in favour of "nat¬
ural" landscapes composed of hills,
woods, ponds and waterfalls. The
Romantics liked their paintings to
include ruins and mausoleums. The
garden became a theatre set,
expressing the aspirations of 18th-
century man in search of knowledge.
Landscaped gardens:
the Désert de Retz
The Désert de Retz, some 20 kilo¬
metres west of Paris, is an astonish¬
ing example of this in France (the
word "désert" here being used to
designate an isolated, "deserted"
place). It is a landscaped garden
which François Racine de Monville
began to create on a 40-hectare site
in 1774.
In a vale in the heart of Marly
Forest, he built a house in the form
of an ancient ruined column 15
metres in diameter. Visitors enter
the park through a grotto which
leads them on a kind of initiatory
Detail from a 14th-century manuscript of
the Latin translation of a medical treatise
by the great Arab physician Abul Kasim
(Latin Albucasls), who lived in Córdoba in
the 10th century.
journey from the outside world into
the "Désert". The park, which has
an "English-style" layout, contains
an open theatre and 17 small struc¬
tures or "fabriques": an Egyptian-
style obelisk and pyramid, a temple
dedicated to the Greek god Pan and
a votive altar and a tomb evoking
ancient Rome. A Tartar tent stands
on an "Island of Happiness", and
beside a pond there is a Chinese
house with outhouses and an
enclosed garden, reflecting ideas of
China current in France at that time.
This high spot of the Enlighten¬
ment attracted visitors from all over
the world. Thomas Jefferson, for
example, architect and future Pres¬
ident of the United States, took
inspiration from it for the Univer¬
sity of Virginia in Charlottesville*.
Visionary film-maker Abel Gance
chose it as a setting for one of his
films. The surrealists were fasci¬
nated by its mystery.
Perhaps gardens are a synthesis
of all art forms. René Pechère
believes that a garden is "architec-
FURTHER READING:
/ Plants in Garden History,
Penelope Hobhouse,
Pavilion Books, 1992.
/ European Gardens,
ajournai published by The Historic
Gardens Foundation (London) as part of
the Council of Europe's Cultural Routes
Programme, Strasbourg (France).
In English and French.
/ Tous lesjardins du monde,
GabriellevanZuylen,
"Découvertes", Gallimard, 1994.
/ Jardins dessinés,
Grammaire desjardins,
René Pechère, editor.
Atelier d'art urbain, 1987.
ture by virtue of its composition;
sculpture via the art of landscaping;
painting via the effect of coloured
trees; music through the rhythms
of its composition; poetry, theatre
and even dance".
Our round-the-world garden tour
will be continued in the next issue.
* See Mr. Jefferson's Dream ¡louse by
Francis Lcary in the February 1997 issue
of the UmksCO Courier, "Radio, a future for
sound". Editor
i initiatives
The International Council
on Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS)
The International Council on Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS) was founded in 1965 at Warsaw (Poland),
as a result of the adoption the year before of the International Charter for the Conservation and Restora¬
tion of Monuments and Sites, widely known as the Venice Charter. It is the only international non-govern¬
mental organization that works to promote the application of theory, methodology and scientific techniques
to the conservation of monuments and sites. With IUCN (the World Conservation Union), ICOMOS advises
UNESCO on the nomination of new sites to the World Heritage List.
ICOMOS has 5,300 members in 88 countries. They include architects, art historians, archaeologists,
town-planners, engineers, librarians and administrators, and constitute ICOMOS National Committees in
their respective countries. ICOMOS has 15 international committees, specializing in fields such as
stained-glass windows, cave painting, and historic gardens and sites. Each y ear ICOMOS organizes sym¬
posia on technical themes, e.g. open-air museums, the restoration of cave complexes, the conservation
of wood, stone or adobe, photogrammetry, and the reconstitution of historic gardens.
ICOMOS has a well-stocked documentation centre (more than 20,000 documents) that is open to the
public. It produces a range of publications, including the proceedings of national and international sym¬
posia, technical dossiers, reviews {ICOMOS Bulletin, ICOMOS Information and Monumentum) and
bibliographical and thematic catalogues of all reference works available at the Documentation Centre.
In order to increase awareness of heritage conservation issues, ICOMOS and UNESCO have declared
18 April International Day for Monuments and Sites. I
ICOMOS publications may be ordered from:
ICOMOS Documentation Centre, 49-51, rue de la Fédération, 75015 Paris, France.
Tel.: (33) (0)1 45 67 67 70. Fax: (33) (0)1 45 66 06 22.
46
THE UNESCO ^)URI ERB APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
THE AEGEAN ISLANDS,
EUROPEAN
CULTURAL PARK
A number of island groups in the
Agean Sea are considered the cra¬
dle of Creek civilization and have
remained virtually unchanged for
centuries. With UNESCO support,
the Creek government has decided
to protect them, and to symboli¬
cally declare the Aegean Archi¬
pelago "Cultural Park of Europe".
Its pilot "Aegean Archipelago"
action programme will seek to man¬
age historical centres, modernize
museums and renovate and protect
monuments. The programme is
part of the World Decade for Cul¬
tural Development. I
RISING C02
HITS THE FOREST
Carbon dioxide (CO.,) levels in the
atmosphere have been rising since
the mid-19lh century as a result
of increased human activity. The
French National Institute for Agro¬
nomie Research (IN RA) has dis¬
covered that one effect of the rise
has been an abnormal increase in
the diameter of certain trees in
temperate forest ecosystems. For
example, the average diameter of
silver firs in the Vosges massif
(France) has increased by 160%
since 1850, and that of the pedun¬
culate oak in Lorraine by 55%.
The balance of certain forest
ecosystems may be affected, and
this is hound to have repercussions
on forest management and the tim¬
ber industry. I
TONGA TURNS
TO PUMPKINS
The Kingdom of Tonga, an island
nation in the Pacific with some
101,000 inhabitants, is trying hard
to improve its balance of pay ments.
After abandoning the idea of incin¬
erating millions of used tyres, which
would have had a disastrous effect
on air quality, Tongans turned to
growing pumpkins for sale to the
Japanese, who insist that their
pumpkins must be perfectly
shaped. Tonga is hoping eventually
to export 8,000 tons a year, but for
the moment the island kingdom is
groaning under the weight of imper¬
fectly shaped pumpkins. M
Compostela, the famous pilgrimage
centre in northwest Spain, has
recently been published in French.
Lavishly illustrated with photos and
maps, Guide européen des chemins
de Compostelle, by Jean liourdarias
and Michel Wasielewski (Fayard,
Paris, 1996), gives details of 9 dif¬
ferent routes starting in various
European countries.. H
For further in formation:
Cultural Houles Secretariat,
Council of Europe, 67075
Strasbourg Cedex, France.
Tel: (33) (0)3 88 4 135 37;
Fax: (33) (0)3 88 41 27 88.
NOT SO PROTECTED
SPECIES
The ortolan {Emberizia hortulana)
is a little bird in great danger. Its
numbers are thought to be declining
in Europe, where it is a protected
species covered by the European
Union's "Birds" Directive. But
although ortolan hunting is thus
strictly forbidden, the bird is threat¬
ened w ith extinction in France. Each
year an estimated 50,000 ortolans
are killed in southwest France as a
gastronomic delicacy. B
CONSERVATION
AND THE COMMUNITY
In Africa wildlife conservation
areas are often set up to the detri¬
ment of the local people, who are
not consulted. The World Wide
Fund for Nature (WWF) is trying
to avoid this error in Namibia. In
collaboration with a non-govern¬
mental organization, Integrated
Rural Development and Nature
Conservation (IRDNC), WWF has
established a network of commu¬
nity game guards who are directly
responsible for keeping tabs on
wild animals and poaching in their
areas, and, when wildlife numbers
permit, for organizing hunts and
distributing the meat. Villagers
are also being directly involved in
tourism so that they can benefit
from it while insisting on respect
for their culture. M
TERMINATING TERMITES
Ilicn Lam Cae temple (Soul Porch)
in Viet Nam, one of the monuments
in the Imperial City of Hue
included on the World Heritage
list in 1993, is infested with ter¬
mites. Insecticides used so far to
eradicate the 200-odd species of
white ants that are playing havoc
with the wooden buildings and the
crops outside have been highly
toxic but ineffective. To save the
Hue monuments, UNESCO has
appealed to a petro-rhcmiral com¬
pany that has developed a selec¬
tive insecticide which is effective in
small doses and does not pollute
water. H
EUROPE'S CULTURAL
ROUTES
The Council of Europe's Cultural
Routes programme, launched in
1987, seeks to throw light on the
itineraries along which Europe's
main religious, artistic, scientific,
technical and commercial trends
and movements have spread.
Themes chosen include Celtic
routes, monastic influence routes,
the silk routes, and rural habitat.
Within the framework of the pro¬
gramme, a guidebook devoted to
the routes leading to Santiago de
> ÇoURITHE UNESCO CO IER« APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
LISTENING ISABELLE LEYMARIE TALKS TO
RIDOBAYONNE
Versatile instrumentalist, band-leader and singer, Rido Bayonne is a musicaljack of all trades who blends Bantu, Cubanjazz, soul and funky
beats into a unique personal style that bursts with vitality. Born in the Congo, near Pointe-Noire, he became his country's most popular
drummer before moving to Paris, where he played with a number of international stars. Since 1985 he has performed in clubs and festivals
at the head of his big band, with which he recently made a recording. Gueule de Black.
M You play several instrumentsbass,
piano, guitar, the drums, African drums and
the marimba. Do you identify with any
4,
particular one?
Rido Bayonne: No, they all give me some¬
thing. I have a different relationship with
each one. Hut it was through playing the
bass that I became well known.
Your music has a strong beat. When you
compose, do you start with the beat, the
harmony, the melody or the structure?
R. B.: The heat. Because rhythm is life's
motor. Heartbeats, breathing and all
sounds are rhythm, even the silence that
goes with them. In this sense you can say
that everybody makes music without
realizing it. Hut don't forget that in
Africa the drum is the basic instrument.
In any ease, my music, is always chang¬
ing, and I nev er play my pieces the same
way twice.
Where do you get yourinspiration from?
R. B.: From many sources, but the most
important thing is that I have to feel emo¬
tionally involved. If I'm not, I can't com¬
pose. I am very receptive to what goes on
around me ... a conversation, a crying
child or even sounds like the clinking of
forks in a restaurant. Forks striking plates
can create rhythm and melody. When you
love music, you hear it everywhere!
Your music is also the result of various
traditions.
R. B.: Hesides my African cultural back¬
ground, I've learned from European liar-
48 r
** THE UNESCO COURIERS ATRIL 1997
monies and American music, especially
James Hrown, who has had a big influ¬
ence on me. Hut I was born in a cotton
field and I first heard the musicians of my
village during festivities and the impor¬
tant ritual ceremonies that marked birth,
initiation, marriage and death. We spoke
French at home, and I had a Western-
style education. Cultural intermixing is a
tremendous thing. My father had me lis¬
ten to Franco, a Congolese musician who
played a very important part in popular
African music, and also to Miles Davis,
Duke Ellington, European and American
popular music and Cuban music. Several
Congolese of my great-grandfather's gen¬
eration were sold into slavery in Cuba,
and my family has always been particu¬
larly fond of Cuban music.
Did you always want to be a musician?
R. B.: Always, despite my father's strong
opposition, lie didn't think music was a
real job. My late mother told me that I
was already beating time when I was still
in her belly. I am self-taught. As a child
I made my own bongos and guitars with
the spokes of bicycle wheels. I had no
idea how to tune a guitar, but that never
stopped me from playing. When I was
eighteen I started composing and har¬
monizing songs. Five years later I earned
a bit of money by playing in the Hantu
National band in Brazzaville a well
known band that had an excellent saxo¬
phone section. Then I played in
Cameroon with Mann Dibango*. In the
1960s, to keep my father happy, I stud
ied law for five years. When I finally gave
that up to devote myself full-time to
music, my father declared war on me,
although since then I have often helped
my family get by. My brothers, who
stayed in the Congo, are having a hard
time, even those who are doctors and
lawyers, because of the economic situa¬
tion. Eventually my father came to feel
happy about my success and even became
proud of me.
What kinds of bands have you played
with in France?
R. B.: At first I played in dance-halls in
Lyons, then Paris. There weren't many
blacks in France in the 1960s, and peo¬
ple often came to "see" the band because
there was a black in it. In fact up till
then I didn't even know I was black; I
was so caught up in my music that I never
realized!
What are you doing at the moment?
R. B.: I'm studying classical harmony at a
conservatory. I'm the oldest in the class.
I've got to be humble, because every day
I see that it is not musicians who are
great, but music. It transcends us. I'm
always amazed to see that everything in
music that I thought was innate can be
taught and learned. Recently I had fun
taking sixteen bars of Mozart's Requiem
and re-harmonizing them, changing the
melody and re-orchestrating them for
brass, voice, keyboard, piano and drums.
You can tell it's Mozart, but it is actually
a re-creation. Classical musicians are
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
afraid to innovate and certainly can't
improvise; whereas jazz and pop musi¬
cians are a lot freer and more open from
that point of view. As far as I'm concerned
only Mozart is qualified to play Mozart.
But for the past 200 years people have
made themselves play and replay his
works note for note as if they were pre¬
served in amber. Every musician has a
streak of madness. And to get inside your¬
self and find this streak of madness and
your own voice, you've got to be pos¬
sessed. I like Mozart's madness. He took
his obsessions to their very limit.
Your record Gueule de Black was
recorded at a concert in Bayonne.
R. B.: Yes, in 1995 an old dream of mine
came true. I'd long wanted to see the
city of Bayonne, and it was a revelation to
me. My family name, Bayonne, originated
with a Basque sailor who settled in the
Congo long ago and had children he
named after his home town. So I've got
Basque ancestors. Bayonne is a great
town with old buildings that have been
very well ¡»reserved. I gave an open-air
concert at a town celebration, and every¬
one there welcomed me with open arms.
It was incredible. That same year I
turned fifty. It was an opportunity to
bring together dozens of French-speak¬
ing musicians from all sorts of back¬
grounds. I am a happy man. Music still
gives me all I could ever hope for. M
* See the interview wilh Mann Dilnuigo
in I In; Umcsi.o ('«liner ("A world of iiuisir",
March 1991) Editor.
letters
to the editor
WORDS AND DEEDS
I have been a subscriber to the Cour/'erfor
several years and each month I read with
great interest Mr. Federico Mayor's "Com¬
mentary" column, which expresses in
straightforward terms ideas with which I
very broadly agree. In the December 1995
issue ("Troglodytes, a hidden world") Mr.
Mayor wrote that when Unesco speaks of
"the need for development with a human
face ... it is merely complying with one of
its basic precepts: the duty to act as the
conscience of the United Nations system".
I feel that the UN doesn't often listen to
the voice of its conscience, that behind a
façade of good intentions its different
organs and institutions too often seem
to act on behalf of a minority of rich and
powerful countries that increasingly exploit
the rest of the world. I also feel that,
instead of really working to construct a bet¬
ter world, institutions like the World Bank,
the International Monetary Fund and the
World Trade Organization are playing into
the hands of the rich nations and financiers
centred in the Clubs of Paris and London.
I was not convinced by what Mr. Ismail Ser-
ageldin said in his interview with the Courier
(June 1996) about the World Bank's activ¬
ities on behalf of the poor countries, since
there is widespread agreement that the
inequalities between poor and rich are
steadily growing.
I heartily approve of Unesco's goals in
the field of social development as
expressed on pages 30 and 31 of your
March 1995 issue ("Development, the
haves and the have-nots"). But how can
those who possess the necessary politi¬
cal and economic clout be persuaded to
take the decisions needed to achieve those
goals? To my mind, the main political play¬
ers have no desire to change things. How
can nations be made to respect the com¬
mitments they make at international meet¬
ings? Ought not some aspects of the work¬
ings of international organizations be
reviewed in the interests of more effective
democracy and greater justice?
Mr. Mayor also rightly condemns vio¬
lence and intolerance. I believe that the first
and most serious type of violence is the
institutional violence of public institutions
and states which, sometimes under the
cover of democracy and liberalism, create
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
letters to the editor
injustices, inequalities and inhuman living
conditions. Would it not be possible for
Unesco and the Unesco Courierto denounce
more openly the institutions, states and
organs of economic and financial power that
are leading humanity towards such a prob¬
lematic future?
Bernard Lucas
Aigrefeuille-sur-Maine (France)
" VORACIOUS MEGA-CITIES
After reading Mr. Federico Mayor's column
devoted to "The city, environment and cul¬
ture" in your May 1996 issue ("Silence") I
should like to make the following com¬
ments. I have spent thirty-five years of my
life working on town and country planning
in France and elsewhere, and my analysis
of the reasons for the rise of mega-cities dif¬
fers from that put forward by Mr. Mayor. In
my opinion these cities are the result of a
total lack of town and country planning pol¬
icy, a total lack of co-ordinated development
policy, and excessive economic laissez-faire
which is detrimental to the organization of
human needs into a hierarchy and to their
fulfillment.
Observation reveals that every city
has a "zone of attraction" of which it is the
centre because of its administrative, com¬
mercial, educational, sanitary and cultural
facilities. Mega-citles are monsters that
devour their environment. If a branch of
education is ever devoted to urban living,
it should teach that an economy based
on maximum profit should be replaced by
one based on an organized hierarchy of
needs, that a market economy should be
replaced by one based on service, and that
megalomania and individualistic gigantism
should be replaced by respect for the
human dimension and co-operation within
the community.
Robert Caillot
Lyons (France)
MISTAKEN IDENTITY
There was an error in the article about Colo¬
nia del Sacramento published in your Jan¬
uary 1997 issue ("Helping the poor to help
themselves"). While it is true that Admiral
William Brown is acclaimed in Uruguay for
his role in the struggle waged by Latin Amer¬
ican countries against the shackles of colo¬
nialism, he was actually in the service of
Argentina, where he is regarded as the
founder of the Argentine navy. It was
another Irishman, Pedro Campbell, who dis¬
tinguished himself in Uruguay's struggle
for independence by fighting under the ban¬
ner of General José Artigas and became a
Uruguayan national hero.
Victor N. Dodino
International Maritime Organization
(London)
OVERLOOKED!
The February 1997 issue of the Unesco
Courier devoted to radio ("Radio, a future
for sound") made interesting reading, but I
was disappointed that there was no men¬
tion of Slovenian broadcasting in the selec¬
tive list of key dates compiled by Prof.
Bernard Blm.
Here are a few dates to fill this gap:
1924: Marij Osana makes an experimental
radio broadcast with a transmitter made by
himself.
1926: The first experimental radio broad¬
cast of a concert is made in Ljubljana.
1941: Seven months after the destruction
of the Radio-Ljubljana station by the Ger¬
man air force, the Slovenian Liberation Fro n t
founds a clandestine station called Kricac
("The Yeller").
1944: Radio Liberation Front is founded in
the liberated territory of Bela Krajina.
1946: Creation of the Slovenian Radio
Board.
Joze Bergant
Deputy Director,
Transmitters and Communications
Department,
RTV Slovenia
Ljubljana (Slovenia)
AUTHORS
MAURO ROSI is a staff member of the Unesco
Publishing Office.
DAVID LE BRETON, a French sociologist,
teaches at the University of Human Sciences ¡n
Strasbourg (France). His published works
include Des visages, Essai d'anthropologie
(Métailié, Pans, 1992) and Anthropologie du
corps et modernité (PUF, Paris, 1995).
SHIGENORI NAGATOMO, of Japan, teaches
Japanese philosophy and Buddhism in the
Religious Studies department at Temple
University, Philadelphia (U.S.A.). He is the author
of Attunement Through the Body (State
University of New York Press, 1992).
DAVID BIALE, of the U.S.A., is Koret Professor
of Jewish History at the Graduate Theological
Union in Berkeley, California. Notable among his
published works are Eros and The Jews: From
Biblical Israel to Contemporary America (Basic
Books, 1992) and The Invention ofJudaism
(Schocken, 1997).
MANGA BEKOMBO PRISO.aCamerooman
ethnologist, is a researcher at the French
National Centre for Scientific Research (CNRS).
Among his recent publications is an edition of
Défis et Prodiges: la fantastique histoire de Djèki-
la-Njambê (Classiques africains, Paris, 1994).
ROMAIN MAITRA is an Indian anthropologist
and journalist specializing ¡n the performing arts.
ABDELWAHAB MEDDEB is a Tunisian writer who
teaches comparative literature at the University
of Pans X. He recently published an essay
entitled Blanches traverses du passé (Fata
Morgana publishers, Fontfrolde, France, 1997).
ANN-MARIE JOHNSON is a New Zealand
journalist.
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American
journalist specializing in the environment.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-American
musicologist, ¡s the author of Du Tango au
reggae, Musiques noires d'Amérique latine et des
Caraïbes (From Tango to Reggae, Black Music of
Latin America and the Caribbean, Flammarion,
Paris, 1996) and Musiques Caraïbes (Caribbean
Music, Actes Sud, Aries, 1996).
50
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Verier Nikon
announce an
international
photo competition
on the theme of
THE THEME:
The theme of the competition, inspired by
î the Preamble to Unesco's Constitution, is
, peace in the down-to-earth context of
everyday life.
Peace in
everyday life
CONDITIONS
OF ENTRY:
The competition is open to professional
photographers in all parts of the world.
Contestants are requested to constitute a portfolio of up
to twenty black and white or colour prints of their work on
the theme "Peace in everyday life", and send it in with a
completed entry form. The portfolios must reach the .
Unesco Courier offices by
15 July 1997.
THE JURY:
An international jury will meet
in Paris and choose the winning entry from
among 120 portfolios short-listed by a
preselection committee. Short-listing and
jury deliberations will take place at
Unesco Headquarters in Paris.
A "Unesco Courier- Nikon Prize'
of
50,00 I
will be awarded to the winning entry.
Prize-winning photos will be published
in the Unesco Courier.
For further information, contact:
"Peace in everyday life" competition
Unesco Courier
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 PARIS CEDEX 15,France
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 69
Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
ESsSa BiS
Ak
THEME OF THE NEXT ISSUE:
PEOPLE AND
LANDSCAPE
INTERVJEWJIVITH:
AIME CESAIRE
HERITAGE:
THE ISLAND OF
MOZAMBIQUE
ENVIRONMENT:
CHINESE AND
JAPANESE GARDENS
]]>
</page>
</document>
