<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="109505eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
r*
en
O»
ÛS
m
ó
r-
u
o
UNESCO
OURIER m
BE prepared!
I
M 1205-9710-22.00 F
III
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ENCOUNTERS7̂*
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered for
publication in this feature. Your
photo should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of architecture
or any other subject which seems
to be an example of cultural
cross-fertilization.
Alternatively, you coutd send us
pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds in
which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all
photographs.
THE HERO WITH
A THOUSAND
WOUNDS
by Balzan
1996, wood
(height: 159 cm,
width: 72.5 cm,
depth: 53.5 cm)
Balzan is a French artist
who practises sculpture as a
formofideography.The
shape of this work, which
evokes the dignity of the
upright and resolute human
figure, recalls that of the
Chinese ideogram for man.
© Balzan, Templeuve, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (OU RI ER
48
Colombian scientist
Manuel Elkin Patarroyo,
who has developed a vaccine that marks
an important stage in the struggle
against malaria.
42
Taxila (Pakistan),
once the capital of the ancient region of
Gandhara, is an archaeological site ofmajor
importance.
Cover:
A tornado in Nevada (U.S.A.) in 1996.
© Keister/Liaison/Gamma Pans
contents
OCTOBER 1997
Natural disasters
Month by month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat	5
Safety first!	6
by Badaoui Rouhban
A decade for international action	8
Interview with Frank Press
Nature on the rampage 11
by Walter W. Hays
Making cities safer	16
by Mustafa Erdik
The do's and don'ts of risk reduction	19
by Barbara Carby
Sounding the alarm	23
by Fabrizio Ferruca
Women in the front line 27
by Debarati Guha-Sapir
Insurance: halting an ominous trend	30
by Gerhard Berz
Fact file	34
Consultant: Badaoui Rouhban
Commentary Federico Mayor 36
GREENWATCH New Caledonia: threats to biodiversity by France Bequette 38
REFLECTIONS Spreadingthe word by Odon Vallet 45
AUTHORS 50
r 3
THE UNESCO (^OUREER OCTOBER 1997 ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
tb& unesco
Courier
^*^50th YEAR
Published monthly in 29 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15, France.
Fax (33) (0)1 45 68 57 45
e-mail, unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet http //www.unesco org
Director: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition. Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmma Sopova
Art Unit/Production Georges Servat
Illustrations Ariane Bailey (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68.46 90)
Documentation: José Banaag
(Tel. (33} (0)1.45 68. 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press
Solange Beim (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 46 87)
Film duplication. Daniel Meister
Secretariat* Annie Brächet
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45.68 47.15),
Administrative Assistant Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68 45.69)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic. Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian: Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil. M Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian" Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Bart Chnstiaens (Antwerp)
Portuguese. Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili: Leonard J Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene. Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek- Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish Rntta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Sunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese- Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa Ahyu Muhammad Bunza (Sokoto)
Ukrainian Volodymyr Vasihuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax. (33) (0)1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68 45.65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Customer service: Michel Ravassard,
(Tel (33) (0)1 45 68 45 91)
Accounts. (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68 45 65)
Shipping Daniel Meister (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 45 65
1 year: 211 French francs 2 years- 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries'
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing trie credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor Signed
articles reprinted must bear author s name Non-copyright photos will
be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not nec¬
essarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of
the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are written by the
Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris. (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100
U S A . (3) N C R Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc , 111 West 40lh
Street, New York. U S A , (4) Bell and Howell Co,. Old Mansfield Road,
Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S A
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL Cl - OCTOBER 1997
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure:
Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z.I Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 10-1997-OPI-97-563 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 50-51
©J Hartley. Panos Pictures, London
> QuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
MONTH BY MONTH
by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
-
Where does fatality end and human willpower step in?
Myths, religions and philosophies have long sought to
pierce the mystery of this shadowy line of demarcation which
runs like Ariadne's thread through the labyrinth of human
experience. Perhaps the most striking expression of this mys¬
tery is the confrontation between humankind and the nat¬
ural elements. How otherwise can we explain why some peo¬
ple go on living at the foot of a volcano or in an
earthquake-prone area, though they are fully aware that in
so doing they risk their lives?
Until a few decades ago humankind seemed to be partic¬
ularly helpless in the face of earthquakes, cyclones and volcanic
eruptions. It was impossible to predict when they would hap¬
pen and what their effects would be. Human intellect and
determination could only bow to divine caprice.
But worse was to come. It became apparent that in some
cases human activity could actually trigger disasters or aggra¬
vate their impact. It was discovered, forinstance, that unwise
and anarchic land use caused drought, and that deforestation
could be linked to flooding. Then came new disasters that
were not of natural origin but were no less dramatic, such as
the radioactive cloud that blew from Chernobyl, the green¬
house effect and the hole in the ozone layer.
All the same, there is no need for "catastrophism". What
is in question is not progress but the ambivalence of its poten¬
tial effects, the dark side that is inherent in any new i nvention .
But let us not forget the bright side. Progress has made it
possible for us to take effective action to mitigate and some¬
times even prevent the worst consequences of some natural dis¬
asters, as well as those caused by human activity.
We are no more capable of preventing earthquakes today
than we were in the past. But we can map high-risk areas and
assess the probabilities of future occurrence by taking para¬
meters from the past into account. We know what building
techniques and materials to use in high-risk areas, what pre¬
cautions to take when certain warning signs appear and what
to do in the immediate aftermath of disaster.
Experience has taught us to take three key steps: to assess
the risks from natural hazards as far as possible so as to mit¬
igate their most devastating effects, and to educate people
about potential dangers and ways of coping with them. We
must also train the most active members of the population
andperhaps most important of allmake decision-makers
aware of their responsibilities. If we want to get the most out
of existing knowledge and skills, the whole of the population
must be mobilized.
A dust storm
in Burkina Faso.
© J. Hartley, Panos Pictures. London
JJ '.-^
3 ^)URIIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
BY BADAOUI ROUHBAN
Throughout history, the violent side of
nature has manifested itself in
destructive phenomena such as floods,
volcanic eruptions, severe storms, wildfires,
earthquakes and tidal waves. Disasters and
risks are a part of our life, and they will con¬
tinue to threaten, kill and destroy. "Zero
risk" is out of reach in the contemporary
world. The basic problem is how to prevent
hazards from causing increasingly large-scale
disasters. The answer is that the disastrous
effects of natural phenomena will only be
eliminated, reduced or stabilized when peo¬
ple decide to make cities, settlements, infra¬
structures and houses safer.
I A culture ofprevention
For people are the agents of disaster. "It's
not the bullet that kills, it's the hole". Earth¬
quakes and windstorms do not kill; the col-
6 ) COURIER I OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
A call¡or a 'culture oj prevention 'to counteract
increasingly destructive natural disasters
lapse of houses and buildings from shak¬
ing is the main cause of death. Natural haz¬
ards themselves arc not on the increase; nor
are they likely to be in the future. It is the
frequency of natural disasters that is
expected to grow, as well as their complex¬
ity, scope, gravity and destructive capacity.
There will be an increase in multiple or syn-
ergistic-type disasters causing society-wide
impacts. In a time of globalization, large-
scale damage caused by an earthquake in a
world financial centre such as Tokyo or Cal¬
ifornia is bound to have an effect even on the
economies of faraway countries.
Natural disasters are not always entirely
"natural". On the one hand, natural forces
are at work on a planet whose environment is
being altered day after day by humankind:
floods arc made more severe by deforestation,
global warming more preoccupying by the
unchecked emission of greenhouse gases. On
the other, natural disasters will increasingly
generate or magnify concurrent technological
disasters. Floods can devastate chemical com¬
plexes, earthquakes can affect critical plants.
The good news is that disaster reduction
is both possible and feasible. While we cannot
prevent an earthquake ora windstorm from
occurring, or a volcano from erupting, we
can use the scientific knowledge and technical
know-how that we already have in order to
increase the earthquake- and wind-resistance
of houses and bridges, and to issue and dis¬
seminate early warnings of volcanic eruptions
and organize proper community response to
such warnings. The extent to which society
puts this knowledge to effective use depends
upon its social, cultural, political, economic,
and even religious specificities.
I Informing thepublu
Disaster prevention and preparedness start
with improving our understanding of risks
by assessing the distribution in time and space
and the intensity of the natural phenomena
When Colombia's Nevado del
Ruiz volcano suddenly erupted
on 13 November 1985, It
struck the towns of Armero
and Chinchina and claimed
nearly 25,000 lives. Above,
victims flee the disaster.
The eruption of Vesuvius
In 1794 (anonymous
19th-century painting).
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
involved and the exposure of people and struc-
tures to them. On the basis of this assess¬
ment, protective measures may be taken such
as land-use restrictions, adequate construc¬
tion measures and wise environmental man¬
agement. Detection and warning systems may
be installed, and contingency and emergency
plans be set up. One permanent measure of
paramount importance is the education and
information of the public.
A number of cases show that loss of life,
injuries and physical damage can all be sig¬
nificantly reduced by the application of bet¬
ter warning and disaster prevention mea¬
sures. Because of inadequate use of, and
response to, warning, more than 300,000
people died in Bangladesh due to a cyclone
in November 1970. In May 1985, better pre¬
diction and proper response to warning of
a cyclone of the same intensity kept the
death toll below 10,000. Similarly, appro¬
priate warning and evacuation saved the
30,000-strong local community during the
1991 eruption of Mount Pinatubo in the
Philippines. The population of the city of
Armero in Colombia had been less fortunate
in 1985 when a comparable eruption of
Nevado del Ruiz volcano caused 25,000
deaths within minutes.
Disaster prevention measures cost much
less than relief and reconstruction expendi¬
ture following a disaster, yet many deci¬
sion-makers tend to focus on relief and to
treat disaster situations in an ad hoc way
when they are presented with them. Today
most typical strategies are crisis-oriented.
Furthermore, information about natural
hazards and disaster reduction techniques
is not well disseminated, and planners, pro¬
ject managers and communities do not inte¬
grate hazard management into development
planning. Resources spent on relief and
recovery continue to account for 96 per cent
of all resources spent on disaster-related
activities annually, leaving a pitiful 4 per cent
for disaster prevention. It is high time to
make a shift in emphasis from post-disaster
reaction to pre-disaster action.
8
a Decade for
In 1984 you became the first person to call
for an international decade to reduce loss of
life and property from natural hazards.
Yes. One of the highest callings of scientists
and engineers is to improve the lives of people
everywhere. Natural hazards do not recognize
international boundaries, nor does any one
nation have all the knowledge or material
resources needed to cope with them. Only
through international co-operation will signif¬
icant progress be made, especially in developing
countries with limited resources and few pro¬
fessional workers.
What are the successes of the Decade so
far? What happens when it's over?
The Decade has raised the priority of disaster
mitigation in many countries, particularly in
the developing world. Government disaster
o ffices have been established and risk assessments
have been carried out in many countries. Train¬
ing programmes were implemented and inter¬
national teams organized to assess the dangers
of particular disasters. Many countries have pre¬
pared national plans for the first time and shared
them with the international community.
More could have been done, particularly to
help developing nations, which suffer most fro m
natural disasters. Unfortunately we have not been
able to raise enough funds to realize the Decade's
THE UNESCO ^JURIIERBOCTOPER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
hternational action
Interview with ri\AI\IK r Ktbb,
President Emeritus of the U.S. National Academy of Sciences
and 'father' of the International Decade for Natural Disaster Reduction (1990-2000)
full potential. Nevertheless, we are grateful to the
countries whose financial support enabled us to
achieve some results. Hopefully the momentum
inspired by the Decade will not be lost.
Do you think natural hazards are a world
issue which deserves, amid other proliferating
environmental and societal issues, priority
attention?
Mitigation of natural disasters in the form of
environmental protection, preservation of biodi¬
versity, prevention of disease, education and the
dissemination of knowledge, and equitable eco¬
nomic growth must be priorities on the agenda of
a civilized and humane global society of the twenty-
first century. Science can contribute to all of these.
What are the primary decisions that the
government of a hazard-prone country should
take?
Almost every country is prone to one or more
natural hazards. Within the governmental structure
there should be a body responsible for disaster
mitigation and relief. Among its tasks would be
assessment of risks from natural hazards, disaster
relief planning, land use and construction regula¬
tions appropriate for indigenous hazards, public
education, warning systems, evacuation planning,
training and drill and arrangements for interna¬
tional co-operation. I emphasize that many devel
oping countries will need help in establishing such
programmes.
Can the public participate in disaster
reduction?
Some governments have educated their citi¬
zenry in public safety measures. Unfortunately
many countries have yet to achieve this degree of
preparation.
What is the link between dealing with natural
disasters and potential human-made disasters?
All of these disasters result in human suffering
and should be tackled by the international com¬
munity. Perhaps we could dedicate the new century
to reducing all aspects of human suffering. How¬
ever, these potential disasters differ, have various
causes and solutions, and affect nations differ¬
ently. It will be hard to get universal agreement
on how to address such complex global problems.
It may be worthwhile to treat these several cate¬
gories of disasters separately in the short term.
Dealing with disasters requires co-operation
between many disciplines and between the
public and private sectors. How can this best be
achieved?
First by establishing an organizational structure
Once a structure is in place, a strategic plan or road
map will have to define the roles to be played by
professionals in diverse disciplines and by public
and private sectors. All are currently involved one
way or another but not in a truly collaborative
enterprise. They meet and share information
more on disaster relief than pre-disaster planning
and mitigation.
Electronic communication, universally acces¬
sible data archives, software for learning from
experience and building "virtual teams", spin-offs
of bureaucracy-free entities are some of the mech¬
anisms used to spur collaboration and increase
efficiency in attacking complex problems.
Left, building a barrier to hold
back mud-flows caused by
volcanic eruption in
Galunggung (Indonesia).
Right, earthquake drill at a
Los Angeles school (U.S.A.).
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
TRUE OR FALSE?
This test, created by Dorothy Hoffmann and Gilbert Padey
of the World Health Organization (WHO), was reproduced
from the Jan./Feb. 1991 Issue of WHO'S World Health magazine.
1. In case of disaster, an immediate appeal for international
medical personnel should be sent out. True or false?
2. When a disaster occurs, people in other countries should not
react by immediately organizing the collection and despatch of
whatever can be obtained in the way of medicines, clothing,
equipment, etc. True or false?
3. A few weeks after a disaster occurs, things are usually back
to normal and most of the major services are restored. True or
false?
4. Disasters cause fewer deaths in rich countries than in poor
countries. True or false?
5. Disasters bring out the worst in human behaviour. True or
false?
6. When disaster strikes, outbreaks of infectious diseases are
inevitable due to the presence of unattended dead bodies.
True or false?
7. Mass hunger can be avoided after a disaster strikes. True or
false?
8. Following a disaster, it is best to house people as close as
possible to their own dwellings rather than in settlement camps.
Trueorfalse?
9. In case of limited food supplies following a disaster, priority
should be given to the young and old. True or false?
10. When disaster strikes, individuals should take care of their
own families and belongings first? True or false?
11. The intensity of two earthquakes in Armenia and San Fran¬
cisco was the same but in Armenia several thousand died
whereas in San Francisco sixty people died. This is mainly due
to the difference in earthquake-proof construction. True or
false?
12. The Sahelian drought is caused by a combination of cli¬
matic and human factors. True or false?
Answers on page 34
EVERY YEAR
ON EARTH THERE ARE:
100,000 thunderstorms
floods
of landslides
100 earthquakes which cause damage
of wildfires
of hurricanes, cyclones, typhoons and
tornadoes
of volcanic eruptions, tsunamis and
droughts
ature on
\#<rWr<- -r ¿M
Natural hazards originate
from the air (storms, wildfires,
droughts), the earth (earthquakes,
landslides, volcanic eruptions) or
water (flooding).
When communities cannot cope
with them they turn into disasters.
10 > ^lURIERI OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
the rampage
BY WALTER W.HAYS
Gyumri, formerly
Leninakan
(Armenia),
stricken by an
earthquake in
December 1988.
Earthquakes
Small quakes happen every day all over the
world. Large ones, which are rarer, can cause
more damage than floods and severe storms.
Earthquakes are dangerous because they strike
without warning, trigger disaster in less than a
minute and forecasts of their effects are difficult.
Undersea earthquakes can generate tsunami
flood waves which can have effects at great dis¬
tances. Buildings and communities near active
earth-fault zones, or on soft or unstable soil
or slopes, or at the water's edge are especially
vulnerable to ground shaking, earthquake-trig¬
gered fires and tsunamis. Some recent earth¬
quake disasters:
« Kobe Qapan), 1 7 January 1995. This 6.9 mag
nitude1 tremor was the world's most costly
earthquake disaster, with losses of about $140
billion. Centred 20 km from Kobe, it struck
just before dawn and destroyed 200,000 homes,
set off 600 fires, put the city's port out of oper¬
ation, severely damaged the Hanshin elevated
expressway, and left 6,000 dead and 34,000
injured.
w Northridge, California (U.S.A.), 17 Janu¬
ary 1994. Also striking before dawn, this 6.8
magnitude quake affected 3.5 million people
and led to the highest earthquake insurance pay¬
out in history more than $13 billion in claims.
Its centre was 20 km from downtown Los
Angeles and damage was estimated at $40 billion.
It damaged parts of the elevated freeway sys¬
tem, left 50,000 people homeless and 15,000
injured. Sixty-one people were killed.
«- Spitak (Armenia), 7 December 1988. A 6.9
magnitude earthquake in mid-morning, it
demonstrated the well-known weakness of unre-
inforced old buildings. But many new reinforced
concrete buildings collapsed too, among them
schools and hospitals. Some 25,000 people were
killed and reconstruction cost $16 billion.
'*" Mexico, 19 September 1985. Its epicentre was
400 km (240 miles) from Mexico City, but its
magnitude (8.1) brought down 400 government
buildings, hospitals, schools, businesses and
high-rise apartment blocks in the old lake bed
area of the city. Between 5,000 and 1 0,000 peo¬
ple were killed and losses were estimated at $5
billion.
<*- Tangshan (China), 28 July 1976. A 7.8 mag¬
nitude quake which struck in the middle of the
night while most of the million people living
and working in this industrial and coal-mining
centre in northern China were asleep. The city
mostly unreinforced buildings was devas¬
tated. At least 240,000 people died and 800,000
were injured. Reconstruction took more than
a decade.
1 The Richter scale is widely used to express the
magnitude of an earthquake by the quantity of energy
released. The highest value yet registered is 9.5. Editor
3 (jïURI ER OCTOBER 1997
il
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Droughts
Droughts may be annual or may occur once
every few years. They can last for many years,
devastating agriculture and creating deserts.
Two major droughts:
* The Sahel (Africa), 1969-73. From 1968,
a lengthy drought in West Africa extended
across the Sahara Desert southwards in the
Sahel countries of Mauritania, Senegal, Mali,
Burkina Faso and Chad. It was no worse
than many previous ones, but 250,000 peo¬
ple died and millions of refugees poured
into cities. Millions of head of livestock
died. Farm production dropped sharply.
The "Dust Bowl," Mid-Western U.S.,
1930s. This 10-year drought spread across
the entire Great Plains from North Dakota
to Texas. One dust storm in May 1934 car¬
ried hundreds of millions of tons of earth
for thousands of kilometres. In one day,
Chicago was covered with 12 million tons of
dust and distant New York City had many
gloomy, dusty days. Wheat and corn pro¬
duction fell by up to 75%. Hundreds of
thousands of people fled the area for places
further west.
In Somalia, a
development
worker and a local
official discuss a
sand dune
stabilization
programme
designed to combat
desertification.
St. Charles (U.S.A.), one of many towns in
the states of Illinois and Missouri that
were flooded in July 1993 when the
Mississippi River overflowed its banks.
Right, chart
showing the travel-
time of a tsunami
caused by an
undersea
earthquake In the
middle of the
Pacific.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Floods
The most common natural hazard, mainly
caused by flash floods after very heavy rain or
from melting ice and snow. Towns and villages
on the coast or in river plains are most at risk.
Floods cause property damage, social disruption
and health care problems and damage the envi¬
ronment (mainly soil erosion and pollution).
Some major recent floods:
*- The U.S. Midwest in April 1997 and the east¬
ern U.S. in January 1996. Heavy snowfall and
then a rapid thaw along with heavy rain flooded
North Dakota in 1997 and river valleys from
New York to Philadelphia to Virginia in 1996.
More than 100,000 people, including entire
communities, were evacuated. Losses exceeded
$2 billion mainly damage to buildings, infra¬
structure, dams and bridges.
*" Italy, 4-5 November 1966. After many hours
of rain, the River Arno burst its banks. Florence
was soon under five metres of water. Moving at
more than 130 km/hour, the flood made 12,000
people homeless, inundated more than 5,000
homes, destroyed some 10,000 cars and the
contents of half the city's shops, knocked out
the electricity, water and sewage systems and
destroyed bridges. Worst of all, oil from bro¬
ken oil tanks mixed with nearly a million tons
of mud and ruined more than a million art
treasures.
Tsunamis
These are usually set off by undersea earth¬
quakes and can travel across oceans at the speed
of a jet airliner, smashing into coastal towns
and villages with waves 30 metres high.
On 22 May 1960, a 9.5 magnitude undersea
earthquake set off a tsunami which destroyed
I 400,000 houses along 1,000 km of coastline,
| leaving 5,000 people dead. The ground shook for
g three and a half minutes and subsided as much
I as two metres. Tsunamis with waves as high as
¡ 10 metres affected every Pacific rim country,
| damaging ships, flooding coastal areas and
g destroying buildings and factories.
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Landslides
These occur daily all over the world and are
caused either by heavy rains or earthquakes. A
big quake can can set off tens of thousands of
landslides of all sizes.
One such disaster occurred in Peru, on 31
May 1970, when a 7.6 magnitude earthquake
centred 25 km off Chimbóte, on the north
coast of Peru, caused Latin America's biggest
recorded landslide. A mass of ice 5,500 metres up
Mt Huascaran was dislodged and in three min¬
utes had slid down a glacier and travelled another
1 0 km to bury the towns of Yungay and Ran-
rahirca, killing all but 400 of their 20,000 inhab¬
itants. In Chimbóte, 96% of the town's adobe
houses were destroyed by ground tremors and
more than a thousand people killed.
In the wake of
Hurricane Gilbert,
Jamaica
(September 1988).
Hurricanes, cyclones,
typhoons and tornadoes
These tend to be seasonal and confined to cer¬
tain parts of the world. Coastal settlements are
most at risk. Physical damage and social dis¬
ruption are caused by high winds, storm surge
floods, very heavy rain, beach and coastal ero¬
sion, lightning and hail.
Notable storm disasters in recent years:
*" East Pakistan and Bay of Bengal, 12-13
November 1970. Winds of up to 240 km/hr
and a storm surge flood killed about 596,150
people in Bangladesh. More than four million
people were affected, 335,000 houses damaged
and 264,000 head of cattle killed.
« Bangladesh, 30 April 1991. A typhoon
whipped up an eight-metre storm surge which
hit the city of Chittagong after midnight, leav¬
ing 10 million people homeless, some 200,000
dead and 139,000 injured. More than 1.5 mil¬
lion buildings were damaged. An early warn¬
ing system, evacuation and the use of cyclone
shelters meant that casualties were fewer than in
the 1970 disaster.
m The Caribbean, 10 September 1988. Hurri¬
cane Gilbert, dubbed "the storm of the cen¬
tury", hit the eastern Caribbean and caused
unprecedented devastation as it swept across
Guadeloupe, Martinique, St Lucia, Puerto Rico,
the Dominican Republic, Haiti, Jamaica and
Mexico. A fifth of all the houses in Jamaica were
destroyed or badly damaged by high winds and
half a million Jamaicans were left homeless.
Banana plantations, coffee trees and food crops
were ruined by flooding, winds and landslides.
Surprisingly few lives were lost but economic
losses were more than a billion dollars.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
wtrm
» «0U
I*"*
A village
devastated by a
mud flow during
the eruption of
Mt. Pinatubo
(Philippines) in
June 1991.
A forest fire near
Marseilles (France)
on 26 July 1997.
More than 3,000
hectares of pine
forest and scrub
were destroyed.
Volcanic eruptions
The world's 500 active volcanoes erupt infre¬
quently, but when they do, the effects can be
devastating. Nearby towns can be affected by
clouds of volcanic ash (which can also seriously
threaten aircraft in the area), lateral blasts, pyro-
clastic flows of red-hot rocks and gases, lava
flows and lahars (debris flows). A major explo¬
sive eruption can affect the world's climate.
Notable volcano disasters include:
*" Mt. Pinatubo, in the Philippines, 15-16 June
1991. This was the biggest volcanic eruption of
the century. It lasted 15 hours and sent ash 30
km into the sky and set off pyroclastic flows
and lahars. More than 200,000 people, including
those at the U.S. Clark Air Force Base, were
evacuated the largest-ever evacuation before a
volcanic eruption. Typhoon Yunya passing 50
km to the north added to the disaster. Because
of the evacuation, the death toll was limited to
320, but the region was economically devas¬
tated. Strategic military alliances were altered
by the eruption as the Clark base was
abandoned.
'*" Nevado del Ruiz (Colombia), 13 November
1985. After being dormant for 140 years, the
volcano erupted and hot pyroclastic material
melted the mountain's ice cap and set off lahars.
These travelled at 30 km/hr along four river
beds to the towns of Armero and Chinchina.
The debris buried the towns late at night, killing
24,740 people, injuring 5,485 and destroying
5,680 homes.
** Agung (Bali), 1963. Two violent eruptions
in March and May generated a huge hot ash
cloud and set off lahars, which killed 1,148 peo¬
ple and injured 296. Seventy-three villages were
destroyed, leaving 70,000 people homeless and
400,000 destitute. They also destroyed 54,289
hectares of farmland and 1 1,745 hectares, of for¬
est and swept away bridges and roads.
Wildfires
Thousands of wildfires flare up every year
around the world, threatening towns and vil¬
lages. Many are caused by hot, dry summers
and set off by lightning. Others are started by
lava flows or triggered by earthquakes. A few are
the result of arson.
One recent major wildfire disaster occurred
in Great Khingan Range (China), on 6 May
I 1987. Fanned by high winds for 20 days, the
| fires burned down 750,000 cubic metres of for-
| est over a million hectares 13% of the total
| forested area or a fifth of the annual timber
¡ production of the region. The fire killed 191
| people.
THE UNESCO COURIER OCTOBER 1997 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The defences ofovercrowded cities with fragile buildings and vulnerable infrastructures
must he strengthened
making v>ities safer BY MUSTAFA ERDIK
All over the world, economic expansion,
use of new technologies and growing
interdependence are boosting the risk
of natural disasters. Cities need to draft mas¬
ter-plans to cope with them assessing threat,
predicting its effects and proposing action.
Earthquakes, which cause most natural dis¬
asters, can set off chaos in the crowded slums
of poor countries and topple badly-con¬
structed, badly-located buildings. In rich
countries, ageing populations and a growing
reliance on technology are weakening the
defences of towns and cities. There is also more
of value to be destroyed.
Landslides are another big cause of urban
disasters, often related to earthquakes, when
housing is built on steep or unstable hillsides:
Volcanoes are more predictable than earth¬
quakes, but because they lie dormant for hun¬
dreds of years, the danger from them is often
ignored and people build and live on their
slopes. Severe flooding threatens towns and
cities which are set among denuded mountains
where there are frequent thunderstorms.
16
THE UNESCO lOURIER «OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The aftermath of
the Kobe (Japan) earthquake
of 18 January 1995
Natural disasters can wreck social structures,
production, employment and income, as well as
cause physical damage. Building regulations are
crucial. In the 1995 Kobe earthquake in Japan,
countless buildings were destroyed because of
inadequate rules. Where they exist in developing
countries, such regulations are seldom enforced.
In the Erzincan (Turkey) quake of 1992, half
the medium-sized reinforced-concrete build¬
ings were destroyed. This is four times more
damage than at Kobe and twelve times more
than at Northridge (California) in 1994. Even
where modern buildings are only slightly dam¬
aged, their movable contents in the case of lab¬
oratories, hospitals, offices, museums and art
galleries can be destroyed.
A rescue team extracts a
survivor from the ruins of a
Mexico City building after the
1985 earthquake.
3 QouriTHE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Roads and bridges are vital in an emergency.
But earthquakes move and damage them. At
Northridge, ten viaducts and 157 overpasses
were heavily damaged, costing some $1.5 bil¬
lion. At Kobe, the loss was from four to five
times greater and the urban transport system
was damaged in 1 ,257 places. Rescue and recov¬
ery from a major earthquake in Istanbul would
depend heavily on vulnerable roads and bridges
linking the city to Europe.
Underground pipelines can also break, leak
ing water and gas and setting off fires. This
hampered rescue work at Kobe, where more
than 150 fires could not be put out because
the water supply to fight them failed, as did
the damaged road network.
In human terms, single-parent families,
women, handicapped people, children and the
elderly are the first victims of a natural disas¬
ter. Indirect economic damage from an earth¬
quake includes loss of production and tax rev¬
enue and increased unemployment payouts.
Northridge was the most costly earthquake
in U.S. history. At $200 billion, Kobe was the
most expensive urban disaster of modern times.
In both, the damage worked out at between
$40,000 and $50,000 per affected person. At
Erzincan, it was only about $10,000 because of
the very limited infrastructure and industry.
Such huge losses will occur again. A big
quake in Istanbul would probably cost about
$50 billionabout a fifth of Turkey's 1996
Gross National Product (GNP). A repeat of the
1923 Kanto earthquake in the Tokyo region
would cost perhaps sixteen times more than
Kobe, or two-thirds of Japan's 1994 Gross
Domestic Product (GDP). Another San Fran¬
cisco quake as big as the tremor of 1 906 (8.3 on
the Richter scale) would cause losses seven times
greater than at Northridge.
Vehicles were crushed when an
apartment building collapsed
onto its parking lot during the
Northridge (California, U.S.A.)
earthquake in January 1994.
An old house in a Turkish
village which collapsed after
being weakened by several
earthquakes.
18
THE UNESCO lOURIER« OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
What individuals
and societies can
do to cut the toll
ofhuman and
economic loss
he do's and don'ts of risk reduction
Above, the European
Laboratory for Structural
Assessment in Ispra (Italy). T
JL r
fhe most effective disaster mitigation
measure that can be taken at commu¬
nity level is for people not to build in
high-risk areas such as unstable slopes, river
beds or flood plains. Local knowledge about
these hazards is usually good, especially among
older people. Sometimes though, a hazard such
as a geological fault is not obvious or visible, and
surveyors and geologists have to be called in.
BY BARBARA CARBY
People can also ensure they reduce risks in
their houses. Roofs should be secured against
hurricanes. Roof shape is important for wind
resistance. A flat roof is much more likely to
be blown off than a pyramid-shaped one.
Some worry about the cost of such measures,
but they are no more than a small percentage
of the total cost of the building and are well
worth the investment.
19
THE UNESCO (^pURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Map showing earthquake
monitoring centres in southern
California (U.S.A.).
17
- ¿SJt-"^^
i
. .. 1 I \-A
Earthquake mitigation focuses on building
codes, including correct use of steel and the
strength of concrete mixes. Wooden build¬
ings can be reinforced by braces and tying cor¬
ners so as to make the structure react as a box.
Hazards in the home are not all structural.
If you live in an earthquake-prone area, you
should check the following:
*- Are heavy objects like cabinets, TV stands
and entertainment centres attached to the
wall?
*- Are heavy objects on the lowest shelves?
Are water heaters and gas cylinders bolted
to the wall?
Do household members know how to
turn off the gas, electricity and water sup-
ply?
* Are hanging objects such as fans and ceiling
lights securely fastened?
Are shelves fitted with wire or board to
prevent objects falling off them during
tremors?
*- Are dangerous substances like fuel, poi¬
sons and chemicals secured against spillage?
*- Are plate-glass windows and doors covered
with safety film to prevent shattering?
At the national level, governments should
include mitigation in their disaster manage¬
ment policies. Zoning and land use laws should
ensure there are no buildings in an area likely to
20
be flooded, say, once every thirty years. Golf
courses and parks could be built there instead.
Steep slopes would be left as wooded areas.
But planners and policy makers do not
usually have this freedom. Many rivers already
flow through towns, so mitigation will take
the form of reducing loss of life and damage
after a flood. Ground floors can be designated
non-sleeping areas, levees can be built and flood
warning systems and evacuation plans can be
developed.
Building codes should be drafted and
where they already exist, should be reviewed
and strengthened. They should ensure that
buildings can survive a 7 magnitude earth¬
quake or 200 km/h winds.
Standards ofsafety
Many buildings were put up before codes were
drafted, so they need to be "retrofitted" by
strengthening. This is more expensive than
building to resistant standards. Large public
buildings and bridges are prime candidates for
retrofitting. But small traditional buildings
should be strengthened too. Much work has
been done on this in India and Peru. Chicken
mesh and mortar has been effective in rein¬
forcing walls of adobe-type buildings against
earthquake damage. 5tf*r^
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Emergency facilities such as hospitals,
police stations and shelters, along with water,
electricity and sewage systems, must also be
able to remain functional after a disaster. They
should be designed to a higher standard of
safety than other buildings and retrofitted
where necessary. This especially applies to hos¬
pitals crucial after a disaster as they can be
knocked out of action without structural
damage. So non-structural mitigation mea¬
sures are vital.
Cost is one of the reasons cited for lack of
mitigation measures in poor countries. But one
could say that such countries cannot afford not
to take measures. Tropical Storm Debby set off
extensive flooding and landslides in the small
Caribbean island of St. Lucia in 1994. Agricul¬
tural losses alone were about 12 per cent of the
island's 1993 Gross Domestic Product (GDP).
Vulcanologist Maurice Krafft
measures the temperature of a
lava flow using a device called
a thermocouple.
Even reducing direct damage by one per
cent through mitigation would have been
worthwhile. But political support for miti¬
gation is hard to drum up because little work
has been done on quantifying the benefits of
mitigation as opposed to cost.
I Hurricane-resistant roofs
Bangladesh is a mitigation success story how¬
ever. Improved warning systems and the build¬
ing of cyclone shelters has sharply cut loss of
life and livestock. In Jamaica, Hurricane Gilbert
in 1988 showed the benefit of roofs shaped
for wind resistance. Many specially-designed
buildings which went up after a hurricane in
1951 kept their roofs in 1988, while more
modern and expensive structures with fash¬
ionable flat or slightly-sloping roofs which
went up in the 1970s and 1980s, did not.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
A Sri Lankan engineer
inspects coastal hurricane
defences south of Colombo.
Recent earthquakes in California and Japan
have successfully tested earthquake-proof
buildings. In California, many old masonry
structures which had been retrofitted survived.
But little is heard about this success since news
is about buildings which collapse. However
the media can do a lot to publicize the advan¬
tages of mitigation, especially just after a dis¬
aster when mitigation measures should be
included in repair work.
Mitigation is also very important in the
natural environment. Action taken in water¬
sheds in the mountains will eventually affect
the marine environment, especially in small
countries where the distance between water-
Damage in a San Francisco
(U.S.A.) store after an
earthquake in October 1989.
shed and sea is small. Eroded soil washing
down into the ocean results in silting which
kills off coral and fish. Coral reefs help control
beach and coastal erosion, and if they are dam¬
aged the coast is more vulnerable to flooding
which will in turn cause more erosion. Coral
reefs are also important fish hatching grounds,
so loss of reefs will harm the fishing industry,
especially in island states. Destruction of reefs
and beaches also harms countries which live
off tourism. Chemical spills into waterways
eventually reach the sea and also damage coral
reefs and marine life. Damaged or stressed reefs
are more vulnerable to natural hazards because
they arc less resistant to wave action.
Dialogue between environmental and dis¬
aster managers is essential. For mitigation to
work, the entire society must be involved. Pro¬
grammes should ensure local communities take
part in planning at the same time as they ensure
political and financial support at national and
international level. Mitigation must be part of
our daily life. If the present century "invented"
mitigation and moved disaster management
beyond mere response, the next must see that
mitigation becomes an integral part of plan¬
ning at all levels of society.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
sounding the
From tolling bells to remote sensing
by satellite, disaster warning
systems have come a long way
BY FABRIZIO FERRUCCI
Hurricane Fran (September
1996) as seen from a weather
satellite.
rhe tolling of bells was once the usual way
to warn people of impending disasters
like floods, fires or approaching armies.
Warnings based on eye-witness reports
were passed on from town to town. The fur¬
ther away the town was from the disaster, the
longer it had to prepare its defences. These
days, the approach is much the same even
though the technology is very different. Warn¬
ings are still issued at one point and propa¬
gated across a network of users who deploy
skills to mitigate the impact of the event.
Today's warning systems rely on measure¬
ment techniques, mostly from physics and geo¬
physics, and on communications technology.
The science of risk prediction is young, and the
systematic observation of natural processes is
not much older. Quantitative meteorology dates
back to the 1 940s, quantitative seismology to the
1960s, and quantitative vulcanology is only
about twenty years old. Remote-sensing fro m
space only began in the late 1970s. Meanwhile,
advances in communications technology have
made it possible to speak to people anywhere on
earth from a disaster site.
I Technological risks and
natural risks
Technological, or human-made risks are usually
limited in time and place, even if they cause
dramatic and long-term effects. Warning
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER I9SJ d
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
systems are built into industrial plants and are
based on all possibilities of failure known to
the designers. Natural risks are much more dan¬
gerous because they involve the biggest energies
on earth, and because we have less access to risk
sources that were not designed by human
beings.
The concept of warning implies forecasting
in space, time, or both. In some cases warnings
can be issued if we can foresee the short,
medium- and long-term evolution of an
impending event, and its consequences. In oth¬
ers they are possible if we can identify minor
events that are precursors of a much bigger one.
Good examples of early warning are the fore¬
casting of weather conditions twelve, twenty-
four and forty-eight hours ahead, and of extreme
meteorological events such as hurricanes, their
path and timing. A bad example is earthquake
prediction, which is seldom attempted and when
it is all too often fails. The Table on this page
shows today's capacity to forecast the occur¬
rence of some major natural events.
As a general rule, the capacity to issue reliable
early warnings requires: good approximate
knowledge of the specific source of the hazard
in question; availability of one or more mod¬
els allowing description of the event in time
and place; appropriate surveillance systems being
in operation; transmission of information
ahead of the development of the hazard.
Sometimes one type of risk is linked to
Houses in flames as fire
spreads through a city block
following the January 1995
earthquake in Kobe (Japan).
Opposite page,
decontaminating a building at
Chernobyl (Ukraine) in 1986.
another. Extreme meteorological events may
lead to flash floods, plain floods and land¬
slides. Industrial fires may lead to explosions,
severe chemical pollution of air, ground and
water. If there is full control of the source of
primary risk, warnings about secondary effects
are possible.
How do we stand in practice with regard to
warning techniques of some natural phe¬
nomena today?
A mother and daughter look
on helplessly as their house
burns down.
Weatherforecasting
Weather forecasts are generally reliable because
meteorologists can model in detail the behav¬
iour of large masses of air and because a very
As the Table below shows, we must answer a categorical "no" about the reliability of many
types of forecast in time. This does not exclude the possibility that, locally and sometimes,
correct forecasts are issued. However, these cannot be "generalized" and extended
successfully to other places and other scenarios. F. F.
IS IT POSSIBLE TO FORECAST THE OCCURRENCE OF DISASTROUS NATURAL EVENTS?
IN SPACE IN TIME
Long term
(a year or more)
Medium term
(month to weeks)
Short-term
(days to hours)
Earthquakes Yes Yes, almost No No
Extreme meteorological events Yes No No Yes
Flash floods Yes No No Yes/almost
Forest fires Yes No No No/almost
Landslides Yes Yes Yes Yes/almost
Plain floods Yes No No Yes
Volcanic eruptions Yes Yes Yes No/almost
THE UNESCO ipURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
complete set of worldwide observations at all
scales is available. Weather satellites provide a
flow of images of cloud distribution over con¬
tinents and oceans, while a dense network of
ground stations reports continuously updated
information about temperature, humidity
and wind direction and speed at ground level
and in the troposphere (the lowest level of
the atmosphere).
Earth observation from space and efficient
telecommunications on land and with space
make it possible to combine national forecasts
into a global system which can predict extreme
events in time for precautions to be taken.
Weather forecasts can warn of heavy rainfall
which may lead to flooding because of its con¬
centration in space and the structure of river
basins. Ground-based weather radar plays an
important part in short-term flood warning
by making it possible to estimate the location
and amount of rainfall, whose effect on a river
basin can be monitored by sensors which make
it possible to issue short-term warnings and
take steps to avoid or limit overflows. A good
topography of the river basin and the river
bed are needed to predict the behaviour of
flood waters on the basis of rainfall density
and duration and soil type.
Although flood warnings are not always
timely, many recent instances show that lack
of co-ordination rather than lack of warning
is the weak point in flood risk mitigation.
Volcanic eruptions
It is relatively feasible to predict volcanic erup¬
tions because the volcanic process is condi¬
tioned by many physical and chemical factors
that can be individually monitored. Eruptions
are always preceded by intense seismic activity
and ground inflation, and the reawakening of
a dormant volcano can easily be detected by
just a few seismic instruments, making it pos¬
sible to issue a long-term warning.
As the magma makes its way to the sur¬
face, ground inflation will begin and new gas
vents will appear, along with changes in the
gas composition and local disturbances in the
earth's gravity and magnetic fields. The appear¬
ance and growing intensity of these phenom¬
ena make it possible to issue a medium-term
warning based on data provided by a complex
blend of instruments including a seismic net¬
work, networks for monitoring the hori¬
zontal and vertical components of the ground
deformation, a network of magnometers, a
network for measuring very small changes in
the local gravity field, and instruments for
analysing volcanic gases.
At this point forecasting becomes more
complex. Firstly, as the magma gets close to
the surface, its effects are concentrated in an
ever-smaller area, so many more and closer
spaced instruments are needed to pinpoint the
highest area of risk.
Secondly, the shallow part of the earth's crust
(2-3 km) is much weaker than the intermediate
crust where the magma was earlier and so erup¬
tion is easier. The moment of eruption is pre¬
ceded by much more rapid physical and chem¬
ical changes. The closer we are to eruption time,
the greater the forecasting uncertainties.
Short-term warnings of eruptions are
therefore still rare and mostly unreliable, how¬
ever, because the complete range of measure¬
ment networks is only available for one per
cent of the world's active volcanoes.
THE UNESCO COURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
In the case of explosive volcanoes, which
pose a major threat to people living nearby or
to aircraft flying into the dense volcanic ash
thrown up a medium-term warning should
lead to the establishment of no-go zones but
this is difficult to enforce for understandable
social and economic reasons, especially in
densely populated areas.
Earthquakes
The accuracy of earthquake prediction is poor,
the main reason for the failure of short-term
forecasting being the abundance rather than
the lack of events that precede an earthquake.
Many earthquakes are preceded by tremors,
sizeable ground deformation, local changes in
the earth's electrical or magnetic fields, changes
in the level of water wells, and emissions of
radon, carbon dioxide and other gases along
fault lines. But these events also occur inde¬
pendently of earthquakes, and in the case of
big quakes have never all occurred together or
been observed on the right scale by use of a sin¬
gle instrument network.
Although we know a lot about the source
of earthquakes these days, we do not know
much in detail about the earthquake prepara
tion process nor about the exact meaning, at
any given moment, of a hundred or so poten¬
tial earthquake precursors. So it is easy to
understand why governments and scientists
are reluctant to risk their credibility by issu¬
ing warnings. The most reliable warning that
can be given for earthquakes today is in fact
simply to note where and when they have
occurred and act accordingly.
Regional networks of seismographs can be
set up in these earthquake-prone areas. Data can
be processed in real time or near-real time
through automated systems which make it
possible to pinpoint the time, magnitude and
epicentre of a quake a few minutes after the
event. In this way rescue services can be alerted
and directed to the places where they are most
needed.
Today early warning of natural disasters is
either possible or else we know why it is not.
There is every reason to believe that through
technology, our disaster-warning capacity will
improve and that soon it will be possible to
organize a timely response to all natural risks.
Until then, keep an ear cocked for the
tolling bells. It may be just a wedding, but
you never know.
A demonstration provoked by
the escape of toxic fumes
(dioxin) from a chemical plant
in Seveso, near Milan (Italy),
in 1976.
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
omen in the front line BY DEBARATI GUHA-SAPIR
Women in developing countries should be key players
in disasterpreparedness and relief
"Women in traditional rural
societies feel reluctance to
consult male doctors. The use
of women health workers and
nurses would be a step in the
right direction." Above, a
community health worker (at
right) informs Bangladesh
village women about medical
treatment for children.
/t too often goes unreported that women
and children usually suffer more than men
in natural disasters, especially in the coun¬
tries of the South.
Preparedness and prevention programmes
mostly ignore their vulnerability and few relief
programmes are designed with them in mind.
Since they play only a marginal role in com
munity decision-making, they can rarely com¬
mandeer relief supplies or have a say in post-
disaster rehabilitation.
Most of the 100,000 people who died in the
1991 Bangladesh cyclone, for example, were
women. Many died trying to protect their chil¬
dren and some because they stayed in their
homes and kept away from the cyclone shelters
THE UNESCO tOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
because they felt obliged to safeguard their
property. Although the cyclone warning system
was in place, it was only partly effective because
gender was ignored. Furthermore, the absence
of women doctors meant that many women
and girls needing care did not venture to emer¬
gency clinics for treatment.
In severe droughts, women face a sharply
increased workload because men often migrate
in search of work. Their health suffers, and as
water tables get lower and lower they have to
fetch water from further and further away.
Hygiene deteriorates as the physical strain
takes a toll on their already malnourished bod¬
ies. High mortality of cattle means less milk
and meat to go round.
And yet women in traditional communities
can play a key role in disaster preparedness and
relief in areas they are used to handling such as
distribution of food, water, blankets and jer-
rycans and the siting of lavatories. They take
decisions about the welfare of children, includ¬
ing their evacuation, feeding and safe keeping in
chaotic times. Education and public informa¬
tion campaigns should take account of these
social and cultural responsibilities. Informa¬
tion on where food or other supplies can be
obtained and the claims to such relief should be
spelled out for the general public but should
keep women very much in mind. Illiteracy and
other factors may limit a woman's access to
such information.
Drought preparedness programmes should
strengthen women as farmers in their own
right and ensure that water distribution plans
recognize that they are usually responsible for
this task.
Cultural and social constraints also aggra¬
vate the problems displaced women face in
using health and sanitary services. Although it
is widely known that women in traditional
rural societies feel reluctance (in some cases
reinforced by taboos) to consult or be treated
by male doctors, standard relief response does
not seem to take this into account. The use
of women health workers and nurses, rather
Above and above right, victims
of the cyclone that hit
Bangladesh in May 1991.
28
THE UNESCO lOURIERBOCOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
than male doctors, would be a step in the right
direction.
Risk mapping in disaster-prone areas
should identify the vulnerable population by
sex and identify ways in which women are
particularly at risk. The development of
women's networks and community groups
to discuss disaster preparedness, examine past
experiences and decide on solutions should
also be encouraged.
Reporting of sex-differentiated mortality
and morbidity data would improve field inter¬
ventions. In camps for persons displaced by
natural disasters registration for services such
as food or health care should also be done by
sex of recipient. Knowledge of the different
ways in which men and women use services is
critical in planning and targeting unreached
population groups.
There has been a spectacular rise in relief
funding in the last few years, and donors under
pressure from relief and development agencies
clamouring for increasing resources are raising
"Since women play only a
marginal role in community
decision-making, they rarely
have a say in post-disaster
rehabilitation." Below, a scene
of devastation in Bangladesh
after the 6 May 1991 cyclone.
questions about traditional approaches. Relief
operations are coming under greater pressure
to provide better quality of service and higher
levels of cost-efficiency. A first step towards
reducing the vulnerability and number of dis¬
aster victims would be to integrate women
more fully into the planning and execution of
disaster preparedness and relief schemes.
LV f*"f&
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
hsurance: halting
an ominous trend
BY GERHARD BERZ
The insurance industry is adapting in response to growing risk from natural disasters
Over the last ten years, major natural dis¬
asters have caused economic losses
amounting to more than $400 billion
and insured losses of some $100 billion. Com¬
pared with disaster losses in the 1960s the eco¬
nomic loss burden has increased eight-fold,
discounting inflation, and insured losses by as
much as fifteen-fold.
Individual disasters like Hurricane Andrew
(U.S.A., 1992) have cost as much as $30 bil¬
lion in economic damages, two thirds of which
was borne by the insurance industry. Where
there was only one insured disaster loss exceed¬
ing $1 billion before 1987, eighteen such dis¬
asters have occurred since then.
These trends toward a new dimension of
loss potential are primarily caused by a rapidly
growing concentration of people and prop¬
erty in towns and cities, especially in coastal
regions and other areas highly exposed to nat¬
ural hazards.
Natural disasters: $ billion insurance
Area
losses
Insured losses
(million U S.S)
Rank Year Event Total costs (in
millions of dollars)
17 1983 Hurricane Alicia United States 1275 1650
6 1987 Winterstorm Western Europe 3100 3 700
5 1989
1990
Hurricane Hugo Caribbean, United States 4 500 9 000
4 Winterstorm Daria Europe 5100 6800
16 1990 Winterstorm Herta Europe 1300 1900
8 1990 Winterstorm Vivian Europe 2100 3250
15 1990 Winterstorm Wiebke Europe 1300 2 250
3 1991 Typhoon Mireille Japan 5 200 6 000
11 1991 Oakland fire United States 1700 2 000
1 1992 Hurricane Andrew United States 20000 30 000
12 1992 Hurricane Iniki Hawaii (U.S.A.) 1600 3 000
10 1993 Blizzard United States 1750 5000
19 1993 Floods United States 1000 12000
2 1994 Earthquake United States 12 500 30000
7 1995 Earthquake Japan 3 000 100 000
18 1995 Hailstorm United States 1135 2 000
14 1995 Hurricane Luis Caribbean
United States
1500
2100
2 500
9 1995 Hurricane Opal 3 000
13 1996 Hurricane Fran United States 1600 3 000
As of 01/97. Original figures, not adju sted for inflation. © Münchener Rück, 1997
This dramatic and skewed growth of
insured losses is changing the insurance indus¬
try. Availability of cover against natural disas¬
ters used to be mainly a matter of the right
price. Nowadays it is much more a matter of
capacity. The world reinsurance industry, which
handles most catastrophe risks and had a huge
stake in recent disasters 98 per cent in both the
1985 Mexico earthquake and Hurricane Gilbert
(Jamaica, 1988) and 65 per cent in the Euro¬
pean winter storms of 1990 has realized the
precariousness of giving unlimited propor-
30
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
tional catastrophe coverage and has switched
to limited non-proportional coverage.
This shrinkage of insurance capacity will
mean more even distribution of disaster risk
among the four parties concerned insurer,
reinsurer, insured and government. The first
two will still bear most of the burden, but
where losses look like being more than the
insurers could bear, governments will have to
help out as "last-resort" insurers or else give tax
relief so as to preserve the insurance companies'
catastrophe reserves. Even so, the insurance
industry must seize every opportunity to
stop or reverse the ominous rising trend in
loss burdens from natural disasters.
Preparingfor the worst
Insurance is by definition a form of disaster
preparedness. It represents an important, if
not decisive, prerequisite for many economic
activities. Without insurance cover, engineer¬
ing projects in highly exposed regions, such as
offshore installations in the North Sea, or
power stations in earthquake zones, would
Great Natural Disasters 1960-1996
Decade
1960-1969
Decade
1970-1979
Decade
1980-1989
Last
10 years
1987-1996
Factor
80s'60s
Factor
Last 10 years:
60s
Number 16 29 70 64 4.4 4
Economic losses* 48.4 93 147.6 404.4 3 8.4
Insured losses* 6.5 10.9 29.8 98.8 4.6 15.2
* All figures in U.S. $ billion (1996 price level) © Munchener Rück, Munich
Damage caused by Hurricane
Andrew to a mobile-home park
in Florida (1992).
be a gamble with a high risk of failure that no
business enterprise could take on.
Consequently the development and appli¬
cation of modern technologies and the eco¬
nomic development of regions where the risk
level is high or unknown have always been
accompanied and promoted by the insurance
industry. Often enough these ventures have
ended with adverse results and sometimes in
total loss. This makes it all the more important
for insurers to assess the risk as realistically as
possible and to bring all available knowhow to
bear on the process. In so doing, they very
often find themselves at the forefront of sci¬
entific and technological development.
I Financial incentives
Once people are insured for a risk, they often
forget about it and lose interest in taking any loss
prevention measures. Insurers must counteract
this mode of thought and behaviour, and they
can best do so by applying financial incentives.
If they unload part of the loss onto the
insured by means of a substantial deductible
a clause in the insurance policy relieving the
insurer of responsibility for an initial amount
of the loss or some other form of "co-insur¬
ance", but at the same time reward him or her
with an equally substantial premium rebate,
they can very effectively motivate the policy¬
holder to prevent losses.
The number of loss cases eligible for set¬
tlement in natural disasters is drastically
reduced by relatively modest deductibles,
because such disasters always entail a large,
sometimes enormous number of minor losses.
Alerting thepublic
Insurance companies publish information in
the form of leaflets, brochures, films and TV
spots in order to alert the public to risks and
draw attention to the precautions they could
take. In the past, such information campaigns
have concentrated on fire, accident and bur¬
glary prevention, but today efforts are shift¬
ing more and more to natural hazards, where
many possibilities for loss prevention have so
far scarcely been tapped.
THE UNESCO COURIER OCTOBER 1997 %
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The insurance industry also has at its dis¬
posal comprehensive worldwide loss experi¬
ence which it uses not only in calculating pre¬
miums and in classifying hazard areas, known
as rating zones, but also in tracing relationships
between event intensity and loss intensity and
estimating loss potentials from realistic disas¬
ter scenarios. In these and other areas of disas¬
ter preparedness, mitigation and relief it can
contribute a wealth of experience to worldwide
co-operation with governmental, non-gov¬
ernmental and scientific institutions, industry
and the media. In the insurance industry the
International Decade for Natural Disaster
Reduction has a natural partner and ally which
can help to ensure that its success endures far
beyond the present decade.
great natural disasters of 1996
Number on the map
Area
Event/Date
1 Indonesia
2 Australia
3 United States
4 United States
5 Morocco
6 United Kingdom
7 China
8 South Africa
9 Brazil
10 Costa Rica
11 Indonesia
12 United Arab Emirates, Saudi Arabia, Kuwait
13 India
14 Mongolia
15 United States
16 United States, Mexico
17 Australia
18 United States
19 Bangladesh
20 United States
21 United States
22 Yemen
23 Italy, Austria
24 China
25 South Africa, Lesotho
26 United States, Puerto Rico, Virgin Islands
27 Bangladesh, India
28 United States
29 Canada
30 Philippines, Thailand, China
31 Viet Nam, Thailand
32 Dem. People's Rep. of Korea, Rep. of Korea
33 Nicaragua, Costa Rica, El Salvador, Guatemala,
Honduras, Mexico, Venezuela
34 United States
35 China
36 Spam
37 Pakistan
38 India
39 United States
40 Caribbean (esp. Puerto Rico), Canada
41 China, Viet Nam
42 Sudan
43 Iceland
44 Viet Nam
45 India
46 United States
47 United Kingdom, Germany, Netherlands,
France
48 India
49 Europe
50 United States, Canada
Flooding/January
Tropical windstorm, flooding/January
Winterstorm, flooding/January
Snowstorm, frost, floods/January
Storms, flooding/January
Snowstorms, flooding/January
Earthquake/February
Flooding/February
Flooding/February
Flooding/February
Earthquake, tsunami/February
Flooding, hail/March
Drought/April
Forest and grassland fires/April-May
Tornadoes, hail/April
Drought/May-June
Flooding/May
Storms, tornadoes, flooding/May
Tornadoes/May
Tornadoes, storms, flooding/May
Forest fires/June
Flooding/June
Flooding, storms/June
Flooding, debris flows/June-August
Winter damage/July
Hurricane/July
Flooding, landslides/July
Flooding, tornadoes/July
Flooding, landslides, hailstorms/July
Typhoon, flooding/July
Tropical cyclone/July-August
Flooding, landslides/July
Hurricanes/July
Forest fires/Summer
Typhoon/July-August
Flash flood, landslide/August
Flooding/August
Cold spell, storms/August
Hurricane, flooding/September
Hurricane/September
Typhoon/September
Flooding/September-October
Volcanic eruption/October-November
Flooding/October-November
Flooding, storms/October
Storms, flooding/October
Winter storm/October
Tropical cyclone, flooding/November
Cold spell, snowstorms/December
Winter storms, flooding/December
338
38
2 700
17
10
325
2
10
43
100
67
67
89
86
111
226
22
26
163
100
162
338
4
7
970
170
20
32
24000
400 195
150
200 110
1100 370
110
310
2 300
200
30
1200
3 000
250
1500
17
360
90
350
300
1500
300
750
115
1600
150
240
240
200
370
<> Earthquake
O Windstorm
D Flooding
A Others
Symbols shaded if number of
deaths > 200 and/or economic
losses > U.S. $300 million and/or
Insured losses > U.S.$100 million
Great natural disasters
Hurricane Fran, United
States
5-8 September
22 deaths
Total losses:
$3 billion U.S.
Insured losses:
$1.6 billion U.S.
Floods in China
June-August
2,700 deaths
Total losses:
$24 billion U.S.
Insured losses:
$0.455 billion U.S.
32
THE UNESCO IpURI ER «OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
6
47
36
49
14
32
12
22
42
37
24
41
7
35
19
38 27
13
45
48
44 30
31
11
25
8
17
Number of loss events
AFRICA 49
AMERICA 195
ASIA 184
AUSTRALIA | 30(5/16/5/4)*
EUROPE
WORLD
Number of deaths
Percentage
distribution
worldwide
594
AFRICA
AMERICA
ASIA
AUSTRALIA
EUROPE
WORLD
530
1020
67(6/10/6/45)*
720
Worldwide breakdown:
percentage according
to type of event
9 525
11860
15 000
1 (Earthquake/Windstorm/Flooding/Others)
Earthquakes I
Storms I
Flooding
Others
Earthquakes
Storms B
Flooding
Others
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
FACT FILE
BUILDING A CULTURE
OF PREVENTION
The International Decade for Natural
Disaster Reduction 1990-2000
In 1989, 155 Member States of the United Nations co-sponsored
a UN Resolution which declared the years 1990 to 2000 the
"International Decade for Natural Disaster Reduction"
(IDNDR). The purpose of the decade is to marshal the politi¬
cal resolve, experience and expertise of each country to reduce
loss of life, human suffering and economic losses from natural
hazards.
According to IDNDR targets, by the year 2000 all countries
should:
COMPLETE NATIONAL RISK ASSESSMENTS
Identify natural hazards which pose the threat of disaster
Evaluate the geographic distribution of hazard threats and
their frequency and impacts
' Assess the vulnerability of the most important concentra¬
tions of population, development and resources
IMPLEMENT NATIONAL AND/OR LOCAL PREVENTION AND
PREPAREDNESS PLANS
*" Adopt land-use and construction practices that will reduce
disaster risks
*" Adopt emergency-response plans that identify hazard sce¬
narios, essential actions and responsible organizations
*" Implement awareness programmes to educate people about
risks and training programmes to improve the capabilities of
responsible personnel
*" Implement concrete measures to mitigate damages and
increase resilience to hazards
IMPLEMENT GLOBAL, REGIONAL, NATIONAL AND LOCAL
WARNING SYSTEMS
' Implement systems for monitoring and predicting threat¬
ening phenomena in time to reduce impacts
Implement communication systems for disseminating warn¬
ings
Educate decision makers about hazards and options for
reducing disaster risk.
Source: United Nations, IDNDR
IDNDR Secretariat
UN Department of Humanitarian Affairs
Palais des Nations
1211 Geneva 10, Switzerland
Tel: (41-22) 798 6894
Fax: (41-22) 733 8695
Email: idndr@dha.unicc.org
Documentation available on request:
Cities at risk, 1996. (also in French, Spanish and Italian)
Learning about naturaldisasters, 1995 (also in French, Spanish,
Chinese, Russian, Hindi, Farsi, Macedonian, Turkish, Alban¬
ian and Serbo-Croat)
Yokohama Strategy andPlan ofAction, 1995 (alsoinFrench and
Spanish)
World Disaster Reduction Campaign (information bulletin)
Stop Disasters (quarterly magazine, also in French, Spanish
and Italian)
Also available: posters, stickers, video catalogue.
World Disaster
Reduction Day 1997
making communities
safer from floods and
drought
Coastal and river flooding are the most frequent natural disasters and
drought is the disaster that affects more people than any others. For
this reason the 1997 World Disaster Reduction campaign, an annual
programme within IDNDR, is designed to stimulate efforts to reduce
the social and economic impact of floods and droughts. The high
point of the campaign, an annual programme within IDNDR, is World
Disaster Reduction Day on Wednesday 8 October.
TRUE OR FALSE?
Answers to quiz on page 10
1. False. Local health services are normally able to cope in case of disaster. They have the advan¬
tage of speaking the local language and are familiar with the health service infrastructure. For¬
eign teams may provide specialized skills and equipment, but they have to be housed and fed.
2. True. A fast international response to disasters is not necessarily the best solution. An eval¬
uation of the most urgent needs should first be made so that communication channels do not
become blocked by unessential items or by outdated medicaments and food products.
3. False. Although disasters may disappear from the news headlines, their impact may last for
years. There is often permanent damage to water supplies and health services; reconstruction
and rehabilitation are time-consuming and costly.
4. True. Poverty leads to poor living conditions and the poor are more vulnerable in case of dis¬
aster. The richer countries have the resources with which to rebuild their lives and are usually
better prepared.
5. False. Although some people might encourage us to believe that looting and other forms of
selfish behaviour are common following disasters, it has been shown that disaster situa¬
tions bring out the best in people and solidarity is strengthened.
6. False. Dead bodies do not cause epidemics or disease transmission during the first 72 hours;
after this, the decomposition process may cause contamination of water supplies. First pri¬
ority following a disaster should be to care for the injured.
7. True. Disasters such as earthquakes do not damage crops although drought, hurricanes
and floods do. However, if adequate preparations such as storage and rationing of foods have
been properly organized, there should not be any serious hunger. When international assistance
is requested, seeds and tools are often more important than food.
8. True. Keeping people as close to their homes as possible is best; settlement camps should
be a last resort since they create other problems. International assistance in the form of
building materials and tools may be desirable.
9. False. Careful rationing should be organized so that everyone is fed. Those involved in sal¬
vage work and reconstruction are particularly in need of a regular food supply.
10. False. Team work is the most efficient way of dealing with the aftermath of disaster. Train¬
ing of teams prior to a disaster so that each person knows his or her responsibilities is indis¬
pensable for the proper management of a disaster.
11. True. Strict adherence to the building code in earthquake-prone areas significantly dimin¬
ishes the loss of human life.
12. True. Overgrazing, a failure to plant trees and mismanagement of land use lead to soil ero¬
sion. In the Sahel, when added to the effects of climate change, all this means an advance of
the desert.
34 > G,uTHE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO AND NATURAL DISASTER REDUCTION
UNESCO's Unit for Disaster Reduction seeks to encourage the adoption of
policies and action designed to anticipate potential risks and favouring a
shift in emphasis away from post-disaster reaction and response toward
pre-disaster planning, preparedness and prevention.
For further information:
Unit for Disaster Reduction
Bureau for Coordination of Environmental Programmes
Science Sector
Unesco, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 41 20. Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 58 30
Email: b.rouhban@unesco.org
Documentation available on request:
Standing up to natural disasters, 1991 (also in French and Spanish)
Many Unesco programmes have proven experience
in the scientific study of natural hazards. They include:
THE INTERNATIONAL HYDROLOGICAL PROGRAMME (IHP)
IHP is designed to improve management of the world's freshwater
resources. Its activities include
improving scientific knowledge of the water cycle
gathering information, e.g. on climate, surface and groundwater con¬
ditions, and water use
helping train personnel that will minimize risks in hazardous situations
developing models and observing systems to help forecast river floods
and storm surges
International Hydrological Programme (IHP)
Division of Water Sciences
Unesco, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 40 44. Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 58 11
Email: ihp@unesco.org
Internet: http://www.pangea.org/orgs/unesco/
THE MAN AND THE BIOSPHERE (MAB) PROGRAMME
MAB studies long-term natural hazards such as drought and human-
induced desertification. These can can be just as devastating as rapid-
onset events, but reducing their impact calls for a different set of skills,
particularly the fostering of greater ecological and social awareness. MAB
projects to mitigate the effects of drought and desertification in Africa
have notably concerned the Sahel countries and the Turkana region of
Kenya.
Programme on Man and the Biosphere (MAB)
Division of Ecological Sciences
Unesco, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 41 51. Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 58 04
Email: mab@unesco.org
Internet: http://www.unesco.org:80//mab/themabnet.html
THE INTERNATIONAL GEOLOGICAL CORRELATION PROGRAMME
(IGCP)
To understand the changes which will affect the future of the earth's con¬
tinents and islands, it is necessary to study past and present geological
processes. IGCP, a joint venture of UNESCO and the International Union
of Geological Sciences (IUGS), compares and correlates geological processes,
events and formations, including rocks, fossils and mineral deposits. Pro¬
jects make use of and contribute to the further development of scientific
knowledge and technology, from deep-core drilling to space imagery.
International Geological Correlation Programme (IGCP)
Division of Earth Sciences
Unesco, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 58 22
THE INTERGOVERNMENTAL OCEANOGRAPHIC COMMISSION
(IOC)
In 1965, in the aftermath of the great destruction caused by the tsunami
which struck the coast of Chile on 22 May 1960, the IOC accepted an offer
made by the United States to expand its Tsunami Warning Center in Hon¬
olulu to become the headquarters of an International Pacific Tsunami Warn¬
ing System. Today 25 nations belong to the Pacific System, plus some terri¬
tories that maintain stations for it. Besides the main Centre in Honolulu, there
are regional tsunami warning centres in Alaska, Japan, Russia, Chile and
French Polynesia which transmit warnings in their respective areas.
Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission (IOC)
Unesco, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 58 12. Email: i.oliounine@unesco.org
Internet: http://www.unesco.org/loc
International Tsunami Information Centre (I0C/1TIC)
737 Bishop Street, Suite 2200,
Honolulu, Hawaii 96813, U.S.A.
Tel: (1-808) 532 64 22. Fax: (1-808) 532 55 76. Email: itic@itic.noaa.gov
THE DIVISION OF CULTURAL HERITAGE
When disaster strikes, the cost of losing part of the cultural heritage must
be added to the toll of human life and suffering. If requested, UNESCO
will intervene and advise on restoration or safeguarding of the cultural her¬
itage. Some of the best-known international campaigns for cultural soli¬
darity have had their starting point in the emergency that followed a nat¬
ural disaster.
Division of Cultural Heritage
Culture Sector
Unesco, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 55 96
THE EDUCATIONAL BUILDINGS PROGRAMME
One of the main activities of UNESCO's educational buildings programme
is the development and design of educational structures able to withstand
disaster forces. Practical advice is given on how to build schools that will
be relatively safe if a natural disaster occurs. UNESCO damage-assessment
and rehabilitation missions to disaster-stricken countries have led to the
development of schools that can be used as refuge and relief centres.
Architecture for Education Section
Education Sector
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 09 06. Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 56 31
INTERNETADDRESSES
IDNDR Internet Conferences: http://www.quipu.net/
International Decade for Natural Disaster Reduction:
http://hoshi.cic. sfu.ca.hazard/idndr.html
Emergency Preparedness Information Exchange (EPIX):
http://hoshi.cic.sfu.ca/epix
Environmental Organisation Web Division Disasters:
http://www.wcb.directory.com/disasters
Global Emergency Management Disaster Counselling Support Network:
http://tin.ssc.plym.ac.uk/gemc.html
Natural Hazards Research and Applications Information Centre, University of
Colorado: http://adder.colorado.edu/hazctr/home.html
Pan American Health Organization (PAHO/WHO) Emergency Preparedness:
http://www.paho.org
US Agency for International Development (USAID): http://www.info.usaid.gov
US Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA): http://hoshi.cic.sfu.ca. hazard
Volunteers in Technical Assistance (VITA): http://www.vita.org
OTHER ADDRESSES
IDNDR Regional Office for Latin American and the Caribbean
Apartado 3745-1000. San José, Costa Rica
Tel: (506) 257 2141. Fax: (506) 257 2139
Email: hmolin@undpcos.nu.or.cr
Documentation available on request:
IDNDR Informs (Newsletter, also in Spanish)
"Stop Disasters" International Institute
Via di Pozzuoli 110, "Villa Medusa". 80124 Naples, Italy
Tel/fax: (39-81) 570 6340
Sources: IDNDR Secretariat and IDNDR Disaster Preparedness and Response: An Audit of UK
Assets, D. Sanderson, I. Davis, J. Twlgg, B. Cowden, Oxford Centre for Disaster
Studies/Intermediate Technology, 1995.
THE UNESCO f3>URI ER OCTOBER 1997
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
commentary Federico Mayor
ater and
Water and civilization are indissociable. The earliest civiliza¬
tions arose in the great river valleys of the Euphrates, the Nile,
the Indus and the Yangtze, where the transition could be made
from subsistence farming to agricultural surplus. Today, the
future of the world's water supplies depends on the civilized
use of this finite and vulnerable resource.
Human civilization is a response to challenge, and I take a
more optimistic view of the water crisis than the prophets of
doom who speculate on the prospect of resource wars in the cen¬
tury to come. Water scarcity can be a source of conflict among
competing users, particularly where combined with other fac¬
tors of political or cultural tension. But it can also be an induce¬
ment to co-operation, as evidenced by the growing number of
water allocation agreements today being signed and imple¬
mented, even in high-tension areas. I believe that human civi¬
lization can find within itself the resources to respond suc¬
cessfully to this global challenge.
To say this is not to underestimate the scale of the challenge
facing us. The warning signs are clear: severe water scarcity in many
regions of the world, falling water tables, shrinking rivers and
lakes, widespread pollution, creeping desertification. To these we
must add the human cost of water shortage malnutrition, dis¬
ease, abandonment of rural areas, swollen urban settlements and
the increased burden placed on women in water-scarce environ¬
ments. All this and the need to remain alert to the threat of
climate change adds up to a challenge of the first magnitude.
In this century, total world demand for water has increased
seven-fold. This compares with a three-fold increase in world
population over the same period. The fact that demand for
water in this century has increased at twice the rate of popu¬
lation growth underlines the point that changes in lifestyle
linked to socio-economic development are the principal source
of increased water use. This is bad news inasmuch as demand
will continue to accelerate as living standards worldwide hope¬
fully improve. But it is good news inasmuch as it points to a sub¬
stantial margin for water savings through the modification of our
priorities, policies and practices.
civilization
Fresh water represents 0.26 per cent of the total water
mass on the surface of the earth 0.007 per cent if we discount
groundwater resources and polar ice. This scarce resource,
essential for life, must be seen asa natural treasure, as part of
the common heritage of humankind.
To provide for foreseeable future needs, water resources
development must be placed at the top of national and inter¬
national agendas. New water projects conceived in an eco¬
logically sensitive way take from fifteen to twenty years to
plan and implement. If we delay, the pressure to quench the
thirst of needy people in water-scarce environments may force
the recourse to ecologically or otherwise unsound projects. In
many parts of the world, the solution of water problems should
orient the formulation of socio-economic development goals.
Integrated river basin and watershed planning and manage¬
ment at scales ranging from the regional to the international are
an important element in such a strategy.
A new ethic
Everywhere, water resources development must go hand in
hand with energetic policies for conservation, re-use and the
elimination of all forms of wastage. Better technical informa¬
tion and the deployment of new technologies have an important
part to play in the more rational management of water use.
Yet it is doubtful whether technical solutions alone are suffi¬
cient to achieve a sustainable relationship between supply and
demand. The challenge posed by the water crisis is ultimately
one of values.
This has important implications for our decision-making
processes in the environment and development field. I am a
strong believer in the need to increase scientific input and the
participation of scientists in policy making at all levels. But we
should not entertain the illusion that the solution to problems
lies in perfect data. In a world of uncertainty, data are never
complete. In the hydrological field, for example, there is an
increasing awareness that our emphasis on measures of averages
and trends has led us to underestimate the impact of extreme
36
THE UNESCO ^>URIIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
events and random climate changes. To put off making urgent
decisions on the grounds that all the data are not available is
to forget that time in the form of irreversible events has an
ethical dimension. The perfect diagnosis is an autopsy. But a
post mortem review of water and civilization is something we
cannot afford.
Dealing with uncertainty and risk is part of the human con¬
dition. This is why, while daring without knowledge is risky,
knowledge without daring is fruitless. Daring, caring and shar¬
ing are among the human parameters within which solutions to
the water crisis will be found.
One aspect of technological progress that is worth noting is
its role in the creation of transboundary networks of co-oper¬
ation and solidarity. New forms of software and visual display
are now facilitating the joint creation of water resource mod¬
els by political and technical stakeholders. Satellite technol¬
ogy gives countries and authorities the ability to build a fairly
accurate picture of water flow in other jurisdictions. This tech¬
nological capability is transforming the relationships and nego¬
tiations among jurisdictions and is being disseminated and
democratized faster than anyone could have foreseen.
To address the problem at source, we need to promote a new
attitude to water I would go so far as to speak of a new water
ethic. Pricing policies and market mechanisms although they
pose some difficult problems of social equity and public
accountability clearly have a role to play in the revaluation of
water and a reduction of demand. But so too does education.
Cross-frontier agreements
Education for water awareness has a rich imaginative heritage
on which to draw. Water connects us. It connects us by flowing
across imposed boundaries, by linking diverse terrains and set¬
tlements. In religion, myth and legend, water is a universal sym¬
bol of wholeness and purification. It is the original element, a
source of life, a metaphor for natural and mental process, the
image of all that unites us in time and space. This civiliza-
tional inheritance is one that education can and must turn to
account.
Of course, the problems with which water management has
to contend are very complex . They include a whole range of com¬
peting interest groups and established structures of rights,
values and priorities. Reconciling differences and reforming
structures to take account of new realities implies difficult
legal, administrative and investment changes. It risks pitting dif¬
ferent constituencies such as urban and agricultural com¬
munities against one another.
The situation is even more complicated at the international
level, where differences of perceived interest may be greater,
traditions more divergent, and the search for agreement vitiated
by political tensions. Here, we need to be aware of the water-
sharing rules and traditions to be found in most cultures. The
sharia Islamic law embodies precepts for water use and
public water management as well as community-based conflict
management strategies. The Jewish tradition includes similar
prescriptions for not prejudicing the interests of other river-
dwellers. Shared principles of this kind can provide a useful
basis for the building of cross-frontier agreements.
Throughout history, human beings have responded to the
need to pool their efforts and share resources in the interests
of larger security. Water, in particular, has been one of human¬
ity's historic learning grounds for community building, and we
should see it as a potential source not of conflict but of agree¬
ments that can serve as a paradigm for the constructive shar¬
ing of knowledge and resources essential for the transition from
a culture of war to a culture of peace.
A resource to be shared
UNESCO's International Hydrological Programme (HIP), which
was launched some twenty years ago and is the only science
and education programme within the United Nations system
devoted to freshwater problems, addresses most of these issues
in association with its many governmental and non-governmen¬
tal partners. Its main concern is with the promotion of techni¬
cal co-operation worldwide: upgrading hydrological knowledge
and research capacities in our Member States; working with
bodies such as the World Climate Programme to understand the
links between hydrological processes and climate change;
studying with our Man and the Biosphere programme factors
of vulnerability in the land-water system; assessing problems of
groundwater contamination; examining hydrological processes
in arid zones and the humid tropics; and supporting post¬
graduate hydrology courses for participants from the developing
world.
At the same time, taking advantage of UNESCO's position at
the crossroads of science, education, culture and communica¬
tion, the IHP also ranges more widely. For example, it analyses
needs for integrated urban and freshwater resources develop¬
ment as in the case of our recently launched project in the his¬
toric city of Essaouira (Morocco). Under its auspices, we are also
instituting a new interdisciplinary programme entitled Water
and Civilization. Conceived as part of UNESCO's broader Culture
of Peace programme, it will include among other things a com¬
ponent aimed at providing technical support for water-related
conflict resolution.
The water issue is vast and diverse in its implications. Water
is life, and life is sharing. Let water be a source of life , of mutu¬
ality, of progress. Let it irrigate the smiles of our children and
their children, testifying that we, the inhabitants of planet earth
on the threshold of a new millennium, have proved equal to the
ethical, political and scientific challenges of our time. M
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
threats to
New Caledonia:
iodiversity
by France Bequette
Oro Bay on the Isle
of Pines.
New Caledonia is a French
Territoire d'outre mer (over¬
seas territory forming part of the
French Republic) in the southern
part of Melanesia, half-way between
Australia and New Zealand. Unlike
its neighbours Vanuatu, the Solomon
Islands and Fiji, the island is not of
volcanic origin but became separate
from the great landmass of Gond-
wana 80 million years ago, whereas
the 1,600-km barrier reef sur¬
rounding it and the three Loyalty
Islands of Mare, Lifou and Ouvéa
were formed much more recently. A
range of mountains runs down the
centre of New Caledonia, which is
nicknamed "Ze Caillou" (the Rock).
With an area of about 19,000 sq.
km., the main island oí Grande Terre
is slightly smaller than Wales but has
only 165,000 inhabitants, of whom
65,000 live in the capital, Nouméa. It
is a place of diversity in every respect,
starting with population, since
Kanaks, Wallis Islanders, Indonesians,
Ni-Vanuatu, Arabs and Europeans
live there side by side. It is ranked
fourth in the world for its biological
diversity and second for the extent of
its coral reefs and atolls. It has 3,250
species of flowering plants (76% of
them endemic to the island), 4,500
invertebrates, 148 birds and many
species of reptiles such as turtles,
lizards and geckos. But unfortunately
this haven of wildlife is being gravely
threatened by human activities.
The landscape is very varied.
While the south and west of the island
are relatively dry (1 to 1.5 metres of
rainfall a year), average annual rain¬
fall in the east is between 1.5 and 3.5
metres (and as much as 8 metres on
the island's highest mountain, Mont
Panié), and it is in that part of the
island that the lush tropical vegeta¬
tion, the thousands of streams, the
famous colonial pines (of the Arau¬
caria family), tree ferns and orchids
are found.
RICH PLANT AND ANIMAL LIFE
According to the American non-gov¬
ernmental organization Conservation
International, research carried out
© ~ . ^^ - *
by botanists Norman Myers and Russ
Mittermayer, the organization's Pres¬
ident, show that New Caledonia is
one of the richest places in the world
in terms of biodiversity, and one of
the places where biodiversity is most
threatened.
The fauna of New Caledonia is
typical of a remote island. There are
many endemic, species. Out of 116
species of nesting birds, 18 are
endemic. The most extraordinary of
them, the big grey woodland bird
known as the kagu (Rhynochetos
jubatus) is the country's emblem.
Like the extinct Mauritian dodo, it
is flightless and thus an easy prey for
wild dogs and cats. Today, like the
Hawaiian goose (Branta sandvicen-
sis), it survives only because it is care¬
fully protected, having been made
the subject of an active conservation
policy in 1990. Luckily for the bird,
it is not a gastronomic delicacy and is
not hunted, unlike the notu (Duculia
goliath), the world's largest pigeon.
The island is also home to the largest
known gecko, the Rhacodactylus
leachianus. As regards insects, 4,000
species have so far been recorded but
no-one can tell whether this repre¬
sents half or even a fifth of those actu¬
ally living in New Caledonia. No thor¬
ough study of the island's fungi has
yet been carried out.
The most serious threat to the
island's vegetation is that affecting
the dry (sclerophyllous) forest on
the eastern side, of which only 2%
remains, in isolated clumps. Its dis¬
appearance is due to the combined
effects of forest fires, encroachment
by grazing lands and urbanization,
and introduced species such as the
Timor deer (Certrts timorensis), the
population of which has grown since
the end of the last century to nearly
110,000 and which trample or eat
the saplings, preventing any regen¬
eration of the forest cover. The rain¬
forest and scrub which cover 20%
38
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
and 24% respectively of the terri¬
tory represent the principal habitat
of the endemic plant species (88%
and 81% respectively). Some of
these species are now only repre¬
sented by a few specimens, while
others have disappeared altogether.
Conversely, a new species of wild rice
(Oryza neocaledonica) was identi¬
fied in 1994 near Pouembout, which
goes to show that much remains to
be done before a complete inventory
is made.
Research is also being conducted
to determine on an objective basis
the therapeutic value of plants used
in traditional medicine. The Kanak
have, for instance, treated the trop¬
ical food poisoning known as ciguat¬
era (see box) for centuries with an
infusion of the leaves of the false
tobacco plant (Argusia argéntea) or
a maceration of the false pepper tree
(Schinus terebenthifolius). Although
the toxins causing this illness have
been isolated, no Western medical
treatment is capable of curing it, let
alone preventing it.
'FIRE PAINTS
THE MOUNTAIN BLACK'
A drive through the country will show
whether the pessimism expressed by
Conservation International over the
state of nature conservation in New
Caledonia is justified. The road from
Nouméa to Koumac runs along the
west coast of the main island. Bare
\ - 1 \
Y\u
/ 1^1 \\ 1
t 1 )\
umii
ft 1 i ill /V\|l I JA
A flooded forest in
the artificial lake
behind Yaté dam.
hillsides with occasional patches of
vivid green forest dominate the savan¬
nah from which emerge the white
trunks of the niaoulis (Melaleuca
quinquenervia), close relatives of the
eucalyptus, and large trees grow in
profusion along the river banks, but
the countryside has been ravaged by
fire. Plumes of smoke and the scars
left by previous conflagrations are a
constant reminder that fire is an ever-
present danger (it rages through more
than 50,000 hectares every year). Its
main causes are carelessness, slash-
and-burn cultivation, the setting of
fires to flush out game animals or
exterminate rats and other vermin,
CIGUATERA
Ciguatera , the tropical food poisoning commonly known as "la gratte''''
or "the itch" because of the pruritis it often causes, affects all the trop¬
ical regions, from the Caribbean to the islands of the Indian Ocean, hut
is particularly widespread in the south Pacific. In 1993, it was estimated
that in Nouméa and the adjacent area alone nearly 20,000 people
25% of the population had contracted it at least once.
The illness is caused by eating reef-dwelling tropical fish conta¬
minated by the microalgae (Gambierdiscus toxicus) which prolifer¬
ate when coral reefs are disturbed by natural causes such as cyclones
or earthquakes or by human activity such as coastal land-use devel¬
opment, the building of sea walls and marinas or the extraction of sand
from the lagoons.
As the toxins accumulate in the food chain, consumers have also
to be wary of large carnivorous fish like barracuda, loach, moray eel
or shark, and, in badly infested areas, offish at the bottom end of the
chain, parrotfish and surgeonfish. The food poisoning in itself is usu¬
ally mild, but the digestive, neurological and cardio-vascular disor¬
ders it brings on can, in serious cases, cause paralysis, coma and even
death.
Plants grown in
this nursery will
bring greenery to
slopes disfigured
by mining.
c
the burning of rubbish, and arson,
and its results are impoverishment of
the soil, the acceleration of erosion,
shrinkage of natural forests, the dis¬
appearance of unique plants and the
destruction of the nests of rare birds
and insects. Everything burns, even
the sheerest mountain sides. "Fire
paints the mountain black," say the
Kanak. Only the tropical rainforest
areas manage to resist.
STRIP MINING
Respect also needs to be shown for
New Caledonia's soil, which is
extremely rich in nickel, chromium,
cobalt, manganese and lead all of
them usually toxic for plants. Nickel
(probably the world's biggest deposit),
discovered here in 1864, is so abun¬
dant that the country is one of the
world's largest producers, and stocks
are nowhere near exhausted. When
ore was found on the tops and slopes
of the mountains, the early mine-own¬
ers did not hesitate to strip them bare.
From far off, the access roads look
liter:
THE UNESCO ^>UR1IER OCTOBER 1997
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
These niaouli
trees, left, have
survived a fire.
like great steps cut into an orange
pyramid.
Until the 1970s, spoil from the
mines was unceremoniously shoved
down the mountain sides , taking with
it the thin layer of fertile humus.
Planting of the spoil-heaps is now
being carried out by private compa¬
nies, in collaboration with ORSTOM
(the French government agency for
overseas scientific and technical
research) and CIRAD (France's Inter¬
national Co-operation Centre of Agri¬
cultural Research for Development),
using local species specially chosen
for their capacity to tolerate heavy
metals and fix nitrogen, but the task
is a mammoth one. Furthermore, the
alumina and iron oxide leached out
by the rains pollute first the rivers
then the coral lagoons. .
UNRELIABLE PROTECTION
Another problem is erosion: the rate
in New Caledonia is one of the highest
in the world, since the effects of min¬
ing are combined with those of defor¬
estation. Sandalwood, rosewood and
the tall kauri trees (Aguthis lanceo-
lata) have all but disappeared. There
is still a single giant kauri, the sole
surviving witness to a bygone age, in
Rivière Bleue Park, south of Nouméa.
Some 800 years old, 40 metres tall
and with a trunk nearly three metres
in diameter, it has become a visitor
attraction. The Park, which forms
part of the 15,900-hectare Haute
Yaté wildlife reserve, covers 9,045
hectares. In one spot, a forest has been
engulfed by the Yaté reservoir, from
whose bright blue waters emerge tree-
trunks seemingly carved out of ivory.
In another, the botanical reserve of
the Chutes de la Madeleine, the local
authorities have, to the fury of ecol-
ogists, laid out a recreation area with
shelters , barbecues and toilets . Even
worse, Neocallitropsis araucarioides
trees belonging to a rare species with
a distinctive twisted shape, which
were probably a thousand years old,
once grew near to the river but have
been felled for their perfumed essen¬
tial oils.
Fires, mining and poaching are
wreaking slow but sure destruction
upon natural sites of exceptional
value in New Caledonia. Small areas
and pockets have, it is true, been
declared land-based or marine
reserves, but do they really provide
protection? The delisting, in 1980,
of the Oro peninsula nature reserve
on the Ile des Pins shows just how
unreliable such protection is. A
hotel complex will soon occupy this
exceptionally beautiful site, once a
sacred Kanak burial-ground
prompting Russ Mittermayer to
remark that, in New Caledonia, the
protection of the environment is not
a priority. I
The extension of
grazing land for
cattle farming,
above, is one of
the many causes
of deforestation.
A mining site on
the east coast
near Poindlmié.
40
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
initiatives
!
In defence of New Caledonia
The Association for the Protection of Nature in New Caledonia
(ASNNC), which was founded in 1971, is one of many local organi¬
zations that act to protect the environment on Grande Terre. It has
4,000 members, and publishes and distributes free of charge a
news magazine {Le Journal vert) and educational material. It also car¬
ries out a range of field activities, including a recent operation on the
islets to the north of Grande Terre to tag loggerhead turtles [Caretta
caretta), which are eaten during traditional ceremonies and hunted
by poachers. ASNNC has taken steps to have these islets classified
as a reserve, but the declassification of the Oro Peninsula in 1980
for the construction of a hotel complex (scheduled for completion in
1998) raises the spectre that similar kinds of declassification could
happen again, especially since legislation does not oblige promot¬
ers to carry out impact studies on the coastline. ASNNC hopes that
a Biosphere Reserve will one day be established m Kouakoué mas¬
sif in the southeastern part of the island. This would be tangible evi¬
dence that New Caledonia is taking part in the world-wide move
ment for the conservation and sustainable development of natural
resources.
In 1992 breakaway members of ASNNC started a new associ¬
ation named Action Biosphère, whose activists alert the authorities
and public opinion whenever they think a project is a threat to the envi¬
ronment. One of the cases they are dealing with at the moment
arises from the presence of Australian Red Claw crayfish (Cherax
quadricannatus) which have been illegally introduced to the island.
The introduction of new species to a biotope is usually detrimental
to one or more Indigenous species, especially when the new species
is predatory. These crayfish are especially hardy and prolific and
are dangerous to the local fauna. One threatened local species is a
very rare fish (Nesogalaxias neocaledonicus), a veritable living fos¬
sil that dates back 135 million years.
ASNNC, BP 1772, 98 802 Nouméa.
Tel. and fax: 00 687 28 32 75.
Action Biosphère, BP 120, 98 810 Mont Dore,
New Caledonia. Tel. and fax: 00 687 41 83 87.
CITY SPECIAL
World Resources 1996-9 7, A guide to the global envi¬
ronment, the 7th report in a series produced by the
Washington-based World Resources Institute, devotes
a special section to urban environmental problems
in developed and developing countries, and analy¬
ses policies for addressing them. The second part of
the report surveys trends in population growth,
forests and land cover, food and agriculture, health,
water and fisheries, atmosphere and climate. Core
data is provided for 152 countries. This valuable tool
for all concerned with environmental issues is avail¬
able from the World Resources Institute, 1709 New
York Ave. N.W., Washington, DC, 20006, U.S.A. I
REMEMBERING IRELAND'S POTATO
FAMINE
On 1 June 1997, the UN Food and Agriculture Orga¬
nization (FAO) commemorated the potato famine
that raged in Ireland between 1846 and 1850, claim¬
ing the lives of over a million people and forcing at
least as many to emigrate. During this period, a fun¬
gus known as "late blight" (Phytophthora infestans)
devastated the potato crop, the main source of food
in Ireland. FAO took this opportunity to recall the
dangers of genetic uniformity, which leaves crops
susceptible to attack by pests and diseases, and to
underline the importance of protecting biological
diversity for farming and food production.
MANATEES IN DANGER
In 1996, biologists counted a record 2,600 mana¬
tees off the Florida coast but also a record 415 car¬
casses. A large number of the aquatic mammals
were killed by motorboats. In 1997, despite a mild
winter and a smaller number of reported carcasses,
the observed manatee population had dropped to
2,229. There are fears that the species is heading for
extinction in the U.S.A. Enforcing motorboat speed
limits would be one way to start protecting them,
but is the manatee lobby strong enough?
ENVIRONMENT-FRIENDLY DOG
With its turquoise lagoon, white sand beaches and
forests dominated by 40-metre-high araucarias, the
Ile des Pins (Isle of Pines) is a well-known vacation
paradise located south of New Caledonia. But tourists
do not always keep it tidy, and their tendency to leave
litter along the roadside and on beaches led islander
Roland Kaatheu to start an association named "Des¬
tination Paradise, Clean Island". A big black dog
called Police has become an unlikely ally in his war
on litter. When Police is riding on a litter-picking truck
and spots a can on the ground, he jumps down, picks
it up and adds it to the pile in the back of the vehicle.
Roland trained Police to do this job because he
thought it was wrong to get schoolchildren to collect
the litter left by adults.
PESTICIDES WARNING
In many developing countries, unsafe use of pesti¬
cides of chemical origin is a serious threat to health
and the environment. According to FAO, farm work¬
ers are in the front line because they often do not
know enough about pesticides, cannot read instruc¬
tions on handling, do not wear masks or protective
clothing and use spraying equipment in poor condi¬
tion. Groundwater pollution caused by indiscrimi¬
nate use of pesticides is spreading in some coun¬
tries. For many years, FAO has been recommending
integrated pest management, especially through the
introduction of insects. Until plant-based pesticides
like pyrethrum are more extensively used, FAO is
appealing for "good, standard quality equipment and
operator training".
SWITZERLAND'S DRY MEADOWS
Since the 1950s, Switzerland's dry meadows have
become increasingly endangered. Today an estimated
40% of their flora are threatened throughout the coun¬
try and 70% on the Plateau or Moyen Pays. "About
13% of Swiss plants, representing over 350 species,
are found on the dry meadows and grasslands", says
Switzerland's Federal Office for the Environment,
Forests and Landscape. "Since the average plant
hosts over ten animal species, the diversity of the
fauna in these areas is easy to imagine. About half
the country's butterfly species depend on this type of
environment." Contrary to a widely held belief, these
meadows have to be grazed or cut every two or three
years for their rich flora to survive.
GREEN TAXES
Taxes, charges and auctioned permits are the main
economic instruments used in environmental policy.
The Organization for Economic Co-operation and Devel¬
opment (OECD) has published a report evaluating the
effectiveness of these tools and how they work in its
Member States. In Sweden, sulphur taxes introduced
in 1991 have resulted in a 40% drop below legal norms
of sulphur contents in oil-based fuels. In Australia,
Canada, Denmark, Finland and Sweden, the promotion
of lead-free fuel and catalytic exhausts led to such a
steep fall in the consumption of leaded fuel that the lat¬
ter was pulled off the market. In several American
cities, unit charging for household refuse disposal
has reduced the volume of household waste.
THE UNLSCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
HERITAGE
AXILA the cradle of Gandhara art
by Laurence Gourret
Afghanistan
Traces of several ancient civilizations of the north
Indus basin have survived in present-day Pakistan at
Taxila, a site that was included on the World Heritage
List in 1980
LThe archaeological site of
Taxila, which lies in a well-
irrigated, fertile valley forty kilo¬
metres from Pakistan's capital,
Islamabad, hears the traces of unin¬
terrupted human occupation
extending hack 6,000 years. It
emerged onto the arena of history
during the second millennium B . C . ,
when the snake-worshipping Takka
people chose it as the site for their
city, Takshasila (in Sanskrit, "hill
of Takshaka", the serpent-prince).
Its rapid development in the course
of the following millennium was due
to its exceptionally advantageous
geographical situation at the junc¬
tion of three great trade routes link¬
ing the Indian subcontinent with
central and western Asia, and to the
introduction of iron-working tech¬
niques in the Gandhara region, of
which it became the capital.
In the sixth century B.C., Gand¬
hara was absorbed into the Persian
empire of the Achaemenids. The
city drew great economic and cul-
Meditating Buddha,
a stone sculpture in
the Jaulian monastery
(Gandhara art,
2nd century A.D.).
tural benefit from this contact with
the West, among other advances
developing a system for transcribing
vernacular Sanskrit, later replaced
by the Brahmi script. Next, Alexan¬
der the Great's conquest of the Per¬
sian empire marked the beginning
of Hellenistic influence on the city,
which was to give rise to an original
art, that of Gandhara.
There were four decisive phases
in Taxila's development: the Indian
dynasty of the Maurya (c. 321-189
B.C.), the Greeks of Bactria (189-50
B.C.), the Parthians (50 B.C. -60
A.D.), and domination by the pow¬
erful Central Asian Kushan dynasty
(until c. 230 A.D.). Thereafter the
city's political decline, as a result of
dynastic quarrels, led on to its eco¬
nomic and cultural decline, which
was precipitated by the incursions of
the Huns in the fifth century.
Taxila , which was excavated by
British archaeologists in the latter
part of the nineteenth century and
the early years of the twentieth,
contains the vestiges of three suc¬
cessive towns and many small monas¬
tic sites, bearing witness to the
refined nature of the city's spiri¬
tual and cultural life during its hal¬
cyon days.
THE FIRST CITY: BHIR
Bhir was the first urban community
on the Taxila site (sixth to second
centuries B.C.). When Alexander
the Great arrived there in 326 B.C. ,
he found the main street badly
paved and unprepossessing and the
architecture rudimentary, the
houses built of stones bonded with
mud, the roofs flat and the walls
vividly painted but without windows
on to the street. The town had a
central refuse tip and a network of
open drains, but no wells. The
inhabitants drew water straight
from the river, which was where
they washed themselves and did
their laundry.
In the third century B.C.,
Asoka, the grandson of Chan-
dragupta, founder of the Mauryan
dynasty, converted to Buddhism.
He built the great stupa of Dhar-
marajika, placing therein the relics
of the Buddha in a golden casket.
Vandals many times mutilated the
sacred edifice as they vainly
searched for this casket. Over the
years, the stupa was enlarged by
the addition of large numbers of
other religious structures (small
votive stupas, chapels, etc.).
42
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Cattle graze among
archaeological
remains on the Taxila
site.
FURTHER READING:
Taxila, by Ahmad Hasan
Dani, UNESCO/The Centre
for East Asian Cultural
Studies, Paris/Tokyo,
1986
"Taxila: ancient
university centre of the
Orient", by SyedAshfaq
Naqvi, Uhesco Courier,
October 1972
This monument was largely
destroyed by an earthquake in 30
A.D., but it was rebuilt and its
imposing mass (15 metres high and
50 in diameter) was shored up by
several retaining walls, which resem¬
ble the spokes radiating out from
the hub of a wheel and thus recall
the dharma-cakra (the wheel of
law), from which the site complex
takes its name.
The surrounding wall of the
stupa, embellished with painted
and gilded statues of the Buddha,
dates from early in the second cen¬
tury A.D. Further north, all that
remains are the ruins of a monastery
that had a hundred monks' cells.
It was completely sacked by the
Huns in 455 A.D.
THE PARTHIAN CITY: SIRKAP
Sirkap (second century B.C. to first
century A.D.), the second town on
the Taxila site, is half an hour's
walk north from the site of Bhir.
Excavations have brought to light
the city walls, dating from various
periods, including those built by
the Parthians in the first century
A.D., which were six metres thick,
had tall bastions and were in places
nine metres in height.
When Saint Thomas, who
brought the Gospel to India, vis¬
ited the Parthian king Gondophares
in 47 A.D., he found a flourishing
town where caravans from China,
India and the distant western lands
all met. Unlike Bhir, Sirkap was
built according to a plan, with
streets regularly laid out along two
perpendicular north-south and east-
west axes. Scattered among its
huge, rectangular dwelling-houses,
in the oriental style, with rooms
arranged around an open central
courtyard, were Jain stupas, Bud¬
dhist altars and private chapels.
Like Bhir, Sirkap had neither wells
nor mains drainage. The main thor¬
oughfare was lined by a large num¬
ber of open-fronted shops with
wooden stalls. Numerous Greek-
inspired objects have been exca¬
vated, including a silver head of
Dion) sos and a cornelian seal with
representations of Eros and Psyche.
One particularly remarkable
stupa, known as the shrine of the
double-headed eagle (first century
A.D.), provides a perfect illustration
of the fusion of Indian and Greek
styles: pilasters with Corinthian cap¬
itals, recesses decorated in a man-
nerinspired by Greek architecture,
and Bengali-style roofs. A similar
cross-fertilization of cultures is evi¬
dent in the sculpted representation
of the Buddha and bodhisattvas at
the foot of the votive stupas. The
way in which the robes hang, the
smiles and the facial features, exe¬
cuted in accordance with the stan¬
dards of the Hellenistic school, are
combined with the traditional med¬
itative poses of Buddhist art.
On the Jandial site, near the
northern gate, are the ruins of two
temples built by the Bactrian
Greeks. Pillaged by the Scythians
in the second century A.D., they
disappeared in the earthquake of
30 A.D.
THE KUSHAN CITY: SIRSUKH
Sirsukh (first to fifth centuries
A.D.), the last of the three fortified
towns on the Taxila site, was the
regional capital of the Kushan, who
originally came from Central Asia
and brought to Taxila their own
ideas of town-building and their own
construction methods. We have less
information about the life of the
inhabitants than in the case of
Sirkap since few excavations have
been carried out here. It neverthe¬
less appears that Gandhara art ben¬
efitted considerably from the con¬
tributions made by the Kushan,
who encouraged local sculptors and
promoted the development of Bud¬
dhist monasteries.
Taxila's decline, resulting from
internal dynastic dissension, began
at the end of the second century
A.D. The town seems to have
3 QuTHE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
HERITAGE
escaped the Sassanid invasions,
although Sassanid influence may be
discerned, particularly in the
coinage. The preponderant influ¬
ence thereafter was Indian. The
Brahmi script came into use, Hindu
divinities like Shiva and Vishnu
made their appearance in local stat¬
uary art, and the influence of clas¬
sical Gupta art made itself felt in
that of Gandhara. Taxila 's economic
and cultural ruin was, however,
largely due to the Huns, who swept
into Gandhara in the middle of the
fifth century.
MONASTERIES
Taxila also became an influential
centre of Buddhism. It was said to
be here that the Buddha, emaci¬
ated by the long practice of asceti¬
cism, beheaded himself, as a sym¬
bolic gesture denoting the
renunciation even of thinking, in
order to attain illumination. Stu¬
dents came from all over northern
India to follow the many courses of
study on offer, which in addition to
Mahayana Buddhism included the
teaching of the Vedas, military sci¬
ence, medicine, law, political econ¬
omy, astronomy, mathematics, the
arts and letters. Among the students
was the celebrated Indian gram¬
marian Panini (c. 400 B.C.).
As well as the sites of the three
fortified towns, Taxila contains those
of many Buddhist monastic estab¬
lishments which testify to its reli¬
gious significance. Scattered about
beyond the walls of the three towns
but always built near to a spring,
most of them date back to the
Kushan and post-Kushan periods.
Dharmarajika is undoubtedly the
most important of them, but men¬
tion should also be made of the
monasteries of Khader Mohra and
Akhauri, which, with two others,
form the four corners of a vast
quadrilateral with sides measuring
between 400 and 500 metres. Prob¬
ably erected in the Kushan period,
these builldings show signs of a cer¬
tain evolution in monastic architec¬
ture. In three of them, the stupa is
separate from the monks' cells,
which are arranged around a central
courtyard, while two of them have
neither a refectory nor commons.
Kalwan ("the caves"), the largest
of the Buddhist sites at Taxila, also
dates from the Kushan period. It
comprises three groups of cells, each
built around a cloister, and a central
stupa encircled by smaller stupas and
by numerous shrines decorated, in
particular, with clay and stucco stat¬
ues of the Buddha and bodhisattvas.
The floors of theliving quarters were
of rammed earth, while the court¬
yards were generally cobbled with
stones from the river-bed. The roofs
were made of rough, clay-covered
beams. Water was drawn from an
enormous well nearly four metres in
diameter, with a stone lining almost a
metre thick at the mouth.
Among the many other monas¬
teries, Mohra Moradu has some of
the finest examples of stucco statu¬
ary, and Jaulian, built on a hilltop, is
Meditating Buddha
(2nd century A.D.). It
forms part of aseries
of reliefs adorning
the base of a stupa
at the Jaulian
monastery.
The main street of
Sirkap, a city on the
site of Taxila founded
by the Partisans in
the 2nd century B.C.
one of the best preserved in Taxila.
Excavations conducted here by Sir
John Marshall in 1912 uncovered
various buildings such as the com¬
mons, refectory, kitchens and store¬
rooms. The monastery probably
catered for many pilgrims and trav¬
ellers, which would explain its many
outbuildings and the fact that it had
three entrances. One of these
opened on to the southern slope of
the hill, where the wells providing
the monastery with water were sunk,
while the eastern entrance gave
access to the living quarters proper.
The northern entrance opened
directly into the lower courtyard in
which stood stupas decorated
around the base with many statues
of the Buddha. At the feet of these
statues was a stucco frieze depicting
allegorical scenes from his life and
showing him surrounded by bod¬
hisattvas, lions and elephants. In the
central courtyard stands the dome
originally gilded of the great
stupa, more than 20 metres high
and surrounded by a score of votive
stupas, all of whose bases are richly
decorated with animals, bod¬
hisattvas and columns in the form
of human figures. At the base of the
main stupa is a "healing Buddha"
which has a hole where the navel
should be: for centuries, believers,
while praying to be healed, put their
fingers in this hole. M
**«» THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
REFLECTIONS
Spreading the word
by Odón Vallet
Retracing the
highways and
byways taken
by the world's
great religious
ideas (See the
June 1997
issue, 'How
ideas travel').
Just as a rumour spreads from street to
street, so "good news" (which is the
meaning of the word "gospel") can travel
from village to village, from oasis to oasis, and
in this way cover thousands of kilometres
without its bearers needing to travel them¬
selves. In Black Africa, the prophet Muham¬
mad's message was conveyed from one water-
hole to the next, and Islam spread southwards
in this way without the Faithful ever having
to leave their native region.
For thousands of years, religions have been
propagated in this way, by capillary action
rather than by transplantation, and their his¬
tory has been shaped by the gradual spread of
influences as much as by brutal invasions. To
take one example, the face of the Buddha,
which was never portrayed in early Buddhism,
made its appearance early in the Christian era
in Gandhara art (in what is now Pakistan),
which represents it with the features of a
Greek Adonis or a mustachioed warrior.
Seen from Europe, and especially from its
Western marches, all religions seem to origi¬
nate in the Orient: first the Greek and Roman
religions, then Judaism, Christianity and Islam,
which came from the Near East. But seen from
the eastern extremities of Asia, all religions
inevitably come from the West. China, Korea
and Japan received Buddhism from India, and
Indonesia received Islam from Arabia. Jôdo,
the Pure Land of Amidist Buddhism practised
in Japan, lies in the West and it is to the West
that Indonesian Muslims turn to pray.
Paths of peace and war
The great religions spread along paths that
were by turns peaceful and warlike. Buddhist
monks and Muslim traders propagated the
message of their respective religions along the
silk route. Mithraism (an Iranian religion
which grew out of Zoroastrianism), Judaism
and Christianity were Eastern religions that
spread along Roman roads. Islam travelled on
horseback up through Spain and through
France as far as Poitiers. On the roads of
Greece stelae dedicated to Hermes were
replaced by statues of St. Christopher. With
the progress of navigation, Buddhism spread
along the coasts of China and Indochina. From
the sixteenth century onwards, European
ships carrying monks, soldiers and settlers
took Christianity to the continents of Amer¬
ica, Africa and Asia.
The purpose of religions is twofold: they
try to spread a message and to unite a com¬
munity around that message. In a sense, all
religions are "catholic" in the etymological
meaning of the word (i.e. "universal"). Even
Judaism has been taken to the four corners of
the earth by the diaspora of emigrant or
exiled Jews. Hinduism draws its origins from
the common heritage of Indo-European reli¬
gions and is beginning to expand to all five
continents. Yoga, born of the Indian tradi¬
tion, is now practised by many Westerners.
A coherent message
In the ancient Greek city-state, on the other
hand, the local religion was reserved for citi¬
zens alone. That is the principle of religions
for initiates, esoteric cults which, in a period
of globalization of trade and blending of
beliefs, are experiencing a renewal to which
the proliferation of sects bears witness today.
According to the two Latin etymologies of the
word sect (sequi, to follow and secare, to cut),
believers follow a charismatic leader and
break with the main or dominant religious
movements.
A religion must possess a certain degree of
coherence before it can expand. Beliefs must
THE UNESCO ^_OURIER OCTOBER 1997 ~
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
be harmonized so that they can be distributed
as widely as possible and passed on to future
generations through families and schools. The
secular authorities are bound to be involved
in these attempts to promote harmony against
schismatic movements and heretical doctrines
because they alone possess the necessary legal
and economic resources. The Christian faith
was spread by the apostle Paul, who had a
vital safe-conduct, his Roman citizenship,
which saved him from execution by the local
authorities. Then it acquired official status
at the instigation of Emperor Constantine who
in 32 A.D. convened the Nicene Council, which
promulgated dogmas of orthodoxy that still
obtain today. On the Buddhist front the Indian
King Asoka seems to have convened a similar
Council (at Pataliputra, in the mid-third cen¬
tury A.D.) to reduce doctrinal differences
between monasteries.
The dissemination of religions, like that
of secular ideologies, requires both the
putting down of roots and propagation. In this
regard the work of St. Paul is remarkable.
He deepened the Christian doctrine and dis¬
seminated it through his epistles, while
46 r
W THE UNESCO V^OURIER «OCTOBER 1997
regarding himself as an "apostle", a title
which in the Athenian city-state designated
the head of a diplomatic mission or a mar¬
itime expedition.
Religion and global
communications
By turns nomadic and sedentary, faiths first
travelled on foot. Buddha, Jesus and Muham¬
mad were great walkers who delivered their
messages on camp-sites and recruited disci¬
ples at every halt. As these messages became
religions they assumed immobile form in pago¬
das, churches and mosques. Today, stupas,
bell towers and minarets rise skywards like
so many lighthouses to guide the earthly trav¬
eller. Sometimes, the age-old solidity of these
places of worship that are resistant even to
earthquakes and radically changing life-styles
leads to ossification, parochialism and a
refusal to engage in dialogue.
Today modern technology can help indi¬
viduals both to become rooted in their own
convictions and to become receptive to the
beliefs of others. Coverage of the Pope's jour¬
neys is beamed all over the world. Imams
Extracts from the Qur'an are
read at the burial of a Uygur in
Kashgar, north-western China.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
record their sermons on cassettes for believ¬
ers in other countries, and religious broad¬
casts can be picked up from distant coun¬
tries via satellite dishes.
Thanks to air travel, Catholics and Mus¬
lims from all over the world make pilgrimages
to Lourdes or Mecca. Kathmandu airport has
opened Himalayan Buddhism to the West,
and Denpasar airport has done the same thing
for Balinese Hinduism.
As a result of modern technology the reli¬
gious message is now communicated world¬
wide with the same audiovisual accuracy. The
time is past when story-tellers could embroider
the sacred stories and copyists amend the
scriptures. Could the founder of a religion
today, a true prophet, adjust to the transmis¬
sion of his message in real time? After all, the
microphone and video camera seem to bring
fame while abolishing mystery. Churches have
their crypts and monasteries their precincts:
there can be no religion, however open, without
secrets. Each sacred treasure is guarded by
iron bars and each spiritual path hides a
labyrinth.
Another aspect of technical progress con
sists of the pollution and nuisances of all kinds
which have led, by reaction, to the rise of
environmentalism, which is neither more nor
less than a scientific version of the old reli¬
gion of nature. It is no coincidence that the
first national parks were created in the late
nineteenth century in the American West (Yel¬
lowstone, Yosemite) where the Indians ven¬
erated the sun, the moon and the trees. In a
world which is becoming a dustbin, humanity
harks back to the old animist religions. It is
transforming nature into a sanctuary with
reserves as sacred enclosures. Tourists from all
over the world travel to Asia to venerate ele¬
phants, just as, in times past, people prayed
to Ganesh, the elephant god, son of Shiva. Or
else they go into ecstasy before birds which
evoke Garuda, the eagle with a man's body,
Vishnu's mount.
Those who believe in Heaven and those
who do not here join in the same movement to
safeguard creation which some prefer to
call the ecosystem threatened with destruc¬
tion by terrible exploitation. The blessed and
the infidel reach the same conclusion: we have
only one Earth. I
A candlelight procession in
Lourdes (France), a Catholic
pilgrimage site.
THE UNESCO (1>URI ER OCTOBER 1997
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
interview Manuel Elkin Patarroyo
In 1986 Colombian physician and
biochemist Manuel Patarroyo made a
synthetic vaccine, SPf66, which has since
shown considerable efficacy in the
struggle against malaria, one of the
world's most widespread diseases. In this
interview with Flor Romero he looks back
to the day when he vowed to follow in the
footsteps of Louis Pasteur.
'Science with consdence'
How did you first become interested in science?
Manuel Patarroyo: I think my scientific curios¬
ity was whetted for the first time when I was five
years old, on the day when my aunt Alicia turned
up in Ataco, the village where I was born, with
two little dog-shaped magnets. It was then that
I heard the word magnetism for the first time. I
insisted on being told what it meant. Ever since
then I have always needed to understand. When¬
ever I went fishing and came back with a catch,
it wasn't to cook the fish but to open them up and
see what was inside.
When I was eight years old, I read a biogra¬
phy of Louis Pasteur in a book my father gave
me. From that day on, Pasteur became my hero,
my model. I decided that I too would make vac¬
cines to serve humanity. I have devoted my life to
fulfilling this childhood dream.
I don't know how much credence should be
given to what the ancient Greeks called/atum, the
destiny that shapes a person's life and leaves lit¬
tle room for freedom. But the fact is that even as
a child I already knew what I wanted to do. I have
never been tempted to leave my chosen path.
But how did you manage to develop a chemical
vaccine against malaria in a country without a
scientific tradition and without the necessary
infrastructure for such an important discovery?
M.P.: The story of this vaccine, SPf66 (Synthetic
Plasmodiumfalciparum, 66th tested formula)
began in 1978 after we had mastered the method¬
ology developed by Bruce Merrifield, who won
the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1984. The first
step in our research was to isolate Plasmodium
falciparum, the deadly parasite that causes
malaria, from cultures of infected blood. Then
we had to isolate the proteins of which it is com¬
posed. After vaccinating Amazonian monkeys with
these molecules, we exposed them to the parasite.
We succeeded in defining four molecules that
were immunologically useful. We established
their molecular structure and then synthesized
them and endeavoured to find the combination
that protected the infected monkeys. The 66th
combination was the successful one. This was how
SPÍ66, the first entirely synthetic antiparasite
vaccine, was discovered in January 1986.
And yet I would be incapable of explaining in
detail why the product works. No one knows
parasites' pathogenic mechanisms.
Was this why the scientific community reacted
oddly to your discovery?
M.P.: We were blamed for having discovered this
vaccine empirically, in a situation involving mul¬
tiple combinations oîfalciparum molecules.
We first of all tried the vaccine in the owl
monkey, Aotus trivirgatus, which is one of the
few animal hosts of the human malaria parasite
and is plentiful in Colombian Amazonia. The
results, published in the scientific journal
Nature, met with considerable scepticism from
the scientific community, and so did the first
human trials in 1987.
I understand this scepticism, not only because
48
THE UNESCO lOURIER OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
of the synthetic nature of the vaccine but also
because my country has no scientific tradition.
But no one can deny that in Colombia we have dis¬
covered a vaccine which is revolutionary on two
counts as the first antiparasite vaccine and as
the first totally synthetic vaccine. And while for
the moment it is only partially effective, SPf66
can prevent around a million deaths each year.
Can a higher standard of protection be
achieved?
M.P.: Since 1986, we and other research teams
have discovered other molecules on the surface
of the parasite. In order to maximize the vac¬
cine's efficacy, we have tried to find out more
about these parts of the parasite which enable
it to adhere to the cells and invade them. We
are continuing to work along these lines so that,
hopefully, the vaccine can one day be adminis¬
tered orally.
At present the vaccine's efficacy in Latin
America varies between 38.9 per cent and 60.2
per cent, depending on patients' age. The vaccine
seems to be much more effective on children
under five. The side-effects (which do not affect
more than 5.6 per cent of patients) are limited
and require no medication. It is an absolutely safe
vaccine without any of the problems associated
with biological vaccines.
Under the auspices of the World Health
Organization (WHO), the vaccine has been tested
in the most malarious areas of the planet, the
United Republic of Tanzania, and Gambia. In
late 1994, the prestigious medical journal The
Lancet published the results of vaccinations in
the United Republic of Tanzania, after a two-
year trial between 1992 and 1994 whose objec¬
tive was to determine the efficacy of the vac¬
cine on children aged from one to five in an area
of intense malaria transmission. The results
showed that the protective efficacy of SP1'66
was 31 per cent.
The epidemiological situation in Tanzania
provided a particularly stiff test for SPÍ66
because people living in this part of the world are
a hundred times more exposed than those living
in Colombia to the bites of the mosquito that
harbours fulciparu m. In these conditions, as
Nicholas White of the Oxford Tropical Medi¬
cine Research Programme pointed out, the pro¬
tection obtained with our vaccine is a positive
and important result.
But we must be realistic. This vaccine will
make it possible to reduce the incidence of
malaria, but will not eradicate it completely. We
must continue to control the disease, diagnose it
and use medicine and insecticides. Only a prag¬
matic and multifactorial approach to the problem
will make it possible, if not to eradicate this
scourge, at least to reduce the number of victims.
How do we stand with regard to malaria today?
M.P.: Malaria currently kills more people than
any other disease. It occurs in hot, humid trop¬
ical regions, i.e. where the vast majority of peo¬
ple in the developing world live. It affects 40
per cent of the world's population and causes
between 2 and 3 million deaths each year, far
more than Aids, for example.
But malaria is not equally virulent every¬
where. Some ethnic groups are more resistant
to infection than others. Susceptibility to malaria
is related to blood group. In Africa, for example,
the epidemic is particularly intense and can
worsen during the rainy season. It is the world's
malaria hot spot. One and a half million children
under five die of malaria in Africa each year.
You have developed a top-level scientific
laboratory in Colombia . . .
M.P.: Yes, and I am extremely proud of the team
I work with. Most of its dynamic young
researchers (average age thirty) are Colombian
chemists, physicists, bacteriologists, molecular
biologists and medical doctors.
In the grounds of Bogota's San Juan de Dios
hospital, where I worked, there was a derelict
building constructed at the beginning of the cen¬
tury by a Colombian architect who had studied
in France. Incredible though it may seem, in a
kind of delayed-action response to my childhood
dream, this building was an almost identical
reproduction, albeit in ruins, of the Pasteur
Institute in Paris. I was able to lake it over and
use it as the premises of the Bogotá National
Institute of Immunology, where thousands of
doses of SPf66 are made today.
What was the most difficult time in your life as a
researcher?
IV1.P.: The most anxious moment of my life was
when I administered the vaccine to thirteen vol¬
unteer soldiers. Experiments had already been
carried out on monkeys, but their kidneys and
brains are not identical to those of human beings.
For nine months I woke up at three o'clock in the
morning feeling sick with anxiety. I said to myself
that if their kidneys were damaged a transplant
was always possible. But if their livers were dam¬
aged these young men would be exposed to incur¬
able hepatitis. The thought that these thirteen
boys might die was a nightmare.
When the time came to introduce the para¬
site into their veins, for eleven days I was unable
to sleep. I visited the hospital at all hours of the
day and night to see how they were.
One day, in Cartagena, I went to the beach and
threw myself into the water. I was so panic-stricken
that I wanted to drown myself. Fortunately every¬
thing turned out all right. The results of the tests
turned out positive.
THE UNESCO tOURIER OCTOBER 1997
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
As a child you saw the ravages of tuberculosis
at close quarters. Have you ever thought of trying
to find a synthetic TB vaccine?
M.P.: There are currently 27 million cases of
tuberculosis in the world, and two and a half
million people die of the disease each year.
Tuberculosis is my wife and malaria my mistress.
I can say that I have spent as much time with the
one as with the other.
After a long spell of secret work at the San
Juan de Dios Institute of Immunology, we suc¬
ceeded in identifying the molecules exclusive, to
the tuberculosis bacillus and synthesized them
chemically. I hope it will be possible for this
vaccine, which we will call COLTU VAC (Colom¬
bian Tuberculosis Vaccine), to be used on a mas¬
sive scale by the year 2000.
You have given the patent of the malaria vaccine
to humanity via the World Health organization.
M.P.: I received very tempting offers from a num¬
ber of American, European and Asian laborato¬
ries. But the vaccine should be made available to
governments so that they can organize massive
vaccination campaigns . It should not be sold and
I do not want to earn money from it. That is why
I offered it to WHO for nothing, because in my
opinion WHO is the most suitable organization to
distribute it in the countries where it is needed.
Didn't you think of using proceeds from your
discovery to develop your Institute and improve its
research facilities?
M. P.: Giving is giving, not a form of exchange. To
ask for something in return would tarnish the
gesture. But Pasteur said that though the results
of science are universal, the scientist has a coun¬
try and his merits belong to that country. That is
why I wanted the vaccine to bear the name of
Colombia. I also want the main production plant
to be in Bogotá and the price of the vaccine to be
very low so that it will be accessible to the needy.
So far the price has been calculated as thirty
U.S. cents for the three "adult" doses and half
as much for a child's dose.
It's your way of fulfilling your cherished dream
of becoming a benefactor of humanity . . .
M.P.: One should fight to fulfil one's childhood
dreams. The world we live in has lost the capac¬
ity to dream. We should teach children to dream
and encourage them to work for the good of their
fellows. Aptitudes are fostered in the home dur¬
ing childhood, not in universities.
You have often talked of demystifying science.
What do you mean by this?
M. P.: One of the problems of science is that it
tends to lock itself up in an ivory tower and invent
a coded language that only initiates can under¬
stand. That is a mistake. The scientist is a product
of society and must act in and for society. Knowl¬
edge must help to free and elevate the human
being. If it does not, we are condemned to suicide.
We must vaccinate the world against selfish¬
ness and pessimism. Solidarity, goodness and gen¬
erosity must not be empty words. Researchers
have a moral responsibility to work for the wel¬
fare of all humanity. "Science with conscience"
should be their watchword. M
AUTHORS
BADAOUI ROUHBAN
is a civil engineer who Is chief of Unesco's Unit for
Disaster Reduction.
FRANK PRESS,
a distinguished American geophysicist and
seismologist, is a former president of the U.S.
National Academy of Sciences (1981-1993). He is a
principal of the Washington Advisory Group LLC, a
company of high-level consulting experts in scientific
and technical matters. Notable among his published
works is Understanding the Earth (1994, with
Raymond Siever).
WALTER W. HAYS,
an American engineering seismologist, directs
various research application activities in the .
Climate/Hazards team of the Geological Division of
the United States Geological Survey.
MUSTAFA ERDIK,
of Turkey, is chairman of the Department of
Earthquake Engineering at Kandilli Observatory and
Earthquake Research Institute, Bogaziçi University
(Istanbul), where he also teaches.
BARBARA CARBY,
of Jamaica, is a researcher in the Department of
Geography and Geology at the University
of the West Indies' Mona Campus and a member of
the Scientific and Technical Committee
for the International Decade for Natural Disaster
Reduction.
FABRIZIO FERRUCO,
of Italy, is professor of seismology and applied
geophysics at the University of Calabria and advises
the Italian government on land and space-based
methods for reducing natural risks.
DEBARATIGUHA-SAPIR,
an Indian epidemiologist, is a professor in the
Department of Public Health in the Faculty of
Medicine of the Catholic University of Louvain
(Belgium).
GERHARD BERZ,
a German geophysicist and natural-hazards expert, is
a senior manager with the Munich Reinsurance
Company.
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist specializing in
environmental questions.
LAURENCE GOURRET,
a French journalist and expert on Asia, recently
published a book about former Pakistani Prime
Minister Benazir Bhutto entitled Benazir, l'envers du
voile ("Benazir, the Other Side of the Veil", Denoël,
Pans, 1997).
0D0N VALLET,
of France, teaches political and religious
anthropology at the Universities of Paris I and VII.
His most recent publications include Les religions
dans le monde ("World Religions", Flammarion, Pans,
1995) and Jésus et Bouddha ("Jesus and Buddha",
Albin Michel, Pans, 1996).
FLOR ROMERO,
a Colombian writer, founded Mujer de América
("Woman of America") magazine and is the author of
many works of fiction, including La calle ajena. ("The
Street of Others").
50 ) G>u'RIEB« OCTOBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
NEsco on line via Internet
http://www.unesco.org
Currently on-line are: an index of the contents of the last 22 issues of the Unesco Courier,
Unesco press releases, addresses, fax, telex and electronic mail numbers of Unesco's re¬
gional offices, National Commissions and Unesco Clubs, the directory of Unesco databases
and information services, colour images of the Japanese Garden and other architectural
sites at Unesco Headquarters, as well as works of art such as Henry Moore's reclining
sculpture.
10 comae
THE UNESCO I OUR1ER
directly with suggestions and comments, type:
unesco.courier@unesco.org
Your passport
to Learning
opportunities
abroad
Scholarships and
financial assistance
University-level courses
Entry-level upgrading
and short-term courses
Student employment possi
bilities
Facilities for
handicapped students
Extramural and continuous
education possibilities
Training courses
offered by international or¬
ganizations to
Entries in English,
French or Spanish accor¬
ding to the country
30th edition
ISBN 92-3-003401-0
1,300 pp., 120 French
francs (+ 30 FF postage)
New!
Study Abroad
On CD-ROM
ISBN 92-3-003403-7
120 FF
Special offer:
Book plus cd-rom:
180 FF
(+ 30 FF postage)
The cd-rom provides
quick and easy access to
all the information
contained in the book.
Runs on PC and Mac.
UNESCO Publishing
1, rue Miollis
75732 Paris Cedex 15,
France
Fax: +33-1 45 68 57 41
Internet:
http://www.unesco.org/
publications
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
IN THE NEXT ISSUE:
THEATRE TODAY
INTERVIEW
ANDRÉE CHEDID
HERITAGE
IRONBRIDGE GORGE (UNITED
KINGDOM), HEARTLAND OF THE
INDUSTRIAL REVOLUTION
ENVIRONMENT
SERVICEABLE SEAWEED
]]>
</page>
</document>
