<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="111114eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
¿a*
?&*?::
i£$m9¡S*8
INTERVIEW WITH
PAULO COELHO
ENVIRONMENT:
HEALTHY HOUSING
HERITAGE:
NAZCA (PERU)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (OURIER NlkOli
A selection of photos entered in the competition will be
featured on this page in forthcoming issues. The photos may
also be seen at an exhibition being held at Unesco's Paris
Headquarters (see inside back cover).
INTERNATIONAL PHOTO
COMPETITION
PEACE IN EVERYDAY LIFE
Nunavut, Inuit country. Eugenio Manghi (Italy)
Mobile cinema in Kyrghyzstan. Richard Manin (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (oURIER
34
Paulo Coelho
A celebrated Brazilian novelist talks about
his personal'quest.
44
Nazca (Peru)
The enigmatic meaning of immense designs
traced in the soil
more than 2,XÎ years ago.
contents
MARCH 1998
life beyond life?
Month by month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat	5
Africa: the breath of life	6
by Nimrod Bena Djangrang
China: a down-to-earth hereafter	10
by Françoise Aubin
India: cycles of birth and rebirth	15
by A. S. Gnanasambandan
Medieval Europe: the antechamber of eternity	19
by Jacques Le Goff
A materialist vision of the afterlife	25
by Greg Oxley
Living to tell the tale 29
by Peter Fenwick
Consultant: Souad Waheidi
Commentary Federico Mayor
GREENWATCH Healthy housing by France Bequette
listening Ton-That Tiêt talks to Isabelle Leymarie
Words for music by Adám Fellegi
40
49
50
Cover: © Alan Kearney/Viesti Associates/Ask Images, Pans
-
THE UNESCO QpURlER MARCH 1908 %i
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THfe. UNESCO
Courier
^"^51st YEAR
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Pans CEDEX 15, France.
Fax' (33) {0)1 45 68 57.45
e-mail unesco couner@unesco org
Internet http //www unesco org
Director: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor Gillian Whitcomb
English edition Roy Malkin
French edition. Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production Georges Servat
Illustrations' Ariane Bailey (Tel (33) (0) 1.45 68 46 90)
Documentation: José Banaag
(Te!. (33) (0)1 45 68 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press
Solange Beim (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 87)
Film duplication. Daniel Meister
Secretariat Annie Brächet
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45 68 47.15),
Administrative Assistant Theresa Pmck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean. (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 69)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian: Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi. Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil M Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Portuguese. Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay Sidm Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili Leonard J Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian DragomirPetrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Smhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish' Rntta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque JuxtoEgaña(Donostia)
Thai. Duangtip Sunnlatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Pashto Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician. Xabier Senin Fernandez (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax' (33) (0)1.45 68 57 45
Subscriptions Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 45.65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Dm
(Tel (33) (0)1 45 68.49.19)
Customer service: Michel Ravassard,
(Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91)
Accounts- (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68.45 65)
Shipping Daniel Meister (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel (33) (0)1.45 68 45 65
1 year: 211 French francs 2 years 396 FF.
Students lyear 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues 72 FF
Developing countries.
lyear 132 French francs. 2 years 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier" plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor Signed
articles reprinted must bear author's name Non-copyright photos will
be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage,
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not nec¬
essarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of
the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are written by the
Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced m microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche} by (a) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Pans, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100
U S A . (3) N C R Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc . Ill West 40th
Street. New York U S A , (4) Bell and Howell Co , Old Mansfield Road.
Wooster. Ohio 44691 USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL Cl -MARCH 1998
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
NM P P.
Photocomposition, photogravure
Le Courrier de I'Unesco
Impression Maulde&Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 3-1998-0PI-98-569 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 50-51
© Mark Downey/Viesti Associates/Ask Images, Pans
THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
month by month
by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
A pilgrim takes a ritual bath in
the Ganges at Benares (India).
I ho can failto wonder about the mystery of the hereafter?
Even those who do not believe in an afterlife feel driven to ask them¬
selves why so many others do. Materialists, for example, view such a belief as
a response to the travails of life on earth. The promise of a hereafter replete
with everything that has been lacking in this earthly life compensates for an
earthly existence bereft of hope and mired in poverty, ignorance and fear. In
other words, the afterlife is a necessary illusion.
Most religions, however, regard the hereafter as the supreme reality
although they do not all visualize it in the same way. Monotheists link the soul
to a single life on earth and see the hereafter as a place where a terrifying last
judgmentascent into Heaven or descent into Hellis made on human
beings. Animists regard the beyond as simply the other side of the here and
now. They would maintain that life is a cosmic principle which both encom¬
passes and transcends individual births and deaths, enfolding us all together
in time and space. Believers in reincarnation, on the other hand, consider after¬
life to be the one intemporal and omnipresent reality. They see the manifes¬
tations of existence as incomplete reflections of this reality, illusions to
which we cling because of desire and fear and through which we must pass
one after the other in order to reach the ultimate principle.
But experience of the beyond does not necessarily have anything to do
with organized religion. Descriptions of the so-called near-death experi¬
ences (NDEs) undergone by millions of people in many countries who have been
revived from "clinical death" are strikingly similar. Irrespective of their reli¬
gion, most of those who "return" are convinced that they have seen a light
beyond, which has removed their fear of death.
The NDE contains echoes of a more profound experience, the spiritual
quest pursued by mystics since time immemorial. All mystics, whatever the
religious tradition to which they belong, describe a state of beatitude that
transcends not only religious particularities but all imaginable forms of
expression. It exists outside ordinary awareness based on the five senses, a
normally functioning brain, the use of language and the expression of an
ego. And yet all those who have attained this state of grace testify to its
manifest and incontrovertible authenticity. Incontrovertible yet surpassing
all understanding because of its links to a Reality beyond time and space, a
Life that flows eternally within us and joins us to the Whole which is also part
of ourinnermost being.
This ineffable state, as Paulo Coelho suggests in this month's interview,
may be revealed to the simplest of mortals as long as they remain true to them¬
selves on a lifelong journey to self-fulfilment.
> QuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Africa: the breath of life
BY NIMROD BENA DJANGRANG
In African tradition, the material and spiritual worlds
are contiguous
At some time or other, every school-
child in French-speaking Africa has
recited this poem:
Listen more to
Things than to people
The voice ofFire can be heard,
Listen to the Voice of Water
Listen in the Wind
To the sobbing bushes:
It is the Breath of the Dead Ancestors,
Who have not departed
Who are not beneath the Earth
Who are not dead.
The Senegalese poet Birago Diop (1906-
1989) called this poem Breaths, to describe a
person's space. All beings everywhere overflow
the place where they are, surpass their specific
location, have more to them than their body.
Only a single side of a person is ever visible,
while the other remains invisible. This division
also explains the importance of the shadow
that a person bears, a shadow or nether side of
the body. Looked at in this way, the beyond
is less a metaphysical notion than something
rooted in tangible reality, its soul, energy and
Breath.
Diop's poem, like a well-sung song, is an
invitation to understand the "Breaths" that
invigorate "things": fire, water, wind, grass,
bushes, huts, a woman's breasts, forests. It is a
list of everyday things, an inventory of the
rural African's environment. One criticism that
can be made of Diop is that his use of capital let¬
ters for Fire, Voice, Ancestors and Earth is inap¬
propriate. It is perfectly natural for the spirit of
the dead or the gods to find embodiment in
these phenomena. In the African tradition, the
gods are usually approachable.
At home with the gods
The gods arc the breath of the universe. African
religions could be described as an attempt to
define nature in terms of vital force and har¬
mony. This is why the word animism is often
used to describe them. The poet invites us to
listen to the "Voice of Fire", the "Voice of
Water" or the "sobbing bushes" because they
are the crucible of energy, the place where the
world's harmony prevails.
Into the intangible content of "breath"
comes a fragment of the cosmic force which
underpins the natural equilibrium. In West,
Central, Eastern and Southern Africa, human
beings are regarded as an integral part of nature.
The idea of dominating or using nature does
not exist. Religion is about increasing the cos¬
mic energy of which human beings arc a con¬
stituent part. Lack of respect for nature is seen
Left, carved mythological
figures adorn the door of a
Dogon granary (Mali).
HE UNESCO Ç)URIER MARCH I
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
as an energy failure or breakdown. There is no
such thing as sin or blame. Sacrifices are
intended to repair the field of living forces.
Nobody is exempt from this system. In
the voodoo religions of the Gulf of Benin, a
priest-medium who can no longer attend to
the replenishment of energy because of illness
or old age is simply done away with, because
his incapacity imperils nature and society. It is
possible for the flame of the world to be extin¬
guished, but this must not be allowed: the
flame must burn for ever.
As we noted earlier, the "flame", "breath"
or natural energy is not something "beyond"
the world, but rather the "secret" of the world,
its most intimate part. Elsewhere, Diop writes
that "Those who are dead have never
A village among the sand
dunes in the region of Gao
(Mali). departed/They are in the Shadow which lights
up/And in the shadow which deepens/They
are in the tree that rustles. . . /They are in the
Hut, they are in the Crowd/The dead are not
dead". In a sense, the visible world seems only
to connect with its invisible counterpart, so
that the dividing line between life and death is
erased. The "visible" must keep watch over the
"invisible", and the "body" over "breath".
So there arc only the living, visible or invis¬
ible. Life is so constituted that the visible owe
gratitude and goodwill to the invisible. This is
why prayers to the gods and the spirits, and
the sacrifices owed to them, arc made with
great discretion; there is no need for altars or
monumental temples. Ritual and other reli¬
gious practices are performed at home, with
> Courier I
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
everyday food grain that has just been har¬
vested and water that is sprinkled on the dry
ground as a libation before people drink.
Worshipping the dead
Looking more closely at the poem "Breath ",
we can see that it contains intimations of the
immortality of the soul. Or at least this is
hinted at. We usually think of breath as being
as inconsistent as the soul, which wc imagine as
something indeterminate, hardly even air, "vir¬
tual nothingness", as the French philosopher
Vladimir Jankclcvitch called it. This "virtual
nothingness" distinguishes the immaterial
nature of the soul from absolute nothingness
and denotes a soul which vegetates, thereby
surviving the disturbances caused by the com¬
ing of death.
These moments when the soul "vegetates"
outside life are not a form of purgatory. Exiled
between heaven and earth, the soul cannot take
refuge in God, who is not interested. The leg¬
ends of the Dogon people of Mali tell how
God went away after creating the world, never
to return. The Xhosa of South Africa regard
God as not only inaccessible but unconcerned
about human beings, who have to fend for
themselves from the moment of their creation.
Hence the malicious urges of the souls exiled
between heaven and earth. If they make a baby,
a hunter or a confused rich man ill, it is because
they are asking to come back to life. This hap¬
pens when they become someone's "sponsor"
or "ancestor" in other words the surplus
energy of the living.
This is how people tune in to the strength,
the breath of the universe, which is "physi¬
cally" speaking an "organ" wafting air that is
cool, or at least damp. In many African lan¬
guages, the same term is used to designate the
spirit, the act of breathing and the faculty of
thought. The dead too want to "breathe".
Their transition from the other side of life is
evidence of what they were: like efficient
"functionaries" they have fulfilled their oblig¬
ations to life. Thus, if they want to become liv¬
ing creatures again, in other words ancestors,
altars and sacrifices must be made for them,
followed by regular, permanent rituals.
Sacrifice renews the vital force of the dead,
restoring balance to the world in general. "The
dead are thirsty", say Dogon "initiates". The
living are called upon to nourish the dead. In
so doing, they prevent the dead from exhaust¬
ing their energy, which in this instance is
described as "thirst". This "thirst" disturbs
families which have not yet built altars to hon-
"In Africa, human beings are a
constituent part of cosmic
energy". Below, the Masai
Mara National Reserve, Kenya.
8 THÍ UNESCO (^URIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
our their dead. Failure to do this puts the dead
in a delicate position and the living do not
fare much better. Uneasiness and tension build
up in such families, which are destined to suf¬
fer illness or accidents.
At this point, a mediator appears in the
shape of the village soothsayer or sorcerer. He
tells them that ancestor worship is their way to
salvation. The ancestors must be brought back
to life by "breathing" into them the energy
contained in the blood and food that are indis¬
pensable to the living. For as long as the dead
remain unhonoured, they will always be
troublemakers who disturb the peace of the
living. In order for them to become acclima¬
tized, they must be allowed to "leave death
behind". There is a "no-man's-land" that is
beyond life and just short of death. Removing
them from this limbo is the only way to com¬
pletely restore them to the status of the living.
As the French ethnographer Marcel Gri-
aule noted, African religious thought is a
hymn of praise to the restorative powers of
water. Water is the breath and the rich soil in
which something can take root and give birth
to all aspects of life. Thinking about an after¬
life is the act by which the living and the dead
drink living water from the same gourd.
Entrance door to a fortified
farmhouse, or tata, of the
Somba people (Benin).
Outside the house, protective
conical altars, trophies and
fetishes are used for sacrifices
to the gods and ancestors.
A 19th-century bronze
Dogon sculpture of an
ancestral couple (Mali).
HE UNESCO f^lURIER MARCH 1998 M
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
China: a down-to-earth hereafter
BY FRANÇOISE AUBIN
In Chinese
civilization, the
dead, the gods
and the living
have sound
practical reasons
to keep in contact
Chinese civilization has never held a hard-
and-fast view of the hereafter, although
some aspects of it have never changed. The gods
are believed to be all-pervasive: they are an imma¬
nent part of the earthly world, and if carefully
handled they can help fulfil human aspirations
to material well-being. In Mediterranean soci¬
eties, on the other hand, the gods (or the one
God the creator) are transcendental and live
outside the perceptible universe. According to
another time-honoured Chinese tradition, the
human soul is divided into a series of superior
souls, destined for a spiritual future after death,
and a scries of inferior, material souls linked to
the corpse and the grave.
When China was united into an Empire
in the third century B.C., popular expecta
tions of the afterlife were couched in terms
of a rather dismal sojourn at the springs of
the Yellow River. Those who could do so tried
to avoid this fate by engaging in a frantic quest
for immortality and in mystic journeys under
the guidance of a Taoist master. The disciples
of Confucius, on the other hand, sought only
to achieve a state of moral righteousness with
which to serve the ruler. They regarded immor¬
tality only as an allegory for mental purity.
Between the third and sixth centuries A.D.,
the introduction of Buddhism revolutionized
the religious landscape, and the different reli¬
gions began to adapt to each other. The Indian
religion soon became a Chinese one as its writ¬
ings were translated and as it came to absorb
local beliefs and practices. Taoism, for its part,
10
TUT UNESCO £)UR1 ER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
On the occasion of a Taoist
festival in Singapore, "paper
money" is burnt as an offering
to the dead by their
descendants.
The turtle and the snake,
symbols of yin and yang,
feature on a contemporary
Chinese print (right).
made substantial borrowings from Buddhism.
Meanwhile, the popular religion practised daily
by lay people of all social classes took from
Buddhism and Taoism a pantheon of protective
gods, and Confucianism continued to uphold
filial piety as the model of all virtue.
Underworld tribunals
By about the ninth century, the shape of the
hereafter had been clearly established. A man is
endowed with three souls or series of souls.
Women are rarely mentioned, except to con¬
firm that they follow their menfolk in the next
world, as they do in this one, although usually
without laying down their lives to do so.
Of the three souls with which men are
endowed, the hun or spiritual soul remains
attached to the gravestone in memory of the
deceased on the family altar and receives trib¬
ute from the descendants in the form of offer¬
ings of incense and food. The earthly soul,
p'o, resides in the grave, and is also sustained
by the gifts of descendants during festivals
honouring the dead. The third soul is tried
by a series of tribunals in an underground
world located, according to the most com¬
mon tradition, on the Eastern Sacred Peak of
T'ai-shan, in Shantung province.
The pragmatism of Chinese civilization
shows itself here. The underworld tribunals,
although Buddhist in origin, arc structured
and run on the lines of imperial tribunals. The
dead person is held there as a prisoner accused
of a crime. But, as in earthly justice, a
favourable verdict can be bought from an
underworld tribunal with paper money
handed over by the family of the deceased.
The time spent beyond the grave is not an
everlasting confinement but a period of transi¬
tion, varying in length, between two earthly
episodes. The usual period is three years, except
in the case of particularly heinous crimes, which
earn the culprit a longer roasting over the fires
of hell. Usually, and especially if the descen¬
dants have been moved by their filial piety to
pay the proper price for their salvation, the
deceased awaits the end of his three years in a
purgatory similar to the earthly surroundings
to which he was accustomed. All his needs are
provided for by his pious descendants, who
burn for him all kinds of objects in the form
of paper a house, furniture and money and
even, these days, a car and a television set.
The burning of paper objects is the stan¬
dard way of transferring goods to the hereafter.
Hell's treasury carefully counts the paper
money sent to it by fire. In exchange for good
treatment by his children and grandchildren
after his death, the deceased shows them that
he is an effective guardian ancestor. In accor¬
dance with the Buddhist theory of transmi¬
gration of souls, the rulers of the hereafter
allow him to return to earth, and he is usually
reincarnated in his own line of descendance, in
accordance with the Confucian theory of the
supremacy of the family.
A seemly death is one where the deceased
leaves behind enough descendants and prop¬
erty to feed the souls of the family. A soul
has to be properly nourished with meat and
rice before it can be benevolent. If spirits are
hungry, they come back to earth and roam
about as ghosts which take pleaure in attract¬
ing misfortune. Various methods of counter¬
ing their malign influence have been found,
from the "spirit wall" blocking off their entry
to villages to fireworks and mirrors meant to
scare them off and a general gift of food which
they are offered when the jails of hell open
their gates to allow the inmates a day out on
the midsummer Feast of the Spirits which has
become popular not just in China but also in
Viet Nam, Japan and Korea.
Gods from the grassroots
Between the ninth and thirteenth centuries,
the services of these forlorn souls were grad¬
ually enlisted so that their violence could be
channelled for the benefit of the community
which worshipped them. They thus became
THE UNESCO Courier march 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
the guardians of the supernatural good order
and the material welfare of a particular location.
This grassroots creation of a vast pantheon of
protective gods, most of whom had met vio¬
lent deaths in wars or accidents, is a key phe¬
nomenon whose importance in the Chinese
notion of the hereafter has only come to be
appreciated in recent years. It meant that lay
people took over management of the super¬
natural, which had hitherto been the preserve
of specialists in Taoist or Buddhist liturgy,
and thereby established direct two-way links
with the deities.
If the gods really want to live, they must
be effective and protect the community which
sponsors them (and which they sponsor in
return) from such dangers as epidemics, rob¬
beries and floods, and grant the wishes of the
faithful as to their descendants, success in
examinations, healing and wealth. If they do
not do this, they are abandoned by every¬
body and are forced to return to the ranks of
lost souls. The most effective gods, on the
other hand, receive imperial recognition in the
form of an honorary title which may be fol¬
lowed by a promotion in the hierarchy of
nobility if they merit it.
Between the tenth and the thirteenth cen¬
turies, when the coastal area of southern China
became much more prosperous, gods were
born and travelled around with pilgrims and
merchants. They were honoured by roadside
sanctuaries and were transformed themselves
as new needs grew. At the time of the inva¬
sions which engulfed northern China, the
people of the south called more fervently than
ever on warrior gods and protectors.
Since the start of the present millennium,
the gods have taken firm control of all strate¬
gic sites. In towns, the god of ditches and walls
is of key importance. In households, the gods
of the cooking-stove, the threshold and the
cesspit hold sway. Mass-produced coloured
New Year prints showing the gods and aus¬
picious scenes are put up in every home and are
changed every year.
The heaven of theJade Emperor
The emergence of all kinds of gods during the
second millennium revolutionized the notion
of the hereafter, which was softened and
humanized, especially when female gods
become increasingly important from the four¬
teenth century onwards. It also offset the hell-
Opposite page, a 10th-century painting on silk from
Dunhuang entitled the Paradise ofAmithaba, or the
"Buddha of Infinite Light". At centre of painting, the
seated Buddha is shown preaching.
Below, painting on silk by
Korean artist Chai Mying
Kyong (1567-1621) depicts a
group of Immortals dancing
with a crane. The 8 Immortals
are mythological figures
blending elements of Taoist,
Confucian and Buddhist
traditions.
like hereafter, with its repression and red tape,
with a heavenly one comprising a court of
kings and emperors benignly presided over
by an old god from ancient mythology, the
Jade Emperor.
The lesser local gods, however, stay close to
everyday life, mounting guard in houses,
towns and villages and at roadsides. When the
god of the stove, the main household divin¬
ity, makes a detailed report at the turn of the
lunar year on the behaviour over the past year
of all the household's members who have fed
him and over whom he has kept watch, he
does not descend into hell but flies up to
heaven, to the Jade Emperor's court.
Heavens belonging to the two established
religions (those with a liturgy supervised by
religious specialists, in contrast to popular reli¬
gions) have also existed at least since the sixth
E UNESCO (oURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
century. The Taoist heaven, centred on Mount
T'ai-shan, the holy mountain containing the
entrance to hell, is populated by immortals,
who are delightful and elusive beings.
"Their skin is as fresh as crisp snow, they
are delicate and modest as virgins. They eat no
grains, but breathe the wind and drink the
dew. They climb onto the clouds and the wind
and fly off astride giant dragons to disport
themselves beyond the four oceans [i.e. the
inhabited world]." All Taoists, who practise
asceticism, who have renounced worldly cares
and who fast and eat plants from the moun¬
tains, aspire to such a passage to immortality.
Buddhism offers two kinds of heaven.
One, messianic and apocalyptic, is the Future
* World, presided over by the Buddha Maitreya,
hopes of which have inspired the ideology of
countless popular uprisings throughout his¬
tory. The other is a heaven which offers salva¬
tion the Pure Land, located in the West and
adorned with flowering lotus and precious
stones, which the Buddha Amithaba opens
to all the male faithful (women are excluded)
who have made a sincere appeal to him.
However, this enchanting, ultimate paradise
was prevented from taking serious root in Chi¬
nese society by resistance from local beliefs.
The notion of irrevocable salvation, putting
an end to repeated reincarnations, offended the
feelings of devout sons who venerated their
father's soul in the gravestone and of families
seeking souls to perpetuate themselves throu gh
reincarnation in future generations.
-te-a^g-*^ f#m ;tH X
: fi n n n ñ S .<; /ji ij i; i n . h
India:
cycles of
birth and
rebirth
BYA.S.GNANASAMBANDAN
Household gods pictured on a
contemporary Chinese print.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
What role has the time-honoured belief in reincarnation played in Indian society?
Above, ritual cremation on the
banks of the Sabarmati River
outside Ahmedabad, a town in
Gujarat State (India).
I Once upon a time a snarling dog was
I standing outside an Indian temple.
Another dog came up to him and asked why he
was so angry. The first dog replied: "I was a
priest in this temple in my previous birth. The
trustee of the temple, a powerful man, goaded
me into becoming his accomplice in the theft of
the jewellery of the goddess of the temple, and
as a result I am now born as a dog. I am waiting
to see that fellow. As soon I see him, I shall
pounce on him and tear out his throat. The
second dog said: "Please don't do that. I was
that trustee in my previous birth."
This story and others like it were often told
by Indian sages to illustrate the belief, com¬
mon to all schools of Indian philosophy, that
life is a cycle of births and rebirths. After their
death, human beings are reborn into this world
in various forms; all of them have passed
through several earlier births and will pass
through several future births. What they think
and do in this life will determine the form
(human, animal, insect, etc.) in which they will
live their next life, as set forth in the doctrine of
Karma (action) and rebirth. "Accordingly as
one acts, accordingly as one behaves, so does
one become in the next life," says the ancient
treatise known as the Brihadaranyaka Upan-
ishad. "The doer of good becomes good, the
doer of evil becomes evil. One becomes virtuous
by virtuous action, bad by bad action."
What happens to the soul after death and
before rebirth? Each school of Indian philos¬
ophy has its own answer to this question,
although they all agree that there is a celestial
world and that those who do right things and
live a godly life go to it and enjoy its benefits
while awaiting their return to the terrestrial
world.
Because there are differences in the amount
r 15THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH )9C>B
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
f . ;
and quality of good and evil that people do,
the upper world is divided into seven regions
or lokas; the underworld where evildoers go is
also divided into regions. The doers of good
go to one of the seven different upper worlds
depending on the quality and quantity of the
good they do. The lowest upper world, for
example, is reached by those who do good
and lead a pious life, performing the prescribed
rituals to propitiate the gods, but do not con¬
trol their senses and mind. To go to a higher
upper world one must control one's senses
and one's mind, and as far as possible one's
inner mind also.
Only a human being can achieve emancipa¬
tion (moksha) from the cycle of birth and
death. This fate is reserved for the select few
(jnanis or yogis) who are unaffected by worldly
things or by the pairs of opposites {dwandas)
such as suffering and happiness. According to
the Bhagavad Gita: "The serene one absorbed
9 THE UNESCO fpuRlER MARCH 1998
Lake Brahma in the Thar
(Great Indian) desert,
Rajasthan. in the Atman [eternal self] masters his will, He
knows no disquiet in heat or in cold, In pain or
pleasure, In honour, or dishonour." Only
someone who transcends the pairs of oppo¬
sites attains the lotus feet of the Lord.
Even if a person's soul reaches the seventh
upper world it is still not entitled to achieve
emancipation if a very small amount of
desire even desire for emancipation remains
in his mind.
"Eradicate desire," wrote the southern sage
Tirumoolar.
"Eradicate it even if the desire is to attain
the lotus feet of the Lord.
The more you desire the greater will be
your suffering."
Some believe that the life which goes out
of the body has a form, the sukshma sarira or
astral body, with which we accede to the upper
world or lower world according to the good or
bad that we have done in this one. Another
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
belief is that a dying person's last thought gives
an indication as to their next birth. This is why
Indian philosophy stresses that you should
go to bed with pure thoughts, repeating the
name of the Lord. If you die in your sleep, the
purity of your last thought will ennoble your
soul through the next birth which will cer¬
tainly be into a higher spiritual life.
Karma and caste
How far have these philosophical tenets and
beliefs been practised in society? Traditional
Indian society was broadly divided into a
minority of intellectuals and philosophers
and a majority which fully accepted their
teachings about the cycle of birth and death.
Even today, illiterate villagers say that some¬
one who harms another person will be born as
a street dog in his next birth.
The doctrine of Karma and rebirth has long
Below, a painting of the Wheel
of Life, one of the most ancient
Buddhist symbols. Gripped by
the claws of Yama, the Lord of
Death, the image depicts the 6
worlds of potential rebirth.
influenced people to do what would lead them
to a good afterlife. It might be said that they
were motivated by a foolish fear of the other
world, which may or may not exist. But what
about the postulates of modern science regard¬
ing the atom, electromagnetic force and energy,
which cannot be perceived by our senses, but
whose existence we accept because wc can see the
results of their actions?
There is however one big difference
between the findings of modern science and the
Indian "life chain" philosophy. The Darwin¬
ian theory of evolution postulates that life
can only evolve upwards, whereas according
to Indian philosophy, those who have reached
a very high spiritual level can come down in the
next birth to the lowest level if they commit
an action in a fit of emotion or anger. There is
no guarantee that people will always rise fro m
one birth to the next. Their next birth is
decided by their thoughts and actions in the
previous one and by the Karma that they have
already accumulated.
THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
This deeply rooted faith in the life chain
has shaped Indian society from time immemo¬
rial. As an explanation of why some are more
talented and enjoy higher social status than
others, and why some suffer while others
enjoy good fortune in this life, it led people
to accept what was inevitable and at the same
time enjoy peace of mind. When people feel
that they alone are the cause of the good and
evil which befall them, they do not try to
blame others for their situation. In the words
of a Tamil poem written in the third century
B.C.: "All places in the world are ours, all
human beings are our kinsmen; good and bad
which befall us are not inflicted by others."
However, as the centuries went by, an intel¬
lectual hierarchy began to rule society and its
- members realized that they could use the doc¬
trine of Karma and rebirth as a weapon to sub¬
jugate the majority and thereby perpetuate
their power. The caste system came to be
twisted into an incgalitarian hierarchy based on
birth. The higher castes began to assert that
the lower castes in the hierarchy were meant to
serve them. Since the majority of the lower
rank were deliberately left without education
and intellectual pursuits they had to accept
this incgalitarian structure based on birth,
which determined what work they should do
in this world.
So for many centuries the theory of a chain
of birth and rebirth helped perpetuate the
inequalities and injustices of the caste system
based on birth. Saint Tiruvalluvar's dictum
that all souls are born equal in this world could
not exert much sway over the majority of peo¬
ple because they were denied the capacity to
read it and understand it.
It is hard to know how far modern Indians
believe in the doctrine of Karma and rebirth
and how much they think about it. Modern
Indian society is a competitive society in which
the pursuit of wealth is accompanied by many
pressures and evils. And yet the majority of
people still have a wonderful way of keeping
their peace of mind. Of someone who acquires
wealth by wrongdoing they are inclined to say
peacefully: "Let him earn, he is not going to
carry anything he acquires now into his next
birth. He has to go empty-handed."
This article is an edited
version of a longer study
prepared for the Unesco
Courier by Professor
Gnanasambandan.
A 13th-century bronze figure of
dancing Shiva from southern
India. The supreme divinity of
Hinduism, Shiva is both static
and changing, destructive and
creative.
18
THE UNESCO Ç)UR1 I MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Medieval Europe:
the antecham
of eternity
BY JACQUES LE GOFF
The medieval Christian Church
in Europe created a complex
system of the afterlife which
played on fear
The view of the hereafter current among
men and women in medieval Europe was
largely the Christian one. Although it included
elements borrowed or inherited from Greco-
Roman paganism, from Oriental religions and
beliefs, from the Old Testament and from
Judaism, it was based mainly upon the New
Testament, the Gospels in particular.
Christianity, with its doctrine of salva¬
tion, flourished in those early years of the
Christian era that have been referred to as an
"age of anxiety", and a preoccupation not only
with what became of men and women after
their death but also with the question of where
they would spend the afterlife occupied a
prominent place in it.
Christianity proclaims the resurrection of
the body, of which the resurrection of Jesus
after his earthly life ended on the cross is the
exemplar and the guarantee. What happens to
resurrected human beings depends on the will
of almighty God, but in accordance with rules
that He Himself has laid down, whereby the
fate of the resurrected is made to depend on
their conduct during their earthly life. They are
consigned after the resurrection, which occurs
at the last day, to different, opposite places in
the beyond, in accordance with a binary sys¬
tem. The "good" live forever in a place of
delights, Paradise, while the "bad" are doomed
to dwell eternally in a place of torments, Hell.
A distinction must be drawn between
Heaven and the earthly Paradise, its eternal
mirror-image, Eden. Similarly, "Hell", as a
place of torments for those damned eternally,
is not to be confused with the infernal regions,
closely resembling the Jewish Sheol and the
Greco-Roman Hades or Tartarus, where the
righteous who have not known Christ and
thus could not be baptized (including Adam
Heaven and Hell,
a 15th-century painting of the
School of Bologna (Italy). and Eve, the first human couple) wait for
Christ to come and free them.
The precincts ofParadise
From the early centuries of Christianity and
throughout the Middle Ages, the hereafter was
the subject of a whole range of apocryphal texts
and stories that grew up around the fringes of
Catholic orthodoxy. This was one of the areas
that most exercised the medieval imagination,
inspiring many literary compositions and an
abundant iconography that bear witness to the
fertile creativity of medieval artists.
Christians had from the very beginning
great difficulty in dealing with the Last Judg¬
ment/Hell/Heaven system. The situation of
the two afterworlds in relation to the Earth
was established soon enough: Hell was below
the Earth and Heaven was above, in the sky.
The terms Heaven and Paradise became syn¬
onymous, although for a long time the topog¬
raphy of the world beyond the grave distin¬
guished several heavens, Paradise being "the
highest Heaven". In general terms, two heav¬
ens coexisted: the natural heaven, or sky, knowl¬
edge of which was the province of science (the
o-	...-
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Middle Ages had borrowed heavily from the
cosmology of Ancient Greece); and a meta¬
physical Heaven, the everlasting abode of God
and the elect.
The two main questions posed by the here¬
after concern the timing of the judgment
whereby God consigns the departed either to
Heaven or Hell, and the possibility of defer¬
ring the final reckoning to some point in the
period between the death of the individual
and the Last Judgment.
There were two opposing views, both of
them accepted by the medieval Church, on
the first of these points. Some held that all the
deceased must await the Last Judgment at the
end of this world to know their fate in the
world beyond. Others held that God wel¬
comed into Heaven those who were indis¬
putably among the elect, the saints, immedi¬
ately after their death. Either they were exempt
from the Last Judgment or it was in their case
a mere formality, a foregone conclusion.
Various answers were put forward to the
question as to whether those destined to be
among the elect would be able to await the res¬
urrection in a specific place. In the early cen¬
turies of Christianity, such a place was imagined
as a refrigerium, a haven of coolness, the very
antithesis of the devouring fires of hell. Accord¬
ing to another idea, which continued to be held
until the thirteenth century and was frequently
depicted in religious art, the elect-to-be rested
in Abraham's bosom. In all these scenarios
those so privileged after death would be spared
punishment and suffering but would never¬
theless be denied the supreme bliss enjoyed
by those definitively admitted into Heaven,
that of being accorded the grace to see God
face to face, the beatific vision. The invention
of Purgatory in the twelfth century was to
overturn these conceptions.
Guided tours
Living mortals could learn, at least in outline,
about Heaven and Hell from the meagre infor¬
mation supplied by the Bible, and especially
the Gospels, and from the stories of those who
had travelled to the world beyond the grave.
These stories, originating in the Jewish and
Christian apocrypha from the beginning of the
Christian era, developed in the Latin West
mainly from the seventh century onwards. They
were the accounts given by those to whom God
had accorded the grace to visit Hell and Heaven,
often under the guidance of an angel or
20
THE UNESCO ÇîURIIER MARCH 1996
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Above and opposite page,
detail from The Last Judgment
by the Italian painter Fra
Angélico (1387-1455). Above,
the Damned; opposite page,
the Elect.
archangel, except for the celestial Holy of Holies
where God abided, hidden from their sight.
The principal Latin accounts of these jour¬
neys take the form of visions granted mainly to
monks (monasteries being regarded as places
midway between this world and the next,
between Earth and the hereafter). In the twelfth
century, the account written by an English Cis¬
tercian of the knight Owen's visit to "St.
Patrick's Purgatory" in Ireland definitively
shaped the changed landscape of the afterworld
by localizing Purgatory in a specific place.
As may be seen from the descriptions of
Heaven and Hell in these stories, most Chris¬
tian imagery of the hereafter was drawn fro m
earlier sources. It owes little to the Old Testa¬
ment or to the Jewish tradition, except for
the two paradisiacal themes of the Garden of
Eden and the celestial Jerusalem. Judaism
makes no clear distinction between the grave
and the world beyond it, and the Jewish hell,
Sheol, is a grim and gloomy place that does
not lend itself to description.
The main borrowings of imagery for the
torments of hell are from India and to an even
greater extent from Iran and Egypt. In ancient
Greek mythology, Orpheus, Pollux, Theseus,
Heracles, and Odysseus (in Book XI of the
Odyssey) all descend into the underworld, but
the main heritage in this respect is from Rome,
namely from Aeneas' voyage into the infernal
regions, in Book VI of Virgil's Aeneid. This
was where the two abodes of the dead were
reached, by first going down into the cavern
that served as an antechamber, through the fields
where the souls of the unburied dead wandered
and across the river Styx, before turning either
left into Tartarus (Hell) or right into the
Elysian Fields (Heaven).
The main features of the Christian image of
the world beyond had taken definitive shape
by the early Middle Ages.
Torment and delight
To get there involved standing trial either col¬
lectively, at the Last Judgment, or individually.
In the former case, the leading role was played
by Christ, throned in judgment in a setting
reminiscent of the courts of Ancient Rome,
and verdicts were handed down after consul¬
tation of the books kept by the angels, in
which men's good and bad deeds are recorded.
In the latter case, the crucial moment comes
with the weighing of souls after the resurrec¬
tion. The Archangel Gabriel holds the great
21
THE UNESCO (pURI I MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
scales, while the gatekeeper of Heaven, St. Peter,
and the Master of Hell, Satan, vie for posses¬
sion of the soul by pulling down on one side
or other of the scales. When the verdict has
been rendered, the elect ascend into Heaven,
where St. Peter opens the gate for them, while
the damned are pitched into the jaws of Hell.
Heaven is a place of peace and rejoicing
where the senses of the elect are delighted by
flowers and light for the eyes, songs for the
ears, fragrant odours for the nose, the taste
of delicious fruits for the mouth and fabrics
soft to the touch (since in their modesty the
elect usually wear beautiful white robes, only
a few artists portraying them as restored to
the naked state of the innocent in Eden before
the Fall). Heaven is sometimes shown as gir¬
dled with high walls of precious stones and
consisting of concentric areas, also surrounded
by walls, where the colours, the fragrances,
the tastes and the harmonies become more and
more delightful the nearer they come to the
Centre, the abode of God, who holds the
beatific vision in reserve. Whereas in Genesis
Paradise was a garden, in keeping with the cli¬
matic conditions and the mythopoeic tradi¬
tions of the East, in the medieval West, a world
of towns ancient and modern, Heaven was
generally conceived of as a walled city, on the
model of the celestial Jerusalem, and it was
strictly reserved for the righteous who had
been baptized, baptism being the necessary,
albeit insufficient, passport to Paradise.
The invention ofpurgatory
Hell is a place of inextinguishable flames that
unrelentingly burn the damned, giving off
blackish smoke and a fearsome red glow that
sheds the only light on a world of darkness, ter¬
rifying cries, noises and stench, a hell in red
and black. Worse still, the damned are forever
doomed to suffer cruel torments inflicted by
hideous demons. The landscape, when it can
be glimpsed, is a horrible scene of steep moun¬
tains, deep chasms, stinking rivers and lakes of
molten metal, reptiles and monsters. The way
into hell is either by being cast down a wellshaft
or by taking a bridge over the abyss that
becomes narrower and more slippery the fur¬
ther one goes across it. Hell is sometimes
divided into different parts that receive differ¬
ent categories of sinners; at other times it is all
of a piece but arranged in circles, each specializ¬
ing in some particular punishment for the
damned, or in levels of ever-increasing dark¬
ness and burning heat that lead down to the
ultimate depth where Satan reigns in person.
Although medieval Christian imagery of
the hereafter owes a great deal to that of pagan¬
ism, it differs from it structurally in one essen¬
tial way. Heaven and Hell are not next door
to each other in the underworld but arc placed
on a vertical plane, in symbolic accordance
with the Christian representation of space,
with the heavens above (good) and the infer¬
nal regions below (evil).
22 r
^ THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
Relations existed in time and space between
the quick and the dead, God, Satan and peo¬
ple; in other words the eternal world beyond
made its presence felt in earthly life. Angels
continually descended to Earth and mounted
up into the heavens again, as, more seldom,
did the Son of God and the Virgin, while the
wicked demons and Satan himself likewise
came and went between Earth and Hell. The
hereafter played a role in earthly history. Quite
apart from the rare voyages of a few favoured
individuals to the realms beyond, visions,
miracles, signs and portents established what
medieval Europe saw as the relationship
between this world and the next.
Orpheus in the Underworld
(1594), oil on copper by the
Flemish painter Jan Bruegel,
known as Velvet Bruegel
(1568-1625).
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The linchpin of the system, however, was
not Heaven, but Hell. To urge Christians to
work out their salvation, the Catholic church
employed fear of hellfire rather than desire for
Heaven. In the face of death, they were less
afraid of dying than of Hell, and Christianity
thus became, with some slight variations of
emphasis, a religion of fear.
The bipolar character of the Christian after-
world continued more or less unchanged until
the twelfth century, when major religious and
social changes resulted in a new society with a
new view not only of this world but also of
the next.
St. Augustine had divided men into four
categories: the "entirely good", who were des¬
tined for Heaven, the "entirely evil", who were
consigned to Hell; and the "not entirely good"
and "not entirely evil", the fate ordained by
God for these last two categories being some¬
what uncertain. It was supposed that those
who died with only a "light" burden of sin
upon them would rid themselves of it in the
afterlife by undergoing "purgatorial penal¬
ties", passing through "purgatorial fire" sim¬
ilar to hellfire, in "purgatorial places" whose
location remained very vague. In the latter half
of the twelfth century, a separate place was
invented for those whose admission to the
number of the elect had been deferred. This
THE UNESCO ÇoURI ER MARCH 1998
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
was Purgatory, the "third place of the world
beyond", midway between Heaven and Hell,
which would vanish at the Day of Judgment
and would be emptied when all its inhabi¬
tants rose up into Heaven.
The amount of time spent in Purgatory
depended on three factors. It was in the first
place proportional to the number of sins
(referred to thereafter as "venial", i.e.
redeemable and thus allowing the sinner to
avoid damnation, as against irredeemable mor¬
tal sins) with which the dead were burdened at
the time of their death. It depended next on the
suffrages (prayers, alms and masses) offered by
living relatives and friends to reduce the length
of time spent by certain "souls" in Purgatory.
Lastly, the Church could obtain a remission of
the time still to be served in Purgatory, in
jreturn for money the indulgences in which
the Church carried on a growing trade from
the thirteenth century onwards. Purgatory, it
should be added, was a one-way street. Souls
could only go on from there to Heaven, and
not back towards Hell.
This "third place", which reduced the pop¬
ulation of Hell and replaced the binary system
of the afterworld by a more complex, less rigid
system in keeping with the evolution of the
"estates" of society on Earth, and which was
widely disseminated by the friars of the Men¬
dicant orders established in the early thir¬
teenth century (Dominicans and Franciscans),
was of the greatest importance.
In a Purgatory resembling Hell,
an angel's hands reach out to
a soul which has completed its
time of penitence. Detail of a
17th-century mural from the
church of Saint Laurent in the
Tinée valley, southern France.
The triumph ofdeath
It brought about the triumph of the idea of
individual judgment at the moment of death
and, in conjunction with the fact that at least
one yearly confession was imposed on all indi¬
viduals by a decree of the Fourth Lateran
Council in 1215, it contributed greatly to the
affirmation of the individual in relation to
groups and orders. It transformed the social
structures and behaviour patterns in the world
of the living and resulted in a mathematical
attitude to sins and penances that gave rise, at
this point in history when trade and the mer¬
chant class were developing rapidly, to a kind '
of book-keeping approach to the afterlife. It
also contributed to a great increase in the
power of the Church (which in the thirteenth
century designated the existence of Purgatory
as dogma) over the dead, inasmuch as the suf¬
frages and indulgences of which it was in charge
gave it an authority, previously exercised by
God alone, to administer justice in the after-
world of Purgatory.
In this period when the new society of the
thirteenth century was being put in place on
Earth, the geography and system of the after-
world (that of St. Bernard and St. Thomas
Aquinas) took definite shape. The basic system
was that of the essential "three places" Hell,
Purgatory and Heaven made up to five by the
addition of two limbos: the limbuspatrum, or
limbo of the patriarchs, the former abode of
the just who died before Christ's incarnation
and the institution of baptism, the place that was
to be emptied byJesus when He descended into
Hell to take its inhabitants up into Heaven; and
the limbus infantium, or children's limbo, the
abode of infants dying without baptism.
It was this new arrangement of the after-
world that inspired the great masterpiece of
medieval Christian literature, Dante's Divina
Commedia (early fourteenth century), in
which the author, guided by the ancient
Roman poet Virgil, visits every part of the
afterworld the circles of the Inferno where
the damned are punished severally according to
their respective categories of mortal sin, and the
terraces of Purgatory, which is presented as a
mountain that has to be climbed to attain the
beauties and joys of Paradise.
A study of fifteenth-century texts and
images raises the question as to whether by
the end of the Middle Ages people still believed
in Hell. It seems that, despite the best efforts
of the Church, such a belief was by that time
much watered down. Christians, showing
signs of the emergence of a modern sensibility,
were now afraid not so much of Hell as of the
phase that immediately precedes the afterlife
death itself.
THE UNESCO ^>UR1ER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A materialist
vision of the
afterlife
BY GREG OXLEY
For Marxists, the hereafter is an
instrument of power wielded by
the dominant social classes
The Ladder of Virtues,
facsimile of an illustration
from a lost medieval
illuminated manuscript, the
Hortus Deliciarum (Garden of
Delights).
The story of the hereafter in human
I thinking is almost as old as humanity
itself. The material conditions in which early
man strove for survival posed problems to
which empirically acquired knowledge, the
primitive "science" of the times, could not
provide answers. The history of human beings,
as distinct from the history of apes of a more
or less advanced type, begins with the history
of their production of the means of their own
existence. The degree of sophistication of the
tools and weapons developed by primitive
humans, of the "means of production" of the
necessities of everyday life, conditioned their
mental representation of the world.
To the extent that the laws of nature
remained hidden from human understand¬
ing, natural phenomena necessarily appeared as
being animated by wild, uncontrollable forces
which influenced human fate. Imaginary "spir¬
its" inhabited the trees and forests, the rivers
and marshes, animated the skies, the rain, the
wind, light and darkness, and the animals man
hunted. In his own dreams, in his ideas and
imagination, man was inclined to see the man¬
ifestations of a spirit within himself.
With the emergence of the early civilizations,
and with the corresponding increase in human
power over the environment, the general trend
in human thought, which can be traced in var¬
ious forms through surviving artistic represen¬
tations and inscriptions, was to separate the
world of gods and spirits from the environ¬
ment, and to imagine their existence in another
world. From their distant abodes, the gods
weighed the greatness and virtues of humankind,
and rewarded or punished earthly beings.
Each new step in the acquisition of pro¬
ductive techniques led to changes in the rela¬
tions between humankind and the natural
world, and also in the social and economic
relations existing between the producers them¬
selves. These changes would in turn shape and
transform the fantastic representations of the
world in human minds. Once worldly phe¬
nomena are understood as the consequence of
a natural process, the belief in divine or spir¬
itual influences is weakened and tends to dis¬
appear, not immediately, but after a certain
delay. "Human consciousness lags behind
events", as the materialist philosophers of the
nineteenth century explained.
Thus the development of the means of travel
and of commercial exchange and the emergence
of common language over wider areas, under¬
mined locally-based folklore and gave way to a
> GTHEUNESCO I OURIER MARCH 1998 '
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
new, more universal, hierarchy of beliefs and
attendant rituals. The emergence of monothe¬
ism, the belief in a single divinity, reflected the
understanding of the world as a "whole", as a
single entity whose different component phe¬
nomena arc related to and in interaction with
one another.
Historically, therefore, through many dif¬
ferent forms, the basis of the belief in the exis¬
tence of other worlds was the human attempt
to explain the material environment, filling
the gap, as it were, left by the still rudimentary
level of empirically acquired knowledge.
Monks are shown collecting
tithes from the people at the
time of Pope Innocent II (12th
century) in this illustration
from a 19th-century French
History of the Popes.
Ideologicalpressures
However, this is not the only reason for the
rooting of such beliefs in social conscious¬
ness. When the level of development of pro
ductive technique renders possible the eman¬
cipation of a part of society from physical
labour, dividing society into different and
mutually antagonistic social layers, people's
relationship with the world of spirits becomes
not only the expression of a given level of cul¬
tural development but also an expression of
the social relations established between groups
and classes. The perception of gods and super¬
natural powers becomes an element in social
conflict. The dominant layers of society create
for themselves a heavenly justification for the
perpetuation of their rule.
The history of the Christian religion is a
clear illustration of this. At each historical
stage, Christian ideas about the world reflected
not only the general cultural and scientific lev¬
els reached by society, but also the ideological
and political pressures of the contending social
26
THE UNESCO I OURIER M4RCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
At Wittenberg, on 10
December 1520, the German
religious reformer Martin
Luther burns the Papal bull
Exsurge Domine calling on
him to retract his ideas. (19th-
century French engraving).
forces of the times. The hierarchy of the
Roman Church spent centuries haggling over
the origins of the Devil, his role in the world,
the extent of his powers, his relation to God.
It would be wrong to see in such seem¬
ingly interminable debates only the product of
over-excited imaginations. Underlying the
need to give a more precise definition to the
role of the Devil, for instance, was an essen¬
tially political problem. To minimize the pow¬
ers of Satan would weaken allegiance to the
Empire as a safeguard against devilish male¬
dictions. On the other hand, Rome was con¬
cerned that the tendency to see the "work of
the Devil" behind the most ordinary misfor¬
tunes would lead to a greater respect for the
Devil than for his divine opponent, whose
influence was perhaps less perceptible to poor
peasants. Thus the need to give a more restric¬
tive definition of the powers of the Devil on
earth.
The ideological conservatism of the Church
reflected its position as an integral part of the
ruling land-owning classes within feudal soci¬
ety. The imagery of heaven and hell used by the
medieval church reflected and idealized the
existing social order. God, the king, was pic¬
tured as sitting at the head of a pyramid of
orders, the lower orders owing deference to the
higher, whose place and authority was con¬
ferred by God himself. Heaven was depicted as
a place of joy, peace, and general well-being.
On the other hand, those who, during their
passage on earth, fell foul of God, whose
The German reformer Thomas
Münzer preaching in the
Klettgau region. (19th-century
engraving).
"word" was infallibly interpreted and commu¬
nicated to them through the laws of the Roman
Church, would be condemned to everlasting
torture in hell. To this day, the walls of many
church buildings are decorated with the most
horrifying representations of what hell reserved
for those who strayed from religious con-
formism. The concepts of heaven and hell were
inseparable. It can be safely assumed that, in the
mind of a medieval peasant, one of the best argu¬
ments for doing whatever was necessary to get
into heaven was to avoid being sent to hell!
Social unrest
and religious beliefs
When social antagonisms reach such a point
that conflicting interests break out into open
struggle and warfare, the interpretation of the
"holy word" and the role attributed to the
"hereafter" in earthly affairs form part of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
ideological expression given to the needs and
interests of the contending forces.
A great many illustrations of this idea could
be given, and not, of course, solely in relation to
the Christian world. But perhaps one of the
most striking examples is to be found in the
period of the reformation and of the peasant
war in Germany which took place in the first
quarter of the sixteenth century. When Martin
Luther launched his attack on the clergy of the
Roman Church, this was seen as a signal for
revolt on the part of all those social strata who
sought to free themselves from its domination.
The burghers, the lesser nobility and the princes,
joined by some elements of the lower clergy,
stood to gain from a weakening of the power of
Rome and from the confiscation of Church
lands and property, much of which had been
acquired by means of forced tributes, forged
documents, or political blackmail at their
expense. The peasantry, which bore the entire
feudal hierarchy upon its back, stood to gain
most of all from a change in the social order.
Initially, Luther himself adopted a particu¬
larly virulent tone in relation to Rome and the
ruling layers of society. But with the outbreak
The City of Cod,
facsimile of a medieval
miniature from the Hortus
Dellciarum (Garden of
Delights).
of a peasant uprising on a massive scale, he
changed his tone in favour of mere "passive"
opposition to the Catholic hierarchy. He turned
against the "murdering peasant hordes", and
called upon the princes to "stab and strangle
them". After a bloody civil war, the peasant
armies were finally defeated, and their most out¬
standing representative, Thomas Münzer, was
among those put to death.
Heaven on earth
For Münzer, the notion of heaven as another
place, visited in another life, was a snare for
the poor. He brought paradise down to earth.
It was to be established here and now by the
revolutionary realization of the will of God.
Hell was pictured as being no different from
the existing social order, ruled as it was by
"robbers and murderers".
Münzer's doctrine was a striking example
of the translation into religious terms of the
social and economic aspirations of a particular
social class, namely the poor peasantry of his
times. His vision of the Kingdom of God was
one of a classless society, where work and
rewards for work were to be shared, without
private property, or, at any rate, with an equal
sharing of property.
The same phenomena occurred during the
English revolution which overthrew the
Monarchy in 1649. Early protestantism in
England, and particularly that preached within
the ranks of Cromwell's "New Model Army",
was very close to Münzer's doctrine, and was
accompanied by a flourishing of movements
aiming to establish "heaven on earth", form¬
ing communities based on the sharing of prop¬
erty and earnings. Faith in salvation in an after¬
life is most prevalent in times of social inertia,
and recedes as soon as social forces move into
action on a massive scale. Even Cromwell's
famous battle-cry shows the entirely subor¬
dinate place the "Defender of the Faith" attrib¬
uted to heaven in earthly affairs: "Trust in
God . . . and keep your powder dry!"
The prevailing religious ideas of a given soci¬
ety in a given epoch are established not in a vac¬
uum, not as the result of "pure" reasoning, but
in close relation to the societies and modes of
existence in which they emerge. The role attrib¬
uted to the "afterlife" by human beings has a
definite function within human society, and
is constantly shaped and altered to bring them
into conformity with the requirements of the
different social groupings and classes within it.
In the final analysis, no religious beliefs can
stand above the social and economic foundation
upon which they rest, nor free themselves fro m
the influence of the material interests of con¬
tending social forces in a given epoch.
28 > QuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Living to tell the tale
BY PETER FENWICK
© Steve Schapiro. Sygma, Pans
Many people have crossed to the 'other side' and
returned with surprisingly similar stories
In the American film Heaven
Can tVa/r(1978), Warren
Beatty, above, plays a
footballer who dies
prematurely and is given a
second lease of life on earth.
* Raymond Moody, Life
after Life, Bantam Books
(38th printing, 1983).
I It is likely that for as long as man has
I been aware of the certainty of death he
has contemplated the possibility of survival.
There is nothing particularly new about the
notion that people can "die" and live to tell the
tale. Myths and legends recounting these talcs
go back well over 2,000 years. But it was not
until 1973 when the American psychiatrist Dr.
Raymond Moody collected the first contem¬
porary accounts of near death experiences
(NDEs) that it was recognized that these were
worthy of serious scientific study.::"
Studies of the NDE produced some fasci¬
nating data, and raised some interesting ques¬
tions. It is clear that these experiences are not
specific to near-death situations they also
occur as a response to extreme stress or terror
or pain, in childbirth, under anaesthesia, spon¬
taneously, and possibly also during sleep.
Moreover, not everybody who comes near
death has an NDE.
Although cross-cultural studies indicate
that NDEs have a strong cultural component,
it is unlikely that they are entirely the product
of cultural expectations, because there are many
accounts of children too young to have such
expectations who have had NDEs. If they are
dreams or hallucinations, why do so many
people dream more or less the same dream, or
have more or less the same hallucination?
The other side
No two near death experiences are identical,
but there are uncanny similarities between
them. In the majority of cases the NDE is a
profoundly emotional experience, vividly
remembered for years. Dr. Bruce Greyson, a
psychiatrist and editor of the American/o«r-
nal ofNear Death Studies, has laid out a blue¬
print of a characteristic experience, although
the features do not always occur in the same
order, and few people experience every event.
The experience often starts with feelings
of peace, joy or bliss, described as more than
29
THE UNESCO I OURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
ordinary happiness. If there is bodily pain, it
drops away. The out-of-body experience often
follows, the person seems to leave his or her
body, and can look down on it from some
vantage point, usually near the ceiling. They
may then enter what is usually described as a
dark tunnel, which they pass or float through
rapidly without making any physical effort.
At the end of the tunnel is a pinpoint of light
which grows larger as they approach it.
For many people the light is the most sig¬
nificant part of the experience. It is nearly
always described as white or golden, brilliant
but in spite of its brightness not dazzling.
Often the person feels drawn towards it.
Sometimes it manifests itself as a "being" of
light, an intensely emotional and positive pres¬
ence that is warm and welcoming and loving.
At some point people sense a barrier
between them and the light, sometimes a phys¬
ical barrier such as a gate or fence, sometimes
simply a feeling that this is a point beyond
which they cannot pass. They may glimpse an
idyllic pastoral scene beyond the barrier, or
see people, usually dead relatives, sometimes
beckoning to them, sometimes signalling to
them that they should go back.
The feeling that it is not yet their time to
go is a very common feature of the experience.
Sometimes people will make the decision to go
back themselves, usually because they feci their
families still need them. Sometimes they are
sent back either by the being of light or by the
relatives they have met.
More rare is the "life review", a sort of Day
ofJudgment which some people experience, in
which their past actions are reviewed. Some
have a life preview, in which they are shown
events which are to take place in their future,
and told there are tasks ahead of them which
they must go back to complete. The return
to the body is sudden and rapid, often
described as a "snapping" back into their body
as if on the end of an elastic cord.
Cultural variants
Nearly everyone who has the experience says
that through it they lose any fear of death.
Often their attitudes change in other ways. Life
often seems to have an added purpose and value
after such an experience. It may confirm reli¬
gious belief for those who previously held it
and many of those who have no particular reli¬
gious belief return believing that death is not the
end. A few people believe they have been given
The Hereafter (1938),
oil on canvas by the Belgian
painter René Magritte.
Opposite page, "The Elect",
detail of Heavenly Paradise, a
panel from Visions of the
Hereafter (c. 1500-1516) by the
Dutch painter Hieronymus
Bosch.
psychic powers such as precognition or the gift
of healing, after the experience.
The near death experience is intriguing for
two major reasons. First it is very common
some studies suggest that between a tenth and
a third of people who have had a cardiac arrest
had an NDE. This makes a prospective study
feasible. Secondly it seems to be a universal
human experience and not a culture-bound one,
although it is, as might be expected, influenced
by the particular culture in which it occurs.
In Indian experiences, for example, the pos¬
itive feelings of peace and joy which seem to be
a significant hallmark of Western experiences are
much less often reported. Out of body and
tunnel experiences are rare. Instead the subject
is taken by "messengers," and as a result of
some bureaucratic bungling, usually a case of
31
THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
mistaken identity, is finally brought or pushed
back. Stigmata seem to be a quite common
phenomenon of the Indian NDE. In one
reported case, for example, fissures were seen in
the skin on the front of the knees of a man
who had had an NDE in which he reported
having been captured by ten people who cut
his legs off at the knee to prevent his escape.
Relatives or friends do not play a significant
part in Indian experiences, while well-known
figures in Hindu mythology do.
But even within Western cultures there are
differences in the NDE. The life review, for
example, is far more often reported in Amer¬
ican experiences than British ones, religious
figures tend to figure more prominently, and
the experiences have an evangelical quality
which probably reflects the more fundamen¬
talist religious culture of that society.
The NDE is almost always a positive expe¬
rience. Glimpses of Hell are rare. Is this because,
where life after death is concerned, we are all
past-masters at giving ourselves the benefit of
the doubt? Or because the stereotypical view
of heaven, with pastoral landscapes and fig¬
ures in flowing robes, is more frequently
depicted and more likely to be fixed in mem¬
ory than archetypal visions of Hell?
It has been suggested that the reason why so
few hellish experiences have been described is
that they are quickly forgotten. However, it
seems more probable that people who have bad
experiences are just as strongly affected by them
as people who have good ones, but they are
much more reluctant to talk about them. But 1
o.
perhaps the most likely explanation is that J
when an experience includes feelings of peace |
or joy, as about 80 per cent do, these are para- ®
mount and override everything else, so that
whatever else occurs is interpreted in this pos¬
itive light. Many experiences include moments
of terror and in the absence of positive emo¬
tional feelings these may colour the experience
so that it is felt as neutral or even "hellish".
The search for an explanation
Is there any scientific explanation for the
NDE? Is it nothing more than a hallucina¬
tion, a trick played by a brain disordered by
drugs, pain, lack of oxygen, or sickness? Some
experiences are clearly drug induced. Of the
other explanations which have been advanced
anoxia, hypercarbia, the release of endorphins
during pain or stress while some of these
may be involved in the NDE in some cir-
32 r
m THEUNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
This statue of Vaishno Devi, a
form of female energy or
"shakti", stands in the Hindu
sanctuary at Kulu, Himashal
Pradesh State (India).
cumstances, none can account for every aspect
of the experience or are applicable in every sit¬
uation in which NDEs occur.
The NDE confounds many of our assump¬
tions about how the brain works, and it is dif¬
ficult to find a rational scientific explanation
for it. Many NDEs occur during uncon¬
sciousness, when the brain is theoretically inca¬
pable of building the coherent and often com¬
plex models which people who have had NDEs
report. Moreover, memory does not function
in unconsciousness, so even if the brain was
able to make such models, they should not be
remembered. From the point of view of both
memory and model-building, it should be
quite impossible to have an NDE when brain
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
function is seriously compromised or the brain
is seriously damaged. And yet there are cases in
which this has happened. To explain it we have
to postulate that the brain can retain the capac¬
ity for making images in unconsciousness and
that when the memory circuits are damaged,
memory can be retained by some other means.
There is evidence, stretching back to the
first brain mapping experiments of Wilder
Penfield in the 1930s and 1940s, for the
involvement of the temporal lobes. Penfield
found that stimulation of the temporal lobes
produced sensations of leaving the body, feel¬
ings of tranquillity, hallucinations of people.
Some people reported having flashes of mem¬
ory. The right temporal lobe is primarily con¬
cerned with emotion, and the NDE is a very
emotional experience. Most people say that
the NDE is ineffable, impossible to describe
or categorize, and this suggests that it may be
arising in the right hemisphere, which is con¬
cerned more with spatial than verbal func¬
tions. The loss of spatial boundaries and deep
feelings of unity which are characteristic of
the NDE arc probably due to an alteration in
right hemisphere function.
Perception of time is often altered during
an NDE and the misordering of events in time
is yet another right-hemisphere function.
NDEs always seem to carry the feeling of
absolute reality; often they are felt to be more
real even than everyday life. This attribution of
certainty to ongoing perception is possibly
another temporal lobe function. A similar feel¬
ing of "knowing" something emotionally is
sometimes experienced by people who have a
right temporal epileptic focus.
Beyond the frontiers ofscience
Thus it seems likely that the NDE is mediated
by the temporal lobe. But this still leaves two
questions unanswered. How does such a coher¬
ent integrated experience like the NDE occur
during unconsciousness when it is impossible
to postulate an organized sequence of events in
a disordered brain? And why is it that spon¬
taneous experiences in which it seems highly
unlikely that there can be a physical or psy¬
chological mechanism at work, also sometimes
occur?
One possibility is that the NDE is a form
of mystical experience, and the brain struc¬
tures which mediate it arc probably the same
structures which mediate any mystical expe¬
rience. The nineteenth-century Canadian psy
chiatrist Richard Bucke (1837-1 902) was one of
the first Western scientists to try to define the
characteristics of the mystical experience. The
nine features he listed were: feelings of unity,
feelings of objectivity and reality; transcen¬
dence of space and time; a sense of sacredness,
deeply felt positive mood; paradoxicality
the experience is felt to be true even though it
violates Aristotelian logic; ineffability; tran¬
siency; positive change in attitude or behaviour.
The probability is that the NDE is a mys¬
tical experience, timeless and independent of
death, but part of the spectrum of normal
human experience. If wc accept this, it explains
why not everybody who is near death has one,
and why there is no common cause.
Does the NDE do anything to confirm the
continuation of personal consciousness after
death? People who have had the experience say
that it does. But to accept this we have to step
beyond the boundaries of science, which does
not accept subjective experience as evidence.
Only by trying to establish a new science, which
does attempt to explore and to validate human
subjective experience can we decide whether
there is in fact meaning behind the mechanism
of the NDE and perhaps even allow for the
continuation of personal consciousness.
The world of the hereafter is evoked in two books published (in French) in the
Unesco Collection of Representative Works. One, Gan Bao's In Search of Spirits
(Sou shenji; published by Gallimard, Paris, 1992) comes from ancient China; the
other, Han Mahlsook's The Melodious Song of Souls (Arumdaun Yongga;
published by L'Harmattan/UNESco Publishing, Paris, 1995) is from modern
Korea. Although very different in tone, both works are a hymn to life and love in
which the dead are closely linked to the everyday experience of the living.
> (ouiRIER MARCH 1996
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
interview Paulo Coelho
The beyond
is accessible
to those
who dare'
In the two centuries since the Enlightenment,
man has become the measure of all things. This
attitude of mind has changed many things for the
better, but it gives short shrift to the spiritual
dimension of human existence. People today need
to rediscover a relationship with transcendence, but
only on condition that it is through their own
experience and that they freely consent to that
experience, which should not be subjected to any
religious authority. By putting forward a model for
an individual spiritual quest in your novel The
Alchemist, you put your finger on this overriding
concern of people today. Perhaps this is one of the
reasons for its tremendous success.
Paulo Coelho: The Enlightenment did not pre¬
vent people from having their irrational side or
rule out intuition or enthusiasm. Humanity
gradually turned its back on them for other rea¬
sons. Yet I am convinced that humanity is now
quietly opening its doors again to things which
it had rejected and ceased to respect. The most
important of these seems to me to be the idea
of mystery. This is something that must be
understood not so much the fact that there is
a limit to human knowledge as the fact that mys¬
tery is part of the human condition. When I fall
in love, it is not because the person I love is the
best in the world or even the best person for me.
Love is beyond reason, and so is spiritual quest¬
ing. Why do we need spirituality? I do not know.
That's part of the mystery. Some people have
sought a recipe for the human condition. "You've
got to do this," they tell us. "You've got to do
that." I don't trust them. But I do trust those
who have sufficient humility to respect the mys¬
tery surrounding our lives and to acknowledge
that there are major reasons that are beyond our
Brazilan writer Paulo Coelho has won international acclaim with his prizewinning
philosophical tale The Alchemist, which has sold more than 10 million copies worldwide.
He is also the author of Diary ofa Magus: Lessons in the Art ofSelf-Discovery, an account of
a pilgrimage he made to Santiago de Compostela, and of By the River Piedra I Sat Down
and Wept. His most recent book. Mount Five, which retraces the life of the prophet Elijah,
has just been published. Since 1997, Paulo Coelho has been a special adviser to the
Director-General of Unesco for the "Routes of Faith" project*.
Here he is interviewed by Baghat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat.
See the Uitsco Couritt. M ly 1995, "Tlie Pilgrim's Way", p. 16
understanding. When I wrote The Alchemist, I
obviously did not know that it was going to be
such a success. I only wanted to write about what
I firmly believe, which is that everybody needs to
live out their personal legend.
This is what's new, that people who feel the need
to get down to essentials no longer have to go
through a priest, a rabbi or an imam. The Alchemist
suggests that they can find self-fulfilment by
pursuing a personal quest which is a source of
fulfilment rather than a curtailment of their
freedom. This changes a lot of things.
34
THE UNESCO ÍOURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
P.C.: We all feel an inner need to see the world not
only as it appears to our senses but as a vaster
intangible reality embracing the Whole. This is
what I called the "soul of the world" in The
Alchemist. Spirituality, which caters for this need,
can therefore only be a personal quest. There is a
path to God, marked by signs which are so many
letters of an alphabet ensuring direct communi¬
cation with the divine. However, this does not
preclude the need at certain times for collective
adoration and prayer. At those times, we turn
to religion. Religion is there to satisfy a desire to
belong to the community, to find brothers and
sisters. But it does not show us the path to God.
This path starts from within each of us. It is up
to us to unravel the thread	
Yet your own personal quest first led you in
different directions. At one time you were a hippie
and then you flirted with left-wing politics	
P.C.: Yes. I have tried just about everything. I
have wanted to live my life to the hilt. I was raised
by the Jesuits, which is the best way of com¬
pletely losing your faith, because God is forced
on you. I left the Catholic church precisely
because it had been forced on me. I returned to it
later after a pilgrimage to Santiago de Compostela,
not because it is the best or ultimate religion but
simply because I carry it within me. The world
opened up in the 1 960s. People, especially young
people, started to travel, meet and make contact
with each other. It was a magic moment, a
moment in the history of humanity when an
entire generation set about answering basic ques¬
tions such as: What am I in this world for? Who
am I? Why was I born in Brazil instead of in
Egypt? These questions have been pursuing peo¬
ple ever since the dawn of time. They can't be
avoided, even if people sometimes feel they have
given up on them. In an attempt to answer them,
people have explored the three paths of art, sci¬
ence and spirituality. These are three very differ¬
ent things, but they impinge on each other. In
fact, the three overlap and blend together. But
there are certain things that it is very dangerous
to mix up. Spirituality and art can cross-fertilize
one another and great scientific geniuses often
have poetic intuitions. But when people want
to find some kind of scientific basis for religion,
the result is catastrophic. The experience of faith
belongs to an order of reality that cannot be
reduced to the world of concepts or be forced
. into a scientific mould.
Collective religious experiences are creating
many conflicts, instead of prompting people to
understand each other better and share things	
I am convinced
that humanity
is now quietly
opening its doors
again to the idea
of mystery.
BIBLIOGRAPHY
The Alchemist, a fable
about following your dream.
Harper, San Francisco, 1993
* By the River Piedra ISat
Down and Wept, Harper, San
Francisco, 1996
* Diary ofa Magus: Lessons
in the Art ofSelf-Discovery,
Harper, San Francisco; 1995
P.C.: The experience of true faith always brings
us back to the Other. This being so, the first per¬
son I see is my neighbour. There is a sense of joy
which I want to share with him or her. If that joy
is not shared, it ceases to be joy. On the other
hand, in sadness that is truly shared there is room
for joy	
Even misfortunes are opportunities to learn the
price of things.
P.C.: Yes, provided we persevere along the path of
our own personal legend, provided that we do
not give up. Unfortunately, in the course of their
journey, many people betray the dream which
connects them to the soul of the world. They sac¬
rifice it to the acquisition of social status. If a per¬
son's true vocation is to become a gardener and if
by becoming a gardener that person achieves self-
fulfilment, nothing should deter him or her.
However, in our day, people will be forced more
and more often to abandon their dream often
under family pressure and become lawyers or
doctors. They will forget their personal legend,
they will lose their sense of belonging, they will
no longer have the resources to transform each
experience and each misfortune into a fresh oppor¬
tunity to lift themselves up	
No sooner has the hero of The Alchemist
decided to follow his dream than he is robbed.
You can imagine his disillusionment! He who
had found the inner strength to fulfil his personal
legend, who thought, as if by right, that the
whole world would conspire on his behalf, finds
himself alone and penniless. You need courage
to launch out into an unknown world, aban¬
doning all you possess. At the threshold of our
quest, the fear of stepping into an unknown
world and the desire to stay at home lie in wait
for us. It is a crucial moment of initiation. But we
cannot stand on the threshold for ever. We must
dare to move. Only corpses do not move. Life is
movement. But where to? This is what we all
have to discover for ourselves.
The need to cast off from our moorings	
P.C.: To do this, we have to give free rein to our
rebellious side. I am a great believer in inner rebel¬
lion not lifelong rebellion or rebellion without
cause or restraint, but rebellion against the force of
habit, against the fear of change which is really
fear of living rebellion that will enable us to
make our own way by strengthening our deter¬
mination. Take the example of the struggles wc
have to wage with the family from childhood on.
My mother was always opposed to my personal
destiny. But at the same time she helped me find
THE UNESCO QpURI ER MARCH 1998
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
the strength and skills to control myself, persevere
and find my own way. Without this conflict, I
would never have developed willpower. These are
quite legitimate struggles!
I do not know where this rebellion comes
from. It is a force which is liberated in us and
which liberates us in turn. It is the quest for per¬
sonal space and time. We cannot accept that our
life span should be measured in terms of so many
years of primary school, followed by secondary
school and then a job. All this is only our col¬
lective space-time and it should on no account sti¬
fle our personal space-time. It is necessary to
strike a balance between the two.
You say that we do not know where we are
going, and yet you speak of rebellion. Isn't there a
contradiction in this?
P.C.: Yes there is, fortunately. This is what free¬
dom is all about. There has to be rebellion against
the forces of inertia and death in order to liber¬
ate the forces of life and creation, which are not
programmed in advance. Otherwise, there would
be no freedom. By that I mean freedom in its
existentialist sense, in other words a compro¬
mise. I am free, I can leave this room right now,
but I won't because I have freely imposed a cer¬
tain code of behaviour on myself. I am also free
to write a book, but to do so I have to sit at the
computer for several hours a day. I impose this
constraint on myself in complete freedom. On
the other hand, if I am sitting in front of the
computer and all the ideas are already in my head,
there will be nothing creative about it. We have to
leave a space so that inner freedom can express
itself.
How did you set about writing The Alchemist?
What ideas did you start out with? Did you know
how the story would develop beforehand?
P.C.: You may be amazed to learn that the story
of The Alchemist comes from the Thousand and
One Nights. It is quite a short tale, only a few
lines long, about a hidden treasure for which the
hero searches far from home, only to find it even¬
tually within himself. I took four guiding ideas
from it: the personal legend, the language of
signs, the soul of the world and the need to lis¬
ten to one's heart. I started the novel with this
very short tale as my guide. The rest was vague,
like being in a fog. The only thing I knew was
that the boy would eventually return to his start¬
ing point. Therewere times and this is the expe¬
rience of creation when I felt as if I was trapped
by my own story. At one point, the boy has to
transform himself into the wind. It is a matter of
life or death. He has to do it. But how do you
W the unesco Courier march 199a
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Alchemist seeking
the philosopher's
stone (1848), oil
on canvas by the
French painter
Jean Vetter.
start describing such a thing? As you can imag¬
ine, I myself have never transformed myself into
a wind. I panicked	 Then I told myself that I
had to take the plunge and I went right on to the
end of the book.
Hemingway used to say that when he started a
novel he had no guiding theme, but that when he
stopped writing in the evening, he knew what he was
going to write on the following day. . . .
P.C.: In my youth, when I came across quota¬
tions like that, I used to say to myself that they
were hooey. Now I know they make sense. The
wellsprings of creation bubble up in ways that are
to some extent unpredictable. In Hemingway's
case, the limits of the predictable were on the
following day. The day after that was always a
blank page. Writers are like pregnant women.
They have made love with life and have a child
without knowing who the father is.
In my own case, I don't write all the time. I
let two years go by between one novel and the
next. Things happen during those two years
which, together with many others that happened
long before, beget a novel in me, like begetting a
child. Everything we say today may find its way
into some future book.
Frédéric Rossif, the well-known film director
who died some years ago, once met a Sufi mystic in
a cave in Iran and asked him: "What is a saint?" The
holy man's answer struck everybody to whom Rossif
told the story. It was: "A saint is a man who has
pardoned God".
P.C.: That was a brilliant answer. It strikes a par¬
ticular chord with me since my book Mount
Five starts out from the idea that we should
struggle with God. According to the Bible, God
should be accepted as a father. Personally, as I
said earlier when talking about my mother, I am
rather more inclined to wrestle with Him. It is a
legitimate struggle. Pardoning God implies that
one has already fought with him, as a way of
gradually coming closer to Him.
By raising all these questions, The Alchemist
has gone well beyond the realm of literature.
P.C.: The novel has inspired a classical symphony,
composed in the United States, which will be
played at Tarifa in Spain next June. This concert
will also be an occasion for an international debate
to be held on religions and on ways and means of
defusing the religious wars that are threatening us.
It is in this capacity, in fact, that I have been
appointed an adviser to the Director-General of
Unesco.
THE UNESCO ^)URI ER MARCH 1998
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
commentary Federico Mayor
Africa and
the world
The international community formed by the ] 86 Member States
of UniîSC.O, conscious ¡is it is of what Africa lias to offer )ct wor¬
ried about the difficulties it is experiencing, has made the
continent one of the priority targets of its action. As a follow-
up lo this decision, 1 convened a meeting entitled "Audience
Africa" at UlNICSCO's Paris Headquarters in 1995. The primary
aim for all of us was to "tunc in" to the continent, to give its
countries an opportunity lo express their needs and priorities
and, perhaps for the first time, to set forth their own approach
to the solutions I hat could be applied by Africans themselves.
The fact is that it is for Africans lo determine and map out
the paths their future will lake, even when they resort to exter¬
nal assistance. 1 have recently set up in U.MiSCO an Interna¬
tional Fund for the Scientific and Technical Development of
Africa because I know that no country today can claim to enjoy
effective autonomy without endogenous scientific and techni¬
cal capacities. However, decisions in this field arc political.
The African countries must make sure ihat at least 3 per cent
of the resources managed by the United Mations Development
Programme (UJNI)P) are earmarked for scientific and technical
development and it is clearly up lo these countries to invest a
reasonable proportion of their gross domestic product in science
and technology.
It would be sufficient for them and 1 am referring here to
UMDP's Human Development Report to redeploy 4 per cent
of their military expenditure in order to reduce adult illiteracy
by half, generalize primary education and give women a standard
of education equivalent to that of men. Unfortunately, I am only
too well aware that when the possibility of reducing arms expen¬
diture is raised with African leaders, many of them reply that oth¬
ers should be the first to set an example! I also gather that a sim¬
ilar response is made by the countries which sell them arms and
which are obviously in competition with one another.
That being said, the \ cry great majority of African countries
are just as aware of their difficulties as they are of their respon¬
sibilities. Whenever they have the opportunity to express them¬
selves in a multilateral framework at follow-up meetings to
38
Audience Africa or at meetings concerning the United Mations
New Agenda for the Development of Africa in the 1990s or the
United Mations System-wide Special Initiative on Africa the
African countries clearly state their wishes and plans: they
mean to become partners in progress. For that purpose, in
addition to significant debt relief, they demand an improve¬
ment in the world climate in so many words, markets that
are more open lo their goods.
The entire international community realizes that if Africa
lakes off economically, the rest of the world will derive con¬
siderable benefit because the integration of the African
economies into the international system will be less fragmentary.
The African countries are also stepping up their determination
to pursue the struggle against poverty for the sake of social
development and the democratization of political systems.
The right to peace
Peace, development and democracy are three interdependent
concepts working in synergy with each other. They are the
three apexes of an interactive triangle which we are endeav¬
ouring lo create in co-operation with our sister institutions of
the United Mations system by supporting the efforts made by
ihe authorities of the African countries. It is only in a democ¬
ratic framework preserving plurality, diversity and difference
in accordance with rules accepted by everybody that individ¬
uals can fulfil their potential and society can move forward. This
democratic framework alone meets the conditions for devel¬
opment and allows the full exercise of the human rights set out
in the Universal Declaration, that landmark instrument whose
fiftieth anniversary we are celebrating this year.
However, just as development and the spread of democ¬
racy are bound up with the existence of civil peace, these
human rights cannot be respected in the absence of one essen¬
tial right, and that is the right to peace for which so many men
and women are clamouring in countries stricken by conflict.
This is so powerful an aspiration that it can no longer be ignored.
THE UNESCO I OURIER I
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
I accordingly took the initiative of drawing up a draft Decla- jointly accepted and undertaken and which focus on values
ration on the Human Right to Peace, the ideas behind which such as solidarity and tolerance, the community is regaining con-
were approved by Um-'.SCO's most recent General Conference fidenee in itself and in the future.
held in the autumn of 1997. This idea of the right to peace is In Bujumbura, the capital of Burundi, a Unksco House
gaining ground and 1 hope that it will win widespread recogni- for a Culture of Peace has been in existence for the past three
tion on the occasion of the celebration of the fiftieth anniver- years. It is a simple building, with a large number of windows,
sary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights. in which five people are hard at work. It might be thought to
In addition to recognition of this right, since 1989 I have be a rather insignificant venture, considering the scale of the
been endeavouring lo focus Um'.SCO's activities on the estab- recent tragedy and of the task of reconstruction. Slowly but
lishment and promotion of a culture of peace worldwide. This surely, however, it is making headway. Its activities are pri-
coneept, which was difficult to narrow down at the outset, marily addressed to young people who are, sometimes in spite
has made considerable of themselves, a prey to ethnic
progress: it has been recog- hatred. It is urgent to give
nized by the General Assem- , , , them scope for dialogue. In
lily of the United Nations, has TfirOUgfl prOjeCtS Which arejOWtly 1996 and 1997, two festivals
become part the vocabu- accepted and undertaken and which i"r 1H';'(C !,roi;«,,t u^\hi'r
lary used by politicians, the Hutu, lutsiaiul Jwa children,
military and teachers, and foCUS (M VallieS SUCh 8S Solidarity and who realized, rather hesi-
serves as a common denomi- , . ,, ., . tantly, that living together is
natorforaiikindsofpraetieai tolerance, the community is regaining possil)1(, wh(.n tlu,y can tak(.
initiatives in a wide variety of Confidence 111 ltSelf and in the future. pleasure in a shared project
fields, including basic; educa- and festive happening,
tion, environmental proteo- In the very few secondary
tion, preservation of the her- schools which have been
itage and the struggle for press freedom. immune from the "balkanization" of the country, the pupils
In Africa, there have been countless activities coming under bring the violence surround ing them into the classroom. Then,
this heading. The Peace Week held in Mali from 24 to 28 from time lo time, a team from UM'.SCO arrives, brings the chil-
Mareh 1997 and the International Conference on the Culture dren together and calls on them to speak about the acts ol'vio-
of Peace and Good Governance held in Mozambique from 1 to lenco they have suffered and the violence they themselves have
4 September 1997 are among the events at which a number of inflicted and to try to understand its causes,
leaders voiced their commitment to peace, widespread (lia- In Burundi, however, where the conflict has been responsi-
logue and the peaceful settlement of disputes. ble for a 7 per cent drop in secondary enrolments, it is neces¬
sary to go beyond the confines of the school and reach out to
those young people who have not had any schooling. This is
what we are attempting to do by organizing reconstruction
Innorth-western Mozambique, a country which still displays the training seminars for them, for example.
gaping wounds caused by thirty years of war as a result of col- It is very difficult to evaluate the impact of all these ini-
onization, the liberation struggle and civil war, there is a small tiatives, which are like a delicate fabric woven thread by
town called Chiputo. Half of its 15,000 inhabitants, mostly thread. Less violence was observed in schools in Burundi in
farmers, fled to other regions of the country or else to Zambia, 1997, but it is difficult lo say to what extent we have con-
Malawi or Zimbabwe. In exile, some of them were given train- tribu ted to this. In view of this uncertainty, of the inadequate
ing and emergency assistance, while others were given noth- resources, of the political fluctuations and the demands of the
ing, and even lost everything they had. With the end of the moment, we press on, in the modest yet deep-seated conviction
conflict, they are all returning home, but ihcir resettlement is that it is through education, and education alone, that it is
not without its upsets. UM'.SCO has undertaken to help these possible to foster, develop and enhance the chances of dia-
coinmunities achieve successful integration and learn afresh how logue, for as UiMvSCO's Constitution so aptly puts it "since wars
to live together. begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the
What is above all necessary is to get them to focus on a defences of peace must be constructed",
common purpose, so that the diversity of individual situations The fact remains that time is not the same everywhere,
will become a source of collective enrichment rather than divi- "World time" only exists on computer screens. "Real time"
sion. Iii Chiputo, two teachers provideinstruction for 650 chil- could well turn out to be something different from what it
dren in a primary school; the people who will supervise the means in laboratories and cybercafés. Perhaps time is what
future adult literacy campaign have already been trained; a was inscribed centuries ago on a sundial in Bavaria: "Time hur-
sports ground, a community development centre and a sec- ries, time tarries, time divides, time heals". All these eontra-
ondary school are under construction; and a community radio, dictory properties are characteristic of time in Africa, time
with a range of six kilometres, is planned. It is true that these that is both pitiless and generous, heart-breaking and creative,
activities are on a fairly modest scale, owing to the limited This being so, we need to know both how to overtake time in
resources available, but they are helping to piece together a cases where it is that of division and hatred and how to trust
social fabric that was in tatters. Through projects which are time when it is that of dialogue and rejoicing. M
THE UNESCO (oURIER MARCH 1998
A delicate fabric woven thread by thread
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Greenwatch
Healthy
housing
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
r Although indoor pollution is
often overlooked, it directly
orindireetly affects the health of a
broad spectrum of people, from
those living in mud huts to those
whose homes are in modern sky¬
scrapers. This pollution can come
from three different sources: out¬
door air pollution (whose planetary
impact was described in our Decem¬
ber 1997 issue); building materials;
and the activities of occupants.
A healthy home must he
designed to protect its inhabitants
from extremes of cold and heat, rain,
noise, dust, insects, and rodents. It
must he constructed on a well-
drained site, and have access to run¬
ning water and a waste-disposal sys¬
tem. Overcrowding should be
avoided to reduce the risk of conta¬
gious diseases. Neither the heating
system nor the cooking facilities
should give off noxious fumes.
Unfortunately, not everyone living in
the Third World or in industrialized
countries lives in these conditions.
The very poor have to make do with
insalubrious shelters on the edges
of cities and endure a range of dif¬
ferent kinds of pollution.
Another situation that is often
overlooked, although it is very com¬
mon, is that where the home is also
a workplace. In such cases, the use
and storage of toxic or dangerous
chemical substances needs to he
reviewed in order to make sure that
people are better protected. In addi¬
tion, the stress caused by the cost of
housing, insecurity of tenure, and
the threat of expulsion when a home
is being illegally occupied, can have
an important hearing on mental
health.
A POLLUTED ENVIRONMENT
In industrialized countries where cur¬
rent standards arc well respected,
these risks arc generally very low.
« o. Q,.t .
Children's
drawing of the
favela (shanty
town) of Vioigal,
Rio de Janeiro
(Brazil).
Architects arc closely concerned with
the structure of buildings and with
the quality of building materials. The
World Health Organization (WHO)
nevertheless observes that in these
countries, "the advent of air condi¬
tioning and energy conservation mea¬
sures have been accompanied by
growing problems of indoor air qual¬
ity. . . . Some pollutants arise from
insulation products, some from
kerosene heaters, and others from
modern housing materials. As many
Kuropeans spend up to 90% of their
lives in buildings, the health effects
of the indoor climate are significant."
Some construction materials,
including fihreboard, insulation
foams and certain glues (for carpets or
nigs, for example), emit organic prod¬
ucts such as formaldehyde. Heat and
humidity increase formaldehyde
emissions and the gas seriously irri¬
tates the eyes. Paint, lacquer, varnish
and other resins can also release
volatile organic compounds into
indoor air.
In 1976, members of the Ameri¬
can Legion, an organization of U.S.
war veterans, met in an air-condi¬
tioned hotel in Philadelphia. More
than 200 of them came down with
pneumonia and 34 of them died.
Later, the bacteria that caused their
deaths was identified and named
Legionella pne.umophyla. These
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
MU» *- g 1
i 39 i' ^ - I
it J
HI
«ai
*
îsl4
3«..*
» IL
i
j « m ' ¡"*
K4> 0Ü
«' »i il I» i i
u iua^ i
5îîi
i
i
»ay Mm-
ii |B£r. (S!
Stt - "K
"*.!! II"E'á¿lJll
* Î J ¡^ - H J| ¡ft
MB« Í. if-
' Ji. :
''*..H" mäWk" Sa » .JE M
*%t "M" a. -|
al^,. -ft* ! ¿. S?
ja. i-
pp
.1 s ^
F^ ' i
«jf> M » r
-j
bacteria proliferate in humid areas,
in toilets, and poorly maintained
bathrooms. Steps can he taken to
prevent what became known as
Legionnaire's Disease by means of
simple hygiene measures, starting
with very careful, regular cleaning
of sanitary appliances.
The land on which buildings are
sited may also contribute to pollu¬
tion. Some kinds of granite or similar
rocks contain traces of radium. As it
breaks down, this naturally radioac¬
tive element produces radon, a
radioactive gas that seeps through
tiny cracks in walls, porous floors
and building materials, and makes
its way into home interiors. The bet¬
ter the homes arc insulated, the
more the gas accumulates. Radon's
main affect on health is to increase
the risk of lung cancer. Ten years
ago in the United States, radon panic
made radon detection all the rage.
People bought themsclv es detectors
similar to those used by nuclear
technicians, even in areas where
there was no danger whatsoever!
THE RAVAGES OF ASBESTOS
Construction materials can cause
serious damage, especially when
they contain asbestos. Asbestos is
naturally present in rock formations
worldwide. It belongs to a family of
mineral substances composed of
solid, non-combustible fibres. These
Public housing in
Hong Kong
(People's Republic
of China).
Removing
asbestos from the
Headquarters
building of the
European
Commission in
Brussels
(Belgium).
Taking a last look
before being
expelled from a
squat In the
London suburb of
Peckham.
properties make asbestos a highly
sought-after construction material.
Its production and commercial use
began in the Western world at the
turn of the century and became very
widespread after World War II. As
early as 1931, however, public
health officers in the United King¬
dom revealed the connection
between inhaling asbestos dust and
respiratory diseases (asbestosis, lung
cancer).
Asbestos workers were, the first
to be affected. Professor Bignon, a
French lung specialist, claims that
no epidemiological study has so far
proven incontrovcrtibly that there
is a link between lung cancer and
exposure to rooms where asbestos
has been used. Nevertheless, pre¬
cautionary measures should be
taken to eliminate asbestos as
quickly as possible from buildings
(as has been done at UNESCO Head¬
quarters in Paris), and especially
from rooms used by children.
New Caledonia offers an inter¬
esting case in point. The island's
inhabitants suffer from a very high
incidence of pleural cancer, a rare
form of asbestos-related cancer that
affects the moist membrane lining
the chest cavity and surrounding the
lungs. This cancer seems unrelated
to any industrial activity, however.
The French National Institute for
Health and Medical Research
(INSERM) carried out an investiga¬
tion which determined that a white
plaster coating, called pö, used by
the Kanak tribes to protect the walls
of their homes, was toxic. The plas¬
ter is produced locally from a
crumbly rock that turned out to he
a form of asbestos. Pö was very
widely used from the 1930s onwards
when the colonial authorities
encouraged indigenous Caledonians
to replace their traditional branch
and leaf huts with mud-walled
houses on the grounds that these
were more hygienic. The affected
dwellings must be identified and a
new technique developed to elimi¬
nate the asbestos from the mud
walls.
PARASITES, LEAD AND SMOKE
In Latin America, from the south of
the United States to Tierra del
THE UNLSCO (7)URIIER MARCH 100B
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Solar panels on
the roof of a
private house
(United States)
Fuego, Chagas' disease, also known
as sleeping sickness or American try¬
panosomiasis, affects 18 million peo¬
ple and threatens 100 million more.
First described at the turn of the
century in Brazil by Carlos Chagas,
this parasitic disease is transmitted
to humans by a trypanosome carried
by blood-sucking bugs of the lledu-
viidae family. In Brazil it is respon¬
sible for one in every ten deaths
among 25- to 64-year-olds. The lar¬
vae live in the crev ices of walls and in
the dust of poor rural dwellings, and
they thrive particularly well in
warm, moist areas. Plastering the
walls and regularly spraying them
with insecticide would solve the
problem, but this solution is too
expensive.
Lead poisoning is another illness
linked to the age and decrepitude of
housing. Paint in old buildings eon-
tains a great deal of lead. Children
swallow some of this when they
break off bits of peeling paint and
put them in their mouths. This type
of poisoning also affects people who
drink water which has remained in
lead piping for some length of time.
Children with lead poisoning have
behaviour problems and perform
poorly in school.
The gas and smoke given off by
fuels used in homes can also prove
dangerous. When coal burns in an
open or poorly designed fireplace or
in badly ventilated rooms, it gives
off dense toxic fumes, particularly
of sulphur dioxide. In cold regions
such as the Himalayas, the high¬
lands of Papua New Guinea and cer¬
tain Chinese provinces, families are
exposed to smoke from open
42 r
THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
hearths. Heating stoves can also pro¬
duce indoor pollution. Oil-fired
stoves give off nitrogen oxide and
carbon monoxide. Biomass fuels,
such as wood, animal dung and agri¬
cultural waste produce hundreds of
highly carcinogenic chemical com¬
pounds. This problem ran only be
solved by using efficient smoke-
extraction methods and providing
adequate ventilation.
HELPING COMMUNITIES
TO HELP THEMSELVES
Improving household living and health
conditions is the goal of Health in
Housing (HIH), a U.S. research centre
that works with the World Health Orga¬
nization (WHO) and the Pan-American
Health Organization. Auxiliary centres
are located in universities worldwide
and courses are given by doctors,
nurses, architects, health workers,
engineers and other professionals work-
ingin this field. HIH does notimpose
solutions but tries to encourage com¬
munities to be active lyinvolved, and to
work out what they want and can do to
improve their living conditions.
Contact address:
Health in Housing (HIH)
School of Medicine and Biomedical
Sciences
State University of New York, 167 Färber
Hall
Buffalo, NY, 14214, U.S.A.
^^^ initiatives
MEDICINE FROM GARDENS
A French ethnopharmacologist, Dr. Jean-Pierre Nicolas, has recently set up an association called
Jardins du Monde ("Gardens of the World"), which seeks to develop traditional pharmacopeias and
promote the use of medicinal [liants in southern hemisphere countries where most people have no
access to basic medicines.
In the Quiche department of Guatemala, for example, Dr. Nicolas has contacted a number of
Indian populations the K'iche, Ixil, Kekchi and Mam and has worked with several French non¬
governmental organizations including Médecins sans Frontières, Médecins du Monde and Vétérinaires
sans Frontières, as well as various diocesan organizations.
Dr. Nicolas started out by conducting field investigations, discussing traditional know-how with
local practitioners including Mayan priests, midwives, healers, bone setters, elders and mothers. He
then had to make an inventory of available natural and cultural resources, and work out a strategy
with the local populations for combating disease. To encourage the traditional uses of plants, he
set up medicinal gardens planted with local scientifically recognized, non-to\ic species that are effec¬
tive, available and well known. A team of health workers maintains and develops these gardens that
arc both nurseries and training schools. Mothers help with the gardening and are given plants and
seeds that enable them to have their remedies on hand.
As Jean-Pierre Nicolas points out, "a wound immediately treated with/lZoe lera gel does not
get infected, ambrosia helps reduce worm infestations, and Indian carnations calm diarrhoea."
The success of this initiativ e has led to a flow of requests for the creation of medicinal gardens, includ¬
ing from other countries. There area grow ing number of similar projects in Honduras, Nicaragua,
Colombia and the countries of the Caribbean.
The same respect for local populations and their traditional knowledge can be found among the
250 members of the French Ethnopharmacology Society, spread over 30 countries, particularly
in Africa, Latin America and the Caribbean.
Jardins du monde. Laboratoire de botanique, Faculté de Pharmacie, BP 83, 59006 Lille, France
Tel.: (33)-(0)3-20-96-40-40. Fax: (33)-(0)3-20-95-90-09
Société française d'ethnopharmacologie, 1 rue des Récollets 57000 Metz, France
Téléphone: (33)-(0)3-87-75-81-83. Fax: (33)-(0)3-87-36-41-98
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
CURITIBA: A MIRACLE
OF URBAN PLANNING
Curitiba, the capital of the southern
Brazilian State of Parana, has 1.6
million inhabitants and the cleanest
atmosphere of all the cities in Brazil,
partly due to a master plan for urban
planning which was drawn up in
1964. The city's development has
been organized around a number of
3-lane traffic axes, the central lane
of which ¡s reserved for a 500-kilo¬
metre network used by a growing
number of increasingly efficient low-
cost buses accessible to the dis¬
abled. Nearly 70% of the population
takes public transportation every
day, as a result of which fuel con¬
sumption is 30% lower than in other
Brazilian cities of comparable size.
Old buses are used as classrooms,
clinics and libraries.
MINKE WHALES
UNDER SIEGE
Between May and June 1997, in defi¬
ance of the moratorium on whaling
decided in 1993 by the International
Whaling Commission, Norwegian
whalers harpooned 503 minke
whales, an increase of 100% over
the previous year. Including Japan's
440 captures made for "scientific
reasons" in the Antarctic sanctuary
and its 100 captures made In the
North Pacific, 1,000 minke whales
are now being killed annually.
MÊÊOÊÊÊIÊÊÊÊËIÊÊÊÊÊÊÊm
TOGO'S LOST SOIL
Of Togo's 4.2 million inhabitants,
90% make their living from agricul¬
ture. Subsistence crops account
for 85% of the agricultural sector.
Soil resources are therefore
extremely important. However, a
study made by the French Institute
of Scientific Research for Co-opera¬
tive Development (ORSTOM) has
shown that soil is deteriorating
owing to a set of factors including
reduction in the length of time when
fields lie fallow, deforestation,
uncontrolled brush fires, overgraz¬
ing, and Industrial activities. If fore¬
casts are correct and the popula¬
tion triples before the year 2035,
each inhabitant will have no more
than one quarter of an hectare to
provide subsistence (the world aver¬
age is close to two hectares). If soil
degradation continues unchecked,
$10 million will be needed to restore
the 90,000 hectares of seriously
affected land.
PAKISTAN'S MANGROVES:
REPLANTING HOMES
FOR SHRIMP
Mangrove trees afford protection
against erosion and provide shelter
for many kinds of animals, especially
certain species of edible crus¬
taceans. The destruction of these
aquatic forests threatens the
shrimp and crab populations that
reproduce in them. To combat this
trend, the World Wide Fund for
Nature (WWF) has launched a refor¬
estation project in Sonmlani Bay on
the western coast of Pakistan,
where villagers use mangrove wood
to build their homes and for cooking.
While the project initially met with
considerable scepticism, local peo¬
ple eventually agreed to build nurs¬
eries on more than 2.5 hectares,
where 60,000 saplings are already
growing. With the help of explana¬
tions about the project given by the
village schoolteachers, children have
come to understand that "planting
a mangrove means harvesting
shrimp." They now spend their free
time working on the project.
MANAGING
DROUGHT
The warm Pacific Ocean current
known as El Niño contributes to
global climatic changes, and partic¬
ularly to drought. Without effective
water resources management,
drought is an extremely costly propo¬
sition. In California drought resulted
in losses of up to $710 billion
between 1987 and 1992, and
drought crises in Africa and else¬
where have prompted the World
Bank to examine the possibilities of
long-term strategic planning to tackle
the problem. During the 1991-92
drought in Zimbabwe, the stock mar¬
ket declined by 62% and GDP by
11%. During the same drought in
South Africa, agricultural production
fell significantly. In order to improve
drought management, rational water
allocation policies must be designed
and investments made in commu¬
nity groundwater gardens, con¬
veyance and storage facilities, and
irrigation structures.
OECD
ON THE ENVIRONMENT
The Organisation for Economic Co¬
operation and Development (OECD)
has recently published the 1997 edi¬
tion of its bilingual (French-English)
Environmental Data Compendium.
Statistical data compiled from OECD
Member countries link pollution and
natural resources with energy, trans¬
portation, industry and agriculture.
One piece of information to be
gleaned from the Compendium, which
addresses air, inland waterways, soil,
forests, wildlife, and waste, is that
more than 20,000 species of mush¬
rooms have been identified in the
United Kingdom compared with only
300 In Iceland!
SENEGAL'S DJOUDJ PARK:
OF BIRDS ANDMEN
Senegal's Djoudj National Park is a
16,000-hectare wetland in the Sene¬
gal River Delta. The world's third
largest bird sanctuary, it is a haven
for nearly 400 species and is
included on the World Heritage List
and on the Ramsar Convention's
list of wetlands of international
importance. A biological station has
been built in the Park with assis¬
tance from Germany's North Rhlne-
Westphalia region. The local popula¬
tion Is not necessarily involved in
protecting the Park, however. Live¬
stock graze in the regularly flooded
fields and fishing deprives birds of
their food supplies. What could be
done to settle this clash of Inter¬
ests between men and birds?
THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
H E R I T A G E
by Parisina Malatesta
Ecuador
s
Colombia
: N
MlW'i'
Brazil
mx-
UMA Peru
Vi
NAZCA Hi
\
Pacific Ocean V
Below, wells (puquios) spiral into the
earth along the vast network of
underground irrigation channels that
cross the Nazca valley.
Vast networks of Lines etched in the soil of Nazca (Peru)
over 2,000 years ago form uncanny designs whose meaning
still puzzles many archaeologists. The site has been on
Unesco's World Heritage List since 1994.
The desert air, already
shimmering in the heat
despite the early hour, roars
through the windows of the small
aircraft in which we are overfly¬
ing the world's largest and most
impressive concentration of geo-
glyphs grooves incised in the
earth. Beneath us is the archaeo¬
logical site of Nazca, in southern
Peru, which has been on the
World Heritage List since 1994.
The lines, which form geo
metrical designs or figurative
motifs, mirror a cosmogonie sys¬
tem which we are only just begin¬
ning to understand. Traced more
than 2,000 years ago by the peo¬
ple of the Nazca culture, like
writing on a giant slate, they cover
an area of almost 500 square kilo¬
metres of arid land surrounded
by outcrops of rock.
As if fascinated by the spec¬
tacle beneath it, the small one-
engined plane slowly circles over
the huge designs a pelican 285
metres long, a guanay (guano
bird) of 280 metres, a lizard of
180 metres (cut in two by the
Pan-American highway!). The
number of these large etchings in
the soil and the period of time
over which they made from the
fourth century B.C. to the fifth
century A.D. are equally
astounding. Virtually invisible
from the surface, they can only
be fully taken in from the air.
Their existence was unknown for
centuries, and even today they are
an archaeological enigma.
Who were the Nazca, the peo¬
ple whose culture flourished in
Above, an aerial view
of the humming-bird,
one of the Impressive
animal outlines
etched into the
Nazca desert.
Opposite page, one
of many specimens of
Nazca pottery In
Peru's National
Archaeological
Museum in Lima.
44
THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH I 99B
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
/
^¿yr-m
this sun-scorched and windswept
region of the world? What is the
meaning of their designs?
A COMPLEX CULTURE
Although the spiritual universe
of the Nazca children of the off¬
shore winds blowing in from the
Pacific and ancestors of the Iluari
culture is still shrouded in mys¬
tery, sufficient vestiges of their
culture and craftsmanship have
survived for us to answer the first
question. If the early ceremonial
centre of Kawachi is included,
their territory extended between
the rivers Grande and Nazca. It
included the oases of the Ingenio
and Palpa river valleys situated
between the cordillera of the
Andes and the Pacific and the
uninhabited alluvial plains
stretching between the towns of
Palpa and Nazca, where the geo-
glyphs are to be found.
It is in this inhospitable
region one of the most arid on
the planet that the Nazca devel¬
oped a complex and industrious
culture. Much of their history is
reflected in their craft produc¬
tion, such as textiles, beaten gold
artefacts and above all funerary
pottery, in which they used as
many as seven colours, whose dif¬
ferent shades mark an amazing
contrast with the austere tones of
the surrounding desert. The
National Archaeological Museum
of Peru has some 2,500 of these
ceramic pieces, which have a per¬
fect finish and are in an excellent
slate of preservation owing to the
region's dry atmosphere.
Further proof of the level of
development reached by the
Nazca can be seen in the vast
hydraulic engineering works
which they built to make up for
the shortage of water and fertilize
THE UNESCO (oURIIER MARCH I99B
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
the land and which are still in
working order. They form an
extensive network of underground
channels, sometimes conveying the
water for kilometres before
emerging from time to time in
superbly designed wells known as
puquios. Seen from the sky, these
lines of funnel-shaped cavities spi¬
ralling into the earth appear to
stitch together whole stretches
of the valley.
AN IMMENSE SLATE MADE OF SAND
Over the eight centuries during
which they were created, the geo-
glyphs seem to have evolved from
figurative motifs to increasingly
geometrical and symbolic patterns.
Whether or not this is the case,
two main kinds of design can be
distinguished. The first category,
comprising some seventy items,
consists of drawings of animals and
plants. The largest and most spec¬
tacular concentration of animal sil¬
houettes is on the slopes of the
Ingenio river valley and includes a
monkey, a spider, a dog, a hum¬
ming-bird and a killer whale. The
few human figures, such as the
thirty-metre-tall "astronaut" or
owl-man etched into a hillside near
Jumana, are creatures of fantasy.
Other drawings depict flowers,
plants or twisted trees, and every-
A dog (above) and a
monkey (top) are
among the most
readily identifiable
Nazca designs.
Top right, a monkey
with a colled tall on
a piece of Nazca
pottery resembles
the one etched in the
earth.
day objects, such as a weaver's
loom.
These figurative motifs moved
towards a more consolidated sym¬
bolic form, which gave rise to the
second category of geoglyphs.
These are lines which look as if
they have been traced with a ruler
and cut through the plain, some¬
times for kilometres on end, to
form a variety of geometrical fig¬
ures such as triangles, spirals and
rectangles. Others span outwards
from a central promontory or
encircle it like the quipu cords
used in Inca accounting systems.
Yet another group is formed of
"paths" for the guidance of peo¬
ple travelling on foot.
Most of the motifs, figurative
and geometrical alike, are found
on pottery and textiles dating from
the same period. Maria Reiche,
who spent many years studying the
Nazca lines, came to the conclu¬
sion that these geometrical draw¬
ings were symbolic writing in which
the same words were sometimes
written in giant characters and in
other instances in small letters.
The technique used by the
Nazca to produce these designs
was both simple and ingenious. All
they had to do was to rake back
the dark and gravelly topsoil to
uncover the much lighter-coloured
clay layer and to pile the waste
material in 30-centimetre-high
banks on either side of the line.
The high degree of oxidation of
the soil and the moist winds at
night, which clean out the furrows
clogged with sand by the winds
blowing during the day, have pro¬
tected the Nazca lines until the
present time. In addition to these
engraved intaglio-like designs are
some executed in relief and oth¬
ers, which are much older, incised
into the sides of mountains.
46
THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
IIow did the Nazca solve the
problems of scale? According to
Maria Beiehe, they had plans on
which they plotted short dis¬
tances, which they then had only
to multiply and transpose using
stakes and ropes like a gigantic
set of compasses. The precision
of the measurements and angles
shows that they had a thorough
command of geometry.
THE MYSTERY UNVEILED?
When the Peruvian scholar Mejia
Xesspe first saw the Nazca lines
in 1926, shortly after their acci¬
dental discovery, he thought that
they were "sacred roads", since
some of them were like paths along
which it was possible to walk.
However, it was not until 1911 that
the first scientific exploration mis¬
sion was organized under the direc¬
tion of the American historian Paul
Kosok, with the assistance of the
Peruvian air force.
On 22 June 1941, the shortest
day of the year in the southern
hemisphere, Kosok noticed that
the sun set precisely at the end
of one of the lines. He concluded
that it was a solstice line and thus
came to regard the Nazca geo-
glyphs as being the world's biggest
astronomy book.
The following year, Kosok
returned to Nazca with Maria
Reiche, a German translator from
Lima. Stunned by the spectacle
and intrigued by the mystery of
Left, a viewing
platform beside the
Pan-American
highway allows
tourists to look at
the giant figures
engraved in the
earth.
Some pottery pieces
are decorated In as
many as seven
different colours,
right.
the geoglyphs, she was to spend
the rest of her life elucidating the
enigma of Nazca and protecting
the site.
According to Reiche, who eon-
firmed this aspect of Kosok's the¬
ory, the Nazca lines are a gigantic
astronomical calendar recording
the passing of the seasons and pre¬
dicting eclipses of the sun and the
moon. In her book Contribuciones a
la geometría y astronomía en el
antiguo Perú" (1993, "Contribu¬
tions of ancient Peru to the history
Above, a frigate bird,
a seabird with a very
broad wingspan.
Left, the owl-man, or
astronaut, one of the
very few
anthropomorphic
Nazca designs.
Right, this jug
illustrates the highly
skilled craftsmanship
of the Nazca potters.
THE UNESCO QpURI ER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
of geometry and astronomy"), she
wrote: "The Nazca knew about
the movements of the heavenly
bodies and knew how to calculate
exactly when to start sowing and
when to gather in the harvest.
They can accordingly claim to have
their place in the history of astron¬
omy". In her opinion, the stars
were the template for the orien¬
tation of the Nazca lines. The 46-
metre long spider, for example,
was connected with the constella¬
tion of Orion and the spectacular
110-metre-long monkey with the
Pleiades.
However, the theories of Kosok
and Reiche are countered by
research conducted by the astro¬
physicist Gerald S. Hawkins, who
in 1967 reconstituted by com¬
puter the changes in the map of
the sky in the Nazca region over
the past 7,000 years. He demon¬
strated that 80 per cent of the
geoglyphs bear no relation to the
movement of the forty-five main
heavenly bodies in the sky over
Nazca and that only thirty-nine
lines coincide with the movements
of the sun and moon.
OPEN-AIRTEMPLES
Disregarding the far-fetched the¬
ories of Erich von Daniken, Hunt
Williamson and others, who
looked upon the lines as landing
strips meant to be seen from the
sky by extraterrestrial creatures,
most scientists now agree that the
geoglyphs performed a ritual
function connected with astron¬
omy. The designs were probably
totemic representations connected
with the organization of elans (ayl-
lus), which helped to maintain the
social and religious hegemony of
the Nazca over the centuries.
Some archaeologists regard the
designs as fantastic open-air tem¬
ples which made it possible for the
people to enter into communion
with the cosmic force of the spirit
they represented. It is true that
most of the drawings have a clearly
identifiable "entrance". For exam
ple, it is possible to start out from
the eoiled-up tail of the monkey
design, which like the others is
formed by a single unbroken line,
and follow the whole figure in out¬
line right back to the starting
point. It can be readily surmised
that such continuity must have
had a ritual purpose.
Like a large map of the celes¬
tial world, these lines on the
pampa challenge us not only to
decipher their meaning but also to
preserve them in an environment so
fragile that every footprint leaves
its mark. Through Maria Reiche's
endeavours, a viewing platform
has been built for visitors, but this
does not prevent motor vehicles
from driving on the existing tracks
and leaving indelible tyre-marks
in the landscape. Unless the nec¬
essary protection measures are
taken, this exceptional archaeo¬
logical site, which has come down
to us intact after more than 2,000
years, could disappear forever in
the space of a few decades.
Some theorists have
maintained that
these long straight
lines traced In the
desert indicate
landing strips for
extraterrestrial
creatures.
THE UNESCO COURIER MARCH 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Ton-Thatlïêt
talks to ISABELLE LEYMARIE
Ton-That Tiêt, who was born in 1933 in Hue, the former capital of imperial Viet Nam, and has
lived in Paris since 1958, is a composer who has succeeded in marrying Western musical styles
with a profoundly Oriental form of thinking and sensibility. Silence, as well as the expressive
beauty of sounds, plays an important part in his works, which reflect their author's
preoccupation with the harmony between humanity and the universe.
How did you come to Western music?
Ton-That Tiêt: When I was about fourteen or fif¬
teen, I wanted to play the violin. My brothers and sis¬
ters clubbed together to buy me one, which they
arranged to be sent from France. One of my cousins,
who played the violin a little, gave me lessons, but
when he emigrated to France, I found nobody in
Hué to replace him and I had to work on my own,
with a method and scores which I ordered specially.
How did you continue your studies?
T.-T. T.: I dreamed of going to Paris and entering
the Conservatoire. I worked and saved for two years
in order to pay for the journey. When I got to Paris,
I was introduced to a teacher at the Conservatoire,
Georges Dandelot. My knowledge of music theory
was so sketchy that I had to start all over again, or
almost. I had so much work that I had to give up
the violin. I soon learned that I could not work at an
instrument and go in for advanced theoretical stud¬
ies at the same time. I also studied counterpoint
with Madame Honegger at the Paris Ecole Nor¬
male de Musique. At the end of two years, I
obtained a degree in harmony and applied for a
place at the Conservatoire.
Were you already composing?
T.-T. T.: Not yet. However, in order to be accepted
in the composition class, I had to submit some¬
thing. I composed a piece for string quartet which
left no abiding impression. When I started to study
composition in the early 1960s, I was attracted by
serial music and started studying it by myself. At
the time, many of my fellow students were com¬
posing in that idiom. However, my teacher Jean
Rivier advised me to give it up. One day he said to
Select discography
HyVong267(CBS)
Incarnations Structurales (Erato)
Tuong Niem (G.L.B.)
Terre-Feu (CRI)
Niem/Trung Dzuong
For further information:
Association
France-Viet Nam pour la musique
16, ruedu Dauphiné
94100
Saint-Maur-des-Fossés
France
Tel: (33) (0)148 83 73 28
me: "Go back to Asia and try to find your own way".
He encouraged me to go deeper into my knowledge
of Asian traditional music and to study Oriental
philosophy. André Jolivet, who took over from him,
was also a considerable influence on me in that
respect. Rediscovering Oriental thinking was an
important step, because it created a mental uni¬
verse which enabled me to find my own personal
style. At the end of three or four years, Jolivet saw
that the path I had chosen was beginning to emerge.
How did you rediscover Vietnamese music?
T.-T. T.: The Guimct museum in Paris has a col¬
lection of recordings of Vietnamese music and used
to hold concerts of Oriental music. The musicolo¬
gist Tran Van Khê, who worked there, introduced
me to lîiulilhist music.
How did you come across the idea of composing
on the basis of the five elements: wood, fire, earth,
metal and water?
T.-T. T: By stud) ing Chinese philosophy, and espe¬
cially ihcYiChing. My first work, an orchestral piece
called Five Elements, which was based on the Yi
Ching, was composed in 1972, and I returned to the
same theme in 1981. However, I did not use the Yi
Ching in a random fashion, like John Cage, or as a div-
inatory form, since that did not interest me. What
fascinates me in the Yi Ching is the explanation it
gives of the evolution of the universe. I also took an
interest in Great Vehicle Buddhism, but strictly
from a philosophical standpoint, since I do not prac¬
tise any religion. The two main themes of my work
are humanity and the universe. Buddhism and the
other Oriental philosophies stress universal love and
the fact that all human beings are brothers.
THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Do you use Asian instruments in your
compositions?
T.-T. T.: I used a single-stringed instrument on one
occasion, in a piece for flute and magnetic tape
commissioned by the French Institute for musi¬
cal-acoustical research and co-ordination (IRCAM).
What projects do you have in hand at the moment?
T.-T. T.: I am working on a second ballet for the
Régine Chopinot company I already wrote one
for them in 1996 on the theme of fire, in harmony
and opposition with the five elements. I am now
looking into the concept of time. I am interested in
handling this theme in the Oriental rather than
Western manner. The West invented linear and cycli¬
cal time, whereas in Asia the concept of time draws
on its absence, since time does not exist in the uni¬
verse. The Yi-Ching speaks neither of beginning
nor end. There is no original "big bang".
You are also endeavouring to safeguard the
musical traditions of Viet Nam.
T.-T. T.: In 1992, 1 had an opportunity to attend
Words for music
BYADÁMFELLEGI
In spite of the large number of festivals, concerts
and cultural gatherings, often of a very high stan¬
dard, that are held worldwide, each year, classical
European culture, traditionally the culture of
elites, is attracting fewer and fewer young people.
Artists themselves painters and musicians
alike bear their share of responsibility for this
deplorable state of affairs. Since they disdain
change and are indeed hostile to it, they rely on
refining their art, in the hope that virtuosity alone
will be sufficient to bring back the audience which
they no longer command. The grave error they com¬
mit is that they do not make adequate allowance for
public, expectations and disregard the fact that, in
art, lack of communication rules out any possibil¬
ity of communion with the work.
My own experience as a pianist has taught me
that a few simple but well-chosen words of intro¬
duction often make it possible for the public to go
deeper into the work I am about to play and to appre¬
ciate it all the more. The form which this brief intro¬
duction takes matters little: it may be a formal or
historical analysis, a biographical overview, putting
the work in perspective through comparisons or a
general cultural commentary. The important thing is
to give an idea of the work being presented.
50 r
W THE UNESCO lOURIER MARCH 1998
some courses on traditional music at Hanoi Con¬
servatory and I was appalled at what I heard: the
music had been altered and harmonized and new
features had been tacked on to it.
The following year, in Hanoi, I met a very old
woman who was a wonderful exponent of catru, a
style of singing notable for its vibrato and special
vocal techniques. She was the only surviving expo¬
nent of this style. I asked her to train some young
singers, so that the tradition would not be lost. In
fact, the family of musicians accompanying her
had a daughter who sang some catru. Madame
Quach Thi Ho agreed to take her under her wing.
In Hué, I contacted all the performers of tra¬
ditional music. I organized a meeting with the three
leading master musicians and asked them to recre¬
ate a court music orchestra.
They regularly sent me cassettes, so that I could
hear what progress they were making. After one
year, the imperial orchestra was proficient, but
the younger musicians still had tobe trained. I was
amazed to find that the girl who was learning cairu
had perfectly mastered the vocal technique. I was
subsequently able to organize a concert of tradi¬
tional Vietnamese music at the Maison des Cul¬
tures et du Monde in Paris in 1993. I
Obviously, the length of the introduction should
not exceed that of the piece itself. The performer
speaking should be sincere and convinced of what he
is saying, and should use language that a child can
understand. Care should be taken to avoid technical
jargon. It is essential for the performer in person to
present the work about to be played. Using a tape
recorder to play a pre-recorded message is likely to
alienate the audience. On the other hand, the con¬
tortions and mimicry in which a virtuoso in swallow¬
tails may indulge while playing ran have a deterrent
effect on would-be music-lovers.
At each of my recitals I endeavour to say a few
words, in four languages, about the masterpieces
which I am going to perform, masterpieces which
are now so seldom played in public, such as the
sonatas of Mozart and Beethoven or Bach's ÏVie
Well-Tempered Clavier. Through this approach, I
believe that I have found a way of combating one of
the afflictions currently affecting the world of
music. Unfortunately, the effectiveness of such an
approach does not prevent it from being disre¬
garded by professionals who, like me, have been
brought up to worship the technicalities of per¬
formance, to the detriment of a broader approach
to the work and its reproduction. I
AUTHORS
NIMRODBENADJANGRANG.a
Chadian poet, short-story writer
and novelist, is editor of Aleph,
Beth, a review of the arts,
philosophy and literature published
in France.
FRANÇOISE AUBIN, a French
sinologist and a specialist on Islam
and Christianity in Chinese
civilization, is a research officer at
the French National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS).
A.S. GNANASAMBANDAN.an
Indian philosopher and writer, is a
specialist ¡n Tamil literature, on
which he has published over 30
books. He is also the author of a
comparative study on Western and
Eastern philosophies.
JACQUES LE GOFF, a French
medievalist and former President of
the School of Advanced Studies in
Social Sciences (EHESS) in Pans, is
the author of many published
works, including La naissance du
purgatoire ("The Birth of
Purgatory"; Gallimard, Paris, 1981)
and, more recently a biography of
St. Louis (Gallimard, Pans, 1996).
GREG OXLEY, a British journalist
and photographer, is head of the
English language section of the
French academic review Etudes
Orientales.
PETER FENWICK, a British
neuropsychiatrist and specialist in
epilepsy, is a consultant at The
Radcliffe Infirmary, Oxford. He is the
author of a large number of research
papers and, with his wife, of a
study on near-death experiences
entitled The Truth and the Light
(Headline Press, London, 1995).
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-
American journalist specializing in
environmental issues.
PARISINA MALATESTA, an Italian
writer and journalist who lives in
Venezuela, is the author of a
collection of children's stories Les
Aventuras de Juan y Juana ("The
Adventures of Juan and Juana",
1995).
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-
American musicologist, is the
author of La musique sud-
américaine, Rythmes et danses d'un
continent ("South American Music,
a Continent's Rhythms and
Dances", Gallimard, Pans, 1997).
ADAM FELLEGI is a Hungarian
pianist whose recordings include
works by Bartok, Berg and
Schoenberg.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (OURIER JVffiOfI INTERNATIONAL PHOTO COMPETITION
PEACE IN EVERYDAY LIFE
exhibition
23 February - 9 March
Unesco House, Miró Hall
9, place de Fontenoy
75007 Paris
Condemning war, tyranny and oppression; encouraging freedom, tolerance, democracy and
mutual understanding among peoples.
To celebrate its fiftieth anniversary, the Unesco Courier is organizing an exhibition of photos
entered in the Unesco Courier-NIKON international photo competition. Some 300 professional
photographers from 39 countries took part in the contest, which was held in 1997.
Award-winning entries and photos which the judges considered particularly noteworthy
will be on show to the public.
Les revues s'exposent au
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
«*C;\
THEME OF THE NEXT ISSUE:
ROCK ART '
INTERVIEW WITH
BOSNIAN POET IZETSARAJLlC
ENVIRONMENT
CUBA'S BIOSPHERE RESERVES
]]>
</page>
</document>
