<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="111392eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m r
tf^Wà
k^\
s V
*-r
-
l \
interviKhvith
IZET SARAJLIC
ENVIRONMENT: x
CUBAS BIOSPHERE RESERVES A
>
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (OURIER J
INTERNATIONAL PHOTO
COMPETITION
PEACE IN EVERYDAY LIFE
A selection of photos entered in the competition will be
featured on this page in forthcoming issues.
A Dinka herdsman
(Sudan) with a newborn
calf. Photo by Roger Job
(Belgium).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (bu RI ER
INTERVIEW
48
IzetSarajlic
The hopes andfears ofa noted Bosnian poet.
contents -+^~
APRIL 1998
primeval art
ROCK PAINTING AND ENGRAVING
The first stirrings of creation	4
by Robert G. Bednarik
The writing on the wall 11
40,000 years of Homo intellectualis
by Emmanuel Anati
The prehistoric imagination	17
by Denis Vialou
'For Australian Aborigines, rock painting is a title to their land' . . . .22
Interview
The shaman's journey	24
by Jean Clottes
An endangered art 29
by François Soleilhavoup
An open-air museum in the Sahara	32
by Axel and Anne-Michelle Van Albada
Rock art of sub-Saharan Africa: a thumbnail guide	36
by Osaga Odak
Fact file	38
Consultant: François Soleilhavoup
Commentary Federico Mayor
GREENWATCH Cuba's biosphere reserves by France Bequette 42
ANNIVERSARY Elijah ben Solomon Zalman, thegaonof Vilna by Henri Minczeles 45
Cover:
Hunting an armadillo. A rock painting at
Pedro Furâda, Serra Capivara, Piauí state (Brazil)
© All rights reserved
LISTENING It's rumba time! by Isabelle Leymarie
AUTHORS
46
50
HE UNESCO ^ÍURIER APRIL 1998 %
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The first stirrings
of creation BY ROBERT G.BEDNARIK
Rock art, found in almost all the world's regions,
is a mine of information about early man's intellectual development
Handprints in a rock shelter
at Rio Pinturas in Argentina's
Chubut province.
Prehistoric rock art is by far the largest
body of evidence we have of human¬
ity's artistic, cognitive and cultural beginnings.
It is found in most countries of the world,
from the tropics to the Arctic regions, in sites
ranging from deep caves to high mountains.
Many tens of millions of rock art figures or
motifs have been found, and more are being
discovered each year. This massive, semi-per¬
manent and cumulative record is the most
direct evidence we have of how pre-humans
first became human and then evolved complex
social systems.
Some widely held misconceptions about
the origins of art must be dispelled at the out¬
set. Art as such did not appear suddenly, but
developed gradually with the cognitive evo
lution of humans. By the time that the famous
cave art of France and Spain was being pro¬
duced, art traditions are thought to have been
well established at least in southern Africa,
the Levant, eastern Europe, India and Aus¬
tralia, and no doubt in many other regions
that have yet to be examined adequately.
When were humans first able to produce
abstractions of reality? In addition to its inter¬
est for the art historian and the archaeologist,
this question is of wider concern, if only
because ideas of cultural precedence have been
effective in shaping racial, ethnic and national
value judgments and even fantasies. The notion
that art began in the caves of western Europe
furthers myths of European cultural prece¬
dence, for example. Secondly, the origins of art
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL I 9<*8
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Rock carvings at an open-air
site at Twyfelfontein, Namibia.
are thought to be intimately intertwined with
the emergence of several other distinctively
human faculties: the ability to form abstract
concepts, to symbolize, to communicate at an
advanced level, to develop a notion of the self.
Apart from prehistoric art we have no tangible
evidence from which to infer these capacities.
The beginnings ofart
Art production was preceded by "non-utili¬
tarian" behaviour patterns, i.e. behaviour that
seems to lack practical purpose. The earliest
discernible archaeological evidence for this is
the use of ochre or haematite, a red mineral
pigment collected and used by people several
hundred thousand years ago. These early
humans also collected crystals and petrified
fossils, and colourful or oddly shaped pebbles.
They had begun to distinguish between ordi¬
nary, everyday objects and the unusual, the
exotic. Presumably they had developed con¬
cepts of a world in which objects could be cat¬
egorized into different classes. Evidence of
this appears first in southern Africa, then in
Asia and finally in Europe.
The oldest known rock art was produced
in India two or three hundred thousand years
ago. It consists of cup marks and a meander¬
ing line hammered into the rock of a sand¬
stone cave. At about the same time, simple
line markings were made on a variety of
portable objects (bone, teeth, ivory and stone)
which have been found at the camp sites of
early humans. Sets of bunched engraved lines
j (puTHEUNESCO ÍOURIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
: ; ' :§t^M^t"¥m'
fJtr
>/
Pi'V
first appear in central and eastern Europe; they phase rock art also appears in Europe, the old-
developed into distinctive arrangements that est known example being an arrangement of
can be recognized as motifs such as zigzags, eighteen cup marks in a French cave, on a rock
crosses, arcs and sets of parallel lines. slab placed over a child's burial spot.
This phase, which archaeologists call the Perhaps the most interesting aspect of this
Middle Palaeolithic (perhaps 35,000 to 150,000 period is the cultural uniformity that prevailed
years ago), is crucial in human intellectual and throughout the then-settled world. Despite
cognitive development. This was also the time differences in tools, doubtless due to responses
when people developed seafaring capacity, and to environmental differences, cultural behaviour
crossings of up to 180 km were eventually was surprisingly consistent. The use of ochre
made by colonizing parties. Regular ocean nav- and the fairly uniform repertoire of geometric
igation clearly required an advanced system of markings are indications of a universal artistic
communication, presumably language. language among archaicrTomo sapiens, includ-
People of this period also mined ochre and ing the Neanderthal people of Europe and oth-
flint in several world regions. They began ers about whom we know from fossil remains,
building large communal dwellings of mam- Figurative depiction in the round (sculp-
moth bones in southern Russia, and erected ture) first appears in Israel (c. 250-300,000 years
stone walls in caves. But most importantly, ago), as modified natural form, then in Siberia
they produced art. In Australia, some speci- and central Europe (c. 30-35,000 years ago), and
mens of rock art may be up to 60,000 years later in western Europe. By 30,000 or so years
old, as old as human occupation of the conti- ago, rock art included complex finger mark-
nent itself, and hundreds of sites contain ings on soft cave surfaces in Australia and in
examples which are thought to predate the Europe, and hand stencils in France. Finally,
cave art of western Europe. But during this two-dimensional pictures of objects began to
Stylized animal figure at
Helanshan, Ningxia (China)
THEU-JESCO G-RIER APRIL I
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Examples of early rock art,
dating back to the Middle
Palaeolithic (35,000-150,000
years ago). Object (c) is a
tooth, (d) is a fossil nummulite,
and the rest are bone
fragments. The finds are fro m
Ukraine (a-c), Hungary (d),
France (e) and Bulgaria (f).
appear; the oldest examples, about 32,000 years
old, are from France, followed by paintings
from Namibia in southern Africa.
By about 20,000 years ago, quite recent in
terms of human history, cultures began to
diverge noticeably. In western Europe, Upper
Palaeolithic people developed sophisticated tra¬
ditions of both sculpted and graphic art for
ritual or decorative use. By 15,000 years ago,
this tradition produced glorious masterworks
in such caves as Altamira (Spain) and Lascaux
(France), and thousands of finely carved fig¬
urines made of stone, ivory, bone, clay or other
materials. This is the time of the finest poly¬
chromatic cave art, painted or engraved with
the confident strokes of master artists. Graphic
art traditions elsewhere, however, developed
very differently. In Russia and across Asia, geo¬
metric art forms were elaborated into highly
developed systems, some of which resemble
formal records, while others may have been
mnemonic devices, memory prompters
designed to record texts.
From about the end of the Ice Age, about
10,000 years ago, rock paintings begin to appear
outside caves. This almost certainly reflects the
selective survival of rock art rather than a new
preference in the choice of sites. Rock paint¬
ings can survive very well in the stable envi¬
ronments of deep limestone caves but not on
rock surfaces that are more exposed to damage.
The apparent proliferation of rock art around
the end of the Ice Age therefore indicates, not
an increase in art production but that a thresh¬
old of preservation has been crossed.
On all continents except Antarctica, rock
paintings now bear witness to a multitude of
art styles and cultures, to the progressively
increasing ethnic diversification of humanity
on all continents, and to the development of the
major religions. Even the recent historical devel¬
opments of mass migrations, colonization and
religious expansion are all reflected in rock art.
Dating
There are two basic forms of rock art, petro-
glyphs (or carvings) and pictographs (or paint¬
ings). The motifs of petroglyphs were created
by engraving, hammering, incising or abrading
Rock carvings of four human
figures. Toro Muerto (Peru).
: rWW.
t r
:/)
\
Vf
<#
I
J f J, r"
J
i. ;
I
t
i . *
1
y f i
the Unesco Courier atril iqos B
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
t rock surfaces. In pictographs some material
was added to the rock surface, usually paint.
The distinction is important because it deter¬
mines approaches to dating.
The methodology of dating rock art scien¬
tifically has only developed over the last fifteen
years or so. It is still therefore in its infancy, and
nearly all the world's rock art remains effec¬
tively undated. This does not mean that we
have no idea of its age, however, since there are
often various indicators of approximate or at
least probable age. It is sometimes possible to
determine the age of rock paintings quite accu¬
rately, especially when the paint contains organic
' substances or microscopic inclusions that arc
datable through their radiocarbon content.
Careful interpretation of such analytical results
can make dating quite reliable.
Set of 18 cup marks on the
underside of a rock slab placed
over a Neanderthal child's
grave (France).
© Robert Bednank. Melbourne, Australia
Stylized painted animal
figures at Raisen, near Bhopal
(India).
.*v.
Dating petroglyphs, on the other hand,
remains very difficult. Most current methods
seek to establish the age of a mineral skin that
may have formed over the rock art and thus
provide merely minimum ages. One technique
is to analyse microscopic organic material
encased in such mineral skins; laser technology
can be used successfully for this purpose. But
currently only one method is available to deter¬
mine the age of the petroglyph itself. It is based
on the fact that the mineral crystals that were
fractured when the petroglyph was hammered
into the rock initially had sharp edges, which
became blunt and rounded with age. By deter¬
mining from nearby surfaces of known ages
how fast this process operates, the age of a pet¬
roglyph surface can be estimated.
Several archaeological dating methods can
also provide limited assistance. If, for instance,
an archaeological, datable layer of soil covers
petroglyphs on a rock wall, it can be assumed
to provide a minimum age for the rock art.
Stylistic comparison has often been used to
construct chronological frameworks for rock
art, but not very successfully.
The most promising methods of studying
rock art often resemble those of forensic sci¬
ence. For instance, paint components may tell
us how the paint was mixed, what implements
and additives were used, where the pigment
came from, and so forth. Human blood,
which was used as a binding agent in the Ice
> GuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
I I «
J*
IIP*''' 4
V
Vtfe*
-
I *
V,
jrtf] .
V
*
Age, has been detected in ancient Australian
rock paintings. Australian researchers have also
found as many as forty very thin superim¬
posed layers of paint at many sites, indicating
continuous repainting of the same rock sur¬
faces over long periods of time. Like the pages
of a book, these layers record the history of
the site's use by artists of many generations.
The study of such sequences is only just begin¬
ning and may result in entirely new insights.
Paint brush fibres have been found in rock
art paint, and so has pollen which can indi¬
cate vegetation contemporary with the time
of painting. In some French caves, distinctive
paint recipes have been identified from their
chemical makeup. In the case of charcoal pig¬
ment in a black painting, even the genus of
the tree from which the charcoal originated
has been established.
Rock art research has become a scientific
discipline in its own right, and already draws
on many other disciplines, from geology to
semiotics, from ethnography to computer
science. The methodology includes colour
enhancement of electronic imagery derived
Stencilled outlines of
boomerangs, axes and hands.
Carnarvon Gorge, Queensland
(Australia).
© Robert Bednank, Melbourne, Australia
from very faded, barely visible pictures; vari¬
ous specialized recording techniques; and
microscopic study of tool marks and minute
residues.
fragile vestiges
Methods of rock art conservation are also
being developed and increasingly applied. Rock
art panels and even entire sites are being repli¬
cated in order to protect the original from
deterioration. Yet much of the world's pre¬
historic art is now severely threatened. Acid
rain dissolves the protective mineral coating
that covers many petroglyphs. Increasing cul¬
tural tourism, encroaching urban, industrial
and mining development, even misguided
research all take their toll.
Efforts are being made in some countries
to protect and preserve this remarkable but
fragile cultural resource. International agencies,
especially UNESCO, can help by encouraging
international uniformity of protective legisla¬
tion, streamlining research and applied science,
and helping develop global approaches to rock
art conservation and site management.
> GuTHE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
'
Â
X.
1. Rock paintings produced by
a society of early gatherers,
Tassih-N'Ajjer, Algeria (so-called
"round head" phase around
5000 B.C.). They show 2
figures, each wearing a
mushroom-shaped mask and
holding a mushroom from
which a line of dots reaches
up to its head. Three elements
of rock art "grammar" are
found In this composition: the
human figure, the mushroom
shape and a set of small dots.
Drawings on pages 10 16
© Emanuel Anati 1997. WARA. Centro Camuno de
Studi Preistorici. Capo di Ponte. Italy
3. Rock paintings of
anthropozoomorphic figures
produced by Neolithic
hunters (5,000-6,000 years
ago) atOuan Meilen in the
Tassili-N'Ajjer.
2. Rock paintings made by hunters of the
Mesolithic period (6,000-8,000 years ago) in the
Levante area of southeastern Spain.
Anthropozoomorphic figures occur in rock art all
over the world and over several millennia. These
are carrying weapons.
10 THtUNtSCO lOURIER ATRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
iü
40.000 YEARS OF HOMO INTELLECTUALS
The writing
; on the wall
* BY EMMANUEL ANATI
Prehistoric rock paintings and engravings
may be a language with its own grammar
and syntax
4. Rock engravings found at Tamgali
(Kazakhstan). Two anthropomorphic
wolves or foxes armed with hooks or
having hook-shaped hands are moving in
on a small creature with a tail and a
feather on its head. The scene appears
to depict a dance relating to a myth.
Stag hunt (500 B.C.). Chelly
Canyon, California (U.S.A.).
© Monique Pietn. Pans
All over the world, in more than 120
countries, groups of human beings have
left behind examples of rock paintings or carv¬
ings. Rock seems to have been the first support
they chose on which to create their works of
art; it is, at any rate, on rock that examples of
their art have come down to us. Body-paint¬
ing and tattoos, ornaments, decorations,
paintings on bark or on palm leaves, draw¬
ings in sand and collections of unusually
shaped or coloured pebbles are other art forms
that may have existed before rock art, but they
have not withstood the passage of millennia,
while music and the dance have left only indi¬
rect evidence of their existence in graphic rep¬
resentations or in the remains of musical
instruments discovered in the course of archae¬
ological excavations.
Rock art is typically the product of pre-lit-
erate societies, beginning with the emergence of
Homo sapiens and generally dying out when
the communities that practised it acquired a
"written" form of communication. It thus
constitutes by far the most important record
we possess of humanity's history before the
invention of writing. It also provides invalu¬
able source material for the study of human
beings' cognitive development, which is why
it is so important to establish a world data
bank, as the WARA (World Archives on Rock
Art) project aims to do (see Fact file, page 39).
Almost all prehistoric art focuses on three
basic themes: sex, food and territory. Humans'
main concerns seem not to have changed very
much down the ages. . . .
The art and its environment
Before looking at the graphic, intellectual and
ideological content of the works themselves,
we need to clarify a number of essential points
concerning the relationship between them and
their environment.
Space. The natural forms and the position
selected on the rock face are the most obvious
such relationship so obvious, indeed, that
it is often overlooked. In fact, the relation¬
ship between the thing depicted, the sign, and
the positioning of the depiction is a concrete,
physical one, and corresponds to a specific
choice, whether conscious or unconscious.
Comparative studies carried out world-wide
have demonstrated that the artists chose the
positions of their images in accordance with
widely recurring criteria.
The individual. The person making that
choice obviously had a specific identity: he or
she may have been young or old, a shaman or
a lay person art has never been practised by
all and sundry. Another type of relationship
is therefore to be sought in the linkage between
the surviving work of art and the type of indi¬
vidual who created it. In some cases, in tribal
art of a later date as well as in prehistoric art,
it is possible to ascertain whether the work
was executed by an initiate or a non-initiate, by
a man or by a woman.
5. Rock engraving at Tiout (Algeria) produced by hunters some time during the 2nd millennium B.C. The way in
which the various elements are combined shows a certain logic and an ability to synthesize and handle
abstractions. Analysis of the "syntax" of the engraving highlights the parallel between hunting and sex. The
ostrich hunter (centre) is using a bow and arrow and is accompanied by a dog. A line runs from the hunter's
penis to the pubis of a female figure behind him whose gender ¡s indicated by a pair of parallel lines on either side
of her body. Similar lines, or "lips", represent the female sex organ.
Between these two figures is a goat with a triangular symbol between its horns, and the same symbol recurs
on the woman's head. This may be an ideograph providing a particular item of information: the animal figure
associated with it could be a clue to the woman's identity or name. The huntsman's identity is established by
three vertical lines above his head. The figure of the ostrich, the huntsman's prey, is accompanied by two dots,
conferring the status of an object on it and meaning "something to be hunted".
THE UNESCO ÇpURIE I APRIL 1998
ll
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
6. Rock engraving by early hunters of the Murray
River region (southern Australia). It features a
schematic outline of a quadruped accompanied by
several ideographs. A sign representing the vulva
occupies a central place. There are also several
series of dots, lines, groups of lines and a dot-and-
line ideograph that recurs several times. This
combination of graphemes denotes a repetitive
syntax characteristic of a certain type of cognition
found world-wide.
7. Quadruped
Tim e. The painting or engraving was made
at a particular time of the day or night, in sum¬
mer or in winter, or even at a particular point in
the artist's personal life, The act of executing it
occurred within a dynamic context, before,
after or during other physical or mental activ¬
ities before or after the hunt, before or after
eating or sleeping, before or after doing other
things. It also took place under particular cir¬
cumstances, at a moment spent in solitude or
in company, during a ceremony or the practice
of meditation, in a noisy place or in total
silence like any other act, it fits into a temporal
and sequential context. We are thus presented
with yet another type of relationship, that
between the work and its temporal context. In
our efforts to recreate that context, we can often
do no more than speculate, even when we are
able to establish whether the painting in ques¬
tion had a public or private function.
Types ofsign
There are several types of sign, and relation¬
ships exist both between similar signs and
between different signs. I apply the term "syn¬
tax" to the mode of relationship (juxtaposi¬
tion, sequence, scene) and "grammar" to the
specific form of each sign.
Three grammatically distinct types of sign
recur everywhere (drawing 1):
Pictographs (or mythographs). These are
recognizable representations of real or imagi¬
nary objects, animals or human beings.
Ideographs. These are repetitive signs or
combinations of signs, sometimes taking the
form of discs, arrows, branches, sticks, signs
in the shape of trees, crosses, mushrooms,
stars or snakes, "lips", zigzag patterns, "phal-
luses" or "vulvas". Their recurrent nature and
the particular relationship between them indi¬
cate that they are intended to convey conven¬
tional concepts (drawings 2 to 5).
Psychographs. These seem neither to repre¬
sent objects nor to be symbols. They appear to
have been created as a result of violent dis¬
charges of energy, perhaps in order to express
feelings about life or death and feelings of love
or hate, but could also be interpreted as
expressing portents or other very subtle per¬
ceptions. They occur more often in cave art
and on moveable objects than in open-air rock
art, in which the choice of rock and its actual
shape seem to fulfil the psychograph's role.
The syntax specific to the art of the early
hunters combines pictographs representing
various common types of animal, such as ele¬
phant and giraffe in the case of the United
Republic of Tanzania or bison and horse in
western Europe, with, in both these cases,
ideographs which are in many cases identical.
Various studies are at present being carried out
on the significance of these combinations of
pictographs and ideographs, but the general
opinion seems to be that they are based upon
the same logic as that which underlies the first
pictographic writing systems, and indeed may
Rock engravings on the
so-called "Newspaper
Rock", Canyonland,
Utah (U.S.A.)
IDEOGRAPHS
Vulva sign
v.
Series
of dots
Groups
of dots
and lines \
Combined
dot-and-lign sign
i ['ri,
THE UNESCO ^JURIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
9. Quadruped
8. Stylized profile of a quadruped accompanied by ideographs
careved on rock at La Ferrassie, Dordogne (France) by
Palaeolithic hunters (around 27,000-30,000 years ago). The
way of combining the graphemes is reminiscent of
representations found on the other side of the globe, e.g.
that shown on opposite page (drawings 6 and 7).
' //
/
1/
Human and animal figures.
Rock engravings at Toro
Muerto (Peru).
IDEOGRAPHS
Vulva sign
Series of dots
Group of dots
and lines
Pairing of dot
and line
Combined
dot-and-line sign
g
already constitute one such system which
would indicate that the logical process leading
to the invention of writing was already under
way 40,000 years ago (drawings 5 to 9).
A common conceptual basis
The physical dimensions of a picture are a very
inadequate means on which to base an under¬
standing of everything that it represents. In
Renaissance painting, for instance, although
the dove is shown as a particular species of bird ,
to grasp the full significance of a dove appearing,
say, in an Annunciation scene by Fra Angélico
it is not enough to say that there is a bird, in this
case a dove, in the corner of the picture. Only if
the viewer is familiar with the subject being
illustrated by the artist and with the mythical
and conceptual background of the artist's native
region does the full symbolism and specific sig¬
nificance of the dove, representing the Holy
Spirit in Christian mythology, emerge. Simi¬
larly, Picasso's dove of peace is far from being
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
just a dove: the artist has added to the picto-
graph an ideograph, the characteristically
Mediterranean olive branch, the symbolism of
which we can appreciate only because we have
been initiated into it.
Prehistoric pictographs, often accompa¬
nied by ideographs, should be perfectly "leg¬
ible" to all who are aware of their conceptual
content, but the handing on of the tradition
direct from generation to generation has been
interrupted, and it is precisely the job of the
archaeologist to assemble as much material and
as many observations as possible to try and
determine that content.
10. Stylized profile of a quadruped accompanied by
jdeographs carved around 8000 B.C. on rock in the valley of
the river Lena (Siberia). A vulva sign has been drawn near the
animal's penis. Note the combinations of lines and dots and
the presence of a zigzag motif. Though different in style, the
manner of combining the different elements is reminiscent of
that in the 2 works shown in drawings 6 to 9, illustrating how
certain archaic typologies survived down the ages.
12. Rock paintings at
Rio Pinturas,
Patagonia (Argentina).
Three distinct phases
can be recognized:
group of graphemes,
hand stencils and
prints, stencilled
outlines of animal
spoors, objects
(tools), zigzag motif;
series of animals
added later; series of
dots added later.
13.
11. Quadruped
pgñ(üjjtrl Handprint and
stencilled outlines of
hands
V*
IDEOGRAPHS
Vulva sign
Group
of dots
and lines
Rock engravings of concentric circles
associated with a warrior (right), at Bedolina,
Val Camonica, Italy. (Iron Age, 850-700 B.C.).
Animal spoor
outlines
Animal figures drawn
on top
VWW^AA1 Zigzag
Tool (?axe)
Series of dots added
later
THE UNESCO ÇpURIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
16. Rock paintings at Nabarlek, Arnhem Land, Australia (art of
archaic hunting peoples). Stencilled outlines of hands, animal
spoors and tools. Three of the hands represented are
mutilated, a detail that recurs in archaic paintings all over the
world. Two further ideographs have been added later, a disc
(female) and a "branch" (male).
At many rock art sites and in the earliest
forms of writing, ideographs are signs con¬
veying ideas, in a process of transmission from
writer to reader and from the painter to the real
or imaginary beings to whom the message is
addressed.
Research reveals a number of constants in
rock art, on whatever continent it may have
been produced, such as the use of similar tech¬
niques and colours, a narrow and repetitive
range of subjects, the same ways of combining
different elements, the same type of logic, the
recurrence of a range of symbolic ideographs
and, especially, the combination of pic¬
tographs, ideographs and psychographs
(drawings 10 to 13). This raises further ques¬
tions and suggests that the same structural
basis and the same conceptual dynamics may
underlie all creative art.
Five major categories ofart
In terms both of style and of content, it is
possible to distinguish five broad categories
Concentric circles
engraved in the rock at Oraibi,
Arizona, U.S.A. (Neolithic
period, 5000-3000 B.C.).
17.
Hand outlines
"Boomerang"
Ideographs added
later:
disc (female),
branch (male)
! 18. Drawing of an early Palaeolithic rock engraving,
probably made 27,000-30,000 years ago, at La
Ferrassie, Dordogne (France). The artist skilfully chose
to work on a rock with a natural shape suggesting the
; figure of a bison, adding engravings of horns and an
eye (left). Two vulva ideographs and several cup marks
were also added.
> >'- V
14. Rock paintings in
Queensland (Australia) ^^"
produced by very early hunting
peoples show stencilled
outlines of hands, in
combination with stencilled
animal spoors, zigzag motifs
and shapes of tools. The forms
are grouped according to a
syntax identical to that used in
the earliest phase of the
previous work (drawings 12 and
13) produced on the other side
of the world.
15.
Stencilled
outlines
of hands
Objects:
"clubs" and
an "axe"
Zigzag
of art, each with its own characteristics that
may be found everywhere.
Early hunters: art practised by hunters who
were ignorant of the bow and arrow, com¬
bining signs and figures but without com¬
posing scenes as such. Its syntax consists chiefly
of logical sequences and metaphorical associa¬
tions.
Early gatherers: art practised by peoples
whose economy was based mainly on the gath¬
ering of wild fruit, taking the form of simple
scenes of a metaphorical nature depicting a
surreal world. Much of this art seems to have
been produced in a state of hallucination.
Later hunters: art practised by hunters who
knew how to use the bow and arrow, con¬
sisting of anecdotal and descriptive scenes and
mainly depicting the hunt and events in the
community.
Pastoralists and herdsmen: art practised by
peoples whose main economic activity as
depicted therein was raising livestock, and
focussing on the depiction of domestic ani¬
mals and scenes of family life.
The complex economy: art practised by
peoples with a diversified economy, includ¬
ing farming, and consisting mainly of mytho¬
logical scenes and compositions made up of
signs and patterns.
This classification is necessarily only a
rough outline; there are transitional phases
and groups that display a mixture of charac¬
teristics, and there can also be marked differ¬
ences within a given category. In the present
state of research, however, and given the con¬
siderable amount of evidence available to us, an
approach based on style and subject-matter is
clearly the one to be followed in order to tran¬
scend the limitations of regional frontiers.
Applying a set of criteria based on the sub¬
jects and on the typology of representations, it
has been possible to pinpoint certain recurrent
and significant elements, and also to put for¬
ward the hypothesis that there exist certain
i (ouTHE UNESCO ÏOURIER APRIL 1998
ID
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
universal reflexes, linked to given ways of life,
that may have influenced not only people's
behaviour but also their thinking and their
associative processes (and hence their ideology)
and, consequently, their art forms. From the
very beginnings of art as we know it, some 40-
50,000 years ago, human beings have acted in
accordance with specific mental processes that
have led them to invent relationships, sym¬
bols, abstractions or sublimations which even
to this day constitute one of their specific uni¬
versal characteristics.
A universal language
Before the advent of Homo sapiens and of art,
the human race had been evolving for four
million years, so that, counting from the time
.when beings capable of laughing and crying
and of wondering about life and the future
first appeared on earth, art may be said to have
existed for only the last one per cent of human
history. In relation to what earlier hominids
20. Rock painting executed by early hunters at Pahi,
Masai Escarpment (United Republic of Tanzania). It
features the stylized outline of a quadruped, probably a
rhinoceros, with a "branch"-type ideograph pointed
towards the vulvo-anal region and a pattern of small dots
forming concentric circles.
19. Symbols of male and
female. The rock engravings
executed by the Neolithic
farmers of the Gobustan
(Azerbaijan, c. 5000 B.C.) use
the same graphemes as those
employed several millennia
before by early hunters. The
"branch" symbolizes the male
sex organ, while the two parallel
lines or "lips" on the woman's
hip stand for the female organ.
achieved, this represented not so much evolu¬
tion as a revolution. Various attempts have
been made to prove that apes and Homo erec-
tus were capable of producing art, supposi¬
tions that are, to my mind, totally unfounded.
The emergence of our identity as Homo sapi¬
ens presupposes the acquisition of a whole set
of specialized functions and particular attrib¬
utes, of being able to see, hear and feel with a
lucidity and in a manner quite specific to the
genus sapiens (drawings 12 to 17).
Some things about rock art from the distant
past are still relevant today. The visual language
of early hunters is a universal language since,
quite apart from systems of representation and
styles that are often very similar in different
parts of the world, it also displays combina¬
tions of figures and symbols that derive from
the same logic, suggesting a similar way of'
thinking and of self-expression (drawing 1 8). It
is not unreasonable to assume that the spoken
language was also based on universal principles
(drawings 19 to 22).
In intellectual terms, it would seem that
the capacity oíHomo sapiens to produce art is
innate. It would perhaps be better to replace
the somewhat pretentious term Homo sapi¬
ens (sometimes even cited as Homo sapiens
sapiens) by that oí Homo intellectualis.
21. Rock paintings by early gatherers at Kundusl (United Republic of
Tanzania). Ideographs have been used to depict the heads of two
anthropomorphic figures so as to make the figures identifiable. One
consists of a chevron pattern with a wavy double line emerging from the
top, probably representing a "branch"; the other is a group of dots forming
a kind of sphere. The resemblance to the previous illustration Is
unmistakable, although the latter dates from an earlier period.
'
22. Illustration of a Great Plains
Indian (United States) story
about the winter of 1876-1877:
"Chief Three Stars [General
Crook] took with him the young
braves of Chief Red Cloud to
fight with them against the
Cheyenne".
Mythical beast over two
metres long, at Helanshan
(China).
THE UNESCO lOURIER
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The prehistoric imagination
BY DENIS VIALOU
Prehistoric art combines unity of subject and
technique with an astonishing symbolic diversity
in different cultures and periods
Top, the black bull, a rock
painting in the Lascaux cave,
Dordogne (France).
Prehistoric art was an art closely bound
up with the lives of the hunters and
herdsmen who created it, an art of nature and,
first and foremost, an art of the open air. Scat¬
tered all over the world are millions of rock-
art sites bearing witness to the creative activi¬
ties of human beings over a period stretching
back at least ten millennia into prehistory. The
art in question consists of engravings and, to
a lesser extent (probably because they have not
been so well conserved), drawings and paint¬
ings, on surfaces that vary from region to
region in accordance with their geological char¬
acteristics single boulders or blockfields
(boulder-covered areas), flat rocks and latérite
surfaces, protruding parts of mountainsides or
the walls of rock shelters. In comparison with
this abundance of rock art in open-air sites,
there are relatively few examples in caves.
By contrast, the art of Palaeolithic Europe
and especially that of the Magdalenian period
(17,000-10,000 years ago) is mainly to be
found underground. About 250 caves deco¬
rated with paintings or engravings have so far
been discovered, mainly in France and Spain,
as against ten or so open-air sites, either
engraved rocks or shelters decorated with carv¬
ings. Unlike the art, open to light and life,
created by societies on the move, the parietal
(i.e.wall) art of the caves is hidden away in the
dark depths of the earth.
The symbolic conquest
of the dark
Signs of prehistoric human habitation dis¬
covered in cave mouths in the nineteenth cen¬
tury lent credence to the old myth of the cave
man. In actual fact, however, the great hunters
of the Palaeolithic never lived or stayed for
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
long in dark caves, and indeed it would be
impossible for humans to live there for long.
This only serves to emphasize the symbolic
significance of the parietal art which was
invented by Palaeolithic painters and engravers
and of which they became masters. These
artists must have enjoyed a high status in soci¬
ety by virtue of their skills and of the fact
that they gave expression to the lore and beliefs
of the communities to which they belonged.
The artists of the Gravettian cultu re (25,000-
20,000 years ago), named after the La Gravette
site in south-western France, were the first to
dare set foot in caves, some ten of which have
so far been reconnoitred, but they never ven¬
tured too far in and away from daylight. The
Pair-non-Pair cave (in France's Gironde départe¬
ment) with its dozens of engravings and the
Gargas cave (Haute-Garonne, France), which
contains both engravings and paintings (out¬
lines of hands), are splendid examples of the
work of these pioneers. The artists of the
Solutrean period (21,000-18,000 years ago),
named after the La Solutré site, also in France,
were scarcely more adventurous: fewer than
twenty caves decorated by them have been
found in France and Spain, but on the other
hand they were remarkably skilful at creating
low-relief carvings at sites in the open air.
The examples of Magdalenian parietal art
scattered about the chambers and galleries of
Head of a bull carved in
limestone, originating from
Angles-sur-Anglin, Vienne
(France).
Ivory head of the "Venus" of
Brassempouy, Landes (France).
This sophisticated
representation of the
human face dates from the
Gravettian period (27,000-
22,000 years ago).
caves, some of them vast (those at Rouffignac in
France's Dordogne region, for instance, stretch
for several kilometres), show that the Magdale-
nians had acquired and perfected the skills
required for working underground: they used
bowls hollowed out of stone, usually lime¬
stone, filled with animal fat and with wicks
made of vegetable material, as lamps that, as
recent experiments have shown, could burn for
several hours.
Cave art and cave architecture
With one or more entrances, chambers, gal¬
leries and one or more accessible extremities,
caves are an ordered and restricted space in
which to work, unlike open-air shelters, which
provide a more or less vertical, two-dimen¬
sional surface like a screen blocking out the
horizon, and even less like an open area of
more or less horizontal rock.
The placing of the rock paintings in rela¬
tion to the topographical features of the cave
is integral to their symbolism. In the Niaux
cave (Ariège, France), for example, certain types
of red-painted signs, some being patterns of
dots and others "claviform" or club-shaped,
appear in combination and are spaced out along
the corridor that leads into and runs through
the cave. Other types of geometrical or abstract
drawings, angular signs for example, occur
almost exclusively in a large apsidal hall known
18
THE UNESCO G>URI
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
as the Salon noir, where they are to be found
in combination with drawings of bison and
other animals, also drawn in black.
In a Palaeolithic cave, the thematic structure
of the wall paintings (i.e. the types of signs and
species of animals) and their symbolic struc¬
ture (the spatial relationship between themes)
is thus conditioned by the natural architecture
of the site, the spaces and volumes of which
proceed in sequence from the mouth to the
rear of the cave and back again towards the
mouth and thus towards normal life outside.
The walls enfold the visitor and create an
infinite variety of volumes, some easier of
access or passage than others, some as vast and
impressive as cathedrals and others no better
than oppressively narrow crawl spaces. These
natural properties of the site are also incor¬
porated into the layout of the wall paintings
and contribute to their symbolic significance.
A visitor standing in the middle of the
Rotunda of the Lascaux cave in the Dordogne
is struck by the frieze of huge bulls running
round the chamber on the background of a
band of spotless white rock that stands out
between the blackish base of the walls and the
deeply furrowed, lumpy ceiling.
Open-air sites obviously do not have the
infinite variety of shapes and volumes that
caves and their walls, ceilings and floors pos¬
sess. A rock painting or engraving in a shelter
can usually be taken in at a glance or from a sin¬
gle vantage point. In a cave, on the other hand,
the viewer has to walk through the symbolic
space created by the representations in order to
see and "read" them in their entirety; whether
juxtaposed in groups or isolated and dispersed,
they only come to life as the viewer, and
accordingly the light source, moves along.
Immobilized in the darkness and scattered
about on the surface of the complex and infi¬
nitely varied naturally occurring forms, they
need time in order to be viewed in succession
and then perceived in combination as parts of
a single whole the cave itself.
The ivory "Venus" of Lespugue
(France), a masterpiece of
prehistoric carving (about
22,000 years old).
© Hatala/Musée de l'Homme. Pans
Bear engraved on a pebble,
France, Upper Palaeolithic
(35,000-10,000 years ago).
Subjected to these double limitations of
§ space and time and to the flickering illumina-
I tion of an artificial light source, Palaeolithic
| cave paintings live on only in the memory of
I those who are familiar with them or in the
I immediate experience of those who first come
I upon them. They are outside and apart from
I normal life, belonging entirely and definitively
to the realm of the imagination.
Apart from this physically and symboli¬
cally isolated parietal art, Palaeolithic art exists in
the form of many artefacts: paintings and
engravings done on flat pieces of stone or bone
or on the handles of weapons and tools, count¬
less personal ornaments such as beads, pendants
and bracelets, and statuettes carved in stone,
19
'RIL 1908THE UNESCO (pURI
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
bone or ivory. All these objects, thousands of
which have been found in many of the occupa¬
tion sites in Europe that were inhabited in Palae¬
olithic times, from the early Aurignacian period
around 35,000 years ago to the concurrent end
of the Ice Ages and of the Magdalenian civiliza¬
tion, represent a vast iconography of symbols,
fully integrated into everyday life. Easily trans¬
portable, they contributed to the development
of exchanges and contacts, and to the propaga¬
tion of ideas and myths.
Artistic unity . . .
The famous Gravettian "Venuses" some hun¬
dred or so statuettes found at occupation
sites in south-western France, at Brassempouy
(Landes) and Lespugue (Haute-Garonne) for
* example, and as far away as the plains of Rus¬
sia, at Kostienki or Avdeyevo, attest to a certain
degree of unity of conception and styles that
were the same or similar from end to end of
Europe for four to five millennia.
In all forms of rock art, in Brazil or Aus¬
tralia, central India, the south-western United
States, the Middle East, southern Africa or
the Sahara, the paintings or engravings com¬
bine three major categories of graphic repre¬
sentation: geometrical figures or abstract signs
(i.e. signs with no explicit figurative reference),
animals, and human figures.
Even when sketchily executed or stylized,
This horse has been painted on
a rock face naturally
suggesting the shape of the
animal in profile and is
surrounded by large blobs of
paint and stencilled outlines of
hands. Pech-Merle cave, Lot
(France), Aurignacian period
(35,000-25,000 years ago).
the representation of animals is usually natu¬
ralistic and is sometimes so accurate that the
species represented can be identified, for exam¬
ple the Magdalenian artists' salmon, the Bush¬
men's Cape eland (Taurotragus oryx), the
Palaeoindians' armadillo, or the giraffes and
ostriches of the Neolithic artists of the Sahara.
Conversely, the representations of the human
figure are treated with a freedom that is some¬
times pushed to such extremes as to make
them almost indecipherable, as in the case of
the painted stick figures in certain rock shelters
in Brazil, which have little additions at either
end that could be the head and the limbs. Pro¬
files and silhouettes are often given zoomor-
phic features in many cultures, and it is just as
common, in rock art of all periods, for the
human figure (as regards the head, hands and
sexual organs, and more rarely the feet) to be
segmented.
Within the limitless range of painted and
engraved signs to be found everywhere in the
world (dots, circles, rectangles, etc.), there are
innumerable points of convergence, which is
not to say that the dots painted by a Palae¬
olithic artist necessarily carried the same mean¬
ing as those done by Palaeoindians.
Another constant is the absence of any
representations of plants, fruits, flowers or
landscapes.
A further point to be stressed is the uni¬
formity of prehistoric artistic techniques, local
THE UNESCO Ç'LIRIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
variations being of relatively minor impor¬
tance. Drawings and paintings were done using
mineral pigments, mainly ochres and man¬
ganese oxides, or charcoal. Incised engravings
and pecked outlines were always made with
hammer or blade tools fashioned from stone
harder than that of the surface being worked,
which was usually sandstone or limestone.
This identity of subjects and techniques
in prehistoric art, which reflects the relative
uniformity of entirely nature-oriented pre¬
historic ways of life and economies, should
not, however, disguise the fact of its remark¬
able diversity of symbolism.
. . . and diversity ofsymbolism
The choice of subjects and their arrangement
in space in fact create a specific symbolism that
varies from one culture and one era to another.
Neighbouring Magdalenian caves in France
(Font-de-Gaume, Combarelles, Bernifal and
Rouffignac, all in the Dordogne), for instance,
feature a common "tectiform" or roof-shaped
design not found in other Magdalenian caves,
although their animal subject-matter is very
different. Comparative analysis of rock shel¬
ters in the Tassili-N'Ajjer, in the Algerian
Sahara, and in the Drakensberg mountains of
South Africa reveals analogous differences,
and this phenomenon is repeated from site to
site, even when there are hundreds of shelters
on the same site, as at Bhimbetka in central
India.
Within this widespread semantic diversity,
it is possible to distinguish two main trends,
one towards pure symbolism and the other
narrative in character or tending towards a cer¬
tain degree of realism. Generally speaking,
Palaeolithic parietal art (and artefacts) represent
symbolic arrangements in which there is no
discernible link between the juxtaposed and/or
superimposed subjects, figurative or non-fig¬
urative. Horses, bison, mammoths, dots, rec¬
tangles, club shapes and human figures appear
side by side, for no apparent reason other than
the artists' own coded languages.
These main similarities and differences illus¬
trate both the unity and the diversity of the
prehistoric arts practised by Homo sapiens sapi¬
ens in various parts of the world, thirty or
forty millennia ago in the case of the oldest
examples, reflecting the basic links that exist
between cultures, economies and their forms of
graphic expression. The ability to express, to
symbolize, an imaginary universe through the
use of highly diverse systems of symbolic con¬
ventions and norms reflects the unique cultural
characteristics of human communities and the
specificity of their languages and customs, their
beliefs, their myths and their gods.
Figure of a horse
(on right) at Bhimbetka,
Madhya Pradesh (India),
where there are over 500 small
caves and rock shelters
decorated with paintings
(2000 B.C.).
> G>uTHE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Devil's Marbles, near Alice Springs (Northern Territory), regarded as a sacred site by Australian aborigines. esiamsiasFauiré/Ask images. pans
'For Australian Aborigines,
rock painting is a title to their land'
Tim Fox talks to three Australian Aborigines invited to a Unesco Forum on rock art
rl The Aborigines of Australia have always
J been hunter-gatherers, living in harmony
with their surroundings. They believe that
through ritual they help sustain the cycles of
the natural world and that they are as much a
part of nature as the wind, the rain and the soil.
Understanding nature's secrets is a lifetime
process, completely revealed only to tribal or
clan elders.
Art for the Aborigines is the expression of
present-day life, that is, a life that has been con¬
sidered in the present tense since the beginning
of time. Theirs is both the oldest and the youngest
continuous civilization in the world, the oldest
as attested to by the dating process called ther¬
moluminescence; and the youngest because the
practices depicted by rock paintings are still a
part of Aboriginal culture to this very day.
According to the Aborigines, what is etched
in or painted onto stone is the expression of
the world's immutable laws, which emerged
from the Dream Time, the gelatinous, amor¬
phous time before the world emerged in the
form we know today. These laws were placed
there by ancestors and were until recently only
for the eyes and understanding of a few initi¬
ates, the elders who have demonstrated their
worthiness to know.
In June 1997 three elders and a young dis¬
ciple of the Ngarinyin community left their
native Kimberley Plateau in Australia's remote
northwest and travelled to Europe to exhibit
photographs of their sacred rock drawings and
explain what the drawings meant. By this act,
which not so many years ago would have been
punishable by death, they sought to protect
their access to their sacred sites against pres¬
sure from cattle-grazing, mining companies,
tourists and souvenir hunters.
Without immediate contact with their lands,
the Ngarinyin people cease to exist, for they
are an integral part of the land, and the land Is
an integral partofthem. If they do not actively
maintain the land, the Aborigines believe it will
cease to sustain life just as they will cease to
exist if they are removed from it. This is why
they had asked a painter/film-maker friend,
Jeff Döring, to record on film some of their rock
drawings so that the outside world could learn
of their existence and understand the ways in
which they bind Aborigines to their land.
The role of delegation leader seemed to fall
to David Mowaljarlai, who has perhaps had the
most extensive contact with Westerners through
his many encounters with ethnologists and
anthropologists and the many conferences on
Aborigines he has attended in Australia. Paddy
Wamma is a walking encyclopaedia of the plants
found on the Kimberley Plateau and their medi¬
cinal, practical and nutritional applications. Paddy
THE UNESCO ^)URIE
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Neowarra is president of the Ngarinyin Aboriginal
Corporation and People (N.A.C.) and a firm
believer that traditional law must rule in all
aspects of social life and predominate in decid¬
ing land rights. Even when asked direct ques¬
tions, the youngest of the four, Jason Ninowatt,
deferred to the older men, who answered for
him protectively. The group of four was accom¬
panied by Jeff Döring and anthropologist Tony
Redmond, who often clarified or provided back¬
ground to points made by the Aborigines.
Why this reversal of the age-old practice
of keeping the meaning of the rock
drawings a secret?
David Mowaljarlai: Our paintings are our title
to the land. If we lose our title, the paintings
are empty. It's as simple as that. Besides we
are not revealing all the secrets. Not the most
essential ones. We are grateful to UNESCO for
inviting us to tell our story. We don't normally
travel so far from our land. We are under heavy
pressure from pastoralists, mining companies
and tour operators, who are trying to block us
from our land. They are trying to extinguish our
Native Title.
What Is Native Title?
Tony Redmond: it's a concept initiated by Aus¬
tralia's Northern Territory when it passed the
Aboriginal Land Rights Act in 1976. The Act
gave Aboriginal people inalienable freehold
title to all Aboriginal reserves and a mecha¬
nism by which they could claim vacant Crown
Land. Claimants have to be able to demonstrate
traditional ownership of the land, and claims
are heard by an Aboriginal Land Commissioner.
Theoretically, Aboriginal landowners are able to
limit incursion onto their land for mineral explo¬
ration or commercial development. But it is
proving very hard to enforce.
D.M.: And some peoplemining companies,
pastoralists and the likeare still trying to
deny us our rights by saying we can't prove that
we are the traditional owners of the land. But
we can. There are the rock drawings.
What do the rock drawings prove?
Jeff Döring: Rock art is a visual document. It is
the "written" law in Aboriginal terms. The infor¬
mation in the drawings and the stone arrange¬
ment are totally explicit. White man's law
changes from year to year, but these drawings
never change. The illustration of one man pass¬
ing an object to another, for example, is never
modified, and it has been there, as far as the
Aborigines are concerned, forever. And for the
Aborigines it has the force of law.
Well what, for example, does the
drawing of a man passing an object to
another man mean?
D.M.: Wunan, the act of sharing.
P. W.: The wunan law works for everybody.
Everything has always been shared by every¬
body. No one lives outside the chain. Every¬
one me, everyoneIs inside wunan. Ani¬
mals, things, birds, everything, are all part of
the wunan law.
It all started at the stone wunan table. It's
the stone table that guides us. All our people
Dating of various examples of rock art in
Australia confirms that some of them are over
20,000 years old. Below, a decorated cave at Keep
River, near Kununura, Northern Territory. Right,
detail of drawings on the cave roof.
gathered here to set rules and make laws. All
the clans came from the four corners of the
region to establish the wunan law. They talked
and agreed how the land should be shared out
and where the sacred places should be. All the
men of the wunan law formed a line. No one
was left out. We divided up the land. No one
was left out; no one forgotten.
They made a big cake with the fruit of the
gulangi. "We have to create a rule and establish
a law," they said. "It is our life, this tree before
us." They ate the cake piece by piece. There
was enough for everyone. But the emu grew
impatient for his share. He waited on the crest
of the hill until he felt he'd waited long enough.
Then he came down to get a piece. "No," they
said, "you come from the rising sun. You've got
a long time to wait yet for your share." So he
shouted and stole the cake. They tried to talk
him out of taking the cake, but he would not be
swayed and ran away.
The emu ran faster than any other animal.
The ground shook as he ran. All the birds tried
to catch him, but he was too fast. So they went
to the wowara, pigeons with bronze-coloured
wings. "You are fast runners," they said. "You
are the only ones who can catch the emu." Just
then the wowara were honing the tips of their
spears. They agreed and set out after the emu.
They followed his tracks and finally caught up
with him. He was punished because he had
transgressed the law, as are all those today
who follow in his footsteps. If you look up at
the Milky Way you can see him looking back
over his shoulder at the spear sticking in his
back which he can never pull out because his
arm is too short.
-
i i m . -»"
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1996
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The shaman's journey
BYJEANCLOTTES
Shamanism may provide a clue to the meaning of rock art
I With very few exceptions (in some parts
of Australia, for example) rock art all
over the world is a fossil art. Its creators dis¬
appeared long ago, and with them went the
myths and beliefs depicted in their rock paint¬
ings and engravings. Research can thus only
be based on the art of the last two or three
centuries when various peoples in the Amer¬
icas, Africa and Australia still regularly painted
on the walls of rock shelters. This approach is
not without dangers, however. Neither the
reported evidence nor its interpretation is
always reliable. Furthermore, there is no guar¬
antee that a group of nineteenth-century Ab o-
rigines living in a particular area shared the
V^a
same beliefs as their ancestors who produced
rock art in the same region several thousand
years earlier. Comparative ethnology extrap¬
olating practices noted in one place and context
to other world regions should be practised
with extreme caution, in a very general way,
taking into consideration some universal fea¬
tures of human thinking and without hoping
to come up with complete, detailed explana¬
tions that can be applied everywhere.
The term shamanism, first used to describe
Siberian populations, has come to include
beliefs and practices with a common basis
found, even today, among many peoples in the
world. Some of the many characteristics of
shamanistic systems are fundamental and wide¬
spread.1 Here we shall examine three of them.
Other worlds
The first is a belief in a layered universe with
several superposed or parallel worlds. Accord¬
ing to this belief, the events in our world, the
world we live in, are directly conditioned by
the influence of powers living in one or
another of the other worlds. The second fea¬
ture is the belief that certain individuals can in
certain circumstances directly make contact
with the(se) other world(s) and in this way
influence events in our world. They usually
do this for practical reasons to heal the sick
or restore a lost harmony, to create good con¬
ditions for hunting, to bring rain to dry areas,
or, more rarely, for evil purposes. The third
characteristic is that contact with the other
world is made directly, in one direction or
another, through a visit by auxiliary spirits,
often in animal form, which come to the
Left, shaman figure holding a
shaman or towards which he goes. This will snake, and various signs.
24
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The walls of this shelter at
Pleito Creek, California
often be an occasion for identification between (U-S-A'» were comed with
vividly coloured paintings of
the shaman and the spirit, or a belief in a total geometric figures, probably
i r rj from trance visions,
or partial transformation ot the man into an
animal. If the shaman's auxiliary spirit is a griz¬
zly bear, identification between the human
and the grizzly is total. A shaman can also send
his soul into the other world to meet spirits
and obtain their protection and help by going
into a trance, sometimes during collective cer¬
emonies, sometimes alone.
Ethnologists consider that shamanism is
often found in egalitarian societies, usually of
hunter-gatherers, although hunter-gatherer
societies are not all shamanistic. Nor are these
the only societies where shamanistic practices
are found.
The fact that shamanism is found the world
over is not of course due to direct or indirect
contact between distant populations. The ulti¬
mate reason may be, at least partially, rooted in
the inevitable need to rationalize and use the
altered states of consciousness that are part of the
human nervous system and appear in one form
or another in every society. Certain people have
been subject to hallucinations and visions, every¬
where and at all times, for reasons as varied as the
phenomena themselves. These experiences may be
due to drugs or to certain pathological states,
fasting, isolation, darkness, suffering, intense
concentration, or throbbing, recurrent sounds.
Rationalist cultures like ours disapprove of these
phenomena and consider that psychiatrists (for
spontaneous hallucinations) or the police (for
hallucinogenic drugs) should deal with them.
In others visionaries are regarded as being in con¬
tact with otherworldly powers and therefore
become spiritual leaders, prophets or shamans.
This does not mean that they will neces¬
sarily record their visions on rocks. But in
some cases they have done so, and what is
more the ethnographic material collected by
researchers in recent decades reveals many sim-
> r^"1THE UNESCO lOURIER AfRIL 1908
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
ilarities in the ways that visionaries think and
act. These convergences are due to the fact that
rock art is the embodiment of similar funda¬
mental beliefs or conceptual frameworks. These
have to do with the sites where the art was
made, the themes depicted, and the reasons
for this form of art.
Decorated rock shelters are often regarded as
two-way "doors" between the real world and
the other world. Spirits can emerge from them
and it is possible to pass through them into
the world beyond and meet spirits. Such places
are also propitious for experiencing visions.
Anyone wanting to be visited by a helpful
Human figures, probably
shamans. Little Petroglyph
Canyon, California (United
States).
> G>uTHE UNESCO ÍOURIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
F
/ \ y
Three line drawings: Above
left, grizzly bear (Tule River
Reservation, California,
U.S.A.). The bear's facial
secretions recall the nose¬
bleeds sometimes suffered by
shamans during the trance
state (after D. Whitley).
Above, hallucinatory figure
with bow and arrows
(Drakensberg Mountains,
Natal, South Africa; after D.
Lewis-Williams). Above right,
rain-maker shamans capturing
a rain animal (South Lesotho,
recorded by J. M. Orpen in
1874; after D. Lewis-Williams).
spirit or enter the world of the spirits by going
into a trance will go in solitude, which favours
these encounters, to the foot of decorated walls.
When we enter this other world, whether it is
below or parallel to our own, we do so through
a tunnel protected by animal guardians. In Cal¬
ifornia, these were bears or rattlesnakes.
The images themselves were charged with
power they were painted one over the other
on the same walls and each new work drew
from and added to the accumulated power of
those beneath. Certain dominant themes recur,
differing from region to region. In the Drak¬
ensberg Mountains, South Africa, elands pre¬
dominate. In the Coso mountains of central
California, big-horned sheep are the animals
most commonly depicted since they were asso¬
ciated with rain and rain was vital in this desert
area. These distinctive local features illustrate
the choices and beliefs of the creators and users
of this art. Part-human part-animal figures
also appear. These are creatures seen during the
shamanistic journey or as a result of the
shaman's transformation.
The purpose of rock art was often to depict
visions after they had been experienced. David
Whitley, who has studied rock art in the
southwest of the United States,2 considers
that if the Nevada and California visionaries
had not drawn their visions, they would have
"lost" them and died as a result. On other
occasions, the shaman's supernatural journey
was depicted metaphorically. Death, for exam¬
ple, was a metaphor for a trance. In California's
Coso mountains, "killing a big-horned
sheep", the rain animal, meant that the shaman
was going to the other world to bring back
rain. The metaphor of death for a trance and
for sexual relations ("little death") was com¬
mon. Other metaphors were less common and
remind us of the impossibility of grasping
the specific meaning and nuances of art with¬
out direct help.
Rock art could also depict something other
than the visions of a trance and still be linked
to a shamanistic vision of the world. David
Whitely reports, for example, that until the
end of the last century female puberty rites
included several days of isolation, instruction
in maternity taboos, fasting and various cer¬
emonies, and eating native tobacco to provoke
hallucinations during which the girls met an
animal spirit, usually a rattlesnake. Afterwards,
they ran to a painted shelter called the Shaman's
House, and drew their hands on its walls, pos¬
itively or negatively, with red paint (a colour
associated with young girls) to show that they
had "touched" the supernatural.
Bridging two worlds
David Lewis-Williams, a South African
researcher who has spent years studying the
paintings and beliefs of the San Bushmen of
his country, is behind much current research
on shamanism and rock art.3 Before him, sev¬
eral authors had explored this field but with¬
out great success, perhaps due to a lack of a
rTHE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1008
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
sufficiently rigorous approach. Following his
work, undeniable links with shamanism have
been established between rock art images pro¬
duced by cultures in different parts of the
world, especially throughout southern Africa
and in North and South America.4 It is even
likely that much European palaeolithic art, or
"cave art" originates in shamanistic practices.
This hypothesis, which is not a complete
or exclusive explanation but an explanatory
framework, is based on several observations.
For more than 20,000 years, deep caves were
used not as dwellings but for drawings. Those
who went into them went into their deepest
recesses. All over the world the underground
world has always been regarded an other-
A shaman with antelope head
and feet touching the
hindquarters of a dying eland
in this metaphorical
representation of a trance
(Drakensberg Mountains,
Natal, South Africa).
world, the realm of spirits and of the dead.
Penetrating into the depths of these caves
therefore was certainly nota simple matter of
exploration. Palaeolithic people knew that they
were in the realm of spirits, and expected to
meet spirits in these caves. The flickering light
of their torches brought the walls to life and
they saw animal shapes on them. We know
this because they very often used the more or
less suggestive natural relief of the walls, which
acted as a kind of permeable veil between this
world and the other-world. Many figures were
also painted or engraved where there were fis¬
sures, gaps or openings in the walls, as if ani¬
mals entered or left the cave at these points.
In addition, many speleologists describe the
hallucinatory effect of caves, where cold,
humidity, darkness and the absence of all sen¬
sory references encourage visions. Caves could
therefore play a dual role: help produce altered
states of consciousness, i.e. visions, and com¬
municate with spirits through the cave wall.5
It thus seems extremely likely that much
palaeolithic art was created in a shamanistic
framework.6 This does not mean, of course,
that all the images of this art are the result of
visions or that they all serve the same purpose.
Human imagination and creativity are limitless
and traditional thinking is never simple. The
same holds true for the world's open-air art.
Some of it, in America, Africa, and perhaps else¬
where, certainly originates in shamanistic prac¬
tices. We cannot, however, impose this model on
all prehistoric rock art irrespective of its ethno¬
logical context. It would only be justified to do
so after making a thorough, critical analysis of
all the elements of the rock art concerned.
1. Michel Pcrrin, Le cbamanisme, Paris, Presses
Universitaires de France ("Que sais-je?" series) 1995.
2. David Whitley, A Guide to Rock Art Sites. Southern
California and Southern Nevada. Missoula, Mountain
Press Publishing Co., 1996.
3. David Lewis-Williams and T. Dowson, "The Signs of
all Times. Entoptic Phenomena in Upper Paleolithic
Art," Current Anthropology, 29, 2, pp. 201-245.
4. S.-A. Turpin (editor), Shamanism and Rock Art in
North America, San Antonio, Rock Art Foundation,
Inc., Special Publication 1, 1994.
5. Jean Clottes and David Lewis-Williams, Les
chamanes de la préhistoire. Transe et magie dans les
grottes ornées, Paris, Le Seuil publishers, 1996.
6. Jean Clottes and David Lewis-Williams, "Les
chamanes des cavernes," A rchéologia, no. 336, 1997,
pp. 30-41.
» THE UNESCO ^>URIER APRIL 1908
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
What can be done to stop the
deterioration of rock art?
An endangered art
BY FRANÇOIS SOLEILHAVOUP
and on the collective level of institutions, and
a new approach to heritage education.
Attitudes to rock art were for many years
dominated by leading scientists schooled in
the great traditions of history and classical
archaeology, and attention was accordingly
focused more upon questions of interpreta¬
tion than on the problems of conservation.
Scholars such as these thought the most
important thing was to locate, record and
make explanatory comments on the works in
question, and were less concerned about their
actual survival. This is no longer the case.
Everywhere in the world, rock art is suffering
increasing deterioration. As we now know,
anything done to a rock surface upsets the
delicate dynamic balance between the rock and
the atmosphere, which in normal circum¬
stances is regulated over time by environmen¬
tal factors. The micro-organisms present in
and on the rock can then proliferate and either
damage the surface by producing mineral sub¬
stances (biomineralization) or destroy it.
An example of recent
vandalism: this superb
shamanic figure at Black
Dragon Canyon, Utah (United
States), was "enhanced" with
chalk by tourists so that they
could take better photographs.
t| Rock art, whether the kind found deep
inside caves or out in the open, consti¬
tutes a vital feature of the history of humanity.
Fragile and thus exceptionally precious, its sur¬
vival bears witness to the ancient human urge to
leave footsteps in the sands of time. That urge,
which we still feel, is now linked with a duty,
the duty of ensuring that such art is passed on
to future generations. If this duty of conser¬
vation is to be effectively performed, there
must be a code of ethics applicable to research,
both on the individual level of the researcher
Open-air archives
Exposed to the air, any rock surface behaves as
a device for recording environmental varia¬
tions. With current laboratory techniques, it
is possible to study the natural evolution of
the climate and even to date the main stages
of that evolution, but a thoughtless action,
whether by a researcher or by a tourist, can
destroy irreplaceable sources of information.
Although it is sometimes essential to take
microsamples, an ethical approach demands,
both of the researcher and of any decent citi¬
zen, that they show proper respect for the
work itself and for the natural setting of which
it forms part.
As more and more of rock art's rich sources
of information are discovered and recorded, a
better understanding of the complex causes of
damage or even destruction is emerging. In
response to the increasingly rapid urbanization
and industrialization that are profoundly mod¬
ifying many natural landscapes, urgent on-site
rescue and recording operations are being carried
out, but the impact of the methods employed
is not always properly assessed. The fact is that
operations such as the wetting of prehistoric
paintings at sites in an arid environment, the
THE UNESCO G>URIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
highlighting of engravings with chalk or even
paint, the application of whitewash and the
taking of casts with the aid of chemicals all
bring about physical, chemical and microbio¬
logical changes in the paintings themselves and
in the rock on which they have been executed.
Pleading recently in favour of conservation,
the Australian specialist Robert G. Bednarik
even urged that books on rock art which
demonstrated direct-contact methods of record¬
ing should be withheld from publication.
It was with such ideas of conservation in
mind that the first International Seminar on
the Conservation of Paintings in the Open
Air held in Algiers and at the Tassili N'Ajjer,
one of the prime World Heritage sites was
convened by UNESCO in 1978. Many such
meetings have since been held, on all five con¬
tinents.
The pros and cons ofecotourism
Rock art is part of the common heritage and
should not be the jealously guarded preserve
of a few specialists, but public interest in and
admiration for it raises major problems. This
is true both of the wealthy countries, where
increased leisure time and cultural tourism
help to step up the pressure on the environ¬
ment, and of the poor countries, where the
development of ecotourism has to serve eco¬
nomic purposes such as bringing in foreign
currency and providing employment, and
where natural sites are treated as consumer
products.
The Manila Declaration on World Tourism
indicates that modern tourism corresponds to
a basic human right to rest and holidays, but it
also points out that "in the practice of tourism,
Three views of the 12,000-year-
old rock paintings at Pedra
Furada, Serra da Capivara,
Piauí State (Brazil). Above, a
rock face. Left, zoomorphic
figures and signs. Right, small
human figures surrounding
animals.
C reation of replicas of the
decorated caves of Lascaux
and Niaux (France) near to the
original sites, This protective
measure was undertaken after
serious damage had been
caused by the presence of large
numbers of tourists in the
caves, which are now closed to
the public. Below left, a
sculptor and a painter
faithfully recreate the walls
and paintings of Lascaux II
from extremely precise
photogrammetric records.
Below and below right, an
engraver and a painter at work
at Niaux II.
spiritual elements must take precedence over
technical and material elements", those spiri¬
tual elements being "the total fulfilment of the
human being, a constantly increasing contri¬
bution to education, equality of destiny of
nations, the liberation of man in a spirit of
respect for his identity and dignity, [and] the
affirmation of the originality of cultures and
respect for the moral heritage of peoples."
One may well wonder whether the princi¬
ples enshrined in that Declaration are not being
violated by the upsurge in organized tourism
over the last twenty years, and whether the
tour operators who offer visits to open-air
rock-art sites anywhere in the world under
the label of ecotourism and "green" or cul¬
tural tourism are not quite simply hijacking
nature by putting a monetary value on it.
To take the case of national parks, the World
Conservation Union (IUCN) defined them in
1969 as areas of land and/or sea especially ded¬
icated to the protection and maintenance of
biological diversity, and of natural and associ¬
ated cultural resources, and managed through
legal and other effective means. At present, only
9 per cent of the dry land surface of the globe
enjoys this status. In such places, priority
should be given to the protection and conser¬
vation of the natural and cultural heritage, but,
in response to understandable public curios¬
ity but also for less honourable reasons wherein
rivalry and conflicts of authority and interests
are intermingled, natural parks and reserves are
being visited by more and more people every
year. Such mass tourism at the world's main
heritage sites is causing their inexorable physi¬
cal deterioration and a diminution of their
essential spiritual dimension.
) ^>URIITHI UNESCO lO IER APRIL 191B
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
*s-V*
ïèEftV**; i?
t?0z*3Z
These are difficult contradictions to resolve.
While it is somewhat hypocritical to try and
protect sites by keeping strict control over
visitors' right to roam (so much more is some¬
times declared out of bounds than is accessi¬
ble that a good video cassette might seem a
better bet than an actual visit), what is one to
make of the suspect notion of an "integral
reserve", which, by trying to create little
islands of unspoilt nature, ends up establish¬
ing de jure two categories of nature, one where
anything goes and another where everything is
banned?
Freedom and responsibility
The present tendency to confuse culture with
consumption in "leisure" activities poses a
growing threat to the heritage. Anything that
is consumed is, by definition, destroyed or
at the very least loses much of its value; and
"consumption" of the heritage in general and
of rock art in particular is on the increase. As
a result of too much machine-made pollu¬
tion, the general public and some of the polit¬
ical decision-makers have developed a need for
nature and a concern for the environment.
Many states have adopted a responsible atti¬
tude to their heritage, but much needs to be
done to rally individuals and the public at
large to this cause and to raise their awareness.
This is why education is so important.
From a very early age, children must learn
from their parents, from their immediate
Some of the petroglyphs at the
site of Ausevik (Norway) have
been repainted to increase
their effect and supposedly to
protect them, although this
practice actually causes the
paintings to age more quickly.
Other works have been left as
they were.
These Bronze Age engravings
at Tomskaya Pisanitsa in
southern Siberia (Russia) have
been disfigured by vandals
who carved over them a date
with a double ring around it.
social environment and from elementary
school the basic attitudes and reflexes that
make up life skills, as well as acquiring knowl¬
edge and learning self-respect and respect for
others. It is up to schools to instil in them
from a very early age the rudiments of the eth¬
ical code which they, as future citizens and
members of the public and as potential inter¬
ested amateurs or specialists, will adopt
towards the natural and cultural heritage, so
that a responsible form of freedom as regards
that dual heritage may prevail.
THE UNESCO ^>URIER APRIL 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
An open-air museum in the Sahara
BY AXEL AND ANNE-MICHELLE VAN ALBADA
Hunter-gatherers have left a vivid collection of
petroglyphs on the Libyan plateau of Messak
A man with the head of a
jackal or hunting dog returns
from a rhinoceros hunt on the
back of an elephant. Drawing
of rock art figures at Wadi
Imrawen in the Messak massif.
"The rock art of the Sahara is one of
humanity's most astonishing books of
hours. There may be different, older ones, but
there are few that are so beautiful or so fresh.
It is charming as well as surprising, and it
makes us think deeply about the enthralling
message it has brought down tous."
Henri-Jean Hugot [Le Sahara avant le désert)
The Messak plateau in the central Sahara
(Libyan Arab Jamahiriya) has been inhabited
since the Old Stone Age. But it was probably
only during a wet phase of the New Stone
Age that groups of hunters and herdsmen dec¬
orated the walls of its oases with beautiful
engravings. Unlike the Djebel Akakus and Tas-
sili N'Ajjer regions elsewhere in the Sahara,
which are rich in rock art, there are hardly any
paintings on the Messak plateau and the few
exceptions to this rule clearly originate from
outside the area.
The petroglyphs found on the plateau can
be dated by reference to differences in the nature
and colour of the patinas that have formed on
the rock surface. The most recent date from
what is known as the camel era, which began
some 2,000 years ago. Others executed nearby
show horses, two-wheeled carts and warriors
armed with spears and round shields, and may
have been executed some time around 1500 B.C.
An even older patina coats engravings of many
small spotted Bovidae (animals of the ox fam¬
ily) that are somewhat crudely and flatly por¬
trayed. Many ostriches and giraffes are also
depicted in these engravings, suggesting that
they were made by herders contemporary with
the onset of a very dry period in the region
towards 2000-3000 B.C.
These engravings are very different, partic¬
ularly in terms of style, from the older engrav¬
ings which constitute high-quality naturalis¬
tic art. They incorporate abstract signs and
living creatures, and were doubtless intended
to convey sophisticated ideas.
A hunter-gatherer society
It is possible to talk in terms of an area specific
to a "Messak culture."
The engravings are striking first of all by
virtue of the number and originality of the
scenes, their rich contents, and by the tech¬
niques used to make them. Some are bas-reliefs
where foreground and background are realis¬
tically depicted by fine hammering and partial
polishing. A special "double line" technique
emphasizes the impression of depth in some
areas such as paws and muzzles.
Wild and domesticated animals are the prin¬
cipal theme. The impression of numbers or a
herd is often created by a fan-shaped series of
heads poised at different angles and gradually
shading off into the background from a whole
animal portrayed in detail in the foreground.
The overall effect is striking and bespeaks a
high degree of compositional talent. Different
kinds of horns, often represented in one small
herd, are an indication of diversity. At least
three engravings show milking scenes. Milk
was probably stored in skins or gourds slung
between forked branches. Cattle were used as
32
© Van Albada, Arzens, France
) G>uiTHE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Herd of giraffe in movement on
a promontory of the rich rock-
a rt site at Wadi Issanghaten.
'.r^ u
'H
Hl
ftti
s
¿?*-#
S
"«Si
X
a
g
MF
Ht K -
-*»>
T ¿^fll lu
"*!
a*
Í
pack animals and occasionally as mounts.
Highly ornate saddles and decorated horns
suggest ritual celebrations.
Representations of human beings are not
infrequent but seem to be connected with spe¬
cial events (hunting, rituals, symbolic scenes)
rather than routine activities. The main hunt¬
ing weapons include simple curved bows, ham¬
mers, throwing sticks (probably boomerangs)
and a sort of hook or lasso for trapping
ostriches by the neck. Ban-Barur, or hobbling
stones (found in abundance on the plateau)
used to immobilize wild animals appear in
many engravings featuring aurochs, rhinocer¬
oses, giraffes, ostriches, lions and donkeys. In
some scenes, a braided tie seems to hold the
animal's legs.
A few hieratic figures portrayed in great
THE UNESCO ^>URI:ER APRIL 1993
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
detail give us some idea of the clothing worn
by these people, including short pants and
short-sleeved shirts. Some figures wear paral¬
lel cloth strips and a loincloth which is some¬
times topped with a striped belt to which a
pendant holding a triangular structure is
attached. Short bulging tunics are also depicted.
Some men are shown wearing a codpiece.
Women usually wear full, almost ankle-length
dresses and have conical hairstyles possibly
constructed with plaits or braids. They often
have heavy features and prominent noses, but
they may be wearing face masks. These stereo¬
typed women are usually shown with wild
beasts or domesticated Bovidae.
A rich array ofbeasts
The engravings are executed with such preci¬
sion that some of the animals depicted can be
identified with a fair degree of certainty. This A naturalistically rendered
gazelle's head turning to face
backwards. (Wadi Bedis).
>
particularly applies to the large, wild Bovidae,
some of which have since become extinct. These
animals either stand alone or are surrounded
by archers who are usually small. In addition
to several species of antelopes, there are three
large undomesticated animals: the early buf¬
falo, the aurochs and the African buffalo. The
frequency with which aurochs and buffalo are
portrayed indicates their importance in this
area. Engravings representing aurochs trapped
by a hobbling stone suggest attempts at
domestication. Since this animal is the ances¬
tor of the domesticated ox, this mountain¬
ous part of the Sahara may have been an impor¬
tant early centre of domestication.
Wild animals are abundant and carefully
depicted. Elephants and rhinoceroses are often .
shown with their young in a range of
dynamic, realistic poses. Hippopotami and
crocodiles appear in a number of places where
there may have been permanent watering holes
or lakes in a wet climate. Today, there are only
a handful of short-lived gueltas or watering
holes, which do not fill annually but may in
some cases hold water for more than six
months. Fish are rarely depicted. There are
many pictures of giraffes, whose nuptial
parades are sensitively and gracefully shown.
Their coats are sometimes shown by means
of small cup marks that give a beautiful effect.
Ostriches, donkeys, large and small felines
(leopards, lions, jackals), and some wild fox¬
like canines also appear. A few specimens of
warthogs can also be seen.
While this bestiary is limited to a small
number of species, it is nonetheless represen¬
tative of a biotope a small area that supports
its own distinctive community probably a
wooded savannah with permanent watering
holes on the edge of the Murzuk dunes. After
the unusually heavy rains of 1997, the Messak
gueltas held thousands of cubic metres of
water for several months and some of them
even became lakes several hundred metres
long providing a glimpse of what was prob¬
ably a common occurrence several thousand
years ago.
A fertile imagination
Some sandstone walls are adorned with surre¬
alistic animals which reflect a highly original
collective imagination. Fantastic hybrids
gazelle-headed ostriches, elephants with rhi¬
noceros heads, a simian body with a hare's
head rub shoulders with other flights of fancy
that astutely combine the lines of a giraffe, the
THE UNESCO lOURIER ATRIL 1 998
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
body of a rhinoceros and an ox's head. A few
birds, probably mythical, are also shown.
The most original creatures are also the
most common. More than 140 men with the
heads of jackals or hyenas suggest the first
glimmerings of a well-structured mythology.
Their superhuman activities are directed at
large wild animals. They attack and kill rhi¬
nos and aurochs with stone axes or clubs and
then effortlessly carry them on their shoulders
or under their arms, wearing a satisfied grin.
Hanging from their belt is the head or some
other kind of trophy from a rhino or in some
cases an aurochs.
Their relationship with elephants is more
subtle and complex. They stalk elephants
aggressively, their lips curled back to give a
ferocious display of teeth, and brandishing
axes or clubs, but never seem to wound their
Small delicate figure of a
giraffe on a slab of rock.
Wadi Imrawen.
prey. One outstanding engraving shows a
jackal- or hyena-headed elephant driver astride
a calm elephant which holds a small rhino
pinned upside down beneath its thigh.
Another shows a small jackal-headed man on
the heels of a large pachyderm, catching and
licking its fresh excrement.
A mysterious cosmogony
The absence of written sources makes it diffi¬
cult to interpret this cosmogony. The figures
described above all seem to belong to ritualized
scenes in which composition and the attitudes
of the figures are stereotyped. The role of
masked men should probably be interpreted
symbolically. A new reading of the animal
representations might make it possible to
identify traces of a specifically Messak cos¬
mogony.
Any discussion of the engravings on the
Messak plateau must address the hundreds of
identical, abstract signs they depict, includ¬
ing oval cup marks and reticulated circles. A
local interpretation associates these with sink¬
ing wells. There might be a generic link with
water, or more generally, with some kind of
fertility symbolism. These signs were certainly
important, given their number, but their
meaning nonetheless eludes us.
The existence of this surprising universe
1 in the world's largest arid desert is certainly
I no accident. The cultural centres in these for-
| gotten mountains are closely linked to the cli-
I matic past of the Saharan sub-continent. Their
altitude and the moister climate of the early
Holoccne epoch (beginning around 10,000
years ago) fertilized the deep and silty earth
where today the aridity and erosion of thou¬
sands of years have sterilized it.
The origins and histories of these cultures
are still a mystery. We can, however, suppose
that the Messak plateau along with other
mountain ranges of the central Sahara was one
of the centres of development of the New
Stone Age. The high proportion of symbolic
images left by the people who lived there
should not veil the message of these open-air
engravings, namely that the people of the Mes¬
sak were above all hunters and herdsmen who
were perfectly integrated into a living nature
that they respected.
The authors would like to thank Messrs Mohammed
Ibrahim Meshai and Saad Salah Abdulaziz, curators of
the antiquities of the Fezzan, for their kind assistance
in revealing the full extent of this prehistoric heritage.
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Rock art of sub-Saharan Africa:
a thumbnail guide BYOSAGAODAK
Men running at full speed.
Rock painting in the Matopo
Hills (Zimbabwe).
Africa has a vast heritage of rock art
which three main factors have helped to
preserve: belief systems, inaccessibility, and
secrecy.
The sites arc generally located in highlands
and comprise rock shelters, caves and smooth
open rock surfaces. Most of the shelters with
paintings are high on bush-covered hillsides,
facing or overlooking plains, valleys or rivers.
The painters seem to have preferred such loca¬
tions because they commanded a wide view
of the plains and of immediate surrounding
areas which enabled them to watch game and
sometimes, perhaps, hostile warring peoples.
Hilltops were also suitable for camping, espe¬
cially during the wet seasons, when the low
lying plains would be flooded.
Most sites were accessible only to special
groups of people at particular times, and there
were strict taboos against visiting, cutting
trees, herding or even collecting firewood from
them. As a result their environment was left
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
undisturbed. Most sites were inaccessible to
villagers, and people who did manage to reach
them were deterred by taboos from vandaliz¬
ing the art. Most important of all, some sites
were usually known only to elders and prac¬
titioners of rituals, who tried to keep their
location secret.
Unfortunately, the situation has drasti¬
cally changed. Belief systems that guarded the
sites have broken down and are no longer
respected. Population growth has stepped up
demands on land for agricultural use, and since
taboos no longer act as a deterrent, people
encroach on the sites with impunity.
Distribution areas
and themes
*~ The Horn (Ethiopia, Eritrea, Jibouti,
Somalia): Paintings mainly depicting long
horned humpless cattle (also found in Kenya
on sites around Mount Elgon).
*" Sudan: Painted rock shelters and caves in
Dajo Hills South of Darfur. Depictions of
wild animals and horses whose riders are armed
with shields, and foot soldiers armed with
shields and spears.
>* Zambia, Zimbabwe, South Africa: Paint¬
ings of animals and humans; schematic designs
such as parallel lines and concentric circles with
lines radiating from the centre.
'*" East Africa: The richest area is in central
Tanzania (Dodoma, especially Kondoa district,
and Singida regions). Isolated concentrations
of sites in Tanzania are found in the Masasi,
Mbulu, Mwanza, Bukoba, Unyamwezi and
Haida Plain areas. The Mwanza and Bukoba
sites extend to include sites in the Kenya and
Uganda sides of Lake Victoria Island.
*" Northern Kenya: Engravings ofwild animals
(e.g. antelopes, gazelles, hippos, giraffes and
rhinoceros) and domestic animals (e.g. camels,
donkeys, cattle) and stylized humans.
Painting of men and
animals. Drakensberg
Mountains, Natal
(South Africa).
Dromedaries
and cattle, rock art of
the Saharan plateaux
of the Ennedi (Chad).
The Saharan style
extends as far east as
part of the Horn of
Africa and as far south
as Mount Elgon
(Kenya).
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The
universality
of rock art
Unesco ¡s mandated by its Con¬
stitution to assure "the con¬
servation and protection of the world's
inheritance of works of art and monu¬
ments of history and science".
For fifty years Unesco has therefore
sought to encourage and promote inter¬
national action designed to ensure that
the physical and non-physical expres¬
sions of human creativity are consid¬
ered as an indivisible whole by the inter¬
national community. It is important that
all these expressions should be
respected as elements of the universal
heritage, and conserved, studied and
transmitted to future generations.
In accordance with its mission to
aid its Member States, Unesco has
included in its priorities "The safeguard
of rock art all over the world, particu¬
larly with regard to compiling an inven¬
tory of it, conserving it, training tech¬
nicians, and promoting exchanges of
knowledge and public information."
These pursuits are a token of interna¬
tional recognition of the universal value
of a fragile cultural heritage.
Rock art is a classic example of a
universal art. These first known expres¬
sions of the sensibility and aesthetics of
our distant ancestors are inscribed on
rock surfaces in many world regions.
From Australia to Africa, from Asia to
the Americas and Europe, our prehis¬
toric predecessors inscribed the places
38
m /
*
/':/
m
:* "à:$ à
FOZ COA (Portugal) is an open-air rock art site at least 18,000 years old which extends over 15 km.
This exceptional complex is threatened by the construction of a dam. A Unesco mission visited the
site and later published a report outlining the steps necessary to safeguard the engravings. Above,
drawing of a Magdalenian-style horse at Foz Coa.
where they halted on their journeys,
their shelters and their sanctuaries with
works of art which stir our feelings and
our admiration. Rock art is the only
form of human cultural expression
which has been practised without inter¬
ruption from tens of thousands of years
ago until the present day.
In its original cultural context, it was
protected by the respect that surrounded
it, just like the environment of which it
formed part. Now, in shelters or on rocks
in the open air, rock art is subject to all
kinds of aggression from nature and
from people. This precious art has today
become a threatened heritage.
MARIE-JOSÉE THIEL
Cultural Heritage Division
Unesco
Extracted from: i.e chemin secret des
Ngarinyin du nord-ouest australien, Paris,
Muséum National d'Histoire Naturelle,
1977 © Pathway Project Pty Ltd 1997
FOR FURTHER INFORMATION:
Mme Marie-Josée Thiel
Cultural Heritage Division, Culture Sector
Unesco, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Pans Cedex, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 44 20
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 55 96
Telex: 204461 Paris
FURTHER READING
Rock Art, a universal cultural message, a bilingual
(French/English) booklet by Jean Clottes, Paris,
Unesco/ICOMOS, 1997 (available free)
The following issues of the Unesco Courier.
The state of the world heritage, September 1997
Troglodytes, a hidden world, December 1995
Articles:
"The rune-stones of Jelling", by Jens Boel (May 1996)
"The painted caves of Mogao", by José Serra Vega
(December 1993)
"The rock artof Tassili n'Ajjer", by Caroline Haardt (July 1991)
TO SUBSCRIBE
to the quarterly periodicals Museum Internationaland The
World Heritage Review, please contact:
Unesco Publishing,
1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 43 00
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 57 41
Website: http://www.unesco.org/publishing
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
I ROCK ART ON THE WORLD HERITAGE LIST
(Sites and their years of inscription)
Algeria: Tassili n'Ajjer (1982)
Australia: Kakadu National Park (1981, 1987, 1992), Uluru-Kata Tjuta National Park
(1987, 1994)
Brazil: Serra da Capivara National Park (1991)
Chile: Rapa Nui National Park (1995)
France: Decorated Grottoes of the Vézère Valley (1979)
Ireland: Archaeological Ensemble of the Bend of the Boyne (1993)
Italy: Rock Drawings in Valcamonica (1979)
Libyan Arab Jamahiriya: Rock Art Sites of Tadrart Acacus (1985)
Mexico: Rock Paintings of the Sierra de San Francisco (1993)
Norway: The Rock Art Site of Alta (1985)
Spain: Altamira Cave (1985)
Sweden: Rock Carvings in Tanum (1994)
U.S.A.: Mesa Verde (1978)
THE INTERNATIONAL COUNCIL ON MONUMENTS AND SITES
AND THE INTERNATIONAL ROCK ART COMMITTEE
The International Council on Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS) is an international non¬
governmental organization that works to promote the application of theory, methodology
and scientific techniques to the conservation, protection and enhancement of monu¬
ments and sites.
Objectives
« To bring together conservation specialists from all over the world and serve as a
forum for professional dialogue and exchange
To put its network of qualified professionals at the service of the international
community
« To collect, evaluate and disseminate information on conservation principles, tech¬
niques and policies
To co-operate with national and international authorities on the establishment of
documentation centres specializing in conservation
* To work for the adoption and implementation of international conventions on the
protection, conservation and enhancement of monuments and sites
To participate in the organization of training programmes for conservation spe¬
cialists on a world-wide scale.
The documentation centre
Working with Unesco and the International Council of Museums (ICOM), the documen¬
tation centre covers all the regions of the world and all aspects of the preservation of
monuments and sites. It is open to all researchers and institutions concerned. It can
be reached by telephone or by e-mail and is open to the public on working days for con¬
sultation of reference works. It maintains a bibliographical database with more than
20,000 entries derived from its own resources.
International Newsletter on Rock Art
The International Rock Art Committee (CAR) of ICOMOS has for the past four years pub¬
lished an International Newsletter on World Rock Art (NORA), in English and French (three
32-page issues per year), in order to encourage communication on all subjects relat¬
ing to the world's heritage of rock art. The newsletter is distributed in 104 countries,
and plays an important role in diffusion of knowledge and in heritage protection.
Further information from:
International Committee on Rock Art (CAR-ICOMOS)
11, rue du Fourcat, 09000 Foix, France
Tel: (33) (0) 5 61 65 01 82
Fax: (33) (0) 5 61 65 35 73
A number of ICOMOS publications on rock art are on sale at the
International Council on Monuments and Sites
49-51, rue de la Fédération, 75015 Paris, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 67 67 70
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 66 06 22
E-mail: icomos@cicrp.jussieu.fr
Website: http://www.international.icomos.org
THE WARA PROJECT
(WORLD ARCHIVES OF ROCK ART)
Since 1983, Professor Emmanuel Anati and his team at the Cen¬
tre of Prehistoric Studies of Valcamonica (Centro Camuno di
Studi Preistorici) at Capo di Ponte (Italy) have been working on
an ambitious project to draw upan inventory of rock art sites on
five continents. More than 100,000 slides and a mass of back¬
ground material have so far been assembled.
The compilation of these World Archives of Rock Art at the
Valcamonica Centre and at the Musée des Sciences de l'Homme
in Paris is being supported by Unesco and the International Coun¬
cil for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies (ICPHS).
Prof. Anati considers that one of the goals of these archives,
which cover 40,000 years of the history of art, is to lay the
groundwork for broader comparative and synoptic studies on a
world-wide basis. "In these archives," he notes, "we have assem¬
bled documentation concerning thousands of areas on all the con¬
tinents in which we have chosen the 150 known rock art sites
which are most important historically and artistically speaking.
Some of them comprise over a million prehistoric figurations, and
many have more than 100,000 images."
Further information from:
Centra Camuno di Studi Preistorici
25044 Capo di Ponte
Valcamonica (Brescia), Italy
Tel: (39-364) 42 091
Fax: (39-364) 42 572
I A WORLD PERSPECTIVE ON ROCK ART
In 1983, Unesco commissioned a world report on the state of
research into rock art. This was the first attempt on a world¬
wide scale to present an overall picture of this early form of
artistic creativity.
The report was published by Unesco in its "Studies and Doc¬
uments on the Cultural Heritage" series in 1984. A fuller version
appeared in the same year in volume 21 of the Newsletter of
the Camunian Centre of Prehistoric Studies. In 1993, ICOMOS
commissioned another report on the state of research into rock
art. It was presented in August of the same year at a Congress
held at Colombo (Sri Lanka) and published as a monograph by
ICOMOS.
"As the author of these two reports," writes Prof. Emmanuel
Anati, "I have seen the amazing progress made in this field in the
course of a decade. In November 1997, Editions Larousse in
Paris published one of my works, L 'art rupestre dans le monde,
L'imaginaire de la Préhistoire (the Italian edition, // museo
immaginario délia preistoria, is published under the Jaca Book
[Milan] imprint). Here the main considerations and conclusions
set forth in the two world reports are accompanied by further
reflexions, an exploration of the signification of symbols and the
syntax of associations.
"During the writing of the two world reports, the hypothesis
emerged that since art is the reflection of a mental outlook,
rock art is a documentary source of primary importance for
research into the conceptual and psychological foundations of
modern men and women. In the earliest art, we find archetypes
and paradigms which are still profoundly relevant to our own
time.
Further reading:
Rock Art, Colombo, ICOMOS, 1993
Í. 'art rupestre dans le monde, L'imaginaire de la Préhistoire, by
Emmanuel Anati, preface by Yves Coppens, Larousse-Bordas
publishers, Paris, 1997
> G>uTHE UNESCO lOURIER ATRIL 1998
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
commentary Federico Mayor
The ethics
of the future
"Our inheritance was not willed to us". With these
words, the French poet René Char reminded human¬
ity, amid the ruins of the Second World War, of its hasic
responsibility towards history. Thus, a generation of sur¬
vivors took up the cause of future generations.
This new approach, this quest for human solidarity
through both space and time, has for over fifty years been
the task of the United Nations in general and of UNESCO in
particular. "To save succeeding generations from the
scourge of war" is the solemn commitment introducing the
Charter of the United Nations. This, too, is what is meant by
UNESCO's Constitution when it speaks of contributing to
peace and security by promoting collaboration among nations
through education, science and culture.
The world has, however, changed in the last fifty years,
as have the issues, the challenges and, it must be acknowl¬
edged, the dangers of modern times. On the eve of the twenty-
first century, diffferent wars are breaking out: we have had
experience of world wars and bloody conflicts between
nations, but today we are witnessing conflicts that tear peo¬
ples apart within nations. This is not the place to dwell on
other forms of violence: violence against hope and the future
of human beings, against their dignity, or the latent conflicts
between cultures and between generations. The scourge
seems to be universal. All over the world, the citizens of
today are claiming rights over the citizens of tomorrow, threat¬
ening their well-being and at times their lives. I repeat:
today's citizens are claiming rights over tomorrow's, and we
are beginning to realize that we are jeopardizing the exercise
by future generations of their human rights. More than ever,
the ethics of the future requires that we devise and dissem¬
inate that culture of peace which was the aim of UNESCO's
founders, and see that it is shared.
Limiting the power of technology
In the economic and social field, debt, division and instabil¬
ity make up the inglorious heritage, the poisoned legacy we
leave to our successors. Look at the earth and the natural
environment: gas emissions, desert encroachment, pollution
and the misuse of natural resources seem to foredoom the
planet. The essential, vital needs of our children, not only the
earth, water and air but also knowledge, freedom and soli¬
darity, are being sacrificed on the altar of short-term expedi¬
ency, ambition and profit, thus encouraging the soft options
and selfishness of a short-sighted age, bringing to mind the
famous saying attributed to the king of a world on the wane:
"Après moi, le deluge".
There are more serious matters still: it is not only society
and the environment but the very essence and biological
integrity of the human person that are imperilled. It is now
within the realms of possibility for humans to modify the
genetic heritage of any species, including their own. They
even possess the grim privilege of being able to plan their own
disappearance. With modern science we have almost reached
the point of no return. Never mind the arguments about the
compensation in technological or financial terms: there will
be no replacement since what is destroyed has no equivalent,
and there will be no payout since what is destroyed is with¬
out price. Who can compensate for genocide? Who would
dare to claim that we can pay for the earth? Ifwe want to pro¬
tect our descendants, we must first of all recognize, accept
and come to terms with this fundamental paradox: progress
and civilization are one side of the coin, but the other side is
the possibility of an apocalypse, of irreversible destruction,
of chaos. A lucid realization ofthat fact is the prime require¬
ment of our responsibility to future generations. Agreeing to
curb the now unbridled power of technology by ethics and
wisdom is henceforth the proper course. Lord Acton's dictum
that "absolute power corrupts absolutely" needs to be
applied to technology, while science needs to be reminded of
Rabelais' saying that "science without conscience is but
ruination of the soul".
But where does science dwell, and where are we to look
for wisdom? We are nowadays able to travel to the other end
of the earth in a matter of hours, and we are able to see for
ourselves that, while the great cities of the industrialized
40
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
countries may possess the
knowledge, it is in the
remotest villages that the
wisdom is to be found. On
the eve of the twenty-first
century, we at last have the
ability to reconcile knowl¬
edge and wisdom and to
make them benefit from each
other's virtues. With this in
mind, we in UNESCO drew
up, with the assistance of the
International Bioethics Committee, the Universal Declara¬
tion on the Human Genome and Human Rights which was
adopted by the Organization's General Conference in Novem¬
ber last the first universal declaration to apply to science
and to lay down ethical principles in this field which will
remind us all that we are born free and equal.
Foreseeing in order to build
I said we must in the name of ethics and wisdom agree to
curb the power that technology gives to humans over humans.
The issue looms large and the challenge is a real one. In an
age of globalization and of the acceleration and multiplication
of exchanges, the future appears, if not dark, then at least
unclear. Complexity and uncertainty are the key words of
our time. I therefore invoke the virtues of an education of con¬
cern, since concern stirs us to action, whereas conformity
and optimism benumb us. This is, of course, to assume will¬
ingness on our part to observe and ask questions of the future,
for our temporal short-sightedness is often coupled with a
wilful blindness,when not serving as a justification for it.
Caught in the whirl of the quick fix, held in the tyrannical grip
of short-termism, we do not take the time to shape our actions
or think about their consequences. We are hurtling into the
future with no brakes and in conditons of zero visibility. But
the faster a car goes, the brighter its headlights must be: it is
no longer, therefore, a question of adjusting or adapting
adjustment and adaptation always lag behind events, which
move ahead more rapidly but a matter of taking pre-emptive
action. We should stop talking about adjustment and adap¬
tation and take a clear-sighted, forward-looking approach,
casting a future-oriented eye on the world. We should plant
today the seeds of tomorrow, protecting them as they grow, so
that tomorrow our children may harvest the fruits of our fore¬
sight . To foresee in order to prevent and to foresee in order to
build these are our objectives.
Preserving the human element
Prevention is not merely a possibility: it is an obligation and
The ethics of the future is an ethics of the
fragile and the perishable. We must
bequeath to future generations the right
to live in dignity in a world preserved.
principle which has pre¬
vailed has been that of a
principle of inaction rather
than one of vigilant action.
Risk-taking without knowl¬
edge is dangerous, but
knowledge without risk-tak¬
ing is worthless. Today, alas,
more than five years after
the Rio Summit, what has
been the outcome, where
are the results? The com¬
mitments then made have given way to evasiveness, and
Agenda 21 has to all intents and purposes remained a dead
letter. "Rio plus 5" is "Rio minus 5". We have to ponder this
lesson, and sow within democracy itself the seed that can
revitalize and reconstitute it. That seed is and can only be
the ethics of the future, made central to decision-making,
central to democratic deliberation, central to the kind of
adversarial appraisal that, rather than obfuscating, appeas¬
ing or misleading opinion by serving vested interests, the
authorities and the powers that be, must enlighten the pub¬
lic and form its judgment.
Prevention means first and foremost preserving. The
ethics of the future is an ethics of the fragile and the per¬
ishable. We must hand down to future generations an inher¬
itance that has not been irreparably damaged and polluted.
We must bequeath to them the right to live in a world pre¬
served. This concerns first of all our living environment
the new preoccupation of the present age and such endur¬
ing values as health, education, culture, equality, freedom,
peace, tolerance and solidarity. The Catalan poet Salvador
Espriii told his children: "I have lived to preserve these few
words which I bequeath to you: love, justice and freedom".
We are responsible not only for our tangible heritage; the
essential objects of our duty and responsibility are often
invisible and intangible. The concept of heritage has thus
taken on new meanings in recent decades: from the straight¬
forward preservation of historic monuments to the Con¬
vention for the Protection of the World Cultural and Nat¬
ural Heritage, adopted in 1972, and from the recognition of
our non-material, symbolic and spiritual heritage to the
work currently being done by the International Bioethics
Committee on the protection of the human genome, the con¬
cept of being has gradually pervaded that of having. It is
human beings themselves who are the true common heritage
of humanity, our priceless universal birthright.
At the dawn of a new century and a new millennium, at
a time when the global village no longer seems so distant a
prospect, we must shoulder our responsibilities as citizens of
the world. This means that we must become aware of our
a moral imperative. This idea has indeed already made some position, in human history as well as in space, and must reflect
headway in public awareness and in international law. It has
even given rise to a new principle, enshrined in 1992 at the
Earth Summit in Rio and incorporated into the Maastricht
Treaty and some national standard-setting instruments: I
refer to the precautionary principle. But the view ofthat
on our role on the planet and in history. One's love for one's
neighbour is indeed also to be measured by the respect one
shows for those far distant. Near or far, yesterday or today,
other people are still our fellow creatures. Both in space and
in time, humanity is one body and we are its members.
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Cuba's
biosphere
reserves
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
rl The Soviet-made jeep, an
I aged vehicle with many thou¬
sands of kilometres on the clock,
turned off the motorway leading
from the Cuban capital, Havana, and
headed for Playa Girón, on the Zap¬
ata peninsula. This was where the
Third National Seminar on Cuba's
Protected Areas, organized at the
request of Antonio Perera Puga,
head of the Environment Agency's
Protected Areas Centre, was being
held. Seventy participants, from all
the provinces of Cuba, were attend¬
ing this seminar, part of whose remit
was to respond to a UNESCO ques¬
tionnaire drawn up with the aim of
having the swampland on the Zapata
peninsula (the Ciénaga de Zapata)
listed as the island's fifth hiosphere
reserve.
Cuba is the largest island in the
Caribbean, 1,250 km long, nearly
200 km wide, and surrounded by
some 1,600 islets and reefs. Since
two-thirds of its eleven million inhab¬
itants live in towns and cities, there
are scarcely more than ten people
to the square kilometre in the rest of
the island, with the result that the
human impact on the environment is
very limited.
Seen from the air, Cuba appears
predominantly green, with innumer¬
able rectangular fields of sugar-cane
and groves of royal palms that alter-
THE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
An orchid of the
Cattleya genus
(Guanahacabibes
biosphere
reserve).
nate with plantations of citrus fruits
and bananas. The soil is deep purple
shading into violet, and there is
water irrigation canals, lakes and
rivers everywhere. In 1900, the
island was still half covered with for¬
est, hut now only 19 per cent of it is
forested.
THE CIÉNAGA DE ZAPATA
The Ciénaga de Zapata is the
Caribbean's largest area 500,000
hectares of wetland. Its maze of
freshwater channels, islands and man¬
grove swamps is a haven for manatees,
5,000 or so crocodiles, 27 species of
reptiles and 15 species of mammals,
hut above all for 10,000 pink flamin¬
goes and for 160 species of birds,
most of them, like the colourful
tocororo or Cuban togon (Priotelus
temnurus) which together with the
royal palm is the country's national
emblem or the ivory-billed wood¬
pecker (Campephilus principalis),
threatened with extinction. Strangely
enough, this peninsula is still not
listed among the sites protected
under the Convention on Wetlands of
International Importance Especially
as Waterfowl Habitat (known as the
Ramsar Convention, having been
adopted at Ramsar, Iran, on 2 Feb¬
ruary 1971).
Scattered around among several
small villages, the peninsula's 9,000
inhabi tants make a living from fishing,
charcoal burning and tourism. As
everywhere else in Cuba, environ
mental education forms part of the
syllabus at all grades in the schools
here. The Cuban educational system
is, incidentally, so well developed that
illiteracy has almost been eradicated,
and as for the free national health
system, the figures speak for them¬
selves: one doctor for every 275
inhabitants and an infant mortality
rate of 9 per thousand, as against 90
per thousand in Africa and 41 in
Latin America, for example. Cubans
joke that they can have a heart trans¬
plant for free but can't get hold of
aspirins for love nor money.
The problems of managing Cuba's
biosphere reserves are inseparable
from the country's overall economic
situation. When we visited the Sierra
del Rosario reserve, its manager,Mar-
itza Garcia, who does not own a car,
had to come to meet us by hitch-hik¬
ing (a method known as botellas in
Cuba). Although she has a brand-new
computer provided by UNESCO, she-
has trouble in obtaining paper and
ink for it. Like everything else here,
including nails and machetes, they
can be bought for dollars, while on
the other hand only Cuban nationals
can use the national currency, the
peso (it should also be pointed out
that 300 pesos, regarded as a good
salary in Cuba , are equivalent to $12) .
Slogans displayed on walls drive home
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
the message that Cuba should not
count on outside help, but well-tar¬
geted aid would be invaluable for the
nature conservation enthusiasts whom
we encountered everywhere on our
travels.
SIERRA DEL ROSARIO
The Sierra del Rosario reserve is a
25,000-hectare mountain region, 50
km from Havana, with four rivers
running through it. There are four
types of vegetation within the
reserve: tropical rainforest, decidu¬
ous woodland, pinewoods, and savan¬
nah, this last being home to many
orchids and endemic plants. There
arc 608 species of higher plants, 90
species of birds, many of them
Freshwater
channel in the
Ciénaga de
Zapata biosphere
reserve.
Coconut-palm
nursery (Cuchillas
del Toa biosphere
reserve).
k Mff ^
^ÄS*w.
r
¡SflHt r-J=J
i
r
rjflnjUUf * ^wEj mwm% "
*mIÖK
i\u^
Pratt
wJV*i
Trees are
incorporated in
the structure of
this "eco-hotel" in
the Sierra del
Rosario biosphere
reserve.
endemic to this site, 16 species of
amphibians, including the world's
smallest frog, Smithilus limbatus,
and 33 species of reptiles. The two
central zones consist of two rocky
peaks rising to over 500 m. In the
1 ,000-hectarc buffer zone, tra¬
versed by 175 km of roads acting as
fire-breaks, tree-felling and hunting
are prohibited. Guides accompany
visitors along nature trails. There
are several villages where the region's
4,000 or so inhabitants live, the most
remarkable of these being Las Ter¬
razas, where, thanks to income from
tourism, a hotel with trees built into
its design has been constructed, and
local craftspeople and artists sell
wood-carvings and superb paintings
of orchids.
GUANAHACABIBES
The Guanahacabibes biosphere
reserve is located at the extreme
western end of the island. Its name
derives from that of the indigenous
cave-dwelling people who lived there
for almost 2,000 years, until the six¬
teenth century. Its 101,500 hectares
of never-ending beaches, jagged lime¬
stone pavements, marshland, peat
bogs and mangrove swamps provide
a habitat for about 600 species of
plants, 15 of which are found
nowhere else, deer, a large rodent,
the Initia (Capromys), bats, reptiles,
wild cattle and any number of birds.
Much research has been carried
out on this reserve since 1985. Jorge
Ferro, Director of the Environment
for the large province of Pinar del
Rio, who is writing a book on tiny
orrhids, has to hitch-hike to get
there and has to make do with one
roll of camera film a year. He guided
us on the nature trails that hav c been
laid out through the reserve, one of
them in the central zone. The people
living on the reserve arc employed
by a State forestry enterprise, in the
village of Valle de San Juan there
are 1,200 beehives, producing 59
tons of honey a year. Funds provided
by a Spanish organization have made
it possible to build a large hothouse
for growing tomatoes, for which
there is a ready market, and solar
panels are due to be installed in the
village. The oldest inhabitant,
Esther, grows and prescribes medi¬
cinal plants.
BAC0NA0
From Havana we Hew to Santiago de
Cuba, which is only two kilometres
west of the 84,600-hcctare Raconao
reserve, an integral part of the Gran
Parque Nacional Sierra Maestra.
The reserve is managed by Riocco
(Eastern Centre for the Study of
Ecosystems and Riodivcrsily), a very
acliv e organization for which 47 sci¬
entists work in Santiago's Natural
History Museum. Also in Santiago is
a garden run by Manuel Caluff, a
veritable research centre linked to
the reserve, established in 1976,
where 350 species of fern and an
abundance of orchids grow.
Some superb cacti, including an
endangered endemic species, Meto-
cactus harlowii, are to be found on
the dry coastal tablelands. The
scenery is very different around the
Gran Piedra, a mountainous area of
the reserve which has 138 species of
endemic plants and 919 species of
animals. Its pines, which were grown
for timber and are gradually being
replaced by native species, are inter¬
spersed with tree-ferns and other
types of fern no fewer than 335
species and terrestrial orchids
(Phaius tunckervillie ).
THE UNESCO lOURIER AI*RIL 1998
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
CUCHILLAS DEL TOA
From Raconao, a mountain road
leads to the Cuchillas del Toa
reserve, near Raracoa, the first town
in Cuba, founded in 1512. The
reserve's central zone encompasses
the Alejandro de Humboldt Park,
60,000 hectares ofmountainous ter¬
rain traversed by countless rivers and
with an annual rainfall of 4,000mm,
where there is no question of ven¬
turing without a guide.
We were shown around by the
park's director, Rael Acebal Suárez,
who told us that 70% of its plant
species are endemic; more than half
of the species growing in Cuba are to
be found there. There are four farm¬
ing communities within the park. Its
67,000-hectarc buffer zone has been
seriously damaged by agricultural
activities, and a recent forest fire did
nothing to improve matters. The local
inhabitants arc helping to replant the
mangrove swamps, where there is a
population ofmanatees. Since meat,
like other staple foods, is rationed,
they are allowed to hunt wild pigs
and hutia but are urged to do so in
moderation. Two villages designed to
meet the needs of "ecotourism" are
being built with funds provided by
Germany.
PRIVILEGED RESERVES
Compared with so many other bios¬
phere reserves we have visited on four
continents, those in Cuba even if
their boundaries are not always
defined as accurately as they might
be are on the whole in a very good
state of preservation, the reason being
that there is very little industry in
Cuba, its population density is
extremely low, its transport system
is sketchy and its economic situation
is such that nothing can be wasted.
Since bottles, plastic bags and paper
are in short supply, people don't lit¬
ter the countryside with them . Those
who enjoy the privilege of access to
the reserves appreciate their value
and respect their biodiversity. Last
but not least, the scientists who work
there are dedicated to their task and
do not look for financial rewards.
They manage as best they can,
uncomplainingly, endorsing the
Cuban proverb, Cuando no hay
perro, se montea con gato if you
haven't got a dog, a cat will do, or,
beggars can't be choosers. I
WORLD
UNPOPULAR BISON
By 1900, therewere no more than two dozen bison
left in Yellowstone National Park (U.S.A.). Bison have
since been reintroduced and the herds have been re¬
established, but the proliferation of these animals
has not been to everyone's taste. Around a third of
all the bison that died during the unusually harsh
winter of 1996-97 were killed outside the park at the
request of nearby ranchers who claimed that they
could infect their cattle, with brucellosis in particular
although no cases of brucellosis have been officially
reported and elk, which also carry the disease, have
not been shot.
PROTECTING
SRI LANKA'S MEDICINAL PLANTS
A $4,570,000 loan from the Global Environment Facil¬
ity will enable the Sri Lankan government to set up five
protected zones to preserve medicinal plants. Of the
1,414 plants that are commonly used by Sri Lankans
for medicinal purposes, at least 189 are endemic to
the island, and 79 of these are threatened with extinc¬
tion through uncontrolled gathering and the conver¬
sion of their natural habitats into farmland. This loan
will make it possible to improve existing nurseries and
create new ones, to create a network providing infor¬
mation about these plants, and to raise public aware¬
ness of the need to protect them.
COMPLETE RECYCLING
The United States Information Agency recently raised
the possibility of creating new materials to replace
plastic. These biopolymers (many molecules linked
together to create one large molecule) made from the
waste products of the agro-food industry would
have all the characteristics of normal plastics but
would be biodegradable. When composted, they could
be used as fertilizers.
REDUCING WASTE
The United Nations Zero Emissions Research Initia¬
tive (ZERI) programme at the United Nations Univer¬
sity (see Unesco Courier, March 1996) is enjoying
increasing success. The University of Tokyo has con¬
tributed $10 million to the programme. In 1995, a
ZERI office opened in Bogotá (Colombia), and another
in Windhoek (Namibia), where, with funding from Japan
through Unesco and UNU, a first chair was created
in 1997. On the occasion of the programme's Third
Annual World Congress, held in Jakarta (Indonesia) in
1997, six universities agreed to collaborate on a 500-
hour interdisciplinary course leading to a Master's
degree in integrated blosystems that will enable stu¬
dents to establish direct links between science and
technology. The aim of turning waste matter into raw
materials may thus finally become a reality.
WILLTHE BI0-BI0
CONTINUE TO RUN WILD?
The Bio-Bio River (Chile), one of the world's last major
free-flowing rivers, is about to be blocked by a second
hydroelectric dam. Activist Juan Pablo Orrego, founder
of a river protection group, claims that this dam will
flood 34 square kilometres of a richly diverse forest,
dooming 14 plant and animal species to extinction
and, more especially, covering the ancestral burial
grounds of 101 Pehuenche Indians. Orrego, who
received an ecology award in 1997, was unable to
prevent the construction of a the first, smaller Pangue
dam. In addition, the Pehuenche Indians have mixed
feelings about the project.
IS THE END IN SIGHT
F0RTIGERS?
No-one can say for certain how many tigers there are
left in the world, most estimates ranging from 5,000
to 7,000. It is, on the other hand, easier to count
dead ones: in India, for example, 63 were killed in
1997. Carcasses have even been found ¡n the Andhra
Pradesh reserve, which is where they are supposed
to be best protected but where the wardens, less
well armed than the poachers, have great difficulty in
protecting them.
A NEW PARK FOR CAIRO
The Aga Khan Foundation plans to invest $15 mil¬
lion to lay out a 30-hectare public park in the Al Azhar
neighbourhood of Cairo (Egypt). The creation of this
park will form part of the Foundation's programme of
support for historic cities, under which it will also
undertake, with the co-operation of local community
development organizations, the rehabilitation and
protection of the environment along Cairo's historic
city wall.
© h M J
44
THE UNESCO ^>URIIER APRIL 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Anniversary Elijah ben Solomon ZaliTian,
the gao/7 of Vilna BY HENRI MINCZELES
A great 18th-century Jewish scholar
and spiritual leader who marked
the thinking of eastern Europe's Jewish communities
I Elijah ben Solomon Zahnan, who
I was born in 1720 in Seletz, near
Grodno, was considered to be a genius
from his childhood. Even before he was
thirteen years old and passed the bar
mitzvah ritual admitting him into the
Jewish community as an adult, he had
already become interested in the natural
and religious sciences.
He married at eighteen, and had many
children. After a stay in Keidany with
his father-in-law, he travelled to Poland
and Germany and visited numerous Jew¬
ish communities. Then he settled on the
outskirts of Vilna in the Grand Duchy
of Lithuania, and later moved into a
house of study in the city which was cre¬
ated for him and which he directed.
Thanks to an inheritance, he and his
family had a home and a small stipend for
life, in addition to the regular salary paid
him by the city's Jewish community,
which had elected him its gaon or spir¬
itual leader. By the time he was thirty
years old, his reputation had spread
beyond his own community, but he
nonetheless firmly refused to become a
rabbi or to accept any other official posi¬
tion. He preferred to remain a spiritual
leader and live a secluded life devoted
to study.
The story goes that he studied at
night by candlelight in order to be able to
concentrate, and slept only two or three
hours a day. This also enabled him to
keep up a voluminous correspondence
with rabbis and especially to study the
compilation of law known as the
Jerusalem Talmud.
When he was over forty, he emerged
from seclusion and began to teach some
twenty pupils. His reputation grew even
further. An important rabbi from
Jerusalem paid tribute to him as "the
brilliant light of the century". His advice
was much sought-after and his opinions
had the weight of authority.
The dispute with Hassidism
However, a pietist movement known as
Hassidism developed in Galicia and
spread rapidly to Jewish communities
throughout eastern Europe. Its mysti¬
cism appeared to many as an antidote to
hard times, and instilled in them a com¬
plete change of heart. Hassidism, which
in a sense "democratized" the faith,
preached the joyful adoration of God,
rejected asceticism and attempted to
make the medieval mystical doctrine of
Kabbalah widely accessible.
The gaon of Vilna was violently hostile
to the Ilassidim, whom he described as
"mystics like leprosy on the body of
Israel." lie thought the Hassidie cult of
the Tsaddikim (Just Men endowed with
divine power and perception) could give
rise to false Messiahs. He managed to
have their centres closed and pronounced
an anathema (here m) on their books.
The Czarist authorities became
involved and the dispute became more
than a purely theological debate. A num¬
ber of Hassidie leaders were even briefly
imprisoned. In 1777, two of the move¬
ment's leaders, Menahem Mendel of
Vitebsk and Sehneur Zahnan of Liadi,
vainly attempted to bring about a recon¬
ciliation. Elijah ben Solomon stood firm,
and in 1791 ordered a public burning of
the book written by the movement's
founder, Israel ben Eliezer, known as the
Baal Shem Tov (Master of the Good
Name). This established the ga on as the
leader of the mitnagdim, or those who
opposed the Hassidie movement.
The gaon's message
The ga oil's refutation of Hassidism was
based on the principle of the eternity of
the Talmud, the first five books of the
Bilde, which record Jewish haw, includ¬
ing the ten commandments received by
Moses in the desert. The gaon of Vilna
believed that true Jewish learning could
only be based on a close study of the scrip¬
tures and that it was necessary to know
the Bible as well as all later commentaries
and writings, notably the Talmud.
The gaon also considered that knowl¬
edge of biblical texts should not be eon-
fined to an elite, and that for educational
reasons women should also have access
to it, especially the Book of Proverbs.
He was also interested in the natural
sciences, and claimed that "if a man lias
no knowledge of the secular sciences, he
cannot truly understand the Torah." lie
was a keen student of the natural sci¬
ences and other disciplines including
music and medicine.
1 le is credited with some seventy stud¬
ies and commentaries, more than fifty of
which were printed after his death.
These include explanations and discus¬
sions of Talmudic texts as well as analy¬
ses of Hebrew grammar, a subject which
fascinated him. His pupil Issachat Baer
anthologized his prayers and favourite
reading in a volume entitled Maaseh Rav.
A number of sayings attribu ted to the
gaon of Vilna have survived, such as "The
Torah is like the rain; it nourishes useful
plants and weeds", and "Life is endless
pain and suffering, and sleepless nights
arc our common lot". His personality
helped shape an outlook typical of the
Lithuanian Jew, influenced by the
region's cosmopolitanism and by the per¬
sistence of rationalistic Judaism.
Towards the end of his life, the gaon
was obliged to confront another progres¬
sive reform movement, the llaskala, led
by Moses Mendelssohn, the translator of
the Bible into German. He feared that
this movement would lead to Jewish assim¬
ilation and the loss of Jewish identity.
On the eve of Yom Kippur 1798, the
gaon of Vilna fell ill and died shortly
thereafter. The exact date of his death
is uncertain and some sources date it to
1797. The plain mausoleum where he is
buried is set in the Jewish quarter of the
new Vilna cemetery. It recalls to Jews a
great thinker and rigorous man who was
a faithful servant of Judaism.
THE UNESCO f3>URI£R APRIL l908 '
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
LISTENING
It's rumba time!
BY ISABELLE LEYMARIE
The deportation of millions of Africans to the Americas during the dark centuries of the slave
trade was one of the worst tragedies of history. It also gave rise to an extraordinary process of
cultural exchange. The story of the rumba shows this transatlantic cross-fertilization at work.
t Afro-American music began making its
way back from the Americas to African
shores in the 1920s. It had changed, and
returned in a creolized, hybrid form which
engendered stimulating new musical forms
such as mbaqanga in South Africa, juju in
Nigeria, "highlife" in Ghana and mbalax in
Senegal. At the same time, contemporary
Africanmusic, influenced by jazz, soul, funk,
rap, Cuban rhythms, reggae, beginne and
calypso began moving to the New World, bear¬
ing fertile seeds of change.
Much secular Afro-Latin and Afro-
Caribbean music is of Bantu origin, from
regions which once belonged to the ancient
kingdom of Kongo. American dances such as
chumbe, paracumbe, fandango, candombe,
yuka, makuta, samba and conga are all
danced to a regular drum beat with strong
hip gyrations and pelvic thrusts and can incon-
testably be traced back to Kongo sources.
The Congolese musician Rido Dieudonné
Bayonne (see box) has recently traced the
remarkable history of the rumba.
The rumba brava, which is derived from
fertility and war rituals, first appeared in Cuba
in the mid-nineteenth century. Today, it is still
danced in the poor neighbourhoods of Havana
and Matanzas, and in Cuban communities in
the United States. The dance has three vari¬
ants: theeroticguaguaucó, the yambu, which
is more buttoned up, and the acrobatic Colum¬
bia, which is usually a men-only dance. The
most popular version today is Úieguaguancó,
and its rhythms have been widely incorporated
into Latin jazz and salsa.
The birth of son
Some years later, a more hybrid rhythm known
as son was born in the rural areas of Cuba's
Oriente province. Spanish in origin, son has
become syncopated through contact with
Blacks. It was initially played using a mar im¬
buía (xylophone) or a tres (a type of guitar
with three double chords), a bongo and a
botija, a jug which the instrumentalist blows
into to produce sounds like a bass. Needy
musicians often made rough-and-ready 1res
out of packing boxes for codfish. Like samba
or calypso, son lyrics are a mine of broad and
satirical humour and constitute a juicy chron¬
icle of Cuban life.
Son took root in Havana in the early twen¬
tieth century. It was censored in the 1920s
during the dictatorship of Gerardo Machado
because it was regarded as too "African", but
it survived in the city's Black neighbourhoods.
Under the influence of jazz, the trumpet soon
became part of son combos, which were seven
strong and usually included two singers. Com¬
petitions were held among different groups
and occasionally degenerated into altercations
requiring police intervention.
In the 1920s, when the tango and popular
Mexican music were all the rage in the United
States, several American firms offered record¬
ing contracts toson groups. The Sexteto Occi¬
dente, the Septeto Habanero, the Septeto
Nacional and the Trio Matamoros all helped
win a reputation for this music which then
very quickly made its way into the homes of the
46
THE UNESCO COURIER 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Rido Bayonne
o on stage
Further reading and listening about slavery,
Rido Bayonne, and Afro-Cuban music:
Slavery: an Unpunished Crime, Unesco Courier, October 1994.
Interview with Rido Bayonne, in The Body and the Self,
Unesco Courier, April 1997.
"Gueule de Black," Rido Bayonne in concert,
DC Jazz aux Remparts, JAR 64008
La salsa et le latinjazz, by Isabelle Leymarie, Presses
universitaires de France ("Que sais-je?" series), Paris, 1993.
Du tango au reggae, Musiques noires d'Amérique latine
et des Caraïbes ("From the Tango to Reggae, Black Music of
Latin America and the Caribbean"),
by Isabelle Leymarie, Flammarion, Paris, 1996.
Cuban Fire. Musiques Populaires d'expression cubaine,
Isabelle Leymarie, Outremesure, Paris, 1996.
Musiques caraïbes, Isabelle Leymarie,
Actes Sud-Cité de la Musique, Paris, 1996.
white, Cuban middle class. Havana's elegant
clubs soon began ojtening their doors to son
musicians.
Together with rumba brava, son is still
highly popular among Cubans today, and is the
basis of the dance music known as salsa.
From rumba to soukous
At the same time, in Africa and particularly in
Congo and the former Zaire, where music lovers
hear the distant echo of their own musical her¬
itage in Cuban rhythms, many "Latin" bands
were created, their singers reproducing Span¬
ish lyrics phonetically without understanding
what they meant. Promoted under the more
commercially appealing name of "rumba", a
blend of son, West Indian beguine and indige¬
nous rhythms later gave rise to Zairean and
Congolese rumba. Just as anecdotal as its Cuban
cousin, this African rumba recounts the small
details of daily life, and praises the charms of
women and nature using the melodic scansion
of lingala (a Bantu language).
With the rise of Rock n' Roll and the pop¬
ularity of the twist in the 1960s Congolese
groups replaced their acoustic guitars with
electric guitars. Towards the end of the
decade, the soukous, a hippy dance that is
particularly suggestive when performed by
women, became more popular than the local
rumba. Influenced by soul and by the Chris¬
tian hymns introduced to Africa by mission¬
aries, sukous also underwent changes and
became more dynamic and more fundamen¬
tally African.
A festival of rumba
In April 1998, the Congolese composer, band-leader and multi-instrumentalist
Rido Bayonne is organizing a four-day music festival in the Paris suburb of Clichy
la Garenne to commemorate the abolition of slavery in the French colonies in 1848.
The event, entitled "Autour de la Rumba", will feature Cuban and Congolese
music, zouk, Senegalese reggae, hip hop, the art of African griots, and rhythm
and blues. There will also be a more surprising encounter between rumba and
baroque and classical music.
Rido Bayonne's Big Band Afro-Jazz, the Saint-Chaffre du Monastier Band
and a chamber orchestra will join forces for the first performance of Bayonne's
latest composition, Mémoires (Cause à effet) which is inspired by the transat¬
lantic musical saga.
West -African chordophones, Arabic drums, fifty horns and some 20 Western
string instrumentsviolins, cellos and basseswill all perform together. Five
flautists perched in a baobob tree will then play "a hymn to life and to the
spritual communion of the continents." Below them, female singers and dancers,
accompanied by guitar, piano, keyboard, drums, and other percussion instruments
will celebrate the latest forms of this creative blend of jazz, blues, sukuss,
calypso, reggae and rumba.
The slave trade and the upheavals it caused thus give way to a euphoric
musical marriage celebrated byeffervescentrhythms.Thisheartfeltand highly
personal tribute to African ancestors who were forced to make the journey to Amer¬
ica is also a hymn to human brotherhood brought together on this occasion by
the magic of art, and the artist's universal vision and creativity. I. L.
THE UNESCO C3ur| ER APRIL 1998
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
interview
Izet Sarajlic
'Poetry
is on the side
of love'
Poetry has been part of your life for half a
century. How do you see this art-form today?
Izet Sarajlic: I'm sorry to see that poetry has lost
the place it should occupy in people's lives, Poets
are partly responsible for this, but the spirit of
the age is also to blame. When I was young,
Neruda, Sartre, Malraux, Camus, Tuwim, Frost
and Ungaretti were the important writers. Living
in that world brought responsibilities as well as
pleasure; you had to surpass yourself. Imagine
having a poem published in a magazine next to
one by Neruda! We couldn't afford to be
mediocre. In today's literary world, it's not dif¬
ficult to pass yourself off as a poet. The poet will
soon belong to an extinct species. I fear that peo¬
ple will eventually stop reading us altogether.
Are you equally pessimistic about the future
of prose?
LS.: Yes, because I think that modern novelists
couldn't care less about that essential thing
known as love. I can't remember the last heroine
I fell in love with. The age of Anna Karenina is
gone for good. Today's novelists write against a
background of violence, and they want to shock
their readers. In modern novels there is a kind
of indifference, a failure to connect, whose causes
I cannot fathom. Is it because writers are trying
to appeal to the culture moguls who announce a
"new sensibility" every five years or so?
After the Sarajevo tragedy, I had the oppor¬
tunity to make several trips abroad. I was amazed
to see splendidly bound works by so many
nonentities displayed in bookshop windows.
There are so many bestsellers and so few great
writers. The era of great art is over. It seems as
though we've lost the joy of creation.
A Russian poet once said that even sadness is
joyful in your poetry. But your recent war poems
give the opposite impression.
LS.: The fact is that all values have been turned
IzetSarajlic is widely
regarded as Bosnia's greatest
living poet. A member of the
Bosnia and Herzegovina
Academy of Arts and Sciences,
he has published more than
15 collections of poetry and a
volume of memoirs. A volume
of his works was published in
English under the title Poetry
by Dist 136 Press,
Minneapolis, in 1975. His two
most recent books, written in
Sarajevo during the war, have
been translated into French as
Le livre des adieux and
Recueil de guerre sarajévien
(1997). Here he is interviewed
by Jasmina Sopova.
upside down, not only for me but for everybody.
All the old landmarks have gone. Immorality will
soon replace moral values and lies will replace truth.
This change has happened very quickly. If the
world had moved more slowly in this direction
(which actually leads to a dead end), people might
have had the time to prepare themselves psycho¬
logically. But this is impossible because of the
speed at which things are moving.
I feel that civilization took a wrong turning
about thirty years ago, as if the powers-that-be
had pointed it in a direction in which I can see no
future. It appals and depresses me that this utter
confusion is accepted as the normal human
condition.
Was it the war that changed your view of the
world?
LS.: To some extent, yes. I've always thought
that humanity needed responsible politicians
and that there were fewer and fewer of these. It's
no accident that the war which has destroyed my
former homeland should have happened at a
moment in history when there was no longer
anyone capable of giving a constructive turn to
political events and leading this poor world, so
rich in trivia and so poor in basics, into the
twenty-first century.
When foreigners who came to Sarajevo dur¬
ing the war asked me what I thought about the
West's attitude to Bosnia, I used to tell them
that while Tito had had the guts to stand up to
the might of Stalin, nobody today neither the
United States, nor France nor Germany is capa¬
ble of saying "no" to a local bandit.
The war also taught me something else. It
showed me that the behaviour of the world's
48 > GuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL I99B
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
thinkers is not only irresponsible but immoral.
And so was the conduct of some of the generals
stationed in Bosnia and Herzegovina. I'm think¬
ing of one of them in particular who was reported
to have raped young Muslim girls who were
brought to him in brothels. Everybody knew
about it. Everybody turned a blind eye.
The war also showed me the meaning of sol¬
idarity. We received great support from ordinary
people, especially in France, Italy and Switzer¬
land, and without it we would not have sur¬
vived. I used to think that the Swiss were people
who didn't show their feelings. Well, it was the
Swiss who showed us more kindness than any¬
one else.
Cultural life in Sarajevo was pretty dynamic,
wasn't it? Musical life, theatre and publishing all
went on.
LS.: The Latin saying whereby people fall silent
when the guns roar is false. Some very fine work
was produced in Sarajevo during the war. It would
be a good thing if foreigners could read some of
the stuff we wrote, so that they could under¬
stand that civil war is a plague, that it is conta¬
gious and that it could happen elsewhere in the
world, in an even more terrible form.
In one of your books, Recueil de guerre, you
say: "If I've survived all this it's thanks to poetry
and to a dozen or so people, ordinary folk, true
saints of Sarajevo, whom I hardly knew before the
war."
LS.: I wrote my two war books in my cellar as
shells whistled overhead. I couldn't, like Eluard,
paint the word "freedom" on the walls of Sara¬
jevo because no walls were left standing. So I said
to my wife: "Look at me, I am like a late twen¬
tieth-century Milton, writing a Paradise Lost oy
candlelight."
But I didn't start out with the idea of writ¬
ing poetry. I didn't care about poetry. It's a long
time since I was interested in poetry. Just before
the war, I wrote that the worst places for poetry
were the very places where poetry could be found.
When I said that poetry had saved me, I meant
that these extremely unhappy war years were per¬
haps the happiest years of my life as a poet. I was
motivated, I had readers, or rather listeners. We
had no paper for printing and I was not on close
terms with the few publishers who had any. In
any case, they specialized in pseudo-religious
work and propaganda, and so I wasn't very keen
on being published by them. Nevertheless, my
poems reached the public, which made me very
happy indeed. During the war, my literary and
moral standing in the eyes of my fellow citizens
seemed to be high. I saw that they wanted to
help me in one way or another. They would step
aside for me when we queued for water, although
'I am Muslim. My wife is
Catholic, herfamily came
from Austria, and our
daughter married an
Orthodox Christian.
I hope that my grandson
will put his hand on the
shoulder of a Jew.
That would complete
the family portrait.'
I naturally never took advantage of that, and
they would give me a cigarette, or an apple for my
grandson.
In those circumstances, poetry becomes
something different, doesn't it?
LS.: When a man has a dressing gown, when he
has enough to eat, when he can step out onto
his balcony, eat cherries or drink his coffee with
his own cigarette and not one he has had to beg
for, then he can think about aesthetics and aes-
theticism. But when he's surrounded by mis¬
ery and is a prey to it as well, when he finds him¬
self completely isolated and degraded, he asks
himself "Where are the simple, normal words?
Have they abandoned art ? "
I have had a portrait of one of my favourite
poets, Boris Pasternak, in my bedroom for a
long time. For me, it was a relic. It's still there,
despite the three million shells that have report¬
edly fallen on the city. One day, when I happened
to be in my bedroom and not down in the cel¬
lar, I looked at it and suddenly thought that even
he, the wonderful Pasternak, no longer meant
to me what he once did. So many fine words,
such perfect harmony, yet nothing about my
suffering, nothing about human suffering.
Has the war changed your poetry?
LS.: I don't think there's any fundamental dif¬
ference between what I wrote before and during
the war. The form may vary somewhat here and
there. When shells are bursting around you, you
have to get it down as quickly as you can, so you
don't pay much attention to form. In any case,
when you have something to say, the form
chooses itself. I'm not the kind of writer who
searches for a poem. A poet shouldn't do that. A
poem should search for and find its poet.
I haven't changed and I haven't felt any need
to. I got into poetry after World War II. In 1942,
the Italian fascists shot my older brother. In
everything I've done since, I've tried my hardest
not to betray the memory of that young man.
I'm now over fifty years older than he was then.
He's the person I'm answerable to.
In today's super-ideological age which repu¬
diates all previous ideologies, I stick to the posi¬
tion I chose at the end of what we now call the
"other" war, 1 939-45. That was a time when we all
believed that love could be revived and we
thought we had to write as if we were planting a
birch tree in the municipal park or fixing a door¬
bell to a door. We were all in favour of love and
remained faithful to it, except for some who
betrayed it during this recent war.
Do you think that such idealism is still
possible today?
LS.: I don't know. I can't think now the way I
> G>uiTHE UNESCO lOURIER APRIL 1998
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
did when I was young. I'm no longer capable of
being as generous as I was then. "Universal"
thoughts are far from my mind. My doorstep is
the limit of my world these days. I'm concerned
about my wife's health, my daughter's job, my
grandson's future.1 I'm eager to redecorate my
flat and put my bedroom in order. If I write a
poem or two amidst all that, well and good, but
If not, too bad. Perhaps I have written enough.
A French television programme about
Sarajevo and your family showed that part of your
flat had been seriously damaged.
LS.: One day, the Chetniks2 shelled my flat three
times. They thought they'd killed me, so they
stopped firing and went away. I received a blow
on the head and collapsed. When I came to, it
was quite funny. A painting had fallen on top of
me and I woke up with my head in the frame, like
a Rembrandt!
I've known you since I was a child but I've
never asked you about your religion.
LS.: I'm a Muslim. So what? I've never lived in a
predominantly religious environment any more
than any of my compatriots. I can't see people as
Orthodox or Muslim or whatever. Religion may
be important to some, but it's a personal matter.
I was in Strasbourg not long ago and I
couldn't understand why everyone kept insist¬
ing on the fact that I was Muslim. They told mc
that it was important to say so. I didn't consider
it to be important at all. In the same way, foreign
journalists who came to Sarajevo would often
ask me whether I thought that all these ethnic
groups could live together. I would always answer
by introducing my family to them and saying:
"My wife is Catholic, her family came from Aus¬
tria and our daughter married an Orthodox
Christian. I hope that fifteen years from now,
when the time comes for my grandson Vladimir
to experience the same kind of sufferings as
Goethe's young Werther, he will put his hand
on the shoulder of a Jew. That would complete
the family portrait."
Do you think that Bosnia has any future in the
present situation?
I.S.: I don't know. Like many people, rightly
or wrongly, I support the Dayton Agreements.
Yet I know that they are not the real solution.
The people who are deciding the fate of Bosnia
have not grasped the soul of the country, but
they talk with amazing glibness about corridors,
republics, federations, and so on.
There's one thing that the West doesn't
understand, or doesn't want to. In Spain, we saw
a dress rehearsal for Western fascism, and in
Bosnia we saw the same thing for Eastern Euro¬
pean fascism. In Spain, fascism came to power,
unfortunately; as luck would have it, ours did
not. But there is no proof that it has definitively
failed. Anything is possible today.
1. Mme Sarajlic passed away shortly after this interview was
completed. Editor
2. Serbian ultra-nationalists. Editor
AUTHORS
ROBERT G. BEDNARIK, of Australia, is the founder and Secretary of the Australian Rock Art Research Association (AURA) and
Convener of the International Federation of Rock Art Organizations (IFRAO). Among the journals he publishes are two leading
scientific periodicals, Rock Art Research and The Artefact.
EMMANUEL ANATI, of Italy, is Professor of Palaeo-Ethnology at the University of Lecce and Director of the Centra Camuno di Studi
Preistorici. He is the co-ordinator, on behalf of Unesco, of the WARA (World Archives of Rock Art) Project, and the author of many
scientific publications, including The Mountain of God: HarKakom (Rizzoli, New York, 1986) and World Rock Art. The Primordial
Language (Edizioni del Centra, Capo di Ponte, 1993).
DENIS VIALOU, of France, teaches at the Muséum National d'Histoire Naturelle in Pans, and conducts research at his country's
National Centre for Scientific Research (CNRS). He is the author of several books on prehistory, including La préhistoire and Au
ctur de la préhistoire, Chasseurs et artistes, published by Gallimard, Pans, in 1991 and 1996 respectively.
JEAN CLOTTES, a French prehistonan and high-ranking official in his country's heritage conservation service, is President of the
International Committee on Rock Art of the International Council on Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS). He is the author of many
publications, including The Cave Beneath the Sea. Paleolithic Images at Cosquer (with Jean Courtin, Abrams, 1996) and (with David
Lewis-Williams) Les chamanes de la préhistoire. Transe et magie dans les grottes ornées (Le Seuil, Paris, 1996).
FRANÇOIS SOLEILHAVOUP, a French geologist and natural science teacher, specializes in the geomicrobiology of rock surfaces. He
takes a special interest in the study, protection and conservation of the world's open-air rock-art sites and in education relating to
the world cultural and natural heritage. He has written several studies on subjects including the conservation of petroglyphs in
Kazakhstan and the rock art of the western Sahara.
AXEL and ANNE-MICHELLE VAN ALBADA, of Belgium, formerly taught and carried out research at Brussels Free University and
have for the last fifteen years been engaged in drawing up a comprehensive map of rock art in Libya's Messak region.
OSAGA ODAK, of Kenya, is a Professor of Anthropology at the University of Nairobi. He specializes in the study of rock art and
traditional technology and culture, and has published many articles and studies on these subjects.
HENRI MINCZELES is a French historian and journalist whose publications include Vilna, Wilno, Vilnius: La Jérusalem de Lituanie (La
Découverte publishers, Pans, 1993) and Histoire générale du Bund: un mouvement révolutionnaire juif (Austral, Pans, 1995).
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American journalist specializing in environmental topics.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE is a Franco-American musicologist whose publications include La musique sud-américaine, Rythmes et danses
d'un continent (Gallimard, Pans, 1997).
tb& unesco
Courier
^"^51stYEAR
Published monthly in 27 languages and in
Braille by Unesco, The United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin,
75732 Paris CEDEX 15, France
Fax- (33) (0) 1 45.68 57.45
e-mail: unesco.couner@unesco org
Internet, httpy/www unesco org
Director: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition: Araceli Ortiz de Urbma
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations Ariane Bailey (Tel. (33) (0)
1.45.68 46 90)
Documentation: José Banaag
(Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and
press' Solange Beim
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45.68.46.87)
Film duplication: Daniel Meister
Secretariat: Annie Brächet
(Tel. (33) (0)1 45 68 47 15),
Administrative Assistant. Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish
and Korean. (Tel (33) (0) 1.45 68 45 69)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German. Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian: Gianluca Fomnichi (Rome)
Hindi. Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jahl Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de
Janeiro)
Urdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay Sidm Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish. Rntta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egana (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Sunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician. Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de
Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax (33) (0)1.45.68 57 45
Subscriptions Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68.45 65), Jacqueline
Louise-Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed
Salah El Dm (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 49.19)
Customer service Michel Ravassard,
(Tel. (33) (0)1 45 68 45 91)
Accounts. (Tel (33) (0) 1.45.68.45.65)
Shipping: Daniel Meister
(Tel. (33) (0)1 45 68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel.: (33) (0) 1.45 68.45 65
1 year. 211 French francs. 2 years. 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries.
1 year: 132 French francs 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible
currency to the order of Unesco or by Visa,
Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
Unesco Courier", plus dale of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor Signed articles reprinted must
bear author s name Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon cov¬
ering postage Signed articles express the opinions o( the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier *
staff The boundaries on maps published in the magazine
do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco
or the United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fonienoy. 75700 Pans. (2) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100 U S A . (3) N C R Micro-
card Edition. Indian Head Inc . Ill West 40th Street. New
York, U S A : (4) Bell and Howell Co , Old Mansfield Road.
Wooster, Ohio 44691, USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - APRIL 1998
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ
PAR LES N.M P P.
Photocomposition, photogravure
Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression Maulde&Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 4-1998-0PI-98-5 70 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page
insert between pages 2-3 and 50-51
50
THE UNESCO lOURIER Al'RlL 1908
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Unesco on line via Internet
Currently on-line are: an index of the contents of the last
22 issues of the Unesco Courier, Unesco press releases,
addresses, fax, telex and electronic mail numbers of
Unesco's regional offices, National Commissions and Unesco
Clubs, the directory of Unesco databases and information
services, colour images of the Japanese Garden and other
architectural sites at Unesco Headquarters, as well as works
of art such as Henry Moore's reclining sculpture.
The world in your hands
World Heritage Review
From volcanoes, mountains and waterfalls to cities
rich in history and monuments that eloquently speak
of great cultures and civilizations, the quarterly
World Heritage Review chronicles the history, beauty
and singularity of sites on the World Heritage List.
Learn about these destinations and keep informed of
efforts under way to preserve our natural and cultural
heritage. A superb gift for readers of all ages, professions
and continents with an interest in preserving humanity's
treasures.
SUBSCRIPTION FORM
World Heritage Review
i
t
YES, I wish to subscribe to the World Heritage Review
1 year (4 issues)
140 FF/£18/US$28 plus airmail charges:
-O EU: 64FF/£8.15/US$13
-O Other European countries: 72 FF/£9.15/US$14.65
-»O Other countries: 96FF/£12.20/US$19.65
Full name:
Address:
City and postcode:
Country:
© World Heritage! ©Irld Heritage
©World Heritage:
© World Heritage
Payment enclosed:
Cheque
-»O Visa "KD Eurocard MasterCard
Diners ~*0 American Express
Card No.:
Expiry date:
Subscription forms and payment (cheques payable to Jean De
Lannoy) should be sent to UNESCO Publishing's subscription
agent:
Jean de Lannoy, Service abonnements
Avenue du Roi, 202
B-1190 Brussels (Belgium)
Tel: (+32 2) 538 51 69/538 43 08; fax: (+32 2) 538 08 41.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
H'S ISSUE:
,
HERITAGE
]]>
</page>
</document>
