<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="111704eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Progress, risk and responsibility
ENERGY:
WINDS OF CHANGE
UNITED KWOBO» Il Fmu«E: UFT «UÏTHAUJl: MI.» - lELCIUM VIH CIMUt CM.7* - »»A: MM (MlWHAN* *t*- HKnmmjm*: H 1» DUMM«. «
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (OURIER NikOSl INTERNATIONAL PHOTO COMPETITION
PEACE IN EVERYDAY LIFE
A selection of photos entered in the competition will be featured on this page in forthcoming issues.
The Leap. Sâo Paulo (Brazil).
Photo by Lorry Salcedo-Mitrani (Peru).
Presumed by his family to have been killed in the war,
Papa is greeted by his younger brother as he returns to his new home (Liberia).
Photo by Rip Hopkins (United Kingdom).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO lOURIER contents
MAY 1998
Progress, risk and responsibility
47
Marcel Marceau
The great French mime talks about his craft
and the highlights ofhis career.
HERITAGE
42
The Monastery of Haghpat (Armenia)
.4 centre oj Armenian Christianity and <tn
architectural masterpiece.
Science and social responsibility	4
by Georges B. Kutukdjian
Energy: a fair deal for all 8
by Jean Audouze
The right to know	14
by Nicholas A. Ashford
The ethics of conservation
1. The natural world 18
2. The cultural heritage	21
by Gordon Bennett and Nikita Lopoukhine
How predictable is nature? 23
by Jens Erik Fenstad
Genetic testing and discrimination	29
by Michael Kirby
Fact file	34
The Universal Declaration on the Human Genome and Human Rights
Consultant: Georges B. Kutukdjian
Commentai-}' Federico Mayor
GREENWATCH Renewable energy: winds of change by France Bequette
36
38
LISTENING Dizzy Gillespie, a jazz giant by Isabelle Leymarie 45
Cover:
Oil painting by the American artist Theo Rudnak.
©Theo Rudnak/SIS Pans
AU1THORS
EUNLSCO ÇoURICR MAY 1908 %
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
> Science and social
responsibility BY GEORGES B. KUTUKDJIAN
The ethical implications of scientific progress concern everyone
L Today there is a certain degree of disil¬
lusionment about science, especially in
the industrially developed countries. Science
and scientific progress arc indeed raising urgent
questions, for example in the field of genetics.
Who should determine the priorities and
choices of science and technologies and on the
basis of which social goals ? How can we define
democratically the risks which can be consid¬
ered as "acceptable"? What is the level of
responsibility and solidarity which can be
expected from individuals and groups in rela¬
tion to both present and future generations?
The answers to these questions go beyond
the narrow confines of professional practice
and national borders. In a multipolar world
characterized by an unprecedented splinter¬
ing of perceptions, it is more than ever neces¬
sary to strive for the emergence of values which
will make our common existence technologi¬
cally, ecologically and socially viable.
Such ethical reflection calls for a free and
open exchange of experience and ideas among
decision-makers, specialists and representa¬
tives of the civil society, in all its diversity, in
order to identify the issues, set points of ref¬
erence and advocate a range of forward-look¬
ing alternatives.
The development of science must hence¬
forth be examined in a new framework. At
the end of the twentieth century, the "battle¬
field" has become primarily one of economic
warfare, and economies are increasingly being
dominated by scientific knowledge, tech¬
nologies and information. What has to be
done is to develop new forms of knowledge
and share them. Sharing knowledge goes
together with sharing responsibilities. Science
needs to be perceived as a liberating force.
At the same time, wc cannot overlook the
gap between the state of science in the developed
and developing countries. Some of the dcvel-
This model at a research
centre in Faridpur
(Bangladesh) is used to study
flood patterns. The results will
be helpful in designing and
building flood-control
barrages.
> QuTHE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1098
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
1
oping countries are facing crucial choices. Should
the State devote its resources to science or should
it tackle more urgent problems such as access to
drinking water, for example? It should be
recalled that industrial research is non-existent in
the developing countries and that some of them
do not allocate even one per cent of their gross
national product (GNP) to science. For exam¬
ple, there is no research centre for industrial
chemistry in any developing country. Mean¬
while, the industrially developed countries seem
to be suffering the consequences of the lack of
flexibility that characterizes their unwieldy
research institutions. It is as if the ability of sci¬
ence to create wealth were a burden on its own
organization. These cumbersome and adminis¬
tration-oriented structures are discouraging
investment by the industrial sector.
Digital composite image
showing a biochemist using a
virtual reality system to
investigate molecular
interactions.
This is why there is a need to work out
new strategies of scientific development. It is
necessary to establish flexible structures of
international co-operation and to turn science
into an "international undertaking", for exam¬
ple through partnership programmes and by
tightening the links between research work in
all countries through conferences, publica¬
tions, networks, the use of new information
and communication technologies.
It can be seen today that there is a profound
failure of understanding between laboratory
science and the general public. This failure often
stems from a lack of knowledge and is based on
mistrust and fear: research workers sometimes
have a dehumanizing and reductionist view of
the public and, at the same time, the public is
becoming increasingly wary of science.
> QuTHE UNESCO lOURIER MAY I09B
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Scarcity of resources forces
some developing countries to
make the painful choice
between investing in research
and tackling more pressing
problems. Right, a genetics-
microbiology laboratory in
Harare (Zimbabwe).
The public increasingly expects that major
engineering works, in particular those involv¬
ing technological hazards, should be preceded
by comprehensive, stringent and independent
technology assessment studies. These studies
should take into account unavoidable tech¬
nological risks, which cannot be altogether
eliminated but must be reduced to a mini¬
mum, and should also address the question of
hazard management. Their results should be
made public in accessible form.
Transparency, truth and trust
The three Ts in this exercise are: transparency,
truth and trust. Of course, transparency is
time-consuming, but it is an essential ingre¬
dient of trust. This is also the case of truth.
Misinformation or half-truths fuel rumours,
induce fears and discredit those responsible
for public information.
Accumulated experience illustrates that
information provided in an impartial way is
generally rewarded by responsible behaviour
by the population concerned. This is particu¬
larly true in the case of the prevention and
management of natural disasters, where
UNESCO has acquired some expertise.
Surveys show that this is also true in the
medical field, in particular in genetics. In fact,
such a trustful relationship can stimulate the
creativity of a population in response to a new
and unexpected situation. Of course, a number
of international guidelines and directives
adopted by intergovernmental bodies, address¬
ing these issues, exist; for instance in experi¬
mentation on human subjects or clinical tri¬
als, not to mention national Parliamentary
legislation.
The safety issue is closely linked to the
principle of precaution. (See article page 23.)
More specifically, there is a felt need for edu¬
cation and information of the public at large,
starting with the populations directly con¬
cerned. Mechanisms that guarantee the
informed participation of the public should be
devised. To be effective, these mechanisms
must rely on the local authorities and involve
leading figures of the civil society, as well as
associations, consumer groups and other non¬
governmental organizations which have a key
role to play in this area provided they arc
involved from the inception of the project.
Public debate can only enhance a democra¬
tic process very much needed in this area. The
road lies before us, and if there is still a long
way to go, wc know the indispensable provi¬
sions needed for the journey. One such pro¬
vision is a strategy of communication, in order
to ascertain comprehensive information and a
sense of solidarity.
Appropriate communication can only be
based on accurate information, including that
concerning uncertainties when these exist. Nev¬
ertheless, it would be illusory to think that
irrationality can be completely eliminated; it
can only be reduced. As a matter of fact, irra¬
tionality, nurtured by ill-understanding, can
L UNESCO ÇoURILR MAY tlvo
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Training farmers in Togo.
be built into a rational argument. This is an ele¬
ment which has often been overlooked.
The most topical example of the need for
ethical safeguards in regard to scientific
progress lies in the field of genetics. This exam¬
ple reminds us of the ambiguity of science,
which is one of the most powerful ingredients
of societies. Today wc can no longer close our
eyes to the ethical issues implicit in science. It
is no longer possible to envisage an ethical neu¬
trality of knowledge that would be indepen¬
dent of its subsequent applications. Thus, the
General Conference of Unesco, on 11
November 1997, adopted a Universal Decla¬
ration on the Human Genome and Human
Rights. This Universal Declaration provides a
NASA scientists set up
equipment to measure gases
that will be given off during
the burning of a deforested
area in the Amazon (Brazil).
consistent and comprehensive set of ethical
principles which should guide both research
and applications of research findings in biol¬
ogy and medicine. (See page 34.)
We also need to be able to think out the
conditions of ethical control over discovery.
Scientific institutions have a responsibility
with regard to the environment of research
workers and must ensure that research is gov¬
erned not solely by the lure of gain but also by
the desire to protect life and cater to the wel¬
fare of human beings.
Finally, science can no longer be regarded as
the repository of truth. Science docs not state
mere certainties. It constantly challenges itself.
It is in the balance between doubt and cer¬
tainty that the ethics of science places its role.
Scientific knowledge no longer depends on
the genius of human beings, it calls for gigan¬
tic resources, both human and technological.
Hence scientists themselves recognize the
importance of the social acceptability of their
undertakings. The level of acceptability relics
heavily upon a balance of measured risks and
unwarranted risks. And present societies have
a clear perception of the need to establish pri¬
orities, even when the alternatives are not
always clearly defined.
This situation places new responsibilities
upon the scientist, the engineer, private and pub¬
lic decision-makers (in particular in the indus¬
trial sector) and the citizen. These responsibili¬
ties can only be assumed through discussion
and the construction of common values.
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY l<398
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
>>.
Wí
i
J. Guichard/Sygma, Pans
> Energy: a fair deal for all
BYJEANAUDOUZE
Both the supply of energy and the
demand for it have spiralled in modern
societies, where everyday life and changes to the
environment, global as well as local, are con¬
ditioned by energy production and use. At
the same time, there are more than a billion
people in the world with an income of less
than a dollar a day, and more than two bil¬
lion rely on firewood as their sole source if
any of energy. There is a crying need for a
fairer share-out of material goods, energy and
economic resources.
Energy comes in three forms: so-called
"fossil" fuels (coal, oil and natural gas); nuclear
power; and "renewable" energies (hydroelec
tric power, thermal or photovoltaic solar
energy, wind and tide power, wood, etc.). Each
of these has its own undeniable advantages
and drawbacks.
Fossilfuels
Fossil fuels are abundant and very simple to
use. Oil, for example, can be very easily trans¬
ported and processed, and is relatively cheap.
The technology for producing its many deriv¬
atives is highly developed. What's more, it is
particularly well suited for use in all forms of
land, sea and air transport. Its handy fluid
form and its price make it appropriate to the
> G"THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 19*8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
I.
&S*$E
World energy resources are inequitably distributed.
The author of a Unesco report on the ethics of energy suggests
ways of righting the balance.
I
"-^J
Above, White Cliffs solar
power plant, New South Wales
(Australia).
Right, gathering firewood near
Lake Abaya in southwestern
Ethiopia.
1 TOE or "tonne oil
equivalent" is the energy
supplied by the combustion
of one tonne of oil. G stands
for giga = one billion, 109.
needs of poor communities or those that are
unable to invest in capital goods.
Fossil fuels account at present for 77 per
cent of all the energy produced and will,
according to the most realistic projections,
still account for 73 per cent in 2020. Worldwide
annual consumption of coal, natural gas and
oil stands, respectively, at 2.3, 1.7 and 2.7
GTOE.1 Proven reserves at 1990 consumption
levels stand at 200 years for coal, 40 for oil and
60 for natural gas. These figures may be mul¬
tiplied by between two and five if improve¬
ments in productivity and efficiency and the
exploitation of the last remaining deposits,
such as those of oil shales, are taken into
account. The resources will be strictly limited
geographically as well as in duration, being
restricted to certain regions such as the Gulf
and the Caspian Sea. This state of affairs is
fraught with the risk of tensions and even
conflicts, owing to the strategic importance
of energy supplies.
Fossil fuels are, furthermore, responsible
for the man-made increase in the carbon diox¬
ide content of the earth's atmosphere, with the
associated danger of an increase in the green¬
house effect and, as a direct result, global warm¬
ing of the order of Io to 4° C in the next twenty
years, which would adversely affect the climate
and the environment. Though much uncer¬
tainty remains as to the scale of these effects, the
risk is great enough to mean that every effort
should be made to slow down the increasing
"carbonization" of the atmosphere due to the
intensive use of fossil fuels.
Nuclearpower
The main advantage of nuclear power is that it
has no effect on the carbon dioxide content of
the atmosphere. As it is also cheaper (per
energy unit) than hydroelectric or thermal
energy, some countries, France for instance,
have opted strongly for this way of produc¬
ing electricity.
THE UNESCO ^>UR1ER MAY 1998 *
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Nuclear power is, however, far from being
unanimously accepted. Public opinion is very
conscious of the lack of candid information
and of the safety of nuclear plants, two aspects
that have not always been treated, in some coun¬
tries, with all the necessary care and clarity by
the authorities and the operators. The public is
also worried about the disposal of long-lasting
radioactive wastes, an acute problem to which
the experts seem confident that a long-term
solution can be found. It would also be a mis¬
take to underestimate the danger of the spread
of nuclear arms, even though the main powers
are now significantly reducing their arsenals of
these weapons. A final point is that only those
countries which can afford to make the huge
investments required can put nuclear plants
into operation. The investment is offset by the
low cost of the fuel but is recouped only in
the medium and long term.
Renewable energy sources
The ecological movements, which arc worried
both by global warming and by the real or imag¬
ined dangers of nuclear power, would like renew¬
able energy sources to be developed faster than
is now the case. These forms of energy at present
supply some 1 8 per cent of total demand, which
puts them well ahead of nuclear power.
Technology is moving rapidly forward in
this field. Thanks to technical improvements,
the price of energy produced by photovoltaic
cells, for instance, is due to fall from $5 per
kilowatt-hour in 1990 to $0.5-0.8 by 2010.
These forms of energy arc capable of meet¬
ing the needs of communities that it would be
too expensive to connect to a central grid sup¬
ply, but despite improved productivity and
falling costs, they remain on the whole dearer
than the two previous forms. It will be a long
time before they can constitute the main
source of supply. Other problems that remain
to be solved include the major investments
required for hydroelectric power stations and
the environmental damage caused by the build¬
ing of dams and wind farms.
We must face the fact that as of now there
is no "miracle" energy that is risk-free for
humans and their environment and is also
cheap and inexhaustible. There is no such thing
as absolute security as regards power generation
and use, and it will not be possible in the
future to do without any of the above-men-
Making batteries for electric
cars in Bordeaux (France).
he unesco Courier may i
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
tioned sources. Energy demand will continue
to grow as a result of irreversible technologi¬
cal advances, of the justified demands of the
non-industrialized countries, and of popula¬
tion growth that is in any case set to continue
for at least the next fifty years.
Demonstrators protest
against the shipment of
nuclear waste to Gorleben
(Germany) in 1997.
Some ethicalprinciples
A number of imperatives must thus be borne
in mind by every individual, every nation and,
in particular, the citizens of the industrialized
countries. These are: the right of each indi¬
vidual to sufficient sources of energy; our
responsibility towards our children and our
children's children; protection of the envi¬
ronment; prevention of the potential major
risks from the production of energy on a mas¬
sive scale; the control of costs and the need to
carry on with research in all these fields.
Some of these obligations those relating to
population growth, climate change or the dis¬
posal of nuclear wastes, for example are of a
very long-term nature, while others efforts to
deal with pollution caused by road transport or
chemical waste disposal are short-term. These
differences of time-scale and the various possi¬
ble interactions between the quantitative and
qualitative aspects of the question have to be
taken into account in observations of an ethi¬
cal character such as the following:
*~ The present situation, whereby nearly one
person in four in the world is without access
to the energy resources he or she requires, can¬
not be accepted with resignation. Those with
an active role in world energy policy deci¬
sion-makers, industrialists, research workers
and so forth must ultimately ensure that
there exist, and continue to exist, sufficient
resources of sufficiently cheap energy for all
countries to have access to them, regardless of
their geographical or economic situation. It is
accordingly essential that genuine co-opera¬
tion in energy matters be established on a
sound basis between the countries of North
and South.
*" There should be no pretext for unnecessar¬
ily keeping the countries of the South, which
u rgently need proper infrastructures, on short
commons as regards energy use. This is one
area where, more than in any other, people
THE UNESCO (ouiIRIIR MAY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
A solar dryer in Ghana.
need to be informed, so that they can take part
in discussion and decision-making on subjects
where scientific and technological knowledge is
essential.
*" Our duty to future generations enjoins us
to use energy resources as sparingly and ratio¬
nally as possible, especially as wc know that a
major part of these resources may be exhausted
in a century or two. Wc must also take collec¬
tive action to avoid creating irreversible situ¬
ations with regard to the environment and
energy management. We must take particular
care to apply the "precautionary principle" so
as to avoid causing too great an increase in
atmospheric carbon dioxide, to be careful and
economical in our output and use of energy,
and to do all we can to prevent any event with
irreparable consequences from occurring.
Even though rapid progress is being made in
the exploration of space, wc must acknowledge
the obvious fact that we have only one Earth and
must therefore preserve and protect it. Since
energy production and use may jeopardize our
environment, there is an urgent need for appro¬
priate measures to be taken as rapidly and as
effectively as possible. The management of
nuclear waste and campaigns to combat all forms
of pollution arising from energy use constitute
unconditional obligations in this connection.
*~ Whenever massive quantities of nuclear or
other forms of energy are produced or trans¬
ported, e.g. when oil is transported by sea or
big dams arc built, major risks to life and
health ensue. Absolute safety is unattainable,
but the various energy authorities arc never¬
theless under an obligation to issue and enforce
appropriate safety regulations. These precau¬
tions should be applied to the two risk situ¬
ations just mentioned and should also cover
everyone working in the power-generating
industry, especially those employed at nuclear
and major hydroelectric plants.
Unit cost will continue to be the main fac¬
tor influencing the choice between different
forms of energy. Production costs must be
controlled and savings constantly sought if
energy supplies are to be available to all. In the
case of nuclear power, the costs arising from
safety procedures and the decommissioning
of plants should be taken into account.
*~ Research sometimes seems to have been
neglected in work on energy production and
consumption, but it is an indispensable duty.
Efforts to find new sources of energy and
1 > G>uiTHE UNtSCO I OUR1ER MAY 1 998
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
more economical ways of using it must con¬
tinue. One example is the use of natural gas,
which is in itself a vast field for research. Other
priority areas for research include technolo¬
gies for producing nuclear power fast breeder
reactors, energy-boosting systems, ther¬
monuclear plants, etc. and waste disposal
systems. Efforts must also be made to reduce
the cost of renewables. The industrialized
countries must give effective support to
research in the developing countries and show
them how to maintain their energy facilities.
Further recommendations
We must keep our eyes open for the early
warning signs of potentially dangerous or irre¬
versible situations, and react quickly to them.
Application of the "precautionary princi¬
ple" remains an unconditional obligation. Wc
must take economic and fiscal measures
designed to avert the risks of tension between
producers and consumers and to encourage
proper control of the resource in question.
The tax instrument should be used to rcdis-
Indigenous people of the
Amazon at the 1992 United
Nations Conference on
Environment and Development
in Rio de Janeiro (Brazil).
tribute resources between privileged and less
privileged groups of the population.
The man and woman in the street and their
elected representatives must be informed about
everything relating to the production and con¬
sumption of every kind of energy. Parliaments
should have their own scientific and techno¬
logical evaluation services, as is the case in certain
countries such as France. Projections made on the
basis of different economic and demographic
hypotheses ought to be regularly updated.
Last but not least, systems must be created
to enable internationally enforceable measures to
be taken. The environmental balance sheet drawn
up by the United Nations five years after the Rio
Summit was, inevitably, an admission of failure
and reflected the deep disappointment aroused
by governments' inability to engage in dialogue
and undertake joint action.
Now it is realized that no form of energy
can replace any other form, we must endeav¬
our to preserve the balance between producers
and consumers, between rich and poor coun¬
tries, and between those that are spendthrift
and those that arc thrifty.
lííf
E UNESCO (7>URIER MAY 19Q8
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
^The right to know BY NICHOLAS A. ASHFORD
What are the legal and ethical responsi¬
bilities of industrial enterprises when
communities and workers arc at risk from the
sudden and accidental releases of toxic and/or
radioactive substances into the atmosphere?
Well-known examples of such incidents
occurred at Seveso (Italy) in 1973, at Bhopal in
India in 1984, at the Three Mile Island (Penn¬
sylvania) nuclear power plant in 1 979, at Cher¬
nobyl in Ukraine in 1985, off Alaska in 1989
and the French coast in 1978 due to oil spills
from the supertankers Exxon Valdez and
Amoco Cadiz, as well as a large number of
chemical production and petroleum refining
catastrophes.
Such events sometimes engender legislative
responses. The passage of the U.S. Emergency
Planning and Community Right-to-Know
Act (1986) and the so-called first and second
Seveso Directives of the European Union
(1982) are examples. In the United States, the
Clean Air Act Amendments of 1990 require
increased attention to the risks of sudden and
accidental releases, placing obligations on both
government and on industrial firms.
Democratic risk management
Right-to-know, the mandatory sharing of
information between management, workers,
and the community, embodies a democrati¬
zation of risk management decisions.
Early right-to-know legislation in the
THE UNESCO Q)URI
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
United States and elsewhere addressed workers'
and communities' right to know scientific
information about the ingredients in chemicals
and materials used in production, waste con¬
tent, actual chemical releases to the environ¬
ment, and information about exposure to grad¬
ual, expected pollution. But technological
information about potential system failures,
unexpected chemical reactions and releases, and
ameliorative control technology is also needed,
and here, right-to-know legislation is more
recent and less adequate. While risk manage¬
ment plans requiring "worst case scenarios" to
be explored by firms are increasingly common,
obligations to identify superior, inherently
safer technologies are notably absent. In addi¬
tion, much of the important information is
held closely by industrial firms and is not
shared with either workers or the community.
The relevant rights and obligations under
right-to-know fall into three categories.
*" The duty to generate and/or retain infor¬
mation, i.e. a firm's obligation to compile and
The public's right to be informed about risks of
industrial accidents and man-made catastrophes is still
far from fully recognized
retain a record of certain facility-based events
such as near misses or system failures.
*" The right ofaccess (and the corresponding
duty to disclose upon request), i.e. the right of
a worker, union, community member or
agency to request information and access to
information held by a manufacturer or
employer.
*" The duty to inform, i.e. the firm's obligation
to disclose, without request, information
needed by government, workers, and com¬
munities to understand the potential risks of
sudden and accidental releases; to assess the
adequacy of in-placc technology and human
resources that can prevent, minimize or address
Alaska (U.S.A.), May 1989: the tne consequences of those risks; and to iden-
battle against the oil slick tify the technological options that could have
discharged after the . . . .
supertanker Exxon Valdez ran been adopted but were not.
aground.
Conflict analysis
The law establishes legal rights and provides
remedies to correct their violation. But it also
recognizes that conflicts of legitimate interests,
conflicts of legal duties, and differences in per¬
ception of what is right or wrong, fair or unfair,
require an appropriate balancing in the fash¬
ioning of remedies. Indeed, there are both legal
Hydraulic engineering class in
a Chinese university.
E UNESCO Courier may 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Chemical spillage training
(Malaysia).
iv remedies (usually of statutory origin) and equi¬
table remedies that give great discretionary
power to the courts or adjudicating institu¬
tions. In examining questions of conflict, the
law views behaviour in the context of relation¬
ships, and will sometimes find a duty when
none was intended by original legal arrange¬
ments, because it was reasonable that workers
or the community expected certain behaviour
on the part of an industrial enterprise.
The law does not, however, always serve
the ethical interests of society so nobly. Leg¬
islation and legal institutions can be compro¬
mised by powerful special interests. In addi¬
tion, if there is a lack of societal consensus or
interest about a moral issue, the law may cither
not address that issue or fail to give helpful
guidance concerning the boundaries of fair or
equitable behaviour. Thus, it is important to
engage in both a legal and ethical enquiry con¬
cerning human and institutional behaviour.
16
In the context of the risk management of
low probability, high catastrophic events, legal
and ethical norms are in a state of consider¬
able flux. Conflicts of interest and conflicts of
duty (for example, for the corporate or gov¬
ernment official in charge of protecting the
community and workers) abound. Just how
much should workers and the community be
told? Given the arguable scientific uncertainty
of constructing worst-case scenarios for sud¬
den and accidental releases, questions of what
risk communication activities and preventive
actions to take or not to take may reflect dif¬
ferences in perceptions of fairness and
risk-averscness. In possible contrast, a duty
on the part of industrial firms to identify and
implement superior, inherently safer tech¬
nology that would both reduce the risks of
sudden and accidental releases and bestow cost
savings on the firms themselves, would seem
to be morally irrefutable.
THE UNESCO ÇpURI ER MAY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Students in Zanzibar are
taught how to dispose of
agricultural chemicals as part
of a Netherlands Council of
World Development project.
Internal conflicts among the duties of var¬
ious stakeholders (firm and government offi¬
cials, workers, community residents) can lead
to psychological distress and sometimes to
unethical behaviour. Community residents
may feel torn between a duty to be well
informed (so as to anticipate and respond
appropriately to danger) and a duty to main¬
tain their own peace of mind (which is con¬
ducive to rational thought) and present a calm
exterior for the benefit of their families.
Environmental and public health profes¬
sionals have experienced conflicts between their
duties to prevent panic in the community and
to inform the public of potential danger, as
well as between the duties associated with their
roles as scientists, wage earners, public servants
and employees of a particular branch of gov¬
ernment. Other individuals who work for
governmental agencies have experienced con¬
flicts as a result of their multiple roles as pro¬
moters and regulators of a particular industry,
such as nuclear energy.
Conflicts arise from the relative significance
of "subjective" versus "objective" informa¬
tion and from the nature and degree of uncer¬
tainty, error, and/or risk that is tolerable.
Community residents, workers, and agency
professionals may disagree about priorities:
residents and workers worry about experts'
ability to assess and control risk, while
"experts" fret about citizens' and workers'
"unreasonable demands" for certainty. All the
members of a group will not necessarily share
the same views on these matters. Conflicts
occur between those trained and socialized in
a technical field and those who identify more
closely with humanistic traditions.
Anxiety and stress affect key figures who
are faced with unprecedented situations, scien¬
tific uncertainty, and a need to make decisions
quickly. Since the catastrophic incidents men¬
tioned above, professionals have acquired expe¬
rience and received specialized training. Never¬
theless, in the political controversies that
develop and the continuing scientific uncer¬
tainty surrounding sudden and accidental
releases of toxic substances, government officials
and professionals still find their personal moral
integrity threatened. Workers or residents of
communities where a dramatic accident has
recently occurred, arc generally not well pre¬
pared to cope and can be expected to respond
emotionally and with confusion. They need
to be treated in a non-patronizing way like any
other victims of natural disasters, with under¬
standing, patience and counselling.
As risks become more uncertain and seri¬
ous, the case for fuller partnerships between
industrial firms and their workers or commu¬
nities concerning risk management options
becomes stronger and more ethically imperative.
Shared decision making
Participation by members of the affected com¬
munities is an essential element in construct¬
ing ethically-sound risk management deci¬
sions. This can be facilitated in a number of
ways, notably including the utilization of
advisory panels.
A variety of possible technical and legal
interventions is available, from minor to major
changes to plant and production, from train¬
ing existing personnel to hiring new profes¬
sionals, from adopting specific legal require¬
ments to suggesting administrative processes.
Both new laws and institutions and informal
ad hoc mechanisms are needed to involve the
affected public and other key actors more fully
in risk management involving sudden and acci¬
dental releases of toxic and radioactive sub¬
stances. In general, the earlier that people are
involved, the more effectively adverse effects
and loss of trust arc likely to be avoided or
minimized. Firms, government, communities
and workers have begun to explore ways to
address the problems. Law provides little
structure at this time, but the ethical and moral
imperatives remain.
THE UNESCO CpllR,ER MAY 199S J
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
>The eu
1. The natural world
BY GORDON BENNETT AND NIKITA LOPOUKHINE
tion
The creation of protected natural areas raises a host of dilemmas
Nature is in a state of constant flux. It
I is shaped over time by dynamic natural
processes such as flooding, fire, wind, volca¬
noes and climate, and in response to these
forces some physiographic features, species
and ecosystems have disappeared and others
have evolved. People, of course, have also
played an integral part in this process, and in
recent times modern technology has dramat¬
ically increased the scope of human influence.
Change is inevitable, but how should we
respond to it? There arc generally three
options. First, a "laissez-faire" or natural reg¬
ulation approach to the management of natural
resources. A more commonly exercised option
is to channel or even arrest change by "active
management", an option frequently associ¬
ated with wildlife, water and forest managers
who are chiefly concerned with the extraction
of resources, although it may also be used to
compensate for damage to natural processes
or for extirpated species. A third option, also
a form of active management, is to try to
restore conditions which once existed or even
create new assemblages of plants, animals and
physiographic features, e.g. creating wetlands
where none previously existed. The ethical
choices facing managers of protected areas arc
intricately linked with all three options.
Systems of protected areas are usually estab- I
lished to embody a country's varied landscape |
in accordance with a bioregional framework. |
For various reasons representation of a biorc- |
gion's full variety is not always a realistic objec- I
tive within a protected area. The size of pro- I
tcctcd areas, their configuration, and the lack of j
< -^
Air view of a tourist complex
in Lanzarote, one of the
Canary Islands (Spain).
Lanzarote has been the site of
a Unesco biosphere reserve
since 1993.
> ÇsuTHE UNESCO lOURIER MAY (991
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
"*"£
N-«
V ..'
Hinchinbrook Island National
Park (Australia).
linkage to other protected arcas all add to the dif¬
ficulty of maintaining representation over time.
Nevertheless, it is often possible to approach
representation by choosing sites that are rela¬
tively undisturbed or that have the necessary
potential. An important aspect of this approach
is to write a goal or purpose statement that
declares the level of desired representation.
Islands in an unfriendly
environment
Most of the world's protected areas are sur¬
rounded by land that is used in ways inimical to
them and are subject to long-range as well as
local influences. The trajectory of a protected
area's ecosystems is likely to be deflected away
from the originally defined representation val¬
ues, and in response the park manager is faced
with choosing cither to ignore the changes or to
address them through one of the options noted
above. The "laissez-faire" option abandoning
the area to the vagaries of influences within and
outside it is, in effect, an acceptance of change.
The ethical dimension of a "laissez-faire"
approach is to determine whether the original
intention to achieve biorcgional representation
and the biodiversity associated with this goal
are placed in jeopardy and whether the outcome
is appropriate. For example, to permit a forest or
prairie fire to burn or to have ungulates prolif¬
erate unchecked has significant consequences on
the biodiversity of a protected area.
It is not our intention here to judge
whether the consequences are good or bad but
to point out that change will occur even when
the decision not to intervene is made. Ethics
here require the manager to be forthright in
THE UNESCO Courier I MAY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
providing information on the consequences of
a decision, even a "laissez-faire" decision. The
notion that natural regulation will manage the
protected area does not absolve the manager
from the responsibility of setting objectives. It
is impossible to determine the success of a par¬
ticular management regime unless the changes
arc forecast in advance, debated, agreed upon
by stakeholders and finally set as objectives.
The second option attempting to mini¬
mize change by setting fires, culling, mowing,
girdling, or modifying water flow regimes
raises more fundamental ethical questions:
what right do wc have to alter nature to meet
our objectives? Does the manager of a pro¬
tected area, of all places, have the right to dom¬
inate nature? Are the objectives of conserving
the genetic values, structures and functions of
ecosystems a good enough reason to inter¬
vene? Even if one answers in the affirmative,
the question immediately arises of deciding
which genetic values, structure and functions
are appropriate. The matter becomes a debate
between biocentric and anthropocentric val¬
ues between what might be called "deep ecol¬
ogy" and utilitarianism.
Open discussions
In the past century, the rationale for estab¬
lishing protected areas has moved steadily away
from the utilitarian to the biocentric. The ini¬
tial motivation was to create places which peo¬
ple could enjoy. Later, protected areas grew in
number as societies wished to absolve them¬
selves from guilt over destroying the envi¬
ronment while also responding to economic
opportunities. Today, the ideas of ecological
integrity, biodiversity conservation and biorc-
gional representation are the driving forces
behind the establishment of protected areas.
These goals provide a framework within which
appropriate ecosystem structures and func¬
tions can be defined. Nevertheless, to be assured
of continued support, open discussions on
management objectives must take place. In
these discussions, it may very well be that the
best way of defending proposed objectives
and goals is to present the alternatives to them.
In simple terms, would it be acceptable to con¬
sciously decide to have biodiversity values
decline, lose ecological integrity, and witness
the decline of ecosystem health?
The third option for managing protected
A ranger in Kluane National
Park, southwest Yukon
(Canada), a Unesco World
Heritage site.
areas, centred on restoration, raises another eth¬
ical issue. Restored sites are seldom, if ever, repli¬
cas of the targeted state. Extirpated species and
genetic stock, modified natural processes and
landscapes, and altered physiographic condi¬
tions make it impossible to recreate what may
have once existed. Substituting close represen¬
tatives is not the real thing.
A more fruitful debate arises from the ques¬
tion of whether it is appropriate to reconstitute
the functions and structure of an ecosystem,
particularly in a protected area. If the protected
area contains degraded sites and altered natural
processes, and species have been extirpated fro m
it, should these be restored? The debate over
biocentric and utilitarian objectives is to be'
expected in this context as well.
A fundamental question which arises in all
restoration projects is that of the historical
model which the project seeks to reconstitute.
A wilderness model (prior to European set¬
tlement) is commonly put forward as the
appropriate target in many North American
sites. This is a questionable objective if the
model rejects human influences. Clear evidence
exists that humans have played a significant
role in influencing ecosystems within North
America for thousands of years, as they have
elsewhere in the world. To be ethical, then,
exclusion of human influences is inappropri¬
ate. Instead, the objective should focus on the
restoration of a social fabric where the prac¬
tices of humans sustain the ecosystem and vice
versa.
b
THE UNESCO QuRI ER MAY 1098
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
A Canadian
approach to
cultural resource
management
> The ethics of conservation
i^HM^MHMMMMM
2. The cultural heritage
BY GORDON BENNETT AND NIKITA LOPOUKHINE
Louisbourg (above), on the
Saint Lawrence River (Nova
Scotia), was a key French
fortress in Canada and a
major trading centre. Part of
this historic landmark is being
rebuilt following the original
plans.
In the late 1980s, Parks Canada, the agency
responsible for the conservation of
Canada's cultural and natural heritage, began to
develop a cultural resource management policy,
partly to synthesize good work that had been
done elsewhere, but also to help to cope with
apparently conflicting expressions of conserva¬
tion ethics. The Parks Canada Cultural Resource
Management (CRM) policy drew upon a wide
range of policy and ethical formulations devel¬
oped by other national and international con¬
servation organizations, and in 1994, after sev¬
eral years of development and public
consultation, it was approved by the Minister of
Canadian Heritage, who tabled it in the Canadian
Parliament.
The CRM policy takes into account that
ethical issues operate at at least three levels:
*" ethics of intent or purpose (why?);
*" ethics of means (how? and often who?);
*" ethics of results (what?).
The levels or categories are not mutually
exclusive, but neither arc they necessarily
mutually reinforcing. Ethical means may not
always lead to the desired ethical result, and an
ethical result may be achieved by means that
might not have been the first choice in terms
of the second category. The CRM policy
attempts to ensure an alignment of all three.
The policy consists of three parts: principles,
practice and activities. A training programme
designed to facilitate its implementation empha¬
sizes that ethical decision-making requires that
all parts of the policy be used. In other words,
the policy is not a menu from which you pick
and choose. One of its key features is that it
docs not distinguish between various types of
cultural resources and establish different man¬
agement approaches for each, as is the case with
most other cultural resource management poli¬
cies and international charters. Another is that
it does not focus only on conservation.
Three Canadian examples may help to
demonstrate how the ethic inherent in CRM
rTHE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1998 *
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
has led to better decision-making and to
enhanced respect for cultural resources. Two of
the examples call into question some practices
of professional conservationists, whereas the
third deals with a site facing serious financial
challenges and a series of development pro¬
posals that divided people into pro-dcvclop-
ment and pro-conservation camps.
Critical to all three was the application of a
concept developed by Parks Canada called com¬
memorative integrity, which is used to describe
the health and wholeness of a national historic
site. A site possesses commemorative integrity
when:
'*" the resources (including the place) that
symbolize or represent its importance are not
impaired or under threat;
'*" the reasons for the site's national historic
significance arc effectively communicated to
the public;
the site's heritage values (including those
not related to national significance) arc respected
by all whose decisions or actions affect the site.
LowerFort Garry Walls
(Manitoba)
Lower Fort Garry National Historic Site, which
is located north of Winnipeg, Manitoba, was
an important 1 8th-ccntury fur trade establish¬
ment operated by the Hudson's Bay Company.
Technical experts advised that if action were not
taken, the then 130-year-old perimeter stone
walls would collapse. Consequently, an approach
was developed that led to the reconstruction of
two of the walls. The action was highly con¬
troversial, but proceeded with the blessing of
senior conservation specialists. Following the
development of the Cultural Resource Man-
Fort Garry, north of Winnipeg
(Manitoba), below left, was a
major 18th-century Hudson
Bay Company fur trading post.
Below right, re-enactment of
18th-century daily life in the
fort.
agement Policy, this approach was called into
question on the grounds that the action did
not respect the historic value of the walls and vio¬
lated the commemorative integrity of the site.
The reconstruction approach was abandoned
and the surviving walls have been stabilized.
Fire protection for wooden
buildings
This illustrates a case of conservation ethics gone
awry. For at least a generation many conserva¬
tionists were opposed to the opening of certain
historic wooden buildings to the public on the
grounds that a requirement to provide fire sup¬
pression facilities for buildings accessible to the ,
public was incompatible with the preservation
of the buildings' authenticity. Professional con¬
servationists should have recognized that in the
case of wooden buildings, fire suppression was
not a threat to conservation, but rather an indis¬
pensable instrument in its attainment.
FortHemy, Kingston (Ontario)
Confronted with significant reductions in gov¬
ernment funding, the agency responsible for
operating Fort Henry, a site located in Kingston,
Ontario, developed a business plan that pro¬
posed several initiatives to raise revenues. The
proposals divided the community, various stake¬
holders, and agency staff into pro-development
and pro-conservation camps. A decision was
made to develop a Commemorative Integrity
Statement for the site with the participation of
the various competing interests. The statement
led the persons who had initially advocated con¬
troversial development proposals to conclude
that the proposals were inappropriate.
> G1"THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY rv98
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
> How predictable is nature?
BY JENS ERIK FENSTAD
In spite of
progress in
mathematical
modeling, natural
phenomena still
defy precise
forecasting
Above, a man outside his
home in flood-ravaged Grand
Forks, North Dakota (U.S.A.)
in April 1997.
The future of science is not what it used
to be. The optimistic public perception
that scientific insights and technological advances
would provide a better future has suffered a
severe setback. Such "benefits" of scientific
progress as atomic power, new chemical com¬
pounds and foodstuffs produced by genetic
manipulation now generate uncertainty, even
fear, as to what the future holds in store for
man and nature.
The post-war period was a good time for
modern science-driven technology: it had
played a decisive part in the allied victory and
now it was to be harnessed to the tasks of
post-war reconstruction, promoting increased
welfare, better health and improved security.
Few were troubled if at times scientists and
engineers showed little concern for the preser¬
vation of nature after all, the aim of tech¬
nology has always been to transform nature
for the benefit of humanity. There may, how¬
ever, be limits to what nature can tolerate.
Relatively few doubts were raised until the
United Nations World Commission on Envi¬
ronment and Development issued its report,
Our Common Future, in 1987. By that time
there was growing concern about the environ¬
mental problems progress was bringing in its
wake: the fossil fuels used in industrial devel¬
opment were increasing the carbon dioxide con¬
tent in the atmosphere, threatening to create a
greenhouse effect; urbanization was eating into
agricultural land and woodlands; industrial
expansion was causing increased pollution and
loss of fresh water resources. Further ahead
loomed the threat of the loss of biodiversity.
Addressing these problems, the Commission's
report, often referred to as the Brundtland
Report, advocated a policy of sustainable devel¬
opment, whereby current demands could be
met without prejudice to the legitimate demands
of future generations.
The Brundtland Report became the charter
THE UNESCO QouRIER MAY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
^^^ nmoKfr« ucncc no wrvt-mm
IHAC>MChM«tf*«OMi «Q MOW3V«
I ¿>.rj TfNUHK IÍAS*MOO>
PROJECT «UHCQ> BT ^V
PUBLIC BANK BHD@
BERSIH Di BUDAYA KITA
>;-. p>.
N.
:,-:
document for the "Earth Summit", the United
Nations Conference on Environment and
Development held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992.
One of the most important things to come
out of this conference was the Rio Declaration,
which set forth guidelines for the future envi¬
ronmental policy of United Nations Member
States. One key element in this was the recom¬
mendation that, in order to protect the envi¬
ronment, nations should apply the "precau¬
tionary principle", which may be summarized
as follows: Whenever there is a threat ofseri¬
ous or irreversible damage, lack ofabsolute sci¬
entific certainty shall not be used as an argu¬
ment for delaying cost-effective measures to
prevent the destruction or degradation of the
environment. Never precisely defined, this prin¬
ciple is open to different legal interpretations
and raises problems about uncertainty and
actual risks.
The Brent Spar controversy
The story of the Brent Spar oil rig provides an
object lesson in the complexities of applying
the precautionary principle in practice. The
24 r
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY '998
Shell oil company wanted to get rid of this
platform, which had served its useful life in the
North Sea oilfields, by sinking it at a suitable
spot in the Atlantic. The environmentalist
movement Greenpeace successfully campaigned
to persuade the public and hence the politi¬
cians that this would present an unaccept¬
able environmental risk. Shell claimed the
opposite but was not believed, and the plat¬
form was towed to a Norwegian fjord, where
it still awaits its fate.
With the benefit of hindsight, it seems that
the risk analysis carried out by Shell was cor¬
rect and that the Greenpeace assessment was
based on inaccurate data. This does not neces¬
sarily mean, however, that the platform can
safely be disposed of at sea. Scientific risk analy¬
sis is only part of the story: there are strongly
held emotional convictions about the purity
of the sea and opposition to its becoming a
rubbish dump. As a basis for action, risk
analysis needs to take account of all aspects of
a case.
In the Brent Spar case, the decisive issue
was whether sinking the platform at sea would
lead to serious or irreversible environmental
Destruction of rain forest for
housing development (shown
on hoarding in foreground)
east of Ipoh, Malaysia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The blue and green circles are
computer-generated
theoretical models of how the
distribution of galaxies
evolved. Gold circle at bottom
shows the real distribution as
observed from Earth.
damage. As in many environmental conflicts,
the debate was adversarial in form, which is
usual in normative and legal contexts but has
hitherto been unusual in scientific arguments
overissues of "scientific certainty". Does this
mean that in environmental issues we are con¬
fusing questions of fact with matters of opin¬
ion? Should Shell and Greenpeace have got
together to conduct a dispassionate enquiry
about scientific laws and facts before embark¬
ing, if necessary, on a discussion of the pros
and cons of possible action? Can factual
knowledge be separated from the question of
how that knowledge is used?
A positive answer to the latter question
presupposes that scientific laws exist and that
scientific certainty can be established, at least
within acceptable error limits, which has been
the received view of science and technology.
From Newton's classical mechanics to Ein¬
stein's relativity and up to the time of Bohr's
quantum mechanics, the laws of nature were
expressed in the language of linear mathemat¬
ics, and the future was computable.
The relationship between mathematics and
the laws of nature has, however, become more
complex, and in a way that has implications for
our understanding of the precautionary prin¬
ciple. The fact that those laws are still written
in the language of mathematics no longer
means that the future is necessarily predictable.
To explain this issue, let us see how the math¬
ematical modelling of nature works.
Models ofnature
There are three stages in mathematical model¬
ling: first, the specific scientific and/or tech¬
nological problem is analysed; next, a mathe¬
matical model is created and analysed; and
lastly, efficient algorithms problem-solving
procedures which can be run on a computer
are developed for use, in the scientific context,
in making predictions and, in the industrial
context, in construction tasks. With the rapid
development of computer technology, the
range of applications is vast, testifying to the
central role of mathematics in today's "knowl¬
edge society".
Successful application depends, however,
on the "correct" choice of mathematical model.
One class of models is particularly relevant to
a proper understanding of the precautionary
principle. We often need to understand the
behaviour of a system ora population of indi¬
viduals over a certain period of time, e.g. the
flow of oil and gas in the North Sea fields, or
plant and animal populations in areas with a
high concentration of acid precipitation. The
models used for this purpose can be divided
into three main classes, according to the
dynamics that governs their behaviour.
Nature as a machine
Models of nature as a machine represent our
inheritance from Newton and Descartes. They
are defined by the forces acting upon the body
or bodies involved in the system, and the laws
that determine the system are expressed by a
linear equation. To take as a typical example the
laws governing the trajectories of planets, once
the proper parameter values in this case the
position in space and time and the initial acting
force have been established, the future devel¬
opment of the system is completely deter¬
mined. To use mathematicians' terminology,
the system is defined by a "unitary group",
with time as the independent variable.
This is the kind of mathematics used in
numerical calculations and industrial applica¬
tions. Assuming that our equations faithfully
describe a slice of reality, we extract algorithms
from them, and the computer then goes to
) (^OUR.ER MAY 1998THE UNESCO lOURI 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
work, either to predict the future state of a
physical system or to produce a set of speci¬
fications for an industrial task. Our confidence
in the equation is sometimes so great that the
results of the corresponding calculations are
presented as true facts of nature.
Computer simulations can be used for
many purposes. In science, measurements can
be extended to values beyond those obtainable
from experiments and observations, e.g. to
study systems under extreme temperature con¬
ditions, and the development of a physical
system can be speeded up, e.g. in studies of
the early universe. In industry, simulation can
replace the use of prototypes it is faster and
cheaper to simulate collisions on a computer
than to crash real cars and can be used in the
design of new pharmaceutical products. The
presupposition underlying all this is that our
models correspond with reality and that the
future is determined by our equations.
Chance and uncertainties
So far we have assumed that the law is deter¬
ministic and that, in principle, the results of
experiments and observations can be measured
with absolute precision, but this is in most
cases too much to ask: wc may be in a situation
characterized by chance and uncertainties.
Mathematical modelling knows, however, how
to deal with such situations.
Where parameter values cannot be precisely
measured for technical reasons, there are estab¬
lished theories for measurement techniques and
many statistical methods arc available for con¬
trolling errors. Where uncertainty is inherent in
the fundamental theory, however, new issues
arise, especially in the case of quantum mechan¬
ics, where the development of a system is gov¬
erned by a probability distribution. In this case
too, the process is nevertheless still determined
by a unitary group. The new feature is the use
of a transformation of probability distribu¬
tions where the Newtonians used point trans¬
formations. The latter allow us to follow
closely the planets in their trajectories, but not
quantum particles.
Another form of uncertainty arises when
the dynamical law is no longer deterministic
but may include a stochastic or random element.
This marks a shift from ordinary to stochastic
equations, which are now widely used in math¬
ematical modelling. The applications arc some¬
times opportunistic: in the absence of complete
knowledge, a random term is added in the hope
of obtaining a better fit with nature. In most
cases, however, our knowledge of nature and
observed fluctuations is sufficiently precise to
Children, the elderly and
people with heart and lung
disorders are particularly
vulnerable to the effects of air
pollution.
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY ! 998
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Brent Spar oil rig is
prepared for towing into the
Atlantic, June 1995.
SSW « M~ ^«
provide "faithful" models for phenomena rang¬
ing all the way from the flow of oil and water in
porous geological structures to speculation on
the stock exchange.
Common to the models examined so far is
a belief in numbers and measurements. There
has been a strong tradition in physics accord¬
ing to which theory is driven by measure¬
ments, i.e. by exact numbers. It has been held
that good theories yield numbers, explain
numbers, help design good apparatus, and
allow us to control and manipulate the objects
they describe. But are all theories of nature
equally amenable to numbers and control?
Chaos and catastrophes
The unitary group thus encapsulates the
notion of linearity and the associated possi¬
bility of exact prediction, but despite several
hundred years of progress in physics and tech¬
nology we must conclude that only a few of
nature's phenomena can be modelled in this
way. One solution to the problem is to intro
duce chance and uncertainties, as described
above. Another is to keep to deterministic
equations but to proceed beyond the well-
known domain of linear equations into the
new and largely unexplored territory of non¬
linear phenomena.
Physical theory has always acknowledged
the existence of non-linearity, which typically
occurs where small variations may have large
effects on the future evolution of a system,
but only now is the outline of a reasonably
complete science of non-linear dynamic
processes beginning to emerge. The first really
convincing application of non-linear theory to
a natural phenomenon came in 1 963, when the
meteorologist E. Lorenz published a paper
entitled "Deterministic nonperiodic flow",
which had basically all the "correct" mathe¬
matics. His equations were a simplified form
of those used in modern numerical weather
forecasting, but they were sufficiently complex
to capture the unpredictable even chaotic
behaviour inherent in the long-term develop¬
ment of the weather.
THE UNESCO Courier i 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
"Chaos" and "non-linear science" have
become fashionable terms but, unlike many
other fashions, there is substance behind them.
The transition to non-linearity marks a change
of paradigm in the modelling of natural phe¬
nomena, but with non-linearity there is no
longer a guarantee for long-term prediction.
This is the lesson we learned from Lorenz in
1963.
Instead of computing a single given future,
wc can, however, simulate various possible
future scenarios. The computer can be taught
to serve another master: there has been a
change-over from "hard" science based on
computable predictions to a broader perspec¬
tive with greater emphasis on insight and a
critical attitude. Hence, though we cannot pre¬
dict the occurrence of the next avalanche, we
can use our models to gain a better insight
into such phenomena and to develop strategics
for warding off their adverse effects.
Earthquakes are also impossible to "pre¬
dict", in the sense of giving the time, place and
strength of a future occurrence within accept¬
able error limits. Such an operation presup¬
poses a system governed by a unitary group,
but the earth as a geophysical system is far more
complex than Earth as a planet. Planets arc pre¬
dictable in their trajectories; they form a deter
ministic system. The earth as a geological system
is in what the experts call "a state of critical self-
organization", where there is a positive prob¬
ability of even the smallest earthquake devel¬
oping into a major disaster. Many attempts
have been made to devise a warning system for
earthquakes, but they have all failed.1
The global processes that drive earthquakes
are typical of the very many global processes
in nature. These processes need to be seen in
conjunction with a social and economic system
committed to a high per capita consumption
of natural resources. It is in this context that
the precautionary principle becomes urgent: we
are dealing with natural processes that we
know to be non-linear, where the dynamics of
the system is poorly understood and where
our interference may have irreversible conse¬
quences. Unlike a standard industrial process,
nature is not a mechanical system that can be
controlled by ingenuity and engineering skills
alone. Instead of relying on our ability to fix
and restore, we must therefore adopt a strat¬
egy of prevention. In these circumstances, the
precautionary principle is more than politi¬
cal rhetoric. It is the best advice that science
can offer.
1 Sec the Uni:sco Courier, October 1997: Natural
disasters: Be Prepared. Editor
"Spiralunar 3D", a fractal
landscape based on the
mathematics of chaos theory,
which is used to analyse
turbulent (non-linear) dynamic
systems.
<~ THE UNESCO ([pURIER MA^ 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The development
of genetic testing
confronts
humanity with
urgent challenges
> Genetic testing and
discriminationBY MICHAEL KIRBY
Above, symbol of the Human
Genome Project. The baby's
silhouette stands out against
a karyotype (chromosome set).
LAt the heart of adverse discrimination
lies difference. Many people only feel
comfortable with others who appear exactly
the same as themselves. Inject an element of
differentiation and such people may feel enti¬
tled to act in prejudicial and even cruel ways.
Sometimes making distinctions may be
justified. A person with a highly contagious
disease may need to be isolated for the pro¬
tection of society and the proper treatment
of the individual. But the history of the cen
tury now drawing to its close has been one
of irrational and unwarranted discrimination.
It is still going on. The grounds have included
the victim's race, skin colour, gender, disabil¬
ity and sexual orientation. All of these are
wholly or partly genetic in origin.
For some people, the fact that an individ¬
ual did not choose to be different does not
matter. Even if the difference is completely
irrelevant, it can sometimes affect most seri¬
ously the individual and the society concerned.
90
THE UNESCO CpUR'tR MAY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
proclaimed fifty years ago, has offered the
world a beacon of hope to guide us away from
irrational and irrelevant acts of adverse dis¬
crimination. But whilst much progress has
been made, the abiding challenge of discrimi¬
nation, grounded in the fear of the unknown
and the unfamiliar, remains. Now, at the end
of the century, new potentialities for dis¬
crimination are presented. They arise from the
rapid development of genetic testing which
promises to identify more indelible elements
of human differentiation upon which adverse
discrimination could be based.
Genetic testing
Testing human beings for genetic conditions
is not entirely new. Pregnant women in many
countries have for years been able to undergo
amniocentesis to detect the presence in the foe¬
tus of genetic abnormalities such as Down's
Syndrome. For years, physicians have been able
to test patients for Tay Sachs disease (an inher¬
ited and ordinarily fatal nerve disorder), sickle
This British researcher
belongs to a team that has
engineered a molecule which
"switches off" a gene causing
leukaemia.
cell anaemia and other inherited conditions.
But the progress made over the past decade in
the Human Genome Project will ultimately
ensure that genetic causes of human differences
are identified. Many that are responsible for
inherited cancers and other serious diseases have
already been isolated. Amongst those discovered
are the genes causing several late onset disor¬
ders such as cystic fibrosis, muscular dystrophy,
Huntington's disease and, most widespread of
all, Alzheimer's disease.
Mistakes can occur in the performance of
tests to identify the presence of genetic dis¬
orders. As with the well-known tests for HIV
(human immunodeficiency virus), there can
be false positives and false negatives. But apart
from this problem, current tests cannot pre- ,
diet, with accuracy, precisely when a genetic
condition will manifest itself. The genetic test
for Huntington's disease (an inherited con¬
dition which manifests abnormal movements
and mental deterioration, generally occurring
in middle age) has a 99 per cent accuracy rate.
But there is enormous variation in the age of
onset and in the range of symptoms that will
appear in a given individual. In the past, fam¬
ily members would often know generally
about inherited conditions which might man¬
ifest themselves in succeeding generations.
Now there is the potential to remove the
uncertainty and to diagnose with near perfect
accuracy the presence of the gene which, in
due course, will manifest itself and, in some
conditions, lead on to profound disabilities or
certain death. Here, clearly, are new founda¬
tions for differentiation between individuals
by reference to a wider category of distinc¬
tions that mark them off from most people in
society. Is this a problem? In these enlight¬
ened and scientific times, need we really be
worried about threats of discrimination on
genetic grounds?
Foundations ofdiscrimination
Unfortunately, despite progress in education
and in domestic and international human
rights law, the past teaches us that wc should
be concerned. Millions of people this century
have lost their lives, or have suffered pro¬
foundly, because of obvious genetic distinc¬
tions. When new distinctions, previously hid¬
den, are added to the list, we should be alert to
provide effective social responses.
As a result of learning the outcome of a
genetic test, an individual's life may be pro¬
foundly changed. A patient learning of the pres¬
ence of a fatal and untreatable disorder may
undergo profound psychological disturbance.
Some may choose not to submit to the test
W THE UNESCO ÇoURIER MAY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
A scientist points out a defect
on a human karyotype: an
extra copy of chromosome 8
which is commonly found in
some forms of leukaemia.
V
x
fc.
because of the effect which knowledge of a neg¬
ative result could have for the subject's well-
being and that of the immediate family.
The greatest dangers from adverse discrim¬
ination lie principally in the context of social
arrangements which may be affected by knowl¬
edge, or access to knowledge, about an indi¬
vidual's genetic makeup. Take insurance. In the
past, the availability of insurance, and the rates
of premiums, were ordinarily fixed by reference
to a sharing of the risks of the onset of a mul¬
titude of genetic disorders amongst all members
of the insuring public. Now that it is possible
to subject a proponent for insurance to genetic
tests, the sharing of risks may disappear or be
substantially reduced. If the presence of inher¬
ited disorders can be ascertained with near per¬
fect accuracy, the cards may be stacked in favour
of the insurance company. There may be no
risk of the onset of defined disorders. Or it
may be absolutely certain.
Insurers argue that they are merely substi¬
tuting the latest scientific information for the
old-fashioned medical check-ups and replacing
generalized data of life expectancy with accu¬
rate predictive data of genetic disorders. If
insurers can offer policies at lower premiums
to non-smokers, should they not be able to
31
THE UNESCO (T'UR.IER MAY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
do so to those who, genetic testing reveals,
are unlikely to manifest a range of life-threat¬
ening inherited conditions? These are some
of the dilemmas we face.
Employers may wish to subject certain
employees to genetic testing. They may argue
that training, the provision of disability bene¬
fits and the costs of sick leave and replacement
justify having access to genetic information con¬
cerning members of their workforce. Theprob-
lem with this is the same as with insurance. Will
the individual with "negative" genetic results be
refused employment? In the relationship
between the individual proponent for insur¬
ance or the individual applicant for employ¬
ment and the potential insurer or employer,
will the former be sufficiently empowered to
refuse access to his or her genetic data?
Unless the law intervenes to prevent threats
of adverse discrimination, will the practical
consequence be that insurers, employers and
possibly the State itself will be empowered to
require individuals to discover the range of
long-term genetic disabilities which, left alone,
the individual might prefer not to know?
DNA fingerprinting in a British
laboratory. Fragments
extracted from an individual's
tissue are processed to
p roduce a kind of genetic
"identity card". DNA
fingerprints are used to prove
whether people are related and
to identify criminals from
tissues left at the scene of a
crime.
Some scientists believe that sexual orienta¬
tion is, at least partly, genetically determined.
If this were scientifically established, would it
help or hinder the world-wide efforts to reduce
discrimination against people on the ground of
their sexuality? It might help by proving that
something so innate is determined naturally
and is not defiantly chosen to flout society's
moral rules. But out of fear or hatred of differ¬
ence, it might lead to demands for destruction
of foetuses showing this propensity.
The diversity of the human gene pool has
been one of the principal causes of humanity's
strength and survival. The ultimate threat of
discrimination would arise from demands to
eradicate all inherited conditions conceived of
as "intolerable". The advance of genetic testing
will therefore present fundamental challenges
to humanity. How do we alleviate unnecessary
suffering and eradicate the scourge of prema¬
ture death from inherited disorders whilst at
the same time retaining the precious variety of
humanity and the diversity of its gene pool?
Social management
On 11 November 1997, the UNESCO General
Conference unanimously adopted the Uni¬
versal Declaration on the Human Genome and
Human Rights (see page 34). This path-break¬
ing charter proclaims, in its first article, that the
human genome underlies the fundamental
unity of all members of the human family as
Ullll11
IV III
the unesco Courier may 1098
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
well as the recognition of their inherent dig¬
nity and diversity. The Declaration addresses
itself to the problem of adverse discrimina¬
tion and says: "No one shall be subjected to
discrimination based on genetic characteris¬
tics that is intended to infringe or has the
effect of infringing human rights, fundamental
freedoms and human dignity".
Translating these principles into effective
protection of vulnerable people against threats
of adverse discrimination is a major challenge
which now faces the international commu¬
nity, the nation states and the professional
and commercial organizations that are involved
in genetic testing.
The international community is to estab¬
lish machines for monitoring the implemen¬
tation of UNESCO's Universal Declaration.
Already an ad hoc group has met in Paris to
consider the ways in which the principles of
the Declaration can be implemented.
Nation states must introduce laws and poli¬
cies to give effect to the principle of non-dis¬
crimination. Several countries have already
enacted laws to govern the use of genetic test¬
ing in particular fields. But so far, comprehen¬
sive laws dealing with the threats of discrimi¬
nation have been slow in coming. The Council
of Europe in 1997 adopted a Convention for
the Protection of Human Rights and Dignity
of the Human Being with regard to the appli¬
cation of biology and medicine. But in most
"The diversity of the human
gene pool has been one of the
principal causes of humanity's
strength and survival." Above,
Silhouettes in the Sun by the
American artist Katherine
Arion.
British researchers cloned a
lamb, Dolly (right), from a
single cell of a ewe in 1997.
societies, the advances in genetic testing have
outstripped the lawmaking process. Protection
of vulnerable individuals, and society, against
the threats of discrimination are mostly left
to depend, if on anything, upon the ethics of
the healthcare professions and such general laws
and policies forbidding unwarranted discrim¬
ination on health grounds as were adopted years
before genetic testing became possible.
Professional bodies such as the Human
Genome Organization, supported by its
Ethics Committee, devise guidelines which
arc recommended to scientists in the field for
their guidance. Industry bodies, such as those
representing insurers and employers, may
adopt rules of self-regulation to limit demands
for genetic test results to circumstances where
they can clearly be justified. But the hard work
of preparing enforceable laws and policies to
address a multitude of issues presented by
genetic testing, lies ahead.
Education in the risks and dangers will have
a part to play. So will the development of
enforceable laws which balance the demands of
those who claim that knowledge of genetic data
is relevant to their decisions against the demand
of the individual to maintain the privacy of
such data and control over its use. In every coun¬
try, lawmakers should have the assistance of
expert and multi-disciplinary bodies to give
guidance on the way in which the right balance
is to be struck. To refrain from providing pro¬
tection against discrimination is to condone the
dangers of the discrimination which will fol¬
low. To do nothing is to make a decision.
QoURITHE UNESCO ÏOURIER MAY 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION ON THE HUMAN
GENOME AND HUMAN RIGHTS
Preface
The Universal Declaration on the Human Genome and Human Rights, which was adopted unan¬
imously and by acclamation by the General Conference of Unesco at its 29th session on 1 1 Novem¬
ber 1 997, is the first universal instrument in the field of biology. The uncontested merit of this text resides
in the balance it strikes between safeguarding respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms
and the need to ensure freedom of research.
Together with the Declaration, UNESCO's General Conference adopted a resolution for its imple¬
mentation, which commits States to taking appropriate measures to promote the principles set out in
the Declaration and encourage their implementation.
The moral commitment entered into by States in adopting the Universal Declaration on the Human
Genome and Human Rights is a starting point, the beginning of international awareness of the need
for ethical issues to be addressed in science and technology. It is now up to States, through the measures
they decide to adopt, to put the Declaration into practice and thus ensure its continued existence.
Federico Mayor
3 December 1997
THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION
ON THE HUMAN GENOME
AND HUMAN RIGHTS
A. HUMAN DIGNITY AND THE HUMAN
GENOME
Article 1
The human genome underlies the fundamental unity of all
members of the human family, as well as the recognition of their
inherent dignity and diversity. Ina symbolic sense, it is the heritage of
humanity.
Article 2
a) Everyone has a right to respect for their dignity and for their
rights regardless of their genetic characteristics.
b) That dignity makes it imperative not to reduce individuals to their
genetic characteristics and to respect their uniqueness and diversity.
Article 3
The human genome, which by its nature evolves, is subject to
mutations. It contains potentialities that are expressed differently
according to each individual's natural and social environment includ¬
ing the individual's state of health, living conditions, nutrition and
education.
Article 4
The human genome in its natural state shall not give rise to finan¬
cial gains.
B. RIGHTS OF THE PERSONS
CONCERNED
Article 5
a) Research, treatment or diagnosis affecting an individual's genome
shall be undertaken only after rigorous and prior assessment of the
potential risks and benefits pertaining thereto and in accordance with
any other requirement of national law.
b) In all cases , the prior, free and informed consent of the person
concerned shall be obtained. If the latter is not in a position to con¬
sent, consent or authorization shall be obtained in the manner pre¬
scribed by law, guided by the person's best interest.
c) The right of each individual to decide whether or not to be
informed of the results of genetic examination and the resulting con¬
sequences should be respected.
d) In the case of research, protocols shall, in addition, be submit¬
ted for prior review in accordance with relevant national and interna¬
tional research standards or guidelines.
c) If according to the law a person docs not have the capacity to con¬
sent, research affecting his or her genome may only be carried out for
his or her direct health benefit, subject to the authorization and the pro¬
tective conditions prescribed by law. Research which docs not have an
expected direct health benefit may only be undertaken by way of
exception, with the utmost restraint, exposing the person only to a
minimal risk and minimal burden and if the research is intended to con¬
tribute to the health benefit of other persons in the same age category
or with the same genetic condition, subject to the conditions pre¬
scribed by law, and provided such research is compatible with the
protection of the individual's human rights.
Article 6
No one shall be subjected to discrimination based on genetic char¬
acteristics that is intended to infringe or has the effect of infringing
human rights, fundamental freedoms and human dignity.
Article 7
Genetic data associated with an identifiable person and stored or
processed for the purposes of research or any other purpose must be
held confidential in the conditions set by law.
Article 8
Every individual shall have the right, according to international and
national law, to just reparation for any damage sustained as a direct and
determining result of an intervention affecting his or her genome.
Article 9
In order to protect human rights and fundamental freedoms, lim¬
itations to the principles of consent and confidentiality may only be
prescribed by law, for compelling reasons within the bounds of pub¬
lic international law and the international law of human rights.
34
THE UNESCO ^)URI:ERB MAY I99S
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
C. RESEARCH ON THE HUMAN GENOME
Article 10
No research or research applications concerning the human genome,
in particular in the fields of biology, genetics and medicine, should pre¬
vail over respect for the human rights, fundamental freedoms and human
dignity of individuals or, where applicable, of groups of people.
Article 11
Practices which arc contrary to human dignity, such as reproduc¬
tive cloning of human beings, shall not be permitted. States and com¬
petent international organizations are invited to co-operate in iden¬
tifying such practices and in taking, at national or international level,
the measures necessary to ensure that the principles set out in this
Declaration arc respected.
Article 12
a) Benefits from advances in biology, genetics and medicine, con¬
cerning the human genome, shall be made available to all, with due
regard for the dignity and human rights of each individual.
b) Freedom of research, which is necessary for the progress of
knowledge, is part of freedom of thought. The applications of research,
including applications in biology, genetics and medicine, concerning
the human genome, shall seek to offer relief from suffering and
improve the health of individuals and humankind as a whole.
D. CONDITIONS FOR THE EXERCISE
OF SCIENTIFIC ACTIVITY
Article 13
The responsibilities inherent in the activities of researchers, includ¬
ing mcticulousness, caution, intellectual honesty and integrity in car¬
rying out their research as well as in the presentation and utilization
of their findings, should be the subject of particular attention in the
framework of research on the human genome, because of its ethical and
social implications. Public and private science policy-makers also have
particular responsibilities in this respect.
Article 14
States should take appropriate measures to foster the intellectual
and material conditions favourable to freedom in the conduct of
research on the human genome and to consider the ethical, legal, social
and economic implications of such research, on the basis of the prin¬
ciples set out in this Declaration.
Article 15
States should take appropriate steps to provide the framework
for the free exercise of research on the human genome with due regard
for the principles set out in this Declaration, in order to safeguard
respect for human rights, fundamental freedoms and human dignity
and to protect public health. They should seek to ensure that research
results arc not used for non-peaceful purposes.
Article 16
States should recognize the value of promoting, at various levels,
as appropriate, the establishment of independent, multidisciplinary
and pluralist ethics committees to assess the ethical, legal and social
issues raised by research on the human genome and its applications.
E. SOLIDARITY AND INTERNATIONAL
CO-OPERATION
Article 17
States should respect and promote the practice of solidarity towards
individuals, families and population groups who are particularly vul¬
nerable to or affected by disease or disability of a genetic character.
They should foster, inter alia, research on the identification, preven¬
tion and treatment of gcnctically-bascd and genetically-influenced
diseases, in particular rare as well as endemic diseases which affect large
numbers of the world's population.
Article 18
States should make every effort, with due and appropriate regard
for the principles set out in this Declaration, to continue fostering the
international dissemination of scientific knowledge concerning the
human genome, human diversity and genetic research and, in that
regard, to foster scientific and cultural co-operation, particularly
between industrialized and developing countries.
Article 19
a) In the framework of international co-operation with develop¬
ing countries, States should seek to encourage measures enabling:
i) assessment of the risks and benefits pertaining to research on the
human genome to be carried out and abuse to be prevented;
ii) the capacity of developing countries to carry out research on
human biology and genetics, taking into consideration their specific
problems, to be developed and strengthened;
iii) developing countries to benefit from the achievements of scientific
and technological research so that their use in favour of economic and
social progress can be to the benefit of all;
iv) the free exchange of scientific knowledge and information in the
areas of biology, genetics and medicine to be promoted.
b) Relevant international organizations should support and promote
the initiatives taken by States for the above-mentioned purposes.
F. PROMOTION OF THE PRINCIPLES SET
OUT IN THE DECLARATION
Article 20
States should take appropriate measures to promote the principles
set out in the Declaration, through education and relevant means,
inter alia through the conduct of research and training in interdisci¬
plinary fields and through the promotion of education in bioethics,
at all levels, in particular for those responsible for science policies.
Article 21
States should take appropriate measures to encourage other forms
of research, training and information dissemination conducive to rais¬
ing the awareness of society and all of its members of their responsibilities
regarding the fundamental issues relating to the defence of human dig¬
nity which may be raised by research in biology, in genetics and in med¬
icine, and its applications. They should also undertake to facilitate on
this subject an open international discussion, ensuring the free expres¬
sion of various socio-cultural, religious and philosophical opinions.
G. IMPLEMENTATION
OF THE DECLARATION
Article 22
States should make every effort to promote the principles set out
in this Declaration and should, by means of all appropriate measures,
promote their implementation.
Article 23
States should take appropriate measures to promote, through
education, training and information dissemination, respect for the
above-mentioned principles and to foster their recognition and effec¬
tive application. States should also encourage exchanges and networks
among independent ethics committees, as they arc established, to fos¬
ter full collaboration.
Article 24
The International Bioethics Committee of Unlsco should con¬
tribute to the dissemination of the principles set out in this Declara¬
tion and to the further examination of issues raised by their applica¬
tions and by the evolution of the technologies in question. It should
organize appropriate consultations with parties concerned, such as
vulnerable groups. It should make recommendations, in accordance
with UNESCO's statutory procedures, addressed to the General Con¬
ference and give advice concerning the follow-up of this Declaration,
in particular regarding the identification of practices that could be
contrary to human dignity, such as gcrm-linc interventions.
Article 25
Nothing in this Declaration may be interpreted as implying for any
State, group or person any claim to engage in any activity or to per¬
form any act contrary to human rights and fundamental freedoms,
including the principles set out in this Declaration.
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1018
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY Federico Mayor
A shared future
I Day by day our planet is shrinking. Today it
I is smaller and more fragile than yesterday.
And yet arc wc really any "closer" to each other?
The interdependence of the peoples and nations
making up our world has become self-evident. No
country, however powerful in terms of its economy
or population, can any longer get by completely on
its own. Transnational problems whether they
be environmental, cultural or economic can no
longer be solved at the national level. It is through
international strategies, through concerted action
between states and between regions that such
problems can be addressed. Poverty, Aids, pol¬
lution, climate change, drugs and violence know
no boundaries, whether national, ethnic, natural
or political.
Globalization also means that the issues are
interconnected. The sectoral, specialized, disci¬
pline-specific approach has shown its limitations,
and these are becoming more and more of a con
straint as real life, or at least our awareness of it,
grows in complexity. Bioethics is an obvious exam¬
ple of a domain that "cuts across" several disci¬
plines. If we wish to influence reality, we must
adopt a transdisciplinary approach that makes use
of all available expertise and skills.
This awareness of the interdependence of
human beings and of the interconnectedncss of
the issues they face has become clearly apparent
in recent years at the highest levels of political
action and in global forums. Within the United
Nations system, a series of major conferences has
highlighted the connections between the various
challenges we must take up between environ¬
ment and development, for example, and between
education and population. Jomtien, New Delhi,
Vienna, Cairo, Copenhagen and Beijing are among
the cities that have hosted these global summits.
Too long overlooked or neglected, the human
dimension is once again compelling recognition as
'Compare the hundreds of billions of dollars siphoned off
by the arms or drug trade with national education budgets.
What a shameful disparity!'
36 THE UNESCO (pURICR MAY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
'We must multiply our bonds of allegiance, build more bridges
between the individual and communities of various kinds and sizes,
strengthen "community citizenship" while at the same time
promoting the idea of "world citizenship".'
or no future
the measure of all things . In the United Nations sys¬
tem, the approach to social development, to human
development has become broader, more diverse
and more flexible. Human beings, with all their
unfathomable qualities, their strengths and weak¬
nesses, are again moving to the centre of the eco¬
nomic stage.
And yet . . . compare the hundreds of billions
of dollars siphoned off by the arms or drug trade
with national education budgets! What a shameful
disparity! Is not education a fundamental human
right?
"Ecce homo. Behold the man!" exclaimed Pope
John Paul II at UNESCO's Paris Headquarters eigh¬
teen years ago in an address that left its mark on all
of us. "Behold the man! . . . the rich creativity of
the human mind" which makes "untiring efforts
to fathom and affirm the identity of man . . . always
present in every form of culture".
For human beings to be worthy of the name,
they must "belong" to the human species and expe¬
rience that sense of belonging. If they know and
feel themselves to be members of the human fam¬
ily, they will have no difficulty in assisting their fel¬
low beings without ranking people close to them
any higher than those who are far away. We must
multiply our bonds of allegiance, that is to say,
build more bridges between the individual and
communities of different kinds and sizes, strengthen
"community citizenship" while at the same time
promoting the idea of "world citizenship", and
think globally while acting locally, so that human
solidarity may flourish.
The "intellectual and moral solidarity of
mankind", seen by UNESCO's Constitution as the
basis of lasting peace, is a form of solidarity targeted
at social disparities, one which strives against intol¬
erance, jolts indifference and builds bridges
between haves and have-nots, between Muslim and
Jew, between prince and pauper. It is an active
kind of solidarity between individuals who may be
poles apart in many ways, a sense of community in
diversity. And it is that solidarity, which grows up
between different languages and cultures, beliefs
and customs, ways of being and of thinking, and
soon becomes indestructible, that makes people
accept the idea of sharing, and indeed want to share.
Share their riches, resources and knowledge,
and also their doubts. It is this universal impera¬
tive which must underpin our individual and col¬
lective thoughts and actions. Though we now
know and have known for several decades that
we, as civilizations, arc mortal, it is only right that
we should also know, as human beings, that the
future will be one of sharing or there will be no
future at all.
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1998
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Renewable
energy:
winds of change Èa
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
Svartsengi
geothermal plant,
which supplies
Reykjavik (Iceland)
with hot water.
While the planet is heing sti¬
fled by atmospheric pollution
from the gases given off hy fossil
fuels such as oil 64 million hands
of which are consumed every day
and coal, alternative sources of
"renewable energy are there
for the using. But looking around
the world, even those places where
sources such as water, sun, wind,
plant residues or volcanoes are plen¬
tifully available, we see how little
use is actually being made of them.
The reason lies both in the cost of
the necessary capital goods, which
remains high because they cannot
be mass-produced, and in the lack of
information and training.
UNESCO recognized that renew¬
able energies are one of the keys to
sustainable development as long ago
as the 1950s, when they were still
seen as a bee in the bonnet of woolly-
minded conservationists. A number
of factors growing environmental
awareness, the realization of the
impact of the greenhouse effect on
world climate, the catastrophic acci¬
dents that have occurred in the very
nuclear plants that promised clean
power, and the progress made con
currently in the technology of renew¬
able energy use have, however,
drawn increasing attention to the
potential they represent.
Rocketing oil prices in the early
1970s reinforced this interest still
further, but when prices fell, fifteen
years later or thereabouts, interest
again waned and research pro¬
grammes went on lo the back burner.
Today's very low oil prices ($16 a
barrel) are no inducement to econ¬
omy, nor do they encourage invest¬
ment in new energy technologies,
especially since they are mainly
intended for the developing coun¬
tries, which are either insolvent or
getting on that way. They are, fur¬
thermore, complicated to put into
operation, requiring an interdisci¬
plinary approach, which is why
UNESCO's Engineering and Technol¬
ogy Division co-operates with other
institutions of the United Nations
system, with many non-governmen¬
tal organizations and with bilateral
and multilateral aid agencies.
AN URGENT NEED
In 1993, Unesco hosted the World
Solar Summit, at which, for the first
time, the international community
examined the problem of renewable
energy sources. As explained by Elie
Absi, a member of the secretariat
of the World Solar Commission
which was set up in 1993, the
generic term "solar" is used because
all sources of energy, with the excep¬
tion of nuclear and geothermal
energy, are linked with the sun. The
choice of the most suitable of these
energy sources depends on local cir¬
cumstances, available resources and
level of consumption.
Demographic pressure is making
the use of renewables a matter of
even greater urgency. The planet's
population is now increasing at the
rate of nearly 250,000 a day. Agri¬
culture is incapable of feeding the
developing countries' four-and-a-half
billion rural inhabitants (700 mil¬
lion households) scattered about the
relatively isolated regions of Africa,
Latin America, India and China.
To keep these people on the land
and restrict migration both from
countryside to towns and from one
country to another, it is essential lo
launch cost-effective craft, indus¬
trial or agro-food activities, on
however modest a scale, and this
cannot be achieved without energy
supplies.
Output of electricity by conven¬
tional means has increased by leaps
and hounds over the last thirty years
but the main consumers have been
city-dwellers. The World Bank
spends $3.3 billion a year in the
energy sector but only 7% of this
goes lo renewable energy in the
developing countries. Out of the
total of $8 billion similarly provided
by multilateral aid agencies, only
$1.5 billion is spent on rural elec¬
trification. Electricity supplies to
the rural population are no better
than thirty years ago. The reason is
that maintenance and repairs are
38 THE. UNESCO ^HIRIER MAY I9"S
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Inside the hub of a
100-metre tall
wind turbine,
Brusbuttel
(Germany)
difficult, connection to the mains
supply is costly, human settlements
are widely scattered, access to iso¬
lated areas is difficult and con¬
sumption is often low (less than one
kWh a day).
BIOGAS, GEOTHERMAL ENERGY
AND WIND POWER
A few examples will suffice to show
what can be done with renewable
energy sources. In Guatemala, for
instance, there is an ongoing short¬
age of oil and gas, and only 36% of
the. population, mainly in the towns,
are connected to the electricity sup¬
ply. This being the case, the main
source of energy is firewood, leading
to 900 sq.km. of woodland being
deforested yearly far exceeding the
forest's regeneration capacity. The
national agency responsible for the
management of renewable energy, set
up in 1983, employs locally-based
technicians throughout the country.
With the assistance of an anthropol¬
ogist who helps persuade the local
inhabitants to accept the new tech¬
nologies, these technicians have the
job of promoting and monitoring the
use of solar installations (biodigesters
and photovoltaic systems).
A geothermal unit and two small-
scale hydroelectric power stations
are planned. Backed by $2 million
from the United Nations Industrial
Wind turbines in
the Mojave desert,
California (U.S.A.)
Development Organization (UNI DO),
a three-year (1996-1999) plan will
provide dispensaries, schools and
food shops with photovoltaic instal¬
lations. In the village of Xetzé, for
example, where one of these systems
has been installed, electric light now
enables the womenfolk lo carry on
with their weaving in the evenings
and, as their output of cloth has
thus been put on a more regular
basis, they have been able to set up
long-term deals with foreign buyers.
Biogas is one of the cheapest
sources of renewable energy,
obtained by fermenting animal or
vegetable waste products in a special
container, the hiodigester. Rich in
methane and carbon dioxide, it is
used for lighting, cooking and other
purposes (see "A waste-free farm",
Um<;sc,() Courier, September 1997).
Geothermal energy makes use of
underground heat, which increases
with depth (a drill can go down to a
maximum of 5,000 metres), allow¬
ing a turbine to be driven by water or
steam and produce electricity.
Another technique consists in inject¬
ing water into fissures in rock, and
retrieving it when it has been natu¬
rally heated. Heating for 85% of
the population in Iceland comes
from geothermal sources. A score of
countries, mostly developing, use
geothermal energy, and there are
250 geothermal power stations in
operation in various parts of the
world, but cost restricts their fur¬
ther development.
Wind power is the most promising
of all the renewable energies and the
one that has undergone the most spec¬
tacular development. Germany, India
and Denmark are the three countries
best equipped in this respect. Spain,
which comes fourth, is the first coun¬
try in the European Union to enact
legislation incorporating the recom¬
mendations made in the European
Commission's While Paper on renew¬
able energy sources; wind generators
are in wide use in the Canaries, for
sea-water desalination among other
purposes. Over a hundred wind pumps
are already operating in Mauritania,
where a non-governmental organiza¬
tion, the Groupement de recherches
et d'échanges technologiques (Tech¬
nological Research and Exchanges
Group), working in partnership with
iheMauritanianencrgy authority, has
installed wind-powered battery-charg¬
ing stations in fifteen villages in the
Tzarza region, a south-eastern area
where there is plenty of wind. These
batteries supply electricity to bouses
or nomads' tents. A $5-a-month sub¬
scription buys the use of an individual
battery that can be recharged when
Hat by the wind generator. Wind gen¬
erators power pumps supplying vil¬
lages with drinking water in the
remotest regions of the Adrar.
THE WORLD SOLAR
PROGRAMME
The sun is an immense renewable
energy source equivalent to about
10,000 times the total world
demand for power. It is ever-pre¬
sent albeit varying in intensity
throughout the world. It can be har¬
nessed directly, in the form of heat,
or converted into electricity. In the
former case, all that is needed in the
developing countries is a black-
backed sheet of glass or plastic to
make a cheap drying rack for fruit,
vegetables or fish. The latter
method the photovoltaic system
requires panels, a battery and a
device for con verting direct current
to alternating hut also needs an oper¬
ator who has to be trained to use
and maintain it.
THLUNtSCO
r ;
^_OURlER MAY 10*58 ^1
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
A house in Nepal.
Left, the
fermentation tank,
or hiodigester,
used for producing
biogas. Right,
cooking with
biogas.
"Solar technology", explains
Erench researcher Michel Rodot,
"represents a major potential, but
development runs up against real
financial problems, firstly because
installation costs are fairly high but
mainly because village people and
rural extension workers need to be
committed to the idea of solar
power. It also requires political will
on the part of the State and support
from the banks. Consumers will have
to learn that the supply of solar elec¬
tricity is a service they must pay for,
however modest the price."
Conscious of the part renewable
energies can play, UNESCO has
devised a ten-year (1996-2005)
World Solar Programme, which aims
"to develop and implement 300-odd
top-priority renewable energy pro¬
jects of national, regional and inter
national value ... in order to demon¬
strate the technical feasibility, eco¬
nomic viability and social and polit¬
ical acceptability of solar energy."
The Organization is also offering an
extremely well-stocked database,
available both in printed form and on
computer, and a summer school for
French-speaking engineers, instruc-
tors, academics, researchers and
economists. I
FOR FURTHER INFORMATION:
World Solar Programme:
Internet:
http://www./unesco.org/general/fre/pro-
grammes/science/wssp
Summer school:
Mr O.Benchikh, Unesco
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 39 16
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 58 20
Books:
Renewable Energy. Sources for Fuels and
Electricity, Earthscan Publications, London,
1993 (an excellent collective work of over
1,000 pages)
Le solaire thermique au service du
développement durable, Guide de l'énergie
solaire, a guide to the application of solar
energy to sustainable development,
published by the Réseau international
énergie solaire, Canada, and containing some
remarkable case studies
Energie et environnement en Méditerranée,
Enjeux et prospectives (Energy and
environment m the Mediterranean, Issues
and prospects), by Michel Grenon et al.,
Económica, Paris, 1993
CD-ROM:
Unesco/ISEEK Energy Database, 3rd edition,
1997 (Database of the International System
of Energy Expertise and Knowledge)
On sale from Unesco Publishing, 1 rue Miollis,
75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 43 00
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 57 41
Internet: http://ww.unesco.org./publishing
initiatives ^^^
'ENERGIES F0RTHE WORLD'
On the initiative of the French renewable energy body Observatoire français des ener¬
gies renouvelables, twelve public and private partners, ministries and major companies,
came together to set up, in Paris, the Fondation Energies pour le monde (Energies for
the World Foundation). Established and granted State-approved status in 1990, it car¬
ries out renewahle-encrgy-based electrification projects to help the development of the
local economy and improve living conditions in impoverished rural areas.
Its activities, international in scope, include:
Africa: electrification of ten or so youth clubs (Mandé region, Mali) and thirty dis¬
pensaries (Casamance, south Senegal); practical and theoretical instruction in the tech¬
nology and maintenance of photovoltaic pumps at a school for rural engineers in
Ougadougou (Burkina Faso); installation of a solar generator for recharging ten batter¬
ies a day in the douar (nomad encampment) of Igoudar Jebel (Atlas Mountains, Morocco).
Asia: in Bangladesh, the Foundation is advising the Rural Electricity Develop¬
ment Board on the electrification of isolated villages. In Viet Nam, in the Mekong Delta
and many southern islands, it has electrified some forty community centres, which now
have television sets, video players and battery chargers. In Cambodia, ten or so dispen¬
saries have electric light and refrigerators for vaccines.
The Pacific: in Vanuatu, nearly twenty schools now have a power supply.
The Foundation's activities extend to many other countries, including Georgia, Togo,
Madagascar, the United Republic of Tanzania, India, Nepal, Haiti and China.
In addition to its own small staff, it has a network of field officers who carry out its pro¬
jects in liaison with the local authorities. It works in partnership with UNESCO, the World
Health Organization and the United Nations Development Programme. The Foundation pub¬
lishes many simple, practical documents on renewable energy sources, and a bimonthly review,
Systèmes solaires, Energies-Environnement-Développement, 146 rue de l'Université,
75007 Paris. Tel: (33) (0)1 44 18 00 88; Fax: (33) (0)1 44 18 00 36.
40
THE UNESCO (oURIIER MAY 19*&
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
world
CAULERPA:
DOING WELL-AND DOING DAMAGE
Caulerpa taxlfolia algae, which appeared
twelve years ago in the Mediterranean, pose
a threat to the beds of Posidonia (a marine
plant similar to the eelgrass) and to the fauna
that lives in them. Three thousand hectares
of the coastal waters of France and Italy are
already infested with this "green plague".
It reproduces at a great rate by putting out
suckers, and its proliferation has been fur¬
ther speeded by the anchors of pleasure
craft, fishing nets and the dumping of the
contents of ballast tanks. The French Acad¬
emy of Sciences has recommended that
pleasure-boat owners and fishermen be given
more information about the danger it pre¬
sents and, in particular, that in-depth
research should be carried out into its
method of propagation and ways of halting
the invasion.
A WORLD COMMISSION
ON DAMS
Establishment of this new body was
announced in February 1998 by Kader
Asmal, South Africa's Minister of Water
Affairs and Forestry, who chairs the Com¬
mission. He will be assisted by ten commis¬
sioners, drawn from widely varying back¬
grounds industrialists or
ecologists. The Commission's aim will be to
bring about a more reponsible approach to
the building of large dams by conducting a
global review of their costs and benefits. '
UNITED STATES INVADED
BY CANADA (GEESE)
When an animal species has been too well
protected, as has happened with the resi
dent population of Canada geese (Branta
canadensis) introduced into the eastern
United States by wildlife managers in the
1960s, drastic measures may be called for.
These birds, about a million of them, gobble
up grass, foul reservoirs, and present a
safety hazard for airports. After an attempt
had been made to relocate them, shortage
of space made it necessary to cull several
thousand before the arrival of the 300,000
migratory geese, who have priority!
PLASTICS
MAKE GOOD FUEL
Barely 4% of the three million tonnes of plas¬
tics thrown away every year in France is recy¬
cled. The Association of Plastics Manufac¬
turers in Europe has demonstrated that 1.4
tonnes of coal would be saved for every tonne
of plastic waste products burned as fuel in an
energy-guzzling cement works. If this prac¬
tice was generally applied in Europe, which
accounts for 25% of the world's cement out¬
put, 3.8 million tonnes of coal could be
saved, an especially environment-friendly
outcome since coal pollutes the atmosphere
but plastics leave no solid residues or ash
and burning them would not lead to any
increase in atmospheric emissions.
THREAT FROM OBSOLETE
PESTICIDE STOCKS
The United Nations Food and Agriculture
Organization (FAO) has drawn attention to
the fact that over 100,000 tonnes of obsolete
and unused pesticides continue to pose a
threat to health and the environment in the
developing countries. In town and country¬
side alike, thousands of barrels are rusting
away and leaking their toxic contents, some¬
times contaminating irrigation and drinking
water. The best way to get rid of them would
be high-temperature incineration, but most
of the countries concerned lack the neces¬
sary installations. In Africa alone, the dis¬
posal cost is reckoned at $80 million, but
the agro-chemical industry is proposing to
put up only 30% of the disposal costs.
ETHNO-DEVELOPMENT
IN ECUADOR
The World Bank has approved an "ethno-
development" project in Ecuador. Backed by
a $25 million Bank loan, it aims to develop,
in indigenous and Afro-Ecuadorian commu¬
nities and villages, activities such as improv¬
ing schools, managing community forestry,
farming activities, fisheries or water ser¬
vices. There are 2,500,000 hectares of land
yet to be titled in Ecuador and, against this
background, the project helps the indigenous
peoples to obtain title to their ancestral
lands.
BORNEO:
THE ORANGUTAN IN RETREAT
Seventy orangutans have been taken into
care at the Wanariset research centre, a
sanctuary in the forests of East Kalimantan,
the Indonesian part of the island of Borneo.
Most of them are young orphans whose
mothers have fled to escape the forest fires
or have been killed or kidnapped by poach¬
ers. Though protected as one of the world's
most endangered species, these great apes
are hunted for their meat or sold into cap¬
tivity. Their numbers have declined by 50% in
the last ten years in Borneo and Sumatra,
and there are now thought to be less than
20,000 left.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
HERITAGE
The monastery of
Haghpat
by Elisabeth Baudourian
A masterpiece of religious
architecture and a major
centre of [earning in the
Middle Ages, Armenia's
Haghpat Monastery was
placed on Unesco's World
Heritage List in 1996.
Tradition has it that two of
, Christ's apostles, St. Thad-
dcus and St. Bartholomew, intro¬
duced Christianity into Armenia
at a very early date. Later, at the
beginning of the fourth century,
Armenia became the first country
to adopt Christianity as an official
religion. Against a backdrop of the¬
ological disputes, but above all
motivated by political reasons, the
Armenian church soon began to
elect its own archbishop. Since it
rejected the dogma of the two
natures of Christ (human and
divine), the church came into con¬
flict with Byzantium. But this the¬
ological dispute masked a political
concern: Armenia wanted to set
itself apart from both Byzantium
and Persia, two rival empires which
often clashed on its territory. The
break with Byzantium was com¬
pleted in 609.
The determination to be inde¬
pendent also resulted in the cre¬
ation of an Armenian alphabet in
about 405. Written Armenian
replaced liturgical Greek and
became one of the church's main
instruments for unifying the Armen¬
ian people. Drawing strength from
their specific religious and linguis¬
tic identity, the Armenians man¬
aged to survive in a hostile environ¬
ment and thwart repeated attempts
by other nations to assimilate them.
Towards the middle of the sev¬
enth century, the Arabs conquered
Byzantine Armenia. People con¬
verted in increasing numbers to
Islam, especially among the nobil
ity. Only two princely families on
the outer reaches of Armenia
remained Christian: the Bagralids
in the north, and the Artsrunis in
the south. But in 862 the Caliph
appointed Ashot Bagratuni
"Prince of Princes", and made him
"King of Armenia" twenty years
later. Armenia regained its inde¬
pendence shortly thereafter.
TH E RENAISSANCE OF ARMENIAN ART
Ashot, who had become Ashot I
after being crowned by the
Catholicos (the spiritual head of
the church), ushered in a period
of peace and prosperity that was
Bas-relief on the east
gable of Surb Nshan
church, below, shows
Princes Smbat and
Kurike, sons of the
church's founder,
holding a model of
the building.
,/^-S
^Ê^^Ê
42
the unesco Courier may t99s
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The monastery roofs.
Left, Surb Nshan
(Holy Cross) church.
to last 120 years. Armenian art
enjoyed a renaissance. In about
961, the Bagratid family founded
a new capital at Ani, now part of
Turkey. At that time a mere for¬
tified village, Ani was transformed
into a wondrous city "with forty
gates, 100 palaces and 1,000
churches", according to chroni¬
clers of the time.
Armenian architecture blos¬
somed with the construction of
the church of the 1 loly Cross, on
Aghtamar Island, and of Ani
cathedral. Philosophy, theology
and literature faculties were set
up within tin; precincts of monas¬
teries. The neighbouring monas¬
teries of Haghpat and Sanabin
were restored and enlarged and
became cultural and educational
centres by the end of the tenth
century. The period's leading
architect, Trdat, restored Ilagia
Sophia cathedral in Constantino¬
ple, built Ani cathedral and was
responsible for the expansion of
Haghpat monastery.
The Haghpat monastery com¬
plex overlooks the Pambak River
in northern Armenia's Lori region.
It was built, not on a peak, but
halfway up a hillside on a site cho¬
sen to afford protection and con¬
cealment from prying eyes and
also in response to a kind of monas¬
tic humility. It is built on a ver¬
dant promontory located in the
middle of a mountain cirque,
which is often wreathed in clouds.
A peak on the opposite side of the
river is over 2,500 metres high.
The monastery seen
from the northeast.
At left, the 13th-
century bell tower.
The monasteries of northern
Armenia are not isolated, unlike
their counterparts in the coun¬
try's arid regions. They were built
ina village environment. Haghpat,
for example, is surrounded by
many hamlets, and Sanahin's
domes rise from the centre of a
village.
THE ORIGINAL CHURCH
The little church of Surb Nshan
(the 1 loly Cross) is Ilaghpat's ear¬
liest building. Begun in 966-67,
it was later enlarged and embell¬
ished by the architect Trdat and
his team. Like many other
churches and monasteries, it was
endowed by prominent feudal
families. A typical example of
tenth-century Armenian archi¬
tecture, its central dome rests on
the four imposing pillars of the
lateral walls. The outside walls
are dotted with triangular
recesses. A fresco in the apse
depicts Christ Pantocralor. Its
donor, the Armenian Prince
Khutulukhaga, is depicted in the
south transept (a transversal nave
intersecting the main jiave). The
sons of the church's founder,
Princes Smbal and Kurike, are
shown with Queen Khosravanuche
in a bas-relief on the east gable.
Apart from one or two minor
restorations carried out in the
eleventh and twelfth centuries,
the church has retained its origi¬
nal character.
THEUNLSCO ÇçHIRICR MAYI^S
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
A local noble family, the
Kiurikians, made the church their
spiritual centre and the monastery
grew spectacularly. Two new build¬
ings were added to it St. Gre¬
gory's church (1005-25) and the
chapel of the Virgin Mary along
with several circular defence walls
with two fortified gates.
Armenia's golden age came to
an end in the mid-eleventh cen¬
tury. Ani was taken by the Byzan¬
tines. The last Bagratid king abdi¬
cated. At the end of the century,
Turkish-Mongol Seljuks com¬
pleted their conquest of Arme¬
nia. In about 1130, an earthquake
damaged Haghpat, which was not
restored until fifty years later. But
those eventful years did not in any
way impair the monastery's spiri¬
tual influence.
A khatchkar, a stone
slab engraved with a
cross and intricate
designs.
A khatchkar set in
the monastery wall.
paved by tombstones of the
Kiurikan family.
At that time, several hundred
monks lived in Haghpat monastery.
They could eat in a refectory, but
there was no dormitory because
they had formed the habit of lodg¬
ing in villages in the valley. They
produced the Haghpat Gospels
(1211), an illuminated manuscript
renowned for miniatures in which
secular features blend into reli¬
gious scenes. One illumination
¡ shows a man and a woman in
I Armenian dress welcoming Jesus
Ï before the gates of Jerusalem.
The fortress of Kaian was built
nearby in 1233 to protect Hagh¬
pat and Sanahin from invading
Mongols. Although the monastery
was captured and destroyed a few
years later, its life did not come to
a halt.
In the mid-thirteenth century,
three important buildings were
added to the site. One of them was
the campanile, or zangakatun,
which stands apart from the
church at the highest point of the
site. An elongated construction
topped by a short octagonal spire,
it has three floors, each contain¬
ing recesses and apses with one or
more altars. The library, or mate-
nadaran (1258-68), is a square,
compact building directly con¬
nected to the church by what is
known as the "Saviour's Passage".
The great jamatun or chapter¬
house which the monks used for
assemblies is also connected to the
church by a vaulted arcade. Built
in the same style as the gavit, it is
the work of the father superior,
Hamazasp. Outside the monastery
walls, the monks also built the
Holy Zion chapel (1268) in a vil¬
lage farther down the hill.
But the Mongol incursions
resumed. Tamerlane's invasions
(1387-1405) put an end to fur¬
ther attempts to reconstitute a
Greater Armenia. Between the
fourteenth and seventeenth cen¬
turies, Haghpat was frequently
damaged, and on two occasions,
in 1651 and 1677, the Armenian
apostolic church undertook
restoration work.
On the eve of the Second
World War, the Soviet Socialist
Republic of Armenia's Commit¬
tee for the Preservation ofMonu¬
ments made plans for a compre¬
hensive restoration of the site. At
the end of 1991, Armenia again
became independent. The town
council of Tumanian is now respon¬
sible for the upkeep of Haghpat,
which still belongs to the church
of Armenia, while the culture min¬
istry is responsible for its restora¬
tion. A long-term approach to the
preservation ofArmenia's historic
and spiritual heritage can finally
be adopted.
A WIDENING SPHERE
OFINFLUENCE
At the beginning of the thirteenth
century, the monastery acquired
a gavit, a large construction resem¬
bling a narthex (an entrance hall
between the porch and nave of a
church) which shows this feature
of ecclesiastical architecture in its
most fully developed form. The
gavit was used for meetings, teach¬
ing and funerals. In line with the
principles of vernacular wooden
architecture, its roof rests on four
central pillars. Above the arches
of the square central area, inter¬
secting arches divide the building
into nine parts. Light streams into
the building through a lantern
crowning the highest central sec¬
tion (the yerdik). The floor is partly
> .**"*, ,
#
TAN
NINE CENTURIES OF INFLUENCE
966-991:
Construction of Surb Nshan church
1105:
Destruction of the church by the Seljuks
13th century:
Northern Armenia's main spiritual and educational centre;
construction of new buildings
Mid-17th century:
Restoration of the site
1688:
A destructive earthquake
1940-1960-1980:
Plans for restoring the site during the Soviet period
1996:
Inclusion on the World Heritage List
- - i lirti
44
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 199S
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
LISTENING
BY ISABELLE LEYMARIE
Pioneer of bebop, Afro-Cuban and Brazilian jazz,
Dizzy Gillespie (1917-1993) was a colourful figure
and, with Louis Armstrong and Miles Davis, one of
jazz's trinity of great trumpet-players.
Roy Eldridge, six years his senior, who was
regarded as the fastest and most innovative trum¬
peter then playing and who was at that time with
Teddy Hill's band. When not rehearsing or per¬
forming, Dizzy spent all his time studying har¬
mony on the piano, a grounding to which he later
attributed his ability to play in any key. It was
about this time that his fellow trumpeter Palmer
Davis, impressed both by his virtuosity and his
non-stop fooling about, nicknamed him "Dizzy".
John llirks Gillespie was born in Cheraw,
a small town in South Carolina. Neither
his father, a builder who led a dance-band at
weekends, nor his mother took much interest in
his education. But young John was bright and
curious about everything, especially music.
Unbeknown to his father, he practised on the
various band instruments stored in the house
and learned to play the trumpet with a neigh¬
bour's son.
As a teenager, he worked for a time on one of
the public-works projects set up by the Roo¬
sevelt Administration under the New Deal. But
manual labour was not to his liking, and he soon
obtained a scholarship to the Laurinburg Tech¬
nical Institute, an agricultural college for Blacks
in North Carolina. He played trombone and then
trumpet in the college band, and started study¬
ing musical theory and trying his hand at the
piano. At weekends he performed with a small
group of teenage musicians. The cornetist King
Oliver, who was giving a concert locally, heard
him play and offered him a job, but Dizzy pre¬
ferred to stay with his friends.
In 1935, he left high school to move with his
mother to Philadelphia, where he sat in on innu¬
merable jam sessions and, at eighteen, joined the
Frankie Fairfax band. His first role model was
The birth of bebop
In 1937, Dizzy moved in with his brother in
Harlem, where he hung around the Savoy Ball¬
room and jammed with the Savoy Sultans, Fess
Williams, Claude Hopkins, Willie Bryant and
Chick Webb. Webb, who had just discovered a
young singer named Ella Fitzgerald, realized
that his was an exceptional talent and often
called him in as replacement solo trumpet. When
Dizzy started his first big band in 1946, he
toured the southern states with Ella and encour¬
aged her to take up scat-singing.
Dizzy became friendly with Mario Bauza, one
of Webb's trumpeters, and, at the Cotton Club,
with the flautist Alberto Socarras, who between
them introduced him to Cuban music. A few
months later, he met the sax and clarinet player
Teddy Hill, who was just about to set off on a
European tour and was looking for a trumpeter.
Dizzy talked him into giving him a break and, in
a career move that went beyond his wildest
dreams, took over from his mentor Roy Eldridge
in the band. He impressed audiences with his
embouchure and perfected his high-register play¬
ing, his soaring riffs and a harmonic concept that
was far ahead of its time (so far that the singer Cab
Calloway, who hired him in 1939, forbade him to
> G"THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1998
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
play what unable to understand it he called his
"Chinese" music).
After the commercially-oriented swing era
with its mainly While big bands (Benny Good¬
man, Jimmy and Tommy Dorsey), Black jazzmen
were gripped by a fever of creativity. The most
innovative of them, guitarist Charlie Christian,
Thelonious Monk, drummer Kenny Clarke and
Charlie Parker, the latter fresh from Kansas
City, met for jam sessions in the clubs of Harlem,
including the famous Million's Playhouse. That
was where, according to Miles Davis, musicians
really cut their teeth; they had lo have played at
Minion's to earn a reputation among jazzmen.
Dizzy and his friends experimented there with
unfamiliar harmonies and frenzied tempo, and
created numbers with jokey titles. It was from
these experiments that bebop was to emerge,
soon to lake definite shape in the clubs of Fifty-
second Street, jazz's new centre of gravity.
The elder statesman of jazz
In 1941, Dizzy was accused by Cab Calloway of
throwing a spitball at him during a gig and was
thrown out of the band. He played with various
groups, including the one led by pianist Karl
Hines for which he wrote Night in Tunisia, and
then formed a revolutionary little group with
bass-player Oscar Pettiford, performing at the
Onyx Club on Fifty-second Street, As he tells it,
they played lots of untitled original numbers,
with Dizzy chanting "Dee-ba-pa-n-bebop" as the
lead-in. When the fans wanted to hear one of
these unnamed pieces they would call out for
"bebop". The press soon got hold of the term
and started to call their music bebop.
Dizzy next joined Billy Eckstine's big band,
the first to be inspired by bebop, at the same
time pursuing a career as an arranger. In 1945, a
year that was to be decisive for him, he teamed
uj) with Charlie Parker, his musical alter ego, and
recorded the historic bebop tracks Grooviu'
high, All the Things You Are, Salt Peanuts and
Hot House with various groups of musicians. It
was at this time that he began to blow out his
cheeks like a hamster when playing and to sport
a beret, a goatee and wire-framed glasses, a look
that all his fans hastened lo copy.
In 1946, Dizzy formed a big band that was
joined, the following year, by the remarkable
Cuban conga player Chano Pozo, who could speak
no English. When asked how they managed to
communicate, Pozo would reply: "Dcchee no peek
pani, me no peek Angli, bo peek African". This
was the first time drums played with the hands
rather than with drumsticks entered the jazz
world in the slavery period, Whiles had sys¬
tematically destroyed African-style drums.
Together, Dizzy and Pozo wrote Manteca, Tin
Tin Deo and Cubana lie Cubana Bop, composi¬
tions that led the way for "Latin jazz". A concert
they gave at the Salle Pleyel, Paris, in 1948 had
a stunning effect on all French jazzmen, coming as
a revelation both of bebop and of the red-hot
rhythms of Afro-Cuban music. On 2 December
that same year, at the age of thirty-three, Pozo
was murdered in a Harlem bar.
On 6 January 1953, at a party in a club, an
actor accidentally fell on Dizzy's trumpet, bend¬
ing the mouth and giving it the famous upturned
shape. "My instrument, when you hit a note, Bam!
You hear it right then, instead of waiting," he
said. In 1956, Dizzy, then at the height of his
powers, was sponsored by the State Department
to lour the Middle East and Latin America with
his new big band. Refusing to act as an official
spokesman for the United Stales, he made friends
among the locals in the various countries he visited
and gave free invitations to his concerts to children
and poor people. In Brazil, he discovered the
samba and the bossa nova, which he popularized
in the United Slates, and in Buenos Aires he met
the young pianist Lalo Schifrin, signing him up
for his band a few years later.
In 1964, he ran for the presidency of the
United States on a platform of abolishing racism
and uniting all the peoples of the world. He sug¬
gested that the White House be renamed the
Blues House, and that Miles Davis be appointed
head of the CIA and Max Roach Minister of
Defense. In the late 1960s, he converted to
Baha'ism, a faith of Persian origin that preaches
tolerance and universal love.
Dizzy performed until the end of his life in
many different venues, including the While
House, where, with President Jimmy Carter, he
played Sait Peanuts, the anthem of bebop. "I
like playing. I like people. I love making people
laugh, and I do just as I please", he said. Deco¬
rated by the American and French Governments,
proclaimed bashere (a Yoruba princely title) of
Iperu, Nigeria, he became towards the end of his
days an elder statesman of jazz.
Somebody once asked Dizzy what legacy he
would like to leave behind. "I would like people
to know how to pronounce my name: Dizzy, D-I-
Z-Z-Y!", he answered.
46 he unesco Courier may i
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
T E R VI E W Marcel Marceau
The art
of silence
You have been appearing on stage all over the
world for more than fifty years. Why is it that you are
more popular abroad than at home in France?
Marcel Marceau: I have performed a great deal
in France. It was here, in 1 947, that I created the
character of Bip, the dreamy little poet who
appears in all my shows. After performing in
Jean Louis-Barrault's troupe, I set up my own
company in 1948, and between then and 1964
I staged twenty-six mime plays, or "mimod-
ramas" as I prefer to call them. Since pure
mimodrama was not recognized as a theatrical
art form I received no subsidy, so I had to
raise the funds for my productions by inter¬
national tours. I have given performances on all
five continents, with particular success in the
United States and Japan, and appeared many
times on television. But my financial difficul¬
ties, particularly after the only partial success
oí Donjuán, a mimodrama adapted from the
play by Tirso de Molina, produced in 1964,
forced me to disband my troupe that year and
begin appearing alone on stage.
I became a solo mime, but unlike singers,
who can be listened to at any time on records
or on the radio, mimes are masters of silence,
soon forgotten if they don't appear on stage
regularly.
Mime is a universal language that doesn't
require translation. Perhaps that is another
explanation of your success?
M.M.: Yes, that's true, but French audiences
seem to me rather conservative, despite the
fact that France has a great tradition of mime
and has produced many famous exponents of
the art. Unesco asked me to be one of its
goodwill ambassadors but unfortunately, as I
am always on tour, I didn't think I could be
very effective in that role, though I did work
with that splendid Organization on a film
defending copyright and authors' rights.
Eventually I asked the French authorities to
help me prevent the art of mime from disap-
The world-famous
French mime Marcel
Marceau breaks his
silence and talks
about the secrets of
his craft and the
highlights of a career
spanning five
decades. Interview by
Michel Fargeon.
pearing. As a result I was able to set up the Mar¬
cel Marceau International School of Mimo¬
drama in Paris, which receives a subsidy from the
City of Paris. It provides courses of training in
several subjects (dance, fencing, acrobatics,
drama) and is attended by students from all
over the world. Some former students arc work¬
ing with me on the preparation of a show, The
Bowler Hat, a tribute to Chaplin that will be
performed internationally in several theatres.
Do you feel when you are on stage that you are
delivering a text, even though you don't say a word?
M.M.: Yes indeed, I feel that I am both an
author and an actor at the same time. Although
my performance is silent, I am not acting by
means of gesture alone. I am using the power
of thought. I communicate with the audience
by means of the thought that goes into every
movement and every pose. Writers make con¬
tact with their readers by means of words and
THÏ UNESCO (oUKIER I 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
the way they give form to words through a
story. Mimes are always, by definition, word¬
less, but they present the fable of human life
on stage by means of an art that transcends
words. I often make use of themes that tran¬
scend language, suchas The Heart Eater, The
Cage, or The Mask-Maker, which are the
titles of some of my sketches. They are actu¬
ally parables that express deep thoughts.
Dancers do this by movement, but the mime
does it by remaining motionless, by simply
being there.
Could it be said that the spectators recreate
within themselves what you are doing on stage?
M.M.: Yes, exactly. Unless the audience is
drawn into the action, the mime has failed to
get his message across the footlights, his per¬
formance is closer to mimesis than to the true
art of mime. He has not succeeded in radiating
the poetical aura that evokes in the spectator
what I would describe as a "zen" identifica¬
tion with the character portrayed. Laughter
is aroused by what appear to us as distortions
or discrepancies in relation to what is "nor¬
mal", but the laughing stops when the out¬
come is tragic, when death intervenes. The great
Charlie Chaplin's films illustrate this very well.
Although the cinema audience go along to
laugh at Chaplin's antics, at some point they
stop laughing, they succumb to emotion and
suddenly see the character he plays in a differ¬
ent light. Comedy and tragedy disrupt the
rules established by society.
What influence have Chaplin's films had on your
work?
M.M.: The character of Bip was entirely inspired
by Chaplin. He was very popular when I was a
child, and by the age of ten I was already imi¬
tating his funny walk. He and my teacher, Eti¬
enne Decroux, who invented the grammar of
mime, its rigorous control of the body, inspired
me to opt for the art of silence. I also studied
under Charles Dullin, who taught me about
lyrical rhythm and the inspiring power of the
spoken word. Chaplin in fact started out by
performing in music halls, as a singer, dancer
and acrobat. His performance in silent films was
pure mime and he was so affected by that expe¬
rience that, long after the talkies had come in, he
was still turning down speaking roles.
You could have been a dancer. . .
M.M.: No, I might have had a talent for move¬
ment, but dancing involves pirouettes and leaps
whereas mime, an art of bodily expression, of
what my mentor Etienne Ducroux called
"moving statuary", borrows its postures from
Graeco-Roman statues, giving it scope for
beauty and virtuosity. Immobility is a very
important part of it, but so are acrobatics and
the visual element. Since it can be abstract, sur¬
realist or melodramatic at will, it has an explo¬
sive impact on the feelings. There is in the the¬
atre of mime a kind of inner respiration that
renders visible the invisible, sculpts forms out
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
_
! ^
1 ^
i
^^B ^^r
^¡¿3 1 1
.. .
1
1
m
^^ j
of space and lends wings to the characters'
thoughts. Whereas the dancer is more ethereal
and tends to fly away like a balloon, the mime
artist is held down by his body movements.
Do you also find inspiration in art forms like
Japanese kabuki, nôor butho, or African dances?
M.M.: Yes, mime naturally borrows from the
other arts: the Japanese theatre, as you rightly
say, including bunraku, the traditional puppet
theatre, from which I learned a great deal
I've toured Japan twenty or so times and
the Italian commedia dell'arte, the British
music-hall, Indian and Cambodian dancing
and contemporary Western dance. Not need¬
ing words to express itself, mime is in touch
with all cultures
You both design and perform your own pieces,
and recreate and reinvent them with every
performance. Do you have a favourite audience, one
that is more receptive, more knowledgeable than
others?
M.M.: Mime has a grammar of its own that
needs to be respected, an insistence upon clas¬
sical perfection that has to be constantly
upheld and renewed. As to spectators, chil¬
dren are the most receptive; they make a mar¬
vellous audience. In the silent ceremony of
mime, which demands intense concentration,
they are in perfect communication with the
performer. They are totally responsive; unbe¬
known to themselves, they are telling the
story. When I play an angel, for instance, they
identify so fully with the character that they
become that angel themselves, thanks to a
power of imagination that no adult possesses
to the same degree. Like fairy stories, mime
reinstates that imaginative faculty of theirs.
Even though they sometimes become fidgety,
they are spellbound. They think they are magi¬
cians, and so do I.
Why are there so few female mimes?
M.M.: That was true a few years ago, but more
and more women now want to take it up. In
nineteenth-century mime theatre, women
played frivolous creatures or great men's
muses, seductresses or unfaithful wives. They
were always a foil to the male characters. In
her mime play La mémoire des femmes, Anne
Sicco, my former wife, gave women a more
important role than they had in my produc¬
tions, where they only played so-called female
parts, as flower-sellers for instance. There are
more and more parts now for women. Dozens
of them are studying mime in my school.
Why doesn't the cinema show much interest in
mime?
M.M.: Charlie Chaplin and Harry Langdon
were brilliant mimes. Films like Modern Times
(1936), which Chaplin directed and in which
he showed his incomparable mime artistry,
have kept the world laughing for generations,
but it is true that mime does not interest mod¬
ern directors. I am sure film-makers in the next
century will take an interest in it.
How do you manage to stay so young?
M.M.: Although I am over seventy, I still find
time to enjoy life. I also stick to a healthy diet,
not eating much and not drinking alcohol. I
have several projects on the go. As an illustra¬
tor I am working on a book for bibliophiles
entitled La ballade de Paris et du monde. As
an author, I have written a book about Bip
that has been translated into five languages,
and another, entitled Pimporello, a poetical
story about an Italian mime and a young
orphan girl that I would like to adapt for the
screen. Age means different things to different
people, that's all there is to it! {He mimes an
old man who suddenly becomes a child.)
THE UNESCO ÇpURIIER MAY 1998
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
At the crossroads of
science and ethics
Introducing a new Unesco book series
TrÄ UNESCO
Courier
^^51st YEAR
Published monthly in 27 languages and in
Braille by Umesco, The United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
31, rue François Bonvin,
75732 Paris CEDEX 15, France.
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68.57.45
e-mail unesco couner@unesco org
Inlernet http //www unesco org
I
At a time when the consequences of rapid developments in science and technology
are increasingly difficult for non-specialists to grasp, citizens require tools to help
them make informed choices in a wide range of fields. To meet this need UNESCO Pub¬
lishing has launched a series of books, entitled "Ethics", aimed at a wide public and
designed to present some complex issues facing modern societies within a global
context and to stimulate reflexion on their ethical dimensions.
The first book in the series, The ethics oflife, consists of contributions by noted
scientists, philosophers, jurists and theologians from a variety of cultural, linguis¬
tic and religious backgrounds to a meeting on "Physiology and the Respect for
Life" organized by the International Union of Physiological Sciences (IUPS) and
UNESCO. It examines such questions as respect for life and the founding of bioethics,
animal testing, the legal aspects of experimentation on the living, and respect for
human life in research and medicine.
Forthcoming titles in the Ethics scries will focus on the ethics of women's
health, the ethics of energy consumption, ethics committees and the ethics of the
Human Genome Project.
The ethics of life
edited by Denis Noble and Jcan-Didier Vincent. 1998,238 pp. 135 French francs.
AUTHORS
GEORGES B. KUTUKDJIAN, a philosopher and anthropologist, is director of Unesco's Bioethics Unit. He is the author of several
published works, and was co-editor, with Antonio Papisca, of a collective work on the rights of peoples published by CEDAM,
Padua, 1991.
JEAN AUDOUZE, a French astrophysicist, is a research supervisor at his country's National Centre of Scientific Research (CNRS).
He has written several science books intended for the general public, including Regards sur le visible ("Looking at the Visible", with
Jean-Claude Carrière, Pion publishers, Paris, 1996) and L'Univers {"'[he Universe", "Que-saisje?" series, Presses Universitaires de
France, 1997). He is the author of a report for Unesco preparatory to the creation of a World Commission on the Ethics of Scientific
Knowledge and Technology.
NICHOLAS A. ASHFORD, of the United States, is professor of technology and policy at the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology (MIT), where he teaches environmental law and policy. He is the author of Crisis in the Workplace: Occupational Disease
and injury (MIT Press, 1976) and co-author of Chemical Exposures: Low Levels and High Stakes (John Wiley Press, second edition,
1998).
GORDON BENNETT, a Canadian public servant, is chief of policy and strategic planning at the National Historic Sites Directorate,
Parks Canada. He is the author of Mon Transportation: A History (1978) and of many articles on cultural heritage policy.
NIKITA LOPOUCHKINE, a Canadian public servant, is acting director of his country's Natural Resources Branch at the National
Parks Directorate. He is the author of many works on ecology and the restoration of ecosystems.
JENS ERIK FENSTAD, of Norway, is professor of mathematical logic at the University of Oslo and a member of the Norwegian
Academy of Letters and Sciences. He is chairman of the Standing Committee for the Physical and Engineering Sciences of the
European Science Foundation.
MICHAEL KIRBY, an Australian High Court justice, is a member of Unesco's International Bioethics Committee and of the Ethics,
Law and Social Issues Committee of the Human Genome Organization.
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American journalist specializing in environmental questions.
ELISABETH BAUDOURIAN, an Armenian-born French journalist, is general co-ordmator of Nouvelles d'Arménie magazine.
MICHEL FARGEON is a French journalist specializing in the performing arts.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-American musicologist, has recently published La musique sud-américaine, Rythmes et danses d'un
continent ("South American Music: A Continent's Rhythms and Dances", Gallimard, Pans, 1997).
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor Gillian Whitcomb
English edition. Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel (33) (0)
1.45 68 46 90)
Documentation" Jose Banaag
(Tel (33) (0}1 45 68. 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and
press. Solange Beim
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45 68 46 87)
Film duplication: Daniel Meister
Secretariat: Annie Brächet
(Tel (33) (0)1 45 68 47 15).
Administrative Assistant Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish
and Korean. (Tel, (33) (0) 1.45 68.45.69)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian. Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian Jahl Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de
Janeiro)
Urdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili. Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese Feng Mmgxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Smhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Rntta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai DuangtipSunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali: Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernandez (Santiago de
Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax: (33) (0)1.45.68 57 45
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68.45.65). Jacqueline
Louise-Julie, Mamchan Ngonekeo, Mohamed
Salan El Din (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 49.19)
Customer service: Michel Ravassard,
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45 68.45.91)
Accounts: (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 65)
Shipping" Daniel Meister
(Tel (33) (0)1 45.68 47 50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel.: (33) (0)1 45 68 45.65
1 year- 211 French francs 2 years: 396 FF
Students, lyear 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues 72 FF
Developing countries.
1 year: 132 French francs 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible
currency to the order of Unesco or by Visa,
Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
Unesco Courier", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to Ihe editor Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon cov¬
ering postage Signed articles express the opinions ol the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
Umesco or those ol the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff The boundaries on maps published in the magazine
do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco
or the United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, (2) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100 U S A . (3) N C R Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head Inc , 111 West 40th Street, New
York, U.S A , (4) Bell and Howell Co , Old Mansfield Road.
Wooster, Ohio 44691, USA
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL CI -MAY 1998
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ
PAR LES N M P P.
Photocomposition, photogravure*
Le Courrier de I Unesco
Impression. Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 5-1998-0PI-98-571 A
50 ) QuTHE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1918
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S World Reports-
topical and engaging references UNESCO
Publishin
World Education
Report 1998
Teachers and Teaching in a
Changing World
Lack of resources, lack of support,
lack of training, poorly equipped
schools and overcrowded
classrooms: this new edition of the
World Education Report focuses
on the world's 57 million teachers.
(178 pp.)
World Communication
Report
The media and the challenge
of the new technologies
The digital revolution and the
convergence of technologies have
radically altered the world's media
landscapes, giving rise to a number
of concerns, from disparities
between regions to risks stemming
from the globalization of media and
the standardization of contents.
(298 pp.)
World Information Report
1997/98
A comprehensive picture of library and
information services on the five
continents and an analysis of the
challenges facing this field, from the
future of books and copyright to the
information highways and economic
intelligence.
(390 pp.)
World Science Report
1998
The organization and conduct of science
and technology around the world and
the role played by science in resolving
major issues facing human society such
as food security, water resources and
disease.
(approx. 300 pp., available in May 1998)
World Culture Report
1998
First edition of an intercultural report
that analyses the multiple links between
culture, development and identity,
backed up by a wealth of indicators,
(approx. 350 pp., available in June 1998)
UNESCO Publishing
7, place de Fontenoy
75732 Paris 07 SP
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 41
Internet:
http://www.unesco.org/
publishing
Unesco on line via Interne
ÏÏM
rrently on-line are: an index of the contents of the last
issues of the Unesco Courier, Unesco press releases,
[dresses, fax, telex and electronic mail numbers of
esco's regional offices, National Commissions and Unesco
lbs, the directory of Unesco databases and information
ivices, colour images of the Japanese Garden and other
zhitectural sites at Unesco Headquarters, as well as works
art suchas Henry Moore's reclining sculpture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
THEME OF NEXT MONTH'S ISSUE:
PRISONS
A system on trial
INTERVIEW
AMERICAN CHOREOGRAPHER SUSAN BUIRGE
HERITAGE
THE IMPERIAL CITY OF HUÉ (VIET NAM)
msJR
St.'';' %:."-..
I
^__
]]>
</page>
</document>
