<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="112053eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m
i . r
V
r
/ H
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (oURIER. NUiOti INTERNATIONAL PHOTO COMPETITION
PEACE IN EVERYDAY LIFE
Indonesian boys work
together on an outdoor
task. Photo by Gede
Gusti (Indonesia).
In 1994, Archbishop
Desmond Tutu called the
new South Africa the
"rainbow nation". Left,
rainbow children pose
with a cardboard cut-out
of the famous cleric.
Photo by Guy Hobbs
(United Kingdom).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO Q>U RI ER
48
Susan Buirge
A choreographer intent on bringing together
contemporary and traditional forms ofdance
Cover:
A plane flies over the prison walls.
Photo taken by Guy Oprey while he was an inmate
in London's Wandsworth prison
(see page 35).
© Guy Oprey/Znside fye/Panos Pictures. Londres
contents
JUNE 1998
PRISONS
a system in crisis
An institution on trial	4
by Edmundo Oliveira
A prisoner's testimony 6
by Louis Perego
Waiting behind bars Photos	8
Alternatives to jail 10
by José Luis de la Cuesta Arzamendi
Invisible chains 13
by Linda Johansson
From revenge to reparation	15
by Tony Peters
South Africa: puppets in prison Photos	18
Prisons for profit 20
by Leonard L. Cavise
Offenders' rights	23
by Monika Platek
Women inmates with their children Photos	26
The changing role of prison staff 28
byAbdel-AzIm Wazir
The hard way back	30
by Amadou Cissé Dia
Political prisoners 31
par Dirk van ZylSmit
Prison through prisoners'eyes Photos	35
Fact file	38
Consultant: Edmundo Oliveira
Commentary Federico Mayor 40
GREENWATCH Water: will there be enough? by France Bequette 42
LISTENING Colombian champeta by Isabelle Leymarie 10
AUTHORS 50
THE UNESCO ^URIER JUNE 1998 V
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
An institution on trial
BY EDMUNDO OLIVEIRA 2L¿^¿^Ú^^
Prison causes more ethical, social, psychological
and economic problems than it solves. What can be done to improve
the penal system?
In the late twentieth century, an age of
supposedly scientific penology,
humanity has far to go before it reaches that
perfect state where it can do away with prisons.
Modern society still finds it necessary to
respond to crime with punishment.
The retributive character of penal measures
stems directly from the nature of the appara¬
tus used to fight crime. In spite of advances
in criminology in discovering the causes of
crime, there still remains a probability that
crimes and misdemeanours will be commit¬
ted, and the threat of sanctions as a deterrent
is thus indispensable.
But if punishment is a necessity, it must
not infringe certain inalienable human rights.
Above all, penalties must be proportional to
the wrong that has been caused and to the
o ffender's degree of culpability. The principle
in physics that every action gives rise to an
equal and opposite reaction might be applied
here. But perhaps the idea of the just penalty
is a Utopian dream. Although a perfect solu¬
tion is unattainable, a reasonable solution must
be sought, which means proceeding, as in
mathematics, by successive approximations,
setting the offence and its consequences against
the sacrifice imposed on the perpetrator by
the punishment inflicted. What, for instance,
is the point of inflicting a penalty involving
loss of civil rights on someone who has already
brought his own name into disrepute?
Regrettably, prison continues to generate
more ethical, social, psychological and eco¬
nomic problems than it solves. In practice, the
rehabilitation desired by many systems of
criminal law around the world ends in disil¬
lusionment, despair and revolt against a soci¬
ety that closes its doors to ex-convicts. The
judicial system is still seeking ways to carry out
Visiting day at Gatesville
women's prison, Texas
(U.S.A.).
THE UNESCO lOURIER |UNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The cell's naked light bulb.
Photo taken by Michael Inns
penal sanctions that provide adequate «hile he was an inmate at
Wandsworth prison in London
responses to the need for the psychological (see page 35).
rehabilitation of offenders and their reinte¬
gration into society.
There is an urgent need to find alternatives
to custodial sentences, so that offenders with
the exception of those who posea definite and
continuing threat can be re-educated for pro¬
ductive lives in society. Every penologist knows
that most criminals retain some vestiges of
morality, feel rejected and scorned, seek for¬
giveness from their families and the community
for the offence they have committed and fre¬
quently acknowledge the validity of their pun¬
ishment. They often turn themselves in, and
remorse even leads some of them to take their
own lives.
If the judicial system itself regards sentences
as punitive measures, how can inmates faced
with the soul-destroying experience of prison
life hope that they can ever again be useful mem¬
bers of society? It is indispensable to improve
and modernize penal and judicial systems so
that sentences and their application can restore
the inmate's dignity and prepare him or her
for a constructive role in society. Imprison¬
ment should be a last resort, for individuals
who pose a clear threat to the community.
The problems facing prison systems cannot
be solved in isolation, but must be consid¬
ered in relation to social justice and to the law-
enforcement and judicial systems and inte¬
grated into society as a whole. This requires the
active participation of all sectors of society,
THE UNESCO (^OURIER JUNE 1 998
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
which must set aside their prejudices and shed
their indifference.
Dealing with the problems of the prison
system calls for an innovative approach to
incarceration and the adoption of alternative
measures that, while punishing the offence,
are likely to re-educate the offender for respon¬
sible citizenship.
Should prison
be abolished?
A recent penal reform movement has put forward the
idea of abolishing prison, but although its underlying
logic can be defended in theory, there seems no obvious
way of putting the idea into effect in institutional terms,
given the current state of society.
Abolitionists emphasize the penal system's selective
nature and its limited operational capacity (prisons are
filled with poor people). They argue that incarceration
as a form of punishment has already been abolished for
those they call "underground criminals"lawbreakers
who escape imprisonment because of their prestige,
privilege or influence.
But blame for the impunity of "underground crimi¬
nals" should be laid at the doorstep of the judicial rather
than the penal system. What should be done is not abol¬
ish prisons or imprison all and sundry, but improve the effi¬
ciency of the criminal law. It would also be a good idea if,
once a sentence is handed down, it could subsequently
be adapted to take account of the offender's develop¬
ment during the rehabilitation process. H E. 0.
A prisoner's
Statue of blind justice in an
American library. She is
holding a sword and scales,
the symbols of truth and
impartiality.
After long years in gaol
a man becomes a student
and a writer
It is hard to talk about prison
without losing your cool. And if
you do, you risk getting caught up in a
confrontation with the supporters or
opponents of a system that, although
ineffective, seems indispensable.
My reason for testifying publicly
about areas of my life where the scars
have still not healed is that I would
like to help in the search for more sat¬
isfactory and more caring responses to
the problems of delinquency.
I come from what is euphemisti¬
cally known as a working-class back¬
ground, in other words from the
underclass. I was one of seven children,
and we were so poor that none of us
was able to stay on at school beyond
the minimum leaving age. The prospect
of working as a boiler-maker did not
appeal to me at all a wrong direction
that in the circumstances it was diffi¬
cult to correct. The mood of resigna¬
tion that settled in after 1968 put paid
to whatever illusions I still had about
a better and fairer world. In January
1970 I was arrested, with some of my
childhood buddies, for a hold-up
committed with a dummy weapon.
Prison came as a brutal shock. The
appalling physical conditions and to
an even greater extent the prevailing
outlook made me feel I had stepped
back into an age of barbarity. The grim
universe within the prison walls not
only seemed out of touch with the
outside world but to be embedded in
a punitive mentality bordering on bes¬
tiality. I felt utterly isolated from the
prison officers and my fellow inmates.
I also felt cut off from myself, and this
was not the least of the dangers I was
up against. I soon learned what life in
the jungle is all about. If you want to
> G>u:THE UNESCO l^pURIER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
testimony BY LOUIS PEREGO
survive you can't afford to trust
another living soul.
You start by withdrawing into a
shell. Then, if you don't crack up, you
get tougher, carefully concealing your
slightest weaknesses. You have to think
twice about every move you make. A
misplaced word or glance could lead
to all sorts of trouble. The pressure
was so intense that whatever vague feel¬
ings of remorse I might have had gave
way to a strong sense of injustice.
When you're always on your guard
you suffer physical and psychological
harm that is impossible to measure.
After serving four-and-a-half years of
a six-year sentence, I came out broken
and bent on revenge.
Drawing of a peephole used by
guards to look inside a cell
(France).
I tried to settle down; I became the
father of a little girl. But three years
after my release I was imprisoned for
armed robbery. The 1974 prison riots
had led to a handful of vague reforms.
Inmates were allowed to listen to the
radio, and washbasins and toilets were
installed in some (but not all) cells.
But the mentality had not changed and
arbitrary power still reigned supreme.
I found time to think about the
way my life was going. A spell of soli¬
tary confinement for a breach of disci¬
pline gave me an opportunity to brush
up on what I had learned in school and
pursue my education. I wasn't allowed
to attend the prison school, so I had to
work on my own. This time I served
eight years of a twelve-year sentence
and was released with a Master's in psy-
¡ chology under my belt. I knew things
¿ would be tough, but I had no idea how
| tough.
| Reintegration is a term that should
s be added to the list of empty, mean-
| ingless words. Mysteriously, everyone
| I contacted with a view to a job shied
3 away as if they had been tipped off
I about me. In July 1987, I committed
s another offence and was arrested again.
I wondered for a long time whether
life was worth living but loving sup¬
port from my companion and our
children helped me get back on my feet.
Writing my first book led to my
conditional release after three and half
years of preventive detention. But when
I showed up for a court date eighteen
months later, I was sentenced to twelve
years imprisonment, in other words I
had more than eight years to serve. I still
do not know how I managed to sur¬
vive that additional ordeal. Love and
the confidence a few people showed in
me had, of course, a lot to do with it.
Which just goes to show, whatever
some people may think, it's never too
late to start again. But what a waste.
Looking back, I can't help thinking it
could have been avoided.
THE UNESCO lOURIER I
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
aitin
"Most of the young men with numbers on
their white T-shirts are just waiting for the
sound of the gong which means that
another day has passed and there is one day
less to count before they can go back to
their families, where maybe a new brother
or sister has arrived, see their friends who
will have grown but not changed and live in
'a neighbourhood which will always produce
victims who cannot obtain the quality of
life produced by a society where money,
Mercedes and beauty are the ingredients that
count. As long as honesty and pride don't
count in society young men will commit
crimes which will put them behind bars and
give them boundless hours of waiting."
These lines by British photographer Tina
Gue accompany her coverage of a prison for
young men and a women's prison in
Djakarta (Indonesia). On these pages, a
selection of her photos.
The canteen
Chess game
8 ) QuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Mealtime
The prison school
THE UNESCO f3,URIER IUNEI998
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Alternatives to jail
BY JOSÉ LUIS DE LA CUESTA ARZAMEN DI
The application of non-custodial
sentences should be encouraged
wherever possible
Despite efforts to improve the quality
of inmates' lives, in most countries
prison is still by and large a place of exclusion
and segregation, synonymous with injustice
and pointless suffering. The steadily rising
prison population is straining the system's
capacity to breaking point and hindering the
application of more ambitious penal policies
that look further than the immediate prob¬
lems of imprisonment and overcrowding. Secu¬
rity requirements are so pressing in over¬
crowded prisons that the authorities do little
to create effective rehabilitation and social rein¬
tegration programmes (although such pro¬
grammes do exist). Add drug abuse in prison
and its associated problems Aids being the
most serious and the control of prison gangs
over inmates, and the picture looks grim indeed.
The prison system's difficulties in achiev¬
ing objectives such as rehabilitation and social
reintegration are not exactly new. Deprivation
of freedom, which was institutionalized in
the European judicial system during the late
eighteenth century, was intended as a more
rational and humane response to criminal acts
than the punishments that had previously
been meted out. But its framework of appli¬
cation prison soon proved incapable of
solving the individual and social conflicts that
crime brings about or reveals. Since then,
prison as an institution has always been in cri¬
sis. Its legitimacy has been called into ques¬
tion, and penologists have sought new ways of
improving the situation and, at the same time,
IP THE UNESCO (3)URIER |UNEI<>98
Two social rehabilitation programmes for young offenders in Los Angeles, California (U.S.A.).
Above, working in a school for severely handicapped children. Above right, a poetry reading
with senior citizens.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
¿VftUfryvCúvv
G ruvberget, below, is a former lumberjacks' village north of Stockholm where inmates
can spend a few days' vacation with their families. It was purchased by the Swedish
prison service in 1971.
m
5 ÇoUTHE UNESCO ^URIER JUNE 1998
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
looked for alternative solutions. This trend
has been gathering momentum since the sec¬
ond half of the nineteenth century.
A wide variety of alternatives to custodial
sentences are currently in use in many penal
systems. The most noteworthy include:
Attenuated execution ofsentences, includ¬
ing detention at home, semi-liberty, freedom
on licence, and various forms of discontinu¬
ous detention (e.g. during leisure time and/or
at weekends);
Probation, which ranges from a suspended
sentence to conditional remission of a sen¬
tence and a broad gamut of probationary and
conditional release measures;
Alternatives to custodial sentences that
benefit the offender as much as society. In
addition to fining, as traditionally used in
penal codes, many other alternatives now exist,
THE UNESCO GîURIER JUNE 1998
Top, young offenders at a "fire
camp" in Los Angeles, where
they train alongside
professional firefighters.
Above, physical training at
Harris County boot camp near
Houston, Texas (U.S.A.).
including accessory penalties or penalties that
restrict freedom or impose a ban on profes¬
sional activities, the deprivation or suspen¬
sion of certain rights and payment of dam¬
ages to the victim by the offender.
Community service as an alternative to
prison has been highly successful in many
European countries.1 Introduced for petty
delinquents in the United Kingdom in 1972,
this penalty deprives offenders of their free
time but should not prevent them from ful¬
filling their normal professional commitments.
Convicted offenders are required to do
between 40 and 240 hours of unpaid, socially
useful work over a period of one year to eigh¬
teen months. Community service is performed '
for charitable, humanitarian associations and
could include such tasks as helping the sick
or collecting blood or organs.
Community service is not applicable in
every case. It is primarily suitable for teenagers
and young adults who, though they have
committed minor offences, have not had their
sentences conditionally suspended. To become
common practice, this type of penalty requires
the creation of an assistance and supervisory
service as well as sufficient numbers of com¬
munity service jobs.
The search for alternatives to incarceration
is no remedy for the prison system's short¬
comings. The prison population includes
many individuals who have not been sen¬
tenced, but who are being held for question¬
ing or have been remanded in custody by a
court decision and are awaiting trial. In many
countries, they account for up to 50 per cent
of the total number of inmates.
Theoretically, these prisoners benefit from
the presumption of innocence, but their expe¬
rience of prison life is not really different from
that of convicted offenders. Methods other
than incarceration must be found to ensure
that they show up for trial. Some already exist,
such as mandatory rules of conduct, surrender
of certain documents, and bail. Judges should
encourage these practices as alternatives to
prison.
1 Community service as a main or alternative sentence is
applied in European countries including Austria (for
minors), Denmark, France, Germany, Ireland, the
Netherlands, Norway, Portugal, Spain, Sweden and
Switzerland.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Invisible chains
*£G
BY LINDA JOHANSSON
Sweden's electronic tagging project
miurowHUwntt
Electronic tagging is still only
practised in a few countries,
including Sweden and the
United States. Above, an
electronic bracelet strapped to
a young offender's ankle in
Tucson, Arizona (U.S.A.).
© Patrick Bard/Editing, Pans
Imprisonment is the most expensive
form of punishment in modern soci¬
ety. In Sweden, the upkeep of an inmate in an
open prison costs approximately 1,500 kroner
($200 or £120) a day, and around 2,000 kroner
($250 or £160) in a closed prison. Studies have
shown that incarceration has a negative impact
on detainees, who are forced to leave their fam¬
ilies, jobs and social life, and that prisons are
breeding grounds for criminality where young
inmates learn about crime from more experi¬
enced lawbreakers.
To address these issues, Sweden launched a
pilot project in 1994 in which minor offend¬
ers can choose to be put under electronic sur¬
veillance instead of going to prison. In six pro¬
bation districts, lawbreakers sentenced to
prison terms of two months or less were given
the option of living at home and wearing an
electronic ankle bracelet. Results surpassed
expectations and three years later the pro¬
gramme was expanded to include all offenders
nationwide sentenced to terms of three
months or less. Nearly half the 4,000 people
THE UNESCO G'lJ111^ JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
eligible for electronic tagging in the first six
months of 1997 had been convicted of
drunken driving.
O ffenders must meet several requirements
to be eligible for the programme. They must
have a recognized home, aphone and a job. In
addition, they must pay 50 kroner ($6 or £4)
a day for the duration of their sentence to
Victim Support, a charitable organization. A
1997 study showed that several offenders who
did not request the bracelet said the reason
was they could not afford the 50 kroner a day
or had neither a job nor a home.
Probation officers do all they can to assist
applicants, including trying to find them jobs
and slots in training programmes. A tempo¬
rary phone line paid for by the national pris¬
ons and probation administration can be
installed and offenders are encouraged to ask
relatives or friends to help them find hous¬
ing. Those who cannot afford the 50 kroner a
day are exempted from payment.
The tag is fastened around the offender's
ankle. A 50-centimetre high electronic trans¬
mitter installed at his or her home beams sig¬
nals to a surveillance centre. If the tag is
removed or the offender leaves home, the
transmitter immediately triggers an alarm and
the centre rings up the offender's home to
check for a possible malfunction. If the
offender is found to have broken the rules,
the tag is withdrawn and the rest of the sen¬
tence must be served in prison. But that sel¬
dom happens. The study showed that per¬
mission to work was suspended for
misconduct in only 5 per cent of cases, usually
because the offender had been drinking alco¬
hol. Infractions were most common among
offenders serving longer sentences.
Tight restrictions on movement
A probation officer draws up a tight schedule
that must be rigorously followed. Freedom
of movement is strictly limited. Offenders are
only allowed to leave home during working
hours, except for one hour each Saturday and
Sunday. If they are more than ten minutes off
schedule, the alarm is set off.
Most of the people who have been elec¬
tronically tagged say that it's at least as dis¬
tressing as being in a prison where there is
greater freedom of movement. In addition to
restrictions on leaving home, total abstinence
from the consumption of drugs and alcohol
is required. Probation officers make surprise
visits at all hours of the day or night, and at
these times offenders have to take an alcohol
breath test.
"If I didn't have a family," said Jan-Erik
Bengtsson, after wearing his tag for a very long
week, "I would rather have stayed in jail. I
can't even take out the garbage and I feel like
I'm always being watched. The breath tests are
very demeaning. You don't feel trusted and
it's very unpleasant not knowing when the
probation officer will show up." But like most
people who wear a tag, Mr. Bengtsson still
thinks it has some advantages. He can work
and continue living at home with his com¬
panion and their three children.
Electronic tagging has resulted in much
heavier workloads for probation officers,
many of whom say they no longer have
enough time for their regular duties and believe
that prison staff should be responsible for
keeping tabs on tagged offenders. They con¬
sider themselves overqualified for such tasks
most of them are sociologists with several
years of higher education behind them.
But electronic tagging also results in sav¬
ings. The upkeep cost per offender is approx¬
imately 450 kroner a day, two-thirds less than
the cost of imprisonment, and several correc¬
tional facilities have closed down for lack of
inmates. The next step will probably be to
include in the programme offenders sentenced
to terms of up to four months. The possibil¬
ity has been raised of extending eligibility to
lawbreakers sentenced to up to eleven months,
but the authorities prefer to act cautiously so
as not to jeopardize the potential of this alter¬
native to imprisonment.
Eighteenth-century convicts
employed on public works in
Bern (Switzerland). Period
engraving.
© Jean-Loup Charmet, Pans
14 > QuTHE UNESCO t^OURIER JUNE I 998
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
From revenge to reparation
BY TONY PETERS
Penal policy takes a new direction by confronting
offenders with the consequences of their acts and
giving them a chance to make amends
Over the past few decades, more atten¬
tion has been focused on the victims of
crime than on criminals. This raises two ques¬
tions. How far do legal systems take into
account victims' demands for justice in the sen¬
tences they mete out to offenders? And to
what extent do sentences respond to those
demands?
Eighteenth-century theories of law and
justice developed by the Enlightenment
philosophers in Europe form the basis of
what is now regarded as classical penal proce¬
dure, whose non-arbitrary character is quite
different from the procedure that prevailed
before the French Revolution. Many forms
of corporal punishment disappeared and were
replaced by simple, clear-cut punishments like
fines and prison sentences.
In the nineteenth century, the purpose of
prison sentences was to make criminals pay
their debt to society. Incarceration temporar¬
ily kept offenders out of the way while serv¬
ing as an example and a warning. Imprison¬
ment was also supposed to give offenders time
to reflect on their misdeeds.
With the citizen's safety uppermost in
Blackwell's Island
penitentiary in New York City
(U.S.A.) in the 19th century.
Period engraving.
mind, classical penologists emphasized a strictly
legal definition of crime and punishment. How¬
ever, as a result of the growing influence of the
behavioural sciences views of delinquency
changed and the idea that a single sentence is
appropriate for all offenders regardless of the
crime committed came under attack. A new
trend emerged whereby sentencing was
required to take each offender's circumstances
THE UNESCO (^URIER JUNE 1998 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
and personal history into account. Sentencing
criteria were no longer based on the legal defi¬
nition of the crime but on the threat to society
posed by the offender. A battery of alterna¬
tives to fit specific individuals and situations
were developed from the late nineteenth century
onwards, including prison terms for hardened
criminals, suspended sentences and probation
for occasional offenders and protective and
rehabilitation systems for young delinquents.
Sentences were seen as a useful means of reinte¬
grating the criminal into society.
Crowdedprisons
After the Second World War and the 1948 Dec- g
Jaration of Human Rights, new alternatives f
to prison opened up prospects of more ®
humane sentencing with a view to reintegrat¬
ing offenders into society. But these hopes
came to nothing and alternative sentences
remained by and large marginal. Imprison¬
ment did not become a solution of last resort.
In the 1970s, the flagrant inhumanity of
correctional facilities, the psychological impact
of incarceration and the social exclusion result¬
ing from this form of punishment resulted in
Inmates in Brazil protesting
against poor prison conditions
and the slowness of the
judicial system.
A turn-of-the-century
lecture against alcoholism at
Fresnes prison (France).
Period engraving.
a growing scepticism about the prison sys¬
tem's capacity to rehabilitate inmates. In many
facilities they also led to strikes, revolts and
uprisings, which were sometimes violently
put down.
Since the 1980s, two opposing viewpoints
have emerged. On the one hand, prison seems
to have lost its legitimacy as a punitive insti¬
tution. On the other, some organizations
insist that inmates serve out their full sen¬
tences, thereby restoring the punitive func¬
tion of imprisonment. At the same time, those
who remain unconvinced of the socializing
virtues of deprivation of freedom stress that,
in a democratic state under the rule of law,
inmates are citizens entitled to legal protec¬
tion and basic human rights.
Over the past ten years, crowded prison
conditions have overshadowed ideological dis¬
cussions about the appropriateness, useful¬
ness and humaneness of incarceration. The
average length of sentences has increased and
procedures for early release have become more
complicated. Keeping the offender off the
streets seems to have become the main pur¬
pose of imprisonment.
The debate on sentencing
One major innovation that has emerged over
the past two decades is the idea of reparation.
Recent studies of the victims of crime have
strongly influenced the debate on sentencing.
The question of how far sentences solve the
problems of victims is increasingly being asked.
In this context, the definition of criminality
and the penal approach to it become part of a
horizontal exchange relationship between
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
"* ^ * - M>.* * w »V^ _ . k .........
Fighting a fire started
during a riot at Dijon prison
(France).
offenders and victims. Both are equally con¬
cerned in the solution that is found for the
problem posed by a criminal offence.
Numerous offender-victim conciliation
projects show that this is in many cases a real¬
istic approach and, what is more, highly sat¬
isfactory for both parties and effective in
changing the offender's behaviour. Concilia¬
tion plays a major role in helping to build a
criminal justice system in which offenders
make some amends to their victims.
In handing out prison terms, little attention
was given to the victim. An intelligent execution
of the sentence should take into consideration
how the offender and victim experienced the
crime. The systematic denial of the meaning
and consequences of the offence and its accep¬
tance or rejection by victims and offenders
strongly dehumanizes the application of the
sentence. Confronting offenders with the con¬
sequences of their deeds and giving them an
opportunity to make amends should become
a basic function and priority of the criminal
justice system in the very near future. In a soci¬
ety where attention is now focused on the vic¬
tim, sentencing which does not require offend¬
ers to make amends to their victims lacks
credibility and meaning.
THE UNESCO G'URIER JUNE 1 998 W
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Rehearsing a scene depicting
"the boss" and his slave.
South Africa: puppets in prison
Puppeteer Nyanga Tshabalala
(centre) during a warm-up
exercise with inmates.
"Why use puppets to educate prisoners about
Aids ? The puppet is a visual metaphor, repre¬
senting 'real life' and at the same time one step
removed from the real world. Puppets can be
highly controversial and thus often 'say more'
than live actors. Especially when tackling taboo
subjects like sex and death, they can be less
embarrassing to the audience. Puppetry can be
used to break down racial and social barriers,
and can reach all audiences, including the illit¬
erate. Combining them with humour and
music is entertaining, holds up a mirror to
Puppeteer Gary Friedman with a puppet head
created by inmates.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
society and enables people to look and
laugh at themselves."
In 1987 Gary Friedman and Nyanga Tshabalala
founded Puppets Against Aids, a non-gov¬
ernmental organization that raises awareness of
the disease. In 1996 they held a six-week pilot
workshop, Puppets in Prison, with a group
of young prisoners in Diepkopf prison in
Johannesburg (South Africa). Participants
developed performances whose scenarios
included rape, sexual practices, drugs, human
rights, prostitution and the correct use of con¬
doms. A documentary video about the project
was made and televised in several countries. This
creative, informative experience had a con¬
structive effect on inmates. Photos on these
pages were taken by Gisèle Wulfsohn at Diep¬
kopf during the workshop.
Inmates carving
puppet heads.
A scene from one
of the puppet shows.
> G"1THE UNESCO lOURIER . JUNE I 998
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Prisons for profit / /
BY LEONARD L. CAVISE
rtTKW íH»iuU»wtmw. 'WMtwhWu
A police raid on a Moscow
pool hall breaks up a brawl
between rival gangs.
In the modern era, it has only been since
the 1980s that private, for-profit cor¬
porations have sought to operate entire prison
systems1. The private sector has long been
involved in running various components of
prison systems such as catering, industries,
juvenile offender facilities or community-
based programmes. Only recently, however,
have governmental entities, mostly in the
United States and Europe, considered turning
over the entire management and operation of
a state's or locality's correctional system to
private contractors.
The concept of prison privatization has
given rise to wide debate. Its proponents argue
that private contractors can build larger pris¬
ons faster and thus accommodate a prison
population that is, generally speaking, on the
increase. They also argue that the private sector
is not encumbered by bureaucracy, which is
usually seen as a major impediment to the effi¬
cient operation of a state system. Corpora¬
tions tend to be more streamlined and more
willing to be flexible to meet expanding needs.
Opponents of prison privatization argue
that crime is not a private matter between the
offender and his or her gaolers, but an issue
that concerns society as a whole. If the inter¬
ests of society and the rights of the individual
are to be safeguarded, the "government of the
people" is under an obligation to ensure that
the goals of incarceration are met by the con¬
stant control and monitoring exercised by a
state agency that is not motivated by profit
but by societal and individual concerns.
Cheap labour
The modern prison system came into being
during the period of rapid industrialization in
the Western world in the latter part of the nine¬
teenth century. Prison labour was regarded by
private entrepreneurs as a potentially lucrative '
resource. It was cheap, and the capitalist did
not have overall responsibility for the welfare
of the prison worker. As a result, prison work¬
shops were equipped, and the prisoners trained,
by the enterprise concerned. The entrepreneur
profited from the discounted labour, while the
prison itself often made a financial gain by
entering into a joint arrangement with the pri¬
vate contractors. Abuses were, however, com¬
mon. In France, inmates' living and working
conditions were deplorable and were seldom
monitored by state officials. In Germany, many
contractors supplied only minimal quantiti-
ties of the cheapest food. In the United States,
corrupt prison adminstrators often entered
into agreements whereby the prisoners would
be paid nothing at all for their labour.
The state retained overall responsibility
for the incarceration and rehabilitation of the
prisoner, for dispensing punishment was seen
as too important a government function to be
ceded to private entities. As recently as 1986,
the American Bar Association took a position
against privatization, on the principle that
incarceration is an inherent function of gov¬
ernment. If the private sector is allowed to
control the terms and, to some degree, the
length of incarceration, the argument goes,
the state will have abdicated one of its princi¬
pal moral duties.
Privatization:for and against
Proponents of privatization counter by say¬
ing that the government should retain moni¬
toring and supervisory authority over prisons.
The courts should, for example, review all
prison decisions to grant or refuse parole, grant
or refuse remission for good behaviour, or
restrict or grant rights which might implicate
the Constitution or other legislation. The total
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The gavel, symbol of the
judge's authority (U.S.A.).
delegation of all powers to the private sector
would compromise the sovereignty of the state.
On the other hand, to require that the gov¬
ernment actually staff and operate the prison is
too great a concession to symbolism.
We are, at the present time, witnessing a
shrinkage in the role of government. Govern¬
ment programmes and regulatory powers are
facing budget cuts or, in more and more cases,
elimination, particularly in the social sector. At
the same time, community-based correctional
The private
sector runs an
increasing
number of
correctional
facilities in
Europe and the
United Statesa
trend which is
giving rise to
controversy
programmes are being scaled back, while the
prison population of most countries is
increasing dramatically. The humanitarian and
reform-minded approaches to incarceration
exert less and less influence while, with crim¬
inality increasing worldwide, the retributive
and incapacitation models of punishment are
on the increase. The issue in the privatization
debate thus becomes, not whether the private
sector can duplicate the social and rehabilitative
goals of the prison system, but whether it can
998THE UNESCO lOURIER I
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
house prisoners and dispense punishment as
efficiently as the state. If so, the role of gov¬
ernment will again be minimized and the
stereotype of government-run agencies as inept
and generally inferior will be perpetuated.
Mixed results
Opponents argue that the government still
plays an essential role in many spheres, includ¬
ing the criminal justice system, public health,
the environment, social security, and welfare.
Wth private control, there is a danger that pris¬
oners, traditionally among society's most
neglected members, will suffer abuse and
exploitation for profit. There are concerns about
the development of a " criminal justice industrial
.complex" which could become a political force
that would affect incarceration rates, length of
term, and conditions of confinement based not
upon societal interest but the profit motive.
On the level of legality, the issue is whether
private control constitutes an acceptable dele¬
gation of the discipline- or rule-making
authority. The private controller can hardly
be considered a neutral rule-maker inasmuch as
the expectation of profit will usually be the
dominant rationale for any given rule. A com¬
promise might be to have a state authority
review disciplinary decisions by the prison
for compliance with the governing legislation
or constitution. In that way, the government
would be relieved of the actual running of the
system, while retaining overall responsibility
(and liability) for it.
As the debate continues, many countries
are going ahead with privatization projects. In
1994 alone, the number of privately-operated
facilities increased by more than 20 per cent.
The number of inmates in these facilities is now
more than 30,000 in the United States alone.
Although the largest of these projects is in the
United States, other countries such as France,
Australia and the United Kingdom have opened
privately-controlled prisons. While the phys¬
ical facilities generally seem to be of higher qual¬
ity, the results as regards the quality of food,
educational programmes, and, more generally,
the opportunity for inmates to engage in mean¬
ingful pursuits are mixed. The private compa¬
nies tend to make excellent profits, and all the
estimates indicate that the future for prison
privatization is, in economic terms, bright; but
whether privatization will improve the social
goals of prison remains to be seen.
1. Many prisons in Europe were privately operated in
the Middle Ages and as recently as the nineteenth
century. Author's note.
Right, a representative
of a humanitarian
organization visits
a Rwandan prison in 1994.
©J Langeirn/Sygma, Pans
Food service was one of the
first prison functions
contracted out to the private
sector. Below, meal trays at
the Chateaudun detention
centre (France).
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
1 1 a
pi Jf K
1 J^B \ fl
^1 few '^^^m. IB ^^. wipj
Offenders' rights bymonikaplatek j
The defence of prisoners' rights is the foundation of
democratic penal policy
Incarcerated persons are still commonly
viewed simply as prisoners, and the
deprivation of their freedom as merely the pre¬
lude to a series of other ordeals. However, the
quite different idea that imprisonment is harsh
enough retribution in itself is slowly and spas¬
modically gaining ground in the law and pub
lic opinion. This shift in attitude is due to the
impact on national legislation of international
regulations covering the rights of minors and
adults subject to detention or imprisonment,
the spread of democracy in many countries
and, especially, the growing acceptance of the
concept of human rights.
THE UNESCO lOURIER . JUNE 1998 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The word "rights" can be used only when
clear procedures allowing their enjoyment exist
and unbiased, public and competent bodies
in most countries, the courts guarantee their
proper application.
The general state of a country's prison sys¬
tem is a yardstick of its level of civilization.
Acknowledging that prisoners are still mem¬
bers of society, allowing them to keep most of
the rights enjoyed by free citizens and grant¬
ing them rights specific to their incarcerated
status are expressions of basic tenets of human-
itarianism and social solidarity. Because this
approach defends human dignity, it helps to
prevent crime and improve public safety. Low
self-esteem or lack of self-respect often lead a
person to be indifferent to the rights or dig¬
nity of others, and constitute one cause of
deviant and criminal behaviour. The idea of
prisoners' rights is the basic premise of any
penal policy claiming to be rational, preventive
and concerned with public safety and citizens'
quality of life.
The large number of international regula
tions, resolutions and conventions regarding
prisoners' rights shows how central this issue
is and also how far the actual situation and
legal status of prisoners still fall short of the¬
oretical international standards. In spite of
many efforts to curb, if not end, torture,
physical abuse and humiliating treatment, the
reality inside prison walls remains grim. Only
international acceptance of prisoners' rights
and their recognition on the local level can
bring to prison systems the real accountabil¬
ity which is the essential safeguard of respect
for prisoners' dignity.
Some prisoners have been detained because
they have committed acts of cruelty, others
merely because of their opinions, background,
nationality, religion or even skin colour.
Among them are children, young persons, the
elderly and people with serious illnesses. Oth¬
ers are paying with their freedom for miscar¬
riages of justice and other people's thirst for
power and political ambitions. These inmates
come from many walks of life. But a closer
look at the prison population as a whole
V
Above, life goes on. Inmates
and their children in Matroska
Tishino women's prison in
Moscow (Russia).
Opposite page, family visit at a
Hungarian prison for men.
A drawing class in a Chinese
prison for minors.
*«t
THE UNESCO IpURIER |UNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
reveals that most detainees are penniless, and
lack education or support; they are outcasts
regarded as useless by the rest of society. This
is one reason why the application of prison¬
ers' rights still faces so many obstacles.
For many years, the United Nations sys¬
tem (see Fact file, page 38) and numerous gov¬
ernmental and non-governmental organiza¬
tions have been working to turn the situation
round through a series of legal instruments
including the European Penitentiary Rules,
the American Convention of Human Rights
and the African Charter of Human and Peo¬
ple's Rights. Respect for human dignity is a
basic right of any prisoner, and is a more effi¬
cient pillar of the law than humiliation and
threats.
E UNESCO ^JURII1ER . JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
E UNESCO ^URIER |UNE
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Women
inmates with
their children
"On visiting day at the men's prison, you
can see lines of women who have sometimes
been waiting to get in since the night before.
You don't see that at the women's prisons.
The women are left more alone." (Bailiff at
the San Martin courthouse)
In Argentina, women who have been
charged with an offence or who are serving
time can keep their children with them until
the age of two. Adriana Lestido spent a year
photographing mothers with their children
at Los Hornos prison n° 8 in La Plata. U|
THE UNESCO lOURIER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The changing role of prison staff
BY ABDEL-AZIM WAZIR sai
lrffi\ÍMPrt«TM\\Mm
The role of the prison service has
changed. It is no longer simply concerned
with keeping prisoners under lock and key. It
1 seeks to equip them to return to live in society.
Correctional facilities have become an
important social tool. They systematically use
advanced methods and call on a wide variety of
experts doctors, pharmacists, nurses, teach¬
ers, librarians, coaches and art instructors.
Chaplains take inmates into their pastoral care,
and psychiatrists, psychologists and social
workers help them sort out their lives. Last
but not least, each facility must see to it that
inmates leave prison with a trade or profes¬
sion, whether carpentry or engineering.
Each staff member must have the scientific
or technical background required for his or her
field, as well as special training to work in a cor¬
rectional facility. Most are employees although
some are volunteers, especially in the area of
social services. Volunteers are often very helpful
because of the trust they inspire in prisoners.
Administrative staff and warders, as well as
specialists, have to learn special skills so that
they do not lose sight of their role as educa¬
tors. Professional and administrative staff can
Opposite page, a homeless
child is questioned at an
intake centre (Romania).
Opposite page below, a warder
in a London prison for women
holds a baby belonging to a
prisoner.
Below, anxious families ask for
news about their children after
a police round-up in Rio de
Janeiro (Brazil).
28 ) ^>URIITHE UNESCO {^OU IER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
do their jobs well only if there is a healthy
relationship between inmates and warders.
Progress in training courses, which cover
social problems as well as specific professional
topics, is measured by theoretical and practi¬
cal testing. Raising the level of recruitment in
this way enhances the social standing of prison
employees and helps ensure they will work
with a spirit of integrity.
It is just as important to provide training
for serving prison staff, most of whom began
their careers when prior training was not
required. Trained personnel should also have
regular opportunities to brush up on their
skills and update their working methods.
29
THE UNESCO lOURIER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The hard way back BY AMADOU CISSEDIA
*§£ wKSE' aSot
After eight years and four months in
custody, I was released on parole two
years ago.
At the end of the day, a prisoner's release
depends on the law, in the fullest sense of the
term. The system must not only be concerned
with punishment; it should also keep track
of each inmate's moral development by means
' of interviews. The prison service must be inter-
Painter Amadou Cissé Dia at
the opening of one of his
exhibitions in Dakar (Senegal)
in 1994.
ested in their fate. In the facility where I was
held, administrators and warders kept an eye
on every move we made, good or bad, and
wrote up reports on our behaviour. I believe
those reports play a decisive role.
During my eight years of confinement, I
saw several judges visit the prison to make
direct contact with certain inmates. That
enabled them to understand the prisoners,'
true personalities. I am sure that this in-depth
knowledge is crucial in the decision to release
them.
Getting back into society is a tough propo¬
sition for any ex-convict. But people must
realize that in some cases crime is a curable dis¬
ease. An inmate who really wants to change,
who has thought deeply during his years
inside and who has come to enjoy work
knows what he wants to become and what he
wants to do. He has a clear picture of his past
and present. He knows why his life has been
filled with pain and suffering and he thinks
back nostalgically to when he was a child.
He would like to have a second chance.
He finally manages to understand society,
something he had never done before because he
had never stopped and taken a close look at
human behaviour. He discovers the self-respect
and inner peace that come with honest work.
He wants to cling to happiness with all his
might. That is why it is vital for an ex-convict
to find a way to make a living.
The road to rehabilitation is fraught with
pitfalls that only the bravest souls can avoid.
The main problem is the relationship with
society; an ex-convict needs plenty of under¬
standing.
Speaking for myself, I am successfully
working my way back into society. I am start¬
ing to make my mark as a painter. I managed on
my own to obtain a commission to paint a
large fresco in a bank. Some of my works are
in local collections and I am earning an honest
living.
I had already dabbled in painting before I
went into prison, but it was while I was inside
that I began to take it seriously. By steadily and
painstakingly devoting myself to painting all
those years, I acquired a passion for work.
30 THE UNESCO ^JURIER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Political prisoners
BYDIRKVANZYLSMIT
Inmates whose
status is a subject
of controversy
Above, South African political
prisoners and their families
explode with joy in a post¬
release rehabilitation centre.
© DarryJ Evans/Vu. Pans
Few concepts in penology are as con¬
tentious as that of the "political pris¬
oner", the implication of which is that such
prisoners form a discrete group of detainees
who, because of the nature of the conduct for
which they have been incarcerated, should be
treated differently.
The first point of contention is usually as to
whether the existence of a discrete category of
political prisoners should be recognized. The
qualification "political" indicates that the pris¬
oners concerned have committed acts which
directly challenge the authority and legitimacy
of the government that is detaining them. Rec¬
ognizing that they are "political prisoners"
therefore entails recognition by a government
that it is facing a challenge going beyond that
posed by "ordinary criminals", whose infringe¬
ment of the laws of the land is not aimed specif¬
ically at the government itself. The result is that
governments are often very reluctant to admit
that they are holding "political prisoners" in
their gaols.
In democratic societies, it is unacceptable
for a government to maintain power by
imprisoning those who do not support it.
Where large numbers of a government's oppo¬
nents are imprisoned without trial under
emergency legislation or following the decla¬
ration of martial law, it is difficult for that
government to deny outright that it is hold¬
ing people in its gaols for political reasons.
Governments that act in this way usually claim
that such measures are temporary and intended
to prevent disorder. In these circumstances,
public campaigns demanding that such
detainees be either charged or released may be
very effective, since the government has already
conceded the principle that its conduct is
undemocratic.
Terrorists orfreedom fighters?
The position is more complicated if oppo¬
nents of a government are imprisoned after
having been charged and convicted under the
criminal law. Such a course is attractive to gov¬
ernments, since it enables them to deny that
THE UNESCO (OURIEF Oí
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
the persons concerned are political prisoners,
and to claim that they are being held because
they infringed the criminal law and not because
they opposed the government of the day. In
this way, the government can attempt to cap¬
italize on the legitimacy which the criminal
law as a whole possesses in most societies.
Opponents of a government imprisoned
after being convicted by the criminal courts can
and do object to their incarceration on a num¬
ber of grounds. Most simply and directly, they
can claim that they were not guilty of the
offences with which they were charged, but that
their convictions were the result of biased or
unfair procedures. Second, they can challenge
the offences as defined in the criminal law by
arguing that they were not "ordinary crimes"
but conduct which had been criminalized by
the government in order to muzzle its oppo¬
nents. Third, they can reject their convictions
directly by arguing that the conduct which the
government attempts to criminalize, treason
for example, is justified because of the essential
illegitimacy of the government itself.
Debates about what constitute political
offences and who should be regarded as polit¬
ical prisoners may transcend national borders.
When one state seeks the extradition of an
alleged offender from another state in order to
bring him or her to trial, international law
Former dissident Vaclav Havel
on his election as president of
the Czech and Slovak Republic
in 1990.
The Burmese political leader
Aung San Suu Kyi (upper left,
holding microphone), was
held under house arrest in
Rangoon from 1989 to 1995.
In 1991 she was awarded the
Nobel peace prize.
32
THE UNESCO lOURIER I
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
allows the request to be denied if the extradition
is being sought to try that person for an offence
of a political character. This exception to general
extradition agreements is controversial. States or
their courts differ about whether a particular
offence is political in character. States may also
agree among themselves that certain forms of
conduct are so reprehensible that their perpe¬
trators should be subject to extradition, irre¬
spective of the fact that they were conducted
with a political motive. International conven¬
tions which allow the extradition of persons
suspected of aircraft hijacking or terrorism are
examples of an emerging international consen¬
sus to limit the political offence exception, but
the difficulty remains that a person who is
regarded as a terrorist by some may be regarded
as a freedom fighter by others.
'Prisoners ofconscience'
One way to avoid difficulties of definition is
by focusing on only some of all those
detainees who may be regarded as political
prisoners. Amnesty International, for exam¬
ple, has been particularly successful with its
campaigns on behalf of "prisoners of con¬
science". It has defined as prisoners of con¬
science all persons detained because of their
beliefs, but has specifically excluded those who
have used or advocated violence. This meets
the objection that the organization is sup¬
porting the cause of "violent terrorists". How¬
ever, many prisoners who were motivated by
political ends and who may have turned to
violence only as a last resort have been excluded.
On this test, for example, Nelson Mandela
could not be regarded as a political prisoner,
for in his many years in prison he did not
renounce the violent overthrow of the then
South African Government.
In practice, the solution of the problem as
to who is a political prisoner has often been
pragmatic. Typically, governments insist that
all those who claim political status are ordinary
criminals, but mete out different treatment
to certain subgroups of them. In Northern
Ireland, for example, the British Government
consistently refused to grant Republican or
Loyalist detainees the status of political pris¬
oners, but at various times granted them a
special-category status, which meant that they
were subject to regimes very different from
those applied to other prisoners. Attempts to
reverse this special-category status met with
g strong resistance from the prisoners.
| Even qualified recognition of a special
¡" political prisoner status has potential advan-
| tages for the prisoners concerned. At the most
| general level, such public acknowledgment
| that their actions are motivated by ideals of
° social and political change may advance their
g cause. Even limited special status may mean
Apartheid opponent Nelson
Mandela spent nearly 30 years
in prison. In 1993 he shared
the Nobel peace prize with
Frederik De Klerk and was
elected president of the
Republic of South Africa the
following year.
THE UNESCO lOURIER I 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
that prisoners whose alleged offences were
politically motivated are grouped together.
There are numerous examples of such prison¬
ers developing increased solidarity and com¬
mitment to their shared cause while in prison.
There are also examples of individual political
prisoners obtaining a special status while in
prison because the government that put them
there recognized that it might have to negoti¬
ate with them at some future date.
Recognition of a special political prisoner
status is potentially a mixed blessing, how¬
ever. There are many examples of political pris¬
oners being treated with particular severity.
Quite simply, a state may decide to use its
prison system to break the morale of its oppo¬
nents. Labour and concentration camps in
wartime are variations of the prison system
which have been used to this end, with
» depressing frequency. There are even instances
of courts colluding in this process. In South
Africa, for example, in 1978, a group of pris¬
oners managed to approach the highest court
in the land to ask for some access to news of
current events. In court, they defined them¬
selves as political prisoners, a status which the
authorities at that time vigorously contested.
The court accepted this self-imposed catego¬
rization but used it to argue that, precisely
because the applicants were political prison¬
ers, they could be denied news which was rou¬
tinely available to other prisoners.
When the rule of law
is flouted
In practice, the status of political prisoners may
also play a part in determining when they will
be released from custody. In this respect too, the
impact may be positive or negative. Political
prisoners may be required to serve a far higher
portion of their sentence before being consid¬
ered for parole. On the other hand, a change of
regime or even a shift in the political climate
may lead to early release for those whose
offences may be regarded in the new circum¬
stances as being of a political character.
Such flexibility is contrary to the rule of
law, since it indicates that, where political pris¬
oners are concerned, executive intervention is
allowed to disrupt the normal operation of the
criminal justice system. The rule of law requires
the system to operate according to clear, pre¬
viously determined and impartial principles.
The fact that the rule of law is routinely
flouted in these instances indicates that the
imprisonment of political dissidents is never
an ideal way of solving a political dispute, but
is an admission of failure in the political sphere.
Governments should recognize that when
prisoners claim political status it is a signal
that they and the section of the population
which supports them feel excluded from the
political process. Almost certainly, political
solutions rather than the intervention of the
criminal justice system are required to meet
this challenge.
the Unesco Kurier june 1998
FUJI RDPn
Drn o i
The snow-covered yard, by Michael Inns.
© Michael Inns/inside Eye/Panos Pictures. London
My friend Sami, by Mohamed Manssor.
© Mohamed Manssor/inside Eye/Panos Pictures, London
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Prison through prisoners' eyes
". . . there is a better way to deal with our
problems of crime and punishment than the
one we have at the moment. That way
involves education and understanding. By
putting more people in prison we are not
going to solve the problem. And if people
have been in prison we should urgently help
them not to go back in. Depriving them of
their liberty is their punishment, not
treating them inhumanely. Help them prize
liberty above everything and they will be
less likely to lose it. And art is liberty.
Freedom to express, freedom to
communicate."
These lines are from a book of photographs
entitled Wandsworth Prison as Seen through
the Prisoners' Eyes, by Marc Schlossman and
Adri Berger ("Inside Eye", London, 1997).
Inmates themselves took pictures of
everyday life in the prison. The project,
entitled Inside Eye, was the brainchild of a
group of British photographers who in
1993 had the idea of teaching Wandsworth
inmates photographic skills and then
exhibiting their images outside the prison,
giving the public a view of the prisoners'
world through their own eyes. A few of the
prisoners became professional
photographers after their release. Some of
their photos are featured here and on the
double page overleaf.
Gary's wedding day, by Jon Purl
© Jon Purl/ínsJde fye/Panos Pictures, London
> G"THE UNESCO I^OURIER JUNE I 998
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
A guest speaker talks to the prisoners, by
Dennis Hudson.
© Dennis Hudson/inside £ye/Panos Pictures, London
36
THE UNESCO lOURIER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
fuji RL>rn RDPI 1 43
. O
The library, by Sid and Larry.
© Sid and Larry/Inside Eye/Panos Pictures, London
Self-portrait, by Michael Inns.
© Michael lnns//ns/cíe Eye/Panos Pictures, London
) ^>URIITHE UNESCO URIER JUNE 1998
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
United Nations international instruments
concerning the protection of persons subjected
to detention or imprisonment
<*- Universal Declaration of Human Rights, 10
December 1948
< Standard Minimum Rules for the Treatment of
Prisoners, 30 August 1955
* International Convention on the Elimination of
All Forms of Racial Discrimination, 21 December
1965
« International Covenant on Civil and Political
Rights, 16 December 1966
« Declaration on the Rights of Mentally Retarded
Persons, 20 December 1971
<*- Declaration on the Protection of All Persons
from Being Subjected to Torture and Other Cruel,
Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment, 9
December 1975
« Code of Conduct for Law Enforcement
Officials, 17 December 1979
« Principles of Medical Ethics relevant to the Role
of Health Personnel, particularly Physicians, in the
Protection of Prisoners and Detainees against
Torture and Other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading
Treatment or Punishment, 18 December 1982
*- Safeguards Guaranteeing Protection of the
Rights of Those Facing the Death Penalty, 25 May
1984
*- Convention against Torture and Other Cruel,
Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment, 10
December 1984
* United Nations Standard Minimum Rules for
the Administration of Juvenile Justice (The Beijing
Rules), 29 November 1985
'* Declaration of Basic Principles of Justice for
Victims of Crime and Abuse of Power, 29 November
1985
Basic Principles on the Independence of the
Judiciary, 29 November 1985
» Body of Principles for the Protection of All
Persons under Any Form of Detention or
Imprisonment, 9 December 1988
« Principles on the Effective Prevention and
Investigation of Extra-legal, Arbitrary and Summary
Executions, 24 May 1989
*" Convention on the Rights of the Child, 20
November 1989
" Basic Principles on the Use of Force and
Firearms by Law Enforcement Officials, 7 September
1990
< Basic Principles on the Role of Lawyers, 7
September 1990
*- Guidelines on the Role of Prosecutors, 7
September 1990
<* Basic Principles for the Treatment of Prisoners,
14 December 1990
* United Nations Rules for the Protection of
Juveniles Deprived of their Liberty, 14 December
1990
United Nations Standard Minimum Rules for
Non-custodial Measures (The Tokyo Rules), 14
December 1990
* United Nations Guidelines for the Prevention of
Juvenile Delinquency (The Riyadh Guidelines), 14
December 1990
<* Model Treaty on the Transfer of Proceedings in
Criminal Matters, 14 December 1990
Model Treaty on the Transfer of Supervision of
0 ffenders Conditionally Sentenced or Conditionally
Released, 14 December 1990
" Declaration on the Protection of All Persons
from Enforced Disappearance, 18 December 1992
Drug Addiction, a poster by Ruedi Baur and Félix
Müller (France). This work was shown at an
exhibition of posters and writings organized by
International Prison Watch, a non-governmental
organization based in Lyons (France). The
purpose of the group is to monitor prison
conditions worldwide and to draw attention to
violations of prisoners' rights.
A UN-Unesco manual
on prison education
Most of the millions of people in
the world's prisons and other cor¬
rectional institutions have had no higher
education. Even in countries with a univer¬
sal right of access to 10 or more years of
schooling, a large minority faces difficulties
in reading, writing and numeracy and in
conducting social transactions. Providing
them with basic education is a prerequisite
for achieving the internationally agreed goal
of ensuring a basic level of education for all.
Some of the ways in which prison edu¬
cation can be promoted and some existing
practices in countries throughout the world
are reviewed in Basic Education in Prisons, !
a manual published jointly by the United
Nations and the UNESCO Institute for
Education (UIE), UNESCO's specialized
centre for research and development in adult
and continuing education.
The manual arose from a UIE project to
investigate basic education in prisons and in
response to a United Nations request for a
tool to provide the basis for development
of prison education and to promote inter¬
national exchange of expertise and experi¬
ence in this field.
Designed for decision makers, admin¬
istrators, educators and non-governmental
organizations concerned with education in
penal establishments, Basic Education in
Prisons reports on the status and potential
of prison education strategies, giving con¬
siderable attention to the views of practi¬
tioners and, where possible, of inmates.
This overview is complemented by case
studies from Botswana, China, Costa Rica,
Egypt, Finland, Germany, the Netherlands,
Sri Lanka and the U.S.A.
1 Basic Education in Prisons, United Nations Office
at Vienna/UNESCO Institute for Education, 203
pp., Hamburg, 1995, ISBN-92-1 -1 30-164-5.
For further information:
Unesco Institute for Education
Feldbrunnenstrasse 58
D-20148 Hamburg, Germany.
Tel: (+49) (0)40 44 80 41
Fax: (+49) (0)40 410 77 23
Internet: http//www.education. unesco.org/uie
38 > G'THE UNESCO COURIER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
THE UNITED NATIONS,
UNESCO AND PRISONER EDUCATION
I The United Nations is the foremost
I international organization concerned
with the global question of prisoner educa¬
tion and has set many standards and norms
in this field. UN action has focused on
inmates' basic human right to an education
designed to concentrate on their mental,
physical, social and spiritual development. Its
framework has been the Universal Declara¬
tion of Human Rights and the International
Covenant on Economic, Social and Cul¬
tural Rights, whose signatories recognize
"the right of everyone to education" and
that education shall be geared to "the full
development of the human personality".
The UN has adopted several sets of pris¬
oner education standards. The most impor¬
tant, the Standard Minimum Rules for the
Treatment of Prisoners (1955), stipulates
that "provision shall be made for the further
education of all prisoners capable of profit¬
ing thereby", and that penal education
should be integrated "so far as practicable"
with each country's educational system.
Another set of principles, the United
Nations Standard Minimum Rules for the
Administration of Juvenile Justice (The Bei¬
jing Rules) establishes standards on the
rights of juvenile offenders. Rule 26 stipu¬
lates that a juvenile penal education system
should help young people in institutions
"to assume socially constructive and pro¬
ductive roles in society". The focus is on the
"wholesome development" of young
offenders and on training to ensure that
they do not return to society at an "educa¬
tional disadvantage".
Significant new UN resolutions on
prison education were adopted in 1990,
including a recommendation that "all pris
oners have access to education, including
literacy programmes, basic education, voca¬
tional training, creative, religious and cul¬
tural activities, physical education and
sports, social education, higher education
and library facilities".
While UNESCO had previously said lit¬
tle on the specific subject of prisoner edu¬
cation at the international level, the Fourth
International Unesco Conference on
Adult Education (1985) adopted a decla¬
ration on the right to learn for all, which
consists of: a) the right to read and write;
b) the right to question and analyse; c) the
right to imagine and create; d) the right to
read about one's own world and to write
history; e) the right to have access to edu¬
cational resources; f) the right to develop
individual and collective skills. Like the
human rights articulated by the UN, these
UNESCO rights are considered fundamental,
with the goal of developing the whole per¬
sonality. This means that prisoners should
be given access wherever possible to libraries,
laboratories, workshops, cultural events
and similar educational resources to develop
themselves to the fullest extent.
The Fifth International Conference on
Adult Education, organized by the
UNESCO Institute for Education in Ham¬
burg, 14-18 July 1997, adopted the Ham¬
burg Declaration on Adult Learning and
its accompanying Agenda for the Future
which sets out in detail UNESCO's new
commitment to adult learning. The Agenda
recognizes "the right to learn of all prison
inmates: a) By providing prison inmates
with information on and access to differ¬
ent levels of education and training; (b) By
developing and implementing comprehen-
" *: " ©
Street children in Tananarive, the capital of
Madagascar, where around 4,000 homeless
children between the ages of 2 and 18 survive by
begging and doing odd jobs. The non-governmental
humanitarian organization Doctors Without
Borders has been running a medical, social and
legal assistance programme to help them since
1993.
sive education programmes in prisons, with
the participation of inmates, to meet their
needs and learning aspirations; (c) By mak¬
ing it easier for non-governmental organi¬
zations, teachers and other providers of
educational activities to work in prisons,
thereby providing prisoners with access to
educational institutions and encouraging
initiatives that link courses carried out
inside and outside prisons."
For further information on the 1997 conference:
Internet:
http://www.education.unesco.org/confintea
Bibliography:
Further reading in the Unesco Collection of
Representative Works:
The Lava of this Land, South African Poetry
1960-1996, Denis Hirson (ed.), 1997
The Prisoner, Fakhar Zaman, 1996
Journal de ta félicité, Nicolae Steinhardt, 1995
South African ShortStones, D. Hirson with M.
Trump (eds.), 1994
Post-scriptum et autres nouvelles, Vassili
Choukchine, 1997
From the Unesco Courier.
"The education of prisoners", Stephen
Duguid, April 1996 {Learning to Learn)
The above publications are on sale at:
Unesco Publishing, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75352
Paris 07 SP, France.
Tel: (33)(0)1 45 68 43 00; Fax: (33)(0)1 45 68 57 41;
Internet: http://www.unesco.org/pubhcations
THE UNESCO ^_OLIRIER |UNE1998
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
commentary Federico Mayor
or a broader
In our rapidly changing world, literacy should
be seen as an important evolutionary variable in
every society. For the further a society progresses, the
more it needs to adjust and adapt to new demands and
pressures, so that literacy is a lifelong necessity for all.
Literacy, in the broad sense, is the foundation for life
skills, ranging from basic oral and written communi¬
cation to the ability to solve scientific and social prob¬
lems. Today it involves much more than the acquisition
of the 3Rs and a limited set of traditional skills. It is
linked with the changing demands of life in a given
socio-cultural context.
This means that local communities should be fully
involved in defining the content of literacy progammes.
The local dimension of literacy is extremely important,
not only for accommodating the real needs of learners,
but also for taking into account the linguistic and cul¬
tural realities of multicultural societies. For in the
end, only the learners actually decide what they need
to learn.
Building bridges between cultures
I am very pleased to see that this broader, more dynamic
and culturally sensitive stance is accepted by most
literacy specialists. It marks a long overdue acknowl¬
edgment of the positive role that local languages and
cultures can play in removing some of the serious ped-
40
agogical and psychological hurdles often encountered
by learners. It is the only way to ensure the relevance
and authenticity of literacy work.
I should like to insist here on the importance of
multilingual education. Today education is as much
about learning to live together as learning to know, to
do and to be. Yet we cannot live together if our possi¬
bilities of expression are limited to a single linguistic
frame. This is often at the root of problems encountered
in multicultural societies. Of course, inequality in all
its forms is a major factor. But internal conflicts often
have purely cultural causes. It is more difficult for peo¬
ple to forge links with each other when they cannot
communicate linguistically.
Yet children learn languages easily much more
so than the adults who take the decisions. We need to
take much greater advantage of this fact. Children are
expected to store too much information in their "hard
memory" much of it frankly useless! Giving them
language skills provides them with bridges between
cultures, enabling them to grow up without the debil¬
itating sense that other cultures are alien. It is UNESCO's
task to try to ensure that education at all levels, and
particularly basic education, promotes multilingualism.
And we must invest in such education, since to do so
is to invest in peace.
It is also important to remind ourselves that literacy
THE UNESCO ^>URII1ER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
'If we truly believe in lifelong learning, and if we seriously
believe in redressing the balance of learning in our societies,
then we should seek to develop in every country an open and more
enabling system of education/
approach to education
is not a neutral process which can be applied in all sit¬
uations, all the time, regardless of social and economic
realities. Such a narrow concept of literacy ignores its
critical role as a tool of empowerment. The Brazilian
educator Paulo Freiré compared to banking those
methods that treat adult learners as empty vessels
waiting to be filled with predetermined bodies of knowl¬
edge disconnected from their social experience. Liter¬
acy must provide space for intellectual development,
motivations for learning and a sense of self-esteem, if
it is to be a genuine education for empowerment.
Bringing adult education into
the mainstream
Many individuals and families around the world are fac¬
ing unexpected changes in the pattern of their daily
lives, disrupting their plans for the future. The
demands on educational services are increasing dra¬
matically, especially in countries where the state is
the main provider of education for children and adults.
In today's world, we cannot afford a short-sighted
approach which, in effect, excludes adult education
from the mainstream of the education system, even
after the concept of lifelong learning has been accepted
as a framework for educational policy.
Literacy programmes must be given the priority they
deserve. Lifelong learning for all requires quality adult
education and literacy programmes with qualified per¬
sonnel, relevant teaching programmes, appropriate post-
literacy materials and decent facilities. We must ask
ourselves whether we really are prepared to make the
necessary investments in adult education and literacy
to ensure universal access to the types of programmes
needed to reach the targets of education for all.
If we truly believe in lifelong learning, and if we
seriously believe in redressing the balance of learning
in our societies, then we should seek to develop in
every country an open and more enabling system of
education, breaking with past concepts of education as
something which happens to people between the ages
of six and twenty and which only the privileged few
were entitled to. Synergy has to be created between for¬
mal and non-formal education programmes.
A case in point is the family literacy concept. We all
know that the continuing education of parents, par¬
ticularly when they are illiterate or under-educated,
can contribute very effectively to their children's suc¬
cess in school. In fact, the family literacy approach is
one of the most effective ways of breaking the cycle of
inter-generational illiteracy. Education and training
policies should include all types of learning, whether
it takes place in a school, in the workplace or at home.
There should be more innovation and creativity in
using different methods and approaches.
JNEI998 1THE UNESCO ^>URI
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH Water:
will be there
enough?
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
Women fetch
water in
Rajasthan (India).
Humankind has a special
relationship with water. In
every civilization, the most ancient
traditions associate this precious
resource with the origins of life,
purification and regeneration. Far
from being a mere raw material
such as oil, water is vital for life,
indispensable to the economy and so
rich in symbolic value that it trig¬
gers passionate responses. "All the
computers in the world will never be
able to express the real perception
of the value of water or codify the
interactions between it and peo¬
ples," says Andras Szöllösi-Nagy,
director of UNESCO's Division of
Water Sciences and secretary of
the International Hydrological Pro¬
gramme (IHP). "But that is pre¬
cisely UNESCO's role to tackle an
issue that involves science, culture,
education and communication."
For decades, experts have been
making grim forecasts that the
Earth will start running out of
water and that conflicts over this
precious liquid will erupt into
wars. The situation is indeed
alarming. In the first half of 1998,
two international conferences on
the world's water resources took
place at UNESCO Headquarters in
Paris. The theme of the first, orga¬
nized by the French government
and held in March, was Water and
Sustainable Development. The sec¬
ond, in June, was jointly organized
by UNESCO and the International
Association of Hydrological Sci¬
ences and entitled "Water: A
Looming Crisis?" Both events took
stock of current knowledge, and
participants discussed ways of cop¬
ing with the problem.
IIow much water is there in the
earth's reserves? Highly expensive
probes have been sent to the moon,
Mars and the satellites of Jupiter
and Saturn to find out whether
there is water on them, but we still
lack accurate data about the
earth's hydrological resources.
Such information would help to
provide a clearer picture of the
future and, especially, to foresee
the global repercussions of demo¬
graphic and climate change.
One thing we know about water
is that there is plenty of it. The
total volume is put at 1.4 billion
cubic kilometres which could be
imagined as a 2,650-metre-deep
layer of liquid evenly distributed
over the entire surface of the
planet. But 98% of it is saltwater,
mainly in the oceans and seas. Most
of the earth's fresh water is trapped
in the polar ice caps. Less than 1%
of it is available in lakes, rivers and
shallow, easily-accessible aquifers.
These water resources are con¬
stantly in flux. Water from the
oceans and land evaporates into the
atmosphere before falling again as
rain or snow, nourishing plants and
swelling rivers that flow into the
sea. It also seeps through the
ground and percolates down to
aquifers. Very deep groundwater,
known as fossil wa ter, is impervious
to seepage and not renewable.
42 ) G»THE UNESCO V^URIER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
In the industrialized countries,
all you have to do is turn a tap and
before you know where you are
you've used a considerable amount
of water up to 600 litres per per¬
son a day in the United States. In
hot developing countries, where
shanty-towns on the edges of cities
are crowded with growing numbers
of migrants from the rural areas, a
spigot and two litres of water a day
are a luxury. "In the 1950s," says
Mahmoud Abu-Zeid, president of
the World Water Council, "only a
few countries had this problem. But
in the late 1990s, water is scarce in
26 countries where 300 million peo¬
ple live. Forecasts for 2050 indi¬
cate that 66 countries with approx¬
imately two-thirds of the world's
population will experience a mod¬
erate to severe water shortage."
Over 1.3 billion people received
improved drinking water services
and some 750 million got better san¬
itation facilities during the Inter¬
national DrinkingWater Supply and
Sanitation Decade (1980-1990).
But, says Mr. Abu-Zeid, approxi¬
mately 1.2 billion people still have
no access to drinkingwater and2.9
billion lack sanitation. The resulting
Itaipu dam on the
Parana river
(Brazil and
Paraguay).
water-borne diseases take the lives
of five million people a year, most
of them children.
Farming and manufacturing
account for most of the world's
water consumption, far outdistanc¬
ing human needs. Of the 3,240 km3
of fresh water drawn every year, says
the World Resources Institute, only
8% are used for human consump¬
tion. Each year fewer than ten coun¬
tries use 60% of the world's 40,000
billion m3 of surface and ground¬
water. Lastly, per capita consump¬
tion rises with the standard of living,
ranging from 260 litres a day per
person in Israel to 200 in Europe,
70 for a Palestinian on the West
Bank and 30 in Africa.
THE DANGERS
OF IRRIGATION
Demand runs highest in places
where irrigation is indispensable,
such as central Asia, Iraq, Iran,
Pakistan, Madagascar and also in
some industrially developed coun¬
tries such as the United States.
Farming accounts for two-thirds
of the total water resources used
by humans a figure that rises to
80% in the Southern countries.
Developing countries consume
twice as much water per hectare of
irrigated land as industrialized
nations, yet their production is
three times lower.
Because of the heat, half the
water evaporates in storage areas
(1 m3 per 8 m3 at the Aswan dam
in Egypt, for example) or when
flowing through open-air irrigation
canals. Poorly-conceived irrigation
projects lead to deterioration of
the soil, as French geographer and
drought expert Monique Mainget
demonstrates , using two examples .
The first is Pakistan. During
the first half of the twentieth cen¬
tury, 10 million hectares were
abundantly irrigated in the Indus
plain. Waterlogging caused by irri¬
gation, combined with a high rate
of evaporation, has led to saliniza-
tion of the soil, making it unpro¬
ductive. The second example, the
Aral Sea in the former Soviet
Union, is different but the result is
the same. Much of the water from
the Syrdarya and Amu Darya rivers
that flow into the huge lake has
been diverted to feed 180,000 km
of irrigation canals, only 12% of
which have been made watertight.
The rivers' flow is considerably
restricted and the Aral Sea is dry¬
ing up. "Irrigation for agricultural
purposes is expensive," Ms.
Mainguet says. "To make it prof¬
itable, farmers must use massive
amounts of pesticides, herbicides
and fertilizer on increasingly
exhausted soil. The impact of pes¬
ticides on health has been over¬
looked. The child morbidity and
mortality rates are among the
world's highest."
The Food and Agriculture
Organization of the United Nations
(FAO) says that 10 to 20% of the
water used for agricultural pur¬
poses could be saved with more
efficient irrigation methods. One
case in point is the foggaras,
underground canals which have
been used since ancient times in
Iran, Chile and the oases of North
Africa, to carry water from wells
> Qu HER JUNE 1998
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
located many kilometres away.
Another is the modern under¬
ground drop-by-drop technique
used in Israel. But how can the
water needs of the planet's 240
million hectares of irrigated farm¬
land be realistically met?
Industry is less greedy than
agriculture, but it still consumes
23% of the planet's available
freshwater resources. Michel
Bâtisse, a UNESCO adviser on the
environment, says it is primarily
used for three purposes: "cooling,
production (as part of the prod¬
uct's composition or for process¬
ing) and heating (to make steam or
ensure the smooth running of the
manufacturing process). These cat¬
egories differ widely in terms of
both consumption and pollution."
Untreated waste water is still
commonly discharged into the envi¬
ronment, especially in poor coun¬
tries. But the number of antipollu¬
tion projects and water treatment
plants is on the rise, particularly to
stem effluents from pulp mills and
nitrogen and phosphorus run-off
from the food processing industry.
Manufacturers are especially care¬
ful to take the necessary precau-
44
tions when the "polluter pays"
principle is applied.
COSTS FOR THE CONSUMER
With water consumption rising
twice as fast as population growth,
the idea of free water for all is
increasingly unrealistic. This pre¬
cious, shared resource must have a
price, and it should be based on a
sliding scale to ease the burden on
the needy. Even a nominal cost dis¬
courages waste. French President
Jacques Chirac says it would take
at least $400 billion to fund the
facilities needed to cover priority
water needs over the next ten years
worldwide. But "neither taxes, nor
development aid will be enough,
even though solidarity is a duty."
Consumers must help pay dis¬
tribution costs, while facilities are
financed by local communities and
international aid. But this is assum¬
ing that equipment is standard¬
ized. In Senegal alone, nearly 800
pumping stations are equipped
with 62 different types of motors
and 67 different kinds of pumps.
It is easy to imagine the logistical
nightmare of storing spare parts.
Another problem is that
Tanzanian
villagers fill in a
trench containing
the pipes of their
village's newly
installed water
supply system.
Giant sprinklers
automatically
move across a
field in Arizona
(U.S.A.).
experts' analysis of needs based on
scientific data are often quite dif¬
ferent from the actual require¬
ments of users, whose conception
of water is shaped by their own
culture, manage it according to
their own ethics of sharing and pro¬
tect and use it according to their
own development needs. Very
often, there is a lack of communi¬
cation between government offi¬
cials, users' organizations and non¬
governmental partners. Poorly
understood water resources man¬
agement has an immediate nega¬
tive impact on a community's bal-
THE UNESCO ^JURIEl
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
anee and cohesiveness, penalizing
women most of all because they
are responsible for fetching water
in many developing countries.
A case in point is Maharashtra ,
India, where a boom in sugar cane
production led to an increase in the
number of deep wells for irrigation.
Shallower wells for domestic con¬
sumption ran dry and the women
were forced to trudge long dis¬
tances in search of water, adding
considerably to their burden of
chores. In Misalai, Tanzania, more
women than men volunteered to dig
the trenches for a water supply pro¬
ject. But when the pipes were laid,
the network went only to the part of
the village where local leaders lived.
The women decided to stop par¬
ticipating in other development
activities for as long as the water
was not fairly distributed. Their
reaction is all the more under¬
standable since African women
spend an average of six hours a day
in search of water.
SPRINGS OF WAR?
On the Pacific Ocean island of
Tonga, women who had formed
their own environmental and health
affairs organization boycotted a
community sanitation project when
the men's committee and the devel¬
opment agency did not involve them
in its planning and management.
Learning from the experience,
neighbouring villages invited both
men and women to meetings. Each
time project managers, for the sake
of convenience, consult only men,
the consequences can be dramatic.
Men try to appropriate women's land
when irrigation drives up its value.
The women, deprived of their
source of income and their inde¬
pendence, can no longer shop at the
market, with the result that the
children suffer from malnutrition.
This has happened in western
Kenya and northern Afghanistan.
In cities, large amounts of water
go to waste in drinking water dis¬
tribution networks. It is estimated
that 10% is lost due to leaks in
the industrialized countries, a fig
ure that may be as high as 60% in
the developing nations. Industrial
waste, pollution from non-point
sources and lack of sanitation seri¬
ously affect municipal water
resources. The situation is exac¬
erbated by unauthorized connec¬
tions to the supply network and
the failure of some customers to
pay their bills. Meters encourage
consumers to save water, but they
have not yet come into widespread
use around the world. Improving
urban water supplies is a major
challenge for tomorrow. Fifteen
mega-cities already have a popu¬
lation of 10 to 20 million, and their
number is exported to double over
the next two decades.
Jean-Marc Flores of the FAO
says we already consume half the
planet's available water resources
and demand will outstrip supply by
2025, when the world's population
hits 8.3 billion. After that, it will
be necessary to introduce water-sav¬
ing measures or tap reserves of fos¬
sil groundwater provided they
have not already been over-
exploited. Further complicating the
issue is the fact that there are 215
international rivers, as well as
approximately 300 groundwater
basins and underground aquifers
shared by several countries.
Some rivers, such as the
Mekong, Paraguay and Senegal, are
good examples ofjoint management
of a shared resource. But there are
at least 70 water-related flashpoints
in Africa , the Middle East and Latin
FOR FURTHER READING:
Man, Drought and Development, by Monique Mamguet, Springer
Verlag (in press)
Small Tropical Islands, by Anthony Falkland, IHP series no 2
Tropical Cities: Managing their Water, by John Gladwell and Low
Kwai Sim, IHP series no 4
Les femmes dans les zones tropicales humides, by Annabel Rodda,
IHP senes no 6
Water and Civilization, by Fekn A. Hassan and Jerome Delli Priscoli,
IHP study, Unesco, 1997
Ground water, by Christine Coughanowr, IHP series no 8
Helping Children in the Humid Tropics: Water Education, by
Claudine Brelet-Rueff, IHP series no 11
Culture and Negotiation, by Guy Olivier Faure and Jeffrey Z. Rubin.
A Unesco-IIASA Project. Sage Publications Inc., London, 1993
Unesco Water Sciences Division
1 rue Miollis 75732 Pans cedex 15 France
Fax: 33 145 67 58 89
E-mail: ihp@unesco.org
Websites: http://www.unesco.org and
http://pangea.org/orgs/unesco
America. No country has actually
gone to war over water yet. But a
set of factors including demo¬
graphics, rising demand resulting
from improved living standards , the
predominance of upstream over
downstream the first-served con¬
trol the flow of rivers may stoke
smouldering conflicts.
In medieval Europe, kings had
the right to "use and abuse" water,
which was a private possession and
a source of wealth. Those days are
over. The right to use this increas¬
ingly scarce resource must be part
of a community perspective. That is
why UNESCO Director-General Fed¬
erico Mayor has made an appeal for
"a new water ethics demonstrating
our awareness of the need for fair
distribution, partnership and,
beyond that, sharing."
A river polluted by
mining in Peru.
THE UNESCO lOURIER JUNE 1996
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
LISTENING
COLOMBIAN CHAMPETA
BY ISABELLE LEYMARIE
A scene from the Colombian-
French-Venezuelan film Les
rois créoles de la champeta
( The Creole Kings of
Champeta) by Lucas Silva and
Sergio Arria.
The Cartagena region, on Colombia's
Atlantic coast, is fertile agricultural
land which also produces bumper crops of
new music. For years, artists from all over the
Caribbean performed at the city's popular
music festival in the old wooden bullring, an
event fostering cross-fertilization between var¬
ious musical currents. Another rich source of
sounds is the San Basilio palenque, a former
settlement of fugitive slaves 70 kilometres away,
which has jealously preserved centuries-old
Bantu traditions such as lumbalu, a ritual for
the dead accompanied by instrumental music,
dances and songs. Son, a beat from Cuba's Ori¬
ente province, came to the palenque in the
early 1930s, where it is still played on instru¬
ments that are no longer used in Cuba.
For many years African slaves passed
through Cartagena, and even today the city is
the meeting point of a wide array of outside
influences. In the late 1960s, seamen brought
back records of new African popular music,
including soukous from Zaire (which stems
from Cuban son), mbaqanga from South
Africa, makossa from Cameroon and highlife
from Ghana and Nigeria, with which the young
local black community immediately identified.
Soukous caught on like wildfire among young
Born in the
shanty-towns of
Colombia, one of
the most inventive
forms of popular
music today
people from the palenque who sensed their
Bantu roots in the music.
It wasn't long before local DJs and musi¬
cians were experimenting with these rhythms,
reinterpreting them in their own way and, in
the early eighties, blending them with rap and
raggamuffin in lively remixes. That is when a
new kind of music emerged in the black neigh¬
bourhoods in and around Cartagena and in
the San Basilio palenque. It was first known as
champeta, then as terapia criolla ("creóle
therapy"). Today the terms are used inter¬
changeably.
Self-taught musicians
Born in the slums, champeta at first devel¬
oped surreptitiously outside the mainstream of
cumbia and vallenato, internationally known
forms of Colombian popular music which also
originated on the Atlantic coast, and of salsa,
which started in Cuba but has taken deep
root in Colombia.
Champeta is played over huge sound sys¬
tems, or picas (from the English term "pick¬
up"), painted with psychedelic designs in vil¬
lages and run-down city neighbourhoods. A
kind of Latin American soukous, it features a
throbbing bass, front-and-centre guitar and
46
THE UNESCO lOURIER I
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
percussion solos, repeated "breaks" and riffs of
Haitian compas, Trinidadian soca andrap. At
first it was popular among gangs of hoodlums
who squared up to each other around thepicós
with long fishing knives known as champetas
(hence the name of the music). Then it spread
among the working classes, the people of the
port and door-to-door salesmen.
Champeta was created by self-taught musi¬
cians who sing using both the typically African
phrasing of the San Basilio palenque and the
community's Bantu-based dialect. The records
are produced by small, sparsely-equipped,
storefront independent labels. Just about any¬
one can drop in off the street for an a cappella
audition. But as the Colombian film-maker
Lucas Silva shows in his documentary Los
reyes criollos de la champeta ("The Creole
Kings of Champeta"), champemos (exponents
of champeta) have very fixed ideas when it
comes to music. They draw inspiration from
everyday life, sometimes even from American
cartoons shown on television. Anything is grist
for their mill.
A cultural phenomenon
At first, owners of sound systems went down
to the docks to buy the latest hit records
imported from Africa and the Caribbean from
seamen. As in Jamaica, they vied with each
other to attract audiences and to see who had
the most innovative mixer, the most talkative
DJ, the loudest sound system and the widest
range of records.
In the 1980s, a handful of Colombian busi¬
nessmen who realized how popular African
music was becoming locally invited African
and West Indian groups to the Festival of
Caribbean Music. These performers, includ¬
ing Kanda Bongo Man, Bopol Mansiamin and
M'Bilial Bel from Zaire, Mahlathini and the
Mahotella Queens from South Africa and
Coupé Cloué from Haiti, were a smash hit with
the public. Around the same time, Justo
Valdez, a young musician from San Basilio,
founded Son Palenque, Colombia's first souk¬
ous group. "But," he says, "I sing in our lan¬
guage and keep many of the palenque's tra¬
ditional elements."
Champeta singers, rappers and DJs sport
outlandish attire, nimbly engage in hyperbole,
verbal one-upmanship and sexual innuendo,
and using unbridled, colourful language,
bring audiences to their feet with hot dances
that recall despelote, currently popular with
young Cubans in Havana.
Among the rising stars of Colombian cham¬
peta and soukous are the Kusima group,
Shaka the Zulu King of Cartagena, Cándido
Perez ("the doctor of la terapia''''), Luis Tow¬
ers and especially Elio "Boom" (Francisco Elio
Corrales), a young Black from Turbo in the
Antioquia region on the Pacific coast. Boom
started performing songs by Panamanian stars
in his home village at the age of seven and
today lives in Cartagena where he is an idol of
the poor. His first two records La Turbina
and El caballero de la champeta criolla.
sold in thousands. He sings La Turbina in the
language of his birthplace, which he describes
as a mixture of Spanish, Haitian Creole and
English. His fame has spread to Panama,
Puerto Rico, the Dominican Republic, Jamaica
and, by word-of-mouth, the Spanish-speak¬
ing communities of the United States.
The commercial success of terapia criolla
spawned a festival, which took place in the
Cartagena bullring for the first time on 2 April,
1997. Headliners included Melchor El Cruel ,
Alvaro El Bárbaro and Dogardisc y Bustafá.
José Quessep, who organized the event, says
"Champeta has always been thought of as
aggressive music for common people and gang
members, but we're sure this festival will show
that it is also a cultural phenomenon that has
taken root in Cartagena and is catching on
world-wide."
Brimming with vitality, champeta is both
nostalgic and a novelty, strengthening the
bonds between Africa and the New World,
and yet again reflecting the boundless cre¬
ativity of Blacks in the Americas .
SELECTIVE DISCOGRAPHY;
TRADITIONAL MUSIC FROM THE SAN BASILIO PALENQUE:
Colombie: El Sexteto Tabatá, OCORA C 560126
CHAMPETA:
Elio Boom, El Caballero de la Champeta Criolla, Rey Records RR 003
Elio Boom, Sigo Reinando, Rey Records RR 006
Elio Boom, Viva la champeta criolla 96, Flecha Records
THE UNESCO lOURIER I 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW SUSAN BUIRGE
'The dancer
is a bond
between
earth
and sky'
What is choreographry for you?
S.B.: For me, there are basically two kinds of
choreographers. There are the visionaries who
project their mental images on stage the
American choreographer Alwin Nikolais is a
good example of this type and there are those
like myself for whom dance is part of a ques¬
tioning process. For me, choreography is like
a detective novel in which the questions are:
who does what? where? when? and how? I
leave out "why"? because in choreography the
"why" emerges from all the other factors.
Could you tell us something about your
methods?
S.B.: My approach to choreography is not nar¬
rative, but abstract. I have developed a process
in which a series of questions are asked about
the structure, space and time. For example:
where the dance is situated on stage, which
dancer enters from which side, who begins,
and so on. I have evolved a process of ques¬
tioning in which the answers are given by using
the tools of chance flipping a coin, drawing
lots, or throwing dice. This allows me to work
on the borderline between what I know and
what I do not know. By using methods of con¬
struction based on chance I can construct pieces
that I could never have imagined otherwise.
48
Susan Buirge is an American
choreographer who livesin
France, where she is associate
artist to the Arsenal in Metz.
For some years she has been
profoundlyinfluenced by
Japanese traditions and
civilization, and her most
recent work with
conte mporary Japanese
dancers and gagaku musicians
will be performed at this
year's Avignon Festival (15-21
July 1998). A compilation of
the notes she made during
visits to Far Eastern countries
has been published under the
title En allant de l'ouest à
l'est, Carnets 1989-1993
(Editions Le bois d'Orion,
1996). Here she is interviewed
by Romain Maitra.
I prepare a section of the choreography on
a piece of paper, beginning with the structure
and the many details of each movement its
direction, which part of the body evokes
which quality, its duration, and various other
details. Then, working with the dancers in the
studio, drawing on their energy and the
atmosphere at that specific moment, I read the
results of the questions from the paper I have
prepared. The dancers have to be very alive and
alert to capture the essence of the movement
that flows out of my body at that precise
moment because once I repeat it, it loses its
initial impact.
Would you agree with the idea that dance is a
cerebral art?
S.B.: I strongly believe that movement in
post-modern dance springs from thought,
setting aside movements prompted only by
animal instincts. The principles of post-mod-
> GuiRIER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
ern dance originate in a certain tradition that
can be traced back to theories set forth by
Kandinsky and Klee.
When we see choreography as the result of
a thought process, we can always feel an under¬
lying sense of construction. All human beings
have a basic need to build, in the same way
that birds build nests. When choreography is
"constructed", spectators can sense its latent
structure even if they cannot actually see it or
identify it. I think one of the reasons why
contemporary dance is interesting and elicits a
wide public response is that it responds to
this basic need. Of course there is the pleasure
of seeing the dancer dance, but there is also
something more.
Do you believe that gestures and movements
have a cultural origin?
S.B.: Of course they do. I noticed this when I
came from America to France in 1970, but I
have felt it even more strongly working with
Japanese dancers since 1992. The Japanese live
very close to the floor, they take off their shoes
when they enter a house, and they kneel for
long periods while working or discussing. This
relationship to the ground and this sitting pos¬
ture give them a unique sense of verticality,
something quite different from the Western
experience. This verticality, incidentally, gives
theJapanese very powerful hips and I have taken
advantage of this in my work with them.
If there is such a thing as a culture of space,
it certainly exists in Japan where space is a
highly elaborated code. People do not touch
one another in public. Although they are
packed like sardines in the subway, there is a
feeling that they are not touching. When meet¬
ing, there is always a sense of distance between
people not as a divider but as something that
brings people together and relates individu¬
als to the community. True contact is based
on an absence of physical contact.
This creates a specific approach to the way
people work together. This "non-touching"
makes the body more vibrant and emphasizes
the way it situates itself in space. Japanese
dancers are far more keenly aware than West¬
ern dancers of where they are in space. Dancer,
choreography and space become one. As a
choreographer who is passionate about space,
I felt entirely at home in Japan.
What else did you learn from your time in Japan?
S.B.: During my first visit to Japan in 1989, 1
discovered bugaku, a dance form that came to
Japan from China in the seventh century and
is performed in a strictly confined space. In
'Human beings
have a basic need
to build, in the
samewaythat
birds build nests.
Contemporary
dance responds to
this need/
Japan, special architectural spaces are set aside
for dance, whereas in the West dance is always
performed in borrowed spaces.
The indigenous traditional dance ofJapan is
kagura, whose many forms are directly related
to the agrarian cycle from planting to har¬
vesting, particularly rice. There are nearly 60,000
kagura dance forms still in existence in Japan
today. Each is danced but once a year, by the vil¬
lagers, conceived for a specific place, on a specific
date, for a specific reason. We know from writ¬
ten sources that some of these forms have
existed for at least a thousand years. All the
dances take place in specially created areas which
are sometimes destroyed after being used.
These forms are thoroughly choreo¬
graphed, in other words the dancers do not
express themselves spontaneously. Their struc¬
tures are extremely sophisticated and complex.
To my mind they comply with all the princi¬
ples of post-modern choreographic con¬
struction because they are based on process.
Most of these dances are performed for the
people of the villages, for the well-being of
the community, the land and the crops. As
such, the dance is the responsibility of the
community. Many of these villagers, who may
be farmers, craftsmen or postmen in their
working lives, are good dancers.
The difference between dance and theatre is a
convention that arose relatively late in Europe.
Where do you draw the line between the two?
S.B.: To me, there is a big difference between
dance and theatre, and it is essentially a differ¬
ence of responsibility. Theatre is the art of the
city, of the polis. It is a moment when the peo¬
ple of the city gather around a subject that
someone has written and that concerns them.
Dance is something different. With his feet
firmly planted on the earth, his body erect and
his head in the sky, the dancer is a bond between
earth and sky. In traditional Japanese kagura,
the dance assumes responsibility for tying what
is of the earth to what is of the sky.
Theatre, on the other hand, ties people to
each other and to the city. In the West, when
dance wants to tell stories, it tends towards
theatre. But this is a use or application of dance
and not its primary function. Today my work
focuses on reaffirming the dancer's responsi¬
bility as a link between earth and sky.
Do you think there is a crisis of creativity in
traditional dance cultures? Are they finding it hard
to adapt to modern sensibilities?
S.B.: As a contemporary artist, I feel a respon¬
sibility to perpetuate traditional dance cultures
everywhere. I believe that cultural traditions
r 49
THE UNF-SCO lOURIER |UNEI99ß ~
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
and the contemporary arts should exist on an
equal footing in every culture. There is need to
talk about the distinctions and boundaries
between the traditional and the contempo¬
rary, but as complementary forms. Some of
my own works could never have been created
without the ancient Japanese kagura. But every
culture also needs contemporary artists.
For the Japanese, "contemporary art" is
often trendy art from an American or Euro¬
pean ethos, something that is not part of their
culture. So much contemporaryJapanese dance
that I have seen is an imitation of well estab¬
lished styles, what has been learnt in dance
classes in the United States. Most contempo¬
rary Japanese choreographers discard or ignore
cultural traditions. I am interested in
how they are going to find their own con¬
temporary art. On the other hand, the Japan¬
ese also regard noh, kabuki and bugaku dances
as contemporary forms.
Innovations have been taking place in India
where Chandralekha, for example, has used
the techniques of Bharata Natyam to generate
modern sensibilities. Wu Kuo-Chiu from Tai¬
wan, who was trained in Chinese Opera, has
worked on Macbeth using Chinese opera tech¬
niques as well as certain Western ideas about
space and decor, and an innovative recon¬
struction of the narrative.
In the West, dancers retire young, but this does
not seem to be the case in the East. Why this
difference?
S.B.: The idea of dance as the image of youth
comes from classical ballet. But in contempo¬
rary dance this is not so. Mary Wigman and
Martha Graham danced long after they were
sixty years old, and Jiri Kylian has formed a
company of dancers over forty. Nevertheless,
contemporary dance is not easy on the body.
We aren't made of iron or rubber, and even¬
tually the knees and the hips go! However,
some of the thinking about dance in this cen¬
tury has defined beauty as emerging from
inside, rather than outside, the body.
On the other hand, there are bugaku dances
specially conceived for six-year-old children.
These are not childish dances, they have strict
rules. There is a bugaku dance intended for
performance by a centenarian. Also there is a
"last dance" when one knows one is going to
die, a moving way of acknowledging the span
of a life gone by. This wonderful idea takes
us back to the question of the place of dance
in society, of whether it is merely a decora¬
tive art or whether it can be functional like
much of what we find in ancient dances in tra¬
ditional societies.
Choreography cannot go back to ancient
times it must go forward. In our age of
information processing, computers and mul¬
timedia, the counterpoint of live dance with
live music is more necessary than ever.
AUTHORS
EDMUNDO OLIVEIRA, of Brazil, ¡s professor of penal law at the Federal University of Para and professor of medical ethics at the
State University of Para. His most recent works are Política criminal e alternativas à pnsâo (1996, "Criminal Policies and Remedies
to Incarceration") and Deontologia, erro médico e direito penal (1991 , "Deontology, Medical Error and Penal Law").
LOUIS PEREGO, of France, is an ex-convict. His published works Include Retour à la case prison and Le coup de grâce (L'Atelier
publishers, Paris, 1990 and 1995).
JOSÉ LUIS DE LA CUESTA ARZAMENDI, of Spam, is professor of penal law at the university of the Basque Country in San
Sebastian, and deputy secretary-general of the International Association of Penal Law. He is the author and/or co-editor of several
works including El delito de tortura (1990, "The Crime of Torture").
LINDA JOHANSSON is a Swedish journalist.
TONY PETERS, of Belgium, is professor of criminology and victimology at the Catholic University of Leuven. He has recently
published Van Orientatienota naar Penaal Beleid (1997 , Leuven University Press).
LEONARD L. CAVISE, of the United States, is professor of law at DePaul College of Law in Chicago and a practising attorney.
MONIKA PLATEK, of Poland, is professor of criminology at Warsaw University's Institute of Penal Law.
ABDEL AMADOU CISSÉ DIA, a Senegalese artist, is an ex-convict.
DIRK VAN ZYL SMIT, of South Africa, is professor of criminology in the faculty of law of the University of Capetown. A specialist
in prison law, he is co-editor of a book entitled Imprisonment Today and Tomorrow (1991).
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American journalist specializing in environmental issues.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-American musicologist, has published La musique sud-américaine, Rythmes et danses d'un
continent ("South American Music, a Continent's Rhythms and Dances", Gallimard, Paris, 1997).
ROMAIN MAITRA is an Indian journalist and anthropologist specializing in the performing arts.
Tr>6 UNESCO
QpURlER
51st YEAR
Published monthly in 27 languages and in
Braille by Unesco, The United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin,
75732 Paris CEDEX 15, France.
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 57.45
e-mail: unesco couner@unesco org
Internet http://www unesco.org
Director, a. i.: René Lefort
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor. Gillian Whitcomb
English edition" Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lêvêque
Spanish edition: Araceli Ortiz de Urbma
Features. Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. (33) (0)
1 45.68 46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45 68 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions
and press: Solange Beim
(Tel. (33) (0)1 45 68.46.87)
Film duplication. Daniel Meister
Secretariat Annie Brächet
(Tel. (33) (0)1 45 68 47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck t
Selection in Braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean. (Tel. (33) (0)
1 45 68.45 69)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian" Irina Utkma (Moscow)
German. Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian. Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil. M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jahl Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese' Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de
Janeiro)
Urdu. Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay. Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian: DragomirPetrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Rntta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Sunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasihuk (Kiev)
Galician" Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de
Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax: (33) (0) 1 45.68 57.45
Subscriptions Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel.
(33) (0) 1.45.68.45 65), Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah
El Din (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68 49.19)
Customer service* Michel Ravassard, (Tel.
(33) (0) 1.45.68 45 91)
Accounts (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 45.65)
Shipping: Daniel Meister
(Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel: (33) (0)1.45.68.45 65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years- 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible
currency to the order of Unesco or by Visa,
Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing trie credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier', plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the edi¬
tor Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not nec¬
essarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those
of the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff The boundaries on maps published in the
magazine do not imply official endorsement or accep¬
tance by Unesco or the United Nations The Unesco
Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or
microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy.
75700 Pans, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Michigan 48100 U S A , (3) N C R Microcard
Edition, Indian Head Inc , 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U S.A.. (4) Bell and Howell Co , Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, USA,
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL-C1-JUNE 1998
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 -
DIFFUSÉ PAR LES NM P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure:
Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 6-1998-0PI-98-572 A
This issue comprises 52 pages.
50
THE UNESCO l^OURIER JUNE 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Unesco on line via Interne
Currently on-line are: an index of the contents of the las!
22 issues of the Unesco Courier, Unesco press releases,
addresses, fax, telex and electronic mail numbers o
esco's regional offices, National Commissions and Unesco
Clubs, the directory of Unesco databases and information
services, colour images of the Japanese Garden and other
:hitectural sites at Unesco Headquarters, as well as works
í art such as Henry Moore's reclining sculpture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
mïtlVimllHlMi
]]>
</page>
</document>
