<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="118279eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
PLANET
Forests:
a hot deal
for a cooler world
CONNEXIONS
International radio
makes
new waves
IN T ERV IEW
Wangari Muta
Maathai, Kenya’s
green militant
PEOPLE AND PLACES
Circus
flashbacks
Me m o ry :
making peace
with a violent pas t
December 1999
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
52nd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris Cedex 15 F rance
Fax: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1. 45.68.57.47
e-mail: unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet: http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions: 
Annie Brachet (Tel: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: John Kohut
English edition: Roy Malkin
Spanish edition: Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition: Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Cynthia Guttman
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: Georges Ser vat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press: 
Solange Belin (Tel: 33 (0) 1. 45.68. 46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel: (33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committe e
René Le f o rt (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fall, Sue Wi l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian: G i ovanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Flore n c e )
Hindi: Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese: Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U rdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l ovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Suchitra Chitranukroh(Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali: Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian: Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax: (33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel: (33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line re a d s
“ Reprinted from the UNES CO Courier”, plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author’s name.
Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re q u e s t .
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon
c overing postage. Signed articles express the opinions
of the authors and do not necessarily re p resent the
opinions of UNES CO or those of the editors of the
UNES CO C o u r i e r. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the UNES CO Courier staff. The boundaries on
maps published in the magazine do not imply official
endorsement or acceptance by UNES CO or the United
Nations. The UNES CO Courier is produced in micro f o r m
( m i c rofilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UNES CO, 7 Place
de Fo n t e n oy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Micro f i l m s
( Xe rox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R.
M i c ro c a rd Edition, Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th
St reet, New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Ol d
Mansfield Road, Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - NOVE MBER 1999
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UNES CO Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in
Paris by UNES CO. Printed in France. Periodicals postage
paid at Champlain NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’UNESCO.
Impression: Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 12-1999-OPI 99-587 A
C o n t e n t s
December 1999
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 Circus flashbacks Photos by Massimo Siragusa; Text by Tonino Guerra
EDITORIAL
9 Into action Ko ï c h i ro Matsuura
PLANET
10 Forests: a hot deal for a cooler world Sophie Boukhari
13 Toyota makes trees Yoshinori Takahashi
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Spare the rod, save the child E t h i rajan Anbara s a n
ETHICS
37 Police against racism Asbel López
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 The year 2000: whoÕs coming to the part y ? Jasmina Sopova
CONNEXIONS
43 International radio makes new wave s Cynthia Guttman
TALKING TOÉ
46 Wangari Muta Maathai, Ke n y aÕs green militant
1 7 Focus Me m o ry: making peace 
with a v i o l e n t p as t
The second half of this century has been stained by
crimes against humanity. For the victims, the path of
reconciliation winds between re m e m b rance and
f o rg e t t i n g . The complexities of this process are
i l l u s t rated by stories on South Africa, Chile, Guatemala,
Russia, Cambodia, Rwanda and Bosnia.
Detailed table of contents on page 17.
C over: Mi Lay massacre memorial, Da Nang, Viet Nam; © J.M. H u ron/Editing, Pa r i s
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Under the big top of Italy’s Embell Riva Circus, an equestrian act prepares to go through its paces. The circus, owned by the Bellucci family, 
tours mainly in southern Italy.
CIRCUS
FLASHBACK S
◗ Photos by Massimo Siragusa; text by Tonino Guerra
Massimo Siragusa’s circus photos conjures up a world of happy memories for Italian poet 
Tonino Guerra, the scriptwriter of Federico Fellini’s 1974 film Amarcord (‘I Remember’)
■
When autumn began and leave s
from the chestnut trees covered the
road between the station and the
square, a moment would come when I
would open the window overlooking our
vegetable garden and see with delight the
tent of the little circus which had been
pitched on the village green overnight.
When I opened the same window in
springtime, my surprise came from the
cherry tree, bursting with white blossoms.
I was a small boy then, full of excitement
at discovering the big top which had gone
up in front of our house.The evening air
was filled with the sounds of trumpets
and the rumble of drums.
It was usually the same circus that
Federico Fellini had applauded before me
in Rimini, the chief town of the Adriatic
R i v i e r a , near the village where I wa s
b o rn—Santarcangelo di Romagna. I
remember how Fellini and I often talked
about it during the shooting of Amarcord,
the film in which he remembered his
youth in Rimini.
By then, both of us had been living in
Rome for many years. On Sunday mor-
nings, Fellini would often drive me to
Cinecittà1. He just loved to be there when
it was deserted and quiet. He would ask
for the keys to Set no. 5 and we would
make our way to that dank, empty place.
Let the show begin!
As soon as we arrived, he would say in
a voice charged with emotion: “Let the
show begin!” and would start to switch on
the lights one by one. We watched the
1.The centre of the Italian film industry, founded
62 years ago on the Via Tuscolana just outside
Rome.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
This lanky giraffe is one of many performing animals in the Moira Orfei Circus. The Orfeis are a famous Italian circus family.
A lonesome clown looks into a mirror before going into the ring.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
The spotlight picks out spinning hoops and silhouettes a high-stepping dancer during a Rome performance of the Togni family’s three-ring American Circus.
A tightrope walker with the Roncalli Circus treads the high wire in Vienna (Austria). The Roncalli is a German circus, but most of its performers are Italian.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Acrobats caught by the camera in mid-air during a performance by Livio Togni’s Circus in Palermo.
An elephant arrayed in a fluorescent costume.Flying trapeze artists of the American Circus.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
P OET, 
S TOR Y-T EL L ER 
A ND
SCRIP TW RI T ER 
The Italian poet Tonino Guerra, who was born
in Santarcangelo di Romagna in 1923, gra-
duated in education studies from the University
of Urbina and is a world-famous scriptw r i t e r. He
has written over 100 screenplays, which have
been made into films by directors including
Michelangelo Antonioni (with whom he has just
written L’ Aq u i l o n e, an illustrated story for the
third millennium, published by Editoriale Delfi,
Cassina, Milan), Andrei Tarkovsky, the Ta v i a n i
brothers, Federico Fellini, Francesco Rosi and
Vittorio de Sica.
Some of his poems and short stories have
been translated into English, French, German,
Dutch and Spanish. Of one poem, H o n e y, the
great Italian writer Italo Calvino has said: “To n i n o
G u e r ra turns everything into fiction and poetry —
via the spoken word, writing or film, in Italian or
in the Emilio-Romagna dialect. We should all
learn his dialect so we can read these wonderful
stories in their original language.” ■
To contact Tonino Guerra, write by e-mail to
<delfi@pointest.com>
fuzzy glow from the dusty bulbs dotted all
around the huge drab area, and the
sounds and images of shows we had seen
as children came flooding back.
On days when the circus was in town,
even my mother Penelope joined in the
fun. Every morning, she would ask the
keeper of the African animals for the
droppings of the giraffes and the old lion,
and would use them to work wonders on
the flowers she grew in old saucepans.
The beautiful photos by Massimo
Siragusa which illustrate this scrapbook of
golden memories take me back to those
childhood days as well as my long visits
with the prodigious Fellini to Set no. 5
(one of 16) at Cinecittà. For him this set
was the real Via Veneto, the Via Veneto of
La Dolce Vita. Set no. 5 served as the back-
drop when the coffin with the great direc-
tor’s body was displayed to the public for
the last time on November 1, 1993.
These memories also take me back to
Russia, one of the countries I’ve loved
most, and bring to mind the time when I
worked for the director A n d r e i
Khryanovsky. A few years ago, I gave him
the script of a cartoon story called The
Grey-Bearded Lion. A film was recently
made of it which tells the story of a little
circus whose main attraction is an unu-
sual lion called Amedeo, or Teo to his
friends. As the years go by and he gets
older, divisions grow among the small
family of circus folk.
The great Popov
I also remember, like so many colou-
red bubbles, the times when I met the
gr e at Russian clow n s , e s p e c i a l l y
Karandash, who was so short that when
he stood behind a table, he seemed to be
sitting at it.
And Popov, the great Popov who per-
formed his finest routine one day when he
was in Amsterdam. He entered the ring
and prepared to eat a meal in a small
spotlight which lit up part of the ground.
When he finished, he gathered up the
light with his hands, as if it were bread-
crumbs, a trick he’d worked out with the
lighting technician. Just as he was leaving
the ring, he put the light in a shopping
bag. He received so much applause that
he stopped and threw the bag towards the
audience, which was then flooded with
light.
I can’t forget either the statues that
Ilario Fioravanti, an old sculptor from
Cesena, shaped with hesitant child-like
hands. In Pennabilli (the village in the
Marches region of Italy between Pesaro
and Urbina where I’ve lived for the past
d e c a d e ) , he assembled all the stat u e s
which reminded him of the circus and cir-
cus life.They are still in the rooms of an
old palazzo in the heart of the ancient vil-
lage, the Bargello. In cells which once
held prisoners, Fioravanti’s statues now
stand as if waiting for a round of applau-
se that might break out at any moment,
applause suspended in mid-air.
There’s something irresistible about
this world that floods my memory with
joy but also fills me with melancholy—the
last notes of the music we heard in the vil-
lage as the circus caravans prepared to
leave and then went on their way. The
sounds trailed away in the fog and beca-
me a kind of poignant lament that, stan-
ding on the tips of our toes, we strained to
hear until the very last note.
Afterwards, we would gather on the
patch of ground where the circus ring had
been. Sometimes we’d plant candles and
create a ring of light around us. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
An elephant of the Embell Riva Circus gives its trainer a ride.
The ringmaster of the Moira Orfei Circus.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
E D I T O R I A L
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 9
■
UNESCO is a factor of hope,because it is the one international organization which,
through all its progr a m m e s , respects and defends what is of unive rsal wo rth and dignity
in the mat e rial and spiritual heritage of all cultures, and thereby, the absolute
dignity of all human beings. . . .
G l o b a l i z ation is accelerating with dramatic speed, presenting a global challenge which
demands a global answe r.Yet the response must be made with all due respect for cultural
d i ve rsity and identity, for that priceless individual component that makes up the true dignity
of our many peoples.
But UNESCO can only go on providing the world with such hope, and such defence,
if it proves itself to be an adequate world instru m e n t . UN E S C O is not an end in itself. UN E S C O
is a world service,a tool which is at once delicate,highly complex, and precious. Huma-
nity may all the better avail itself of such a tool if all the wo r l d ’s states—and peoples—agr e e
once again to make proper use of it, and so contribute to its efficiency and universality.
UNESCO must once more represent the whole world, with no exceptions. I pledge to do
my best,in the course of my stewardship, to persuade those who stand outside to return
or to join.
But criticisms,not all of them unfair,have been leveled against this great instrument:
and failings,where verified,must be made good.The purpose of sound management is,
a g a i n , not an end in itself, but a duty to ensure that our institution fully discharges its gr e at
task as a true world serv i c e , responsible and accountable to the world—and to the wo r l d ’s
taxpayers.
Our resources are therefore not unlimited,nor should we spread ourselves too thin. I
propose that we streamline our activities within the limits of our bu d g e t s , and closely focus
upon those programmes which are our true mandate—not for the sake of fashionable aus-
t e ri t y, but in order to make a real impact where best we may, and where truly we must,p r o-
vide our needed service: in our ongoing war against poverty, through education and the
nurturing of human resources.
I suggest pursuit of our most practically conceived progr a m m e s , in co-operation with
leading institutions, scientists and scholars around the world, in terms of our four great
directives, on behalf of education,science,culture,and communication.
UN E S C O is a challenging paradox . It cannot lapse into a mere club for intellectuals, bu t
it must serve as a forum for international intellectual exchange.It cannot pretend to be
a research institution but must keep abreast of and stimulate research.It is not an opera-
tional agency, yet it must see that global ethics for peace, justice and solidarity, through
international co-operation in education, science, culture and communication, are both
morally observed and tangibly applied. F i n a l l y, UN E S C O is not a funding agency, a l t h o u g h
it must provide catalytic funds to generate further funding: in order to demonstrate that
ideals only take shape through action. . . .
In the whirl of this changing age, let us stand firm and faithful to our enduring pur-
pose: building peace in the minds of men. ■
(Extracts from an address gi ven by Mr Koïchiro Matsuura in Pa ris on 15 Nove m b e r , on the occa-
sion of his investiture as Director-General of UNESCO.)
IN TO ACT ION
Koïchiro Matsuura
Koïchiro Matsuura, who was
born in Tokyo in 19 37 ,
studied law at the University
of Tokyo and economics at
Haverford College
( Pennsylvania, U.S.A.). In
19 59, he began his career at
the Japanese Ministry of
Foreign Affairs, where he has
s e rved as Director-G e n e ral of
the Economic Co-opera t i o n
Bureau (19 8 8 - 19 9 0 ) ;
D i r e c t o r -G e n e ral of the
North American Affairs
Bureau (19 9 0 - 1992); Deputy
Minister for Foreign Affairs
( 19 9 2 - 1994), in which post he
oversaw Japan’s hosting of
the First Tokyo International
Conference on Africa n
Development; and since 19 9 4
as Ambassador to Fra n c e ,
A n d o r ra and Djibouti. He
also served for one year,
until November 1999, as
chairperson of UNESCO’ s
World Heritage Committee.
On November 12, UNESCO’ s
supreme ruling body, the
G e n e ral Conference grouping
188 Member Sta t e s ,
c o n firmed the choice made
by the Executive Board on 12
November and appointed Mr
M a t s u u ra to the post of
D i r e c t o r -G e n e ral of UNESCO.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
P L A N E T
F ORESTS: A HOT DEAL 
F OR A COOL ER WORL D
◗ Sophie Boukhari
Forests can play a key role in combating the greenhouse effect but current proposals for using
them raise a thicket of thorny issues
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
Many reforestation projects are underway in Brazil, but deforestation is still gaining ground. 
According to Greenpeace, 80 per cent of the felling is illegal.
■
Why are industrialists so keen on
trees these days? After the Japanese
vehicle-maker Toyota (see page 13)
and others, the French car firm Peugeot
launched a huge reforestation project in
late 1999. The result will be 10 million
trees growing on 12,000 deforested hec-
tares in the heart of the Brazilian
Amazon.
The aim of the $10 million project,
says Peugeot chief Jean-Martin Folz, is to
“make the idea of a carbon sink a reality.”
In other words, to show that reducing
consumption of fossil fuels—gas, oil and
coal—is not the only way to fight global
warming. By using the ability of vegeta-
tion to absorb and store carbon dioxide
( C O2) , the main greenhouse gas, t h e
amount of CO2 in the atmosphere can be
reduced.
Tropical forests:
a controversial role
Through the process of photosynthe-
sis a growing tree gives off oxygen and
absorbs water, light and CO2, which is
why expanding forests are what is known
as “carbon sinks”. Full-grown forests on
the other hand cease to be carbon sinks
and become carbon reservoirs.They store
huge amounts of carbon above and below
ground and play a neutral role in the CO2
equation. The carbon dioxide given off
when old trees decompose can be offset
by that which is absorbed when young
trees gr ow in their place. And when
forests burn, they give off CO2 and beco-
me sources of carbon.That is the theory.
In practice, however, very little is known
about the global carbon cycle and the role
of forests in it.
It is also unclear how forests will react
to global warming. “There are uncertain-
ties regarding the implications of increa-
sed CO2 concentration in the atmosphere
for photosynthesis, forest growth rates
and changes in carbon stocks in forests,”
says Indian scientist N.H. Ravindranath,
one of the three co-ordinators of a special
r e p o rt on forests produced by the
I n t e r g ove rnmental Panel on Climat e
Change (IPCC). Today’s carbon sink can
become a source of CO2 tomorrow.
According to currently available data,
the world’s main forest carbon sinks are in
the countries of the North (the United
S t at e s , C a n a d a , Europe and Russia).
After centuries of deforestation,mainly to
create farmland, these regions have been
gaining trees again in the past 100 years
or so. As a result of the revolution in
intensive agriculture, less land is needed
for farming.
On the other hand, large-scale defo-
restation is still taking place in tropical
countries where land hunger is constantly
increasing (see box opposite page). This
contributes to the increased concentra-
tion of greenhouse gases in the atmosphe-
re. The role of tropical forests in this
context is highly controversial. In theory,
as mature forests they should absorb as
much CO2 as they give out. But recent
studies suggest they actually absorb more
CO2 than was thought. In fact, says Youba
Sokona, deputy director of Enda Tiers
M o n d e , a non-gove rnmental organiza-
tion,“we have no clear idea of the state of
forest resources or the way they behave in
developing countries.” Forest sur veys are
very expensive, and not many have been
done in the countries of the South. The
estimates of the Food and Agriculture
O r g a n i z ation of the United Nat i o n s
(FAO) have sometimes been questioned.
Carbon 
credits
Despite all these unknown factors, the
notion of carbon sinks has become highly
topical—for political rather than scientific
reasons. It came of age in 1997, when it
was introduced into articles 3.3 and 3.4
of the Kyoto Protocol on Climat e
Change.
Under the protocol, which was the
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Article 3.3 says that “direct human-indu-
ced land use change and forestry activi-
ties, limited to afforestation, reforestation
and deforestation since 1990” can be
used by states parties to meet their com-
mitments. For example, a company may
fund a reforestation project in its own
c o u n t ry, or else a country like T h e
Netherlands,say, could sponsor tree plan-
t ations in Po l a n d . In 2008-2012, t h e
amount of CO2 these trees have absorbed
or “sequestrated” will be calculated and
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
Women carry seedlings into a wooded area as part of a forest rehabilitation project in Tanzania.
result of tough negotiations in the wake of
the 1992 United Nations Framewo r k
C o nvention on Climate Change, t h e
i n d u s t rialized countries promised to redu-
ce their annual net emissions of gr e e n h o u-
se gases by an average 5 per cent a ye a r
until 2008-2012, using the 1990 level as a
b a s e . To do this, some countri e s , n o t a b l y
the United Stat e s , insisted on the esta-
blishment of three “ flexibility mecha-
n i s m s ” .
The first involves setting up a market
where the rich countries will bargain with
each other to buy and sell emission per-
mits. The second is a “joint implementa-
tion” (JI) arrangement under which they
will earn carbon credits in exchange for
funding reduction of emissions in former-
ly communist eastern Europe through,
for example, industrial cleanup projects.
The third is a “clean development mecha-
nism” (CDM), which is like JI but ope-
rates between industrialized and develo-
ping countries. Many environmentalists
have sharply criticized this “international
trading in hot air” and accuse the coun-
tries that are the worst polluters of see-
king to shirk their obligation to thorough-
ly revamp their own energy consumption
practices.
Including the carbon sink idea in the
Kyoto Protocol is another way of making
the Protocol’s application more “ fle x ible”.
counted as part of such countries’ reduc-
tion in their own greenhouse gases.
Article 3.4 adds, without going into
specifics, that other human activities rela-
ting to carbon sources and sinks can be
taken into account. “These articles are
last-minute compromises,” says Michel
Raquet of Greenpeace Europe. “They
were drafted without much idea of their
implications or whether everyone agreed
on the meaning of the terms used. In fact,
they vary from one institute or country to
DEF ORES TAT ION GAT HERS SPEED
Over the last 150 years, says the Wo r l d
Resources Institute (WRI), deforestation and
changes in land use have been responsible for 30
per cent of the increase in greenhouse gas emis-
sions into the atmosphere.
At present, according to FAO, CO2 emissions
from these sources, especially in the tropics,
represent a fifth of the world’s carbon dioxide
emissions resulting from human activity. Forest
clearance to create farmland or pasture is a big
part of this. In the 1990s, Brazil emitted 27 times
more CO2 because of deforestation than from
fossil fuel combustion, according to Biomass
Users Network, a non-governmental organiza-
tion.
“Wood is usually burned on the spot because
it’s not worth keeping it,” says French forestry
expert Arthur Riedacker. “It’s also too expensive
to move. In Congo, it costs $130 a cubic metre to
bring timber out of the forest to the coast, while
pine wood or spruce only fetches $50 a cubic
metre in France.”
The WRI says that if nothing is done, deforesta-
tion could account for 15 per cent of the CO2 in the
atmosphere by 20 50, with the rest mainly due to
industrial pollution. Most of it will come from the
Amazon region. After 20 50, deforestation will decline
b e cause there will not be many forests left. The
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change ca l c u-
lates that 73 per cent of the world’s tropical forests
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
P L A N E T
Villagers water seedlings at a tree nursery in India.
another.” Future negotiations will sort
this out.
These talks will also try to decide—
this will be a far-reaching debate—whe-
ther or not to include carbon sinks in the
CDM. If they are included, rich countries
will be able to fund afforestation or anti-
deforestation projects in poor countries as
a way of obtaining carbon credits, instead
of carrying out often more costly schemes
at home to curb emissions from industry
or transport.
The Intergove rnmental Panel on
Climate Change (IPCC), the scientific
organ of the 1992 Convention,thinks that
carbon sinks can play an important role.
As the FAO report notes,“IPCC has esti-
mated, with a medium level of confiden-
c e , t h at globally, carbon sequestrat i o n
from reduced deforestation, forest rege-
neration and increased development of
p l a n t ations and agr o - f o r e s t ry betwe e n
1995 and 2050 could amount to 12 to 15
per cent of fossil fuel carbon emissions
over the same period.”
Arthur Riedacker, a French expert
involved in the IPCC’s work, also points
out that such schemes produce biomass
and timber, so reducing fossil fuel
c o n s u m p t i o n . Biomass is a renewa b l e
energy source. Wood can replace plastic
or concrete, whose manufacture uses
hydrocarbons. But Ashley Mattoon of the
Worldwatch Institute says the trade-off in
carbon sinks may be “a major loophole
[in the Protocol] which admits vast quan-
tities of fossil carbon into the skies” and
“encourages types of forestry that aren’t
very good for forests.”
Questionable
gains
To head off these dangers, everyone
agrees the carbon sink idea should be very
closely examined and tightly regulated.
The IPCC, which will report back in
2000, will have to be more precise about
the meaning of the terms “afforestation”,
“ r e f o r e s t at i o n ” and “ d e f o r e s t at i o n ” i n
article 3.3 so as to prevent abusive prac-
tices developing. For example, the text
currently says a country can chop down
an old forest and replace it by one of fast-
growing trees, notes Greenpeace expert
Bill Hare.The felling would not be coun-
ted in the country’s emissions but the
reforestation would earn carbon credits.
So the country involved would gain, but
not the atmosphere or the environment,
because an old forest and its soil contain
more carbon, which would be released by
the felling, than a managed forest ever
will. Biodiversity would also suffer.
Another problem would arise if Japan,
say, were to fund a forest protection pro-
ject in Malaysia. In return, it would ask
for carbon credits equal to the emissions
which the felling of the forest would have
produced. But how can we be sure that
the protection project is actually respon-
sible for preventing the forest from being
destroyed? And what is the point of pro-
tecting, say, a stretch of African savannah
if the local population can simply chop
down trees further away?
For the moment, the world is roughly
divided into three camps about the issue
of carbon sinks. One consists of several
rich countries (including the U.S., New
Zealand and Australia) that want a broad
definition and flexible use of carbon cre-
d i t s. In some countri e s , like New
Zealand, carbon sequestration from tree
plantations covers a very high percentage
of their greenhouse gas emissions. If they
are unrestrictedly taken into account in
2008-2015, they will allow such countries
to meet their commitments without
taking any steps in areas such as industry,
transport and human settlements.
In the U.S., which has pledged to cut
its emissions by 7 per cent over the next
10 years, the carbon sink mechanism is
being used to persuade Congress to drop
its refusal to ratify the Kyoto Protocol,
says Mattoon. The Clinton administra-
tion argues that the sinks “could compri-
se a significant portion of the country’s
total required emissions reductions.”
A recent article in New Scientist maga-
zine said Washington is even pressing for
article 3.4 to be amended to include
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 13
P L A N E T
TOYOTA MAKES TREES
◗ Yoshinori Takahashi
waste from wood products in the defini-
tion of a carbon sink. It is certainly better
to bury paper and wood waste in the
ground than to burn it and release more
CO2 into the atmosphere. But how far is
this going to go? “The spirit of Kyoto
demands that we should focus on things
t h at produce fewer greenhouse gases,
which means encouraging energy-saving,
transport reform and improved industrial
processes and housing, with improve-
ments in forestry practices as an extra,”
says Riedacker.
Conflicting 
interests
A second group includes European
countries which take a cautious stand and
are waiting for the IPCC report before
making up their minds.The third group is
mostly made up of poor countries, which
are divided on the issue, s ay s
R av i n d r a n at h . “ T h e y ’re interested in
development, not so much in carbon,”
says ENDA’s Sokona, who is a member of
the IPCC working party.
E ve ryone has different wishes and
constraints as far as development goes.
India, China and the countries of sou-
theast A s i a , which have competitive
industries, seem opposed to introducing
forestry projects into the CDM. They
would prefer the rich countries to invest
in them via industrial projects, which
would include more technology transfers.
But some Latin American countries,such
as Costa Rica, are basing their develop-
ment on eco-tourism, so they have an
interest in improving their forests.
Africa, where half of all greenhouse
gas emissions are caused by deforestation,
is hesitating because in a continent where
food security is still the top pri o ri t y,
people fear farmland will be lost if trees
are planted. But Africa’s weak industrial
base means it will probably not benefit
much from the CDM if forestry projects
are not included in it. So some experts are
in favour of it under certain conditions.
“Protected parks don’t interest us,”
says Sokona. “They mean moving people
off land without giving them anything in
return. It’s too easy for rich countries to
come and plant trees in our countries,put
a fence round them and earn carbon cre-
dits. However, I’m in favour of agrofores-
try, which meets our needs.”
Few countries have taken a clear stand
so far. Others are still making their calcu-
lations and trying to work out their posi-
tion. The real battle over the world’s
forests will come after May 2000, when
the IPCC will make its report. ■
Industrialists can no longer ignore the effects of
their activity on the environment. In a world
which is more and more polluted and threate-
ned by global warming, their reputation and
future depend on doing something about it.
The Japanese vehicle-maker Toyota has
understood this since the end of the 1980s. It
launched its “Toyota Forest” programme in
1992, the year of the Rio Earth Summit, with the
goal of using biotechnology to turn trees into
anti-pollution agents.
Today Toyota is proud of its experimental
forests, including Foresta Hills, half an hour by
car from the company’s headquarters. The fir m
is trying to revive s a t oy a m a, which are ancient
protected hills on the edge of populated areas.
They are a source of wood and prized items like
m a t s u t a ke mushrooms and u r u s h i, Japanese
l a c q u e r.
“In this forest, we’re developing the same
activities our ancestors did in the 19th century , ”
says Yasuhiko Komatsu, the project’s chief. “We
want to create s a t oy a m a for the 21st century. ”
The giant company’s engineers say they are
t rying to reduce vehicle emissions but cannot get
rid of them completely. So other solutions have
to be found—by using trees.
At Foresta Hills, the effect of different kinds of
trees on the level of carbon dioxide in the air ca n
be measured. In some places it is 10 to 20 times
l ower than in others. The most “effective” trees
are those which grow quickly, stand up to diffi-
cult surroundings and resist diseases and
insects, so these are the ones biologists want to
learn how to cultivate. Increasing the number of
chromosomes of some trees has boosted their
a b i l i ty to absorb toxic gases by a third.
Toyota is also researching into how to speed
up the growth of trees in very acidic soil with a
v i ew to the reforestation of southeast As i a ,
which has been devastated by deforestation.
Recently, the company began organizing refo-
restation activities outside Japan, and in August
1998 joined with paper manufacturers to set up
the firm of Australian Afforestation Pty. Over the
next decade, 5,000 fast-growing, drought-resis-
tant eucalyptus trees will be planted in Austra l i a ,
later to be chopped down and made into paper.
Toyota’s work has drawn criticism how e v e r.
Environmentalists are worried about the effects
on the environment of genetica l l y - m o d i fied spe-
cies. Others argue that the main priority in fig h-
ting the greenhouse effect is to reduce emissions
of pollutants and cut back on motor tra f fic .
“The car-makers are planting trees to give
themselves a nice green image while hoping
their vehicle sales don’t drop,” says Michel
Raquet of Greenpeace Europe. “What will they
get in return? Carbon credits, even though there
is no scientific guarantee that their forestry pro-
jects will have any effect on the atmosphere.”
“One of these days,” says Ashley Mattoon of
Worldwatch Institute, “we will have to ask our-
selves how much more time, energy and money
should be spent on tinkering with nature and
s a t i s fying our dependence on fossil fuels.” ■
◗ Tokyo-based journalist
Right,  a tree seedling whose chromosomes have been doubled. It will grow into a tree with greater
efficiency at absorbing toxic gases than the ordinary specimen, left, of the same species.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
encourage violence and revenge as solu-
tions to problems,experts say.
M o r e ove r , child rights activists contend
that corporal punishment goes against the
1989 United Nations Convention on the
Rights of the Child, which affirms the chil-
d ’s need for care and protection. A rticle 19
of the convention, which has been ratified
by 191 countries including Kenya , s p e c i-
fies that states must take appropriate mea-
sures to protect children from “all forms of
p hysical or mental violence, i n j u ry or abu s e ,
neglect or negligent treat m e n t , m a l t r e at-
ment or exploitation.”
The HRW report , based on a fie l d
study, including scores of interviews with
s t u d e n t s , t e a c h e rs , parents and offic i a l s ,
says that Kenyan children are often puni-
shed for petty offences like coming late to
school or wearing a torn uniform.
The problem has dire implications for
basic education.A recent study shows that
the enrolment rate in pri m a ry schools is
fast declining and only 42 per cent of those
enrolled in  first grade complete the pri-
mary school cycle.The decline is, among
other reasons,due to poverty and a hostile
learning environment,say analysts.
“Some students told us that they drop-
ped out of school because of severe beat i n g
by their teachers.This is in clear violation of
children’s right to education,” says Thon-
den.
“So far no teacher has been convicted
for these deat h s ,” s ays Jemimah Mwa k i s h a ,
a journalist who has written extensively on
the subject in Kenya’s leading newspaper
14 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
■
When Justus Omanga, a fourth gr a d e
student at Mobamba Secondary
School in Kenya ’s Kisii distri c t ,r e p e a-
tedly denied allegations that he had brought
a girl into the school compound one night
last A u g u s t , his teachers became furi o u s.
Four of the teachers kicked, hit and beat
Omanga so hard with a huge stick that the
b oy fell unconscious.A month later he died
in hospital as a result of severe damage to
his kidneys and other internal injuri e s ,
according to family members.
O m a n g a ’s case is not isolat e d . A c c o r-
ding to the Kenyan media corporal punish-
ment has led to the deaths of at least six
students in the last four ye a rs.While caning
is a regular feature in schools, some stu-
dents have suffered serious injuries which
include “ b ruises and cuts, broken bones,
knocked-out teeth and internal bleeding,”
s ays a recent report from the New Yo r k -
based non-gove rnmental organizat i o n
Human Rights Watch (HRW) titled Spare
the Child: C o rp o ral Punishment in Kenya n
Schools.
An incentive to violence
and revenge
K e nya is not the only country in the
world that still practises corporal punish-
m e n t .I n d e e d , only 70 countri e s ,b e gi n n i n g
with Sweden in 1979, h ave banned the
p r a c t i c e . But experts say Kenya is one of
the worst offenders when it comes to vio-
lence stemming from corporal punishment.
“In Kenya corporal punishment against
children in schools has reached dange-
rously high levels,” says Yodon Thonden, a
Tibetan-American who led the five-mem-
ber research team which prepared the
HRW report.
A p a rt from the brutality which is often,
in Kenya at least,associated with the prac-
t i c e , c o rporal punishment in itself can
p r ovoke anger in its victims, leading to
resentment and low-self esteem. It can also
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
SPA RE THE ROD, 
SAVE THE CHIL D
◗ Ethirajan Anbarasan
The widespread use of corporal punishment in Kenyan schools has led to increasing dropout
rates and in a few cases, to death
Daily Nation.
Neither are teachers commonly sen-
tenced for inflicting serious injuri e s. V i c-
tims often come from rural areas, w h e r e
people don’t have the finances to hire a
l aw yer and where legal aid is poor. In some
instances where teachers have been taken to
c o u rt , they have gone unpunished, as it has
been difficult to prove a motive in the killing
as required under the criminal law, Mwa-
kisha says.
Parents scared
to speak out
E x c e s s i vely harsh corporal punishment
tends to be particularly common in the
countryside.“In rural areas,parents don’t
f o rmally object to their children being bea-
ten for fear they [the children] might be
victimized further,” says Mwakisha.
In public, K e nyan education ministry
o f ficials have strongly denied the HRW alle-
g at i o n s ,s t ating that some isolated incidents
in rural schools have been exaggerat e d .
H owe ve r , in pri vat e , a senior educat i o n
ministry official admits that the report was
“more or less corr e c t .” He says teachers
“ b rutally beat children in many schools
without any proper reason.This is a prac-
tice that can only be stopped by abolishing
corporal punishment altogether.”
Nevertheless the recent deaths and the
r e p o rt have triggered a debate in Kenya on
banning corporal punishment, as other
A f rican countries including Namibia, B u r-
kina Faso, South Africa and Ethiopia have
done in recent years.
According to government regulations,
c o rporal punishment may be inflicted only
in cases of continued or gr ave neglect of
work, lying, bullying and gross insubordi-
nation.The beating, with a cane no more
than half an inch thick, can be gi ven only by
or in the presence of a head teacher. Regu-
lations state that boys should be hit on the
backside and girls on the palm of the hand.
Students are not supposed to get more than
six strokes as punishment and a wri t t e n
‘Some students told us that
they dropped out of school
b e cause of severe beating by
their teachers. This is in clear
violation of children’s right to
e d u ca t i o n ’
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
record of all the proceedings should be
kept.
“The rules are hardly followe d . Te a-
c h e rs use clubs, bamboo canes, s o m e t i m e s
even a rubber whip to beat the students,”
says Thonden.
For many teachers, a tool to cope
with big classes
A strong constituency of Kenyan tea-
c h e rs is in favour of retaining corp o r a l
p u n i s h m e n t , e ven though they concede
more restrictions are required. A few ye a rs
ago when the Director of Education tried to
make the practice illegal, the teachers ’u n i o n
said it would not recognize such a ban.
Many teachers argue that without cor-
poral punishment the schools would des-
cend into chaos and that children wo u l d
become even more unruly by the time they
reached high school. In fa c t , they believe
that in the long run corporal punishment
means less rather than more violence.
“ We s t e rn countries gi ve excessive freedom
to their children. Look at the violent inci-
dents in many schools in the United
S t at e s ,” s ays Lawrence Kahindi Majali,
Assistant Secretary General of the Kenya
punishment by citing Kenya ’s long tradi-
t i o n . “When we were under British ru l e ,
those who refused to pay taxes or those who
did not obey the rules were caned in public.
The use of the cane was a symbol of autho-
rity and the legacy continues,” s ays Majali.
M a ny teachers admit that they often
c a rry out corporal punishment without the
presence of the headmaster. In violation of
the rules,the students are sometimes bea-
ten all over the body, and often records of
c o rporal punishment are not kept in
schools.
Stephen P, a fifth grade student in Moi
p ri m a ry school in Nairobi, s ays teachers
cane him or slap him regularly. His offences
include coming late to school and not
p aying school fees on time. Elizabeth Z,
who is in the fourth standard, s ays teachers
slap her and pinch her on the cheeks for
not doing homework.
“My children were not treated well by
the teachers after I complained about
caning by their class teacher,” s ays Deborah
N,a mother of two living in Nairobi.
Teachers are also afraid.They quote a
growing number of instances in which tea-
c h e rs have been attacked by students. I n
National Union of Teachers (KNUT).
M a ny Kenyan teachers also contend
that corporal punishment is one of the few
d i s c i p l i n a ry tools available gi ven large class
s i z e s. According to a gove rnment report
there are 5,718,700 students and 192,000
t e a c h e rs at pri m a ry school leve l , giving a
teacher-pupil ratio of 1:31. In many schools
classes of 50-60 students are common.
The burden is heaviest in rural areas
where retired and transferred teachers ’
posts are often left va c a n t . As a result,
a u t h o rities frequently combine two or three
schools in a regi o n , putting additional pres-
sure on the existing teaching staff.
Te a c h e rs also try to justify corp o r a l
December 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
“The best method of teaching mathematics?” A cartoon published in Daily Nation, a leading Kenya newspaper.
‘When we were under British
rule, those who refused to pay
taxes or those who did not
obey the rules were caned in
public. The use of the cane was
a symbol of authority and the
l e g a cy continues’
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
HE AVY HANDED TRE AT MEN T
one extreme case,a class prefect was killed
by students in the town of Nye ri , near Nai-
r o b i , early this year for being too strict with
them.
The fact that corporal punishment
leads so often to brutality may be sympto-
m atic of the pressures facing the whole tea-
ching profession. Te a c h e rs ’ s a l a ri e s — r a n-
ging from 4,000 Kenyan shillings ($60) to
about 15,000 ($200) a month—are among
the lowest in the civil serv i c e .Te a c h e rs seem
to take their frustrations out on their stu-
d e n t s , s ay expert s. “ L ow salaries reduce
teacher morale, and many of the lowe s t -
paid teachers are forced to find housing in
slum areas,” says the HRW report.
Mounting tension
E d u c ation ministry officials say gui-
dance counsellors in secondary schools
encourage teachers to adopt methods to
deal with depressed or problem students
and thus avoid tensions leading to corp o r a l
punishment.
The counsellor discusses with the
concerned student why he or she commit-
ted an offence and tries to find solutions.
But officials admit that there are not
enough counsellors in schools due to fin a n-
cial constraints and even those who have
been posted as counsellors undertake other
responsibilities due to shortage of staff.
Te a c h e rs in favour of reducing corp o r a l
punishment feel that the best place for
introducing altern at i ve disciplinary
methods is the Teacher Training Pro-
gr a m m e s. At present teachers say that they
hardly spend more than four to five hours
on classroom management during their ini-
tial two - year training period for pri m a ry
school.
Realizing the gr avity of the problem,
m a ny non-gove rnmental organizat i o n s
h ave now joined the campaign to abolish
c o rporal punishment and have started wo r-
king with teachers to minimize its use until
the law is changed.
“Until a legal sanction is obtained, we
decided it would be better to work with the
teachers,” says Jacqueline Anam-Mogeni,
child rights adviser at the Netherlands
Development Organization (NDO).
The Nairobi-based NDO organizes
workshops and training programmes to
help teachers to get to grips with their pro-
blems and encourage them to use counsel-
ling methods and other forms of punish-
ment,such as manual work.
Alternative
solutions
NDO selects a group of teachers and
vo l u n t e e rs from other non-gove rn m e n t a l
o r g a n i z ations from a particular regi o n
where corporal punishment incidents are
h i g h , and organizes workshops exposing
them to human rights and child ri g h t s
issues.After a week’s training, the teachers
go back to their schools and return for eva-
luation every three months.
“We first ask the participants how they
t r e at their own children at home. Once they
realize there is a problem they themselves
come up with altern at i ve solutions,” s ay s
Mogeni.
The first session attracted 24 part i c i-
pants from different parts of Kenya.Some
t e a c h e rs say their attitude towards children
has changed after part i c i p ating in the
course.
“Before I went for the child rights trai-
n i n g, I always viewed the punishment as
p a rt of the learning process. N ow I wo r k
with the pupils almost at a level of part-
n e rs h i p,” s ays Esther Nyakio Ngugi , a tea-
cher at Kiri giti Girls A p p r oved school in
K i a m bu .
Teachers who participated in the pro-
gramme say they have realized that they
were basically driving away students from
schools due to constant beatings.
“This is only a begi n n i n g . We need
more gove rnment and public support till
we finally abolish corporal punishment,”
says Mogeni. ■
Co r p o ral punishment is legal not only in Ke n y a ,
but also in a number of other east Africa n
countries, including Tanzania, Sudan and Somalia.
Governments complain that there are not enough
resources and trained personnel to reduce the size
of big classes, which some teachers find difficult to
manage without corporal punishment.
In Tanzania, a few students have reportedly
died after severe corporal punishment in schools.
Many teachers do not like using this form of
punishment but they “think it is the easiest way to
manage big classes,” says Dale Chandler, Executive
Director of Kuleana, a Centre for Children’s Rights
based in Tanzania.
Kuleana works with other NGOs in the region to
raise awareness among teachers and parents of 
the negative aspects of corporal punishment. 
Chandler says the campaign aims to drive home the
point that if you mistreat children they tend to
disobey rules when they become adults.
A legal ban on corporal punishment in schools
has not improved matters in Ethiopia. “Students
continue to be beaten by teachers despite the ban
enforced in 1988,” says Tibebu Bogaie, progra m m e
co-ordinator of “Swedish Save the Children”, an
NGO based in Addis Ababa. The organization,
which published a report on corporal punishment
in Ethiopia early this year, is campaigning against
the practice in schools as well as in homes.
In Sudan, teachers say schools run by
missionaries in the south organize guidance and
counselling programmes for students to identify rea-
sons for their misbehaviour. But they warn that
ever growing classes might force them to switch to
corporal punishment to deal with indiscipline.
However, experts disagree with the view that
indiscipline can be tackled only by corporal punish-
ment. Peter Newell, co-ordinator of EP O CH - Wo r l d-
wide, an NGO campaigning against corpora l
punishment, says that in countries where the pra c-
tice was banned decades ago “schools are not fal-
ling apart due to indiscipline. Beating can’t be an
excuse for lack of resources. It is a fundamental
breach of human rights.” ■
+ É
Useful websites
http://www.unicef.org
http://www.stophitting.com
http://www.freethechildren.org
For more information on child rights and
corporal punishment
EPOCH-Worldwide
77, Holloway Road, London N7 8JZ
Telephone: 00-44-171-700 0627
Fax: 00-44-171-700 1105
E-mail: epoch-worldwide@mcrl.poptel.org.uk
‘Before I went for the child
rights training, I always 
v i ewed the punishment 
as part of the learning process.
Now I work with the pupils
almost at a level of
p a r t n e r s h i p ’
‘ Low salaries reduce 
teacher morale, and many 
of the lowest-paid teachers 
are forced to find housing 
in slum areas’
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 17
FOCUS
Me m o ry: making p e a c e
with a violent pas t
C o n te n ts
1 8 The evil that men doÉ
Tz vetan To d o rov
2 0 Building blocks of international justice
2 1 Guatemala: ÔWe canÕt forg i ve until 
we have justiceÕ
I n t e rview with Rosalina Tuyuc by Maite Rico
2 2 South Africa:
¥Quandaries of compro m i s e
Njabulo S. Ndebele
2 4 ¥The price of truth
Max du Pre e z
2 5 C h i l e :
¥Doing a deal with memory
Oscar Goday Arc a y a
2 6 ¥An unwritten page of history
Fabiola Letelier del Solar 
and Victor Espinoza Cueva s
28 Russia: an unfinished job
Alexis Bere l ow i t c h
3 0 Cambodia: a wound that will not heal
Rithy Pa n h
3 3 Rw a n d aÕs collective amnesia
Benjamin Sehene
3 5 Bosnia and Herze g ovina: 
an impossible re c o n c i l i a t i o n ?
James Lyo n
3 0 Can we pre vent crimes against humanity?
I n t e rview with Louise Arbour by Martine Jacot
A
s much of the world has its eyes fixed,
at the turn of the millennium, on the
future, this Focus section, in contrast,
looks back at the past. How, it asks, have
nations that endured atrocities in the
second half of this century come to terms
with their ordeal? What obstacles have lain
in their path? Between remembrance and
forgetting, how can they make peace with
the past and build the foundations for a
better future?
In a scene-setting article, Tzvetan
Todorov explains why we ought to
remember the past but not endlessly rake
over it. Rosalina Tuyuc from Guatemala
develops this idea and insists that the first
step to reconciliation involves knowing who
to forgive.
The ways in which societies react to
terrible experiences are shaped by their
history, the forces that propel them forward
or hold them back. Post-apartheid South
Africa made a new departure, as Njabulo
Ndebele points out, when it brokered a deal
offering amnesty in return for truth. But
although this may have helped to ease the
reconciliation process, some victims protest
that freedom should not be bought by
confessing to a crime. In Chile, Oscar Godoy
notes that amnesty for crimes committed
under the dictatorship has smoothed the
transition to democracy, but, say Fabiola
Letelier and Victor Espinoza, it has not
softened grim memories.
In Russia, the work of memory is
incomplete. In Cambodia it is to a large
extent blocked, laments film-maker Rithy
Panh, and in Rwanda it is impossible,
according to Benjamin Sehene. A similar
situation exists in Bosnia.
Finally, Canadian jurist Louise Arbour
hopes that the increasingly long arm of
international law, by establishing
irrefutable facts, can at least prevent the
past from being mythologized and may
even prevent crimes against humanity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
The evil that men do. . .
◗ Tz vetan To d o rov
The collective memory must be free to come to terms with grief and shape a better future
◗ Mr Todorov, who was born in
Bulgaria and has lived in
France since 1963, is a director
of studies at the French
National Scientific Research
Institute (CNRS). His books
translated into English include
Morals of History (University of
Minnesota Press, 1995), French
Tragedy: Scenes of Civil War,
Summer 1944 (Dartmouth
College Press, 1996) and
Convergences: Inventories of
the Present (Harvard
University Press, 1993).
‘W
e must draw a veil over all the horr o rs
of the past,” said Winston Churchill not
long after the end of the Second Wo r l d
Wa r. Around the same time, the A m e rican philoso-
pher George Santayana issued a wa rn i n g, o f t e n
r e p e ated since, to the effect that “those who forget
the past are condemned to repeat it.” For those of
us who have experienced the painful history of the
20th century, which of these two injunctions is the
most useful? W h at should we do—forget or
r e m e m b e r ?
The two operations are contradictory in
appearance only. Remembering is always, by defi-
nition, an interaction between forgetting (erasu-
re) and complete preservation of the past—some-
thing that is virtually impossible. The Argentine
writer Jorge Luis Borges creates a character in his
s h o rt story Funes el memori o s o (Funes the
Memorious) who remembers every detail of his
life. It is a terrifying experience.
Memory selects from the past what seems
important for the individual or for the communi-
ty. It organizes this selection and imprints its
values on it. Peoples prefer to remember the glo-
rious pages of their history rather than shameful
episodes, and individuals often try unsuccessfully
to free themselves from the memory of a trauma-
tic event.
How to live with painful memories
Why do we need to remember? Because the
past is the very core of our individual or collecti-
ve identity. If we do not have a sense of our own
identity and the confirmation of our existence
that it provides, we feel threatened and paralyzed.
The need for an identity is thus quite legitimate.
We have to know who we are and what group we
belong to. But people, like groups, live among
other people and other groups. And so it is not
enough simply to say that everyone has the right
to exist. We also have to consider how our exerci-
se of this right affects the existence of others. In
the public arena, not all reminders of the past are
worthy ones, and those that encourage revenge
are always suspect.
The victims of evil may, in their personal lives,
be tempted to try to forget the experience com-
pletely, blotting out painful or humiliating memo-
ri e s. To a woman who has been raped, f o r
example, or a child who has been the victim of
incest, might it not be better to act as if these
traumatic events never happened? We know from
people’s reactions that this is unwise, because
such a blanket refusal to remember is dangerous.
Repressed memories remain more alive than ever
and give rise to severe neuroses. It is better to
accept a distressing past than to deny or repress
it. The important thing is not to go to the other
extreme and endlessly brood over it, but to gra-
dually distance oneself from it and neutralize it—
in a sense to tame it.
This is how mourning functions in our lives.
First we refuse to accept the loss we have expe-
rienced and we suffer terribly from the sudden
absence of a loved one. Later,while never ceasing
to love them, we give them a special status—they
are neither absent nor present as they were befo-
re. A distancing process develops, and eases the
pain.
An act of faith in the future
Communities are rarely tempted to try to for-
get completely evil events that have befallen
them.Afro-Americans today do not seek to forget
the trauma of slavery their ancestors suffered.The
descendants of the people who were shot and
burned to death in Oradour-sur-Glane1 in 1944,
do not want the crime to be forgotten.In fact they
want to preserve the ruins of the village left by the
event.
Here too, as in the case of individuals, it might
be hoped that the barren alternatives of totally
erasing the past or endlessly poring over it could
be avoided.The suffering should be inscribed in
the collective memory, but only so that it can
increase our capacity to face the future. This is
what pardons and amnesties are for.They are jus-
tified when crimes have been publicly admitted,
not to make sure they are forgotten but to let
bygones be bygones and give the present a new
chance. Were Israelis and Palestinians not right
when they met in Brussels in March 1998 and
noted that “just to start talking to each other, we
have to leave the past in the past”?
When Churchill called for for a veil to be
drawn over past horrors, he was right in a sense,
but his injunction must be qualified by all kinds
of conditions. No one should prevent memory
from being regained. Before we turn the page,
said future Bulgarian president Jeliu Jelev after
the fall of communism, we should first read it.
And forgetting means very different things to evil-
doers and to their victims. For the latter, it is an
act of generosity and faith in the future; for the
1.A French village where the SS massacred 642 persons as
a reprisal for attacks by the Resistance.
It seems unjust to
ask victims to pro t e c t
those who tormented
them ye s t e rd a y, and
yet this is the
responsibility they
must now shoulder.
B e r n a rd Ko u c h n e r, 
United Nations Sp e c i a l
Re p re s e n t a t i ve for Ko s ovo
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
A person or a community may need to appro-
priate the memory of a past hero or—more sur-
prisingly—a victim as a way of asserting their
right to exist.This serves their interests, but does
not make them any more virtuous. It can in fact
blind them to injustices they are responsible for in
the present.
The limits of this kind of remembering, which
emphasizes the roles of the hero and the victim,
were illustrated during the ceremonies held in
1995 to mark the 50th anniversary of the bom-
bing of Hiroshima and Nagasaki. In the United
States,people were only interested in recalling the
heroic role of the U.S. in defeating Japanese mili-
tarism. In Japan, attention focused on the victims
of the atomic bombs.
But there is a lot to be said for rising above
one’s own suffering and that of one’s relatives and
opening up to the suffering of others, and not
claiming an exclusive right to the status of former
victim. By the same token, accepting the wrongs
we have done ourselves—even if they were not as
serious as the wrongs done to us—can change us
for the better.
The past has no rights of its own. It must
serve the present, just as the duty to remember
must serve the cause of justice. ■
December 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 19
Me m o ry: making p e a c e with a violent pas t
former it results from cowardice and refusal to
accept responsibility.
Yet is remembering the past enough to preve n t
it from repeating itself, as Santayana seems to say ?
Far from it. In fa c t , the opposite usually happens.
To d ay ’s aggressor finds justific ation for his actions
in a past in which he was a victim. Serb nat i o n a l i s t s
h ave sought justific ation by looking ve ry fa r
back—to their military defeat by the Turks in
K o s ovo in the 14th century.
The French justified their belligerence in 1914
by referring to the injustice they had suffered in
1 8 7 1 . Hitler found reasons in the humiliat i n g
Tr e aty of Ve rsailles at the end of the First Wo r l d
War to convince Germans to embark on the
S e c o n d . And after the Second World Wa r , the fa c t
t h at the French had been victims of Nazi bru t a l i t y
did not prevent them—in many cases the same
people who had joined the army after fighting in
the resistance—from attacking and tort u ring civi-
lians in Indochina and A l g e ri a . Those who do not
forget the past also run the risk of repeating it by
r e ve rsing their role: there is nothing to stop a vic-
tim from later becoming an aggr e s s o r.The memo-
ry of the genocide which the Jews suffered is vivid
in Israel, yet the Palestinians have in turn been vic-
tims of injustice.
Remember to forg e t !
Immanuel Ka n t ,
German philosopher 
( 17 2 4 - 1 8 0 4 )
Portraits of people who disappeared under the Pinochet regime look out from a wall in Santiago de ChileÕs Humachuco Renca neighbourhood.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
T h e re, at Auschwitz,
something happened
that could not
p reviously have been
imagined. T h e re
people touched the
p rofound layer of
solidarity between all
those who have a
human face, the
essence of the
relationship betwe e n
man and man. . . .
A u s c h w i t z
t ransformed the
conditions of
permanence in
relations betwe e n
human beings.
J  rgen Habermas,
German sociologist (1929- )
Crimes against 
humanity
The first definition of these crimes was given
in the Charter of the Intern ational Military
Tribunal set up by the Allies to prosecute the
major Nazi war criminals (the Nuremberg
Tribunal) in 1945. It runs as follows: “murder,
e x t e rm i n at i o n , e n s l ave m e n t , d e p o rt at i o n , a n d
other inhumane acts committed against any civi-
lian population, before or during the war, or per-
secutions on political, racial or religious grounds
in execution of or in connection with any crime
within the jurisdiction of the Tribunal,whether or
not in violation of the domestic law of the coun-
try where perpetrated.”
The United Nations Convention on the Non-
Applicability of Stat u t o ry Limitations to Wa r
Crimes and Crimes Against Humanity of 1968
added the following provision:“eviction by armed
attack or occupation and inhuman acts resulting
from the policy of apartheid, and the crime of
genocide.”
Genocide
This term coined by Raphael Lemkin, a
Polish-born American scholar, comes from the
Greek word genos (race or tribe) and the Latin
suffix cide (from caedere, to kill).
Regarded as the most serious crime against
h u m a n i t y, it was legally defined by the
Convention for the Prevention and Punishment
of the Crime of Genocide, which was unani-
mously adopted by the United Nations General
Assembly on December 9, 1948, entered into
force in 1951, and has so far been ratified by 130
states. Three major conditions for the identifica-
tion of genocide (article 2) are:
1) The victims must belong to a national, ethni-
cal, racial or religious group, as such. Political,
economic or cultural groups (e.g. the victims of
the Khmer Rouge in Cambodia) are thus 
excluded.
2) The members of this group are killed or perse-
cuted because of their membership of the group.
3) Genocide is a planned collective crime com-
mitted by those who hold state power, on their
behalf or with their express or tacit consent.
Article 3 defines as punishable acts: genocide;
conspiracy to commit genocide;direct and public
incitement to commit genocide; an attempt to
commit genocide; and complicity in genocide.
Article 4 stipulates that all persons commit-
ting genocide shall be punished, whether they are
constitutionally responsible rulers, public officials
or private individuals.
The International 
Criminal Court (ICC)
The notion of an international penal tribunal
is mentioned in the 1948 Genocide Convention.
But it was not until 1998 that 120 countries (out
of 160 participants) meeting in Rome adopted a
statute for a permanent International Criminal
Court (ICC) to sit in The Hague (Netherlands).
The Court will be created when 60 states have
ratified the treaty on its statutes, a process which
should take two or three years.
The ICC will have (non-retroactive) jurisdic-
tion over war crimes, crimes against humanity,
and genocide, under certain conditions.
Signatories have the opportunity not to recognize
its jurisdiction over war crimes.
Ad hoc 
War Crimes Tribunals
The War Crimes Tribunal for the former
Yugoslavia was set up by a resolution of the UN
Security Council in May 1993. Based in The
Hague, it is empowered to prosecute those char-
ged with serious violations of international law on
the territory of the former Yugoslavia, including
war crimes, crimes against humanity, and genoci-
de.
So far 91 persons have been charged (inclu-
ding Yugoslav President Slobodan Milosevic), 31
of whom are in custody. Sentences ranging from
seven days to 20 years have been handed down to
eight defendants. Four trials are currently being
held.
The Tribunal for Rwanda, based in Arusha,
Tanzania, was set up by the UN Security Council
in November 1994. It has jurisdiction over the
same crimes as the above, committed in Rwanda
or neighbouring countries between January and
December 1994.
So far, 48 persons have been charged, 38 of
whom are in custody. Five defendants have been
sentenced, including three to life imprisonment
for genocide. Three trials are currently being
held. ■
B u i l d i n g b l o c k s
of international justice
War crimes presuppose combat between nations. Genocide and crimes against humanity, on
the other hand, may be committed during conflicts within states. An international criminal
c o u rt to try these offences is in the works.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
ÔWe canÕt forg i ve until 
we have j u s t i c eÕ I n t e rview with Rosalina Tu y u c
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 21
Me m o ry: making p e a c e with a violent pas t
R
osalina Tuyuc has spent the past 17 ye a rs wa i t i n g.
One night in June 1982, the Guatemalan army
came and took her father away.“ F rancisco Tuyuc is
d e a d ,”she was later told by the military,who never return e d
his body.Another night,in May 1985,they took away her
h u s b a n d ,a peasant leader.
But Rosalina, a 43-year-old Kakchiquel Maya n
I n d i a n ,was not deterred and in 1988 she founded the
N ational A s s o c i ation of Guatemalan W i d ows (Conav i-
g u a ) ,whose 15,000 members are today fighting to ensure
the victims of the country ’s civil war are not fo r go t t e n .I n
1 9 9 5 ,Rosalina was elected to parliament as a deputy for the
coalition of left-wing part i e s.
Can time ease the pain for those who have lost
a loved one?
No, you never find peace from that. My children
still ask me what’s happened to their father and if
he’s coming home. We relatives of people who’ve
disappeared are looking for our loved ones, and
we don’t find them,either dead or alive.Now that
the state has admitted that abuses occurred,it has
a moral duty to tell us where our dead are buried.
Many of them were executed at military bases. In
the name of reconciliation, the army must say
where they are. Most people just want to give
their spouses or children a Christian burial.
Have the aims of Conavigua changed since the
peace agreement was signed in 1996 and the
Historical Clarification CommissionÕs report
was published in February 1999?
The report confirmed we ’d been right about the extent
of the repression.N ow we ’re fighting to get the peace
accords applied and for Indian rights to be recogni-
z e d . But we’ll continue to seek compensation for vic-
tims of the wa r , to be told where the mass gr aves are
and to bring impunity to an end.
What kind of compensation?
The gove rnment has launched a plan to compen-
s ate communities—by introducing electri fic at i o n
and building schools, roads and bri d g e s — but it’s
forgotten the widow s.We want direct individual
c o m p e n s ation for the women themselve s ,i n c l u d i n g
a psychological support progr a m m e , s c h o l a rs h i p s
for their children and help in recovering their rela-
tives’bodies from unmarked graves.
Can anything more be done to fight impunity? 
Keep on trying those responsible. We don’t want
revenge, we want justice.We’d like to take matters
to an international court because it’s very hard in
Guatemala to obtain justice.The trials are costly,
they drag on for years and the results are not very
credible. But we’re going to bring to court at least
a few of the 80,000 cases we’ve listed.
How do you balance the demands of the vic-
timsÕfamilies and political reality, which
involves making concessions to safeguard the
transition process?
Forgiving doesn’t mean forgetting. First we need
to know who to forgive. Many families don’t
know who killed their relatives. And if we don’t
manage to establish who was responsible, history
may repeat itself. There’s always the fear of a
backlash from certain sectors but we can’t forgive
until we have justice.
Do the peace accords take the victims into
account?
The agreements led to a “ r e c o n c i l i ation law ”w h i c h
we regard as an amnesty. It doesn’t apply to acts of
g e n o c i d e , kidnapping and tort u r e .We voted against
this law and we will oppose any other amnesty.T h e
a rmy and the guerrillas share responsibility for the
wa r , though in different measure. I t ’s normal that
their leaders have made peace with one another,
but in the villages, families are not even speaking to
each other. T h e r e , r e c o n c i l i ation will take a long
t i m e . ■
I n t e rview by Maite Rico, Guatemalan journalist
Ti m e l i n e
1 95 4: The CIA ove rt h rows the left-wing government of President Jacobo Arbenz,
ushering in a series of military coups and upheavals.
1962: The first guerrilla groups appear.
1 9 8 1 - 8 3: The height of the civil war. The four rebel groups combine to form the
Guatemalan National Revolutionary Union (URNG).
1986: Election of the first civilian president for 16 years, Vinicio Cerezo.
1991: Start of peace negotiations between the URNG and the government.
1 9 9 6: Signature of peace agreements on “the rights and identity of indigenous
peoples”, in December under UN auspices.
1 9 9 9: The Historical Clarification Commission publishes, in Fe b r u a r y, a re p o rt called
“ Remembering silence”. It estimates that more than 200,000 people disappeared or
were killed between 1962 and 1996, and blames the army for 93% of the 626 mas-
sacres it says took place. ■
Many things 
a re torn away 
that I wished 
to keep for eve r, 
and the tearing will, 
I know, bring
m i s f o rtune, gre a t e r
than the span of 
a human life.
Franz Kafka, Cze c h
writer (1883-1924)
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
South Africa: quandaries 
of c o m p ro m i s e
◗ Njabulo S. Ndebele
South AfricaÕs Truth and Reconciliation Commission was set up to offer amnesty in exc h a n g e
for disclosure of events in the apartheid years. How successful has it been?
◗ Former Vice Chancellor and
Principal of the University of
the North in South Africa and
author of South African
Literature and Culture:
Rediscovery of the Ordinary
and Fools and Other Stories.
I
n his book Tomorrow is Another Country, South
African journalist Allister Sparks describes how
Nelson Mandela’s A f rican National Congr e s s
( A N C ) , and the apartheid gove rnment of South
A f rica were forced to recognize the need for a nego-
t i ated settlement. In a crucial meeting between the
ANC and the right-wing generals of the South A f ri-
can armed forces,Mandela declared:
“ ‘If you want to go to wa r , I must be honest
and admit that we cannot stand up to you on the
battlefield.We don’t have the resources. It will be a
long and bitter struggle, many people will die and
the country may be reduced to ashes.But you must
remember two things.You cannot win because of
our numbers : you cannot kill us all.And you cannot
win because of the international community.They
will rally to our support and they will stand with
us.’ General Viljoen was forced to agree.The two
men looked at each other . . . [and] faced the truth
of their mutual dependency.”
This declarat i o n , and its acceptance by eve ryo n e
at that meeting, i l l u s t r ates one of the major fa c t o rs that
led to the foundation of the Truth and Reconciliat i o n
Commission (TRC) in 1995 (see box ) .The basis of
a ny compromise is that contending parties display a
willingness to gi ve up irreconcilable goals, and then
enter into an agreement that yields substantial bene-
fits to all part i e s.The apartheid gove rnment of South
A f rica desired to continue to hold on to the reins of
p owe r , but was willing to allow for increased political
p a rt i c i p ation by blacks.The liberation move m e n t ,o n
the other hand, desired the complete removal of white
p owe r. Neither of these goals seemed achieva b l e
without an all-out wa r. It seemed in the best interest
of all to avoid such a situat i o n .
One of the demands of the beleaguered apar-
theid gove rnment was that in exchange for loss of
p ower there should be a blanket amnesty for all the
agents of apart h e i d ,p a rticularly the police and the
a rmed forces. But while such an outcome would be
b e n e ficial to whites, it would not enjoy the support of
those who were victims of apart h e i d .They wo u l d
rightly feel that the benefic i a ries and enforcers of
a p a rtheid were getting away too easily. The wo rs t
outcome of such a solution would be that black
South A f ri c a n s , victims of apart h e i d , would lose
c o n fidence in any of their leaders who could accept
such a solution.
The flaw in this equation is that it does not offer
a substantial benefit for both sides, and therefore
does not inspire unive rsal confid e n c e .W h at wa s
finally agreed upon was conditional amnesty.
F i rs t l y, the victims of apartheid should have the
o p p o rtunity to tell what happened to them, and for
their sufferings to be publicly acknow l e d g e d .
S e c o n d l y, the perp e t r at o rs of political crimes should
account for their deeds by making full and tru t h f u l
disclosure of their actions. L a s t l y, r e p a r at i o n s
should be made to the victims.
An important aspect of the amnesty process is the
s t i p u l ation that the life of the TRC be prescri b e d ,
on the grounds that a time frame would provide an
i n c e n t i ve for perp e t r at o rs wishing to come forwa r d
a n d , after making full disclosure, to be amnistied.
Failure to take advantage of the process within the
p r e s c ribed time would open perp e t r at o rs to prose-
cution in the ordinary courts of law.
The shame of public exposure
D u ring the hearings held by the T R C , h a rr o-
wing stories of suffering and cruelty were heard.
Did the process result in reconciliation?
One strong criticism of the amnesty process is
that it frustrates justice and the desire for punish-
ment.This does not take into account the fact that
m a ny of the recipients of amnesty experience a kind
of punishment they never anticipat e d : the shame
of being publicly exposed. The exposure of their
p a rt i c i p ation in despicable acts of cruelty has in
some cases resulted in broken families,disorienta-
tion and loss of self-esteem—a form of punishment
t h at can arguably be far more deva s t ating than that
exacted by an ordinary jail sentence. Equally, the
contrition leading to a plea for forgiveness,as part
of a quest for reacceptance in society, can be fa r
more restorative than the hoped-for rehabilitative
effects of an ordinary prison term.The cure in the
method of the TRC is located within social practice
rather than in the artificiality of punitive isolation.
This experience raises legitimate questions about
traditional methods of retributive justice.
It can be said that as a result of the T R C ,S o u t h
A f rica has become a more sensitive and a more com-
plex society. South A f ricans have been forced to
confront the complex contradictions of the human
c o n d i t i o n , and the need to devise adequate social
a rrangements to deal with them.The healing that
results will not be instant. It will come from the 
I was chained as yo u
we re chained. I was
f reed, and you have
been freed. So if I can
p a rdon my
o p p ressors, you can
t o o.
Nelson Mandela,
former President 
of South Africa (1918- )
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 23
Le sida dferle: a l e rte z l es jeunes !Me m o ry: making p  a c e with a violent pa t
Ti m e l i n e
1 9 4 8 - 1 95 1: The National Pa rty comes to power in 1948 and strengthens segre g a t i o-
nist laws against Blacks (76% of the population) adopted since 1911 and builds apar-
theid (segregation between “Whites, Coloureds and Africans”) into a system.
1 959 - 1 9 6 4: Mounting protest. The regime takes a harder line. African National
Congress (ANC) leaders, including Nelson Mandela, are imprisoned for life in 1964.
1976: Soweto riots: 575 killed, mostly young people.
1989-1993: Prime Minister Frederik de Klerk negotiates with the ANC. Nelson Man-
dela is freed in 1990; the last three apartheid laws are abolished in 1991.
1994: Nelson Mandela is elected president in the first multiracial elections, held in
April.
1995: The Truth and Reconciliation Commission (TRC) headed by Archbishop Des-
mond Tutu is set up to investigate human rights violations committed between 1960
and 1994 and grant reparation to victims. It has no legal powers except to amnesty
the authors of violations who so wish, on condition of “full disclosure of all re l e va n t
facts relating to acts associated with a political objective”.
1 9 9 8: The T RC ’s final re p o rt lists 21,000 victims, 2,400 of whom have testified in
public hearings. Of some 7,000 requests for amnesty, most are granted, but decisions
on several cases are still pending.
1 9 9 9: Thabo Mbeki (ANC) is elected president in June, succeeding Nelson Mandela. ■
new tendency for South A f ricans to be willing to
n e g o t i ate their way through social, i n t e l l e c t u a l ,r e l i-
gi o u s , political and cultural dive rs i t y. In sum, it will
come from the progr e s s i ve accumulation of ethical
and moral insights.
C e rt a i n l y, some objectives have been achieve d .
No South A f ri c a n ,p a rticularly white South A f ri c a n s ,
can ever claim ignorance of how apartheid disru p t e d
and destroyed the lives of millions of black people in
the name of the white electorat e .All South A f ri c a n s
can now claim to have a common base of know l e d g e
about where they have come from, p a rticularly in
the last 50 ye a rs , and this is an essential foundat i o n
for the emergence of a new national value system.
Public acknowledgment of South A f ri c a ’s history of
racism represents a form of reconciliat i o n .
Moving towards social justice
The TRC has not by any means been a smooth
process. Many whites, particularly among Afrika-
ners, felt that the TRC was a punitive witch-hunt,
targeting them as a community.This criticism did
not take into account the fact that the TRC also
addressed gross human rights violations perpetra-
ted by the liberation movements themselves. The
even-handedness of the TRC in this regard is very
clear in its report,and could itself be regarded as a
significant contribution to reconciliation.
There are people who are not happy with the
amnesty mechanism and strongly feel that justice has
been compromised (see next page). Fo rt u n at e l y, a
n e g o t i ated transition ensured there were functioning
institutions in place for citizens to exercise their ri g h t s.
R e c o n c i l i ation is not a single eve n t . It is a process.
The TRC was a mechanism to deal with enorm o u s
human tensions which could have exploded with
d e va s t ating consequences.It enabled South A f ri c a n s
to nav i g ate successfully through ve ry rough seas.T h e
question is whether after its second democratic elec-
tions South A f rica has the will and resourcefulness to
take full advantage of the foundation it has inheri t e d .
Continuing disparities in we a l t h ,h o u s i n g,e d u c at i o n ,
and health between blacks and whites indicate that the
process of reconciliation must move to a second stage:
the achievement of social justice. In this regard, t h e
d e fin i t i ve test of a new democratic society is underway.
But the disintegr ation of the South A f rican stat e
through racial conflict is unlikely in the foreseeable
f u t u r e .This outcome is a highly significant measure of
Archbishop Desmond Tutu, chairperson of South AfricaÕs Truth and Reconciliation Commission, at the first hearings 
of the T RC in Cape Town on April 30, 1996. Some 2,400 victims testified before the Commission over a thre e - year period.
And we forg e t
because we must
And not because we
w i l l .
Matthew Arnold,
English poet (182 2 - 1 8 8 8 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
The price of t r u t h
◗ Max du Pre e z
Amnesty applications have shed light on unsolved murders in South Africa, but for some
families knowing the truth is not enough
W
hy should victims of apartheid accept that the
South A f rican Truth and Reconciliation Com-
mission (TRC) gave amnesty to assassins and
mass killers of the former apartheid regime? This is
just one of the questions asked by critics of the T R C
process inside the country.At the heart of all cri t i c i s m
is the legal power gi ven to the commission to gr a n t
a m n e s t y,under certain conditions to people who com-
mitted politically motivated crimes between 1960 and
1 9 9 4 . Amnesty means a person can never be cri m i-
nally charged with that cri m e , nor can he be sued in
a civil court for damages resulting from that act.
More than 7,000 people applied for amnesty,
including two former cabinet ministers of Pri m e
Minister P. W. B o t h a ’s gove rnment and several of
his police generals. Most have been granted amnesty,
although several cases are still under considerat i o n .
Ve ry often, the families of the victims murdered
by former policemen and soldiers , and in a few cases
by members of the two liberation arm i e s ,h ave rejected
the entire notion of amnesty.The most prominent
include the widow and son of Black Consciousness
leader Steve Biko, who was beaten to death in a cell
by policemen, and the family of Gri f fiths Mxe n g e , a
black law yer whose throat was cut by three policemen
because he represented anti-apartheid activists.
They argue that the provision for amnesty robs
them of any sense of justice. In their view, m u r d e r e rs
should face a criminal trial and be jailed—failing to
do so cheapens the lives of their victims.Simply confes-
sing to these brutal acts should not be enough to bu y
the perp e t r at o rs complete freedom, they argue.T h e y
are also against the provision that no civil claims may
be made against the killers once they receive amnesty,
arguing that it cuts out the chance of obtaining com-
p e n s ation for the death of a breadwinner to their fa m i-
lies as well as for pain and sufferi n g .
The counter-argument, s t ated many times by
Commission chairp e rson Desmond Tu t u , is that it
would not be in the interest of national reconciliat i o n
to send hundreds of former policemen, s o l d i e rs and
e ven politicians to jail. N o n e t h e l e s s ,t wo of the wo rs t
k i l l e rs in the apartheid police force,Eugene de Kock
(whose request for amnesty is pending) and Ferdi Bar-
nard (who did not ask for it), were prosecuted and
gi ven life sentences.Wouter Basson, the head of the
f o rmer gove rn m e n t ’s Chemical and Biological Wa r-
fare progr a m m e , is currently on tri a l .There is no evi-
dence to suggest that these cases undermined the
r e c o n c i l i ation process in any way.
Another argument often put forward in favour of
amnesty is that much, if not most, of the inform at i o n
the TRC obtained about the evils committed by the
a p a rtheid gove rnments was disclosed to them through
the amnesty applications of perp e t r at o rs of gross human
rights violat i o n s. If it were not for these stat e m e n t s ,t h e
t ruth about a large number of unexplained events and
u n s o l ved murders would not have come out.And for
the nation as a whole, if there had to be a tradeoff, t ru t h
was considered more important than justice.
New heroes
The amnesty applications of Phila Ndwa n d we ’s
m u r d e r e rs is a case in point.The young mother of a
baby boy and a unit commander of the A f rican Nat i o-
nal Congress army, N d wa n d we was stationed with
her unit in neighbouring Swaziland when she crossed
the border one day, n e ver to be seen again. For many
ye a rs the ru m o u rs dogged her family that she could
possibly have been a collaborator of the apart h e i d
g ove rn m e n t .Then the story came out in the amnesty
a p p l i c ation of four policemen.They had lured her ove r
the border with a false message, and then kept her in a
d e s o l ate house.There they assaulted and tortured her
in an effort to get her to join the apartheid police or
tell them her unit’s secrets. According to the police-
m e n ’s stat e m e n t s , she told them she would prefer to
d i e .They shot her in the head and bu ried her.
Phila Ndwa n d we ’s remains were dug up and
r e bu ried at a huge public funeral, where her nine-
year-old son received a medal for exceptional bra-
very on behalf of his dead mother. Instead of Phila
N d wa n d we being remembered as an apartheid col-
laborator,South Africa gained a new hero. ■
What is true of
individuals is true of
nations. One cannot
f o rg i ve too much.
The weak can neve r
f o rg i ve. Fo rg i ve n e s s
is the attribute of the
s t ro n g .
Mahatma Ga n d h i ,
Indian philosopher and
politician (1869-1948)
A father and daughter mourn at the graveside of Matthew Goniwe, an anti-apartheid activist
who was murdered in 1985 on the orders of the South African government. The Truth and
Rehabilitation Commission honoured his memory.
◗ Journalist in Johannesburg
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
p r e s e rve the history of the repression in the collec-
tive memory.
The Commission’s report has neve rtheless had
a considerable impact.The truth began to come out,
opening up new opportunities for “justice as far as
possible”. Under the current president, Eduardo
Frei, the courts have handed out prison sentences
to the former head of the DINA, the dictat o rs h i p ’s
secret police,and to other military and police offi-
cers involved in the repression.1
But two big issues have been put on the back
bu rner—the crimes covered by the amnesty law
(committed between 1973 and 1978) and the res-
ponsibility of General Augusto Pinochet. M a ny
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 25
Me m o ry: making p e a c e with a violent pas t
Chile: 
doing a deal with m e m o ry
◗ Oscar Godoy Arc a y a
Chileans have made a pact to ease the transition to democra c y. But the collective memory 
has played a more crucial part in pro g ress tow a rds a rule of law
◗ Professor at the Institute 
of Political Sciences of the
Catholic University of Chile and
a member of the Academy of
Social, Political and Moral
Sciences of the Institute of
Chile
1 Manuel Contreras, the former head of the DINA, was
sentenced in Chile for the murder in Washington of
Orlando Letelier, Minister of Foreign Affairs in the Allende
government,because Chile’s amnesty law does not cover
crimes committed abroad. In July 1999, in a decision
described as “historic”, Chile’s Supreme Court confirmed
the indictment of high-ranking officers on the grounds that
when victims’ bodies could not be found, the crimes
involved were “permanent and not subject to limitation”
and therefore not covered by the amnesty law. Editor
T
he question of human rights violations by stat e
o f ficials during the military dictat o rship is not
a priority in the current political debate.Chi-
leans have been saying this since 1990 in political
s p e e c h e s , in the media and through public opinion
p o l l s.Yet at regular interva l s , this serious issue fla r e s
up in the national debate.When it does, political
figures feel obliged to make amends, but as a rule
they prefer to let time do its work. Is this passivity
or a laissez faire attitude that should be legally
condemned?
“Justice as far as possible,” was the line taken by
Pat ricio Ay lwin while he was president.The work of
the Truth and Reconciliation Commission (see box
page 27) formed part of this approach. Its aim wa s
to compile a list of victims of human rights violat i o n s
under the military regime and identify the guilty par-
t i e s. The idea was to establish the tru t h , awa r d
m at e rial and moral compensation to the victims, a n d
lay the foundations of national reconciliation.But
the Commission’s work has been limited by an
amnesty law passed under the military regime. In
other words, its role has been largely symbolic: to
An anti-Pinochet demonstration outside the Chilean embassy 
in Madrid in October 1998.
D i s re g a rd and
contempt for human
rights have re s u l t e d
in barbarous acts
which have outra g e d
the conscience of
m a n k i n d .
Preamble 
to the Universal Declaration 
of Human Rights (1948)
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
S
ome people have alleged that the crimes of the
Pinochet dictatorship in Chile should not be
punished because pouring salt into this open
wo u n d , establishing the truth and obtaining justice
would destabilize democracy and endanger so-
called social peace.
But all efforts to stifle memory have fa i l e d .T h e
arrest of Augusto Pinochet in London on October
16, 1998 revealed how fragile the Chilean demo-
c r atic system is and showed the true face of a
c o u n t ry which cannot face up to a period of its
h i s t o ry which continues to divide Chileans into
two irreconcilable camps.
The systematic cover-up of the dictatorship’s
c rimes began on the day of the military coup d’état
against President Salvador Allende in 1973. But
Chileans and foreigners wonder why a democratic
g ove rnment has not managed to repeal a law which
seems a disgrace and was passed in undemocratic
circumstances.
H ow is it that Pinochet has remained beyond the
reach of the law and that his political and criminal
responsibility has not been established? The answe rs
to these questions are connected to the special
nature of Chile’s transition to democracy, which
includes an unspoken agreement to keep the
amnesty law on the books and guarantee immunity
for Pinochet.The transition is the result of a pact,
whose effects have been strengthened by the exis-
tence of a right-wing electorate comprising up to 40
per cent of vo t e rs and an electoral system that pre-
vents a majority from dominating parliament.A gr e e-
ments have been made; there has been neither pas-
sivity nor laxity.
Reawakened memories
The society’s collective memory is stronger than
this, however.Whenever a debate arises about the
political heritage of the military regime or someone
tries to amend the constitution,memories are rea-
wakened of pri s o n e rs who va n i s h e d , e xe c u t i o n s
with or without trial and the torture inflicted on
thousands of Chileans. There is no collective
amnesia: the wickedness of the crimes has left an
indelible mark.
For nearly nine ye a rs , there was a tug-of-war bet-
ween collective memory and political determ i n at i o n
to forget. On the one hand, s e veral legal actions we r e
s t a rted against Pinochet and members of his regi m e .
On the other, one could point to a certain sluggi-
A n unwritten page of history
◗ Fabiola Letelier del Solar and Víctor Espinoza Cueva s
Only a few of those responsible for crimes under the dictatorship have so far been tried
◗ Respectively president and
executive secretary of Chile’s
Corporation for the Defence of
the People’s Rights (CODEPU)
from the start of the repression, human rights orga-
n i z ations and groups of victims’ families tried to fin d
out the tru t h . They all worked together to bu i l d
this collective memory of the past.After a while, t h e
action of a band of mothers who denounced the
c rimes committed against their loved ones became
the mainspring of the struggle to restore demo-
c r a cy.The main theme of the campaign was “ n e ve r
again”—only the establishment of a nat i o n w i d e
culture of respect for human ri g h t s , a complete
account of what went on and full rights to justice
could ensure that history would not repeat itself.
We were critical of the National Truth and
R e c o n c i l i ation Commission set up at the begi n-
ning of the transition process (see box).Why, we
a s k e d , did its brief only cover those who disap-
shness in the legal system, a veto by the arm e d
forces, and the feeling that drawn-out legal pro-
ceedings against Pinochet would not catch up with
him and that he would die a natural death before
coming to tri a l .This was the situation when he wa s
arrested in London.
Pinochet enjoys immunity because he has a
d i p l o m atic passport and is a senator for life, a n d
the Chilean gove rnment has accepted this. T h e
g ove rnment maintains that it cannot accept foreign
jurisdiction over him that it has neither recognized
by treaty nor through ratification of an internatio-
nal legal instrument.
I approve of this approach because states are
subject to international law even if it conflicts with
my ideals. I also approve of it because I think the
democratic transition is our business. I would like
to see,in my lifetime,Chilean courts put Pinochet
on trial for what he did and remove him from par-
l i a m e n t . I would like to see the armed forces quietly
accept and respect court decisions and see the pro-
Pinochet right accept the requirements of the rule
of law and representat i ve democracy. In sum, I
would like to see judicial sovereignty in Chile fully
deployed,as part of the rule of law in a strong and
established democracy.
P i n o c h e t ’s detention has moved the Chilean
justice system forward. Politicians have turned a
spotlight on the crimes of the dictat o rs h i p, a n d
public opinion is starting to accept that globaliza-
tion doesn’t only involve trade. This is a process
which is taking us towards a cosmopolitan society
equipped with supra-national bodies based on
freedom and the defence of human rights. ■
K n owing how to
f o rget is more a
matter of chance
than an art .
Baltasar Gra c i a n ,
Spanish moralist and essayist
( 1 6 0 1 - 1 6 5 8 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 27
Me m o ry: making p e a c e with a violent pas t
Ti m e l i n e
1970: A socialist, Salvador Allende, is elected president.
1 9 73: Allende is ove rt h rown in a military coup led by Gen Augusto Pinochet on 
September 11.
1 9 7 8: Gen Pinochet pushes through parliament a law (still in force) granting amnesty
for all crimes except non-political offences committed between September 1973 and
March 1978, the main period of repression.
1988: Gen Pinochet loses a referendum he has organized in a bid to stay in power
until 1997.
1 9 8 9: A Christian Democrat, Patricio Aylwin, is elected president in December in the
first democratic election for 16 years. Gen Pinochet remains commander in chief of
the army.
1 9 9 1: A Truth and Reconciliation Commission set up to investigate the re p ression bet-
ween 1973 and 1990 and headed by Sen Raul Rettig produces a figure of 3,197
people killed, including 850 whose bodies are missing.
1993: Eduardo Frei (Christian Democrat) is elected president.
1 9 9 4: The Truth and Reconciliation Commission awards compensation to 2,115
families of the victims.
1996: A Spanish judge, Baltasar Garzón, issues a request for Gen Pinochet’s extra-
dition to stand trial for genocide, tort u re and the disappearance of a number of people,
all of them Spanish citizens in Chile.
1998: Gen Pinochet, now a senator for life, is arrested at a London clinic where he
is having medical treatment.
1 9 9 9: On March 24, the British House of Lo rds refuses to grant Gen Pinochet immu-
nity but limits the extraditable offences to tort u re perpetrated after 1988, when
Britain ratified the international convention against torture. In May, the High Court
in London rejects Pinochet’s appeal. On October 8, magistrate Ronald Bartle rules that
he can be extradited to Spain. If the general loses an appeal against this decision,
the British home secretary will make the final decision on his extradition. ■
peared and leave aside those who were tortured,
forced to flee abroad, a r b i t r a rily arrested or sent into
internal exile?
Most of all, we objected to its decision not to
name those responsible for the cri m e s , which wo u l d
have at least been symbolic justice. And the truth
that the Commission established was only the ver-
sion presented by the victims, their families and
human rights organizat i o n s , since the main cul-
p ri t s , the armed forces, refused to have anything to
do with it.So it was only half the tru t h . A page of our
history is still unwritten.
International solidarity
Yet through the Commission’s bri e f, the gove rn-
ment recognized that the dictatorship had syste-
m atically violated human rights on a massive scale.
This organized remembrance of the recent past
was really an appeal for people to face the future bol-
stered by a determination that such crimes must
never happen again.
Later, fearing the clashes that digging up the
truth and dispensing justice would inevitably pro-
vo k e , the nine-year-old gove rnment coalition passed
measures that removed the issue from the public
arena.The Truth and Reconciliation Commission
and its successor,the Reparations and Reconcilia-
tion Commission, were supposed to have settled the
problem once and for all. But far from recognizing
A woman with photos of her father and other missing people 
takes part in a candlelight vigil organized in Chile in October 1999 by relatives of those who
disappeared during the dictatorship.
the ethical, p o l i t i c a l , judicial and social dimensions
of the problem, they reduced it to a search for the
remains of those who disappeared, with the result
that the nation’s ordeal was revived.
P i n o c h e t ’s arrest means the country cannot avo i d
facing the events whose memory, h owe ver painful it
m ay be, we have been fighting to keep alive .I n d e e d ,
over 40 complaints have been made against Pinochet
before a judge which have so far led to the arrest and
t rial of a dozen military offic e rs (see note page 25).
The determination of the complainants, along
with international solidarity, made possible an act
of justice none of us had imagined: the imprison-
ment of Pinochet in a gilded cage. As the former
head of stat e , he is the chief perp e t r ator of what we
regard as crimes against humanity committed under
his rule inside and outside the country.These cri m e s
should be tried by an international tribunal. Since
such a tri bunal is still not functioning, P i n o c h e t
ought to be tried in his own country.
But Chile has neither adequate institutions nor the
political will for that .So far there has been no real move
to repeal the 1978 amnesty law or end the system of
appointed senat o rs.All this means that Chile is a par-
tial and hesitant democracy,unable to guarantee a fa i r
t rial for Pinochet.A l s o,because he is a senator for life,
his parliamentary immunity would have to be lifted
before he could be tri e d . But since he is still a military
o f fic e r , an examining magi s t r ate could declare himself
incompetent to handle the case and might send it to
a military court , which obviously would not be inde-
pendent enough. So Pinochet should be tried in
S p a i n .This would be a big step towards ending impu-
n i t y, and an exe m p l a ry act against the treachery and
t y r a n ny of all dictat o rs h i p s.
Building a collective memory implies know-
ledge of the past and all its consequences. As long
as it is shrouded in the veil of pardon without jus-
tice, we cannot plan a future of peace in a society
reconciled with itself. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
◗ Sociologist specializing in
contemporary Russian society
and teacher at Paris IV
university
Russia: an unfinished j o b
◗ Alexis Bere l ow i t c h
Russians looked back in anger when p e re s t ro i k a re vealed the full scale of Stalinist massacre s
and re p ression. But current difficulties have largely halted this re a p p raisal of the past
The body of a dictator is buried and dug up
s e veral times in Georgian filmmaker Te n gi z
Abuladze’s 1986 movie Repentance. Stalin
had a similar fate: he was symbolically exhumed
d u ring the political “ t h aw ” of Nikita Khru s h c h e v ’s
r e i g n , hidden away during the Brezhnev ye a rs ,
d i s i n t e rred again during p e r e s t r o i k a and is today
more or less out of sight.
These ups and downs show how hard it is for
Russians to perform acts of remembering and
m o u rning as a prelude to accepting and coping
with what happened in the dark days of Stalinist
terror.
D u ring the thaw ye a rs ,b e t ween 1956 and 1964,
Soviet society was confronted with its past for the
first time when Khrushchev denounced Stalin’s
c ri m e s. But the denunciation only went part of the
way, and a thoroughgoing reappraisal of Stalinism
was not possible. From the mid-1960s on, all refe-
rences to Stalin were censored. D u ring the Brezhnev
years, the dictator was quietly rehabilitated as the
architect of the victory over Nazi Germany.
But while the Soviet establishment offic i a l l y
t ried to play down or make people forget about
S t a l i n i s m , the most radical wing of the liberal
i n t e l l i g e n t s i a , the dissidents, continued their scru-
t i ny of the Stalinist era. The high point of this
s t ruggle to remember came in 1974 with the
p u b l i c ation in the West of Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn’s
The Gulag A r c h i p e l a go.
In the grip of
a reading frenzy
When p e r e s t r o i k a a l l owed people to speak freely,
from 1985 on, the first thing the intelligentsia did
was to turn to the past and try to make sense of it.
In 1986 and 1987, h i s t o rical novels which had
been written decades earlier and had either been
unpublished in the Soviet Union or published only
in the West turned the spotlight back onto Stalinism.
Nearly 10 million copies were printed of the most
popular of these nove l s ,A n atoly Rybakov ’s C h i l d r e n
of the A r b at. All the key moments and events of the
Stalinist era were now dealt with—the 1930s,col-
l e c t i v i z at i o n , the Second World War and stat e - s p o n-
sored anti-semitism.
In 1988, Vassili Grossman’s gr e at novel L i fe
and Destiny, which had been published in the West
in 1980, appeared in Russia, followed in 1990 by
The Gulag A r c h i p e l a go.The circulation of the maga-
zine Novy Mir in which these works appeared rea-
ched two million.The whole country was gripped
with a reading frenzy.
When the Soviet people discovered the scale
of the disaster it came as a terrible shock. A sense of
shared responsibility spread throughout the country.
People wondered whether the whole society should
repent,and there was a call for a Nuremberg-type
trial of Stalinism. It was no longer just a matter of
contrasting an evil Stalin with good communists and
comrades of Lenin, as had been done during the
1987 rehabilitation of the victims of the Stalinist
show trials, but of asking what it was in Russian
society that had made Stalinism possible. E s s ays and
a rticles by historians took over from literat u r e .
Most authors belonging to the liberal intelligentsia
looked for the causes in Russian history — i n
serfdom, the absence of a civil society and demo-
c r atic practices, and the huge size of the state sector.
E s s ays and articles by historians took over where lite-
rature left off.
Waning interest
in the past
The duty of remembrance was performed by
groups which painstakingly sought out the names of
the victims, as the young historian Dimitri Yu r a s ov
did,or looked for mass graves.
This movement led to the founding in 1987-
1988 of a Moscow-based human rights associa-
tion called Memori a l , with member groups all ove r
the Soviet Union. It drew a map of the labour
camps,set up a museum and compiled lists of vic-
tims. In 1989, the Leningrad newspaper Vecherny
published day after day the names of people who had
been shot.
At first Memorial was a mass organizat i o n
which planned to put up a monument to the vic-
t i m s. But which victims? The victims of Stalinism
or eve ryone who had been persecuted by the Sov i e t
r e gime? From 1988 on, c riticism was levelled not
only at the Stalinist period but at the entire socia-
list regi m e , and this encouraged the adoption of the
second defin i t i o n .
But just as the monument project was being
discussed,public opinion began to lose interest in
the past. In 1996, the inauguration of a memorial
called The Mask of Sorrow in the Kolyma region,
where the most terrible labour camps had been,
passed largely unnoticed.
There seem to have been several reasons for
this public loss of interest. F i rst the economic
disaster and its social consequences are leading
Russians to gi ve pri o rity to the present.They are also
making people question the ve ry validity of the
d e m o c r atic project. M a ny Russians feel nostalgic for
Concern about the
f u t u re cannot be
re g a rded as
willingness to forg e t .
Fo rgetting should
n e ver be thought of
as a passport to
social peace.
Memory is part of
civil peace.
B ronislaw Gere m e k ,
Polish historian and politician
( 1 9 32-  )
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
the Soviet era and about a quarter of them hanker
after what they call the most “glorious” era, when
the USSR was feared and respected, d u ring Stalin’s
rule.
The sense of national humiliation Russians have
felt in the 1990s has weakened their desire to delve
into the darkest ye a rs. Opinion polls show more and
more people think there is too much talk about
Stalinist crimes. For some Russians,as the French
historian Maria Ferretti has shown, the desire to
forget this period of the past has sprung from a
rejection of the whole Soviet period as an unfortu-
n ate interlude in Russian history and from the glo-
ri fic ation of pre-1917 Russia. To d ay ’s Russia is
coming to be seen as the direct heir of T s a ri s t
R u s s i a , passing over the black hole of socialist ru l e .
So the Stalinist experience has now been erased.
The dictator remains the least popular figure in
Russian history—though those with favourable opi-
nions of him rose from eight per cent in 1990 to 15
per cent in 1997, while his disapproval rating fell
from 48 per cent to 36 per cent in the same peri o d .
The proportion of the population which listed the
mass repression of the 1930s among the main eve n t s
of the 20th century fell from 38 per cent in 1989 to
no more than 18 per cent in 1994.
This new situation has not stopped inve s t i g at i o n s
into Stalinism and its cri m e s , but it has gr e at l y
changed their nature.During perestroika, research
was a joint effort and a central part of daily life, bu t
n ow it is confined to professional scholars. M e m o-
rial has became mainly a research centre. H i s t o ri a n s
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 29
Me m o ry: making p e a c e with a violent pas t
Ti m e l i n e
1917: The October Revolution brings the Bolsheviks to power under Lenin’s leader-
ship.
1 9 1 8 - 1 9 2 2: Civil war and famine, confrontation between the Red and White armies,
political executions. Foundation of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR).
1924: Death of Lenin. Stalin becomes general secretary of the communist party.
1 9 3 0 - 1 9 3 1: The rich peasants (kulaks) are dispossessed of their land and massacre d .
At least two million dead.
1936-1937: Moscow show trials, purges, reign of terror. The number of prisoners in
the gulag rises from 500,000 in 1934 to 2.5 million in the early 1950s.
1953: Death of Stalin. Thousands of prisoners freed.
1 95 6: At the 20th Communist Pa rty Congress, Khruschev denounces St a l i n’s crimes.
The thaw begins.
1964: Khruschev is removed from power; end of thaw; rise of Brezhnev.
1 9 8 5: Mikhail Gorbachev launches p e re s t ro i k a ( restructuring) and g l a s n o s t ( p u b l i c
openness and accountability).
1 9 9 1: Boris Yeltsin is democratically elected president of the Russian Fe d e ration. T h e
USSR is officially dissolved in December. Proclamation of the Commonwealth of Inde-
pendent States. ■
working on the Soviet period are devoting most of
their efforts to publishing official archive s ,p r ov i d i n g
people with a less romantic and increasingly accu-
rate view of what went on.But the task of remem-
bering for society as a whole has again been inter-
rupted before Russians have been able, at last, to
reconcile themselves with their own history. ■
Files on thousands of prisoners of the Gulag are kept in the archives of Memorial, a Moscow-based association.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
◗ Rithy Panh’s films include
Site 2 (1989), Cambodia:
Between War and Peace (1991)
Rice People (1994) and One
Evening after the War (1997).
I
left Cambodia when I was 15 with a spiritual
wound I knew would never heal. I had survi-
ved the terrible ordeal of the Khmer Rouge
genocide, which killed a quarter of the country’s
population. I didn’t understand how such a mas-
sacre had been possible. Even now, I hardly do.
As soon as I reached the camp at Mairu t , in T h a i-
l a n d , I stopped fearing for my life, but I felt a pro-
found sadness, whereas I should have been happy. I
felt my whole life was already behind me, t h at it
belonged to those ye a rs of struggle for surv i va l .
I wanted to forget. Go somewhere else, where
I’d have no memory and no recollections, where
nobody would know what I’d been through. I’d
seen and heard my relatives suffer. Our family
had been deported from Phnom Penh to Chrey, a
village in the middle of nowhere. One of my sis-
ters was brought back to my parents, physically
and psychologically exhausted after bu i l d i n g
dikes and digging canals. Soon afterwards, my
father died. He was a peasant’s son who had
become a teacher and then a primary school ins-
pector. He decided to stop eating.He chose to die
as an act of rebellion, a last act of freedom.Then,
one after another, my mother, my sisters and my
nephews died of hunger or exhaustion.
SurvivorÕs guilt
I didn’t want to talk about any of that . I had
made it part of my s e l f, and it became almost the
m a i n s p ring of my surv i va l .When I was living as an
exile in France, there was a long period when I refu-
sed to speak my nat i ve language and rejected any
link with Cambodia. I had been uprooted and I felt
s o m e h ow incomplete, t o rn between forgetting and
r e m e m b e ri n g, b e t ween past and present, a lways ill
at ease. I lived with memories of my relat i ve s , w i t h
the anxiety—the cert a i n t y — t h at the same tragi c
s t o ry would repeat itself. It was bu rned into my
flesh foreve r , as if with a branding iron, t h at this is
w h at the world is like: a place where there’s a lot of
indifference and hy p o c risy and little compassion.
When you come out of a wa r ,yo u ’re not sure that
yo u ’ ve left violence behind yo u .You are locked in a
culture of surv i va l .And when yo u ’ ve surv i ved geno-
c i d e1, you always feel guilty about being a surv i vo r.
Cambodia: a w o u n d
that will not heal
◗ Rithy Pa n h
A Cambodian film-maker describes how he came to terms with horro r. His country will neve r
re c over its lost identity, he says, unless it puts the past on trial
When the Italian writer Primo Levi came back
from the Nazi death camps, he said that “you feel
others have died in your place, that we’re alive
because of a privilege we haven’t deserved,becau-
se of an injustice done to the dead. It isn’t wrong
to be alive, but we feel it is.”
Long afterwa r d s , I learned to speak again and
to accept what had happened to me.Then I redis-
c overed my memori e s , my ability to imagi n e , t o
l a u g h , to dream, to rebuild my life. In Cambodia,
they say people who’ve died a violent death can’t
be reincarn at e d , t h at the souls of dead people who
h ave n ’t had a religious funeral and bu rial wa n d e r
the earth foreve r , haunting the living. There are
bones all over the place in the country s i d e . Pe o p l e
find them whenever they start bu i l d i n g .
A machine to destroy memory
If you can’t grieve, the violence continues.The
Cambodian mother of a model family, well inte-
grated in France, cut off her child’s head just as
the Khmer Rouge killers had chopped off her
fat h e r ’s. Similar cases have occurred in
C a m b o d i a . At Preah Sihanouk Hospital in
Phnom Penh, the only department that provides
psychiatric treatment takes patients from all over
the country. Sometimes there are 250 of them
waiting in the corridor.You only have to see how
many are depressive and destitute to realize that
something must be done.There is a massive col-
lective wound.
The terrible thing about past wars and about
the Cambodian genocide is not only the millions
of dead, the widows, the orphans, the amputees
and the depressed, it’s also our shattered identity,
the ruins of our social cohesion.
The first political decisions of the Khmer
Rouge, after they won power on April 17, 1975,
were unutterably violent. They emptied towns
and hospitals, closed schools, abolished money,
deported people en masse to the countryside,
defrocked monks and looted old houses.2
“Absolutely everything belongs to Angkar [the
communist party],” they said. “If the party tells
you to do something you must do it! Anyone who
We live in a world
w h e re a man is more
likely to be tried if he
kills a single person
than if he kills
1 0 0 , 0 0 0 .
Kofi Annan,
Ghanaian diplomat, Se c re t a ry
G e n e ral of the UN (1938-  )
1. The author use this word in its broader sense; contrast
UN’s stricter definition, see page 20.
2. The Khmer Rouge divided the Cambodian people into
two categories: the “old”people living in rural areas and
the “new”people in the cities who were “tainted” by
culture and knowledge.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 31
Me m o ry: making p e a c e with a violent pas t
objects is an enemy, anyone who opposes is a
corpse.” People had to dress in black, change the
way they spoke, use certain words and exclude
others from their vocabulary. It was forbidden to
sing, dance, say prayers and even talk to other
people. My father, who had spent all his life
trying to improve Cambodia’s public education
system, was particularly worried about the deci-
sion to ban teaching.“The spade is your pen, the
rice-paddy is your paper,” was the message
Angkar drove home.
All social classes were affected to varying
degrees by mass deportations to the countryside,
forced labour, summary executions and famine.
Paradoxically, all these absurd sacrifices were
made in the name of restoring the glory of the
Angkor era.All the roots of our culture and iden-
tity, the basic social relationships and symbolic
links which attached Cambodians to their world
were methodically and deliberately attacked and
destroyed.
Most of the detention centres were set up in
pagodas, places of prayer and compassion, or in
s c h o o l s , places of know l e d g e . A n g k a r was a
machine for destroying identity and wiping out
memory.
Before they executed their victims, the killers
tortured them and made them write hundreds of
pages of false confessions dictated by Khmer
Rouge officials. After being forced to denounce
their families and friends, the prisoners were exe-
cuted. “By eliminating you,” Angkar said, “we
don’t lose anything. It’s better to wrongly arrest
somebody than to wrongly let somebody go.”
One of the executioners at Camp S-21, in
Tuol Sleng—Pol Po t ’s main torture centre—
today only expresses his “regrets”; he doesn’t feel
guilty. He destroyed non-persons, people the
Khmer Rouge had stripped of all humanity.
This genocide was “ s i l e n t ” . The Khmer
Rouge imposed a reign of terror, and most execu-
tions were carried out without witnesses and
without noise.The world let Cambodians die and
didn’t seem to care. Not many people denounced
the massacres.
When I arrived in France in 1979, I was ama-
zed to find that the Khmer Rouge still occupied
Cambodia’s seat at the United Nations. A few
years later, I took the absence of the word “geno-
cide” from the Paris peace accords as a refusal to
allow the survivors to remember, as an insult to
the victims’ dignity.
The best memory is
that which forg e t s
nothing but pard o n s
injuries. Wr i t e
kindness in marble
and write injuries in
d u s t .
Persian prove r b
Survivors should have the courage to confront their history as Òa debt owed to the dead and 
an obligation to their childrenÓ.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
Ti m e l i n e
1953: Cambodia, a French protectorate since 1863, gains independence, becoming
a constitutional monarchy under King Norodom Sihanouk.
1960: Emergence of the Khmer Rouge organization, led by Pol Pot.
1 9 70 : Coup d’état by Prime Minister Lon Nol and proclamation of a republic. Sihanouk
aligns with a faction of the Khmer Rouge. In the ensuing civil war he is supported by
China and North Viet Nam, while the United States and South Viet Nam back Lon Nol.
1975: The Khmer Rouge seize the capital, Phnom Penh, in April and impose a totali-
tarian regime. Over 1.7 million people, or a quarter of the population, are killed.
1978: Viet Nam invades Cambodia in December and a new civil war begins.
1982: Sihanouk forms a government to resist the invasion with two other factions,
including one from the Khmer Rouge, and then moves closer to the pro - Vi e t n a m e s e
Prime Minister, Hun Sen.
1989: Vietnamese troops withdraw.
1 9 9 1 : A ceasefire takes effect in July. The Paris Agreement, on October 23, re c o g n i ze s
the Supreme National Council headed by Sihanouk and places Cambodia under UN
control.
1993: The monarchy is restored under Sihanouk.
1 9 9 7 : The Khmer Rouge breaks up. Pol Pot dies in 1998. Seve ral former Khmer
Rouge leaders join the royal army.
1999: Prime Minister Hun Sen, who has agreed to put the main leaders of the
Khmer Rouge on trial, opposes plans for the future court to be composed mainly
of foreign judges, as the UN wishes. He also opposes setting up a “truth commis-
sion”. At least three major Khmer Rouge leaders are left at large. ■
Film director Rithy Panh in Cambodia in March 1999
during the shooting of a documentary film about the
installation of a trans-Cambodian optic fibre cable.
Human bones were discovered when trenches for the
cable were dug.
I went back to Cambodia in 1990 after 11 ye a rs
in exile. I wanted to find the surv i vo rs of my fa m i l y
and recover the remains of the dead and gi ve them
a proper bu ri a l , so their souls would stop wa n d e-
ring the earth and could be reincarn ated in the cy c l e
of life and deat h . I wanted at least to confirm they
had died,so I could start to mourn properly.
I went to Tuol Sleng camp, which has been tur-
ned into a “genocide museum”. I wanted to try to
find a photo of my uncle among the hundreds of
pictures of the dead pinned on the wa l l s. But I
couldn’t bring myself to go in.I went back in 1991
to film the few surv i vo rs of the camp (only seven out
of some 15,000 people who passed through it). I
wanted to understand the banalization of evil and
the dehumanizing machinery of the Khmer Rouge.
But we ’re afraid of this recent past. C a m b o d i a n s
who dare to talk about it are divided. Some think we
should forget and look to the future, t h at there’s no
point in inflicting another ordeal on ours e l ves by try i n g
to bring back memories and pick over old wo u n d s.
They fear that if trials are held they will revive seri o u s
political quarrels which might set off another civil wa r.
Or else they generalize about Cambodians and say
most of them are “ fat a l i s t i c ” and accept a history of
war and genocide as their “ k a rm a ” .
This approach was dismissed by a 30-year-old
peasant called Torng, who was typical of many
people I spoke to while I was filming. “The
Khmer Rouge didn’t just kill people,” he said.
“They turned our generation into ignoramuses,
animals, idiots, who don’t know where they’re
going.We didn’t study. All we know is how to use
our physical strength. So we can only get jobs as
peasants or labourers. The Khmer Rouge should
be put on trial. If they aren’t, people like me will
be tempted to take revenge.”
I believe ,and so do others ,t h at we should face up
to our history, so that our relat i ves and friends didn’t
die in va i n .M o u rning wo n ’t be possible unless moral
and political responsibility for the Cambodian geno-
cide is established.A trial of the Khmer Rouge, b e f o-
re the Cambodian people, is absolutely essential.We
h ave to gi ve meaning to basic ideas of law and justi-
ce in this country. In a democratic society, you can’t
kill without being punished.
We must gi ve our memory a fair and dignifie d
t rial in order to understand the past. I’m not bothe-
red about the sentences that would be handed dow n .
Only the truth can free us—the whole tru t h ,h owe-
ver horri fic.The other point of such a tri a l , which is
just as import a n t , would be to restore our identity.
The Khmer Rouge have plunged generations of Cam-
bodians into a vicious circle of cultural loss.
Not many Cambodians tell their children about
the genocide, which is a fuzzy corner of their
memory. But we can’t build our future by forget-
t i n g .The surv i vo rs must tell their stories and ensure
t h at the memory of what happened is handed dow n
from the past to the present.We owe a debt to the
dead and we have an obligation to our children.
We shan’t be able to get rid of this 30-year
culture of violence, cast out the monster that is
fear and put behind us the collective guilt we feel
as survivors unless we manage to understand our
history. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 33
Me m o ry: making p e a c e with a violent pas t
Rw a n d aÕs collective a m n e s i a
◗ Benjamin Sehene
Christianity tried to destroy the collective memory of Rwandans. 
After independence, ethnicity became the yardstick of identity and the Tutsis we re
d e m o n i zed. Then came the horrors of genocide.
I
n Kigali, they are known as b a f u ye bahaga ze— t h e
living dead.They are the hundreds of thousands
of surv i vo rs of genocide who have psychologi c a l
p r o b l e m s. In September 1994, I met one of them—
a little girl called Élise, the only member of her
family who had survived. She was just under five
years old,the same age as the civil war in Rwanda,
which went on from 1990 to 1994.
Élise suffered from loss of memory and had a ve ry
l ow attention span. She could never remember my
first name. She had no recollection of anything that
had happened more than 20 minutes before—it wa s
as if she was trying to protect hers e l f. One evening I
found a way of getting her to remember my name.
She wore ove rsized pyjamas and I said,“Think of the
word ‘ p y j a m a ’e ve ry time you see me—pyjama-Ben-
j a m i n .”W h e n e ver she saw me after that , she wo u l d
happily shout:“ H e y, wa i t ,i t ’s pyjama-Benjamin!”
Like that little girl clinging to an image,Rwan-
dans should perhaps look for a common symbol
which could unite them around their lost memory.
For centuri e s ,R wandan civilization rested on a
pyramidal power structure which was rooted in
my t h s. It shaped the economy and conditioned
social relations. It built (and still builds) a tyranny
based on hierarchy, but a hierarchy imbued with a
sense of restraint.In an atmosphere of self-censor-
ship and silence, things are left unsaid—betwe e n
parents and children, husbands and wive s , s h e bu j a s
(bosses) and their b a ga ra g u ( s e rvants) and betwe e n
Tutsis, with their sense of superiority, and Hutus,
who feel inferior.
Severing links with the past
But the establishment of Chri s t i a n i t y, w h i c h
began with the arri val of missionaries in 1900, d e s-
t r oyed Rwa n d a ’s collective memory. In 1931, t h e
Church deposed Musinga, the Tu t s i s ’ last divine-ri g h t
m o n a r c h , when he refused to be conve rt e d .C o nve r-
sion to Christianity would have undermined his legi-
t i m a cy and destroyed the meaning of the magical and
r e l i gious functions of the monarchy, the pillar of
R wandan society.All the traditions which made up the
c o u n t ry ’s social and spiritual fa b ric were dubbed
pagan rites and banned, despite the fact that they fos-
tered social cohesion by bri n ging together the three
ethnic gr o u p s — H u t u s ,Tutsis and Twa s.
The abolition of the A b i ru s, the royal committee
of wise men that was the official guardian of the
s o c i e t y ’s collective memory and its esoteric ri t e s ,
marked the end of the only high-level institution
that acted as a counterweight because it was made
up mostly of Hutus. A proverb in the Kinya r wa n d a
language was coined to describe this break with the
esoteric past:Kerezia ya kuyeho kizira (the Church
has forbidden the forbidden).
After independence in 1962, the new republic of
R wanda tried to ove rt u rn the traditional pyramid-
shaped power stru c t u r e ,d e s t r oyed even more of the
traditional sense of national identity and wiped out
the nat i o n ’s collective memory.The republic defin e d
its identity by abolishing the old order,which it regar-
ded as being too strongly marked by centuries of Tu t s i
m o n a r c h s , and by basing its legi t i m a cy on the majo-
rity ethnic gr o u p, the Hutus.
E ve rything with a Tutsi connotation was ban-
n e d .Thousands of words rooted in Rwa n d a ’s his-
tory and social organization were struck out of the
l a n g u a g e .The ethnicization of the stat e ,s u p p o s e d l y
to create a “social balance”, led to a quota system
which limited the proportion of Tutsis in higher edu-
cation and the civil service to nine per cent.It was
based solely on numbers. Pe o p l e ’s ethnic affil i at i o n
could be checked from their identity documents.
The new ru l e rs said they were redressing the social
balance after centuries of feudal domination.
In the vacuum left by the collapse of the tra-
ditional collective memory, ethnicity became the
only point of reference.This eventually led to the
demonization of the Tutsis in order to justify their
exclusion from society. The Tutsis were dehuma-
nized and dubbed inyenzi (cockroaches), just as
the Nazis had called German Jews “vermin”.
Many terms of abuse were used to indicate they
were unwanted parasites. It is easier to crush a
cockroach underfoot than to kill a person.
The “social revolution”which gave birth to the
new Rwandan republic began in 1959 with a
bloody revolt by the Hutus, involving the terrible
massacre of 20,000 Tutsis and the flight of thou-
sands of others into Burundi and Uganda.This irr e-
parable act was the first step towards the descent
into amnesia.But a past that is forgotten is bound
to repeat itself because forgetting invo l ves a refusal
to admit wrongdoing. In Rwanda, amnesia led to
◗ Rwandan writer, author of
Le piège ethnique (Dagorno
publishers, Paris, 1999)
The country lived for 35 years in a
state of growing amnesia,
dominated by the law of silence,
of the unspoken, of memories
c o l l e c t i vely re p re s s e dBringing the truth to
light is already a
s t a rt, as a victory for
justice and a form of
relief for the victims.
Ro b e rt Badinter,
French lawyer and politician
( 1 9 28-  )
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
Ti m e l i n e
1 959 : Hutus carry out a “social re volution”, killing members of Rwanda’s Tutsi mino-
rity and overthrowing the Tutsi monarchy. Many Tutsis flee the country. Formerly
German colonies, Rwanda and Burundi have been administered by Belgium since 1924.
1 9 6 2 : Rwanda gains independence. Massacres of Tutsis increase and an ethnic
Hutu regime is gradually established in Kigali.
1 9 9 0 : The Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF), a Tutsi-dominated organization, launches
an offensive against the regime of General Juvenal Habyarimana, in power since 1973.
In October, intervention by Zaire, Belgium and France. French troops remain in the
country.
1993: An accord signed in August at Arusha (Tanzania) provides for power-sharing
with the RPF. It is stalled by President Habyarimana and his political allies. The UN
sends in an international peace-keeping force, UNAMIR.
1 9 9 4 : President Habyarimana is assassinated, setting off a wave of killings aimed at
Tutsis and moderate Hutus. UNAMIR withdraws. T h ree months later, the Fre n c h
establish a “p rotection zo n e” in the southwest. The RPF forms a government of
national union. In November, the UN creates an International Criminal Tribunal for
Rwanda, which sits at Arusha.
According to the Red Cross, the victims of genocide number more than a million
dead, mostly Tutsis, and over two million refugees.
1999: The RPF government extends its term of office by four years, promising elec-
tions and a new constitution. ■
s u c c e s s i ve pogroms against the Tutsis which began
in the 1960s and ended in the genocide.The coun-
try lived for 35 years in a state of growing amnesia,
d o m i n ated by the law of silence, of the unspoken, o f
m e m o ries collectively repressed. Silence inevitably
gave rise to impunity and impunity made amnesia
acceptable.
I had a hard job interviewing Tutsi survivors in
1994 because the genocide divided Rwandans into
two camps—Hutus and Tutsis,the perpetrators of
genocide and the rest. In Rwanda today, you are
forced to be on one side or the other; there is no
h a l f way house. Just after the genocide, the Tu t s i s
who returned were suspicious of Tutsis who had
e s c a p e d , presuming they had collaborated with the
enemy to save their skins.
If you were a Hutu, you were automatically guilty
of genocide, just as the Tutsis were from 1959 to 1994
considered guilty just because they happened to be
Tu t s i . The genocide was a crime committed bet-
ween neighbours ;k i l l e rs and surv i vo rs of the at r o c i-
ties still live side by side today.The exterm i n ation of
a million people in 100 days with crude weapons like
m a c h e t e s ,c l u b s ,a xes and hoes,could not have taken
place without the part i c i p ation of a massive number
of people.A third of all Hutus are thought to have par-
t i c i p ated in one way or another.
Fear of reprisals
About 135,000 people suspected of invo l ve m e n t
in genocide are languishing in ove r c r owded jails, a n d
the legal system, which was destroyed in the pro-
v i n c e s , is finding it hard to get the trials underway.T h e
I n t e rn ational Criminal Tri bunal for Rwanda (the
A rusha Tri bu n a l ) ,which has scant resources, is not get-
ting ve ry far either.All this is keeping Rwandans from
the task of remembering their past, especially since
s t at e - e n d o rsed ethnic attitudes still condition the
Hutu killers to think they killed their historic neigh-
b o u rs to ensure the surv i val of their own ethnic gr o u p.
To d ay, the guilty flatly deny there was any genocide.
So in one of A f ri c a ’s most densely populat e d
c o u n t ri e s , the surv i vo rs see their torm e n t o rs return i n g
to live peacefully on the hillsides because there is not
enough evidence to bring charges against them. In the
first months after the genocide witnesses spoke freely,
but they have become tight-lipped since a number of
s u rv i vo rs have been murdered by unknown killers.
“ W h at ’s the use of giving evidence?” one victim
asked me. “ T h e y ’re not being punished any way.”
All Rwandans live in an atmosphere of ethnic mis-
t ru s t . Fear of reprisals is still ri f e .
The new Rwandan authorities may want to curb
individual score-settling and encourage nat i o n a l
r e c o n c i l i at i o n ,but the ragtag soldiers who carried out
the 1994 massacres are still lurking in the forests of
n e i g h b o u ring Congo and have not gi ven up their
plans to exterm i n ate the Tu t s i s.As long as the threat
of a new genocide hangs over Rwa n d a , the present
r e gi m e ’s pri o rity will be to defend national frontiers ,
as shown by the on-going war in Congo.
The present is still barring the way to memory.
■
A Rwandan boy in a Catholic church which is now a memorial to the genocide. 
In 1994, thousands of Tutsis were massacred in the churchÕs grounds.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 35
Le sida dferle: a l e rte z l es jeunes !Me m o ry: making p  a c e with a violent pa t
Ti m e l i n e
1 9 9 1: Slovenia and Croatia, two of the six republics of the Yugoslav federa t i o n ,
declare their independence.
1992: In Bosnia and Herzegovina, the Croat and Muslim communities press for the
independence of their republic. They are opposed by Bosnian Serbs who lay siege to
Sarajevo and seize 70% of the country. Massive “ethnic cleansing” begins, mostly
conducted by Bosnian Serb forces.
1 9 9 3 - 1 9 9 4: After the rejection of a peace plan by the Bosnian Serbs, the UN declare s
six “safe areas”, but ground hostilities persist. Formerly allies, Croats and Muslims
clash before signing an accord in March 1994. The UN Security Council creates an
International War Crimes Tribunal for former Yugoslavia based at The Hague (Nether-
lands). NATO goes into action against the Serbs.
1995: In July, Bosnian Serbs take over Srebrenica and Zepa “safe areas”. In August,
NATO bombs their positions around Sara j e vo. The Dayton (USA) peace agreement in
November ends hostilities. The republic is divided into two associated entities, the
Fe d e ration of Bosnia and Herze g ovina (51% of the land area, including Sara j e vo )
and the Serb Republic. A NATO force monitors application.
In this conflict some 200,000 people were killed and almost 200,000 were dis-
placed. Around 600,000 refugees have returned to their homes. ■
duct of the wa r. R at h e r , they were a tool to achieve its
p ri m a ry aim:ethnic separatism or domination of one
ethnic group over another. By the wa r ’s end in early
1 9 9 6 , all three sides had retreated into ethnically pure
a r e a s , controlled by their respective arm i e s.
To d ay, the Croat and Serb politicians insist on
remaining separat e . In fa c t , it is those ve ry groups res-
ponsible for the wo rst crimes who insist most ve h e-
mently on ethnic separat i o n .The lack of consensus
on a multiethnic society plays into the hands of Mus-
lim extremists, who also practice a more subtle policy
of ethnic exclusion.All three groups have formed their
own school curri c u l a , which reinforce ethnic hat r e d ,
blame the other gr o u p s , and glorify their own my t h o-
l o g y. Each has begun religious instruction in the
s c h o o l s , which often takes the most pri m i t i ve form of
ethnic indoctri n at i o n . All this only serves to cement
the wa rtime ethnic cleansing.
The sad truth is that four ye a rs after Dayton (see
b ox ) , neither side is any closer to reconciliation than
in late 1995. M a ny Bosnians of all nationalities will
s t ate openly that they can stop hat i n g, but that they
will neither forgi ve nor forget what happened duri n g
the wa r.And many add that they wish to be left alone
with their own ethnic gr o u p. After what the other
groups did to them, they no longer wish to live with
them any way. In a political climate that works against
the emergence of any reliable non-nationalist refe-
rence point,m e m b e rs of all communities still fear firs t
and foremost for the surv i val of their ethnic identity
and place group interests above all else.
R ather than work toward calming nationalist pas-
sions and anger, local politicians use these fears to fur-
ther their own political agendas.This is seen part i c u-
larly in the cases of the Serb and Croat populat i o n s ,
both of whom look toward a mother country outside
the borders of Bosnia and Herzegov i n a , and dream of
e ventually seceding and uniting their region with it.
From Belgrade and Zagr e b ,politicians continue to fa n
the flames of nationalist desire.The continued insis-
tence of nationalist parties in Bosnia and Herzegov i n a ,
urged on by nationalists outside,on creating ethni-cally
pure terri t o ries stands as the gr e atest obstacle to recon-
c i l i at i o n . Until the outside forces live up to their obli-
g ations under Dayton and stop pushing for “ gr e at e r ”
n ational progr a m m e s , little progress will be made in
the reconciliation of the country ’s pre-war ethnically
d i ve rse populat i o n .And until that time,its citizens will
l i ve in an environment of fear of the other ethnic gr o u p s.
I
n November 1995,Bosnia and Herzegovina signed
the Dayton Peace A c c o r d s , a document designed
to create a new unified state comprised of two multi-
ethnic entities. It would have a functioning central
g ove rn m e n t ,hold democratic elections and adhere to
i n t e rn ational human rights standards.Displaced per-
sons were to be allowed to return to their homes and
indicted war criminals were to be arrested and turn e d
over to the Intern ational Tri bunal of The Hague.
To d ay ’s reality is dramatically different.The coun-
t ry consists of three de facto mono-ethnic entities, t h r e e
s e p a r ate arm i e s , three separate police forces, and a
n ational gove rnment that exists mostly on paper.M o s t
indicted war criminals remain at large.N ationalist poli-
tical part i e s , including many of the ethnic cleansers
who were responsible for the war in the first place,
remain securely in powe r. N ationalist extremists—
often backed by the ruling political parties—still bomb
and torch the homes of returning refugees in cert a i n
a r e a s.
C o n t r a ry to the pronouncements of local nat i o n a-
list politicians or intern ational officials wishing to avo i d
taking responsibility, the Serbs, C r o ats and Muslims
l i ved together relat i vely peacefully in Bosnia and Her-
z e g ovina for hundreds of ye a rs.All three groups res-
pected each others ’r e l i gious customs and holidays and
i n t e rm a rriage was common. But something changed
when all sides committed gri e vous atrocities duri n g
the wa r.These crimes were not an accidental by-pro-
Bosnia and Herze g ov i n a :
an i m p o s s i b l e re c o n c i l i a t i o n ?
◗ James Lyo n
A once ethnically diverse population lives in a climate of fear and distrust
fuelled by nationalists
◗ Director of the International
Crisis Group (ICG) project in
Bosnia and Herzegovina. This
private, multinational
organization, which aims to
strengthen the capacity of the
international community to
understand and respond to
crises, produces analytical
reports targeted at key
decision-makers.
(http://www.crisisweb.org)
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
Can we p re vent c r i m e s
against humanity?
Canadian judge Louise Arbour, former chief prosecutor with the
International Criminal Tribunals (ICT) for ex- Yugoslavia and Rwanda, 
b e l i e ves international law is making great strides in violence pre ve n t i o n
How has setting up ICTs helped the groups of
people directly concerned to turn the page on
atrocities they have experienced?
These tri bunals have been a spectacular innovat i o n .
For the first time, the intern ational community has
shown its concern not only with the short term—
stopping armed confli c t — but also with the long
term. It has noted that in the Balkans and Africa’s
Great Lakes region there was very little hope of
achieving lasting peace based on reconciliation and
social reconstruction unless the truth about past
events was established.The recording by interna-
tional inve s t i g at o rs of irrefutable evidence of cri m e s
prevents history from being falsified and the past
from being distorted.
When the truth is told, the need to dispense jus-
tice becomes obvious. I t ’s ve ry important to pin cri-
minal responsibility for any crimes that have been
committed not only on those who actually committed
them but also on political and military leaders. In so
d o i n g, the law at least recognizes that the victims
h ave a legal status and to some extent restores their
d i g n i t y. It also stops them from setting themselves on
a course for reve n g e , an agenda which can be handed
d own from generation to generat i o n .
Do you feel the ICTfor the former Yugoslavia
has helped victims to come to terms with the
burden of memory, a process which is crucial to
reconciliation? In Bosnia, thereÕs a kind of
ÒapartheidÓ between communities.
The ICT has not yet contributed to reconciliation
in Bosnia because it has not been given the neces-
sary resources. Justice cannot be fully done part-
ly because of the refusal of some governments to
gather evidence and arrest people who’ve already
been indicted.
The existence of an ICTfor the former
Yugoslavia doesnÕt seem to have prevented the
events in Kosovo.
The ICT did not have an immediate deterr e n t
effect because the UN Security Council didn’t use
its resources to oblige Serbia (the Federal Republic
of Yugoslavia) to carry out the arrest warrants the
ICT had issued.This encouraged the criminals to
feel that in practical terms they were going to enjoy
impunity and immunity. Throughout the Kosovo
conflict, from January to June 1999, I repeatedly
urged the intern ational forces there to arrest people
under indictment. I think this was the right deter-
rent message to send to the parties in Kosovo.
It’s clear that those who committed crimes in
K o s ovo were more aware of the risk of being
indicted and that this influenced their methods.
The common gr aves in Kosovo dug up by ICT
investigators have provided a lot of evidence, cer-
tainly enough to make the authors of these crimes
realize that the law can always find such evidence,
whatever lengths the criminals may go to in order
to cover up their crimes.
How has the ICT helped to promote reconcilia-
tion in Rwanda, where people are afraid of the
massacres starting again?
M i l i t a ry leaders , people accused of ve ry seri o u s
responsibilities for the genocide, m i n i s t e rs and eve n
the former prime minister (who has confessed his
guilt) are awaiting trial in prison in A ru s h a , in Ta n-
zania.They are no longer in a position to fan the
flames of tension, so the risk of violence has been to
some extent reduced. In Rwanda,even more than
in Bosnia, the culture of impunity has existed for
d e c a d e s.Violence goes in cy c l e s , but responsibility
for it has not been proven.The ICT represents a
change of direction in this respect but it wo n ’t have
an immediate impact.
What can we expect from the proposed
International Criminal Court (ICC), which will
be the first permanent institution of its kind?
Setting up the ICC is a huge and irreversible step
for the world.When it’s up and running it will be
able to respond fairly quickly to events and to indict
suspected criminals before they can commit furt h e r
m a s s a c r e s. ICTs were set up after crimes were com-
mitted in Bosnia, C r o atia and Rwa n d a . But in
K o s ovo, indictments were made at the highest leve l
at the beginning of June 1999 for crimes com-
mitted between January and May. Such speed was
possible because the ICT and its infrastru c t u r e
were already in place.
So an ICC, if it has the necessary muscle, will be
able to act and intervene in real time,which is an enor-
mous step forwa r d . If there’s the political will to arr e s t
people who’ve been indicted, e f f e c t i ve prevention of
c rimes against humanity can be env i s a g e d . ■
Interview by Martine Jacot, 
UNESCO Courier journalist
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
P OL ICE AG A INST RACISM
◗ Asbel López
Training schemes in several European countries are getting to grips with the stereotyping and
prejudice that all too often influence police behaviour
■
In a vast salon in Monceau Castle
( B e l gi u m ) , 13 policemen from
Charleroi,a town in the centre of the
country, have been divided into teams
and are absorbed in a boisterous card
game.The officers, unarmed and wearing
civilian clothes, are all men in their for-
ties. Today, in early October, they are
taking part in the fourth session of a
workshop against racism and xenophobia
run by the Centre for Equal Opportunity
and the Fight Against Racism, a Brussels-
based public institution founded in 1993.
Laughter erupts from the policemen
and the Centre’s two instructors when the
w i n n e rs of each game go on to the next
round of the contest.This time they will be
playing a game according to rules none of
them will know.
A game with unknown rules
Jean,who has spent half his 42 years in
the police force, s ays this is what happens to
i m m i grants when “they arri ve in a country
without knowing the rules and when the
rules they have back home are no use
because they don’t work in the new society.”
For example,he says, rules for women
in Islamic countries are ve ry different from
those in the We s t .L ater on, d u ring a review
of the session, Jean says he has never had the
chance to talk about such things or discuss
the relationship he has with immigrants in
the course of his work.
The workshop is one of 11 projects that
nine European countries are carrying out
under an international programme called
NGOs and Police Against Prejudice
(NAPAP), set up by the European Com-
mission in 1997 to fight racism and xeno-
phobia through workshops for members of
the police.
Each country has its own pri o rities and
m e t h o d s. As part of the British project
m e m b e rs of minority ethnic groups are
invited to take part in the training courses.
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
The Catalans hold day courses for their
police run by local immigrant gr o u p s.
France stresses the social integr ation of
i m m i gr a n t s. In Germ a ny emphasis is laid on
making police more aware of the problems
that arise in a multicultural society.
In recent years racism and xenophobia
h ave increased in many European coun-
t ri e s , especially because of economic cri s i s ,
u n e m p l oy m e n t , a rise in the immigr a n t
population and anti-foreigner propaganda
by extreme right-wing parties who are get-
ting more and more vo t e s1. In this situat i o n ,
police forces are in a particularly exposed
position.
The Centre, which records and pur-
sues cases of racist behaviour, says that in
Belgium more complaints about discrimi-
n ation based on the ori gin of an individual
are laid against the police than against any
other gr o u p2.The situation is also troubling
in other European countries. In Britain, a
report by a former High Court judge, Sir
William Macphers o n , said in early 1999
t h at there was “institutionalized racism” i n
L o n d o n ’s Metropolitan police force. I n
G e rm a ny, an official survey showed that
police violence against foreigners was “ n o t
just a matter of isolated cases”. Amnesty
I n t e rn at i o n a l ’s 1999 report detailed abu s e s
by the police in France, S p a i n , Greece and
Switzerland against immigrants and mem-
bers of ethnic minorities.
In a democratic system, such things
should not happen and the police should
respect the principle of equal rights for all
citizens. To ensure such respect, the first
thing to be done is to see that stereotyping
and prejudice do not affect the professional
b e h aviour of the police. This is not easy
because police opinions and attitudes are
developed at first hand in the front line of
social confli c t , and are usually the result of
an accumulation of personal experiences,
frustrations and misunderstandings.
The workshops run by the Belgi a n
centre are special because they feature gr o u p
work drawing on personal experience and
incidents the policemen agree to talk about.
Belgian police inspector Nestor Van Villinghen with a young immigrant. This photo and those on the
following pages show scenes from a video used in Belgian police training courses.
1.The recent electoral successes of the extreme
right in Austria and Switzerland illustrate this
process.
2. Égaux et reconnus, bilan 1993-1998 et perspectives
de la politique des immigrés et de la lutte contre le
racisme, Centre pour l’égalité des chances et la
lutte contre le racisme, page 16,Brussels, 1999.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Just speaking freely and openly about these
issues is already a big step, she say s ,b e c a u s e
“putting things into words and talking about
them allows you to be more objective about
t h e m , to realize their seriousness and impor-
tance and to start thinking about them.”
This was not happening when she
s t a rted the Centre’s workshops six ye a rs
ago. At that time, training focused on the
immigrant, not the police.The aim was to
throw light on the culture of immigrants’
countries of origin, how they had come to
B e l gi u m ,p o p u l ation statistics and the signi-
ficance of religious festivals like Ramadan or
practices like we a ring the chador, the shaw l
or veil worn by Muslim women.
But the Centre’s officials soon noticed
t h at this kind of inform ation session not
only failed to make the police aware of cul-
tural diversity but was even counter-pro-
d u c t i ve .The policemen got the impression
t h at by explaining how immigrants live d ,t h e
i n s t ru c t o rs were trying to justify behav i o u r
that to them was unacceptable.They felt
they were being made fun of and this gene-
r ated gr e at hostility towards the cours e
organizers.
Their comments were bru t a l . “The ins-
38 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
E T H I C S
The starting point of the six-day course is
not a lecture on tolerance or study of the
U n i ve rsal Declaration of Human Rights, bu t
c o n t ri butions from the policemen duri n g
activities including card games, r o l e -
p l ay i n g, and looking at photos and fil m
e x t r a c t s.
M a risa Fe l l a , an instructor at the
C e n t r e , s ays these “apparently simple”
e xercises encourage serious reflection by the
policemen about their professional beha-
v i o u r. She remembers one occasion when
solving a puzzle opened up the subject of
c o m m u n i c ation and aggressivity and eve n-
tually turned into a debate about police
b ru t a l i t y.“They discussed their own violent
b e h aviour as policemen, when and why
they had been violent or not violent, a n d
h ow they dealt with violence by offic e rs
under their orders.” A “ f o rum for talking
and thinking” was opened and allowe d
them to distance themselves from their
j o b s , something which can be hard to do
when you are in the thick of things.
A forum for talking and thinking
Bit by bit,as confidence is built up, the
participants stop using official jargon and
begin to recognize nuances. For example,
when one policeman said he could not
accept the position of women in Islam, t h i s
was already a step forwa r d , because he wa s
b e ginning to distinguish between whole-
sale rejection of Muslims and his disap-
proval of one aspect of their culture.
Fella says the most heartening aspect of
her work is to see that “behind the uni-
f o rms there are human beings who ask
t h e m s e l ves questions about their profes-
sion and about how they do their jobs.”
t ru c t o rs think we ’re ignorant and therefore
r a c i s t . . . .They gi ve us nice little talks about
i m m i gr a n t s , as if they’re all nice and
f ri e n d l y, but they’ve never patrolled the
streets like we have.”
These days, such resistance has disap-
peared or at least has subsided.The door to
change has opened. But problems still exist.
The police say they do not know exactly
h ow to put into practice what they have
l e a rned in the workshops about confli c t
management, non-verbal communication
and handling aggression when they are back
doing their job, which nearly always invo l ve s
speed, stress and confusion.
Another big problem is the progr a m m e ’s
lack of resources.The Centre has just five
instructors, three of them full-time. Only
about 300 of Belgium’s 36,200 police and
gendarmes attended workshops like these
between 1994 and 1998. A medium-term
proposal to overcome this is to have the
current instructors train new ones.
Another weak point is that it’s senior
officers who ask for courses to be held for
their men, who are not necessarily stat i o n e d
in places where the incidence of racial dis-
c ri m i n ation is high.W h at ’s more, the entire
staff of a police station rarely attends the
course, and this causes friction when they
go back to work.
But despite everything, those who take
p a rt agree that the process of exchange and
discussion between instru c t o rs and police is
encouraging.
Long-term effects
One instructor tells a group that five
vo l u n t e e rs are needed for a role-play i n g
game in which three policemen will play the
part of young immigrants and two others
will be the police.The first volunteers are
those who want to play the immigrants.
When the two policemen pass the gr o u p
of “ i m m i gr a n t s ” , the policeman playing the
p a rt of Fa b i o, an 18-year-old Belgian citizen
of Mediterranean ori gi n , calls them “p o u l e t s”
(chickens) a French slang word meaning
“ c o p s ” . The two policemen immediat e l y
t u rn round to arrest the yo u t h s , while their
f riends laugh at a nickname that , as police,
they have all been called at one time or
another.
When this episode is discussed after-
wa r d s , some of the policemen say they
would have just kept on walking and not
a rrested anyone for “such a trivial mat t e r ” .
Another notes that a few ye a rs ago, t h e
youths would have had their ears boxed.
The instructor uses the episode to show
how the idea of what constitutes an insult
can change over the ye a rs , pointing out that
this is not just a subjective matter and that
Sensitive issues are discussed in a relaxed and friendly atmosphere.
‘Behind the uniforms 
there are human beings
who ask themselves
questions about their
profession and
about how they do
their jobs’
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
the students gradually come to see the
connection between what they learn in the
classroom and real-life situations.
Before continuing, one of the instru c t o rs
explains to the police that they were called
“ c h i c k e n s ” because Pa ris police headquar-
ters is built on the site of an old chicken
fa rm .“ R e a l l y ? ”m u rm u rs one of them who
had no idea of this, while his colleagues
laugh.
François Delor, a psychiatrist and ins-
t ructor at the Centre, thinks this reaction is
i m p o rtant from a methodological stand-
p o i n t .“ L a u g h t e r ,” he say s , “is a way of avo i-
ding confrontat i o n . Laughing together is
sharing a kind of intimacy and that makes
it possible to work together in a climate of
trust.”
The instructor’s job is to monitor eve-
rything that is said and done during the
sessions and also to spot certain expres-
s i o n s , put them in a broader context and use
that to break down prejudices.
Fred,who has spent 17 of his 40 years
as a policeman, tells how he was once gi ve n
what he thought was a “stupid” order to
a rrest all the Gypsies in the market in C h a r-
l e r o i . But a colleague supported the order,
s aying that “regular checks, especially of
G y p s i e s , will curb cri m e .” Fred retort e d
t h at “ my job isn’t to arrest Gypsies just
because they’re Gypsies” and said it wo u l d
be better to deploy plainclothes police
who could catch thieves red-handed, w h e-
ther they were foreigners or Belgi a n s.
F r e d ’s story about the clearly xe n o p h o b i c
aspect of an order is more effective in
c o m b ating racist attitudes than any speech
because it does not come from one of the
i n s t ru c t o rs but from a fellow policeman.
Amid jokes and friendly chat in a conv i-
vial at m o s p h e r e ,s e n s i t i ve and serious sub-
jects are raised quite easily. But how can we
be sure these policemen will incorp o r at e
into their professional lives some of the
things they have seen and heard in these
workshops and behave more fairly towa r d s
immigrants in general?
Delor is firmly convinced that exchanges
like these have positive effects which may
some day influence the minds of these men
and change the way they act. “Words and
exchanges which seem unimportant some-
times have surp rising effects in the long
term.” He adds that people tend to absorb
as a “potential cognitive resource” s c at t e r e d
elements whose utility may not be obvious
at the time.
This seems to be confirmed by Chri s t i a n
Raes, an assistant police commissioner in
B ru s s e l s. In an interview in the Belgi a n
daily newspaper Le Matin in July 1999, he
said that during the training at the Centre
“bonds were forged between members of
the group and something of that has
remained. I haven’t changed dramatically,
but sometimes I look at things in a different
way and also try to spend a bit more time lis-
tening to my men.”
The Centre’s workshops are undoubtedly
helping the fight against racism and xe n o-
p h o b i a .But changing behaviour pat t e rns that
are deeply rooted in a society is a long-haul
job whch depends,as eve r ,on the enthusiasm
and determ i n ation of eve ryo n e . ■
Group work drawing on personal experience is a key feature of the Belgian police training courses against racism and xenophobia.
‘Laughter is a way of avoiding
c o n f r o n tation. Laughing
together is sharing a kind of
i n t i m a cy which makes it
possible to work together in a
climate of trust’
+ É
Centre pour l’égalité des chances et la lutte contre
le racisme
Rue de la Loi, 155 Résidence Palace
1040 Brussels.
Tel: (32 2) 233 06 11
email: centre@antiracisme.be
http://www.antiracisme.be
Robin Oakley, Police Training concerning
Migrants and Ethnic Relations: Practical Guide-
lines, Council of Europe Publishing, 1994.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
■
At midnight on December 31, t h e
world will enter the year 2000. Fo r
months, sometimes years, plans have
been made to celebrate this special New
Ye a r ’s Eve , especially in the Chri s t i a n
world.But what,if anything, does the date
mean to non-Christians?
“December 31 may herald a new year,
a new century and a new millennium, but
for me it’ll just be a normal day,” says an
amused P. B a l a s u b r a m a n i a n , the chief
accountant of a large firm in the Indian city
of Madras.
For a large part of humanity, the arri va l
of the year 2000 will pass completely unno-
t i c e d . But because globalization means fol-
l owing trends or simply because there is
money to be made, m a ny people have yielded
to the temptation to join the festivities.
Marketing 
the millennium
In India,a d ve rtising razzmatazz orches-
trated by millennium marketeers has rea-
ched most of the populat i o n , thanks to
satellite television. New Delhi is staging a
“Millennium Night Celebration”.Railway
s t at i o n m a s t e rs will blow their whistles to
send trains off on prestigious trips around
the sub-continent. In most of India’s major
tourist centres,from Agra, Khajuraho and
Jaipur,all the hotels are booked up.Yet for
m a ny Indians, mostly Hindus, there is
really little to get worked up about.
According to the V i k ram Samvat, t h e
calendar of the Hindus and Sikhs of nor-
thern and western India, we are already in
the year 2055, while the Shaka, the coun-
t ry ’s most widely used Hindu calendar,
only clocks up 1920. As Indian Catholics
mark the end of 1999, Buddhists will be
e n j oying the year 2542 and Muslims the
year 1420 of the Hegira.A hundred years
a g o, according to another ancient Hindu
c a l e n d a r , the sixth millennium of the
K a l i y u ga era began, supposedly the wo r l-
d’s last (see box).
When all’s said and done, only the we a l-
thiest and most westernized Indians really
feel concerned by the millennium celebra-
tions. “It’s a legacy of colonial times and a
product of marketing,” s ays Bhupinder
S i n g h , a practising Sikh who has retired
from the higher civil service and become a
bu s i n e s s m a n . But he admits he has gone
along with it all. He is promoting Pa k i s t a n ’s
most famous classical singer, S h a f q at A l i
K h a n , in India with the slogan “The Star of
the Millennium”.
Another “ s t a r ” is the island of Kat c h a l l ,
one of the Nicobar Islands in the Bay of
B e n g a l , which will be the first place in India
to see the sunrise on New Ye a r ’s Day 2000.
The ministry of culture is cashing in on the
event (as well as making up for India’s lack
of infrastructure) by inviting seven luxury
ships from all over the world to anchor off
the Nicobar Islands for the big moment.
Other ships are being encouraged to
go to Tonga, in the middle of the Pacific
near the international dateline. To attract
them, Tongan King Taufa’ahau Tupou IV
has decreed a switch to summer daylight
saving time on October 3, thereby gaining
14 hours over Greenwich Mean Time
(GMT) and making the archipelago the
first place on earth to enter the “third mil-
lennium”. This kind of thing has been
done in the past. When Pope Gregory
XIII shortened the year 1582 by 10 days
as part of his reform of the Julian calen-
dar, it meant that St Teresa of Avila died
during the night of the 4th to the . . . 15th
of October.
Weddings and marathons
The U. S . M a rine Observat o ry in T h a i-
land has put forward the controve rsial theory
t h at the sun will rise at 7 a.m. on Ja n u a ry 1
a b ove the frontier between Mya n m a r
( B u rma) and Thailand and that this will be
“the best place in the world to see in the mil-
l e n n i u m .” But while the Thais have a front
s e at for the big show, they may be giving it a
m i s s. Like Laos, C a m b o d i a , M yanmar and
S ri Lanka,Thailand is a country where T h e-
r avada Buddhism is practised; it celebrat e d
its third millennium 543 ye a rs ago. W h at ’s
m o r e ,Thailand marks the new year in mid-
A p ri l ,d u ring S o n g k ra n, the water festiva l .
All the same, some attempts are being
made to stir up enthusiasm for the ye a r
2000.The Tourism Authority of Thailand
( TAT) is organizing events with a “new mil-
l e n n i u m ” tag—millennium weddings for
2,000 couples, a millennium marathon and
a big seaside concert . But in Southeast
Asia, which is struggling to recover from a
t wo - year economic cri s i s , the “new millen-
nium”is on the whole generating little real
interest or extravagant projects. TAT says
there has been a 30 per cent increase in
T HE YEAR 2000: WHO ’ S
COMING TO THE PA RTY ?
◗ Jasmina Sopova
From Osaka to San Francisco, from Beijing to Moscow and Pretoria, millennium fever seems to
have gripped most—but not all—of the planet
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
CA L ENDA RS
F OR ALL:
We are in the year:
● 11 of the Heisei era, which corresponds to the
reign of Japanese Emperor Akihito.
● 1420 of the Hegira, the Muslim era, which
begins on the day when the prophet Muhammad
left Mecca and went to Medina.
● 1999 of the Gregorian ca l e n d a r. Used all over
the world, it is named after Pope Gregory XIII ,
who reformed the Julian calendar in 1582. The
Julian calendar was itself a reform of the Roman
calendar (starting from the date of the foundation
of Rome) instituted by Julius Caesar. The Julian
calendar began to be observed by Christians in the
year 532, when the Church fixed the start of the
Christian era as the presumed day of Christ’s birth.
● 5100 of the Ka l i y u ga e ra, the “age of
c o n flicts”. According to Brahman cosmogony this
is the last cosmic phase of human history. It is
considered to have begun in 3102 B.C. at the
end of the Great War which is the main topic of
the Mahâbhârata epic. The era is supposed to
end in the year 428,999.
● 5543 of the Buddhist era, which commemo-
rates the death of Buddha.
● 5760 of the Jewish calendar, which is based
on the Babylonian calendar, that starts from the
supposed date of the creation of the world. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
December 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 41
hotel reservations for December compared
with December 1998, but nearly all of them
have been by foreigners.
Japan has followed the We s t e rn calendar
since 1873, as part of the modern i z at i o n
process it embarked on during the Meiji
Era. Until then, the country had used the
lunar-solar Ta i i n t a i yo r e k i calendar dat i n g
from the Nara Era (645-794), Ja p a n e s e
civilization’s golden age. For nearly a cen-
t u ry, t h o u g h , the Ja p a n e s e , especially those
living in the countryside, went on celebra-
ting the “old”New Year as well as the new
o n e .And since tradition demands that time
is measured again from zero whenever a
new emperor comes to the throne, the Ja p a-
nese followed three different calendars at
the same time.
These days the Ta i i n t a i yo r e k i is only
o b s e rved by a few sentimental folk and
New Year is celebrated on December 31.
But though calendars come and go, tradi-
tions remain. And so the Japanese will be
marking the New Year as their ancestors
d i d , with ancient games and decorat i o n s ,
f o rmal clothes and special “ l u c k y ” f o o d
dishes.
One we l l - k n own restaurateur has
announced grandly he will make a Tale of
G e n j i m e a l , r e f e rring to a famous 1,000-
year-old classic nove l . On the menu will be
35 dishes for four gourmets. All for a mere
$8,000. More accessible will be the wildly
popular television programme Kohaku Uta
G a s s e n, a contest between the ye a r ’s best
male and female singers,which most Japa-
nese watch eve ry December 31—especially
this year when the Y2K computer bug will
encourage people to stay at home.
To the west of the Land of the Rising
S u n , the new Gregorian year will be gr e e t e d
with typical panache in China.Beijing city
council has gone to great expense, helped
by generous donors in Hong Kong, to bu i l d
a “Chinese Altar of the Century ” .The bu i l-
ding complex, which includes several exhi-
The church of the Nativity at Bethlehem. To mark the year 2000, the Palestinian Authority has launched a major construction and renovation programme in the town.
bition halls,has cost some $24 million and
mobilized some 200 architects and art his-
t o ri a n s.The rotating altar, 47 metres across,
has a huge stage which can accommodate
more than a thousand singers and dancers.
You enter it through a 300-metre-long
“ Tunnel of T i m e ” , d e c o r ated inside with
bronze reliefs showing scenes from the
country’s 5,000-year history.
But the older generation prefer to wait
until February to celebrate the start of the
Year of the Dragon, and remote provinces
will mostly ignore the fuss about the third
m i l l e n n i u m .Young people howe ver can’t
wait for New Ye a r ’s Eve , and brush aside
the rebukes of the ardent defenders of the
Chinese calendar who publicly oppose this
“biblical” anniversary, as well as the insis-
tence of astronomers, who have taken the
matter seriously and are trying to explain
t h at the new millennium will not in fa c t
arrive until a year later.
I n d e e d , in a calendar beginning with
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
the year 1, a new century does not strictly
b e gin until the year 101, and so on until
2 0 0 1 . The Gregorian calendar in its pre-
sent form has only existed for 418 ye a rs ,
and it is really 2,044 ye a rs old when seen as
a direct descendant of the Julian calendar.
W h at ’s more, C h rist was actually born a
few years before the official Christian date
of his birth. So perhaps it’s not surprising
t h at young Confucians,B u d d h i s t s ,Ta o i s t s ,
M u s l i m s , C h ristians and atheists have
concluded that the year 2000 just repre-
sents a worldwide desire to enter the new
millennium as quickly as possible—cele-
b r ating and making money at the same
time—and are keen to take part.
The same enthusiasm can be found in
the Jordan va l l e y. On the Israeli side there is
“Nazareth 2000”and on the Palestinian side
“Bethlehem 2000”.Luckily the share-out of
the holy places is fair to the two peoples
w h i c h , despite the small number of Chri s-
tians among them, are doing up these sites,
which date back to the dawn of Chri s t i a n i t y.
In a region with so many celebrat i o n s ,
there are countless welcoming banners.A f t e r
c e l e b r ations to mark the 3,000th annive r-
s a ry of Je rusalem and 50 ye a rs of Israeli his-
t o ry have been played down because of the
stalled peace process, I s r a e l ’s Lod intern a-
tional airp o rt is building an extension cal-
led “Ben Gurion 2000” (after the country ’s
first prime minister) to welcome the pilgri m s
w h o, b e t ween this Christmas and Easter
2 0 0 1 , will climb the Via Dolorosa which
symbolizes the life of Chri s t .
Will there be six million of them,as the
Vatican predicts, or three to four million as
Israel has provided for, or the 2.5 million
foreseen by the pessimists,who are prepa-
ring for only a 20 per cent increase in tou-
rist numbers?
Storm in a wine-glass?
For Bethlehem, the year 2000 is an eco-
nomically important one.Experts forecast
t h at the influx of tourists will boost the
income of the Palestinian population by
$100 per capita during the ye a r.The Wo r l d
Bank has asked donor countries to beat the
Three Wise Men to it in Bethlehem, by pro-
viding $85 million to do up the town.The
private sector has also come up with funds
to build 6,000 extra hotel rooms.
But the millennium has also produced
some inappropriate tidings. A world away
from the rosari e s , the merchants of the
Temple have had the ultimate bad taste to
offer a “ Je rusalem 2000” C a b e rnet wine.
Its label shows the Dome of the Rock,
Islam’s third most holy place (after Mecca
and Medina) despite the fact that Islam
prohibits consumption of alcohol.A storm
in a wine-glass? The matter has been taken
up with the Arab League.
In the Arab wo r l d , Egypt has decided
In Shanghai, a young couple watch the Bell of the Century.
to be the champion celebrant of the mil-
l e n n i u m , and is avoiding any religious ove r-
t o n e s.The occasion coincides with the start
of ancient Egypt’s seventh millennium, so
the celebrations will naturally take place at
the foot of the Giza pyramids. More than a
thousand perform e rs will gather on a
20,000-square-metre stage and join Jean-
Michel Jarre,a French composer who spe-
cializes in mega-events, to present The 12
Dreams of the Sun.
The producers are happy, as the $9.5
million spent on the project will be recove-
red from some 50,000 people expected to
attend with tickets ranging from $150 to
$400 apiece. Such sums are beyond the
reach of most young Egyptians, who will
be able to have a “place in the sun” for a
more modest amount.
The concert will begin at dusk on the
last day of 1999 and continue until dawn on
the first day of 2000.When the first ray of
the sun appears in the Egyptian sky, a nine-
metre-high golden pyramid will be placed
on the Cheops pyramid to mark the birth of
the “new millennium”.
Happy New Year! ■
With contributions from Indian journalist Utpal Borpujari
( N ew Delhi), Thai journalist Wanphen Sresthaputra (Bang-
kok), Paris-based Japanese journalist Missawa Kano, Chi-
nese journalists Li Xiguang and Huang Yan (Beijing) and
French journalist Claudine Meyer (Isra e l )
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
■
In Budapest (Hungary ) ,B ri t i s h ,F r e n c h
and German public radio broadcasters
are making a joint bid to open an FM
s t ation in 2000.The venture is emblematic of
the new world in which intern ational radios
are nav i g at i n g . Almost ove rn i g h t , the fall of
the Iron Curtain radically called into question
the traditional mission of these broadcas-
t e rs—to send an oxygen balloon of inform a-
tion to citizens living in one-party states or
under repressive regi m e s.
Not that this mission has lost its rele-
va n c e . Afghanistan and China are among
Voice of A m e ri c a ’s top five markets, and in
the latter jamming is standard practice, a
measure of the broadcaster’s undesirable
i n flu e n c e , at least by Chinese gove rn m e n t
s t a n d a r d s.In times of crisis such as the recent
K o s ovo confli c t , audiences surge.Faced with
the most drastic budget cuts in the history of
G e rman public broadcasting in 1999,
Deutsche We l l e ’s director general Dieter We i-
rich remained adamant about the mission of
an intern ational serv i c e : “ Two thirds of
humanity live in countries without freedom of
the press or inform at i o n .We regard it as our
p a rticular duty to provide them with unin-
t e rrupted objective inform ation from credible
s o u r c e s.”
A buoy for freedom
But in many parts of the wo r l d , the end of
the Cold War has taken a time-old ideologi c a l
edge off the equat i o n , forcing intern at i o n a l
b r o a d c a s t e rs to adjust rapidly to a radically
n e w,more fragmented env i r o n m e n t .No lon-
ger can they claim to be the sole altern at i ve to
censored gove rnment broadcasts; no longer
are they viewed as a freedom bu oy to some, a
s u b ve rs i ve force to others. F u rt h e rm o r e , i n
numerous developing countri e s , newly elec-
ted gove rnments have yielded control ove r
IN T ERN AT IONAL 
RA DIO MAKES 
NEW WAV ES
◗ Cynthia Guttman
Once the sole source of outside news for many countries, international public broadcasters
have had to adapt to a new competitive environment
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist, with additional reporting
from Canada by Anne Pelouas
the airwave s ,often opening the way for a plu-
rality of opinions to be expressed on new FM
( f r e q u e n cy modulation) stat i o n s.
“Because of a different political context,
radios whose main goal was to provide infor-
m ation to countries that didn’t have access
to any outside news sources have had to
change their tune and develop on trans-
mission mediums other than short wave ,”
explains Hugues Salord, director of inter-
n ational affa i rs at Radio France Intern a-
t i o n a l e . In a sense, they have had to learn
to “sell themselve s ” on markets with enti-
rely different cultures and expectat i o n s ,b e
it in Europe, A f ri c a ,Asia or Latin A m e ri c a .
In short ,e x t e rnal broadcasters have had to
become both local and international.
The process of adapting to open markets
has been tantamount to an intensive immer-
sion course for external broadcasters. In a
d e r e g u l ated audiovisual landscape, the firs t
m ove for all broadcasters was to strike up
p a rt n e rships with FM stations around the
world for rebroadcast of their progr a m m e s ,o r
to acquire FM transmitters to set up local fre-
q u e n c i e s , a more expensive option. As a
m e d i u m , FM represents a quantum quality
leap over crackly short wave ,a l l owing broad-
c a s t e rs to speak faster and insert music into
p r o gr a m m e s.
The BBC,according to the World Serv i-
c e ’s European news and current affa i rs edi-
tor Mark Bray n e , was “streets ahead of almost
a nybody else” in building up FM netwo r k s ,
s t a rting with Finland in 1987. In 1990, t h e
World Service was in Romania just after the
fall of the Communist regime signing deals
with emerging radio stations and has built up
a network of 97 local rebroadcasters.A recent
study shows that the British broadaster has
captured 17 per cent of the Romanian radio
a u d i e n c e :“ We have become a national broad-
caster in a sense.We cover Romanian news in
quite some detail but with BBC journ a l i s t i c
In the Uighur Autonomous Region of Xinjiang (People’s Republic of China) a Mongolian boy listens 
to the radio in uplands near the border with Kazakhstan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
C O N N E X I O N S
values embedded into a solid analytical fa r e
of intern ational news,” s ays Bray n e .
A f ri c a , where broadcast markets deregu-
l ated faster than in A s i a , is a particularly cove-
ted zone.W h e r e ver an external broadcaster
can get onto FM, audiences shoot up.T h e
BBC and RFI pull in huge audiences in their
f o rmer A f rican colonies while Ethiopia ranks
among VOA ’s top five markets. RFI has star-
ted to open up FM relays outside West A f ri-
can capitals, in the second and third largest
c i t i e s ,and is introducing locally produced pro-
grammes in the Bambara language in Mali.
“RFI is practically perceived as a full-fle d-
ged national radio serv i c e , with audience
scores of up to 30 to 40 per cent of the
French-speaking populat i o n ,” s ays Erlends
C a l a bu i g, director of foreign languages.T h e
French broadcaster is now trying to make
inroads outside the francophone zone, w i t h
the recent opening of an FM station in Ghana
and one to follow in Lagos.“There is a clear
desire for countries in the region to break
away from their zone of traditonal cultural
i n flu e n c e ,” s ays Salord.“I think anglophone
A f rica is taking a gr owing interest in the fran-
cophone wo r l d ,not only in a linguistic sense,
but also from a political, economic and cul-
tural standpoint.”
Demand for accurate information
C l e a r l y, there is a strong demand for
e x t e rnal broadcasters , and not only as pro-
v i d e rs of intern ational news. “There is fa r
gr e ater competition on a large number of
m a r k e t s , but not always for accurate and
i m p a rtial news,” s ays Caroline T h o m s o n ,
deputy chief exe c u t i ve of the BBC Wo r l d
S e rv i c e . “In many countri e s , a lot of music
s t ations have come on the air as a result of
d e r g u l at i o n , but news is quite heavily regu-
l ated or of ve ry poor quality and subject to
considerable local interference.”
Voice of A m e ri c a ’s director Sandy Unger
c o n c u rs that there is a strong demand in emer-
ging democracies for balanced and accurat e
i n f o rm at i o n .“Where media are not fully deve-
l o p e d ,where there are criminal libel laws and
all sorts of constraints on free flow of infor-
m at i o n , reliable inform ation ve ry often has to
come from the outside,”he affirm s.E v i d e n c e
seems to speak for itself. Pointing to VOA ’s
400 affil i ate FM stations in Latin A m e ri c a ,
he asks: “ W hy are they signing up for this if
there is no need, if they were confident that
i n f o rm ation is being provided in their socie-
t i e s ? ”
While all the major broadcasters are pre-
sent on local FMs, they each have a mission
to uphold.The BBC World Service stands by
its reputation for trust and quality,r e p e at e d l y
singled out in its audience surve y s.Voice of
A m e ri c a , which became an independent
federal entity in October, upholds its man-
d ate to report on world news and on A m e ri-
can politics, society and culture. RFI pri d e s
itself on presenting a French reading of the
news that reflects the dive rsity of opinion in
the country. DW ’s director Dieter We i ri c h
underlines the broadcaster’s role in “ f o rm i n g
an intern ational awareness about the new
m o d e rn Germ a ny.” But how this mission is
c a rried out has changed, because FM calls
for a more upbeat ,i n t e r a c t i ve style of pro-
gramming than short - wave broadcasting.A n d
because FM stations are locally based,b r o a d-
c a s t e rs have to understand and cultivate their
niche audiences.
“It is really a matter of zooming in,”
explains RFI’s Calabu i g .“ We have move d
away from reaching an indiscri m i n ate mass of
l i s t e n e rs via one means of transmission span-
ning the whole globe to a focus on prox i m i t y,
which means cat e ring to the expectations of
l i s t e n e rs.”While intern ational news remains
the backbone of all the broadcasters ’ p r o-
gramming and has been significantly expan-
ded over the past few ye a rs to provide round-
the-clock cove r a g e ,menus have also become
more eclectic,mixing music and features adap-
ted to different regi o n s. Local production has
taken on a heightened import a n c e .
From 1989 onwa r d s , the BBC start e d
r e c ruiting younger people in the former Eas-
t e rn bloc who were familiar with the target
a r e a .In Bucharest and Sofia ,R F I ’s subsidiari e s
broadcast a mix of locally produced pro-
grammes along with others from Pa ris offe-
ring a more Franco-European angle on eve n t s.
There is a strong conv i c t i o n , voiced by all
European external broadcasters ,t h at they have
a role to play in “ a c c o m p a nying a dialogue bet-
ween Central and Eastern European coun-
t ri e s , to offer an opening onto Europe,” a s
C a l a buig puts in.And there is also a common
responsibility towards building a unifie d
E u r o p e :Radio E,a current events progr a m m e ,
is put together with contri butions from seve r a l
public European broadcasters ,giving listeners
a richer reading of regional issues.
Local language broadcasting
Broadcasting in local languages is one of
the keys to reaching new audiences. R F I ’s
e f f o rts to break into anglophone A f rica will
be stalled until the broadcaster can afford to
m ove into local languages, namely Swa h i l i
and Hausa, as VOA , BBC and DW have all
d o n e .The BBC has introduced several lan-
guages spoken in the newly independent repu-
blics of the former Soviet Union, n o t a b l y
U z b e k ,A z e ri , U k r a i n i a n , Kazakh and Ky r-
g y z .At the same time, it has shut down other
language services—mostly ve rnacular lan-
guages in We s t e rn Europe—which doesn’t
n e c e s s a rily mean loss of influ e n c e .
The BBC’s strategy is to target elites,
and more often than not this can be done in
E n g l i s h . “When we have cut languages, i t ’s
tended to be because we thought that they
were no longer effective rather than because
our budget had been slashed,” says Thom-
s o n .The BBC’s most recent decision to pull
out of German was taken after studies sho-
wed that most of the broadcaster’s audience
in the German-speaking world listened to
its programmes in English. In the U. S . ,t h e
World Serv i c e ’s audience has even recor-
ded growth in recent years.
Faced with cutbacks, DW is ending its
p r o grammes in Japanese and Spanish,and is
in the process of closing several other language
s e rv i c e s , including Czech, S l ovak and Hun-
g a ri a n ,j u d ging that the countries where these
languages are spoken are now “ e s t a b l i s h e d
democracies with a gr e at va riety of media ava i-
l a b l e ” . It is howe ver expanding its Russian
and English-language progr a m m e s , and aims
to make headway in the Asian market via the
A s i a S at 2 sat e l l i t e . Regardless of bu d g e t
c o n s t r a i n t s , all the major playe rs have intro-
duced broadcasts in Albanian and Macedo-
n i a n ,r e flecting the pri o rity they put on being
on air as fast as possible when political cir-
cumstances wa rr a n t .
Introducing new languages may be at the
h e a rt of broadcasters ’s t r at e gies in emergi n g
democracies and developing countri e s ,but it
costs money.While all broadcasters underline
their editorial independence from gove rn-
m e n t , they all rely on them for funding, a n d
IN T ERN AT ION A L
BROA DCAS T ING ’ S
BIG LEAGUE
BBC World Service : 1,120 hours reaching 143
million listeners weekly in 43 languages; budget:
£175 million ($280 million)
VOA (Voice of America): 870 hours reaching 91
million listeners weekly in 53 languages; budget:
$106 million*
D W (Deutsche Welle): 718 hours reaching 28 m i l-
lion listeners weekly in 36 languages; budget:
DM606 million ($336.6 million)
RFI (Radio France Internationale)**: 313 hours
reaching 45 million listeners weekly in 20 lan-
guages; budget: FF754 million ($125.6 million)
*Salaries and reporting costs only. Excludes
transmission costs.
** Including its subsidiary, RMC Moyen Orient.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
none has been graced with a generous influ x
over the past decade.VOA ’s director Sandy
Unger fears “ d r a m atic cuts” if Congress only
grants the service a straightline budget for fis-
cal 2000,which would mean absorbing a 4.8
per cent cost of living increase.The World Ser-
v i c e ’s budget has declined in real terms ove r
the past eight ye a rs. R F I ’s has been stable.
DW ’s budget for 1999 was reduced by DM
30 million ($16.6 million/4.7 per cent), a n d
will be slashed by a further 10 per cent to DM
546 million ($302.3 million), up to the ye a r
2003—seemingly a turnabout from last ye a r ,
when the newly elected gove rnment promi-
sed “an improvement in the way the country
represents itself to the outside wo r l d ”a c c o r-
ding to We i ri c h .Besides six language closures,
over 700 jobs are to be cut.
In the early 1990s, Radio Canada Inter-
n ationale (RCI), a smaller player on the wo r l d
s t a g e , cut seven of its 15 languages and
s h runk its staff, and nearly went off the air in
1996 when it was was saved at the eleve n t h
hour by a federal gove rnment gr a n t .F l o ri a n
S a u va g e a u , a professor at Laval Unive rs i t y
( C a n a d a ) , argues that the crisis reflected the
g ove rn m e n t ’s lack of interest in intern at i o-
nal culural relat i o n s. RCI now aims to put
f o r ward the country ’s economic strength and
cultural dive rs i t y, and is boosting broadcas-
ting to China and A f ri c a .
In this belt-tightening env i r o n m e n t ,o n e
of the dilemmas is how to be present on all
f r o n t s. In politically sensitive zones, e x t e r-
nal radios have to maintain a short - wave pre-
sence in addition to their FM frequencies
and satellite broadcasting. Then comes
i nvestment in new technologi e s.The Inter-
net is top pri o rity for all public broadcasters.
“ I t ’s the short wave of the future,” a f firm s
T h o m s o n .“The trouble with FM is that yo u
are ve ry susceptible to local pressures,” s h e
c o n t i n u e s , noting that at any one time, t h e
World Service has a couple of FM stat i o n s
off the air because an item has offended the
p owe rs in place.“If you are looking at how to
maintain vibrant intern ational broadcasting
in 20 ye a rs time, yo u ’ ve got to invest in the
I n t e rnet now. I t ’s a much freer medium.”
Digitalizing short wave
Thanks to the net, Indian and Pa k i s t a n i
communities in Britain can, for example,
access programmes in Hindi and Urdu.V i e t-
namese can do the same in their own language,
whether they are in the U. S . or V i e t n a m .A l l
b r o a d c a s t e rs are also keeping a close watch on
Worldspace—direct reception via satellite on
individual dishes allowing for an exceptional
quality—and the imminent digi t a l i z ation of
s h o rt wave ,which is likely to gi ve this medium
a new lease on life. D i gitalized short wave will
not only ensure higher listening quality, bu t
also reduce production costs, a l l owing for a
bu rst of new stations to go on air and cater to
increasingly specific audience segments.
M a ny of the countries where deregu-
l ation is underway inherited state broad-
casting services from their former impe-
rial powe rs. N ow, the latter are helping
the liberalization process along, often by
p r oviding training courses and technical
a s s i s t a n c e . RFI recalls that its launch of
the first FM station in Dakar (Senegal) in
1991 played a significant role in “ o p e n i n g
up and enriching the radio landscape and
r e i nv i g o r ating national public radio.” Fo r
VOA ’s Unger, in a number of deve l o p i n g
c o u n t ri e s ,“ i n t e rn ational broadcasters are
s e rving as an example of what can be
d e ve l o p e d .”W h i c h e ver technology wins
out—and colossal investments are at
stake—only contents can gi ve extern a l
b r o a d c a s t e rs the cutting edge.Their gr e a-
test asset, for Salord, lies in their exper-
t i s e , k n ow - h ow and worldwide netwo r k
of corr e s p o n d e n t s. “ I n t e rn ational radio
b r o a d c a s t e rs have a role to play in decry p-
ting the complexity of the world we live
i n .This is our job, not to gi ve value judg-
ments or lessons but to provide facts and
elements that help the listener in form i n g
his or her own opinion.” ■
In Tanzania, Rwandan Hutu refugees stand on a mound to get better radio reception.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
WA NG A RI MU TA MAAT H A I :
K EN YA’S GREEN MIL I TA N T
A noted environmental and pro-democracy activist hopes the next millennium will see a new
African leadership that puts people first
You once said that the quality of the
environment cannot be improved unless and
until the living conditions of ordinary people
are improved. Could you enlarge on this?
If you want to save the environment
you should protect the people firs t ,
because human beings are part of biologi-
cal diversity. And if we can’t protect our
own species, what’s the point of protec-
ting tree species?
It sometimes looks as if poor people are
d e s t r oying the env i r o n m e n t . But they are
so preoccupied with their surv i val that they
are not concerned about the long-term
damage they are doing to the env i r o n m e n t
simply to meet their most basic needs.
So it is ironic that the poor people
who depend on the environment are also
p a rtly responsible for its destru c t i o n .
That’s why I insist that the living condi-
tions of the poor must be improved if we
really want to save our environment.
For example, in certain regions of
Kenya, women walk for miles to get fire-
wood from the forests, as there are no
trees left nearby. When fuel is in short
supply, women have to walk further and
further to find it. Hot meals are served
less frequently, nutrition suffers,and hun-
ger increases. If these women had enough
resources they would not be depleting
valuable forest.
What is at stake in the forests of Kenya and
East Africa today?
Since the beginning of this century,
there has been a clear tendency to cut
d own indigenous forests and to replace
them with exotic species for commercial
e x p l o i t at i o n . We ’ ve now become more
aware of what this invo l ves and have reali-
zed that it was wrong to cut down indige-
nous forests, thereby destroying our ri c h
b i o l o gical dive rs i t y. But much damage has
already been done.
When the Green Belt Movement (see
box page 47) started its campaign in 1977
to plant trees, Kenya had about 2.9 per
cent of forest cover. Today the forested
area has further dwindled to around two
per cent.We are losing more trees than we
are planting.
The other important issue is that the
East African environment is very vulne-
rable. We are very close to the Sahara
desert, and experts have been warning
that the desert could expand southwards
like a flood if we keep on felling trees
indiscriminately, since trees prevent soil
erosion caused by rain and wind. By clea-
ring remaining patches of forests we are in
essence creating many micro-Sahara
deserts. We can already see evidence of
this phenomenon.
We hold civic education seminars for
rural people, especially farmers, as part of
campaigns to raise public awa r e n e s s
about environmental issues. If you were to
ask a hundred farmers how many of them
remember a spring or a stream that has
dried up in their lifetime, almost 30 of
them would raise their hands.
What has your Green Belt Movement (GBM)
achieved and in particular to what extent has
it prevented environmental degradation in
Kenya?
The most notable achievement of the
GBM in my view has been in raising envi-
ronmental awareness among ordinary
citizens, especially rural people. Different
groups of people now realize that the
environment is a concern for everybody
and not simply a concern for the
government. It is partly because of this
awareness that we are now able to reach
out to decision-makers in the govern-
ment. Ordinary citizens are challenging
them to protect the environment.
Secondly, the GBM introduced the
idea of environmental conservat i o n
through trees because trees meet many
basic needs of rural communities. We
started out by planting seven trees in a
small park in Nairobi in 1977. At that
time we had no tree nursery, no staff and
no funds, only a conviction that ordinary
country people had a role to play in sol-
ving environmental problems.We went on
from there and now we have planted over
20 million trees all over Kenya.
The act of planting trees conveys a
simple message. It suggests that at the
very least you can plant a tree and impro-
ve your habitat. It increases people’s awa-
reness that they can take control of their
e nv i r o n m e n t , which is the first step
toward greater participation in society.
Since the trees we have planted are
visible, they are the greatest ambassadors
for our movement.
Despite the Rio Earth Summit of 1992 and the
Kyoto Climate summit in 1997, there has been
no significant progress in environmental
protection programmes and campaigns at a
global level. Why?
Unfortunately, for many world leaders
development still means extensive far-
ming of cash crops, expensive hydroelec-
tric dams,hotels,supermarkets,and luxu-
ry items, which plunder human and
natural resources. This is short-sighted
and does not meet people’s basic needs—
for adequate food, clean water, shelter,
local clinics, information and freedom.
As a result of this craze for so-called
d e ve l o p m e n t , e nvironmental protection
has taken a back seat.The problem is that
the people who are responsible for much
of the destruction of the environment are
precisely those who should be providing
leadership in environmental protection
campaigns. But they are not doing so.
‘The act of planting trees
conveys a simple message. 
It suggests that at the very
least you can plant a tree and
improve your habitat. 
It increases people’s awareness
that they can ta ke control of
their environment, which is 
the first step toward greater
participation in society ’
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
December 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G  T O …
Also, political power now is wielded
by those who have business interests and
close links with multinational corpora-
tions (MNCs). The only aim of these
MNCs is to make profit at the expense of
the environment and people.
We also know that many world political
l e a d e rs are persuaded by MNCs not to pay
attention to declarations made in intern a-
tional environmental conferences. I stron-
gly believe that as citizens we should refu-
se to be at the mercy of these corp o r at i o n s.
C o rp o r ations can be extremely merciless,
as they have no human fa c e .
You started your career as an academic. Later
you became an environmentalist, and now you
are called a pro-democra cy activist. How would
you describe your evolution in the last 25 years?
Few environmentalists today are wo r-
ried about the we l fare of bees, bu t t e r fli e s
A 20 - MIL L ION -T REE
GREEN BELT
In a country where women play a marginal role
in political and social affairs, 59-year-old Wa n-
gari Muta Maathai’s achievements stand out as an
exception. A biologist, she was the first woman
from East Africa to receive a doctorate, to become
a professor and chair a department—all at the Uni-
versity of Nairobi.
Maathai began to be active in the National
Council of Women of Kenya in 1976 and it was
through the Council that she launched a tree-plan-
ting project called “Save the Land H a ra m b e e” (a
Swahili word meaning let’s all pull together). The
project was renamed the Green Belt Movement
(GBM) in 1977.
The GBM initiated programmes to promote
and protect biodiversity, to protect the soil, to
create jobs especially in rural areas, to give
women a positive image in the community and to
assert their leadership qualities. 
The overall aim of the GBM has been to create
public awareness of the need to protect the envi-
ronment through tree planting and sustainable
management. Nearly 80 per cent of the 20 million
trees planted by the GBM have survived. At pre-
sent the GBM has over 3,000 nurseries, giving job
opportunities to about 80,000 people, most of
them rural women.
In 1986 the GBM established a Pan-African
Green Belt Network and has organized work-
shops and training programmes on environ-
mental awareness for scores of individuals from
other African countries. This has led to the adop-
tion of Green Belt methods in Tanzania, Uganda,
Malawi, Lesotho, Ethiopia, and Zimbabwe.
Maathai, who is a member of the UN Secre-
t a ry General’s Advisory Board on Disarmament,
has won 14 international awards, including the
prestigious Right Livelihood Award. She won the
award, presented by a Swedish foundation and
often referred to as an Alternative Nobel Prize, in
recognition of her “contributions to the well-
being of humankind”.
In a country where single-party rule prevailed
for decades, Maathai has been teargassed and
severely beaten by police during demonstra t i o n s
to protect Kenya’s forests.
“The government thinks that by threatening
me and bashing me they can silence me,” says
Maathai. “But I have an elephant’s skin. And
somebody must raise their voice.”
Maathai, a mother of three children, is cur-
rently involved in a struggle to save the 2,50 0 - a c r e
Karura forests, northwest of Nairobi, where the
government wants to build housing complexes.
■
and trees alone. They know that it is not
possible to keep the environment pure if
you have a gove rnment that does not
control polluting industries and deforesta-
t i o n .
In Kenya , for example, real estate deve-
l o p e rs have been allowed to go into the
middle of indigenous forests and bu i l d
e x p e n s i ve houses. As concerned indivi-
duals we should oppose that . When yo u
s t a rt intervening at that leve l , you fin d
yo u rself in direct confrontation with poli-
cy - m a k e rs and you start to be called an
a c t i v i s t .
I was teaching at the University of
Nairobi in the 1970s, when I felt that the
academic rights of women professors
were not being respected because they
were women. I became an activist at the
u n i ve rs i t y, insisting that I wanted my
rights as an academic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The UNESCO Courier - December 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
Meanwhile,I found myself confronted
by other issues that were directly related
to my work but were not clear to me at
the outset, like human rights.This direct-
ly led me to another area, governance. As
a result I was drafted into the pro-demo-
cracy campaign.
I realized in the 1970s that in a young
democracy like ours it was very easy for
leaders to become dictators. As this hap-
pened they started using nat i o n a l
resources as though they were their per-
sonal property. I realized that the consti-
tution had given them powers to misuse
official machinery.
So I became involved in the pro-
democracy movement and pressed for
constitutional reforms and political space
to ensure freedom of thought and expres-
sion. We cannot live with a political sys-
tem that kills creativity and produces
cowardly people.
With your academic qualifications you could
have lived a comfortable life in the U.S. or
e l s ewhere in the West. But you decided to
come back and settle down in Kenya. In the
last 25 years, you have been verbally abused,
threatened, beaten, put behind bars and on
many occasions forbidden to leave the
c o u n t ry. Have you ever regretted returning to
Kenya and becoming an activist?
I did not deliberately decide to beco-
me an activist, but I have never regretted
the fact that I decided to stay here and to
contribute to the development of this
country and my region. I know that I have
made a little difference.
Many people come up to me and tell
me that my work has inspired them.This
gives me great satisfaction because in the
earlier days, especially during the dicta-
torship, it was difficult to speak.
Until a few years ago, people used to
come up to me in the street and whisper
“I am with you and I am praying for you.“
They were so scared of being identified
with me that they did not want to be
heard. I know a lot of people were afraid
of talking to me and being seen with me
because they might be punished.
I have been a greater positive force by
staying here and going through trials and
tribulations than if I had gone to other
countries. It would have been very diffe-
rent to live in the West and say my coun-
try should do this and that. By being here
I encourage many more people.
Do you think you were subjected to virulent
attacks and abuses because you questioned
men’s decisions?
Our men think A f rican women should
be dependent and submissive , d e fin i t e l y
not better than their husbands.There is no
doubt that at first many people opposed
me because I am a woman and resented
the idea that I had strong opinions.
I know that at times men in positions
of influence, including President Daniel
Arap Moi, ridiculed me. At one time
Members of Parliament accused me and
ridiculed me for being a divorced woman.
I have felt that deep inside they were
hoping that by calling into question my
womanhood I would be subdued. Later
they realized they were wrong.
In 1989, for example, we had a big
confrontation with the authorities when
we were fighting to save Uhuru Park in
Nairobi. I argued that it would be ridicu-
lous to destroy this beautiful park in the
centre of the city and replace it with a
multi-storeyed complex.
Uhuru Park was the only place in
Nairobi where people could spend time
with their families outdoors.The park was
a wonderful place for people to go becau-
se it was a place where no one bothered
them.
When I launched the campaign oppo-
sing the construction of the “Park-mons-
ter“, as the project later came to be
known, I was ridiculed and accused of not
u n d e rstanding deve l o p m e n t . I didn’t
‘At one time Members of
Parliament accused me and
ridiculed me for being a
divorced woman. I have felt
that deep inside they were
hoping that by calling into
question my womanhood I
would be subdued. Later they
realized they were wrong’
Nairobi
Tanzania
0      100 km
Indian
Ocean 
Uganda
Sudan Ethiopia
K EN YA
Mombasa
Kakamega
Kisumu
Nakuru
Nyen
Embu
Garissa
In Madagascar, a woman plants rice in the ashes of a felled area of forest, home to the last survivors 
of a lemur species.
K EN YA FACT FIL E
Republic of Kenya (Jamhuri ya Kenya)
A former British colony, gained independence in
1963 and became a republic the following year.
Area: 582,646 sq.km
Capital: Nairobi
Population: 28.4 million
Languages: Kiswahili, English
Life expectancy at birth: 52 years
Adult literacy rate: 79.3 %
GDP per capita: $372
President: Daniel T. Arap Moi
Monetary Unit: Kenya Shilling 
(74 shillings=$1 US)
Source: UNDP Human Development Report 1999
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O …
A member of Kenya’s Green Belt movement. 
study development but I do know that
you need space in a city. Fortunately
other non-gove rnmental organizat i o n s
and thousands of ordinary people joined
our protests and finally the park was
saved.
The government, which wanted to
destroy that park, has since declared it a
national heritage.That’s wonderful.They
could have done that without fighting and
without ridiculing me.
What made you stand in the presidential
elections in 19 97? Despite your popularity, why
didn’t you win a sizeable number of votes?
I decided to stand for election for
several reasons. In 1992, when a multi-
party system was legalized in Kenya for
the first time, I tried very hard with other
political groups to unite the opposition,
but in vain.When there were many oppo-
sition candidates running for the presi-
dency, I withdrew from the campaign.
As expected, the opposition lost those
elections and everybody now accepts that
the campaign we launched for them to
unite was right. We wanted to form a
government of national unity within the
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the U N E S CO CO U R I E R
✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15A) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396French francs ( 6 0 . 35A) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 72FF ( 11A) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10A)
2 years: 211FF ( 32 .15A) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCO COURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa Eu ro c a rd M a s t e rc a rd
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:                  Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O …
‘This generation of Africa n
leaders will go down 
in history as a very
irresponsible one that has
brought Africa to its knees.
During the past three deca d e s ,
A f r i ca has suffered from 
a lack of visionary and
altruistic leaders committed 
to the welfare of their people’
opposition in 1992. This is exactly what
they are now clamouring for.
In the 1997 general elections,my idea wa s
to persuade the opposition to unite and fie l d
a strong candidate from one ethnic commu-
nity against the ruling Kenya A f rican Nat i o-
nal Union (KANU).1 But I was called a tri-
balist by some opposition groups for
proposing that idea.When all my efforts to
unite the opposition fa i l e d , I decided to ru n
for president.
But during the campaign I also came to
realize that in this country it is ve ry diffic u l t
to get elected without money. I didn’t have
m o n e y. I realized that it doesn’t matter how
good you are, h ow honest you are and how
p r o - d e m o c r atic you are, if you don’t have
money to gi ve to the voter you wo n ’t get
elected.So I lost.
All this gave me a new experience.
Now I can speak as an insider. I also rea-
lized that people here are not yet ready for
democracy and we need a lot of civic edu-
cation and political consciousness. People
here are still controlled by ethnicity and
vote along ethnic lines. The ethnic ques-
tion became a ve ry important issue
during the last elections.
Despite having enormous natural resources
A f r i ca still lags behind other continents in terms
of development and growth. Why is this?
Poor leaders h i p, without any doubt.T h i s
g e n e r ation of A f rican leaders will go down in
history as a very irresponsible one that has
brought A f rica to its knees. D u ring the past
three decades, A f rica has suffered from a
lack of visionary and altruistic leaders com-
mitted to the welfare of their people.
There are historical reasons for this.
Just before independence was granted to
many African countries, young Africans
were promoted by colonial rulers to posi-
tions until then unoccupied by the local
people and were trained to take over
power from the colonial administration.
The new black administrat o rs and
burgeoning elites enjoyed the same eco-
nomic and social life-styles and privileges
that the imperial administrators enjoyed.
The only difference between the two in
terms of the objectives for the country
was the colour of their skin.
In the process, the A f rican leaders aban-
doned their people, and in order to maintain
their hold on power they did exactly what
the colonial system was doing, namely to pit
one community against another. T h i s
internal conflict continued for decades in
m a ny A f rican countri e s , draining their
scarce resources.
So what we need is to improve our lea-
d e rs h i p. If we don’t there is no hope,b e c a u s e
h i s t o ry teaches us that if you cannot protect
w h at is your own somebody will come and
take it. If our people cannot protect them-
s e l ves they will continue to be exploited.T h e i r
resources will continue to be exploited.
It is also true that Western powers,
especially the former colonial masters of
this region, have continued to exploit
Africa and have continued to work very
closely with these dictators and irrespon-
sible leaders.That is why we are now deep
in debt, which we cannot repay.
A f rica also needs assistance from inter-
n ational gove rnments to improve its eco-
nomic standing. For example, most foreign
aid to A f rica comes in the form of curat i ve
social we l fare programmes such as fa m i n e
r e l i e f, food aid, p o p u l ation control pro-
gr a m m e s , refugee camps, p e a c e - k e e p i n g
forces and humanitarian missions.
At the same time, hardly any resources
are available for sustainable human deve-
lopment programmes such as functional
e d u c ation and training, d e velopment of
i n f r a s t ru c t u r e , food production and pro-
motion of entrepreneurs h i p. There are no
funds for the development of cultural and
social programmes which would empowe r
people and release their creat i ve energy.
I am hoping that in the new millennium
a new leadership will emerge in A f ri c a ,a n d
I hope this new leadership will show more
c o n c e rn for the people and utilize the conti-
n e n t ’s resources to help A f ricans get out of
poverty. ■
Interview by Ethirajan Anbarasan,
UNESCO Courier journalist
1.The Kenya African National Union (KANU)
was formed in 1960, won the country’s first post-
independence election in 1963, and has been in
power ever since.
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George's Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Brussels. 
Fax: 538 08 41.
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
Oxford Book & Stationery Co, Code No D 820 8 0 52, Scindia House, New
Delhi 110 001. Fax: 33 22 639 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Nalanda Co. Ltd., 30 Bourbon Street, Port Louis. 
Fax: 212 1313 .
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
Los Amigos de la UNES CO, Avenida Urquijo 62, 2 Izd., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 94427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG, Wissenschaftl. Buchhandlung, Pe t e r s g raben 31, 
CH-4009 Basel. Fax: 306 12 34 .
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce
C/C Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: 286 03 26 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
Book/Livre/Libro: 120FF /19.28 €
+ 30 FF /4.57 € postage/frais d’envoi/franqueo
CD-ROM: 120 FF /19.28 €,
postage included/frais d’envoi compris/franqueo incluido 
Book/Livre/Libro + CD-ROM: 180 F F /27.44 €
+ 30 FF /4.57 € postage/frais d’envoi/franqueo 
Études à l’étranger 
2000–2001
3 1E ÉDITION    LIVRE ET CD-ROM (PC/MAC)
Le guide international de l’UNESCO pour tout savoir
sur les possibilités d’études supérieures et sur 
les bourses offertes par les universités, les institutions
spécialisées et les organisations internationales
| Une référence unique depuis 1948
| 2 600 cours dans 124 pays
Toutes les disciplines académiques 
et professionnelles au niveau supérieur  | Adresses
et références, y compris adresses électroniques 
et sites Internet  | Conditions d’admission  | Dates
d’inscription  | Frais d’études et coût de la vie 
dans chaque pays  | Bourses et assistance financière
| Statistiques sur les universités.
| Informations en anglais, français ou espagnol
selon le pays
U N E S C O  P u b l i s h i n g
Edic iones U N E S C O
Éditions U N E S C O
Study abroad 
2000–2001
31ST EDITION    BOOK AND CD-ROM (PC/MAC)
The UNESCO international guide to higher-education
study opportunities and scholarships offered by universi-
ties, specialized schools and international organizations
| A reference since 1948
| 2,600 courses in 124 countries
All higher-education academic and professional disci-
plines  | Addresses and references, including 
e-mail and websites  | Admission requirements  |
Application deadlines  | Scholarships and financial aid
| Fees and living expenses in each country | Various
statistics concerning the institutions.
| Entries in English, French or Spanish according 
to the country
Estudios en el extranjero
2000–2001
31.A EDICIÓN    LIBRO Y CD-ROM (PC/MAC)
La guía internacional de la UNESCO indispensable para
informarse sobre las becas y los cursos universitarios
ofrecidos por universidades, instituciones especializadas
y organismos internacionales
| Una fuente de referencia única en su género
desde 1948
| 2.600 cursos en 124 países
Todas las disciplinas académicas y profesionales 
de nivel postsecundario  | Direcciones e información
general, incluido el correo electrónico y las páginas
Internet  | Condiciones de admisión  | Fechas 
de inscripción  | Becas y ayuda financiera  | Costo
de los estudios  | Estadísticas sobre las instituciones.
| Informaciones presentadas en inglés, francés 
o español, según el país
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Fo c u s :
International Year
for the Culture of Peace 2000
■ A new arena for individual action
■ The South: people adrift in fragile States 
■ Three unsung peace-makers
■ The Community of Sant’Egidio: serving the poor,
working for peace
■ Jubilee 2000: a campaign to cancel Third World debt
■ Indian farmers against GMOs
■ Mali: the culture of peace in power
■ Towards a coalition of alternative movements
Fe a t u res include
■ Photo report on Japan’s teenagers
■ The long haul to save the Aral Sea
■ Teachers up against classroom violence
■ The Hermitage comes out of its shell
■ The meaning of mortality: euthanasia and world religions
■ Interview with American philosopher Michael Walzer:
the quest for social justice
]]>
</page>
</document>
