<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="118482eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
PLANET
Aral Sea: back
from the brink?
CONNEXIONS
Middle East:
media diversity
via satellite
IN T ERV IEW
Michael Walzer:
a user’s guide
to democracy
January 2000
International Year 2000
Peace is
in our hands
PEOPLE AND PLACES
For Japan’s
perplexed teenagers,
the end of an era
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
53rd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief:John Kohut
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Cynthia Guttman
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat,
Hervé Tissot,Annick Coueffé
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant:Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corral,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e : Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh(Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UN E S C O or those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. P h o t o
captions and headlines are written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r
s t a f f. The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O o r
the United Nations. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7
Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfil m s
( X e r o x ) , Ann A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C . R .
Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfie l d
R o a d , Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - JANUARY 2000
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Pa r i s
by UN E S C O. Printed in Fr a n c e. Periodicals postage paid at
Champlain NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’UNESCO.
Impression:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 1-2000-OPI 99-587 A
C o n t e n t s
January 2000
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 For Japan’s perplexed teenagers, the end of an era
Photos by Bertrand Desprez;Text by Ryu Murakami
OPINION
9 The knowledge divide Francisco Sagasti
PLANET
10 Aral Sea:back from the brink?
Sue Lloyd-Roberts and Ethirajan Anbarasan
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Unruly classrooms Lucía Iglesias Ku n t z
ETHICS
37 Euthanasia and religion Courtney S.C a m p b e l l
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 The Hermitage comes out of its shell Alexander Kan
CONNEXIONS
43 Middle East:media diversity via satellite Christophe A y a d
TALKING TO…
46 Michael Wa l z e r : a user’s guide to democra c y
C o v e r : © Pascal Lafay/EDITING, Pa r i s
1 7 Focus International Year 2000:
Peace is in our hands
The year 2000 has been proclaimed International Year for the
Culture of Pe a c e. Peace-building is not a state monopoly.
Everyone can and should contribute to it.
This Focus section looks at initiatives by individuals and groups
united by common humanist values and a can-do approach.
Detailed table of contents on page 17.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
All hands on stage! Pupils take a peek at a school show at Hanamaki, in the north of Honshu island. All photos in this “People and Places” feature were taken in 1998.
F OR JA PA N ’ S
PERPL EX ED TEEN AGERS ,
T HE END OF AN ERA
w Photos by Bertrand Desprez; Text by Ryu Murakami
For over a century Japanese society was welded together by a struggle to catch up
with the West. Now, as the old certainties fade away, Japanese youth faces
a complex and ruthless world.
n
It has often been said that Ja p a n ,u n l i k e
the United Stat e s , is not a country of
i m m i gr a n t s , and that for all practical
p u rposes it has a single religion and a single
l a n g u a g e .W h at ’s more, since their country
emerged from isolation in the Meiji Pe ri o d1
the Japanese have had one ove r w h e l m i n g
n ational aim: m o d e rn i z at i o n .The profound
desire for modern i z ation worked like a cen-
t ripetal force on the people to bring them
all into a single close circle of stability.To d ay,
t h at circle is disintegr at i n g .The modern i-
z ation of Japan ended in the 1970s.T h at
was when the gr e at national aim that had
existed since the Meiji period ceased to exist
and as a result the nat i o n ’s centripetal force
petered out. In eve ry fie l d , the communi-
t y ’s standards, the way things were done and
e ven communicated were called in ques-
t i o n . For previous generations of Ja p a n e s e
yo u t h , it was enough just to become part of
a ny highly ranked sector of the Ja p a n e s e
c o m m u n i t y. E n t ry into highly selective uni-
ve rs i t i e s , major industries and powe r f u l
bureaucracies brought with it the promise
of a stable life.
To d ay, in a Japan fully conscious that
m o d e rn i z ation is over and that we have
caught up with the We s t , we turn to our
youth and ask them not for the devotion that
s e rved us so well in the past but for fully
1 Meiji was the throne name of Mitsuhito (1852-
1912), emperor of Japan from 1867 to 1912.
During his reign Japan began a rapid process of
Westernization, industrialization and expansion in
foreign affairs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A tea ceremony class instils inner discipline, serenity and appreciation of harmony, qualities that are highly valued in traditional Japanese culture.
A hard rock concert in Tokyo’s Telecom Centre.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
What’s that he’s writing? An artistic interlude during
a school athletics competition in a Tokyo suburb.
It’s been a hard day’s night. Revellers recuperate
after a Tokyo rock concert.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A weary student at Hanamaki agricultural high school at the end of a long day in the classroom.
Young shoppers in a Tateyama supermarket. 
d e veloped skills and immediately useful
k n ow l e d g e . I think that less than five per
cent of young people have actually regi s-
tered this message from society and are acti-
vely seeking an education that will provide
the necessary training.Whether this per-
centage falls to three or rises to eight is going
to be what makes or breaks Japan in the
future.
The gr e at number of young people who
have not got the message fritter away their
time as slaves to commercialism or fa l l
under the sway of some chari s m atic fa s h i o n .
The problem is that society has not made it
clear enough to them that to lead a full life
they now need specialized skills. So many
e l e m e n t a ry schoolchildren are still locked
into gruelling exam preparation schedules,
but no one is encouraging them to think
about what sort of training they are heading
for or how best to prepare for the future. I
think this is unfair.
My son is nineteen.He is studying phar-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 -The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Happy Birthday Sakura! Yokohama teenager Sakura Nakamura (background) invited a few friends round to celebrate her 16th birthday.
JA PA NESE LITERAT URE ’ S
UNPREDICTA BLE CHIL D
p rising that we so often hear them say i n g
that they don’t know what to do next.
To d ay, so many Japanese have lost confi-
dence in themselves that the young have
become contaminated with it.This is unfor-
t u n at e . At the same time, m a ny consider
t h at the Japanese tradition of indirectness
in communication is no longer functional.
This is not so unfortunate.
From now on, Japanese youth will be
divided between the few who succeed and
the many who fa i l . For the large number
who are bound to fa i l , the future is uncer-
t a i n .To forget this uncert a i n t y, they delude
t h e m s e l ves with video games, m u s i c,
fa s h i o n ,H o l l y wo o d ,s e x , d rugs or cults. I f
we leave them as they are, they will eve n-
tually seek revenge against a society which
did not give them clear advice when it was
n e e d e d . U n e m p l oyment amongst Ja p a n e-
se youth has gone over the 10 per cent mark,
but no adults here, politicians included,
seem to be worried. n
macology at college and later plans to go to
an American or European university to do
advanced work in toxicology. I have taught
him since he was a child that in the future
living a free life will be difficult without a
basis of highly professional know l e d g e .H ow
m a ny Japanese reach the age of twe n t y
without getting any such advice? It’s not sur-
The prolific novelist, essayist and fil m - m a k e r
Ryu Murakami is a leading figure in the new
wave of Japanese literature that emerged in the late
1970s and the 1980s. He was born in 19 52 in Sasebo,
a city dominated by the nearby U.S. Navy base, and
the experience of growing up in the shadow of the
base underlies his views of America and Japan
and forms a major theme of his writing. Described
by another young Japanese novelist, Masahiko
Shimada, as “Japanese literature’s unpredictable
child”, he made a sensational debut as a novelist in
1976 with the semi-autobiogra p h i cal Almost Tra n s-
p a rent Blue, a best-seller which portrayed the lives
of young people immersed in a culture of sex,
drugs and rock n’ roll. Notable among his many
other novels, which have been widely translated, is
the award-winning Coin Lo c ker Babies ( 19 81), the
s t o ry of two infants abandoned by their mothers in
train station lockers. The ambivalence of his fasci-
nation with Western, and particular America n ,
popular culture can be seen in 69 ( 19 87), set in the
midst of Japan’s 1969 student unrest, and also in his
collection of essays American Dre a m ( 1985). Mura-
kami has directed film adaptations of some of his
novels. In 19 97, T i m e magazine named him one of
11 people who would revolutionize Japan. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A group of teenagers take a breather from a game of beach soccer at Enoshima, a popular resort near Tokyo. Soccer is increasingly popular in Japan which, with
Korea, will be co-hosting the World Cup in 2002.
A young passenger on a local train between Sapporo and Otaru gives her friend a beauty tip.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
O P I N I O N
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 9
n
G l o b a l i z ation looks ve ry different when it is seen, not from the capitals of the We s t , bu t
from the cities and villages of the South, where most of humanity live s. Four examples
taken from my own country, Pe ru ,i l l u s t r ate how the paradoxical forces shaping glo-
balization look when seen from the other side.
In October 1999,28 schoolchildren died in Taucamarca,a remote village in the high-
lands of Peru,after drinking water and powdered milk mixed in a vat that had contained
a powerful insecticide. Nobody could read the label on the vat and the children we r e
poisoned.The insecticide in question has been banned in practically every industrialized
nation;its sale continues only in places like my country.
S e c o n d l y, an important annual event recently took place in Cajamarca, in the nort h
of Pe ru . Po t ato gr owe rs gather there to exchange the best seeds they have produced in the
last ye a r. It is an act of pride for communities to share with others seeds that will help
i m p r ove the production of potat o e s. In 1999, t r a n s n ational corp o r ations attended the fes-
tival and are now working to patent the genes of these traditionnal foodstuffs in order to
sell them at profit.
Pe ru ’s macro-economic indicat o rs are excellent. In the offices of investment ban-
k e rs , you will be told that Pe ru is a gr e at investment opport u n i t y.The situation is not so
rosy howe ve r , when considered from the pers p e c t i ve of Pe ru v i a n s. Fifty per cent of the
population have been living below the poverty line for the last ten years.Twenty per cent
of the population are living below the critical pove rty line: their income is insufficient to
pay for even minimal nourishment.Two-thirds of the workforce is unemployed or under-
employed,and between now and 2005,more people will enter the labour market in Peru
than in the whole of the European Union.
A distinguished North A m e rican political scientist, D r. Benjamin Barber, r e c e n t l y
pointed out that in the United States democracy had degenerated into bri n ging one gr o u p
of rascals in for four years,and then throwing them out and replacing them with another
group of rascals for four ye a rs. From the pers p e c t i ve of the South, t h at looks ve ry good!
In a context where rascals manipulate elections and stay in power for fifteen or sixteen
years,I would appreciate the chance to throw them out through peaceful elections every
four years.
T h u s , the complaints of the North are often the aspirations of the South.P r o gress in indus-
trialized nations can be a threat to developing countries.
Ten ye a rs ago, in the euphoria of globalization and the expansion of services and fin a n-
ce that followed the fall of the Berlin Wa l l , I advanced the idea that we were entering a frac-
tured global order. G l o b a l i z ation brings us into contact with one another, but it also streng-
thens profound divisions and fractures in terms of societies and income, and most
i m p o rtantly in our capacity to generate and utilize know l e d g e .O ver the last ten ye a rs ,t h e
concentration of wealth and power has greatly increased both within and between socie-
ties.
There is a real risk of two civilizations emergi n g, with two ways of viewing and relat i n g
to the world:one based on the capacity to generate and utilize knowledge;the other pas-
sively receiving knowledge from abroad and deprived of the ability to modify it.
The world now faces the prospect of this Knowledge Divide becoming an unbri d g e a b l e
a b y s s.We need the intern ational community to return to the basic principles of intern a-
tional co-operation and introduce the idea that a minimum level of science and techno-
l o gical capability, including access to the Intern e t , is an absolute necessity for deve l o-
ping countries and should be the subject of international solidarity.
This can be achieve d . H owe ve r , c o n t r a ry to the situation of 20 ye a rs ago, n at i o n a l
g ove rnments are no longer the major playe rs in the game of science and technology.W h e-
ther we like it or not, the pri vate sector and the intern ational community of scholars must
be invited to the table with gove rnments from the North and South to begin discussing
an agenda for the mobilization of science and technology for deve l o p m e n t. UN E S C O, t h e
only United Nations agency with a mandate for the development of the sciences, has a spe-
cial role to play in the revitalization of intern ational co-operation in this fie l d . n
T HE KNO W L EDGE DI V IDE
Francisco Sagasti
A former chief of stra t e g i c
planning and senior adviser
at the Wo r l d
Bank, Mr Sagasti is director
of the Agenda Pe r u
p r o g ramme at FORO
N a c i o n a l / I n t e r n a c i o n a l ,
an institution which
promotes democra t i c
governance and fosters
dialogue and consensus on
development issues. He is the
author of over 20 published
works, the most recent of
which is D e v e l o p m e n t
C o o p e r a t i o n
in a Fractured Global Order
(with Gonzalo Alcalde, IDRC ,
1999). The present text has
been extracted from his
contribution to a series of
“ 21st C e n t u ry Talks” held at
UNESCO Headquarters in Pa r i s ,
on November 6, 19 9 9 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
P L A N E T
T HE ARAL SE A :
BACK FROM THE BRINK ?
w Sue Lloyd-Roberts and Ethirajan Anbarasan
An ecological disaster area, the shrinking Aral Sea generated a flood of assessment studies but
little follow-up. Humanitarian action is now an urgent priority.
w Correspondent with the BBC, London,
and UNESCO Courier journalist respectively.
n
“The health of women of child-
b e a ring age is steadily deteri o r at i n g
because of the bad quality of the dri n-
king water.There are as many pregnancies
as ever but the women either miscarry or
gi ve birth to stillborn or handicapped
b a b i e s.We have one of the highest infa n t
m o rtality rates in the wo r l d ,” s ays the direc-
tor of the mat e rnity hospital on the edge of
the Aral Sea in the port city of A r a l s k , i n
Kazakhstan.
Behind him, pregnant women lie on
r ows of hospital beds. They have been
brought in to ensure that they get clean
food and water for at least the last tri m e s t e r
of their pregnancies.The eyes of one wo m a n
b e t r ay terr o r. “This is my ninth pregnancy,”
she says, “I have yet to give birth to a live
child and I am frightened.” Similar situa-
tions exist elsewhere in this Central Asian
region.
Man-made
environmental disasters
The wo rsening health and env i r o n-
mental problems of people living in the
Aral Sea basin, which consists of parts of
Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Turk-
menistan and Uzbekistan, are the direct
consequences of man-made env i r o n m e n t a l
d i s a s t e rs in the region—the shrinking of
the sea and pollution of the rivers which
flow into it.
Experts say the disaster has left behind
a 36,000-sq.km sea bed covered with accu-
m u l ated salts, which the wind carries away
and deposits over thousands of square kilo-
metres of cultivated land. Pesticides and
f e rt i l i z e rs have also found their way into
water and irri g ation channels, p o i s o n i n g
food and drinking water affecting the lives
of about five million people.
After the collapse of the Soviet Union
in 1991, i n t e rn ational donor agencies
rushed to the Central Asian region to
assess the environmental impact of the
s h rinking of the Aral Sea and to find way s
of restoring it to its ori ginal leve l . N ow,
almost a decade lat e r , after countless stu-
dies and reports have been wri t t e n ,e x p e rt s
s ay that restoration is impossible and
e f f o rts should now focus on avoiding a
h u m a n i t a rian cat a s t r o p h e .
Rescue missions
The Aral Sea,covering an area the size
of Lithuania, s t a rted receding in the
1960s after Soviet state planners diverted
its water sources,the Amu Dar’ya and the
Syr Dar’ya rivers, to irrigate cotton and
other crops.
From 1960 to 1990, the area of irri g a-
ted land in Central Asia increased from 3.5
million hectares to 7.5 million. Cotton pro-
duction soared, making the region the
wo r l d ’s fourth largest producer. But by the
1980s the annual flow of fresh water into
the Aral was barely one-tenth of the 1950
s u p p l y. The salinity level increased, d e s-
t r oying the sea’s flora and fa u n a . T h e
fishing industry suffered; all but two of the
30 species once found in the sea died out.
With no other means of water supply,
the sea started to recede, eventually losing
half of its former area and a third of its
volume. In 1989, it divided into a smaller
northern sea and a larger southern one.
The two main fishing ports, Moynaq in
Uzbekistan and Aralsk in Kazakhstan
were left high and dry, and fishing com-
munities found themselves 100 kilo-
metres or more away from the shore.
Today, drinking water in the region
contains four times more salt per litre
than the limit recommended by the World
Health Organizat i o n . This has caused
increases in kidney disease, diarrhoea and
other serious ailments. Tuberculosis has
reached epidemic proportions. In some
towns there are an estimated 400 cases
out of a population of 100,000.
The people of this once-fertile region
Kazakhstan
Uzbekistan
Turkmenistan
Afghanistan
Tajikistan
China
Kyrgyzstan
Iran
Caspian Sea
Aral Sea
TEHRÀN
ASHGABAT
ALMATY
DUSHANBE
TASHKENT
Samarkand
Aralsk
Urlsk
BISHKEK
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
s ays Antonius Lennarts of the World Bank,
in A l m aty (Kazakhstan).“There have been
lots of donor activity and promises but no
follow-up, and long delays because of the
huge funds involved.The money available
to solve a problem of this magnitude simply
isn’t available.”
In view of the gr avity of the situat i o n ,
the Nobel Prize-winning medical relief orga-
n i z ation Médicins Sans Frontières (MSF),
which is more usually associated with the
wo r l d ’s hot spots, has launched an emer-
g e n cy programme to save the people of Cen-
tral Asia from what it calls in a recent report ,
“possibly the wo r l d ’s gr e atest env i r o n m e n t a l
disaster and human tragedy.”
“ To dat e ,” the MSF report say s ,“ m i l l i o n s
of dollars wo rth of assessments have been
made of the Aral Sea regi o n , resulting in ve ry
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
High and dry. Rusting fishing boats dot the desolate landscape at Moynaq (Uzbekistan), once a fishing port, now far away from the sea.
h ave been calling for help since Soviet times,
but after their countries became indepen-
dent at the end of 1991 their cries became
more urgent than eve r. I n t e rn ational agen-
cies including the World Bank,the United
N ations Development Progr a m m e
( U N D P ) ,U n e s c o,and the European Union
rushed to the region to offer help. I n i t i at i ve s
like the Aral Sea Basin Programme (ASBP),
the Intern ational Aral Sea Rehabilitat i o n
Fund (IFAS),and the Interstate Commis-
sion for Water Co-ordination (ICWC) we r e
launched to assess the problems and find
s o l u t i o n s. The activities they proposed
brought high hopes to the people of the
Aral Basin, who thought their problems
would eventually be solved.
So why after nearly a decade of rescue
missions does the Aral Sea remain on the
c ritical list of world environmental cat a-
strophes? According to expert s , it is a classic
case of too many players entering too late,
with too few resources but in many cases
with a huge stock of vested interests that
are not necessarily consistent with
environmental protection.
The intern ational aid agencies soon
gauged the enormity of the problem and
realized that the funds allotted were not
enough to rectify a disaster of this magnitude.
“Of course people here have been disap-
pointed by the international community,”
little direct humanitarian action in the area.”
MSF has some justific ation for lamenting
t h at so much has been spent in the last eight
ye a rs on talking about the Aral Sea and so
little has actually been done.But why has this
happened? “It could be because the problem
is just so huge and eve ryone wants to help bu t
m a ny agencies just don’t know where to
s t a rt ,” explains Barbara Britton of the United
S t ates A g e n cy for Intern ational Deve l o p-
ment (USAID), the biggest donor agency
i nvo l ve d , in Ta s h k e n t .
There is another major hurdle as well as
lack of funds—lack of co-ordination among
the five Aral basin nations. “They started
competing with each other to get interna-
tional aid rather than co-operating in solving
the problem,” says Professor J. A.Allan, a
water resources specialist at the Unive rs i t y
of London.
In the absence of the kind of federal
authority that existed in Soviet times, the
five states set up the Intern ational Aral Sea
R e h a b i l i t ation Fund (IFAS) in 1993 in
order to co-ordinate water and agri c u l t u r a l
projects. In 1995, their leaders attended a
UN-sponsored meeting in Nukus (Uzbe-
k i s t a n ) , which concluded with a resoun-
ding declaration saying they would co-ope-
r ate to resolve the human and
e nvironmental consequences of the A r a l
Sea cri s i s. B u t , according to Bri t t o n ,d i s t ru s t
Drinking water 
in the region 
c o n tains four times 
more salt per litre than 
the limit recommended 
by the World Health
O r g a n i z a t i o n
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
P L A N E T
The Aral Sea region has one of the world’s highest rates of malformed or handicapped children.
between the states continued.
For example, when the Uzbekis were
given the responsibility for water manage-
m e n t , they were accused of producing a
p r o gramme that would irri g ate Uzbekistan
and not other countries.Then the Uzbekis
accused Kazakhstan of draining water away
from its southern neighbour by constru c t i n g
a dam across the northern Aral Sea.
Anatoly Buranov, technical director of
the Executive Committee of IFAS,admits
t h at the states could have done better.“ Pa rt
of the problem is that we were all excited by
independence and after so many years of
enforced togetherness we enjoyed the cen-
t rifugal forces which the collapse of the
S oviet Union allowed us. N ow, h owe ve r ,
we are realizing the importance of co-
operation.”
Ironically, the slow and delayed action
from outsiders and their governments has
had a positive effect on one Aral basin
country. Frustrated by years of unfulfilled
promises, the people of Kazakhstan raised
an astonishing $2.5 million and built them-
s e l ves a sand dam 14 kilometres long and 30
metres wide, c r e ating a lake in the nort h e rn
Aral Sea,close to Aralsk.
Kazakh officials say they also made
e f f o rts to draw less water from the Syr
Dar’ya than in the past and that the dam
contained the increased inflow into the
s m a l l e r ,n o rt h e rn A r a l .As a result, the wat e r
level rose by three metres for the first time
in 30 ye a rs , b ri n ging back gr e e n e ry and
birdlife to the desertified area.
As a result of increased inflow of fresh
water the salinity level in the nort h e rn A r a l
f e l l , reviving the hopes of the fishing
industry. Above all,the dam brought hope
to the people of A r a l s k , “a commodity
which until recently has been as scarce
around here as water,” says Aitbai Kuser-
baliv, the city’s mayor.
U n f o rt u n at e l y, Kuserbaliv explains, t h e
dam keeps breaking as a result of rainfall
and increased inflow into the sea.In 1998,
from three to five kilometres of the dam
were washed away and water flowed into the
s o u t h e rn A r a l . Officials say the project
cannot be sustained unless they get $15
million funding they have asked from the
World Bank to build a permanent stru c t u r e .
“I wrote to them several months ago and
they still have not got back to me,” s ays the
mayor.
With the survival of the reclaimed sea,
the efforts of dozens of dam builders and
the livelihoods of several hundred fis h e rm e n
at stake, the World Bank seems likely to
come up with some funds.“ We have agr e e d
that it is a highly necessary dam and the
money will be fort h c o m i n g,” s ays A n t o n i u s
Lennarts of the World Bank.
Even if the World Bank funds this pro-
ject it will save only the smaller part of the
Aral Sea. To maintain the present wat e r
l e vel of the bigger southern part , at least 20
cubic kilometres of water per year are
r e q u i r e d . Some grandiose schemes have
been proposed,including diverting waters
from Siberian rivers or from the Caspian
Sea, over 2,400 km and 500 km away res-
p e c t i ve l y, projects which could cost up to $8
billion each.The Central Asian countries do
not have the resources to embark on such
costly undertakings.
Another option would be to allow more
water to flow into the Amu Dar’ya river,
which means that agricultural patterns in
With the prospects 
of saving the sea remote,
experts and locals 
now seem to be 
turning their attention 
to relieving 
the social disaster
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 13
P L A N E T
At a children’s hospital in Nukus (Uzbekistan), a baby is treated for a serious pelvic malformation.
the regi o n , especially in Uzbekistan, t h r o u g h
which most of the river flows, would need
to be changed.This proposal could invite
stiff resistance from fa rm e rs in Uzbekistan
who heavily depend on the river for irriga-
t i o n . “It is a ve ry uneasy situation for them.
You cannot stop agri c u l t u r e . People wo u l d
lose their live l i h o o d ,” s ays Prof Ja n o s
Bogardi, senior water resources expert at
UNESCO.
The first priority:
saving people’s lives
There is no doubt that it would take
billions of dollars and decades to change the
a gricultural pat t e rn by introducing new
technology and less water consuming
p l a n t s. It is highly unlikely that Uzbekistan,
the second largest cotton exporter in the
world, would agree to shift from its prime
cash crop.
With the prospects of saving the sea
remote,experts and locals now seem to be
t u rning their attention to relieving the social
disaster. If present conditions persist,then
the southern part of the Aral is likely to
disappear in the next 25 ye a rs.The pri o ri t y
should be saving the lives of the people,
s ays Ve fa Moustafa e v, a UN E S C O wat e r
resources expert.
After a decade of research and assess-
FACT FIL E
Uzbekistan
Capital: Tashkent
Area: 447,000 sq km
Population: 23.7 million
Adult literacy rate: 99%
GNP per capita: $870
GNP per capita annual decline (1988-98): 2.1%
Life expectancy at birth (years): 69
Infant mortality (per 1,000 live births): 24
Kazakhstan
Area: 2,717,300 sq km
Capital: Astana (former capital Almaty)
Population: 15.7 million
Adult literacy rate: 99%
GNP per capita: $1,310
GNP per capita annual decline (1988-98): 6.7%
Life expectancy at birth (years): 65
Infant mortality rate (per 1,000 live births): 24
Source: World Bank statistics, 1999
ment report s , the intern ational agencies
h ave now started implementing some of
their projects to help the Aral basin popu-
lation, mainly by providing clean drinking
water and better health care facilities.The
World Bank has financed a project to esta-
blish 25 stations to monitor drinking wat e r
quality across the Central Asian regi o n .
The Bank also plans to fund projects to
i m p r ove agricultural practices which
consume a lot of fresh water.
E x p e rts say that the region may require
an estimated $20 billion for much-needed
d e velopment and environmental activities,
mainly to modernize agri c u l t u r e , to reduce
river pollution and provide clean drinking
wat e r.At present, the cash-strapped Central
Asian countries are in no position to raise
such funds on their own.
But the region is not without hope as fa r
as its natural resources are concern e d .W i t h
their enormous gas and oil reserves the
Central Asian states would be among the
major players in the global power sector in
the coming years. However, it is far from
clear what the consequences of oil and gas
exploitation would be for the Aral Sea.
“There is still lots of hope in the regi o n .
But the countries need to co-ordinate their
efforts,” says Bogardi. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Discipline, order and commitment are values that Glenwood School in Illinois (USA) seeks to inculcate in its pupils, many of whom come
from troubled backgrounds. Below, 14 boys being punished in a corridor.
d a ry school teachers in both pri vate and stat e
s e c t o rs are being confronted with examples
of bad behaviour—the destruction of school
equipment or furn i t u r e ,p u p i l s ’ lack of res-
pect for each other or for adults—which
impede normal school routine.
B e rnard Charlot, professor of educat i o n
at the Unive rsity of St. D e n i s , near Pa ri s ,
s ays there are four kinds of misbehav i o u r.
F i rs t , real violence, i nvolving “ p hy s i c a l
attacks or serious injury, which would be
punished in a court of law.”Then there is
u n ru l i n e s s , “a disrespect for school ru l e s ,”
and ru d e n e s s , “breaches of good manners ,
like slamming a door in the face of a teacher
or fellow pupil.”The fourth kind of indis-
cipline—just as seri o u s , he says—is “ s o m e-
times ostentatious indifference by pupils
which is increasingly stressful for teachers.”
14 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
n
M e r l o,A r g e n t i n a :“A 13-year-old wo u n-
ded by a bullet at school.” S p ri n g fie l d ,
United Stat e s :“One dead and 30 wo u n-
ded in a shooting.” K o b e , Ja p a n :“A school-
child decapitated by a 14-ye a r - o l d .”
In the past few ye a rs , k i l l i n g s ,p hy s i c a l
at t a c k s , r o b b e ri e s , attempted arson and
fights between children that end in tragedy
h ave become headline news.With the appea-
rance of security guards, police checks and
metal detectors , the most “ d i f fic u l t ”s c h o o l s
h ave turned into armed camps before the
incredulous eyes of the public and bu rn e d
out teachers.
But school violence is not just a problem
of knive s , baseball bats and marijuana in the
c l a s s r o o m .D ay after day pri m a ry and secon-
w UNESCO Courier journalist
UNRULY CLASSROOMS
Charlot cites the cases of pupils who say
they ought not to be punished for absen-
teeism because “since they aren’t there they
d o n ’t do anybody any harm ” or those who
sit right at the back of the classroom doing
w h at they like and when asked to take part
in the lesson say “But sir, we aren’t bothe-
ring yo u .”
Visiting a school staff room and asking
the teachers about their pupils means lis-
tening to a litany of complaints about dis-
r e s p e c t , insults and vandalism and realizing
w h at little back-up teachers have to help
them keep order.
Paloma Garri d o, who teaches transla-
tion at a pri vate unive rsity in Madri d ,l i s t s
d i s c i p l i n a ry problems such as unpunctuali-
t y,yaw n i n g, mobile phones that ring in class
and “an insolent attitude towards the tea-
w Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Teachers are not getting enough training and back-up to help them with worsening
behaviour in schools
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
c h e r. Because I’m yo u n g, they think they can
t r e at me like one of their pals,” s ays 31-ye a r -
old Garri d o,who has seven ye a rs ’e x p e ri e n c e
teaching children between 14 and 20. S h e
s ays the teacher must set the rules from the
ve ry first day and “ k n ow how to keep a dis-
tance so they know yo u ’re the teacher and
not just a chum.”
In Mexico or Italy, in Germ a ny or India,
teacher training, when it exists, focuses on
the curri c u l u m . No one says that lessons will
be gi ven to classes which are often too big
and comprise pupils who, as in Spain for
e x a m p l e ,m ay witness during the school ye a r
an average of 8,000 crimes and 200,000 acts
of violence on television.
But Alfredo Furlán, an Argentine edu-
c at i o n i s t ,s ays that “although the subjects of
discipline and indiscipline are ve ry rarely if
e ver tackled during teacher training, t r a i n e e
t e a c h e rs soon learn their strat e gic impor-
t a n c e .Keeping order in the classroom is the
first professional skill they will have to
d e m o n s t r ate because if they don’t ,c o n fli c t s
i m m e d i ately arise which have wo rse conse-
quences than failing to get good academic
results from their pupils.”
The causes of bad behaviour are extre-
mely dive rs e . Some studies make a distinc-
tion between “ s t ru c t u r a l ” fa c t o rs such as the
inevitable conflicts between teenagers and
adults who try to educate them and fa c t o rs
t h at are more specific to the age we live in.
G u s t avo Calotti, who teaches languages
at a secondary school in Mayotte in the
Comoros Islands and has 15 ye a rs ’t e a c h i n g
e x p e ri e n c e , s ays today ’s schoolchildren 
are “much more badly-behave d ” than their
we r e n ’t allowed in or were expelled, a n d
classrooms were quiet because the discipli-
ne was strict enough to ensure that pupils 
d i d n ’t break the ru l e s.”
Charlot admits that “these days yo u ’r e
getting children in school whose parents or
elder siblings have had no secondary edu-
c at i o n , and the moment the school system
s t a rts taking in a new cat e g o ry of children,
some of the unspoken rules don’t work any
m o r e . Pupils don’t turn up with the ‘ p r e -
s o c i a l i z at i o n ’ they used to get and this show s
up in their behav i o u r.”
A social microcosm
A school is not like a lone soap bu b b l e
s e p a r ate from society, but a place where
social problems are seen in a microcosm—
problems like lack of communicat i o n ,p ove r-
t y, m a r gi n a l i z at i o n , intolerance and loss of
va l u e s. All of them lead to what A n t o n i o
García Corr e a ,professor of educational psy-
chology at the Unive rsity of Murcia, i n
S p a i n , calls “emotional illiteracy ” . E d u-
c ational systems, he say s ,“ h ave been more
c o n c e rned about filling heads with know-
ledge rather than teaching children to think
and reason.A lot of research has been done
on children’s academic results and how to
i m p r ove them, but we have been less
c o n c e rned about their social and emotional
d e ve l o p m e n t .The result is that pupils know
more but behave wo rs e .”
Changes in educational systems also
h ave a lot to do with children’s behav i o u r.
“ We ’ ve switched suddenly from a system
based on prohibitions and punishment to
one based on sharing where the most impor-
p r e d e c e s s o rs 10 or 15 ye a rs ago. He thinks
one reason is that “ young people look at 
the adult world and see what ’s in store for
them when they leave school—a strong pos-
sibility being that they either wo n ’t find a 
job or else end up in one that is badly paid.
They gradually lose the desire to make an
e f f o rt or feel the sat i s faction of completing
a job of wo r k . Add to that the widespread
belief that only those with a winner’s 
mentality will make it and you get a kind
of don’t-care at t t i t u d e , an apat hy which is
r e flected in their behav i o u r.”
UN E S C O e d u c ation specialist A l e x a n d r a
Draxler does not see bad behaviour as a
plague or isolated phenomenon but as “a by-
product of the tremendous advance in indi-
vidual rights and the broad democrat i z at i o n
of public life over the last 25 to 30 ye a rs.”
Before that , she say s , “social problems stop-
ped at the school gat e s.The situation wa s
s o rted out beforehand: violent pupils just
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
SUPP ORT SYSTEMS FOR TEACHERS
Experts, businesses and institutions in severa l
countries have come up with ideas to help edu-
cational authorities to deal with bad behaviour in
schools. In southern Spain, schools can join the
S AVE (Seville against school violence) project set
up in 1996 by Rosario Ortega Ruiz of Seville Uni-
v e r s i ty’s department of educational and deve-
lopmental psychology. The project seeks to pre-
vent outbreaks of violence between children by
creating a friendly school atmosphere and impro-
ving interpersonal relations.
Using questionnaires and other forms of
consultation, a group of experts study a specific
school situation and make a detailed report on it.
If the teachers decide to join the project after rea-
ding the report, SAVE experts build a support sys-
tem for their work in the classroom and set up a
task force to prevent violence. With European and
Spanish funding, Ortega’s team has also produ-
ced a teaching kit called “Stepping stones to friend-
ly schools,” which has been distributed in all state
schools in Spain’s Andalusia province.
In the U.S. state of Georgia, a law passed in
April 1999 requires its 6,500 schools to “imple-
ment a character education programme for all
g rade levels” as from the 20 0 0 - 20 01 school year.
To help apply the law, the state education depart-
ment recently set up a Character Education Cen-
ter, which encourages children to develop quali-
ties including courage, patriotism, citizenship,
h o n e s ty, fairness, respect for others, kindness, co-
o p e ration, self-respect, self-control, courtesy, com-
passion, tolerance, diligence, generosity, punc-
t u a l i ty, cleanliness and respect for the
e n v i r o n m e n t .
Jason We tzel, the center’s associate director,
hopes “the Georgia model”, as it is now becoming
k n own in the national media, will “reduce vio-
lence, increase academic performance and gene-
rally create a better and more civil community. ”
In France, the Gaspar network (Aca d e m i c
Group for Support and Prevention for Problem
Teenagers), set up by the education authorities in
Lille in 1989, has so far been active in about 150
schools in northern France. Its chief work is pre-
vention, and one of its salient features is the invol-
vement of student volunteers alongside teachers
and administra t o r s .
In Japan, the Education for Compassion (Koko-
ro no kyoriku) programme, sponsored by the
m i n i s t ry of education, aims to revive civic values
and a sense of responsibility among Japanese chil-
dren, as well as defending and encouraging the
spiritual and moral aspects of educa t i o n .
In a number of places, such work is being done
further outside the mainstream, and special
schools have been created for children with serious
b e h a v i o u ral problems. Such schools are really
places of last resort, though most experts disap-
prove of this kind of segregation—nearly always
t e m p o ra ry—of problem pupils.
Ortega Ruiz thinks keeping problem children
away from others is not a good idea because “free
state education should deal with them in their
social context and face up to the real-life problems.
In the worst cases, where such children need spe-
cial re-education, this can be done in their nor-
mal surroundings, using whatever individual
approaches are needed.” n
“Although the subjects
of discipline and indiscipline
are very rarely if ever ta c k l e d
during teacher training, tra i n e e
teachers soon learn their
s t rategic importance. Ke e p i n g
order in the classroom is
the first professional skill they
will have to demonstra t e . ”
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
tant thing is agreement between eve ryo n e
i nvo l ved in the education system and we ’ ve
not yet learned how to put that new system
into practice,” s ays Nora Rais, who teaches
l i t e r ature in Pat a g o n i a ,A r g e n t i n a . She say s
t h at “ r e t u rning to an authori t a rian regi m e
i sn ’t the way to fix the situat i o n . E n c o u r-
a ging dialogue, making compromises and
adopting values is one possible way.Te a-
c h e rs must act as mediat o rs , but we must
have the resources to do that.”
The parents’ role
The schoolteacher is no longer someo-
ne held up as an example to others , and edu-
c ation is no longer a guarantee of social
a d va n c e m e n t . But the school remains a vital
i n s t i t u t i o n , along with the fa m i l y, for encou-
r a ging and instilling human values in yo u n g
people. Many professionals blame parents
for not pulling their weight here by being
often only interested in their children’s aca-
demic results and getting them into the next
school year.
“ Parents are spending less and less time
on their children’s educat i o n ,” s ays Calot-
t i . “They think it’s enough to pack them off
to school and they don’t make a distinction
b e t ween the academic education we gi ve
children and their education as members of
society, which has to begin at home.”
But teachers are less and less alone in
the face of danger. A glance at the educa-
tional plans of several countries shows that
tackling these problems is a pri o rity in desi-
gning policies for inve s t i g at i n g, h a n d l i n g
and preventing bad behaviour (see box ) .
The responses are starting to appear on the
h o ri z o n , although eve ryone agrees that the
more resources a school has, the fewer pro-
blems it will fa c e . Boosting resources will
a l l ow more teachers to be hired, enable class
sizes to be reduced, good administration to
be established and the number of teaching
aids and non-teaching staff to be increased,
introducing key figures such as psycholo-
gists and social workers into the school.
An educational priority
The one thing teachers increasingly
a gree on—and they, after all, are the people
who work day after day in the classroom—
is that the answer is not to punish or expel
pupils or to send them to the head teacher’s
o f fic e . Civil behaviour and sociability are
not values that can be instilled ove rn i g h t .
They are the fruit of a daily effort by eve-
ryone—the authori t i e s , the educat i o n a l
c o m m u n i t y, the parents and of course the
most important people, the children.T h e
rounded academic and social education of
future generations depends on recognizing
t h i s.” n
+ …
Antonio García Correa (1998) Una aula pacífica
para una cultura de paz (“A peaceful classroom for
a culture of peace”). Electrónica Interuniversitaria
de Formación del Profesorado, 1 (1). Available at
<http://www.uva.es/aufop/publica/revelfop/v1n1a
gc.htm>
The control of discipline in schools is the main
theme of Prospects, the quarterly review of compa-
rative education (vol. XXVIII, no. 4, December
1998) published by UNESCO’s International Bureau
of Education.
SAVE Programme: University of Seville, faculty of
psychology, department of educational and deve-
lopmental psychology, San Francisco Javier, s/n
41005 Sevilla, Spain. Email: <ortega@cica.es>
”In the past few years fights between children that end in tragedy have become headline news.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 17
FOCUS
International Year 2000:
Peace is in our hands
C o n t e n t s
1 8 The fabric of peace
René Zapata
2 0 A new arena for individual initiative
Interview with Zaki Laïdi
2 1 The South’s fragile states
Mohamed Sahnoun
2 2 C o l o m b i a :
• Videos to dispel despair
Carlos Mauricio Ve g a
2 3 C h i n a :
• Stars through the ra i n
Katherine A r m s
2 4 B ra z i l :
• The houses that Francisco built
Maiá Menezes
2 6 M a l i : a fli c kering fla m e
Sophie Boukhari
2 9 I n d i a :G a n d h i ’s disputed heritage
Darryl D’Monte
3 1 Jubilee 2000: c h u rches spread 
the word on debt
Madeleine Bunting
3 3 S a n t ’ E g i d i o ’s diplomacy of friendship
Mario Giro
3 5 Revolt against violence
Interview with Manuel Castells
The United Nations General Assembly has
decided to voice the univers a l
a s p i ration for peace, an end to war and
to all kinds of violence spawned by injustice
and oppre s s i o n . On UN E S C O’s initiative it has
p roclaimed the year 2000 as the
International Year for the Culture of Pe a c e.
This decision also salutes the
participation of “civil society”. Today a host
of individuals and movements are bre a k i n g
down traditional political fra m e w o r k s
t h rough their contributions to community
l i f e, in different ways and on different scales,
on their own doorstep or at the planetary
l e v e l . As French political scientist Zaki Laïdi
and Spanish sociologist Manuel Castells
point out in this issue, they are either short-
c i rcuiting or joining forces with governments
which have hitherto
called the tune.
Peace is in our hands. It is within reach of
all of us, if we can show the spirit and
p e rs e v e rance of some of the people
p o r t rayed in this Focus section: a Chinese
mother who opened her country’s firs t
school for autistic childre n ; a man who
m a kes videos to combat violence in Bogotá’s
biggest shantytown; a scientist who has
opened his labora t o r y
to the slum-dwellers of Rio de Ja n e i ro to
help them build houses for themselves.
On a wider stage, a number of
movements inspired by these same humanist
values have devised original methods of
achieving their goals. Among them are the
Jubilee 2000 campaign to cancel T h i rd Wo r l d
debt and the Sant’Egidio Christian
Community in Rome, which has acted as a
mediator in several wars.
M e a n w h i l e, the struggle of Indian
f a r m e rs against genetically modifie d
o rganisms shows that a movement
originating in civil society may
be motivated by the best intentions without
fully belonging to this culture of peace.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
w Head of the co-ordination
unit of UNESCO’s transdisciplinary
project “Towards a Culture of
Peace”.
F rom time immemorial,peace—in the sense of
peace between nations and peace within socie-
ties—has been exclusively based on the inter-
p l ay between justice and force, a relationship which
is at once conflictual and consensual.
Over 300 years ago, this idea was expressed by
the French philosopher Blaise Pascal when he wrote:
“Since force cannot be made to submit to justice,
men have made it just to submit to force; and since
justice cannot be fort i fie d , we justify force so that
justice and force go together and we have peace,
which is the sovereign good.”
H i s t o ry shows that peace has been and conti-
nues to be primarily an affair of state and of states,
based on the use of force—in other words,ultima-
t e l y, on recourse to wa r.This force is legitimized by
highly dive rse and in some cases contradictory
concepts of justice.
In our time, h owe ve r , the nature of war has chan-
g e d . Most often it is no longer waged between stat e s
but within their borders. C o n flicts within states have
become so widespread that wa r fare has never been
so rife—and in many cases so unnoticed—as it is
t o d ay. F u rt h e rm o r e , violence exists in all our socie-
ties in one form or another, e ven if it does not neces-
s a rily erupt into armed confrontat i o n . It takes many
f o rm s , and may even be considered the norm . I t s
most glaring symptom is the gr owth of inequalities
and the social exclusion to which this gi ves ri s e .
Societies torn to the point of disintegr ation by civil
war or violence are societies whose regulat o ry
mechanisms—the bodies which exist to settle
conflicts—are warped or paralyzed.
Some might say that this gloomy analysis heralds
a future in which war and violence will inevitably
prevail.The fact is,however,that these three deve-
lopments—the changing nature of wa r , the prolife-
r ation of different forms of violence and the we a-
kening of mediat o ry mechanisms, a process
a c c e l e r ated by globalization and the inform at i o n
r e vo l u t i o n — c r e ate a new arena in which a culture
of peace can emerge. And the prime mover in this
culture of peace will no longer be the state but the
i n d i v i d u a l , in other words each and eve ry one of us.
For surely the road to peace must start within
o u rs e l ves—in va l u e s ,b e h aviour and attitudes which
can foster a sense of community that is today threa-
t e n e d .Where else can the foundations of peace be
built but in our daily live s , through willingness to
listen and talk things through with others on equal
terms within the framework of a caring society?
The only obstacles to this enterp rise are those
we create ours e l ve s , because of ignorance or fa n a-
ticism or because of the selfishness that today we
are all too often asked to regard as the hallmark of
human identity.This approach requires more than
The fabric of peace
w René Zapata
In a world pervaded with violence, the struggle for peace must begin in everyday life
The quickest wa y
of ending a war 
is to lose it.
G e o rge Orwell, British author
( 1 9 0 3 - 1 9 5 0 ) Seattle, December 1999.A demonstration against the World Trade Organization’s new round of negotiations.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 19
International Year 2000: peace is in our hands
Each person can 
help build a culture of
peace and 
non-violence by living
in each moment,
joyfully 
and thankfully in deep
consciousness of the
sacredness 
of our own lives, t h e
lives of all beings, a n d
c r e a t i o n .
M a i read Corrigan Maguire,
Nobel Peace Laureate 1976,
social worker in Northern
I reland (1944-)
Manifesto 2000
A group of Nobel Peace Laureates have written Manifesto 2000, which is open to signature by people all over the
world. The goal is to present 100 million signatures to the United Nations General Assembly in September 2000. The
Manifesto’s full text is as follows:
Recognizing my share of responsibility for the future of humanity, especially for the children of today and tomorrow,
I pledge in my daily life, in my family, my work,my community, my country and my region,to:
— respect the life and dignity of every person without discrimination or prejudice;
— practice active non-violence, rejecting violence in all its forms: physical, sexual, psychological, economical and
social,in particular towards the most deprived and vulnerable such as children and adolescents;
— share my time and material resources in a spirit of generosity to put an end to exclusion,injustice and political and
economic oppression;
— defend freedom of expression and cultural diversity, giving preference always to dialogue and listening without
engaging in fanaticism,defamation and the rejection of others;
— promote consumer behaviour that is responsible and development practices that respect all forms of life and pre-
serve the balance of nature on the planet;
— contribute to the development of my community, with the full participation of women and respect for democratic
principles, in order to create together new forms of solidarity.
You can sign Manifesto 2000 on the Internet:www.unesco.org/manifesto2000,or send a signed copy to:International
Year for the Culture of Peace, UNESCO, 7 Place de Fontenoy, F-75352 Paris 07 SP, France 
good intentions or the occasional act of generosity.
The capacity to talk and listen to others and be
r e c e p t i ve to their needs can pave the way to peace
through an acceptance of a shared responsibility
t owards other people as well as towards ours e l ve s.
The mainspring of the culture of peace is making
common cause with others in peace-building pro-
jects in eve ry d ay life, in what e ver area of society we
may be involved.
A participatory process
This message is not new.The culture of peace
is a fa b ric that has been woven for generations in all
s o c i e t i e s , though its practices are not necessari l y
d e n o m i n ated by that specific title. In some places
it may be known as tolerance, non-violence or jus-
t i c e . In others , as harm o ny, s o l i d a rity or conv i v i a l i-
t y.All over the world it has its defenders , some wo r-
king in obscuri t y, o t h e rs in the spotlight of public
l i f e . But its scope would be much smaller today had
it not been gi ven expression in the disinterested acts
of thousands of anonymous men and wo m e n
capable of listening to others , talking to them and
acting with them and on their behalf.
The concept of “a culture of peace”has clearly
not appeared from now h e r e . But to have a single
expression to describe a multitude of ethical and
practical initiat i ves may help to highlight their com-
mon purpose,make them more widely known and
b ring them together. It may sharpen the impact and
focus of movements that are active in a vast range
of fields and settings.
The importance of the culture of peace has now
been recognized by the world community. O n
N ovember 20, 1 9 9 7 , the General Assembly of the
United Nations unanimously proclaimed the ye a r
2000 as the Intern ational Year for the Culture of
Pe a c e . In taking this step, UN Member States accept
their own limitations and their urgent need for a
concept of peace that will be a part i c i p at o ry process
to which all members of society can contri bu t e ,
no matter how humble their circumstances.
The culture of peace is intended to be a rallying
point that transcends the treaties and agr e e m e n t s
that have so often been given short shrift by histo-
ry. It will become a real and living culture if we take
its tenets to heart and shape a common future in
our words and deeds.
UN E S C O’s role as the seedbed of the culture of
peace is inscribed in the opening words of its Consti-
tution:“Since wars begin in the minds of men it is
in the minds of men that the defences of peace must
be constru c t e d .”The text goes on to say “ t h at a
peace based exclusively upon the political and 
economic arrangements of gove rnments would not
be a peace which could secure the unanimous,
lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the
wo r l d , and that the peace must therefore be foun-
d e d , if it is not to fa i l ,upon the intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.”
One of the chief architects of UN E S C O’s Consti-
t u t i o n , the A m e rican poet Archibald MacLeish, u s e d
the following eloquent words when he addressed
UNESCO’s first General Conference in 1946:“The
peace to which the Constitution refers… is a condi-
tion of mutual confidence,
h a rm o ny of purp o s e , and co-ordination of activi-
ties in which free men and women can live a 
satisfactory life.” n
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
A new are n a
for individual i n i t i a t i v e
Zaki Laïdi* believes that politics today revolves round three unequal poles: the state
(slimmed down but still alive and kicking), the market and civil society
There is a lot of talk about the weakening of the
state’s role in national and international life.
What exactly is the situation?
In the last twenty years or so, the state’s regulatory
p owe rs have declined.This decline began in the eco-
nomic fie l d ,with the 1973 world oil crisis in the ri c h
c o u n t ri e s , which noticed that their economies no
longer automatically responded to kick-start mea-
sures imposed from above. It was then that people
s aw how far the Keynesian model of economics had
broken down.
Three things happened in the 1980s to speed
up this process.The first was ideologi c a l . It was asso-
ciated with the advent of new governments in Bri-
tain and the United States which were strongly
opposed to state interve n t i o n .These gove rn m e n t s
f u rther discredited the stat e ’s role as a social and
economic regulat o r. S e c o n d l y, in the mid-1980s,
the deregulation of financial markets and the free
m ovement of capital began.This was a major tur-
ning point.T h i r d l y, the collapse of the Berlin Wa l l
rubbished the ideology of socialism and socialist
policies around the world.
How have these changes been transmitted to the
South?
Mainly through the structural adjustment pro-
grammes of the Intern ational Monetary Fund
(IMF) and the World Bank, b e ginning in the 1980s.
This process had mixed results, depending on the
c o u n t ry invo l ve d . But the pressure of stru c t u r a l
adjustment was ve ry strong until the 1997-98 A s i a n
economic cri s i s , when we saw the effects of exces-
s i vely rapid and poorly-organized economic 
liberalization.
Is there a link between the reduction of govern-
ment economic regulation and the emergence of
civil society?
Yes and no.There is no automatic relat i o n s h i p. I n
most countries of the South and the East where eco-
nomic pri vat i z ation has been put into effect, yo u
can usually see that traditional elites have jumped
on the bandwagon and taken control of the
resources made available by pri vat i z at i o n .This is
w hy there is more talk about the pri vat i z ation of the
s t ate rather than about the pri vat i z ation of the eco-
nomy. So we must avoid being overly simplistic.
At the same time, the loss of confidence in the
s t at e , its diminishing redistri bu t o ry functions and its
increasing ineffectiveness have spurred the members
of society to take action and to abandon their 
deference to the stat e . In human rights and the env i-
r o n m e n t , for example, NGOs have triggered new 
i n i t i at i ves that gove rnments have been forced to act
o n .
Fragments of a worldwide public awareness are
n ow having their say. I t ’s impossible to hold a wo r l d
conference about anything these days without 
i nvolving NGOs, which are a kind of indicator of
the democratization of world relations.
Why is this?
Because they encourage and fa c i l i t ate the wo r l d ’s
p l u r a l i z at i o n .S t ates have lost their monopoly of vio-
lence and of authori t at i ve declarat i o n .We ’re seeing
an extraordinary and far-reaching reconfig u r at i o n
of power into three components—the stat e , the mar-
ket and civil society.
But bewa r e . Here too we must avoid stereotypes
and utopianism.These playe rs are not necessari l y
opposed or in contradiction with each other. It is
too abstract simply to say that “civil societies” a r e
in process of taking powe r. Something far more
complex is going on.There is now a stronger and
more complicated interaction between the three
components of power I’ve been talking about. A n d
they aren’t very equal components either.
A l s o, we mustn’t forget that gove rnments can
be tempted to outsource their functions and get
va rious groups or the pri vate sector to take over res-
ponsibilities they formerly assumed.Yo u ’re not going
to understand much about what ’s happening if yo u
look at it in terms of a zero-sum game.
What role do you think civil society will play in
the future?
As I said, I think we ’re moving more and more
t owards a kind of tri p a rtite politics, a s s o c i at i n g
g ove rn m e n t , the pri vate sector and social gr o u p s.
But I don’t think the stat e ’s retreat means the end
of politics.That would be an enormous step back-
wards which would bring us face to face with the
nightmare of the 17th-century English philosopher
Thomas Hobbes of a “ war of eve ry one against eve ry
o n e ” . So the really important thing is to expand the
frontiers of politics,to think about politics beyond
the stat e .After all, e ve rything of concern to the com-
munity is politics. And what people call “the cri s i s
of politics” va ries in intensity from society to socie-
t y. I t ’s always more noticeable in countries where
there is only limited mediation by cultural and wo r-
k e rs ’m ovements between gove rnment and society.
In these cases, when the state gets we a k e r , s o c i e t y
feels weaker too.
I want to stress one point.The state isn’t dead,
far from it. E ven in the developed wo r l d , p u b l i c
expenditure has risen as a percentage of gross 
Wars are beneficial as
long as they are not
wa g e d .
F rancis Umbra l , Spanish author
and journalist (1935-)
*French scholar and professor at
the Institute of Political Studies,
Paris. Mr Laïdi was visiting
professor at the European Center
of the Johns Hopkins University in
Bologna (Italy) between 1995 and
1997.Among his recent works
published in English is Crisis of
Meaning in World Politics
(Routledge, 1998).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 21
International Year 2000: peace is in our hands
The South’s fragile states
Developing countries are still wrestling with the business of fashioning a nation-state and building structures which in
the West grew and matured over several centuries into modern, integrated societies.These societies only became demo-
cratic after going through an industrial revolution.
Until the late 1980s, the construction of nation-states in the countries of the South was seriously hampered by colo-
nization and then by the Cold Wa r.Before independence, nothing was done to integrate the different peoples living insi-
de artificially drawn frontiers. In fact,the colonial powers conducted a policy of divide and rule.
Then during the decades of East-West confrontation, heads of state only won power through their loyalty to one side
or the other, not because they were good rulers. The great powers clearly played a hand in this by often backing dicta-
tors at the expense of certain “founding fathers of independence”who had better intentions towards their people.
To d a y, a third generation of rulers is gradually taking the reins in the countries of the South, mostly as a result of more
or less democratic elections. But when these leaders are called upon by their subjects, sometimes violently, to install real
democracy and develop their countries, they more than ever lack the means to do so.
Development aid has fallen by 20 per cent since the end of the Cold Wa r. Interest payments on debt are an increasing
burden on government fin a n c e s. Structural adjustment programmes have eroded the legitimacy of the state by dis-
mantling public services and widening the gap between the haves and the have-nots. The deterioration of the environ-
m e n t , notably soil degradation (six million hectares are lost every year) and deforestation (10 million hectares destroyed
each year), is depleting vital resources already in short supply.Another destabilizing factor is that 60 per cent of the worl-
d’s weaponry ends up in developing countries.
So how can young and fragile states be strengthened? How can people be persuaded,as they struggle to survive, n o t
to look to their clan or tribe as a way of defending themselves, when their government can neither guarantee their secu-
rity nor a basic standard of living? 
Making fine speeches about good governance is not enough in poor countries handicapped by the heavy legacy of
the past. Such countries must have access to development, and the North, which in the past built its prosperity partly on
their lands, their manpower and their natural resources, must help them. n
Mohamed Sahnoun, special envoy of the United Nations Secretary-General in Africa
Peace is not the
absence of wa r, it is 
a virtue, a state of
m i n d , a disposition for
b e n e v o l e n c e,
c o n fid e n c e, j u s t i c e.
Baruch Spinoza, D u t c h
philosopher (1632-1677)
n ational product in eve ry single country. This is
because the solemn responsibilities of the state remain
ve ry gr e at in the domains of social securi t y, p e n s i o n s
and debt repay m e n t .There are also gr owing demands
on the state in several areas, including educat i o n .S o
the state isn’t dead, just a certain conception of it—
one that makes refri g e r at o rs , for example.
E ven civil societies need an organized state in
which to flo u ri s h , one anchored in the rule of law
and capable of expressing va rious demands and
c o n c e rns at an intern ational leve l . The recent
attempt in Seattle to launch a new round of world
trade negotiations shows the tightly-knit relat i o n-
ship between gove rnments and economic and social 
players.
What’s the role of new information technology in
the emergence of a worldwide civil society?
A tremendous one, p r ovided of course that yo u
d o n ’t look for ove rsimplistic explanat i o n s. I t ’s
obvious that the Internet plays a decisive role in
mobilizing people about the env i r o n m e n t ,h u m a n
rights and trade.The speed at which inform ation is
exchanged gr e atly strengthens the building of cam-
paign plat f o rm s. It undoubtedly takes less time to
mobilize social groups than to mobilize states. But
once again, t h e r e ’s no innate conflict between the
t wo. One might think, for example, t h at the social
m o b i l i z ation of Europeans against genetically-
modified organisms is an important bargaining
counter for the European Commission as it fa c e s
the United States. n
Interview by René Lefort
Director of the UNESCO COURIER.
Demonstrating against child labour in Colombo 
(Sri Lanka) in 1997.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
For most men,
war is the end of
s o l i t u d e.
For me, it is 
i n finite solitude.
Albert Camus, F re n c h
author (1913-1950)
“The future for youths like me in Ciudad Bolívar is
g u n s ,” s ays 20-year-old Victor Manuel.“ F i rst yo u
h ave to surv i ve the gangs.Then you spend a ye a r
in the army, hoping not to be sent to a combat zone.
After that , if you want to raise a fa m i l y, you get a job as
a security guard for a firm or a block of flat s. Or else yo u
do dirty work for the militias or the drug lords.”
Victor is one of thousands of dead-end kids who
gr ow up on the dusty hillsides of Ciudad Boliva r , in the
slums around the Colombian capital of Bogotá. O ve r
the past 40 ye a rs , one and a half million people have
poured into the area—a fifth of the city’s population.
Victor decided to steer clear of guns. He didn’t wa n t
to be a security guard, a soldier,a smuggler or a gang-
s t e r. He didn’t want to get into drugs either. “ Ta k i n g
d rugs is a form of we a k n e s s ,” he say s. “It shows yo u
c a n ’t face up to life. I t ’s the same with violent cri m e .”
Instead,Victor wants to make videos.
His new home is Ciudad Bolíva r ’s Youth 
L e a d e rship School, a rather pompously named asso-
c i ation which was created by and for needy yo u n g
people and which operates from the basement of a four-
storey bu i l d i n g .Victor and his friends make big sacri-
fices to pay the $100 monthly rent for these premises.
With help from pri vate unive rsities and a foundat i o n
run by a Colombian bu s i n e s s m a n , they are trying to set
up a community radio station and meanwhile produce
videos about the lives of young people living in the
slums.
They believe communication is the only way to
change the lives of future gang members—the gr o u p s
of street youths who hang out in houses or on wa s t e
ground where they meet to compose rap songs and
sometimes plan petty crimes.
The themes of the videos, which reflect life in
Ciudad Bolíva r , are worked out together.V i c t o r ’s
first production, A Taste of Evil, tells the story of a
family that fled from the countryside when they
heard ru m o u rs of massacres. For the children of this
family violence was just that—a rumour of some-
thing that happened in the next village.T h e n ,w h e n
they got to Ciudad Bolíva r , they encountered vio-
lence on a daily basis, along with the lure of cri m e
and dru g s.
D u ring the making of the second video, D r e a m s
and Dreamers,a gang member from the slum stole the
equipment the team had painstakingly 
a s s e m b l e d .The boys at the Leadership School we r e
ready to reve rt to their old habits of gang fighting to
get the mat e rial back. But it wa s n ’t necessary.T h e
local people protested and the gang members retur-
ned the equipment. “They didn’t realize it was as if
they had stolen something of their ow n ,” s ays V i c t o r.
The Leadership School’s goal is to change the
attitudes of young delinquents.The fil m i n g, w h i c h
i nvo l ves about 50 yo u t h s , is a chance to establish
a dialogue with the street kids.The videos are show n
in churches, s c h o o l s , community centres and at local
festivals with the aim of trying to influence groups
of youths by using codes and symbols they are fa m i-
liar with.
But it isn’t easy to persuade teenagers to aban-
don violence when their cultural environment is full
of despair. “ L i ve hard and die young because the-
re’s no hope,” say rock,rap and heavy metal songs.
“It’s also hard to compete when a kid can make 50
or 100,000 pesos ($25 or $50) in a 15-minute rob-
bery,” says Victor.
The Leadership School offers no real job oppor-
tunities but it does provide one-year courses which
gi ve yo u n g s t e rs experience in community 
m a n a g e m e n t . It equips them to contri bute to the
hundreds of small organizations and informal gr o u p s
which spring up in the slums and constitute the only
c o l l e c t i ve response to pove rty and neglect.
Fo rty young people have already gr a d u ated from
this neighbourhood unive rsity where Victor took a
second shot at life. n
Videos to dispel d e s p a i r
w Carlos Mauricio Ve g a
Amid the poverty and violence of a Bogotá slum, Victor Manuel makes videos
to divert young people away from guns and drugs
The hillsides of Ciudad Bolívar, around Bogotá, where over a million and a half
people have settled in the last 40 years.
It isn’t easy to pers u a d e
t e e n a g e rs to abandon violence
when their cultural enviro n m e n t
is full of despair
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 23
Le sida déferle: a l e r t e z les jeunes!International Y ar 2000: peace is in our ha ds
When Tian Huiping discovered that her son,
Ta o t a o, was autistic, the world closed in
on her. Her doctor in the huge inland
metropolis of Chongqing had never seen a case of
autism and was in no position to give any counsel.
Neither could she turn to a community or a
g ove rnment department for support , China being
a country where disabilities are even today not publi-
cly discussed, scarcely researched and to all intents
and purposes not treat e d .
N ow, eight ye a rs after the painful discove ry of
Ta o t a o ’s condition,Tian has managed not only to
find a way to support her son, but also through crea-
ting the country ’s first and so far only school for
autistic children,has offered a ray of hope to those
suffering from the disease.
To bring the Stars and Rain School for autis-
tic children to where it is today required determ i-
nation,hard work and creativity in fund-raising.It
also demanded a dri ve to keep going even when the
mission seemed doomed.“People say to me,‘Why
should we spend all of this time and money if there
is no cure?’ I try to tell them that to get a child func-
tioning will give that child a better life,” she says.
Tian came to Beijing in 1992 with nothing but
a suitcase and her son to look for someone who
could offer her help and advice.One doctor’s offi-
ce had a pamphlet about children with autism, a
condition marked by severely limited responsive-
ness to others and abnormal speech pat t e rn s. F r o m
w h at little inform ation the pamphlet gave her,T i a n
decided she was the best person to try and help Ta o-
t a o, n ow 14. Her personal quest soon turned into a
mission to help others like her.
Her idea for a school was picked up by a bu s i-
nessman who thought it might be a good way to
make money. She enrolled six autistic children and
hired two teachers.The businessman backed out of
their arrangement but Tian was so encouraged by
the improvement of the children that she and one
of the teachers decided to go it alone.They pac-
ked all their possessions into a cardboard box and
moved to a single dingy room in Beijing.
The fees for the cours e , which among other
things teaches parents to help their children and
lasts about three months,are about $120 per child—
a lot of money in a country where most make just
about that each month. E ven so, these funds are
i n s u f fic i e n t .T h a n k f u l l y,T i a n ’s work has at t r a c t e d
the attention of the foreign community in Beijing,
and a few foreign children from diplomat fa m i l i e s
have attended the school.
Tian says that to meet annual costs she needs to
raise about $12,000, while development will
demand another $24,000.The school has recei-
ved aid from the Canada Fund, the A u s t rian gove rn-
m e n t , and Hong Kong’s Round Ta b l e , a philan-
thropic organizat i o n . For the past few ye a rs a
C h ristmas Bazaar has been held at the Germ a n
embassy in Beijing with some of the proceeds going
to Tian’s school.
Before Stars and Rain,autistic children in Bei-
jing could only attend schools for the mentally disa-
b l e d . In many cases this doesn’t work well for autis-
tic children because often they are extremely
intelligent and above the level being taught. S t a rs
and Rain tries to enable the child to function first,
and then  hopefully integrate into regular schools.
When Tian started the school and parents wo u l d
come to her or telephone from across the country
asking for inform ation about autism to help their
c h i l d r e n , she had a list of three doctors in China
who could diagnose the illness. N ow, six ye a rs lat e r ,
she proudly  shows a list of more than 20 doctors
who have an understanding of autism.
The school holds four sessions a year and is boo-
ked at least six  months in adva n c e .The current ses-
sion has 27 pupils and that ’s about the maximum
the school can handle at a time.
Next project on T i a n ’s hori z o n : raising money
to buy a house for adult sufferers. n
S t a rs through the  ra i n
w Katherine A r m s
In China, t h e re were no facilities to educate autistic children until Tian Huiping started
a school in Beijing to help her son and other suffere rs.
w Beijing-based writer
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
The houses that Francisco built
w Maiá Menezes
A Brazilian professor teaches slum-dwellers low-cost brick-making techniques
w Journalist with O Dia,
Rio de Janeiro
One day, when the
weather is bad,
A ray of sunshine will
light the grey clouds.
On that day, e v e r y o n e
alive on our planet
Will join to form a ring
crossing the oceans.
This ring will be so big
that everyone 
will rejoice,
Be they black, yellow or
w h i t e, big or small,
From A s i a , Africa or
A m e r i c a .
They will know the
eternal meaning of
p e a c e.
If only this dream
would come true…  
Poem sent to the U N E S C O
C o u r i e r by Matthew Pra s,
a 10-year-old schoolchild fro m
Lyon (Fra n c e )
By using this original brick-making process, the costs of
building a small house can be halved.
Brazilian chemist and civil engineer Francisco
C a s a n ova makes houses for the poor. He has
developed a technique that has allowed fami-
lies to move out of their shacks and into proper
houses with solid wa l l s.Working alone, he teaches
700 low-income people—80 per cent of them slum-
d we l l e rs—to make special bricks which halve the
cost of building a house.Then they learn how to
build their own houses and can earn some money
by working in one of the five co-operat i ves set up by
Casanova to make and sell the bricks.
Casanova,45,who teaches civil engineering to
p o s t gr a d u ates at Rio de Janeiro Federal Unive rs i t y,
is a solitary campaigner who does not rely on help
from the gove rnment or any big company. “ Po l i-
ticians don’t want people to organize among them-
s e l ve s ,” he say s.“ T h e y ’re afraid of losing control of
them.”
His personal battle invo l ves teaching more than
just the basics of civil engineering.What his pupils
also learn in his classes are the principles of citi-
z e n s h i p. “I’m not doing this for religi o u s , p o l i t i c a l
or financial reasons,” he says.“I want to see people
becoming more confident. The idea is to teach
people to fish and then give them a fishing rod.It’s
not much good just giving them the fish.”
In the three ye a rs his project has been going, a
lot of fish have been caught. His impove rished pupils
h ave built 18 houses for themselves to live in and
another 10 are planned over the next year.
The country’s first 
self-governing condominium
Another triumph for Dr Casanova is the Duque
de Caixas slum, in the Baixada do Rio de Ja n e i r o —
one of the poorest places in Rio prov i n c e . In the ye a r
2000,it will have the country’s first self-governing
c o n d o m i n i u m . About 15,000 bricks are ready for
C a s a n ova ’s pupils, who will build 10 houses with
them.The land still has to be bought, and this will
be done with funding from the Research Assistan-
ce Fo u n d ation of Rio de Janeiro (FA P E R J ) , the only
public body interested in helping the project.
C a s a n ova will sign agreements with other
d e p a rtments at his unive rsity to provide the condo-
minium with solar powe r , its own water puri fic at i o n
system and a plan for organic gardening and fa r-
m i n g .The residents will be pupils of Casanova who
c u rrently live in the Rato Molhado (“Wet Mouse”)
s l u m , among fil t hy puddles, foul smells and violent
drug-dealers.
It has not been easy for Casanova .S o m e t i m e s
d ru g - d e a l e rs have ordered work in a slum to stop,
apparently because they are suspicious of social pro-
jects and help from outside which they fear might
u n d e rmine their authority in the slums.The big hou-
sing deve l o p e rs do not like this kind of project either.
When Casanova teaches people to make cheaper
c e m e n t , it means less business for them.“The deve-
l o p e rs try to block anything that cuts costs,”he com-
plains. But he is not deterred by such threats.
W h at dri ves Casanova in his lone crusade is gr a-
t i t u d e , especially towards his unive rs i t y, which is
public and free. He regards his unive rsity studies as
a kind of gift from society.“Society has allowed me
to study,” he says,“and if there’s anything I can do
in return,then I must do it.”
But this does not stop him criticizing scientific
research geared to developing discoveries made in
rich countri e s. “Ninety-nine per cent of what the
u n i ve rsity does serves the interests of those who can
afford to pay,” he notes.
It is true that Brazil’s unive rsity system is 
heavily involved in projects sponsored by big firms
such as the oil company Petrobras and the Rio de
Janeiro subway system. U n i ve rsity departments are
researching into fields like high speed calculat i o n
and high-resistance cement manufacture.“On top
of that ,” he say s , “the unive rsity is the home of
e l i t e s.” In defiance of this elitism, three ye a rs ago he
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
to attend the classes and when the money supply dri e d
u p, they va n i s h e d . “The project is working today
because people are working to build their own homes,”
says Casanova.
Some businessmen are also turning to 
C a s a n ova , but he says “the product isn’t really accep-
ted by the market” because it is not designed to make
a profit and is not pat e n t e d . Under Brazilian trade and
i n d u s t ry ministry ru l e s ,C a s a n ova ’s technique cannot
easily be registered because the bricks are made nei-
ther of new mat e rials nor in a new way.The only inno-
vation is in the proportion of the ingredients used.“ I t
would be like patenting the recipe for chocolate cake,”
he says with a smile. n
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 25
International Year 2000: peace is in our hands
brought 15 of his building technology students to
the unive rs i t y.When they went into the canteen, t h e
u n i ve rsity students were shocked and the most pre-
judiced even laughed at them.
“I brought these people from the slums without
telling the unive rsity because I knew that if I had
they wouldn’t’ve been allowed in,” says Casanova,
who eventually managed to get them registered at
the unive rs i t y. After the project achieved intern a-
tional recognition, there were no more problems.
“ To d ay, no one dares to criticize me,” he say s
happily.
Dulcinéia da Rocha is 60 ye a rs old and the kee-
nest of Dr Casanova ’s students. After studying, s h e
decided to teach, became his unofficial assistant
and recently went to Paris with him to present the
project at UNESCO Headquart e rs together with
other grassroots anti-poverty initiatives within the
f r a m e work of the UN Decade for the Eliminat i o n
of Pove rt y.The trip was a dream come true for Dul-
cinéia, who lives in the Rato Molhado slum and is
one of the lucky future ow n e rs of a new house in
Duque de Caixas.
A non-profit technique
without a patent
C a s a n ova spent 400 reals (about $200) on da
R o c h a ’s visit to Pa ris and also bought her a set of
false teeth because she did not want to go without
first visiting the dentist. But she paid Casanova back
with interest by becoming an excellent example of
wo m e n ’s determ i n ation to bu i l d . “Some men don’t
seem to have a will to live ,”he say s ,“ but women will
do anything to change their lives.”
The seeds of Casanova ’s revo l u t i o n a ry enter-
prise were sown in 1973,when he was an enginee-
ring student and began studying road-building tech-
n o l o gi e s. “One day I said to my s e l f : ‘ W hy don’t
people use this technique to make bricks? If we can
make cheaper roads, w hy not cheaper houses too?’”
Ye a rs lat e r , one of Casanova ’s students received a
letter from someone who had bought a machine for
making bricks and didn’t know how to use it. C a s a-
nova helped him and,after the story appeared in a
popular magazine, s t a rted hearing from people wa n-
ting to learn how to build their own houses.
Offers of funding followed,although not many
actually mat e ri a l i z e d .The Comunidade Solidari a
p r o gramme run by Ruth Cardoso, B r a z i l ’s Firs t
L a d y, d o n ated 33,000 reals ($16,500). But fin a n-
cial aid turned out to be no more than chari t y,
because the pupils were paid 50 reals ($25) a day
Former slum-dwellers, Francisco Casanova’s pupils have built 18 houses of this type for
themselves and their families. A dozen more are under construction.
Magic bricks
By using a mixture of earth, cement and wa t e r, s t r o n g
and environment-friendly bricks can be produced fiv e
times cheaper than the market price.They are shaped to
slot into each other horizontally so that no mortar is
n e e d e d ; this alone brings the price down by at least half.
The bricks are machine-manufactured, t a ke five or six
days to dry and do not absorb wa t e r.They also protect the
natural environment. For every thousand bricks made,
12 fewer average-size trees need to be felled.
The main adva n t a g e, h o w e v e r, is the low production
c o s t . For about $12.50, it is possible to make 1,000 bricks
measuring 20 x 10 x 5 cm.Transport costs are also lower
since the bricks are made with ordinary earth. n
“I want to see people 
becoming more confid e n t .
The idea is to teach people
to fish and then give them 
a fishing ro d . I t ’s not much 
good just giving them the fis h .”
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
On the edge of the Sahara, donkeys and camels
amble around a little square that slumbers
b e n e ath the sunny skies of T i m bu k t u . O n
March 27, 1 9 9 6 , it was thronged with the city’s joy-
ful inhabitants who had come to get a look at “the
flame of peace”, which danced before them as 3,000
guns were burned,to signal with a flourish the end
of the “northern rebellion”.
O ver the six preceding ye a rs , first the Malian
a rmy and then vigilante groups of the sedentary
black Ganda Koy people had fought a war against
Tuareg and Arab rebels. Many civilians were killed
and about 200,000 nomads (about a fifth of the
population of the North) fled.
In choosing negotiation and sponsoring meet-
ings between the communities to end the fighting,
President Konaré’s Mali won a solid intern at i o n a l
r e p u t ation as a champion of the culture of peace.
The intern ational community provided consider-
able technical and financial aid (development assis-
tance makes up 20 per cent of Mali’s budget) and
the country was held up as an example. D e s p i t e
recent troubling deve l o p m e n t s , the United Nat i o n s
hails Mali as an island of tranquillity in an ocean of
wa rs and autocratic regi m e s. S y m b o l i c a l l y,T i m-
buktu has recently been awarded Unesco’s Cities
for Peace prize.
M a l i: a fli c kering flame 
w Sophie Boukhari
Malian President Alpha Oumar Konaré is committed to a culture of peace. But crime 
has been rising in Mali for several years now and the political climate is getting wors e
w UNESCO Courier journalist
At President Konaré’s instigation,the authori-
ties always use kid gloves when trying to curb 
“ r e s i d u a l ” violence and new local confli c t s. In recent
ye a rs , especially 1999, s e veral communities in the
N o rth and in the we s t e rn Sahel—the country ’s other
“ p r o b l e m ” r e gi o n , on the borders with 
M a u ritania and Senegal—have been caught up in
bloody clashes.
“Negotiation and consensus are at the heart of
Sahelian culture, of which Mali is to some extent
the epicentre,” s ays historian Doulaye Konat é ,w h o
has just completed a study of how Malians see the
culture of peace.“ We live in societies that are dive r-
s e , hierarchical and ve ry conflictual, where 
we can’t live together unless eve ryone makes 
concessions.”
Community peacemakers
M a rriage is used to strengthen ties between clans
and between communities. A vast network of
alliances has also arisen from sacred pacts betwe e n
the ancestors. S a n a n k o u ya ( “ r e l ationship through
jokes”) is a practice that brings together gr e at fa m i-
lies such as the Diarras and the Traorés,socio-pro-
fessional groups (Peul herders and smiths) and
peoples such as the Dogon and the Sonrhai.“S a n a n-
k o u n” h ave a duty to help one another and to inter-
vene in conflicts between their allies and
outsiders.
Some members of the community specialize
in peacemaking. G riots (story t e l l e rs) and smiths are
the peacemakers among the Mandingo and Bam-
bara people, while village chiefs and 
councils of wise men (ulemas and leading citizens)
p e r f o rm this role in Arab-Berber cultures. “ We ’r e
lucky this tradition still exists,” s ays Mahamadou 
D i a g o u r a g a , the gove rn m e n t ’s commissioner in the
n o rt h . “The traditional chiefs, the priests and the
notables are still listened to, even if it’s hard to talk
to the young people.”
When potentially explosive incidents occur, t h e
a u t h o rities gather these conciliat o rs together for
s e veral day s , with the help of the United Nat i o n s
(especially the UN Development Programme) and
m a ny national and intern ational NGOs. “ Pe o p l e
are all worked up when they arrive, but when they
get talking about their history and all the other things
they have in common,they usually end up making
peace with each other,” s ays Firoun Maiga, a for-
mer Ganda Koy combatant.
For the past seven ye a rs , the gove rnment has
been relying on this underlying cultural cohesion to
t ry to keep the peace. President Konaré says he
wants to build a model democracy based on the
Malian tradition of seeking consensus. The 
Blood can no longer be
s h e d . M o t h e r s
watching television will
not tolerate seeing their
sons’ blood being
spilled in front of their
very eyes. The civilian
population will no
longer be content with
a diplomatic peace. Th e
culture of peace is an
economic and
intellectual dialogue
between peoples. Wa r
claims a dreadful price.
Peace can bear fruit.
Fruit is a better choice
than tears.
Shimon Pe re s, Nobel Pe a c e
L a u reate 1994, I s raeli political
leader (1923-)
Mauritania
Guinea
Mali
Algeria
Burkina Faso
Benin
NIAMEY
BAMAKO OUAGADOUGOÜ
Timbuktu
Mali factfil e
Population:10.6 million.
Main languages: Fr e n c h , B a m b a r a , S e n o u f o,
Sarakole, Dogon, Peul, Tamasheq (Tuareg),Arabic.
Area:1,240,000 sq.km.
GNP per capita:$250.
Illiteracy:65%
Source: World Bank,1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 27
International Year 2000: peace is in our hands
o f t - r e p e ated project of this unive rsity lecturer and
son of a teacher, with his approachable manner and
r e p u t ation for honesty, seems to be one of the most
promising in A f ri c a . He wants freedom to flo u ri-
s h , n ational identity and memory to be revive d ,
differences to be respected and grassroots 
democracy established.
His first task was to end the war and the 
m a r gi n a l i z ation of the Nort h ,a region which cove rs
nearly three-quart e rs of the country and has tra-
ditionally been a hotbed of rebellion.Sidelined for
decades and long administered by the military, i t
has been a prey to arbitrary rule and abject pover-
t y.The gr e at droughts of the 1970s and 1980s we r e
the last straw and the region exploded in 1990.
After the “ T i m buktu peace agr e e m e n t ” , t h e
g ove rnment set about bri n ging some 12,000 for-
mer rebels back into civilian life, s ays commissio-
ner Diagouraga.About 2,400 ex-combatants were
absorbed into the army and the civil serv i c e .A total
of 9,530 others were gi ven demobilization pay m e n t s
of 300,000 CFA francs (about $500), s o m e t i m e s
topped up with micro-credit to start a small bu s i-
n e s s. Only about 10 per cent of the former rebels
subsequently deserted the army or abandoned their
new civilian jobs and the rate of their absorp t i o n
into the pri vate sector is reckoned to be 70 per cent.
“Today you can even find Tuaregs in the presi-
d e n t ’s personal security unit,” s ays the armed forces
and veteran affa i rs minister, Mohamed Salia Soko-
na.
The gove rnment believes long-term peace can-
not be achieved unless pove rty is rolled back, so it
has spent money to try to bring the North up to the
l e vel of the rest of the country. “ We ’ ve built schools
and clinics, bored we l l s , and created ponds and ri c e
p a d d i e s ,” s ays Diagouraga. “This gove rnment has
done more in eight years than was done in the pre-
vious 30.”
“Nearly all the Tuaregs are semi-sedentary,” s ay s
Houloulou ag Mohamed, who is invo l ved in social-
ly integr ating them.They live in big camps where
there is often a school and sometimes a clinic. E a c h
family has a few goat s , the children are healthier and
they go to school.The legendary lords of the desert
feel uncomfortable in their new situation but they
are resigned to working at a regular job.
Decentralization
As the final component in its peace plan and
to encourage people to organize their lives in one of
the wo r l d ’s poorest countri e s , the Konaré gove rn-
ment has set up 682 decentralized villages,adding
to the 19 that already existed.This reform is “ t h e
political answer to the rebellion,” s ays Ibrahim ag
Yo u s s o u f, a Undp consultant. “There is no other
choice.When everything is run from Bamako, you
see the result. Civil servants posted in the prov i n c e s
are either absentees or are only there to keep people
down.”
H owe ve r , the “culture of peace” the president
and UN officials talk about so much seems fragi-
l e .The different communities still distrust each
A downbeat disarmament campaign
It’s common knowledge that guns are easy to get hold of in northern Mali.When the rebel-
lion ended,very few were handed in by the locals.And getting a fresh supply is child’s play.
Mali is a landlocked country in a West Africa where there are and always have been many
c o n fli c t s, e. g . in Liberia, Sierra Leone, and A l g e r i a .Arms dealers from the We s t , from China
and former communist countries dump their leftovers there, says Robin-Edward Poulton,of
the United Nations Institute for Disarmament Research (UNIDIR), who has lived in Mali for
15 years.
“For example, I’ve just been told of two new shipments to Sierra Leone, one from Chine-
se sources, the other from British,” he said in November 1999.They reach Mali from Sierra
Leone via Guinea. “ They go down the Niger River in waterproof sacks tied to the bottoms
of boats,” he says.“ You can’t look underneath every canoe and besides, customs officers are
easy to bribe.Western intelligence services also think several regional heads of state are invol-
ved in arms smuggling.”
The situation did not deter President Konaré from proposing a halt on the import,export
and manufacture of light weapons in West A f r i c a , and a moratorium to this effect was signed
on October 31, 1 9 9 8 .The moratorium is being backed by the United Nations, which in March
1999 set up a Programme for Co-ordination and Assistance for Security and Development
in West Africa (PCASED).
A downbeat disarmament campaign among the population is being launched.“ We wa n t
people to be involved in it,” says Mahamadou Diagouraga, the government’s commissio-
ner for the northern region.“Some villagers would like to hand in their weapons in exchan-
ge for money, but we won’t do that.Instead,we offer them a school,a well or a cattle mar-
ket.PCASED can help us fund these projects.” n
A Tuareg mother and child in Mali. Today, fewer and fewer Tuareg follow their traditional
nomadic way of life.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
How can we talk about
a culture of peace, i f
that peace is predicated
on the existence of
weapons of mass
destruction? How can
we persuade the young
generations that they
should cast aside the
culture of violence,
when they know that
we are relying for
peace on a balance of
terror? If we genuinely
want to develop the
culture of peace in the
new millennium, w e
will have to get rid of
nuclear weapons.
Joseph Rotblat, Nobel Pe a c e
L a u reate 1995, British physicist
( 1 9 0 8 - )
other. “It’s OK as long as the money keeps flowing
i n , but if it stops fighting will flare up again,” s ay s
a former combat a n t . On top of that , the pace of
completed projects is too slow and the democratic
process has suffered serious setbacks.
The disbu rsement of more than $200 million
e a rmarked for the development of the North has
been held up since 1995 by red tape,rampant cor-
ruption and the lengthy bu r e a u c r atic procedures of
the funding agencies,say all the experts.
“You can build schools,” says Youssouf, “but if
you want to hire a teacher, you have to have a gr e e n
light from the World Bank because Mali is under a
s t ructural adjustment progr a m m e .Who’ll pay the
teacher? The villages don’t have the money and the
g ove rnment has just enough to pay the civil
servants.”
Some jobless young people have got tired of wa i-
ting for the peace dividend and are choosing to go
abroad or make easy money by joining gangs of ban-
dits and smugglers who roam the country. C ri m e
is on the increase and large-scale smuggling of A m e-
rican cigarettes is gr ow i n g . A packet of Marlboros
bought for 250 CFA francs ($0.40) in Burkina Fa s o
sells for 650 ($1) in Mali and 850 ($1.30) in Alge-
ria.
The gove rnment does not have the means to
curb these illegal activities over such a wide area.
Local people are calling for military posts to be set
up again, on a temporary basis.“When the gove rn-
m e n t ’s strong, it crushes us,and now it’s we a k , we ’r e
dying,” says an inhabitant of Timbuktu.
“ D e m o c r a cy is a hard road to follow,” s t r e s s e s
Gen Amadou Toumani To u r é , who ove rthrew the
dictatorship of Moussa Traoré in 1991.Decentra -
l i z ation led to local elections in June 1999 which
upset the balance of powe r. The subsequent 
r e d e finition of terri t o rial boundaries has stirred up
old land disputes.
“The North is experiencing a social revo l u t i o n ,”
s ays Diagouraga. “ D e c e n t r a l i z ation disturbs peo-
p l e ’s habits and their vested interests and 
a rr a n g e m e n t s. Disputes are often settled under the
p a l aver tree and sometimes in court , but they can
also degenerate into explosions of violence.”
Clashes have already taken place. In the second
half of 1999 about 40 people were killed in the most
s e rious confrontat i o n ,b e t ween “ A r a b s ” and “ K o u n-
tas”(Muslim spiritual chiefs,who are also Arabs).
The minority Kountas, who lost the elections, r e f u-
se to yield control of an area they had dominat e d
for centuries.
Stalled political dialogue
The Arabs have become rich in recent times by
smuggling cigarettes, which has enabled them to
buy arm s , one of the country ’s most frequently tra-
ded items (see box).This old rivalry also takes the
f o rm of a “ m o d e rn ” political confli c t : the Koun-
tas have stood as candidates for the ruling A d e m a
p a rt y, while the Arabs have supported the 
opposition.
Political dialogue has been completely broken
off ever since the “failed”elections of 1997,which
human rights organizations said were marred by
m a ny irr e g u l a ri t i e s.They were boycotted by the
opposition and produced virtually a one-party 
parliament.
“ We don’t recognize the present institutions,”
snap Choguel Maiga and Mountaga Ta l l , the two
main opposition leaders , who accuse the gove rn-
ment of bias in settling local crises.
Such a situation is unlikely to boost the legi t i-
macy of the state,which sprang from colonial rule
and 23 ye a rs of dictat o rs h i p, or to strengthen the
a u t h o rity of modern institutions such as the legal
s y s t e m , which allegedly lacks resources and inde-
p e n d e n c e .And no one knows how much longer tra-
ditionalism can keep the lid on the old hatreds 
lurking beneath the Saharan sand. n
On March 27,1996, 3,000 weapons were burned in Timbuktu during a “flame of peace”ceremony.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 29
International Year 2000: peace is in our hands
G a n d h i ’s disputed heritage
w Darryl D’Monte
The leadership of an Indian farmers’ movement against transgenic crops says it embodies
Gandhian principles but critics wonder whether it is being manipulated
In December 1998, Indian farmers burn cotton plants that had been genetically modified using knowhow provided 
by the U.S. multinational Monsanto.
In December 1998, when fa rm e rs in the south
Indian states of Andhra Pradesh and Karn at a k a
torched cotton plants bred with know h ow pro-
vided by the U. S . chemical multinational Mon-
s a n t o, their activism was cited intern ationally as an
example of grassroots Third World opposition to
genetically modified organisms (GMOs). T h e i r
action against the plants, which were being tested
for their resistance to pests, won particular note
from Rural A d vancement Fo u n d ation Intern at i o-
nal (RAFI), which has been at the forefront of the
worldwide movement against GMOs and coined
the term “ Te rm i n ator Te c h n o l o g y ” .
The fa rm e rs belonged to the Karn ataka Rajya
Raitha Sangh (KRRS), a movement that regards
the spread of transgenic breeds as “a new imperi a-
list assault” on the Third Wo r l d .To d ay the KRRS
claims to have 10 million members in Karn at a k a ,
whose total population is 60 million.
This was not the first time that the KRRS had
taken direct action against a multinational seed
bu s i n e s s. In 1992, for example, its members occu-
pied and ransacked the offices of the giant U. S .s e e d
c o m p a ny Cargi l l , in Bangalore, the state capital,
and its administrat i ve building in Bellary.
The KRRS was formed in 1980. Its founding
p r e s i d e n t , Prof M.D. N a n j u n d a swa my, told the
C o u rier that at first “the fa rm e rs tackled conve n-
tional gri e vances like debts, a gricultural prices and
d i s c ri m i n at o ry taxe s.Within a ye a r ,h owe ve r ,t h e y
had spontaneously developed a comprehensive
ideology to address issues raised by Green Revo-
lution technology.”
D. S .K a l m at , a fa rmer from Sindhanoor, a vil-
lage in Karn at a k a ’s Raichur distri c t , where Mon-
s a n t o ’s GM cotton was tried out on a tiny quart e r -
acre plot, d e s c ribed for the Courier some of the
e vents leading up to a crop-bu rning operat i o n .
Outflanking traditional 
political parties
“ We had read many articles against genetical-
ly modified va ri e t i e s ,” he said. “Prof Nanjun-
d a swa my telephoned me in December 1998 to fin d
out where the trial was being conducted.We dis-
c overed that the seeds had been provided by an
Indian company.The gove rn m e n t ’s A gri c u l t u r e
D e p a rtment had no inform ation about the tri a l ,
and the fa rmer himself had no idea of its implica-
t i o n s. He was willing to co-operate with us till the
B h a r at i ya Kisan Sangh [a movement affil i ated to
the party heading India’s coalition gove rn m e n t ] ,
asked him to resist any action by our organizat i o n .
Then Prof Nanjundaswa my arri ved with two acti-
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
Peace is not just
absence of wa r, a n d
non-violence is not just
absence of violence.
Non-violence and
peace are very much
dependent on the
practice of active
c o m p a s s i o n . Vi o l e n c e
and non-violence
cannot be distinguished
from external factors
a l o n e. The real test of
compassion is our
correct motivation and
how we conduct
ourselves in daily life
and not what we
merely say or do
p h y s i c a l l y.
The Dalai Lama, Nobel Pe a c e
L a u reate 1989, religious leader
( 1 9 3 5 - )
vists from Spain and Germ a ny and we bu rned the
c r o p.”
K a l m at was one of 400 fa rm e rs , half of them
from Karn at a k a , who in May 1999 went on a
month-long trip to Europe organized by the KRRS
to press their case.“An Intern ational Caravan tra-
velled through Europe and was in Cologne to pro-
test at the European Union Summit and the G8
c o n f e r e n c e ,” s ays Nanjundaswa my.
Opposition environmental movements like the
KRRS have often outflanked India’s traditional
political part i e s. For example, no party in any
Indian state has come out openly either for or
against GMOs.The mainstream parties have exces-
s i vely ri gid structures and rely on their own fa r-
m e rs ’o r g a n i z at i o n s , which are reluctant to launch
spontaneous actions and wait for diktats from the
central party leaders h i p,often based in New Delhi.
N o n - p a rty mass movements like the KRRS
h ave often shown up the shortcomings of the
c o nventional political system and its inability to
comprehend the linkages between economic libe-
r a l i z ation and threats to freedoms on many fronts.
Such groupings are much looser, i d e o l o gically and
s t ru c t u r a l l y, than traditional classic parties and
d r aw their support from an assortment of fa rm e rs ,
urban activists, academics and sometimes inter-
n ational environmental NGOs.
One reason why a mass movement against
GMOs has risen in India, a country where 750 mil-
lion out of the total population of one billion live
in the country s i d e , is that it is easy to whip up pas-
sions against technologies that are reminiscent of
the oppressive rule of British colonialists.
N a n j u n d a swa my says his movement is “ b a s e d
on Gandhian ideology.” M a h atma Gandhi saw the
Indian village as a keystone in his non-violent 
s t ruggle against British domination in the first half
of the 20th century.
“In the Indian village,” Gandhi wrote,“an age-
old culture is hidden under an encasement of cru-
d e n e s s.Take away the encru s t at i o n ,r e m ove the vil-
l a g e r ’s chronic pove rty and illiteracy and you will
find the finest specimen of what a cultured,
c u l t i vat e d , free citizen should be.”
The Gandhian lineage of the KRRS’s ideas has
also been stressed by a famous Indian env i r o n-
m e n t a l i s t ,Vandana Shiva , who has gi ven the move-
ment much of its intellectual ri g o u r.
For Shiva , non-violence means that “ we live
e c o l o gically and at peace with all species. In India,
the Earth community has never been seen to be
d o m i n ated by humans. A species are part of Va s u d-
h a i va Ku t u m b h a k a m, the Earth fa m i l y. L e av i n g
space for others is a measure of non-
v i o l e n c e . . . . Genuine non-violence and democra-
cy call for pluralistic coalitions and multiple res-
p o n s e s , r ather than monopolization and manipu-
l ation of move m e n t s.The horizon for activism is
ve ry wide.”
H owe ve r , KRRS violence in destroying GM
crops and the offices of multinationals has been cri-
ticized by hard-core Gandhians who emphasize
t h at means are as important as ends. N a n j u n-
d a swa my defended KRRS actions against this accu-
s ation when he told the C o u ri e r t h at “It is similar to
bu rning British goods during the freedom stru g g l e .
D u ring the Quit India movement against the Bri-
t i s h , Gandhi was asked whether bu rning cargo
trains constituted violence and he said it didn’t ,
unlike passenger trains.”
Rhetoric  and symbolism
C ritics are also sceptical about the KRRS’s 
credentials as a mass move m e n t .They say it is res-
t ricted to a few agi t ating fa rm e rs and to their urban
l e a d e rs h i p, which seeks support from the media
and the courts rather than organizing action by eve n
r e l at i vely small numbers of fa rm e rs who tend to be
among the better-off, with larger holdings.T h e y
also point out that the KRRS has a traditional hie-
rarchical stru c t u r e , with a President, t wo General
S e c r e t a ries and a Treasurer in Bangalore, and that
it is dominated by its founder, who is said to beha-
ve autocrat i c a l l y.They also maintain that the com-
plexities of GM crops are in any case usually beyo n d
the comprehension of the peasant.They point out
t h at Monsanto spokespersons in India cite other
Indian fa rm e rs ’ o r g a n i z ations which have enthu-
siastically supported the introduction of GMOs.
As for last ye a r ’s European tri p, the KRRS lea-
d e rship emphasized that the fa rm e rs paid their ow n
air fa r e s , though it is hard to imagine poor peasants
being able to do this. Obviously these were com-
f o rtably placed fa rm e rs , although Kalmat , w h o
owns just 6 acres, denies there are any of these in
K a rn ataka because of land reform s.
On the whole the media have been support i ve
of the KRRS, which is port r ayed as David bat t l i n g
against Goliaths which are often backed by the stat e
and powerful multinat i o n a l s. It is certainly true that
much of the rhetoric raised against these techno-
l o gi e s , and Monsanto and Cargill in part i c u l a r , i s
couched in nationalist term s. D e m o n s t r at i o n s
against multinationals often attract nation-wide T V
c ove r a g e .The media are always keen to sniff out
c o n s p i r a c i e s , and the threat to fa rm e rs and food
s e c u rity from powerful We s t e rn commercial inter-
ests is the stuff of many stori e s , not all of them 
a c c u r at e .
In some ways neo-Gandhian movements like
the KRRS are open to accusations of being high
on rhetoric and symbolic action but low on deli-
ve ring the goods in intern ational and national fora.
From all accounts, l e a d e rs like Nanjundaswa my
are today somewhat isolated and may not be able
to sustain a movement against GM crops and the
introduction of other fa rm technologies into India
for much longer. n
On the whole the media have
been supportive of the KRRS,
which is portrayed as David
battling against Goliaths which
a re often backed by the state
and powerful multinationals
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 31
International Year 2000: peace is in our hands
Jubilee 2000 is cited as as one of the biggest
single-issue global campaigns eve r. It is eve n
compared with the anti-apartheid movement of
the 1980s and has clearly had a more global outrea-
ch than campaigns on nuclear power or nuclear
d i s a rm a m e n t .With partner coalitions in 89 coun-
t ri e s , the initiat i ve has already exceeded its target of
collecting 22 million signatures by the end of the
year 2000.
All over the wo r l d , g ove rn m e n t s , e x p e rts and
c a m p a i g n e rs are watching Jubilee 2000’s extraor-
d i n a ry success both in mobilizing a global activist
movement and achieving demonstrable success in
pushing debt onto the agenda of the G-8 industri a l
nations and forcing the World Bank and the Inter-
n ational Monetary Fund (IMF) to tackle the indeb-
tedness of the poorest countries. Jubilee 2000 suc-
ceeded in getting tens of thousands of people onto
the streets for the G-8 summits in Birm i n g h a m
( U K , 1998) and in Cologne (Germ a ny, 1 9 9 9 ) .
D u ring the lat t e r , finance ministers agreed in 
p rinciple to cancel $70 billion of the $130 billion
owed by the wo r l d ’s poorest nat i o n s. R i val campai-
g n e rs amongst env i r o n m e n t a l i s t s , human rights acti-
vists and trade unionists marvel at the way Jubilee
2000 has trounced those who talked pessimisti-
cally about the apathy and fatalism of civil society.
Meanwhile,some governments are seeking advice
from think tanks as to how such campaigns can see-
mingly appear from now h e r e , mobilize such force
so quickly and with so few resources.
The secret of Jubilee 2000’s success is simple
but unfa s h i o n a b l e : it is the Christian churches.T h e r e
is a polite disagreement over who first came up with
the idea of linking the Biblical concept of jubilee,
expressed in the Old Testament Book of Leviticus,
with the millennium and debt cancellat i o n .C at h o-
lics maintain the Pope spoke of it firs t ,while the UK
evangelical aid agencyTearfund claims to have ini-
t i ated the campaign’s idea in 1994.W h at is without
doubt is that both Catholics and evangelicals have
found a common purpose in the 
c a m p a i g n .Tearfund provided crucial initial funding
for the Jubilee coalition and the Pope has played a
vital role in raising the profile of the campaign in 
southern Catholic countries.
The concept of Jubilee in the Old Testament is
t h at annive rs a ries should be marked by measures
of social justice: s l aves should be freed, land and
wealth redistri buted and debts cancelled. P r ov i d i n g
a target, a date and a biblical justific ation galva n i-
zed the long-running Debt Crisis Netwo r k , a Bri t i-
sh debt cancellation campaign.
The invo l vement of the churches was crucial for
t wo reasons.Their backing brought with it millions
of churchgoers in the UK and the ready-built stru c-
ture of churches and pari s h e s , along with their publi-
c at i o n s. News could—and did—spread fa s t , a n d
Jubilee 2000 found the idea taking off as an integr a l
p a rt of the churches’ c e l e b r ation of the millennium.
Alongside plans for parish parties and fir e works wa s
debt cancellat i o n . Jubilee 2000 found itself addres-
sing church meetings up and down the country.
A winning combination
S e c o n d l y, the churches brought an intern at i o-
nal stru c t u r e .As the idea gained ground in the UK,
it began to spread through diocesan links, b e t we e n
b i s h o p s ’ conferences and via parish twinning to the
s o u t h e rn countri e s. M i s s i o n a ry societies and orders
spread the wo r d . For the first time, the churches
found their belief in solidarity with the wo r l d ’s poor
taking concrete form and direct political expression.
At times, this made the church hierarchies nervo u s ,
admit senior Jubilee 2000 staff, but they found
t h e m s e l ves swept along by the enthusiasm of the
rank and file in the pew.This was faith in action,
their pari s h i o n e rs assert e d , and it helped them make
sense and give meaning to a date in the calendar.
Jubilee 2000’s winning combination was to per-
suade aid agencies (such as Oxfam and Chri s t i a n
Aid) and the churches to work together. It wa s —
and still is—a relationship of creat i ve tension. L e f t -
If you want peace,
strive for justice.
Pope Paul VI (1897-1978)
Jubilee 2000:
c h u rc h e s s p re a d
the word on debt
wMadeleine Bunting
I n s p i red by the biblical concept of jubilee, a global campaign to cancel T h i rd World debt has
managed to influence the agenda of the world’s richest countries
w Senior writer for The
Guardian (UK).Ms Bunting has
overseen the newspaper’s
sponsorship and coverage of the
Jubilee 2000 campaign for
eighteen months.
For the first time,
the churches found 
their belief in solidarity 
with the world’s poor taking
c o n c rete form and 
d i rect political expre s s i o n
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
wing aid activists do not like working with religi o u s
institutions such as the Catholic church in Lat i n
A m e ri c a , of which certain sectors have been sup-
p o rt i ve of oppressive regi m e s. But while the aid
agencies offered expertise on debt and campaigning,
the churches provided the footsoldiers to gat h e r
s i g n at u r e s ,t u rn up at demonstrations or swamp the
UK treasury or the German embassy with post-
c a r d s. It proved a powerful combinat i o n .D e s p i t e
ri va l ries betwen aid agencies anxious to maintain
their profile and funding, the fact that a coalition of
over a hundred groups—including trade unions and
professional bodies—managed to agree on how to
tackle the gr owing inequality of the global econo-
my added immeasurably to the campaign’s 
credibility.
One other aspect of the churches’ i nvo l ve m e n t
was specific to the British campaign but had glo-
bal consequences.The Labour gouve rnment elec-
ted in 1997 had been particularly sympathetic to
the churches’ r e p r e s e n t ation in the campaign.T h i s
is partly a shrewd political move from a gove rn m e n t
anxious to extend its political base from a traditio-
nal left-wing to a centrist position, and it part l y
stems from conv i c t i o n . Both Prime Minister To ny
Blair and Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon
B r own are strongly influenced by Christian socia-
l i s m .The latter took on the issue of debt as a per-
sonal commitment and has consistently pushed the
issue up on the intern ational agenda, p r oving a cru-
cial ally in chivying other finance ministers to consi-
der the issues.
What is interesting is that although many point
to Jubilee 2000 as a new form of global activism now
possible because of the Intern e t , it is again the
churches rather than new technologies which have
fuelled its deve l o p m e n t .The Jubilee 2000 we b s i t e
gets about 15,000 visitors a week, but much of the
i n f o rm ation requested has to be printed out and
sent to southern campaigners because their tele-
phone links to the net are so poor.
Advance information
Where the net has been crucial is in connecting
about 180 key activists and organizations around
the wo r l d , enabling them to share strat e gies and
i n f o rm ation to move the global campaign along.
Jubilee 2000 often received inform ation from part-
ner coalitions on debt negotiations forming in a par-
ticular country before the UK Tr e a s u ry.As a result,
when lobbying ministers , c a m p a i g n e rs were often
better informed and could outmanoeuvre them.
There has only been one assembly of all the part-
n e rs ; otherwise meetings have been rejected as
e x p e n s i ve and not ve ry productive .The effic i e n cy
of the information exchange enables a huge global
campaign to be run with only 15 full-time staff in
London supporting the entire edifice.
Jubilee 2000 is a long way from achieving its tar-
get but it has succeeded in getting a considerably
more generous debt relief initiat i ve underway. N o
o n e , t wo ye a rs ago, b e l i e ved the movement wo u l d
be able to achieve what it has. In part influenced by
the campaign, the IMF and the World Bank have
recognized for the first time that their legi t i m a cy
depends on engaging with civil society and are sho-
wing an unexpected reconsideration for some of the
p rinciples which have dri ven their policies since the
wa r. H e a rtened by this, some would claim Jubilee
2000 is a taste of global activism which might achie-
ve real change in this new century. O t h e rs wo rry
t h at with church attendance continuing to decline,
the moral imagi n ation of churchgoers which has
fuelled this campaign might become a thing of the
past and leave a gap in how to motivate people to
express their solidarity. Only time will tell. n
+ …
A list of national coalitions as well as additional information
can be found on the the Jubilee 2000 website at
http://www.jubilee2000uk.org
At the industrialized countries (G8) summit held in Cologne in June 1999,an accord on partial
debt relief for the world’s poorest countries was reached.Above, a supporter of the Jubilee
2000 movement, which played a big part in achieving this agreement.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 33
International Year 2000: peace is in our hands
S a n t ’ E g i d i o ’s diplomacy
of f r i e n d s h i p
w Mario Giro
A lay Catholic movement dedicated to helping the needy 
and mediating in international confli c t s
An old woman barricades herself in a dilapi-
dated building in the slums of an Italian city.
She refuses to open her door. Her neighbours
are convinced she’s becoming a derelict.A member
of the Sant’Egidio community knocks at her door
and starts to speak to her. She replies in monosyl-
l a b l e s. He leaves but comes back later to continue
a dialogue that may go on for months,even a year,
until she agrees to open the door and let him in and
finally start getting some help.
Using these skills in patient communicat i o n
based on fri e n d s h i p, the community later made
contact with a guerrilla chieftain hidden away for
years in the heart of Africa,brought him out of his
i s o l ation and persuaded him to negotiate instead of
fight.
“The Church is a home for eve ryo n e ,e s p e c i a l l y
the poor,” said Pope John XXIII, who set the Chur-
ch on the road to modern i z ation and opened it up
to the wo r l d , m oves which were endorsed by the
Vatican II Council. In line with this, a group of
C atholic students decided in 1968 to set up a
m ovement which would not be an N G O but a Chri s-
tian community where religious devotion we n t
hand in hand with putting the Gospel into prac-
tice by personal commitment to the poor.T h e i r
leader was Andrea Riccardi, who now teaches his-
t o ry at Rome Unive rsity and has been awa r d e d
UN E S C O’s Gandhi Medal for his commitment to a
culture of peace.
A language
of reconciliation
The Sant’Egidio community, which takes its
name from the disused Roman church it has adop-
ted as its headquart e rs ,t o d ay has 20,000 members
in some 300 grassroots communities in 34 coun-
t ri e s.The community began by helping abando-
ned children in the slums of Rome, then went on
to work with immigr a n t s , the elderly, the home-
l e s s , the handicapped,Aids victims and many other
groups of disadvantaged people in Europe and in
d e veloping countries of A s i a , L atin A m e rica and
A f ri c a .
One country where Sant’Egidio (St. Giles in
English) has been particularly active is Mozambique,
where famine and war raged in the early 1980s.T h e
fighting began against Po rtuguese colonial rule in
1 9 6 3 , stopped with independence in 1975,and star-
ted again a few ye a rs later for external and intern a l
r e a s o n s.The apartheid regime in South A f rica wa n-
ted to destabilize all its neighbours who refused to
recognize its regional dominance. S o c i a l i s t - ru l e d
Mozambique was a front-line target.
H u m a n i t a rian aid provided by the Sant’Egi-
dio community disappeared into a bottomless pit
because it was impossible to solve the hunger pro-
blem as long as a war was going on.The search for
a traditional mediator—a state or an intern at i o n a l
o r g a n i z at i o n — failed because diplomats couldn’t
make contact with an invisible armed opposition
and thought,wrongly as it turned out,that the war
would not end until apartheid disappeared in South
Africa.
The community reluctantly saw it had no choi-
ce but to act as a mediat o r. Lacking experi e n c e ,
it had to learn what to do as it went along. It inve n-
ted a “language of reconciliat i o n ” whose syntax
it picked up as a humanitarian organization wo r-
king for the poor.
S a n t ’ E gidio had discovered how to talk to all
kinds of people from its compassionate work in a
wide va riety of constantly changing situations in
which its members related to the poor, shared their
l i ve s , spoke their language, went to the same places
they did and regarded them not as we l fare cases bu t
as full members of society.
Turning weakness
into strength
Such a dialogue might be regarded as ineffective
when the resources to overcome pove rty are una-
va i l a b l e . But the community refuses to gi ve in to
these circumstances. E x p e rience has shown that its
mere presence can be vitally import a n t , e ven if it
d o e s n ’t lead to any immediate results. In the age of
the Intern e t ,i s o l at i o n , or solitude, is a serious ail-
ment of our time. Pe rsonal isolation or loneliness
can dri ve a person mad.The isolation of a move-
m e n t , a party or a country can lead to wa r , e s p e-
cially if the intern ational community stands idly by.
The persistence of wa rs in A f rica—in southern
S u d a n , for example—provides ample proof of this.
The community’s work has also taught it to be
p at i e n t .When the foreign minister of an import a n t
c o u n t ry travels to mediate in a gi ven situat i o n , he or
she has limited time yet their mission must lead to
r e s u l t s.They cannot risk failing because failure wo u l d
damage their credibility, because there is pressure
from public opinion or because elections are immi-
n e n t . But how can conflicts that have taken shape
over several decades be solved in a matter of months?
w Head of West Africa
Section,Sant’Egidio community
The culture of peace is
rooted in respect for
l a w ; in a spirit of
mutual respect,
goodwill and
t o l e r a t i o n ; and in the
acceptance that real
peace cannot be
achieved by threat 
or force.
F rederik Willem de Klerk, N o b e l
Peace Laureate 1993, S o u t h
African political l eader (1936-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
The community has no target date for results.
Peace negotiations started at the same time in
Angola and Mozambique. In A n g o l a , they we r e
completed in three and a half months, and it wa s
said that the talks in Mozambique were draggi n g
on.Many people told the mediator he was wasting
his time and theirs too.The negotiations were indeed
long—11 sessions over 27 months, b e t ween June
1990 and October 1992. E ve ry detail was careful-
ly scrutinized because the mediator regarded him-
self as a begi n n e r.To d ay the Mozambique peace
a greement is still holding, whilst sadly war has bro-
ken out again in Angola.
The community’s weakness is also its strong
p o i n t . It cannot mobilize an army or sign enorm o u s
c h e q u e s.This “ we a k n e s s ” is in fact a guarantee of
its sinceri t y — t h at all it’s interested in is peace-
m a k i n g, t h at it has no weapons except its belief in
f riendship and peace. So different sides come to
t rust it and talk about their problems freely, w i t h o u t
the restraints they would feel if dealing with offic i a l
bodies as part of the power plays that are inevitable
in such contacts.This fa m i l i a rity with the wa rri n g
p a rties goes hand in hand with the in-depth unders-
tanding of the societies in confli c t , especially in A f ri-
c a ,t h at Sant’Egidio has gathered from its local gr a s s-
roots communities.
A peace process is not just about negotiating and
then signing a document.The follow-up is extre-
mely complex.It involves development and demo-
c r a cy, r e c o n c i l i ation and rememberi n g . The 
community cannot do this by itself and has neve r
sought to do so. It does not believe in parallel diplo-
m a cy but in promoting a synergy of resources and
actions.
Gatherings to pray
for peace
A peace accord’s chances of success depend
mainly on those who sign it but also on civil socie-
ty and the intern ational climat e . So Sant’Egi d i o
encourages consistent and prolonged efforts by
m a ny other intern ational part i e s — g ove rn m e n t a l
and otherwise—to boost any peace process in which
it is invo l ve d .O b s e rve rs representing the United
N ations and the gove rnments of Italy, F r a n c e ,N o rt h
America, Portugal,the United Kingdom and even
South A f rica took part in the final stage of the
Mozambique negotiations.
These talks brought the community into the
limelight and it acquired a reputation and credibi-
lity that have since been used by wa rring part i e s
from Guatemala to Buru n d i , from Congo-Kinsha-
sa to Kosovo and A l g e ri a . In A l g e ri a , S a n t ’ E gi d i o
managed to bring Muslim enemies to the negotia-
ting table by using another of its methods, i n t e r - r e l i-
gious dialogue.
For more than a decade,Sant’Egidio has orga-
nized intern ational gat h e rings to pray for peace.
These are a key factor in the language of reconci-
l i ation because they build a genuine culture of inter-
r e l i gious peace. But Sant’Egi d i o ’s commitment to
peace continues to be an extension of its commit-
ment to fight pove rt y, to which it still devotes 80 per
cent of its efforts. n
The isolation of a movement,
a party or a country can 
lead to war, especially 
if the international community
stands idly by
Get up, stand up
Stand up for your rights
Get up, stand up
Don’t give up the fig h t !
Bob Marley, Jamaican musician
( 1 9 4 5 - 1 9 8 1 )
Andrea Riccardi,founder of the Sant’Egidio community, in one of the canteens where his movement provides
meals for the needy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 35
Le sida déferle: a l e r t e z les jeunes!International Y ar 2000: peace is in our ha ds
War and peace
For me, the culture of peace and the humanist values that I insist on are one and the same
t h i n g .N a t u r a l l y, the culture of peace includes the idea of the absence of wa r. Th a t ’s essential
because in a sense peace has become the luxury of developed societies.These societies have
managed to eliminate war from daily life, but only recently. My generation, now reaching the
age of 50,is the first in European history which has not set about killing each other. But war
hasn’t disappeared from everywhere in Europe—look at the former Yu g o s l a v i a .And certainly
not from the rest of the world, which is torn by dozens of armed conflicts which the media
only occasionally report on.We, the developed countries, are no longer at war, but the worl-
d ’s poor people are.The culture of peace is first and foremost about ending war because wa r
isn’t an abstract problem for most of humanity.
If we define war more broadly, to include personal daily violence, from the violence of chil-
dren in the United States who kill their schoolmates with guns to the violence that so many
women are still subjected to, then the culture of peace is part of a broad context of social pro-
b l e m s.Violence is at the root of our societies, and radical cultural change is needed to get rid
of it.The culture of peace is the most fundamental principle of our time, and one that’s easy
for anybody to understand and accept. M.C. n
Revolt against v i o l e n c e
Spanish sociologist Manuel Castells* thinks violence aggravated by globalization will trigger a
new wave of planet-wide opposition
* Mr Castells is professor of
sociology and city and regional
planning at the University of
California at Berkeley (USA).His
trilogy about information
technology and the global
economy, The Information Age:
Economy, Society and Culture,
has been published by Blackwell,
Oxford,UK.
The 3 volumes are: The Rise
of the Network Society (1996),
The Power of Identity (1997) and
End of Millennium (1998).
You predict that a multitude of what you call
ethical-pragmatic movements will gradually join
hands until they’re strong enough to counter the
negative effects of globalization.Do you think
they’ll grow into a kind of worldwide “grand
coalition”?
F i rs t , the word “ c o a l i t i o n ”here shouldn’t be unders-
tood in an organizational sense. I don’t see a sort of
huge intern ational solidarity organization emergi n g
to replace old-style working-class and political orga-
n i z at i o n s. But tools like the Internet could enable
these multifarious movements to keep in touch far
more effectively without coming under the kind of
bu r e a u c r atic control which organizations inevita-
bly deve l o p. I envisage stronger and more regular
interaction between active grassroots communities.
By being perfectly in tune with their own environ-
ments and at the same time connected by the Inter-
n e t , these communities will be capable of precise-
ly targeted activities,while still focusing from time
to time on major international efforts.
What is the basis of your prediction?
A process of eliminat i o n .H i s t o ry shows that injus-
tice and oppression always provoke a reaction.We
l i ve in a ve ry creat i ve wo r l d , where the wealth of
information is growing exponentially, but also in a
world that is increasingly unjust, o p p r e s s i ve and
a b s u r d .There is a huge contrast between the cur-
rent widespread violence and the unive rsal harm o-
ny we could achieve . So there must be a potential
for revolt.
A l s o, the political tools and organizations we ’ ve
used over the past century, especially gove rn m e n t s ,
h ave lost their legi t i m a cy.The vast majority of people
no longer trust them to do anything except follow
initiatives originating elsewhere.
C o l l e c t i ve mobilization against injustice and
oppression is not only inevitable but is already taking
shape—individualism and cynicism are defin i t e l y
not universal;social change is bound to come.But
because political systems are no longer capable of
spearheading it, it will come from outside, from these
m ovements which share humanist ideals and orga-
nizational innovations.
But doesn’t the idea of people coming together
conflict with the general trend towards indivi-
dualism?
Yes and no.Ye s , as far as the dominant ideology of
our advanced societies is concern e d .N o, b e c a u s e
if you take the world as a whole, this grouping of
forces is in tune with vast grassroots move m e n t s
of community solidarity based on spiritual va l u e s
and sense of identity. On the other hand, this col-
l e c t i ve force is radically different from insular gr o u p s
or movements based on exclusion of others. E ve n
if it only acts on a one-off basis it can find a place
for anyone who shares unive rsal values or who
believes in solidarity between humans and human
solidarity with nature.In fact that’s its hallmark.
Will it be strong enough to foster a strategy 
to counter the current shortcomings of globaliza-
tion?
I don’t think a united, c o h e r e n t , l o n g - t e rm strat e-
gy based on a kind of counter-programme is going
to emerge.That would just be harking back to old-
style militancy, an attempt to put new wine in old
b o t t l e s , something which an overwhelming majori-
ty of these new move m e n t s ’m e m b e rs reject.T h e y
will organize highly symbolic gat h e ri n g s , like that
which took place during the World Trade Organi-
z ation conference in Seattle in December 1999. B u t
b a s i c a l l y, they will continue to act in an unco-ordi-
n ated way, focusing on issues that are sometimes
local and sometimes global.By global,I mean eve-
rything from saving whales to fighting against sla-
very.
These movements are having an undeniable
effect on the process of globalizat i o n .The public
m o o d , at least in democratic societies, is playing a
key role. B a s i c a l l y, their most immediate action is
to change the prevailing values of public opinion.
They manage to get traditional political forces and
g ove rnments to adopt these va l u e s ,e ven in a somew-
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
h at mangled form , because movements use them as
a kind of common curr e n cy at election time.“ A d o p t
these values and we’ll urge people to vote for you,”
they say.Take the example of ecological va l u e s.T h e y
h ave emerged from a changed perception of our
r e l ationship with the env i r o n m e n t .They have ended
up influencing the political system to such an extent
that it has markedly changed its ways in the last 10
or 15 ye a rs , something it wo u l d n e ver have done on
its own.
So the state’s role will still be crucial?
D e fin i t e l y, and that ’s one paradox for these move-
ments which distrust the state so much. A n o t h e r
paradox is that if they were to give priority to pres-
s u ring states to change their policies, they would fa i l
because they would lose their influence in society.
The transmission mechanism does not run from
these movements directly to the stat e , but from the
m ovements to the society and from the society to
the stat e .Basically it’s through awa r e n e s s - c h a n gi n g
in society that they can make their mark.
So are we moving towards a politics which is
increasingly fragmented and fluid?
Yes indeed.And one in which political parties will,
at best, become interm e d i a ries instead of the ini-
t i at o rs they once we r e .They’ll be reduced to taking
the pulse of social movements and translating them
into options for gove rn m e n t . Pa rties unable to do
this will be swept away by the democratic system
because the control and monopoly of inform at i o n
are getting weaker all the time.C o n t r a ry to the recei-
ved wisdom, the media will increasingly report on
e ve rything that ’s going on in society because of the
emergence of countless networks of altern at i ve infor-
m at i o n .The end of the monopoly on inform at i o n
also means the end of gove rn m e n t ’s monopoly on
action. n
Interview by René Lefort,
Director of the UNESCO Courier
Radical French farmers’ leader José Bové holds an impromptu press conference.
Social change is bound to come.
But because political systems are
no longer capable of
spearheading it, it will come fro m
o u t s i d e, f rom these movements
which share humanist ideals and
o rganizational innovations
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
n
In “The Parable of the Mustard Seed”,
the Buddha teaches a lesson that is va l i d
for all cultures:human beings receive no
e xemption from mort a l i t y. Deep in the
throes of grief after the death of her son, a
woman seeks wisdom from the Buddha,
who says that he does indeed have an ans-
wer to her queri e s. Before giving it, h owe-
ve r , he insists that she must first collect a
grain of mustard seed from eve ry house that
has not been touched by deat h . She can-
vasses her entire community, but fails to col-
lect a single seed. R e t u rning to the Buddha,
she understands that , like all other living
beings, we are destined to die.
w Professor of Philosophy, Oregon State University,
USA
Staving off death may sometimes compromise a fundamental value, the quality of human life.
D e ath is a defining characteristic of
human experi e n c e .Ye t , while the event of
d e ath remains elusively beyond human
c o n t r o l , the process of dying has increasin-
gly been brought into the domain of medi-
cine and life-extending technologi e s. S o m e
t e c h n o l o gi e s , including organ transplan-
t at i o n ,r e s p i r at o rs , antibiotics like penicil-
l i n , and feeding tubes, enable life to be pro-
l o n g e d . Other technologies may hasten
death.
The decision to use these technologi e s
is a moral choice, because it invo l ves a deci-
sion about a fundamental human good, t h e
p r e s e rvation of life.Ye t , in some situat i o n s ,
a resort to technology to stave off deat h
comes at a price of compromising another
fundamental human va l u e , the quality of
t h at life. Decisions about continuing treat-
ment for the dying or of allowing death to
take place by foregoing or term i n ating such
t r e at m e n t , or even by phy s i c i a n - a s s i s t e d
suicide or euthanasia are thus both existen-
tially and ethically agonizing.As individuals
and their families face these controve rs i a l
questions and as many countries consider
revising their laws on end-of-life choices,
r e l i gious traditions and values can offer gui-
dance and insight, if not solutions.
H i s t o ri c a l l y, r e l i gious communities have
sought to appropri ate death within the life
cycle through rituals of remembrance, a n d
r e l i gious teachings have emphasized that
d e ath brings meaning to mort a l i t y.The pro-
cess of dying is often port r ayed as an inv i t a-
tion to spiritual insight and a key moment
EU T H A N ASIA 
A ND REL IGION
w Courtney S. Campbell
The advance of technologies to prolong life and control dying can raise agonizing 
moral dilemmas. What guidance is offered by the great world religions?
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
making capacity, but also by relat i o n s h i p s
(with loved ones, for example) and bodily
i n t e gri t y. These characteristics support
human responsibility in addressing end of
life decisions, including refusals of medical
procedures that invade the body with no
real benefit , in the context of a caring com-
m u n i t y. Put another way, p r e s e rving life is
not an absolute good in and of itself. Life is
a good that opens the way to achieving
higher goods that constitute the religi o u s
self.
So by looking within the moral para-
meters set by these three values of soverei-
g n t y, s t e wa r d s h i p, and the self, we find that
a patient can decide to forego life support.
A doctor can also allow a patient to die if
the continuation of life (by technologi c a l
means) assaults the dignity of the pers o n —
if it attacks their rationality, freedom,rela-
tionships with others or their bodily inte-
gri t y.C e rt a i n l y, differences can be discern e d
between these traditions precisely over the
p ri o rity of these goods.For example, O rt h o-
dox Jewish thought emphasizes the sancti-
ty of life (as displayed in bodily integri t y )
which translates into a stronger commit-
ment to life-extending technologies than in
Roman Cat h o l i c i s m , which stresses the
capacity for human relationships as a thre-
shold for determining the permissibility of
stopping life support.
The monotheistic faiths have also focu-
sed a gr e at deal on the legalization of phy-
sician assistance in hastening death by pro-
viding a terminally ill patient with a lethal
p r e s c ription of medicat i o n . In each instan-
c e , arguments supporting phy s i c i a n - a s s i s-
ted suicide have to overcome a long-stan-
ding prohibition of suicide. For a va riety of
r e a s o n s , suicide is sinful according to the
three traditions. Suicide constitutes a wrong
against one’s nature and personal dignity
( “ r e l i gious self” ) . It also harms the com-
munity and violates the sovereignty of God.
As a result, a physician assisting in suicide
may be seen as a moral accomplice in evil,
u n d e rmining the sacred covenant of the
healer.
H owe ve r , some faith communities in
Protestant Christianity and in Reform e d
Judaism have argued otherwise.When fa c e d
with terminal illness, one may well be dis-
posed to ending life, and one’s immediat e
community (or family) may support this
method of deat h .These kinds of arguments
38 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
E T H I C S
in the cultivation of spiritual identit y.
The wo r l d ’s gr e at traditions of moral
wisdom all begin with a strong predisposi-
tion to favour the preservation of life,
although the specific reasons for this conv i c-
tion va ry from tradition to tradition.Tu r-
ning first to three monotheistic religious tra-
ditions which have had global influ e n c e ,
J u d a i s m ,C h ristianity and Islam, for all their
d i f f e r e n c e s , basically address ethical issues
concerning the end of life from a common
value pers p e c t i ve . In part i c u l a r ,d i s c u s s i o n s
centre on the values of sove r e i g n t y, s t e-
wardship, and the self.
S overeignty denotes that the lives and
bodies of persons are created by, and ulti-
m ately return to,G o d .We owe our existen-
ce to a loving Being who has gr a c i o u s l y
brought us into being. T h u s , the funda-
mental passages in human life, i n c l u d i n g
b i rth and deat h , are of divine concern .T h i s
u n d e rstanding of sovereignty has signific a n t
i m p l i c ations for decision-making at the end
of life. It bestows sacredness upon human
l i f e , which supports the impulse towa r d s
p r e s e rving life by available medical tech-
n o l o gi e s.Yet sovereignty also entails that the
ultimate authority for deciding our mortal
passages belongs to God. Human beings
must not ove rstep these boundari e s , or so
to speak “play God”with life and death.
‘Agents of God’
Through the value of stewa r d s h i p, we
are considered “agents of God”, called to
c a rry out the work of divine intent on eart h .
This task entails decision-making respon-
sibilities for which we are accountable:our
actions either further or violate divine intent.
In addition, as emphasized in Islamic tea-
c h i n g,we are the trustees or stewards of our
b o d i e s.We are therefore entrusted with the
capacities and responsibility to make appro-
p ri ate decisions when confronting a treat-
ment choice at the end of our own life or
that of a loved one.
I n d e e d , with ve ry few exceptions, t h e
major faith traditions of the West have rejec-
ted a view known as “ v i t a l i s m ” , which holds
t h at biological life is to be preserved at all
costs and with all available technologi e s.
Vitalism is considered theologically mista-
ken because it appears to make divine will
and intent contingent upon the state of
medical technology. In other wo r d s , it puts
technology in the role of God.
The dignity of pers o n s , linked to the
notion of “ s e l f” , is another core value of
these monotheistic faith traditions. In Je w i-
sh and Christian thought,this is expressed
in the idea that humans are distinctively in
the “image of God”.Islamic theology does
not use such language, but no less affirm s
the significant value of pers o n s.The “ r e l i-
gious self” is constituted in part by the per-
s o n ’s rat i o n a l i t y, f r e e d o m , and decision-
stress the dignity of the individual as a free
decision-maker (which also applies to per-
sons entrusted with the decision-making
responsibilities of others ) .This dignity pro-
vides the basis for a political and philoso-
phical claim to self-determ i n ation and opens
the possibility for choosing the timing, cir-
cumstances and method of one’s deat h .S o
p hysicians may be permitted to hasten deat h
by prescribed medicat i o n s , or even by admi-
nistering lethal medication.Yet they would
never be obligated to do so.
M a ny religious communities have
denounced the question of legalizing phy-
sician euthanasia,or administrating death.
The most vigorous opposition has come
from the Roman Catholic tradition, w i t h
Pope John Paul II describing euthanasia as
an example of the “culture of deat h ” in We s-
t e rn societies.The Pope believes euthana-
sia is a manifestation of social views that
h ave abandoned the protection of life and
lent support to liberalized abort i o n ,c a p i t a l
punishment,and incessant warfare. In
g e n e r a l , much religious opposition is based
on concern for patients who may be in vul-
nerable positions because of their illness or
their lack of social and economic resources.
There is fear that patients who cannot afford
e x p e n s i ve treat m e n t , for example, will be
pressured to accept euthanasia.There is also
gr e at concern about the moral nature of the
d o c t o r ’s professional self. Islamic teaching,
for example, stresses the phy s i c i a n ’s com-
mitment or covenant to healing. E u t h a n a-
sia would violate this sacred role.
Although few in number, there are indi-
vidual theologians within both the Je w i s h
and Christian traditions for whom eutha-
nasia is not a contradiction but a culmina-
tion of religious values such as compassion,
mercy, and love.By joining these values to
respect for self-determ i n at i o n , some theo-
l o gians can find a way of tolerating eutha-
nasia as a final resort.
Eastern faith traditions
To die we l l ,s ay the teachers of eastern
r e l i gi o n s , one must live we l l .The views of
e a s t e rn religious traditions and philosophies
h ave been ve ry influential in global unders-
tanding about providing appropri ate care
to the dying. For example, the pioneeri n g
work of the Swiss-born psychiat ri s t
D r. Elisabeth Kubler-Ross in unders t a n-
ding the experiences of dying patients in
We s t e rn medical institutions drew direct-
ly on understandings of the meaning of
“good death”and “stages”in life in Hindu
t r a d i t i o n . Buddhist values of compassion,
n o n - v i o l e n c e , and suffering have also
i n fluenced the discourse of We s t e rn medi-
cal ethics.The ethical tension in these two
traditions about end-of-life choices is roo-
ted in two main va l u e s ,l i b e r ation and a h i m-
sa (non-violence).
Judaism, Christianity
and Islam basically address
e t h i cal issues concerning
the end of life from
a common value perspective
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
In Hinduism and Buddhism, h u m a n
beings are captured in endless cycles of
r e b i rth and reincarn ation (k a rm a - s a m s a ra) .
The goal of mortal life is detachment from
the mat e rial wo r l d ,c u l m i n ating in the libe-
r ation of the true self from the body-mind
c o m p l e x .To experience the good life and
the good deat h , we must be constantly
aware of the ultimate trajectory towa r d s
liberation.
In both traditions, all living creat u r e s
( h u m a n s , a n i m a l s , p l a n t s , e t c.) represent
manifestations of the laws of karmic rebir-
t h .To honour these law s , one must show
gr e at respect for the preservation of life and
n o n - i n j u ry of sentient beings. Acts des-
t ru c t i ve of life are morally condemned by
the principle of a h i m s a, which is the concep-
tual equivalent of the We s t e rn principle of
the sanctity of life. In most circumstances
ahimsa b e a rs a moral bias towards life-pre-
s e rvat i o n .Yet there is some ethical fle x i b i l i-
ty which opens the possibility of foregoing
t r e atment or seeking assistance to hasten
death.
As a general ru l e , both Hinduism and
Buddhism oppose suicide as an act of des-
t r oying life. H owe ve r , a distinction is made
in both traditions between self-regarding
(or self-destru c t i ve) reasons and other-
regarding (or compassionate) motives for
seeking deat h .To commit suicide over the
loss of a child or because of economic hard-
ship (self-regarding reasons) is to commit
a morally reprehensible act which refle c t s
the individual’s ignorance about the nat u-
re of life and human destiny. Instead of
achieving the ultimate spiritual goal of libe-
r at i o n , a person who acts in this way will
remain trapped in the ongoing karmic cy c l e
of life-deat h - r e b i rt h .Those who assist in
this suicide may also be subject to karm i c
p u n i s h m e n t , for they have violated the pri n-
ciple of ahimsa.
H owe ve r , a ve ry different pers p e c t i ve
emerges when individuals seek death for
s p i ritual motive s , of which there are
basically two kinds.The first revo l ves around
c o m p a s s i o n ; c o n c e rn for the we l fare of
others as one is dying can be seen as a sign
of spiritual enlightenment. So a person can
decide to forego treatment to avoid impo-
sing a heavy burden of caregiving on fami-
ly or fri e n d s. He or she may also stop treat-
ment to relieve loved ones of the emotional
or economic distress of prolonged dying.
The spiritual goal of liberation can also
be seen as an ethical reason for seeking or has-
tening deat h . When physical sufferi n g
impedes self-control and lucidity, it is per-
missible to shorten life.Pain or lethargy might
cloud the awareness and consciousness at
d e ath that both Hindus and Buddhists belie-
ve is necessary to ensure a favourable rebir-
t h .Extreme suffering might also cause someo-
ne to be so attached to their mat e rial life
(bodily condition) that they cannot purs u e
the ultimate spiritual goal of liberation from
the mat e rial wo r l d .
This pat t e rn of reasoning—the pri m a-
cy of spiritual goals of liberation or com-
passion relat i ve to the preservation of life—
also applies to euthanasia through phy s i c i a n
injection or administration of a lethal dru g .
Hindu and Buddhist scholars have found
s u p p o rt for this so-called “ a c t i ve ” e u t h a-
nasia in their traditions by reflecting on the
meaning of death as a door to liberat i o n ,t h e
c u l m i n ation of life in detachment from the
m at e rial wo r l d .They then go a step furt h e r
by linking compassion to the norm of self-
similitude:“one should act towards others
as one would have them act toward one-
self”.So euthanasia can be seen as a com-
p a s s i o n ate act or a “ m e r cy killing” for a
dying person striving to the highest purp o-
se of human destiny, liberation.
A moral problem arises with euthana-
s i a , h owe ve r , if the administered medica-
tion renders the patient unconscious or
unable to comprehend their descent towa r d
d e at h .The patient is unaware precisely at
the moment when he or she should be most
s e n s i t i ve and receptive to spiritual teaching
and meaning. For these reasons, o t h e r
modes of bri n ging about death are prefe-
rable morally and religiously. n
To die well,
say the teachers
of eastern religions,
one must live well
Hindus and Buddhists believe that it may be permissible to shorten life when physical suffering impedes a patient’s self-control and lucidity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
n
“I wo u l d n ’t think of trading n ow, in spite
of the constant shortage of money and
the incessant struggle to find it, for the
seemingly carefree t h e n with its guaranteed
100 per cent budget allocat i o n ,” s ays Mikhail
P i o t r ov s k y,director of St. Pe t e rs bu r g ’s Stat e
H e rmitage Museum.
P i o t r ovsky knows what he is talking
a b o u t , because he has seen, and has been to,
both wo r l d s.The son of the Herm i t a g e ’s pre-
vious long-time director, P i o t r ovsky was vir-
tually born in the museum, which is housed
in the magnificent imperial Winter Pa l a c e
and is home to one of the wo r l d ’s richest art
c o l l e c t i o n s. He trod all 350 rooms of the
palace as a toddler,and inherited his fat h e r ’s
d e d i c ation to the ancient art of the Ori e n t .
From early childhood he was also expo-
sed to museum administration as a kind of
family bu s i n e s s. “My father did not have to
think of all the countless financial problems
we are facing now,” he say s.“But eve ry step
he took had to be approved by Ministry of
Culture bu r e a u c r ats in Moscow.The cur-
rent lack or shortage of funding is the pri c e
we pay for freedom to make our own deci-
s i o n s.We must preserve this freedom.”
Although this idea sounds like simple
common sense, it is revo l u t i o n a ry for the
H e rmitage even now. For nearly two and a
half centuri e s , since its beginning as a
modest domestic collection of Russia’s impe-
rial Romanov dynasty, the Hermitage wa s
an ivo ry tower of art , far removed from the
mundane and ignoble need to earn its daily
b r e a d . It was cheri s h e d , both by the T s a r ’s
g ove rnment and later by the Po l i t buro of the
ruling communist part y, as a symbol of the
s t at e ’s wealth and might, and promptly and
regularly received generous budget alloca-
t i o n s.
The break-up of the Soviet Union at the
end of 1991 brought freedom from we a ri-
some bu r e a u c r ats but also brought the digni-
fied museum up against an entirely new pro-
b l e m : chronic failure by the gove rnment to
f u l fil its budget obligat i o n s. E ven in relat i-
vely stable 1996, the gove rnment approve d
$40 million instead of the $60 million the
museum requested.W h at the museum recei-
ved in fact totalled no more than $18 mil-
l i o n . In 1997, n ow looked back upon as the
most successful year in Russia’s post-com-
munist history, the Hermitage requested $90
m i l l i o n , $30 million were approved and a
m e a gre $12 million actually allocat e d . I n
1 9 9 8 , $7.4 million were requested and $ 5 . 4
million were approve d , but the Museum
actually received only $2.7 million.
H owe ve r ,P i o t r ovsky remembers 1992,
when he was appointed director, as the most
d i f ficult ye a r.This was not only because he,
a distinguished scholar in Arabic history,
was suddenly faced with tedious routine
a d m i n i s t r at i o n , but also because the Her-
m i t a g e , like the rest of Russia’s cultural ins-
t i t u t i o n s , had to learn how to swim in the
t u r bulent wat e rs of the ruthless initial stage
of the market economy. Subsidies were dras-
tically cut; there was ru n away
i n flat i o n ; and there was not even enough
money for basic maintenance of the bu i l-
d i n g, let alone expanding and deve l o p i n g
the collection.
An influx of advisers and part n e rs did
not make decision-making any easier.T h e y
often made contradictory recommenda-
t i o n s , and their business reputations we r e
d i f ficult to ve ri f y.T h e n , along with the Bol-
shoi T h e atre and Moscow ’s Lenin Library,
the Hermitage was selected as a UN E S C O
flagship project in Russia.An intern at i o n a l
team of experts headed by Edmund (“Te d ” )
P i l l s bu ry, f o rmer director of the Kimbell
Museum of A rt in Fo rt Wo rt h ,Te x a s ,c a m e
to St.Pe t e rs bu r g .This team eventually deve-
loped into the Intern ational A d v i s o ry Board,
which now compri s e s , under Pillsbu ry ’s
c h a i rm a n s h i p, a group of respected fig u r e s
in the intern ational museum world inclu-
ding former and current directors of the
L o u v r e , the National Galleries in Wa s h i n g-
ton and London, the Philadelphia A rt
M u s e u m , and the Rijksmuseum in A m s t e r-
d a m .The board, whose members all wo r k
on a vo l u n t a ry basis, meets in St. Pe t e rs bu r g
once a year.
Rembrandts restored
in Amsterdam
UNESCO used a massive development plan
worked out by the team as a foundation for
grant proposals, and in 1994 the first major
gift of $1.2 million came from the govern-
ment of the Netherlands.“The Dutch we r e
extremely enlightened,” r e m e m b e rs Stuart
Gibson,co-ordinator of UNESCO’s Hermi-
tage project.“They were interested in spen-
ding the money on a series of projects to
i m p r ove the management of the museum,
T HE HERMI TAGE COMES OU T
OF ITS SHEL L
w Alexander Kan
Long swathed in bureaucratic red tape and cushioned by hefty state funding, the great
St. Petersburg museum is adapting as best it can to the rigours of the global marketplace
w Russian journalist and editor 
with the BBC World Service
A TRE ASURE TRO V E
OF WORLD ART
176 4 : Russian Empress Catherine the Great buys
225 pictures by Dutch and Flemish masters for a
court museum in the Winter Palace, her new resi-
dence in St. Petersburg. This forms the nucleus of
a collection today totalling almost three million
objects mirroring cultures and civilizations from
the Stone Age to modern times.
18 52 : A building (later known as the New Her-
mitage) is added to house the main collections
and opened to the public by Tsar Nicholas I.
Other collections acquired include: Scythian gold
from south Russia (18 30 s on), Greek and Roman
antiquities (Rome, 18 61), Oriental, Byzantine and
medieval objets d’art (Paris, 18 8 4) .
1917 : The Winter Palace and the Hermitage beco-
me state museums.
19 41 : Nazi Germany attacks the Soviet Union. Tw o
million items evacuated to the Urals for safety. Pa r t
of the collections blocked by the siege of the city
stay in the museum and survive intact.
June 19 9 9 : The Hermitage opens a Web site
(w w w. h e r m i ta g e m u s e u m . o r g) giving access to
a digital catalogue of its collection: More than 3,000
works have so far been copied onto the site. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 41
including such boring but essential things
as accounting software and feasibility stu-
dies on hy d r o - i s o l ation of flooding in the
basement.”
The same grant made it possible for a
group of Hermitage restorers to take
the famous Rovinski collection—640 Rem-
brandt etchings and prints—for restorat i o n
at the Rijksmuseum in A m s t e r d a m , at the
same time making valuable contacts with
their Dutch colleagues. N ow a foundat i o n
in the Netherlands has decided that it wo u l d
be a good idea to raise money for a Herm i-
tage room or rooms in Amsterdam.A per-
manently rotating exhibition,called “Her-
mitage on the Amstel”,is in the works.
In October 1999 it was announced that
the Hermitage would take the same “ s at e l-
lite museum” idea to London, where it plans
to open a permanent exhibition space at
S o m e rset House, an 18th-century mansion
which is the home of the Courtauld Insti-
t u t e ,B ri t a i n ’s leading college of art history,
and a gallery with an outstanding collection
of Impressionist and neo-Impressionist
paintings.
F u n d r a i s i n g, a concept so new for Rus-
sia that a proper Russian term does not eve n
exist to describe it, is suddenly becoming
an increasingly important source of the Her-
m i t a g e ’s reve n u e s.While the federal contri-
bution to the annual budget keeps fa l l i n g
(from 70 per cent in 1997 to 61 per cent
in 1998),takings from the gate have fallen
e ven more drastically. In 1989 the Herm i-
tage had 3.5 million visitors ; in 1998 the
figure had plunged to 1.8 million.
Since most visitors are Russians, w h o
p ay a ve ry lenient 15 roubles (less than a
dollar) per ticket, takings cannot really pro-
vide a substantial slice of the budget.True,
foreign visitors have to pay considerably
more—250 roubles ($10), but Piotrov s k y
has no qualms about justifying this double
pricing policy.
“Russian citizens have already paid their
dues to the museum via taxe s ,” he say s ,“ s o
t h e y ’re fully entitled to a discount, and so
are children and students of any nationali-
t y.C riticism of double pricing usually comes
from tourist operat o rs who once used to bu y
our cheap tickets and resell them to forei-
gn tourists at a 1,000 per cent margin.”
Russians simply cannot afford more
In Catherine the Great’s winter Palace, above, there is only room to display 5 per cent of the Hermitage’s collections. Plans are now underway to provide additional space.
e x p e n s i ve tickets.The average monthly sala-
ry of a Hermitage curat o r , at 1,000-1,500
roubles ($40-$60) far from the lowest in the
country, proves the point.
Another potential source of reve n u e -
museum shops—has not been a pri o rity for
the same reason.While the Russian public’s
buying capacity remains ve ry low, m a j o r
i nvestment to develop proper merchandi-
sing would not be worthwhile.
This brings us back to fundraising, a n d
the extreme importance eve rybody I talked
t o — P i o t r ov s k y, G i b s o n ,P i l l s bu ry— at t a-
ched to the fact that the Herm i t a g e , firs t
among Russian cultural institutions, m a k e s
its annual budget,calculated with the help
of software purchased with the Dutch
g ove rn m e n t ’s gi f t , publicly available and
transparent.
“This is a revo l u t i o n a ry change,” s ay s
Nicholas Hoffman, an A m e rican fundrai-
sing specialist who helped the Herm i t a g e ’s
newly created Development Depart m e n t
to work out fundraising strat e gies and learn
the complex techniques of putting them into
practice.“There has been a dramatic lear-
ning curve . People at the museum have fig u-
red out that donors really have to see the
results of their money and feel confident it
i s n ’t being wa s t e d ,h i d d e n , mismanaged or
e ven stolen. So far the Hermitage has done
better than any other institution in Russia
The break-up
of the Soviet Union at
the end of 19 91 brought
the museum up against
an entirely new problem
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
at that . I t ’s not perfect, and it’s not nearly
as easy as it would be for a foundation to
gi ve money to, s ay, the Metropolitan
Museum of A rt in New Yo r k , if only becau-
se the Met has had 30 or 40 more ye a rs of
practice doing this.”
P i o t r ovsky likes to point out that 10
ye a rs ago, the overall budget of the Herm i-
tage was one per cent of that of the Metro-
politan.Now it’s 10 per cent—still in a dif-
ferent league, but he is justifiably proud of
the tenfold growth.
Among the more recent successful
m atches between the Hermitage and major
corporations is the elaborate bilingual web
site developed with the help of a two - m i l-
lion-dollar grant from IBM. And eve n
though the digital library represents so fa r
only a small share of the museum’s enor-
mous 2.5-million-exhibit collection, it is “ s o
advanced that it puts the Hermitage at the
forefront of the wo r l d ’s museums in the use
of computer technology,”c o n fidently claims
Dr. Pillsbury.
I couldn’t help asking Piotrovsky whe-
ther among the gr owing number of We s t e rn
d o n o rs and sponsors there are any mem-
bers of Russia’s burgeoning business com-
munity.“It takes generations for new busi-
ness people to become genuine art donors ,”
he says,“and it would be wrong to say that
Russian businesses are lining up to give us
their money. On the other hand, we recent-
ly had a major breakthrough— a seri o u s
donation from Vladimir Potanin,the foun-
der and owner of the United Export Import
Bank (UN E X I M) and one of Russia’s we a l-
thiest men.”
M r. Po t a n i n ’s office explained that his
d o n ation “will be used for creating the new
H e rmitage exhibition to be opened later this
year in the General Staff building.” Half of
this crescent-shaped neoclassical bu i l d i n g,
which along with the baroque Winter Pa l a-
ce forms St. Pe t e rs bu r g ’s Palace Square, h a s
been gi ven to the Hermitage and is sche-
duled to be developed in a project called the
G r e ater Herm i t a g e .The additional space
will increase the proportion of the collec-
tion on public display from the current five
per cent to 10-15 per cent.
The ori ginal idea was to create a new
Museum of Applied and Decorat i ve A rt to
ri val London’s V i c t o ria and A l b e rt Museum
and the Pa ris Musée des A rts Décorat i f s.
H owe ve r , museums of decorat i ve arts tend
to attract less visitors than collections of pain-
tings and sculpture.
Then the Intern ational A d v i s o ry Board
proposed a radical solution—to move the
famous Impressionist collection from the
Winter Palace to the new bu i l d i n g .The firs t
step has already been taken. Huge canva s e s
In 1998, 1.8 million people visited the Hermitage.
by French painters Maurice Denis and Pier-
re Bonnard, n e ver previously exhibited, a r e
on display in a few newly renovated rooms
of the General Staff bu i l d i n g .
“ R e l o c ating the Impressionists is abso-
lutely the right move ,”muses Russian art cri-
tic Kira Dolinina. “They have been tradi-
tionally exhibited on the second floor of the
Winter Palace with its low ceilings, c r a m m e d
into small rooms where in summer it is so
unbearably hot that the wardens have to
open the window s ,which damages the pain-
t i n g s.The collection is extremely popular
and in the new building it will be considered
in a new way. It is definitely wo rth a sepa-
r ate museum. But is it conceptually compa-
tible with the applied and decorat i ve arts? In
fact we are talking of two different museums.
The big museums that have recently exten-
ded their premises—the Rijksmuseum, t h e
L o u v r e , the National Gallery in London—
all found conceptual solutions before they
actually set out for the major move . For the
time being the artistic idea of the Great e r
H e rmitage looks ve ry va g u e .”
An ambitious project
M e a n w h i l e , the tireless Piotrovsky is set
on a more ambitious project. He has plans
for turning the entire Greater Hermitage into
a cultural and commercial centre with a
c o n c e rt hall, c i n e m a ,r e s t a u r a n t s ,h o t e l ,g a l-
l e ries and shops.The overall cost of the pro-
ject is estimated at $150 million, and Pio-
t r ovsky in his frequent visits to London and
New York is actively seeking inve s t o rs and
a deve l o p e r. This is a long-term project,
aimed rather at the museum’s 250th anni-
ve rs a ry in 2014 than the city’s tercentena-
ry in 2003.
So is the Hermitage an exceptional suc-
cess story in an otherwise dim Russian land-
scape? On the one hand it definitely is. A n
undisputed leader among Russian museums,
headed by a confid e n t ,i n t e rn ationally res-
pected director, it is slowly claiming its place
amongst the wo r l d ’s best, not only by the
scope and grandeur of its collection but by
the scale of its development plans. On the
o t h e r , it remains ove r burdened by an under-
d e veloped infrastructure and excess staff,
some of whom have trouble unders t a n d i n g
and accepting the ever accelerating pace of
c h a n g e .
So far the Hermitage has been able to
keep its yo u n g e r , competent and dedicat e d
staff who are prepared to moonlight as cab
d ri ve rs so that during the day they can return
to the world of art . In short , the museum is
a rather optimistic microcosm of the coun-
t ry it lives in. If the entire country can thru s t
itself into the third millennium as confid e n t l y
as the Hermitage seems to be doing, t h e
museum itself will have much less reason for
c o n c e rn . n
Fu n d raising is a concept so
n ew for Russia that a proper
Russian term does not
exist to describe it
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
n
On October 21, 1 9 9 9 ,S y rian securi t y
forces mounted an attack on the house
of President Hafez al-Assad’s brother
R i fa at in Lat t a k i e h . The latest of Syri a ’s
m a ny political vicissitudes, the event wa s
t riggered by an interview with a former U. S .
ambassador to Jordan which had been
broadcast on the Arab News Netwo r k
( A N N ) , a satellite TV channel run by
Rifaat’s eldest son Sumar.
D u ring the interview the ex-ambassa-
dor had expressed scepticism about the
capacities of the president’s son and heir
MIDDLE EAS T :
MEDIA PLURA L ISM
VIA SAT EL L I T E
w Christophe Ayad
Satellite TV channels are making inroads on state-run monopolies and widening programme
choice, but the number of households equipped with dish receivers is still generally low
w Middle East specialist
Bashar to succeed his fat h e r. E a r l i e r , i n
1997,a report on a reception given in Lat-
takieh by Rifa at in honour of Saudi A r a b i a ’s
C r own Prince Abdullah had provoked the
S y rian gove rn m e n t ’s wrath because it had
v i o l ated protocol and, e ven wo rs e , had been
broadcast on ANN.
Crumbling censorship
W h at e ver its real aim—inform ation or
p r o p a g a n d a — s atellite broadcasting has hel-
ped turn TV into a major factor in the poli-
tical life of a region which has never been
noted for audiovisual pluralism. ANN is
only one of the players in this process.
On the 50th anniversary of what Arabs
call the n a q s a (disaster)—the founding of
the Israeli state in 1948 after the A r a b
d e f e at—Arab viewe rs of the Middle East
Broadcasting Corp o r ation (MBC, see box )
were able to see the same documentary fil m ,
made by Bri t a i n ’s BBC, t h at the Israelis saw
on their national channel.
“The Jordanian gove rnment angri l y
denied the accuracy of a sequence in which
King Hussein was said to have wa rned Israel
of the imminence of a war in October 1973,”
s ays Jon A l t e rm a n , a programme officer in
the Research and Studies programme at the
U. S . Institute of Peace (USIP).
Satellite dishes have sprouted on the rooftops of Aleppo, in Syria.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
C O N N E X I O N S
“The main thing was that they couldn’t
censor it,” s ays A l t e rm a n .“In the long ru n ,
the obstacles to the freedom to inform and
be informed are gradually going to cru m b l e .
The ability of gove rnments to act as censors
is weakening year by ye a r ,e ven if countri e s
like Egypt and Jordan have recently passed
repressive press laws.”
G ove rn m e n t s , he feels, will at least have
to take account of public opinion in their
c o u n t ri e s , e ven if they do not set up real
d e m o c r a c i e s.“And those that hesitate most
about this will be left behind by the rest of
the world.”
The success of the Qatar satellite T V
channel A l - Jezeera is significant in this res-
p e c t . “It introduced discussions which sho-
wed a clash of contradictory opinions,” s ay s
Alterman.Since it was started in 1997,Al-
Jezeera has become a beacon of free expres-
sion in the Arab wo r l d , thanks to the pro-
fessionalism of its journ a l i s t s , who once
worked in the BBC’s former Arab Service.
And because Qatar is a small country, w h i c h
is ve ry rich but has no major geopolitical
interests to defend, it can afford to rub its
p owerful neighbours up the wrong way and
s e rve as a meeting-point for the Arab wo r l-
d ’s opposition politicians.The station has
even brought Qatar regional prestige.
Is this an exception which proves the
rule? Jo u rnalist Daud Kuttab does not share
this very “liberal”vision of steady progress
t owards democracy made possible through
free competition in the inform ation market.
Ku t t a b , who is highly respected in the A r a b
wo r l d , was the first chairman of Pa l e s t i n i a n
Television but was soon dismissed for his
independent approach. He was successive-
ly jailed by the Israeli army and the Pa l e s t i-
nian A u t h o rity and now runs the Je ru s a l e m
Film Institute.
A two-speed information society
He points out that many Arab sat e l l i t e
channels are simply offshoots of stat e - ru n
TV. “Most were set up just so that govern-
ments could extend their influence beyo n d
n ational borders.T h at ’s why they often only
broadcast classical music and a screen sho-
wing pink flamingos,with a small emblem
or a flag in the top left corner of the screen.
I t ’s also why they spend more money on the
technical side of broadcasting than on pro-
gramming.”
Such channels are also the last place an
independent Arab film-maker would go to
look for funding, he say s. For cost or poli-
tical reasons, p r o grammes (animal fil m s ,
u n c o n t r ove rsial feat u r e s , soap operas) are
mostly bought in Europe and the United
S t at e s.This has a schizophrenic effect on
v i e we rs : the gap between their own env i-
ronment and the pictures they see on the
screen is just as big whether they are loo-
king at a stat e - run national channel or sat e l-
lite channels.
Kuttab is just as sceptical about the role
of satellite channels in the emergence of
independent news report i n g . He has seen
no sign of this. Not long ago, a minister of
i n f o rm ation told him “I can change and
modernize as much as I want, but the first
item on the television news will always be
the daily report on the president’s activi-
t i e s.”This news programme will usually be
broadcast on the satellite channels of this
particular state.
Kuttab also thinks that satellite chan-
nels are first and foremost powerful we a-
pons that some states and politicians can
use against their neighbours or ri va l s. I n
fa c t , he say s ,“ e ven when the news they carry
is better and more va ried than on local chan-
n e l s , the aim is more to harm their enemies
than to inform the public.”Saudi channels,
for example, talk a lot about pluralism when
n e i g h b o u ring countries such as Yemen are
c o n c e rn e d , but say ve ry little about Saudi
internal politics.
The other danger, s ays Ku t t a b , is that
“these channels create a two-speed 
i n f o rm ation society where you have people
T HE MAJOR PLAY ERS IN ARAB SAT ELLITE TV
I t was during the 1990-1991 crisis in the Gulf that
pictures from the sky burst in on the Arab world
in a spectacular way. As in other regions, the confli c t
brought CNN with it and showed up local covera g e
as mediocre.
E gypt was the first to respond, in 1990, by using
its channel on Arabsat (a satellite launched in 19 8 6
by the Arab League) to broadcast a short progra m-
me for its troops involved in action against Iraq. The
government expanded the experiment by launching
soon afterwards the Egyptian Satellite Channel (ES C ) .
But it was the arrival on the scene of wealthy
Saudis that really marked the start of the “satellite
revolution”. In 1991, billionaire Saleh Kamel set up
MBC (Middle East Broadcasting Corporation), a
g e n e ral interest, non-subscription channel out of
London, which was later taken over by Walid and
Abdelaziz al-Ibrahim, two brothers-in-law of King
Fahd. In 1994, Kamel joined up with Prince al-Wa l i d
ben Talal ben Abdel Aziz and founded a group of
subscription-only channels called ART (Arab Radio
and Television). The third big private Saudi TV group
in the region is the Orbit group of channels, set up
in 1994 by Prince Fahd ben Abdullah ben Abdel Az i z ,
a nephew of the king.
These powerful initiatives were a spectacular
response to Egypt’s traditional domination of regio-
nal broadcasting. Throughout the 1960s, the Voice
of the Arabs, broadcasting from Cairo, had ca l l e d
for the overthrow of Saudi “reactionaries”.
Starting in the mid-1990s, most Arab countries
set up at least one satellite channel, which often pic-
ked up broadcasts from their national TV station.
E gypt made a special effort in 1998 by launching the
A rab world’s first national satellite, Nilesat, which
increased the number of special-interest channels
and enabled Egypt to impose its digital decoder on
the market. Another innovation in the late 19 9 0 s
was the appearance of all-news channels like Qatar-
based Al-Jezeera, founded in 19 97, and ANN (Ara b
N ews Network), started in the same year and run
by Sumar al-Assad, nephew of the Syrian president.
They have all been successful and Al-Jezeera has
emerged as the “CNN of the Arab world”. Its contro-
versial talk shows, open attitudes and spectacular
n ews presentation have won it a sizeable, though
hard to measure audience.
Lebanon is a special case. During the 1975 - 19 9 0
civil war, the country’s audiovisual facilities deve-
loped in complete disorder which encouraged plu-
ralism and free expression. In the mid-1990s, 
the authorities took things in hand again and 
d ra s t i cally reduced the number of broadca s t i n g
licences and divided up broadcasting on a politi-
cal and community basis. Today, two channels domi-
nate the market and have won a name for them-
selves outside Lebanon. They are LBCI (Le b a n e s e
B r o a d casting Corporation International), famous
for its professionalism and attractive women pre-
senters, and Fu t u r e -TV, owned by businessman and
former prime minister Rafiq Hariri.
Jon Alterman, an American academic, says
“nobody knows exactly how many people watch
the satellite TV channels, or who they are or what
they watch.” As yet there is no commercial and mar-
keting infrastructure. But one thing is certain: none
of them is making a profit, except perhaps Le b a-
non’s LBCI.
Al-Jezeera has given itself five years to balance
its accounts and to be privatized. The chances are
it will be bought back by its powerful benefactor and
founder, Sheikh Hamad ben Jassem ben Jabr al-
Thani, Qatar’s foreign minister. Pa y - p e r - v i ew chan-
nels like Orbit are a long way from making money.
C r e d i b i l i ty, audience size and benefactors’ fin a n c i a l
resources will serve as a natural selection process
in years to come. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
with access to inform ation from abroad and
the vast majority who have to make do with
o f ficial propaganda.” A l t e rman notes that
the numbers of households equipped to
r e c e i ve satellite TV are bound to increase
but they are still generally low.“In the Gulf,
t wo-thirds of the population have sat e l l i t e
d i s h e s , but only 20 per cent in Pa l e s t i n e ,
Lebanon and Jo r d a n , and only between 7
per cent and 10 per cent of Egyptians.”
So in Egypt, the Arab wo r l d ’s most
populous country but also one of the poo-
r e s t , access to a choice of inform ation is just
one more privilege for the ruling class. I n
a less  serious ve i n , Egyptian TV viewe rs last
summer could not see the matches of the
C o n f e d e r ations Cup, in which the Egyptian
football team was playing, because ART, a
group of subscription-only satellite chan-
nels (see box),had bought exclusive rights
to screen the matches.
The rare attempts to ban satellite recep-
tion have not amounted to much.In 1994,
the Saudi authorities tried to do this, f o r
commercial rather than political and moral
reasons (some satellite-transmitted fil m s
are seen as offensive to Islamic morality).
They were actually trying to promote the
interests of cable operators who were close
to the royal fa m i l y. L ater the gove rn m e n t
took a more tolerant view of satellite 
d i s h e s.To d ay, Iraq is the only Arab country
which has not entered the era of sat e l l i t e
television.
It cannot be denied that satellite chan-
nels are having profound effects on A r a b
s o c i e t i e s. For example, they help to creat e
w h at A l t e rman calls “a real basic identity”,
based on a common mental landscape and
references that are transmitted by the new
channels all over the Arab world and thus
transcend national frontiers.This identity
is much more sturdy than the one gove rn-
ments have hitherto tried to create by
“ b r a i n wa s h i n g ” .S atellite channels are also
a link between Arabs living in the region and
the Arab diaspora in the West.
Competition prises
open state-run channels
The appearance of a new kind of audio-
visual operat o r , albeit few and far betwe e n ,
has helped to transform the media scene.
“The competition has to keep up,” s ay s
A l t e rm a n . One example is MBC, w h i c h
“has clear links with the Saudi gove rn m e n t
but can no longer afford to appear as
the Voice of Riyadh if it wants to keep
its viewers.”
The new satellite channels are more
attractive and modern and have an impact
on the state monopolies. Douglas Boy d ,
who teaches in the Unive rsity of Kentuc-
k y ’s Communication Depart m e n t ,s ays the
lack of credibility of local media is the chief
reason for the popularity of satellite TV.
The competition from the sky has for-
ced the state-run channels to open up and
i n n ovat e .The official Egyptian TV channel
n ow screens a lot of talk shows which,
though uncontrove rs i a l , at least gi ve an
impression of public debate. Jordanian TV
has also gi ven air time to the monarchy ’s
fiercest opponent,Laith Shbelat ,r ather than
see him appear yet again on Al-Jezeera.
“ E ven Syria has seen remarkable pro-
gress in its television services over the past
15 ye a rs ,” s ays Nabil Dajani, a sociology
professor at the A m e rican Unive rsity of Bei-
ru t . In Qat a r , the ministry of inform at i o n
has simply been abolished.
“ Pa r a d ox i c a l l y, i t ’s the interaction of
c o n flicting interests, d e f e n s i ve gove rn m e n t
policies and competition between va ri o u s
channels which has increased pluralism,”
s ays Boy d .“A biased and narr ow pluralism
but an embryonic pluralism all the same.”
n
+…
Further information can be found in
“TBS-Transnational Broadcasting Studies”,
the electronic journal published by the American
University in Cairo’s Adham Centre for Television
Journalism: http://www.tbsjournal.com
Outdoor televiewers in Cairo. Only around 10 per cent of Egyptians have access to satellite TV.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
T A L K I N G  T O …
ethnic history.These connections are essen-
tial for a society to be capable of caring for
its most vulnerable members. Radical indi-
vidualism does not make for the kinds of
ties that are necessary for basic decency —
not for justice, e i t h e r , which is another two
stages away.
There is often tension between the left and
m i n o r i ty ethnic groups. These groups are
criticized for alienating the majority in a labour
union, for example, by raising issues of racism or
prejudice. They are told to leave their
“ i d e n t i ty politics” at the door and join the wider
cause of the poor. How do you draw the line bet-
ween identity politics and multicultura l i s m ?
There are a couple of different issues here,
one of which is the relation between class
and racial or ethnic identity. Class identity
used to be something not all that different
from what ethnic identity is today.The wo r-
king class used to have a language,a mode
of dress, and a set of values just like any eth-
nic group in A m e rican society today. It is
the decline of the cultural cohesiveness and
d i f f e r e n t i ation of the working class that has
so gr e atly weakened the union move m e n t
in the U. S .The union movement was neve r
simply a movement of people purs u i n g
interests,it was also a movement of people
who shared a way of life—a sense of identi-
ty.
E ven so, the distinction is commonly
made between economic interests (which
are supposedly rational and bring people
You’ve written a great deal in support of multi-
culturalism. In short, you describe systems in
which individuals wear different “hats”—that of
the citizen, a religious affiliation, a union, etc.—
and forge alliances with others in different
groups. While many critics claim that multicul-
turalism dilutes the common glue (national
identity) which binds society, you maintain that
the real culprit is rampant individualism.
A c t u a l l y, multiculturalism can work in both
directions. Some cultures are coercive and
need an individualist corrective.But when
individualism is all powe r f u l , the society
needs the corr e c t i ve of community and cul-
tural cohesion.
I was recently in Je rusalem—where an
Israeli leftist intellectual turned to a visiting
A m e rican communitarian political theori s t
and said:“ For yo u , community is a dream.
For us it is a trauma.” In Israel, the stru c-
ture of religious communities is so powe r-
ful that it divides the polity in fri g h t e n i n g
way s.Ve ry strong ethnic national and reli-
gious communities are often oppressive to
m a ny of their members , most import a n t l y
to women.To be committed to a democra-
tic society of which these women are sup-
posedly equal citizens, you have to find some
way to break into these communities and
reshape their internal life.The only agent
for doing that is the state and that means
you need a strong sense of citizenship and
common values in order to foster resistan-
ce or intervention in the groups.
And what about more individualist societies?
In the U. S . , for example, individuals are
radically focused on themselve s , on their
c a r e e rs , their part n e rs or a rapidly shifting
s e ries of part n e rs h i p s.The individual has
l i t t l e , if any, sense of being obligated or
connected.In such a society, there is a real
necessity to foster and strengthen the bonds
of community. For these bonds to be
a u t h e n t i c, they have to be local or parochial
in some sense.They aren’t going to connect
e ve ry A m e rican to eve ry other A m e ri c a n .
They connect much smaller groups of
people to one another—neighbours , fa i t h
communities or people with common
MICH A EL WA LZ ER :
A USER’S GUIDE
TO DEMOCRACY
A leading American political philosopher’s 30-year quest for a more just society
together) ve rsus birth and blood, c u l t u r e
and history (which separate people). It is
a common complaint on the left, to tell
people defending identity politics,“You’re
just getting in the way of the class struggle
and a rational defence of the interests of the
p o o r.” This isn’t entirely wrong because
identity politics is often ve ry divisive . But at
the same time, identity politics is a form
of egalitarian politics which must be held in
some kind of useful tension with class.W h e n
g ay men and women can live openly in a
society that has previously forced them into
invisibility, they are not just enjoying more
freedom.The society is more egalitarian.
How can we bring new groups into society?
It is important that the naturalization pro-
cess isn’t too long or discri m i n at o ry.T h e
old price for admission—especially in coun-
t ries like France—was that you had to leave
the old culture behind.You not only beca-
me a French citizen, you were supposed to
become French. In the United Stat e s ,a nyo-
ne who has gr own up in an immigr a n t
neighbourhood has felt that there was some-
thing shameful about the old culture.We
knew that our parents or gr a n d p a r e n t s
would stay aw k wardly representat i ve of
something that we were going to and had to
leave behind.It was an imposed surrender
of identity. Now we’ve raised the question:
can we redefine the terms of assimilat i o n ,
of democratic citizenship?
To be an A m e rican citizen, I have to
l e a rn the English language, study A m e ri c a n
history and learn about the political mores
of A m e ri c a n s. But what more is required?
H ow much of my old identities, c o m m i t-
ments and loyalties can I retain and eve n
c u l t i vate and still be within the body of citi-
zens? The terms are now being renegotia-
ted to the advantage of the incomers.T h e r e
are sure to be a lot of difficulties in that
negotiation but I think the product will be
a more egalitarian society.
At the same time, there are real demands
t h at have to be made on people entering a
democratic society.You can see that in any
r e l i gious fundamentalist example any w h e-
When gay men and women
can live openly in a society that
has previously forced them
into invisibility, 
they are not just enjoying
more freedom. The society 
is more egalita r i a n
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
January 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G  T O …
re in the wo r l d . R e l i gious fundamentalists
want their children to attend schools tea-
ching doctrines profoundly hostile to demo-
c r atic politics.And they often want the stat e
to pay for that education.The body of citi-
zens has the right to say,“But your children
are going to vote in our elections.They are
going to determine the fate of this country
and of our children. So we will insist that
you teach your children about the values of
d e m o c r atic politics, the right of opposition,
the plurality of part i e s , the freedom of argu-
ment and the history of democracy in this
country.”
You maintain that multiculturalism can
encourage social equality. Through political
activism, groups will forge alliances while pres-
sing ahead with their own interests. Yet you
never examine the ways in which
institutionalized racism can block the path
to equality. Why do you barely even mention
the word racism?
Racism may be too broad a term.The U.S.
is an immigrant society within which 
i m m i grants have been ve ry successful.T h e
conquered Nat i ve A m e ricans and the ensla-
ved black A m e ricans are the two groups that
A FISH OU T
OF WAT ER
One of the United States’ most renow n e d
political philosophers, 64-year-old Michael
Walzer is like a fish out of water. “Living in the U.S.,
where there is no leftist movement or social
democratic party, I have a rarefied political exis-
tence,” he says, explaining that his main activity
is to write: books and a constant stream of articles
for left-wing reviews, most notably as editor of D i s-
s e n t, a pillar of America’s intellectual landsca p e .
Unlike so many of his entourage of 19 6 0 s
activists who fashioned themselves as profes-
sors, Walzer was not a “red diaper baby” raised
by communist parents. Experience piqued the
p o l i t i cal awareness of this philosopher. Born in the
melting pot of New York City, Walzer was steeped
in multiculturalism with his family of Jewish shop-
keepers of Eastern European origin. Life veered
left at the age of nine with the family move to a
small Pennsylvanian steel and mining tow n ,
where the strength of the local labour unions
offered a vision of activism. Walzer’s formal poli-
t i cal education began at Brandeis University —
the first Jewish-sponsored university in the U.S.
and a refuge for leftist intellectuals subjected to
the McCarthyite red-hunts of the 1950s.
Next stop for Walzer: the civil rights move-
ment. Within a week of the first sit-in at a segre-
gated lunch counter, Walzer headed south to
write about the movement for Dissent. Within
months, he was involved in organizing northern
support for the movement while pursuing his
g raduate studies in political theory at Harvard Uni-
versity. In the mid-1960s when “white agitators”
were “pushed out of the civil rights movement,”
Walzer explains that he shifted camps to take an
active role in the anti-war movement against U.S.
intervention in Viet Nam. 
“The only way to survive as an American poli-
t i cal scientist,” says Walzer, “is to have one door
outside the academy through political action.” So
throughout his teaching career at Princeton Uni-
versity and Harvard, he has used his pen as a
lance, most importantly through D i s s e n t, “now a
movement magazine without the movement,”
he says. “But we keep going in the hope that we
will encounter our necessary alter ego somew h e r e
down the line.” A.O.  n
h ave been forcibly prevented but also disa-
bled from the inside in a va riety of way s. S o
they have not achieved anything close to
equal status in the society. But the A s i a n
A m e ricans are doing fa bulously well and
yet they initially encountered a racist res-
p o n s e . And I would guess that Hispanic
A m e ricans will ove rtake both black A m e ri-
cans and Nat i ve A m e ricans in terms of eco-
nomic well-being in the near future. So the
problems of American society are the pro-
blems of the two non-vo l u n t a ry immigr a n t
groups—those did not choose, t h at were not
able to choose, to be part of this society.Yo u
can tell long stories about the diffic u l t i e s
va rious immigrant groups have encounte-
r e d . But I don’t think the story about insti-
tutionalized racism helps to explain the dif-
ference betwe e n , s ay, the Irish and the
Japanese.
You reject affirmative action programmes assu-
ring minority representation in
universities, for example. What then are the
alternatives for redistributing resources?
There is a reason for the success of affir-
m at i ve action. It is inexpensive and doesn’t
make any demand on social resources. I t
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The UNESCO Courier - January 2000
T A L K I N G  T O …
wo r l d , it would be a huge gain.Then you can
work towards higher levels of mutuality.
Most philosophers on the left seem panicked by
the rise of tribalism since 1989. Why aren’t you
so alarmed?
All forms of parochialism or particularism
are dangerous. A parent’s love for a child
can produce gross injustice and spaw n
f o rms of favo u ritism and nepotism.Yet yo u
wouldn’t want to give up on parental love.
The tri b a l , ethnic or national forms of par-
t i c u l a rism have gr e ater dangers than favo u-
ritism or nepotism because of the command
of resources and weaponry.There is some-
thing to wo rry about.But many leftists have
made the gr e at mistake of opposing eve ry
f o rm of part i c u l a ri s m .This is like setting
yourself against humanity itself.
Consider the hypothetical argument of
m a ny philosophers on the left: I suddenly
find myself in the situation where my child
and another child whom I don’t know are in
d a n g e r. If I can only rescue one, the ri g h t
thing to do, according to these philosophers ,
would be to toss a coin to decide which child
to save .But it’s not possible to turn that from
a philosophical position to a real-life
d e m a n d . It doesn’t recognize forms of
attachment that are natural to human beings.
We have to find a way of living with tri-
bal loyalties that develop historically among
groups of people.This is the 17th-century
English philosopher John Locke’s ori gi n a l
argument for tolerat i o n . Living in an age of
r e l i gious civil wa rs , he said: establish a regi-
me of tolerat i o n .G i ve each community the
right to wo rship as it wants to, in its ow n
bu i l d i n g s , without interference.With this
one thing, he said, you will end the wars.
We have to experiment with forms of
b e n e fits a small, mostly yo u n g e r ,s u b s e c t i o n
of black A m e ricans and creates a small,
r ather vulnerable, black middle class.At the
same time,it avoids the kind of investment
t h at would be necessary for improving the
l e vel of inner city schools, or for changi n g
the racial hierarchy in the U.S.
The rectific ation of inequalities requires
a political movement far bigger than the
black community. But gi ven the political
context in the U. S . , there isn’t going to be
in the near future a significant redistri bu-
tion of resources to individuals. H owe ver it
might be possible to organize a redistribu-
tion to gr o u p s. For example, a signific a n t
p a rt of the A m e rican we l fare state is run by
r e l i gious communities through hospitals,
n u rsing homes, and day-care centres.W h e n
the Republican majority in Congress began
cutting the we l fare budget in 1995, the lou-
dest screams of protest came from the cha-
ritable organizations of the Lutherans,
C atholics and Jews—the three most suc-
cessful groups in getting money for we l fa-
re services from the state—which prov i d e d
in fact something like 60 per cent of their
charitable budgets.
W hy shouldn’t black Baptists control
the same share of tax money as white Luthe-
rans or Catholics or Jews? These other
groups have gr e ater organizational powe r ,
and a long history of collecting this money—
so it’s going to take a deliberate political
decision to make it available to black Bap-
t i s t s. I am not religious myself but I reco-
gnize that these religious institutions are
socially useful.We saw this in the 1960s
when the whole civil rights movement was
run out of the Baptist churches in the sou-
t h e rn tow n s. N ow they might serve as agents
of redistribution.
Tolerance is becoming a buzz-word, sometimes
sounding like a polite way of accepting the
u n a c c e p table. Shouldn’t we strive towards
something more?
The crucial thing is not tolerance but tole-
r at i o n .Tolerance is a mental attitude bu t
t o l e r ation is a set of arr a n g e m e n t s. I think
t h at the attitudes matter less and will come
in time if you get the politics right—if yo u
find the right regime of tolerat i o n . T h i s
reminds me of a Puritan sermon (from the
1630s or 40s) against divo r c e . It said  sim-
p l y : if you hold the estranged couple toge-
ther long enough, something will happen
t h at makes the marriage possible. I don’t
b e l i e ve that about marri a g e , but it may be
t rue for the less intimate coexistence of
gr o u p s. If you force Greeks and Turks to live
together for 200 ye a rs , there is going to be
commerce and friendship and even inter-
m a rriage across the borders—if the politi-
cal regime is successful and imposes peace.
My stress is not on mutual respect but on
peaceful coexistence. S t a rt there. In today ’s
“The conquered Native Americans and the enslaved black Americans… have not achieved anything close to
equal status in American societ y.”
‘Give each community
the right to worship 
as it wants to,
in its own buildings,
without 
interference. 
With this one thing, 
you will end the wars.’
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
a u t o n o my and federation—and we must do
so quickly. Somebody has to be able to move
into places like Kosovo to find forms of poli-
tical association to gi ve vulnerable
communities some room of their ow n . I t
s h o u l d n ’t always be sovereignty or political
independence—there can be many form s
of autonomy and federal gove rn m e n t .We
had better start experimenting because we
T A L K I N G  T O …
are not going to eliminate tribal feelings.
Politics is the art of finding arr a n g e m e n t s
that accommodate those feelings.
You once wrote, “We become social critics 
naturally, by elaborating on existing moralities
and telling stories about a society more just
than our own.” You have been telling stories for
more than 30 years. How have they changed?
It has gotten harder to tell stories about
societies more just than your ow n . N o t
because my own society has gotten more just
but because there has been such a massive
loss of faith in the altern at i ve visions that we
used to refer ours e l ves to.The democrat i c
left longed for the collapse of communism.
We always believed that the fall of those
r e gimes would immediately open oppor-
A record number of immigrants to the U.S. were naturalized in 1996. Above some of the 10,000 “new Americans” who attended a mass naturalization ceremony 
at Texas Stadium, Irving (Texas).
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER
"
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15€) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396French francs ( 6 0 . 35 €) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 72FF ( 11€) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10€)
2 years: 211FF ( 32 .15 €) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. — — — — — — — — — — — — — — — — Expiry date: — — — — — — — —
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:                  Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O …
tunities for a “third way”—a socialism that
d i d n ’t rely on the state but encompassed a
decentralized and highly part i c i p at i ve form
of democratic politics, with wo r k e rs ’c o n t r o l
of fa c t o ries and new social movements like
feminism and env i r o n m e n t a l i s m .
But instead of opening this new pat h ,
1989 unexpectedly brought a crisis of fa i t h
in any sort of radical altern at i ve .The stori e s
of more just societies now sound like uto-
pian fa n t a s i e s. So before we can start telling
those stories again, we ’ ve got to argue that
there are forms of life different from what
we see around us which are still sociologi-
cally or economically feasible.
I don’t mean to sound gri m . Po l i t i c a l
o p p o rtunities often take shape in unexpec-
ted way s.We always misjudge the time inter-
va l s. 1989 came sooner than we thought and
the opportunities may come lat e r.
Maybe you’re also a bit nostalgic for the excite-
ment and activism of the 1960s and 70s. What
about the new forms of opposition developing
at the international level around a wide range
of single issues—from genetically modified
crops to human rights abuse?
(With a broad smile and a chuckle.) Yo u
m ay be always nostalgic for those moments
of exhilarat i o n . But there certainly are new
f o rms of organization with groups functio-
ning in a space that is beginning to be cal-
led intern ational civil society.They recru i t
m e m b e rs from different countries and act
across boundaries even though they are
most often trying to bring pressure on spe-
c i fic national gove rn m e n t s. But it is not clear
t h at these organizations can be fully part i-
c i p at i ve and democrat i c. Instead of active
m e m b e rs , they have a dues-paying mem-
b e rship which supports the work of a 
highly mobile, professional staff. Po l i t i c a l
activism often amounts to little more than
signing a cheque.I am not sure that this is
the kind of activism that makes for demo-
cratic decision-making.
How do you account for this decline in acti-
vism?
In the U. S . , for example, political part i e s
used to operate at many different leve l s —
the stat e , city and even the precinct (neigh-
b o u r h o o d ) .When you have a party art i c u-
l ated with activists at eve ry leve l , you can be
pretty sure of that group of people’s abili-
ty to hold leadership responsible.The broa-
der the activism, the wider the responsibi-
lity of the leadership.
To d ay, the precinct party offices are
g o n e .You have a candidate and an entou-
rage of publicity and make-up people who
function like a commando unit.They des-
cend on a place in time to make the eve n i n g
TV news and then depart .There is no local
structure to hold them responsible.
An altern at i ve might be a civil society
a rt i c u l ation of democratic politics. I n s t e a d
of relying on party structures which are so
far removed from local communities, c i t i-
zens might form associations through
c h u r c h e s , unions or philanthropic gr o u p s
to press for their demands and hold politi-
cal leaders responsible.
When describing the “good life”, most
philosophers offer sweeping reflections
on universal principles and ideals. Yet you
focus strictly on the nuts and bolts of political
arrangements. Why?
I t ’s a feature of We s t e rn philosophical, r e l i-
gious and more recently political tradition
to focus on the good society and the good
life where that definite article is ve ry defi-
nite and singular in character. Monotheis-
tic religion with its notion of the messianic
kingdom contri butes to that singular
conception which the left inheri t e d . M o s t
people who talk nowa d ays about the good
society are on the left.
I have never believed that there could be
either a definite or a singular picture of the
good life.You could tell stories of good live s.
You could point to people who had live d
we l l .You could describe a va riety of good
societies in move m e n t s , communities and
even states. But given the immense variety
of human beings and the extraordinary crea-
tivity of humanity, it never seemed plausible
to think there can be one way of living, o r
one correct form of social organization.n
Interview by Amy Otchet,
Unesco Courier journalist.
SEL ECT
BIBL IOGRA PH Y
Just and Unjust Wa r s ( 1977, second edition
1992), S p h e res of Justice ( 1983), I n t e r p re t a t i o n
and Social Criticism ( 19 87), Thick and Thin: Mora l
A rgument at Home and Abroad ( 1994), On To l e-
ration (1997). n
+ …
For more information on D i s s e n t : h t t p : / /
www.igc.apc.org/dissent/
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George's Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Brussels. 
Fax: 538 08 41.
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa Po s t a l
6 2 . 591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
Oxford Book & Stationery Co, Code No D 820 8 0 52, Scindia House, New
Delhi 110 001. Fax: 33 22 639 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Nalanda Co. Ltd., 30 Bourbon Street, Port Louis. 
Fax: 212 1313 .
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
Los Amigos de la UNES CO, Avenida Urquijo 62, 2 Izd., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 94427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG, Wissenschaftl. Buchhandlung, Pe t e r s g raben 31, 
CH-4009 Basel. Fax: 306 12 34 .
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham MD
2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce
C/C Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: 286 03 26 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
Book/Livre/Libro: 120FF /19.28 €
+ 30 FF /4.57 € postage/frais d’envoi/franqueo
CD-ROM: 120 FF /19.28 €,
postage included/frais d’envoi compris/franqueo incluido 
Book/Livre/Libro + CD-ROM: 180 F F /27.44 €
+ 30 FF /4.57 € postage/frais d’envoi/franqueo 
Études à l’étranger 
2000–2001
3 1E ÉDITION    LIVRE ET CD-ROM (PC/MAC)
Le guide international de l’UNESCO pour tout savoir
sur les possibilités d’études supérieures et sur 
les bourses offertes par les universités, les institutions
spécialisées et les organisations internationales
| Une référence unique depuis 1948
| 2 600 cours dans 124 pays
Toutes les disciplines académiques 
et professionnelles au niveau supérieur  | Adresses
et références, y compris adresses électroniques 
et sites Internet  | Conditions d’admission  | Dates
d’inscription  | Frais d’études et coût de la vie 
dans chaque pays  | Bourses et assistance financière
| Statistiques sur les universités.
| Informations en anglais, français ou espagnol
selon le pays
U N E S C O  P u b l i s h i n g
Edic iones U N E S C O
Éditions U N E S C O
Study abroad 
2000–2001
31ST EDITION    BOOK AND CD-ROM (PC/MAC)
The UNESCO international guide to higher-education
study opportunities and scholarships offered by universi-
ties, specialized schools and international organizations
| A reference since 1948
| 2,600 courses in 124 countries
All higher-education academic and professional
disciplines  | Addresses and references, including 
e-mail and websites  | Admission requirements  |
Application deadlines  | Scholarships and financial aid
| Fees and living expenses in each country | Various
statistics concerning the institutions.
| Entries in English, French or Spanish according 
to the country
Estudios en el extranjero
2000–2001
31.A EDICIÓN    LIBRO Y CD-ROM (PC/MAC)
La guía internacional de la UNESCO indispensable para
informarse sobre las becas y los cursos universitarios
ofrecidos por universidades, instituciones especializadas
y organismos internacionales
| Una fuente de referencia única en su género
desde 1948
| 2.600 cursos en 124 países
Todas las disciplinas académicas y profesionales 
de nivel postsecundario  | Direcciones e información
general, incluido el correo electrónico y las páginas
Internet  | Condiciones de admisión  | Fechas 
de inscripción  | Becas y ayuda financiera  | Costo
de los estudios  | Estadísticas sobre las instituciones.
| Informaciones presentadas en inglés, francés 
o español, según el país
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Fo c u s :
Small media, new voices
n Technology as liberator
n In Israel, everyone’s a television producer
n Sri Lankan expats find a guardian angel
n Romania’s unquenchable thirst for news
n Oxijeunes, Dakar’s breath of fresh air
n In Algeria, a new webmagazine
n With Internet closing in, are journalists being closed out?
n Making sense of information overload
Fe a t u res include
n Verdict on Libya’s great man-made river
n Argentina’s child reporters
n Rude awakening for East Europe’s women
n Nursing Dubrovnik’s war wounds
n Indonesia: learning the ropes of press freedom
n Balkan film director Goran Paskaljevic on war,
nationalism and Hollywood
]]>
</page>
</document>
