<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="118789eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
PEOPLE AND PLACES
When Tibetan eyes
are smiling
PLANET
Black and blue,
Libya‘s liquid
legacy
WORLD OF LEARNING
Will education 
go to market?
IN T ERV IEW
Serbian 
film-maker Gora n
Pa s k a l j e v i c
February 2000
Small media,
new voices
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
C o n t e n t s
February 2000 53rd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief:John Kohut
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Cynthia Guttman
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat,
Photoengraving:Annick Coueffé
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant:Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,A l c i n o
Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh(Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n :Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher copies
are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
a u t h o r ’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
r e q u e s t . Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering
p o s t a g e. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UN E S C O o r
those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the UN E S C O Courier staff. Th e
boundaries on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the United
N a t i o n s. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform
( m i c r o film and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de
Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,A n n
A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition,
Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ;( 4 )
Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road,Wo o s t e r, O h i o
4 4 6 9 1 , U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - FEBRERO2000
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Paris by
UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e. Periodicals postage paid at Champlain
NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’UNESCO.
Impression:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 2-2000-OPI 99-588 A
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 When Tibetan eyes are smiling
Photos by Michel A m e n d o l i a ;Text by Mohan Bir Th a p a
OPINION
9 The electronic gap Paul Ke n n e d y
PLANET
10 Black and blue, L i b y a ’s liquid legacy Amy Otchet
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Will education go to marke t ? Nico Hirtt
ETHICS
37 For east Europe’s women,a rude awakening Elisabeth Ku l a ko w s k a
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 D u b rovnik re b o r n Maja Nodari
CONNEXIONS
43 Indonesia learns the ropes of press fre e d o m José Manuel Te s o r o
TALKING TO…
46 Serbian film-maker G o ran Pa s k a l j e v i c
C o v e r : © Giacomo Pirozzi/Panos Pictures, London
1 7 Focus Small media, new v o i c e s
“Small media” are proliferating today thanks to a technological
revolution that has boosted the development of low-cost, u s e r-
friendly equipment. They range from community radio and television
to neighbourhood newspapers and, i n c r e a s i n g l y, Internet sites.
People and communities who once lacked a voice can now talk to
each other and to the public. Could journalists’ monopoly on
information be coming to an end?
Detailed table of contents on page 17.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A Tibetan monk blinded by cataract waits to have his eyes examined.
W HEN TIBETAN EY ES 
A RE SMIL ING
◗ Photos by Michael Amendolia; Text by Mohan Bir Thapa
Thanks to ingenious and inexpensive surgery, a Nepalese doctor has brought vision 
to thousands of people in Tibet, which suffers one of the world’s highest rates of cataract
blindness
■
While staying at a small hotel in Meta-
gonga about four hours east of Lhasa en
route to T i b e t ’s famous Ganden monas-
t e ry,D r.Sanduk Ruit had a chance, four ye a rs
a g o, to savour one of the sweeter fruits of his
wo r k . It was on that occasion that a we l l - d r e s-
sed woman in her early 40s approached him
o f f e ring the traditional k a d h a (white scarf)
and c h h u rp i ( d ried cheese).
As it happened, she was the same wo m a n
upon whom Dr. R u i t , a Nepalese opthal-
m o l o gist who has caused a stir in T i b e t ,h a d
o p e r ated two ye a rs previously. At that time,
she had been totally blind as the result of a
c at a r a c t ,which is a cloudy patch over the lens
◗ Michael Amendolia is an Australian photographer.
Mohan Bir Tapa is Chief Editor, Today magazine,
Kathmandu, Nepal.
of the eye . Her husband had left her when
she had become totally blind and she wa s
living like an animal. D r. R u i t ’s operat i o n
had enabled her not only to regain her vision,
but also to regain her dignity and fin a n c i a l
we l l - b e i n g .The woman told the doctor she
was now back with her fa m i l y.
Over the past 15 years,45-year-old Dr
Ruit has performed 20,000 cataract ope-
rations, each time replacing the damaged
natural lens with a plastic intraocular lens,
an approach dating from the 1980s when it
was popularized by Australian eye surgeon
Fred Hollows,Dr. Ruit’s teacher.
From a base at the Tilganga Eye Centre
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Choki (centre) arrives at the eye clinic in Gucho
(Tibet). She wears glasses but is completely blind.
in Kathmandu where Dr.Ruit works today,
H o l l ows developed high quality intraocular
lenses for an affordable $7 each, m a k i n g
the operation economically feasible in deve-
loping countries.
The development was a godsend for
T i b e t , an autonomous region of China that
nestles on the border with Nepal.Tibet has
perhaps the wo r l d ’s highest incidence of cat a-
r a c t s ,p a rtly because Tibetans live in one of
the wo r l d ’s highest inhabited regi o n s.As alti-
tude increases, so does exposure to ultra-vio-
let radition that is harmful to the eye s.T h e
incidence of cataract blindness in Tibet is
about six times that found elsewhere in China.
Operating on the roof
of the world
Dr. Ruit always had a fascination with
T i b e t , from where his own ancestors set off
three centuries ago to settle in eastern
N e p a l . Finally it was in 1994, with the
financial help of New Zealand Rotary
Clubs and at the inv i t ation of the T i b e t
D e velopment Fund (TDF), a non-gove rn-
mental organizat i o n , t h at he was able to
make a foray on to the “roof of the world”.
During Dr. Ruit’s first visit, members
of the TDF asked how many operat i o n s
could be done during a four-day session at
C h u s u , a village between Lhasa and its air-
p o rt . They gaped with surp rise when Dr
Ruit replied that going on past experience
in Nepal, some 200 operations would be
possible in that time. In T i b e t , only 150
cataract operations had been done throu-
ghout the whole of the previous year.
D r. Ruit performs his operations within
five minutes. It is actually a ve ry simple surgi c a l
procedure which can be performed by eve n
a neophyte doctor in half an hour. F i rst the
e ye is wa s h e d , then a local anaesthetic is
applied below the lower eye l i d .The clouded
i n t e rior of the lens is removed through a tiny
i n c i s i o n , and finally the intraocular lens is
i n s e rted into the empty lens capsule.
For centuries, until around the 1950s,
Tibetans are believed to have practised cou-
ching, an operation which involves remo-
ving the clouded part of the lens but which
provides no replacement.
With Dr. R u i t ’s surgery, which is vir-
tually painless, bandages cove ring the eye
can be removed  within a day. From being
able to see only vague outlines of objects at
firs t , within weeks patients are able to enjoy
full eyesight. ■
Dr Nyini screens patients in a makeshift surgery in
Gucho.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
These two women travelled 120 kilometres for eye care. Dr Ruit takes a quick look before treating them at the clinic.
Tibetan ophthalmologist Dr Mingma examines a patient at his clinic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Ophthalmic assistant Chansi Shrestha is watched by trainees while operating at the hospital in Tsetang. Eye doctors are much needed in Tibet, where the incidence of
cataract blindness is high.
A mature cataract is revealed after dilating 
a patient’s eye in an ophthalmic screening 
at the Gucho clinic.
Lhasa
Ganden
Kathmandu
Nepal
India
Tibet Autonomous Region
China
Bhutan
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A friend watches over Choki (see page 4) as she recuperates from an operation.
Weights on the patients’ eyes compress the cataracts and make them easier for the surgeon to remove.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Chang Zhou sees her daughter for the first time in over three years after cataract surgery.
Dr Ruit removes Choki’s eye patch after her operation. It will be several weeks before she completely recovers her sight.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
O P I N I O N
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 9
■
In the United Stat e s ,business journ a l s , market guru s , economics professors and highly
paid consultants talk incessantly about the coming global boom, the transform at i o n
of the wo r k p l a c e , the technology revolution and the knowledge explosion. It is
implied that the world is slowly becoming a reproduction of Silicon Valley. It is asserted
that this is the future. But instead of swallowing this hype, perhaps we should pull back
and look at the globe as a whole.
The pessimistic view would be to point out what is currently occurring in Kosovo,We s t
A f ri c a ,R wa n d a ,C h e c h nya , Kashmir and elsewhere.We might also follow Robert Kaplan
in the trips he describes in To the Ends of the Earth1, only to discover that much of huma-
nity is headed for disaster and self-destruction. I do not wish to be as negative as that.
However, I would like to offer a caution to those who portray globalization in an uncri-
tical and overly enthusiastic manner.
Each day I send and receive up to 40 messages on the Internet.From my home I can
search the web sites of the World Bank and the United Nations to find new dat a , read the
New Yo rk Ti m e s and check the 9 million book titles in the Yale Unive rsity Library.The Intern e t
gi ves me, my students and my children immediate access to know l e d g e , and the know l e d g e
explosion is at the heart of the modernization and globalization of world society.
One in three A m e ricans are regular, daily Internet users. E ven within A m e ri c a n
s o c i e t y, the computer and e-mail have widened the gap between educated people (chiefly
whites and Asians) and the less educated (chiefly black Americans).This gap will be felt
in every aspect of life,whether it is in opportunities,potential,education or job-hunting.
The United States will be divided into two gr o u p s , one which is computer-literate and the
other which is not.
This phenomenon has been replicated at the international level.The most important
fact is that we are in the midst of a technology revolution that seems less likely to close the
gap between rich and poor countries than to widen the gap even further.
The technology revolution and the communications revolution still bypass billions of
human beings. From UN E S C O’s standpoint, the Internet may have more influence than any
single medium upon global educational and cultural developments in the coming century.
Yet only 2.4 per cent of the wo r l d ’s population is on the Intern e t , or one person out of 40.
In Southeast A s i a , only one person in 200 is linked to the Intern e t . In the Arab stat e s ,o n l y
one person in 500 has Internet access, while in Africa only one person in a 1,000 is an
I n t e rnet user.This situation will not change as long as those lands lack electri c i t y, t e l e p h o n e
wires and infrastructure.They cannot afford either computers or the expensive software
they require.If knowledge indeed equals power,the developing world may have less real
power nowadays than it did 30 years ago, before the Internet was developed.
If we want to work toward a knowledge-based society in the coming century, over at
least the next 10 years we need to make a concerted effort to bring poorer societies into
the system of electronic communications.This effort will need to be coordinated by the
World Bank,the UN Development Programme, UNESCO, the NGO community and the
global business community.
The altern at i ve is to perp e t u ate a world which is fundamentally undemocratic and stru c-
turally unsound.If we do nothing, if we let the knowledge explosion intensify in techno-
logy-rich societies while poorer societies fall further and further behind,the growing gap
b e t ween haves and have-nots will lead to widespread discontent and threaten any prospect
of global harm o ny and intern ational unders t a n d i n g .This is the most significant challenge
we face.We have no time to waste in responding. ■
1. Robert Kaplan’s book suggests that in most of the Third World conditions will get worse,largely
because of the effects of overpopulation, environmental deterioration and social breakdown.
T HE EL ECT RONIC GAP
Paul Ke n n e d y
British historian Paul Kennedy 
is the J. Richardson Dilworth
Professor of History at Yale
University (U.S.A.). He is the
author of a widely acclaimed
work, The Rise and Fall of the
Great Powers: Economic
Change and Military Conflict
from 1500-2000 (Random
House, 1987), in which he
analysed the factors
underlying the rise and fall of
empires over the past five
centuries. In the final chapter
he evoked the coming collapse
of the USSR, and also
speculated about the decline
of the United States as a great
power and the rise of Japan
and China. Notable among his
other works are Preparing for
the Twenty-first Century (1993)
and Strategy and Diplomacy,
1870-1945 (1983).
The present text has been
extracted from Prof. Kennedy’s
contribution to a series of 
“21st Century Talks” held at
UNESCO Headquarters in Paris 
on November 6, 1999.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
P L A N E T
BLACK AND BLUE, 
L IBYA’S LIQUID LEG ACY
◗ Amy Otchet
Libya is mining water to feed its Great Man-Made River but is still not sure how to use 
this precious resource
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
Huge pipelines have been laid to link wellfields in the desert with the coastal strip inhabited by 85 per cent of Libya’s population.
■
Ye a rs can roll by without a single sho-
wer raining on much of Libya ’s
Sahara—one of the wo r l d ’s most for-
bidding stretches of desert ,c ove ring 90 per
cent of the country. Like a slab of clay for-
gotten in an ove r - h e ated kiln, flat bands of
scorched sandstone, cracked and bri t t l e , gi ve
way to wind-rippled dunes,o f f e ring the only
gentle touch to this barren landscape, w h e r e
a scraggy tree exudes an almost spiritual aura
by its defiance to surv i ve .
Yet beneath this baked crust of eart h ,
there is water—not just the last trickles of
nearly dry streams but phenomenal supplies
p e r c o l ating in four sandstone aquifers. I m a-
gine filling a pool the size of Germ a ny, s e ve-
ral hundred metres deep, to grasp the quan-
tities of water contained in these basins.
The aquifers are the liquid legacy of a
climate gone by. About 10,000 years ago,
the barren Sahara was a green sava n n a h ,
crawling with crocodiles, giraffes and ele-
p h a n t s. Tropical rainforests bloomed on
mountaintops while our Neolithic ances-
t o rs harvested wheat-like crops in the
p l a i n s. H e avy rains regularly refilled the
ri ve rs and lakes, but significant amounts
also seeped undergr o u n d , s at u r ating the
layers of sandstone until they sloshed with
wat e r.At the bottom of the basins, r e a c h i n g
depths of four kilometres, there may be
water millions of years old.
Little remains from that green period:
climate change choked off the rains about
3,000 ye a rs ago. For millennia, the aqui-
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
shifted in the 1970s when the oil boom tri g-
gered a looming water crisis with the sharp
rise in living standards and populat i o n
gr owth (from 1.5 million to the current five
m i l l i o n ) .O f ficials didn’t need a crystal ball to
see gr o u n d water supplies falling prey to the
s e a ’s intru s i o n . I m a gine a war of at t ri t i o n
b e t ween land and the sea, e ve r - h u n gry for
more terri t o ry. The gr o u n d water supplies
reinforce the land’s resistance to the bat t e-
ring waves of the sea. So a steep fall in wat e r
tables is like an open inv i t ation for the sea
which now intrudes another 100 metres
u n d e r ground each ye a r. This saline trail
c o n t a m i n ates what little freshwater remains
and ravages the fine coat of ochre soil, l e a-
ving the roots of orange trees so choked with
salt that many bear little more than gr e e n
f ruit the size of ping-pong balls.
“The question has never been: should we
mine water or not?” s ays Omar Salem,d i r e c-
tor general of the General Water A u t h o ri t y.
“ R ather it’s been: if we don’t find a solution
to the water short a g e ,we will face a ve ry dark
future.” After weighing the options, the
g ove rnment ruled out desalinat i o n ,c o n s i d e-
red too expensive and risky as the country
would be entirely dependent on foreign tech-
nology and expertise to maintain the plants,
explains Salem.With such fa bulous supplies
lining the desert (ve ry roughly estimated at
120,000 cubic km), the choice was clear:
m ove the people to the water or the water to
the people. With few families enticed by
d e s e rt life, the gove rnment opted for the lat-
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
f e rs lay largely untouched as ve ry little
water flowed in or out,according to scien-
tists.Yet today most of Libya’s citizens are
drinking and bathing in these extraordina-
rily pure “fossil waters”.
War of attrition 
between land and sea
A u t h o rities first turned on the taps of the
G r e at Man-Made River Project (GMRP) in
1 9 9 1 . Considered the wo r l d ’s largest civil
e n gi n e e ring project,the ri ver is a work in pro-
gr e s s.To d ay,about half a million cubic metres
of water are flowing daily through two gi a n t
u n d e r ground pipelines connecting we l l - fie l d s
deep in the desert to the coastal rim where
about 85 per cent of the population live .T h e
g ove rnment is mining water in much the
same way as oil—and in so doing adds a new
twist to an old debat e :w h at are the risks of
relying on a non-renewable resource? W i t h
e ve ry litre used today lost for tomorr ow,w h at
about generations to come? You don’t only
i n h e rit resources from your parents, s ay
c o n s e rvat i o n i s t s ,you borr ow them from yo u r
c h i l d r e n .
But as the Libyans remind us, scarcely a
whimper is heard today about the wo r l d ’s
dependence on another finite fossil resource,
p e t r o l e u m .W hy balk at mining water and
not oil? The two come hand-in-hand in
L i b ya . In the mid-1960s, d i s c ove ry of the
c o u n t ry ’s vast petroleum resources led geo-
l o gists to explore the aquifers for a simple
r e a s o n : o i l rigs require wat e r. But the scale
ter in 1983 and began building the Man-
Made River which is both praised as the
Wo r l d ’s Eighth Wonder and branded as Col.
Q a d h a fi’s “Pipe Dream”.
It took an army of Asian construction
wo r k e rs ye a rs to dynamite and dig the tun-
nels to lay the giant concrete pipes, f o u r
metres in diameter, wide enough for a sub-
way train to pass—or tanks, missiles and
troops, according to a few Western media
r e p o rts citing anonymous sources which
claim that the Man-Made River is inten-
ded for cove rt military purp o s e s. W h i l e
these stories are rejected as fantasy by
e x p e rts in intern ational organizat i o n s
(including UN E S C O) , the scale of the project
opens the floodgates of the imagination.A
road from Tripoli to Bombay could be
paved with the five million tons of cement
used to build the pipelines, which stretch
over a total length of 3,500 km. I m a gi n e
transposing the conve yance system on a
map of We s t e rn Europe: the pipeline wo u l d
b e gin in southern Switzerland and head
through Germ a ny and on up to Po l a n d
before cutting west to northern Scotland.
In reality, it takes an average of nine days for
every drop of water to travel from Libya’s
desert well- fields to the coast.
The nightmare of construction logi s-
tics took a surreal turn in 1986 when the
U.S. government imposed sanctions limi-
ting travel and commercial operations with
L i b ya1, s ays Mr A . M .E l - G h e ri a n i ,g e n e r a l
manager of the GMRP. The first order of
business lay with the project’s designers, a
consulting firm based in Houston and
1 In 1992, the United Nations also imposed
sanctions (including a ban on civil aviation and
severely restricting commercial activities) in
response to Col. Qadhafi’s refusal to extradite two
suspects in the 1988 bombing of a Pan Am jet
above Lockerbie, Scotland.The UN suspended
these sanctions in 1999 after Tripoli handed over
the suspects for a trial to take place in the
Netherlands.
‘The difficult choice 
is between two development
options. Do we want large-
s cale extraction of
groundwater for max i m u m
b e n e fit of the present
g e n e ration or limited
e x t raction that ensures
s u s tainable development 
and conservation of 
the resource base?’
In the next two or three years, Libya plans to irrigate 150,000 hectares of land in addition to its current
irrigated area of some 500,000 hectares.
Tripoli Darnah
Tobruk
Kufra
Sabha
Ghadames
wellfields
Tunisia
Algeria
Chad
Sudan
Egypt
Mediterranean Sea
Sarir
wellfield
Tazerbo
wellfields
Jebel Hasouna
wellfields
Completed pipelines
Reservoirs
Plans for future pipelines
Sirt
Benghazi
Al Jaghbub
Niger
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
P L A N E T
RI VA L L ING THE NIL E
owned by Hallibu rt o n , whose CEO is none
other than Dick Cheney, f o rmer U. S .s e c r e-
tary of defence.The company quickly pas-
sed into the hands of a subsidiary, Brown
and Root, c o nveniently located in England.
The wheeling and dealing required to
obtain spare parts has inflated the project’s
hefty price-tag, estimated at a total of $27
billion—which the gove rnment has been
financing mostly by conve rting oil into
water by taxing petroleum exports.
“All major civil engi n e e ring projects are
c ri t i c i z e d , but especially the GMRP gi ve n
the country that Libya is,”s ays Dr A b d u l g a d e r
A .A bu faye d ,who is responsible for allocat i n g
GMRP wat e r. L i b ya is not the only country
mining fossil wat e r. Egypt is tapping into
a q u i f e rs in its we s t e rn desert for a massive pro-
ject to irri g ate 200,000 hectares. E ven the
United States is pumping non-renewa b l e
s o u r c e s. While Californ i a ’s water mining is
m a r ginal compared to that of Libya , it is
c o n t r ove rsial gi ven that the U. S . is a wat e r - ri c h
c o u n t ry with altern at i ve supplies. But what
choices are open to hy p e r - a rid countries? Fo r
these countri e s , the question is not whether to
use fossil wat e r , but when and how? 
More today 
means less tomorrow
“The difficult choice is between two deve-
lopment options,” s ays Mohamed Bakhba-
k h i , a Libyan hy d r o l o gist with the Nubian
Sandstone Aquifer System Progr a m m e ,
which promotes data exchange between the
four countries sharing these basins (Chad,
E g y p t ,L i b ya and Sudan).“Do we want large-
scale extraction of gr o u n d water for maxi-
mum benefit of the present generation or
limited extraction that ensures sustainable
d e velopment and conservation of the resour-
ce base?” L i b ya is now at a crossroads: t h e
Man-Made River is only flowing at about a
tenth of its capacity to cover domestic needs
on the coast.The gove rnment must now deci-
de how to use the rest of the water and put
the needed infrastructure in place.Should it
use eve ry last drop for large-scale irri g at i o n
projects or opt for a more conservat i ve poli-
cy, focusing more on ensuring drinking sup-
plies and industrial use,which require far less
than agri c u l t u r e ?
O f fic i a l l y, a griculture is the top pri o ri t y
of the Man-Made Rive r. For the next 50
ye a rs , the project is designed to deliver about
six million cubic metres of water daily, w i t h
75 to 80 per cent going to fa rm s ,a c c o r d i n g
to Dr.Ali Giuma, s e c r e t a ry (minister) of agri-
c u l t u r e .I t ’s important to understand that
major infrastructure projects are norm a l l y
built to last at least 50 ye a rs.The aquifers will
not dry up at the end of that period but they
m ay be far more difficult to mine.“ You might
be able to extend the conve yance system or
put in another we l l - fie l d ,” s ays John Lloy d ,
a British professor at Birmingham Unive rs i-
ty and a leading gr o u n d water expert . In the
L i b yan desert , the wells reach between 400-
600 metres undergr o u n d . In 50 ye a rs ,t h e
water tables of the we s t e rn aquifers , f o r
e x a m p l e , are expected to fall about 80 metres
if they are pumped at full capacity.Te c h n i-
c a l l y, it will be possible to continue pumping
at these lower levels (assuming that the wat e r
quality doesn’t change).In Saudi A r a b i a ,f o r
e x a m p l e , water wells reach down a kilometre
or two underground even though they are
more expensive to operat e . But as Lloy d
points out, “ Water may be more precious
in the future, so it might be wo rth pumping
d e e p e r.”
With this in mind, the agri c u l t u r e
m i n i s t e r , Dr Giuma, ploughs ahead with
irrigation plans to work towards the natio-
nal goal of agricultural self-sufficiency. “In
the next two or three years, we plan to add
another 150,000 irrigated hectares to the
current total of about half a million,” says
Giuma.While fruits and vegetables are in
ample supply, L i b ya relies on wheat and
barley imports to satisfy 60 per cent of
domestic demand.To redress the balance,
government-sponsored farms are starting
to sprout around Sirt , Colonel Qadhafi’s
native city, and Benghazi.
This is big sky country,with the flat l a n d s
s u rrounding Benghazi looking picture per-
fect for a giant wheat belt.Red topcoats of
soil are carefully tilled beside white-domed
water tanks crowning each of the 520 new
fa rm s , which the gove rnment is prepari n g
to virtually gi ve away at prices of just 2,000
d i n a rs ($1,000 at the black market exchan-
ge rate) for 10 hectares. Not by chance, t h e
Man-Made River flows nearby via two reser-
voirs the size of football fields.
Importing wheat
saves precious water
But the apparent abundance of irri g a-
tion water is a kind of mirage, hiding the
fact that this is an arid zone where wat e r
e va p o r ates at rates of 40 to 60 per cent.
I n d e e d , half of all water now used for irri-
g ation is wa s t e d , according to Ayad S.
K a a l , a hy d r o g e o l o gist with the A gri c u l t u r e
Research Centre. Kaal is hoping that
conditions will improve as fa rm e rs learn to
use more efficient techniques such as dri p
i rri g at i o n .
But the decision to invest in agri c u l t u-
re leaves many scientific expert s ,p a rt i c u-
larly from the West,baffled.With the inter-
n ational grain market in a glut, w hy not
i m p o rt wheat and save precious water for
i n d u s t ries that not only use less but also pro-
duce better paying jobs? “Of course it might
be cheaper to buy wheat abroad but what if
there is another embargo to limit these
imports?”asks Dr Ibrahim Salem Haffala,
an economist with the Agriculture Resear-
ch Centre.
As Haffala explains,We s t e rn pri n c i p l e s
of economics don’t seem to apply here as
they fail to take account of surr o u n d i n g
National pride runs high with the Great Man-
Made River. The charming weather foreca s t e r
on the evening national new s cast points to brew i n g
storms over a continental map in which the Man-
Made River appears as naturally as the Nile. And
those giant pipelines offer the perfect backdrop
for Col. Qadhafi to strike a regal pose beside women
and children beaming in good health beside
bundles of wheat—signs of hydrological abundance
depicted in the billboards lining Tripoli’s streets. But
the River has brought another benefit that isn’t as
easy to illustrate: a generation of highly skilled
engineers and hydrologists. 
While foreign consultants have provided the
lion’s share of operational and technical expertise,
the project has been “Libyanized” according to
the general manager, Mr. El-Gheriani, who says that
nationals now make up 80 per cent of all per-
sonnel except for construction which is in the hands
of a South Korean contractor, Dong Ah.
UNES CO began co-operating with the govern-
ment in 1990 to organize training for Libyan
engineers and geologists at institutions in the
Netherlands, UK and Australia. All expenses are
covered by a trust fund, paid for by the government,
which has also been used to finance training and
documentation centres set up with UNES CO’s assis-
tance in Benghazi. 
Once the river began flowing, UNES CO a s s i s-
tance shifted to evaluating the project, with studies
comparing, for example, the costs of the GMR
water with desalination options. An international
a d v i s o ry board—composed of  experts in fields like
geo-hydrology, agriculture and engineering—also
meets regularly to assess the risks and resilience of
the system. The major priority is to evaluate the next
stages of construction, including a third pipeline to
connect the other two. New well-fields are also
under study.
UNES CO is also focusing on wider environmental
and socio-economic issues surrounding the mana-
gement of non-renewable water resources notably in
North Africa and the Middle East. To find out more
about the first major international conference orga-
nized on the subject (Tripoli, November 1999), contact:
w w w. u n e s c o . o r g / s c i e n c e / w a t e r d a y 20 0 0 ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 13
P L A N E T
political and cultural fa c t o rs. For example,
fa rming is seen as a partial solution to ri s i n g
u n e m p l oy m e n t , s ays Dr Giuma. T h e
g ove rnment wants to dive rsify the job mar-
k e t , d o m i n ated by the energy sector, b y
subsidizing a new managerial class in agri-
c u l t u r e .These “gentlemen fa rm e rs ” wo u l d
s u p e rvise foreign wo r k e rs from Egypt,
Sudan and elsewhere in Africa.
“ I t ’s impossible to make a defin i t i ve sta-
tement like, ‘ D o n ’t use water for agri c u l-
t u r e ,’ ” s ays Phillipe Pa l l a s , a French
consultant with the Food and Agriculture
Organization who has worked closely with
Libyan officials for the past 25 years. “But
there are people questioning whether or not
it might be cheaper to import wheat.This
marks a big change.Five years ago, no one
in the gove rnment would even agree to dis-
cuss the option. To d ay there is a nat i o n a l
debate, though it’s difficult to say at what
level it’s taking place.”
In the revo l u t i o n a ry rhetoric of Col.
Q a d h a fi’s Ja m a h i ri ya — s t ate of the masses—
a gricultural self-suffic i e n cy appears to be
an exalted pri n c i p l e ,which few would publi-
cly disavow. But respect for the pri n c i p l e
might not translate into active commitment
to the goal. “ We will be as sufficient as pos-
sible with our resources,” s ays Dr A b o u-
faye d ,who is responsible for allocating wat e r
to fa rm s.“The Great Man-Made River Pro-
ject is not the magic solution to all of our
water problems. It gi ves us the breat h i n g
space to develop new technologies and an
i n t e gr ated water policy.To raise public awa-
reness of the value of wat e r , we are setting
up economic disincentives for waste by
making fa rm e rs pay for the water they use.”
The apparent pragmatism should, h owe ve r ,
be taken with a grain of salt: at just 48
dirham (25-50 cents) per cubic metre,the
price tag reflects only a fraction of the true
costs of delivering the water. And even this
nominal rate won’t be charged until farms
are deemed “profitable”.
It may be a matter of time before offi-
cials admit to what experts like Pallas see as
o b v i o u s : “They would need another two of
three Man-Made Rive rs to be self-suffic i e n t
in agri c u l t u r e ,” he say s , pointing to projec-
tions calculated with Libya ’s General Wat e r
A u t h o ri t y. In the year 2025, L i b ya ’s popula-
tion is expected to reach almost 12 million
(including non-nat i o n a l s ) , with domestic
water needs swa l l owing up about 55 per cent
of the total capacity of the Man-Made Rive r.
Yet even if eve ry last drop of water (GMRP,
r e n e wable gr o u n d water sources and recy-
cled supplies) was used exclusively for agri-
c u l t u r e , L i b ya would still need to import
about half of its food supplies.
‘Big fixes’—
a technological mirage
“The responsible use of such an extra-
o r d i n a ry project demands that you deve l o p
the ve ry best conservation policies possible
so that nobody in the future can look back
and say : ‘ W h at a wa s t e ! ’ ” s ays Mike
Edmunds,a member of the British Geolo-
gical Survey team which explored the aqui-
fers in the 1960s. His praise for the project
is tempered by caution: “I just hope they
[officials] understand that big engineering
‘ fixe s ’ to water crises wo n ’t always be there.”
Big fixes are a virtual obsession for the
general manager of the GMRP, E l - G h e i r a-
n i a . Sceptical that desalination will ever be
a f f o r d a b l e , he aims to keep the Man-Made
R i ver flowing as long as possible. In A u g u s t
1 9 9 9 , pipes bu rst along the eastern corri-
d o r , forcing the gove rnment to close the taps
of this pipeline for about a month. C o rr o s i o n
is the likely culpri t . “With hundreds of thou-
sands of pipes crossing through so many dif-
ferent kinds of soils across a scorched desert ,
you can expect to have diffic u l t i e s ,” s ays El-
G h e ri a n i .G i ven the uncert a i n t i e s , might it
be time to invest in infrastructure to better
c o n s e rve the precious wat e r.“In the future,
c o n s e rvation will be an area of concern for
all countri e s ,” s ays El-Gheri a n i .B e s i d e s ,“ we
d o n ’t have the experience to know that the
a q u i f e rs aren’t being recharged,” he say s ,
b rushing aside the studies showing the
c o n t r a ry. “They [We s t e rn experts] said we
only had enough oil for 30 ye a rs but it’s still
flow i n g .W hy not wat e r ? ” Inshallah!* ■
*Arabic for “God willing”
A ceremony held in September 1996 to inaugurate part of the Great Man-Made River.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
but that situation is likely to change. Part
4 of the GATS agreement (“Progressive
liberalization”) requires that fresh nego-
tiations should be held by the end of 2000
at the latest, and should be directed to
“the elimination of the adverse effects on
trade in services of measures as a means
of providing effective market access”. At
the Geneva headquarters of the World
Trade Organization (WTO), far from the
headlines and the demonstrators, work
still goes on. But independently of the
WTO and national policies, a number of
factors are driving educational systems
towards “commercialization”.
Pressures
for change
First, education is a rapidly-growing
sector in which governments are finding it
harder and harder to satisfy demand,
above all in higher education. Between
1985 and 1992, the number of students
in higher education rose about 26 per
cent—from 58.6 to 73.7 million.
Meanwhile,public spending on education
has tended to stagnate over the past 15
years (5-6 per cent of GDP in rich coun-
tries and 4 per cent elsewhere).
In view of this dearth of public spen-
ding, parents and students are increasin-
gly looking to private education for a
solution. In the United States, every epi-
sode of violence in a state school and
every scandal that rocks official school
systems gives a boost to “home schoo-
ling”, where children no longer attend
school and are taught at home.
Traditional public education is also
coming in for strong criticism. Employers
complain it is not geared to their needs
and is not flexible enough. An influential
European employers’ pressure group, the
Industrial Round Table, deplores the fact
14 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
■
Most of us see education as first and
foremost a public service which is res-
ponsible for providing young people
with instru c t i o n . For inve s t o rs looking for
somewhere to put their money it is also an
annual budget of $1,000 billion wo r l d w i d e ,
a sector employing 50 million people, a n d
a b ove all a billion potential customers in the
f o rm of students. After the collapse of the
S e attle negotiations within the World Tr a d e
O r g a n i z ation at the end of 1999, it is hard
to say when the “Millennium Round” o f
trade talks will start . But education will sur-
ely be somewhere on the agenda,since the
e d u c ation market is gr owing at breakneck
speed.
The decision to extend to services the
liberalization of international trade which
previously applied to commodities was
taken in 1994. The General Agreement
on Trade in Services (GATS) which was
signed in April of that year included edu-
cation on the list of services to be liberali-
zed. To stay outside the scope of this
agreement, a country’s education system
must be completely financed and admi-
nistered by the state, which is no longer
the case anywhere. However, each coun-
try can still decide freely what commit-
ments it wants to make, and especially
which educational sectors it wants to
expose to market forces. The New
Zealand government, for example, has
decided to open up to outside competi-
tion the whole private education sector,
from primary to university level.
So far, New Zealand is an exception,
◗ A member of the Belgian organization Appel pour
une école démocratique (“Appeal for a democratic
school”: http://users.skynet.be/aped), Mr. Hirt is the
author of L’École sacrifiée (EPO, Brussels, 1996), Tableau
noir (EPO 1998) and Les nouveaux maîtres de l’école
(EPO and VO Editions, Brussels-Paris, 2000).
W ILL EDUCAT ION 
GO TO 
M A RK ET ?
◗ Nico Hirtt
The World Trade Organization has launched a process that could open up to competition 
the expanding and highly protected world market in education. What issues are at stake?
that in most European countries, schools
are integrated into a centralized public
system run by a bureaucracy that slows
down the process of change or makes
them impervious to demands for change
from outside.
Under pressure from economic inter-
ests, a process of “deregulating” educa-
tion systems has begun. The gr ow i n g
independence of schools is encouraging
them to look for alternative sources of
funding, ranging from sponsorship to full
management by private companies and
including many kinds of partnerships bet-
ween schools and firm s. A European
Commission working party on education
and training says “the time for out-of-
school education has come. . . . the libe-
ralization of of the educational process
thereby made possible will lead to control
by education service providers who are
more innovat i ve than the traditional
structures.”
The development and spread of infor-
mation and communication technologies
on a massive scale make possible the
development of paid distance learning,
using multimedia and the Internet for
tutorials, exams, etc.
Secondary and primary education are
also affected. More and more pay i n g
Internet sites bill themselves as alterna-
tives to state schools or traditional private
schools. The computer screen takes over
from the teacher, for a fee of around
$2,250 a year.
The WTO secretariat set up a working
goup in 1998 to look at the prospects for
more liberalized educat i o n . Its report
pointed to the rapid growth of distance
learning and noted the increasing number
of partnerships between educational insti-
tutions and private firms such as the
We s t e rn Gove rn o rs ’ U n i ve rs i t y, w h i c h
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
was founded by 17 U.S. state governors
and includes private sector partners such
as IBM, AT&T, Cisco, Microsoft and
International Thomson.
The report also noted the increasing
d e r e g u l ation of higher education in
Europe by gove rnments which have
begun “a movement away from public
financing and toward greater market res-
ponsiveness, coupled with an increasing
openness to alternative financing mecha-
nisms.”The WTO report lists many “bar-
riers” that need to be removed before
trade in educational services can be libe-
ralized.These include “measures limiting
direct investment by foreign education
providers” and “the existence of govern-
ment monopolies and high subsidization
of local institutions”.
Education
for export
It is true that these observations were
made by a working group, but as Martin
Khor pointed out in an article in the
French monthly Le Monde Diplomatique
in May 1997, “in the WTO, as in the
GATT, setting up a working group is
never innocuous. It triggers a chain of
events which participating governments
are soon caught up in. Suddenly it is no
longer a matter of being for or against the
aims of the working group but simply of
how they are to be achieved.”
Some 350 U. S . e x p e rts on intern at i o n a l
Services 2000, was to look at how the
U. S . g ove rnment should “continue to
support the efforts of American business
to take competitive advantage in foreign
m a r k e t s.” The U. S . c u rrently controls
about 16 per cent of the world market in
trade in services, including 170 business -
men and women, gathered at the U.S.
Commerce Department in Washington
on October 16, 1998 to draw up recom-
mendations for the U.S.negotiators at the
WTO.The purpose of the meeting, called
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
IN T ERN AT IONAL TRA DE IN EDUCAT ION
The WTO uses four terms to describe different
kinds of cross-border trade in services. Each
kind is the subject of specific demands from those
who favour liberalization.
In education, “consumption abroad” is cur-
rently by far the most important kind of cross-
border trade, mainly in the field of higher educa t i o n :
in 1995, study abroad was a business worth $27 bil-
lion. The United States had the lion’s share of the
market ($7 billion), followed by France, Germany
and Britain. In this field, advocates of libera l i z a t i o n
want to abolish measures limiting student mobility
( i m m i g ration red tape, exchange controls and non-
recognition of equivalent qualifications).
“Cross-border supply of services” is increasing
in the form of courses sold over the Internet and the
sale of CD-Roms and DVDs. This may be the fastest
g r owing ca t e g o ry of trade in education services, but
precise data are not yet available. Supporters of libe-
ralization want to give young people better access
to the Internet, deregulate distance learning, and
harmonize conditions of access to it and equiva-
lence between courses as well as ensuring reco-
gnition of diplomas at international level.
“Commercial presence”, another term used by
the WTO, mainly refers to the setting up of private
t raining institutes controlled by foreign firms.
Among the obstacles hindering the development of
this expanding market are refusal to recognize
foreign institutions and award recognized qualifi-
cations, conditions related to nationality, etc.
The fourth ca t e g o ry of trade in services involves
the “presence of natural persons”, e.g. foreign tea-
chers. Obstacles braking the growth of the market
include limitations on the numbers of such tea-
chers. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
services. Its services exports have more
than doubled in the past 10 years and
now cover 42 per cent of the non-services
trade deficit.
The United States is also the wo r l d ’s
leading exporter of educational serv i c e s ,
and a working group at the Services 2000
conference paid special attention to this
s e c t o r. It concluded that the sector “ n e e d s
the same degree of transparency, t r a n s f e r a-
bility and interchangeability, mutual reco-
g n i t i o n , and freedom from undue regula-
tion or restraints and barri e rs that the
United States acknowledges on behalf of
other service industri e s.” The report said
t h at three points should be at the centre of
W TO negotiations about educat i o n .
Firstly, there should be a free flow of
electronic inform ation and means of
communication, nationally and interna-
tionally. Secondly, the negotiators should
tackle “barriers and other restrictions that
limit or prevent the provision of educatio-
nal and training services across countries
and internationally.” They were also to
deal with obstacles to the transferability
of degrees and diplomas.
Fighting 
for market share 
The U. S . demands are backed by
most countries of the APEC (Asia-Pacific
Economic Cooperation) zone. In a note
in October 1999, the Australian delega-
tion to the WTO said it would be “encou-
raging all members to make expanded
commitments in all sectors, even the ones
that have proved difficult in both regional
and multilateral services negotiations”,
particularly education.
South Korea took a similar position.
At a meeting of ministers of human
resources from APEC countries that it
hosted in September 1997, the Seoul
g ove rnment put out a memorandum
which clearly stated its vision of education
as a tool of economic competition:
“The emphasis on education for itself
or on education for good members of a
community without a large emphasis on
preparation for future work is no longer
appropriate. Such a view of education and
work cannot be justified in a world where
economic development is emphasized.
“At present, in many economies, the
e d u c ation systems do not suffic i e n t l y
reflect labour market conditions. Their
inflexible and inefficient education sys-
tems could not meet the new economic
environmental challenges.” So education
should be made more “flexible”, i.e. be
deregulated and liberalized. In particular,
“school systems should be established to
allow all students to study what they are
interested in” and “ e m p l oye rs , w i t h
school educators, should share the role of
educating students”.
Some think resistance to liberalizing
education will come from Europe, espe-
cially France. “The future WTO negotia-
tions cannot call in question France’s tra-
dition of public service in the field of
education and health,” stressed a report
on the WTO prepared for the French par-
liament by Béatrice Marre. A few days
before the Seattle meeting, French educa-
tion minister Claude Allègre also empha-
sized his “unshakeable support for educa-
tion as a public service.”
U.S. delegates at the Services 2000
meeting were under no illusions. “It is
likely that other countri e s , e s p e c i a l l y
members of the European Union, may
take the view that education and training
are non-commercial activities and there-
fore should be off the table during GATS
negotiations,” the Americans said. “This
position reflects their self-interest as com-
petitors. . . . It should be resisted.”
France is currently the world’s second
biggest exporter of educational services. A
year ago, the French group Vivendi (for-
merly Générale des Eaux), through its
s u b s i d i a ry Hava s , took control of
Cendant Software, the U.S. educational
and entertainment software gi a n t . I n
January 1999, the French ministers of
education and foreign affairs announced
that France would fight to increase its
share in the “market”in higher education.
So one might well ask how far the 
“anti-American” stance of French educa-
tion officials is simply to protect France’s
position on the francophone education
market. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 17
FOCUS
Small media,
new v o i c e s
C o n t e n t s
1 8 Technology as libera t o r
John Ko h u t
1 | Making it happen
1 9 Je r u s a l e m ’s cub re p o r t e rs
Claudine Meyer
2 0 The global media boom
2 3 R o m a n i a :c o m p u t e r- g e n e rated fre e d o m
Mirel Bra n
2 5 S e n e g a l : O x y - J e u n e s is in the air!
Abou Ya y o b a
2 7 Sri Lankan expats find a guardian angel
E t h i rajan A n b a ra s a n
2 9 Algeria Dot-Com
Djallal Malti
3 1 I n d i a : the information defic i t
Interview with Sevanti Ninan
2 | The messenger 
is the media
3 2 New media, new rules
John V. Pa v l i k
3 5 New media, new headaches
Aidan W h i t e
For centuries journalism has, when
performing at its best, been the craft
through which skilled writer-reporters
working for organizations financially powerful
enough to afford expensive print, recording
and broadcasting infrastructures have tapped
into authoritative, trusted sources and
followed events closely in order to provide
information to the public. But now the rules of
the game are changing.
Today, via the Internet, where users as well
as creators of web sites can contribute news,
members of the public are often performing
the jobs traditionally reserved for the media.
This is but the latest breakthrough in
technology which has helped pluralize control
of the media.
As technology improves, it generally gets
easier to learn how to wield the tools of the
trade. At the same time, costs of setting up a
news service have overall dropped. Small TV,
radio, print and online news outlets have
proliferated (pp. 20-1). More points of view
are being aired  than ever before.
In this Focus section, we discuss a few
examples of the media’s new voices: Israel’s
neighbourhood-run community TV stations;
Romania’s newspaper deluge; a youth-run
radio station that exerts political pressure on
behalf of people living in a sprawling, poor
suburban area of Senegal; a broadcast service
that connects the Sri Lankan diaspora; an
offshore Algerian news service that could
probably have been conceived in no medium
other than the Internet.
We also reflect on the deeper social impact
of the media explosion. John Pavlik, head of
Columbia University’s New Media Center,
explains how the Internet is redefining the
role of journalists and empowering the public.
But Aidan White, General Secretary of the
International Federation of Journalists,
wonders whether the headswirling quantity of
news and information may be at the sacrifice
of quality.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
Technology as l i b e ra t o r
◗ John Ko h u t
The technological revolution is helping to give voice to the voiceless
◗ Editor in Chief of the UN E S C O
C o u r i e r
Over the past two decades, there has been an
explosion of media offerings,from the pro-
liferation of magazine titles, to the hun-
dreds of cable television stations now available
even in some poorer nations, and the never-
ending expansion of the Internet.
Underpinning this are advances in technology
that have drastically reduced the costs of media
production and distribution, making it possible
for those without huge funds to launch their own
ventures or simply to make their voices heard.
Some of the most notewo rt hy technologi c a l
breakthroughs include: digital layout of newspa-
pers, replacing time-consuming and expensive
typesetting; desktop publishing via the personal
computer; increasing simplification of broadcast
equipment; and, of course, the Internet.
Among the more renowned beneficiaries of
this technological transformation has been the
Independent newspaper of the UK, which shook
the media establishment when it was set up in the
late 1980s. Digital layout and transmission to
printers around the country cut production and
d i s t ri bution costs, helping make the ve n t u r e
financially possible.
Since then, t e c h n o l o gical progress has
enabled smaller and smaller players to set up their
own media outlets. In televison,one can now pro-
duce programmes with easy-to-handle digi t a l
video cameras costing as little as $1,000 each.
Time required for programme editing has been
radically slashed, saving on labour as well as other
costs.
Not only is it much cheaper to launch a media
venture today, it’s also a lot simpler. Twenty years
ago, jobs including handling even elementary
radio transmitters, newspaper page layout, and
television programme editing were reserved for
specialists who trained and honed their skills over
several years. Today, a few weeks or even days are
sufficient to acquire the basic skills to accomplish
more or less the same tasks.
The biggest technological leap in media over
the past century has permitted just about anyone
to launch a media enterprise.With the Internet,
“the costs of entry are nothing,” says Brian
Trench, senior lecturer in communications at the
Dublin City University.
All of this has had profound social implica-
tions, challenging the concentration of power in
the media.“The traditional centres of control are
withering away,” says Dr. Anura Goonasekera,
Head of Research at the Asian Media
I n f o rm ation and Communciation Centre in
Singapore. “Mass communication under the pre-
vious modes of production, both capitalist and
socialist,used to be controlled by a group of func-
tionaries. . . . [But now] such direct controls
through ow n e rship are becoming increasingly
difficult.”
To some extent the developing world is rea-
ping the fruits of the technological break-
throughs. But much more needs to be done if
poorer countries are to benefit as much as the
West from the diversity and democracy, not to
mention more jobs and vibrant economies, pos-
sible through new media.
“With the help of new information technolo-
gies, numerous opportunities exist for indepen-
dent media to cut their production costs, add
value to their product, expand their markets and
consolidate their independence,” writes Professor
Guy Berger of the Journalism Department at
Rhodes University in South Africa.
A number of analysts question whether the
technological revolution will in the long term turn
out to be a force of diversification. For instance,if
s t a rt-up costs are miniscule, marketing for
I n t e rnet services can often be enorm o u s l y
expensive in order to win the attention of consu-
mers swamped with choice. University of Illinois
professor Robert McChesney argues in R i c h
Media, Poor Democracy that the major media com-
panies will dominate the Internet because they
already have big newsrooms, war chests and
brand recognition.
But on balance, the new technology appears
to be a force of diversity and, by extension,demo-
cracy. Andrew Shapiro, senior adviser at the
Markle Foundation, in a a book entitled The
Control of Change, cites the example of Radio B92
in Belgr a d e . When Yu g o s l av leader Slobodan
Milosevic shut the station down in late 1996, B92
simply went online on the Internet. ■
‘ With the help of new
information technologies,
n u m e rous opportunities exist 
for independent media to cut
their production costs, add value
to their pro d u c t , expand 
their markets and consolidate
their independence’
Computing 
is not about computers
any more, it is about life.
Nicholas Negro p o n t e,
U. S. Internet guru (1943–)
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 19
Small media, n e w v o i c e s
1 ❘ Making it happen
Je r u s a l e m’s cub re p o r t e rs
◗ Claudine Meyer
I s ra e l ’s pro l i f e rating community TV stations are becoming 
a power in the land. The enthusiasm of their staff helps to compensate 
for lack of funding
The Hebrew expression Lev Haïr means the
“heart of the city”. It is also the name of a
community centre housed in one of the
white stone buildings that are common in the old
neighbourhoods of west Jerusalem, where they
were built at the end of the 19th century to
decongest the ancient city trapped within the
walls.
The doors of Lev Haïr, one of 180 social wel-
fare and leisure centres dotted all over Israel, are
open to everyone and everything, including the
smells that waft in from the nearby Machane
Yehuda Market—the scent of coriander, fresh
mint, guava fruit and the plaited loaves of bread
that Jews break at the start of the Sabbath.
The garbage trucks going up Agrippas Street
rattle the windows.Yoram has closed the blinds of
his photography shop, and his two inseparable
young assistants,Yoni and Yossi, hurry off to shut
themselves away for a couple of hours in a room
at the centre. Here, every Sunday evening, the 15
or so volunteer staff of the local community TV
station, set up three years ago, meet with their
teacher, Gilad, a 34-year-old ex-yoga instructor
who is studying for his Ph.D in Hebrew poetry.
The younger members of the team, like 15-
year-old Roï, are all keen to learn about the tech-
nical side of television—how to hold a camera,
record sound and do lighting.The older ones are
more concerned about what’s going into the next
programme. Because of lack of resources the pro-
grammes only last half an hour.They go out three
times a week on cable Channel 9.
Israel has had cable TV since 1988. Despite
one of the most expensive monthly subscriptions
in the world (around $35), 70 per cent (920,000)
of households have signed up for it and have
access to more than 40 channels, i n c l u d i n g
Channel 9, which only carries community TV.
The variety of topics tackled by the Lev Haïr
team gives some idea of its inclusive nature. Age
differences are blithely ignored by the staff, which
includes Yossi and his mother Shoshana,Anat and
his brother Alon, and Sylvia and Wolf, who have
three little blonde children. Such blood ties bet-
ween staff members sometimes lead to family
wrangles, but a strong sense of camaraderie soon
d e veloped between lay and religious people,
locals and outsiders, emigrants from east and
west, and Jews and Arabs. The team is a kind of
microcosm of Israeli society. Its common deno-
minator is a desire for self-expression.
No taboos
Everyone has had a chance to take a year-long
basic training course for 400 shekels instead of
the usual 2,000 ($470). Over 26 sessions, they
learn how to film and do montage and pick up◗ Jerusalem-based journalist
Bristling rooftop antennae in the old city of Jerusalem.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
The global m e d i a b o o m
123 114 102 100 91 90 87 86 68 64
High-income countries 95.1
Middle-income countries 4.7
Low-income countries 0.2
World 
total
Developed
countries
Developing
countries
Least developed
countries
Number of Internet-connected computers
worldwide, 1981-1999
1981 213
1982 235
1983 562
1984 1,024
1985 1,961
1986 5,089
1987 28,174
1988 56,000
1989 159,000
1990 313,000
1991 617,000
1992 1,136,000
1993 2,056,000
1994 3,864,000
1995 6,642,000
1996 12,881,000
1997 19,540,000
1998 36,739,000
1999 56,218,000
Source:Internet Software Consortium-Domain Survey
(http://www.isc.org).
81
240
263
1970
1997
548
157
23
9.9 0.5
The top 10 countries by density of Internet-connected computers (per
1,000 inhabitants)
Source:International Telecommunication Union
Number of television receivers per 1,000 inhabitants
Source: UNESCO Institute for Statistics
Pe rcentage of distribution of Internet-connected
c o m p u t e rs, by income of countries, July 1999
Television has probably had the gr e atest social
impact over the past century. Its predominance
will likely continue for a long time to come as a result
of the development of cable and satellite distribu-
tion and local channels and the move towards digi t a l
instead of analogue transmission. O ver the past
three decades, the total number of television recei-
ve rs has gr own by 55 times in the developing wo r l d
and their density (number in relation to populat i o n
size) by around 16. The North-South divide is
smaller for television than for the other media.
The so-called inform ation age, marked by the
t riumph of the Intern e t , s t a rted in the early
1980s and really took off in the latter half of the
1 9 9 0 s. In 1981, only some 200 people we r e
connected to the Intern e t .The turning point came
in 1986, when the number of users quintupled. B y
the middle of 1999, 56 million computers we r e
Internet-connected, an increase of almost 20 mil-
lion over the previous 12 months. As the chart at
right show s , the Internet phenomenon is still largely
confined to the rich countries, which have 95 per
cent of the wo r l d ’s Internet-connected computers.
The North-South gap is wider than for any of the
other media (see article page 9).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 21
Small media, n e w v o i c e s
The Medium 
is the Message
M a rshall McLuhan,
Canadian essayist (1911-80)
World 
total
107
96
1970
1997
1970
1997
Developed countries
292
226
Developing
countries
Least developed
countries
60
8
29
4.5
World 
total
245
418
Developed countries
643
1061
Developing
countries
Least developed
countries
245
142
90
56
Number of radio receivers per 1,000 inhabitants
Source: UNESCO Institute for Statistics
Circulation of daily newspapers per 1,000 inhabitants (estimate)
Source: UNESCO Institute for Statistics
The main media (Internet, t e l e v i s i o n , ra d i o, written press) 
a re continuing to gro w, but at very different ra t e s. The North-South gap is vertiginous
for the Internet, and persistently wide for the other media
The printed press is the only one of the mass
media whose situation (in terms of circulation per
thousand inhabitants) is declining on the global
s c a l e .The decline is ve ry marked in the U. S . and the
European Union, but less steep in Japan. In the
d e veloping countri e s , the extension of schooling
and democrat i z ation in the 1980s heralded an
explosion in the number of titles.The increase of
newspaper circulation has been ve ry modest,
h owe ve r , doubling in just under 30 ye a rs ,i n c l u d i n g
in the least developed countri e s. It seems that news-
paper circulation may have reached its ceiling.
It was once predicted that the coming of television
would wipe out radio. However, radio continues
to spread.The coming of the transistor in the 1960s
made possible the manufacture of lightwe i g h t ,l ow -
c o s t ,e n e r g y - e f ficient receive rs and helps to explain
why radio continues to be the mass medium best
suited to poor and isolated regi o n s. But the gr ow t h
in the density of receive rs is more moderate than that
of television (a fourfold increase in 30 years in the
developing world).The North-South gap in radio,
which was narr ower than for TV in 1970, h a d
become wider by 1997.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
English jargon such as “shooting . . . pan . . . tilt
up. . . tilt down”. They also discuss supposedly
taboo subjects including the three Ps—politics,
pornography and publicity. Some of the students
have been keen enough to go on Sundays to the
Zippori training centre, tucked away in the heart
of Jerusalem’s vast pine forest, and brush up their
skills.
Teams like this are appearing all over Israel.
There are now 150 community television stations
set up either by neighbourhood groups or by cul-
tural communities such as Iranian Jews who
speak Pe rs i a n , n e w c o m e rs to Israel from
Ethiopia, or Russians who have arrived in large
numbers since the fall of the Soviet empire. For
all of them, community TV is a forum where
people can say what they feel about all kinds of
things, from their taste in music to their distaste
for bureaucracy.
This flowering, greatly helped by the steadily
falling price of equipment, is what local people
want. Community TV fills in the gaps left by the
national channels. “These channels don’t fully
take into account the diversity of the country’s
population, which contains microcosms and cul-
tural minorities with strong sub-cultures,” says
Yehiel Limor, professor of communication scien-
ce at Tel Aviv’s New School for Media Studies.
The role of local television is particularly impor-
tant because “the local press only stops being
parochial when it brings out weekend editions,”
Limor says, referring to leisure magazines whose
content is usually superficial.
Local gripes
Local television tries to “get things moving”,
and on many occasions has been successful. In a
three-minute interview with the head of Bezek,
the national telecommunications company, a
team from the Gonenim centre managed to speed
up repairs to public phone boxes smashed by
vandals, after users had campaigned in vain for
months. People living in the new out-of-town
neighbourhood of Ramot got a bus service after a
televised interview with the head of the Egged bus
company.
These tussles with local authorities have beco-
me common. A team of reporters questioned the
mayor of the mixed Jewish-Arab town of Ramle
about garbage collection. At first he was hostile,
but after a critical TV programme he improved
the service. In exchange, the reporters abstained
from making a follow-up film,so the mayor could
save face and criticism from the townspeople did
not spread.
Today, the Lev Haïr community TV team has
decided to tackle the sensitive issue of how the
local market and night-time garbage collection
disturb the lives of those living nearby. Shlomi,
who is something of a philosopher, is sitting on a
pile of broken crates and discarded fruit. He
laughs and says he’ll read extracts from what
great thinkers have said about this kind of subject.
Michal says the real issue is that many of the wor-
kers are young Arab boys who stack the stalls with
produce, throw away empty boxes and swill down
the paving-stones when squashed tomatoes and
mangoes have made them slippery. A martial arts
enthusiast, he willingly talks about this serious
topic instead of his favourite subject, tokaido.
M i c h a , a choreogr a p h e r , calls for a progr a m m e
about the gr owth of the underground culture.
Sylvie suggests a vox pop fashion programme to
find out what people think of the famous “ b o b ” ,
the little cloth hat wo rn by Zionist ve t e r a n s. A n
amusing and surrealist vox pop programme wo n
the humour prize at Israel’s last annual communi-
ty TV contest and got its authors a weekend holi-
d ay at Shefaim kibbu t z .The question addressed in
the programme wa s : “Do you prefer white or ye l-
l ow stripes on pedestrian crossings?”
Short of shekels
The last item on the agenda is money and a
report on a demonstration held in Tel Aviv in
mid-November to persuade the communications
ministry not to cut the team’s 20,000-shekel
(around $4,700) annual operating budget, a sum
which would just about buy a camera. Additional
funding amounting to 10,000 shekels ($2,350)
comes from various money-raising activities held
during the year.The proceeds go to each of the 80
member stations of an association led by a tireless
enthusiast and campaigner for communication
rights, Zeevic Zaavi.
Zaavi, who is in his 50s, keeps a stock of com-
munity TV productions in his video library and
compiles from them a 30-minute weekly magazi-
ne for young people called Alternatives, which
Channel 9 has been broadcasting for nearly a
Community media increasingly reflect the diversity of Israel’s population and cultural
minorities. Above, market scene in Jerusalem.
News doesn’t happen,
i t ’s created. If there were
no journalists, t h e r e
wouldn’t be any news.
There would simply be
f a c t s.
Carlos Luis A l v a re z ,
Spanish journalist (1932-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 23
Small media, n e w v o i c e s
‘It ’s only midday and I’ve already sent 10 e-mails
to my colleagues,” says Anca Suciu, head of
c o m m u n i c ations at “ S ave the Children”, a
Romanian organization founded in 1991 and now
the country ’s most active group dealing with aban-
doned children.
Her colleagues are not very far away however.
Their offices are only next door or on another flo o r.
But computers have become indispensable to the
work of this young team whose average age is 30.
Using a network of eight machines, they manage to
R o m a n i a :
c o m p u t e r- g e n e rated fre e d o m
◗ Mirel Bra n
R o m a n i a ’s media landscape has been revolutionized as a profusion of national and local
n e w s p a p e rs have bro ken a state monopoly that lasted for 40 years
◗ Bucharest-based journalist
t u rn out an astonishing range of written mat e rial for
the association’s 6,000 members scattered all over
the world. Magazines, annual reports, studies on
homeless children and gypsy children, h a n d b o o k s ,
l e a fle t s ,e ven stickers — a nything to get the message
across.
“There’s all this,” says a slightly out-of-breath
Suciu, carrying an impressive pile of documents.
“The circulation figures aren’t amazing—they’r e
usually between 500 and 4,000 copies—but we
print everything ourselves.”
year. The ultimate aim is to broadcast for five
hours each afternoon.
Meagre though they are, subsidies are vitally
important for the Lev Haïr centre, and Gilad,
who has nearly finished training a second team,
has a shopping list of equipment he needs.Top of
the list is a third camera, this time a digital one,
and a cutting room so as to avoid having to spend
nearly 1,500 shekels ($350) a month on paying
staff at the Philippe Léon community centre,
where two team members, Yehuda and Walid, are
currently working. One is an immigrant from
France and the other was born in Ras-el-Amud,
east of Jerusalem.
The dream of course is to have a real studio,
like the lucky people in the Baka neighbourhood
who can do studio interviews and broadcast live
debates at election time.
Community TV can also try to find private
sponsors, but Gilad has no business staff who
could spend time looking for would-be investors.
He relies heavily on municipal authorities who,
Zaavi thinks, are “gradually coming to unders-
tand the importance of neighbourhood TV in hel-
ping them to find out what citizens want and
satisfy local needs. Instead of carrying 95 per cent
bad news,” he says, “these stations improve the
image of towns which often have problems. By
doing this, they can help to attract investors and
skilled workers.” ■
In the year after the fall of President Nicolae Ceausescu in 1989,the number of periodicals published in Romania
increased tenfold. Romania also opened up to foreign publications.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
Among the quarterly magazines the associat i o n
puts out, I n fo c e n t deals with helping homeless chil-
dren, “Info Save the Children” presents the asso-
ciation’s projects, and “SOS Street Children”car-
ries news about the 700 or so children who roam
the streets of Bucharest.They all contain features,
i n t e rv i e w s , in-depth reports and practical inform a-
tion—just like any self-respecting magazine.
“These publications have boosted the associa-
t i o n ’s standing,” s ays Suciu. “The doors of institu-
tions are opening more readily to us now and some
of our experimental programmes have been incor-
p o r ated in the policies of gove rnment bodies.”T h e
association’s database of very detailed statistics on
abandoned children is a real goldmine for institu-
tions involved in the field.This shows the impact
these energetic young people have had on Romania’s
political and social life.
Has new inform ation technology expanded
freedom of expression? “ I t ’s done more than that ,”
says Suciu.“It’s our guarantee of freedom.”
Romanians have learned to turn IT to their
best adva n t a g e . Largely due to new technology,
the fortunes of the written press soared after the fa l l
of President Nicolae Ceausescu in 1989.“When he
was in power, there were a total of 400 magazines
and newspapers in the country,” s ays sociologist A l i n
Te o d o r e s c u . “I was amazed to see that figure
increase tenfold in less than a year.”
In 1990,the unchecked expansion of the press
exceeded all expectations and became a honey-pot
for local inve s t o rs looking for quick profit s. T h e
daily paper A d e va ru l ( “ Truth”) was printing 1.8 mil-
lion copies, România Libera (“Free Romania”) 1.5
million,and the weeklies sometimes topped a mil-
lion copies.These were huge figures for a country
of 23 million people.
“The media has been the biggest laboratory of
private enterprise in Romania,” says Teodorescu.
“Including adve rtising reve n u e , it accounts today for
2.5 per cent of GDP. If the whole economy was like
t h at , our national income would be higher than
that of Greece.”
The figures speak for themselve s. In 1989, t h e r e
were only 2,500 people working in the media.To d ay
there are 12,500. About 3,000 modern pri n t i n g
works have replaced old ones, some of which dat e d
back to 1894.The local capital the media at t r a c t e d
has been reinvested in computerizing editori a l
offices.
At the start of the 1990s, paper and powe r
supply were still gove rn m e n t - s u b s i d i z e d , w h i c h
made production costs low and newspapers very
cheap for the public. But low prices were not the
only factor in boosting readership. After nearly 40
ye a rs of silence under the Ceausescu regi m e ,R o m a-
nians were hungry for inform ation and any pri n t e d
material interested them. Social and political life
became an endless source of hot news, and most
intellectuals abandoned their field and turned to the
p r e s s , which became a kind of mirage of demo-
cracy.
Aware that people also needed to be entert a i-
ned after being numbed by long ye a rs of bori n g
l a n g u a g e ,m a ny new papers—big and small, n at i o-
nal and local—were unashamedly lightwe i g h t .T h e
ye l l ow press flo u ri s h e d .C o m m e n t a ry and pers o n a l
o p i n i o n , expressed in language that was often vul-
gar and sometimes violent and insulting, t u rn e d
the press into a bat t l e field between the reform e rs
and those who looked back nostalgically to the
p a s t .
Competition from TV
Things began to change in 1992. Production
costs went up, people’s incomes fell and political
c o n t r ove rsy lowered the tone.The audiovisual sector
was also rapidly taking off and making Romania into
the eastern European leader in the field with, t o d ay,
48 television channels (40 of them local) and 250
radio stations (all but five of them private). As a
result,circulation fell dramatically and the written
press had to rethink its strat e g y. It has since become
more professional, with improved content and pre-
s e n t at i o n . It has mainly opted for news and left the
job of entertainment to television.
“Competition from television was a shock for the
p r e s s ,” s ays Te o d o r e s c u , “especially when TV made
off with 61 per cent of advertising revenues.Today
they’re quits, each of them drawing 50 per cent.
Income from adve rtising has actually risen by about
a fifth every year and is a real powerhouse for the
media.
Freedom of expression, the market economy
and new technology are the mainsprings of this
extraordinary expansion of the press in Romania,
‘ When Ceausescu was in power,
t h e re were a total of 400
magazines and newspapers in the
c o u n t r y. I was amazed 
to see that fig u re increase tenfold
in less than a year.’
A newsstand in Bucharest.
Everyone has the right
to freedom of opinion
and expression; t h i s
right includes freedom
to hold opinions without
interference and to seek,
receive and impart
information and ideas
through any media and
regardless of frontiers.
U n i v e rsal Declaration 
of Human Rights, Article 19.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 25
Small media, n e w v o i c e s
‘Iwish I could listen to O x y - Je u n e s, P i k i n e ’s
community radio stat i o n , while I’m at work bu t
we can’t get it here in Dakar,” s ays Babacar, a
young garage mechanic who works in the Senega-
lese capital but lives out in the suburb of Pikine.
When you tell him there are plenty of radio stat i o n s
in Dakar, all broadcasting music and news, h e
replies with a laugh: “ Ye s , but they don’t say enough
about the place where I live.”
P i k i n e , an enormous suburban settlement with
1.15 million inhabitants, was officially declared a
t own not long ago.Each day, thousands of people pour
out of it to try to make a living in the “ i n f o rmal sector”
in Dakar. Pove rt y - s t ricken Pikine is where migr a n t s
from the countryside end up, but it’s also known for
the richness of its community life and the energy of its
young people.
When the people of Pikine set up Radio Oxy-Je u n e s
( “ Je u n e s ”means young people in French), they came
up against the tough world of Senegal’s bu r e a u c r at i c
j u n g l e .They drafted a proposal with the help of Fo ru m
Je u n e s s e, a non-gove rnmental organization (NGO)
S e n e g a l: O x y - J e u n e s is 
in the air!
◗ Abou Ya y o b a
Young people in a poor suburb of Dakar fought hard to get a radio fre q u e n c y.
Since their station started broadcasting in June 1999, it has given many ordinary citizens 
a chance to speak their mind
◗ Dakar-based journalist
which has several thousand members in Senegal and
is backed by the World A s s o c i ation of Community
Radio Broadcasters and a Canadian NGO,the Cat h o-
lic Organization for Development and Pe a c e .For three
ye a rs , they wrote letters galore, hung about for hours
at the ministry of communications and even resort e d
to scribbling gr a f fiti on the walls of Dakar.
Until recently, the authorities only issued FM
broadcasting licences to foreign stations such as Radio
France Intern ational and A f rica Number One and to
S e n e g a l e s e - owned commercial stat i o n s.They made a
lot of money because the stations were forced to pay
an annual fee of several thousand dollars. H owe ve r ,
u n d e rresourced local community stations had little
chance of getting official approva l . Until recently,
there was only one community radio station in Senegal.
But in June 1999, a young man from Pikine
boldly cut his way through this thicket of restri c t i o n s.
When he shook President Abdou Diouf’s hand at
the inauguration of Dakar’s new stadium, he seized
the opportunity to say :“Mr President, young people
are still waiting for their radio frequency so they can
which now has more than 800 publications.They
include about 100 dailies, 200 weeklies and 250
monthlies. Half of the total are local (two-thirds
in the case of the dailies). The media run by
voluntary organizations are also flourishing. The
success story of “Save the Children” is by no
means unique in post-communist Romania,
where thousands of active community groups are
the flesh and bones of the new civil society.
Despite the country’s current material shortages,
most of them have computers and print their own
material.This is an astonishing achievement in a
c o u n t ry where, a decade ago, most people’s
dream was to buy a typewriter.
This optimism has infected everyone,even the
yo u n g e s t .Two ye a rs ago, backed by “ S ave the Chil-
d r e n ” , a quarterly magazine titled “ C h i l d r e n ’s
Thoughts and Vo i c e s ” a p p e a r e d , produced and
designed by schoolchildren in Bucharest. T h e s e
budding journalists are already learning how to
express ideas and share opinions—to communi-
cate freely, in fact.This is something their parents’
generation had very little opportunity to do. ■
The Oxy-Jeunes community radio team
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
make themselves heard on the airwave s ! ” T h i s
simple sentence did the trick.
The president responded at once by asking his
prime minister to give the matter top priority.The
next day, the people at Forum Jeunesse received a
s u m m o n s , d e l i vered by a motor-cy c l i s t , to go to
the gove rn m e n t ’s main administration bu i l d i n g,
the citadel of the bu r e a u c r a cy.When they got there,
they were told they could use the frequency 103.4.
From then on they were on their own!
To d ay, the O x y - Je u n e s transmitter is a fa m i l i a r
sight to all the inhabitants of Pikine. It stands on the
roof of the Léopold Sédar Senghor Cultural Centre,
an imposing building that houses the municipal
g ove rnment and several community gr o u p s. P hy s i c a l
p r oximity to the local authorities does not seem to
wo rry the 50 or so vo l u n t e e rs from community orga-
n i z ations who run the stat i o n . The radio gi ves the
t own authorities a hand by broadcasting offic i a l
announcements of general interest, but it carefully
defends its independence. “O x y - Je u n e s is clearly not
in the authori t i e s ’ p o c k e t ,” s ays opposition MP
Amadou Yoro Sy.
The station broadcasts 40 hours of progr a m m e s
a we e k .Within six months it had established itself
as a forum of opinions focused on life in Pikine and
the concerns of its inhabitants. Its recipe is simple.
The producers gi ve the floor to listeners and allo-
c ate plenty of air time to social and political dis-
c u s s i o n .The titles of the programmes are reve a-
ling—“Mbedd mi” (the street),“ B l a - B l a ”( p o l i t i c a l
s atire) and “ Fadiou T h i o s s a n e ” (traditional hea-
l i n g ) .The stat i o n ’s aims are to gi ve a plat f o rm to
m a r ginalized people, strengthen grassroots and com-
munity organizations,get people involved in deve-
lopment and raise civic awareness.
The different communities in Pikine soon reali-
zed how useful O x y - Je u n e s could be in getting
through to politicians and bu r e a u c r at s , and also in
c o m m u n i c ating with each other. All Senegal’s lan-
guages can be heard on the station—French is only
gi ven 20 per cent of air time—and all the country ’s
ethnic groups have access to it. For example, s ay s
O x y - Je u n e s c o o r d i n ator Oumar Ndiaye Seck, “ t h e
nearly one million Peulh-Fuutas people from
Guinea who live in this country no longer have to
send their announcements to Radio Labé in
Guinea because they have no outlet in Senegal.”
O x y - Je u n e s has knocked a few local politicians off
their pedestals.When they answer listeners ’q u e s t i o n s ,
they come across as ordinary citizens,accountable to
the people who voted for them. In a country bu i l t
around traditional hierarchical relationships and poli-
tical favo u ri t i s m , this kind of awakening has not come
e a s i l y.
The prefect of Pikine distri c t , Cheikh T i d i a n e
N d oye , points out that “the most popular pro-
grammes are those in which mayo rs and local offic i a l s
are invited to speak directly to the listeners.” T h e
highly popular local news bu l l e t i n , which presents an
hour of news “about Pikine for Pikine”, is an oppor-
tunity for grassroots Pikine to bring its struggles for
s u rv i val to the attention of offic i a l d o m .
P i k i n e ’s citizens, especially the younger ones,m a k e
no bones about reminding officials of broken election
promises and demanding explanat i o n s.They also use
the station to get decision-makers to promise to pro-
vide basic social serv i c e s.They realize that asking for a
public drinking fountain in a poor area by cleve r l y
using colloquial language is much more effective in a
society with an oral tradition than sending letters that
supposedly get lost in the mayo r ’s offic e .
Publicity about O x y - Je u n e s’ a c h i e vements is
causing a few problems.“ W h at about us?” s ay other
communities which have seen nothing come their
way.This increases the pressure on the station and
on local offic i a l s , who often cannot deliver the
goods. And this pressure is increasing.
Scrambling for funds
“There’s too much music and not enough dis-
cussion on Oxy-Jeunes,” say members of the eco-
nomic pressure group Bok Xalat (“shared vision”),
who also complain that few of the programmes are
presented by women.
Another big problem is the lack of trained pre-
senters and the paucity of resources.The manage-
ment would like to have a core of paid professionals,
but it has no money to hire them.It is also waiting
anxiously for the end of the stat i o n ’s first year to see
if it will have to pay the $3,200 licence fee which is
c o m p u l s o ry for community radio stations but which
it cannot afford.
The future is financially uncert a i n . T h e
Canadian NGO backing the project has already
The different communities in
Pikine soon realized how useful
O x y - J e u n e s could be in getting
t h rough to politicians and
b u re a u c ra t s, and also in
communicating with each other
An Oxy-Jeunes studio during a broadcast.The station’s most popular programmes are phone-
ins with local authority officials.
[ The media’s] selection
and description of
particular events—far
more than their
editorials—help to
create or promote
national issues, to shape
the minds of the
Congress and public,
and to influence the
P r e s i d e n t ’s agenda and
t i m i n g .
T h e o d o re C. S o re n s e n ,
Special Counsel to U. S.
P resident John F. Ke n n e d y
( 1 9 2 8 - )
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 27
Small media, n e w v o i c e s
Rasaiah Yoganathan, a 40-year-old Sri Lankan
Tamil,arrived in Marseilles last year without
valid immigr ation papers after fleeing his
c o u n t ry ’s ethnic confli c t . H owe ve r ,Yo g a n at h a n ’s
efforts to explain his tenuous situation to the local
a u t h o rities proved futile, as he could not speak
French.
A month passed and Yo g a n athan decided to
w rite to the Intern ational Committee of the Red
Cross (ICRC) in Geneva explaining his plight.T h e
ICRC responded to his request and asked him to
provide documentary evidence justifying his case.
Unfortunately, the reply was in French and Yoga-
nathan was unable to understand it.
It was then that he came upon a Tamil radio
broadcast from Pa ris in which there was a phone-in
p r o gramme addressing issues related to obtaining a
s t ay permit or refugee status in France.Yo g a n at h a n
Sri Lankan expats 
find a guardian angel
◗ E t h i rajan A n b a ra s a n
A Paris-based radio and television channel keeps Sri Lankan Tamils abreast of news from home
while helping them adapt to life abro a d
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
immediately called to seek their help. He received
guidance and assistance in obtaining his papers and
is now living in France with his family.
Yo g a n at h a n ’s case is not an isolated one. Fo r
more than half a million Sri Lankan Tamils—most of
them refugees—living in we s t e rn Europe, the Pa ri s -
based Tamil Radio and Television (TRT) netwo r k
not only functions as a news source and an enter-
tainment channel but most importantly helps them
to better cope with living abroad. Because the conti-
n e n t ’s mainstream media takes little interest in their
a f fa i rs ,Tamils also say that T RT has gi ven them a
voice and an identity in their adopted countri e s.
Started in January 1997 as a limited company
by journalists and professionals from the Ta m i l
community in Europe, T RT focuses mainly on
news and current affa i rs. There are hourly news
bulletins in Tamil devoted pri m a rily to the Sri Lan-
kan situat i o n ,f o l l owed by current affa i rs in the sub-
continent and other parts of the world.The radio
channel was an instant success among Tamils in
E u r o p e , who until then had no other daily source of
information about their homeland.
Wanting to feel
at home
T RT is more than a traditional news prov i d e r. I n
a weekly programme called “U d h av u vo m a” (“Can we
h e l p ? ” ) , it invites experts to answer queries in Ta m i l
on how to obtain work permits and on other admi-
n i s t r at i ve issues. “They don’t just ask about immi-
gr ation problems; they are often looking for infor-
m ation about mat t e rs ranging from divorce to school
a d m i s s i o n ,”s ays Sagadeva n ,an expert on French legal
a f fa i rs who hosts this weekly progr a m m e .
On the lighter side, the channel also airs inter-
views with Sri Lankan and Indian celebri t i e s , l i t e-
r a ry reviews, s p o rts and popular cultural pro-
p r ovided some $63,000 to buy equipment and pro-
vide basic training for several presenters.The gr a s s-
roots groups which ask for air time are usually so
poor that it is unrealistic to expect them to contri-
bu t e . There is also fierce competition for aid from
i n t e rn ational organizations such as UNICEF and
from national bodies that subsidize some radio sta-
tions on a one-off basis to support health campaigns
and the like. More professional pri vate commercial
s t ations with bigger audiences are also after this
kind of funding.
After six months on the air, O x y - Je u n e s k n ow s
it cannot live off the three awards it won at the
Radio Fe s t i val (Fe s t i val des Ondes) in Bamako
(Mali) in November 1999. Its sponsors and bene-
fic i a ries will need to use imagi n ation if the stat i o n
is to surv i ve . As it learned right at the start , w h e n
yo u ’re poor it pays to be bold. ■
Sri Lankan refugees who arrived in western Europe in the early 1980s often found it difficult
to adapt to life in countries they knew little about.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
gr a m m e s. L i ve coverage of community cultural
e vents and festivals organized in Europe is at t r a c-
ting a gr owing number of listeners.T RT also made
a rrangements with a local Tamil radio station in
Canada so that its programmes could reach the
100,000-strong Tamil community living there.
“The overwhelming support from our people
encouraged us to start a 24-hour television channel
six months after we launched the radio,” s ays Guha-
n athan Sabapat hy Suppaiah, director-general of the
TRT network.
S t a rted with an investment of $5 million in June
1997,TRT’s television channel today boasts over
7,000 subscri b e rs , mostly Sri Lankan Tamils living
in we s t e rn Europe. Its programmes are beamed
across Europe as well as to South A f ri c a , M a u ri-
tius and the island of Réunion where there is a
sizeable Tamil expatriate population.TRT officials
claim they have an estimated viewing audience of
b e t ween 50,000 and 60,000 people.The channel is
free-to-air in places like Mauritius and Réunion.
An alternative
to Western films
and serials
Unlike radio, T RT television charges its sub-
s c ri b e rs in Europe about $25 per month, mostly to
meet operating costs. At the Pa ris headquart e rs ,
there are about 20 full-time staff members and
some 50 freelancers working round the clock.T RT
has its own correspondents in the Ta m i l - d o m i n at e d
n o rt h e rn and eastern parts of Sri Lanka, in sou-
t h e rn India and in major west European cities,
where there is a substantial population of Sri Lan-
kan Tamils.The television channel also has a pro-
duction unit in India.
W h at prompted such a large-scale ve n t u r e ?
“Our pri m a ry objective is to inform our people
about what is happening at home and to address the
problems of our community now scattered in
various parts of Europe,” says Guhanathan.
S ri Lankan Tamil refugees started arriving in
Europe in the early 1980s after fleeing the ethnic
conflict in their country. Britain, France and Ger-
many took in most of them.Making a livelihood in
the host country was their prime concern .T h e n
came wrangling with officials for visas and wo r k
p e rmits for family members. Without any know-
ledge of the area or the country in which they were
living, they often found it hard to become accusto-
med to conditions there. Their first community
n e w s p a p e r , E e l a n a d u, was published in 1991 in
Paris and carried news reports about Sri Lanka as
well as local community events.
To attract the younger generation,TRT intro-
duced popular feature fil m s , classical music and
soap operas produced by Indian television chan-
nels as well as Tamil pop and rap music. V i e we rs
can ask to hear their favo u rite songs or pose a ques-
tion to an actor or actress during phone-in pro-
gr a m m e s. T RT also regularly broadcasts pro-
grammes produced by the Madras-based Sun TV
c h a n n e l . “Previously we used to ask our parents
about our music and dance traditions. N ow we
often watch them on T RT,” s ays A m i rt h ava rs h i n i , a
university student living in Paris.
The channel also provides the younger gene-
r ation with an incentive to learn Ta m i l . “Until T RT
came along, my cousins, who were born here, we r e
not interested in listening to Tamil songs and
m ov i e s. N ow they are regular T RT viewe rs. As a
r e s u l t , they have also picked up the language,” s ay s
5 5 - year-old Fe rnando T h o b i a s , who works at the
Hotel Méridien in Pa ri s.Among other things,T RT
o f f e rs an altern at i ve to We s t e rn films and seri a l s ,
which Tamils sometimes find offensive . “They we r e
eagerly looking for something close to their cul-
ture which T RT now prov i d e s ,” s ays Siva b a l a n ,
who has been living in Pa ris for the last 15 ye a rs
and often takes part in the channel’s literary pro-
gr a m m e . In addition,T RT ’s phone-in progr a m m e s
help displaced Sri Lankan Tamils to get back in
touch with their friends and relat i ves living in dif-
ferent countri e s.
Community 
support
Some might wonder why it took so long for the
Tamils to start up their own radio and television
channel.“We came here as refugees. At that time,
survival was our first priority,” says TRT’s Guha-
nathan.“It’s only recently that some of our people
h ave started to branch out into different areas,
which has given us a greater sense of confidence.”
TRT mainly depends on Indian satellite channels
for its film-based programmes and most of those
n e t works were started after 1992. It was perfect
t i m i n g, since by then the Tamils were in a posi-
tion—both technically and financially—to start up
and operate their network.
But T RT is not without its problems. C o m-
mercials are not generating sufficient revenue to
run the netwo r k , which costs about $800,000 a
ye a r. But T RT officials stress that their aim is not to
make a profit but pri m a rily to serve the commu-
n i t y. They are confident that once the subscri b e r
The TRT television channel launched in June 1997 serves Sri Lankan emigrants living 
in western Europe, South Africa,Mauritius and Réunion.
The free press may
doubtless be good or
b a d , but without
freedom it will never be
anything but bad.
Albert Camus,
F rench writer (1913-1960)
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 29
Small media, n e w v o i c e s
◗ Freelance journalist
year. Its farewell editorial said that “the present
situation makes it no longer possible to publish a
newspaper which believes in democracy, plura-
lism and respect for human rights.”
The turning-point came after Khelassi met
Rolf Gauffin, a retired Swedish diplomat and a
well-known expert on the Middle East and the
Maghreb. In the mid-1990s, Gauffin had covered
Algeria as a journalist, so he knew how hard it
was to get unbiased news. Every time he visited
the country, he was assigned bodyguards by the
authorities. All foreign journalists were obliged to
have bodyguards to “guarantee their security” but
in fact this was the best way for the government
to restrict their activities and intimidate people
they spoke to.
In 1996, a plan for an independent mains-
tream newspaper reporting on political,economic
and social matters was presented to the Swedish
Development Agency (SIDA). “Our idea was to
set up a paper written by Algerians for Algerians,
with reporters living and working inside the coun-
try, and so give Algerian journalists a chance to
write freely,” says Gauffin. But the project was
soon dropped in favour of a news-paper which
would be put on the Internet.
Building a network of correspondents 
Publishing on the Internet meant minimal
production costs and free distri bu t i o n . Fe w
Algerians have access to the Internet, but the
Swedish backers counted on people’s ingenuity to
boost the paper’s readership by printing it out
and photocopying it. Another big advantage was
that the Internet would give the paper a worldwi-
de readership, especially as it would be in both
English and French. “The Internet enabled us to
exist. Without it, we probably would never have
1.Usually defined as newspapers controlled neither by the
government nor a political party and seeking to publish
non-partisan news.
base enlarges,they will be able to generate enough
revenue to run the network.
Although T RT officials maintain that their net-
work provides only news and cultural progr a m m e s ,
c ritics assert that some of the content support s
Tamil Tiger rebels who are fighting for a separate
homeland for minority Tamils in Sri Lanka.
During the conflict that raged late last year in
the Wanni region of nort h e rn Sri Lanka, T RT
appealed to its viewe rs to help the thousands of dis-
placed Tamil refugees.There was an ove r w h e l m i n g
response from the channel’s audience in Europe as
well as in Canada: d o n ations added up to about
$400,000 and were sent to the displaced populat i o n
in Sri Lanka.
With overwhelming support from the commu-
n i t y,T RT now has ambitious plans to build “ b r o a d-
casting bridges that reach out to Tamils around the
wo r l d .”As Thulasi Mageswa r a n , a 14-year-old stu-
dent from London, puts it,“I feel proud to tell my
n o n - Tamil friends that this channel exists and espe-
cially that it is run by Tamils.” ■
People had dreamed about publishing unbia-
sed news of the crisis in Algeria but saw no
easy way to do it. Until the Internet came
along.
Journalists have long been unable to work
freely in Algiers. The independent press1 was the
first target of the authorities and the armed fac-
tions, which had a shared interest in snuffing out
dissent. Algerian journalists, faced with censor-
ship and more and more of their number being
killed, tried to start newspapers outside the coun-
try. But their efforts failed, often because of lack
of resources or because would-be financial bac-
kers lacked credibility. The only real successes
were a handful of supplements on Algeria written
by Algerian journalists and published in the inter-
national press, which showed there was a demand
for news about the country.
Noureddine Khelassi was one of the journa-
lists who dreamed of starting up a newspaper
abroad, though he had no funds to do so. He had
worked on the independent press at the end of the
1980s as editor of the daily paper La Nation. But
like many of his colleagues, he was forced to flee
Algiers in 1993 after an attempt to kill one of his
journalists. The paper closed on March 30 that
A l g e r i a D o t - C o m
◗ Djallal Malti
Algeria-Interface uses the Internet to put out ‘completely impartial news’ about A l g e r i a
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
be found by any search engine. “We had 90,000
hits between December 1 and 13, and we’ve had
550,000 since we started in November,” says
Derradji. “Easily a third of them have come from
France, which has a large Algerian community.
Another third have come from Algeria and the
rest from countries such as Canada, Belgium and
Switzerland, where there are sizeable communi-
ties of Algerians who have been exiled because of
the conflict.”
Gearing up
for real-time working
Encouraged by this success and with a large
amount of news to put online, Algeria-Interface
switched from fortnightly to weekly. “We’re now
p r e p a ring to work in real time,” s ay s
Benramdane, “but we’ve got a lot of problems to
solve before we get there.”
First there is the matter of the Internet in
Algeria itself, where there is only one Internet ser-
vice provider,CERIST, which is controlled by the
government and sometimes people have to make
dozens of attempts before they can connect.The
authorities are afraid that they won’t be able to
control the Internet, so they have still not allowed
it to develop freely.
Another problem is how to invo l ve local jour-
n a l i s t s. They are sometimes totally taken up with
their regular jobs and many have not yet visited
the A l ge ri a - I n t e r fa c e web site. “The Internet isn’t
yet part of people’s daily lives and some are not
sure whether a journal can be a serious enterp ri-
se if it isn’t printed on paper,” s ays Benramdane.
But most of all there are problems of funding.
The Internet means about a two-thirds saving in
production costs, but overall costs are still nearly
$24,000 a month. “The fact that the money
comes from Sweden—a neutral country with a
solid anti-colonial tradition where there wa s
strong popular and official support for Algeria’s
war of independence—gives immediate credibili-
ty to Algeria-Interface,” says Gauffin. “But we
know we have to broaden our sources of funding
to ensure long-term viability.”
Substantial investment is needed to finance
serious investigative reporting and news gathe-
ring. The Internet is a valuable tool for dissemi-
nating unbiased news and getting round some
kinds of censorship, but it does not solve the more
important problem of financial independence. ■
+ …
● http://www.algeria-interface.com/
come out,” says Gauffin.
As soon as SIDA released the funds,with help
from the Olof Palme International Centre, a
Swedish NGO, the small team on the paper,
which was called Algeria-Interface, started work.
They were based in Paris and consisted of an
accountant, two part-time journalists and an edi-
tor, Djamel Benramdane. They soon found an
office and bought computers. Within weeks they
had set up an Internet web site.
Benramdane had been working for some time
on the trickiest aspect of the project: during his
many trips to Algeria he had set about building
up a network of reliable and professional corres-
pondents. The network, consisting of a dozen
people, soon got off the ground. For the moment,
the reporters prefer not to have bylines in print,
partly to protect themselves but also to avoid
making fellow journalists jealous, since Algeria-
Interface pays its contributors a lot more than they
would get in Algiers.
A crucial
interview
A l ge ri a - I n t e r fa c e went online at the begi n n i n g
of November 1999 with the declared aim of
“ r e p o rting the news completely objectively while
remaining faithful to the basic principles of free-
dom of expression and press freedom, defence of
human rights and promotion of democrat i c
va l u e s ” . The paper was launched quietly at a
reception in Pa ri s. “ We sent inv i t ations to the
A l g e ri a n , Tunisian and Moroccan embassies,”
s ays Ta o u fiq Derr a d j i , the head of Inforu m , t h e
p u b l i s h e rs of A l ge ri a - I n t e r fa c e, “ but only the
Moroccans turned up.”
The real test came a few weeks later, when
Abdelkader Hachani, the number three man in
the former Islamic Salvation Front (FIS), was
murdered in Algiers on December 13. “At the
time, negotiations were in full swing between the
regime and the Islamists over how to apply the
law on civil peace,” says Benramdane, “so I
thought it would be interesting to ask Hachani
what he thought. An Algeria-Interface reporter
met him the day before he was killed. As soon as
we heard he was dead, we put the interview onli-
ne, describing how we’d got it. We weren’t happy
about the situation, but it was a minor scoop and
we were mentioned by many other media, inclu-
ding the French daily Le Monde.”
That day the site was visited by a record 6,000
people. Algeria-Interface usually gets a fair num-
ber of hits, even though at that time it could not
News is what 
the editor chooses 
to publish.
Arthur McEwen,
U. S. j o u r n a l i s t
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 31
Small media, n e w v o i c e s
I n d i a:
the information defic i t
Indian media expert Sevanti Ninan* re g rets that the absence of community media is depriving
r u ral Indians of information they need
What is the status of community radio, newspapers
and television in India?
A m a z i n g l y, a large vibrant democracy like India
is totally devoid of a tradition of community radio sta-
t i o n s ,whereas neighbouring countries like Nepal,B a n-
gladesh and Sri Lanka have allowed them.The Indian
g ove rnment is not interested in allowing community
radio centres because it is wo rried that secessionist
groups and some non-gove rnmental organizat i o n s
could use them to spread subve rs i ve propaganda. I
think this fear is unfounded,since there are always safe-
g u a r d s , as in the case of commercial broadcasting,
through which you can term i n ate licences and seize
the equipment of broadcasters who violate ru l e s.
In the case of community newspapers , there are no
legal hurdles, but it costs a lot to start a newspaper,
h owe ver small it may be. In the past, community news-
p a p e rs have not been able to generate sufficient adve r-
tising reve n u e , unlike the mainstream dailies, and as
a result many of them have closed dow n .In recent ye a rs ,
some pri vate cable operat o rs in the big cities have star-
ted providing community news and inform at i o n ,bu t
again these are ve ry small initiat i ve s.A c t u a l l y, there is
no culture of community media in India.
Do you think countries like India are losing out socially
and politically by restricting the number of voices that
can be heard in small media like community ra d i o ?
The restriction of community radio means that vil-
l a g e rs are not getting the local inform ation they need
about crop gr ow i n g, c attle diseases and commodity
p ri c e s.Mainstream as well as marginalized groups have
their own communication needs. I n f o rm ation should
be gi ven in local languages,and it should be recognized
t h at communication needs differ from region to regi o n
and community to community. In many deve l o p i n g
c o u n t ries like India the existing media do not alway s
take account of these issues.
In Medak district in the southern Indian State
of Andhra Pradesh, UNESCO has helped set up a
small local radio station with a 100-watt trans-
mitter which still awaits gove rnment approva l . It wa s
to be run by rural women members of a local NGO
and would help them to send messages to members
of their group and other organizations in the area.
The women argue that without a communication
channel of their own, which is the case at present,
their work is much more complicated.
U n f o rt u n at e l y, there has been no sustained
campaign on behalf of community radio in India. I n
1995 the Supreme Court ruled against gove rn-
ment control of the airwaves and declared that they
belong to the public, but so far no individual or
group has sought legal intervention to help them
start up a community radio centre.
What is the status of the Internet in India?
In India use of the Internet is less dive rse than in
the We s t . E - c o m m e r c e , I n t e rnet magazines and
I n t e rnet-based news sources have yet to become as
popular as they are in the developed wo r l d .This could
be due to the fact that in India there are more Intern e t
u s e rs than subscri b e rs.People are accessing Intern e t
mainly through Internet cafes and pri vate computer
centres rather than through connections of their ow n
at home or at wo r k . So they spend less time surfing the
net than Internet users in the We s t .
India has only recently allowed pri vate Internet ser-
vice prov i d e rs to operat e .The cost of Internet sub-
s c ription is falling as a result, but computer prices are
still high. An average middle-class person cannot
afford to buy a computer as it costs four times more
than a television set.So the Internet is accessible only
to a select group of people. To narr ow the gap, t h e
g ove rnment should introduce a computer policy to
b ring down the prices of computers and install them
in community centres. If this is done, then there is a
chance that the Internet will spread much faster and
more evenly than at present. ■
Interview by Ethirajan Anbarasan,
UNESCO Courier journalist
◗ Sevanti Ninan is a media
columnist with The Hindu
newspaper, published in Madras.
She is the author of The Magic
Window a n d Television and
Change in India.
The Internet is an elite
o r g a n i z a t i o n ; most of
the population of the
world has never even
made a phone call.
Noam Chomsky,
U. S. t h e o retical linguist (1928-)
A cybercafé in Bangalore (India).
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
New m e d i a , n e w r u l e s
◗ John V. Pa v l i k
The Internet is challenging the media establishment, empowering 
the public and re d e fining the role of journalists in society
2❘ The messenger 
is the media
About midnight on Fe b ru a ry 4, 1999 22-ye a r -
old West African immigrant Amadou Diallo
stepped through the doorway of his Bronx,
New York apartment bu i l d i n g . As he reached for his
wa l l e t , four members of a special police Street
Crime Unit drew their guns and fired 41 times.
Nineteen bullets struck the unarmed man,
several entering the soles of his feet as he lay dead.
I t ’s unclear why the police opened fire on the man;
as of this writing they had yet to be interviewed in
the case, which is scheduled to go to trial in early
2000.They were apparently seeking a suspect in a
rape case,and may have thought Diallo was him.
The case attracted world-wide attention and stir-
red considerable controve rsy over the use of excess
force by the police,especially in cases involving mino-
rity suspects in the outer New York City boroughs,
such as the Bronx. News media provided extensive
c overage of the story, r e p o rting in detail the eve n t s
t h at transpired that eve n i n g, as best could be surm i-
s e d .
One news organization, in collaboration with
students in my class at Columbia Unive rs i t y, o f f e r e d
an alternative perspective, or perspectives, on the
Diallo case. In addition to providing the standard
reporting on the events of that evening, an inter-
d i s c i p l i n a ry team of Columbia students, i n c l u d i n g
students of journ a l i s m ,i n t e rn ational affa i rs , bu s i n e s s
and computer science, worked with journalists at
A P B n e w s , an online-ori ginal news organizat i o n
devoted to crime coverage, to offer a multi-angled
news report on the story.
To provide a more contextualized view of the
killing, the Columbia-APBnews team employed a
new type of camera invented by a Columbia Uni-
ve rsity professor of Computer Science, Shree Naya r ,
which shoots a 360-degree view, to photogr a p h
both the ve s t i bule of Diallo’s apartment bu i l d i n g, a s
well as the street where he lived.
◗ Professor and Executive Director,
the Center for New Media,the
Graduate School of Journalism,
Columbia University, New York
Those who visit the APBnews.com web site
can examine the street and the vestibule,panning,
tilting or zooming anywhere in the entire field of
view. The view from inside the vestibule approxi-
mates to the view Diallo would have had that eve-
ning, but you can now see the bullet holes that
pock-mark the walls.
Letting the facts
speak for themselves
The view from outside the bu i l d i n g, t h o u g h
taken during the day t i m e ,a p p r ox i m ates to the posi-
tion the police would have had, giving the viewer a
sense of pers p e c t i ve on the shooting not possible
with conventional photojourn a l i s m .To g e t h e r ,t h e s e
n avigable images, only possible on the Intern e t ,n o t
only provide more context for the events of that eve-
n i n g, but can engage the audience in ways impos-
sible in the world of analog journ a l i s m .This heigh-
tened engagement and gr e ater context are cri t i c a l l y
important for journalism in the 21st century.
As A B P n e w s.com demonstrat e s , I n t e rnet not
only makes possible a more engaging form of jour-
n a l i s m ; it also puts gr e ater control in the hands of
the audience.The facts presented need be less fil-
tered by journ a l i s t s ; the public can draw its ow n
conclusions as to their meaning. In other wo r d s ,
j o u rnalists online can increasingly let the facts speak
for themselve s. Is this not one of the most long-che-
rished goals of journalism?
The Internet also permits a gr e ater range of jour-
nalistic voices to speak to an increasingly global
a u d i e n c e .APBnews was founded only two ye a rs ago,
in 1998,and is already recognized by many other lea-
ding news organizations as a reliable source of cri m e
n e w s. In fa c t , the APBnews service is carried by
dozens of other news organizat i o n s.
M a ny other credible Intern e t - o ri ginal news sources
h ave also arisen in recent ye a rs.O n e ,T h e S t r e e t . c o m ,
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 33
Small media, n e w v o i c e s
which cove rs the financial markets, is so respected by
premier news organizations that on November 24,
1 9 9 9 , The New Yo rk Ti m e s, perhaps the most highly
respected news organization in the wo r l d ,a n n o u n c e d
t h at it was going into part n e rship with TheStreet to
launch a news gat h e ring operation that would prov i d e
i m p r oved business news report i n g .
Examples abound of freelance journalists who
provide credible news reports from all parts of the
wo r l d . Freelance journalist Mario Profaca (Croa-
t i a ) , for example, r e p o rts on the situation in Kosovo
and also provides extensive coverage of the spy wo r l d
( h t t p : / / m p r o fa c a . c r o. n e t / m a i n m e n u . h t m l ) .G e o r g e
Adams edits “Not the South China Morning Po s t ” ,
o f f e ring a sat i rical view on press freedom in Hong
K o n g .These and other online news sources prov i d e
a global audience with altern at i ve journalistic vo i c e s
to contrast with the mainstream reporting of mul-
tinational commercial media organizations.
Research suggests that the public, especially yo u n-
ger audiences who have gr own up with the Intern e t ,
is increasingly finding value in this dive rsity of news
vo i c e s. One study has shown that as of 1998 some 36
million persons in the U. S . (including 30 per cent of
18 to 29-ye a r - o l d s , up from just seven per cent in
1995) look to online sources for news each we e k ,a n d
t h at 77 per cent of those aged 18-29 “like having so
m a ny sources to chose from.” In contrast, older age
groups less accustomed to interactive media are not
so likely to find this dive rsity appealing (70 per cent
of those aged 30 to 49,64 per cent of those aged 50 to
64 and 52 per cent of over 65s).1 I t ’s still too early to
tell just what impact this increasing use of online news
is having on the public.
Personalized news
The Internet also permits much greater custo-
m i z ation of news. Because of its ability to enable
on-demand media, as well as audience segmenta-
t i o n , the Internet permits audiences and news orga-
n i z ations to provide increasingly personalized news.
This pers o n a l i z ation is a two-edged swo r d .
Although it can permit audiences to get just the
news they wa n t , such as financial news customized
to their own investment port f o l i o, it can also increase
the level of audience fragmentation already ram-
pant in the media.
H owe ve r , i t ’s also wo rth noting that there is a
second type of customization of news possible only
on the Intern e t , and this type is not necessarily a
c o n t ri buting factor to fragmentat i o n .U n f o rt u n at e l y,
it is only in its earliest form ,and in fact few news orga-
n i z ations are actually employing it, although it embo-
dies a fundamental news value—localizing the story.
O n l i n e , it is possible to use databases that inclu-
We have usually
imagined a certain
special occupation when
we heard 
the word journalist. B u t ,
in the Internet era , t h e r e
is no separa t i o n
between sender and
receiver of information.
Each can participate in
journalism . . . . Each has
a potential competence 
to convey information 
and knowledge 
to others.
Kazuo Nomura,
Japanese sociologist (1955-)
1.Andrew Kohut,“Internet News Takes Off”, the Pew
Research Center, June 8,1998.
A web site showing the hallway where immigrant Amadou Diallo was shot by New York police.
Internet surfers can analyse for themselves the trajectory of the bullets. At right,poems dedicated to the dead man.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
de vast repositories of inform ation about entire
c o u n t ries or even the entire globe, and perm i t
audience members to see how a specific story,
e ve n t , process or phenomenon affects them in their
own community, interest group or life situat i o n .
Direct
access
B e l ow are three illustrat i ve examples, one from
an online news organizat i o n , one from a company
interested in exploiting the capabilities of the online
world for profit , and perhaps the public good, and a
third from a consortium of gove rnment agencies,
j o u rnalistic organizations and educational institu-
t i o n s.All three examples illustrate how a single story,
such as crime rat e s , election campaign contri bu-
tions or we ather pat t e rn s , can be transformed from
a generic story reported in a uniform fashion for the
widest possible audience, to customizable, i n t e r a c-
t i ve multimedia inform ation that can permit anyo n e
a nywhere in the world to see what that story means
for them in their own context.
APBnews permits users living in the United Stat e s
to enter their zip code and find out the crime rate in
t h at neighbourhood.This is an unprecedented resource
for citizens concerned not just about the overall cri m e
r ate in their city, s t ate or nat i o n ,but in the neighbou-
rhood where they live , or may be traveling or mov i n g
t o.The data come from a company that specializes in
making crime maps.
Po l i t i c s.com permits users to enter a name and
find out how much and when that person has contri-
buted to a political candidat e ’s campaign. U s e rs can
also enter a zip code and find out who in that neigh-
bourhood has contri buted to particular candidat e s ,
as well as how much they contri buted and when. It is
also possible to see how much particular candidat e s
h ave received in donations relat i ve to other candidat e s
and by month.The data come from the U. S . Fe d e r a l
Election Commission.
F i n a l l y, the Digi t a l E a rt h . g ov initiat i ve is an effort
to provide a virtual representation of the planet enabling
a nyone online to “explore and interact with the va s t
amounts of natural and cultural information gathered
about the Eart h .” Not yet fully functional, the site does
offer a series of operational prototypes, including three
dimensional (3D) interactive models of the entire Eart h
o f f e ring detailed we ather data collected via sat e l l i t e
around the globe, i n t e r a c t i ve 3D terr e s t rial topogr a-
phic visualizations of any part of the Earth,and much
m o r e . One of the principal agents in the Digi t a l E a rt h
i n i t i at i ve is the U. S . g ove rn m e n t . In contrast to day s
p a s t , g ove rnment agencies, such as NASA, can now
easily bring their “ n e w s ” directly to the public via the
Internet.
This third example also illustrates an important shift
in the long-standing relationship between news sources,
news organizations and the public. In the past, n e w s
sources had to be challenged almost exclusively through
news organizations before the public. In turn , the public
looked almost exclusively to news organizations to fil t e r ,
or act as gat e k e e p e r , for news produced by others.T h e
I n t e rnet changes this triangular relat i o n s h i p. N ow ori-
ginal sources of news and the public interface directly.
■
The journalist: a disappearing
species in the online world?
What is the role of the journalist in the new, direct-access media system? Is the journalist obso-
lete? I believe not.I believe that in an online world where there is an abundance, in many
cases an over- a b u n d a n c e, of information the role of the journalist becomes more important than
e v e r. But that role must change. Journalists must amplify their role as sense-make r s, helping direct
the public to reliable information, and pointing out when certain online information should be ques-
tioned because of the partial nature of its source.
Journalists in the digital age must be even more zealous in their pursuit of the truth, of balance
and fairness. These values are not necessarily part of the tradition of other “content”providers
who now have a ready-to-use medium to reach a global audience.
D e m o c racy depends on the effectiveness of its journalistic institutions to provide a fourth bra n c h
of government to act as a check on the other three, the executive, the legislative and the judicial.
J o u r n a l i s m ’s only real power comes in the court of public opinion, and without credibility, this power
is lost.
In the age of online digital media, entrepreneurial journalists and journalism organizations must
seek new ways to re-engage an increasingly global public without sacrificing any of the tra d i t i o n a l
newsroom values of accura c y, f a c t - c h e c k i n g , use of reliable sources and independence from com-
mercial,governmental and other influences. If it can succeed in striking this balance, journalism
will enjoy a renaissance in the 21st century, and society will be its benefic i a r y.A failure to find this
balance can only lead to the collapse of impartial journalism and the loss of reliable information
upon which society today relies for self-governance. J.V.P.■
The DigitalEarth.gov web site from which surfers can
explore the Earth’s natural and cultural life.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 35
Small media, n e w v o i c e s
◗ General Secretary, International
Federation of Journalists
New m e d i a , new h e a d a c h e s
◗ Aidan W h i t e
Is the Internet really the democratic force it is made out to be?
For much of the 1990s journalists have tended
towards Mark Twain’s wry observation, “I’m
all for progr e s s ,i t ’s change I don’t like.” But the
rapid development of the Internet has forced
changes,like it or not,in newsroom behaviour.
While some changes are breathing new life into
n e w s g at h e ri n g, o t h e rs are less we l c o m e .L o n g - s t a n-
ding notions of accountable, reliable and quality
j o u rnalism are under intolerable pressure in the
hothouse atmosphere of global competition.T h e r e
is little evidence yet that the long-heralded empo-
we rment of users is going to alter the balance of
power in favour of consumers.
Many celebrate the Internet as the vanguard in
the dawning of the new media age, offering inter-
a c t i v i t y, the end of inform ation scarcity and ins-
t a n t ,i n e x p e n s i ve , global communicat i o n .There are
of course great advantages.
Thousands of the nearly four million web sites
now in existence have been developed by traditio-
nal media. Traditional media organizations have
t u rned to the web to establish inform at i o n - ri c h
intranets for internal office use—many of them with
access to collections of public records or back-
ground information on timely subjects.
Pe rsonal computers and digital editors enable
r e p o rt e rs to digest and revise data on spreadsheets, t o
m a n i p u l ate images, to edit sound and image for
b r o a d c a s t , to insert , c u t , a d d , and to check out
i n f o rm ation with virtual librari e s ,public records dat a-
bases and numerous online ency c l o p e d i a .L a b o ri o u s
ve ri fic ation of the past can be done in seconds.
Huge databanks enable rapid and solid
r e s e a r c h .At the same time networks for global soli-
darity ensure that dissidents in China are not for-
g o t t e n , opposition radio in Belgrade stays on the
air in the face of Serbian censors h i p, and thousands
of protesters are mobilized to embarrass the
bureaucrats of the global economy in Seattle.
But there is a dark side of the inform ation revo-
l u t i o n . Much of the inform ation available on the
I n t e rnet is dull, unreliable and tri v i a l .The reality of
using the Worldwide Web for millions is endless
waiting, unintended disconnection,an abundance
of unwanted inform ation and high telephone
c h a r g e s. Discussion gr o u p s , much admired for pro-
viding access to information and diverse opinions,
are in reality hotbeds of rumour and gossip where
c o nve rs ation about issues can swiftly degenerat e
into rude, offensive and tasteless discourse. Tech-
nical questions often elicit inaccurate answers.
Jo u rnalists have to be on their guard in the ru s h
to meet deadlines not to absorb the unsavo u ry pre-
judices of crackpots or be taken in by the bogus
information that swills around the Internet.
At the same time,the radical edge of the Inter-
net is in danger of being blunted by the restructu-
ring of the wider information and communication
Part of the newsroom at the Paris headquarters of the Agence France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
Monopoly 
is a terrible thing,
till you have it.
Rupert Murd o c h ,
A u s t ralian-born U. S. m e d i a
tycoon (1931-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
i n d u s t ry. Increasing deregulation of the inform a-
tion market and the gr owth of global media corp o-
r ations add to a widespread sense of unease over the
suffocating spread of advertising and sponsorship
across the Internet.
Although there are new online news serv i c e s ,
traditional press agencies and mainstream media
leaders—CNN,the BBC,and every major quality
newspaper on the planet—are already established as
key inform ation prov i d e rs. The advantage of low
production and distribution does open the door to
a l t e rn at i ve inform ation serv i c e s , but the Intern e t
increasingly is becoming the domain of media
brand names that are linked to the major playe rs of
the global media market.An unprecedented wave of
m e r g e rs and acquisitions among global media
giants has created ten colossal ve rtically integr at e d
media conglomerates. Six of them—News Corpo-
r at i o n ,Time Wa rn e r ,D i s n e y, B e rt e l s m a n n ,V i a c o m
and TCI—are already able to mix and match a full
range of media serv i c e s , including Internet outlets.
Media conglomeration and commercialism in
media content are driving down standards of jour-
nalism and reducing the range of ideological and
cultural output. Some eminent personages from
within the media world itself complain that media
are increasingly self-serv i n g, v u l g a r , biased and
m a l i c i o u s. N e w s p a p e rs and television are ever more
profit-centred, while journalism is intrusive, inac-
curate and shallow with the dramatization of half-
truths and the promulgation of information from
unidentified sources.
These criticisms were particularly pertinent to
media coverage of the Clinton-Monica Lewinsky
saga where, according one British media cri t i c
“press excitement was too intense for ordinary pro-
fessional standards to preva i l .”1 I r o n i c a l l y, it wa s
this story that provided the first clear evidence of
the Internet’s arrival on the world news scene.The
dramatic online publication of the Kenneth Starr
r e p o rt on President Clinton’s relationship with
Lewinsky wa s , according to United States media
critic Jon Katz,the event that “ratified the Internet
as A m e ri c a ’s premiere means of rapidly dissemina-
ting critical civic information”.2
It certainly generated interest. This 120,000-
word text file was seen by almost 28 million people
in the first two days it was online—gr e ater than the
combined circulation of A m e ri c a ’s top 50 daily
newspapers.
Although Starr proved that the Internet is a
perfect place for breaking news, the event also
u n d e rscored just how important journalism is to the
process of understanding the world around us.W h i l e
millions of surfers had direct access to the Starr
r e p o rt in its tedious entirety, old style media scored
highly by making sense of it. N e w s p a p e rs and tele-
vision ratings soared.
People will always turn to a professional filter to
make sense of massive amounts of raw dat a . B u t
they also appreciate depth in reporting to better
understand what is going on. Too often, however,
m o d e rn news organizations gi ve themselves no time
for inquiry beyond trite and superficial reporting
and analysis.
Sound-bite journalism
In the age of instant news, j o u rnalists are urged
to compress complex and difficult issues into sound
bites. There is no room for detailed research and
b a c k ground report i n g . News organizations are not
in the business of taking risks as they compete
f u riously for market share in the burgeoning media
m a r k e t . Cuts in editorial bu d g e t s , p a rticularly in
the field of inve s t i g at i ve journ a l i s m , m ay explain
w hy so much low-quality reporting finds its way
into media both on and offline.
N e ve rt h e l e s s , the values of editing, of profes-
sionalism and ethical journalism remain the quality
benchmarks for media. But these standards are not
enforced in the online wo r l d .While complaints rage
around the heads of traditional editors , online jour-
nalism is largely unchallenged. In most countries
media content is regulated through transparent
s t ru c t u r e s , often administered by media themselve s.
M a ny people are sceptical about the effectiveness of
Press Councils and broadcasting authori t i e s , bu t
e ven these watchdog bodies are missing in the
online world.
It is clear that the differences between new
i n f o rm ation services and traditional media are
disappearing at a rapid rate. But some journalists
remain unconvinced that the creation of a new
media landscape will succeed in creating better
u n d e rstanding or widening the democratic process.
That will only happen if the traditional mission of
j o u rnalism and media to serve wider public and
democratic interests is restored as the central and
p ri m a ry goal of communication and inform at i o n
policy.
Absurd early predictions of the imminent deat h
of traditional journalism have given way to a reali-
z ation that people suffering from inform ation ove r-
load and drowning in information are starving for
the truth.As much as ever the public needs skilled
news gatherers to sort through the confusion and
chaos of the inform ation society, to put inform at i o n
in context and to present it in digestible chunks.
S o, the future of journalism should be secure.A f t e r
all,software robots will never overtake the work of
journalists.Technology can do many things,but it
cannot yet seek out and then elegantly speak the
t ru t h .Technology is only a tool and it should not be
confused with talent. ■
‘Press excitement was too intense
for ordinary pro f e s s i o n a l
s t a n d a rds to pre v a i l ’
1. The Guardian, November 8, 1999
2. American Journalism Review, November 1998,
http://www.ajr.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
F OR EAST EUROPE’S WOMEN, 
A RUDE AWA K ENING
◗ Elisabeth Kulakowska
Women are starting to react to the fallout from eastern Europe’s economic transition which has 
hit them hard, bringing growing poverty, social decline and prostitution
■
In Romania and Russia, they have
started by highlighting domestic vio-
lence. In Poland, they are fighting for
legal abortion. In Bulgaria and Hungary,
they campaign to make girls aware of the
dangers of making “easy money” through
prostitution. Women everywhere in eas-
tern Europe are trying to organize in
defence of their rights. They have an
uphill job on their hands.
The political and economic changes
which have swept the former countries of
the Soviet bloc since the early 1990s have
generally pushed women aside, both eco-
nomically and in terms of their presence
in gove rnment and administrat i o n .
Equality of the sexes is still written into all
the national constitutions of central and
eastern Europe. But the reality is quite
different.
The first
to be fired
A UN I C E F r e p o rt , Women in
Transition,1 which looks at 27 formerly
communist states, confirms this in detail.
“While communism brought wo m e n
many advantages, especially in education
and health care, it did not manage to
bring real equality of the sexes,” said
UNICEF director-general Carol Bellamy
when the report came out in September
1999. “Today, in the transition to a mar-
ket economy, the situation of women is
deteriorating.”
Since 1990, in every country of the
r e gion except Hungary, e c o n o m i c
◗ Freelance journalist
Women held some 14 million of the 26 million jobs that have disappeared in eastern Europe since 1989.
Some, like this Romanian woman, have gone back to work in the fields.
r e s t ru c t u ring has especially affected
industries with a large number of women
workers. Where there are both male and
female employees, the women have been
laid off before the men, in line with well-
k n own discri m i n at o ry practices which
send women “back to their homes”.
“Of the 26 million or so jobs that have
disappeared in eastern Europe since
1989, about 14 million were held by
women,” says Bellamy. Today unemploy-
ment among women is about five per cent
higher than among men.
Employers, especially in Poland, will
sometimes ask a job applicant to take a
test to prove she is not pregnant. In
Bulgaria and Romania, the newspapers
are filled with blatantly sexist job adverti-
sements.
Because of the seriousness of the eco-
nomic crisis, governments have sharply
cut social welfare expenditure.They have
also abolished many laws passed under
communism that gave privileged status to
single mothers and mothers with young
c h i l d r e n , and provided for infa n t s
through day-care allowances or crèche
facilities.The ending of these benefits has
reduced women’s chances of getting a job
or finding a new one. And when women
do have a job, they get paid less than their
male colleagues. The gap in pay is an ave-
rage 24 per cent in Russia, 16 per cent in
Poland and 15 per cent in Hungary,
UNICEF says. According to specialists, the
result is a “feminization of poverty”.
One of the most serious consequences
of the economic crisis and the opening of
national borders is the growing number of
young women who are being lured into
prostitution or enmeshed in international
sex rings. About half a million young
women from eastern Europe, including
Russia, are now prostitutes in the West,
according to the Polish NGO La Strada
and the Vienna-based Intern at i o n a l
O r g a n i z ation for Migr at i o n . R e gi n a
Indsheva, head of the Women’s Alliance
for Development, in Sofia, says, “10,000
Bulgarian prostitutes are ‘on the market’
1 The report was produced by UNICEF’s Regional
Monitoring Project (MONEE) at the UNICEF
Innocenti Research Centre in Florence, Italy. It
analyses in detail how the fall of communism has
affected the 150 million women and 50 million
girls who live in central and eastern Europe, in
the Commonwealth of Independent States (CIS)
and in the Baltic states.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
in most cases the attacker runs no risk of
prosecution. In Armenia, Bulgaria and
Georgia, hitting a spouse is not illegal. In
Slovenia, it is only punished in “serious”
cases but not where there is only “light”
injury, defined by the law as “a fractured
nose, rib, light contusions and punched-
out teeth.”
Each ye a r , “60,000 women in
Bulgaria are beaten by their partners and
only one per cent of rapes are reported to
the police,” says Indsheva,whose Alliance
is campaigning against the indifference of
the authorities.
In Poland, abortion has stirred up tre-
mendous debate. It was allowed between
1959 and 1993, and was then severely
38 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
E T H I C S
e ve ry year in the countries of the
European Union.”
Sexually transmitted diseases, inclu-
ding A i d s , are spreading. One yo u n g
woman in every 100 in Russia has syphi-
lis, according to UNICEF. In the 27 coun-
tries sur veyed in the report, cases of HIV
infection rose from 30,000 in 1994 to
270,000 by the end of 1998, says Bellamy.
In addition, there is rising alcoholism and
drug addiction among younger and youn-
ger women, especially in Russia.
Domestic violence against women, a
taboo subject that was totally hidden
under communism, has recently made
headlines for the first time in Romania
and Poland.The UNICEF report says that
“a survey in Moscow showed that more
than one in three divorced women had
been beaten by their husbands.” Conjugal
violence is forbidden by law in Russia, but
restricted until 1996, when it was permit-
ted again before being banned once more
a year later except in cases of rape, a
deformed foetus or when the mother’s life
is in danger. These decisions have been
greatly influenced by the Roman Catholic
Church. More than 30,000 secret abor-
tions take place in Poland every year,
according to local NGOs. The Po l i s h
Fe d e r ation for Women and Fa m i l y
Planning, founded in 1991, is campai-
gning along with other organizations for
legalized abortion.
Romania has gone in the opposite
direction. There, abortion was banned
between 1965 and 1989 by the Ceausescu
regime and was allowed without restric-
Three young women caught unawares by a photographer in Moscow’s Gorki Park.
+ …
● The Women in Transition report can be
consulted on the Internet at
<http://unicef-icdc.org>
● The Information Centre for Women’s
Associations (OSKA) publishes a list of
all women’s organizations in Poland
that can be ordered by email:
<oska@oska.org.pl>
● KARAT Coalition:
<http://www.karat.org>
● Albania: Women in Development
Association, Jeta Katro Beluli:
<jkatro@hotmail.com>
● Bulgaria: Women’s Alliance for
Development, Regina Indsheva:
<wad@olb.net>
● Czech Republic: Gender Studies Center,
Linda Simerska: <gender@ecn.cz>
● Macedonia: Union of Women’s
Organizations of Macedonia:
<sozm@mt.net.mk>
● Poland: Women’s Association for
Gender Equal Status, Kinga Lohman:
<kingacom@waw.pdi.net>
‘Each year, 60,000 women 
in Bulgaria are beaten 
by their partners and only 
one per cent of rapes are
reported to the police’
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
tion after 1990.This led to a sharp drop
in the hitherto very common practice of
abandoning unwanted children in dead-
end “ o rp h a n a g e s ” . In many countri e s
(including Hungary, Lithuania, Slovenia,
Slovakia and Ukraine), access to abortion
has been either challenged or restricted.
Equality slogans
with a hollow ring
Barbara Labuda, an adviser on social
questions to the president of Poland, was
a fervent advocate of women’s rights in
the 1980s in Solidarn o s c, e a s t e rn
Europe’s first independent trade union.
This tiny blonde-haired wo m a n , w h o
founded the women’s group in parliament
in Warsaw, admits she is sometimes dis-
heartened by the lack of involvement,
especially political invo l ve m e n t , o f
women in eastern Europe.
Only 13 per cent of the members of
Po l a n d ’s parliament are wo m e n . I n
Bulgaria,the figure is 10.4 per cent, in the
Czech Republic 10 per cent, in Estonia
12.9 per cent, in Hungary 8 per cent, in
Romania 7 per cent, in Slovakia 14.7 per
cent and in Slovenia 7.8 per cent.
Demands by women for a better social
status are still generally scorned in eastern
European societies. “The slogan about
equality of the sexes was drummed into us
for years by the communist party, but we
knew perfectly well it did not correspond to
reality,” says Labuda.“This is why women
now are very wary of us.”
Women feel crushed by a very heavy
daily burden which discourages activism,
says Erzsebet Szabo, Hungary’s official
mediator between the government and
citizens complaining about abuses by
public officials.
Networking
businesswomen
Bellamy is less pessimistic. For a start,
democratization in eastern Europe has
led to the setting up of many women’s
associations and NGOs that are very acti-
ve campaigners. In the Czech Republic,
for example, 70 per cent of the members
of NGOs are women, and 85 per cent of
NGOs were run by women 
in 1984. Poland, where civil society was
the first to organize during the commu-
nist regime, has some 200 associations
and groups working to promote the cause
of women or defend their rights. The
dozen biggest of them have at most 100
m e m b e rs. Romania has about 60
women’s associations, as do Albania and
Bulgaria.
Women are also getting more and
more involved in business. In nine of the
countries2 studied by UNICEF, a quarter
of commercial companies are headed by
women. In Bucharest, C ristina Gri g o r e s c u
runs AFIR which, with 100 members , i s
e a s t e rn Europe’s first bu si n e s swo m e n ’s
association. In all the other countries in
the region, businesswomen are forming
networks, especially to fight the reluctan-
ce of banks to provide credit to women.
The Beijing
connection
A turning point for women’s organiza-
tions in eastern Europe came in 1995.T h at
ye a r , for the first time, they were able to
take part freely in the United Nations Inter-
national Women’s Conference when it met
in Beijing.They made new contacts, with
each other and with We s t e rn organizat i o n s.
Since then, the KARAT Coalition has
brought together 10 associations (from
A l b a n i a , B u l g a ri a , the Czech Republic,
M a c e d o n i a , Po l a n d ,R u s s i a ,R o m a n i a ,S l o-
va k i a , Ukraine and Hungary) and holds
regular conferences.
In all the countries,such organizations
are just starting out on a long journey and
their achievements so far are few. But they
are all still fighting, and counting on sup-
p o rt from younger generat i o n s , to ensure
that women of the post-communist era are
not labelled as “second-class citizens” and
t h at democracy can thus be truly respec-
ted in their countries. ■
2 The Czech Republic, Slovakia,Yugoslavia,
Bulgaria,Romania, Estonia,Latvia,Lithuania and
Russia.
W OMEN’S STAT US 
UNDER SO V IET COMMUNISM 
T EN COURSES 
OF ACT ION
The main aims of eastern Europe’s women’s
movements are to:
● encourage political parties to get more
women to take part in the electoral
process;
● draft policies and professional practices
that broaden possibilities for women;
● encourage women to run companies by
giving them training and access to credit;
● organize public debate about the equality
of the sexes;
● combat violence against women;
● encourage parents to share responsibility
for educating children;
● encourage the state to continue helping
single parents, most of whom are women;
● maintain and strengthen the educational
level of women;
● fulfil the targets of the World Health
Organization and UNICEF in the field of
maternal and child health care;
● press for new laws.
A fter the October 1917 revolution, the Soviet
Union proclaimed the emancipation of
women through a “harmonious blending” of
work and motherhood. The communist Family
Laws, adopted in 1919, amended in 1926 and
1936 and later passed on to the satellite coun-
tries, guaranteed women a large number of
rights.
The state invested heavily to give women bet-
ter access to health care, education and jobs. An
extensive system of child care was set up, except
in Poland. After the Second World War, the deter-
mination to make jobs more accessible to
women had more to do with the urgency of
rebuilding countries in ruins than with egalitarian
ideals. Despite implementing programmes to
improve the situation of women, the communist
regimes did not manage or even try to establish
true equality between the sexes.
Sexual discrimination was never tackled
openly and mentalities remained very conserva-
tive. Women in fact had the double burden of a
job and looking after a home. They worked an
average of 15 hours a week more than men,
according to surveys. Equal access to jobs never
went along with more equal sharing of family
responsibilities or household chores.
Abortion stirred up argument under commu-
nism. In the 19 20s, Bolshevik Russia took a very
l i b e ral position but Stalin banned abortion in 19 36 .
It only became freely available again in 19 55 but
the conditions in which it was performed in hospi-
tals were dreadful. In the present Russian
Fe d e ration, it is still legal but is no longer free. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
■
“My wife and her mother died
without ever seeing our family home
again,” says Ivan Kamber,a retiree in
his 70s who lived until December 1991 in
a magnificent 17th-century baroque
house in the centre of Dubrovnik. “My
brother-in-law, the painter Ivo Grbic, is
still living in a hotel. All his canvases went
up in smoke, along with his ethnographic
collection and photo archive. I try to get
by in this 30-square-metre studio that the
city provided us with in June 1992.I hope
that I shall soon be able to return home.”
A scorched façade and soot-covered
walls are all that remains of the splendour
of Kamber’s old home, which was hit by
fire-bombs on December 6, 1991.
Eight other buildings in Dubrovnik’s
historic centre were just as badly dama-
ged.Their ruins bear eloquent witness to
the recent history of this unique jewel of
the world’s cultural and historic heritage,
which was described in 1929 by the
English playwright George Bernard Shaw
as “paradise on earth”.
A rain
of shells
The medieval commune of Dubrovnik
was founded in Late Antiquity (earlier
than the 7th century AD), and grew first
under Byzantine and then Venitian rule.It
became an independent republic in 1358.
A maritime and trading power that rival-
led the Venetian Republic, it reached its
apogee in the 15th and 16th centuries. It
even managed to keep its political inde-
pendence under Ottoman ru l e , w h i c h
began in 1526. But it was sacked in 1806
during the Franco-Russian war, and lost
its status as a city-state two years later. It
came under French rule and was ceded to
Austria in 1815. A century later, it beca-
me part of Yugoslavia.
D u b r ov n i k ’s urban fa b ric dates from
the 13th century, when its imposing fort i-
fic ations began to be bu i l t . These 1,940-
metre-long walls and ramparts still stand
i n t a c t . The austere elegance of the histori c
centre is a perfect blend of Gothic,
Renaissance and Baroque architecture,
making Dubrovnik the incarn ation of what
the Swiss art historian Jacob Burckhardt
called “the state as a work of art ” .
The city’s style and identity have sur-
vived despite being hit by many earth-
quakes over the centuries, including one
in 1667 which killed half the inhabitants.
More recently, two severe quakes dama-
ged about 1,000 buildings in 1979, the
year the city was put on UNESCO’s World
Heritage List (see box).
The repair work was not complete
when Dubrovnik was attacked in the
autumn of 1991 by the Serbian-
Montenegrin army. The Yugoslav conflict
dealt a terrible blow to the cultural heri-
tage of a city which, apart from the siege
of 1806, had never before come under
fire.Within a year, about 2,000 shells rai-
ned down on the walled city, damaging
563 of its 824 buildings and two-thirds of
its famous “fifth façade”—the roofs which
provide a large part of the city’s beauty
and harmony. Public and religious buil-
d i n g s , h o m e s , cobbled streets, s c u l p-
tures—all Dubrovnik’s ancient heritage
was threatened with destruction. At the
beginning of the bombardment, the city
was placed on the List of World Heritage
in Danger.
Bandaging
the wounds
Reconstruction soon got under way,
but it was not easy to reconcile the urgent
needs of the people of a wounded city
with the imperatives of restoring a World
Heritage site. The first priority was to
provide the inhabitants with a minimum
degree of comfort, e.g. tarred felt was laid
on broken roofs to keep the rain out. But
provisional measures of this kind were
soon replaced by long-term restoration
project. In February 1993, UNESCO laun-
ched an action plan to save Dubrovnik,
and specialists got down to work.
To rebuild the roofs, the original raf-
ters had to be strengthened—some of
them dated from the 16th century. Some
490,000 tiles had to be replaced.The ori-
ginal tiles, known as kupa in Croat, had
been made in the village of Kupari, about
15 km from the city, and dated from the
time of the Dubrovnik republic. But the
workshops had closed at the beginning of
the 19th century, and specialists now
faced the delicate task of finding a kind of
tile which could as far as possible be
made using the original techniques and
materials. After painstaking research they
found a solution, and a Croatian and a
French firm were commissioned to
manufacture the replacement tiles.
Restoration that rigorously respects
the principle of authenticity is no easy◗ Dubrovnik-based art historian and journalist
DUBRO V NIK
REBORN
◗ Maja Nodari
Seriously damaged by the conflict in former Yugoslavia, the great medieval city on the shores 
of the Adriatic has been restored in record time
The historic centre of Dubrovnik was badly damaged
by fire bombs in December 1991.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 41
task when so many old crafts have died
out. After a war, when resources are scar-
ce, it is even harder. Tourism, which was
Dubrovnik’s livelihood, was wiped out by
the war. Revenue from two million over-
night hotel stays per year had been the
main source of funding for heri t a g e
conservation. But in 1998, the municipal
authorities recorded barely 650,000 over-
night stays.
A 7-year
repair job
But determ i n ation tri u m p h e d , a n d
C r o atian and intern ational teams of
architects, sculptors, restorers and other
experts managed to complete the bulk of
the work within 7 years. In December
1998, Dubrovnik was taken off the list of
World Heritage in Danger.
Much of the funding came from the
Croatian government and the Dubrovnik
R e c o n s t ruction Offic e . But the wo r k
could not have been done without aid
from private Croatian and other sources,
notably The Intern ational Trust for
Croatian Monuments (United Kingdom)
and the Rotary Club of Klagenfurt
( A u s t ri a ) . UN E S C O took immediat e
action. It drew up a list of the damage,
earmarking $300,000 for the most urgent
work and launching an intern at i o n a l
fund-raising campaign.Alone, Dubrovnik
could not have tackled a repair job with
an estimated price tag of more than
$18,500,000 for the city within the walls
and $30 million for the urban area as a
whole.
A rtists also pitched in to help. T h e
famous Croatian pianist Ivo Pogorelic gave
t wo charity concert s , one in London and
one in Brussels,whose proceeds made the
first financial contri bution to the costs, e s t i-
m ated at $500,000, of rebuilding the head-
q u a rt e rs of Dubrov n i k ’s summer festiva l , a
p r e s t i gious cultural event that since its
inception in 1950 had attracted theat r e
companies,musicians and folk performers
from all over the world.The headquarters
building is one of Dubrovnik’s most beau-
Dubrovnik’s church of St Ignatius and Jesuit college during restoration work.
tiful palaces, built just after the 1667 ear-
t h q u a k e .On December 6, 1 9 9 1 , fire bombs
completely destroyed the second storey, t h e
rich interior decorat i o n , and archives recor-
ding over 40 years of activity.
Stone from 
ancient quarries
Stonemason Vinko Fa b ris dipped into
his own stock of stone for the most deli-
c ate repairs on the church of St Blaise,
the city’s patron saint, whose nart h e x ,
p i l l a rs and balustrades had been seri o u s-
ly damaged.The ori ginal stonework came
from the nearby island of V rn i k , w h o s e
n ow-abandoned quarries had been
exploited since A n t i q u i t y. To d ay Fa b ri s
uses time-honoured methods to extract
small quantities of limestone from these
q u a rri e s. He is the living embodiment of
a longstanding tradition of the island of
K o r c u l a , where he was born and from
where the bu i l d e rs of Dubrovnik took
most of their stone.
For six weeks, he and a Dubrovnik
sculptor, Ivo Jasic, worked together to
reconstitute the church’s balustrade.
“Although we were restori n g, n o t
creating,” says Jasic, “it was an honour for
me to be involved in the collective work of
art that is Dubrovnik, where the great
local and international masters have left
Dubrovnik
Zagreb
Italy
Croatia
Bosnia and Herzegovina
Hungary
Slovenia
Adriatic Sea
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
their mark.”
The church’s baroque festoon, to the
right of the main entrance, was restored
by French craftsmen Frédéric Mohus, a
s t o n e - c a rve r , and Jean Garder, a sculp-
t o r , who fa m i l i a rized themselves with
the z u b at k a, an ancient Croatian serr a-
ted tool, to obtain results as close as
possible to the work of the old master
c r a f t s m e n .
The damage to the church was a big
b l ow to the inhabitants of Dubrov n i k ,
who have revered St Blaise since 972
w h e n , according to legend, this mart y r
from Sebastia, in Asia Minor, s aved the
city from attack by the Ve n e t i a n s. On the
pretext of wanting to stock up on wat e r
and food on their way to the East, t h e
Venetians landed in Dubrovnik and took
a d vantage of their hosts’ kindness to note
the layout of the fort i fic ations and towe rs
in order to prepare a plan of at t a c k .
St Blaise then appeared in a dream to
a priest, Stojko, as an old man with a
white beard and revealed the Venetians’
intentions. In this way he saved the city
and became its patron saint and the sym-
bol of its freedom, neutrality and well-
being. For centuries, his effigy appeared
on coinage, official seals and state flags.
Statues of him guard the gates of the city.
He is still revered today and on February
3 each year, a solemn procession takes
place in his honour.
In recent years, the parade has passed
through streets cluttered with scaffolding,
but the Dubrovchani have not abandoned
hope.They know that in a few years’ time
their city will have regained its former
peaceful rhythms, its crowds of admiring
visitors from all over the world, and its
charm, immortalized nearly 400 years ago
by the Croatian poet Ivan Gundulic who
wrote that “all the gold in the world, all
the silver and all the blood cannot buy
your perfect beauty.” ■
A battered building receives first aid after the December 1991 bombardment.
W ORLD HERI TAGE IN DA NGER
As well as the World Heritage List, which now
contains 630 sites in 118 countries, the
World Heritage Committee maintains a list of
endangered sites that require special monito-
ring and urgent conservation measures. The list
was set up in 1979 to alert governments and
public opinion about the need to protect natura l
and cultural sites of outstanding universal value
that are threatened by natural forces or human
actions.
Cultural sites that have been placed on the
endangered list include Kotor (Yugoslavia), des-
troyed by an earthquake in 1979, the royal
palaces at Abomey (Benin), seriously damaged
by a hurricane in 1985, and Timbuktu (Mali),
which is under threat from advancing desert
sand. Natural sites include Mount Nimba (Gui-
nea and Côte d’Ivoire) and Ye l l owstone (United
States), both of which are threatened by mining
activity, and the remains of the ancient city of
Butrint, which was looted in the spring of 1997
during the uprising in southern Albania.
In November 1999, four new sites were pla-
ced on the List of World Heritage in Danger,
bringing the total to 27. They were the Iguaçu
National Park (Brazil), the monument complex
at Hampi (India), both of which are threatened
by road and bridge building, the Rwenzori
Mountains (Uganda), which have been occu-
pied since 1997 by rebels who prevent conser-
vation activities, and the Salonga National Park
( D e m o c ratic Republic of Congo), which has
been spared major fallout from armed conflict
but is targeted by poachers and disfigured by
illegal construction.
Like the four other world heritage sites in
Congo, Salonga can now get help from a UNES CO
project. Largely funded by the United Nations
Foundation, the project provides aid to the tune
of $4.1 million, mainly for training and equip-
ping staff and protecting biodiversity.
Once a site is on the endangered list, the
World Heritage Committee draws up an action
p r o g ramme in consultation with the state
concerned, and monitors restoration work
through to its completion. This is a very long job,
as shown by how few sites have been taken off
the endangered list—so far three natural sites
(Djoudj in Senegal, Ngorongoro in Tanzania and
P l i tvice in Croatia) and two cultural sites
(Dubrovnik in Croatia and Wieliczka in Po l a n d ) .
The inclusion of a site on the endangered list
is not always considered a boon by the state
concerned. Some countries ask for sites to be lis-
ted as a way of attracting international attention
to their problems and getting help, but others see
listing as a stigma. However, listing a site as heri-
tage in danger is often the only way to meet
c o n s e rvation needs effectively and urgently.
To benefit from listing, states parties to the
World Heritage Convention must inform the
World Heritage Committee as early as possible
of threats to sites on their territory. Individuals,
NGOs and other groups can also lobby the Com-
mittee by writing to the UNESCO World Heritage
Centre at 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07
SP, France. ■
‘Although we were restoring,
not creating, it was an honour
for me to be involved 
in the collective work 
of art that is Dubrovnik, 
where the great local and
international masters have left
their mark’
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
■
To see just how much Indonesia has
changed since the fall of its longtime
president Suhart o, simply step out
onto the street.Do not even search for one
of the almost daily demonstrations that
snarl traffic in Jakarta and other big cities.
Just head as far as the nearest newsstand.
T h e r e , on display, are the dozens of loud
m a g a z i n e s ,s a u cy tabloids and hard-hitting
n e w s p a p e rs that have sprung up since ri o t s
in the capital ended the former general’s
32-year rule in May 1998.
G r a n t e d , media penetration is still low in
this country of 204 million, the wo r l d ’s fourt h -
largest in size. But in a short period of time,
it has undergone nothing short of a press
e x p l o s i o n . In the 12 months following Suhar-
t o ’s resignat i o n , the gove rnment granted 718
new media licences,a leap from the 289 issued
in the 53 ye a rs since the country ’s indepen-
d e n c e .And more recently, in November 1999,
the gove rnment abolished the all-powe r f u l
D e p a rtment of Inform ation (known as Dep-
p e n ) . For decades, this fixture of gove rn m e n t
e xe rted tight control over the media and for-
bade coverage of any subject that stoked sen-
timents of ethnicity, r e l i gi o n , race or belief—
a justifiable policy in a nation made up of
numerous ethnic and religious gr o u p s. B u t
t h at rule was gradually stretched to cover any-
thing that annoyed the gove rn m e n t .
In the mid-1990s, as Suhart o ’s authori t y
was increasingly questioned, the press
became bolder and the gove rnment har-
dened its stance. When Te m p o, a leading
n e w swe e k l y, c overed a debate within gove rn-
ment over the purchase of 39 wa rships from
the former East German nav y, a deal
a rranged by the then-Minister of Research
and Technology B. J. H a b i b i e , its licence wa s
r e vo k e d .Te m p o successfully challenged the de
facto ban in two lower courts before the
INDONESIA: 
L E A RNING THE ROPES 
OF PRESS FREEDOM
◗ Jose Manuel Tesoro
Tight government control over the Indonesian media has ended, but there is still no social
consensus about how far press freedom really goes
◗ Asiaweek journalist based in Jakarta
Supreme Court upheld Deppen’s decision.
The gove rnment then went after journ a l i s t s
who had formed an independent journ a-
l i s t s ’ u n i o n . M a ny lost their jobs while two
m e m b e rs and an office assistant receive d
jail terms in 1995 for distri buting inform a-
tion considered offensive to the gove rn m e n t .
King of Spades
A popular TV talk show was cancelled
after its host interv i e wed one of the judges
who ruled in favour of Te m p o. But the jour-
n a l i s t s ’r e s o l ve did not wa n e , especially from
l ate 1997, when the media did its best to
c over the increasing discontent and unrest
throughout the archipelago, especially the
student-led anti-Suharto demonstrat i o n s.
After Indonesia’s parliament reelected
S u h a rto to a seventh 5-year term , D & R
magazine ran a cover port r aying the president
as the King of Spades.The act drew a sharp
r e buke from Deppen, which initiated pro-
ceedings against the magazine.But before the
case could be resolve d , riots erupted across
Indonesia and Suharto resigned.
When his vice-president, M r. H a b i b i e ,
stepped up to succeed him as a transitional
fig u r e , there were initial concerns about whe-
ther the small gains the press had made cove-
ring the tumult surrounding Suhart o ’s fa l l
would be rolled back.Those concerns multi-
plied when Habibie appointed East T i m o r
veteran Lieutenant General Yunus Yo s fiah as
minister of inform at i o n .Yet expanded press
freedom has actually been one of the much-
maligned post-Suharto transitional gove rn-
m e n t ’s most significant accomplishments.
One of Yosfiah’s first acts was to take
away Deppen’s right to revoke press
l i c e n c e s. He also streamlined the process of
granting gove rnment approval to new media
o r g a n i z at i o n s. He even asked applicants to
Under the Suharto regime in Indonesia, the newsweekly Tempo was banned for covering 
a politically sensitive topic. Its reappearance in October 1998, above, symbolized the beginning 
of a new era of press freedom.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
C O N N E X I O N S
r e p o rt any Deppen official who sought
favo u rs—such as stakes in media start -
ups—in return for a licence. He cut the
number of daily stat e - run radio news broad-
casts that stations were required to air from
14 to four.And he allowed the form ation of
other journ a l i s t s ’a s s o c i ations than the stat e -
sanctioned PWI. In a recent interv i e w,Yo s-
fiah explained the changes:“Now it’s dif-
f e r e n t .We consider journalists as colleagues.
We have a new paradigm.”T h at new stance
was symbolized by the reopening of Tempo
in October 1998.
At the same time, a group of publishers
and broadcasters also began efforts to revise
S u h a rto-era press regulat i o n s. The result
was Law no. 4 0 , passed in September 1999,
and described as “the first law liberating the
press from tyranny,” s ays S.L. B at u b a r a ,
chair of the Indonesian Newspaper Publi-
shers Association.The new law (see box)
revises 25 articles in the previous press law
t h at left the position of the press largely up
to the discretion of the inform ation minister.
It abolishes the system of licensing the
m e d i a , and transfers regulation of the press
to the industry itself.The Indonesian Press
and Broadcasting Society is now encoura-
ging its members to set up internal ombu d-
smen, and is drafting a common code of
conduct.
Although the law leaves many questions
u n r e s o l ved—especially with regard to
b r o a d c a s t i n g, film and programme censor-
ship and the apportioning of frequencies—
the reform of Deppen’s role and the laws
under which it controlled the press do mark
a step forwa r d .M a ny local journalists report
a reduction—even the disappearance—of
m i l i t a ry or bu r e a u c r atic interference in their
wo r k . But legal restrictions formed only
p a rt of the constraints on Indonesia’s press
under Suhart o.The press is still vulnerable
on other fronts. For example, while Indo-
n e s i a ’s laws expressly forbid foreign ow n e r-
ship of media, less is said about domestic
c o n flicts of interest. Nothing protects jour-
nalists from media owners.
Habits that die hard
Although Habibie himself tolerated daily
c riticism of his gove rnment and its poli-
c i e s , some of his allies and support e rs we r e
less forgi v i n g . Unrest erupted in Ja k a rt a
when Indonesia’s electoral college conve n e d
in November 1998 to confirm Habibie and
his policies. Soon afterwards, private tele-
vision station SCTV came under pressure.
A state-owned bank called in the station’s
$34-million loan, which triggered the sale of
a majority stake in the company. A firm
run by Habibie’s brother took the lead in
n e g o t i ating for a share. In a stat e m e n t ,
SCTV news producers claimed that the
g ove rnment was punishing the station for its
reports on the tumult.
Another grey area is the criminal code,
which retains many articles relating to the
press,including one that threatens as long
as four ye a rs in prison for writing or broad-
casting enmity, h atred or insult to members
of gove rn m e n t . The criminal code poses
an obstacle to coverage of past and present
g ove rnment misdeeds—especially since law
in the past has regularly been used to brow-
beat and control whistle-blowers.Yasmen
U m a r , editor of West Kalimantan’s daily
Pontianak Po s, s ays the public does not
know how to deal with negative coverage.
A g gri e ved part i e s , he says “head straight
for the courts,not the right of reply.”
In addition, public officials’reluctance
to provide prompt and accurate inform at i o n
makes it difficult to report on government
a c t i v i t i e s , much less suspected corru p t i o n .
“It’s a constraint on our industry that our
f u n c t i o n a ri e s , our public fig u r e s ,d o n ’t pro-
vide access to inform at i o n ,” c o m p l a i n s
Batubara. One recent case was a scandal
i nvolving the siphoning of over $70 mil-
lion in bank-restru c t u ring funds by fig u r e s
connected to the gove rnment and the ru l i n g
p a rt y. For over three months, H a b i b i e ’s
g ove rnment refused to release an indepen-
dent audit detailing the money trail and
identifying beneficiaries. The reason cited
was banking secrecy.
Jo u rnalists have to wo rry not only about
those in positions of power. Post-Suharto
I n d o n e s i a , with its economic collapse, ri s i n g
separatist, ethnic and religious sentiments
and politically charged at m o s p h e r e , i s
simply a much more dangerous place for
journalists to work. Not everyone accepts
the need for, or even the principle of, a free
p r e s s.The resistance lies both in a lingeri n g
sense that the media is responsible for poli-
tical education and in perceptions by the
public of bias among publications or jour-
n a l i s t s.“The public for the first time has to
put up with a free press, and views that
m ay be incompatible with one pressure
group or another,” says A. Lin Neumann,
Bangkok-based adviser to the Southeast
Asian Press Alliance.
One example is the coverage of confli c t
b e t ween Muslims and Christians in A m b o n ,
capital of multi-religious Maluku prov i n c e .
After riots broke out there in early 1999, t h e
city was practically partitioned between the
t wo wa rring gr o u p s. C h ristian report e rs
felt safe only in Christian areas.The same
W EBSI T E
OF THE MON T H
h t t p : / / w w w. t h e h u n g e r s i t e . c o m/
Each day, in different parts of the world, 24 , 0 0 0
people die of hunger—one every 3.6 seconds.
Three out of four of them are children under
five. This independent site allows you to make a
donation of food via the UN World Food Pro-
g ramme to hungry people in 80 countries, espe-
cially children through school-feeding projects. A
click on your button triggers the equivalent of a
s e rving of food which is added to a daily total. The
most appropriate staple food is then selected
for any given country or situation. Donations are
paid for by corporate sponsors in exchange for a
small advertising space. More than a million ser-
vings of food have been distributed since the
site opened in June 1999. ■
During a press conference held in Jakarta in December 1998, International Monetary Fund Director Hubert
Neiss greets Megawati Sukarnoputri, now vice president of Indonesia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
Blanketed by smoke and tear gas, journalists run for cover during a demonstration held in Jakarta on October 20, 1999 to protest against Megawati Sukarnoputri’s
defeat in the presidential elections.
went for Muslim journalists in Muslim
n e i g h b o u r h o o d s.The inability to cover both
sides complicated the already sensitive and
emotional issue of reporting religi o u s - l i n k e d
v i o l e n c e . Ambonese Christians felt that the
national press focused more on attacks on
M u s l i m s , and became hostile to Indonesians
working for local news organizations.
M e a n w h i l e , in East Timor in the ru n - u p
to its U. N.-sponsored referendum on inde-
pendence in August 1999, the situation wa s
r e ve rs e d .A rmed pro-Ja k a rta militias sought
out Indonesians and foreigners working for
the foreign press, assuming that most outside
o b s e rve rs favoured the terri t o ry ’s separat i o n
from Indonesia. In the afterm ath of the chaos
t h at followed the vo t e ,t wo journ a l i s t s — o n e
local and one foreign—lost their live s.
With the sudden collapse of gove rn m e n t
r e s t ri c t i o n s , one oft-repeated complaint is
t h at local journalists are not aware of their
responsibilities and duties, much less their
ri g h t s.“At eve ry opportunity I always say the
more the press are gi ven freedom,the gr e at e r
are the responsibilities they must assume,”
s ays Atmakusumah A s t r a at m a d j a ,e xe c u t i ve
director of the Dr. Soetomo Press Institute,
which is one of Indonesia’s few organiza-
tions providing formal training to journ a-
l i s t s. Few unive rsities have journalism fa c u l-
t i e s.
Aside from a flu rry of foreign-funded
s h o rt seminars for local report e rs , by and
l a r g e , Indonesian journalists learn from their
HIGHL IGHTS OF 
T HE 1999 PRESS LAW
● frees the Indonesian media from 
the discretionary control of the Ministry
of Information
● abolishes the system of licensing
● establishes fines and sanctions for those 
obstructing press freedom
● makes supervision of the press a matter 
for the press itself
● calls for an independent code of conduct 
for journalists
s e n i o rs and on the job.As such, standards are
often confused with accepted practice, a
s i t u ation exacerbated by low salari e s. O n e
long-standing habit is so-called “ e nve l o p e
j o u rn a l i s m ” in which report e rs who at t e n d
press conferences receive envelopes of cash
from the event organizer.The press also still
largely cove rs current events by quoting
public fig u r e s ’ views and announcements,
instead of setting its own agenda—a hangove r
from the Suharto era.
Anxious readers
question press freedom
The Indonesian media is now unfet-
t e r e d . But it is also unprotected. G ove rn m e n t
r e s t rictions and direction have va n i s h e d .B u t
w h at is left is disturbingly ill-defin e d .I n d o-
nesian journalists and editors have to find out
for themselves how far their communities will
let them go; in other wo r d s , h ow free their
r e a d e rs or viewe rs will let them be. N o
consensus has been reached over how fa r
the press can go in reporting the unprece-
dented change shaking Indonesian society.A
local media watch organization recently
conducted a survey in which three out of four
respondents believed that media cove r a g e
itself was contri buting to “ n ational disinte-
gr at i o n .”
The experience of Rusdi A m r a l , bu r e a u
chief in South Sulawe s i ’s capital of Makassar
for the national daily K o m p a s, is indicat i ve .
After Habibie, who was born in the pro-
v i n c e , lost his presidential reelection bid
on October 20, 1 9 9 9 , students in Makassar
held a series of demonstrat i o n s , s o m e
demanding an independent Sulawe s i .A b o u t
six truckloads of protesters arri ved at
A m r a l ’s offic e , to demand that their move-
ment be covered prominently in the news-
paper and to complain about K o m p a s’ p e r-
c e i ved Java - c e n t ric focus.“The press at the
moment is now able to overcome threats
from the bu r e a u c r a cy, civil or military,”
s ays A m r a l .“ W h at has become a wo rry for
us is the threat from the people.” Each time
demonstrators approached his office, the
police did not intervene. He and his staff
had to face their critics alone. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
T A L K I N G T O …
H e r z e g ovina but it had no specific
context of place or time. As co-author of
the film script,I wanted to situate the plot
in a definite place and time. So in the
film, everything happens in the course of
a single night in Belgrade.A night “haun-
t e d ” by ordinary people whose pat h s
cross and clash. Each person is a powder
keg, so there’s an explosion.
When we were filming in 1998, I was
expecting a social explosion. I’d felt it
coming in the streets of Belgrade during
m a ny anti-gove rnment demonstrat i o n s
I’d taken part in. But I didn’t think the
film was going to foreshadow a far more
painful explosion, with a rain of missiles.
As an opponent of the regime of Serbian
President Slobodan Milosevic, what was your
position on the NATO bombing in the spring of
1999 that was supposed to overthrow him?
The Powder Keg came out in Paris on
March 24, the day the bombing started.
The France 2 television channel had
scheduled me for a live interview after its
eight o’clock evening news programme.
So I was in the studio, waiting for the
news to end, when I saw live the first
shells exploding over my country. I was so
upset I had to leave the studio before I
could speak.The presenter asked me what
I was going to do. I said I was going to
find a corner to weep in. I didn’t go back
to the studio.
In the days that followed, I really
couldn’t decide whether to return to my
country or carry on with the opening tour
of Powder Keg. Should I be in Belgrade or
should I be going round Western cine-
mas? I chose the second option. I took
part in hundreds of public discussions
and gave as many interviews, trying to
explain that the bombing would only
increase the violence in my country.
When there’s a war on, what can 
a film-maker do?
You can’t be indifferent to war, espe-
cially if it’s ravaging your own country.
But what can you do in practical terms?
It’s very hard for film-makers to react
quickly with their only tool, film. A poet
can rouse the masses at the height of a
war. But a film-maker works slowly and
needs a lot of funding, which means that
when the war is in your own country, your
hands are tied.
Anyway, you need to step back a bit,
in time if not in place. It’s very hard to
make a good war film in the heat of batt-
le. The film-maker should denounce war
while staying neutral. But in fact we very
often take sides, consciously or uncons-
ciously. They say history is written by
people on the winning side. The same
goes for war films.That’s why I don’t like
this kind of film, with all due respects to
Stanley Kubrick’s Full Metal Jacket, the
most brilliant war film of all time, and
Jean Renoir’s La Grande Illusion.
I decided to wage my war on war not
through my work but through my position
as a film-maker. I did that extensively
when my latest film, The Powder Keg,
came out in the spring of 1999, by talking
to cinema audiences and in the media all
over Europe and the United States.
The Powder Keg deals with war but it isn’t a
war film.
For me, war is a total eclipse of human
conscience. It’s that darkening which the
film deals with. The script was based on
an excellent play by Dejan Dukovski, a
Macedonian playwright who a few years
ago, when he was only 26, managed to
capture the mood of the Balkans today.
The play dealt with the war in Bosnia and
SERBIAN 
FIL M - M A K ER 
GORAN PASKA LJEV IC
The director of a dozen feature films internationally acclaimed for their blend 
of lyricism and realism talks about the background of his latest film, which deals with 
‘the eclipse of human consciousness’ caused by war
Events proved me right.The Serbian poli-
ce, paramilitary and army immediately
began expelling Albanians from Kosovo. I
was ashamed of that and ashamed that
such actions were taking place “in my
name” as a Serb. And the violence is still
going on. Now Kosovo, at last a secure
place for Albanians, has become a hell not
only for Serbs but also for Turks, Gypsies
and even for Albanians who don’t support
the Kosovo Liberation Army (KLA).And
Milosevic is still in power.
I tried to explain that the bombs were
actually falling on Serbian democracy and
that by destroying the country, they were
strengthening Milosevic’s hold on power.
How, after bombing Serbia, can Europe
say to the Serbian people that they should
reject the authoritarian, short-sighted and
selfish Milosevic regime and replace it
with Western-style democracy? As a result
of this war, the Serbs have lost the few
points of reference they still had. They
don’t know where to turn.The regime has
led them up a blind alley, the opposition
is sporadic and disunited; Europe has
betrayed them. If I spoke out publicly
against Milosevic in Serbia today, the
authorities would reply at once: “Don’t
listen to him, he’s a NATO hireling.” Not
many people would give me a hearing.
Serbia’s pro-government press has already
accused you of “treachery”.
Ye s , t h at was in September 1998,
before the NATO bombing. It said I’d
betrayed the Serbian people for having
told the Italian newspaper La Repubblica
that Milosevic was the main person to
blame for the situation in Kosovo. The
author of one article even suggested I
ought to commit suicide if I had any self-
respect left. Without dramatizing my
present situation, I don’t think I’m safe
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
February 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G  T O …
FIL MOGRA PH Y
Born in Belgrade in 1947, Goran Paskaljevic
became a film buff at at an early age and
later studied at Prague’s famous Film Academy
of Musical Arts (FAMU). He made about 40
short films between 1969 and 1974, and then
went on to direct:
■ Beach Guard in Winter (1976). Berlin:
Special Jury Prize; Pula Festival (Croatia):
Golden Arena and Critics’ Prize; Film of the Year
in Yugoslavia;
■ The Dog who Loved Trains (1977). Entered at
Berlin Film Festival;
■ And the Days are Passing (1979). Film of the
Year in Yugoslavia;
■ Special Treatment (1980). Cannes (France):
Prize for best supporting actress to Milena
Dravic; Hollywood: Golden Globes nomination;
Pula Festival: Golden Arena; Film of the Year in
Yugoslavia;
■ Twilight Time (1982): UNICEF Grand Prix;
■ The Elusive Summer of ’68 (1984). Orléans
(France): Grand Prix and Public Prize; Bastia
(France): Jury Grand Prix.
■ Guardian Angel (1987). Cannes: Directors’
Fortnight; Rio de Janeiro (Argentina): CIFEJ
(International Centre of Films for Children and
Young People) Prize.
■ Time of Miracles (1990). Cannes: Directors’
Fortnight; San Sebastian (Spain): International
Critics’ and OCIC (International Catholic
Organization for Cinema and Audiovisual)
Prizes.
■ Tango Argentino (1992). Laon (France):
Grand Prix and CIFEJ Prize; 
San Francisco: Public Grand Prix; Vancouver
(Canada): one of the ten best films of the year;
Montpellier (France): Critics’ Prize.
■ Someone Else’s America ( 1995). Cannes:
Directors’ Fortnight. Valladolid (Spain): Grand Prix;
Bastia (France): Silver Olive and Public Prize.
■ The Powder Keg (1998). Venice, Future
Section, International Critics’ Prize; Haïfa
(Israel): Grand Prix. 
from a contrived “suicide” on the streets
of Belgrade. But that doesn’t stop me cri-
ticizing the regime, just as I denounced
the bombing. One shouldn’t confuse the
regime with the people, even if the people
are partly responsible. I’ve noticed that
the two have been bracketed together
both in my country and in the West.
What do you think is the people’s share 
of responsibility?
There was a time when Milosevic was
hailed by millions of Serbs. He was voted
into power three times. OK, the third
time the elections were rigged, but they’d
voted for him before that. But that said,
they were tricked.The rise of nationalism
in the former Yugoslavia wasn’t sponta-
neous. We know who the main culprits
we r e . Milosevic in Serbia, F r a n j o
Tudjman in Croatia and Alija Izetbegovic
in Bosnia and Herzegov i n a . They all
played the nationalist card to entrench
t h e m s e l ves in powe r. I t ’s a card that
always works at troubled moments in
history.
Why didn’t anti-nationalist intellectuals in the
former Yugoslavia react strongly enough to
the rise of nationalism?
Many of us did react, but we have very
little room for manoeuvre. Our vo i c e
doesn’t carry very far. We don’t have any
power and we had no money to reach a
wide audience, either at home or abroad.
But let me ask a few questions. Why
were the Western democracies so indiffe-
rent to the democratic movement in
Serbia? Why did they make Milosevic “the
guarantor of peace”by accepting him as a
s i g n at o ry of the Dayton accords in
November 1995? When we took to the
streets in 1997 after the municipal elec-
tions, it was 10 days before French TV
decided to show that something was hap-
pening in Serbia. Yet these demonstra-
tions went on for three months. If we’d
had a bit of material aid at that time—no
more than the price of a single Tomahawk
missile—we could have set up indepen-
dent media, and Serbs could have heard
another version of events instead of just
the government’s.
You’re regarded as a committed artist. What
But let me ask a question.
Why were the We s t e r n
d e m o c racies so indifferent 
to the democratic movement 
in Serbia?
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The UNESCO Courier - February 2000
T A L K I N G T O …
closeness to life. And if it’s going to refle c t
life fa i t h f u l l y, it has to draw on metaphor,
just like poetry. The Powder Keg is realistic
but it’s a metaphor too. Nights in Belgr a d e
a r e n ’t all like the one in the fil m .
Have you been criticized for being 
pessimistic?
Yes, several times. The public’s need
to see films that end with a ray of hope
comes from the theory of socialist realism
that was dinned into us at school, at any
rate into those of us who were brought up
in eastern Europe. Communism collap-
sed and socialist realism with it, but its
golden rule of “be optimistic and believe
in a radiant future” still lives on in the
public’s mind. Oddly enough, it’s the
American film industry that went furthest
with socialist realism, by introducing the
notions of hope and optimism as intrinsic
parts of a film. From then on it was hard
to convince the public that these were not
the criteria by which a film should be jud-
ged.
I ’ ve been particularly criticized by
some of my compatriots who live abroad
and think the media has already gone
quite far enough in “tarnishing the image
of the Serb people” and that there was no
need for me to contri bute with T h e
Powder Keg. Has anyone ever criticized a
French film-maker for tarnishing the
T IMEL INE
■ May 4, 1980: Death of Josip Broz Tito,
President of the Federal Socialist Republic of
Yugoslavia. The country slips into economic
crisis.
■ September 1987: Slobodan Milosevic
comes to power in Serbia.
■ March 28, 1989: Milosevic abolishes the
autonomy of two Yugoslav provinces, Kosovo
and Voivodina.
■ June 25, 1991: Unilateral proclamation of
the independence of Slovenia and Croatia.
■ June 27, 1991: Sloveno-Yugoslav war
lasting 10 days.
■ August 9, 1991: War breaks out in Croatia.
■ November 7, 1991: The Republic of
Macedonia proclaims its independence.
■ April 8, 1992: War breaks out in Bosnia.
■ October 21, 1995: The Dayton accords are
signed; peace in Bosnia and Croatia.
■ March 24, 1999: NATO bombing of the
Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (Serbia,
Montenegro) begins.
do you mean by commitment?
Politically, my commitment has lain in
carefully avoiding joining any party or
accepting a government job. I value my
independence and my freedom. For me,
being committed means having a dialecti-
cal relationship with reality and never fin-
ding oneself outside or above it.That’s the
sense in which my films are committed.
Guardian Angel denounces the dreadful
reality of the trade in Gypsy children, The
Dog who Loved Trains the plight of social
outcasts and Someone Else’s A m e ri c a
exposes the situation of immigr a n t s.
Although I stress feelings in my films, rea-
lity is their dominant theme.
Which school of film-makers do you 
belong to?
You’re asking me to do the critics’
job! I don’t see myself shut away in a dra-
wer, even one lined with velvet and silk.
I’m claustrophobic. I tend to see myself as
being on a vast plain inhabited by disad-
vantaged people whose fate concerns me.
That’s the backcloth. Form is of seconda-
ry importance. I tailor it to the story I
want to tell. That’s why all my films are
different. The one consistent thread is
their humanism. The cinema classics I
feel closest to are those of the Italian neo-
realist Vittorio de Sica. They are full of
feeling but they say more about Italy than
any documentary. I also feel close to the
works of the French director Jean Renoir,
which are both poetic and realistic.
I don’t like films that go off into wild
fantasies. Dreams are important in our
lives, but life isn’t just dreams. It’s reality
that hurts. Dreams only interest me inso-
far as they bandage wounds.
I also don’t like films that take too
pessimistic a view of life in order to serve
a political cause,however just it might be.
Your films seem to be metaphors rather 
than messages.
I usually send messages by e-mail.
Has life got a message? No. The wonder-
ful thing about life is that it’s a great
mystery whose secrets we constantly have
to discover.The beauty of film for me is its
I’ve been particularly criticized
by some of my compatriots
who live abroad and think the
media has already gone quite
far enough in ‘tarnishing the
image of the Serb people’ and
that there was no need for me
to add my contribution with
The Powder Ke g.
A demonstrator defies police in Belgrade, February 1997.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O …
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498 FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 72FF ( 11 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211FF ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:                  Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
A still from Goran Paskaljevic’s film The Powder Keg
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G T O …
image of the French people?
As an artist from the Balkans, do you think
Western audiences expect something special
from you?
I sometimes feel they expect me to
have an answer for everything, in my
films, in public debate, and in interviews
with journalists. A French film-maker is
questioned about aesthetics; I am asked
what I think of NATO. People also expect
my films to denounce this or that policy.
But I repeat, politics isn’t my business. I
shall be making my next film in Mexico
and it will look at disease and death.
Nothing to do with Serbia. But I always
find I’m defending a gi ven area—the
Balkans—and defending my work within
that area. People forget I’m just someone
who thinks and who tries to express,
through films, what he thinks.
At the 1999 Venice film festival, Scandinavian
critics said The Powder Keg was over the top
and unrealistic. Did they think the film was
too “Balkan”, not universal enough?
The film did go to the limit as far as vio-
lence was concerned and some of the situa-
tions shown might be considered impro-
b a b l e . But there was less blood in it than in
m a ny Hollywood love stori e s. I wanted to
s h ow that no country holds a monopoly on
violence and that any one of us, a ny w h e r e
in the wo r l d , at any time, can be a prey to it.
T h at human beings are not inherently evil
but become destru c t i ve because they’r e
egged on by circumstances. I t ’s in this sense
t h at my film is unive rs a l .
If the Scandinavians did not feel it was
their kind of film, it was perhaps because
they felt that their structured and well-
ordered society is impervious to violence.
Latin American critics and journalists in
Venice, on the other hand, reacted as if
the film might have been made in their
countries, and so did the Italians and to
some extent the French. Later, the res-
ponse of the American public confirmed
for me that the film could have been made
in the Bronx or Brooklyn.
To criticize it for being unrealistic is
like saying Van Gogh’s skies are too blue.
Art isn’t a carbon copy of nature. The
extent to which a film is realistic is of
s e c o n d a ry import a n c e , because reality
itself is relative. The important thing, as
with all art, is that the film is authentic.
Film is an art-form, but it’s also an industry,
isn’t it?
Above all it’s an art, but an expensive
art. This means a film-maker always has
to think about profitability, a concept
from the world of industry and commer-
ce. For fear of not being able to keep on
making films, directors often try to please
a wide public which has been suckled
from its earliest years at the breast of
Hollywood, has acquired a taste for it and
doesn’t want to be weaned.But I trust the
wider public, all the same. I don’t think
the public always wants to see the world
through rose-coloured spectacles. T h e
success of Will It Snow for Christmas?
(1995), the first film by French director
Sandrine Veysset, reassures me about this.
I think it’s the distributors who’ve impo-
sed this false idea of the uniformity of the
public which allows them to always take
the easiest path.
But you’ve made a Hollywood-style film,
Twilight Time. Later you said you’d lost your
soul. Why was that?
I t ’s not, s t rictly speaking, a Hollywo o d -
type fil m . It was ordered by Hollywood and
filmed in Yugoslavia.I gave in to the temp-
tation of the huge amount of money I was
o f f e r e d . When yo u ’re young and used to
working with ve ry little money and you see
the gleaming prospect of gold ingots before
your eye s , you don’t have the strength to
say no.You tell yourself that at last you’re
going to be able to fulfill all your dreams as
a film-maker. But from the start of the fil-
ming, I realized money was creating more
problems than the lack of it and that it’s fa r
from being a guarantee of artistic freedom.
It was a lesson to me. I lost my soul because
I had to make too many compromises.
Do you think there’s such a thing 
as a “Balkan soul”? If so, how would 
you describe it?
It does exist, but it’s impossible to
define. Just when you think you’ve got it
in your grasp, it slips away from you. But
that’s what makes it “Balkan”and why it’s
so splendid. It’s dishevelled and smiling,
emotional and vulnerable. It likes to day-
dream, it has a sense of humour and self-
mockery. It isn’t pragmatic, it’s rather
fatalistic, it believes in myths and it’s
stubborn, very stubborn—to the point of
self-destruction. ■
Interview by Jasmina Sopova,
UNESCO Courier journalist
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George's Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Brussels. 
Fax: 538 08 41.
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
Oxford Book & Stationery Co, Code No D 820 8 0 52, Scindia House, New
Delhi 110 001. Fax: 33 22 639 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Nalanda Co. Ltd., 30 Bourbon Street, Port Louis. 
Fax: 212 1313 .
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
Los Amigos de la UNES CO, Avenida Urquijo 62, 2 Izd., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 94427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG, Wissenschaftl. Buchhandlung, Pe t e r s g raben 31, 
CH-4009 Basel. Fax: 306 12 34 .
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce
C/C Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: 286 03 26 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
Photo album, 112 pp., 37 x 23 cm
ISBN 92-3-103625-4
295 FF / 44.99
UNESCO Publishing / Cofimag
U N E S C O  P u b l i s h i n g
The Great Age
By Dominique Roger 
and Jacques Le Ribault
Older people in 
everyday life.
Dignity and diversity 
in later years. 
The Panama Canal
Transfer of the Panama Canal – 
Special Commemorative Edition
Published on the occasion 
of the transfer of the 
Panama Canal from the 
United States to Panama.
The construction, 
administration, economic 
and strategic importance 
of the Canal and its future.
200 pp., 30.5 x 25 cm, black and white and colour
photographs, maps, drawings
ISBN 92-3-003707-9
250 FF / 38.11
Bilingual: English and Spanish
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Fo c u s :
Education for all:
Schools set on a fresh course
■ The 1990s: new partnerships, uneven results ■ A Ugandan success story: strong leadership and grassroots
commitment ■ Bangladesh: an NGO gets girls into school 
■ 10 million Indian volunteers mobilize for literacy ■ Mongolia: job skills via the airwaves 
■ El Salvador: when parents run schools ■ Will we ever eradicate illiteracy?
Fe a t u res include
■ Wind power on the crest of a wave ■ Animal organ transplants: is humanity at risk? 
■ Argentina’s child reporters ■ Telecentres put rural Africa online
1 8t h Fair for Languages,
C u l t u res, and International Exchanges
E x p o l a n g u e s
2000
Grande Halle 
de la Vi l l e t t e
PA R I S
TRADE DAY- Wednesday 23 February 2000 - From 9.30 a.m. to 9.00 p.m.
e x p o l a n g u e s @ re e d - o i p.fr - http://expolangues.re e d - o i p. f r
E x p o l a n g u e s
23 - 27 February 2000
Grande Halle de la Villette - Paris
ADMISSION
FF 30 instead of FF40
with this coupon
Free for language teachers
]]>
</page>
</document>
