<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="119217eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
March 2000
PEOPLE AND PLACES
Potosi’s silver 
tears
PLANET
Energy’s wind 
of change
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
Computers rebuild
the past
IN T ERV IEW
John Abbott,
South Africa’s 
c i ty stitcher
Education for all
Schools reach out
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
C o n t e n t s
M a rch 2000 53rd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Cynthia Guttman
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat,
Photoengraving:Annick Coueffé
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corral,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh(Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UN E S C O or those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. P h o t o
captions and headlines are written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r
s t a f f. The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O o r
the United Nations. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7
Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfil m s
( X e r o x ) ,Ann A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C . R .
Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfie l d
R o a d ,Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - MARCH2000
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Pa r i s
by UN E S C O. Printed in Fr a n c e. Periodicals postage paid at
Champlain NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 3-2000-OPI 99-589 A
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 Potosi’s silver tears Photos by Stephen Ferry;Text by Amalia Barron
PLANET
9 E n e rg y ’s wind of change Birger T. M a d s e n
11 G e r m a n y : tilting at windmills Hartmut We w e t z e r
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Quiet please! Children talking Silvia Bacher and Monica Beltran
ETHICS
37 Animal tra n s p l a n t s : safe or sorry? Amy Otchet
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 C o m p u t e rs rebuild the past Sophie Boukhari
CONNEXIONS
43 Te l e c e n t res share the tools of the information age Richard Fuchs
44 Timbuktu online Sophie Boukhari
TALKING TO…
46 John A b b o t t ,South A f r i c a ’s city stitcher
1 6 Focus Education for all
Schools reach o u t
On the eve of an international conference which is being held to
take stock of action to promote education for all during the last
decade, this Focus section showcases projects that reach the
excluded through grassroots involvement. But if education is to
become a right and a source of enrichment for everyone, many
other innovative approaches and bold commitments will be
required.
Detailed table of contents on page 16.
Editorial by Ko ï c h i ro Matsuura on page 17.
C o v e r : © Spier Donati/Rapho, Paris 
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 -The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
P OTOSI’S 
SILV ER TEARS
◗ Photos by Stephen Ferry; Text by Amalia Barron
The city that once made Europe rich is dying. 
The impoverished miners who live there are struggling 
to survive amid the ruins of its bygone splendour
Deep within Potosi’s Cerro Rico (“Rich Mountain”), silver miners sometimes work more than 10 hours a day.
They chew coca leaves to help to alleviate the harsh conditions.
◗ Stephen Ferry is an American photographer.
Amalia Barron is a journalist based in La Paz, Bolivia.
■
“ I t ’s so poor, it makes you want to
we e p,” s ays Bolivian historian Va l e n-
tin A b e c i a . H e ’s not exaggerat i n g . A
visit to Po t o s i , which helped to maintain the
splendour of Europe from the 16th to the
18th centuri e s , is today a spine-chilling
experience.
Around two billion ounces of silver we r e
extracted from the city’s Cerro Rico (Rich
Mountain) during the Spanish colonial era.
C e rro Rico silver paved Po t o s i ’s streets, f u e l-
led the European Renaissance and helped
fund the “ I nvincible A rm a d a ” , the Spanish
fleet that sailed against Elizabethan England
in 1588.
But today Potosi is dying. “When a mine
c l o s e s , all that ’s left is a ghost tow n ,” s ay s
the city’s mayo r , René Jo a q u i n o. S o m e t h i n g
of Potosi ebbs away whenever a seam of
metal is exhausted or world mineral prices
d r o p. Most of the mines closed down after a
c risis in 1985 and many people left for good.
Two ye a rs lat e r , when the Bolivian gove rn-
ment introduced new incentives to mining,
u n e m p l oyed miners began to trickle back
and set up 50 co-operatives.
Streets paved with silver
Most of the city’s population of around
120,000 are Quechua Indians,who live by
scratching at what is left in the old mines.
They have no access to modern techno-
logy and no social security protection.T h e r e
is practically no middle class in Potosi. “I
d o n ’t know any rich people who live in this
c i t y,” s ays A b e c i a .“Some have made money
here but then they left to live elsewhere.T h e
old houses are falling into ruins, and their
furniture and fittings have been removed.
The few things that have been preserved are
in the Casa de la Moneda (the Roya l
M i n t ) .”Abecia is the curator of the museum
funded by Bolivia’s Central Bank which is
housed in this historic building.
In 1572, in colonial times, S p a n i s h
V i c e r oy Francisco de Toledo created a system
of forced labour called “la mita”. E ve ry seve n
ye a rs , for a period of four months, all males
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
P O V ERTY ON A SILV ER THRONE
M ining has always been Potosi’s lifeblood.
Modern prospecting technology has disco-
vered that the mountain still contains at least as
much silver as the Spaniards extracted from it. The
Bolivian government has invited foreign firms to
bid for the contract to mine it.
In recent months, argument has focused on
what form the new mining operations should take.
Should the top of the mountain be cut off—this
would be the cheapest method but it would disfi-
gure the mountain—or should a horizontal tunnel
be bored through to the heart of the ore-bearing
r o c k s ?
Geologist Jaime Villalobos, a former Bolivian
minister of mines, says “most of the ore is concen-
trated inside the peak. El Cerro’s rock has lots of
m i n e ral seams of different sizes suitable for
modern methods of extraction. It’s economica l l y
feasible to remove all the rock, crush it and process
it. The cheapest way to extract it would be the
open-cast method.”
This means cutting into the top of a mountain
that is a national emblem. The people of Potosi are
against that: 97 per cent of them said in a poll they
would rather starve than see the silhouette of El
Cerro disappear and, with it, the World Heritage title.
They would prefer to see a horizontal shaft
bored, as UNES CO has advised. However, this
option is more expensive. It means digging the shaft
and extracting the ore while preserving the shape of
the mountain. When he was minister, Villalobos says
his investigations showed the Cerro contained
“more than half a million tons of silver-bearing ore.
But that doesn’t mean it’s economica l l y feasible to
e x t ract because a lot of it is low - g rade ore.” The
company that wins the contract to mine the moun-
tain will have to study this.
People in Potosi show discontent when they talk
about mining. Villalobos understands. Mining, he
says, “whether in colonial times, or whether by the
private sector or by the state-owned Bolivian Mining
C o r p o ration, has taken non-renewable resources
from the area and left behind only contamination
and poverty. This project should have a built-in gua-
rantee to create wealth for Potosi,” he says. ■
LA PAZ
La Paz
POTOSÍ
Potosi
Oruro
Beni
Cochabamba Santa Cruz
Tarija
Argentina
Paraguay
Brazil
Chile
Peru
Chuquisaca
A worker sorts out different metals from ores taken from the mine.
b e t ween 18 and 50 were ordered to work in
the mines. They were paid a pittance and
rarely saw the light of day.Eighty per cent of
the male population of the 16 provinces of
the viceroyalty of Pe ru died in these condi-
t i o n s.“ E ve ry peso coin minted in Potosi has
cost the life of 10 Indians who have died in
the depths of the mines,”wrote Fray A n t o n i o
de la Calancha in 1638.
Mining methods have changed little ove r
the ye a rs.The miners still toil from dawn till
d u s k .G e n e r at o rs pump air into the tunnels
so they can breat h e .Children still wriggle into
t i ny places where adults cannot go.Wo r k i n g
sometimes for 10 hours or more a day in
extreme temperat u r e s , the miners keep going
by chewing coca leave s. Two-thirds of the
p o p u l ation have respirat o ry ailments.
“Barely 20 per cent of the mine-wo r k e rs
are actually members of the co-operat i ve s ,”
says Joaquino. “The other 80 per cent are
casual labourers who earn next to nothing.
They are peasant migrants from the nort h ,
the poorest part of the department of which
Potosi is the capital.”
The historic centre of Po t o s i , w h e r e
the Spanish settlers once live d , is today
home to a small middle class. It is ringed by
a pove rty belt inhabited by miners who
work in the co-operat i ve s. Both these areas
are surrounded by a wider pove rty belt
filled with those who have fled the hunger
of the countryside to hire themselves out as
unskilled labourers in the mines.
Peasant women from the north come to
the city to beg. They sleep on the gr o u n d
in the markets, numb with cold, cradling in
their arms the babies they have brought
with them. B e rnardina Soles has had 10
c h i l d r e n . F i ve of them have died—a gri m
reminder of an infant mortality rate of 135
per 1,000. Her dream is to take some of her
children away from her home village, w h e r e
they could only have two ye a rs of pri m a ry
s c h o o l i n g .The illiteracy rate in the depart-
ment of Potosi is 30.8 per cent.
Lost splendour
“ Potosi society is rotten with ostentat i o n
and extrava g a n c e ,” s ays Uru g u ayan wri t e r
Eduardo Galeano, “ but the memory of its
past splendours still lingers and it still has
the ruins of its churches and palaces.”UN E S C O
is backing restoration projects for about 2,000
colonial buildings and is monitoring the
c o n s e rvation of the Cerro Rico, where the
mining installations dating from colonial
times are historic monuments.They include
t u n n e l s , e q u i p m e n t , m i l l s , f u rnaces and a
n e t work of 22 art i ficial pools built by V i c e r oy
Toledo to help power the equipment.
“I remember that when I was a boy the
Cerro was a perfect cone, a beautiful red
mountain just south of the city,” s ays A b e c i a .
“But over the past 50 ye a rs , it has aged, b e e n
hacked about and fallen apart .The co-ope-
r at i ves have extracted so much rock from it
that it doesn’t look the same any more.”
UN E S C O’s main goal is to convince the Boli-
vian authorities to take steps to preserve as
World Heritage a site which Spanish chro-
n i c l e rs regarded as a “perfect and endu-
ring wonder of the world”. ■
Bolivia
Area: 1,098,581 sq km
Population: 7,773,000
Capital: Sucre (official) and 
La Paz (seat of the government)
GDP per capita: $1,003
Source:Anuario Iberoamericano 1999,Agencia Efe
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Miners manhandle a wagonload of ore from the mouth of the mine to the crushing machine.
A “palliri”, a miner’s widow, searches the surface of the mountain near the San German mine shaft for stones containing silver, tin or zinc. 
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Children of “palliris” (miners’ widows) at school. As well as doing schoolwork, the children shoulder many responsibilities at home. Sometimes they work 
to help support their families.
A family of miners in their one-room home in Potosi’s Calvario neighbourhood.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
The miners’ carnival is a time of religious fervour and heavy drinking.
A Quechua Indian family on the Cerro Rico mountain peak. During colonial times the Quechua and Aymara inhabitants of the viceroyalty of Peru’s 16 provinces were 
a reservoir of forced labour for the Potosi mines.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A miner doffs his hat to salute the passing of St Bartholomew during a pilgrimage near Potosi. The miners honour their favourite saints over several days of Christian
and pagan celebrations.
A drunk miner chews coca leaves during a festival in honour of Tio, the devil of the mines. The miners sacrifice a llama to Tio three times a year in the hope 
that he will spare their lives.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 9
P L A N E T
ENERGY’S WIND 
OF CH A NGE
◗ Birger T. Madsen
Wind energy is rapidly developing as an environmentally sound and cost-effective option 
for power generation. Here, one of its champions describes an industry with wind in its sales
■
It takes a stiff upper lip not to smile
when Don Quixote almost falls off
his horse in fright after mistaking a
windmill for a giant.But perhaps the unli-
kely hero of Cervantes’literary masterpie-
ce can be credited with foresight. Today’s
windmills, dubbed wind turbines, dwarf
their predecessors, as their steely arms
slice through the air at heights of up to
100 metres. More and more of these
giants sprout on land and at sea, and they
are gaining new ground in the marketpla-
ce. And while at present wind power pro-
vides just 0.15 per cent of the world’s
total electricity, it has become the fastest
growing form of energy production.
The basic principles of wind energy
have been known for many centuries.The
earliest references to windmills date back to
7thcentury Persia, but for many the image
most closely associated with wind power is
t h at which gave Don Quixote such a fri g h t :
a picturesque timber tower supporting four
long cloth-covered sails rotating in the
w i n d . To d ay ’s wind turbine consists of a
giant propeller fixed on top of a tall metal
p o l e .When it rotat e s , the propeller dri ves a
g e n e r ator which churns out electricity that
can either supply nearby users,possibly in
an isolated rural community, or alternati-
vely be sent down a cable hooked up to a
central energy gri d . One problem is that no
way has yet been found of storing electri c i t y
to enable the wind’s “ups and dow n s ” t o
be evened out.The trend is for wind farms
to move offshore, where their appearance
and the sound of whirring propellers wo n ’t
bother local communities, and strong and
steady sea winds will keep the turbines tur-
ning at full force.
For the past 25 ye a rs , m a n u fa c t u r e rs
h ave been streamlining components and
installing on-board computers to tilt the
propeller blades, for example, to suit part i-
cular wind conditions. In the early 1980s,
◗ Managing Director of BTM Consult Aps (Denmark), 
a leading consultancy group specializing in wind power
the average turbine was 20 metres high with
a 26-kilowatt (kW) generator and a rotor
diameter of 10.5 metres. A typical turbine
t o d ay may be perched 55 metres high, h ave
r o t o rs with a diameter of around 50-60
metres and a capacity of up to 1,650 kW.
The amount of energy it can produce is
equivalent to that consumed by about 350
European households.
Since 1992, more commercial wind
fa rms have been installed in more coun-
t ries than ever before. There are now
40,000 turbines in 40 countri e s , and the
world’s wind energy capacity is growing at
nearly 27 per cent annually. In 1998, it top-
ped 10,000 megawatts (MW), about the
total energy producing capacity of a coun-
t ry like Denmark.The 1999 figures are not
all in, but we know that 1998 was a boom
year for the wind power industry. E q u i p-
ment sales topped $2 billion and there we r e
35,000 jobs in the sector wo r l d w i d e .
G r owth is expected to continue at about
25 per cent a year.
The prime motors of expansion are
increasing environmental awareness and
political commitments to reduce gr e e n-
house gas emissions made under the Kyo t o
Protocol of 1997.Wind is free and supplies
of it are inexhaustible, and when it pro-
duces energy it doesn’t release heat or
greenhouse gases.
The European Union has taken the
lead in rolling out the “green carpet” by
introducing tax breaks and investment
plans aimed at developing renewa b l e
energy sources such as wind power.There
are plans to install 40,000 megawatts by
the year 2010. Denmark, the wind energy
pioneer, covers 10 per cent of its electrici-
ty consumption from wind power, delive-
red from an installed capacity of some
1,700 MW. Germany is quickly catching
up, and is now the wind sector’s fastest
gr owing market (see article page 1 1 ) .
Spain, with its ample grazing lands and
steady winds, is also soon likely to be
attracting investment.
Rolling out a green carpet
The climate in the U.S. has been more
vo l at i l e . E ve ry two ye a rs , a congr e s s i o n a l
b attle erupts around the renewal of an
important tax credit to spur the industry.
The same tumult rattles state legislatures
that have their own credit schemes.Accor-
ding to U.S.energy secretary Bill Richard-
s o n , wind power should provide five per
cent of the nation’s electricity demands by
the year 2020, compared to the current 0.1
per cent.
For the up and coming energy gi a n t s ,
notably India and China, interest in wind
p ower has less to do with env i r o n m e n t a l
awareness than with economics. T h e s e
countries where broad swathes of the rural
population are without electricity are keen
to take advantage of wind investment plans
offered by Denmark, G e rm a ny and the
N e t h e r l a n d s.With nearly 850 MW installed
c a p a c i t y, India ranks first among deve l o-
ping countries and fourth in the world after
Germany in the wind power league table.
About 600 turbines are churning out 260
MW in China.
Asia and the Pa c i fic used to be conside-
red the coming hot spot for wind powe r.
The prime motors 
of expansion are increasing
e n v i r o n m e n tal awareness 
and political commitments 
to reduce greenhouse gas
emissions made under 
the Kyoto Protocol of 19 97.
Wind is free and supplies 
of it are inexhaustible, 
and when it produces energy 
it doesn’t release heat 
or greenhouse gases.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
P L A N E T
On a wind farm near Muppandal, Tamil Nadu (India) women dry their saris in the breeze.
H owe ve r , the regi o n ’s financial crisis of
1998 knocked many energy inve s t m e n t
plans off cours e , with the notable excep-
tion of New Zealand’s Ta r a rua W i n d
Farm—the largest in the southern hemis-
phere with a capacity of 12 MW.
Turbines are few and far between in
South America, aside from a few installa-
tions in Costa Rica,Argentina and Brazil.
Danish manufa c t u r e rs are making some
inroads into North A f ri c a : M o r o c c o
recently installed 50 MW and Egypt 30
M W.The rest of the continent is in the dol-
d ru m s , an unfort u n ate state of affa i rs gi ve n
the tremendous need for renewable energy,
especially in rural areas.
While the wo r l d ’s richest wind resources
are found in North A m e ri c a , China and the
former Soviet states, particularly those in
Central A s i a , we believe that wind powe r
could provide at least 20 per cent of every
continent’s energy needs.There is enough
wind to provide twice the expected global
e l e c t ricity demand for 2020. E ven if only 10
per cent of energy needs were met by wind
p owe r , the world would be spared about 10
billion tons of carbon emissions (out of a
total of 60-70 billion tons).To achieve this
goal, 120 times more wind capacity would
h ave to be installed than there is today.T h e
initial investment required would be ve ry
h i g h , but operation and maintenance costs
would be marginal.
M a n u fa c t u r e rs today are building bigger
and better turbines, and as a result wind-
p ower prices have been falling at about 20
per cent over the past four ye a rs. In Den-
m a r k , for example, e l e c t ricity generated by
wind power cost almost 17 cents per kilo-
watt hour (kWh) in the early 1980s. T h e
fig u r e , which cove rs all costs (equipment,
l a b o u r , interest on loans, o p e r ation and
maintenance) fell to 6.15 cents by 1995 and
has since dropped to about 4.6 cents.
M e a n w h i l e ,e l e c t ricity produced by the ins-
t a l l ation of a new coal-fired power plant
would cost 5 to 6.4 cents kWh, 4 and 5.7
cents kWh in the case of a gas-fired plant,
and 4.6 to 6.5 cents kWh in a nuclear fa c i l i t y,
according to calculations by UNIPEDE, the 
European Utility A s s o c i at i o n .
But while the cost of wind-powered elec-
t ricity will continue to fall in the future,
c o m p e t i t i ve prices are not enough—there
must be a political will to develop the 
market.Developing countries often find it
d i f ficult to raise the capital to cover the steep
s t a rt-up costs of installing wind turbines.
This is the downside of wind powe r.T h e
initial costs of installing coal-fired plants,
for example, are relat i vely cheap but fuel
then has to be imported and in the long ru n
this carbon-based energy will cost more
than wind energy. If these countries are to
d e velop an environmentally sound energy
sector using wind powe r , they will need help
in finding the initial investment.
The situation is radically different in
N o rth A m e rica and We s t e rn Europe, b o t h
of which have enough installed energy capa-
city to meet demand. In these countries the
market for wind energy is dri ven by env i-
ronmental  considerations rather than eco-
n o m i c s. If gove rnments do not adopt “ gr e e n
p o l i c i e s ”r e q u i ring utility companies to close
d own classical power plants and switch ove r
to renewable energy sources, the market for
wind power will not be very dynamic.
Green parties are stepping up the
pressure on gove rnments to promote
clean energies by helping to fund R&D
c o s t s , for example. Other measures that
could be taken include subsidizing
e l e c t ricity payments or offering tax
credits and low-interest loans for
m a n u fa c t u r e rs. The “polluter pay s ”
p rinciple might also be applied, with a
special tax being levied on carbon-
emitting energy producers , as opposed
to a clean energy source such as wind.
A ‘doped’ market
Some argue that a truly promising
energy source should not require gove rn-
ment support . O t h e rs maintain that sub-
sidies will do more harm than good by
d i s t o rting the energy market and art i fi-
cially boosting what remains an unpro-
mising altern at i ve . I would argue the
c o n t r a ry — t h at gas, c o a l , oil and nuclear
energy have been “ d o p e d ” on state subsi-
dies from the start .
M a ny power companies using these fuels
There is enough wind 
to provide twice the expected
global electricity demand 
for 20 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
◗ Berlin-based journalist
GERM A N Y :
T ILT ING 
AT WINDMIL L S
◗ Hartmut Wewetzer
Germany is the world’s top producer of energy
from wind power. But whether more wind farms 
should be built is sparking fierce debate
■
The north German plain is looking
different these day s. Where once
fie l d s , m e a d ows and forests stret-
ched as far as the eye could see, t o d ay the
landscape is dotted with spectacular
w i n d m i l l s , some of which tower 100
metres or more above the gr o u n d .
The further north you go, the more
there are. In East Friesland (Lowe r
S a x o ny) and on the west coast of
S c h l e swig-Holstein (where windmills
c r owd the horizon) thousands of small
businesspeople (Germ a ny ’s associat i o n
of wind energy producers has more than
6,000 members) have built huge wind
fa rms to produce electricity for the nat i o-
nal gri d .
Since 1997, G e rm a ny has ove rt a k e n
the United States as the wo r l d ’s leading
producer of wind energy. It accounted for
700 of the 2,035 megawatts (MW) of
new wind energy capacity installed
worldwide in 1998 (the equivalent of the
output of two large nuclear powe r
p l a n t s ) . Each ye a r , new records are set. I n
the first quarter of 1999 alone, 228 new
wind turbines were hooked up to the
n ational gri d . The number of turbines in
G e rm a ny rose from about 6,200 in
Ja n u a ry 1999 to 7,200 by the end of that
year (3,750 MW).
But so far these devices produce only
1.3 per cent of Germ a ny ’s electri c i t y.T h e
rest comes largely from fossil fuels (58
per cent), nuclear plants (36 per cent)
and hy d r o p ower (5 per cent). The wind
energy association predicts that by 2020
about 25,000 wind turbines will be ins-
t a l l e d , producing 30 per cent of the coun-
t ry ’s electri c i t y. G ove rnment sources say
t h at some 30 billion Deutschmarks ($1.8
billion) will be spent on strengthening
the sector.
Wind powe r ’s success in Germ a ny is
p a rtly based on public and media appro-
va l . G e rm a ny is the only We s t e rn country
where nuclear power has, since the
1 9 7 0 s , met almost unanimous and often
violent opposition. The anti-nuclear
m ovement led to the birth of the Green
p a rt y, which has been in gove rn m e n t
with the Social Democrats since the end
of 1998. This coalition wants a rapid
s h u t - d own of nuclear power stat i o n s ,
although it has not yet reached an agr e e-
ment with the energy distri bu t o rs. If they
fail to agr e e , a law may be passed to res-
t rict the life of nuclear plants to 30 ye a rs ,
forcing the industry to close them one by
o n e .
Global warming is another argument
in favour of using wind power, a non-pol-
luting energy source. Germany has pled-
ged to reduce its greenhouse gas emis-
sions by 21 per cent between 1990 and
2010.The public largely sees this as evi-
dence of an “ecological revolution” and a
new civilization where humans are at
peace with nature.
Subsidized wind farming
The only problem—a big one—is that
wind energy is very expensive. Extracting
one kilowatt/hour of energy from the
wind costs four times as much as using
fossil fuels. So the political decision to
develop renewable energy, taken by the
previous government and reaffirmed by
the present one,can only be applied if aid
is available in the form of tax breaks for
firms producing wind energy, low-interest
bank loans, subsidies from the state and
from provincial governments and favou-
rable legislation.
began as state monopolies protected by
n ational legi s l at i o n .They control the powe r
gri d s. Often they bar new energy producers
from the grids or impose rules which oblige
n e w c o m e rs to sell their energy at unfa i r
p ri c e s.The development of wind power has
also been hurt by the absence of legi s l at i o n .
For example, the UK has the best wind
resources in Europe, but commercial
attempts to set up wind fa rms in the last
three ye a rs were stymied when local autho-
rities failed to issue permits for turbine
c o n s t ru c t i o n . Had the national gove rn m e n t
set up guidelines and policies inciting local
a u t h o rities to co-operat e , there might be
more wind fa rms in Britain today.
The two notable champions of wind
p ower are Denmark and Germ a ny. Fe r o-
ciously anti-nuclear, the public in both
these countries studied their energy options
before giving wind a “ green light”. T h e i r
diligence is now paying off at home and
a b r o a d , as their turbines blow a fresh breeze
into global energy production. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
P L A N E T
The 1991 “ i n t e gr ation law ” , which is
the key to the present system, obliges the
e l e c t ricity distri bu t o rs to buy wind energy
at guaranteed prices (90 per cent of the
p rice paid by consumers ) , and this enables
the wind fa rm e rs to make a profit .
But the growth of wind energy seems
to be threatened by the opening up of the
energy market, which started in April
1998 and has sharpened competition and
reduced the price of electricity paid by
consumers.This trend worries wind ener-
gy firms because they sell their product at
prices which are specifically tied to consu-
mer prices. With their profitability in jeo-
pardy, they want more subsidies to pro-
tect themselves against the ups and downs
of the market.
Meanwhile, opposition to wind power
is growing. A few years ago, it chiefly
came from the electricity distributors,
who campaigned to have the 1991 law
declared unconstitutional.They failed but
managed to get it amended to limit their
obligation to buy wind energy, which now
comprises a maximum 5 per cent of the
electricity they purchase. But in some
parts of northern Germany, this quota is
not enough to absorb the output of wind
energy, and producers are looking for
other outlets. A proposed new law would
be even more advantageous to renewable
energy than its predecessor in that it
would abolish the 5 per cent rule.
The fiercest opponent of wind energy,
Prof. Otfried Wolfrum, from Darmstadt,
thinks that to continue backing wind
energy is “a disastrous stupidity for the
environment, for human beings and the
economy”. The current policy, he says,
will in the coming years produce a loss of
about 30 billion Deutschmarks (around
$15 billion),which consumers will pay for
in the form of electricity costing more
than it would if the distributors were not
forced to buy wind energy. He says wind
fa rms are simply “a licence to pri n t
money”.
He and other economists argue that
subsidized wind energy may be creating
jobs now but will end up cutting down on
t h e m . ( U n e m p l oyment in Germ a ny is
over 10 per cent.) If energy prices are not
competitive in Germany, they say, some
electricity firms will move their plants to
c o u n t ries where conditions are more
favourable. On top of this, these “appal-
ling machines” are a blot on the landsca-
pe in important tourist areas. Wolfrum,
the founder of Germ a ny ’s League to
Protect the Countryside, has made him-
self spokesman for a citizens’ movement
that is growing fastest in areas where wind
turbines are most common.
Wind energy has become the centre of
a major battle in Germany. Wolfrum’s
strong at t a c k s , contained in his book
“Wind Energy, a False Alternative”, have
provoked an equally strong riposte. An
influential member of the lower house of
the German parliament, H e rm a n n
Scheer, a wind energy lobbyist who recei-
ved the 1999 Right Livelihood Award,
also known as the A l t e rn at i ve Nobel
Prize, recently even accused Wolfrum of
using “fascist” arguments, which gives a
good idea of how heated the debate has
become. Scheer, working with journalists
and environmental campaigners , h a s
published a reply to his opponent’s book
called Windy Protest.
Despite these polemics, the rapid
d e velopment of wind energy seems set to
c o n t i n u e . In case public anxiety about
h a rm to the countryside increases, w i n d
energy entrepreneurs are planning to
build wind fa rms out at sea.The biggest is
s l ated for a spot 35 km east of the Baltic
island of Rügen and will comprise 200
turbines capable of generating 1,000
m e g awat t s.This is roughly the output of a
big nuclear power plant, s ays a spokesman
for W i n k r a - E n e r g y, the company concer-
n e d , “and from the shore, you wo n ’t be
able to see a single windmill.” ■
Wind power supplies these pyramid-shaped houses designed by architect Gerard Schouten at Huizen (The
Netherlands).
The fiercest opponent of 
wind energy, Prof. Otfried
Wolfrum, and other
economists argue that
subsidized wind energy may
be creating jobs now but 
will end up cutting down on
them. If energy prices are not
competitive in Germany, 
they say, some electricity
firms will move their plants
to countries where conditions
are more favourable.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 13
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
■
The teacher asks her pupils to listen
to the tape of a radio news item in
which a gove rnment official say s
i m m i grants are to blame for other people
being out of wo r k .The statement makes a
strong impact. The children, fifth gr a d e
pupils at a school in the Parque Ave l l a n e d a
d i s t rict of Buenos A i r e s , fall silent. T h e n
A m p a r o, a 10-year-old Bolivian gi r l , s p e a k s
u p. “When I was in hospital,” she say s ,
“they didn’t want me to stay.They shouted
at my mother and said: ‘go back to yo u r
c o u n t ry.’They didn’t gi ve my father a job
because he’s Bolivian.”
The news story, and Amparo’s reac-
tion to it, gave the children the idea of
choosing “Immigrants at School” as a
topic for their radio broadcasting work-
shop.
“We chose the subject because most
of the children here are Bolivian,” says the
QUIET PL E ASE! 
CHIL DREN TA L K ING
◗ Silvia Bacher and Monica Beltran
Armed with microphones, tape recorders and cameras, the schoolchildren of Buenos Aires 
are learning to express their opinions and look at the news with a critical eye
school librarian, Fany Opino. “The first
thing we do is collect information. Then
we rehearse the programme before it goes
on the air. But the most important thing
is that the children not only think about a
situation they come up against every day,
but that they feel they’re being listened
to.”
The radio workshop is part of a Media
Production in Schools scheme started up
10 years ago by the Journalism, Commu-
n i c ations and Education Committee of the
city of Buenos Aires.The scheme is known
as the child journalist project but its aim is
not so much to train young reporters as to
increase the children’s capacity to express
their opinions and to use the media to help
them to think for themselves.
For the “Immigrants at School” work-
shop, the children were asked to go out
and interview immigrants, in some cases
their own relatives. They wrote up their
reports, read them out in class and dis-
cussed them.Then they collected material
about racial discrimination from books
and magazines. Finally, they worked out a
structure, chose some music and put their
radio programme together.
In the child journalist scheme, the
process whereby children investigate, dis-
cuss, defend their opinions and listen to
others, is more important than the end
product, whether it be a newspaper, a
video or a radio programme. In other
words, the school is given the key task of
training citizens who can think critically
about the world they live in. “The work-
shop on immigrants helped me to unders-
tand why people sometimes shout at me
in the street,” says Maria Esperanza, ano-
ther Bolivian pupil.
According to the teacher, making the
radio programme enabled the children to
know what it feels like to be rejected
because of skin colour or place of origin.
It also taught them to look at radio and
television news with a critical eye and,
through their own communication media,
◗ Respectively communication and education specialist
and Buenos Aires-based journalist
“Keep the presses rolling!” Media workshops in Buenos Aires schools have mobilized tremendous enthusiasm.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
to protest against the plight of those who
feel victimized.
Producing radio programmes and
magazines is a well-established activity in
many countries’ education systems. The
Argentine programme has some unique
features, however, because of the political
and social context in which it developed
in the late 1980s. The long years of mili-
tary dictatorship and censorship had ins-
tilled a culture of silence into Argentine
society. Within communities, the lines of
communication were broken or frayed.
The media production project seemed to
be a good option for strengthening demo-
cratic practices via the school and for
repairing the social fabric by building
bridges between the school and the com-
munity and teaching children to interpret
c ritically messages transmitted by the
media.
Breaking the culture 
of silence
This objective may well be the key fac-
tor in the success of a programme which
has managed to survive both lack of fun-
ding and political vicissitudes. In 10
years, the number of schools involved has
grown from 34 to more than 200, most of
them in poor neighbourhoods of Buenos
Aires. About 50,000 children, mostly of
primary school age but also some older
children and some in special schools, have
worked as reporters, editors, announcers,
picture or film editors, researching, plan-
ning and producing more than 600 school
m a g a z i n e s , 700 hours of radio pro-
grammes broadcast by local radio stations
and about 100 videos.
The fact that the topics covered by the
to see some ballet and, helped by craft
and science teachers , made the 
puppets and wrote the script,” says the
school’s music teacher, Lucia Salgado.
One of the biggest and most pers i s-
tent obstacles to changing the old educa-
tion model is the lack of properly trained
t e a c h e rs , and so theoretical and practical
teacher training has been made a key ele-
ment in the child journalist scheme.
Once a week over two months, groups of
interested teachers get together to produ-
ce and discuss media mat e rial with the
help of a colleague who has classroom
e x p e rience of the scheme. With UN E S C O
s u p p o rt , the programme has since 1994
built up a network of 350 teachers with
special skills.
New horizons for teachers
Participants say the media workshops
help them to recover their appetite for
enquiry and learning in a school context
which is by and large unexciting. For the
children, they mean greater freedom and
more contact with real life. “The work-
shops allow us to interview people and go
out into town, while in the classroom we
read and study to pass exams,” says one
young reporter. They open new horizons
for teachers like Monica, who described
how she learned to have more respect for
the children’s experience and realized that
she had no monopoly on wisdom. “The
workshop enables us to break free from
stereotypes and find out things for our-
selves,” she says.
Teachers taking part in the experi-
ment agree that producing radio pro-
grammes and newspapers is a good way
of fostering children’s verbal and writing
skills since it doesn’t involve reciting a les-
son from memory but getting across per-
sonal ideas and opinions clearly and effec-
tively so that readers and listeners outside
the classroom can grasp them.The school
newspapers the children produce, either
in the form of a single sheet or a magazi-
ne, are distributed in the school and the
neighbourhood.The videos they make are
workshops are suggested by the children
themselves and reflect their interests and
needs is in itself a small revolution.Titles
such as “From junior to senior”,
“Generation 2000” and “From caning to
caring” give an idea of the subjects that
most interested these budding journalists:
relations with adults, human rights, vio-
lence, ecology and discrimination.
Some topics are directly related to the
school curriculum (the role of women in
history, mathematics, climate change and
health care); others focus on community
problems and lead to specific action.
Children who took part in one journa-
lism workshop, for example, were worried
about the disappearance of trees near
their school, so they carried out a “tree
c e n s u s ” in the neighbourhood. T h e y
interviewed the oldest residents, talked
with experts and officials, and expressed
their concern in a video made for the
community. Then they launched a cam-
paign to replant the area with trees.
Other children made a video about
the rights of children “so that adults know
more about us and don’t mistreat us.”
This led them to take an interest in the
lives of street children, some of whom
they interviewed to find out how they
managed to survive.
Workshop activities can also be purely
creative and artistic. The presence of a
Ukrainian child among sixth-graders at a
school in the Caballito district gave the
children the idea of collecting informa-
tion about Slavonic history and culture.
Next, they decided to create a puppet
s h ow based on Strav i n s k y ’s ballet
Petrushka and to video it. “They resear-
ched the composer’s life and work, went
Budding journalists choose photos for their school newspaper and learn about page layout.
+ …
● Producción de medios en la escuela.
Reflexiones desde la práctica .
Coordinación de Periodismo, Comunica c i ó n
y Educación, Secretaría de Educa c i ó n ,
Gobierno de la Ciudad de Buenos Aires,
19 9 8 .
● Internet:
http://www.buenosaires.gov.ar/educacion/
chicosperiodistas
● sbacher@rocketmail.com
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
AN IN T ERN AT IONAL NETW ORK
Argentina’s budding journalists have colleagues
in other countries including France, Chile,
South Korea, Switzerland and Benin. Wo r k i n g
together, these young reporters put out a weekly
magazine for children called F a x !, which was laun-
ched in France in 1989 by the Centre for Liaison
b e tween Teaching and Information Media (CL EMI) .
Each issue is put together by a group of children
from a single school who organize an editorial
team, draw up a table of contents around a genera l
theme and commission articles from young cor-
respondents in different countries. The contributions
are sent in by fax.
The editors responsible for the issue take charge
of the magazine’s design and its distribution by
f ax to the participating schools, which use it in lan-
guage lessons. Each number of F a x ! is produced in
two languages, though not always the same ones.
Judging by the headlines and contents, some of
the topics chosen by the young journalists would be
the envy of quite a few of their adult colleagues. Fo r
example, schoolchildren in the Romanian town of
Timisoara produced in 1999 an issue called “Dif -
ferent but not indifferent.” Children in Guadeloupe,
aware of the need to teach by example, printed their
issue, titled “The environment: we’re all respon-
sible”, on recycled paper.
F a x ! , which is now up to its 170th issue, is
aimed at children between 11 and 18. It also pro-
duces an edition called Fax Junior! for 6-to-11 -
year-olds who are taking their first steps in written
journalism. ■
Centre de Liaison de l’enseignement 
et des moyens d’information 
(Centre for Liaison between Teaching and
Information Media [Clemi]),
391 bis rue de Vaugirard, 75015 Paris, 
France.
usually shown at school festivals and
other special events that parents and
neighbours can attend. Since 1994, radio
programmes have been broadcast weekly
on FM community stations as part of a
series called “Kaleidoscope: Children’s
Voices.”
Learning to decode 
media messages
The purpose of the Buenos A i r e s
scheme is not to set schools against the
media but to channel the natural enthu-
siasm of children and teenagers. Latin
American children spend an average of
four hours a day watching TV or listening
to music on the radio. A r g e n t i n a ’s
Educational Television Foundation disco-
vered that out of 10.5 million households,
9.5 million have a television set and more
than half of them are signed up with some
kind of pay-TV, making Argentina num-
ber three in the world in terms of cable
TV subscribers.
By the time children get to the age of
16, they’re spending about 46,000 hours
a year sleeping, 22,000 watching TV and
13,000 at school. “Television became the
main cultural activity of the 20th centu-
ry,” says Sara Critto, the head of the
Fo u n d at i o n . “But schools don’t take
account of this and children aren’t pro-
perly prepared for it.”
The most influential media in Latin
American countries—radio, TV and the
written press—are often controlled by
small but powerful groups which usually
obey economic interests and pay little
regard to the citizen’s right to informa-
t i o n . W h at ’s more, the social context
leaves little time for the clash of ideas and
p r ovides meagre access to sources of
information outside television and radio.
This sometimes produces audiences
addicted to certain editorial approaches
which sacrifice accuracy to newsiness.
But using the latest computer or a fil m
camera doesn’t necessarily sharpen the cri-
tical fa c u l t i e s.Technology cannot replace the
t e a c h e r , whose role should be to help chil-
dren analyse the news. By producing infor-
m at i ve mat e ri a l , children learn how to accept
the existence of conflicting viewpoints, d i s-
tinguish opinion from facts and objectivity
from sensat i o n a l i s m , and find out how to
attract a reader’s or listener’s at t e n t i o n .
All these experiences help children
u n d e rstand the nuts and bolts of
c o m m u n i c ation from the inside. T h e y
soon realize that a news story is not the
same thing as “the fa c t s ” but a
c o m p i l ation that is rarely 100 per cent
o b j e c t i ve because it depends on who is
doing the report i n g . The A m e ri c a n
e s s ayist Alvin Toffler has said that to
p r e vent children becoming passive
r e c e i ve rs and to teach them how to
decode media messages, “the best thing is
to gi ve them video cameras and send
them out to film something by themselve s.
They will soon learn to interpret the
media in a critical way. They’ll also fin d
out how easily images and ideas can be
m a n i p u l at e d , h ow to spot hidden
a d ve rtising in entertainment progr a m m e s ,
and see how politicians use demagogi c
pictures and opportunistic poses.”
Media programme production will not
become widespread in Latin A m e ri c a n
schools until political leaders are conv i n c e d
of the need for them and the reluctance of
the schools is ove r c o m e .The impact of the
media is so gr e at that schools cannot stand
by and do nothing.Whether teachers like it
or not, the media are in competition with
schools as agents of socializat i o n .
Teachers should realize that although
they have little money to buy new equip-
ment and although there are many obs-
tacles to tackling extracurricular subjects,
the media and new technology can be
their allies and schools are the most sui-
table place to teach children how to mas-
ter media skills, interpret media messages
and equip children to question them. ■
When they are given a video camera and sent out on an assignment, young people can find out for
themselves how journalism works.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Education is a right and one of the most decisive tools for escaping
poverty, but today there are still over one million children who do not
make it into school and close to 900 million illiterate adults. Why?
Education systems remain overly rigid and commitment by the state alone,
in particular a financial one, is inadequate to reach the excluded. Ten years
ago, the World Conference in Jomtien (Thailand) affirmed that education
could not reach everyone unless it became everybody’s business. It required
new partners and an expanded vision. Ten years later, how do things stand?
This section opens with five flagship projects illustrating the “Copernican
revolution” that UNESCO Director General Koïchiro Matsuura calls for. Uganda
has tripled enrolment in primary school by combining mobilization at the top
with delegation to the local level. In El Salvador, parents are co-running
schools in rural areas. A Bangladeshi NGO has managed to educate over one
million children, most of them girls. Ten million Indian volunteers are giving
a new impetus to literacy work.In Mongolia, radio programmes provide new
job skills to a dispersed population.“Give private initiative more responsibi-
lity, more space, more freedom,” says Sanjit Bunker Roy, father of the
Barefoot College in one of India’s poorest states. The advice merits our atten-
tion given the uneven record of the past decade. Literacy remains education’s
poor relation, as Mohamed Maamouri of the University of Pennsylvania
underlines. Without true reciprocity, partnerships remain a hollow concept,
both at the national level (Mark Bray, Hong Kong University) and between
Northern donors and developing countries (Kenneth King, E d i n b u r g h
University).And without bold initiatives, educa-
tion will continue to widen rather than reduce
the gap between rich and poor, c o n c l u d e s
H a r va r d ’s Fe r n a n do Reimers. ■
Education for all 
Schools reach out
Focus
C o n t e n t s
1 7 A Copernican re v o l u t i o n
Koïchiro Matsuura
1 8 A global campaign 
Cynthia Guttman 
1 9 I n d i a ’s Barefoot College genera t i o n
Neelesh Misra
2 0 Basic education: gaps on the map
1 | Five flagship pro j e c t s
2 2 U g a n d a ’s full school benches
Dan Elwa n a
2 4 B a n g l a d e s h : girls firs t
Shahnoor Wa h i d
2 6 El Salvador: power to the pare n t s !
Carlos Mario Marquez
2 7 M o n g o l i a : distance is no object
Michael Kohn with additional reporting 
by Altangerelyn Degelermaa
2 9 I n d i a : local hero e s
Meenakshi Shedde
2 | Uneven pro g re s s
3 1 World litera c y : what went wro n g ?
Mohamed Maamouri
3 2 Pa r t n e rships in pra c t i c e
Mark Bray
3 4 A i d : an unfair deal?
Kenneth King
3 5 Do schools foment inequality?
Interview with Fernando Reimers 
16 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 17
◗ D i r e c t o r-General of UN E S C O
Education for all: schools reach out
A Copernican
re v o l u t i o n
◗ Koïchiro M a t s u u r a
Ten ye a rs ago, the World Conference on
Education for All held in Jomtien (Thailand)
pledged to guarantee five years of primary
education for every child in the world and to
halve the adult illiteracy rate by the year 2000.
These were ambitious objectives.
The World Education Forum to be held at
Dakar in April will take stock of what has been
done to achieve these goals during the last 10
years. In absolute terms the number of children
not enrolled in primary schools and the number
of adult illiterates have slightly declined. Because
of demographic growth, the decline is more pro-
nounced expressed in relative terms.
But figures are only part of the balance-sheet.
The Jomtien Conference maintained that educa-
tion is not only a right but also the key to all deve-
l o p m e n t .This conviction is now unive rsally accep-
t e d , and so is the urgent need for schools to reach
o u t , especially to all those still excluded by tradi-
tional forms of educat i o n . New part n e rs (commu-
n i t i e s , N G O s , local civil and religious authori t i e s
and the pri vate sector) are proving to be inva-
l u a b l e . A b ove all, o b j e c t i ve analysis of the state of
basic education which emerges from the country
r e p o rts prepared for the Dakar Fo rum will allow a
ve ry precise diagnosis of the situation to be made
for the first time.
A radical change of course
Pa r a d ox i c a l l y, the failures that have been
recorded during this decade of action have taught
a key lesson:more of the same will not be enough;
different approaches will have to be adopted.
Unless there is a radical change of course, educa-
tion for all will remain a vain objective both in
quantitative and qualitative terms. Basic educa-
tion will only become accessible and relevant for
all if there is a “Copernican revolution”in schools
and schooling.
It is a truism that the capital on which every
society draws to shape its future consists of the
knowledge at its disposal and its capacity to
extend and transmit that knowledge. In the age of
the Internet and globalization, however, it is
important to emphasize the growing contradic-
tion between the new demands made by “know-
ledge societies” and the immobility of the major
systems whereby knowledge is acquired.
These systems are chiefly based on a single per-
iod of time (whereas education should be a lifelong
process) a fixed place (one to which many poten-
tial learn e rs lack access), a specific group of actors
(thereby neglecting the contri bution that other seg-
ments of society can make), u n i f o rm content (whe-
reas education should affirm cultural dive rs i t y ) ,
and a single source of funding (whereas public
spending on education is not keeping pace with the
inevitable increase in the cost of basic educat i o n
and lifelong education for all). These stru c t u r e s ,
p r o grammes and methods are increasingly being
ove rtaken by the radical developments that are
c h a n ging the face of all societies.
The contours of the revolution we shall be
required to carry out are starting to take shape.T h e
purpose of education can no longer be reduced to
the transmission of learning or the mastery of job-
related skills.We must not forget that “Education”
literally means “ d r awing out”, enabling learn e rs to
a c h i e ve their full potential. To lose sight of this
a p p r o a c h , to stress the “ a l l ” in “ e d u c ation for all” t o
the detriment of “ e d u c at i o n ” would lead to the
gr owth of a new kind of illiteracy and an increase in
the disparities and inequalities against which edu-
cation should be the most powerful weapon. ■
E d i t o r i a l
To lose sight of this appro a c h ,
to stress the “ a l l ” in “ e d u c a t i o n
for all” to the detriment 
of “ e d u c a t i o n ” would lead 
to the growth of a new kind 
of illiteracy and an increase 
in the disparities and inequalities
against which education should
be the most powerful weapon
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
Enough is enough. Around the wo r l d , NGOs are
on the campaign trail to pressure gove rn m e n t s
and donors into keeping the promises they
will make at an upcoming intern ational conference
on education in Dakar (Senegal)1.
Their concern :p r o gress since the World Confe-
rence on Education for all held at Jomtien (Thai-
land) in 1990, where gove rnments committed them-
s e l ves to an expanded vision of education and a set
of goals (see box), has fallen short of targets set.
“Whereas we emerged from the Cold War and the
risks of military conflict decreased compared to
the 70s and 80s, we did not use this margin of
manoeuvre as we could have. History gave us this
o p p o rtunity and we did not take it,” s ays Elie Jo u e n
of Education International, one of the world’s lar-
gest teachers’ organizations and a partner in the
campaign.
Spelling out 
solutions
“ We are wo rried that Dakar is going to turn
into another talking shop where eve ryone reaffirm s
things already agr e e d , sets new targets and then, a s
after Jomtien,goes home, cuts the aid budget and
a l l ows debt problems to continue underm i n i n g
education systems of Third World countries,” says
Kevin Watkins of Oxfam Intern at i o n a l , author of a
hard-hitting report on education and poverty (see
b ox p. 3 6 ) . “ For these conferences to wo r k , yo u
need to create a public perception that there is a
serious problem which people have to tackle.And
you have to come up with solutions.”
The campaign reflects not only the rising invo l-
vement of NGOs in educat i o n , but also their emer-
ging role as a watchdog with formidable advocacy
t o o l s.And they have realized that to be effective ,t h e y
have to act in numbers.The founders of the cam-
paign launched last October encompass a broad
range of interest groups: Education International,
the Global March against Child Labour, and deve-
lopment aid agencies ActionAid and Oxfa m . A t
the gr a s s r o o t s ,i n i t i at i ves from rallies to media cam-
paigns and consultations with ministry officials are
being conducted in over 60 countri e s. C o m m u-
nity organizations are working on national reviews
to ensure that the voices of civil society groups are
heard. More broadly, the campaigners are urging
g ove rnments to take a hard look at their educat i o n
strategies and spell out the steps required to meet
commitments.
At the international level, the campaign is lob-
bying for deeper and quicker debt reduction,r e f o rm
of structural adjustment policies and increased aid.
In some countries, it may be a question of reallo-
c ating resources. In others , especially in sub-Saharan
A f ri c a ,c o u n t ries cannot fill the resource gaps alone.
Best estimates suggest that it would cost about $8
billion extra a year to achieve unive rsal pri m a ry
e d u c at i o n , a sum equivalent to about four day s ’
global military spending.
While praising the advo c a cy powe rs of this coa-
l i t i o n ,m a ny caution against singling out the resource
issue.“In many countries,it’s just as much a ques-
tion of good governance and making better use of
existing resources,” says UNESCO’s Sven Osttveit.
Aïchah Bah Diallo, director of the division of basic
e d u c ation at UN E S C O, stresses that gove rn m e n t s
who have made a difference are those with an edu-
c ation policy “ t h at sells.”T h i s , she assert s , can only
come about through part n e rships not only with
other ministries but with the society at large,espe-
cially teacher trade unions and the media. Next,
“ you need transparency, and for this, a stop to cor-
ruption.”That being said,Osttveit regrets that the
Jomtien Declaration failed to specify global finan-
cial targets. Nor will Dakar. The danger is that
pledges without resources run a high risk of ri n gi n g
hollow. Hence the critical role of public opinion in
defending basic education as a right and a key to
escaping the trap of poverty. ■
A global c a m p a i g n
◗ Cynthia Guttman
Voices are rising up around the world to make governments keep their word on basic
education in the years ahead
1 .The World Education Fo ru m , to be held A p ril 26-28, 2 0 0 0 .
The 1990 Jomtien confere n c e
established six key goals:
● expansion of early childhood care and
development,especially for the poor
● universal access to and completion of primary
education by the year 2000
● improvement in learning achievement based on an
agreed-upon percentage of an age group attaining
a defined level (e.g.,80% of 14-year-olds)
● reduction of the adult illiteracy rate to half its
1990 level by 2000,with special emphasis on
female literacy
● expansion of basic education and training for
youth and adults
● improved dissemination of the knowledge, skills
and values required for better living and
sustainable development
Education is the most
powerful weapon
which you can use to
change the world.
Nelson Mandela, South African 
statesman (1918- )
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 19
Education for all: schools reach out
When Sanjit Bunker Roy came face to face
with a deva s t ating famine that killed thou-
sands in the Indian state of Bihar over 30
ye a rs ago, his vo c ation was suddenly sealed. I t
would not be in the city but in the countryside, it
would not be in the upper echelons of the civil ser-
vice but at the grassroots,with the village people.
Since founding the Social Work and Research
Centre in 1972, R oy has been living in T i l o n i a , a vil-
lage in one of India’s largest, d riest and poorest
s t at e s ,R a j a s t h a n . Better known as the Barefoot Col-
l e g e1, the centre has trained two generations of vil-
l a g e rs without any formal paper qualific ations to
become health-care wo r k e rs , solar engi n e e rs ,h a n d -
pump mechanics and teachers in their communities.
Thanks largely to its effort s , over 100,000
people in 110 villages now have access to safe dri n-
king wat e r , e d u c at i o n , health and employ m e n t .
Rural youth once regarded as “ u n e m p l oya b l e ”i n s-
tall and maintain solar electricity systems, h a n d
pumps and tanks for drinking wat e r. At special
wo r k s h o p s , young artisans upgrade local skills
acquired through generat i o n s. And on an ave r a g e
e ve n i n g, about 3,000 children (60 per cent of
whom are girls) who spend their days grazing cat t l e
and helping their elders make their way to night
school (there are now 150 of them around T i l o n i a ) ,
taught by local residents with rarely more than
eight ye a rs of schooling.
The project’s success is proof that sometimes an
o u t s i d e r ’s view can be a lasting catalyst for deve l o p-
m e n t . Since gr a d u ating from New Delhi’s St Ste-
p h e n ’s College,one of India’s most prestigious edu-
c ational institutions, R oy has devoted his life to T i l o n i a
and bettering the conditions of the rural poor. It wa s
a radical move : “If someone wants to do work in a
v i l l a g e , the formal education system discourages him,”
a s s e rts Roy.“The mindset that this system inculcat e s
in students is that going back to the villages is a losing
p r o p o s i t i o n . Remaining in the city is considered a
s u c c e s s.”
Roy looks upon the Barefoot College as a mul-
tiplier force that uses traditional knowledge as a tool
to reach the goals that conventional government
policies have often been unable to achieve.Twenty
Barefoot College field centres can now be found in
13 of India’s 26 states, and the expansion is set to
continue.“The idea is to use local wisdom before
we involve expertise from outside,” states Roy.
In T i l o n i a ,e d u c ation and development are inex-
t ricably linked.Youth are trained to use technologi e s
that serve their communities while children learn
about environmental themes such as solar electri-
city, which is used in most of their schools. “Night
school students learn from resource persons who are
not only their teachers , but also fa rm e rs ,p o l i c e m e n ,
or local officials,” explains Roy.
For Roy, taking some of the responsibility for
education out of the hands of government could
speed up progress towards universal primary edu-
c ation in his country.“Encourage pri vate initiat i ve
without commercializing educat i o n .G i ve pri vate ini-
t i at i ve more responsibility, more space, m o r e
freedom,” he says. As things stand now, the formal
system alone cannot answer the challenge of rural
education. “It destroys initiative and creativity. It
expects you to do everything the way they say, the
way they do,” he say s. The starting point is to
u n d e rstand the reality of the rural poor—“about 60
or 70 per cent of children never go to school in the
m o rning because they are supposed to work and rear
cattle”—and to channel these children into voca-
tional training at an early age so that they can gain
new skills while continuing to help their families.
If Roy feels that creativity is not always the
strength of gove rn m e n t , the Barefoot College is
breeding its own generation of committed and poli-
tically minded individuals:in Tilonia,it is the chil-
d r e n ’s parliament, an elected body of girls and boy s
between 10 and 14 years of age that is responsible
for making sure that schools are run properly—an
ingenious way of giving children a hold on their ow n
lives—and that of their villages. ■
I n d i a ’s Bare f o o t
College 
g e n e ra t i o n
◗ Neelesh Misra
Educator Sanjit Bunker Roy has found that tapping 
local wisdom and initiative can help villagers 
achieve empowerment 
◗ Journalist based in 
New Delhi (India)
Sanjit Bunker Roy
1 .The centre is funded by the gove rnment of Rajasthan 
(40 per cent), i n t e rn ational donors (40 per cent) and its ow n
activities (20 per cent).
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
Basic 
e d u c a t i o n : g a p s
on the map
An overview of world education trends highlights
glaring inequalities
Adecade after governments and the interna-
tional community pledged to ensure unive-
ral access to primary education by 2000
and to reduce the adult illiteracy rate to half its
1990 level, there are still around 130 million chil-
dren in the world who never attend school and an
estimated 872 million adults who do not have the
most basic skills to break their way out of pover-
ty.The education crisis is most flagrant in the two
regions with the lowest per capita incomes in the
world, South Asia ($385) and sub-Saharan A f ri c a
( $ 5 1 3 ) . In the lat t e r , sixteen countries have 
suffered a decline in enrolment rat e s.
To put the crisis in perspective, it should be
noted that in 1960,fewer than half the developing
world’s children aged 6 to 11 were enrolled in pri-
mary school, compared with 79 per cent today.
But these tremendous efforts were insufficient to
match population growth while the debt crisis of
the 1980s in many cases arrested progress. Over
the past decade, net enrolment ratios have been
inching up slowly (from 53 per cent to 56 per
cent in sub-Saharan Africa, from 65 to 72 per
cent in South Asia). Public expenditure on edu-
cation has crawled up from 5.1 to 5.6 per cent of
GDP in sub-Saharan Africa and from 3.9 to 
4.3 per cent in South Asia.
The gender
trap
Girls crowd the ranks of out-of-school children
d i s p r o p o rt i o n at e l y, representing nearly two of
e ve ry three children in the developing world who
do not receive a pri m a ry educat i o n , according to
U N I C E F. Half the girls in sub-Saharan A f ri c a
and South Asia never attend school, with the
highest disparity found in the latter region (15
p o i n t s ) .The Middle East and North A f rica have
much higher enrolment rat e s , but the gender gap
in pri m a ry education remains significant 
(8 points).
These inequalities at the primary level natu-
rally go on to swell illiteracy rates: in the same
three regions, over half the female population
over 15 years of age is illiterate, with South Asia
posting the highest rate and the most glaring 
Middle East and North Africa
Latin America and Caribbean
Industrialized countries
Sub-Saharan Africa
East Asia and Pacific
CEE/CIS and Baltic States
South Asia
13 13 15 12
%
100
50
0
gender gap (29 points). This situation has parti-
cularly critical implications for human develop-
ment given the beneficial impact of several years
of primary education on decreasing infant morta-
lity and reducing fertility rates.
But there are other inequalities aggravating
the situation. Although many countries in the
developing world are predominantly rural, educa-
tion is frequently skewed in favour of urban chil-
dren: Burkina Faso and Niger are extreme cases,
with primary school attendance over 40 per cent
lower in the countryside than in urban areas.
Another major cause for concern is not reflec-
ted on this map: the number of children who
actually finish the primary school cycle. In South
Asia and sub-Saharan Africa, between 30 and 40
per cent of children entering primary school drop
out before reaching grade five without acquiring
the basic skills enabling them to improve their
lives and have a voice in society. The problem is
equally troubling in regions where most children
go to school: in Latin A m e rica and the
Caribbean, one quarter of the children entering
primary school drop out before reaching grade
five. ■
The illiterates 
of the 21st century will
not be those 
who cannot read and
w r i t e, but those 
who cannot learn,
u n l e a r n , and relearn.
Alvin To f fle r,
U. S. writer and 
f u t u rologist (1928-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 21
Education for all: schools reach out
49 41
53
35
23 15
53
29
3 3 2 1
50
35
67
38
8 7 4 1
1 1
25
10
%
100
50
0
%
100
50
0
%
100
50
0
%
100
50
0
%
100
50
0
%
100
50
0
Out-of-school
Girls
Boys
Adult illiteracy rate
Female
Male
Egypt, Pakistan 15
Uganda 16
Cameroon,Rwanda 17
Ghana 19
Guinea,India 20
Côte d’Ivoire 21
Guatemala 22
C e n t ral African Rep. ,H a i t i 26
D e m .R e p. of Congo,Ye m e n 28
Zambia 29
Madagascar, Nigeria 30
Senegal 33
Mali 34
Morocco 38
Niger 42
Burkina Faso 49
The rural gap
Countries where primary school attendance in rural areas is
lower than in urban areas by 15% or more, 1 9 9 0 - 1 9 9 5
%
Pe rcentages of children not enrolled in primary school 
and illiteracy ra t e s, by sex and re g i o n
Poverty is a woman
sending her children
out to beg in traffic
rather than to school
because otherwise
there will be nothing to
e a t . The mother knows
she is repeating a cycle 
that trapped her,
but there is no way out
that she can see.
Alicia Gentolia, urban 
social worke r, P h i l i p p i n e s
G l o s s a r y
Basic education encompasses early childhood 
and primary (or elementary) education for children, as
well as education in literacy, general knowledge and life
skills for youth and adults; it may extend into secondary
education in some countries.
It refers to education intended to meet basic learning
needs, namely the knowledge, skills, attitudes and values
necessary for people 
to survive, to improve the quality of their lives,
and to continue learning.
Adult illiterate: a person 15 years or over who cannot
read,write and understand simple written messages in
any language.
Functional illiterates: adults with inadequate literacy
skills to meet the demands of everyday life.
Illiteracy rate: number of illiterate adults expressed as a
percentage of the total adult population 
(15 years and over).
Net enrolment ratio: the number of pupils enrolled who
are in the officially defined primary school 
age-group, expressed as a percentage of the total
population of that age-group.
Source: UNICEF
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
U g a n d a’s full school
b e n c h e s
◗ Dan Elwa n a
Driven by strong political will and local involvement, Uganda has embarked on an
ambitious pro g ramme to get all children into school by 2003
When a country decides that education is
going to become a top pri o ri t y, then moun-
tains can be moved in a very short time.
Uganda is a case in point. Since President Yoweri
Museveni fulfilled his campaign pledge to provide
free education for up to four children per family in
1 9 9 6 , enrolment figures have soared from 2.3 to 6.5
million primary-aged children.
As Museveni has often said,“If we are to indus-
t ri a l i z e , we need an educated populat i o n .”The will
to promote such a policy is rooted in Uganda’s
emergence from ye a rs of conflict during the seve n-
ties and eighties. Between 1971 and 1985, gross
domestic product (GDP) declined, and educat i o n ’s
share of it fell from 3.4 to 1.4 per cent—about four
times below the A f rican ave r a g e .When the Nat i o n a l
Resistance Movement (NRM) assumed power in
1986,the education system had collapsed and the
c o u n t ry had become one of the poorest in the
wo r l d .The gove rnment immediately commissioned
an in-depth analysis of the education sector, c o n s u l-
ting widely with all stakeholders around the country.
This process fostered a broad-based sense of ow n e r-
ship of the ensuing national education policy and
paved the way for the declaration of the Universal
Primary Education programme (UPE), officially
launched in December 1996.The time frame for
completion is 2003.
G r a n t e d , the country now boasts one of A f ri c a ’s
best performing economies, with real GDP gr o-
wing at an average of 6.5 per cent since 1987. It wa s
the first to be declared eligible and to benefit from
the Heavily Indebted Poor Countries initiative in
April 1998, with a fraction of debt relief allocated
to educat i o n .O verall expenditure on pri m a ry edu-
c ation increased 40 per cent for the first year of UPE
and another 28 per cent the subsequent year. Pri-
m a ry education now accounts for 64 per cent of the
total education budget,up from 30 per cent at the
b e ginning of the 1990s, and the programme is also 
benefiting from strong donor support.At constant
p ri c e s , Uganda spent only US$8 annually per pupil
in the early 1980s, compared to $32.50 in the fin a n-
cial year 1997/98.
“When the policy was announced, there wa s
quite a bit of confusion at the community level,”
recalls UNICEF’s Charles Nadongo. “It wa s
thought that the central gove rnment was supposed
to take care of eve ry t h i n g .N ow the policy has been
c l a ri fied to ensure that all part n e rs understand their
roles.”The policy coincided with the decentraliza-
tion of several public serv i c e s , notably putting
schools under the management of the country ’s
39 distri c t s. S e n s i t i z ation and training seminars
were held for local political and religious leaders ,a s
well as administrative personnel, while radio pro-
grammes also gr e atly helped in clarifying roles.
“Because of the decentralized nature of powe r ,l e a-
ders are accountable at the local level and have a
strong obligation to make sure it works.”
The progr a m m e ’s hallmark lies in suddenly
making education affordable for thousands of fa m i-
lies. Before the introduction of UPE,parents bore
the cost of school fees, were expected to provide uni-
f o rm s ,e xercise books, textbooks and in some cases
money for a building fund used by authorities for
expanding school blocks or renovating existing
o n e s. Fees alone could range from 35,000 to 45,000
Ugandan shillings ($23-$30) per school term . In a
survey conducted in January 1997, 80 per cent of
parents interviewed stated that lack of money had
p r e vented them from sending their children to
s c h o o l . Under the current progr a m m e , school fees
are wa i ved and textbooks are free, but the rest of the
deal is a cost-sharing one.
G ove rnment provides iron sheets, c e m e n t ,
timber and nails for building classrooms, with local
a u t h o rities and communities expected to supply
additional inputs. Parents must provide uniforms,
pens and exercise books as well as help in managi n g
◗ Journalist with The East African
(Uganda),with additional
reporting by UNESCO Courier staff
1❘Five flagship pro j e c t s
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Primary school pupils at Mbarara in Uganda. Their school was built by parents using material paid for by the state.
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 23
Education for all: schools reach out
schools. “As parents, we provide voluntary labour
and ensure that the materials sent by the central
g ove rnment are properly used,” s ays A h m e d
S e k a n d i , who is helping to reconstruct a school
destroyed by war. In some cases,local councils are
imposing an education tax to raise revenue for
school deve l o p m e n t . School management com-
mittees have been strengthened and expanded to
include teachers , parents and community repre-
s e n t at i ves and are much more active than in the past
according to Mary Kasozi, aWorld Bank officer.
Part of the programme’s success is owed to a
“new part n e rship between the gove rnment and the
NGO sector,” according to Albert Byamugisha of
the Ministry of Education and Sport s. In some
c a s e s , old alliances have been revitalized, e s p e c i a l l y
with the churches, which were once the backbone
of the education system. Church organizations have
p r ovided input into the new syllabu s.According to
the NGO World Vision, which is involved in edu-
c ation projects in 17 Ugandan distri c t s , “The rela-
tionship between gove rnment and NGOs has gr e at l y
i m p r oved because the gove rnment officials now
view the latter as a great asset.”
In many cases, the funds previously used by
NGOs to support tuition fees have now been
released and earmarked for classroom constru c-
t i o n , teacher training and help in providing lunches
and uniforms.Technical co-operation with foreign
donors has also been bolstered.
Although it is too early to assess their impact,
i nvestments are also being made in quality. S o m e
20,000 teachers have been hired, training has been
b o o s t e d , notably through community-based pro-
gr a m m e s , and salaries have significantly increased,
although most say that the current wage (U. S h s.
72,000/US$48 per month) is too low to make ends
m e e t .A new syllabus is being developed which places
gr e ater emphasis on practical subjects such as agri-
c u l t u r e , home economics, animal husbandry and
e nvironmental studies.
But considerable hurdles remain.There are not
enough schools.The official pupil-teacher ratio is 63
(up from 37 in 1996), but it is not rare for pri m a ry
school teachers to have to cope with classes of 150
p u p i l s. According to World V i s i o n , there is bittern e s s
in urban areas because of ove r c r ow d i n g, and many
families have started opting for pri vate schools.T h e
c u rrent strat e gic education investment plan (1998-
2003) calls for the building of some 25,000 class-
rooms and the renovation of dilapidated bu i l d i n g s
along with the establishment of community poly-
technics to provide multi-skill training for pri m a ry -
school leave rs. G i ven present enrolment trends, i t
can be foreseen that students will run up against a shor-
tage of secondary schools in a few ye a rs time.And eve n
though the programme has opened up the school to
new leagues of children, UNICEF expresses concern
t h at this is not enough.
G i r l s ’ enrolment is only slowly inching up (47
per cent in 1999).“ We estimate that there are about
15 per cent of children who are not making it to
s c h o o l .The curriculum and learning experiences have
to be better adapted to vulnerable gr o u p s ;o t h e r w i s e
the push-out effects will be gr e at ,” s ays Nadongo.
E f f o rts are underway to better cater to the most mar-
ginalized gr o u p s , in particular nomadic communities
in the nort h e a s t e rn Karamoja regi o n ,where the UPE
p r o gramme has had a minimal impact.H e r e , in part-
n e rship with gove rn m e n t ,NGOs and UN agencies are
spearheading projects to make school fit in with the
l i ves of children, and not the other way around. ð■
Uganda:
basic indicators
Population:
20.9 million
GNP per capita:
US$320
Literacy rate:
64 per cent 
(female literacy rate:
53 per cent)
Net primary school
enrolment:
85 per cent
Source:ADEA
It takes a village 
to raise a child.
African saying
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
B a n g l a d e s h:
girls firs t
◗ Shahnoor Wa h i d
F rom modest beginnings, an NGO attracts over one million children from poverty-stricke n
b a c k g rounds into the classroom and gets them to stay there
Outside a one-room school in a village 40 kilo-
metres from Dhaka, the Bangladeshi capital,
a mother balks at the idea of marrying her 14-
year-old daughter Mukta if a proposal comes along,
e ven more at sending her to work in a fa c t o ry to
supplement the family income.“I’ll never do such a
t h i n g . I want my children to get an education firs t ,”
she assert s. “ E d u c ation will help them get a good
job later and become established in life.You can rob
a person of all their goods, but not of an educat i o n .”
I n s i d e , Mukta is one of twenty girls and five boy s
sitting on mats arranged in a “ U ” shape on the ear-
then flo o r. L e a rn e rs each have their own textbooks,
n o t e b o o k s , pencils and slat e s. D r aw i n g s , poems and
r hy m e s , a map of Bangladesh, a calendar and a
blackboard brighten up the bamboo walls of this
modest classroom run by the Bangladesh Rural
A d vancement Committee (BRAC ) . Fo rmed in 1972
to help thousands of refugees returning from the
previous ye a r ’s wa r ,1 this NGO has become one of
the most influential in the country for its work in
rural development,health  and education.
Were it not for BRAC , it is more than likely that
the children in this classroom—the sons and daugh-
t e rs of ri c k s h aw pullers , small traders or fa c t o ry wo r-
k e rs — would never learn to read and write in a coun-
t ry where almost half the population lives below the
p ove rty line. Despite progress in expanding pri m a ry
e d u c ation over the past decades, the poorest of the
poor are still likely not to make it to school or to
drop out in the early stages. B R AC launched its edu-
cation programme in 1985 after a question from a
mother enrolled in one of its adult literacy classes:
“But what about our children? Will they have to wa i t
until they are 18 to join your school?”
From modest beginnings with 22 experi m e n t a l
s c h o o l s ,B R AC ’s education programme now counts
34,500 schools cat e ring to 1.2 million students, o f
whom 70 per cent are gi r l s.Additional progr a m m e s
for children between 11 and 14 and for those living in
urban slums have also been launched in the past deca-
d e , and community-based libraries have been set up
across the country. B e t ween 1985 and 1999,a total of
1.5 million students gr a d u ated from BRAC schools.
The model is being replicated in several East and South
A f rican countries and is inspiring in-depth pri m a ry
e d u c ation reforms in South Asia and Central A m e-
ri c a .
The visitor to BRAC schools in villages on the
o u t s k i rts of Dhaka is immediately struck by the high
attendance rate and percentage of girls in the class-
r o o m . One major asset of BRAC schools is that they
are always located close to students’ h o m e s , d i s-
tance being one of the chief impediments to gi r l s ’
schooling in developing countri e s. Another plus is
class size: there are never more than 33 students per
c l a s s , compared with an average 73 in gove rn m e n t
s c h o o l s. In some cases, schools run morning and
a f t e rnoon shifts, with classes held three hours daily,
six days a we e k .These are agreed upon with parents
and can be changed during harvest time if neces-
s a ry. House ow n e rs often volunteer to rent out a
room to BRAC at minimal cost.
A confidence booster
Parents are met in groups by BRAC staff seve r a l
times before a school is opened and are required to
pledge to send their children to school each day and
to attend monthly parents’ m e e t i n g s.Three parents
(often mothers) also sit on the school management
committee alongside the community leader and tea-
c h e r.And when children don’t show up at school for a
few day s , the teacher or supervisor goes to check on
t h e m .The curriculum essentially cove rs the same
ground as in formal schools but is presented through
s i m p l i fied learning mat e rials that are relevant to the
life and environment of the children. According to 
Dr A riful Islam, c o o r d i n ator of the education pro-
gr a m m e ,“the school hours ,l o c at i o n , teacher and cur-
ricular activities like singi n g, dancing and draw i n g
capture the students’ interest and boost their confi-
d e n c e .Te a c h e rs and superv i s o rs monitor the progr e s s
of each individual learner with care.”
Te a c h e rs , the single most decisive influence on
the quality of schooling, are what BRAC calls “ p a r a-
p r o f e s s i o n a l s ” .N i n e t y - s e ven per cent of them are
women—a key factor in attracting girl pupils.T h e y
generally have nine ye a rs of educat i o n , making them
less qualified than their counterp a rts in gove rn-
ment schools who are required to have finished
s e c o n d a ry school. Most are married and live in the
village where the school is locat e d . Although their
wages are below those in gove rnment schools, t h e i r
◗ Associate editor,
The Independent (Bangladesh)
1 . From 1947 until 1971, the federal state of Pakistan consisted
of East Pakistan and West Pa k i s t a n , which were separated 
g e o gr a p h i c a l l y. In 1971 East Pakistan broke away, and achie-
ved independence as the Pe o p l e ’s Republic of Bangladesh after
a civil war which lasted from March to December.
Bangladesh:
basic indicators
Population:
122 million
GNP per capita:
US$260
Literacy rate:
58 per cent 
(female literacy rate:
35 per cent)
Net primary school
enrolment:
81.4 per cent
Source: World Bank and Government of
Bangladesh
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 25
Education for all: schools reach out
s t atus as teachers carries intangible benefit s , such as reco-
gnition within the community.The recruitment procedure
is straightforward and the accent thereafter is put on bu i l-
ding skills and keeping motivation high: after being hired,
t e a c h e rs go on to take a two - week BRAC training cours e
t h at is complemented by refresher training one day a
m o n t h .
The results? BRAC schools boast a much lower dro-
pout rate than gove rnment pri m a ry schools 
(8 per cent compared with 32 per cent). Almost 
90 per cent of the students who gr a d u ate from them go on
to the formal schools, passing admission tests with little
d i f ficulty and proving that non-formal learning is not syno-
nymous with lower quality. Cost per student is a yearly $20,
compared with an estimated $52 in gove rnment schools.
S i g n i fic a n t l y, t e a c h e rs ’s a l a ries account for less than 40 per
cent of costs (close to 90 per cent in gove rnment schools),
l e aving more funds available for student books and sup-
p l i e s ,c u rriculum deve l o p m e n t , teacher training, m a n a g e-
ment and support at the local level.
O ver the ye a rs , B R AC has won the confidence of
p a r e n t s ,m a ny of whom now claim in chorus that “ t h e s e
schools are better run than gove rnment ones, t e a c h e rs come
on time and students learn in one week what those in
g ove rnment schools do in a month.” According to UNI-
C E F ’s Manzoor A h m e d ,“ B R AC ’s non-formal pri m a ry
e d u c ation programme has the same elements as all other
traditional or non-traditional educational progr a m m e s , bu t
it is the character and composition of these elements that
make it distinctive and are the key to its success.” He under-
lines that BRAC “has exploded several widely held myths
about pri m a ry educat i o n :t h at poor and illiterate rural fa m i-
lies are not concerned about their children’s educat i o n ,
t h at parents in traditional communities do not support
e d u c ation of girls and wo m e n ,t h at only teachers with for-
mal credentials and qualific ations and expensively bu i l t
school buildings provide the setting for quality pri-
m a ry educat i o n ; t h at NGOs can be relied on for
only small-scale pilot projects in pri m a ry educat i o n ;
and that serving hard-to-reach groups effective l y
makes schools more expensive.”
Although the gove rnment has acknowledged that
u n i ve rsal pri m a ry education can’t be achieved without
embracing non-formal avenues to learn i n g, it gi ve s
no support to BRAC ’s progr a m m e .C o s t - s h a ri n g
n e g o t i ations are underway, but so far the organiza-
tion remains highly dependent on a consortium of
b i l ateral and multilateral aid donors. B R AC ’s edu-
c ation budget for the 1999-2004 period totals $112
m i l l i o n , of which $109 million will be funded through
foreign donors. Since 1998, the organization has been
asking for a 5 takas (around US10 cents) monthly
c o n t ri bution eve ry month from each student, w i t h
an exception made for the most destitute families and
the second child enrolled.This income cove rs about
three per cent of total costs. B R AC ’s success howe-
ver has not left the gove rnment entirely indifferent.
It has turned over 67 poorly functioning communi-
ty schools to the organizat i o n , with the hope that
B R AC will get them running again. B R AC is also one
of several NGOs which has received gove rnment fun-
ding to run 225 schools cat e ring to children wo r k i n g
in fa c t o ries or as domestic serva n t s , an initiat i ve that
is not part of BRAC ’s own non-formal pri m a ry edu-
c ation progr a m m e .
Although it has no plans to open new schools,
B R AC is stretching its education programme to the
full five - year pri m a ry cycle (instead of the present
three)—to give the underprivileged an extra chan-
ce of getting an education. ■
It is easy to substitute
our will for that of the
child by means of
suggestion or coercion;
but when we have
done this we have
robbed him of his
greatest right, the right
to construct his own
p e r s o n a l i t y.
Maria Montessori,
Italian educator (1870-1952)
At a factory owned by the Bangladesh Rural Advancement Committee (BRAC), slates are packed 
for free distribution to children.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
L ike all of El Salva d o r ’s institutions, t h e
school system suffered from the effects of
the bloody civil war that ravaged the country
between 1980 and 1992. When the war came to
an end, half a million children, most of them in
rural areas, were illiterat e , and a shortage of
teachers meant they had little chance of going to
s c h o o l . The war caused $2,125,000 wo rth of
damage to the educational infrastru c t u r e ,
according to a government report.
Backed by officials from the educat i o n
m i n i s t ry (MINED), parents in some of the
poorest villages decided to act, and in 1991 the
EDUCO Community-Based Educat i o n
P r o gramme programme was launched. L o c a l
self-management of schools was a new concept
for Latin America.
Pa re n t - d i re c t o rs control 
the purse strings
EDUCO enabled parents to take part in
running schools, from hiring teachers to pay i n g
their salaries. The parents—farmers and manual
labourers—soon began to draw up plans and to
use the money transferred to them by the
ministry to pay teachers and running costs.
At Los Izotes, a village 35 km north of the
c a p i t a l , San Salva d o r , 260 children gather each
day in a small building surrounded by trees and
painted blue and white, El Salva d o r ’s nat i o n a l
colours. Their school has the same timetable, the
same equipment and the same lessons as any
other in the country. Unlike most Salva d o ri a n
schools, however, it is run by local people.
EDUCO was first tried out here and in five
other villages in very poor and inaccessible areas
before being extended to the rest of the country
and becoming the centrepiece of the
government’s education strategy. The number of
children attending such locally-run schools rose
from 8,400 in 1991 to more than 237,000 in
1999, according to MINED.
Each of the schools is managed by a
community education association (AC E ) , w h o s e
m e m b e rs are parents elected at a general
a s s e m b l y. This allows courses to be
decentral ized and the administration to be
s t r e a m l i n e d . According to MINED, 1,722 AC E s
were operating nationwide in 1999, with more
than 4,700 teachers.
At Los Izotes the school population has
increased, especially since the children no longer
had to make the long journey to attend school in
the nearest city, Q u e z a l t e p e q u e . To meet the
gr owing demand, the families asked the
government to build new premises in the village.
“MINED asked us to look for a building that
could house a temporary school while the new
one was going up on a plot donated by a local
landowner,” says Jorge Alberto Molina, president
of the Los Izotes ACE.
M o l i n a , a 34-year-old father of five boy s ,
s ays that after several months’ wo r k , the new
building was opened in May 1999 and that this
year it is expected to receive 300 children, f r o m
i n fants to seventh gr a d e . The children are visibly
happy about having a school to go to. “ We really
want our new school, and it’s near to where we
l i ve so we can help our parents at home or in the
fie l d s ,” s ays 11-year-old Victor Va l e n c i a , who is
in sixth gr a d e .
At the end of each month, the teachers , who are
on yearly contracts, make out a bill and the directors
of the ACE pay their salaries and send the staff ’s
c o n t ri butions to the national social security and pen-
sion authori t i e s. As in any pri vate firm , the parent-
d i r e c t o rs are allowed to make pay deductions if a
teacher is absent without a good reason.
At the end of the ye a r , the ACE directors
assess the teachers’ work and decide whether or
not to renew their contracts. Te a c h e rs in the
EDUCO programme earn 3,485 colons ($400)
and if they work double shifts (morning and
afternoon), they get $514.
Stirring intere s t
in other countries
A 1997 MINED study, backed by the Wo r l d
B a n k , found that although children attending these
schools were socially and economically wo rse off than
those at traditional schools, the rate of academic suc-
cess in both kinds of schools was about the same. B u t
some in the stat e - run education sector criticize the
EDUCO schools. Jesus Rive r a ,s e c r e t a ry-general of
the National A s s o c i ation of Salvadoran Te a c h e rs ,
which has 21,000 members ,s ays the EDUCO pro-
El Salvador:
power to the pare n t s!
◗ Carlos Mario Marquez
To cope with the ravages of civil war, p a rents in some of 
El Salvador’s poorest villages took over the running of local schools.
The experiment has caught on nationwide
◗ San Salva d o r-based journalist
Education has 
an important role 
in creating and defin i n g
the values that will
m a ke Africa politically
and culturally united,
coherent and forwa r d -
l o o k i n g . Only when the
purpose 
of education has been
clearly defined can
Africa decide what type
of education is suitable
for development.
Fay Chung, former minister 
of education of Zimbabwe,
member of the International
Commission on Education 
for the Tw e n t y - first Century
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 27
Education for all: schools reach out
T wo ye a rs ago, l i f e ’s opportunities were few and
far between for Underm a a . At the age of 20,
jobless and virtually destitute, she was caring
for her newborn baby after her husband had left for
the army. Her days were spent tending live s t o c k
beside her ge r (white felt tent) on the outskirts of
Darkhan in nort h e rn Mongolia.The country wa s
in the depths of an economic depression.The last
thing on her mind was politics.
To d ay Undermaa and her husband are living
d ow n t ow n ,where she works for the Mongolian Nat i o-
M o n g o l i a :
d i s t a n c e is no object
◗ Michael Kohn with additional reporting by Altangerelyn Delgermaa 
Camel-borne tutors range the steppe to back up a nationwide radio learning scheme which
packages human rights awareness as well as job skills
◗ Respectively journalist with 
the Mongol Messenger,
a weekly English-language
newspaper based in Ulaanbaatar,
and Mongolian freelance
journalist
nal Democratic Pa rt y. For the first time she has a
steady income and a passion for politics.
In Underm a a ’s fa m i l y, politics were taboo. H e r
gr a n d father had been branded an “ e n e my of the
s t at e ” by the old Soviet-backed regime and exiled to
the countryside in 1964 for supporting one of Mon-
g o l i a ’s few dissidents.To bu ry this “ c ri m e ” ,U n d e r-
maa’s grandmother changed the family name and
moved to a new city.
It wa s n ’t until 1990, after the collapse of the old
r e gi m e ,t h at Undermaa learned of this dark past.B u t
gramme “ d e p ri ves teachers of many of their ri g h t s ,
i n c l u d i n g the right to form a trade union.And since
the contracts are renewed on a yearly basis, the tea-
chers have no job security at all.”
Despite the criticism, the World Bank praised
EDUCO in 1997 as a “flagship programme.” In
the almost 10 years it has been going, EDUCO
has also stirred interest in other countri e s.
Missions have come from Brazil, M e x i c o,
G u at e m a l a , H o n d u r a s , Costa Rica, Pa n a m a ,
Uganda, Senegal and a dozen other countries to
have a look at El Salvador’s experiment.
The 1997 study noted that EDUCO “has been
remarkably successful in expanding educat i o n a l
o p p o rtunities for the poor in rural areas.” S a n t i a g o
M i r a n d a , a member of the Los Izotes AC E ,e m p h a-
tically agrees and say s : “EDUCO has brought us
d e velopment and gi ven us the means to carry out
other projects, such as building a road. Before that ,
no vehicles could get here. We also dug a well to
p r ovide water for the school.Then we got electri c i t y
and now we ’ ve even got phones in our village.” ■
El Salvador:
basic indicators
Population:
5.9 million
GNP per capita:
US$1,810
Literacy rate:
77 per cent 
(female literacy rate:
74.2 per cent)
Net primary enrolment
rate:
80.1 per cent
Source:UNDP
Parents meet to discuss the running of the local school at Los Izotes, one of the first villages to take part 
in El Salvador’s community-based education programme.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
the facts were not enough, she say s. H ow could she
analyse tyranny without the slightest notion of human
rights? The missing “ l i n k s ”came from an unlikely sour-
c e :a free sewing course adve rtised on the radio.U n d e r-
maa simply thought the course might help her get a
j o b. But it came complete with a primer on human
rights and good gove rn a n c e .
U n d e rm a a ’s classes are part of a national distan-
ce education project,“ L e a rning for Life”, run by the
Mongolian gove rnment and UN E S C O with the fin a n-
cial assistance of the Danish aid agency, D a n i d a .A
total of 3,000 young students have tuned into we e k-
ly radio programmes on job-oriented topics rangi n g
from basic marketing to computer skills and carp e t -
m a k i n g . In between progr a m m e s ,students follow exe r-
cises in textbooks and meet in groups eve ry week or
so for learning sessions with trained tutors. S p e c i a l
d e m o n s t r ations are organized for hands-on training
in the more technical skills.
While the focus is on helping students adjust to
the country ’s economic transition to a more open eco-
n o my, the project also aims to prepare them for more
open gove rn m e n t , which explains the section on
human ri g h t s. At the same time, the aim is to rein-
force the educational gains made under the previous
communist stat e , notably with literacy rates in Rus-
sian Cyrillic script of about 85 per cent.
Distance education is not entirely new to Mon-
g o l i a , one of the few countries where nomads make
up 20 per cent of the population.During commu-
n i s m , s t at e - run radio and television stations bea-
med educational programmes across the gr a s s y
steppes. But there was no need for a massive cam-
p a i g n , as virtually all children received schooling at
county or provincial centres—even children of her-
ding families living on the livestock co-operat i ve s
which dotted the vast Gobi Desert . Room and board
were paid for by the stat e . E ven unive rsities we r e
free for those who gained admission.
But those days are ove r. U n i ve rsity education is
no longer free, l e aving those without means no other
option than to forego higher education and join the
wo r k f o r c e . Local NGOs are concerned that children
are dropping out of school and living on the streets in
cities like the capital, U l a a n b a at a r. In the rural areas,
m a ny children stay at home to help their parents tend
their herds of goat s , ya k s , camels and hors e s.
Against this backdrop, the coalition gove rn m e n t
elected in 1996 jumped at the chance of revitalizing
the old concept of distance education with a new set
of part n e rs.At the top of the ladder,UN E S C O p r ov i d e s
the technical and conceptual experience to make the
most of the funding provided by Danida ($1.7 million
for five ye a rs ) .
Pooling re s o u rc e s
On the next ru n g, the education ministry is for-
ging a new gi ve-and-take relationship with other minis-
t ri e s.For example,p a rt of the project money has gone
to re-equipping the studios of national and regi o n a l
public radio stations which are not just broadcasting
p r o grammes but helping to produce them.Jo u rn a l i s t s
team up with education experts and bu s i n e s s p e o p l e
to produce shows on topics ranging from accountan-
cy to starting a small restaurant. P ri vate publishers
h ave also got in on the act,and are producing new text-
books on sewing,h a i r d r e s s i n g,p h o t o gr a p hy and other
skills that are a far cry from 
standard school subjects.
This pooling of resources includes the key actors ,
t u t o rs , who supposedly volunteer but are often desi-
g n ated by local authori t i e s.Most of them are school-
t e a c h e rs but some are economists, accountants or
other professionals, who take crash courses to assu-
me their new role.
Initial results are encouragi n g . In an eva l u at i o n
study involving 500 students in Ulaanbaat a r ,a l m o s t
half had found jobs, while over 10 per cent had 
In between radio programmes students get down to their homework.
Education is not 
a way of escaping the
c o u n t r y ’s 
p o v e r t y. It is a way 
of fighting it.
Julius Nyere re (1922-1999)
former school teacher 
who became the first Pre s i d e n t
of the United Republic 
of Ta n z a n i a
Mongolia:
basic indicators
Population:
2.6 million
GNP per capita:
US$400
Literacy rate:
84 per cent 
(female literacy rate:
78.6 per cent)
Source: World Bank and UNDP
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 29
Education for all: schools reach out
◗ Assistant editor of The Times of
India
ve r , it was never perceived as a people’s progr a m-
me,and suffered from embezzlement of funds and
poor target achieve m e n t . In 1988 the system wa s
turned on its head.An autonomous National Lite-
r a cy Mission A u t h o rity was established, to which
the central gove rnment directly sanctioned funds,
by-passing the state governments. District literacy
committees were put at the centre of the program-
m e , receiving 100 per cent of the funds.This brought
it success at the grassroots level.”
These committees are autonomous bodies
which report directly to the National Literacy Mis-
s i o n . E d u c ation experts and NGOs are strongly
represented on them alongside local offic i a l s.T h e y
conduct door-to-door surveys to identify non-lite-
rates, organize mobilization activities, select orga-
nizations and volunteers to participate in the cam-
p a i g n , and develop locally-relevant learn i n g
materials while keeping the larger national canvas
and its concerns in view.
“ We realized that in order to succeed,l i t e r a cy had
to become a grassroots social move m e n t , and that is
w hy we put vo l u n t e e rs at the heart of our strat e g y,”
explains Mr D. R . Pa ri h a r , M a h a r a s h t r a ’s deputy
s e c r e t a ry of school educat i o n .The campaign is dri ve n
by over 10 million unpaid vo l u n t e e rs nat i o n w i d e —
t e a c h e rs and students from schools, colleges and uni-
ve rs i t i e s , public sector employe e s ,h o u s e w i ve s ,e x - s e r-
v i c e m e n , retired gove rnment officials and NGO
m e m b e rs.E ve ry state has a specialized resource centre
which conducts a two - d ay training programme for
vo l u n t e e rs  and provides them with literacy 
m at e ri a l s. “The pri m e rs are simple with lots of dra-
w i n g s , w ritten in the local Marathi language, a n d
about ve ry practical things like purchasing ve g e t a b l e s
‘You know, my daughter has gr a d u ated from
u n i ve rsity and now wants to study for a
Master’s degree,” exclaims Sagar More as
t e a rs of pride well up in her eyes at the thought that
her own daughter can dare to dream so big.
M o r e , who is invo l ved in India’s National Lite-
r a cy Mission as a volunteer with CORO (Commit-
tee of Resource Organizat i o n s ) , is a Dalit. As such,
she belongs to the “Scheduled Castes”—the lowe s t
castes in India.“As an ‘ u n t o u c h a b l e ’ , I had to sit one
outstretched arm away from the upper caste girls in
my class,” she recalls.“I was constantly humiliated by
the teacher,and dropped out after one year of school.
But after becoming literate through CORO,
I became a volunteer teacher with them.”
When India’s planners acknowledged that deve-
lopment could never really take off as long as the
c o u n t ry was anchored down by illiteracy, a nat i o n a l
l i t e r a cy mission was initiated in 1988 to impart
functional literacy to adults between 15 and 35
years. It ushered in a radical change of course by
emphasizing initiative at the grassroots level.
D ri ven by some ten million vo l u n t e e rs , the mis-
sion has recorded remarkable progr e s s , especially in
rural areas and amongst wo m e n . I n d i a ’s literacy
rate,which was 18 per cent of the total population
in 1951, rose from 52 per cent in 1991 to 62 per
cent in 1999.If the present trend continues, India
could attain a 75 per cent literacy rate by the year
2005, well ahead of 2011,as originally forecast.
“The national adult education programme wa s
actually started by the gove rnment in 1978, w i t h
NGOs assigned barely 10 per cent of the funds,”
explains Murlindhar Gode, f o rmer chairman of the
Maharashtra State Literacy Commission.“Howe-
I n d i a : local h e ro e s
◗ Meenakshi Shedde
To tackle illitera c y, the Indian government made a U-turn by putting local communities 
and volunteers at the helm of the campaign
s t a rted their own businesses within six months of
finishing the cours e s.About 20 students had enrol-
led in college.The rest were still looking for work.
But the real test lies in the “ d i s a d va n t a g e d ”c o u n-
t ry s i d e , where 90 per cent of the project part i c i p a n t s
l i ve . Tu t o rs , who make just $10-$20 for the entire
c o u rse (4-6 months), meet 15 families each month.
Tr avelling mostly by camel or on hors e b a c k , the tutor
can cover distances of 80 kilometres to reach the
families scattered across the steppes, which have vir-
tually no roads, telephones and a monthly mail deli-
ve ry at best. G i ven the harsh conditions, e s p e c i a l l y
d u ring the long fri gid winter, the tutors cannot set a
p e rmanent teaching schedule and must make the
most of their time with students. Most will liaise with
one family member who teaches the others.
M i n i s t ry of Enlightenment (Science and Educa-
tion) spokesman P.Te n gis says the gove rnment sees
no better option for rural people than long-distance
e d u c at i o n .“ E ver since the livestock were pri vat i z e d ,
families need all the help they can get,” said Te n gi s.
With few families willing or able to send their children
to dorm i t o ry schools,Te n gis explains that “kids from
h e r d e rs ’ families are spending their entire childhood
out on the steppes. . . . So as long as we have our
n o m a d s , we will need distance learn i n g .”
The gove rnment says it plans to take over the pro-
ject—and could one day offer accredited distance
c o u rses complete with exams and diplomas. But the
same spokesperson also admits that this could be
decades away — M o n g o l i a ’s transition is far from ove r ,
l e aving few resources for anything but the basics. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
or bri n ging up children,” explains P. Wa n k h e d e , a n
adult education officer in Maharashtra stat e .
In the Bombay area, C O RO was founded when
NGOs active in wo m e n ’s rights and youth move-
ments and amongst trade unions realized to what
extent illiteracy was impeding their wo r k .“ We have
n e ver seen literacy as an end, only a means,” s ay s
S u j ata Khandekar, C O RO ’s chief secretary. K h a n-
dekar is actually an engineer with the state electri c i t y
b o a r d . Because of her interest in literacy issues and
the campaign’s national dimension, she was autho-
rized to work for CORO while continuing to receive
p ay from her employe r. “ L i t e r ates must be able to
use literacy to enrich their lives—to learn to demand,
to question, to have a commitment to changing their
s i t u at i o n .Mere fa m i l i a rity with alphabets and coun-
ting numbers up to 100 is of no use.Therefore, we
also have programmes for neo-literates relating to
s av i n g s , legal literacy, social ri g h t s , alcoholism and
atrocities against women.”
Through community functions involving popu-
lar film stars ,p l ays and television seri a l s , vo l u n t e e r
t e a c h e rs are mobilized.“Most of our teaching vo l u n-
t e e rs are between 15 and 30.T h e y ’ ve followed about
s e ven ye a rs of schooling.We prefer to choose them
from the same community as the learn e rs ,” K h a n-
dekar points out. “ We cover an area of 1 million
people in Bombay—of which 70 per cent live in the
s l u m s , including Dharav i , one of the biggest in A s i a .”
One indicator of CORO’s success can be gau-
ged, not from asking students like Sagar More to
count up to 100 or sign her name, but from her
a s s e rt i veness and confident smile. She has been
t r a n s f o rmed from an illiterate woman who was too
timid to speak up even when spoken to into a zea-
lous motivator,a treasurer of the women’s Federa-
tion Credit Society and a librarian in charge of a
mobile library. Although Sagar abandoned her 
f o rmal studies after one ye a r , she and her husband,
also a Dalit,h ave ensured that all their four children
have passed the 10th grade.
“I feel so gr at i fied when our learn e rs tackle local
civic problems and take social responsibility for
o t h e rs. I ’ ve worked for CORO for five ye a rs without
being paid, but now they give me a salary of 1,500
rupees ($36) a month,” s ays More. “ S o m e t i m e s
they can’t pay even that , but A m b e d k a r ’s idea of
e d u c ating others through s h ra m d a n ( d o n at i n g
labour) means much more to me.” More is referri n g
to Dr Babasaheb A m b e d k a r , a Dalit from Mahara-
shtra state who rose to become the architect of
I n d i a ’s constitution. Throughout his career, h e
emphasized education and women’s rights and is
considered a pioneering social reformer.
M o t i vation among the Dalits is especially high.
“I found I was more effective when I made educa-
tion an emotional issue,” s ays Vilas Sarm a l k a r ,a n o-
ther volunteer teacher.“The Dalits really revere Dr
A m b e d k a r. O n c e , when I was dealing with a fa m i l y
that was reluctant to come to the class,I asked if I
could then take down the portrait of him that they
hung in their house. N o, n o, they said, h o rri fie d ,
and made sure they came from the next class on.”
While volunteer teachers show unquestionable
commitment to their wo r k , their enthusiasm could
wane in the long run in the absence of monetary
b e n e fits for them. “Of cours e , e d u c ation through
vo l u n t e e rs makes for financial  sav i n g s. But the tru t h
is that even if you have the money, it cannot buy yo u
community part i c i p at i o n ,” s ays Pa ri h a r.As CORO ’s
Khandekar sums it up, an important means of sus-
taining vo l u n t e e rs ’ momentum is by applauding
their efforts in the larger community. “Right now,
they are only local heroes,” she say s. “But in fa c t ,
they should be eve ry b o d y ’s heroes.” ■
30 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
India:
basic indicators
Population:
979.7 million (1998)
GNP per capita:
US$430
Literacy rate:
62 per cent 
(female literacy rate:
50 per cent)
Net primary school
enrolment ratio:
60.3 per cent
Source: World Bank and the Government
of India
A school for the rural poor in India’s Andhra Pradesh state.
It is the supreme art of
the teacher to awa ke n
joy in creative
expression and
k n o w l e d g e.
Albert Einstein,
German-born U. S. physicist and
mathematician (1879-1955)
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 -The UNESCO Courier 31
Education for all: schools reach out 
◗ Associate Director of the
International Literacy Institute,
University of Pennsylvania
2❘ Uneven pro g re s s
T he unfortunate and sobering news at the end
of the second millennium is that the number
of illiterate people in many developing coun-
tries still represents more than half their youth and
adult populations, with girls and women compri-
sing two-thirds of this number. Although regional
i l l i t e r a cy rates have been declining in the last
d e c a d e s , there are still close to 900 million illite-
rates in developing countries, representing nearly
25 per cent of the wo r l d ’s youth and adults. A trou-
bling question must be asked:Why haven’t we era-
dicated illiteracy or fulfilled the promises made at
the Education For All Conference held in Jo m t i e n ,
Thailand,in 1990 (see box page 18)? 
All too often,“basic education”has been taken
to mean formal pri m a ry schooling, and gove rn-
ments in developing countries and intern at i o n a l
donor agencies have followed this policy perspec-
tive, putting the vast majority of educational fun-
ding into improving access to primary schooling.
But in spite of major investments in pri m a ry schoo-
ling the results are far from satisfactory.
B u d g e t a ry belt-tightening due to economic
restructuring, falling per-capita spending on basic
e d u c at i o n , high demographic gr owth rat e s , a n d
wars and endogenous conflicts have taken a heavy
toll on formal educational systems in many deve l o-
ping countries of sub-Saharan A f rica and South
Asia, leading to a serious decline in the quality of
school-based instruction and children’s educat i o n .
One consequence of this decline has been an
increase in illiteracy and low literacy rates among
out-of-school youth and young adults. In poor
c o u n t ri e s , especially those with significant popula-
tion gr ow t h , the literacy situation may have become
worse rather than better over the past decade.
It is almost unive rsally true that , in spite of
political rhetori c, l i t e r a cy work has remained at
the bottom of the bu d g e t a ry ladder for both nat i o-
World litera c y:
what went wro n g ?
◗ Mohamed Maamouri
Ten years ago the world community pledged to halve the world illiteracy rate 
by the year 2000. It failed to meet the targ e t . How can it get back on tra c k ?
nal agencies and multilateral donors. H owe ve r ,
bu d g e t a ry limitations alone cannot explain why it
has proved so difficult to make inroads on illite-
r a cy in poor developing countri e s.A review of past
policies and practices indicates that a number of
problems have been endemic.
Firstly, mass literacy campaigns presented lite-
racy as a panacea for a variety of social ills and a
p a s s p o rt to social and economic deve l o p m e n t .T h e y
were often more political than pedagogi c a l , a n d
made empty and unfulfilled claims that eventually
led to the systematic dow n grading and dismant-
ling of literacy education.
Secondly, literacy work has been hampered by
a general lack of motivation among teachers and
l e a rn e rs ,p a rtly because definitions of literacy have
been va riable and poorly unders t o o d , t e a c h i n g
m at e rials have been lacking, and career deve l o p-
ment possibilities for teachers have been non-exis-
t e n t . L i t e r a cy classes have not been perceived as
h aving something immediat e , r e l e vant and direct
to offer that would offset the opportunity costs of
participation.
T h i r d l y, in many developing countri e s ,r e a d i n g
and writing in adult literacy classes are often taught
in indigenous languages, whereas formal primary
schooling has used the official or cosmopolitan lan-
guage (often that of the former colonial powe r ) .
These conflicting language policies have establi-
shed a barrier between the formal and non-formal
systems of educat i o n , c r e ated problems for lear-
ners and their access to socio-economic opportu-
nities.They often sow confusion and lower learner
and teacher motivation.
Literacy statistics and the outcomes of literacy
p r o grammes are questionable.They are often mea-
sured only in terms of the numbers of those who
have participated in the programmes.The empha-
sis on learning achievement made at the Jo m t i e n
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
conference has not been a major part of literacy
work over the past decade,though some encoura-
ging trends are now being seen.
In many developing countries facing severe fis-
cal cri s e s , the fle x i b i l i t y, d i ve rs i t y, and low - c o s t
f r a m e work of non-formal education offer sub-
stantial opport u n i t i e s , especially since basic skills
are tools enabling the poor to enter economies
undergoing major and rapid changes. B e c a u s e
market economy principles require more decen-
t r a l i z ation and more cost-sharing in educat i o n ,
g ove rnments in developing countries are turning to
i n n ovat i ve part n e rships and collaboration with
N G O s. Their aim is to launch literacy and non-
f o rmal education programmes that can teach more
basic learning skills in less time and at less cost
than conventional schooling.
However more attention must be given to tea-
cher training and ways of assessing results that go
b e yond the simple question of “can you read”? New
assessment methodologies and low-cost multime-
dia teacher training tools are now being developed
by the Intern ational Literacy Institute and UN E S C O.
The growing “feminization”of poverty and its
p e rsistent burden on the status of women in the
d e veloping world are now recognized as cri t i c a l
areas of concern for literacy work,and several cur-
rent literacy programmes are focusing on learning
skills and strategies aimed at redressing the gender
i m b a l a n c e . These programmes offer a va riety of
practical solutions for the empowerment of needy
women and are built around income-generat i n g
activities and productive employ m e n t , credit mana-
gement skills, good parenting and child-reari n g
practices.
Many curriculum development innovations in
l i t e r a cy programmes invo l ve the use of gender-sen-
sitive materials in nutrition,primary health,home
economics and HIV-Aids education.Linkage bet-
ween adult learning and the education of youth and
children has also emerged as a promising approach.
The successes of several literacy programmes such
as the community-based intergenerational pro-
grammes in Ghana or Egypt and the Tostan Project
in Senegal* provide evidence that more progress is
likely in this domain.
These emerging trends show that real progress
can be achieved in the coming decade.Though lite-
racy has moved nearer to the top of the agenda in
m a ny developing countri e s , it still needs to be gi ve n
a more important place in the development plans of
g ove rn m e n t s ,n ational part n e rs ,N G O s , the pri vat e
s e c t o r , and intern ational agencies, along with gr e a-
ter investment and co-operation. ■
* This programme and other projects are described on
ILI’s website: www/literacyonline.org
“Breaking Through”,Tostan’s non-formal basic education
programme in national languages in Senegal. Education for
All,Innovations Series,no. 6.
Ten ye a rs ago, the architects of the Jo m t i e n
D e c l a r ation acknowledged that in many set-
tings  governments alone could not be expec-
ted to provide basic education for all.They stressed
t h at new and revitalized part n e rships at all leve l s
were necessary—betweeen governments and non-
g ove rnmental organizat i o n s , the pri vate sector, l o c a l
communities,religious groups and families .
The notion of partnership has a positive ring,
suggesting that the state and its part n e rs work toge-
ther in harm o ny. The reality is much more com-
plex. Partnerships require strong mutual interest,
trust on both sides, and a clear understanding of
roles and objectives. All too common are cases of
w h at Jo m t i e n ’s architects had wa rned against,
namely false part n e rships which, simply put, c o m e
d own to “passing the bu c k ” . The most fla gr a n t
examples have occurred in countries where central
g ove rnments have collapsed, r e n d e ring them
unable to collect taxe s. Whether it be in Chad,
S o m a l i a , Cambodia or Uganda until the early
1 9 9 0 s , communities realized that if they wa n t e d
s c h o o l s , they would have to provide for themselve s.
Studies have shown that in several of these coun-
t ri e s , households and communities have carri e d
between 60 and 90 per cent of the costs of primary
education, which has barred many children from
attending school altogether.
Cost-sharing
In many gove rnment-sponsored schemes,
community financing is seen as an alternative to
direct taxation. However, it is not necessarily pre-
ferable. In progressive systems of taxation, the
rich pay more than the poor, but in many systems
of community financing, the poor bear a heavier
burden than the rich. Communities may also be
given only limited control in schemes sponsored
Pa r t n e rs h i p s in pra c t i c e
◗ Mark Bray
Partnership will simply be a fashionable buzzword unless it is founded on mutual interest
and trust and focuses on clear objectives
◗ Professor of Comparative
Education,University 
of Hong Kong
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 -The UNESCO Courier 33
Education for all: schools reach out
Let us not forget that
the cost of each jet
fighter equals one
million children in
primary school.
Dr Mahbub ul Haq 
( 1 9 3 4 - 1 9 9 8 ) ,e c o n o m i s t ,
former editor of the Human
Development Report
by donor agencies. In other cases, the state has
been unwilling to relinquish control but has allo-
wed NGOs to flourish and fill the gaps, enabling
a parallel system of schooling to emerge. Pakistan
is a case in point,with over 5,000 NGOs involved
in education.
In some instances,the collapse of the state has
led of necessity to new partnerships,most notably
in the ex-Soviet Union which was formerly charac-
t e rized by a highly centralized system. In Russia
and A z e r b a i j a n , for example, communities have
moved in to maintain at least some of the previous
high standards of education.
In such settings, the economic and political cri-
sis softened the rigid attitudes of the past on both
sides:governments became more interested in the
idea that communities could share some of the
financial burden of schooling, and communities
showed willingness to contribute resources.What
s t a rted with a rather narr ow focus on finance in
many cases broadened to include planning, curri-
culum and other dimensions.
A dialogue between 
school and community
The point is instructive: genuine partnerships
i nvo l ve much more than mere contri bution of
fin a n c e .They are not a simple mechanism to secure
resources and to reduce budgetary crises. Nor are
they necessarily part of decentralization initiat i ve s.
In some settings, c o o r d i n ation and more rat h e r
than less centralization are needed.
The goal of part n e rships should be clearly kept
in mind: to improve pupils’ attendance, retention
and the quality of learn i n g . School boards on which
p a r e n t s ,t e a c h e rs , local officials and other commu-
nity representat i ves have a voice are one of the most
effective tools for giving communities a greater say
in the planning, running and monitoring of 
education.
Some countries do not have school boards; bu t
in others the model has passed the test of time. Fo r
the past thirty ye a rs , Papua New Guinea has pro-
moted in law and in practice the part i c i p ation of
parents and communities on pri m a ry school boards
of management. Communities even have the powe r
to decide on the languages of instruction despite
the fact that the gove rnment meets the major costs
of elementary educat i o n . Community members
commonly join forces with teachers and others to
encourage children’s attendance and punctuality.
Targets cannot all be reached ove rn i g h t , o f
c o u rs e . Parents need to learn about broader policy
i s s u e s , and the teachers need to find out more about
their pupils’ h o m e s. In some countri e s ,r e s o u r c e s
i nvested in school-level and community-level wo r k-
shops have gr e atly improved the effic i e n cy and effec-
t i veness of education systems.They have fa c i l i t at e d
dialogue between the school and the community.
The role of teachers on school boards should
not be underestimated:they tend to hold different
attitudes from central authorities regarding criti-
cal issues such as student drop-out, a major pro-
blem in the developing world. Many teachers see
drop-out (or push-out) as a way of reducing class
size and dealing with troublesome students rather
than a problem. Discussion of these issues during
workshops can change perspectives and attitudes,
and can make the school a friendlier place in
which to learn.
G ove rnments have a major role to play in
m o n i t o r ing and guiding part n e rships with
c o m m u n i t i e s : checks and balances are needed to
ensure that school boards are not autocrat i c,
t h at certain groups of students are not being
d i s c ri m i n ated against on the basis of race,
Building a school at Bafoussan,in Cameroon.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
At the end of some 40 ye a rs of development co-
o p e r ation it may seem heart - wa rming that
“ p a rt n e rs h i p ” is currently one of the key
words in the development dictionary, or at least in
its Nort h e rn edition. It is by no means as clear that
it is as salient a term in the Southern editions. A n d
this holds particularly true in the education and trai-
ning sector.
It is good to hear so many donors talking of the
need for part n e rships with the South to be genuine
and respectful,a tacit admission that to date many
were not at all symmetrical.Yet even now, it is still
the donors who are laying down the cri t e ria for
genuine part n e rs h i p. S e veral of them are swa p p i n g
some of their old part n e rs for new ones who appear
to comply with new requirements on governance,
pro-poor gr ow t h , gender equity and basic educat i o n .
With some of these part n e rs , the donors are
trying out a new form of aid delivery known as the
Sector Wide Approach or SWA P. H owe ve r , d e s-
pite their title, S WAPs are often not sector-wide, bu t
t u rn out to be co-ordinated donor support to a
single sub-sector, p ri m a ry educat i o n .And it some-
times seems that the sheer scale and complexity of
S WAPs means that they can be more inva s i ve of the
n ational sovereignty of a state than previous donor
projects ever were.
This suggests a paradox at the heart of the
SWAP partnership approach.The SWAP assumes
t h at the gove rnment is in the driving seat—to use the
d o n o rs ’ commonest metaphor—and has deve l o p e d
its own sector-wide policy framework and medium-
t e rm expenditure plan. It is then meant to co-ordi-
nate the financial inputs of perhaps as many as 18
d o n o rs (as for example in the current SWAP to
◗ Director, Centre of African
Studies and professor of
International and Comparative
Education at the University of
Edinburgh (Scotland).Editor of
NORRAG NEWS, an aid policy
bulletin.Its December 1999 issue
focuses on partnerships.
education in one African country) and be able to
make its own judgments about its technical assis-
tance needs. This is a tall order. A n d , a r g u a b l y,
c o u n t ries that actually have this kind of capacity at
national and provincial levels don’t need this huge
amount of co-ordinated donor funding.While those
which still do desperately need external assistance
d o n ’t have the capacity to be part n e rs on these
demanding terms.
A second kind of emerging part n e rship encom-
passes a series of new alliances that are no longer
solely dependent on aid.They involve all kinds of
twinning—of schools,of universities and colleges,
and of educational and cultural resources such as
museums. But in what kind of countries and insti-
tutions do we find these new twinning part n e rs? Not
s u rp risingly it is in the richer countries of the South,
and in Asia rather than in some of the ve ry poor ins-
titutions of sub-Saharan A f ri c a ,t h at such alliances
are being cemented.
It is also in these richer countri e s , i n c l u d i n g
p a rt of South A f ri c a , t h at there is increasingly a
p owerful business dimension to the new part n e rs h i p
discourse. In these kinds of environments, North-
South part n e rships turn out to be centrally
c o n c e rned with selling Nort h e rn expert i s e , s y s-
t e m s ,f r a m e wo r k s ,d e grees and franchises—to “ p a rt-
ners”whose key characteristic is capacity to pay.
T h u s , despite the president of the World Bank’s
admission in December 1999 that deve l o p m e n t
co-operation needs to be fundamentally rebuilt,it
is a pity that some of the principal designs for this
new architecture of part n e rship appear to have
been already completed and the new bu i l d i n g s
commissioned.In the North. ■
r e l i gi o n , ethnicity  or gender, and that
c u rriculum standards are met. The challenge is
to strike a balance that safeguards the rights of
children while not stifling local initiat i ve .
One final word of wa rn i n g : community part-
n e rships almost inevitably invo l ve resource contri-
butions of some nat u r e , in the form of fees and/or
other levies. Opposition to fees has deep roots in
va rious intern ational declarat i o n s , and debate on
the issue tends to be polari z e d . E d u c ation is of
c o u rse never free: somebody has to pay. S i g n i fi-
c a n t l y, the 1990 Jomtien Declaration observed that
fee-free education provided by gove rnment alone is
often of an insufficient quality to benefit the indivi-
dual child, the community or the country.
The World Bank,in a 1999 policy report, went
f u rt h e r , s t ating that “in pri n c i p l e , fees and other
c o n t ri butions paid by non-poor benefic i a ries could
free up public resources for targeting to the poor.”
Rather than flatly condemning fees, we would do
better to sensitize school boards to the needs of the
p o o r , and find eve ry mechanism possible to pro-
tect them. In this endeavour, once again,the state
has a pivotal role to play in promoting genuine part-
n e rships with communities that serve , first and 
foremost,the child. ■
A i d : an unfair d e a l ?
◗ Kenneth King
A new donor discourse suggests that partnerships up to present have not been symmetrical.
But new approaches seem equally fla w e d
*A study by Mark Bray on community part n e rships prepared for
the Dakar conference (April 2000) will shortly be available on
UN E S C O’s we b s i t e :h t t p : / / u n e s c o. o r g / e d u c at i o n / e fa
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 35
Education for all: schools reach out
Do schools foment 
i n e q u a l i t y?
Fernando Reimers◗ a rgues that unless bold innovations are made,
the education gap between rich and poor is bound to widen
In Uzbekistan,a mother gives her son a helping hand with his homework.
The role of education in reducing poverty has often
been stressed. How exactly do education and
poverty relate?
There are several reasons why education can help
reduce pove rt y. One of them is that the cognitive and
social skills and credentials which can be gained in
school expand the choices available to people and the-
refore their freedom.They increase the probability
t h at people will become more productive , get better
paid jobs,and adopt practices that lead to better health
and having fewer children. But the impact of educa-
tion on improving the living conditions of the poor
and its impact on reducing social inequality are two
different things. In some Latin A m e rican countri e s ,
for example, the wage gap between college gr a d u at e s
and those who do not have a college education has
widened during the last decade.
How does this change our way of thinking about
education? 
Making sure the poor have the basic skills that will
enable them to be productive is not enough to reduce
inequalities in a context where the non-poor are also
i nvesting all they can in educat i o n . As a result of the
big effort in expanding access to education that took
place in many developing countries in the 1950s and
1 9 6 0 s , there has been plenty of intergenerational edu-
c ational mobility. In Mexico, for example,40 per cent
of children in their sixth year of school have exceeded
the educational level of their parents.T h at ’s a terri fic
a c h i e vement of the education system.But at the same
t i m e , the parents of the wealthiest 10 per cent are
i nvesting significantly more in the education of their
c h i l d r e n ,who are reaching levels far beyond their ow n .
The distance between these kids and those of the poor
m ay even be widening. So we have a narr owing gap
in terms of average ye a rs of schooling but a widening
gap in terms of the quality of education received by
different socio-economic groups and exclusion from
access to the education levels that matter for social
mobility (upper secondary and tert i a ry ) .
You argue that education systems often re i n f o rc e
this gap.
Let’s examine the origins of these educational
equity gaps. One is that if every parent spends the
same proportion of their resources on educating
their child, richer parents will spend more in abso-
lute terms. At a time when more and more private
resources are likely to be invested in educat i o n ,
this is particularly problemat i c. S e c o n d l y, w h i l e
p r o gr e s s i ve educat o rs would say that it’s the stat e ’s
job to try to close the gap between rich and poor by
directing tax revenue towards those who need it
m o s t , w h at we ’re seeing in many education sys-
tems is the reve rs e . More is spent on urban children
and on unive rs i t i e s , and less on groups with a we a k
political voice.A third source of inequality is that
p e r f o rmance is determined not just by what teachers
do or by resources in the school but also by resources
in the home—by having a parent read to you at
n i g h t , help you with homework and take an interest
in your education.A fourth source stems from the
fact that all too often teachers treat low - i n c o m e
children as defic i e n t , disrespect them and their
p a r e n t s , and as a result teach them in ways that lead
to school failure rather than success.
Do we know what kind of compensatory policies
work best?
Here we have to look seriously at the content of
w h at ’s being taught.A lot of the effort at expansion that
took place in the 1960s and 1970s assumed that if we
just gave more of the same to eve ry b o d y, t h at wo u l d
be enough.T h at is a questionable assumption. S o m e
children are barely grasping a small part of the curri-
culum and the little they do learn will not help them
get good jobs.
In the 21st century it’s probably not going to be
enough just to be able to read,w rite and add numbers.
◗ Associate Professor at the
Harvard Graduate School of
Education,where he is director of
a new Masters programme on
International Education Policy,
with a specific focus on equality
of educational opportunity
(http://gseweb.harvard.edu/
apsp/iep.html).His latest book,
Unequal School Unequal Chances,
The challenges to equal
opportunity in the Americas will
be be published in August 2000
by Harvard University Press and
the David Rockefeller Center for
Latin American Studies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
+ …
36 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
People will need skills to help them solve their pro-
b l e m s ,d e velop the capacity to learn throughout life,
c o m m u n i c ate and work in teams. We also have to
realize that traditional education systems in deve l o p i n g
c o u n t ries lack the resources and capacity to prov i d e
all kids with educat i o n , especially at the levels that
m atter for social mobility.
The next education divide will not be measured by
whether or not children complete pri m a ry educat i o n
but by their access to and completion of secondary
e d u c at i o n . But the traditional model of secondary
and tert i a ry education is expensive , with its separat e
subject matter specialists teaching separate gr a d e s ,a n d
some would argue that on effic i e n cy grounds yo u
cannot bring it to small rural communities.This is tan-
tamount to excluding most of the poor.We should be
thinking about altern at i ve approaches such as multi-
grade secondary schools and distance educat i o n .Te l e-
c o m m u n i c ations technologies make it possible today
to think in radically different ways about how to orga-
nize educational dialogue.
Where’s the best place to start designing pro-poor
educational policies?
The home, by designing curricula that tap
resources existing among disadvantaged children.
The assumption should be that low-income kids are
not deficient in any way and that an education should
be designed for them that is relevant to their talents
and can invo l ve their parents. But all too often,
u n f o rt u n at e l y, we don’t know enough about these
children to design relevant curricula for them.It is rare
t h at education systems, p o l i cy m a k e rs and teachers
d e m o n s t r ate sufficient respect for the excluded to ask
them what they want to know and organize educa-
tional encounters in ways that fit their part i c u l a r
demands and circumstances.
Are these innovations difficult to bring about?
They are problematic because you are asking
the most vulnerable part of the education system, t h e
one that deals with peripheral gr o u p s , to do more.
● UNESCO’s World Education Report 2000, forthcoming
in April,focuses on “The right to education:towards
education for all throughout life.” Available from UNESCO
Publishing:
Fax:+33 1 45 68 57 37 or + 33 1 45 68 57 41;
e-mail:publishing.promotion@unesco.org
● Ahead of the Dakar conference (see page 18),features,
news updates, a discussion forum and country reports
produced as part of the EFA 2000 Assessment can be
found on UNESCO’s education for all website at:
www.unesco.education.org/efa 
Thematic studies will also be put online in the months to
c o m e. Information on innovative projects aimed at
marginalized youth can be found on:
w w w. u n e s c o. o r g / e d u c a t i o n / e x c l u s i o n /
● Education International, a valuable source of
information on the status of teachers.
www.ei-ie.org
● The Association for the Development of Education
in Africa (ADEA) aims to develop partnerships between
Ministers of Education and funding agencies.
www.adeanet.org
● ActionAid is one of several NGOs involved in a global
education campaign.
For more information,www.elimu.org
● Reports by Oxfam, “Education Now:Break the Cycle of
Poverty”and “The IMF:Wrong diagnosis, wrong medicine”
are available on the organization’s site at www.oxfam.org
● The Forum for African Women Educationists (FAWE)
is a pan-African organization seeking to raise awareness
about the benefits of girls’ education.Information from
www. fawe.org
● UNICEF’s State of the World’s Children 1999 is
devoted to education. The 2000 report is also available at
www.unicef.org
● UNDP’s Human Development Report 1999 gives a
comprehensive understanding of the impact of
globalization on human development,including education.
● Learning:the Treasure Within, Report to UNESCO of
the International Commission on Education for the Twenty-
first Century, UNESCO Publishing,1998. ■
W h at ’s more, not all education systems have the
same capacity for innovat i o n . Institutional capacities,
resource bases and cultural and historical determ i-
nants differ from place to place. But I’m conv i n c e d
t h at insisting on a single model of education is an
impossible aspirat i o n .
What about resources?
Political pri o rities are invo l ved here. S o m e
g ove rnments might say that they don’t have the
resources to innovat e . But how much are they spen-
ding on defence? How much are they spending on
bailing out private banks that have gone bankrupt
and in many cases fuelled corruption and capital
flight out of the country? In the long term , t h e
solution is to deepen democratic processes so that
the least empowered have more power and more
voice. In the meantime inequalities are widening.
The non-poor have to realize that it’s in their interest
to pay attention to the educational chances of the
p o o r. Until and unless that happens, I think we are
going to see reforms that are episodic and unsus-
tainable in the long term . I t ’s ve ry important to
reach a consensus in each society on the role edu-
c ational equity will have as a common aspirat i o n , a
balance of interests.The demand for a more equi-
table distri bution of educational opportunities has
to come from both the poor and the non-poor.
This is one of the main differences that you observe
b e t ween the most and the least equitable nat i o n s :i t ’s
a certain ideology, a culture of how acceptable it is
to have these kinds of disparities. There are ways,
through social marketing campaigns for example, i n
which governments can educate and sensitize the
population at large about certain priorities.
One of the lasting contri butions educat o rs can
make to improve equality of opportunity is to engage
their students and the public,both poor and non-poor,
in conve rs ations about these kinds of issues,about the
value of aspiring to equal education outcomes and
about the avenues to achieve it. ■
Interview by Cynthia Guttman
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
In Homer’s Odyssey, Circe the enchantress turns men into swine.
A NIMAL TRA NSPLA N T S :
SA FE OR SORR Y ?
◗ Amy Otchet
Animal organ transplantation into humans may save many lives or cause untold harm from
diseases crossing the species barrier. How should society decide whether or not to go ahead?
■
Just over 15 ye a rs ago, Baby Fa e
became a household name when
American doctors replaced her ailing
h e a rt with the heart of a baboon. F r o m
Australia to Brazil, millions were ri veted by
the news reports and followed her progr e s s
with baited breat h . If they were half-expec-
ting a Frankenstein’s monster, they we r e
d i s a p p o i n t e d . Baby Fae looked like any
other wee newborn child. But the sci-fi l u l-
laby turned grim 20 days after the trans-
p l a n t . On November 15, 1984 Baby Fa e
died.Later her mother angrily maintained
t h at she hadn’t been informed about the
possible dangers invo l ve d . U n b e k n ow n s t
to the doctors at the time, h owe ve r , t h e
stakes concerned far more than a single
infant’s life.We now know there is a possi-
bility that the transplantation of animal
organs into humans might unleash infec-
tious diseases similar to Aids.
The scientific community is only begi n-
ning to understand the possible risks of
xe n o t r a n s p l a n t ation—the use of animal
organs and tissue in “ s p a r e - p a rt ” s u r g e ry
for humans. O ver the past century, t h e r e
have been about 25 documented cases of
such organ transplants, the most recent
case being reported in 1993. K i d n e y s ,
hearts and livers from baboons and mon-
keys were the organs of choice. S u rv i va l
r ates were dismal—most patients died
within we e k s. To d ay, h owe ve r , thanks to
progress in biotechnology and drug treat-
m e n t s , there is renewed interest in opening
another round of human experi m e n t s.
Scientists in the United States have already
begun implanting pig cells to treat pat i e n t s
with Pa r k i n s o n ’s disease and diabetes.
O t h e rs await the green light to begin trans-
planting organs from pigs into people.
This gr owing interest is matched by
rising fear, h owe ve r , t h at an animal viru s
could jump from the pig to the human
p at i e n t , spread to others and unleash a pan-
d e m i c. When viruses cross the species 
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
barrier, the results can be catastrophic. At
least one strain of HIV is believed to have
jumped from monkeys to people after a
single infectious event 60 ye a rs ago. T h e
i n fluenza epidemic of 1918-19, w h i c h
killed tens of millions, may have been trig-
gered by a pig infecting one person.
X e n o t r a n s p l a n t ation thus confronts
the whole of society—not just individual
p atients—with the promise of sav i n g
thousands of lives and the possible risk of
causing tremendous harm . The lack of
scientific data transforms the safety issues
into an ethical dilemma which scientists
alone cannot answer.
Human transplantation has been a vic-
tim of its own success. Surgeons can now
transplant about 25 different kinds of
human organs and tissue, and surv i val rat e s
are constantly improving (60 per cent of
p atients live more than five ye a rs ) . M o r e
than one million people worldwide have
benefited since 1954,when the first trans-
plant was made. But supply cannot meet
d e m a n d . In the United Stat e s , for 
example, 3,900 people died while waiting
for an organ transplant in 1996,compared
to around 1,500 in 1988.
There are also strong economic argu-
ments in favour of xe n o t r a n s p l a n t at i o n .
About 700,000 patients suffering from kid-
ney disease world-wide are strapped to dia-
lysis machines at an annual cost of about
$19 billion, according to the Organization
for Economic Co-operation and Develop-
ment (OECD). It costs about 60 per cent
less to transplant a kidney than to keep the
p atient on life-long dialysis. Success in
xe n o t r a n s p l a n t ation could open up an
international market worth $6 billion plus
another $5 billion in related drug treat-
ments (to prevent the immune system from
rejecting the organs). One of the biggest
c o n t e n d e rs is the pharmaceutical gi a n t
N ova rtis—which not only produced cy c l o-
sporin A, the leading drug used in human
transplants, but also owns Imutran,a UK-
based biotech company famous for geneti-
cally engi n e e ring pigs for xe n o-
transplantation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
E T H I C S
focused on three strains of PERV, w h i c h
h ave been described as “second cousins”
to HIV or human immunodeficiency virus
which causes Aids.Two of them can infect
human cells.
We i s s ’s findings sent shockwave s
through public health organizations and the
industry. Researchers immediately set out
to survey as many patients as they could
find who had been exposed to porcine tis-
s u e . Out of about 175 patients screened,
none were infected by PERV.
“ I t ’s a relief,” s ays We i s s , but it’s not
c o n c l u s i ve . “This particular virus is not
going to be highly contagious but this
d o e s n ’t necessarily mean that xe n o t r a n s-
p l a n t ation is safe.”The patients in question
Pigs are the xeno-prize-winners. Non-
human primates, like baboons, have been
ruled out because their biological similari-
ties to human beings could increase the ri s k
of disease transmission, so brutally high-
lighted by the Aids and Ebola viru s e s.
M a ny people also have ethical qualms
about using our “cousins” for spare parts,
whereas we have been slaughtering and
e ating pigs for many centuri e s. F i n a l l y, p i g s
are easier to breed and genetically engi n e e r.
Duping the human 
immune system 
The human body would norm a l l y
consider a pig organ to be a dangerous
“foreign agent” and kill it within minutes
by cutting off its blood supply. I m u t r a n
and other laborat o ries are trying to get
past this defence (immune) system by
lining the pigs’ organs with human pro-
teins through genetic engi n e e ri n g .T h e s e
proteins endow the pig organ with a kind
of human disguise. After a time, h owe ve r ,
the human body would gradually realize
t h at the pig organ isn’t acceptable and
would launch an attack on it. Imutran is
n ow trying to develop new drugs and may
add more human genes to the pigs, s ay s
D r C o rinne Sav i l l , the company ’s chief
o p e r ating offic e r.
These “designer pigs” m ay, h owe ve r ,
make it easier for the animals’ g e rms to
infect people, says Dr Robin Weiss of Uni-
ve rsity College London. About two ye a rs
a g o, Weiss began publishing articles sho-
wing how pig viruses could hide behind the
human proteins (added to the pigs) and slip
past a pat i e n t ’s immune system. T h e
human proteins might also invite the
v i ruses into human cells. For example, o n e
of the human proteins used by Imutran and
other biotech companies is CD55. T h i s
protein makes the human body vulnerable
to several polio-related viru s e s. S u p p o s e ,
s ays We i s s , t h at pigs have similar viru s e s.
O r d i n a ri l y, they wo u l d n ’t affect humans
because of genetic differences. But imagi n e
that the pig viruses learn (through genetic
modification) to use CD55 and infect the
patient who receives the pig organ.Once a
pig disease has crossed over into a single
human being, it could mutate further and
spread to others.
None of these questions would matter if
the pigs could be issued with a “clean bill of
h e a l t h ” ,s ays We i s s. I m u t r a n , for example, i s
t rying to breed germ-free pigs in tightly
controlled fa c i l i t i e s. But even in a herm e t i-
cally sealed tank all the risks would not be
eliminated,particularly those arising from
v i ruses known as PERV retrov i ruses which
are found in the animal’s genes. Weiss has
r e c e i ved porcine tissue not organs, w h o s e
sheer volume may increase the risk of infec-
t i o n . S e c o n d , they were screened for the
three known retrov i ru s e s.W h at about unk-
n own germs? Weiss also wo n d e rs whether
the retrov i ruses might be hiding somewhere
in the body and become more powerful ove r
t i m e .
François Meslin of the World Health
O r g a n i z ation describes a wo rst-case scenari o :
a xe n o - p atient harbours an undetected viru s
which is passed to others by sexual inter-
c o u rs e , a likely means of transmission.As the
virus moves from one host to another, it
becomes increasingly dangerous.
“You can take a lot of precautions but
you never know how far to go to bring the
Should humans harvest spare parts from animals?
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
risks down to an acceptable leve l ,” s ay s
M e s l i n , who points to the case of bov i n e
s p o n gi f o rm encephalopat hy—“mad cow
disease”—as the closest example of this
kind of dilemma. Since Weiss sounded the
alert, public health authorities around the
world have observed a de facto morat o ri u m
on human experiments with xe n o t r a n s-
p l a n t at i o n , which doctors describe as cli-
nical tri a l s.This doesn’t mean that they are
giving up on the research, h owe ve r.W h at is
happening is that most We s t e rn gove rn-
ments are setting up special advisory or
regulatory bodies to review any future cli-
nical trials and prepare strict guidelines for
monitoring them.
The U.S.and Britain, who are the lea-
ders in xeno-research,are currently finali-
zing guidelines to monitor not just the
p at i e n t s , but their fa m i l y - m e m b e rs and
h e a l t h - wo r k e rs.While the authorities refuse
to release the details, it has been said that
xe n o - p atients should refrain from hav i n g
c h i l d r e n ,m a rrying or even travelling inter-
nationally.This sounds like a replay of dis-
cussions concerning people infected with
HIV, says Prof Bartha Maria Knoppers, a
Canadian bioethicist regularly called on by
OECD to examine the ethics of xe n o -
r e s e a r c h . Close monitoring of pat i e n t s
should not mean trampling on their human
ri g h t s , K n o p p e rs believe s. “ B e s i d e s ,” s h e
s ay s , “are we really going to be able to
enforce these conditions?”Would it be pos-
s i b l e , for example, to take legal steps to pre-
vent a patient from deciding to have a child
two years after a clinical trial? 
Assessing the risk
of viral infections
The sponsors of these tri a l s — m o s t l y
biotech companies—will also come under
the microscope. O r d i n a ri l y, proposals to
test new medical procedures or treat m e n t s
on humans are considered commercial
secrets which are restricted to the company
i nvo l ved and the relevant gove rn m e n t a l
r e g u l at o ry body, e . g . the U. S . Food and
Drug Administration (FDA) which is res-
ponsible for approving tests on humans for
new medical drugs or procedures. This is
not so with xe n o t r a n s p l a n t at i o n , h owe ve r.
In the United Stat e s , a special advisory
committee composed of some 15 scientific
e x p e rts will openly review all requests to
test animal organs in people before the FDA
r e n d e rs a decision.
“Absence of evidence is not absence of
ri s k ,” s ays Phil Noguchi, director of the
FDA’s division of cellular and gene thera-
pies. For example, two years ago bio-tech
companies proudly insisted that their pigs
were germ - f r e e . But when news of the
P E RV retrov i ruses came out, Noguchi say s ,
the companies suddenly “ worked a lot har-
d e r ” to examine the ri s k s. Noguchi also
maintains that viral infections are difficult
to evaluate. “They may not happen often
enough to be a publishable event,” he says.
“But in a clinical experiment one tenth of a
sixth of a chance of infection is a whole lot.”
This is why the FDA is counting on help
from the advisory committee to look in all
the “nooks and crannies” where a viru s
might hide. “ We ’re still in a ve ry diffic u l t
position because to a large extent we rely on
i n d u s t ry to provide the proof that a clinical
e x p e riment is safe,” Noguchi notes. “ B u t
we also depend on our own scientists.”
For Noguchi, the advisory body also
scores extra points by offering a “ p u b l i c
f o ru m ” to discuss the ethical issues—from
animal we l fare concerns to deciding who
should receive an animal organ. F i rs t ,c o m-
panies might focus on patients with the
gr e atest chances of surviving instead of
those most in need of a transplant. S e c o n d ,
it will take ye a rs—if ever—before pig
organs are effective . For a patient on the
verge of death a pig organ could buy a few
extra weeks until a human organ becomes
ava i l a b l e . Should such patients receive
p ri o rity on the waiting list? There is a third
major concern , s ays John Davies of the
U. S . N ational Kidney Fo u n d at i o n , t h e
wo r l d ’s largest non-profit charity for kid-
ney pat i e n t s. “ We don’t want people to
stop donating the organs of their love d
ones [for human transplants] after the firs t
animal transplant tri a l s ,” s ays Dav i e s ,
“because they think the problem has been
r e s o l ve d .” While Davies supports xe n o -
r e s e a r c h , he is not convinced that it will
p r ove successful.
The problem is that these discussions
take place between people with ve s t e d
interests of one kind or another.They fail to
include the largest group affected, t h e
public.“It can be argued that there should
be some sort of ‘community consent’,” s ay s
Dr A . S . Daar of Oman, who chaired the
World Health Organization’s consultation
on xe n o t r a n s p l a n t at i o n . “Is the FDA man-
d ate to protect the public enough of a prox y
for community consent?” asks Daar. “ U n t i l
the public is informed about the issues and
is discussing them, I don’t think you wo u l d
want to go ahead with clinical trials.”
Daar is looking for ways of stimulat i n g
public debate and consent by working with
an intern ational committee of “ c o n c e rn e d ”
citizens—mostly scientists and bioethicists
brought together by the prestigious Has-
tings Center, a bioethics think-tank in New
Yo r k .The aim is to help countries to deve l o p
n ational but non-gove rnmental committees
of individuals from va rious walks of life—
e c o n o m i c s , l aw, r e l i gi o n , the media, e t c. —
who will take time to become inform e d
about xe n o t r a n s p l a n t ation but don’t them-
s e l ves have any vested interests in the mat-
t e r.These committees would hold “ c o n s e n-
sus conferences”—what A m e ricans call
“ t ownhall meetings”—to spread inform a-
tion about xe n o t r a n s p l a n t ation and gauge
the public’s response to it.
This idea is the brainchild of Fritz Bach,
a scientist at Harvard Medical School who
first called for a legal morat o rium on clini-
cal trials in the U. S . Bach is often port r aye d
as a virulent opponent of xe n o t r a n s p l a n t a-
tion and yet he is a leading scientist in the
field as well as a paid consultant for Nova r-
t i s. His corp o r ate sponsor isn’t thrilled by
his idea of townhall meetings. “ You cannot
go forward by publicly discussing such com-
p l i c ated subjects,” s ays Imutran/Nova rt i s ’s
Dr Sav i l l .“ N ow, whether gove rnments have
set up the right agencies is another ques-
t i o n . Like anything else in society, are the
right people in the right place making the
decisions? And does the public have confi-
dence in them?”
Bach isn’t convinced. “Some insiders
think this [moratorium and public consul-
t ation] would be a good thing for Nova rt i s ,”
he say s. “Just look at the tremendous 
hullabaloo over genetically modified orga-
n i s m s. If a blue ribbon committee—without
a ny connections to Monsanto—had
informed the public that they thought the
[GM] food was safe on the shelve s , we
wo u l d n ’t have had this reaction.The scari e s t
thing is always the unknown.” ■
The problem is that discussions
ta ke place between people
with vested interests of 
one kind or another. They fail
to include the largest group
affected, the public.
+ …
● To find out more or to express your views
on ethical and policy issues related 
to xenotransplantation, contact the
electronic discussion group set up by the
World Health Organization and Health
Canada:
www.oecd.org/dsti/sti/s_t/biotech/xenosite
/country.htm
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
COMPU T ERS
REBUIL D
T HE PAS T
◗ Sophie Boukhari
Three-dimensional imaging is increasingly used to recapture the appearance of ancient sites 
and legendary figures. But not everybody is happy about seeing the past through 3-D specta c l e s
■
“Come back from the land of the
dead!” is the startling exhortation
made at the beginning of a new tele-
vision film about Ramses II using digital-
ly-engineered images. The film, not yet
c o m p l e t e , b rings history ’s best-know n
pharaoh back to life from among his fel-
low mummies.
In one sequence, Ramses is puzzled
when he finds that his temple of A bu Simbel
no longer stands on the site where he built it.
It was moved by UN E S C O in the 1960s to
s ave it from flooding caused by constru c-
tion of the A swan Dam. But he goes inside
it when asked to do so by the god A m o n .
To d ay, the images engr aved on the inner
walls of the temple have lost their ori gi n a l
c o l o u ri n g, but they appear in the film in all
their former splendour.Thanks to French
archaeologist Cécile Breton,their brilliant
colours have been digitally restored.
“I worked from traces of colouring left on
the wa l l s ,” she say s.“Egyptian art was highly
c o d i fie d .We know a certain god’s crown should
be red and his hat should be blue, and that
I s i s ’s robe is either red or gr e e n . In the lat t e r
case we solve the problem by looking at other
temples where the colours have n ’t disappea-
red and choosing the more likely colour.”
Portraits in the round
The fil m ,which is scheduled to be show n
in September 2000, continues with an
account by Michel Eve n o t , an official of the
Pa ris Court of Appeal who for ye a rs compiled
identikit portraits for legal use. E ve n o t ,w h o
died in July 1999, was pleased to be invo l ve d
in the first attempt to make a three-dimen-
sional reconstitution from a mummy.
“ We were used to producing full-fa c e
and profile pictures,” he say s , which in two
dimensions (2-D), cannot be 100 per cent
c o m p at i b l e .F u rther research had to be done
so that the two images were perfectly consis-
t e n t . In 3-D, no “ c h e at i n g ” is possible.T h e r e
is no room for approx i m ations in digi t a l
models constructed from real dat a .
The Ramses II fil m , which is expected to
cost around $1.5 million, is a spectacular
example of the extraordinary potential of
new imaging technology for presenting the
wo r l d ’s cultural and monumental heri t a g e .
Initially developed for use in industry,
d i gi t i z ation and animation techniques can
be used to recreate the appearance of fa m o u s
h i s t o rical figures and sites that have cru m-
bled away or disappeared beneath the wave s.
They also make for more effective restora-
tion of fragile or badly damaged art wo r k s
and provide useful tools for archaeologi s t s
and curat o rs of museums and sites.
“These technologies can be used in two
ways with heri t a g e ,” s ays Benoît Coignard,
a French “ i n f o - s c u l p t o r ” .“ You can recons-
titute and preserve the shape of something
and use it scientifically in va rious way s ,a n d
you can recreate a world and an env i r o n m e n t
for people to marvel at .”
E x p e ri m e n t ation in 3-D imaging has pro-
l i f e r ated since the late 1980s. M a ny places,
from Egyptian heritage sites to ancient Indian
villages in Ohio, p r e h i s t o ric grottoes and
j e wels of A n t i q u i t y, h ave been made into 3-
D models for use in fil m s , on the Internet or
on interactive CD-Roms.The user can move
around freely, whether just taking a casual
look or carefully scrutinizing the image from
e ve ry angle. Specialists note that the tech-
nique is only in its infa n cy.
“There are still only a few centres where
this kind of work is underway at a sophisti-
c ated leve l ,” s ays John Hancock,of the Cen-
ter for the Electronic Reconstruction of His-
t o rical and A r c h a e o l o gical Sites, at the
U n i ve rsity of Cincinnati (U. S . ) .“ H a r d l y
a nyone is pursuing the level of architectural
and visual detail that is really required to
b ring ancient worlds to life.”
The obstacles are financial as well as
t e c h n i c a l . Synthesis imagi n g, which has
made tremendous progress in the past
d e c a d e , still cannot produce total realism.
H e ritage experts and engi n e e rs also some-
times have trouble understanding each other
and working together.The equipment is still
ve ry expensive ,e ven though prices are stea-
dily fa l l i n g .A 3-D scanner costs more than
$ 1 5 0 , 0 0 0 , and making a computer model
of a two-metre-high statue costs about
$ 3 0 , 0 0 0 .This is not counting the cost of
r e s e a r c h , which makes the bill even bigger.
“If you want to work scientific a l l y,” s ays Bre-
t o n , “it can take a week of research to pin
d own the exact position of a door or a detail
of a piece of clothing.”
U n i ve rsity projects are funded by
g ove rnments or philanthropists. M a ny firm s
h ave become invo l ved as a way of testing
their new technology and getting publicity
for themselve s. Television stations and
museums also invest in producing educa-
tional or entertainment programmes and
along the way pay for archaeologi c a l
r e s e a r c h . But ove r a l l ,s ays Richard Lapointe
of Quebec’s Laval Unive rs i t y, these tech-
n o l o gi e s , under-used because they are so
e x p e n s i ve , are far from being generally ava i-◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
“Archaeologists spend their
time dealing with uncertainty
and think that when you
don’t know something, you
have to leave dotted lines in
the drawings. But 3-D images
force you to come down off
the fence.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
tion of new know l e d g e . At a prehistoric site
in the Ohio Valley, “the surrounding land-
scape context was restored to its original
condition in order to test astronomical ali-
g n m e n t s ,” s ays Hancock. In Greece,
a d vanced equipment belonging to Fran-
c e ’s stat e - owned utility Electricité de France
and designed for testing nuclear power sta-
tions,produced a far clearer impression of
the tholos (circular temple) at Delphi.
With the increasing threats to world heri-
tage from wa rs , p o l l u t i o n , urban expansion
and theft, back-up digital images of monu-
ments and objects could be extremely useful.
In A f g h a n i s t a n , for example, where the sta-
tues of Buddha in the Bamyan Valley have
been looted by the Ta l i b a n , Coignard say s
such imaging would have enabled the shape
of these remarkable objects to be recorded so
they could be reproduced in the future. B u t
the cost of such work is currently so prohi-
b i t i ve that only a few projects are underway.
One of them, the ECHO project run by the
U n i ve rsity of California at Berkeley (U. S . )
and sponsored by a group of big compa-
n i e s , seeks to record the shape of about 100
endangered Egyptian monuments.
These virtual clones can be used in res-
t o r ation wo r k . H e r e , the German city of
Dresden has played a pioneering role.A f t e r
G e rman reunific at i o n , the gove rnment deci-
ded to rebuild this “Florence on the Elba”
which had been bombed by the Allies in the
Second World Wa r.The city began by orde-
ring a computer model of one of Dresden’s
architectural jewe l s , the Church of Our Lady
(the Frauenkirche), an 18th-century church
which had been reduced to ru b b l e .
“When I presented the synthesized images
for the first time in 1993, there was an extra-
o r d i n a ry silence,” r e m e m b e rs Luc Génévri e z ,
who made them. “ People were we e p i n g .”
The virtual reconstitution, which drew on a
mass of historical documents and photo-
gr a p h s , was used as a guide in the real-life
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 41
l a b l e . “The world powe rs in heri t a g e ,
archaeology and technology are Europe,
N o rth A m e ri c a , Japan and A u s t r a l i a ,” h e
says. In these rich parts of the wo r l d ,
the new imaging technologies are start i n g
to be added to the archaeologi s t ’s toolkit.
They make it possible to “ d o c u m e n t ”
objects without touching or spoiling them,
says Philippe Martinez,an Egyptologist at
the French National Centre for Scientific
Research (CNRS).
In 1993, for example, a “ v i rt u a l ”
archaeological investigation reconstituted
the cargo scattered around an inaccessible
wreck that has been lying in more than 660
metres of water since the first century AD.
Three sets of photos were taken from a
s u b m a rine that glided over the site. T h e
pictures were then processed by a com-
puter to make a digital 3-D model.
In T h a i l a n d , the ancient capital of the
kingdom of Siam,Ay u t t h aya , has been “ r e a s-
s e m b l e d ” on a CD-Rom from vestiges scat-
tered around the modern city.The church of
C l u ny in France was once the biggest edific e
of medieval Chri s t i a n i t y. Little is left of it
t o d ay, but its appearance has been reconsti-
tuted thanks to  synthesized images.
Using 3-D scanners and digital cameras,
a r c h a e o l o gists report they can build models
from drawings with unprecedented accu-
r a cy.These models can help them to refin e
their interpretation of historical evidence.
“Hypotheses can be inve s t i g ated and tested
in new ways,” says Hancock.
“ We wo n ’t be able to say what ’s tru e , bu t
we’ll be able to say what isn’t true,” says
Martinez.“In 2-D, if part of the structure
gets in the way, you pick a new angle where
it doesn’t show and you get round the pro-
b l e m . In 3-D, e ve ry part has to fit perfectly
with the others.”
C o m p u t e rized simulation of archaeo-
logical hypotheses has often led to the dis-
proval of theories and even to the acquisi-
r e c o n s t ruction of the church,which should be
complete in 2003.The computer model wa s
also used in a televised appeal to Germans that
raised money for the project.
The advantages of imaging in heritage
restoration have also been seen in Alexan-
d ri a , in Egypt. Coignard tells how he recons-
tituted the city’s colossus in 1998 using
huge blocks of stone fished out of the sea.
“ We carried out a virtual reconstru c t i o n
by digitizing bits of the sculpture with a 3-
D scanner, m oving them around the screen
to see if they fitted together and then simu-
lating the reassembly of the whole statue.”
Since the head of the statue weighs three
t o n n e s , the arms several hundred kg and
the entire colossus about 20 tonnes, n o t
h aving to bother about weight was a gr e at
a d va n t a g e . “The best thing,” s ays Coignard,
“ was being able to test the equilibrium of the
s t at u e .With the colossus, whose fragments
were ve ry wo rn , we managed to come up
with a stable structure and a base which
fitted perfectly and in theory enabled the
s t atue to resist even eart h q u a k e s.”
The new virtual images have “ e n o rm o u s
p o t e n t i a l ” for visitors to museums, s ays Cliff
O g l e b y, of Melbourne Unive rs i t y, in A u s-
t r a l i a . More and more museums are instal-
ling multimedia facilities and commissio-
ning interactive products which both educat e
and entertain visitors.They can also display
and sell them on their we b s i t e s.
The museum next to the site of the huge
Roman amphitheatre at El Djem, in Tu n i s i a ,
t o d ay echoes as of old to the sound of gla-
d i at o rial combat . In France, the inaccessible
u n d e r water prehistoric site of the Cosquer
Grotto has been turned into a film of digi t a l
images which will be presented at the Mar-
seilles Museum in A p ril 2000. In many
p l a c e s ,major exhibitions of world heritage are
e n riched by interactive features that help
fund the museums where they are held.
Like television and the film industry,
Computer imaging recreates the face of pharaoh Ramses II (right) from his mummified body (left).
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
“video games make wide use of 3-D model-
ling of heritage sites to flesh out their adve n-
t u r e s ,” s ays Lapointe. “This is the i n f o rm a-
tion age and archaeology is being populari z e d
w h e r e ver there’s money to be made.”
Some historians and archaeologists are
u n c o m f o rtable with this mingling of 
different wo r l d s. G é n é v riez recalls the fuss
the scientific community made in the early
1990s when he was asked, as part of IBM’s
c o m m u n i c ation policy, to make synthesis
images of the Cluny church and the
Roman baths in Pa ri s.
Beware of bogus images
“There were tremendous battles among
the experts over the site, to the point where I
had to work out my own ideas about it and
finish the job by my s e l f.The resulting fil m
s t i rred up a dreadful row. I was accused of
h aving distorted ‘the tru t h ’ e ven though
nobody knew what the truth wa s. S c i e n t i s t s
are scared of pictures.” O f t e n , he say s ,n e w
technology upsets them because it makes
them question their practices and fa m i l i a r
ideas and forces them to make choices.
“ A r c h a e o l o gists spend their time dealing with
u n c e rtainty and think that when you don’t
k n ow something, you have to leave dotted
lines in the draw i n g s ,” s ays Breton.“But 3-D
images force you to come down off the fence.”
A lot of “bogus images”made from unre-
liable mat e rial are in circulat i o n , s ays Mar-
t i n e z .A r c h a e o l o gists also resent the fact that
people make no distinction between images
based on a massive amount of scientific wo r k
and images in video games.”From this pers-
p e c t i ve , the dangers of the virtual world are
r e a l . The general public is presented with
reconstitutions of ancient sites but has neither
the means nor the desire to question their
s c i e n t i fic quality now that technology can
produce images almost as good as photo-
gr a p h s.
But despite these reservat i o n s , more and
more scientists, especially in the English-spea-
king countri e s , are moving into 3-D model-
l i n g .“ A ny means of representation invo l ve s
c o n j e c t u r e s ,d i s t o rtions and the possibility of
m i s r e a d i n g s ,” admits Hancock. But these
d r awbacks are outwe i g h e d ,he believe s ,by the
a d vantages of increasing public awareness of
world heritage and the importance of pro-
tecting it. ■
In 1945, the church of Our Lady in Dresden (Germany) was reduced to rubble by bombing (top). 
The edifice is now being rebuilt (middle photo). To help the builders, the city authorities commissioned 
a virtual reconstruction of the monument (above).
+ …
● Website of the International Festival of
Multimedia in Archaeology, Archeovirtua:
perso.cybercable.fr/platypus/inscrit.html
Other websites:
● www.cdv.berkeley.edu/ECHO/
● www.learningsites.com
● www.cerhas.uc.edu
● www.sli.unimelb.edu.au
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
■
C h ristopher Senono used to travel by
b i cycle 16 kilometres each way to
make a telephone call. A 30-ye a r - o l d
businessman from Nakaseke, U g a n d a ,h e
managed his small lumber and brick retail
trade by talking on the phone with suppliers
in Kampala.The trip seemed natural in a
country where the “teledensity” is roughly
three phone lines per 1,000 inhabitants. N o t
a ny more! Life in this village 60 km from
Kampala has changed since the opening of
a multipurpose community telecentre
(MCT) in 1999.
F i rst launched in 1985 in the fa rm i n g
community of Velmdalen (Swe d e n ) , t e l e-
centres aim to introduce new inform at i o n
and communication technologies to isola-
ted areas and provide people with the skills
to benefit from them.After spreading throu-
ghout rural areas of the Nort h , they are now
cropping up in A f ri c a , L atin A m e rica and
A s i a , often with support from intern at i o n a l
d e velopment agencies. It is likely that at least
s e veral hundred new centres are being star-
ted up each ye a r. In countries where indi-
vidual ow n e rship of inform ation and com-
munications is out of most people’s reach,
these telecentres may become the primary
way of allowing vast numbers to part i c i p at e
in the inform ation economy, p r ovided a few
basic conditions are met.
The first step is often to demonstrat e
h ow the equipment and facilities ava i l a b l e
in a telecentre can be made to work for the
communities where they are locat e d .
S e c o n d , time must be spent helping local
fa rm e rs ,t e a c h e rs or entrepreneurs unders-
tand the value of inform ation and the tools
t h at can be used to access it.T h i r d l y, s t a f f
T EL ECEN T RES SH A RE 
T HE TOOLS 
OF THE INF ORM AT ION AGE
◗ Richard Fuchs
Telecentres offer a promising route for rural communities of the developing world 
to break out of their isolation
◗ Sociologist, president of Future Works Inc, 
based in the Canadian rural community of To r b a y ,
N ewfoundland (www. f u t u r ew o r k s . ca). 
The author was involved in establishing North America ’ s
first rural telecentres and has assisted with telecentre
startups in Africa and Indonesia.
must have the training and skills to keep
abreast of developments in softwa r e ,h a r d-
ware and networking technology.The most
e f ficient way to do this is to ensure that they
h ave a forum within which to meet, b o t h
v i rtually and humanly, so that links are crea-
ted among them. F i n a l l y, once the telecentre
is up and ru n n i n g, its staff must court the
community at large and introduce its mem-
b e rs to basic computer skills and identify
ways in which they might benefit from the
facilities and services.
Identifying and training local champions
who will nurture a telecentre project can
make or break the success of such a serv i c e .
It is especially important to have local sta-
k e h o l d e rs from health clinics, m u n i c i p a l i-
t i e s , e l e m e n t a ry schools and teacher trai-
ning colleges looking over your shoulder.
They are the people who are most likely to
become the core users who will diffuse the
t e c h n o l o gies widely. In Uganda, a candi-
d ate in a local election in the Nakaseke dis-
t rict turned the telecentre into a local cam-
paign issue, going as far as to promise people
who supported him a free trip to visit a
European or North A m e rican telecentre.
Without necessarily going to these ends,
g e n e r ating community interest in the ear-
liest stages of planning is a long-term asset.
O f t e n , in developing regi o n s ,c o m m u n i t i e s
are invo l ved by providing rent-free fa c i l i t i e s
to accommodate a telecentre or by bu i l d i n g
new ones.
It takes between $50,000 and $75,000 to
s t a rt a standard telecentre,although the early
p l a n n i n g, organizing and mobilization wo r k
can significantly increase the price tag (the
budgets of several current projects run from
$450,000 to $850,000). Annual operat i n g
costs are much less and generally include two
or three staff people.There are different pat h s
to sustainability: telecentres sometimes
become an integral part of a hospital serv i c e ,
a school or a municipality after three to five
ye a rs.A l t e rn at i ve l y, they can sustain them-
s e l ves by offering such profitable services as
t e l e p h o n e , fa x ,p h o t o c o p y i n g, résumé wri-
t i n g, training in desktop publishing and wo r d-
p r o c e s s i n g .And if they don’t manage all of
t h i s , telecentres at least have the benefit of lea-
ving behind a new corps of locally trained and
skilled people.
As intern ational development agencies
increasingly come to recognize the corr e l a-
tion between the adoption of inform at i o n
and communications technologies (ICTs)
and economic deve l o p m e n t , we need to
u n d e rstand that a social investment is requi-
red for the services available in a telecentre
to take root and offer benefits in the deve l o-
ping wo r l d .We should see telecentres as a
social investment which can help build a
future in the inform ation economy that is
i n t e r a c t i ve , not extractive . At the telecentre
in Nakaseke and in many other communi-
ties in the developing wo r l d , there are increa-
sing numbers of people who are committed
to making sure this happens. ■
As international development
agencies increasingly come 
to recognize the correlation
between the adoption 
of information and
communications technologies
(ICTs) and economic
development, we need 
to understand that a social
investment is required 
for the services available in 
a telecentre to take root 
and offer benefits 
in the developing world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
C O N N E X I O N S
■
“Internet! Internet!” A street urchin
rushes towards a journalist who has
just arri ved in T i m buktu (Mali).
“Look what a French reporter gave me,”
he boasts in front of his chums, showing
an e-mail address scrawled on a little
notepad. “I’m going to the MCT1 this
afternoon to write to him.”
Since its MCT (Multipurp o s e
Community Telecentre) opened in May
1998,Timbuktu (30,000 inhabitants) has
felt less of a prisoner of the Sahara desert.
Along with traditional local hangouts,
where the menfolk gather in the evenings
to gossip, the MCT has become the tren-
diest place in town.
Men in traditional dress, women and
inquisitive youngsters regularly crowd in
the doorway of the temporary premises in
an annex of the town hall.“They all come
to look,” says Birama Diallo, the centre’s
energetic coordinator, with a laugh.
Electronic advice
Like most people in Timbuktu, the
mayor,Ibrahim Mohamed,sees the MCT
first as a source of the kind of knowledge
needed to revive the region’s stagnant
social and economic life.The most encou-
r a ging MCT-based projects are being
drawn up in the fields of medicine, tea-
ching, the media, culture, agriculture and
tourism.
“A group of doctors has been trained
to look for information on the Web,” says
Canadian France Henri , a UN E S C O
consultant. “They’ve already found some
terrific pages about gynaecological pro-
blems. They printed them out, photoco-
pied them and handed them out at the
hospital.They’d also like to be able to get
‘electronic advice’ from their colleagues
in Bamako [Mali’s capital] and elsewhe-
re.”
“The most urgent thing for us is to
find out about other people’s expe-
riences,” adds a teacher. “Some countries
have the same problems as we do, for
e x a m p l e , in getting girls enrolled in
school.2 We’d like to know what solutions
they’ve found.” He suggests material from
the Internet could be used to produce
some good school textbooks, which are
few and far between.
The Net could also be useful to the
four local radio stations, says Diallo. “For
example, they could use it to find out how
to make best use of the new varieties of
floating rice that were recently introduced
into the region and put that information
out in their farming programmes.”
The regional director for cultural
affairs wants to commission the MCT to
create some web pages about the history
and heritage of Timbuktu. The tourist
sector, still in its infancy, wants to do the
same kind of thing to attract visitors.
Through its website,not yet complete,the
MCT presents an attractive view of “the
town of 333 saints.”
The townspeople do not want to be
just consumers of ideas and pictures, says
Diallo. “They’re also very keen to make
themselves known.” He recalls that in the
Middle Ages, “Holy Timbuktu” was a
beacon throughout West Africa and the
Islamic wo r l d . It had 180 madrasahs
(Koranic schools) and the renow n e d
Sankore University, which was attended
by up to 25,000 students. The mosques
and tens of thousands of ancient manus-
cripts, preserved by families and by the
Ahmed Baba cultural centre,are evidence
of this intense intellectual activity.
But beyond this mat e rial heri t a g e ,
Timbuktu is banking on its intangible
attraction as a place to escape from the
world, on the aura of the unknown and
the inaccessible that it conjures up in
Western minds. “Our asset is our name,”
s ays Mayor Mohamed. “The wo r d
Timbuktu says something to everybody,
even people who don’t know where Mali
is,” adds Culture and Tourism Minister
Aminata Traoré. “These days, people in
the West have a great urge to get away
T IMBUKTU ONL INE
◗ Sophie Boukhari
A historic city on the edge of the Sahara is banking on an Internet connection 
to revitalize its economic life 
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
1.The French term, which is actually used in
Timbuktu,is TCP = Télécentre Communautaire
Polyvalent. 2 The proportion of girls attending school in Mali
is very low (41 per cent) and particularly low in
the Timbuktu area (23.7 per cent).
Timbuktu’s telecentre has attracted more than 2,000 visitors since it was opened in May 1998.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
from it all.Timbuktu hasn’t got much to
sell, but it can sell dreams.”
The way the MCT works is simple.To
raise money for community deve l o p m e n t
p r o j e c t s , it sells a range of serv i c e s , such as
t e l e c o m m u n i c ations (public phones, fa x ,
e-mail and Internet access), the produc-
tion of databases and web pages, d i gi t i z i n g
text and wo r d - p r o c e s s i n g . It charges less
than a dollar (U.S.) to send an e-mail and
$2.50 to surf the Web for an hour.
The centre also runs courses, inclu-
ding an introduction to the Internet and
new technologies, how to find informa-
tion online, and library science.“Students
and other people come to us because uni-
versities in Mali don’t offer proper com-
puter training,” says Diallo. “If they want
to get a job in Bamako, they have to know
something about computers.”
In a country with fewer than 2,000
people connected to the Internet among a
population of more than 10 million, the
MCT is the only “decentralized” server
and the only one that is publicly owned.
The five others are private and based in
Bamako. For the moment, MCT’s capaci-
ty only allows 20 subscribers (so far, 17
have signed up, at a monthly fee of $28).
“The quality of the phone line to the
Internet connection node in Bamako is
also poor,” says Diallo. “If 30 people go
online at the same time then the line is
saturated,” admits Zourkoufili Maïga, the
regional director of the state telecommu-
nications company, Sotelma. “And since
the telephone arrived in rural areas in
1999, this has often happened.”
Diallo is waiting impatiently for the
arrival of a VSAT (Very Small Aperture
Terminal), promised by the International
Telecommunication Union, to improve
the situation.The VSAT, a small satellite
antenna, will mean the MCT will no lon-
ger need to use terrestrial phone lines.
The centre cost about $850,000 to set
up, half of which was provided by inter-
national funding agencies.3 It employs six
people and has 11 computers, but will get
several dozen more machines when it
moves into permanent premises, which
are near completion and being paid for by
the townspeople. To raise the $50,000
start-up costs, the town authorities have
staged a number of events, including a
gala of the T i m buktu Residents and
Friends Association and a cultural week,
and also appealed to local people to
contribute. In 1999, an airport tax for
tourists was introduced, with all the pro-
ceeds going to help pay for the building
work.
Despite technical problems, the MCT
seems to have impressed the tow n s-
people. “Since it opened, people have
started buying computers,” says Diallo.
So fa r , about 2,000 have visited the
c e n t r e , and members of professional
organizations and NGOs, tourists, guides,
librarians,secretaries,students and others
have come looking for information or to
buy one of the services on offer.
But the future is not yet secure. If the
centre is to survive, it will have to be self-
financing by 2001, when outside funding
ends. Financial independence is especial-
ly important because the main national
body behind the project,Sotelma,is being
privatized.
“ We can make it if we have 200
I n t e rnet subscri b e rs ,” s ays Diallo.This is a
lot for the nort h e rn region of the country,
which has only 570 telephone subscri b e rs
(400 in T i m buktu and 170 in rural areas)
and an illiteracy rate of over 80 per cent.
But Diallo is counting on better quality
s e rv i c e , especially when the V S AT arri ve s ,
to win customers outside the regi o n .
From the Sahara
to cyberspace
“The private Internet providers are
complaining about unfair competition,”
he admits, “but what are they doing to
develop their own services and to set up
cybercafés outside the capital?” He says
only a public service can take the first
steps to allow people in the countryside
access to cyberspace. It costs five to 10
times more to install a phone in a rural
area than in a town.
“ To safeguard the future of the MCT,
i t ’s not enough to ensure its commercial
s u c c e s s ,” s ays Henri , the UN E S C O c o n s u l-
t a n t .“The money earned must keep on fun-
ding community development projects.”
For these people on the sidelines of
the global village, the centre is not just a
fancy telecommunications shop. It gives
hope of a new world. “The Internet isn’t
a luxury of the rich,” says Mohamed.“On
the contrary, it’s really for the poor, who
have very little access to information.” On
the edge of the Sahara, books are few and
expensive, and half the population has
never seen television. ■
3 Mainly the International Development Research
Centre, the International Telecommunication
Union, UNESCO, the UN Food and Agriculture
Organization and the World Health Organization.
Timbuktu’s telecentre sells a range of telecommunications and word processing services.
W EBSITE 
OF THE MON T H
h t t p : / / w w w. w o r l d w a t e r f o r u m . o r g
T he sca r c i ty of freshwater is one of today’s
most pressing issues. The equation is alar-
m i n g — 20 per cent more water is needed than is
available to feed the additional 3 billion people
expected to be living on the earth by 20 25! Addres-
sing this problem is the World Water Forum which
convenes in The Hague this month, the culmina-
tion of a two-year process bringing together thou-
sands of specialists, decision-makers and
concerned citizens. They will unveil a World Wa t e r
V i s i o n — s p e c i fic actions to achieve a common set of
goals ensuring everyone’s access to clean water.
The forum will serve as the launching pad for a new
set of strategies and activities to create mass public
awareness and generate political commitment
with a view to making that vision a reality. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
T A L K I N G  T O …
s t r ategy to cope with the number of people
m oving in from the country s i d e . T h e s e
people are looking to improve their econo-
mic opportunities but they can’t afford for-
mal housing.
Doesn’t the solution lie in building and
subsidizing more public housing?
The public service is a bu r e a u c r a cy which
cannot cope with this type of problem. I n
e ve ry city, the authori t i e s ’ first approach is
the same: t ry building more formal housing
to replace informal settlements. But they
n e ver succeed because they will only deve-
lop areas that conform to certain standards of
i n f r a s t ru c t u r e , p l a n n i n g and housing
c o n s t ru c t i o n . Instead of considering the
a l t e rn at i ve s , these bureaucracies plod along,
building too few houses too slow l y — h o u s e s
which are too expensive for the people they
were intended for.These standards actually
d i ve rt gove rnment from the real problem,
which is assisting the urban poor. Look at
w h at happened in Brazil. Despite all the
good intentions,public housing was taken
over by the middle class and never reached
the poor.
Most city authorities find informal settlements
in such deplorable states that they feel they
Shantytowns, squatters’ communities, 
slums—these are some of the names used 
to describe informal settlements. How many
people in the world call them home?
B e t ween 40 per cent and 50 per cent of
the population in the cities of the South are
living in these settlements—that ’s roughly
one billion people.The rate at which the
settlements are gr owing va ries from regi o n
to regi o n . In most of Latin A m e ri c a , t h e
gr owth rate has peaked, but it’s still increa-
sing in Asia and sub-Saharan A f ri c a . In my
own city, Cape Tow n ,i n f o rmal settlements
are gr owing at about 10 per cent per ye a r —
but you must remember that South A f ri c a ’s
s t a rting point is relat i vely low. I n f o rmal sett-
lements were rarely allowed to deve l o p
under apartheid.
What are the main characteristics of informal
settlements? 
F i rs t , the people don’t generally have
a ny legal tenure to the land they occupy.
S e c o n d , the settlements lie outside the for-
mal planning process. As a result, t h e y
usually lack or have ve ry low levels of basic
s e rvices like water and sanitat i o n .A n d , o f
c o u rs e , the dwellings are informal in the
sense that they are built by the people them-
s e l ves out of basic mat e rials in a ve ry simple
manner.
Why are these settlements growing? 
Is it because formal housing projects are 
too expensive? 
The problem encompasses fin a n c i n g
and the availability of land. Land is a com-
modity available to the rich and the middle
class but not to the poor. On the one hand,
you have pri vate landow n e rs who want to
get the highest return from their land—and
dealing with ve ry poor people is generally
not perceived as bri n ging good fin a n c i a l
r e t u rn s. On the other, m a ny cities still have
a lot of public land. But city authorities in
the South have neither resources nor 
JOHN ABBOTT, 
SOUTH AFRICA’S 
CI TY STITCHER
Squatter settlements are ‘home’ to around a billion people in and around Third World cities. 
The authorities usually want to bulldoze them. South African urban engineer John Abbott
thinks they should be upgraded and woven into the urban fabric
must start from scratch, destroy the old shacks
and rebuild new homes. Why are so you
adamantly opposed to this?
F i rs t , because it destroys a physical asset.
Yo u ’re not building new shelter; yo u ’re sim-
ply replacing existing shelter. So you aren’t
adding to the overall stock of housing. I n s-
tead of a financial benefit , there is a major
financial loss. Yo u ’re also creating an
immense social cost by destroying all the
social networks and mechanisms which
people have built to surv i ve in these infor-
mal settlements.T h i r d , you never end up
r e l o d ging eve ry fa m i l y. Some are bound to
be uprooted and left with no place to go
except another informal settlement.T h at ’s
been proven over and over again.
But isn’t it better to offer people a proper
house than leave them in a slum?
Let’s turn the question round. Is it
better to house 10 per cent of the popula-
tion and leave the rest in slum conditions
or is it better to work with 100 per cent 
of the population so that they slowly
improve their own condition?
You often refer to the social networks 
of informal settlements as “social capital”.
What do you mean by this?
I t ’s something of a paradox . On the one
h a n d , these settlements can be ve ry dange-
rous places. In Rio de Ja n e i r o, for example,
it is felt that drug dealers use the inform a l
settlements as a base because the police can-
not access or monitor them easily. It is also
t rue that people in informal settlements suf-
fer more from serious crime than people in
higher income areas. But this tends to draw
them closer together.You cannot put a dol-
lar figure on these social netwo r k s , but this
social capital is extremely va l u a b l e .S u rv i va l
is based on interdependence.You don’t have
the resources in an informal settlement to
o p e r ate as an individual. If you want to go
out and sell food informally at the market,
If you want to go out 
and sell food informally 
at the market, who is going 
to look after your children?
If you don’t get paid 
on a regular basis, 
how do you live from month
to month? 
If you get sick, who is going 
to help you?
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
March 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G  T O …
who is going to look after your children? If
you don’t get paid on a regular basis, h ow
do you live from month to month? If you get
s i c k , who is going to help you? 
But don’t people take this capital from one
settlement to another? 
When an informal settlement is des-
t r oye d , people are generally moved in a ran-
dom fa s h i o n .They lose the linkages that
exist not just between individuals but bet-
ween gr o u p s.Ve ry often, people from cer-
tain rural areas move to particular inform a l
settlements in the cities. So when they
a rri ve , they have a lot of things in common.
They operate collective l y.When they get
m ove d , they lose those communal ties.To
make things worse, the local authorities in
the new settlements treat families as indi-
vidual units—e.g., by the design of the phy-
sical dwelling they live in and the taxes they
p ay.The whole framework of their life forces
them to behave as individuals, not collec-
tive units.
You’ve described the major faults of the top-
down approach cities usually take in dealing
with informal settlements. What are the
alternatives?
T h at depends to some extent on the
culture and the income level of the city.
There are two major approaches: the firs t
is people-based and exists in countries like
I n d i a ,S ri Lanka and Pakistan where there is
gr e at pove rt y.The most famous example is
the Orangi settlement in Karachi.T h e r e ,
the people decided that their first pri o ri t y
lay in building a sanitation system because
the municipal authority wo u l d n ’t do any-
thing about it. So they raised the money and
the manpower to lay their own sewer pipes,
with technical assistance from an NGO.T h e
pipes ran from the shacks to open ditches
on the outskirts of the settlements.This for-
ced the local authority to connect their sani-
tation system to a treatment facility.
The second approach is found in Bra-
zil where there is a more structured part-
n e rship between community organizat i o n s ,
professionals and NGOs.This kind of part-
n e rship makes it possible to look beyo n d
i m m e d i ate issues and develop a longer-
t e rm , wide-range vision for the community.
Instead of focusing on one aspect like sani-
t at i o n , you can also look at others such as
housing and access to public transport a-
t i o n .You begin by developing plans as to
where you want your settlement to be and
how you want it to grow and develop.This
generally requires external funding, e s p e-
cially for infrastru c t u r e .The two different
approaches basically reflect the different
levels of wealth in cities like Rio and Kara-
chi.
How have you gone about things 
in Cape Town?
We have developed the Brazilian model
and are working at a people-driven level to
reinforce the economic base of inform a l
s e t t l e m e n t s. But we want to do more than
just improve the physical infrastructure of
the settlements as dorm i t o ry subu r b s —
Ve ry often, people 
from certain rural areas 
move to particular informal
settlements in the cities. 
So when they arrive, 
they have a lot of things 
in common. They opera t e
c o l l e c t i v e l y. When they get
moved, they lose those
communal ties.
John Abbott (left) and two colleagues engaged on a Cape Town project to upgrade an informal settlement (see also photos on pages 48 and 49).
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
AT HOME 
IN THE SLUMS
48 The UNESCO Courier - March 2000
T A L K I N G  T O …
‘Iwas born in a very poor area in England,
which is probably why I feel very comfor-
table in informal settlements,” says John
Abbott. Co-ordinator of the University of Cape
Town’s urban management programme, he is
an urban engineer who has won an internatio-
nal reputation for improving conditions in
South Africa’s informal settlements. “Pe o p l e
come together because they need each other,”
he says, “especially in situations where 60 or 70
per cent of the population is very poor. I’m not
saying it’s only poverty [that creates this solida-
r i ty] but if you don’t have individual tra n s p o r t ,
TV and all those luxuries that draw you more
into your private world, you tend to rely on col-
lective action or entertainment for a social life
as well as for social need.”
Abbott first landed in Africa at the age of 12
when his parents moved to Uganda and Ke n y a .
He went back to England for his university stu-
dies, but soon returned to the continent, wor-
king in South Africa as a civil engineer before
switching to urban engineering.
Increasingly aware of the brutalities of apar-
theid while living in Johannesburg and then Cape
Town, in 1985 he started Planact, an NGO which
brought together civic organizations and tra d e
unions in the struggle for urban equality in South
A f r i ca and became famous throughout the coun-
t ry. 
This struggle came to a head for Abbott in
1986, when he began working with an informal
settlement near the coastal city of Po r t
Elizabeth. Parts of the sprawling settlement
“could be seen by white residents and there
was a move to get rid of it,” says Abbott.
Instead of destroying the settlement, Abbott
and Planact tried to upgrade it with the help of
civic movements and with financial support
from several big companies. But just as the
u p g rading plan was taking shape, the govern-
ment decreed a state of emergency across the
c o u n t ry, which provided “a blanket of secrecy
for the army to move in and totally destroy the
c o m m u n i ty,” says Abbott. “Every family was
bulldozed out. They moved to a tempora ry
camp, but quite a lot of people died from mal-
nourishment and disease.” 
Ve ry few people knew about the destruc-
tion, he says, because the newspapers were
banned from reporting on what was conside-
red a “military secret”. “It was one of the tra n s-
forming events of my life,” he says. From then
on, he kept one foot in the academic world of
urban management at the University of Cape
Town, but, he says, “I shifted my work increa-
singly towards informal settlements.” ■
places where people sleep but do not wo r k .
I don’t think physical restru c t u ring alone is
going to promote economic deve l o p m e n t .
You have to go to the roots of the problem.
Our ultimate aim is to integrate these sett-
lements into the fabric of the city.
At the Unive rsity of Cape Tow n ,we have
a pilot project involving over 2,500 fa m i l i e s
or about 10,000 people.We began by using
s atellite images of the settlement to deve-
lop a computer-based map which offers eve-
ryone a clear vision of the settlement—each
family can see its place in the community.
We are starting to collect demographic and
economic inform ation about their house-
h o l d s. For example, there turns out to be a
fair number of people in the house-bu i l d i n g
t r a d e . So we ’ ve introduced support schemes
to build a corps of trained wo r k e rs to
upgrade the settlement.
We ’ ve also found that about 60 per cent
of the people are in formal employment bu t
about 20 per cent work in the informal sec-
tor and 20 per cent had no visible means of
financial support .We highlighted all the
i n f o rmal businesses on the map and are
t rying to find ways of supporting them. Fo r
e x a m p l e , the community is now linked with
a number of tour operat o rs who are bri n-
ging overseas tourists into the area to spur
bu s i n e s s.We ’re also fund-raising ove rs e a s
to construct a market to sustain tourism.
Are you suggesting that there’s no point in
upgrading a settlement without an overall
development strategy? 
T h at depends on the city. In cities in
I n d i a , for example, i t ’s hard to imagine a
time on the horizon when you will have for-
mal settlements because there are just so
m a ny people and so little space. In Cape
Tow n , we still have the time to transform
i n f o rmal settlements into formal areas. I n
A f rican cities in general, it is possible to
combine long-term planning and vision with
more immediate needs.
What does it mean to transform an informal
settlement into a formal settlement? 
There has to be some sort of land secu-
ri t y. Land titles are the common but not the
only form of tenure.The issues of access,
social services and health care also have to
be dealt with. Cape Tow n , for example, p r o-
bably has the highest incidence of tubercu-
losis in the world because of flooding in win-
t e r. I n f o rmal settlements are part i c u l a r l y
hard hit by water-borne diseases.The high
i n fant mortality is also caused by living in
d a r k ,d a n k ,c o n fined spaces reeking of paraf-
fin.
So far, we’ve talked about upgrading
conditions for people already living 
in informal settlements. But how do you plan
for and manage the flow of newcomers? 
You d o n ’t b e gin by wo rrying about foo-
lishly high standards for roads, large bu i l-
ding plots and big open “public spaces”.
Instead you work on planning a basic mini-
mum which can be developed ve ry cheaply
and quickly. Local authorities can begin by
marking out building plots that use space
as economically as possible. In Brazil, t h e y
opt for multi-storied bu i l d i n g s , but here in
A f rica people prefer single-story dwe l l i n g s.
You can still plan for a density of up to 100
d wellings per hectare. Large public open
spaces aren’t necessary at this point. I n s-
tead of high-quality roads, you design access
Computerized mapping technology is used to help plan an access road to the settlement.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O …
a u t h o rities also have a constituency in the
f o rmal areas where people are frightened by
the informal settlements.There is also what
might be called a technical fear of these sett-
lements on the part of the city authori t i e s.
These are places which don’t seem to have
a ny identity or order.They don’t corr e s p o n d
to any official standards.The authorities are
f rightened and throw up their hands,s ay i n g,
“ H ow can you deal with such places?”
routes.You lay down a basic water scheme
which puts a standpipe within 100 metres
of eve ry dwe l l i n g . Then you look at the
ground conditions and the culture before
installing some basic sanitation—either pit
latrines or communal toilets.The aim is to
p r ovide the infrastructure and services that
people need and relate to. In Brazil, f o r
e x a m p l e , ground that cannot be used for
housing is used for football fields which no
one would dream of squat t i n g . In South
A f ri c a , you might make some space for a
crèche or a school, if that ’s what people
want.
Your work has met with a lot of political
resistance. Why?
F i rs t ,i n f o rmal settlements are conside-
red dangerous and undesirable places that
should be got rid of. S e c o n d , m u n i c i p a l
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 72FF ( 11 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211FF ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:                  Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
Construction workers who live in the settlement are being mobilized to improve housing conditions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O …
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George's Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Brussels. 
Fax: 538 08 41.
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
Oxford Book & Stationery Co, Code No D 820 8 0 52, Scindia House, New
Delhi 110 001. Fax: 33 22 639 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Nalanda Co. Ltd., 30 Bourbon Street, Port Louis. 
Fax: 212 1313 .
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
Los Amigos de la UNES CO, Avenida Urquijo 62, 2 Izd., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 94427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG, Wissenschaftl. Buchhandlung, Pe t e r s g raben 31, 
CH-4009 Basel. Fax: 306 12 34 .
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce
C/C Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: 286 03 26 .
A slum in Guatemala Cit y.
We responded by first of all showing that
all attempts to focus on formal housing
would not solve the informal housing pro-
blem and that this problem would continue
to gr ow no matter how much was spent on
f o rmal housing. It took a few ye a rs , but this
has finally been accepted.The next step lies
in showing that upgrading is a viable, r e p l i-
cable methodology.
You’ve described how to upgrade the informal
settlements in Cape Town. But how are you
trying to integrate them into the rest of the
city?
To begin with, we are putting the infor-
mal settlements on the map.We know where
they are so we can now create access routes
and other services to link them to the rest
of the city. Just putting these places on the
map is a major step forward.The Brazilian
city of Belo Hori z o n t e , which is in some
ways our model, has three million people,
40 per cent of whom live in informal sett-
l e m e n t s. If you look at a map of the city
dating from around 1980,a time when the
m i l i t a ry junta was leaving powe r , you wo n ’t
see a single sign of the informal settlements.
At that time maps simply showed as blank
spaces settlements where thousands of
people lived without any physical linkages
to the rest of the city.
You cannot just work locally, i n s i d e
i n f o rmal settlements. You must also 
tackle the problem at the metropolitan leve l .
You must know where the settlements are
and how they are likely to gr ow.Then yo u
can create physical linkages so that they
a r e n ’t islands of exclusion, cut off from the
c i t y. Once you have done that , you can go
to the planning level and work with people
and ask questions. H ow do you want this
area to look? How is it going to integr at e
into commercial life? These people wa n t
access to shops and work opport u n i t i e s.
How do we create those linkages?
Why is it so important to integrate a city? 
A city is a complex link between indivi-
duals and gr o u p s. Its fa b ric is built on
mutual dependency, although we tend not
to notice that ve ry much these day s. I n s e-
c u rity and crime in one area are bound to
affect other areas. We drain the city’s
resources by failing to support people who
are poor. By dividing a city between ri c h
and poor—or informal and formal areas—
you reinforce the fortress mentality and
actually limit the city’s capacity to gr ow and
develop.
I t ’s not enough to focus on people’s
s h o rt - t e rm needs.You need a long-term
vision and plan so that eve ryone can contri-
bute in some way to the city’s deve l o p m e n t .
■
Interview by René Lefort and 
Amy Otchet, respectively Director and 
journalist with the UNESCO Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
ISBN 92-3-103642-4
196 pp., 17 x 24 cm
100 FF / 15.24
U N E S C O  P u b l i s h i n g
ISBN 92-3-103559-2
265 pp., 17 x 24 cm
120 FF / 18.29 
UNESCO Publishing / 
United Nations Division for the 
Advancement of Women
Towards 
a Women’s
Agenda 
for a Culture
of Peace
Edited by Ingeborg Breines, 
Dorota Gierycz and Betty Reardon
Olives 
from
Jericho
Peace in 
winter gardens
by Anees Jung
| Women’s roles 
in times of war and
in times of peace. 
| Peace and 
security policies 
and practices 
from the feminine
point of view.
| An attempt to find
moments of luminosity
hidden in unexpected
corners of a world 
of increasing violence 
and chaos.
| A collective report
of what women and men
are doing all over the
world to bring peace into
their lives and into that 
of their communities and
nations.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Fo c u s :
Languages at war and peace
6,000 languages: a threatened heritage
n Ecuador: the last of the Zaparas
n English rules, OK?
n Rebels with a cause: defenders of Basque, Berber, Gikuyu 
and Shuar
n Can languages live together?
n International co-operation: Babel, Linguapax, Terralingua . . .
n India: a vast language laboratory
n Which tongues will survive?
Fe a t u res include
n Restoring the great mosque of Djenné (Mali)
n Large dams trigger a flood of controversy
n U.S. school TV goes commercial
n Biopiracy: the South repels boarders
n African museums: will the public please step forward?
n Ethical codes and press freedom in the South
]]>
</page>
</document>
