<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="119663eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
PEOPLE AND PLACES
THE SOUL
OF OLD CAIRO
PLANET
WAR‘S CHAIN
REACTION
INTERVIEW
OCIMAR VERSOLATO:
HYBRID
CREATIONS
B i o d i v e rs i t y :
a friend
for life
May 2000
P u b l i s h e d
in 27
l a n g u a g e s
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
C o n t e n t s
May 2000 53rd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Roy Malkin
Spanish edition: Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition: Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Cynthia Guttman
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: Georges Servat,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,A l c i n o
Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh(Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n :Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher copies
are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
a u t h o r ’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
r e q u e s t . Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering
p o s t a g e. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UN E S C O o r
those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the UN E S C O Courier staff. Th e
boundaries on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the United
N a t i o n s. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform
( m i c r o film and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de
Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,A n n
A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition,
Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ;( 4 )
Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road,Wo o s t e r, O h i o
4 4 6 9 1 , U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - MAY 2000
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Paris by
UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e. Periodicals postage paid at Champlain
NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 5-2000-OPI 99-591 A
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 The soul of Old Cairo Photos by Denis Dailleux;Text by Samir Gharib
PLANET
9 From Viet Nam to Rwanda: war’s chain reaction Fred Pe a r c e
11 The pollution of the Balkans Nevena Popovska and Jasmina Sopova
WORLD OF LEARNING
13 Science teaching’s quantum leap Asbel Lopez
ETHICS
38 The battle for an ethical buck Lucia Iglesias Ku n t z
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
41 Timeless Angkor Fabienne Luco
CONNEXIONS
44 Asia’s alternative television
E t h i rajan A n b a rasan and K. J. M . Va r m a
INTERVIEW
47 Brazilian couturier Ocimar Versolato:hybrid creations
C o v e r : © Steve McCurry/Magnum, Paris 
1 6 Focus B i o d i v e rs i t y : a friend for life
Biodiversity is the essence of life. Without nature’s tremendous
variety, our planet would be hostile to human life. Our existence
and well-being on Earth depend upon learning how to preserve
this diversity.
To do so, we must strike a new balance with nature 
and commit to sharing its precious resources more fairly between
the haves and the have-nots.
Detailed table of contents on page 16.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 3
T HE SOUL OF OLD CA IRO
◗ Photos by Denis Dailleux; Text by Samir Gharib
A traveller weaves his way through streets and alleys 
crowded with memories ■
I was a child when I first discovered
C a i r o, one morning when I had
t r avelled from my nat i ve Upper
Egypt on the famous midnight train. I
stayed with my aunt on my father’s side,
who lived in the Fostat quarter [name of
a city founded in 641 by the Muslim
conqueror Aman ‘bn Al ‘Ass] on the outs-
kirts of Old Cairo. The air was filled with
◗ French photographer Denis Dailleux has been a 
member of the Vu agency since 1995. This year he won a 
World Press Photo award in Amsterdam (Netherlands).
Samir Gharib, Egyptian writer and journalist, was 
appointed chairman of his country’s National Library
and Archives in 1999. His published works include The
Vitality of Egypt and Engravings on Time (Egyptian Book
Organization, 1996 and 1997).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
4 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
an acrid, p e n e t r ating smell from a nearby
t a n n e ry.
On the first evening, I went to the nea-
rest mosque, d e d i c ated to the memory of an
extremely pious man named Sidi A b d u l
S a o u d . From an adjoining house came the
sound of wo m e n ’s vo i c e s ,c ri e s , and beat i n g
t a m b o u ri n e s ,m e r ging into a kind of incan-
tation. I could not resist. Trying not to be
noticed,I slipped into the courtyard of the
house.
A group of common women, clad in
long black dresses, were dancing in a
circle, keeping pace with an increasingly
quick, breathless beat. Their bodies mer-
ging into a single whole, their hips rocked
by a movement they could no longer
control, projected an irresistible sensuali-
ty.
A young man with hair as long as the
wo m e n ’s and we a ring a tight gown wa s
standing in the middle of the circle and
b e ating the rhythm with small cy m b a l s.
Some of the women dancing around him
were playing tambourines.
It was a zar ceremony—a ritual held
to remove a spell.The women had gone
into a collective trance to expel from their
bodies the demons that had possessed
them. It had become so intense that some
had collapsed and lay prostrate on the
ground.The young man leaned over each
one and whispered mysterious words into
their ears and revived them.
I shall never forget that scene.It unex-
pectedly introduced me,as if I were a tres-
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
passer, into the very heart of Old Cairo.
If you take the road that today leads
from Fo s t at to the intern ational airp o rt ,
you come to the foot of the great plateau
and the overlooking Citadel built by Saladin
in 1176.The impregnable silhouette of this
symbol of power abutting the Moqat t a n
hills rises above the capital and keeps wat c h
over it day and night. When Bonapart e
entered Cairo in the last days of the 18th
c e n t u ry, it was here that he installed his
a rt i l l e ry. It was from here that he shelled the
rebellious poor neighbourhoods.
Before the time of the illustrious French
g e n e r a l , the Citadel was the place where the
Turkish gove rn o rs representing the Sublime
Porte were inducted in great splendour. It
was here too that Mohammed Ali, seeking
to take the reins of power in the early 19th
century, invited all the Mameluke lords to
his son’s wedding—and then had them
slaughtered to the last man.
One of the Citadel’s gates leads to the
Fatimid city, in other words the ori gi n a l
C a i r o, Al Qahira, founded by Gohar the
S i c i l i a n , who commanded the troops of the
dynasty that conquered Egypt in 975.
The jewels of the Muslim city can be
found there: Al Azhar Unive rsity and the A l
Hussein mosque, s u rrounded by dozens of
other mosques that are lit up and come alive
at night, calling to one another with the ebbing
and flowing of the vast Cairo crow d .D u ri n g
R a m a d a n , the month of fasting and of feasting
t o g e t h e r , circles of believe rs chant praises to
their Creator in harm o ny. And mystic bro-
therhoods from all over Egypt meet to sing
and dance their love of God until daw n .
I never tire of we aving my way with
friends at night through the latticework of
streets and alleyways in this neighbourhood
where the soul of Cairo never sleeps.
A nything can happen on Al Bat i n i ya
Street.The first time I innocently turned
d own this street, at nightfa l l , a man came up
to me and asked if I wanted some oil. I
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 5
I never tire of weaving 
my way with friends 
at night through 
the latticework of streets 
and alleyways in this
neighbourhood where the soul
of Cairo never sleeps. 
A n ything can happen on 
Al Batiniya Street.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
6 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
politely turned him dow n . “It is top quality,”
he insisted.Why on earth should I want to
buy oil I didn’t need in the middle of the
street? But I was intrigued by the gaze of
t h at man who, while talking about oil,
seemed to have something else in mind.
When at last I figured out that he was talking
about hashish, I ran away as fast as my legs
could carry me. But that did not keep me
from noticing other young people seated
behind little tables offering passersby the
same sort of oil.
All that happened a long time ago.
This first visit to Cairo was followed by
m a ny others. For a long time, I dreamed of
living in the Al Ghourieh quart e r.The seve r e d
head of Touman Bey,E g y p t ’s last Mameluke
s u l t a n , was hung over the gate to this neigh-
bourhood after the Ottoman Turks killed
him in the 16th century. A year earlier his
fat h e r , Sultan Al Ghouri , had been killed
resisting the new conquerors.The quarter has
b o rne his name to honour him ever since.
Al Ghouri e h ’s elusive charm lies, I think,
in the omnipresence of the past.The we i g h t
of history can be felt in each narrow street
a n d ,e ven more so, in the faces of the people
who live there, which express, often uncons-
ciously, the tranquil certainty that this has
a lways been and always will be their home.
I really discovered this neighbourhood
when I visited three artists who in the 1970s
represented the creative genius of Egypt’s
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 7
common people: the blind composer Sheik
I m a m , the poet Ahmad Fuad Negm and the
l u t e - p l ayer Muhammed A l i . In their public
p e r f o rm a n c e s , these three men dared to
voice the anger of the poor, the outrage of
students and the dreams of a better life
t h at were embodied in those days by Ho Chi
Minh and Che Guevara.
They lived in a shack that seemed in a
state of imminent collapse.You had to be
very careful where you put your feet.You
might be invited to have a cup of tea, but
c e rtainly not a dish of grilled chops. I n s t e a d
you had to settle for the smell that wafted in
from a nearby stall.
Such a neighbourhood can hold a
strange at t r a c t i o n . Something in the close-
knit fa b ric of the bu i l d i n g s , in the vibra-
tions of the passing crow d , excites the
i m a gi n at i o n . You can almost guess what
the interi o rs of the houses look like, e n t e r
the alcove s , share amorous e m b r a c e s ,
follow the silent gaze of women behind
the musharabiehs.1
Fo rt u n at e l y, the women now go out
into the street, often draped in wide black
veils that are supposed to conceal their
bodies from intru s i ve eyes but actually
emphasize their shapely curves.There is a
language in the undulations of the female
body that I never tire of learning.
Al Ghourieh leads into a street named
after Al Hakim Bi Amr Illah (“He who
g ove rns by divine decree”), the illustri o u s
Fatimid caliph whose mystic personality has
a lways baffled histori a n s. In this street you can
e n j oy all the scents of the East, from per-
fumes to medicinal plants. Here traditional
remedies for most known physical and psy-
1. In Arab architecture, balconies closed by lat t i c e-
work allowing one to see without being seen.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
8 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
c h o l o gical ailments can still be found.
This street crosses another wo r l d - fa m o u s
t h o r o u g h fa r e , Khan Al Khalili Street, w h e r e
t o u rist coaches pour forth their passengers all
year round. H e r e , E g y p t ’s most skilful
craftsmen display a dazzling arr ay of hand-
made products in gold, s i l k , g l a s s , wo o d ,
copper and ivo ry. All kinds of things are for
s a l e — e ven dresses for belly-dancers.
A visit to the celebrated Al Fichawi cafe,
where they provide you with a royal hookah,
is a must for anyone who wants to claim they
really saw Old Cairo.This coffee-house is a
microcosm of street life, an endless stream of
newspaper ve n d o rs , shoe-shine men, b e g-
g a rs , street peddlers—as well as poets,n ove-
lists and journalists of eve ry stri p e .
L a s t l y, this neighbourhood was long the
home of Egypt’s national glory, our coun-
t ry ’s first Nobel Prize-winner for literat u r e ,
Naguib Mahfouz. His best-known novels
take place in this spellbinding maze of
narrow streets and dead-ends, where the
h e a rt of the city beats and is haunted by his
larger-than-life pers o n a g e s. From the
immense fresco of characters in his nove l s ,
w hy am I tempted to recall only the f u t u wa?
They were men who, with panache, mas-
culine generosity and effic i e n cy, enforced a
c e rtain order, e ven a certain justice, in their
n e i g h b o u r h o o d s. They formed a sort of
p e o p l e ’s police who stood up for the needy
and the weak in the name of a chivalrous
code of honour.
To d ay, they have disappeared.And with
t h e m , a whole wo r l d — t h at of Naguib Mah-
fouz himself—which gave Old Cairo its
soul is disappearing from our lives.
As you will have guessed, I am uncon-
solable. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
P L A N E T
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 9
FROM VIET NAM 
TO RWA NDA: 
WAR’S CH A IN RE ACT ION
◗ Fred Pearce
From destroyed vegetation to health hazards, the environment has been a systematic casualty
of recent wars and pays the price long after peace returns
◗ Freelance environmental writer and consultant for
The New Scientist
■
C o n c e rn about the env i r o n m e n t a l
impact of wa r fare began in earnest with
O p e r ation Ranch Hand, the U. S .c a m-
paign to defoliate Viet Nam’s jungles and flu s h
out guerrillas during the late 1960s.A m e ri c a n
m i l i t a ry aircraft sprayed some 70 million litres
of extra-strong herbicides, mostly a form u l a-
tion known as Agent Orange, over the coun-
t ry between 1962 and 1971,dousing 1.7 mil-
lion hectares, often several times ove r. By the
end of the wa r , a fifth of South V i e t n a m ’s
forests had been chemically annihilat e d ,a n d
more than a third of its mangr ove forests we r e
d e a d . Some forests have since recove r e d , bu t
much of the land has turn e d , apparently per-
m a n e n t l y, to scrubby gr a s s l a n d .
An unwarranted experiment 
in chemical warfare
From the start there was concern that
Agent Orange was toxic to humans as well as
t r e e s. In 1964, the Fe d e r ation of A m e ri c a n
Scientists condemned Operation Ranch Hand
as an unwa rranted experiment in chemical
wa r fa r e . But the operation continued until a
s p ate of reports in 1970 and 1971 that A g e n t
Orange was causing birth defects. S o o n
research showed that 2,4,5-T, one of its two
main constituents,caused malform ations and
s t i l l b i rths in mice and contained diox i n ,a by-
product that turned out to be one of the most
poisonous substances known to science.It
d i s rupts the body’s horm o n a l , immune and
r e p r o d u c t i ve systems, and causes fat h e rs to
produce damaged sperm .
N ature has cleansed Vietnamese soils and
ve g e t ation of most of the diox i n , but the che-
mical has lingered on in human blood, fat and
breast milk.According to Le Cao Dai, d i r e c-
tor of the Agent Orange Victim Fund set up
by the Viet Nam Red Cross, the breast milk
of women in former South Vietnam who we r e
exposed to Agent Orange in childhood
contains about ten times more dioxin than
t h at of women in former North Vietnam or
i n d u s t rialized nations such as the U. S .
Appalling birth defects among the chil-
dren of veterans exposed during the war to
Agent Orange and other pesticides are we l l
d o c u m e n t e d .According to Professor Hoang
Dinh Cau, the chairman of Viet Nam’s 
10-80 Committee, which inve s t i g ates the
consequences of the use of chemicals duri n g
the wa r , tens of thousands of children are
a f f e c t e d . Common symptoms are limbs
twisted in a characteristic way or missing
a l t o g e t h e r , and eyes without pupils. A n d
n ow there is gr owing concern that a third
generation of children may be affected.
Although less well documented, I r a q i
attacks on civilian populations of Iraqi Ku r-
distan between A p ril 1987 and August 1988
h ave had equally long-term effects. In the tow n
of Halabja,bombed over three days in March
1988 with chemical and biological agents,
about 5,000 to 7,000 people were immedia-
tely killed and tens of thousands injured.T h e
first medical study of the at t a c k ’s long-term
effects was carried out by Dr Christine Gos-
d e n ,a professor of medical genetics at the Uni-
ve rsity of Live rp o o l . In a report to the UN Ins-
titute for Disarmament Research, she detailed
s e rious medical problems, including rare can-
c e rs , congenital malform ations in children,
i n f e rt i l i t y, m i s c a rri a g e s ,r e c u rrent lung infec-
tions and severe neuropsychiat ric disorders.
She noted that delayed effects such as the deve-
lopment of cancers following exposure may
occur five to ten ye a rs lat e r.
All wa rs produce environmental damage.
Some is deliberate and for direct military objec-
t i ve s.Clearly that cat e g o ry includes the defo-
l i ation of Indochina—as well as the accompa-
nying physical clearance of some 300,000
hectares of forest using heavy tractors. O t h e r
One of the many Vietnamese children affected by their parents’ exposure to Agent Orange.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
P L A N E T
10 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
d e s t ruction is equally deliberat e , but has a less
clearly military objective ,such as Saddam Hus-
s e i n ’s sabotaging of Ku waiti oil wells at the
height of the Gulf War in 1991. His forces
attacked some 730 we l l s , setting some 630
a l i g h t .M a ny continued to discharge oil into
the desert and thick black smoke into the air
for many months.The total release of oil wa s
finally estimated at 10 million cubic metres.
Some 300 oil lakes at one point covered 50
square kilometres of desert .
After Saddam threatened to set fire to the
we l l s , some scientists wa rned that the black
smoke could rise high enough into the upper
atmosphere to upset global climate systems
such as the Asian monsoon.These fears prove d
u n f o u n d e d . But the local fallout of soot,c a r-
cinogenic particles and acidic sulphur diox i d e
spread for hundreds of kilometres around the
G u l f. Ku wait City experienced “darkness at
n o o n ”comparable to the wo rst London smogs
of the early 20th century, causing a rush of
r e s p i r at o ry illnesses. It took six months and
$10 billion to stop the fires and repair the
damage to the we l l s. Some of the thick black
oil remains in hollows in the desert .
The war damaged the desert in other
way s. G r avel beds that once held the desert
sands in check were fractured by thousands
of bu n k e rs ,weapon pits and trenches.And the
tracks of tanks and trucks compacted fragi l e
soils and killed ve g e t at i o n .The Ku waiti Ins-
titute for Scientific Research concluded that
more than 900 square kilometres of desert
were damaged by military vehicles and eart h
m ove m e n t . The result has been more ero-
s i o n , sand storm s ,a d vancing sand dunes and
diminution of plant life. The war released
one million cubic metres of oil (out of the total
10) into the Pe rsian Gulf, p a rtly from Sad-
d a m ’s sabotages but much of it from the
bombing of strat e gic installations by the U. S .
and others. It severely contaminated some
400 kilometres of Ku waiti and Saudi coastline
with tar, and destroyed shrimp fis h e ri e s.S t u-
dies five ye a rs after the event revealed that
Saudi coastal ecosystems had largely reco-
ve r e d , though turtle populations nesting on
islands in the Gulf had not returned to their
f o rmer leve l s.
But much environmental damage in wa r
is unintended “ c o l l ateral damage”.The detri-
tus of munitions such as cluster bombs and
land mines are a major long-term threat 
to env i r o n m e n t s.The U. S . dropped some 1.5
million cluster bombs during the Indochina
Wa r , containing an estimated 750 million
b o m b l e t s ,according to A rthur We s t i n g, a lea-
ding historian on the environmental conse-
quences of wa r. It dropped a further 60,000,
containing some 30 million bomblets duri n g
the Gulf Wa r.They were left scattered across
the desert along with some 1.7 million mines
planted by the Iraqis. Most were cleared up
a f t e r wa r d s. But this caused further damage to
d e s e rt ecosystems as bomb disposal units plou-
ghed up large areas of the desert .
Worldwide it is estimated that there are
some 65 million functional land mines strewn
around the countryside posing a threat to
inhabitants and wildlife in 56 countries from
Angola to Nicaragua, E ritrea to Laos.A ny-
thing bigger than a rabbit is likely to set them
o f f.According to the Intern ational Commit-
tee of the Red Cross, they kill around 800
people and maim thousands more each
m o n t h . It estimates that Cambodia has 36,000
amputees as a result, and Somalia 23,000.
One of the more gruesome and unexpected
consequences of the massive flooding in sou-
t h e rn Mozambique in Fe b ru a ry this year wa s
to flo at land mines left over after the coun-
t ry ’s long civil war from known minefie l d s
into villages and fie l d s.
Refugees and deforestation
A new concern is the long-term conse-
quences of the use of depleted uranium
(DU)—a mildly radioactive and ve ry dense
m at e rial that weapon makers now put on the
tips of munitions to penetrate tank arm o u r.
About 300 tonnes of DU was dispers e d
across the bat t l e field during the Gulf Wa r.
The environmental and human health
impacts of the radioactive mat e rial left behind
by these munitions remain unclear.T h e r e
h ave been frequent claims that DU has rai-
sed cancer rates in southern Iraq and caused
Iraqi soldiers exposed to it to father seve r e l y
d e f o rmed babies. But so far no studies have
c o n firmed this link.
The social dislocation caused by war is a
f u rther cause of environmental damage.
Floods of refugees in particular can threat e n
n atural resources such as water and forests.
The Rwandan conflict and the events that it
t riggered in the Democratic Republic of the
Congo (DRC,ex-Zaire)became a major cause
of deforestation in central A f ri c a .One casualty
was A f ri c a ’s first national park, the V i ru n g a
N ational Pa r k , on the border between the
DRC and Rwa n d a .The World Conservat i o n
Union (IU C N) reported that in six months, t h e
R wandan refugees and Hutu soldiers from
camps around the town of Goma in the DRC
had deforested some 300 square kilometres
of V i runga National Park in their search for
food and wo o d .At the height of the cri s i s ,t h e
IU C N e s t i m ated that some 850,000 refugees
were living within or close to the park and took
b e t ween 410 and 770 tonnes of forest pro-
ducts out of the park daily. In the confusion,
Z a i rian soldiers were raiding the park for tim-
ber to sell to refugees and relief organizat i o n s.
Similar destruction became a feature of
civil and cross-border conflicts across much
of A f rica in the 1990s. In March this ye a r ,
the UN Environment Programme report e d
on the “ t r a n s f o rm ation of natural land and
forest areas” with “ s e vere impacts on bio-
d i ve rsity and water systems” in southern
Rwandan refugees in ex-Zaire have deforested areas in their search for food and firewood.
Worldwide it is estimated that
there are some 65 million
functional land mines strew n
around the countryside posing a
threat to inhabitants and wildlife
in 56 countries from Angola to
N i ca ragua, Eritrea to Laos.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
P L A N E T
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 11
The Pancevo oil refinery near Belgrade burning after NATO bombings 
in April 1999.
G u i n e a , f o l l owing the influx of some
600,000 refugees from recent conflicts in
n e i g h b o u ring Sierra Leone and Liberi a .
Most of the refugees had hacked out forest
to grow crops for food.
G u e rrilla armies do as much damage as
r e f u g e e s ,p a rticularly when they have to live
off the land or generate income to buy arm s
from the plundering of natural resources in
the region where they are fig h t i n g .A rmies also
h ave to eat , and for guerrilla armies “ bu s h-
m e at ” is a frequent source of food. G u e rri l l a
wa rs in Cambodia and west and central A f ri c a
h ave been sustained during the past decade
through the cutting and sale of valuable hard-
wood timbers.Wildlife suffers too.In the Horn
of A f rica in the 1980s,Somali war bands we r e
frequently behind the rampant poaching of
elephants for their ivo ry.War in Uganda in
1979 killed off much of the country ’s bu s h
elephant populat i o n , and conflicts in A n g o l a
and Mozambique have since caused the who-
lesale slaughter of elephants in those coun-
t ries too.The Rwanda conflict and succee-
ding guerrilla activity in the surr o u n d i n g
r e gions through the 1990s saw the slaughter of
mountain gorillas in V i runga and elsewhere—
a fact that understandably gained little at t e n-
tion beside the massive slaughter of humans.
Silence on Chechnya
War and the environment have , of cours e ,
a lways been linked. Some of the earliest
b attles between city states in Mesopotamia
5,000 ye a rs ago invo l ved the breaking of
dykes to flood fa rm l a n d . But the Indochina
War was the first time scientists seriously pro-
bed the effect of a major confli c t .The Gulf
War was perhaps the first time those conse-
quences were seriously addressed before they
h a p p e n e d , with experts (erroneously) fore-
casting a global climate change if fire was set
to the oil we l l s. D u ring the Kosovo confli c t ,
the environmental consequences of the bom-
bing of fa c t o ries gained precedence in much
r e p o rting over the intended economic 
d a m a g e .There can be little doubt that the
e nvironmental impacts of Russian military
activity in Chechnya and Afghanistan has
been as severe as that of the U. S . and its allies
in southeast A s i a , the Gulf and elsewhere.
But far less is known as independent inve s-
t i g ations have been notable only by their
a b s e n c e . In Chechnya , the seve rity of the mili-
t a ry battles and the physical destruction of
G r o z ny has been so gr e at that likely env i-
ronmental damage such as pollution of wat e r
s u p p l i e s , though of undoubtedly long-term
i m p o rtance for rebu i l d i n g, has to date barely
been remarked upon. The continuing
c o n flicts in Afghanistan have made indepen-
dent assessment of the impacts of 20 ye a rs
of war there hard to purs u e . ■
T HE POL LU T ION 
OF THE BA L KA NS
◗ Nevena Popovska and Jasmina Sopova
Air, soil and water were severely polluted by NATO’s bombing of Yugoslavia last spring, 
raising fears of long-term effects on health
◗ Respectively journalists in Skopje (Republic of
Macedonia) and with the UNESCO Courier
■
The Atlantic Alliance officially reco-
gnized on March 21, 2000 that it
used depleted uranium ammunition
in shells in Yugoslavia during the previous
year’s war. Kosovo and southern Serbia
bore the brunt of these radioactive wea-
pons, used for the first time during the
Gulf War in 1991.They release clouds of
uranium dust that contaminate water and
the food chain. Particles enter the human
body through inhalation or ingestion,
remaining there from one to three years,
increasing the risk of steri l i t y, b i rt h
defects and cancer tenfold.
From March 24 to June 10, 1999,
NATO warplanes flying close to 31,000
s o rties bombed the entire Yu g o s l av
Fe d e r ation (Serbia, M o n t e n e gr o,
Voivodina, Kosovo). Thousands of mis-
siles were fired, some of which landed in
neighbouring Bulgaria and Macedonia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
P L A N E T
12 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
Chemical industry
Fuel storage
Oil refinery
Industry
Electric power
plant
National park
National capital
Administrative
capital
Other cities
Airport
BELGRADE
SKOPJE
SARAJEVO
Pristina
Podgorica
Sar Planina
Nis
Bor
Pancevo
Fruska Gora
Novi Sad
Kopaonic
Kragujevac
SERBIA
BOSNIA AND
HERZEGOVINA
CROATIA
HUNGARY
ROMANIA
BULGARIA
REPUBLIC OF MACEDONIA
ALBANIA
MONTENEGRO
KOSOVO
VOIVODINA
0 60 km
Targeted sites with potential negative environmental impacts.
Tara
Furthermore, many pilots flying back to
their bases dropped bombs into the
Adriatic Sea off the Croat, Slovene and
Italian coasts. According to NATO
sources, 1,600 cluster bombs, which are
banned by the Geneva Convention of 10
October 1980, were dropped, releasing
200,000 bomblets. Thousands have not
yet exploded, becoming as dangerous as
antipersonnel mines. They have already
killed nearly 200 Kosovars.
A year after the strikes,the real scale of
the environmental damage has not been
clearly established.According to the joint
UN Balkans Task Force (BTF)1, pollu-
tion has severely affected four areas:
Pancevo (20 km from Belgrade), Novi
Sad (the capital of Voivodina),Kragujevac
(southern Serbia) and Bor (near the bor-
der with Bulgaria).
The Pa n c e vo petrochemical complex
was bombed approx i m ately ten times. A
press release by the mayo r , Srdjan Mirko-
v i c, published in autumn 1999 in the Yu g o-
s l av review Petroleum Te c h n o l ogy Quart e rl y,
announced that the “direct strike on the
depot containing 1,500 tonnes of vinyl chlo-
ride monomer (VCM) caused a fire that
bu rned eight hours and destroyed approx i-
m ately 800 tonnes” of that carcinogenic sub-
s t a n c e . “When it bu rn s ,” s ays a Belgr a d e
d o c t o r , “it gi ves off, among other things,
c h l o r hy d ric acid,which causes chronic bron-
c h i t i s , d e rm atitis and gastri t i s ; as well as
d i ox i n , regarded as the wo r l d ’s most tox i c
organic pollutant; and possibly phosgene,
which was once used in chemical wa r fa r e .”
Mercury enters
the food chain
Ammonia depots used to make fertili-
zer were also bombed. Had they not been
emptied beforehand as a precaution, their
explosion would have killed any person
within a 10-kilometre radius, as direct
exposure to ammonia is lethal to humans.
The worst was avoided, but the ammonia
was released into the Danube, w h e r e
wildlife was killed 30 kilometres downs-
tream. In addition, “over 1,000 tons of
ethylene dichloride and a few thousand
tonnes of natrium hydroxide”were leaked
into the Danube, according to a report by
the Regional Environment Centre for
Central and Eastern Europe (REC).
Since then, fishing has been abandoned
and crop irrigation has become proble-
matic. The river’s sandy bed has trapped
heavy metals, which are toxic even in
small concentrations, for dozens of years.
In addition to Yugoslavia, Romania and
Bulgaria are affected.
“The soil has been contaminated by
approximately 100 tonnes of mercury,”
s ays Pa n c e vo ’s mayo r. M e r c u ry is an
extremely toxic metal that enters the food
chain and builds up in the human body,
causing irreversible organ damage. The
BTF however found that eight tonnes of
the substance had leaked from the petro-
chemical plant and reported that “the air
strikes on the oil refinery caused an esti-
mated 80,000 tonnes of oil and oil pro-
ducts to burn. This would have released
n oxious substances into the air.”
According to Belgrade’s Public Health
Institute, VCM concentrations in the air
were 10,600 times above the tolerated
norm near the Pancevo petrochemical
plant. At the time, the wind was blowing
from the west, sending the harmful fumes
into Romania and Hungary as well.
Black spring
and acid rain
The other three “ecological hotspots”
suffered a similar fate. The Novi Sad oil
refinery was bombed a dozen times bet-
ween June 5 and 9.Approximately 73,000
tonnes of crude oil and derivative pro-
ducts bu rned or leaked into pipes.
Polluted underground water seeped into
wells near the refinery, depriving the local
population of drinking water.
The strikes against the Zastava auto-
mobile factory in Kragujevac “reportedly
caused extensive environmental pollu-
tion, with damage to soil, water and air,”
reports the BTF, which detected high
l e vels of polychlori n ated bipheny l s
(PCBs).Banned in the mid-1980s becau-
se they are so toxic, these substances can
still be found in old electrical facilities.
Very persistent, they bind with sediments
in rivers and streams and degrade only
after many years.
PCB contamination and severe air pol-
lution caused by emissions of sulphur
d i oxide gas (which is especially hazardous
for asthmatics) were reported in Bor.
Bombings of copper mines, the powe r
plant and the hydrocarbon fuel depot near
Bor also affected nearby Bulgari a . T h e
S o fia newspaper 24 Hours r e p o rted that
birds fell dead out of the sky and the cloud
s p r e a d , causing acid rain. At the same
t i m e , fa rm e rs in Kosovo witnessed trees
losing their leaves in the middle of spri n g .
The entire food chain was affected,
from livestock fodder—and, c o n s e q u e n t l y,
m e at and milk—to fruits and ve g e t a b l e s
intended for consumers. Chronic bronchi-
t i s , a s t h m a , e c z e m a , d i a rrhoea and thy r o i d
d i s o r d e rs have already been detected, bu t
S e r b i a ’s officials would rather cover up the
fa c t s. W h at seems clear is that the most
s e rious health problems are yet to come.■
1. The Kosovo Conflict.Consequences 
for the Environment and Human Settlements,
UNEP-UNCHS, 1999.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 13
■
When Mexican teacher Jose A n t o n i o
Lopez Tercero was a student, h e
regarded as quite plausible the idea
t h at velocity and potential energy are like
t wo machines that can be stored in a cup-
b o a r d . Back in those day s , he was led to
b e l i e ve all kinds of outlandish things. H i s
innocence was caused not by reading
G a b riel Garcia Marquez’s magic realist
n ove l s , but by dozing through abstract
p hysics classes. “They were aw f u l ,” r e c a l l s
Lopez Te r c e r o, who now teaches chemistry
at the Escuela del Sur Institute, a seconda-
ry school in Mexico City.
Today he tries to teach science in the
way he would liked to have learnt it. As
often as possible, he uses everyday objects
to help his students grasp abstract
concepts. A washing machine can  illus-
t r ate dispersion by centrifugal force;
clothes show how to distinguish natural
and synthetic fibres; plastics aid the study
of oil derivatives; lemon juice and red
cabbage bring acids to life, while televi-
sion helps explain how electromagnetic
waves work.
This approach represents a huge qua-
litative change, at least in comparison to
what Lopez Tercero had to go through as
a pupil. Back at secondary school, he
remembers that “the teacher would arri-
ve, announce a concept, write down a for-
mula, and teach us how to solve problems
using the lat t e r. All I did was wo r k
through the formulas by replacing letters
with numbers.”
This traditional teaching method,
based on the transmission of a body of
knowledge and the study of problems
with little relevance to many students, is
still practiced, and not just in Mexico.
According to Jacob Bregman, a specialist
in science education at the World Bank,
“science education in developing coun-
tries often relies too much on memoriza-
tion of facts and not enough on learning
to understand the relevance of knowledge
and its application in the local context.”
In the industrialized countries there is
much greater emphasis on the problem-
solving approach, decision-making, and
developing the ability to analyze and work
in a team.
Failings in the educational systems of
Third World countries are particularly
alarming because economic development
is increasingly linked to scientific and
t e c h n o l o gical know l e d g e . But there is
n ow a widespread desire for change,
reflected in a wave of reforms in scientific
education that have taken place around
the world in the last few years.1 And
though the reforms differ from country
to country, they have certain common
features.
One of them is relating science to eve-
ry d ay life, as Lopez Tercero does in
Mexico. As well as improving the learning
p r o c e s s , this method makes students
more enthusiastic and genuinely interes-
ted in science. In recent years, half of the
gr a d u ates from the Escuela del Sur
Institute have embarked on scientific
c a r e e rs , 30 per cent more than the
Mexican school average.
Unearthing the practical end 
of knowledge
Relating science to everyday life also
means anchoring teaching more firmly in
the local context. Using problems that
affect the community, teachers endeavour
to show the practical value of scientific
knowledge in determining the causes of
specific phenomena.They encourage stu-
dents to come up with ways of possibly
SCIENCE TEACHING ’ S
QU A N T UM LEAP
◗ Asbel López
Teachers must prepare not only future scientists, but also citizens who will confront
unprecedented technological and ethical challenges in their lifetime
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
1. Sylvia A.Ware (editor): Science and
Environment Education,Views from Developing
Countries,The World Bank, Washington D.C.,
1999.
Paul Black and Myron Atkin (editors):
Changing the Subject, London: Routledge with the
Organization for Economic Co-operation and
Development (OECD),1996.
Hands-on learning: in Namibia, students test the resistance of mudbricks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
14 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
preventing environmental catastrophes.
Teachers are making “huge efforts in
their classes to treat problems which are
relevant to the students instead of using
abstract examples from textbooks,” says
Bettina Walther, the co-ordinator of a
science education project in Tanzania’s
secondary schools. Launched in 1997,the
project involves maths teachers from 27
schools, who focus lessons on develop-
ment projects in the towns where they
teach. For example, geometry courses
might be based on the practical case of
installing electricity and telephone lines
to explain concepts while applied maths
lessons look to using fertilizers and pesti-
cides for learning various operations.
Even while looking at the stars, these
teachers base their classes on widely held
local beliefs. Peter Lesala, a science edu-
c ation adviser to Lesotho’s secondary
schools, is writing a course on astronomy
that will feature in his country’s curricu-
lum. “The first thing I did,” he explains,
“was to do some research into Basotho
beliefs about the stars. My course will
start with a discussion of those beliefs.”
for the World Bank and director of
Education and International Activities at
the American Chemical Society believes
in science for all, not just for future scien-
tists. “Those involved in reforming scien-
ce education believe that science is too
important to be left up to scientists alone.
The general public must have a much
broader and more subtle understanding
of science than they have at the moment.
Problems of developing countries such as
water supply, health, industrial develop-
ment or land use have to be addressed by
people who understand the science and
technology involved.”
In other words, the goal is to provide
basic scientific literacy so that citizens can
take an active part in crucial debates on
issues ranging from environmental pro-
Some science education projects
might be inspired by a foreign model. In
this case, the key lies in adapting themes
to local conditions, as some teachers and
students have done in a highly creat i ve way
using “ C h e m C o m : C h e m i s t ry in the com-
m u n i t y ” , a secondary school course draw n
up by the Washington-based A m e ri c a n
Chemical Society, an organization dedica-
ted to advancing knowledge and research
in the field of chemistry and relat e d
sciences (see box ) .
Science for all
Underlying this reform trend is the
conviction that far more young people
should have access to scientific education.
Sylvia Ware, author of several reports on
science education in developing countries
AN EX PERIMENT 
ON DENSI TY
Lemon, water, salt and a glass are all that Mexi-
can secondary school teachers need to prove
that bodies float in denser liquids. A lemon is den-
ser than water, for instance, which means that it
sinks to the bottom if put in a glass of water. By
adding salt, the density of the solution gra d u a l l y
increases until it is greater than that of the lemon,
which thus rises to the surface. 
(El Libro para el maestro. Quimica. “Teacher’s che-
m i s t ry manual”, Educacion secundaria, Public Edu-
cation Secretariat, Mexico, page 64, 19 9 4 ) .
During an in-service training workshop in the Philippines, teachers build a bridge model using local materials.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 15
tection, to the use of genetically modified
organisms, to the new ethical dilemmas
posed by modern biological discoveries.
Through activities like sorting garbage,
protecting certain endangered animal and
plant species and conserving wat e r
r e s o u r c e s , science education can help train
citizens to be aware of their social respon-
s i b i l i t i e s. One example is the Globo project
in Costa Rica, whose goal is to make stu-
dents aware of environmental protection
by studying the El Niño climatic pheno-
m e n o n .Young Costa Ricans measure tem-
p e r atures and record rainfall levels in their
c o m m u n i t i e s.This dat a , g athered by relat i-
vely complex instru m e n t s , is then used in
m aths courses to draw gr a p h s , in the social
sciences to study the impact of floods on
communities and in biology classes to
explain life cy c l e s.
Ware says the issue of “science for all”
has been debated “from Argentina to
Zimbabwe”. The big question is how to
make scientific knowledge more acces-
sible to more students without lowering
standards in courses for those who will
become the scientists of tomorrow. The
answer is complex, requiring a system
that is flexible enough to offer more pre-
cise and in-depth knowledge to those
planning to follow a scientific career,
while at the same time giving everybody
else scientific training that allows them to
function in society.
Although developing countries are far
from having solved this issue, nations like
Argentina, Brazil and Chile have chosen
the route of specialization. In Chile, stu-
dents in the first ye a rs of secondary
school follow the same programme. The
aim is to give them a grounding for beco-
ming well-rounded, socially responsible
citizens. In the last two years, a streamed
system offers two specializations: a tech-
nical and professional kind, aimed at trai-
ning future employees able to compete in
the world market; and a more theoretical
scientific course that stimulates analytical
thought and strives to instil higher levels
of conceptual understanding.This stream
is more specifically geared at students
interested in pursuing a scientific career.
Using this mix,the Chilean model aims to
ensure the creation of a highly trained
workforce that can respond to rapid
changes in the labour market, while at the
same time establishing a scientific com-
munity which can carry out the technolo-
gical innovations needed to modernize
the country’s economy.
Investing
in teachers
These sorts of innovations may well
be major advances, but according to Ware
“you can’t just change the curriculum
and expect things to change in the class-
room.You have to work with teachers and
help them become familiar with the new
m at e rial and new ways of teaching.”
U n f o rt u n at e l y, t e a c h e rs in deve l o p i n g
countries are in a precarious position,and
are thus unable to assume natural leader-
ship in the reform process.
In Chile, teachers work between 33
and 44 hours a week in two or sometimes
three different schools. In Mexico, stu-
dents—numbering up to 60 per class—
are generally taught by dentists or doctors
retrained for the purpose, or by teachers
with more knowledge of classroom tech-
nique than the subject they are supposed
to be covering. Neither students nor tea-
chers stray far from the textbook. “The
main problem with science education in
Mexico is no longer the issue of pro-
grammes or of textbooks; the weak point
lies in teacher training, which is practical-
ly left up to fat e ,” declares V i c e n t e
Ta l a n q u e r , a chemistry professor at
Mexico’s Autonomous University. What
he qualifies as a “big gap” still divides
educational plans and study programmes
from the abiding reality of the classroom.
In Ware’s opinion, there is only one
way to fill this gap: “invest as much as
possible in teachers’ professional develop-
ment.” While adapting the ChemCom
course for use in Russia, the American
Chemical Society, supported by UNESCO,
has also offered training workshops for
teachers, even for those from the most
far-flung towns in Siberia.As a result, the
t e a c h e rs get to know the educat i o n a l
materials and methods, as well as new
evaluation tools that enable them to find
out whether a student has simply learnt
concepts by rote, or if on the other hand
he or she has understood the ideas and is
able to apply them in different situations.
E n o rmous public investment and
resolute political will are required to gua-
rantee this training in the long term.
Given that the reform of scientific educa-
tion in Mexico began only seven years
a g o, and invo l ves 200,000 secondary
school teachers and 600,000 teachers in
primary school, it is clear that the radical
changes everyone is seeking will not hap-
pen overnight. ■
CHEMISTRY IN THE COMMUNI TY
ChemCom is a chemistry curriculum written for
s e c o n d a ry school students by the America n
C h e m i cal Society (ACS) in 1980. It attempts to
enhance science literacy by emphasizing chemis-
try’s impact on society. Despite being the world
leader in science and technology, the U.S. still
records generally unsatisfactory levels of scientific
education—a fact which has worried government,
teachers and parents alike. Since the late 1990s, the
p r o g ramme has been used in schools in many
other countries, from the suburbs of Buenos Aires
to towns in Siberia. It has been translated into
Japanese, Russian, Italian and Spanish, and a Fr e n c h
version will shortly be completed.
One 14-year-old student from Kra s n o y a r s k i i
Krai in Siberia describes ChemCom’s methods as
f o l l ows: “First, the teacher introduces a problem, for
example the pollution of a river, then we students
try to find out what kind of scientific knowledge is
needed to solve the problem. But the most impor-
tant thing is that we consider several possible
approaches and discuss them before making a
final decision.”
The subject of one of the ChemCom course units,
“ Petroleum: To build? To burn?” is based on details
from the U.S. context. But that was no obstacle to stu-
dents from a rural Siberian school, the Bolshoi Ului,
who made full use of the course for their own region—
an oil-rich area like Texas. Two students went with their
parents to gather information on local oil production
from the Environmental Protection Committee in
the nearest town, Achinsk. Not only did they get the
facts they wanted, but the local media launched a
campaign to collect and donate newspapers and
magazines to the students for their project, which has
since been titled: “Natural Resources in Bolshoi Ului:
p r e s e rve them or use them?” ■
ChemCom’s internet site is at
http://lapeer.org/chemcom
Through activities like 
sorting garbage, protecting
c e r tain endangered animal 
and plant species and
c o n s e rving water resources,
science education can help
t rain citizens to be aware 
of their social responsibilities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
S
ince the time of A r i s t o t l e, we have been trying to inventory the world’s
plant and animal species.Yet in the year 2000, this colossal task is now-
here near being achieved. It probably never will be, despite the efforts
of taxonomists and scientists prospecting for this “green gold” ( p p. 1 8 - 1 9 ) .
N a t u r e ’s riches are beyond measure and its mechanisms all the more dif-
ficult to grasp insofar as biodiversity is a broad concept, encompassing genes,
species and ecosystems (pp. 2 0 - 2 1 ) . But scientists are clear about one fact: t h e
unprecedented environmental damage caused by human activity is putting a
record number of species at risk of extinction (pp. 2 2 - 2 3 ) .
And yet, biodiversity is the very essence of life (pp. 1 7 ,2 4 - 2 5 ) .E c o s y s t e m s
provide a host of environmental services (pp.26-27) that make our planet habi-
t a b l e. Genetic diversity is key to assuring the world’s food supply and provides
a formidable gene pool for biotechnology, especially agriculture (pp. 2 7 - 2 9 )
and medicine (pp. 3 0 - 3 1 ) . It also offers a boon for eco-tourism (pp. 3 1 - 3 2 ) .
Yet it would be a grave mistake to think we can preserve biodiversity by trying
to isolate it. People are an integral part of this dynamic system. S u s t a i n a b l e
c o n s e r vation demands support for a global network of nature reserves invol-
ving local people closely in their management (pp. 3 3 - 3 4 ) . Seed and gene banks,
l i ke that of Kew Gardens in London (pp. 3 5 - 3 6 ) , are also gaining ground. B u t
managing the planet’s “green gold” is also sparking legal and ethical battles
beyond what anyone could have imagined in 1992,when the international com-
munity adopted the Rio Convention on Biological
D i v e r s i t y. ■
C o n t e n t s
O p i n i o n
1 7 A necessary partnership with nature
Catherine Larrère
1 | Nature under thre a t
1 8 The lair of the batfis h
Timothy B. We r n e r
2 0 Uncharted territory
2 2 Doomed to early demise
E d ward O. W i l s o n
2 | Scientific truths
2 4 Too valuable for price-tags
Sophie Boukhari
2 6 E c o s y s t e m s : our unknown pro t e c t o rs 
José Sarukhán
2 7 Genetic diversity and food security
Geoffrey C. H a w t i n
3 0 Out of the forest and into the bottle
Cécile Guérin
3 1 B o r n e o : reaping the fruits of ecotourism
Robert Basiuk
3 | The next step
3 3 E c o p ro t e c t i o n : an international go-slow
Interview with Seydina Issa Sylla
3 5 Kew turns over a new leaf
David Dickson
3 7 To w a rds a world conservation ethics
M . S. S wa m i n a t h a n
16 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
Fo c u s B i o d i v e rs i t y:
a friend
for life
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
B i o d i v e rs i t y: a friend for life
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 17
The giant panda and the blue whale are sym-
bols of a wildlife whose richness and diversi-
ty we want to preserve, for the protection of
threatened species is one of the oldest ways of
protecting nature itself.
But we now know that biological dive rs i t y,
or biodive rs i t y, is a concept that refers not only 
to species but to the entire living wo r l d , f r o m
genes to the biosphere, the regions of the 
e a rt h ’s crust and atmosphere occupied by living
o r g a n i s m s.
Biodiversity is not static. It can be defined as
a constantly evolving system. Scientists say it
allows living organisms to adapt to environments
that change over time, thus ensuring the conti-
nuity of evolutionary processes.
To d ay, human activities are acknowledged 
to be part of this, but for a long time people 
were seen mainly as agents external to nat u r e ,
ones that upset biodive rs i t y. E f f o rts were 
made to preserve “ v i r gi n ” or “ w i l d ” n at u r a l
spaces by keeping them separate from all human
a c t i v i t y.
The power to destroy
and sustain
It is a fact that human beings are the source
of clear threats to nat u r e . Po l l u t i o n , e x c e s s i ve
h a rvesting of living species, the exterm i n at i o n
of “ h a rm f u l ” s p e c i e s , and the fragmentation 
or destruction of habitats cause species to
disappear and speed up the erosion of biodive r-
s i t y. But since biodive rsity has been conceive d
from a dynamic standpoint, humans have 
also come to be regarded as capable of sustai-
ning biodive rs i t y, as has been shown in France 
in the wooded pasturelands of Normandy 
and Bri t t a ny. E ven tropical forests are often 
the fruit of a lengthy co-evolution between indi-
genous populations and their natural 
e nv i r o n m e n t .
This power to both destroy and sustain biodi-
ve rsity emphasizes the breadth of our responsibi-
l i t y. Human beings are just one species among
o t h e rs , but one that exercises a part i c u l a r l y
demanding process of selection. No part of the
planet can now escape human activity, so the
idea of conserving nature as a whole is no longer
t e n a b l e .
However, we have to weigh up the conse-
quences of our actions on the evolutionary pro-
cess so that we can regulate them.The principle
of the “sustainable management” of biodiversity
springs from this necessary partnership between
human beings and nature.
But what are the yardsticks for such regula-
tion? Perhaps the instrumental value of biodive r-
sity—the goods and services it provides and the
k n owledge scientists draw from it. But since we
e n j oy nat u r e ’s beauty, we have to add in the aes-
thetic or religious feelings it inspires.
The intrinsic value 
of nature
This leads us to the intrinsic or ethical value
of biodiversity. Nature has its own worth, inde-
pendently of how it can serve people. All living
organisms, through their existence and their use
of complex, non-mechanical strategies to survive
and reproduce, have their own value. Beyond
that, biological diversity itself, because it is the
product of evolution and also the condition for its
continuation, has its own intrinsic value, as the
opening lines of the Convention on Biological
Diversity (Rio, 1992) acknowledge.
The human bias behind the instru m e n t a l i s t
approach has often been set against the ecologi-
cal bias underlying the intrinsic value approach,
as if a choice had to be made, as if eve ryone had
to die for the last wolf to be save d , or vice-ve rs a .
But apart from the fact that such options 
are entirely art i f i c i a l , the two approaches 
can coexist, as soon as there is agreement 
about a dynamic and integr ated view of
b i o d i ve rsity as an evolving system that includes
p e o p l e .
H owe ve r , the rise of genetic engi n e e ri n g,
which treats genes as raw mat e ri a l , has put bio-
d i ve rsity in quite a new light. It is now seen as an
e n o rmous pool of resources to be speedily tap-
p e d . As such, genetic biodive rsity is no longer
about the wise management of nat u r e . I t
becomes a source of profit and of conflict among
those seeking to control it. ■
O p i n i o n
A necessary
p a r t n e rs h i pw i t hn a t u re
◗ Catherine Larrère
◗ French philosopher and author of
Les Philosophies de l’environnement
(“Philosophies of the Environment”;
P U F, Pa r i s,1997) and Du bon usage
de la nature (“Of the Good Use of
N a t u r e ” ;A u b i e r, Pa r i s, 1 9 9 7 )
Man is a rope stretched
between the animal and 
the Superman – a rope
over an abyss.
Friedrich Nietzsche,
German philosopher 
( 1 8 4 4 - 1 9 0 0 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Day 1: Nova Vi ç o s a
Aboard two fishing boat s , we ’re chugging through
the muddy wat e rs of the Caravelas River to the first sur-
vey site at Nova Viçosa reef.Once out of the ri ve r ’s mouth,
the blue water teems with coral reef animals that only
l i ve in this part of the wo r l d .On our first dive , I descend
past a mat of anemone-like creatures commonly called
“ b a b a - d e - b o i ” , or bu l l ’s slobber. B rush up against this
a n i m a l ’s mucus lining, and you instantly unders t a n d
h ow it got its name.B e l ow this mat , I am surr o u n d e d
by a number of ancient and endemic corals that make
this area such a pri o rity for global conservat i o n .
Over the next three weeks our team of leading
m a rine scientists will log about three dives a day to
document the bank’s marine biodiversity.
Days 2-3: Popa Ve rd e
Our Brazilian fish specialist, R o d rigo Moura,s p i e s
a lemon shark and what will be one of only two shark
sightings for the whole surve y.For the shark-wa ry this
is good news, but to a marine conservationist it is
wo rri s o m e . Sharks are important top predat o rs in the
o c e a n .R e m ove them and you can disturb the ecologi c a l
b a l a n c e .Around the wo r l d , they are increasingly rare
18 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
◗ Director, Marine Biodiversity
Program,Centre for Applied
Biodiversity Science, Conservation
International
from heavy demand particularly for their fin s ,m e at and
l i ver oil. Fo rt u n at e l y, on this same dive I see a huge
grouper—longer than I am—which is a good sign.
Large fish still thri ve in the wat e rs of A b r o l h o s.
Day 4: In the wake of Cabra l
Exactly 500 ye a rs ago, the Po rtuguese mari n e r
A l vares Cabral reported seeing lush tropical forest
from the same spot where we are anchored. Our view
is ve ry different. L o g ging has destroyed all but about
8 per cent of this unique forest, prompting Conserva-
tion Intern ational to classify it as one of the wo r l d ’s top
“ h o t s p o t s ”or pri o rity areas for conservation (see p.2 1 ) .
D e f o r e s t ation also takes its toll on the ecology of
coastal wat e rs. Erosion unleashes a steady stream of
sediments that can “ c h o k e ” or even bu ry corals.M o s t
of the corals found on the Abrolhos Bank appear
adapted to the turbid conditions that would kill spe-
cies in other parts of the wo r l d .We find one of the
endemic coral,Scolymia we l l s i i, in a pit five centimetres
b e l ow the muddy sea flo o r !
Day 5: C o r u m b a u
We are anchored directly across from the fis h i n g
village of Corumbau where local elders claim they once
bu rned coral to produce house paint.Elsewhere along
the Brazilian coast, there are houses built of coral
b o u l d e rs.These practices have been abandoned bu t
corals and other living marine animals are still har-
vested illegally for sale in the curio trade. One of the
most coveted is the Brazilian snail, S t r o m bus go l i at h ,
which can reach lengths of 35 cm. D u ring our entire
s u rvey we will see only one individual.
Day 8: Pa re d e s
To d ay ’s destination is Brazil’s largest coral reef,
Pa r e d e s.At firs t , the reef looks barren but in crevices
we find several interesting fishes and corals we
haven’t yet seen during the survey.
At the bottom of a steep wall I see one of the
wo r l d ’s strangest looking marine fis h e s : a bat fis h .
Dull green and shaped like a swollen arr ow, the bat-
fish not only swims but crawls along the sand like a rep-
t i l e , using its fins as feet.
1 N a t u re under thre a t
The l a i r of the batfis h
◗ Timothy B. We r n e r
Dive into the turbid waters of Bra z i l ’s A b rolhos Bank to explore the mysteries 
of its marine biodiversity with a team of leading scientists
Mussimila braziliensis, a coral species found only in Brazil, produces unique mushroom-like
formations known as chaperiões.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
B i o d i v e rs i t y: a friend for life
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 19
Day 13: California Reef
After hours of searching, our boat ’s depth fin d e r
picks up California reef—between 20 and 35 metres
d ow n . But it turns out to be well wo rth the search.
Wrapped in a luxurious gr owth of gorgonian corals,t h e
r e e f’s pinnacles produce new records of corals and
fishes for the surve y.W h at a surp rise to find several colo-
nies of the coral species Po rites bra n n e ri with bright red
tentacles—a sharp contrast from its usual drab brow n -
and-white colour.
R e t u rning to our anchorage at Santa Barbara Island,
we see boats fishing illegally well inside the boundary of the
Abrolhos National Marine Pa r k .The morning before we
radioed in the name and identific ation number of one of
these boats to the park guard.T h at aftern o o n ,we heard a
n aval officer speaking by radio with the alleged offender,
telling him that he shouldn’t get overly concerned as it
was only a “ t o u ri s t ”who provided the inform at i o n .
In the eve n i n g, we decide to check out the local
n i g h t l i f e .Much like a submerged city, a coral reef has
t owe ring structures of stone crawling with denizens,
some of whom spring to life only when the sun sets.
Thousands of polychaete wo rms wriggle around
our underwater lights in a reproductive frenzy know n
as swa rm i n g . On certain nights of the ye a r , linked to
the lunar cy c l e , polychaete wo rms release masses of
s p e rm and eggs. If I keep my light on too long at a cer-
tain spot, I began to feel these wo rms scurrying inside
my ear and brushing my fa c e .We have just observe d
the first known spawning event to take place in Brazil
in Fe b ru a ry.
Day 17: A look at the edge
We are as close as we will get to the edge of the
continental shelf.This is an ideal location for observ i n g
“cleaning stat i o n s”. At certain rocky outcrops,small fis h
await the arri val of the larger fis h ,much like a pit crew
in a motorcar race.The large fish swim up and stop
while the smaller fish begin picking off their parasites.
Day 18: W rapping up
The whole team meets on deck to discuss our
p r e l i m i n a ry fin d i n g s. It looks ve ry likely that our fie l d
collections will reveal many new species, possibly
including 20 polychaete worms and many records
for this area, such as 20 new plant species and five
new fis h e s.We have also discovered that a species of
reef coral once thought rare in Brazil, Stephanoco-
enia michelenii, is actually common.
To our dismay, fish populations seem to be
fewer in number than expected and many of the
individual fish tend to be small.The closer we come
to fishing communities, the wo rse the situat i o n
appears to be.
S e veral months of analysis remain before we
release our final conclusions.The next step will be
to put this inform ation in the hands of conservat i o n
managers. Beyond the mud-choked waters of the
C a r avelas River lie essential areas of biodive rs i t y.We
cannot afford to lose them simply because we
couldn’t evaluate their extraordinary wealth. ■
Setting sail
For three weeks this past Fe b r u a r y, B razilian marine scien-
tists and international conservation experts teamed up
to survey the Abrolhos Bank as part of the Rapid A s s e s s m e n t
P r o g ram (RAP) set up by Conservation International, a n
NGO based in Wa s h i n g t o n . RAP has launched a total of 29
expeditions—exploring land,freshwater and marine envi-
ronments—which have resulted in the discovery of hundreds
of new species, improved biodiversity management by iden-
tifying priorities at the local and global levels, and led to the
creation of six protected areas in five countries.
In contrast to the world’s two great areas of coral reefs—
in the Indo-Pa c i fic and the Caribbean Sea—Bra z i l ’s coral reefs
are not very rich in biodiversity, but they do harbour a large
number of endemic species. The main focus of the A b r o l h o s
survey was less on finding new species and more on helping
local managers understand how different parts of the bank com-
pare in terms of biodiversity and environmental threat. M a n y
of the sites we selected for our survey had never before been
s c i e n t i fically inventoried.
The Abrolhos Bank is the single largest area of coral reefs
in the southern A t l a n t i c ,covering about 8,000 km2 off the sou-
theastern corner of the Brazilian state of Bahia. As far as we
k n o w, there is no other place on earth where you can see a kind
of coral reef pinnacle known as a c h a p e i r ã o, which look like
giant mutant mushrooms, overgrown with fans of fire coral and
round knobs of endemic brain cora l .
Months of preparation went into the expedition.Wea-
ther was a major concern because most of the bank consists
of loose sediments which are easily stirred up by wa v e
action and create underwater “ d u s t ”s t o r m s. Fo r t u n a t e l y, w e
ended up with 18 days blessed by sunshine and light winds.
In the coming months, our science team will be analy-
zing the results to help us formulate a list of recommenda-
tions and priorities for conserving the marine biodiversity of
the Abrolhos Bank. ■
+ …
http://www.conservation.org
The Dusky damselfish (Stegastes fuscus) is one of the many species found 
only in Brazilian waters.
Nature makes nothing in
va i n .
A r i s t o t l e,
G reek philosopher 
(384-322 B. C. )
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
U n c h a r t e d
t e r r i t o r y
Pa ra d o x i c a l l y, scientists know more about the stars in our galaxy than about the number 
of species living on Earth
Coined by American researchers in the mid-
1980s, the term biodiversity has been in the
media spotlight ever since. It is a highly
complex concept which is still not widely unders-
tood by the general public. For scientists,the area
of research it covers remains uncharted territory.
According to the Convention on Biological
Diversity adopted in Rio de Janeiro (Brazil) in
1992, biodiversity is defined as “the variability
among living organisms from all sources inclu-
ding, inter alia, terrestrial, marine and other aqua-
tic ecosystems and the ecological complexes of
which they are part; this includes diversity within
species and of ecosystems.”
In plain English, biodiversity is both an idea
and a physical reality. As an idea, it refers to the
“variability” of living organisms, namely to their
ability to evolve in space and time, to adapt and
to survive.But it is also a physical reality, compri-
sing all living organisms and the relationships bet-
ween them. The concept of biodiversity can be
broken down into three different levels: genes,
species* and ecosystems*.
S u rp rising as it may seem, scientists know more
about the number of stars in our galaxy than they
do about the number of species living on Eart h .
Taxonomists* have inve n t o ried approx i m ately 
1.7 million living organisms—plants, animals and
micro-organisms (bacteri a , v i ru s e s , f u n gi , e t c. ) .
But a host of others exist in nature and it’s any b o-
d y ’s guess exactly how many. The most common
e s t i m ates va ry between eight and 15 million, bu t
some range up to 100 million. It would appear that
the environments with the highest number of ende-
mic* species are humid tropical forests.
2,000 apple varieties
identified worldwide
With the exception of mammals, the higher
plants and birds, scientists are rather unfamiliar
with species—and so they are light years away
from understanding everything there is to know
about genetic diversity. On the one hand, each
individual in the same species possesses a multi-
tude of genes that are responsible for its own cha-
r a c t e ri s t i c s. Humans have approx i m at e l y
100,000, and researchers have not yet identified
them all. On the other hand, genetic diversity is
expressed through the existence of distinct popu-
lations within the same species. For example,
some 2,000 varieties of apple have been identified
worldwide. For thousands of years, humans have
taken advantage of genetic diversity to domestica-
te wild species, particularly through cross-bree-
ding. Today, biotechnology* allows scientists to
go faster and further by creating new varieties of
transgenic* plants and animals.
In nature, species are not isolated but live in
r e l ationship with larger ecological complexe s ,
which make up, with their physical environment,
the planet’s ecosystems. Here again, scientists
acknowledge that they know very little about how
ecosystems work (see pp. 26-27) and the role they
play in the diversity of living organisms. ■
* These terms are defined in the glossary opposite.
+ …
Biodiversity in Questions, a series of colour wallcharts for
teachers and students, published by UNESCO/MAB in 1998.
Global Biodiversity Assessment, UNEP/Cambridge
University Press, 1995.
www.wri.org
www.iucn.org
www.conservation.org
Known and estimated total number of species
Species Known number Estimated total number Accuracy
Insects 950 000 8 000 000 poor
Fungi 70 000 1 000 000 poor
Arachnids 5 000 750 000 poor
Nematodes 15 000 500 000 poor
Viruses 5 000 500 000 very poor
Bacteria 4 000 400 000 very poor
Plants 250 000 300 000 good
Protozoans 40 000 200 000 very poor
Algae 40 000 200 000 very poor
Molluscs 70 000 200 000 moderate
Crustaceans 40 000 150 000 moderate
Vertebrates 45 000 50 000 good
World total (all groups) 1 700 000 12 500 000 very poor
Source : World Conservation Monitoring Centre ;Global Environment Outlook 2000 (UNEP, Earthscan).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 21
B i o d i v e rs i t y: a friend for life
The Earth’s 25 “ h o t s p o t s ”
What can be done to ensure that every dollar invested
in the conservation of biodiversity pays off? The selec-
tion of 25 “hotspots”,the most ecologically rich places on
the planet,is one step towards answering that question.
A team of researchers led by British scientist Norman
Myers (Oxford University) and the NGO Conservation Inter-
national made the selection.They hope that their choice will
lead to a worldwide conservation campaign focused on
the 25 sanctuaries. Most of the sites are in the tropics. F i v e
of them are in the Mediterranean region.Their conserva t i o n
will probably cost $500 million a year.
Ta ken together, the sites cover an area as large as
Greenland (1.4 per cent of the Earth’s surface) and may har-
bour 44 per cent of the Earth’s plant and 35 per cent of its
v e r t e b rate species.They do not include areas rich in endemic
species that are not yet under threat from humans. Fo r
e x a m p l e, the forest in French Guyana has a population
density of under five inhabitants per km2, but according to
a recent report by the NGO Population Action International,
the population density in the 25 “ h o t s p o t s ” is twice as
high as the world average.
Although this approach may be effective, it is not uni-
versally accepted by the scientific community. Critics argue
that too little is known about the geographical distribution
and richness of biodiversity to identify priority areas.They say
the 25 hotspots are too focused on tropical forests and
neglect deserts, m e a d o w s, t u n d ra and temperate forests, a s
well as the wealth of marine biodiversity. ■
G l o s s a r y
Biotechnology: any technological application that uses
biological systems, living organisms, or derivatives
thereof, to make or modify agricultural or industrial
products or processes
Conservation: sound management of biological
resources, ensuring their long-term viability
Ex situ conservation: conservation of elements of
biological diversity outside their natural habitat
In situ conservation: conservation of ecosystems and
natural habitats, maintenance and reconstitution of
viable populations of species in their natural habitat,
and,in the case of domesticated and cultivated species,
in the habitat where their distinctive characters
developed
Ecosystem: a dynamic complex of plant,animal and
micro-organism communities and their non-living
environment interacting as a functional unit
Species: a group of organisms which are naturally
capable of interbreeding because of their genetic and
physical resemblance
Endemic species: species present within a localized
area (e.g.an ecosystem,island, or country)
Protection: prohibition or reduction of human activities
in natural areas in order to maintain biodiversity
Taxonomy: the study, designation and classification of
living forms
Transgenic: used to describe a living organism into
which genetic material has been introduced from
another species in order to cause new characteristics to
appear ■
California
Floristic
Province
Choco/
Darien/
Western Ecuador
Central
Chile
Tropical Andes
Brazil’s
Cerrado
Brazil’s
Atlantic
Forest
Cape Floristic
Province
Madagascar
Mediterranean
Basin
Caucasus
Indo-Burma
South Central
China
Philippines
W. African
Forests
Eastern Arc
and Coastal
Forests of
Tanzania/
Kenya
Succulent
Karoo
Mesoamerica
Polynesia/
Micronesia
Polynesia/
Micronesia
New
Caledonia
New
Zealand
Southwest
Australia
Sundaland Wallacea
Western
Ghats and
Sri Lanka
Caribbean
Plants seem 
to have been sown
with profusion over the
Earth like
the stars in the sky to
invite man 
by way of pleasure and
curiosity to 
the study of nature.
Je a n - Jacques Rousseau,
F rench writer and philosopher
( 1 7 1 2 - 1 7 7 8 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
In the Amazon Basin the greatest violence can
begin as a flicker of light beyond the horizon.
There, in the bowl of the night sky, an approa-
ching thunderstorm sends lightning bolts that
illuminate the wall of the rain forest. Spear-nosed
bats fly through the tree crowns, palm vipers coil
in the roots of orchids, jaguars walk the river’s
edge, and around them grow 800 species of trees,
more than are native to North America. A thou-
sand species of butterflies,six per cent of the enti-
re world fauna, wait for the dawn.
About the orchids, we know little. About the
fli e s , b e e t l e s , and fungi we know almost nothing.
Rainforests like the Amazon with their my t h - i n s p i-
ring plants and animals are still mostly unexplored.
B i o l o gists believe that they shelter more than half
of the wo r l d ’s plant and animal species. Tr a gi c a l l y,
they are being quickly torn down by human activi-
t y. It is difficult to assess quantitat i vely the loss of
species there and elsewhere because we do not
k n ow the precise number of species that exist on
e a rt h . Probably fewer than 10 per cent of them
h ave even been gi ven a  scientific name. A n d
extinction is hard to observe .We don’t see the last
bu t t e r fly of its species snatched from the air by a
bird or the last orchid of a certain kind killed by the
collapse of its supporting tree.
We know from the fossil record that six gr e at
extinction events have occurred in the past half bil-
lion ye a rs.The latest of these eve n t s , caused by a gi a n t
m e t e o rite strike near present-day Yu c atan (Mexico)
65 million ye a rs ago, ended the age of dinosaurs.
These catastrophes va riously obliterated 30 to 90 per
cent of the wo r l d ’s plant and animal species. A f t e r-
wa r d ,e volution replaced the biodive rsity ve ry slow l y,
d u ring periods of millions of ye a rs.
Equilibrium
B i o l o gists agree that we are now in the earliest
stages of a seventh mass extinction eve n t , c a u s e d
not by an act of nature but entirely by human acti-
v i t y.The current rate of extinction is generally esti-
m ated to be 100 to 1,000 times higher than it wa s
before the ori gin of modern humanity about half a
million ye a rs ago.Throughout most of the geologi-
cal past, individual species and their descendants
l i ved for an average of roughly one million ye a rs ,
and disappeared naturally at about one species per
million each ye a r. On a grand scale, new species
replaced vanishing ones at about the same rat e .N o
D o o m e d
to early d e m i s e
◗ E d ward O. W i l s o n
Many biologists believe we are in the midst of one of the great extinction spasms 
of geological history. This time however, human activity, not nature, is the culprit
◗ Professor of Science and Curator
in Entomology at Harvard
University and the winner of many
scientific awards in addition to two
Pulitzer prizes for his books, in
particular The Diversity of Life
(Harvard University Press, 1992),
which inspired this text.
In Sumatra,Indonesia,a Kubu tribesman contemplates a calcinated forest area,used by generations for hunting 
and gathering medicinal plants.
Forests precede people.
Deserts follow them.
F rançois René 
de Chateaubriand,
F rench poet (1768-1848)
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
B i o d i v e rs i t y: a friend for life
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 23
m o r e . Not only has the extinction rate soared, bu t
also the birth rate of new species is falling as the
natural environment is reduced by human action.
According to estimates by the World Conser-
vation Union (IU C N) , about one quarter of the wo r l-
d’s mammals and more than a tenth of its remai-
ning birds are at a high risk of extinction. O n e - fif t h
of all reptile species, a quarter of all amphibians
and as many as 34 per cent of all fishes (mostly fre-
shwater species) are in similar jeopardy.And these
p r o p o rtions only refer to species we know relat i-
vely we l l . In the less studied gr o u p s , more than 500
insect species, 400 crustaceans and 900 molluscs
are also threat e n e d , according to IU C N, figures that
are surely vast underestimat e s. F i n a l l y, about an
eighth of the wo r l d ’s flowe ring plants are edgi n g
toward extinction.
Human demographic success has brought the
world to this cri s i s. Human beings have become a
hundred times more numerous than any other
large land animal in the history of life. By eve ry
c o n c e i vable measure, humanity is ecologi c a l l y
a b n o rm a l . Our species appropri ates between 20
and 40 per cent of solar energy captured in organic
m at e rial by land plants. There is no way we can
d r aw upon the resources of the planet to this
d e gree without reducing many other species to
r a rity or extinction.
The leading cause of the decline is the des-
truction of natural habitats to make more room
for urban and farming areas and to extract tim-
ber, ore, and other natural resources. Not many
habitats in the world covering a square kilometre
contain fewer than a thousand species of plants
and animals. Patches of rainforest and coral reef
harbour tens of thousands of species, even after
they have been partly chipped away by human
intervention.
But when an entire habitat is destroye d ,a l m o s t
all of the species specialized to live in it are destroye d .
Not just eagles and pandas disappear but also the
s m a l l e s t , still uncensused inve rt e b r at e s , algae and
f u n gi , the invisible playe rs that make up the founda-
tion of the ecosystem.
Celebrity pandas
For ye a rs ,c o n s e rvationists often focused on sav i n g
“ s t a r ” species like pandas as opposed to the entire
ecosystem in which they live . N ow, with a better
u n d e rstanding of the extinction process, they have
switched gears by, for example, focusing on the need
to protect particularly rich environments that contain
numerous vulnerable species, r e f e rred to as biodi-
ve rsity “ h o t s p o t s ” (see page 21).
The second major cause of extinction is the
invasion of alien species. When Polynesian voya-
gers set shore in Hawaii around 400 A.D., the
islands were a special kind of paradise.Their lush
forests and fertile valleys contained no mosqui-
toes, ants, poisonous spiders nor snakes or plants
with thorns or poisons. All these are now abun-
dant. Human commerce introduced invasive spe-
cies, deliberately or by accident. As the natural
habitats were decimated and the alien invaders
pressed on, the original fauna and flora have
retracted. Most are now rare or extinct.
The third major cause of decline is pollution.
Freshwater faunas and floras, for example, are
especially vulnerable to the increasing flood of
industrial and agricultural pollution. The fourth
agent of destruction, destined to rise in impor-
tance in the future, is global warming, which itself
is the result of pollution by excess greenhouse
gases. Among the more fragile environments most
threatened are the arctic tundras and the unique
South African fynbos (scrubland) “trapped” on
the tip of the continent.
Shrinking rainforests 
Just how fast is dive rsity disappearing? We are fa r
from an exact answe r , except to say,“ c at a s t r o p h i c a l l y
fa s t ” .Yet it is possible to get a handle on the ri c h e s t
e nvironment of all, the tropical rainforests. By loo-
king at the rate of reduction of the forest area, we can
roughly estimate the extinction rates of species.F i rs t ,
we must dispel the myth of the regenerat i ve powe r
of rainforests, which are actually among the most fra-
gile habitat s. More than half of the area of the forest
s u r face worldwide consists of acidic and nutri e n t -
poor soil.When the forest is cut and bu rned by fa r-
m e rs , the ash and decomposing ve g e t ation flu s h
enough nutrients into the soil to support vigorous
new herbaceous and shrubby gr owth for two or three
ye a rs. But as the nutrient levels decline, the land can
no longer support healthy crops and forage. So the
fa rm e rs must add fertilizer or move on to slash-and-
bu rn the next patch of forest.
In prehistoric times, the great forests—the
greenhouses of planet Earth—covered 14 to 18
million square kilometres. Only about half of the
original area remains. Much of the destruction is
recent, with about one million square kilometres
cleared every five to ten years. If this destruction
rate continues, a quarter or more of the remai-
ning rainforest will be gone by 2025.
N ow let’s conservat i vely assume that the forests
presently shelter 10 million species and focus exclu-
s i vely on the impact of deforestat i o n .We wo n ’t eve n
consider species lost to over-hunting or those erased
by new diseases, alien weeds and animals such as rat s.
Within these cautious parameters , 27,000 species are
doomed each ye a r. In other wo r d s , 74 will disappear
or start their descent to endangered status eve ry day,
three each hour.
If rainforests are as rich in diversity as most
biologists think, their reduction alone will elimi-
nate at least five to ten per cent of all the species
on earth. I think that a far greater number of spe-
cies are on the edge, perhaps irreversibly so.
Clearly we are in the midst of one of the great
extinction spasms of geological history. Humanity
needs a moral awakening together with all of the
scientific and technological ingenuity it can bring
to bear, in order to avoid impoverishing the pla-
net for all generations to come. We can, we must
find the way. ■
The Russian forests are
going down under the
a x .
Millions of trees are
p e r i s h i n g , the homes of
wild animals and birds
are being laid to wa s t e,
the rivers are dwindling
and drying up,
wonderful scenery is
disappearing never to
r e t u r n . (…) 
The climate is ruined,
and every day 
the earth is growing
poorer and more
h i d e o u s.
Anton Chekhov,
Russian writer (1860-1904)
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
Too valuable 
for price-tags
◗ Sophie Boukhari
Why should biological diversity be protected? Scientists are putting 
forth many new answers : some to convince the public and decision-make rs 
and others they consider scientifically valid 
Eve ry week it seems, b i o l o gi s t s , a n t h r o p o l o gists or
e nvironmental scientists publish studies with a new
reason explaining why it is vital to slow down the
depletion of biodive rs i t y. For example, in early March
t wo A m e rican scholars , James Kirchner and Anne We l l ,
wrote in the British review N at u r e t h at , after an era of
mass extinction, it took nature much longer than anyo n e
had previously thought to reach its current level of ri c h-
ness and dive rs i t y.
If humans continue destroying wild habitats at the
c u rrent pace, not only will we cause a major new crisis in
the history of life, it will take nature at least 10 million
ye a rs to recove r.T h at stunning argument bemuses some
s c i e n t i s t s , who say that in just five million ye a rs , H o m o
s a p i e n s and the other large ve rt e b r ates will have gone the
way of the dinosaurs. So why care about what happens
after that? 
“The question is not what will happen to tigers 10
million ye a rs from now,” s ays Michel Bat i s s e ,who hel-
ped set up UNESCO’s biosphere reserves and is on the
board of directors of the non-governmental organiza-
tion Conservation Intern at i o n a l . “ T h e r e ’s no doubt
they will no longer exist. But what about 100 ye a rs
from now? W h at we need is to find good reasons to
protect biodiversity in the next few centuries.”
The tempestuous debate over the “ va l u e ” of biodi-
ve rsity is sometimes skewed by the need to convince at
any price. Genuinely alarmed about the scope of the
destruction,some experts have taken up “ideological”
positions, says Talal Younes, executive director of the
I n t e rn ational Union of Biological Sciences. “ T h e y
think any argument that can help put the message
across is good,whether or not it is scientifically valid.”
The values most commonly invoked to raise public
awareness are economic and aesthetic. “The Western
public pictures biodiversity like Noah’s ark, with the
giraffe and the sequoia,the parrot and the tulip,” says
Batisse. In the industrialized countries,where wilder-
ness has become a rare, h i g h l y - p rized commodity,
people are willing to take action so that their gr a n d-
children will have the chance to see elephants roa-
ming free.
But Peter Bri d g e wat e r , director of UN E S C O’s eco-
l o gical sciences division, thinks biodive rs i t y ’s aes-
thetic value is relat i ve .“ People living in cities in New
Z e a l a n d , for example, think that whales are in gr e at
danger and should be protected from hunters. B u t
Inuit in Alaska will tell you that whales are an impor-
tant part of their diet and that they should be allowe d
to sustainably hunt whales.Who is right? ”
A gene pool
for biotechnology
The aesthetic argument works with a cert a i n
segment of the general public, but it falls short of
c o nvincing decision-makers.“When ministers hold
a meeting, you have to demonstrate the economic
a d vantages of preserving biodive rs i t y,” s ays Bat i s s e .
T h at task is all the harder because gove rn m e n t s
sometimes deri ve tremendous economic benefit
from the destruction of ecosystems, e s p e c i a l l y
forests,and they are under pressure from powerful
lobbies (the timber and paper industri e s , f o r
example). Researchers reply that biodiversity is a
boon for the tourism industry (see pp. 3 1 - 3 2 ) ,h e l p s
to cure illnesses (pp.30-31) and to feed people at
little cost (pp.27-29) and constitutes an inestimable
gene pool for biotechnology.
In the past several ye a rs , scientists have also
come up with a battery of figures aimed at putting
a monetary value on the services ecosystems pro-
vide for human societies (see pp. 2 6 - 2 7 ) .A group of
A m e rican scholars estimates their wo rth at $319
billion a year in the United States (5 per cent of the
U.S.GDP),and nearly three trillion dollars a year
wo r l d w i d e . The leading ecological economist,
R o b e rt Costanza, has published other estimat e s
assessing the total value of services rendered by
biodiversity at $33 trillion a year—more than the
GDP of all the world’s countries combined.◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
2 S c i e n t i fic truths
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
B i o d i v e rs i t y: a friend for life
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 25
While these figures might hit home, m a ny scien-
tists consider them to be totally off the mark. Peter
B ri d g e water goes even furt h e r , arguing that the
attempt to put price-tags is not only a “ waste of
time” but dangerous. “The economically-minded
people are setting up a system of discri m i n ation by
c o n s i d e ring some species and ecosystems to be
valuable (because they provide ‘ p r o fit a b l e ’s e rv i c e s )
and deeming others worthless. Ecological systems
are not built-up on the basis of discrimination but
c o - o p e r at i o n .They must be considered as a whole.”
B ri d g e water says biodive rsity is too valuable to be
e va l u at e d . It is priceless because it guarantees the secu-
rity of the human race. It would be idiotic,he say s ,t o
d e s t r oy ecosystems which make air breat h a b l e , the cli-
m ate tolerable,water drinkable and soil fertile (see pp.
2 6 - 2 7 ) .To those who argue that technological pro-
gress will offset environmental damage,he retorts that
the costs would be exorbitant.And technological solu-
t i o n s , he adds,will not hold up in the long run because,
unlike nat u r e , they will be incapable of adapting to
c h a n g e .W h at ’s more, adds Jeffrey McNeelly, of the
World Conservation Union, the most advanced tech-
n o l o gies are based on mechanisms observed in living
things—an additional reason to take care of them. I n s-
tead of pitting nature and technology against one ano-
t h e r ,b i o d i ve rsity specialists are counting on an alliance
b e t ween them to better manage the environment and
to develop ecological engi n e e ring (which would make
it possible, for example, to restore the functions of a
d e graded tropical forest).
Last but not least, they say, i n s t rumentalist argu-
ments pale in comparison to the only one that really
m at t e rs : b i o d i ve rsity is the essence of life. “ W h at is
l i f e ,when you get down to it?”asks Robert Barbault,
director of the French Institute of Basic and A p p l i e d
E c o l o g y. “It is what lasts. And it lasts because it
adapts to changes in the environment by dive rs i-
f y i n g . A host of species has continued demonstra-
ting this for over four billion ye a rs. Humans are no
d i f f e r e n t , e ven though they are more sophisticat e d .
They face the same problems: e at or be eat e n . P r e-
d at o rs try to kill as much prey as possible and prey
t ries to escape from predat o rs.T h at leads to co-evo-
lution based on genetic and behavioural va ri a b i l i t y.
I t ’s a race that never ends,” s ays Barbault.“ D i ve rs i t y
is the ve ry reason for the success of  living pheno-
m e n a , and therefore for our own existence.” But if
living things have always adapted, w hy wo rry now ?
Most specialists are cat e g o ri c a l : to regenerat e , l i f e
needs time and space, t wo things it no longer has
because of the pace and scope of the damage caused
by people.
Becoming aware
of our interdependence
Because of its biological and technological pro-
gr e s s , Homo sapiens are jeopardizing their own we l-
fa r e .The present environmental cri s i s ,s ays Robert
Barbault,has the advantage of helping to raise the
We s t e rn individual’s awareness of our connections
with nature,which has long been considered as an
e x t e rnal entity to be tamed. “ We ’re beginning to
understand that our planet must be managed and,
c o n s e q u e n t l y, to think about the new civilizat i o n
we want to build.The ability to conceive a project
is precisely what sets us apart from other species.We
will have to change our behaviour, especially diet
and technology, and our mentalities.We must have
a different, more ecological vision of the world and
be more aware of our interdependence with all
other living things.” And perhaps, a touch more
humble. ■
In Madagascar, an Antandroy tribesman holds the fossilized egg of an elephant bird (Aepyornis maximus), a species that
became extinct about 500 years ago.
The Earth is our mother,
the eagle 
our cousin.
The tree draws 
blood from us and the
g rass is growing.
Our ancestors 
told us:
Now that we have done
all these things, y o u
must watch 
over them 
and ensure that they are
f o r e v e r.
It is in this way 
that human beings
became 
the custodians of 
the planet.
Gagudju account of cre a t i o n
( A u s t ra l i a )
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
In my view, b i o d i ve rs i t y ’s fundamental value is
neither aesthetic nor economic but env i r o n-
m e n t a l , e ven though most people are largely
u n aware of this.The value of biodive rsity is often
measured in terms of the number of species
living in a gi ven area. But the interactions bet-
ween the many species in an ecosystem, and bet-
ween them and the env i r o n m e n t ’s physical and
chemical components are also ve ry import a n t .
This highly intri c ate web of relationships makes
an ecosystem more valuable than the sum of the
species it contains.
Ecosystems perform services that are essential
for the survival of the human species. They fix
carbon in the atmosphere and produce oxygen,
protect soil from erosion and keep it fertile, filter
water and replenish aquifers, provide pollination
and anti-parasite agents and so on.
The first two of these services are closely rela-
ted to each other. They result from photosynthe-
sis, whereby green plants, starting with algae,
absorb carbon dioxide (CO2) and emit oxygen.
For millions of years, the balance between the
various gases in the atmosphere remained stable.
But with the coming of the industrial revolution,
humans began burning increasing amounts of
fossil fuels. Today, three billion tonnes of carbon
build up in the atmosphere each year, and natural
ecosystems can no longer absorb all these emis-
sions—especially since they are disappearing at
an alarming rate. Deforestation alone releases
such tremendous amounts of CO2 and other
gases, such as methane, that it has become the
second-leading cause of global warming.
Storing freshwater, protecting soil and kee-
ping it fertile are three other closely related func-
tions. Ecosystems are veritable “freshwater facto-
ries”. They absorb rainwater and slowly filter it
through the soil before draining it towa r d s
streams, rivers, lakes and underground aquifers
that supply us with the precious liquid.When the
vegetal ground cover is degraded, the water cycle
is disrupted. Rain strikes the bare earth, washing
away huge amounts of nutritional substances.
Reservoirs, lakes and rivers silt up and terrible
mudslides, such as those that recently ripped
E c o s y s t e m s, our u n k n o w n
p ro t e c t o rs
◗ José Sarukhán
How ecosystems work and what part they play in biodiversity remain a mystery.
But we do know that they perform a host of invaluable services for the human species
◗ Director of the Ecology Institute
at the University of Mexico City,
president of Diversitas, an
international biodiversity
programme sponsored by UNESCO
and the International Council for
Science 
Nickel mining in New Caledonia has severely eroded the upper parts of certain massifs and has had a devastating impact
on the environment.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
B i o d i v e rs i t y: a friend for life
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 27
For thousands of ye a rs , fa rm e rs have used the
genetic va ri ation in wild and cultivated plants to
d e velop their crops and raise new breeds of live-
s t o c k . Genetic dive rsity gi ves species the ability to
adapt to changing env i r o n m e n t s , including new pests
and diseases and new climatic conditions. P l a n t
genetic resources—that component of genetic dive r-
sity of actual or potential use to humanity—prov i d e
the raw mat e rial for breeding new va rieties of crops.
◗ Director General of the Rome-
based International Plant Genetic
Resources Institute, devoted to
promoting the conservation and
use of plant genetic resources
T h e s e , in turn ,p r ovide a basis for more productive
and resilient production systems that are better able
to cope with such stresses as drought or ove r gr a z i n g
and can reduce the potential for soil erosion.The use
of genetic dive rs i t y — o n - fa rm , through field experi-
m e n t ation or in sophisticated gene transfer proce-
dures—remains arguably the best route to securi n g
our food and that of our children.
Although science has made enormous strides in
through Central A m e ri c a , Mexico and
Mozambique, kill thousands of people and cause
incalculable damage.
Uncertain reaction 
to climate change
Despite years of research, scientists still know
very little about how ecosystems work. We are
generally incapable of predicting how they will
react to certain transformations in the environ-
ment, especially climate changes. Nor do we
know any more about whether a species present
in a given environment is superfluous or “repla-
ceable”,even when it is very rare. Likewise, we do
not know which key species are indispensable to
maintaining an ecosystem, with a few exceptions
such as pine forests, where that tree is obviously
the dominant species.
We know even less about the part biologi c a l
d i ve rsity itself plays in maintaining ecosystems and
the services they perform . One simple example is a
highly dive rs i fied forest that absorbs carbon diox i-
de—a vital function, as we have seen, for limiting
global wa rm i n g . Suppose the forest is cleared to
make way for a single-crop forest. The service will
still be perform e d , perhaps even better at firs t
because yo u n g, fa s t - gr owing trees absorb more
C O2 than old ones, which regenerate slow l y. B u t
w h at will happen in the long term? After seve r a l
d e c a d e s , the consequences of the loss of biodive r-
sity will probably be felt. Replacing many species
with a single one will have certainly depleted the
soil and, in the long term , s l owed down the forest’s
gr owth and consequently its ability to absorb CO2.
More generally, diversified ecosystems seem
more productive. Specialists remain wary about
their conclusions, but today they believe that bio-
diversity helps ecosystems to resist alien species
and diseases and to recover faster in the event of
disruption. In the face of doubt, and to find out
more about them, it is better to preserve as many
different ecosystems as possible.
A costly lesson 
for New York City
Most people take it for granted that ecosys-
tems will carry on performing services without
receiving anything in return. They think nature
will continue benefiting humanity, no matter how
much damage is done.The survival of organisms
other than our own species is perceived as a frill
that future generations can live without.
These preconceived ideas are wrong and dan-
g e r o u s , as the city of New York has recently come
to realize.The city’s water has always enjoyed such
a good reputation that it was sold throughout the
n o rt h e a s t e rn United Stat e s. Its quality was due to
the Catskill Mountains’ n atural puri fic ation sys-
t e m . But that ecosystem has suffered so much from
p o l l u t i o n , especially fertilizer run-off from fa rm s ,
t h at by the late 1990s New Yo r k ’s water had beco-
me undri n k a b l e . The city planned to build a puri-
fic ation plant, whose cost was put at between six
and eight billion dollars , not including the $300
million in yearly operating costs—an astronomical
bill for a service that had always been free! T h e
p rice was so staggering that the city eve n t u a l l y
decided to restore the Catskill Mountains’ d e gr a-
ded environment at a cost of only one billion dol-
l a rs.
This story clearly illustrates where our interests
l i e . We must preserve ecosystems and the condi-
tions that enable our planet to ensure the surv i va l
of Homo sapiens o r , at least, the short - t e rm mainte-
nance of our current quality of life. ■
Genetic diversity 
and food s e c u r i t y
◗ Geoffrey C. H a w t i n
Maintaining a diversity of crops and varieties is a key to survival for millions 
of farmers living on impoverished land
It should not be
believed that all beings
exist for 
the sake of man.
On the contrary,
all other beings 
too have been intended
for 
the sake of something
else.
Moses Maimonides,
t h e o l o g i a n , Jewish philosopher
and doctor (1135-1204)
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
improving the world’s ability to feed itself over the
past three decades, we cannot afford to rest idle.
Nearly 800 million people in the developing wo r l d
do not have enough to eat.1 In these regions, the
rural poor represent about 73 per cent of the people
living in pove rt y. They often live in marginal or
unsuitable fa rming areas, such as zones with saline
soils, arid conditions, or degraded or hilly areas.
Often isolated from other fa rms and far from urban
a r e a s , m a ny poor fa rm e rs have barely benefit e d
from agricultural developments elsewhere. In many
cases they do not have access to commercially bred
high yielding crop va ri e t i e s. D i ve rsity flo u ri s h e s
and remains important under such conditions.
Selections and breeding
Poor fa rm e rs are well aware of the relat i o n s h i p
b e t ween the stability and sustainability of their pro-
duction systems and the dive rsity of crops and crop
va rieties on their lands.Their management and use
of a dive rse range of plants has often helped them to
s u rv i ve under the most difficult conditions. By gr o-
wing a range of different crops, fa rm e rs have a better
chance of meeting their needs.These might be crops
t h at mature at different times or that can be easily
stored to help to ensure a stable food supply throu-
ghout the ye a r.They may also help fa rm e rs prov i d e
a nutritionally balanced diet for their fa m i l i e s ,e x p l o i t
different environmental niches that exist on their
l a n d , or dive rsify their income sources.
I m p o rt a n t l y, the genetic dive rsity contained in dif-
ferent va rieties provides fa rm e rs with options to deve-
l o p, through selection and breeding, new and more
p r o d u c t i ve crops that are resistant to pests and diseases.
The result may be a vast range of local va rieties of crops
gr own by fa rm e rs in any one area. In the A n d e s ,f o r
e x a m p l e , fa rming communities use about 3,000 dif-
ferent va rieties of potat o e s , and in Java fa rm e rs may
plant more than 600 species in a single home garden.
Not respecting dive rsity can incur high costs: i n
1 8 t h - c e n t u ry Ireland, where potatoes were the only
s i g n i ficant source of food for about one third of the
p o p u l at i o n , fa rm e rs came to rely almost entirely on
one ve ry fertile and productive va ri e t y, which prove d
susceptible to the deva s t ating potato blight fungus.
The resulting famine caused the death or emigra-
tion of more than 20 per cent of the population.
The value of diversity goes well beyond its abi-
lity to support stable production systems in margi n a l
e nv i r o n m e n t s. As the wo r l d ’s human populat i o n
ri s e s ,e nvironmental problems (desert i fic at i o n, d e f o-
r e s t at i o n , e r o s i o n , e t c.) are intensifying. C l i m at e
c h a n g e , p a rticularly global wa rm i n g, could bri n g
about drastic changes in the location of the wo r l d ’s
a gr o - e c o l o gical zones. Fa rm e rs will require new crop
va rieties capable of producing under dive rse condi-
t i o n s , without adding ever-increasing amounts of fer-
t i l i z e rs and other agr o - c h e m i c a l s. Because of the
limited scope for gr owth in the wo r l d ’s cultivat e d
a r e a s , each new generation of va rieties will have to be
more productive than its predecessors.
Much has been written about the use of genetic
e n gi n e e ring in plant breeding. M o d e rn molecular
techniques can be used to transfer genes from one
living organism to another or to change the genetic
m at e rial within to produce more desirable traits.
Genetic engi n e e ring has enormous potential to help
s o l ve problems that have proved intractable using
c o nventional breeding approaches, such as deve l o p i n g
North America
Cranberry
Jerusalem artichoke
Muscadine grape
Sunflower
Andes/South
America
Cashew
Cayenne
Cocoa
Groundnut/peanut
Lima bean
Manioc
Pepper
Pineapple
Potato
Pumpkin
Mexico/Central America
Avocado
Common bean
Maize/Corn
Papaya
Pecan
Sweet potato
Tomato
Tabasco pepper
Vanilla
Belgium
Brussel sprout
Mediterranean
Asparagus
Broad bean
Cabbage
Cauliflower
Celery
Common grape
Globe artichoke
Mint
Oat
Parsnip
Sugar beet
North Africa
Cattle
Marjoram
1. See the Food and Health Organization’s 1999 Report on
the State of Food Insecurity in the World.
Caribbean
Grapefruit
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
B i o d i v e rs i t y: a friend for life
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 29
crop va rieties with in-built resistance to key pests and
diseases and tolerance to stresses such as drought.
H owe ve r , the possible impact of these techniques,p a r-
ticularly on human health and the env i r o n m e n t , i s
giving rise to fierce worldwide debat e .
Take the case of banana and its close relative
p l a n t a i n ,t wo of the developing wo r l d ’s most impor-
tant crops.Their improvement is hindered by the
sterility of most cultivars, a problem that can be
addressed through genetic engineering. It is now
possible to transfer gene constructs, such as those
a s s o c i ated with disease resistance, directly into
varieties with other desirable characteristics, dras-
tically reducing the need for pesticides. Currently,
many crops are sprayed more than 40 times with
fungicides to control the devastating banana and
plantain disease,Black Sigat o k a .The first transgenic
banana and plantain plants have been produced
and are now undergoing testing.
To d ay, research on genetic engi n e e ring is focused
on the development of commercial va rieties of the
wo r l d ’s major crops of interest to industrialized fa r-
m e rs. M a ny of the staple crops of importance to poor
fa rm e rs in developing countri e s , such as cassava ,b a n a-
n a s , beans and ya m s ,h ave received relat i vely little
at t e n t i o n .This situation is likely to continue as plant
breeding is increasingly pri vatized and biotechnology
becomes the fa s t - gr owing province of pri vate indus-
t ry. M e a n w h i l e , the high costs of the new technolo-
gies are quickly exceeding the capacity of many, if not
m o s t , public research institutions—both in deve l o-
ping and developed countries—to support them.T h u s ,
for the time being, increasing agri c u l t u r e ’s role in the
d e velopment of the wo r l d ’s poor is likely to continue to
depend on the identific at i o n , maintenance and use of
genetic dive rs i t y. ■
+ …
Website of the International Plant Genetic Resources
Institute: www.cgiar.org/ipgri
India/
Indo-Malaya
Black pepper
Breadfruit
Cardamon
Chicken
Chickpea
Citron
Dwarf wheat
Lime
Mango
Moth bean
Rice
Safflower
Sesame
Near East
Alfalfa
Barley
Cabbage
Eincorn Wheat
Fig
Goat
Hazelnut
Leek
Lentil
Pea
Pig
Plum
Rye
Shallot
Sheep
Spelt wheat
Sugar beet
Sweet cherry
Horn of Africa
Black-eye pea
Bread wheat
Castor bean
Coffee
Cowpea
Date palm
Finger millet
Mustard
Okra
Pearl millet
Sorghum
Yam
European
Siberian Region
Cattle
Chicory
Gooseberry
Kale
Lettuce
Licorice
Pear
Watercress
Central Asia
Almond
Apple
Carrot
Common grape
Cucumber
Garlic
Onion
Rhubarb
Spinach
East Asia
Buckwheat
Chive
Foxtail millet
Ginseng
Litchi
Mulberry
Peach
Radish
Soybean
Sweet orange
Tea
Turnip
Water chestnut
Southeast Asia
Apricot
Banana
Cinnamon and Cassia
Clove
Coconut palm
Eggplant
Indian almond
Lemon
Mung bean
Sugar cane
Tangerine
To market in Pe r u :f a r m e rs in the Andes cultivate up to 3,000 potato varieties.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
molecular biology, they have begun designing
tailor-made drugs. Knowing the shape of a given
biological “lock”, they use computers to design
the molecular “key” that may trigger the mecha-
nism resulting in a cure. This method works in
theory, but in practice it is extremely complicated
to create ex nihilo an artificial substance that is not
found in nature. Hence the advantage of combi-
ning natural molecules that result from 4.5 billion
years of evolutionary development.
Recent successes have confirmed the value of
using substances from nature. The discovery of
cy c l o s p o ri n , an immunosuppressant, in a
Norwegian mushroom has led to decisive pro-
gress in preventing the rejection of transplanted
organs. Researchers working for the American
pharmaceutical giant Merck & Co. have recently
detected a chemical component in a Congo
mushroom that acts like insulin and may be used
to make the much sought pill for diabetes. At the
same time, in vitro methods for detecting active
molecules have evolved. Pharmaceutical compa-
nies have giant robots capable of testing up to
100,000 samples a day.
Calling on 
local healers
N e ve rt h e l e s s , in practice the road leading from
plant to drug is still extremely long and fraught with
u n c e rt a i n t y. F i rs t , samples must be collected in stra-
t e gic places, where pri m a ry forest surv i ve s.They are
l o c ated in “ c o u n t ries in the inter-tropical zones of
A f ri c a , South A m e ri c a , Asia and the Pa c i fic,” s ay s
T h i e rry Séve n e t , research director at the French
Institute for Natural Substance Chemistry.
In the field, biological prospectors are follo-
wing three different and complementary leads.
Scientists collecting plants at random bring back
as many samples as they can for screening by
robots. But the traditional knowledge of local
healers can narrow down the search. Folk reme-
dies have led to the development of several drugs,
starting with quinine and digitaline. Researching
in the South Pacific, American ethno-botanist
Paul Cox recently studied a stem of Homolanthus
nutans that Samoans prepare for the treatment 
of fevers. Chemists scrutinizing the plant found
that it contains a known molecule, prostratine,
which acts upon the Aids virus. Lastly, using the
In Madagascar’s Isalo mountain range, t h e
guide stops. At his feet, a tiny flower displays its
pink petals. “This plant is good for cancer,” the
man says proudly. Long consumed to relieve hun-
ger, the Madagascar periwinkle was first descri-
bed by the French botanist Etienne de Flacourt
in 1645.Then, in the 1960s, it was discovered to
be effective in treating cancer.
Humans have always found substances in
nature to relieve their suffering and cure their ills.
In developing countries, 80 per cent of the popu-
lation relies on traditional remedies extracted
from plants to treat illnesses. Some “modern”
d rugs that contain a single active ingr e d i e n t
rather than a mixture of substances owe their
existence to natural biodiversity. Morphine, qui-
nine, digitaline and 116 other drugs made from
plants are in widespread use, according to
American pharmacologist Norman Farnsworth.
An estimated two-thirds of the drugs sold in
pharmacies are of natural origin. They account
for some $30 billion in sales every year.
There is an urgent need for therapeutic
research to find new treatments that can be help-
ful in fighting recent, emerging diseases such as
Aids as well as overcoming resistance to current
treatments for cancer,malaria and bacterial infec-
tions. Researchers are following several leads,
such as gene therapy, which is still in its earliest
stages, and drug design. With the advent of
O u t of the forest and 
into the bottle
◗ Cécile Guérin
Pharmaceutical companies are taking an increasing interest in plants, insects and bacteria. B u t
f rom nature to clinical trials, the road is a long one
Collecting species: a “bioprospector”on the job in Costa Rica.
◗ French science writer
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
N a t u re ’s
medicine chest
Relieving pain
18171: morphine is extracted
from poppy flowers.
Treating inflammation
1829:aspirin is extracted from
willow bark.
Regulating heartbeat
1868:digitaline is extracted
from digitalis.
Fighting malaria
1820:quinine is extracted from
cinchona bark.
1972:artemisine is extracted
from artemisia.
Preventing the rejection of
transplanted organs
1970:cyclosporin is extracted
from a Norwegian mushroom.
Fighting cancer
1958-1965:the derivatives
vinblastine and vincristine are
extracted from the Madagascar
periwinkle.
1971:taxol is extracted from
the Pacific yew.
1980:taxotere is extracted
from the European yew.
1 . Dates refer to the isolation of the
active ingredient, usually 10 to 15
years before the drug is marke t e d .
B i o d i v e rs i t y: a friend for life
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 31
chemo-taxonomic approach, scientists probe spe-
cies from the same family already reputed for
containing useful substances.
Once the samples are gat h e r e d , chemists take
ove r ,extracting and purifying substances from the raw
m at e rial in order to produce mixed or pure che-
mical components.T h e n , the extracts are tested to
d e t e rmine whether they are biologically active .At this
s t a g e , the screening process is extremely thorough.
G e n e r a l l y, a single molecule is kept out of 10,000
compounds analysed. A l t o g e t h e r , it takes 15 to 20
ye a rs from the time the plant is gathered in the forest
to the final clinical trials conducted before a drug can
be marketed.
Profit-sharing
P h a rmaceutical research is sluggish and
u n c e rt a i n , while the threats to biodive rsity are
i rr e ve rsibly and rapidly gaining ground (see pp.
2 2 - 2 3 ) . In the face of this urgency, which coin-
cides with rising interest on the part of resear-
c h e rs , prospecting projects are being deve l o p e d ,
despite the increasingly strong constraints on the
i n d u s t ry. Before the 1992 Earth Summit in Rio
de Ja n e i r o, We s t e rn laborat o ries—the only ones
t h at can afford to invest huge sums in research—
drew from the biodive rsity of the Southern coun-
t ries without giving them anything in return . B u t
in the past ten ye a rs or so, these countries have
demanded a share of the profits—and pharm a-
ceutical companies are beginning to listen. I n
1 9 9 1 , for the first time, Merck & Co. paid ove r
one million dollars to INBIO, Costa Rica’s
National Institute for Bi o d i ve rs i t y, to gain access
to the country ’s genetic resources. If a drug is
d e ve l o p e d , the institute will receive between two
and six percent of profit s , of which half must be
e a rmarked for the preservation of national parks.
In five other projects carried out by the United
S t ates with South A m e rican and A f rican coun-
t ri e s , U. S . u n i ve rsities are co-operating with local
o n e s. It remains to be seen how the indigenous
people who help in the selection of plants will be
r e m u n e r at e d .
In the shadows of the wo r l d ’s big pharm a c e u t i-
cal companies, smaller local laborat o ries have joi-
ned the green gold ru s h . M a d a g a s c a r ’s Institute of
Applied Research has begun a study of 12,000
n at i ve plants. Working with France’s Natural Hi s-
t o ry Mu s e u m , the institute has identified a sub-
stance that strengthens the effectiveness of chloro-
quine against malari a .With a bit of luck, this plant
from the S t ry c h n o s family will follow the same trail
blazed by the Madagascar peri w i n k l e . ■
B o r n e o : re a p i n g t h e
fruits of ecotourism
◗ Robert Basiuk
The Iban people are highly dependent on the riches 
of the forest for their survival, and tourism has become an added
incentive to protect this wealth
Since they settled in the Malaysian state of
S a r awak over 400 ye a rs ago, the Iban have
made the surrounding rainforest their super-
market and hardware store, tapping the tremendous
va riety of plants, animals and raw mat e rials for
their food,medicines, dwellings and rituals.
This region of nort h we s t e rn Borneo is identifie d
as one of the wo r l d ’s most biodive rs i t y - rich areas. I t s
resources are so important to the Iban that local cus-
t o m a ry laws stipulate taboos against felling cert a i n
t r e e s , killing va rious animals and cutting forest
areas containing valuable fruits and construction
materials.
The traditional Iban dwelling is the longhouse, a
s e m i - p e rmanent structure housing 20 or more fa m i-
lies in separate living apart m e n t s.Their main live l i-
hood is from fa rming (hill ri c e ) , fis h i n g, s m a l l - s c a l e
r e a ring of live s t o c k ,g at h e ring of jungle produce and
occasional hunting. Until recently, r e s i n s , r at t a n s ,
animal products and scented wood were among the
i m p o rtant items exchanged for non-forest goods
such as steel and cloth. Demand for some products
has ceased and with it their value as a barter trade
i t e m . Transition towards a cash economy has also
changed the needs of the villages.While supplies of
r attans and sandalwood have diminished, t o u rism has
emerged as a new market for biodive rsity over the past
ten to fifteen ye a rs.
Ulu A i , established by the Kuching-based ope-
rator Borneo Adventure, is one example of a new
g e n e r ation of tourism products promoting the intri-
c ate relationship between the rainforest and its
dwellers. The Ulu Batang Ai is a remote, unspoilt
a r e a : the ri ve rs are tree-lined and clear and the
landscape is rugged with steep hills giving rise to
many waterfalls.
◗ Canadian biologist who has lived
in Sarawak (Malaysia) since 1983.
Mr Basiuk has served as a wildlife
officer for the Sarawak National
Park,held various senior positions
with the state tourism board and
helped to set up Borneo Adventure.
Since 1998,he has worked as a
consultant on a variety of projects
related to tourism and natural
resource management.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
B e yond the Ai ri ver are the Lanjak Entimau W i l d-
life Sanctuary and the Batang Ai National Pa r k ,e s t a-
blished to protect the last wild population of orang-
u t a n .While the Iban living in this area are reasonably
s e l f - s u f ficient in terms of food and can manufa c t u r e
most of their daily necessities from local mat e ri a l s ,t h e y
did not—until recently—have a steady cash income as
the distance from markets makes cash crop fa rm i n g
and market gardening unfeasible.
Premium orang-utan
The village was first approached in 1986, s h o rt l y
after Borneo Adventure had been formed, to see if
its inhabitants would be interested in receiving visi-
t o rs in their longhouse.The arrangement proposed
was that the village would provide transport ,g u i d e s ,
food and accommodation and Borneo Adventure
would bring in the touri s t s. From the start , t h e
project aimed to bring visitors to experience the lon-
ghouse and up-ri ver lifestyle and to provide an
incentive for the community to conserve the local
wildlife—in this case cash earned from taking tou-
rists on jungle hikes.
The area is prized for its orang-utan populat i o n ,
a totally protected species although sporadic hun-
ting by outsiders has occurred in the past.While
local fa rm e rs would not harm the orang-utan them-
s e l ve s , they were reluctant to protect them from out-
side hunters, as they can cause extensive damage.
Because local village guides are tipped over and
above their daily wage when orang-utan are seen,
longhouse people now view this species as a precious
c o m m o d i t y, keeping track of their movements and
informing authorities if hunters are believed to be
in the area. A secondary benefit has been the re-
kindling of traditional stories and lore concerning
the links between the Iban and the orang-utan,
which are often referred to as “grandfathers”.
The village invo l vement in tourism has also bene-
fited other wildlife in the area. Fish catches have
r e c overed from the pre-tourism days when one of the
few sources of cash income was to sell the fish to
d ow n - ri ver bu ye rs.With no control over catch rat e s ,
the stocks were in danger of being depleted—and with
t h at an important source of protein and reve n u e .
With a reasonably steady altern at i ve cash flow from
t o u ri s m , stocks have now been stabilized.
In 1999, 26 families received over RM 300,000
($82,000) in touri s m - r e l ated pay. In addition to the
wages earned as guides,b o at dri ve rs and cooks, as we l l
as rental for the guesthouse, the village people also
e a rn money selling traditional handicrafts such as
woven blankets ($10,000 in 1999).This income has
also allowed the village to break out of the subsistence
a griculture cycle and dive rsify their economy to include
more efficient cash crops.The reduced demand for
expansion onto new land means that less forest is cut,
u l t i m ately providing more habitat for wildlife.
The project receives about 1,000 visitors a ye a r ,
considered a threshold number.Villagers are gra-
dually taking on more managerial roles, such as
ove rseeing quality control. Fe a ring that they could
lose a valuable source of income and employ m e n t ,
they are also intent on ensuring that the land sur-
rounding the longhouses is secured and managed by
them. They recently presented a proposal to the
government of Sarawak to this effect.Their desire
is to have the state land area beyond the longhouse
land and before the existing National Park offi-
cially designated as village conservation land to be
managed for tourism by the village.
As of today, the government has not answered
their proposal. In the meantime, visitors are still
enjoying the experience of the lush, tropical Iban
s u p e rmarket and sightings of wild orang-utan are on
the rise. ■
In Sarawak,the Iban people welcome some 1,000 tourists every year into their longhouses.
Species that go extinct
are lost forever. This is
not like Jurassic Pa r k .
Stuart Pimm,
British biologist (1949-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
B i o d i v e rs i t y: a friend for life
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 33
The 1992 Rio Convention on Biological Diversity
gives priority to in situ conservation in protected
areas. Why?
The key aim is to conserve all the ecological
e l e m e n t s — p l a n t s , a n i m a l s , soil and wat e r — a s
well as the interactions between them, which
maintain the evolutionary process. This kind of
approach is crucial in poor countries, which rare-
ly have the means to put together ex situ conser-
vation projects such as gene banks,zoos and bota-
nical gardens. It also guarantees access to data on
natural resources and to the results of research
carried out on their territory.
Why is it a good idea to create physical land links
between different parks?
E l e p h a n t s , for example, m i gr ate from dry areas
to wet ones as they need to. If you try to stop them,
you threaten their survival.Protected areas should
be linked by corridors that allow species to move
around and also permit genetic exchange between
wildlife from different regi o n s. More and more
reserves these days straddle national borders.
What are biggest threats to protected areas?
Lack of intern ational co-operation and sup-
p o rt . A f rican gove rn m e n t s , which can no longer
satisfy the basic needs of their populations, have
downgraded the importance of protecting nature.
In many countri e s ,d e c e n t r a l i z ation of authority to
r e gional bodies has complicated park management
too.You can’t create new parks in Africa any more
E c o p ro t e c t i o n :
an international g o - s l o w
P rotected areas are the key to conservation policies. But how should they be run? Fo r
Seydina Issa Sylla ◗, lack of international co-operation is the biggest pro b l e m
3 The next step
◗ Co-ordinator for West Africa of
the NGO Wetlands International
Villagers in Senegal’s Niokolo Koba park are closely involved in the management of this biosphere reserve.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
The world of pro t e c t e d
a re a s
Under the 1992 Rio Convention,a protected area is “a
g e o g raphically defined area which is designated or
regulated and managed to achieve specific conservation
objectives”. This broad definition covers all kinds of situa-
t i o n s. The World Conservation Union (IU C N) , the main orga-
nization working on the development of protected areas,
identifies six situations, ranging from uninhabited reserves
dedicated to scientific research (the A n t a r c t i c , for example)
to the countless parks run by local populations.
There are more than 30,000 protected areas world-
wide, covering 8.83 per cent of the surface of the planet.
Most of them are no bigger than 10 km2 and are isolated,
fragile zones in areas where nature has been subjected to
human needs.A quarter of that total area (3.3 million km2)
has been classified as having exceptional value under
s e v e ral international agreements, including the Ramsar
Convention on Wetlands (1971), UNESCO’s World Heritage
Convention (1972),the Statutory Framework of the World
Network of Biosphere Reserves set up by UN E S C O s i n c e
1976,and various European Union directives.
Some kinds of ecosystems are better preserved than
o t h e r s. G rasslands in temperate zones, as well as lake s,
tend to be ignored in the world of conservation in favour of
islands and tropical forests. What’s more, as IUCN says, too
many reserves exist only on paper. This is not really surpri-
sing in view of the meagre $6 billion the world sets aside
each year for in situ conservation.
About $2.3 billion more would be needed to adequately
protect all the reserves. Governments could come up with
this money, say scientists and ecologists, simply by abolishing
certain environmentally unfriendly subsidies to farmers and
industrialists that amount to more than $1,000 billion annually.
■
and existing ones are short of eve ry t h i n g, e s p e-
cially staff.
Protected areas are also under pressure from
p o p u l ations whose resources are getting scarcer
because of pove rty and environmental changes.
These people are looking for new farmland, fire-
wood and animals to hunt. The introduction of
outside species like the sparr ow, which was unknow n
in sub-Saharan A f rica before 1978, is another des-
tabilizing element, because they come to occupy the
e c o l o gical space of nat i ve species and end up dri v i n g
them out. Package tourism and urban expansion are
other big threat s , though they are less important in
Africa than elsewhere.
Why do you campaign for involvement of local
people in managing reserves?
C o n s e rvation efforts have sometimes fa i l e d
because it was long believed that nature could be
c o n s e rved without involving people. But at t i t u d e s
h ave changed over the past two decades, thanks lar-
gely to the influence of the poor countri e s. P r e s s u r e
on resources is constantly increasing, and local people
see parks as obstacles to deve l o p m e n t . So we have to
c o m p e n s ate these people. Instead of investing in the
protected area itself, viable projects must be funded
in the surrounding area. S e veral approaches have
been tested, such as UN E S C O’s biosphere reserve s ,o f
which there are now 368 in 91 countri e s.
What have been the results?
Mixed,because of lack of money. But two pro-
jects in Senegal have proved that we were on the
right track.The Popenguine Reserve,for example,
is the first in the world entirely run by wo m e n ,
who live in eight nearby villages. They maintain
the park, grow food for market, manage stocks of
cereals and fuel, organize visitors ’a c c o m m o d at i o n
and act as tourist guides.At the begi n n i n g, in 1987,
they agreed to help the gove rnment run the park in
exchange for permission to continue gat h e ri n g
medicinal plants there.They worked for 10 years
without asking for a penny in payment. Then in
1 9 9 7 , a three-year $400,000 programme funded by
the European Union and the French Nicolas Hulot
Fo u n d at i o n , made it possible to start deve l o p m e n t
projects. Now the women are independent.They
p atrol the reserve , looking after its conservat i o n
and benefiting from the income from tourism.
For one success, t h e re seem to have been a lot of
f a i l u re s. Some people are calling for protected are a s
to be privatized. What do you think about that?
H ow can we stop the pri vate sector from try i n g
to improve their own fortunes? The Fazao Reserve ,
in Togo, was privatized in 1990.The wildlife there
i m m e d i ately began to be sold. T h at ’s a seri o u s
m at t e r.T h e r e ’s no altern at i ve to part n e rship betwe e n
the state, conservation organizations and the local
p o p u l at i o n . But we have to go further in the field of
participation. ■
Interview by Sophie Boukhari,
UN E S C O C o u r i e r j o u r n a l i s t
Mapping a biosphere re s e r v e
Core area
Buffer zone
Transition area
Human settlements
Research station or
experimental research site
Monitoring
Education and training
Tourism and recreation
R
M
E
T
R
R
E
M
T
T
C o n s e r vation means
development as much as
it does protection.
T h e o d o re Roosevelt,
former U. S. p resident 
( 1 8 5 8 - 1 9 1 9 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
G u e r re et paix des l a n g u e s
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 35
B i o d i ve rs i y:  friend for life
For thousands of Londoners , the Royal Botanic
Gardens at Kew are best known as a favourite
picnic spot on the edge of the city, famous for
their picturesque Palm House and Chinese pagoda,
their unri valled collection of plants and their exten-
sive, highly manicured lawns.
The novelty of the gardens, when they were esta-
blished in the 18th century, was the way in which
they combined the function of cultivating a wide
Kew turns over 
a new leaf
◗ David Dickson
At the hub of the British Empire, Kew Gardens once scoured the world for plants.
Now its Millennium Seed Bank puts it in the vanguard of international conservation efforts
◗ British scientific journalist,news
editor of Nature magazine
va riety of plants with an aesthetically pleasing land-
s c a p e , a sharp contrast to the formality of the plant
collections that preceded them.
This remains their charm today.V i s i t o rs can
wander through a selection of carefully selected and
individually labelled trees, and shrubs and flowe-
ring plants from all over the wo r l d .These range from
m a s s i ve rhododendendron bushes from China, t r o-
pical palms grown in a spectacular Victorian glass-
house,to the smallest alpine flowers in a specially-
built rock garden.
Kew played an influential role at the heart of the
B ritish Empire in the 19th century, when it acted
as a central clearing house for trees and other plants
d i s c overed in one part of the empire that could be
p r o d u c t i ve l y, and often profit a b l y, gr own in ano-
t h e r. By the end of the 19th century, Kew was recei-
ving over 2,500 packets of seeds a year from around
the wo r l d , and exporting more than 3,500. O n e
c u r ator wrote that as a result of Kew’s 19th-century
activities the world had been “pretty well ransac-
ked.”
Biopiracy
in an imperial light
It was as a result of Kew’s effort s , for example, t h at
rubber plants from South A m e rica were transferr e d
to highly productive environments in Southeast A s i a .
Less controve rs i a l l y, Kew officials also arranged for
the transfer of cinchona, source of the anti-malari a l
d rug quinine, from its nat i ve Andes to malari a - ri d d e n
areas of A s i a .“In the mid-19th century such activities
r e flected the then global superp ower encouraging the
use of plant resources,” s ays Kew’s director, Pe t e r
C r a n e .“ To d ay they would be seen as pure biopiracy.”
Although Kew’s imperial role ended with the
collapse of the empire early in the 20th century, it conti-
nued to play a major role as a research institution, p r e-
s e rving and cataloguing plants from across the wo r l d .
But it was only in the final decades of the cen-
t u ry that concern for the preservation of biodive r-
sity placed Kew back at the centre of the political
stage as one of the focal points of global ex situ e f f o rt s
to preserve the planet’s biodiversity.
In an ideal wo r l d , all living organisms would be pre-
s e rved in their natural habitat—a strategy known as i n
s i t u c o n s e rvat i o n .But a va riety of fa c t o rs ,from the needs
of researchers for easy access to the fact that many plants
and animals are threatened with extinction in the wild,
In the famed tropical greenhouses of the world’s largest botanic garden.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
h ave led to the gr owth of ex situ s t r at e gi e s.
Perhaps the clearest evidence of Kew’s new role
in supporting global conservation efforts is the Mil-
lennium Seed Bank currently under constru c t i o n
at its outstation atWakehurst Place,a 200-hectare
e s t ate in West Sussex.When completed later this
year,it will be the largest in the world dedicated to
c o n s e rving the seeds of world plants. Its long-term
aim is to collect and conserve 10 per cent of the
wo r l d ’s seed-bearing flora (about 24,000 species)
mainly from arid drylands by the year 2010.
The bank will make seeds available both for
research purposes and for reintroduction into the wild.
In Bri t a i n , seeds of the starfru i t , a small white flowe r
t h at has almost died out were collected and stored at
Wa k e h u rst and samples sent to Kew for DNA fin g e r-
p ri n t i n g .Plants gr own successfully from the seeds are
n ow being reintroduced in their natural habitat .
Roger Smith, head of Kew’s seed conservat i o n
d e p a rt m e n t ,s ays that one of the goals of the seed
bank initiat i ve is to achieve Bri t a i n ’s conservat i o n
o b l i g ations as signat o ries to the 1992 Convention on
B i o l o gical Dive rsity (CBD) “in a way that reduces
c o u n t ri e s ’l e a rning curve invo l ved in setting up their
own collections and allows them to have the insu-
rance policy of seed collections under our control.”
The CBD requires anyone taking plant samples
out of a country to enter a formal agreement spe-
cifying the conditions under which this is being
d o n e , and in particular the compensation that a
c o u n t ry can expect to receive if a commercial appli-
c ation is eventually developed from the plant.
Informed consent
This compensation could, for example, take the
f o rm of an agreed share of the royalties resulting
from the licensing of a patent based on the plant’s
genetic propert i e s.A hypothetical case might be that
of a plant discovered in the Amazon shown to have
p owerful anti-cancer propert i e s. Pa rticularly in light
of their previous reputat i o n , Kew researchers are
keen to be seen to meet CBD requirements.
A greements are currently being negotiated with
c o u n t ries around the world on the conditions under
which seed specimens can be collected and added to
the bank. N ations that have already signed up
include Mexico, South A f ri c a ,N a m i b i a , M o z a m-
b i q u e ,Ve n e z u e l a ,M o r o c c o, E g y p t ,S y ria and Leba-
n o n . Often this means reaching agreement on crea-
ting two parallel collections. One is located in the
c o u n t ry concern e d .The second, “ b a c k - u p ”c o l l e c-
tion will be held at Wa k e h u rst Park while remaining
accessible on request to the depositing country.
Smith says that the need for a binding agr e e-
ment on what Kew can do with the seeds that it
stores can cause problems, for example when a
c o u n t ry lacks any formal mechanism for prov i d i n g
the “ p rior informed consent” for obtaining data on
its plants as required under the CBD.
The same desire to use Kew’s knowledge and
e x p e rience is reflected in a separate initiat i ve to har-
monize procedures for access to seed and germ-
plasm collections around the world.
Conservation 
w o r l d w i d e
For mammals,b i r d s, reptiles and amphibians, the standard
form of e x - s i t u c o n s e r vation is in zoological parks. Th e r e
are currently an estimated 500,000 living creatures in zoos
w o r l d w i d e. Some species such as the Californian condor now
only exist in zoos. Others such as Przewa l s k i ’s horse and the
Pere David deer have only survived because they were pro-
tected in zoos. They are now being released back into the
wild.
The main forms of ex situ plant conservation are botanic
gardens (for whole specimens) and germplasm and seed
b a n k s. Botanical Gardens International, a non-govern-
mental organization, estimates there are 1,500 botanic
gardens worldwide, containing at least 35,000 species,
over 15 per cent of the world’s total. Some put the estimate
as high as 70,000 to 80,000 species.
Most botanic gardens are in the industrialized nations
(only 230 are in tropical countries, despite their greater plant
d i v e r s i t y ) . Many seed and germplasm banks are linked directly
to botanical collections.Others are owned by multinational cor-
p o ra t i o n s, which use them as source material for developing
new plant va r i e t i e s. One survey found that 88 per cent of
plant-breeding companies keep their own store of genetic
r e s o u r c e s.
A third major source of seed and germplasm samples are
university departments and the research institutes forming
the Consultative Group on International A g r i c u l t u ra l
Research,funded through the World Bank. ■
A guide to zoos worldwide:
http://www.mindspring.com/~zoonet 
www_virtual_lib/zoos.html
A complete list of arboreta and botanical 
gardens can be found on:
http://www.helsinki.fi/kmus/botgard.html
As a result of this initiat i ve , r e p r e s e n t at i ves of
14 botanic gardens in 11 countries agreed at a mee-
ting in Beijing last year to adopt a common set of
p o l i cy guidelines setting out their commitments on
a c q u i ring and conserving genetic resources, on the
use and supply of such resources, and on the sha-
ring of benefits arising from their use, for example by
commercial organizations.
The new pri o rities that make up Kew’s curr e n t
agenda are ve ry different from those which determ i-
ned its influence a hundred ye a rs ago.“The last thing
we want is to be accused of being biopirat e s ,” s ay s
S m i t h .“ We must not deny that we ever did it. But we
must acknowledge that that world has gone.” ■
+ …
The Royal Botanic and Millennium Seed Bank:
www.rbgkew.org.uk
Common Policy Guidelines for Botanic Gardens:
The recognition 
of the fact that 
the wildlife of the world
is irreplaceable but is
being rapidly destroyed
is necessary if we are 
to realize in time 
that areas must be set
aside where,
in the ultimate interests
of mankind as a whole,
the spread of man must
t a ke second place to 
the conservation 
of other species.
Julian Huxley,
British biologist,
first dire c t o r- g e n e ral of UN E S C O
( 1 8 8 7 - 1 9 7 5 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 37
G u e r re et paix des l a n g u e sB i o d i ve rs i y:  friend for life
To w a rds a world
conservation e t h i c s
◗ M . S. S wa m i n a t h a n
The Rio convention marked the first major international step towards 
the sharing of biodiversity based on the principle of social fairness
It has become commonplace to say that the
C o nvention on Biological Dive rsity (CBD)
adopted during the Rio Summit in June 1992 is
an important landmark in integr ating the pri n-
ciples of ethics and equity in the use of biodive rs i t y.
To stem the increasingly rapid decline of biodiver-
sity, it was necessary to take action, and quickly,
without waiting for the scientific community to
gather further knowledge. First and foremost, the
CBD was an acknowledgment of this urgent need.
It entered into force in December 1993 and so fa r
has been rat i fied by 177 Stat e s — but not by the United
S t at e s.This agr e e m e n t , the only one of its kind,sets up
a framework for worldwide action aimed at ensuri n g
the conservat i o n , the sustainable use and—a note-
wo rt hy development—the fair sharing of biodive rs i-
t y ’s benefit s. More specific a l l y, the CBD focuses on the
d e finition and the financing of conservation policies,
access to genetic resources,N o rth-South technology
t r a n s f e rs stemming from the use of those resources,
and trade in genetically modified organisms (GMOs).
In part i c u l a r , it acknowledges that poor countri e s
cannot meet their commitments to preserve biodi-
ve rsity unless the developed nations provide them
with access to biotechnologies and the related fin a n-
c i n g .B i o d i ve rsity will unavoidably be depleted through
ove ruse if the current co-existence of unsustainable life-
styles and unacceptable pove rty continues, and if the
means of subsistence of families putting strains on
resources are not strengthened.
The CBD has first and foremost been an effec-
t i ve awareness-raising tool. Political leaders , t h e
media and the general public now know that taking
from nature without restraint jeopardizes humani-
t y ’s securi t y.M a ny states have changed their nat i o n a l
l aws to create or strengthen mechanisms to manage
biodiversity.The convention has also lent support
to the idea that preserving species with their nat u r a l
habitats and enlisting the local people’s support in
managing them are vital priorities.
The convention has also prompted over 130 Stat e s
to adopt a protocol last Ja n u a ry 29, 2000 in Montreal
(Canada) on biosafety in order to regulate intern at i o n a l
trade in GMOs.The negotiations led to a stand-off bet-
ween the European Union and the “Miami Group”,
consisting of the leading GMO producing countri e s
led by the United Stat e s , Argentina and Canada.
According to the text eventually adopted, c o u n t ri e s
m ay oppose GMO imports deemed hazardous for the
e nvironment or health by invoking the principle of pre-
caution—in other wo r d s , without necessarily hav i n g
i rrefutable scientific proof that they are dangerous.
H owe ve r , the issue of whether the protocol ove rri d e s
the rules of the World Trade Organization (the W TO,
which so far has not recognized the principle of pre-
caution) remains to be settled.Only a specific dispute
brought before the W TO will show whether the pro-
tocol has any teeth.
The CBD has certainly enabled progr e s s , but the
funding of conservation projects is far from gua-
ranteed.Development aid has been steadily decli-
ning since 1992.The Global Environment Fa c i l i t y
in charge of, among other things,managing inter-
n ational financing for biodive rs i t y, has received and
distributed about $2 billion in 10 years.
Protecting traditional knowledge
Lastly and, most import a n t l y, scant political
e f f o rt has been focused on guaranteeing a fair share
of biodive rs i t y ’s benefit s. M a ny developing countri e s
continue to denounce what they call “ b i o p i r a cy ”b y
the gove rnments and companies of the Nort h ,
which collect their biological resources for com-
mercial purposes.There is an urgent need to take
steps that would acknowledge and compensate the
inestimable contri bution of indigenous rural fa m i-
lies to the conservation and improvement of the pla-
net’s genetic resources.
T h at task requires changing intellectual propert y
ru l e s.They are currently being revised in the frame-
work of the Tr a d e - R e l ated Aspects of Intellectual
P r o p e rty (TRIPS) agr e e m e n t , which regulates bio-
technology patents and new va rieties of crops.T h e
system in force,based on individually-owned pri vat e
p r o p e rt y, is unsuitable for protecting indigenous
p e o p l e ’s collective traditional know l e d g e .The Wo r l d
Intellectual Property Organization (WIPO), w h i c h
has launched a study on the need to recognize their
ri g h t s , is likely to help identify altern at i ve solutions.
N e x t , the intern ational community must carry out a
c rucial task: drafting and adopting a protocol on
a gr o b i o d i ve rsity that would protect traditional know-
ledge and fa rm e rs ’ rights over plant genomes. ■
◗ Holder of the UNESCO-Cousteau chair in Ecotechnology, chairman
of the M. S. Swaminathan Research Foundation (Chennai,India),
author of I Predict: A Century of Hope-Harmony with Nature and
Freedom from Hunger, East West Books Pvt.Ltd,Chennai,1999.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
E T H I C S
38 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
P r o fit and solidarity have stopped
giving each other the cold shoulder and
are becoming part n e rs explains Juan
Pina, a Spanish journalist who specializes
in the social economy. “We are heading
towards a set of ethics more attuned to
reality, in which profit stops being a kind
of necessary evil linked to greed,while the
public good stops being the exclusive res-
ponsibility of politicians.”
Alongside credit cards whose issuers
and users contribute a fixed amount of
money or a percentage of takings to
groups like the Red Cross, Greenpeace or
Amnesty Intern at i o n a l , a number of
“ethical banks” h ave set up shop in
Europe, Japan or Canada, and are measu-
■
The jobs and wages of millions of
people throughout the world depend
indirectly on a bell which at four
o’clock every afternoon marks the end of
trading on the Dow Jones, the index of
leading shares on the New York stock
exchange. Almost two billion dollars shift
each day from one continent to another at
staggering speed. Speculation can make
almost every currency tremble, and few
trading floors are shielded from an abrupt
slump in value. But people’s desire to live
in a better world is increasingly affecting a
commodity that,whether we like it or not,
determines our lives: money.
ring their profitability more in social
terms than by pure financial gain. The
basic message which these banks try to
spread is that, through no extra effort, the
small or large amounts of savings that
many people deposit each month in their
bank accounts can be used to further
their ideals. And that this can be done
without abandoning the guarantees offe-
red by traditional banking: s o l ve n cy,
interest, readily available cash and good
returns.
The slogans of some of these banks are
more than explicit: “The highest interest
is that of eve ry b o d y,” announces an
a d ve rtisement for the Italian Ethical
Bank. “Are you content to turn a blind
T HE BATTLE 
F OR AN ET HICAL BUCK
◗ Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Ethical banks that include socially responsible investments in their bottom line are winning
support from people who share their ideals
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
A fair trade boutique in Belfast: making sure producers get a fair end of the deal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
E T H I C S
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 39
eye to the way your money is being used,
or are you ready to put your principles
into practice?” the UK Co-operat i ve
Bank asks its potential clients. “ T h e
Citizen’s Bank’s mechanism is value-dri-
ven, rather than by economic growth and
e f fic i e n cy,” declares a pamphlet from
Japan’s Citizen’s Bank.
Historical 
roots
The roots of modern ethical invest-
ment can be traced to the United States
in the 1920s. The Methodist Church,
which until then had regarded the stock
exchange as a shady gambling den, deci-
ded to start investing, but only on condi-
tion that it would not put money into the
liquor trade or get involved in the betting
industry. But social investment did not
come into its own until the 1970s.
During the Viet Nam War, groups of
citizens decided to boycott the firm that
made napalm gas, which had been
deployed in the Vietnamese jungle, cau-
sing terrible physical deformities in affec-
ted communities. From then on,
c h u r c h e s , f o u n d ations and unive rs i t i e s
s t a rted to ask themselves what their
money was being used for. Nowadays,
ethical considerations are found in a wide
spectrum of bank products: from “ethical
investment funds”, which look very close-
ly at the companies they buy shares from,
excluding those with unacceptable busi-
ness activities or a proper wage or social
p o l i cy ; to current accounts that offer
interest lower than the going market rate,
but promise to invest some of their profits
in development projects. Likewise, ethical
investment institutions come in all shapes
and sizes. Some work like normal banks,
with branches, cash machines and che-
quebooks. Others are more like mutual
funds or credit co-operatives, such as the
French NEF (Nouvelle Economie
Fraternelle), which since 1988 has been
lending funds solely to teaching, organic
farming and health projects.
In keeping with the Internet era, seve-
ral banks base themselves largely in
cy b e rs p a c e . One of them is Italy’s
Universal Ethical Bank, which opened its
doors for business in Padua just over a
year ago, and now has offices in Brescia,
Milan, Rome, Florence and Modena. Its
president, Fabio Salviato, speaks proudly
of having assembled in a short time funds
totalling $4.5 million used to finance 250
projects in Italy and abroad. “Our slogan
is defence of the poor. In the Third World,
of course, but also in Italy, where approxi-
mately seven million people live below the
poverty line,” says Salviato. His bank spe-
cializes in social investments made in four
a r e a s : the co-operat i ve sphere—funda-
mental in a country like Italy, which has
deciding which kind of development it
will be. I don’t accept that the only crite-
ria guiding investment policies should be
‘giving money to those who already have
money.’ I believe the right policy is to give
money to those who do good things, even
if the return is less. That’s why I’m a
member of an ethical bank.”
Ethical investment, Rinaldo adds,“is a
concrete response to criticism of our eco-
nomic system, which is centred on maxi-
mizing profit.This is the start of a revolu-
tion, a real revolution based on each one
of us, showing that it’s possible to build
an economy that is also based on values
such as the common good, conservation
of the environment, peace, respect for
marginalized people. In short, an econo-
more than 4,000 co-operatives,the volun-
tary sector, the environment and interna-
tional partnerships.
“Above all,” Salviato says, “we finance
NGOs with micro-credit projects in
Albania and Macedonia. In Guatemala,
we’ve helped set up a small community
bank in the town of Chajul, which pro-
duces coffee to sell to businesses which
agree to fair trading. The return we pay
on deposit accounts is the same as the
Italian rate of inflation, which oscillates
between two and 2.5 per cent, while the
interest we pay on current accounts is one
per cent, somewhat less than the going
market rate. But the account’s adminis-
tration costs are also lower than those in
conventional banks.” This is made pos-
sible in large part by the thousands of
volunteers from other non-profit organi-
zations who were behind the creation of
the Ethical Bank, and which have current
accounts and credit needs.
Two thousand registered groups and
10,000 people now have savings in the
Ethical Bank. E nvironmental engi n e e r
Loris Rinaldo is one of the bank’s custo-
mers. “I strongly believe that the econo-
my, much more than politics, is control-
ling world development,” Rinaldo says,
“and that banks have a crucial role in
my centred on people.”
Clearly not everybody is as keen as
Rinaldo. In an Internet discussion forum
on ethics and the economy initiated by
Canada’s Citizens Bank, there were seve-
ral comments along the lines of “congra-
tulations for your intelligent marketing
c a m p a i g n , but I’m not interested in
banks’ ethical opinions. I would prefer
them to concentrate on giving the client
better service at lower cost.”
Reconciling 
different views
It is also worth asking whether ethical
investment, which on one side owes its
existence to people’s aspiration to live in a
better world, might also become part of
an image campaign waged by traditional
banks desperate to capture this new and
socially conscious client base. G u y
Hooker, the director of Britain’s Ethical
I nvestment Co-operat i ve , b e l i e ves that
“people are choosing ethically sound
investments and ethically sound banks
because they have become collectively
conscious of the power of their money,
and because in many cases they get better
customer service.”
The idea of what is moral is obviously
not the same for eve ryo n e . Some of us
Each time members of Canada’s Citizens Bank use their credit card, the bank donates about 10 cents 
to Amnesty International or Oxfam.
‘I strongly believe 
that the economy, much more
than politics, is controlling
world development, and that
banks have a crucial role 
in deciding which kind 
of development it will be.’
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
E T H I C S
40 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
might think it appalling that a bank fin a n c e s
businesses which deal in arm s , though they
would not think it so bad if the funds were
lent to tobacco companies or to political
p a rt i e s. L i k e w i s e , some might prefer to
finance literacy programmes rather than
s ave-the-whale campaigns or fair banana tra-
ding projects. With these discrepancies in
m i n d , a number of banks, including the Tri o-
dos Bank created in the Netherlands in 1980
with affil i ates in Belgium and Bri t a i n , o f f e r
their clients the option of directing their
i nvestment to specific areas, such as organic
fa rming or the development of solar energy
projects in countries of the South.
Bank spokesman Thomas Steiner
explains how his bank tries to reconcile dif-
ferent viewpoints: “Our offices in Belgi u m ,
the Netherlands and the United Kingdom
do not work like McDonald’s, which is
exactly the same in eve ry country. Our Bel-
gian partner has a certain Belgian flavo u r ,
and emphasizes social development projects;
in the United Kingdom we focus more on
helping charitable organizat i o n s ; and in the
Netherlands our main concern is the env i-
r o n m e n t .”
When the time comes to hand out
loans or choose companies that will recei-
ve funds, the Dutch bank applies very
strict standards. “Like any other bank, we
make loans. The criteria we use before
deciding whether to grant them are ‘posi-
tive’; anyone who asks us for money must
belong to one of the areas in which we
work: nature, the social economy, non-
profit organizations, culture and develop-
ment co-operation. We only lend money
to projects that comply with these positi-
ve criteria. On the other hand, we have
investment funds. We invest the money
that our clients entrust us with on the
stock exchange through criteria we call
‘negative’.We invest only in firms with no
links to nuclear energy, arms or tobacco.”
After 20 years of existence, Triodos has a
portfolio of 40,000 savers and 4,000 sha-
reholders.
The goal 
of transparency
Tr a n s p a r e n cy is a prized goal for ethical
b a n k s , including Switzerland’s Banque
A l t e rn at i ve Suisse (BAS), which in a
c o u n t ry where the law protects bank secrecy
annually publishes the names of people and
businesses that have received its loans as we l l
as details of the sums invo l ve d . C i t i z e n s
B a n k , owned by the Va n c o u ver City Sav i n g s
Credit Union, C a n a d a ’s largest credit union,
goes one step further. As part of its com-
munity donations programme, clients are
i nvited to suggest groups which they believe
deserve a share of a fund.The suggestions
are classified into four groups according to
the area in which they fa l l . Clients are then
i nvited to vote on which groups should
r e c e i ve 50 per cent of the fund, 25 per cent,
15 per cent and 10 per cent,and funds are
a l l o c ated according to the results of the
p o l l . In 1999, for instance, clients voted to
donate $17,700 to the Canadian Catholic
Organization for Development and Peace,
which fights against pove rty and injustice in
the world through its partner groups in 50
countries. Second place went to Frontier
College, a group of university volunteers
a c t i ve in literacy progr a m m e s , w h i c h
received $9,000.“This procedure involves
an extern a l l y - fa c i l i t ated advisory committee
c o m p rised of NGO leaders and bank
members and staff,” explains Gillian Dus-
t i n g, the bank’s public relations director.T h e
Citizens Bank also pledges to reply within
24 hours to all queries about its ethical
standards sent by e-mail, while its website
hosts a chatline on ethical inve s t m e n t .A f t e r
three ye a rs in bu s i n e s s , the Canadian bank
has deposits wo rth over $680 million, w h i l e
its pre-tax profits in 1998 were almost three
million dollars.
Credit and 
ethical banking
The power of ethical banks in the wo r l d
economy is still small,though it is growing
year by ye a r. According to figures publi-
shed by EIRIS, a research group on ethical
finance, the total volume of ethical funds
i nvested in the United Kingdom rose from
$3,300 to $4,100 million between Ja n u a ry
1999 and January 2000.The Organisation
for Economic Co-operation and Develop-
ment (OECD), meanwhile, recognizes that
although ethical banks “ h ave had some suc-
c e s s , they are far from changing the at t i t u d e s
of conventional banking institutions”. I n
OE C D’s opinion, the banks’ main at t r a c-
tion is that they offer social firms an alter-
native response to the problems of getting
credit.
David Perry, head of the Markkula
Centre for Applied Ethics at California’s
Santa Clara Unive rs i t y, c o n c u rs that
“such banks are sometimes the only
means of obtaining loans for people with
no credit history and no major assets. And
they often combine loans with training in
starting and running businesses, which
can be extremely helpful to folks with no
experience in commerce.”
As for the future,G i ovanni A c q u at t i ,p r e-
sident of the Milan-based financial co-ope-
r at i ve MAG2 and a leading proponent of
ethical finance in Italy for the last 20 ye a rs ,
b e l i e ves it will “depend less on the invo l ve-
ment of public authorities like the Wo r l d
Bank or the European Commission, a n d
more on the strength, courage and resources
t h at we use in personally convincing people
t h at they should behave in a different way.
We have a lot of work to do, and we mustn’t
lose hope.And I never do.” ■
+ …
Citizens Bank of Canada: www.citizensbank.ca
Triodos Bank: www.triodos.nl
Banca Etica Universale: www.bancaetica.com.
Banque Alternative Suisse: 
www.bas-info.ch
Triodos Bank supports the Flemish campaign for the prevention of HIV/Aids. Here, stands set up in Antwerp
(Belgium) on World Aids Day, December 1999.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 41
■
It is a phantasmagoric world. When
European trave l e rs discove r e d
Angkor in the 19th century, they
were astounded by the grandeur and the
my s t e ry of the temples, c overed with
sculptures of “airy figures stifled and cru-
shed by the forest,” in the words of the
French writer Guy de Pourtalès. “I have
before me,” he wrote,“not only an empty
capital but 700 years of unrecorded histo-
ry. And death’s most dreaded prodigy:
s i l e n c e .” The silence that enve l o p e d
Angkor when it was abandoned in the
15th century seemed immutable, bu t
appearances can be deceptive.
A fa bulous archaeological site, t h i s
gr e at stone skeleton is also a living place, at
once the realm of divinities and a city of
m o rt a l s , where eve ry d ay business is stee-
ped in customs from a prestigious past.
Tales of a nine-headed 
serpent
Between the 9th and the 14th centu-
ries,Angkor,the capital of the kingdom of
Cambodia, grew up between the Kulen
hills and Tonle Sap, the Great Lake. At
the height of its power, the kingdom
included parts of present-day Thailand,
Laos and Viet Nam. Over the centuries,
kings who practiced religions that came
from India, Hinduism and Buddhism,
erected monumental stone temples where
they honoured their gods. They also built
an elaborate hydraulic system comprising
huge reservoirs (baray) linked to a net-
work of canals, dikes and moats.
Only one contemporary description of
Angkor’s former splendour has survived.
It was written by a member of a Chinese
diplomatic mission, Chou Ta-Kuan, who
a rri ved in A u g u s t , 1 2 9 6 . His vivid
account includes anecdotes about the
daily life and customs of Angkor’s inhabi-
tants. He wrote that every night in a gol-
den tower, the king had to mate with a
nine-headed serpent that took on the
appearance of a woman. In the palace,
bare-breasted women “as white as jade”
wore their hair in a bun.At the other end
of the spectrum, the commoners were
described as “rude, black and very ugly”.
The nobles were carried about in gold
palanquins and dressed in precious
fabrics whose patterns were an indication
of rank. They lived in houses with lead
and tile roofs, while those of “the com-
mon people were covered only with that-
ch”. Farmers tilled their fields on the
banks of the great lake. In the dry season,
when the waters receded from the flooded
forest around the lake, the farmers came
down from the hills and grew rice.
When the Siamese conquered and
plundered Angkor in 1432, the king and
his court left the devastated city. The
forest overran the ruins. Wooden buil-
dings and writings on latania leaves and
scraped hides disappeared, victims of the
damp climate and insects.
In the late 19th century, archaeologists
◗ French ethnologist who has been working at Angkor
(Cambodia) for the last seven years.
T IMEL ESS
A NGKOR
◗ Fabienne Luco
A fragile thread of continuity connects life around the ancient capital of the kingdom 
of Cambodia to the distant past
Angkor Wat:  realm of divinities and city of mortals.
1.The precise functions of these hydraulic
engineering works have given rise to considerable
debate.As well as providing water for irrigation
they reflected the symbolic role of water within an
architectural cosmogonic conception in which the
temples are an earthly representation of the city
of the gods surrounded by the oceans. This
irrigation system has for the most part either
dried up or been filled in.The only operational
section is the western baray which has been
repaired and today still provides water for some
dry-season rice-fields.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
p ower of at t r a c t i o n .
The topographical conditions provide
an ideal setting for modern dwellings. In
the past, people left a profound imprint
on the earth by building networks of
roads and dikes as part of a water mana-
gement system. The plain is still shaped
by vestiges of these large-scale enginee-
ring works. In search of high ground that
will escape flooding during the rainy sea-
son, Cambodian farmers find the terrain
highly suitable for building their homes.
How long has the current population
lived in the area and what is the nature of
their relationship to Angkor? Unfortun-
ately, there is little information on the size
and location of ancient villages. The few
recent local writings vanished during the
torment of the Khmer Rouge period.And
French explorers in the late 19th century
considered the temples more important
than the people who lived around them—
only five or six villages seem to have been
recorded.They consist of groups of two to
ten houses built around squares in the
heart of the forest.
Do the local people consider them-
selves heirs of the Angkor tradition? Their
history is obscure; village memory goes
back no further than two or three genera-
tions. A few scraps of ancient history have
come down to us orally, but it is impos-
sible to establish with certainty whether
they are real or imaginary, history or
i n t e rp r e t at i o n . The building of the
temples is said to have taken place in a
mythical period peopled by figures who
were half-divine, half-human. The villa-
gers believe that these imposing monu-
ments can only be the work of divinities
or of people who came from elsewhere
and knew much more about architecture
and sculpture than they do.
The legend surrounding the founda-
tion of the temple of Angkor Wat tells the
story of Preah Ket Melea, son of the king
of heaven and a mortal woman.The divi-
began deciphering the inscriptions and
scenes depicted in the bas-reliefs carved
in the stonework of the temples, which
contributed precious information to their
understanding of historical timelines and
myths, battles and aspects of everyday
life, including hunting, fishing, marketing
and habitat.
Today, life in nearby villages is much
the same as when it was captured in those
ancient sculptures. The wooden wheel-
barrow that squeaks as it is pushed round
a corner is identical to one on a bas-relief.
The vendor dozing in front of her stall at
the market in Siem Reap, the provincial
capital (population 75,000) seven kilo-
metres from Angkor, is resting in the
same position as her distant ancestor
depicted by a sculptor. On the basin of
Srah Srang, located in the heart of the site
and bordered by two villages, the fisher-
man casting his net makes the same ges-
ture as his counterpart of seven centuries
ago.
More than an outdoor museum,
Angkor is home to religious and rural life
revolving around the temples. Inside col-
lapsed sanctuaries and more recently-
built Buddhist pagodas, smoke from
incense threads its way heavenward befo-
re statues of ancient gods and the
Buddha. At the threshold of a temple or
on a heap of loose stones, the eye comes
to rest on cigarettes, rolled betel leaves
and candles set down by an anonymous
hand. They are offerings to one of the
many neakta, land spirits who often dwell
in Angkor’s statues.
A celestial
architect
One of these spirits, Ta Pech, lives in a
huge termite nest in the southern pavilion
of the first wall surrounding Angkor Wat.
Ta Pech has a reputation for malevolence.
According to a monk, “People say that
when an aircraft flies over Angkor,it must
make three turns around Ta Pech; other-
wise, there is a chance it may crash into
the lake. If you give Ta Pech wine and
cigarettes, he can also divulge winning
lottery numbers.”
Other signs of human activity can be read
in the present landscape.The grid pat t e rn of
nearby rice paddies appears behind the screen
of ve g e t ation that cloaks many of the temples.
Not always visible from the tourist routes, a
score of villages can be made out through
gr oves of sugar palms. They are home to
some 22,000 people in a 300 square-kilo-
metre area. Such a high population density on
an archaeological site is due as much to the
lie of the land as to the temples’ e c o n o m i c
nities said they were disturbed by the
smell of Preah Ket Melea and asked his
father to send him down to Earth. The
king acceded to their request, offering his
son the opportunity to have an exact
replica erected on Earth of any edifice in
heaven with the help of Preah Visnukar,
the celestial architect whom villagers still
invoke whenever a building is construc-
ted. A modest man, Preah Ket Melea
chose the stable. An ox was released onto
the plain of Angkor and the place where it
lay down was designated as the site for
Angkor Wat.
Ebbs and flows
of memory
From the orally-transmitted past, vil-
lagers above all recall the wars against the
Siamese and the Chams, a people from
Champa, a vanished kingdom that was
located in the centre of present-day Viet
Nam, and the accompanying raids and
forced displacement of populations. “We
Cambodians are accustomed to wa rs.
When you look at the bas-reliefs, you see
m a ny battle scenes from the days of
Angkor. Since then, those images have
constantly repeated themselves,” says a
farmer. The scenes depict distant times
called boran (“ancient”, in Khmer), or
muoy roy chnam (“100 years”). Nobody
can accurately date them, as this com-
ment by a villager illustrates: “My father
says the temples were there when he was
born.They must be very old.”
By and large, the local people have dif-
ficulty imagining that a connection may
exist between them and the people who
built Angkor. However, in a village north
of Angkor Thom there are reports of
families who claim to descend from the
kings of Angkor. In the early 20th centu-
ry, they still lived in small, tumbledown
wooden hovels at the foot of the royal
palace. After the French began restoring
the temples, they had to move north.
Their current living conditions are the
same as their neighbours’, but they enjoy
a certain recognition.“Like the king, they
have the power of life or death over the
villagers,” says one local resident.
Today, Angkor’s hydraulic system no
longer functions and farmers use rain to
water the rice paddies which are still their
economic mainstay. Due to the lack of
irrigation and the poor quality of the
sandy, clay-filled soil, there is only one
meagre harvest a year (less than one
tonne per hectare). Complementary acti-
vities are necessary, such as fishing, mar-
ket gardening, palm sugar production,
sales of handicrafts to tourists and work
ANGKOR
Phnom Penh
0 100 km
Thailand
Laos
Viet Nam
Gulf of Siam
Tonle Sap
South
China
Sea
Siem Reap
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 43
on the temple restoration projects.
Technical jobs such as motorcycle, radio
and television repair and battery-charging
are also emerging.
A n g k o r , t h e n , c r e ates jobs for the local
p o p u l at i o n . In the late 19th century, a f t e r
French explorers recognized the temples’
h i s t o ric and artistic va l u e , ve g e t ation wa s
cleared away and stones that had lain half-
forgotten in the middle of the forest resur-
fa c e d . In 1907 the Angkor Conservat i o n
A u t h o rity (the French archaeologi s t s ’ f o r-
mer headquart e rs and the present sculptu-
re storage site) began restoration wo r k .T h e
few villagers who lived within the temple
complex itself were hired as “ c o o l i e s ” . B y
the late 1960s, over 1,000 people we r e
working on the site.
The tourist
revival
Before March 1970, when a coup
d’état toppled Prince Norodom Sihanouk
and war came to Cambodia, the local
people had begun crafting small, hand-
made wooden items, including musical
instruments (flutes and violins), toy ox-
c a rt s , k n i ve s , a xes and fin e l y - w r o u g h t
canes. They started making and selling
these objects anew when tourists began
streaming back in the early 1990s. In
1999, the estimated number of visitors
was put at 350,000, a figure expected to
triple by 2005.
The people living on the site seldom
enter the temples, even when they are
close to home. “We’re just farmers. I
heard my grandfather say that during the
Angkor epoch,folks like me were not allo-
wed within the walls of the capital,
Angkor Thom,” says one villager. “Only
n o b l e s , civil servants and merchants
could venture inside. It was the same for
the temples: only priests and dignitaries
could enter them.”
These are something more than remi-
niscences of a bygone age. Today, reli-
gious rituals in the temples are celebrated
mainly by masters of ceremony who come
to honour the neakta. Local people wor-
ship these spirits, especially in the vil-
lages, by calling upon a medium incarna-
ting the supernatural beings. Most of the
tokens of devotion laid in front of the sta-
tues in the temple of Angkor Wat have
been left by tourists from other parts of
Cambodia and Asia on a religious pilgri-
mage to the site.Local religious activity is
c o n c e n t r ated in more recently bu i l t
Buddhist pagodas. Especially numerous
within the walls of Angkor Thom, the
pagodas were built near the temples as a
way of honouring new divinities in the
shadow of the old. Continuity in Angkor
can still be felt in the local people’s daily
lives.
As peace returns and Angkor gears up
for major tourism deve l o p m e n t , the people
living there must meet new challenges and
s t rike a delicate balance. Villages along the
road-embankments are gr owing rapidly, a n d
settlement has become dense in some form e r-
ly scattered communities.This is a direct out-
come of the population gr owth that followe d
the Khmer Rouge period (1975-1979).To d ay,
there are five children in the average fa m i l y,
and half of all Cambodians are under the age
of sixteen.
Rice paddies are steadily encroaching on
the bushy plain. Angkor is protected by royal
decrees which limit the expansion of farm-
land and the cutting of firewood.Traditional
secondary activities, such as palm sugar and
charcoal production, are now seldom practi-
ced. In Angkor, many issues remain unresol-
ved, including preservation of the temples
(especially from plunder), protection of the
e nv i r o n m e n t , ru n away population gr ow t h
and the development of tourism.
The loss of traditional values, accelerated
by opening up too fast to the outside world,
is another cause for concern. The chain of
oral transmission broke down during the
Khmer Rouge period, and it has proved
impossible to revive some ancient traditions.
Television, now in every village, is speeding
up the loss of cultural identity. It is vital to
s ave A n g k o r ’s architectural heri t a g e , bu t
equally important to protect its intangible
heritage: the tales, legends and place names
that only local people know. ■
Modern times: Angkor’s challenge is to strike a balance between preserving its heritage and coping with expanding tourism.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
C O N N E X I O N S
44 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
would draw their attention to social and
cultural issues instead of bombarding them
with Western pop culture,” says Ahamed.
The idea for a television network focu-
sing on env i r o n m e n t ,d e velopment and cul-
ture was first raised in a conference of South
Asian broadcasters in 1989, a proposal
which was welcomed by UN E S C O. But it
was the Rio Earth Summit in 1992 that
actually paved the way for setting up an
a l t e rn at i ve television unit.The Non-Gove rn-
mental Organizat i o n s ’ (NGO) forum at
Rio gave the mandate to the W I F, which has
been in the field of development commu-
nication in Asia since 1980.
The W I F, funded mostly by Norwe gi a n
and Swedish aid agencies, set up the netwo r k
in Colombo where it has  a full-fle d g e d
media centre.YATV was launched with an
initial investment of about $18 million. It is
a business enterp rise with 51 per cent ow n e d
by the WIF and 49 per cent by pri vate inve s-
t o rs , mostly multinational corp o r at i o n s.
For WIF, Asia was the obvious place to
launch an alternative network. Half of the
r e gi o n ’s three billion inhabitants are under
2 4 , hence the tremendous impact of televi-
sion. In addition, there were no television
n e t works or channels dedicated to pro-
grammes dealing with social and environ-
mental issues.
YATV started with one-hour we e k l y
p r o gr a m m e s , based mostly on inform at i o n
about developmental issues provided by
the United Nations and NGOs. In 1996 the
network started producing seven different
30-minute programmes broadcast each day,
focusing on a wide range of subjects.To d ay,
on ave r a g e , about 15 hours of YAT V ’s pro-
grammes are shown every week on terres-
t rial and satellite channels throughout
Asia—such as India’s Doordarshan Metro
( D D 2 ) , Pa k i s t a n ’s PTV Wo r l d , N e p a l ’s
NTV, Malaysia’s RTM, Bangladesh’s Ten
Network,Thailand’s ITV and Channel 5,
and Viet Nam’sVTV 2.
Despite this wide geographical spread
and with an estimated viewership of about
250 million people,YATV producers admit
that they have not yet conquered a mass
a u d i e n c e . Without a channel of its ow n ,
this will be diffic u l t . Recent surveys estimat e
■
To a first-time visitor it might look like
a journalism school or a college campus.
Walking along the corri d o rs of Yo u n g
Asia Television Netwo r k ’s (YATV) head-
q u a rt e rs in the Sri Lankan capital,C o l o m b o,
one can find yo u n g s t e rs in casual clothes
occupying newsrooms and studios. In A s i a ’s
vast and expansive electronic media wo r l d ,
YATV may sound like one more television
c o m p a ny trying to be successful with enter-
tainment-only progr a m m e s.
Not so.The netwo r k ’s young crew is put-
ting together entertainment progr a m m e s
based on Asian cultural and social va l u e s ,
e nvironment and sustainable deve l o p m e n t .
“ YATV is a network for Asian yo u t h . O u r
motto is ‘infotainment and edutainment’.
It is a combination of education and infor-
m ation with a lot of entert a i n m e n t ,” s ay s
H i l my A h a m e d ,m a n a ging director of YAT V
n e t wo r k .
S t a rted in 1995 by the Worldview Inter-
national Foundation (WIF) and some pri-
vate inve s t o rs ,YATV produces progr a m m e s
t h at are broadcast on television channels in
c o u n t ries all over A s i a , including Sri Lanka,
India, Pakistan, Nepal, Bangladesh,Thai-
land, Laos,Malaysia and Viet Nam.
An estimated viewership
of 250 million people
The Asian satellite television boom in
the early 1990s opened up new opportu-
nities for many channels and companies
producing programmes for local
audiences, triggering a race for maximum
viewership. This eventually led to many
Asian television networks opting for the
shortcut method of making or buying
p r o grammes based only on entert a i n-
ment. According to YATV officials most
of these programmes lacked creativity and
imagination, and were simply imitations
of Western television programmes.
“There was a crying need for an alter-
n at i ve television, especially for yo u t h ,w h i c h
ASI A’S ALT ERN AT I V E
T EL EV ISION
◗ Ethirajan Anbarasan and K J M Varma
An Asian broadcasting network run by young professionals focuses on social and
environmental issues
◗ Respectively UNESCO Courier journalist and 
Colombo-based journalist
A young crew: recruited from across Asia, the network’s journalists and technicians are on average 24 years old.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
C O N N E X I O N S
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 45
t h at about 30 million Asians watch YAT V ’s
p r o gr a m m e s. “This is not a mass appeal
programme. We cater to a niche audience
wishing to see more meaningful and quali-
t at i ve programmes than watching Music
Television (MTV),” says Ahamed.
But even getting this far has not been a
smooth ride.YATV has had to battle with
giants like the STAR TV network and we l l -
established television companies from other
Asian countri e s. They soon realized that
only by being innovat i ve and different from
other playe rs could they gain viewe rs ,e s p e-
cially among youth.
To begin with,YATV recruited yo u n g s t e rs
without any experience in television journ a-
lism and trained them to make progr a m m e s.
To d ay, it manages a crew of about 120 yo u n g
media professionals drawn from va rious A s i a n
c o u n t ries—the average age being 24.
“We asked our young team members
w h at type of programmes they would like to
see and how they would go about making
them.This helped to develop a style of our
own,” says Ahamed.Apart from few high-
level positions, young people, between 18
and 25 handle editorial planning, r e s e a r c h ,
w riting and fil m i n g, making YATV a unique
television network in the region. In short,
these are programmes made by yo u n g
Asians for young Asians.
YATV programmes are characterized by
their fashionable and creat i ve camera wo r k ,
their animated and art i c u l ate presenters and
their extensive use of computer gr a p h i c s ,s t i l l
not ve ry common among many Asian pro-
d u c e rs. The Pan-Asian background of the
professionals is also an asset in making pro-
grammes that attract yong people from dif-
ferent countri e s.
But slick presentation aside, young vie-
we rs are attracted by Made-in-Asia qua-
lity programmes dealing with sustainable
d e ve l o p m e n t , wo m e n ’s rights and more
i m p o rtantly their own culture and tradi-
tions. “Previously no producer thought of
making programme series on Asian folk
music, dance and arts,” says Parthiban, a
23-year-old producer atYATV. Slowly but
surely YATV programmes have gained
p o p u l a ri t y. Within a year after its incep-
t i o n ,YATV gained entry into the top twe n t y
of Sri Lanka’s favourite programmes.
Advancing
the cause of women
N ature Calls is a popular YATV pro-
gramme now shown in many Asian coun-
t ri e s. It looks at environmental problems from
the rainforest of the Amazon to the plains of
Tanzanian Serengeti, from the peaks of the
H i m a l ayas to the coral reefs of the Maldive s.
The programme presents stories show i n g
our common heritage and highlights the need
for a balance between exploiting and conser-
ving resources.
A recent N ature Calls focused on
ancient irri g ation systems and organic fa r-
ming techniques practiced in the A s i a n
r e gion for centuri e s. It also discusses how
e c o - f riendly traditional fa rming techniques
could help to improve env i r o n m e n t a l
conditions in the regi o n . A feature on Eco-
wa rri o rs profiles leading env i r o n m e n t a l
activists who are invo l ved in the struggle to
s ave our planet.
Another popular progr a m m e , Space to
L e t, tackles a wide range of social issues of
c o n c e rn to wo m e n , including educat i o n ,
e m p l oy m e n t , h e a l t h c a r e , s e x u a l i t y, r e p r o-
d u c t i ve ri g h t s ,a b o rt i o n , and discri m i n at o ry
practices like the dow ry system, a rr a n g e d
m a rriages and female circumcision. I t
d o e s n ’t just look at “ wo m e n ’s issues” bu t
rises to the challenge of conveying wo m a n ’s
views and takes a firm stand against cert a i n
practices upheld in the name of tradition.
The YA Tri b e aims to celebrate A s i a ’s
d i ve rs i t y. A special segment of the progr a m-
m e , The Gong, is devoted to promoting tra-
ditional Asian musical forms and art i s t s , a s
well as exploring the fusion betwe e n
E a s t e rn and We s t e rn form s. View to Te l l p r e-
sents folk tales and my t h o l o gical stori e s
passed on from one generation to another,
keeping this intangible heritage alive among
the yo u n g .
“The Asian focus of the progr a m m e s
appeals to me a gr e at deal because there is so
much to learn and relate to from our ow n
r e gi o n ,” s ays Chri s t i n e , a housewife in
C o l o m b o.
Learning the ropes: over sixty YATV trainees have moved on to secure jobs with Asia’s major television networks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
C O N N E X I O N S
46 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
In the past three ye a rs , young people from
N e p a l ,I n d i a ,B a n g l a d e s h , Pa k i s t a n ,M a l ay s i a
and the Philippines have trained and worked
alongside Sri Lankans at the production head-
q u a rt e rs in Colombo.After gaining a few ye a rs
e x p e rience at YAT V, trainees often move on
to other mainstream netwo r k s.To d ay, over 60
of its trainees have landed jobs in almost all
the major television networks in Asia.
“At YATV I feel that I am doing something
t h at has the potential to make a difference, t o
e m p owe r , to inform , to show that someone
c a r e s ,” s ays 22-year-old Robin Dav i d , a n
Indian media professional who produces YA
C a f é, a programme on Asian music, c o o k e ry
and fashion.
To ensure that programmes include content
from countries across the regi o n ,YATV has pro-
duction centres in Nepal, I n d i a ,B a n g l a d e s h
and Malay s i a , along with a network of stri n g e rs
in Pa k i s t a n ,T h a i l a n d , the Philippines and Sin-
g a p o r e .The programmes are mainly produced
in English and either dubbed or subtitled in dif-
ferent languages.
In addition, Pakistan Television’s satellite
s e rvices provide an Urdu ve rsion of the pro-
gramme N ature Calls to Bangladesh and the
Gulf Stat e s.V i j ay - T V, a satellite television
channel in southern India, broadcasts a Ta m i l
ve rsion of N ature Calls. An Astro Satellite T V
cable and satellite services provide Malay s i a
with Bhasa Malaysia and Tamil ve rsions of the
p r o gr a m m e I - Z o n e, dealing with youth issues.
YATV is about to make its debut in China.
Chinese Educational Television (CETV) has
a greed to broadcast YAT V ’s two progr a m m e s
on N ature and Culture.YATV officials say that
these programmes will be adapted to Chinese
v i e we rs.With the new deal the channel hopes
to broaden its audience substantially.
YATV mostly buys airtime from terr e s-
t rial and satellite networks preferably at pri m e
time in order to attract the largest possible
a u d i e n c e . Income is generated mainly by pro-
gramme sponsorship and adve rt i s i n g .S o m e
n e t works buy programmes directly or enter
into a cost-sharing or co-production arr a n-
gement with YAT V.
Recently organizations such as UNICEF,
the Asian Development Bank,S ave the Chil-
d r e n - N o r way and WHO have started spon-
s o ring programmes on children’s ri g h t s ,
d e m o c r a cy, sustainable development and
n at u r e .O p e r ating with an annual budget of
$3 million,YATV made modest gains for the
first time in 1999 and hopes to turn a gr e at e r
p r o fit this ye a r.
YATV recently started dealing with sen-
sitive political topics through programmes
on Sri Lanka’s long-drawn-out ethnic
c o n fli c t . S at h i ( Awareness) in Sinhala and
V i l i p p u ( Awakening) in Tamil are the net-
wo r k ’s responses to the perceived apat hy,
insensitivity and resignation of a large num-
ber of people to events in the country.P r o-
d u c e rs put the blame on a lack of awa r e n e s s
about the needs and experiences of those
most affected by war.
“It was not easy in the beginning as
h a r d - l i n e rs from both sides were not happy,”
s ays Sulochana Pe i ri s , a 26-year-old pro-
ducer in charge of Sathi.
Opening up
a dialogue
The two progr a m m e s , telecast nat i o n a l l y,
look at the need for initiat i ves to be taken by
both communities to achieve peace and
r e c o n c i l i ation in Sri Lanka.For the first time,
Sinhala viewe rs get the Tamil pers p e c t i ve of
the conflict through one programme while
the other gi ves Tamil viewe rs the Sinhalese
side to this 25-year-old saga.
“It has a good response from the yo u n g
p e o p l e .This is the reason why we want to
continue with it,” says Nimal Perera,news
director of the Talashine Network Ltd
(TNL),a private channel in Sri Lanka.
N ow YATV is looking beyond Asian bor-
ders. As a first step they want to produce a
s h ow called Planet A s i a, a compilation of its
best programmes,aimed atWestern coun-
t ri e s , to raise awareness among yo u n g
people of the issues facing their Asian peers.
YAT V ’s future plans include entering the
European ethnic television market.T h r o u-
ghout Europe there are many ethnic Asian
channels trying to cater to immigrant com-
munities.
With their success, do they hope to
fight Western culture? “No it was not our
aim. We know that it is difficult to fight
the likes of MTV culture,” says Ahamed.
■
+ …
Worldview International Foundation (WIF) 
is an independent, non-profit organization with
headquarters in Sri Lanka. Founded in 1980, it
has consultative status with many United Nations
agencies. WIF operates a network of Media
Centres in Asia and the Middle East.
Useful website: http://www.lanka.net/yatv
W EBSI T E
OF THE MON T H
h t t p : / / w w w. u n e s c o . o r g / v i r t u a l - l i b ra ry
A selection of UNESCO books are now entirely
available online and free of charge. This vir-
tual libra ry is part of the Organization’s new
efforts to make books available to the widest
possible public using the latest developments in
c o m m u n i cation technology. Though presently
limited as to the number of titles, many in this fir s t
selection of works are out-of-print. The majority
are concerned with world heritage sites, complete
with photographs and maps. This experimental
project plans to add more titles on a regular
basis. Arctic languages or Simon Bolivar, Hué or
Gorée, the choice is yours. On your bookmarks!
■
The network makes extensive use of computer graphics, still a fairly rare practice in Asia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
I N T E R V I E W
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 47
Paris has Japanese, South Korean, Malian and
Moroccan designers, but few people from the
South have achieved the rank of “couturier”.
Fashion design now exists in eve ry
c o u n t ry in the wo r l d , but I am only the
third designer from the South—after A z z e-
dine Alaïa of Tunisia and Oscar de la Renta
of the Dominican Republic, for the Bal-
main fashion house—to have achieved the
rank of couturi e r , recognized by their peers
of the Pa ris haute couture professional trade
b o d y. Until now, t h at distinction wa s
reserved for Western designers from coun-
tries with a more developed fashion tradi-
tion. I was lucky enough to start out at a
time when haute couture was opening up to
new talents and encouraging new fashion
houses that were able to express a part i c u l a r
aesthetic sensibility despite their limited
financial resources. So I didn’t suffer from
chauvinistic ostracism, in fa c t , it was just the
o p p o s i t e . From Italy’s Schiaparelli to Spain’s
B a l e n c i a g a, haute couture has alway s
embraced people from different countri e s.
Because Pa ris is in a class of its ow n . It is no
more French than New York is A m e ri c a n :i t
belongs to the world. On the other hand,
Pa risians are so uptight and demanding
t h at you have to be really talented to express
yourself here.
Do you consider fashion a form of artistic
expression?
The couturier is not an art i s t , but a
craftsman with his or her own sensibility. N o
a rtist is expected to change so fa s t ,c r e at i n g
two collections a year. And then, fashion
comes with commercial obligat i o n s. M y
work provides a livelihood for a whole team:
I don’t have the right to run out of inspira-
t i o n . So people shouldn’t imagine us as
egotistical artists bullied around by fin a n c i a l
b a c k e rs. Fashion is an artistic industry resul-
ting from compromise rather than tension.
D e s i g n e rs and their financial backers know
t h at they have to move ahead together.
OCIMAR 
V ERSOLATO’S 
H Y BRID CRE AT IONS
Though too pricey for the average consumer, Brazilian couturier Ocimar Versolato interweaves
multiculturalism and sensuality to create designs that match women’s dreams
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
I N T E R V I E W
48 The UNESCO Courier- May 2000
D e s i g n e rs can no longer make their wil-
dest dreams come true and then just for-
ward the bill,like they used to.
If fashion is not an art, then what is it?
Fashion designers and couturi e rs appre-
hend the subconscious life of our societies
and go on to represent it with their own par-
ticular sensibility.There is a crucial need for
fashion to maintain this transparent channel
to people’s sub-conscience, in order to
u n c over their hidden desires and gi ve
expression to them.That ’s why we don’t
look at our surroundings the way others
do. Our minds are fast as rockets and we
look at eve rything through emotional,
impassioned eye s. I admire the speed of
videos that gi ve you a maximum amount of
i n f o rm ation in a minimum amount of time.
N ow that ’s a truly contemporary language!
How do you justify haute couture prices?
An evening gow n ,which is entirely sewn
by hand so that all the stitches are inv i s i b l e ,
requires hundreds of hours of highly specia-
lized wo r k .Add to that the employe r ’s pay r o l l
expenses and ove r h e a d ,and I have to sell it for
around 80,000 French francs ($13,300).
In spite of the high prices, is haute couture a
profitable business?
My fashion house, like many others ,l i ve s
off the patronage of approx i m ately fif t y
c u s t o m e rs. We aren’t losing money, but we
a r e n ’t making much, e i t h e r. M a ny houses
take advantage of the prestige associated with
fashion to sell perfumes and accessori e s ,
which are more immediately profit a b l e .I ’ ve
refused to do that : you cannot exercise a crea-
t i ve activity with nothing but the profit motive
in mind. If I want to communicate the image
of my creation to customers , I must absolu-
tely not ruin that image by launching, f o r
e x a m p l e , a shampoo with my name on it.O r
you have to justify your approach.Mine start s
at the top: I began with haute couture,d e ve-
loped luxury ready-to-wear clothes and laun-
ched my line of jeans,a lways sticking as close
as possible to my customers ’n e e d s
Your dresses follow the outlines of an ideal
woman: the Versolato woman. Do your
customers look like her? 
I’m surp rised to see how much my cus-
t o m e rs resemble each other both because of
their age—between 18 and 40—and cha-
r a c t e r.They are self-confident women who
A MODEST STA RT
Ocimar Versolato was born to parents of Italian
origin in 19 61 near São Paulo, Brazil’s industrial
capital. Deprived of an income following the death
of his father, an industrialist, his mother opened up
a sewing workshop patronized by the cream of São
Paolo society. Unlike his five brothers and sisters,
young Ocimar fell in love with the business. 
Since there was not yet a place to study fashion
in Brazil, Versolato went to architecture school,
but soon dropped out and started a successful
business making accessories that he sold to ready-
to-wear shops. In 1987 he left for Paris after mee-
ting Marie Rucki, director of the prestigious Berçot
fashion design school, where he enthusiastically
took classes.
The young Brazilian perfected his training during
a four-year stint with the designer Hervé Léger
before launching a luxury ready-to-wear line in
1993. Staged with the help of a few friends and a
3 , 0 0 0 - f ranc budget ($500), his first show of evening
g owns won him many offers. Versolato joined
Lanvin, where he designed women’s ready-to-wear
for two years, introducing jeans to the venerable
house’s collections. Funded by Pessoa de Queiroz,
a Brazilian trust, Versolato set up a workshop on the
Place Vendôme, where he presented his first haute
couture collection in 1998. His label–which makes,
among other things, ready-to-wear, and lin-
gerie–has changed hands several times and is cur-
rently finding new backers. ■
Diaphanous drapings in Rajasthan (India): doesn’t every woman invent her own style?
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
I N T E R V I E W
May 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 49
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498 FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 72FF ( 11 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211FF ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:                  Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
do not feel inhibited about showing their
b o d i e s. By choosing my light clothes, w h i c h
enhance their character, they feel like they
are reaching the perfect balance that defin e s
elegance.These women come in sneakers
and jeans. They put on an evening gown.
And suddenly their postures, their at t i t u d e s
and even their faces change.They feel beau-
t i f u l , t h e y ’re no longer the same. I enjoy
the fact that haute couture enables me to
h ave direct contact with my customers ,
which would hardly be possible in ready-to-
we a r , where the only people designers eve r
meet are buyers.
Too many people cannot afford haute
couture...
To offer eve rybody the pleasure of a
p u r c h a s e , I have created a line of jeans star-
ting at 400 French francs ($67).To d ay, t h e
h e a rt of dreams—haute couture—is on tele-
vision when the two annual collections take
place.In my view, having access to dreams
is more important than possessing the item
t h at nurtures them.When I arri ved in Pa ri s ,
I had a very tight budget.And yet I visited
a rt galleri e s , examining eve rything I wa n t e d
to buy without paying any attention to the
price, but trying to picture what it would
look like at home. I t ’s the same with clothes.
You can’t afford to buy eve rything yo u
want, but you should at least be given the
chance to see what’s out there and savour
the dream inspired by these fashions.
Even though fashion has become an
international industry, do the dresses you design
for your customers reflect your origins a little?
They attempt to express the nat u r a l
seduction which has free rein in Brazil. M y
f e l l ow citizens are open, smiling and fri e n d l y.
They want to seduce eve rybody all the time.
My dresses bear the mark of a country where
people are not ashamed of their bodies.W h e-
ther or not they have perfect looks,B r a z i l i a n s
l i ve almost naked six months a ye a r ,we a ri n g
just a pair of shorts or small items. I discove-
red that in Europe, on the other hand, t h e
body had to remain hidden. Its cultural tra-
dition advises against displaying a less-than-
perfect chest or we a ring a mini-skirt if yo u
d o n ’t have pretty knees.The couturier in me
is trying to treat these traumas.
Brazil is a mixture of ethnic and religious
groups. Does your fashion reflect cultural
diversity?
I remember two Arab princesses. The
m o t h e r , who was rather stri c t , got upset
when she saw that her daughter was inter-
ested in a see-through dress. Until I offered
to add a bodysuit to gi ve a layer of cove ri n g .
The cultural dive rsity expressed by my
fashions consists, among other things, of
o f f e ring sensuality to those who are depri ve d
of it because of their culture. As for the
r e s t , I’m impervious to race, except when I
can use it as a source of inspiration.I desi-
gned an haute couture collection based on
the theme of multicultural melange, dres-
sing Japanese like A f ri c a n s , A f ricans like
R u s s i a n s , and these amusing twists we n t
over we l l . For fashion is a world unto itself,
f r e e , without prejudices—and therefore
open to all kinds of mixing.As an interna-
tional form of expression, fashion must
i n t e gr ate all cultures. My team includes
B r a z i l i a n s ,I t a l i a n s , Japanese and Germ a n s ,
whose skills round each other out.
Do people in Brazil and the rest of South
America keep up with your career?
HAUTE COU T URE
In 18 58, Charles Worth of Great Britain, Empress
Eugénie’s couturier, moved to the Rue de la Pa i x
and, towards the end of the nineteenth century,
presented his creations on living models. “Haute
Couture”, which stood apart from hand-made
garments by its luxurious nature, quickly beca m e
a form of expression practiced by all the great
names in fashion history, including Poiret, Chanel
and Balenciaga. Industrial production methods
based on American Taylorism developed in the
1930s and 1940s, and by the 1950s hand-made
garments entered the era of mass production:
ready-to-wear was born.
At the same time, haute couture prices conti-
nued to climb, partly to factor in expensive labour
costs. Meanwhile, its clientele steadily declined.
By the 1980s, haute couture was being exhibited
in museums, raising it to full-fledged art form
status. Based exclusively in Paris and, secondarily,
in Italy, where Versace and Valentino have their
own ‘Alta Moda’ lines, haute couture designers
present two collections a year including approxi-
mately 60 pieces per couturier, which make
headlines in newspapers’ fashion sections around
the world. Although haute couture is in the red
today, its prestige allows companies to sell less
expensive but more profitable items like ready-
to-wear, handbags, fra g rances, watches and eye-
glasses.
Haute couture sales may not be rising in
volume, but overall the fashion market is expan-
ding by leaps and bounds. The most powerful
groups are Calvin Klein and Ralph Lauren of the
United States, followed by France’s LV MH (Dior,
Givenchy, Lacroix) and, far behind, Italy’s Armani,
Gucci and Prada. These companies are still very
discreet about their profits. For comparison’s
sake, French designers and couturiers recorded
sales of 20 billion francs ($3.3 billion) in 19 97, as
opposed to 16 billion ($2.6 billion) for Calvin
Klein alone. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
I N T E R V I E W
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George's Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Brussels. 
Fax: 538 08 41.
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
Oxford Book & Stationery Co, Code No D 820 8 0 52, Scindia House, New
Delhi 110 001. Fax: 33 22 639 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Nalanda Co. Ltd., 30 Bourbon Street, Port Louis. 
Fax: 212 1313 .
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
Los Amigos de la UNES CO, Avenida Urquijo 62, 2 Izd., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 94427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG, Wissenschaftl. Buchhandlung, Pe t e r s g raben 31, 
CH-4009 Basel. Fax: 306 12 34 .
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce
C/C Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: 286 03 26 .
I have n ’t worked at becoming a sort of star
in South A m e ri c a , but fame is part of my
p r o f e s s i o n .For example, I didn’t think anyo n e
had ever heard of me in Buenos A i r e s.So I wa s
totally surp rised when television journ a l i s t s
there got in touch with me.They consider me
South A m e rican rather than Brazilian,a n d ,a s
s u c h , a representat i ve of A r g e n t i n a .
Does Brazil have an innovative, lively fashion
scene?
The reality is that too many people there,
as elsewhere in the southern countri e s ,m a k e
c o p i e s. More accurat e l y, copies of copies of
c o p i e s. But Brazil is a country where any-
thing is possible.D i rt poor provinces exist next
to highly developed metropolises such as São
Pa u l o, where luxury can find some expre-
s i o n .And Brazilians, like any other people,a r e
able to show the world their particular sense
of aesthetics. I’m delighted that Brazilian
fashion designers have made headway and
n ow have the courage to show themselve s.B u t
they have neither the know - h ow nor the stan-
dards to be intern ationally successful.They are
n a i ve to the point of designing a whole col-
lection with a flat pat t e rn , a simple sewing
machine and an overcast machine1. T h e i r
clothes don’t have any vo l u m e , roundness or
s o p h i s t i c at i o n .Nobody ever taught them how
to make a well-tailored jacket.
How can they get out of this dead end?
Brazilians are curious by nat u r e , a n d
they want to learn .I ’d like to help them by
e n c o u r a ging a transfer of techniques. I n
F r a n c e , labour in the fashion industry is in
s h o rt supply, highly specialized and expen-
s i ve , while tens of millions of people are
u n e m p l oyed and looking for work in Brazil.
By training some of them in France,we ’d also
find a long-term way of improving technical
skills and raising standards back in Brazil
which could make quality shoes and clothes
for all the designers in the wo r l d .
Are you advocating globalization?
I t ’s already here.To d ay, you can design a
g a rment here, assemble it there and embroider
it somewhere else.So yo u ’re better off making
the most of what eve ryo n e ’s best at .After the
wa r , s m a rt people in ove rp o p u l ated India
opened small embroidery fa c t o ri e s. To d ay,
almost all the embroidery sold around the
world comes from India, and the quality can
be as good as it is in Pa ri s.
Have other developing countries specialized in
other techniques?
Right now, e ve rything is incredibly cen-
tralized in Europe—or in Japan, a country
t h at can be considered We s t e rn . But China
has developed techniques for silk, of which
it is the world’s leading producer. One day
it will probably have the same stat e - o f - t h e -
art technology as Europe. And when that
d ay comes, the other countries will tremble.
Does Brazil have any women fashion designers?
Most of the neighbourhood designers
are men, but Brazilian women have never
come up against any obstacles to enter the
fashion industry. Each one is a designer in
her own right.Gifted with an innate sense
of gr o o m i n g, they know how to dress for
a ny occasion without falling into stereo-
types or ridiculous clichés.
Do women prefer being dressed by men?
Male designers gi ve themselves the
freedom to be more daring than their female
c o u n t e rp a rt s , simply because they don’t
have to wear what they create.Their aes-
thetic sense blossoms without restraint and
their customers , who don’t hesitate put-
ting on eight-centimeter heels to look beau-
tiful, prefer aesthetics to comfort.
What’s your state of mind when you design
your collections?
C o u t u ri e rs are wrongly described as
h e a rtless and inaccessible. On the contrary,
like all creat i ve individuals, they are ve ry sen-
s i t i ve and try to defend their fragi l i t y. I f
they want to sell dreams, they must find an
image of the world that expresses happiness.
So it really doesn’t matter whether they
keep their feet on the gr o u n d . C l o t h i n g
designed by a couturier is different from
o r d i n a ry ready-to-wear because of the fee-
lings it conveys. During a fashion show, a
dress has just 30 seconds to express a whole
universe.
Have you used your fame to serve useful
causes?
I’ve staged a fashion show that people
had to pay to see,with the $20,000 in pro-
ceeds going towards the construction of a
building for children with cancer. R i g h t
now, I’m working with the photographer
Sebastião Salgado on a reforestation project.
The funding will come from a show I’m hel-
ping to put on. ■
Interview by Jacques Brunel, j o u r n a l i s t ,
contributor to Le Monde and V o g u e, and René
L e f o r t , director of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r.
1.An overcaster is a machine used to stitch the
edges of two pieces of fabric together.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
VOLUME 5.
Sustainable Development and
Environmental Management
of Small Islands. 
W. Beller; P. d’Ayala; P. Hein (eds)
340 FF/ 51.83
VOLUME 8 .
Biohistory: The Interplay
between Human Society 
and the Biosphere - Past 
and Present. 
S. Boyden. 380 FF/ 57.93
VOLUME 15.
Brazilian Perspectives 
on Sustainable Development
of the Amazon Region. 
M. Clösener-Godt; I. Sachs (eds)
410 FF/ 62.50
VOLUM E 1 8.
Biodiversity in Land-Inland
Water Ecotones.
J. Lachavanne; R. Juge (eds)
380 FF/ 57.93
VOLUM E 2 0.
Forest Biodiversity Research,
Monitoring and Modeling:
Conceptual Background 
and Old World Case Studies.
F. Dallmeier; J.A. Comiskey (eds)
600 FF/ 91.47
VOLUME 2 1.
Forest Biodiversity 
in North, Central and South
America and the Caribbean:
Research and Monitoring.
F. Dallmeier; J.A. Comiskey (eds)
690 FF/ 105.19
MAN AND THE 
BIOSPHERE SERIES
UNESCO Publishing/Part h e n o n
O R D E R S  :
U N E S C O P U B L I S H I N G
7, place de Fontenoy, 75732 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
WORLD BIODIVERSITY SERIES ON CD-ROM
UNESCO Publishing / ETI (Expert Center for Taxonomic Identification of the University of Amsterdam)
Easily accessible, high-quality
information on the environment
UNESCO PUBLISHING
Marine Mammals 
of the World
CD-ROM, PC or Mac    393 FF/ 59.91
A complete overview of sea mammals in
their natural environment with a
description of their lives and behaviour,
particularly addressed to teachers, whale-
and dolphin-watchers, environmentalists,
zoologists and ocean-lovers. Contains
detailed full-colour drawings, spectacular
underwater photographs, call-sounds for
most species, an interactive identification
key and distribution maps.
Fishes of the Nort h - e a s t e rn
A t l a n t i c a n d
t h e M e d i t e rr a n e a n
CD-ROM, PC or Mac    1,180 FF/ 179.89
CD-ROM version of UNESCO’s best-
selling book for ichthyologists all over the
world. Presents up-to-date information on 
1,265 fish species, with a fully illustrated
identification key, drawings, full-colour
illustrations, photographs and distribution
maps. The text is hyperlinked to an
illustrated glossary defining more than 
500 scientific terms and to over 5,000
bibliographical references.
Birds of Europe
CD-ROM, PC or Mac    288 FF/ 43.91
A must for birdwatchers and scientists,
who will find in this complete interactive
multimedia system a unique inform a t i o n
s o u rce for more than 400 bird species.
Contains full-colour drawings of birds and
their eggs, summer and winter distribution
maps and a pictorial field guide for easy
i d e n t i fication. Users may listen to samples
of each bird call and test their knowledge
of birds’ habits and calls by means of a
q u i z .
Five Kingdoms
CD-ROM, PC or Mac    393 FF/ 59.91
A full multimedia information program for
the general public interested in the Eart h ’s
b i o d i v e r s i t y. Presents data on 92 phyla, with
examples from selected genera. Includes
500 illustrations, QuickTime videos,
drawings and a glossary of 700 scientific
t e rm s .
Marine Lobsters 
of the World
CD-ROM, PC or Mac    393 FF/ 59.91
A must for specialists and the fis h i n g
i n d u s t ry. Describes more than 140 lobster
species with detailed drawings, full-colour
p i c t u res, an illustrated interactive
i d e n t i fication key and world distribution
maps. Hyperlinked text to an illustrated
g l o s s a ry defining more than 300 scientific
t e rm s .
Plant Resources of 
South-East Asia
CD-ROM, PC/Mac    590 FF/ 89.94
Describes about 100 important vegetables
and gives a brief description of 125
species of minor importance. Also lists
800 species that yield vegetables as 
a by-product only.
Turtles of the World
By R. W. Barbour
1999
Mac, ISBN 92-3-103700-5
655 FF/ 99.85
An update and extension of Ernst and
Barbour’s standard Turtles of the World
(1989) with many unique colour
photographs. About 40 new species have
been added and the taxonomy has been
completely revised. New distribution
maps, interactive identification key,
literature references, hyperlinked text and
an illustrated glossary defining about
1,000 terms. Suitable for all scientific
libraries and for anyone appreciating the
beauty of nature.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
m a n y v o i c e s o n e w o r l d
P u b l i s h e d
in 27
l a n g u a g e s
In the next issue:
Fo c u s :
Wo m e n :
taking on the political bastion
■ Landmarks of the women’s movement
■ Swedish nurses go to court
■ I ra n : mobilization with a veil
■ India divides over quotas
■ R e d rawing the lines in South Ko r e a ’s 
e l e c t o ral battle
■ United States: loud voices, weak results
■ Do women change politics?
Fe a t u res include
■ Return to Chiapas
■ A clean tide for the Rhine
■ Homeschooling moves into the public spotlight
■ Gypsies in Europe: u n ravelling the ra c i s m
■ I n t e r v i e w : Margarita Salas, the human face 
of science
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
]]>
</page>
</document>
