<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="122144eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
P ro fil de
l ’ i n t e r n a u t e
en rupture
de To i l e
Le nucléaire,
p a ra d e
à l’effet
de serre ?
I t s u k u s h i m a
et son temple:
le temps
re t ro u v é
Afrique CFA:1000 F.CFA,Antilles:18 FF, Belgique:160 FB, Canada:3,95$Can,
Espagne:550 Ptas, USA:4,25 $US, Luxembourg:154 F.Lux, Portugal:700 Esc ,
Suisse:6,20 FS , United Kingdom:2,5£,Maroc:20 DH.SOS cora l :
ree fs
in tro u b l  d
w a t e rs
H ow
O t p o r ’s y o u t h
d rove out
M i lo s e v i c
Spôjmaï Zariâb:
w r i t i n g
the A f g h a n
t ag e d y
March 2001
Canada:$3.95 Cdn,United Kingdom:£2.5,USA:$4.25
P R I VACY IN A WIRED W O R L D
They’re watching you…
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Teaching material 
on human rights
■ How to promote and
teach human rights
■ How to set the bases
of a tolerant society
■ Easy-to-understand,
basic documentation
and practical material.
U N E S C O  P u b l i s h i n g
All Human
Beings …
Manual for Human
Rights Education
Human Rights:
Questions and
Answers
By Leah Levin
Illustrated by Plantu
24 x 17 cm, 172 pp.
50 FF/ 7.62
21 x 14.5 cm, 148 pp.
80 FF/ 12.20
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP
France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
◗ PEOPLE AND PLACES
4 All roads lead to the franchise
Kuwaiti women from all walks of life are campaigning for their citizenship
rights, and namely, the right to vote. 
Photos by Isabelle Eshraghi, text by Haya Al-Mughni
◗ PLANET
10 Corals under siege
Why more half the world’s coral reefs might be lost
within our lifetime. Christl Denecke
11 Patrolling the reefs: an Indonesian initiative John C. Ryan
◗ EDUCATION
13 They’re connected, but are they learning?
Nearly all Canadian schools are connected to the Intern e t ,
but a learning revolution is yet to come. Sean Fine
15 Interview with the OECD’s Edwyn James
◗ ETHICS
38 Otpor, the youth who booted Milosevic
Meeting the generation that rocked Serb society. Christophe Chiclet
◗ CULTURE
41 Pirates and the paper chase
In some countries, pirated books are raking in bigger pro fits than the re a l
t h i n g .
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
43 Chile: a judge steps in Francisca Petrovich
◗ MEDIA
44 Testifying from the front
The trials faced by journalists in covering modern wars. Shiraz Sidhva
◗ TALKING TO…
47 Spôjmaï Zariâb
An exiled Afghan writer tirelessly denounces the nightmare bringing ruin to
her nation.
C O N T E N T S
MARCH 2001
Detailed table of contents on page 16© Jean Lecointre,
Paris
Fo c u s T h e y ’ re watching you…
Privacy in a wired world
Each step forward in the field of new technologies
marks a deeper intrusion into your privacy. This is
the price we must supposedly pay for economic effi-
ciency and security. But more and more people are
rejecting the tradeoff and the rise of a high-tech
surveillance society. In the battle to protect privacy,
choose your weapon wisely: l e g i s l a t i o n ,t e c h n o l o g i-
cal tools, a c t i v i s m , media and even humour… T h e
choice is yours in shielding that intimate space—
p e rsonal liberty—where neither government nor
c o r p o ration has the right to tre a d .
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily re p resent the opinions of UN E S C O or those of the edi-
t o rs of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r s t a f f. The boundaries on maps do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the
United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
I N T H I S I S S U E
◗ The power of words
March 8 is International Women’s
Day, a stark reminder of the long road
to be travelled before the two sexes
share the same rights. In Kuwait,
women are fighting for the right
to vote (pp. 4-9).In Afghanistan,they
are being humiliated by the Taliban.
With words as her only weapon,
the exiled writer Spôjmaï Zariâb has
taken up their cause and denounced
the nightmare imposed upon
her people (pp. 47-51).It is also
with words that young women—and
men—belonging to the Otpor
movement (“Resistance” in Serb)
rocked the establishment to bring
down the Milosevic dictatorship.
◗ …and of technology
New technologies can serve the cause
of freedom,but they are also chipping
into our privacy and eroding our
rights. Under the pretext of economic
efficiency or security, our daily lives
are too often placed under
surveillance (pp.16-37). While these
new technologies have enabled
journalists to chronicle wars in real
time, they have not always been
to truth’s advantage (pp. 44-46).
Technologies are also a formidable
arm for book pirates, who are making
a dent in authors’ royalties while
putting cheap quality works on
the market (pp. 41-43). They are
omnipresent in Canadian schools,
although their impact on learning
is yet to be gauged (pp.13-15).And
their unbridled use is contributing
to global warming, killing off coral
reefs, one of the world’s greatest
underwater riches (pp. 10-12).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
All roads l
the fra n c hi
On a shopping spree in Kuwait City.
4 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Fifty years ago, few Kuwaiti women received more than a basic religious education.Those from
wealthy households were confined to their courtyards, in a section of the house without win-
dows so their voices could not be heard from the outside. Women from more modest hou-
seholds fared slightly better:some worked as midwives, marriage brokers, dressmakers and
Koranic teachers who used their homes as schools,while others were peddlers or market tra-
d e r s. In public, h o w e v e r, all women had to cover themselves in long black cloaks (the
abbayat) and veil their faces with thick black cloths, the boshiat.
Change was prompted by Kuwait’s transformation from a small seafaring community
relying on maritime trade to a major oil producer after 1945.Such rapid economic expansion
created a demand for an educated workforce and the state made education available to all
Kuwaiti citizens.The educated woman became a symbol of modernity, an icon of the modern
s t a t e.The new generation removed the traditional black veil, enrolled in higher education and
competed with men in the labour market. By the 1990s, Kuwaiti women made up 35 percent
of the workforce,with a vast majority employed as teachers, doctors,engineers and lawyers.
Despite these strides, Kuwaiti women continue to be legally defined as family members,
whose rights and responsibilities are circumscribed by their roles as mothers, wives and
daughters. Although the constitution does not discriminate between women and men with
respect to their citizenship rights, a number of laws passed since its adoption are discriminatory.
The 1962 Election Law, for example, restricts the right to vote and run for office to Kuwaiti
men.
After the Gulf Wa r, the Kuwaiti women’s movement brought the voting issue to the fore-
f r o n t , providing the ground for an alliance between Islamist and liberal women activists. S u f-
fragists invoked the heroic roles of women under Iraqi occupation,the sacrifices of female
martyrs and wartime hardships as justifications for gaining political rights. Women inside
Kuwait had participated in armed resistance and risked their lives smuggling food, money and
medicine through military checkpoints. Many were caught,tortured,and killed.
PHOTOS BY ISABELLE ESHRAGHI, TEXT BY HAYA AL-MUGHNI
ISABELLE ESHRAGHI IS A FRENCH PHOTOGRAPHER.
HAYA AL-MUGHNI IS A KUWAITI SOCIOLOGIST AND AUTHOR OF
WOMEN IN KUWAIT: THE POLITICS OF GENDER (LONDON: SAQI BOOKS, 2001).
ead t o
s e
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 5
Since the end of the Gulf War, Kuwaiti women have
stepped up their campaign for the right to vote. Even the
most ardent Islamist activists espouse the cause, touting a
different vision of women’s role in Muslim society
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
All roads lead to the fra n c h i s e
Eye to eye:in other circles,women talk business.
The educated
woman became 
a symbol of
modernity, 
an icon of 
the modern 
state 
Bedouin women latch onto tradition.
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
6 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
But whatever the sacrifices made and stereotypes chal-
l e n g e d , the all-male parliament remained reluctant to extend to
women full citizenship rights, theoretically guaranteed by the
c o n s t i t u t i o n . In November 1999,an Islamist-tribalist coalition suc-
ceeded in defeating a decree issued by Kuwait’s ruler, Sheikh
Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah,which would have granted women the
right to run for office and vote in parliamentary and municipal
elections.
Opponents appeal to narrow interpretations of religious
law to justify the denial of citizenship rights to women.But the
real impetus for their actions is a deep anxiety over a sluggish
economy and changing gender roles. Climbing unemployment
among Kuwaiti youth has raised questions about male identity
as a breadwinner.Masculinity appears to be in crisis.Women are
not only beginning to dominate some sectors in the labour
m a r k e t , they are also moving into positions of power in govern-
ment and industry. The president of Kuwait University, t h e
u n d e r-secretary in the ministry of higher education, and the
managing director of the oil industry are all women.Female suf-
frage would not only undermine male supremacy, but also
strengthen women’s power in the public sphere. Hence, throu-
ghout the 1990s, Islamists and their Bedouin supporters used dif-
All eyes on the bride at the Crown Plaza hotel.
Mama Anessa, hostess of an educational TV show.
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ferent rationales to confine women to their traditional identities.
They blamed rising divorce rates, child delinquency and decli-
ning family values on women’s departure from their traditional
r o l e s. This Islamist-tribalist coalition even managed to force
parliament to pass a law allowing working mothers early reti-
rement in an attempt to make  more public-sector jobs available
to Kuwaiti men.
N e v e r t h e l e s s, Kuwaiti women are not willing to give up
their gains, nor to end their movement for political rights. Fol-
lowing the defeat of the decree, female activists filed six court
cases against the ministry of interior for not allowing them to
register to vote, a move intended to force a ruling on the consti-
tutionality of the Election Law.
Education has changed women’s perceptions of themselves
and their role in society. Even the most ardent Islamist women
activists advocate the extension of the franchise to women and
their participation in the public domain.Unlike liberal women
activists who forged alliances with men’s democratic groups, I s l a-
mist women have opted  to work  from within religious move-
ments. For almost  two decades, they have played the role of
d ay ̀  a t ( p r e a c h e r s ) , converting young women to Islam and
extolling the virtues of a moral  society.They succeeded in chan-
ging Kuwaiti women and popularizing the wearing of the Islamic
veil.
Involvement in Islamist movements has actually given
women new forms of power and prominence.The idealization
All roads lead to the fra n c h i s e
Involvement in Islamist movements has actually 
given women new forms of power and prominence
Asserting themselves:calling for reforms at Kuwait University.
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
8 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Key fig u re s …
Population: 2 million
Surface area: 18,000 sq. km 
Female/male literacy rate: 78.5%/ 83.2% 
Female/male GDP per capita:
$13,347 vs  $34,466
Sources: World Bank,
UNDP (1998,1999).
… a n d
d a t e s
1899: A protectora-
te treaty is signed
with Great Britain.
1961: Full indepen-
dence achieved.
August 1990: Iraqi troops invade the country.
February 1991: US-led UN coalition forces liberate
Kuwait.
1994: Iraq informs the UN that it recognizes
Kuwait's sovere i g n t y, territorial integrity and
international boundaries.
P e r s i a n
G u l f
of the role of mothers as educators has increased their authority
in the home. At the same time, by elevating the importance of
female modesty, Islamist women have acquired a dignified and
respected position in the public arena.
Empowered Islamist women activists share with their male
counterparts the same dream of achieving an Islamic society
ruled by religious idioms and norms. H o w e v e r, their ideal
society appears to differ from the masculinist, h i e r a r c h i c a l ,
ethical order in which women are disenfranchised  and confin e d
to roles dictated by their biological constitution. Islamist women
activists are today embracing a more autonomous vision of an
Islamic society and gender roles.Working from within the reli-
gious movements has given them the chance to engage in a dia-
logue over women’s rights issues and create a new model of
Muslim womanhood.
Wo m e n ’s gender activism in Kuwait is as diverse as it is
c o m p l e x , and highlights the ambiguity of their social status in a
rapidly modernizing country. Most importantly, it reflects the
variety of women’s choices and aspirations in their struggle for
gender equity. ■
Despite setbacks,there’s no letting up on the right-to-vote campaign.
I R A N
KUWAITCITY
K U W A I T
I R A Q
S A U D I
A R A B I A
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
T
CHRISTL DENECKE
PROGRAMME FELLOW AT THE CORAL REEF ALLIANCE
(BERKELEY, CALIFORNIA)
C o rals under siege
Threatened by pollution, overfishing and global warming, coral reefs— a lifeline
for millions of people—are dying off at an alarming rate 
he vibrantly coloured rainforests of the
sea received a disturbing bill of health
during a recent gathering of marine bio-
logists in Bali: in the past few decades,
more than one quarter of the world’s
coral reefs have been destroyed by
human activity. At the present rate, a t
least 57 percent will
be lost within our
lifetime.
This destruction
threatens not only
coral reefs, but also
the lives of some
5 0 0 million or so
people in southeast
and southern Asia,
eastern Africa and
the Caribbean. For
many of these
coastal communi-
t i e s, corals are the
largest source of
p r o t e i n : a healthy
reef can provide
more than 15
tonnes of fish and
seafood per square
kilometre each
y e a r, enough food
for 2,500 people.And often they are the
only source of income, employment and
foreign exchange.
Coastal communities depend on their
reefs to attract tourists,develop the capa-
city for commercial fis h i n g, and protect
shorelines from erosion and storm
d a m a g e. In the British Virgin Islands, f o r
e x a m p l e, 45 percent of revenue comes
from tourism, which provides more than
half of the territory’s employment.A loss
of reefs would probably cause the water
to cloud with algae and the beaches to
erode under the pressure of waves,l e a d i n g
to an estimated  $130 million loss in
i n c o m e.
Created by more than 50 million
yearsof evolution,coral reefs are one of
the most complex and fragile webs of
biodiversity on earth. Naturalists have
catalogued more than 800 species of
r e e f-building coral and 4,000 species
o f reef-dwelling fish. In total, c o r a l
r e e f s may shelter as many as one quarter
of all marine species, and are especially
important as nurseries for young fish.
So why are these lifelines disappea-
ring faster than ever? On a local level,
overfishing has decimated many indivi-
dual reefs,notably in Malaysia,Vi e t n a m ,
Indonesia and the Philippines. Th e
removal of too many plant-eating fis h
allows algae to overgrow and kill the
c o r a l , beginning a chain reaction of local
extinctions that quickly grows beyond
the reef’s natural ability to recover.
Several fishing techniques are particu-
larly lethal.
Blast fis h i n g, when fishers explode
homemade devices over reefs to kill fis h ,
has severely damaged corals in eastern
A f r i c a . Fishing with sodium cyanide is
no better: exposure to this chemical
makes tropical fish slow and clumsy, and
therefore much easier to catch,while at
the same time killing off corals and many
other reef animals.
Cyanide-fished reefs are often
stripped of their marine life and over-
grown by algae. Despite efforts to halt
cyanide fishing, its frequency has
increased in the past few years,driven by
the high prices paid for live fish at tropical
fish restaurants in Asia and aquariums
in North A m e r i c a . Since this form of
fishing began in the 1960s, the amount of
cyanide dumped on coral reefs in the Phi-
lippines alone has exceeded one million
kilograms.
But fishing is
just one chapter of
the story. R e e f s
are  also being
killed by indus-
trial pollution,
sediments running
down rivers from
deforested land
and run-off from
a g r i c u l t u r a l
f e r t i l i z e r s .
Activities such as
coral mining,
d r e d g i n g, s h i p -
grounding and
c o n s t r u c t i o n
break apart large
coral strips and
shatter delicate
b r a n c h e s. S i n c e
r e e f - b u i l d i n g
corals only grow at a rate of  1.3 to 10.2
centimetres per year, each blast-fis h i n g
explosion and dragged object can destroy
a century of reef development.
To make matters worse, global war-
ming is adding to the plight of the reefs.
Not only are corals fragile, but they are
highly sensitive to temperature change.S o
when the 1998 El Niño winds warmed
tropical waters from Africa through Indo-
nesia and the Philippines and out into
the Pacific, reefs in the region turned pale
and quickly faded to an eerie shade of
bone white, a phenomenon known as
b l e a c h i n g. Many bleached corals are
finally killed by algae.The Global Coral
No more shelter for fish: a diver explores a blasted reef.
◗ P L A N E T
10 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Reef Monitoring Network estimates that
bleaching in 1998 destroyed 16 percent of
the earth’s reefs. In the Indian Ocean,
the Maldives, Sri Lanka and western
I n d i a , bleaching had a devastating effect
on reefs already damaged by sedimenta-
tion and pollution from onshore industry
and land-clearing. Those that continue
to be exposed to harmful human impacts
are unlikely to ever recover. Above and
beyond all other destructive pressures,
there’s a good chance that coral reefs as
we know them will be gone in 30 to 50
years if global warming continues as
expected.
While communities cannot do much
about global warming, they can find ways
to ally protection with economic growth.
For example, tourism development and
coral protection go hand-in-hand at the
Bonaire Marine Park in the Dutch
A n t i l l e s. The park, established in 1979,
employs rangers to enforce bans on the
collection of coral, s p e a r fishing and com-
mercial fishing in park areas. To make
the park self-sustaining, managers began
charging a user fee to all visitors in 1992.
Bonaire was one of the first marine parks
to fund itself, instead of relying on money
from foundations or local taxes.
N o w, the degradation of unprotected
reefs elsewhere in the Caribbean has left
Bonaire with some of the healthiest coral
in the area.Almost 30,000 visitors flock to
the park each year,which has fed Bonai-
r e ’s tourism industry. The continuing
efforts of park rangers to protect their
reefs indicate that the island is set to
maintain healthy coral and increase its
revenue from tourism.
Bonaire is just one example of about
400 marine parks designed to protect
reefs. Unfortunately, many of these are
“ p a p e r ” p a r k s, lacking the funding or
community support to enforce protec-
tion laws. Many are geographically iso-
lated and,more often than not,near coast-
lines that are not managed properly,
allowing erosion and chemicals from
areas outside the park to flow in and
damage coral.
With financial resources in develo-
ping countries stretched thin, the most
effective path to protection lies in part-
nerships between local governments,
international aid groups, NGOs and
national foundations.The goal: to design
effectively managed marine parks where
communities maintain control over their
resources with help from more expe-
rienced and better funded national or
international organizations. We a l t h y
nations have an added stake in these bio-
diversity havens: they could well harbour
precious chemicals for developing medi-
c i n e.The most notable is azidothymidine
(AZT), a drug widely used in industria-
lized countries to treat people with A I D S.
AZT was created from a chemical pro-
duced by a Caribbean sea sponge that
slows the growth of viruses. It is unknown
how many more chemicals derived from
coral reef animals may become the basis
for similar life-saving drugs, but that is
just one more good reason for speeding
up the protection of our imperilled reefs.
■
+ …
www.coral.org
Clive Wilkinson (ed.), Status of Coral
Reefs of the World: 2000 , Australian
Institute for Marine Science.
L
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 11
JOHN C. RYAN
ENVIRONMENTAL JOURNALIST
ooking down on the islands and straits of
I n d o n e s i a ’s Komodo National Park from
a rickety turboprop plane, the scenery
seems timeless. From the air, the coral-
studded seas and palm-tree-dotted grass-
lands look much as they have for centu-
r i e s. If not for a few wooden fishing boats,
the primordial scene of stark landscapes
ruled by giant reptiles could almost be
something out of Jurassic Park.
But landing just east of the park, t h e r e
can be no doubt that we are in 21st-cen-
tury Indonesia.Outside the tiny Labuan-
bajo airport, protesters are exercising
their newly-won political freedoms to
demand that the regent in charge of this
part of the province hear their call for
greater local autonomy before he steps on
the twice-weekly flight out of town. I n s i d e,
a glossy display from the U. S. - b a s e d
Nature Conservancy (TNC) alerts new
arrivals to the tremendous diversity of
Komodo’s reefs and the many threats to
t h e m , from anchors to bombs to cy a n i d e.
With their bewildering array of
c o l o u r s, s h a p e s, textures and behaviours,
I n d o n e s i a ’s psychedelic reefs leave fir s t -
time visitors, even experienced scuba
d i v e r s, s l a c k - j a w e d . Komodo National
Park alone is home to 250 species of reef-
building corals and 1,000 fish species—
more than the entire Caribbean. Coral
reefs are tremendously important for the
people of Indonesia, providing half of
the animal protein in the national diet.
With more underwater species and more
people living near reefs than in any other
n a t i o n , the stakes are high in the struggle
Pa t rolling the re e f s
Riding on political reforms and foreign aid, scuba diving operators and villagers
are taking matters into their own hands to salvage some of the world’s richest
reefs
CORALS UNDER SIEGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
to stop the destructive fishing practices
that constitute the biggest threat to the
country’s coral reefs.
Most Indonesian fishers use simple,
low-impact techniques like hand-held
lines or small nets suspended from
bagan, the graceful, square-platformed
crafts whose lonely kerosene lanterns
dot the horizon at night throughout eas-
tern Indonesia.But a minority of  fis h e r s
make big money—often four times a
government official’s salary—by squir-
ting cyanide or throw-
ing home-made bottle bombs, b o t h
brutally effective means to catch fis h
and kill reefs. Blast fishing has already
affected four- fif t h s
of the nation’s
r e e f s.Though these
practices are ill-
e g a l , laws against
them are seldom
enforced by Indo-
n e s i a ’s underfund-
ed and often cor-
rupt authorities.
Yet a few large national parks and
small community-based reserves are suc-
ceeding in slowing down destruction of
these habitats. Routine boat patrols,
begun by authorities in 1996 with assis-
tance from T N C ’s Indonesia Programme,
have reduced fish bombing in Komodo by
roughly 80 percent.In 2000,a new “floa-
ting ranger station,” funded by the area’s
scuba diving operators and TNC, made
two mass arrests in its first weeks of ope-
r a t i o n .The patrols have been controver-
s i a l , dividing local communities between
those who welcome the protection of eco-
nomically important reefs and those who
resent the intrusion of a wealthy Ame-
rican NGO.
Reef-protection efforts have been
more of a hit with local communities
around Bunaken National Park in North
Sulawesi province.Members of the North
Sulawesi Watersports Association charge
a US$5 tax per scuba diver to fund reef
patrols and have started scholarship and
handicraft marketing programmes for
communities in the
park.“We pay the
police approxima-
tely $250 for a two-
day patrol and
have gotten two
big busts for bomb
fis h i n g,possibly the
first in Indonesia.
And the local com-
munity actually supports it,” explains bio-
logist Mark Erdmann, who works as an
adviser to the park and with the water
sports association.
Some North Sulawesi villages have
taken matters into their own hands, s e i z i n g
the opportunity for community involve-
ment in resource management presented
by Indonesia’s ongoing r e f o r m a s i, o r
d e c e n t r a l i z a t i o n ,p r o c e s s. In late 1998, t h e
villagers of Blongko set aside six hectares
of degraded coral reefs and mangroves
as the first community-run marine sanc-
tuary in Indonesia. Less than a year later,
local fisheries have already made a noti-
ceable recovery.
“ We started the sanctuary to bring
the fishing back to how it was in the past,”
explains Blongko’s village head, D o l v i
Ja n i s.“ N o w, for the first time in years, w e
can even cast a line from the beach near
the sanctuary and catch a pelagic [open-
ocean] fish.”
Two other Sulawesi villages have since
established their own marine sanctua-
ries, and all 13 coastal villages in Blong-
ko’s district want to establish their own
reserves. No-fishing reserves, even small
o n e s, let fish recover so dramatically that
they spill over to adjacent areas,a c t u a l l y
allowing more fishing to occur than
before the reserve was established.
The community-run reserves to date
are quite small compared with national
parks like Ko m o d o,but they can be repli-
cated widely at low cost.If the reformasi
and international conservation forces on
display in Labuanbajo airport combine to
support them,even these small reserves
have big potential to help Indonesia’s
r e e f s,fis h e r i e s, and coastal villages flo u r i s h
into the future. ■
Komodo National Park is seeking to attract more ecotourists to its underwater treasures.
“For the first time in
years, we can cast 
a line from the beach
and catch a pelagic
fish.”
Blongko
Manado
JAKARTA
Komodo
Bunaken
National Park
Banda Sea
Celebes 
Sea
Indonesia,an archipelago of 17,000 islands
◗ P L A N E T
12 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
SEAN FINE
EDUCATION EDITOR AT THE GLOBE AND MAIL NEWSPAPER
(TORONTO, CANADA)
T h e y ’ re connected,
but are they learning?
Canada’s ambitious vision of computer learning has made it one of the most
connected nations on Earth. But in the country’s classrooms, teachers are not
getting the help they need to make the most of new technology
w o r l d . By 1999, the country
could boast that it was the fir s t
to hook up every willing school
and library to the Internet.
Only Sweden has a higher per-
centage of its students logging
on at school.
But education in Canada
remains the responsibility of
the provinces. Each one has its
own education budget to allo-
c a t e. And each has its own
views on how and when to
integrate computers into the
c u r r i c u l u m . In A l b e r t a , for ins-
t a n c e, computers are inte-
grated in grade one, while in
Ontario they are not generally
given that kind of prominence
until as late as grade seven.
Alberta,after years of squee-
zing the schools for money, is
now making extra funds avai-
lable for innovation, and Cal-
gary’s school board has been
quite bold in tapping into those
f u n d s.The Galileo Educational
Network is one of its innova-
tive projects designed to bring
schools into the age of the
knowledge-based economy.
Explore and
discover
The three-year project,
funded by $600,000 from the
province and matching funds from
i n d u s t r y, is in place in ten schools, i n c l u d i n g
Glendale Elementary.The idea is that tea-
chers learn to use computers not only as a
means of instruction, but as a tool for chan-
ging the very nature of the classroom.
“Schools are set up on the industrial model.
Children are educated to be workers for
i n d u s t r y,”says Pat Clifford,the president of
Galileo.“They learn very early on the vir-
tues of compliance. They are moved on
every year.The learning is very structured
and hierarchical.”
N o w,she says, students must take more
responsibility for their own learning, with
the teacher acting as a guide and facili-
t a t o r. But it is unrealistic to expect that
teachers can do this alone. The Galileo
programme works closely with school prin-
cipals and the local school boards, a n d
allows teachers to take time off to chart out
new approaches.When given this support,
teachers can afford to confidently test out
different ways. Susan Marinucci,a Grade
At To r o n t o ’s Holy Family Catholic Ele-
mentary school, grade eight teacher Irene
Korbabicz-Putko yearns to help her stu-
dents make the most of computers. H e r
school board offers instruction to the tea-
chers, but in a suburb a good 45 minute-
drive away in rush hour. Not surprisingly,
M s. Korbabicz-Putko sometimes has other
commitments.
Halfway across the country, at Calga-
r y ’s Glendale Elementary School, the local
school board has received funding not only
for on-site teacher training but for an inno-
vative programme that sends experts in
computer education into classrooms to
serve as mentors to the teachers.
Schools like Glendale are finding that
new technology holds extraordinary pro-
mise. But Canada’s experience with com-
puters is very much a tale of two schools.
Holy Fa m i l y, for instance,has just one com-
puter connected to the Internet for 600
students from kindergarten to grade eight.
Glendale has several per classroom.
N a t i o n w i d e, the computer revolution is
still in its early stages.
“Clearly we’re in pioneering days,”
says Richard Smith, the director of Simon
Fraser University’s Centre for Po l i cy
Research on Science and Te c h n o l o g y, w h o
is studying the introduction of computers
into the country’s classrooms. “There will
be missteps and mistakes made, but some-
thing is changing in education and clearly
computers are part of it.”
Back in 1994, Canada set a goal of
having a computer connected to the
Internet in every school and library.
Federal politicians felt that for Canada to
t h r i v e, it must move beyond its traditional
resource-based economy and prepare its
young people for the knowledge-based
Preparing students for the knowledge economy.
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Five teacher at Glendale Ele-
m e n t a r y, has woven computers
into projects involving team work
and real-life situations. When I
recently visited the school, h e r
28 students were enthusiastically
involved in a math and chemistry
p r o j e c t .With their teacher’s help,
they had made soap and were
discussing the best price to sell it
a t . The whole exercise had
involved searching for recipes
and pricing information on the
I n t e r n e t . In another class,
younger students had to imagine
they were on a desert island and
design survival tools with very
few resources at hand. A g a i n ,
with the teacher’s help, they drew
some inspiration from pictures
of tools found on the Internet.
These fledgling efforts refle c t
S m i t h ’s vision of computers as
“providing an opportunity to
engage students in a new style of
learning—the explore and discover style.”
This includes opening up connections to
new people and information sources. For
M a r i n u c c i , the prime benefit is obvious:
“ w e ’re connected to the world,” she asserts.
An end to
the sage?
C o n n e c t i o n , so far, is probably the key
word to describe a flurry of initiatives
across the country, inside and outside the
c l a s s r o o m .The Writers in Electronic Resi-
dence programme, for instance, connects
budding student-writers at several schools
to far-off professional authors who act as
readers and mentors. In the eastern pro-
vince of New Brunswick, a programme
keeps teenage mothers in electronic
contact with their schools after they give
b i r t h . In numerous schools, students are
developing CD-ROMs documenting envi-
ronmental and heritage issues, c r e a t i n g
web pages and producing online maga-
zines.Through its SchoolNet programme,
the government works with the private
sector and education groups to fin a n c e
and promote these innovations.
Teachers experienced with computer
learning understand that their roles must
change, but that they are still vital to the
l e a r n e r. Larry Danielson,of Garden Va l l e y
Collegiate Institute in Wi n k l e r, M a n i t o b a ,
has been teaching an English course avai-
lable partly online for students enrolled
in a co-operative programme (combining
schooling with part-time employment).
But his first principle stresses human
c o n t a c t :“ We really focus on personal rela-
t i o n s h i p s,whether on-line or face to face.”
“What we’re seeing,” says Elise Bois-
j o l y, the executive director of Canada’s
SchoolNet,“is gradually the teachers are
becoming less of the ‘sage on the stage’
than a ‘guide on the side.’ It’s a cultural
shift,and one that will take a bit of time.”
Her hope is that such methods begin as
early as grade one. “If you start early it
will be in the culture of the learner.That’s
part of the larger goal of building a lifelong-
learning culture.”
But she acknowledges that there is a
long way to go. Lack of teacher training is
a major barrier,she says. In Ontario, for ins-
t a n c e, the number of annual professional-
development days has been cut from nine
to four.And money is short for maintaining
and repairing the computers. “If computers
a r e n ’t used in the right way, they can
impede learning,” Boisjoly says.“The gui-
dance of the teacher is critical.”
But as the experience of Irene Korba-
bicz-Putko suggests, Canada has only
begun to address the issue of how to train
its 300,000 public school teachers. “There
are exceptional cases of well-trained tea-
c h e r s, but overall it’s not one of our bright
lights,” says Smith. Until teacher training
receives its due, the country will miss out on
the real benefits of the computers it has ins-
talled at such expense and effort in the
classroom. ■
“When students venture into the virtual landscapes, they are often dazzled
and confused by all the choices available. A Montreal teacher visited
some 40 elementary schools to find out just how the Internet was being used and
d i s c o v e red that the grade 5 and 6 students changed sites on average 15-25
times per hour. He also found they were unable to take in what they were
seeing. After observing 1,000 or so students, he concluded that most of them
simply weren’t absorbing anything of any value. Teachers must also become
conversant with new varieties of plagiarism made possible by computers. Before
the Internet can be of use to anyone, and to prevent it from being an expensive
distraction in the classroom, a human scaffolding must be put into place. There
may be no filters on the Internet, but in schools, there are filters, and they’re called
teachers.” ■
Extracted from an address by Alison Armstrong, co-author of The Child and the Machine,
to the British Colombia Public Education Conference in Canada.
A DISSENTING V I E W
Guiding students through the virtual universe.
14 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
+ …
http://bert.eds.udel.edu/oecd/
roundtables/
INTERVIEW BY
CYNTHIA GUTTMAN
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
OECD countries allocate one to two perc e n t
of their education budgets to information
and communication technology (ICT). H o w
far have they come in making them real
learning tools?
Relatively speaking,education hasn’t
even begun to look at what the implica-
tions are, and they are huge. On average,
OECD countries spend around 0.25 per-
cent of their education budgets on
research and development compared to
seven percent for certain sectors of
industry. As a result, we still know very
little about ICT impact on individual lear-
n i n g, and teachers are not being equipped
with the necessary skills to use these new
tools.
So schools are being equipped without
much thought about the next step?
Here there is a paradox. ICT can help
students develop a range of skills required
by the modern economy, such as learning
how to learn, problem-solving, knowing
how to acquire and evaluate informa-
t i o n , but these are not reflected in the
school curriculum.Teachers are not going
for open-ended inquiries and the
exchange of ideas with other schools and
p e o p l e. Leaving exams at the end of
secondary school are still broadly based
on a corps of knowledge and the ability to
p r o d u c e.Why should teachers invest time
in developing new techniques that are
not sufficiently valued by the system? A t
the same time, those who are doing so
run the risk of prejudicing their students’
chances at exams.
Is ICT nonetheless changing the teacher’s
role?
I recoil strongly from the idea of the
teacher just being there when a student is
having trouble. It suggests an aimless kind
of educational experience. Learning is a
planned exercise.But the pace of change
ushered in by computer technology has
made us more aware than ever that know-
ledge is transient.We cannot see the tea-
cher as someone who gets pumped up at
university and repeats the same lessons
for the next 40 years. Teachers have to
develop more ties with universities and be
well enough connected within society to
know whom to turn to and ask questions,
on a basis of mutual respect.
How could training be improved?
Teachers have to be empowered to
use ICT. If professional development
could take place online and provide  tea-
chers with resources to integrate ICT,
they would gain confidence in these tech-
n o l o g i e s. Po o r-quality software is ano-
ther big obstacle. The way forward is to
encourage dialogue between manufac-
turers and teachers in order to decide
what type of software is required and
what is feasible,both technically and eco-
n o m i c a l l y. This is just beginning to
happen.
Is ICT economically viable?
Most computers have five-year write-
off periods at the very most. How do you
justify putting enormous amounts of
hardware into a school open six hours a
day, 40 weeks a year, when in five years,
things will be obsolete anyway? Th e r e
are universities where facilities are open
around the clock,allowing users to plug
in when they wish.The school should also
give the community a chance to take
advantage of its facilities. For example,
technically skilled students could receive
modest honoraria for doing work in the
evenings at school. You have to see the
school as part of the community, n e t w o r-
king in both directions, rather than as a
walled entity. ■
To find out how ICT—notably CD-
ROMs and the Intern e t — h e l p
or hinder learning, CERI set up an
i n t e rnational network comprisedof
29 students between 17 and 20
years old, which culminated in a
roundtable in December 2000. Whe-
ther they came from North Ame-
rica, Europe or the Pacific, their
assessments were remarkably ali-
gned. While recognizing that the
I n t e rnet was a powerful tool for
learning, many expressed frustra-
tion with it: “Teachers say ‘You can
s e a rch on the Internet,’ but mostly
do not give us time to do so”;
“Sometimes teachers give us
a d d resses but we discover that they
do not exist”; “Very often the
lesson is spoiled by having to solve
technical problems”; “the tradi-
tional method of searching [in the
encyclopaedia] is faster and safer.” 
While crying out for better teacher
training and software, students
also proposed steps for re d u c i n g
the frequent “digital divide” bet-
ween school and home. Finally,
they expressed unease over the cul-
tural dominance of Microsoft, re j e c-
ting the idea of a commerc i a l
monopoly making big pro fits fro m
schools. Students felt that greater
priority should be put on develo-
ping materials with a local cultural
fla v o u r, while acknowledging that
computers had the potential to
start bridging the cultural divide. 
■
STUDENT W O R D S
Time for schools to tune into
the information age
Schools still have to make a quantum leap if they are to prepare students
for the information society, says Edwyn James, of the OECD Centre for
Educational Research and Innovation
THEY’RE CONNECTED, BUT ARE THEY LEARNING?
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
C o n t e n t s
1 8 The spy in your re f r i g e ra t o r …
Simon Davies
2 0 …and the spy who loves us all
S . D .
2 2 Ja p a n : voyeuristic games
Michel Temman and Yves Bougon
2 4 D a t a - s w i n d l e rs : mining for gold
in the badlands of e-commerc e
Catherine Maussion
2 6 The dot.bomb syndro m e
Evan Hendricks
2 7 The quiet re v o l u t i o n
Suelette Dre y f u s
2 9 Fo rsaking genetic secre t s
Amy Otchet
3 1 A tireless tro u b l e s h o o t e r
Glenn Schloss
3 2 Labour pains:
the birth of a movement
David Banisar
3 4 S h h h … . t h e y ’ re listening
Duncan Campbell
3 6 Videomania in George Orwell’s
h o m e l a n d
Jack Cheshire
3 7 B S K , the provider that says N i e t
Anne Nivat
THEY’RE W A
Privacy in
olice and corporate forces are so quietly wiring their way
into daily life that we barely notice it, says Simon Davies,
d i rector of Privacy International. Before long, someone
s o m e w h e re may be watching as you switch TV channels or
call on a mobile phone (pp. 18-19). We are witnessing the
rise of a surveillance society, where social control is deemed
essential for economic efficiency and security (pp. 20-22).
Yet even in Japan, where a high-tech market in voyeurism
has skyrocketed, few can afford to treat their lives as an
open book (pp. 22-23). 
Protect yourselves! To reinforce defences, the European Union is fighting to
protect personal data in e-commerce (pp. 24-25), while companies are rival-
ling to market technologies to guarantee online anonymity (p. 26). Fro m
Guatemala to Haiti, human rights activists are learning the art of encryption
to protect their sources (pp. 27-28). And then there is the ultimate, yet diffi-
cult, defence: by foregoing testing to protect their genetic secrets, many
Americans are simply rejecting
the new technologies (pp. 29-30).
A counter- o ffensive is also taking
shape through activists like
James To, a renegade legislator
in Hong Kong (p. 31). Meanw-
hile an eclectic crew of cyber-
rights and corporate groups is
taking aim at a proposed cyber-
crime treaty (pp. 32-33), while
Duncan Campbell, the journ a l i s t
who revealed the spy network
Echelon, continues his investi-
gation on international sur-
veillance (pp. 34-35). Finally, Bri-
tish satirist Mark Thomas leads a
merry dance around the ubiqui-
tous surveillance cameras of
George Orwell’s homeland (pp.
36-37).
Dossier concept and
co-ordination by Amy Otchet and
Sophie Boukhari. 
F O C U S
P
16 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Over the past decade, the talk,and to
some extent the practice, of privacy in rich
countries has undergone a sea change. P r i-
vacy, once seen as a minority concern of
paranoid activists, is today at the centre
of e-commerce and information society
discussions.
Is this concern limited to rich coun-
tries? Is Internet and telecom privacy not
a policy issue or a public concern in coun-
tries on the bleak side of the digital divide?
Is privacy a non-universal human right? I
address these questions from the dual pers-
pectives of a student of privacy and of a
former privacy policy-maker.
There is little, if any, evidence on the
level of public concern about privacy in
poor countries. But it is a fact that the issue
does not figure large in the policy agendas
of these countries. For example in Sri
L a n k a , the civil war and its attendant pro-
blems of security, the cost of living and
unemployment are likely to be listed as
priority issues, not privacy. Even if the
focus were to be narrowed to Internet and
t e l e c o m , it is likely that access to voice
telephones would be given more weight.
Attitudes toward telephone numbers
can indicate the intensity of telecom pri-
v a cy concerns.In parts of the United States
such as Nevada well over 50 per cent of
residential telephone numbers are unpu-
b l i s h e d . Home telephone numbers are
usually not printed on U. S. business cards.
By contrast, it is a rare Sri Lankan business
card that does not flaunt one. The street
sign of the Coroner’s Court of Sri Lanka’s
capital city displays the Coroner’s home
number.
In 1998-99,I chaired a public hearing
on the improvement of telephone billing
that addressed the making available of
hitherto undisclosed and uncollected call
d e t a i l s. I was surprised that only one of
the over 400 public submissions mentioned
p r i v a cy—an objection to the distribution of
telephone bills unprotected by envelopes.
Until the hearing, the major operator did
not collect or provide call details.This was
good for privacy but cause for much
consumer unhappiness and billing disputes.
The hearing had to decide on the form of
disclosing more information.
Do these facts not reinforce the claim
that privacy is not universal? A c a d e m i c
research suggests otherwise. Irwin A l t m a n
of the U.S. has shown that the essence of
p r i v a cy—the ability, explicitly or impli-
citly, to negotiate boundary conditions of
social relations—is transcultural.What dif-
fers among cultures is the concrete form of
p r i v a cy concern.It is natural to see a heigh-
tened awareness of Internet privacy in the
U. S.The same form will not be found in Sri
L a n k a ,where there are less than four tele-
phones per one hundred people.
When privacy was given concrete form,
such as indiscriminate access to the details
about telephone calls, people understood
and cared. That enabled the crafting of a
final order of the public hearing that safe-
guarded privacy while improving the trans-
parency of the billing process.
Policy discourses in digitally deprived
countries have emphasized external forces
as drivers of privacy policies. In develo-
ping elements of the legal information-
communications infrastructure for the Sri
Lankan government in the late 1980s, I
found most persuasive the claim that our
p r i v a cy policies must meet European
Union standards for the sake of our trading
r e l a t i o n s h i p s. But the external rationale
alone is a weak foundation.Effective poli-
cies need public support. P r i v a cy advo-
cates within and outside government must
rethink their missions as including a strong
component of public education. What I
learned in the public hearing was the need
to translate abstract privacy concerns into
stories that relate to the everyday lives of
c i t i z e n s. This is the key to bridging the
privacy divide. ■
A PRIVA C Y D I V I D E?
BY ROHAN SAMARAJIVA
VISITING PROFESSOR AT DELFT UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY, NETHERLANDS; DIRECTOR OF EXTERNAL PROGRAMS, LIRNE.NET [LEARNING INITIATIVE FOR REFORMS IN NETWORK
ECONOMIES]; AND FORMER DIRECTOR GENERAL OF TELECOMMUNICATIONS OF SRI LANKA.
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 17
ATCHING YO U …
a wired world
O P I N I O N
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
SIMON DAVIES
DIRECTOR OF PRIVACY INTERNATIONAL, A HUMAN RIGHTS GROUP BASED IN LONDON (WWW.PRIVACYINTERNATIONAL.ORG)
The spy
in your re f r i g e r a t o r. . .
Governments and corporations are wiring their way into your home and
you may not even notice it, according to Simon Davies. The world’s
leading privacy advocate chronicles the rise of the surveillance
society where the bedrock of civil rights—privacy—is being
systematically chipped away (pp. 20-22)
T
O imagine the year 2020, forget for a
moment the cumbersome technology por-
trayed in George Orwell’s  Nineteen Eighty-
Fo u r.If present trends continue,s u r v e i l l a n c e
tools will be so seamlessly integrated in our
environment that we won’t even notice the constant
intrusion into our privacy.
Closed circuit television cameras (CCTV) may be
the most obvious—and onerous—future intrusion.A s
is already the case in Britain (see p. 3 6 ) , cameras will
become a fixed component in the design of modern
urban centres,new housing areas,public buildings and
the road system (thanks to a massive network of linked
number plate recognition cameras). Perhaps it is only
a matter of time before legal and community pres-
sures force the cameras into our homes.
As visual surveillance becomes ubiquitous, so will
mass surveillance of Internet and telephone activity.
American and European law enforcement agencies
have already laid the foundations for a massive eaves-
dropping system capable of intercepting all mobile
p h o n e s, Internet communications, fax messages and
pagers throughout Europe.The plan,known as Enfopol
9 8 ,has been drawn up in secret by police and justice offi-
cials as part of a strategy to create a “ s e a m l e s s ” web of
telecommunications surveillance that will one day cross
all national boundaries—touching citizens everyw-
h e r e.
The strategy will oblige all ISPs (Internet Service
Providers) and telephone networks to provide
agencies with “real time, full time” access to all com-
m u n i c a t i o n s,regardless of the country of origin.All new
communications media, including interactive cable
t e l e v i s i o n , will be required to do the same.
Enfopol will be aided by a subject-tagging system
capable of continually tracking targeted individuals.
Known as the “International User Requirements for
I n t e r c e p t i o n ” ( I U R ) , the system, which is currently
being designed, will include not only the names,
addresses and phone numbers of targets and asso-
c i a t e s, but email addresses, credit card details, P I N s,
passwords and even geographic data from mobile
p h o n e s.
Enfopol is just one of several burgeoning systems
used to monitor and profile international
c o m m u n i c a t i o n s. Perhaps the most astounding is
E c h e l o n ,a global eavesdropping system established by
the U. S. National Security A g e n cy that is further dis-
cussed on pages 34-35.
Perfect surveillance requires perfect identity, a n d
the next 20 years will see a comprehensive effort by
authorities to achieve this end. As well as creating
D NA databases—notably to identify people convicted
of violent crimes and missing children—governments
and companies are likely to expand the use of national
electronic finger and hand-scanning systems.
Known as “biometric identifie r s,” these systems
are already used throughout the world.They are sup-
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 19
posedly able to perfectly identify an individual by
electronically scanning the fine details of a hand,fin g e r
or eye (retina). Spain has begun a national fin g e r p r i n t
system to control unemployment benefits and health-
care entitlements. Russia has announced plans for a
national electronic fingerprint system for banks.Ja m a i-
cans are required to scan their thumbs into a database
before qualifying to vote at elections. In France and
G e r m a n y, tests are underway to put fin g e r-print infor-
mation onto credit cards.
For the past five years, the U. S. Immigration and
Naturalization Service (INS) has been developing an
automated passport control system using hand geo-
metry captured on a “ s m a r t ”computer chip card.At the
a i r p o r t , frequent travellers present their card and then
pass their hand through a scan. More than 70,000
people have already enrolled in the plan which,a c c o r-
ding to an INS spokesman, will be expanded world-
w i d e.
But it is the growth of workplace surveillance that
will most directly affect people.In a majority of coun-
t r i e s, employers are permitted—“within reason”—to
place all employees under constant surveillance.Th e y
can tap phones, read email and monitor computer
s c r e e n s. They can bug conversations, analyze com-
puter work, peer through CCTV cameras and use
tracking technology like “ s m a r t ” ID badges to even
monitor trips to the bathroom.I n d e e d , employers now
routinely insist on urine tests to detect drug use and
review the most intimate personal and medical data.
The current telephone software for keeping tabs on
employees’ calls seems primitive compared to the new
g e n e r a t i o n , which can analyze keystrokes on a ter-
minal to determine if time is being efficiently used
between conversations.Even highly skilled workers can
expect to be regularly put under the microscope. I t ’s
likely that network-operating software (which lets
you exchange files with a colleague) already permits
your manager to eavesdrop by observing your screen
in real time, scanning data files and email and even
overwriting passwords. All of which leads us in one
d i r e c t i o n : the workplace of tomorrow will have many
features of the Dickensian workhouse.
Even your home will not be free from surveillance.
The new generation of interactive digital television
(known as i-TV) services, currently being developed,
will offer a new intimacy between TV service pro-
vider and customer. By directly drawing information
on viewing habits,financial transactions and on-screen
“vox pop” s u r v e y s, the company can create a com-
plex profile of every customer.
A recent investigative book, S py T V (edited by
David Burke,an American researcher), describes how
i-TV broadcasters will use neural network software to
create “psychological profil e s ” and then “modify the
b e h a v i o u r ”of viewers.B a s i c a l l y,your TV will show you
a product, monitor your response and then show you
something else based upon it.This cycle will let your T V
set learn enough about you until it has you doing what
it wants.And one day, the person controlling your T V
will be replaced by a computer running artificial intel-
ligence software.
P r i v a cy is and will be eroded in countless other
w a y s. Mobile phones are being turned into geogra-
phical tracking devices with the aim of providing cus-
tomers “ u s e f u l ” i n f o r m a t i o n , like the location of the
nearest petrol station or an advertisement for a local
r e s t a u r a n t . The question is not whether you want or
need these services, but do you want to be trailed? 
You are probably already being followed on the
I n t e r n e t .While some on-line companies keep track of
consumers’ purchases, others offer personalized ser-
vices like news searches, free email and stock portfo-
l i o s.They then sell or trade this information to business
associates without the consumer’s consent (see p. 2 4 ) .
Every time you visit a website, a small file contai-
ning an ID number—known as a “cookie”—is auto-
matically placed on your hard drive to make it easier
to “ fli p ” back through pages on a website. H o w e v e r,
advertising networks can use a single cookie to track
a user across thousands of websites.The Internet Engi-
neering Task Force (made up of network designers,v e n-
dors and researchers) is now developing a system to
assign a permanent ID number to every device, like a
V C R ,hooked onto the net.So it may be only a matter
ot time before  somebody somewhere knows exactly
what you keep in the refrigerator. ■
K E E P I N G  P R I V A T E  I N  A  W I R E D  W O R L D
+ …
To join the i-TV boycott: http://www.spytv.co.uk
© Jean Lecointre, Paris
The electronic
computer is to
individual privacy
what the machine
gun was to
horse cavalry.
Alan W. Scheflin,
American law professor
(1942-) 
and Edward M. Opton,
Jr., American
psychology researcher
(1936-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
S.D.
…and the spy
who loves us all
T
H E picturesque streets of Edinburgh
(Scotland) are currently playing host to
an extraordinary episode in the ancient
struggle between individual privacy and
state power. H e r e, at the headquarters
of the Lothian and Borders Po l i c e, the DNA of the
local population is being systematically archived.
For the past two years,every person arrested or
detained by Edinburgh police has been forced to
take a DNA test. The offences that warrant this
practice are not confined to the obvious categories
of murder, rape and burglary, but also to traffic
o f f e n c e s, s h o p l i f t i n g, and public order transgres-
sions such as breach of the peace.
The collection and storage of DNA must surely
rank as one of the most intimate invasions of the
person,and yet the policy appears to have secured
substantial public support.A recent opinion poll sug-
gests that nearly three-quarters of the local popu-
lation would be willing to give up their DNA in
the “pursuit of a crime.”
The UK Home Office and other government
agencies have also been excited by the potential of
DNA testing. Recent Child Support Agency legis-
lation requires all alleged runaway fathers to submit
to a DNA test. Failure to do so is tantamount in law
to an admission of guilt.
The current mania for DNA testing is merely a
symptom of a much broader trend throughout the
w o r l d . In the past, surveillance was based on the tar-
geting of specific individuals or groups. In recent
y e a r s, governments and private sector organiza-
tions have moved to incorporate it into almost
every aspect of our finances, communication and
lifestyle. While paying lip service to privacy, they
argue that surveillance is necessary to maintain
law and order and to promote economic effic i e n cy.
The rationale is often self-serving, and somewhat
b o g u s, but a substantial number of people have
nevertheless been persuaded that the surrender
of privacy is the price we must pay for a better and
safer society.
The result is that many countries are becoming
surveillance societies. There has probably never
been a time in history when so much information has
been amassed on the population-at-large. Details of
the average economically active adult in the deve-
loped world are located in around 400 major data-
bases—enough processed data to compile a formi-
dable reference book for each person.
It is common wisdom that the power, capacity
and speed of information technology are accelera-
ting rapidly.The extent of privacy invasion—or cer-
tainly the potential to invade privacy — i n c r e a s e s
correspondingly. But it is not merely the increased
capacity and decreasing cost of information tech-
nology that creates threats to privacy. G l o b a l i z a t i o n
of systems such as the Internet removes geogra-
phical limitations (and legal protections) to data
flo w s. Modern information systems are increasingly
compatible and can exchange and process diffe-
rent forms of data.Meanwhile multimedia, which
fuses many forms of transmission and expression of
data and images, creates vast difficulties for legis-
lators wishing to protect personal privacy.
An example: the company UK InfoDisc has
produced a CD-ROM that merges the electoral
roll data with the telephone book and geo-demo-
graphic data.So now the most basic and innocent
information about you can be entered into the disc,
revealing all manner of facts. Your telephone
number leads instantly to your address.Your name
leads automatically to your occupation and age. It
goes without saying that the finance and credit
You see, that’s
the problem
with terrorists—
they have no
respect for your
private life.
Arnold
Schwarzenegger,
Austrian-American
actor, in “True Lies”
(1947-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 21
i n d u s t r y,private investigators, n e w s p a p e r s, m a r k e-
ting companies and police all make extensive use of
the product.
These issues are important because the growing
informational bond between citizen and state (and of
course the private sector) is nibbling away at human
a u t o n o m y. As decision-making by institutions
becomes automated, the factors that affect our lives
are made on the basis of an increasing mass of inti-
mate personal data.The risk of statelessness or dis-
crimination correspondingly intensifies.
In developing countries, the threat is magni-
fied. The perfect identification of individuals can
have fatal consequences. Governments of develo-
ping nations rely on first world countries to supply
them with equipment for digital wiretapping, trac-
king and deciphering data along with scanners, b u g s
and computer intercept systems. The transfer of
surveillance technology from first to third world
(sometimes known as the repression trade) is now
a lucrative sideline for the arms industry. Wh i l e
information technology companies routinely pro-
mote their products as a means of achieving social
reform,the human rights community increasingly
d e fines them as a means of social and political
control.
In this environment, the struggle to strike a
balance between individual autonomy and state
power is more complex than ever. Not surprisingly,
no other fundamental right in the public policy arena
has generated such turbulence and controversy as pri-
v a cy. While the international community has rea-
ched a baseline consensus on torture, d i s c r i m i n a-
tion and racial hatred, p r i v a cy is viewed by many
governments and corporations as the bogeyman of
human rights.While opinion polls consistently indi-
cate that people care about privacy,public opposition
even to the most blatant intrusion is sporadic.
In the United States, the fingerprinting of wel-
fare recipients has proceeded with scarcely a
K E E P I N G  P R I V A T E  I N  A  W I R E D  W O R L D
The world’s leading experts are still unable to agree on a
single definition of privacy despite decades of academic
debate. One pioneer in the field, Alan Westin of the U.S., des-
cribed privacy as “part philosophy, some semantics, and
much pure passion.” On that point, at least, everyone agre e s .
The recognition of privacy is nevertheless deeply rooted in
h i s t o r y. The Bible makes numerous re f e rences to it. Jewish
law has long recognized the concept of freedom from being
watched. There were also protections in Classical Greece and
ancient China. The Hippocratic Oath, dating from 300 BC,
demands the confidentiality of doctor-patient re l a t i o n-
ships. We s t e rn countries have had protections for hun-
d reds of years by, for example, applying rules to arre s t
peeping Toms or eavesdroppers. In the early 19th century,
parliamentarian William Pitt famously wrote, “The poo-
rest man may in his cottage bid defiance to all the force of
the Crown. It may be frail; its roof may shake; the wind may
blow through it; the storms may enter; the rain may enter—
but the King of England cannot enter; all his forces dare not
cross the threshold of the ruined tenement.”
Indeed privacy is neither a modern nor a western concept.
While the idea of privacy as a fundamental human right
still raises eyebrows in many developing countries, the
concept is familiar to the citizens of those cultures. At a
societal and government level, privacy may be viewed with
some suspicion, and yet at a personal level, everyone draws
a curtain around certain aspects of family and private life.
In some respects, privacy is similar to freedom: the less you
have of it, the easier it is to recognize. Like the concept of
f reedom, privacy means diff e rent things to diff e rent cul-
t u res. In France, it equates most closely to liberty. In America,
it is an inseparable component of individual fre e d o m s —
particularly freedom from intrusion by federal govern m e n t .
Many European countries interpret privacy as the pro t e c t i o n
of personal data.
For numerous Anglo-Saxon and French authors, the right to
privacy entails respect for “private life”: the right to live, as
far as one wishes, protected from publicity and to develop
fulfilling relationships. 
“In one sense, all human rights are aspects of the right to pri-
v a c y,” as Fernando Volio Jimenez, a champion of democracy
f rom Costa Rica, once observed. Privacy protection is one way
of drawing the line on how far society can intrude into your
a ffairs. In that context, privacy is a question of power—
your own as well as that of the government, your family,
employer and neighbour. It can even be a benchmark to
indicate how much autonomy a nation should have in the
emerging international order. ■
THE BEDROCK OF CIVIL LIBERTIES
© Jean Lecointre, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
MICHEL TEMMAN AND YVES BOUGON
FRENCH JOURNALISTS BASED IN TOKYO
Japan: v o y e u r i s t i c g a m e s
Gadgets and “electronic leashes” are the rage in Tokyo where people
don’t just spy on their neighbours but on the latest star in vogue
22 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
murmur of discontent,while in Australia,attempts
by the federal government to introduce a national
identity card sparked the biggest public protest in
recent memory.And yet while Australian legislation
forcing banks to report suspicious transactions
passed without notice, similar legislation in the U. S.
provoked more than a quarter of a million written
c o m p l a i n t s. In Germany and Au s t r a l i a ,proposals to
introduce digital phone services sparked wides-
pread privacy concerns. Identical technology in Bri-
tain was introduced with little or no discussion.
The most dangerous enemy of privacy,h o w e v e r,
is the well-meaning individual who argues “I have
nothing to hide, so I have nothing to fear.” N o t h i n g
could be further from the truth. Everyone has a
sphere of private life which must be protected from
i n t r u s i o n . Few people could honestly claim that
their life—their family details, financial affairs and
health history—is an open book.Even if this were
s o, their happy position should not provide a ration-
ale for the invasion of other people’s lives.
But the argument for privacy goes well beyond
the integrity and autonomy of each individual.
Privacy is the fundamental test of a free society’s
s t r e n g t h .The right to privacy is the right to protect
ourselves against intrusion by the outside world. I t
is the measure we use to set limits on the demands
made upon us. It is the right we invoke to defend
our personal freedom, our autonomy and our
identity. It is the basis upon which we assess the
balance of power between ourselves and the world
around us.
P r i v a cy is also the natural partner of freedom of
expression. They are equal and compatible rights.
More so, both have evolved in the modern context
as a synergy.As the world embraces the information
society and our lives go increasingly on-line, t h e
forces that promote censorship also diminish pri-
vacy—and vice versa.
It will become apparent in the coming years
that these two rights will form the Great Pillars of
any free society. ■
A
k i h a b a r a ,To k y o ’s electronics retail dis-
t r i c t ,has been bustling since 1998,w h e n
the new economy really took off in
Ja p a n .“New computers and cell phones
with Internet access are the best-sel-
ling products,” says Toshihiro Miyazaki, a salesman
at Laox, a huge mass-consumer temple devoted to
e l e c t r o n i c s.
But another section of the store is also packed:
the one selling gadgets for spying on spouses,n e i g h-
bours and co-workers—miniature digital cameras
with pictures that can be viewed from a distance,
m i c r o - c h i p s, miniature recorders and electronic
“ l e a s h e s ” so small they are almost invisible.R e s e a r-
chers and engineers in the laboratories of Sony,
Sharp, Panasonic and others are busy developing
© Jean Lecointre, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 23
more and more miniaturized devices. Prices range
from 30,000 yen ($255) to
200,000 yen ($1,700), and sales
at Laox have been rising since
1999.These items are especially
popular with 15 to 25 year-olds
(the s e d a i video-game genera-
tion) and with o t a k u (children of
the virtual empire). O t h e r s,
known as the camera kozô , get
their share of fun from snapping
embarrassing pictures with
remote-controlled miniature
cameras.
In Ja p a n , a society influ e n c e d
by Confuciansim, control over
the self and others has always
been the norm. The neighbou-
rhood police station (k o b a n) and
foot patrolmen still frequently
draw up detailed lists of local
residents and inquire about the
identity of newcomers as soon
as they move in.N e i g h b o u r h o o d
committees (t o n a r i g u m i) , an ins-
titution dating back to the 16th
c e n t u r y, were used during the
Second World War to punish acti-
vities deemed anti-Ja p a n e s e.
Although the committees are on
the wane, they still exist.
To d a y, these traditional ways of watching people
seem harmless compared to the spying being done
with new electronic products. There are regular
reports on television about acts of voyeurism. S o m e
people specialize in spying on public toilets, while
others hide cameras and microphones in the homes
of friends or young, single women. Others have
turned into Internet paparazzi, broadcasting their
s t e a l t h y pictures on the We b. R e c e n t l y, the marathon
runner Naoko Takahashi, who has become a star
since bringing home a gold medal from the Sydney
O l y m p i c s, found that her fame had stretched beyond
acceptable limits. Thousands of copies of a video
featuring her naked in her bathroom have been ille-
gally sold.A miniature camera filmed the pictures
without her knowledge.
The Japanese are increasingly concerned about
the rising number of abuses. In Ja n u a r y, a high school
teacher was arrested for filming his students changing
in the locker room, and a cameraman from the
national NHK television network filmed people at
home without their knowing it.Debate is stepping
up over an inexpensive service called Imadoko
(“where are you?”),which allows parents to track
their children’s every move. A microchip built into
a cell phone tells the company where the user is at
all times.At the parents’ request, the company sends
them a map showing their child’s exact wherea-
bouts.
The Japanese feel even more anxious because
the government has recently passed a law streng-
thening the powers of the central police authorities
( N PA) and the justice ministry to use spying tools
such as phone taps and email screening.“ This law
is designed to help criminal investigations, not to
interfere in people’s daily lives,” the NPA says.
But some specialists, such as Shin Mizukoshi, a
media expert at Tokyo University, are asking
uneasy questions:“Has Big Brother broken into
our homes? Isn’t police interception of commu-
nications a new invasion of privacy?”
These methods are mainly used to combat com-
puter piracy. A law “forbidding illegal access”has
just come into force — it punishes computer crimes
with a year’s imprisonment and a 500,000-yen fine
($5,000).Eighty engineer-police officers stalk cri-
minals at the NPA’s High-Tech Crime Te c h n i c a l
Expert Center, a cyber-surveillance centre with an
annual budget of 190 million yen ($1.85 million).
But trouble-makers are also honing their elec-
tronics skills. Recently, a pair of kidnappers used
prepaid phones to announce their ransom
demands and conditions. “The omnipresence of
advanced mobile communication systems creates
new challenges,” says an NPA official.“Compro-
mises are necessary in the interest of the public
and its security.” As legal expert Yoichi Higuchi
o b s e r v e s, the right to privacy may remain “ v i r t u a l ”
in Japan. ■
K E E P I N G  P R I V A T E  I N  A  W I R E D  W O R L D
Sony unveils the “world’s smallest and lightest”digital still camera,weighing just 26 grammes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
CATHERINE MAUSSION
JOURNALIST AT THE FRENCH DAILY LIBÉRATION
D a t a - s w i n d l e rs: gold mining
Trading personal data on Internet users is a booming business that is
also spurring laws to protect e-consumers
T
wo hundred dollars just for answering a
q u e s t i o n n a i r e. The offer from an A m e-
rican group called Greenfield Consulting
recently landed in the electronic mailbox
of a member of Fr a n c e ’s Information Te c h-
nology and Freedom Commission (CN I L) .The attrac-
tive proposal reflects the high premium that com-
panies put on gathering data about Internet users.
Every year in late January, a huge file fair, the
“customer relations” e x h i b i t i o n , takes place in
Paris. At this year’s event, entirely devoted to e-
commerce and the Internet, I - B a s e, a start-up
founded in 1999,offered its file of 15 to 35 year- o l d s,
“a behavioural database of over 700,000 young
p e o p l e.”Where do the names and data come from?
The company refuses to answer the question.A n o-
ther firm taking part in the event, C o n s o d a t a , i s
one of Fr a n c e ’s two megabase companies. E a c h
y e a r, Consodata and its counterpart, C l a r i t a s, s e n d
a form to millions of mailboxes with questions
about outstanding loans,reading habits,h o b b i e s, e t c.
Every bit counts:with time, these information snip-
pets turn into refined consumer profiles that are
worth gold.
In the age of e-commerce and personalized
s e r v i c e s, these companies are increasingly inter-
ested in Internet users.To find out their every whim,
Consodata has set up a special subsidiary called
C a b e s t a n , w h i c h
offers online games
as bait to subscribers
of Spray, an access
p r o v i d e r. P e r s o n a l
information left
behind while answe-
ring a quiz thus
became a gold mine
for Cabestan, which
will put the data on
the market soon.
These practices
are already very far
advanced in the
United States, t h e
cradle of the Net
economy and of
“data mining.” S e r g e
G a u t h r o n e t , a
consultant speciali-
zing in these issues, went there to visit “e-mail mar-
k e t e r s ” with “a mind-boggling artillery.” Fi r s t ,t h e y
send forms to the most popular sites, asking visitors
to answer questions about their profession, l e i s u r e
a c t i v i t i e s, children and so on. Wh a t ’s more, t h e
Internet users are “ t r a c k e d ” while making pur-
chases and surfing the Net. This enables online
marketing firms to send them increasingly specific
offers.These companies boast about being able to
send up to 100 million emails a day! Since there are
about 200 of them worldwide, their total strike
force may be as high as 20 billion emails a day,
says Gauthronet,or “about sixty emails per elec-
tronic mailbox every 24 hours!”
When the cookies
crumble
Gauthronet has just submitted a detailed report
about these practices to the European Commis-
s i o n . His first conclusion is that data-gathering
methods seem more transparent now than they did
a few years ago,when the overwhelming majority of
companies collected information without Internet
users knowing it. Their most widespread methods
consisted of using “ c o o k i e s ” (software installed on
hard drives to record users’ comings and goings on
the Net), or directing their questions to children,
who are more forthcoming. N o w a d a y s, i n f o r m a-
tion is increasingly gathered with the express
consent of the consumer (known as the “opt-in”
p r i n c i p l e ) , who can pull out of the game at any
time.Another advance is “permission marketing”:
e-marketers are starting to ask users for their
DoubleClick, the Intern e t ’s largest advertising firm, had better watch its
step. The company puts advertising banners on websites—and spies
on users with electronic informers called cookies. The purpose is to deter-
mine Internet surfers’ pro files so that they can be sent tailor-made adver-
tisements.
As long as Internet users were identified only by information about their
computers, they remained relatively anonymous. But everything changed
in 1999 when DoubleClick bought out Abacus, a database company that
kept track of some two billion online orders—and the names of millions
of Americans who placed them! DoubleClick combined its own files with
that of Abacus to make an even bigger, more accurate database—and, more
alarming still, one with names.
Privacy watchdog groups went on the offensive and sued the company.
Eventually, DoubleClick was forced to give up its megabase. 
M o re re c e n t l y, the world’s biggest e-bookseller, Amazon, sparked another
c o n t ro v e r s y. In September 2000, the money-losing business suddenly
decided to rent customer information to third parties, something it had
a g reed not to do. Again, American privacy advocates sued. The bookseller
THE LONG ARM OF THE LAW
24 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
consent before bombarding them with advertising
emails.
So, where’s the threat? First,says Gauthronet,
some companies don’t always have a very scrupu-
lous vision of opt-in.“ For example,” he explains,“ a n
Internet user just has to bookmark a site to be
considered giving consent for everything and any-
t h i n g.” In another abuse, sensitive information
sometimes finds its way into a routine and autho-
rized data-gathering procedure without the Internet
user knowing it. Beyond that, Gauthronet raises
issues of freedom and “the dispossession of the
s e l f”that databases are going to bring about.“ Wh e n
your identity is frozen,” he says,“ y o u ’re stripped of
the right and means to define yourself the way you
want to.” And of course, he mentions the steady
erosion of the consumer’s privacy.
Vacancies
in the safe harbor
On October 25, 1 9 9 5 , the European Union
unanimously adopted a directive that gives all its
citizens the right to access databases, the right of rec-
tification,and the right to refuse the sale of data to
a third party.The measure also stipulates that no fil e
may leave Europe for a third country unless the
latter can guarantee an “ a d e q u a t e ” level of personal
data protection.This means that American Express
and Microsoft, for example, cannot repatriate
employee and client files to the United States unless
they sign a contract agreeing to respect certain
rules.
H o w e v e r, even a united Europe is having a hard
time making its views heard, especially in the United
S t a t e s. Shortly before the directive entered into
force on October 25, 1 9 9 8 , Washington was still
defending the principle of “ s e l f - r e g u l a t i o n .” Th e
deadlock between the U. S. Federal Trade Com-
mission and the European Commission dragged
on for two years. E v e n t u a l l y, in July 2000,both par-
ties signed the “safe harbor”accord,which quietly
entered into force on November 1.According to the
a g r e e m e n t , to keep trans-Atlantic data flo w i n g,
companies must agree to observe the European
directive’s basic principles and to accept sanctions
if they don’t .The United States, Hungary and Swit-
zerland have received the EU’s “clean country”
label.
H o w e v e r, the measure is not to American com-
panies’ liking. So far, just seven businesses have
joined safe harbor! French legal expert Etienne
Drouard,who is following the issue for the CNIL,
doubts it will be successful:American companies
“consider the agreement as a relinquishing of
national sovereignty!” he says.But the whole issue
may crop up again this year, because Washington is
showing signs of taking a harder line on privacy.
After the Amazon and DoubleClick scandals (see
box) among others, privacy has become a hot poli-
tical issue. The new congressional members had
barely taken their seats when several of them put
forward bills on the matter.A p p a r e n t l y, f r e e - m a r k e t
America is coming up against its citizens’ increa-
singly fierce resistance. ■
A global view of data protection laws.
■ ■ Legislation in effect
■ ■ Legislation pending
n g in the badlands of e-commerc e
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 25
K E E P I N G  P R I V A T E  I N  A  W I R E D  W O R L D
Did you know…
In a survey of the 100 most popular sites in
their respective countries, 92% of the U.S.-
based sites placed at least one cookie while
47% did so among the EU-based ones. 80%
of those in the U.S. and 72% in the EU col-
lected some form of information.
http://www.consumersinternational.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
EVAN HENDRICKS
EDITOR/PUBLISHER OF PRIVACY TIMES, BASEDIN WASHINGTON DC
The d o t . b o m b s y n d ro m e
Everyone agrees that privacy is good for business. But is there a market
for companies offering to protect it?
W
hile several firms have recently suf-
fered class-action lawsuits and public
outrage over apparent intrusions
into customers’ personal data,
American Express is one of a
number of businesses that may be blazing the right
path from privacy to profit s.
Last year, the credit card issuer rolled out
“Private Payments,” enabling its customers to go
online and obtain “ D i s p o s a b l e ” credit card numbers
that could be used for only one online purchase. If
the number was ever stolen after being used for a
purchase, it would be worthless.
A key lesson is that protecting privacy, in this
case the credit card number,became an “ e n h a n c e d
value”to an existing service. Moreover,American
Express understood that the credit card number
was the “tip of the privacy iceberg”—it plans to
roll out a suite of related services, like anonymous
Internet browsing, in 2001. Rival companies, like
Visa/Mastercard,are following the same trail.
Another company to watch is PrivaSys, of San
Fr a n c i s c o,which has patented technology to enable
plastic credit cards to generate disposable num-
bers for each purchase.
PrivaSys does this by
equipping the card with a
c a l c u l a t o r-styled key pad
and LCD screen, a very
thin battery, and a special
magnetic stripe. The card-
holder punches a 4-digit
PIN into the credit card
itself and—v o i l à !—the card
generates the disposable
number.
But securing payments
is just one part of an emer-
ging privacy protection
m a r k e t . Other firms are
offering anonymous or
“ p s e u d o n y m o u s ”b r o w s i n g
t o o l s, packages to control
cookies—the strings of
code that are planted on
the user’s computer by
websites—and services to
block hacker intrusion.
Only time will tell which
companies will control niche markets or achieve cri-
tical mass.
Wh a t ’s clear is that the nascent e-commerce
industry badly miscalculated the importance of pri-
vacy to their business model. For without privacy,
there was no consumer confid e n c e, and without
such confid e n c e,e-commerce had no chance of ful-
filling the short-term, high expectations that ini-
tially sent their stock values soaring. The current
shake-out of the “dot.bomb” industry shows how
costly this miscalculation over privacy was.
An added but
essential value
But if you thought privacy was a big issue for e-
c o m m e r c e, consider the debate on the wireless
i n d u s t r y.Referred to as Mobile or M-commerce, t h i s
industry appears to have unlimited potential to
deliver information and location-based services,
advertisements, and discount coupons to cellular
phones and hand-held wireless devices. M - c o m-
merce risks hitting the major “ p r i v a cy buttons”:
constant surveillance via location-based tracking;
unsolicited ads clogging communications devices;
detailed profiles of individuals’ interests and move-
ments;and insecure payment mechanisms.
Nonetheless, the industry is showing signs that
it has learned from the mistakes of e-commerce.A
few months ago at a workshop of the U.S. Federal
Trade Commission, leading wireless industry groups
unveiled guidelines requiring companies to obtain
a consumer’s consent before collecting or using
personal data. This wasn’t altruism: the industry
understands that consumers will not tolerate com-
mercial services to their cell phones unless they
explicitly consent.
So far, privacy’s brief tenure in the commercial
marketplace indicates that some people are willing
to pay extra to protect their privacy. But the more
important lesson is that consumers are unlikely to
take more than a few extra steps to secure their data.
If they perceive that a given medium, like the
I n t e r n e t , is not privacy - f r i e n d l y, they either change
their habitual uses or actually refrain from them
altogether.
The likelihood is that privacy will become an
“added value,”creating a market for those who can
integrate privacy into payment mechanisms without
excessively burdening the consumer. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 27
A
quiet revolution is creeping through
human rights groups around the world.
D o n ’t expect to see noisy marches
through the streets of Guatemala or
angry protests in Ko s o v o, though both
places are hotspots in the transformation.The revo-
lution is running through electronic ether and human
grey matter.
Computer technology, and particularly crypto-
graphy software (which uses secret codes to trans-
form data into a stream of seemingly random cha-
racters), is subtly changing the balance of power
between repressive governments and the human
rights groups that watch them.From Cambodia to
El Salvador, grassroots human rights organizations
are embracing software that allows them to track
government abuses and then hide their data in
order to protect sources.
A driving force in this revolution is Dr. Patrick
B a l l , deputy director of the science and human rights
program at the American Association for the A d v a n-
cement of Science (AAAS).For the past nine years,
Ball has been discreetly travelling in the wake of wars
and insurrections to train human rights workers in
the science of information gathering.He has shaped
and protected databases in places such as El Sal-
v a d o r, G u a t e m a l a ,H a i t i ,E t h i o p i a ,A l b a n i a , Ko s o v o
and South Africa,among others.
Crucial testimony 
under lock and key
When Ball first began this training in the early
1 9 9 0 s, most human rights workers were techno-
phobes. Technology, used for so long as a tool of
spying by repressive governments, was clearly the
e n e m y. Every project was tough work, as Ball tried
to convince people in the field to adopt increasingly
cheap computer software as a means of deftly tur-
ning the tables on governments.About three years
ago however, the climate began to change.
“Human rights groups are beginning to reco-
gnize the tremendous analytic power large-scale
data brings to us and you simply cannot do that
without technology,” says Ball.While visiting groups
in Cambodia who were learning to use this tech-
n o l o g y, I was struck by the enormous piles of paper
on every desk. It could take two weeks to extract one
simple fig u r e, such as how many rapes were reported
in Cambodia in a month.
Cheap computers and, more importantly,e a s y -
to-use software programmes are changing that, s a y s
Ball. Database, spreadsheet, word processing and
communications programmes have made it pos-
sible for even small organizations to track abuses
with scientific rigour.
This analytic precision makes a powerful
weapon.It also makes a logical target for political
o p p o n e n t s.Witnesses often risk life and limb when
they come forward to report an abuse committed by
SUELETTE DREYFUS
AUSTRALIAN JOURNALISTAND AUTHOR OF
UNDERGROUND—TALES OFHACKING ,
MADNESS AND OBSESSION ON THE ELECTRONIC FRONTIER (RANDOM
HOUSE, 1997)
The quiet
re v o l u t i o n
From Guatemala to Kosovo,
human rights groups
have taken a page out
of a spy thriller by learning
the art of encryption
K E E P I N G  P R I V A T E  I N  A  W I R E D  W O R L D
Encryption helped break the silence over Guatemala’s “vanished”children.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
the government.As a result,“human rights groups
are using cryptography in the field to secure data-
b a s e s, i n v e s t i g a t i o n s,field reports and witness iden-
tities—all data that might put somebody’s security
or liberty at risk,” Ball says.
In fact,encryption played a key role in breaking
the silence born from 36 years of terror and civil war
in Guatemala, which killed more than 100,000
p e o p l e, most of them Mayan Indians.Until recently,
most Guatemalans would have been shocked by the
fact that the following testimony was publicly docu-
mented:“My sister went shopping in Rabinal,but
when she got to the hamlet of Plan de Sanchez the
army was already there. There they grabbed her
and raped her in a house. There were fifteen girls
raped and then they were riddled with bullets.A f t e r-
wards, they were buried by the people in a clan-
destine cemetery.”
New flashpoints in 
the crypto-wars
This personal account, from a report by A A A S
and the International Center for Human Rights
Research (CIIDH) in Guatemala City, was one of
many given by witnesses who wanted their names
kept secret for fear of retribution.The CIIDH and
several partner organizations gathered more than
5,000 testimonies between 1994 and 1995.
CIIDH was one of the first human rights groups
in the world to secure its database by using PGP,
now the most popular cryptography software in
the field.Workers smuggled laptop computers and
solar panels into remote mountain areas where
they spent months scouring the region by foot and
mule to gather testimony from people forced to
hide from the military. They systematically burnt
every paper trace of their work and encrypted the
data before sending it back to the capital for analysis.
They later emailed PGP-encrypted copies of the
material overseas to a safe back-up site.
Guatemala remains one of the best examples of
how a human rights community embraced techno-
logy, according to Ball.They continue to use secu-
rity software to protect the identities of witnesses as
well as the integrity of the data—to ensure that
political opponents don’t sneak into databases to
corrupt the information and discredit the group’s
work.
Nevertheless, “some groups choose not to use
cryptography because hiding their work would
make the government consider them a national
security threat,” says Ball.“I don’t really think that
any of the human rights groups is a security threat.
They may embarrass certain military or police offi-
cials who have committed atrocities, but all the
groups I know are dedicated to their country’s
democratization and civil liberties.”
Throughout the 1990s, the U. S. government and
activists fought a political war over the right to use
and to share strong cryptography with the rest of the
world—a war that Ball says has now finished in the
U. S. “At the end of the day,” he says, “the U. S.
government decided the economic and civil liberty
costs of regulating crypto were greater than the
rather shrill claims made by law enforcement and
national security offic i a l s,” who maintained that
the tools would assist criminals and terrorists.
While he has not seen any crypto-wars waged in
the countries where he has worked, there are still
places that either control the use of cryptography or
are hoping to do so in the future.According to Ball,
“the war front in the fight for widespread human
rights access to crypto is currently in North Korea,
Iran, Vietnam—and the UK.” To avoid this battle,
many groups don’t admit to using encryption.Wh y
advertise the fact that a computer screen of see-
mingly random characters can be transformed into
witness reports of killing and torture? ■
+ …
The report, State Violence in Guatemala, 1960-96: A
quantitative reflection, can be found at:
http://hrdata.aaas.org/ciidh
The revolution in human rights work isn’t just
about securing data, it’s also about uncovering
and analyzing the right information. A case in
point is Haiti’s Truth Commission, which has wor-
ked with Dr. Ball since 1995. After conducting
about 5,500 interviews, the commission documen-
ted more than 18,000 reported human rights
abuses before analyzing the data to determine the
truth about what happened in Haiti under milita-
ry rule, specifically in 1993-94. 
“When we took a list of all the people who were
killed and made a graph of it, we saw that political
murders bunched up in a couple of different points
in time,” says Ball. When the team timelined the
data against other events, they discovered a surge
in human rights abuses at the same time as a U.S.
t roop carrier entered the waters around the
island—a possible first step to military interven-
tion.
“What was interesting is that a lot of apologists
for the Haitian regime had argued that this vio-
lence in the streets was just nationalist fever—
that it was really the fault of the U.S. by threate-
ning to intervene. But over time, you see the same
fights all over the country implying a kind of co-
ordination of those who were committing the ter-
ror,” says Ball. “You also wouldn’t expect deten-
tion by state authorities to increase at the same
time as extortion by paramilitary organizations.” 
The most logical conclusion, says Ball, was that
Haitian paramilitary groups created state-sanctio-
ned terror in the streets to intimidate and dissua-
de Haitian society from calling for U.S. interven-
tion and the restoration of President Aristide. ■
THE TRUTH ABOUT HAITI
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 29
“A
bout five years ago,my mother started
acting bizarre: telling secrets and lies.
She was only 59 but she began falling
down a lot and her eyebrow would
twitch uncontrollably.The day after I
found out she had Huntington’s I went to the library
because I knew nothing about the disease. I
remember standing there,my two young boys playing
at my feet, as I went through the medical jargon to
find out three things: fir s t , there is no cure—my
mother is going to die; s e c o n d , her children—my
b r o t h e r, two sisters and myself—have a 50 percent
chance of inheriting the gene causing the disease; a n d
t h i r d , our kids are at risk.”
“I knew that I had to keep this secret—from eve-
ryone but my family. I went on the Internet where
I found a kind of underground Huntington’s com-
munity—they told me about the genetic test for
the disease but warned me to be careful.After hea-
ring the stories about people losing their jobs and
medical insurance, I decided not to test.”
Julie Sando is not alone in the U. S.Many people
are protecting their genetic secrets by foregoing
intimate knowledge about themselves and their
f a m i l i e s. Indeed fear of genetic discrimination is
cited as the major reason why about one-third of
people approached by the National Human
Genome Research Institute (NHGRI) refuse to
participate in testing, according to Barbara Fuller,
senior policy advisor.After geneticists first identi-
fied the gene linked to Huntington’s in 1993,they
predicted that they would eliminate the disease in
a generation. Yet only 15 to 25 percent of eligible
people in the U. S.have undergone testing.To grasp
the emotional stakes embedded in these genetic
secrets, Julie Sando recounts her experience.
A hazy view of genetics as
a window on the soul
“I waited four and a half years to have a test.N o t
one day went by that I didn’t think I saw a symptom
of the disease—I’d see my hand twitch or just
stumble over my words.Every time, I asked ‘is that
it?’ I couldn’t stand the mental anguish of not kno-
wing if my kids had the disease. It was time to face
it… There are two ways of testing:either go through
your insurance and put it on record or stay anony-
mous and pay out of pocket (about $1,000). We
didn’t have the cash so I took the ultimate risk.”
To protect patients like Julie, about 75 percent
of the states have passed laws,mostly in the last fiv e
y e a r s, to protect the confidentiality of genetic infor-
m a t i o n .A new set of federal regulations to reinforce
medical privacy in general is supposed to apply in
2003,but the new administration may re-open the
debate.
Yet some studies suggest that fear of genetic
discrimination overshadows the actual number of
cases documented.A major survey of health insu-
rance regulators, company representatives, agents
and genetic counsellors from seven states was publi-
shed at the end of 1999 to compare the impact of
genetic privacy legislation.According to one of the
a u t h o r s, Mark Hall, a professor at Wake Fo r e s t
University School of Medicine, “we didn’t find a
single well-documented case of discrimination.”
On the contrary, he reported that a person with a
serious but asymptomatic genetic condition faces
little or no difficulty in obtaining health insurance.
The reason,Hall says, is that insurance companies
assume people will change jobs and therefore poli-
cies every two to five years. So by the time a client
actually requires treatment, it is likely that he or she
will have moved on to another insurer.
But as critics point out, though this may be
t h e case for a 35-year-old woman genetically
AMY OTCHET
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Forsaking g e n e t i c s e c re t s
For fear of losing their jobs and health insurance, many Americans are chosing
not to learn of their own “secrets” by foregoing genetic testing
K E E P I N G  P R I V A T E  I N  A  W I R E D  W O R L D
Julie Sando’s lifeline, her family.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
predisposed to breast cancer, what about a woman
at the age of 50? As genetic tests become more
accurate and accessible in the next few years, “ I
cannot think of a reason why underwriters would
not use them,” says Fuller of the NHGRI. Hence
Julie Sando’s expression,“I took the ultimate risk.
”By notifying her insurer, she may have put her chil-
dren at risk of being denied coverage in the future
(see box).
“At the first appointment,” recalls Ju l i e, “ t h e
geneticist asked all kinds of questions: ‘who will
you tell about the test and why?’ But the real kicker
was, ‘Do you have nursing home insurance?’ I was
35 and asked if that wasn’t far- f e t c h e d . The res-
ponse was a dead,‘No.’
“At the next appoint-
m e n t , they took my blood.
The two months’ wait for
the result were the hardest
in my life. On January 22,
1 9 9 9 , I got up early with
my husband and we
p r a y e d .The wait at the hos-
pital seemed like forever.
The doctor wasn’t smiling
when he led us into a room
and there were tissue
boxes everywhere. Finally
he said,‘ You don’t have the
gene and neither do your children.But that doesn’t
change anything for your siblings.’ I felt like a
zombie. It took a year to get over survivor’s guilt.
“I’m the only one in the family who has gone for
a test. I recently asked my sister what keeps her from
g o i n g. She said, ‘ I ’ve a friend who tested negati-
vely for the disease but her company found it in her
files and they let her go. I have a sick husband. H o w
would we live if I lost my job and our insurance
benefits?’”
While recognizing the threat of discrimination,
some experts like Dorothy Wertz of the Shriver
Center (a research organization) wonder whether
public fear may be tinged by confusion over gene-
tics and the notion that “we are the sum of our
genes,” which pervades popular culture. For many
people, test results are seen as windows onto our
s o u l s, says We r t z .Not only are we powerless to alter
this information, but it may be used against us.
Hence the gut instinct to preserve “genetic pri-
vacy”at all costs.
Yet this notion of “genetic privacy ” d o e s n ’t
make sense biologically. For example, many of
the state laws offer special protection for genetic
testing of a disease like Huntington’s.Yet an ordi-
nary cholesterol test can reveal a great deal about
family history like predisposition to heart disease.
“ The state laws are
good faith efforts but may
offer a false sense of secu-
rity,” says Thomas Murray,
president of the Hastings
Center for Bioethics.“It is
dishonest to assign gene-
tics special moral status,”
h e s a y s, because most
common and serious condi-
tions are a complicated mix
of genetic and non-genetic
factors.
Julie agrees that the
solution lies in protecting
medical, not just genetic, privacy. Yet this does not
rule out the need for laws to prevent genetic discri-
mination,according to patient rights advocates like
Joanne Hustead, director of the non-profit National
Partnership of Women and Fa m i l i e s.“ This is the new
frontier of civil rights—which is about protecting
people from discrimination on the basis of immutable
and very personal characteristics, like race and reli-
g i o n . There is also a bit of self-interest involved,”
she says. “Everyone has genetic mutations and the
moment that you start making decisions on the basis
of one mutation or another, there is no end to it.We
are all at risk.” ■
Unlike the universal healthcare systems of
Canada or France, most people in the
U.S. rely on their jobs for access to health
insurance. Either employers negotiate com-
petitive deals with the major insurance com-
panies or they actually pay for their wor-
kers’ medical services. Employers are
increasingly (55-65 percent) opting for the
latter option because of tax benefits.
H o w e v e r, their employees risk paying a high
price in terms of privacy. As medical re c o rd s
become incorporated into electronic data-
bases, employers may increasingly identify
“expensive” workers: those suffering from or
p redisposed to a serious condition. More o v e r,
these employers are exempt from state insu-
rance regulations protecting genetic infor-
mation. 
Individuals can also apply directly to insu-
rance companies. However, most policies
a re “rated”: diff e rent customers pay diff e re n t
costs according to their health risks and
family histories. So it may be only a matter
of time before genetic tests are used in the
screening process. ■
THE LUXURY OF INSURANCE
“I waited four years
to have a test.
Not a day went by
that I didn’t think 
I saw a 
sign of the disease.”
No one is
compelled to
show to others
more of his inner
life than he feels
is natural to
show.
Albert Schweitzer,
French missionary
and theologian
(1875-1965)
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 31
J
ames To is convinced his telephones are
t a p p e d . A policeman tipped him off but To
feels neither paranoid nor outraged, s i m p l y
r e s i g n e d .For the past ten years,he has relent-
lessly monitored the surveillance tactics of
Hong Ko n g ’s
rulers—British and Chinese—and phone-
tapping has been on top of his list.
“My interest is very simple:it’s about Big Bro-
t h e r. The government should have the minimum
amount of information about citizens,” says the
Democrat Party legislator.“I don’t want the govern-
ment to be my friend.It should leave us alone and
then we will have the potential to develop our-
selves into what we want to be.”
To ’s strong views were forged by experience. H e
was first elected at the age of 28 in 1990—a pivotal
moment in Hong Ko n g ’s history when British admi-
nistrators sought to reassure a population panicked
by the 1989 violence at Tiananmen Square and the
return to Chinese rule in 1997.The colonial powers
sought to calm public fears by introducing a Bill of
Rights to locally enshrine the International Cove-
nant on Civil and Political Rights.
After examining the much-touted law, t h e
young To found little in the way of privacy pro-
t e c t i o n , which was not surprising. “Even in the
mother country, Britain,there is no Bill of Rights
or mechanism to ensure privacy,” says To, aside
from jurisprudence. I r o n i c a l l y, it was a British lec-
t u r e r, Raymond Wa c k s, who first introduced him to
the concept as a law student at the University of
Hong Kong in the 1980s. Since then, a c a d e m i c
curiosity has become a personal commitment.
The colonial authorities paid little heed to To’s
warnings. But they could not ignore the European
U n i o n ’s threats in 1994 to prohibit its member
countries’ banks from dealing with their counter-
parts in Hong Kong without legal data protection.
A year later, the legislature passed the Personal
Data Ordinance.Once again,To uncovered a major
loophole:the law did not apply to the Telecommu-
nications Ordinance that gave the government
extensive wiretapping powers. He introduced his
own bill requiring a judge to oversee the process,b u t
the British authorities rejected it.
Today his battle against phone-tapping covers
wider ground. New laws permit the police to create
an extensive DNA database by collecting samples
from anyone suspected or convicted of a serious
crime. Immigration officials are also spearheading
efforts to install a national system of “ s m a r t ”c a r d s,
embedded with microchips, to replace the paper
identity cards. Residents must now carry these paper
documents at all times and apply for identification
numbers for the most banal tasks, like getting a
phone line installed, visiting a residential building
after hours or even booking a tennis court.
The omnipresent
“smart” card
The smart cards are supposed to offer more
efficient services, but privacy advocates fear they
could do far more. By centralizing the most personal
and minute details—from the title of a book bor-
rowed from a library to medical data—any “card-
r e a d i n g ” authority could use these profiles to exert
leverage over the individual by, for example, p a s s i n g
sensitive information to an employer.
Yet as To pushes for legal protection, his fellow
citizens seem uninterested. The entrenched habit of
carrying identification papers, he says, has made sur-
veillance seem normal in Hong Ko n g. People are
willing to tolerate intrusion so long as it doesn’t
hinder their attempts to make money, according to the
l e g i s l a t o r.And if the situation becomes diffic u l t ,t h e y
are prepared to emigrate overseas.“ P r i v a cy is viewed
as a luxury,” he says.“ I t ’s not part of Chinese culture,”
which privileges the collective over the rights of the
i n d i v i d u a l . But for To, the opposite is true: the well-
being of the group depends on the security of each
and every one of its members. ■
GLENN SCHLOSS
JOURNALIST FORTHE SOUTH CHINA MORNING POST
IN HONG KONG
A tireless t ro u b l e s h o o t e r
A renegade legislator introduces Hong Kong to the “luxury” of privacy
K E E P I N G  P R I V A T E  I N  A  W I R E D  W O R L D
James To:bugged by surveillance.
Don’t you
meddle with me,
and I won’t
meddle with you.
George Eliot,
British novelist
(1819-1880)
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
DAVID BANISAR
U.S. ATTORNEY AND DEPUTY DIRECTOR OF PRIVACY INTERNATIONAL, A UK-BASED HUMAN RIGHTS GROUP
Labour pains:
the birth of a movement
Cyber-rights and business groups are fighting a proposed cybercrime
treaty. While there is strength in numbers, the groups’ diversity may
prove too much for the coalition to bear
A
s you flip through the pages of this
March issue,members of the Council of
Europe will be poring over a blueprint
to force its countries and others around
the world to dramatically increase sur-
veillance and invade your privacy in the name of
preventing cybercrime (see box).An eclectic coalition
of civil rights and corporate groups however, h a s
launched an offensive against the proposed cy b e r-
crime treaty as well as a battery of controversial
national laws and international standards.
Not surprisingly, the first privacy campaign
emerged in the U. S. , an Internet stronghold, a g a i n s t
the infamous Clipper Chip.According to the govern-
m e n t , this cryptographic device would have offered
a standard for securing private voice communication.
Two government agencies would have held the
“keys,” to be handed out only with “legal authori-
z a t i o n .” P r i v a cy-minded citizens quickly saw the
dangers of this in light of the federal government’s
history of illegal domestic surveillance. In 1994,
50,000 people—a hefty chunk of the cybernaut popu-
lation—signed the largest Internet petition of its
time against the proposal,which died soon after.
Perhaps the most striking feature in the battle to
protect privacy has been the diversity of groups
i n v o l v e d .The year 1996 saw a motley crew of immi-
gration groups, gun-owners, liberals and conserva-
tives band together to oppose legislation that would
notably have extended wiretapping and allowed
for more investigations of political groups. I r i s h -
American and Arab-American associations joined
out of concern that they would be more aggressively
targeted in the “war on terrorism.” M e a n w h i l e, t h e
fear of a more invasive government rallied gun-
owners alongside groups from across the ideological
s p e c t r u m . Once again, by tapping the Internet’s
power to organize and disseminate information,
they shelved the legislation.
But this ad hoc co-operation is based on shaky
ground. There was considerable coordination, for
e x a m p l e, between civil liberties groups and the
industry to oppose the 1994 Communications A s s i s-
tance for Law Enforcement A c t , which requires
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 33
telecommunications carriers to modify their equip-
m e n t , facilities and services in order to comply with
authorized electronic surveillance. Yet once the
industry received a promise of government fun-
ding to implement the law, it quickly abandoned the
coalition.Corporate representatives then jumped
sides again and sued the government over imple-
mentation rules in a controversy that is still brewing.
Old enemies
become new allies
With the Internet’s growth, the privacy battle is
becoming increasingly international.Most We s t e r n
European countries have at least one cyber-rights
g r o u p,a trend that is spreading across the continent
and Asia, particularly in Japan.At the same time,
existing human rights groups have also started to
focus on the Internet. All it takes is for a single
national government to ban free speech on the We b
and the issue instantly takes on a global character.
For decades, international bodies like the Orga-
nisation for Economic Co-operation and Develop-
ment (OECD), the Council of Europe and the
European Union (EU) have been developing inter-
national standards relating to privacy, free speech
and other civil liberties issues. Their work has
included brokering common rules on data protec-
tion and encryption policy to promote e-commerce.
While some government representatives have put
a stronger emphasis on protecting human rights,
economic interests have clearly dominated the
d e b a t e, strongly influenced by the International
Chamber of Commerce, a powerful lobby of
industry groups.To d a y,by pressuring governments
bilaterally and multilaterally, the U. S. is leading the
efforts to expand surveillance worldwide.This pres-
sure amounts to what privacy advocates call “ p o l i cy
l a u n d e r i n g ” : by pushing other governments into
accepting controversial plans like the Clipper Chip,
international standards will be developed which
will in turn force the U.S. Congress to accept pro-
posals it had originally rejected.
To respond with more muscle to these trends,a
new opposition front emerged in 1996:the Global
Internet Liberty Campaign (GILC), started by the
Electronic Privacy Information Center, H u m a n
Rights Watch and the American Civil Liberties
A s s o c i a t i o n . The group now represents over 50
NGOs from some 30 countries. GILC operates by
c o n s e n s u s. Member organizations propose specific
actions such as drafting letters to world leaders,
releasing reports and holding conferences.M e m b e r
groups then agree to join in the action.
GILC and groups like the Tr a n s - A t l a n t i c
Consumer Dialogue (TACD) are making inroads
into the policy processes. Perhaps the most tan-
gible signs of their success are the frequent invita-
tions to participate in OECD meetings. But the
movement has just one foot in the door: the next
step lies in strengthening the role of NGOs out-
side the U. S.Th e problem lies in the old Achilles heel
of international movements:a lack of funding. ■
K E E P I N G  P R I V A T E  I N  A  W I R E D  W O R L D
In 1997, a Council of Europe working group formed by law
enforcement officials and interior ministers from select COE
member countries, the U.S., Canada and Japan began drafting
an international convention on cybercrime. Since then, the
treaty has gone through 25 drafts.
Unlike similar actions at the OECD, civil liberties and industry
associations were not invited to participate. The Committee
met behind closed doors for several years and did not re l e a s e
a draft until April 2000. Instead of openly discussing the pro-
posal, the COE asked people to submit comments via the
I n t e rnet. Despite the hundreds of emails sent, only minor
changes have been made to the original draft. 
The treaty is extremely law-enforcement oriented, bare l y
mentioning civil liberties, human rights or corporate inter-
ests. The basic premise is that behaviour is prohibited unless
allowed. The first section creates broad new categories for com-
puter crimes that could, for example, outlaw the develop-
ment of basic tools to test the security of computer systems. 
The treaty also expands the definition of hacking to include vio-
lations of contracts and the terms of service posting on web-
sites. One example: bypassing the main page (and the adver-
tising) of a commercial site to reach an inner page would be a
violation of law. Similarly, Internet service providers could be
held liable if their users link to child porn o g r a p h y, even if
they are not aware of it. Average citizens could even be held
guilty for putting incorrect information on web forms to pro-
tect their privacy.
Governments would also have the mandate to enact broad
new powers on wiretapping, real-time collection of traffic
data as well as the search and seizure of information. 
Most strikingly, the draft treaty fails to incorporate the COE’s
long-standing human rights protections. When asked publicly
why the proposal has nothing on procedural protections for
civil liberties, the chair said that it would be too difficult to come
up with privacy standards, perhaps inadvertently admitting
that the members of the panel knew very little about the
subject.
GILC and industry associations led by AT&T and the Interna-
tional Chamber of Commerce have recently begun working
together to oppose the convention. The companies are pri-
marily concerned about the costs of redesigning systems and
undertaking surveillance activities on behalf of govern m e n t s .
They also fear being held liable for the actions of their users
or third parties. 
Whether this NGO/corporate alliance will manage to ove-
rhaul or stop the treaty remains to be seen. Not only must they
reverse years of secretive negotiations, but the unity of the
g roups has yet to be tested. Many companies sit on the oppo-
site side of NGOs when dealing with the protection of consu-
mers’ personal data. ■
CYBERCRIME CONVENTION:
ONE FALSE MOV E , AND YOU’RE A HAC K E R !
+ …
www.gilc.org/privacy
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
DUNCAN CAMPBELL
SCOTTISH INVESTIGATIVE JOURNALIST
S h h h . . . t h e y ’ re listening
The journalist who first uncovered Echelon, a major electronic spy
network, reveals how international surveillance touches us all
C
onstellations of giant golf balls can be
spotted in the most remote locations across
the world, from China’s Pamir mountains
to the swampy north coast of Australia and
atop tiny coral atolls in the Indian Ocean.
Between 30 and 50 metres wide, these smooth, s y m-
metrical white domes also loom among rice fields in
northern Japan and the vineyards and mountains of
New Zealand’s South Island.
The clusters are the most visible signs of concealed
electronic networks that watch the world. Each dome
is filled with satellite tracking dishes that silently soak
up and examine millions of faxes, email messages,
phone calls and computer data that keep business and
political affairs aflo a t .Unknown to the communicators,
their messages are running through the domes, i n t o
computer networks and onto listeners who may be on
the other side of the planet.
As the world has globalized and international
communications have become central to human
a f f a i r s, these listening networks have grown expo-
n e n t i a l l y.They are part of systems called signals intel-
ligence or “ s i g i n t ,”operated by a handful of advanced
c o u n t r i e s.
For many years, sigint networks were secret: d i s-
cussion of their existence was strongly discouraged or
even forbidden by law in the countries concerned.
Now the European Parliament is seriously investigating
sigint organizations and their impact on human rights
and international trade. Europe is focusing on
“ E c h e l o n ,” a system that relies on listening stations in
about ten countries to intercept and process interna-
tional satellite communications. Echelon is just one
part of an immense network run by the U. S. and its
English-speaking allies—Britain, C a n a d a , Au s t r a l i a
and New Zealand—known as UKUSA after a secret
agreement that created the alliance in 1948. L i t t l e
escapes the UKUSA network, which intercepts mes-
sages from the Internet, undersea cables and radio
transmissions as well as from monitoring equipment ins-
talled in embassies.It even operates in space with a fle e t
of orbiting satellites.
The history of systems like Echelon is as old as
radio itself.The first international scandal over secret
listening occurred in the 1920s, when the U. S. S e n a t e
discovered that British agents were copying every
international telegram sent by American telegraph
c o m p a n i e s. To d a y ’s international networks were
founded in the early years of the Cold Wa r, w h e n
many western countries began jointly monitoring the
former Soviet Union.
Fear not 
the word “ b o m b ”
Who is listened to, and why? Officially govern-
ments only admit that surveillance is aimed at com-
monly agreed perils such as arms proliferation, t e r-
r o r i s m , drug trafficking and organized crime.But this
is the tip of the iceberg.The main aim is to spy on other
governments’ diplomatic messages and military plans
while collecting information about trade. In fact, i n
1 9 9 2 , the U. S. re-adjusted its national intelligence
p r i o r i t i e s, specifying that 40 percent would be eco-
nomic or “economic in nature,” according to Robert
G a t e s, director of the Central Intelligence A g e n cy at
the time. International and non-governmental orga-
nizations like Amnesty International and Greenpeace
are also targets.
While UKUSA is the world’s largest network,
Fr a n c e, Germany and the Russian Federation have
similar systems. On a smaller scale, so do countries in
Scandinavia and the Middle East, including Israel,
Saudi Arabia and the Gulf states. The budgets of all
government sigint agencies probably add up to an
annual expenditure of $20 billion,according to my cal-
culations for a European Parliament report publi-
shed last year.
Despite the extraordinary scale of Echelon and
its sister systems, the press has mistakenly reported
that the network could intercept “all email, t e l e p h o n e,
and fax communications.” Nor can it recognize theThe listening base Menwith Hill,UK.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
on Human Rights and the International Te l e c o m m u-
nications Convention, which assures the privacy of
international communications.Indeed sigint agencies
trample over a long line of treaties.
While individuals probably never know that they
have been spied upon, their organizations and coun-
tries may pay a high price for it. During trade nego-
t i a t i o n s, sigint agencies can sweep up the messages of
a producer nation to discover their bottom line.A r m e d
with such secret reports, the negotiators for the deve-
loped world can force prices down to a minimum.
Several governments have recently begun targeting
environmental organizations or those protesting unfair
world trade.
Even when there are no direct adverse conse-
q u e n c e s, the mere existence of powerful surveillance
systems can exercise a chilling effect on free speech,
inhibiting political and cultural development.
As these activities have become more contro-
v e r s i a l , the U. S. has tried to expand its circle of
c o l l a b o r a t o r s. Countries like Switzerland and
Denmark are currently building new satellite stations
to gather and trade spy data with the U. S. B u t , as the
ongoing European Parliament inquiry indicates,p u b l i c
awareness and concern are growing fast.Yet vigilance
is not enough: if countries and peoples are to have
equal rights in the global information infrastructure,
concerted action must quickly follow. ■
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 35
content of every telephone call. And it is pure fic t i o n
that by typing key words like “ b o m b ” in an email, y o u
can trigger a tape recorder in some secret base. Fo r
every million messages or phone calls intercepted, l e s s
than 10 will be used for intelligence purposes.Most per-
sonal communications are ignored except those of
“ i m p o r t a n t ”i n d i v i d u a l s, like politicians, top business
executives and their families.
The UKUSA network, h o w e v e r, does have the
power to access and process most of the world’s satel-
lite communications and relay contents to client states.
The system provides participating countries an enor-
m o u s,unfair political advantage,since most developing
nations cannot afford the expertise and equipment
necessary to protect the privacy and security of their
n e t w o r k s.
Spying on the goverment
for the people
News about these systems began to leak out in the
1970s as U. S. intelligence agencies came under scrutiny
in the “ Wa t e r g a t e ” a f f a i r, when former president
Richard Nixon used electronic bugging against his
election opponents.Since then, an increasing number
of whistleblowers have revealed the scale and effects
of sigint spying.
I first wrote about electronic spying by Britain in
the 1970s. While completing a university degree in
p h y s i c s, I ’d noted that the countryside was dotted
with mysterious radio and satellite stations.In 1976, I
uncovered the British dimension to the activities of
A m e r i c a ’s National Security A g e n cy (NSA), w h i c h
had been revealed the previous year by Congres-
sional enquiries.O f ficials were aghast that a sacred cow
of eternal and indivisible secrecy had been slaughtered.
Soon after the article’s publication, my American co-
author was deported from Britain as a “threat to
national security.”
The government then arrested me, along with
another journalist and our source. The authorities
d i d n ’t dare accuse us of espionage for a foreign
c o u n t r y. Our “ c r i m e ” was spying on the government
for the people. Had the prosecution succeeded, w e
would have faced heavy jail sentences.
Over the next 20 years, o f ficial secrecy relaxed as
U. S. Congressional investigations notably turned the
spotlight on sigint agencies. In Britain in the 1980s, a
controversial ban on trade union membership at the
Government Communications Headquarters
(GCHQ) boomeranged by shifting attention on its
spying activities.
The growth of the public information culture on
the Internet has taken these developments a step fur-
t h e r. N o w, even GCHQ and NSA have websites to
reassure UKUSA citizens that they are not targets.N o
such safeguards apply to the rest of the world: t h e s e
citizens are by default denied the right to privacy.Th e
countries intercepting their communications are free
to use the intelligence for whatever they wish.
Such conduct violates the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights,as well as the European Convention
K E E P I N G  P R I V A T E  I N  A  W I R E D  W O R L D
+ …
For the European Parliament report:
www.europarl.eu.int/stoa/publi/default.en.htm
For further information on the networks:
United States: www.nsa.gov 
United Kingdom: www.gchq.gov.uk 
Canada: www.cse.dnd.ca 
Australia: www.dsd.gov.au 
New Zealand: www.gcsb.govt.nz 
Russia: www.fsb.ru 
Germany: www.bundesnachrichtendienst.de
Little escapes the trawling net of Echelon.
Bad Aibling
GERMANY
Misawa
JAPAN
Morwenstow
ENGLAND
Sugar Grove
UNITED STATES
Sebana Seca
PUERTO RICO
Waihopai
NEW ZEALAND
Shoal Bay
AUSTRALIA
Geraldton
AUSTRALIA
Yakima
UNITED
STATES
Menwith Hill
ENGLAND
Leitrim
CANADA
Did you know…
Echelon may intercept as many as 3 billion
c o m m u n i cations per day (telephone conver-
sations, email messages, Internet dow n-
loads, satellite transmissions, etc.), including
2 million telephone calls per minute. It sifts
through approximately 90% of all tra f fic
flows via the Internet.
http://www.echelonwatch.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
JACK CHESHIRE
FREELANCETELEVISION PRODUCER AND JOURNALIST
BASED IN LONDON
Videomania in
G e o rge Orwell’s homeland
Satirist Mark Thomas uses the law to sidestep the UK’s ubiquitous
surveillance cameras
B
rits may appear to be paragons of discretion
but actually we’re a nation of voyeurs and
e x h i b i t i o n i s t s. For the past 25 years, t h e
government and citizens have been instal-
ling closed circuit television cameras
(CCTV) in the most banal places: train stations,b u s e s,
a i r p o r t s, town centres and even telephone booths.We
have hidden cameras in the changing rooms of shops
and parade before men in uniform with cameras tucked
inside their police helmets.
George Orwell’s homeland has the most sur-
veillance cameras per capita in the world: one for
every 55 people, according to a recent study by the
University of Hull. In 1995 almost 80 percent of the
Home Offic e ’s crime prevention budget went into
funding new cameras. And the private sector now
accounts for about 30 percent of the market, w o r t h
£150 million ($210 million) a year according to conser-
vative estimates, and growing 15 to 20 percent annually.
In the words of former Home Secretary Michael
H o w a r d ,“CCTV catches criminals, spots crimes, i d e n-
t i fies lawbreakers and helps convict the guilty,” y e t
there has never been an official Home Office assess-
ment of the cameras’ impact on crime rates. O n l y
weeks ago, it emerged that the Scottish Parliament has
no information on the number of convictions resulting
from evidence gathered by CCTV. And yet, Ja m e s
D i t t o n , a professor at the Scottish Centre for Crimi-
n o l o g y, reported in 1999 that the 32 cameras in
Glasgow city centre had produced just one arrest
every 40 days.
Indeed the exponential growth of CCTV has been
accompanied by rising crime rates and falling numbers
of police on the streets. Crime rates doubled between
1980 and 1990 and reached an all-time high last year
at 5.22 million, with violent crimes rising eight percent
n a t i o n a l l y. On any one night in London, a city of
seven million people, only 300 police officers are
actually on patrol, according to the Police Fe d e r a-
t i o n .
Sketches, lies
& videotape
So let’s scratch the crime prevention argument
and return to the original hypothesis:an obsession with
surveillance for social control—which seems only fit-
ting given that the British don’t have a legally ensh-
rined right to privacy. But we do have data protection
l e g i s l a t i o n , first introduced in 1984 and reinforced in
March 2000, which gives citizens the right to see and
correct personal information kept by anyone—govern-
m e n t , company or fellow citizen.
I work with Mark Th o m a s, who spends a lot of
time in front of and behind cameras for the TV pro-
g r a m m e,“ The Mark Thomas Product.”So in the spirit
of public service,we have sought to uphold the new law.
According to the guidelines, CCTV operators must
register their activities with the government, which is
good news because just about anyone can install a
Cameras in Newhill couldn’t pick out the dancing Morrismen.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 37
camera anywhere. Quite logically, we made our fir s t
stop at a security industry exhibition.Of about 200 exhi-
b i t o r s,we discovered that 127 had failed to register and
were therefore breaking the law.We invited them to the
e x h i b i t i o n ’s cyber café to register online.Most declined
and we were soon ejected from the conference but not
before the organizers had drafted a letter to all exhi-
b i t o r s, notifying them of their legal obligations.
We then stumbled upon an interesting phrase in
the act: “the same legally enforceable information-
handling standards as have previously applied to those
processing personal data on computer now cover
C C T V.”Tr a n s l a t i o n :any identifiable individual fil m e d
by a camera now has the right to obtain a copy of those
i m a g e s.This is a satirist’s dream. If we are to be fil m e d
half our lives, then we want the footage for a 40-year
long out-of-home video.Perhaps this is the real reason
for the new law: why else would it stipulate that ope-
rators put their contact information on each camera? 
This took us to our next stop, B r i t a i n ’s privatized
and chaotic railways. We figured that a lot of people
were getting into trouble for being late to work.So we
found several harassed commuters eager to act as
guinea pigs by standing under their local station’s
cameras holding a half-metre high clock. All it took
was a quick letter of request and each commuter
received a personal video, courtesy of Railtrack, t o
prove to their bosses that they weren’t the culprits—
the company was.
The real surprise came while testing the latest
CCTV hi-tech wizardry. Newham Council in London
has spent £2 million ($2.8 million) on computerized
cameras to automatically recognize certain vehicle
number plates and identify known villains with facial
mapping software. We sent six traditional English
folk dancers, donning garters and bells, to do the
“ r a t t l e b o n e ” and “ p l o u g h j a c k ” through the streets of
the housing estate.Shortly after our visit, we received
a letter explaining that the council couldn’t release our
footage since “it has not been possible for us to extra-
polate your images from those of unknown third par-
t i e s.”
Announcing the world’s first
international CCTV competition
We had a major dilemma: had taxpayers’ money
been used for faulty equipment, or was something
else going on? We happened to be outside a Fo r d
Motor Company plant when a few union people dis-
tributing leaflets about a forthcoming strike ballot
were suddenly threatened by employees. Ford com-
plied with our request for the CCTV footage of the
i n c i d e n t . But aside from a riveting view of the nearby
car park, there was no sign of life. Another round of
technical problems? 
All of which leads us to the following conclusion:
C C T V ’s potential lies in the entertainment fie l d .As a
r e s u l t ,w e ’ve launched a competition for the best foo-
tage obtained through data protection laws. N o n e
other than Jonathan Ross, the BBC’s film critic, w i l l
judge the results. And perhaps most importantly, I
hereby formally announce the creation of the new
c a t e g o r y, “Best International Picture.” Any CCTV
footage will qualify, edited or uncut, from countries
with or without appropriate legislation. Please send
your tapes marked “CCTV Competition” to Ve r a
P r o d u c t i o n s,3rd Floor,66-68 Margaret Street,L o n d o n ,
W1W 8SR, L o n d o n , United Kingdom. ■
K E E P I N G  P R I V A T E  I N  A  W I R E D  W O R L D
+ …
jack.cheshire@clara.net
In the USSR, the state has always had its nose in citizens’ pri-
vate business. Ten years after the fall of the Soviet empire,
how closely are the Russians watched?
Of course, the communist party is no longer the almighty
power it used to be. But old habits die hard. In 1998, the
g o v e rnment decided to take a close
i n t e rest in Russia’s three million Intern e t
users. By passing a resolution setting up
SORM 2, (an acronym for a system of
operative investigation measures), the
s e c ret services and the State Te l e c o m-
munications Committee extended SORM
1 to the Internet. Since 1995, that system
has allowed the Federal Security Bure a u ,
the KGB’s successor, to eavesdrop on tra-
ditional communications (telephones,
telex, fax and so on), as long as it had a
warrant.
So far, a single man has dared to challenge SORM 2. Naïl Mur-
zakhanov, 34, is the chairman of Bayard-Slaviya Communi-
cations (BSK), an Internet access provider based in Vo l g o g r a d
(1,500 kilometres south of Moscow). “When the FSB agents
came to have me sign their co-operation plan, I refused,” he
says. “My team and I went through the document with a fin e -
toothed comb and we came to the conclusion that it was
illegal.” Murzakhanov, who has a degree in robotics, explains
that “we’re not against all forms of co-operation. We’d be
willing to go along in specific cases, but not systematically.
For example, if the FSB brought us court documents pro-
ving that an individual is suspected of tax
evasion or pedophilia, we could coope-
rate. But that has never happened.”
Cut to the quick, the ministry of com-
munications threatened to take away
the rebellious provider’s license. But in
January 2000, Murzakhanov sued. The
court has met three times. Each time the
session was adjourned because the
m i n i s t r y ’s re p resentatives failed to show
up. The case dragged on. Then, in
August, Murzakhanov received a letter
f rom the minister himself, who with-
drew his threat to take away BSK’s license. “There was no
longer a need to maintain our lawsuit,” the young busi-
nessman says, frustrated at seeing the Russian government
get off the hook so easily. ■
Anne Nivat, Moscow correspondent for the French daily Libération.
B S K , THE PROVIDER T H AT SAYS N I E T
Did you know…
The CC TV market in the United Kingdom
i s currently the biggest in Europe at over
$ 616 million per year, with 200,000 ca m e ra s
in place. In 1999, 500 towns and cities had
public CCTV systems, up from 74 in 1996!
http://www.indexoncensorship.org
http://www.privacyinternational.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
S
CHRISTOPHE CHICLET
FRENCH JOURNALISTAND HISTORIAN,
AUTHOR OF THE MACEDONIAN REPUBLIC (1999), AND KOSOVO: THE TRAP (2000), BOTH PUBLISHED IN FRENCH BY L’HARMATTAN, PARIS
O t p o r : the youths
who booted Milosevic
It took a generation of 20 year-olds without a manifesto or leader to shake
Serbia out of its lethargy. Armed only with slogans and spray paint, they dealt
a fatal blow to the dictatorship
lobo, save Serbia:kill yourself,” chanted
a band of youth in the streets of Bel-
g r a d e,Yu g o s l a v i a ’s capital city. D e f e a t e d
in the presidential election on September
2 4 ,2 0 0 0 ,Slobodan Milosevic—Slobo for
short—kept clinging to power. O n
October 5,the dictator fell.
Opposition parties, i n t e r n a t i o n a l
pressure and mass demonstrations contri-
buted to Milosevic’s doomsday. So did
Otpor (“Resistance” in Serb), w h o s e
story is unique in the annals of eastern
European protest movements. Without
leaders or a clear cut political ideology,
the group played a decisive role: like a
termite colony, Otpor gnawed away at
the regime’s foundations before the top
realized that the whole edifice was roc-
king.
Founded by a handful of libertarians
in October 1998, Otpor counted
4 , 0 0 0 members by the end of 1999, a
number that has swelled to 100,000 today.
The overwhelming majority can’t even
remember when the movement was born.
Vague memories of
the war’s early days
All it takes to meet them is a visit to
49 Knez Mihajlova Street, B e l g r a d e ’s
most stylish pedestrian thoroughfare,
where anti-NATO demonstrators sacked
the French, British, German and Ame-
rican cultural centres during the March
1999 bombing campaign.Otpor squatted
an old, run-down Belgrade university
annex there. In this tiny beehive of acti-
v i t y, covered with stencils of the resis-
tance movement’s famous black fist and
jam-packed with fil e s, l e a flets and posters,
initiatives were hatched that brought a
1 3 - y e a r-old mafia-ridden political system
to its knees.
S o fia ,A n a , Milos and Mihaïlo are bet-
ween 17 and 24 years old.When a western
journalist arrives,many of their friends in
the office join in the discussion,held in a
s m a l l ,narrow room.Soon the tiny desk is
cluttered with cups of Turkish coffee.
Everyone serves each other and trades
cigarettes in a good-natured atmosphere.
The first observation is that all those pre-
sent come from the same social back-
g r o u n d . Like most Serbs, their parents
get by on $40 to $80 a month, working
occasional odd jobs.Their grandparents,
who still live in the countryside, send a
little food to help out.
It doesn’t take long for the conver-
sation to switch to recent history. In 1989,
nationalism of all stripes was tearing the
Yugoslav federation apart. In June 1991,
war broke out in Slovenia, spreading like
w i l d fire to Croatia and, in spring 1992, t o
B o s n i a . The Yugoslav army was made
up of draftees, and an entire age group
was mobilized.By the end of 1991,Bel-
g r a d e ’s youth were in the streets, and the
police brutally cracked down on the pro-
tests. Otpor’s young activists only have
vague memories of these events. Barely
10 years old at the time, they were living
in a climate of war,deprivation and impo-
verishment.
On November 17, 1 9 9 6 , S l o b o d a n
Milosevic lost the municipal elections
and annulled them.Tens of thousands of
Serbs took to the streets in Belgrade and
A student demonstrating in the streets of Belgrade in October 2000.
◗ E T H I C S
38 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
other cities. Students, who spearheaded
the protests,demanded that the results be
r e c o g n i z e d . E v e n t u a l l y, after three
m o n t h s, Milosevic made concessions and
the movement ran out of steam.
Recruiting the
disenchanted
Sofia Jarkovic, 17,is in her penulti-
mate year at a Belgrade high school.
She took part in these demonstrations
alongside her parents.Their failure made
a lasting impression on her, and on
March 20, 2000 she joined Otpor, w h o s e
sole aim was Milosevic’s overthrow.A n a
Vuksanovic, 24,who is working on her
m a s t e r ’s degree in French literature,
participated in every day of the 1996-97
protest marches .“ The problem was, w e
had set our sights too low,” she says.
“ We were demanding recognition of the
voting results, when in fact we should
have been demonstrating for new muni-
cipal, legislative and presidential elec-
tions, under the supervision of interna-
tional observers. Like many people, I
took this failure hard.Th a t ’s why I joined
Otpor as soon as it was founded two
years later.”
The movement got off to a quiet start
outside Serbia’s mainstream opposition.
Milosevic had managed to corrupt
several opposition municipalities while
students had become disgruntled with
politicking and established parties. The
leaders of the 1996-97 movement went
into exile, as many deserters and draft
dodgers had done during the 1991-1995
w a r s.S o o n , they were joined by deserters
from the Kosovo war (March-June 1999).
In less than ten years, several hundred
thousand Serbs became expatriates.A n d
most of them were the elite of pro-demo-
cratic youth.
The next generation found itself iso-
l a t e d . They had to come up with their
own methods of struggle, forge their own
experience, and above all, avoid selling
o u t . These teenagers had political
a c u m e n , but more than anything else,
i n t u i t i o n . And they wanted to stop a
regime that was stealing the fire of their
youth.
Armed with their impetuousness,
they managed to shake their parents and
grandparents out of lethargy. A d u l t s
started feeling ashamed of their apathy.
Rather than stir up revolt in army bar-
racks and corridors, they preferred to
convince the people around them.Po l i c e
manuals had no chapters on how to stifle
the awakening of civil society. Meanw-
h i l e,M i l o s e v i c, shut up in his ivory tower,
was incapable of sensing the agitation
that was about to sweep him off the stage.
One of Otpor’s greatest strengths lay
in its absence of hierarchy, a rule of
thumb for a movement grounded in
joyous anarchy. I t ’s a free-wheeling,a n y-
thing-goes protest movement.“I showed
up at their headquarters on March 20,
2 0 0 0 ,” recalls Sofia Ja r k o v i c. “I was a
little scared. I opened the door and said,
‘ H i , my name is Sofia and I want to be an
a c t i v i s t .’ They handed me a membership
form. I filled it out and left. Two weeks
l a t e r, they called me up, gave me an
appointment and I joined.” Milos Stan-
kovic, 17,is in his penultimate year at a
Belgrade high school and has belonged to
Otpor since Fe b r u a r y, 2 0 0 0 . “I joined
Otpor because it was against political
p a r t i e s,” he says.“I wanted to help change
t h i n g s, because I couldn’t stand seeing
people dealing with so many problems in
their day-to-day lives anymore.” A n a
Vuksanovic adds,“What got me excited
was that there weren’t any leaders, s o
there was no risk of being betrayed.”
Within a year, the movement took
root in four Belgrade universities,m o s t l y
with first and second-year students.The
hard core consisted of three small groups:
Democratic Students, the Students’
Union and the Students’ Fe d e r a t i o n .
Otpor forged relationships with N e z a-
v i s n o s t ( I n d e p e n d e n c e ) , S e r b i a ’s only
free trade union, as well as with the
defence workers’ union and the pensio-
ners’ organization.There were no ulterior
political motives for these choices. It was
just that the kids had parents in these
organizations.That’s vintage Otpor.
Sowing revolt 
in the family 
Milosevic took a harder line after
losing Kosovo in June 1999, but graffiti
calling for “Resistance until Vi c t o r y ”
began flourishing on walls.Slogans were
increasingly disrespectful and, t h e r e f o r e,
incomprehensible for rank-and-file mili-
tiamen and their leaders (see box). S o m e
100,000 copies of the newsletter S e r b
R e s i s t a n c e were secretly circulating.
During school vacations, university stu-
dents, joined by many high school and
even junior high school students, sowed
the seeds of revolt in their families,n e i g h-
bourhoods and villages.Otpor infil t r a t e d
the provinces. The democratic termites
were at work.
They scored a major success when
they went after the sacrosanct Yugoslav
a r m y. Activists held demonstrations in
front of military tribunals every time a
“What got me
excited was that
there weren’t any 
leaders, so there
was no risk of 
being betrayed.”
“Because I love Serbia.”
E T H I C S ◗
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
deserter went on trial.Adults, who had
lost so many children on the Croatian
and Bosnian fronts, could only be deeply
m o v e d . Otpor was changing mentalities.
The teens struck a painful nerve, w i t h o u t
ever resorting to violence. The police
were baffled by this type of protest move-
m e n t . In one year, they arrested 60
people for spraying graffiti or wearing
badges with the black fist,but balked at
beating up the kids, who were the same
age as their own children.
Sofia took part in her first street
demonstrations in April 2000:“One day,
a policeman tore off my badge. But he
d i d n ’t dare arrest me.”Ana and her boy-
f r i e n d ,B r a n k o, were expelled from their
university dorm rooms for protesting,
and her parents were summoned to the
police station.
In July 2000, Milosevic laid the
groundwork for a constitutional coup
d’état and announced a presidential elec-
tion for September 24.The divided oppo-
sition managed to cobble together an 18-
party coalition, the DOS (Democratic
Opposition of Serbia).At the first mee-
t i n g, Otpor representatives solemnly
offered their black flag with a white fist.
They were not joining, but warning:
Otpor will keep an eye on you until the
final victory.No more wheeling and dea-
ling.
The Otpor wave had risen.“I wasn’t
old enough to vote on September 24,”
says Sofia. “My parents were against
Milosevic. My mother, Mira, wanted to
vote for the DOS,but my father, D r a g a n ,
thought of abstaining. I talked him into
voting.”
The defeated dictator annulled the
election results.The wave swelled,c o v e-
ring the whole country with the same
graffiti:“He’s finished”and “Slobo, save
S e r b i a : kill yourself!” Provincial opposi-
tion municipalities, the DOS, trade unio-
nists and veterans started talking to
Otpor.
On October 5,all of them were ready.
“ That day, I dragged my father to the
parliament building at 2:30 in the after-
noon,” recalls Milos. “I joined Otpor in
front of the philosophy department at
the university,” says Sofia . “ We stayed
there until three o’clock before conver-
ging on the parliament. I was always
afraid of the crowd the whole time.”A n a
adds, “With four boys, I was part of an
Otpor group in touch with the DOS.O u r
job was to call on Belgrade’s citizens to
come out into the streets.We were among
the first wave of protesters who occu-
pied the B92 radio station, which the
government had taken over. I couldn’t
sleep several nights in a row. I was afraid
the government would launch a counter-
attack.”
Otpor could have disbanded on
October 6, b u t , mistrustful of politicians,
the movement decided to stay alert and
uncompromising until democracy is fir m l y
e s t a b l i s h e d . Mihajlo Cvekic, 1 8 , is in his
last year at Belgrade’s vocational  school,
where his major is tourism. He became a
member of Otpor on October 8 “ b e c a u s e
of their decisive role on October 5,” h e
e x p l a i n s.“Before then, I didn’t dare join
because I was afraid of retaliation, b u t
also because of my parents and grandpa-
r e n t s, who were hard-core Milosevic sup-
p o r t e r s. To d a y, they feel ashamed.” Th e
teenagers have quietly instilled demo-
cratic aspirations into the minds of family
members corrupted by nationalism.
“I’m as mobilized as ever,” a s s e r t s
Sofia.“I don’t want to join a party. The-
re’s still a need for Otpor. I don’t have a
sense that any meaningful changes have
taken place in everyday life.”Ana adds,
“I’m not afraid anymore. I’ve found an
apartment, I feel relieved and free. I’m
o p t i m i s t i c, but we have to be patient.
A n y w a y, I want to spend my life in
S e r b i a .”“So do I,” Milos chimes in.“ E v e n
though I know there won’t be a brighter
future for a long time to come.” ■
Otpor became famous because of its favourite weapon: caustic slo-
gans spray-painted on the walls of Serbia’s cities. The first, when
nobody had heard of them yet, was the clearest and simplest, a kind of
birth certificate: “Resistance until Victory.” In December 1999, Otpor
wished everybody a “happy new
year of resistance.” A few months
before the events of October 5,
“The year 2000 will be the one”
could be read on walls everyw-
here. They were right. They also
invented a new resistance mea-
surement unit called the “otpor-
meter.” After the September 24
elections, the famous “Gotov je”
( “ H e ’s cooked”) became the
slogan spray-painted most on walls, staircases and in bar re s t rooms. On
October 5, when a bulldozer broke down the door of the state radio and
television headquarters, the government’s main propaganda mouth-
piece, Otpor printed posters and calendars with the slogan, “A bulldozer-
operator is asleep in all of us.” Leery of all politicians, even if they belong
to the opposition, Otpor’s new slogan is, “We ’ re keeping an eye on you.”
■
THE WRITING ON THE WA L L
Key dates
December 1989: S l o b o d a n
Milosevic elected president of
Serbia.
Summer 1991: The Yu g o s l a v
Federation is dismantled.
November 1996-January 1997:
Unsuccessful student
demonstrations in Belgrade.
October 1998: Otpor is founded in
Belgrade.
September 24, 2 0 0 0 : M i l o s e v i c
loses the presidential election in
Yugoslavia.
October 5, 2 0 0 0 : Otpor activists
take part en masse in the
demonstrations that overthro w
the dictatorship. 
October 6: DOS candidate Vojislav
Kostunica is elected president of
the Republic of Yugoslavia. ■
“We started from nil.”
◗ E T H I C S
40 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
O
LUCÍA IGLESIAS KUNTZ
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
P i rates and the paper chase
Book piracy is a thriving trade in poor nations, sometimes raking in bigger profits
than the real thing. In Spanish-speaking countries, publishers and governments are
stepping up their campaign to stop the scourge
One of Lima’s largest bookshops is on
Amazonas Street. It sells books by
Nobel Prize winners such as Gunther
G r a s s, José Saramago and Gabriel
García Marquez, along with titles like
Guía Triste de Paris by Peruvian writer
Alfredo Bryce Echenique, Yo soy el
D i e g o, the autobiography of footballer
Diego Maradona and La fiesta del
Chivo by Mario Vargas Llosa.
This shop, h o w e v e r, gives no bills or
receipts. When there are no classes in
nearby schools, its vendors move to
some other busy part of the city—a
t r a f fic-light intersection or even a beach.
Its bookshelves are the pavement and
its shop-window the road, for all the
books on sale are pirated versions,
copied and printed secretly without the
permission of the author or publisher,
and of course without paying any royal-
ties or taxes.
Making a dent in
authors’ royalties
Usually the prices are three to five
times lower than for normal books,
although El misterio del capital, a
popular work by Peruvian economist
Hernando de Soto, which cost about $8
when it came out, was snapped up so
quickly that its “clone” now fetches a
higher price than the genuine version.
The business of plagiarizing CDs,
c a s s e t t e s, videos and computer software
is thriving everywhere, but pirated
books are found almost exclusively in
poor countries. It is a scourge that threa-
tens the whole Spanish-language publi-
shing industry.
According to estimates from the
Interamerican Publishers’ Group, a b o u t
50 billion book pages are illegally
reprinted every year in Latin A m e r i c a ,
ranging from photocopies to the repro-
duction of entire books.The annual tur-
nover of the legal publishing industry in
Latin America and Spain is about $5
billion a year, compared with the $8 bil-
lion of the pirate sector. This means a
loss of about $500 million in royalties
every year.
Carmen Barvo, a Colombian publi-
shing consultant and leading expert on
the subject, cites a particularly blatant
c a s e.“Even the book C h e ck m a t e w r i t t e n
by Rosso José Serrano, C o l o m b i a ’s
national police chief and a model offic e r
for the whole country, was pirated and
sold in the streets,proving that criminals
don’t care who the author is.”
Pirated books these days are such
good copies of the original that they
are sometimes hard to detect, even by
the authors and publishers themselves.
Not only is the text copied, but also the
d e s i g n , the cover, the colour and the
bar code. Pirated Argentine books made
in Colombia or Brazil are ironically
marked “printed in A r g e n t i n a ” w h i l e
those in Chile shamelessly carry the
warning that “reproduction is for-
bidden.” Loaded into trucks and vans,
they are exported from one country to
the next, even making it to the display
windows of genuine bookshops—per-
haps innocently, perhaps not.
New technologies 
speed up the task
Those who support book piracy, by
buying the forged copies for example,
argue that the original versions are too
e x p e n s i v e.As Barvo notes, the issue has
to be seen in a social context.“Selling a
pirated book is part of a vendor’s daily
b r e a d .Today he may be selling books at
traffic lights, but tomorrow it might be
c i g a r e t t e s, paper handkerchiefs or
Barbie dolls. I don’t regard him as the
guilty party—that honour belongs to
the person who produces the book and
violates the rights of the author and
Tight budgets:a university student checks out a street vendor’s offerings in Lima.
C U L T U R E ◗
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
publisher.”
New technologies clearly make it
much easier—and much cheaper—to
pirate books.“ Technically speaking, y o u
can do it all these days,” says the owner
of a legal Paris printing works.“ To copy
a book, all you need is two copies of
the original, a scanner, a computer with
an optical recognition programme,s o m e
ink, paper, a small rotary press and a
binding machine.” With all this and a
place to operate the printing press, a
pirated book can be produced in two or
three days.
Resorting to police
raids and law suits
Attempts to fight book piracy
through technology appear to have
f a i l e d .All that is left are the weapons of
police raids and the law, both of which
are exploited to the full by bodies such
as the Regional Centre for Book Pro-
motion in Latin America and the Carib-
bean  in Bogota and the Spanish Centre
for Reproduction Rights in Madrid.
The strategy depends largely on
legal action, says Manuel José Sar-
m i e n t o,sub-director for anti-piracy and
illegal reproduction at the Colombian
Chamber of Books. “Since 1997, t h e
C h a m b e r, the publishers and the
ministry of culture have stepped up
their efforts, ranging from police raids
to publicity campaigns in the press and
on television.” By January 2001, a total
of 139 lawsuits had been successful in
Colombia’s courts, leading to the clo-
sure of places where pirated books
were being produced, distributed or
sold.
In Peru,on the other hand,pirated
books continue to flourish,and publi-
shers are denouncing the government’s
failure to act. Germán Coronado, h e a d
of the Peisa publishing house, says the
country has “quite progressive legisla-
tion protecting intellectual property in
accordance with international stan-
dards. Our 1996 intellectual property
law punishes illegal copying with up to
eight years’ imprisonment and clearly
supports authors by giving their heirs
the right to receive royalties for up to
70years after an author’s death.
“All this sounds wonderful and Per-
uvian technocrats turn up at interna-
tional meetings to boast about it. But
the law isn’t worth the paper it’s written
on. The pirates have a bigger turnover
now than the legal sector,and we reckon
they sell nearly three times more books
than we do.”
Calls for lower sales tax
and quality paperbacks
In A r g e n t i n a , which has a strong
publishing industry and the best book-
shops in the region, “it’s mainly tech-
nical and self-help books that are
pirated,” says Ana Cabanellas, head of
the Heliasta publishing house, some of
whose books have been copied. “ I t ’s
very painful, like being raped. Th e
pirates are very clever and however
much we try, they always manage to
make copies.Each year I publish a B a s i c
Legal Dictionary written by my father,
Guillermo Cabanellas, and we change
the colour of the cover each time. E v e n
that doesn’t stop them.”
As well as cracking down, p u b l i-
shers could make an effort to put out
high-quality works in pocket editions,
an area in which Spanish-language
publishers lag far behind.
Governments could also help to
boost the legal book sector by lowe-
ring the sales tax,which is one of the
highest in the world (18 percent in
C h i l e ) , or by building networks of
public libraries where all Latin Ame-
ricans can have free access to their
favourite authors.
The task is huge, but so is the deter-
mination of some. “ We ’re going to
stamp out book pirating,” says Sar-
m i e n t o. “ I t ’s almost a personal thing
for me. We’ll get there.” ■
A crime in many shapes and sizes
Asia is another continent afflicted by book piracy. In India, where the
country’s 11,000 publishers put out more than 57,000 new titles a year,
an education ministry survey pinpoints three kinds of forgery. The most
common is copying a book and selling bogus versions—the Indian writer
Arundhati Roy and her book The God of Small Things is one of the most recent
victims. Another more laborious method is to print books ostensibly by
famous authors but in fact written by clumsy imitators. A craftier way is to
sell foreign books that have been translated illegally, without any formal
contract. The famous young sorcerer’s apprentice, Harry Potter, had just
such an unfortunate experience in China. A few days before the legally-
translated version of one tome came out, a version translated in Taiwan
was selling on the streets. The state company publishing the book then
printed the genuine version with green pages to distinguish it from the
bogus one. ■
In Bombay, a young boy sells pirated versions of a science bestseller.
◗ C U L T U R E
42 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
T
FRANCISCA PETROVICH
CHILEAN JOURNALIST
C h i l e : a judge steps in
Are illegally copied books like forged banknotes and should they be destroyed?
Judges, authors and publishers in Chile are all taking a stand in a heated debate
he basketball court in a Santiago police
station was piled high a few months ago
with over 150,000 books, galley-proofs
and printing materials—all of them
illegal.Seized in a series of police raids
in three Chilean cities ordered by Carlos
Escobar, a deputy judge of the Second
Criminal Court, the collection marked
the biggest defeat yet for the country’s
pirate book industry.
But these impounded books only
created a new problem: what should be
done with them? Judge Escobar took
the initiative, ordering that they be dis-
tributed to the city’s poorest neighbou-
rhoods and other parts of the country.
“I did so because a judge is free to
decide what happens to seized items,
and if they’d stayed under court control,
their condition could have deteriorated,”
he explained.“Our country is poor and
there’s an urgent need for our children
to read. Th a t ’s why I think burning
books is an outrage.”
Just a bargain or the only
road to reading?
The judge’s decision sparked very
different reactions. Most people thought
it was a good idea. Some authors, such as
journalist Patricia Ve r d u g o — w h o s e
many books investigating the Pinochet
dictatorship have been widely pirated—
thought the judge was wrong. “ Wh a t
right does he have to give away things
that don’t belong to him?”she asked in
an interview with the daily newspaper
La Te r c e r a.“ These books should be des-
t r o y e d , just like confiscated drugs are
destroyed.”
Her colleague Hernán Rivera Lete-
l i e r, a popular Chilean author translated
into several languages, does not agree.
Pirated books, he argues, are a way to
reach more readers.“I’m not siding with
the pirates but with the readers,”he says.
“The people who buy one of my books
in the street aren’t the same as those
w h o ’d buy it in a bookshop.Th e y ’re less
well-off and can’t afford the official
prices.” Not true, replies Bartolo Ortiz,
general manager of the Planeta en Chile
publishing house. “ I ’ve seen very ele-
gant-looking people buying books on
the street. I think reading is just less
important for them compared to other
things.”
Whichever stance is adopted, o n e
fact is certain: the publishers are going to
appeal Escobar’s decision.
During the year 2000, a total of
308,000 pirated copies of 400 books put
out by various publishers were seized in
Chile. “We reckon we lost $25 million
last year,” says Eduardo Castillo, presi-
dent of the Chilean Book Association.
“ This country is top of the league in
terms of pirated books.”
The publication of pirated books in
Chile grew out of the need for under-
cover political activity. During the 1973-
89 military dictatorship, for example,
the Chilean Communist Party publi-
shed Che Guevara’s diaries and other
banned material. Various people
recently interviewed in the book
industry insist that certain unnamed
employees of lawful publishing fir m s
themselves deal out original copies of
books to the forgers, obviously in return
for money.
Bringing the government
to heel
Castillo disagrees, noting that publi-
shers have joined together to investi-
g a t e, file lawsuits and gather evidence in
an effort to punish the guilty. P e d r o
B o s c h , a lawyer who works for Editorial
S u d a m e r i c a n a , says that in two years of
i n v e s t i g a t i o n s, the firm has filed 60 com-
plaints resulting in charges against
200 people, 50 trials and the seizure of
over 30,000 books. “In this way we’ve
been able to find out who the pirates
a r e, build a database and curb the
damage being done,” he says. “But the
market isn’t going to go away.”
Au t h o r s, p u b l i s h e r s, booksellers and
judges at least agree that the govern-
ment has so far paid little interest in
taking a firm stand against book piracy.
They nevertheless hope an imminent
report commissioned by Chilean Presi-
dent Ricardo Lagos from the Book
Association may change all that.
M e a n w h i l e,on a corner of Santiago’s
busy Avenida Providencia, a street
vendor asks his assistant to fetch some
more Harry Potter books.She goes off to
get them from her makeshift storeroom,
hidden behind an ice-cream cart.I was
interested in one book and asked the
price. It was $6, less than a third of the
price in a bookshop. She said she sold
between $35 and $55 worth of books
each day.
The average monthly salary of most
Chileans is about $625. I told the vendor
it was a pirated version of the book. S h e
nodded and asked me:“Are you going to
buy it?” ■
P I R AT E S AND THE PAPER CHASE
The book was a third
of the store price.
I told the vendor it 
was a pirated version
of Harry Potter.
She nodded and 
asked me,
“Are you going 
to buy it?”
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
T
◗ M E D I A
SHIRAZ SIDHVA
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Testifying from the fro n t
Modern wars are fought with huge propaganda machines or through the rule of
terror. How can a journalist in the midst of conflict decipher the truth?
he first casualty when war comes, is truth,”
observed U. S. Senator Hiram Johnson in
the midst of World War I. Nearly a cen-
tury and many conflicts later, technolo-
gical advances have brought wars into
living rooms across the world.But truth
still remains the first casualty, b u r i e d
under layers of propaganda, vested inter-
ests and fear.
Reporting from the battlefront has
never been technically easier, with satel-
lite phones and live news relayed in real-
time. But this has only accentuated the
dilemmas that journalists encounter when
covering confli c t s : authoritarian regimes
and even democracies go to even greater
lengths to conceal the truth.
The last century has seen large-scale
battles between countries give way to
deadly internecine confli c t s, often bet-
ween governments and their own people.
From Africa to East Ti m o r, from Kashmir
and Sri Lanka to the killing fields of
Chechnya, Bosnia,Colombia and Sierra
L e o n e,old ethnic hatred is rekindled,a n d
wars are fought not on battlefronts but in
the midst of civilian populations. Accor-
ding to Robert Manoff, director of New
York University’s Center for Wa r, P e a c e,
and the News Media,mass violence is so
“universalized” that there are currently
over 200 communal groups fighting poli-
tical and military wars in 93 countries.
The media’s role remains essentially
to act as a messenger.Yet journalists also
have the power to change the course of
c o n flicts by influencing public opinion.
“ The outcomes of these small, p o s t -
modern wars may depend as much on
how they are perceived as on how they
are fought,” writes Tom Gjelten of U.S.
National Public Radio. Gjelten,who has
covered major conflicts worldwide,
believes journalists must recognize that
their task is not to please diplomats or
facilitate peace processes,but to describe
a conflict as truthfully as possible.
Local journalists
are prime targets
Do the exigencies of war justify a dif-
ferent set of ethics from those of peace-
time? The principles are essentially the
s a m e, but for one major difference: j o u r-
nalists are more vulnerable in war. I n
Sierra Leone, East Timor and Chechnya,
the bulletproof jackets that Western jour-
nalists donned provided little protection
from the wrath of a killer squad or a vin-
dictive soldier’s bullet. For local journa-
l i s t s, the terrors are even starker. Y v e s
S o r o k o b i , who coordinates the A f r i c a
programme for the Committee to Pro-
tect Journalists, recounts that ten repor-
ters were executed by rebels in Sierra
Leone over 21 days in 1999 (see box).
Reporting is also hampered by
44 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
Rwanda 1994:Magnum photographer James Nachtwey carries an orphaned baby to shelter while cameras zoom in on a suspected
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 45
government restrictions on access to
trouble spots.Since 1995,hardly any jour-
nalists in Sri Lanka have had access to the
area where the government is fighting a
deadly battle with the separatist guer-
rilla group, the Liberation of Tamil Ti g e r s ’
Eelam.“We don’t get anywhere close to
the confli c t ,” says Nirupama Subrama-
n i a n , special correspondent of The Hindu
in Colombo. I n s t e a d , both sides transmit
their version of the news via contradictory
press releases.“It is a fax war we are cove-
r i n g,” Subramanian says.“ Th e r e ’s no way
of knowing the truth.”
The proliferation of real-time news
has made political control even tighter.
Journalists often find they have little trai-
ning for the choices they are forced to
make in tense situations.When two coun-
tries are at war,whose “ t r u t h ” should the
correspondent convey—that of the
country to which the journalist belongs or
that of the enemy,whose version might be
more compelling? For the writer and war
correspondent John Pilger, it is exactly
this “virulence of an unrecognized cen-
s o r s h i p,often concealed behind false prin-
ciples of objectivity”that serves to “ m i n i-
mize and deny the culpability of We s t e r n
power in acts of great violence and ter-
rorism,such as the Gulf and Kosovo.”
Powerless observers
of unfolding dramas?
War reporting has nevertheless come
a long way since the two world wars,w h e n
most journalism was an uncritical arm of
the war effort.Twenty years later, g o v e r n-
ments learnt from Vietnam that unres-
tricted access to war zones, particularly
with the advent of television,was poten-
tial political suicide. In his classic book
The First Casualty, Phillip Knightley
concludes that the freedom journalists
had to operate in Vietnam “to go anyw-
here, see anything, and write what they
liked is not going to be given again.”
“In a democracy,you cannot get away
with the crude authoritarianism of clo-
sing down newspapers or taking over
b r o a d c a s t e r s,” w r i t e s
Steven Barnett, senior lec-
turer in communications
at the University of We s t-
m i n s t e r,reviewing Knight-
l e y ’s book. “ You can,
h o w e v e r, have a subtle
mixture of information
c o n t r o l , drip-feed propa-
ganda stories about the
e n e m y, cosy briefings for
‘friendly’ journalists and
more blatant attempts at
intimidation for the less
o b l i g i n g.”
The British devised an
excellent strategy to
manage the media during
the Falklands war in
1982—they denied access,
except to “ f r i e n d l y ” j o u r-
nalists willing to report
defence briefin g s.
The Gulf War was the
first in history where the
public expected regular
reporting from an
“ e n e m y ” capital under
s i e g e.Fought mostly from
the air, with attacks deep within enemy
t e r r i t o r y, it was impossible for interna-
tional journalists to verify military infor-
mation or report on Iraqi casualties. I t
was only later that the deceptions were
e x p o s e d , whether it was Iraqis fli n g i n g
premature Kuwaiti babies out of incuba-
tors (which turned out to be the work of
an American public relations agency com-
missioned by the Kuwaiti government), o r
the filmed preparations for an allied lan-
ding on the Kuwaiti coast, which was
never part of the military plan.
During the NATO bombing of Serbia
in 1999, the press was actively used to
drum up public support. The pitfalls of
instant news became all too obvious during
the confli c t .With 2,700 media personnel in
the region when NATO entered Kosovo
(compared with 500 in Vietnam at the
w a r ’s peak), the war could have produced
unprecedented free and fair reporting.
But instead, the story behind the sound
bytes was missing.“ The public drowned in
wave after wave of images that added up
to nothing,” writes Knightley.
Above all the clamour, h o w e v e r,
several war correspondents have worked
at great risk. John Burns of the New Yo r k
Ti m e s, a Pulitzer Prize winner, spent more
than a year in besieged Sarajevo, sharing
many nights of terror with the local people
to tell the world what was really going
on. For such journalists, objectivity may
have little to do with neutrality,e s p e c i a l l y
when the choice is between hapless vic-
tims and perpetrators of genocidal crimes.
For many reporters, the greatest
dilemma comes down to how involved
they should get. O f t e n , journalists are
overwhelmed by fear and helplessness,
but are still called upon to provide the
only link between a war-afflicted people
and the outside world.“I couldn’t stop the
smallest part of it,” recalled Lindsey
Hilsum of the British news service ITN
about reporting the massacres of Tutsis in
Rwanda in 1994.“I could only watch and
s u r v i v e.” Yet Hilsum decided to testify
before the International Criminal Tr i-
bunal for Rwanda. “It was not my res-
p o n s i b i l i t y,and testifying could even have
compromised my role as a journalist,”
ted Hutu death squad member.
“You can have a subtle
mix of information
control, drip-feed
propaganda stories,
cosy briefings and
more blatant attempts
at intimidation.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
◗ M E D I A
46 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
she explained.“But I also have responsi-
bilities as a human being.”
Courses at journalism school and pro-
fessional guidelines drawn up by media
organizations like the Freedom Fo r u m
are widening the debate on professiona-
lism in war reporting, though most agree
that the basic qualities needed are inte-
grity and a good dose of common sense.
Anthony Borden, executive director of
the Institute of War and Peace Reporting
in London, stresses the importance of
engaging and valuing the work of local
j o u r n a l i s t s, especially at a time when com-
mercial pressures threaten the continued
coverage of conflicts in regions not per-
ceived to have strategic importance.
Given all the dangers, why do journa-
lists choose to cover certain conflicts? It is
unlikely they do it for fame or fortune, or
as some people believe, for the thrill of it.
Most reporters believe their writing will
make a difference. The legendary corres-
pondent Martha Gellhorn, who covered
wars for nearly half a century, explained it
b e s t : “… in all my reporting life, I have
thrown small pebbles into a very large
p o n d , and I have no way of knowing if any
pebble caused the slightest ripple. I don’t
need to worry about that.” ■
Seeing is not always believing
In 1995, when the historic town of Charar-e-Sharif in the Kashmir valley
was burnt to a cinder, army officials escorted busloads of visiting foreign
and Indian journalists to see the devastation. To prove it was the work of
mercenaries from Pakistan, reporters were guided to a courtyard to photo-
graph five corpses they claimed were “foreign” mercenaries killed in a gun-
battle with the army.
Journalists who returned to the site after the “guided tour” discovered that
the bodies were not “foreign” at all. Five men from a nearby village had
been arrested that morning and killed to serve the government’s propa-
ganda machine. Almost every Indian newspaper carried the photograph of
the “dreaded Afghan mercenaries.” Only one foreign news magazine publi-
shed photographs of the anguished villagers grieving their dead that day.
■
+ …
www.ccpdc.org / www.cpj.org
www.iwpr.net / www.rsf.fr
www.freedomforum.org
Phillip Knightley, The First Casualty,
Prion Books, London, rev.ed. 2000.
Since it began in 1991, Sierra Leone’s conflict between
rebels and the government has claimed close to 30,000
lives while mutilating 120,000. Outside the warring fac-
tions, no group has been more targeted than journalists.
Reporting involves a constant face-to-face meeting with
death, kidnappings, torture and even long detention
without trial.
Every Sierra Leonean journalist has a horror tale to tell of
his or her experience in the field. I received my war bap-
tism in 1995 while heading for the southern town of Bo to
investigate alleged collaboration between government
forces and Revolutionary United Front rebels. Barely an
hour into the journey the convoy of more than 100 vehicles
ran into an ambush. That was the closest call to death I
have ever had. More than 75 vehicles lay in ruins and 36
people were killed. Those of us who survived were forc e d
to tote the rebels’ loot back to their base.
Many have not gotten off so lightly. Mustapha Sesay, who
used to work for the Standard Times, had his left eye perma-
nently damaged by a machete while trying to flee the
rebel invasion of the capital, Freetown, in 1999. The inva-
ding troops killed Sesay’s deputy editor, Paul Mansaray, and
his entire family in front of their home. Rebels went on to
set the paper’s offices ablaze and destroy five other news-
paper offices. Both parties to the conflict, meanwhile,
conducted house-to-house searches for blacklisted jour-
nalists, raising the question of whether it is necessary to
prostrate one’s life at the abattoir table for an objective
report in a war like ours.
Objective reporting was constantly on the mind of Corinne
Dufka, a researcher with Human Rights Watch, during a
visit to Freetown last year. “Don’t the authorities know
that you journalists are re q u i red to have every side of the
story including that of the rebels?” Ms. Dufka asked while
discussing the fate of a local journalist, Abdoul Kouyateh,
who was detained for six months for having links with the
rebels.
T h e re is no official rebel-run newspaper in the country, and
a balanced or critical article written about either of the two
stakeholders (government and rebels) in the peace pro c e s s
is invariably interpreted as partisan reporting. Write an opi-
nion piece or editorial lampooning the government for not
honouring its side of the 1999 Lome peace deal and people
will brand you a rebel. Give me a local newspaper, and I
will tell you which government minister or official fin a n c e d
its publication.
In times of “peace,” what you write and say in your re p o r t
will be the bullet that kills you when the war intensifies.
Most local journalists, especially those in the print media,
have unfortunately contributed to this deplorable state of
affairs.
In October last year, the pro - g o v e rnment Kamajor militia
abducted and tortured me for three days. The whole epi-
sode was the machination of the country’s defence chief
and militia head, Sam Hinga Norman, who four days
before my abduction had tried to bribe us into dropping
a story of a clash between his militia and the army. A col-
league of mine, who doubled as a militia informer, had
leaked the story to his patrons.
We are now fearing a possible attack from the Kamajors,
whose head we recently lambasted for alleged corruption.
I have yet to see a local court which could pass a guilty ver-
dict on the militia or security apparatus.
The few journalists who dare to file stories from this death ro w
should be encouraged and highly appreciated. But they need
to understand that no matter how important a story is, it is use-
less to risk their lives for it: war reporting is for the living, not
for the dead. ■
* Editor of The Standard Times, Freetown
JIA KANGBA I * : REPORTING FROM DEATH ROW
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
a b u l , the A f g h a n
c a p i t a l , is  now a
desolate and terro-
rized city. But you
knew it in better
times.
I was lucky
enough to live there
when my country was starting to
taste democracy, modernize, intro-
duce reforms across the board and
fight the feudal system that still pre-
vailed in some regions. In 1954,d r e s s
Spôjmaï Zariâb:
a pen against a nightmare
The Afghan writer Spôjmaï Zariâb is haunted by bitter memories and deeply
apprehensive about her people’s future. Exiled in France, she tirelessly
denounces the wars that have laid waste to her country, without ever losing
hope. Each of her short stories rings like a verdict against the regime of terror
imposed upon her compatriots, and against the humiliations inflicted upon
Afghan women
rules were abolished. It was rare to see
women wearing ch a d o r s (veils) in
t o w n s. Women quickly asserted them-
selves in all areas of life, becoming doc-
tors, members of parliament, soldiers,
parachutists and bus-drivers.They may
not have represented a big percentage,
but they were active in such a wide
range of activities.
The university was mixed and the
first primary schools teaching both
girls and boys sprang up. In Kabul, y o u
could find books of all kinds from
around the world, translated into Per-
sian. We lived free and fulfilling lives.
We could hold public meetings, speak
openly and set up political parties.
Afghanistan achieved a kind of poli-
tical and social stability after a long
and turbulent history.
But this short period of great hopes
came to a sudden end in 1973 with the
coup d’état of Mohammed Daoud,
which paved the way for communist
rule and later the arrival of the Red
Army.
A shrouded Afghan woman and her daughter make their way through a war-torn district of Kabul.
March 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
K
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
“I had to accept that I m i g h t
never see my country again”
A LITERARY JOURNEY
Born in Kabul in 1949, Spôjmaï Zariâb began publishing short stories
when she was 17. “My father gave me a love of literature,” she says. “He
was a exceptional man. He never made me feel I was just a girl and never
forbade me or forced me to do anything. There was no television when I
was a child, and in the evening he read us poems, which I came to know by
heart.  My father would recite the first part of a poem and I’d continue to
the end. I must have been about three or four years old. After that, Persian
classical poetry greatly helped me on my literary journey.  But the short
story, my favourite literary form, is a Western invention  I owe my love for
it to foreign writers, especially Europeans and Americans.”
After attending the Faculty of Literature and the Fine Arts School in
Kabul, Zariâb spent a year studying literature in France. When she retur-
ned home in 1973, a military coup by Mohammed Daoud, the king’s cou-
sin, ended the constitutional monarchy and a series of conflicts began.
Five years later, Daoud was murdered in another coup d’état, and in
September 1979, President Noor Mohammed Taraki was killed by his
deputy, Hafizullah Amin. Two months later, Amin was assassinated by
Soviet forces. They installed Babrak Karmal in power and invaded the
country in December 1979.
During the 10 years of Soviet rule, Zariâb continued to work as a trans-
lator at the French embassy in Kabul. She published her work in Iran and,
despite censorship, through Afghanistan’s only publisher and printer, the
Writers’ Union.
In 1991, when the situation was fast deteriorating, Zariâb moved to
Montpellier with her two daughters. When the Taliban seized Kabul in
1994, her husband Rahnaward Zariâb, himself an eminent Afghan writer,
joined his family in France.
Spôjmaï Zariâb’s short stories—written in Dari, a variation of Persian
which, with Pashtun, is the official language of Afghanistan—are crafted
in a harmonious blend of simplicity, sparseness and poetry. Humanism
and universalism are the two features of her work, which continues to
draw inspiration from her native land.
Her collection of short stories, “The Plain of Cain,” won her many readers,
as well as “Portrait of a City on a Purple Background,” a theatre adapta-
tion of her work presented at the Avignon Off festival in 1991.  In the
postscript of her book, “These Walls That Listen to Us,” Michael Barry, a French
expert on Persian literature, writes that “Spôjmaï, whose name means
‘full moon,’ is one of the three greatest Afghan writers of our time, along
with the two poets, Khalîlî, who died in exile, and Madjroûh, who was
assassinated.” ■
Your short story, “Boots of Delirium,”
describes the Soviet invasion.
The narrator is a dying woman who
witnesses Soviet tanks arriving in her
v i l l a g e. She has one obsession: to keep
the gate to her house firmly shut.But
the soldiers break it and come in. Th e
image represents the outright viola-
tion of a country.
The young woman,suffering from
head injuries, becomes delirious. She
wanders through the country in her
i m a g i n a t i o n . Instead of bunches of
grapes hanging from vines, she sees
a r m s, legs and heads. The cows no
longer give milk but blood. In the
town,she approaches a group of chil-
dren but sees they’re wearing huge
muddy boots like the soldiers. Th e i r
eyes have turned to stone pebbles,
expressionless and inhuman. Th e y
stand for the lost youth of my country,
young people turned into instruments
of war.
In another short story,“Identity Card,”
you describe a teenager whose mother
hides him for fear he’ll be drafted into
the army.
This story symbolizes the future of
the country, which was subjected to a
totally fabricated war. The two great
powers of the time [the Soviet Union
and the United States] made the
country a battleground for their Cold
Wa r. The Afghans were just cannon
fodder. Their trust was betrayed and
their rage against the invader cy n i c a l l y
m a n i p u l a t e d . They became tools of
ideologies that didn’t serve their coun-
t r y ’s interests.This fratricidal war conti-
nues today and has taken on wider
dimensions of ethnicity and language.
Did the Afghans have a choice other
than siding with one of these camps?
Unfortunately those extremes
were the only choice. But most
p e o p l e, the “silent majority,” d i d n ’t
join either camp.This was my family’s
case. For this majority, killing people
on either side was equally horren-
d o u s, because it was always an A f g h a n
who died. A nation is like a wall—
each brick that falls off makes it
weaker.
As a writer,what was your experience of
Soviet rule?
The new regime banned the import
and translation of all foreign books,
even censoring Persian classics. Only
Soviet books, translated into Persian by
48 The UNESCO Courier - March 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Ta j i k s, were to be found in the foreign
literature shelves of bookshops. They
seemed to have been written  by
m a c h i n e s, not people.That being said,
there were also some very good books,
such as those by Chingiz Aytmatov. I
could never have imagined that deep in
K i r g h i z s t a n , under such a regime, a
writer of this stature could exist. His
short-story “The White Ship”
enchanted me. It said everything, i n d i-
r e c t l y.Aytmatov became a ray of hope
for me.
When writers find themselves in
this situation, they have to find lite-
rary techniques to convey their mes-
sage. Fortunately, the censors did not
quite measure up to their job. Th e y
d i d n ’t know much about literature and
a lot of poets and novelists were publi-
shed by the Afghan Writers’ Union,
which was very active and had a
sizeable budget.
When the Soviet troops left, what did
you think would happen to the country?
There are some historical moments
when you simply can’t predict any-
t h i n g. After all that had happened
since 1973, we were still in for some
s u r p r i s e s. Anything was possible.
Nothing could be forecast.We missed
opportunities to take quick and wise
decisions to head off disaster. N o w
w e ’ve ended up  with the Ta l i b a n ,w h o
know nothing about A f g h a n i s t a n .
They’re religious apprentices who’ve
I wanted to protect them for a while
and I went to live in Montpellier. But
I didn’t intend to stay. I couldn’t face
applying for the status of political
refugee and giving up my Afghan pas-
sport. Many times I went to the post
o f fice to send the application, but I
could never bring myself to post it.
But when my husband arrived in 1994,
I realised all the bridges had been
burned. I had to accept that I might
never again see my country, my home-
town and my house.
Do you have any contact with Afgha-
nistan these days?
been trained in Koranic schools in
Pakistan from the youngest age.They
arrived with a rage to destroy, to des-
troy everything.
I heard they burned all the
vineyards and pulled up the pistachio-
nut trees. Pistachios were one of
A f g h a n i s t a n ’s main exports. All the
Ta l i b a n ’s actions are guided by one
idea:to make the country completely
dependent – no more agriculture, no
more irrigation systems, no more eco-
n o m y, just a completly devastated
country. With the Russians, it was the
t a n k s. With the Ta l i b a n , i t ’s fir e. We
had political fanaticism
and now we’ve got reli-
gious fanaticism. A n d
fanaticism of any nature
leads to  a kind of blind-
ness.
You emigrated to France
in 1991 a few years
b e f o re the Taliban took
o v e r, having stayed right
t h rough Soviet rule.
Why?
I didn’t want to leave
but Kabul had become
too dangerous. Th e
schools had closed
because of repeated
bombings of the city.At
the time, my two daugh-
ters were seven and
e l e v e n . I have three now. A lost generation.
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396 French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498 FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 48French francs ( 7. 32 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u ro c a rd M a s t e rc a rd
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:     Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
“ D i s p e rsing a country i s
the best way to wipe it out”
We had friends there, but they’ve
all left. So has my entire family. We
stayed for as long as we could in the
c o u n t r y. We always said that every-
thing could change but they couldn’t
take away the country.
A re there ties between Afghan com-
munities around the world?
There are some associations,
newspapers and magazines. But such
links are very hard to maintain. For
o n e, immigrants don’t have the
money to keep in touch all the time.
A l s o,Afghans don’t have a long expe-
rience of exile.There was no Afghan
emigration before the Russians came.
We’re a people very attached to the
l a n d , to our families. Now we’re scat-
tered all over the world—Europe, t h e
United States, C a n a d a ,Australia and
A s i a .Most of the refugees don’t know
the language of their host countries. I t
takes them five or six years to adapt.
I t ’s very tough being forced to look
for refuge somewhere else in the
world.The war’s been going on for 20
years now. It’s a lost generation. Six
million Afghan refugees — it’s a terri-
fying fig u r e. Dispersing a nation is the
best way to wipe it out.
How do you see the future of Afgha-
nistan?
As I say,after 1973 all bets were off.
This hasn’t changed. No prospect
seems more likely than another. But
there’s still hope.
One solution might come from
King Zahir Shah. H e ’s the only person
who all the tribes, all A f g h a n s, s t i l l
listen to. But we have to move quickly.
Time is running out. My country is
losing another generation because chil-
dren aren’t getting access to educa-
tion.And education is a basic right of
all the world’s children. Why should
it be an impossible dream for Afghan
girls?  They’re only allowed to go to
Koranic schools, until they’re about 10
or 12. And what do they learn? To
recite verses in A r a b i c,a language they
d o n ’t even understand. It isn’t any
better for boys. The lack of teachers,
administrators and equipment has
reduced schools to nurseries, without
the facilities.
But people are organizing to pro v i d e
minimal education services.
There are underground schools in
K a b u l . Mothers teach girls in their
homes. It’s a kind of resistance. You
have to be very brave to do that
because it’s illegal and the regime
cracks down hard on illegal activity.
For example, a woman just has to be
accused of adultery, by anyone, w i t h o u t
any proof, and she is stoned.
How do the men—their husbands and
their sons—react to this kind of punish-
ment?
The Taliban control nearly 90 per-
cent of the country. Read the latest
reports of Amnesty International and
the UN Human Rights Commissioner.
They describe these atrocities. Not only
have ethnic minorities been uprooted
and persecuted, the entire population
lives under the constant threat of sanc-
tions and all kinds of punishment and
humiliation.Most people who  stayed
in Kabul are those who could not
afford to escape. So they obey the
“ l a w s ” to survive, laws that are uni-
maginably absurd.
One example: I heard of one
Afghan living in Pakistan who died.
He wanted to be buried in Kabul, so
his family decided to take him there in
his coffin. When they reached Afgha-
nistan,the procession was stopped by
the Ta l i b a n .They wanted to check the
contents of the coffin , since smuggling
is common. They saw the corpse, but
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George’s Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
Gordon & Gotch Australia Pty. Ltd., Private Bag 290, Burwood VIC 3125 .
Fax: 03 9888 8561
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Partner Press, 11 rue Charles Parenté, B-1070 Brussels.
Fax: (32 2) 556 41 46/Tel.: (32 2) 556 41 40/partner press@ampnet.be
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: UNES CO O f fice, 8 Po o rvi Marg, Vasant Vihar, New Delhi 110 0 57
Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg, Ballard
Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Editions Le Printemps Ltée., 4 Route du Club, Va c o a s .
Fax: 686 7302. 
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
UNES CO Etxea, Alda Urquijo 60, Ppal. Dcha., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: Distriplumes, Apartado 49232, Colinas Bello Monte, 10 4 2
A Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 979 8 36 0
UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce C/C
Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 28 6 0 326 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
noticed the dead man didn’t have a
b e a r d . It isn’t obligatory in Pakistan
like it is in Afghanistan. So the body
was given 80 lashes as punishment. I t ’s
madness.
T h e re ’s been an increase in re l i g i o u s
fanaticism in many countries. Why has
t h e re been this radicalization of Islam?
The two keys to the rise of Islamic
fundamentalism—whether in Afgha-
n i s t a n , I r a n , Algeria or other A r a b
countries—are illiteracy and ignorance.
They pave the way for a  “poor unders-
tanding” or rather a total misunders-
tanding of religion. To add to these
deficiencies, there’s the gap between
generations, and the deep divide bet-
ween rural and urban people. Don’t
forget most members of the  j i h a d
(holy war) movements come from the
c o u n t r y s i d e, where people generally
distrust modernization and freedom,
regarding them as a threat. In recent
y e a r s, globalization and other kinds of
progress that serve the political and
economic interests of large industria-
lized countries have been imposed on
these countries at a vertiginous pace.
Perhaps the fundamentalists are trying,
in their panic, to bolster their move-
ments by taking an increasingly hard
l i n e. In any case, the rise of funda-
mentalism harms Islam because it
makes it look like a fanatical religion,
devoid of spirituality.
The horrors of war have inspired most
of your short stories so far. What are you
focusing on today?
Before being a writer, I am an
Afghan, and I think that all Afghans
today share the same concern—that
the nightmare their country has
endured for the past 20 years come to
an end.That the country be saved from
the discriminatory rule of the Taliban
who are still backed by Pakistan, S a u d i
Arabia and the United Arab Emirates.
That Afghan women be rescued from
the clutches of these religious luna-
tics. Before the Taliban,40 percent of
teachers were women, a clear proof
of their intellectual level. Now they
are excluded from society. Their phy-
s i c a l , intellectual and psychological
plight is alarming.Th e y ’re not allowed
to consult male doctors. Worse still,
many are being sold into sexual slavery
in Pakistan.
Never before have the women of
my country been subjected to such
h u m i l i a t i o n , and never has A f g h a n i s t a n
gone so far backwards.Wh a t ’s left of my
country? The land is destroyed and
strewn with landmines.There are many
thousands of widows, orphans and
maimed people.The country is ravaged
by war, c o l d , drought and famine. M i l-
lions of refugees live in camps,mostly in
Pakistan and Iran,without any means
of subsistence and in inhuman condi-
tions. What I write, and will write can
only be about these concerns.
INTERVIEW BY JASMINA SOPOVA
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Dispersed for the first time: an Afghan refugee camp in Iran.
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
54th year
Published monthly in 28 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1. 45.68.57.47
e-mail: unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet: http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Cynthia Guttman
Spanish edition: Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
French edition: Sophie Boukhari
Michel Bessières
Ivan Briscoe
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Shiraz Sidhva
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: Gérard Prosper,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel: 33 (0) 1. 45.68. 46.87)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corral,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fall, Sue Williams
Non-headquarters editions 
German: Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian: Giovanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Flore n c e )
Hindi: Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese: Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U rdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Suchitra Chitranukroh (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali: Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian: Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Russian: Valeri Kharkin (Moscow)
Circulation and promotion
Fax: (33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel: (33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel: (33) (0) 1. 45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O Courier”, plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are
sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author’s
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re q u e s t .
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be re t u rned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. The UN E S C O
Courier is produced in microform (micro film and/or micro fiche) by:
(1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
M i c ro films (Xerox), Ann A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R.
M i c ro c a rd Edition, Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New
York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wo o s t e r,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL: C1 - MARCH2001
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly
in Paris by UN E S C O. Printed in France.
Periodicals postage paid at Champlain NY and additional mailing
o ffic e s .
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing: Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No.03-2001-OPI 00-592 A
March 2001 - The Unesco Courier 51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Focus:
■ From indifference to action: a new approach
to looting
■ Pillage and the rape of history
■ Mali’s all-out effort to save its heritage
■ Afghan relics find sanctuary in Switzerland
■ American Indians knock at museum doors
■ Özgen Acar : a Turkish journalist
on the robbers’ trail
■ Europe’s police join forces
■ The Getty Museum lights the way to repatria-
tion
Features include:
■ The feet of peace: how football is reuniting
Liberia
■ Saving the world or spreading the empire?
Critics of “green imperialism” speak out
■ Therapeutic cloning and the embryo question
■ Smoke in the valley: Viñales, home of
the Cuban cigar
■ Central Africa joins the airwaves
In the next issue
many voices one world
FOCUS
April 2001:
Getting
tough on the
art thieves
@ www.unesco.org/courier
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
Published in 28 languages
]]>
</page>
</document>
