<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="123057eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
P ro fil de
l ’ i n t e r n a u t e
en rupture
de To i l e
Le nucléaire,
p a ra d e
à l’effet
de serre ?
I t s u k u s h i m a
et son temple:
le temps
re t ro u v é
Afrique CFA:1000 F.CFA,Antilles:18 FF, Belgique:160 FB, Canada:3,95$Can,
Espagne:550 Ptas, USA:4,25 $US, Luxembourg:154 F.Lux, Portugal:700 Esc ,
Suisse:6,20 FS , United Kingdom:2,5£,Maroc:20 DH.S o u t h e r n
N G O s t a l k
back to donors
Long live 
a  trilingual 
Quebec !
Basque philosopher
Fernando Savater:
a call to re a s o n
July/August 2001
Canada:$3.95 Cdn,Uni ed Kingdom:£2.5,USA:$4.25
The new body
B E AUTY AND DREAMS OF PERFECTION…
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
◗ PEOPLE AND PLACES
4 Kuito, a child’s map of war and infinity
C h i l d r e n ’s laughter fills the silence of this Angolan city, brought to its knees by wa r.
Photos by Guy Tillim, text by Ana Paula Tavares 
◗ PLANET
12 This park is no longer your land
For over a century, millions of people were driven off their land in the name
of nature conserva t i o n . Now their voices are being heard. Marcus Colchester
15 Tales of white elephants in South Africa’s parks Eddie Koch
◗ CULTURE
16 Indian textiles find their patron
How a love affair with India has led to the flourishing of top quality crafts.
Jenny Housego
18 A prince embroiderer without a kingdom
Ngoc Loan Lam
◗ ETHICS
60 Partnership or purse-strings:NGOs in the South speak up
Discontent is rising among NGOs in developing countries over stringent
conditions imposed by donors. Philippe Demenet
◗ WORLD OF LEARNING
64 Vive a trilingual Quebec!
French is not the only language thriving in Canada’s Belle Province,
and few are worried about it. Filippo Salvatore
◗ MEDIA
67 Mexico’s mercenary legacy
The Mexican press has replaced old docility with hard-nosed opposition and helped to topple a
7 1 - y e a r-old system.Will it continue? Rafael Rodríguez Castañeda
69 Rise of a new watchdog in Latin America Mario Diament
◗ TALKING TO…
70 Fernando Savater, the hostage of purity
Threatened with death for his opposition to armed struggle, the Basque philosopher practices
his own brand of “active pessimism.”
JULY-AUGUST 2001
Detailed table of contents on page 20
© Jacques Prayer/Gamma, Paris • Stephen Lock/FSP/Gamma, Paris • Victor de Schwanberg/SPL/Cosmos, Paris
Fo c u s Beauty and dreams of
p e r f e c t i o n …
The cultural corsets confining our views of the human
body no longer fit in a world engulfed by Aids and global
a d v e r t i s i n g . From the former freedom fighter in South
Africa to the Tokyo fashion victim, individuals are
struggling to redefine what it means to be a “ r e a l ”m a n
or woman. Each advance in the operating theatre brings
us closer to
the dream of physical transformation—the promise
and curse of modernity. Aspiring beauty queens flo c k
t o Ve n e z u e l a ’s cosmetic surgeons while Indian peasants
sell their kidneys to make ends meet. M e a n w h i l e,
cyberpunks slip computer chips under their skin,
anticipating the next leap in evolution.
C O N T E N T S
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily re p resent the opinions of UN E S C O or those of the
e d i t o rs of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r s t a f f. The boundaries on maps do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the
United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
I N T H I S I S S U E
◗ Mutation
Will the 21st century be the age
of body mutations ad infinitum?
By transgressing beauty codes and
diverting medicine from its therapeutic
ends, a new generation is writing on
flesh the rules of a new game and
shaking up all our assumptions about
bodily norms (focus, pp. 20-59).
◗ Protection
The notion that nature can only be
protected in a virgin state is obsolete.
Its inhabitants, in most cases indigenous
people, are the rightful custodians
of the land.But there is no miracle
solution:as ecotourism in southern
Africa goes to show, the record is mixed
(pp. 12-15).Do crafts need the market
to survive? An experience in India
seems to prove the case, while
a Laotian prince’s vocation to protect
gold-thread embroidery is something
of a lone struggle (pp. 16-19).
In Quebec, the arduous efforts
to protect French through stringent
language laws are now loosening up
to make place for English and
“allophone”tongues (pp. 64-66).
And the laughter of children in
the war-ravaged Angolan city of Kuito
is keeping hope alight,for the young
are the ones pushing “the world
onwards to infinity”(pp. 4-10).
◗ Minorities
Spanish philosopher Fernando Savater,
of Basque origin,speaks out against
those minorities who are “fragmenting
humanity,” driven by an “ethnic-
totalitarian”ideology that is imposing
violence in place of the rule of law
(pp. 66-69).In Mexico, the uprising of
a Zapatista minority has stirred
the press from its age-old subservience.
Elsewhere in Latin America,
restoration of democracy and
the technology revolution are pushing
forward the same cause (pp. 66-69).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Ku i t o, a child’s
of war and infi
“Children in their white Sunday best walk the city from north to south…”
4 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The children’s days pass like light scattering on the wings of a bird.Small waves
buoy them along, their fragile bones, their vast souls opened wide towards
the sky.
A sense of eternity lies in each window turned toward the light,the sun
glides in through blankets of pollen settling on the ground.Children move
forth as if the world under their little feet was a theatre stage. Far in the
distance, the rumours of fountains can still be heard.
C h i l d r e n ’s laughter fills the silence,as if the soul of the rain had risen and
was beckoning the rivers to return and tempt wheat, maize and manioc
from the earth. Every wall is a mountain, and the higher one climbs, the farther
one sees into the future. Through the doors of grand,darkened houses, the
voices of adults, slow and unstinting as the afternoon,gather letters of the
alphabet and dreams to teach children of vanquished utopias, the secrets of
the wind and the two-times table.
The day advances in the wake of birds—the birds who leave small grains
behind so they can retrace their steps and dream once again.
These children live free,while the clocks, jammed by bullets,are destined
to repeat time, just as the to and fro of bells sounds the cycle of birth and
death.
They tame the silence, sowing laughter into the folds of day.There is still
milk in their laughter, fermenting the hopes of an afternoon.Beyond the doors
of houses, the children are exploring the labyrinthine walls.They have a key
for everything—even to the stairs that they climb up to reach the sky, b a r e d
by a missing roof.They sleep on the ground,parched by bullets, under a sheet
of stars that slowly descends until the light is eclipsed and night ushered in.
PHOTOS BY GUY TILLIM,TEXT BY ANA PAULA TAVARES
GUY TILLIM IS A FORMER ECONOMIST FROM SOUTH AFRICA;
ANA PAULA TAVARESISAN ANGOLAN POETANDWRITER
“Through something small, one can sometimes discover
the great things of life; there is no need to explain, one
simply has to look.”
Drawing on the wisdom of her countryman
and fellow writer Ondjaki, the Angolan poet
Ana Paula Tavares reflects on the photos of children taken
in the devastated town of Kuito
(Continued on page 8)
s map 
n fin i t y
July/August 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A child’s map
“The dogs devour dead bodies, the living eat the dogs,” wrote T h e
I n d e p e n d e n t’s special correspondent from Kuito during the nine-
month conflict that pitted the National Union for the Total Liberation of
Angola (UN I TA) against government forces in 1993-1994. Since the country’s
independence from Portugal in 1975,the two camps have been at war, but
this time, they fought on either side of Kuito’s main street. The fighting and
p r i vations left 40,000 dead.To date, the Angolan conflict has cost close to one
million lives.
“At the height of the Bosnian war, my eyes, like many others, were fixed on
S a r a j e v o ’s agony,while at the same time, another city was on its knees,” w r o t e
French writer Bernard-Henri Lévy, who visited the city in 2001 for the Fr e n c h
newspaper Le Monde. Located at the heart of Angola’s main plain, Kuito is
the most devastated city in Africa. Following the breakdown of the 1994
Lusaka peace agreement, fighting resumed in December 1998.Since then,
UNITA has been upholding a state of insecurity around Kuito. The city, only
reachable via armed convoy, is in “a desperate situation,” according to its
bishop, Dom Jose Nambi.
It counts about 240,000 inhabitants of which close to half are displaced. L i ke
a quarter of Angola’s population, war has forced them to flee their homes.
The city has no running water or electrical network.
Close to one child in two dies before reaching the age of five. Apart from a
tiny minority profiting from the diamond trade, the majority of Ku i t o ’s
inhabitants survive through a bit of farming around the city and a host of “ o d d
jobs.”
The displaced are almost entirely reliant on the World Food Programme. But
for financial reasons, the latter has just been obliged to limit its aid to the
“vulnerable groups,” such as pregnant women and very young children.
A CITY ON ITS KNEES
Cabinda
LUANDA
D E M O C R A T I C
R E P U B L I C
O F  C O N G O
Kuito
A N G O L A
N A M I B I A
“The children tame the silence by sowing laughter into the folds of day.”
Population:
12 millions (1999)
Surface area:
1,247,000km2
GNP per capita:
$270 (1999)
Life expectancy
at birth:
47years
Adult literacy rate:
n.a.
Source: World Bank.
ANGOLA: KEY FIGURES
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
6 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
“Children’s laughter fills the silence, as if the soul of the rain had risen and was beckoning the rivers
to return and tempt wheat, maize and manioc from the earth.”
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
A child’s map
“The voices of adults,slow an
Children in their white Sunday best walk the city from north
to south.
One thing is certain:here in Kuito, children push the world
onwards to infinity. ■
“The two-times table.”
“Children slide along this map with little speed cars made of tin cans.”
This is the map of a war:territories, frontiers and sprawling
craters are inscribed in black and white—it is the map of a new
w o r l d . Children slide along this map with little speed cars made
of tin cans, their bodies puffed by the wind,navigating the world
to its farthest limits.
They tell each other the tales of the great chiefs, heard from
elders sitting around water pipes and fires lit on the edge of night.
“Once upon a time there was a man,his wife and a snake,” or
“Once upon a time, there was a girl who asked many questions,”
or “Once upon a time, there was a magic box that should have
been hidden.”
(Continued from page 5)
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
8 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
One thing is certain: here in Kuito, children push the world
onwards to infinity
and unstinting as the afternoon, gather letters of the alphabet and dreams to teach the children…”
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
A child’s map
Beyond the doors of houses, the children are exploring
the labyrinthine walls
“A sense of eternity lies in each window turned toward the light, the sun glides in through blankets of pollen settling on the ground.”
Born in 1952,Ana Paula Tavares specializes in African lusophone
l i t e r a t u r e,w h i ch she teaches at the Catholic University of Lisbon.
Po e t r y : Ritos de passagem (“Rites of passage”) published by
the Union of Angolan Writers (1985); O lago da lua (“The lake
of the moon”), published by Editorial Caminho, Lisbon,1989;
Dizes-me coisas amargas como os frutos ( “ Tell me of bitter
things like fruit”), same editor 2001. In prose: O sangue da
b u g a n v i l i a (“The blood of the bougainvillea”), Cape Ve rd e
Portuguese Cultural Centre, 1997.
Ana Paula Ta v a r e s ’s poetry also appears in an anthology co-
edited by UNESCO and Acte Sud, Poésie d’Afrique au Sud du
Sahara,1945-1995.
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
10 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
“They have a key for everything—even to the stairs that they climb up to reach the sky, bared by a missing roof.”
“Every wall is a mountain,and the higher one climbs,the farther one sees into the future.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
C
MARCUS COLCHESTER
DIRECTOR OF THE UK-BASED FOREST PEOPLES PROGRAMMEANDWINNEROFTHE BRITISH ROYAL ANTHROPOLOGICAL
INSTITUTE’S LUCY MAIR MEDALFOR APPLIED ANTHROPOLOGY
This park is no longer
your land
For over a century, millions of indigenous people around the world were driven off their land in the
name of nature conservation. While local communities are regaining the right to manage these
protected areas, their struggle often runs up against deep prejudice 
reating protected areas to conserve nature
is a recent invention,born in the tumultuous
rush of land grabbing during the A m e r i c a n
conquest of the west. This was the time
when pioneers, the U. S. c a v a l r y,gold miners
and Indians struggled to impose their
different visions of life and land use on the
continent.
When the first national parks were
created (see box), one single vision had
excluded the others. The 1964 U. S.
Wilderness Act formalized this ideal notion
of nature as wilderness, untouched by
humans. It stated that national parks were
to preserve areas “where man himself is a
visitor who doesn’t remain.” The reality,
h o w e v e r, was different:most of these areas
were inhabited,used,managed and owned
by indigenous peoples. I n d e e d , nearly all
the most important protected areas in the
United States are owned or claimed by
Indians.
Many indigenous peoples remain
perplexed by western views of what
conservation means. “My Dad used to say
‘that’s our pantry.’ We knew about all the
plants and animals, when to pick,when to
h u n t ,” remarked Ruby Dunstan of the
Nl’aka’pamux people,who have been trying
to prevent the logging of their ancestral
lands around Stein Valley in the Canadian
province of A l b e r t a .“But some of the white
environmentalists seemed to think if
something was declared a wilderness, no-
one was allowed inside because it was so
fragile. So they have put a fence around it,
or maybe around themselves.”
An export model
Over a century, the U. S.model of nature
conservation has been exported worldwide.
In Africa,the practice of mass exclusion of
indigenous peoples to make way for
protected areas intensified in the 1960s and
has continued to this day. The Central
Kalahari Game Reserve was originally set
up for the benefit of the resident hunting
and gathering San, but they are currently
being expelled from the area by the
government of Botswana.
Some one million square kilometres of
f o r e s t s, pasturelands and farmlands have
been expropriated in Africa to make way for
conservation over the course of a century.
No one has been able to document how
many indigenous people were displaced as
a consequence, but they must number in
the millions.
Early 
warning
One widow belonging to the Twa people
recalls how she was expelled from the
C o n g o ’s Kahuzi-Biega National Park in the
1 9 6 0 s.“It was early in the morning. I looked
through the door and saw people in
uniforms with guns. Then one of them
forced the door of our house and started
shouting that we had to leave immediately
because the park is not our land.I first did
not understand what he was talking about
because all my ancestors have lived on these
lands.They were so violent that I left with
my children.”
Denied their traditional lands and
livelihoods, these Twa—traditional hunting
and gathering “pygmies”—now eke out an
existence in a number of squatter camps on
the fringes of their once-extensive forest
territory.They suffer extreme malnutrition,
landlessness, demoralization and despair.
We likewise lack accurate statistics about
A s i a . In 1993, an estimate by the Society
for Participatory Research in Asia suggests
that in India alone, as many as 600,000 tribal
people have been forced off their land due
to the setting up of protected areas.
Concerns about the social impact of
protected areas were voiced from their
i n c e p t i o n . By the 1970s, UNESCO had
developed the idea of “biosphere reserves,”
in which strictly protected “core zones”—
the old type of protected area—were to be
encircled with “buffer zones,” w h e r e
provisions were made for the local
inhabitants to continue their traditional
lifestyles and engage in controlled
community development projects.
Conservation agencies implementing
projects along these lines could get them
listed by UNESCO to gain international
recognition of their efforts. H o w e v e r, w h i l e
enlightened for their time, the management
◗ P L A N E T
12 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
Standing up for their rights: in Brazil,
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
of these experimental reserves has not been
markedly successful from the local peoples’
point of view.They continue the tradition of
imposing outsiders’ views of nature on local
peoples’ lands.
A review of buffer zone projects,c a r r i e d
out by the World Conservation Union in
1991 concluded that they had been,for the
main part,“disappointing…Local people,
often with good reason, frequently see parks
as government-imposed restrictions on their
legitimate rights. Patrolling by guards,
demarcation of boundaries and provision of
tourist facilities will therefore not deter
them from agricultural encroachment.”
The report also noted that the best
buffer zone projects had “not been short-
term aid projects but initiatives taken by
local community groups or resource
managers who […] made creative attempts
t o solve the day-to-day problems which
they faced.”
A well-documented example of these
d i f ficulties is the Amboseli National Park in
Ke n y a . Established on Maasai lands, i t
initially denied them access to dry season
pastures and watering points. The Maasai
showed their resentment for the loss of
their livelihoods by spearing rhinos, lions
and other wildlife. To compensate the
Maasai, a “buffer zone” was built up, with
World Bank support.New watering points
were established outside the “core zone”
and compensation fees were planned.
Promising at fir s t , the project broke down—
compensation went unpaid and the water
supply system deteriorated.
In the Philippines in the early 1970s,
World Bank plans to fund the construction
of dams on the Chico River, which would
have displaced some 80,000 Kalinga and
Bontoc people from their ancestral lands in
central Luzon, led to co-ordinated resistance
and the emergence of strong local
associations promoting land rights and
a u t o n o m y.Similar struggles in the A m e r i c a s,
Asia and Africa have resulted in the
emergence of vigorous national and
international coalitions of indigenous
p e o p l e,which have pushed their demands at
the United Nations and other international
bodies.
The movement has been dramatically
successful in obliging a re-evaluation of
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 13
Ta m i n g
the Wild We s t
On June 30, 1864, President Abraham
Lincoln signed the Yosemite Land
Grant bill, giving 39,200 acres of federal
land encompassing Yosemite Valley to the
state of California for public enjoyment and
p r e s e r va t i o n . The creation of the fir s t
national park took place during the
disruptions of the American Civil War at a
time when a devastating series of “Indian
Wars” was being waged to subdue Indian
autonomy. Thus the startling landscapes of
Yo s e m i t e, substantially an outcome of
Indian systems of land use, were proposed
for conservation by the very same settlers
who, twelve years previously, had waged
the “Mariposa Indian Wa r ” against the
area’s indigenous people—the Miwok. The
main proponent of the park, L a Fa y e t t e
B u r n e l l , who led the Mariposa Battalion and
professed a “take-no-prisoners” approach
to the Miwok, wanted to “sweep the
territory of any scattered bands that might
infest it.”
Once the Park was established, it was run by
the U.S. Army for the next 52 years before
being taken over by the National Pa r k s
Service.
The Miwok petitioned the U.S. government
in 1890. They called for compensation for
their losses and denounced the managers of
the park. “The valley is cut up completely
with dusty, sandy roads leading from the
hotels of the white in every direction… All
seem to come only to hunt money… The
valley has been taken away from us [for] a
pleasure ground….” Their pleas were
ignored and further evictions of remnant
Miwok settlements were made in 1906,
1929 and as late as 1969.
What the Miwok had noted was that the
national parks, set up to preserve
“wilderness” regions “unimpaired for the
enjoyment of future generations” were also
designed with a profit motive. Indeed, the
first parks of Yosemite and Ye l l o w s t o n e,
were created largely as a result of pressure
from the railway-building lobby, w h i c h
sought to increase the numbers of fare-
paying passengers by routing their tracks
near  scenic sites for what today we have
reinvented as “eco-tourism.” ■
zil, Indians from various indigenous groups stage a protest over territorial boundaries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
international human rights principles.As a
r e s u l t , existing conventions have been
reviewed and new ones developed which
recognize that indigenous peoples have the
right to own, control and manage their
traditional territories and to represent
themselves through their own institutions.
Recently the UN established a Permanent
Forum to address their concerns.
The same movement has also
demanded that conservationists change
their thinking and practice. For example,
in 1998, tribal people in southern India
forced out of the Indira Gandhi National
Park as part of an “ e c o - d e v e l o p m e n t ”
scheme funded by the Global Environment
Fa c i l i t y, successfully addressed their
concerns to the World Bank Inspection
P a n e l .Communities impacted by the Bank’s
projects can appeal to this independent
body if they believe the Bank is not
adhering to its principles.Their complaints
were upheld.
Rethinking old ways
By the 1990s, it became clear that very
many of the protected areas imposed
against the will of local residents were failing
to achieve their conservation objectives.
The denial of indigenous rights only meant
that protected areas seeded their own
failure by surrounding themselves by
h o s t i l i t y.The Manas Tiger Reserve in A s s a m
(India), for example, enclosed part of the
traditional homeland of the Bodo. L o c a l
resentment led to three quarters of the
rhinoceroses being killed.
To align with the changes in
international law, the World Conservation
Union revised its systems of categories of
protected areas to accept that indigenous
peoples may own and manage protected
areas, not just state agencies as previously
required. In the 1990s, the World Wildlife
Fund for Nature (WWF), the Wo r l d
Conservation Congress and the Wo r l d
Commission on Protected Areas all adopted
new policies and resolutions which strongly
endorse indigenous peoples’ rights and
promote the co-management of protected
areas, based on negotiated agreements.
Putting these principles into practice,
however, is easier said than done. In many
c o u n t r i e s, laws on protected areas
automatically extinguish residents’ rights
of natural resource use, free movement and
a c c e s s. Implanting the “new model” o f
conservation implies undertaking major
national reforms.
I n d e e d , because of deeply held
p r e j u d i c e s, governments in many countries
continue to deny indigenous peoples’ rights
and seek to assimilate them into the
national majority through forced
r e l o c a t i o n ,re-education and by breaking up
their communal lands, as in Malaysia and
I n d o n e s i a . National policies towards
indigenous peoples thus also need
reforming if conservation is to wear a
human face. Recent changes in the
Venezuelan constitution recognize
indigenous peoples’ rights to their
“habitats”and a law has just been passed
encouraging Indians to map and demarcate
their own lands to regularize their rights in
these areas.
Community-based conservation also
implies real challenges for indigenous
peoples themselves. Regaining control of
their territories may mean reactivating long-
submerged systems of self-government.
Changes in indigenous economies will also
need to be addressed—many indigenous
peoples have adopted new ways of farming
their lands, harvesting timbers and other
natural resources. Many now hunt with new
weapons and use industrial technologies to
process and transport crops. C u s t o m a r y
systems of regulating access to these
resources now need rethinking if they are to
be effective. In the Brazilian Amazon,the
WWF is now working with the Xavante
I n d i a n s, to help them devise new strategies
for managing their reserves. The aim is to
strengthen traditional ways of managing
resources with new knowledge about
environmental limits.
As the International Alliance of
Indigenous-Tribal Peoples of the Tropical
Forests noted in 1996:“Indigenous peoples
recognize that it is in their long-term interest
to use their resources sustainably and
respect the need for environmental
c o n s e r v a t i o n . They recognize that the
expertise of conservation organizations can
be of use to their self-development and
seek a mutually beneficial relationship
based on trust, t r a n s p a r e n cy and
accountability.” ■
14 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
+ …
World Rainforest Movement:www.wrm.org
www.forestpeoples.org
International Alliance of Indigenous-Tribal
Peoples of the Tropical Forests:
www.gn.apc.org/iaip
Survival International:
www.survival-international.org
World Conservation Union: www.iucn.org
Worldwide Fund for Nature:www.wwf.org
A new mission for protected areas? Tourists glide along Botswana’s Okavango
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
P L A N E T ◗
EDDIE KOCH
DIRECTOR OFTHE MAFISA RESEARCHAND PLANNING AGENCY
AND FREELANCEWRITER
Tales of
white elephants
Foreign companies keep the lion’s share of ecotourism profits but the Makuleke of South Africa are
trailblazing a juicy commercial venture based on their firm control of ancestral land and resources
game lodges in national parks and game
reserves across southern A f r i c a , which is
fast becoming a prime tourist desti-
nation.
Bottom of the ladder jobs
Until recently, the upscale lodges
dotting the wilderness were excluded
from the state-owned national parks,
where hunting is also prohibited. This is
beginning to change as ongoing land
reforms, which began in the mid-1990s,
give indigenous people often chased from
their lands during apartheid,the right to
use them for sustainable commercial
a c t i v i t i e s, particularly in the field of
ecotourism.
On the books, ecotourism rings like a
sensible way out of poverty and
u n d e r d e v e l o p m e n t . The U. S. b a s e d
International Ecotourism Society defin e s
it as “responsible travel to natural areas
that conserves the environment and
sustains the well-being of local people.”
Yet few studies have actually
examined its impact on local people’s
l i v e l i h o o d s, making the Ford study
something of a landmark. Its conclusion:
local residents in southern A f r i c a
generally get a raw deal, amounting to
little more than a few poorly paid and
unskilled jobs. Most of the money spent
goes to foreign-owned airlines, h o t e l s,
travel agencies and transportation
companies, along with consumer goods
produced abroad to satisfy tourists’ tastes.
I n d e e d , the World Bank estimates that 55
percent of tourist spending in developing
countries eventually leaks back to the
North,while some organizations put the
rate at 90 percent,especially in southern
Africa.
There are, h o w e v e r, a few
countervailing examples in the region.
In the far north of South Africa’s famed
Kruger National Park,about 900 families
belonging to the Makuleke tribe have
July/August 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 15
go Delta, led by local guides.
Winning back land rights is one side of the
battle waged by indigenous people,
finding ways to live off the earth is
another. Is ecotourism the answer?
Not always says a study conducted
for the Ford Foundation by Mafisa
Research and Planning, a South African
a g e n cy specialized in ecotourism. I t
examined the economics of about 30
won back the rights to own and use about
25,000 hectares of one of the park’s most
spectacular landscapes which,according
to some experts, contains up to two-thirds
of its biodiversity. They are now dealing
with a commercial operator, M a t s w a n i
S a f a r i s, to develop a luxury 24-bed lodge,
along with a tent-camp and even a
m u s e u m . Instead of resettling on the land,
they have decided to use it as an
economic base for their villages on the
park’s frontier.
In addition to lodging, the Makuleke
have also decided to offer some trophy
h u n t i n g, arranged by a private safari
company. Last year, two elephants and
two buffaloes were hunted, which brought
about $57,000 for local development
projects (and meat which was distributed
among Makuleke villages). The yields
are supposed to increase this year
(including animals like nyala and zebra),
which adds fuel to a simmering
controversy about trophy hunting in
g e n e r a l .H o w e v e r, the Makuleke leaders
vow to phase out the hunt once the other
tourism projects turn a decent profit.
Negotiating power
When running at 60 percent capacity,
the lodge will pay rent of $75,000 a year
to the Makuleke people, in addition to
about $150,000 in yearly wages to local
e m p l o y e e s. In total, the programme
should inject some $35,000 a year into
the coffers of the Makuleke—roughly
$400 per family, in a region where four out
of every ten adults is unemployed and
the average annual wage is about $750.
Projects like this offer food for
thought on the eve of the United Nations
Year of Ecotourism,slated for 2002. O n e
of the keys lies in equal terms: w h e r e
local residents have strong rights over
their wildlife and other natural resources,
they can negotiate with private operators
to ensure that their interests—financial,
THIS PARK IS NO LONGER YOUR LAND
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
A
◗ C U L T U R E
JENNY HOUSEGO
ART HISTORIANANDTEXTILES EXPERT
Indian textiles fin d
their patro n
High quality crafts can’t survive without skillful marketing, argues the author,
who has woven close ties with Indian craftspeople to build up a business. When will
aid agencies follow suit? 
s an art historian, I had long been
fascinated by the fragments of medieval
hand-painted and block-printed fabrics
excavated in the rubbish heaps of Fo s t a t ,
old Cairo. These were almost certainly
made in Gujarat in western India, a n d
attest to a flourishing trade with Egypt in
Indian textiles in the 13th and 14th
centuries.
Some years ago, I decided to see if I
could revive the patterns of these ancient
textiles with techniques still available
today.
I met Mohammad Bhai Siddiqui—a
famous master block-cutter and printer
from Kutch in Gujarat—and showed him
illustrations of some of these fragments,
now in museums in different parts of the
w o r l d .He was very excited,said he had no
blocks like this, but recognized them as
part of his tradition.He promised to see
what he could do.
Mohammad Bhai was as good as his
w o r d . From an illustration of a small
fragment,he had  worked out the repeat
in the design. He had created a superb
Fostat tablecloth, in rich,glowing colours,
made from the same natural ingredients
that had been used in the past.
We launched the tablecloths onto the
market,certain that buyers  would be as
excited as we were. A l a s, we were
d i s a p p o i n t e d . Long used to Indian block
prints being cheap, buyers found our
tablecloths too expensive. They were
unable to appreciate the centuries of
expertise that had gone into recreating
them.
Why should craft be cheap? Wh y
should beautiful, hand-made things be
expected to compete with mass
production? Why have the crafts of India,
once so highly renowned, b e c o m e
associated with bad quality, r u n n i n g
colours, boring designs?
Because the old traditions of
patronage have not been replaced by new
o n e s. Because craftsmen, no longer
working for their own communities, h a v e
great difficulty in finding new markets
and fall prey to filling orders where only
the price counts. Because the idea of high-
quality craft items aimed at discerning
markets is not yet fully understood in
this region. Because the importance of
aid in helping to improve quality and
identify market outlets has not been
addressed by governments and crafts
organizations.
Craft and commerce are inextricably
linked.Very early on,an embroiderer in
the first village centre established by my
company said to me,“How fortunate that
you are a commercial company, because
you have to make money and therefore so
will we!” She then told me about a
government agency and an NGO that
had set up training programmes in the
v i l l a g e, but as there was no instrument for
marketing or selling any of the products,
the projects had collapsed.
This is not a unique story. I hear the
same all over India.A friend in Delhi who
tirelessly promotes craft bewails that aid
is always available if she wants to build a
shed in a village,buy some looms or dig a
well,but not to help in marketing crafts.
16 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
Without promotion or marketing,
crafts are perceived as charity. P e o p l e
buy them to “help the poor craftsmen”
rather than because they are well-made
and a delight to have.
From the village up
For the tradition of hand-made
textiles to survive,new patrons have to be
f o u n d . My long interest in textiles and in
craft convinced me that something could
be done to revive India’s fabled
reputation of producing the world’s fin e s t
fabrics.
For many years, my interest in the
field was academic, but I have always
enjoyed working in the field and learning
about the past from the present.When I
came to live in India almost 15 years ago,
the two began to merge; I found I wanted
to develop textile crafts myself.
This is why, together with my husband
David,we established Shades of India, a
company that makes high quality textiles
for the home.We do not believe that craft
should remain static, so we combine the
best of traditional techniques with
innovative designs, some ancient,others
contemporary. We have established our
markets ourselves, presenting our
collections to buyers, instead of them
telling us what they want.A buyer from a
famous London shop once told us:“ M a k e
me dream!”This is what we attempt to do.
And increasingly, international buyers
are coming to us because they recognize
that India is the only place left in the
world where such a variety of hand-made
textile techniques can still be found.
It is not an easy road.There is nothing
I enjoy more than sitting with a group of
craftspeople and working out ideas for a
new collection.We work with craftspeople
all over India,and at the centres we have
established not far from Delhi, in villages
where there had been no employment
for women before.
The same philosophy lies behind the
Why should craft be
cheap? Why should
beautiful, hand-made
things be expected to
compete with mass
production? 
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Kashmir Loom Company, which I
established  a couple of years ago in
Srinagar with Kashmiri brothers A s a f
and Hamid A l i . Kashmir understands the
spinning and weaving of high quality
wools like nowhere else in the world.Th e
softest of these is Shahtoosh,now banned
because the wild Chiru antelope from
which it comes, faces extinction.
Pashmina is also timeless, w e i g h t l e s s,
and a delight to wear. It comes from the
Changra goat, that thrives in Ladakh and
Tibet at altitudes of over 4,000 metres.
This must not be confused with the poor-
quality fabric mixed with silk and other
fibres, from Nepal, marketed under the
same name.
In spring, nomad herders lovingly
comb out the fleece by hand.This is then
brought to Kashmir to be carded and
spun by hand and woven on traditional
hand-looms. This gossamer yarn is too
delicate to be treated by any machine.
No wonder, then,that it is so expensive.
What else could it be, when so much
skill and time have gone into making a
shawl?  
Team work
We work closely with our craftsmen.
At first hesitant to experiment,they are
now the creative force behind what we do.
They know their craft can survive only by
bringing new vitality into it, that the
market is demanding, and that we work
together as a team, respecting each
others’ talent and contribution. Th e y
make a good living, and their sons and
daughters often follow in their footsteps.
I feel deeply privileged to be a part of
their lives, their craft.As an art historian
I was an outsider, an onlooker into the art
of their ancestors.Now I am living it with
them.
If large agencies could add carefully
thought-out marketing and sales strategy
into their craft development projects, a n d
do on a larger scale what we attempt in
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 17
Bashir Ahmad Jaan toiled two and a half
years to produce “ S a m a va r,” an exquisite
Pashmina shawl embroidered with silk
thread in 14 different hues. His skill, i n h e r i t e d
from his forefathers, was rewarded with the
UNESCO crafts prize this year. He shared the
$5,000 first place (for the Asia region) with
Kim Taeja of the Republic of Ko r e a , w h o
created “Gilsando,” a six-panelled folding
s c r e e n , representing the finest silk-thread
court embroidery.
Established in 1990, the prize encourages
craftspeople to merge their technical mastery
of age-old skills with inventive and
contemporary designs. A warded by
international juries during regional crafts
fairs around the world,the prizes are given
to works of exceptional artistic quality, w h i c h
are also deemed marketable.
UN E S C O works closely with the International
Trade Centre in Geneva to help craftspeople
m a r ket their products both locally and
internationally.“Though UNESCO’s role ends
when the actual business of marke t i n g
b e g i n s, the activities of the crafts programme
do not make a separation between
m a r keting and art,” explains Indrasen
Ve n c a t a c h e l l u m , chief of the crafts and
design section. “ The basic question for
craftspeople is how to sell their products,
because very often, their craft is their only
means of subsistence.” One of UN E S C O’s most
recent projects (April 2001) is the opening of
a crafts showroom near Luang Prabang in
Laos.A renovated building now serves as a
centre where crafts produced in workshops
in three nearby villages are marketed directly
to customers, allowing craftspeople to reap
higher profits by selling without
intermediaries. ■
PRIZED TA L E N T S
Labour of love:in Srinagar, Habibullah Palgaru, aged 80,delved into his art.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
T
NGOC LOAN LAM
JOURNALIST SPECIALIZED
IN SOUTH-EAST ASIANISSUES
A prince embro i d e re r
without a kingdom
Tiao Somsanith is among the last of a dying breed skilled in gold-thread embroidering, an ancient
tradition from the court of Luang Prabang in Laos. Today, he is trying to save this vanishing art,
without resorting to commercialism
he Laotian prince-embroiderer Ti a o
Somsanith has lived in the French royal
city of Orléans, or more exactly in the
suburb of Saint-Marceau, since 1985.To
reach the two small rooms of his home
filled with Laotian court treasures, y o u
must leave Orléans and cross the Loire
R i v e r.With a little imagination, it recalls
the Mekong, which flows past Luang
P r a b a n g, once the royal capital of
L a o s, where the smooth-faced, n i m b l e -
fingered “young man”was born 43 years
a g o.
That court vanished after the Pathet
Lao communists took power in 1975 in
the aftermath of the Vietnam Wa r.“ M y
maternal grandfather was the last
viceroy of Laos,” says the prince. “ M y
paternal grandfather was a famous court
h i s t o r i a n , and his wife was an excellent
e m b r o i d e r e r. My father was advisor to
the king in Vi e n t i a n e, the administrative
c a p i t a l .”
A secret gard e n
He has not lost stock of his rank and
d u t i e s.“ The mission of the royal family
and the viceroy was to protect c u l t u r e
and tradition,” he says.“One of them is
the gold thread embroidery that is
s p e c i fic to the Luang Prabang court.
Only women of noble birth were
allowed to learn this craft, w h i c h
probably came from China, j u d g i n g
from the technique and symbolism of
d e s i g n s, such as the dragon.”
During the Laotian cultural week
last March in Orléans, visitors could
admire a lavish red and gold silk
ensemble that the queen would have
worn either for her coronation in Luang
P r a b a n g, had the monarchy not been
a b o l i s h e d , or to celebrate New Ye a r ’s,
had she not perished in a re-education
c a m p. It took the prince one long year
working at night to make the garment,
since he earns a living by running a
daytime creativity and self-expression
workshop for mentally handicapped
a d u l t s. Before that, he gained degrees in
fine arts and psychology in Fr a n c e.
“I drew inspiration from the
writings of my father, who was in charge
From his two-room home outside Orléans (France), Tiao Somsanith embroiders by night to complete a prayer fan,intended for a pagoda in
18 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
of protocol,” he says.“I remember the
festivals that punctuated life at the
c o u r t , where an appropriate outfit was
necessary for each ceremony.This work
represents both my secret garden, m y
h i s t o r y, and the cultural heritage of
L a o s.”
The costume reflects the court’s
h i e r a r c h i e s, with colours and
embroideries corresponding to social
s t a t u s.Culling from a repertory based on
w i l d l i f e, f l o w e r s, mythology and
Buddhist iconography, e m b r o i d e r e r s
were nevertheless free to compose
n u a n c e s, the movement of embroidered
patterns and to model reliefs with gold
and silver braiding. “ The yellow of the
j a c k e t , reserved for the queen, r e c a l l s
the dazzling sun, and the red of the skirt
evokes the blood of life,” e x p l a i n s
S o m s a n i t h .
An ard u o u s
a p p re n t i c e s h i p
The royal ornamentation
embroidered by the prince includes
golden phoenixes taking flight among
interlacing plant patterns. Like an
endless river, they continue on the back
of the jacket, suggesting the eternal life
cycle and the wheel of reincarnation.
“ I ’ve embroidered good-luck bats, b i r d s
of paradise with elephant trunks and
b u t t e r flies symbolizing the ephemeral,”
he says.
Somsanith borrowed these designs
from inscriptions he gazed at on the
ceilings of pagodas as a child. H e
embroidered without using the carved
wooden templates, which were
indispensable for beginners who
fastened them to silk with big stitches
and reproduced the outlines with gold
t h r e a d .
Only experienced embroiderers
between the ages of 30 and 40 reached
that level of perfection. The road was
long and the apprenticeship arduous.
The prince, who was the last in a family
of nine children living in Vi e n t i a n e, s p e n t
summers with his grandmother in Luang
P r a b a n g. “I was so rambunctious that
my parents sent me to keep her
c o m p a n y,” he recalls laughing. “I also
met some of the requirements for
learning this exclusively feminine
p r o f e s s i o n , which is passed down from
mother to daughter.”
At six, like all nimble-fingered
a p p r e n t i c e s, the prince was coating silk
threads with wax to make them
straighter and threading them into
needles for his grandmother and aunts,
who worked in a special room every
m o r n i n g. In the hope of being released
from this painstaking work, s o m e t i m e s
the young prince secretly finished his
g r a n d m o t h e r ’s embroidery, trying to
copy her style.
“By the time I was 10 or 12, I already
had a certain amount of experience,”
he says. “My grandmother probably
guessed what I was up to, a n d
introduced me to the art of purling by
letting me finish the buds on a bouquet
of flowers she had started.”
Back to
the pagoda
The different steps in an
e m b r o i d e r e r ’s career were clearly
spelled out. Little girls traced the edges
framing the designs and decorated
pillows and prayer cushions.A d o l e s c e n t s
embroidered skirts and collars. A d u l t
women made their wedding dresses,
ceremonial costumes and burial clothes.
Between 50 and 60, at the peak of their
s k i l l s, they gradually stopped making
secular garments to focus on religious
accessories intended for pagodas.
Religion is exactly the means by
which Somsanith intends to breathe new
life into his art. In August 2001, t h e
e m b r o i d e r e r-prince is going to Luang
Prabang to offer one of his works—a
prayer fan decorated with a Buddha in
the teaching position—to the Sene
p a g o d a .
Now this guardian of an endangered
tradition has just one goal in mind:
passing it on to young Laotians, a n d
introducing the diaspora to the art of
living that goes with it.
He refuses to give into the
temptation of the market.“Some of my
relatives embroider to order for tourists,
especially from Th a i l a n d , and rich
families of the diaspora. G o l d - t h r e a d
embroidery is acquiring a market value
and losing its meaning. The women
wearing them are parvenus who only
care about the glittering outer
appearance of things without knowing
their intrinsic value.”
The prince wants to pass on both
technique and meaning. “ E m b r o i d e r y
is more than just a technique…. E v e n
though an embroidered garment might
only be worn once during an exceptional
c e r e m o n y, it requires an apprenticeship
that is so long it builds character, a n
idea that has fallen by the wayside.
Passing this tradition down from one
generation to the next also teaches
future artists that they are merely
p r a c t i t i o n e r s. Before setting down to
w o r k , my grandmother performed her
devotions to the inspiring spirits and
the ancestors who trained her to bring
about her act of creation.”
With exhibitions, lectures and a
documentary made with the Fr e n c h
national research council, Somsanith is
also sounding the alarm on the
disappearance of other crafts connected
to gold-thread embroidery, such as
l a c q u e r i n g.“ The last master lacquerer is
81 years old and no longer working. H e
has stopped making the baskets
Designs inspired by childhood memories.
VIENTIANE
Luang Prabang
C H I N A
V I E T N A M
T H A I L A N D
C A M B O D I A
Gulf
of
Tongking
M e k
o n g
C U L T U R E ◗
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
C o n t e n t s
1 / Shattered ideals
Global advertising and Aids reshape the cultural corsets confin i n g
views of the human body
2 2 The body jigsaw Philippe Liotard
2 5 A d v e r t i s i n g, my mirro r Interview with Christian Blachas
2 6 In and out of slavery Nicholas Mirzoeff
2 9 I n d i a ’s wings of desire Shreedar Rajan
2 / Passing rites
R e d e fining what it means to be a “real” man or woman
3 2 The sirens of To k y o Muriel Jolivet
3 4 The rise and fall of the South African “ s i x - p a c k ” Th o kozani Xaba
3 6 Minding the muscle tone Martin Gambarotta
3 7 C h i n a ’s timid coming out Stéphanie Ollivier
3 9 The passing of bodily seasons S o u m a ya Naamane Guessous
4 0 “ Taking the dre s s ” Khadi Diallo
3 / Escaping destiny
Physical transformation,
the curse and promise of m o d e r n i t y
4 4 I l l u s i o n s, scalpels and stere o t y p e s Sander L.Gilman
4 6 Under the sun, under the knife R a kel Sosa
4 7 Beauty and the blind Georgina Kleege
5 0 The organ of last re s o r t Nancy Scheper- H u g h e s
5 3 The knot in the bra i n A . C. G ra y l i n g
5 4 A release from life Wybo A l g ra
5 6 A lunchbox for longevity I van Briscoe
4 / C y b e rs p e c i e s
The next leap in human evolution?
5 7 Te flon under my skin Marc Millanvoye2 / New Bonds
5 8 Goodbye biology, hello software Interview with Ray Ku r z w e i l
B E AUTY AND DRE
the new
F O C U S
20 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
Dossier concept and co-ordination
by Ivan Briscoe, Cynthia Guttman
and Amy Otchet,
UNESCO Courier journalists
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The faculty at the University of
Hawaii went on strike on April 5, 2 0 0 1 . I
participated every day on the picket line
and in a demonstration at the state
Capitol Building. I sat with a sign on my
l e g s, tied to my wheelchair, saying “ U H PA
(University of Hawaii Professional
Assembly) on Strike.” I had a button
pinned to my shirt, reading “United We
Bargain,Divided We Beg.”
During the strike,many people often
told me or commented to friends within
e a r s h o t , “Britt is really a hero.” Th e r e
was also the constant question:“Are you
t i r e d ? ” . I was not tired. But I did feel as if
people were dismissing me, as if people
wanted me, along with my A L S
(amyotrophic lateral sclerosis) atrophied
body and wheelchair, to go away. (This
disease attacks motor neuron cells in the
b o d y, brain and spinal cord, leading to
varying amounts of paralysis and often
death.)
Another recurring question that
people asked my wife or accompanying
research assistant was,“How is he doing?”
That question was never directly
addressed to me. S t r a n g e r s, as well as
people who knew me well, applied the
stereotypes of the tired hero to me. No
one had evil or limiting intentions. Ye t
they rarely stayed long enough for any
form of interaction. I cannot speak and
have very limited movement of my head
and neck but, like anyone else, I enjoy and
require conversation. My wife and helpers
can read my lips, gaze and gestures. Yet
very few of my supposed admirers were
interested in a chat.
Being called a hero for participating
in everyday life events, like the strike, is
not limited to American culture. I was
recently invited to Japan to address
universities and communities. Th e
listeners would break into sobs and wind
up calling me a hero. My speeches were
videotaped and played over and over on
Japanese television. I could not go to a
restaurant without being noticed.
I do not want to leave the impression
that I did not enjoy the trip to Japan or the
participation in the faculty strike. I had
many authentic conversations in both
settings with people who knew my
sociological work. H o w e v e r, I did not
have the anonymity that most people
e n j o y. I find myself powerless in changing
newspaper accounts or television stories
about my so-called heroism.I cringe when
I read reviews of my sociological work,
typifying me as a hero.
If limiting references are contained in
languages and the implicit knowledge
accompanying ways of speaking, w h a t
can be done to free up the disabled?
There are two tasks. The first is to play
back the constricting language on those
who utter it. If I get the chance, I ask
those who ask me whether I’m  tired if
they are tired and in need of rest. This
provokes awareness. It also ruffles some
feathers.
The second task is to teach people
the awesome power in ways of speaking
and writing about disabled people.Po w e r
and the entirety of social institutions are
contained and continuously reproduced
in ways of talking, writing, reading, and
visually representing society. We are
agents in this reproducing society and
are capable of change in the way we
linguistically regard the disabled.
Although we have laws to protect their
civil rights, we need to go much further
and address the power of discourse.
By playing back the language on my
well-meaning friends and colleagues, I do
not want to impose a kind of sturm und
d r a n g discipline of a movement. M y
objective is to make people conscious of the
way words and phrases create,make things.
I really want to create the festivity of the
picket line, where middle-class professors
felt free to identify with, if only for a
m o m e n t , historical working-class labour
s t r i k e s.I want disabled people to experience
the same freedom,where their disability is
i g n o r e d . I am tired of being trapped in
c a t e g o r i e s ; I no longer want to be a hero.
I wish to thank Katherine Tr owell and
Shannon Gau for their assistance in
preparing this paper.
I AM NOT A H E R O
BY ALBERT BRITT ROBILLARD
SOCIOLOGY PROFESSORAND SENIOR RESEARCHER, UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII,
AND AUTHOROF MEANING OF A DISABILITY: THE LIVED EXPERIENCE OF PARALYSIS (TEMPLE, 1999)
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 21
AMS OF PERFECTION…
w body shop
O P I N I O N
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
PHILIPPE LIOTARD
PROFESSOR AT THE UNIVERSITY OF MONTPELLIER I
AND CO-FOUNDER OFTHE MAGAZINE QUASIMODO
The body j i g s a w
Imagine the body as a canvas, a space to mix and match physical
and cultural elements in defining who or what you want to be.
Here lies the great paradox. The scarring and piercing of tribal aesthetics
are all the rage in rich countries, while in the South, western ideals
are coveted by a monied few
1 . S H ATTERED IDEALS
I
n 1976, the punks barged into the lives of the
reserved British with a bang. Disrespect was
their word of order,as they went about ranting
against the predictable world mapped out by
their elders. They insulted the Queen and
heaped abuse on nuclear energy, the economy,
p o l l u t i o n , work and the media.
For even greater shock value, they tapped the
power of the image. They spat on staid English
conventions by donning a revolting, yet carefully
studied appearance. A skirt could no longer be
called a skirt, and punks gleefully paraded in torn,
stained and gaudy clothes,marrying colours against
all the cannons of good taste.
They cut their hair into crests,
horns and other shapes,
plastered themselves with lurid
make-up and wore chains.
They covered their arms, f a c e s,
necks and heads with tattoos,
reinvented piercing using
safety-pins, studs and rings in
their noses, eyebrows, lips and
cheeks, and went so far as to
deliberately scar themselves.
With their altered, r e b e l
bodies, the punks quickly gave birth to a charged
s e l f - i m a g e. Their very own promoters conspired
with the media they despised and turned them into
symbols of decadence,before exporting their bodily
aesthetics throughout Europe, North America and
Japan.
N o w, a quarter of a century later, the punks
have spawned a loyal following. Top models,
sporting personalities, singers and show-business
stars jostle to display original hairstyles and body
piercings. In rich countries, teenage girls show off
their navel rings and stick out their bejewelled
tongues, while boys wear rings in their eyebrows.
Tw e n t y - five years on, the socially-scorned practices
of piercing or altering one’s body have become
musts for counting on the fashion scene. Yo u n g
westerners have appropriated once “ u n d e r g r o u n d ”
practices to gain entry into the trendy but ultimately
mainstream club.
There is, h o w e v e r, a paradox in all this. O n e
would expect originality and innovation. In fact,
what we are witnessing is a sweeping trend of
cultural mix and match,drawing on body-altering
techniques long used by non-western cultures for
purposes of religion, aesthetics or identity. Th e
American artist Fakir Musafar  coined the term
“modern primitives,” giving rise to a new ideal, a
patchwork that “tribalizes”the western body. For
the past 50 years, he has explored alternative forms
of spirituality incorporating primitive body
decoration and rituals.
How did these alternative ways of changing the
body travel so far afield? What drives young
westerners to have tattoos from the South Sea
islands or Japan? What do these “ t r i b a l ” o r
“ p r i m i t i v e ” markings and
decorations mean in a western
society?
Certainly not a return to
the rituals that originally
produced them: most of those
who go for such adornments
know nothing about these
distant practices. M o r e o v e r,
the bodies now being used as
models were those that were
stigmatized and displayed
during colonial exhibitions in
Europe and the United States right up to the early
20th century.They were curiosity objects and more
s i g n i f i c a n t l y, living symbols of the supposed
“ b a c k w a r d n e s s ” of the colonized peoples. S e e n
through European eyes, piercing, body scars and
elongated lips, necks and ears were evidence of
“barbarism,” justifying the West’s self-appointed
duty to civilize. Such practices incarnated the
opposite of the ideal “civilized”body.
By way of homage to the civilizations the
colonial powers seemingly sought to stamp out,
the vanguard of the “modern primitives” set out to
investigate these body rituals.The “tribal aesthetics”
of Maria Ta s h j i a n , who owns a chain of body-
alteration shops in the United States, is vaunted as
a way to educate people by preserving the memory
of extinct cultures and passing on their idea of
What do these “ t r i b a l ”o r
“ p r i m i t i v e ” markings and
d e c o rations mean in a 
western society? What drives
w e s t e r n e rs to have tattoos
f rom the South Sea islands?
22 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
beauty. Through piercing, stretching the ear-lobe
and body scarring, we can thus create a jigsaw of
ancient and modern aesthetics.
Others such as Musafar see these practices as
the chance to work on one’s own profound sense of
S e l f. “Body play,” in his words, consists of
experimenting with every known body-alteration
t e c h n i q u e.By willingly going through the initiation
ordeals of traditional societies, one actually re-
lives a primal experience that has long been
forgotten in the industrialized world.It is the path
towards rediscovering an original innocence.
Forget about 
those blonde surfers
Wh a t ’s important is not the markings left on the
b o d y, says Musafar. I n s t e a d , what matters is the
confrontation with physical pain that takes one
toward another plane of consciousness, shunned in
western societies where all is done to combat
s u f f e r i n g. But unlike the physical and symbolic
violence of initiation rites in traditional societies,
these bodily alterations are the fruit of a conscious
personal choice.
Such discourse, however, will be rarely heard
among the millions of people who flirt with body
decorating.The vast majority are merely fulfilling
the modern-day desire for self-knowledge and
recognition from others. They might invoke
aesthetics, spirituality, sex games or the desire to
belong to a group, but whatever the reason, t h e
process of altering the body and putting it to the test
comes down to playing with identity.This reflects a
profound cultural shift.
The urge to assert oneself goes hand in hand
with a desire to challenge social norms and values,
and to advocate different ways of experiencing,
feeling and displaying one’s body. Many fans of
body-art, piercing and tattooing say they can no
longer accept the western model of a sanitized,
bland,alienated body.
The ideals of the blue-eyed blonde and the
Californian surfer with the sleek and muscular
bronzed body have to go. In this light, a l t e r i n g
one’s body becomes a battle against conventional
a p p e a r a n c e, a quest to give meaning to a life
The mind’s terror
of the body has
probably driven
more men mad
than ever could
be counted.
D. H. Lawrence,
British novelist
(1885-1930)
A carefully studied statement that speaks out against convention.
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 23
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
d e m a n d s, constructing an appearance becomes the
royal road to upsetting normality. E v e r y o n e
becomes an actor,capable of displaying their body
in a unique way. Rather than sinking into the
c r o w d , they spark a chain of reactions (grounded or
not), from attraction and fascination to rejection
and fear.
The refusal to comply with social norms, the
awareness that looking different has an impact,is
all part of a battle against creeping standardization.
In this light,such a philosophy stands at opposite
ends from the promise of cosmetic surgery,diets and
the like.
Television and the Internet are giving play to all
these trends. Day after day, we are exposed to a
million ways of perceiving the body, culled from
past and present, from the imagination and real
experiments. Such depictions remind us that the
body is not about a static anatomy, and that there
is more than one way to signal membership to a
g r o u p.They also remind us that culture is always on
the move.What is exotic one day is undesirable the
next and rediscovered later. The globalization of
images has spawned multiple models of the
“ c i v i l i z e d ” b o d y, breaking with the western
standard-bearer.
Dressed to kill
in Kinshasa
In developing countries, however, those with
money go to no ends to cling to the most common
western model, plucked straight out of television
s o a p - o p e r a s. South American immigrants in the
United States go for breast implants, lighten their
skin and bleach their hair. In southern Africa and
among African A m e r i c a n s, skin-lighteners and hair-
straightening products are all the rage.The famed
s a p e u r s of Kinshasa, in the Democratic Republic of
Congo, make enormous sacrifices to keep up with
what they see as the latest in Parisian chic.C o s m e t i c
surgery is as popular in the U. S. as in South
A m e r i c a , where women have operations that bring
them eerily close to the Barbie doll ideal.In Asia,
they ask surgeons to attenuate the “slant”of their
e y e s.… Does a perceived or real context of political
and economic domination lead some to hide their
s p e c i fic features? “ We s t e r n i z i n g ” the human body
reads like a strategy to fit in with globalization.
For now, creating a hybrid ideal of the body is
a game for the privileged.Among the poor, only a
minority is going about removing the stigmas they
have historically borne. But popularizing this new
ideal is stirring debate. By hijacking appearance
codes and adopting body-altering techniques that
were originally designed for medical purposes,
people are carving in flesh the rules of a new game.
Their efforts will likely herald an all-round
deemed otherwise insignificant.
To this end,it’s not enough to go shopping for
t r a d i t i o n s. Piecing together a body can also be
d o n e using modern materials, knowledge and
t e c h n i q u e s. By inserting foreign objects under
t h e i r s k i n , some body artists are creating
protuberances on foreheads, breastbones and
forearms to radically challenge age-old perceptions
of the physical self.
A battle against
creeping standardization
All these interventions can be seen as a quest to
escape a destiny spelt out in terms of sex,age and
social origin. In this sense, they have political
i m p l i c a t i o n s. By shattering models, rejecting beauty
standards circulated in the mass media and asserting
the right to do, wear and display what they see fit,
this avant-garde is holding up the body as one of the
last bastions where individual freedom can be
expressed.
Faced with the pressure to conform, to discipline
one’s body in order to meet economic and social
A Masai in Kenya shows off her pineapple can earring.
24 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 25
Has the spread of globalization pro d u c e d
an increasingly standardized ideal of
the human body?
Oddly enough, the more
globalization advances, the less of a
single ideal there is.As far as pure physical beauty
g o e s, the American model prevailed for several
d e c a d e s. It changed slowly, from brunettes like
Audrey Hepburn and Lauren Bacall to blondes
epitomized by Marilyn Monroe and others. Then
various ethnic groups demanded their place in
a d v e r t i s i n g.The result is that today, a wide range of
human models is held up to us.
To what extent does advertising create people’s
image of the human body?
That image comes to us from the fashion world.
People like to say advertising starts trends, like the
recent wave of “fashion pornography.” But this
came straight from designers and fashion
journalists. The job of advertising is to pick up on
trends. It’s rarely subversive because brands don’t
gain anything from shocking people too much.
Advertising’s a remarkable mirror, but it doesn’t
start fads.
So are the accusations unfair that advertising has
c reated an ultra-thin ideal of the body, as pers o n i fie d
by top model Kate Moss?
Kate Moss has certainly had a big influence on
anorexic teenagers, but it isn’t just because of
a d v e r t i s i n g. I t ’s her presence on the screen.M u s i c,
video clips and television are just as responsible as
advertising for promoting this ideal of thinness.
The image of men has changed quite a lot too, h a s n ’ t
it?
The depiction of homosexuals, especially in
Fr a n c e, is a major revolution. Surveys show people
a r e n ’t in the least shocked by the presence of
homosexuals in advertising images. All this has
helped to win acceptance for the idea that a man has
the right to take care of his body. Sales of male
beauty products are booming.Men are trying to fin d
their bearings.Their three reasons for being, in the
West at least—going to war, bringing home the
bacon and making babies —are disappearing as
more women work and science advances. M e n
have mentally accepted that they should do
housework (though only three percent actually do
any) and help to look after their children. B u t
women are also calling for men to be more
masculine again, while demanding they show a
sensitive, feminine side…
Advertising reflects this confusion.
A b s o l u t e l y. France is the country that seems
to have the freest attitude by far to morals and
morality.The Anglo-Saxons are very prudish.You
never see naked breasts in American ads. Three
years ago, there was an uproar when the lingerie
firm Victoria’s Secret mounted a big advertising
campaign in the United States, complete with
parades by top models. It was the first time people
had seen women moving in public wearing nothing
but a bra and panties. We’d been seeing that on
French television for 20 years.
Has that image become routine?
Ye s, and we’re not bothered by it. A recent
survey we conducted showed that most Fr e n c h
people aren’t shocked when they see very sex-
oriented advertising. Scandinavian countries have
even less of a complex with regard to nudity,
although the images are not erotic. They are very
puritanical Protestant societies.
In Fra n c e, a law has been suggested to safeguard the
image of women in advertising.
Some feminist groups deplore excessively
sexual advertising and the depiction of women as
o b j e c t s, but I think it’s dangerous to pass laws about
t h a t .Wh o ’s going to decide what’s what? It’s not up
to judges to say whether an ad is degrading to
w o m e n . People will eventually get bored with very
sexual images and a balance will be restored
naturally.
A re there any taboos left in the way the human
body is depicted?
The last taboos, t h a n k f u l l y, are pedophilia
a n d z o o p h i l i a . The trend of portraying sado-
masochism shocks feminists but at the same time,
advertising works with fantasies. If there’s no
physical threat to the human body, such allusions
INTERVIEW BY CYNTHIA GUTTMAN
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
A d v e r t i s i n g , my m i r ro r
Christian Blachas, a seasoned observer of world advertising and publisher of
the French magazine C u l t u r e p u b m a g, decodes the images of the body
s u r rounding us
1 . S H ATTERED IDEALS
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
To love or hate
your body are 
two mistakes to
avoid. Narcissism
and self-hate,
money and
suicide are 
of the same
substance.
Philippe Sollers,
French writer (1936-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
NICHOLAS MIRZOEFF
PROFESSOR OFART AND COMPARATIVE STUDIES AT THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK AT STONY BROOK, NEW YORK.
HIS MANYPUBLICATIONS INCLUDE DIASPORA AND VISUAL CULTURE: REPRESENTING AFRICANSAND JEWS (ROUTLEDGE, 2000)
I n and o u t of slavery
Do artists uphold prejudice or offer a novel way of looking at ourselves?
A few hints culled from the colonial era and beyond give a sense of how
art goes about telling the body’s history
1 . S H ATTERED IDEALS
W
hen visual artists represent the body,
whose body is being talked about,
and can that body stand for others
or only for itself? It would be
comforting to tell a story in which
people from the past misused the body, only for more
enlightened figures from our own time to set the
record straight.Like most stories with a happy ending,
this would be just a story.History is more complicated
and less reassuring. In trying to think about a history
of bodies, it is necessary to highlight certain themes
because the body is in a sense everything: m e d i c i n e,
w a r, s e x u a l i t y,“ r a c e,” g e n d e r,p e r f o r m a n c e,dance and
so on. On the other
h a n d , the body can be
treated as nothing, o r
as a commodity, t h a t
is to say, s o m e t h i n g
that is bought and sold
in slavery.
Slavery has been
defined as “ s o c i a l
d e a t h .” If humans are,
in Aristotle’s phrase,
“social animals,” t h e n
to be a slave is to be
d e fined by others as
simply a body, a dead
person who works.
B y looking at the
changing depictions
of the body in and out
of slavery, we get a
measure of how our
own bodies have
been evaluated over
time.
Some might think
that this is a
“politically correct”
t o p i c, detracting from
the impact of art.Th e
reverse can also be
a r g u e d : a failure to
understand the social
and historical context
in which artworks
were made reduces them to mere decorations. It is
precisely because art is so powerful that we need to
understand more about how it works. To take an
e x a m p l e, the brand-new Sainsbury gallery for A f r i c a n
art in the British Museum, L o n d o n , places the entire
continent in three galleries divided only by medium—
sculpture, fabrics, pottery. Here self-confident and
highly realistic 16t h-century bronze sculptures from
the powerful kingdom of Benin stand alongside the
tormented abstract minkisi power figures from the
Belgian Congo, as if both expressed something about
an eternal A f r i c a . In fact the Benin bronzes show so
powerfully what Africa was capable of before slavery
and colonization that 19th-century Europeans
assumed that they could not have been made by
Africans and theorized that perhaps refugees from
the lost city of Atlantis had been responsible.
The Cartesian
heritage
The m i n k i s i figures were made at the height of the
colonial terror in the Belgian Congo and were used
by a nganga, or operator, to call on the spirits of the
ancestors in the struggle against colonization. If this
seems to be evidence of a supposed A f r i c a n
“primitivism,” it should be noted that the Belgian
colonizers believed that the power figures worked
and did everything they could to capture them, w i t h
the result that many American and European
museums have fine examples. By trying to place
these figures into grand, abstract categories like art,
or even Africa, the curators missed the chance to
show how art tells the history of the body as one of
conflict and change.
The modern Western history of the body usually
begins with the separation by French philosopher
René Descartes of mind and body. Writing in the
mid-17th century, Descartes argued that the body
was only connected to the mind at the pineal gland—
which in fact produces hormones in response to
light—that became a point of interface between two
radically separate entities.In his view, the body simply
responded to the environment and to sense
p e r c e p t i o n s, whereas the mind reflected on those
perceptions and took decisions that might or might
not agree with them. For example, the eye sees a
perspective drawing as “ r e a l ,” while the mind knows
Former slave Jean-Baptiste Belley strikes a royal pose.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 27
it is an illusion. By introducing doubt, D e s c a r t e s
broke the traditional continuum between mind and
body that saw both as natural and asserted a higher
status for the mind. Perhaps the body was something
that the European elite wished to distance itself from,
now that the trade in human beings across the A t l a n t i c
was in full swing.
The French port
of Nantes sent out
108 slavers to the
Guinea coast as
early as 1666,taking
on board 37,340
A f r i c a n s. Slavery in
the French colonies
was controlled by
the infamous C o d e
N o i r decreed by
Louis XIV. Th i s
separate legal code
for the enslaved gave
the slave owner the
same kind of power
on his plantation
that the king enjoyed
nationally—that is to
s a y, the power of life
and death.The king’s
body was uniquely
powerful, especially
as depicted in art.
For the king was held to have two bodies, one physical
and one spiritual.The spiritual body was the essence
of the monarchy that never died, slept or became ill.
That body was shown in portraits and statues around
the nation and the French colonies. By the same
token, the bodies of the king’s subjects were mere
o b j e c t s,whether that of a French peasant or a colonial
s l a v e. So the philosophical division of the person
into body and soul was complicated by the political
doubling of the royal body and haunted by the ghosts
of the enslaved.
Race takes
the stage
During the French Revolution of 1789, t h e s e
tensions burst into the open. At that time Santo
Domingo (now Haiti), the jewel in the Fr e n c h
colonial crown, received 1,587 ships, more than
France’s largest port, Marseilles. But beginning in
1 7 9 1 ,H a i t i ’s enslaved Africans joined the revolution
and overthrew the colonial regime.As the revolution
thought through the consequences of the Declaration
of the Rights of Man (1789) and the abolition of the
monarchy (1792), it became clear that slavery would
have to go. On February 3,1794,a group of Haitian
delegates to the Convention, the revolutionary
parliament, successfully proposed the abolition of
s l a v e r y. One of these men was Jean-Baptiste Belley,
a former slave who had been born in West A f r i c a .I n
1 7 9 7 , the artist Anne-Louis Girodet painted Belley’s
p o r t r a i t . It is a remarkable evocation of the tensions
of the period expressed through one person’s body.
Belley stands against a tropical landscape,
wearing the uniform of a Convention member. His
face is rendered in the traditional three-quarter style
used for nobles and monarchs.At the same time, h i s
body has an unusual twist to the hips, giving it a
somewhat feminine feel. His masculinity is
nonetheless asserted by a prominent bulge in his
trousers.
Belley rests on a bust of the abbé Raynal,who
had called for the abolition of slavery. The marble
whiteness of the bust and its classical straight
forehead contrast with Belley’s dark skin and a
prominently sloped forehead. In the period, t h i s
cranial angle, as it was called, was taken as a mark of
low intelligence. How should this portrait be
understood? The simple fact that an African was
painted in the royal style by a European artist marks
a remarkable shift, while the various markers placed
on his body by the artist tried to assert a new form of
superiority:that of race.
Revisiting The Jungle Book
Ironically the very success of the movement to
abolish the Atlantic slave trade engendered a new
form of distinguishing between human bodies as
belonging to different races. Under slavery people
were legally different. Now a new means of
classifying human bodies was devised. A n
extraordinary volume of scientific and artistic work
was produced in the effort to define and make visible
the supposed eternal differences of race.E v e r y t h i n g
Unlike ugliness,
beauty cannot
really be
explained:
it is stated,
affirmed and
repeated in every
part of the body,
but can never be
described.
Roland Barthes,
French semiologist
(1915-1980)
Edwin Long’s Babylonian Marriage Market (1875), a cornucopia of stereotypes.
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
from skin colour to the shape of the skull,nose and
b r e a s t s, and every aspect of culture was used as
evidence to prove that humans were biologically
d i s t i n c t .Art played an important role in the system,
from supplying evidence of difference in the
comparison of Greek statues to African bodies to
instructing young people how to make race visible
in images.While many radical artists were involved
in the struggles to abolish slavery, they were
exceptions to the mainstream rule.
The highest price paid for the work of any artist in
the 19th century was for Edwin Long’s 1875 T h e
B a bylonian Marriage Market.This painting showed a
slave auction in antiquity, with authentic historical
d e t a i l . In the foreground, facing the viewer, was a
racialized hierarchy of
enslaved women ranging
from a white woman at
left who looks at herself
c o n fidently in a mirror via
Asian women to an
African woman who
covers her face in
apparent shame.The main
action of the scene
showed a woman being
unclothed on the slave
block to the appreciative
gaze of a male audience,
who appear to be mostly
Je w i s h . This cornucopia
of stereotypes won Long
a position in Britain’s
Royal Academy and a
career as a portrayer of
the “ t y p e s ” that science
then assured everyone to
be real.
In the present, race is
a term whose very
meaning is uncertain.
Scientists have shown
that all humans share
9 9 . 9 percent of their
genes and the visible
markers of the body are minor variations of no
substantive importance. But racism has not gone
away as the recent wave of hostility to outsiders in
Western Europe clearly shows. In part that is because
race is no longer understood as it was in the 19th
century as science but as part of popular culture.
One of the first feature films was D.W. Griffith’s
1916 epic Birth of a Nation that tells the story of the
rise of Ku Klux Klan in the American South, using
white actors in black face to portray A f r i c a n
Americans in atrocious stereotypes. Throughout the
20th century, films like Tarzan of the A p e s p r e s e n t e d
Africans as primitive savages. When such subjects
were challenged by the civil rights movement and
d e c o l o n i z a t i o n , they were simply displaced to
cartoons like The Jungle Book (1966) that portrays
jazz as literally the music of monkeys.
A new generation of artists is challenging us once
again to rethink old means of imagining ourselves
and others.The controversial young African A m e r i c a n
artist Kara Walker has challenged the prevailing
assumption that all images of minorities in the United
States should show people engaged in positive and
uplifting activities. By contrast, her silhouette fig u r e s
cut out of black paper show both Africans and
Europeans in an extraordinary range of what might be
called perverse activities.
By using the 19t h-century silhouette format once
taught to polite Victorian ladies, Walker at once
reminds us that the leisure of such women was
enabled by the free or unfree labour of others and
suggests that not that much has changed since then.
Her work makes us realize that oppression really
functions to denature both the oppressor and the
o p p r e s s e d .While some critics have fiercely denounced
her work, Walker has already won a MacArthur
“genius”grant.
Another contemporary artist who sees the
Victorian past in the present is Nigerian Yi n k a
S h o n i b a r e, who recreates elaborate ball-gowns of
the period, correct in every detail, except that the
fabrics he uses are West African kente cloth, not the
sedate cottons and silks that Europeans of the period
once wore.These dresses make colour in all senses of
the term visible. In similar vein, the Ja p a n e s e
photographer Yosimasa Morimura photographs
himself in a variety of staged situations, often wearing
drag. Posing as the model for Manet’s 1865 painting
Olympia, Morimura completely alters the dynamic
of the image. Whereas the original showed a white
p r o s t i t u t e, whose sexuality was alluded to via the
figure of her African maid, the photographic
recreation forces us to reconsider the question of
what whiteness might actually be.
All these artists take the long view.They seem to
suggest that despite the advances of recent decades,
the historical legacy of slavery and colonialism is far
from played out.At the same time, the very fact that
artists from around the world are engaging in such a
reevaluation of history is itself grounds for a degree
of hope. One thing is certain:the body is going to be
a key subject in art for a long time to come. ■
28 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
T h ro u g h o u t
the 20th century,
films like Tarzan of the Apes
p resented A f r i c a n s
as primitive savages.
A twist on Victorian ball-gowns by Nigeria’s Yinka Shonibare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 29
K
o o v a g a m , in the Indian state of Tamil Nadu,
has attracted the limelight in recent years—
thanks to A i d s.The village is the traditional
seat of chitirai pournami, an ancient
transsexual festival marking the anniversary
when Lord K r i s h n a is believed to have taken on the
form of a maiden to enjoy sexual bliss with A r a v a n, a
P a n d a v ap r i n c e.
For centuries, the festival has been celebrated on
a full moon day in April and is patronized by urban and
rural folk and hijras (transsexuals and eunuchs) from
across India.In the last three years, Aids prevention
organizations from Chennai have stepped in to confer
“new respectability” to this expression of alternate
sexuality by organizing an annual beauty contest for the
“third gender.”“ We want people to realize that h i j r a s
are as much a part of society as anyone else,and use the
opportunity to provide Aids information and
c o n d o m s,”says Dr. Manorama Pinagapany, director of
a community health NGO.
While the local media has become more daring
about promoting “new lifestyles,” Indians are generally
considered  “conservative and orthodox” in sexual
m a t t e r s. There is an irony in this: it was after all in
countries like India that various sexual cultures claimed
their natural place in society from time immemorial.
Hindu culture views the physical body as a
container of the soul,a divine but transient abode of
the spirit. The body is revered because  it houses the
S e l f, the life-force. The Kama Sutra, the ancient Hindu
treatise on sex by Va t s y a y a n a, notes that kama ( s e x u a l
desire) is one of the means to attain m o k s h a
( s a l v a t i o n ) . These primeval thoughts still pulsate
through the subcontinent. The S h i v a l i n g a , a phallic
symbol of the deity Shiva in sexual union with his
c o n s o r t , goddess Parvati, is worshipped all over India.
Lord Rama and his wife Seetha may be glorified for
their sense of duty and fid e l i t y,but India is also the land
of Krishna, celebrated for his dalliances with celestial
beauties.
Temple sculptures of Hindu deities seek neither to
conceal any body parts nor even censor their
p r o p o r t i o n s. Depictions of Hindu gods and goddesses
are usually of graceful,sensual proportions, the men
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
SHREEDHAR RAJAN
AWARD-WINNING INDIAN FILMMAKERWHOHASPUBLISHED EXTENSIVELY ONTHE SOCIALAND CULTURALASPECTS OF AIDS
I n d i a ’s wings of desire
Hindu civilization glorified the sensual body and gave the world a famed
treatise of physical love. While the advent of Aids was first met
with intolerance, traditional practices are regaining right of place
1 . S H ATTERED IDEALS
The Media Foundation, an Indian NGO, has found a new vocation for the sculptures of the Khajuraho
Just as, in this
body, the Self
passes through
childhood, youth
and old age, so
after death, 
it passes to
another body.
From the Bhagavad-Gita,
ancient epic poem 
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
long limbed and athletic, the women with slim waists
and fulsome bodies. Stone figurines of divinities and
mortals at the 10th century Khajuraho temples in
Madhya Pradesh depict a variety of sexual unions,
almost in clinical fashion.
The unabashed honesty of the nudity that embel-
lishes almost every Hindu temple divests the body of
crude eroticism,raising it to a near ethereal plane in
Hindu consciousness. The average Hindu was
conditioned to accept the body and sexuality as natural
aspects of the cycle of birth and death.
Cultures driven 
underground
Sexual openness was an ordinary aspect of
everyday life, as temples also served as centres for
social interaction.An assortment of sexual orientations
were an integral part of traditional Hindu societies.
Transsexual courtesans, dancers of the d e v a d a s i
t r a d i t i o n , street dancers, singers and musicians offered
pleasure and sensual fulfil l m e n t . Multiple partner sex,
bisexuality and other so-called sexually “ d e v i a n t ”
cultures were never explicitly disowned but instead,
had their own social, religious and artistic space within
mainstream society.
Sex work, for example was conferred religious
respectability in the culture of the devadasi s e c t .Th e s e
women were given in marriage to God and
ritualistically dedicated themselves to fulfilling the
sexual needs of society. They lived in or around the
temples and enjoyed considerable respect.
Indian civilization allowed for a diversity of
perceptions, lifestyles and values to the extreme and
was non-judgemental almost to a fault. Yet there
appears to have been a method to this madness:
complex social and spiritual systems had evolved,
allowing for a certain unity in diversity, a harmonious
co-existence.
Hindu cultures came under pressure from
Buddhist and Jain teachings that advocated physical
and sexual renunciation. During the Mughal rule of the
subcontinent (1556-1707), sexuality was put under
purdah (veil) and women further withdrew from the
public domain. Colonization by the British and
subsequent missionary efforts at “ c i v i l i z i n g ” t h e
sexually “exotic natives” deepened the departure
from uninhibited sexual mores. Victorian prudery
and double standards were added to this conundrum.
Indian sexuality, which had enjoyed abundant
expression in the public domain for centuries, s u d d e n l y
found itself choked. Caught between many worlds, i t s
natural growth became warped: hypocrisy, denial of
one’s roots and the self, fueled by a sense of shame,
began to gain momentum.Aping the culture of the
colonizers to gratify them led to a situation where
traditions were disowned.
The year 1947 saw the birth of an independent
I n d i a . The spawning of an English-speaking,
westernized Indian minority, which had internalized
many of Britain’s missionary values, now ruled as the
country’s political elite, setting new moral standards,
codifying what kinds of sex and between whom was
permissible by law.The d e v a d a s i t r a d i t i o n , for instance,
was criminalized and legally banned.
The upshot was a burgeoning culture of clandestine
sexuality, lurking in respectable neighbourhoods, the
dark by-lanes of towns and the deserted corridors of
t e m p l e s. It was into such an environment of sexual
hypocrisy and repression that the HIV virus made its
unfettered entry.
A foreigner’s
disease
When the first cases of  infection were detected in
India,the government responded by passing an HIV
quarantine law. The illness was perceived as a
f o r e i g n e r ’s disease from the “immoral and excessively
p e r m i s s i v e ”We s t .Some government officials called for
the repatriation of African students and a ban on sex
with foreigners. The government also made public
appeals for a return to the nation’s “pristine”values,
offered to pay sex workers to retire, or at least to
tattoo HIV-positive ones to forewarn clients.
The world is now twenty years into the A i d s
e x p e r i e n c e,with Asia stealing the spotlight during the
second decade. Until it was recently overtaken by
South A f r i c a , India had the largest HIV positive
population in the world—–about 3.86 million.
Available reports indicate that the epidemic remains
concentrated among groups like sex workers and drug
users. By the mid-1990s, more than 25 percent of sex
workers in Indian cities had tested positive for HIV. I n
M u m b a i , the prevalence rate among them had reached
71 percent in 1997. Interviews with HIV- p o s i t i v e
women in India revealed that despite public
30 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
Reconnecting with a sensual past.
I hold flesh-food
to be unsuited
to our species.
We err in copying
the lower animal
world—if we are
superior to it.
Mahatma Gandhi, 
Indian politician and
philosopher (1869-1948) 
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
information campaigns, women only learned about
the importance of condom use after they had become
i n f e c t e d .While gender inequality can be fatal as far as
Aids is concerned, the reality in several Asian countries
is that women remain largely uneducated and exploited
at home and in the fie l d s. They know little about
protecting themselves from HIV, or negotiating
condom use with their husbands or sexual partners.
Sex workers
in the open
But there is another side to the coin: Aids has
been the single most significant factor that helped
traditional sexual practices and orientations to at least
partially regain their rightful place in the public
d o m a i n .I r o n i c a l l y, this too is the result of international
p r e s s u r e s.Prostitution and homosexuality, it now turns
o u t , must be de-criminalized and women given the
right to safer sex in the age of A i d s. Sexuality must now
be redeemed from its underground sanctuary. P e o p l e
of different sexual orientations must be rehabilitated
into mainstream society, destigmatized and even re-
c h r i s t e n e d . With the arrival of A i d s, the circle is
c o m p l e t e, and the d e v a d a s i has re-emerged in her new
avatar of “sex-worker.”
Sex education is donor- d r i v e n , funded and
f a s h i o n a b l e. Sex is not a dirty word any more, just like
the good old days, centuries ago, when we took our
children to the temples where the most graphic details
of all forms of sexual practices were aesthetically
signified in stone, where grandmothers told tales to
their grandchildren about sexuality with utmost
r e v e r e n c e.The difference in this era of Aids is, h a v i n g
come the full circle,we sadly discover that we have lost
the natural ease, grace and élan that came
spontaneously in the distant past.There is a visible self
consciousness attached to public perception and
expressions of the human body.
After more than a decade of A i d s, the sheer
magnitude of the threat to human lives is finally
blowing away the layers of hypocrisy and painting a
brave new assertive face on Indian sexuality and the
b o d y.C a l c u t t a , which has A s i a ’s largest red light district,
S o n a g a c h i, is home to the Durbar Mahila Samanwaya
Committee —a forum of 60,000 sex workers and their
children.
The founding members, all sex workers, c a m e
together through their active involvement as peer
educators in an STD/HIV prevention intervention
programme. “We have been successfully networking
among sex workers in India and some other countries,
particularly in South and Southeast Asia,to promote
and protect our rights,” claims the forum’s
s p o k e s p e r s o n . “Our political objectives are
decriminalization of adult prostitution and securing
social recognition of sex work as a valid profession ”
How has the literate middle class and the polity
responded to the Aids epidemic? According to psycho-
analyst and author Dr.Sudhir Kakar,“sexual attitudes
have changed much less than what the media portrays.
Sexuality is still not seen as freedom of the psyche
and body.It is still surrounded by feelings of shame and
g u i l t .” Although middle class women have become
more vocally aware of their bodies, says Kakar,
sexuality can be very subversive for family stability.
“One believes that for family stability one has to be
sexually conservative.”The deep bonding within Indian
families is ensuring that people with Aids are largely
not being left to their own devices,although a husband
with the illness is more likely to be looked after by his
family than his wife.
People with HIV, irrespective of caste or class, a r e
subjected to considerable social ostracism. Th e
stigma can go to extremes: in 1989, a young HIV-
positive man in Goa was isolated and incarcerated
for having a “contagion that was dangerous to public
h e a l t h .” A decade later, a man rumoured to be
infected with HIV and supposedly attacking
residents of a Chennai suburb
with a needle contaminated with
his own blood, led to a hysterical
mob burning him alive.
Sitcoms vs 
morality
Even explicit HIV prevention
education attracted censors in
some Indian states. In June 2000,
two members of an Aids Service
Organization working in a village
in northern India were arrested
and jailed for having distributed
graphically explicit material on
HIV prevention.The couple had to
remain in custody on charges that
they had attempted to corrupt the
morals of society under the guise
of Aids education. A year later,
women in Bhopal (Madhya
P r a d e s h ) , publicly burnt HIV
prevention leaflets containing
graphic depictions of how to use
c o n d o m s, spurred on by a sense of
moral outrage.
With the opening up of the
Indian economy in the early 1990s,
American television serials
regularly flood urban middle-class
drawing rooms with sex and semi-
n u d i t y. Sexual talk is in vogue
among young,mostly urban Indians, but the emphasis
on virginity until marriage is still the norm,says Kakar,
especially among women  
Modernity and traditions are colliding under the
onslaught of globalization.Primordial beliefs, values
and norms are now awash with science, technology and
w e s t e r n i z a t i o n . Perceptions of the body and sexuality
are less self-conscious and the wheel seems to have
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 31
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
Straight talk.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
MURIEL JOLIVET
PH.D. IN ASIAN STUDIES, PROFESSOR AT SOPHIA UNIVERSITY IN TOKYO,
AUTHOR OF HOMO JAPONICUS (PHILIPPE PICQUIER, ARLES, 2000).
The s i re n s of To k y o
The outrageously eccentric young women of Tokyo’s trendy
neighbourhoods use their bodies as a provocation, simply to attain
the illusion of being loved
2 . PASSING RITES
I
t all started in 1996 with Amuro Namie, a
s u p e r b, 1 7 - y e a r-old siren and graduate of
O k i n a w a ’s A c t o r ’s School.An excellent dancer,
she performed on stage in a strapless bra and
then in a pant suit with long jackets.Her look—
golden skin, m o t h e r-of-pearl hair and carefully
tweezed eyebrows—immediately became all the
r a g e, launching the “ t r o p i c a l ”s t y l e.Amuro Namie
also introduced the vogue of “platform boots,”w h i c h
she even wore in the middle of summer to make up
for her short stature.
Her clones have multiplied like mushrooms
after a rainstorm in To k y o ’s trendy neighbourhoods,
like Shibuya. H i y a k e tanning salons have cropped
up just about everywhere, and young women who
have overdone it—or fallen asleep under the UV
rays—are called ganguro, “black faces.” They find
a mischievous pleasure in
accentuating the contrasts by
highlighting their eyes and lips
in white.
“I went through my
kogyaru [literally, ‘little girl’1]
phase,” says Sanae, a 21-year-
old student,“my teachers just
about pushed me into it.Wh e n
they let me know that they
couldn’t stand me anymore—
that I would never make it in
their eyes—I realized it was no longer worth
wearing myself out trying to please them.To get out
of my teenage crisis, I hung out with a group of girls,
between 15 and 18,who were as lost as me. Some
of them were ‘occasionals’ who turned tricks to
buy clothes or name-brand handbags without the
least bit of remorse.They clung to the illusion that
they were envied.”
Writer Murakami Ryu2 thinks that high school
prostitution is the sign of a much wider malaise in
Japan.To him,young “occasionals”are just trying
to act like adults by sacrificing themselves to the
ritual of consumption.After all,a r e n ’t the Ja p a n e s e
the world’s leading consumers of designer Louis
Vuitton bags? “These young people cling to their
mobile phones like a life raft to give themselves the
illusion of being loved,” he says.“In reality, t h e y ’r e
terribly lonely.Each girl is in her bubble, i n c a p a b l e
of communicating.”
The k o g y a r u of the late 1990s vanished as
quickly as they appeared. Men now find them
v u l g a r,and nobody seems to miss them.In Shibuya,
they have been replaced by superb creatures on
s t i l t s, their pants held up by garters that offer a
glimpse of legs molded by red fishnet stockings.
Clothes are just an excuse. Hanging out in Shibuya
mostly means wandering around in search of an
identity, or at least a visual one. What began as a
very affected anti-conformism has ended up
becoming a new way of fitting into the standard
m o u l d . You cannot tell one Shibuya girl from
a n o t h e r.Their password remains m u r e r u,“ m e e t i n g
in groups to share,” if not the same philosophy of
l i f e, at least the same
eccentricity or the courage to
exhibit part of their bodies.
Until the 1970s and 80s,n o
self-respecting woman ever
went out with bare arms, m u c h
less uncovered legs or feet.
Sleeves were mandatory and
going bare-legged was out of
the question, even during the
hottest months of the year.Th e
measure of how much a
woman in a kimono cared about her appearance
was the cleanliness of her tabi (linen socks worn
with sandals or wooden clogs),which she discreetly
changed during the course of the day to always
look impeccable.
To d a y ’s young women are just as conscious
and strict about their appearance but display it in
other ways. They walk around bare-legged,bare-
backed and barefoot in spangled mules and
plunging necklines. They wear carefully polished
fingernails (real or false, they are incredibly long)
and false eyelashes, their bodies burned to a crisp
by UV rays and their hair dyed blond or bleached.
The Shibuya generation, the heir to the
“bamboo shoots”generation (takenoko zoku) of
the 1970s and 80s, is so eccentric they would make
Until the 1970s or 1980s,
no self-respecting
woman ever went
out with bare arms,
much less uncovered
legs or feet.
32 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
London’s former punks blush. “The plasticity of
Japanese women’s bodies lets them change their
look whenever they feel like it,” says Erika,a 17-
y e a r-old Fr e n c h - Japanese high school student.
“They can be black or white. For an African look,
they overdo it in the tanning salons, wear clothes
with leopard designs, have their hair kinked and
permed and use make-up with an emphasis on
brown pastels and white refle c t i o n s. If they want to
look white, like the singer Hamazaki Ayumi,they
cultivate a pale look, bleach their hair, put on false
eyelashes and sometimes even wear blue contact
lenses or sunglasses.”
At twenty,
the fun stops
To obtain a kogao, or “little face,” there is an
endless range of products, from sauna masks to
c r e a m s. The hard part is maintaining the iron
discipline necessary to stay slim as a reed, with a
narrow waist and spaghetti legs. “Anorexia has
been taking a heavy toll since the 1980s,” s a y s
psychiatrist Saitô Satoru, who is the author of a
book entitled Onnarashisa no yamai (The Pain of
Fe m i n i n i t y) . “Over 60 percent of young women
today are underweight.”
Th a t ’s because being beautiful in
Japan means being young, very young.
The singers in Morning Musume, a real
h i t , are between 12 and 20 years old.
The senior member (called “the old
lady”!) just quit the band at the age of
28.Amuro Namie was a star when she
was 18. To d a y, she has practically
disappeared.
Why then do these girls go through
so much trouble for their look? They do
it more for themselves than to attract
attention from boys. To have fun and
show off. But showing off implies the
presence of an audience likely to admire
t h e m , or at least appreciate all their
e f f o r t s. The blond sirens in Shibuya
know that their daring outfits are less
shocking when they walk around in
g r o u p s, as if to give themselves the
courage to face disapproving stares. In
any case, they don’t stand a chance of
getting through the high school door
with their look.Education is a serious
b u s i n e s s, and all the more so when
university begins.
A rich man
is hard to find
“ The student style has nothing to
do with the kogyaru s t y l e,” s a y s
C h i k a k o, a third-year student who
works for the magazine Can Can.“Our readers, w h o
are between 18 and 23, are looking for smart,
resourceful men who make a good living and spend
their money like water.The guys these girls want to
meet most graduated from the top universities.
They work in business,advertising or for a famous
foreign company, unless they’re future doctors.
Since the speculative bubble burst and economic
growth came to a screeching halt in the early 1990s,
the student style has become much more toned
d o w n . Girls used to own several name-brand bags,
now they settle for just one. They spend more on
their hair than on their clothes. All of them want
dirty blond hair. I t ’s gotten to the point where girls
with black hair are a minority in university lecture
halls!”
After graduation, they reappear in preppy suits,
white blouses buttoned up to the neck and fla t -
heeled shoes, like perfect office ladies. At 30,they
drop their boyfriends for somebody more serious
and hard-working who will help them fulfill their
role as mother and do all they can to put their
children on the path to a bright future.
So much conformism is almost enough to make
one yearn for the days when the k o g y a r u gave free
rein to their fantasies. ■
1. From the Japanese k o,
l i t t l e, and the English
g i r l pronounced with a
Japanese accent.
2. Author of Coin Locker
B a b i e s ( Ko d a n s h a ,1 9 9 5 )
Tokyo’s fashion victims seldom travel on their own.
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 33
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
The rise and fall of the South
African “s i x - p a c k”
Yesteryear’s heroes are now villains in South Africa, where
former guerrillas pushed to the fringes of society cling to the cult 
of the hard body
THOKOZANI XABA
RESEARCH FELLOW AT THE UNIVERSITY OF NATAL, SOUTH AFRICA
2 . PASSING RITES
I
had just moved back to Kwamashu (near Durban,
South Africa) when I went to meet the son of a
f r i e n d , who had been like a brother to me before
his untimely death.It had been ten years since I had
last seen Fe r n a n d o.The 11-year-old boy had grown
into a tall young man, w h o,despite his size,greeted me
o b s e q u i o u s l y.
“Uncle! I was afraid you wouldn’t recognize me.”
“I was unsure at first, but I couldn’t miss the
resemblance between you and your father.” Th e
mention of his father made Fernando jolt.“ You should
tell me about my old man sometime,” he said sadly.
When we parted, I couldn’t help noticing the
number of people staring at us. L a t e r, I found out that
they had never seen Fernando talk with anyone but
former guerrillas or comrades who put their bodies “ o n
the line” in the struggle against apartheid. S o m e
thought that he was holding me up.
In the following year, I met Fernando about a
dozen times. We mostly just greeted each other but
once he asked me to loan him a few coins. Was he
looking for a job? “I can’t,” he said.“I don’t have ID
p a p e r s.” Did he want me to speak with the authorities?
“No,” he said.“The police are looking for me.”
A few months later, Fernando was dead. A
neighbour explained that the police had killed him in his
safe house.“Get up,y o u ’re arrested!”t h e y ’d yelled at his
friends. But when Fernando tried to stand up, a bullet
went through his forehead, another through his
cheekbone and five or so riddled his body. The officers
then found a cache of arms in the house—some of
which had belonged to policemen who had been robbed
and killed.
Fe r n a n d o ’s story is not unique.Unable to find a job,
he began training former guerrillas to protect
themselves from police attacks because many had
turned to crime.Some robbed banks, others turned to
contract murders. They replenished their stocks of
arms by attacking police. But there was one taboo:
they did not attack their neighbours.They eliminated
Fear and loathing in an impoverished township of South Africa.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 35
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
those who preyed on the community. One man
captured the feelings of many when he mourned
Fernando’s passing,“We have lost a hero…”
Scarred egos
Like in many transitional societies, y e s t e r y e a r s ’
heroes—the young guerrillas and comrades who
sacrificed their studies and often their lives under the
banner “Liberation now,education later!”—are today’s
villains in South A f r i c a .The “ r e a l ”man is no longer the
militant, anti-authority warrior, but the law-abiding,
wage-earning professional or artisan.
In a world of globalized advertising, the male
muscle-bound torso is an icon of power, fine-tuned in
the air-conditioned confines of an expensive
gymnasium. But in South Africa, that torso, called a
“six-pack,” embodies inequality and oppression. The
poor nutrition and gruelling labour conditions of
apartheid inured the bodies of African men to hardship.
These hard bodies were the perfect raw material for
capitalists of the racist regime. They also served
individuals seeking fame in the professional sports
a r e n a .Yet the glorification of physical strength reached
new social heights as the liberation struggle moved into
the guerrilla phase in the 1970s and 80s. C o m r a d e s, l i k e
Fernando, decided to go beyond the daily hide-and-
seek with apartheid administrators and police to pursue
formal military training outside of the country. Boys
who had never known a word of praise from their
families became respected heroes, revered as
“ l i b e r a t o r s.”Yet despite their inflated egos, these young
men were still scarred by the emasculation of
apartheid’s class and racial domination.To be a “real
m a n ,” many inflicted considerable violence against
w o m e n , which was largely concealed during the
struggle.
Once the liberation elite moved from a state-in-
exile to government, the aura and adulation
surrounding the warriors faded. Those hard bodies
were progressively stripped of their decorations as
the African National Congress took power in 1994
and distanced itself from the guerrilla’s methods and
f u n c t i o n s. Some were absorbed in the ranks of the
new army, private security firms hired others, but many
were left on their own.Lacking the skills to compete
for scarce jobs, they put their guns “to work” in crime.
Power of the gun
With about 13 million firearms circulating in a
country of 40 million people, the gun has become a
veritable extension of the body.It represents the power
to “ h a v e ”w o m e n ,to rob and dominate others,to dismiss
the victim’s humanity. South Africa has the highest per
capita rate of reported rape in the world (for every
100,000 women,1,300 are raped each year,according to
a 1999 study).The country also has the highest rate of
police killed. The grisly details of horrific crimes are a
mainstay for journalists,with equal space dedicated to the
swift hand of justice in the form of brutal police attacks.
The TV footage of the lifeless bodies of alleged
“robbers”may satiate public hunger for revenge.Yet
they drive repudiated young men, like Fe r n a n d o,
deeper into the bunkers of a violent masculinity.
Perhaps the situation will change as the socio-economic
landscape evolves. But so long as police attacks
continue and poverty prevails, young men will fin d
armoury in the cult of the hard body. ■
+ …
Both authors contributed to Changing Men in Southern
Africa, edited by Robert Morrell,University of Natal Press
and Zed Books, 2001.
Ihave spent nearly 250 shifts (each about 14 hours long) observing the
body language of the Soweto Flying Squad, an emergency-response unit of
250 policemen and a few women working in one of the most violent areas in
the country.
Of the 275 South African policemen killed in 1998, more than 60 died in
S o w e t o.Those who survive greatly rely on the hair-trigger control of just about
every muscle, from head to foot. Experience has taught them to avoid the
stereotypes of the macho cop, as one officer explains, “We’d be killed if we
did that shit.” The following scene underscores the powerful fluency of the
Flying Squad body language.
Driving through heavy traffic,the police car suddenly stops:in the next lane,
a group of seven or eight men are punching one another beside two taxis.
Another battle has broken out between two rival taxi companies.As the two
policemen get out of the car, a man at the centre of the fighting falls and is
k i c ked hard, the sound of boots thudding against flesh audible above the noise
of the gathering crowd.
The two policemen begin pushing back the attacke r s, when another taximan
suddenly shoves through the crowd to kick the already bleeding head of the
victim.A dozen taxis have stopped at the junction,passengers pointing and
shouting.
One of the policeman takes a step back from the standoff and casually
t a kes a cigarette from his top pocke t . He lights it, breathing in hard,wa t c h i n g
intently as his colleague stands face-to-face with the most aggressive
attacker. The former refuses to look up at this man,who is taller than he is.
Instead he squares his shoulders, using the muscles of his upper body to appear
l a r g e r. He then sways back an inch or two to look directly into the eyes of the
attacking taximan.
Using his body as armoury, he suddenly shouts a sound rather than a word and
the taximan fli n c h e s, jerking his head back. More than a hundred people are
fixated on the drama. The police wouldn’t have a chance if the crowd turned
against them.But the flinch of the taximan was crucial.
The other officer throws his cigarette away with an abruptness that spells
readiness to act. The two begin using their voices to push the crowds back.
Control has been established.The man on the ground drags himself into his
t a x i . He sits for a moment, slumped over the steering wheel, and smiles at the
police. ■
* Senior lecturer in history, Curtin University of Technology, Australia
J OAN WA R D R O P * : PATROLLING WITH SOWETO’S FLYING SQUA D
I sing the body
electric.
Walt Whitman,
American poet
(1819-1892)
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
MARTÍN GAMBAROTTA
POET AND JOURNALIST, AUTHOR OF PUNCTUM (LIBROS DE TIERRA FIRME, 1996)
Minding the m u s c l e t o n e
Argentine men used to earn their family’s keep and rule the domestic
roost. Severe recession has pushed some towards the bench press
2 . PASSING RITES
R
odolfo Fo g w i l l ,aged 59, is one of A r g e n t i n a ’s
best writers. Also a respected sociologist,
he served as a marketing advisor for many
leading companies and claims to have made
up to $30,000 a month in his days as a young
e x e c u t i v e. Yet he is anything but economically home
and dry in Buenos A i r e s.
Car companies and candy manufacturers—his
main clients—have dropped production by about 25
to 30 percent in recent years. Suddenly, Fogwill has
free time on his hands and a black cloud over his
h e a d . He has found two solutions: writing poetry and
intense exercise.“At least I am now producing some
muscle,” he says. “I could work for three pesos an
hour. But you set yourself a price. When you are not
paid that,you have time to spare.”
Clad in a track-suit, he demonstrates his latest
kick-boxing move before talking about his daily
exercise routine. “On a typical day, I walk two
kilometres after getting up and smoking a few
c i g a r e t t e s. Then I do an hour of work at a gym,
followed by push-ups and stretching for about 45
minutes.”
Fogwill may be relatively well-off, but his
quandary—and his muscular solutions—are far from
unique. For the last three years, Argentina has been
stuck in a recession. The turbulence in the local
economy came at a crucial time, just as the country
was trying to adapt to free market reforms. For the
p o c k e t s, the minds and the bodies of men, it has been
a time of harsh austerity and rebuilding.
“ N o r m a l l y, man is the provider in an
underdeveloped society’s handout of roles,” s a y s
labour lawyer Horacio Va l l a , 5 1 . “But what we
consider to be basic necessities in an urban society
have a degree of sophistication that is incompatible
with current salary and unemployment levels.”
Unemployment peaked at 18 percent in 1995.
Currently it stands at 14.7 percent, w h i l e
underemployment languishes at 9.3 percent according
to the national statistics bureau.
Precarious
identities
Browse through a newspaper and you can find the
human stories behind the cold fig u r e s. S t e w a r d e s s e s,
pilots and mechanics engaged in a labour confli c t
with the former state-run Aerolineas A r g e n t i n a s
recently spewed onto the main runway of the
Metropolitan A i r p o r t , outside Buenos A i r e s. A
struggle with riot police ensued. By the end of the
n i g h t , a pilot had a black eye and blood stains on the
gold bars of his blue uniform jacket.The pilot, with 22
years of service, was later interviewed on television.
This is the message beamed out on the evening news:
the country is hurting and it is grown men, those who
had a career and more mundane concerns only a
decade ago, who are taking the punches.
It used to be very different.According to Emilio
C a f a s s i , head of the sociology department at the
University of Buenos A i r e s, men formerly dominated
the country’s social life in a “classic Vi c t o r i a n
structure” until around the 1930s. Only in 1926, for
instance, was the woman formally allowed to work
without the permission of her husband or father.As
for the men,writer Luis Medrano speculated half a
century ago that they could be conveniently divided
into two classes: those who go to football matches and
those who go to horse races.
N o w, h o w e v e r, economic free-fall has brought
redundancies and a particular crisis for men,whose
“self-esteem is linked to institutional recognition,”
argues Cafassi.“Never in capitalism has there been
such a degree of social vulnerability.’’
For men trying to meet the standards of a highly
White-collar malaise: jobless lining up in Buenos Aires.
36 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
developed urban society, building muscle in the
gymnasium or elsewhere can come as a relief and
reassertion of their precarious identity. But it’s not
only men trapped in a situation of economic check-
mate who take to the weights.
Fabián Casas, a 36-year-old editor at El Gráfico,
the country’s leading sports magazine, claims that
the publication also has its share of economic tension.
Exercise is a vital part of his routine since he took the
job three years ago. Casas, who is single, talks about
pressure and a growing existential void.“If I didn’t
produce some muscle, I would
go nuts,” he says.
Others, who have lost their
steady jobs, simply refuse to be
absorbed by the market again.
Gustavo López, 4 0 , was laid off
two years ago from the power
utility he worked for in Bahía
B l a n c a , a port city of almost
300,000 inhabitants. “I went
from making 2,500 pesos a month to having no
income,” he says.
López used his severance pay to open a “cultural
c e n t r e ” in a downtown venue that was once a butcher’s
s h o p.Night activities include ethnic music concerts and
Indian food.“All the family helps out,” he says. But his
body also feels the strain.“Right now I’m tired because
the change from one activity to another is physically
d e m a n d i n g.” Only one thing remains as steady as
ever:playing football twice a week.
“Men are under double pressure, because they do
not meet demands due to unemployment, or because
the salary they make is insuffic i e n t . Some men are able
to respond, but without fully satisfying the
expectations women have of their role,”Valla says.
Besides losing their traditional role as family
b r e a d w i n n e r s, competition for employment from
women has soared. Cafassi reports that there are now
more female university students than male ones, w h i l e
the number of women who head households is growing.
“Masculine problems are
c h a n g i n g.Stress produced by auto
workers manning production lines
used to trigger sexual problems at
home.Today production lines are
s l o w e r,but the problems produced
by unemployment are more
fierce,” he adds.
Alejandro Belloni,3 6 ,was out
of work for over a year before his
sister found him a job as a hospital cleaner. He makes
1,50 pesos ($1.50) an hour, and works 12 hours a day,
six days a week. B e l l o n i , who lives with family, says he
felt the demands of what he described as a machista
society when he was out of work. “ For women it is
e a s i e r, but men are expected to give support.” He now
feels more comfortable when he dates women. B u t
habits change. When out of work, he used to enjoy
drinking beer with his friends at a corner kiosk.Now
he has quit drinking—and shed several kilograms of
weight. ■
“If I didn’t pro d u c e
some muscle,
I would go nuts.”
STÉPHANIE OLLIVIER
FREELANCE JOURNALIST BASED IN BEIJING
C h i n a ’s timid coming out
Psychiatrists no longer view homosexuality as a mental illness, while the
media is broaching the topic. But authorities prefer to keep the lid on a
subject that could spiral into a human rights debate
2 . PASSING RITES
“I
think of my homosexuality as a source of
c r e a t i v i t y,” says Cui Zi’en,with a cheeky
look in his eye.Few militant homosexuals
in China, such as this scriptwriter and
t e a c h e r,dare to go public.H o m o s e x u a l i t y
is not illegal, even though the law against “ s o r d i d ”
offences that bars sexual relations in public was long
used against homosexuals who met in parks.
The law was rescinded several years ago,but the
attitude of Chinese doctors is still ambiguous. S o c i a l
stability is cited as a reason for not treating sexuality
as a private matter. Homosexuality, with its power
to break up families and transmit A i d s, is therefore
seen as an illness.A handful of doctors, s o c i o l o g i s t s
and campaigners,h o w e v e r, are managing to drag the
debate onto more scientific territory.
Last A p r i l , the Chinese Psychiatrists’ A s s o c i a t i o n
removed homosexuality from its list of mental
i l l n e s s e s. “But it’s still seen as a psychological
d i s o r d e r,” says Cui Zi’en. “Psychiatrists have
r e c l a s s i fied it,which isn’t enough.” Some doctors,h e
s a y s, probably still want to “ c u r e ” h o m o s e x u a l s,
which only prolongs the distress of those who
“consider themselves abnormal.”
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 37
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Liu Dalin, a well-known sexologist, s a y s
homosexuality can be seen as criminal, an illness or
normal.“China is still at the illness stage,” he says.
“People still regard it as a problem.”
Rejecting the pleasure principle
Public opinion is an obstacle to any change.
Attitudes have been shaped for centuries by
Confucian morality and then communist puritanism.
For decades, individual pleasure—dismissed as
“bourgeois”— was beyond the pale. “ You just
couldn’t talk about sexuality,” says sociologist Li
Yinhe, who specializes in sexual behaviour.
Since the 1980s,h o w e v e r, individual freedom has
e x p a n d e d , especially in the big cities, and the
Chinese are once again learning how to listen to
their feelings. “But sexuality is still regarded as
simply procreation,” says Ye Guangwei,a volunteer
at an advice centre for homosexuals in Beijing.
“The idea of pleasure is poorly regarded.” All the
less so when it concerns homosexual pleasure, he
c o n t i n u e s :“A man who isn’t masculine is disdained.
And for him to take on a female role during a
sexual act is unthinkable and a disgrace in people’s
eyes.”
In Confucian tradition,a man’s job is to start a
family in order to produce male heirs who will
ensure the continued worship of the ancestors. N o t
s u r p r i s i n g l y,a large number of Chinese homosexuals
still marry to save appearances and lead clandestine
sex lives.
In cities, tradition does not hold such weight,
partly because of the government policy of the
one-child family, according to Li Yi n h e. When a
couple has a daughter, the family lineage is broken,
and it becomes impossible to respect tradition.
F u r t h e r m o r e, greater professional mobility also
allows young people to escape the pressure of their
parents.
The “comrades,” as Chinese homosexuals call
each other, think a change in media attitudes could
alter public opinion.After he appeared in a televised
debate broadcast by a provincial station, Cui Zi’en
received calls from mothers who said they had been
amazed he did not seem to be perverted or
unbalanced.
In recent years, local media have touched on the
s u b j e c t , but only timidly for fear of igniting the
s t a t e ’s wrath.“ We ’re not really a danger in the eyes
of the government,” says Ye Guangwei, “but it
prefers to stay in line with the moral convictions of
the majority.” To support a sexual minority would
risk extending debate to the slippery slope of human
rights in general.
Respect begins at home
The media prefer to ignore homosexuality so as
not to offend the authorities. They in turn avoid
disturbing public opinion,keeping prejudices well-
entrenched through lack of information. To break
this vicious circle,“we have our part to play too,” h e
says. “We have to teach people to like their own
bodies and to respect them before they can be liked
and respected by others.”
Many would simply like to be able to live openly
as homosexuals. “In the We s t , i t ’s frowned on to
criticize homosexuals and even more to make them
feel different,” says Cui Zi’en.“I can understand a
heterosexual being startled at seeing a very
effeminate man. Chinese society is changing, but
t h e r e ’ll always be people who’ll feel disgust, like they
might jump if they saw a snake.We’re not going to
tell them they have to start liking snakes, are we?”
■
CROSSING THE LINE
Released in 1999, Men and Women, directed by
Bingjian Liu, was the first Chinese film t h a t
depicted homo-
sexuals as normal
people living normal
lives. Cui Zi’en wrote
the script. “I wanted
to show how we live
day by day and to
suggest that
everyone can have a
homosexual side,”
he says.
The film is set in a
rapidly changing ur-
ban society where
different lifestyles
coexist. In this context, the line between male and
female sexual roles is blurred.“Encouraging people to
think in these terms could be more effective than
waving banners,” he says.
Homosexual characters in earlier Chinese films appear
as victims. In Chen Kaige’s Farewell my Concubine, for
example, a young actor with the Beijing Opera is
condemned to be a sexual plaything of a lustful
m a n d a r i n . Or else they try to understand their
“problem,” as shown in the confrontation between a
proclaimed homosexual and a policeman in Zhang
Yuan’s film East Palace, West Palace.
Is the vision of Cui Zi’en premature?  So far, the
authorities have not allowed his film to be shown in
China. ■
38 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
SOUMAYA NAAMANE GUESSOUS
MOROCCANSOCIOLOGIST, UNIVERSITYPROFESSOR , AUTHOR OF PRINTEMPSET AUTOMNE SEXUELS (EDDIF, 2000)
AND AU-DELÀ DE TOUTEPUDEUR, EDDIF, 1988.
The passing of bodily seasons
For Moroccan young women, sexual awakening rhymes with danger. In the
countryside, girls are often married off at 14 and deemed old by 30. But in
cities, the young are starting to hold their ground
2 . PASSING RITES
D
uring recent fieldwork in Bni Meskine, i n
southern Morocco,I felt disarmed,w o r t h l e s s
and at a loss before the cruelty of what
turned out to be a veritable slave market.
For the first time in my life, I lied to conduct
my study.My ploy: S a n a a ,one of my students, is seeking
to marry off her two brothers with 13- or 14-year-old girls.
As for myself,I’m supposedly looking for a spouse for my
u n c l e,widowed at 70.My goal: to prove that this market
indeed exists,and that parents in the countryside pay little
heed to the legal age of 15 for marrying their daughters.
In this region and many others, the s m a s y r a ,
brokers who supply city dwellers with child labour,a r e
also sought out to find potential brides. From one
home to the next,we witnessed scenes like these…
We are greeted by three women belonging to
different generations:the matriarch,her daughter-in-
law and her 14-year-old granddaughter. The young
girl busily skirts around us, wiping the table, putting
away our shoes, shaking the cushions. I observe her, a
budding beauty, her body charged with promise. I s
her father prepared to betroth her without a marriage
license? “Yes, he married the eldest when she was 14.
The girls have nothing to do. As soon as their zmane
(destiny) arrives, we marry them.” Then the paternal
uncle greets us.“ I ’ll give you 15 girls if you want.Th e y
are educated, never lift their eyes from the ground
nor raise a voice of complaint. Th e y ’ll put up with
anything without a whimper.”
Another home: the wife of the household greets us.
She is pregnant with her seventh child.“Choose the one
you like.They’ve all had the same education.All they
do is work. They never go out of the house. They get
pregnant on their wedding night.”
I felt like screaming at the thought that these girls
would be married so young, savagely deflowered and
left disgusted by the sexuality forced upon them. M e n
keep a close watch on their daughters.Their honour lies
in controlling the female body. Women uphold this
tradition by muzzling their own bodies which they
learn to do from puberty on. Female sexuality is
channeled by marrying off young nubile bodies. Such
dramatic practices are part and parcel of everyday
life in a countryside mired by poverty and isolation,
where nine out of ten women are illiterate.
Our research in Casablanca found that in cities,
puberty is no less of a painful experience. Young girls
are taught by their mothers,aunts and grandmothers an
outdated sex education revolving around taboos. Th e
young woman’s body beholds danger. Her sexuality
does not belong to her. She cannot be entrusted with
something so fragile yet potentially explosive, for it
can lead to her loss and that of her whole family. S o
every sexual drive must be stifle d .As one young woman
e x p l a i n e d ,“My mother controlled my movements. I was
told not to jump or to spread my legs for fear of losing
my virginity. I was terrified by my sexuality.”
Double
standards
While older women once went into shock when
they started bleeding unknowingly, the younger
generation is better informed about menstruation.
Yet they still suffer from a pervasive sense of anguish.
From the outset,teenagers live in
conflict with their bodies.
Menstrual blood is impure, d i r t y,
s h a m e f u l . “I learned that it was
h a r a m [a sin] to let anyone see the
blood because God punishes this
s e v e r e l y.” Menstruation provokes a
feeling of rejection of the body:“I
feel dirty, I no longer take care of
myself, I hate myself.”
There has been some progress
in the cities where the age of
marriage has been pushed back to
about 26 years old. S t i l l , s o c i e t y
strictly condemns extra-marital sex,
a taboo that in practice,only applies
to women. When one student told
me that girls who made love before
marriage were prostitutes, I asked,
“So are you a virgin?”I reminded
him that the proscription applied to
both sexes. D i s a r m e d , he replied,
“No! Religion applies to girls,
tradition to boys!”
Even though a Moroccan
woman can expect to live longer
than her husband to the ripe age of
7 0 , her femininity is ephemeral.
Society kills her sexuality
prematurely by imposing a “ s o c i a l A young bride in traditional dress.
© Sabine Weiss/Rapho, Paris 
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 39
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
a g e ” after which she is no longer considered seductive.
At 31,according to men,she is past the age of getting
married.At 40,she is old.A blossom barely in flower,
she becomes an elder in a body without promise.By the
time she reaches 47—the average age of menopause—
she no longer exists as a woman.She is banished to live
roughly 23 years within an asexual body.Amputated of
her femininity, she must grieve her feelings of desire
and seduction.
She renounces her sexual role and devotes herself
to playing mother and grandmother. Having put her
body at the service of her husband and procreation, s h e
can now only exist through a soul that has to be
p u r i fie d . Religion becomes her refuge, as if Islam
s t i fled desire. Illiterate older women may renounce
their bodies in this way,but young women are reacting
o t h e r w i s e. Even mothers are now denouncing
p r o c r e a t i o n .“I refuse to see my daughter live like me.
So many pregnancies take their toll. She has to
maintain her figure and stay beautiful,” says a woman
of 65. “I refuse to be like my mother,” chants the
younger generation. Indeed women today have an
average of three children,down from seven 40 years
ago.
Could this break the vicious circle? Yo u n g
women—48 percent of the Moroccan population is
under 20—are becoming emancipated,playing more
sport and keeping an eye on their figure. B e a u t y
cannons have changed, despite the pressure and
expectations of older generations.“A beautiful woman
must be well-endowed. To d a y, girls have no more
charm, they’re as thin as reeds,” laments an elderly
p e a s a n t .“ You can see their bones—they must prick in
bed.”
The divorce rate is rising among the young. It’s a
sad reality, but one which proves that this population
“is standing up for itself.” Traditions may still be
e n t r e n c h e d , but young women are cultivating body
and mind. Through education and work, they are
gaining their independence.“I’m not afraid of old age.
Unlike my mother I won’t let myself be treated like a
useless old thing.I earn a living and have interests,”s a y s
one young woman.“I don’t only exist as a wife and
mother. My life is in my hands.” ■
Life may be
short or long. 
It all depends on
how you live it. 
Paulo Coelho,
Brazilian writer
(1947-)
T
hat day will remain etched in my memory
f o r e v e r. At the time, in 1966, I was 12, m y
sister 10. Like every summer, we were
visiting our paternal grandparents in our
village 15 kilometres from Bamako in M a l i .
Early one morning, we went to see my aunt, m y
f a t h e r ’s sister, whom we were always happy to visit
because she spoiled us.
I didn’t suspect a thing. My aunt called me into
the bathroom. Several women jumped on me and
held me down. They spread my legs open. I was
s c r e a m i n g. I couldn’t see the knife but felt them
cutting me. I was crying as the blood flowed
e v e r y w h e r e. They said, “ D o n ’t cry, i t ’s shameful!
Yo u ’re a woman, what we’re doing to you is
n o t h i n g.”They started clapping.They dressed me in
a white skirt. No bandages, just something they had
prepared with shea oil and leaves. I left.It was my
little sister’s turn. I heard her crying and begging me
for help, and that hurt even more.
KHADI DIALLO
ACTIVIST FORTHE PARIS-BASED WOMEN’S GROUP FORTHE ABOLITION OF
SEXUAL MUTILATION (GAMS)
“ Taking the dress”
A Malian woman who underwent excision at the age of 12 recalls the
experience which led her to combat this ritual practice
2 . PASSING RITES
“We were betrayed.”
40 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
The excision was a plot.We were betrayed.We
were living in Senegal,where my father was a civil
s e r v a n t . My parents were educated people, t h e y
were against excision. But at that time, it was a
widespread practice in the countryside and city.
Most little girls were excised much younger than us,
and the occasion was followed by a party.We stayed
with our aunt for almost three
w e e k s. A woman she knew
helped us because we couldn’t
stand up by ourselves. It hurt so
much we avoided going to the
b a t h r o o m . Our mother cried
and kissed us the first time she
came to see us, but she couldn’t
do anything. In A f r i c a , t h e
f a t h e r ’s family decides whether
children live or die.
Meanwhile, we were given
our female education.We were
told that a woman must be strong, tough,secretive
and not too talkative. Sex was a taboo topic.
Mutilation never heals
I was filled with hatred and rage. I had not been
brought up with that mentality. But I was resigned,
despite the pain.I got married at 22.I never talked
about the feeling of being incomplete, of missing a
part of my body. Women were not allowed to
express desire or pleasure. I could only talk to close
friends about the fact that excision is not a wound
but a mutilation.A wound heals, but a mutilation
means disfig u r e m e n t . It means removing a part that
never grows back. When I had daughters of my
o w n , I told my husband that I did not want them to
be excised. He agreed. I protected them by not
sending them to visit Africa when they were little.
It was not a sacred or religious rite, but a ritual
p a s s a g e. There is an expression in Bambara that
says “taking the dress,”which means becoming a real
woman.Before excision,a girl is innocent,she can
walk around bare-chested or even naked. A f t e r
e x c i s i o n , she must keep her body covered. Th e
person who has his or her child excised does so
because that’s the way things have been for
g e n e r a t i o n s.They are afraid that evil will befall the
child if they don’t.They have always heard,“when
you have a daughter, you must have her excised so
that she can become a perfect woman.” But Islam
never said “excise your daughters,” even though
many people think the Koran orders them to do so.
Men invented excision to control women’s sexuality.
To be a real woman, her clitoris,which is considered
to represent a man’s sex, is removed. E x c i s e d
mummies dating back prior to the appearance of
Islam have been found.
African women have been denouncing excision
since 1924, but at that time they were considered
c r a z y. More recently,we have been lucky enough to
have support from European women and the media
to make ourselves heard.When I came to Fr a n c e, I
started campaigning with several organizations,
including GAMS (see box).To d a y,we are invited to
clinics and maternity wards to tell mothers that
excision is against the law. We campaign for
prevention in schools and with social workers. We
also see families individually.
P s y c h o l o g i c a l l y, i t ’s more
d i f ficult for girls born in Fr a n c e
to undergo excision.Those who
are 18 or 20 today will have or
have had problems during their
first sexual experience. Th e
men of my generation learned
to accept the unacceptable.B u t
t o d a y ’s boys will not want girls
who are undergoing excision
now and will be old enough to
marry around 2020. I know a
girl who had to leave her neighbourhood because
people made fun of her.
We are against excision in all its forms, even if
it takes place under anesthesia in the hospital.
Our campaign isn’t just against the pain at the
time of excision,but against the mutilation of our
bodies. ■
IMore than 130 million girls and women have undergone genital mutilation, according to
the World Health Organization (WHO), which estimates that another two million are at risk
every year.The mutilation (known as FGM) can take many forms but about 80 percent of cases
involve the removal of the clitoris and often the small lip-like structure surrounding the vulva .
The most extreme form is infib u l a t i o n : the external genitalia are partially or entirely removed
and the vaginal opening is stitched closed. FGM is concentrated in 28 African countries,
although a growing number of cases are being reported among immigrant groups in
E u r o p e,A u s t r a l i a , Canada and the U. S. Cases have also been reported in the Middle East and
Southeast Asia.
FGM is considered a human rights abuse by a growing international movement of NGOs and
UN agencies.These activists seek to eliminate the practice, not legitimate it on the grounds
of cultural or religious tradition. They also reject its medicalization in which health
professionals reduce the risk of infection.
The opposition is largely fuelled by African women like Mrs. Diallo, who volunteers with the
French section (GAMS) of the Inter-African Committee on Traditional Practices Affecting the
Health of Women and Children.Public awareness campaigns target communities, families and
health authorities, while efforts are underway to develop laws to ban and sanction the practice.
Some groups are also pushing for provisions to offer asylum to those at risk of mutilation in
their countries of origin. ■
WHEN T R A D I T I O N
BECOMES A B U S E
+ …
www.who.int/frh-whd/FGM/
www.rainbo.org
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 41
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
In our female education,
we were told that a
woman must be strong,
tough and not too
talkative. Sex was
a taboo topic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
Above:languishing in
Istanbul’s famed
Cagaloglu baths,
built in 1741 in baroque
style. The other two
photographs feature
the Yani Kaplica 
baths in Bursa,
northwest Turkey.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 43
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
© Ferando Molares/Panos Pictures, London
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
M
ust you live with the body you are born
with or can you remake it? We have
long been confronting this question.
Whether it be the removal of body parts
in religious practices (such as
c i r c u m c i s i o n ) , the surgeon’s ability to sculpt a chin or the
promise of geneticists to alter and improve bodies of the
f u t u r e.
This is the promise of innate malleability that we
increasingly take as a given in our world, whether in
Ve n e z u e l a , South Africa or Hollywood.And nowhere
is this desire for transformation more clearly seen
than in aesthetic surgery.
In the west and beyond,we believe that we have
the right not only to remake our bodies, but to control
the process. Indeed the patients of aesthetic surgery are
the ideal patients of modern medical systems.They are
exemplars of autonomy, who question their doctors to
explore their treatment options. Breast implants, f a c e -
lifts and tummy tucks were not pushed upon people by
the medical profession or industry. Virtually every
procedure in cosmetic surgery has been in response to
popular demand.
This desire for individual transformation is a
distinctly western notion. It stems back to the
Enlightenment ideology (beginning in the 17t h
century) that each individual could remake him or
herself in the pursuit of happiness. I n d e e d , it is
remarkable how often aesthetic surgeons cite
“ h a p p i n e s s ” as the goal of their procedures.They have
a utilitarian notion like that espoused by John Stuart
Mill (1806-73): the active citizen, working for progress,
is a happy one.
This idea took on biological dimensions once
surgeons were able to reduce their patients’ pain and
risk of infection. The anesthesia and antisepsis
originally developed by military doctors to heal battle
wounds were quickly picked up by surgeons seeking
to correct their patients’ birth defects and then fulfill
their desires. “ H a p p i n e s s ” in aesthetic surgery lay
i n the individual’s autonomy to transform him- or
herself.
I n d e e d , by the late 19th century, the Enlightenment
notion of self-improvement had moved from the
b a t t l e field of liberalism to the laboratories and surgical
t h e a t r e s.The destabilization experienced and repressed
during the American and French revolutions re-
emerged in a sea change in imagining who we are and
what our bodies are. The political “unhappiness” of
class and poverty, which led to the storming of the
B a s t i l l e, was experienced as “ u n h a p p i n e s s ”within the
body. Before, it was revolutionary change that would
cure the body;later, it was the cure of the individual.
The hygiene of the body thus became the hygiene
of the spirit and that of the state. By removing
“ugliness,” the aesthetic surgeon provided a type of
surgical eugenics,a means of improving the individual
and ultimately the state. Aesthetic surgery could
transform the body into one that fulfilled the
expectations of a new society and could change with
them.
“Vanishing” into society
So by the turn of the 20thcentury, it was possible
to start altering the body in order to become a “real”
citizen in a foreign or hostile land.In the United States,
for example, light-skinned African-Americans had
their lips thinned and their noses rebuilt so that they
could cross the colour line.And if they were too dark,
they had their skin lightened. In New Yo r k , I r i s h
immigrants had their “pug noses” transformed into
“English noses” and their ears pinned back so that
this sign of their “degenerate Irish nature” vanished
and they could “pass”as American.
In Berlin there was Jacques Joseph (1865-1934), a
highly acculturated young German Jewish surgeon.
Born Jakob Joseph, he altered his too Jewish name
while studying medicine at university, where he joined
a dueling fraternity and bore the scars with pride. For
some Jews like Jo s e p h , a dueling scar marked the
socially healthy individual in German society.But at the
very close of the 19t h c e n t u r y, after Joseph left
u n i v e r s i t y, Jewish men were excluded from the
Christian dueling fraternities: they were considered
different and thus dishonourable. For a Jew to bear a
facial scar was to hide his sickly essence from the
m a i n s t r e a m .So Joseph enabled his Jewish compatriots
to “ v a n i s h ” in society. He developed the first procedure
of reducing the size and shape of the “Jewish”nose.
SANDER L. GILMAN
PROFESSOR IN HUMAN BIOLOGY AT THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGOAND AUTHOR
OR EDITOR OF OVER 50 BOOKS INCLUDING, MAKING THE BODY BEAUTIFUL: A
CULTURAL HISTORY OF AESTHETIC SURGERY (PRINCETON, 1999)
I l l u s i o n s, scalpels and
s t e re o t y p e s
By sculpting a chin or enlarging a breast, aesthetic surgeons appear
to be operating on the body. But we know better: they are reshaping
our fantasies of ourselves 
3 . ESCAPING DESTINY
44 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
P re c u rsor Jacques Joseph.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 45
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
In January 1898, a 28-year-old man came to Jo s e p h ,
complaining that “his nose was the source of
considerable annoyance.Wherever he went,e v e r y b o d y
stared at him...”Joseph took the young man’s case and
proceeded to perform his first reduction rhinoplasty,
cutting through the skin of the nose to reduce its size
and alter its shape by chipping away the bone and
removing the cartilage. On May 11,1898 he reported
on this operation before the Berlin Medical Society.H e
provided a detailed “ s c i e n t i fic ” rationale for performing
a medical procedure on an otherwise completely
healthy individual: “ The depressed attitude of the
patient subsided completely. He is happy to move
around unnoticed.” The patient was cured of the
“disease”of “nostrility.”Yet Joseph was not satisfied.
T h e
procedure left small scars that revealed the
inauthencity of the body.
On April 19, 1904 Joseph undertook another
procedure entirely within the nose.No scars remained
to mark the individual. Joseph had learned that only
(in)visibility left his patients “happy.” They “passed”
into German society. They desired to forget their
b o d i e s, to become one with those they imagined had no
worries about the acceptability of their features.
This is the essence of “ p a s s i n g ” and it sets the
model for a radical rethinking of how we imagine our
b o d i e s. It is the model of malleability that we find in late
19thcentury Meiji Japan when it opened to the west.
German physicians started modern medical schools
and the Japanese began to remake themselves to
approximate western images of beauty. The eyelids
became double and the nose larger.They were passing
into the world of the modern.
Promise or curse?
By the 1970s in the United States, Vi e t n a m e s e
Americans were undergoing the same sets of operations.
N o w, they are “ p a s s i n g ” into a modern, global world of
pan-Asian appearance. They give their 16-year- o l d
daughters the gift of aesthetic surgery just as the
American Jews on Long Island had done in the 1950s.
Today Japanese girls are having breast implants at the
age of 13—before their bodies have fully developed—
to “pass”into the teen-world of global pop-stars.
We “pass” to regain control of ourselves and to
efface that which is seen (we believe) as different.
Aesthetic surgery allows relief from imagining oneself
as different. The happiness of the patient lies in
achieving his or her fantasy of being in control, r a t h e r
than in the control of the observer on the street (who
classifies people according to their physical
a p p e a r a n c e ) . The decision to remake oneself is not
vain,nor is it morally wrong. Our claim of autonomy
can and does make people happy.
This is an illusionary but necessary claim of
happiness.The fantasy of “passing,” unlike the fantasy
of controlling the world, focuses on a single, l i m i t e d
aspect—a nose too large, hair too sparse, a breast too
small.Changing that has symbolic significance for the
individual—for the body that we change is symbolic, n o t
real. It may seem that surgeons are operating on the
material of the body, but they (and we) know better: t h e y
are reshaping our fantasies of ourselves.The new nose
may resolve those fantasies or may lead us to demand
even more proof of our control over our bodies. But the
vocabulary of images is always shifting.We shall remake
o u r s e l v e s. Into what remains to be seen. Such is the
promise and the curse of the modern world. ■
“The depressed attitude of the patient subsided
completely,” reported the surgeon,
following an operation to reduce the size
of the man’s nose in the early 1900s.
Anatomy is
destiny.
Sigmund Freud, 
Austrian neurologist and
father of psychonalysis
(1856-1939) 
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
A
few statistics are sometimes more telling
than heavyweight sociological analysis.
Venezuela has won more international
beauty contests than any other country
in the past 50 years, including five Miss
World titles, four Miss Universes and countless other
crowns and prizes. This is no accident: the record is
proof in Venezuela and elsewhere in Latin A m e r i c a
of some very deep social trends. Like in Brazil,the
o f ficial line is that Venezuela is a tolerant multiracial
country. But under the surface lies a subtle racism
against the descendants of black slaves. It is
expressed by an ideal of beauty which vaunts white
skin,blonde hair and light-coloured eyes.
“ They come to my clinic wanting thinner noses,
slightly fuller lips, big breasts, firm bottoms and
above all slimness—they all want to be slimmer,”
says Dr Pedro Meneses, a member of the
Venezuelan Plastic Surgery Association.
Beauty in Venezuela has become a social value
that often defines success or failure, personally and
professionally. It is a value that sits atop the many
other conventions demarcating the role of the
woman in a society that has yet to accept various key
feminist principles.
Torn between racism and machismo, m a n y
women regard beauty as an efficient way to leap
upwards through the social ranks and often the
only way to live.
The cult of beauty in Venezuela explains the
country’s huge boom in cosmetic surgery over the
past decade. There are no official figures, but the
reality is probably similar to that described by the
American Association of Plastic and Reconstructive
Surgery (AAPRS),which reports that the number
of people seeking cosmetic surgery has risen by
6 0 percent in the past two years. Between 1992 and
1 9 9 8 , the association says, the most popular
operations were liposculpture (up 264 percent),
breast enlargement through implants (up 306
percent),face lifts and nose jobs.
Beauty budgets
Notions of beauty, h o w e v e r, are constantly
changing. “The ideal for the last decade has come
from the United States, which is only two hours by
plane from Ve n e z u e l a ,” says Meneses. “ Th e
difference is that our women are not blonde and
b l u e - e y e d ,yet they struggle to make their bodies and
features resemble this white ideal. I ’ve never
operated on a white woman who wanted a broader
nose so she could look more like a black woman. I t
always goes in the other direction.”
Despite the country’s vast oil wealth,70 percent
of Venezuelans live in poverty. But when it’s a
matter of looking good, no expense is spared. A
1999 study by the U.S. market research firm Roper
Starch Worldwide showed that Venezuelans spend
a fifth of their income on personal grooming and
beauty products.
Breast surgery, one of the most common
o p e r a t i o n s, costs between $1,000 and $3,500 for
each implant.Given the overriding importance of
appearing and feeling attractive, even women from
the poorer end of society manage to find the money
needed.
RAKEL SOSA
VENEZUELAN JOURNALIST
Under the sun,
under the knife
Venezuela may be in the economic doldrums, but cosmetic surgery
is booming, highlighting the power of hidden racial discrimination and
the ever-present North American concept of beauty
3 . ESCAPING DESTINY
Looking good, the first step toward feeling good.
46 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
More and more women between 17 and 35 are
seeking not only slimmer noses and bigger breasts,
but also different shaped bodies. “They resort to
surgery because they feel socially rejected or aren’t
s a t i s fied with their image,”says Dr Alberto Salinas,
who has been operating on stomachs for more than
15 years and is one of the country’s few experts in
the field. He reduces the size of a stomach so the
patient eats less and gets thinner.“Half my patients
d o n ’t want to feel better, they just want to look
better,” he says.
Images of success
Although they are not fat,many teenage girls are
referred to his surgery for psychological reasons.
“ The social pressure is so strong that these kids
swallow a box of diuretic pills and a box of laxatives
every day,” says Salinas. “When they’re doing this
and risking addiction to medication, I prefer to
operate.”
Many professional people, m e a n w h i l e, turn to
the operating table in the hope of improving their
social image and self-esteem. Morelia Pelayo, a
successful dentist, says the breast operation she had
a few years ago changed her life: “ I ’ve always
regarded myself as a successful woman personally
and professionally. But I had a complex about the
size of my breasts. Since the operation, I ’ve dressed
d i f f e r e n t l y. Because this is a Caribbean country
with a lot of sunshine, I can now show off my fig u r e
to more effect and wear dresses with a lower
neckline.”
She nevertheless admits to being pushed to the
big decision by the subliminal effects of television
a d v e r t i s i n g.“All the women you see there have big
breasts and bottoms, spectacular bodies and look
beautiful and successful.It’s natural to want to be
like them,” she says.
Amid this confusion between being and
appearing, the fascination of Venezuelans for the
quick and drastic changes the surgeon’s knife can
bring is starting to become a cultural trait—
imported from abroad,yet strong enough to change
the very nature of Venezuelan society. ■
My nose is huge!
Vile snub-nose,
let me inform you
that I am proud
of such an
appendange,
since a big nose
is the proper 
sign of a friendly,
good, courteous,
witty, liberal and
brave man, 
such as I am.
From Cyrano de Bergerac, by
Edmond Rostand, French
playwright 
(1868-1918)
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 47
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
W
hen I was young I used to think that
most people were beautiful. Th i s
belief does not reflect an excessively
benevolent view of humanity, o n l y
the fact that I am blind. I assumed
that the majority of people around me must be
beautiful because I could see nothing wrong with
t h e m . But to have nothing wrong is to be merely
a v e r a g e,o r d i n a r y,p l a i n .Beauty is rare,and like most
rare things, desirable and precious.
Although I still don’t know what beauty looks
like, I now know a lot about it; at least I know the
things people say. I gather that youth is generally
assumed to be more beautiful than age, and that
regular features and symmetrical forms are prized.
And the eyes are always crucial, always the focal
point of the ideal look.But it is not enough just to
have youth, symmetrical proportions and lovely
e y e s. Every culture in every age admires certain
traits and disparages others. Particular body types
and body parts are esteemed; the size and shape of
facial features, and the colour of skin, hair and eyes
are all assigned relative values.An American beauty
today might have less appeal in A s i a , and probably
would have been considered too thin a century ago.
Even within the same culture,individual preferences
play a role. On numerous occasions I have heard
friends debate the relative beauty of common
acquaintances and public figures, and have always
been struck by how rarely everyone agrees.
Beauty is easy to recognize and hard to define.
People spend a lot of time talking about it, and a lot
of money and energy trying to achieve it.And the
GEORGINA KLEEGE
AMERICAN AUTHOR BASED IN NEW YORKWHOSE MOST RECENT BOOK IS A
COLLECTION OF AUTOBIOGRAPHICAL ESSAYS TITLED, SIGHT UNSEEN (YALE UP,
1999)
Beauty and the blind
A blind writer offers a piercing look at our penchant for staring at
“beautiful people” and wonders why we so rarely agree on who 
belongs to this club
3 . ESCAPING DESTINY
Reading society’s gaze.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
blind are not exempt . From childhood we, and our
caretakers, are bombarded with advice about the
need for good grooming,physical fitness and tasteful
a t t i r e. But for us the goal is not merely to make the
most of whatever attractions we might possess, b u t
to make ourselves visually appealing to others in
order to dispel the expectation that the blind are
always indigent and helpless. In other words,we are
encouraged not to become more beautiful, but to
look less blind. I recognize that new clothes or a new
haircut will make me feel good about myself. This
will show in my face and may counteract the
discomfort my blindness rouses
in others.
Inviting attention
S t i l l , in a world where
the vast majority of the
blind are
u n d e r e d u c a t e d
and under-
e m p l o y e d , I
think that
p e r s o n a l
a p p e a r a n c e
should be t h e
least of our
w o r r i e s. All the
advice we
r e c e i v e a b o u t
our looks only
r e i n f o r c e s the idea that blindness
is unsightly, best kept concealed in
homes and institutions.
Once I met a blind man who
always wore extremely vivid colours,
school bus yellow, safety orange,
electric green. I knew this because,
like many blind people, I have
some residual vision, i n c l u d i n g
colour perception. This man
however was totally sightless, with
no direct experience of the colours
he wore. It was his mother who
chose them for him when he was a
child so he would be more visible to motorists.As an
adult he continued the practice because,as he said,
“if people are going to stare anyway, I might as
well make it worth their while.”
It is no secret to the blind that people stare at us.
We can hear the hush that comes over a room when
we enter. We can feel heads turn, then turn away,
then turn back to stare. People believe they can
stare at us with impunity because we cannot see
their fixed gaze and thus will not be offended by
their scrutiny. People also stare at the beautiful,
and in a sense get away with it, because beautiful
people seem to invite the attention.Does this mean
that the blind are beautiful? 
Certainly, blind women in movies are usually
b e a u t i f u l :Audrey Hepburn in Wait Until Dark a n d
Uma Thurman in Jennifer Eight, to name only two
e x a m p l e s.But their friends seem to feel that beauty
is wasted on the blind woman because she is so
unconscious of it.She cannot see her reflection in the
mirror or the impact her appearance has on others,
so her beauty is somehow muted or effaced. True
b e a u t y, at least in movies, is not merely on the
surface but is enhanced and magnified by an inner
awareness of others’ admiring gaze.
In fact, I have observed that people have a way
of letting me know they’re beautiful even though I
c a n ’t see them. They project a self-assurance
that shows they have always been
accustomed to attention and favourable
t r e a t m e n t .This quality does not feel
the same as vanity or arrogance; I
have met beauties who were
quite modest. They do not
necessarily take credit for
their beauty,but bear it with
the good grace of the
recipient of a surprise gift.
Nature’s freaks
S t i l l , beauty remains a mystery
to me.A person can have all the
prescribed characteristics and
still not be beautiful. Beauty
requires something extra, a n
element of surprise, even
n e a r- v i o l e n c e. B e a u t y
arrests the gaze,
catches the breath
and stops the
h e a r t . Beauty is
an anomaly, a n
improbable freak
of nature that so
many idealized
qualities should
occur in a single
i n d i v i d u a l .
Beautiful people complain that potential friends
a n d l o v e r s are intimidated by their looks and that
potential employers doubt their intelligence.
They should spend more time with the blind
because we have much in common.We too know
what it’s like to create a sensation when we walk
down the street. We know how it feels to be
judged for our appearance alone. And while we
cannot display the admiring gazes the beautiful
have come to expect, we also will not detect the
pimples and wrinkles they fear will spoil their
b e a u t y.And our view of them will remain constant
long after the rest of the world tells them they’r e
The timeless beauty of Queen Nefertiti,
whose name means
“the beautiful-one-is-come.”
© Grantz-Giraudon/Paris, Agyptisches
Museum,Berlin
48 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
D
uring the summer of 1998,I was sitting at a
sidewalk cafe in downtown Sao Paulo with
Laudiceia da Silva,who had just requested
a legal investigation into the large public
hospital where she had “ l o s t ” a kidney
during an operation to remove an ovarian cy s t .
The young woman’s family doctor had discovered
the kidney was missing during an examination soon
after surgery.When confronted with the information,
the hospital representative told a highly improbable
s t o r y : that Laudiceia’s missing kidney had been
embedded in the large “mass” around her cyst. The
h o s p i t a l , h o w e v e r, refused to produce either their
medical records or the evidence—the diseased ovary
and the kidney had been “ d i s c a r d e d ,” she was told.To
make matters worse, L a u d i c e i a ’s brother had been
killed in a random act of urban violence several weeks
earlier, and the family had arrived at the hospital too
late to stop his organs being removed on the basis of
Brazil’s new “presumed  consent”law.
“Poor people like ourselves are losing our organs
to the state, one by one,” Laudiceia said angrily.
“Follow the bodies”
Hers is but one of several credible stories of
“kidney theft” that anthropologist Lawrence Cohen
and I have encountered in South America,India and
Bangladesh as part of our work for the Berkeley
Organs Wa t c h , an independent human rights
organization seeking to investigate allegations of
medical abuse in the harvesting, distribution and
transplantation of organs.
The project stems from experience on a prestigious
international taskforce set up to investigate the organ
trade and develop ethical guidelines to prevent abuses.
Soon after reaching the conclusion that the trade was
far more extensive than previously thought, t h e
Bellagio taskforce was disbanded.In the absence of any
other institution of its kind, Organs Watch was
conceived as a stop-gap measure, offering a frontline
response to reports of illegal organ and tissue sales or
theft anywhere in the world.
Our simple mandate is to “follow the bodies.”We
follow transplant patients from dialysis clinics to
s u r g e r y, and donor bodies from township shabeens
[bars] to police stations and public mortuaries and
from there to the various eye banks, medical clinics and
research laboratories where their parts are harvested
and redistributed.At times, the surgery theatres feel
more like theatres of the absurd, as a few scenes
plucked from our fieldwork will show.
In a Chennai (Madras) slum in South India, my
colleague Lawrence Cohen met five local women,
each of whom had sold a kidney for 32,500 rupees
(about $1,200 in 1999). Each had undergone their
operation at the clinic of D r. K . C.R e d d y, I n d i a ’s most
outspoken advocate of the individual right to sell a
k i d n e y. Unlike the more seedy “organs bazaars” o f
B o m b a y, D r. Reddy prides himself on running an
exemplary clinic: his kidney sellers are carefully
screened, fully informed about the medical risks and
provided with free health care at his clinic for two
NANCY SCHEPER-HUGHES
MEDICALANTHROPOLOGIST
AT THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, BERKELEY
The organ of last re s o r t
Modern medicine has given rise to a booming trade between poor and
rich countries—the trade in human organs. But what of the bodies that
are being plundered?
3 . ESCAPING DESTINY
A woman reveals a scar left after her husband’s kidney was re
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 51
years after kidney removal. The women Cohen
interviewed were mostly low-paid domestic workers
with husbands in trouble or in debt.The kidney sale was
usually preceded by a financial crisis.Did the sale make
a difference to their lives,Cohen asked.Ye s, for a time,
but the money was soon swallowed by the usurious
interest charged by the local money lenders. Wo u l d
they do it again if they could? Ye s, the women answered.
Several months later, I sat next to Rosemary
Sitsheshe at her home in  Guguletu township outside
Cape To w n , South A f r i c a . Her only son, 1 7 - y e a r- o l d
Andrew, had been caught in the crossfire of township
gang warfare just before the end of apartheid.He died
of a chest wound under police surveillance. The next
day Rosemary went to the local police mortuary to
claim his body, but officials turned her away. Two days
l a t e r, when the family was finally allowed to view
Andrew’s body, they were shocked:the blanket over it
was covered with blood and there were two deep holes
on either side of his forehead. Rosemary protested,
saying he had been killed by a single, clean bullet to his
c h e s t .The state pathologist treated her and her husband
abusively.
L a t e r, accompanied by her own private pathologist
paid for by the African National Congress, Rosemary
learned at the morgue that her son’s eyes had been
removed and that inside his abdominal cavity the organs
had all been severed and carefully replaced.“But were
those my son’s organs?”she asked.“I know my son’s
eyes but not the colour or shape of his heart or kidneys.”
At the local eye bank, Rosemary was told that her son’s
corneas had been “ s h a v e d ” and given to two “ l u c k y
p a t i e n t s.” The remains of A n d r e w ’s eyes were being
kept in the refrigerator and the director refused to
return them to Rosemary for burial.
“Although my son is dead and buried,” she said,“ i s
it good that his flesh is here, t h e r e,and everywhere, a n d
that parts of his body are still floating around? Must we
Africans be stripped of every comfort?” R o s e m a r y
Sitsheshe has since taken her complaint against the
police mortuary and eye bank to South Africa’s Truth
and Reconciliation Commission. She asked that her
case be treated as one example of a practice that was
widespread in police mortuaries under apartheid and
which continues in some instances.
Transplant tourism
In the most bizarre fieldwork expedition of my
c a r e e r, I went under cover to the grounds of Montes de
Oca state mental asylum in the province of Buenos
Aires in January 2000, accompanied by a private
detective. We went there to see what, if anything, we
could discover about persistent reports of blood, t i s s u e,
and organ stealing from the bodies of profoundly
mentally retarded, but otherwise physically healthy,
inmates. The reports first surfaced in the early 1990s
following the “ d i s a p p e a r a n c e ” of a young psychiatrist,
D r. G u b i l e o, who had lived on the grounds of the
i n s t i t u t i o n . She was apparently on the verge of
revealing the illicit practices by the director of the
a s y l u m . A court-ordered search of the grounds of
Montes de Oca did not recover the remains of Dr.
Gubileo, but did recover a few bodies of unidentified
missing patients.
The only witnesses to the doctor’s kidnapping were
two asylum patients, who said they saw her being
pushed into the back of a van belonging to the asylum.
But declared mentally incompetent, the witnesses could
not give testimony in court. The allegations of other
nefarious goings-on at Montes de Oca led,ultimately,
to the arrest of the medical director, followed by his
unexplained death in a prison cell the day before he was
to give testimony in court.The case was then closed.
Human strip mining of the dead for usable parts is
not limited to former police states in South A f r i c a ,
B r a z i l , and A r g e n t i n a . Similar practices can be found in
one of the wealthiest communities of the United States.
In the fall of 1999,I sat in a diner in Hollywood with
J i m C. , notorious “organs broker” who solicited
international buyers and sellers from his home.“ Th e r e ’s
no reason for anyone to die in this country while waiting
for a heart or a kidney to materialize.There are plenty
of spare organs to be had in other parts of the world.”
Though Jim is operating in a grey netherworld, h e
insists that what he does is not illegal.“Don’t think of
me as an outlaw,” he said.“ Think of me as a new version
of the old-fashioned marriage broker. I locate and
match up people in need.”
Organ transactions today are a blend of altruism
and commerce; of science, m a g i c, and sorcery; o f
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
moved without his consent in a private clinic in Bangalore, India.
The quality,
not the longevity
of one’s life,
is what’s
important.
Martin Luther King,
U.S. civil rights leader (1929-
1968)
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
52 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
voluntarism and coercion;of gift,barter, and theft.In
general, the organs flow from South to North, from
poor to rich, from black and brown to white, and from
female to male bodies. To d a y, affluent transplant
tourists can travel to select medical sites in Turkey,
Eastern Europe,C u b a , Germany and the United States
in search of transplants that they cannot arrange
quickly or safely enough at home.These special clinics
can resemble four-star hotels or even as in Cuba,
health spas for the rich and famous.
Israel has recently become something of a pariah in
the transplant world. Without a strong culture of organ
donation and under the pressure of angry transplant
c a n d i d a t e s, the Ministry of Health has refused to crack
down on the country’s multi-million dollar business
in transplant tourism that arranges junkets from dialysis
clinics in Jerusalem and Tel Aviv to medical centres in
Europe and the United States.
“ Why should we Israelis be made to travel to third
world clinics to get the kidneys we need to survive
from the bodies of peasants, s o l d i e r s, or guest workers
who may be in worse physical shape than ourselves?”
a 71-year-old “kidney buyer”
from Tel Aviv asked me
rhetorically. “Organs should be
seen as a human,not as a national
r e s o u r c e.” It was good to see
“Av i r h a m ,”an elderly gentleman,
alive and happy with h i s
revitalizing 22-year-old “ p e a s a n t ”
k i d n e y.And his living donor? “A
p e a s a n t , without anything!” h e
replied.“Do you have any idea
what $1,000, let alone $5,000
means in the life of a peasant?”
For most bio-ethicists, the “slippery slope” i n
transplant medicine begins with the emergence of a
black market in organs and tissue sales. For the
anthropologist,it emerges much earlier:the first time
a frail and ailing human looks at another living person
and realizes that inside that other body is something
that can prolong his or her life.The desire is articulated:
“I want that; I need that even more than you.” I n
terms of transplants, the kidney has emerged as the
ultimate fetish,promising to satisfy the most basic of
human desires—that for life, vitality and élan.
The sale of human organs and tissues requires that
certain disadvantaged  individuals and populations have
been reduced to the role of “suppliers.” It is a scenario
in which bodies are dismembered, t r a n s p o r t e d ,p r o c e s s e d
and sold in the interests of a more socially advantaged
population of organ and tissue receivers. I use the word
“fetish”advisedly to conjure up the displaced magical
energy that is invested in the strangely animate kidney.
Avirham,who flew from Jerusalem to Georgia for his
k i d n e y, explained why he would never tolerate a
donation from a corpse:“ That kidney is practically dead.
It was probably pinned down under the wheels of a car
for several hours. . . I was able to see my donor. He was
young, healthy, strong. Just what I was hoping for.”
In Brazil,the refusal of a corpse’s kidney was just
as virulent. A surgeon  in the area of Copacabana
Beach said that most of his patients refuse to consider
an organ from an “ a n o n y m o u s ” dead person. “ M y
patients do not trust the public health system.They fear
that the organ will come to them full of pollutants.”Th e
ultimate fetish is the idea of “ l i f e ” itself as an object of
m a n i p u l a t i o n . This fetishization of life—to be
p r e s e r v e d , prolonged and enhanced at almost any
cost—erases any possibility of a social ethic. O f t e n
when I speak of troubling issues in organs
p r o c u r e m e n t , I am accused of “taking a chance for
l i f e ”away from someone.But I am trying to underscore
that there is another “body”of patients whose needs
are being ignored or violated.
Notions of bodily autonomy and integrity are
almost universally shared today. They lie behind
patients’ rights movements, the demands of the
wretchedly poor for dignified burial and popular
resistance to “presumed consent” l a w s. But for some of
those living on the margins of the global economy,
the possibility of selling an organ
seems like an act of
e m p o w e r m e n t .“I prefer to sell it
[my body] myself rather than to
let the state get it,” was a
sentiment frequently expressed
by shantytown residents in urban
Brazil.
In fact, it is in the West where
the values of bodily autonomy
and integrity are most under
a s s a u l t .As commercialization has
entered almost every sphere of life—from markets in
“beauty queen” ova and “genius sperm”—those in the
North cannot claim any moral high ground. M e a n w h i l e,
the new constitutions and bills of rights adopted by
democratic Brazil and post-apartheid South Africa are
far more developed than “ o u r s ” in recognizing human
rights to bodily autonomy and integrity.
Organs Watch is seeking assurances that transplant
practices include attention to the needs and wishes of
d o n o r s, both living and dead. We ask that surgeons pay
close attention to where organs have come from and
the manner in which they were procured. We want
the “risks”and “benefits”of organ transplant surgery
to be more equally distributed among and within
nations, and among ethnic groups, genders and social
classes. Finally, we want assurances that the so called
“gift of life” never deteriorates into a
“theftof life.” ■
+ …
Organs Watch website at:
http://sunsite.berkeley.edu/biotech/organswatch/
Be quiet,
be pure,
toil not
your body,
perturb not
your vital
essence,
and you will
live forever.
Chuang-tzu,
Chinese philosopher
(350-275 B.C.)
In terms of tra n s p l a n t s,
the kidney has emerg e d
as the ultimate fetish,
p romising to satisfy the
most basic of human desire s
—that for life, vitality and élan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
A
mong the most important questions still
facing human enquiry are those about
the mind and its place in nature.What is
m i n d , and what is it relation to body?
How should we best understand our
common sense concepts of such mental phenomena
as belief, d e s i r e, i n t e n t i o n , e m o t i o n , reason and
memory? How does the grey matter of the brain
give rise to our rich and vivid experiences of colour,
s o u n d ,t e x t u r e, taste and smell?
Discussion of the mind-body problem was given
an especially sharp form by Descartes. He argued
that everything that exists falls under the heading
either of material substance or mental substance,
where “ s u b s t a n c e ” is a technical term denoting the
most basic kind of existing stuff. He defined the
essence of matter as occupancy of space, and the
essence of mind as thought. But by thus making
matter and mind so different, he raised the
seemingly insuperable problem of how they interact.
How does a bodily event like pricking oneself result
in the mental event of feeling pain? How does the
mental event of thinking “ i t ’s time to get up” c a u s e
the bodily event of rising from bed? 
Descartes himself did not have an answer, and
his successors had to resort to heroic solutions to the
problem his theory had bequeathed.Their strategy
was to accept dualism but to argue that mind and
matter do not in fact interact,their appearance of
doing so being the result of the hidden action of
G o d .Thus for Leibniz,God acted like a clockmaker,
setting the mental and material realms going in
exact unison at the universe’s beginning so that
they thereafter act in parallel.
A much more plausible alternative, h o w e v e r, i s
m o n i s m : n a m e l y, the view that there is only one
s u b s t a n c e.Three possibilities rise to the fore. One is
that there is only matter.The second is that there is
only mind. The third is that there is a neutral
substance which gives rise to mind and matter.Each 
of the three has had proponents but it is the first
option—the reduction or annexation of all mental
phenomena to matter—which has been most 
influential.
One materialist approach is the “ i d e n t i t y
t h e o r y,”which asserts that mental states are literally
identical with states or processes in the brain. In its
earliest form, it asserted that types of mental
phenomena are nothing other than types of brain
o c c u r r e n c e s, but this was quickly seen to be too
s w e e p i n g,for a particular mental event (e. g.a mental
image of the Eiffel tower) might in my brain activate
one set of cells, while in yours another.
A football match between
sociologists and physicists
On the basis of this theory, a number of
philosophers currently maintain that as
neuroscience advances, we will be able to eliminate
the old-fashioned and imprecise mental vocabulary
we standardly use. Research in neurology and
cognitive science have built an overwhelming case
for accepting a very intimate relation between
mental and neurological phenomena.
Neuroscientists now have highly detailed empirical
knowledge of brain function and its relation to
mental activity, and are able to locate the seat of
many conscious processes in precisely defined brain
structures.
But these advances only serve to correlate brain
activity with mental occurences; they do not explain
how the former actually produces the latter. Given
the persistent difficulties in identifying that relation
precisely, various strategies are proposed.One is to
accept that our ways of talking about mental and
physical phenomena are irreducibly different,even
A.C. GRAYLING
READER IN PHILOSOPHY, BIRKBECK COLLEGE,
UNIVERSITY OF LONDON
The k n o t
in the b ra i n
Philosophers since Descartes have
striven to understand the
connections between the material
world, the body and the mind.
Have brain scans brought us to the
verge of an answer?
3 . ESCAPING DESTINY
Science is piercing the mystery of the brain,but consciousness remains an enigma.
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 53
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
WYBO ALGRA
JOURNALISTFOR THE DUTCH NEWSPAPER TROUW
A re l e a s e from life
Strides in medicine may allow people to live longer, but the result is not
always a happy one. In the Netherlands, euthanasia is now legally
available—but just how far should we go?
3 . ESCAPING DESTINY
though they are about the same thing. Imagine, for
e x a m p l e, how sociologists and physicists would
respectively describe a football match, each focusing
upon features which his particular science can address
to describe the same thing.
The film inside the mind
Consciousness, on the other hand,can appear
much easier to understand than the relation
between mind and body: anyone capable of
thinking is after all intimately conscious of being
c o n s c i o u s. But consciousness is by far the most
perplexing mystery facing philosophy and the
neurological sciences. Some philosophers, in the
tradition of Descartes, think that it is too hard for
human intelligence to understand. Others even
claim that there is no such thing as consciousness;
we are actually zombies, just very complicated
o n e s. In defiance of these views, enquirers have
p r o fited from powerful new investigative tools,
especially brain scanning devices, to watch brains at
work.One result is a great increase in knowledge
of brain function and a refined understanding of the
correlation between specific brain areas and specific
mental capacities.
The central problem remains, however, of how
coloured pictures,evocative smells and sounds arise
in the head as if it were an inner cinema-show. One
recent theory offered by neurophysiologist A n t o n i o
Damasio is that consciousness begins as self-refle x i v e
awareness constituting a primitive level of selfhood,
a powerful but vague awareness of being “ I .”
Emotional relations to an evolving self and external
objects then construct a model of the world,a feeling
of knowing, giving each of us the sense that we are
the owner and viewer of a movie-within-the-brain.
Consciousness has arisen amongst higher
m a m m a l s, according to these theories,because of its
survival advantage—an organism’s appropriate use
of energy and protection from harm are much
enhanced when it is able to place itself in a map of
the environment and make plans about the best
courses of action in it.Creatures which are merely
biological automata,even if highly sensitive to their
s u r r o u n d i n g s, would not be as adaptive as creatures
that are genuinely conscious
Debate about the mind has certainly resulted in
a widespread consensus that mind is part of nature
and amenable to investigation by scientific means,
but there are still fundamental mysteries about
what it is and how it relates to the rest of nature.Th e
next great leap in understanding the mind will
doubtless involve a conceptual and scientific
revolution of such magnitude that we cannot at
present envisage it. ■
I
s a human body worth less in the Netherlands
than elsewhere? Does it lose its meaning here
once it gets old and decrepit? One might think so,
for this European country of 16 million people is
the only nation in the world where doctors, i n
accordance with the law,are able to end patients’ lives.
In April 2001, the Dutch senate gave the new law
on euthanasia the green light. The decision grabbed
international attention, although it was the predictable
outcome of a debate that has lasted a quarter of a
century. The law only established what was slowly
becoming normal procedure: that doctors are no
longer punishable if they carry out euthanasia as
long as they strictly conform to certain requirements
of due care. For example, they must be satisfied that
the patient is, according to medical criteria, s u f f e r i n g
unbearably and incurably, and has made the choice to
end his or her life without any outside pressure.
With the new law’s approval,the glorification of
suffering—a once pervasive streak in the Christian
tradition—seems to have been consigned to the
c o u n t r y ’s past. As Dutch theologian Annelies van
Heyst recently put it in Tr o u w, an ordinary life brings
enough suffering as it is. She nevertheless went on to
regret that along with the glorification of suffering, t h e
common rituals and comforting symbols of
Christianity had also been swept away:“Our culture
is focused on success and self-development. Fa s t ,
flashy, healthy—and when a problem comes up, this
is felt as if life is taking you for a ride.”
54 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
“ D e g r a d i n g ”and “ h u m i l i a t i n g.”With these words
euthanasia was justified from the very first lawsuits in
the 1970s and 1980s. Degrading meant, in the first
p l a c e, physical decay, such as terrible bedsores,
incontinence and loss of mobility. A culture that
places increasing emphasis on a flawless and beautiful
body is increasingly unable to cope with such ailments:
this might be one explanation for the support for
euthanasia,albeit rather a cynical one.
Advocates of euthanasia instead speak of self-
determination and compassion. They feel that it’s a
doctor’s duty to mitigate suffering, and the ultimate
consequence of this duty is death at request.An oft-
heard argument is that doctors themselves cause a lot
of suffering in their efforts to repair the old, s i c k
b o d y. In the past,
elderly people would
often die as the result
of a short and fierce
i n f e c t i o n , such as
t u b e r c u l o s i s. Th e s e
days, they have to live
for years in a body that
slowly gives up before
finally dying after a
wasting disease.
Everybody has the
right to go on to the
very end, those in
favour of euthanasia
s a y,but nobody should
be obliged to do so.
Many European
countries might share
the same
d e m o g r a p h i c s, b u t
t h e y ’re not necessarily
ready to follow in
Dutch footsteps. Th e
law is the fruit of a
unique set of
circumstances. First, it
required an influential
o r g a n i z a t i o n , t h e
Dutch Voluntary Euthanasia Society, which counts
around 100,000 members, including many prominent
n a m e s. S e c o n d , a small group of influential politicians,
who had been trying for years to get euthanasia
legalized, garnered support within the present left-
liberal government coalition.Dutch doctors, finally,
had long been seeking to be treated as integrated
m e d i c a l , psychological and social workers.
Euthanasia—literally “a good death”—fit this holistic
description to a T.
This particular alliance of doctors, politicians and
patients, however, is now threatening to fall apart.
Doctors see the new law as the final conclusion—“no
further than this.” But the Dutch minister of national
health care, Els Borst,let it be known that she wants
to initiate a debate over giving elderly people who are
simply tired of life the means of putting an end to it,
even if they are not terminally ill.The minister has the
full support of the Voluntary Euthanasia Society.
A g a i n , the magic word is “ h u m i l i a t i o n .” What if a
p e r s o n , after a rewarding social life, has to spend the
rest of his or her years in total solitude after everyone
around has passed away and every new day adds
only more torment? Is this not just as humiliating as
the last phase of cancer, with all the pain and loss of
decorum that accompany it?
Over 80 percent of the Dutch population are in
favour of euthanasia carried out by a doctor, o n
condition that all the legal demands about due care
are met.There is much less enthusiasm for a more or
less easily available
suicide pill for those
who are old and weary
of life. According to a
recent poll,46 percent
of Dutch people are
against this, of which a
significant number are
over 60. Doctors doubt
that the right to self-
determination should
go this far. Psychiatrist
Frank Ko e r s e l m a n
argued recently that
“autonomy is an
i d e o l o g y, even a
relatively fanatical one,
to which the
boundaries between
life and death are being
subordinated.”
In the mid-1990s,
Dutch doctors actively
ended about 3,200 lives
a year, r e p r e s e n t i n g
about 2.6 percent of all
d e a t h s. The ageing of
the population and
developments in
medical science will undoubtedly increase the demand
for euthanasia,but not without limits:it has become
clear that doctors refuse two out of three requests.
Most do not regard being tired of life or “not wanting
to be a burden to others”as valid reasons to carry out
this procedure. Euthanasia mainly concerns cancer
patients in their last days, and this is likely to remain
the case in years ahead. When questions about
terminating life are raised,doctors tend to fall back
on familiar territory: the body. “ They are there to
help when there are biological functional disorders,”
wrote Ko e r s e l m a n .“ To do this, they have instruments
such as pills and psychotherapy. Suffering is only
what brings people to the doctor. That the doctor
can sometimes alleviate this suffering is a fortunate
Tired of life?
When the soul
suffers, 
so does 
the body.
Paracelsus, 
Swiss physician and
philosopher (1493-1591)
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 55
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
A lunchbox
for l o n g e v i t y
Thirsting for the fountain of youth? 
There is  no shortage of tactics to live longer,
or perhaps forever.
Step number one: starve yourself…
3 . ESCAPING DESTINY
A d d i t i v e s
“Oxidative damage” is caused when cells in the body fail to process
food efficiently and instead churn out molecules that oxidize the
body—much as metal rusts, the flesh sags and genetic material
withers. Vitamins A, C and E come highly recommended,as does beta
carotene. Gingko, Ginseng,Bilberry, Soy Lecithin and Hawthorn leaves
each have their supporters. Similar miraculous claims have been made
for onions and garlic,which can either be taken raw, crushed into oils,
served in juices or soaked in alcohol for over a week to produce an
aromatic tincture. Taken together, this course of curative infusions is
guaranteed to keep the doctor away.
E a t i n g
“One must eat to live, and not live to eat,” wrote Molière, and the
world of dieticians would tend to agree. Five to nine plates of fresh
fruit and vegetables a day just about encapsulate the recommended
diet for a lengthy life. Out go pizza,pastries, fried breakfasts and juicy
steaks—all guilty of high cholesterol and “oxidative damage” to the
body. Instead,bid welcome to broccoli (rich in antioxidants),bran (rich
in fibres), steamed spinach and skinned chicken, rotated at one’s
pleasure and served with skimmed milk. Of course there have been
notable dissenters. David Henderson,a Scottish farmer who died aged
109 in 1998, swore by a diet of porridge, prunes and a mixture of
cattle salts and gin. Other suggested elixirs include champagne and
vintage port. Scientists, on the other hand, insist that all laboratory
tests point to the same conclusion: the best way to live longer is just
to eat less, much less. Undernourished, cold and terminally bad
tempered animals, they say, generally live to a ripe old age.
Going genetic
But why stop there? Who says evolution and its army of tight-fisted
genes should get in the way of immortal gratification? Now that the
human genome has been plotted, numerous scientists believe the
average life span can be stretched to 100 or 120.
Tissue engineering, laboratory generated organs and therapeutic
cloning have all been proclaimed as the next great breakthrough. In
particular, much is expected of stem cells that can fill in for wasted
neurons, bone marrow and tissue. And if that doesn’t do the job, there
are always alternatives.
How about freezing your brain upon death and waiting around for a
lucky break? Or what about porting into a computer or well-oiled
robot? But if neither the vat nor the android tempts you, there is still
some consolation: as Jorge Luis Borges wrote, the immortals lead
numbingly empty lives, for like animals they have no consciousness of
death. “It is divine, terrible and incomprehensible to know one is
immortal,” he wrote.
P i l l - p o p p i n g
Enough of raw cauliflower and Chinese leaf treatments—the busy
Western consumer wants long life, and wants it before breakfast.
Acutely aware of the market interest in user-friendly longevity
treatments, researchers have been sifting through the potions. Top of
the list at the moment is Dehydroepiandrosterone, or DHEA for short,
a hormone produced naturally in the body by the adrenal glands, and
that later transforms into oestrogen and testosterone. According to its
disciples—and there are many—use of this drug can tighten skin, firm
up bones and transform sex without a murmur of complaint.
Unfortunately the evidence is limited, the influence on the liver and
other organs unknown, and the usual perverse effects of hormone
replacement (breasts for men,beards for women) as present as ever.
Compiled by Ivan Briscoe, UNESCO Courier journalist
56 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
© Erling Mandelmann/Rapho, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
W
e ’ll just call him Z.L. H e ’s about 30
and has a body-piercing shop in
southern Fr a n c e. His head is shaved
and his chest is bare. A tangle of
p i p e s, body organs and pieces of
metal is tattooed on his right arm. His smile reveals a
charming row of chrome cobalt teeth.The man dreams
of building his very own steel skeleton and has already
started his transformation by implanting five Te flo n
ball-bearings between his chest muscles.
Z.L.is a former punk,who went through a self-
destructive phase of drug abuse but turned “ w i s e ”b y
focusing on his “technological body.” Now he calls
himself a cy b e r p u n k .“A few years ago, I almost died.
I needed a reason to live and that led me to create a
new personality.As I rebuilt myself, I became a very
positive person,” he says.
Hosting parasites
The cyberpunk movement has followers around
the world. In Australia, an artist called Stelarc has
implanted himself with a third ear made of Te flo n ,t h e
only metal the human body does not reject. In the
United States, the method of sub-cutaneous
implanting used by Steve Hayworth and Jon Cobb,
extends beyond the world of art. Two hundred
Americans have permanently changed their bodies at
around $900 an implant.In France, such operations
are strictly illegal except for medical reasons.
“ When I used to get high in a stairwell, I was
committing the crime of bodily harm. I was violating
the law protecting the integrity of my body. But the
law doesn’t distinguish between the harm of getting
high and positive reconstruction. So officially
speaking, we get our implants abroad.”
Z . L . swears by the apocalyptic writings of
cyberpunk authors such as Bruce Sterling of the U. S.
and Australian William Gibson, who regard human
bodies as foreign objects. For these sci-fi g u r u s, b o d i e s
are just hosts for parasites of various kinds—physical
for now, but before long, technological or even virtual.
Be it a laptop computer, mobile phones,
smartcards or an electronic tag for a criminal—
technology is increasingly becoming an extension of
the human body. Z . L . is an assiduous reader of
specialist publications like those of the Massachusetts
Institute of Te c h n o l o g y. It is only a matter of time, h e
s a y s, before technology is integrated within the body.
Anticipating the revolution, he has already taught
himself how to do surgical implants and other
operations.
“ The state uses technology to strengthen its control
over us,” he says.“By opposing this control,I remain
a punk.When the first electronic tags are implanted in
the bodies of criminals,maybe in the next five years, I ’l l
know how to remove them,deactivate them and spread
viruses to roll over Big Brother.” His work as Fr a n c e ’s
first body artist to experiment with implants is
confidential. He won’t just operate on anyone. He
carefully evaluates the philosophical, artistic or
political motives of those who seek his services. For
Z . L . , technology stands for liberation, n o t
enslavement.
He follows in the steps of Kevin Wa r w i c k , a British
professor who pioneered research into implants and
nanotechnology and is determined to cross the line
and change himself irrevocably into a “cyborg.”
“Right now I’m working on how to implant a
chip in my arm to operate, for example, my computer
by remote control,” he says. “I want to make
technology part of my body so I’m not controlled by
machines any more. It might seem a bit crazy, but at
the rate computer technology,virtual memory and the
power of computer chips are increasing, we’ll all be
asking in 10 years’ time for implants to increase our
knowledge, our intelligence and our memories. I’m
just a step ahead of you.” ■
MARC MILLANVOYE
FRENCH JOURNALIST
Te flon under my skin
Meet an aspiring cyborg who’s already started experimenting on his own
body, in the wake of the cyberpunk movement. He claims it’s allowed him
to turn the page on drugs and literally, rebuild himself
4 . C Y B E R S P E C I E S
“Handswriting,” by the Australian performance artist Stelarc (1982).
July/August 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 57
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
58 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
How close is Artificial Intelligence to creating
something that resembles a human?
There are broadly two levels of A r t i fic i a l
Intelligence (AI).The narrow level is about
getting non-biological systems to perform activities
that require human intelligence when we perform
t h e m .Strong AI is about applying the full range,d e p t h
and subtlety of human intelligence in a machine.
We have many examples of narrow AI today.
Machines can diagnose blood cells, guide cruise
missiles and play games likes chess better than any
h u m a n .They can read books and they can understand
human speech. In comparison to humans, t h e i r
memories are more accurate, they are faster and they
can share their knowledge instantly by quick
downloading.
There are two basic requirements for moving onto
the next stage. One is just the brute force hardware
capacity. Already, we are working on certain circuit
technologies that will be a million times more powerful
than the human brain, at least in terms of raw capacity.
But the more important issue is the software of
i n t e l l i g e n c e. In this regard, the most compelling project
underway is one to reverse engineer the human brain,
possibly by using billions of tiny high-resolution
scanners or nanobots that can travel through
capillaries and scan the brain from inside.
My feeling is that by 2030,w e ’ll be able to recreate
how several hundred regions of the human brain
work in non-biological mediums.
Would that non-biological medium then be equivalent
to a human?
We already have technology called a neuron
transistor—an electronic circuit that can communicate
wirelessly in two directions with biological neurons.We
also have examples of intelligent machines placed in
human brains via neural implants. A treatment for
P a r k i n s o n ’s Disease, pioneered in France by Dr A l i m -
Louis Benabid replaces the biological cells destroyed
in the first seven or eight years of the disease. The
doctor demonstrated this by controlling the device
from outside: when turned off, the patients remained
in an advanced stage of Parkinson’s—they were rigid
like statues. He flicked a switch, and it was as if they
had suddenly come alive.
By 2030, we will be able to send billions of
nanobots inside the human brain to communicate
wirelessly with billions of different points in the brain.
They will give us the ability to combine our biological
intelligence with non-biological intelligence.
Ultimately you will have entities that are completely
non-biological,with copies of human brains derived
from reverse engineering,and you will have biological
humans that have billions or trillions of nanobots in
their brains augmenting their intelligence or enabling
them to exist in virtual reality. So we will no longer be
able to say humans on the left, machines on the right.
One of your most startling ideas is that of downloading
the brain of an individual onto a computer system. Is this
truly possible?
I discussed in my book some thought experiments
of what that would be like. Is that the same person,f o r
example? One simple thought experiment argues that
it’s not,that if you scan my brain while I’m sleeping
and then reinstate it in a non-biological medium, I
would not even necessarily know about it. I ’d wake up,
feeling nothing was different.Someone would come
up to me and say:‘Good news,R a y,we don’t need your
old brain any more.’ I would probably not accept that
perspective. If you spoke to the new Ray, he would
have a memory of having been me, but at that point he
is a different person.
There’s also the issue: is he a person at all? Is he
conscious, or is he just acting that way? But the core
essence of consciousness is ultimately not penetrable
by scientific examination.We have a shared assumption
about humans that they are conscious,but that shared
consensus breaks down if you go outside humans. I ’ m
really making a political prediction that humans will
accept non-biological entities as conscious because
they’ll be so convincing in their behaviour.
What would be the benefits of being transferred onto
a non-biological medium?
A lot of profound scenarios emerge, one of which
is full immersion in virtual reality.These virtual reality
environments will incorporate all of the senses,and will
also be able to augment human intelligence. R i g h t
INTERVIEW BY IVAN BRISCOE
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
G o o d b y e b i o l o g y,
h e l l o s o f t wa r e
Do we really need our flesh and blood? Ray Kurzweil, guru of Artificial
Intelligence, believes that the conscious machine is only decades away—
so get ready to download
4 . C Y B E R S P E C I E S
I let my body do
what it wants.
When you are 
in love, you
cannot organize
your body.
Roberto Benigni,
Italian film director
(1952-) 
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 59
now we’re restricted to a mere hundred trillion neuron
connections per second, millions of which are needed
to operate one chunk of knowledge. We’ll be able to
vastly expand the human brain—think faster, think
b i g g e r, more complex thoughts, have more knowledge
and download knowledge.
But many neurological theories argue that consciousness
is in fact very much mixed up with emotions, with a
sense of being in the body and having objects act upon
the body.
Intelligence is the ability to solve problems using
finite resources, including time.And the problems we
solve have much to do with our body—protecting it,
feeding it, clothing it, providing for its needs and
d e s i r e s.A lot of our thinking has to do with our bodies:
a disembodied human intelligence would quickly
become depressed.
But as virtual reality becomes more and more
c o m p e l l i n g, human civilization will be spending more
of its time in it.By 2030 or 2040,these virtual reality
environments will be extremely competitive with real
ones through the ability to meet with people regardless
of physical proximity and emulation of earthly and
imaginary environments.These non-biological entities
will be able to have human-like bodies in virtual
r e a l i t i e s. A l s o, through nanotechnology1, t h e y ’ll be
able have human-like bodies in real reality.
What is driving this technology?
Ultimately we as a species have adopted
e v o l u t i o n ’s goals, and they are in my mind virtual
o n e s. If you look dispassionately at biological
evolution, it has created entities that are more and
more intelligent,creative, beautiful,more capable of
higher emotions like love. God is a term that has been
used to denote infinite levels of these qualities.What
the new paradigm signifies is the end of biological
humanity as the cutting edge of evolution.I see what
we have been talking about as the next step in
evolution through humanity merging with its
technology and continuing its exponential growth in
intellectual,creative powers. ■
1. Nanotechnology is the construction of materials or
circuits on the basis of complex, s e l f - r e p l i c a t i n g
chemical molecules.
T H E  N E W  B O D Y S H O P
Science at its most hairbrained, or the incisive portrait of a future where humans and
machines blend seamlessly into one? The debate over Massachusetts-based scientist Ray
Kurzweil’s predictions for a post-biological era not far from now have stirred angst and
controversy in about equal measure.
The one thing that cannot be doubted is Ku r z w e i l ’s track record in artificial intelligence. In 1976,
he pioneered the first print to speech machine for the blind,in 1984 the first computer music
keyboard and the first speech recognition programme three years later. His vision of the near
future was set to paper in a book in 1990 that predicted the world wide web, the spread of
“ s m a r t ” military weapons and the emergence of a computer that would conquer the world of
chess by 1998.He was one year out.
No litany of inventions or honours, h o w e v e r, could spare Kurzweil a hostile reception to the
ideas laid out in his latest volume of prophecies, The Age of Spiritual Machines ( Vi k i n g ,1 9 9 9 ) .
For many in philosophy, neuroscience and artificial intelligence, full human consciousness
hovers beyond even a super- m a c h i n e ’s potential—and possibly beyond all scientific
u n d e r s t a n d i n g .Writing in T h e New York Review of Books, philosopher John Searle castigated
Kurzweil for supposing that a computer simulation of a brain can be conscious: t h e
computer, Searle argues, “just shuffles the symbols.”
On a different note, Bill Joy, head of Sun Microsystems, drew from Kurzweil’s work to rail
against technologies that might eventually exterminate humankind. His fears have even been
echoed by robot researchers such as Hugo De Garis, who recently called for urgent debate
over what might happen if machines turn conscious and treat us much as we now treat dogs
and cats. ■
M ACHINES AND THE MAN
Companion or rival of the future? 
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
O
PHILIPPE DEMENET
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Pa r t n e rship or purs e - s t r i n g s :
NGOs in the South speak up
Riding on their new-found influence, NGOs in the developing world are increasingly critical of the
stringent conditions imposed on them by richer counterparts. Partnership,
they argue, has to become more than a buzz-word
ver the last decade, non-governmental
organizations (NGOs) in richer
countries have tried out audacious and
sometimes far-fetched methods to check
how their aid is being spent by recipients
in developing ones.
“ We lent a video camera to a
Ghanaian partner running a fair-trade
p r o j e c t ,” says Chris Roche, p r o g r a m m e
director at the British NGO Oxfam,
which funds more than $130 million
worth of development projects each
y e a r. The Ghanaians did their own
assessment,video camera in hand. The
footage revealed a project agent
embezzling craft workers’ money. “We
call this a participatory self-assessment,
because it allows our partner to get more
involved with the beneficiaries at the
grassroots.”
Other NGOs use peer reviews,
crossed assessments (when partners in
the developing world assess projects in
the North) or consultations via a kind of
travelling parliament. Last spring, M a r c
B e r g e r, programme director at the
French Catholic Committee against
Hunger and for Development (CCFD),
visited three continents to meet
“ p a r t n e r s ” in developing countries.
During a series of seminars he spoke
about the organization, with a budget of
$26 million per annum,and how it goes
about selecting projects.“Our openness
empowered them and made the terms of
our relationship more equal,” he says.
These various methods, which are
still in the pilot stages, aim to rectify the
lopsided relationship between donor
Benin’s Songhai team is training 240 farmers in organic agriculture:“the North arrives with ready-made projects.”
◗ E T H I C S
60 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
NGOs in the North and their bene-
ficiaries in the South. But invariably,
“the hand that gives is above the one
that receives,” as an African proverb
g o e s. Even after such consultations,
CCFD is still the one which chooses the
projects to fund and the rules to be
imposed.“They’re consulted but in the
end we decide, even though their
opinion can carry weight,” a d m i t s
Berger.
Mounting
dissatisfaction
World Bank figures show that NGOs
have “grown exponentially” over the
past ten years, especially in developing
countries. In India,more than a million
community-based groups are involved in
local development. In Bangladesh, 5 , 0 0 0
organizations are involved in literacy
efforts—so many that a child there is
more likely to learn to read with their
help than via the state education system.
In the former communist countries of
Eastern Europe, 100,000 NGOs sprung
up between 1988 and 1995.
In terms of human development—
health care, education, help in finding
w o r k , social services and emergency
aid—“the role of NGOs in the South
has become key,” says Guillaume
d ’ A n d l a u , a lecturer at Strasbourg’s
Political Studies Institute and author of
a book on humanitarian action.“Even
governments in the North call upon
them for their overseas development
programmes.”
Their influence may be indisputable,
but NGOs in the developing world are
increasingly dissatisfied with the unequal
terms of the relationship. Since the early
1 9 7 0 s, NGOs based in the richer nations
have used the impressive term
“ p a r t n e r s h i p ” to describe their links
with colleagues in the South.The word
“has been part of approved rhetoric in
the ‘development community’ for a very
long time,” according to Gerry
H e l l e i n e r,1 an economics professor at
the University of To r o n t o.“It has rarely
been effectively practised. S o m e
practitioners have long doubted whether
it was possible.”
Delivering results
Far from ebbing away, N o r t h e r n
NGOs are putting increasing pressure
on those in developing countries.
According to Oxfam’s Roche, the idea is
“to get them to increase their
involvement and provide tangible proof
of their effectiveness.”
Novib, a Dutch NGO with a $120-
million annual budget, requires aid
recipients to supply accounts every year,
S o n g h a ï * : the North looks for an echo of its own song
Does partnership mean equality? At Songhai, we don’t think so.
Here, it means complementarity, a shared approach towards a
mission, mutual respect and transparency at all costs. It’s a question
of not letting one side trample over the other.
Unfortunately, the world is far from this ideal.In the South, NGOs are
too often born in a burst of enthusiasm or as a reaction to a problem,
without any long-term strategy. After that, their sole concern is
survival.All too often, there’s a frenetic race to win the attention of
Northern “partners,” gleefully described as “donors.”
NGOs in the South live on a drip: they’re ready to take all the aid they
can find.In a perpetual state of dependency, they don’t try to mobilize
local resources in the field that might help make their projects
sustainable. “White elephants”—abandoned edifices that have cost a
fortune—are the sad result.
The weaknesses on the other side are just as flagrant.Our “partners”
from the North arrive with ready-made projects devised in offices in
London, Paris, Washington and Brussels, with preset conditions and
eligibility criteria. Then they go off searching for people and
institutions to back them up, looking for an echo of their own song as
it were. And they have no problem finding one. Even though their
priorities change all the time—one day it’s environment or gender
equality, the next capacity-building—their Southern “partners” are
ready to change strategy and even their identity simply to satisfy the
Northern “partners.”
Sometimes, though, the latter come across institutions like Songhai,
who have their own ideas and want to preserve their dignity through
mutual respect. This leaves them rather confused. In the past, we’ve
had to return funding already paid into our account, notably to two
religious groups (one Protestant and the other Catholic), and to a
multilateral aid agency.The reason:their goals and conditions were no
longer in line with the vision and strategies that we’d tried in vain to
share with them.
Not all donors have this one-track attitude. Songhai is currently
working with a public international aid organization which, after
seeing how we operated,agreed to give us some leeway in the use of
their funding. All Songhai’s activities and programmes aim to boost
our own resources in order to reduce the amount of aid we receive
from NGOs or aid agencies. We think self-sufficiency is the only way to
sustainable development. ■
* The Beninese NGO Songhai—named after an empire that existed in
the bend of the Niger river in the 15th century—was set up in 1985
by a Catholic priest, Brother Njamuno. It is currently training 240
apprentice farmers at three centres in integrated organic farming
based on making the best use possible of local resources. 
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
as well as twice-yearly financial
statements and a final report on the
project.“When there’s a problem with
the spending of funds, the local partner
might get a visit from an expert,” says
Jan Ruyssenaars from Novib’s project
d e p a r t m e n t . The organization, w h i c h
d e fines itself as a donor at the service of
Southern NGOs, is far from the fussiest
in the field.
Not all NGOs make the same
d e m a n d s, but there are fewer and fewer
who make none at all and advocate a
hands-off approach,according to Rick
D a v i e s, a social development consultant
based in the UK,who has studied how
donors in general operate. The most
“laissez faire” tend to be Christian
organizations. At the other end of the
spectrum are the hard-liners, such as
the U. S. A g e n cy for International
Development (USAID),which requires
extensive information and the meeting
of set targets akin to a business contract.
Between the two camps are the
m i n i m a l i s t s, who think producing
reports diverts the energy of Southern
NGOs from their most important work.
You also have the “apologetic realists,”
such as Novib and Oxfam. Th o u g h
aware that the reports are a burden,
they need them for their own donors.
“ Without being neo-colonialist,” s a y s
R o c h e,“every time money is disbursed,
we need to know exactly where it goes
out of respect for the British citizens
who give us donations.”
Sending back
the money
The bottom-line is that demands
made by richer NGOs are meeting with
increasing resistance. Some NGOs in
the developing world even return money
to donors who become too
“ d o m i n e e r i n g.”More often, in countries
where several sources of funding are
a v a i l a b l e, they shun donors who are too
bureaucratic or finicky.
“Everyone wants a donor who will
l i s t e n , take time to learn and allow
r o o m for local initiatives,” says Lisa
B o r n s t e i n , a researcher at Natal
U n i v e r s i t y ’s School of Development
S t u d y, in South A f r i c a . Certain NGOs in
the South which accept a more
contractual relationship insist that
funding arrives on time, and that the
donor does not change priorities or
monitoring procedures in the middle of
a project,as often happens.
When asked—and when they dare
speak up—NGOs in the developing
world usually repeat the same lament:
“the North claims to knows what’s best
for us, poses as an expert and doesn’t
take the time to listen or the trouble to
use local skills and resources.”
Passing on
expertise
By the mid-1990s, d o n o r
organizations could already see the
danger of stifling local initiative by being
too heavy-handed.“ The principles that
underpin partnership are incompatible
with the notion of conditionality
imposed by donors,” said the chairman
of the OECD’s development aid
committee at the time.
Conditionality has lost none of its
relevance, whether it relates to gender
e q u a l i t y, environmental protection or
other domains. But the notion is
challenged by NGOs that have several
donors to choose from.“ Fishermen from
the Cape, who are mostly men, didn’t
understand why they had to bring
women into their profession,” s a y s
B o r n s t e i n . “ They complied, but these
conditionalities can lead to absurd
s i t u a t i o n s, just to please the donor.As for
the environment, the deep poverty in
our country still makes it seem like a
luxury.”
To escape this unequal relationship
caused by money transfers, some NGOs
in the South see only one way out:
strengthen their ability to fund
themselves.
The CCFD’s South A f r i c a n ,M e x i c a n
and Chilean partners have said as much.
“You talk to us about self-sufficiency,”
they told Berger, “but why don’t you
pass on to us some of your expertise in
fund-raising and mass-mailing?” ■
1. In UNDP’s magazine C o o p e r a t i o n
South, Number Two, 2000.
Noel A g u i r re Ledezma*:
We can help the North
Our relationship with Northern donors depends largely on the NGO we’re working with.
When mutual understanding is strong, the desire to draw up joint projects arises quite
n a t u r a l l y. These are based on a shared political vision and similar technical and
organizational approaches. When that happens, the discussion is not just about sums of
money or how to handle them. It’s even less about the need to respect the goals of the
project down to the last comma. In this scenario, you’re close to the notion of a true
partnership.
But with other NGOs, the relationship only repeats and underscores the South’s dependence
on the North. In these cases, you only talk about preset criteria for the project’s aims or
management.Everything is seen through Northern eyes, with the unspoken assumption that
“people in the South don’t know how to manage.”
You’ll find these trends in most NGOs in the South. Some are only interested in securing
funds and reducing North-South relations to a straight transfer of money. This has to be
changed. The first question we should ask is what we can build together. How can we help
the North in our own field of competence, whether it’s education,culture or human values?
What networks can we create so that together we don’t just build up a poor part of the
world—the South—but a different world altogether, rooted in fairness and solidarity? ■
* An educator who heads the Bolivian Centre for Educational Research and Action (CBIAE),
an NGO with Dutch, German and Spanish funding.
62 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
Zafrullah Chowdhury*: We choose our donors
For the first two years of our existence as an NGO, we didn’t ask
anyone for money. We lived in tents pitched around a clinic and
the peasants would bring us rice. Then Abbé Pierre, from France, gave
us some funding so we could build a house. That was the first money
we received from abroad.
When I went to Europe in the winter of 1972, he told me:“I’d like to
give you more because you’ve done good work. But I have one
condition...” I cut him off at once:“I don’t want your conditions, nor
your money!”
He replied: “I’ll show you Paris.” And one freezing cold night, he
showed me “his” Paris—places where the poor were being given
soup and sheds where the
Companions of Emmaüs were
restoring abandoned furniture to
raise money. I realized that he and I
belonged to the same world despite
our language differences.
Then he said:“Here’s the condition.
Never forget that I’m giving you the
money of the poor to help the poor
of Bangladesh. Always make sure
they’re the ones who truly benefit.”
Thirty years later, we still ask
ourselves that question: “Will it
help the poorest people?” This is
what Abbé Pierre taught us and I
still remember that. Conditionality
is not a bad thing, as long as it’s
founded on an ethic and favours
human development. The problem
comes when Western donors set
poor conditions.
An example: child labour in the
Bangladeshi textile industry is
indefensible and I’m against it. But
should it be simply banned, with its
abolition made a condition of
foreign aid? I don’t think so. This is
how the question should be looked
at: what will happen to all the girls
between 10 and 14 when they no longer work in the textile industry?
They may become prostitutes or end up as slaves in a rich person’s
house. They certainly won’t go to school, because the prices you pay
in the North for the clothes made in these factories don’t allow their
mothers to earn a decent wage. It would be better for the child to
keep on working and go to classes in the evening, paid for by the
mill-owner or a foreign NGO.
At our People’s Health Centre, we choose our foreign donors. The first
thing we tell them is that we prepare our programmes and budgets.
Then we tell them we have two “conditions.” The first is that donors
have to recognize that they know nothing about Bangladesh, and
that I know the country better than they do. Then they have to be
patient, because development is a slow process. That’s why I ask
them for long-term funding, of at least five years.
In the first year, the donor listens to us and learns. The second year,
we discuss and negotiate. And because we know they’re accountable
to the body that provided the money—a worthy concern—the third
year is given over to checking that every cent of the aid is used well.
In the fourth year, disputes will most likely arise. But by the fifth year,
we’ll understand each other better. We’ll even begin to see where
we’ve succeeded, and where we haven’t.
Five years is the time it takes to build a relationship of mutual
understanding and friendship. But that’s not enough. We also have to
get out of this “secrecy illness”
that donors bring with them (the
World Bank and the Northern
NGOs alike) and which has
poisoned NGOs in the South. Who
knows how much money has been
handed over, to whom and for
what? Secrecy breeds corruption.
We’re the only NGO in Bangladesh
that posts details of our wages and
financial statements in our local
health centres. Because we are
accountable to the people we serve
before anyone else.
Transparency starts there. A f t e r
that,with the Northern NGOs, it’s a
matter of mutual respect and trust.
If we’re dealing with a donor who
understands us and believes in
human development, I’ve no
objection to him or her examining
our accounts. But that person has
to recognize my right to examine
theirs. ■
* A Bangladeshi doctor who
founded Gonoshasthaya Kendra
(GK), the People’s Health Centre,
whose 2,000 employees, mostly
women, promote primary health care, education and female
empowerment in Bangladesh. The NGO trains its own paramedics
(primary health workers) and manufactures antibiotics and generic
medicines. It provides two-thirds of its own funding.
A paramedic on duty in a Bangladeshi village.
E T H I C S ◗
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
W
◗ W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G
FILIPPO SALVATORE
COMMUNICATIONS PROFESSOR AT CONCORDIA UNIVERSITY, FORMER MEMBER OF QUEBEC’S FRENCH LANGUAGE COUNCIL
AND A FORMER MONTREAL CITYCOUNCILLOR
Vi v e
a trilingual Quebec!
The laws that forced French into the schools and workplace of Quebec have worked far better than
anyone imagined. Trilingualism is gaining ground in the province, much to the chagrin of hard-line
nationalists
ith her rugged natural beauty and charming
a c c e n t , Quebec shines as an emblem of
cultural resolve in countries with strong
minorities, ranging from Spain to Nigeria.
The little francophone island thrives in a sea
of English-speakers*, thanks to its carefully
constructed rampart of laws and
educational policies promoting Fr e n c h .B u t
C a n a d a ’s “Belle Province” is set to change
c o u r s e : a new government inquiry has
found that it’s time to roll back the legal
l o c o m o t i v e, Bill 101, which has forced
French into the school system and
workplace for the past 30 years.
All children must attend Fr e n c h
elementary or high schools, according to
Bill 101 (also known as the Fr e n c h
Language Charter), with one exception:
old-time Quebeckers who attended the
province’s English elementary schools can
choose their children’s language of
i n s t r u c t i o n . French is the rule, h o w e v e r, f o r
all newcomers, from Canada or beyond,
until the college or university level.
Born in 1977,Bill 101 is the brainchild of
Q u e b e c ’s nationalist movement whose
ultimate goal has been to separate from
the rest of Canada,or at least seek greater
autonomy within the federation (see box).
The law stems back to the heady days of the
Quiet Revolution, when Fr e n c h
Quebeckers (the “Québécois”) wrested
control of the province from a powerful
English elite, who controlled its huge
natural wealth. Then they turned to the
cultural landscape, using laws like Bill 101
to “Frenchify” (or “francify”) the schools
64 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
“All Quebec on the march to live in French”in 1989.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
and workplace as well as the commercial
environment through rules restricting the
use of English on public signs or even on
the beer coasters of a neighbourhood bar.
Language police still roam the streets,
measuring the letters of billboards to ensure
that “Poulet-frit”dominates the fast-food
world of “fried chicken,” for example. The
provincial government regularly adds a
fresh coat of legislative paint to reinforce
the spirit of 101. With each major
brushstroke another wave of English
Quebeckers migrates to other parts of
Canada or the U.S.
When the “natives”
feel outnumbered
Today the old-stock of English
Quebeckers accounts for just 8.5 percent of
the population, down from 13 percent in
1971. Yet according to the nationalists, the
anglophone threat has not faded but taken
on new dimensions, thanks to the
“ a l l o p h o n e s,” a nice way of referring to
immigrants whose first language is not
Fr e n c h . Every year, about 25,000 to 35,000
immigrants arrive mostly from Latin
A m e r i c a , the Middle and Far East.To g e t h e r
the two minorities—anglophone and
allophone—comprise 18 percent of the
provincial population. The pure wool
Québécois still make up about 82 percent
of the population, despite having one of
the lowest birth rates in the world. B u t
many of these “ n a t i v e s ” are convinced that
they will soon become a minority in their
financial capital, M o n t r e a l , where most
minority communities settle.According to
a survey conducted last year by the daily L e
Devoir, 55 percent of all Quebeckers are
convinced that French is in danger
throughout the province.
So with alarm bells ringing, t h e
provincial government launched an inquiry
last year asking “what should Quebec do to
ensure the future of the French language?”
This kind of inquiry, known as the language
e s t a t e s - g e n e r a l , is somewhat of a ritual.
Each time the provincial government
pushes for a referendum on separating
from the rest of Canada (see box), t h e y
turn up the heat on the language debate by
pointing to the lamentable state of Fr e n c h .
But after spending more than two million
Canadian dollars on a string of public
hearings across the province, t h e
nationalists got far more than they
bargained for.According to the preliminary
report released on June 5, French has never
been healthier in the “Belle Province.”
“ The French language is no longer the
property of the majority. It has become the
language of everyone,”announced the head
of the estates-general, Gérald Larose, a
former union leader and long-time Quebec
s e p a r a t i s t . Almost 95 percent of Quebec
residents know and use French in their
daily activities, up seven percent in just
over a decade.
More than 90 percent of the province’s
newly arriving pupils are heading straight
for French schools, according to Quebec’s
education ministry. Then again,their only
alternative is to enroll in the private sector.
But Bill 101 cannot force these kids to
speak French outside of the classroom, y e t
many continue to babble and scream the
language in the school-yards and
playgrounds even in Montreal, w h e r e
immigrants make up almost half of the
French school population.
Even the old-time minorities—anglo-
and allophones born and bred in Quebec—
have adopted the spirit of 101. Th e s e
parents could legally send their kids to
English schools, yet about 75 percent opt
for the French sector.There is one notable
exception: the Italians, one of the largest
and most established of Quebec’s cultural
communities. The majority continue with
English schools. Instead of rejecting
bilingualism,these families are embracing
three languages at once. Fr a n c o - I t a l i a n
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 65
The birth of 101
Before Bill 101, Quebec residents had the right to send their children to either French or
English-speaking public schools, which owing to a twist in history were generally
organized along religious lines. Back in 1867 when the Canadian confederation first emerged,
Quebec had two major ethnic groups: French Catholics and British Protestants. Each group
formed their own set of schools within the public system.But by the end of the 19th century,
a new immigrant group settled in Montreal and confounded the clean division: the Irish
Catholics. The compromise permitting the Irish to attend English schools set an important
precedent.Since then,nearly every immigrant group, from Catholic Poles to Italians, has gone
through English schools. Even francophone groups, like Moroccan Jews, were sent (by
officials) to English classrooms to avoid the Catechism of the French system.
This arrangement suited French Canadians, who didn’t want non-native French-speakers
enrolling in their schools. But this tolerance lasted only so long as the French-Canadian birth
rate remained high. It quickly faded during the Quiet Revolution when French Quebeckers
began breaking free from the strict confines of traditional Catholic society. The new
generation moved into the cities, focusing on improving their financial lot rather than settling
down to raise large families in the countryside. At precisely the time when French family-size
declined,immigration surged,particularly among Italians.
As English schools mushroomed in Montreal, the nationalist movement calling for Quebec
independence emerged as a credible and powerful political force. These nationalists
demanded measures to “correct” the linguistic and demographic imbalance reflected in the
school system. A compromise was sought in 1968 with a law favouring French language
instruction.But the nationalists were not satisfied. They wanted all children to attend French
schools.
Two years later, French became the official language of Quebec but tensions continued to
simmer until a full-fledged language war erupted in 1976, when the new separatist Parti
Québécois, founded and led by the charismatic leader René Lévesque, won the provincial
election. A year later, the nationalists passed Bill 101, a milestone in Quebec’s language
debate. ■
“I remember”on every numberplate.
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
marriage rates increase each year. L o v e,
n o t
c o e r c i o n , is winning this community over to
French.
The trilingual allure has also won over
hearts in the estates-general. While the
final recommendations aren’t expected
before Au g u s t , the Larose commission
dropped a bombshell on June 5: the anglo-
and allophone communities are no longer
enemies but role models.“ The old English-
French antagonism in Quebec has been at
least a little bit blurred and softened. A n d
maybe a lot,” announced Larose, before
laying out a plan to not only promote
French but English. Instead of reinforcing
Bill 101, as many hard-liners expected, t h e
commission suggested partially dismantling
it by, for example, abolishing the language
police.
Time to learn 
English?
According to the Larose commission,
Quebec needs a new charter or constitution
to officially recognize French as the
province’s language of citizenship. Yet, it
c o n t i n u e d ,English also merits respect as the
language of Quebec’s official “ n a t i o n a l
m i n o r i t y.” Anglophones would have
guaranteed access to judicial services, h e a l t h
c a r e, social assistance programmes and
e d u c a t i o n . “ We ’re trying to say to the
anglophone community that your place in
this society is recognized,that your future
is assured,” said one of the 11 commission
members, Dermod Travis, president of the
non-governmental Forum Action Quebec,
which aims to promote dialogue among all
Quebeckers.
Perhaps the ultimate irony lies in the
recommendation that French pupils
improve their English.As it stands now,
children attending English schools must
learn French from the first grade. Ye t
francophone pupils wait until the fif t h
grade before taking English classes,w h i c h
tend to be of rather poor quality. As a
r e s u l t , only about 38 percent of Fr e n c h
Quebeckers are bilingual. I t ’s as if they
have been lulled into complacency,
convinced that in the land of 101,English
i s n ’t necessary to earn a living. But not
only do their job prospects plummet the
moment they step outside of Quebec, b u t
the competition is already heating up
within as bilingual and trilingual
allophones grow in number.
“ B l a s p h e m y ! ” cry the hard-liners of
the nationalist Parti Québécois. The state
of French remains “precarious” because
there are still too many people who speak
English in the privacy of their homes.
Immigrants may use French in the
workplace or at school but, say the hawks,
switch immediately into English at home
or when socializing. For these hard-liners,
integration amounts to assimilation and
anything less than that is treason.
If the father of Bill 101,Camille Laurin,
wanted to mould newcomers into good neo-
Québécois, the result is disappointing.The
Bill 101 generation learns to speak Fr e n c h ,
but still keeps an open mind towards North
American culture, while holding on to its
own maternal language and values. These
young people and their parents generally
accept the principle of French dominance in
Q u e b e c. It is now time for the Québécois to
assume their role as a well-established and
respected majority, not a threatened
m i n o r i t y.The white, Fr e n c h - s t o c k ,C a t h o l i c
paradigm has been shattered and replaced
by a multiracial, multireligious and
multilingual one.It is time for less coercion
and more incentives.
* Q u e b e ckers represent a quarter of the
Canadian population (29.5 million).
66 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
The Canadian divide
Quebec’s language debate stretches beyond its provincial boundaries to touch the core of
Canadian identity and unity. For the past 30 years, Canada’s ten provinces have tried to amend
their constitution to resolve the conflict between a federalist vision of the country and
Quebec’s demands for greater sovereignty.
The debate stems back to 1971, when the Québécois nationalist movement first threatened
to separate from the rest of Canada,leaving a gaping hole in the middle of the confederation.
Prime Minister Pierre Elliott Trudeau,(a French Quebecker),proposed the vision of an officially
bilingual and multicultural country, with a strong federal government and ten equal provinces.
Separatists like René Lévesque rejected the concept and launched the notion of a political
sovereign Quebec,economically “associated” with the rest of Canada.
Lévesque presented this proposition in a referendum that the people of Quebec rejected in
1980.A second referendum was organized in 1995 by Jacques Parizeau,the provincial premier
and leader of the Parti Québécois (PQ). Once again, the proposal was rejected but this time
by a slim one percent margin. Parizeau attributed the loss to “money and the ethnic vote,” a
comment widely interpreted as a xenophobic and anti-Semitic allusion to Montreal’s minority
communities. The scandal forced Parizeau to resign.
In 1996, a more conciliatory leader, Lucien Bouchard, took control of the PQ and the seat of
the premier. While open to negotiations with the federal government, Bouchard still tried to
satisfy the hard-liners of his party by organizing the estates-general on the future of the
French language in Quebec. For some of the hawks, the inquiry marked a first step towards
another referendum on sovereignty. Once again, a nationalist, Yves Michaud, evoked the
spectre of “the Jewish ethnic vote.” Stunned by this anti-Semitism and the deep divisions it
caused within the PQ, Bouchard resigned last December. Yet his moderate voice continues to
echo in the conciliatory stance of the estates-general. ■
◗ W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G
Beware of the language police!
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
O
RAFAEL RODRÍGUEZ CASTAÑEDA
EDITOR OFTHE MEXICAN MAGAZINE PROCESO
AND AUTHOROF PRENSA VENDIDA (EDITORIAL GRIJALBO, 1993)
M ex i c o ’s
m e rcenary legacy
For decades the Mexican media was paid to do the government’s bidding. But what future lies in
store for the press after last year’s defeat of the all-powerful Institutional Revolutionary Party (the
PRI) and the electoral victory of President Vicente Fox?
n New Ye a r ’s Day 1994, the world was
astonished by the sight of a hooded
guerrilla fighter giving a televised press
conference in the main square of the
Mexican town of San Cristóbal de las
C a s a s. Sub-comandante Marcos, t h e
flamboyant leader of the Zapatista
National Liberation A r m y, had decided to
exploit the media as part of his movement’s
s t r a t e g y. His first goal was achieved: in the
smokey aftermath of New Ye a r
c e l e b r a t i o n s, the Mexican people awoke to
find a war on their home turf and an abrupt
end to the modernizing dream of the then
president,Carlos Salinas de Gortari.
The media embraced the Zapatista war
as they might an unexpected lover. They
longed to be witnesses and players in the
fighting around the mountainous state of
Chiapas—and they got what they wanted.
The 10 days that shook Mexico were
covered fully and freely by the country’s
m e d i a . Editors and reporters basked in
the freedom and independence they had
previously forsaken, learning a lesson that
only a few of them had absorbed up to
that point—press freedom could be good
business. As a result, part of the Mexican
press discovered a liberty and an influ e n c e
it has clung to ever since.
The Untouchable and 
the Invincible 
But what was the press like before the
year when Mexicans lived in danger? In
1 9 6 8 , during the big student
demonstrations that led to the infamous
October 2 massacre in Mexico City’s
Tlaltelolco Square [in which at least 500
people are believed to have died],the cry
of “prensa vendida! ” [mercenary press]
rang out through the city streets,
encapsulating the fury people felt for the
largely corrupt press.The PRI—nicknamed
“The Invincible”for having by fair means
or foul won every election since it was
founded in 1929 as the National
Revolutionary Party—thrust its roots deep
into a rotten ground that spawned, a m o n g
other things, a docile press.
To start with, the government
controlled all supplies of newsprint.
Newspapers were allowed to pay for it
later, and in some cases were never asked
to pay at all. The same went for their
employees’ social security contributions.
Some companies were exempted from
t a x e s. Most newspapers and magazines
depended on advertising from the state.
Politicians and public officials bribed
journalists and editors as a matter of
r o u t i n e, handing over so much cash (called
e m b u t e s or ch ay o t e s in the journalistic
argot) that many depended more on these
payments than on their own salaries.As for
news, the press—with a few exceptions—
simply fed at the trough of information
that the government had decided to make
public.
The slavishness of the media was
especially visible in its attitude to the
president of the day. Under the Mexican
s y s t e m , the president had an almost divine
s t a t u s.As owner of the country’s destiny,h e
Zapatista leader Subcomandante Marcos counts down the seconds to a press conference in February 2001.
M E D I A ◗
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 67
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
was also regarded as master of its citizens’
s o u l s. He was the Untouchable. Th o u g h
guaranteed in the national constitution,
the freedom of the press was nevertheless
treated by editors as a gift from this
benevolent president, and thus an object
for the deepest gratitude.
Exceptions to this miserable state of
affairs played key roles in determining the
later evolution of the press. In 1968, Julio
Scherer García took over E x c é l s i o r,one of
the country’s biggest newspapers.He soon
turned it into the most influential one, a n d
it became recognized as one of the world’s
10 best newspapers. Faced with its
systematic criticism and attacks, t h e
tyrannical government reacted in the
manner it knew best. In 1976, t h e
government of Luis Echeverria organized
and funded a palace coup inside the paper,
and Scherer García was forced out.
He and a team of reporters then
founded the
weekly magazine
P r o c e s o, which has
been the bastion
o f the oppostion
press ever since it
first appeared on
November 6,1976.
Following its ex-
a m p l e, s o m e
sectors of the
traditional press
made timid
attempts over t h e
next 20 years to break their bad habit of
depending on the government. N e w
papers sprang up, with different aims and
s t r a t e g i e s, but in general the corrupt rules
of the game were preserved until Ja n u a r y
1 ,1 9 9 4 , the day President Salinas launched
what he saw as the glittering triumph for
his economic policy:the North American
Free Trade Association (NA F TA )
between Mexico, the United States and
Canada.
From then on, criticism of the
government became routine. Th e
monolithic political system began to show
cracks which some of the media ventured
into, more often drawn by instinct than a
high degree of professionalism and
responsibility. Ernesto Zedillo, who took
over from Salinas de Gortari, could not
and did not want to curb the mounting
backlash against the PRI system. E i t h e r
through indifference or scorn, the press
was let off the leash.
Many papers were confused. Th e y
d i d n ’t want to stop acting like poodles, b u t
they sensed that a change of master was
i m m i n e n t . By the time of the 2000
presidential elections, an unfettered press
was in place. The leading candidates were
the PRI’s Francisco Labastida and a rising
political star called Vicente Fox,officially
standing for the right-wing National A c t i o n
Party, but who was launched into the race
by a solid group of independent
b u s i n e s s p e o p l e, marketing experts and
some social organizations unconnected to
political party machines.
In fact,Mexicans were ready to dump
the PRI, and on July 2, 2 0 0 0 , Fox beat
Labastida by a landslide;71 years of history
ended without a hint of violence. But did a
period of transition then begin? Perhaps,
but perhaps not.The more sceptical argue
that Fox is not the statesman needed to
preside over a
genuine national
t r a n s i t i o n . O t h e r s
rightly note that the
keystones of
M e x i c o ’s oligarchic
power structure are
still untouched.
Whatever the truth
of the matter, t h e
press has played a
major part in the
political change. I t
helped demystify
the regime and above all show that the
president was no longer the Untouchable,
and the PRI no longer the Invincible.
So what comes next? In its special issue
on Fo x ’s election, P r o c e s o summed up the
challenge now facing the country and the
press. The cover shows supporters of Fox
carrying a coffin painted in the PRI’s
colours with the words “And now what?”
written above it.
A year later, the question remains.Th e
Mexican press is operating in an ill-defin e d
c o n t e x t .It has replaced its old docility with
persistent opposition,helped bring about
the change in power and is now wondering
what side of the fence it can or should be
on—criticizing the new government or
generously giving it the benefit of the
doubt.
Is the press truly ready to be part of a
genuine transition? I am not optimistic.
Mexico has a high birth rate as far as the
press is concerned—every week a new
publication seems to hit the streets—but
there are very few readers.After last year’s
election fever, with unemployment now
on the rise and purchasing power in
d e c l i n e, readers are drifting away.Wi t h o u t
state subsidies, small or family-owned
papers and those stuck to the ways of the
past are disappearing.
The challenge is how to adapt to the
new situation. In Fo x ’s pragmatic world
there is only room for the strongest and, i t
would appear, for the business-minded. I n
M e x i c o, the information industry could
well draw foreign investors, especially now
that the doors of our economy are not just
open but have disappeared altogether.
It remains to be seen how much press
criticism Fox’s government,which is itself
a child of the opposition, is prepared to
t o l e r a t e. New governments tend to be over-
sensitive toward the press.We shall have to
wait and see. ■
+ …
Mexico publishes 328 newspapers and 1,600
magazines. Excélsior has a daily circulation of
130,000.
Source: National Chamber of the Mexican
Publishing Industry, 2001
Censored! The Guatemalan newspaper
Many papers didn’t
want to stop 
acting like poodles,
but they sensed a
change of master was
imminent.
68 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
21st century renamed itself 14th century.
INTERVIEW BY LOUISE CORRADINI
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Rise of a new watchdog 
in Latin A m e r i c a
Buoyed by the spread of democracy, Latin America’s press is fast gaining in influence, boldness and
credibility, says journalism professor Mario Diament1. The technology revolution stands to make the
process irreversible
L atin America has been through
quite a few profound political
t ransitions over the past two
d e c a d e s. What part has the
p ress played in this process?  Is
t h e re a kind of regional model that defin e s
its relationship with political power?
You can’t really talk about a
“regional model,” but of similar
e x p e r i e n c e s.According to conventional
wisdom,the more democracy you have,
the more press freedom there is, but this
still varies from one country to the next.
In the past, a sizeable part of the Latin
American press had close ties to political
and economic interests through its
owners. Those interests routinely took
precedence over journalistic impartiality.
But during the 1970s, journalists became
very politicized. Many became
subversive and partisan writers,
distorting the role of the press and badly
undermining its credibility. However in
the 1980s, as democracy spread across
the region and a new generation of
journalists less marked by past events
came to the fore, a very refreshing and
positive change took place.
Can you give a few examples?
Mexico and Guatemala are two of
the most interesting cases.The Chiapas
uprising in Mexico had the effect of
cutting short press allegiance to the
ruling party, the PRI, which went hand-
in-hand with rampant corruption.
Chiapas came on so suddenly that the
government of President Carlos Salinas
d i d n ’t have time to put together a media
strategy to deal with the situation.As a
result,part of the Mexican press began
reporting very openly on events. I think
i t ’s safe to say that to a large extent, t h i s
new attitude on the part of the press
sounded the death knell of one-party
domination and opened the way for
Vicente Fo x ’s victory in the presidential
elections in 2000.
In Guatemala, during the short-lived
seizure of full powers by President Jo r g e
Serrano on May 25,1993, censorship was
imposed and the press defied the
government for the first time. Th e
newspaper Siglo Ve i n t i u n o ( 2 1 s t
Century) renamed itself Siglo Catorce
(14th Century) and ran black columns in
the place of censored material, e x p o s i n g
the government’s attempt to stop the
press from reporting on events.
Colombia should also be mentioned:
many journalists have and continue to
risk their lives there reporting amid
threats from guerrilla forces,p a r a m i l i t a r y
groups and drug-lords.
In the past,the Latin American press has
often been submissive and engaged in
s e l f - c e n s o rs h i p, sometimes to the point of
complicity with the powers in place.Why
has this changed?
In my eyes, the two most important
factors are the return to democracy and
the revolution in technology.The South
American dictatorships of the 1970s
created a spineless and obliging press, b u t
as these regimes began to crumble, the
media became more independent.Wi t h
the return to democracy, j o u r n a l i s t s
became even more daring and
inquisitive.
In some places, such as A r g e n t i n a ,
the press’ credibility and influence grew
as political parties became discredited.
During the 1989-99 rule of President
Carlos Menem, the Argentine press
published a remarkable series of
investigations into corruption and
money-laundering that shook the
g o v e r n m e n t .At one point, opinion polls
showed that the public trusted the press
more than any other institution in the
country, including the Catholic Church.
The revolution in technology, which
began with photocopies and faxes and
moved onto satellite TV and the
I n t e r n e t , has diversified information
sources to the point that nobody can
seriously hope to impose any kind of
c o n t r o l . The relative cheapness of the
technology has made the spread of
information more democratic than ever
before. ■
1. An Argentine journalist and play w r i g h t
living in Miami, where he is professor
of journalism at Florida International
University.
M E D I A ◗
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 69
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
Fe r n a n d o
S a v a t e r
70 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
◗ T A L K I N G T O . . .
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
o u ’ re a philosopher,
writer and univers i t y
p ro f e s s o r. Despite your
many activities and over
45 books that you’ve
w r i t t e n , it seems people
only want to hear your
views on the Basque
conflict.Does that upset you?
I t ’s a little tedious and one-
dimensional because one does many things
in one’s life, maybe too many, though the
only thing that interests people is the fact
that one day you stood at a corner with a
p l a c a r d . But in the end it’s just one of
those problems. Nobody’s required to be
interested in philosophy, but I think you
should be interested in your own country.
I ’ve got no desire to draw attention to
m y s e l f. I just want to use the audience I can
attract to promote something that seems
vital to me—defending the rule of law and
fighting totalitarianism in my country.
It must be terrible to be unable to move
without bodyguards.
The other day someone asked me with
the best intentions what I felt about that,
and in response I asked:what do you feel
like when you see a large number of your
fellow citizens—journalists, t e a c h e r s, t o w n
c o u n c i l l o r s, housewives—having to live
with bodyguards? Why should someone
with bodyguards have a psychological
p r o b l e m , but not the person who sees him
or her passing by with a police escort?
People should be asked how we can talk
about European unity when there’s
suddenly a part of the continent where
people can’t walk freely down the street.
The Basta Ya (Enough is enough) movement
that you’re the spokesman for has just been
a w a rded the Sakharov Prize for human
rights by the European Pa r l i a m e n t . Can you
tell us about Basta Ya?
I t ’s another of the many recent
attempts in the Basque country to
denounce and oppose violence. Perhaps
what makes this one special is that we’v e
taken to the streets not just to say what
w e d o n ’t want—violence, crime and
killings—but also to say what we do want,
namely autonomy and constitutional rule.
In other words, we think Spain’s rule of
law is better than what the Basque
separatists are calling for.This rule of law
can of course change and evolve, but not
by force.
In the quarter-century since the death of
G e n e ral Fra n c o, the Basque country, l i ke
other regions of Spain,has won increasing
a u t o n o m y, yet ETA terrorism has killed more
than 800 people.Why is there such violence?
The violence is fed by an ethnic-
totalitarian ideology that has developed
over time, probably incorporating
elements from the past, from the Franco
e r a , but which has festered and turned
into quite an unusual threat inside Europe,
because I really can’t see how such
extremes can now be justified.
Wh a t ’s happening in the Basque
country is unheard of. Violence is not
justified but in some places there are
genuine political and economic
inequalities and clear violations of human
rights that explain why it breaksout. This
is not the case in the Basque country.
What other places are you thinking of?
C o l o m b i a , for example, is an extremely
unjust country, with vast economic and
educational inequalities. I certainly don’t
think the guerrillas there represent a
liberation movement, but you can
understand why people take up arms.Th e
same goes for El Salvador, Guatemala and
I r e l a n d , where the Catholics have been
discriminated against and marginalized to
the advantage of Protestant unionists.A n d
of course, t h e r e ’s Palestine and the Middle
E a s t .Without going as far as saying armed
struggle is a good thing, you can
understand why people resort to violence
in some places.
Why do you think the Basque struggle is
different?
People in the Basque country have
the same freedoms as any other people in
E u r o p e. Th e r e ’s more political and
economic self-government than in the
German l ä n d e r, and it has its own
parliament with all political parties
r e p r e s e n t e d , including the separatists. I t ’s
a developed area with no economic
p r o b l e m s. The main Basque problem is
that there isn’t one—there’s no objective,
historical or economic basis for one.And
ETA’s ideas, or to put it bluntly, the ideas
of Basque nationalism, w o u l d n ’t be taken
seriously were it not for the violence. Just
as they aren’t taken seriously in France.
Why is that?
For two reasons.The fir s t ,as the Fr e n c h
ought to know or recall, is that the Fr e n c h
Basque nationalists were discredited by
their collaboration with the Nazis. Hitler
began trying to expand his rule throughout
Europe by preaching freedom, a u t o n o m y
and self-determination for Europe’s ethnic
minorities. Many minorities collaborated
with the Nazis because they thought that
if Hitler destroyed Fr a n c e, for example,
he would give the Basques special status,
and if he conquered England, he would
free the Irish.The fall of Hitler at the end
of the Second World War silenced the
French Basque nationalists for quite a long
t i m e. S e c o n d l y, we must not forget that
ultra-nationalist positions are hard to
reconcile with a citizens’ Europe. If they
h a d n ’t used violence, who would have
given them the time of day? In a free and
prosperous country, where the local
language and human rights are respected,
who is really going to be interested in
Y
The hostage
of purity
Differences aren’t necessarily a good thing, says Basque
philosopher Fernando Savater. Threatened with death for his
opposition to armed struggle, he practises his own brand of
“active pessimism,” fighting weapons with words 
July/August 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 71
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
“I don’t believe that it’s legitimate to replace
a civic democracy with an ethnic democracy”
THINKING UNDER SURV E I L L A N C E
He’s been called Spain’s Jean-Paul Sartre and compared to Salman Rushdie. They also say he’s a hero,
though he hates that.He’s just a concerned citizen with an interest in nationalism,for simple reasons
of self-defence.
Fernando Savater, born in San Sebastián in 1947, studied philosophy and literature in Madrid, where he
began his career as an assistant lecturer at the Autonomous University. But after a brief spell in Franco’s
jails, he was expelled from the teaching profession in 1971 for political reasons. In 1975, he earned his
doctorate with a thesis on Nietzsche and shortly afterwards returned to teaching, this time ethics at the
University of the Basque Country. He has been teaching philosophy since 1995 at the University of Alcalá
de Henares, in Madrid,“although this year I haven’t been able to teach my classes because I was advised
not to for security reasons.”
Savater, who describes himself as “more a philosophy teacher than a philosopher,” has written more than
45 works—essays, novels and children’s books. His philosophical ideas, detailed in a personal
philosophical dictionary (unpublished in English) are based on thoughtful rebellion against the
establishment,with a touch of humour and irony.
His speciality is ethics, which he defines as “the belief that not everything is equally valuable and that
there are reasons for choosing one course of action over another.” He has written several books on the
subject,including The Task of the Hero (1982),which won the Spanish National Essay Prize that year, The
Questions of Life: Invitation to Philosophy (1982), Ethics as Self-Respect (1988) and Ethics for Amador
(1991),which has been translated into 18 languages.
In 1997,he published The Value of Education, an essay dedicated to his mother, who was his first teacher,
in which he professes that education is the cure for most of society’s ills. “Intolerance, fundamentalism
and extreme nationalism must be tackled from schooldays on,” he says. In January 2001,he published
an anthology of his many articles criticizing extreme nationalism that had been published in the Spanish
daily El País and the Bilbao daily El Correo. It is the catalogue of an unarmed battle against weapons, an
indictment of civil society for its passivity towards terrorist violence and a call to citizens to stand up to
the ETA.
A horse-racing fan, Savater has visited the world’s main racecourses. His latest book, “Astride the
Millennium”(2001,yet untranslated) is a collection of articles about horse-racing.
As well as the Sakharov Prize for human rights that he received in December 2000 on behalf of the civic
movement Basta Ya, for which he is the spokesman,Savater has won the Anagrama Prize, the Ortega y
Gasset Journalism Prize (2000) and the Fernando Abril Martorell Prize for “his contribution to the defence
and promotion of freedom,tolerance and human rights.”
The ETA has been threatening to kill him for several years now. He lives in San Sebastián and Madrid
with his bodyguards, from whose “friendly protection”he would be delighted to be “released as soon as
possible.” ■
setting up a state that has never existed
before?
What would you say to those who back the
ETA,at least in terms of its broad goals, on
the grounds that armed struggle is the only
way to gain independence?
Well it’s obviously the only way they’v e
got to gain independence since they’re a
minority in a society that doesn’t want it.
The ETA is as legitimate as a group of
armed bank robbers who, because they
d o n ’t have any money in the bank and the
manager isn’t going to give them any, f o r c e
their way in at gunpoint to get what they
w a n t . Both the methods and the very
ideology of ETA are illegitimate. I don’t
believe that it’s legitimate to replace a
civic democracy with an ethnic democracy.
Creating a state can be a political project
because states are made through
agreements, but it is not a right,nor is it a
duty, that people should be interested or
excited about a political programme
advocated by those whose ideology,
methods and ideas—half racist,half radical
Marxism—are not shared by the rest of the
population.
Some say the Basques suffered more than
other Spaniards during Franco’s regime.
That’s pure myth. Franco didn’t have
many Catalan ministers, but he did have
lots of Basques in his cabinet. He also
spent summers peacefully in a yacht off
San Sebastían’s La Concha beach,
something Prime Minister José María
Aznar obviously couldn’t do today. Th e
Falangist anthem, the Cara al Sol ( Face to
the Sun),was composed by a Basque. Of
c o u r s e, Basques were oppressed,
persecuted and wounded like all other
S p a n i a r d s. The Basque language was
m a r g i n a l i z e d , though not as much as
people said because there were still
conferences and classes in Euskara. But
the Basques suffered so little that their
provinces had the highest per capita
incomes in the whole country. Wh e n
Franco died in 1975, Guipúzcoa had the
highest and Vizcaya ranked second. I think
today they come 13th and 14th. So it’s a
myth that the Basques suffered more than
other Spaniards. Most Basques—and of
course most of those who became
nationalists only after Franco died, since
until then they’d been his supporters—
b e n e fited from Fr a n c o ’s regime at the
expense of other Spaniards.
Some historians are surprised that Spain
made no effort to commemorate the past
during the transition period. Franco died,
and the next day there was a constitutional
m o n a rc h y. Don’t Spaniards want to
remember?
The vast majority of Spanish society
tried to look the other way during Fr a n c o ’s
rule, especially in the final years. People
told themselves:“ D o n ’t get too mixed up
in the details—let the guy die naturally, h e
doesn’t have much longer to go.” In the
Basque country, the process of
remembering was more of an agreement
to forget: “ I ’ll forget what you’ve done
and you forget what I’ve done.” In 1978
there was a general amnesty in the Basque
country for every kind of crime, a n
amnesty so global and absolute that its
72 The UNESCO Courier - July/August 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
like had never been seen before in
Europe. The excuse for not investigating
o f ficials from Fr a n c o ’s regime was that
the Basque terrorists were not being
investigated either.The ETA militant who
had murdered was freed, as was the
general or police chief who had committed
other crimes.
Are there any minorities whose claims to
self-determination are legitimate?
Self-determination is a political right
People might think you are against
minorities...
I’m not against them.We all belong to
minorities that are caricatured by others—
to groups of enthusiasts, interest groups
or religions. I belong to the minority of
people who love horse-racing, b u t
anthropologists don’t talk up for us and
w e ’re not represented at the United
Nations. The world is full of such groups,
and there’s nothing wrong with that.Wh a t
I’m against is people inventing identities for
certain groups and fragmenting humanity
even more, instead of seeking to bring the
b e n e fits of civilization to all. E s p e c i a l l y
when the identities feature the circumcision
of women or other such outrages.
But isn’t there a risk of uniformity?
I don’t think we need to crave
difference or be horrified by similarity.
Being different is not good in itself. Some
differences are valuable and enriching and
increase the joy of human existence, but
others are terrible ancestral leftovers best
forgotten as soon as possible. So slavery is
different to an employment contract,but
an employment contract is better and it
would be silly for the sake of diversity to
have some people with work contracts
and others as slaves. I would like the whole
world to be educated, have social security
and give protection to children,pregnant
women and old people. It’s a pity that the
world is becoming more uniform only in
and a historic achievement by certain
communities who join together to form
s t a t e s. For historical reasons, the borders
and area of modern Spain are not those of
1,000 years ago and may be different again in
1,000 years’ t i m e. The same goes for the
United States or anywhere else. But that
d o e s n ’t have anything to do with minorities.
The world has about 200 countries and more
than 5,000 languages, which means most
countries contain many languages and ethnic
groups.
The Basque country (Euskadi) is one of Spain’s 17
autonomous regions. Since 1979,it has had two
official languages, Spanish and Euskera, and
since elections in 1980, its own parliament. The
autonomous Basque government is responsible
for education,health and taxation and has more
powers than any other regional body in Europe.
The ETA (Euskadi Ta A s k a t a s u n a , or Basque
Fatherland and Freedom) is calling for
independence for Euskal Herria, an are a
between the Ebro and Adour rivers that includes
Navarre, the Spanish Basque country and two
departments of southwest France.
The org a n i z a t i o n , founded by a group of
students in 1959, carried out its first terrorist
actions in 1968 and has since caused the death
of more than 800 people, 90 percent of them
after the advent of democracy in 1975.
For many years,the ETA’s main targets were the
police and the army, but in recent years, it has
stepped up physical attacks on politicians and
extended them to other sectors of society, such
as university teachers and journalists.
S P A I N
Vitoria
Bilbao
MADRID
F R A N C E
Atlantic Ocean
THE BASQUE COUNTRY: 33 YEARS OF CONFLICT
Basque country
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 51) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396 French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 48French francs ( 7. 32 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:     Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
“Purity produces nothing. Virgins don’t 
bear children”
commercial terms, with speculative capital
rushing back and forth, and not in
desirable things like education and the
defence of human rights.
Do you regret globalization?
U n f o r t u n a t e l y, despite another myth I
hear a lot, I don’t see the world moving
towards equality for all—far from it.
Differences between let’s say Sweden and
Rwanda are going to increase, n o t
d i m i n i s h . Yet some countries have such
horrifying features that you would wish
for a more uniform world in terms of
respect for basic rights.
What should we be fighting for these days?
Creative ability. I t ’s vital that we
defend all possibilities for creation
wherever they are. Conservation of some
oddity because “ i t ’s always existed here”—
when in fact it’s a matter of four or five
folklore experts, archaeologists or
anthropologists conjuring up a historical
identity that everyone then has to conform
to—really doesn’t help at all. So I’m not in
the slightest worried about identity,w h i c h
I’m not interested in at all,or defending
p l u r a l i s m , which I think is guaranteed
because people will always be born
different to each other.
What about cultural mixing?
The whole history of humanity is a
constant process of mixing.The greatness
of the human species is precisely that we’r e
all a mixture of something. When the
human race started in A f r i c a , we were
probably all black and identical, but bit
by bit we became different, taking on
various ethnicities,colours and sizes.Th o s e
multiple mixtures are the salt of the earth,
and will be even more so in a century,
when you’ll be able to travel and circle
the world in just a few hours, o r
communicate through a computer at the
other end of the planet. In my opinion,
everything pure—pure identity, p u r e
ethnicity—seems sterile. Purity produces
nothing. Virgins don’t bear children.
You say education can also change things
and describe it as “supreme anti-fatalism,
the only way to free people from their fate.”
Please explain.
Societies where education plays no
part are stratified societies, in which each
group is supposed to follow in the footsteps
of its ancestors or the minority they belong
t o.The peasant’s son learns from his father
how to till the fie l d s, mothers exchange
information about children and childbirth,
and soldiers learn how to shoot arrows or
ride horses because that is the destiny
society has given them. E d u c a t i o n , on the
other hand, moulds open-minded humans
who can fit any number of roles within
society. Greece in the time of Pericles, for
e x a m p l e,educated its citizens so that each
could become whatever he wished,
whereas there was no education in the
Persian Empire because everyone was
predestined to play a set role. In our
modern-day society there’s also a kind of
fatalism condemning the child of a poor
person always to be poor, and the child of
an uneducated person always to be
u n e d u c a t e d .E d u c a t i o n , on the other hand,
is a progressive force, powerful enough to
bust that social fatalism and create
something new. In open,mobile societies,
the street-sweeper’s child can become
president or head of a university thanks to
education.
In this reinvention of society thro u g h
e d u c a t i o n , what parts do the family, t h e
school and the pupils respectively play?
By education, I don’t just mean its
academic side, which is the easiest to
m e a s u r e, but is not the sole kind of
l e a r n i n g.Although the family has evolved
and is not the same as it was half a century
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George’s Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
Gordon & Gotch Australia Pty. Ltd., Private Bag 290, Burwood VIC 3125 .
Fax: 03 9888 8561
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Partner Press, 11 rue Charles Parenté, B-1070 Brussels.
Fax: (32 2) 556 41 46/Tel.: (32 2) 556 41 40/partner press@ampnet.be
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: UNES CO O f fice, 8 Po o rvi Marg, Vasant Vihar, New Delhi 110 0 57.
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Editions Le Printemps Ltée., 4 Route du Club, Va c o a s .
Fax: 686 7302. 
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
UNES CO Etxea, Alda Urquijo 60, Ppal. Dcha., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: Distriplumes, Apartado 49232, Colinas Bello Monte, 10 4 2
A Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 979 8 36 0
UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce C/C
Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 28 6 0 326 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
a g o, it still has a role in bringing respect and
emotional intelligence into the world.Th e
problem is that adults in today’s families
h a v e,or say they have, little time to educate
their children, often preferring to pay
others to carry out this work. S c h o o l
education for its part acclimatizes children
to a more egalitarian and abstract world
that is not just about feelings, but also legal
entitlements, which is an important step
f o r w a r d . The media of course educates
people too,as do socially influential people
such as performers and sports
p e r s o n a l i t i e s. But in the end, i t ’s the person,
the pupil, the beginner who learns. Th e
most us teachers can do is teach. Only the
pupils can learn.What we have to do above
all else is awaken the child’s willingness to
do so. As soon as that appears, he or she
will find the best ways to move forward.
Your books Ethics for Amador and Politics for
Amador were attempts to explain to your
son Amador and other childre n , the bases of
those subjects. Do you think children are
really interested in that?
I ’ve never met a young person who
i s n ’t . Most aren’t interested in learning
such things from their teachers, but in all
my 30 years in education,I’ve never met
kids of 15 or 16 who weren’t interested in
freedom,beauty, justice and death.But I
have certainly known adults busy making
money and doing other things they believe
are important who’ve stopped being
concerned by these things.
At the risk of boring you, I would like to
finish by asking if you’re hopeful about a
solution to the Basque crisis.
There is a m i l o n g a [a popular
Argentine song] which says hope often
means wanting a rest. If this is the case,
then hope means saying:“ w e ’ll sort this out
in the end, bit by bit, through life and
t i m e.” I don’t think space or time will sort
out anything by themselves—that’s why
I’m an active pessimist. Things don’t get
settled on their own: the situation is very
serious and utterly awful. Letting Europe
know what’s happening here, so that it
takes responsibility or somehow helps
those of us fighting fascism, could prove of
use. The same people who rallied to help
those threatened by totalitarianism in
Kosovo and elsewhere need to take action
h e r e.When you do something you hope it
turns out well, and in that sense it is
optimistic because you think the situation
might improve. But it isn’t an automatic
process. The problem isn’t about getting
nationalists and constitutionalists to reach
agreement—it’s nothing to do with that.
Are we going to change the way we
educate our children? Are we going to
change the propaganda on television? A r e
we going to change the systematic instilling
of hatred in the Basque country for
everything connected with Spain or the
Spaniards, who make up more than half
the population living here? Are we going
to change that? Is there some law that can
be passed to change that? We have to keep
on struggling.
Are you going to continue?
I’m going to try, if I’m allowed to.
INTERVIEW BY
LUCÍA IGLESIAS KUNTZ
Fernando Savater marching in a Basta Ya demonstration in San Sebastián.
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
54th year
Published monthly in 28 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Cynthia Guttman
Spanish edition: Louise Corradini
French edition: Sophie Boukhari,Philippe Demenet
Michel Bessières
Ivan Briscoe
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Shiraz Sidhva
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: Gérard Prosper,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Pushplata Taneja (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Sardinian:Diego Corraine (Nuoro)
Russian:Valeri Kharkin (Moscow)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing the
credit line reads “Reprinted from the UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author’s
n a m e. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering
p o s t a g e. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by:
(1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,
A n nA r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 1 1 1
West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road,
Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - JULY 2001
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly
in Paris by UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e.
Periodicals postage paid at Champlain NY and additional mailing offic e s.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 07-2001-OPI 00-592 A
June 2001 -The Unesco Courier 75
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[
Focus:
■ Indigenous people: forever invisible
■ The rise and fall of science-based racism
■ India’s untouchables: a 25-million strong pariah
■ Xenophobia engulfs Africa
■ Brazil: beyond the rainbow façade
■ How Europe screens its immigrants
■ The racist spin on globalization 
Features include:
■ Can we feed the planet without genetically modified food?
■ Wanted: teachers in the North
■ Intangible heritage: taking stock of our living legends
■ Ad-free television for kids: is the Swedish model
ready for export?  
■ Talking to Amartya Sen, India’s Nobel laureate
for economics
In the next issue
many voices one world
FOCUS
September 2001:
Racism, xenophobia,
discrimination,
ethnic hatred…
The sources
of a global scourge
@ www.unesco.org/courier
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
Published in 28 languages
]]>
</page>
</document>
