<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="123512eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
P ro fil de
l ’ i n t e r n a u t e
en rupture
de To i l e
Le nucléaire,
p a ra d e
à l’effet
de serre ?
I t s u k u s h i m a
et son temple:
le temps
re t ro u v é
Afrique CFA:1000 F.CFA,Antilles:18 FF, Belgique:160 FB, Canada:3,95$Can,
Espagne:550 Ptas, USA:4,25 $US, Luxembourg:154 F.Lux, Portugal:700 Esc ,
Suisse:6,20 FS , United Kingdom:2,5£,Maroc:20 DH.C h i l d ren as
cannon fodder
in 41 countries
Can GMOs
feed a hungry
w o r l d ?
The advent
of “ i n t a n g i b l e
h e r i t a g e ”
Adam Michnik:
the Sisyphus
o f d e m o c ra c y
September 2001
Canada:$4.65 Can,United Kingdom:£2.5,USA:$4.25
Why ra c i sm?
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
7, place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.orgU N E S C O Publishing
Dream Trackers
Yapa Art and Knowledge of the Australian Desert
■ Aboriginal artists and story-tellers lead us on a journey
through their ritual painting, singing and dancing, on 
the tracks of their Dreaming Ancestors, who are embodied in
the land.
■ The complex, cultural, ritual and ecological knowledge 
of the Warlpiri people.
■ An ideal tool to convey the dynamism and wealth 
of oral traditions.
Prices and license agreements 
for museums or learning institutions: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
Atlas of the World’s Languages 
in Danger of Disappearing 
New enlarged and updated edition
By Stephen A. Wurm
Cartographer, Ian Heyward
■ Close to half of the 6,000 languages spoken in the world
are doomed or likely to disappear in the foreseeable future, 
an irreparable loss for the heritage of humankind. 
■ This new edition of the Atlas of the World’s Languages 
in Danger of Disappearing is intended to give a graphic picture
of the magnitude of the problem in many parts of the world. 
90,00 FF / 13,72, 90 pp., maps, index, 20 x 29 cm
Online version available at www.unesco.org/publishing
Seven Complex Lessons 
in Education for the Future
By Edgar Morin
■ Some fundamental problems are overlooked or neglected in
education. These problems, presented as ‘seven complex
lessons’, should be covered in all culture, according to means
and rules appropriate to those societies and cultures. 
■ Provocative essay by Edgar Morin, to stimulate discussion
on how education can and should act as a force for the future
and promote a transdisciplinary perspective to meet the great
challenge of sustainable development.
60,00 FF / 9,15, 95 pp., 21 x 14,5 cm
Online version available at www.unesco.org/publishing
CD-ROM
14 hours of navigation, 
500 photos, 
3 hours of songs and stories in Warlpiri, 
1/2 hour of film.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
◗ PEOPLE AND PLACES
4 Jerusalem Utopia
A plea for peace in the city of three religions.
Photos by David Sauveur, text by André Chouraqui
◗ PLANET
10 Can genetically modified organisms feed the world?
Biotechnologies might usher in the next Green Revolution, but many wonder whether poor
farmers will benefit . Philippe Demenet
◗ WORLD OF LEARNING
13 New Zealand: the right medicine
An International Literacy Day prize-winning programme steps straight
into the workplace. Libby Middlebrook
15 Learning Hebrew Ethiopian-style Allyn Fisher-Ilan
◗ ETHICS
38 The child in arms
In Myanmar, an estimated 50,000 children have been recruited to fig h t
in the country’s protracted ethnic wa r s. Bertil Lintner
40 Converting the cannon fodder Interview with Jo Becker
◗ CULTURE
41 Preserving the magic
D a n c e, m u s i c , theatre and crafts now have their own UN E S C O heritage list,
but defining the intangible is no simple job. Richard Kurin
43 A tangible debut Asbel López
◗ MEDIA
44 Temptation-free television for children ? 
Sweden would like the rest of Europe to follow its strict policy on advertising,
but powerful lobbies are ready for a fig h t . Pascaline Dumont
◗ TALKING TO…
47 Adam Michnik: the Sisyphus of democracy
The dissident at heart struggles with democracy’s eternal imperfection.
Detailed table of contents on page
1 6
Fo c u s C o l o u r, n a t i o n , ethnic hate…
Why Racism?
Once founded on the traditional notion of
“ ra c e,” racial discrimination today comes
i n many guises, whether based on one’s colour,
nation (xenophobia), ethnic belonging or caste.
This dossier looks at its roots and impact
o n indigenous groups and black communities
i n Latin A m e r i c a , the lowest castes in A s i a , a n d
f o re i g n e rs in Africa and Western Euro p e. E c h o i n g
the World Conference against Racism (Durban,
South A f r i c a , August 31-September 7), we strive
to give a voice to the hundreds of millions of 
victims around the world.
“We are one.”
SEPTEMBER 2001
C O N T E N T S
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily re p resent the opinions of UN E S C O or those of the
e d i t o rs of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r s t a f f. The boundaries on maps do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the
United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
I N T H I S I S S U E
◗ Democracy
It may involve an endless search
for compromise, but former Polish
dissident Adam Michnik is proud to
see democracy at work in his country
(interview, pp. 47-51).In stark contrast
to utopian projects, he says, the aim of
democracy is to deal with clashing
viewpoints and eclipse discrimination
in any shape or form. While “scientific
racism” is on the wane, millions of
people around the world are victims
of racial discrimination,which comes
in many guises (pp. 16-37). Their
plight represents a formidable
challenge for the World Conference
against Racism, Racial
Discrimination,Xenophobia and
Related Intolerance (Durban, South
Africa, August 31-September 7).
◗ Education
The figure is not mentioned often
enough:300,000 children serve
as cannon fodder for an array
of guerrilla groups and regular armies.
Is there a way out for these 15-year-
old veterans? One is to give them
a chance to catch up on the school
years they’ve missed (pp. 38-40).
Otherwise, they too will join
the world’s 900 million illiterates.
International Literacy Day on
September 8 rewards organizations
which refuse to accept the status quo,
like Workbase in New Zealand,while
recognizing the innovative efforts
made by many other prize candidates
like Israel (pp. 13-15).
◗ Malnutrition
Can genetically modified organisms
feed the Third World? Many experts
and biotechnology companies say
“Yes.” But other agronomists
are more sceptical:without equity
and reforms, new technology will only
make the rich richer (pp. 10-12).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
PHOTOS BY DAVID SAUVEUR, TEXT BY ANDRÉ CHOURAQUI
DAVID SAUVEURIS A FRENCH PHOTOGRAPHER; ANDRÉ CHOURAQUI HASTRANSLATEDTHE BIBLE ANDWRITTEN SEVERAL BOOKS.
HIS LATESTWORKS INCLUDE JÉRUSALEM, VILLE SANCTUAIRE (EDITIONS DU ROCHER 1997) AND LE FEUDE L'ALLIANCE (BAYARD PRESSE 2001).
Jerusalem Utopia
The Church of the Holy Sepulchre, rebuilt in the 11th century when Jerusalem was seized during the crusades.
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
“Above all Jerusalem, whose name awakens so many mysteries and startles the imagination: it seems
that everything must be extraordinary in this extraordinary city.”
Chateaubriand, Itinéraire de Paris à Jérusalem (1811)
Je r u s a l e m , the ancient capital of Ju d e a , has been resuscitated
today as a microcosm of the entire world, in all its contrasts and
most glaring contradictions. Stand at an intersection in the city,
and you’ll see pass by a collection of the world’s most diverse
people, hailing from every country and century.
Since 1950 I have watched these crowds—crowds which no-
one could have imagined or planned. The government of Israel
opened the gates of Jerusalem to all Jews who wanted to move
The tunnel beneath the Wailing Wall,sole remant of the temple destroyed in 70 A.D. by the Romans.
IN MEMORY OF RENÉ CASSIN,
THEMAIN DRAFTER OFTHE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS
t h e r e. They have flowed in since from around the world,
becoming neighbours in the city of Christ with Ja p a n e s e
M a k u y a s1,members of 45 different Christian denominations and
Muslims representing all the rites and geographic origins of
Islam.
The merchants of the Old City hawk their products to
passers-by and, in honour of trading tradition,barter over prices.
Depending on the season,market stalls overflow with oranges,
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
An Orthodox Christian in the Holy Sepulchre.
The conflict,which the United Nations had hoped to settle,
has continued to this day through war between the state of
Israel and the Palestinian people’s representatives.The creation
of a Palestinian state would help to end the violence that still
drenches the city of peace in blood.The union of two states,o n e
Israeli,the other Palestinian,in a single confederation open to
other countries in the Middle East, could bring peace and
progress to all in the future.2
No one,h o w e v e r, can speak of Jerusalem without mentioning
its prophets, the tragedies of its history, the 2,000-year-old exile
of its people and their homecoming after the Shoah. Then,the
foundation of the state of Israel and its tragic consequences
for the Muslim population, the Arabs’ refusal to create a
Palestinian state, the resulting inextricable conflict and the
consecutive stalemate, made worse by a smouldering war that
dares not speak its name.
No war can settle the conflict between two nationalisms
and the three religions that share blood-soaked Jerusalem.Let
us recognize that, and proclaim that this city is the historic
capital of the three religions which have their roots there. Let us
unite the people who live in the city by dividing their
responsibilities:the holy sites are already administered by the
religions laying claim to them.
Let us bring the Hebrew Bible, the Greek New Testament
and the Arab Koran back to what they originally stood for:
peace and reconciliation. Let Jerusalem at last become the
model capital for universal peace, as the prophets of the three
religions stemming from Abraham had always dreamt.
Jerusalem Utopia
Amongst the remains of the Herodian quarter ( first century B.C.).
g r a p e s,dates and all the other fruits and vegetables that grow in
the city’s many orchards and gardens.
S p i c e s, i n c e n s e, c a k e s, pitta bread and sweets proliferate
alongside religious trinkets and local crafts, made from wood and
metal according to age-old techniques in little workshops nestled
in the Old City’s narrow streets. It is here that tens of thousands
of pilgrims from every corner of Christendom flock to gaze on
Christ’s tomb.
Alongside Judaism and Christianity, another religion born
from the Bible’s fertile soil takes special interest in the city, for
Jerusalem is also the place where the Prophet Muhammad
ascended to A l l a h ’s heaven to meet A b r a h a m , Moses and Je s u s.
All of Jerusalem—all 30 centuries of fervent history—are
concentrated in 90 hectares enclosed by ramparts.
The city has roots in the Hebrew Bible (or the Book of the
C o v e n a n t ) , the New Testament (or Book of the New Covenant)
and the Koran (or Book of the Realization of all the Covenants
since A b r a h a m ) . A revived Jerusalem became the land of
Israel’s homecoming after the Balfour Declaration (1917) and
the United Nations resolutions on November 29,1947, which
recommended the creation on territory then under a British
mandate of two states—one Israeli, one Palestinian—around
Je r u s a l e m , placed under UN control.That homecoming was to
reconcile all of A b r a h a m ’s children—Je w s, Christians and
Muslims—and enable them to achieve together their common
ideal:the universal covenant of humanity.
Let Jerusalem at last 
become the model capital 
for universal peace
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
6 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Is it utopian to believe that in the New Israel and its reborn
c a p i t a l , M u s l i m s, Christians and Jews can dwell together in
peace? If you think so, know that the future of world peace
depends on achievement of this utopia.And that is probably why
the psalms attributed to King David already exhorted:
Pray for the peace of Jerusalem! (Psalm 122.6 ).
Why especially Jerusalem? Because this city is where
c u l t u r e s, religions and people of all ages and languages meet.Ye s,
let us pray for the peace of Je r u s a l e m , a peace that could
foreshadow that of the world’s other cultures, w h e n , q u i t e
simply, all men and women will recognize each other as their
brothers and sisters. ■
1. A group of Japanese Christians who since WWII have sought
closer ties with traditional Christianity, the “people of the
Bible”and Judaism.
2. André Chouraqui:Lettre à un ami arabe, J.-C.L a t t è s, 1 9 9 4 ,a n d
Jérusalem revisitée, Ed.du Rocher, 1995.
Stalls selling to tourists and pilgrims in the Old City’s Christian Quarter.
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Jerusalem Utopia
Near Damascus Gate, the northern entry to the Old City, where traces remain of the Ottomans, Romans,Byzantines and the crusades.
This city is where cultures, 
religions and people of all ages 
and languages meet.
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
8 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Sugar and honey: pastries in Arab Jerusalem.
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
N
PHILIPPE DEMENET
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Can genetically modifie d
o rganisms feed the world?
The controversy over biotechnologies is raging. Advocates claim they’re the only answer
to malnutrition, while opponents warn that drought-resistant millet and vaccinated yams will only
increase poverty
ear A f r i c a ’s mighty Niger River, f a r m e r s
are anxiously waiting for rain to fall
before they sow millet or sorghum,then
h o e, h a r v e s t , feed their families and
replenish their granaries. M e a n w h i l e,
researchers in Ja p a n e s e, C h i n e s e,
P h i l i p p i n e, European and U. S.
laboratories are making strides in
sequencing the 12 chromosomes and
50,000 genes composing rice, the matrix of
all grains and a staple for three billion
human beings. In five to ten years, they
hope to know enough to genetically
modify not only rice, but millet, s o r g h u m ,
manioc and sugar cane as well.The aim is
to make them “ n a t u r a l l y ” resistant to
drought,soil salinity, viruses, blights and
other scourges.
Will these genetically modified
organisms (GMOs) really guarantee
“food security”in the short term for the
w o r l d ’s 826 million undernourished
i n d i v i d u a l s ?1 Will they help the small-
scale farmers cultivating the Niger’s
b a r r e n , powdery soil to feed their
families? The controversy is raging. In its
2001 report, the United Nations
Development Programme (UNDP) says
they will, emphasizing GMOs’ “unique
potential”to feed the world.In 50 years,
the Earth’s population will have soared to
nine billion— three billion more than
today.2 And most of the newcomers will
increase the already overwhelming
pressure on the southern countries’ much-
depleted soil.The alarm has already been
sounded for sub-Saharan Africa where,
unlike India and China, the population
growth rate is still sky-high and the
When it comes to developing technologies for indigent farmers,scientists rely mainly on the cash-strapped public sector.
◗ P L A N E T
10 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
number of undernourished people is
barely declining. GMO supporters say
only a major,revolutionary “ t e c h n o l o g i c a l
l e a p ” will enable the planet to feed all
its children.
Experimenting with
miracle seeds
But others strongly disagree,a r g u i n g
that low food production is not what
causes malnutrition. There is enough to
eat in the southern countries, they say.
But the world’s poorest people, t h o s e
with neither money nor land, living in
d i s i n t e g r a t i n g,w a r-torn countries, s i m p l y
have no access to food. They argue that
land-use conditions must change, p o o r
people must have access to credit and
local markets and small land-owners must
be freed from money-lenders.Better use
could be made of traditional seeds instead
of importing high-risk technology with
unpredictable consequences, most of
whose patents belong to giant
multinationals.
Advocates of the GMO revolution
work in biogenetics laboratories,
multinational seed and agrochemical
companies, genome research,American
foundations and some UN agencies,w h i l e
most skeptics are out in the field.A case
in point is Kanayo Nwanzé, a Ph.D. i n
agronomy who heads Adrao (Association
for the Development of Rice Growing
in West Africa) in Bouaké,Côte d’Ivoire.
“Are GMOs being developed for the
needs of small-scale farmers or
multinational corporations?” he asks.“ I f
we manage to negotiate with these
patent-holding multinationals a
technology that meets the needs of small-
scale farmers and that’s not under license,
then ‘ Ye s ! ,’ GMOs will have a role to
play in A f r i c a . But their impact will have
to come under careful scrutiny and the
r e g i o n ’s countries must have safety rules
and the means to enforce them.”
Adrao researchers have experience
with miracle seeds. With international
f u n d i n g, they have developed a
revolutionary variety of rice called Nerica.
Genetically unmodifie d , it is the result
of a conventional cross between a high-
yield but fragile variety of Asian rice and
a local variety that has had 35 centuries to
adapt to Africa’s stressful environment.
Nerica offers tremendous possibilities. I t
reaches maturity in 90 days instead of
the usual 120 to 150, resists insects, y i e l d s
three tonnes per hectare with neither
fertilizers nor irrigation—compared with
1.5 tonnes for traditional varieties—and
grows like a weed. I d e a l l y, it should
improve life for hundreds of thousands of
small-scale farmers who practice pluvial
rice farming on plots of land ranging in
size from 20 to 200 square metres and
help West Africa’s countries drastically
cut their rice imports, perhaps even to
export the grain.
Fear and red tape
H o w e v e r, this breakthrough is having
d i f ficulty leaving the laboratory. Th e r e
are approximately 3,000 variants of
N e r i c a , and for four years Nwanzé has
been trying to involve small-scale farmers
in selecting which ones to market.But in
the summer of 2001,only a thousand Côte
d’Ivoire farmers grew this “miracle rice”
on a total of just one hectare. . . . R e d
t a p e, administrative delays and lack of
communication between ministries and
farmers, seed-certification organizations
and rural credit institutions are to blame.
A “technological leap” is not likely to
help matters much.On the contrary.“If we
offer a farmer genetically modified seeds,
he’ll say ‘no thanks, I don’t want to kill
myself!’”says the head of Adrao.
Several A f r i c a n , Asian and South
American countries have already passed
laws regulating GMO production. B u t
can they enforce them? Wh i c h
laboratories will monitor the changes in
biodiversity that might result from
unforeseen crossbreeding between
GMOs and related wild species? A n d
with what funding? Who will see to it
that pollen from GMOs capable of
transmitting their defense mechanisms
against insects and viruses do not spread?
Researchers retort that it would be a
mistake to focus on first-generation
G M O s, which are necessarily flawed.
“Soon we’ll see the appearance of the
s e c o n d , third and fourth generations,
which will meet developing countries’
needs better,” says Jean Claude Prot, w h o
is currently dissecting rice’s 12th
chromosome at the Development
Research Institute,a French public outfit
affiliated with the International Rice
Genome Sequence Project.
Biogenetics makes it possible, f o r
example, to insert an insect’s gene into a
plant or vaccines into bananas or
potatoes. To create a variety of rice that
needs no more water than a camel
(instead of the 4,000 to 5,000 litres
The United States alone harbours 70% of the
world’s transgenic crops, followed by Argentina
(14%) and Canada (10%). Soya (used for oil and
flour for animal feed) accounts for 54% of these
cultivated areas, ahead of corn, colza and
cotton. 
Low prevalence and low depth of hunger
Moderate prevalence and low depth (and vice versa)
Moderate prevalence and moderate depth
High prevalence and moderate depth
High prevalence and high depth
Transgenic crops and malnutrition:maps that don’t overlap
Degrees of malnutrition GMOs in the world [ ]
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
necessary to produce one kilo), or again,
to enrich plants with vitamins and
minerals and develop others that
revitalize acidic soil devastated by over-
f a r m i n g. So why not carry out the wildest
projects?
It is easy to understand the
enthusiasm of certain researchers and
philanthropic institutions. For example,
the Rockefeller Foundation sees what it
calls the biotech-driven “second Green
Revolution”as a way to make up for the
first one’s mistakes and tragedies.Tr u e, i n
the 1960s, the Green Revolution helped
double food production by creating high-
yield varieties of wheat and rice, k e e p i n g
pace with the world’s population growth.
But these seeds, which need
plentiful inputs (irrigation,
f e r t i l i z e r s, herbicides and
p e s t i c i d e s ) , have primarily
b e n e fited farmers who could
afford to invest. Africa and
the poorest areas in Asia and
Latin America were left out.
M o r e o v e r, the results for
beneficiaries, such as China
and Vi e t n a m , are mixed:
traditional varieties have
v a n i s h e d , irrigation has
increased soil salinity, a n d
farmers have over- u s e d
herbicides and pesticides to
the detriment of their health
and the environment.
Great 
expectations
Supporters of the “second Green
R e v o l u t i o n ”say GMOs should spark an
explosive increase in yields without
inputs and in extreme farming conditions.
But will they benefit the poorest farmers?
Until now, multinational agrochemical
companies converted to the “ l i f e
s c i e n c e s ” have focused all their
investments on intensive crops with close
connections to industry and built a wall
of prohibitively-expensive patents
around their discoveries. Only publicly-
funded research has taken an interest in
indigent farmers living in tropical areas.
Strapped for cash,the public sector has
been forced to sign cooperation
agreements with the private sector at the
risk of losing its independence.
Major biotech companies are
a c c u s e d , of producing “ Fr a n k e n s t e i n
f o o d ,” especially in Europe.They quickly
caught onto the image-enhancing
advantages of helping to develop GMOs
for the Third Wo r l d . In 2000,amid a blaze
of publicity, biotech heavyweights
granted the free use of 70 patents to help
develop a genetically-modified variety of
rice enriched with beta carotene. Th e
grain was heralded as a “miracle rice”
capable of conquering Vitamin A
d e fic i e n cy, which kills one to two million
children each year. But so far, t h e
“golden rice” has fallen far short of
e x p e c t a t i o n s. The publicly-funded,
Philippines-based International Rice
Research Institute (IRRI) estimates that
it will take five to ten years before seeds
can be distributed free to farmers with
annual incomes of under $10,000, in line
with the agreements signed with industry.
F u r t h e r m o r e, it is still unclear how much
of the rice has to be consumed to make
up for a Vitamin A deficiency.
For non-governmental organizations
campaigning to protect the environment
and preserve biodiversity, such as the
Rural Advancement Fo u n d a t i o n
International (RAFI) network,this deal
“could kneecap other, low-tech and more
cost-effective solutions, such as re-
introducing the many vitamin-rich food
plants that were once cheap and
available.”
Lessons
from the past
Will GMOs help wipe out
malnutrition? The golden rice episode
has set the tone for the debate.A d v o c a t e s
say it would be utopian to wait for a better
world while existing technology can help
solve the problem here and now.“Some
argue that lack of food is simply a
problem of unequal distribution.
If poor people were not poor, t h e y
could buy the food they need,” s a y s
Rockefeller Foundation president
Gordon Conway. “ This is true, b u t
o v e r s i m p l i s t i c. There are no signs the
world is about to engage in a massive
redistribution of wealth.”
Adversaries of the “ G M O
r e v o l u t i o n ” have diametrically opposed
priorities:equity first,technology later.
Otherwise, they say, the same mistakes
that were made during the 1960s will
be repeated. The Green Revolution
“increased production and the number
of poor people at the same time,” says
Jean-Pierre Roca, director of France’s
Institute for Training and Support to
Development Initiatives.“ Where there
i s n ’t a credit system, middlemen and the
powerful are the ones who
appropriate improved seeds
and the use of pesticides.Th e
poorest farmers must go into
debt and sell their land to
wealthier ones. GMOs are
hazardous if measures aren’t
taken to go along with
them.”
A pragmatic Nwanzé says
that “GMOs aren’t a priority.
First it is necessary to improve
the conditions of agricultural
production and soil
m a n a g e m e n t , keep the
ground from getting hard
after clearing and decrease
rice imports by impoverished
West African countries. All that can be
achieved without GMOs, which run the
risk of impoverishing biodiversity.” ■
1. In 1996-98, 792 million of whom live in
developing countries (34% of the
population of sub-Saharan A f r i c a ,3 5 %
of the population in Asia) and 34
million in the developed countries
( s o u r c e : FAO, the United Nations Fo o d
and Agriculture Organization).
2. U.N. World Population Prospects: the
1998 Revision (United Nations, N e w
York,1999).
+ …
OGM, le champ des incertitudes (“GMOs, a
field of uncertainty,” published in French by
UNESCO-Solagral,2000).
http://www.solagral.org/publications/environn
ement/pedago/ogm_unesco_2000/indexbis.ht
m
www.rafi.org
www.irri.org
Nerica, a miracle rice still in search of fertile ground.
◗ P L A N E T
12 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
W
LIBBY MIDDLEBROOK
EDUCATION REPORTER FOR
THE NEW ZEALAND HERALD
New Zealand:
the right medicine
Rich or poor, no country is spared from a literacy problem. In New Zealand, caregivers
in a retirement home have gained a new grasp on their job thanks to Workbase, one of this month’s
International Literacy Day prize-winners 
hen Julie Ahloo was first employed as a
rest home caregiver four years ago, she
hardly spoke to her work mates.She kept
quiet to hide her difficulty with reading
and understanding the medical terms on
patients’ care plans. The 34-year- o l d
Samoan woman did not have the courage
to ask for help either, in case her poor
literacy skills caused her to lose her job.
At the time, Julie Ahloo was not the
only caregiver in this position at
Au c k l a n d ’s Mercy Parklands Hospital
and Retirement home.The 94-bed private
i n s t i t u t i o n ,owned by the Sisters of Mercy,
had noticed rising inaccuracies and lack
of detail in patient care plans, on which
caregivers are supposed to record a
r e s i d e n t ’s food and liquid intake and
other issues relating to their health.M a n y
of the 45 caregivers, employed to feed,
dress and bath patients,were also having
problems reading basic flow charts and
detailing a patient’s weekly activities,
including dates and times.
Overcoming shame
“ We thought the flow charts were
quite simple to understand,but we started
to realize that many of our workers
c o u l d n ’t understand basic math,” s a i d
Jacki Richardson, the chief executive of
M e r cy Parklands. In an effort to improve
the business’ day-to-day operation, M e r cy
Parklands decided to offer its staff on-site
l i t e r a cy and numeracy programmes, w i t h
the incentive of being paid to improve
their skills. Richardson said the business
also wanted to boost the confidence of its
caregiver staff members,who were largely
unqualified Maori and Pacific Island
women.Most spoke English as a second
l a n g u a g e. M e r cy Parklands was also
committed to running community
outreach projects, which could benefit
staff and their families.“ We really wanted
to improve staff morale...the caregivers
didn’t feel like they had anything to say,
but we wanted their input into the
business,” she said.
M e r cy Parklands employed
Wo r k b a s e,New Zealand’s national centre
for workplace literacy and language, to
design a programme to help any non-
q u a l i fied staff who wanted to improve
their skills.
Established in 1996, Workbase is a
n o n - p r o fit organization that works in
Programmes are tailored for Maori,who tend to be at the low end of the literacy scale.
I N T E R N ATIONAL LITERACY DAY
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
partnership with business, the education
sector and the government to improve
English language, l i t e r a cy and numeracy
skills in the workplace. New Zealand’s
participation in the OECD’s
International Adult Literacy Survey
(1998) found that 40 percent of people
employed in New Zealand businesses are
below the minimum level of literacy
competence required for everyday life
and work.
Today there are about 40 Workbase
l i t e r a cy programmes running in New
Zealand businesses, operating across a
range of sectors, including manufacturing,
forestry and construction. Th e
p r o g r a m m e s,which predominantly reach
Maori and Pacific Island people, a r e
designed to build literacy skills
concurrently with the technical skills and
knowledge needed within a particular
w o r k p l a c e. Since 1997,more than 20 staff
at Mercy Parklands have attended weekly
sessions with a Workbase tutor. Twelve
caregivers have just completed National
Certificates in Support of the Older
Person.
All of them started out learning basic
l i t e r a cy, n u m e r a cy and oral
communication programmes, accredited
by New Zealand’s national qualific a t i o n s ’
framework.“When they started,some of
them were too embarrassed to show me
their answers,” said tutor Andi McNish.
“Now they’re a really feisty bunch,with
heaps of confidence and ideas.” S p e n d i n g
around 30 minutes with each caregiver
once a week, McNish designs personal
study programmes for each caregiver,
including homework and assessments. S h e
also has the help of a part-time registered
nurse from the hospital, who has been
trained as a tutor to assist the caregivers.
Moving up
in the world
“Everything has been tied in to their
w o r k . For example, if we were doing
r e a d i n g, then we would look at the in-
house staff newsletter,” said  McNish,
who works with several other companies
as a Workbase tutor. M e r cy Parklands,
which spends more than $30,000 a year
running the programme, has been
rewarded with fewer mistakes and a more
confident and motivated workforce.
Morale has soared.
Caregivers take greater interest in
the operational side of the business and
are not afraid to offer suggestions about
patient care, according to senior staff.
Richardson said the quality of
d o c u m e n t a t i o n , required by health
a u t h o r i t i e s, had improved dramatically.
“They are much closer to the patients
and are able to advocate for their needs
much more. Because they [the
caregivers] have achieved something,
t h e y ’re so much more confid e n t .I t ’s like
working with a completely different
group ofstaff.”
Four years after beginning a basic
n u m e r a cy and literacy programme
through Workbase, Julie Ahloo has just
earned her first qualification — a National
Certificate in Support of the Older
Person. She has received a pay rise and
helps her young children with their
reading and writing homework after
school.
“I’m a very different person now,”
she said.“I used to have low self-esteem,
I wanted to speak up but I couldn’t.But
I’m very assertive now, I’ve got so much
more confidence,” said Ahloo, who left
school at age 14 with no qualifications.
Today she is making plans to study
nursing. ■
When Moroccan fisherman upgrade their skills, when women in India
become financially self-sufficient,when villagers in Rwanda pick up
the pieces and move forward through a community education programme,
each and everytime, a life is changed,and a small victory is won over the
twin battles of poverty and illiteracy.
International Literacy Day, celebrated each year on September 8, offers a
chance to honour these achievements, notably through several prestigious
p r i z e s, but also, to reflect on where we stand. Our planet counts 900 million
illiterate adults, two thirds of whom are women, a figure that runs the risk
of rising if the over 110 million out-of-school children fail to receive
quality education of some kind.
The issues are complex:literacy involves more than simply learning the
3Rs (reading, writing and arithmetic).It is closely interwoven with the
e c o n o m i c , cultural and political dimensions of a person’s life. Faced with
expanding poverty and the ever- widening gap between rich and poor, t h e
HIV/AIDS pandemic, globalization of trade and the exponential burst of
new information and communication technology, providing literacy has
become a more complex task than ever before.
We must go beyond one shot programmes, projects or campaigns.
Research and experience have provided us with considerable insight
into the nature of literacy acquisition, yet outmoded teaching and learning
approaches prevail.The long acknowledged and emphasized need for a
two-pronged approach to literacy, linking school and out-of-school
e d u c a t i o n , child and adult literacy, has seldom been incorporated into policy
design and programmes.
For literacy work to be worthwhile, it has to be up-to-date, carefully
targeted and useful for learners in tackling their varied and most pressing
concerns. It has to be attuned to the flux of complex changes affecting
their lives. Economic independence and spiritual well-being are but two
examples of what  literacy must help people achieve.Above all,literacy
has to help people develop self-confidence and take charge of their
own lives, equipped with the tools to tackle whatever challenges that
might arise.
Literacy programmes that work may not be called literacy programmes.
They might be called an HIV/AIDS prevention, or Information and
Communication Technology programmes for the poor. Call them what you
wish,literacy is at the base of all these provisions.
The United Nations Literacy Decade, soon to be launched,must serve as
an impetus for investment. Eliminating poverty and illiteracy are two sides
of the same coin,and political will is the key to success on both fronts.Th e
bottom line is that without Literacy for A l l , the world’s goal of Education
for All will remain an elusive dream. ■
* UNESCO’s section for literacy and non-formal education
NAMTIP A K S O R N KO O L * :
SELF-CONFIDENCE AND ECONOMIC RETURNS
14 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Y
ALLYN FISHER-ILAN
EDUCATION REPORTER FOR THE JERUSALEM POST
Learning Hebrew Ethiopian-style
In Israel, thousands of Ethiopian immigrants are learning to read and write for the first time. They
begin not with their native Amharic but Hebrew 
o u ’ve got to make it “ r e l e v a n t ,” insists Meir
P e r e t z , the Israeli Education
Ministry official in charge of adult
e d u c a t i o n , in explaining a new approach to
t e a c h Hebrew to thousands of illiterate
Ethiopian immigrants.
Since the early 1980’s, Israel has
brought in tens of thousands of Jews from
E t h i o p i a , including two spectacular airlifts.
More than 40,000 arrived in the 1990s and
about 100 immigrants continue to trickle in
each week.
The government earmarks about $30
million a year to teaching all immigrants
H e b r e w, according to Peretz. With the
Ethiopians it’s not an easy job, since as
many as 90 percent cannot read or write in
their native tongue, A m h a r i c. The scale
and scope of the project is unprecedented
i n t e r n a t i o n a l l y,whereby “a group of mostly
illiterate people is simultaneously trying to
learn to read, write and converse in a
foreign language,” says Peretz.
Peretz realized several years ago that
rote learning of vocabulary and grammar
simply didn’t work with most Ethiopian
adults enrolled in the compulsory
10 months of government-funded classes,
keeping many from joining the workforce
and blending into Israeli society.
Peer learning
A major obstacle is the huge cultural
difference between the rural lifestyle led by
most of the Ethiopians and the customs of
their adoptive Western country, P e r e t z
s a y s.“If I’m speaking with a native English-
s p e a k e r, and he doesn’t know what the
Hebrew word is for glasses, then I can say
what the word is. When a person doesn’t
even know what glasses are, then I have a
cultural problem.”
Peretz has sought to address this
problem by putting A m h a r i c - s p e a k i n g
veteran immigrants, like Isayas Hawaz,
into the classroom for at least a quarter of
the 25-hour a week lessons. H a w a z , 2 5 ,
immigrated four years ago and now helps
teachers translate their lessons into
Amharic at an absorption center in
Mevassaret Zion, a suburb of Jerusalem.
Hawaz said Peretz’s method made all the
difference for him when he was learning
H e b r e w. “At fir s t , I wanted to run away
from class, I couldn’t make any sense of the
alphabet lessons we were getting. My self-
c o n fidence plummeted. Then when they
[older Ethiopians] started translating, i t
all made sense,” says Hawaz.
A temple lesson
P e r e t z ’s curriculum also seeks to pique
pupils’ interest by peppering language
lessons with discussions of current events or
cultural issues.“It is not a good idea to wait
until someone knows Hebrew to explain
what is happening in the country,” he says.
On a hot July afternoon at the
Mevasseret centre , teacher Rina Rosler
discusses Tisha Be’Av, a recent Jewish day
of fasting marking the anniversary of the
destruction of the second holy temple in
the Roman period.She reads her pupils a
legend about the origin of the first temple
which recounts that God chose the site
because two quarreling brothers embraced
there. She writes the key verbs in Hebrew
on the blackboard and asks students for
translations in A m h a r i c.“ The temple could
only be built at a site where?” she asks.
“...Where there is love,” answers Sana’it
Farada,20,a newcomer from the Gondar
region of Ethiopia.
Yet today that site is the scene of
frequent Israeli-Palestinian violence.Wh i l e
the intifada didn’t come up directly, t h e
relevancy of the discussion wasn’t lost on
at least some of the 14 pupils. After class,
teenager Mandefo Mengistu remarks in
Hebrew that “the recent bomb attacks are
not good.”While beaming with confid e n c e,
M e n g i s t u ’s grasp of the language is
e x c e p t i o n a l . Noa Navot, director of the
Mevasseret classes, estimates that only half
of the pupils with previous education in
Ethiopia end up learning enough Hebrew
to land a job. Navot feels the classes should
be extended.“If you plant the seeds and
don’t bother to water them, they just go
dry,” she says.
Yet according to Peretz, very few
immigrants have asked for extended
c o u r s e s.There is, h o w e v e r, growing interest
in a new project to mix language
instruction with vocational training. In the
end, says Peretz,patience is required on
both sides. ■
I N T E R N ATIONAL LITERACY DAY
Grappling with an entirely new cultural universe.
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
hen it comes to dealing with racism, “silence is the worst
attitude”says Lilian Thuram,member of France’s World Cup-
winning football team.Echoing his remarks, NGOs campaigning
in the run-up to the World Conference against Racism (Durban,
South Africa,August 31-September 7) have insisted that the
voices be heard of the hundreds of millions of people around
the world who are still victims of racial discrimination.
Institutional racism, the last incarnation of the myth that
certain “ r a c e s ” are born inferior, died with the end of apartheid.
Dating back to the Renaissance, nourished by religious then scientific thought, it reached its
culmination with Nazism (pp. 21-23).Although the myth is flatly discredited today, its legacy lives
on,as the status of blacks in South America goes to prove (pp. 24-26).
Most importantly, the decline of racist ideology does not signal the end of racial discrimination,
g r o u n d e d , as the UN stipulates, on “ r a c e, c o l o u r, or ethnic origin.”Victims of this “veiled apartheid”
are no longer discriminated against in the name of biological “ i n f e r i o r i t y,” but because of religious
tradition—the lowest castes in India (pp. 27-29)—or economic and political instability, which is
fuelling waves of xenophobia in black
Africa (pp. 3 0 - 3 2 ) . Discrimination also
occurs in the name of “ c u l t u r a l
d i f f e r e n c e,” deemed so profound that
harmonious co-existence becomes
i m p o s s i b l e. Many indigenous peoples,
l i ke the Mapuche in Santiago, C h i l e
(pp. 18-19), are in this position. So are
millions of immigrants in Western Europe
( p p. 3 3 - 3 5 ) , where racism does not appear
to be simply “spontaneous”:rather, it is
intricately linked to tensions generated by
globalization (pp. 36-37).
Dossier concept and co-ordination by
René Lefort and Ivan Briscoe, respectively
UNESCO Courier director and journalist.
WC o n t e n t s
1 / Roots 
1 8 Shadows in the big city
Andrea A ravena Reyes
2 1 The rise and fall of the
l a b o ratory ra c i s t
George M. Fr e d r i c k s o n
2 / The excluded 
2 4 B ra z i l : stuck at the gates
of para d i s e
Diane Ku p e r m a n
2 7 I n d i a ’s hidden apartheid
Gopal Guru, with Shiraz Sidhva
3 0 Côte d’Ivoire :t rouble in the
hospitable land
Theophile Ko u a m o u o
3 3 Fo r t ress Europe bids you welcome
I van Briscoe
3 6 A return to nature
Interview with Alberto Burgio
C O L O U R , N ATI O
Why ra
F O C U S
16 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The first time I came up against racism
was in France. I was nine years old,and
blacks were given nicknames in my
s c h o o l . Was this racism? Coming from
c h i l d r e n , it might just seem like
f o o l i s h n e s s, but still it affected me. I ’d
come from Guadeloupe, where many
communities live together, and I’d never
felt any discrimination there.
Racism isn’t natural. I t ’s thought out,
and generated by adults who establish
differences on the basis of skin colour
and culture. To do away with it, schools
have a critical role to play. Children still
learn about “human races,” whereas there
is in fact only one race. It would be more
accurate to speak about different
communities.
The history of peoples is very badly
taught: each country grabs hold of it to
justify their past behaviour. L i k e w i s e, I ’v e
always been shocked that blacks only
appear in the history books from the time
of slavery.Their life before this dramatic
page of history is never revealed, as if
they had always been slaves! Their true
past and culture are all too often scorned,
creating a historical void and pulling a
veil down over the memory of these
peoples.
If we want to have the slightest hope
of eradicating racism,we have to commit
ourselves to the task of memory.C e r t a i n
nations must recognize the wrongs they
have done, especially with regard to
s l a v e r y, which I believe is one of the
sources of racism. The truth must be
w r i t t e n ,not in a spirit of vengeance, but as
a way to set us on the path toward
genuine reconciliation.
The battle is far from won. When I
arrived in Italy in 1996, I didn’t notice
any signs of racism or xenophobia.Then
the situation suddenly took a turn for the
worse. Why this rejection of the other?
Why this aggression? These questions
remain unanswered.
I lived through a painful experience
during a match in Parma,my club at the
time. Some fans started chanting a song
about two black players:“Ba eats bananas
in Weah’s hut.”At the end of the match,
I raised the incident with other members
of the club. I felt their indifference, and
could not accept it. Keeping silent is the
worst attitude to take. The fight against
racism is also a fight against silence.
I meet regularly with Italian school
kids and try to drive home the importance
of communities mixing with one
another—a source of vital cultural
e n r i c h m e n t . I’m convinced that these
youngsters would not throw their weight
behind the kind of racist antics that are
given free rein in football stadiums.
I t ’s not enough to talk about the good
things being done.You have to face what
is bad, and use it to consider what is
w r o n g. Evil must be fought on the spot so
that it does not lead to intolerable
p r o b l e m s. Fo o t b a l l , for example, is a very
powerful social force: we have to work
towards eliminating all forms of racism in
stadiums and stop people from using this
sport as a platform for their unacceptable
opinions.
I am disappointed that racism is still
alive and kicking. I t ’s been around for
c e n t u r i e s. We ’re always being told that
we live in a wonderful world that has
brought people closer together thanks
to new technologies.But reality is harsh:
we have not made much progress in
spiritual terms. The right to be different,
even from one’s neighbour,does not exist.
G l o b a l i z a t i o n ,as I see it,means respecting
the other, respecting a person’s
d i f f e r e n c e s,because each and everyone of
us carries a different history inside. ■
S I L E N C E IS THE GREATER SIN
LILIAN THURAM
MEMBER OF FRANCE’S WORLD CUP-WINNING NATIONAL FOOTBALL TEAM
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 17
I O N , ETHNIC HAT E …
c i s m ?
O P I N I O N
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ANDREA ARAVENA REYES
ANTHROPOLOGISTAND SANTIAGO OFFICE CHIEFFORTHE NATIONAL CORPORATION
OF INDIGENOUS DEVELOPMENT (CONADI)
Shadows in the big city
Far from their native region of Araucanía, half a million Mapuche Indians
live in the Chilean capital Santiago—a place of stigma and segregation
1 . R O OT S
T
he Mapuche Indians make up 10 percent
of Chile’s adult population—almost a
million people in total, half of whom live
in and around the city of Santiago. In the
minds of most Chileans, h o w e v e r, t h e
Mapuche is still thought of as a person with an
indigenous surname, living in the southern region of
A r a u c a n í a ,belonging to an old-fashioned community
and fighting for rights to land.All the rest are ignored
and segregated.
As in most Latin American countries, Chile’s
Indigenous People’s Law  bans discrimination.
Victims of prejudice, h o w e v e r, argue that the law is
useless since not even Santiago’s police offic e r s
believe what an Indian says. “When you complain
to a military policemen and tell them that
discrimination is against the law, they don’t even
know what the law is,” says Elba Colicoi from the
district of Peñalolen.“ They look at us in amazement,
laugh and tell us to ‘calm down and go home.’ But
if one of us hits a naughty child, the neighbours say
Mapuches are violent people and the police believe
everything the Chileans say.”
In the Mapudungun language, “ m a p u c h e ”
means “people of the earth.” Until Chile gained
independence from Spain in the early 19th century,
the Mapuches lived in a 100,000 square kilometre
region in south-central Chile—an area as big as
Chile’s Mapuche Indians on the march for recognition.
18 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Po r t u g a l . Between 1866 and 1927, they were forced
to live in settlements covering only 5,000 square
k i l o m e t r e s, barely five percent of the original area.
According to the last census in 1992, 9 2 8 , 0 0 0
Mapuches now live in Chile.
Restrictions on Mapuches’ property rights, l a c k
of resources and the impoverishment of rural
communities set off a huge migration from the land.
Following 135 years of exodus—most of it forced—
around half the country’s Mapuches live in and
around Santiago. If children are counted, one in 10
of Greater Santiago’s inhabitants are from this
c o m m u n i t y. Some indigenous intellectuals actually
refer to the Mapuche diaspora.
Traditional dress unwelcome
in the classroom
Although only 20 percent of Mapuches now live
in the countryside, people still tend to have a
stereotypical view of them as rural peasants which,
consciously or not,makes it hard for any of them to
feel like full-fledged citizens. The media compound
these prejudices with pictures of land occupations in
the south and armed battles with landowners near the
v i l l a g e s, conveying a negative image of “ p o v e r t y -
stricken”Indians.
Yet after a century of emigration, the Mapuche
urban diaspora is here to stay. Over 70 urban
organizations have been set up in recent years to
fight for their rights and end discrimination. In spite
of this,the image of them as a rural folk still prevails.
In the city, they are “invisible people”who, as they
themselves admit, bear the stigma imposed by a
society that regards them as lazy, drunk,culturally
backward and aggressive.
This hostility has made most Mapuches
renounce their identity, reject their language and
change their names,all of which has caused serious
psychological problems.To survive in the city, they
have to camouflage their origins and try to appear
like mere southerners or peasants.As a result, t h e y
are helping to make themselves invisible.
Both the discrimination suffered at the hands of
society and the difficulties incurred in overcoming
their marginal social status prevent Mapuches from
i n t e g r a t i n g.Victims of discrimination lose self-esteem
and marginalize themselves. Once they have thus
rejected their individual identity, they naturally
reject the customs of their own social group.
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 19
W H Y  R A C I S M ?
At school,Mapuche children have to grapple with the Spanish language.
Since the adoption of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights in 1948,
the international community has made important strides in the fig h t
against racism. But at the turn of the new century—and despite the fact that
the mapping of the human genome has reaffirmed our common humanity—
racial prejudice persists in all parts of the world.
The World Conference against Racism, Racial Discrimination, Xenophobia and
Related Intolerance, to be held in Durban (South Africa) from August 31 to
September 7,2001,is the first such conference in the post-apartheid era.It
stands as one more landmark in the UN’s ongoing campaign. Since the
Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide
( 1 9 4 8 ) , the UN has adopted a series of conventions and declarations,
proclaimed an International Year of Mobilization against Racism (2001), a n d
organized three decades against racism (1973-1982, 1 9 8 3 - 1 9 9 2 , 1 9 9 4 -
2003) along with two world conferences on the same theme, held in Geneva
(1978 and 1983).
While these previous conferences focused chiefly on apartheid, the delegations
in Durban will debate an array of questions reflecting the complex interplay
of racial prejudice and intolerance: p o l i t i c a l , social and economic exclusion,
m i g r a t i o n , human traffic k i n g , indigenous peoples, minority rights, the role of
the media, the Internet, religion and education. The conference aims to
review progress made in the fight against racism, scrutinize stumbling
b l o c k s, analyze the root sources and contemporary manifestations of racism,
and draw up concrete recommendations to combat it through education,
prevention and the protection of victims.
For the first time, the heated question of slavery is on the agenda.Will it be
proclaimed a crime against humanity? According to Doudou Diène, d i r e c t o r
of UN E S C O’s division for intercultural projects,“ Th e r e ’s a theoretical consensus
on the recognition of the slave trade as a crime against humanity.” But on
the issue of reparations, opinions diverge. One camp is demanding fin a n c i a l
c o m p e n s a t i o n . The other stresses the need for moral and historical
atonement—they argue that money cannot paper over a tragedy that lasted
for four centuries. Proclaiming the slave trade a crime against humanity and
describing it as such in school history books might instead encourage people
to empathize with the fate of millions of humans, and thus prove the most
effective route to repairing this injustice. Others are advocating the
cancellation of African countries’ foreign debt, a measure that could jumpstart
and give a jolt of optimism to many national economies. ■
D U R BA N : THE LEGACY OF SLAV E RY
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
c l o t h e s, which is rather like turning the Mapuche into
a sort of “fancy dress.”
As for the typical urban Mapuche worker, he
or she is someone with few qualifications who
changes jobs often,works long hours for a pittance,
faces discrimination because of physical
appearance and is the target of ill-treatment and
excessive demands by employers.
“ The bosses and the companies don’t hire us
because they think we’re aggressive,” argues Juana
Coliqueo from the district of Quilieura.“When they
do hire us, they want us to work in the kitchen, up on
the scaffolding or in the storeroom, where nobody can
see us. Have you noticed that the bigger the fir m ,
the more blonde, blue-eyed secretaries there are?”
For women,the most common job is in domestic
service, which provides them with food and lodging,
but also conceals them from urban society. Men get
jobs in construction or in bakeries, which allow them
to sleep in the daytime and work at night.This enables
the urban Mapuche to stay “ h i d d e n ,” a v o i d
discrimination and become familiar with life in the
c i t y. Even though such jobs are seen as forced,
undesirable, degrading and lowly, they are still the
main source of income for Mapuches.
In line with legislation across the continent,
Chilean law strongly condemns discrimination.
Taking this law as a yardstick,Mapuches are quick
to point out that Chilean society clearly harbours
racist and xenophobic features, and practises
discrimination on the basis of racial, ethnic or social
origin. The main victims are half a million citizens
who, to be accepted by society, have to swallow the
humiliation of hiding their identity and passing
unnoticed. ■
Most urban Mapuches live in precariously built
shanty-towns that have sprung up around Santiago
in the past century. Besides poverty and other forms
of exclusion,life in the slums also means enduring
discrimination from their own neighbours.“ C h i l e a n s
look down on us in the settlement,” says Ju a n
Lemugnier, a Mapuche community leader. “They
say ‘here come the mini-Mapuches.’ When they get
a n n o y e d , they say ‘get over here, I n d i a n , or get lost,
I n d i a n .’ This changes when they get to know us,
but the problem is we always have to make more of
an effort than other people.”
The main hurdle for Mapuche children is language.
At home they speak Mapudungun,but most schools
only teach Spanish and foreign languages, w h i c h
means Mapuche children have a harder time
absorbing the mainstream culture. As a result,more
and more parents are deciding not to teach them the
Mapuche language in the hope that they will speak
better Spanish—a kind of linguistic demolition aimed
at achieving a sense of ethnic belonging.Families fear
in particular that children who do not speak Spanish
properly will be laughed at. One community leader
recalled that as a child he was called “chamaco,” the
Mexican word for a little boy, because people in
Santiago who did not know a word of Mapudungun
thought his accent was Mexican.
When community leaders take their children to
school in traditional Mapuche dress to assert their
identity and “ v i s i b i l i t y,”they run into opposition from
school inspectors, who refuse to let the children in
unless they are clothed like other pupils. Only during
folk festivals are they allowed to wear traditional
20 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
Demanding their rights during a rally in Santiago.
A  Q U I C K  G L O S S A R Y
According to The Social Science Encyclopedia (Routledge, 1996), racism is “the idea that
there is a direct correspondence between a group’s values, behaviour and attitudes,
and its physical features.” The International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of
Racial Discrimination (adopted by the UN General Assembly in 1965) defined racial
discrimination as “any distinction, exclusion, restriction or preference based on race,
colour, descent,or national or ethnic origin which has the purpose or effect of nullifying or
impairing the recognition, enjoyment or exercise. . . of human rights and fundamental
freedoms.”
Ethnicity, derived from the Greek ethnikos—the adjective of ethnos, meaning people or
nation—refers to “a fundamental category of social organization which is based on
membership defined by a sense of common historical origins, and which may also include
shared culture, religion or language” (The Social Science Encyclopedia). Ethnocentrism,
according to the Dictionnaire de Sociologie (Le Robert/Seuil, 1999) is the “tendency to
make the group one belongs to the single model of reference.”
Multiculturalism is “the idea,or ideal of the harmonious co-existence of differing cultural
or ethnic groups in a pluralist society” according to The Dictionary of Race and Ethnic
Relations (Routledge, 1984). Xenophobia—derived from the Greek xenos for strange and
“phobia,” a fear or aversion—literally means a fear of strangers. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 21
R
acism exists when one ethnic group or
historical collectivity dominates,e x c l u d e s,o r
seeks to eliminate another on the basis of
differences that it believes are hereditary
and unalterable. An ideological basis for
explicit racism, in this sense, came to a unique fruition
in the West during the modern period: no clear and
unequivocal evidence of racism beyond discrimination
or rivalry between communities has been found in
other cultures or in Europe before the Middle A g e s.
Perhaps the first sign of this racist view of the
world appeared in the identification of the Jews with
the devil and witchcraft in the popular mind of the 13th
and 14th centuries. O f ficial sanction for such attitudes
came in 16th-century Spain, when Jews who had
converted to Christianity and their descendants b e c a m e
the victims of a pattern of discrimination and
exclusion.
The period of the Renaissance and Reformation
was also a time when Europeans were coming into
increasing contact with people of darker pigmentation
in A f r i c a , Asia and the A m e r i c a s, and were thus
making judgements about them. The motive for
enslaving Africans was primarily economic—their
labour was needed on the plantations of the New
World—but the official rationale was that they were
heathens. Slave traders and slave owners sometimes
interpreted a passage in the book of Genesis as their
GEORGE M. FREDRICKSON
PROFESSOR OF HISTORY AT STANFORD UNIVERSITY, AUTHOROF THE COMPARATIVE IMAGINATION: ONTHE HISTORY OF RACISM, NATIONALISM AND SOCIAL
MOVEMENTS (UNIVERSITY OF CALFORNIA PRESS, 1997)
The rise and fall
of the laboratory ra c i s t
Until the Middle Ages, communities discriminated against each other and
vied for power. In the following centuries, the Bible, economics and
science gave birth to a new phenomenon: the hierarchy of race
1 . R O OT S
W H Y  R AC I S M ?
We may have 
all come on
different ships,
but we’re in the
same boat now.
Martin Luther King, American
civil rights leader (1929-
1968)The Inquisition strikes:a 15th-century engraving depicts the fate of Jews who refused to renounce their
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
justification.Ham,they maintained,committed a sin
against his father Noah that condemned his
supposedly black descendants to be “servants unto
s e r v a n t s.” When Virginia decreed in 1667 that
converted slaves could be kept in bondage,not because
they were actual heathens but because they had
heathen ancestry, the justification for black servitude
was thus changed from their religious status to
something approaching race. Beginning in the late
17th century, laws were also passed in British North
America forbidding marriage between whites and
blacks and discriminating against the mixed offspring
of informal liaisons. Without clearly stating so, such
laws implied that blacks were unalterably alien and
inferior.
During the Enlightenment,a secular or scientific
theory of race moved the subject away from the
B i b l e ’s teachings,with their insistence on the essential
unity of the human race. E i g h t e e n t h - c e n t u r y
ethnologists such as Linnaeus, Buffon and
Blumenbach began to think of human beings as part
of the natural world,and subdivided them into three
to five races, usually considered as varieties of a single
human species. In the late 18th and early 19th
centuries, however, an increasing number of writers,
especially those committed to the defence of slavery,
maintained that the races in fact constituted separate
species.
The 19th century was an age of emancipation,
n a t i o n a l i s m ,and imperialism—all of which contributed
to the growth and intensification of ideological racism
in Europe and the United States. Although the
emancipation of blacks from slavery and Jews from the
ghettoes received most of its support from religious or
secular believers in fundamental human equality, t h e
consequence of these reforms was to intensify rather
than diminish racism. Race relations became less
rigidly hierarchical and more competitive. Th e
insecurities of a burgeoning industrial capitalism
created a need for scapegoats. The Darwinian
emphasis on “the struggle for existence” and concern
for “the survival of the fittest”was conducive to the
development of a new and more credible scientific
racism in an era that increasingly viewed race relations
as an arena for conflict rather than the outcome of a
stable ranking.
Moral 
revulsion
It was nationalism,especially a type of romantic
cultural nationalism marrying ethnic heritage (thought
of in terms of blood) to a sense of collective identity,
that marked the growth of a new variant of racist
t h o u g h t , especially in Germany. Beginning in the late
1870s and early 1880s, the coiners of the term “anti-
S e m i t i s m ” made explicit what some cultural
nationalists had previously implied: that to be Je w i s h
in Germany was not simply to adhere to a set of
religious beliefs or cultural practices, but meant
belonging to a race that was the antithesis of the race
to which true Germans belonged.
Western imperialism in the late 19th century,
m e a n w h i l e, was reaching a climax.The “scramble for
Africa”and forays into parts of Asia and the Pacific
represented an assertion of the competitive ethnic
nationalism believed to exist between European
nations (and which, as a result of the Spanish-
American War came to include the United States). I t
also constituted a claim, allegedly based on science,
that Europeans had a natural-born right to rule over
Africans and Asians.
It was nevertheless only in the 20th century that
the history of racism reached its zenith: the rise and fall
of overtly racist regimes. In the American South,
segregation laws and restrictions on black voting
rights reduced African Americans to lower caste
s t a t u s.A key feature of this regime was fear of sexual
contamination through rape or intermarriage, which
led to efforts to prevent the conjugal union of whites
with those that had any known or discernible A f r i c a n
ancestry.
Racist ideology was of course carried to its extreme
in Nazi Germany through the attempted extermination
of an entire ethnic group. H i t l e r, it has been said, g a v e
racism a bad name. The moral revulsion of people
throughout the world against what the Nazis did,
reinforced by scientific studies undermining racist
genetics (or eugenics), served to discredit the scientific
racism that had been respectable and influential in
the United States and Europe before World War II.
Explicit racism also came under devastating attack
from the new nations created in the wake of the
decolonization of Africa and Asia. The Civil Rights
The way it was:a slave market in Virginia, circa 1861.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 23
movement in the United States, which succeeded in
outlawing legalized racial segregation and
discrimination in the 1960s, drew crucial support from
the growing sense that national interests were
threatened when blacks in the United States were
mistreated and abused. In the competition with the
Soviet Union for “the hearts and minds” o f
independent Africans and Asians, racial segregation
became a national embarrassment with possible
strategic consequences.
“Cultural racism”
The one racist regime that survived World War II
and the Cold War was the South A f r i c a n .Laws passed
in 1948 banning all marriage and sexual relations
between different “population groups,”and requiring
separate residential areas for people of mixed race and
Africans, demonstrated a clear obsession with “race
purity.” But the climate of world opinion in the wake
of the Holocaust induced apologists for apartheid to
rest their case for “separate development” mainly on
cultural rather than physical differences.
The defeat of Nazi Germany, the desegregation of
the American South and the establishment of majority
rule in South Africa suggest that regimes based on
biological racism or cultural purity are a thing of the
p a s t .But racism does not require the full and explicit
support of the state and the law. Nor does it require an
ideology centred on the concept of biological
i n e q u a l i t y. Discrimination by institutions and
individuals against those perceived as racially different
can long persist and even flourish under the illusion of
n o n - r a c i s m , as historians of Brazil have recently
d i s c o v e r e d .The use of allegedly deep-seated cultural
differences as a justification for hostility and
discrimination against newcomers from the developing
world—whether they be Algerians in Fr a n c e,Turks in
G e r m a n y,Pakistanis in Britain,Mexicans in the United
States—have evoked charges of a new “ c u l t u r a l
r a c i s m ” despite the dominant group’s explicit
disavowal of any kind of biological superiority.
Such recent examples of racism are not
unprecedented.They rather represent a reversion to
the way that the differences between groups could be
readily made to seem indelible and unbridgeable
before the articulation of a scientific or naturalistic
W H Y  R A C I S M ?
“ The great and terrible war which has now ended was a war made
possible by. . .the propagation. . .through ignorance and prejudice, o f
the doctrine of the inequality of men and races,” declares UN E S C O’s
C o n s t i t u t i o n . For over a half a century, the Organization has devised strategies
aimed at tackling the root causes of racism, essentially through education
and exchange of knowledge. Alongside special UN E S C O university chairs
and programmes of anti-racist education, many publications, campaigns and
projects have been employed in the fight against prejudice and cultural
b i g o t r y.
It is a long and painstaking task,aimed not only at removing obstacles to
mutual understanding, but also proving that human history is a tale of
continuous exchange such that no people or ethnic group can be deemed
“pure.” All culture, in short,is the fruit of dialogue.
By emphasizing this history of cultural diversity, projects such as the Silk
Roads (launched in 1988), the Slave Route (1994) and the Iron Roads in A f r i c a
(1995) have enabled UN E S C O to tackle racism by shedding light on the
cultural and spiritual ties between peoples.
This same approach is employed in a series of comprehensive history
works published by UNESCO that describe the complexity and wealth of
contradictions underlying human development: the History of Humanity, t h e
General History of Africa, the History of Civilizations of Central Asia, The
Different Aspects of Islamic Culture, the General History of the Caribbean
and the General History of Latin America.
Other projects such as Intercultural Dialogue in Everyday  Life, M.U.S.I.C
( m u s i c , u r b a n i s m , social integration and culture), or Culture in the
Neighbourhood are more specifically oriented toward young people.
For the past ten years, UN E S C O has turned its attention to momentous
developments in the field of health and life sciences: its International
Bioethics Committee, made up of 55 members (including scientists, j u r i s t s,
e c o n o m i s t s, d e m o g r a p h e r s,a n t h r o p o l o g i s t s, philosophers and nutritionists)
drew up a Universal Declaration on the Human Genome and on Human
Rights that was adopted in 1997.Two decades after the UN E S C O D e c l a r a t i o n
on Race and Racial Prejudice (1978), this first international text on bioethics
disclaims once and for all the pseudo-scientific foundations of racism. ■
U N E S C O : OVERCOMING IGNORANCE
O U R C O M M O N B L U E P R I N T
When scientists unveiled a blueprint of the human genome about a year ago, t h e
press trumpeted the potential windfall of new drugs and treatments to remedy
inherited diseases, l i ke certain forms of diabetes. But beyond the potential of medical
b e n e fit s, the research also marks a decisive strike against racism by disproving the myth of
r a c e. Genetic research demonstrates that we all descend from a common ancestor in
A f r i c a . F u r t h e r m o r e, most human genetic differences are found in all populations and
presumably arose before modern humans left Africa some 50,000 years ago and subsequently
divided into ethnic or “ r a c i a l ” groups Indeed, it has been estimated that only 0.012 percent
of the variation between humans in total genetic material can be attributed to differences
between the so-called “races.”
However, the roots of some genetic diseases may lie in this small amount of diversity that
has spawned a major debate in the international scientific community.When collecting and
comparing DNA samples, should geneticists record the ethnicity of the donors? 
Those opposed to ethnic labelling point out that this kind of information will probably not
be very helpful because most genetic diseases are linked to variations which are spread across
the entire human population. These critics also point out medical research related to
ethnicity is regularly distorted by racist groups.
On the other side, by tagging or monitoring ethnicity, geneticists can be certain that they
are not inadvertently ignoring a particular group in their surveys. Some bioethicists also point
out that,if handled properly, these population studies could be used to show people just
how much we share genetically and disprove the widespread belief that some groups are
“genetically”more intelligent or advanced than others. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
DIANE KUPERMAN
BRAZILIAN JOURNALISTANDWRITER
Stuck at the gates
of para d i s e
Brazil enjoys a reputation as a multiracial haven, but prejudice 
still has a stranglehold on society and slavery remains far 
from a distant memory 
2 . THE EXCLUDED
I
n a very short time—what is 501 years on the
scale of human history?—immigrants from
around the world have streamed to Brazil.
The mixture of colours and peoples along
with the joys of living in tropical latitudes
soon gave rise to the myth that Brazil is a “ r a c i a l
d e m o c r a cy.”This stereotyped image,so well spread
by the media, proclaims that Brazil is a socially
harmonious country where people of different
colours always get along.
But behind the smiles that light up in black,w h i t e,
b r o w n , red and yellow faces when the first drum is
struck in the samba schools, the truth is hidden:
r a c i a l , social and economic prejudices exist, a n d
must be denounced.
After Portuguese explorers discovered Brazil
in 1500, slavery existed on its soil for over three
c e n t u r i e s. On May 13, 1 8 8 8 , it became the last
western country to abolish the practice. B r a z i l
was also the biggest importer of slaves in modern
history: 40 percent of the blacks exported from
Africa to the New World ended up there.
As a result, Rio de Janeiro became the world’s
largest African city and slave port, and the
Mercado do Valongo the biggest slave market.
Today Nigeria is the only country to have a larger
black population.
Bleaching 
the society
Sexual relations between whites and their
slaves—especially white sons having sex for the
first time with black women—gave rise to a large
mixed-race population that today outnumbers
blacks. Sometimes freed slaves were “adopted,”
which eased their plight by sparing them the
struggle with a world for which they were
A vicious circle:poorly educated,Afro-Brazilians are often restricted to low-paid jobs.
24 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
u n p r e p a r e d , but kept them in their erstwhile
menial jobs and perpetuated the apparent (and
sometimes genuine) affectionate relations with
the “masters in the big house.”
The expression “racial democracy ”a p p e a r e d
in the 1930s and was intended to mask the
intentions of the government, which wanted to
“ b l e a c h ” society by encouraging the “ m o s t
advanced races”—in other words, w h i t e
Europeans—to migrate to Brazil. The country
had accepted the myth of black racial and
intellectual inferiority, and urgently wanted to
take action to change the racial make-up of the
Brazilian population, where descendants of
Africans were in the majority.
The immigrants’ arrival only worsened the
plight of blacks: the few jobs they could aspire to
fill became even scarcer. Forty years after
e m a n c i p a t i o n , former slaves and their descendants
swelled the ranks of street people and beggars.
Those who did have a place to live dwelled in
shantytowns, and when they had jobs, their skills
and wages were low.
Skewed job
applications
Statistics today point to
glaring inequality, s t a r t i n g
with child mortality: out of
every thousand children,
6 2 blacks and 37 whites die at
an early age (76 blacks and
45 whites among children
under fiv e ) . Life expectancy
for adult Afro-Brazilians is
six years shorter than it is for
whites: 62 years for men and
68 for women.
The illiteracy rate among blacks is 22 percent,
the average length of time they spend in school
six years. When they reach the labour market,
most are still children or have a teenager’s
s c h o o l i n g. Barely 18 percent have access to higher
education, and among that 18 percent, just 2.3
percent graduate from university.The inadequacy
of their training is reflected in professional life,
where blacks are restricted to low-paid menial
jobs.
When looking for work, they know beforehand
that if a white person with the same qualific a t i o n s
is applying for the same position, the odds are
hopelessly stacked against them.And when they do
find work, they are often the victims of unfair wage
policies that favour whites in identical jobs. Th i s
vicious circle is visible in statistics on unemployment
(the jobless rate is 11 percent for black men and 16.5
percent for black women) and poverty (34 percent
of blacks live below the poverty line and 14 percent
are classified as destitute).
Five years ago, O Dia, R i o ’s best-selling
newspaper, carried out a survey of the bars and
restaurants along the beaches of Copacabana
and Ipanema.The findings revealed that just one
of the 318 employees working in these businesses
was black. Hotels, restaurants, banks and shops
seldom hire blacks, arguing that customers do
not like people of colour to wait on them.
Discrimination is blatant in the classified ads of
n e w s p a p e r s, where “neat appearance” is actually
code for “blacks need not apply.” Code Four of
B r a z i l ’s National Employment System is even
more perverse: it requires job-seekers to mention
their skin colour, enabling employers to turn
down applications on the pretext that the position
has already been filled.
In recent years, racial hatred, which is blatant
in big cities such as São Paulo and Rio de Ja n e i r o,
has unfortunately spread to Je w s,I n d i a n s, g y p s i e s,
gays and even Nordestins (white Brazilians from
the country’s north-eastern region in search of
better living conditions).
The significance of racist
activities can no longer be
downplayed by calling them
s c a t t e r e d . Though offic i a l l y
p r o h i b i t e d , anti-Semitic and
revisionist publications are
l e g i o n . The Internet distills
hatred of blacks, Jews and
g a y s. Desecration of Je w i s h
cemeteries and spray-painted
swastikas or insults on walls
have become everyday
occurrences.
Things are getting out of
h a n d , and tomorrow
xenophobes may target any
group, regardless of colour, origins or religion.
M e a n w h i l e, the white population turns a deaf
e a r.A recent survey by the University of Brasilia
reveals that 35 percent of those polled reluctantly
admitted to being racist, while 65 percent denied
it. The insidiousness of invisible racial prejudice
was compared to a B-2 Stealth bomber, w h i c h
radars cannot detect.
Working against
the grain
In the 1980s, black community leaders decided
it was time to react and began organizing efforts
to combat prejudice, fear and resistance.
Overcoming their political and religious
d i f f e r e n c e s, they joined forces to create non-
governmental organizations that defend the rights
of blacks and commissioned studies to gain a
truthful assessment of the situation.At the same
t i m e, they started working to preserve their
African ancestors’ cultural and religious values.
Hotels, restaurants,
banks and shops
seldom hire blacks,
arguing that
customers do not like
people of colour
to wait on them.
Xenophobes are
those who don’t
have faith in the
virtues of their
own people. 
Jorge Luis Borges, Argentine
writer 
(1899-1986) 
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 25
W H Y  R A C I S M ?
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The goal was to strengthen black identity and
make Afro-Brazilians feel proud of their colour
and traditions. Publications of the highest quality
sought to create and extol black role models that
might replace white ones.
P u b l i s h e r s, including children’s book
p u b l i s h e r s, started singing the praises of real and
fictional black heroes. Even cosmetics companies
hopped on the bandwagon, selling beauty
products for every skin tone, type of hair and
style of dress.
A government
stand
The government, which until now was
concerned by poverty but never by racism, has
even started to address the issue. It must be
acknowledged that Brazil has signed the main
international human rights conventions and is
on the cutting edge of anti-racist legislation.Th e
constitution prohibits all forms of prejudice and
considers racism “a crime without statutory
l i m i t s.” Last year, the state of Rio took a new
initiative by creating “SOS Racism and anti-
Semitism,” a hotline set up by the secretariat of
public safety to receive complaints from victims
of racism.
But outlawing racism is not enough.
Regardless of their colour, Brazilians must take
action to raise each individual’s awareness of
social injustice, and incite everyone to help wipe
out inequality. ■
Benedita da Silva,the first black woman elected to the Brazilian Congress.
“But there aren’t any blacks in Colombia!” exclaimed a Colombian now
living in New York after hearing the ethnologist Luz Riviera discuss
her recent research into the country’s black indigenous communities.“ W h a t
do you mean there aren’t? They’re over 22 percent of the population,”
replied Riviera. “If there are, then they aren’t Colombians,” insisted the
lady.
Luz Riviera tried to explain that the seven million blacks now living in the
country are not only as Colombian as her, but that it was also highly likely
that she had at least one black ancestor. “God save me from having a black
in my family!,” the aggrieved woman replied.
As in other Latin American countries, racism towards blacks and indigenous
peoples is a fact of life in Colombia.And just as in other countries of the region,
victims of this racism tend to be “ i n v i s i b l e ” in the eyes of those who practise
the discrimination.
Black slaves were introduced into what is now Colombia by the first Spanish
c o n q u i s t a d o r s. From the very beginning they clustered in communities
largely along the northern coast close to Cartagena, the principle “black port”
of the era, as well as on the western Pacific coastline and the Caribbean
archipelago of San Andrés and Providencia.
The “Afro-Colombians”—as they are officially known—also live in the
c o u n t r y ’s big and medium-sized cities, such as Cartagena,B u e n a v e n t u r a ,C a l i ,
Tu r b o, Barranquilla or Medellín, places where their segregation takes on all
the features of marginalization.“In Cartagena, the only blacks who can enter
certain clubs and restaurants are those who are serving. In Bogotá and Cali,
most domestic servants are black, often dressed in pink uniforms,” e x p l a i n s
Luz Riviera.
Over time, continued discrimination has led many to setting up home in rural,
isolated areas, where they live in virtually self-sufficient communities working
on small land-holdings or as employees for large farms. Some simply live on
the fish they can catch.
Life in such communities is not much better than in other parts of the
country. According to the Third report on the Human Rights Situation in
C o l o m b i a , carried out for the Organization of American States and published
in 1999, “a disproportionate number of blacks live in conditions of extreme
p o v e r t y.”Afro-Colombians inhabit some of the most conflict-ridden parts of
the country and earn incomes below the national per capita average.
Illiteracy rates both in rural and urban areas remain extremely large, while
black communities suffer high rates of infant mortality and serious diseases
such as malaria, dengue fever, gastro-enteritis and lung infections. Th e
report puts this down to a lack of drinking wa t e r, electricity and basic
medical services.
Faced with their exclusion from the rest of society, many communities
continue to co-operate closely with groups of indigenous peoples, w i t h
whom they first formed links under slavery when blacks were forced to work
in gold and silver mines while Indians tilled the land. Luz Riviera has studied
these inter-ethnic relations in an isolated village on the banks of the
Guayabero river in the region of Serranía del Baudó.
“Thirty or so black families living there have created ritual family ties with
indigenous families living deeper in the jungle.What frequently happens is
that an indigenous person asks a black man to be the godfather of his son,
sealing a relation of compadrazgo [joint fatherhood] which helps make the
lives of both families somewhat easier in light of the discrimination both
suffer.” ■
C O L O M B I A’S COLOUR-BA R
26 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
F
or centuries,the untouchables of Paliyad,a
nondescript village in western India’s
Ahmedabad district, have known their
p l a c e.Many of them are manual scavengers,
cleaning the toilets of upper-caste villagers
or toiling the land,sometimes for less than a handful
of rice a day.
“ We ’ve known that we must stay away from
them [upper-caste people] since the day we were
born,” says Rajesh,who is going on 19. “At the tea
s t a l l s, we have separate cups to drink from, c h i p p e d
and caked with dirt, and we’re expected to clean
them ourselves.We have to walk for 15 minutes to
carry water to our homes,because we’re not allowed
to use the taps in the village that the upper castes
u s e. We ’re not allowed into temples, and when I
attended school, my friends and I were forced to sit
just outside the classroom… the upper caste children
would not allow us even to touch the football they
played with… we played with stones instead.”
More than 160 million people, a sixth of India’s
p o p u l a t i o n , continue to bear the burden of a
2,000-year old caste system sanctioned by Hindu
t h e o l o g y, which locks people into a rigid role by
virtue of their birth.
Codes to suit
the upper class
Though the term “ u n t o u c h a b l e s ” was abolished
in 1950 under India’s constitution,the “oppressed
p e o p l e ” or Dalits as they are now referred to,
continue to be discriminated against. They are
denied access to land, forced to work in humiliating
and degrading conditions and are routinely abused
by the police and upper-caste groups, which enjoy
the state’s protection
Though India has sought to overcome the
inequities of caste and discrimination through
a f firmative action—reserving quotas in education,
government jobs and political bodies—these policies
have benefited only a few.The highest office in the
l a n d , that of the largely ceremonial President, i s
today held by a Dalit,K.R.Narayanan.But all the
horrors of India’s caste system persist at the
grassroots; attempts to defy this rigid social order
invariably result in violence or economic retaliation.
Perhaps the world’s longest surviving social
h i e r a r c h y, I n d i a ’s caste system entails a complex
ordering of social groups on the basis of ritual
p u r i t y.Attributed to the law-giver Manu, the system
was spelt out over 2,000 years ago in the Dharma
Shastra,the cornerstone of the Hindu religion.
According to Manu, every individual is born
into one of four principal v a r n a s, or large categories,
and must remain within that caste until death,
although the particular ranking of that caste may
vary among different regions in the country and
over time. In order of precedence, the Brahmins are
the priests and teachers,presiding over knowledge
and education; the Kshatriyas are the rulers and
s o l d i e r s ; the Va i s h y a s, merchants and traders;and the
Shudras, the peasants, labourers and artisans. The
untouchables fall into a fifth category outside the
varna system, and were often assigned tasks too
“ritually polluting” to merit inclusion within the
traditional varna system.
C l e a r l y, caste discrimination was an ideological
construct that was deployed by the upper castes to
create and maintain their monopoly over cultural
capital (knowledge and education), social capital
GOPAL GURU, WITH SHIRAZ SIDHVA
PROFESSOR OF POLITICAL STUDIES AT PUNE UNIVERSITY AND FELLOW, CENTRE
FORTHE STUDY OF DEVELOPING SOCIETIES (DELHI). SHIRAZ SIDHVA IS A
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 27
W H Y  R A C I S M ?
I n d i a ’s “hidden apartheid”
India’s ancient caste system persists, subjecting millions to degrading
poverty and human rights abuses. Attitudes die hard, despite government
legislation to usher in change
2 . THE EXCLUDED
Street sweepers in Bombay: a “ritually polluting” job.
There is no
difference 
among classes 
of people.
All the world is
of divine origin.
The Mahabharata, 
ancient Sanskrit epic
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
(status and patriarchal domination), political capital
(power),and material capital (wealth).
The codes were often pernicious,and rules were
bent to suit the upper castes. In northern India,
for example,untouchables were forced to use drums
to announce their arrival,and even their shadows
were thought to be polluting. In the south, some
Brahmins stipulated that the lower castes would
have to maintain a distance of 65 feet (22 metres)
from them in order not to contaminate their betters.
Yet this caste-based discrimination also had a
pragmatic dimension. The untouchables, excluded
from the education and books of the Brahmins,
were nevertheless allowed to develop their own
stores of knowledge, in agriculture or midwifery
for example.But there was a catch—this knowledge
was only allowed because it benefited the upper
castes.
A case of
racism?
Caste is still frequently used as a cover for
exploitative economic arrangements. Even today,
most Dalits are not permitted to cross the invisible
“ p o l l u t i o n ” line that divides their part of the village
from that occupied by the higher castes. And yet
a Dalit woman,whose very shadow is polluting, i s
allowed to massage the body of the upper-caste
woman she serves. Upper caste men,meanwhile,
think nothing of raping Dalit women or consorting
with lower-caste prostitutes, even though touching
them by accident in the street is a sacrilege.
One of the main reasons why the caste system
has survived is because the hierarchical notion of
social good it perpetuates is legitimized by the
lower castes themselves. They replicate this
hierarchy by imitating the cultural values of the
upper castes, imposing discrimination on castes
even lower than their own.Sociologists claim there
are more than 2,000 castes and sub-castes within
the five categories. These are called j a t i s,
endogamous (inter-marrying) groups that are
divided along occupational, s e c t a r i a n , r e g i o n a l
and linguistic lines. Even as outcasts, the Dalits
divide themselves into further castes. Th i s
proliferation allows for discrimination both
horizontally and vertically, thus making social
relations all the more rigid and impermeable.
The plight of India’s untouchables and the
regular human rights abuses against them elicits
short-lived public outrage, leaving the state
u n d e r little pressure to engineer large-scale social
c h a n g e.This is why a coalition of Dalit groups and
activists have lobbied hard for their plight to be on
the agenda of the UN World Conference against
Racism.
“Caste is India’s hidden apartheid,” says Martin
M a c w a n ,4 1 ,convenor of the National Campaign on
Dalit Human Rights. He argues that like racism,
caste discrimination is “based on descent.”
Their demand has sparked off a national debate
about the nature of caste discrimination and
whether other countries should be allowed to
interfere in what the Indian government considers
There is only one
caste—humanity
Pampa, Indian poet and
writer, ninth century 
A woman defending India’s Untouchables garners support in the countryside.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
“an internal matter.”
The government has opposed the inclusion of
caste on the UN conference’s agenda on the grounds
that caste and race are not synonymous.“Race and
caste are distinct,” insists Soli Sorabjee, I n d i a ’s
attorney general and a member of the UN
Subcommission on Prevention of Discrimination.
I n d i a , a vigorous campaigner against apartheid,
claims that it has done everything possible to grant
equality to India’s lowest castes.A fifth of the seats
in parliament are reserved for members of the
scheduled castes (the official term for Dalits),and
some states are governed by powerful political
parties based on alliances with the lower castes.
Campaigns to
end the stigma
Quotas and job allocations, h o w e v e r, h a v e
n o t brought equality, d i g n i t y, or even safety for
I n d i a ’s “broken people.”In villages, the social stigma
remains too strong to obliterate by laws alone.
Official figures speak for themselves:recorded
crimes and atrocities against the lowest castes
averaged 26,000 a year between 1997 and 1999 (the
latest figures available).Considering the police are
often reluctant even to record claims against the
upper castes, these figures expose just the tip of the
iceberg.
About two-thirds of the Dalit population are
illiterate, and about half are landless agricultural
labourers. Only seven percent have access to safe
drinking water,electricity and toilets.And a majority
of the estimated 40 million bonded labourers (who
work as slaves to pay off debts), including 15 million
children,are Dalits.
A national campaign to highlight abuses against
Dalits was spearheaded by human rights groups in
eight Indian states in 1998,and caste has been taken
up as an issue internationally for the first time by
organizations including Human Rights Wa t c h .Wh i l e
some Dalits have resisted subjugation and
discrimination by armed struggle, these are
invariably quelled by more powerful upper-caste
private militia like the Ranbir Sena in Bihar,w h i c h
has been held responsible for a series of massacres
of poor Dalit peasants and landless labourers.
Macwan agrees that including caste
discrimination in the conference’s final resolutions
would be only a symbolic victory, changing nothing
in reality. “The only solution is to change people’s
minds,” he declares. ■
+ …
Broken People: Caste Violence against India’s
Untouchables, published in March 1999 by Human Rights
Watch,www.hrw.org
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 29
W H Y  R A C I S M ?
“Ja p a n ’s smooth social fabric is just an illusion,”says Nadamoto Masahisa,
who teaches modern history at Kyoto University. “It’s still based on
invisible castes and as Burakumin, we’re at the bottom of the ladder.”
Alongside his teaching,Masahisa is fighting to defend the Burakumin (or Eta-
Hinin, which can be translated as “polluted or dirty non-persons”) whom
society continues to shun.
The Buraku,as they are also known,were seen until the second half of the
19th century as an “untouchable”minority. Numbering over two million in
a country of 126 million people, they live in some 5,000 ghettos, which are
the direct result of an official outcast status that was abolished in 1871 at
the start of the Meiji era,when the country began industrializing at a rapid
pace.
The word Burakumin referred then to those who laboured mainly in
s l a u g h t e r h o u s e s, t a n n e r i e s, k n a c ke r ’s yards and morgues—people who
w o r ked with bodies, carcasses and blood, occupations that are unclean
according to Japan’s ancient Shinto religion.
All official discrimination against the Buraku has long disappeared. Th e
authorities point to the fact that members of this invisible caste today have
the same legal rights as all other Ja p a n e s e.They have the same physical traits,
speak the same language and share the same religion.
But written laws are not always the same as what goes on in people’s
minds. Masahisa and other militants are campaigning against unofficial
discrimination toward the Burakumin by property-owners, estate agents and
company offic i a l s. “A lot of Japanese think twice before renting to a
B u r a k u m i n ,” he says.“If a person is identified as one or says he is, e v e r y t h i n g
becomes harder. If you rent to a Buraku,people say you’ll have bad luck.”
In modern Ja p a n , the Burakumin are also socially marginalized. “In the
1960s and 1970s, they provided most of the workers in construction and
i n d u s t r y,” says a lawyer who is fighting against the wage discrimination long
practised in large companies against the Burakumin.“ Today they’re the fir s t
victims of the economic crisis.”
Their concentration in areas such as Osaka and the old imperial capital of
Kyoto makes them easier to spot, which only encour-
ages many to deny their social origins. To take one example, an influential
politician from the ruling Liberal Democratic Party, Hiromu Nonaka, has
always denied his connection with the Burakumin.
Even worse, some bourgeois Japanese families make illegal checks on the
ancestors of their children’s future spouses “to avoid polluting the family,”
as they put it.They hire special genealogical agencies to comb through the
old koseki (family registers) at the prefectures, often with the tacit approva l
of local officials. ■
Richard Werly, French journalist based in Japan
THE BURAKUMIN, JA PAN’S INVISIBLE OUTCASTS
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Tro u b l e i n
the hospitable land
Xenophobia has gained a foothold in Côte d’Ivoire: overcrowded land, common
law and economic crisis have spawned a “pro-Ivorian” movement hostile to
immigrants from neighbouring Mali and Burkina Faso
THEOPHILE KOUAMOUO
FREELANCE FRANCO-CAMEROONIAN JOURNALIST
T
hings aren’t the same any more between
Mamadou Ouedraogo and his old
school friends and former football
chums in the village of A s s e, in the fertile
black-soiled countryside of eastern Côte
d ’ I v o i r e.
“I’m on my guard now,” he says bitterly.
Mamadou,37,was born in Côte d’Ivoire but his
parents were immigrants from Burkina Fa s o.Th e
turning-point for him came earlier this year when
a strong wave of xenophobia swept the Abouré
people, who belong to the Akan, the country’s
largest ethnic group.
It all started with an argument between a
young Abouré and a Burkinabé night watchman
at the market in the town of Bonoua. Rumours
spread that the “foreigner”had killed “the local
m a n ,” which set off public fury and attacks on
the property of “aliens.”
Ousmane Sawadogo, the elderly chieftain of
the region’s large Burkinabé community, c a n ’t
forget what happened. “ They attacked the
Burkinabé district, smashed up and set fire to our
shops and broke open our barrels of cooking oil,”
he says. Several hundred shocked foreigners—
mainly Burkinabés and Malians—returned to
their countries or moved to friendlier parts of
Côte d’Ivoire. Those who decided to stay were
abused.
The king of Bonoua warned the immigrants to
stop growing pineapples, the province’s main
r e s o u r c e.“Several young Abouré then went round
the farms to check which foreigners were still
growing them,” says Sawadogo’s son Boukari.
“If they were, the Abouré marked the fields with
stakes and red cloth and then returned to destroy
the crops.”
Envy and
the soil
Bonoua is not the only place in Côte d’Ivoire
where this happens. Land disputes,once the norm
between local people and Ivorians from other
parts of the country, are now the commonest form
of violence between Ivorians and foreigners. At
the end of 1999, more than 20,000 Burkinabés
fled by the busload from the southwestern region
of Tabou after a dispute over land ownership
between an immigrant and a local farmer
degenerated into bloodshed.
At Blolequin,in the westernmost part of the
country, six people, including a policeman,were
killed early this year. But the local authorities
managed to keep the foreigners on their land,
against the advice of local elected officials and
despite public protests.
Why this upsurge of xenophobia in what the
Ivorian national anthem calls “the land of
hospitality”?
Until the end of colonial rule in 1960, Fr e n c h
authorities encouraged the immigration of
workers from the Sahel to help develop
a g r i c u l t u r e.This continued during the long rule of
Félix Houphouët-Boigny, the “father of the
nation,” who liked to say that “the land belongs
to those who make use of it.” The “ p r e s i d e n t -
f a r m e r,” who entered politics through rural trade
unions, had mainly economic ambitions. “Côte
d’Ivoire could never have become the world’s
Population (millions) 16
Surface area
(thousand sq.km) 322
Gross national income
per capita ($) 1,654
Life expectancy at birth (years) 48
Adult literacy rate (%) 46
Population below 15 years
of age (% of total) 43
Source: World Bank, UNDP.
All data 1999.
KEY DATA, CÔTE D’IVOIRE
C Ô T E  D ’ I V O I R E
ABIDJAN
Atlantic Ocean
M A L I
B U R K I N A
F A S O
G H A N A
L I B E R I A
G U I N E A
Tabou
30 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
2 . THE EXCLUDED
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
biggest cocoa producer if it had just used Ivorian
labour,” says Jean-Paul Chausse, an expert with
the World Bank.
To d a y, Côte d’Ivoire has a very high
proportion of resident foreigners—26 percent
of the total population, according to offic i a l s, a n d
more than 35 percent according to other
e s t i m a t e s. Their presence caused no problem
during Houphouët-Boigny’s rule, a time of
prosperity that lasted until the end of the Cold
War for this faithful ally of the We s t . But as
economic recession set in, relations with
immigrants deteriorated.
Their success irritates the locals. “ They say
we’ve got rich, have big cars and that we don’t
respect them any more,” says Boukari.“ They say
they don’t want to see us with their women any
more and if a foreigner’s caught with an Abouré
woman,he gets fined about $200.”
“ B e f o r e,” grumbles Niamkey Eloi, an Ivorian
farmer from Asse,“the Burkinabé didn’t ask for
anything, they simply worked for us.”
With the economic crisis and the austerity
imposed by international financial institutions,
many Ivorians can no longer get work in the
towns, either as government employees or in the
private sector, so they fall back on the soil.“ We ’r e
seeing competition for land now as a result of
land overcrowding,” says Chausse. “These days,
many fathers don’t leave more than a hectare or
two of land to their children because they’v e
already sold most of what they had.”
Deforestation and the expansion of towns have
speeded up this process.
At Bonoua, in the Akan country, the tradition
of matriarchy exacerbates the problem.“Young
uneducated people return to the village to find
their parents’ lands controlled by their maternal
uncles, who are the rightful heirs under common
l a w,” says deputy prefect Julie Aka Sonoh.“ Th e y
d o n ’t agree with that but they can’t challenge
their own uncles. So they divert their aggression
and target the foreigners these lands have been
rented to.”
In this explosive situation, H o u p h o u ë t -
B o i g n y ’s successor, Henri Konan Bédié, who was
overthrown by the army in December 1999,
introduced the notion of “I v o i r i t é,” a reference to
native-born Ivorians. The goal: to force out of
the electoral race his old rival in the shadow of the
“father of the nation,” the economist and former
prime minister Alassane Ouattara, on the grounds
that one of his parents came from neighbouring
Burkina Faso, where he had been educated.
A new legal solution?
To some, the aim was to forge a common
identity for the country’s 60 or so ethnic groups,
to others it was a nationalist ploy. Either way it
stirred up a strong brew of intercommunal
b i t t e r n e s s. In A b i d j a n , the political debate
revolved around foreigners, who were accused
of being the secret weapon of Ouattara’s
Republican Rally party and became the scapegoat
for the turbulent election campaign.
Laurent Gbagbo, leader of the social-
democratic Ivorian Popular Fr o n t , was elected
president in October 2000 and made the land
question his top priority.To solve the problem,t h e
government decided to enact the rural land law,
In 1999,over 20,000 Burkinabés fled from the Tabou region after a dispute over land ownership.
All the pots have
been fired in the
same way and in
the same kiln, 
yet they are
different, for the
pigment takes on
some better than
others. . . and the
colour varies in
beauty. 
Proverb from the Mongo
tribe, Congo
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 31
W H Y  R A C I S M ?
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
passed unanimously by parliament in 1998,which
said Ivorians owned all the land but could rent it to
foreigners.
The law is broadly based on various common
law systems, under which “land belonged to the
ancestors,” explains Chausse.
“ The right to use it could be sold but not
t h e land itself. In the southwest, for example, a c c e s s
to land is easier. Foreigners were able to negotiate
a deal which was nearly as good as ownership.”
H e n c e f o r t h , foreigners who have acquired land
can keep it until they die, after which their children
can rent it from the state. Burkinabé President
Blaise Compaoré recently expressed concern that
it could deprive Burkinabé in Côte d’Ivoire of
“their”land.
“ The law has its good sides but it’s also
d a n g e r o u s,” says Chausse.“It wants to clarify things
and encourage settlement of disputes. If it’s
properly applied, it can settle many things. But if it’s
a b u s e d , it will exacerbate tension between local
people and foreigners.” ■
In the early 1970s, there were approximately 700,000 refugees in black
A f r i c a ;20 years later, that figure had soared to over six million1.Today nearly
one in every three Africans is a refugee on the African continent. Forced
displacements and the destabilization of populations have rocked Africa more
than any other part of the world in recent years. Around seven million
Africans are internally displaced (within their own country), while traditional
or new economic immigration flows have further swollen the number of
refugees.
Waves of xenophobia in several black African countries must be understood
in this context (see box).Periodic droughts drive hundreds of thousands of
people from their homes, but geopolitical changes within and between
states do even more to bring about these population transfers and the
human rights violations underpinning them.
O b v i o u s l y, the sudden,massive arrival of hundreds of thousands of foreigners
in a neighbouring African country already struggling to feed its own
population can be source of tension and rejection.However, the generosity
of the African countries that offer first asylum is striking. For example, in the
1 9 9 0 s, Guinea and Côte d’Ivoire welcomed over a million people fleeing the
civil wars in Liberia and Sierra Leone.Ten years later, most of them have still
neither gone back home nor found a permanent place to live.
The wars in Liberia and Sierra Leone were emblematic in many ways. They
have often been portrayed as having an “ e t h n i c ”c o m p o n e n t , but the desire
to control economic resources—wood smuggling in Liberia and diamond
t r a f ficking in Sierra Leone, with the active complicity of multinational
corporations—is also a cause of these conflicts and a means to finance them.
In both cases, the protagonists, b a c ked by foreign parties and neighbouring
or even geographically distant countries, took the war outside national
b o r d e r s : refugee camps were used as bases for revenge. The climate of
insecurity that often prevails in them, the remote prospects of settling
permanently in a wealthier country, the international community’s indifference
and even disengagement, in contrast, for example, to what happened in
Kosovo and East Ti m o r, fuel the flames of revenge. Recruits are easier to enlist
for the next round of violence, sparking a new exodus.
The widespread destabilization of populations is more to blame for African
xenophobia than “ethnic hatred.” States that have been frail since their
c r e a t i o n , because their national borders seldom match historical and cultural
realities, are further weakened by corruption and their inability to ensure
d e v e l o p m e n t . The Cold Wa r ’s “ c o n flicts by proxy” have been replaced by new
c o n fli c t s, used by the more powerful African states, that play the ethnic card
and give that dimension a charge of hatred and rejection that is far from
s p o n t a n e o u s. In the final analysis, the “struggle for power” over which
“groups, movements and clans fight,often ruthlessly,” is the driving force
behind ethnic conflict.
Cast as “tribal wa r s,” these conflicts and their attendant human rights
violations and hatred might last unless the world’s conscience feels moved
or responsible.The genocide in Rwanda was the cruellest proof of this. ■
* Secretary general of the International Federation for Human Rights
(IFHR).
1. Refugees by numbers 2000 edition, UNHCR, 2000
2. Gildas Simon, Géodynamique des migrations internationales, PUF,
Paris, 1995
DRISS EL YA Z A M I * :
B L ACK A F R I C A : “ETHNIC HAT R E D ” IS NOT INEVITA B L E
MASSIVE EXPULSIONS IN A F R I C A
1958 Côte d’Ivoire: Expulsion of 10,000 natives of
Dahomey (present-day Benin).
1969 Ghana: Flight of nearly one million 
people.
1983 Nigeria: Flight of 1.5 million citizens from
West African countries.
1985 Nigeria: Expulsion of  700,000 citizens from
Ghana, Niger and other countries.
1985 Côte d’Ivoire: 10,000 Ghanaians expelled.
1993 South Africa: Expulsion of some 80,000
Mozambicans.
1994 South Africa: Expulsion of  90,000 citizens
from other African countries.
1995 Gabon: Forced flight of 55,000 foreigners.
1998 Ethiopia: Expulsion of 50,000 Eritreans.
32 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 33
W H Y  R A C I S M ?
IVAN BRISCOE
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Fo r t ress Euro p e
bids you welcome
Europe’s governments are struggling to stem the flow of migrants from
poor countries while opening the gates wide for the best of the world’s
workers. Is their policy tenable?
2 . THE EXCLUDED
W
hen Huzefa Hundekari decided it was
time for a change of scene, the doors
of Western Europe swung invitingly
o p e n . Helped by some very co-
operative immigration officials and
the promise of a hefty salary, this 29-year-old Indian
manager in a multinational IT firm glided into his new
posting in Fr a n k f u r t .“ They have a defined process laid
o u t . They require a set of papers, then you get your
green card. It does not take more than 15 to 20 days.”
From the perspective of a vast squat in central Paris,
H u n d e k a r i ’s experiences seem closer to a work of
fic t i o n . Ten years ago, Mamadou Tr a o r e, now aged 35,
fled for a new life.Coming from Mali,he crossed several
thousand kilometres of desert,ventured through A l g e r i a
just as civil war was beginning, crossed the
Mediterranean in a perilous dinghy, and arrived in Paris
three months later, penniless and not knowing a soul.
Unfortunately for Tr a o r e, French immigration
o f ficials rarely give visas for effort. His applications for
legal residency have been refused three times. Now he
lives frugally with 350 others, all in similar straits.“A t
any time we could be arrested or deported.You always
have to prepare for the worst.”
Wanted:
“the best brains”
To judge from these rival experiences, no single
account can now be given of immigration to Europe.
Whereas Hundekari has profited from a desperate
effort by the German government to reinforce the
new economy, Traore and an estimated four million
other illegal migrants in the European Union live
hand-to-mouth,shunned by governments and by the
citizens of their host countries.
Open to the skilled, restricted for the poor and
even the persecuted, Western Europe is conceiving a
new model of welcome. “ We do not consider
immigration to be just a burden any more, but an
e n r i c h m e n t ,”declared Rita Süssmuth, head of an offic i a l
German commission that has called for up to
2 0 0 , 0 0 0 visas to be handed out each year, preferably to
the “best brains.” For the first time in 30 years,
governments are championing the economic utility of
n o n - E u r o p e a n s. But the question remains: if migrants
are gauged on their use, then what becomes of their
s t a t u s ?
“Europe has not escaped from what seems to be
the destiny of all areas experiencing rapid growth:
the need to bring in labour supplies from outside,”
wrote the American sociologist Saskia Sassen in her
b o o k , Guests and Aliens (New Press, 2 0 0 0 ) . Indeed the
past 200 years of European history have been rich in
mass movement and its usual companion, x e n o p h o b i c
hatred: Poles, Slavs and Jews moved West in number
in the 19th century,earning a wary reception from host
countries that showed much less reluctance in peopling
colonies and dispatching 50 million migrants across the
Atlantic prior to 1914.Following the devastating racial
politics of the next three decades, Europe resumed its
normal labour-absorbing course, this time recruiting
workers from A s i a , Africa and the Middle East in
unprecedented quantities—around 70 million,
including those who returned to their countries of
origin—for the job of postwar reconstruction.
The downturn of the 1970s put a swift end to all
t h a t . Workers were no longer free to come, o n l y
relatives of those already settled and asylum-seekers.
Unemployment and prejudice in turn nurtured a
virulent right-wing backlash in Fr a n c e, Germany and
B r i t a i n , the main countries at risk of being “ s w a m p e d .”
For today’s political elite, the lessons of those
decades are still fresh. Buoyant economic performance
may well have blunted the extremists’ appeal, b u t
In Calais (Fra n c e ) , checking trucks for migrants being smuggled into Euro p e.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
containment of numbers remains a critical part of
immigration policy. For EU ministers, this means
whittling down the 390,000 asylum applications made
last year and halting the unregistered human cargo—
if only, as they claim, to protect immigrants’ well-
being.
“ Those who co-operate on this issue at the
European level are from interior and justice
m i n i s t r i e s,”explains Virginie Guiraudon,an expert in
migration policy from the University of Lille. “ Fo r
t h e m , immigration policy means immigration control.
As long as these people control the agenda, t h e r e ’s no
reason to see any change in the repressive policy,
meaning most decisions are about illegal migration,
human smuggling, barrier sanctions or restricting
asylum.”
Yet despite the ministers’ best efforts, the flow of
people does not seem to have relented. The world
counts  an estimated 21 million refugees, m o s t l y
displaced by war or political breakdown.Only a tiny
proportion are now in Europe, but the spread of
global media,means of transport and sharply widening
inequality between the developing world and
Europe—historically the most fundamental cause of
mass migration—promises to deliver many more
people like Traore to the shores of affluence.
The danger of opening the doors to this exodus,
politicians maintain, lies in Europe’s perennial
spectre—the draconian right.Vlaams Bok is one such
political force.Founded in 1977 as a Flemish nationalist
p a r t y, its policies towards Belgium’s migrant
population call for total closure of borders, i m m e d i a t e
deportation of all illegal migrants, summary expulsion
of any foreigner who has turned to crime.“ I m m i g r a n t s
d o n ’t adapt,” declares Philippe Van Der Sande,
spokesman for the party in A n t w e r p, where it won 33
percent of the vote in 1999 elections. “ They don’t
want to learn the language.They are not interested in
our culture but just winning easy money.”
The far right’s new clothes
Opinions like these can be heard in all European
c o u n t r i e s, and have even risen to government rank in
Au s t r i a . Yet in place of the boisterous nationalism
that characterized the previous generation of far-
right parties, groups like Vlaams Bok take a defensive
p o s t u r e : the party is not racist,Van Der Sande says, b u t
only wishes to preserve what Flemish society has
laboured to achieve.“ We Europeans are a minority in
the world, and we are considered to have a good
welfare system. If we give the impression that
everyone is welcome here, millions of people will
want to come.”
For modern Europe’s far right—and for sizeable
minorities of the population in Fr a n c e, B e l g i u m ,
Germany and Scandinavia according to surveys—the
immigrant may be avaricious, bedridden,criminal or
simply a job-stealer, s e l fishly milking the society that
happens to be richer. As critics point out, the far-
r i g h t ’s rhetoric on immigration now differs from that
An assembly in the teeming quarters of a hostel for immigrant workers on the outskirts of Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 35
W H Y  R A C I S M ?
of governments only by a matter of degree.
The irony is that the debate has moved back into
the economists’ camp:far from crippling a high quality
of welfare, immigrants are now touted as possibly the
way to preserve living standards in an ageing Europe.
The UN Population Division claims that 13.5 million
new migrants are needed each year to keep Europe’s
ratio of workers and pensioners steady.
Until now, certain businesses have clamoured for
unimpeded access to the global labour market.
Shortages in new technological industries have already
toppled Germany’s 30-year freeze on foreign labour.
The rest of Europe is chasing alongside, while bumped-
up quotas for the exceptionally computer-gifted have
been brandished by Australia, Japan and the United
S t a t e s.Recession in Silicon Va l l e y,h o w e v e r, may have
slammed one door shut: 400,000 foreigners are believed
to be at risk of losing their jobs. Each sacked worker
will have 10 days to leave the country.
Closed borders,
an invitation to slavery 
Yet it is not only high skills that Europe has been
searching. As expectations of comfortable desk-jobs
have become the norm,workers to fill more gruelling
vacancies are also lacking. And it is here that the
current immigration policy shows its deepest
contradictions. Several countries now run quotas for
these jobs:Italy plans 83,000 visas this year for farm
labourers while Spain indulges migrant house-cleaners.
But there are few illusions as to where the bulk of
this cheap labour is going to come from. “ I n
construction,packaging and agriculture it’s the same
all over Europe. Nobody wants to pick up asparagus
w h o ’s not an illegal migrant any more,” o b s e r v e s
Guiraudon.
C h e a p, utterly unprotected by the law and willing
to work in the most menial conditions, illegal migrants
are some employers’ ideal candidates.Though Tr a o r e
has been refused his visa three times, never have the
French authorities sought to stop him from working,
n o r,he insists, from paying social security contributions
for services he was never eligible to use.
“Closing the frontiers serves above all else to
make slaves,” argues Jean-Pierre Alaux,an official at
G I S T I , a Paris-based NGO that helps immigrants.
“People are going to arrive all the same:all the interior
ministers know it,and all the bosses know it.”
The critical question for Europe’s governments
and peoples is whether this opening of borders, sotto
v o c e and driven by purely economic criteria, is the best
way to create well-integrated societies.Riots in several
northern English cities have proved in the last few
months that even communities dating from the post-
war migrant influx can continue in utter segregation.
For many pro-migrant activists, the danger is that the
new economic opening will simply reinforce a deep-
seated racism.“In some part of our collective cultural
mentality in the We s t ,w e ’ve kept a certain number of
values which are the same as from the time of slavery,”
argues A l a u x . “ For us, the South is a sort of raw
material.”
A chilling demonstration of these prejudices came
last year, when the murder of a native woman by a
mentally disturbed Moroccan labourer triggered anti-
migrant riots in the Spanish town of El Ejido. Fo r
y e a r s, workers have come from North Africa to farms
that have brought an unprecedented wealth to this
desert region. Necessary or not, these illegal labourers
live apart,often in shacks without water and electricity,
paid pitifully little and despised by the local
agricultural elite.“ Th e r e ’s an expression local people
u s e : they say let [the migrants] cross the straits, take a
w a s h , so long as they throw away the water and
become Spanish,” reports Antonio Puertas, p r e s i d e n t
of the local NGO Almeria Acoge.
“How do you get accepted here? Even if you could,
do you really want to drop your sense of self, whiten
your skin and become a Christian?”wonders Traore.
Though Europe has managed to create a few
urban centres of multi-racial harmony, c u l t u r a l
discrimination and economic segregation, shown at its
extreme in El Ejido, have proved much harder to
o v e r c o m e. In closing borders, referring all justific a t i o n
for immigration back to economics, establishing quotas
and limiting rights to permanent settlement—even
for the highly skilled—governments might appear to
be accentuating the view that foreigners are second-
class citizens and potential parasites. As Guiraudon
points out, one country that has heavily depended
on quotas of short-term foreign labour is Switzerland,
also one of the last countries to pass a law on racial
integration.
But there are many other imponderables.Will the
pension crisis be as severe as the UN expects? Could
an enlarged Europe with freedom of movement for a
largely white population harden prejudices against
non-EU migrants or assuage them? Might recession
trigger a violent anti-migrant movement that even
reaches the professional echelons (as occurred during
For most migrants arriving in developed countries, seeking asylum remains the only way
to secure a right to stay. Last year, 390,000 people applied for asylum in Europe.A similar
total is expected for 2001, with figures from the United Nations High Commissioner for
Refugees suggesting that Germany and Britain will remain the principle receivers, while
Afghanistan, Turkey and Iraq continue as the main countries of origin.
Western European countries have responded with strict border controls and rejection of up
to 90 percent of asylum claims, often arguing that the migrants are driven by pure economic
n e c e s s i t y. British Foreign Secretary Jack Straw has even called for the 1951 Geneva
Convention to be amended in light of these supposed abuses.
But the migrants have not stopped—from the 16 Romanians found under a Eurostar in early
A u g u s t , to the 908 Kurds whose boat grounded on the French Riviera in Fe b r u a r y, to the dozens
who cross from Morocco every day. Once in Europe, the migrants can expect possible
detention (1,000 asylum seekers are in British jails), illegal work,administrative indifference
and public contempt.According to Arun Kundnani of the London-based Campaign Against
Racism and Fa s c i s m , o f ficial “demonization of asylum seeke r s ” has fostered “a new,
popular racism.” ■
THE ROAD TO A S Y L U M
I am the colour 
of those who are
persecuted.
Alphonse de Lamartine,
French poet (1790-1869)
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
What do you believe are the fundamental sources of
racism in the world?
The first thing we must be clear about is that racism
as an ideology is a product of the modern world.
Obviously history has given us many examples of
violence between different human groups, but not
until the modern era was this violence justified by
reference to racist thinking. In my opinion,the link is
the following: modernity is characterized by forces
that are inclusive and universal,while in practice—in
p o l i t i c a l , social and military affairs—it is discriminatory.
This contradiction is partly resolved by a racist ideology
which excludes groups of peoples who are defined as
essentially different.
In your opinion, has globalization accentuated racism or
reduced it?
I t ’s difficult to give a very general answer,but I have
the impression that at the moment the main effect of
the process is to increase racism.The reason for this is
fairly simple: globalization is a classic example of
m o d e r n i t y. I t ’s clearly unifying the world, but on a
hierarchical and exclusive basis. Remember that when
we talk about globalization we are talking largely
about the unification of money markets, speculative
financial flows, information and the organization of
p r o d u c t i o n .But the same definitely does not go for the
movement of people. Somehow this contradiction
between the free movement of money and the
segmentation of the world must be justifie d , and this is
done by reference to supposed natural differences.
Do you believe that the outbreaks of racism observed in
Africa,Asia and Europe all stem from the same causes?
No two examples of racism are the same since
their historical contexts are always different.Having
said that, I believe it is possible to say how racism
functions in general: n a m e l y, as a naturalization of
identity that aims to legitimate the discriminatory
treatment of different groups, leading in extreme cases
to those groups’ destruction or genocide. But though
we can make such a generalization, we are still obliged
to study each case for its particular historical origins.
I t ’s clear that in Asia and Africa there are racist
phenomena that are strongly influenced by
g l o b a l i z a t i o n , and are thus similar to the racism
characteristic of Europe and the Americas. But there
are also violent ethnic conflicts that stem from the
specific histories of those continents.
You have stressed the ro l e, especially in Euro p e a n
p o l i t i c s, of the “ d e m o g raphic factor.”What exactly do you
mean by this?
Racism can’t be understood as the simple
consequences of demographic pressure—it’s not a
mechanical phenomenon. Large migratory fluxes have
become a real problem for the first time in 50 years.
And though “south to south” migration barely makes
the news—being seen as a minor aspect of the “new
world order”—the dismemberment of Yu g o s l a v i a
drew attention to supposed masses of refugees.This has
transformed demographics into a critical element on
European governments’ political agendas.
In my recent work,I develop an analogy between
Europe today and in the1930s. It’s clear that we have
been pushed back to one of the principle historical
features of that time,when the idea of mass deportation
or social engineering was considered a fundamental
part of geopolitics.
Some experts would arg u e, h o w e v e r, that unlike the
INTERVIEW BY IVAN BRISCOE
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
A re t u r n to nature
Is it possible to gauge the influence of globalization and mass migration
on the future of racist thought? Alberto Burgio*, a leading Italian analyst
of racism, examines the ethnic panorama
2 . THE EXCLUDED
* Professor of the history of
ideas at the University of
B o l o g n a , author of
L’Invenzione delle Razze
[The Invention of Races],
I volumi (1998) and L a
Guerra delle Razze [The
Race Wars],(2001)
Illegal asylum seekers from the
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 37
1930s extremist parties in Europe are on the decline:
F ra n c e ’s National Fro n t , for instance, is no longer so
strong.
When you make a historical analogy, you obviously
have to be aware that history does not repeat itself. I t ’s
a question instead of asking if there is a set of shared
phenomena which can help us find our way around
contemporary politics. I point to three such
p h e n o m e n a ,which I believe were extremely important
in the 1930s and continue to be very heavily present in
the first years of the new century.
Firstly, war has returned to the heart of Europe
through the Balkans, and is once again seen as a real
political option by European and We s t e r n
g o v e r n m e n t s. S e c o n d l y, as I mentioned earlier,
demographics and frontier protection have become key
parts of government policy,especially for the European
Union since the implementation of the Schengen
accords in 1995.Th i r d l y, racism has become once again
an ideological weapon,and the representation of social
and political relations in ethnic terms has become an
ideological means of producing consensus in We s t e r n
democratic societies. Not only in Au s t r i a ,S w i t z e r l a n d
or Belgium,but also in Britain,Germany and France:
in March 2000, over 60 percent of Fr e n c h p e o p l e
admitted in a survey to holding racist opinions.
In Italy and other countries there has been earnest
debate over the issue of national culture and its
protection.Is this is just a cover for racist prejudices or
a reflection of wider concerns?
If an Italian like me compares myself with a Fr e n c h
c i t i z e n , I can obviously talk about my eating habits, m y
l i f e s t y l e, my tastes, indeed everything which
distinguishes an Italian from another nationality,
without necessarily being racist.But there is a point
when the discussion becomes racist,and that is when
one says these differences are too large to be
eliminated,they are too large to allow people to live
together as equals.
Turning to the Muslims and Arab peoples in Italy,
it’s said that the culture of these people is not only
different from our own,but also prevents them from
i n t e g r a t i n g. Therefore assimilation in a democratic
country where everyone is equal before the law
becomes impossible.The ambiguity of the racist stance
is that it acknowledges essential human
characteristics—it talks of culture,of religion, of history,
of traditions—yet treats all of these as if they were only
aspects of nature. It translates what is historical into
what is natural,and thus impossible to change.
Giacomo Biffi, the Archbishop of Bologna, h a s
clearly stated that we must welcome only immigrants
who come from Christian countries, starting with
Filipinos since they are Catholics. And it’s not just
B i f fi.An important writer and political scientist called
Giovanni Sartori, who lived for several years in the
United States and taught at Columbia University, h a s
written a book saying exactly the same thing.
Do you believe the coming years will see incre a s e d
exploitation of racism at the political level?
It’s difficult to make predictions. If the hawkish
approach to governing globalization wins—by which
I mean that of a confrontation between poor and
rich—I believe we will see years of hard conflict,and
amid this conflict there is sure to be a violent rejection
of the continuous flow of people coming to the richer
parts of the world. These conflicts will also be
interpreted politically by the right, namely by the
political entrepreneurs of spontaneous racism.
But there is also the possibility, or rather the hope,
that leaders of the richest and most powerful countries
try to govern these differences between the rich and
poor parts of the world in a less violent and more
reasonable way.This is unfortunately less likely than the
first option,but if it occurs, we may see a progressive
reduction in the problem of racism.
Can anything be done to combat racism in individual
countries rather than at the global level?
Anti-racist campaigns must be rooted in the
concrete reality of different countries or regions,
otherwise you can make only moral platitudes—and
no-one needs those. Instead we need to be able to
make practical interventions in real situations. Th e
United Nations and other large organizations must
continue to make governments aware of this problem,
as must world public opinion. ■
W H Y  R A C I S M ?
Balkans under arrest in Greece.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Brang Ja (not his real name) was only 16
when he was enlisted in the Myanmar
army in 1997.But the decision wasn’t his.
He was on his way to visit his mother in the
far north of Myanmar when the police
arrested him in the city of Mandalay
because he wasn’t carrying any
identification papers.
Two months later, military policemen
visited him in jail and offered him a way
out by joining the army. He agreed, f e a r i n g
that he would otherwise remain in jail for
y e a r s. One of the officers remarked that he
was “at the best age to begin military
t r a i n i n g.”But when he and other released
prisoners arrived at a military training
camp in the northern town of Shwebo,
they found that some recruits were as
young as nine.A few of them had tried to
escape from the camp, but no one had
succeeded.
BERTIL LINTNER
SENIOR WRITER,
FAR EASTERN ECONOMIC REVIEW
The child in arms
Myanmar’s protracted civil and ethnic wars have forced one of the highest number of children in the
world onto the battlefield, bringing them face to face with beatings,
murder and a blossoming drugs trade
After serving in one of Myanmar’s
numerous civil wars between its myriad
ethnic groups, Brang Ja managed to flee
through the jungle to Thailand,where he
related his experiences.
Since 1988, when the military brutally
suppressed a nation-wide uprising for
d e m o c r a cy, the strength of Myanmar’s
armed forces has more than doubled,f r o m
about 185,000 men to 450,000 today. The
officially stated goal is to build a 500,000-
strong army to crush the widespread ethnic
unrest and stifle any popular dissent.
Myanmar (formerly Burma) is the
only country in East Asia that is expanding
its military instead of reducing it. Th i s
rapid growth has been possible because
children are routinely recruited.The total
number of child soldiers here is difficult to
e s t i m a t e. But observers guess that at least
50,000 children are engaged in military
a c t i v i t y. Many of these boys are kidnapped
or forcibly conscripted into the Ta t m a d a w
(the Burmese name for the armed forces),
and about half this number serve in the
private armies of various ethnic groups.
The Coalition to Stop the Use of Child
Soldiers (see interview p. 40) believes that
Myanmar “rivals parts of Africa as one of
the largest recruiters of child soldiers”in
the world.
A 1992 document from UN I C E F s t a t e s
that 14-year-olds are officially conscripted.
Placed in military camps for training, t h e y
are called “Ye Nyunt Lunge,” or “Brave
Sprout Youth.”
These recruits are often expected to
perform the same duties as adult soldiers,
and may be beaten or killed if they are not
able to do so. Children are sometimes used
in frontline combat or in dangerous
human-wave attacks, in which hundreds
have been killed. Others are used to dig
t r e n c h e s, cook or serve as porters carrying
ammunition and supplies.According to a
report entitled “No Childhood at A l l ? ”
by Images A s i a , an NGO based in Chiang
Mai (Thailand),most child soldiers have
never attended school or were pulled out
after just a few years.
A “mother and 
father” army
“Many of us were only 14 or 15 years
o l d ,” says an unnamed child soldier,
quoted in the report.“ There were three or
four soldiers who were only 12…they
c o u l d n ’t carry their rifles properly, t h e y
were so small, but they had to do the same
training as regular soldiers. Chiko, a 12-
y e a r- o l d , served as an attendant to a
c o r p o r a l . One day, he was beaten up really
badly by him and sent to hospital. H e
ended up blind and half-paralyzed from
it… I actually saw this beating.”
Street children and orphans are
particularly vulnerable and are taught that
the army is their only “mother and father.”
The UNICEF report identified at least one
military camp near Kengtung in eastern
Shan state. It noted that children as young
as seven were being trained and used as
“porters, human shields or human mine-
sweepers.”
The Images Asia report is replete with
examples of atrocities against Myanmar’s
child soldiers. Aung Tay, 14,talks about a
drunk battalion commander who shot
three boys while they slept because they
did not obey his command to wake up.
“ They couldn’t wake up because they had
Per Ler, a 13-year-old child recruited by the God’s Army, a Karen militia.
◗ E T H I C S
38 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
been making bricks all night and were
exhausted,”Aung Tay says.
The report says most child soldiers
have either witnessed murders or been
forced to kill and plunder. During an
offensive in Mawchi, Kayah state, Ay e
Myint and a band of boy soldiers “ e n t e r e d
a village and shot all the villagers, b e c a u s e
we thought of them as our enemies. We
took all their pigs and chickens, all usable
goods…then we burnt the village.We took
all the women and raped them, and fin a l l y
we murdered them.”
Some child soldiers join the army
willingly to protect their families from the
army or to provide a much-needed income.
These perceived “ b e n e f i t s ” are rarely
r e a l i z e d , especially when child soldiers are
stationed far from their own villages. C h i l d
recruits are underpaid or not paid at all due
to rampant corruption in the military.
“They are forced to grow up too quickly,”
says Ma Mi Suu Pwint,a female soldier in
a resistance militia (All-Burma Students’
Democratic Front),quoted in the report.
“I joined the military in 1993,when I
was 16,” says Tai Ling Au n g, a fis h e r m a n ’s
s o n , quoted in the report.“My family was
very poor and I had to join the Ta t m a d a w
to support them.”
The plight of Myanmar’s children has
been highlighted in recent reports by the
World Bank and the Asian Development
B a n k . The lack of educational
opportunities for young recruits only
compounds the grave economic and social
problems affecting the country.
Since Myanmar’s independence from
Britain in 1948, several of the country’s
ethnic minorities, who make up an
estimated 40 percent of the
p o p u l a t i o n ,have been fig h t i n g
for autonomy or outright
s e p a r a t i o n .This tragedy is seen
as the main reason why
M y a n m a r, a country with no
real external enemies, began to
build up a strong army as early
as the 1950s. In 1962,the army
seized direct power over the
state in a coup d’état and began
to rule by decree, a b o l i s h i n g
M y a n m a r ’s fragile
parliamentary system. Th e
military also introduced a
disastrous policy  called “The
Burmese Way to Socialism,”
which turned what had once
been one of A s i a ’s most
prosperous countries into a
political and economic wreck.
A narcotics militia
Annual resolutions by the United
Nations urging the military to open a
dialogue with the opposition have
produced few tangible results, d e s p i t e
recent efforts by the UN’s special envoy to
Myanmar, Razali Ismail.
Since the 1988 uprising, the military
authorities have signed ceasefire
agreements with more than 20 ethnic rebel
a r m i e s, which have thus been “ b r o u g h t
into the legal fold.” The level of fighting
and military recruitment of children
should have fallen.Yet many of the armies
continue to recruit them after a ceasefir e.
The worst of these offenders is the
drug-running United Wa State A r m y
( U W S A ) , which controls a large swathe of
territory adjacent to the Chinese border.
The group stopped fighting with the
government after a peace agreement in
1 9 8 9 . N o w, leaders of the group are
frequent visitors to the capital, R a n g o o n ,a s
well as Mandalay and other cities, where
they have substantial investments in real
e s t a t e, the hotel business and
m a n u f a c t u r i n g. But they still seem to need
an army to protect the many heroin and
methamphetamine laboratories that have
been established inside UWSA’s territory.
According to international anti-
narcotics agencies, the UWSA is the most
heavily armed drug-trafficking
organization in the world. More than half
of this 20,000-strong army consists of
c h i l d r e n ,many of them 10- or 12-years-old.
Among the ethnic armies still
rebelling against the government, t h e
Karen National Union (KNU) is known
to recruit very young children and use
them in combat. In early 2000, a n o t h e r
much smaller Karen militia called “ G o d ’s
A r m y ” attracted worldwide attention
after they attacked a hospital in
R a t c h a b u r i , a town across Myanmar’s
border with Thailand.
The guerrilla force was led by two 12-
y e a r-old twin boys, Johnny and Luther
H t o o, and most of their troops were other
Karen children who had been orphaned in
the civil war. These children have known
nothing but violence since they were born.
And this tragic state of affairs is likely to
continue as long as Myanmar remains a
war zone. ■
Sizing up youngsters enlisted in the Mong Tai Army, run by former druglord Khun Sa.
Population (millions): 45
Surface area (thousand
sq.km.) 677
Gross national income
per capita ($): 1,027
Life expectancy at birth (years)
56
Adult literacy rate (%) 84
Population below 15 years of
age (% of total) 33
All data 1999. Sources: World Bank,
UNDP.
KEY DATA
M y a n m a r
RANGOON
I N D I A
C H I N A
Andaman 
Sea
Gulf
of
Siam
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
How many child soldiers are there?
More than 300,000 children under 18
are fighting as soldiers with government
armed forces and rebel groups in 41
countries worldwide. A d d i t i o n a l l y,
thousands of under-18s stand
ready for combat in 87
c o u n t r i e s. While most child
soldiers are 15 to 18, t h e
youngest age recorded is
seven.
A re children recruited because
t h e re is a shortage of adult
s o l d i e rs? Or is this a more
deadly form of child labour? 
The more protracted the
c o n f l i c t , the more likely
children will participate.
Children are cheap, m o r e
g u l l i b l e, and easier to
condition into fearless killing
and unthinking obedience
than adults are.We ’ve heard
stories of children who have rushed into
g u n f i r e, not realizing that the bullets
could kill them.During the border war
with Eritrea in 1999-2000, E t h i o p i a n
government forces reportedly press-
ganged [forcibly recruited] thousands of
students from marketplaces and villages,
some of whom were used in human wave
attacks across minefields.
What pushes children into combat? 
Many who have experienced or
witnessed abuse by state authorities  join
to feel secure or to protect and feed their
families, which rarely works. Ethnic and
indigenous children are often targeted,a s
in Guatemala during the civil war.They
are also trafficked across borders—
children from Rwanda and Uganda have
fought in the Democratic Republic of
C o n g o, while Pakistani children have
been used in Afghanistan.
The rebel Tamil T i g e rs group has used girls
as suicide bombers in Sri Lanka because
they are less likely to arouse suspicion. D o
you know of any similar examples of
female recruitment? 
S i g n i ficantly more boys are recruited,
but in some confli c t s, as many as a third of
the child soldiers are girls.They have been
abducted in large numbers in northern
Uganda and Sierra Leone by resistance
groups and used for combat duties and as
sexual slaves. They were also used in El
Salvador during the civil war.
What is the impact of soldiering on
c h i l d ren? Besides the obvious physical
r i s k , do they ever get over the
psychological trauma? 
The impact is dramatic. I ’ve spoken to
former child soldiers who have fla s h b a c k s
and nightmares about their combat
e x p e r i e n c e s, and get nervous simply
being approached from behind.They are
always on the alert,ready for an attack.
Children have been through years of
military experience, but don’t know how
to read and write, and have no skills that
can be used in a civilian economy.
What can be done to ensure that these
c h i l d ren aren’t written off even though
they are generally illiterate and have no
job skills? 
If they have support and are given a
second chance at education or vocational
t r a i n i n g, they can become
very successful members of
s o c i e t y. I t ’s important to
have long-term
programmes in place. I n
L i b e r i a , there was a very
rapid demobilization of
child soldiers followed by
very few rehabilitation
p r o g r a m m e s, so many
children ended up being re-
recruited or joined criminal
gangs. In other places like
Angola or Sierra Leone,
conflicts erupt again.
Ongoing programmes
have worked well in
Mozambique and in
northern Uganda. The best
ones involve the community and combine
modern psychology and child
development with traditional custom and
r i t u a l . This could involve the use of
cleansing rituals to help children feel that
they are putting their war experiences
behind them.In Mozambique and Sierra
L e o n e, children visited families of
individuals they had harmed or killed and
contributed labour or built schools as
restitution.Donors are committing more
resources to this critical area of peace-
b u i l d i n g, but a more consistent
commitment is needed if this problem is to
be effectively addressed. ■
INTERVIEW BY SHIRAZ SIDHVA
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
C o n v e r t i n g
the cannon fodder
Jo Becker of Human Rights Watch, one of the authors of a seminal report on child soldiers,
explains why their rehabilitation is crucial to building peace. The best programmes judiciously
combine modern child psychology with traditional rituals
T H E C H I L D I N A R M S
+ …
Global Report on Child Soldiers , 2001.
www.child-soldiers.org
A training session in Russia, one of the countries that enlists under-18s.
◗ E T H I C S
40 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Traditional Kunqu opera of China,N ô g a k u
theatre of Ja p a n , Kutiyattam dance in
I n d i a . M e n ’s polyphonic choral singing
from Georgia.The ancient knowledge of
crafting Lithuanian wooden and metal
c r o s s e s. The Niagassola Sosso Bala
musical tradition of Guinea. In a new
p r o g r a m m e, UN E S C O proclaims these,
among others,“masterpieces of intangible
cultural heritage.”
Intangible cultural heritage is a
technical term used by experts, not by
shamans or musicians. It generally refers
to immaterial aspects of culture—
ephemeral products like stories and
language itself, as well as to the beliefs,
v a l u e s, and forms of knowledge and skill
that give cultures their vitality. Th i s
heritage can, for example, i n c l u d e
wedding dances and funeral laments,
artisans’ skills and orally conveyed
knowledge of farming.
It can even include festivals and
spaces where people gather, such as the
wondrous Djamaa el-Fna square in
Marrakesh.You might find its traces in a
museum—plants used by a traditional
healer, for example—but it is mostly the
living, oral tradition of a people. It is not
culture under glass! 
Japan’s living
national treasures
Scholars have long recognized the
intangibility of culture. In the 18th and
19th centuries philologists, folklorists and
others tried to document the world’s oral
t r a d i t i o n s. Yet the term “ i n t a n g i b l e
cultural heritage”is relatively recent.In
1 9 5 0 , Japan initiated a living national
treasures programme to recognize the
great skills of masters of the traditional
arts.
Similar programmes began in Ko r e a ,
the Philippines, Th a i l a n d , the United
States and France. Intangible heritage is
seen as an asset or resource to be
p r o t e c t e d , a p p r e c i a t e d , utilized and
managed—an idea traceable back to the
Meiji period. In the We s t , m e a n w h i l e,
jurists recognized the idea of intellectual
property as an asset, defining copyright
and patent as putting an idea into material
f o r m .But collective, cultural creation that
was unwritten or unrecorded remained
problematic—it still does.
In the 1970s, discussion of UNESCO’s
World Heritage List,which later came to
include natural landscapes, s t i m u l a t e d
RICHARD KURIN
DIRECTOR OFTHE SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION CENTERFOR
FOLKLIFEAND CULTURAL HERITAGE, WASHINGTON, D.C.
P reserving the magic
We can be swept away by a traditional wedding dance or entranced by the poets of a vanishing
language—but defining this intangible cultural heritage is far from simple,
as UNESCO’s efforts to safeguard endangered masterpieces go to show 
The hill of crosses in Lithuania,where cross crafting is a longtime tradition.
C U L T U R E ◗
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
expression of ethnicities has turned
violent.
Questions of how best to understand
and respond to intangible cultural
heritage sparked debate among the jury
considering nominations for the
U N E S C O ’s designation as intangible
“ m a s t e r p i e c e s.”Fi r s t , there is the question
of defin i t i o n . A staged performance of
an ancient play may have many tangible
elements—written scripts, a temple
theatre and elaborately crafted costumes.
Yet does the fact that it is a performance
render the tradition intangible? How long
does the cultural practice have to be
around before it is called tradition? Does
it have to be widely shared among a
people? If people alter their practice to
respond to changing circumstances,
should the tradition be seen as a
successful adaptation to be treasured or
as a deprived derivative to be shunned?
As hard as it may be to define this
heritage, the question of its value looms
l a r g e r.To some extent,every language is
a masterpiece.How to weigh the worth of
one language against another in
determining value and significance—by
the number of speakers, its role in history,
the beauty of its poetry? 
But perhaps more difficult is the
question of if and how to preserve the
wide range of this heritage. Is it more
important to safeguard vanishing or
fragile traditions than popular,vital ones?
To preserve the tradition,it is necessary
to preserve the ability of people to
practise it. We might like the look or
sound of the tradition,but its continued
practice would condemn people to labour
with low pay and terrible conditions.
The strategies used also spark debate.
In some cases, intangible cultural heritage
may be viewed as a national treasure
meriting government support, tax breaks,
or subsidies.
Looming 
dangers
This can be positive, but it can also
turn a practice controlled by the
community into an institution controlled
by bureaucrats. In other cases, a ritual
celebration may be seen as an under-
exploited asset prompting commercial
i n v e s t m e n t . This may bring funding
support,but it may also destroy the very
meaning of the tradition, turning it into an
activity staged for tourists. The very
broader thinking about the need to
safeguard intangible cultural heritage.
Meetings of experts ensued,
recommendations were developed and
the technical discussions continued until
they reached a pinnacle in May 2001, w h e n
UN E S C O’s Director-General Ko ï c h i r o
Matsuura proclaimed the first 19
Masterpieces of the Oral and Intangible
Heritage of Humanity.
Why so long for this concept to make
it into international consciousness? We l l ,
for one, it has suffered the problem of
vagueness long associated with the term
“ c u l t u r e.” “ H e r i t a g e ” and “ i n t a n g i b l e ”
just compound the difficulty. S e c o n d ,
t h e r e ’s a terminology problem—what to
call it? It is hard to imagine the term
“intangible cultural heritage”sliding off
the tongue of any laureates.
Vagueness and terminology aside,
interest in the subject has grown with
public awareness of globalization.On the
m a c r o - l e v e l , cultural resources, in a
similar way to natural resources, seem to
be endangered or disappearing. Of more
than 6,000 languages still spoken on the
p l a n e t , linguists predict that 50 to 95
percent will not last through the next
c e n t u r y. The great majority are not
written and lack any tangible form.Wh e n
a language dies, there is a startling loss of
knowledge and expression accumulated
over generations.
On the micro-level,many people do
not want to accept a social universe of
homogenized global consumers bereft of
a n c e s t o r s, s t o r i e s, and meaningful
e x p e r i e n c e s.Local cultural reassertion is
a way of saying, “my world may have
become bigger, but I still have a place
within it.” In less benign circumstances,
intangible cultural heritage has captured
the world’s attention when conflict over
the practice of religions and the
recognition of the value of intangible
cultural resources can initiate or
exacerbate conflicts—people within the
society fighting for control over the
t r a d i t i o n , people from the outside
affecting the power balance within.
I m p o r t a n t l y, there is the question of what
is being preserved—is it the tradition
itself as product (for example, the song),
is it the documentary record of the
tradition (the recording), or the people
(singers) and process (the singing)?
Fi n a l l y, there is the issue of who
d e c i d e s. Nations belonging to UN E S C O
must nominate those cultural traditions
for consideration as treasures. M a n y
nominations may be put forth with the
best  intentions, but some might reflect
narrow interests of a group in power.
Some minority traditions may be
overlooked or even censored from
c o n s i d e r a t i o n . Given that many folk
traditions arise as forms of resistance to
national domination, the idea of national
nomination may be flawed.
As member of the jury and an
a n t h r o p o l o g i s t , I was skeptical about the
ability to define and select intangible
cultural treasures and address the many
questions that could be raised about the
concept and its applicability. I still have
my doubts about the particulars. Th e y
will surely be refined as UN E S C O’s
programme evolves.
But I must say that I was impressed
with UN E S C O’s selection of the first 19
“ m a s t e r p i e c e s.” One could take heart
that in the age of globalization, l o c a l
cultures have survived, and sometimes
even flo u r i s h e d . One would appreciate
that in an age of constant innovation,
tradition had some lasting value. Th e
power and tenacity of the selected
traditions and their practitioners was
p a l p a b l e. One can only hope that with
l o c a l , n a t i o n a l , and now international
A ritual celebra t i o n
may be seen as an
u n d e r- exploited asset,
p rompting commerc i a l
investment...and turning
it into a activity staged
for tourists.
How to weigh the
worth
of one language
against another—
by the number of
speakers, its role in
history, the beauty of
its poetry?
42 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
When UN E S C O’s Oral and Intangible
Heritage of Humanity list was
announced in Paris last May, s e v e r a l
Spaniards dashed out of the ceremony
and shouted jubilantly into mobile
phones.They were letting people know
that the mystery play of Elche had been
proclaimed a masterpiece. The news
spread like wildfire in the southern
Spanish town and soon hundreds of
people were out in the streets, l e t t i n g
off fireworks in an early start to the next
day’s official festivities.
Such delight might seem a bit over
the top, since Elche already figures on
the World Heritage List with El Palmeral,
a grove of date palms planted at the time
of the Arab invasion 1,000 years ago when
the town was in Muslim hands. But El
Palmeral doesn’t move the people of
Elche half as much as the “Misteri d’Elx,”
as it is known in the local Va l e n c i a n
language.
Attracting media
attention
Every year, on August 14 and 15,300
volunteers stage a play in the town’s Santa
Maria Basilica depicting the death,
assumption and coronation of the Vi r g i n
M a r y.The sacred musical drama is a part
of the town’s cultural and linguistic
identity that has been maintained since
the 15th century.
The first to appreciate a cultural
treasure being put on the Intangible
Heritage List are those at the heart of
such masterpieces—such as the five
Indians who still speak the Zápara
language in the jungles of the Amazon or
the storytellers of the Djamma el-Fna
Square in Marrakesh (Morocco). All of
them are proud the world has recognized
the deepest roots of their identity.
Getting on the list can also mean an
end to decades of media indifference.
India has thus rediscovered the
Kuttiyattam dance theatre, kept alive
today by five Chakyar families in the
southern part of the country. In China, t h e
oldest and one of the most influ e n t i a l
theatrical traditions, Ku n q u , has become
the talk of the town.Such treasures were
recognized already, but their arrival on
the list gives them “a new dimension,”
says Noriko A i k a w a , head of UNESCO’s
Intangible Heritage Section. This sudden
fame is the key to raising funds, getting
the authorities involved and securing
international help.
Getting straight
with history
This has happened with the Garifuna
culture in Central A m e r i c a , which was
put on the list for its language,music and
dances. The Garifuna people (known as
Garinagu or Black Caribs) are
descendants of rebel African slaves who
live in Belize (which presented their
c a n d i d a cy) and along the coasts of
Honduras, Nicaragua and Guatemala.
To prevent their language from dying
o u t , teachers from Belize’s National
Garifuna Council went to Nicaragua to
keep it alive. Roy Cayetano, B e l i z e ’s
deputy minister for rural development
and culture, says that after the list’s
a n n o u n c e m e n t , Nicaraguan culture
ministry officials asked if they could
support the project.This is important for
plans to standardize Garifuna spelling,
and provides valuable recognition for the
11,000 or so Garifuna scattered in 10
communities in the four countries.
UN E S C O will also be funding other
projects submitted by the new list
members to preserve and promote such
endangered cultural treasures. ■
ASBEL LÓPEZ
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
A tangible debut
A new era is beginning for the 19 cultural treasures that have been declared Masterpieces
of the Oral and Intangible Heritage of Humanity by UNESCO
P R E S E RVING THE MAG I C
In Bolivia, the annual Oruro Carnival features a ceremonial parade involving 20,000 dancers.
C U L T U R E ◗
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 43
+ …
www.unesco.org/culture/heritage/
intangible
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
I
PASCALINE DUMONT
FRENCH FREELANCEJOURNALIST
Te m p t a t i o n - f re e
television for childre n ?
Advertisers spend millions to reach children via television, but how gullible is this young audience?
The debate over whether TV advertising aimed at children should be banned or regulated is in full
swing
n 1932, the American psychologist
Edward Chace Tolman said,“Give me a
child from any background and I’ll turn
him into anything you want—a scientist,
politician or even a criminal.”A l t h o u g h
the theorist of manipulative education
never achieved convincing results, t o d a y
his methods are discretely emulated by
big-name brands and advertising
agencies that use television to try and
turn children into consumers.
Children are an ideal target,simply
because they are avid television viewers.
A survey of seven to 12-year-olds in
France and Switzerland by the
newspaper Journal de Genève s h o w s
that they spend an average of two and a
half hours in front of their sets every
d a y. Little Germans watch less, w h i l e
American children consume between
four and five hours of television every
day! Fo o d , t o y, clothing and record
companies already invest millions of
euros to win them over. In the United
S t a t e s, the Consumers’ Union says each
child sees 30,000 commercials a year.
Their behaviour shows it: t h e y
choose what they consume, insist on
their favourite brands and influ e n c e
their family’s choices.“More than ever,
children are making decisions and
voicing their desires at an increasingly
early age,” says Claude-Yves Robin,
general manager of the Fr e n c h
c h i l d r e n ’s cable television network
Canal J. In an interview with the Fr e n c h
daily Le Monde, Moeata Melard, a
c h i l d r e n ’s market specialist with the
MSM Marketing Research agency,
Talking straight to children,who increasingly choose what they consume.
◗ M E D I A
44 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
claimed that “over half” of innovations
such as electronic games, CD-Roms and
multimedia products “reach households
through children.” In more than 50
percent of families, parents are said to
agree to their offspring’s requests
simply to avoid an argument.
C h i l d r e n ’s exposure to television
advertising is hardly a new debate.
“Many studies have shown that
children under eight cannot tell the
difference between a programme and
a commercial,” reports the American
Academy of Pediatrics, which has
taken a clear stance:“ We consider that
advertising aimed at children is
d e c e p t i v e.” In the U. S. , m a n y
psychologists criticize advertisers’
m e t h o d s, arguing that they sometimes
border on mind control.
Just one-third of the European
U n i o n ’s member states have passed laws
in the framework of the Te l e v i s i o n
without Frontiers directive (see box),
but most of them are quite loose.
Sweden is the only one that has adopted
strict regulations.
A hard sell for
the Swedish model
Erling Bjürstrom, a communications
professor whose research was used to
draft the law,says that children under 10
are incapable of telling the difference
between a commercial and a
p r o g r a m m e, and cannot understand the
purpose of a commercial until the age of
1 2 . In light of those fin d i n g s, S w e d e n
banned all advertising during children’s
prime time in 1991, when private
networks started broadcasting.
F u r t h e r m o r e, commercials featuring
characters children are familiar with are
prohibited until 9 p.m.during the week
and 10 p.m.on weekends.
Standing by its policy, Sweden would
like other European countries to follow
s u i t . In May 2001, when her country
held the rotating European Union
p r e s i d e n cy, Culture Minister Marita
Ulvskog held a conference on the issue
with her European counterparts. Th e
debate is timely because the Television
without Frontiers directive is up for
revision in 2002. Several states—Greece
and Portugal in the south, Great Britain,
Denmark and the Netherlands in the
north—have already come out in favour
of strengthening European regulations,
while the others are satisfied with the
status quo, which lets each country
decide on its own measures.
Since the item is on the European
Union agenda, c o m m u n i c a t i o n
professionals have been girding
themselves for battle. Their first
argument is globalization.“Nothing will
keep thematic networks from
broadcasting advertising aimed at
c h i l d r e n ,” says Robert Gerson, t h e
former head in France of Mattel, w h i c h
m a k e s, among other things, Barbie dolls.
The exponential growth of satellite
multi-channel packages in Europe, a
powerful springboard for A m e r i c a n
networks such as MTV, Disney Channel
and Nickelodeon, would make it
impossible to enforce such a Europe-
wide ban. In Sweden,TV3 and Kanal 5,
two private networks broadcasting from
Great Britain, simply operate outside
the law.
The second line of defence is that
bombarding children with advertising
is harmless.The Advertising Education
Forum—an organization whose board of
directors includes advertisers,
broadcasters and communication
consulting agencies—has just published
the findings of a survey of 5,000 parents
in 20 European countries. Some 85
percent of those polled said that
advertising has little or no effect on their
offspring.
In the past few years, Je f f r e y
G o l d s t e i n , a researcher in the
communications department at the
University of Utrecht (the Netherlands),
has conducted four surveys for the
European Commission in Sweden,
B e l g i u m , the Netherlands and Great
B r i t a i n .“ There is no convincing proof,”
he wrote, “that advertising affects
c h i l d r e n ’s values, eating habits, s m o k i n g
and consumption of alcohol… Children
are more influenced by their parents
and playmates than the media.”And he
concludes that “people exaggerate the
power of advertising simply because it is
omnipresent.”
Bringing up
critical consumers
Goldstein has just completed a
separate report for the European
Commission as part of its revision of
the Television without Fr o n t i e r s
d i r e c t i v e. “He appeals to advertisers’
sense of responsibility,” says Daniel
Aboaf, vice-president of the European
Toy Industry (ETI), a manufacturers’
o r g a n i z a t i o n .“Self-regulation based on
simple guidelines is better than
prohibitive measures.”
To prove that their influence on
children is weak,advertisers also stress
the price argument. They claim it costs
three times less to reach a child than an
adult through advertising. The new
generation is more diverse, thus harder
to target and create brand loyalty.
Although they are influenced by
w h a t e v e r ’s new, advertisers claim it’s
more difficult to capture their attention.
In May, the Swedish culture minister (centre) rallies support at an EU meeting.
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
In a study requested by the European
C o m m i s s i o n , Reinhold Bergler, a
university professor in Bonn, shows that
33.6 percent of children under six
express scepticism with regard to
advertising’s credibility.
Defenders of the status quo, t h e n ,
argue that despite the substantial
amounts of money poured into
advertising that targets children,it has
little effect on them. Pushing the
paradox further, they emphasize that
children have a strong critical sense.
And a sense of responsibility. Rather
than deprive them of advertising, i t
would be better to teach them how to
watch it.“ I t ’s up to parents and teachers
to teach children the realities of the
commercial world. Just like they teach
them how to cross the street,” says the
British magazine The Economist.
Bound by 
money
Television networks and producers
have also taken sides in the debate,
pointing out that children’s advertising
creates jobs. In the European Union,
revenues from this business have
reached between 670 million to one
billion euros  ($620 and $930 million) a
y e a r. In countries that have imposed
quotas to encourage the development of
home-grown entertainment, that income
finances domestically-produced shows
and curbs imports of series and cartoons
from the United States and Ja p a n .
France, for example, is now the world’s
third-leading producer of cartoon series.
But with just 300 hours, that country is
still far behind the two world leaders.
But regardless of whether one
prefers European series to their foreign
counterparts for reasons of style or
c u l t u r e, their purpose remains the same.
Whenever advertising finances
p r o g r a m m i n g, the main aim is to attract
an audience, preferably a specific one,
towards the product. Television and
business are unabashed about their
incestuous relationship. As soon as a
series is successful, the characters are
licensed to sweet-makers, fast food
chains and service stations, w h i c h
duplicate them ad nauseaum.A case in
point is the Japanese series Pokemon.
“Any prohibition or additional
restrictions on children’s advertising in
Europe would have a devastating effect
on television production,” says Cindy
R o s e, a lobbyist for the Walt Disney
group in Brussels. Her concern is not
limited to defending artistic creation
and the jobs that go with it.In addition
to selling programmes to television
networks, the Eurodisney park,movies
and countless derivative products also
fuel the company’s prosperity in Europe.
Production and advertising feed off one
another.
Companies in
the classroom
Whatever their future on television
n e t w o r k s, advertisers are already active
in other areas.The increased presence of
companies in schools is a worrisome
trend for many childhood specialists.
Fast food,s o d a , sports shoe and clothing
brands do more than distribute samples
and advertising kits with the quiet
complicity of teachers. “ P r o d u c t
managers think that each cafeteria, e a c h
classroom…is a serious opportunity to
chase after whatever’s cool,” w r i t e s
Naomi Klein in No Logo ( P i c a d o r,
2 0 0 0 ). The government in Britain has
had no qualms about asking private
companies to rescue public schools with
dwindling resources.
Even in this area,television plays a
r o l e. In the United States, the private
Channel One network,which broadcasts
educational programmes to an
estimated eight million children in
12,000 schools, charges advertisers twice
as much as general interest networks.
The paradise of childhood is green,the
colour of the dollar. ■
Children are a prime influence on household purchases of multimedia products.
Television without Fro n t i e rs 
The Television without Frontiers directive, adopted on October 3, 1989 and modified in
1997, was designed to standardize the legal framework for television networks in the
European Union.One of its clauses says that television advertising must not directly entice
minors to buy by taking advantage of their inexperience and gullibility. Member states
have the leeway to enforce this guideline as they see fit. Sweden bans children’s
advertising on television altogether, whereas Luxembourg and Belgium prohibit it five
minutes before and after children’s programmes. In Italy, commercials may not interrupt
cartoons, and in Denmark an agreement between the government and the private TV2
network restricts children’s advertising. ■
◗ M E D I A
46 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Sisyphus
of democracy 
fter the coming
to power in 1989
of the Eastern
B l o c ’s first non-
c o m m u n i s t
g o v e r n m e n t
since  World War
I I , Poland was
quick to learn the game of democracy.
Twelve years after the “ Ve l v e t
R e v o l u t i o n ,” most of Central and
Adam Michnik:
Whether as a dissident or editor-
in-chief of Poland’s leading daily
newspaper, Adam Michnik has
never ceased to stir up debate.
How does he see democracy
in Europe, over a decade after the
fall of the Soviet empire? 
A
Eastern European countries are
d e m o c r a c i e s. But democracy here is
a i l i n g. Fi r s t , because our democratic
structures are young, weak,lacking in
tradition or a political culture. But also
because western democracy is ailing.I n
both places, corruption is inherent to
the system. In the Po l i s h , C z e c h ,
Hungarian and Slovak democracies,
this scourge has happened on a more
serious scale than in western countries,
September 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
“D e m o c racy does not claim infallibility.
We a p o n s can be replaced by a rg u m e n t s”
A THOUGHTFUL INSURGENT
From inside his feverish lookout,a tiny office cluttered with paper in Warsaw, Adam Michnik,
54, has never stopped being a dissident.With his fine, acerbic writing,he opposes populism
and criticizes Catholics seeking to set up a new moral order. And he does it with humour. His
newspaper has become Poland’s leading daily because, he says, “I haven’t managed to drive it
completely into bankruptcy.”
In 1989, he founded Gazeta Wyborcza (“Electoral Gazette”), “the first free daily between the
Elbe and Vladivostok,” to support the independent trade union Solidarity during the first free
elections in the history of the communist bloc. The Berlin Wall was still standing.Right from the
start, the newspaper declared its independence from political movements and trends. Michnik,
who was elected to parliament, advocated “shock therapy” for Poland—a radical overhaul of
the economy—and urged everyone to take part in building democracy. That is when he parted
ways with Lech Walesa, the historic leader of Solidarity and future president.
For Michnik, thought and insurrection have always gone together. He was a student leader in
1968, a co-founder of the KOR (Workers’ Defence Committee) and an adviser to Solidarity.
Altogether, he spent six years behind bars. His struggle and achievements have earned him many
rewards. ■
where democracy has struck deeper
r o o t s. But the nature of the problem is
the same.And corruption remains the
overriding challenge to the democratic
order.
Was it this “ n o r m a l i t y ” of a western-
style democracy that you aspired to
when you were in the underg ro u n d
opposition?
Not really! But all is not lost! Th a n k
God we have a free press. We can
expose a scandal every day. I t ’s a
complex struggle. But when all is said
and done, I would rather suffer
corruption in democracy than
corruption in dictatorship. Our role at
the G a ze t a, where I’m editor in chief, i s,
of course, to defend freedom and truth,
but also to exercise the power of the
p r e s s. We keep a close eye on the
g o v e r n m e n t . We fuel the debate on
democratic values, national traditions,
the legacy of history, t o l e r a n c e.We also
think of the excluded: the poor,
religious and ethnic minorities. For us,
working at the G a ze t a is a way of
pursuing what we did in the democratic
opposition during communism.
O n c e, the dissidents of Central and
Eastern Europe made their voices heard
in the West.This is no longer the case.
Because our fight has become an
everyday struggle! We ’re no longer
talking about the “ final reckoning.”
During the dictatorship, the main
difference between us and
revolutionary movements was that we,
the anti-communist opposition, did not
harbour any illusions about the “ u t o p i a
of a perfect society.”
P e r s o n a l l y, I believe in T h e
Unperfect Society, to borrow the title of
a book by Milovan Djilas.That’s why I
don’t feel any great disillusion.Maybe
you idealists in the West do! But
Western intellectuals have made a
specialty of placing their hopes in the
Viet Cong, Fidel Castro, Mao Zedong,
the Soviet Union, the Sandinistas of
Nicaragua and I don’t know what else.
Our movement—that of
C z e c h o s l o v a k i a ’s Vaclav Havel,
R u s s i a ’s Andreï Sakharov, S o l i d a r i t y —
did not strive for utopia. What we
wanted was a return to “ n o r m a l i t y.” O f
c o u r s e, we idealized western democracy.
Today we’re more familiar with the
system and its weaknesses. But that
h a s n ’t kept us from fighting, in the
moral sense of the term, a g a i n s t
c o r r u p t i o n ,unemployment and poverty,
and for the construction of a fairer
s y s t e m . But one specific feature of that
struggle is that it will never be over. It
is endless, like Sisyphus in hell,
constantly pushing his huge boulder up
to an unreachable hilltop.
You often sing the praises of grey… 
The world of dictatorship was in
black and white. It was a struggle
between Good and Evil, between total
Truth versus absolute Lies.You had to
be an idiot or a hoodlum to dare be
against it. Democracy is qualitatively
d i f f e r e n t . I t ’s a world of clashing
v i e w p o i n t s, fragmentary and confli c t i n g
interests where the overriding colour
i s g r e y. I t ’s an endless search for
c o m p r o m i s e, eternal imperfection…
D e m o c r a cy does not claim infallibility.
Weapons can be replaced by arguments.
It’s an alternative to civil war. In that
s e n s e, the Basques’ terrorist attacks
against the Spanish state, which is a
perfectly democratic state, a r e
unacceptable.
Twenty years ago, on December 13,
1 9 8 1 ,G e n e ral Jaruzelski declared martial
l a w.You and thousands of other people
w e re arre s t e d . What gave you the
courage to act and keep on going?
For my generation, the road to
freedom began in 1968.While students
in Paris and Berkeley were rejecting
bourgeois democracy, we in Prague or
Warsaw were fighting for a freedom
that only the bourgeois order could
guarantee. In appearance, everything
divided us.
But something brought us together:
the need to rebel stemming from the
conviction that,as long as the world is
the way it is, i t ’s worth not dying a
peaceful death in your bed. Here, we
were the first generation able to build
projects for the future and those
projects were not groundless, a s
subsequent events showed. Th e
situation did change after a few years.
Many factors came into play at the
same time.Poland was going through a
deep economic crisis. The changes
48 The UNESCO Courier - September 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
taking place in the Soviet Union also
had an impact. Lastly, the communist
n o m e n k l a t u r a itself was evolving,
becoming more pragmatic. It was the
end of the utopian dream, and it
enabled us to dismantle the
dictatorship by negotiation.The “ r o u n d
t a b l e ” [negotiations between the
g o v e r n m e n t , the opposition and the
Church in 1989] was our great
contribution to 20th-century history!
Admit that it is extremely rare to see
opposition forces and leaders of the
dictatorship—put another way,
prisoners and their guards—sitting
down at the same table to negotiate a
Often after a period of dictatorship, a
f ree press is tempted to settle score s
and take some kind of re v e n g e. Did that
happen in Poland? 
We played our role and helped to
shed light on some of the dictatorship’s
criminal secrets. But our philosophy is
just the opposite of the spirit of
r e v e n g e. We ’re for reconciliation,
because it’s impossible to take a step
ahead when you’re looking back. To
move from dictatorship to democracy,
we campaigned for compromise and
national reconciliation: with neither
r e p r i s a l s, nor winners and losers.
Reform in Poland would have been
impossible without that social
c o n s e n s u s, without dialogue and
c o m p r o m i s e. The way I see it,
“ d e c o m m u n i z a t i o n ,” d i s c r i m i n a t i o n
against former civil servants or party
a c t i v i s t s, would have been anti-
d e m o c r a t i c. On the other hand, w e
wanted the truth to come out,and felt
that task was up to historians and
j o u r n a l i s t s, rather than prosecutors and
police officers.Amnesty doesn’t mean
amnesia.
Is that why you wanted to broach a
dialogue with General Jaruzelski? 
I wanted to behave like a normal
human being in a free country: I had
been his unrelenting opponent, h i s
p r i s o n e r,but I was interested in what he
had to say. H e ’s an intelligent man and
decolonization and democratization
pact. That did not happen in Franco’s
S p a i n , H o n e c k e r ’s East Germany,
P i n o c h e t ’s Chile or even in Kadar’s
Hungary.
Talking together to bring a country out
of dictatorship is a good way to learn
about democratic compromise.
Today in Poland, no political force
openly contests the democratic order.
When they’re in power, it’s clear for all
the parties, whether they’re post-
communist, right-wing or centre-right,
that democracy is a stable, reassuring
system.
On air with General Jaruzelski (right) in 1992.
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 51) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396 French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 48French francs ( 7. 32 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:     Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
“The old split between l e f t and r i g h t e n d e d
with the anti-communist re v o l u t i o n”
Poland’s roads to freedom sometimes
took very different courses.Some went
through prison, others through the
corridors of power. Deep down, I ’ m
convinced Jaruzelski is a Polish patriot
and a partisan of democracy. He’s not
a cy n i c. He didn’t want to turn
communism into a rampaging
chauvinism,like Serbia’s Milosevic or
C r o a t i a ’s Tu d j m a n , who ripped the
Balkans apart in the 1990s. He didn’t
want to build his own identity by
stirring up hatred among others, t h o s e
who belong to a different ethnic group,
religion or class.N o. I’m sure he always
wanted to build a non-ethnic, secular
Po l a n d . That is very similar to what
w e ’ve always stood for at the G a ze t a: a
state for all citizens.
We must reject one camp’s
domination over another, with endless
settlings of scores. Our country must
make room for everybody. That’s the
only way to build a sovereign,
democratic state.
Soon Poland will join the Euro p e a n
Union. But Europe is in crisis, and has
botched reforms considered necessary to
expand and integrate newcomers.
The debates in the European Union
pit two fundamentally different views
against each other: the idea of a E u r o p e
of Nations defended by de G a u l l e
[president of France from 1959 to
1 9 6 9 ] , and the notion of a federal
Europe of regions that Denis de
Rougemont1 put forward in his book
Open letter to Europeans. I and the
people of my generation are closest to
the Gaullist position. Each nation’s
culture has something sacred about it in
its heart.And for my generation,that
sacred something is independence.We
have a hard time letting go of that.
Although we’re told it’s worth the
s a c r i fic e, our emotions stand in the way.
More generally, the fall of communism
has led to a thaw in Western Europe.
Beneath the ice, we have seen both
flowers and signs of decay appear:
crises that jeopardize the cohesiveness
of states and of Europe.
Western democracies are facing other
p ro b l e m s, such as the weake n i n g
o f t raditional intermediaries—tra d e
u n i o n s, political parties—between
government and the people. I t ’s as
though heads of state now find
themselves alone in front of television
and its omnipotence.
We ’re seeing the same
phenomenon in Poland and don’t have
any solutions to fight it.It strengthens
politicians’ temptation to offer populist
r e c i p e s, and we’re afraid of being swept
away by this groundswell. But it goes
further than the simple perverse effect
of television or the triumph of a certain
n i h i l i s m . Politics itself is undergoing
an upheaval.The old split between left
and right has had its day. That rift,
which was created by the Fr e n c h
R e v o l u t i o n , came to an end with t h e
anti-communist revolution.To d a y, t h e
new fault line runs between those who
defend the idea of an open,
multicultural society based on human
rights and the rights of citizens, a n d
those who are rebuilding walls around
a closed society, stone by stone.
Whether we are talking about the
M a a s t r i c h t2 treaty or NATO
intervention in Ko s o v o, t r a d i t i o n a l
political divisions no longer fit in with
the new world’s real needs. This can
be seen with all the major issues: w h i c h
Europe should be built? What should
be religion’s role in public life? What is
the right vision of the state:an ethnic
state, a religious state or the opposite,
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George’s Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
Gordon & Gotch Australia Pty. Ltd., Private Bag 290, Burwood VIC 3125 .
Fax: 03 9888 8561
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Partner Press, 11 rue Charles Parenté, B-1070 Brussels.
Fax: (32 2) 556 41 46/Tel.: (32 2) 556 41 40/partner press@ampnet.be
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: UNES CO O f fice, 8 Po o rvi Marg, Vasant Vihar, New Delhi 110 0 57.
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Editions Le Printemps Ltée., 4 Route du Club, Va c o a s .
Fax: 686 7302. 
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
UNES CO Etxea, Alda Urquijo 60, Ppal. Dcha., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: Distriplumes, Apartado 49232, Colinas Bello Monte, 10 4 2
A Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 979 8 36 0
UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce C/C
Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 28 6 0 326 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
a citizens’ state? What policy should
be adopted towards asylum-seekers or
immigration? Recently, a debate over
the Jedwabne massacre has rocked
Poland.A historian revealed that the
1,600 Jews in this village under German
occupation in 1941 were slaughtered by
their own neighbours. In Poland, this
debate has been as violent as the
D r e y f u s3 affair in Fr a n c e. It has deeply
divided families and the country. And
there again,the fault line does not run
along the old rift between left and right,
but between advocates of an open and
a closed Poland.
The vision that everyone has of
the nation in Europe has also come
into play. Are we eternally innocent
victims or accomplices in the
subjugation of others, whether they
were Ukrainians, Jews or even
Germans,against whom we practised
a form of ethnic cleansing after Wo r l d
War II.The defenders of an “ e t e r n a l l y
innocent” Poland include right-wing
e x t r e m i s t s, post-communists and
b i s h o p s. I t ’s a dangerous concept.Th e
Serbs have always considered
themselves eternal victims as well.
Today they’re paying the price.
“A n t i - g l o b a l i z a t i o n ”d e m o n s t rations also
reflect a whole range of opinions. How
do you interpret them? 
What is globalization? Internet,
mobile phones, open borders? I’m
afraid that fear is leading new
volunteers to enlist under the banner
of new ideological crusades. Th e s e
people say they’re “ p r o - p o o r,” b u t
they are not campaigning to open up
the markets of rich countries in
Europe and America to products
from the developing world. They’re
not debating reform of the IMF or
the World Bank. That would be too
s p e c i f i c, too down to earth. L i k e
Daniel Cohn-Bendit, Joschka Fi s c h e r
and Rudi Dutschke in 1968, they’re
fighting in the name of certain
r e v o l u t i o n a r y - c o m m u n i s t ,a n a r c h i s t ,
s i t u a t i o n i s t , Maoist or Tr o t s k y i s t
utopias. I can understand them. But
today we are well aware of these
utopias’ genuine nature: t h e y ’r e
stupid. To me, the anti-globalization
movement is more the symptom of a
crisis of thought. ■
INTERVIEW BY PHILIPPE DEMENET
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
1. A thinker and writer, Denis de
Rougemont (1906-1985) promoted
“dialogue between cultures” a n d
supported a federal Europe.
2. Signed in Maastricht on February 7,
1 9 9 2 , implemented on January 1,
1 9 9 3 .The Maastricht treaty led to the
creation of a single currency and
strengthened the European Union’s
powers.
3. In 1894, the French officer Captain
Alfred Dreyfus was arrested on false
charges of espionage. The “Dreyfus
a f f a i r ” deeply divided France and
fuelled anti-Semitism. M a n y
intellectuals came to the defence of
Dreyfus, including the writer Emile
Zola, who wrote his famous article
J’Accuse.
Michnik (left)  on the campaign trail in 1989 with Lech Walesa at the Gdansk
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
54th year
Published monthly in 28 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Cynthia Guttman
Spanish edition: Louise Corradini
French edition: Sophie Boukhari,Philippe Demenet
Michel Bessières
Ivan Briscoe
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Shiraz Sidhva
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: Gérard Prosper,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Pushplata Taneja (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Sardinian:Diego Corraine (Nuoro)
Russian: Valeri Kharkin (Moscow)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing the
credit line reads “Reprinted from the UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author’s
n a m e. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering
p o s t a g e. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by:
(1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,
A n nA r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 1 1 1
West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road,
Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL: C1 - SEPTEMBER2001
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly
in Paris by UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e.
Periodicals postage paid at Champlain NY and additional mailing offic e s.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 09-2001-OPI 00-592 A
September 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Focus:
■ A resource too precious to fight over
■ Facts and figures on a dehydrated world
■ Blue gold on the Blue Nile
■ Israel/Occupied Te r r i t o r i e s : keeping wa t e r
outside the cycle of violence 
■ The Danube’s dirty politics
■ Secrets of the Kalahari
■ Negotiating with nature
Features include:
■ A passion for Thai boxing
■ When coasts lose their pristine
beauty
■ Wanted: teachers in the North
■ Foreign aid hits an all-time low 
■ Digital television: welcome to
the era of convergence
■ Talking to Malian actor
Sotigui Kouyaté 
In the next issue
many voices one world
FOCUS
October 2001:
The mirage
of the
“water wars”
@ www.unesco.org/courier
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
Published in 28 languages
]]>
</page>
</document>
