<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="137745eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
October  2 0 0 4
Education:
A vaccine for HIV/AIDS
the newCourier
The price 
of  school fees
Talking to 
James Morris
Sciences lose
their glamour
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
2
message
UNESCO | the new Courier | April 2004
Cover photo: 
© Stephan Gladieu/Gamma, Paris
Thestatistics on HIV/AIDS are heartbreaking, the 
  human distress each case represents even more 
 so. Two decades after the start of the pandemic, 
the New Courier takes stock and devotes its “Focus” dossier 
to shedding new light on this devastating topic.
We know more and more about the progression of the 
pandemic. Decision-makers’ lack of determination to see 
and tackle the problem is compounded with all the factors of 
precariousness: poverty, social isolation, low level of education, 
difficulty in accessing medical care, etc. The results are tragic: 
the huge vulnerability of so many young African women or other 
high-risk groups, such as drug addicts in certain countries. In 
the face of such destruction, as deadly as the worst of wars, the 
international community has progressively organized to fight 
on all fronts, under the banner of UNAIDS, which UNESCO co-
sponsors. Here and there, we can see sparks of hope. 
Improving medical treatment is crucial to limit damages, 
but the principal keys to checking the spread of the disease 
remain preventive action and education, relayed by mobilization 
at all levels. The numbers and the stories reported from 
Thailand, Brazil, South Africa or Uganda are eloquent. The 
results – victories large and small – depend mainly on partners 
joining forces. Brazilian authorities, for instance, were able 
to put together the NGOs’ capacities to contact marginalized 
populations, rely on the competence of UNESCO’s office in 
Brasilia, and involve the media, including directors and producers 
of extremely popular television series.
The articles in this issue of the New Courier testify, each from 
a different angle, to UNESCO in action, illustrating its multitude 
of links to organizations of all kinds, corporations or individuals 
who want to act with it. We go to Kazakhstan, where innovative 
solutions using distance education are needed to alleviate the 
side-effects of nuclear testing. Then to Barcelona, where the first 
Universal Forum of Cultures mixed and mingled multiple forms of 
cultural expression for four months. Then to the 34 new sites just 
inscribed on the World Heritage List. We will meet Navarre Scott 
Momaday, Manu Dibango and Miyako Yoshida, recently appointed 
“Artists for Peace”. Everywhere, UNESCO pursues its ideals, 
seeking to build step by step the defenses of peace in people’s 
minds. 
Vincent Defourny
the new Courier is published
by the United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
7, place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Tel: 33 1 45 68 46 85
Fax: 33 1 45 68 56 52
Email: unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet: http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director of publications: Vincent Defourny 
Editor in Chief: Sue Williams 
Editorial Assistant: Agnès Bardon
Editorial staff: Roni Amelan, Pierre Gaillard, 
Lucia Iglesias-Kuntz, Cathy Nolan, Bassam Mansour, 
Vladimir Sergueev, Jasmina Sopova
Research and documentation: José Banaag
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, Niamh Burke, 
Michel Ravassard
Editions produced away from headquarters:
Michiko Tanaka
Artistic direction: Jean-Francis Cheriez
Production: Gérard Prosper, Eric Frogé
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Distribution: Pilar Morel Vasquez
Printed by: Imprimerie Corlet, 
Condé-sur-Noireau, France
Electronic version: Richard Cadiou, 
Fiona Ryan-Jacqueron
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads 
“Reprinted from the new Courier”, including the 
date and issue. Non-copyright photos will be 
supplied upon request. Unsolicited manuscripts and 
articles will not be returned unless accompanied 
by an international reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors 
and do not necessarily represent the opinions 
of UNESCO or those of the new Courier.
Photo captions and headlines are written by the 
magazine’s editorial staff. 
The boundaries on maps do not imply official 
endorsement or acceptance by UNESCO or 
the United Nations of the countries and territories 
concerned.
ISSN 0041-5278
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
3
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
summary
Talking to   4
JAMES MORRIS
“A hungry person can’t think”
UNESCO in action
Education   14
THE PRICE OF
SCHOOL FEES 
Not easy to reconcile 
quality education and school 
access for all
Culture   18
BARCELONA,
CULTURAL
CROSSROADS
Success for the Catalan 
capital’s forum
Focus   30
EDUCATION: 
A VACCINE FOR HIV/AIDS
Despite two decades of prevention efforts,
the epidemic is progressing. Yet from Thailand
to Brazil signs of hope exist
Partners   48
Projects organized, sponsored or supported by UNESCO 
with civil society: personalities, universities, NGOs, 
corporations…
Zoom   52
TEA IN THE SAHARA
Living tribute to Morocco’s intangible 
heritage, the Tan-Tan Moussem 
is reborn
Books   56
Contacts   58
UNESCO in brief   27
News from the organization
Communication   8
JUST A MOUSE CLICK AWAY:
SCHOOL FOR KAZAKH CHILDREN
New technologies help compensate for teacher shortage 
Science   11
SCIENCES
LOSE THEIR GLAMOUR
Young people are turning away 
from scientific careers
Culture   21
WORLD HERITAGE
LIST ACQUIRES
34 MORE SITES
© UNAIDS/G. Pirozzi
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
talking to
4
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
JAMES MORRIS
The New Courier:
What is the idea behind School Feeding?
James Morris:  Every child should have at least one good meal 
every day and there is nothing more important in any person’s 
life than education. Providing a school meal is a powerful 
incentive for a child to attend school, and a good way to see 
a child has a good meal every day. It also offers opportunities 
to do other things of enormous value for a child. For example, 
it gives the World Health Organisation the opportunity to offer 
medicine that can eliminate worms from a child’s system. 
Having a child in school is the most powerful way to offer 
HIV/AIDS education. 
What is the link between education and nutrition?
JM:  A hungry person has no ability to think or do physical 
work, and anyone’s success, day by day, is related to their 
capacity to do physical work and ability to think. We know 
that a child’s being well fed makes all the difference in the 
world. Food for Education is a powerful vehicle. Teachers say 
if there was a distribution of food the week before, children 
“A HUNGRY PERSON
CAN’T THINK OR WORK”
Empty stomachs 
are not conducive 
to learning.This 
simple observation 
sparked the School 
Feeding programme. 
James Morris, 
Executive Director 
of the World Food 
Programme, hopes it 
will eventually feed 
50 milllion pupils 
In Afghanistan, 
after the Taliban’s 
departure,
distribution of food 
at school helped 
significantly
increase the number 
of children enrolled, 
particularly girls
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
an
oo
ch
er
/W
eb
is
ta
n
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
5
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
are bright and alert. If they are not fed, they pass out at school 
and vitality in the classroom is substantially diminished.
What is the scale of hunger?
JM:  We believe there are 840m hungry people in the world, at 
least 300m of them children. It’s likely half of hungry children 
don’t go to school -- and most of them are girls. If a girl can go 
to school and be fed, her life changes for the better in many 
ways. She will delay her child-bearing years until she is 20, 
instead of 12 or 13; she will have two or three children instead 
of seven or eight, and different expectations, aspirations for 
them. She will be a better mother, better citizen, teacher, 
entrepreneur, farmer -- whatever she chooses she will do it 
better, be more successful as a human being and economically. 
A very small investment in a child, especially a girl, has an 
enormous future payoff.
Where are children hungriest?
JM:.  In Africa there are a couple of hundred million. There 
are 50-60 million in Latin America, 150 million in South-East 
Asia. Many countries have intense pockets of poverty and often 
when that is the case children are most affected. In Guatemala 
46% of children under five are chronically malnourished; and 
39% in Honduras. There are School Feeding programmes in 69 
countries, and the schools are everywhere – though more likely 
in rural communities.
How does the School Feeding Programme work? 
JM:  Where the WFP is working, UNESCO and other UN 
agencies will be present, so we can bring all services together 
through the schools. We often work with [international] NGOs 
such as World Vision, Save the Children, Care, Oxfam, Mercy 
Corps, and with local government and community leaders, 
NGOs, parents’ groups. Our job is generally to see the money 
is available to procure the food, transport it in or buy it locally, 
and then it is often prepared and distributed by NGOs, parents’ 
or local school groups. I have seen places where parents rapidly 
learn to prepare highly nourishing meals. In Afghanistan we 
supported 280 bakeries to produce loaves for children. Clearly, 
education and health ministries are critically important. About 
20 countries have “graduated” from the programme, but we 
will always be there to help if needed. Often we try to deliver 
emergency food assistance through schools; in a crisis kids 
often stop going to school.
Do teachers also receive food? 
JM:  These are decisions made by local school boards, but 
clearly teachers are key to the success of this programme and 
there are places where we provide food as interim short-term 
compensation for teachers. When Afghanistan didn’t have cash 
to pay for teachers, we paid them in food.
What results have the programmes had? 
JM:  We know school feeding has a powerful impact on 
the percentage of children going to school, and going on to 
secondary school. In Pakistan it has tripled the number of 
girls attending school. We have seen substantial progress in 
Bangladesh and Honduras.
One of the first places I visited was Dodoma in Tanzania where 
the number of children going to school rose from 400 to 800 
and the percentage of kids going on to secondary school rose 
from 8% to 22%. There was a Kabul school with 1,500 boys 
and no girls; after the Taliban, and with introduction of the 
School Food Programme, there were 3,200 pupils -- 1,700 boys 
and 1,500 girls.
In North Korea the results are remarkable. These are not 
necessarily related to school feeding, but between 1998 and 
2002 we were feeding millions of children and our nutritional 
survey shows the percentage of underweight children fell from 
60% to 20%. The acutely malnourished went down from 16% 
to 9%; and chronically malnourished from 60% to 40%. It’s 
still way too high, but it is an extraordinary example of the 
impact of therapeutic feeding on children’s lives.
▲
Standardized School 
Feeding Survey
Launched in 2001, this now 
covers 63 countries and has 
surveyed more than 10,000 
primary schools with school 
feeding programmes. Findings 
from 21 countries with a 
2001 baseline and follow-up 
in 2002-3 show that in Africa 
enrolment rose in schools by 
14% for girls and 9% for boys, 
considerably reducing the 
gender gap. Over four years 
in Africa the number of girls 
per boy enrolled in schools 
in WFP-assisted feeding 
programmes grew by 16%. 
In Africa, school feeding 
programmes helped keep 
children in school on average 
2.5 additional school days 
each month. In Asia, girls 
gained an extra school day 
monthly, and boys two days. 
In Latin America and the 
Caribbean, girls and boys 
gained one day a month..
In Africa, for every additional 
activity – such as deworming; 
nutrition, health and HIV/
AIDS education; curriculum 
development; water supply; 
sanitation – gender disparity 
decreased by 3%.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
talking to
What are UNESCO and other agencies doing?
JM:  Development in humanitarian work is guided by the 
commitment to Millennium Development goals: reducing 
hunger and poverty, infant mortality, HIV/AIDS; improving 
maternal health, gender equality, universal primary education, 
the environment; strengthening democratic institutions. I 
believe hunger, food security and nutrition are at the basis 
of all these -- there will be no progress if people are not well 
nourished. If you address hunger and malnutrition, lives can 
turn around overnight. 
Who funds the programme? How much does it cost to feed 
children?
JM:  We have donor countries and private individuals, 
companies and NGOs who have contributed specifically to the 
School Feeding Programme. Thirty euros a year can provide a 
meal for a child every school day – about 200 days a year. We 
aspire to feed 50 million children. 
What are the difficulties? 
JM:  There are challenges. We often have to provide kitchen 
facilities and utensils, get the programme started and make 
sure it has nutritional strength to benefit a child, and over the 
long term to see the government and local community take 
over the programme. We have a special effort now in nine 
Sahelian countries [Burkino Faso, Cape Verde, Chad, Gambia, 
Guinea, Mali, Mauritania, Niger, Senegal, which face common 
difficulties such as desertification, water shortage, deforestation, 
▼
A
t 
a 
gl
an
ce
For James Morris, 
the fight against 
hunger is at the heart 
of all humanitarian 
causes
James Morris: Between business and humanitarian work
◗ Named Executive 
Director of the 
United Nations 
World Food 
Programme in 
April 2002, James 
T. Morris oversees 
the world’s 
largest food aid 
organization,
which last year fed 
104 million people 
in 81 countries with 
new contributions 
totalling
US$2.6 billion.
◗ WFP reaches out 
to hungry people 
who cannot help 
themselves – victims 
of war and natural 
disasters, families 
affected by HIV/AIDS 
and orphans who 
have lost their
parents to the 
pandemic, and 
school children in 
poor communities.
◗ In July 2002, 
Mr Morris was 
appointed UN 
Secretary-General
Kofi Annan’s
Special Envoy for 
Humanitarian Needs 
in Southern Africa, a 
region which
continues to be 
gripped by a major 
food emergency.
In 2003, he
successfully guided 
the World Food 
Programme in 
carrying out the 
largest
humanitarian
operation in history, 
feeding 27 million 
Iraqis.
◗ Mr Morris, a native 
of the United States, 
earned his BA in 
Political Science from 
Indiana University 
and MBA from 
Butler University. 
After serving in 
city government in 
Indianapolis, Indiana, 
he moved to the Lilly 
Endowment, Inc., 
one of the world’s 
largest charitable 
foundations, in 
1973. Mr Morris 
then became 
chairman and chief 
executive officer 
of IWC Resources 
Corporation and 
Indianapolis Water 
Company in 1989.
◗ Among his 
philanthropic
activities, he has 
been affiliated with 
the United States 
Olympic Committee, 
the American Red 
Cross, and the Board 
of Trustees of Indiana 
University.
©
W
FP
/R
ei
n 
Sk
ul
le
ru
d
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
7
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
educational problems] where we have been working with the 
education and health ministries to bring in school feeding. 
Then there are children orphaned by HIV/AIDS. In sub-
Saharan Africa 11-14 million children orphaned by AIDS are 
in care of grandparents, or other children; these kids are less 
likely to go to school, will have poor health care and less 
adequate nutrition. Their number will rise to 20 million over 
the next few years. 
But the good news is that the WFP, UNESCO, UNICEF, UNAIDS 
and WHO are working hard to address these issues. We have 
rethought our programming, how to help governments and 
community organisations. UNAIDS says most important is to 
educate 5-to-15-year-olds; second, to prolong parents’ lives 
so they have more time with their children; third, addressing 
orphans’ needs. There are places that have lost teachers, health 
professionals, agricultural workers. All the antiretroviral drugs 
won’t make any difference without good food and clean water 
and people who can administer the programmes.
How are results monitored?
JM:  Our work is monitored and evaluated every day, in every 
place in the world, so we know the benefits. We have our own 
staff and outside people, including local governments in the 
community. Teachers, principals and parents have a good idea 
of our practices. (See Standardized Feeding Survey box.)
What next?
JM:  We are heavily focused on investigating where we are 
most needed, so we can target resources on the hungriest, 
poorest people There is nothing more important than feeding 
schoolchildren; food and education are the keys to their future. 
Interview by Jane Marshall
School Feeding 
Programmes and 
Education For All 
(EFA)
School Feeding is very 
relevant to EFA because 
the last children to attend 
school are those with 
serious problems that 
prevent them attending, 
such as hunger, lack of 
food at home and poverty. 
Other issues it addresses 
include HIV/AIDS 
prevention, early marriage, 
child labour.
School feeding has much 
support among members 
of the EFA working group 
– UNESCO, UNICEF, 
the Millennium Project, 
donor governments and 
most developing country 
governments – as a way 
to help poor children, 
especially girls, those in 
conflict zones and those 
otherwise vulnerable, to 
attend school by offsetting 
costs to the family, to 
receive needed nutrients 
and to learn. They benefit 
from school-based 
health and sanitation 
programmes, stay in 
school and have a meal 
during the day, reducing 
short-term hunger that 
disrupts learning and 
behaviour.
*Donor governments: 
Algeria, Andorra, Bangladesh, 
Belgium, Canada, European 
Union, France, Germany, 
Honduras, India, Italy, Kenya 
Luxembourg, Malawi, 
Monaco, Norway, Switzerland, 
USA.
Mali: distribution 
of food aid at school
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/T
er
es
a 
M
ur
ta
gh
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO in action communication
8
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
JUST A MOUSE CLICK AWAY:
SCHOOL FOR KAZAKH CHILDREN
Only 700 out of 
5400 educational 
institutions in 
Kazakhstan are 
linked to the 
Internet
©
B
ak
ht
iy
ar
 O
sp
an
ba
ye
v/
U
N
ES
C
O
 A
lm
at
y
©
B
ak
ht
iy
ar
 O
sp
an
ba
ye
v/
U
N
ES
C
O
 A
lm
at
y
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
9
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
Decades of Soviet 
nuclear testing have 
poisoned large areas 
of Kazakhstan. Result: 
Qualified teachers 
refuse to work there. 
To bridge the gap, 
UNESCO is launching 
an ICT distance learning 
programme.
contamination was carried by winds across the 
steppes far beyond the confines of the range. The 
contaminated area now covers some 550,000 km 
sq., about 1/5 of Kazakhstan, or an area “roughly 
the size of France, but without the Louvre or 
Montmartre,” wryly observes renowned Kazakh 
poet Olzhas Suleimenov, his country’s Permanent 
Delegate to UNESCO.
LETHAL
LONG-TERM EFFECTS
All information regarding the tests was cloaked 
in the deepest secrecy, including their impact on 
health. The only hospital in the region, military 
run, denied the existence of the numerous strange 
and disturbingly debilitating diseases appearing 
in the region, including leukaemia, other types 
of cancer and genetic mutations causing physical 
and mental defects. It’s impossible to know how 
many people have been affected since 1959 but 
Kazakh government estimates run as high as 1.7 
million with about 350,000 still afflicted today.
Semipalatinsk was renamed Semei after 
Kazakhstan became independent in 1991 and the 
Polygon was officially closed down. But the effects 
Massive
Soviet-era atomic testing has left the children of 
vast areas of Kazakhstan a lethal legacy, which 
extends beyond the obvious health issues posed 
by exposure to radioactivity. Coupled with 
economic hardship, contamination renders these 
zones unattractive to qualified teachers, who 
refuse to be posted there, thereby dampening 
hopes for the future entertained by the area’s 
children.
A recent UNESCO-sponsored study shows that 
the schools that do exist are inadequate. One 
teacher often teaches all subjects to all grades 
from 1 to 11 in a decrepit building and higher 
education is unavailable. UNESCO is launching 
a pilot project aimed at using Information and 
Communications Technology (ICT) to develop 
distance learning software that will fill the void 
left by the shortage of teachers and ensure that 
the children in the contaminated areas are not 
denied their educational rights.
The most devastated zone is around 
Semipalatinsk, in eastern Kazakhstan, which 
was a huge nuclear testing range. From 1959 
until 1989, the Soviet military nearly succeeded 
in blasting the region off the map, conducting 
456 nuclear tests on the 18,000 km sq. site, 
called the Polygon. For 50 years, the radioactive 
Schools without boundaries
UNESCO is launching 
pilot comprehensive
distance education projects 
at secondary level in both 
Kazakhstan and Namibia. 
The Kazakh project will be 
extended to other countries 
in Central Asia, while the 
Namibia scheme will serve 
isolated regions in Africa. 
In the Kazakh project, the 
University of Erlangen 
Psychology Department in 
Germany will develop 
teaching software for student 
classes and teacher training. 
A kick-off meeting of all private 
and public partners, including 
the Ministry of Education 
and Katelco, a satellite 
television channel, was to be 
held in late summer in Almaty. 
The Namibia project is still 
being defined but will focus 
on math and science. While 
the country has a relatively 
well-developed primary 
school system, it has few 
secondary schools. Start-up 
dates for the projects are set 
for the 2004-05 school year. 
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
of radiation last thousands of years, sometimes 
with dramatic consequences. Even now, children 
are born without arms, hands growing directly 
from their shoulders, a result of radiation-caused 
genetic mutations. Parts of the area are 1,000 
times more polluted than Chernobyl. Some 
ground water is radioactive and, because so vast 
an area cannot be closed off, livestock are free to 
graze on contaminated grasslands.
Cleaning up has begun and serious efforts 
are being made to address the health needs of 
populations in these areas. But this is only one 
of many problems the country faces. There are 
a dozen other former nuclear sites to deal with 
along with the disaster of the drying up of the 
Aral Sea, causing desertification of arable land. 
With so many pressing needs, Kazakhstan is 
hard put to find funds for education.
FUNDS SCARCE FOR
EDUCATION
The schools that do exist in the area are 
isolated and remote. The shortage of teachers 
for the country is estimated at 3,700, but since 
independence, priorities have shifted along 
with the demands of the burgeoning market 
economy leading to a fall in public spending, 
including in education. Public sector teachers 
earn less than those in the highly popular private 
schools and are often forced to take a second job 
making them less available for their students. 
Teaching materials in Kazakhstan are generally 
outdated and of poor quality, 
and supplies are insufficient 
to meet the demands of 
the country’s 3,004,900 
schoolchildren.
Programmes in Asia, Africa 
and Brazil show that ICT can 
provide innovative solutions 
to a dearth of teachers. 
UNESCO is developing an ICT 
education programme that will 
draw on previous UNESCO 
experiences in other regions 
to produce a comprehensive 
system, says Team Leader Dana 
Ziyasheva. The project will 
adapt free software available 
in Europe aimed at education 
management and course 
production. It will also provide teacher training 
on how to use the software and strengthen 
infrastructure in selected pilot sites. “Relying on 
the educational expertise of Kazakh specialists 
and the transfer of know-how are the key to a 
sustainable project,” says Ziyasheva. A first step 
is training teachers to use both ICT and traditional 
methods efficiently to reach students. The steppes 
lack computers and remain mostly internet-
free. At present only 700 of Kazakhstan’s 5,400 
secondary schools are linked to the internet, but 
the government aims to have them all connected 
by the end of 2007.
Decontamination is the best way to solve 
the health problems and entice teachers back, 
but this is a long-term and costly undertaking. 
So far only $15 million of $43 million pledged by 
international donors in 1999 has trickled to the 
region. “We are not holding out a begging bowl,” 
Suleimenov says, but adds that the magnitude of 
the task is too daunting for any single country.
Pat Brett
UNESCO in action communication
Schools in the Semei 
region are isolated 
and remote
▼
© Bolatbek Amanbekov/UNESCO Almaty
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
11
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
UNESCO in action science
SCIENCES LOSE THEIR GLAMOUR
international Conference on the teaching of 
sciences and technology which was held at 
UNESCO Headquarters in June 2004 represented 
a new step in the collective approach to the 
problem. Several recommendations were made 
during this meeting (see box 1), which was 
organised by the American Association for the 
Advancement of Science (AAAS) with the support 
of the National Science Foundation (NSF).
More than ever before, research appears to 
be one of the major driving forces of economic 
development. In OECD member countries alone, 
the number of researchers rose from 2.4 million 
in 1990 to 3.4 million in 2000, and the demand 
continues to rise1. In early April 2004, the High-
Level Group on Human Resources for Science 
and Technology in Europe called on the members 
Are
young people fed up with 
 science? How can their curiosity 
  and taste for scientific 
adventure be stimulated? Many observers fear 
a shortage of scientists in the near future. This 
fear, repeated again and again in developed 
countries in recent years, is replicated in emerging 
and developed countries, where the training of 
young people to work in research is a vital issue, 
as much for the development of democracy as 
for their economic future. In this respect, the 
Considered boring and badly-paid, 
science is inspiring fewer and 
fewer vocations. Yet the world needs 
more and more scientists.
©
La
 m
ai
n 
à 
la
 p
ât
e/
A
cc
ad
ém
ie
 d
es
 s
ci
en
ce
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO in action science
12
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
▲
of the European Union to take action to reach 
the target of recruiting 500,000 new researchers 
by 20102. The NSF meanwhile estimates that 
2.2 million scientific and engineering jobs need 
to be created in the decade 2000-2010. In such a 
context, it is easy to see why there are concerns 
when certain scientific disciplines are being 
deserted, the population is aging, especially in 
Europe, and there are the risks of relying on 
foreign “human capital”.
In emerging or developing countries, science’s 
lack of appeal can largely be attributed to the lack 
of infrastructure and a policy on science. This is 
certainly the case on the African continent, as 
Professor Nyiira Zerubabel, executive director of 
the Ugandan National Council for Science and 
Technology, told the conference: either young 
people go abroad, or they choose another training 
path which offers more promising employment 
terms and salary. The brain drain hits these 
countries hard. In order to resolve this situation, 
Pakistan has put financial incentives in place, as 
Syeda T.K. Naim, a consultant on the Ministerial 
Committee on scientific and technological 
policy of the Organization of Islamic Conference,
explained. These include a raise in salaries for 
those researchers who publish in an international 
journal and for holders of a PhD. In India, Amitabh 
Mukherjee, director of the Centre for Science 
Education and Communication at the University of 
Delhi told the conference that the number of staff 
in the scientific streams had been rising since 2001.
The relative lack of interest in science is part 
of a complex picture in which the global migration 
of students plays an essential role. For example, 
more and more Chinese and Indian students 
choose other OECD countries over the United 
States, or they stay in their own countries3. Less 
is known about why certain streams are losing 
their appeal. The French physicist and academic 
Yves Quéré believes there are three reasons for 
this: “Science (in the way it is taught these days) 
is boring, it is considered dangerous and people 
believe they will never earn much by working in 
it.” Everyone seems to agree with this analysis 
of the problem and on the necessity to begin 
teaching science from primary school level. This 
aim currently has even greater support because 
the InterAcademy Panel (IAP) backs it, according 
to Yves Quéré, who co-chairs this international 
federation of science academies.
INTRODUCING SCIENCE
IN PRIMARY SCHOOL
It is precisely on this subject that most 
experiments have been done thanks to several 
high-level pioneers.
First there was the remarkable work of the 
American physicist and 1988 Nobel Prix Prize 
winner Leon Lederman in schools in under-
privileged suburbs of Chicago, of which Yves 
Quéré spoke with admiration: “Everyone was 
leaving these schools and violence reigned. 
Leon Lederman introduced an initiation to 
science using active methods and he educated 
the teachers at the same time as the pupils. He 
completely turned the situation around. It was 
very impressive.” In the mid-1990s, Yves Quéré 
and astrophysicist Pierre Léna discovered this 
work with Georges Charpak, winner of the 1992 
Nobel Prize for Physics, who had been invited 
to see it by his colleague and friend Lederman. 
Once they returned to France, the three academics 
created the “La Main à la Pate” association 
(see box 2). Their objective was to reintroduce 
the teaching of science to primary schools, by 
putting the emphasis on experimentation and 
investigation. The experiment was sufficiently 
successful for it to be repeated around the world.
In her speech to the international conference 
in June 2004, Shirley Malcom proposed that this 
approach be considered for use at higher levels. 
Malcom, the director of the education section of 
human resources at AAAS, said access to science 
for everyone was similar to UNESCO’s promotion 
of Education for All. She was also echoing the 
Improving Science 
and Technology 
Education
The international 
conference jointly 
organised by UNESCO 
and the AAAS brought 
together around 50 
high-level delegates, 
including two Nobel 
Prize winners for 
Physics, Leon Lederman 
(USA) and Georges 
Charpak (France). The 
participants agreed on 
the need to improve 
teaching methods and 
syllabuses, in both the 
primary and secondary 
sector, and to evaluate 
the impact of new 
educational practices. 
They proposed to hold 
an international forum 
on the teaching of 
science and technology 
in about two years.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
13
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
La Main à la Pâte
Mao la Massa in Brazil, Learning
by doing in China, Penser avec les 
mains in Switzerland..., La Main 
à la Pate has spread around the 
world. The educational technique 
advocated by this association is 
simple. “It is all about starting by 
questioning children,” says Marc 
Jamous, one of the association’s 
leaders. “Then the teacher helps 
the children to express what they 
think, to show them what happens 
in reality and to reformulate their 
original ideas.” The children are 
following essentially the same 
path as a real researcher; the 
process finishes with a statement 
and a conclusion, which the pupils 
write. “Not only do children 
discover science, they make 
enormous progress in their oral 
and written expression,” says 
Yves Quéré. In 1996, Georges 
Charpak, Pierre Léna and Yves 
Quéré created La Main à la 
Pate, after making a surprising 
discovery: barely 3% of French 
primary schools give their pupils 
an introduction to science. 
With the support of the French 
Education Ministry and the French 
Academy of Science, the three 
academics launched their scheme. 
They began by experimenting 
with 400 primary school teachers 
who volunteered. Today, this 
approach, supported by teachers 
and scientists, has spawned 
imitations in Mexico, Brazil, 
Chile, China, Malaysia, Senegal, 
Morocco, Afghanistan, Cambodia, 
Colombia, Slovakia and Serbia. 
Almost a century after the book by 
Frenchman Célestin Freinet, who 
introduced printing to schools in 
the 1920s, these new practitioners 
of pedagogy founded on freedom 
of expression and the joys of 
discovery and experimentation 
share their experiences via 
internet, on national websites and 
an international one: (http://inrp.
fr/lamap/reseau/interna/accueil.
html). As Yves Quéré points out, 
Marie Curie invented an early 
version of La Main à la Pate at the 
beginning of the 20th century. An 
account of what happened when 
she taught elementary physics to 
her daughter Irene and several of 
her colleagues’ children has just 
been published.
Founded in 1996, the association 
Main a la Pate introduces 
primary school children to the 
scientific method
“Declaration on Science and the Use of Scientific 
Knowledge” which was adopted in Budapest in 
19994: “ (...)Science education is essential for 
human development, for creating endogenous 
scientific capacity and for having active and 
informed citizens”. This declaration received the 
backing of UNESCO Director-General Koïchiro 
Matsuura who saw it as fitting in perfectly with 
the Johannesburg World Summit on Sustainable 
Development.
Dominique Chouchan
1. Mario Cervantes, project manager of the Directorate 
for science, technology and industry at the OECD, 
L’Observateur, http://observateurocde.org/, mars 2004
2. http://europa.eu.int/comm/research/
conferences/2004/sciprof/index_en.html
3. Third European Report on Science & Technology 
Indicators 2003, http:www.cordis.lu/indicators/third_
report.htm
4. The World Conference on Science was held in 
Budapest from 28 June to 1 July 1999 organised by 
UNESCO in cooperation with the International Council 
for Science (ICSU).
©
La
 m
ai
n 
à 
la
 p
ât
e/
D
ES
C
O
/I
N
R
P
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO in action education
14
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
THE PRICE 
OF SCHOOL FEES
Emotion surged across 
Kenya when 
President Mwai Kibaki kept his campaign promise 
to abolish school fees in 2003. Propelled by pent-
up hope, parents swarmed overnight to enrol 
their children in school. But as principals turned 
away pupils, the rosy picture was dimmed by the 
spectre of “the masses” swamping an already 
fragile education system.
Today, the good news is that more than a 
million new pupils are squeezing into classrooms. 
But unfortunately, the expected foreign assistance 
has not fully materialized. In short, “School fees 
were abolished with great euphoria but little 
planning,” according to Andiwo Obondoh of the 
Global Campaign for Education. 
THE AFRICAN MOVEMENT
The confusion is a rite of passage in the bold 
move towards free primary education made 
first by Malawi in 1994, followed by Uganda 
(1997), Cameroon (1999), the United Republic of 
Tanzania (2001) and Zambia (2002). Today any 
debate on free primary education must inevitably 
focus on these African countries, which offer 
valuable insight for Africa and for countries with 
high tuition fees such as Bhutan, Cambodia, 
India, Lao People’s Democratic Republic, Nepal, 
Pakistan and Papua New Guinea.
Steve Packer of the EFA Global Monitoring 
Report was in Malawi when the government 
removed all school fees. “Enrolment surged from 
1.9 to 3.2 million in just three months. Some 
said it was crazy – the quality of the system 
was already appalling. But from a human rights 
perspective, can you deny millions of children 
ANY education, even if it is poor quality?” he 
says.
No is UNESCO’s resounding answer. 
“UNESCO believes that it is better to uphold 
the principle of free primary education and to 
address energetically the quality challenge 
posed by an enrolment surge than to ration 
In Sri Lanka, the 
law guarantees free 
primary school. But 
parents have to deal 
with indirect costs of 
schooling.
As countries abolish school fees, millions more 
children are entering primary school. But 
how much are they learning in overcrowded 
classrooms with no textbooks?
The challenge: ensure access while maintaining 
quality of schooling.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
15
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
access to school through fees,” according to 
John Daniel, the former Assistant Director-
General for Education.
A POLICY SHIFT
While UNESCO focuses on the normative and 
policy front, UNICEF has launched a hands-on 
campaign to eliminate all primary education user 
fees in Africa. Cream Wright, UNICEF’s Chief 
of Education, explains why: “First, we have 
repeatedly seen that once you remove school fees, 
the demand for education soars. On the negative 
side, AIDS is leaving a wake of orphans while 
devastating the community and family networks 
that used to help poor kids go to school. Without 
drastic action, more and more children will have 
no chance.”
Even the World Bank has come around to 
encouraging countries to remove school fees. 
According to the Bank’s lead education specialist, 
Bob Prouty, Bank officials watched the African 
movement to abolish fees with skepticism that 
gave way to amazement. “These countries have 
achieved the biggest success in Education for All 
overnight,” comments Prouty.
UNEXPECTED COSTS
According to a 2001 World Bank survey in 
79 countries, only Algeria and Uruguay have 
no fees. In the rest, about one third of fees are 
“unofficial” or illegal (see box). Not included are 
indirect costs, like transportation (in Cambodia, 
21 percent of household spending goes on 
education) or opportunity costs that hit the 
poorest families sending their children to school 
instead of work.
There are also the “unexpected” costs, detailed 
in a recent report1 by the United Kingdom aid 
agency DFID comparing how very poor families 
cope with primary school costs in Bangladesh, 
Kenya, Nepal, Sri Lanka, Uganda and Zambia. 
Officially, primary school tuition fees are illegal in 
all six countries.
The case of Uganda, committed to providing 
©
K
ar
en
 S
to
w
 L
ee
/C
am
er
a 
Pr
es
s/
G
am
m
a,
 P
ar
is
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
UNESCO in action education
▲
free education, is most striking, as parents 
continue to pay a range of official fees as well as 
“unexpected” costs – teachers’ funerals, year-
end celebrations, classroom construction and 
telephone connections. Asked why pupils left 
primary school, 48% of parents cited inability 
to pay expenses. After food, education was the 
largest household expenditure in Uganda (and 
other countries, except for Nepal2).
ENSURING QUALITY
The authors don’t recommend fees, but 
conclude that “It is important for governments 
to recognize that the removal of tuition fees 
may result in schools having to insist on other 
charges.” In all countries surveyed, households 
routinely make sacrifices to continue paying for 
their children’s education. In Kenya, parents 
tend to skip meals, while in Sri Lanka, they defer 
medical treatment. But while cost is a major 
barrier, it is not alone in determining the demand 
for education.
In the decision to send children to school 
or not, parents also consider the question of 
quality. A World Bank survey of school fees in 79 
countries (see box p.17) found that poor families 
are theoretically willing to pay slightly more for 
education seen as “good”. But when standards 
are not up to expectations, parents stop making 
sacrifices to cover costs.
When Uganda abolished school fees in 1997, 
total net enrolment reached 84% but fell to 
76% by 2000. While it is too soon to draw firm 
conclusions, some experts argue that quality of 
education is to blame for dropout rates. 
Mary Pigozzi, Director of UNESCO’s Division 
for the Promotion of Quality Education, is 
concerned that countries are focusing exclusively 
on getting children into school without policies 
designed to keep them there. “There is a common 
misunderstanding that access to education must 
always precede attention to quality,” she says. 
“Quality clearly costs money but can we afford 
NOT to address it?”
SUPPORTING COUNTRIES 
For Katarina Tomasevski, the first Special 
Rapporteur on the Right to Education by the 
In Nepal, as well as 
school fees, parents 
often have to pay for 
books and uniforms
© Thomas Kelly/Gamma, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
17
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
Fees of every stripe
and colour
According to a World Bank 
Survey (2001)*, school fee types 
vary considerably. In Africa, 
community contributions are the 
most common (81% of countries), 
then uniforms (48%) and tuition 
(41%).
Tuition fees, collected 
unofficially, exist throughout the 
transitional economies of Europe 
and Central Asia. In contrast, Latin 
America has almost no tuition fees, 
except in Colombia. Textbook fees 
are also relatively rare (29% of 
countries surveyed) but compulsory 
uniforms (76%) and community 
contributions (65%) are the norm.
Most Middle Eastern and 
North African countries have 
the constitutional right to free 
education. Yet tuition fees exist in 
Egypt, Jordan, Tunisia and Yemen. 
Community contributions and 
textbook fees are charged in half of 
the countries.
Private tutoring is common in 
South Asia, where Bhutan, India, 
Nepal and Pakistan charge tuition, 
although the fee is legal only in 
Bhutan and Pakistan. Over half of 
the region imposes textbook fees 
and community contributions.
In East Asia and the Pacific, 
uniforms and community 
contributions are obligatory in 
80% of countries, followed by 
textbook fees (70%). Tuitions exist 
in Indonesia, Papua New Guinea, 
the Solomon Islands, China and Viet 
Nam.
Fees represent up to 20% of all 
education spending, an estimated 
30% in Africa and even 40% in the 
Commonwealth of Independent 
States and Eastern European 
countries.
*User Fees in Primary Education by Raja 
Bentaouet and Nicholas Burnett
UN Commission on Human Rights, the funding 
gap is not about economics but the lack of 
international consensus to provide free primary 
education. “Look at the Millennium Development 
Goals – not a word about guaranteeing free 
education,” she says. She notes that governments 
that abolished fees are not getting firm pledges 
that their efforts to enroll and keep pupils at 
school will be rewarded by generous aid and 
debt relief.
This is where the World Bank is trying to step 
in, through its Fast-Track Initiative (FTI), an 
EFA financing initiative. A formally approved 
“credible” action plan is the basis for FTI 
eligibility, for which the Bank has developed a 
set of benchmarks based on characteristics of 
successful EFA countries. For example, a credible 
plan works towards directing 50 percent of the 
education budget to primary schooling. The 
benchmarks are supposed to inspire confidence in 
donors. 
“I think the FTI will provide a much better 
understanding of whether aid is moving to 
the right places,” says Steve Packer. But he 
is dubious about its mobilizing the resources 
which developing countries are now expecting. 
According to the Global Monitoring Report, 
about 5.6 billion dollars are needed each year to 
achieve universal primary education and gender 
parity.
Whether or not that money will arrive, 
countries are indeed lining up to join the FTI, 
with the number of eligible members expected to 
grow from 18 to more than 40 next year.
Abby Riddell, programme specialist on 
educational planning for UNESCO – which is 
an FTI partner advising governments on policy 
– lauds the World Bank initiative, but fears the 
quality of education is at risk.
THE ROLE OF AID
Riddell points to Malawi, Kenya, the United 
Republic of Tanzania, Uganda and Zambia. “In 
all five, you see similar visions of education,” 
she says, “but they are dealing with very 
different circumstances.” Uganda was able to 
abolish school fees in part by building on a 
tradition of decentralized government with truly 
representative local school boards. Zambia 
does not have this base, yet the policy reforms 
look the same.
The challenge lies in developing school 
systems that don’t simply try to catch up with 
industrialized countries. For that, Education 
Ministries will have to master the ‘budgetary 
speak’ of aid agencies to fund homegrown visions 
of quality learning.
Amy Otchet
(First published in UNESCO’s Education 
Today bulletin, July-September, 2004)
1. Reaching the Poor – The Costs of Sending Children 
to School, by Siobhan Boyle, Andy Brock, John Mace 
& Mo Sibbons, U.K. Department for International 
Development, August 2002.
2. Because of Nepal’s harsh winters, clothing costs 
outweigh education spending.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO in action culture
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
BARCELONA,
CULTURAL CROSSROADS
Access 
to drinking water, 
the death of 
languages, reading 
in the digital age, conflict prevention or the 
conditions faced by millions of refugees: all these 
issues and many more featured in the debates 
at Barcelona. Experts from almost 200 countries 
joined in a cultural marathon that also included 
20 exhibitions, 423 concerts – with artists ranging 
from Mstislav Rostropovich to Sting, Lenny 
Kravitz, Norah Jones, Bob Dylan, Alicia Keys, 
BB King and Alejandro Sanz – 20 circus shows, 
cabaret, puppetry, street theatre and much more. 
All of which took place in a 30-hectare area on 
the banks of the Mediterranean, in the presence of 
heads of state, intellectuals, artists, and above all 
else, almost three million visitors.
UNESCO entered into partnership with the 
Universal Forum of Cultures through a resolution 
adopted by the General Conference in 1997. 
UNESCO and the Forum’s Organizing Consortium 
– made up of the Spanish government, the 
autonomous government of Catalonia and the 
Barcelona Town Hall – signed a framework 
agreement, which first of all entailed general 
planning of the event, and later a detailed series 
of activities which have since taken shape at the 
Forum. The fruit of this collaboration has included 
The Barcelona Forum 2004, which has just closed its doors, 
turned the Catalan capital into a must-see cultural meeting point – 
in which UNESCO played a key part.
18
No less than 423 
concerts were held 
during the Barcelona 
Forum 2000
©
Fo
ru
m
 B
ar
ce
lo
na
 2
00
4/
Jo
an
 A
. 
R
oc
a 
de
 V
in
al
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
19
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
The festivities 
attracted nearly 3 
million visitors
Photos: © Forum Barcelona 2004/Agusti Argelich
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
20
UNESCO in action culture
such notable events as the Youth Parliament, the 
UNESCO Cities for Peace Prize, the presentation 
in Barcelona of UNESCO’s Fellini medals, or the 
participation of specialists from the Organization 
in dialogues on issues such as “poverty, micro-
credits and development” or “audiovisual 
communication and cultural diversity.”
Last May, the UNESCO Director General, 
Koïchiro Matsuura, explained the motives 
behind this alliance in a speech at the inaugural 
ceremony: “The Forum is, in my opinion, the 
symbol of civil society’s mobilization around 
some of the great challenges that all the cultures 
of the world will have to confront in the new 
century. Cultural diversity, urban planning 
for lasting development and peace are central 
themes of the Forum’s activities, and also three of 
UNESCO’s strategic priorities.”
GUARANTEED CONTINUITY
Now that its doors have closed, it must be said 
that the Forum proved one of those events that 
leaves neither its supporters nor its detractors 
entirely satisfied. In its defence, one could argue 
that the Forum was a success from the very 
day of its opening, for the simple reason that it 
was unprecedented and confounded those who 
gave it little importance or even predicted that 
it would never see the light of day. The Forum’s 
other great accomplishment is to have found a 
successor, thanks to a proposal from the Mexican 
city of Monterrey, capital of the state of Nuevo 
León, to host a second event in 2007. Nuevo 
León’s governor, José Natividad González, visited 
UNESCO last August to discuss with the Director 
General the broad outline of his plan. Based 
on the experience in Barcelona, Monterrey is a 
planning a shorter Forum (90 days long), with 
a smaller budget and a lower expected turnout. 
Even so, there is no doubt that the endeavour 
to stimulate dialogue between cultures so that 
progress can be made on the road to peace is 
worth all the effort.
Marcelo Aparicio
UNESCO has 
partnered the 
Universal Forum of 
Cultures since 1997 
© 
Fo
ru
m
 B
ar
ce
lo
na
 2
00
4/
B
la
i C
ar
da
Photos: © Forum Barcelona 2004/Xavi M. Miro
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
21
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
WORLD HERITAGE COMMITTEE INSCRIBES
34 NEW SITES ON THE WORLD HERITAGE LIST
The Iranian city of Bam, where 26,000 people died in a 
brutal earthquake in December 2003, was among the new sites 
inscribed on UNESCO’s World Heritage List. Twenty-nine 
cultural and five natural sites were inscribed at the 28th session 
of the World Heritage Committee, held from June 28 to 
July 7 in Suzhou, China.
Five
countries - Andorra, the 
Democratic People’s Republic 
of Korea, Iceland, Saint Lucia 
and Togo - entered the List for the first time 
during the session, which was chaired by Zhang 
Xinsheng, Vice-Minister of Education of China 
and Chairperson of China’s National Commission 
for UNESCO.
The new inscriptions brought to 788 the 
number of listed sites (611 cultural, 154 natural 
and 23 mixed). The 21-member Committee also 
added three properties requiring urgent attention 
to the List of World Heritage in Danger: the City 
of Bam, the Cathedral of Cologne (Germany) 
and the Ruins of Kilwa Kisiwani and Ruins of 
Songo Mnara (Tanzania). At the same time 
the Committee decided to strike three sites 
– Cambodia’s celebrated temples and palaces at 
Angkor, the Bahla Fort in Oman and Rwenzori 
Mountains National Park in Uganda – off the 
Danger List due to the success of internationally-
coordinated efforts to improve their preservation. 
The List of World Heritage in Danger numbers 
35 sites.
The World Heritage Committee examined ways 
to improve its work and the implementation of 
the 1972 World Heritage Convention. Aiming 
to encourage the growth of under-represented 
categories of sites and improve geographic 
distribution on the World Heritage List, it decided 
to test new rules on a temporary basis. The 
Committee has decided that at the 30th session, 
in 2006, it will examine up to two nominations 
per State Party, provided that at least one of the 
nominations concerns a natural property. The 
total number of nominations to be reviewed, 
1
2 ©
Jo
sé
 L
ui
s 
M
ag
an
a/
A
P/
Si
pa
, 
Pa
ri
s
©
IC
O
M
O
S,
 P
ar
is
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
22
UNESCO in action culture
including nominations deferred by previous 
sessions, extensions, transboundary nominations 
and nominations submitted on an emergency 
basis, has been capped at 45.
Also during the 28th session, a Chinese 
edition of UNESCO’s World Heritage Review was 
launched. It is the fifth language version of the 
Review, which has been published in English, 
French and Spanish since 1996 and in Russian 
since 2002.
The 29th session of the World Heritage 
Committee will be held in Durban (South Africa) 
in July 2005.
▲
3
4
5 ©
IC
O
M
O
S,
 P
ar
is
©
IC
O
M
O
S,
 P
ar
is
© ICOMOS, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
23
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
NEW CULTURAL SITES 
INSCRIBED THIS YEAR
ANDORRA – Madriu-Claror-PerafitaValley;
AUSTRALIA – Royal Exhibition Building and Carlton 
Gardens;
CHINA – Capital Cities and Tombs of the Ancient 
Koguryo Kingdom;
DEMOCRATIC PEOPLE’S REPUBLIC OF KOREA – Complex 
of Koguryo Tombs;
GERMANY – Dresden Elbe Valley – The Town Hall and 
Roland on the Marketplace of Bremen;
GERMANY / POLAND – Muskauer Park / Park Muzakowski;
ICELAND – Þingvellir National Park;
INDIA – Champaner-Pavagadh Archaeological Park (4) 
– Chhatrapati Shivaji Station (formerly Victoria 
Terminus);
ISLAMIC REPUBLIC OF IRAN – Pasargadae – Bam and its 
Cultural Landscape;
ITALY – Etruscan Necropolises of Cerveteri and Tarquinia 
– Val d’Orcia;
JAPAN – Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii 
Mountain Range;
JORDAN – Um er-Rasas (Kastron Mefa’a) (1);
KAZAKHSTAN – Petroglyphs within the Archaeological 
Landscape of Tamgaly;
LITHUANIA – Kernave Archaeological Site (Cultural 
Reserve of Kernave);
MALI – Tomb of Askia;
MEXICO – Luis Barragán House and Studio (2);
MONGOLIA – Orkhon Valley Cultural Landscape (7);
MOROCCO – Portuguese City of Mazagan (El Jadida);
NORWAY – Vegaøyan - the Vega Archipelago;
PORTUGAL – Landscape of the Pico Island Vineyard 
Culture;
RUSSIAN FEDERATION – Ensemble of the Novodevichy 
Convent (5);
SERBIA AND MONTENEGRO – Dečani Monastery (6);
SWEDEN – Varberg Radio Station;
TOGO – Koutammakou, the Land of the Batammariba (3);
UNITED KINGDOM – Liverpool - Maritime Mercantile 
City (8).
NEW NATURAL SITES
INSCRIBED THIS YEAR
DENMARK (GREENLAND) – Ilulissat Icefjord;
INDONESIA – Tropical Rainforest Heritage of Sumatra;
RUSSIAN FEDERATION – Natural System of Wrangel Island 
Reserve;
SAINT LUCIA – Pitons Management Area;
SOUTH AFRICA – Cape Floral Region Protected Areas.
6
8
7
©
IC
O
M
O
S,
 P
ar
is
©
IC
O
M
O
S,
 P
ar
is
©
Se
tb
ou
nP
ho
to
s/
Si
pa
, 
Pa
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO in brief
24
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
The Hague 
Convention 
celebrates 
50th anniversary
The Hague Convention for the 
Protection of Cultural Property 
in the Event of Armed Conflict 
has marked its 50th birthday. The 
Convention, adopted with its First 
Protocol on May 14, 1954, at The 
Hague (Netherlands), was the 
first international treaty to focus 
exclusively on the protection of 
cultural property in the event of 
armed conflict. It was reinforced 
by a Second Protocol, which was 
adopted in 1999 and entered into 
force on March 9, 2004.
Since its Adoption, 109 countries 
have become party to the 1954 
Convention. To date, 88 of them 
have joined the First Protocol, and 
22 have joined the Second Protocol.
Educational Radio and TV Centre
Re-Opened in Kabul
After being almost 
totally destroyed during 
years of civil conflict, 
the building housing 
the Educational Radio 
and Television Centre 
(ERTV) of Afghanistan’s 
Ministry of Education 
has been fully renovated 
and equipped with 40 
computers, internet 
access and some digital 
television equipment. 
Radio and television 
studios will follow shortly, 
but the Centre is already 
operational and producing 
a range of educational 
programming. Funded by 
a $2.5m grant from the 
Italian government , the 
renovation was carried 
out under the aegis of 
UNESCO which has 
also organised intensive 
training in fields such as 
TV and radio techniques, 
use of digital equipment, 
programme production, 
English language 
proficiency and computer 
literacy. 
UNESCO and Afghanistan: 
http://www.unesco.org/
afghanistan
Education and ICT: http://
portal.unesco.org/ci/
Two Film Directors 
Receive Fellini
Medal
Film directors Ousmane Sembene (Senegal) 
and Chantal Akerman (Belgium) received 
UNESCO’s Fellini Medal on May 28 in 
Barcelona. The medal is awarded to directors 
and actors for contributing to the respect and 
promotion of cultural diversity. Ousmane 
Sembene is a leading figure of African 
literature and cinema. He has won a number 
of prizes in his career, including the “Un 
Certain Regard” prize at the 2004 Cannes 
Film Festival for his film “Moolade”. Chantal 
Akerman has directed 41 films, written 21, 
and acted in eight. Her best-known feature is 
“I, You, She, He.”
Zone devastated by war 
in Beirut (Lebanon)
Reconstructed bridge in Mostar 
(Bosnia-Herzegovina)
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ou
ni
r 
B
ou
ch
en
ak
i
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/A
la
in
 R
ou
ss
el
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
25
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
At what age can 
schoolchildren work, 
get married or be 
taken to court? A 
report from Right 
to Education* 
and UNESCO’s 
International Bureau 
of Education answers 
this question. 
Only 45 of the 158 
countries examined 
have synchronized 
school-leaving age 
with the minimum 
age of employment. 
In 38 countries, no 
minimum age is set 
for marriage. In six 
countries, there is 
no minimum age 
for criminal liability, 
and children can 
be held criminally 
responsible starting 
at age seven in 32 
others. The report 
can be read on line: 
www.right-to-
education.org 
Children everywhere are 
spending more time in school 
than ever before, but there 
remain substantial differences 
between countries and regions, 
according to UNESCO’s Global 
Education Digest 2004. A 
child in Finland, New Zealand 
or Norway can thus expect 
to receive over 17 years of 
education, almost twice as 
much as in Bangladesh or 
Myanmar and four times as 
much in Niger or Burkina 
Faso. The Digest, published by 
UNESCO’s Institute for Statistics, 
presents detailed global data 
on pre-primary through tertiary 
education, teachers and finance. 
It is available at the following 
address: http://www.uis.
unesco.org
Obliged to go to school, 
but already allowed to work 
or get married!
New edition of Global 
Education Digest
A prize for ethics
The first winner of the 
Avicenna Ethics in Science 
Prize is Margaret A. 
Somerville, who holds dual 
Australian and Canadian 
nationality. She received the 
prize from Director-General 
Koïchiro Matsuura on April 
26, in the presence of Jafar 
Towfighi, Iranian Minister 
of Science, Research and 
Technology. The laureate 
holds the Samuel Gale 
Professorship of Law and 
is a professor at the Faculty 
of Medicine at McGill 
University in Montreal 
(Canada). Through her books, 
conferences and other work, 
she has made an important 
contribution to the global 
development of bioethics, 
and to the ethical and legal 
aspects of medicine and 
science. 
Young people view 
cultural diversity
UNESCO’s new publication 
“All Different, All Unique” 
is produced in collaboration 
with the International Youth 
Parliament and the British 
NGO Oxfam. It consists of 
a bilingual French-English 
text, in magazine format, 
presenting commentary on 
each article of UNESCO’s 
Universal Declaration on 
Cultural Diversity and listing 
concrete initiatives for young 
people to put it into action. 
The project is a compilation 
of the suggestions made 
by young people in ten 
different countries, during 
preparatory workshops 
organized by UNESCO and 
Oxfam International’s Youth 
Parliament (in Argentina, 
Australia, Colombia, Fiji, 
Guatemala, Indonesia, Italy, 
Jordan, Kenya and Togo).
“All Different, All Unique” is 
also available on line:
http://unesdoc.unesco.
org/images/0013/001345/
134556e.pdf 
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/A
. 
U
rt
ia
ga
 C
am
ad
o
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ic
he
l R
av
as
sa
rd
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
UNESCO in brief
First Ratifications of 
the Convention for the 
Safeguarding of the 
Intangible Cultural Heritage
Algeria, Mauritius and Japan 
have become the first three 
Member States to ratify the 
Convention for the Safeguarding 
of the Intangible Cultural 
Heritage, adopted by the General 
Conference in 2003.
The Convention, which will 
enter into force when 30 
States have ratified it, aims 
to safeguard oral traditions 
and expressions, performing 
arts, social practices, rituals, 
festive events and knowledge 
and practice concerning nature 
and the universe, as well as 
traditional craftsmanship skills. 
Text of the Convention: http://
unesdoc.unesco.org/images/
0013/001325/132540e.pdf 
Houphouët-Boigny
Peace Prize
The Grand Mufti of Bosnia, 
Mustaf Ceric, and Cardinal 
Roger Etchegaray, former 
president of the Pontifical 
Council for Justice and 
Peace, received the 2003 
Houphouët-Boigny Peace 
Prize at a ceremony at 
UNESCO Headquarters 
on September 21 attended 
by several religious and 
political personalities. The 
Chairman of the Council of 
Ministers from Bosnia and 
Herzegovina Adnan Terzic 
was among the guests, along 
with Henri Kona Bedié, 
the former president of 
Côte d’Ivoire, and Alassane 
Dramane Outtara, the former 
Prime Minister.
World Forum 
on Human Rights 
in Nantes
At the initiative and with the support 
of UNESCO, the city of Nantes (France) 
organized the World Forum on Human 
Rights from May 16 to 19. Some 
1,200 policy makers, representatives 
of civil society and human rights 
experts participated in the forum, 
which focused on three major 
themes: Human Rights and Terrorism; 
Globalization and the Struggle Against 
All Forms of Discrimination and 
Exclusion; and Poverty as a Violation 
of Human Rights.
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ic
he
lR
av
as
sa
rd
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ic
he
lR
av
as
sa
rd
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/J
ea
n 
M
oh
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
27
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
Saving the DRC’s Unique 
Ecosystems
Donors gathered at a conference 
held at UNESCO headquarters 
last September pledged over 
40  million dollars to safeguard 
five sites in the Democratic 
Republic of Congo that are 
on the List of World Heritage 
in Danger. The conflicts that 
have ravaged the region and 
killed three million people have 
also inflicted serious damage 
on the unique ecosystems of 
these natural sites. They have 
also decimated certain animal 
species with commercial value, 
such as elephants and rhinos. 
Until now, efforts allocated to 
reinforce the protection of the 
sites have been thwarted by 
armed militia who attack park 
guards. Funds promised are 
designated to help Congolese 
institutions in charge of 
conservation. Donors attending 
the conference, however, 
stressed that the project’s 
success depends on greater 
involvement by local authorities 
and an end to the war in DRC.
Web portal for 20,000 
Portuguese-language books
47th session of 
International Education 
Conference
The Sharjah Prize
Thanks to an initiative of 
the Brazilian government, 
supported by UNESCO’s office 
in Brasilia, more than 20,000 
books in Portuguese will be 
made available in Portuguese-
speaking countries via the web 
portal E-libro (http://www.
e-libro.com). The books, as well 
as publications from more than 
150 international publishers 
including UNESCO, will now 
be accessible free of charge 
to thousands of computers in 
libraries, schools and universities 
in Portuguese-speaking African 
countries (Angola, Cape Verde, 
Guinea-Bissau, Mozambique 
and Sao Tome and Principe) and 
Timor-Leste. 
The Sharjah Prize for 
Arab Culture for 2004 
has been awarded to 
Tunisian researcher 
Abdelwahab Bouhdiba 
and Spanish historian 
Juan Vernet Ginés. Born 
in 1923 in Barcelona, 
Juan Vernet Ginés is a 
renowned specialist in 
Arab science and the 
evolution of science 
– especially astronomy 
and map-making – during 
the Middle Ages and the 
Renaissance. Abdelwahab 
Bouhdiba, a sociology 
professor at the University 
of Tunis and President 
of the Tunisian Academy 
of Sciences, Literature 
and Arts, is notably the 
author of La Sexualité en 
Islam (Sexuality in Islam),
which has been translated 
in English, Arabic, 
Bosnian, Spanish and 
Japanese, and will soon be 
available in Portuguese. 
“Quality education for all 
young people: challenges, 
trends and priorities” was the 
theme of the 47th Session of 
the International Conference 
on Education, organized by 
UNESCO’s International Bureau 
of Education in Geneva last 
September. Delegates from more 
than 135 countries attended 
the meeting and identified a 
range of priorities to improve 
the quality of education for all 
young people, including: the 
increased use of information 
and communication technology 
to improve access and equity 
for all young people to 
quality education; emphasis 
on innovating and creating, 
including the reform of 
educational delivery; affirmative 
action to compensate gender 
imbalance; recognition of the 
importance of teachers and 
trainers; increased research; 
and improved use of resources 
and better partnerships. The 
delegates also appealed for the 
mobilization of all partners in 
order to achieve this goal. 
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ic
he
lR
av
as
sa
rd
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ic
he
lR
av
as
sa
rd
©
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ic
he
lR
av
as
sa
rd
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
EDUCATION: A  
■ The figures are staggering. Every day 8000 people die 
of AIDS and another 14000 are infected. With nearly 70 
percent of the world’s 40 million people living with HIV, 
Africa is hardest-hit by the disease, and the continent’s 
women and children are most vulnerable. In sub-Saharan 
Africa almost six out of every ten people infected are 
women [p. 33].
And the virus continues its deadly progression almost 
everywhere, ignoring all borders and taking hold in areas 
which, until now, have been relatively untouched. In 
Eastern Europe for example, and notably in Russia, HIV/
AIDS is rapidly gaining ground, especially amongst drug 
users [p. 35].
Considerable efforts have been made to prevent its spread, 
but have often proved ineffective. Despite being well 
informed of the dangers of AIDS, Kenyan truck drivers, 
caught in the trap of poverty and insecurity, are among 
those considered most at risk [p. 38].
However, there are signs of hope. Following the example 
set by Thailand [p. 40] several countries have introduced 
policies that have served to brake the spread of the disease. 
The diversification of prevention techniques has also 
paid dividends. From Delhi to Rio and Abidjan, popular 
television series based on AIDS help to relay information 
about the virus and the different problems it raises [p. 43].
Antiretroviral treatments are also giving new momentum 
to prevention efforts, in that they offer a new perspective 
to AIDS sufferers and encourage people to get tested. 
Eight years ago, Brazil implemented a policy of universal 
access to treatments, and the rate of new infections is now 
falling [p. 46].
But the battle is far from won. The World Health 
Organization and UNAIDS predict that unless prevention 
efforts are not dramatically increased, the number 
of or AIDS-infected people around the world will reach 
45 million by 2010.
©
H
us
ia
ny
ci
a 
Ya
ne
k/
G
am
m
a,
 P
ar
is
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
focus
29
VACCINE FOR HIV/AIDS 
A SOCIAL DISEASE
Unknown 20 years ago, AIDS is now the number one 
cause of death among young adults in the world. The 
evolution of the epidemic has consistently exceeded the most 
pessimistic predictions. Today almost 40 million people are 
infected and AIDS orphans number more than 13 million.
In the absence of a vaccine or a treatment that can 
cure the disease, prevention remains the best antidote. 
WHO estimates that two-thirds of infections likely to 
occur between now and 2010 can be avoided if prevention 
strategies are reinforced. Much has already been done. Many 
countries have integrated AIDS education in school curricula. 
Millions of dollars have been invested in projects aimed at 
high-risk populations and campaigns for the general public. 
The city of Paris recently put up posters showing a tourist 
on a beach, surrounded by exotic beauties. Almost a banal 
souvenir postcard, except that the floral wreath he wears 
around his neck is a funeral wreath.
Despite all these efforts, ignorance about HIV/AIDS and 
its means of transmission remains daunting. In Mali, Benin 
and Haiti, 40% of young girls do not know how to protect 
themselves. (DHS, 1998-2002). Even people who are the 
most exposed often continue to deny the gravity of the 
disease. More than 90% of Haitian adolescents, for instance, 
think that the risk of their contracting the virus is low or 
even non-existent, when the country has one of the highest 
rates of the disease after sub-Saharan Africa (UNAIDS).
MISINFORMATION
Furthermore, inaccurate ideas about the virus and 
stigmatization of patients continue to flourish, even in 
developed countries. A study carried out in the US in 2000 
shows that 40% of those questioned think they can be 
contaminated by sharing a glass of water with someone who 
has AIDS, or by his cough (UNAIDS). In these conditions, 
the recommendations adopted by the United Nations General 
Assembly in June 2001 in the wake of the Millennium 
Summit seem practically unattainable. It is difficult to see 
how 90% of young people aged 15 to 24 will gain access, 
between now and 2005, to information and education and 
reduce their vulnerability to the virus.
▲
According to WHO, 
nearly two-thirds 
of new infections 
likely between now 
and 2010 could be 
avoided with better 
prevention
Conceived and prepared by Agnès Bardon
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
To explain the failure to halt the spread of the 
epidemic, many have criticized the approach 
taken thus far as too moralistic, too simplistic, 
and not taking into account the pathology’s 
singular aspects. Experience has proved that mere 
information is not sufficient to change sexual 
behaviour. “We reacted to AIDS as we did to any 
public health problem, with the same rational 
information campaigns,” regrets Mary Crewe, 
director of the Centre for the Study of AIDS at the 
University of Pretoria (South Africa). “It’s not a 
disease like other diseases. We should have tried 
to better understand what governs sexuality and 
desire.” 
Others also deplore the fact that emphasis 
was systematically put on changing individual 
behaviour rather than focusing on the disease’s 
social ramifications. “AIDS was long considered 
from a simply medical angle, without taking 
into account the social context in which it 
was developing,” analyzes Michael J. Kelly, 
former professor at the University of Zambia 
and a specialist on the relationship between 
HIV/AIDS and education. The virus, which is 
now primarily transmitted through heterosexual 
contact, infiltrates society through its weaknesses, 
▲
striking the most vulnerable: the poor, women, 
ethnic minorities, migrants, youths. “AIDS takes 
advantage of war, lack of education, gender 
inequality. It is truly a social disease,” stresses 
Alexandra Draxler, programme specialist at the 
International Institute for Educational Planning 
(IIEP).
NO MAGIC BULLET
FOR PREVENTION
Experience does prove that prevention can work, 
but only under certain conditions. “There’s no 
magic bullet. We know that in order to get results, 
a policy of prevention has to work in several 
directions at the same time and be advocated 
by political leaders, health services, school and 
civil society,” explains Peter Aggleton, Dean of 
Research and Consultancy at London University’s 
Institute of Education and HIV/AIDS specialist. 
If a country as highly affected as Uganda has 
succeeded in significantly reducing the epidemic, 
it is because efforts were supported by political 
will at the highest level. The instituting of 
rigorous epidemiological controls, the mass 
distribution of condoms, the absence of taboo 
about the disease, and the commitment of 
AIDS in the world In 2003, 38 million people were living with HIV/AIDS.
(Source: UNAIDS, 2004)
Prevalence
in adults
15.0% – 39.0%
 5.0% – 15.0%
 1.0% –  5.0%
 0.5% –  1.0%
 0.1% –  0.5%
 0.0% –  0.1%
Not available
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
focus
31
political, community and religious leaders all 
contributed to the policy’s success.
School also emerges as a key factor in the 
fight against the virus, among other reasons 
because the 15-24 age group is the first to be 
hit. According to estimates, nearly half of new 
infections occur among young people under the 
age of 24, while statistics indicate that attending 
school decreases the risk of infection. A study 
conducted in Africa and Latin America shows 
that girls who have had schooling have their first 
sexual relations later and are more likely to insist 
that their partner use condoms (UNAIDS). In 
contrast, young people who have had little of no 
education are 2.2 times more likely to contract 
the virus than those who have finished primary 
school (World Bank). 
The influence of school is such that experts 
often refer to the “education vaccine”. It is not 
only because AIDS information is available in 
schools. In a more general way, education gives 
young adults greater self-confidence and control 
over their lives. “School is a very effective 
social protection. It gives students the ability 
to process information they receive but also to 
become more empowered and independent, 
notably strengthening their capacity to resist peer 
pressure,” adds Michael Kelly.
THE “EDUCATION VACCINE”
Under these conditions, UNESCO’s role is crucial. 
Its 2004-2008 strategy for preventive HIV/AIDS 
education, elaborated in the context of its 
collaboration with UNAIDS, places education 
at the heart of preventive action. The goal is to 
give everyone the opportunity to acquire the 
knowledge and attitudes necessary to limit the 
impact of the virus, by working with ministries, 
NGOs and experts as well as teachers. The idea 
is to make sure that the message fits the targeted 
audience as closely as possible. “Social values, 
religion, family relationships all determine how a 
message will be interpreted. A campaign based on 
the idea of death will not have the same impact 
in a Christian country and a society that believes 
in reincarnation,” underlines Helena Drobna, 
assistant specialist for UNESCO’s Programme on 
Cultural Approach to HIV/AIDS.
Access to the new antiretroviral treatments is 
also an essential factor in prevention. Accordingly, 
one part of UNESCO’s strategy is devoted to 
access to care and education about treatment. 
Nearly 90% of 
Haitian adolescents 
say they are not 
concerned about 
AIDS, when the 
country has one of 
the highest rates of 
the disease in the 
world.
©
St
ep
ha
n 
G
la
di
eu
/G
am
m
a,
 P
ar
is
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
focus
While no cure is available at present, existing 
drugs do increase life expectancy and quality of 
life for people infected with HIV/AIDS, and can 
incite those who have doubts about their HIV 
status to get tested. When treatment exists, an 
increase in consultations and voluntary testing is 
noted in many regions, according to WHO’s most 
recent World Health Report.
Nearly 6 million people currently need 
antiretroviral drugs. In 2003, only 400,000 of them 
received them. The “3 million by 2005” initiative 
launched by WHO to increase the number of 
patients receiving treatment is a tough challenge 
for the finances of countries and the international 
community, but the end justifies the means. 
“We have to act quickly and decisively,” insists 
Michael Kelly, “if we don’t want AIDS to become 
a disease of the poor.”   ■
▲
“The biggest challenge to EFA goals”
To what extent does HIV/AIDS affect the goals of 
Education for All?
HIV/AIDS is perhaps the biggest challenge in the 
face of EFA goals. The impact of the pandemic on 
schools is certainly much more extensive than we 
ever imagined. It affects the supply, the demand 
and the quality of education. In the most afflicted 
countries, teachers are often in the high-risk social 
groups. And as for the pupils, the regularity of their 
school attendance is notably reduced if they are 
infected by the virus, or if someone in their family is. 
Because then they have to work to help support their 
families. And on top of that, schools are not free from 
the discrimination exercised against people who are 
affected by HIV/AIDS.
At the same time, education remains the most 
effective means of preventing the disease. We can 
hope that this crisis situation the epidemic has 
caused, which is having disastrous effects on the 
institution, can also serve in the long run to bring 
about a reform of schools, for instance by promoting 
peer teaching, better adaptation of schedules to the 
rhythm of children’s lives, particularly in rural zones, 
or by acting to prevent discrimination.
The last UNAIDS report shows that the epidemic, 
instead of decreasing, is continually growing. In this 
context, what action should UNESCO take?
To eliminate the disease, it is not enough to advise 
people not to have sexual relations, or to use 
condoms. More in-depth work is needed. That is 
why UNESCO is pursuing its strategy of prevention 
education. And that means not only delivering a 
prevention message, but also inciting people to think 
about their lives and to make the right decisions. It 
involves teacher training, integration of HIV/AIDS-
related issues in school curricula, and consideration 
of the social context in which the epidemic develops. 
Human rights, gender and poverty issues are crucial 
in understanding the disease. UNESCO also has a 
Mary Joy Pigozzi is director of the Division for the Promotion of Quality Education. 
Angola
Cameroon
Central African Rep.
Chad
Côte d’Ivoire
Dem.Rep. Congo
Gambia
Guinea-Bissau
Sierra Leone
Somalia
Vietnam
Zambia
Percentage of women who know how to 
protect themselves from HIV/AIDS 
(Source: UNICEF, 2001-2002). 
No education
    Primary level
          Secondary level or higher
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
©
Is
so
uf
/A
FP
, 
Pa
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
focus
33
▲
Women are not only 
more vulnerable 
to the disease 
physiologically, 
they are also more 
fragile socially. Yet 
AIDS prevention 
programmes have 
been slow to focus 
specifically on their 
needs.
A NEW KIND OF VIRUS
role to play in treatment education.
Furthermore, as part of its cooperation with UNAIDS, UNESCO 
has launched a new initiative that consists of providing 
education ministries with a “tool kit” of methods that have been 
tested and can be adapted to different contexts and countries.
This presupposes, however, political will at the highest level. 
What can be done when the political will is lacking?
When political leaders are elected, voters have a chance to act. 
What is essential, in all cases, is to succeed in breaking the 
silence. The Ugandan government has done this very effectively. 
It is an example to countries most affected by the virus. The 
media also has an important role to play. Everyone has to be 
made aware that HIV/AIDS is not somebody else’s problem. Very 
often, people start to feel concerned only when the disease hits 
those close to them. We have to get the message across before 
the situation becomes that dire.
“M
any of my friends would be 
alive today if they’d been 
as lucky as me,” Angeline 
Mugwendere states bluntly. A 24-year-old woman 
from Zimbabwe, now head of an organization that 
assists young women in rural areas, she knows she 
is privileged. An NGO paid her school fees, giving 
her access to secondary education. Some of her 
friends had no other choice but to give in to the 
advances of “sugar daddies”, older and wealthier, to 
finance their studies. That was how several of them 
contracted the virus.
Such stories are tragically commonplace. Ten 
years ago, women were less affected by the 
disease than men, but the trend has reversed 
in certain regions. In sub-Saharan Africa, 58% 
of the 29.4 million people now living with 
HIV/AIDS are women. The risk of infection for 
young African women is 2.5% per cent higher 
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
than for men. More vulnerable biologically – the 
risk of contamination from a man to a woman 
is estimated at twice that of a woman to a man 
– they are also more vulnerable socially.
The reason: in societies where men are 
dominant, women have little freedom of choice. 
“Young women like me who grow up in rural 
areas learn to be quiet and obedient, to work on 
the farm and around the house, to get married 
early and have children. That kind of education 
considerably reduces their capacity to negotiate 
with men,” confirms Angeline Mungwendere. 
Marriage does not protect them. Many women are 
infected by their husbands or steady boyfriends. 
A recent study conducted in Zimbabwe shows 
that only 11% of the women questioned thought 
they had the right to ask their husband to use a 
condom, even when the husband was unfaithful 
and HIV-positive.
PROGRAMMES NEED TO ADAPT 
TO WOMEN’S SITUATION
Yet prevention programmes have taken a long 
time to address women’s specific problems. “Most 
of them are based on abstinence, fidelity and use 
of condoms. These are not realistic options for 
women,” says Sally Smith of the Global Coalition 
on Women and AIDS, an initiative launched last 
February by UNAIDS. The result is that rumours 
and myths about how the virus is transmitted 
persist. In Cambodia and Vietnam, 50% of 
women between the ages of 15 and 24 believe 
that a mosquito bite can cause infection.
In that context, education remains the best 
antidote. Women who know how to read and 
write are three times more likely than illiterate 
women to know that a healthy-looking person can 
be carrying the virus, and four times more likely 
to know how to protect themselves from AIDS 
(UNAIDS, World Bank, 2002).
Science may also provide another part of the 
solution. For the last several years, scientists 
have been working on developing vaginal 
microbicides. In the form of gel, lubricant or 
suppositories, these products could give women 
more control of their sexuality, despite the fact 
that they are apparently only 60% effective. But 
funds are lacking. “Research in this area is cruelly 
underfinanced,” says Sally Smith. US $775 million 
are needed to test existing products, and only US 
$343 million have been allocated.
Such an investment, however, seems crucial. 
In its 2004 report “Changing History” the 
World Health Organization warns that women’s 
disproportionate mortality rate is leading to an 
imbalance in the adult population, with as-yet 
unforeseen consequences.    ■
Most prevention 
programmes
aimed at women 
recommend
abstinence, fidelity 
and using condoms
©
U
N
A
ID
S/
G
. 
Pi
ro
zz
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
focus
35
RUSSIAN FEDERATION:
A QUESTION OF ATTITUDE
According to the 2004 UNAIDS report, Russia 
is one of the countries where the epidemic 
is spreading the fastest. The number of new 
cases recorded in 2000 is almost twice the 
previous total since 1987. Yet the importance 
of the disease continues to be widely 
underestimated. His plight is repeated hundreds of times over in 
Russia, but people don’t really care. 
The recent World AIDS day “memorial March” 
in Moscow saw a small turnout and little media 
coverage. “We don’t have an AIDS problem” said 
Maria Zhakarova, an office worker and member 
of Russia’s burgeoning middle class. “Why would 
I go to a memorial day for AIDS victims when I 
know no one who has died of the disease? None 
of my friends are gay” she added.
Maria’s attitude is by no means unusual. 
When it first emerged in the former Soviet Union, 
AIDS was restricted largely to homosexuals, sex 
workers and prisoners. The picture, however, is 
changing, and faster than officials can cope with. 
The rate of infection from heterosexual sex has 
P
avel doesn’t really know how he 
contracted the HIV virus. It could have 
been when he was sharing needles in the 
metro underground with other addicts. Or during 
unprotected homosexual intercourse, the proceeds 
of which provided him with enough money to feed 
his addiction. Whichever it was, Pavel is a physical 
wreck. Unable to work, he lives on a meager 
government pension in a run-down apartment on 
the outskirts of Moscow and is struggling at age 22 
to see his way forward to any sort of future.
Few people in Russia 
rally to the AIDS 
cause
©
M
is
ha
 J
ap
ai
dz
e/
A
P/
Si
pa
, 
Pa
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
quadrupled from 5% in 2001 to 20% in 2003. The 
overcrowded conditions many city people live in, 
added to poverty and a prevailing sense of despair 
among the poorest, explain the progression to a 
certain degree. Fatal ignorance about the infection 
also contributes. According to certain studies, 
fewer than 60% of sexually active people think 
that condoms provide protection from the virus.
More women are becoming infected and as a 
result the number of mother-to-child infections 
has sharply escalated. And with a dire working 
class economic problem still predominant, 
prostitution is increasing almost as rapidly as the 
infection. Encouraging men to wear condoms 
doesn’t appear to be a major priority either in a 
nation where condom use has traditionally been 
low and sex education frowned upon by both the 
Orthodox Church and parents. 
HIGHEST RATE OF NEW INFECTIONS 
CURRENTLY IN RUSSIA
Still, it is infection rates amongst intravenous 
drug users which remains most worrisome: the 
annual growth rate of drug users is 5% and 
their number is currently estimated at between 
2 and 2 and a half million people. Meanwhile, 
substitute drugs such as Methadone are illegal in 
Russia, and doctors are often quoted saying that 
installing dispensers for sterile syringes would 
only encourage drug abuse.
It is hardly surprising, therefore, that UNAIDS 
claims the former Soviet republics have the 
highest growth of HIV infections in any part of the 
world today. Indeed, the US National Intelligence 
Council, which advises the US President, believes 
that Russia could have 8 million new HIV 
infections in the next decade. That would equal 
10% of the Russian workforce.
Yet only 280,000 HIV and AIDS cases are 
registered officially in Russia, though the figure 
is probably much, much higher. According to 
Vadim Pokrovsky, Federal AIDS Centre official 
and a long-time AIDS activist, it is close to 1 
million. With negative population growth in 
Russia since the collapse of the Soviet state, the 
economic impact of the AIDS epidemic will be 
▲
acutely felt. Not only will the virus cause loss in 
human capital and productivity: the annual cost 
of retrovirals will impact heavily on the health 
budget. The World Bank estimates that treatment 
costs are unsustainable at current prices (World 
Bank, Russia Office, 2002).
The key to lowering infection rates is education. 
But as Pokrovsky notes: “We spend $1 million 
per year on awareness programs. We should be 
spending $70 million.”
A Russian doctor, trained in epidemiology, 
told me anonymously that there is virtually no 
information on the virus available to the medical 
profession. “People walk through the door every 
day with AIDS-like symptoms and a lot of the 
time doctors at my polyclinic don’t recognize that 
the person they are looking at is HIV positive. 
They just treat the symptoms. Anyway, even if 
they knew, what could they prescribe?” said this 
dispirited doctor.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
focus
37
Although pessimism is never in short supply in 
Russia, what is called for in the fight against AIDS 
in this country is hope that can turn into action. 
Few would disagree. Not even office worker 
Maria. But harnessing minds – and with them, 
hearts – is the challenge. 
Says Pavel: “I am not a leper. I am not a bad 
person. I have AIDS. I need drugs. That’s it! It’s 
simple. So why can’t people just understand and 
accept the situation?”
Monica Attard
in Moscow
In observance of World 
AIDS Day on December 1, 
several events will take 
place at UNESCO.
✖ Sida Info Service and 
UNESCO are organizing, 
on November 20 at Paris 
headquarters, an evening 
of solidarity entitled 
“Africain(e)s d’ici et de 
là-bas unis pour vaincre 
le sida” (Africans from 
here and there united to 
conquer AIDS). Under the 
patronage of the French 
National Commission 
for UNESCO, the event 
aims to raise awareness 
in African communities 
living in France.
✖ On December 1, a 
major concert will be held 
at UNESCO in the context 
of 50th anniversary 
commemorations of 
the death of German 
orchestra conductor 
Wilhelm Furtwängler. 
Proceeds from ticket 
sales will go towards 
financing AIDS prevention 
education projects. 
Agenda
The most rapid 
spread of the virus is 
among drug users 
The increase in 
prostitution is 
also a vector for 
transmitting AIDS
Photos © Dima Korotayev/Laski Diffusion/Gamma, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
U
nshaven, scowling, his face drawn with 
fatigue, Rashid Ahmed shakes his head 
disapprovingly. Leaning on his truck, a 
tired and dented old Iveco, the long-distance driver 
recites the list of his colleagues who have died 
because of what he calls their “lack of discipline on 
the road”. The man with the greying hair, who has 
spent more than 20 years driving back and forth on 
the roads of East and Central Africa, isn’t referring 
to traffic accidents. He’s talking about AIDS.
“Places like this,” he grumbles, as he loads 
sacks of cement into his truck, “You find all 
along the road. Guys stop here to fill up on gas 
and alcohol and buy themselves girls. And you 
know the rest.” The place is Naivasha, a truck-
stop town on the edge of the Rift Valley, some 
80 kilometres from Nairobi. Every day dozens 
of trucks pull up for the night. In the streets, 
A truck driver’s life doesn’t 
stop being dangerous at 
sunset. Nights are risky too, 
in the stopover towns along 
Kenya’s major highways.
KENYAN TRUCK DRIVERS 
TAKE A GAMBLE
In Kenya, an 
estimated 40% of 
truck drivers are HIV 
positive.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
focus
39
close to the shops and the bars with the garish 
signs, women aged 16 to 35 hang around, on the 
lookout for a potential client.
In Kenya, on the only road that links Mombasa 
to Busia, there are no less than a dozen towns 
like Naivasha. For the drivers, far from home 
for weeks on end, the street women are a great 
temptation. With dire epidemiological results. 
UNAIDS considers truck drivers a high-risk 
population and a significant vector for the spread 
of the virus. Kenya fits the pattern. The rate of 
infection is estimated at 40% among the drivers, 
compared to 12% in the general population. 
PREVENTION ON THE ROAD
In Naivasha, nearly everyone is aware of the 
reality of AIDS. But they place the responsibility 
elsewhere. Drivers tend to blame the promiscuity 
of the prostitutes. “For three beers, you can buy 
a girl for half an hour. In one night, she might 
go with five drivers, so if she’s infected, it’s a 
disaster,” Joseph Marenya, a seasonal driver, calls 
out from the cab of his truck.
As for the women, they talk about the drivers’ 
reluctance to use condoms. “After all those hours 
taking risks on the road, it’s another gamble for 
the Mambuyus (drivers). They don’t want to 
put on condoms. Some of them flatly refuse,” 
says Joyce Njambi, an adolescent who works in 
a beauty salon during the day and at night as a 
prostitute. “We know about prostitution and AIDS 
being dangerous,” adds another young girl, barely 
20, who calls herself Lucy. “But what does that 
mean compared to an empty stomach?”
Initiatives have been launched to combat 
the problem. All along the truck routes, large 
billboards warn against the risk of AIDS and 
recall the means of protection. The government’s 
programme to fight against AIDS and control 
sexually transmissible diseases, NASCOP, has 
conducted several information campaigns aimed 
at truckers. The Kenya Long Distance Truck 
Drivers’ Union has also tried to draw its members’ 
attention to the risks of unprotected sex with 
prostitutes. It cooperates with an American NGO, 
Africans United Against Aids Globally (AUAAG), 
to set up prevention centres all along Kenya’s key 
highways. Four reception centres have already 
opened on the Nairobi-Mombasa route. Drivers 
can pick up information brochures, advice and 
free condoms.
The campaigns, however, are slow in achieving 
results. Though drivers are generally informed 
about the disease, a number of them continue to 
ignore it. Besides, the miserable pay and dreadful 
working conditions inflicted by the trucking 
companies keep drivers in a precarious state 
that also nurtures the epidemic. “It’s a long-
term campaign,” admits the head of NASCOP, 
Dr Kenneth Chebet, “but it will pay off in the 
long run.”
Hands covered in cement dust, Rashid Ahmed 
is ready to take to the road again with his load. 
“You can’t prevent men in their prime from 
having sex on the road,” he says. “You have to 
give them condoms, force information on them, 
make them realize the part they play in spreading 
AIDS. It’s the only way.” 
Bogonko Bosire
in Nairobi
Prostitutes and 
their clients
©
Pr
ic
e/
Si
pa
, 
Pa
ri
s
© Price/Sipa, París
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
1980s and the beginning of the 1990s, the virus 
spread throughout the country at devastating 
speed, particularly in the northern region, which 
remains the most affected by the disease. In 1988, 
the percentage of drug addicts infected with the 
virus went from 0 to 30% in six months. Just in 
Chiang Mai, a 1989 study showed that 44% of 
the prostitutes were HIV-positive. In 1991, at the 
height of the epidemic, 143,000 new infections 
were counted in the country’s population of 
62 million.
TOUGH TACTICS TO HALT 
INFECTION
Starting in 1991, Thai authorities reacted 
vigorously to the crisis. Owners of brothels, 
nightclubs, hotels used by prostitutes and 
massage parlours were ordered to impose the use 
of condoms, or risk having their businesses closed 
down. At the same time, ads about the dangers of 
the virus and how to be protected against it were 
aired constantly on radio and TV. “If the strategy 
worked, it was because commitment at the 
highest level of government was behind it, relayed 
Using draconian methods, Thai 
authorities managed to reduce the 
epidemic in rather spectacular 
fashion. But warning signals seem 
to be flashing again. 
S
porting a perpetual grin, Khun likes to make 
conversation as he drives his songthaew, 
a collective taxi that cruises the streets of 
Chiang Mai, second largest city in the country 
about 800 kilometres from Bangkok. A cheerful 
man, unfazed by the suffocating heat that weighs 
on the city at the start of the rainy season or by the 
uninterrupted roar of traffic, Khun is telling the story 
of his life. His life before, when he was a dishwasher 
in a London hotel, or his life now, with his wife, two 
daughters…and his mistresses. Khun confides that 
sometimes he has adventures. What about AIDS? In 
response he opens the glove compartment and takes 
out a box of condoms, hidden behind a jumble of 
music tapes and old papers. “I never go out without 
them,” he says, holding up the box.
Khun, 43, is part of that generation of Thais 
hardest hit by the epidemic. Between the mid-
MIXED RESULTS FOR THAILAND
©
Er
m
ak
of
f/
T
hu
an
/S
ip
a,
 P
ar
is
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
focus
41
fighting AIDS. Many organizations had to close 
down for lack of funding. The distribution of free 
condoms in places of prostitution was suspended. 
And the effects of slackened effort in prevention 
are being keenly felt. The Ministry of Education, 
despite its crucial role in prevention, has limited 
involvement. “Teachers are expected to teach 
prevention in the classroom, but either because 
they are shy or they lack training, they often 
don’t,” explains Alice Schmidt, from the UNESCO 
office in Bangkok. “And if they’ve all heard of the 
virus, some very high-level education officials 
know very little about the disease.”
In Chiang Mai, the idea of Thailand as an 
in the community by numerous actors, from 
policemen to military to NGOs,” adds Sompong 
Charoensuk, country programme adviser of 
UNAIDS in Bangkok.
Consequently, the number of new infections 
was divided by six, reaching 23,673 in 2002. And 
people’s behavior evolved, in a country where 
men tend to have extramarital affairs. The use of 
condoms during paid sexual relations rose from 
14% in 1989 to more than 90% five years later. 
Another example, the percentage of enlisted men 
patronizing prostitutes dropped from 60% in 1991 
to 25% in 1995. For all these reasons, Thailand 
was held up as a model in the region, particularly 
in comparison with some of its neighbours, like 
India, where the virus is spreading at an explosive 
rate. UNAIDS considers Thailand as one of the 
few success stories in the fight against the disease.
BUDGET CUTS
Yet while the statistics are undeniable, the 
practical reality is more ambiguous. First because 
the economic crisis that struck Asia in 1997 
provoked serious cuts in the budget allocated to 
In ten years, the 
number of new 
infections has been 
divided by six.
Left: in the early 
1990s, owners 
of prostitution 
establishments were 
ordered to require 
the use of condoms
© Lalit Sakchai/AP/Sipa, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
exemplary case is being called into question by 
some. “The numbers concerning new infections 
are seriously underestimated,” according to 
the head of an NGO who prefers to remain 
anonymous. “And men around here continue to 
think that using a condom is an insult to their 
manhood.”
Now considered among the new high-risk 
categories are young people, homosexuals and 
drug addicts, as well as ethnic minorities and 
migrants. “In my country, Myanmar, many 
villagers go seek their fortune in the big cities of 
Thailand,” says Muang, a young Buddhist monk 
from the state of Shan. “When some of them 
return, they die of malaria or tuberculosis. They 
don’t know they are carrying the virus.”
DISCRIMINATION AGAINST 
AIDS PATIENTS
Muang is in Chang Mai to attend a three-day 
workshop on AIDS. In the old Wat Pa Pao temple, 
sheltered from the noise and incessant bustle of 
the city, some 30 monks and novices are silently 
taking notes. On the blackboard is a drawing of 
a ship. Aboard are pregnant women, workers, 
prostitutes, drug addicts, migrants and children. 
The question the monks are given to ponder: if 
there is a storm, who should be the first to be 
thrown overboard? The prevention work done by 
the Sangha Metta project, the NGO organizing 
these workshops, is based on Buddhist principles. 
The idea is that the monks will go back to their 
communities to participate in prevention efforts 
and contribute to reducing stigmatization.
In a country where nearly a million people 
are infected, rejection of those afflicted remains 
chronic. Cases of employees fired or students 
expelled because they are HIV-positive are not 
rare. “Stigmatization is less pronounced in rural 
areas that are heavily affected by the disease, 
simply because it’s become a daily reality,” 
explains Gareth Lavell, director of the Rejoice 
Urban Development Projects, an organization 
that distributes drugs to people who are ill. “But 
in cities, the number of schools that will take 
an HIV-positive child can be counted on one 
hand.” On the eve of the 15th International AIDS 
Conference in Bangkok last July, a 4-star hotel in 
the capital had no qualms about separating clients 
according to their HIV status: those who were 
positive were asked to take their meals separately.
Yet with the support of the statistics, Thai 
authorities continue to defend their country’s 
success. “Thailand is still today a very good 
example of what can be done to stop the 
epidemic,” insists Sompong Charoensuk. Only 
as long, however, as prevention efforts continue, 
particularly in regard to young people. Otherwise, 
Thailand may cease to be a good example.
Agnès Bardon 
in Chiang Mai
1985 1990 1995 2000 2005 2010
10
8
6
4
2
0
Number
of infected
people
(in millions)
Estimation of number of 
infections avoided due to 
prevention efforts in Thailand 
Source: WHO, World Health report, 2004
Years
Infections avoided
without prevention
with prevention
||
©
D
oo
rd
ar
sh
an
/B
B
C
 W
or
ld
 S
Er
vi
ce
 T
ru
st
/N
at
io
na
l A
ID
S 
C
on
tr
ol
 O
rg
an
is
at
io
n
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
focus
43
FICTIONAL PREVENTION
▲
Amidst romantic intrigue and 
action scenes, television series are 
promoting prevention without being 
obvious. With surprising results in 
the ratings. 
W
ill Sipho, handsome black male nurse, 
fall for sexy Ayanda, a doctor in the clinic 
where he works, or go back to his ex-
girlfriend Chantal? The question kept South African 
TV viewers on the edge of their seats for weeks. 
Young and seductive, members of the post-apartheid 
society, the characters of the series “Soul City” know 
the pitfalls of love and betrayal. But what really 
sets this soap opera apart is that on the fringes of 
the usual romance novel plot, it brings up serious 
issues, the most prominent being AIDS. In this case, 
Sipho, who finally proposes to Chantal, learns that 
she is HIV-positive. Initially, he is shocked by the 
news, but finally decides to stay with her.
Since it was first aired in 1994, “Soul City” has 
known unflagging popularity. Every week more 
than 13 million viewers, most of them black, are 
glued to their screens. And yet the series was 
invented not by a screenwriter or a network, but 
by an NGO. The production and creative aspects 
are the work of a private television company, 
but the content is defined by the eminently 
serious Institute for Health and Development 
Communication (IHDC).
“Every episode takes a great deal of 
preparation,” explains Sue Goldstein, director 
of research at IHDC. “We organize outside 
discussion groups on a regular basis, preferably in 
underprivileged areas. That’s where we identify 
issues. Then we work with the producers and 
The detective in the 
Indian series Jasoos 
Vijay is brave, sexy 
and…HIV positive
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
▲
screenwriters to incorporate them into the series.” 
Once the script has been written, it is presented 
to discussion groups, community activists and 
people living with HIV for further assessment. 
The result is a high level of realism that mixed 
with a skilfully concocted romantic intrigue 
has succeeded in attracting millions of regular 
viewers.
A HIT WITH VIEWERS
“Soul City ”is not the only TV series to blend 
education and entertainment. In the last several 
years, fiction has increasingly been used to 
communicate messages about prevention, with 
unexpected ratings success. In India, the series 
“Jasoos Vijay”, aired every Sunday night for the 
last two years, is now one of the most watched 
TV shows in the country. The detective Jasoos 
Vijay is typically brave, he likes action, he flirts 
with his pretty female partner and he always 
gets the bad guy. This hero, who is very popular 
in India’s rural areas, does have one unusual 
characteristic for the genre: he is HIV-positive. 
In Brazil, homeland of the telenovela, AIDS has 
also made its appearance in certain soap operas. 
“Malhaçao”, show for young audiences, increased 
its ratings after one of the adolescents in the 
series found out that he was HIV-positive.
Popular as they are, television series are an 
excellent means of conveying information, 
particularly because they do not address the 
rational part of our personalities. “Issues that have 
to do with love and sex depend on very complex 
emotional processes,” explains Sue Goldstein. 
“It is not enough to tell people ‘you have to use 
condoms’ to make them do it. But a series can 
explore sexual questions in all their emotional 
complexity.” Programs of this kind elicit strong 
feelings of identification with the characters 
and situations, adds Mary Myers, independent 
consultant in communication development and 
author of a study on the topic. “This identification 
facilitates discussion and can help bring about 
changes in behaviour.”
There is evidence that these shows have 
impact. In Japan, while the series “Kamisama Mo 
Sukoshidake” was on the air, portraying a female 
student who becomes infected with the virus 
after prostituting herself, the number of HIV tests 
doubled. Another example: a poll of TV viewers in 
Cote d’Ivoire showed that those who had watched 
at least ten episodes of the series “Sida dans la 
Because they are so 
popular, television 
series are an 
excellent means of 
information
Photos © Doordarshan/BBC World SErvice Trust/National AIDS Control Organisation 
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
focus
45
Cité” were much more likely to use a condom 
than those who hadn’t.
FINANCING FROM DONORS
Consequently, soap operas are being taken 
seriously by funding agencies, which are a main 
source of financing. The Institute for Health and 
Development Communication, creator of “Soul 
City”, gets most of its budget from foreign donors 
like the European Union, Japan or Great Britain. 
The Indian series “Jasoos Vijay” was made thanks 
to the sponsorship of the National Aids Control 
Organization (NACO) and the BBC World Service 
Trust.
Television series can therefore succeed where 
many official campaigns have failed, but only 
if health and social structures are keeping up 
with them. “To reach their goal, producers must 
cooperate with the health services and with actors 
in the community,” stresses Mary Myers. “It’s 
useless for the hero of a TV series to demonstrate 
the importance of getting tested if the test is 
unavailable or beyond the means of the majority 
of viewers.”
Agnès Bardon
The South African 
series Soul city was 
one of the first to mix 
entertainment with 
information
UNESCO has been active in the area of 
HIV/AIDS prevention education for well 
over a decade. Its activities throughout 
this period include: 
1990
The Section for Preventive Education 
developed a conceptual framework for 
identifying strategies and priority areas 
for prevention education programmes.
1993
UNESCO entered into a collaborative 
project with the World Foundation 
for AIDS Research and Prevention. 
Publication, jointly with WHO, of School
health education to prevent AIDS and 
sexually transmitted diseases, a resource 
package for curriculum planners, adapted 
to different socio-cultural contexts.
1994-98
Development of national prevention 
programmes.
1998
UNESCO launched, in cooperation with 
UNAIDS, a project untitled A Cultural 
Approach to HIV/AIDS Prevention and 
Care. Country-specific and thematic 
studies, training and sensitization 
workshops as well as pilots projects have 
been carried out since.
1999
UNESCO/UNAIDS launched a youth 
initiative on HIV/AIDS and human rights.
2000
Co-publication with UNAIDS of Migrant
populations and HIV/AIDS. Publication of 
Media and HIV/AIDS in East and Southern 
Africa : a resource book.
UNESCO’s International Institute for 
Educational Planning launched a 
programme on the Impact of HIV/AIDS on 
education.
2001
Publication of Elmina resource guide on 
HIV/AIDS and education. Co-publication: 
Reporting on AIDS in South East Asia.
UNESCO/UNAIDS joint publication: HIV/
AIDS and Human Rights: Young people in 
Action Kit. 
Publication of four methodological 
handbooks on developing culturally 
appropriate responses to HIV/AIDS. 
2002
Establishment of a global UNESCO 
HIV/AIDS Clearing House on the Impact of 
HIV/AIDS on education and on Curricula 
for HIV/AIDS preventive education. 
2003
Education Sector’s Responses to HIV/AIDS 
on Nigeria. Report and Framework for 
Action.
Training for Teachers Manual on 
Preventive Education against HIV/AIDS
and Advocacy Kit for Ministries by 
UNESCO, Bangkok.
UNESCO/UNAIDS Small Grants Facility 
established to support the implementation 
of youth projects addressing HIV/AIDS 
related discrimination.
Round table on Stigma and 
discrimination: an anthropological 
approach and publication of proceedings 
in the framework of the World AIDS 
campaign.
Publication of a manual on AIDS and 
Theatre : How to use theatre in the fight 
against HIV/AIDS-Manual for youth 
theatre groups followed by a series of 
training sessions for trainers in French 
speaking Western Africa. 
2004
Living and learning in a world with 
HIV/AIDS - a kit for young people, their 
parents and teachers. Developed in 
collaboration with ASPnet schools and 
with financial support from UNAIDS. 
Situation analysis of HIV/AIDS among 
children in difficult circumstances in 
Lesotho, Namibia and Zambia undertaken.
The global initiative on prevention 
education and HIV/AIDS, « Towards an 
AIDS-Free Generation : A Global Initiative 
to Expand Prevention Education against 
HIV/AIDS », is launched by UNESCO and 
UNAIDS.
© Soul City Institute of Health and 
Development Communication
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
of anti-retroviral drugs to those who are sick - has 
turned out to be particularly effective.
Currently, 140,000 Brazilians, or nearly all of 
those who are aware that they have the disease, 
are receiving free medication. Result: the AIDS-
related death rate has been cut in half since 1997. 
And contrary to what some people feared, the 
widespread access to treatment has not had an 
adverse effect on prevention. The number of new 
HIV infections stood at 22,000 in 2003, down from 
25,000 in the 1990s. In addition, the incidence of 
high-risk behavior has dropped. For example, the 
percentage of soldiers who use a condom when 
having sex with a paid partner increased from 69 
percent in 1999 to 77 percent in 2002.
“It’s impossible to carry out prevention efforts 
By combining prevention campaigns 
and free access to drug treatment, 
Brazil has successfully curbed the 
AIDS epidemic.
SHOCK THERAPY IN BRAZIL
E
xplosive. That was the word to describe the 
AIDS epidemic in Brazil. In 1992, the World 
Bank predicted that the number of cases 
would exceed one million in the year 2000. The 
demographic growth of Brazil, a country of nearly 
170 million people, heightened fears of an epidemic 
comparable to that sweeping Africa. But while 
Brazil is one of the countries in Latin America that 
has been hardest hit by the disease, with more than 
600,000 people living with HIV, the numbers are far 
below the catastrophic forecasts made 10 years ago. 
The country has even become a point of reference 
for numerous developing countries in the throes 
of the epidemic. The daring policy adopted by the 
authorities in Brasilia - based on active prevention 
campaigns and, since 1996, the free distribution 
© Alexandre Meneghini/AP/Sipa, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
focus
47
today and not pay attention to treatment issues. 
It makes no sense to convince people to be 
careful if you don’t treat those who are sick,” says 
Alexandre Granjeiro, the national coordinator 
of Brazil’s program to fight AIDS and sexually 
transmitted diseases (STDs), which is overseen 
by the country’s health ministry. However, 
implementing such an innovative policy did not 
come easily. From 1997, Brazil began producing 
generic versions of anti-retroviral drugs that were 
not, or were no longer, protected by patents. For 
the treatments still under patent protection, the 
government battled it out with the world’s major 
pharmaceutical groups to obtain price cuts of 40 
to 70 percent.
400 MILLION CONDOMS
Meanwhile, prevention efforts were not neglected. 
Brazil distributes the most free condoms of any 
country in the world. Each year, the government 
offers some 400 million condoms to prison 
inmates, drug addicts, young people and military 
recruits. Beyond efforts targeting transsexuals, 
prostitutes, homosexuals and truck drivers, 
the health ministry runs a major nationwide 
awareness campaign three times a year. Two years 
ago, one television ad showed a guardian angel 
waiting for a young man to come home from a 
night out at Carnaval. Annoyed, the guardian 
angel told the young partygoer that he could not 
protect him from all his mistakes, and that he 
could certainly do nothing for him if he failed 
to use a condom. “Our policy is based on two 
ideas. The first aims to make information about 
HIV/AIDS widely available, the second aims to 
drive home the idea that using a condom is the 
most effective way to prevent infection,” explains 
Alexandre Granjeiro.
But Brazil’s success is also due to the 
mobilization of non-governmental organizations 
(NGOs). “This dynamic approach was a deciding 
factor because civil society can reach people that 
the government is not used to dealing with. And it 
so happens that in Brazil, as opposed to in other 
countries where they have to fight for their rights, 
transsexuals, prostitutes and homosexuals are 
very organized,” explains Cristina Raposo, who 
runs the AIDS programs at the UNESCO office in 
Brasilia.
The lack of taboos about sex in Brazilian society 
was also a definite plus. With UNESCO’s help, 
the government recently launched a pilot program 
to hand out condoms in high schools. The goal 
is that by 2006, some 2.5 million teenagers will 
have access to them. Elsewhere, such an initiative 
would have caused a major stir. In Brazil, no one 
said anything at all.
Lisandra Paraguassu 
in Brasilia
Since 1997, Brazil 
has been producing 
generic versions of 
anti-retroviral drugs 
that are not, or no 
longer, patented
All patients in Brazil 
get free medicine. 
Result: the mortality 
rate from AIDS has 
been cut in half 
since 1997
© Alexandre Meneghini/AP/Sipa, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
Globo
GLOBO AND UNESCO
JOIN FORCES
Globo TV, the Brazilian 
television network, and 
UNESCO Brazil signed 
a protocol of cooperation last 
April that will allow them to 
join forces on such projects 
as the Criança Esperança 
campaign. Launched in 1986 
by Rede Globo, it has already 
raised more than 40 million 
dollars to finance some 4,850 
projects for the benefit of more 
than 2.7 million Brazilian 
children and adolescents, and 
has inspired similar campaigns 
in Argentina, Colombia and 
Ecuador. The Globo-UNESCO 
partnership will also concern 
other projects such as Globo e 
Universidade, Amigos da Escola 
(Friends of School) that aims 
to reinforce the role of schools 
as community cultural centres, 
Abrindo Espaços (Open Spaces) 
that opens public schools on 
weekends to facilitate access 
to culture, sport and other 
leisure activities, Açao Global, 
Geraçao de Paz and others. 
Joint projects will be organized 
to reduce violence and provide 
AIDS prevention education.
T
he group Culture and 
 Development has 
received a donation 
of over 21,000 euros following 
a joint project undertaken by 
UNESCO in collaboration with 
the publisher and bookseller 
Maxilivres. This chain of 
bookstores, with outlets in 
France and Belgium, held a 
special sale for a week last 
April in the run-up to the 
World Book and Copyright Day. 
Culture and Development will 
use the proceeds of the event 
to buy books produced by 
African publishers, which will 
then be donated to the poorest 
libraries of Senegal. This 
project forms part of the Global 
Alliance for Cultural Diversity, 
a UNESCO programme aimed 
at supporting the growth of the 
culture industry in developing 
countries. During the ceremony 
in which the donation was 
made, the president and 
director general of Maxilivres, 
Xavier Chambón, voiced his 
wish that “this joint experience 
with UNESCO be repeated as 
part of the next World Book 
Day,” due to take place on 
April 23, 2005.
A
new partnership between UNESCO
  and the Japanese Television channel 
NHK will see the co-production 
and broadcast of some 200 short television 
programmes that will form of the core of a new 
Heritages Image Archives Initiative.
The Initiative aims to produce quality three-
dimensional moving images and reconstruction 
images, using state-of-the-art digital visual and 
sound processing technology. At the same time, a 
data base system will be built that will allow such 
images to be utilised for various projects, such 
as DVDs and other audio-visual packages, public 
exhibitions, new types of exhibitions using virtual 
reality systems, and production of quality replicas 
for exhibition and academic uses. Furthermore, 
this database and other related databases will be 
connected through network systems in order to 
promote international exchange of educational 
and academic research across the globe.
All programmes co-produced within the 
framework of the agreement will be shot on 
HDTV, a cutting edge digital television technology 
that generates high definition crystal-clear 
images on wide screens. Several heritage sites 
will be shot by NHK from an airship, which will 
travel from Europe to Japan. The airship will be 
presented at the 2005 Aichi Exposition.
An advisory committee, chaired by UNESCO 
Goodwill ambassador Professor Ikuo Hirayama 
and made up of members of UNESCO’s 
secretariat, representatives of the Japanese 
National Commission for UNESCO and renowned 
Japanese heritage specialists, will supervise 
programme content.
NHK
WORLD HERITAGE
ON THE SCREEN
UNESCO Global Alliance –
Maxilivres
BOOKS FOR AFRICA
partners
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
©
Ju
nk
o 
O
ht
an
i/
N
H
K
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
49
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
DaimlerChrysler
DAIMLERCHRYSLER AND UNESCO ANNOUNCE WINNERS 
OF WORLDWIDE SCHOOL CONTEST
T
eams from Azerbaijan and Nigeria, 
Germany and Kuwait, and Fiji and the 
Czech Republic are the winners of the 
DaimlerChrysler-UNESCO “Mondialogo School 
Contest”. They were selected by an international 
jury from among 50 finalists from 36 countries, 
who were invited to attend and present their work 
at a symposium held in Barcelona last September 
to close this first edition of the contest.
First place was awarded to the partner team 
from Azerbaijan and Nigeria, who developed a 
joint intercultural game and illustrated their daily life for their 
partner school in pictures. 
The German team took second place with their partner 
school from Kuwait. Under their project, the students created 
an adaptation of William Shakespeare’s play “The Tempest”, in 
which the action in the play is transferred to Berlin’s Zoo Station 
and a central location in Kuwait. The highlight of the project 
work came with performances of the play in Berlin and Kuwait. 
Third prize went to the school 
partnership from Fiji and the Czech 
Republic, for a survey conducted 
by the school students from the 
Czech Republic in which the young 
people compared lifestyles in the two 
countries and published them on 
their website. In addition, the Fijian 
team designed a colourful album to 
describe traditional elements of their 
culture. 
A Special Prize was awarded to 
a partner team from Ghana and Mexico. The 
students wrote a song about the deadly disease 
of AIDS and the beauty of life. 
More than 24,000 school students in 1,466 
teams from 126 countries took part in the 
“Mondialogo School Contest”. Their key task 
was to develop a creative project with the 
school students from their partner school.
The “Mondialogo School Contest“ is part of the initiative 
“Mondialogo – Intercultural Dialogue and Exchange”, which 
was launched in October 2003 by DaimlerChrysler and UNESCO 
in order to promote more understanding, respect and tolerance 
between civilizations and to encourage young people of differing 
cultural backgrounds to communicate with each other. 
www.mondialogo.org
Photos © Mondialogo
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
partners
50
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
UNESCO artists
for peace
THREE NEW LAUREATES
Manu Dibango (Cameroon), one 
of Africa’s most renowned popular 
musicians joined the ranks of 
UNESCO’s Artists for Peace on May 
27, “in recognition of his exceptional 
contribution to the development of the 
arts, of peace and to dialogue among the 
world’s cultures.” 
Born in Douala, Cameroon, in 1933, 
Manu Dibango is the father of the 
dance music genre Makossa. Over five 
decades as a saxophonist and composer 
Mr Dibango has toured Europe, Africa 
and the United States. His numerous 
recordings have influenced popular 
music in the three continents, and won 
him an international place as an original 
artist who drew inspiration from African 
and African American music.
Japanese ballerina Miyako Yoshida was 
appointed UNESCO Artist for Peace on 
Wednesday, July 21st “in recognition of 
her outstanding contribution to classical 
dance and for her devotion to the cause 
of the Organization’s goals and aims, 
in the field of its programme for arts 
education”.
Miyako Yoshida began studying dance 
at the age of nine. After training in 
Tokyo, she moved to London in 1983 
to study at the Royal Ballet School. 
Promoted in 1988 to the rank of principal 
dancer at the Sadler’s Wells Royal Ballet 
(now the Birmingham Royal Ballet), 
Miyako Yoshida joined the Royal Ballet 
US
author Navarre Scott
Momaday became 
a UNESCO Artist for 
Peace on May 12 in recognition of “his 
outstanding achievements as a writer 
and painter, his action in support of the 
restoration and preservation of Native 
American heritage and cultural traditions 
and communities […] and in recognition 
of his dedication to UNESCO’s 
Programme for intercultural dialogue 
and for the safeguarding of indigenous 
cultures.”
Mr Momaday is the founder of 
the Buffalo Trust, which is working 
with UNESCO to create Community 
Multimedia Centres in partnership with 
Native American communities in the 
USA, to help safeguard and revitalize 
the intangible heritage of the American 
Indians, using traditional and electronic 
communication technologies.
Mr Momaday won the Pulitzer Prize 
for Fiction in 1969 for his first novel, 
House Made of Dawn. Other works 
include: The Way to Rainy Mountain,
The Names, The Ancient Child, and The 
Man Made of Words. National Museum 
of the American Indian, which will open 
in Washington later this year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
51
Stade français – BNP Paribas
VALUES INVITED
TO ROLAND GARROS
For the third consecutive 
year, the BNP Paribas Cup 
– Stade Français tennis 
tournament, organized 
by the Stade Français 
and the BNP financial 
group, took place under 
the auspices of UNESCO. 
More than 300 young 
tennis players - ages 12 
to 14, from more than 60 
countries - participated 
in the event, nicknamed 
“Junior Roland Garros”. 
During the competition, 
UNESCO put on a 
series of activities at the 
tournament site, located 
in the Paris suburbs. 
Between matches, young 
players could find out 
about values linked to 
education, science and 
culture and understand 
their essential role in 
development. They 
could also sign up for 
workshops on doping, 
learning about values and 
cultural diversity through 
sport, and non-violence. 
For the first time this year, 
the finals were played on 
the central court at Roland 
Garros. The boys’ cup 
was won by Nassim Silla 
(France) and the girls’ 
cup by Renee Reinhard 
(Netherlands).The complete list of UNESCO’s Artists 
for Peace and Goodwill Ambassadors is 
available on line at: 
www.unesco.org/goodwill
in 1995. During the course of her career, 
she has won various prizes and honors 
including “Dancer of the Year” in 1991. 
She has displayed her immense talent in 
starring roles in the world’s great ballets 
including Swan Lake, Romeo and Juliet, 
Giselle, Cinderella, Don Quixote and 
Coppelia.
Along with her artistic work, Miyako 
Yoshida teaches classical dance and 
would like to support UNESCO’s 
programme for arts education and the 
training of professional artists.
Photos © UNESCO/Michel Ravassard
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
zoom
52
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
Tea in the Sahara
Suspended for 23 years, the Tan-Tan Moussem reincarnates 
as a showcase for Moroccan intangible heritage
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
53
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
“Do you know how we treat a broken 
bone? Bury the person in sand. The bone 
sets itself,” the Saharawi herbalist in 
charge of the traditional medicine tent cheerfully 
informs a visitor from France. Then he explains 
various remedies on display, effective for common 
ailments from indigestion to bronchitis. The scene 
was this year’s Tan-Tan Moussem, or traditional 
festival, held in the southern Morocco town from 
September 13 to 19, which brought together several 
thousand Sahara nomads from more than 30 tribes 
to show off their unique customs and folklore. Other 
Moussem attractions included fantasias - galloping 
horsemen firing rifles in perfect synchronicity – as 
well as sleek racing camels, story telling and poetry 
reading in dialect, ululating young women in bridal 
finery and antique silver jewelry, and musicians and 
dancers from as far away as Mali and Mauritania. 
The Tan-Tan Moussem used to be a major social, 
commercial and cultural event for the desert tribes, 
held annually in honor of revered holy man Saint 
Sidi Mohamed Laghdef, but it died out in the 1970s. 
At the instigation of Spanish explorer and goodwill 
ambassador Kitin Munoz, UNESCO sponsored 
its revival in the context of the organization’s 
promotion of oral and intangible cultural heritage, 
Photo exclusive by Michel Ravassard
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
54
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
zoom
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
55
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
particularly of endangered ethnic groups. This year’s 
version reestablished the Tan-Tan Moussem as tribal get-
together, cultural crossroads, tourist attraction and tribute 
to the nomad’s ancient, ephemeral way of life.
AN OPPORTUNITY FOR EXCHANGE
More than just a colourful celebration, it was a rare 
opportunity for exchange between desert people and a 
variety of distinguished visitors. At the closing festivities 
on September 18, presided by Morocco’s Prince Moulay 
Rachid and UNESCO Director-General Koïchiro Matsuura, 
actresses Claudia Cardinale, Marisa Berenson (both UNESCO 
goodwill ambassadors) and Isabelle Adjani were among 
the VIPs mingling with nomads, ministers, diplomats and 
local dignitaries. The guests from Europe, some donning 
Saharawi dress for the day, toured exhibition tents depicting 
tribal life. Food preparation, weaving, saddle-making 
and other crafts, popular games, tribal arbitration and 
Koranic education were illustrated as well as medicine.
“The living testimony of the Saharawi oral and artistic 
cultures that we are able to discover at the Tan-Tan Moussem 
is a lesson of knowledge and creativity from which we 
have much to learn,” said Mr Matsuura in his speech. He 
congratulated Morocco on its efforts, and expressed the hope 
that Morocco would be among the first countries – there 
are already five - to ratify UNESCO’s 2003 Convention for 
the Safeguarding of the Intangible Cultural Heritage.
Cathy Nolan
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
56
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
books
THE CHALLENGE OF 
INDIGENOUS EDUCATION: 
PRACTICE AND 
PERSPECTIVES
This book describes the 
challenges facing both the 
providers of education for 
indigenous peoples and 
indigenous communities 
themselves. 
Part I of this study reflects 
upon the challenges and 
obstacles facing indigenous 
education, the situation of 
indigenous peoples with 
regard to education, aspects 
of the political and legal 
context, prospects and general 
objectives. Part II develops a set 
of criteria for the identification 
of successful examples 
of quality education for 
indigenous peoples, illustrated 
by some relevant experiences. 
Part III presents case studies 
of programmes and initiatives 
of quality education from 
different regions of the world. 
This book offers insights for 
policy makers, researchers 
and all those concerned with 
educational provision.
By Linda King and Sabine Schielmann
284 pp., 
24 x 15,5 cm
2004, ISBN 92-3-103934-2
19.80 €
UNESCO Publishing 
THE FUTURE OF VALUES
“Can
we hold to 
the vision of a 
universal project compatible 
with the multiplicity of our 
heritages and enriched by their 
interwoven histories?” This 
is one of the key questions 
addressed in this second 
anthology originating from 
UNESCO’s “21st century Talks”, 
orchestrated by Jérôme Bindé, 
Director of UNESCO’s Division 
of Foresight, Philosophy and 
Human Sciences and Deputy 
Assistant Director-General for 
the Social Sciences Sector. 
It brings together about 50 
renowned scientists, researchers 
and thinkers from a range of 
disciplines – legal experts, 
anthropologists, astrophysicists, 
historians, sociologists, biologist, 
geneticists, linguists, writers, 
psychoanalysts and philosophers 
– who set out to redefine and 
anticipate tomorrow’s values, 
and reflect on the direction these 
values may lead humanity.
The volume is divided into 
four chapters: The Future of 
Values, Globalization, New 
technologies and Culture; 
Towards New Social Contracts?; 
and Science, Knowledge 
and Foresight: Each section 
comprises a series of articles that 
can be read separately. But the 
publication is more than a series 
of brilliant presentations. It has 
its own logic and structure, 
which only reveals itself when 
the book is taken as a whole. 
The Future of Values is also 
an example, par excellence, of 
UNESCO’s role to serve as a 
forum for ethical discussion. 
“At the dawn of the twenty-first 
century,” writes Jérôme Bindé 
in his introduction, “at a time 
when attempts to reappropriate 
values seem to have foundered 
– whether in relation to 
revolutionary schemes of 
political emancipation or 
ventures into the realm of 
philosophical, spiritual, 
ideological or political renewal; 
when certain prophets of doom 
are proclaiming the advent of 
‘post-humanity’, not to say 
of the inhuman; when tragic 
events leave us disoriented 
and discredit the hypothesis 
of the ‘end of History’; and 
when societies are mobilized 
in the search for new ethical 
codes, UNESCO could not 
fail to address the question 
of the future of values from a 
forward-looking philosophical 
standpoint.”
The Future of Values
21st Century Talks
Edited by Jérôme Bindé
352 pp.
2004,
ISBN 92-3-203946-X
UNESCO Publishing/Berghahn Books
21.50 €
George J. Annas
Arjun Appadurai
Mohammed Arkoun
Adalberto Barreto
Jean Baudrillard
Hélé Béji
Aziza Bennani
Jérôme Bindé
Denise Bombardier
André Brahic
Fay Chung
Jacques Delors
Jacques Derrida
Lord Meghnad Desai
Souleymane Bachir Diagne
Thierry Gaudin
Nadine Gordimer
Jean-Joseph Goux
Claude Hagège
Ryuichi Ida
Jeliou Jelev
Axel Kahn
Paul Kennedy
Julia Kristeva
Michel Maffesoli
Victor Massuh
Koïchiro Matsuura
Achille Mbembe
Elikia M’Bokolo
Candido Mendes
Luc Montagnier
Edgar Morin
Salikoko Mufwene
Thomas Odhiambo
Eduardo Portella
Nicolas Prantzos
Paul Ricœur
Jeremy Rifkin
Francisco Sagasti
Pierre Sané
Michel Serres
Daryush Shayegan
Peter Sloterdijk
Roger Sue
Jacques Testart
Trinh Xuan Thuan
Mostafa K. Tolba
Alain Touraine
Gianni Vattimo
Wolfgang Welsch
Eduard O. Wilson
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
57
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
SOLAR DETOXIFICATION
Divided into two parts, the first 
part of this book addresses 
the theory and fundamentals 
of water decontamination by 
means of solar energy. This 
prepares the reader for the 
second part, which deals with 
the practical applications and 
systems engineering of the 
process. Although it is designed 
for university students and post 
graduates it can also be read by 
any professional or technician. 
All subjects are treated in depth, 
with scientific rigor, but are 
also illustrated throughout with 
a wide array of pictures and 
graphics. 
Edited by Julián Blanco Gálvez 
and Sixto Malato Rodríguez
208 pp., 
27 x 21 cm
2003,
ISBN 92-3-103916-4
24.80 €
UNESCO Publishing
Renewable Energies Series
GEOTHERMAL ENERGY: 
UTILIZATION AND 
TECHNOLOGY
A concise but complete 
description of geothermal 
phenomena and geothermal 
exploitation. Features include 
a comprehensive introduction 
to the nature, classification 
and distribution of geothermal 
resources; a description of 
geothermal electricity generation 
and non-electric uses; an 
analysis of the potential impact 
of geothermal energy utilization 
on the environment, and 
socio-economic and regulatory 
aspects. This publication will 
appeal to under- and post-
graduate students in power 
engineering, mechanical 
engineering and physics who 
wish to further their knowledge 
in geothermal applications.
Edited by Mary H. Dickson 
and Mario Fanelli
226 pp., 
27 x 21 cm
2003,
ISBN 92-3-103915-6
24.80 €
UNESCO Publishing 
Renewable Energies Series
UNESCO TOOLKIT OF LEARNING
AND TEACHING MATERIALS
The toolkit consists of two companion volumes – Solar
Photovoltaic Systems: Technical Training Manual and Solar 
Photovoltaic Project Development.
The overall objective of this toolkit is to provide 
comprehensive training material on the innovation, 
application, installation, operation, monitoring and 
evaluation, management maintenance and rehabilitation 
of PV systems as well as providing useful information for 
advocacy, awareness raising, innovation, policy and planning.
It contains comprehensive technical, educational and 
geographical coverage. It provides a complete course in PV 
applications for rural electrification at three levels: instructor, 
senior technician and field technician.
This toolkit is based on experience gained in the Pacific, 
where solar photovoltaics and rural electrification were 
pioneered in the 1970s and 1980s.
SOLAR PHOTOVOLTAIC 
PROJECT DEVELOPMENT
Intended more as a text for 
teachers both to support the 
technical training manual, and 
to discuss wider issues relating 
to project development for PV 
systems. 
By Herbert A. Wade
156 pp., 27 x 21 cm
2003,
ISBN 92-3-103903-2
16.80 €
UNESCO Publishing
Renewable Energies Series
SOLAR PHOTOVOLTAIC 
SYSTEMS TECHNICAL 
TRAINING MANUAL
Contains detailed descriptive 
texts and graphics.
By Herbert A. Wade 
Illustrated by Gloria McConnaghy
124 pp., 
27 x 21 cm (landscape format)
2003,
ISBN 92-3-103904-0
12.80 €
UNESCO Publishing
Renewable Energies Series
www.unesco.org/publishing
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
contacts
58
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
Documentation Centres
UNESCO Offices
Archives (BSS/AM)
☎ (33-1) 45 68 19 50/55
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 17
E-mail: archives@unesco.org
Coastal Areas and Small Islands
☎ (33-1) 45 68 39 34
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 58 08
E-mail: c.nollet@unesco.org
Communication
☎ (33-1) 45 68 42 67
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 55 82
E-mail: n.nguyen-van@unesco.org
Culture
☎ (33-1) 45 68 43 43
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 55 74
E-mail: culture.doc@unesco.org
Education
☎ (33-1) 45 68 10 29
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 24
E-mail: sdi@unesco.org
Information et Informatics
☎ (33-1) 45 68 43 99
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 55 82
E-mail: g.mensah@unesco.org
Information about UNESCO
☎ (33-1) 01 45 68 16 81
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 57
E-mail: p.morel-vasquez@unesco.org
Library
☎ (33-1) 45 68 03 56
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 98
E-mail: library@unesco.org
MAB – Man and the Biosphere
☎ (33-1) 45 68 40.59
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 58 04
E-mail: mab@unesco.org
Natural Sciences
☎ (33-1) 45 68 40 17
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 58 23
E-mail: p.murugaiyan@unesco.org
Oceanography
☎ (33-1) 45 68 39 82
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 58 12
E-mail: p.boned@unesco.org
Photo Library
☎ (33-1) 45 68 16 91
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 55
E-mail: photobank@unesco.org
Studio Radio-TV, Archives, Audiovisual
☎ (33-1) 45 68 00 68
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 56
E-mail: studio@unesco.org
Social and Human Sciences
☎ (33-1) 45 68 38 07
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 77
E-mail: dare@unesco.org
Statistics
☎ (1-514) 343- 68 80
Fax: (1-514) 343-68 82
E-mail: uis.resource-centre@unesco.org
Hydrology
☎ (33-1) 45 68 40 04
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 58 11
E-mail: ihp@unesco.org
World Heritage
☎ (33-1) 45 68 18 76
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 55 70
E-mail: wh-info@unesco.org
Youth Coordination
☎ (33-1) 45 68 16 54
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 57 90
E-mail: ucj@unesco.org
Afghanistan
UNESCO Kabul
P.O. Box 5, Kabul
☎ +93-70-283.008
Fax:  +873-763 468 836,
E-mail: martin.hadlow@undp.org
Bangladesh
Idb Bhaban (16th floor)
E/8-A Rokeya Sharan
Sher-e-Banglanagar, Dhaka 1207
☎ (880-2) 912 34 69/6522
Fax: (880-2) 912 34 68
E-mail: dhaka@unesco.org
Brazil
SAS Quadra 5 Bloco H Lote 6
Edificio CNPQ/IBICT/UNESCO 
9º andar, 70070-914 Brasilia D.F.
☎ (55-61)21 06 35 00
Fax: (55-61) 322 42 61
E-mail: brasilia@unesco.org
Burundi
Avenue du Luxembourg, 
Bujumbura
☎ (257) 21 53 82/84 
Fax: (257) 21 53 83 
E-mail: bujumbura@unesco.org 
Cambodia
P.O. BOX 29
House 38, Samdech Sothearos 
blvd, Phnom Penh
☎ (855-23) 217 244, 426 726 
Fax: (855-23) 426 163, 217 022
E-mail: phnompenh@unesco.org
Cameroon
Immeuble Stamatiades, 
(2nd floor), Avenue de 
l’Indépendance, BP 12909, 
Yaoundé 
☎ (237) 22 57 63
Fax: (237) 22 63 89
E-mail: yaounde@unesco.org
Chile
Calle Enrique Delpiano, 2058
Providencia, 3187 Santiago
☎ (56-2) 472 4600/655 10 50
Fax: (56 2) 655 10 46, 655 10 47
E-mail: santiago@unesco.org
China
Waijiaogongyu 5-15-3, 
Jianguomenwai Compound, 
Beijing 100600
☎ (86-10) 65 32 28 28
Fax: (86-10) 65 32 48 54
E-mail: beijing@unesco.org
Congo
134 bd du Maréchal Lyautey, 
Brazzaville
☎ (242) 81 18 29 
Fax: (242) 81 17 80
E-mail: brazzaville@unesco.org
Costa Rica
Paseo Colon, ave 1 bis, calle 28, 
casa esquinera, 2810 San José
☎ (506) 258 76 25
Fax: (506) 258 74 58, 258 76 41
E-mail: san-jose@unesco.org 
Cuba
UNESCO Regional bureau 
for Culture
Calzada 551 – Esq. a D
Vedado, Havana
☎ (53-7) 832 76 38,
(57-3) 33 34 38 
Fax: (53-7) 33 31 44
E-mail: habana@unesco.org
Democratic Republic of the Congo
Immeuble Losonia, 
Boulevard du 30 Juin, Kinshasa
☎ (243) 88 48 253
Fax: (243) 88 48 252
E-mail: kinshasa@unesco.org
Ecuador
Juan Leon Mera 130 y
Ave. Patria, Edificio CFN 6to Piso, 
Quito
☎ 2 5932 2529 085/2 5932 2562 327
Fax: 2 5932 2504 435
E-mail: quito@unesco.org
Egypt
UNESCO Regional Office 
for Science
8 Abdel-Rahman
Fahmy Street, Garden City, 
Cairo 11541
☎ (202) 79 504 24 
Fax: (202) 79 45 296
E-mail: cairo@unesco.org 
Ethiopia
P.O. Box 1177, ECA Building, 
Menelik Avenue,
Addis Ababa
☎ (251-1) 51 39 53
Fax: (251-1) 51 14 14
E-mail: mlconde@hotmail.com
Gabon
A la Cité de la Démocratie, 
Bâtiment N° 6, B.P. 2, Libreville
☎ (241) 76 28 79
Fax: (241) 76 28 14
E-mail: unesclbv@inet.ga
Ghana
32 Nortei Ababio Street, Airport, 
Residential Area, Accra
☎ (233-21) 765 497, 765 499 
Fax: (233-21) 765 498
E-mail: accra@unesco.org
Guatemala
Edificio Etisa, Ofic. 7 “A”
Plaza España, Zona 9, 
Guatemala City
☎ (502) 360 87 17, 
360 87 27
Fax: (502) 360 87 19
E-mail: guatemala@unesco.org
Haïti
19, Delmas 60, Musseau par 
Bourdon, Petion Ville
☎ (509) 511 04 60/61/62
Fax: (509) 257 8158
E-mail: unescohaiti@hainet.net
India
B 5/29 Safdarjung Enclave, New 
Delhi 110 029
☎ (91-11) 671 3000 
Fax: (91-11) 671 3001/2
E-mail: newdelhi@unesco.org
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP
France
Tel. +33 1 45 68 10 00
Internet:
www.unesco.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
59
UNESCO | the new Courier | October 2004
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/N
ia
m
h 
B
ur
ke
Indonesia
UNESCO House, Jalan Galuh 
(II)
N° 5, Kebayo Baru,
Jakarta Selatan, Jakarta 12110
☎ (62-21) 739 9818
Fax: (62-21) 7279 6489
E-mail: jakarta@unesco.org
Iran (Islamic Republic of)
Bahman Building, Sa’ad 
Abad Palace Complex
Tehran
☎ (98-21) 27 40 
141/142/143 
Fax: (98-21) 27 40 144
E-mail: tehran@unesco.org
Italy
Palazzo Zorzi, Castello 4930 
Venice
☎ (39-041) 260 15 11
switchboard
Fax: (39-041) 528 99 95
E-mail: roste@unesco.org
Jamaica
The Towers, 25 Dominica 
Drive, 3rd Floor, Kingston 5
☎ (1-876) 929 70 87, 
929 70 89
Fax: (1-876) 929 84 68
E-mail: kingston@unesco.org
Jordan
Wadi Saqra Street
Amman 11181
☎ (962-6) 551 42 34/65 59
Fax: (962-6) 553 21 83
E-mail: registry@unesco.org
Kazakhstan
4th Floor, UN Building
67, Tole Bi Street, Almaty
☎ (7-3272) 58 26 37/38
Fax: (7-3272) 79 48 53
E-mail: almaty@unesco.org
Kenya
United Nations Offices, 
Gigiri, Block C, United 
Nations Avenue, Gigiri 
Nairobi
☎ (254-2) 62 12 34
Fax: (254-2) 62 27 50
E-mail: nairobi@unesco.org 
Lebanon
Cité Sportive Av., Beirut
☎ (961-1) 85 00 13
Fax: (961-1) 82 48 54
E-mail: beirut@unesco.org
Mali
Badalabougou Est
B.P. E 1763, Bamako
☎ (223) 223 34 92, 223 34 93
Fax: (223) 223 34 94 
E-mail: bamako@unesco.org
Mexico
Pte Masaryk n.° 526, 3er piso
Colonia Polanco, 11560 
Mexico, D.F.
☎ (52-55) 5230 76 00
Fax: (52-55) 5230 76 02
E-mail: mexico@unesco.org
Morocco
35 av du 16 novembre, 
Agdal, Rabat 1777
☎ (212-37) 67 03 72,  
67 03 74, 77 81 82
Fax: (212-37) 67 03 75
E-mail: rabat@unesco.org
Mozambique
515, av. Frederick Engels, 
Maputo
☎ (258-1) 49 44 50, 49 34 34
Fax: (258-1) 49 34 31, 49 45 03 
E-mail: maputo@unesco.org 
Namibia
Oppenheimer House,
5 Brahms St., Windhoek
☎ (264-61) 291 7000, 
Fax: (264-61) 291 7220
E-mail:
windhoek@unesco.org
Nepal
Ring Road-Bansbari
Kathmandu
☎ (977-1) 437 40 09, 
Fax: (977-1) 437 30 04
E-mail:
kathmandu@unesco.org
Nigeria
Street Plot 777,
Bouake Street, off Herbert 
Maccaulay Way
Wuse Zone 6, Abuja
☎ (234-9) 52 37 088
Fax: (234-9) 52 38 094
E-mail: abuja@unesco.org
Pakistan
Saudi-Pak Tower, First Floor, 
Blue Area, Jinnah Avenue, 
Islamabad 44000
☎ (92-51) 28 000 83
Fax: (92-51) 28 000 56 
E-mail:
islamabad@unesco.org
Palestinian Authority
17, Ahliyyah College St. West 
Bank via Israel Ramallah
☎ (972-2) 295 9740
Fax: (972-2) 295 97 41
E-mail: unesco@palnet.com
Peru
Avenida Javier Prado Este 
2465 - 8 piso, Museo de la 
Nacion, San Borja, Lima 
☎ (51-1) 476 98 71,
224 25 26
Fax: (51-1) 476 98 72
E-mail: unescope@amauta.
rch.net.pe
Qatar
57, Al-Jazira Al-Arabia 
St. Doha
☎ (974) 486 77 07/ 77 08/ 
75 49
Fax: (974) 486 76 44
E-mail: doha@unesco.org
Romania
◗ UNESCO European Centre 
for Higher Education, 39, 
Stirbei Vodà Str., Bucharest
☎ (40-21) 313 08 39 / 06 98
Fax: (40-21) 312 35 67 
E-mail: bucarest@unesco.org
Russian Federation
Bolshoi Levshinsky per. 15/28, 
blg. 2, 119034 Moscou
☎ (7-095) 202 80 97/
202 87 59/202 81 66
Fax:  (7-095) 202 05 68,
956 36 66 
E-mail: moscow@unesco.org
Rwanda
Mineduc Compound
☎ (250) 51 58 45/ 44/ 46
Fax: (250) 51 38 44
E-mail: kigali@unesco.org
Samoa
P.O. Box 615
Matautu-uta Post Offi ce, Apia
☎ (685) 242 76
Fax: (685) 222 53
E-mail: apia@unesco.org 
Senegal
UNESCO Regional Office 
Dakar and Regional Bureau 
for Education
12 av.L.S Senghor,
Dakar
☎ (221) 849 2323
Fax: (221) 823 83 93
E-mail: dakar@unesco.org
Switzerland
Villa « Les Feuillantines »
CH-1211 Genève 10
☎ (41-22) 917 33 81
Fax: (41-22) 917 00 64
E-mail: geneva@unesco.org
Tanzania (United Republic of) 
Oyster Bay, Uganda Av.,
Plot N° 197A, Dar-es-Salaam
☎ (255-22) 2666 623/26 
671 656
Fax: (255-22) 26 66 927
E-mail:
dar-es-salaam@unesco.org
Thailand
920 Suhumvit Rd., 
Bangkok 10110
☎ (662) 391 05 77/391 0879
Fax: (662) 391 08 66
E-mail: bangkok@unesco.org
United States ef America
2, United Nations Plaza,
Suite 900
New York, N.Y. 10017
☎ (1-212) 963 59 95, 
Fax: (1-212) 963 80 14
E-mail:
e.minchenberg@unesco.org
Uruguay
UNESCO Office Montevideo 
Regional Bureau for Science 
in Latin and the Caribbean
Edificio del Mercosur (ex 
Parque Hotel), Calle Dr. Luis 
Piera, 1992
Montevideo
☎ (598-2) 413 2075/413 
2094
Fax: (598-2) 413 2094, 
E-mail: orcyt@unesco.org.ury 
Uzbekistan
95, Amir Temur Str., 
Tashkent, 70 000
☎ (998-71) 12 07 116
Fax: (998-71) 13 21 382
E-mail: tashkent@unesco.org 
Viet Nam
23 Cao Ba Quat, Hanoï
☎ (84-4) 747 0275/6
Fax: (84-4) 747 0274
E-mail: registry@unesco.org
Zimbabwe
8 Kenilworth Rd. Newlands, 
Harare
☎ (263-4) 77 61 16
Fax: (263-4) 77 60 55
E-mail: harare@unesco.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
Madres y niños 
Oswaldo Guayasamín (1919-1999)
4,72 x 6 m.
A gift from Ecuador to UNESCO in 1993, 
the mural by Oswaldo Guayasamín adorns the 
entrance to the Executive Boardroom.
In 1976, the Ecuadorian artist (1919-1999) 
described his style in these words: « I have 
painted for half a century as if I were crying 
in desperation. And my cry was added to 
all the other cries expressing the humiliation 
and anxiety of our era. »
gallery
]]>
</page>
</document>
