<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="139497eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
2
message
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
59
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/N
ia
m
h 
B
ur
ke
Indonesia
UNESCO House, Jalan Galuh 
(II)
N° 5, Kebayo Baru, 
Jakarta Selatan, Jakarta 12110
☎ (62-21) 739 9818
Fax: (62-21) 7279 6489
E-mail: jakarta@unesco.org
Iran (Islamic Republic of)
Bahman Building, Sa’ad 
Abad Palace Complex
Tehran
☎  (98-21) 27 40 
141/142/143 
Fax: (98-21) 27 40 144
E-mail: tehran@unesco.org
Italy
Palazzo Zorzi, Castello 4930 
Venice
☎  (39-041) 260 15 11 
switchboard
Fax: (39-041) 528 99 95
E-mail: roste@unesco.org
Jamaica
The Towers, 25 Dominica 
Drive, 3rd Floor, Kingston 5
☎ (1-876) 929 70 87,  
929 70 89
Fax: (1-876) 929 84 68
E-mail: kingston@unesco.org
Jordan
Wadi Saqra Street 
Amman 11181
☎ (962-6) 551 42 34/65 59
Fax: (962-6) 553 21 83
E-mail: registry@unesco.org
Kazakhstan
4th Floor, UN Building
67, Tole Bi Street, Almaty
☎ (7-3272) 58 26 37/38
Fax: (7-3272) 79 48 53
E-mail: almaty@unesco.org
Kenya
United Nations Offices, 
Gigiri, Block C, United 
Nations Avenue, Gigiri 
Nairobi
☎ (254-2) 62 12 34
Fax: (254-2) 62 27 50
E-mail: nairobi@unesco.org 
Lebanon
Cité Sportive Av., Beirut
☎ (961-1) 85 00 13
Fax: (961-1) 82 48 54
E-mail: beirut@unesco.org
Mali
Badalabougou Est
B.P. E 1763, Bamako
☎ (223) 223 34 92, 223 34 93
Fax: (223) 223 34 94 
E-mail: bamako@unesco.org
Mexico
Pte Masaryk n.° 526, 3er piso
Colonia Polanco, 11560 
Mexico, D.F.
☎ (52-55) 5230 76 00
Fax: (52-55) 5230 76 02
E-mail: mexico@unesco.org
Morocco
35 av du 16 novembre, 
Agdal, Rabat 1777
☎  (212-37) 67 03 72,  
67 03 74, 77 81 82
Fax: (212-37) 67 03 75
E-mail: rabat@unesco.org
Mozambique
515, av. Frederick Engels, 
Maputo
☎ (258-1) 49 44 50, 49 34 34
Fax: (258-1) 49 34 31, 49 45 03 
E-mail: maputo@unesco.org 
Namibia
Oppenheimer House,
5 Brahms St., Windhoek
☎ (264-61) 291 7000, 
Fax: (264-61) 291 7220
E-mail: 
windhoek@unesco.org
Nepal
Ring Road-Bansbari
Kathmandu
☎ (977-1) 437 40 09,  
Fax: (977-1) 437 30 04
E-mail: 
kathmandu@unesco.org
Nigeria
Street Plot 777,
Bouake Street, off Herbert 
Maccaulay Way
Wuse Zone 6, Abuja
☎ (234-9) 52 37 088
Fax: (234-9) 52 38 094
E-mail: abuja@unesco.org
Pakistan
Saudi-Pak Tower, First Floor, 
Blue Area, Jinnah Avenue,  
Islamabad 44000
☎ (92-51) 28 000 83
Fax: (92-51) 28 000 56 
E-mail: 
islamabad@unesco.org
Palestinian Authority
17, Ahliyyah College St. West 
Bank via Israel Ramallah
☎ (972-2) 295 9740
Fax: (972-2) 295 97 41
E-mail: unesco@palnet.com
Peru
Avenida Javier Prado Este 
2465 - 8 piso, Museo de la 
Nacion, San Borja, Lima  
☎  (51-1) 476 98 71, 
224 25 26
Fax: (51-1) 476 98 72
E-mail: unescope@amauta. 
rch.net.pe
Qatar
57, Al-Jazira Al-Arabia  
St. Doha
☎ (974) 486 77 07/ 77 08/ 
75 49
Fax: (974) 486 76 44
E-mail: doha@unesco.org
Romania
◗ UNESCO European Centre 
for Higher Education, 39, 
Stirbei Vodà Str., Bucharest
☎ (40-21) 313 08 39 / 06 98
Fax: (40-21) 312 35 67 
E-mail: bucarest@unesco.org
Russian Federation
Bolshoi Levshinsky per. 15/28, 
blg. 2, 119034 Moscou
☎  (7-095) 202 80 97/ 
202 87 59/202 81 66
Fax:  (7-095) 202 05 68, 
956 36 66 
E-mail: moscow@unesco.org
Rwanda
Mineduc Compound 
☎ (250) 51 58 45/ 44/ 46
Fax: (250) 51 38 44
E-mail: kigali@unesco.org
Samoa
P.O. Box 615
Matautu-uta Post Office, Apia
☎ (685) 242 76
Fax: (685) 222 53
E-mail: apia@unesco.org 
Senegal
UNESCO Regional Office 
Dakar and Regional Bureau 
for Education
12 av.L.S Senghor,
Dakar
☎ (221) 849 2323
Fax: (221) 823 83 93
E-mail: dakar@unesco.org
Switzerland
Villa « Les Feuillantines »
CH-1211 Genève 10
☎ (41-22) 917 33 81
Fax: (41-22) 917 00 64
E-mail: geneva@unesco.org
Tanzania (United Republic of) 
Oyster Bay, Uganda Av., 
Plot N° 197A, Dar-es-Salaam
☎ (255-22) 2666 623/26 
671 656
Fax: (255-22) 26 66 927
E-mail:  
dar-es-salaam@unesco.org
Thailand
920 Suhumvit Rd.,  
Bangkok 10110
☎ (662) 391 05 77/391 0879
Fax: (662) 391 08 66
E-mail: bangkok@unesco.org
United States ef America
2, United Nations Plaza,
Suite 900
New York, N.Y. 10017
☎ (1-212) 963 59 95,  
Fax: (1-212) 963 80 14
E-mail: 
e.minchenberg@unesco.org
Uruguay
UNESCO Office Montevideo 
Regional Bureau for Science 
in Latin and the Caribbean
Edificio del Mercosur (ex 
Parque Hotel), Calle Dr. Luis 
Piera, 1992
Montevideo
☎ (598-2) 413 2075/413 
2094
Fax: (598-2) 413 2094,  
E-mail: orcyt@unesco.org.ury 
Uzbekistan
95, Amir Temur Str., 
Tashkent, 70 000
☎ (998-71) 12 07 116
Fax: (998-71) 13 21 382
E-mail: tashkent@unesco.org 
Viet Nam
23 Cao Ba Quat, Hanoï
☎ (84-4) 747 0275/6
Fax: (84-4) 747 0274
E-mail: registry@unesco.org
Zimbabwe
8 Kenilworth Rd. Newlands, 
Harare
☎ (263-4) 77 61 16
Fax: (263-4) 77 60 55
E-mail: harare@unesco.org
the new Courier is published 
by the United Nations Educational, Scientific 
and Cultural Organization
7, place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Tel: 33 1 45 68 46 85 
Fax: 33 1 45 68 56 52
Email: unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet: http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director of publications: Stefanino Muñoz Gomez 
Editor in Chief: Vincent Defourny 
Issue coordinator: Agnès Bardon
Editorial staff: Roni Amelan, Christophe Bouton, 
Pierre Gaillard, Lucia Iglesias-Kuntz, Cathy Nolan, 
Bassam Mansour, Vladimir Sergueev, Jasmina 
Sopova
Editorial Assistant: José Banaag
Photo editor: Ariane Bailey
Photographers: Niamh Burke, Michel Ravassard
Editions produced away from headquarters: 
Michiko Tanaka
Artistic direction: Jean-Francis Cheriez
Production: Gérard Prosper, Eric Frogé
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Distribution: Pilar Morel Vasquez
Printed by: Imprimerie Corlet,  
Condé-sur-Noireau, France
Electronic version: Richard Cadiou, Fiona Ryan
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted 
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads 
“Reprinted from the new Courier”, including the 
date and issue. Non-copyright photos will be 
supplied upon request. Unsolicited manuscripts and 
articles will not be returned unless accompanied  
by an international reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors 
and do not necessarily represent the opinions 
of UNESCO or those of the new Courier. 
Photo captions and headlines are written by the 
magazine’s editorial staff.  
The boundaries on maps do not imply official 
endorsement or acceptance by UNESCO or  
the United Nations of the countries and territories 
concerned.
ISSN 0041-5278
Cover photo:
© Mikkel Ostergaard/Panos Pictures, London  
Among all the reports about the Indian Ocean tsunami of 
December 26 and its tragic consequences, two extraordinary 
stories went to the very heart of education for sustainable 
development.
A little English girl on a beach in Thailand with her family 
remembered what she had learned at school and understood the natural 
phenomenon that was unfolding before her eyes. She raised the alarm 
in time and was able to tell people the best course of action to take.
The Moken people from the Surin islands, who from the dawn of 
time have made listening to the signals given by nature part of their 
everyday life, also understood what was happening and escaped the 
giant wave.
It was partly education and partly traditional knowledge rooted in 
their culture that gave them the means, limited perhaps but effective 
all the same, to face up to the tsunami. When education and culture 
combine with rigorous scientific observation of the oceans, social 
organization of warning systems and the media’s ability to spread 
information, it is possible to forge, as is the case in Chile and Japan, 
individual and collective behaviour that integrates natural risk 
prevention. UNESCO does not believe a global tsunami warning system 
can operate in any other way.
While education for sustainable development is the central issue 
in this edition of the New Courier, current events have prompted us to 
return to several aspects of December’s catastrophe and put them into 
perspective.
This regional disaster had repercussions in every region of the 
world, not only because the killer wave affected so many countries 
bordering the Indian Ocean, but also because so many tourists were 
involved and the emotion and solidarity generated from the disaster 
embraced the whole world. The often invisible threads which join the 
people of the world together appeared in the blinding white light of this 
tragedy. The event must also be seen as an echo of the warning made 
by United Nations experts in their “Millennium Ecosystem Assessment 
Synthesis Report”, published on March 301
To give everyone the chance to change their behaviour, a decade 
is hardly long enough. Representatives of every country in the world 
gave the United Nations a mandate to set up the Decade of Education 
for Sustainable Development (2005-2014). They gave UNESCO the task 
of leading the way. This symbolic act is undoubtedly no more than 
a means to attract public attention. The scant resources available for 
the Decade are not in themselves going to change the course of the 
future. However, growing awareness of the importance of our daily 
acts and UNESCO’s ongoing actions in education, science, culture and 
communication give us hope that the UN Millennium Development 
Goals2 will be reached by the target date of 2015.
Vincent Defourny
1. http://www.millenniumassessment.org/
2. http://www.un.org/french/millenniumgoals/
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
3
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
summary
Tsunami Special
SRI LANKA:
PAINFUL AFTERMATH   5
Scenes of desolation in the wake of the giant wave
TALKING TO LAURA KONG   8
Advocating an early warning system for tsunamis
CHILE: THE LESSONS OF A TRAGEDY    11
Following the 1960 tsunami, a early warning system
was established in the Pacific
UNESCO in Action
Communication   14
UNESCO’S CHANGING 
PARTNERSHIP WITH
THE PRIVATE SECTOR
Partnerships are multiplying between 
UNESCO and business
Culture   17
THE SHIPWRECKED 
MEMORY OF THE UTILE 
SLAVES
A lost chapter in the history 
of the slave trade
Focus   26
PROJECTING THE PLANET 
INTO THE FUTURE
In order for humans to safeguard their future,
they must learn to change their behaviour. 
The Decade of Education for Sustainable Development 
is emphasizing this fact 
Partners   51
New projects underway with a range of partners from
the public and private sectors, as well as civil society and
leading figures in the arts
Zoom   53
SPARED BY THE SEA
After the disaster, the Mokens from 
the Surin Islands (Thailand) rebuild their 
village
Books   56
Contacts   58
UNESCO In Brief   23
News of the organization
Education   20
PRECARIOUS 
FUTURE FOR IRAQI 
UNIVERSITIES
Assessing the state of higher 
education in Iraq
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4
Tsunami Special
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
PAINFUL       AFTERMATH
On December 26, 2004, the waters of the 
Indian Ocean crashed into the Sri Lankan 
coast, killing more than 30,000 people. 
The giant waves have left behind a 
devastated landscape of ruins and debris. 
Martin Hadlow, Director of UNESCO’s 
Antenna for Post-tsunami Operations in 
Colombo (Sri Lanka) tells the story. 
When the earth began to shake in 
Sumatra, Indonesia, on March 28, the 
tsunami that devastated the Indian Ocean 
coasts in December 2004 was fresh in 
everyone’s mind.
Terrified that they would see the sea 
rise up once again, people living on the 
coast rushed out of their homes and ran 
for higher ground. The scars inflicted by 
the disaster are still visible everywhere in 
affected countries, adding to the climate 
of fear (see article p. 5). This time the 
earthquake did not cause a giant wave, 
but the new alert re-emphasized the 
urgent need for a tsunami early warning 
system.
UNESCO has a long history 
of experience in this field. The 
Intergovernmental Oceanographic 
Commission (IOC) launched a tsunami 
warning system for the Pacific in 1968 
(see article p. 11). Thanks to the data 
supplied by hundreds of seismic stations 
and tide gauges installed in the Pacific, 
the system makes it possible to detect 
the appearance of a huge tidal wave and 
to warn the countries concerned, so that 
they in turn can alert their citizens living 
on the coast. Transmitting information 
at maximum speed is a key factor in the 
prevention of disasters.
That is why, in the aftermath of the 
catastrophe that struck the countries 
bordering the Indian Ocean, UNESCO 
proposed putting in place, as of June 
2006, an interim warning system in 
the Indian Ocean region, until a global 
system comes into operation in June 
2007. Experts believe that such a device 
can save numerous lives (see interview 
p. 8). But the chances for success and 
for the system to work also depend on 
the long-term efforts of all the countries 
involved. Because tsunamis are rare 
occurrences, they may eventually be 
relegated to a secondary level of priority. 
That is why it is crucial to develop a 
culture of prevention that sustains a 
constant awareness of the risk.
Agnès Bardon
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
5
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
PAINFUL       AFTERMATH
 Welcome to the tsunami affected 
areas. The wording on the 
sign by the main road south of Colombo seems 
incongruous. The name of the sign’s sponsor, a 
local commercial firm, is written below. Within 
minutes of leaving the outskirts of greater 
Colombo, the first indications of tsunami damage 
become apparent. Broken houses, collapsed walls, 
scattered debris. Even here, on the relatively 
sheltered west coast of Sri Lanka and away 
from the full impact of the tsunami, the water 
held enough energy to cross a major highway, 
scouring the earth, flattening trees and buildings, 
▲
disrupting the main railway line and bringing fear 
and misery in its wake.
But this is just the beginning.. All along the 
low-lying parts of this busy, two-lane beachside 
road are scenes of unparalleled destruction. One 
can only look and wonder. Wonder at the sheer 
terror created when a wall of water, somewhere 
between three and ten metres high, suddenly 
reared up from the calm sea, consumed the 
beach, roared into hotels, houses, shops, schools. 
Buses, trucks, even a moving railway locomotive 
and carriages, were thrown great distances by the 
raw power of the flood.  “These heavy vehicles 
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/S
us
an
ne
 O
rn
ag
er
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6
Tsunami Special
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
▲
floated like feathers on water” I was told. Three 
of the recovered railway carriages now stand on 
display as a reminder of the day when some two 
thousand passengers lost their lives. Death visited 
hundreds and hundreds of kilometres of this 
coastline. Recent burial sites are clearly evident, 
white cloth both indicating deep mourning and 
marking the resting places of the deceased.
REBUILDING 
FOR THE FUTURE
As we drive further south towards Galle and 
Matara, the destruction becomes even worse. 
Affected area. Please help us! pleads a hand-
written sign with a red arrow pointing off the 
main road and down a small alley towards the 
sea shore. Large black plastic tanks containing 
potable water become commonplace by the side 
of the road. Local dwellers stand quietly by them 
in small queues, containers in hand. Whole 
encampments of tents, neatly laid out in rows, 
become more evident on sporting and recreation 
fields on the inland side. Everywhere, there are 
further tangible examples of the outpouring of 
funds from the global community: small wooden 
structures funded by a German NGO, blue plastic 
sheeting provided by the refugee agency, UNHCR, 
rugged structures from Japan….
Families are laying concrete blocks and bricks 
as they start afresh. Everyone seems busy 
rebuilding their lives and their futures. One can 
only marvel at their strength and 
fortitude. Less then two months 
after the tsunami, the railway 
tracks, grotesquely twisted and 
buckled beyond use, have been re-
laid by Sri Lankan rail workers and 
much of the main line reopened to 
train traffic.
But amid the signs of hope 
and renewal are the elements of 
ongoing despair. The foundations 
of a house stand near the beach, 
concrete steps leading up to what 
was once the first floor. Now, there 
is nothing above. A man sits on 
the steps staring out to sea. But the 
tsunami was also cruelly selective, 
some buildings looking remarkably 
unscathed, while neighbouring 
properties were completely 
destroyed. Even the dead have 
found no peace, cemeteries being 
disturbed by the raging water and headstones 
smashed and toppled. 
The ancient city of Galle also awaits the return 
of tourists. The huge Galle Fort, a UNESCO World 
Heritage listed site, seems, to my untrained eye, 
to be relatively unscathed. Within the walls of 
the Fort, the old houses are intact. I am told 
that the water from the sea flowed through old 
portals in the walls and into the town’s drainage 
system, but without causing damage, apart from 
minor flooding. Soon-to-visit UNESCO teams will 
expertly assess the effects of the tsunami on the 
Fort and another old fortified area at Matara, a 
town further south.
WAITING FOR BETTER TIMES
At the Rampart Hotel, the veranda restaurant 
overlooking the Galle Fort and the sea is almost 
empty. The hotel staff laments their current fate 
and look forward to better times. On the way 
out, the shop manager calls me into his empty 
store. It’s a quiet time for him too. Outside the 
walls, the tsunami swept through Galle’s main 
bus station and market, carrying many people to 
their deaths. Galle’s famous cricket ground also 
bore the brunt of the sea’s invasion, the playing 
turf being sodden by saltwater and needing 
replacement before international cricket fixtures 
can again be played.
Lost hopes and shattered dreams crowd each 
side of the road as we travel onwards to our 
It will take time 
for the Hotel Al 
Madeena in Galle 
(Sri Lanka) to reopen
© UNESCO/Nigel Swann 
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
7
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Devastation in Galle 
(Sri Lanka)
terminus, Matara. Houses within Matara’s old 
Dutch-era fort have fared less well than those 
in Galle. Without the protection of an all-
surrounding wall and caught between the beach 
and a lagoon, the homes were brutally destroyed 
by the seawater. In the lagoon, four young men 
carrying long wooden prod at the sea floor. We 
are told that they are looking for some 15 missing 
vehicles which now lie somewhere in the lagoon, 
probably under tonnes of mud and sand. There is 
little chance of finding human remains here as the 
sea, when it retreated, took back to itself much 
of what it had destroyed. Across the lagoon, a 
large fishing vessel sits high above the level of the 
water, thrown there by the tsunami’s destructive 
force.
INCALCULABLE COST OF 
SHATTERED DREAMS
As we drive back towards Colombo, I realise 
that I have seen just a small part of the southern 
region affected by the tsunami. The east coast 
of Sri Lanka was, apparently, more harshly 
struck and devastation in some places is almost 
complete. Sri Lankan authorities estimate that, 
nationwide, some 31,000 people were killed by 
the tsunami and over one million displaced. More 
than 100,000 homes and some 176 schools were 
destroyed or damaged, and many museums and 
archives completely wiped out. This is human, 
social and cultural catastrophe writ large.
Nothing that I have watched on the television 
news has prepared me for the reality of seeing 
the damage with my own eyes. While a monetary 
figure can be placed on replacing bricks and 
mortar, fishing boats and railway lines, the human 
toll is incalculable. It can only be imagined how 
these people, who have lived with the sea as their 
friend, livelihood, food source and cultural focal 
point for countless generations, can ever view the 
now tranquil Indian Ocean waters in the same 
way again. As I drive northwards to Colombo, I 
watch the waves rhythmically rolling ashore on 
the white sandy beach. A now benign sea hides 
its capability to crush entire villages, kill whole 
families, traumatize millions of survivors and 
carry away trucks and trains, as if they were just 
“feathers on water”..
Martin Hadlow 
Colombo (Sri Lanka), February 21, 2005
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/N
ig
el
 S
w
an
n 
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
talking to LAURA KONG
“MANY LIVES COULD 
HAVE BEEN SPARED”
According to the latest estimates, the tsunami that struck countries with  
coasts on the Indian Ocean in December 2004 caused nearly 300,000 deaths. 
Had an early warning system been in place in the region, the toll would not 
have been as heavy. UNESCO’s Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission 
set up such a tsunami alert system in the Pacific in 1965, and is now working 
on a world-wide one that will be operational by June 2007. Laura Kong, 
Director of the International Tsunami Information Centre based in Hawaii, 
outlines the project’s benefits.
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ic
he
l R
av
as
sa
rd
8
The Pacific Tsunami Warning Centre had detected and 
located the earthquake, but was unable to warn people on 
the coasts of the Indian Ocean countries of a tsunami risk. 
Could we have imagined a different scenario?
LK. We could have, if there had been an early warning 
system. First it detects an earthquake, determines how large 
it is and then sends out a warning to the right people, in the 
right manner. It’s also necessary to confirm that a tsunami 
wave has been generated, because most earthquakes don’t 
generate tsunamis. That requires instruments. Such a system 
also means that those notified then have to know exactly 
what to do, which is to get at least 1km inland or move  10 
meters uphill. If such a system had been in place, many lives 
could have been spared in December 2004.
 But the problem is that many countries don’t have a 24-
hour instant alert system. Japan and Hawaii have sirens, as 
well as radio and TV broadcasts. Japan can get a message 
out in two to five minutes. But they often get earthquakes 
and tsunamis, so they can justify the amount of money 
they put into the system, while Hawaii’s notification system 
was developed with other hazards in mind as well, like 
hurricanes, because regional scale tsunamis are rare.
But Indonesia, for example, doesn’t have the necessary 
communication infrastructure at the local level.  It’s a pretty 
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Tsunami Special
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
9
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
The offices of Radio 
Republic Indonesia 
could not withstand 
the gigantic wave
tough challenge for them to set up a 
system. And their special case, being 
in a seismically active area, is that the 
hazard is right off their coast. So they 
probably don’t have much time to 
make a warning. 
Q. There have been pledges to get an 
early tsunami warning system for  
the Indian Ocean up and running in 
12-18 months. Is that feasible? 
LK. An interim system can be ready 
soon, using the existing warning 
centres and data stream. The seismic 
network is probably already there to 
detect the largest earthquakes. But it 
is not good enough to be able to tell 
accurately whether the earthquake 
is in the water or on land. They’re 
going to need a lot more instruments 
to do that – and the data have to 
be collected and sent somewhere in 
real time. With unlimited resources 
in terms of money and people, it’s 
possible to deploy these instruments 
and get a system running in a year or 
two.
In Bangladesh, a lot of money was 
put in to develop a storm surge early 
warning system in the last decade. If it is able to deliver a 
message instantly at all hours of the day, you no longer have 
to develop that component; you’re just adding the tsunami 
warning. So there’s no need to wait. Work can start now in 
these countries. But this means education of public officials, 
elected officials, government heads, agency staff, fire, police, 
and then the public. 
Q. So there are seismic detectors already in place  
in the Indian Ocean?
LK. They’re there. The existing global network has enough 
fidelity to identify when there’s a very large earthquake, 
and then to locate it. To have a more precise location it 
would take more instruments, perhaps 5 or 10 more stations 
– and probably that will happen. But if there were a large 
earthquake tomorrow, the Pacific Tsunami Warning Centre 
and all the other geophysical observatories that get this freely 
available data stream would know instantly about it. They’d 
be able to locate it quickly and be able to estimate its size. 
Q. How do you detect a tsunami and where it’s heading?
We can detect it in the open ocean using deep ocean 
detection systems, but we still have to model it or propagate 
it to shore. These systems are very sensitive gauges that sit 
on the ocean floor and measure changes 
in pressure in the water column above. 
It’s a new technology that has just 
become operational in the last few years. 
Because tsunami waves go out in 
every direction from the epicentre, there 
is a very simple way to know if one has 
been generated, by using tide gauges at 
the coasts. So, if another tsunami event 
occurred off western Sumatra, that wave 
would hit at least one tide gauge before 
it started heading towards Thailand or 
Malaysia. And if a large wave generated in 
Indonesia is detected on a coastal gauge, 
that’s a pretty strong indication that as 
much or more energy is going the other 
way towards Sri Lanka. If you had a deep 
ocean gauge between where it occurred 
and the Indian continent, then that would 
be a direct indication that a large wave 
had been generated.  We would still need 
to carry out numerical models to estimate 
its wave height or coastal impact.
Q. Once you have a system in place,  
the instruments have to be maintained. 
What does that involve?
One of the limitations of the deep ocean 
pressure gauges is that they need power. 
They sit on the ocean bottom and talk to the surface by 
modem when there’s a large signal. If it’s big enough 
they transmit the data to a satellite. But this requires 
maintenance. At present, every year after you deploy one 
of these instruments, you have to go back in a ship, locate 
the gauge, bring it to the surface from perhaps 4000 metres 
▲
At a glance
A Life in 
Seismology
Laura Kong has been Director 
of the UNESCO/IOC International 
Tsunami Information Centre, 
based in Honolulu, Hawaii (USA) 
since 2001. 
After finishing her PhD 
in marine seismology at the 
Massachusetts Institute of 
Technology and the Woods 
Hole Oceanographic Institution 
(USA) in 1990, she spent a year 
as postdoctoral fellow at the 
Earthquake Research Institute in 
Tokyo (Japan), before taking up a 
post as geophysicist at the Pacific 
Tsunami Warning Center. 
From 1993 to 1995, she 
worked as a seismologist at the 
Hawaiian Volcano Observatory. 
From 1996 to 2001, before 
becoming Director of ITIC, she 
held a research post at the 
Hawaii Institute of Geophysics.
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/T
or
be
nB
ra
nd
t 
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10
Tsunami Special
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Ocean buoys ready 
to be deployed in the 
Pacific
▼
depth, change the batteries and the hard disk, service it, then 
throw it back in the water. This has to be done for each of 
the instruments. So the recurring cost is high, in addition to 
the initial investment. These deep ocean devices might cost 
up to $300,000 to deploy initially and then perhaps $50,000 
a year to maintain. So you can put in ten of the coastal tide 
gauges, which are a lot easier to install and maintain than 
these ocean buoys, for the cost of one deep ocean gauge. But 
the ocean buoys give you a data point in the middle of the 
ocean, which the other one can’t. And they buy you extra 
time for a warning.  Technology is improving very quickly 
these days so it’s very probable that the costs of the deep-
ocean systems will go down and servicing time may be 
reduced as better and more reliable electronic components 
are developed. 
Q. So what will be the next stages?
LK. The IOC can’t implement an Indian Ocean system 
by itself. It doesn’t have the funding base, or the human 
resources. It has information and guidance that we’ve used 
in the Pacific. Each nation has to contribute what they can 
in terms of instruments and infrastructure to build a regional 
system. The IOC doesn’t own any of it.
In order to build a truly regional system, nations need 
to contribute national resources in a freely available way, 
especially in terms of data sharing. This is critical to its 
success.
Q Do all the States involved agree on this?
LK. We are aware that some countries have not freely  
shared their data in real time in the past. Some countries do 
have networks that are not yet generating real-time data,  
and so we hope to encourage and work with them so that 
they will be able to contribute for example, sea-level  
data, to a regional warning centre.   It’s well known that  
data sharing is critical, and so we will want every country 
who participates in the system to  
contribute Through the IOC 
coordination process, we hope to 
achieve this consensus opinion, as 
well as agree on where and how the 
regional centre will function.
Q. Is there a working group to  
see the proposed global early warning 
system through to its becoming 
operational in 2007?
The IOC will coordinate the regional 
effort inter-governmentally. But the 
regional effort has to be built on 
national efforts, with each country 
responsible for its own national system, built according  
to their particular seismology, organisational structures, 
culture, and ways of interpreting warnings. That’s a big job. 
The IOC, and particularly the ITIC, which I run, are of  
course ready and willing to assist in their efforts. 
Countries are moving very quickly to identify monitoring 
requirements and establish plans for communicating 
information to their peoples. That is a good sign that we  
will see a minimal system implemented in the next year or 
two.  But if that’s going to happen, it means a huge amount 
of work and resources. No one’s getting any sleep now.
Interview by Peter Coles
Paris (France)
© 
C
om
m
an
de
r 
Em
ily
 B
. 
C
hr
is
tm
an
, 
N
O
A
A
 C
or
ps
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
11
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
It was early afternoon on May 22, 1960, 
in the thriving port of Corral, southern 
Chile, when disaster struck. The town’s 
inhabitants were at first startled to see the sea 
rising and then disappearing: the water simply 
withdrew, leaving boats marooned on the mud 
of the sea floor. Just a few minutes later, the 
terrified inhabitants began to witness the return 
of the water, but this time in the shape of a 
gigantic wall that was decimating everything in 
its path. Thousands of people died that day on 
the shores of southern Chile and in lands as far 
away as Hawaii or Japan, for the giant wave (or 
“tsunami,” as the Japanese call it) travelled the 
entire Pacific Ocean, coast to coast.
That tragedy taught Chile a tough lesson, 
which bore fruit six years later via the 
creation of the Sistema Nacional de Alarma de 
Maremotos, or National Tidal Wave Warning 
System (SNAM). At the same time, UNESCO’s 
Chiloe Island (Chile) 
the day after the May 
22, 1960, tsunamiThe giant waves that 
devastated the Indian 
Ocean’s coastline clearly 
demonstrated the need 
to create at the global 
level a tsunami warning 
system similar to the one 
UNESCO established in 
1968 in the Pacific Ocean. 
CHILE: 
THE LESSONS OF 
A TRAGEDY
▲
© 
A
FP
, 
Pa
ri
s 
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
Tsunami Special
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission 
(IOC) was finalizing The International Pacific 
Tsunami Warning System, which now allows for 
direct communication with 26 separate member-
states, enabling warnings to be sent and received 
whenever emergencies arise in any part of the 
ocean.
In Chile, both of these tasks now fall to the 
Navy’s Hydrographic and Oceanographic Service 
(SHOA), based in Valparaíso, which employs 
advanced technology alongside a warning 
management system and public awareness-raising 
to ensure that the disaster of 1960 will never be 
repeated.
THREE REGIONAL CENTRES
Commander Roberto Garnham, director of the 
SHOA, explains that this system is working very 
effectively in the Pacific Ocean, and that much 
has been learnt from previous tragedies along 
the coastlines of both South America and Asia. 
The system, which relies on antennae stationed 
in every one of the member countries, is based 
around three regional centres - one in Hawaii, one 
in Alaska and a third in Chile – which together 
monitor and supervise events across the whole 
Pacific Ocean. In the case of Chile, this is carried 
out by a network of digital devices placed along 
the coast of Chile and its nearby islands, which 
keep tabs on abnormal variations in the sea level 
and in seismic activity. The system is triggered 
whenever a seismic event leads to a tsunami 
warning within the national territory, or whenever 
the Valparaiso centre receives a memo or a 
warning from the Pacific Tsunami Warning Centre.
When a warning is issued, the SHOA passed 
on the alert to a public agency called Onemi (the 
National Emergency Office), which immediately 
▲
© 
Sh
oa
, 
Va
lp
ar
ai
so
, 
C
hi
li 
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
13
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Buoy in Chile, a 
component of the 
Pacific Tsunami 
Warning System
activates the network that has been set up to 
organize contingency plans through direct radio 
contact with regional governments, which in 
turn relay information directly to provincial and 
community authorities. This network means that 
the whole country can be warned of a possible 
approaching tidal wave within five minutes or 
less.
Commander Garnham notes that the best 
way of knowing if an earthquake will produce a 
tsunami is the strength of the tremor: whether it is 
weak enough to allow someone to stay standing, 
or strong enough to force people on the ground 
to lose their balance. “If this happens, the best 
recommendation I can give is that people who live 
in the coastal zone should take a torch, batteries 
and a radio, and head for higher ground, which 
must be over 25 metres above sea level,” he says. 
Once the first alert is given, if the SHOA confirms 
that a tsunami wave has been produced, then the 
news is conveyed once again to Onemi, which can 
then determine the estimated time of arrival of the 
water for different parts of the country.
From that moment on, each affected community 
must put into practice its evacuation and civil 
defence plans. As part of these plans, the 
country’s 28 main ports have maps showing 
the areas that will be flooded in the event of 
a tsunami. Two of them, the northern cities of 
Arica and Antofagasta, have also set up helpful 
signposts, and keep their local populations 
regularly informed of emergency plans.
GLOBAL COOPERATION 
IS VITAL
While many districts have yet to put enough 
work into preparing their communities for a 
possible tsunami, the SHOA and Onemi continue 
to produce information and educational material. 
Above all else, these organizations stress that 
with sound evacuation plans and a well-informed 
and prepared population, over 90 percent of the 
members of any locality can be saved in the space 
of 10 to 15 minutes.
“The benefits of a tsunami warning 
system are so great that UNESCO, through its 
Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission, 
is intent on establishing a worldwide warning 
system. And we are ready to contribute our 
experience and our knowledge if they are 
needed,” declares Garnham, adding that the 
centre he heads operates 24 hours a day, 365 days 
a year.
Garnham observes that knowing which areas 
can be flooded can affect the value of land and 
tourist sites, as well as the possibilities for general 
development, but emphasizes that a much 
greater good is being served. “The world must 
acknowledge that certain events are adverse, 
and that they must be prepared for as Chile has 
already done. This country now has buildings 
made to resist earthquakes and flooding maps, 
which enable plans to be drawn up to protect 
local populations,” he concludes.
Emilio Lorca, head of SHOA’s geophysics 
department, warns for his part that it is not 
enough for one country to have a warning centre 
if this is not connected with others. “The system 
works precisely because it is interconnected with 
other locations that exchange information. If not, 
this would be useless,” he states.
Organizing a system such as the one across 
the Pacific Ocean is, of course, far from easy. 
Provisional estimates suggests that a similar 
emergency network in the Indian Ocean would 
need around $30 million, well-trained staff, a 
tailor-made communication system and a lot of 
time. “A system such as this can raise awareness 
of the risk of a tsunami, and that is very positive, 
because it helps countries to organize themselves 
and work in cooperation,” insists Lorca. 
According to this expert, the number of fatalities 
caused by the tsunami in South Asia would have 
been much lower if the region had benefited from 
a system like that operating across the Pacific.
Marcia Franque 
journalist from the daily “El Mercurio”, 
Valparaiso (Chile)
www.unesco.org/tsunami
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO in action communication
14
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
UNESCO’S CHANGING PARTNERSHIP 
WITH THE PRIVATE SECTOR
The idea came in 1999, at the World 
Economic Forum in Davos. 
United Nations Secretary General 
Kofi Annan invited the private sector to work 
with the UN. The Global Compact was launched, 
and a new relationship between business and 
multilateral organizations was born. Since 
then, the concept has developed, particularly 
in the field of information and communications 
technology (ICT), integral to achieving global 
Millennium Development Goals.
The new cooperation is also key to meeting the 
Education For All goals. As Mr Abhimanyu Singh, 
Director of UNESCO’s Division of International 
Coordination and Monitoring of EFA points out: 
“If we are to have a better chance of achieving 
the EFA goals, then it cannot be done without 
broadening the partnership to the private sector, 
globally and in-country.”
Elizabeth Longworth, Director 
of UNESCO’s Information Society 
Division, agrees. “The digital divide 
is one of the greatest obstacles to the 
fulfilment of UNESCO’s key mandate 
to help create, share, disseminate and 
preserve knowledge,” she said. 
UNESCO’s growing list of 
partnerships with ICT companies 
include Hewlett-Packard, Intel, 
Microsoft, Alcatel and Hitachi, 
and range from teacher syllabus 
programmes to community access 
centres, science networks and 
recording cultural heritage. The 
nature of the partnerships also varies, 
from more traditional sponsorship to 
strategic agreements where each side 
contributes individually and no money 
changes hands. 
STRATEGIC OBJECTIVES
So far, results from the field are impressive. 
Where UNESCO might have funds to train one 
teacher, a partnership in the same area with an 
IT company can enable 1,000 teachers to be 
trained. However, partnerships with business 
need to be carefully considered, particularly when 
commercial interests are at stake. “We can’t enter 
strategic partnerships for the sake of partnering 
with the private sector. There has to be a very 
strong strategic objective for UNESCO,” said Ms 
Longworth. While each agreement is different, 
all must fit within the Guidelines on Cooperation 
between the United Nations and the Business 
Community, issued by the Secretary-General in 
July 2000
In recent months, much attention has 
ICTs are key in 
reaching Millennium 
Goals
Once limited to sponsoring, partnerships between the private sector and 
UNESCO are now becoming more numerous and ambitious. Information 
and communications technology (ICT) are providing a special opportunity to 
experiment with a new form of cooperation with business.
© 
A
FP
, 
Pa
ri
s 
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
15
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
▲
been focused on two particularly high profile 
partnerships between UNESCO and the private 
sector: a Memorandum of Understanding 
with Intel and a Cooperation Agreement with 
Microsoft. These represent a new level of strategic 
engagement with the private sector, taking 
partnerships beyond the more traditional idea of 
funding and sponsorship to defining how to meet 
the needs of developing countries. While these 
new partnerships have attracted much media 
attention, not all reactions have been positive. In 
December 2004, the French newspaper Le Monde 
cited fears that such agreements were diluting 
UNESCO’s strong support for Free and Open 
Source Software (FOSS).
For Ms Longworth, such fears are are based on 
misunderstanding. In 2003, the World Summit 
for Information Society produced a Declaration 
of Principles and Action Plan stressing the 
need for all software, whether proprietary or 
non-proprietary, to be in a technology-neutral 
approach to development. To this end, Ms 
Longworth said UNESCO gives strong support to 
the development of free and open software. One 
example is the software “Moodle” in six branches 
of the Arab Open University.
GUIDED BY COMMON INTEREST 
IN SOCIAL PROGRESS
“Our mandate is about knowledge transfer,” Ms 
Longworth said. “We could argue that we are 
absolutely committed to open source and we have 
done a huge amount to promote this ideologically 
and practically.In an ideal world we would all use 
open source – it has low prices, it’s interoperable, 
there are lots of advantages. But if we are talking 
about immediate development we cannot always 
wait, and how can we tell developing countries 
they must only use open source where developed 
countries have a choice?” she asked.
Philipp Müller-Wirth, Specialist for Cooperation 
with the Private Sector at UNESCO, is acutely 
aware of the new challenges and opportunities 
for UNESCO in working with the private sector. 
When he arrived at the Organization in 1993, the 
idea of working with business extended to the 
latter contributing money through sponsorship 
programmes. Today, he facilitates a plethora of 
public-private partnerships, from L’Oréal’s high 
profile Women in Science programme to the 
Hewlett-Packard partnership to reduce brain drain 
in Southeast Europe. “In working with UNESCO, 
companies not only associate themselves with a 
legitimate image, but they obtain access to our 
networks which are often strong in countries 
where their structures are still weak,” he explains 
Though sometimes diverging, the interests 
of UNESCO and the private sector can also be 
common interests. UNESCO needs the private 
sector’s powerful influence and ability to leverage 
funds, while business benefits from better 
educated and trained populations.
 “The long-term interests of the private sector 
are the same as those of UNESCO. Both have a 
fundamental interest in sustainable development 
which allows people and their countries to 
achieve real social progress and prosperity,” 
stresses Wallace Baker, a senior partner in the law 
HP and UNESCO 
work to reduce “brain drain”
From 1990 to 2000, Southeastern 
European countries affected by the 
Balkans conflict lost intellectual 
capacity on a massive scale. 
Research indicates that up to 70 % 
of teaching and research jobs were 
lost in some university faculties. 
UNESCO’s partnership with 
Hewlett-Packard (HP), “Piloting 
Solutions for Alleviating Brain 
Drain”, implemented in seven 
universities in Albania, Bosnia 
and Herzegovina, Croatia, FYR 
of Macedonia, and Serbia and 
Montenegro, entails a three-step 
process of reconnecting faculties 
to the web, connecting scholars 
to international colleagues 
and university resources and, 
finally, identifying international 
partnerships and funding 
opportunities.
“Without the partnership,” 
says Michel Benard, HP University 
Relations Manager for Europe, the 
Middle East and Africa, “HP would 
not have had access to existing 
UNESCO’s higher education 
and scientific networks, both at 
governmental and institutional 
levels.”
Iulia Nechifor, Programme 
Specialist in Science Policy and 
Capacity-Building at UNESCO’s 
Venice office, said initial research 
indicated some positive signs of 
reversing brain drain. For example, 
in Croatia, some academics 
are  returning to their previous 
faculties, which offered them new 
opportunities.
According to Stamenka Uvalic-
Trumbic, Chief of UNESCO’s Section 
for Access, Mobility and Quality 
Assurance, Division of Higher 
Education, the partnership has not 
only strengthened scientific and 
educational capacity at national 
level but also re-established 
dialogue among young researchers 
and linked them to their research 
fellows abroad. Encouraged by 
these results, the Education Sector 
intends to replicate the project in 
Africa, a region heavily affected by 
massive brain drain.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
UNESCO in action communication
firm Baker and McKenzie, in his 2003 study on 
UNESCO.
This common interest is consistently cited by 
UNESCO’s ICT partners. For Microsoft, the digital 
divide will not diminish unless public and private 
organizations work together. Frank McCosker, 
Microsoft Senior Director of Global Strategic 
Accounts, said the ICT revolution had been one of 
the single biggest drivers of economic growth and 
prosperity ever witnessed: “By working together, 
we can most effectively reach our common 
goals to support regional and local economic 
development,” he said.
For Intel Foundation President Wendy Hawkins, 
the collaboration with UNESCO enables Intel 
to leverage the best practices developed via its 
professional development curriculum. Above all, it 
enables Intel, which has already trained 2 million 
teachers worldwide, to maximize its impact.
“The challenge of preparing all students to 
participate fully in the worldwide knowledge 
economy is a big one, and we believe it can be 
addressed most effectively through the cooperation 
of all interested parties,” Ms Hawkins said.
Kerry Elgar
Paris-based freelance journalist
Training teachers: 
Intel and UNESCO 
collaborate
In November 2004, Intel 
signed a Memorandum 
of Understanding with 
UNESCO to develop 
a syllabus for training 
teachers in the use of 
ICT in the classroom. 
Intel has become one 
of the key players in the 
area of teacher training 
and ICT.
For Intel, which has 
already invested US$ 1 
billion in primary and 
secondary education 
since 1989, and which 
has trained 2 million 
teachers worldwide in 
more than 50 countries, 
the agreement is an 
important step. As Intel 
Foundation President 
Wendy Hawkins said, 
“Our view is that public 
and private sectors share 
the same objective in 
this area – finding the 
best use of technology 
for improving the quality 
of teaching and learning 
around the world.  We 
all win when graduating 
students have the best 
possible preparation for 
the knowledge-based 
economy.”
Building bridges 
across the digital divide 
with Microsoft
The global Cooperation 
Agreement between UNESCO 
and Microsoft was signed 
in Paris last Novermber 17 
by  Director-General Koichiro 
Matsuura and Microsoft 
Chairman Bill Gates. 
It covers areas including 
ICT’s and education (a standard 
syllabus for teacher training); 
training for disadvantaged 
youth and adults; and the 
development of on-line 
communities of practice among 
many other areas of mutual 
interest. Certain “UNESCO 
Knowledge Communities” will 
be founded on a new Microsoft 
platform which offers a rich 
set of functions for online 
collaboration and knowledge 
management. As Axel Plathe, a 
Senior Program Specialist with 
UNESCO’s Information Society 
Division, explains, the platform 
has many advantages, including 
the creation of a virtual space 
“where civil society can gather 
like a café or a marketplace to 
speak about issues”.
In several of the projects 
envisaged, work will feed into 
existing UNESCO programmes. 
Some of the work is already 
underway, such as teacher 
training and the E-learning 
initiative now available through 
UNESCO’s portals. Others, 
including programmes for 
refurbishing old computers 
and the Sub-Regional Resource 
Centre to support Youth 
Information and Learning 
Structures in the North African 
Arab States, are currently in the 
planning phase.
Dr Tarek Shawki, UNESCO’s 
Regional Communication and 
Information Advisor for the Arab 
States, believes that staunch 
defenders of Free and Open 
Source Software (FOSS) are 
missing the point when they 
criticize UNESCO’s work with 
proprietary software companies. 
“UNESCO has very limited 
programmes resources and in 
order to have any real impact 
we have to revolutionize our 
execution modalities,” he 
explains.
While very supportive of 
open source programs (he 
facilitates three of them through 
the Cairo office), he believes 
in pragmatism. “To make it a 
religious matter is a mistake; 
it’s whatever works best for 
our Member States,” he said. 
“It is important to understand 
that we are not biased towards 
Microsoft, we are simply 
coordinating our efforts in areas 
of mutual interest. Our value is 
as a neutral broker agency.”
Microsoft agrees. Says Frank 
McCosker, Senior Director of 
Global Strategic Accounts, 
“As an international corporate 
citizen of conscience, Microsoft 
is committed to initiatives 
throughout the world that seek 
to create social change and to 
expand opportunities through 
greater access to ICTs.”
▲
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
17
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
This Indian Ocean 
island is named 
Tromelin, after the 
survivors’ rescuer
THE SHIPWRECKED MEMORY 
OF THE UTILE SLAVES
On July 31, 1761, the French 
ship L’Utile is shipwrecked on 
a tiny island in the Indian 
Ocean. Not long after, the sailors 
manage to reach Madagascar, 
but they leave behind the 
Malgache slaves they had 
embarked illegally on L’Utile. 
Only a handful of survivors 
remain when they are found 
15 years later, in 1776. UNESCO 
has reopened this lost chapter  
in the history of the slave trade.
A corvette drops anchor near a small 
island, lost in the Indian Ocean, on 
November 29, 1776. The island seems 
completely deserted, a stretch of white sand 
with a few palm trees. Yet the sailors discover a 
baby and seven women, all former slaves from 
Madagascar. Dressed in tunics of woven feathers, 
they are the only survivors of a shipwreck 15 
years earlier. They survived by eating birds, turtles 
and shellfish.
Max Guérout, former French navy officer and 
vice-president of France’s marine archaeology 
research group, GRAN, tells the story: “L’Utile left 
Bayonne in southwest France for the Mascarene 
Islands on November 17, 1760. It called at 
Madagascar to replenish food supplies, and the 
captain, Commander La Fargue, decided to take 
aboard 60 slaves, against the governor’s orders. 
He set sail for the Ile de France, now Mauritius. 
Blown off course by the bad weather, the ship 
was wrecked on the reefs of a small island, one 
▲
UNESCO in action culture
Training teachers: 
Intel and UNESCO 
collaborate
© MERCIER Thierry/Météo-France 
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
18
kilometer square, which now bears the name 
of the man who saved the last few survivors: 
Tromelin.”
A “relation”, one of the gazettes sold on the 
street in those days, gave details of the shipwreck: 
“Traversing a host of dangers, most of the 
crew finally succeeded in reaching the island. 
Almost all were injured, maimed and covered 
in bruises; they were specters rather than men.” 
At the beginning of their exile, the survivors 
salvaged wood from the wreck as well as tools 
and supplies: “a few kegs of brandy and a few 
barrels of flour.” They built a forge and dug two 
wells, “the thick white milky liquid” from the 
first proving to be toxic. In spite of the hostile 
environment, food was not a major problem. All 
they needed to do was catch one of the 500-kilo 
sea turtles that lived on the island.
ABANDONED, FORGOTTEN, 
FINALLY RESCUED
Just two months after the wreck, the survivors 
managed to build a boat. “Preparations were 
made for an imminent departure on the night of 
the 26th to the 27th of September,” according to 
the gazette. “All hands worked feverishly… they 
were able to move the boat along rollers, despite 
several accidents and unrelenting terror…Finally 
it was launched, held by an anchor salvaged from 
the wreck.” But not all the shipwreck victims 
were invited aboard the “Providence”, name given 
to the vessel. “The 122 French sailors boarded 
hopefully, arms around each other so they 
could all fit, with a small amount of food. The 
blacks, whom they were forced to leave behind, 
maintained an oppressive silence.”
About 60 men and women stayed on the island, 
with a “writ testifying to their services” and the 
promise that the sailors would return to 
rescue them. As for the French sailors, 
they reached Madagascar a few days 
later, and continued to Mauritius where 
they made a report on the shipwreck 
and the slaves. “The governor of the 
Ile de France was so angry at the late 
captain La Fargue for having disobeyed 
his orders by taking slaves aboard the 
Utile that he refused to send a ship to 
get them,” says Max Guérout. “On the 
day the crew arrived, he wrote, ‘Today 
the Utile survivors arrived. The captain 
has died. Good for him.’” Yet it was the 
slaves who paid for his transgression.
After waiting in vain for two years, the 
desperate survivors built a raft and 18 of them 
sailed for home. We do not know if they made it. 
We do know is that the second attempt at escape, 
10 years later, failed. A French sailor was on the 
second raft, and had they succeeded, he would 
have produced a written account.
In 1773 or 1774, when the Utile shipwreck 
victims were long forgotten, a passing ship 
spotted signs of life on the Ile de Sable. The new 
governor dispatched the vessel the Sauterelle to 
the rescue, but it failed in its attempt to approach 
the little coral island, surrounded by waters 4000 
meters deep. Two sailors headed for shore in a 
canoe, but smashed up against a reef. One sailor 
managed to swim back to the ship, the other was 
left on the island. According to the women who 
were finally rescued, the sailor and the last three 
male survivors then built a raft. The four men, 
with three of the women, sailed away from the 
island. They were never seen again.
Another two expeditions failed before the 
corvette La Dauphine finally arrived, on 
November 29 1776. The Chevalier de Tromelin, a 
royal navy officer, was its captain. What happened 
when he met the last survivors, and where is his 
report?  Hard to say, because “It’s mentioned in 
the archives, but I can’t get my hands on it,” says 
Max Guérout, who is trying to trace the officer’s 
descendants in Lorient, in southern Brittany.
So far, much of the historical research linked 
to these events has been fruitful, due largely 
to UNESCO’s financial support. More than 100 
documents have been examined in several cities 
in France, notably Bayonne, where the ship was 
commissioned. Genealogical research has begun 
to find descendants of the Utile sailors; more is 
planned on Mauritius, where Tromelin took the 
seven women and the little boy. 
GENEALOGICAL RESEARCH
This historical research is one of three dimensions 
of the “Forgotten Slaves” programme launched 
by the GRAN, as part of the International Year 
for the Commemoration of the Struggle Against 
Slavery and its Abolition (2004), and of UNESCO’s 
Slave Route Programme. (http://www.unesco.
org/culture/dialogue/slave).  Inspired by the story 
of the Utile, “Forgotten Slaves” aims to conduct 
historical and archaeological research to elucidate 
every aspect of this terrible event, representative 
of the slave trade. It will also serve as part of an 
information campaign targeting the media, the 
▲
UNESCO in action culture
An account of 
supplies the Utile 
took on board when 
it left Bayonne 
(French Navy 
Archives)
© 
M
. 
G
ué
ro
ut
/A
rc
hi
ve
s 
na
ti
on
al
es
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
19
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Map of Île de Sable, 
drawn after the 
Utile’s shipwreck 
(French National 
Archives)
general public and schools, to raise awareness 
of issues surrounding slavery.  Software called 
“I-maj”, recently launched on GRAN’s website 
(http://www.archeonavale.org/) allows partners 
to write, edit and post texts approved by the 
project’s supervisors. 
A group of 17 children from a primary school 
in Brittany (France) are the first partners in 
this category. The school is not far from the 
Tromelin family manor, and the pupils are 
focusing on the Chevalier’s life. Guérout looks 
forward to extending the network of schools to 
Reunion Island, Polynesia and Martinique and to 
forming partnerships with UNESCO’s Associated 
Schools Project Network and the 90 schools in 
SEED (Schlumberger Excellence in Educational 
Development Programme) in New York.
Finally, an exceptional adventure will begin 
in 2006 with the archeological phase of the 
“Forgotten Slaves” project. A dozen archeologists, 
divers, scientists and doctors are off to Tromelin 
Island for a 25-day land and underwater survey.
“It’s a complicated operation,” says Guérout. 
“Tromelin is not a tourist destination. There are 
no flights and access by sea is particularly risky 
because of whirlpools, currents and breakers.”
Where there’s a will, there’s a way. On the 
island, the GRAN will try to locate the old camps, 
the forge, the well and the only permanent 
building dating back that far, a shelter for the 
fire. “There’s a theory that they kept the fire 
going for 15 years,” says Guérout. “That does not 
seem very likely, given the trade winds and the 
frequent hurricanes.” The doctor looking after the 
team will also do physical anthropology research 
should they find burial places.
Underwater, the team will explore the wreck, 
and also vast sedimentary basins, which 
according to Guérout “are a sort of receptacle at a 
depth of six or seven meters, into which objects 
may have fallen”. Pieces of ceramic have already 
been found washed up on the shore. Each little 
fragment is significant to recreate the history of 
the forgotten slaves, who are now being rescued 
from oblivion.
Jasmina Sopova
For more information:
http://www.unesco.org/culture/ 
dialogue/slave>
http://www.archeonavale.org
1. The island is still 
today home to a large 
colony of sea turtles, 
and has been listed 
as a natural reserve. 
Its “green turtle” 
is an endangered 
species and protected 
since 1981 by 
the Washington 
Convention (1975). 
© 
M
. 
G
ué
ro
ut
/A
rc
hi
ve
s 
na
ti
on
al
es
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO in action education
20
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Once regarded as the best universities 
in the region, Iraqi universities are 
today in a pitiful state. A round 
table focusing on revitalising higher 
education in Iraq, organized by 
UNESCO, was held in February in Paris. 
Its goals: evaluate the situation and 
define future needs.
In 2003 when the coalition forces moved in, 
Iraqi universities were already reduced 
to a pale shadow of their former selves. 
Gone was the time that they had established close 
ties with British universities, in the years before 
the Iran-Iraq war. Thousands of Iraqis studied for 
their doctorates at universities across the UK.
The flow stopped almost overnight. Iraqi 
academics quickly became isolated in a precarious 
university system where political allegiance was 
as important as intellectual competence. Many 
left, either because of political differences with 
Saddam Hussein’s regime or because the career 
opportunities were better overseas. Now, as 
democracy flickers into life and international aid 
for the stricken university system at last begins 
to be felt on the ground, the Diaspora is being 
encouraged to return.
PRECARIOUS FUTURE FOR 
IRAQI UNIVERSITIES
© 
Sa
m
ir
 M
iz
ba
n/
A
P/
Si
pa
, 
Pa
ri
s 
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
21
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
▲
At Baghdad’s 
Mustansiriyah 
University, lab 
equipment  
is rudimentary
The country needs its elite more than ever. 
The universities, struggling to cope with a 
massive infrastructure deficit, are bulging with 
students. The situation is all the more critical 
as two Gulf wars have also contributed to 
damaging the system. Idris Salih, Iraq’s deputy 
minister for higher education, told a round table 
meeting in Paris convened by UNESCO’s higher 
education division that 85% of the universities’ 
infrastructure was destroyed in the months of 
chaos as the coalition struggled to gain control.
In any case, reconstruction is clearly going to be 
founded as much on Iraqi as on imported know-
how. After the fall of the old regime, USAid put 
together a $20 million strategy based on consortia 
of US universities with partner universities in Iraq. 
A few weeks later, Qatar launched a $15 million 
project to revitalise the universities as part of a 
$100 million reconstruction plan. But Mr Salih 
says: “We were unable to benefit from financial 
resources from donors because they arrived late or 
were not paid at all.”
PROBLEMS WITH AID DELIVERY 
AND SECURITY
Progress on the ground has been limited, 
partly because of security issues. The USAid 
programme was predicated on the inclusion 
of non-US universities in the partnerships, but 
only a small number joined up. Only Oxford 
University represented the UK, as a partner with 
the State University of New York Stony Brook 
in a consortium for rebuilding Archeology, 
Assyriology, and Environmental Health. But 
Oxford’s involvement ended with the tragic death 
of the one academic who was pivotal to the 
project.
Some countries, notably the UK through the 
British Council and Germany through DAAD, have 
given direct assistance in the form of intensive 
training courses for university administrators 
and updating opportunities for academics in 
economically and socially strategic fields.
UNESCO has already drawn on some of 
the Qatari US$15 million to send medical and 
engineering laboratory equipment and textbooks. 
At the end of 2004, a shipment of US$4.6 million 
of equipment and materials for medical and 
related disciplines such as dentistry, pharmacy 
and nursing, as well as for engineering faculties, 
was delivered to universities in Iraq. It also 
included textbooks for students and reference 
books valued at a further US$1 million. Ten tons 
of books were delivered by the British Council to 
universities in Baghdad and Basra. 
New pledges were announced from Qatar 
and the Republic of Korea during the Paris 
conference. The First Lady of Qatar, Sheikha 
Mozah Bint Nasser Al-Misand, who is a Special 
UNESCO Envoy for Basic and Higher Education, 
pledged a further US$1 million dollars; Korea 
pledged US$200,000; and the Doha Bank pledged 
US$30,000.
“These donations are warmly appreciated and 
will be used for the implementation of concrete 
projects for the benefit of students, academics 
and researchers,” Mr Koichiro Matsuura, 
UNESCO’s Director-General, said. But that 
depends on promised aid being delivered. In 
February one Iraqi university president privately 
estimated that barely 10% of the resources 
pledged had materialised on the ground. The 
amount is not sufficient to stem the brain drain 
affecting Iraq. Numerous Iraqi academics leave 
in search of opportunities closed to them in their 
own country. One initiative to be taken further is 
to encourage the Iraqi academic Diaspora to be 
encouraged to return, through temporary leave of 
absence from universities elsewhere in the Middle 
East or in the West.
Salaries are being increased – from A$150-400 
a month to A$1,000-1,500. But the most severe 
disincentive is the security situation. Baghdad 
University president Mosa Al-Mosawe said that 
since the fall of the old regime 47 academics 
had been assassinated – 17 of them from his 
own university. Kidnapping for ransom is rife 
– “the threats come from lazy students to get 
some finance, especially near the time of final 
assessments”.
BRAIN DRAIN
Mr Salih said that more than 2,000 academics 
had left Iraq under the old regime. Since its fall 
a further 260 have followed them “The 19,000 
[who remain] are heroes working under difficult 
conditions – lack of electricity, power cuts every 
day, terrorism and the fear of terrorism that 
weighs on them every day,” he says. But whether 
academics who have relocated to countries where 
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
secularism is the norm would return to an Islamist 
university system to teach segregated classes is 
highly questionable.
Meanwhile some experts question whether it is 
sensible to rebuild the system along the lines left 
by the previous regime. Some universities, created 
to serve political rather than academic needs, 
demand vast injections of resources to enable 
them to offer quality higher education. But are 
they worth the investment? Jairam Reddy, who 
guided South African universities’ emergence from 
the apartheid era, has recommended a critical 
appraisal to determine whether unsustainable 
institutions should be shored up, or efforts 
concentrated on bringing stronger universities 
back to their former levels. Georges Haddad, 
director of UNESCO’s Higher Education Division,, 
was upbeat about the prospects. “It is important 
for us to have a strong, democratic Iraq…Without 
higher education there is no future. I do not 
expect the moon but it is important that the 
dialogue is started and partnership is under way,” 
he said.
UNESCO in action education
MOVE QUOTE
As the round table wrapped up its proceedings 
there was a clear acceleration of pledges of 
support – the inclusion of Iraqi academic 
leaders within the world university community, 
scholarships and exchanges.
Mr Salih concluded: “Higher education 
needs more help – this is the key to the future 
in building a new Iraq based on multi-party 
democracy and respect for human rights.”.
Since then, a real dynamic has taken form 
around the projects initiated by the round 
table and the Higher Education Division is 
receiving offers of cooperation from institutions, 
governments and other donors.
David Jobbins
Journalist, Times Higher Education 
Supplement
At Baghdad 
University, a black 
banner recalls 
the names of slain 
teachers
▲
© Samir Mizban/AP/Sipa, Paris 
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
23
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Montreal World Book 
Capital City
On April 23, 2005, World Book and 
Copyright Day, UNESCO named 
Montreal the “World Book Capital 
City 2005-2006”. It is the fifth city 
to receive the honour, after Madrid 
(2001), Alexandria (2002), New Delhi 
(2003) and Antwerp last year. The 
selection committee is made up of 
representatives of the International 
Publishers Associations (IPA-UIE), 
the International Booksellers 
Federation (IBF), the International 
Federation of Library Associations 
and Institutions (IFLA), and 
UNESCO. This year the committee’s 
selection was made in recognition 
of the quality of Montreal’s 
programmes to promote books  
and reading, and of the dedication 
of all players in the book industry. 
The city’s literary scene is, 
moreover, extremely vibrant and 
situated at the crossroads of diverse 
cultures: English, native, Caribbean, 
French, Hispanic and Asian. All 
means of communication will be 
used to celebrate the special year 
of books, with a selection of 200 
works of fiction evoking Montreal 
in libraries, bookshops, and on the 
internet. Festivals and exhibitions 
will take place throughout 2005. At 
the close of the event, which will 
also include cultural exchanges with 
cities such as Barcelona, Hiroshima, 
Turin and Shanghai, an International 
Copyright Symposium will be held, 
bringing together 300 publishers and 
specialists in April 2006.
UNESCO in brief
World Heritage  
in Images
Thanks to the high 
definition images and 
sounds of Japanese 
television channel NHK, 
it is now possible to view 
brief documentaries on 
10 World Heritage sites 
on UNESCO’s website. 
The partnership between 
NHK and UNESCO 
builds on state-of-the-art 
digital visual and sound 
processing technologies. 
The images were selected, 
adapted and made 
accessible on the web 
by UNESCO. In the long 
term, these documentaries 
are expected to cover 
all World Heritage 
sites, as well as all 
cultural expressions and 
spaces protected by the 
International Convention 
for the Safeguarding of 
the Intangible Cultural 
Heritage. Concurrently, 
a data-base system will 
allow such images to 
be used for various 
projects, such as DVD 
and other audio-visual 
package operations, 
public exhibitions, new 
types of exhibition using 
virtual reality systems, 
and production of quality 
replicas for exhibition and 
academic purposes. An 
advisory committee has 
been formed to ensure 
the project’s quality, 
headed by Professor 
Ikuo Hirayama, UNESCO 
goodwill ambassador.
For more information: 
www.portal.unesco.
org/culture
Campaign against Racism
“All equal in diversity: 
mobilizing schools against 
racism, discrimination and 
exclusion”: that was the slogan 
of UNESCO’s campaign on 
March 21, to mark International 
Day for the Elimination of 
Racial Discrimination. Schools 
belonging to UNESCO’s 
Associated Schools Project 
Network in countries 
participating in the “Breaking the 
Silence” Transatlantic Slave Trade 
(TST) Education Project signed 
up for the initiative, launched 
at the International TST Youth 
Forum in Port of Spain (Trinidad 
and Tobago). It is a follow-up 
activity to the International Year 
to Commemorate the Struggle 
against Slavery and its Abolition, 
celebrated in 2004. It is also 
a new point of departure for 
a series of actions and joint 
activities with other ASPnet 
schools.
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/J
ea
n 
O
’S
ul
liv
an
 
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/D
om
in
iq
ue
 R
og
er
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
At the opening of the 
International Conference 
on Biodiversity: Science 
and Governance, held at 
UNESCO January 24 to 
28 2005, French president 
Jacques Chirac called upon 
the international community 
to create an “international 
group on the evolution of 
biodiversity”. More than 
7000 animal species and 
some 60,000 plant species 
are in fact threatened, 
according to the World 
Conservation Union (IUCN). 
Koïchiro Matsuura, Director-
General of UNESCO, 
declared to the audience, 
including a number of other 
heads of state, that “The 
accumulation of knowledge 
must go hand in hand 
with the establishment 
of systems for observing 
and preventing ecological 
and social dynamics.” 
This is the function of 
UNESCO programmes such 
as the Intergovernmental 
Oceanographic Commission 
(IOC) and MAB (Man 
and the Biosphere). 
Madagascar’s President 
Ravalomanana pointed out 
that in his country, “85 
percent of our 12,000 plants 
are unique in the world”. 
He went on to present the 
“Madagascar, naturally” 
national plan, underlining 
that “At the present rate, we 
predict that more than half 
of the coral reef areas will 
be lost in the next 30 years.”
Biodiversity 
threatenedPhysics Honored
In the context of the World 
Year of Physics, proclaimed by 
the United Nations in 2005, 
UNESCO hosted a conference 
from January 13 to 15 entitled 
“Physics for tomorrow”, in 
which eight Nobel Prize winners 
participated. More than 1200 
participants, 600 of them 
students, followed the debates. 
All year long, events aimed 
at the general public will take 
place all over the world. The 
initiative aims to present the 
discipline as something other 
that a daunting school subject. 
Exactly 100 years after Einstein’s 
discoveries, physics allows us to 
find solutions to major problems 
faced by our society, particularly 
in the areas of energy, 
environment and health. The 
World Year of Physics also aims 
to counteract students’ current 
disinterest in physics, which 
particularly affects developing 
countries.
For more information: www.
wyp2005.org 
Educational Websites 
Win Prizes
In March, the website of the 
Puente Alto library centre 
in Chili, www.biblioninos.
cl, created by Cristian 
Maturana, won first prize in 
a contest to find the “best 
educational web portals 
in Latin America and the 
Caribbean”. Organized by 
the Information Society 
Programme for Latin 
America and the Caribbean 
(INFOLAC) and supported 
by UNESCO’s office in 
Quito (Ecuador), the 
contest received 180 entries. 
The jury was composed 
of multidisciplinary 
professionals with 
experience in on-line 
publishing. The sites 
« Museo de los Niños 
de Caracas-Venezuela » 
(Children’s Museum, 
www.curiosikid.com) 
and “Colombia Aprende” 
(Know Colombia, www.
colombiaaprende.edu.co) 
received second and third 
prizes. For the 2006 edition, 
the INFOLAC contest will 
give awards to the best 
museum websites in the 
region.
UNESCO in brief
Atlases for Somalia
A 32-page atlas on Somalia and bordering countries, An Atlas for 
Somalis, was published in February in Somali and English. Produced 
jointly by the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) and 
UNESCO’s PEER programme, it comes with a calendar for the year 
and a canvas map of the region. The initiative was created within 
the framework of cooperation between UNESCO’s Nairobi (Kenya) 
office and the European Union. With financing of three million euros 
over two years, the programme aims to support a certain number of 
educational establishments by providing them notably with books 
and educational materials.
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/A
SP
ne
t/
M
SC
 V
al
do
 J
os
e 
To
rr
es
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
25
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
UNESCO Helps Media
The Bureau of UNESCO’s International 
Programme for the Development of 
Communication (IPDC) will give 
US$1,050,000 million to 51 media 
projects in developing countries 
and countries in transition. The 
announcement was made at its 
meeting at UNESCO headquarters 
March 7 – 9, 2005. Projects include 
broadcast, print and electronic media, 
as well as training programmes. 
Among them is a project to enable 
radio stations in the Indonesian 
province of Aceh, severely damaged 
by last December’s tsunami, to resume 
operations. 
The sum of US$319,000 was 
channelled to 13 projects in Africa. 
Three Palestinian projects will be 
funded, including a literary audio 
library to serve for radio broadcasts 
and general educational programmes 
and to provide access to literature to 
the blind.
Proposals this year concerned a 
total of 112 projects, submitted by 
media organizations in 62 developing 
countries and 26 regional media 
organizations. Since its creation in 
1980 the programme has supported 
over 1,000 projects in 137 countries.
For more information: www.unesco.
org/webworld/ipdc
Education for All 
Week
Citizens’ Radio  
in India
Millions of students and adults transmitted 
life-sized cardboard and paper cut-outs 
representing children out of school to their 
respective governments during Education 
for All Week (April 24-30). Entitled “Send 
My Friend to School”, the operation aimed 
to call the attention of politicians all over 
the world to the plight of 105 million out-
of-school children and 860 million illiterate 
adults, a majority of them women and girls. 
The campaign also stressed the importance 
of gender parity in school.
For more information:
www.unesco.org/education/efa/fr/index.
shtml
Namma Dhwani (“Our Voice”), a community 
radio broadcasting in southern India, played 
a pivotal role in a local election last March. 
Supported by UNESCO’s International 
Programme for the Development of 
Communication (IPDC), the station aired a 
series of special programmes on the elections. 
And voters expressed their opinions. The 
majority of people questioned asked that 
candidates “not try to bribe people to vote for 
them”. Sensitive subjects such as corruption 
and violence during the voting were raised 
through radio plays and songs. In the course 
of previous elections, there was no media 
coverage of the voting process and results were 
announced by the authorities. This time, the 
coverage was live.
Using his mobile telephone, a journalist from 
the station updated listeners every 15 minutes 
on voting results. His comments were relayed 
over loudspeakers in nearby villages. When 
it was all over, the election’s biggest winners 
were Namma Dhwani, its audience and good 
governance.
© 
St
an
is
la
s,
 F
ra
nc
e
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/T
or
be
n 
B
ra
nd
t 
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ic
he
l R
av
as
sa
rd
 
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ic
he
l R
av
as
sa
rd
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
PROJECTING THE PLANET INTO THE FUTURE
•    Baltic Sea: Introduction to Nature 101   p. 32
•   Japanese pupils first in prevention   p. 35
•     The San: Sustainable Development before its time    p. 38
•    A biosphere reserve teams up with green tourism    p. 41
•    Raising the curtain on AIDS    p. 44
•   Chiapas women invest in the future    p.47
•    Education for Sustainable Development on line    p. 50
© 
M
ic
ha
el
 R
ey
no
ld
s/
EP
A
/S
ip
a,
 P
ar
is
 
Decade of Education for Sustainable Development (2005–2014)
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
27
 “Do jeans grow on trees?” The question is 
ludicrous, but that is the point, to fire the 
children’s imagination and make them think 
about their clothes: what they are made of, where 
they come from and where they end up... From 
there, the children are encouraged to think up 
stories inspired by the process that produced their 
sports shoes or their jacket. 
The idea for this kind of role-playing is included 
in an educational pack distributed by the German 
Commission for UNESCO to almost 300 schools 
that belong to the Associated Schools Project 
▲
Report planned and prepared by Agnès Bardon
At a Beijing (China) 
dump, recyclable 
materials are 
salvaged for resale
PROJECTING THE PLANET INTO THE FUTURE
Network (ASPnet), ranging from pre-school to 
secondary establishments. The aim is to raise 
awareness among young people about sustainable 
development, starting by taking a look at their daily 
lives. The approach is original because sustainable 
development has failed to find a place in most 
school curricula.
Yet since sustainable development first emerged in 
1987, the idea has made headway, as demonstrated 
by the current popularity of fair trade, organic food 
and ethical investments. Even more significantly, 
the 2004 Nobel Prize was awarded to the militant 
Kenyan ecologist Wangari Maathi “for her 
contribution to sustainable development”.
FOCUSED ON HUMAN BEHAVIOUR
Intended to meet “the needs of the present without 
compromising the ability of future generations to 
meet their own needs”, according to the definition 
of the United Nations Commission chaired in 1987 
by Gro Harlem Brundtland, sustainable development 
requires that the environment be taken into 
consideration when shaping development policy. 
It encompasses economic and social dimensions, 
as was stated during the Johannesburg Summit in 
2002, as well as cultural aspects (see box p. 30). 
Furthermore, the prevention of natural catastrophes, 
the fight against HIV/AIDS, water management and 
even reducing poverty are all linked to the concept 
of sustainable development.
“Unlike education about the environment, 
which is focused on preserving natural resources, 
sustainable development is centred on man,” 
says Claude Villeneuve, director of the eco-
consultancy chair at the University of Quebec 
at Chicoutimi (Canada). And it is humankind, 
being asked to change its behaviour, that is at the 
heart of the Decade of Education for Sustainable 
Development (2005-2014). UNESCO was among 
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
the first organizations to undertake an examination 
of the relationship between humans and their 
environment, with the launch in 1972 of the Man 
and the Biosphere (MAB) programme.
It is a mammoth task. The destruction of 
ecosystems and the rapid consumption of natural 
resources threaten human wellbeing in the medium-
term future. For example, the amount of water 
available per capita has decreased from 12,900 m3 
in 1970 to less than 7,000 m3 today and is expected 
to fall to 5,100 m3 by 2025. Another worrying 
statistic is that 17 of the world’s biggest fishing 
zones have reached or exceeded their natural limits, 
according to the Food and Agriculture Organization 
(FAO). And it is primarily the developing countries 
which pay the price; poor people in rural areas 
“tend to be more directly dependent” on services 
from ecosystems according to the Millennium 
Ecosystem Assessment report (see Box p. xx).
But merely knowing that the planet is under 
threat is not enough to change people’s attitudes on 
a daily basis. The knowledge has to be taken into 
consideration. “Research on the habits of consumers 
tells us that the correlation between awareness and 
action is low. Most people agree with the idea that 
we should all save energy, but most people don’t do 
it,” says Clayton White who teaches education for 
sustainable development at the Peace University in 
Costa Rica. Studies in industrialised countries show 
that only 5% of consumers have adopted a lifestyle 
compatible with sustainable development.
FROM WORDS TO ACTION
Pleas for consumers to adopt a more responsible 
attitude seem to fall on deaf ears. “The messages 
from governments exhorting people to use their cars 
less or to avoid buying products which cause severe 
damage to the environment do not work. You will 
only have limited success by making people feel 
guilty about their lifestyle and their buying habits,” 
Klaus Toepfer, the director of the United Nations 
Environment Programme (UNEP), said in 2003.
In this context, education has a key role to play. 
But sustainable development, because it concerns 
our production methods as much as our transport, 
food or construction, cannot be taught as if it were a 
subject like biology or algebra.
“It is less about a prescribed body of knowledge 
and more about concrete exploration of issues. 
Education for sustainable development needs to 
▲
2005-2014: 
A Decade for Change
The four priority axes of action for the Decade of Education 
for Sustainable Development aim to:
Promote basic education
It will not be enough to reinforce 
literacy and numeracy to 
make significant progress in 
sustainable development. 
Efforts must also have impact 
on the content and methods of 
education and its adaptation 
to the cultural context. 
Basic education must also 
encourage and support people’s 
involvement in community life 
and decision-making.
Reorient and revise education 
programs 
Programmes must be 
restructured from nursery school 
to university to include explicitly 
the study and comprehension 
of problems linked to the social, 
economic, environmental 
and cultural sustainability 
of our planet, emphasizing 
interdisciplinary 
approaches.
Develop public understanding 
and awareness
While the concept of sustainable 
development is now familiar 
in institutional, academic and 
specialized milieus, it still needs 
to be spread at the grass-roots 
level. All sectors of society must 
be targeted.
Provide practical training
All trained, informed people 
can play an active role: this is 
a basic precept of sustainable 
development. Specific training 
must be provided through 
scientific and technological 
education, but also with the help 
of partners in the world of work, 
particularly in business and 
industry.
The quantity of water 
available per capita 
has decreased from 
12,900 m3 in 1970 to 
less than 7000 today
▲
Continued p. 30
© 
Te
xi
er
/S
ip
a,
 P
ar
is
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
29
“As much a 
philosophy as an 
academic concept”
Aline Bory-Adams is head of the Division  
of Education for Sustainable Development  
at UNESCO. 
Education for Sustainable Development  
(ESD) is often talked about, but making it a 
reality is problematic. Why is that?
It’s true that the notion of ESD was 
originally promoted from outside the 
education sector.  I would also add 
that after the Rio Summit the term 
‘sustainable’ was not easily translated 
into every language and hence not 
understood by all.  However, it is clear 
that education is indeed at the heart 
of sustainable development.  Since 
Johannesburg, the concept seems to 
more easily understood, particularly if we 
refer to some glaring issues such as lack 
of clean water, the spread of HIV-AIDS, 
high population and the management 
of natural resources. ESD is about the 
interconnectedness of all of these issues. 
With time, understanding of the concept 
has grown, and that’s why the movement 
is picking up momentum. 
How can we make ESD a reality?
ESD is not just an academic concept, 
but also a philosophy and way of life. As 
long as people have not inculcated the 
understanding of how they can contribute 
on an individual level towards ESD, it 
cannot be a success. Some years back, 
the UN Commission on Sustainable 
Development (UNCSD) had identified 
over 20 sustainability issues that, if not 
adequately addressed in the next two to 
three decades would create problems 
with possibly irreversible consequences.  
It is this awareness and sense of 
responsibility that ESD must inculcate 
through learners worldwide.
What is UNESCO’s expertise in this domain?
UNESCO has a long experience of 
examining the relationship between 
humanity and the environment. In 
addition to playing the role of lead 
agency for the Decade, UNESCO plans 
to develop its own strategy for the 
next ten years. The Organization will 
work towards increasing the attention 
given to sustainable development by 
school curricula and textbooks. We are 
considering launching studies to evaluate 
SD’s place in educational systems around 
the world. The Asia-Pacific region, for 
instance, is going to conduct studies 
on the topic and their results will guide 
future initiatives.
How would you respond to certain  
developing countries who maintain that 
education for sustainable development  
is not a priority?
ESD is applicable at every level of 
learning in developing countries. When 
farmers in rural areas learn to read  
and write, they can better understand 
how to read fertilizer and pesticide labels, 
for instance, to reduce the risk to personal 
and environmental health, and to use  
this know-how for sound decisions  
at the community level. .  A skills-based 
lower secondary level education in a 
rural context might be able to respond 
to alternative off-farm employment, or 
enhance marketing skills for handicrafts 
or organic foods. However, I must make 
clear that simply increasing the access 
and level of education in societies does 
not mean that ESD is happening.  The 
increase in level of education must be 
coupled with the quality of education that 
nurtures critical thinking skills. ESD is  
as much about personal development as 
it is about the community.
Environmental 
education class in 
Brazil
© 
M
ar
c 
D
ev
ill
e/
G
am
m
a 
Pa
ri
s 
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Sustainable 
Development: 
Six Key Dates
1968 
UNESCO organized the 
first intergovernmental 
conference aiming to 
reconcile environment and 
development. It led to the 
creation of UNESCO’s Man 
and the Biosphere (MAB) 
Programme. 
1987 
The World Commission 
on Environment 
and Development, 
presided by Gro Harlem 
Brundtland, used the 
expression “sustainable 
development” for 
the first time in its 
report, “Our Common 
Future”. The concept, 
at first emphasizing 
the environment, 
has encompassed 
socioeconomic domains 
since the Johannesburg 
Summit (2002). It now 
incorporates other areas 
such as culture, recognized 
as a full-fledged source 
of development by the 
Universal Declaration of 
Cultural Diversity adopted 
by UNESCO in 2001.
1992 
The main points of the 
sustainable development 
concept are defined by 
Agenda 21, the Action 
Programme for the 21st 
century adopted by 
governments at the Rio 
Earth Summit in 1992.
be related to the learner’s needs and to engage 
with ‘real world’ issues,” says Stephen Sterling, 
an independent British consultant on education 
related to environmental issues and sustainable 
development. “It is important to ‘start from where 
the people are at’ in order to establish the issue’s 
personal relevance. Then we can help people expand 
their perspective.”
The aim therefore is not to create an abstract 
concept but rather to cultivate a form of good 
citizenship applied to our everyday behaviour. 
Anyone can do this, for example by opting for 
seasonal produce. A strawberry imported by plane 
and purchased in France in March consumes 24 
times more energy than the same fruit bought in 
June and grown locally. When you find out that 
the annual consumption of paper in offices is 75 
kilograms per person, in other words the equivalent 
of one tree, it can also help encourage people to be 
less wasteful.
▼Tuna fishermen 
in Abidjan (Cote 
d’Ivoire). Seventeen 
of the world’s largest 
fishing zones have 
reached their natural 
limits
2000 
Heads of state and 
government from 
all over the world, 
assembled at United 
Nations headquarters in 
New York, adopted the 
Millennium Declaration 
that reaffirms 
the international 
community’s support 
of “development that 
is truly sustainable”. 
The Millennium 
Development Goals 
represent an ambitious 
commitment to 
reduce poverty and 
“ensure environmental 
sustainability”. 
2002 
The Johannesburg 
World Summit on 
Sustainable affirmed its 
collective determination 
to promote the 
pillars of sustainable 
development – 
economic development, 
social development 
and safeguarding the 
environment.
2005 
Launching of the 
Decade of Education 
for Sustainable 
Development (DESD), 
adopted in 2002 by the 
United Nations General 
Assembly.
© 
ST
R
/E
PA
/S
ip
a,
 P
ar
is
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
31
Planet Earth is Living 
Beyond its Means
The image is particularly 
striking: More land was 
converted to agriculture since 
1945 than in the 18th and 
19th centuries combined. 
Another significant statistic: 
approximately 60 percent of the 
ecosystem services that support 
life on Earth are being degraded. 
At that rate, human well-being 
will be seriously threatened 
in the near future. That is the 
conclusion of the “Millennium 
Ecosystem Assessment (MA) 
Synthesis Report”, launched 
on March 30 worldwide and 
notably at UNESCO’s Paris 
headquarters.
At the request of the United 
Nations, 1,300 scientists in 95 
countries examined closely the 
state of global ecosystems (1). 
Result: it appears that humanity 
has caused ecosystems to 
change more rapidly and 
extensively in the last 50 years 
than in any other period of 
history.
The study, less concerned 
with diagnosing the state of 
the environment than with 
evaluating services provided by 
ecosystems, covers such topics 
as climate regulation, natural 
hazards and fresh water. First 
observation:  humans have 
modified ecosystems mainly 
in order to meet their rapidly 
growing demands for food, fresh 
water or fuel. In fact, certain 
changes have “contributed 
substantial net gains in human 
well-being and economic 
development,” the study notes. 
The increase in agricultural 
production, for instance, is now 
greater than that of the world’s 
population. Progress has been 
made in decreasing hunger and 
improving health, but at what 
price?
One result is loss of 
biodiversity, with some 10 to 30 
percent of the world’s mammal, 
bird and amphibian species 
currently threatened with 
extinction. Another is threatened 
resources. Two services 
– capture fisheries and fresh 
water – are now well beyond 
levels that can sustain current, 
much less future, demands. 
According to the experts, the 
ongoing degradation of 15 
of the 24 ecosystem services 
examined increases the 
likelihood of changes that will 
seriously affect human well-
being. Examples include the 
emergence of new diseases, 
changes in water quality, the 
destruction of fisheries. The 
outlook is all the more ominous 
because global warming – that 
could turn the Amazonian region 
into savannah in a few decades 
– will make it difficult to reverse 
negative changes.
The report further notes 
that it is the world’s poorest 
people who suffer most from 
ecosystem changes. In Sub-
Saharan Africa, for example, 
the number of poor people is 
forecast to rise from 315 million 
in 1999 to 404 million by 2015.  
Achieving the United Nations’ 
Millennium Development Goals, 
which the world’s leaders 
adopted in 2000, will be all 
the more difficult under these 
circumstances. Unless human 
societies decide to ease the 
strains we are putting on the 
nature services of the planet. 
“Achieving this, however, will 
require radical changes in the 
way nature is treated at every 
level of decision-making,” notes 
the MA board of directors. “The 
warning signs are there for all of 
us to see. The future now lies in 
our hands.” 
(1) Natural system formed by a 
community of interdependent 
organisms (plants, animals, 
microorganisms)
www.millenniumassessment.org
So instead of giving a theoretical lesson on 
recycling waste, Claude Villeneuve encouraged his 
students at the University of Quebec at Chicoutimi 
study concretely the way the university managed 
its own waste. The first thing to note was that the 
university only recycled paper and there was so 
much waste that a garbage truck had to come every 
day at an annual cost of 45,000 dollars. “So starting 
from that basis, we found companies who recycle 
old computers, plastic and metal and we called 
in a company that deals with organic waste and 
comes to collect it for free,” Villeneuve explains. 
Recyclable material such as wood is now processed 
by companies that employ staff from socially 
disadvantaged backgrounds. The result is that the 
amount of waste has been greatly reduced and the 
cost of processing it has been cut by 80 percent. 
Everyone comes out ahead.
“Sustainable development begins at home. You 
have to realize that everything you do counts,” 
stresses Villeneuve. It is then up to society’s other 
actors to follow through. “Changing attitudes is 
important and education can help,” says Clayton 
White, “but we must also work to create the social, 
economic and political institutions that will make 
sustainable development a reality.” 
Agnès Bardon
Like the black caiman, 
between 20% and 
30% of animal species 
are threatened with 
extinction
© 
M
ar
c 
D
ev
ill
e/
G
am
m
a 
Pa
ri
s 
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
On the second floor of the Jenny 
Niström high school in Kalmar, a 
small port in southeastern Sweden, 
the laboratory used by the environmental awareness 
class is spotless. Various lab instruments arranged 
neatly on the shelves, often made by the students 
themselves, are used to analyze samples taken 
on school field trips. In one corner, two glass 
beakers on a burner contain yellowish liquids. 
“It’s an experiment in progress,” says earth science 
professor Sven Åhlin, explaining that the students 
are inspecting water taken from a pond near Kalmar, 
which could contain suspicious substances.
On the balcony behind the lab, a small 
greenhouse houses several aquariums where plants 
of all kinds are growing. “The students planted 
them and they take care of them,” Åhlin insists. 
The results of each experiment carried out by the 
BALTIC SEA: 
INTRODUCTION TO NATURE 101
High school students in Kalmar, Sweden, are  
not learning about the environment from textbooks.  
By taking water samples and analyzing their make-up, 
they are learning about pollution in the Baltic Sea. 
Their high school is one of 200 institutions working 
together in the Associated Schools Project  
Network (ASPnet) to try to improve environmental 
conditions in the landlocked sea. 
© 
Sc
an
pi
x 
Su
ed
e/
Si
pa
, 
Pa
ri
s 
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
33
students are carefully logged in a notebook so that 
the class can study the evolution of environmental 
conditions in the Kalmar area.
These experiments are more than just a classroom 
science lesson: they are evidence of true interest in 
the environment. And that interest did not just crop 
up yesterday. Since the high school opened its doors 
in 1992, Åhlin has taken his students every year 
to collect samples from the Baltic Sea in order to 
observe the evolution of the water quality.
The results have been poor. Very poor, even. “Not 
only have the levels of phosphorus and nitrogen 
continued to increase,” says the teacher, who speaks 
of the “eutrophication of the Baltic Sea”. But since 
he moved to Öland Island, just off the coast of 
Kalmar, more than 20 years ago, Åhlin has noticed 
other dramatic changes. “Several species of fish are 
in the process of disappearing, and bird fertility rates 
are consistently dropping”, he says. He is not the 
only one who is alarmed. At a meeting of European 
Union environment ministers in Brussels on March 
10, Lena Sommestad warned her colleagues. Citing 
the worrying conclusions of a report published in 
early March in Stockholm, the Swedish minister said 
that without quick and effective action, the Baltic 
Sea, its marine life on the point of suffocating, soon 
would be beyond help.
But Åhlin, who is in his 50s, refuses to give in 
to pessimistic predictions. On the contrary, the 
teacher is convinced that “the future of the planet 
lies with the younger generations”. And that’s one 
of the reasons why he chose, starting in 1992, to 
participate along with his students in the Baltic Sea 
project. Launched three years earlier, the project 
stemmed from a conference of European education 
ministers held at UNESCO’s Paris headquarters in 
1988. At that meeting, the ministers in attendance 
agreed on two points. One, they acknowledged the 
need to improve water quality in the Baltic Sea, 
and two, they voiced their wish to bolster relations 
between young people in the region.
200 SCHOOLS LOOKING FOR 
ENVIRONMENTAL SOLUTIONS
Inspired, Finland’s national commission for 
UNESCO invited representatives from all countries 
bordering the Baltic Sea to Helsinki in May 1989. 
The commission proposed to launch a project aimed 
at “encouraging schools in the countries along the 
Baltic Sea to reflect together on the environmental 
problems that the region and its residents must 
face”. The initiative, sponsored by UNESCO’s 
Associated Schools Project Network, earned a 
favorable response.
Fifteen years later, more than 200 schools are 
participating in the Baltic Sea project in Sweden, 
Finland, Denmark, Poland, Germany, Russia and 
the three Baltic states. And while the goal has not 
Shallow and partially 
closed, the Baltic 
is threatened with 
enthrophication due 
to pollution
Every year, students 
take samples to 
evaluate water 
quality
▲
© 
Ly
cé
e 
Je
nn
y 
N
ys
tr
öm
, 
K
al
m
ar
, 
Su
èd
e 
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
by the central board of the Baltic Sea project. For 
one week, about 100 youths from nine countries 
bordering the Baltic Sea and from the region around 
Africa’s Lake Victoria studied the problem of 
eutrophication and its consequences for the survival 
of tuna.
Before the Nacka conference, each school 
invited drew up proposals aimed at stamping out 
the scourge threatening the Baltic Sea. “Nearly 
70 percent of cultivated land in Sweden produces 
fodder,” explains Therese. “It would therefore be 
good to reduce meat production in order to slow the 
production of fodder and cut the use of fertilizer, 
traces of which are still being found in rivers and the 
sea.” That was just one suggestion discussed during 
the week of seminars, at which experts listened 
attentively to the ideas put forth by the youths. 
Therese, who is 19, admits that even just a few 
years ago, the environment was not exactly one 
of her top priorities. But after three years at Jenny 
Nyström high school, she says she is now aware of 
the important consequences her actions may have 
for the environment. Once she graduates, she hopes 
to enroll at the environmental sciences school at the 
University of Umeå in northern Sweden.
But Sven Åhlin wants to keep things in perspective. 
“My goal is not to turn all of my students into 
fire-breathing ecologists, but to turn them into 
responsible adults,” he says. Mission accomplished? 
Since 1992, things have really changed at Jenny 
Nyström high. Not only does the cafeteria sort its 
recyclable garbage, the school has 30 bicycles for 
use on field trips and its environmental council is 
hoping to soon receive the “green high school” seal 
of approval. 
 
Anne-Françoise Hivert
Freelance journalist, Lund (Sweden)
changed since 1989, the Baltic Sea project is now 
focused on the idea of sustainable development. 
As the coordinator of the Swedish project, Martin 
Westin, explains, “the goal is to help students 
understand the scientific, social and cultural aspects 
of the relationship between man and nature”.
KEY INGREDIENTS, STUDENT 
EXCHANGE AND COOPERATION
Even more so than environmental awareness, the 
project aims to encourage students in different 
countries to work together. For the past several 
years, Åhlin has worked with high schools in 
Kalmar’s two sister cities in Lithuania and Russia 
-- schools that are not yet participating in the Baltic 
Sea project but which are soon expected to join 
UNESCO’s Associated Schools Project Network. In 
May 2003, about 30 students from the high school 
in Zelenogradsk, in Russia’s Kaliningrad province, 
spent a week in Kalmar before welcoming their 
Swedish counterparts the following autumn. An 
“unforgettable” experience, according to Stina 
Andersson and Maria Carlsson, two high school 
graduates who made the trip. 
Despite their initial apprehension, “we quickly 
realized that despite our cultural differences, we 
pretty much had the same values,” says Maria. 
“We all had the same goal: the fight to protect our 
environment,” adds Stina. This is a point of view 
shared by Therese Henriksson, a student in her final 
year of high school who participated last September 
in a conference in Nacka, near Stockholm, organized Students learn 
ecology in the field
▲
© 
Ly
cé
e 
Je
nn
y 
N
ys
tr
öm
, 
K
al
m
ar
, 
Su
èd
e 
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
35
Judging from the champion’s pose, arms  
 outstretched with trophy in hand, you might  
 have thought that 15-year-old Tomoya 
Hirata’s team had just won one of Japan’s 
prestigious national sporting events.  
But triumph for Hirata and his 61 classmates 
at Shinjo Middle School, came for their tsunami 
preparedness project at the second annual “Disaster 
Prevention Education Challenge Plan” workshop, 
held last month [February 27, 2005].  The national 
program, sponsored by the cabinet and several 
ministries, selects the year’s top twenty local 
disaster prevention programs and then awards one 
top prize.  
They take tsunami disaster mitigation seriously in 
Japan, especially in places like Tanabe, Wakayama 
prefecture, where Hirata’s school is.  The town sits 
The recent tsunami that devastated 
the Indian Ocean coasts has made 
it obvious that high-risk areas need 
to mitigate the effects of natural 
disasters. Japan long ago put together 
the world’s best tsunami warning 
system. The key to its effectiveness: 
making even the youngest citizens 
aware.
▲
JAPANESE PUPILS FIRST 
IN PREVENTION
Japan is regularly 
hit by tsunamis: 
Hokkaido Island in 
September 2003
© 
A
P/
Si
pa
, 
Pa
ri
s 
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
▲
out on the Kii peninsula which, facing the Nankai 
and Tonankai seismogenic zones, has been struck 
several times by deadly tsunamis and is thought to 
be prime target for another major one in the near 
future.   
With earthquake generating zones all around, the 
country has developed a national tsunami warning 
system that is generally taken to be the best in the 
world. 
But the warnings alone mean little.  “A warning 
alone doesn’t save lives,” says Haruo Hayashi, a 
professor at Kyoto University’s Research Center 
for Disaster Reduction Systems, who chaired the 
organizing committee for the workshop.  “The 
warning is just a trigger,” he says.  “People need 
priming.”
BEATING 
THE CLOCK
Japan’s warning system is an impressive one, whose 
development accelerated in the 1980s.  In 1983, a 
hundred people died when a magnitude 7.7 quake 
gave rise to a tsunami hit on the Japan sea coast.  
The warning came in 17 minutes.  The tsunami 
came in seven.  
The current system is based on a network of 
180 seismometers cabled to onshore monitoring 
stations.  It takes only two minutes for a preliminary 
measurement of an earthquake to reach one of six 
regional monitoring stations.  
Then the computer magic begins. The Japan 
Meteorological Association has pre-calculated 
100,000 scenarios based on location, depth, and 
magnitude of a given earthquake.  Within one 
minute, the simulations predict whether and where 
the earthquake might produce a tsunami.  The 
warnings ride along television screens and set in 
motion local disaster mitigation measures. 
Estimates may be off, and small tsunami can be 
either missed or their impact overestimated. But 
with the looming threat of a large tsunami from 
the nearby Nankai trough, which runs only Japan’s 
pacific coast, there is no choice.  “Speed is more 
important than accuracy,” says Hayashi. 
Experts think that an earthquake is overdue 
there.  The greatest fear is that it could wreak 
havoc on Tokyo. But tsunamis are a great fear 
all along the coast.  A Nankai earthquake of 
magnitude 8.6 would, according to simulations, 
throw a 7.5 meter tsunami wave at Wakayama in 
eight minutes. 
Japan’s system would get a warning in time.  But 
would people have the wherewithal to react? 
CHILD’S PLAY 
Preparedness exercises take place in most Japanese 
coastal towns. And the training starts young. 
Efforts start with construction of tsunami hazard 
maps, based on the country’s tsunami disaster 
prevention manual distributed by the cabinet office.  
The maps outline potential dangers such as narrow 
roads likely to be washed out and bridges likely to 
be wiped out in a tsunami event. They also clearly 
mark where refuge points are.  
Part of the Tanabe team’s winning entry is a 
3-D map of the coastline showing where the water 
would likely inundate.  Another group added an 
inductive approach to estimating tsunami arrival 
times, interviewing the town’s tsunami veterans 
about how long previous tsunami took to reach their 
homes.    
Preparedness measures also take into 
consideration that, like the Sumatra tsunami in 
December, tsunamis often victimize people not 
familiar with the area.  Across the Kii peninsula 
from Tanabe, students at three schools in 
Kushimoto, created easy to grasp pictograms that 
indicate the height of a given location above sea 
level and the direction of the ocean.  The signs have 
Posters with 
prevention messages 
aimed at people on 
the street
© 
D
av
id
 C
yr
an
os
ki
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
37
been placed at easily noticeable spots around town 
making it easier for people, especially visitors, to 
know where to go for refuge. Takaharu Sugimoto, 
an official in the local government, says they are 
hoping that UNESCO will adopt the design, which 
won a runner-up prize at this year’s workshop, as 
an international standard.
Striving to impress upon the community 
tsunami’s potential danger, Shinjo middle-schoolers 
hit on a morbid historical lesson.  They designed 
a traditional Japanese “kamishibai”—a play using 
drawings along to illustrate the speakers’ narrative—
based on an 1944 episode, “unthinkable today”,  
in which the government stopped issuing weather 
reports and information on disasters lest they prove 
a disadvantage to the war effort.  Unsure of what 
to do, the protagonist, the son of a fallen soldier, 
is swept away by a tsunami leaving his mother 
completely alone. 
Materials produced by the students in Tanabe 
and elsewhere are incorporated into role-playing 
activities and drills. In Tanabe, some 80% of the 
citizens turn out for these yearly events. The sirens 
sound and the people dart off towards the refuge 
site.  At the end, they meet to discuss how much 
Students have 
produced an 
illustrated story to 
raise awareness  
of tsunamis
time expired—and what the implications would 
have been for their safety.
But some preparedness activities might not be 
suitable for children.  Three years ago, citizens 
living on a landfill coast in Kushimoto came to grips 
with news that a tsunami would come in less than 
10 minutes after an earthquake.  In their drills they 
knew it took 15 minutes to make the roundabout 
trip to the appointed refuge site. 
A direct path would force them to go over one of 
the national railway tracks.  Negotiations with Japan 
Railways went nowhere. In the end the citizens took 
matters into their own hands and built the bridge 
anyway.  Now they can get to their refuge in six 
minutes.
David Cyranoski, 
Asia-Pacific correspondent 
for Nature
© 
D
av
id
 C
yr
an
os
ki
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
THE SAN: SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT 
BEFORE ITS TIME
Key element of sustainable 
development, water 
management presupposes 
a solid knowledge of 
the environment and its 
resources. Indigenous 
populations often have 
mastered this knowledge 
for generations. This is 
true of the San, who for 
centuries were able to 
make the most of the scant 
water resources to be found 
in the desert region of the 
southern Kalahari (South 
Africa). This knowledge, 
however, based on respect 
of the local ecosystem, 
was lost at the time of 
colonisation. 
When the political leadership 
of the ‡Khomani San 
Association (1) sat with 
three of the most fluent speakers of the ancient N/u 
language, they asked the elders for guidance on 
the land claim and restitution process. The elders 
identified the three most important resources of their 
aboriginal culture in the Southern Kalahari: !haa, 
!ão, //kx’am. That is: water, land and truth. Water, 
and access to water, has been a key variable in the 
defense, conquest and colonisation of the Southern 
Kalahari.
The oldest members of the San community 
remember a time when there were no boreholes in 
the Southern Kalahari. There was no surface water 
available except during the rains. The people lived 
off those plants that absorbed water, including the 
all important tsamma melon (Citrillus Lanatus), a 
favored wild food with plenty of liquid. During the 
19th century, settlers could not penetrate the interior 
of the Southern Kalahari (where the present borders 
of South Africa, Namibia and Botswana come 
together) without using the traditional technology of 
the San people. 
WAR AND WATER 
When this region became engulfed in the Nama-
German war (1904-1908) that spilled over from 
neighboring Namibia, the humble tsamma melon 
became critical to all parties. The German imperial 
Elders of the San 
community consider 
water a fundamental 
element of their 
culture
© 
K
im
 L
ud
br
oo
k/
EP
A
/S
ip
a,
 P
ar
is
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
39
▲
army had to water its men, horses and camels 
entirely on desert food. This all took place in the 
peak of summer when temperatures soar up to 50 
degrees in the shade - and there is very little shade. 
Both sets of aggressors kidnapped San trackers to be 
able to help them through the endless sand dunes 
and find all the crucial plants to feed and water 
them.
The San themselves had a number of techniques 
for capturing and managing water. Ostrich eggshells 
would be cleaned out and buried deep within the 
red sand dunes during the rainy season. Water 
would percolate down through the sand dunes, 
weeks after the rains and the surface water were 
gone. The eggs would be recovered when necessary 
and plugged with a wax stopper. To this day the 
practice continues on some farms, though people 
now use plastic bottles.
The government of Britain and the Union of South 
Africa were deeply disturbed about the sovereignty 
issues involved in the German invasion of the 
Southern Kalahari, and soon Britain was at war with 
her previous ally. The South African government of 
the day decided to recruit white settlers to fill up 
the frontier and consolidate the border. Boreholes 
had to be sunk to achieve this. During the early 
1920s the government sponsored white farmers 
to sink boreholes, particularly along the riverbeds 
(the Auob, N‡osob, Molopo and Kuruman) where 
subterranean water was easily accessible. 
CULTURAL IDENTITY  
VERSUS COLONISATION AND 
TECHNOLOGY
The sinking of the boreholes had a drastic effect 
on the Southern Kalahari. Firstly, the seasonally 
nomadic San people lost all of their territory in 
a matter of a few years. Fences were put up and 
people were not permitted to move freely. Secondly, 
as elsewhere, the settlers went on killing sprees, 
devastating the wild animal population. By 1927 
there was a famine throughout the area, as game 
had become so scarce. This drove San to live and 
work on farms where they would earn a meagre 
income to afford to buy food that had once been 
theirs for the taking and managing. Farmers banned 
the San from practicing their traditional religion, 
including the powerful trance dance that was 
used for healing. The San identity was ruthlessly 
suppressed. First there were scientific efforts to 
determine authenticity that involved measuring 
people’s heads, noses and genitalia. During this 
time much of the culture, language and traditional 
knowledge was not passed down to the younger 
generation for fear of stigmatising them. All of this 
because of borehole technology.
The Southern Kalahari is composed of a number 
of different soil types, but the predominant type is 
that of red sand dunes. When it rains, water runs 
down between two dunes. This is called a ‘street’. 
Where several streets meet and the water cannot 
run off anywhere a ‘pan’ is formed. Some of these 
pans may have been in place for up to a million 
(1) In most San languages, 
extra-alphabetic signs are 
used to represent clicks, 
which are predominant 
and distinct. The phonetic 
inventory of the San 
language is in fact so rich 
that all the other symbols 
of the roman alphabet 
are already used for 
something else. N u has 
145 different phonemes, 
which is three times 
more than in standard 
English. Many of the 
signs used come from the 
International Phonetic 
Association alphabet.
= dental click; = lateral 
click; != alveolar-palatal 
click; = palatal click
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
years. According to the San (and confirmed by 
scientists), the chemical composition of each dune 
and pan is distinct. Some pans are now mined for 
salt. The San know which streets produce the best 
plants, and which pans have potable surface water 
after rains. The water in some pans will cause 
immediate diarrhoea or can even be poisonous to 
humans. There are, however, traditional methods for 
purifying some of the water. The San give names to 
pans to remember this, such as Large Diarrhoea Pan 
(Xausndi ‡gas).
During the process of the land claim against the 
Kalahari Gemsbok National Park (now Kgalagadi 
Transfrontier Park), the Park officials argued that 
there was no potable water in the park. A mapping 
project has demonstrated that not only is water 
available through the plant life, there are also a 
number of sites where water can be had on the 
surface or just below the surface. These water 
sources were already pointed out seventy years ago 
to the settlers and the warden, and are still known 
to some of the older people.
On March 21, 1999, the South African government 
awarded the Southern Kalahari San almost 40,000 
hectares of land outside the national park, and 
25,000 hectares inside the park as restitution and 
redress for their losses. On the day that Thabo 
Mbeki gave the land back, the N/u speaking elders 
gathered and prayed to their ancestors to send rain. 
This article is excerpted from 
the following publication 
coming out soon in English:
WATER AND INDIGENOUS 
POPULATIONS
Coeditors: Rutgerd Boelens
Coordination, WALIR (Water Law and 
Indigenous Rights Progreamme)
Wageningen University, Netherlands
Moe Chiba and Douglas Nakashima
UNESCO-LINKS (Local Indigenous 
Knowledge System)
UNESCO Publications
As Mr. Mbeki climbed into his limousine to depart, 
a large rain cloud moved over the land settlement 
site and rained huge drops of rain in the otherwise 
hot and dry desert. For many of the westerners this 
was a marvellous and inexplicable phenomenon. 
After the transfer of the first farm to the San in 
December 1999 a great rainy season began, with 
the highest rainfall since the early 1970’s, when the 
last San were expelled from the park. The new rains 
have restored all of the wonderful plant life and 
replenished the animal life. Some of the elders are 
back on the land and are taking their grandchildren 
out into the dunes to collect tsammas, gemsbok 
cucumbers and desert onions. So much rain fell that 
the streets filled like reservoirs and both the N‡osob 
and Auob began to flow for only the third time in 
a hundred years. Ironically, the massively irrigated 
agriculture along the Orange River, land that was 
taken from the indigenous peoples by the settlers, 
was swamped with water and the crops started 
rotting that year. 
Nigel Crawhall
In the Kalahari 
desert, tsamma 
melons are a vital 
source of water
President Thabo 
Mbeki during 
ceremonies for 
restitution of San 
land, 1999
▲
© 
So
ut
h 
A
fr
ic
an
 S
an
 I
ns
ti
tu
te
 (
SA
SI
) 
A
rc
hi
ve
s 
© 
A
FP
, 
Pa
ri
s 
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
41
▲
Under threat from urban development and demographics, the Sao Paulo City Green  
Belt Biosphere Reserve in Brazil is receiving an increasing number of visitors.  
A plan to teach sustainable tourism is designed to make the local young people aware 
of the fragile nature of their environment while also lifting them out of the poverty trap. 
ocean of greenery. But this paradise is under threat 
from the anarchic urbanization of the surrounding 
towns. With already 92 percent  of its original 
surface area lost, Mata Atlântica is a victim of the 
attraction it holds for the people of the Sao Paulo 
region. Already a popular destination for Sao Paulo 
residents, the forest is attracting increasing numbers 
of foreign tourists - with disastrous consequences for 
the environment.
That is why in 1994 UNESCO made the Sao 
Paulo City Green Belt a Biosphere Reserve, in order 
to preserve this natural heritage site that is home 
to one of the greatest examples of biodiversity 
A BIOSPHERE RESERVE TEAMS UP 
WITH GREEN TOURISM
The road that leads to Paranapiacaba 
crosses the heart of the Mata 
Atlântica, the Brazilian Atlantic 
forest. This little town is dependent on Santo André, 
one of the towns in the suburbs of Sao Paulo that 
is part of what is known as the “Green Belt”. In 
summer, the road is sprinkled with manacas flowers, 
whose white and violet colours contrast with the 
green of the abundant vegetation. It is difficult to 
believe that such a natural paradise can exist near to 
a megalopolis of 17.8 million people like Sao Paulo. 
And that in the space of barely 40 minutes, you 
can go from a world of concrete and asphalt to this 
© 
D
an
ilo
 C
os
ta
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
in the world, and to ensure that protecting the 
environment, improving the residents’ social 
conditions and developing the economy go hand in 
hand. 
Paranapiacaba thus became one of the bases 
for the Youth Training Programme for Eco-
jobs, an educational project created in 1996 to 
introduce pupils to activities related to sustainable 
development and to promote environmental 
protection in the region.
NEW LIFE FOR 
LOCAL ECONOMY
Seven town authorities in the Greater Sao Paulo area 
and the State Forestry Institute participate in this 
programme, which trains girls and boys aged 15 to 
21 from under-privileged families over a two-year 
period. Seven hundred of them have already taken 
the course; another 290 are currently studying.
“We offer them lessons in ecotourism, forestry, 
sustainable agriculture and waste recycling so that 
they leave here aware of the necessity of protecting 
nature,” explains Rodrigo Victor, the reserve 
coordinator. And so that they leave better qualified 
to find jobs.
Because in the long term, the project is all about 
energizing the local economy. “The whole Sao Paulo 
City Green Belt, including its forests and waterfalls, 
has enormous potential. Not only can sustainable 
tourism lead to more respect for the  environment, 
it can also help local communities by bringing them 
work,” says Vanessa de Souza Silveira, one of the 
programme’s coordinators. According to the Tourism 
Secretariat of the State of Sao Paulo, activities 
related to ecotourism could increase 70% in five 
years.
In the classroom of the Paranapiacaba Youth 
training programme, the girls and boys look just 
like teenagers anywhere else in the world. André 
Fantineli, 20, wants to be a disc jockey; Paulo 
Pinheiro, 16, has ambitions to be a policeman; 
Salatiel Santos, 15, wants to be a lawyer... All of 
them aspire to a better future. From low-income 
families, they live in the poor suburbs that surround 
▼
More than 700 young 
people have already 
taken the training 
courses for “ecojobs”
© 
Va
ne
ss
a 
Si
lv
ei
ra
, 
B
ré
si
l 
© 
D
an
ilo
 C
os
ta
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
43
the big cities and are exposed to many of society’s 
ills: drug dealing, domestic violence, unemployment, 
poverty...
Today, one year after they began the training 
offered by the Youth programme, some say they 
have changed. Salatiel views the forest in a new 
way. “Before, for me the forest represented a 
place where you could enjoy yourself, tearing 
down trees... Now I know that the vegetation is 
important for all of us,” he says. Renata Silva, 20, 
has discovered her vocation in life. “I really want to 
work in tourism. I have learned to speak in public, 
as a guide,” she says.
POSITIVE RESULTS
Some have already taken the first step. On the 
former motorway linking Sao Paulo and the coastal 
town of Santos, which has been transformed into 
an ecological route, young guides lead tourists on 
walks and explain to them the importance of Mata 
Atlântica, giving them information about local 
history or the fauna and flora of the region. “We 
have managed to convince our partners that it is 
preferable, for the development of the region, to 
take on young people from around here rather than 
bring in people from other regions, even if they are 
qualified. This allows us to create more jobs in the 
city,” Vanessa says.
The results speak for themselves, especially for 
the young people, a large number of whom are 
now free from the trap of social exclusion. Elaine 
Cristina Alves da Silva, 19, is one of the guides. 
Thanks to the lessons, she has overcome her 
shyness. Eventually, she would like to study biology 
at university, just like another guide, 18-year-old 
Ednalva Aparecida Oliveira, who is already taking 
courses at the tourism school. It represents a victory 
for her, given that her parents were opposed to her 
taking part in the Youth training programme. “They 
wanted me to continue working in the family bar 
and they thought the lessons were a waste of time,” 
she says.
 A waste of time? In Sao Bernardo do Campo, a 
community to the south of Sao Paulo, 18 teenagers 
have followed the Youth training programme for two 
years. When they completed it, they all found work 
as guides for the Sao Bernardo Ecotouristic Office for 
Coastal Paths.
Gabriela Michelotti
Freelance journalist, São Paulo (Brazil)
Manaca flower. The 
Sao Paulo reserve 
is home to one of 
the world’s richest 
biodiversities
© 
D
an
ilo
 C
os
ta
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
RAISING THE CURTAIN 
ON AIDS
By decimating entire generations, 
the epidemic has emerged as a 
dramatic obstacle to sustainable 
development in Africa. By 
calling on Prosper Kompaoré, a 
specialist in interactive theatre, 
the UNESCO office in Dakar has 
chosen to tackle the issue of 
prevention in a different way. 
In the market square of Manga, a 
town located 105 kilometres east of 
Ouagadougou, vendors close their shops 
one after another as the sun dips lower. In the 
middle of cabarets selling dolo, the local millet beer, 
the troupe from the Burkinabe Theatre Workshop 
(ATB) starts setting up its performance area in 
front of an impatient crowd. In next to no time, the 
stage is set. The evening’s show: The Cough of the 
Serpent, a play to heighten awareness of tuberculosis 
– an illness often linked to HIV/AIDS – that is being 
presented at the request of the National Tuberculosis 
Programme and the regional health authority.
At the start of the play, a malfunctioning 
microphone prompts vocal protests from the 
audience members. And they continue to make their 
presence felt throughout the performance. Spectators 
shout out their disapproval of a “patient” who 
refuses to follow his treatment properly, or respond 
to questions from the actors, who keep them 
involved. At the end of the rowdy show, queries 
fly from all sides. The actors, joined by healthcare 
professionals, answer them. 
“How can we know if we have tuberculosis?” asks 
a man in the audience. 
Excerpts from the 
“AIDS and theatre” 
manual
© 
Pr
os
pe
r 
K
om
pa
or
e,
 B
ur
ki
na
 F
as
o 
© 
de
ss
in
s 
ti
ré
s 
de
 S
id
a 
et
 T
hé
at
re
, 
20
03
/U
N
ES
C
O
/B
R
ED
A
/O
N
U
SI
D
A
  
  
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
45
message sticks in spectators’ minds. Thus, rather 
than piling on warnings against early sexual 
relations, the theatre instead shows a girl on stage 
confronted with the negative consequences: an 
unwanted pregnancy, expulsion from school, 
infection with HIV…. Everybody understands. And 
no one wants to identify with the reviled characters 
who reject infected people or show irresponsible 
behaviour.
BREAKING THE SILENCE
That is why UNESCO’s Regional Office in Dakar 
called on the director and founder of the ATB, 
Prosper Kompaoré. Devoted proponent of interactive 
theatre, he has already trained some 20 troupes in 
west Africa. “What gives this sickness its strength,” 
he explains, “is the silence surrounding it. Thanks 
to the theatre, we can get people to leave those 
deathly zones of silence and lead them to take on 
healthier behaviour.” At the door of the workshops 
he teaches, a manual titled “AIDS and Theatre” is 
available, produced by the Dakar Office to allow 
theatre workers to make authoritative statements on 
HIV/AIDS awareness. “It’s a teaching tool to educate 
young troupes in the different steps in creating a 
“You can’t diagnose it yourself, but if you have a 
cough that lasts more than two weeks, you have to 
get yourself to a health centre,” answers a member 
of the medical team. 
“I didn’t know that treatment was free. That’s 
good to know,” says Salif Tiendrebeogo, a village 
resident who happened across the play and stayed 
to watch.
The reactions, sometimes strongly worded, 
are the core of “forum theatre”, an interactive 
show that relies on direct participation from the 
audience. Extensively used by the ATB, this form 
of participatory theatre is today widely employed 
by NGOs and institutions to spread messages of 
prevention. There is an urgent need. With an HIV 
prevalence rate above 4%, Burkina Faso is one of 
the countries on the continent worst hit by HIV/
AIDS.
While more traditional information campaigns 
are now showing their limits, the theatre allows 
messages to be communicated to large groups 
of people whose attention has been grabbed. 
It is especially useful in communities with low 
levels of education. Dressed up as fiction, rules 
for prevention are more easily accepted. And the 
▲
In Burkina Faso, 
the prevalence of 
HIV/AIDS infection is 
higher than 4%
© Georges Gobet/AFP, Paris 
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
theatrical work themed on HIV/AIDS; the basics 
of building a character and directing,” Prosper 
Kompaoré says. In it, there are guidelines on how to 
make sure characters are not mere puppets spouting 
messages but reasonably rounded, with real 
psychological layers, and it explains how to develop 
plots based on problems linked to the illness 
– the difficulty in talking about sex with parents, 
infidelity, and how to negotiate the use of condoms. 
With his own troupe, the ATB, Prosper Kompaoré 
has written and presented many plays with 
HIV/AIDS as the theme. Some 15 years ago, there 
was The Sickness of the Century, inspired by the 
epidemic. Since, there have been Dangerous Liaisons 
and Sida, sid sida (taking its title from the French 
word for AIDS, Sida). For and Against tells the tale 
of a group of high school students who discover 
the devastation of HIV/AIDS. The main female 
protagonist, a girl brilliant at school but from a poor 
family, ends up giving herself to a rich, seropositive 
merchant to meet her family’s material needs. These 
forum theatre plays are put on either through the 
initiative of the ATB itself, or in partnership with 
certain institutions such as the Populations and the 
Fight Against HIV/AIDS Programme, the National 
Council for the Fight Against HIV/AIDS, and the 
Family Health Authority.
DRAMA AS A FLEXIBLE 
COMMUNICATION TOOL
“HIV/AIDS encompasses sexual issues, sometimes 
religion and culture too, and we have to be able 
to talk about it freely and we think that forum 
theatre lets us lift taboos and prompt people to 
break their silence, their shame, their passivity and 
their resignation. And during the shows, we’ve 
noticed that those who wouldn’t talk under normal 
circumstances express themselves, react,” says 
Prosper Kompaoré. 
And the approach is popular, as the packed tour 
schedule of the troupe shows. While the performers 
put on The Cough of the Serpent in Manga, another 
group of actors is in the village of Kayibo, some 
20 kilometres away, playing Land, about property 
issues. 
“We don’t believe that theatre by itself will 
revolutionise things, but we believe that we can’t 
change things by sidelining theatre because theatre 
has the advantage of being both a tool for mass 
communication and a tool for communicating locally. 
▲
It’s a flexible tool of communication, effective for 
raising certain sensitive topics,” Prosper Kompaoré 
explains. And AIDS is, indisputably, one of them. 
Mathieu Bonkoungou
Correspondent, Reuters agency, Ouagadougou 
(Burkina Faso)
Theatre is emerging 
as a more effective 
means of prevention 
than conventional 
public information 
methods 
© 
Pr
os
pe
r 
K
om
pa
or
e,
 B
ur
ki
na
 F
as
o 
© 
Pr
os
pe
r 
K
om
pa
or
e,
 B
ur
ki
na
 F
as
o 
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
47
CHIAPAS WOMEN INVEST 
IN THE FUTURE
Responsible for half the world’s food 
production, women play a key role in 
sustainable food security, particularly 
in developing countries. Yet they have 
considerably less access to land and 
investment funds than men. That is why 
microcredit, celebrated by an International 
Year in 2005, often seems like the only 
solution to break poverty’s vicious circle. 
An example: In the province of Chiapas 
(Mexico) women are taking advantage of 
both loans and literacy classes, provided by 
a programme UNESCO supports.
M aría Pérez Pérez, from the district 
of Zinacantán, never thought she 
would be able to learn to hold a 
pencil at 48, or pick up an exercise book and scan 
the lines to make sense of its content.
“I didn’t go to school when I was a girl because I 
had to look after the animals, and help my parents, 
who were very poor. But now I regret never having 
made the effort to learn,” says María, who like the 
vast majority of indigenous women, only speaks her 
mother tongue.
But she is one of the 345 women talking 
literacy classes, thanks to UNESCO’s support 
of the Alternativa Solidaria Chiapas (Al Sol), a 
non-governmental organization that provides 
microcredits to poor women so they can raise their 
▲
A majority of Tzotzil 
women cannot read 
or write
© 
V
ic
to
r 
M
an
ue
l C
am
ac
ho
 V
ic
to
ri
a,
 M
ex
iq
ue
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
own and their families’ living standards.
One of the 25 groups of women enrolled in the 
literacy programme holds its classes in Zinacantán, 
a municipality located around 10 kilometers from 
the colonial city of San Cristóbal de las Casas and 
a stronghold of the Tzotzils, one of the main ethnic 
groups to have descended from the Mayans. Every 
fortnight, around a dozen women, all of them 
adults with children, meet for an hour’s class given 
by their teacher, Rosalinda Bolom, who is herself 
Tzotzil and speaks in their language – without 
which her work would be impossible.
MAKESHIFT SCHOOL IN A 
STUDENT’S HOME
The classes themselves are held in the patio of 
a modest home belonging to one of the group’s 
members: there are neither chairs nor tables, and the 
students write either standing up or sitting on the 
ground, both of which are clearly uncomfortable.But 
since they are thrilled to be learning, these minor 
handicaps don’t worry them. Most of the students 
start to laugh nervously once the teacher arrives: 
the time has come to hand over homework. The fact 
that one student has not written her letters correctly 
sparks a chorus of laughter and whispers in their 
native tongue. Learning new letters or phrases also 
prompts excited reactions.
Using a small white piece of cardboard as a 
blackboard, Rosalinda Bolom writes Va-Ve-Vi-Vo-Vu, 
and asks her students to repeat the sounds to check 
they have not forgotten the previous lesson. With 
small children hanging from their large skirts, the 
indigenous women copy down the latest lesson.
“We can’t make progress as quickly as we’d like 
because these are not the very best conditions to 
work in, and because we only have classes every 
fortnight, but even so many of the women have 
learnt to read and write,” observes the teacher, 
who adds that María is one of the most advanced 
students. She and some other students have finished 
the first of the three levels, and are now learning 
how to add, multiply, divide and subtract.
“I didn’t know how to sign my name, but now 
I do and I’m very happy about it,” declares María 
with delight. She adds, “I want to keep on learning 
so that I can do the accounts for my business and 
live a bit better.” Her husband, she explains, instead 
of getting angry with her, has supported her in 
From Bangladesh 
to Chiapas
Alternativa Solidaria 
Chiapas (Al Sol Chiapas) 
is a copy of the microcredit 
programme that has been 
operating in Bangladesh. 
Established in 1998 in San 
Cristóbal de las Casas, it hands 
out loans to poor women who 
would like to embark on a 
productive business venture. 
Executive Director Claudia 
Rovelo explains that the project 
began with 23 women, but has 
since expanded to cover 4,679, 
most of them indigenous rural 
workers.
Upon joining, a woman 
receives a 1,000-peso loan 
(worth a little under $100), but 
over time they can increase 
their credit to 15,000 pesos in 
order to finance projects such as 
setting up small grocery stores, 
or businesses that buy and sell 
fruit, vegetables and chicken, or 
craft and flower workshops.
Al Sol was created by Pilar 
García and Claudia Rovelo 
after they made contact with 
members of the Grameen 
Bank in Bangladesh, owned 
by Muhammad Yunus, who 
loaned them a “seed capital” of 
$20,000 on a 2 % interest rate. 
“We began the programme with 
those resources and then we 
paid back the credit, allowing us 
to work with other foundations,” 
says Rovelo. “Any woman who 
wishes to start or expand any 
productive venture, and needs 
money to do so, is a candidate 
for a microcredit from Al Sol,” 
declares Rovelo, who explains 
that the programme is oriented 
solely towards women because 
they have the least chance 
of securing money for such 
activities. “And women are 
very reliable. Al Sol has a bad 
loan rate of only 0.1 %.” At the 
same time, Al Sol offers other 
non-financial programmes, such 
as literacy training, improving 
the quality of homemade 
craftwork, and a novel project 
about nutrition that began in 
January this year. Demand is 
now so high that by 2008, Al 
Sol estimates it will have made 
microloans to 15,000 women.
▲
© Victor Manuel Camacho Victoria, Mexique 
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
focus
49
to receive the credit, and that condition is enough 
to persuade them to make the effort to learn,” he 
declares. “At the start, many of them refused to take 
classes, saying they were very old and stupid, but 
bit by bit they became more confident.”
The literacy programmes are underway in five 
indigenous districts in Chiapas: Zinacantán, San 
Juan Chamula, Teopisca and San Andrés Larráinzar. 
In December 2004, 345 women were taking part, 
while 50 more are on the waiting list. Claudio 
Rovelo, executive director of Al Sol, underlines the 
importance of the basic literacy programme, pointing 
to the fact that 80 percent of the 4,000 members of 
Al Sol do not know how to read or write. “The main 
problem we had was a lack of money to support 
the programme, but in 2002 we secured finance 
from the Gills Foundation in Belgium, and then we 
contacted UNESCO. Our application was approved 
in 2002, and we were given $8,000 to start off with. 
In November 2003 they gave us another $4,000, 
and we have just signed an agreement to keep the 
programme going,” he says.
UNESCO’S CONTRIBUTION
Rovelo observes that UNESCO checks the 
methodology used in the classes, and suggests 
relevant changes in accordance with its experience 
in providing adult education. The finance provided 
by UNESCO is employed to pay the teacher’s wages, 
acquire teaching materials and fund visits to the 
communities where classes are held, he says. For its 
part, Al Sol pays its representatives’ travel expenses.
“Every month we send UNESCO a report on 
how the programme is going,” Rovelo says, adding 
they although they currently only have one teacher 
- albeit supported by volunteers from the Puebla 
Iberoamerican University - they are thinking of 
employing another to meet ever-rising demand.
Elio Henríquez Tobar
Correspondent of the Mexican daily “La Jordana”
taking the course and improving herself. Thanks 
to a small loan from Al Sol, she has also been able 
to plant flowers that she later sells, generating a 
small income for the family. During each class, 
Rosalinda is joined by an Al Sol representative, who 
is in charge of handing out credits. While Rosalinda 
teaches, he collects the repayments on debts every 
fortnight – an effective strategy, which tends to 
guarantee that the students turn up for class.
LITERACY AS A CONDITION 
FOR CREDIT
The Al Sol representative who accompanies 
Rosalinda is also a Tzotzil, Domingo Hernández 
Díaz, who explains that the idea of teaching the 
women how to read and write emerged once Al Sol 
decided it would not accept thumb and fingerprints 
on its loan contracts. “Even if they only put their 
initials, at least they have to learn how to write 
Despite Spartan 
conditions, women 
attend literacy class 
assiduously
© 
V
ic
to
r 
M
an
ue
l C
am
ac
ho
 V
ic
to
ri
a,
 M
ex
iq
ue
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50
focus
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
EDUCATION FOR SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT ON LINE
http://www.unesco.org/education/
Languages: English and French
UNESCO’s Education for Sustainable 
Development division site.
http://www.un.org/esa/sustdev/
Languages: English, Spanish and French. 
The rest of the site is also in Arabic, Chinese 
and Russian.
The United Nations Commission on 
Sustainable Development site. It contains 
all the international accords and official 
documents.
http://www.worldbank.org/depweb/
Languages: English, Spanish and French.
World Bank site. Data tables, case studies 
and maps are on line. An online quiz 
allows visitors to test their knowledge of 
the issue. An educational book can also be 
downloaded (also in Russian).
http://europa.eu.int/
Languages: 20 European languages.
The European Union site publishes official 
texts, which all be downloaded. 
http://www.wwf.org
Languages: 15 languages. 
This very complete site features all 
sustainable development actions related to 
those safeguarding nature. You can choose 
your country and language; the default 
language is English. Every country updates 
its information and adapts it “regionally”. 
http://iblnews.com/di/
Language: Spanish.
All information about sustainable 
development is archived under three major 
themes: economy, science and general 
information. The search engine is very 
efficient. The site is a division of a general 
information site.
http://www.csq.qc.net/
Languages: English and French.
This organization that represents Canadian 
unions promotes the relevance of sustainable 
development at every level of education. 
Firm commitment is backed up by past and 
future action. The site is recommended to 
teachers. The “DIDA” (« Des idées dans 
l’air ») section proposes an approach to 
climate change that is simultaneously 
artistic, ethical and scientific.
http://www.comunidadandina.org/desarrollo.
asp
Language: Spanish.
The « Andean Community » site represents 
Bolivia, Colombia, Ecuador, Peru and 
Venezuela. It gives all kinds of institutional 
information in various areas on those 
countries. The section on sustainable 
development presents and updates texts 
from institutions involved in sustainable 
development.
http://www.iisd.org/
Language: English.
The International Institute for Sustainable 
Development makes recommendations 
at international level, and not only on 
natural resources or climate change. The 
organization’s wealth – besides its links with 
numerous governments – is its library. You 
can consult its catalogue on line, do research 
or subscribe to newsletters.
http://www.novethic.fr/
Language: French
The site of the Caisse des Dépôts, a French 
public financial institution, gives information 
and makes available expert tools to 
professionals in business, finance, local 
organizations or NGOs who are interested 
or already involved in socially responsible 
activity or investment.
In Calcutta (India) cow dung 
is a source of fuel
© 
G
eo
rg
e 
G
eo
rg
io
u/
Pa
no
s 
Pi
ct
ur
es
, 
Lo
nd
re
s 
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
51
partners
Five remarkable women physicists received 
the L’ORÉAL–UNESCO For Women in 
Science Award on March 3 at UNESCO in 
Paris. It was the 7th edition of the award, 
which aims to give international recognition 
to women, traditionally under-represented 
in science. This year’s awards coincide with 
the World Year of Physics and are devoted to 
material sciences.
The laureates were: for Africa, Zohra 
Ben Lakhdar (Tunisia); for Latin America, 
Belita Koiller (Brazil); for North America, 
Myriam P. Sarachik (United States); for 
Asia, Fumiko Yonezawa (Japan); and for 
Europe, Dominique Langevin (France). 
They work in the most promising areas of 
physics: nanoscience or quantum physics. 
Their research concerns the technologies 
of semiconductors, measuring atmospheric 
pollution, the extraction of heavy petroleum 
trapped underground. It is also the stuff 
of dreams, such as building a module for 
the international space station on Mars or 
developing quantum computers that could 
revolutionize the way we work today.
As an extension of the L’ORÉAL-UNESCO 
Awards, a L’ORÉAL-UNESCO Fellowship 
programme was founded to encourage young 
women researchers in the life sciences. The 
L’ORÉAL
SCIENCE NEEDS WOMEN
GOODWILL AMBASSADORS
ANNUAL MEETING 
AT UNESCO
Education for all, education for 
sustainable development and 
UNESCO’s response to natural 
disasters were the three themes on 
the agenda for the annual meeting 
of UNESCO Goodwill Ambassadors 
on March 3 and 4 at Organization 
headquarters. Following UNESCO 
Director-General Koïchiro Matsuura’s 
opening speech, the Ambassadors 
presented their work over the past year 
and discussed their experiences.
During this meeting, Aicha Bah 
Diallo, interim Assistant Director-
General for Education, and Mary Joy 
Pigozzi, Director of the Division for 
the Promotion of Quality Education, 
presented the objectives of the 
United Nations 
Decade of Education 
for Sustainable 
Development (2005-
2014).
2005 list of 15 Fellows includes a strong 
showing from emerging countries such as 
Burkina Faso, the DPR of Korea, Jordan, and 
Cuba. This programme’s international impact 
is strengthened by initiatives organized 
in more than 15 countries – national 
fellowships, seminars, conferences and 
mentoring programs to familiarize young 
girls with science as a career. These actions 
are all intended to encourage women to 
pursue scientific activities.
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
© 
M
ic
he
lin
e 
Pe
lle
ti
er
/G
am
m
a,
 P
ar
is
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/M
ic
he
l R
av
as
sa
rd
 
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
52
NASA
NASA: WORLD HERITAGE SITES 
SEEN FROM ABOVE
On March 1, NASA 
and UNESCO signed a 
cooperation agreement 
at NASA Headquarters in 
Washington D.C. According 
to the agreement, UNESCO 
will benefit from NASA’s 
expertise in the earth sciences 
and space technology to 
strengthen its work in the 
conservation of World Heritage 
sites and monitoring of 
Biosphere Reserves via satellite 
observation. The cooperation 
should increase the efficiency 
and cost-effectiveness of 
conservation work. 
This expertise will also 
contribute to UNESCO’s work 
relating to prevention of 
natural hazards, a high priority 
in view of the recent tsunami 
disaster. Finally, concerning 
education, cooperation with 
NASA will broaden the scope 
of UNESCO’s Space Education 
Programme and other activities 
aiming to raise interest in 
science.
The agreement expands 
the long-standing relationship 
between NASA and UNESCO. 
It is, moreover, the first new 
science agreement with a U.S. 
organization since the country 
returned to full membership of 
UNESCO in October 2003.
UNESCO has also been 
establishing partnerships with 
other space agencies within the 
framework of UNESCO’s Open 
Initiative on the use of space 
technologies to support the 
World Heritage Convention and 
UNESCO’s Biosphere Reserves.
UNESCO has had an interest 
in space programmes since 
the early 1960s when it began 
working with the International 
Astronautical Federation.
partners
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
OPEC
REDUCING HIV/AIDS INFECTION
AMONG YOUNG PEOPLE
The heads of the OPEC Fund for 
International Development and UNESCO 
signed an agreement on March 7 to launch 
a joint HIV/AIDS initiative in 12 Asian and 
Arab countries. The two-year joint project 
will receive a grant from the OPEC Fund of 
US$2,250,000. The project aims to reduce 
infection among young people by integrating 
prevention awareness into national education 
programs.
HIV/AIDS continues to claim lives around 
the globe. For developing countries, the 
pandemic represents a serious hindrance to 
socio-economic growth. In Asia, an estimated 
8.2 million people were living with the virus 
by the end of 2004, including 1.2 million 
infected that year.
The two-year project seeks to develop and 
implement a generic program on HIV/
AIDS prevention education that is simple 
and standardized, yet comprehensive and 
sensitive to the particulars of each country, 
as well as adaptable to each community. 
The targeted countries are Afghanistan, 
Bangladesh, Cambodia, Jordan, Lao PDR, 
Lebanon, Syria, Uzbekistan, Vietnam, China, 
Kazakhstan and Thailand. All share common 
obstacles in their fight against the pandemic: 
access to healthcare services is poor, there 
is limited or no reproductive 
health education in schools, 
and little exists in the way of 
easily understood information 
materials.
Activities to be carried out 
under the two-year project 
include: the development of 
advocacy materials for senior 
policy makers to help them 
implement effective education 
programs; the promotion of 
HIV prevention education 
through the media; and the scaling up of HIV 
prevention education in schools.
The OPEC Fund is an active partner in 
the global battle against HIV/AIDS. To date, 
over US$21 million has been committed in 
support of priority activities in 58 countries 
worldwide.
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/N
A
SA
 
© 
O
N
U
SI
D
A
/G
. 
Pi
ro
zz
i 
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
53
It is December 26, 2004. Several elders from the Moken tribe, a small  
 community of sea gypsies from the Surin islands Marine National Park 
 off the coast of Phang-Nga Province, Thailand, notice that the sea is 
churned up and moving in an unusual way. They raise the alarm. Most of the 
inhabitants rush to take refuge further inland. When they return, the village 
has been entirely swept away by La Boon, as the Moken call the tsunami that 
devastated the region. Their boats and houses mounted on piles have been 
reduced to a heap of wood and debris. But while Thailand mourns more than 
5,000 victims, the Moken community was spared. The elders’ knowledge of the 
sea saved their lives. And ever since, their story has spread around the world.
In the aftermath of the catastrophe, UNESCO Bangkok took part in one 
of the missions launched by the United Nations Disaster Assessment and 
Coordination (UNDAC), based in Phuket, Thailand, to evaluate the damage 
done to the environment and settlements in the region. Through the Science 
Sector’s Coastal Regions and Small Islands (CSI) programme and the Local 
and Indigenous Knowledge Systems (LINKS) CCT project, UNESCO has for the 
last several years taken an interest in the indigenous peoples of the Andaman 
Spared by the sea
zoom
▲
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/D
er
ek
 E
lia
s,
 E
SD
 C
oo
rd
in
at
or
 A
si
a 
Pa
ci
fi
c 
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
54
zoom
The Moken village, 
built right on the 
beach, as it was 
before the tsunami 
(above)
Photos Derek Elias
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
55
▲
Islands and especially the Moken, who live in a protected zone that has 
been a national park since 1981. Acting on the conclusions of the UNDAC 
mission, the team working on the project for the Surin islands travelled 
there to assess damage and determine what aid the community required.
The Moken are now rebuilding their village, using bamboo and leaves 
woven together, in a non-traditional location inland, as dictated by the 
local government authorities. They have settled in a forest, further from the 
sea, and therefore a presumably safer but certainly not more advantageous 
site. The new village is less sanitary and has poor  ventilation and a 
cramped design. Of most concern, the visibility of the Moken’s natural 
environment, the sea, is substantially reduced.
The influence of the outside world is growing all the time. Since the 
national park authorities forbade them from catching certain species such 
as the sea cucumber and some shellfish that they used to sell, the Moken 
have been deprived of one of their sources of income. A number of them 
have already abandoned fishing to work as diving guides for tourists or 
garbage collectors. The objective of UNESCO’s Coastal Regions and  and 
Small Islands programme is to call attention to their plight and help 
influence policy to allow the Moken and other sea gypsy communities in 
Thailand to continue to uphold their traditions and livelihoods, within the 
National Parks that encompass their traditional homelands and waters.
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
56
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Books
S cientists, managers, development agencies 
and anyone concerned with environmental 
issues, will find in this book, in-depth 
studies about the many and varied aspects of 
deforestation – a process whose consequences 
and effects are not always as negative as 
perceived. In trying to answer the key question 
of whether the irreversible destruction of forests 
and their biodiversity actually masks a wide 
range of patterns, this book provides thought-
provoking answers that draw on the results of 
fieldwork and theoretical studies spanning the 
natural and social sciences.
This book also examines questions on the 
true nature of deforestation, how it can be 
measured, what changes result from it, and 
how human societies can manage them. It also 
looks at the kinds of research needed to address 
these complex issues. Examples from Latin 
America, Asia and Africa illustrate the different 
dimensions and perceptions of deforestation, 
underlining the importance of a cross-
disciplinary approach on this issue.
BEYOND TROPICAL 
DEFORESTATION
FROM TROPICAL DEFORESTATION 
TO FOREST COVER DYNAMICS AND 
FOREST DEVELOPMENT
BIOSPHERE 
RESERVES: SPECIAL 
PLACES FOR PEOPLE 
AND NATURE
Compiled and edited by Malcom Hadley
Man and the Biosphere series
2002, 208 pp., colour photographs, illustrations, drawings, maps
29,7 × 21 cm
ISBN 92-3-103813-3 
€ 16.00  
UNESCO Publishing
The book outlines the analytical and historical  
foundations of the Man and the Biosphere (MAB) concept 
as well as major environmental conventions. It also 
presents concise portraits of diverse reserves to highlight 
accomplishments as well as difficulties encountered in 
promoting sustainable development in different socio-
economic, cultural and geographic contexts.
This guide is primarily targeted at biosphere reserve 
constituencies, including MAB National Committees, 
biosphere reserve co-ordinators and managers, and 
collaborating institutions. It will also be of great use to  
other readers interested in approaches to biodiversity 
conservation and sustainable development. 
EDUCATION KIT ON COMBATING 
DESERTIFICATION
Publication co-ordinators: Thomas Schaaf (UNESCO) and Rajeb 
Boulharouf (UNCCD)
The Teacher’s Library series 
2003, two books (98 and 100 pp.) illustrated with photos and maps + 3 
copies of an illustrated children’s book + 1 poster presented in a slipcase 
30 × 21.5cm 
€ 30.00  
ISBN 92-3-103892-3
UNESCO Publishing
This education kit comprises a teacher’s guide, a series of 
case studies, an illustrated children’s book and a poster. This 
kit is principally targeted at teachers and pupils at the top end 
of primary school and the beginning of secondary school in 
countries affected by desertification.  It has been conceived 
to enhance the school programme. Teachers can easily 
incorporate elements of the kit into existing lesson plans.
Edited by Didier Babin 
Man and the Biosphere series 
2004, 526 pp., figures, tables 
24 ×15.7 cm 
ISBN 92-3-103941-5 
€ 59.80  
UNESCO Publishing/CIRAD
NEW
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
57
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
PLANNING EDUCATION 
IN AND AFTER 
EMERGENCIES
Margaret Sinclair 
Fundamentals of Educational Planning 
series, no. 73 
2003, 144 pp., 21 × 13.5 cm 
ISBN 92-803-1225-1 
€ 12.20  
UNESCO-IIPE
Educating populations that 
have been affected by crises 
or natural disasters is vital to 
the rebuilding of communities. 
This book argues that education 
should figure as priority among 
all the crucial issues to be 
addressed, as it is essential to 
the future of these populations.
This book will be of invaluable 
help to organizations and 
educational planners who will 
find discussion of issues such 
as funding, inclusive education, 
safety in schools, trauma 
healing, curriculum activities 
and distance learning among 
many others.
EXPLAINING BIOSPHERE 
RESERVES
Text by Christine Sourd -Translated 
from French by Barbara Thompson 
Discovering the World series 
2004, 40 pp., colour photographs, 
illustrations 
21 × 15 cm 
ISBN 92-3-103844-3
€ 4.60 
UNESCO Publishing
La série Raconte-moi, Explique-
moi propose en quelques pages, 
tout ce qu’il faut savoir sur le 
patrimoine mondial, les océans, 
les réserves de biosphère, 
des sujets chers à l’UNESCO. 
Ces petits livres guideront la 
réflexion et fourniront toutes 
les informations nécessaires 
aux jeunes lecteurs (à partir 
de 10 ans). Ils seront des outils 
parfaits pour les écoliers ou 
les collégiens qui souhaitent 
présenter un dossier ou un 
exposé sur ces sujets. S’adresse 
aux enfants, aux parents, aux 
enseignants et aux animateurs.
Aimed at ages 10+. A 
colourfully and easy-to-read 
book that provides accessible 
answers to questions related to 
biosphere reserves, including: 
What is biodiversity? Why is 
it in peril? Why should we 
preserve it? What do biosphere 
reserves look like? How do 
they function? Where are they 
located in the world?
EDUCATING FOR A 
SUSTAINABLE FUTURE: 
COMMITMENTS AND 
PARTNERSHIPS
Contributors: Kader Asmal, Paul 
Cappon, Jacques Diouf, John Fien, 
Rob Fincham, Monique Fouilhoux, Kul 
C. Gautum, Hans van Ginkel, Mayor 
Hagiwara, Griselda Keynon, Heila 
Lotz-Sisitka, Marina Marcos Valadão, 
Koïchiro Matsuura, Bedrich Moldan, 
James T. Morris, Tony Pigott, Thomas 
Rosswall, Tove Skutnabb-Kangas, Niels 
Thygesen, Daniella Tilbury. 
Education on the Move series 
2004, 258 pp.
24 × 15.5 cm 
ISBN 92-3-103935-0 
€ 19.80 
UNESCO Publishing
This publication collects the 
proceedings of a seminar 
organized jointly by UNESCO 
and the South African 
Ministry of Education during 
the 2002 World Summit on 
Sustainable Development in 
Johannesburg. It features the 
contributions of a wide range of 
education specialists, including 
representatives of civil society, 
higher education institutions, 
non-governmental institutions, 
private companies, United 
Nations agencies, Ministers of 
Education and Heads of State. 
It considers the many facets 
of education for sustainable 
development, ranging from the 
need for global action, through 
the sustainability of education 
itself, poverty eradication 
and the current context and 
new perspectives. It is a key 
reference work on the nature, 
scope and purpose of educating 
for sustainable development, 
today and for the years to come.
www.unesco.org/publishing
WATER FOR PEOPLE - 
WATER FOR LIFE
The United Nations World Water 
Development Report
2004, CD-ROM, PC/Mac  
ISBN 92-3-103929-6 
€ 50.00
UNESCO Publishing
This CD-ROM provides an interactive 
version of Water for People Water 
for Life: The United Nations World 
Water Development Report, the most 
comprehensive assessment of the 
world’s freshwater resources, based 
on the collective input of 23 United 
Nations agencies and convention 
secretariats. Generously illustrated 
with more than 25 full-colour 
global maps, numerous figures, 
tables (including country tables) 
and photos, the report opens with 
a chapter describing the water 
crisis. It reviews progress and 
trends, proposes methodologies 
and indicators for measuring 
sustainability. It then assesses 
progress in 11 challenge areas 
including: health, food, environment, 
shared water resources, cities, 
industry, energy, risk management, 
knowledge, valuing water and 
governance. Finally, it presents 7 
pilot case studies of river basins 
representing various social, economic 
and environmental settings.
With an easy and attractive 
navigation, fully searchable with 
many additional functions, this 
CD-ROM is an essential tool for 
professionals at all levels, teachers 
and students.
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
contacts
58
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
Documentation Centres
UNESCO Offices
Archives (BSS/AM)
☎ (33-1) 45 68 19 50/55
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 17
E-mail: archives@unesco.org
Coastal Areas and Small Islands
☎ (33-1) 45 68 39 34
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 58 08
E-mail: c.nollet@unesco.org
Communication
☎ (33-1) 45 68 42 67
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 55 82
E-mail: n.nguyen-van@unesco.org
Culture
☎ (33-1) 45 68 43 43
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 55 74
E-mail: culture.doc@unesco.org
Education
☎ (33-1) 45 68 10 29
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 24
E-mail: sdi@unesco.org
Information et Informatics
☎ (33-1) 45 68 43 99
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 55 82
E-mail: g.mensah@unesco.org
Information about UNESCO
☎ (33-1) 01 45 68 16 81
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 57
E-mail: p.morel-vasquez@unesco.org
Library
☎ (33-1) 45 68 03 56
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 98
E-mail: library@unesco.org
MAB – Man and the Biosphere
☎ (33-1) 45 68 40.59
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 58 04
E-mail: mab@unesco.org
Natural Sciences
☎ (33-1) 45 68 40 17
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 58 23
E-mail: p.murugaiyan@unesco.org
Oceanography
☎ (33-1) 45 68 39 82
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 58 12
E-mail: p.boned@unesco.org
Photo Library
☎ (33-1) 45 68 16 91
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 55
E-mail: photobank@unesco.org
Studio Radio-TV, Archives, Audiovisual
☎ (33-1) 45 68 00 68
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 56
E-mail: studio@unesco.org
Social and Human Sciences
☎ (33-1) 45 68 38 07
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 56 77
E-mail: dare@unesco.org
Statistics
☎ (1-514) 343- 68 80
Fax: (1-514) 343-68 82
E-mail: uis.resource-centre@unesco.org
Hydrology
☎ (33-1) 45 68 40 04
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 58 11
E-mail: ihp@unesco.org
World Heritage
☎ (33-1) 45 68 18 76
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 55 70
E-mail: wh-info@unesco.org
Youth Coordination
☎ (33-1) 45 68 16 54
Fax: (33-1) 45 68 57 90
E-mail: ucj@unesco.org
Afghanistan
UNESCO Kabul 
P.O. Box 5, Kabul
☎ +93-70-283.008
Fax:  +873-763 468 836,
E-mail:  martin.hadlow@undp.org
Bangladesh
Idb Bhaban (16th floor)
E/8-A Rokeya Sharan
Sher-e-Banglanagar, Dhaka 1207
☎ (880-2) 912 34 69/6522
Fax: (880-2) 912 34 68
E-mail: dhaka@unesco.org
Brazil
SAS Quadra 5 Bloco H Lote 6
Edificio CNPQ/IBICT/UNESCO 
9º andar, 70070-914 Brasilia D.F.
☎ (55-61)21 06 35 00
Fax: (55-61) 322 42 61
E-mail: brasilia@unesco.org
Burundi 
Avenue du Luxembourg, 
Bujumbura
☎ (257) 21 53 82/84 
Fax: (257) 21 53 83 
E-mail: bujumbura@unesco.org 
Cambodia
P.O. BOX 29
House 38, Samdech Sothearos 
blvd, Phnom Penh
☎ (855-23) 217 244, 426 726 
Fax: (855-23) 426 163, 217 022
E-mail: phnompenh@unesco.org
Cameroon
Immeuble Stamatiades, 
(2nd floor), Avenue de 
l’Indépendance, BP 12909, 
Yaoundé 
☎ (237) 22 57 63
Fax: (237) 22 63 89
E-mail: yaounde@unesco.org
Chile
Calle Enrique Delpiano, 2058
Providencia, 3187 Santiago
☎ (56-2) 472 4600/655 10 50
Fax: (56 2) 655 10 46, 655 10 47
E-mail: santiago@unesco.org
China
Waijiaogongyu 5-15-3, 
Jianguomenwai Compound, 
Beijing 100600
☎ (86-10) 65 32 28 28
Fax: (86-10) 65 32 48 54
E-mail: beijing@unesco.org
Congo
134 bd du Maréchal Lyautey, 
Brazzaville
☎ (242) 81 18 29 
Fax: (242) 81 17 80
E-mail: brazzaville@unesco.org
Costa Rica
Paseo Colon, ave 1 bis, calle 28, 
casa esquinera, 2810 San José
☎ (506) 258 76 25
Fax: (506) 258 74 58, 258 76 41
E-mail: san-jose@unesco.org 
Cuba
UNESCO Regional bureau  
for Culture
Calzada 551 – Esq. a D
Vedado, Havana
☎  (53-7) 832 76 38, 
(57-3) 33 34 38 
Fax: (53-7) 33 31 44
E-mail: habana@unesco.org
Democratic Republic of the Congo 
Immeuble Losonia,  
Boulevard du 30 Juin, Kinshasa
☎ (243) 88 48 253
Fax: (243) 88 48 252
E-mail: kinshasa@unesco.org
Ecuador
Juan Leon Mera 130 y 
Ave. Patria, Edificio CFN 6to Piso, 
Quito
☎ 2 5932 2529 085/2 5932 2562 327
Fax: 2 5932 2504 435
E-mail: quito@unesco.org
Egypt
UNESCO Regional Office  
for Science
8 Abdel-Rahman
Fahmy Street, Garden City,  
Cairo 11541
☎ (202) 79 504 24  
Fax: (202) 79 45 296
E-mail: cairo@unesco.org 
Ethiopia
P.O. Box 1177, ECA Building, 
Menelik Avenue, 
Addis Ababa
☎ (251-1) 51 39 53
Fax: (251-1) 51 14 14
E-mail: mlconde@hotmail.com
Gabon
A la Cité de la Démocratie, 
Bâtiment N° 6, B.P. 2, Libreville
☎ (241) 76 28 79
Fax: (241) 76 28 14
E-mail: unesclbv@inet.ga
Ghana
32 Nortei Ababio Street, Airport, 
Residential Area, Accra
☎ (233-21) 765 497, 765 499 
Fax: (233-21) 765 498
E-mail: accra@unesco.org
Guatemala
Edificio Etisa, Ofic. 7 “A”
Plaza España, Zona 9,  
Guatemala City
☎ (502) 360 87 17,  
360 87 27
Fax: (502) 360 87 19
E-mail: guatemala@unesco.org
Haïti
19, Delmas 60, Musseau par 
Bourdon, Petion Ville
☎ (509) 511 04 60/61/62
Fax: (509) 257 8158
E-mail: unescohaiti@hainet.net
India
B 5/29 Safdarjung Enclave, New 
Delhi 110 029
☎ (91-11) 671 3000 
Fax: (91-11) 671 3001/2
E-mail: newdelhi@unesco.org
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP
France
Tel. +33 1 45 68 10 00
Internet: 
www.unesco.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
2
message
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
59
UNESCO | the new Courier | May 2005
© 
U
N
ES
C
O
/N
ia
m
h 
B
ur
ke
Indonesia
UNESCO House, Jalan Galuh 
(II)
N° 5, Kebayo Baru, 
Jakarta Selatan, Jakarta 12110
☎ (62-21) 739 9818
Fax: (62-21) 7279 6489
E-mail: jakarta@unesco.org
Iran (Islamic Republic of)
Bahman Building, Sa’ad 
Abad Palace Complex
Tehran
☎  (98-21) 27 40 
141/142/143 
Fax: (98-21) 27 40 144
E-mail: tehran@unesco.org
Italy
Palazzo Zorzi, Castello 4930 
Venice
☎  (39-041) 260 15 11 
switchboard
Fax: (39-041) 528 99 95
E-mail: roste@unesco.org
Jamaica
The Towers, 25 Dominica 
Drive, 3rd Floor, Kingston 5
☎ (1-876) 929 70 87,  
929 70 89
Fax: (1-876) 929 84 68
E-mail: kingston@unesco.org
Jordan
Wadi Saqra Street 
Amman 11181
☎ (962-6) 551 42 34/65 59
Fax: (962-6) 553 21 83
E-mail: registry@unesco.org
Kazakhstan
4th Floor, UN Building
67, Tole Bi Street, Almaty
☎ (7-3272) 58 26 37/38
Fax: (7-3272) 79 48 53
E-mail: almaty@unesco.org
Kenya
United Nations Offices, 
Gigiri, Block C, United 
Nations Avenue, Gigiri 
Nairobi
☎ (254-2) 62 12 34
Fax: (254-2) 62 27 50
E-mail: nairobi@unesco.org 
Lebanon
Cité Sportive Av., Beirut
☎ (961-1) 85 00 13
Fax: (961-1) 82 48 54
E-mail: beirut@unesco.org
Mali
Badalabougou Est
B.P. E 1763, Bamako
☎ (223) 223 34 92, 223 34 93
Fax: (223) 223 34 94 
E-mail: bamako@unesco.org
Mexico
Pte Masaryk n.° 526, 3er piso
Colonia Polanco, 11560 
Mexico, D.F.
☎ (52-55) 5230 76 00
Fax: (52-55) 5230 76 02
E-mail: mexico@unesco.org
Morocco
35 av du 16 novembre, 
Agdal, Rabat 1777
☎  (212-37) 67 03 72,  
67 03 74, 77 81 82
Fax: (212-37) 67 03 75
E-mail: rabat@unesco.org
Mozambique
515, av. Frederick Engels, 
Maputo
☎ (258-1) 49 44 50, 49 34 34
Fax: (258-1) 49 34 31, 49 45 03 
E-mail: maputo@unesco.org 
Namibia
Oppenheimer House,
5 Brahms St., Windhoek
☎ (264-61) 291 7000, 
Fax: (264-61) 291 7220
E-mail: 
windhoek@unesco.org
Nepal
Ring Road-Bansbari
Kathmandu
☎ (977-1) 437 40 09,  
Fax: (977-1) 437 30 04
E-mail: 
kathmandu@unesco.org
Nigeria
Street Plot 777,
Bouake Street, off Herbert 
Maccaulay Way
Wuse Zone 6, Abuja
☎ (234-9) 52 37 088
Fax: (234-9) 52 38 094
E-mail: abuja@unesco.org
Pakistan
Saudi-Pak Tower, First Floor, 
Blue Area, Jinnah Avenue,  
Islamabad 44000
☎ (92-51) 28 000 83
Fax: (92-51) 28 000 56 
E-mail: 
islamabad@unesco.org
Palestinian Authority
17, Ahliyyah College St. West 
Bank via Israel Ramallah
☎ (972-2) 295 9740
Fax: (972-2) 295 97 41
E-mail: unesco@palnet.com
Peru
Avenida Javier Prado Este 
2465 - 8 piso, Museo de la 
Nacion, San Borja, Lima  
☎  (51-1) 476 98 71, 
224 25 26
Fax: (51-1) 476 98 72
E-mail: unescope@amauta. 
rch.net.pe
Qatar
57, Al-Jazira Al-Arabia  
St. Doha
☎ (974) 486 77 07/ 77 08/ 
75 49
Fax: (974) 486 76 44
E-mail: doha@unesco.org
Romania
◗ UNESCO European Centre 
for Higher Education, 39, 
Stirbei Vodà Str., Bucharest
☎ (40-21) 313 08 39 / 06 98
Fax: (40-21) 312 35 67 
E-mail: bucarest@unesco.org
Russian Federation
Bolshoi Levshinsky per. 15/28, 
blg. 2, 119034 Moscou
☎  (7-095) 202 80 97/ 
202 87 59/202 81 66
Fax:  (7-095) 202 05 68, 
956 36 66 
E-mail: moscow@unesco.org
Rwanda
Mineduc Compound 
☎ (250) 51 58 45/ 44/ 46
Fax: (250) 51 38 44
E-mail: kigali@unesco.org
Samoa
P.O. Box 615
Matautu-uta Post Office, Apia
☎ (685) 242 76
Fax: (685) 222 53
E-mail: apia@unesco.org 
Senegal
UNESCO Regional Office 
Dakar and Regional Bureau 
for Education
12 av.L.S Senghor,
Dakar
☎ (221) 849 2323
Fax: (221) 823 83 93
E-mail: dakar@unesco.org
Switzerland
Villa « Les Feuillantines »
CH-1211 Genève 10
☎ (41-22) 917 33 81
Fax: (41-22) 917 00 64
E-mail: geneva@unesco.org
Tanzania (United Republic of) 
Oyster Bay, Uganda Av., 
Plot N° 197A, Dar-es-Salaam
☎ (255-22) 2666 623/26 
671 656
Fax: (255-22) 26 66 927
E-mail:  
dar-es-salaam@unesco.org
Thailand
920 Suhumvit Rd.,  
Bangkok 10110
☎ (662) 391 05 77/391 0879
Fax: (662) 391 08 66
E-mail: bangkok@unesco.org
United States ef America
2, United Nations Plaza,
Suite 900
New York, N.Y. 10017
☎ (1-212) 963 59 95,  
Fax: (1-212) 963 80 14
E-mail: 
e.minchenberg@unesco.org
Uruguay
UNESCO Office Montevideo 
Regional Bureau for Science 
in Latin and the Caribbean
Edificio del Mercosur (ex 
Parque Hotel), Calle Dr. Luis 
Piera, 1992
Montevideo
☎ (598-2) 413 2075/413 
2094
Fax: (598-2) 413 2094,  
E-mail: orcyt@unesco.org.ury 
Uzbekistan
95, Amir Temur Str., 
Tashkent, 70 000
☎ (998-71) 12 07 116
Fax: (998-71) 13 21 382
E-mail: tashkent@unesco.org 
Viet Nam
23 Cao Ba Quat, Hanoï
☎ (84-4) 747 0275/6
Fax: (84-4) 747 0274
E-mail: registry@unesco.org
Zimbabwe
8 Kenilworth Rd. Newlands, 
Harare
☎ (263-4) 77 61 16
Fax: (263-4) 77 60 55
E-mail: harare@unesco.org
the new Courier is published 
by the United Nations Educational, Scientific 
and Cultural Organization
7, place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Tel: 33 1 45 68 46 85 
Fax: 33 1 45 68 56 52
Email: unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet: http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director of publications: Stefanino Muñoz Gomez 
Editor in Chief: Vincent Defourny 
Issue coordinator: Agnès Bardon
Editorial staff: Roni Amelan, Christophe Bouton, 
Pierre Gaillard, Lucia Iglesias-Kuntz, Cathy Nolan, 
Bassam Mansour, Vladimir Sergueev, Jasmina 
Sopova
Editorial Assistant: José Banaag
Photo editor: Ariane Bailey
Photographers: Niamh Burke, Michel Ravassard
Editions produced away from headquarters: 
Michiko Tanaka
Artistic direction: Jean-Francis Cheriez
Production: Gérard Prosper, Eric Frogé
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Distribution: Pilar Morel Vasquez
Printed by: Imprimerie Corlet,  
Condé-sur-Noireau, France
Electronic version: Richard Cadiou, Fiona Ryan
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted 
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads 
“Reprinted from the new Courier”, including the 
date and issue. Non-copyright photos will be 
supplied upon request. Unsolicited manuscripts and 
articles will not be returned unless accompanied  
by an international reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors 
and do not necessarily represent the opinions 
of UNESCO or those of the new Courier. 
Photo captions and headlines are written by the 
magazine’s editorial staff.  
The boundaries on maps do not imply official 
endorsement or acceptance by UNESCO or  
the United Nations of the countries and territories 
concerned.
ISSN 0041-5278
Cover photo:
© Mikkel Ostergaard/Panos Pictures, London  
Among all the reports about the Indian Ocean tsunami of 
December 26 and its tragic consequences, two extraordinary 
stories went to the very heart of education for sustainable 
development.
A little English girl on a beach in Thailand with her family 
remembered what she had learned at school and understood the natural 
phenomenon that was unfolding before her eyes. She raised the alarm 
in time and was able to tell people the best course of action to take.
The Moken people from the Surin islands, who from the dawn of 
time have made listening to the signals given by nature part of their 
everyday life, also understood what was happening and escaped the 
giant wave.
It was partly education and partly traditional knowledge rooted in 
their culture that gave them the means, limited perhaps but effective 
all the same, to face up to the tsunami. When education and culture 
combine with rigorous scientific observation of the oceans, social 
organization of warning systems and the media’s ability to spread 
information, it is possible to forge, as is the case in Chile and Japan, 
individual and collective behaviour that integrates natural risk 
prevention. UNESCO does not believe a global tsunami warning system 
can operate in any other way.
While education for sustainable development is the central issue 
in this edition of the New Courier, current events have prompted us to 
return to several aspects of December’s catastrophe and put them into 
perspective.
This regional disaster had repercussions in every region of the 
world, not only because the killer wave affected so many countries 
bordering the Indian Ocean, but also because so many tourists were 
involved and the emotion and solidarity generated from the disaster 
embraced the whole world. The often invisible threads which join the 
people of the world together appeared in the blinding white light of this 
tragedy. The event must also be seen as an echo of the warning made 
by United Nations experts in their “Millennium Ecosystem Assessment 
Synthesis Report”, published on March 301
To give everyone the chance to change their behaviour, a decade 
is hardly long enough. Representatives of every country in the world 
gave the United Nations a mandate to set up the Decade of Education 
for Sustainable Development (2005-2014). They gave UNESCO the task 
of leading the way. This symbolic act is undoubtedly no more than 
a means to attract public attention. The scant resources available for 
the Decade are not in themselves going to change the course of the 
future. However, growing awareness of the importance of our daily 
acts and UNESCO’s ongoing actions in education, science, culture and 
communication give us hope that the UN Millennium Development 
Goals2 will be reached by the target date of 2015.
Vincent Defourny
1. http://www.millenniumassessment.org/
2. http://www.un.org/french/millenniumgoals/
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
