<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="142021eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
   at 60
the newCourier
November 2005
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
On November 16, 1945, the Constitution of the Organization was signed and sealed to 
give expression to the international community’s hopes for a world of solidarity and 
dignity following the “great and terrible war” to which it had just put an end.
And just as our forerunners denounced at the root of that war “the denial of the 
democratic principles of the dignity, quality and mutual respect of men”, so we must be 
alert, for the future, to the threats looming over those principles and that dignity. Horror 
always arrives suddenly, in the form we least expect. Twelve years before 1945, nobody 
could have imagined that the “fi nal solution” would be conceived and put into practice. 
We must derive from that example of historic blindness the resolve never to relax our 
vigilance and the desire to forestall any lessening of respect for human dignity.
Following the end of the Second World War, as the world assessed the extent of 
the crimes and disasters caused by oblivion, contempt and assaults on human dignity, 
UNESCO was created to avert the recurrence of such a tragedy and to build the foundation 
for “the intellectual and moral solidarity” of humanity.
Today, as the 21st century begins, the intrinsic value of UNESCO’s mandate appears in 
its full power. More than ever, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must 
be built. This means affi  rming dignity in and through diversity.
To celebrate its 60th anniversary, UNESCO has chosen to highlight the coherence 
and intelligibility of its long existence. Besides celebrating the date of its creation 
on November 16, we have also decided to evoke, over the course of 60 weeks, the 
activities developed over 60 years, with results obtained, projects launched and the new 
challenges we are now facing.
In that spirit, this special issue of the new Courier celebrates the 60th anniversary by 
presenting reports on ten key subjects. Each puts into perspective UNESCO’s action and 
illustrates with a few concrete examples how much progress has been made and which 
questions are still pending. The themes resonate with global news and demonstrate the 
relevance of the issues that concern UNESCO. The close ties between the latest events, 
the major issues of our time and UNESCO’s activities – often less than spectacular – best 
reveal the instrument of international cooperation that was intended by its founders and 
emphasize how essential it is today.
Finally, this issue is also special because it marks a turning point in the 50-year history 
of the Courier. It opens a door to another way of sharing its articles with the greatest 
number of readers, and contributes to UNESCO’s presence on the internet. The 60 themes 
of this 60th anniversary will be presented on the website as a certain number of reports 
that fi nd their continuation in the thousands of pages that are on line. In 2006, the 
electronic version will prevail.
My wish, therefore, is that as you read the reports in the new Courier and take the 
time to refl ect today on human dignity, you will contribute to bringing about, in the 
face of what Hannah Arendt called “the banality of evil”, the emergence of new forms of 
analysis and refl ection to help us fi nd the path to solidarity.
Koichiro Matsuura
Cover photo: 
School for girls, Pahla Kadam,
Uttar Pradesh, India.
© Ami Vitale/Panos Pictures, London
the new Courier is published
by the United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
7, place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Tel: 33 1 45 68 46 85
Fax: 33 1 45 68 56 52
Email: unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet: http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director of publications: Saturnino Muñoz-Gomez 
Editor in Chief: Vincent Defourny 
Issue coordinator: Agnès Bardon
Editorial staff: José Banaag, Laura Berdejo, 
Christophe Bouton, Lucía Iglesias Kuntz, 
Cathy Nolan, Delphine Tissier
Photo editors: Ariane Bailey, Micaella Zyss
Photographers: Niamh Burke, Michel Ravassard
Editions produced away from headquarters: 
Michiko Tanaka
Artistic direction: Gérard Prosper
Production: Eric Frogé
Distribution: Pilar Morel Vasquez
Printed by: Imprimerie Corlet, 
Condé-sur-Noireau, France
Electronic version: Richard Cadiou, Fiona Ryan
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads 
“Reprinted from the new Courier”, including the date 
and issue. Non-copyright photos will be supplied 
upon request. Unsolicited manuscripts and articles 
will not be returned unless accompanied 
by an international reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors 
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of 
UNESCO or those of the new Courier. Photo 
captions and headlines are written by the magazine’s 
editorial staff. 
The boundaries on maps do not imply official 
endorsement or acceptance by UNESCO or 
the United Nations of the countries and territories 
concerned.
ISSN 0041-5278
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Summary
Education for all  2
Key to the future 2
Afghanistan: a diffi  cult return for girls  4
School for girls: creating equal opportunity 5
Uganda: the price of free school for all 6
Big classes, a threat to standards 8
The success of private schools in Zambia: 
a dirty secret 9
1945-2005: WORLDS APART 11
Oceans 12
Monitoring the oceans 12
Predicting the sea’s anger 14
What atmosphere! 15
Senegal: coastal zones at the mercy of the waves 16
UNESQUIZ  17
Heritage 18
A tribute to the past 18
Last but not List 20
Natural sites under pressure 22
The rebirth of kunqu opera 23
UNESCO IN FILMS 25
Copyright 26
Seeking the right balance 26
Paraguay and the pirate’s song 29
HAPPY ANNIVERSARIES!  31
Bioethics 32
Giving science a conscience 32
Born to cure a brother or a sister 34
The cells of discord 35
Plant pirates in Costa Rica 36
UNESCO’S FIRST AND LATEST 37
Environment 38
Taking the pulse of the planet 38
The Inuit, fi rst witnesses of climate changes 40
Selling the air we breathe 42
Cape Town: garden wonderland in the midst of urban sprawl 43
THEY WORKED AT UNESCO 45
Cultural diversity 46
A burst of creativity 46
The Global Alliance on all fronts 48
“Cultural diversity can neither be decreed nor improvised” 49
MAJOR WORKS 51
Water 52
The rush for water 52
Back to the future 54
The Mekong: an exception to the rule 56
Water wars and peace 57
UNESCO IN NOVELS 59
Digital divide 60
Bridging the North South divide 60
Radio Ada, the voice of those without a voice 63
IN-HOUSE ART  65
Crises and emergencies 66
Coping with emergencies 66
Education: a priority response 68
Learning for a better future 69
Bhaktapur: open-air museum 70
www.unesco.org/en/courier 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
 2 The new Courier – November 2005
E ducation for  All
In 2000 UNESCO was asked to lead a worldwide drive to achieve 
Education for All by 2015. The aim: provide a good quality primary 
education for every child, halve adult illiteracy and secure equality 
of opportunity between girls and boys, women and men. Other 
key objectives: widening early childhood care and youth and adult 
learning. Five years on, however, progress has been uneven. Two of the 
most critical challenges: achieving gender equality and ensuring the 
quality of learning as enrolment rises. 
Primary school pupil in 
Trinidad
Key to the Future
© Caroline Penn/Panos Pictures, London
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
E ducation for  All
It has been a landmark year for development. Anti-
poverty campaigns and the Live 8 concerts helped 
turn up the heat on the leaders of the G8 group of 
industrialized countries, who raised hopes by pledg-
ing an extra US$50 billion of aid to Africa. Th at was 
followed by an EU members’ pledge to increase aid 
to 0.7% of gross national income by 2015.
While this represents a welcome boost of 
resources, the US$1.16 billion per annum spe-
cifi cally targeted at basic education remains far 
short of the estimated US$5.6 billion funding 
gap required to reach universal primary educa-
tion and gender parity alone.
Peter Smith, UNESCO’s Assistant Director-
General for Education, is not satisfi ed: “I want 
to see more commitment from donors,” he 
stresses. But developing countries must raise 
their spending too, or donor fatigue will set in, 
he says: “Th ey will say ‘Who wants to invest in 
something that the people who own it don’t 
want to invest in’.”
| New ideas needed
Globally only 47 of the 163 countries with data 
had achieved universal primary education by 
2002, leaving 100 million children out of school. 
There is certainly a growing commitment 
among countries to creating national plans to 
widen education provision. But other chal-
lenges exist, such as quality of education, the 
subject of UNESCO’s 2005 Education For All 
Global Monitoring Report, “Th e Quality Imper-
ative”. For instance, in Zambia and Uganda, 
which have both abolished school fees, it is easy 
to fi nd schools with well over 100 and even 200 
children per class. Another challenge is how to 
ensure the poorest and most disadvantaged 
children are brought into the system, starting 
with girls but also AIDS orphans, disabled chil-
dren and street children.
One avenue would be to expand or comple-
ment the World Bank’s Fast Track Initiative, 
which is designed to channel multilateral funds 
to countries with sound plans to expand educa-
tion. Th e idea is to widen the fl ow of funds, and 
urge donor countries and developing countries 
to make commitments. Th e hope is to work with 
politicians to bring the private sector into dis-
cussions about investing in educational infra-
structure. 
 UNESCO has a key role to play, says Smith, 
not only as a convenor, but as a provider of new 
thinking, to help countries fi nd imaginative ways 
to tackle the shortfall in teacher quality that do not 
involve recreating expensive and outmoded fac-
tory-style learning environments. Th is will mean 
fi nding new models of teaching – perhaps by par-
aprofessionals or even mothers. “Our job is to 
show people best practice, to show them the new 
ideas that work and give them the best resources 
– then they have to make their own minds up 
about what they want to do,” Smith says.  ◆
Brendan O’Malley
International editor of
Th e Times Educational Supplement
Th e record so far
 Worldwide, 100 million children are not in school.
 Two-thirds of countries have achieved gender parity at primary level, 40% at 
secondary level and 3% at tertiary level.
 To achieve universal primary education and gender parity alone, aid targeted 
specifi cally at basic education needs to be raised to US$5.6bn.
 Globally 771 million adults are illiterate. The adult literacy rate is expected to 
reach 86% by 2015.
Source: 2006 Education For All Global Monitoring Report
In Nectangula, 
Mozambique, pupils 
help build their school
www.unesco.org/en/courier/education 3
©
 S
e
a
n
 S
p
ra
g
u
e
/P
a
n
o
s 
P
ic
tu
re
s,
 L
o
n
d
o
n
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
 4 The new Courier – November 2005
E ducation for  All
Afghanistan: A Difficult Return 
for Girls
 Four years after the fall of the Taliban, education for girls and other 
marginalised children is not yet a reality
Kokabar is something of a celebrity in Afghani-
stan’s Parvan province because she ran an under-
ground beauty parlour during the Taliban years, 
when make-up salons were banned.
“Th e fi rst time the Taliban entered our prov-
ince, they smashed up my shop and beat up my 
husband. Aft er that I worked in secret with local 
brides,” she says.
Now she has two salons in the bazaar in Cha-
rikar city, north of Kabul. She is the inspiration 
and master trainer for dozens of girls who want 
to learn literacy and some skills they can use to 
secure their future. Th is is a UNICEF-supported 
scheme, one of several ways the NGO is trying to 
reach the children, especially girls, left  with no 
hope of an education in a country blighted by a 
quarter of a century of war - and the Taliban’s 
ban on girls setting foot in class.
Crammed into a tiny room with a large mir-
ror, ten of them are watching Noorzia, 15, taking 
tips from Kokabar as she prepares the face of 
Samia, 14, with heavy make-up for a “Night of 
Henna” ceremony, when the groom’s family visit 
the bride’s home before the wedding.
“I’ve not been to school,” says Noorzia, and 
neither have any of her peers. Her family was 
forced by fi ghting to move three times during the 
war years - once when a rocket hit their house. 
Th e scheme is run by another NGO, Aschiana, on 
a strict commitment to provide  50% of places for 
girls.  Th e 500 learners are a mixture of refugees, 
street children and demobilised fighters, who 
have all been deprived of education by war or 
poverty or both.  Aschiana gives them a year’s lit-
eracy classes and ten months’ vocational training, 
plus a placement in income-earning activities 
such as beauty treatment, tailoring, carpentry or 
livestock management. Th ey will then be able to 
enter formal school by sitting an exam to deter-
mine their grade, or go off  and make an income. 
“Th e priority is their literacy training,” says 
Mohammad Israel, project supervisor. 
| Inventing new solutions
It’s an unconventional approach, but then new 
models of learning are needed in a country where 
the school age population is increasing by a mil-
lion a year as refugees return and so many schools 
are in ruins. In the Salang Valley just north of 
Charikar, 15 of the 19 schools don’t even have a 
tent to house them.
UNICEF representative Bernt Aasen says 
that despite a massive campaign to get girls into 
school, boys have benefi ted more. “In nine prov-
inces less than 10 % of pupils are girls and in two 
or three there are virtually none at all.”
High on the Salang slopes is one possible 
solution. In a cliff -edge hamlet of stone cottages, 
two girls are teaching a class in their home - two 
dozen girls and a handful of boys sit on an 
Afghan carpet covering the mud fl oor. It’s the 
last of three shift s.
Parwin, 18, and Nasreem, 15, are returnees 
from Iran where they reached grades 11 and 10 
respectively. Th ey have been given 15 days’ inten-
sive training in child-centred methods and acceler-
ated learning techniques, under a community 
school scheme run jointly by the government and 
UNICEF. Th e community is meant to provide a 
room and salary, but in this case the father has 
received nothing. He is investing in hope that one 
day his girls will become professional teachers. It 
means the girl pupils don’t have to walk an hour to 
the nearest school with the attendant risk to their 
Preparation for the 
henna ceremony
©
 B
re
n
d
a
n
 O
’M
a
lle
y,
 L
o
n
d
o
n
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
E ducation for  All
in Ethiopia - the development of a paraprofes-
sional teaching workforce that is trained on the 
job over ten years - a village-based teacher work-
force could liberate a mass of rural girls in this 
country from the constraints of custom and isola-
tion on their schooling.
But even in the cities there are many social 
obstacles to overcome. At the Charikar training 
salon, Noorzia says her real hope is that when she 
fi nishes the training course she will be able to 
attend formal school. “But I am already engaged,” 
she says. “It depends if [my fi ancé] will allow me 
to go or not.” ◆
Brendan O’Malley in Charikar, Afghanistan
honour, one of the main reasons why parents keep 
them at home. The training of 70,000 religious 
leaders across the country to convince parents that 
it is not a sin in Islam to send girls to school will 
tackle another barrier. “We are planning to cover 
half a million children, most of them girls,” says 
Mohammad Rostam Faqirzada, national director 
of primary education. Th ere are 10,000 schools so 
far, reaching 170,000 pupils. “Th e idea is that they 
will study there for three years, during which time 
the government will be able to build a school close 
to their community or children will be able to travel 
further,” he says.
Only 15% of Afghan teachers are qualifi ed. If 
UNICEF were to borrow an idea it is advocating 
School for Girls: Creating Equal Opportunity
 For the last three years, the United Nations has implemented a programme in Asia 
aimed at bringing girls back into the classroom
Many ministry staff  battling to improve girls’ 
education in Asia are highly motivated but iso-
lated within their own countries, as their govern-
ments barely acknowledge the importance of 
“mainstreaming” gender issues into all aspects of 
policy. “Oft en offi  cials say we don’t have gender 
problems because all girls are in school but in 
terms of equality and opportunities there are 
many problems,” says Ochirkhuyag Gankhuyag, 
from UNESCO’s Bangkok bureau. Girls must 
not only be given the chance to fi nish school, 
they must be able to get jobs without facing dis-
crimination, he says. Th e UN’s Gender in Educa-
tion Network in Asia (GENIA) programme was 
launched in 2002 to provide support and train-
ing to those who can make a diff erence. Based in 
Bangkok, GENIA identified “Gender Focal 
Points” (GFPs) – ministry of education offi  cials 
responsible for promoting equality -  in 11 Asian 
countries* and organises workshops for them so 
that they can learn from each other. 
“GENIA has strengthened our capacity to 
respond,” says Yangxia Lee, head of the Gender 
and Ethnic Minority Education unit of the Laos 
Ministry of Education.
Before, Laotian officials were dismissive 
about gender mainstreaming, but with UN 
involvement, senior offi  cials are more likely to 
come to meetings, she says. “We are able to show 
them there is a problem of gender equality, for 
example through analysis of textbooks, where 
few girls are represented in key roles,” she says.
Now offi  cials realise that unless the govern-
ment tackles the tradition of girls shouldering 
the burden of housework, few will attend school, 
and that simple interventions such as providing 
adequate toilet facilities for girls in all schools 
could make a huge impact.
Taj Mohammed Qureshi of the Pakistan 
Ministry of Education said simply erecting a 
boundary wall around a school has helped 
Girls in school
 104 of 180 countries for which 2002 data are available have reached gender 
parity in primary education
 Signifi cant gender disparities - favouring boys - are concentrated in the Arab 
states, South and West Asia and in many Sub-Saharan countries
 Despite overall progress between 1998 and 2002, gender parity in secondary 
education is the exception rather than the norm. 
 In fourteen Sub-Saharan countries where less than one in three teachers is a 
woman, 20 % fewer girls go to school than boys. But in several southern African 
countries, where three out of four teachers are women, more girls go to school 
than boys.
Source: 2006 Education For All Global Monitoring Report
www.unesco.org/en/courier/education 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
 6 The new Courier – November 2005
E ducation for  All
increase the number of girls attending. “Parents 
feel girls are insecure without a boundary wall 
because passers-by will gaze at their daughters,” 
he said. Hence, two provinces of Pakistan have 
erected some 64,000 boundary walls around 
schools in recent years.
Early marriage – sometimes as young as 12 to 
14 – is common to both Laos and Pakistan. 
“Married girls must be brought back to school,” 
says Lee. “Even if there are just two classes with 
mixed age groups. Th ere should be a school close 
by.” Th e further away the school, the greater the 
fear of parents that their girls will be sexually 
molested; the longer the walk, the less time the 
girl has from domestic duties, she says.
In Laos, creating a “Grade Zero” has enabled 
girls to bring their small siblings for whom they 
have responsibility, or their own children, to be 
cared for while the girls learn in the upper classes. 
Th is is being extended to all schools by 2010. In 
Pakistan, providing girls with a midday meal 
gave parents an added incentive to send girls to 
school. Th ese are just some of the ideas that other 
Asian countries can draw from. The GENIA 
workshops have helped develop the UNESCO 
toolkit for promoting gender equality in educa-
tion, particularly helpful on how to explain the 
issues to senior offi  cials. Translated into many 
languages and much in demand, the toolkit also 
helps monitoring and evaluating of gender 
equality. ◆
Yojana Sharma
*Cambodia, Laos, Viet Nam, Thailand, Mongolia, Pakistan, Tajikistan, 
Uzbekistan, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan
In Pakistan, special 
measures are taken 
to incite parents to 
send their daughters 
to school
Uganda: The Price of Free School for All
 Increasing enrolment is one objective, but the quality of learning must 
be preserved at the same time. An illustration  in Masindi, Uganda.
Although seven-year-old Fred Sekayingo cannot 
see, his hand shoots up regularly to answer Har-
riet Myendwoha’s questions. Each time he 
speaks, his 103 classmates burst into thunderous 
applause. Fred beams.
Th is is primary 4 class in Kamurasi Demon-
stration Primary School in rural Masindi, 130 
miles from Kampala, Uganda. It boasts 145 disa-
bled children on its 1,091 pupil roll, which has 
tripled since the government abolished primary 
school tuition fees in 1997.
Despite having a teacher: pupil ratio of 1:110, 
sparse learning resources and a shortage of qual-
ifi ed special needs teachers, headteacher Byoona 
Ntairaho is determined to deliver primary edu-
cation for all - ensuring girls, orphans and disa-
bled children are in his fold. Myendwoha, who 
self-funded her course in special educational 
needs, visits parents to encourage them to send 
their disabled children to school. She is training 
Kamurasi’s other teachers to teach Braille and 
has taught all pupils to sign so the special needs 
children feel included.
“Although it is government policy, most 
headteachers don’t even attempt inclusive spe-
cial needs education because it’s a bother, but I 
have an interest,” explains Ntairaho.
With funding from UK charity Farmer’s 
Overseas Action Group, he is building a special 
needs boarding house so the children can receive 
an inclusive education even if they live miles 
away. He already has a special needs resource 
centre, funded by charity Sight Savers Interna-
tional. Last year the school achieved a 100% pass 
rate in primary leaving exams (PLE), with six 
girls scoring grade 1 passes. 
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ir
e
ill
e
 V
a
u
th
ie
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
E ducation for  All
When countries rapidly expand primary 
enrolment by abolishing school fees in one 
stroke, the class sizes can rocket, weighing heav-
ily on the quality of learning. In Uganda, which 
now spends a quarter of its budget on education, 
the number of primary 6 pupils achieving 
national numeracy and literacy competencies 
has halved since 1999.
So what is Ntairaho’s secret? “Kamurasi is 
really shining because it has a visionary 
headteacher,” says district education officer 
Derek Nkata, who oversees Masindi’s 186 pri-
mary schools. But a closer look shows the school 
also has support from a visionary district offi  ce.
| The quality imperative
“Th e general attitude towards universal primary 
education is ‘it’s always there, even if I don’t 
come in today,’” Nkata says. “We are now get-
ting headteachers to sign performance contracts 
to eradicate this laisser faire attitude. We hope 
this will have a positive impact on teachers as 
well.”
Ntairaho employs several strategies to ensure 
his pupils come to school and focus on work. He 
conducts home visits to promote girls’ education, 
and even self-funds surprise pregnancy tests for 
girls - to deter men from defiling his female 
pupils, which might force them to drop out.
Concerns are shared at regular parents’ meet-
ings. “I keep reminding parents of their duty to 
provide exercise books for their children,” he 
says. “Because they have survived with-
out education, they don’t understand 
its worth and would rather use their 
children as a source of income.” Other 
schools that have won over skeptical 
parents have seen a dramatic increase 
in resources, through community fun-
draising, and also in results. 
Like all Masindi schools, Kamurasi 
is benefi ting from a fi ve-year-old part-
nership between the district and Link 
Community Development, a non-
governmental organization that sends 
British teachers to Uganda, Ghana 
and South Africa to gain and share 
leadership experience, boost numer-
acy and literacy teaching, and help 
schools with development plans.
Since 2000, PLE results in Masindi 
have jumped from near bottom of the 
56-district league to ninth place. And in 2003, it 
was the highest performing rural district in the 
country. Nkata attributes this success to a com-
bination of Link’s support and an infl ux of more 
highly qualifi ed teachers, because the govern-
ment has raised the minimum entry requirement 
to six O Levels, which must include English and 
Maths. Th e government this year has also allo-
cated time to numeracy and literacy in the lower 
primary curriculum to combat the national 
decline in results.
Nkata is now doing research at London’s 
Institute of Education to establish whether the 
quality of teaching can be raised by adopting 
alternative teaching methods and using existing 
resources diff erently. “Large classes are here to 
stay so we need eff ective teaching methods for 
big groups,” he explains. He believes co-opera-
tive learning among peer groups and interactive 
teaching would make learning more eff ective in 
over-crowded classrooms. 
In the meantime, he is trying to fi nd funds 
to train 200 unqualifi ed primary teachers in 
service and is building 1,000 classrooms – 
helped by British government aid - to reach the 
pupil: teacher ratio target of 1 to 55. At the rate 
of 50 classrooms per year, this could take 20 
years. Th at’s a long time for education for all to 
become a reality. Sekayingo is lucky that he has 
Ntairhao on his side.  ◆
Abi Newman
Abolishing school 
fees has caused 
skyrocketing numbers 
of pupils
www.unesco.org/en/courier/education 7
©
 D
e
re
k 
N
ka
ta
, U
g
a
n
d
a
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
 8 The new Courier – November 2005
E ducation for  All
Big Classes, a Threat to Standards
 Faced with infl ation in the number of pupils, teachers have no choice 
except to adapt their methods.
“Many teachers are only teachers on paper,” 
says Georges Hedad, Director of UNESCO’s 
Division of Higher Education. Many countries 
are indeed reducing the years of training as the 
demand for teachers rises.
UNESCO is focusing on trying to redress 
the balance with a strong push to increase the 
capacity and quality of teacher training in Sub-
Saharan Africa. “If quality of education is to be 
reformed, the best approach is to start with 
reforming teacher education, which itself will 
change primary education,” says Virgilio 
Juvane, of the Commonwealth Secretariat, 
which is working with UNESCO to study the 
problem of teacher education in both English 
and French-speaking African countries. 
“Large class-sizes are unlikely to be reduced 
in the next 10-15 years, so it is more realistic to 
provide teachers with the techniques to teach in 
a better way,” Juvane says. 
| Teachers learning new roles
In Namibia and Uganda and in several districts 
of Tanzania, multigrade classes where pupils 
are divided into small groups, each with sepa-
rate activities, have been an eff ective way to 
improve learning at primary level.  But fi rst, 
teacher training has to be changed from the 
Primary school class 
in the Central African 
Republic
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/ 
S
. S
ch
w
a
rz
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
E ducation for  All
The Success of Private Schools 
in Zambia: A Dirty Secret
 Public schools are free in Zambia, but many parents prefer to send their 
children to private schools.
The Ngoma community school in southern 
Zambia is private, but there is nothing grand 
about it. Its makeshift  new classroom is missing 
walls and there are holes between the empty can-
vas fertiliser sacks that make up its roof. Inside it 
is easy to spot the many pupils who have lost 
their parents, usually to AIDS or malaria, because 
they are allowed to attend classes without wear-
ing the school’s simple blue uniform.
Th e Zambian government may have made 
primary education free in all its schools three 
years ago, but some state schools still turn away 
students whose families cannot aff ord uniforms, 
books or Parent Teacher Association fees. Par-
ents who work on the sugar plantations that 
surround Ngoma say they choose the private 
school because it is more practical and cheaper 
for them to pay its 62 pence monthly fees than 
to send their children to the nearest state-
funded school 10 kilometres away.
James Daka, an irrigation supervisor with 
three children, says:  “It’s a good school. Th e 
teachers are not all trained like at the govern-
ment school, but community schools are 
cheap.”
| Success for unregistered schools
Headteacher Emily Mwembe says her pupils 
outperform pupils at the nearest state school 
when they bus them there to sit reading and 
writing tests.
Ngoma is far from unique. Researchers led 
by James Tooley of the University of Newcastle 
(United Kingdom) have found hundreds of 
similar private schools doing successful work in 
the poorest areas around the world. Th e schools 
are oft en unregistered and their pupils missing 
from offi  cial data. In the Indian city of Hydera-
bad, the researchers found that 35% of the 
schools were state-run, 23% were private 
widespread chalk-and-talk teacher-led model 
towards a more child-appropriate model where 
teachers act as facilitators.
Initially, 17 countries* have been selected to 
help set up a national plan of action for teacher 
training, beginning with Angola, Niger, Zam-
bia and Ethiopia, says Hedad. Another 30 coun-
tries will join within 5 years. 
With rising enrolment and huge classes, 
teachers need support and mentoring. Zambia 
has set up teacher resource centres in school 
areas, where teachers can update and refresh 
their skills. Mozambique and Tanzania are pro-
viding in-service education through distance 
education, which includes the use of radio, tel-
evision and videos. It is cost-effective and 
includes a small group of tutors and educators 
to provide assistance. 
Th e training of school principals is key for 
improving secondary education quality. “If 
school leaders do not support teachers’ train-
ing, it will not have an impact on teaching qual-
ity,” says Sonia Bahri, UNESCO’s Chief of 
Section for General Secondary Education. Th e 
UNESCO-linked International Institute for 
Capacity-Building in Africa, based in Addis 
Ababa, has been running programmes for prin-
cipals, while workshops are being conducted in 
the Democratic Republic of the Congo and 
other countries. ◆
Yojana Sharma
*Angola, Burkina Faso, Burundi, Cape Verde, Central African Republic, Chad, 
Congo, DR Congo, Ethiopia, Ghana, Guinea, Madagascar, Niger, Nigeria, Sierra 
Leone, Tanzania and Zambia.
www.unesco.org/en/courier/education 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
 10 The new Courier – November 2005
E ducation for  All
schools recognised by the Government, and 
37% were private schools that did not offi  cially 
exist.
Th e researchers tested 9,000 children from 
government and fee-paying schools in India, 
Ghana and Kenya. Th ey found, once they con-
trolled for background variables, that the chil-
dren at the unregistered private schools 
performed 14 percentage points better in maths 
and 20 percentage points better in English.
“No one suspected that private slum schools 
would be better,” says Tooley. His fi ndings raise 
the question of whether international agencies 
should consider giving fi nancial backing to the 
fee-paying schools.
Th e priority should be to help governments 
provide a free education for all, says the World 
Bank, but it also recognises that fee-paying 
schools can play a crucial role.
Bob Prouty, an education advisor to the 
World Bank, says that many children in the 
Democratic Republic of the Congo would have 
missed out on education altogether during the 
last 15 years of political upheaval and civil war 
if they had not been able to attend private com-
munity schools. “It’s kind of a dirty little secret,” 
he says. “But where private schools are provid-
ing an education for the very poorest commu-
nities, it has to be seen as an indictment of the 
existing system.” ◆
Michael Shaw in Ngoma, Zambia
More than reading, writing 
and counting
 UNESCO will have a demanding role to play over the next ten years in co-
ordinating eff orts to achieve Education for All, according to Abhimanyu Singh, 
UNESCO’s Director for EFA Co-ordination and Monitoring. “We must keep everyone 
working towards the EFA goals,” he says. 
 UNESCO’s research institutes will attempt to focus more sharply on 
helping countries form eff ective national education plans and improving the 
eff ectiveness of regional support networks and country programmes.
 Initiatives have also been launched on three key issues: training for teachers in 
Sub-Saharan Africa, adult literacy for empowerment and the fi ght against HIV/
AIDS, which is doubling teacher attrition rates in some countries. The ambitious 
training programme will attempt to raise the quality of teaching in 17 countries 
from 2006. UNESCO is already coordinating the international UN eff ort on 
HIV/AIDS, but will also expand its preventive education work. The ten-year 
adult literacy programme, LIFE, will operate in 34 countries that have 10 million 
illiterates or an adult literacy rate below 50 %.
 “Literacy is no longer about the 3Rs but about human development, 
community development and country development,” says Shigeru Aoyagi, Chief 
of UNESCO’s Literacy Section, adding that programmes must go beyond the 
basics. Ann Therese Ndong-Jatta, a former Minister of Education in Gambia and 
now the Director of the Basic Education Division at UNESCO, says the Organization 
must also work more at the country level to share expertise, improve 
governments’ ability to use aid eff ectively and increase their ability to negotiate 
with international donors. “When they want an accord, developing countries 
tend to agree with partners,” Ndong-Jatta says. “UNESCO must help them respond 
better to get a better outcome for themselves.”
Yojana Sharma
Public schools are free 
in Zambia, but many 
parents choose private 
schools
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/A
n
g
e
la
 N
g
a
la
ti
 K
a
m
b
a
ila
/A
S
P
n
e
t
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
1945-2005: Worlds Apart
UNESCO was founded following the Second World War.
Sixty years later, the world is not quite the same. Examples. 
 1945 2005
World population   2.2  6.5
(billions) 
Urban population  less than 29 49
 (% of total) 
Adult literacy   less than 50  81.7
(%) 
Life expectancy at birth   less than 46  65
(years)
Countries with parliaments 26 186
Women in parliaments   3 16
(% of total)
Fertility rate   more than 5  less than 3
(children per woman)
Child mortality   ~– 224 ~– 86
(children per 1,000 not surviving
to age 5)
 
Forest area   50 39
(million km²) 
Annual water consumption   797 2,425
(km3)
Annual oil consumption   less than 470 more than 4,000
(million tonnes)
Tourists  less than 25 808
(millions)
Sources : Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inter-Parliamentary Union, United Nations system, Worldwatch Institute.                                           
NB : In general, the collection of data on a global scale only began in the 1950s, which explains the approximate fi gures before that time.
www.unesco.org/en/courier/interalia 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
 12 The new Courier – November 2005
Oceans, vital to the planet’s survival, are being misused.  
Overpopulated coastal areas have suff ered damage due to marine 
pollution that causes the proliferation of algae capable of poisoning 
ecosystems. The 19 million tons of carbon being injected daily by 
human activity could permanently upset the marine environment. 
For 45 years now, UNESCO’s Intergovernmental Oceanographic 
Commission (IOC) has been busy getting to know the ocean. Regular 
global monitoring and data sharing constitute the essential two-fold 
challenge, whether the task is sending tsunami warnings or creating 
reliable predictive models, keys to adapting to future disturbances.   
Ocean s
Off  the coast of 
Mauritius
Monitoring the Oceans
©
 B
ru
n
o
 B
a
rb
e
y/
M
a
g
n
u
m
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
“
It’s every oceanographer’s dream!  In real time, 
the Argo network lets us measure water salinity 
and temperatures throughout the world’s oceans,” 
says Mathieu Belbeoch, technical coordinator of 
the Argo project. Aided by the Intergovernmental 
Oceanographic Commission (IOC), this is a project 
devised to help understand the ocean’s role in cli-
mate. Since 2000, fl oats have been cast from boats 
and even airplanes at a steady rhythm of around 80 
per month. Coverage is not yet uniform but already 
worldwide, aft er the installation of 1,955 devices 
out of an expected total of 3,000. Th is is the fi rst 
time in history that we have been able to observe 
the superfi cial layer of oceans to such an extent.
But even if knowledge has progressed, the 
oceans still hold many secrets. Th ey occupy 71% 
of our earth’s surface and also play an essential 
role in the regulation of the climate. Because they 
cannot be reproduced in a laboratory, they must 
be observed. Oceanography, however, is a young 
science and doesn’t yet have the measuring net-
work of meteorology. Created 80 years aft er the 
World Meteorology Organization, the IOC came 
into being at UNESCO in 1960 to coordinate 
research on oceans, an essentially international 
subject of study. Its objective: encouraging the 
collection of scientifi c information in the marine 
environment and sharing it with the 131 Mem-
ber States. 
| Improving models for forecasting
Th e stakes are enormous. More than half of the 
world’s population lives less then 200 kilometres 
from the coast.  Th at type of high concentration is 
the origin of coastal zone pollution, 70% of which 
comes from water waste and household and 
industrial refuse dumped directly into the sea. 
Fishing, upon which many developing countries 
depend, is also a problem.  Between 50 to 90% of 
the largest  predatory fi sh have disappeared in the 
last 15 years because of the over-exploitation of 
fi sh resources. On top of that, marine currents are 
spreading climatic abnormalities on a large scale. 
Take for example El Niño, whose disastrous 
eff ects (scarcity of fi sh, drought and torrential 
rains) have been felt from Alaska to Australia and 
from East Africa to Brazil. The phenomenon 
aff ected some 125 million people and cost 30 mil-
lion euros in damages due to fl ooding, forest fi res 
and cyclones in 1997.  
To forecast the arrival of El Niño, a type of 
natural disturbance that generally occurs every 
three to five years, 72 floating sensors were 
installed in the tropical Pacific Ocean in the 
beginning of the 1990s. Th is network enabled 
the forecasting of the 1997 episode six months in 
advance. Today the system has been extended to 
all the oceans. “Th e major challenge now is to 
establish and perpetuate the Global Ocean 
Observing System called GOOS. Argo is one of 
the components” explains Patricio Bernal, IOC 
executive secretary. GOOS coordinates the 
eff orts of 61 Member States participating in the 
collection and unrestricted exchange of data on 
the marine environment. Th e in situ measuring 
network is already half-installed, and is comple-
mented eff ectively by satellites. Th ese provide a 
picture of all the oceans, in essentially real time.
The information is the basis for models 
describing the sea’s condition. Improving the 
models, and thus the ensuing predictions, is 
essential for tracking climate change. “But we 
also have to worry about developing countries 
having access to data and being able to use it,” 
Patricio Bernal points out. For these predictions 
allow us not only to anticipate phenomena such 
as the rising of sea level, coastal erosion and the 
decrease in fi sh resources, they also enable us to 
determine the ideal moment for harvest or the 
location of shoals of fi sh. ◆
Mathilde Elie
A network of data for Africa
 Marine Institutions from 25 African countries have come together in the 
Ocean Data and Information Network for Africa (ODINAFRICA), supported 
by IOC and the Government of Flanders. Designed to provide access to the 
latest oceanographic information, the network has developed the necessary 
infrastructures and competencies for archiving and management. Each 
Member State is now equipped with an Information Centre and a National 
Centre of Oceanographic Data.
Ocean s
Argo network, September 2005
2,041 active fl oating sensors
Australia (62)
Brazil (3)
Canada (76)
Chile (2)
China (10)
European Union (31)
France (162)
Germany (99)
India (75)
Ireland (1)
Japan (300)
Republic of Korea (52)
Mauritius (2)
Mexico (1)
Netherlands (7)
New Zealand (4)
Norway (8) 
Russian Federation (2)
Spain (9)
United Kingdom (86)
United States (1049)
©
 J
C
O
M
M
O
P
S
 www.unesco.org/en/courier/oceans 13
2EN_COURRIER.indd   13 28/10/05   17:36:01
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
 14 The new Courier – November 2005
Ocean s
Predicting the Sea’s Anger
 Strengthened by its experience in the Pacifi c, the Intergovernmental 
Oceanographic Commission is encouraging the installation of an early 
warning system in the Indian Ocean.
On July 23, 2005, Tokyo (Japan) was hit by the 
most powerful earthquake to occur since 1992. 
Th is time, as it does every time there is a tremor, 
the computer of the Japanese Tsunami Warn-
ing Centre automatically informed the Japanese 
media. Meanwhile, seismologists were deter-
mining whether the earthquake detected could 
cause a tsunami, trying fi rst to locate its epicen-
tre and measure its intensity from information 
sent around the clock by the 200 seismic sta-
tions that monitor the country. If an earthquake 
is likely to provoke a tsunami, an evacuation 
order is sent out. Th is time it wasn’t necessary. 
Th e alert was canceled.
In all, these operations took less than fi ve 
minutes. “Combating tsunamis is a fi ght against 
time,” notes Masahiro Yamamoto, director of 
the Warning Centre. Th e interval between an 
earthquake and its warning signal has been 
divided by fi ve since the 1970s.  Th at is still not 
fast enough, however, for tsunamis as rapid as 
the one in Hokkaido in 1993 whose 30-foot 
wave swept over the town three minutes aft er 
the quake.
According to experts, if such a system had 
existed in the countries aff ected by the tsunami 
that hit Asia in December 2004, numerous lives 
could have been spared. Which is why 
UNESCO’s Intergovernmental Oceanographic 
Commission (IOC) is pushing for the installa-
tion of a Tsunami Warning System in the Indian 
Ocean.
| Installing an alert system
In the meantime, a temporary alert system has 
been put into place in the region. Th e Pacifi c and 
Japanese Tsunami Warning Centres communi-
cate information about tsunamis to the 25 Mem-
ber States. Warning time will be 
reduced thanks to 23 real-time 
sea-level stations, modernized by 
the IOC. Right now it takes one 
hour, which would have been fast 
enough for Sri Lanka, hit two 
hours aft er the earthquake, but not 
for Indonesia.
Each country is working out 
ways to alert its population: 
sirens, bulletins to the media, 
mobile phone text messages, 
police patrols or even using the 
minarets in Malaysia and Indo-
nesia. Th e system should be fully 
operational by 2007, but there is 
still much to do.  Even though 
Th ailand has started evacuation 
drills in tourist resorts, the task of 
informing the population remains 
a challenge. Evaluation of the 
exposed areas is also necessary, in 
order to make appropriate evacu-
ation plans and organize coastal 
zones. After the Indian Ocean, the IOC has 
decided to install the same type of system for 
the Caribbean, North-east Atlantic and Medi-
terranean seas.     ◆
M.E
The town of Banda 
Aceh (Indonesia) the 
day after the tsunami
©
 P
a
o
lo
 P
e
lle
g
ri
n
/M
a
g
n
u
m
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Ocean s
What Atmosphere!
 Oceans absorb a large quantity of the greenhouse eff ect gases that are 
emitted.  But how long can they go on acting as carbon reservoirs?
An inseparable couple runs the earth’s climate: 
the ocean and the atmosphere.  By constantly 
exchanging their energies, they carry and dis-
tribute the heat the earth receives. If the atmos-
phere seems to have «forgotten» disturbances it 
underwent 15 days prior, the ocean can remem-
ber climatic variability for decades, and even 
centuries.
Th e ocean, then, sets the rhythm. “Th e most 
obvious sign of the increase in temperature 
recorded since the beginning of the industrial 
era is an elevation in sea level,” explains Guy 
Jacques, marine ecologist and co-author of a 
book about climate change (1). Since the end of 
the 19th century, the average temperature at the 
earth’s surface has gone up a little less than one 
degree. Th e superfi cial layer of the oceans, down 
to about a hundred metres in depth, heats up 
and dilates, making the water level rise.  Th e 
20th century has recorded a yearly increase of 
1.8 mm, a rate that has been accelerating since 
the beginning of the 1990s. 
| Increased acidifi cation
Paradoxically, oceans reduce global warming. 
Indeed, they largely absorb the most important 
of the greenhouse eff ect gases: carbon dioxide 
or CO2. But their storage capacity has its limits. 
“Th e only way to get a defi nite idea about how 
oceans function is by modeling this phenome-
non,” says Maria Hood, programme specialist 
at the IOC. Especially since decreasing concen-
tration of the greenhouse eff ect gases is not all 
that is at stake: water acidifi cation caused by the 
dissolution of CO2 threatens the chemical bal-
ance of the ocean’s superfi cial layer. Th is phe-
nomenon could cause damage to marine 
ecosystems. In more acidic water, coral, calcif-
erous phytoplankton and shellfi sh have more 
diffi  culty secreting the carbonate that forms 
their skeletons. Fifty years from now, coral 
reefs, already weakened because of an increase 
in water temperature, could disappear faster 
than they form. And they make up one of the 
richest and most vital ecosystems known to 
man. ◆
M.E.
Figures
 The average depth of the ocean is 3,800 metres. The deepest part, located in 
the Pacifi c, attains a depth of 11,000 metres.
 Oceans contain 1,370 million km3 of saltwater; the Pacifi c alone represents half 
of that amount.
 Oceans and the ice fl oe make up in volume almost 98% of the planet’s water.
 Each year 380,000 km3 of water evaporate from the earth’s surface.
 The oceans have absorbed approximately 120 tons of carbon since 1800.
 Average global sea level has risen by probably 18 cm during the 20th century.
Sources: NOAA, Satellite Topex/Poseidon
Rising water 
temperature is a direct 
threat to coral reefs
1. Jacques, G. and Le Treut, H. 2004. “Climate Change” (Le changement clima-
tique). UNESCO Publishing (IOC Ocean Forum Series.)
www.unesco.org/en/courier/oceans 15
©
 P
e
te
r 
S
co
o
n
e
s/
S
ci
e
n
ce
 P
h
o
to
lib
ra
ry
/C
o
sm
o
s,
 P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
 16 The new Courier – November 2005
Ocean s
Senegal:  Coastal Zones at the Mercy 
of the Waves 
 With more than 700 kilometres of seashore, Senegal is one of the 
countries that suff ers most from coastal erosion.
Children cast their fi shing lines into the sea. At their 
feet waves break against enormous cement blocks. 
Th e blocks are all that remains of a wall built between 
the sea and the fi shermen’s houses lining the coast. 
Loosened by the swell, the wall collapsed. 
Th e ocean is advancing everywhere in Rufi sque, 
situated 25 kilometres south of Dakar. Standing in 
her doorway, in a traditional African robe, Tiébama 
can’t stop talking about the problem. “Th e wall just 
in front of my home fell down,” she complains. 
“When it rains, the sea moves forward. In two weeks 
my house will be flooded.” The rainy season is 
approaching, and the inhabitants are worried. 
Currents sweep away the sand from Rufi sque’s 
coast and deposit it further south. Th e beach is 
slowly being hollowed out and the shore is reced-
ing. Abdoulaye Ndiayhe, an old fi sherman who 
off ers his services as guide, insists that more than 
100 metres once separated the sea from a house 
whose ruins are now being lapped by the waves. 
Some fi shermen’s shacks have already been par-
tially claimed by the sea. 
Erosion of the coastline is one of the most criti-
cal environmental problems facing the coastal 
countries of West Africa, according to the “African 
Process”, a project supported by UNESCO’s Inter-
governmental Oceanographic Commission (IOC). 
Initiated by 11 sub-Saharan countries, the “African 
Process”, launched in 1998 during the Pan-African 
Conference on Sustainable Integrated Coastal 
Management (PACSICOM), analyzed the situa-
tion. In Africa, the Atlantic Ocean carries away an 
average of one or two metres of beach per year, and 
up to 20 metres in certain areas. Senegal, with its 
700 kilometres of coastline is particularly aff ected. 
More than half of the population lives on the coast 
where 85% of industry and services are located, in 
particular the country’s two most important 
resources, fi shing and tourism. Th e threat is very 
real. Already, in Mbao, to the south of Dakar, a 
mosque has fallen into the water. A little further, in 
Sally, tourist facilities have had to be abandoned. 
| Crucial need for data
People are mainly responsible for the erosion. Th e 
natural transportation of sediment by currents is 
defi nitely compounded by human activity such as 
sand extraction. Th e rise in sea level is another fac-
tor that accounts for 20% of the phenomenon. And 
for the last twenty years, the swell seems to have 
become more powerful. Climatic changes that mod-
ify winds from the West may be the cause. “Th ere 
are indications but we don’t have enough data to 
prove it,” says Isabelle Niang-Diop, a specialist in 
coastal geology at the University of Dakar.
In such a context, access to oceanographic data 
is crucial: the understanding and prediction of oce-
anic phenomena depend on it. Th at is why the ODI-
NAFRICA project (see box p. 13) has started making 
existing data available. Information centres have 
been connected to the Internet for access to world-
wide bases and specialized electronic newspapers. 
Scientifi c publication catalogues about Africa have 
been put online and oceanographic data available 
for each country has been referenced and digitized. 
“We are also centralizing data compiled in coun-
tries originating from the satellite network of the 
IOC, from oceanographic campaigns, and our seven 
coastal stations,” specifi es Anis Diallo, the adminis-
trator of Senegal’s Centre of Oceanic Data. Dakar’s 
tide gauge, which ODINAFRICA will modernize 
between now and the end of the year, will once 
again measure sea level, an important element in 
understanding coastal erosion. 
In the meantime, Tiébama worries about the 
wall that collapsed. She has been trying to call 
attention to her problem for a year now, in vain. 
Soon her house too will be lapped by the inexorable 
waves.   ◆
M.E
Battered by the 
waves, Rufi sque’s wall 
collapsed
©
 F
ré
d
é
ri
c 
N
a
u
d
o
n
/A
ls
a
ce
 M
e
d
ia
 S
ci
e
n
ce
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
1 Which artist did not sign his 
work at UNESCO’s Fontenoy 
Headquarters?
a. Picasso
b. Miró
c. Calder
d. Vasarely
2 What was the name of the 
forerunner of UNESCO founded in 
Paris in 1925?
a.  Conference of Allied Ministers of 
Education
b.  International Institute of Intellectual 
Cooperation
c.  International Council of Scientifi c 
Unions
d. League of Nations
3 The Director-General is elected 
by the General Conference for a 
term of offi  ce of what length?
a. 4 years
b. 5 years
c. 6 years
d. 7 years
4 Which statesman said, “Wars 
begin in the minds of men….”, 
a phrase that made its way 
to the preamble of UNESCO’s 
Constitution?
a. Winston Churchill
b. Jacques Maritain
c. Clement Attlee
d. Franklin D. Roosevelt
5 The above sentence from the 
preamble continues, “…it is in the 
minds of men that the defences 
of peace must be constructed.” 
These words were written by 
which poet?
a. Pablo Neruda
b. William B. Yeats
c. Archibald MacLeish
d. Paul Valéry
6 We could have ended up 
with the acronym UNECO, 
UNSCO or UNESO? One of the 
three fi elds of competence was 
the subject of a campaign and 
was added the last. Which one 
is it?
a. E for Education
b. S for Science
c. C for Culture 
 
7 Who is the most widely-
translated individual author 
in the Index Translationum 
database?
a. Jules Verne
b. Barbara Cartland
c. Lenin
d. Agatha Christie
8 According to UNESCO’s Atlas of 
the World’s Languages, how many 
languages are spoken in the 
world today?
a. 6,000
b. 4,000
c. 3,000
d. 7,000
9 UNESCO played a key role in 
the conception and construction 
of an ancient library, which its 
country unveiled in 2002. Which 
library is it?
a.  Academy of Sciences Library 
in Saint Petersburg, Russian 
Federation
b.  Bibliotheca Alexandrina, Egypt
c.  Czech National Library, Prague
d.  Lithuanian Academy of Sciences
10 The working languages of 
the General Conference are 
Arabic, Chinese, English, French, 
Russian and Spanish. But it has 
three other offi  cial languages. 
Which ones are these?
a. German, Italian and Portuguese
b. Italian, Japanese and Portuguese
c. Hindi, Italian and Portuguese
d. German, Japanese and Portuguese
ANSWERS. 1 : a. Picasso, whose mural, “Th e Fall of Icarus” hangs outside the main conference hall. 2 : b. Th e International Commission for Intellectual 
Cooperation of the League of Nations. 3 : a. 4 years (amended in 2001). 4 : c. Clement Attlee, UK Prime Minister at UNESCO Constituent Conference, 
London, November 1945. 5 : c. Archibald MacLeish, American poet, later completed the phrase. 6 : b. S for Science. During the Preparatory Conmission 
in 1945, the campaign was led by British biologists Joseph Needham and Julian Huxley, British Minister of Education Ellen Wilkinson was also a staunch 
supporter. 7 : d. Agatha Christie (5,700 references in the database). Jules Verne has 3,700, Lenin 3,500 and Cartland 3,200. 8 : a. About 6,000. 9 : b. 
Egypt’s Bibliotheca Alexandrina, inspired by the library founded by Ptolemy in 290 BC. 10 : c. Hindi, Italian and Portuguese (Rules of Procedure, General 
Conference, Rule 54).
 So you really think you know UNESCO? Here are10 questions 
to test yourself. The answers appear below. 
www.unesco.org/en/courier/interalia 17
© Drawings Christian Roux
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
 18 The new Courier – November 2005
Signatories to the World Heritage Convention on November 16, 
1972 were not fully aware of the far-reaching implications of their 
action. But now, over 30 years later, the UNESCO label on remarkable 
sites represents national pride combined with substantial benefi ts 
from tourism. Each year new sites are added to the World Heritage 
List. Further eff orts are needed, however, to make the list more 
representative. Long-term protection from war, looting, natural 
catastrophes, tourist overfl ows and climatic change represent other 
major challenges to the survival of these sites.
A Tribute to the Past
Her itage
Certain sites, like the 
Acropolis in Athens, 
are victims of their 
own success
© Martin Parr/Magnum, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Her itage
“
Come discover over 2000 years of history,” 
promises a Chinese on-line travel agency, off er-
ing tours to several World Heritage sites including 
the Summer Palace in Beijing and the Great Wall. 
Obviously, being on the List is a selling point that 
tour operators are eager to tout.
Th e success of the World Heritage List has 
not fl agged since 1972. With 180 States Parties, 
the Convention is one of the world’s most rati-
fi ed international instruments. Each year, new 
sites are added to the list, which has expanded 
from a dozen in 1978 to 812 in 2005.
Over the years, inscription on the World 
Heritage List has become synonymous with 
national pride and non-negligible windfalls in 
tourist revenue. “As a result the pressure applied 
by elected officials at nomination time has 
increased; it is proportional to the stakes,” says 
Léon Pressouyre, a UNESCO expert and pro-
fessor at the University of Paris I-Sorbonne. 
“Th ere is no doubt the candidacies are becom-
ing more politicized,” confirms Mechtild 
Rössler, Chief of Europe and North America at 
the UNESCO World Heritage Centre.
While it is diffi  cult to measure the exact 
repercussions of a nomination on the number 
of visitors, it clearly has an impact on the image 
of the site. “Visitors to Lyons increased in 
number by about 20% in 1998 aft er the city 
was inscribed,” says Bruno Delage, offi  cial in 
charge of heritage issues for the city of Lyons 
(France). “It is very diffi  cult to attribute this 
rise directly to the listing. But Lyons, which 
before was essentially a city for business tour-
ism, has recently seen cultural tourism 
develop.” 
| Growing interest in heritage
Th e general public, fond of old stones and large 
parks, has become the most vocal defender of 
the quality of sites. “Heritage, which originally 
was the privilege of experts, has become every-
body’s business,” says Dinu Bumbaru, Secre-
tary-General of ICOMOS, the International 
Council on Monuments and Sites. 
Each day, the UNESCO Heritage Centre 
receives dozens of emails, postcards or letters, 
oft en to warn of degradations noted on a site. 
“One morning, I was unable to open my desk, 
there were too many letter bags. In a few days, 
I had received 30,000 letters,” says Mechtild 
Rössler. It was just aft er the 1999 campaign 
against the expansion of a salt production 
plant at Laguna San Ignacio, near several whale 
sanctuaries at El Vizcaino, Mexico. Th e Mexi-
can government fi nally refused to authorize 
the expansion project, bowing to pressure 
from the World Heritage Committee and the 
intergovernmental body that every year exam-
ines the state of conservation of sites and nom-
inations. 
Not all such stories have a happy ending. “I 
can think of a number of monuments that are 
in very bad condition,” says Henry Cleere, of 
ICOMOS. Some sites are overrun by tourists 
and become victims of their own popularity. 
One example is Machu Picchu in Peru. Since it 
was inscribed on the Heritage List in 1983, the 
number of visitors to the Inca citadel has soared 
from 9000 in 1992 to 150,000 foreign tourists 
pouring in ten years later. Under these condi-
tions, preserving the integrity of the sites 
becomes a diffi  cult task.
| Dealing with degradation
“Today the Convention has reached the age of 
maturity,” says Francesco Bandarin, Director 
of the Heritage Centre. “In the early years, the 
priority was to identify the sites. Today the 
emphasis is on conservation. We can impose 
high standards.” In theory, at least. With a 
budget capped at US$ 4 billion annually (with 
an additional US$ 11 million of extra-budget-
ary funds designated for specifi c projects), the 
possibilities for action are limited in face of 
damage caused by war, looting, natural catas-
trophes, excessive tourism and even climatic 
change (see article p. 22). Yet the lack of 
resources is but one aspect of the problem. Th e 
means to incite countries to fulfi l their com-
mitments to conservation are also lacking. “We 
sometimes get the feeling that just getting on 
the list is the goal for certain countries,” says 
Guy Debonnet, of the Natural Heritage Section 
of the World Heritage Centre. In theory, the 
Convention allows the removal of a neglected 
site from the list, but this provision has never 
been applied. Th e only mechanism used in case 
of site degradation is to put the site on the 
World Heritage in Danger List, which coun-
tries tend to see as a sanction. As a result there 
are only 33 sites on the In Danger List when 
www.unesco.org/en/courier/heritage 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
 20 The new Courier – November 2005
probably many more are eligible. Countries 
with neglected sites oft en do not respond to 
pressure to comply with World Heritage site 
criteria. “Yet, as long as there is no effi  cient 
monitoring,” warns Raphaël Souchier, an 
anthropologist and co-author of “Le patri-
moine mondial”,1 “it is the market that will 
impose its law”. And rarely does that work out 
for the best.
Agnès Bardon
1. Le patrimoine mondial, Dominique Audrerie, Raphaël Souchier, Luc Vilar. 
Editions PUF, 1998, Paris. 
Her itage
Last but not List
 The World Heritage List gets longer each year but is this to the 
detriment of the “exceptional universal value” attributed to the sites?
When certain sites are mentioned, some experts 
frown; in their eyes, these places do not merit 
the World Heritage label. True, the List has 
become infl ated over the past 30 years, a victim 
of its own success. Is it good or bad for the con-
cept of world heritage to expand as nomina-
tions multiply? “What we are defi nitely seeing 
is a shift  away from the original, exemplary list 
of symbolic sites,” says anthropologist Raphaël 
Souchier.  
Key to the debate is the notion of “excep-
tional universal value”, one of the criteria 
applied to the candidate sites. In the early days, 
many of the sites were synonymous with “won-
ders of the world”, and were not subject to con-
troversy. No one would consider questioning 
the universal appeal of the Pyramids at Giza 
(Egypt) or of the Galapagos Islands (Ecuador), 
but more recent additions have raised eye-
brows.
Comparing the city of Brasilia (1987) and 
the home of Luis Barragan in Mexico (2004), 
Christina Cameron, Research Chair on built 
heritage at the University of Montreal (Can-
ada), points out that the Brazilian capital was 
presented as “an exceptional global example of 
modern architecture and urban planning. As 
for the Barragan house, it was considered the 
modernist building having had the greatest 
infl uence on Latin America. Th ese are diff erent 
interpretations of exceptional universal value,” 
she says1. She estimates that in fact not more 
than 5% of the sites listed in the past fi ve years 
The city of Brasilia, 
inscribed in 1987, is an 
outstanding example 
of modern architecture
©
 R
e
n
é
 B
u
rr
i/
M
a
g
n
u
m
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Her itage
are “unquestionable”, in other words going 
beyond “cultural affi  liation” because they are 
“unique and recognized by all”, compared to 20 
to 30% of sites in the early years.
| Restricting nominations
Given that there is a waiting list of over 1,500 
sites, the process is not going to be reversed any 
time soon, although some measures have been 
taken to curb countries’ enthusiasm. Since 
2003, countries can only present one site per 
year and, since 2004, only one cultural and one 
natural site can be nominated per State Party. 
But the number of listings continues to grow. 
Th ere were 34 additions in 2004, compared 
with 31 in 2001 and 33 in 1993. 
A possible solution is to close the list once 
and for all, or to set a moratorium. But these 
measures would contradict another priority set 
by the Heritage Committee, to make the list 
more representative. Despite consistent eff orts 
to include more countries from the South by 
recognizing non-built sacred sites or cultural 
landscapes, Western aesthetic values continue 
to dominate the selection. Out of 812 sites, 410 
are located in Europe or North America. “Coun-
tries still prefer to list certain types of sites such 
as historic town centres. Who even knows that 
France has the fourth largest coral reef in the 
world in New Caledonia?” points out Mechtild 
Rössler, Chief of Europe and North America at 
the UNESCO World Heritage Centre.
The list is heavily loaded with religious 
monuments, mostly Christian, to the detriment 
of other categories such as examples of modern 
or industrial architecture. Th e 160 natural sites 
are also in the minority. In a report published 
in 2004, the World Conservation Union (IUCN) 
examined all the natural sites on the Heritage 
List. Th e results show that tropical savannahs, 
tundras, temperate prairies and cold-winter 
deserts are clearly under-represented. In this 
context, it would be diffi  cult to close the list in 
the near future.
More pragmatic experts are betting on a 
natural slowdown of nominations. “I am con-
vinced,” says Henry Cleere of ICOMOS, the 
International Council on Monuments and Sites, 
“that if the inscription criteria were rigorously 
respected, the list would reach a natural cut-off  
point of 1,200 within a decade.”  ◆
A.B
1. Paper for an Experts Meeting of the World Heritage Convention held in 
Kazan, Russian Federation, April 2005. 
The universal 
importance of sites 
such as the Pyramids 
of Giza is almost 
beyond question
www.unesco.org/en/courier/heritage 21
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/F
e
lip
e
 A
lc
o
ce
b
a
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
 22 The new Courier – November 2005
Her itage
Natural Sites
Under Pressure
 The eff ects of climate change are already being observed on several 
World Heritage sites. Some environmentalists are calling for them to be 
placed on the endangered list.
From corals that are bleached due to a rise in 
water temperature, to glacier caps that are 
shrinking more and more each year, not to 
mention species that are becoming increasingly 
rare such as snow leopards, marine turtles or 
the manatee: the eff ects of global warming on 
the environment are now known. World Herit-
age sites, especially the natural ones, have obvi-
ously not been spared from this global 
phenomenon.
Some environmentalists have taken the next 
logical step and requested that certain sites be 
placed on the List of World Heritage in Danger. 
In November 2004, Pro Public (Friends of the 
Earth, Nepal) and the Climate Justice Pro-
gramme delivered several petitions to UNESCO 
requesting that the barrier reefs of Belize and 
Australia, the Huascaran National Park (Peru) 
that has the tallest tropical mountain range, and 
the Sagarmatha National Park (Nepal), over 
which looms Mount Everest, be included on the 
In Danger list. This is the first time climate 
change is invoked as a reason for such a move. 
“Th e Convention is an appropriate tool to cope 
with the degradation of the sites due to global 
warming,” says Peter Roderick, co-director of 
the Climate Justice Programme. “It is also a way 
to attract attention to the fact that these invalu-
able and exceptional sites are under threat,” he 
added. 
| Experts to study eff ects
Th e facts are undeniable. Th e snow cap of the 
Himalayas has shrunk by 30% in 30 years. In 
some areas, glacier lakes have formed and run 
the risk of one day fl ooding valley communi-
ties. Th e same is true of the mountains in the 
Huascaran National Park, which have lost 20% 
of their glacial cap since the end of the 1960s. 
As for the barrier reefs, they are threatened by 
rising water temperatures and the increase in 
CO2 concentrations in the ocean. “In the future, 
climate change could eclipse other threats 
weighing on heritage sites, especially in vulner-
able zones such as small coastal states, glaciers, 
coastal zones or coral reefs,” says David Shep-
pard, head of the Programme on Protected 
Areas for the World Conservation Union 
(IUNC). To remedy the situation he calls for 
the creation of buff er zones around the most 
threatened sites so that the ecosystems can be 
restored.
But the petitioners want to go even further. 
“We must not limit our eff orts only to the eff ects 
The snow cover on the 
Himalayas has been 
reduced by 30% in 
30 years
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/J
.M
. G
a
ss
e
n
d
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Her itage
but also to the causes of the phenomenon,” says 
Peter Roderick, who is calling for the World 
Heritage Convention to be used as a means to 
pressure States Parties into reducing their 
greenhouse gas emissions. To support this 
demand he points to the article recognising the 
need for States Parties to “ensure the transmis-
sion of the cultural and natural heritage to 
future generations”. But this interpretation is 
erroneous, according to Francesco Bandarin, 
Director  of UNESCO’s World Heritage Centre. 
“Global warming is a global problem,” he 
explains, “but the Convention, which deals with 
individual sites, rests on a very local vision. 
Th ere is, therefore, a gap between the problem 
and the available tools.” And an ad hoc tool is 
already available, the United Nations Frame-
work Convention on Climate Change.
 Nonetheless, the idea is gaining ground. 
Due to the petitions, the question was added to 
the agenda of the World Heritage Committee 
meeting in July 2005 in Durban, South Africa. 
Although the Committee did not follow the 
environmentalists’ suggestion by putting the 
four sites on the In Danger list, it did call for a 
group of experts to be convened and to provide 
a report on the issue next year. ◆
A.B
The Rebirth of Kunqu Opera
 Proclaimed by UNESCO in 2001 
as a Masterpiece of the Oral and 
Intangible Heritage, this traditional 
Chinese art, once threatened with 
extinction, is now the object of 
renewed interest. 
A young girl appears as soon as the fi rst notes of 
music are heard. Draped in a richly embroi-
dered costume, she performs graceful hand 
movements. Th e elegance of her gestures is 
enhanced by her long silk sleeves. Accompa-
nied by a fl ute, she begins to sing and the audi-
ence holds its breath.
Th e scene is an excerpt from “Th e Peony 
Pavilion”, one of the classic plays of the Kunqu 
Opera. It tells the tragic tale of Du Liniang, who 
dreams during a walk in the park that she meets 
and falls in love with a young man. Unable to 
live her dream in reality, she falls mortally ill 
and, as she is dying, asks to be buried in the gar-
den where she met her beloved. Later, Lui 
Mengmei, a student on his way to the capital, 
passes in front of Du Liniang’s house and asks 
to spend the night there. As he sleeps, he dreams 
of the young girl. Revealing to him that he is the 
one her heart desires, she asks him to open her 
coffi  n. Liu Mengmei does so and Du Liniang 
comes back to life.
Since 2004, this updated version of the play, 
produced by Bai Xianyong, one of China’s best-
known contemporary authors, has been staged 
in a dozen universities in China. Teachers and 
students can buy tickets for as little as 10 yuan. 
Each time the performance attracts a large audi-
ence. “Th e opera is so sweet, so graceful that I 
Shi Hong Mei in a 
performance of “The 
Peony Pavilion” at the 
Huguang theatre in 
Beijing
www.unesco.org/en/courier/heritage 23
©
 H
e
rv
é
 B
ru
h
a
t/
R
a
p
h
o
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
 24 The new Courier – November 2005
Her itage
was profoundly touched,” admits Hu Chunni, a 
political science student at Nanking Univer-
sity.
Th is traditional art form, whose beginnings 
can be traced to the 16th century Ming dynasty, 
is one of the oldest types of opera in China. 
Originating in the eastern province of Jiangsu, 
it combines singing, dancing, gesture and reci-
tation. Its influence on Chinese theatre and 
opera is undisputed. 
| Ongoing revival and new museum
But this golden age is long gone, and the art has 
been declining since the 18th century. Provin-
cial operas, notably that of Beijing, ended up 
replacing Kunqu. Th e performances, oft en very 
long—some could last several days—were soon 
only being staged for a handful of scholars. 
“Historically, this art was kept alive by the intel-
lectual elite. It is considered too diffi  cult for the 
general public to understand,” explains Bai 
Xianyong. In fact, in the second half of the 19th 
century, most of the actors had joined troupes 
engaged in other forms of opera. “Th ere are 
only about 600 professionals left  in China,” 
laments Ke Jun, vice-president of the Jiangsu 
Kunqu Opera Th eatre. As a result, of the 800 
plays in the repertoire at the end of the Qing 
dynasty, less than 200 remained in the 1950s 
and several dozen only have survived to the 
dawn of 21st century. 
Proclaimed a Masterpiece of the Oral and 
Intangible Heritage in 2001, kungqu has expe-
rienced a rebirth in the past few years. Four 
classical plays, including “Th e Peony Pavilion” 
or “The Palace of Eternal Life”, have been 
restored and updated. A Kunqu Opera museum 
was opened in 2003 in Suzhou, in Jiangsu Prov-
ince. The exhibits include masks, costumes, 
manuscripts and ancient instruments.
In 2004 the Chinese government decided to 
devote 10 million yuan per year to revive this 
traditional art form. Th e money will be used 
mostly to collect librettos and ancient materi-
als, to stage new plays and to train profession-
als. Some fear the allotted funds are insuffi  cient 
to fulfi l this enormous task. “Nonetheless, today 
this art form has been brought back to life,” 
notes Ke Jun.  Just like Du Liniang, the young 
girl in “Th e Peony Pavilion”. ◆
Wang Li
Th e Conventions
 Cultural Heritage and Armed Confl ict
The Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property in the Event of Armed 
Confl ict was adopted in The Hague, Netherlands, in 1954 following the massive 
destruction infl icted to cultural heritage during the Second World War It was 
the fi rst universally applicable international instrument aimed exclusively at 
protecting the cultural heritage. It applies to monuments, archaeological sites 
and also manuscripts and scientifi c collections.
 Protection of World Heritage
Adopted on November 16, 1972, the 1972 Convention Concerning the Protection 
of the World Cultural and Natural Heritage protects not only cultural sites but 
also natural and mixed sites. With 180 States Parties, it is one of the world’s most 
ratifi ed international instruments. Signatories commit to preserve the sites on 
the World Heritage List as well as heritage sites of national or regional import.
 Intangible Cultural Heritage
The Convention for the Safeguarding of the Intangible Cultural Heritage 
was adopted on October 17, 2003. Its goal is to preserve oral traditions and 
expressions, the performing arts, social practices, rituals and festive events 
as well as traditional craftsmanship. It commits States Parties to taking the 
necessary steps to safeguard this heritage and calls for inventories of the national 
elements needing protection to be established. It will go into eff ect once ratifi ed 
by 30 States. Twenty states have already signed it.
 Underwater Heritage
The UNESCO Convention for the Protection of the Underwater Cultural Heritage 
was adopted on November 2, 2001. Its goal: fi ght against the increase in 
underwater pillaging, facilitated by the development of technologies permitting 
unprecedented access to shipwrecks. No multilateral international treaty aimed 
exclusively at the protection of this heritage existed until 2001. It will go into 
eff ect once ratifi ed by 20 States; only fi ve have signed so far.
 Illegal Trade in Cultural Goods
Three multinational treaties have been drawn up to fi ght against the illegal trade 
of cultural goods: 
•  The Protocol to the Convention for the Protection of Property in the Event of 
Armed Confl ict (1954)
•  The Convention Concerning Measures to Forbid and Prevent the Illicit Import, 
Export and Transfer of Ownership of Cultural Property (1970)
•  The UNIDROIT Convention on Stolen or Illegally Exported Cultural Objects 
(1995)
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO in films
UNESCO has been featured in a number of fi lms as a setting or by way of a character. 
Here are some of them:
Charade
(Stanley Donen, 1963)
In this romantic 
comedy cum thriller 
set in Paris, Audrey 
Hepburn is a EURESCO 
interpreter whose 
husband is murdered in 
mysterious circumstances. Lost and lonely, she meets 
Cary Grant, a knight in shining armour - or is he? There 
is an establishing shot of what looks like the Fontenoy 
building, then Hepburn in a booth interpreting for 
delegates at an international conference.
Naked Love (L’Amour nu, Yannick Bellon, 1981)
Another fi lm shot in the Fontenoy building, this romantic 
melodrama stars Marlène Jobert as a UNESCO interpreter. In 
the course of an international scientifi c conference, she meets 
oceanographer Jean-Michel Folon. Romance is soon in the air but 
she discovers she has breast cancer.
All Fired Up (Tout feu, tout fl amme,
Jean-Paul Rappeneau, 1981)
Isabelle Adjani, a polytechnicienne from the 
French Ministry of the Economy, maintains 
a tempestuous relationship with her 
irresponsible father Yves Montand, intent on 
opening a casino. She decides to sabotage 
his project, but in comes an imbroglio with 
gangsters. This comedy features a scene 
where she attends a meeting actually shot in 
one of UNESCO’s conference halls. 
Bed and Board (Domicile conjugal,
François Truff aut, 1970)
In this fourth episode of the Antoine Doinel 
saga, Jean-Pierre Léaud now plays the role 
of a young married man. Bored with his new 
job, bored at home where his wife devotes 
her time to their newborn baby, he soon 
succumbs to the temptation of an aff air with 
an exotic Japanese woman, played by Hiroko 
Berghauer. One of their meetings was shot in 
UNESCO’s  Japanese garden.
www.unesco.org/en/courier/interalia 25
©
 D
R
© Coll. Prod DB©Gaumont/DR
©
 c
o
ll.
 P
ro
d
 D
B
 ©
 F
ilm
s 
d
u
 C
a
rr
o
ss
e
/D
R
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
 26 The new Courier – November 2005
Many of us do not realize to what extent copyrights 
are a part of daily life. When we read a book, 
watch a fi lm or listen to the radio, use a computer 
or go to the theatre, we are consuming goods pro-
tected by copyright. At this very moment, you can 
read this magazine or look at its photos by browsing 
on internet. Th is is possible thanks to international 
legislation that established authors’ and artists’ right 
to compensation for the use of their work, allowing 
them to continue working and to publicize their 
creations.
UNESCO is already 60 years old, but inter-
national copyright protection is much older. 
The first international document on the sub-
ject, the Bern Convention for the Protection of 
Literary and Artistic Works, today imple-
mented by the World Intellectual Property 
Organization (WIPO), was signed on Septem-
ber 9, 1886. Even further back, in the 18th cen-
tury, Diderot was already advocating for 
remuneration for artistic endeavour. In earlier 
times, artists offered their talent to the court, 
Writers, musicians, photographers, painters, computer programmers, 
translators….Without copyrights, none of these occupations could claim 
remuneration. But because culture must be accessible to the greatest 
number, UNESCO is engaged in seeking the right balance between the 
interests of the artist and those of the general public. New techniques of 
pirating musical recordings or DVDs, however, are threatening this fragile 
equilibrium. Not only the rich countries have to pay the cost.
Seeking the Right Balance
Copy r ight
© Drawings Christian Roux
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
the church or the local grandee who financed 
their activities. In return the patron appeared 
in the painting or had a book dedicated to him, 
in the manner of the Duke of Bejar for “Don 
Quixote”.
In the 20th century, copyright gained in 
importance to the point of being mentioned in 
the Universal Declaration of Human Rights. 
Th e second paragraph of Article 27 stipulates 
that “everyone has the right to the protection of 
the moral and material interests resulting from 
any scientifi c, literary or artistic production of 
which he is the author.” Th e fi rst paragraph of 
the same Article stipulates that “everyone has 
the right freely to participate in the cultural life 
of the community, to enjoy the arts and to share 
in scientifi c advancement and its benefi ts,” an 
argument used in favour of freer, and some-
times simply free, access to cultural goods.
| Pirate market
“There is no contradiction,” explains Petya 
Totcharova, expert from UNESCO’s Division 
of Arts and Cultural Enterprise, “since the idea 
is to fi nd just the right balance between the 
rights of the author and public interests.” 
Totcharova notes that “copyright does not 
override all other considerations because, when 
a higher public interest is at stake – education, 
scientific advancement etc.— international 
treaties such as the Universal Copyright Con-
vention, of which UNESCO is depository, pro-
vides for exceptions to the rule.” Being allowed 
to quote a few lines from an author without 
paying him royalties is one example.
Th is is not pirating, which is usually moti-
vated by greed. “Most people are unaware that 
some of the most sophisticated forms of organ-
ized crime are involved in pirating because it 
generates easy money, and because it is more 
acceptable and punished less harshly than drug 
or arms traffi  cking,” says Darrell Panethiere, a 
London lawyer who represents several private 
companies. Also, contrary to popular belief, 
victims are not only big London recording 
companies or Hollywood fi lm production com-
panies but also cultural industries in develop-
ing countries. “Many Latin American singers 
record in Miami, and those from French-speak-
ing Africa in Paris,” explains Panethiere, the 
author of a recently published report on the 
subject. “Th eir music is then sold worldwide 
and this money allows them to go on tour, to 
become known, to be paid royalties...If pirating 
were more tightly controlled, local labels could 
also make these recordings”.  
Mexico is a case in point. Th e culture indus-
try, with over one million works copyrighted, 
generates approximately 6% of Mexico’s gross 
domestic product, and the country was listed 
for years among the world’s top ten music pro-
ducers. Today the pirate market sells 76 million 
records a year in over 50,000 sales outlets, out-
Copy r ight
The Indian fi lm 
industry is the one 
that produces the 
most fi lms 
Th ere once was a © 
 The © symbol became the globally-accepted abbreviation for “Copyright” at 
the Universal Copyright Convention of 1952, a legislative text implemented by 
UNESCO that includes 99 States Parties.* The 1971 revised version includes 64. 
The © protects the creators of original works, who are thus granted the exclusive 
right to forbid or allow their reproduction, interpretation, public performance, 
recording, transmission, translation or adaptation.
 More recently came along the opposite idea: the copyleft, symbolized by
a . The copyleft indicates the author’s permission for others to use, copy, study, 
modify or distribute his work, with the proviso that all subsequent versions 
also be copyright-free. The growth in free software, based on decentralized 
co-operation and free access to common databases, proves that the copyleft 
concept has millions of supporters in the cyber-world. Last June, the Wikipedia 
Encyclopaedia, based on this principle and refusing all stolen or copied articles, 
beat the record  previously held by the Encyclopaedia Britannica, with 600,000 
entries in 50 languages and 400 million pages consulted per month.
 It is worth noting that from the beginning of the copyright movement, artists 
have always been free to renounce their copyright or to donate royalties to their 
favourite cause.
*In June 2005
www.unesco.org/en/courier/copyright 27
©
 B
ru
n
o
 B
a
rb
e
y/
M
a
g
n
u
m
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
 28 The new Courier – November 2005
weighing the legal market that can only sell 56 
million.  “We are studying the possibilities of 
legal reforms to increase the sanctions, because 
besides the loss of investment and jobs in the 
country, pirating is hurting our exports, which 
were signifi cant in the region and in the United 
States,” says Victor Manuel Guizar Lopez, 
Director of the Copyright Violations Protection 
Department of Mexico’s National Copyright 
Institute (INDAUTOR).
  Same story in India, which boasts the world’s 
most prolific film industry. With 1,100 films 
produced in 2003, it far outstrips Hollywood’s 
output. According to data provided by the Con-
federation of Indian Industry (CII), India’s fi lm 
industry loses US$ 70 million per year to pirat-
ing, mostly because of illegal sales abroad. It is 
estimated that four out of ten Bollywood-pro-
duced CDs and DVDs sold in the United King-
dom are counterfeit copies. These figures are 
even higher in Bangladesh or Sri Lanka— not 
counting fi lms broadcast on cable television net-
works that don’t pay royalties. And as music is a 
major ingredient of any self-respecting Bolly-
wood drama, the musical rights can represent up 
to 15% of profi ts—or losses—on certain fi lms.
Counterfeiting cuts into profi ts and jobs in 
other places besides India. In Gabon, fi lm thea-
tres have all but disappeared. In certain coun-
tries, 90% of available recordings are pirated. 
But the most serious ills are sometimes the least 
visible. “Recorded music represents the musical 
life of a society at a given point in time. If the 
best musicians of a nation are not commercially 
recorded, their works will not be preserved and 
the losses that represents to local culture are 
incalculable because, with them, an essential 
element of the country’s historical memory dis-
appears,” says Darrell Panethiere. If this dooms-
day prophecy, which holds for literature as well 
as cinema, were realized, where would one have 
to go to fi nd the “right balance”? ◆
Lucia Iglesias Kuntz
Twelve months and a day
for copyright
 Every April 23, on the anniversary of the deaths of both Miguel de Cervantes 
and William Shakespeare, a global tribute is paid to books and copyrights. In 
1995, the UNESCO General Conference proclaimed April 23 as World Book and 
Copyright Day, a day to promote reading and the protection of intellectual 
property. In addition, besides promoting legislation supporting copyright, 
the Organization publishes the online Copyright Bulletin and participates in 
campaigns to raise public awareness of the importance of copyrights. And to fi ght 
pirating, UNESCO has since 2004 organized training workshops involving police, 
customs and judicial authorities, notably in southern Europe and sub-Saharan 
Africa. UNESCO is also considering the creation of an observatory to follow 
pirating issues and serve as an electronic information centre.
“The Persistence of Piracy: the consequences for creativity,
for culture and for sustainable development” 
see:
http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0013/001396/139651e.pdf
MORE INFORMATION…
Copy r ight
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Paraguay and the Pirate’s Song
 Sadly, for geographic and 
economic reasons, Paraguay 
has become the world capital 
of pirated music.
In Ciudad del Este, 330 kilometres from Asun-
cion, the joke going around is that when direc-
tor Michael Mann arrives in town later this year 
to shoot a few scenes of his latest fi lm, Miami 
Vice, he’ll be able to buy illegal copies of his 
own movie – the fi nished version.
Joking aside, the most recent report pub-
lished by the International Federation of the 
Phonographic Industry (IFPI) calls Paraguay 
the world’s leading music pirating country. Of 
100 records sold in Paraguay, 99 are illegal cop-
ies. Paraguay tops the list of 31 countries in 
which illegal sales outstrip legal sales. Th e report 
also shows that Paraguay is a major transit sta-
tion for blank CDs, particularly those that end 
up in Brazil and Argentina. In a country with 
unemployment at 7.3% and under-employment 
at 24.1%, the IFPI fi gures are corroborated by 
the harsh reality of the street.
| Cracking down
In Asuncion, it is easy to buy a fi lm in DVD 
format or VCD (a format which can stock video 
or audio data and still photographs, although 
with poor resolution) before it opens in thea-
tres. Pirated fi lms and discs sell like hot cakes: 
at stoplights, at street corners, and even at cin-
ema entrances where a ticket can cost up to 
10,000 guaranis or US$1.50, the price of a 
pirated CD. Street vendors of illegally copied 
music, fi lms or electronic games can oft en be 
found in the vicinity of high schools, and some-
times set up shop a few metres from the court-
house or the customs offi  ce. 
Th e IFPI report was not appreciated by local 
authorities: the Director of Intellectual Prop-
erty at the Trade and Industry Ministry, Astrid 
Weller, called it exaggerated. Nonetheless, the 
government has put in place a National Plan on 
Intellectual Property to create a Special Techni-
cal Unit comprised of various authorities, 
including the armed forces, charged with appre-
hending those responsible for the production 
and sale of pirated products, an off ence punish-
able under Paraguayan law. 
Carlos Gonzalez Rufi nelli, director of the 
national intellectual property agency, 
announced measures to tighten border con-
trols, including the creation of a list of import-
ers of magnetic, optical and other support 
materials used to make counterfeit copies. In 
Copy r ight
www.unesco.org/en/courier/copyright 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
 30 The new Courier – November 2005
addition, the authorities will launch a campaign 
in schools to explaining the harm pirating 
infl icts on the country and its artists. 
But on the street, not even the poor quality 
keeps the buyers at bay. 
On a bad VCD, the picture and the sound 
are not always synchronized, or, since the fi lm 
was made in a theatre, the person sitting in 
front is visible. Oft en only half the fi lm has been 
recorded. And many of the CDs are defective 
and can’t be played. But the most compelling 
argument for buying pirated works isn’t qual-
ity, it’s the low price.
Yet Paraguay’s main source of revenue from 
the pirated products doesn’t come from local 
sales but from massive export. In the border 
regions, particularly Upper Parana, the police 
are constantly dismantling large production 
units equipped with the most sophisticated 
technology. Yet, these arrests are insuffi  cient to 
put an end to this “industry”, which fl ourishes, 
often with the complicity of authorities and 
local criminals. According to the 2005 Com-
mercial Piracy Report, 11 million blank CDs 
were already confi scated this year, twelve indict-
ments were handed down in two major cases 
linked to pirating and 57 import licences were 
withdrawn from suspect fi rms.
Living from one’s art has never been easy, 
but pirating complicates the situation even 
more. David Arriola, manager of Kamikaze, a 
record label that has been launching young Par-
aguayan talent for the past fi ve years, still can’t 
get over what happened to the nationally-
known rock group Paiko. “When we produced 
the fi rst CD, “Al natural”, it took a year before it 
was pirated. For the second, illegal copies were 
on the streets the day aft er the offi  cial release.... 
We were stunned,” he says. 
We have to put a stop to these practices, in 
the name of Shakespeare and Cervantes. ◆
Natalia Daporta
http://www.ifpi.org
MORE INFORMATION…
Facts and fi gures
 The fi lm industry in the United States loses 3 billion dollars a year because of 
pirating.
 In 2004, 34% of computer software was pirated, one per cent less than in 2003. 
Financial loss, however, increased at the same time from 29 to 33 billion dollars.
 A 10% reduction in software pirating would allow the creation of 1.5 million 
jobs and generate globally 64 billion dollars in taxes.
 In Colombia, authorities confi scated 37,000 pirated books in 1998 and 180,000 
in 2003. In 2005, the publisher Norma advanced the release date of Gabriel Garcia 
Marquez’s latest book, “Memories of my Melancholy Whores”, because pirated 
versions were already in circulation.
Sources: Motion Picture Association, Business Software Alliance, Norma Publishing
Copy r ight
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Happy Anniversaries!
 In August 1947, the UNESCO Monitor appeared, ancestor of the Courier.
Today, the magazine is becoming an on-line publication.
60th, November 2005, published in 6 languages.
With the printing of this anniversary issue of The UNESCO Courier, another page is turned in the history of the magazine since its 
fi rst appearance in 1948. This is the last on paper; henceforth, The New Courier will be available exclusively online, completing the 
transition begun in 2002. Here is a glimpse of past anniversary issues:
50th, July-August 1996, published in 30 languages.
What does UNESCO’s 50th anniversary mean to you? Instead of calling on intellectuals and specialists in the Organization’s various 
fi elds of competence, the magazine gave twenty cartoonists a free hand to express their opinions and judgments. Their reactions 
comprise a series of subjective impressions rather than objective evaluation, a blend of approval and criticism, in this double 
comic-strip issue. 
40th, October 1985, published in 32 languages, with Braille selections in 4 languages.
As part of an ongoing modernization programme, this is the fi rst fully computerized issue of the English, French and Spanish 
editions, prepared entirely in-house up to the fi nal photogravure and printing stage. Instead of taking stock of UNESCO’s 
achievements, the issue leads readers on a journey back to the world of 1945, to witness the birth of UNESCO and the eff orts of 
the men and women whose commitment brought it to life.
30th, March 1976, published in 15 languages.
Julian Huxley, UNESCO’s fi rst director-general in 1946, is the issue’s main subject, with excerpts from the historic document 
he drafted on the Organization’s purpose and philosophy and a tribute to the man by Paulo E. de Berrêdo Carneiro, eminent 
Brazilian scientist. A collective text on the roots of a world crisis, penned by 18 of the world’s leading fi gures in education, science 
and culture, is the other main feature in the issue.
25th, August-September 1971, published in 13 languages. 
For this issue, UNESCO opened its doors to a 25-year-old Canadian student who spent months probing and delving into the Paris 
headquarters. The result is a lively assessment of UNESCO’s activities, viewed with the objectivity of an outsider mixed with the 
critical candour of youth. It also demonstrates how UNESCO’s approach towards young people has evolved over 25 years. 
20th, July-August 1966, published in 9 languages. 
Proudly announcing 8 pages in colour, the issue examines major changes in education, science, culture, mass media and 
social science in the world during the past 20 years and what UNESCO has achieved in each domain. Other stories focus on the 
publication of the six-volume History of Mankind in science and culture and a compilation of quotations on peace by leading 
personalities involved in UNESCO’s creation.
10th, November-December 1956, published in English, French and Spanish.
UNESCO’s fi rst World Survey of Education, published in 1955, revealed that some 250 million children in the world, one out of ten, 
were out of school. The cover, featuring three children dwarfed by a huge globe, is symbolic of their plight. Other main subjects in 
the issue include an assessment of the havoc left by the Second World War; and a feature on the construction of the soon-to-be-
completed Fontenoy headquarters.
These issues are available online at www.unesco.org/courier.
www.unesco.org/en/courier/interalia 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
 32 The new Courier – November 2005
Seoul, February 2004. Professor Hwang Woo-suk 
has just cloned a human embryo for the fi rst 
time. Th e aim is not to obtain a genetically per-
fect baby, but rather embryonic stem cells, which 
could eventually treat diseases that are incurable 
at present. Unlike many countries, the Republic of 
Korea allows therapeutic cloning.
As the fi rst scientist to successfully carry out 
such a feat, Hwang Woo-suk had something to 
celebrate. But his overriding concern was to 
discuss the meaning of this discovery with the 
Archbishop of Seoul, Nicholas Cheong Jin-suk. 
Th e two men met on June 15, 2005. For an hour, 
the professor and the man of the church spoke 
of the beginning of life, respect for human dig-
nity and human rights, the status of the embryo, 
the powers of science and the duties of con-
science... in a word, bioethics.
Cloning, using genetic data, pre-implantation diagnosis, research on 
embryonic stem cells... All these scientifi c advances are a double-edged 
sword: promising for patients and problematic from an ethical point of 
view. In order to guide states in considering the issues, UNESCO has for 
many years played the role of ethical watchdog. After texts on the human 
genome (1997) and on human genetic data (2003), the Organization has 
just adopted the Universal Declaration on Bioethics and Human Rights.
Giving Science
a Conscience
Bioethics
© Drawings Christian Roux
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Faced with the speed of scientifi c progress, 
governments from now on must give their ver-
dict on these issues, as well as on medically 
assisted procreation or the 
choice of a child’s gender 
before birth. Some have already 
established legal mechanisms, 
while others have not.
In line with its mandate as 
an ethical watchdog, UNESCO 
took an early interest in the 
progress of scientifi c research. 
Th e Organization has already 
adopted two declarations, in 
1997 and 2003, to respond 
specifically to the problems 
posed by biology and genetics 
(see box below). The third 
phase of this consultation 
process is the Universal Decla-
ration on Bioethics and Human Rights, and its 
adoption by UNESCO’s General Conference in 
autumn 2005. Th is text is designed as a “global 
response to the ethical implications” arising 
from “rapid developments in science and 
 technology”.
In reality, the Declaration 
gives no defi nitive response to 
the questions raised by thera-
peutic cloning or stem cell 
research. Its role is more to 
nurture a wider debate. “Th e 
status of the embryo, euthana-
sia and abortion are not 
included in it because they are 
too controversial,” UNESCO’s 
Director of Ethics, Henk ten 
Have, explains.
The willingness to find a 
consensus between Member 
States on this diffi  cult subject 
has been paramount at each 
stage of the draft ing process. 
For example, some States are upset that the 
Declaration makes no mention of the “right to 
life”. It is the most sensitive question of all: does 
life begin at birth? Or at conception? Or at the 
fetal stage? Th e experts eventually decided to 
talk about “respect for the life of human beings”. 
It is up to each State to decide what is meant by 
“human being”.
| Social function of science
However, at the initiative of developing coun-
tries, the scope of the Declaration has been wid-
ened to include social and environmental issues. 
Th e text says that progress in science and tech-
nology should make it easier for the destitute to 
have access to proper care, medicine, food and 
water. Additionally, some Latin American 
countries have insisted that the Declaration 
includes a mention of the “illicit trade” in 
“genetic resources”, an allusion to bio-piracy, 
the exploitation of natural resources by private 
companies without the profits being fairly 
shared (see article p. 36). “Science must also be 
conscious of its social function,” said one Latin-
American delegate, explaining why the scope of 
the text needs to be widened. “Research into 
stem cells and cloning does not for now aff ect 
the lives of most people. Th ey remain a hope for 
the future, but right now, people are dying 
because of poor health conditions. We must 
concentrate on this problem,” Henk ten Have 
added.
Bioethics
Th e two previous UNESCO
declarations
 To safeguard the principles of personal dignity and freedom against risks 
of abuse in bio-medical research, UNESCO set up the International Bioethics 
Committee (IBC) in 1993. This consultative body comprises 36 independent 
members from diff erent cultures who are eminent fi gures in varied disciplines: 
doctors and geneticists work with chemists, lawyers, anthropologists, 
philosophers and historians. In 1998, UNESCO also set up an Intergovernmental 
Bioethics Committee (IGBC), bringing together 36 representatives of UNESCO 
Member States who act as a bridge between the independent experts and the 
government bodies dealing with bioethics.
 The work of the International Bioethics Committee (IBC) led to the Universal 
Declaration on the Human Genome and Human Rights, which was adopted in 
1997 by the UNESCO General Conference. In 1998, the United Nations General 
Assembly adopted the text, which already at that stage condemned human 
cloning for reproductive ends. Since then, many countries have incorporated the 
principles set out in this Declaration into their national legislation.
 In 2003, UNESCO adopted an International Declaration on Human Genetic Data. 
The aim was to ensure that the dignity, rights and freedoms of individuals are 
respected in the “collection, treatment, use and preservation” of genetic data 
obtained from blood, skin, bones, etc. The Declaration states that “the identity of 
the person will not be reduced to genetic characteristics”.
www.unesco.org/en/courier/bioethics 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
 34 The new Courier – November 2005
Bioethics
 “We have fi lled a legal, political and ethical 
void,” said Uruguay’s Ambassador to UNESCO, 
Pablo Sader, who chaired the governmental 
experts’ meetings to discuss the draft  conven-
tion developed by the International Bioethics 
Committee (IBC). “Th is document must inspire 
legislation and guide the debate in each coun-
try.” Its role is indeed to inspire and not to 
coerce: it is a declaration, which is not compul-
sory, rather than a far more constraining con-
vention. It may be too early for the latter. Th e 
21st century has only just begun. ◆
Samir Tounsi
Born to Cure a Brother or Sister
 Brought into the world to save a member of their family, the “life-
saving babies” raise a number of ethical issues.
Six-year-old Ian* suf-
fers from a serious 
blood disease. To save 
him, his parents, from 
Leeds in the United 
Kingdom, had only 
one option: to con-
ceive another child 
with the same cell tis-
sue as his. Th e tissue 
is removed at birth 
from the umbilical 
cord, or later from 
the bone marrow. 
Ian’s mother became 
pregnant, but the 
fetus was carrying the same disease. She did not 
keep the baby. A second child was born and its 
tissue was compatible with Ian’s.
To avoid the risks inherent in genetics, it is 
now possible to select the embryo of the “life-
saving baby” that could save Ian. In 2001, the 
Human Fertility and Embryology Authority 
(HFEA), the government body that supervises 
clinics conducting in vitro fertilization, author-
ized pre-implantation diagnosis. A group called 
Comment on Reproductive Ethics (Core) 
immediately took the case to the courts. Aft er 
several more twists, Britain’s highest court, the 
Law Lords, fi nally confi rmed the HFEA’s deci-
sion in April 2005.
Core is still furious. “We think it is funda-
mentally wrong to conceive a child just to help 
another, regardless of how serious a disease 
they have,” said its director and founder, Jose-
phine Quintavalle. Her fear is that it will lead to 
“the creation of babies who are the right sex and 
have the right hair colour.”
“Th e use of such technology is morally justi-
fi ed when it is strictly regulated,” retorts the 
doctor who treated Ian. Th e HFEA stresses that 
it grants permission for pre-implantation 
 diagnosis only on a case by case basis. And it 
points out that 80% of Britons are opposed to 
choosing the sex of babies without a medical 
reason. ◆
S.T.
*The name has been changed
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Bioethics
“One day, I will walk again.” Paralysed from the 
age of 16, Jim Langevin, a United States Con-
gressman from the state of Rhode Island, is pin-
ning his hopes on research into embryonic stem 
cells (ESC). He spoke in support of the research 
at the US Congress in May 2005.
Like him, many researchers think that these 
cells can be used to regenerate organs and dis-
eased tissue. Not yet assigned a function, they 
can play any role. They are “pluripotent” – 
meaning that they can become any sort of cell, 
whether blood, muscle or nerve. Th eir regener-
ative capacity appears to be superior to that of 
adult cells taken from the spine or the umbilical 
cord.
But do we have the right to use and then 
destroy human embryos in order to obtain the 
embryonic stem cells? Even if these are ‘extra’ 
embryos, which would not be used for  in vitro 
conceptions? Most religious authorities are 
opposed to the idea, on the grounds of respect 
for human embryos.
| Cloning for research
Th e research on ESCs also raises the issue of co-
called “therapeutic” cloning. Researchers have 
in fact already cloned embryos from the cells of 
a patient, in order to obtain stem cells with the 
same genetic characteristics as the patient. But 
even when it is done for therapeutic reasons, 
cloning inspires fear. In March 2005, the Gen-
eral Assembly of the United Nations adopted a 
Declaration which invites all Member States to 
“ban any form of human cloning insofar as it is 
incompatible with human dignity”. UNESCO, 
for its part, prefers to refer not to “therapeutic 
cloning” but to “cloning for research pur-
poses”.
For the time being, laws and practices vary 
from one country to another. Th e Republic of 
Korea allows cloning for research purposes but 
bans human cloning. Th e United States recently 
considered relaxing the restrictions it put in 
place in 2001 on research into ESCs. Germany 
and Costa Rica ban the destruction of embryos 
for research purposes. In France, ten research-
ers signed a petition calling for therapeutic 
cloning to be made legal.
As the debates continue, so does the research. 
A privately-owned American company, Geron, 
announced that, providing permission is 
granted by relevant authorities, it would carry 
out the fi rst tests of ESCs on humans in 2006 to 
treat lesions to the spinal cord. But there’s no 
question yet of a cure. ESCs are, at best, a hope 
for the future. ◆
Samir Tounsi
The Cells of Discord
 While they hold out the hope of curing some serious diseases, embryonic 
stem cells raise the question of the moral status of the embryo.
www.unesco.org/en/courier/bioethics 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
 36 The new Courier – November 2005
Bioethics
Plant Pirates in Costa Rica
Several years ago Costa Rica began taking action to fi ght bio-piracy and 
to put to better use the richness of its fl ora, which is highly prized by the 
pharmaceutical industry.
Some of the Ngobe, indigenous people who live 
in Costa Rica and Panama, still remember how, 
in the 1990s, foreign doctors arrived among 
them – not to give them medical care, but to 
take samples of their blood and study their 
genes. A professor of environmental science at 
the University of Costa Rica, Silvia Rodriguez, 
says that during this period scientists collected 
DNA from indigenous communities in several 
countries, as part of a programme called 
“Human Genetic Diversity”, involving scien-
tists from America, Europe and Japan. Th is 
genetic information was supposed to explain 
the resistance or the vulnerability of these eth-
nic groups to certain diseases.  
Two doctors even attempted to patent cel-
lular information from a Ngobe woman in Pan-
ama without her knowledge, in order to study 
her supposed resistance to certain types of 
leukemia. In the face of opposition from indig-
enous organizations, environmental campaign-
ers and academics, the two American doctors, 
Jonathan E. Kaplan and Michael Dale Laimore, 
dropped their project.
But this use of genetic information from 
individuals without their clear consent is not 
the only type of bio-piracy. Costa Rica, which 
has a wealth of biodiversity, also has to defend 
itself against the illicit exploitation of its fl ora. 
Much is at stake: the plants are heavily used by 
the pharmaceutical industry. “Drugs made from 
plants generate business worth US$78 billion a 
year,” said the president of the Costa Rican fed-
eration for nature conservation, Isaac Rojas.
To ensure that the exploitation of its natural 
resources benefi ts the country itself, Costa Rica 
has created an almost unique institution: the 
National Institute of Biodiversity (Inbio). 
Founded as a private venture in 1989, Inbio has 
signed more than 30 agreements with local and 
foreign laboratories. It is currently working in 
partnership with the American biotechnology 
fi rm Diversa to develop new textile products 
using micro-organisms that are “made in Costa 
Rica”. Inbio has also allowed a Costa Rican lab-
oratory, Lisan, to develop drugs to treat diges-
tive and renal problems using the Quassia 
Amara bush, whose medicinal virtues have been 
familiar to Central American people for centu-
ries.
| Sharing profi ts
“Research and prospecting are expensive and 
we believe they should be undertaken in part-
nership with big companies who have the tech-
nology while we have the knowledge of 
biodiversity,” said Ana Lorena Guevara, one of 
Inbio’s directors.
But this approach does not satisfy everyone. 
Some environmental campaigners denounce 
what they see as “privatisation of biodiversity”. 
“We are at the mercy of a few laboratories. We 
don’t know how much they earn and how much 
they give back to us,” says Professor Rodriguez. 
Inbio defends itself against such accusations by 
stressing its compliance with a 1998 law on bio-
diversity.
At the request of countries from the south-
ern hemisphere, the Universal Declaration on 
Bioethics and Human Rights, adopted by 
UNESCO in autumn 2005, states that “scien-
tifi c research is only to be carried out with the 
prior, free, express and informed consent of the 
person concerned”. In future, the Ngobes will 
be able to turn to that article for protection. ◆
Juan Roman Rojas
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO’s First and Latest
Did you know that some of UNESCO’s present institutes and programmes actually predate 
the Organization’s creation? Such is the case of the International Bureau of Education, 
established in 1925. Likewise, Index Translationum was initiated by the International 
Institute of Intellectual Cooperation in 1931. In its 60 years of existence, UNESCO has had 
its share of “fi rsts”. Here are some of them – with updates on the latest developments.
Member States
In 1945, 37 countries signed the UNESCO Constitution, which came into 
force a year later after ratifi cation by 20 signatories. They became the 
fi rst founders of the Organization. With the entry of Brunei Darussalam 
in March 2005, the Organization now comprises 191 Member States and 
6 Associate Members.
National commissions
Brazil was the fi rst Member State to set up one in 1946, followed by six 
others the same year. The latest to establish its national commission for the 
fi rst time was Solomon Islands in 2002, bringing the current total to 192.
Field offi  ces
The fi rst to open was in New York in 1946. The latest was in 2004, the 
UNESCO Offi  ce for Iraq, currently based in Amman. 
Associated Schools Project Network
Launched in 1953 with 33 secondary schools in 15 Member States, the 
latest to join are fi ve schools in Libyan Arab Jamahiriya in 2004. The 
current total for 2005 is 7,900 institutions in 175 countries.
Non-governmental organizations
The fi rst agreement with an NGO was in 1946 with the International 
Council of Scientifi c Unions (ICSU), now known as the International 
Council for Science. To date, 230 NGOs maintain offi  cial relations with 
UNESCO and many others cooperate on an occasional basis.
Clubs
The fi rst to be established was in Sendai, Japan in 1947. In 2005 the 
movement includes 3,600 clubs, centres and associations in 90 countries.
Fellows
Thirteen fellows from six countries were the fi rst awardees in 1947. 
Between 1948 and 1968, some 11,000 people received fellowships and 
study grants, 17% of them women. Today, about 20 awards are given 
monthly. The Fellowships Section distributed awards to some 350 people 
from 123 countries during the period 2004-2005, 56% of them women.
Prizes
The Kalinga Prize for the Popularization of Science, created in 1951, was 
the fi rst. Today, the number of prizes stands at 33, the latest being the 
UNESCO/Jikji Memory of the World Prize, established in 2004. Funded by 
the Republic of Korea, it commemorates the inscription of the Jikji, the 
oldest known book of movable metal print in the world.
Laureates
French physicist and Nobel Prize laureate Louis de Broglie was UNESCO’s 
fi rst prize winner in 1952 when he received the Kalinga Prize. The latest 
laureate is Indian artist Ashok Sukumaran, winner of the main Digital 
Arts Award, “City and Creative Media”.  
World Heritage sites
The nomination of the Galápagos Islands in Ecuador was the fi rst to 
reach UNESCO in 1978, followed by 11 others in seven countries. Twenty-
four new sites were inscribed in 2005, the latest being the Urban Historic 
Centre of Cienfuegos in Cuba. Today, the list comprises 812 sites from 
137 States Parties to the World Heritage Convention.
Goodwill Ambassadors
The diplomat and businessman Sheikh Ghassan I. Shaker was fi rst to be 
appointed in 1990. Nelson Mandela, the former South African president, 
is the latest to join the ranks in 2005.
Artists for Peace
Céline Dion, the popular Canadian singer, was the fi rst appointee in 
1999. The latest is French sculptor and poet Gérard Voisin in 2005.
Commemorative medals
UNESCO issued its fi rst medals, a set of three, in 1961 to celebrate 
its 20th anniversary. The newest medal was issued in October and 
commemorates UNESCO’s 60th anniversary. 
www.unesco.org/en/courier/interalia 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
 38 The new Courier – November 2005
On the eve of World Environment Day (June 5) 
this year, the BBC news website showed a 
number of ‘before and aft er’ images of various 
places around the globe, taken several years apart. 
Th e message is clear. Th e images tell a story of 
dramatic, accelerating loss over the past decades: 
loss of forests, wetlands, fauna, glaciers, air quality, 
fresh water, beaches, sea ice.... Th e list is long. And 
the question the images raise no longer seems to be 
‘what can we do?’ but ‘is it too late?’
Some refuse a ‘doom and gloom’ scenario. 
Urbanisation, for example, may be paradoxi-
cally the best solution to rising population in 
the face of fi nite resources. Some argue that a 
city’s environmental impact per capita is less-
ened, as people may be packed into a relatively 
small space, compared to individual houses 
surrounded by lawn. Others argue that while 
this may be true locally, cities have an unseen 
impact on the ecology of places hundreds, even 
thousands, of kilometres away that supply them 
with water, energy, food and clothing. 
Urbanisation does not only destroy biodi-
versity, either, even if it leads to the disappear-
ance of certain plants. Alien species may not 
always be unwelcome, if they succeed in surviv-
ing in this environment. “Th e most important 
thing is that plants continue to function, 
In French Guyana, a 
forest fl ooded by the 
installation of a dam
With a population due to number 9 billion people by 2050, dwindling 
resources and ever-increasing threats to biodiversity, the Earth is 
suff ering from disquieting symptoms. Some of the damage is already 
irreversible. But all is not lost. Certain changes linked to global warming 
may even be benefi cial, if we can manage them.
Taking the Pulse of the Planet
Env ironment
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
whether they’re from China or Siberia,” says 
Charles Peters, Curator of Economic Botany at 
the New York Botanical Garden (USA), speak-
ing at a 2003 meeting on urban ecology co-
organised by UNESCO.
| Ecosystem approach
According to the World Conservation Union 
(IUCN), the spread of invasive alien species is 
nevertheless a threat to biodiversity. Out of 
their native context, they destroy whole ecosys-
tems. And biodiversity is the best buff er against 
change, constituting a vast reservoir of evolu-
tionary possibilities. 
In South Africa, white settlers introduced 
several species of fast-growing Australian aca-
cia for timber, and to stabilise dunes. In the 
Cape region (see p. 43), the introduced species 
became more successful than the indigenous 
vegetation, rapidly replacing thousands of hec-
tares of one of the world’s richest fl oral king-
doms with water-thirsty shrubs that support 
few of the native birds, insects and reptiles. 
Today, across South Africa, alien invasive plants 
use an estimated 3.3 billion cubic metres more 
water than indigenous plants, in a region that is 
already prone to drought.
In 1995, the South African government 
introduced its Working for Water programme 
and legislation to clear invasive alien species 
and replant indigenous species. It has since 
provided over 40,000 jobs nationally, through 
some 300 programmes, most of them for the 
poorest of the poor, and is one of the most suc-
cessful examples anywhere that environmental 
change can be reversible.
Meanwhile, the Convention on Biodiversity, 
signed by 150 government leaders at the 1992 
Rio Earth Summit, acknowledges that the tradi-
tional conservation ideal of preserving pristine 
nature from the destructive infl uence of people 
is no longer viable. Instead, it adopts an ‘eco-
system approach’, which it defi nes as “a strategy 
for the integrated management of land, water 
and living resources that promotes conserva-
tion and sustainable use in an equitable way.” 
UNESCO’s Man and the Biosphere programme 
(MAB), launched 21 years before Rio in 1971, 
anticipated this inclusive approach.
Recently, in partnership with UNESCO’s 
International Hydrological programme (IHP) 
and the Mountain Research Institute (MRI), 
MAB set up a network of biosphere reserves in 
mountain areas to monitor global change – both 
Biosphere Reserves
 UNESCO launched its Man and the Biosphere programme in 1971. Five years 
later, it named the fi rst 53 Biosphere Reserves in 8 countries. This network has 
since grown to include today 482 sites in 102 countries. 
 Biosphere Reserves are areas of land or coast where the aim is to reconcile the 
conservation of biodiversity with its sustainable use. They are internationally 
recognized, yet nominated by national governments and remaining under 
sovereign jurisdiction of the states where they are located.
 As a rule they are organized into three interrelated zones, known as the core 
area, the buff er zone and the transition area. Only the core area requires legal 
protection, as it is intended to give long-term protection to the landscapes, 
ecosystems and species it contains. The transition area contains human 
settlements, agriculture, etc, while the buff er zone helps limit human impacts on 
the core. Some Biosphere Reserves straddle several countries.
Env ironment
www.unesco.org/en/courier/environment 39
© Patrick Bard/Editingserver.com
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
 40 The new Courier – November 2005
social and climate-related. “Mountain areas are 
very sensitive to climate change,” says Greg 
Greenwood, Director of MRI. “Higher eleva-
tions are expected to warm faster than lower 
elevations in the global circulation models that 
we have.” 
Natarajan Ishwaran, Director of UNESCO’s 
Natural and Earth Sciences Division, is not a 
‘doom and gloom’ supporter either. “Th e chal-
lenge is to identify examples of what works and 
to replicate them, ideally with short-term results 
that people can see,” he says, stressing that it is 
essential to be pragmatic. Using the example of 
illegal logging, he asks: “How do you stop it? 
It’s not just an enforcement issue. First of all 
you have to start talking to the local logging 
industry and see if you can win friends and con-
verts who can help make the changes happen in 
the short term. This can mean some radical 
approaches, like encouraging the poacher to 
turn gamekeeper.” This has literally become 
reality in several ecotourism projects.
Perhaps it’s time to remember Wendy 
Campbell-Purdie, a British woman who, in the 
1960s, planted 130,000 trees on the edge of the 
Sahara in Bou Saada (Algeria) as a ‘green wall’ 
against desertifi cation. Even if her choice of tree 
was not ideal, it worked, with crops soon grow-
ing in their shade. And 2006 is, aft er all, the 
International Year of the Desert. ◆
Peter Coles
Env ironment
The Inuit, First Witnesses
of Climate Changes
 In the Arctic, Inuit people have been noticing the signs of global 
warming for years. 
As a child, Shari Fox Gearheard used to dig 
snow caves around her house in Ontario (Can-
ada), crawl inside and fall asleep, “because it 
was so peaceful”. A couple of decades later, now 
a postdoctoral researcher with the National 
Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration 
(NOAA) based at Harvard University, she lives 
with the Inuit people of Clyde River, Nunavut, 
on the eastern shores of Baffi  n Island (Canada). 
In line with the work of UNESCO’s LINKS and 
MOST programmes that document and pro-
mote indigenous knowledge, she is recording 
the Inuit’s observations of climate change.
According to one of the elders Gearheard 
has interviewed, the weather has become 
uggianaqtuq, which, roughly translated, means 
‘like a familiar friend behaving strangely’. About 
40 or 50 years ago, a snow storm would last for 
four or fi ve days. On the sixth or seventh day 
the weather would improve, and remain good 
for the rest of the season. Nowadays the storms 
come suddenly with no warning, and more 
oft en. Th is means it is hard for Inuit to know 
when it is safe to set off  on long hunting trips. 
“Some people from my community lost their 
lives because they got stranded in a storm that 
happened unexpectedly,” says Norman Attun-
gala, an elder in Baker Lake, several hundred 
kilometres inland. 
Wind patterns have also changed, adding a 
new danger to hunting trips. “Th e wind is pack-
ing the snow too hard to build igloos,” Gear-
heard explains, “making it impossible to build a 
shelter and wait out unexpected bad weather.” 
Meanwhile, the motorised skidoos that most 
hunters now use are less reliable than tradi-
tional dog sleds. “Dogs always knew how to get 
back to their home camp, even during a storm 
or at night,” says Th omas Qaqimat from Baker 
Lake. 
Indigenous knowledge best practices: See http://www.unesco.org/most/bpindi.htm 
 MORE INFORMATION…
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
For Gearheard, the Inuit observations can 
complement scientific knowledge and vice 
versa. “As remote sensing, climate models and 
weather models move to finer scales, Inuit 
should be partners with scientists, because they 
can provide ‘ground truth’ to test remote fi nd-
ings.” But, she says, the two cannot always be 
mapped directly onto one another. “In science,” 
she says, “weather is separated into tempera-
ture, pressure, wind, snow depth, and so on. 
For the Inuit it is a complex whole.” 
| Exchange projects
It is also instructive when science and local 
observations don’t match. For the Inuit, Gear-
heard notes, aniuvat – snow patches that never 
melt – have “always” been there. But scientifi c 
studies of lichen on rocks show that once upon 
a time, further back in history than Inuit mem-
ory goes, the snow was not there. So the melting 
aniuvat “is not necessarily a sign of global warm-
ing, but of the environment going back to nor-
mal.” Th e Inuit fi nd this interesting, she adds.
Th e Inuit may not know that the tempera-
ture of permafrost has risen by two degrees over 
the past decades (see box), but they do see their 
rivers and lakes drying up, as the no longer fro-
zen ground becomes porous, while roads buckle 
and houses and trees collapse or lean over at 
bizarre angles. Meanwhile, in Baker Lake, an 
island to which locals used to canoe in summer 
can now be reached on foot. 
Indigenous peoples from the region are now 
getting together to pool their experiences, as in 
the exchange project between the Inuit of Clyde 
River and Iñupiat of Barrow (Alaska). And, 
Env ironment
Famine or feast?
 Average temperatures have risen in the Arctic over the past few decades at 
twice the rate of the rest of the world, according to a massive 1,400-page analysis 
put together by over 250 scientists. Snow cover has shrunk by 10% over the 
past 30 years, and is expected to decline by a further 10 to 20% by 2070. Sea ice 
– which, to all intents and purposes is ‘land’ for the Inuit, polar bears and walrus 
– has reduced 5% - 10% in extent and 10 - 15% in thickness, says the report, and 
is expected to decline 10 - 50% by 2100. 
 One of the reasons the rate of change is faster in polar areas is that, as the 
snow cover disappears, it exposes bare black rock, which radiates more heat, 
rather than refl ecting it. The report points the fi nger at human activity outside 
the region – the emission of greenhouse gases in industrialised countries.
 The warming of the Arctic may threaten the traditional way of life of the 
region’s 400,000 indigenous people (in eight nations), drive the polar bear 
extinct, and switch off  ocean currents that warm Europe. Yet it could also 
bring benefi ts, says the report, at least in the short term. As permafrost melts, 
forests become viable further north – a potential source of new revenue and 
employment, and also a ‘sink’ to absorb carbon dioxide. Freshwater fi sh and 
berries may become more abundant, while new opportunities for agriculture 
appear. Meanwhile, new shipping lanes could open, gas and oil fi elds could 
become exposed for drilling, and new fi shing grounds appear as migration 
patterns change. 
 But, warns the report, the knock-on eff ects of such changes are unpredictable, 
and not limited to the Arctic. As ecosystems get shaken up, new forms of disease 
could emerge, while sea level from melting snow and permafrost could swamp 
low–lying coastal areas from Bangladesh to Florida.
Peter Paneak,
Clyde River,
Nunavut.
through the Inuit Circumpolar Conference 
(ICC), they have even formed a pressure group 
to sue the United States, which they accuse of 
destroying their way of life by polluting, while 
being unwilling to reduce greenhouse gas emis-
sions through the Kyoto Protocol. ◆
P.C.
www.unesco.org/en/courier/environment 41
©
 S
h
a
ri
 G
e
a
rh
e
a
rd
, N
u
n
a
v
u
t
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
 42 The new Courier – November 2005
Selling the Air We Breathe
 Starting this year, countries can now trade a new commodity: 
greenhouse gases
Clemens Hüttner is no ordinary trader. Since April 
this year, he has been trading on a brand-new kind 
of commodity market. He is not dealing in coff ee 
or minerals, though, but industrial emissions of 
carbon dioxide, one of the so-called greenhouse 
gases thought to be contributing to a global rise in 
temperature since the industrial era began. 
Under the Kyoto Protocol, which came into 
force on February 16 this year, 38 industrialised 
countries, of the total 55 signatories, committed 
themselves to reduce by 2012 their combined 
emissions of greenhouse gases to at least 5 percent 
below the levels they were emitting in 1990. Th e 
European Union, as a whole, has committed itself 
to do even better, reducing its overall emissions by 
8% below 1990 levels. 
To reach these goals, each of the 38 countries 
has set target emissions for their polluting indus-
tries. At the end of the year, industries that come 
under target will get “carbon credits” – a sort of 
pollution allowance – while those that come out 
over the limit will either have to pay a fi ne – around 
40 euros for each tonne of CO2 over limit – or will 
have to buy credits from cleaner industries. Several 
“carbon exchanges” already exist, the largest being 
the International Petroleum Exchange in London, 
where Clemens Hüttner trades. Only European 
industries are trading until 2008, when the global 
emission market opens.
So far, says Hüttner, who trades on behalf of a 
major cement producer, Heidelberg Cement, the 
market has mostly attracted fi nance houses and 
banks, speculating on future rises in the value of 
carbon credits. “When I started to do this job in 
early April the price was something like 12 or 
13 euros per tonne. Within three months it has 
become 25 euros. So you can easily make a huge 
amount of money,” he says.  But this was not the 
aim. “Th e scheme was designed to reduce the emis-
sions of industrials and utilities,” he explains.
Under the Kyoto Protocol, industries can also 
gain emissions credits by “greening” industries in 
developing countries. At their plant in Indonesia, 
explains Hüttner, Heidelberg Cement is replacing 
coal with biomass. “We have a project using coco-
nut shells, or palm oil kernels or palm oil, which is 
pure biomass and has a very high heating value. 
Th en we invest heavily in the energy effi  ciency of 
the plant in general,” he says. 
Th e scheme also allows countries or industries 
to gain carbon credits by investing in reforesta-
tion – the trees act as “sinks” for carbon dioxide. 
But, says Natarajan Ishwaran, Director of 
UNESCO’s Division of Ecological and Earth Sci-
ences, environmentalists are sceptical of the 
scheme, not least because, he says, “Th e error is 
too high in calculating how much carbon dioxide 
forests, coral reefs and the oceans absorb.” Th is 
makes it hard to put a value on the credits that 
industries should earn through planting trees. 
Meanwhile, critics fear that it will lead to further 
degradation of the environment if fast-growing, 
non-indigenous trees are planted in monoculture 
plantations just to gain credits.  ◆
P.C.
Cloud of pollution 
above India and 
Bangladesh
Env ironment
©
 N
A
S
A
/S
ci
e
n
ce
 P
h
o
to
lib
ra
ry
/C
o
sm
o
s,
 P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Cape Town: Garden Wonderland 
in the Midst of Urban Sprawl
 Instead of building fences around its unique fl oral heritage, Cape Town 
(South Africa) explores new ways to involve inhabitants in conservation
Despite their romantic names, Cape Town’s 
tough townships like Lavender Hill are not 
places many Capetonians are likely to venture. 
Yet, a few hundred metres away, down a sur-
prisingly quiet, tidy street, is the Rondevlei 
Nature Reserve. Once inside the gate, a haven 
of tranquil beauty opens up. A kingfi sher dives 
off  a tall reed; pelicans, spoonbills and pink fl a-
mingos mass on the banks of a vlei (lake), and, 
as night falls, a couple of hippos rise like sub-
marines to wallow and graze.
In Cape Town ‘urban’ and ‘natural’ worlds 
oft en coincide – or collide. Table Mountain, the 
heart of the city, is slap in the middle of busi-
ness and up-market residential areas. Yet it is 
home to Fynbos (pronounced fain-boss), a 
unique vegetation, and the main component of 
the Cape Floristic Kingdom – the world’s rich-
est, and geographically smallest, fl oral kingdom 
(plants confi ned to a geographical area). Some 
9,600 species can be found in an area the size of 
Portugal, 70% of them endemic (found nowhere 
else), while 1,406 are listed in the World Con-
servation Union’s (IUCN) Red Data book of 
endangered species. While the Cape floral 
region was inscribed on UNESCO’s World 
Natural Heritage List in 2004 for its unique 
fl ora and fauna, the region also has no less than 
two biosphere reserves – Kogelberg, just to the 
east of the city, and the West Coast Biosphere 
Reserve.
The proximity of this plant biodiversity 
‘hotspot’ to an urban area poses obvious con-
servation problems, especially given Cape 
Town’s open access policy to its national park 
– which means no fences and few pay points. 
The Cape’s townships 
adjoin the Rondevlei 
Nature Reserve
Env ironment
www.unesco.org/en/courier/environment 43
©
 P
e
te
r 
C
o
le
s,
 P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
 44 The new Courier – November 2005
Conservation challenges are multiplied many 
times over by an explosion of economic 
migrants from the rural Eastern Cape in search 
of jobs, arriving at a rate of about 45,000 every 
three months. Under apartheid, black Africans 
were not allowed to live in central Cape Town 
and were confi ned to townships on the urban 
edge. Since the late 1980s, though, almost a mil-
lion (mostly Xhosa people) have settled on the 
city’s outskirts, many in the township of Khay-
elitsha. Th ese vast slums of tiny houses and tin 
shacks stretch as far as the eye can see, across 
the fragile dunes and seasonal wetlands of Cape 
Flats. 
| Involving communities
But the Cape Flats are also part of the Cape Flo-
ristic Kingdom. Yet, to the new arrivals, it looks 
like ‘scrubland’ - an ideal place to put up a 
makeshift  home. “How do you look aft er biodi-
versity in a context of extreme poverty, where 
local communities have little history of involve-
ment in conservation?” asks Tanya Goldman, 
Project Manager of Cape Flats Nature.
One response, she explains, is the City of 
Cape Town’s Integrated Metropolitan Environ-
ment Policy (IMEP), adopted in 2001, accord-
ing to which “there doesn’t have to be a choice 
between environment and people. You can pro-
tect the environment in a way that supports 
peoples’ needs.” At the heart of the IMEP is a 
Biodiversity Strategy, implemented through a 
network of 261 areas that should preserve a 
minimum of Cape Town’s unique biodiversity. 
For the moment, Cape Flats Nature is concen-
trating on four experimental sites.
One, the Edith Stephens Wetland Park, is a 
modest but promising start. “The City has 
started to get the message that they won’t fi nd 
support for conservation in the Cape Flats by 
fencing people out,” says Tanya Goldman. 
“Sustainable conservation management has to 
win the hearts, involvement and understanding 
of the surrounding communities.” Two of the 
other three pilot sites are more of a challenge, 
though. Both the Wolfgat Nature Reserve and 
Macassar Dunes are sensitive areas. Spectacu-
larly beautiful, and studded with arum lilies, 
they are also where gangsters dump their vic-
tims’ bodies. 
While Cape Flats Nature is working with 
traditional healers at Macassar Dunes to grow 
medicinal plants between the shacks and the 
dunes – to act as a buff er against further sprawl 
– Brett Myrdal, Manager of Table Mountain 
National Park, has a more controversial propo-
sition – housing. He wants to see “a middle 
class community from the townships overlook-
ing the coastal area.” But, he says, “Environ-
mentalists don’t see housing as part of a 
conservation solution. Th ey see it as a threat.” 
What if, in the end, both were right? ◆
P.C.
Facts and fi gures
 In 2005, 49% of the world’s population is living in urban areas. In 2030, that 
fi gure is likely to reach 60.8%. The proportion is higher in industrialized countries 
(74.9%) than it is in developing countries (43.2%). By 2030, those fi gures will 
have risen to 81.7% and 57% respectively. And by 2007, for the fi rst time in 
history, more than half the world’s population will be living in urban areas.
 In 2004, forests covered 29.6% of the world’s total land area. But between 1990 
and 2000, 9.4 million hectares of forest per year were lost to deforestation.
 In 2004, 2,791 species were listed as endangered, 1,490 of them plants and 
1,301 animals.
Sources: FAO, United Nations, World Conservation Union, World Bank
Env ironment
The Cape Floristic 
Kingdom is the richest 
in the world
©
 P
e
te
r 
C
o
le
s,
 P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
www.unesco.org/en/courier/interalia 45
They worked at UNESCO!
René Depestre (1926-) 
Th e Haitian author and 
poet’s work is inspired by 
Caribbean magical realism. 
Exiled from his country 
since 1946, he lived in Cuba, 
Chile, Italy and France, 
where he joined UNESCO 
in 1979, fi rst as a member 
of the Director-General’s 
cabinet (1979-1982), then 
as a consultant in the Culture Sector. A prominent 
fi gure in contemporary Haitian literature, Depestre 
is a Communist, and his fi rst works reveal his 
revolutionary doctrine Pour la révolution, pour la 
poésie, 1974 ; Poète à Cuba, 1976). At the same time, 
he was writing “solar love stories” like  Alleluïa pour 
une femme-jardin (1973) that mingles poetry and 
eroticism. He received France’s Renaudot literary 
prize in 1988 for his novel Hadriana dans tous mes 
rêves.
Taha Hussain (1889-1973)
Considered a founding 
father of modern culture 
in the Arab world, Taha 
Hussein was appointed 
Minister of Education of his 
country, Egypt, in 1950. He 
instigated the creation of 
Ayn Sham University and led 
the country to institute free 
primary education. Hussain, 
who had lost his sight at the age of three, studied at 
Al Azhar University in Cairo and the Sorbonne in 
Paris. As a novelist, writer of essays, literary critic and 
university professor, he infl uenced several generations 
of intellectuals all over the Arab world. He 
concentrated his creative energy on helping to bring 
the Arab countries into the modern world. He was 
a member of UNESCO’s Executive Board and vice-
president of the General Conference in 1950-1951.
José Ángel Valente 
Docasar (1929-2000)
University professor, poet and writer of essays, José 
Ángel Valente Docasar was born in Orense (Spain) 
and studied law in Santiago de Compostela as well 
as romanesque philology in Madrid. In the 1950s, 
he taught at Oxford University (UK), and in 1958 
moved to Geneva to teach and work at the United 
Nations. Between 1982 and 1985, he was head of the 
Spanish Translation Section at UNESCO in Paris. 
He made his mark on Spanish literature as of 1954, 
when he won the Adonais prize for his collection of 
poems A modo de esperanza. Particularly noteworthy 
among his many works: Poemas a Lázaro (Premio de 
la Crítica 1960), Interior con fi guras (1976), and El fi n 
de la edad de plata followed by Nueve enunciaciones 
(1995).
Pablo Neruda (1904-1973)
Neft alí Ricardo Reyes Basoalto adopted his 
pseudonym in 1917: Pablo Neruda. A Communist 
party activist in Chile, he energetically supported 
Salvador Allende’s government, which sent him to 
Paris in 1970 as Chilean ambassador and Permanent 
Delegate to UNESCO. In that capacity, he served on 
UNESCO’s Executive Board in 1972 and 1973. Works 
such as Canto general, Twenty Love Poems and a Song 
of Despair and Th e Captain’s 
Verses were translated world-
wide, and Neruda won the 
Nobel Prize for literature in 
1971. In 2004, UNESCO’s 
General Conference made 
a decision to participate in 
the celebration of the 100th 
anniversary of his birth .
Indira Gandhi (1917-1984)
Her father, Jawaharlal Nehru, was independent 
India’s fi rst prime minister, while she herself was 
the fi rst woman to hold the post in 1966, serving 
four terms. Assassinated in 1984, she left  behind a 
legacy as a champion of issues aff ecting the world’s 
developing countries. Elected president of India’s 
National Congress Party 
in 1959, she served as a 
member UNESCO’s 
Executive Board from 
1960 to 1964. She paved 
the way for environmental 
protection policies and 
self-suffi  ciency in food 
grain production in India.
Maria Montessori (1870-
1952)
 
She revolutionized the childhood education methods 
of her time and originated a new one which today 
bears her name. Th e fi rst woman in Italy to earn a 
medical degree, she began her career in education 
as a teacher of handicapped children. To this day, 
her philosophy of education 
– meeting the physical, mental, 
spiritual and emotional needs 
of children – continues to be 
of paramount importance to 
all those who believe in the 
overwhelming infl uence of 
the fi rst six years of a child’s 
life. Member of the Italian 
delegation to the 5th session 
of the General Conference in 
1950, she received the conference’s homage 40 years 
later when it passed a resolution to commemorate 
the 50th anniversary of her death in 2002.
 Cu Huy Cân (1919-2005) 
Th is poet was an Executive 
Board member from 
the Socialist Republic of 
Vietnam from 1978 to 
1983. During the period 
of literary eff ervescence in 
the 1940s, when he was 23, 
he published his anthology 
of poems, Lua Th iêng 
(Sacred Fire), which placed 
him at the forefront of a new poetry movement. 
During this same period, he was active in the 
independence movement, aft er which he occupied 
several ministerial posts, in agriculture and culture. 
Prolifi c throughout his life, he received the Ho Chi 
Minh Prize in 1996 from the State. A collection of his 
poems was translated into English in 2001, under the 
title Tides of the Oriental Sea.
Amadou Hampâté Bâ 
(1901-1991)
Th is Malian diplomat made 
an outstanding contribution 
to winning international 
recognition for African oral 
cultures, notably at UNESCO 
on whose Executive Board 
he served between 1962 and 
1970. While he revealed 
the wealth and value of 
these cultures, he also drew 
attention to their precariousness and played an active 
role in safeguarding them. His manuscript archives, 
the Fonds Amadou Hampâté Bâ, is the product of 
half a century’s research into African oral traditions. 
His story L’étrange destin de Wangrin (Th e Fortunes 
of Wangrin) won him the “Grand Prix littéraire 
de l’Afrique noire” in 1976. He is credited with the 
famous quotation: “Th e death of an old man is like 
the burning of a library.” 
Alva Myrdal (1902-1986)
She was a major infl uence 
in the promotion of social 
welfare in her native 
Sweden in the 1930s. In the 
aft ermath of the Second 
World War, she turned her 
eff orts towards international 
questions, fi rst heading the 
United Nations’ section on 
welfare policy from 1949 
to 1950, then directing UNESCO’s Department of 
Social Sciences from 1951 to 1955. She later served 
as her country’s ambassador to India, Ceylon and 
Nepal, then led the Swedish delegation to the UN 
Disarmament Conference in Geneva in 1962. She 
was also instrumental in the establishment of the 
Stockholm Peace Research Institute (SIPRI). In 1982, 
she received the Nobel Peace Prize.  
Julio Cortázar (1914-1984)
Born in Brussels of 
Argentine parents, 
Julio Cortázar spent his 
childhood and youth in 
Argentina, where he worked 
at the book chamber. In 
1951, when Juan Domingo 
Peron was in power, he 
received a grant that allowed 
him to come and live in exile 
in Paris. He started working for UNESCO in 1952, as 
a freelance translator. He then became translator for 
the General Conference in Montevideo in 1954, and 
met Mario Vargas Llosa, who was also a translator, 
at the General Conference in Athens. Cortázar never 
abandoned his allegiance to the  Latin-American 
left ists (Cuba and Nicaragua). In December 1982, 
already a famous writer, he spoke at the world 
conference on cultural policy organized by UNESCO 
in Mexico. His numerous stories, brimming with 
humor and imagination, and the innovative structure 
of such books as Marelle and Libro de Manuel make 
him one of  Argentina’s greatest writers.
Edouard Glissant (1928-
A major author of West 
Indian literature, Glissant 
produced an abundance 
of works including poems, 
essays, a play and novels. 
In 1967, he created the 
Institut martiniquais d’études 
to promote West Indian 
studies before becoming the 
editor of UNESCO’s Courier 
magazine (1982-1988). A student of Aimé Césaire at 
the  Schoelcher lycée in Fort-de-France, he took up 
the anti-colonial cause, demonstrating in favour of 
Algerian independence, among other issues. From 
Un champ d’îles (1953), and La Terre inquiète (1954) 
to the long poem Les Indes (1956), his writing evokes 
the West Indian people’s long oppression. His novels 
– La Lézarde (1958) or Malemort (1975) – also evoke 
a people haunted by its painful history, in search of 
its identity.
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
©
 U
lf
 A
n
d
e
rs
e
n
/G
a
m
m
a
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/C
la
u
d
e
 B
a
b
lin
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
©
 F
ra
n
ço
is
 L
e
h
r/
G
a
m
m
a
, P
a
ri
s
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
 46 The new Courier – November 2005
Cultural  diversit y
In the course of impassioned debates, the Convention on the Protection 
and Promotion of the Diversity of Cultural Expressions was adopted 
during the 33rd session of UNESCO’s General Conference. Its purpose: 
to protect goods and services that are vehicles of identity, values and 
meaning. Back in 2001, the Universal Declaration on Cultural Diversity 
had already raised cultural diversity to the level of “common heritage 
of humanity”. But this time the Convention, a binding legal instrument, 
commits the States that sign it.
A Burst of Creativity
Books, like fi lms and 
records, are vehicles of 
identity and meaning
© UNESCO/Dominique Roger
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Cultural  diversit y
May 2005, a meeting is convened in St Petersburg 
(Russian Federation) to prepare the World 
Summit on the Information Society (WSIS). Sep-
tember 2005, academic exchanges are organized 
in Ouagadougou (Burkina Faso). October 2005, a 
large advertising company sponsors a photography 
prize. What do these events have in common? All 
of them, in diff erent ways, claim to relate to cul-
tural diversity.
Th is not a new idea. Th e “fruitful diversity of 
cultures” is already mentioned in the 1945 
UNESCO Constitution. But it has taken on par-
ticular prominence since globalization came 
along. Given that now all cultures are able to 
mingle (about 175 million people live outside of 
their countries of origin, and one person out of 
ten living in the industrialized countries is an 
immigrant, according to the United Nations’ 
2002 International Migration Report), we need 
to remember that all forms of expression, value 
systems, traditions and beliefs are unique, frag-
ile and irreplaceable. Th eir fragility is best illus-
trated when we look at languages. Out of 6,000 
known languages, nearly 50% are estimated to 
be threatened with extinction. On the internet, 
90% of languages are not represented. Right 
there, many cultures are threatened. In bridg-
ing the digital divide, defending copyright, col-
lecting data on local and indigenous knowledge 
or safeguarding tangible and intangible herit-
age, UNESCO has been actively promoting cul-
tural diversity since its creation.
| Ethical imperative
“Cultural diversity has become pivotal to the 
future of societies and requires renewed action,” 
declared Director-General Koichiro Matsuura 
on May 21, 2005 (1). Th e unanimous adoption in 
November 2001 of the Universal Declaration on 
Cultural Diversity demonstrates how important 
the issue has become to the international com-
munity. For the fi rst time, it created a normative 
instrument that raises cultural diversity to the 
rank of “common heritage of humanity… as 
necessary for humankind as biodiversity is for 
nature”, and makes its safeguarding an ethical 
imperative indispensable to respect  human dig-
nity. A year later, at the Johannesburg World 
Summit on Sustainable Development in Septem-
ber 2002, a Declaration was adopted that recog-
nizes cultural diversity as a collective force that 
must be promoted to ensure sustainable devel-
opment (para. 16). But a decisive step was taken 
when the 33rd session of the UNESCO General 
Conference adopted in October 2005 the Inter-
national Convention on the Protection and Pro-
motion of the Diversity of Cultural Expressions, 
“considered to have been greatly undermined by 
current processes and not as yet enjoying any 
particular protection” (2). Th is time, unlike the 
Declaration, the Convention is a binding legal 
instrument and represents a commitment by the 
States that ratify it.
Its adoption was not a foregone conclusion. 
Th ree aspects were particularly controversial. 
Th e fi rst has to do with defi nitions, notably of 
cultural goods and services: should they be con-
sidered products like any other goods? Finally, 
in the preamble,  they are defi ned as having 
“both an economic and a cultural nature… ” 
and “must therefore not be treated as solely 
having commercial value”. And the aim of the 
Convention, expressed in Article I, is “to give 
recognition to the distinctive nature of cultural 
activities, goods and services as vehicles of 
identity, values and meaning”. Simply put, that 
means that fi lms, CDs, or books are not only 
subject to the rules of the marketplace, but, as 
vehicles for identity, values and meaning, they 
may benefi t from protection, i.e. preservation, 
safeguarding or promotion, as specifi ed in the 
definitions. The second article affirms that 
States Parties may formulate cultural policies to 
support creativity. Th ey may, for instance, sub-
sidize arts and culture, or grant tax reductions 
to encourage and protect their national cul-
tures, taking into consideration human rights 
and the free fl ow of information. Finally, the 
third point concerns Article 20, which indicates 
that the Convention will not confl ict with other 
treaties, but will work on the principle of 
“mutual supportiveness, complementarity and 
nonsubordination”. Less ardently discussed, 
the point concerning international cultural 
cooperation (Articles 12 to 19) sets out the con-
ditions for a new form of solidarity that places 
culture at the heart of development.
Finally, at the close of the passionate debates, 
the Convention was adopted. It will go into 
eff ect as soon as it has 30 States Parties. ◆
1. Message of the Director-General of UNESCO on the occasion of the World 
Day for Cultural Diversity for Dialogue and Development, 21 May 2005 
2. Ibid
www.unesco.org/en/courier/diversity 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
 48 The new Courier – November 2005
Cultural  diversit y
The poorer countries 
are rarely able to help 
artists make a living 
from their art
The Global Alliance on All Fronts
 Launched by UNESCO in 2002, the Global Alliance helps the countries 
in the South to boost their cultural production.
Reinforcing the independent music industry 
in Colombia, sponsoring a competition of dig-
ital short fi lms in Jordan, developing copyright 
in Namibia, promoting traditional Tibetan 
weaving on the global market…These are 
examples of the projects implemented by 
UNESCO through the Global Alliance for Cul-
tural Diversity. The initiative, launched in 
2002, aims to strengthen the capacity of cul-
tural industries in developing countries in 
production and distribution. Th e challenge is 
major: as vehicles of identity and meaning, 
cultural goods and services hold signifi cant 
symbolic value and form a powerful compo-
nent of cultural diversity. But many countries 
lack the means necessary to develop these 
industries. Only rarely can they remunerate 
their artists so that they can make a living from 
their art, much less attract international atten-
tion to their works.
Th e Global Alliance therefore works to cre-
ate new partnerships between the state, the 
private sector and civil society, in order to cre-
ate conditions favourable to the expression of 
creativity and the plurality of ideas, as well as 
making them available and accessible to all.
| Economic dimension
Meanwhile, cultural goods and services com-
prise an important economic dimension. In the 
last few years, in fact, cultural and creative 
industries represent one of the most dynamic 
economic sectors. To help boost cultural enter-
prise, the Global Alliance works in three direc-
tions: normative action (regulations, legislation, 
employment benefits, copyright); capacity 
building in production; and access to funding. 
Th e Alliance mobilizes some 500 partners in 90 
countries: government agencies, businesses, 
NGOs, artists. Th e proliferation of partnerships 
between the state, the private sector and civil 
society make it possible to increase signifi cantly 
the sums needed for each project. In the last 
three years, these projects have raised nearly 
three million dollars.
Other initiatives are planned, such as the 
organization of a large forum on cultural diver-
sity in China at the end of 2005, the establish-
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
o
m
in
iq
u
e
 R
o
g
e
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Cultural  diversit y
“ Cultural Diversity can neither be 
decreed nor improvised”
 For the fi rst time in 2001, UNESCO recognized cultural diversity as 
the “common heritage of humanity”.
Th e UNESCO Constitution mandates the Organ-
ization both to respect the “fruitful diversity of 
(...) cultures” and to “promote the free fl ow of 
ideas by word and image”. Since the Constitution 
was adopted, UNESCO has spared no eff ort to 
fulfi l this double mission. Its progression between 
1946 and 2005 is easily followed. 
Diversity remains the central issue, but it has 
been a long road in a rapidly changing world from 
recognizing the diversity between cultures, to 
affi  rming that they are of equal dignity, then to 
recognizing cultural diversity in itself and, fi nally, 
the diversity of cultural expressions. In fact, cul-
tural diversity can neither be decreed nor impro-
vised. It constantly raises new challenges and calls 
for new forms of action.
The UNESCO Universal Declaration on 
 Cultural Diversity (2001), for the fi rst time, recog-
nized cultural diversity as “the common heritage 
of humanity”; its defence is considered as an 
We have come a long 
way from the equal 
dignity of cultures 
to the diversity of 
cultural expressions
ment of government policy concerning books 
in Gambia, Guinea and Senegal, as well as meas-
ures to protect copyright and fi ght piracy in 
Lithuania, Bulgaria or Zimbabwe. In 2006, the 
Motion Picture Association (MPA), which 
brings together the Global Alliance and Holly-
wood studios, will stage workshops on produc-
tion. Th e Alliance has also initiated a network 
of “creative cities” that links cities possessing a 
rich tradition in literature, cinema, music, 
design or gastronomy. ◆
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/A
n
d
e
s/
C
Z
A
P
/A
S
A
www.unesco.org/en/courier/diversity 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
 50 The new Courier – November 2005
Cultural  diversit y
 ethical and concrete imperative that cannot be 
dissociated from respect for the dignity of the 
individual.
| A relative notion
Because of its sweeping force, the Declaration 
gave rise to wide debate: oft en used as a slogan, 
cultural diversity remains a relative notion. Th is 
explains that various, and oft en divergent, defi -
nitions can be proposed in economic circles, 
the academic community, the world of politics, 
and by culture professionals or civil society. Th e 
Declaration did not end the recurring debate 
on the role of the State in determining cultural 
policies: some believe that culture belongs to 
the private sector and, as a consequence, reject 
all intervention in this fi eld. Others believe that 
a democratic state must be the guarantor of a 
national and international environment favour-
able to the blossoming of local and global cul-
tural diversity. Finally, the developing countries, 
oft en expressing themselves through the Group 
of 77 (today 130 countries including China), 
refuse to be the providers of global cultural 
diversity while being denied access to the sym-
bolic and economic benefi ts derived from it.
In this context, in which a series of new ques-
tions were raised, particularly because of the accel-
eration of globalization, discussions were opened 
in 2003 to draft  a Convention on the Protection 
and Promotion of the Diversity of Cultural Expres-
sions, to be examined by the 33d session of the 
General Conference in October. Th is new stand-
ard setting instrument is linked to precise aspects 
of the Universal Declaration on Cultural Diversity 
as stipulated in Articles 8 through 11. Th at is, the 
need to recognize that cultural goods and services 
have an identity, values and meaning and cannot 
be considered in the same manner as manufac-
tured or consumer goods; the need for States to 
take all measures necessary to protect and pro-
mote diversity of cultural expression while ensur-
ing the free fl ow of ideas and works; and fi nally the 
need to redefi ne international cooperation, the 
keystone of the Convention. 
By draft ing a Convention within UNESCO, 
the Member States intend to contribute to the rec-
ognition of creative diversity, the driving force of 
development, of international solidarity, and of 
mutual comprehension. A wide availability of this 
creative diversity, whether emanating from inte-
rior or exterior sources, off ers cultural and social 
advantages far beyond its strictly commercial 
dimension.  Particular care was taken to avoid 
certain pitfalls: a polarized debate between the “all 
cultural” and the “all commercial”; cultural rela-
tivism that, in the name of cultural diversity, rec-
ognizes cultural practices contrary to the basic 
principles of human rights; and a narrow concep-
tion of culture as simply entertainment and not as 
a source of identity and dignity for individuals 
and societies. 
| Diversity and development
Th is shows that the Draft  Convention was con-
ceived as a means to link “culture and develop-
ment”, the latter term being understood in both 
its tangible and symbolic sense: economic growth 
combined with the fulfi lment of human beings 
enjoying their basic rights, open to the world 
without losing their bearings. It is also a sign 
that the Convention was conceived as a means to 
link “culture and international solidarity”, by 
favouring exchanges and partnerships that are 
particularly benefi cial to countries whose cul-
tural expression has been damaged. Finally, it is 
a sign that the Convention was conceived as a 
means of tightening the ties between “culture 
and mutual comprehension”: each type of crea-
tion carries the seeds of the discovery of oneself 
and of others. In this, it is part of the mysterious 
alchemy of interaction and releases the tremen-
dous energy of cultural diversity, which does not 
consist of a fi xed inventory of variations or vari-
ables but which carries the hope, forever 
renewed, of a more human future.
We all contribute to and we all benefi t from 
cultural diversity, and we are therefore all respon-
sible for safeguarding it. ◆
Katerina Stenou
Director of the Division of Cultural Policies and 
Intercultural Dialogue 
MUSEUM INTERNATIONAL N° 227
This issue of MUSEUM International proposes to study the 
notion of heritage’s cultural diversity starting with the 
relation to time. The different articles explore how the 
diversity of heritage can be envisaged as the expression of 
the diversity of time in the history of cultures. Furthermore, 
they attempt to analyze how this diversity of time is 
reflected in the global project of safeguarding heritage.
CULTURAL DIVERSITY
AND HERITAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
Major Works
Braille uniformity
UNESCO’s concern with Braille dates back to 1949 when, upon a request 
from India, it undertook the pioneering task of surveying the world 
situation of the Braille system. This resulted in the establishment in 
1953 of the World Braille Uniformity Programme, which standardized 
literary codes, enabling blind people around the world to read the 
same Braille books, learn foreign languages, exchange ideas and 
experiences. This expanded later to include science, mathematics and 
music notations. UNESCO also launched the World Braille Council, thus 
providing an international venue for Braille matters to be discussed. 
Again in 1953, UNESCO published World Braille Usage, as well as the 
Braille Courier in English, French, Spanish and Korean. 
Index Translationum
This is the only international index of translations in the world, a 
bibliographic database that contains references to 1.5 million books 
translated and published in all subjects in 100 countries. To date, some 
250,000 authors are listed and over 500 languages included, and the 
list is updated annually with at least 100,000 new references, thus 
becoming the largest of UNESCO’s databases. Today, it is available on 
CD-ROM and online.
More information: http://portal.unesco.org/culture/
International safeguarding campaigns
If not for UNESCO’s international campaign, the Aswan High Dam would 
have fl ooded the Nile valley, site of the most important Nubian temples. 
Following an appeal from the governments of Egypt and Sudan, an 
international team began dismantling the temples in 1960, then 
reconstructed them on higher ground, a massive operation successfully 
concluded in 1980. The Nubian campaign showed the importance of 
international solidarity and shared responsibility. In addition to the 26 
campaigns, operational projects have also been launched, protecting 
monuments and sites such as those in Angkor, Mostar and Ethiopia. 
More information: http://portal.unesco.org/culture/
Multiple History book series
Among the most important publishing projects UNESCO has undertaken 
is the historiography series on Africa, the Caribbean, Central Asia, 
Latin America, and humanity. Comprising several volumes each, some 
of these have been translated into ten languages. These books are 
considered major reference works, providing a comprehensive approach 
to the history of ideas, civilizations, societies and institutions in their 
respective regions.
More information: www.unesco.org/publishing
Roads of Dialogue
To fi nd out more about the interplay between cultural infl uences and 
people’s movements from one region to another, UNESCO launched a 
series of projects to study the routes that have connected the world’s 
peoples. Scientists and scholars the world over have been mobilized in 
a far-reaching enterprise of research and several expeditions by land 
and sea. This began with the Silk Roads in 1988, the Iron Road (African 
metallurgy) and Roads of Faith (Jerusalem) both in 1991, Vaka Moana 
– Ocean Roads (South Pacifi c) in 1992, the Slave Route in 1994, and the 
Routes of al-Andalus (Muslim Spain) in 1995.
More information: http://portal.unesco.org/culture/
UNESCO Collection of Representative Works
This collection was launched in 1948 as a direct subsidy programme 
to encourage the translation, publication and distribution in major 
languages of works of literary and cultural importance not well-known 
outside their original national boundaries or linguistic communities. 
Thanks to this collection, Nobel laureates like Yasunari Kawabata and 
George Seferis have been accessible to a wider public. The current 
catalogue includes some 1,400 works. 
More information: http://www.unesco.org/culture/
International 
Safeguarding 
Campaign of the 
Monuments of Nubia.
On the Silk Road, Uzbekistan.
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/N
e
n
a
d
o
v
ic
www.unesco.org/en/courier/interalia 51
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
 52 The new Courier – November 2005
Water
Water is set to defi ne our new century in 
the way that oil defi ned its predecessor. 
Across the world there are disturbing signs that 
the world is running out of water. In 2015, ac-
cording to current estimates, 40% of the world’s 
population will experience diffi  culties in obtain-
ing a supply of water suffi  cient for daily needs. 
Already certain regions – northern China, the 
western United States, North Africa and west-
ern Asia – are pumping water faster than aquifer 
sources can be replenished. Some of the world’s 
largest and best-known rivers – the Indus and 
the Nile, the Yellow River and the Ganges, the 
Colorado and the Rio Grande – no longer reach 
the sea in any volume for part of the year. All 
are being exhausted by the demands of irrigat-
ing water-hungry crops and taps in burgeoning 
cities.
In September 2000, countries participating in the United Nations 
Millennium Summit pledged to reduce by half the number of people 
in the world deprived of clean water, between now and 2015. This is a 
highly ambitious goal, considering it means every day providing access 
to running water to another 300,000 people. Given the circumstances, 
how should the world respond to anticipated shortages? Do we need 
more science and engineering, or is the fi rst priority to change the way 
we use this vital resource?
The Rush for Water
The Yangtze, great 
river that irrigates 
southern China
©
 Ia
n
 B
e
rr
y/
M
a
g
n
u
m
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
Water
Among other examples, Lake Chad has 
decreased in size by four-fifths in the last 
40 years. Wells too are emptying as we pump 
out underground reserves that have survived 
for thousands of years. The loss of these 
resources is a hidden holocaust on a par with 
the destruction of rainforests; yet it is barely 
remarked upon.
Worldwide, we are ‘mining’ some 200 cubic 
kilometres of water a year. Half a billion peo-
ple are consuming wheat and rice irrigated 
with water reserves that are not being replen-
ished. 
| Moving water
Can science come to the rescue? Th is is highly 
unlikely. True, ever-bigger engineering projects 
can move water round the planet. In 2003 at the 
World Water Forum a coalition of governments 
and industry leaders called for a doubling in the 
number of large dams across the world. But 
many would be on rivers already running dry. 
Another idea is to move water between river 
basins. China is currently spending tens of bil-
lions of dollars on three giant transfer schemes 
to take water from its great southern river, the 
Yangtze, to relieve the artery of northern China, 
the Yellow River. India has an even bigger plan, 
currently under discussion, to divert part of the 
fl ow of its great northern monsoon rivers, like 
the Ganges and Brahmaputra, to its arid south 
and west – at a cost some believe could reach 
US$200 billion. Th ere are schemes too to divert 
Congo River water into the Sahara and divert 
Australia’s northern tropical rivers into its 
desert interior.
But these schemes are hugely costly, and 
cheaper solutions are available. One way of 
relieving local water crises is by moving water 
in the form of food. Th ere is a huge hidden 
trade in what is being called “virtual water”, 
defi ned as the water needed to grow crops or 
produce other products that would have used 
large amounts of water if grown at home. 
“In recent years, water has become a hidden 
part of world trade,” says Arjen Hoekstra, until 
recently at UNESCO’s Institute for Water Edu-
cation, in Delft , the Netherlands. “Whenever 
we buy a T-shirt made of Pakistani cotton, or 
eat Th ai rice or burgers made of meat from 
Central America, we are infl uencing the hydrol-
ogy of those countries – taking a share of the 
River Indus, the Mekong or the Costa Rican 
rains.” 
Hoekstra estimates the global virtual water 
trade at around 1,000 cubic kilometres a year, 
mostly in crops like grains, vegetable oil, sugar 
and cotton. “About 15% of the water used in the 
world for human purposes is not used for 
domestic consumption but for export in virtual 
form,” he adds. 
This trade is essential for the survival of 
some countries, especially in the Middle East. 
Iran, Egypt and Algeria could starve otherwise. 
Water-stressed Jordan effectively imports 
between 60 and 90% of its water in the form of 
food. More water fl ows into the Middle East 
each year as a result of imports of “virtual water” 
than fl ows down the River Nile.  
| The price of virtual water
But, he says, virtual water is sold as a virtually 
free resource: “Water is generally priced far 
below its real economic, social and environ-
mental cost.” Pakistan, for instance, consumes 
a third of the fl ow of the River Indus in order to 
grow cotton for export. When the Soviet Union 
transformed the deserts of Central Asia into a 
vast cotton plantation, it sowed the seeds of the 
destruction of the Aral Sea. Hoekstra estimates 
the European market for cotton alone is respon-
sible for a fi ft h of the emptying of the sea.
If on the contrary virtual water were prop-
erly priced, it could act as a global market to 
help the world make better use of its limited 
supply of water. And it would be much more 
effi  cient than moving water round in bulk. But, 
besides this route towards the globalisation of 
water supplies, UNESCO’s water scientists have 
taken more interest in the subtler and cheaper 
arts of reviving traditional water systems – 
water systems that give communities greater 
control over their own water supplies.
Often these have the advantage of being 
cheaper, and of making better and more sus-
tainable use of local water resources. Th ey rep-
resent one route towards solving water crises. 
We need to fi nd others, to help prevent water 
from becoming a luxury available only to a 
privileged few. ◆
Fred Pearce
www.unesco.org/en/courier/water 53
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
 54 The new Courier – November 2005
Water
Back to the Future
 Dams are not the only way to capture water. Certain traditional water-
gathering technologies have proven effi  cient.
Typically, if governments want more water, 
they invariably demand a new dam. But there 
are other ways – ways that are oft en more effi  -
cient, cheaper and give control of water sup-
plies back to the communities who use them. 
Some believe it is time for a revival of ancient 
techniques in a modern setting – techniques 
that were forgotten during the 20th century 
could make a comeback in the 21st. 
Take the long underground water tunnels 
known as qanats. Th ey are one of the great engi-
neering treasures of the Middle East, Central 
Asia and North Africa. In these arid regions, 
rain falls only sporadically and mostly in the 
mountains. Th e water swift ly percolates under-
ground. Th e Persians long ago learned to exca-
vate these springs, ‘chasing’ the water back into 
the hillside by digging horizontal tunnels. 
In Iran alone there are an estimated 50,000 
qanats. Assembled end to end, they would reach 
two-thirds of the way to the moon. Wherever 
the Persians went, they took the secrets of 
qanats. Consequently, the technology spread 
along the Silk Road to Afghanistan and China, 
through Arabia and along the North coast of 
Africa as far as Spain.
As recently as the 1960s, their total discharge 
in Iran was equivalent to the flow of twelve 
River Niles. In the hot desert of central Iran, the 
ancient city of Yazd still uses qanats up to 60 
kilometres long to bring water from the snow-
covered Mount Sir. When an earthquake struck 
Bam in eastern Iran in late 2003, one of the fi rst 
discoveries made by aid workers was that the 
town was entirely dependent on qanats for 
water – and most of the tunnels had collapsed 
in the quake. 
| Reinvesting in old methods
Qanats are in decline because in many places, 
boreholes powered by modern water pumps 
have lowered water tables, drying up many 
qanats. But Andras Szollosi-Nagy, director of 
UNESCO’s Division of Water Sciences, says 
they have hydrological qualities that should be 
in great demand. They are self-regulating 
because, unlike electric pumps, they tap the 
aquifer only up to the limit of natural replen-
ishment. If properly designed and maintained, 
they are, as they call them in Yemen, “unfailing 
springs” that keep going in all but the worst 
droughts. 
Some modern water engineers believe that 
the diffi  cult and dangerous work of qanat dig-
ging could be mechanised. But meanwhile, says 
Szollosi-Nagy, there is a good case for making 
better use of existing qanats; and for protecting 
them by placing restrictions on pumped bore-
holes nearby.  
Th is is already the case in Oman, where the 
government has paid for extensive repairs to 
6,000 aflaj. In the Turfan basin in western 
China, more than a thousand qanats dug dur-
ing the Han and Qing dynasties were renovated 
in the 1990s. 
“It is also vitally important to conserve and 
research the basic skills and technologies of 
Terraced rice paddies 
in Java, Indonesia
©
 B
ru
n
o
 B
a
rb
e
y/
M
a
g
n
u
m
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
qanats,” says Szollosi-Nagy, “as well as the 
structures themselves.” In an eff ort to do that 
UNESCO has sponsored the creation of an 
international museum and centre in the Iranian 
‘qanat capital’ of Yazd. 
| Terraces for mountain farming
Qanats are not the only technology worth revi-
talising for sustainable water use in arid zones. 
Th e terraced hillsides of Asia could play a simi-
lar role. Th ese huge and sophisticated earth-
works turn mountain slopes into towering 
‘staircases’ of narrow fi elds. Each step is irri-
gated by water brought down the mountainside 
from springs or reservoirs, using a network of 
canals, sluices, and pipes. 
Among the most spectacular examples are 
the rice terraces of northern Luzon, the largest 
island in the Philippines, which are now 
Rainwater harvesting
 This technology is as old as the hills: catching and storing rainwater. 
Communities that still use it today have greater control over water resources 
than those that rely on distant dams or state-run irrigation systems. In India in 
particular, rain water harvesting is becoming more and more widespread. 
 Vedic scholars, local politicians and environmental activists have all played 
their part. One initiative, set up in western India, persuaded tens of thousands of 
villagers to construct low mud walls on their fi elds to divert the monsoon rains 
directly down some 300,000 specially adapted wells. 
 “Cities can do it, too. Many Indian cities have water reservoirs known as tankas 
and other structures for collecting the rains,” says Sunita Narain, director of the 
Delhi-based Centre for Science and the Environment, an outspoken advocate. 
In Bangalore, in India’s ‘Silicon Valley’, they are trying to boost the aquifers by 
rehabilitating the city’s 60 ancient lakes. 
 Why not develop these concepts on a much larger scale? There are proposals 
for the large-scale diversion of the monsoon fl oodwaters of the Ganges into the 
aquifer beneath its plain by pouring river water into unlined irrigation canals 
and let it seep underground – thus turning conventional notions of irrigation 
effi  ciency on their head. 
Water
Restoration of qanats 
in Yadz, Iran
www.unesco.org/en/courier/water 55
©
 B
ru
n
o
 B
a
rb
e
y/
M
a
g
n
u
m
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
 56 The new Courier – November 2005
The Mekong: an Exception to the Rule
 Unlike most great rivers, which have lost their natural fecundity, 
the Mekong has succeeded in preserving its resources.
UNESCO World Heritage Sites. Growing rice 
on hillside terraces is one of the most character-
istic activities of the whole of Asia. Certainly no 
other societies have proved capable of sustain-
ing such dense populations in mountain areas 
for century aft er century. But the sheer hard 
labour involved in maintaining and farming the 
terraces and irrigation channels has caused 
many to be abandoned. Th e steep terraces and 
narrow access paths mean that most modern 
farm machinery cannot be used.
The stories of qanats and terraces seem 
remarkably similar. Can the world aff ord to lose 
the skills and insights that they contain? Th is is 
a critical issue to be resolved if the hilly areas of 
the world are to remain productive. ◆
 F.P
Water
©
 J
o
h
n
 V
in
k/
M
a
g
n
u
m
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
Once the world’s rivers teemed with fi sh. Th en 
during the 20th century, most of them were bar-
ricaded by dams that tamed their wild waters. 
Almost everywhere this has caused a drastic 
decline in wild fi sheries. One of the few places 
this has not happened is the Mekong River, the 
great artery of Southeast Asia, where half a cen-
tury of warfare kept the dam-builders away.
| Maintaining natural fecundity 
Here, without barriers, the fi sh have prospered, 
especially in a vast forested basin off  the main 
river that still fl oods in the monsoon season, 
called the Tonle Sap, or Great Lake. Th e lake is a 
UNESCO Biosphere Reserve. Its complex 
hydrology, in which the fl ow of the river that 
connects it to the main river reverses its direc-
tion twice a year, maintains it as the nursery of 
the world’s largest inland fi shery, and the source 
of livelihood for more than a million local peo-
ple, according to a joint study by UNESCO sci-
entists and Columbia University in New York.
The lake has a long history of sustaining 
large populations. On its shores sits the World 
Heritage site of Angkor Wat, one of the great 
jungle civilisations 1,000 years ago, which fed 
itself on fi sh from the lake and rice from the 
paddies that it watered. 
Today the Mekong is threatened by increas-
ing demands on the river’s resources, from 
hydroelectric power companies, cities who 
want water supplies, and navigators who want 
to dredge its rapids. UNESCO  scientists are 
working with the Cambodian government and 
the intergovernmental UNESCO-backed 
Mekong River Commission on proposals to 
integrate uses of the river to maintain its 
extraordinary fecundity.
Th is forms part of a wider UNESCO initia-
tive that encourages research on how best to 
maintain and revive the natural fecundity of 
river systems, oft en by concentrating on the wet-
land fish nurseries within their catchments. 
Other examples include the Sudd wetland on the 
Nile, the Iquitos fl oodplain in Peru and the wet-
lands of the Yellow River. But the Mekong, as 
the least domesticated, is a good place to start.
“Th e Mekong is not just another river,” says 
Chris Barlow of the Mekong River Commis-
sion. “It is the least modifi ed of all the major 
rivers of the world.  Th e fi sheries are a source of 
natural wealth for the poor. If they were 
destroyed, people’s only alternative would be a 
job in a factory making textiles for the West.” ◆
 F.P
The Tonle Sap in 
Cambodia is an 
enormous fi shing 
reserve
Water Wars and Peace
 If we do not establish the means to ensure international cooperation, 
water could become a major source of confl ict.
If water is set to dominate our 21st century 
world, then do we risk water wars? Many believe 
so. One vital necessity is a global reconciliation 
service, set up this year by UNESCO and the 
World Water Council. Th e Water Cooperation 
Facility is based at UNESCO in Paris. Its mis-
sion is to “promote cooperation, peace and 
prosperity in developing and managing trans-
boundary waters.” 
Th e task is potentially huge. Almost half the 
world’s population lives in international river 
basins. Two-thirds of these basins have no trea-
ties for sharing their water. The River Nile 
passes through ten countries. The Danube, 
Rhine, Niger and Congo all pass through nine, 
and the Zambezi through eight. 
Africa – a continent of haphazard bounda-
ries mostly created in the chaos of imperial rule 
– has 80 transboundary rivers. In Asia, Bangla-
desh and Pakistan receive more than 90% of 
their water from India. A meeting organised by 
UNESCO in Greece late last year heard how the 
fracturing of the former Yugoslavia has created 
seven new shared river basins. 
Water
www.unesco.org/en/courier/water 57
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
 58 The new Courier – November 2005
Half an Olympic-size 
swimming pool per person
 Few of us realise how much water it takes to get us 
through the day. On average, we drink no more than 
fi ve litres. Even after washing and fl ushing the toilet, we 
usually consume no more than 150 litres. But when we add 
in the water needed to grow what we eat and drink, the 
numbers soar.
 It takes between 2,000 and 5,000 litres of water to 
grow one kilo of rice, over 1,000 litres for a kilo of wheat, 
between 2,000 and 11,000 litres to grow the feed for 
enough cow to make a quarter-pound hamburger, and 
between 2,000 and 4,000 litres for that cow to fi ll its 
udders with a litre of milk. 
 Every teaspoonful of sugar requires 50 cups of water, 
and every cup of coff ee 140 litres. Hoekstra calculates 
that his fellow Netherlanders require the virtual-water 
equivalent of 4% of the fl ow of the Rhine to produce the 
coff ee they drink in a year. To feed and clothe a typical 
meat-eating Westerner for a year takes around 1,500 cubic 
metres – rather more than half the contents of an Olympic-
size swimming pool. 
Increasing numbers of countries also share 
underground water reserves.  Jordan shares 
with Saudi Arabia the Disi aquifer that repre-
sents its “last substantial unexploited water 
resource”, according to a UN study. Th e vast 
Nubian basin aquifer straddles the borders 
between Libya, Egypt, Sudan and Chad. 
Lack of knowledge about underground 
water resources is a major cause of tension. So 
UNESCO is currently undertaking a project to 
create the world’s most detailed map of Inter-
nationally Shared Aquifer Resources (ISARM). 
The African phase of the survey mapped 20 
cross-border aquifers never delineated before. 
Ghanaians discovered they share an aquifer 
with Cote d’Ivoire. Benin learned that the aqui-
fer providing water for the city of Cotonou 
extends across the border into Togo. 
ISARM is helping these countries draw up 
rules for sharing the water. It has also serves as a 
meeting place where Israeli and Palestinian 
hydrologists share data about the much-disputed 
mountain aquifer that straddles the West Bank. ◆
F.P
In Bangladesh, a 
woman collects water 
from the Ganges
©
 L
a
u
re
n
t 
M
o
n
la
ü
/R
a
p
h
o
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO in novels
UNESCO is featured in a number of novels with fi ctional characters working there.  
Some examples:
“Stanley had a job at 
UNESCO; he travelled to 
unexpected places like 
Turkestan or the 
Philippines.”
Th e Prone Gunman
Jean-Patrick Manchette, 1981. 
“I sat down in my old seat and, in order not to be 
disagreeable, told him I was concerned in 
TECHNICAL AID TO UNDERDEVELOPED 
COUNTRIES (…). He seemed to be impressed by 
UNESCO, as he was 
by anything 
international, he 
stopped treating me 
as a “Switzer” and 
listened as though I 
were an authority, 
with positive 
reverence, interested 
to the point of 
subservience (…)”
Homo Faber.
A Report
Max Frisch, 1957.
“But I was really very lucky. Teaching Spanish at 
the Berlitz School in Paris, writing news bulletins 
at France-Presse, translating for UNESCO, 
dubbing fi lms in the studios at Gennevillers, or 
preparing programs for the French national 
radio-television 
network, I had 
always found jobs 
that brought in 
enough to live on, 
yet allowed me to 
devote at least half 
of each day 
exclusively to my 
writing.”
Aunt Julia and the Scriptwriter
Mario Vargas Llosa, 1977.
“And what else,” said Morris, 
with studied casualness, “do 
they say about this chair?” 
He did not really have to 
wait for her reply to know 
that here, at last, was a prize 
worthy of his ambition. The 
UNESCO Chair of Literary 
Criticism! That had to carry 
the highest salary in the 
profession.”
Small World
David Lodge, 1984.
www.unesco.org/en/courier/interalia 59
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
 60 The new Courier – November 2005
Dig ital  div ide
Poverty can be measured not only in economic or social terms. In these 
times of globalization, the planet is now also divided between those who 
have mastered new information and communication technology (ICT) 
and those who have not. This “digital divide” is at the heart of the World 
Summit on the Information Society (WSIS), held in Tunis on November 
16-18, 2005. 
Bridging the North South 
Divide © Drawings Christian Roux
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
Dig ital  Div ide
When it fi rst appeared, the internet seemed a 
most auspicious tool. It would enable the 
planet to become the “global village” envisaged by 
Marshall McLuhan. Th rough the Web, the poor 
countries would be able to benefi t, with unprec-
edented ease, from a myriad of databases, from 
training, from online courses, all of which would 
provide access to the knowledge society and allow 
these countries to catch up progressively with the 
pack of prosperous nations. In 2001, a United Na-
tions Development Programme (UNDP) report 
stated that technological networks are “transform-
ing the traditional map of development” and “cre-
ating the potential to realize in a decade progress 
that required generations in the past.”
Now that a few years have passed, this 
euphoria has somewhat subsided. Th e tool that 
provides immediate access to huge quantities of 
information remains as promising as ever, but 
there is now a greater awareness of the obsta-
cles to be overcome in order to provide access 
for all. In fact, the digital divide, the term 
applied to describe the technological gap 
between the North and the South, has widened. 
A few fi gures suffi  ce to prove this assertion: in 
the rich countries, one person out of three owns 
a computer compared to one out of 130 in 
Africa; in 2003, 19% of the planet represented 
91% of internet users; one third of the world’s 
population is not connected to an electricity 
supply.
| Information summit
It was in this morose context that the World 
Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) was 
held in Geneva in December 2003, with a sec-
ond phase held in Tunis in November 2005. At 
the WSIS, sponsored by the International Tele-
communication Union (ITU), UNESCO, gov-
ernments, non-governmental organizations 
(NGO) and the private sector, participants all 
came to the same conclusion: the digital divide 
can be bridged if there is consensus on the 
means to bridge it. Th e Summit adopted a Dec-
laration of Principles and a 28-point Action 
Plan calling for universal access to information, 
cultural and linguistic diversity and the free 
exchange of ideas on the net. 
Taking concrete measures, the participants 
adopted the proposition of Senegalese Presi-
dent, Abdoulaye Wade, and, in March 2005, 
created a digital solidarity fund. Based in 
Geneva, it has already collected several hundred 
thousand euros. “Th e WSIS is an historic inter-
national discussion allowing the mobilization 
of numerous partners. Many of the principles 
upheld by UNESCO were included in the fi nal 
document,” says Elizabeth Longworth, Direc-
tor of UNESCO’s Information Society Division. 
Th e texts adopted in Geneva consolidated the 
idea of the “knowledge society, which encom-
passes more than just the information society 
because it also includes the issues of develop-
ment, of content and of diversity,” adds 
Axel Plathe of UNESCO’s Information Society 
Division. 
Th e distinction is important: a knowledge 
society is concerned not only with the trans-
mission of information but also with its content 
and use. Bridging the digital divide is not sim-
ply a question of providing equipment. “It’s 
hard to imagine that someone who doesn’t 
know how to read will know how to look things 
up in a library or that a person will become a 
mathematician simply because they have been 
off ered a digital television,” explains Eric Gui-
chard of the National Institute for Research in 
Computer Science and Control in an article 
Information for All: eradicating
“information poverty” 
 An incongruous gathering of women with power and responsibility was 
held in September 2005 in a country, Uganda, where men generally hold the 
reins of power. The group of elected offi  cials and of managers of small farms or 
businesses, young women all, were invited to come sit in front of a computer 
and acquaint themselves with the most recent information and communication 
technologies (ICT). The initiative originated with the Kampala-based non-
governmental organization (NGO) Forum for Women in Democracy (FOWODE). In 
addition, with funding from UNESCO’s Information for All Programme, FOWODE 
will computerize its library and acquire up-to-date materials. That is a fi rst step 
in the process and a second step, to train the women to use the new tools and to 
search online, will ensue.
 The IFAP is an international co-operation programme aimed at reducing the 
gap between the “information rich” and the “information poor” through regional 
and international partnerships. Another project on libraries and copyrights was 
created in September 2005. Benefi ting from a US$34,000 grant, the project, 
implemented by the international foundation eIFL.net, provides librarians, 
mainly in the former Soviet Union, with political and legal training.
www.unesco.org/en/courier/digital 61
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
 62 The new Courier – November 2005
Dig ital  Div ide
entitled “Does the ‘Digital Divide’ Exist?” (1). 
Owning a computer is a fi rst step, but one “also 
requires a social capital in order to get help 
when  one  doesn ’ t  unders tand  the 
(dys)functioning of a soft ware programme, of 
an online service or of one’s computer; and, 
fi nally, one needs cultural capital to know where 
to look for the information one is seeking,” 
adds Guichard. UNESCO’s Information for All 
Programme (IFAP) was launched with these 
ideas in mind in order to develop “digital liter-
acy” in countries where access to the web is lim-
ited (see box on p. 61).
To achieve this “literacy,” however, lan-
guage-use on the web must be diversifi ed and 
improved. In 2003, 90% of internet users had 
access to only 11 languages (see chart above). 
English is the language most used by far (31.6%), 
followed by Chinese (13.2%) and Japanese 
(8.3%).  For Annie Chéneau-Loquay, founder 
of Afric’anti, an observatory studying the 
impact of ICT on West Africa, there is a need to 
develop content adapted to developing coun-
tries. “Beyond the transfer of technology issue, 
we must think about creating programmes that 
Other
Dutch
Portuguese
Italian
Korean
French
German
Spanish
Japanese
Chinese
English  31.6
13.2
8.3
6.4
5.9
4
3.4
3
3
1.6
19.5
(Percentages)
better respond to the specific needs of their 
economies and of their educational systems 
which oft en combine modern and traditional 
methods,” she says. 
But the battle may not yet be lost if the gen-
eral trend toward a regular increase in internet 
users is any indication, although this varies 
from one continent to another. There were 
23,000 internet users in Sub-Saharan Africa in 
1995, and there are nearly 9 million in 2005, 
according to the International Telecommuni-
cations Union. The number of mobile tele-
phones per inhabitant has also skyrocketed in 
the same region. According to Chéneau-
Loquay, “the acquisition of a cell phone in soci-
eties with a strong oral tradition is a positive 
sign, if not a defi nite indication.” ◆
Samy Mouhoubi
1. Article published in Globalization and Its New Divides: Malcontents, Recipes, 
and Reform, Dutch University Press, Amsterdam, 2003. 
Languages Used on the Internet
Source: Internet World Stats, 2005.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
Dig ital  Div ide
Radio Ada, the Voice of Those
Without a Voice
 A small radio station 120 miles from the Ghanaian capital 
is transformed into a community multimedia centre
Th e traditional apatam, the external reception 
area, serves as a recording studio at Radio Ada. 
Th is small radio station, heard on 93.3 FM, and 
located in Ada, 120 km east of Accra, the capital 
of Ghana, broadcasts “Th e Voice of the Dangme 
People,” the country’s third largest linguistic 
group. It is also the fi rst of a dozen stations in 
the country to become a UNESCO-funded 
community multimedia centre (CMC). 
“Th e CMC gives the population access to 
useful information about global warming, for 
example. In recent years, the sea has gained 
four metres on the shoreline,” says Radio Ana’s 
Manager, Kofi  Lamweh. He sees the station as 
the “voice of those without a voice”. His “com-
munity service” mission consists of providing 
information on international events or on the 
price of fi sh in the local markets, as well as in 
promoting national cohesion and protecting 
the Dangme cultural heritage.
| Starting operations
Radio Ada broadcasts from a gleaming little 
house. Th e renovation work is almost com-
pleted, the smell of fresh paint lingers in the air. 
As soon as the centre gets its internet connec-
tion, its fi ve computers will be operational. 
With its staff  of 15 paid employees and 50 vol-
unteers of all ages, the centre has the long-term 
goal to “create a team of trainers for the four 
local stations” implanted in the area to service a 
potential audience of 500,000. “It’s like a self-
reproducing cell,” says Kofi  Lamweh.
For now, he says “the priority is digital pro-
duction”, which means training in basic com-
puter skills, from scanner to desktop publishing. 
Th e responsibility of this task rests on 18-year-
old Chinedu, self-taught computer expert who 
is in charge of training. “He has even developed 
a soft ware programme that we use for music 
programming,” says the station manager. For 
the moment, six of Chinedu’s eight students 
are adults, but younger people are starting to 
follow. “Th rough the music, through reggae, 
they are becoming interested in what we do,” 
Chinedu says shyly.
“In terms of training, the community cen-
tres are more effi  cient than regional or national 
workshops, because follow-up can be problem-
atic,” says Hezekiel Dlamin advisor for com-
munications and information in the Accra 
UNESCO Offi  ce. He says that “nearly 20 cen-
tres per country will be established soon.” Th is 
initiative will supplement the one and only 
cybercafé in Ada, which opened this summer, 
and it will save future web surfers a 60 km trip 
to fi nd the nearest internet connection. 
www.unesco.org/en/courier/digital 63
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
 64 The new Courier – November 2005
Dig ital  Div ide
But in a country where 40% of the population 
over the age of six has never been to school and 
only 3% has attended university, where the infor-
mal economy dominates, the priority for educa-
tion policy remains “achieving literacy and 
teacher training” rather than “specifi c internet 
training,” explains Boubacar Camara, education 
specialist at the UNESCO Offi  ce Accra. In order 
to provide “equitable access to quality education,” 
he says, education policy must include informa-
tion and communications technologies (ICT). 
Th e government is striving to meet this goal and 
even organized, in Accra in February 2005, the 
Second Africa Preparatory Conference, a regional 
conference preparing the World Summit on the 
Information Society (WSIS).
Together with the Education Ministry and 
the Universities of Cape Coast and Winneba, the 
UNESCO Offi  ce in Accra, in 2004, implemented 
a training programme for trainers with an 
emphasis on computer skills. “Over a thousand 
people have already benefi ted from it,” says Bou-
bacar Camara. In December 2004, a workshop 
was also held at the University of Ghana at  Legon 
on the free operating system Linux, bringing 
together about 15 universities. Further initiatives 
include a programming contest for secondary 
school students organized on February 26, 2005 
by the Ghana-India Kofi  Annan Centre of Excel-
lence in ICT, fl agship of the Ghanaian educa-
tional system. Th e winner was presented with a 
mobile phone while the winner’s school gained a 
computer. These types of initiatives should, 
in coming years, contribute to training new 
 battalions of Chinedus. ◆
Stéphane Auvray
34.5
28.7
23.8
7.3
2.3 1.8 1.7
(Percentages)
Africa
(+ 258%)
Oceania
(+ 116%)
Middle East
(+ 311%)
Latin
America 
(+ 277%)
North
America
(+ 106%)
Europe
(+ 161%)
Asia
(+ 183%)
(Rise btw 2000 and 2005)
Internet Users
in the World
Source: Internet World Stats, 2005. 
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
 In-house Art
Over the years, UNESCO’s Member States have generously donated to the Organization 
some of the best examples of their country’s treasures. Here are some of the lesser-seen 
ones which today adorn the Headquarters buildings.
Detail showing an early stage of cuneiform writing, from 
a slab of baked clay containing an administrative text, 
Sumerian period, 2038-1985 BC, donated by Iraq.
N’Daanaan,
tapestry by
Modou Niang
(1945-), 3 × 2.28 m,
donated by Senegal.
A devata, Buddhist 
female divinity, from 
Prasat Srange at 
Angkor, Bayon style,  
end of 12th – beginning 
of 13th century, 
sandstone, 0.86 m, 
donated by Cambodia.
UNESCO, tapestry 
based on a sketch 
by Le Corbusier 
(1887-1965), 
3.50 × 6.80 m, 
1962, donated by 
Switzerland.
Mummy shroud
from Puruchuco,
cloth, pre-Columbian 
period, 1350-1450,
2.27 × 1.48 m,
donated by Peru.
www.unesco.org/en/courier/interalia 65
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/N
ia
m
h
 B
u
rk
e
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/N
ia
m
h
 B
u
rk
e
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/J
.-
C
. B
e
rn
a
th
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/B
o
n
si
rv
e
n
-F
o
n
ta
n
a
, M
.L
.
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
 66 The new Courier – November 2005
Cr i ses  and Emergencies
The images of desolation from New Orleans 
(United States), ravaged by Hurricane Katrina 
in September 2005, were seen around the world. 
An exceptional occurrence? Unfortunately not. 
Between 1994 and 1998, 428 natural and techno-
logical disasters were recorded. Between 1999 and 
2003, the fi gure climbed to 707 annually. Th ese are 
the numbers cited in the 2004 World Disasters Re-
port published by the International Federation of 
Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies. 
And the most pronounced increase is noted 
in the poorest countries. Another indicator: in 
2004, according to the United Nations High 
Commissioner for Refugees, there were more 
than 9 million refugees around the world. And 
millions more are victims of the damages caused 
by fl oods, droughts, earthquakes, landslides, 
storms and other natural disasters.
Th ough emergency aid professionals have 
acquired real expertise in the last 20 years, 
coming up with the appropriate response to 
such daunting challenges is not easy. 
Emergency response is more than truckloads 
of high-protein survival bars, blue plastic tents 
Devastating fl oods, brutal wars, 
deadly hurricanes – confl icts and 
catastrophes are competing for 
the news headlines. And in every 
case those liable to suff er the worst 
consequences are the poorest. 
Seven times as many people are 
likely to die if a natural disaster 
strikes a developing country than 
if it hits a rich country. When it 
comes to safeguarding freedom 
of the press, providing the means 
for education in emergencies 
or protecting cultural heritage, 
UNESCO does its part.
Coping
with
Emergencies
Somalian refugee in a 
camp in Jordan
© Alexis Duclos/Gamma, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
Cr i ses  and Emergencies
and mobile health centres. The post-crisis 
recovery requires planning. “Many crises we 
can in fact prepare for. Most importantly, 
when a war breaks out or a disaster strikes, the 
relief eff orts must be placed within a long-term 
strategy for the country” says Louise 
Haxthausen, Coordinator for post-conflict 
operations within UNESCO’s Bureau of Field 
Coordination.
| Holistic approach
UNESCO has traditionally not been classifi ed 
as a humanitarian agency, but reconstruction is 
more than physical rebuilding. “A core objec-
tive is to advocate for a more co-ordinated and 
holistic approach to emergencies in the inter-
national community,” says Haxthausen. 
UNESCO does not focus on providing services, 
but on creating strategies for transition and 
capacity-building of local staff  and institutions.
Its activities range from setting up tsunami 
early warning systems to security training for 
media professionals. In Iraq, for instance, cur-
rently the most dangerous country in the world 
for journalists, UNESCO runs training pro-
grams through the International News Safety 
Institute. Th e Organization is also concerned 
with providing access to education to children 
living in areas hit by crises and confl icts, and 
with preserving cultural heritage. One example 
is a two-year project in Afghanistan to safe-
guard the Bamiyan site, where two gigantic 
Buddha statues were destroyed by the Taliban 
in March 2001.
UNESCO’s work often goes unnoticed. 
Other UN agencies such as UNHCR, UNICEF 
and the World Food Programme tend to take 
the lead roles. Haxthausen admits that coordi-
nation within the UN system and with other 
agencies remains one of the Organization’s 
main challenges in situations of emergencies 
and reconstruction. “UNESCO’s mandate is in 
fact very clear. Th e challenge relates to the con-
ditions on the ground,” she says, and explains 
how tasks and responsibilities in emergency 
situations are in reality oft en assigned on a ‘fi rst 
come fi rst serve’ basis. “UNESCO has not made 
enough early investments. We do not have the 
necessary field presence or the capacity to 
deliver fast enough. It is clear that humanitar-
ian intervention and development are not the 
same,” she notes.
On UNESCO’s part, one new initiative to 
improve its emergency response is the plan to 
draw up a personnel roster for rapid deploy-
ment of staff  in crises and reconstruction situa-
tions. The roster would not consist of relief 
workers in the classical sense, but advisors who 
are experts in UNESCO’s fi elds of competence. 
Th is system is already widely used by aid organ-
izations. One of the biggest rosters, managed by 
the Norwegian Refugee Council, lists 600 civil-
ians of diff erent professions who are on stand-
by, ready to go and lend a hand within 72 hours 
in case of emergency. “In its core areas, 
UNESCO has strong competencies. These 
should be made available as soon as possible in 
crises,” says Marcus Volker at the UNESCO 
Bureau of Human Resource Management.
| Foundation for the future
But are these rapid deployment emergency 
actions compatible with long-term develop-
ment eff orts? Th ose in favour of them see no 
contradiction between the two. What is done in 
an emergency must lay the ground for long-
term development, they argue. Take Sierra 
Leone, where 70% of schools were destroyed in 
the civil war that ended in 1972: the substantial 
amount of aid brought by NGOs and UN agen-
cies in the immediate post-war period was cru-
cial to later reconstruction (see article p. 69). 
“In 2000, 300,000 children had no school to go 
to, and many of them were traumatised. We 
would never have made it without international 
aid,” says William Taylor, General Director of 
Education in Sierra Leone. It is a testimonial 
that should infl uence donors.  ◆
 
Eli Wærum Rognerud
Two months after the 
tsunami, school starts 
again in Hikkaduwa, 
village in Sri Lanka
www.unesco.org/en/courier/emergencies 67
©
 N
iv
iè
re
/S
ip
a
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
 68 The new Courier – November 2005
Cr i ses  and Emergencies
Education:
a Priority Response
 Contrary to the traditional approach, education is as crucial in 
emergencies as food or shelter.
“In emergency situations, many still view educa-
tion as a low priority. Th is is an extremely short-
sighted approach. As if lack of education could 
not kill you!” exclaims Christopher Talbot, Pro-
gramme Specialist at UNESCO’s International 
Institute for Education in Emergencies. He sug-
gests starting by asking the simple question: 
‘where are children if they are not in school?’
“Schooling can protect against recruitment 
into military forces,” he continues. “It prevents 
exploitation in dangerous professions. When 
life is chaos, it gives structure and stability. 
Learning and play can for example help chil-
dren deal with serious traumas. School is also a 
great place to pass on life-saving messages and 
skills. Health and hygiene, HIV/AIDS preven-
tion, landmine awareness and peace and con-
flict management can all be promoted at 
school,” says Talbot. 
Traditionally, education has been seen not as 
a humanitarian priority, but as a long-term 
development activity.  Awareness of the need for 
education in emergency situations is on the rise, 
but what is called the relief-development gap is 
far from closed. Humanitarian agencies still tend 
to focus on people’s biological needs, whilst the 
development community prefer to see a peace 
agreement before they intervene in education. 
| Guidelines and standards
“In the real world, the division between relief 
and development makes no sense. People have 
only one life. Th ey cannot aff ord to ‘wait for 
peace’ before investing in their children” under-
lines Talbot. “In the case of the Southern Sudan, 
for example, people had been ‘waiting for peace’ 
for 21 years. Still, in some areas, local and inter-
national agencies have pulled three generations 
of children through the whole cycle of school-
ing. Just because there is war, it does not mean 
you can do nothing.”
But there is room for error between doing 
nothing and providing quality education. In 
conflict situations, the education system is 
oft en embroiled in the prob-
lems that spurred the emer-
gency in the fi rst place. In some 
cases, it has helped suppress 
the languages, traditions, art 
forms and religious and cul-
tural practices of disadvan-
taged groups. “Schooling does 
not always translate into edu-
cation – i.e. learning - or into 
good education – i.e. learning 
what is worthwhile. We know 
that schooling mirrors society 
and that it can reproduce the 
bad alongside the good,” says 
Anna Obura, an educational 
consultant and the author of 
the book “Never again: Educa-
tional Reconstruction in 
Rwanda”. 
Refugee camp in 
Polataka, Sudan
©
 M
a
rt
in
e
 F
ra
n
ck
/M
a
g
n
u
m
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
Cr i ses  and Emergencies
Th e Inter-Agency Network
for Education in Emergencies 
 The Inter-Agency Network for Education in Emergencies (INEE) is a global 
network of about 1,000 humanitarian and development non-governmental 
organizations, UN agencies, donors, practitioners, researchers and individuals 
from aff ected populations. Its goal: to ensure the right to education in 
emergencies, sharing information and disseminating best practices and 
lessons learned in the fi eld.  In 2003, a Working Group was formed to develop 
global minimum standards for education in emergencies. The resulting 
handbook, “Minimum Standards for Education in Emergencies, Chronic Crises and 
Early Reconstruction”, provides guidelines to help governments, donors and 
education providers to improve the design, implementation, development and 
administration of education programs.
See: http://www.ineesite.org 
Learning for a Better Future 
 Mohamed was only fi ve year old when he was forced out of his village 
in Sierra Leone by armed rebels. Today, as a refugee in Guinea, he is 
going to school to try and build a future. 
“I was only fi ve years old then, but I remember 
well. I still have nightmares about it,” says 
Mohamed Camara. Every minute of that day in 
1996, when his village was attacked by rebel sol-
diers, is an indelible memory. Now 14, the ado-
lescent is one of the thousands of children who 
left  Sierra Leone as civil war raged between the 
army and the Revolutionary United Front 
(RUF). He is now a refugee in Kabamoussaya, 
130 km south of Conakry in Guinea. 
“One day when I was playing outside with 
my friends, a gang of young people came on us 
in a surprise attack. Th ey started fi ring on us 
from their jeep. My friends and I panicked and 
ran to reach our homes.  I found my parents. My 
dad was caught by a machete, and there was 
blood everywhere.  My sister was killed. Some 
time aft erwards they got back into their jeeps 
and drove away.  Th e streets were full of dead 
people.  Aft er they had gone, my dad took us 
into the bush. For many, many days, we ate only 
fruit and wild roots, and drank muddy water” 
says Mohamed. 
Th e fi ght between the government forces and 
the RUF lasted a total 11 years. Attacks like those 
experienced by Mohamed and his family were 
commonplace. Children as young as eight were 
forced to join the fi ghting forces – those who 
refused were killed or mutilated. Between 15,000 
and 20,000 Sierra Leonean children fought as 
soldiers, most of them on the rebel side. 
Mohamed and his parents managed to 
escape, and aft er weeks on the run, crossed the 
border to Guinea, where they were given shelter 
in the town of Kabamoussaya. Th ere, for the 
past nine years, they have been trying to rebuild 
their lives, hoping one day to return. Shortly 
aft er arrival, Mohamed joined Wanifi li, a make-
shift  school constructed out of wood and cov-
ered by plastic sheeting donated by UNHCR. 
 Good practice guides and standards for 
education in emergency situations have now 
been developed. Th e Inter-Agency Network for 
Education in Emergencies (INEE), currently 
hosted by UNESCO in Paris, works to share 
and promote those standards (see box). “People 
out in the fi eld see how vital education is for cri-
sis prevention and recovery. Agencies and 
donors should no longer have any excuse not to 
prioritise education in emergency situations.” 
says INEE Network Coordinator Mary Menden-
hall. Yet given most of the rich countries’ fail-
ure to provide adequate funding for Education 
for All, as reported by the Global Campaign for 
Education’s 2005 report, it is not certain that 
this priority will be recognized. ◆
Eli Wærum Rognerud
www.unesco.org/en/courier/emergencies 69
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
 70 The new Courier – November 2005
Cr i ses  and Emergencies
Bhaktapur: Open-Air Museum
 The Nepalese city attracts tourists, but also looters. Because the 
Kathmandu Valley is threatened by pollution, war and urban sprawl, 
it has been added to the List of World Heritage in Danger.
Fourteen kilometres east of Kathmandu, the 
capital, is Bhaktapur, ‘the city of devotees’ that 
is like an enormous open air museum. Th e city 
features thousands of religious art objects, not 
just in Hindu temples and Buddhist shrines, but 
also in public squares, scattered along the streets 
and narrow lanes, or on the facades and in 
niches of private homes. But while they delight 
tourists, these treasures also attract dealers who 
see them as sources of income in a lucrative 
Asian Art market.
“Looting and illicit traffi  cking have stripped 
this area of some of its most important art 
works and monuments. Sacred gods, wor-
shipped and valued by generations of Nepalese, 
should not lie in glass cases in the West,” says 
Aidan Warlow, Programme Director for the 
Kathmandu University Department of Art and 
Design. 
Eff orts to preserve cultural heritage in Nepal 
have increased in recent years. Yet stolen objects 
can still be found in museums, art shops, auc-
tion houses and private collections around the 
world. An Uma Mahesvara statue, stolen from 
Bhaktapur in 1984, is just one example. The 
statue is on display in the Guimet Museum in 
Paris, one of the world’s leading museums of 
South East Asian art. Retrieval of such objects is 
diffi  cult, because they oft en have been through a 
number of dealers who may even have obtained 
legal documents. 
Fighting illicit trafficking is problematic. 
Increased documentation of valuable items, for 
instance, can have negative effects. A list of 
Classes are still overcrowded with an average of 
80 pupils per class, and teachers, many without 
formal training, are working with scarce 
resources. For Mohammed and his peers, school 
is nonetheless their main hope for the future 
and the place to learn essential life skills. In 
addition to traditional subjects such as science, 
maths and language, teachers use sports and 
music classes to help children cope with their 
traumas. 
“Resources are hard to come by here,” 
explains Mohamed Lansanah, a teacher who 
also comes from Sierra Leone.  “But we are 
investing in the reconstruction and the peaceful 
future of our country through the education of 
these young people.”
 Th e eff orts of Mr Lansanah and the com-
munity groups are paying off . In 2004 Wanifi li 
achieved results above the regional average. 
Mohamed Camara ranks second in his class. He 
dreams of one day returning home: “When I 
fi nish my studies I want to be a professor.  Th at 
way I can fi ght for peace and development in 
Sierra Leone.” ◆
Alhassane Souare 
Mohamed Camara, 14, 
is one of thousands 
of children who fl ed 
Sierra Leone
©
 A
lh
a
ss
a
n
e
 S
o
u
a
re
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
List of World Heritage in Danger
 The walled city of Baku in Azerbaijan. The city of Bam (Iran). Garamba National 
Park in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. All three of these sites are inscribed 
on the List of World Heritage in Danger. A site can be inscribed on the List 
when armed confl ict, natural disasters, poaching, unregulated urbanization or 
uncontrolled development threatens its integrity. The World Heritage Committee, 
intergovernmental body that every year examines the state of preservation 
of sites and nominations, can put on the ‘endangered’ list properties whose 
protection requires “major operations (…) and for which assistance has been 
requested”. This allows the allocation of immediate assistance from the World 
Heritage Fund to the endangered property.
objects to be protected can also be used by loot-
ers. Says Warlow, “It is actually a serious 
dilemma. To a professional art thief, a catalogue 
with the ‘top ten’ valuables in a village is like a 
treasure map.”
| Increasing awareness of danger
Th e Kathmandu Valley was added to the World 
Heritage List in 1978, and was already then a 
region threatened by rapid population growth, 
economic and social change, increasing pollution 
and high earthquake risk. “Looting of statues is a 
serious problem, but the biggest threat lies in the 
gradual deterioration of the ‘urban texture’ sur-
rounding these monuments” says Giovanni Boc-
cardi, Chief of the Asia and Pacifi c Unit at the 
World Heritage Centre. “Ancient architecture 
has for example been irreversibly damaged by 
uncontrolled building work and demolition”.
Th e decade-long confl ict between the Nepa-
lese government and the Maoist rebels has 
added further diffi  culties to the site’s conserva-
tion. “Large areas of the country are now out-
side formal control, and therefore open for 
anyone who wants to loot and traffi  c. As people 
get poorer, or fl ee their homes, the risk of theft  
or simply damage also increases dramatically,” 
says Koto Kanno, Head of the UNESCO offi  ce 
in Kathmandu.  
In 2003, the Kathmandu Valley was inscribed 
on the List of World Heritage in Danger. 
Kanno explains how the labelling of the 
Kathmandu valley as ‘endangered’ caused 
strong reactions: “Th e inscription was a 
big blow to the government as well as the 
population - people felt it was humiliat-
ing.” Th is is not uncommon; most coun-
tries with world heritage sites wish to 
avoid inscription on the ‘endangered’ 
list. 
In Nepal, inscription has nonetheless 
increased awareness amongst offi  cials of 
the need to take fi rm action in World 
Heritage sites. “Th e government is taking 
this work very seriously. A warning from 
the World Heritage Committee that 
Lumbini, the birthplace of the Lord Bud-
dha, may also be moved to the ‘endan-
gered’ list stimulated an immediate 
action plan and the involvement of both 
local and international conservation 
experts”, says Kanno.
More important, however, is to increase the 
awareness in the communities. “In the Kath-
mandu Valley, the surroundings are as much 
part of the cultural heritage as the monuments 
themselves. Yet people are largely unaware of 
the treasures right there in front on them,” says 
Kanno. 
Th e export of art work is oft en also facilitated 
by locals. When impoverished individuals will-
ingly sell a monument or a part of their house 
for a few dollars, it is generally because they do 
not understand its real worth. Once aware of the 
importance of preserving cultural heritage, the 
communities themselves become the best guard 
for their monuments and their surroundings. ◆
Eli Wærum Rognerud 
Bhaktapur, “the city 
of devotees”
www.unesco.org/en/courier/emergencies 71
©
 K
e
w
le
y 
V
a
n
ya
/C
a
m
e
ra
p
re
ss
/G
a
m
m
a
, P
a
ri
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
 72 The new Courier – November 2005
Contac ts
UNESCO Offi  ces
Afghanistan
United Nations Compound
P.O. Box 5, Kabul
Tel : (93-79) 344 229
Fax: 00 873 763 468 836; 004 724 
126 902
E-mail: kabul@unesco.org
Bangladesh
G.P.O. Box 57
Dhaka 1207
Tel: (8802) 986 2073; 987 3210
Fax: (8802) 987 1150
E-mail: dhaka@unesco.org
Brazil
Caixa Postal 08563
Brasilia 
Tel: (55 61) 2106 3500
Fax: (55-61) 3322 4261
E-mail: brasilia@unesco.org
http://www.unesco.org.br
Burundi
B.P. 1490
Bujumbura
Tel: (257) 21 53 82/84
Fax: 257 21 53 83
E-mail: bujumbura@unesco.org
Cambodia
P.O. Box 29, 38 Samdech Sothearos 
Blvd.
Phnom Penh
Tel: (855-23) 426 726
Fax: (855-23) 426 163
E-mail: phnompenh@unesco.org
http://portal.unesco.org/
phnompenh
Cameroon
B.P. 12909
Yaoundé
Tel: (237) 22 257 63
Fax: (237) 22 263 89
E-mail: yaounde@unesco.org
Chile
Casilla 127, Correo 29, Providencia
Santiago de Chile
Tel: (56 2) 472 4600
Fax: (56 2) 655 10 46
E-mail: santiago@unesco.org
http://www.unesco.cl/esp
China
Room 1503, Bldg. 5, 
Waijiaogongyu, Jianguomenwai 
Beijing 100600
Tel: (86 10) 65 32 1725/5790/5883
Fax: (86 10) 65 32 4854
E-mail: beijing@unesco.org
http://www.unescobeijing.org
Congo
B.P. 90
Brazzaville
Tel : (242) 670 55 53
Fax : (242) 81 17 80
E-mail: brazzaville@unesco.org
Costa Rica
Apartado 220-2120
San Francisco de Guadalupe
Tel: (506) 258 7625
Fax : (506) 258 7458
E-mail: san-jose@unesco.org
Cuba
Calzada 551 – Esq. a D, Vedado
Havana
Tel: (53 7) 833 34 38; 832 2840
Fax: (53 7) 833 31 44
E-mail: habana@unesco.org
http://www.unesco.org.cu
Democratic Republic of the Congo
B.P. 7248 
Kinshasa I
Tel : (243) 81 88 48 253
Fax : (243) 99 99 75 361
E-mail : kinshasa@unesco.org
Ecuador
Juan León Mera 130 y Ave. Patria, 
Edifi cio CFN 6to piso
Quito
Tel: (593-2) 2529.085 / 2562.327
Fax : (593-2) 2504.435
E-mail : quito@unesco.org
http://portal.unesco.org/quito
Egypt
8 Abdel-Rahman Fahmy Street, 
Garden City
Cairo 11541
Tel : (20-2) 79 50424
Fax : (20-2) 79 45 296
E-mail: cairo@unesco.org
Ethiopia
P.O. Box 1177
Addis Ababa
Tel : (251-11) 551-3953
Fax :(251-11) 551-1414
E-mail: addis@unesco.org
Gabon
B.P. 2183
Libreville
Tel: (241) 76 28 79
Fax: (241) 76 28 14
E-mail: unesclbv@inet.ga
Ghana
P.O. Box CT4949
Accra
Tel: (233-21) 765 497 ; 765 499
Fax: 233 21 765 498
E-mail: accra@unesco.org
Guatemala
Calle 4, 1-57, Zona 10
Guatemala City
Tel: (502) 2360 5659/73 65
Fax:(502) 2331 1524
E-mail: unesco@guate.net.gt
http://www.unescoguatemala.org
Haïti
19, Delmas 60, Musseau par 
Bourdon, Petion Ville
Port-au-Prince
Tel : (509) 511 04 60
Fax : (509) 244-9366-7
E-mail: unescohaiti@hainet.net
India
B 5/29 Safdarjung Enclave
New Delhi 110 029
Tel: (91-11) 2671 3000
Fax: (91-11) 2671 3001/2
E-mail: newdelhi@unesco.org
http://unescodelhi.nic.in
Indonesia
UNESCO House, Jalan Galuh II, 
No.5, Kebayoran Baru
Jakarta 12110
Tel: (62-21) 739 9818
Fax: (62 21) 7279 6489
E-mail: jakarta@unesco.org
http://www.unesco.or.id
Iran (Islamic Republic of)
Bahman Building, Saadabad 
Complex, Darband Square
Tehran 19894
Tel: (98 21) 22740141-3
Fax: (98 21) 2740144
E-mail: tehran@unesco.org
Italy
Palazzo Zorzi, Castello 4930
Venice
Tel : (39) 041 2601511
Fax : (39) 041 5289995
E-mail: roste@unesco.org
http://portal.unesco.org/venice
Jamaica
Th e Towers, 25 Dominica Drive
Kingston 5
Tel: (1-876) 929 70 87-9
Fax: (1-876) 929 84 68
E-mail: kingston@unesco.org
http://www.unescocaribbean.org
 
Jordan
P.O. Box 2270
Amman 11181
Tel: (962-6) 551 4234/6559
Fax: (962-6) 553 2183
E-mail: registry@unesco.org.jo
Kazakhstan
67, Tole Bi Street
Almaty 050000
Tel: (7-3272) 58 26 37-42
Fax:(7-3272) 79 48 53
E-mail: almaty@unesco.org
http://www.unesco.kz
Kenya
United Nations Complex, Gigiri, 
Block C
Nairobi
Tel : (254-20) 62 12 34
Fax : (254- 20) 62 27 50
E-mail : p.vitta@unesco.org
http://www.unesco-nairobi.org
Lebanon
B.P. 11-5244
Beirut
Tel : (961-1) 85 00 13-5
Fax : (961-1) 82 48 54
E-mail : beirut@unesco.org
http://portal.unesco.org/beirut
Mali
B.P. E 1763, Badalabougou Est
Bamako
Tel : (223) 223 34 92-93
Fax : (223) 223 34 94 
E-mail : bamako@unesco.org
http://www.un.org.ml/snu/unesco.
htm
Mexico
Pte Masaryk n.° 526, 3er piso, 
Colonia Polanco
11560 Mexico, D.F.
Tel : (52-55) 5230 7600
Fax : 52-55) 5230 7602
E-mail : mexico@unesco.org
Morocco
35, avenue du 16 novembre, Agdal
Rabat 1777
Tel : (212) 37 67 03 72-74 ; 37 77 
81 82
Fax : (212) 37 67 03 75
E-mail : rabat@unesco.org
http://portal.unesco.org/rabat
 Mozambique
C.P. 1397
Maputo
Tel: (258) 0149 3434
Fax : (258) 0149 3431
E-mail : maputo@unesco.org
http://www.uem.mz/unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
www.unesco.org/fr/courier/contacts 73
Contac ts
UNESCO European Centre for Higher 
Education (CEPES) 
39, Stirbei Voda St. 
010102-Bucharest, Romania
Tel: (40 21) 3130839; 3130698; 
3159956 
Fax: (40 21) 3123567  
E-mail: info@cepes.ro
http://www.cepes.ro
International Centre for Theoretical 
Physics (ICTP)
Strada Costiera 11, 
34014 Trieste, Italy
Tel: (39 040) 2240111
Fax: (39 040) 224163
E-mail: sci_info@ictp.it 
http://www.ictp.it
UNESCO-IHE Institute for Water 
Education 
P.O. Box 3015
2601 DA Delft , Th e Netherlands
Tel: (31-15) 2151 715
Fax: (31-15 2122 921
E-mail: info@unesco-ihe.org
http://www.unesco-ihe.org
UNESCO International Institute for 
Capacity-Building in Africa (IICBA)
P.O. Box 2305
Addis Ababa, Ethiopia
Tel: (251-11) 5513796
Fax: (251-11) 5514936
E-mail: info@unesco-iicba.org
http://www.unesco-iicba.org
 
UNESCO Institute for Education (UIE)
Feldbrunnenstr. 58 
20148 Hamburg, Germany
Tel (49-40) 448041-0 
Fax (49-40) 4107723 
E-mail: uie@unesco.org
http://www.unesco.org/education/
uie
UNESCO International Institute for 
Educational Planning (IIEP)
7-9, rue Eugène-Delacroix
75116 Paris, France
Tel: (33-1) 45 03 77 00
Fax: (33-1) 40 72 83 66
E-mail: info@iiep.unesco.org
http://www.unesco.org/iiep
IIPE-Buenos Aires
Agüero 2071
1425 Buenos Aires, Argentina 
Tel: (54-11) 4806 9366;  4807 5446
Fax: (54-11) 4806 9458
E-mail: info@iipe-buenosaires.
org.ar 
http://www.iipe-buenosaires.org.ar
UNESCO International Institute for 
Higher Education in Latin America and 
the Caribbean (IESALC)
Apartado Postal 68.394. 
Caracas 1062-A, Venezuela 
Tel: (58-212) 286.0555; 286.1020
Fax: (58-212) 286.0527; 286.0527
E-mail: iesalc@unesco.org.ve
http://www.iesalc.unesco.org.ve
UNESCO International Bureau of 
Education (IBE)
C.P. 199, 1211 Geneva 20, 
Switzerland
Tel.: (41-22) 917.78.00
Fax: (41-22) 917.78.01
E-mail: director@ibe.unesco.org
http://www.ibe.unesco.org
 
UNESCO Institute for Information 
Technologies in Education (IITE)
8 Kedrova St. (Bldg. 3),
117292 Moscow, Russian 
Federation
Tel.: (7-095) 129-29-90
Fax: (7-095) 129-12-25
E-mail: Azat.Khannanov@iite.ru
http://is.iite.ru/html
 
UNESCO International Centre for 
Technical and Vocational Education 
and Training 
(UNEVOC)
Görresstrasse 15
53113 Bonn, Germany
Tel: (49-228) 2 43 37-0
Fax: (49-228 2 43 37-77
Email: info@unevoc.unesco.org
http://www.unevoc.unesco.org
UNESCO Institute for Statistics (UIS)
C.P. 6128 Succursale Centre-ville 
Montreal, Quebec, H3C 3J7 Canada
Tel: (1-514) 343-6880
Fax: (1-514) 343-6882
E-mail:  information@uis.unesco.
org
http://www.uis.unesco.org
UNESCO  Institutes and Centres
Namibia 
Oppenheimer House, 5 Brahms 
Street, Windhoek West
Windhoek
Tel : (264 61) 291 7000
Fax : (264 61) 291 7220
E-mail : windhoek@unesco.org
http://portal.unesco.org/windhoek
Nepal
P.O. Box 14391
Kathmandu
Tel : (977-1) 5554 396 ; 5554 769
Fax : (977-1) 5554 450
E-mail : kathmandu@unesco.org
http://www.unesco.org/kathmandu
Nigeria
Plot 777, Bouake St. off  Herbert 
Macaulay Way, Wuse Zone 6,
Abuja
Tel : (234-9) 461 8502 ; 461 8510
Fax : (234-9) 52 38 094
E-mail: abuja@unesco.org
Pakistan
P.O. Box 2034 A
Islamabad 44000
Tel: (92-51) 280 0083
Fax: (92-51) 280 0056
E-mail: islamabad@unesco.org
http://undp.un.org.pk/unesco
Palestinian Authority 
P.O. Box 2154
Ramallah
Tel : (972-2) 2959740
Fax : (972-2) 2959741
E-mail : unesco@palnet.com
Peru
Apartado Postal 41
Lima 0192
Tel : (51-1) 476 98 71; 224 25 26
Fax : (51-1) 476 98 72
E-mail : unescope@amauta.rcp.
net.pe
http://www.unesco.org/lima
Qatar
P.O. Box 3945
Doha
Tel : (974) 486 7707-8
Fax : (974) 486 7644
E-mail : doha@unesco.org
http://www.unesco.org/doha
Russian Federation
Mytnaya Str. 1
Moscow 119049
Tel : (7-095) 230 0554/1065/0643
Fax : (7-095) 230 6085 ; 956 3666
E-mail: moscow@unesco.org
http://www.unesco.ru
Samoa 
P.O. Box 615, Matautu-uta Post 
Offi  ce
Apia
Tel : (685) 242 76
Fax : (685) 222 53
E-mail : apia@unesco.org
Senegal
B.P. 3311
Dakar
Tel : (221) 849 23 23
Fax : (221) 823 83 93
E-mail : dakar@unesco.org
http://www.dakar.unesco.org
Switzerland
Villa “Les Feuillantines”
CH-1211 Geneva 10
Tel : (41-22) 917 33 81
Fax : (41-22) 917 00 64
E-mail : geneva@unesco.org
Tanzania (United Republic of)
P.O. Box 31473
Dar es Salaam
Tel: (255-22) 266 6623/7165
Fax : (255-22) 266 6927
E-mail: dar-es-salaam@unesco.org
Thailand
920 Sukhumvit Road,
Bangkok 10110
Tel : (66-2) 391 0577/0879
Fax : (66-2) 391 0866
E-mail : bangkok@unesco.org
http://www.unescobkk.org
United States of America
2, United Nations Plaza, Room 900,
New York, NY 10017
Tel: (1-212) 963 59 95
Fax: (1-212) 963 80 14
E-mail: s.bilello@unesco.org
Uruguay
Casilla de Correo 859
Montevideo 11300
Tel : (598-2) 413 20 75
Fax : (598-2) 413 20 94
E-mail : orcyt@unesco.org.uy
http://www.unesco.org.uy
Uzbekistan
95, Amir Temur St.
Tashkent 700084
Tel: (998-71) 12 07 116
Fax : (998-71) 13 21 382
E-mail: tashkent@unesco.org
Vietnam
23 Cao Ba Quat St.
Hanoi
Tel: (84-4) 747 0275
Fax : (84-4) 747 0274
E-mail : registry@unesco.org.vn
http://www.unesco.org.vn
Zimbabwe
P.O. Box HG 435, Highlands
Harare
Tel : (263-4) 776 775-9
Fax : (263-4) 776 055
E-mail : harare@unesco.org
http://www.harare.unesco.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[
“Death Rites”
Gérard Voisin (1934)
Wood installation
Donated to UNESCO 
by the artist in 2005
© UNESCO/Danica Bijeljac
]]>
</page>
</document>
