<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="151580eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 2
Contents
Are women destined to be scientists? They are holding more and more 
positions in laboratories and universities. But even if the proportion 
of women participating in science increases, they are still far from 
playing on an even field with their male colleagues.
WomeN iN ScieNce: 
The miSSiNg LiNkS
This document may be accessed online: www.unesco.org/courier
The trailing 
spouse 
syndrome 8
Budding Plant 
Research 6
Rare as 
hens’ teeth? 2
Argentina: 
the illusion 
of equality 4
“We need the 
best people as 
scientists” - 
interview 0
No statistics, 
no problem, 
no policy... 2
The Courier looks 
back  5
Discoverers - 
Portraits 
of Women  7
“Science has 
neither frontiers 
nor gender 
barriers” - 
interview  6
2007 - number 2
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 22
Even if they are far from reaching parity 
with their males colleagues, more females 
than ever are researchers. But they remain 
largely absent from the highest rungs of the 
profession and must often make difficult 
choices between professional career and 
private life.
When nuclear physicist, Fay Ajzenberg-Selove, was a 
post-doctoral researcher at Princeton University 
(USA) in the 1950s, she had to sneak into the parti-
cle accelerator building at night to work – it was out 
of bounds to women. While this could not happen 
today, a flurry of recent reports shows that women 
scientists are still often at a significant disadvan-
tage compared to their male colleagues, especially as 
their careers advance. 
Data for 2004 just published by the European Com-
mission show that women make up just 29% of those 
employed as scientists and engineers in the European 
Union – even fewer (18%) in the business and enter-
prise sector. And it is precisely this sector that is 
expected to provide the resources for the EU to meet 
its Lisbon Strategy target of 3% of GDP for research 
by 2010. According to a 2006 EC publication, “this is 
likely to involve the creation of some 700,000 new 
research-related jobs by 2010 – which Europe will 
have trouble filling as long as half of its population 
remain sidelined in the S&T field.” 
A similar picture emerges globally. According to 
UNESCO’s Institute for Statistics (UIS) women make 
up less than 30 percent of researchers in 34 out of 89 
countries surveyed, while only 17 – 18% of countries 
have gender parity in science and technology research 
jobs. The picture changes slightly according to disci-
pline, with women even forming the majority of 
researchers in life sciences and medicine. But, accord-
ing to one observer in the USA, women are “rare as 
hens teeth” in mathematics and physics. A 1999 study 
at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) 
revealed only 15 tenured women faculty in the School 
of Science, compared to 194 men. The figure had 
scarcely changed in the previous two decades, 
although swift policy changes in the light of the 
report have gone some way to improve the 
inequality.
For Renée Clair, UNESCO Executive Secretary of 
the L’Oréal-UNESCO For Women in Science programme, 
the 1995 World Conference on Women in Beijing 
(China) marked a turning point in awareness of this 
gender bias in science. “Before that, the issue didn’t 
even arise,” she says, blaming ingrained and largely 
unconscious stereotypes that promote the idea that 
women “aren’t made to do science.” As recently as 
January 2005, the president of Harvard University, 
Lawrence H. Summers sparked a 
furor by arguing that innate dif-
ferences explain why fewer women 
succeed in maths and science 
careers, forcing his resigna-
tion. Findings in psychol-
ogy and neuroscience 
tends to suggest that 
social stereotypes are 
the most potent neg-
ative influence for 
girls, although males 
Rare as hens’ teeth?
© Micheline Pelletier/Gamma
© UNESCO/Michel Ravassard
Renée Clair, UNESCO 
Executive Secretary of the 
L’Oréal-UNESCO For Women 
in Science programme 4
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 2
One of the difficulties women face is whether to 
interrupt their career to have children, often just 
when they also need to intensify their research 
output to get ahead. In the Athena survey, more 
women (32%) than men (4%) had taken career breaks. 
And a higher proportion of women (29%) than men 
(14%) reported difficulties in returning to work. For 
women, the difficulties were mainly centred on find-
ing work, flexible hours of work and childcare, as 
well as the negative attitude of colleagues and man-
agers. Not surprisingly, more women than men move 
‘sideways’ into managerial posts and away from 
research. 
Projects like Athena have already begun to bear 
fruit, with research funding bodies drawing up ‘best 
practice’ guidelines for equal opportunities, with 
incentives for research institutes that introduce 
them. Meanwhile, other obstacles are beginning to 
emerge. In countries like India, with its technology 
boom, young women are preferring to go for highly-
paid jobs in information technology – ironically once 
an all-male preserve, but increasingly dominated by 
women. ■
Peter Coles in London, United Kingdom
and females may differ in the strategies they use to 
solve the kinds of problems encountered in scientific 
research. 
One way to redress the imbalance, says Renée 
Clair, is to “change the image of science and the 
image of women in science,” by providing attractive 
role models. After all, of the 513 Nobel Prizes for 
physics, chemistry and physiology or medicine 
awarded since 1901, only 12 have gone to women - 
two of them to the same person, Marie Curie. This, 
explains Renée Clair, is one function of the L’Oréal-
UNESCO For Women in Science prizes awarded each 
year since 2000 to outstanding women scientists 
from five continents. The 2006 awards will be 
announced in Paris on XX February. 
Boosting the number of female undergraduates 
studying science is one way towards parity in employ-
ment in scientific research, especially in countries 
where girls may be denied access to even basic edu-
cation. “I didn’t even know that one could do research 
in mathematics as a career,” says Ramdorai Sujatha, 
winner of the 2006 Ramanujan prize for her work in 
mathematics at the Tata Institute of Fundamental 
Research in India. “There was absolutely no informa-
tion dissemination.”
But recent evidence suggests that other forms of 
discrimination emerge during the career of a woman 
scientist, effectively barring them from the top jobs 
– what has come to be known as the ‘leaky pipeline’. 
A 2004 survey carried out by the Athena Project, a 
consortium of UK research funding bodies, universi-
ties and government science departments launched 
in 1999, found little evidence for discrimination at 
the bottom of the career ladder. Indeed, women were 
slightly more likely than men to succeed in their first 
application for a lectureship post. But women were 
significantly under-represented at senior levels and, 
in the older age groups, were more likely to be on 
short-term contracts. 
© Peter Coles
23-year-old Hansi Devi repairs a solar lantern at the 
Barefoot College in Tilonia, Rajasthan (India) after a 6-
month training course
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 24
the dubious privilege of being the only female associ-
ate professor in her specialized field in the University 
of Buenos Aires’ School of Medicine. 
“Even within this School,” she says, “most gradu-
ates are women, yet there is not a single one on the 
Board of Directors. And everyone thinks this is normal. 
The same applies to Conicet: there is just one woman 
on its board. In the University of Buenos Aires, it’s 
the same story. These figures conceal the hostility 
which women suffer on a daily basis.” 
Kochen, who also forms part of the Argentine Net-
work of Gender, Science and Technology (RAGCyT), 
points to an interview she had for an academic job as 
one example of this hostility. “They asked me what my 
private life was like, whether I had any children, if I 
was married…. I asked around, and found that none of 
the men had been asked the same.”
Many female scientists; 
few at the top
Women make up 59 percent of university students from 
all disciplines in Argentina. Among those who finish 
their degrees, women represent 66 percent of the total, 
and also achieve on average higher final grades. But 
looking at the scientific and teaching profession as a 
whole, it is clear that the presence of women thins out 
Argentina: the illusion of equality
The latest statistics look promising: 46 percent of all 
scientific researchers in Latin America and the Carib-
bean are women. Argentina, where this figure rises to 
51 percent, has just broken through the gender parity 
barrier, meaning that women form the majority in a 
research industry made up of 35,300 people. Yet 
behind these rosy-looking numbers lurks the truth 
that women are still far from achieving real equality. 
“The statistics are interesting in that they reveal 
how a critical mass of women has occupied this sector, 
but we still have to see what else is taking place. When 
you look at the whole life-span of careers in science, 
you see how the proportion of women starts to decline, 
that women don’t hold important positions, that there 
is no equity in access to grants, which has serious 
repercussions for a researcher’s autonomy and ends up 
generating more inequality,” argues Silvia Kochen, a 
doctor of medicine and neurologist, currently employed 
as a researcher by the National Council of Scientific 
and Technical Research (Conicet). Kochen is also a 
member of specialist neurological associations, and has 
In Argentina, one researcher out of two 
is female. But these numbers hide other 
inequalities.
© Sol Levinas
Silvia Kochen
© Flickr
Students in chemistry lab
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 25
at the top: over the last few years, for instance, the 
percentage of female grantees has risen over 50 per-
cent, but the percentage of women classified as “high 
researchers” - the top category - has stayed extremely 
low at 10 percent. The same applies to the class of 
independent researchers, one step below the top 
research grade, where women make up 25 percent of 
the total. Research institutes are mostly run by men, 
with the exception of those linked to the study of phi-
losophy and literature. In Conicet, meanwhile, women 
make up around 40 percent of total research staff, but 
represent only 12 percent of the Qualification and Pro-
motion Board, and a similar number in other standing 
committees. 
These figures are to be found in the report Wom-
en’s participation in science and technology in Argen-
tina, prepared in 2003 by María Elina Estébanez, who 
states that the situation has changed little since the 
study was drafted. The information provided by 290 
male and female researchers for her report also shows 
that women as well as men tend to prefer male scien-
tific role models, such as in their choice of research 
supervisors. But the report also identifies the spe-
cific obstacles that women face in their careers: the 
surveyed scientists declared that marriage and chil-
dren do affect the development of a career in science, 
and that this is made worse by the fact that doctor-
ates, post-doctorate studies and trips to international 
congresses coincide with a woman’s fertile age. 
Within Conicet, top appointments are made by gov-
ernment officials, who make their choices from a list of 
candidates put forward by working researchers. Noemí 
Girbal is the first, and for now the only woman to have 
been chosen by her peers and to have made it to the 
Board of Directors. The other seven directors, including 
the chair and two deputy chairs, are men. A doctor in 
history and a higher researcher, Girbal, who secured a 
second term as a director in 2005, has argued in public 
against affirmative action for women. She insists that 
it is important not to be led astray by stop-gap, make-
shift solutions, but to get to the roots of the problem: 
“scientific language conveys political power. Participa-
tion in the world of science has a lot to do with power, 
management, and the prestige of arriving at certain 
career rankings – and all of that is male.”
Prestige counts
The best strategy, Girbal insists, is to lay bare the ine-
qualities and hurdles to gender parity, which are far 
from being insuperable, and can be altered by political 
decisions. In the Sixth Iberoamerican Science, Tech-
nology and Gender Congress, held in the Spanish city 
of Zaragoza in September 2006, she made precisely 
this argument in her paper Sex in science. An assess-
ment of gender equality in the Argentine scientific 
system, which included several noteworthy observa-
tions: “There are no female deans in private universi-
ties, and very few in public ones. In scientific journals, 
the editors and editorial committee are often men, but 
articles are written by women, meaning that they do 
the work. On the other hand, we cannot maintain that 
in Argentina – unlike other countries – there are still 
wage differentials between male and female scientists; 
yet there is no doubt that differences arise as women 
are prevented from reaching certain posts. That is why 
I say this is not about substantive economic inequal-
ity, but essentially a question of prestige and power.” 
“None of this is reflected in the statistics, but is 
hidden: we have to deal with it in a different way, by 
looking into the deeper causes behind what is going 
on,” says Kochen, who insists on the end to draw up 
new indicators, a project that has been underway for 
several years in RAGCyT. ■
Soledad Vallejos in Buenos Aires, Argentina
© Sol Levinas
Noemí Girbal
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 26
Laureate for Africa of the 2007 L’ORÉAL-
UNESCO Awards, Ameenah Gurib-Fakim 
has spent much of her life taking 
inventory of plants in her homeland, 
Mauritius.
What if, one day soon, medicinal plants could cure 
diarrhea in children, at little cost? Or bitter melon – 
Momordica charantia – provide a treatment for cer-
tain forms of diabetes? Ameenah Gurib-Fakim believes 
in this. Her team has actually investigated the vir-
tues of the exotic fruit, which acts as a starch blocker 
to slow the release of free glucose into the 
bloodstream. 
When you see Professor Gurib-Fakim sitting at her 
pro-vice-chancellor’s desk at the University of Mauri-
tius, elegant in her tailored suit, her appearance 
doesn’t exactly evoke the countryside. Yet the 45-
year-old professor of organic chemistry, who received 
her degree from the University of Exeter (United 
Kingdom), has devoted much of her life to tracking 
the myriad plants of her native land, the island of 
Mauritius. 
Back when she began, the study of the yellow fan 
palm, bois goudron (Antirrhoa frangulacea) or liane 
calli (Sarcostemma viminale) was hardly in vogue 
among young scientists. “Plant research wasn’t very 
credible,” she admits. Even less so for a female 
researcher. “When you’re a woman, it’s only when 
you’ve made it past the barrier of prejudice and you 
have a list of accomplishments that you’re taken seri-
ously. That’s why many women give up along the 
way,” deplores the scientist and mother of two.
A long-term project
Ameenah Gurib-Fakim didn’t give up. On the contrary. 
Thanks to her, a full inventory exists of the medici-
nal and aromatic plants on Mauritius and the neigh-
boring island of Rodriguez. A long-term project, 
considering Mauritius is a true reservoir of biodiver-
sity. Out of 634 known medicinal plants, 15% are 
endemic (i.e., found only on the island). 
Professor Gurib-Fakim took a particular interest in 
the pharmacological properties of these plants, an 
aspect not covered in previous studies. In addition 
to taking the usual samples, the researcher and her 
team visited villages to collect traditional knowl-
edge. They had to get past the resistance of local 4
© Micheline Pelletier/Gamma
© Micheline Pelletier/Gamma
Budding Plant 
Research
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 27
healers, not always enthusiastic about sharing their 
wisdom with outsiders. 
As a number of these plants could be used as 
alternatives to commercial medicines sold in phar-
macies, the interest they represent is more than 
anecdotal. Nearly 80% of the population of poor 
countries already relies on medicinal plants for 
treatment. What matters now is making sure the 
poor countries don’t miss out on the commercial 
exploitation of these products, for the profit of big 
industrial firms. 
“Africa has already lost so much,” declares Gurib-
Fakim, due to the absence of a legal framework to 
protect intellectual property. This was one of her 
reasons for becoming a founding member of the Asso-
ciation for African Medicinal Plants Standards. Since 
its creation in 2005, the organization, which regroups 
scientists, industrialists, exporters and herbal thera-
pists, has pursued its aim to bring to the world 
market African plant remedies that meet interna-
tional norms.
The plant cause
The initiative is promising, as long as these plants 
with their multiple benefits don’t die out. And some 
are already threatened. On Rodrigues, out of 
193 medicinal plants, 23 of them endemic, about 
20 have dwindled down to only one or two clumps. 
“Young people have to be made aware that plants 
are both rare and useful,” she stresses. As a con-
tribution, she published a guide book in 1983 on 
the flora of Mauritius intended for the general 
public. 
Ameenah Gurib-Fakim doesn’t hesitate to come out 
of her laboratory to advocate for plants. In 1998, she 
participated in a World Bank project to create small 
gardens in schools to cultivate medicinal plants. 
“When we give endemic plants value as ornamental 
plants, it helps to propagate them,” she explains. 
The international recognition she is receiving 
today will certainly be helpful to her cause. It also 
distinguishes this woman scientist as a role model of 
success for young female scientists in the South. “To 
encourage girls,” she insists, “you have to impart 
self-confidence very early on, so that they believe 
they have a chance to succeed.” ■
Amina Osman, in Port Louis, Mauritius
4
© Micheline Pelletier/Gamma
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 28
Like about half of her friends at the time, molecular 
biologist, Claire Wyman, met her husband, Roland 
Kanaar, when they were graduate students at the 
University of California, Berkeley (USA). The crunch 
came when they both started to look for permanent 
jobs. “We were open to all sorts of options in terms 
of jobs and where we might end up,” she says. But, 
as Roland was slightly ahead of Claire in his career at 
the time, “he was offered three pretty good posi-
tions and I didn’t even get an interview.” Claire did 
not want to live apart from her husband, or to take a 
teaching job – alternatives that face many young, 
dual-career scientists. So the couple decided to take 
up one of the offers, and move to the Netherlands, 
where Roland was born. 
At Erasmus University, Claire could work part-
time, which, she says, “was virtually unheard of in 
universities in the USA at the time.” They found the 
flexibility at Erasmus enabled Claire to take time 
off to have children, while remaining active in her 
field, supported by grants. “I was finally offered an 
associate professor position in the same depart-
ment as my husband,” she says. “We ended up work-
ing on the same topic and now have overlapping 
research groups.” In the USA, she adds, “it would 
have been much more difficult to work part time 
when my children were small - and to have main-
tained the respect of my colleagues while doing 
that.”
It’s even harder for physicists
The ‘dual-career’ problem is at its most acute in phys-
ics, where the gender gap is at its widest. Out of 
roughly 40,000 members of the American Physical 
Society, only about 2,400 (6%) are women. And, 
according to a major survey of women physicists car-
ried out in 1998 by Laurie McNeil of the University of 
North Carolina and Marc Sher of the College of Wil-
liam and Mary, about 68% are married to scientists, 
half of them physicists. Even though a smaller pro-
portion (17%) of male physicists marry scientists, 
the study suggests “it is increasingly likely that the 
top candidate in a search (for a job) will have a 
spouse who is also seeking professional employ-
ment.” In most cases, if there is no opening for the 
spouse, he or she is expected to accept a part-time, 
or less secure job, dependent on grant funding. And, 
according to the survey, “the lower-level offer goes 
more commonly to the female member of the couple.” 
This, obviously, perpetuates the scarcity of women in 
high-level physics research. 
According to the survey, some university faculties 
in the USA find dual-career couples an awkward com-
plication, which they would rather avoid. “I went to 
a number of job interviews,” says geographer, Ruther-
ford Platt, of Gettysburg College, “and some were 
quite unprofessional. I had people pull me aside and 
ask me about my spouse, whether she was in academia 
and looking for a job as well.” But, as more women 
compete for permanent positions in science faculties 
in the USA, higher education institutions are under 
pressure to become more flexible.
© Micheline Pelletier/Gamma
The trailing spouse syndrome
Women scientists, especially physicists, are likely to marry other scientists – which can 
create problems if both partners look for jobs at the same institution.
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 2
Creative solutions
One solution, originally favored by smaller teaching 
universities, like Gettysburg, and slowly catching on 
in major research institutions, is to split a tenured 
position into two, part-time posts. This is particu-
larly attractive to young academics looking for their 
first tenured job. 
“We have a joint appointment now,” says Ruther-
ford Platt. “My wife and I are considered 1.5 people. 
I’ve maintained my full-time position and Monica has 
a part-time, tenure-track position. She’s a permanent 
part of the faculty and has half of the teaching obli-
gations. We have a small child and that works well 
for us. It would have been harder to negotiate two 
full-time positions. This is better for us, at our point 
in our life.” 
Rutherford Platt acknowledges that they were 
fortunate. “We both fit in the same department,” he 
says, “but our expertise is different. We compliment 
each other. If two people are in different depart-
ments, one of the departments may have no incen-
tive to make it work for the other person.” 
Increasingly, says Claire Wyman, the male partner 
may well be the ‘trailing spouse’, and even the big 
research universities in the USA are willing to find a 
solution, especially for more senior positions. “There 
are many more highly talented and desirable female 
scientists now,” she says, “and I see universities 
accommodating them. I don’t think it’s because they 
are enlightened. If you want that person to come, 
you have to accommodate what they want. If what 
they want is a building named after them, then you 
do that. If they want a position for their partner, 
maybe you do that. It can be a matter of market 
forces. And women are more interested in demanding 
an appointment for their partner than a building 
named after them.” ■
Peter Coles in London, United Kingdom
4
© Claire Wyman
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 20
Baroness Greenfield, Professor of 
pharmacology at Oxford University and 
author of a UK report on women in 
science, advocates stronger strategic 
approaches to addressing the issue of 
female under-representation in scientific 
careers.
Question: What is the situation of women in the 
field of science? 
Answer: It has changed a lot over the past ten or 
twenty years, but there is still a lot of work to be 
done. It is easier now for women at the junior level 
than when I was an undergraduate and there were 
relatively few women students. Now, in biomedical 
sciences, almost 50% of the students are women but 
there are still problems in the physical sciences. I 
think that at the junior level it is getting easier for 
women to do this. However, there are still serious 
problems as women progress in their careers. 
The report (SET FAIR, 2002) shows that in the 
physical sciences, you have 90% men and 10% women 
across the board. In biological sciences, however, 
there are about the same number of men and women 
in the beginning of university studies. But around 
the late 20’s, early 30s, women begin to drop out. By 
the stage of Professor, the rate in biological sciences 
is just as bad as for the physical sciences, that is 
90% men and 10% women.
Question: What is the biggest hurdle that women 
science researchers face? 
Answer: In particular, as you can see in my report, 
the big problem is for women in their late 20’s when 
they have to make a choice about whether to have 
children. Do they choose not to have children and 
carry on doing science? This is what I did. Or do they 
choose to have children at the biologically optimal 
age but run the risk that they won’t come back to a 
job at all because they don’t yet have tenure? Or do 
they delay having a child until they are beyond the 
biologically optimal age, in which case they may run 
into fertility issues? None of these choices are really 
ideal for women—it’s a problem that hasn’t been 
solved. How can the scientific community accommo-
date women so that they can have children without 
compromising their careers? How can we allow women 
scientists to have as much choice as they want? 
Question: What can we do to change things? 
Answer: There is no quick fix. Men and childless 
women are not taking time off. If you are taking © Baroness Susan Greenfield 4
“We need the best people 
as scientists”
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 2
time off, it is happening just at the time that you 
have to publish papers to get ahead. One option that 
I have proposed is a funding scheme that give money 
to women who have children. That way women who 
want children could apply for a fellowship that is not 
available to anyone else. This enables women to 
come back and work for two years to reestablish 
themselves in their field. They would be competing 
with other women in the same situation.
Question: Why is the lack of women in science 
important? 
Answer: Because we are entering into an era where 
science and technology are at the centre of society, 
and we need the best people as scientists. Not just 
doing research, but in the media, politics, industry. 
You need the best possible brains and it is crazy to 
eliminate 50% of the talent. And also each individual 
should be able to fulfill herself to the best of her 
potential. If you have great potential as a scientist it 
is a great shame if you are prevented from doing that 
because you are a woman. Also the world can’t afford 
to have all that expensive education and training 
wasted. 
Question: What opportunities are there for young 
women studying science today? 
Answer: What women don’t realize is that science has 
a very exciting range of options. So for example, I 
am in the House of Lords now—and there are about 
10% of us who have some sort of science credentials. 
It is hugely exciting to go into politics or to do law 
or the media as a scientist. It is not just bench sci-
ence because science is so central now. Traditionally 
the worst sectors in terms of female representation 
are biotechnology and academia. ■
Interview by Edna Yahil 
© Micheline Pelletier/Gamma
Margaret Brimble, New Zealand
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 22
Myanmar has the world’s highest 
proportion of women researchers at 85%, 
according to the UNESCO Institute for 
Statistics. But why are research hotspots 
like China and the United States missing 
from the list of 100 countries with 
available data? A careful look behind the 
statistics.
Only about one-quarter of the world’s researchers are 
women, according to estimates by the UNESCO Insti-
tute for Statistics (UIS). This is hardly surprising, 
given the hidden barriers and glass ceilings of so 
many laboratories and lecture halls. 
But eyebrows might rise after a closer look at the 
statistics illustrated in the map below, where research 
magnets – like China, the United Kingdom and the 
United States – slip into the grey zone of ‘no data 
available’. 
Are these countries ignoring women in science? Or 
is the UIS sleeping on the job? Fortunately, the 
answer is no to both questions. But these countries 
are using different techniques to collect the data 
which cannot be compared internationally. 
For example, the UIS and other organizations gen-
erally rely upon headcounts of men and women work-
ing in these fields. But many of the most developed 
countries calculate full-time equivalencies instead. 
“So they’re not actually counting people but shifts,” 
explains Ernesto Fernández Polcuch, who is responsi-
ble for science and technology (S&T) statistics at 
the UIS. 
So strangely enough, the UIS can report that 
Myanmar and Lesotho have the world’s highest pro-
portions of women researchers at 85% and 76% 
respectively, topping the list of about 100 countries 
and territories. But the Institute cannot provide 
these statistics for countries like Australia or the US.
Detailed information, but not 
enough
And yet the US probably collects some of the most 
detailed information on the gender, ethnicity and 
disability status of its scientists. The National Sci-
ence Foundation (NSF) isn’t just counting the number 
of women scientists and engineers but keeping tabs 
on the numbers of patents they receive and even 
their demographic circumstances. 
For example, men on average have 12 subordi-
nates compared to nine for women, among supervisor 
scientists and engineers in the private sector. The 
NSF has also found that family responsibilities are 
cited as the reason for not working by about 27% of 
women with science and engineering doctorates who 
are either unemployed or out of the labor force com-
pared to just 1.5% of men. Women scientists and 
engineers are also more likely than men to be 
divorced and separated. 
No statistics, no problem, 
no policy...
© UNESCO/Niamh Burke
Analysis of water samples for trace elements, Athens, 
Greece
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 2
This gold-mine of information can lay the founda-
tions for national policy-making, even if most of the 
data cannot be compared internationally. But for 
other countries, like those of the European Union, 
comparability is critical in efforts to harmonize sci-
ence policies and put women researchers on the 
political agenda. 
“No statistics, no problem, no policy,” as stated 
by Dr Hilary Rose* of University of Bradford (UK). 
“You just get gestures. Statistics help identify prob-
lems and can monitor the effectiveness of 
remedies.” 
Rose’s comments resonate in countries like Aus-
tria, Germany and The Netherlands, where there are 
low percentages of female scientists and relatively 
little data on them, according to the European Com-
mission’s Helsinki Group on Women in Science. In 
contrast, many of the newer members of the Euro-
pean Union and associated countries benefit from 
the communist legacy of good statistics and high 
proportions of women scientists and researchers.
Finding innovative monitoring 
solutions
Through the Helsinki Group, a network of statisti-
cians is trying to better identify and monitor the 
factors that bring women in and out of the research 
field. They are not simply looking at how many 
women pursue research but how they progress in 
their careers. 
For example, to what extent do women set the 
scientific agenda? Part of the answer lies in the 
Map: © UNESCO Institute for Statistics
Share of women researchers, 2003 (UIS)
4
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 24
 composition of scientific boards. Only in Finland and 
Sweden do women constitute more than 40% of board 
members, followed by the UK and Denmark with more 
than 30%. But in most EU countries, the share varies 
from one in five to even less than one in ten, accord-
ing to the report She Figures 2006. 
Another innovative tool is the Glass Ceiling Index, 
which compares women’s and men’s chances of reach-
ing a top academic position. Basically the higher the 
score, the ‘thicker’ the so-called ceiling to women’s 
advancement. Romania and Turkey report the most 
positive results, with 1.1 and 1.4 respectively, com-
pared to the EU average of 2.1. In contrast, the 
greatest barriers were found in Malta (11.7) followed 
by Lithuania (3.2). 
At the UIS, Fernández Polcuch dreams of collect-
ing this kind of data internationally. While glass ceil-
ings are beyond his reach, he will soon have a new 
source of data arising from a joint project between 
the UIS, Eurostat and the Organisation for Economic 
Co-operation and Development (OECD). 
Inspired by a US survey, the three organizations 
have developed a way to track the careers of doctor-
ate holders internationally. In particular, the UIS 
designed a model questionnaire to help countries 
with little experience in this field conduct their own 
surveys. So for the first time, developing and indus-
trialized countries will be able to compare the sala-
ries of male and female engineers, for example, or 
the time it takes them to find jobs in their field. 
A number of countries have already piloted the 
survey, while others prepare to implement it. The 
results, expected by 2008, should considerably 
expand the global perspective on women in science 
while shrinking those disconcerting grey zones of ‘no 
data available’. ■
Amy Otchet, UNESCO Institute for Statistics (UIS)
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 25
The Courier looks back
The October 1967 issue of The UNESCO Courier carried 
an excerpt of a memorandum on international science 
scholarships presented by Marie Curie to the League 
of Nations in 1926. Twice laureate of the Nobel Prize, 
for chemistry and physics, she made a plea for the 
encouragement of vocations in science.
“At this post-university stage of their lives, young students who contemplate careers in science are brought face 
to face with pressing demands. In most cases the family has done its utmost to help the young man or woman to 
come this far and, unable to make further sacrifices, it now asks them to become self supporting. And even in 
well-to-do families the wish to take up very advanced studies may encounter a lack of understanding, such stud-
ies being considered as an extravagance or a mere whim. 
Yet what in fact are the best interests of society in this matter? Should it not give every encouragement to 
those called to a scientific vocation? Is it really so well-endowed that it can afford to reject the vocations it 
is offered? 
I believe, on the basis of personal experience, that the sum total of the aptitudes called for by a true scien-
tific vocation is an infinitely frail and precious thing, a rare treasure that is both absurd and criminal to throw 
away, a gift to which great care must be devoted so that it may grow and fructify. 
What, in reality, are some of the qualities required of the person who aspires to success in the field of inde-
pendent scientific research? The intellectual qualities are an intelligence capable of learning and understanding, 
a sure judgment capable of appraising the significance of theoretical and experimental demonstrations, an 
imagination capable of creative effort. Equally important are the moral faculties: perseverance, zeal and above 
all the unselfish dedication that guides the novice along a path which, in most cases, will never lead him to 
material rewards comparable to those offered by careers in industry or business. 
Thus to foster and safeguard the scientific vocation is a sacred duty for each society which has the inter-
ests of the future at heart. It is gratifying to see that public opinion is becoming increasingly conscious of 
this duty”. 
Marie Curie
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 26
Ligia Gargallo, a professor at the Catholic 
Pontifical University of Chile, located 
in Santiago, is the winner of the 2007 
L’Oréal-UNESCO prize for Latin America. 
In her opinion, the relative scarcity of 
women in science is the effect of cultural 
bias, which education can and must help 
overcome.
When you come face-to-face with a scientific prob-
lem, do you feel there is a distinctively female 
approach, a sort of sixth sense? 
I believe there is room for all sorts of human beings. 
One single scientific phenomenon can be viewed in 
different ways according to the characteristics, curi-
osity and emotions of the observer. This means that 
the way to enrich science is to draw equal contribu-
tions from both genders. 
Is it possible to speak of a specifically female con-
tribution to science? 
Science has neither frontiers nor gender barriers. It 
is one discipline, and it is completely global. What I 
will say is that the contribution of women is much 
smaller than it should be. I think it’s a fantastic idea 
to spur women to study science and encourage more 
women to become professional scientists. Besides 
everything else, they can give a lot to science, such 
as their female intuition, their sensibility and their 
curiosity.
What are conditions like for women scientists in 
Latin America, and particularly Chile? Are there 
wage differentials or other sorts of differences with 
male researchers? 
Female scientists are in a minority in Latin America, 
as they are in Chile. Inequality of course becomes 
more or less visible according to the specific field 
you are looking at. But the relative lack of women 
in science is in the first place a cultural problem, 
although you must not rule out the possibility that 
some women deliberately choose not to study sci-
ence. In any case, it is clear that we urgently need 
to draw up programmes that will enable us to 
encourage young talented people. We should start 
to work from high school onwards to stimulate a 
love for science. Young women must be convinced 
that they can rise to be outstanding scientists with-
out giving up their entitlement to motherhood, if 
that is what they want. 
As regards wages, there are still differences 
between men and women in industrial science, 
© Micheline Pelletier/Gamma
Ligia Gargallo
“Science has neither frontiers nor 
gender barriers”
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 27
though thankfully they have practically disappeared 
from the academic environment. 
Could you explain for us the main research that you 
are doing at the moment? 
I work in fundamental science, especially in com-
pound systems built out of large molecules, giant 
molecules, macromolecules or polymers. These types 
of systems can be found everywhere, but their behav-
iour is complex and quite different from that of small 
molecules. Natural polymers such as proteins, 
polysaccharides, cellulose and starch form part of 
living beings. And synthetic polymers, for instance 
new and modern materials such as polystyrene, 
polymethacrylates, nylon and polyethylene, are part 
of our daily lives, and have taken the place of older 
substances. We are currently studying the properties 
of these synthetic polymers when they are disturbed 
by mechanical or electrical forces, with the aim of 
understanding why they becomes viscous or elastic, 
for example. We are convinced that the only way to 
use these materials in new technologies to the bene-
fit of mankind is by understanding what is going on 
at the most basic, fundamental level – and that is 
what we are looking for. ■
UNESCO’s Santiago Office (Chile) 
in collaboration with L’Oréal Chile
4
Discoverers - Portraits of Women
by José Banaag
Marie Curie 
(1867-1934)
The first woman to receive the 
Nobel Prize in 1903, for physics, 
she and her French husband dis-
covered natural radioactivity. 
Further research led her to the 
new elements radium and polo-
nium, named after her native 
Poland. For this, she was the sole 
laureate of another Nobel, in 
1911, for chemistry. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
Lise Meitner 
(1878-1968)
She entered the University of 
Vienna only in 1901 because of 
restrictions on women’s enrol-
ment. She concentrated in 
nuclear physics, collaborating for 
30 years with Nobel laureate Otto 
Hahn. Together, they developed 
uranium fission. 
Photo: © American Institute of Physics, Emilio 
Segrè Visual Archives 
Gerty Cori 
(1896-1957)
This Prague-born doctor worked 
as a researcher for free while her 
husband taught pharmacology at 
the same American university. 
Their long professional partner-
ship was crowned with a Nobel 
Prize in 1947 for discovering the 
metabolism of glycogen. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 28
Irène Joliot-Curie 
(1897-1956)
Daughter of Marie Curie, wife of a 
physicist, she and her husband 
discovered artificial radioactive 
elements for which they shared 
the Nobel Prize in 1935. She 
actively campaigned for the 
social and intellectual advance-
ment of women in France. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
Barbara McClintock 
(1902-1992)
Sole recipient of the 1983 Nobel 
Prize in Physiology or Medicine, 
this American geneticist observed 
coloration patterns of maize ker-
nels. She found that genes are 
mobile, that they can move 
around chromosomes. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
Maria Goeppert-
Mayer (1906-1972)
For love of physics, this unem-
ployed wife of a university pro-
fessor continued her research 
through the American Depres-
sion. She and two other physi-
cists made important discoveries 
on the nuclear shell structure, 
receiving the Nobel Prize in 
1963. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
Grace Murray Hopper 
(1906-1992)
She was the first to use the term 
“bug” when she opened her mal-
functioning computer and found 
a moth inside. This mathemati-
cian and rear admiral of the 
United States Navy is one of the 
developers of UNIVAC, the first 
commercial computer, in the late 
1940s. 
Photo: Courtesy of UPI/Cortis-Bettman 
Rita Levi-Montalcini 
(1909-)
In 1936, Mussolini passed laws 
discriminating against non-Aryan 
Italians. This doctor built a secret 
laboratory in her bedroom, the 
first of several wartime hideouts. 
She shared the Nobel Prize with a 
colleague in 1986 for discovering 
growth factors essential in the 
treatment of severe burns. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
Dorothy Crowfoot 
Hodgkin (1910-1994)
She devoted most of her life 
teaching chemistry in women’s 
colleges in the United Kingdom. 
Her research led her to crack the 
structures of biochemical sub-
stances, notably penicillin, vita-
min B12 and insulin. She was 
awarded an unshared Nobel Prize 
in Chemistry in 1964. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 2
Gertrude Elion 
(1918-1999)
When her father went bankrupt 
during the American Depression, 
she got a scholarship. When labo-
ratories offered few jobs for 
women, she found an assistant-
ship without pay. She discovered 
acyclovir, an antiviral treatment 
against herpes and chicken pox, 
receiving the Nobel Prize in 
1988. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
Rosalind Franklin 
(1920-1958)
Because her father frowned on 
higher education for women, an 
aunt offered to pay her dues at 
Cambridge University. This scien-
tist’s study of living cells led to 
crucial keys in the molecular 
structure of DNA. She also made 
important findings in virology. 
Photo : Courtesy of the Cold Spring Harbor 
Laboratory Archives 
Rosalyn Yalow 
(1921-)
Graduate schools were reluctant 
to grant fellowships to women, 
so she worked as a secretary at 
Columbia University. Her later 
career in physics culminated in 
the invention of a technique to 
measure the amount of insulin for 
which she received the 1977 
Nobel Prize. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
Christiane Nüsslein-
Volhard (1942-)
Some 40,000 fruit fly families 
provided the keys to her ground-
breaking study of early embryonic 
development, useful for scien-
tists to better understand human 
development. The Nobel Founda-
tion awarded the 1995 prize to 
this German geneticist and two 
others. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
Jocelyn Bell 
(1943-)
While at Cambridge Observatory 
in 1967, she and fellow astrono-
mer Anthony Hewish discovered 
pulsars - quickly rotating, 
strongly magnetised neutron 
stars which regularly emit radio 
signals. Today there are 700 
known pulsars. 
Photo: © 1998 WGBH 
Linda B. Buck 
(1947-)
She and fellow American Richard 
Axel received the 2004 Nobel 
Prize for giving a deeper under-
standing of our sense of smell. 
They catalogued odorant recep-
tors, describing the vast family 
of 1,000 genes which enable us 
to recognize some 10,000 differ-
ent smells. 
Photo: © The Nobel Foundation, Stockholm 
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 220
The UNESCO Courier is published by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization. 
7, place de Fontenoy – 75352 Paris 07 SP, France 
general inquiries by e-mail: courier.unesco@unesco.org 
 Director: Saturnino Muñoz Gómez editor in chief: Enzo Fazzino
 French editor: Agnès Bardon english editors: Stephen Roberts, Edna Yahil
 Spanish editor: Lucía Iglesias Kuntz Arabic editor: Bassam Mansour
 Russian editors: Vladimir Sergueev, Katerina Markelova chinese editor: Weiny Cauhape
 editorial Assistant: José Banaag Photo editor: Fiona Ryan
 Web Platform: Fabienne Kouadio, Chakir Piro Layout: Gérard Prosper
Articles and photos credited UNESCO may be reproduced and/or translated providing the credit line reads “Reproduced from the UNESCO Courier”, 
and include date and hyperlink. Photos without UNESCO credit request specific authorization. 
Articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO. 
Boundaries on maps do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
ISSN 1993-8616 
]]>
</page>
</document>
