<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="158378eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
This document may be accessed online: www.unesco.org/courier
“The first instrument of a people’s genius is its language,” said the French writer Stendhal. 
Literacy, learning, social integration… Everything transits through language, which 
embodies national, cultural and sometimes religious identity for each person. It constitutes 
one of the fundamental dimensions of a human being. Yet specialists estimate that within 
only a few generations, more than half of the 7,000 languages spoken in the world face 
extinction, because they are not represented in government, education and the media. For 
this reason, the United Nations had declared 2008 the International Year of Languages, 
to be launched by UNESCO on 21 February, International Mother Language Day. Produced 
with the support of UNESCO’s Intersectoral Group for Languages and Multilingualism, this 
year’s first issue of the Courier is devoted to languages.
LaNguages matter
© Flickr/Liz Henry
Multilingual mural.
A crucial concern for the writers Boubacar Boris Diop 
and Jean Portante who “migrate” -happily but also 
painfully - from one language to another. language is 
also a “visa” for immigrants who have to adapt to a 
new society for French-Serbian psycholinguist Ranka 
Bijelac-Babic. Her thoughts are completed by Afghan 
novelist Spôjmaï Zariab: “A brutal separation from 
one’s linguistic and cultural context evokes in my 
mind the image of a tree cut down one fine day to be 
planted in different earth.” 
Safeguarding knowledge and know-how is also 
intrinsically linked to local and indigenous languages. 
Examples include the Machaj Juyai, “secret language” 
of the Kallawaya, Bolivian herbalists, whose story is 
told by Carmen Beatriz Loza, researcher at the Boliv-
ian institute of traditional medicine in La Paz, or the 4
2008 - number 1 • ISSN 1993-8616
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
2 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
language of the Ainu people in Japan, described in 
the process of dying out by Kaori Tahara, historian of 
Ainu origin. 
Some languages are disappearing while others 
are emerging. Often they are ancient but only now 
beginning to show up in public life, like the ones in 
the former Soviet Union, for instance. Our colleague 
Katia Markelova has decided to tell you about 
Kirghiz. 
Finally, education is a crucial factor for safeguard-
ing or developing a language: the Indian linguist 
Appasamy Murugaiyan examines the relationship 
between language and school, which is unusually 
complex in India, a country that is home to 1,650 lan-
guages and over a million educational institutions. 
This year, the UNESCO Courier celebrates its 60th 
anniversary and offers its readers something new 
with “ Focus”, announcing in this issue the Interna-
tional Year of Planet Earth (to be launched at UNESCO 
on 12 February) and “Landmarks” where you will find 
portraits of personalities who have had significant 
impact on the history of literature, science and art 
around the world. 
More big news, for the International Year of Lan-
guages: Portuguese is being added to the Courier’s six 
linguistic editions, and will soon be available on line. 
Last but not least, your magazine is becoming 
interactive! Starting with this issue, you can express 
your opinions and have them published on line. Share 
your thoughts!
Jasmina Šopova
Contents
Languages and 
immigration: 
bilingualism is 
an asset 8
Strange language. 
Let’s say it’s a 
whale… 5
Preaching in 
the wilderness 
or banking on 
the future? 3
The secrets 
of Machaj Juyai-
Kallawaya 12
The saga of 
the Ainu language 14
Kyrgyz: 
an “emerging” 
language 16
Landmarks: 
The “Doctor 
Prince” 23
The Indian 
dilemma 19
Focus: 
Hubert Reeves 21
The Courier looks 
back 25
Next month: 
“Women between 
two shores” 25 Partners 24
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
You wrote a dozen books in French before choosing 
Wolof, your mother language. Why this reversion? 
Actually, my language was always there, inside me. 
The only problem I faced was the ability to write in 
my language. I was “corrupted” by French. I spoke 
everyday Wolof, but I didn’t possess it intimately. 
© UNESCO/Gargi Shinde
Boubacar Boris Diop.
Then there was Rwanda. A group of writers I 
belonged to went there after the genocide, in 1998, 
as part of the operation “Rwanda: writing as a duty 
to memory”. I said to myself that if we’d let 10,000 
Rwandans get killed per day for three months, if 
nobody had done anything, this conveyed a certain 
contempt for Africa… 
At that moment I felt even more strongly the 
desire to write in my mother language. It became 
essential. Oh, at first it was painful…I was very 
afraid of writing a French novel in Wolof. I had to 
fight against myself, but the Diops are stubborn! 
Then I began to hear voices – voices that came up 
out of the past. And writing became very easy. I 
am certain that my first novel in Wolof, Doomi golo 
(the she-monkey’s young), is my best piece of 
writing. 
Is writing in Wolof therefore also a political act? 
Absolutely. Coming back to the title of my novel The 
she-monkey’s young: what’s a monkey? It’s an imita-
tion of the other. The passage that best sums up the 
book is the one in which you see a huge mirror in the 
middle of nowhere. Two gorillas find themselves in 
front of the mirror and they see their own images. 
They start fighting their reflections and as a result 
of hitting the mirror, they hurt themselves and die. 
What we call hatred of the other is in fact self-hatred. 
You have to be able to tolerate your image in the 
mirror, assume your identity. 
At the moment I’m translating this novel into 
French. It will be published in France in September 
2008.
Preaching in the wilderness or banking 
on the future?
After prolific production in French, the Senegalese novelist Boubacar Boris Diop decided 
to write in Wolof. For a poor, multilingual population with an oral tradition, books are 
not a priority. Yet African writers who express themselves in their national languages are 
becoming more and more numerous.
Interview by Jasmina Šopova 
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Why didn’t you decide to publish it in French in 
Senegal?
Because now there are only publishers in national 
languages. That’s good news, anyway… even if their 
tongues are hanging out! They work with enthusi-
asm, but with immeasurable difficulties too: no way 
to make a profit, no distribution… True, the state 
occasionally steps in. The “Direction du Livre et de la 
Lecture” (book and reading administration) funded, 
for instance, a second edition of my book Doomi Golo 
after the first run of 3000 copies was sold out. 
Besides my publisher Papyrus, there’s the « Organ-
isation Sénégalaise d’Appui au Développement » 
(OSAD) that does remarkable work. And also ARED 
publishers, but they’re specialized in research and in 
education for development. 
How many readers can you have in Wolof? 
If I’d asked myself that question, I would never have 
started writing! It’s true that where I come from, 
many people don’t know how to read and don’t buy 
books. And they have other priorities: their children’s 
health, feeding their families… There’s also another 
phenomenon: rich people who live in poor societies 
generally prefer buying a fancy car, because you can’t 
show off a book…
We have to accept this situation and bet on the 
long term. It will take a while for books written today 
in the African languages to prevail, but they’ll even-
tually find acceptance. Thirty years ago, literature in 
national languages didn’t exist, except for a few iso-
lated cases. Today the situation is the opposite: hun-
dreds of books have been published in Wolof and 
Pulaar, definitely more than in French. 
There are two writers’ organizations in Senegal, 
one composed of writers in French, the other of writ-
ers in national languages. The latter are far more 
numerous, but they have no visibility, because we 
live in a society where French is the language of 
prestige. 
Do you count on diaspora readership? 
A great deal. But although the younger generations 
of the diaspora speak their mother languages, they 
don’t know how to read or write them. This is why I 
had the idea of organizing a Wolof workshop with 
young people whose background is Senegalese immi-
gration in France. At first the parents didn’t neces-
sarily see any benefit in their children learning their 
mother language, but there was great demand from 
the young people. We’re starting in Bordeaux on 25 
February. It’s an idea that seems odd initially, but if 
it works I’ll be very proud of it.
Often when one travels from one African capital to 
another, one has to stop off in a European capital. 
Does this also happen in the world of African 
literature?
It would be fantastic if I could translate the Kenyan 
writer Ngugi wa Thiongo directly form Kikuyu into 
Wolof, without going through English and French… 
To my knowledge there’s almost no translation from 
one African language into another. My novel Doomi 
© UNESCO/Papyrus
Cover of Doomi Golo, book by B.B. Diop in Wolof, at Papyrus.
4
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Golo is translated into Pulaar now. But who will trans-
late it into Swahili? Do we have to wait two or three 
centuries? Not necessarily, but that’s what I fear, 
alas. 
You know, Africa was divided up by the colonial 
powers in Berlin in 1885. Africans speak to each 
other through the colonial languages. And me, 
making fun of it, referring to the Berlin Wall of the 
Cold War, I call it our “Berlin Wall”. It is invisible but 
terrible – it separates the English- French- and Por-
tuguese-speaking countries in Sub-Saharan Africa. 
With Moussa Konaté, Malian writer who heads 
the French-speaking festival “Etonnants voyageurs” 
(Amazing Travelers) in Mali, I’ve often discussed 
the idea of organizing a big meeting of African 
writers who write in national languages. A way of 
at least making cracks in this wall. But it’s easier 
to find sponsors for French-language writers than 
for those who write in national languages. UNESCO 
could be the perfect venue for such a pan-African 
encounter, particularly this year, international year 
of languages. And it’s an international space. With-
out walls.
4
strange language. 
Let’s say it’s a whale….
Born in Luxembourg into an Italian-
speaking family, having spoken 
Luxembourgeois in the street, studied 
in French, German and English, 
improved his Spanish in Cuba, poet-
novelist Jean Portante tells us here 
about his “strange language”, a medley 
of foreign languages jostling each other 
inside his head. 4
© UNESCO/Éditions Empiria
Italian translation of Mrs Haroy or the Memory of the 
Whale by Jean Portante.
© UNESCO/Collection Présence Africaine
In 2006, UNESCO took part in the 50th Anniversary of the 1st 
International Congress of Black Writers and Artists. Group 
photo of the participants in 1956.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Languages, in my head, are nebulae intermingling 
and giving birth to the “strange language”. When-
ever, for instance, I say or write the word “bougie” 
(French for candle), like a very close echo the Italian 
“buggia”, its enemy brother, appears. And while the 
French evokes illumination – light no matter how 
feeble or fragile its shine – and also to some degree 
truth, in Italian “buggia” means, with no ambiguity, 
“lie”, absence of light. When I say or write the word 
“bougie”, there breathes within it, colliding with the 
light, the lie that brings darkness. 
The whale works like that. Invisible at first glance, 
the lung of terrestrial memory has worked its way 
into what is apparently the body of a fish. Similarly, 
within itself my “bougie” conceals that which erases 
it. Or “shaperases” it. Shapes it as it erases it. 
Because while my “bougie” is no longer clarity, nor is 
it yet concealment. It’s the path leading from one to 
the other. Just like the whale, an animal neither ter-
restrial nor aquatic, is the voyage setting out from 
the mammal trying to reach the fish. 
All this had little impact when as an adolescent 
and then a young man I was passing my exams, flirt-
ing or doing my job as professor (of French, already). 
The new country, Luxembourg, had made me the gift 
of three languages. I used them according to circum-
stances. True providence! To read Goethe, Rilke, Musil 
and Celan in German, Voltaire, Baudelaire, Rimbaud 
and Proust in French, is a blessing. I am indebted to 
the country chosen by my family. 
Things started going wrong when I turned (belat-
edly) to writing. Suddenly trilingualism was no longer 
of any use to me. Suddenly it was time to choose. 
You can’t write a book in several languages at once. 
And yet… 
Suddenly too I realized that despite the linguistic 
plurality that was mine, none of the tools I had 
forged for myself allowed me to really work. The 
inside language was missing, the one that came from 
farther away and being of course on my lips, had 
made me discover Dante, Leopardi and Pavese, but 
was too dead to be able to enter my books. 
Therefore I undertook that other voyage, the long 
conquest of the written word, by setting my sights 
on a cousin of that language, French. And at the 
beginning, to be honest, I felt at ease. Like a fish in 
water, far from the whale. The inside animal said, 
that’s it, the conquest is finished, you’ve arrived in 
your new home. Alive.
A not insignificant anecdote
Anecdote. It takes place where long ago the journey 
began, in Italy. In the spring of 1995, my book Ouvert 
fermé (Open closed) had just been translated in Ital-
ian and the philology college in L’Aquila, in the 
Abruzzi, invited me to come and present it. There we 
were, my translator and I, in the aula magna of the 
university, sacrificing to the ritual of a bilingual 
reading, as is fitting. The translator, Maria Luisa Cal-
dognetto, first read the Italian version and I then 
continued in French, to allow the melody of the orig-
inal to be heard. Nothing but well-rehearsed time-
proven routine. Yet at a certain point, an inexplicable 
stir started up within the audience. The buzz of a 
bouquet of murmurs began to accompany the read-
ing, like a disagreeable echo, every time it was my 
turn. Feeling it would break my concentration, I 
raised my eyes to identify the source. And a student 
sitting in the front row took that opportunity to 
interrupt us. 
Signor Portante (he pronounced it Portante in 
the Italian way, accentuating the second sylla-
ble), lei è italiano, no? (You’re Italian, aren’t 
you?) 
I shook my head no, then corrected myself and 
nodded yes. 
Ma allora, perché non legge lei in italiano? (Then 
why don’t you yourself read in Italian.) 
The thought had not crossed our minds, the trans-
lator and I, when we started the presentation. For us 
it was normal for the author to read the original and 
the translator the translation. The student’s com-
ment troubled me. I looked questioningly at my 
translator, who answered with her own look that she 
didn’t mind switching roles. So we did. I took hers, 
and Italian verses started coming out of my mouth. 
The audience was won over. They were touched that 
one of their own, an expatriate, had returned to the 
homeland to read to them, in their language, verses 
written elsewhere.
4
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
The moment everything switched
Inside me, however, it happened very differently. The 
animal inside began protesting. I felt something 
unprecedented was taking place. I was moved, and 
couldn’t hold back tears. And then a great sadness 
crept in, and it would not go away. 
What had transpired? As I went along in my read-
ing, I discovered with astonishment that what I was 
in the process of reading wasn’t the translation of my 
text. That in fact, just before, when French words, 
therefore the original, were coming out of my mouth, 
this translation had done its work. That the transla-
tion was the genuine original version of my poems, 
and not the text I had written before and which in 
her mouth sounded suddenly like a translation. Eve-
rything had switched. 
Thanks to the interjection of that discerning stu-
dent, to whom I owe this revelation, I had just real-
ized that everything I believed up until then about 
my writing was false. That I was lying when I said I 
wrote in French. That what was claimed about me 
wasn’t true, namely that I was a Luxembourg writer 
of French expression, according to the accepted for-
mula. That like the whale, my writing, which appeared 
to be French, concealed within itself the lung of 
another language. That my writing took a French 
form, but had another breath, of which the text’s 
material nature was nothing more than a more or less 
effective translation. That I wrote in “strange 
language”.
Jean Portante, 
Italian and Luxembourgeois writer
© UNESCO/Stella Portante
Jean Portante during a recent lecture in San Demetrio 
(Italy).
“Who am I? This is a question that others 
ask,
but has no answer.
I am my language,
I am an ode, two odes, ten.
This is my language.
I am my language.
I am words’ writ: 
Be! Be my body! 
And I become an embodiment of their 
timbre,
I am what I have spoken to the words: 
Be the place where my body joins the 
eternity of the desert.
Be, so that I may become my words”.
mahmoud Darwich (Palestinian poet), “A 
Rhyme for the Odes,” 91, Unfortunately, It 
Was Paradise, Regents of the University of 
California, 2003.
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
A large number of “developed” states have official 
languages, but their populations of various ethnic 
origins speak a number of other languages every day. 
“It has been estimated that in the year 2000 more 
than one third of the population under the age of 35 
in urbanized Western Europe had an immigrant minor-
ity background”, said a UNESCO document about lan-
guage diversity (see link), which notes that that “the 
biggest immigrant groups in the European Union are 
Turkish and North African and live in France, Germany 
and Britain”. 
Politicians in western countries are today drafting 
laws to tighten  immigration conditions and are 
introducing language and culture tests. To ask appli-
cants for immigration to know the rudiments of 
French, Dutch or English, as well as the basic rules of 
how the host countries work, does not seem absurd. 
But when they arrive, there is often an attempt to 
“erase” their mother tongues from their heads, espe-
cially if these are considered as “minor” languages. 
We only need to remember the October 2004 report 
about internal security in France (see link to Report 
about the prevention of delinquency). “[For children 
from 1 to 3 years old], only parents, and especially 
mothers, have contact with their children. If the 
children are of foreign origin, the parents should 
force themselves to speak French at home, in order to 
get the children used to having only this language to 
express themselves in” says the report, noting: “But 
if, in certain cases, they feel the reluctance of their 
fathers, who often insist on the use of the dialect of 
their countries of origin at home, they will be dis-
suaded from doing so. It will then be necessary to 
take action to encourage fathers to go in the right 
direction”. 
Languages and immigration: bilingualism 
is an asset
To deprive immigrant children of their mother tongues is to create situations of conflict 
between the family model and the social model, which is to scorn their identities. If 
their languages and cultures were respected by school systems, they would develop a 
better esteem of themselves and of others.
“Like a sleepwalker, along the paths taken 
by smugglers, I was passing from my 
childhood language to the language of my 
chosen country.”
Hector Bianciotti, French writer of Argen-
tinian origin
© UNESCO/Fyona Ryan
Welcome to the Island of Gorée, Senegal.
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
In the original French passage the word ‘français’ 
(French), designating a language, was written in cap-
itals, which is contrary to the rules of French spell-
ing. It may be supposed that ‘speaking a dialect’ is 
understood as speaking Arabic, Chinese, Serbian, 
etc. 
According to this report, the cognitive, educa-
tional and social development of children that are 
not forced to speak French at home would be com-
promised, as they would inevitably have language 
disorders, leading to behavioural disorders, later 
resulting in delinquency!
The mother tongues of 
immigrants under accusation
This absurd position reflects a flagrant ignorance of 
language development and of the role of the mother 
tongue in the psychic, cognitive and cultural con-
struction of an individual. How for a moment could 
one imagine that a mother might speak a language 
that she did not master well to her child? How could 
one be ignorant of the fact that the mother tongue 
conveys affects, that it enables the organization of 
cognitive faculties, that it symbolizes – for children 
of immigrant background – the continuity between 
the country of origin and the family. 
To deprive the child of the mother tongue at home 
is to create a situation of conflict between the family 
model and the social model and between family and 
school, with the further risk of impoverishing cul-
tural references and weakening socialization. 
This also implies that bilingualism is not consid-
ered as an asset but as a handicap, as an obstacle to 
successful education and integration, above all when 
the languages concerned, such as Arabic, Chinese or 
Russian, are, ridiculously, called ‘rare’. When the lan-
guages concerned, such as English or German, are 
‘socially valorized’ languages, bilingualism becomes a 
symbol of the elite! 
The arguments and proposals for the use (or rather 
non-use) of the mother tongue in the 2004 Report 
about the prevention of delinquency have many sup-
porters in political and academic circles in France, 
but the report gave rise to violent reactions: associa-
tions, NGOs, trade unions and intellectuals were 
mobilized, and the wording of the report was modi-
fied. In the 2005 version, the following can be found: 
‘Recognition of early bilingualism as a factor of inte-
gration. After many debates, the commission has 
considerably changed its position on the subject. It 
also seems that maintaining both the mother tongue 
and the dominant language enables children to have 
better results at school (...).’
Conflict or dialogue of languages?
The last twenty years of research into psycholinguis-
tics and sociolinguistics has unequivocally shown 
that the acquisition and learning of several languages 
by children, no matter what their socio-cultural back-
ground may be and no matter which languages may 
be concerned, does not hinder the cognitive and edu-
cational development of these children in the slight-
est. On the contrary, bilingual children show a greater 
speed and flexibility in certain learning situations, 
and develop better communication skills. If they are 
slightly deficient in the second language, this is 
often temporary, and they compensate for this by a 
richer mental system, cognitive skills that are often 
more efficient and a richer vision of the world. 
When educational difficulties affect children of 
immigrants, most teachers in France place the blame 
mainly on the conflict of languages and cultures. How-
ever, if the languages and cultures of immigrants were 4
4
© UNESCO/Niamh Burke
Mother and child in Ireland.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
0 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
emphasized more, taught to all pupils in schools and 
respected by the school system and by the dominant 
society, individuals would develop a better esteem 
and respect of themselves and therefore of others. 
François Cheng, a Chinese author, who arrived in 
Paris at the age of 20 without knowing a word of 
French, and who has been a member of the Académie 
Française since 2003, wrote in his book Le Dialogue 
(2002): “fate made that from a certain time in my 
life, I became the bearer of two languages, Chinese 
and French. Was it only because of fate? Unless, all 
the same, there was a part of deliberate free will in 
it? The fact remains that I tried to take up the chal-
lenge, by coming to terms with the two languages in 
my own way, with the most extreme consequences. 
[…] It is not surprising that since then, in the heart 
of my linguistic adventure, which is directed towards 
the love for an adopted language, one theme has had 
pride of place: dialogue…” 
Dialogue between communities, dialogue between 
languages - linguists know and emphasize the fact 
that immigrants contribute to the dynamism and 
enrichment of languages such as English or French. 
As an example, the mixing of Chinese, Korean, Japa-
nese and Vietnamese with English is a worldwide 
phenomenon, which immigrants of various Asian ori-
gins use to communicate with each other, therefore 
making their own linguistic contributions. It is the 
same for “Spanglish”, a hybrid language that mixes 
English and Spanish, which is very popular with young 
people in United States, and is one of the most strik-
ing examples of changes in a language faced with 
immigration and globalization.
Ranka Bijeljac-Babić, Franco-Serb psycholinguist, 
Université de Poitiers et Paris 5 - CNRS.
4
4
© Chinese Embassy in France
Ceremony conferring François Cheng of the Académie 
française (right) the title of Professor honoris causa of the 
Tongji University, China.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Babylon reconquered
a brutal separation from one’s linguistic 
and cultural context evokes in my mind 
the image of a tree cut down one fine 
day to be planted in different earth. 
the tree that until that day had run its 
roots in its own soil and stood firm and 
solid on its roots found itself suddenly 
uprooted, and made an effort to put 
down its roots again in other soil and to 
remain standing.
the image of this tree in its earth and in 
this different earth inflames my heart and 
I think of the tree’s distress and solitude, 
and I know very well those who at some 
point in their lives were forced to leave 
their linguistic and cultural territory, to 
establish themselves in another linguistic 
and cultural territory, know very well this 
distress and solitude. they fully conceive 
the wrath of god and they live the story 
of Babylon and its tower. the story of 
those people who wanted to be god and 
devoted themselves to building a tower. 
From day to day the tower took shape and 
gained in height, it approached the sky and these people became god… so god became 
angry and took away the unity of their language. No one could understand the other’s 
language. the tower remained unfinished and the desire to become god even more so. 
every language became a wall and people found themselves alone and powerless. Behind 
the wall, they isolated themselves and the desire to become god left them. 
Possibly it was these same cries of solitude, this absence of anyone to speak to intelligibly, 
that took form and gave birth to poetry and literature… and each language became a 
treasure of unconfined unlimited riches. 
While god took linguistic unity away from humans, they on the other hand created the 
diversity of translation. every translation opens a door in the wall, a door that gives onto 
another language, another culture, another existence and another wealth, so that every 
reader of another language may go through these doors, forget Babylon and divine wrath; 
so that another language may become their language, another culture their culture, 
another existence their existence and another wealth their wealth.
Spôjmaï Zariab, Afghan novelist
© UNESCO/Fiona Ryan
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
2 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
The Kallawaya, itinerant herbalist healers from 
Bautista Saavedra province in the state of La Paz, 
have developed down through the centuries a “family 
language” in their kinship groups (ayllu), within 
which they have transmitted their holistic medicinal 
know-how from generation to generation. They 
named it Machaj Juyai, the “folk language”, still 
spoken today by the eight ayllus of the Kallawaya in 
a province where the language of social relations and 
daily life is Quechua. 
Already colonial administrators were curious about 
this language and writers of Hispanic and mixed 
origin testified to its “rareness”. As early as the 17th 
century, information circulated regarding the exist-
ence of a specialized language of herbalist healers 
who spent their time concocting remedies for Inca 
kings and their entourage.
The Kallawaya and the Eiffel 
Tower
Scientists in the 19th century, however, would not 
recognize the Kallawaya as having their own lan-
guage, and questioned them on their knowledge of 
herbal medicines in the dominant language of the 
high plateaus, Aymara. The Kallawaya speak it, in 
order to communicate with a larger number of 
patients and to enlarge their sphere of activity. 
With the aim of publishing a list of medicinal 
plants with industrial properties and present it at 
the 1889 Universal Exposition, the one for which the 
Eiffel Tower was built, Bolivian scientists and civil 
servants asked the Kallawaya to describe in Aymara 
the properties of more than 100 plants brought to 
France for this great “celebration of civilization”. 
This was the moment the idea spread that the Kalla-
waya were Aymara. 
Another half-century had to elapse before the 
Kallawaya were accepted as a specific group with its 
own language and forms of expression. The Machaj 
Juyai-Kallawaya language was 
heard by scientists in cer-
emonial and healing con-
texts, and it was also 
proven that it was used 
to a great extent as a 
language of communica-
tion within the group. 
There was thus, mid-
20th century, renewed 
interest in the Kallawaya’s 
language as an expres-
sion of their know-how. 
According to some, 
Machaj Juyai-Kallawaya 
was the secret language 
of the Inca kings and 
those closest to them. 
Other experts attempted in vain to find parallels 
between Machaj Juyai and the ancient Puquina lan-
guage, or the Uru from the Andean high plateaus. 
Others imagined a possible link to languages of the 
the secrets of machaj Juyai-Kallawaya
Developed down through the centuries, Machaj Juyai is a “secret language” still spoken 
by a few families of traditional herbalist healers, the Kallawaya, who live in the Bolivian 
Andes. They propagate a now-threatened ancestral knowledge, which UNESCO is working 
to safeguard.
© Ministerio de Cultura, Bolivia
Kallawaya ritual.
© Flickr
The Kallawaya’s 
cosmovision was 
proclaimed a masterpiece 
of the oral and intangible 
cultural heritage of 
humanity by UNESCO in 
2003.
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Amazonian forest, where the Kallawaya traveled to 
seek out the herbal, animal and mineral resources 
they used to prevent and cure illness. The Kalawaya’s 
role as intermediaries between the Incas and the 
Amazonian populations may have influenced their 
language.
Chronicle of a death foretold
Obviously the Kallawaya’s language was subjected to 
the influence of Quechua, which was the instrument 
of their forced conversion to Catholicism. The Kalla-
waya elite were persecuted in the 
17th century in the battle led by 
the Catholic Church known as 
“extirpation of idolatry”. Children 
were separated from grown-ups, to 
be brought up by Spanish people 
or Quechua Catholic priests. Que-
chua exerted further influence on 
the Kallawaya in the 19th century, 
when the latter emigrated mas-
sively to Peru, where they found 
numerous clients and even became 
in the early 20th century the offi-
cial doctors of President Augusto 
Bernardino Leguía. On their own 
territory too, the Kallwaya felt the 
demographic pressure of neighbor-
ing ayllus, who spoke Quechua. 
This is why today Machaj Juyai-
Kallawaya has absorbed nearly all 
the phonology and grammar of 
Quechua. 
More recently, Machaj Juyai-Kallawaya’s vitality was 
sorely tested during two historical events. The first 
was the Chaco War (1932-1935) between Bolivia and 
Paraguay. The Kallawaya were mobilized as aides to 
the doctors responsible for giving care to the enor-
mous contingent of indigenous Bolivians, comprised 
of Aymara and Quechuas. Kallawaya lost their lives in 
great number, which would have serious repercussions 
on subsequent demographic development. 
The second event was the 1952 revolution led by 
the National Revolutionary Movement (NRM), which 
led to structural social change: the right to vote was 
extended universally, the biggest national mining 
companies were nationalized and agricultural lands 
were redistributed. The Kallawaya’s traditional 
nomadic way of life gave way to settlement in cities, 
where they became herbalists or jewelers. 
The idea of sending young Kallawaya to medical 
school, sparing them criminal prosecution for prac-
ticing indigenous medicine outlawed by Bolivian law, 
came out of this urban environment. This has created 
space for the struggle to decrimi-
nalize indigenous medicine in 
Bolivia. The Kallawaya are becom-
ing professionals within the 
framework of Western university 
knowledge, but they are doing so 
at the cost of a crucial cultural 
dimension: the Machaj Juyai-Kall-
awaya language. These days a 
large majority of Kallawaya is tri-
lingual – Castilian, Aymara and 
Quechua – but few of them are 
fluent in their original language. 
During the 2001 census con-
ducted by the Bolivian state, the 
existence of the Kallawaya ethnic 
group and its language was not 
recognized. Nor is UNESCO’s proc-
lamation of the Cosmovision of 
the Kallawaya as a masterpiece of 
the oral and intangible cultural heritage of humanity 
legally recognized. At present, the Kallawaya are 
taking steps in order to obtain legal recognition from 
the Bolivian Parliament for themselves and their lan-
guage. The new Constitution (currently in the making) 
could prove them right.
By Carmen Beatriz Loza, researcher at the Bolivian 
institute of traditional Kallawaya medicine 
(El Alto, La Paz, Bolivia)
© Flickr/Alex Shtrahman
Witch market where the Kallawaya get their 
supplies. (La Paz, Bolivia).
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
A true linguistic enigma, Ainu (Ainu Itak) can’t be 
linked with certainty to any family of languages. Yet, 
as numerous specialists agree that the Ainu people 
are descendants of populations from the Jômon era 
(11,000 to 6,000 B.C.) that inhabited the Japanese 
archipelago, it is very probable their language finds 
its origins in Neolithic languages. 
According to historical sources, the Ainu people 
first settled the northern part of the Japanese archi-
pelago. The inhabitants of the Tohoku region (in the 
north of Honshu, the largest Japanese island) gradu-
ally had to abandon their language and culture start-
ing in the 14th century, due to pressure from the 
central government. But further north, in Hokkaido, 
as well as in the southern part of Sakhalin Island 
(the north belonging to Russia) and in the more iso-
lated Kuril Islands, they were able to preserve them 
until the islands were annexed by the new Meiji gov-
ernment in 1869. 
Not long after, following the signing of the 1875 
“Treaty for the Exchange of Sakhalin for the Kuril 
Islands” between Japan and Russia, most of the Ainu 
from southern Sakhalin were displaced to Hokkaido. 
Epidemics decimated the population. The same fate 
befell the Kuril Islands Ainu, who died out entirely 
after being forcibly regrouped, for national security 
reasons, on an island off the coast of Hokkaido. Jap-
anese authorities feared that these Ainu, some of 
them converts to Orthodox Christianity, would serve 
as spies for the Russians established in the Kurils. 
At the end of the Russian-Japanese war, as of 
1906, a good number of the Ainu from Sakhalin 
returned, because Japan controlled the south of the 
island. But on Stalin’s orders all were expelled in 
1945 and they settled in Hokkaido. Sakhalin’s tradi-
tion and dialect disappeared as the expatriates died 
– generally, they hadn’t transmitted their knowledge 
to the next generation. 
Beginning in 1868, the Japanese government 
imposed a new way of life on the Hokkaido Ainu. A 
series of prohibitions concerning hunting and fish-
ing, for instance, traditional Ainu resources, pro-
foundly undermined their culture. The community 
was stigmatized, considered savage and inferior. 
the saga of the ainu language
Several thousand years old, the Ainu language spoken in northern Japan was dying out 
due to political pressure from the central government. At the end of the 20th century, 
this trend was reversed. While Ainu’s future is still not guaranteed because it isn’t 
taught in schools, the resurgence of interest is undeniable.
© DR
In the past, the Ainu occupied the northen part of 
the Japanese archipelago.
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Officially, the new Hokkaido authorities never 
intended to eradicate the Ainu language. But they 
did everything to that end, notably by building 
schools specifically for the “natives” in which they 
were taught Japanese. In order to survive in this new 
Hokkaido society, irrigated by continual waves of 
Japanese immigrants, the Ainu gradually gave up 
their customs and their language. Today, for new 
generations, Ainu is a second language, if they even 
speak it.
The last Ainu is not dead
The exact number of Ainu speakers is unknown. Only 
surveys conducted every seven years since 1972 by 
the Hokkaido government, concerning living condi-
tions among uteri (compatriot, in Ainu) people, allow 
an approximate assessment of the Ainu language sit-
uation. The 2006 poll shows that out of 23,782 Ainu, 
304 know the language, and among these 4.6% feel 
they master it to the point of being able to teach it. 
But we mustn’t forget these answers are subjective 
and don’t necessarily correspond to reality. Further-
more, much of the population doesn’t participate in 
polls and hides its identity. 
This said, assertions that the Ainu language is 
becoming extinct must be understood in relative 
terms. Since the 1990s, whenever an Ainu dies, the 
media announce the death of the last Ainu speaker, 
forgetting that more and more Ainu are starting to 
relearn their language, inspired by elders or 
linguists. 
To replace the 1899 law supporting assimilation 
policies, the Ainu demanded the promulgation of a 
new law in the 1980s. The law for the protection and 
promotion of Ainu culture was finally promulgated in 
1997, facilitating, for instance, language 
instruction.
A law can change everything
Founded in 1946, Hokkaido’s Ainu association, the 
largest in Japan, gives free language courses in 14 
regions in Hokkaido, to both Ainu and Japanese stu-
dents. No statistics on attendance are available, 
however. The foundation for research and promotion 
of Ainu culture, created by the 1997 law, has a sec-
tion for training Ainu language teachers; it accepts 
seven students a year. 
The publication of dictionaries, textbooks and 
bilingual Ainu-Japanese collections of Ainu oral liter-
ature is increasing year by year. A private radio sta-
tion in Sapporo has been broadcasting a weekly Ainu 
language class program over Hokkaido territory since 
the 1980s. In April 2001, Shigeru Kayano, activist for 
Ainu identity and first Japanese parliament member 
from this community (1926-2006), financed the crea-
tion of a radio station, FM Pipaushi that airs a show 
in Ainu locally in central Hokkaido two Sundays a 
month. 
It must be recognized, however, that for now the 
Ainu interested in their language are from relatively 
affluent backgrounds. The Ainu are for the most part 
marginalized and have little time to devote to learn-
ing their language. Despite the upsurge of interest, 
as long as Ainu is not part of the curriculum in 
Hokkaido schools, its future is uncertain. This 
© Flickr/Mistah Sinclair
The exact number of Ainu speakers is unknown.
4
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
 language is part of Japanese intangible heritage and 
is entitled to government protection, notably through 
its official recognition as a second national 
language.
By Kaori TAHARA, historian of Ainu origin, graduate of 
the École des hautes études en sciences sociales, Paris.
© Flickr/Jens Mattow
Post card representing a group of Ainus, around 1990.
4
Kyrgyz: an “emerging” language
In the streets of Bishkek, two languages are found side by side on advertising billboards, 
at newsstands and in conversations. After gaining its independence in 1991, Kyrgyzstan 
adopted Kyrgyz as its national language and kept Russian as the official language. 
Linguistic results are mixed.
Out of the 15 former Soviet republics, Kyrgyzstan is 
the only one – along with Kazakhstan – to keep 
Russian as its official language in addition to its 
national language, Kyrgyz. Yet the latter, a member 
of the Turkic group of languages, is spoken by 73% 
of the population (amounting to 3.7 million people). 
At the same time, in the capital Bishkek, center of 
Kyrgyzstan’s public and cultural life, Russian 
remains present if not dominant. 
The generations educated in Russian at the time 
of the Soviet Union, notably in urban areas, speak 
Kyrgyz without mastering it entirely. Often it’s a 
language they learned in school. “If tomorrow the 
government decided to switch to Kyrgyz, I’d never 
make it in my professional life,” says Jyldyz Asan-
bayeva, program assistant at the Public Policy 
Institute. She’s among the 2 to 3% ethnic Kyrgyz 
who don’t consider Kyrgyz their mother language. 
© UNESCO/Katerina Markelova
Russian and Kyrgyz newspaper stand in Bichkek, the capital of 
Kyrgyzstan. 4
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
The language has a long oral tradition, with its 
famous epic bards called akyns, but the today’s 
alphabet, starting with Latin characters and then 
changing to Cyrillic, dates back only to the 1920s. 
And for the duration of the Soviet period, its use 
was limited to rural areas (within families and 
between friends) or in certain circles of the intelli-
gentsia (concerned about the preservation of the 
language), even if Kyrgyz is used for teaching in 
most schools and is studied at the highest level in 
Moscow and Leningrad (now St Petersburg).
Russian: back and forth
Shortly before independence, with the impetus of 
perestroika, local authorities imposed Kyrgyz as the 
national language, by passing the 1989 law on the 
national language of the Soviet Socialist Republic 
of Kyrgyz. But political will is one thing, reality 
another. Due to insufficient means, the law was 
not applied; very quickly, funds were reduced and 
the civil servants in charge dismissed. 
Interest in the language fluctuated according to 
the numerous changes in government in the coun-
try, where the political situation was in frequent 
upheaval. Different decrees came one after another 
in support of Kyrgyz, but this protectionist linguis-
tic policy only exacerbated tensions in the country, 
which is home to 80 different ethnic groups who 
use Russian to communicate among themselves. 
Concerned to see Russian-speaking people leaving 
the country in droves, deputies in 2000 voted a 
new law on the official language: Russian and 
Kyrgyz from then on had equal status, the first as 
official language and the second as national 
language. 
Good news for Russian speakers in Kyrgyzstan, 
who in 16 years of independence had not felt the 
need to learn Kyrgyz, for lack of a coherent linguis-
tic policy. 
Authorities wanted to “create a necessity” to 
speak Kyrgyz, but didn’t allocate the resources. 
“Our Institute doesn’t have the funds to publish 
our scientists’ research. The manuscript for the 
Great Russian-Kyrgyz dictionary, which has 250 
pages, is sitting in a cupboard covered in dust,” 
laments Kadyraly Konkobayev, director of the Lin-
guistic Institute of Kyrgyzstan’s Academy of Sci-
ences. While during the Soviet era more than 30 
fundamental texts on the Kyrgyz language were 
published, almost none have been produced since 
the country’s independence. 
Konkobayev sounds another alert: “The literary 
and artistic situation is dire. In the literature 
department, we don’t have enough authors to study 
in the area of Kyrgyz national literature and, I have 
to say, many of our contemporary writers are prac-
tically illiterate.” It isn’t only the authors, he adds; 
one only has to look at the poor quality of the 
newspapers. 
“The work accomplished since independence 
regarding the development of the language is 
unsatisfactory,” explains Tachboo Djumagulov, 
president of the Commission for the Development 
of the National Language. But since the March 2005 
revolution (which ousted President Aska Akayev) 
efforts are increasing: “Before 2005 state subsidies 
amounted to US$ 35,000; now they’re US$ 
170,000.” 
© Kyrgyz National Commission for UNESCO
The art of the Akyn was proclaimed by a masterpiece of the oral 
and intangible cultural heritage of humanity by UNESCO in 2003.
4
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Even if that’s nothing compared to the US$ 30 
million spent in neighboring Kazakhstan to pro-
mote Kazakh, results are tangible. Television is the 
best example: before 2005, there was only one 
Kyrgyz-language channel; now five out of ten 
devote 60% of air time to programs in Kyrgyz.
Education: the weak link
Education seems to be the main element missing 
from the national language battle. “On one hand 
the number of hours of Kyrgyz instruction is 
increasing in schools and universities, but on the 
other hand there are very few qualified teachers,” 
explains Konkobayev. Indeed, all universities have 
established a new post: vice-rector for the Kyrgyz 
language, responsible for promoting it and encour-
aging professors to give courses in it (including 
within Russian-language universities). 
Thanks to the Commission’s efforts to develop 
the national language, new teaching methodolo-
gies for Kyrgyz have been developed. They replace 
the old ones, often very cumbersome and ineffec-
tive, and introduce short dialogues, games and 
concrete examples. With 3,000 copies of the course 
in circulation, it is nonetheless difficult to meet 
the needs of the more than 2,100 schools (1,700 of 
them entirely Kyrgyz) and the 40-odd universities 
across the country, some of which give Kyrgyz 
classes. Besides, the state funds the publication of 
textbooks for schools, but not for universities. 
Result: university textbooks simply don’t exist. 
The mixed linguistic results in Kyrgyzstan bring 
up questions about the methods employed. Is it 
really useful to impose a language without devel-
oping the educational infrastructure? Measures 
taken to preserve the Kyrgyz language must be 
entirely revised, in the context of globalization, 
which here too is knocking at the door with English 
and becoming more and more of a threat.
Katerina Markelova, journalist for the UNESCO 
Courier
© UNESCO/Katerina Markelova
In one of the country’s biggest libraries, the most recent 
textbooks in Kyrgyz date back to 2002.
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
The Indian tower of Babel takes the shape of a pyra-
mid, with Hindu and English at the top, both of which 
remain foreign languages for two-thirds of the popu-
lation. Then come the official languages of the States 
and Territories (regional languages), followed by 
minority languages, spoken by more than a million 
people, but with no administrative function. Hun-
dreds of others are located at the foot of this impos-
ing linguistic edifice, under the aegis of a linguistic 
minority commissioner whose mandate is advisory 
and not legally binding. 
In all: 1,650 languages, with 400 used as lan-
guages of communication. Among the latter, 22 are 
spoken by 75% of Indians and are listed in the Indian 
constitution. It guarantees the protection of lan-
guages that are not listed, but only 60 of those are 
taught in schools, 11 of them registered as minority 
or tribal. 
An odd fact: Hindi, the official Indian union lan-
guage along with English, is spoken by only 40% of 
the Indian population and is therefore a minority 
language. The issue of minorities is extremely com-
plex, insofar as language is an element closely related 
to ethnic and religious identity. Muslims, for instance, 
speak Urdu, Sikhs Panjabi, and Anglo-Indians English. 
While their languages are recognized by the constitu-
tion, more than 600 tribal minorities from the moun-
tains speak languages that are not taught in 
schools.
The trilingual formula
The sub-continent counts more than one billion 
inhabitants, 35% of them under 15 years of age. The 
Indian government has the onerous task of managing 
an education system that dates back about 150 years 
and today comprises 664,041 primary schools, 
219,626 upper primary schools, 133,492 secondary 
schools, 297 universities, 8,737 university-level gen-
eral education colleges and 2,409 professional 
institutes. 
Since its independence in 1947, the country has 
been putting into effect educational policies aimed 
at mass literacy and economic development – key 
factors to unite a people split into a multitude of 
religions, languages, castes and cultures. 
Beginning in 1952, the Indian government’s sec-
ondary education commission put forward the outline 
of a multilingual educational policy including the 
mother language, the regional (or State) language, 
Hindi as the language of general communication and 
one of the classical languages (Sanskrit, Pali, Arabic 
or Persian). 
the Indian dilemma
With some 1,650 languages and more than a million schools including all levels, 
India faces a serious challenge: to ensure national cohesion without compromising the 
interests of regional languages. It has invented the “three language formula”, difficult 
to implement.
© Flickr/Orso FIlippi
All languages are good enough for advertising!
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Revised in 1961, the proposal was named “three 
language formula” (TLF) including the regional lan-
guage, Hindi in non-Hindi-speaking areas or another 
Indian language in Hindi-speaking areas, plus English 
or another European language. 
Finally, between 1964 and 1966, the Education 
Commission proposed a modified version of TLF: the 
mother language or regional language; an official 
language, Hindi or English; and another modern lan-
guage, Indian or foreign. 
Over the 12 years of primary and secondary school, 
instruction is given in the mother or regional lan-
guage from the first to the fifth year, and TLF is 
introduced in the sixth year.
No magic formula
Recognized as the national norm, TLF is nonetheless 
not applied to the letter in all states. It is more 
hypothetical project than social reality. Although 
priority is given to the mother language at least at 
the start of formal education, if not throughout 
schooling, it is not obligatory. Certain states, such 
as Tamil Nadu, have opted for two instead of three 
languages; in others, instead of learning a modern 
language, a classic language is substituted, like San-
skrit or Arabic. In some schools French or German is 
taught instead of Hindi. 
Failure of state policy? Or instead, as we would 
say, a dynamic and flexible linguistic policy in edu-
cation, which seeks to reconcile tradition and moder-
nity on one hand and institutional and civic 
responsibilities on the other. 
Because it must be understood that although 
tribal/minority languages are closely linked to cul-
tural, religious and ethnic identity, at the same time 
they are “useless” in contemporary life. Minority 
communities are torn between two trends: some 
demand their rights and struggle to obtain an offi-
cial status for their language, while others choose 
assimilation with the majority instead. 
In order to protect minority languages and safe-
guard the thousand-year-old heritage they contain, 
there is talk of turning the three language formula 
into a four language one. Nothing is yet certain. 
The state may well guarantee schooling in a 
minority language whenever a class contains 10 
pupils who speak it as their mother language, but 
the fact is most parents would prefer their children 
to learn English or be educated in English. The 
“unconstitutional” languages have no “market value” 
and social upward mobility often comes before socio-
cultural identity.
Appasamy Murugaiyan, Indian linguist, 
teaches at the École pratique des Hautes Études, Paris
© UNESCO/Mani Ngonekeo
The Venerable Chandaratana, in Sankassa, India.
© Flickr/Uba Devesh
Primary school in 
western Rajasthan.
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
2 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Why have you gone from the immensity of the uni-
verse to the fragility of the earth? 
Because if astronomy teaches us how we came to 
exist on earth, ecology teaches us how we can stay 
here. We know the wonders of the stars and the gal-
axies, which are linked to our past and our presence 
here – atoms that are formed in the stars and so on – 
and we discover that our survival on earth is threat-
ened. How could one not be concerned? 
People often say to me “Before, you talked about 
galaxies, you made us dream, now you’re telling us 
unpleasant facts.” I answer that we have to be real-
ists. We can’t spend our time dreaming. We can’t play 
ostrich. We need solid knowledge of the situation on 
earth to know what to do. 
I came to the issue of the environment gradually. 
During the lectures I gave in the 1980s, I started 
bringing up the problem, which became more and 
more present as time went by, until it became a cru-
cial issue. But I still give lectures about astronomy 
too. 
I try to speak usefully. That is to say, not to 
preach to the converted, but to address groups that 
are less involved in environmental issues. I’ve given 
lectures to real estate agents, for instance, and nota-
ries, truck drivers….They’re flabbergasted when you 
explain to them what’s going on. 
Are you alarmed? 
Not as much as I was a few years ago. But there’s 
been such a change all over the world that today I’m 
more encouraged. I’m often asked if I’m an optimist 
or a pessimist. I answer with a quote from Jean 
Monnet, one of the founders of Europe, at the time 
when nobody really believed in Europe. He used to 
Focus
Hubert reeves
Engaging geosciences in the service of humanity is the aim of the International Year 
of Planet Earth, launched on 12 February at UNESCO. This year, UNESCO and the 
International Union of Geological Sciences have taken the initiative to place sustainable 
development and the promotion of Earth Sciences (geology, geophysics, palaeontology, 
meteorology…) at the top of their priorities. This is a true pact for a better world. 
To announce the launch of this International Year, to which it will devote one of its 
next issues, the Courier interviewed the famous Canadian (Québécois) astrophysicist 
Hubert Reeves
Interview by Jasmina Šopova 
4
© UNESCO/Michel Ravassard
Hubert Reeves
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
say, “What’s important isn’t being optimistic or pes-
simistic, it’s being determined.” 
It has to be said that in the last two years, aware-
ness of environmental problems has come a long way, 
thanks to people like the American Al Gore (2007 
Nobel Peace Prize), the French ecologist Nicolas 
Hulot, whose le pacte écologique (ecological pact) 
obliged politicians to take positions, or the British 
economist Nicolas Stern, who evaluated the cost of 
global warming at several thousand billion dollars 
(Stern Review on the Economics of Climate Change, 
2006).
In 2001, you became president of the ROC.
The “Rassemblement des Opposants à la Chasse” 
(Union of Opponents of Hunting) was founded in 
1976 by Théodore Monod, at a time when there were 
no controls at all on hunting in France. He was the 
president, and after he died in 2001, I was asked to 
replace him. The problems have since changed, and 
so have the aims, along with the organization’s name, 
which became the Ligue ROC pour la préservation de 
la faune sauvage (ROC league for the preservation of 
wildlife). 
Today we’re very concerned by the disappearance 
of natural habitats and by pesticides, which contrib-
ute to what is called “biodiversity erosion”. The speed 
at which we are exterminating animal and plant spe-
cies represents one of the most disturbing aspects. 
In nature, species are not independent. Each disap-
pearance of a species causes that of many others and 
thus weakens the ecosystem. 
A very striking example is bees. The rapid disap-
pearance of bees causes a decrease in tree pollina-
tion. And without pollination, there’s no fruit. And 
fruit contributes in an essential way to the survival 
of humanity. 
When one element in life’s edifice - built over mil-
lions of years, whose solidity rests on the interde-
pendency of species – disappears, the whole is 
impoverished. Biodiversity, we have to stress this, is 
our guarantee of survival. 
Do you think political decision-makers are taking 
action quickly enough? 
The “Grenelle de l’environnement” (French govern-
ment forum on the environment) held last October in 
France is a good example. French President Nicholas 
Sarkozy promised it and he did it. It’s not every day 
politicians keep their pre-election promises. 
The originality of Grenelle was to bring together 
partners with opposing convictions: for example, 
farmers who defend agriculture relying heavily on 
pesticides, and environmental groups in the name of 
productivisme. This Grenelle represents real progress. 
I have reasons to believe that there will even be 
action to follow the words. Because fundamentally 
people aren’t crazy. And even those who couldn’t care 
less about butterflies or wildflowers dying out are 
beginning to understand that if they don’t invest 
now in positive action, it will cost them a lot more in 
the future.
© Stock.xchng/Terri Heisele
The rapid disappearance of bees causes a decrease in tree 
pollination.
4
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
2 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
And in other countries?
The United States are really on the move. George 
Bush blocked everything, but states such as Califor-
nia or those in New England have become extremely 
“green”. In Europe, the countries in the North are 
generally much more active. France is waking up, 
Spain is starting to move. But what’s very important 
is that China is also beginning to react. Meanwhile 
we don’t have very good news from India, but I think 
it will come because once again people do realize 
what’s going on. 
Is it utopian to imagine a Grenelle on an interna-
tional scale, organized by UNESCO, for instance? 
That would be brilliant if governments would listen 
to constituents of civil societies so that they can 
participate in the world’s evolution, and why not 
overseen by UNESCO. 
And to end the conversation on another seemingly 
utopian subject: do you believe there’s another 
planet that will welcome humanity if we destroy 
ours? 
I have no idea. There are people who believe that if 
things get too bad on earth, we’ll go to another 
planet. For me, that’s not a good solution, because if 
we turn out to be incapable of safeguarding our 
planet, we will only be transporting our problems to 
another one.
© Flickr/Jens Trebtow
A truck on a road in China. The future of the earth is everyone’s 
concern!
4
Landmarks
the “Doctor Prince”
Born two hundred years ago, Prince Wonsa Dhiraj Sanid, son of King Rama II of Thailand 
(1809-1824), devoted his life to promoting peace, health and culture for the benefit of 
his country. In recognition of his achievements, UNESCO joins in the celebration of the 
anniversary of his birth. He is the 17th Thai national to receive this honour.
Phra Chao Barommawongse Ther Krom Luang Wongsa 
Dhiraj Sanid (H.R.H. Prince Wongsa Dhiraj Snid) (1808-
1871) was a son of King Rama II (1809-1824), whose 
contribution in political, scientific, and cultural fields 
was very beneficial for Thailand. Without prejudice, he 
learned from foreign missionaries and used their 
knowledge to help his countrymen. He was hailed a 
great modernist in the midst of the royal family. 
Prince Wongsa Dhiraj Snid dedicated most of his 
life to negotiating for Thailand’s peace and prosper-
ity. His mastery of English, together with his diplo-
matic skill, made him the most important prince in 
Thailand’s international context during the reign of 
his brother King Rama IV (1851-1868). 
Colonialism in the nineteenth century motivated 
European countries to acquire lands in Southeast Asia. 4
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
2 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Thailand, or Siam, was not an exception. Prince Wongsa 
Dhiraj Snid was appointed by King Rama IV head of 
Siam’s negotiation team to sign several treaties with 
western countries, including Britain, France, Prussia, 
Denmark, and United States. The treaties, signed under 
his supervision, were aimed at tightening the politi-
cal, legal and free trade links between Siam and other 
countries. His ability to negotiate led to the success 
of several agreements, creating the balance of power 
between each western state and Siam. This was not 
only the key to help maintain peace but also to open 
the country to the world for modernization.
Diplomat, scientist and poet
Committed to scientific development, Prince Wongsa 
Dhiraj Snid was the first Thai doctor who introduced 
quinine, a western medicine for curing malaria, and 
used it successfully on Thai patients. His mother, 
Chao Chom Marnda Prang (Yai) was a descendant of 
the Bangchang Royal Family, whose role was to pre-
serve and transmit traditional Thai medicine. He 
acquired his knowledge of western medicine from 
missionaries living in Thailand in the early Chakri 
Dynasty (1782-1851). During the reign of King Rama 
III (1824-1851), also his brother, the Prince was 
appointed chief of the Krom Mor Luang department 
(the Office of Royal Medicine) and served as King 
Rama IV’s personal doctor. Foreigners in Thailand 
called him “The Doctor Prince”. 
The Prince also focused his attention on Thai tra-
ditional medicine. He studied the properties of 166 
herb types and wrote the first Thai traditional herbal 
medicine textbook. The book, reprinted several times 
(1922, 1984, 1991 and 2003), can be found at the 
Thapra Palace Library, Silpakorn university, in Bang-
kok. Widely recognized for his medical skills, he was 
invited by many European medical institutes to be an 
active member. He also received a Certificate of Phy-
sician from the New York Academy, being the first 
Thai doctor who obtained this honour. 
At the same time, Prince Wongsa Dhiraj Snid played 
a predominant role in the literary context. He edited 
Jinda Manee, a grammar-book of the Thai language 
inherited from the Ayutthaya period. During the reign 
of King Rama V, the book was included as the first 
grammar textbook in the nation-wide school curricu-
lum. He revised the Annals of Ayutthaya, (Royal Auto-
graph Edition) considered the first Thai history book 
which was reprinted in 2005. He composed Thai poems 
such as Pleng Yao Samchai and Nirat Phra Pathom 
Pathon, which were published in 1921 and 1922 
respectively. His literary works are kept at the Chu-
lalongkorn University Library, in Bangkok.
Watchara Saengsrisin, 
journalist at The Nation (Thaïland)
4
Prince Wongsa Dhiraj Sanid.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
2 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
the Courier looks 
back
since its creation, the UNESCO Courier 
has devoted several issues and many 
articles to questions linked to languages. 
a few examples: 
http://unesdoc.unesco.org/ulis/fre/
index.shtml 
Worlds within Words, February . 
the powers of language by Claude Hagège - article 
published in march 8.
a treasury of tongues, July 8 
Next month
“Women between 
two shores”
From Doris Lessing (united Kingdom) to Kiran 
Desai (India-united states), including Véronique 
tadjo (Côte d’Ivoire), several women of letters 
from all parts of the world express their concerns 
in the Courier’s next issue. 
Issue published on the occasion of 8 march, Inter-
national Women’s Day. 
© Rapho/Edouard Boubat
Sophie, Collioure, France 1954. Exhibition « Edouard 
Boubat – Revelations », from 16 January to 30 March, at 
the Maison Européenne de la Photographie (Paris).
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
2 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
Partners
SIL International
Founded 70 years ago, SIL International 
specializes in serving the lesser-known 
language communities of the world. SIL 
has conducted linguistic analysis in over 
1,800 languages spoken by 1.2 billion 
people in more than 70 countries.  
A UNESCO Partner for more than 50 
years, SIL International collaborates 
currently with the Organization in the 
field of multilingualism in cyberspace, 
multilingual education and the 
preservation and promotion of languages 
in danger of disappearing. 
Latin Union
The Latin Union is an organization founded in 1954 by the Madrid Convention to 
promote and circulate the cultural heritage and identities of the Latin world. On four 
continents, the Latin Union strives to raise awareness of Latin cultures and languages 
by acting in three areas: culture and communication, promotion and language teaching, 
language industry and terminology. 
African Academy of Languages 
The African Academy of Languages, established in 2001 in Mali, is a structure in charge 
of all questions linked to languages on the African Continent. It aims to establish a true 
partnership between African and other languages used today throughout the continent 
(English, French, Spanish, Portuguese…), with a pan-African vision.
© UNESCO/Maro Haas
Cover of the brochure for the International Year of Languages, 
2008
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
2 The UNESCO Courier • 2008 • Number 
The UNESCO Courier is published by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization. 
7, place de Fontenoy – 75352 Paris 07 SP, France 
general inquiries by e-mail: courier.unesco@unesco.org 
 Director: Saturnino Muñoz Gómez editor in Chief: Jasmina Šopova
 French editor: Agnès Bardon english editors: Ariane Bailey
 spanish editor: Lucía Iglesias Kuntz arabic editor: Bassam Mansour
 russian editors: Katerina Markelova Chinese editor: Weiny Cauhape
 editorial assistant: José Banaag Photo and Features editor: Fiona Ryan
 Web Platform: Stephen Roberts, Fabienne Kouadio, Chakir Piro Layout: Gérard Prosper
Articles and photos credited UNESCO may be reproduced and/or translated providing the credit line reads “Reproduced from the UNESCO Courier”, 
and include date and hyperlink. Photos without UNESCO credit request specific authorization. 
Articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO. 
Boundaries on maps do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
ISSN 1993-8616 
]]>
</page>
</document>
