<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="184070eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
MARCH 1989 9 Fr
A SILKEN BOND
BETWEEN EAST AND WEST
PERSIA'S GREATEST LYRIC POET
THE ONCE AND FUTURE
REVOLUTION
POLLUTION UNLIMITED
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
MARCH
'989
A silken bond between East and West
by Ahmad Hasan Dani
11	
Mihai Eminescu:
Romania's national poet
12
Love sacred and profane
Decoding Hafez' mystic message
by Réza Feiz
13
Hafez
The golden age of Persian literature
by Charles-Henri de Fouchécour
17
The once and future revolution
by Maurice Agulhon
23	
The Mermaid of the Dniester
by Osyp Petrash
24	
Pollution unlimited
by France Bequette
31
O
HO
is4
Rediscovering 'The Islands
of the Moon'
by André Libioulle
33
Educational planners go back to school
Statuette of a musician playing a double flute,
4th century BC. Greek influences can be seen
in the robes and headdress of the 12-cm high
figure, which was found at Carthage on the
4 north coast of Africa.
The Courier JUL
A window open on the world 42nd year
Published monthly in 35 languages English
French Spanish Russian German
Arabic Japanese Italian Hindi
Tamil Hebrew Persian Dutch
Portuguese Turkish Urdu Catalan
Malaysian Korean Swahili Croato-
Serb Macedonian Serbo-Croat
Slovene Chinese Bulgarian Greek
Sinhala Finnish Swedish Basque
Thai Vietnamese Pashto Hausa
The American poet-essayist Ralph Waldo Emerson
once wrote that "Great geniuses have the shortest
biographies". His compatriot and contemporary,
James Russell Lowell, declared that the highest form
ofgenius could be described as the voice that speaks
"out of the eternal to the present". The great
Persian lyric poet Hafez, the six hundredth
anniversary of whose death we commemorate this
year, qualifies as a genius on both these counts. We
have only the sketchiest outline of his personal life,
yet his poems speak to us across the centuries as
though they were written yesterday.
Mihai Eminescu, the Romanian poet who died a
hundred years ago, was a genius of another order.
A true Romantic and an expert in folklore and
comparative mythology, his writings express the
genius, the spiritual embodiment ofan entire
nation. The same might be said of the Rusalka
Dnistrovaya, the "Mermaid of the Dniester", the
first collection of Ukrainian literature to appear in
the western Ukraine.
The third anniversary we salute in this issue, as
a foretaste of a fuller treatment in our June
number, is, of course, the bicentenary of the French
Revolution. But when we speak of revolution today
does the word have the same meaning for us as it
did for the revolutionaries of two hundred years
ago?
French revolutionary ideas have since been
carried to the four corners of the world, just as for
centuries both merchandise and ideas have flowed
back and forth between Ea'st and West along the
great cultural and commercial highway we call the
Silk Road. As leisurely caravans plied from
Changan to Istanbul, from Kashgar to Samarkand,
Portuguese seafarers, too, were forging new links
between East and West as they opened up the Spice
Route, becoming in their travels the first Westerners
to marvel at the sight of the Comoros, the "Islands
of the Moon".
Today, sadly, the caravans and the caravels have
been replaced by jet aircraft, giant trucks and fast
cars. Trade in both goods and ideas between East
and West may have expanded, but so too has the
pollution associated with our energy-hungry
industries and our modern "convenience" transport.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A SILKEN BOND BETWEEN EAST
BY AHMAD HASAN DANI
The Buddha's first sermon. Arch-shaped stele in the Gandhara (Graeco-Buddhist) style, Lahore Museum.
THE Silk Road originated in the
early centuries of the Christian
era as a channel of trade in silk
and other goods between China and
India in the east and the Roman world
in the west. It has a permanent place in
world history as an important means of
contact between peoples and cultures and
a conduit for the two-way transmission
of ideas, science and technology, lan¬
guages and literature.
Such contact was not always easy to
maintain in the face of political pressures
and other hindrances, but when one
stretch of the route closed down another
would take its place. Several routes, both
overland and maritime, were actually fol¬
lowed by travellers between east and
west, and the expression "Silk Road" is
a symbolic one evoking an enduring spirit
of communication between peoples. It is
in order to rediscover that eternal spirit
that the project for the "Integral Study
of the Silk Roads" has been undertaken
(see the Unesco Courier, November 1988).
The Silk Roads project is a many-sided
undertaking. Some scholars will be retra¬
cing the various itineraries which con¬
nected China and the West and studying
the geography of the countries through
which they passed. Others will be focus¬
ing on the mechanics of road building and
transport technology and the ways in
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
AND WEST
which they were influenced by climatic
conditions and the physical barriers
which had to be overcome. Still others
will study the technologies used by differ¬
ent peoples for the exploitation of ma¬
terial resources, and analyse the social
systems, languages and literatures of these
peoples, as well as their folklore, their
myths and other aspects of their culture.
Population movements, the great
migrations that shaped the history of
entire regions, will also be studied. But
the individual travellers who made their
way along the Silk Roads will not be
forgottenthe artists, musicians and
craftsmen who were prepared to risk
their lives in pursuit of knowledge from
other cultures and societies, to which in
turn they contributed their own skills.
Love of adventure, a hunger for
knowledge about others, these were but
two of many motives which fuelled the
process of exchange between different
societies and helped to break down the
barriers which isolated people in differ¬
ent regions and to establish the bonds of
co-existence that make human progress
possible. This was the legacy of the Silk
Road and the spirit which brought it
into being.
Orient and Occident:
the first contacts
The foundations of the east-west
contacts, which were later channelled
along the Silk Roads, were laid in the last
few centuries of the pre-Christian era
with the formation of a number of Asian
states whose peoples exploited the
resources they found locally and compet¬
ed for trade. This quest for profit led to
a flourishing exchange of goods and the
movement of men from region to region.
Gradually, the peaceful conditions neces¬
sary for trade came into being. The
diverse peoples involved in this process
are vividly portrayed by the Greek
historian Herodotus, who describes how
their societies were organized, their ways
of life and their close relationship with
the Achaemenid empire in Persia.
One example of this commercial and
cultural exchange is that of the Aramaean
merchants who travelled through Central
Asia where their alphabetic script,
continued on page 8
The miracle of Sravasti. 3rd-century AD Gandhara bas-relief depicting the Buddha's most famous miracle which occurred in the ancient Indian town
of Sravasti (in the present-day state of Uttar Pradesh) where he lived and preached for part of his life.
	 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Art on the move
Gold pendant resembling a Byzantine coin
(6th century AD), comes from the
archaeological site of Astana, near Turfan in
the Xinjiang region of northwest China.
This Chinese bronze from the Warring States period
(475-221 BC), unearthed in the garden of a house at Rome, is
thought to have reached Italy in the 1st or 2nd century AD.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Detail of blue silk damask cloth (13th-14th century), discovered in
the necropolis of Al-Azam, Egypt. Chinese artisans sometimes used
Arabic characters in the designs of silks bound for Egypt, in order to
gratify the tastes of their Muslim clients.
This bronze statuette of a deity (1st
century AD), from Alexandria or an
eastern province of the Roman empire,
was found at Begram, Afghanistan, the
site of one of the ancient capitals of
the Kushan kingdom.
Intaglio figure carved in carnelian (3rd-4th century AD), of
Mediterranean origin, which was found during excavations at the
port of Oc Eo on the southern coast of modern Viet Nam. The
Roman figure with upraised index finger may represent a
philosopher.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
continued from page 5
Aramaic, influenced the evolution of
other alphabets such as Sogdian and
Kharoshti. Among the other peoples
described by Herodotus are the
Scythians, the "Indians", and the Persian-
speaking people who moved eastward,
where their language had a strong
influence on the ancient languages of the
region.
The meeting of the peoples of east and
west, the exchange of ideas and technol¬
ogies, and the two-way transmission of
languages and literature was made possi¬
ble for the first time by the Achaemenid
empire between the sixth and fourth cen¬
turies BC. People were attracted from
many points of the compass to the capi¬
tal of the empire, Persepolis, along roads
built by the emperor Darius. At the same
time, in the outlying central Asian
provinces, cities such as Balkh1, Samar¬
kand and Taxila, which later became im¬
portant staging posts on the Silk Roads,
were connected by overland routes and
developed as meeting points between east
and west. During this period the spirit of
dialogue between the peoples of east and
west was the primary form of the enrich¬
ment of human civilization.
The conquests of Alexander
the Great
Contacts between east and west were
facilitated in the late fourth century BC
by the conquests of Alexander the Great,
who overthrew the Achaemenid empire
and campaigned eastwards as far as India.
A Macedonian who became steeped in
Greek culture after his conquest of
Greece, and then an oriental monarch,
captivated by the idealism of the East,
Alexander was himself the embodiment
of cultural intermingling.
During his time the culture of the
Greek world was transmitted into Asia
in an unprecedented flow of men and
ideas, technologies, artistic trends and
architectural formulae, as well as drama,
poetry, music, religions and above all
language and literature. However, the
[
A«
.1 . liíiDffí
1wr*
*lr
Shiva with three heads. A bas-relief from the 12th-century monastery of Pandrethan, near
Srinagar, State of Jammu and Kashmir, India.
traffic was not only one-way. Alexander
and the scholars who accompanied him
met Asian philosophers, whose ideas they
took back to Greece along with tributes
of gold, cattle and artefacts which
enriched the classical world of the West.
Alexander founded several new cities in
Asia, and his men intermarried there,
introducing Hellenism but at the same
time becoming thoroughly Asianized and
integrated into the local population.
Shortly after Alexander invaded the
sub-continent, Chandragupta Maurya
seized the throne of the Indian kingdom
of Magadha, thus taking the first step in
the creation of the mighty Mauryan em¬
pire, which inherited both the Greek and
the Achaemenid legacy. The empire
reached its zenith during the reign of his
grandson Asoka (274-237 BC). Asoka,
who inaugurated an era of Buddhist mis¬
sionary activity that was to have a far-
reaching impact on central Asia and the
Far East, received many Greek envoys
and in return sent his own ambassadors
to the Hellenistic world.2
After its founder's death, Alexander's
great empire disintegrated into smaller
units including such peoples as the Bac-
trian Greeks, the Sogdians, the Parthians,
and later the Sassanians and the Scythians.
This fragmentation did not prevent the
movement of people and goods; on the
contrary, commercial activity was inten¬
sified as a result of advances in geographi¬
cal knowledge, which also encouraged the
movements of learned Buddhists, Zoroas-
trians, Manicheans and other mission¬
aries. The ruins of monasteries and other
religious centres provide a clue to the
routes they took. Cultural influences
spread along the river valleys of
Mesopotamia, Central Asia and India.
Archaeological excavations at Taxila on
the Indus and Ai-Khanum on the Oxus3
have shown how art and architecture of
that time drew on a wide variety of
traditions.
The growth of sea-borne trade
Another significant development,
thought to have taken place around 100 BC,
was the discovery of the monsoon, which
enabled ocean-going vessels to cross the
Indian Ocean from west to east in spring
and then to return in winter when the
8 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
winds reversed, laden with products of the
East. For the first time the Indian Ocean
had become a lake for ships travelling
between the Roman world, Indian ports,
and the coast of China.
The work of geographers such as
Pliny the Elder in the first century AD
and Ptolemy a century later testifies to
increasing knowledge of the world- The
anonymous author of the first-century
Periplus Maris Erythraei gives a detailed
description of the countries around the
Indian Ocean, their peoples, trade, im¬
ports and exports, climate and currency.
New sea routes were developed, ex¬
tending the range of the coastal shipping
that in ancient times had linked Egypt,
via the land of Dilmun (possibly Bahrein)
with the distant, eastern countries of
Magan and Meluhha, which may have
been located in the Indus valley. Sea
traffic along these new routes would
reinforce, and when necessary replace,
the overland Silk Roads.
China's opening to the West
Meanwhile, tribal conflicts on the
western borders of China had caused the
Qin Dynasty (221-206 BC) to build the
Great Wall of China as a defensive meas¬
ure. Chinese sources describe how these
tribes subsequently moved down the
Oxus valley and penetrated south of the
Kun-lun, Karakorum and Hindu Kush
mountains.
The rulers of the Han Dynasty
(206 BC-220 AD) which followed kept a
strict watch over these tribal movements
on their western borders, but they also
opened up for the first time the route to
central Asia and maintained close contact
with the mighty Kushan empire which
stretched from the Caspian Sea in the
north through the Oxus, Indus and
Ganges valleys to the Arabian Sea in the
south. The Kushan empire was so vast
that it also had close contacts with the
Roman empire. This period of close col¬
laboration between East and West helped
to create the propitious conditions for the
opening of the Silk Road.
Traces of intense cultural activity still
mark the routes that joined East and West
centuries ago. Ruins of ancient cities, such
as Kapisa (near modern Charikar) in the
heart of Afghanistan, tell a story of com¬
plex exchanges with other countries.
Rock carvings portray people wearing the
costumes of different tribes and rock
inscriptions speak of different peoples and
languages. In the,great ancient capital of
Changan {modern Xian), Buddhist
monks from Japan and Korea met learned
scholars from Sri Lanka, India and
Central Asia. Sculptures of Buddhas and
Bodhisattvas stand in spectacular natural
surroundings, most notably at Bamiyan
in Afghanistan, where there are two
colossal Buddha figures carved from the
An apsaras, a goddess-nymph of Indian mythology. Detail from an 11th-century fresco, Alchi
monastery, Ladakh, in which both Indian and Persian influences' cali be seen.
	 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
living rock and hundreds of man-made
caves, many of which bear traces of fine
fresco painting which links them with
contemporary caves in Xin-jiang
(Sinkiang).
The expansion of Islam
The rise of Islam in Arabia in the
seventh century triggered a profound so¬
cial and religious revolution among the
Engraved and embossed silver plate (4th century) showing Shapur II (310-379 AD), king of the
Sasanian empire of Persia, hunting wild boar. Merchants from Khorezm on their way to Europe
via the Caspian Sea and the Volga River may have brought the plate to Perm, in the central
Urals, where it was discovered.
mathematics, the new symbols of number
and the decimal system that became the
foundations of modern science. They also
disseminated the science of chemistry,
knowledge of the properties of metals and
of new Chinese technologies, and above
all medical information which opened up
great possibilities in the human and
biological sciences. Arab interest in
astronomy led to the development of new
concepts of the universe and of cosmogo¬
ny. In the fields of art and architecture
they allied the traditions of the past with
scientific and mathematical precision
and contributed new forms in building
and new tastes in decoration which
incorporated calligraphy and arabesque.
In this way the spirit of the Silk Roads
was carried on. As the caravans plied
from Khotan, Yarkand and Kashgar to
Samarkand, Bokhara and Merv and beyond
to the markets of the western world, or
further south through Balkh, Hamadan
and Damascus to Aleppo, or from China
westwards to the Caucasus and then on
to Istanbul and Venice, they kept alive a
dialogue between the peoples of east and
west, a process of mutual contact and co¬
operation that encouraged the peaceful
growth of human civilization.
1. Balkh: the ancient city of Bactra, capital of Bactria.
2. After conquering the kingdom of Kalinga (the modern
Indian state of Orissa), Asoka renounced war. The name
of Kalinga lives on in the Kalinga Prize for distinguished
popular writing in science which is awarded annually by
Unesco. The Prize was created in 1951 after a donation
from an Indian industrialist from Orissa. Mr. Bijoyanand
Patnaik.
3. Oxus: ancient name of the Amu Darya River, central
Asia, which flows into the Aral Sea. Editor
While the Han Dynasty ruled in China,
the Huns spread from the western
borderland of China and Mongolia into
the heart of Asia and Europe and down
to India. A loose confederation of peo¬
ples, the Huns built a vast empire in cen¬
tral Asia stretching from China to Persia
and from the Oxus to the Arabian Sea.
Many Chinese and western travellers
have left a vivid picture of the Huns'
horsemanship, polo-playing, weapons
and dress. The Huns were followed by
Turkic tribes who established states in
Central Asia which obstructed passage
along the old-established Silk Roads,
although the T'ang Dynasty which began
to rule China in 618 AD still managed to
send goods and people to the West.
Arabs, who expanded into Asia, Africa
and Europe. Their expansion also opened
up new vistas in science and philosophy
as they began to plumb the ocean of
knowledge contained in Greek manu¬
scripts and to translate them into Arabic.
Through their contacts with India and
China they also followed new develop¬
ments in mathematics, medicine and
astronomy and learned how to manufac¬
ture paper, gunpowder, ceramics and silk
and muslin cloth. The Arabs now became
the intermediaries in a dialogue which
extended from China to Venice and then
westwards to France, Spain and Portugal.
As well as passing on Greek science and
philosophy to the newly-developing
world of the time, they propagated Indian
AHMAD HASAN DANI, of Pakistan, Professor
Emeritus at Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad,
and honorary director of the Centre for the Study
of the Civilizations of Central Asia, is the author
of many books and articles on history and
archaeology. This article is adapted from a paper
presented by Professor Dani at the first international
seminar on Unesco's Integral Study of the Silk Roads
project, held in Osaka (Japan) in October 1988.
10 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
MIHAI EMINESCU,
ROMANIA'S NATIONAL POET
M
"IHAI Eminescu
(1850-1889) is recogn¬
ized as the foremost
Romanian lyric poet. His
mastery of language has also
earned him a high place in
world literature.
Eminescu led a tormented
life. Born into the minor
aristocracy, he was educated at
the universities of Vienna
(1869-1872) and Berlin
(1872-1874) and tried his hand
at several jobs before joining
the editorial staff of the
newspaper Timpul ("Time").
In 1883 he suffered a mental
breakdown which, punctuated
by periods of lucidity, lasted
until his death.
Poet, dramatist, journalist,
a specialist in Romanian folk
poetry, Eminescu was a man
of wide intellectual interests.
He produced a vast body of work, but only published one
volume of verse in his lifetime, under the title of Poezii (1883;
"Poetry").
The poems he wrote in his youth, such as Inger si demon
("Angel and Devil") or Impärat si proletar ("Emperor and
Proletarian"), are marked by a Byronic and Faustian revolt
against the social and the cosmic order. Later, his reading of
the philosophy of Kant and Schopenhauer modified his vision
of the world. A short prose fantasy, Särmanul Dionis ("Den¬
nis the Pauper"), published in 1872, illustrates his determina¬
tion to transcend time and space in a quest for absolute liberty.
He gave a new and original slant to the Romantic theme of
the fallen angel.
His interest in folklore and comparative mythology was re¬
inforced by his knowledge of the work of the German Roman¬
tic poets, particularly the Heidelberg school (Achim von Arnim,
Clemens Brentano, Joseph von Görres). After 1874, love be¬
comes a dominant theme of his poetry, in which woman is por¬
trayed in harmony with Nature, bathed in moonlight and the
heavy perfume of lime blossom. His rhyme and verse forms,
as in Floare albasträ ("Blue Flower") and Povestea teiului ("The
Tale of the Lime Tree"), have a gentle, lyrical quality never
before attained in the Romanian language.
After 1877, a cold aura of gloom and death begins to per¬
vade his work. His love poetry becomes the expression of
unrelieved solitude and suffer¬
ing. Some poems, such as
Despartiré ("Separation"),
evoke emotional crisis, while
others, such as his sonnets, are
imbued with a heart-rending
and enchanting beauty.
In the third of five Scrisori
("Epistles") from his mature
work, the patriotic poet evokes
episodes from the glory of
the Romanian medieval past
and, alternating between
lyricism and satire, contrasts
them with the bitterness of the
degraded present.
Eminescu was a true
Romantic, creator of mytho¬
logical worlds in which the
tragedy of the human condi¬
tion is played out. Like the
great lyric poets Friedrich
Hölderlin and John Keats, he
used the classical myth of
Hyperion in his long ballad Luceafarul (1883; "The Evening
Star"), in which he suggests that genius is condemned to soli¬
tude in a society hostile to spiritual values. Written in four-line
stanzas with seven or eight syllables to the line and the rhythm
and style of a folk tale, it is a masterpiece of lyric poetry.
Hyperion, the evening star, who is in love with a mortal
princess and ready to renounce his immortal existence and
become human for her sake, engages in an epic astral journey
which leads him into the presence of God. Warned of the fick¬
leness of mortal love (the princess has fallen in love with a young
page), he understands the futility of the sacrifice which he was
about to make and does not return to the world of humanity:
But this time he does not fall
down to the depths of the sea
but says: "Does it matter to you,
clod of earth, if it's any man or me?
You live in a narrow world,
a plaything offortune.
But I live in my own universe,
immortal and immune. u
This article is based on
University of Bucharest.
a study by Zoe Dumitrescu Busulenga, a professor at the
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
LOVE SACRED AND PROFANE
Decoding Hafez' mystic message
BY REZA FEIZ
HAFEZ is considered in
the Islamic Republic of
Iran, the land of his birth,
and beyond the frontiers of the
Persian-speaking countries, as the
poet of love and as one of the
greatest Muslim Sufi mystics, even
though his worldly language
presents him as a very human and
sensual poet.
The meaning of love in Hafez
must first be elucidated and an at¬
tempt then be made to establish the
relationships between "Love", "the
Lover", and "the Beloved". This
may help to clarify Hafez' use of
language and to define the level at
which his poetry should be read
and appreciated.
For a Sufi like Hafez, love has
a sacred dimension and cannot be
understood in its profane sense.
Love is enacted in a sphere in which
even a profane act automatically be¬
comes sacred. Thus for a Sufi, even
humdrum everyday life remains
spiritual. It is in this sense that
Hafez sings the praises of love:
/ have never heard a sweeter word
than the word love,
It is the only memory that remains beneath the cupola ofthe heavens.
However, this "sweet word" is accompanied by pain, the pain
of man's separation from his celestial origin, a theme magnificently
treated by another great Persian Sufi poet, Mawlana ("Our Lord")
Jalal ad-Din ar-Rumi (1207-1273), in his great work the Masnavi.
Thus all the poetry of Hafez is a hymn to love; for him poetry
is simply a way of revealing and glorifying it. He is also intensely
aware of love's influence on the success of his verse, for he says:
Since love has taught thee eloquence
Thy words are heard in every gathering.
What is the place of love in this movement of the lover towards
the Beloved? The starting point of the process is surely the lover's
longing. For Hafez, however, the Beloved is always the originator,
It is when the Beloved is fully revealed that the lover's ecstasy and
passion come into being. The lover finds the beauty and perfec¬
tion to which he aspires embodied in the Beloved:
In the beginning the reflection of thy beauty revealed itself
Love appeared and enflamed the whole universe.
In Sufi forms of expression, the lover's overwhelming need for
union with the Beloved is called Soluk, which might be
15th-century miniature from a Divan (collection of poems)
by Hafez.
translated as "spiritual journey".
The circle of love begins and ends
with the Beloved. He who accom¬
plishes the journey towards union
with the Beloved lives in the materi¬
al world but also inhabits a spiritu¬
al universe. He sees the world as the
reflection of the beauty of the
Beloved, but he is not thereby
attached to it. Hafez says:
/ was not interested in the affairs of
this world,
It is thy face that has made it beauti¬
ful for me.
Contrary to what might be sup¬
posed from his worldly and even
licentious language, Hafez is a great
Sufi who becomes a poet and not
a poet who speaks as a mystic.
He approaches poetry from a sacred
and spiritual viewpoint. He speaks
of wine, cabarets, cup-bearers; of
loved ones, singers, harpists; of curls
and tresses, of beautiful faces and
marks of beauty ... Ostensibly these
are all worldly images, but to accept
them at their face value is to mis¬
understand completely the social and
cultural ethos of the society of
which Hafez was writing.
The personality of Hafez ("he who has learned the Qur'an
by heart"), also known as "the tongue of the invisible" lisan-ol
ghayb), and "the interpreter of mysteries" (tarjoman-ol asrar), directs
the reader to look for a further meaning to his words. It is evident
that his is a symbolic and allegorical language written in the liter¬
ary style of the period and still valid. The fact that those poems
which seem the most worldly are sung as psalms at Sufi gather¬
ings is proof that Sufis consider him to be a spiritual master.
Hafez' poetry is universal because he touches on eternal truths.
For Hafez, light comes straight from the sun, unfiltered by any
earthly medium, and it is through this pure light of inspiration
that he distinguishes between truth and illusion and, with unusual
realism, recommends forgiveness and tolerance:
Forgive the quarrel of seventy-two rites and religions
Not having known truth, they have followed the path of illusion.
REZA FEIZ, of the Islamic Republic of Iran, is the author of a number of articles
and papers on philosophical themes. A former director of the Iranian Centre for
Cultural Studies, he is currently serving as his country's Ambassador to Unesco.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
HAFEZ
The golden age of Persian literature
BY CHARLES-HENRI DE FOUCHECOUR
View of the interior of the Regent's Mosque, Shiraz, Islamic Republic of Iran. Hafez was born in Shiraz and spent most of his life there.
SHAMS od-Din Mohammad (c. 1325-1389), known
throughout his life as Hafez, was born and died at Shiraz,
Persia, a town he rarely left during a lifetime of over
sixty years.
The year 1353 was a milestone in Hafez' life. He was near¬
ly thirty years old and his obvious talent had already earned
for him the patronage and protection of the Vizier Qevam
od-Din Hassan. In 1353, however, his protector died and was
replaced in the seat of power by a certain Mobarez od-Din
Mohammad, who imposed a rigorous religious and moral
régime that was totally at odds with the lifestyle of many of
the citizens of Shiraz. Poems by Hafez and others, ironizing
on the tyrant's rigid attitudes, were circulated surreptitiously.
Mohammad's reign lasted eleven years, until the day when
his son, Djalal od-Din Shah Shoja, rose up against him and took
his place. Shoja was to reign from 1364 to 1384. These were
golden years, especially for Persian literature, and it was in this
period, when he enjoyed the patronage of the ruler and of court
and state functionaries, that Hafez achieved his greatest liter¬
ary output. It was not long, however, before Hafez fell out of
favour again, for a period of some twelve years during which,
it appears, he frequented the courts of Ispahan and Yazd.
It remains difficult to establish an accurate chronology of
the poems of Hafez on the basis of these facts. The details of
the poet's life can only be deduced, and then very summarily,
by taking the political life of his period as a starting point and
searching in his works for allusions to that life. What else do
we know of him? Many legends, but virtually nothing of which
we can be certain. In a manner typically Persian, he was very
discreet about himself and he may have lived his true life else¬
where than in the court circles in which he earned his living.
Here, for the record, are a few more facts about him. The
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Seated in a garden in flower, a monarch reads a manuscript as a servant pours him some wine
and musicians play. This miniature from a Divan by Hafez, published in the 16th century,
accompanies one of the poet's ghazals (poems).
date of his death, the year 792 of the Hegira (1389 AD), is
known to us from the introduction to an anthology of poems
by Hafez compiled by an anonymous copyist (later identified
as a man called Golandam). There is no indication that he ful¬
filled any particular function at the court, not even that of poet.
Could it be that he worked as a teacher at a Qur'anic school,
as his pseudonym Hafez ("he who has learned the Qur'an by
heart") has led many, to believe? In Tashkent, there is a
manuscript copy of the works, in five volumes, of the poet
Amir Khosrow Dehlavi (1253-1325) which is signed by Hafez
and dated 1355. Perhaps Hafez was himself working as a copyist
at that time. One of his ghazals (lyric poems of from six to
fifteen couplets) laments the death of a child; Hafez, then, like
Ferdowsi or Nezami, wept for the death of a dear one.
Although the elements that can be gleaned from the poet's
works are insufficient to provide even the skeleton of a
biography, it should be noted that, as the British critic
G.M. Wickens has pointed out, his Divan is much more directly
related than it was once widely thought to the court circles in
which the author moved at the time of its composition, and
which provided the patronage essential to literary life.
The works of Hafez mark the apogee of the lyric poetry
produced by the giants of Persian literature. The borrowings
he made from the works of his forerunners are gracefully trans¬
formed and exemplify his mastery of the finest figures of the
Persian poetic tradition; he conjures with them, turning them
upside down and giving them new life. The intellectual skill
with which he gives meaning and implosive force to all these
14 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
figures, simply and as though at play, is such that a hearing
of a ghazal by Hafez is an occasion of high rejoicing. Each figure
is set within the poem in such a way as to give off an endless
series of allusive ripples. Properly to understand Hafez, there¬
fore, we must first place him as a poet.
A ghazal is a poem, that is to say, in the spirit of the time,
a formal construction within which a number of propositions
can be arranged. This construction has two constituent ele¬
ments: a group of scanning lines with a single rhyme. Each line,
or beyt, has two scanning sections each with the same metre.
The metre is the same throughout the poem. The two sections
of the first beyt rhyme with each other.
Consisting normally of eight to twelve beyt, this poetic form
is to be found among the earliest examples of Persian litera¬
ture that have come down to us. Short, highly elaborated, it
was the preferred form in which to speak of love and to sing
the praises of wine. Because of its formal constraints, the ghazal
is very demanding, obliging the poet to develop a technique
and an artistry by which he will for ever be judged.
It was in the twilight of his career, or, more often, after his
death, that a poet's works were brought together in a compila¬
tion known as a divan. Hafez' Divan consisted basically of
ghazals,which was rather unusual, since Persian poets normal¬
ly write their poems in a variety of forms.
However, as it happens, we do not have the authentic texts
of Hafez. Of course, a ghazal was written down by its author,
but it was also recited aloud, with all the niceties of accentua¬
tion, pauses, voice manipulation and articulation. Thus we have
several scattered ghazals of Hafez that were taken down in¬
dividually in writing during his lifetime. Perhaps the author
of the introduction to the Divan mentioned above was the very
first compiler of his works. It would seem, however, that col¬
lections of Hafez' ghazals circulated both before and after his
death and that, as they circulated, he made alterations to some
of his poems.
The two oldest anthologies (consisting of forty-three and
thirty-six works) date from 1404 and before 1408. The first more
or less complete manuscript of the Divan (455 ghazals) dates
back to 1410. But a century after the death of Hafez, there had
been a multiplication of both manuscripts and ghazals (up to
725) and the manuscript tradition had become corrupted. To¬
day, there are numerous printed editions of Hafez' works. They
include a notable critical edition by Parviz Natel Khanlari, pub¬
lished in Teheran in 1983 and based on fourteen ancient and
reputable manuscripts.
Thousands of studies of Hafez' works have been published
in many languages. The central question that they address has
been, and continues to be, the meaning that should be given
to Hafez' poetry. Is it hedonistic, mystical, or pure lyricism?
As early as the fifteenth century, the historian Khandamir
reported that, one day, Shah Shoja reproached Hafez for the
lack of homogeneity in his ghazals, each of which, he said, spoke
of wine, then of mysticism and then of the Beloved One. To
16th-century miniature depicting the all-conquering Tamerlane
(1336-1405). He may have met Hafez at Shiraz in 1387,
when he was seeking to gather sages and poets around him at
his court at Samarkand.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
jj$k ,
"%.
7'; fX
*s**»
*
Map of Shiraz and its surroundings from "The Book of Highways and
Kingdoms" (Kitab al-masalik wa I-mamalik), by al-Istakhri or
al-Farisi (10th century).
which Hafez is reported to have replied that all this was true,
but that he was the only poet whose ghazals were famous
throughout the world.
Critical studies of his works were first undertaken in the
Ottoman empire and took the form of commentaries. Those
of Sham'i and of Sorouri stressed Hafez' mysticism and by the
sixteenth century, in the time of the Safavids, this had become
the accepted interpretation in both Persia and India. The great
sage Soudi, who also wrote commentaries on the works of Sa'di,
restricted himself to a sober study of Hafez based on grammat¬
ical analysis and, in so doing, gave a lead to European critics.
Modern commentators on Hafez abound. The rich scope
of the ghazals is such that none of the accepted interpretations
has succeeded in excluding the others, an exclusive interpreta¬
tion being taken as a sign of weakness.
Two major elements attract our attention. The first is that,
very often, it is difficult to say whether the person to whom
Hafez is addressing his poem is the object of his praise (mam-
douh), his love (mahboub) or his adoration (ma'boud): prince or
friend, beloved one, or God. The second is that, despite the
seeming disconnectedness of many of the ghazals, they all have
a subtle unity which becomes apparent in the atmosphere they
exude. As a number of commentators have expressed it: the
intertwining of figures and allusions around a few central themes
(Wickens); a symphony of themes (Arberry); a hidden coher¬
ence (Stolz); a delicately rational lyricism (Bausani); a symbol¬
ic structure taken to the third degree and capable of offering
incomparably rich resonances (Lazard).
The ghazal has much in common with a diamond, bringing
out all the sparkle of the poetic imagery accumulated in the
literary tradition, and, with a prism, diffracting all the mean¬
ings with which word sounds have become loaded over the cen¬
turies. The commentator Nasrollah Pourdjavadi has aptly
demonstrated the weight of mysticism with which the word
"glance", for example, has become charged as used in the writ¬
ings of Ahmad Ghazali and retained in the sure hand of Hafez.
And the same applies to countless other imagesa glass of wine,
Noah's Ark, a tavern, a mirror, the blood, the wise man, the
libertine, the face ...
Another commentator, Anne-Marie Schimmel, has rightly
spoken of the circular nature of Hafez' ghazals. The mind of
the poet does not focus on a single point, it transports the
listener into the heart of his own realities and breathes mean¬
ing into them. If Hafez succeeds in speaking to each one of us,
it is because his language encompasses two spheres, the world¬
ly and the spiritual, to both of which he belongs. In Hafez'
writing there is a kind of accomplishment of unification, the
towhid at the heart of all Persian mysticismthe reality of hu¬
man life, of love, of wine and, especially, of the prince are in
fact but a metaphor for spiritual reality.
CHARLES-HENRI DE FOUCHECOUR, of France, is professor of classical
Persian literature (10th-15th century) at the University of Paris III (New
Sorbonne). His most recent publication is a study of the concept of morality
in the Persian literature of the 9th to the 13th century.
16 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
THE ONCE AND
FUTURE REVOLUTION
BY MAURICE AGULHON
THIS year France is celebrating the
bicentenary of the 1789 Revolu¬
tion and, to judge by the long list
of public functions and learned confer¬
ences already announced, the eyes of
most of the world will be upon her.
For France, this is the occasion for an
extra-special national day. Celebrated
each year on 14 July, the official nation¬
al day is, after all, a tribute to the Revo¬
lution to which it is directly linked. The
Bastille was taken by storm on 14 July
1789, and 14 July 1790; the first anniver¬
sary of this event, was also the occasion
of the grand and joyous Fête de la Feder¬
ation (a federation of communes set up
in many towns and villages to replace the
former local authorities). Indeed, the en¬
tire French panoply of national sym¬
bolism refers back to the Revolutionthe
tricolour, adopted in July 1789, the na¬
tional anthem, La Marseillaise, composed
in 1792, and La Liberté, the figure of a
woman wearing the famous red Phrygian
cap which became an official French em¬
blem at this period.
The French people of the day were
very conscious of the fact that France had
existed as a state for nearly a thousand
years and had already produced many
heroic, symbolic figuresgreat kings,
such as Philippe-Auguste, François I or
Henri IV, and great servants of kings,
from Jeanne d'Arc to Richelieu. The year
1789, however, marks the beginning of
the modern age of which the world of to¬
day is the direct continuation.
Since then, French public life has been
ordered by a written constitution and by
laws equally applicable to all. The peo¬
ple, through their elected representatives,
have shared in the exercise of power, and
basic rights and freedoms have been af¬
firmed, at least as an objective or an ideal.
1789 marks, not the birth of France, but
Earthenware figurine (1794-1795) which
represents Liberty bringing down despotism.
	 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
maw
rather her attainment of adulthood, of
reason and of freedom. That 14 July
should have been chosen as the national
day is very indicative of the extent to
which the desire to achieve the political
ideal is inherent in the French national
character.
Revolution as Enlightenment
Why are the events of 1789 seen and
celebrated as being more than simply an
incident in French history? It is because
Revolution is seen as having its own in¬
trinsic value.
What, then, it must be asked, is
"Revolution"? Contemporary thought,
especially perhaps in Europe, defines
Revolution in a rather abstract, formal
way as sudden and violent social and po¬
litical change. If we accept this view, then
the principal alternative to revolution is
reform, that is to say, gradual, non¬
violent change. Today, a humanitarian
ethos, which fortunately is fairly
widespread, encourages us to prefer the
reformer to the revolutionary.
^¿
Im*X4r C*.<tnf «uft?rÁLiÁrt,J«<</«r,A_rrvt,rf A*t, ten Liüm AvùJiffiArJrr )JrúÁ/ifUnur nJ/fiii
A lady from Mainz (in the present-day Fed. Rep. of Germany). Round her waist is a sash bearing
the words "Equality" and "Liberty" in French. Some of the city's intellectuals supported the
ideals of the French Revolution and unsuccessfully attempted to create a Republic of Mainz in
1792-1793.
Contemporary engraving of a Revolutionary committee meeting under the Reign of Terror
(1793-1794). Those who instituted it saw the "Terror" as an arm of national defence in face of
counter-revolutionary intrigues within France and the threat from abroad. 17,000 people are
estimated to have been executed, and 500,000 imprisoned, during this period of the French
Revolution.
This point of view, however, and this
interpretation of words, is quite recent.
Throughout the nineteenth century at
least, Revolution, in political terms, was
defined above all by its content, its
programme and its aims. And the alter¬
native to Revolution was Counter¬
revolution. Revolution thus meant
change for the better, change inspired by
faith in the possibility of progress, great¬
er rationality in the means used to achieve
it and having, as its final objective, great¬
er collective well-being. Just as clearly,
Counter-revolution meant resistance to
change by, and possibly the restoration
of, the former centres of power and
former social groupings, based on the
old values of authority, hierarchy and
tradition, often founded in religion and
often oppressive.
The repercussions that the events of
1789 had throughout the world were due
not to the fact that the change they
brought about was sudden, radical and
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
complete, but because it appeared to be
initiated in the name of positive values:
Liberty, Equality, Happiness, Justice.
France leads the way
Did the France of 1789 deserve her
reputation as an example to the world,
which earned her both hatred and
affection? At first sight this is debatable.
We need go no further back than the
eighteenth century to be reminded that
the idea of applying reason to the govern¬
ment of states or of societies was due to
enlightened despots such as Frederick II
of Prussia, the Empress Catherine II of
Russia, Joseph II, Emperor of Germany,
and Gustav III, King of Sweden. And the
notion that a political relationship could
be modified by the will of the people, or
that a government could be set up whose
legal power was based on the consent of
the governed, had been proclaimed in
1776 by the American Revolution.
The dominant ideas of the French
Revolution of 1789 were undoubtedly
closer to those of the American Revolu¬
tion than to those of enlightened despo¬
tism. Louis XVI could have been France's
enlightened despot. That he did not
take on this role can be put down to inde-
cisiveness, due perhaps to lack of personal
attachment to the philosophy of the day
(he was a pious believer whereas the
rulers named above were all more or
less agnostic) and alsothough this
may have been another aspect of his
religious convictions to his failure to
agree to break with the aristocracy. Thus
Louis XVI soon came to resist a nascent
Revolution that had vested hopes in him
and as a consequence lost control of it.
And, as soon as the Revolution was seen
to be in opposition to the King, the
formerly progressive, reforming Euro¬
pean monarchies became fiercely hostile
to it.
Declared a Republic in 1792, revolu¬
tionary France did not for all that follow
the American model. This was because
France remained a great state, an ancient
and a powerful state, which was soon
obliged by the exigencies of war to
strengthen itself still further.
The distinguishing feature of the
French Revolution was, perhaps, that it
emerged as the first synthesis of the two
great changes that preceded it, as the
point of convergence between the philo¬
sophy proclaimed by the American Revo¬
lution (Natural law and inalienable rights,
including the right to life, liberty, and the
pursuit of happiness) and the techniques
of rational administration that had been
tried out in the Old World.
However this may be, the world was
soon struck by the novelty of the French
experiment. The story is told of how
Kant, the philosopher of Koenigsberg, in
1789 changed the previously unvarying
route of his daily walk so as to hear more
quickly the news from France. And who
has not heard quoted the words of the
German poet Goethe on the night of the
battle of Valmy1: "From this day and
this place dates a new era in the history
of the world."
The French Revolution drew atten¬
tion not only because of its novelty but
also because France herself was promi¬
nent on the world scene. At the end of
the eighteenth century, all that could be
described as being on a world scale, that
is to say, everything relating to world
politics that was collective, rational and
interconnected, was to be found in
Freed slave from the Antilles, wearing around his neck the tricolour ribbon and a plumb level,
both revolutionary symbols. The French National Convention abolished slavery in 1794.
	 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Europe of the North Atlantic. And in
this European world, France was the
most populous country (after Russia), the
most powerful and (after Great Britain)
one of the most advanced economically.
French was the main instrument of inter¬
national communication and the language
of the cultivated élite. This gave France
claim to a literary hegemony paralleling
that of Greece and then Rome. Exorbi¬
tant or not, this pretension, in addition
to other more objective factors, undoub¬
tedly helps to explain why the events of
1789 so strongly alarmed and shook the
world. And although the long periods of
warfare between 1792 and 1815 in some
respects limited the impact of 1789, they
also helped to prolong and propagate it.
The universal Republic
It is undoubtedly the case that,
throughout the nineteenth century,
France, as "the country of the Revolu¬
tion" or, to put it slightly differently,
"the country of the Rights of Man", was
to evoke a degree of enthusiasm among
the supporters of Progress and Liberty
matched only by her own messianic zeal.
Although French was then the univer¬
sal language of the educated élite, the mes¬
sage it bore was unreservedly universal.
Not a word in the text of the Declaration
of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen
was specific, all the assertions it made
were general and therefore could be ap¬
plied to any nation. The notions of
Liberty and Equality were enhanced by
the universality of their formulation.
Even the form of Republicanism adopt¬
ed by the French after 1792 followed the
same pattern. What, indeed, could be
more specific than a monarchy, which be¬
longs to a dynasty with a family name
and a geographical location and origin?
What could be more universal than a
Republic, an abstract term like Liberty
or Justice, and a collégial system directly
applicable everywhere?
By the middle of the nineteenth cen¬
tury, the most idealistic of the heirs to the
French Revolution had come to the con¬
clusion that the French Republic itself
was destined to disappear one day within
a World Republic. In evocation of this
grandiose, Utopian notion I quote not an
isolated dreamer but the most famous and
most venerated poet of his time, a man
whose poems were known by heart in
Republican France and on whom she
bestowed the highest symbolic and
political honoursVictor Hugo.
No anthem could be more revolutiona¬
ry or more universalist than the last poem
of his anthology Châtiments, dated 1853.
Le char de la monarchie ("The Royal Coach") sepia pen and wash drawing by Victor Hugo from
his years of exile.
Within the seed-bed of our present woes,
The Hymen of the brother-peoples grows...
Republic universal, you we acclaim
Today a spark, a- tiny flame,
Tomorrow the sun!
Nobody really believed, either in 1870
or in 1900, that this "Tomorrow" was
very near. But the fact that, by adopting
Hugo as their leading prophet, French
revolutionary thinkers allowed them¬
selves to indulge in such dreams has had
its consequences.
The magnificent tribute paid to Vic¬
tor Hugo at his death, in 1885, by the
Portuguese writer José Maria Eça de
Queirós, has recently (1985) been re¬
published. He had a profound admiration
for Hugo for many reasons both moral
and aesthetic. However, he admits that
Hugo perhaps went too far in his affir¬
mation of French messianism and that it
would be more reasonable to declare that
all the peoples of the world will take part
in "the final liberation of humanity".
This, however, is but a mild reproof and
he nonetheless holds it as evident that:
No country has contributed more than
France to fashioning from the rough bar¬
barian of the sixth century the cultivated
man of the nineteenth. France possesses to
the highest and purest degree the divine
spiritual qualities of sweetness and- light,
which are the most powerful agents ofhu¬
man education. No country, like France,
has taught the world the lesson ofequality;
and equality is, in truth, the surest hall¬
mark of civilization ...
It was in terms such as these that, at
the end of the last century, people out¬
side France were speaking of France. The
vaunted "spreading influence of the
French language and culture", due initial¬
ly to such literary figures as Corneille and
Bossuet, was given a kind of re-charge of
energy by the Revolution, and became as¬
sociated also with Voltaire, Mirabeau and
Victor Hugo.
A controversial model
Times, however, have changed, and
for two kinds of reasons that neither
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Victor Hugo nor his extollers could have
foreseen. The French Revolution had
been a long, troubled affair interspersed
with the vicissitudes and drama of both
external and civil war. Doctrinal strug¬
gles, which at times interrupted the war
between the classes, set the partisans
against one another. Various constitution¬
al systems were tried out, rejected and
replaced, giving those ten years of French
history the appearance of a political test¬
ing ground, throwing up a whole stock
of models for the world to follow.
For a hundred years, in a host of coun¬
tries, many political figures who knew
French and were well informed and pas¬
sionately interested in French history,
borrowed French ideas and terminology:
the Right, the Left, political "clubs",
Jacobin, Montagnard, Thermidorian,
Bonapartist, Chouan, émigré, and so on.
The most popular and most radical phases
of the Revolution, those of the year II
(September 1793-August 1794) of the
Republican calendar, were to be of spe¬
cial interest (directly as well as indirectly
through the subsequent events of 1848
and the Paris Commune of 1871) to
socialist revolutions of the twentieth
century. In them, undeniably, can be seen
a further series of historical effects stem¬
ming from 1789. The French Revolution
could no longer be seen as simply a repe¬
tition of the message and aspirations of
the American Revolution. It became the
first in the series that was to lead to the
Russian Revolution.
This French Revolutionary
print, entitled
Citoyen né libre
("Free-born citizen"),
symbolizes the birth of
the new political man.
A declaration for the third
millennium
ON the occasion of the bicentenary of
the French Revolution, an internation¬
al association of young people has set
itself the task of updating the Declaration of
the Rights of Man and of the Citizen which
was adopted by the French Constituent
Assembly in August 1789. Founded in 1985
by three French students, the Association for
the Declaration of 26 August 1 989 ("AD 89")
is currently rethinking the concept of human
rights for the twenty-first century, taking into
account the radical changes that are trans¬
forming society today.
The founders of the Association unveiled
their project at the United Nations in Geneva
in 1985, on the occasion of the fortieth
anniversary of the foundation of the UN.
Since then, the activities of AD 89 at both
the national and the international level have
centred on two major concerns. First, how can
technological progress be used positively, in
the service of humanity? A second and more
ambitious aim is to formulate a doctrine of
human rights based on humanist concepts of
identity and universality.
The young people from very different
geographical, political and social backgrounds
who make up the Association's over 300
members have been organized into working
groups to study a number of themes, includ¬
ing information, computer science, genetics,
the environment and space.
The Declaration of 26 August 1989, based
on the proposals put forward by these groups,
will be drafted at an Extraordinary Conven¬
tion of European Youth (16-23 July 1989),
when 500 young delegates from the twenty-
one member states of the Council of Europe
and representatives of AD 89 groups all over
the world will meet at the Palais de l'Europe
in Strasbourg.
The Association's founders point out that
"1789 brought the individual and the state
face to face, by assigning to the state a duty
to refrain from any interference with the
individual's physical and moral integrity. But,
paradoxically, the state was itself given the
responsibility of guaranteeing ¡ts own non¬
intervention. We are still suffering from the
consequences of this grave misunderstanding,
by which the arbitration of our rights was en¬
trusted to institutions ...
'"Don't give up!', young people are insist¬
ing, as are men and women of goodwill all
over the world.
"The next bridge to be crossed is to put
human rights back into the hands of mankind,
beyond all frontiers and beyond all cynicism.
This is the basis of a new revolution."
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
From this follow two consequences,
both of which tend to diminish the
impact of the French example. On the
one hand, the only possible link that can
be made between 1789 and its aftermath
and 1917 compromises 1789 in the eyes
of those who dislike radical social
struggles. On the other hand, for those
who have revolutionary aspirations, the
recent model of 1917 seems better suited
than that of 1789, which was formulated
long ago when the industrial revolution
was in its infancy. The internationalism
proclaimed by Marx, Lenin and Trotsky
was to blot out the memory of the
Universal Republic of Mazzini and Hugo.
From the universal to the specific
The Third French Republic, officially
inspired by the 1789 Revolution, acquired
a great colonial empire conquered by
force of arms but with a perfectly clear
conscience, in the sure knowledge that,
under the French flag, the Republic was
spreading a morally and intellectually su¬
perior message, an alluring message that
was both civilizing and French inspired.
This was but the French facet of a more
widespread phenomenon. At the begin¬
ning of the twentieth century, Europe
and North America, that is to say the in¬
dustrialized and developed world of the
day, dominated the other continents by
a combination of their material strength,
their cultural and technological superiori¬
ty and their liberal beliefs.
From this was to stem the last and
most important change in the status of
the Revolution of 1789 in the panorama
of world historyit fell victim to an anti-
Western counter-current.
How do things stand today?
The conditions which existed in the
last century and which promoted the
spread of French revolutionary ideas are
clearly much weakened if not virtually
non-existent.
France no longer ranks as a major
power.
French is no longer the main language
of international discourse.
Europe is no longer the centre of the
world.
The world has become a unified, inter¬
connected, inter-related whole with a bet¬
ter mutual knowledge which has upset
notions of a cultural hierarchy that were
formerly taken for granted. Western
liberalism is no longer held to be the only
acceptable form of civilization. Indeed,
we now speak of civilizations in the plural.
All this puts the message of 1789 in
a truer perspective and lessens its impact.
One has only to see how the great
decolonization movement, or, alterna¬
tively, the great uprising of the Third
World against the imperialism of the
North, has achieved its ends. At first it
seemed to be an uprising against France
(or against Europe and the West) in the
name of her, or their, own liberal
principlesdemanding from those who
had colonized in the name of the Rights
of Man the application to the colonies of
those universal rights. This then deve¬
loped into a desire to affirm national
differences, or national authenticity.
Rather than its own universal values, im¬
perialism found brandished in its face the
particular values specific to the oppressed.
Towards a new universality
Was this to be the final, definitive
moral climate of the world, with equal,
complete, but incommunicable cultures?
If this were so, if the Revolution of 1789
were no more than a fragment of French
folklore, and if the ideal of Liberty were
no more than a historical cover-up for
European hegemony, then there would
be no reason for a magazine such as the
Unesco Courier to exist.
Yet the Unesco Courier does exist, as
does Unesco and the United Nations
Organization and, for better or for worse,
the international community. If a few
common rules and a few common values
are accepted, then this means, at least
implicitly, that a philosophy universal in
application indeed exists.
This moral code of Justice and of
Liberty, this notion of Humanity united
by possession of a rationality common to
all, transcends all religious and national
specificities. For if this were not so, noth¬
ing would hold back the world from the
slippery slope that leads to head-on con¬
frontational crusades and the chaos of war.
Universality, that distant heritage from
the Enlightenment, is indeed the philo¬
sophy implicit in, or at least the working
hypothesis of, our international institu¬
tions. Why should we not recall for a
momentwith no outdated triumphalism,
yet without unnecessary deprecationthat
two centuries ago France was the setting
for a step forward in the journey towards
the making of humanity?
1. On 20 September 1^2, the French Revolutionary army halt¬
ed the invasion of Prussian troops at Valmy, north of Paris.
Editor
MAURICE AGULHON, of France, is professor
of modern French history at the Collège de France.
Among his published works translated into English
are Marianne into Battle: Republican Imagery and
Symbolism in France, 1789-1880 (1981), and
Republican Experiment, 1848-52 (1983), both from
Cambridge University Press.
Allegorical engraving from the French Revolution. Reason triumphant, with the support of
Nature, demonstrates that all men are equal. The black man holds the Declaration of the Rights
of Man in one hand, and, in the other, a decree according freedom to mixed races. At left, the
demons of despotism and injustice are fleeing.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
THE MERMAID OF THE DNIESTER
BY OSYP PETRASH
IN 1772, Galicia, in the western
Ukraine, became a part of the
Austrian Habsburg monarchy.
The people of the new province
were severely oppressed and re¬
mained largely illiterate. Intellectual
life was impoverished by the fact
that no books were published in the
Ukrainian language; only a rich tra¬
dition of folk songs and legends
nourished the spiritual life of the
people.
At that time a number of Slav
peoples (Czechs, Serbs and Croats)
were undergoing a national and cul¬
tural revival. The first indications of
a similar revival also began to ap¬
pear in Galicia. In 1833, a clandes¬
tine circle was organized in Lvov, the
capital, with the objective of reviv¬
ing the national culture of the
Ukrainians of Galicia. Its founders
were three friends, Markiyan Shash-
kevych (1811-1843), Ivan Vahylevych
(1811-1866) and Yakiv Holovatsky (1814-1888). Instead of speaking
German or Polish, as was the rule when societies held meetings, they
used their native Ukrainian language, and discussed the culture and
destiny of their people.
The activities of the Shashkevych circle constituted not only a
literary phenomenon, but a social and democratic movement. Its
greatest achievement was the publication of an almanac entided Rusal-
ka Dnistrovaya ("The Mermaid of the Dniester"), which was the
first collection of Ukrainian literature to appear in the western
Ukraine.
Shashkevych prepared a collection of literary works and folk songs,
originally entitled Taria ("The Dawn") and submitted the manuscript
to the board of censors. As there was no censor of Ukrainian books
in Lvov, Toria was sent to Vienna, where Varfolomei Kopitar, the
censor of Greek and Slav books, made positive comments on the
manuscript but pointed out that it was "purely political" and sent
it back to Lvov. Under the new title of Rusalka Dnistrovaya, the
almanac was then sent to the Hungarian censor at Pest. He allowed
it to be published and 1,000 copies appeared in Buda in 1837. One
factor which had helped to make publication possible was
Holovatsky's friendship with the Serbian writer Georgi Petrovich and
other leading figures in the Slav revival.
What were the contents of this almanac that the Habsburg authori¬
ties found so disturbing? Its 150 pages open with an epigraph by
the Czech poet Jan Kollar: "Not sad eyes, but the hands of the wor¬
ker bring hope." These words were meant as an appeal to readers
not to give way to pessimism about the destiny of the people, but
to work towards its cultural and national awakening. The preface,
A copy of the Rusalka Dnistrovaya (The Mermaid of the Dniester") which
escaped the clutches of the censor. This was the first collection of
Ukrainian literature to appear in the western Ukraine.
by Shashkevych, is a manifesto call¬
ing for the revival of Ukrainian liter¬
ature in Galicia. It lists Ukrainian
publications which appeared in
Moscow, St. Petersburg and Kharkov.
Most of the almanac consists of
Ukrainian folk songs, as if confirm¬
ing Kollar's claim that "Folk songs
are the most solid foundation of edu¬
cation. An element of culture, the
support of national identity, they
protect and beautify language." A
chapter is devoted to original writ¬
ing by Shashkevych, Vahylevych and
Holovatsky. There follow translations
of Serbian folk songs, extracts from
"The Kraledvorski Manuscript" by
V. Hanka, an article by Shashkevych
on the importance of historical
monuments in spiritual life, exam¬
ples of the vernacular Ukrainian lan¬
guage, a short description of the
ancient manuscripts of Saint Basil's
monastery, Lvov, and a review of a
collection of marriage songs and folk customs.
The Lvov censor objected both to the contents of the almanac
and its use of popular speech and phonetic orthography. He decided
that its distribution should be prohibited. About 800 copies were con¬
fiscated and legal proceedings were brought against the publishers.
But Rusalka Dnistrovaya was not doomed to perish. Some 200 copies
were widely distributed with the help of friends of the circle in Buda.
Rusalka Dnistrovaya was intended by its authors to lay the foun¬
dations of a Ukrainian literature in tune with the ideological and
aesthetic principles proclaimed by Shashkevych in his work "The
Alphabet": "Written language is for every people its life, its way of
thinking, its other self; it should be born and grow among people...
it must not become like the bird of paradise which is said to be
without feet and is thus condemned to stay in the air for ever. Litera¬
ture is a vital need of the people."
The Rusalka was a powerful voice which spoke out about the
lives and national dignity of the Galician Ukrainians. Mainly con¬
sisting of works by Slav authors, it became a literary landmark in
the Slav world. It is significant that the ideas of the Serbian writer
and scholar Vuk Karadzic (1787-1864), a leading figure in the Slav
Renaissance, should have inspired Shashkevych's circle, and that the
lexical and orthographical principles set forth by Karadzic should have
been the basis of the phonetic spelling system used in the almanac.
"The Mermaid of the Dniester" thus has an important place in the
Slav Renaissance as a whole.
OSYP PETRASH, of the Ukrainian SSR, is the author of a number of studies on
the history of 19th-century Ukrainian literature.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
POLLUTION UNLIMITED
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
MOST human beings seem to be
quite unaware that the small
blue planet on which we live
is very fragile. Although, some twenty
years ago, general concern began to be
expressed about the state of our natural
environment, we continue to inflict
irreversible damage upon it.
The atmosphere, our water resources,
the soil, even our food, are all contami¬
nated, largely as a result of our own ac¬
tions. Rather than the quality of life, the
level of industrial development achieved
is taken as the yardstick by which we
judge our civilization. We create deserts
and cause floods by destroying our
forests. Our homes and work-places are
polluted by the tobacco we smoke, by
harmful particles from the materials we
use and the emanations from ill-adapted
fireplaces. We can no longer afford to ig¬
nore the warnings we are given byíour
most capable and conscientious scientists.
If we do not want to condemn our chil¬
dren to a life of stagnation on a decaying
planet, it is time for us to reflect upon
the consequences of our daily actions.
Once' the atmosphere was pure. Now
the quantity of polluting gases emitted
into the atmosphere exceeds Nature's ca:
"pacity to absorb them. The equilibrium
is broken and we are threatened by an
ever-lengthening list of ' perilsthe
"greenhouse effect", the gap in the ozone
layer, climatic change, a rise in the sea
level.
This copper smelting plant at Douglas,
Arizona, was closed down in January 1987 by
order of the United States Environmental
Protection Agency. Noxious gases and particles
from its smokestacks had caused untold
damage to the environment of the American .
southwest and of neighbour country Mexico.
What is happening? The more the
world becomes industrialized, the more
energy is consumed. No source of ener¬
gy, however, is completely innocuous.
Combustion is a chemical reaction in
which carbon, sulphur and nitrogen ox¬
ides are produced as well as all kinds of
molecules, some of which are highly
toxic. Since wood contains chlorine, an
ordinary domestic fire gives off dioxin (a
highly toxic substance made notorious by
the Seveso disaster1), in minute quanti¬
ties only, it is true, but which augment
the other pollutants present in the air,
especially in poorly-ventilated dwellings.
And the use of fossil fuels (coal, oil, natur¬
al gas), and the need for them; are
continually increasing. Industry, trans¬
port and heating systems emit a constant
stream of pollutants into the atmosphere
in quantities which, though they may
seem small compared to the volume of
the Earth's atmosphere, are sufficient to
have a marked effect.
The greenhouse effect
The most widespread pollutant is car¬
bon dioxide, annual emission of which
has increased from 90 million tonnes in
the last century to 5,000 million tonnes
today. The two World Wars and increases
in the price of oil have slowed this up¬
ward trend somewhat, but the United
Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP) estimates that output of carbon
dioxide may double by the year 2050.
Carbon dioxide is the principal cause of
the greenhouse effect. It is transparent to
incoming radiation from the sun which
penetrates the Earth's atmosphere,
although a large proportion of the ultra-
	 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
violet rays are absorbed by the ozone
layer, situated some 10 to 50 kilometres
above the Earth's surface. On the other
hand, it traps the infra-red radiation
reflected back by the Earth, like the glass
of a greenhouse, thus causing a heating
up of the atmosphere .
Other gases also contribute to the
greenhouse effect. These include the chlo-
rofluorocarbons (CFCs), 700,000 tonnes
of which we release to the atmosphere an¬
nually through the use of aerosols,
refrigerators, and air conditioners and the
manufacture of plastics and the cleaning
of electronic components.
With a lifetime in the atmosphere of
about one hundred years, a CFC
molecule is 20,000 times more efficient
at trapping heat than is a molecule of car¬
bon dioxide, so, proportionately to their
This Canadian scientist is analysing the composition of tiny bubbles of air trapped in glacier ice at
the beginning of the 19th century.
Desert scene in North Dakota. The three-month drought that hit the central United States last year could presage the onset of global warming.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
concentration in the air, CFCs contrib¬
ute much more to the greenhouse effect
than does carbon dioxide. Furthermore,
CFCs are capable of destroying ozone.
The gap in the ozone layer observed over
the Antarctic has become-40 per cent larg¬
er since 1957 and another gap has ap¬
peared above Australia and New Zealand.
The B type ultra-violet rays which can
now pass through these gaps and reach
the Earth's surface are thought to be the
primary cause of some skin cancers.
Nitrous oxide, another gas which
contributes to the greenhouse effect, has
a life of nearly 200 years. It is released by
microbial fermentation in the soil and the
burning of wood and fossil fuels. Of the
12 to 15 million tonnes released into the
atmosphere annually, nearly 10 per cent
is due to the use of nitrogen fertilizers.
Other forms of atmospheric
pollution
Until recently, the industrialized
countries were the main propagators of
atmospheric pollution, but they are being
rapidly caught up by countries which are
becoming industrialized. In Eastern Eu¬
rope and China, for instance, factories
and non-nuclear power stations draw
their energy from cheap, locally-
produced coal. The combustion of coal
releases sulphur dioxide to the
atmosphere. When mixed with rain and
carried by the wind it can travel thou¬
sands of kilometres. The acid deposits it
produces attack forests and buildings and
can also be harmful to man.
The alarm was sounded in 1970 by the
Scandinavian countries where "acid rain"
has destroyed all life in many of their
lakes. These countries soon realized that,
since the prevailing winds were from the
west, the sulphur dioxide being deposit¬
ed on their territory came from British
and American factories. Winds from the
east, however, were the source of the
sulphur dioxide deposited on the Feder¬
al Republic of Germany, which was in
turn responsible for deposits reaching the
forests of the Vosges in France.
In addition to burning tree leaves and
pine needles, these acid deposits also seem
to make the forest floor itself sterile.
Furthermore, they are causing severe
degradation to historic monuments that
were still intact at the beginning of the
century, such as the Parthenon in Greece,
the Coliseum and Venetian palaces in
Dhaka inundated. The catastrophic flooding to which Bangladesh is subject may be in part due to deforestation on the slopes of the Himalayas.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Italy, the Cathedral of Strasbourg in
France, the Taj Mahal in India, and vari¬
ous buildings in the United States. As
these few examples show, the phenome¬
non occurs wherever industrial concen¬
tration is accompanied by heavy
automobile traffic releasing exhaust gases
rich in sulphur dioxide.
Exhaust gases also contain lead,
emissions of which are estimated at
450,000 tonnes annually and are harmful
to health. The struggle for lead-free petrol
is still far from being won.
Soiling the soil
Other heavy metals pollute not only
the atmosphere but also the soil, ground¬
water and the water table. The quantities
involved annually include: mercury,
11,000 tonnes, cadmium, 5,500 tonnes,
and arsenic, 78,000 tonnes. At present we
are handling over seven million different
chemical products and new ones are con¬
stantly being produced. Production,
which amounted to 250 million tonnes
in 1985, appears to be doubling every
seven or eight years.
Although the accumulation of small
quantities of these products, dangerous
though it may be, passes unnoticed,
major disasters, which are becoming
more frequent,- draw our attention to
them. In 1959, for example, at Minama¬
ta, in Japan, mercury which drained into
the water table resulted in 400 deaths and
left 2,000 people seriously ill or deformed.
Farmers continue to lavish fertilizer on
their fields to obtain ever greater yields,
while the nitrates these fertilizers contain
pollute the adjoining water resources.
Another scandalous example of pollu¬
tion is the stocking of dangerous toxic in¬
dustrial wastes on the ground in humid
areas with permeable soils. The industri¬
alized countries do not know what to do
with their industrial wastes and allow
themselves to be cajoled by unscrupulous
agents who are prepared to take these
wastes off their hands and dispose of them
in poorer, less populated countries where
environmental protection is not a priori¬
ty consideration.
Beauty discountenanced. Air pollution and acid rain have defaced this once-graceful marble maiden
(420-415 BC), at the Acropolis, Athens.
As they become more industrialized,
the developing countries are experiencing
similar problems. The factories and
refineries installed around the Bay of
Hann, at Dakar, have caused a level of
pollution of the sea which is causing the
Government of Senegal great concern.
The techniques necessary to master this
problem are costly and take a long time
to learn. An equally dangerous and daily
occurrence, is pollution by untreated hu¬
man wastes. Illnesses linked to water pol¬
lution account for 25,000 deaths per day,
mainly in the developing countries.
Climatic change
It is in these countries that the hydro-
logical cycle has been the most disturbed,
owing to the deforestation of mountain
areas to make way for agriculture, to sup¬
ply the timber trade or to provide wood
for fuel. After the trees have been cut
down, rain water streams down the slopes
carrying with it the cultivable topsoil and
causing flooding. A recent example has
been the serious flooding in Bangladesh,
which was due to deforestation in Nepal.
28 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
If the practice of firing the bush continues
in Guinea, the Fouta-Djalon mountain
massif, where floods alternate with
seasonal periods of drought, may well
soon cease to be "Africa's water tower".
The danger for the world is very real.
Twenty hectares of forest disappear every
minute and it is estimated that 160 mil¬
lion hectares of woodland are degraded
annually. Clearing Amazonian forest
impairs the Earth's "green lung". For
carbon dioxide is taken up not only by
the oceans, but also by plant life which
transforms it, by photosynthesis, into
carbon hydrates. The fewer trees there
are on the planet the more carbon dioxide
there will be in the atmosphere, and this
can only aggravate the greenhouse effect.
If, as most experts predict will happen,
global warming, a process that has already
begun, drives the planet's average temper¬
ature up by 2°C to 4.5°C, melting of
continental glaciers could cause ocean
levels to rise from 40 to 120 centimetres.
The great deltas of the Ganges, the Nile
and the Mississippi would disappear, as
would the Netherlands and a host of
islands of the Pacific and Indian Oceans,
including the Maldives, Tuvalu and
Tonga.
A joint counter-attack
The fight against pollution comes up
against powerful economic and social
interests. Old, heavily polluting factories
which could not afford to install costly
anti-pollution devices would have to close
down, leaving their workers unem¬
ployed. The installation of catalytic
converters would increase the cost of
automobiles and discourage buyers, thus
dealing a blow to the automobile indus¬
try. The new propellant gases for aerosols
now under study are more expensive than
the existing chlorofluorocarbons. Renew¬
able energy sources which could perhaps
replace fossil fuels, such as solar and tidal
power, are still far from being competi¬
tive. Only nuclear energy can supply
cheap and abundant electricity, thanks to
which certain highly toxic wastes can be
destroyed in very high temperature
incinerators.
Unfortunately, no country wants to
stock on its territory nuclear wastes,
which have an extremely long radioactive
life. Furthermore, it is impossible to
eliminate the risk of recurrence of acci¬
dents such as those that occurred at Three
Mile Island in the USA in 1979 and at
Chernobyl in the USSR in 1986. Final¬
ly, the further the cost of oil falls, the less
justification there is for economizing on
energy consumption and the more pol¬
lution will increase.
Nevertheless, the international com¬
munity seems determined to take action.
Negotiations on global reduction of the
emission of sulphur oxides opened in
1979 under the aegis of the United
Nations Economic Commission for
Europe. Seventeen countries undertook
to reduce their emissions of sulphur oxides
by 30 per cent within twenty years. At
Vienna, in 1985, and in Montreal, in
1987, a Protocol was signed concerning
the production of chlorofluorocarbons.
It was agreed that the heaviest users of
CFCs would reduce their consumption
by 50 per cent by 1999. An extended time
limit was agreed for the developing coun¬
tries, whose annual consumption
amounts to only 0.30 kilograms per cap¬
ita. However, since the ozone layer is
being damaged at a faster rate than that
predicted by experts before the Protocol
was signed, it may be questioned whether
these undertakings are sufficient.
One of the steps being taken by
Unesco for the conservation of the en¬
vironment is the creation, within the
framework of its Man and the Biosphere
(MAB) Programme, of a network of
Wind power is harnessed to pump water for irrigation for these garden-smallholdings in Malta.
Greater use of non-polluting, renewable energy sources would help to reduce atmospheric pollution.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
biosphere reserves. This work is being
undertaken in collaboration with the
United Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP), the Food and Agriculture
Organization (FAO) and the Internation¬
al Union for the Conservation of Nature
and Natural Resources (IUCN). There
are now 273 biosphere reserves in some
seventy countries. Some of these reserves,
such as the Kavkazskiy reserve in the
USSR, are specially equipped to monitor
atmospheric pollution.
Conservation in daily life
Quite apart from the efforts being
made at the national and international
levels, each one of us should become
more aware of the consequences of our
actions. Throwing a mercury or a silver
oxide battery away on a rubbish tip could
lead to the pollution of a cubic metre of
soil or 500 litres of water. Emptying out
the engine oil from an automobile on to
the ground could pollute 5,000 cubic
metres of water. Each time we press the
button on a CFC-powered aerosol we
contribute to the destruction of the ozone
layer. To respond to the state of emer¬
gency call put out by the world's scien¬
tists, we must all react, and react quickly.
Pollution knows no boundaries. The
greenhouse effect could have dire conse¬
quences for the environment and for
human societies. It is already late in the
day both for study and for action.
Yet the stakes are highthe survival of
the Earth itself. .
1. In July 1976, as a result of a leak in a reactor at a chemi¬
cal plant producing chlorophenol, a cloud of poisonous
vapour spread over the town of Seveso, near Milan, kill¬
ing hundreds of birds and small animals and causing respira¬
tory problems, burns and other skin lesions among many
of the inhabitants. Editor
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a French-American
journalist with a special interest in environmental
topics. For the last four years she has been
responsible for training African journalists in the
fields of health and the environment for Unesco's
West and Central Africa News Agencies
Development Project (WANAD).
At Donon in the Vosges, France, a research worker examines a batch of young pine trees that have been exposed to acidic fog.
30 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
REDISCOVERING
'THE ISLANDS OF THE MOON'
BY ANDRE LIBIOULLE
BECAUSE of a paradox inherent in
the history of the islands on which
they live, the people of the Como¬
ros archipelago have only had access to
their age-old cultural heritage since 1979,
when the first public library containing
a collection of historical and contem¬
porary sources relating to their identity
was opened at Moroni, the capital.
This tropical archipelago of four
islandsNgazidja (Grande Comore),
Mwali (Mohéli), Nzwani (Anjouan) and
Mahoré (Mayotte)has cast a spell on
travellers ever since the first voyages of
Arabs and Persians to what they called
the "Islands of the Moon" (al-Kamar)
because of the moonlit radiance of their
rugged shores. Sixteenth-century Por¬
tuguese explorers opening up the Spice
Route first made the islands' existence
known to the West.
Navigators must have been attracted
to this volcanic archipelago at the north
ern end of the Mozambique Channel in
the Indian Ocean by its mild climate. But
they were surely also drawn by the
singularity of the population, a mixture
of Bantu, Arab and Persian peoples living
in closely-knit communities, whose
tempestuous history was marked by
rivalry between local chiefs and forays by
pirates. Epic folk tales chronicled the
myths and legends of a culture left
astonishingly intact between its two great
neighboursthe African mainland (Dar
es-Salaam is some 700 kilometres away),
and Madagascar, whose northern coast
lies 300 kilometres from the Comoros.
Why should the Comoros be isolat¬
ed? During the colonial period, from 1912
to 1946, when the islands were ad¬
ministered from Madagascar as a French
colony, they were considered of negligi¬
ble importance because they were so
small. This archipelago which neither
forms part of Madagascar nor of the
Creole-speaking world was overlooked
by researchers. The little that was known
about the Comoros was filtered through
Madagascar, as in the "Comoros room"
established half a century ago in the
Tananarive Museum.
The isolation of the Comoros was
further intensified by the dispersal of
ancient writings and legal, historical and
ethnographic documents into east Africa,
where the Swahili civilization (of which
the Comoros constituted a kind of ocean
outpost) had become an Anglo-Saxon
sphere of influence.
The Comorianslike the people in
the outside worldthus did not know
their own country. In order to discover
their cultural identity, they had to take
matters into their own hands, a task
which was all the more urgent since eco¬
nomic instability, dependence on foreign
aid and imports of essential commodities
had made their country vulnerable.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
In October 1978 the Islamic Federal
Republic of the Comoros was consti¬
tuted, including all the islands except
Mayotte, which remained a French
dependency. A decree was issued the
following year creating a National Centre
of Documentation and Research on the
Comorians (CNDRS), whose facilities
include a library and a national museum
and archive as well as a research centre
on oral traditions.
The multidisciplinary work of the
CNDRS is concentrated on research on
the history and communities of the
archipelago. The Centre and its special¬
ized associations have succeeded in
motivating people to study traditions
which were erased during the colonial
period. These deeply rooted traditions
can be used fruitfully when they are
adapted to modern circumstances.
The guiding principle is that a link
should be created between the CNDRS
and village communities, where groups of
young peoplewho are the best catalysts
in that they are aware of tradition yet
sensitive to modern technology would
bring about an attitude change, not with
the idea of blind acceptance of the trans¬
fer of technology but rather of cultural
transformation based on a "revival" of
the past.
None of the pilot schemes of the
CNDRS, such as the establishment of
associations to safeguard historic or
archaeological sites, the restoration of
ancestral dwellings, the setting up of read¬
ing rooms and small ethnographic collec¬
tions, the reconstitution of forgotten
dances or traditional musical instruments,
are secondary to urgent social needs,
although they may seem to be so. They
are all intended to enrich the present by
looking to the cultural heritage of the
past.
In its early days the CNDRS received
aid from many quarters, including
Unesco and the Agency for Cultural and
Technical Co-operation; and a number of
European and African countries have
contributed either to the purchase of
video equipment or to the training of
technicians. The Centre is now seeking
In a school at Ikoni, near Moroni, the capital of the Comoros, children recite to the rhythm of
tambourines in preparation for the Maulid, the Islamic festival that marks the birthday of the
Prophet.
to improve its facilities to train Comori-
an experts to an international level, par¬
ticularly in the natural and environmental
sciences. Moreover it is essential that a
CNDRS unit should be set up on each
island in order to disseminate information
and identify new needs.
Two progressive educational institu¬
tions, the National Institute of Education
(INE) and the National School of Higher
Education (ENES), are working with the
Centre. The INE aims to establish the
historical and linguistic content of school-
books and promote appropriate teaching
methods, while the ENES wishes to
encourage students to produce original
work on oral traditions, epidemics, botany
or village communities.
Thus a cultural identity, a real inspir¬
ation to the future of the Comoros, is
consciously and progressively taking
shape.
ANDRE LIBIOULLE, a Paris-based Belgian
journalist and producer of radio programmes on
cultural topics, has worked in the Comoros on
behalf of the Agency for Cultural and Technical
Co-operation. He has recently contributed articles
to a Larousse chronicle of the 20th century.
32 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
EDUCATIONAL PLANNERS
GO BACK TO SCHOOL
IN a modern building not far from
Unesco's Headquarters in Paris,
forty-four men and women from all
regions of the world are following a
rigorous nine-month training programme
covering the design, implementation and
evaluation of strategies and plans for the
development of education.
All the participants are specialists who
hold key positions in educational plan¬
ning or training in their respective coun¬
tries. One has been responsible for the
evaluation of Rwanda's educational re¬
form programme; another is deputy
director of -educational planning in
Oman; a third is a section chief at the
State Education Commission in China; a
fourth is responsible for the development
of basic education in Brazil.
They have been selected from a large
number of applicants to participate in
the twenty-fourth annual training
programme organized by Unesco's Inter¬
national Institute for Educational
Planning (HEP). The Institute, which
celebrated its twenty-fifth anniversary in
1988, has so far trained some 850
specialists from 129 countries. It is
acknowledged as the world's leading
training institution in its field. .
The annual training programme
acquaints participants with the most
recent ideas and practices concerning the
relationships between the educational
system and economic, technological,
social and cultural development. It is also
designed to improve their knowledge of
methods of administering educational
systems as well as diagnosing and forecast¬
ing techniques.
In practice this means that a statisti¬
cian from Ghana, grappling with a
problem of cost analysis and budgetary
processes, in his country's technical
education sector, can compare his
experiences with those of colleagues from
Brazil, Finland and Indonesia. An
economist from India, who is particu¬
larly concerned with the relationships
between education, employment and the
labour market, is able to discuss her
problems and learn from some of the
solutions already worked out by her
counterparts in Canada, the People's
Democratic Republic of Korea or
Senegal.
The first phase of the 1988-1989
programme took place last September in
the home countries of the participants,
who began to study specially-produced
teaching materials designed by the
Institute, to update their knowledge of
basic educational planning concepts and
techniques.
The training methods at the Institute
are based on team work and the active
involvement of each participant in exer¬
cises which, as far as possible, reflect
actual working conditions. Simulation ex¬
ercises, seminars, and work in small
groups are combined with lectures, dis¬
cussions, study visits, computer work and
the presentation of experiences in differ¬
ent countries.
During the final stage of the
programme, scheduled for April and
May, each participant will have the
opportunity to make an in-depth analy¬
sis of an educational problem concerning
his or her country.
The annual training programme is
only one component of the IIEP's train¬
ing activities, however. Each year the
Institute organizes several intensive train-
Participation by nationality in HEP training programmes and countries in which research and studies have been undertaken.
A Participants in Annual Training Programme Visiting Fellows Research Studies
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
ing courses on particular aspects of educa¬
tional planning and administration, such
as the evaluation of educational systems,
the utilization of microcomputers in
educational planning or the financing of
vocational and technical education. These
courses, lasting a maximum of four or
five weeks, are held not at the Institute's
Paris Headquarters but in different coun¬
tries. Each one caters for some thirty
planners from the country in which it is
held and often also a few participants
from neighbouring countries. So far,
fifty-one of these intensive courses have
been held, in countries ranging from
Jamaica to Thailand and from Burundi to
China, providing specialized training to
some 1,800 participants.
HEP offers a whole spectrum of other
training opportunities, including an
individually-tailored visiting fellows
programme and a series of workshops
and seminars. Yet training is only one
side of the Institute's activities: an equal
share of its resources goes towards
research.
In carrying out its research
programme, IIEP's basic aim is to in¬
crease understanding of the social, eco¬
nomic and political aspects of education
in order to facilitate planning for educa¬
tional development and reform. In the
twenty-five years since its foundation, the
Institute has carried out research projects
on a wide range of topics in most of
Unesco's Member States. Some of these
projects have been focused on the orien¬
tation and the organization of educational
planning processes in individual coun¬
tries; some have been concerned with de¬
veloping the methodologies used in
educational planning; and others have
examined the implications for planning
of specific policy issues.
The Institute is currently drawing
together the results of over twenty case
studies undertaken during the past five
years on subjects as diverse as education¬
al training policy for the computer indus¬
try in Mexico, the effects of literacy
programmes in Kenya and the Republic
of Tanzania, and the role and utilization
of the information base in Tunisia.
All these studies are reviewed and
evaluated by the HEP in preparation for
the Institute's third main activitythe
dissemination of new concepts, methods
and techniques in educational planning
to individuals and institutions in all
Member States.
A constant effort is made to take
account of the needs of different
categories of clientele. IIEP's traditional
public, which includes decision-makers,
planners and administrators, researchers,
trainers and teachers, is continually
changing and expanding to include
development economists, sociologists,
political scientists and other specialists in
the many branches of the social sciences.
The broad objective of the dissemina¬
tion programme is to ensure that this
clientele is informed of the evolution of
ideas, concepts, practices and techniques
of planning and administration; that prac¬
titioners are kept up to date on impor¬
tant research concerned with their
specialities; and that the results of signifi¬
cant national experiences in the field are
brought to their attention. Special care is
taken to satisfy the needs of the Institute's
clientele in developing countries, who are
very often starved of relevant publica¬
tions and information.
Photo credits
Front cover: Banri Namikawa/Unesco. Back
cover, page 12: Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris.
Page 2: Luc Joubert ©Archéologie Vivante,
Paris. Page 4: ©D. Gander-Gosse & J. Ber,
Paris. Page 5: © Ali Tiuab, Karachi. Pages 6-7:
Source: Sur les routes de la soie: Le grand voyage
des oeuvres d'art, by Cécile Beurdeley, Editions du
Seuil, Paris/Office du Livre, Fribourg. Page 6
(above left & right): © British Museum,
London; (below left): © Ostasiatiska Museet,
Stockholm. Page 7 (above left): © Metropolitan
Museum of Art, Fletcher Fund, New York;
(above right): © Dominique Darbois, Kabul
Museum; (below right): © École Française
d'Extrême-Orient, Paris. Pages 8, 9: © Monique
Pietri, Paris. Page 10: © Freer Art Gallery,
Washington, D.C. Page 11: ©Romanian
Literary Archives. Page 13: ©Mali, Paris.
Pages 14, 18 (below): © Bibliothèque Nationale,
Paris. Page 15: © Edimédia, Paris/British
Library, London. Page 16: © Forschungs
-bibliothek, Schloss Friedenstein, German
Dem. Rep. Page 17: ©Réunion des Musées
Nationaux, Paris/Musée des Beaux-Arts de
Rouen. Pages 18 (above), 21, 22: © Bulloz,
Musée Carnavalet, Paris. Page 19: © Bulloz,
Bibliothèque des Arts Décoratifs, Paris. Page 20:
© Bulloz, Maison de Victor Hugo, Paris.
Page 23: ©Vasil Pilipiuk. Pages 24-25, 26
(above), 28: Ted Spiegel © Rapho, Paris. Page 26
(below): I.L. Atlan ©Sygma, Paris. Page 27:
Chip Hires © Gamma, Paris. Page 29: © Muñoz
de Pablos, Paris. Page 30: Christhn Weiss
© REA, Paris. Pages 31, 32: © Libioulle, Paris.
Page 33: Map: © IIEP, Paris.
BOOKSHELF
The Last Romantic: Mthail Eminescu, trans, by
R. MacGregor-Hastie. Unesco Collection of Repre¬
sentative Works.University of Iowa Press, Iowa
City, 1972.
Pather Panchali: Song of the Road, by Bibhuti
Bhushan Banerji, trans, by T.W. Clark & Tarapada
Mukherji. Unesco Collection of Representative
Works. George Allen & Unwin, London,
1968/Lokamaya Press, London, 1987.
The Fatal Shore, by Roben Hughes. Collins Harvill,
London, 1987.
A Treasury of Turkish Folktalesfor Children, retold
by Barbara K. Walker. Linnet Books, The Shoe
String Press, Connecticut, 1988.
The Muslim Contribution to Mathematics, by Ali
Abdullah Al-Daffa'. Croom Helm, London, 1977.
Desktop Publishing, by Tony Bove, Cheryl Rhodes
& Wes Thomas;
Publishingfrom the Desktop, by John Seybold & Fritz
Dressier, Bantam Books, New York, 1987.
Why Preserve the Past? The Challenge to Our Cultu¬
ral Heritage, edited by Yudhishthir Raj Isar. Unesco,
Paris/Smithsonian Institution Press, Washington,
D.C, 1986.
The Historic City ofTaxila, by Ahmad Hasan Dani.
Unesco, Paris/The Centre for East Asian Cultural
Studies, Tokyo, 1986.
Migration ofTalent: Causes and Consequences ofBrain
Drain,Three Studiesfrom Asia, edited by Yogesh Atal
& Luca Dall'Oglio. Unesco Principal Regional
Office for Asia and the Pacific, Bangkok, 1987.
Acid Earth! The Global Threat ofAcid Pollution, by
John M'cCormick, 1985; Urban Land and Shelterfor
the Poor, by Patrick McAuslan, 1987; Beyond the
Woodfuel Crisis: People, Land and Trees in Africa,
by Gerald Leach & Robin Mearns, 1989. Earthscan
Publications, London.
World Prospects: A Contemporary Study, 2nd edition,
by John Molyneux & Marilyn MacKenzie. Prentice-
Hall Canada, Scarborough, Ontario, 1987.
The International Foundation Directory, 4th edition,
edited by H.V. Hodson. Europa Publications,
London, 1986.
THE FRENCH REVOLUTION
AND EUROPE
An exhibition on the events
of 1789-1799, organized by
the Council of Europe
with the support of
Mr. François Mitterrand,
President of the French Republic,
is to be held at the
Grand Palais, Paris,
from 18 March to 28 June 1989.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
r n
The Courier
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor In your country.
(See list below; names of distributors In countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
ALBANIA. 'Ndermarrja e perpjes se librit', Tirana ARGENTINA. Librería el
Correo de la Unesco - EDILYR. SRL. Tucuman 1685. 1050 Buenos Aires
AUSTRALIA. Books only Educational Supplies Pty Ltd . P O Box 33.
Brookvale 2100. NSW. Periodicals Dominie Pty Subscriptions Dept . P O
Box 33, Brookvale 2100. NSW Sub-agents United Nations Association of
Australia Victorian Division, 328 Flinders Street. Melbourne 3000 Hunter
Publications, 58a Gipps St . Collmgwood, Victoria 3066 AUSTRIA Gerold
and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN United Schools Interna¬
tional. Arab Regional Office, P O Box 726. Bahrain. The Arabian Agencies
and Distributing Co , AI Mutanabi St . PO Box 1 56, Manama BANGLADESH
Kanm International. GPO Box No. 2141 64 / 1 Manipun Para, Teigaon,
Farmgate, Dhaka BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Cave Hill Campus, P O Box 64, Bridgetown BELGIUM Jean de Lannoy, 202
Ave duRoi 1060 Brussels BOTSWANA Botswana Book Centre. PO Box 91
Gaborone BRAZIL. Fundaçâo Getulio Vargas, Serviço del Publicaçoes
caixa postal 9 042-ZC-05 Praia de Botafogo 188, Rio de Janeiro (RJ) 2000,
Books only Imagem Latinoamericana, Av Paulista 750, 1 andar, caixa postal
30455, Sao Paulo CEP 01051 BULGARIA Hemus. Kantora Literatura,
boulevard Rousky 6, Sofia BURMA. Trade Corporation no (9), 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon CANADA Renoul Publishing Co Ltd. 1294
AlgomaRoad. Ottawa. Ontario K1B3W8 (Stores 61 Sparks Street, Ottawa.
21 1 Yonge St . Toronto Sales office 7575 Trans Canada Hwy Sie 305, St
Laurent, Quebec H4T 1V6 CAMEROON. Cameroon Book Centre, PO Box
123, Limbe. Commission Nationale. BP 1600. Yaounde CHILE. Editorial
Universitaria S A , Departamento de Importaciones M Luisa Santander
0447. casilla 10220. Santiago. Editorial 'Andres Bello'. Av, R Lyon 946,
Casillo 4256, Santiago de Chile. Dipublic, Antonio Varas 671 , 2o piso, casilla
14364, Correo 21. Santiago CHINA. China National Publications Import and
Export Corporation, P O Box 88, Bei|ing COLOMBIA. Instituto Colombiano
de Cultura (Colcultura), Carrera 3A, n° 18 / 24, Bogota. Books only Librería
Buchholz Galena, Calle 59. No, 13-13. Bogota CYPRUS. MAM'. Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avene, PO Box 1722. Nicosia CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S N T L ,
Spalena 51-113 02. Prague 1, For Slovakia only Alfa Verlag -Publishers.
Hurbanovo nam 6 893 31 Bratislava. PNS-UED. Jmdnsska 14. praha 1.
Slovart, GottwaldovoNam6. 80532 Bratislava DEM. REP.OFYEMEN 14th
October Corporation. PO Box 4227. Aden DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-
OG Tidssknfiservice. 35 Norre Sogade. DK-1970 Kobenhavn K
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Librería Blasco. Avenida Bolivar, No. 402. esq
Hermanos Deligne, Santo Domingo EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). Un¬
esco Publications Centre. No 1 TalaatHarb St .Cairo ETHIOPIA. Ethiopian
National Agency for Unesco, PO Box 2996. Addis Ababa FINLAND.
Akateemmen Kirjakauppa. P O Box 128. SF-00100 Helsinki Suomalamen
Kiqakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuia 2 01640 Vantaa 64 FRANCE. Librairie de
I Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans Periodicals only Unesco CPD /
V-1. rue Miollis 75015Pans GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchex-
port, Postfach 140, Lenmstrasse 16. 7010. Leipzig FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY For the Unesco Courier Mr H Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kuner
Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57. D5300 Bonn 3, UNO-Verlag. Simrockstrasse 23,
D-5300 Bonn 1. S Karger GmbH Verlag Angerhofstrasse 9 Postfach 2
D-8034 Germering / München For scientific maps only Geo Center. Postfach
800830, 7000 Stuttgart 80 GHANA. Books only Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd , PO Box 195, Accra, Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd . PO 7869 Accra,
The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast. The University Bookshop of Legón. PO Box 1 . Legon Periodicals only
Fides Entreprises, PO Box 14129. Accra GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom GREECE. Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore, 4 Nikis
Street, Athens, John Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers P O
Box 10073. 541 10 Thessalomki Greek National Commission for unesco. 3
Akadimias Street. Athens HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co . 13-15 Lock
Road. Kowloon, Federal Publications (HK) Ltd . Tokwawan. Kowloon. Hong
Kong Government Information Services, Publication Section. Hong Kong,
Periodicals only Beaconsfield House 6th floor Queen s Road Central. Victor¬
ia HUNGARY Kultura-Bushimport-ABT. P O B 149-H-1389 Budapest 62
ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co, HF Hafnarstraeti 9. Reykiavik
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd , Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038
17 Chitaranjan Ave . Calcutta 13. 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road Madras 2
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP), 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd ,
Bangalore 560001. 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 Sub-agents
Oxford Book and Stationery Co . 1 7 Park St . Calcutta 70016. Sandia House,
New Delhi 1 1 0001 INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers. 29,
J 1. Oto Iskandardmata 111. Jakarta Indira P T , Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37.
Jakarta Pusat IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco. 1 188 Englab
Ave. Rostam Give Building, PO Box 11365-4498 Teheran 13158
IRELAND.Pe/iodíca/soníy The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd .POBox
43A, Walkmstown, Dublin 1 2. Booksonly TDC Publishers. 1 1 North Frederick
Street, Dublin 7 ISRAEL. Literary Transactions. Inc , c/o Steimatzky Ltd ,
P O Box 628. Tel Aviv. ABC Bookstore Ltd . P O Box 1 283, 7 1 Allenby Rd ,
Tel Aviv 61000 ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionana Sansoni, S p A ), Via
Lamarmora 45. Casella Postale 552. 50121 Florence, via Bartoimi 29, 20155
Milan, FAO Bookshop, via délie Terme di Caracalla, 00100 Rome JAMAICA.
University of the West Indies Bookshop, Mona. Kingston 7 JAPAN. Eastern
Book Service Inc , 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku. Tokyo 1 13 JORDAN
Jordan Distribution Agency. PO Box 375. Amman Periodicals only Jordan
Book Cerjtre Co Ltd . PO Box 301. AI Jubeiha, Amman KENYA East African
Publishing House. PO 30571. Nairobi. Africa Book Services Ltd, Quran
House, Mangano Street, PO Box 45245. Nairobi KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco. P O Box Central 64. Seoul KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co , Ltd POB 2942. Kuwait. Periodicals only Faralalla Press
Agency. P O Box SAFA 4541 Kuwait LEBANON Librairie Antoine A Naufal
et Frères. BP 656, Beirut LESOTHO Mazenod Book Centre, PO Mazenod,
Maseru LIBERIA National Bookstore, Mechlin and Carey Streets PO Box
590, Monrovia. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd . PO Box 286. Monrovia -
LUXEMBOURG Books only Librairie Paul Brück, 22. Grande-Rue, Luxem¬
bourg, Periodical Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 1022, Luxembourg MALAWI
Malawi Book Service, Head Office, PO Box 30044. Chichm, Blantyre 3
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop Kuala Lumpur
22-11 MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic St, Valletta MAURITANIA GRA LI -
CO MA , 1 rue du Souk X, Avenue kennedy Nouakchott MAURITIUS
Naianda Company Ltd . 30 Bourbon St , Port-Louis MEXICO. Librería El
Correo de la Unesco, Actipán 66, Colonia del Valle. Apartado postal 61 164,
06600 Mexico DF MONACO. British Library, 30 Bd des Moulins. Monte
Cario MORROCCO. Librairie 'Aux belles images', 282 ave Mohammed-V,
Rabat. Librairie des écoles, 12 ave, Hassan-It, Casaglanca. Société cherifien-
ne de distribution et de presse, SOCHEPRESS. angle rues de Dînant et St
Saens, BP 13683. Casablanca 05 MOZAMBIQUE. Instituto National do Livra
e do Disco (INLD). avenida 24 de Julho, 1 921 r / d Io andar, Maputo NEPAL.
Sa|ha Prakashan Polchowk. Kathmandu NETHERLANDS Books only
Keesing, Boeken B V , Hogehilweg IG.Postbus 1118, 1 000 BC Amsterdam
Periodicals Faxon Europe, PO Box 197. 1000 AD Amsterdam
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N V . PO Box 200, Willem-
stad. Curaçao. NA NEW ZEALAND Government Publishing, P O Box
14277-Kilbirnie. Wellington NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of He, The
University Bookshop of Ibadan. P O 286. The University Bookshop of Nsukka,
The University Bookshop of Lagos, The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum. POB 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1.
Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret. Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo
3 Periodicals only NarvesenA/S.LitteraturtJenesten.P O B 6125Etterstad,
N 0602 Oslo 6 PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P O Box No 729, Lahore 3. Unesco Publications Centre. Regional Office for
Book Development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P O Box
8950, Karachi 29 PANAMA. Distribuidora Cultura Internacional, Apartado
7571. Zona 5. Panama PHILIPPINES National Book Store Inc . 701 Rizal
Avenue. Manila POLAND Orpan-lmport, PalacKultury I Nauki, Warsaw, Ars
Polona-Ruch. Krakowskie Przedmiescie No 7 00-066 Warsaw PORTUGAL.
Dias& Andrade Ltda Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70 Lisbon ROMANIA.
ARTEXIM Export- Import, Piata Scienten. no 1, PO Box 33-16, 70005
Bucharest SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan, Olaya Mam Street, Ibrahim Bin
Sulaym Building, Riyadh SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd Kingsgate
House PO Box 1 31 , Mahe, National Bookshop, PO Box 48, Mané SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay College, N|aia University and Sierra leone Diocesan
Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Righteous Enterprises, P O Box 562,
Kallang Basin Post Office. Singapore 9133 SOCIALIST PEOPLE'S LIBYAN
ARAB JAMAHIRIYA General Establishment for Publishing, Distribution and
Advertising, Souf AI Mahmoud. St . PO Box 959, Tripoli SOMALIA. Modern
Book Shop and General, PO Box uàô, Mogadiscio SPAIN. Mundi-Prensa
Libros SA. apartado 1223, Casteiló 37. Madrid 1: Ediciones über, apartado
17. Magdalena 8 Ondárroa (Vizcaya). Donaire. Ronda de Outeiro, 20,
apartado de correos 341. La Coruña, books only Librería Castells. Ronda
Universidad 13 y 15. Barcelona 7. Librería de la Generalität de Catalunya,
Palan Moga, Rambla de los Estudios 118, 08 002 Barcelona SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop. 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, POB 244,
Colombo 2 SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, PO Box 1118, Khartoum
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco. PO Box 2943,
Paramaribo SWEDEN. A/ B C E, Fritzes Kungl Hovbokhandel, Regenng-
sgatan 12, Box 16356. S-103 27 Stockholm 16, For the Unesco Couner
Svenska FN Forbundet. Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104. 65 Stockholm, For
periodicals only Wennergren-Williams AB. Nordenf lychtsvagen 70. S- 1 04, 25
Stockholm. Esselte Tidsknftscentraien, Gamla Brogatan26. Box 62 -101. 20
Stockholm SWITZERLAND Europa Verlag. 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich. Librairies
Payot in Geneva Lausanne. Basle. Berne. Vevey, Montreux. Neuchâtel and
Zurich SYRIA. Aleppo University Books Establishment University of Aleppo,
Aleppo TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. POB 9030, Dar-es-
Salaam THAILAND. Nibondh and Co Ltd . 40-42 Charoen Krung Road.
Siyaeg Phaya Sri. PO Box 402, Bangkok, Suksapan Panit. Mansion 9
Ra|damnern Ave , Bangkok. Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road.
Bangkok. ROEAP. PO Box 1425, Bangkok 10500 TRINIDAD AND TOBA¬
GO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St , St Clair. Port-of-
Spain TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A S . îstiklài Caddesi. No 469, Posta Kutusu
219, Beyoglu. Istanbul UGANDA Uganda Bookshop. POBox 7145 Kampa¬
la UNITED ARAB EMIRATES. Maktabat al Maktaba. POBox 15408 AI Am.
Abu Dhabi UNITED KINGDOM. H M Stationery Office. PO Box 276, London.
SW8 5DT. H M S O Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham. Bristol. Third World Publications 151 Stratford Road. Birming¬
ham B1 1 1 RD. for scientific maps only McCarta Ltd . 1 22 King's Cross Rd
London WC1X 9DS UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. Bernan-UNIPUB,
Periodicals Department, 461 1 -F Assembly Drive Lanham, MD 20706 4391
URUGUAY. Ediciones Trecho. S A . Maldonado 1092. Montevideo USSR.
V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga Ul Dimitrova 39. Moskva 113095
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost. Mica 30/1 1, Zagreb, Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitar-
ieva 2, Lubl|ana. Nolit, Terazije 13 / VIII. 1 1000 Belgrade, periodicals only
Jugosolvena Kniga, PO Box 36, YU 11001 Belgrade ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co of Zambia Ltd . P O Box 2664. Lusaka
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd . 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare
A window open on the world
Published monthly in 35 languages by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
A selection in braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700, Paris.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Director: Baheat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca,
Aracelli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille edition:
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Liaisons with non-Headquarters editions:
Solange Belin
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Non-Headquarters editions:
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Sri Ram (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Abdul Manaf Saad (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chínese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Seham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from trie Unesco Courier", plus date of issue,
and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name.
Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions
of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the
Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche by:
(1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris;
(2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head, Inc., Ill West 40th Street,
New-York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
AU correspondance should be addressed
to the Editor-in-chief in Paris
L J
Imprimé en France (Printed in France) -
Dépôt légal: Cl - Mars 1989.
Photogravure-impression: Maury-Imprimeur S.A.,
Z.I. route d'Etampes, 45330 Malesherbes.
ISSN 0041-5278
N° 3 - 1989 - OPI - 89 - 1 - 466 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Alexander the Great av depicted in an Indian miniature. The Macedonian general's invasion of India in the
4th century BC influenced Indian culture by initiating contacts with the Gracco-Koman world (sec article p. 4).
]]>
</page>
</document>
