<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="184442eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
on the worU
la: 40 cents - France: 1.20 F
1870-1970
7TÏT
education
science
culture
THE ART
JAVA
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
© Syria
Women of Palmyra
These three women, their drapes mingling gracefully in a single arabesque-like pattern, were
carved 1,900 years ago on the entablature surmounting the great temple of Baal at Palmyra,
Syria. Another fragment of the same relief shows bearers of offerings and the camel cara¬
vans to which the city owed its fame and fortune as a trading centre. Palmyra (the Tadmor,
"city of palms", of Antiquity) dates back some 4,000 years, but reached the zenith of its
influence and splendour in the first centuries of the Christian Era. Its imposing ruins rising
above the desert 1 50 miles northeast of Damascus still recall this period when it was one of
the greatest cities of Asia Minor.
1 JUIL18?Û
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
JULY 1970
23RD YEAR
PUBLISHED I IM 13 EDITIONS
English Japanese
French Italian
Spanish Hindi
Russian Tamil
German Hebrew
Arabic Persian
U.S.A.
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e
Annual subscription rates: 20/-stg..; $4.00
(Cañada); 12 French francs or equivalent;
2 years : 36/-stg. ; 22 F. Single copies : 2/-stg. ;
40 cents ; 1 .20 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in August and September when it is bi-monthly (1 1 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German. Arabic,
Japanese, Italian, Hindi, Tamil, Hebrew and Persian. In the
United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is Indexed monthly In The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature, published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York, and In Current Con¬
tents - Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy Paris-7e, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
Ronald Fenton (Paris)
Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Francisco Fernández-Santos (Paris)
Georgi Stetsenko (Paris)
Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneirn El Sawi (Cairo)
Takao Uchida (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
K. D. Bhargava (Delhi)
: T.P. Meenakshi Sundaran (Madras)
: Alexander Peli (Jerusalem)
Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Howard Brabyn
French Edition: Louis Frédéric
Spanish Edition : Simon Izquierdo Perez
Photo Editor: Olga Rodel
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief
English Edition
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Hindi Edition
Tamil Edition
Hebrew Edition
Persian Edition
12
16
18
22
28
33
34
LENIN AND EDUCATION, SCIENCE, CULTURE
by Marie-Pierre Herzog
LENIN AND THE DEVELOPMENT OF SCIENCE
By Mstislav Keldysh
EDUCATION
KEY TO SOCIAL TRANSFORMATION
By Vsevoiod Stoletov
LENIN AND THE CULTURAL RIGHTS
OF MINORITIES
By Lauri A. Posti
MF YOU CAN READ
TEACH YOUR NEIGHBOUR'
THE ART AND MONUMENTS OF JAVA
By Hiroshi Daifuku
HUNTING CLUES
TO AN ANCIENT SUPERCONTINENT
By Daniel Behrman
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
UNESCO NEWSROOM
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
Women of Palmyra (Syria)
Cover
Portrait of Lenin detail from a
photograph (reproduced here in full)
taken in Moscow in 1920, showing
Lenin talking to the famous English
writer H.G. Wells.
Photo © APN
Detail of one of the bas reliefs that
embellish the walls of the temple of
Mendut, built near the great stupa
of Borobudur, in Central Java,
Indonesia, and contemporary with
it (late 8th century A.D.).
Photo © Louis Frédéric - Rapho
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
At the fast session of the Unesco General
Conference held in Paris in November, 1968, the
Director-General was authorized to "take certain
steps to commemorate the hundredth anniversary
of the birth of Lenin and, in particular, to organize
a Symposium with the theme 'Lenin and the
development of science, education and culture'."
(Resolution 3.112).
Arranged in collaboration with the National
Commissions of Finland and the U.S.S.R., the
symposium was held at Tampere, in Fin/and,
from 6th to 10th April. Specialists from twenty
countries were invited to take part on a personal
basis.
This issue of the "Unesco Courier", which is
largely devoted to Lenin and his contribution tú
science, education and culture, has been prepared
within the framework of the same resolution of the
Unesco General Conference.
In the following article, Madame Marie-Pierre
Herzog, Director of the Unesco Division of
Philosophy, who organized the symposium at
Tampere, analyzes the differing points of view
expressed by the participants in the course of
their debate.
4
The commemorative
stamp Issued by the
Finnish government
to mark Lenin's
centenary and the
Tampere Symposium
organized by Unesco.
Commemorative stamps
have also been issued
in Cameroon, India
and the Soviet Union.
by Marie-Pierre Herzog
Director, Division of Philosophy, Unesco
T
HE Symposium held at Tampere from 6th
to 10th April, 1970, brought into relief various aspects
of the thought and action of Vladimir llyich Lenin in
the fields of science,, education and culture.
Everyone at the Symposium found the choice of
subject both interesting and novel. Discussions began
with a general recognition of the importance attached
personally by Lenin to the continual quest for know¬
ledge and his desire to combine theory with practice
in his activities.
From here the Symposium took up the subject in
greater detail. The participants noted that Lenin's
early works already reflected his keen desire to apply
marxist theory to Russia as it actually was in those
days. He wanted to apply it with equal cogency to
the ambiguous attitude of the intelligentsia, the lot
of the peasants, the situation of the workers, support¬
ed by all the statistics, facts and figures he, could
marshal. In this he showed himself to be far removed
from the effusions of the populists and the general
confusion of thought of the time.
Many speakers praised, first, his discernment when
faced with the problems of the science of his day
(the foundations of which had been rudely shaken
by the discovery of radioactivity and the workings
of the electron), second, his broad view, expressed
in Materialism and Empirio-Criticism in 1909, of the
possible future evolution of physics as demonstrated
by his famous dictum: "the electron is as inexhausti¬
ble as the atom", and, thirdly, the distinction he made
between the content of the different, changing scien¬
tific theories concerning the nature of matter, and
the materialist theory, as such, which could itself
never change. (See article page 6.)
A dialectic theory of matter, elaborated by the Japa¬
nese scientist Professor Shoichi Sakata, was pre¬
sented in this connexion by Professor Yoichi Fujlmoto,
Professor of Physics at the Science and Engineering
Laboratories of Waseda University, Japan, in relation
to recent work on elementary particles, in particular
mesons.
It was shown that, while not properly speaking an
educationalist, Lenin gave immense importance to
education, not only in the fight for literacy instituted
by the, famous decree, but also under its second form
in which knowledge, assimilated into the very
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
LENIN
and education
science
culture
substance of life, becomes synonymous with culture.
Some participants, however, recognized in Lenin,
above all, his ability as a man of action, but cautioned
against attributing qualities that he did not possess
to this most modest of men.
"His genius lay in his talent for decision-making as
well as in his acute understanding of political
situations and his eye for the opportune moment and
the practical possibilities they opened up," said Pro¬
fessor Alfred G. Meyer, Director of the Center for
Russian and East European Studies of the University
of Michigan, U.S.A.
Professor Meyer stressed Lenin's unsentimentality
and matter-of-factness and his resolve, despite all
need for polemics, always to look the truth straight
in the face, to face what he called "living life" (zhivaya
zhizn).
"Lenin", Professor Meyer said, "is indeed the one
who would be my first choice if I had to select that
person who has had the most profound impact on
our century. There is no doubt that the revolution he
accomplished and the society he started to build have
had repercussions in all areas of life, including
science, education and culture. My own appraisal
would be that these have not always been positive
repercussions..."
After speaking at length of the great simplicity
and modesty of Lenin, Professor Meyer expressed
his doubts about the manner in which Lenin's perso¬
nality and accomplishments were portrayed in certain
quarters.
Other participants at the Symposium recalled
Lenin's attitude towards problems of minority groups
and languages and stressed his actions in this respect
(see article by Professor Posti of the Faculty of
Philosophy of the University of Helsinki, Finland,
page 16). Finally, Professor Cheikh Anta Diop, Direc¬
tor of the. Radiocarbon Laboratory of the Fundamental
Institute of Black Africa in Dakar (Senegal), examined
the relationship between the history of African
societies and dialectical materialism.
But the focal point of the debate was Lenin and
culture. A discussion began among the participants
to define more clparly the reservations Lenin had
made about "proletarian culture" as conceived by
Bogdanov and the Protelkult, that is, a culture arising
entirely from the. proletariat and wholly created by it.
It was carefully pointed out that Lenin had never
subscribed to such views, not for reasons of personal
taste which, in any event, he would not have intro¬
duced into the debate,, but for general reasons. It
was emphasized .that Lenin considered of capital im¬
portance for the new culture what he described as
"the assimilation of the bourgeois legacy", in other
words, open acceptance of the great cultural trea¬
sures in mankind's cultural past.
"After coming to power", said Professor Alexis
Rumyantsev, Vice-President of the Academy of Scien¬
ces of the U.S.S.R., Moscow, "it is in the field of
culture that the real revolutionary problem lies." In
a study prepared for the Symposium, Professor Ru¬
myantsev had stated: "By culture Lenin meant the
fundamental principles of human behaviour, deeply
rooted in thinking, in the mind. He saw in culture the
organic basis of human actions, their social, psycho¬
logical and intellectual mechanism. That is why, for
Lenin, the social quality of the economy, of the, appa¬
ratus of state, depended necessarily on culture."
Here it is clear that the word culture is taken in a
sense which goes far beyond its usually accepted
meaning and in this context has much broader and
wider connotations and implications.
As Jean-Jacques Marie, Professor of the Lycée.
Voltaire in Paris, stated: "Lenin did not defend culture
as a precious object or as a relic to be admired, but
as a living means to awareness, that is to say, as
a factor in the proletariat's struggle for emancipation
destined ultimately to produce a culture superior to
the existing bourgeois culture, which it would not
destroy but outstrip by integrating it into a world
from which would have vanished the exploitation of
man by man, opposing classes and their struggle,
the division between manual and intellectual work,
all of which have left their mark on the finest pro¬
ducts of bourgeois culture."
Professor Roque Gonzalez Salazar, of the Inter¬
national Studies Centre, College of Mexico City,
Mexico, added that one of Lenin's great merits was
to "have seen clearly that man must base his creative
power on the efforts of his fellows and even on those
of preceding generations."
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
by Mstislav Keldysh
President of the Academy
of Sciences of the U.S.S.R.
Lenin
and
the development
of science
w
6
HEN the first man-made
satellite Sputnik 1 was launched
into space, on October 4, 1957, it focus¬
ed an excited world's attention on the
immense possibilities open to mankind
in an entirely new scientific era.
Yet this first space venture also
marked a watershed ¡n the develop¬
ment of science in the U.S.S.R. and
wjien we look back towards the early
days of the 1917 revolution and the
years that followed it we can distin¬
guish one hand already sowing the
seeds of this triumph of Soviet science
the hand of Vladimir Lenin.
Despite the complex problems with
which he was faced in the early days
following the revolution, Lenin, from
the first, realized the importance of
the role that science was to play in
the rebuilding of his country.
Indeed, all of Lenin's work as a
politician, statesman and public figure
is inseparable from science. As a
scientist myself, what has always
struck me in Lenin's intellectual work
is the manner in which his theoretical
conclusions were invariably based on
a scientific analysis and critical
examination of all the facts and data
available. One other special attribute
of his researches was the close
connexion he always maintained
between theoretical formulations and
their practical application.
A perfect example of the way in
which Lenin grasped the essence of
modern science is to be seen in his
analysis of the cardinal philosophical
problems raised by the progress made
in physics.
The turn of the century, as we know,
was marked bv a series of discoveries
which were to lead to a complete
revolution in physics, and eventually
to the development of the physics of
today. Thus, the advances in electro¬
dynamics opened the way to the theory
of relativity and the discovery of new
and more precise space-time relation¬
ships. Research into the theory of
opaque bodies and the photo-electric
effect made possible the formulation
of the quantum theory.
These new ideas and theories, to
which were soon to be added the
discovery of radioactivity and radium,
could no longer be fitted into the
19th century concept of physics or into
the electro-magnetic concept of the
universe that had succeeded the
mechanical concept.
Serious difficulties arose. In parti¬
cular, the conclusion of the classic
electron theory, according to which
electrons had mass and electro¬
magnetic characteristics, was inter¬
preted by many mechanistic and posi¬
tivist physicists of the time as a verit¬
able "disappearance of matter".
Research scientists spoke heatedly of
"the big crisis in physics".
In 1909, Lenin entered the scene
with his work Materialism and Empirio-
Criticism. This was his reply to the
philosophical problems raised by the
latest scientific discoveries. Lenin
pointed out that the crisis in physics
perceptible at the beginning of the
century was just the first step
challenging "the old laws and basic
principles", and that the change affect¬
ed the postulates of physics that had
been thought unalterable. The crisis,
Lenin said, marked the beginning of
a complete revolution in physics.
Our knowledge is relative, Lenin
wrote, and knowledge of nature pro
gresses by gradual Improvement ¡n
scientific thought approaching ever
closer to the truth. The great dis¬
coveries in physics at the turn of the
century prove one thing, he said,
namely, the inadequacy of the mecha¬
nistic concept. Matter does not
"disappear" but manifests itself in
new, more concrete forms, hitherto un¬
known, providing science with a
deeper understanding of the physical
properties of matter and the inter¬
relations existing between its different
states and conditions.
"To say that matter has disappear¬
ed" Lenin wrote, "is merely to state
that the limits of our knowledge of
matter have disappeared and that our
understanding has deepened. The
properties of matter that formerly
appeared absolute, unalterable and
immutable . . . have disappeared and
are now recognized as being relative
and inherent only in certain states of
matter."
He stressed that "... the one and
only 'property' of matter that philoso¬
phical materialism recognized is that
it is an objective reality, existing apart
from our consciousness". And here
he pronounced his famous philo¬
sophical dictum: "the electron is as
inexhaustible as the atom; nature is
infinite . . ."
I do not think that at that time a
single physicist anywhere suspected
that the electron had other properties
than those of possessing mass and
an electric charge. But in the half
century that has elapsed since then,
the electron has been revealed to have
such multiple properties that the thesis
put forward theoretically by Lenin is
CONTINUED PAGE 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Photo © APN
Lenin's real name was
Vladimir llyich Ulyanov.
He was born at Simbirsk,
now Ulyanovsk, on the banks
of the Volga, on April 22, 1870.
Top right, Jthe house in which
he spent his childhood.
Right, the Ulyanov family
his mother Maria Alexandrovna
and father llya Nikolayevich
with their children. Lenin,
seated far right, was nine
years old at the time. Above,
at the age of seventeen
Lenin graduated from high
school with high honours.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Banished from the University
of Kazan, a central Volga
town, for his part in the
student movement, Lenin
settled in Samara, in 1889,
where he started to study
the works of Marx and engaged
in revolutionary activities. This
photograph, left, was taken
in 1891 and was attached
to his application for permission
to take his law examinations.
He qualified as a lawyer
at the University of
St. Petersburg the same year.
Arrested in 1895 at St Petersburg as a leader
of the League of Struggle for the Liberation
of the Working Class, Lenin was Imprisoned
in this cell, below, for 14 months. Later he was
exiled for three years to the Siberian village
of Shushenskoye, right, where he married
another political exile, Nadezhda Krupskaya.
DEVELOPMENT OF SCIENCE (Continued)
In 1917 one research centre, today 210
8
now recognized as having been widely
and brilliantly proved.
The discovery that electrons were
capable of behaving as waves opened
up a fantastic new world to physicists.
In the 1930s the positron was iden¬
tified. The electron revealed a new
property: united with a positron, it was
transformed into a photon. There
followed the discovery that the elec¬
tron is an active protagonist in the
phenomenon known as weak inter¬
actions and so is also a bearer of a
specific charge of these interactions.
Thus Lenin's thesis has shown itself
to be a great deal more than a mere
prophecy. It has become a philoso¬
phical postulate of the investigation of
the infinitely small. All the later
developments of physics have corro¬
borated the validity of this principle,
confirming the "inexhaustibility" of the
electron, and, more generally, the
inexhaustible physical properties of
matter itself.
Research carried out in the field of
nuclear physics and, later, the physics
of elementary particles has made it
possible to identify a number of these
particles, to dissect the structure of
nucléons, and to understand the nature
of their interactions in the overall
structure of matter. Viewed in this
context, Lenin's words, formulated in
1922, take on special significance:
"Natural science is progressing with
such speed and undergoing such revo¬
lutionary upheavals in every field that
the sciences cannot do without philo¬
sophical conclusions."
Thus we see that not only did Lenin
help to provide an answer to the
difficulties facing science in his day,
but he also foresaw, decades in
advance, many of the trends of pre¬
sent-day scientific development. These
have ranged from research into the
structure of matter and problems of
chemical energy to the study of biolo¬
gical agents.
In Materialism and Empirio-Criticism
Lenin proclaimed that the new dis¬
coveries in science, far from invali¬
dating dialectical materialism, strength¬
ened its philosophical tenets, and
re-affirmed that "modern physics . . .
engenders dialectical materialism."
Thus Lenin's contributions to the
philosophy of science, and the trends
in scientific development which he
clearly discerned, are as meaningful
today as they were yesterday, and
continue to have an important bearing
on the methodology of contemporary
science. The importance of Lenin's
contribution to science cannot there¬
fore be over-emphasized, and the
theories he developed have proved
to be of fundamental importance for
both the social sciences and the
natural sciences.
Lenin was inspired by the exact
sciences when he evolved his basic
idea of the theory of knowledge.
From the outline traced by Marx, he
elaborated and developed the theory
of reflexion which affirms that human
thought reflects the external world and
can in turn act upon and change it.
Thus the social sciences occupied
a predominant place in Lenin's think¬
ing, and he accorded them a primary
role in the renovation df the Soviet
State. In 1918 he worked for almost
two months on the Government's
decree to establish the Academy of
Social Sciences. This was the be¬
ginning of the social science research
institutions ¡n the U.S.S.R. which were
to flourish with the rapid development
of education and the cultural revolution
generally in the new type state.
Lenin was deeply conscious of the
tremendous importance of science for
development. He kept a permanent
eye on all matters having to do with
the organization of scientific research
in the Soviet Union, and lost no oppor¬
tunity to promote the maximum use of
science and technology to improve the
standard of living of the population.
He was convinced that under the
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
, WIK
new regime the social role of science
had changed too. "In the past", he
said, "the genius of man's mind was
used to provide the benefits of techno¬
logy and culture to a part of the
population, depriving the others of the
basic essentials, education and pro¬
gress. Now, all the wonders of
technology, all the conquests of
culture are to be the heritage of all
people . . ."
Lenin saw this new role of science
as part of its democratic function in
society and affirmed that the new
State had a fundamental part to play
to guarantee its development by pro¬
moting scientific research as well as
the practical uses of science.
It was with this in mind that great
impetus was given to research work.
Even in the most difficult years of the
civil war and amidst economic ruin,
scientific research centres and
research workers were encouraged by
Lenin to the maximum.
I am thinking particularly of the
decree of the Council of People's
Commissars which bears his signature
and which entrusted a special com¬
mittee headed by Maxim Gorki with
the task of "ensuring, within the
briefest possible delay, the best
conditions for the research work being
carried out by Academician Pavlov
and his collaborators."
We know that Lenin gave his per¬
sonal attention to the work of such
scientists as Constantin Timiryaziev,
P. Lazarev, I. Gubkin, and many others.
And his interest in new inventions and
discoveries never flagged. Thus, for
example, when the giant iron ore
deposits were discovered in the
"magnetic anomaly" that the Kursk
region represents, Lenin urged that
prospecting operations be undertaken
at once. He gave his support to
research efforts to perfect a system
of hydraulic extraction of peat; and
he did not fail to recognize the
far-reaching significance of the experi¬
ments being carried out at the radio-
technology laboratory of Nijni-Novgo-
rod. He saw that radio, which he
described graphically as "a newspaper
without newsprint" and "the eliminator
of distance", would rapidly become a
powerful medium of cultural diffusion.
Lenin gave his unstinted encourage¬
ment to the development of aviation
and other new technologies. During
his lifetime were created the Central
Institute of Hydro-dynamics (TSAGI)
which later played a leading role in the
development of Soviet aeronautics,
and the National Optical Institute,
which was the beginning of the Soviet
optical industry.
The activities of the U.S.S.R. Aca¬
demy of Sciences received his special
attention. For Lenin, the participation
of this scientific institution in the
economic development of the country
was of capital importance. As early
as April 1918, the Soviet government
decided to make a considerable
increase in the budget of the Academy
to enable it to launch a series of large-
scale experiments and giant prospect¬
ing campaigns.
It was at about this time that Lenin
drew up his "Outline Plan for Scientific
and Technical Undertakings" in which
he placed a number of top priority
problems before the Academy of
Sciences, including a request for a
study of the natural resources of the
U.S.S.R. with a view to their rational
utilization. From this point on the
exploitation of natural resources was
to become a dominant theme of Soviet
science.
In his "Outline Plan" Lenin put for¬
ward the notion of centralized national
planning, to be implemented for the
first time ever in the Soviet Union.
He urged "the drawing up of a plan,
with the help of scientists and techno¬
logists, for the complete electrification
of Russia". This initiative was to
take shape in 1920 as the GOELRO
Plan which was both the nation's first
economic plan and its first national
research project. It called for the
development of the Soviet economy
on the basis of a nationwide electri¬
fication programme.
In fact it was Lenin who elaborated
the principles of political economy on
which the entire structure of the Soviet
socialist state reposed. It was he
who put forward as the nation's chief
task the triple objective of industrializ-
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
DEVELOPMENT OF SCIENCE (Continued)
Photo © APN
In January, 1905, workers in St. Petersburg,
with their wives and children, went to present
their grievances to the Czar but were shot down
in cold blood by the Imperial troops, above.
Lenin, in exile abroad, was already working
with his party for revolutionary change in Russia.
The massacre at the czarist palace marked
the beginning of the first Russian revolution.
The incredible hardship of life in czarist
Russia made it fertile for revolution.
Conditions were so harsh that there
were not only "Volga Boatmen" but also
"Volga Boatwomen" (below).
Photo © APN
ation, co-operative farming and the
cultural revolution. Lenin pointed to
the fact that Industrialization without
electrification was impossible and
announced that "all the conquests of
the human sciences, of human techno¬
logy, all the discoveries and know¬
ledge of scientists and specialists
must be pooled for the one common
objective of the united people."
His plan for co-operatives was
Lenin's answer to the complex problem
of small agricultural holdings and their
conversion under socialist reform to
communal ownership. His ideas on
the socialization of agriculture were
based on a careful study of compa¬
rative agricultural data in Russia and
other countries, including the United
States and the nations of Europe.
Lenin's view of the preponderant
role of the Academy of Sciences in
bringing about a revolutionary change
in the advancement of the country was
to mark its entire later development.
Within half a century, the little coterie
of scientists it had been composed of
before the revolution, became a scien¬
tific centre of the very highest impor¬
tance which was to direct the develop¬
ment of the natural and social sciences
throughout the nation.
In 1917 the Academy had only one
research centre which consisted of a
few laboratories and museums. Today
it controls 210 scientific establishments
including 160 research institutes all of
which are contributing to the develop¬
ment of modern science. With a
complement of some 250,000 research
workers, the Academy's personnel has
multiplied one hundredfold and its
present budget is astronomical when
compared to the meagre sum expend¬
ed in the earlier years.
O
VER the past ten years, the
U.S.S.R. has undertaken a vast pro¬
gramme of development of the huge
natural resources of Siberia. A new
branch of the Academy of Sciences
has been opened in Siberia to act as
a coordinating centre. Concerned
with fundamental research as well as
with the applied sciences, the Siberian
centre at Novosibirsk has now taken
the lead in certain branches of Soviet
research and has won world reco¬
gnition for its pioneering work. New
branches of the Academy are now
being established in the Urals, the
Far East, and other parts of the
country.
One repercussion of the national
policy instituted by Lenin was the
rapid development of training and
research at the level of the national
Republics which make up the Soviet
Union. Beginning with the foundation,
in 1919, of the Ukrainian Academy of
Sciences, new Academies have been
set up now in all the 15 Republics
of the U.S.S.R.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
At first these new focal points of
scientific research had as their primary
concern problems of direct interest
to the economic development of the
Individual Republics. But this implied
a parallel extension of fundamental
research. Today these Academies of
the Republics make an important con¬
tribution to fundamental research.
The Academy of the Ukraine is
world famous for its research into
cybernetics, solid state physics, geo¬
logy and physical chemistry. Also
widely recognized is the work on astro¬
physics being undertaken at the Aca¬
demy of Armenia and research into
theoretical mechanics at the Academy
of the Georgian Republic, the research
into the chemistry of alkaloids at
the Uzbekistan Academy, the geo¬
logical research of the Kazakhstan
Academy, the petro-chemical studies
of the Azerbaijan Academy, the work
of the Academy of Latvia on organic
synthesis, etc.
The Academies of the Republics
play a large part in solving particular
regional problems. Those of Central
Asia pay special attention to the
scientific culture of cotton crops, the
study of deserts and their exploitation
and seismological problems.
One of the prevailing characteristics
of Soviet science is the close link that
has been established between funda¬
mental research and the resolution of
economic problems of a practical
nature. For their part, those scientific
organizations that serve the various
specialized sectors of the economy
participate widely in helping to solve
the great problems of science.
During Lenin's lifetime, a series of
research institutes was set up devoted
especially to the development of
industry, transport and the electrifica¬
tion of the country. Today, these same
Institutes are continuing the job on a
much broader front. Agriculture, medi¬
cine and, education have their own
Academies. The 800 or so establish¬
ments of higher education within the
U.S.S.R. also carry out research
covering a wide field.
This has made it possible to devel¬
op research work across the entire
spectrum of modern science, and has
resulted in a whole series of spec¬
tacular discoveries and scientific
achievements. This is not the place
to attempt to list them all, but I would
like to mention the brilliant successes
of Soviet mathematics, discoveries in
the field of radio-electronics, Soviet
contributions to the theory of solids,
the theory of resistance, aerodynamics
and mechanics.
In chemistry, I am thinking particu¬
larly of the development of the theory
of chain reactions, contributions to
organic chemistry, and the chemistry
of elementary organic combinations.
Soviet scientists have shown the way
towards the peaceful uses of nuclear
energy and have enunciated the basic
principles for the ultimate achievement
of controlled nuclear reactions.
THE YEARS OF EXILE
Living in Russia had become too
dangerous for Lenin and he was obliged
to spend many years abroad, constantly
moving from place to place, studying hard,
writing and directing the activities of the
Bolsheviks in Russia. In May 1908,
Lenin went on a trip from Paris to the
island of Capri (Italy) to visit his close
friend Maxim Gorky to discuss political
matters. Above, Lenin (wearing bowler
hat) plays chess with Alexander Bogdanov,
the Russian philosopher and economist,
while Gorki, hand on chin, looks on.
Lenin adopted that name while in
exile in 1902. Other names he used were:
William Frey, P. Petrov, V. Ilyin,
Jakob Richter, Ivan and llyich. Before
returning to Russia to lead the revolution,
Lenin lived in Switzerland, France,
England, Sweden, Denmark and Finland.
Below left, photo of Lenin
taken in Paris in 1910.
Above, Lenin snatches a rare moment
of relaxation in the mountain village of
Zkopane in Poland during the
summer of 1914.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
by Vsevolod Sto/etov
Member of the U.S.S.R. Academy of
Pedagogical Sciences and Minister of
Higher and Secondary Specialized
Education of the Russian Soviet
Federated Socialist Republic.
EDUCATION
key to social
transformation
W
12
E must at all costs set out,
first, to learn, secondly, to learn and
thirdly, to learn ; and then see to it
that learning shall not remain a dead
letter, that it shall become part of our
very being and a fully constituent part
of our social life."
These words, from one of Lenin's
last articles, "Better fewer, but better",
reflect the love of learning of the
man who has been called "the great
headmaster" and his firm belief that
knowledge means power.
Lenin inherited his profound respect
for and interest in learning from his
father who was a talented and well-
known educator of his time. In 1869,
the year before Lenin's birth, llya Niko-
layevich' Ulyanov was appointed ins¬
pector of primary schools in the pro¬
vince of Simbirsk and later he became
director of schools with the rank of
Councillor of State.
In Simbirsk he was known as "The
Liberal" and his sense of responsibility
towards the people led him to actions
that were at times regarded with some
suspicion by his superiors.
As a gimnaziya teacher he refused
to take money for working with the
poorer students to get them through
their examinations. As inspector and
then director of schools he applied
himself with great energy to the task
of building up the school system in
his province. In 17 years he was res¬
ponsible for the building of 450
schools and doubling the school
attendance.
The humanistic upbringing Lenin
received from his parents, the example
of his father's devotion to his work,
his own extensive knowledge of his¬
tory and his ability to analyse events
awakened in him an ardent desire to
fight for social justice.
Lenin was convinced that social in¬
justice and social inequality must be
abolished before full equality could be
achieved. He reasoned that without
equality in education there could be
neither genuine equality nor genuine
democracy. To achieve this genuine
democracy he outlined a number of
aims, not only in the social, political
and economic, but also in the educa¬
tional fields. As early as 1902 Lenin and
his friends declared that they would
fight for universal, free, compulsory
education for everyone below the age
of 16.
Lenin's parents belonged to a
generation of Russian intellectuals who
took a passionate interest in the ideas
of the great French Enlightenment, the
French and English Utopian socialists,
the writings of the Russian revolu¬
tionary democrat Nikolai Chernyshev-
sky. The works of Robert Owen, Saint-
Simon and Charles Fourier were the
manuals of Russian intellectuals in the
1860s.
Lenin's own views on education and
his pedagogical principles also stem¬
med from the teachings of 18th and
19th century philosophers with their
distinctive tone of historical optimism
and moral courage. He saw the aim
of economic, social, scientific, techno¬
logical and cultural progress as being
"the humanizing of the environment"
and ensuring for men a harmonious
and intellectual development.
His programme of social transform¬
ation was, therefore, closely linked with
education. He realized that the new
state could only be built if everyone
was aware of the greatness of the goal.
For this ¡t was necessary to elevate
man, to free him from the grip of
ignorance, poverty and servitude. And
the first step was to wipe out illiteracy.
As Russia entered the 20th century,
CONTINUED PAGE 14
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
:
i fC-A
f/**
J,/«* U faucet] i
'/?
.i*Jvc<
a
<
Far left, Lenin (carrying
umbrella) in Stockholm on the
way to Russia via Finland
following the February 1917
revolution which overthrew
the Czar. But once back
in Russia, Lenin was forced
into hiding again by the
Kerensky provisional
government. Left, Lenin
disguised as worker
Konstantin Ivanov used
this pass to get to the
Smolny Institute from where
he directed the October
revolution.
Below, Lenin and his wife Nadezhda Krupskaya after
the National Conference of 1919 against illiteracy.
Nadezhda Krupskaya played a major role in forming
Soviet educational policy.
Photo © I ML Archives - Revolution Museum, Moscow
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Photo left, Lenin (in centre, under lamp)
presides as chairman of the first
government of Soviet Russia the
Council of People's Commissars
which was formed at the Second
All-Russia Congress of Soviets, the
day after the October revolution.
The first major decrees on Peace,
Land and Nationalization were followed
by further decrees on education and
the preservation of libraries and
monuments and the opening of the
universities to the workers, etc.
In 1919, the famous decree on the
elimination of illiteracy was promulgated.
EDUCATION (Continued)
'Economize on everything except education'
80 per cent of her population bet¬
ween the ages of 9 and 50 was illitera¬
te. In the provinces, especially in cen¬
tral Asia, the far east and north, lite¬
racy was practically nil (Tajiks 0.5 per
cent, Kirghiz 0.6 per cent, for example).
In discussing this situation Lenin him¬
self wrote: "there is no other country
in Europe so barbarous in which the
masses are robbed to such an extent
of education, light and knowledge . . .
No other country in Europe has remain¬
ed in this condition; Russia is the
exception."
Arguing with his political opponents
on the eve of the Great October Revo¬
lution, Lenin wrote "We are not Uto¬
pians." And he went on to say, "We
know that an unskilled labourer or a
cook cannot immediately get on with
the job of State administration." He
firmly rejected the view that "only the
rich, or officials chosen from rich fami¬
lies, are capable of administering the
State, of performing the ordinary,
everyday work of administration."
Both unskilled labourers and cooks,
Lenin said, are capable of learning to
administer the affairs of society pro¬
vided that they get a good education.
L
14
|ENIN focussed his atten¬
tion on universal education literally the
day after the workers had seized poli¬
tical power. Decrees concerned with
land, peace, the nationalization of finan¬
cial institutions, the railways and heavy
industry were immediately followed by
laws on education.
The decree "On the setting up of a
State Commission for Education", pub¬
lished on November 22, 1917, defined
(as did also a number of subsequent
laws enacted in 1917 and 1918) the
main principles underlying the struc¬
ture of the educational system and its
democratic management.
On the eve of the October revolu¬
tion, Lenin's wife and close collabora¬
tor, Nadezhda Krupskaya, wrote, on
his advice, a book entitled "Edu¬
cation and Democracy" which was also
to serve as a basis for the new edu¬
cational system in Russia.
Under the new order, research ins¬
titutes, libraries, publishing houses,
newspapers and periodicals, museums,
picture galleries, theatres, conserva¬
toires, the radio etc., were all enlisted
to help schools of all levels in the
task of spreading knowledge.
The Red Army became a vehicle
for imparting education. A network of
courses, classes, faculties and study
groups was set up throughout the coun¬
try to teach people to read and write.
The watchword of the day was: "If you
know how to read, teach your neigh¬
bour." "Workers faculties" were
organized early in 1919 to help work¬
ers, peasants and soldiers whose
secondary education was incomplete
to join higher educational establish¬
ments. Within a short time they were
established in all universities and insti¬
tutes.
At the third All-Russia Congress of
the Soviets, on January 31, 1918, Lenin
declared that all scientific and techno¬
logical achievements would become
the property of the people and be
placed at their service. This was an
official declaration and in later
speeches and articles he stressed that
the scientific knowledge of the intelli¬
gentsia should be fused with the initia¬
tive, energy and effort of the masses.
The decree "On the setting up of a
State Commission for Education" and
later documents, laid down the basic
principles for the administration of edu¬
cational establishments; it was to be
based on co-operation between
teachers and the general public.
In the early years the Soviet edu¬
cational system demanded enormous
sacrifices on the part of the people and
the state. The young Republic was
beleaguered on all sides by foreign
armies and a large part of its territory
was occupied by the enemy.
Counter-revolution and espionage
had assumed enormous proportions
within the country. Industry, agricul¬
ture and transport were in havoc, mil¬
lions were starving and mass epidemics
ravaged the country.
Nevertheless, the underlying prin¬
ciples of the educational system were
shaped in those grim days. The slo¬
gan of the moment was: "Economize
on everything except education; eco¬
nomize on everything for the sake of
education."
B
ETWEEN 1917 and 1928,
construction of 7,780 new primary and
secondary schools was completed or
begun. Though battling with its many
enemies, with disease, hunger and
devastation, the government organized
universities in Voronezh, Nijni Novgo¬
rod (now Gorky), Irkutsk and Samara
(now Kuibyshev). A few years later
the Byelorussian, Yaroslavl, Turkestan
and other universities were founded.
Russia was well down amongst the
developed countries with regard to the
number of university students. In 1914
there were only 8 students per 10,000
of the population in Russia as compar¬
ed with 34 in the United States and
16 in Germany. In 1914, Russia's
student population was 127,000
whereas in 1968/69, 4,470,000 students
attended the country's higher educa¬
tional establishments.
Considerable changes were made in
the geographical distribution of aca¬
demic institutions. Before 1917, more
than half of these were in Moscow
and Petrograd. There was only one
higher education establishment outside
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
In 1918, on the first anniversary
of the October Revolution, Lenin
unveiled a memorial plaque In the
Kremlin wall which bears the inscription,
"To those fallen in the fight for peace
and brotherhood of peoples". At that
time Lenin paid much attention to what
he called "monumental propaganda".
This was the first of many plaques,
obelisks and other monuments
erected during Lenin's lifetime.
the present Russian Federation and
Ukrainian Republic. On the eve of
the Second World War there were 146,
including 46 in the Transcaucasian
Republics, 47 in the Central Asian
Republics and 20 in Kazakhstan. Many
higher education establishments were
opened in Siberia.
Today there is not a single Repub¬
lic, territorial or regional centre with¬
out at least one of the country's 794
institutions of higher learning. The
Soviet student population includes
representatives of practically all the
100 different nationalities living in the
U.S.S.R.
There have also been considerable
changes in the social structure of the
student body. In 1914, students from
the privileged classes accounted for
58, per cent of the student enrolment
in ten universities (34,500 students).
Workers were listed under the head¬
ing "others" and the share of these
others amounted to only 2.8 per cent.
In five higher technical institutions
students from the privileged classes
accounted for 41.3 per cent (9,300
students) - and "others" for 4.6 per
cent. A year after the October revolu¬
tion Kazan university still had more
than 1,000 students from the privi¬
leged classes, but there were already
135 students from the urban and rural
working class and 439 of farmer origin.
The government took further steps
to make the student population a
genuinely democratic one and the
process took about ten years. In 1930,
45.9 per cent of the student population
consisted of workers and their chil¬
dren, 19.4 per cent of peasants and
their children, 30.3 per cent of office
workers and intellectuals and 4.4 per
cent of other categories.
The principals of Soviet universities
attempt to make the social structure
of the student body reflect the social
structure of the whole population. It
was with this in view that one-year
preparatory courses were set up at
many higher education establishments
in 1969.
The quality of instruction in the big
cultural centres improves more rapidly
than it does in rural schools and in
schools in the new industrial districts.
As a result pupils from the latter
schools find it difficult to compete with
pupils from the big cultural centres in
the qualifying entrance examinations.
The preparatory courses are intended
to do away with this distinction and
to provide equal conditions for all
young people wishing to acquire a
higher education, irrespective of their
place of domicile.
By 1965, the student population of
the U.S.S.R. had multiplied 28 times
as compared with 1914 and the aca¬
demic staff 33 times. But this was
not only a quantitative growth. Lenin
was anxious that there should be no
break in the continuity of scientific and
cultural development and he ensured
that full use was made of the old
Russia's academic staff amongst whom
were many scholars of world renown.
He maintained that socialist science
and culture would emerge through the
creative assimilation of the scientific
and cultural achievements of preced¬
ing generations.
I
T was this continuity that
Lenin sought to ensure when he laid
down the attitude that the proletariat,
now at the helm of state, should adopt
towards the intellectuals of the old
Russia. He called for active partici¬
pation of all scholars educated in old
Russia in the life of Soviet universities
and institutes and insisted that no arti¬
ficial barriers should be erected bet¬
ween the old and the new scholars.
Comradely co-operation should be
established with the old professoriate
who should be allowed to participate
in research and for whom adequate
living conditions should be provided.
Lenin's attitude towards the older
scholars bore ample fruit and the
majority of them played their part in
helping to develop the educational
system and in training young research
workers.
Nowadays most countries endeavour
to give at least an elementary educ¬
ation to the entire population. Without
it modern industry and agriculture
would be impossible to maintain. Liter¬
acy for the entire population is the
first step in the abolition of the "know¬
ledge monopoly."
The second step is universal com¬
pulsory secondary education and some
developed countries have already
reached this stage. The third stage is
to put higher education within the
reach of all those wishing to acquire
it and capable of benefiting from it,
and the final stage is the elimination
of all distinction between physical and
intellectual labour.
Nobody nowadays any longer doubts
that the aims of these first and second
stages are attainable, but with regard
to the third and fourth stages the old
argument is still being advanced that
people are "biologically unequal" for
hereditary reasons.
Soviet scholars work on the
assumption that, provided their parents
are healthy and lead a normal life, all
people are endowed with equal abili¬
ties. A healthy childhood must be
ensured for all and children must be
provided with the material conditions
for education, rising from one stage to
another.
In other words there must be social
justice, equal access to the achieve¬
ments of the human Intellect and equal
conditions for growth and develop¬
ment. Equal education, therefore,
forms a significant part of that social
justice for which Lenin fought through¬
out his life.
Speaking about this aspect of
Lenin's work, Albert Einstein said:
"I respect in Lenin a man who, with
complete self-forgetfulness, gave all
his strength to the cause of social jus- 1 C
tice. . . one thing is irrefutable people V
like him uphold and renew the cons¬
cience of mankind."
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
by
Lauri A. Posti
Professor at the Faculty
of Philosophy, University
of Helsinki (Finland)
Lenin
and cultural rights
of minorities
I
16
|N the early days of the
Soviet Union, nationalities policy ques¬
tions were vitally important, since
national minorities comprised over
50 per cent of the entire population.
In Czarist times, these minorities were
subdued and oppressed in many ways.
As many of them had never had a
literary language, it was most difficult
to make just arrangements and help
to raise their cultural standards. The
scattered examples of literature written
in certain native languages consisted
mainly of religious books. The minor¬
ity nationalities were mostly illiterate.
Under the Czars, only about 26 per
cent of the whole population was
literate; among some nationalities, not
even 1 per cent were literate.
As a schoolboy, Lenin was already
familiar with this problem. He was
born in Simbirsk (modern Ulyanovsk)
on the Volga, and always had a warm
sympathy for the Chuvashes, Mordvi-
nians, Tatars and Votyaks (Udmurts),
oppressed nationalities who lived in
the area.
The many years Lenin spent in exile,
often far from his native land, no doubt
helped to confirm his conviction of the
importance of the nationalities ques¬
tion. . He mastered several foreign
languages, and, deeply attached as he
was to the Russian language and
culture, it is obvious that his long stay
in foreign surroundings emphasized
for him the importance of native
tongues.
In his extensive literary output Lenin
repeatedly returned to the nationalities
question and the importance of native
languages and cultures, always stress¬
ing that all should have equal impor¬
tance, even going so far as to suggest
that there was no need for an obli¬
gatory official language.
In "Is an obligatory official language
necessary?", published in Proletars-
kaja Pravda on January 18, 1914,
arguing against the views expressed
by the Russian Liberal Party on the
language question, Lenin concludes as
follows: "Hence, Russian Marxists
consider that it is necessary not to
have an obligatory official language;
that the population must be provided
with schools and instruction in all the
regional languages; and that a basic
provision must be included in the
Constitution declaring all privileges
whatsoever null and void of any par¬
ticular nation, this annulment also to
concern all infringements whatsoever
of the rights of national minorities".
Lenin has given his detailed reasons
in "Critical Remarks on the National
Question" and "The Right of Nations
to Self-Determination", books written
in 1913 and 1914, which provided the
theoretical national programme of the
coming revolution.
Soon after the October Revolution
in which the Bolsheviks seized power,
the Council of the People's Commis¬
sars, issued the "Declaration of Rights
of the Peoples of Russia", signed by
Lenin, declaring its intention of basing
Russian nationalities policy on the
following principles:
The equality and sovereignty of .
the peoples of Russia.
The right of the peoples of Russia
to free self-determination, up to and
including secession and the formation
of an independent State.
The abolition of all national and
national-religious privileges and res¬
trictions.
The free development of the
national minorities and ethnographical
groups inhabiting the territory of
Russia.
In accordance with the second of
these principles Lenin, as Chairman
of the Council of the People's Com¬
missars, signed the decision at the
end of December 1917 acknowledg¬
ing the independence of Finland, on
the proposal of the Government of
Finland. This was an act of states¬
manship which the whole Finnish
nation gratefully recognizes.
In many earlier statements Lenin,
who. was well acquainted with con¬
ditions in Finland where he had taken
refuge several times from Czarist
persecution, had expressed the view
that Finland was entitled to indepen¬
dence if the Finnish people so wanted.
w
HEN conditions finally be¬
came settled in the Soviet Union,
energetic efforts were made to develop
the languages and cultures of national
minorities, in accordance with a
decision of the tenth Communist Party
Congress in 1921, with Lenin as Chair¬
man.
Alphabets and principles of ortho¬
graphy had to be created for languages
that had never been written before.
Experts had to decide which dialect
or dialects should provide the basis of
the literary language. This often
demanded extensive research.
The sound system of the language
had to be scrutinized, and what seem¬
ed to be the vital dialect or dialects
identified. Specialized terminologies
had to be created since they were
naturally lacking in languages that had
been used only as regional spoken
languages.
In devising new alphabets, the Latin
alphabet, considered to be the most
international, was taken as a basis. A
centre was set up to handle the
general and theoretical problems,
with local committees for the various
languages. As many nationalities had
no specialists of their own, Russian
experts often had to do the basic
research. In the interests of unifor-
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
miry, the Latin alphabet was Introduc¬
ed- even in languages that already had
some literature published in Russian
or Arabic? letters.
Towards the end of the nineteen-
thirties, the young literary languages
changed over to alphabets based on
Russian letters. This change was
prompted by the close political, eco¬
nomic, and cultural relations with the
Russians and, of course, many non-
Russians knew Russian or wanted to
learn it. Russian has become by far
the most important means of commu¬
nications between the different parts
of the Soviet Union and the different
nationalities.
The Russian alphabet has more
letters than the Latin but not enough
for the needs of all the languages.
The accepted principle is that each
phoneme, I.e. functionally distinctive
sound, has its own character in the
orthography.
In some of the languages, the pho¬
nemes are unusually many. Thus
Lezgian (belonging to the Caucasian
group of languages) has 60 phonemes,
6 vowels and as many as 54 con-
, sonants. Russian has 33 letters;
obviously, more characters were need¬
ed. They were created by combining
additional characters with the basic
Russian letters or by borrowing from
other alphabets. Some phonemes are
indicated by a combination of two
characters.
All in all, these new alphabets
comprise, in addition to the 33 Russian
letters, 55 other characters, i.e. a total
of 88 letters made necessary by the
desire to keep the phonetic value of
each letter about the same in different
languages, with new letters for such
phonemes as differ phonetically from
those of the Russian language.
Accordingly, the same characters
generally indicate similar sounds in
different languages.
In deciding which dialect should be
CONTINUED PAGE 20
Ravaged by the effects of World War I and the civil war, Russia in 1919
was in chaos. Moscow railwaymen decided to work voluntarily
in their free time on Saturday (in Russian "Subbota") to speed up the
clearing and repair of the Moscow-Kazan railway line. Lenin welcomed
this initiative which he described as "the great beginning". The
railwaymen's lead was followed all over the country. Voluntary work
of this kind came to be known as "Subbotnik" and each spring up
until today the whole population of the U.S.S.R. participates in days
of unpaid labour. Above, Lenin (arrow) taking part in the All-Russia
Subbotnik in the grounds of the Kremlin in May 1920.
Lenin encouraged scientific and technological advances of every kind.
Below, he watches trials of a new type of electric plough, near
Moscow, in October 1921.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
For Lenin, any place could serve as an office
and any spare moment was an opportunity for
work. Above, Lenin takes notes on the steps of
the rostrum at a conference in 1921. While not
an educationalist himself, Lenin recognized
how vital education was to the country's
social transformation.
In old Russia over 80 per cent of the
population was illiterate and in
the outlying districts literacy was
practically nil. On December 26,
1919 the Soviet government passed
the decree on the elimination of illiteracy
and the great educational and
cultural drive began. Below left,
a city girl explains the mysteries of
the alphabet to a Russian peasant.
Below centre, a lunchtime lesson In
a factory. Below right, Tajiks from
the mountainous Pamir region and,
right, Turkmenian women from the
deserts of central Asia, attend
literacy classes. Before the revolution,
literacy among Tajiks was 0,5 per
cent and among Turkmenians 0.7
per cent. Today illiteracy has been
virtually wiped out In the Soviet Union.
SO
If you can read
teach your neighbour'
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
2
O.
< Il
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
CULTURAL RIGHTS (Continued)
Photo © APN
Above, winter at the country house at Gorki, a village
just outside Moscow, where Lenin, his health broken by
overwork, lived from 1923 until his death on January 21,
1924. Against his doctor's orders Lenin continued working
right to the end. During this period he wrote several
Important works including "Better Fewer, But Better" and
"On Co-operation". Below, Lenin seated beside his wife
Nadezhda Krupskaya with his sister Anna, his nephew Victor,
and a neighbour's daughter Vera, in the grounds of
the "dacha" at Gorki in summer 1922.
Photo © APN
made the basis of literary language,
the experts took account of the num¬
bers who spoke each dialect and their
weight ¡n economic and cultural terms.
Phonetic, morphological, and' lexical
characteristics were next considered,
and earlier literature ¡f any. In some
cases, where differences in dialects
were very considerable, and popula¬
tions scattered, two literary languages
were created.
When creating a new literary lan¬
guage, great attention must be paid
to the development of the specialized
terminologies lacking in languages
hitherto used only as local spoken
languages. It was often necessary to
resort to loan words mostly of Russian
origin, or international words acquired
via Russian. Part, however, were
native, either borrowed from dialects
or derived by the word formation
typical of the language. The special
committees set up for this work in¬
clude philologists and experts in the
subject matter concerned.
Over fifty nationalities which pre¬
viously had no literature in their native
languages now have literary languages
of their own. With many of them,
development has been very rapid.
Books and newspapers are published
in relatively large numbers, and origi¬
nal literature in the native language
has made noteworthy progress. Na¬
tive language schools allow the
different nations to produce their own
educated classes. The Soviet Union
is divided up administratively in such
a way as to pay due account to the
existence and needs of different
nationalities, and this has encouraged
the growth of the national cultures.
In some cases all the preparations
for developing a literary language were
made, but the project was later drop¬
ped. This happened when too few
people were really involved or inter¬
ested or else were too scattered, the
differences between dialects were too
great, or when the people had a good
command of Russian or some other
important neighbouring language. The
incentives to developing or using a
literary language of their own were
therefore lacking.
All the new literary languages have
not been equally popular or equally
successful. Obviously, those of small
nationalities have not played the same
role as those spoken by large numbers
of people. The languages used ¡n the
administration, in higher institutes, and
in research have developed most ; the
languages of minor nationalities are
often used only in primary education.
Even so, they have been of great
Importance to the lives of the peoples
concerned.
Learning to read and write is much
easier if done in one's own language
and, of course, greatly facilitates the
spread of literacy. Here the Soviet
Union can, with justified pride, refer
to really magnificent achievements.
In Tadzhikistan, for instance, in
Czarist times, only 2.3 per cent of
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Photo © APN
The scene in Red Square on January 27,
1924, the day of Lenin's funeral. At four
o'clock on that day all activity ceased
for five minutes throughout the Soviet
Union and the occasion was also
observed in many other countries.
those between 9 and 49 years old were
literate; as late as 1926, only 3.8 per
cent. The corresponding figures for
1939 were 82.8, for 1959, 96.2 per cent.
In Uzbekistan, the percentage in
Czarist times was 3.6, in 1926 11.6, in
1939, 78.7 and in 1959, 98.1. Literacy
has gone hand in hand with rising
standards of education and cultural
life, which in turn have afforded access
to the science, technology and culture
of other nations.
Lenin himself saw only the very
beginning of this great process of
development. As the whole world is
now celebrating the centenary of his
birth, it can confidently be said, that
the principle of the equality of all
nations and languages, which was
embodied in his nationalities policy,
and which has allowed different
nationalities active educational and
cultural participation, has had a most
significant Influence on the enormous
development that has taken place ¡n
both these sectors in the Soviet Union
since the October Revolution.
Above, the provincial Russian town of Simbirsk, now Ulyanovsk,
as it was in Lenin's boyhood. Below, the Ulyanovsk
of today; part of the memorial centre containing libraries,
lecture-rooms, museums, etc., built to commemorate Lenin's
hundredth anniversary, and inaugurated on April 16, 1970,
by Leonid Brezhnev. The original Ulyanov family home
is housed within this modern building.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
T
22
HE sounds of the gamelan
orchestra the muted thunder of
drums, sonorous gongs or tinkling chi¬
mes are heard throughout Java, their
music pervading palaces and theatres,
squares and even private homes. To
the music of the gamelan are enacted
the Hindu epics of the Mahabharata
and Ramayana. Children and adults
crowd performances and listen en¬
chanted to stories of the deeds of my¬
thical heroes, demon kings, princes¬
ses and comic servants.
One form of traditional Indonesian
theatre art is the wayang kulit, the
famed shadow play by puppets made
of incised and painted buffalo hide,
whose silhouettes are projected on a
screen at night. The puppeteer or
dalang leads the gamelan, sings the
songs, narrates the story, and speaks
for each character in changing tones
and accents.
Wayang, in its widest sense, means
a dramatic performance, a play, or a
story, whether the actors are puppets
or human beings.
Troupes of dancers belonging to pri¬
vate clubs in Central Java also dra¬
matize the great epics in dance
plays (wayang wong). In addition,
professional groups-^each one the
exponent of a particular style move
from city to city, playing in each to
packed houses for two or three months
at a time.
Young children soon become fami¬
liar with the Mahabharata and the
Ramayana. When the wayang kulit
is performed they sit or squat in groups
before the screen, following with wide
eyes the appearance of a prince or
a demon. When dancers rehearse
they too have an audience of children
who frequently try to imitate the move¬
ments and gestures of an admired
dancer. At home they play on toy
instruments themes heard from the
gamelan. Moreover, manner of speech,
patterns of behaviour, ethical and
moral precepts which shape Javanese
mores are, to a considerable degree,
learned in childhood at performances
of the wayang.
In the countryside, around the city
of Jogjakarta are found the temples
dedicated to the Buddhist and Brahma-
nic faiths. Built of volcanic stone their
dark grey masses loom over rice fields
and dominate nearby villages, repeat¬
ing the rhythm of surrounding volcanic
peaks and ridges, silent reminders of
a past civilization whose beliefs still
affect the lives of the people today.
CONTINUED PAGE 24
HIROSHI DAIFUKU is head of Unesco's
Section for the Development of the Cultural
Heritage. He is the author of many studies
on anthropology, conservation and museo-
graphy.
lilt
monuments
of Java
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
by
Hiroshi Daifuku
The mighty temple complex of Loro Djonggrang, at Prambanan, ranks as one of Indonesia's most
magnificent monuments. Built in the 10th century A.D. it originally comprised over 220 temples,
sanctuaries and other buildings. Above, one of Its. smaller sanctuaries viewed from the great
temple dedicated to Shiva. Balustrades on the Shiva temple carry vividly sculpted scenes from the
great Hindu epic, the Ramayana (see "Unesco Courier" special issue, December 1967). They
relate how Rama, helped by an army of monkeys, sets out to rescue his wife Sita after her
abduction by Ravanna, king of Lanka. Right, a courageous bird, Jatayu, carries Sita's ring to Rama
and tells him where she is held captive. Left, another scene from the Ramayana carved on the
temple of Brahma, flanking that of Shiva.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE GROTTO
OF THE HERMIT
At the foot of the Wadjak mountains
near Tulung Agung, Java (site of the
discovery of the remains of Wadjak Man,
a type similar to Neanderthal Man) is a
hermit's cave hewn from the solid rock.
Its walls are decorated with reliefs
illustrating episodes from the story of
the mythical hero Ardjuna, and his
temptation by nymphs sent down to earth
by Indra, god of the sky, to disrupt his
meditations. Right, nymphs descend from
the abode of the gods and alight- hear
a stream. Far right, boatmen, shouldering
their oars approach the grptto where
Ardjuna meditates. (Ardjuna himself is
not shown in this photo).
ART OF JAVA (Continued)
Great scenes from the Ramayana
Thus, though they are no longer
religious centres, their associations
with the cultural life of the people
through music, dance and the theatre
are ever presenfand thus make them
living rattier than dead monuments.
The beginning and growth of Hindu
culture in South East Asia is still not
perfectly known. Archaeological dis¬
coveries of stone and metal inscrip¬
tions, dating from the beginning of the
5th century A.D., show that Indian
influence had already reached the
archipelago. Small states existed,
based on Indian patterns, which traded
with India and China and with each
other, and waged war among them¬
selves.
Gradually a dominant state evolv¬
ed. Mataram, as it was known, gain¬
ed control of Central Java during the
8th century and built the first temples
on the Dieng Plateau, dedicated to
Shiva. Buddhist missionaries prob¬
ably came a short while later.
During the latter part of the 8th cen¬
tury a new dynasty appeared, the Sai-
lendra, which controlled most of Java
and Sumatra. Much of what is known
of Central Java during this period is
derived from the many monuments
constructed by the different kings of
this dynasty.
Borobudur (see the "Unesco
Courier", June 1958 and June 1968) is
the best known of these monuments.
Besides carvings treating the religious
aspects of Buddhism, many panels give
an indication of the life of the people
during this period.
A caparisoned elephant standing
near a prince and princess indicates
its use as a steed. Musicians play on
flutes, drums, cymbals and rattles
while a dancer's gestures carved in
stone centuries ago could easily be
those of a dancer today. A high-prow-
ed, two-masted ship under full sail
laden with passengers and cargo
reveals the level of seamanship achi¬
eved in south east Asia during this
period.
Three kilometres from Borobudur is
the temple of Mendut. Within it
stands the famed statue of the "Preach¬
ing" Buddha, flanked by a statue of the
Bodhisattva of Mercy, Avalokiteshva-
ra, to its right and the Bodhisattva of
Power, Vajrapani, to its left. They
are, says the Netherlands archaeolo¬
gist, A. J. Bernet-Kempers, "one of the
greatest manifestations of Buddhist
spiritual thought and art . . . There
are few, if any, groups of statues
anywhere else in Buddhist countries
which can compete with them."
On the wings of the flight of steps
are carved parables (¡atakas) based
on folk tales such as the story found
in many other East Asian countries of
a talkative turtle who begged a pair
of geese to take him on a flight. On
the panel, the turtle is shown suspend¬
ed by its mouth from a stick held bet¬
ween the two birds. As people make
fun of him the turtle opens his mouth
to reply, falls, and is killed by the on¬
lookers.
The "tree of heaven" carved on the
sides of Mendut and nearby Pawon
recalls the silhouette of the gunungan,
the carved leaf-shaped buffalo hide
which is used to signal the opening
and closing of the wayang kulit puppet
play to indicate changes of scenes,
forests, and in general to symbolize
the entire ritual of the wayang.
Guardian figures found at temples
such as Kalasan, Sewu and Sari, mas¬
sively sculptured, with heavy stone
clubs, protect the entrances from evil.
Their benign features are in contrast
to the more demonic countenances
found in such figures in temples of
the other Asian countries. The tradi¬
tion continued until recent times and
many of the palaces of Central Java
have had such figures added to the
entrances of the grounds.
The varying styles of architecture,
the carved statues of pilgrims, Bodhl-
sattvas, royal personnages, all testify
to the wealth of the civilization as well
as to the, dedication of the Sailendra
rulers to Buddhism.
Accounts of pilgrims and travellers
to the Java of this period give some
indication of the wealth and political
importance of the Sailendra Dynasty.
Apart from the stone temples and the
scenes they portray, little remains of
this former glory for most of the
domestic architecture was built of
perishable materials, such as wood
which is rapidly destroyed in the humid
monsoon climate.
Labour and materials to build all
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
these structures must have been contri¬
buted by the great mass of the people,
who also served in the armies of the
kings, engaged in commerce, and
otherwise produced the wealth which
made possible the activities of the
State.
It is also probable that many indi¬
genous beliefs antedating the intro¬
duction of Hinduism and Buddhism
persisted, as indeed they do today.
The worship of Shiva also probably
continued throughout the Sailendra
period and some authorities suggest
that the attributes of Shiva and Buddha
may have been combined.
In the latter half of the 9th century,
construction was begun of the temples
dedicated to Shiva, Brahma and Vishnu.
This complex of temples, known as
"Loro Djonggrang", at Prambanan,
rivals Borobudur in conception. Tradi¬
tionally it is identified with the Mata¬
ran, kingdom at the close of the Sai¬
lendra period.
It seems to have been gradually
abandoned when the capital of Mata-
ram was transferred to Eastern Java
and the temples were finally destroyed
by an earthquake in 1549. For centu¬
ries they lay forgotten with only low
brush-covered mound hinting at their
presence. Excavation revealed the
importance of the site and it is being
slowly restored.
The visitor today comes upon frag¬
ments of the outermost wall which is
built in a square, with each side
390 metres (1,300 ft) in length. The
complex of temples and shrines are
found within two inner, concentrically
walled enclosures. The square walls
are oriented north to south with gates
at each of the four cardinal points of
the compass. Within the central court
are found the principal temples sur¬
rounded by a wall 110 metres (360 ft)
square. The intermediate court origi¬
nally had 224 minor temples, most of
which are in ruins, surrounded by a
wall 222 metres (730 ft) square.
The central temple dedicated to Shi¬
va towers 47 metres (155 ft) above a
narrow balustraded terrace. It was
carefully restored between 1937 and
1953. However, it was not possible
to complete the roof, and today the
statue of Shiva stands in the open sil¬
houetted dramatically against the sky.
The builders of the temple combined
several Indian styles with Javanese ele¬
ments into a single harmonious archi¬
tectural composition. Matching it in
beauty are the temples dedicated to
Vishnu and Brahma, to the north and
the south of the temple of Shiva.
Of more immediate interest to the
present-day culture of Java, however,
are the dancing figures sculpted on
the balustrades of the temple, and
above all the scenes from the Rama¬
yana on the interior of the balustrades.
Carved in stone, they record the bat¬
tles of Rama, the feats of Hanuman the
monkey general, and all of the legen¬
dary characters and scenes with
which the Javanese and Balinese are
so familiar through their theatre and
dance. The scenes from the Ramayana
are continued on the neighbouring
temple dedicated to Brahma. These
ancestral carvings are studied and
serve as standards of comparison for
the dancers of today.
Because of this an amphitheatre
has been built nearby and during
the full moon of the dry season (June -
September) annual performances of the
Ramayana are given by different dance
groups, coming not only from other
localities of Indonesia, but at times
from neighbouring countries.
The Islamic religion was introduced
into Indonesia by Indian traders dur¬
ing the 13th and 14th centuries. The
religion had already been modified by
Indian influences and as it was
gradually adopted rather than being
imposed by conquest acquired dist¬
inctive Indonesian characteristics, in¬
cluding a marked tolerance for survi¬
ving elements of Hindu religion.
In Central Java the oldest Muslim
monuments are found on the north
coast. The best known is the minaret
of Kudus near the city of Semarang. It
is not monumental in scope, but is
historically important, and in form it
resembles the Balinese drum tower or
kulkul rather than Indian models.
An outstanding example of aristo¬
cratic Indonesian Muslim architecture
exists ¡n Jogjakarta. It is largely in
ruins today, but traces of its former
glory exist. The pleasure palace of
the Sultan, Taman Sari (or "flower gar¬
den") was once located on an island
in an artificial lake which was reached
either by boat or a tunnel leading to
the island from the shore. Today the
island is a low hill surrounded by
garbage as the former lake now serves
as a dump.
The old tunnel, its moss covered
walls and shafts letting in air and
sunlight, bears mute witness to its for¬
mer role. One of the outer gates, sur- HT
rounded by nondescript housing, still ¿J
stands with crumbling masonry.
Behind it lie tanks or basins, partially
filled with silt, but children can still play
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
ART OF JAVA (Continued)
26
in them. Traces of old canals exist
and the lavish architectural plan
calling for a lake, fountains, and pools,
have also earned it the name of the
"water palace". The design of Taman
Sari differs strikingly from the lighter
wooden construction used for later
aristocratic buildings.
The Summer Palace of the Sultan
and the palaces of the Prince of Solo
and other members of the old Javanese
aristocracy offer another type of archi¬
tectural style which is much more Far
Eastern in concept. Here are courts
shaded with trees, low lying pavilions,
quarters for servants, etc. Within the
walled enclosure the most important
building is the front pavilion where
gamelan concerts are given, and
dances practised.
In the palace of the Sultan, now
open to the public as a museum, is one
of the most important collections of
gamelan instruments. In other prin¬
cely houses of the city of Jogjakarta,
dance groups composed of the young¬
sters from aristocratic families and
children from homes in the city and
surrounding countyside are trained. At
all such dancing lessons, crowds of
youngsters gather to watch and thus
learn the movements of the dance and
the modes of behaviour considered to
represent the ideal.
Thus, in Central Java today and in
other regions of this populous Island,
the formal classroom lessons of con¬
temporary civilization are tempered
with those learnt from the religious
and moral heritage and from the an¬
cient monuments of the past.
It is not possible at present for the
government to consider financing the
restoration and conservation of all of
the monuments of Central Java, Irres¬
pective of their importance to the cul¬
tural heritage. At Sewu, for example,
most of the shrines are tumbled heaps
of dressed stone. Some, by the pains¬
taking process known as anastylosis
(the fitting together of pieces like a
gigantic jigsaw puzzle) have had their
component parts identified and partial¬
ly reassembled, but not restored, due
to lack of funds.
Together with the monumental sites
described above, Central Java can
offer to the visitor a unique experience
and perspective of the growth of civili¬
zation in south east Asia which, for
much of the world, is still largely
unknown.
Central Java is heavily populated and
is largely agricultural. Measures to
meet pressing social and economic
needs have priority. The drive to
finance the restoration of Borobudur,
being launched by Unesco, will not in
itself contribute to the well-being of
the local people.
Unesco, however, is aiding the
Government in planning a programme
for the development of cultural tourism
which will help to justify the costly
programme required for the conserva¬
tion of the sites and monuments, and
at the same time open new economic
possibilities for the people.
yn rSaTWI,
i?3^3£S 'V**
CHARITABLE HARE. Disguised as a
Brahman, a god visits four animal friends an
otter, a monkey, a jackal and a hare and
begs for alms. Each offers the holy man
some food, but the hare (none other than the
Buddha in one of his earlier lives) having
nothing else to offer, is ready to sacrifice
his own body the ultimate example of
charity. This relief (800 A.D.) is one of
600 illustrating Buddha's birth stories, on the
galleries of the great Borobudur temple
on the island of Java.
I HE "Jatakas",
or birth tales of the Bud¬
dha, comprise 547 stories
in prose and poetry. They
are believed to have been
written about the 5th
century A.D., based on an
earlier version in Pali,
itself inspired by even
more ancient writings,
possibly dating from the
3rd century B.C. These
tales of the Buddha's
previous lives show how,
before the final incarna¬
tion in which he attained
Enlightenment, the Bud¬
dha had been reborn in¬
numerable times as an
animalas a monkey, an
elephant, an antelope, a
stag, a horse, and many
others. Ancient Buddhist
art, taking its themes
from the Jakata stories,
has depicted a graceful
cavalcade of beasts of
every kind, as in these
sculptured scenes from
Java 's monuments. .
STORIES IN STONE
ÜÜ -
im
I ^
3&.
%à*
&5zm*
MONKEY HERO. The King of Benares seeks and finds a tree covered with
luscious fruit growing by a river. Seeing a troop of monkeys devouring the fruit, he
orders his archers to shoot the animals down. The chief of the monkeys (the
Buddha) rescues his people by making a bridge across the river with a long rattan
and his own body. When the last monkey has passed, the exhausted chief
monkey lets go and is on the point of falling into the water when the king,
moved by such self-sacrifice, spares his life. (Borobudur temple relief).
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
TALKATIVE TURTLE. A turtle asks a pair
of geese to take him on a flight. Gripping in
his mouth a stick held by the birds he rises into
the air. As the people below mock him and
try to shoot him down, he opens his mouth
to return their abuse, falls to the ground and is
killed. This ancient story is one of the Fables
of Bidpai, the name under which a famous
collection of fables of Indian origin became
known in Europe in the middle ages. The original
Sanscrit work, composed by a Brahman in the
3rd century A.D., is still highly popular in India
as the "Pancatantra". The fable of the turtle,
which inspired one of the well-known fables
of La Fontaine, is depicted here on a relief in the
Chandi Mendut temple, Java (800 A.D.).
RESOURCEFUL GOAT. A story from
the Pancatantra has become a famous
fable in Java. A monkey offers to
lead a tiger to where a goat is living,
and lashes itself to the tiger's back with
a rope. Seeing them arrive, the goat
shouts to the monkey: "Thank you for
bringing me a tiger to eat, but where
are the other nine you promised me?"
Hearing this, the tiger panics and
dashes off, dragging the monkey behind
him... (Chandi Mendut temple, 800 A.D.).
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Hunting clues
to an ancient
supercontinent
by Daniel Behrman
Recent studies in oceanic geology have
thrown new light on the theory of
continental drift, according to which
the sea floor has spread out over eons
of time pushing the continents apart.
The process continues today as undersea
volcanic activity forces lava up from
volcanic vents and fissures in the
mid-ocean ridges that girdle the world.
Photo right shows lava formations
(pillow lava) formed when the molten
substance cools rapidly into the shapes
seen here. Photo was taken on the
Mid-Atlantic ridge at a depth of
3,000 metres (10,000 ft) by the French
océanographie vessel "Calypso*.
Scientists used a camera sled capable
of operating at a depth of
8,000 metres. Far right, ocean floor
at a depth of 4,600 metres (15,000 ft)
shows bell-shaped sponge being
deflected by deep currenL In this photo,
taken by a U.S. océanographie expedition
200 miles from Bermuda, needle of
compass attached to equipment indicates
direction of the currenL
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
I
NTEREST is growing
among marine geologists and geophy-
sicists in international co-operative
research to solve the enigmas that are
now raised by the western coast of
Africa.
It is here, according to some current
theories, that the primordial supercon¬
tinent, Pangaea, began to break open
more than 100 million years ago along
a rift that was to become the Atlantic
Ocean. From "the western hump of
Africa, what is now the Atlantic sea¬
board of the United States was split
off.
And there lie the enigmas. The con¬
tinental margin of North America is
perhaps the best known in the world
to marine geologists; that of the wes¬
tern coast of Africa is certainly among
the least known.
This knowledge gap can be best
DANIEL BEHRMAN, author of 'The New
World of the Oceans" (Little, Brown and Co.,
Boston, U.S.A.) is a Unesco science writer.
closed, scientists believe, by investi¬
gations involving not only the world's
leading océanographie nations but also
the developing countries along the
African coast.
Such was the trend of opinion at a
recent symposium organized in the
United Kingdom at Cambridge Univer¬
sity by SCOR, the Scientific Committee
on Oceanic Research of the Inter¬
national Council of Scientific Unions.
SCOR serves as scientific adviser to
Unesco's Intergovernmental Océano¬
graphie Commission that has already
co-ordinated a number of co-operative
investigations at sea.
The symposium brought together no
fewer than 206 scientists from eigh¬
teen countries. They spent an inten¬
sive week of talking, working, eating
and living together under one roof in
the relative isolation of Cambridge's
new Churchill College, a long mile from
the centre of the town.
The subject of their meeting was
"The Geology of the East Atlantic Con¬
tinental Margin", taking in the coast
of the Atlantic from Novaya Zemlya,
the Soviet archipelago in the far north,
to Cape Agulhas on the southern tip
of Africa.
"Continental margin" is the term that
oceanographers use to describe not
only the continental shelf but also the
slope and the rise that separate the
shore from the floor of the deep
ocean.
The subject of the meeting was also
attractive enough to lure scientists from
thirteen companies prospecting for oil
and mineral resources and one current¬
ly mining diamonds from the conti¬
nental shelf.
The symposium showed that explora¬
tion of the northern and the southern
tips of the east Atlantic shoreline is
well under way. As for the coast of
western Europe, it is being intensively
studied under the spur of natural gas
finds in the North Sea and oil pros-
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
Photo Bruce Heezen
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ANCIENT SUPERCONTINENT (Continued)
The Aladdin's cave under the sea
30
pects in the Bay of Biscay. But co¬
ordination is still needed so that, as
one scientist put it, geology on the
continental shelf will not become as
difficult politically as geology on the
continent.
South of the Bay of Biscay, coverage
begins to thin out. This is all the more
unfortunate because it is here that
many problems originate.
Geologists now tend to regard the
earth's surface as a number of
"plates" as many as nine. These
plates are moving, driven by the new
material that surges up from the mantle
below the earth's crust to spread out
from the mid-ocean ridges, thus form¬
ing new sea floor.
Action comes on the edges of these
plates, and the line running from
Gibralter to the Azores is one such
edge. South of this line, it is believ¬
ed that the sea floor is spreading much
"faster" (30 millimetres more a year)
than to the north. On both sides of
the line, therefore, the Atlantic conti¬
nental margin needs to be investigated
so as to determine the consequences
of such a grinding displacement.
Then, further to the south and
around the hump that starts with
Morocco, there is the Y-junction where
Europe, America and Africa may have
been joined in Pangaea. If so, then
how did they break up? The answer
could be buried under the bottom of
the Atlantic in the continental margin
off Africa.
The Cambridge meeting was told of
a proposal to send one of the world's
best-equipped research vessels, the
1,100-ton Atlantis II, operated by the
Woods Hole Océanographie Institution,
at Cape Cod on the U.S. east coast,
to work in several areas off Africa.
Details of the proposal were given
by Dr. K. O. Emery of Woods Hole,
who has been responsible for an
extensive survey of the continental
shelf on the other side of the Atlantic
off North America.
If funds are voted for U.S. participa¬
tion in the proposed International
Decade of Ocean Exploration, there is
a possibility that Atlantis II could sur¬
vey 10,000 kilometres of the African
coast, Dr. Emery stated. Every
200 kilometres, she would run a line
out from the coast, over the shelf, the
slope and the rise, using such techni¬
ques as seismic profiling, gravity and
magnetic measurements and precision
charting of the bottom.
The proposal was welcomed because
knowledge is particularly scanty about
the continental slope and rise out from
the shelf (which ends legally at the
200 -metre depth line). German and
English scientists at the meeting said
they could co-operate in such a survey
by sending scientists to join the
research team aboard the ship, or by
working up data. Dr. Emery said it
was hoped that scientists from African
countries would be able to work
aboard Atlantis II too.
O
N the western European
end of the continental margin, scien¬
tists feel that no such broad reconnais¬
sance is needed. Instead, they
consider that small symposia could
discuss specific areas such as the
Bay of Biscay or the Rockall plateau.
The Rockall plateau came in for a
share of attention too at the Cam¬
bridge symposium. It lies in the
Atlantic about 450 kilometres (300
miles) northwest of Ireland, yet is be¬
lieved to be of continental rather than
oceanic origin. Seismic refraction
surveys made by geologists aboard
the British research vessel Discovery
show the earth's crust to be 31 kilo¬
metres thick there (under the ocean, .
the crust is only about a third as
thick).
The Rockall plateau may have been
marooned far out to sea by three
separate splits of Pangaea: first,
Europe from America, then Greenland
from Europe, finally Rockall from
Greenland.
One's impression at a meeting of
marine geologists is that the ocean
bottom seems to move almost as much
as its top. It can move vertically, too:
the symposium was told that the North
Sea is subsiding under a load of sedi¬
ments 7,000 metres thick, at a rate of
one centimetre every 300 years.
Such sedimentation is a good indic¬
ation of the presence of hydrocarbons,
whether oil or gas. Along the east
Atlantic continental margin, explora¬
tion for petroleum is being carried
out by 10 countries in Europe and
twenty-three in Africa.
In the North Sea off Britain alone,
over sixty companies are working on
23 concessions. Off the west coast
of Africa, thirty-five companies have
acquired or are applying for concess¬
ions. The biggest find here has been w
the offshore Nigerian basin which, it "
was reported, would have produced °
a million barrels of oil per day last f
CONTINUED PAGE 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
BLACK GOLD
FROM
THE OCEAN BED
Man has only recently begun to exploit
the vast resources that lie on and
beneath the ocean bed. So far,
harvesting this wealth has been confined
to continental shelves in waters less
than 100 metres (350 ft) deep and
within 100 km (70 miles) of the coastline.
Currently, oil, gas and sulphur are
produced by drilling; coal and iron ore
from mines driven from land; heavy
minerals tin and diamonds by dredging;
fresh water, salt, magnesium and other
minerals from seawater. Oil and gas
represent more than 90 per cent by value
of all minerals obtained from the oceans
thus far. Left, offshore drilling platform
working through 80 metres (250 ft) of
water in the Gulf of Gascony, France.
Petroleum engineers use the diamond
studded steel drill shown below to obtain
samples from the sea bed as they
prospect for oil.
Photos Photothèque Esso
ELECTRONIC
ANCHOR
The American drilling research
vessel, "Glomar Challenger"
uses a new control system of
"dynamic anchoring" to stay on
"target" while drilling into the
ocean floor in deep water.
Diagram left shows how. Sonar
beacons placed on sea bed
send signals to hydrophones
on ship, and the signals are
fed to a computer which
automatically monitors the ship's
position and controls the
engines so that position is
maintained despite currents and
swell.' The "Glomar Challenger",
while participating in the
U.S. National Science
Foundation's deep-sea drilling
project, has established records
for the deepest water worked
in (6,140 metres) and the
deepest penetration of the
ocean bed (985 metres).
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Geophysicists and oceanographers are becoming increasingly confident about their understanding of the
development of ocean floors. From recent research a picture has been built up of a worldwide system of
mid ocean ridges from which new oceanic crust spreads out to form the ocean floors. How these ocean
ridges may have formed and how land masses drifted apart and collided are shown in these four
drawings (1) As Mid-Atlantic ridge began to develop 120 million years ago, African and Indian land
masses separated from South America. (2) About sixty million years ago, Carlsberg Ridge developed
between Africa and India, driving the latter towards Asia. (3) Thirty million years ago, another ridge formed
in the gulf of Aden and, separated by a fracture zone to north of Carlsberg Ridge, led to East African
fractures. (4) The situation today, with East African Rift continuing to develop independently. Fold
mountains (top right of drawing) including Himalayas, were a dramatic consequence of land mass collisions
from 60 to 30 million years ago.
Drawings © courtesy Science Journal
120
million
years
ago
birth of
the Mid-
Atlantic
Ridge
"
**o»
Mid-Atlaniic Ridge starting to develop
120 MILLION YEARS AGO
East African fractures
starting to develop
Carlsberg Ridge
Mid-Atlantic Ridge
30 MILLION YEARS AGO
60 MILLION YEARS AGO
'^a
\
East African R
^ Carlsberg Ridge
Mid-Allanlic Ridge
PRESENT
32
ANCIENT SUPERCONTINENT (Continued)
year if there had been no civil war.
The North Sea is supplying 1,000
million cubic feet a day of natural gas
to Great Britain. Surprisingly enough,
the sea floor also accounts for 7 per
cent of British coal production: 1 1 mill¬
ion of the 160 million tons mined
annually comes from mines that run
three to four miles out to sea off the
coasts of Cumberland and North¬
umberland with entrances to their
shafts on land. Offshore coal reserves
are estimated at 550 million tons.
Ten per cent of British gravel also
comes from the sea floor. A total of
11 million tons was dredged up in
1969 and, according to Prof. K. C.
Dunham, director of the Institute of
Geological Sciences in London, capital
investment in this industry now
amounts to £25 million.
To the north of the East Atlantic
Continental Margin, gravel comes up
by the ton; on the far south, diamonds
come up by the carat. The symposium
heard a report by R. H. Joynt of Conso¬
lidated Diamond Mines of southwest
Africa on operations near the mouth
of the Orange River.
Exploration for diamonds is not
easy. Profiles are run out from the
shore at intervals of 100 metres,
bedrock must be contoured at one
metre intervals (to the marine geolo¬
gist, this sounds like looking at the
continental shelf through a jeweller's
eyeglass). To explore gullies, divers
must crawl through them with a visi¬
bility of only 30 cm., in water at
10 degrees C.
Undersea diamond prospecting is
hard work and expensive. Only last
year, said Mr. Joynt, did the operation
show a profit. When asked how much
it represented of his firm's total
operations, he replied: "We probably
spend as much each month on postage
stamps."
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
CIGARETTES AND ADVERTISING
Sir,
Your article, "The Case Against
Smoking" (May 1970 number) says that
steps have been taken against the
advertising of tobacco in several coun¬
tries, including France. The only limit¬
ing factor in France, as far as I know,
is that the State holds the tobacco
monopoly and consequently it alone
can advertise French and foreign brands
of cigarettes. But the official orga¬
nization that handles tobacco for the
government can advertise as much as
it deems fit.
To my knowledge, there are no laws
governing the advertising of tobacco
in France. The International Code for
Fair Practice in Advertising, drawn up
by the International Chamber of Com¬
merce, can be discounted since it has
no legal force. In the United States
cigarette packets carry a warning that
smoking is a health hazard. Why not
apply the same rule to American ciga¬
rettes sold in France?
Why do we use advertising to en¬
courage people to smoke? And why do
soldiers in France receive part of their
pay as a cigarette issue (are these a
necessity of life?).
Jean Chaumien
Strasbourg, France
PORTRAIT OF MONGOLIA
Sir.
I was delighted with the article on
my country published in your November
1969 issue. Special thanks are due to
your staff and to the authors of the
article, Konrad Facknitz and Lev Kos¬
tikov, for their first rate account which
accurately describes life today in the
Mongolian People's Republic.
Jambalyn Banzar
Permanent Delegate of the
Mongolian People's Republic to Unesco
WORLD OF SILENCE
Sir,'
I am sure your magazine has contri¬
buted in a large measure to uplift, guide
and channelize the present turbulent
thinking in right directions. My vocation
is teaching the deaf children in Bombay.
Time and again your enlightened maga¬
zine has thrown light on other han¬
dicapped problems like "Blindness" etc.,
but so far I have not come across any
article in your magazine on problems of
the deaf.
The deaf are always misunderstood,
underrated, and their talents always
undermined. Public, Press and States
have not given sufficient thought to
this very vital problem. Because the
deaf wear no crutches, or bandages or
braces and look so normal their han¬
dicap has been badly ignored and
neglected all over the world. In India
the problem is colossal, although since
3-4 years people concerned with it are
trying to rouse public opinion.
The deaf have all normal faculties but
they are imprisoned in a world of no
speech and no sound. The world is
like a silent screen to them. They see
people moving and talking but without
the stimulus of hearing, the world
appears dead for them. May I therefore
request you to take up this problem
in your magazine and give it a deserving
lead.
R. R. Pavrl
Bombay, India
CAIRO'S MOUKHTAR MUSEUM
Sir,
The photo story, "The Fabulous
Treasures of Cairo's Museums", (April
1970) states that works of great Euro¬
pean artists Goya, Delacroix, Rubens,
Van Gogh, etc., and of Egyptian
painters such as Mahmoud Said and
Mohammad Negui, are displayed in
Cairo's Moukhtar Museum.
The art works in question are, in fact,
displayed in the Mohammed Mahmoud
Khalil Museum in Cairo. The Moukhtar
Museum, which was inaugurated in
1964, is exclusively devoted to the
works of the famous Egyptian sculptor,
Mahmoud Moukhtar (1891-1934).
Osman Nowaya
Cairo, U.A.R.
ROOTS OF PEACE
Sir,
Your issue on education (January
1970) was most interesting, but I was
disappointed to find no mention of the
World Association for the School as
an Instrument of Peace (President:
Jacques Muhlethaler, 5 rue du Simplón,
Geneva, Switzerland).
You presented many other subjects
the teacher shortage, how and what
to teach, etc but did not touch on
"schools and peace". In a number
dealing with "Education at the Cross¬
roads", this was a regrettable omission.
How can education be revitalized when,
as you pointed out, $4,000,000,000,000
will be spent on armaments over the
next ten years? If arms take prece¬
dence over education, Is it not because
school lessons are still concerned with
the "art" of war, because national
heroes and national victories are glo-
rirified, because other nations are term¬
ed "enemies", and other peoples not
deemed worthy of respect because they
are "different"? Furthermore, far too
much emphasis is laid on the idea of
nationalities and races. Nor are these
pressures applied only in history
lessons.
In what lessons are children taught
ideas of tolerance, service, respect and
responsibility towards others, or the
need to conquer the spirit of egotism
which creates a barrier in. human rela¬
tions.
C. Testelin
Geneva, Switzerland
LITTLE-KNOWN EDUCATOR
Sir.
I read your special number, "Edu¬
cation at the Crossroads" with great
interest, particularly the article by Paul
Lengrand, "Education put to the Ques¬
tion."
Having worked for a number of years
in the "Modern School Movement" In
France, I was delighted to find the
name of its founder, Célestin Frelnet,
figuring among those of Pestalozzi.
Dewey, Makarenko and other noted
educational reformers.
Freinet is still unknown in France,
even though the "renovation of edu¬
cation" in the country has paid lip
service to this ideas. Why not devote
space in a future issue to Freinet's life,
studies and views?
M. Ducouret
Nohant-Vicq, France
THIRD WORLD SPENDING
ON EDUCATION
Sir,
Your interesting article, "Education...
But for Whom?. ..And How?" (January
1970) states that most of the less well
off countries "despite their poverty,
devote a higher proportion of their na¬
tional income to education than do the
developed countries. The figure is
often as high as 25 per cent and
sometimes even higher..." It is obvious
that "national income" was meant to
be "national budget".
W. B. Dros
Bangkok, Thailand
Our reader is quite right. The state¬
ment "national income", should have
read "national budget" Editor.
FUTILITY OF FORCE
Sir,
Just over a year ago, Morihei Ueshi-
ba, the creator of Aïkido, died in Tokyo
at the age of 86. In his youth, Ueshiba
studied many schools of personal com¬
bat still current in Japan the Daito
school of Ju-Jitsu, Kenjutsu (fencing
with sabres), combat with lances, etc.
After much meditation, he became con¬
vinced that to achieve the ideal of
peace, the martial arts should have a
nobler aim than that of personal vic¬
tory.
The word Ai-Ki-Do means broadly,
"way of harmony of spiritual forces."
The method combines advanced physi¬
cal education with training in self
defence. Force is never countered by
force, nor aggression by aggression;
the object is not to injure an adversary
nor to humiliate him.
The aim is to dodge one's opponent
and then to immobilize him, after "har¬
monizing the opposing forces." It
demonstrates to both protagonists the
futility of brute force, and offers an
everyday means of achieving reconci¬
liation. With competitive matches
excluded, the true adept finds aggressive
urges replaced by the desire to perfect
his art.
Following the death of Morihei Ueshi¬
ba and at a time when the art of
Aikido is being spread by his disci¬
ples throughout the world (In France,
U.K., U.S., Belgium, Fed. Rep. of Ger¬
many, Italy, for example), I suggest
you tell readers more about this
movement for universal understanding
which originated, paradoxically, from
one of the martial arts.
René Le Menn
Bordeaux-Caudéran, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
mm \¡\ sa
New Unesco art slides
Unesco's second series of "Painting and
Sculpture" slides is being issued in a new
form. Each set is presented as a hard
cover book with slides fitting into pockets
In the cover. Commentaries on the works
by leading art authorities are included in
English, French, Spanish and German
language versions. Four sets are available
in the new series "Ancient Greek Sculp¬
ture", "Matisse and the Nude", "Van
Dyck" and "New Guinea Sepik Art". Eight
more are to be published at two monthly
intervals. Sets can be ordered from
Editions Rencontre, Service B, Rue du
Cherche-Midi, Paris-6*, France or from
Unesco's national agents (see inside back
cover). Price per set outside France 26.25
Fr F, or equivalent, or (for subscribers to
the series) 21.60 Fr F .
'African Scientist'
Africa's first general science magazine,
"African Scientist", has begun publication
in Nairobi (Kenya). It seeks to popularize
science, and to "help bring Africa firmly
forward into the scientific age by Inform¬
ing her fully, in scientific terms, of her
problems and those of the rest of the
universe". Published three times a year
by East African Publishing House, P.O.
Box 30571, Nairobi (price: $1.00. 8/6), the
magazine plans to become a monthly.
Americans, a people
on the move
In the U.S.A., 36,000,000 persons rough¬
ly one fifth of the population move their
homes each year according to "Labor
and Migration", an annotated bibliography
by Thomas R. Brooks, published recently
by the Brooklyn College Center for Migra¬
tion Studies, New York. The bibliography,
covering books and studies on the U.S.
internal labour force and on immigrant
labour, points out that since the "Pilgrims"
landed in America in 1620, some 44 million
immigrants have arrived from all points
of the globe.
France adds up
its art and monuments
France Is taking a nation-wide census of
its historic buildings and art treasures.
Using the latest information-processing
techniques including computer studies, the
nation-wide inventory ¡s likely to take
several decades. Following a "spotting
survey" descriptive dossiers will be pre¬
pared for the thousands of works listed
in the initial inventory. The monumental
operation is described in "Some Aspects
of French Cultural Policy", published
recently by Unesco in the series "Studies
and Documents on Cultural Policies".
Europe's latest
U.N. stamps
Two new U.N. stamps, in denominations
of 60 centimes and 10 francs (Swiss cur¬
rency), from a series of fourteen to be
issued In Geneva by the U.N. Postal Admin¬
istration in agreement with the Swiss
postal authorities, were put into circulation
on April 17. The first eight stamps in this
series were issued on October 4, 1969,
and four more will appear on September 22,
1970. Orders for the stamps should be
sent to the U.N. Postal Administration,
Palais des Nations, CH - 1211 Geneva 10,
or to any U.N.P.A. agency.
Flood warning outpost
for Venice
A floating laboratory Installed some ten
miles from the Venice Lido is to collect
weather data, including measurements of
wind strength, water temperature and
currents. Meteorologists hope it will help
them to forecast the sea surges of the
Adriatic which flood Venice periodically,
damaging its ancient buildings and threat¬
ening its monuments and works of art.
Flashes...
A Unesco Regional Office for Education
in Africa has been opened in Dakar,
Senegal.
More than 75% of Information about
the sea stored by the U.S. National Océa¬
nographie Data Center, Washington, comes
from foreign sources among them,
87,000 Japanese data stations.
The 1960s were the most prolific period
for the founding of universities in the U.K.
since the Middle Ages.
Unesco and ILO are helping the Ceylon
Government to set up a national vocational
training scheme which will triple the
number of Ceylon's vocational schools.
The U.N General Assembly has desig¬
nated the year 1971 as International Year
for Action to Combat Racism and Racial
Discrimination.
34
SSSESBMMSSKXa
ruct im jt 6C
(liLJll
i
r
^nVVBl?S
Hill
i\
OKbEOHHEBHME HA J
PEACE BELL AT THE U. N.
Left, the "Peace Bell", presented to the United
Nations by the Japanese United Nations Association,
in 1954, Is featured on 6 cent and 25 cent comme¬
morative stamps recently issued by the U.N. Postal
Administration. The "Peace Bell" was cast from
coins given by children in 60 countries. It now
stands at U.N. headquarters, New York, housed in
a reproduction of a Japanese Shinto temple made
of cypress wood. As agent in France of the U.N.
Postal Administration, Unesco's Philatelic Service stocks all U.N. stamps and
first day covers currently on sale. For details -write to the Unesco Philatelic
Service, Unesco, place de Fontenoy, Paris (7e).
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
Index Translationum - 21
(International Bibliography
of Translations)
1970 ($36, £10 15s. stg.)
Field Manual for Museums
1970 ($7, 42/-stg.)
Statistical Yearbook 1968
Population, education, science and
technology, libraries and museums,
book production, newspapers and
periodicals, paper consumption,
film and cinema, radio and TV
1969 ($24, 144/- stg.)
The Impact of Communication
on Rural Development
An investigation ¡n Costa Rica
and India
By Prodipto Roy,
Frederick B. Waisanen
and Everett M. Rogers
Co-edition: Unesco, Paris - National
Institute of Community Development,
Hyderabad, India, 1969
Science and Technology
in Asian Development
Conference on the application of
science and technology to the
development of Asia in August, 1968.
1970 ($5, 30/- stg.)
Use and Conservation of
the Biosphere
Intergovernmental conference of
experts on the scientific basis for
rational use and conservation of the
resources of the biosphere, Sep¬
tember 1968
1970 ($6, 36/- stg.)
UNESCO'S TRANSLATIONS SERIES
JAPAN
Footprints in the Snow
By Kenjiro Tokutomi
Translated by Kenneth Strong
George Allen and Unwin, Ltd.,
London, 1970 (65/- stg.) ; Pegasus,
New-York ($8.95)
Face at the Bottom of the World
and other poems
By Hagiwara Sakutaro
Translated by Graeme Wilson
Paintings by York Wilson
Charles E. Tuttle Co., Rutland, Ver¬
mont and Tokyo, Japan, 1969 ($4)
U.S.S.R.
Daredevils of Sassoun
by Léon Surmelian
George Allen and Unwin, Ltd., 1969
(30/- stg.) ; Swallow, Chicago.
INDIA
Jnaneshvari
A Song Sermon
on the Bhagavadgita
Translated from the Marathi
by V.G. Pradhan
Edited and with introduction
by H.M. Lambert
Vol. I 1967 (52/6 stg.)
Vol. II 1969 (60/- stg.)
George Allen and Unwin, Ltd.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published
Vacation study abroad XIX
Cours de vacances à l'étranger
Cursos de vacaciones en el extranjero
Vacation courses and scholarships
Cours et bourses de vacances
Cursos y becas des vacaciones
Unesco
Trilingual : English-French-Spanish
93 pages 9/- $1.50 6 F
Vacation
study
abroad
An indispensable Unesco guide to oppor¬
tunities for stimulating study and travel
abroad.
The present edition gives full facts on:
SHORT COURSES
SEMINARS
SUMMER SCHOOLS
SCHOLARSHIPS AND TRAVEL GRANTS
available each year to students, teachers and
others. Information comes from over 500
organizations in 54 countries.
Where to renew your subscription
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See lift
below ; namei of distributors In countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzat. Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Publications : Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O.
Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW ; Periodicals :
Dominie Pty. Limited, Box 33, Post Office, Brook¬
vale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent. United Nations As¬
sociation of Australia, Victorian Division, 4th
Floor, Askew Houss, 364 Lonsdale St., Melbourne
(Victoria), 3000. ($ 2.75). AUSTRIA. Verla; Georg
Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (AS 82)
BELGIUM. All publications: Editions "Labor", 342, rue
Royale, Brussels, 3. Presses Universitaires de Bruxelles,
42, av. Paul Héger, Brussels 5. NV Standaard-We-
tenschappelijke Uitgeverij Belgiëlei 1 47, Antwerp, I. For
the Unesco Courier (1 70 FB) and art slides (488 FB) only:
Jean de Lannoy, 112, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP
3380.00. BURMA. Trade Corporation N- (9), 550-
552 Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Queen's
Printer, Ottawa, Ont. ($ 4.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244
Colombo, 2. (Rs 12.50) World Book Co.
Ltd., 99 Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa). CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1 722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1
(permanent display); Zahranicni literatura 1 1 Soukenicka
Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard, Ltd.,
6, Norregade, 11*5, Copenhagen K. (Dan. Kr. 19.00).
ETHIOPIA. National Commission for Unesco, P.O.
Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 11.90).
FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy,
Paris-7». C.C.P. 12598-48. (12 F). - GERMANY. All
publications: R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse
145,8 Munich, 80. For the Unesco Kurier(Germanedonly)
Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 1 60, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P.
276650 (DM 12). GHANA. Methodist Book Depot
Ltd., Atlantic House, Commercial Street, POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. -
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens; Librairie Eleftheroudakis, Nikkis 4, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 13-1 5 Lock Road,
Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Kónyvesbolt,
Vici u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtarosok Boltja,
Népkoztirsasâg utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H.F.. Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykiavik.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd., Nicol Road, Ballard.
Estate, Bombay 1 ; 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3 ;
36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; 3/5 Asaf AM Road, New
Delhi 1 ; Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16 and Scindia House, New Del¬
hi; Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Youth
Services, 72 Theatre Communication Building, Connaught
Place New Delhi 1. (Rs. 13.50). INDONESIA.
Indira P. T., D|l. Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37, Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, 1/1 54
Avenue Roosevelt, B.P. 1 533, Teheran. McKen¬
zie'* Bookshop, AI- Ràshid Street, Baghdad ; University
Bookstore, University of Baghdad, P.O. Box 75, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press,2.Wellmgton Road, Balls-
bridge, Dublin, 4. ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly
Blumstein's Bookstores, 35 Allenby Road and 48 Nahlat
Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (IL. 12.50.) JAMAICA. Sang-
ster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.Box 366, 101 Water Lane,
Kingston. - JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., P.O. Box 5050,
Tokyo International 1 00-31. JORDAN. Joseph I. Bahous
S Co., Dar-ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. The E.S.A. Limited, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd., P.O. Box 2942, Kuwait. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286.
Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 261, Tripoli.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück. 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg (F.L. 1 70). -MALAYSIA. Federal Publica¬
tions Sdn Bhd., Balai Berita, 31 Jalan Riong, Kuala Lum¬
pur. MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kingsway, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30,
Bid. des Moulins, Monte Carlo. NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 10). NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. G. C.
T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Cura¬
çao. N.A. (NA fl 5.25). - NEW ZEALAND. Govern¬
ment Printing Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland
Street, P.O. Box 5344. Auckland ; 130 Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721,Chnstchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton ; Princes Street, P. O. Box 1 1 04, Dunedin ; Mul-
grave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. (S 2.15) NOR¬
WAY. All publications : A.S. Bokh|ornet, Akersgt 41 -Oslo
1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Litteratur-
jeneste. Box 61 25, Oslo 6 (K.2.75). PAKISTAN. The
West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publication House,
P.O. Box 374 G. P.O., Lahore ; Showrooms: Urdu Bazar, La¬
hore, and 57-58 Murree Highway, G/ 6- 1, Islamabad. Pakis¬
tan Publications Bookshop, Sarwar Road, Rawalpindi ; Pari-
bagh, Dacca. PHILIPPINES.The Modern Book Co., 928.
Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box632, Manila. -POLAND, «li publi¬
cations: ORWN PAN Palac Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw
For the Unesco Courier only : RUCH, ul. Wronia, 23,
Warsaw 1 0. PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda.Livraria
Portugal, rua de Carmo 70, Lisbon . PUERTO RICO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115.
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. SINGAPORE. Federal Pu¬
blications Sdn Bhd., Times House, River Valley Road, Sin¬
gapore 9. SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales
(PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury. SUDAN.
AI Bashir Bookshop, P. O. Box 1118. Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications : A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2. Box 16356, 103 27 Stock¬
holm 16. For the Unesco Courier : Svenska FN.
Forbundet, Vasagatan 1 5, IV 1 01 23 Stockholm 1
Postgiro 18 46 92 (Kr. 18) SWITZERLAND.
All publications: Europa Verlag, 5 RSmistrasse,
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, C.C.P. 1-236. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panic, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
(37.50baht).TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 1 45, Kampala. AFRICA.
All publications: Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty). Ltd.,
Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central
News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie
Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. Sub-agent:
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham and Bristol. (20/-). UNITED STATES.
Unesco Publications Center, P.O. Box 433, New York,
N.Y. 1001 6 ($ 5). U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga .Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zaluzba Slovenije
Mestni Trg. 26, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
i * x a m * : m m x it it
"->*<?,«-«!>,.-
ÎftxtAlOM*« 12-1966
¥ 100
THE UNESCO
COURIER
The illustrated monthly with
a unique international out¬
look, dealing with the major
problems and questions of
our time. Recent issues
published on:
Spïn-off, the fruits of space
research on earth
The race between education
and catastrophe
The ancient civilization of the
Kushans of Central Asia
The fight against cancer
The new food revolution
Can we keep our planet
habitable?
Peaceful uses of the atom
Youth in ferment
Japan, a century of
extraordinary development
Abuse of drugs: the growing
The Parthenon in danger
/^sL«w3tvJ} ^
' ^^ \^++
*---*l>-^VI"'Sr^*ï*ï,J *-r*
Courrier
NOTRE PLANÈTE
DEVIENT-ELLE
INHABITABLE ?
>Â I h
Corriere
Correo
contra el
CANCER
ATTENTI mí Wr
ALLA ¿^W.
DROGA . (
w
PaûCTlim fc-ntdeekun<í der ersten
JLctrColtUXIl klaKsisehffriechisehen F
Offer a gift subscription
to friends and relatives
Annual subscription
20 - stg.
$4.00 (Canada)
12 F (France)
Single copies
2/- stg.
40 cents (Canada)
1.20 F (France)
(Order from Unesco agents listed page 35)
Published monthly in 12 languages
!-««» **C<&* UWaW
ÄÖbxiftiJUr
(V
]]>
</page>
</document>
