<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="192261eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ISSN 2220-2285
e-ISSN 2220-2293
Women
conquering 
new expanses 
of freedom
Global champion for women
Michelle Bachelet
Putting Kyrgyzstan on the map
Roza Otunbayeva
A matter of commitment
Michaëlle Jean 
Rights won, freedoms lost 
Sana Ben Achour
Crime without punishment
Aminetou Mint El Moctar
Afraid of nothing
Sultana Kamal 
A lawyer with thick skin
Asma Jahangir 
Standing up to tyranny
Mónica González Mujica 
Slowly but surely  
Humaira Habib
Stars in my personal galaxy
Luisa Futoransky 
April-June  2011
United Nations 
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization,
Courier
THE UNESCO
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
OUR AUTHORS
Gender equality is a necessary condition for achieving all
internationally agreed development objectives. Central to efforts to
fight extreme poverty, it is also related to limiting the spread of HIV
and AIDS, mitigating the effects of climate change and achieving
sustainable development and peace.
UNESCO has always supported women’s and girls’ rights and has
made gender equality one of its global priorities. In education, it strives
to redress inequalities in access and quality at all levels. This includes
the promotion of women’s increased participation in science,
technology, innovation and research.
UNESCO also aims to address the stereotyping of
women and inequalities in women’s access to
and participation in all communication
and information systems. It raises
awareness among professionals of
the need to include a gender equality
perspective in media content and
organizes training to enhance the
security skills of women journalists. 
The Organization also works towards women’s
empowerment and gender equality by integrating these
considerations into its normative work in areas such as the
ethics of science, culture and human rights.
Within UNESCO, the Division for Gender Equality is the key
contact for ensuring the implementation of “Priority Gender
Equality”, the 2008-2013 action plan that serves as its roadmap.
Noémie Antony
Laura Martel
(France) Sultana Kamal
(Bangladesh) 
Sana Ben Achour
(Tunisia)
Katrin Bennhold 
(Germany)
Feriel Lalami-Fates
(Algeria)
Aminetou Mint El Moctar
(Mauritania) 
Navin Chawla
Anbarasan Ethirajan
Shiraz Sidhva
(India)
Lautaro Pozo 
(Ecuador)
Lorena Aguilar 
(Costa Rica)
Michelle Bachelet
Mónica González Mujica 
(Chile)
Roza Otunbayeva
(Kyrgyzstan)
Michaëlle Jean
(Canada) 
Asma Jahangir
(Pakistan)
Giusy Muzzopappa
(Italy)
Humaira Habib
(Afghanistan)
Luisa Futoransky
(Argentina)
Ernest Pépin
(Guadeloupe)
Princess Loulwah
(Saudi Arabia)
Maggy Barankitse
(Burundi)
I “Scutum”, bronze by Annette Jalilova. © Annette JALILOVA, Paris
Gender Equality:  
A priority for UNESCO
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:53  Page 2
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
©
 a
ll 
ri
g
h
ts
 r
e
se
rv
e
d
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 3
Editorial – Irina Bokova, Director-General of UNESCO       5
SPECIAL REPORT: Women conquering new expanses of freedom
Global champion for women 7
Interview with Michelle Bachelet by Jasmina Šopova
Women political leaders  Shiraz Sidva 9
Putting Kyrgyzstan on the map 13
Interview with Roza Otunbayeva by Katerina Markelova
A matter of commitment 15
Interview with Michaëlle Jean by Katerina Markelova   
Crime without punishment 17
Interview with Aminetou Mint El Moctar by Laura Martel 
Mama Maggy and her 20,000 children 20
Jasmina Šopova meets Maggy Barankitse 
Afraid of nothing 22
Interview with Sultana Kamal by Anbarasan Ethirajan 
A lawyer with thick skin 25
Interview with Asma Jahangir by Irina Zoubenko-Laplante
Rights won, freedoms lost – Sana Ben Achour 28
Now or never – Giusy Muzzopappa 30
Standing up to tyranny 32
Interview with Mónica González Mujica by Carolina Jerez and Lucía Iglesias
Slowly but surely – Humaira Habib 34
Conquering the job market – Feriel Lalami-Fates 36
Gender Equality: a Global Public Good  37
Sanye Gulser Corat and Estelle R. Raimondo 
Davos Forum: women are the future – Katrin Bennhold 39
Sowing the seeds of the future 41
Interview with Lorena Aguilar by Alfredo Trujillo Fernandez
Stars in my personal galaxy – Luisa Futoransky  43
Mother Teresa, the most powerful woman in the world – Navin Chawla 47
Manuela Sáenz, the liberator of the Liberator – Lautaro Pozo 48
POSTSCRIPT 
Homage to Édouard Glissant: The Philosophy of Tout-Monde 50
Ernest Pépin
Youth is the country’s wealth 52
Interview with Princess Loulwah of Saudi Arabia by Linda Tinio                                           
Universal thought: Tagore, Neruda, Césaire, poetry in the service of a
new humanism – Noémie Antony and Jasmina Šopova
Courier
THE UNESCO April–June 2011
United Nations 
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
64th year
2011 – No. 2 
The UNESCO Courier is currently a quarterly published in
seven languages by the United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, place de Fontenoy 75352, Paris 07 SP, France
Free subscription to the Courier on line:
www.unesco.org/courier
Director of publication: Eric Falt
Editor-in-chief: Jasmina Šopova 
j.sopova@unesco.org
Assistant editor: Katerina Markelova
k.markelova@unesco.org 
Editors: 
Arabic: Khaled Abu Hijleh 
Chinese: Weiny Cauhape
English: Cathy Nolan
French: Françoise Arnaud-Demir
Portuguese: Ana Lúcia Guimarães
Russian: Irina Krivova
Spanish: Francisco Vicente-Sandoval
Photos: Ariane Bailey  
Design and layout: Baseline Arts Ltd, Oxford
Printing: UNESCO – CLD
Information and reproduction rights: 
+ 33 (0)1 45 68 15 64 . k.markelova@unesco.org
Web platform: Chakir Piro and Van Dung Pham
With thanks to: Elisabeth Cloutier and Marie-Christine
Pinault Desmoulin
Articles and photos credited UNESCO may be reproduced
and/or translated for non-commercial purposes providing
the credit line reads “Reproduced from the UNESCO
Courier” and includes date and hyperlink. Photos without
UNESCO credit require  special permission.
Articles express the opinions of the authors and do not 
necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO.
Photographs belonging to UNESCO may be reproduced
freely. Photos must carry the following caption: © UNESCO
and photographer's name. For high resolution, please
contact the Photobank: photobank@unesco.org 
Boundaries on maps do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations
of the countries and territories concerned.
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:54  Page 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
This year, we celebrate the 100th
anniversary of the first international
demonstration staged by thousands of
women on both sides of the Atlantic to
demand the right to vote. So much for
the past. Looking to the future, 2011
marks a turning point just as significant
for international women’s rights – the
launch of UN Women.
Michelle Bachelet, who headlines
this issue as the first Executive Director
of the new United Nations agency,
explains its whys and wherefores (p. 7).
Also prominent among the women who
are taking over the international
political scene, Rosa Otunbayeva
describes her mandate as first woman
president of Kyrgyzstan (p. 13) and
Michaëlle Jean, former Governor
General of Canada, the pact of solidarity
with Haiti, her country of origin.
While progress towards gender
parity in politics remains slow (pp. 9-12),
women are gaining ground more
quickly in the human rights arena. There
too, women need a strong hand to
break society’s shackles, like Aminetou
Mint El Moctar from Mauritania (p. 17),
Maggy Barankitse from Burundi (p. 20),
Sultana Kamal from Bangladesh (p. 23),
Asma Jahangir from Pakistan (p. 25) and
Sana Ben Achour from Tunisia (p. 28).
And showing the determination
necessary to ensure success, Italian
women rallied all over the world to
defend their dignity (p. 30).
This arduous campaign cannot
succeed without the media. Two
women who have risked their lives to
defend freedom of expression, one from
Chile and the other from Afghanistan,
comment on what “women’s journalism”
can represent in certain situations (pp
32-35).
Because decent work was a central
theme of this year’s celebration of
International Women’s Day, we also
highlight the situation of Algerian
women, caught in the trap of job
insecurity. If we mention work, we are
talking about economics, another
crucial factor in women’s freedom. We
see signs at an international level that
women’s image and place are starting to
change in this realm, long the exclusive
domain of men. Locally, we note that
women’s role in agriculture contributes
to safeguarding the environment and
mitigating the effects of climate change
(pp. 36-42).
To close our special report, we
rediscover, thanks to Argentine poet
Luisa Futoransky, several women who
earned distinction in the arts and
literature (pp. 43-46), as well as Mother
Teresa – we are celebrating the 100th
anniversary of her birth – and Manuela
Sáenz from Ecuador, fighting fearlessly
for Latin America (pp. 47-48).
In addition, we present a tribute to
Édouard Glissant (1928-2011), former
editor-in-chief of the UNESCO Courier;
interview Princess Loulwah of Saudi
Arabia; and introduce a new UNESCO
project about Rabindranath Tagore,
Aimé Césaire and Pablo Neruda.
Jasmina Šopova
In this issue
4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:54  Page 4
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
Irina Bokova
“To be female in this place is to be an open wound
that cannot heal. Even if scars form, the festering is
ever below,” wrote Toni Morrison1 in   “A Mercy”,
which to me is one of the most poignant novels
ever written about being a woman. The lives of
four women – European, African, Native American
and a mysterious young girl who comes out of the
sea – are intermingled, all of them tragic,
inextricably linked to each other and deeply
rooted in the soil that would a century later give
birth to the United States. These four powerful
female characters stand like caryatids supporting
the emerging American society. And yet, the
author says, they are “open wounds”. Is it the
common fate of women throughout the world to
be both the pillars and the victims of society?
Obviously the situation of women has
undergone considerable evolution. The
International Council of Women (ICW), founded in
1888, followed by the International Alliance of
Women (IAW) in 1904 and the Women
International Democratic Federation (WIDF) in
1945, have played a crucial role in the struggle for
gender equality.
Gender equality lies at the heart of human
rights and fundamental freedoms, which are
essential for the dignity of individuals, for healthy
societies, and for the rule of law. Second, equality
between men and women is a powerful
accelerator of political, social and economic
transformation. Gender equality is a core
development issue. It is also a security issue. Girls
and women suffer disproportionately from armed
conflict. They are also very often the best
advocates for reconciliation. Finally, the last
hundred years have taught us that gender
equality is everyone’s job. Governments are key,
but so are civil society and business, teachers and
administrators, cultural personalities and the
L “Ames“ (Souls),
sculptures by
French artist Hélène
Hiribarne.
© Alicia Cloeren, Texas
1. American novelist Toni Morrison won the Nobel
Prize for Literature in 1993. 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 5
I Irina Bokova visiting
the Tombs of Buganda
Kings at Kasubi (Uganda)
with the Ugandan
Minister of Education and
Sports Geraldine
Namirembe Bitamawire
and the Permanent
Delegate to UNESCO
Elizabeth Paula Napeyok 
© UNESCO/Tosin
Animashawun
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:54  Page 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
media. The international community plays its part
by setting goals and mobilizing support to reach
them.
UNESCO seeks to tighten the link between
gender and the internationally-agreed
development goals. We made this case in 2010
during the 15th anniversary of the Fourth World
Conference on Women in Beijing. We took it to the
Millennium Development Goals Summit in New
York last September. Working with the Republic of
Korea, we pushed education higher on the
agenda of the G20 summit in Seoul. I made the
same argument at the 2011 World Economic
Forum in Davos. Throughout all of this, we worked
closely with the United Nations Girls Education
Initiative and we will continue with the newly-
created UN Women, led by Michelle Bachelet.
Gender equality is woven through the work of
all UNESCO sectors. It has inspired me in
reforming the Organization itself. It guides our
activities on the ground – including in difficult
settings, in Afghanistan and Iraq as well as in
Pakistan. During my recent visit to the Democratic
Republic of Congo, I signed an agreement with
the Government to establish a research and
documentation Centre on Women, Gender and
Peace-building. Located in Kinshasa, this UNESCO
Category 2 Centre will address an issue of vital
importance for human rights, social stability and
development for the Great Lakes Region.
Remembering a visit in the 1980s to
northwest Zimbabwe, her country of origin, Doris
Lessing said, “That poor girl trudging through the
dust, dreaming of an education for her children,
do we think that we are better than she is - we,
stuffed full of food, our cupboards full of clothes,
stifling in our superfluities? I think it is that girl,
and the women who were talking about books
and an education when they had not eaten for
three days, that may yet define us.”2
Beyond the limits of her fiction, the author
was reaffirming her faith in women, even the most
EXPLORE THE COURIER ARCHIVES
See a selection of special reports and articles on women. Enter title in the “Custom Search” box at: http://www.unesco.org/
10 SPECIAL REPORTS
Women between two shores (2008)
Women’s long march to power (2000)
Women: one half of heaven (1995)
Women speak out on the environment (1992)
Women: tradition and change (1985)
The invisible woman (1980)
Turning point for women (1975)
International Women's Year (1975)
Women in the new Asia (1964)
Are women inferior beings? (1955)
10 ARTICLES 
Chiapas women invest in the future (2005)
Afghan women: knowledge and revolt (2001)
For East Europe's women, a rude awakening (2000)
Questioning the ABCs of women's literacy (1999)
Kabul: women in the shadows (1998)
When women are the spoils of war (1998)
Women in the front line (1997)
Africa's women muralists (1995)
Dreams of twenty young women (1994)
The forgotten ones (1993)
disadvantaged. UNESCO has other ways of
reaffirming the same faith. Beyond the limits of
her fiction, the author was reaffirming her faith in
women, even the most disadvantaged. UNESCO
has other ways of reaffirming the same faith. To
empower the world’s poorest girls and women,
we will launch a new initiative on girls’ education
that will engage official and private sector
partners This will focus on the innovative use of
new technologies to expand basic education and
literacy, on the education of women and girls in
situations of conflict and natural disasters, and on
system-wide policy frameworks and teacher
training. To empower the world’s poorest girls and
women, we will launch a new initiative on girls’
education that will engage official and private
sector partners This will focus on the innovative
use of new technologies to expand basic
education and literacy, on the education of
women and girls in situations of conflict and
natural disasters, and on system-wide policy
frameworks and teacher training.
There has been progress. The 2011 Education
for All Global Monitoring Report shows that
gender parity has improved in primary enrolment
since the start of the decade, especially in
countries that featured the greatest gaps. But
disparities have increased at the secondary level,
notably in Africa. And while women are making
breakthroughs in higher education in all regions,
they still account for only 29 percent of
researchers. The share of illiterate women has not
changed over the last 20 years: women still
represent two-thirds of the world’s 796 million
illiterates.
The French writer Antoine de Saint Exupéry
once wrote, “If you want to build a ship, don't herd
people together to collect wood and don't assign
them tasks and work, but rather teach them to long
for the endless immensity of the sea.” A longing for
the endless immensity of the sea has guided us
since 1911. It still inspires us today. ■
2. Doris Lessing’s acceptance
speech for the 2007 Nobel
Prize for literature 
6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:54  Page 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Inequality between men and
women remains deeply
rooted in many societies.
Women are too often denied
access to education and
health care, they face
occupational segregation
and gender wage gaps, they
are under-represented in
decision-making processes
and they suffer violence.
Michelle Bachelet takes on
these challenges as the first
Executive Director of UN
Women, the new United
Nations Entity for Gender
Equality and the
Empowerment of Women.
Can you tell us what inspired you to
make violence against women one of
the key priorities of UN Women? And
what types of violence are women
subjected to in the world?
Violence against women is one of the
most widespread human rights
violations. It is one of five priority areas
UN Women will focus on because
making progress in this area can
accelerate progress for women across
many fields. For example, a woman who
lives free from violence has much better
prospects to find a good job, seek an
education, care for her health and act as
a leader in her community or elsewhere.
Women face many types of violence.
Many societies in the world today have
some elements of this, and the
prevalence rates can be as high as 76%
if you look at women across their
lifetimes. Specific forms of violence
include domestic violence, rape, sexual
violence as a weapon of war, early
marriage and female genital mutilation.
What other priorities are you planning
on tackling and how will you mobilize
the necessary resources to achieve
your goals?
We will actively support and look for
creative ways to empower women
economically, increase women’s roles as©
 U
N
 P
h
o
to
/M
a
rt
in
e
 P
e
rr
e
t
A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 7
Global
champion
for
women
MICHELLE BACHELET was interviewed by Jasmina Šopova
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:54  Page 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
leaders and advocates of change, bring
women to the centre of peace and
security processes, and integrate gender
equality priorities across national
planning. Part of mobilizing resources to
achieve these goals will be to
demonstrate how much of a
contribution women make to
development, not just for themselves,
but for their societies at large. There is
growing evidence of this. The most
recent World Economic Forum Global
Gender Gap Index Report, for example,
shows that out of 114 countries, it is
those with greater gender equality that
are more competitive and grow faster. 
What human and financial resources
does UN Women currently have at its
disposal? Is it enough to achieve your
mission?
UN Women inherited the resources of
the four UN entities that have been
combined to create it. Building on these
resources and moving forward, as
recommended in the Secretary-General’s
comprehensive proposal of January
2010, a minimum annual budget of US
$500 million is foreseen. This is the
target we will be working towards.
Are you planning to prioritize certain
countries? If so, which ones, and for
what reasons?
We will work with all UN Member States
that request our assistance, both
developing and developed countries. UN
Women currently has varying presence
in approximately 80 countries and we
will need to strengthen our exiting
presence in some countries where there
is the greatest need. We will be doing this
over time and as we build our
institutional capacities and resources.
Within countries, a priority will be to
reach the most marginalized groups of
women. They are the most in need of UN
Women’s support and reaching them can
make the most effective use of our
resources. As  UNICEF has started to
demonstrate, investing in the most
marginalized part of the population
offers higher rates of return.
What is the role of gender equality in
the Millenium Development Goals?
How do you plan to give it more
importance?
Achieving Gender equality – Goal three,
is fundamental to achieving all of the
other MDG goals. We will continue to
advocate  on the  critical  linkage
between gender equality and all the
other goals—on poverty, health,
education, the environment —as we
move towards the target date of 2015. 
One MDG issue that is particularly
important is maternal mortality.
Globally, we have not made nearly
enough progress. We can—and must—
do much more. Saving more lives in
childbirth requires basic knowledge and
inexpensive tools that could be readily
available everywhere, if governments
and the international community
decide to really make that a priority.
The number of women elected as
Heads of State and Government and of
UN Agencies has been rising in the past
few years. Has this already had
positive effects on critical issues
concerning women around the world? 
If we look back in time, we can see that
enormous progress has been made over
the last 100 years. Although challenges
remain, gender equality has a
momentum that it has never had before
at any other point in history. This is true
both on the international level and in
most countries. 
This is because women have taken
leadership roles as advocates for gender
equality—at many levels, whether in
communities or as heads of state.
Women leaders have made sure that a
growing number of people understand
that we must bring women fully into
our economies, we must end violence
against women, we must tap into
women’s capacities as agents for
changes that benefit everyone. And that
we must bring resources and take the
actions necessary to achieve these
goals—as we have now done in part
through the creation of UN Women as a
global champion for women. ■
Michelle Bachelet, who trained as a surgeon, is the first Under-Secretary-General
and Executive Director of UN Women. The former President of Chile (2006 to 2010)
was noted for her government’s investment in pension reform, social protection
programmes for women and children, and research and development, despite the
financial crisis. Other initiatives included tripling the number of free early child-care
centres for low-income families and the completion of some 3,500 child-care
centres around the country. On 14 September 2010 when she became chief of the
new UN agency, Ms Bachelet pledged to make it a “strong champion” for gender
equality.
UN Women
In July 2010, the United Nations General Assembly created UN Women to accelerate
the Organization’s goals on gender equality and the empowerment of women.
Launched officially on 24 February 2011, UN Women merges four parts of the UN
system: the Division for the Advancement of Women (DAW), International Research and Training Institute for the
Advancement of Women (INSTRAW), Office of the Special Adviser on Gender Issues and Advancement of Women (OSAGI)
and the United Nations Development Fund for Women (UNIFEM). 
UN Women’s main goal is to support inter-governmental bodies and Member States in their formulation of global and
national policies, standards and norms on gender equality. It can also hold the UN system accountable for its own
commitments on gender equality, including regular monitoring of system-wide progress.
Website: http://www.unwomen.org/ 
©
 U
N
 P
h
o
to
/J
o
h
n
 M
c
Il
w
a
in
e
8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
While most countries acknowledge that
the representation of women in
decision-making structures is crucial for
change, women are rare at the highest
levels of decision-making. The Inter-
Parliamentary Union reports that
despite increased numbers of women in
parliaments, with an all-time global high
of 19.1% in both houses of parliament,
“the target of gender balance in politics
is still a distant one in many countries.” 
There have been some remarkable
stories, however, in the last few decades,
of women who have managed to
shatter the highest of glass ceilings,
surmounting all odds to enter a
predominantly male bastion. These
path-breaking women have managed
to make a difference in their countries,
while inspiring other women across the
globe to make sure their voices are
heard when policies affecting their
societies are being formulated.
Women like Ellen Johnson Sirleaf,
who made history in 2006, when she
was elected President of Liberia, making
her the first female head of state in
Africa. A champion of women’s rights,
the Harvard-educated President said
throughout her campaign that if she
won, it would encourage women across
Africa to seek high political office. The
devoted grandmother figure who has
braved prison and exile in her 30-year
political career, has shown a steely
determination to install peace in a
country ravaged by a decade of conflict.
Johnson Sirleaf was recently
presented the African Gender Award
2011, recognizing “Liberia’s efforts in the
enhancement of women’s rights with a
strong emphasis on girls’ education,
economic empowerment and
legislation to curb violence against
women.” “By promoting gender equality
and empowering our girls, we are also
SHIRAZ SIDHVA, USA-based Indian journalist
Women
political leaders
Some of history’s greatest leaders have been women, and yet, female political leaders are
rare in modern democracies. There have been fewer than 50 female heads of state in
recent times, and today, only 20 of the world’s 192 countries have women leaders at the
helm. In politics, progress towards gender parity may be slow but it is inevitable.
L Group shot of participants at the third forum
of the UN Alliance of Civilizations held in Rio de
Janeiro, Brazil, in May 2010. The only woman:
Cristina Fernández de Kirchner, President of
Argentina  © UN Photo/Evan Schneider.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 9
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
“lifting Liberia,” President Johnson
Sirleaf said in a recent speech to women
graduates who participated in an
economic empowerment programme. 
Iceland’s former President Vigdís
Finnbogadóttir also stresses the role of
education in women’s empowerment.
“My message to the women of the
world: get educated as much as you
can, and never accept a shorter
education than your brother. Skills,
reading, knowing what life is about, are
very important. Not everybody can go
to universities, but if your brothers are
lorry-drivers, learn something that can
be compared to that,” she urges.
President Vigdís, as she is known in
Iceland, became the world’s first
independently elected female president
in 1980..  “I paved the way, not only for
women, but also for men, in politics.
Because as soon as a woman succeeds,
she is paving the way for other women
and societies around the world,” she
points out. 
Iceland, along with other Nordic
countries, continues to top the world in
gender equality, and currently has a
woman prime minister, Jóhanna
Sigurdardóttir, at its helm. But when
President Vigdís got elected 30 years
ago, “it was considered so absurd that a
woman could lead a country. I think my
Icelanders were so courageous to take
that step. It was really breaking a
tradition.” Other women leaders that
preceded her, including Indira Gandhi of
India, Isabel Perón of Argentina, and
Sirimavo Bandaranaike of Sri Lanka,
came to power as “legacy leaders”,
taking over from their fathers or
husbands, while Israel’s Golda Meir and
Britain’s Margaret Thatcher were
nominated by their country’s political
parties. President Vigdís, who did not
belong to a political party, was re-
elected to the Presidency four
consecutive times (between 1980 and
1996), making her the world’s longest-
serving female political leader.  “The first
time, I won by a narrow margin, the
second time, it was not (narrow) .
Because then I had proved it was
possible that I could succeed as a
woman, and in spite of being a woman.” 
When it comes to leadership, does
gender really matter and does it affect
leadership qualities? The contexts in
which these and other women leaders
have emerged are entirely different, and
yet, research by political pundits shows
that certain traits are common among
women leaders. What are the obstacles
that women face to attain the highest
office in their lands? What are the
qualities that have allowed these
leaders to shatter the toughest of all
glass ceilings to blaze new trails, often
with no role models to follow? 
These were some of the questions
that intrigued Laura Liswood, a lawyer,
writer and international advocate for
women’s rights. As part of the Women’s
Leadership project in the United States,
of which she was director, she
embarked on an unprecedented
journey across the globe in 1992 to
interview 15 women leaders. Her
interviews with women presidents and
prime ministers – including Margaret
Thatcher, Gro Brundtland, Benazir
Pratibha Patil 
President of India
© Office of the President of India 
Jóhanna Sigurdardóttir 
Prime Minister of Iceland
© UNPhoto/Aliza Eliazarov 
Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf
President of Liberia
© UNESCO/Michel Ravassard
Laura Chinchilla 
President of Costa Rica
© UN Photo/Aliza Eliazarov
Jadranka Kosor 
Prime Minister of Croatia
©  UN Photo/Jenny Rockett  
Dalia Grybauskaitė
President of Lithuania
©  UNPhoto/Rick Bajornas
Angela Merkel
Chancellor of Germany
© UN Photo/Evan Schneider 
Mary McAleese
President of Ireland
© UN Photo/Evan Schneider 
Dilma Rousseff 
President of Brazil
©  Roberto Stuckert Filho/Presidência
da República/Agencia Brasil
1 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
some cases, gender matters very little,”
explains Michael A. Genovese, Professor
of Political Science, and Director of the
Institute for Leadership Studies at
Loyola Marymount University,
California.  “Margaret Thatcher serves as
an example of this. In other cases,
gender matters a good deal. Here,
Corazon Aquino comes to mind.”
According to him, it is “better to ask
when and under what circumstances
gender becomes more or less important.
There are built-in structural forces that
all leaders face, forces which compel
them to perform certain tasks and
responsibilities in similar or expected
ways:  ceremonial duties, constitutional
or legal requirements, role expectations.
These all bring out more or less common
responses from both male and female
leaders. It is in new and unstructured, or
crisis times that gender can make a great
deal of difference, situations where there
are not clear role expectations to fulfill.
Here, personality and gender differences
can make a huge difference.”
Not surprisingly, most women
leaders bring formidable educational
and professional qualifications to their
positions.  Many of them are authors,
lawyers, diplomats, and ministers before
taking on the top job in their countries.
A majority of claim that, besides
education, their main inspiration came
from a strong role model in childhood,
invariably a father or mother, who made
them believe that girls were as capable
as boys when it came to achieving
things.   
Michelle Bachelet, who was the first
female president of Chile, and before
that, the country’s first female Defence
minister is no stranger to blazing new
trails. “As a young mother and a
paediatrician, I experienced the
struggles of balancing family and career
and saw how the absence of childcare
prevented women from paid
employment,” she said, addressing a
crowd in Liberia on International
Women’s Day.   “The opportunity to help
remove these barriers was one of the
reasons I went into politics. It is why I
supported policies that extended health
and childcare services to families and
prioritized public spending for social
protection.”
Do women have different styles of
leadership that distinguish them from
men?  “It is commonly believed that
men exhibit more of a command style,
and women a more collegial style of
leadership,” explains Genovese, an
authority on global and national leaders
and author of 28 books. “While this
generalization has many exceptions,
there is something to the distinction.
Men tell, women talk. Men do
monologues, women have discussions,”
Genovese says.  “In terms of different
issues that might be promoted, it may
Bhutto, Corazon Aquino and Kazimiera
Prunskiene, former prime minister of
Lithuania, to name just a few – resulted
in a seminal book: Women World
Leaders: Fifteen Great Politicians Tell
Their Stories.
Women’s leadership
Political scientists have long debated
the role of gender in leadership. “In
Iveta Radicová  
Prime Minister of Slovakia
© European People's Party 
Micheline Calmy-Rey 
President of Switzerland
© Patrick Lazic/OIF
Cissé Mariam Kaïdama Sidibé
Prime Minister of Mali
© Primature du Mali
Rosario Fernández Figueroa 
Prime Minister of Peru
© Prime Minister’s office 
Sheikh Hasina Wajed 
Prime Minister of Bangladesh
© UNPhoto/ Eskinder Debebe 
Kamla Persad-Bissessar 
Prime Minister of Trinidad-and-
Tobago  © UN Photo/Aliza Eliazarov
Cristina Fernández de Kirchner
 of Argentina
© UNPhoto/Jean Marc Ferre
Julia Gillard  
Prime Minister of Australia© UN
Photo/Mark Garten
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 11
Tarja Halonen
President of Finland
© UN Photo/Erin Siegal 
President
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
come as a surprise that women tend not
to aggressively promote “women’s
issues” when in office any more than
most men. Here differences of ideology
and partisanship are better indicators of
support for what are traditionally
thought of as women’s issues:
education, welfare support, etc.” 
Entrenched prejudice
Unlike their male counterparts, female
leaders in today’s democracies are
compelled to navigate deeply-
entrenched public prejudices, and are
judged more harshly than men by the
media and the people who elect them.
“There is no glass ceiling, just a thick
layer of men,” insists Liswood. In 1996,
Liswood co-founded  the Council of
Women World Leaders with President
Vigdís, and was appointed its secretary
general. “The urgency lies in preparing
women now for positions of influence, a
goal that cannot be achieved without
role models who are willing to foster
others in this direction,” Liswood says,
and this is where the Council is best
equipped to step in. 
In 1997, Liswood co-founded The
White House Project dedicated to
electing a woman president in the
United States. “I kept hearing so many
similar stories,” she says. “Experiences
were the same, though the leaders were
from different nations, cultures and
backgrounds. They seemed to have
received the same treatment for
reporters and their readers – they were
over-scrutinized. The press looked at
them first as women, excessively
critiquing their person – their clothes,
hair, handbags and scarves.” 
“The widespread perception that
women are not competent leaders is
probably the strongest barrier to greater
participation of women in policy-
making,” says Esther Duflo, professor of
development economics at the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology
(MIT) in the United States. Duflo and her
colleagues, who co-founded the Abdul
Latif Jameel Poverty Action Lab at MIT,
have done a series of ground-breaking
studies in India which show that women
leaders are evaluated more negatively
than male leaders, even though they
tend to provide better services like
clean drinking water and took
significantly fewer bribes. 
In an experiment using actors, Duflo
tested prejudices in hundreds of villages
in India, where one-third of the seats in
rural village councils have been
reserved for women since 1993, a
proportion recently raised to 50%. The
villagers were asked to listen to an
identical political speech—some were
exposed to speeches read by men,
others by women.  Villagers who had
never been exposed to a woman leader
were more likely to judge the female
speech-readers as incompetent. Voters
that had actually seen a woman in
power, however, had no such bias.
“Exposure reduces prejudices,”
according to Duflo, whose findings
show that public policy can influence
simple voter prejudice. 
Brinda Karat, a member of India’s
Communist Party of India (Marxist)
Politbureau and  a member of the
Upper House of Parliament, believes
that “women leaders do tend to raise
issues of concern to women more than
men do.” According to her, the country’s
decision to reserve 50 per cent of seats
for women at the “Panchayat” or local
level, is paying off. “The record of
women’s participation at the grassroots,
overcoming social and cultural barriers
is an inspiring chapter in India’s political
history and is expanding and
intensifying every day”, she says. Yet,
India’s parliament has less than 11%
women, and in most state assemblies,
there are even fewer women elected.  
“Does it therefore mean that women
are not capable or do not have merit on
their side?” asks Karat, who has worked
with women’s movements for the last 40
years.  “Clearly this would be an
outrageous and unacceptable
conclusion. The truth is that
discriminatory attitudes and practices in
the distribution of tickets keep women
out of elected politics. Just as women
fight discrimination in economic and
social spheres, it is necessary to fight
discrimination in the political sphere.
Any discrimination on the basis of
gender weakens democracy. The
struggle for equal representation is a
struggle to strengthen democratic and
citizenship rights.”
Working their way up
Women’s empowerment may be slow in
coming but both Genovese and
Liswood believe change is inevitable.
“Things have changed dramatically in
the past few decades,” Genovese says.
“When I published my book on women
leaders in 1993, I could literally name all
the women heads of government. Today
that number has shot up and women
are more represented throughout the
government than ever before (yet, still
below their percentage in the
population). 
“One of the keys is that today, more
and more women are serving in the
entry positions in politics, at the local
level, working their way up. This means
that there are more women in the
“minor leagues” of politics, more women
in the political pipeline who might earn
their way up the ladder. The chief cause
for this change has been first the
woman’s movement, second, that many
political parties – especially in Europe –
have quotas for women in campaigns,
third,  support groups that raise money
for women (e.g. Emily’s List), and finally,
changes in attitudes in society towards
women in public life.”
“There’s no question that things
have changed,” says Liswood.  “More to
the point is, have things changed
quickly enough?  In many countries,
women are coming into colleges,
getting degrees and entering the
workforce. But they’re seemingly having
a hard time upgrading to higher-level
positions. That I think is where we have
to focus.” 
“There will be a woman president (in
the United States) in my lifetime,”
Genovese believes.  “Perhaps the main
reason it is taking so long, apart from
the already mentioned issues, is that
major powers, super powers, with
significant military entanglements
across the globe, tend to look for men
who exude a certain toughness that
suggests the ability to use force and
even violence when it is deemed
necessary. Prejudices in this regard still
plague women, in spite of the fact that
some of the toughest leaders of the
post World War II era have been women
(Thatcher, Golda Meir, for example). This
stereotype is very hard to break.” ■
Excerpts and quotes taken from:
"Women World Leaders: Great Politicians Tell Their
Stories," by Laura A. Liswood, The Council Press,
2007.
Reprinted from First Edition: "Women World Leaders:
Fifteen Great Politicians Tell Their Stories," by Laura A.
Liswood, Pandora, an imprint of Harper Collins
Publishers,1995.
"Women As National Leaders", by Michael A.
Genovese (Editor), Sage Publications, 1993.
1 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The main problem for newly
independent countries is
their identity, says Roza
Otunbayeva, first woman to
become President of
Kyrgyzstan. The country’s
Iron Lady has seen more
than one crisis come and go
and has overcome many
obstacles in the long career
that brought her to
leadership in July 2010. On
the brink of collapse, the
nation nearly split in two –
she did not let this happen. 
Reading your biography, we note a
number of ‘firsts’: first woman Minister
of Foreign Affairs in Kyrgyzstan, first
woman Ambassador to the USA and
then to the UK and, finally,
Kyrgyzstan’s first woman President.
What is the secret of your success? 
During Perestroika, when I was Vice-
President of the Council of Ministers in
the Republic of Kyrgyzstan, I was invited
to Moscow, to join the Soviet Union’s
National Commission for UNESCO. I
started as Executive Secretary, before
becoming President of the Commission.
It was no small thing to represent the
Soviet Union. The country was a
superpower at the time, and, because
the USA was not a member of UNESCO,
we were the main contributor. That is
how I came to join the Cabinet of the
Soviet Ministry of Foreign Affairs, where,
incidentally, I was also the first woman.
When the Soviet Union collapsed,
Askar Akayev [first president of
Kyrgyzstan, who was deposed by the
March 2005 revolution] invited me to
become Minister for Foreign Affairs. But
as the USA was very important to us at
that time, on the same level as the
World Bank and the International
Monetary Fund on which we depended,
on the map
Putting Kyrgyzstan
©
 J
a
n
a
rb
e
k 
A
m
a
n
ku
lo
v
A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 1 3
ROZA OTUNBAYEVA answers questions put by Katerina Markelova
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
I was appointed Ambassador to the
USA, a post I held for two years, before
returning to Kyrgyzstan as Minister of
Foreign Affairs. 
It was three years later, in 1997, that
Askar Akayev became increasingly
authoritarian. We no longer saw eye-to-
eye. I spent my time criticising him; he
got irritated. In the end, I suggested we
go our separate ways. The idea was not
to go against him – people still trusted
him and wanted him to go through with
his reforms. So I became Kyrgyzstan’s
first Ambassador to Great Britain. That
was also a major pioneering effort, with
members of the UN Security Council. At
the time, our aim was to put Kyrgyzstan
on the map. 
In 2005, having united several
opposition parties, we staged the Tulip
Revolution. But Kurmanbek Bakiyev1
usurped our revolution. He took over
everything and installed a family
dictatorship. For the next five years, we
fought for our ideals, in opposition. I
was head of the opposition in
parliament. In 2010, finally, we took
control!
How do those around you, and
ordinary people, feel about having a
woman as Head of State? 
With the respect traditionally given to
elders, women and mothers. And
among my colleagues I am probably the
one with the most experience. After all, I
deserved this promotion. I have fought
all the way and made many sacrifices. As
for the Kyrgyz people, they also know
that I am not in politics by accident, I am
not someone’s protégé.
Of course there are some people
who think that a woman cannot govern
a country. And to them, I say: the year
2010 was one of the most critical in the
history of Kyrgyzstan. We almost
collapsed as a country and became a
divided nation. But we managed to save
everything. We got ourselves out of a
situation of utter chaos and back onto
dry land. Even though the rest of the
world stood by and did nothing. Let
someone else try to do that! 
The news is full of stories about
countries in turmoil, like Libya. In
Kyrgyzstan, those troubles are behind
us. Our young country still has many
challenges to overcome, but the worst is
over.
Your energy and enthusiasm were
rewarded this year with the
International Women of Courage
award from the US Department of
State. What does this mean to you?
I think the award is more for my country
than for me. The events in the Arab
world are showing that the whole world
is beginning to understand that the
movement of people, countries and
whole continents towards democracy is
unstoppable. What we have gone
through demonstrates that my country
is not out of step with the evolution of
the rest of the world. What my country
and my people have had the courage to
show is that they are motivated by a
love of freedom, and their faith in
progress and democracy. I was just
caught up in the wake of this
movement.
First woman Head of State in Central Asia,
Roza Otunbayeva was born in 1950. With
a degree in philosophy from Moscow State
University and a lecturer early in her career,
she was soon recruited to the party and
rapidly climbed the political ladder. She
played a key role in the overthrow of two
authoritarian regimes in Kyrgyzstan in
March 2005 and April 2010.In June 2010
when a referendum voted in a new
constitution, the people elected the single
candidate, Roza Otunbayeva, as president
of the country. 
©
  U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ije
lja
c
Kyrgyzstan has already done a lot for
women’s equality. There is a 30%
quota for women in parliament. What
more needs to be done, in your
opinion?
Gender equality is a never-ending battle.
Making quotas part of the law, as we did
in the last term of office, is not enough.
These laws are not applied in daily life.
Today, the National Audit Office, which
also has a legal quota of 30% women,
expects three candidates to be
appointed by the President, three by the
opposition and three by the coalition.
The opposition and the coalition only
put forward men, leaving me to put
forward the women. This is just pure
cynicism! 
Women do hold some of our
important posts, though. Apart from my
post, which was the product of a
consensus of political forces, the National
Bank has a woman president, as do the
Supreme Court and the Academy of
Sciences. But, in the government, we
have just one woman, which is quite
simply unacceptable. And, in the
business sector, there is not a single
woman on the boards of any of our
major enterprises. 
This is a special year for Kyrgyz
women. First, because this is the
bicentenary of the birth of Kurmanjan
Datka. This woman, who governed Alai,
in the south, did a great deal to achieve
the unification of this region and to
annex it from Russia. She was progressive
and had prodigious strength and
determination. She is a figurehead for
women and for the nation as a whole.
And second, because my presidency is
coming to an end. This year will
undoubtedly see debates over the role of
women in our country come to a peak.
What would you say is the main
priority for the country?
It is difficult to give a categorical answer
to this question. But I would say that the
most acute problem facing newly
independent countries concerns their
identity. This is a vast, complex and
many-layered issue. All of us, all 200-odd
members of the United Nations, are
being swept along by the same tide,
called globalization. Yet the question of
identity is tormenting every nation and
every thinking person. This is a serious
obstacle to development. We are all
suffering from it and have to find a
solution. ■
1.  Brought to power by the Tulip Revolution,
Kurmanbek Bakiyev led the country from 2005 to
2010. He was relieved of his functions in April 2010
after a popular uprising in which 87 people died.        
1 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
A matter of
commitment
Making sure we do not forget Haiti’s situation of crisis and
vulnerability – this is the primary mission of Michaëlle
Jean, former Governor General of Canada, recently
designated UNESCO Special Envoy for Haiti. Here we trace
the trajectory of an exceptional woman, who has inherited
the courage, perseverance, pragmatism and sense of
commitment of the women of Haiti.  
Interview with MICHAËLLE JEAN by Katerina Markelova
How does a Haitian woman immigrant
become governor-general of Canada?   
And, to top it all, with responsibilities as
Head of State and Commander-in-Chief
of the armed forces! (laughs) I think it’s
first and foremost a matter of
commitment. In Haiti I learned
something very valuable – never remain
indifferent! In a country where
indifference has been responsible for
some terrible problems, my parents
always encouraged me to look around
me, to develop a point of view and to
act. I have inherited my courage,
perseverance, pragmatism and sense of
commitment from the women of Haiti.  
When I first arrived in Canada as a
child, I quickly understood that
integration meant participation. Very
early on I started to become involved in
the women’s movement in Quebec,
particularly by setting up a network of
emergency refuges for battered women
and their children. That set me on the
path of active and responsible
citizenship.  
That experience also brought me
into journalism – 18 years in public
television! Television journalists often
find themselves moving into
entertainment programmes, if they
have the kind of look that stands out.
But I was quickly assigned to the news
service – in a newsroom, anchorwoman,
head of broadcasting, and in front of the
cameras.
Canada is the embodiment of
diversity. For us, diversity is a reality,
rooted in daily life. And, rather than see
it as a threat, we see it as a valuable
asset, despite all the challenges that go
with it. Whenever I have been the victim
of discrimination or racism – because no
society is sheltered from these kinds of
aberration – I always found plenty of
people to support me, and resources
and organisations that would stand up
and, collectively, say “No! Not in Canada.
That’s not acceptable!” That is why a
black woman, militant feminist to boot,
and a former political refugee, was able
to become Governor-general of Canada.
What are your priorities as UNESCO
special envoy for Haiti ?
First of all, to make sure that we keep in
mind the state of emergency and
vulnerability of this country. Haiti was
on the agenda of all the missions I have
been on around the world, as Governor
General of Canada. Whether in the West,
in Latin America or Africa, I have always
sensed the desire to be part of a pact of
solidarity for Haiti. Given that the
ground has already been prepared, I
now intend to ask them for support.
Haiti cannot get out of this alone. It’s a
disastrous situation! But, at the same
time, Haiti must also accept its share of
responsibility. 
I think that the entire world is
watching what is happening in Haiti.
How will the international community
respond? Will the Haitian people – and
the Haitian state in particular – act
responsibly? We have to succeed and
send a message of hope to all of
humanity. Haiti is beset with
emergencies and miseries of every kind.
But it is still possible to act. On one
condition – to make sure the citizens are
included. 
I usually say that, in Haiti, life and
survival both depend on hope. This
country has always been able to pick
itself up after being knocked down. It
triumphed over barbarity through the
Revolution and escaped slavery by
enfranchisement. But hope took a real
body blow with the earthquake.
We often hear about Haitians’
capacity for resilience. But I would prefer
J Street scene in Port-au-Prince, the Haitian capital,
one month after the 12 January 2010 earthquake. A
mother and her children, “pampered, beautiful,
proud” in Michaëlle Jean’s words. 
© UN Photo/Pasqual Gorriz
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 1 5
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
that they were known for their creativity,
their thinking and what they have to say.
If we look only at their capacity for
resilience, we will end up believing that
these people can carry on waiting,
because they are so good at holding on
in the worst circumstances.
What do you think is the role of women
in rebuilding Haiti?
When I went to Haiti in March 2010, I
deliberately chose 8 March, International
Women’s Day, to go back. The women of
Haiti needed to hear someone saying
that reconstruction would fail unless
they were involved. It was truly amazing,
amid this scene of total devastation,
where it was almost impossible to go
anywhere, to see 5000 women turn out
to tell me how much they wanted to see
life triumph over this disaster. 
The women’s movement in Haiti is
extremely well organized. Some leading
women who helped to set up the
movement across the country lost their
lives, including some very close friends.
All of those who survived were in
mourning. But they were possessed by a
limitless energy, determined to make
sure life wins in the end! 
And what part can the diaspora play? 
The diaspora has had to overcome a
number of challenges, and this is not the
first time that Haiti has had to face
difficulties. When the Duvaliers1 left, in
1986, everyone hoped for great things.
We saw ex-patriots selling up and
moving back home. Men, women and
children wanted to contribute to the
renaissance of Haiti, to the construction
of a democratic state and to new
governance. At that time people were
already speaking of refounding,
reconstruction, a new start. But it turned
out to be a minefield. A series of coups
and the army’s straitjacket stifled any
hope there had been. After a fleeting
moment of euphoria, life became painful
for Haitians for a long time.   
When the hurricanes struck in 2008
[taking the lives of nearly 1000 people], I
saw a bad sign – the diaspora did not
respond. Oh, how terrible it was to see
that! In fact, Haitians living abroad had
been disappointed by the behaviour of
their compatriots in the previous years –
the aid they had been sending home lay
rotting in containers or was
appropriated by corrupt officials.  
But the 2010 earthquake touched
the hearts and minds of everybody! The
diaspora pulled itself together and
responded this time. As I speak to you
now, people are struggling to join in this
stage in the country’s development,
which could be a turning point. People
have said it before me – this disaster has
to become an opportunity to act! 
On your visit to Haiti in March 2010,
you emphasized the importance of
education. It was during a round table
discussion in Port-au-Prince that you
chaired alongside the Director-General
of UNESCO. What do expect to do in
this area?
Haiti is a country where it is possible to
do a great deal in terms of education.
Why? Because, in the very fabric of Haiti,
in its culture, in the Haitian way of
being, in its history, education has
always been synonymous with
emancipation and access to freedom. In
the plantations, the slaves remained
illiterate. But there was also another
category of people – the children that
the masters had with their slaves. These
children were not sent to the
plantations and were taught to read and
write. These ‘domestic slaves’ as they
were called, had access to knowledge.
Some even went as far to show off their
talents. And the plantation slaves saw all
of this.
Today, when you see little Haitians
going to school, you cannot imagine the
dreadful circumstances they are being
forced to live in! But when they go off to
school they are always pampered, they
are beautiful, they are proud and their
parents are proud, too. 
All these families, even the poorest,
bend over backwards to send their
children to school! So the conditions are
very favourable. If we invest in
education, if we help Haiti to build a
quality public education system, the
people will immediately take it on board
as something great and useful.
At the present moment, there is an
incredible number of scattered
educational projects, but there is no
coordination. I think that UNESCO has
all the necessary skills to play a
leadership role in this area and to help
the Haitian State to create a standard
framework for schools. ■
Michaëlle Jean was born in 1957 in Port-
au-Prince (Haiti), and sought exile with her
family in Canada in 1968, fleeing the
dictatorship of François Duvalier. After a long
career in journalism (the French network of
Radio-Canada and the English network of
CBC Newsworld) and militating for women’s
rights, Michaëlle Jean became governor
general of Canada (September 2005 –
September 2010). On 8 November 2010, she
was designated UNESCO Special Envoy for
Haiti. With her husband, the filmmaker Jean-
Daniel Lafond, Michaëlle Jean chairs a
foundation that bears her name, focused on
youth and the arts. 
Michaëlle Jean, UNESCO’s Special Envoy for
Haiti  © Stg Serge Gouin, Rideau Hall
1. François (“Papa Doc”) Duvalier and his son Jean-
Claude (“Baby Doc”) Duvalier seized power in Haiti
from 1957 and 1986, a period characterized by
corruption, the repression of civil rights and the
institutionalization of fear.
1 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
L Celebration of International Women’s Day, 8
March 2010, in Port-au-Prince, Haiti. 
© UN Photo/Sophia Paris
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
At 55, you have already spent over four
decades fighting all forms of
discrimination, especially against
women. Where did this militant spirit
come from?
I am a born rebel! The social context and
my family environment only
accentuated this aspect of my character.
I took my first steps as a left-wing
militant at the age of 11. I was living in
the southwest of Nouakchott, the capital
of Mauritania, in a National Democratic
Movement stronghold. This Marxist
movement was calling for economic and
social emancipation, while contesting
the single-party rule of President Ould
Daddah. So, I got many of my ideas after
hearing them in the streets or from
friends or at school. I read a lot – on the
resistance of Vietnamese women, the
Bolshevik revolution and especially the
Commune. I even got nicknamed
“Commune de Paris”! This ideal of the
liberation of the people and equality
was in radical contrast with the old-
fashioned ideas and feudal spirit that
prevailed in my family. We were rich, we
had slaves, and my father ruled as
absolute patriarch. He beat me and
chained me up whenever I stayed out of
school to join demonstrations or hand
out leaflets. All that cost me several stays
in prison, from the age of 12. I was soon
let out, because I was young, but the
worst punishments were handed out at
home. That only served to turn my
spontaneous commitment into
unshakeable convictions. Since then I
have been fighting relentlessly for
equality between men and women, for
an end to slavery and for human rights.
Crime without
punishment
In Mauritania, the question of slavery is closely linked to women because, traditionally,
slave status was hereditary and passed on by the mother. Since 2007, slavery has been a
crime under Mauritanian law. But, in practice, it continues in more or less disguised forms
while the perpetrators escape prosecution. Lawyer Aminetou Mint El Moctar has devoted
her life to the rights of women, especially single mothers.
AMINETOU MINT EL MOCTAR answers questions put by Laura Martel, a journalist at RFI
In Mauritania, slavery has been replaced by domestic
service, deplores Aminetou Mint El Moctar. She is
particularly concerned by the plight of underage
girls. mineures. © UN Photo/Jean-Pierre Laffont
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 1 7
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
the legal age for marriage is 18 years,
but with the guardian’s consent, it may
be celebrated earlier. This, in a way,
legalises childhood marriages and
deprives women of the power to decide.
That was how, one day, when I came
home from school, I discovered I had
been married to a friend of my father. I
was 13 years old. 
Also, when inheritances are divided
up, two-thirds go to the boys, one third
to the girls, while only the husband can
initiate a divorce. Mauritania signed the
Convention on the Elimination of All
Forms of Discrimination against Women
(CEDAW), but added two reservations,
precisely on divorce and inheritance.
AFCF is currently campaigning to get
these two reservations lifted. It is by
inscribing equality between men and
women in the law that we will acquire
the weapons to combat concrete acts of
discrimination, even if this is just the
first step because many laws are not
applied.
This is particularly true of the 2007 law
that makes slavery a criminal offence.
You often point out that no one has
been convicted since this law was
Your commitment goes back a long
way, but you have only recently set up
your Single Mothers Association
(AFCF). What sparked that? 
For years I have been a member of a
number of organizations, like the
Comité de solidarité aux veuves
[Solidarity with Widows Committee] or
SOS Esclaves (SOS Slaves). In 1999, I was
present at the trial of a woman who had
secretly married the head of a company
and was fighting for their two children
to have a share of their deceased
father’s inheritance. The court refused to
recognise his paternity. Hearing this
verdict literally struck her down and she
died on the way to hospital. With no
husband, and so no money, no
education, and therefore no chance of
finding work, she knew that she and her
children would find themselves in the
street. She died because she was unable
to claim her rights. It was then that I
realised it was time to fight for these
abandoned women, so I set up the
Association. Today, the AFCF has over
10,000 members and employs 62
people. Our staff and running costs are
all paid out of members’ subscriptions,
while our projects are funded by donor
agencies.
Mauritanian society is multicultural,
with two main ethnic strands – Arab
Berbers and black Africans. Do women
have the same status in both
communities?
Women traditionally have the same
function in both communities – they are
“made for marriage and to satisfy the
desire of men”, but that translates
differently in daily life. The constraints
aren’t the same. For black Africans, a
good wife pays her way essentially with
household duties, educating the
children and satisfying her husband. If
she does earn money, she generally has
to hand it over to the “master of the
household”. Most Arab-Berber women
escape household chores. This is not
just because their families are generally
better off, but also because a woman
has to be “preserved” to make the best
possible marriage. Pampering her and
feeding her up are an investment.
Family honour depends on girls
marrying young – “she was married
young” being an adage frequently used
by griots as a form of praise. The
nomadic tradition allows more freedom
to Arab-Berber women than their black
K Down through the centuries, religious imperatives
and ancestral customs have been combined to justify
discrimination against women in Mauritania, says
Aminetou Mint El Moctar
© Pepa Martin, Spain
African sisters, in terms of what they can
and cannot do. And Arab-Berber
Mauritanian women have a traditional
concept of divorce that is quite unusual.
Not only is it acceptable, but it can even
give a woman added value! A woman
who has been divorced several times is
considered very sought-after. I, myself,
have three children from different
fathers and have been married 5, 6 or 7
times… but now it’s finished! (laughs).
But, for black Africans, divorce is, on the
contrary, frowned upon, and they are
more likely to practice polygamy than
Arab-Berbers, although the current
obscurantist trend means a resurgence
of this tradition for them too. These are
all, of course, generalisations, for which
there are many exceptions.
Force-feeding, child marriage,
excision, slavery, domestic service…
the list of human rights breaches is a
long one. What is your priority?
The most urgent task is to establish a
legal basis for equality between men
and women. For centuries jurisprudence
has mixed up religious imperatives and
tradition to create a cocktail of
discrimination. In Mauritania, a woman
has a legal guardian for her entire life. It
might be her father, her husband or
even her son. She has no rights of her
own. Let us take marriage as an
example. According to the civil code,
1 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
passed. Does this mean that there are
no more slaves in Mauritania?
It’s difficult to quantify because the
subject is taboo. Nevertheless, we know
that slavery still goes on, because we
regularly pick up victims. Along with
other associations, AFCF has denounced
cases of slavery to the authorities on
several occasions, but so far, no action
has been taken and no one has been
convicted. The “masters” are people with
high positions and are protected. 
The question of slavery is intimately
linked to women, since, according to
tradition, it is hereditary and passed
down through the mother. That means
it is more advantageous for a “master” to
have female slaves, because he can then
appropriate their offspring. Even so, this
traditional form of slavery, where
individuals are the property of a master
from one generation to the next, is on
the decline. Unfortunately it is being
replaced by a more ‘modern’ form of
slavery – domestic service. Poor families
place their daughters with rich families,
where they often receive only board
and lodging. These girls, who are usually
very young, receive no education and it
is not uncommon for them to be
beaten. There are many of them in
Nouakchott. They mostly come from
rural areas of the country, but also from
neighbouring states like Senegal, Mali
or Gambia. In 2009, with the
international human rights
organization, Terre des Hommes, we
launched a programme that enabled us
to help 2200 minors. 
Do you see Mauritania as a hub for
trafficking children?
This form of traffic has existed for a long
time, but has grown over the past few
years. The traffickers seek out children in
poor families in rural areas, promising
their parents that they will find their
girls work, or a religious pilgrimage, a
favourable marriage, a sum of money,
etc. The girls transit through
Nouakchott, before being taken to the
Gulf, where they are sold and married. If
they are black, their skin is lightened.
Once they reach the age of 18 or 20,
their husbands throw them out into the
street, because they are no longer young
enough for their taste; most then fall
into prostitution. If they are still minors,
they may be deported. Three years ago I
met 14 girls at the airport, all about 15
years old, who had lived through this
ordeal and did not know where to go.
The prostitution ring also extends out to
Europe. AFCF is currently looking for
funding for a survey to determine the
extent of this phenomenon.
Are there any areas where you can see
progress ?
Excision! Even though it is disappearing
very slowly, this practice is beginning to
be abandoned collectively, mostly as a
result of a number of agreements and
action by donor organizations, which
have been providing substantial
funding, as well as the commitment of
some highly placed religious figures. A
fatwa [religious law] was signed against
excision in 2010. The police and the
judiciary have also been made more
aware of the issues, but once again,
there have been virtually no convictions. 
Force –feeding is also on the decline,
mostly because of a gradual change in
concepts of beauty. But over 20% of
Mauritanian girls jeopardize their health
to put on weight, even if the traditional
methods have nowadays been replaced
by food supplements, often with
dangerous side effects. 
And then there is political
representation, where we made clear
gains between 2005 and 2007,
particularly with the establishment of a
20% quota for women in elected
institutions. Today, we do have a female
Minister of foreign affairs, but the
number of senior positions held by
women (such as Secretary of state,
police chief, governor) has been falling
since 2008. Symbolically, the Ministry for
the Advancement of Women has once
again been merged within the Ministry
of Social Affairs. Meanwhile, Mauritania,
like some other countries, is under
pressure from right-wing factions that
want to reassign women to a more
primitive role.
What do you recommend women
should do to defend their rights?
Traditionally, women do not follow any
in-depth religious instruction, learning
“just what is needed to pray”. But a
better understanding of religion would
enable them to free themselves from
certain practices. They would know, for
example, that the Koran does not
impose excision and polygamy. I also
think that religions, including Islam, have
to adapt to the modern world – we
should be lobbying religious scholars for
a ‘modern’ exegesis of the scriptures. 
In Mauritania there is a majority of
women – some 52% of the population.
There is, then, the potential to develop a
female elite, able to overcome racial and
ideological schisms. AFCF, in
collaboration with the American
NGOWomen’s Learning Partnership
trains 100 women each year in
leadership skills. Politics is one means
towards our ends, but it may not
necessarily be the best, because many
women, once in power, look after their
own interests first. What is needed is
collective awareness of the issues. It is
starting.
Why did you not go into politics?
Because I prefer to work at grassroots
level, with the victims. It is by getting
women into the streets that we will gain
most power. I know that it is a slow
process, but I do get the feeling we are
at a turning point – the efforts of our
Association were rewarded with France’s
Human Rights Prize in 2007, and the
Heroes Acting To End Modern-Day
Slavery Award from the US Department
of State in 2010. This encourages more
international organizations to fund our
projects. ■
Mauritanian-born, Aminetou Mint El
Moctar is a lawyer and founded the
Association des Femmes Chefs de Famille
(AFCF), organization representing
single mothers..
©
 C
ri
d
e
m
.o
rg
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 1 9
One day, when I came home
from school, I discovered I had
been married to a friend of my
father. I was 13 years old
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Her country was still at war when she set about building
her house. First she took a wheelbarrow. She carried and
buried the remains of the 72 people who had been
murdered in front of her, mostly refugees in the diocese
where she worked. Then she went out on the battlefields to
look for children who had survived. “Some of them had no
eyes, others no arms.” She cared for them, fed them... but
they also had to be housed.
Maggy Barankitse was 37 when the civil
war broke out in Burundi, one of the
smallest and poorest countries in the
African continent. From 1993 to the first
years of the millennium, the conflict
between Tutsis and Hutus saw over
200,000 people lose their lives, but hers
was spared, and she saved thousands of
children in her home region of Ruyigi,
near to the border with Tanzania, as well
as across the entire country. “Today I am
the happiest mother in the world – I
have 20,000 children,” she says, with a
radiant smile. “We have raised the
children of a generation of fratricide and
created a new generation. We made no
distinction between the children of
victims and the children of criminals –
they were all just children who needed
to be loved and comforted. Three
quarters of my colleagues today –
doctors, psychologists, economists,
nurses, teachers – were Tutsi and Hutu
children who grew up in the Maison
Shalom.”
One shouldn’t think of this house as
having four walls and a roof. For 17
years, “Mama Maggy” used different
places that were lent or given to her to
house the war orphans, before creating
three large centres. “But I realized,” she
admits, “that children who grow up in
orphanages lose their sense of
responsibility. So I closed down the
orphanages and opened a series of
outreach centres for the association. I
built 3000 little houses across the
country where siblings could live
together! I also placed children in
families. I compare this house to a boat,
with God as our captain.”
A devoted Christian, Maggy
Barankitse has just one religion – love.
JASMINA ŠOPOVA
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ije
lja
c
2 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
Mama Maggy
and her 20 000children
A meeting with Maggy Barankitse
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:55  Page 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
“Men and women have enough love in
their hearts to say ‘no’ to doom, no to
fratricidal hate,” insists this woman, who
held a ‘democratic poll’ of the children
when they were looking for a name for
the association. “It was the children who
gave their house the name Shalom. It is a
Hebrew word, but has become universal,
as it means ‘peace.’ The little Muslim
children also raised their hands when it
came to the vote.” 
Over the years she built the children
a centre for vocational training –
teaching plumbing, carpentry,
agriculture, animal husbandry and
dressmaking. But her greatest pride and
joy is the hospital she founded in Ruyigi,
with a mother and baby unit. “I opened a
large hospital because, that way, I will no
longer have to repair all the damage. I
had enough of receiving children who
had lost their mothers while they were
still in nappies. No-one in the world can
replace the tenderness of a mother. No
institution, no centre can stand in for a
mother. I built a beautiful maternity
centre and started a nursing school. I
knocked on every door to get hold of an
ambulance. And then I went to see
mothers in the villages to tell them they
could call us if ever a mother was in
need.” 
For those who are HIV positive or are
suffering from AIDS, Maggy Barankitse
opened a special centre where they can
not only be fed, cared for and treated
with antivirals, but also get advice. “They
learn how to organize themselves
through associations and set up little co-
operatives. Look at this…” she says,
pointing to the beautiful red dress she is
wearing as she talks to us, “they made it!
The main thing is not to help these
women, but to help them help
themselves.”  
It is difficult to put figures to the work
of Maison Shalom. “As we work across
the entire country, I cannot tell you how
many people we have supported. The
schools are for all the children living in
the communities where we built them.
The libraries and cinemas we set up are
open to everyone.”    
Today, the association employs 220
people, without counting the volunteers,
and receives support from over 40
charities, institutions and governments.
Maggy Barankitse is very convincing,
even though she does not hold back
from criticising certain forms of
behaviour – or perhaps it is because of
this. While UNICEF is one of the friends
of Maison Shalom, she is outraged at
the hundreds of plastic schools bearing
the name UNICEF, dotted all over the
country. “Rather than send us plastic
manufactured in western factories that
is toxic for the children, why not help us
to buy straw, which is much better
adapted to our climate, so that we can
help build our own schools and earn
money at the same time, to pay for our
children’s education?”
She pulls no punches with UNESCO
either, where she recently came for the
no voice of their own and needing a
spokesperson! Even if they speak
neither English nor French, they have to
be given a chance to have their say.” 
And to conclude the chapter of
remonstrations – “I would like the
United Nations agencies to take a good
look at themselves. They should stop
meeting for grand conferences, they
should stop focusing on statistics, and
be more present at grassroots level.” 
“I, myself, live in the back of beyond,
in a region no-one has heard of,” says
Maggy Barankitse, becoming more and
launch of the Education for All Global
Monitoring Report 2011, which is
devoted to the impact of armed
conflicts on education. “It is this little
girl, a rape victim in the Democratic
Republic of Congo, who we spoke about
today at the conference – she is the one
you should have brought here instead
of me. She should tell her own story. The
doors to conferences and meetings
have to be opened to these people.
They must not be considered as having
more animated. “I live in the ‘danger
zone’ where journalists come to take a
photo or two and high-tail it back out
again, where foreign civil servants
spend three weeks before setting off for
Zanzibar for a rest! When I started my
work, I was shocked by this kind of
behaviour. But later on I understood –
we have to let our tongues loose and
speak. If I do not criticize, it means that I
do not love. There is no love without
truth.” ■
©
 M
a
is
o
n
 S
h
a
lo
m
, R
u
y
ig
i
L Maggy Barankitse is particularly proud of this rural hospital she founded in Ruyigi, Burundi.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 2 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Afraid of
Bangladesh will be celebrating its 40th
anniversary of liberation this year.
How has life changed for women over
these decades?
Lots of things have changed in the last
40 years. To begin with, generally
women are much more conscious of
their rights now. They are much
stronger on demanding their rights and
also very vocal on the political and
social scene.
Of course it is not the same
everywhere in the country, and it could
have been much better, if not for the
interruptions in the democratic process
or the rise of fundamentalism. But in
SULTANA KAMAL was interviewed
by Anbarasan Ethirajan, Indian
journalist for the BBC in
Bangladesh
general, the people have never ever
endorsed the orthodox type of religion.
That is why women always benefited
from a very liberal atmosphere that
gave them the leverage to debate and
to take part in lots of things.
The prime minister of Bangladesh,
Sheikh Hasina, and the opposition
leader, Khaleda Zia, are women, which
is quite unusual for a Muslim majority
country. 
I like the way you put the question – you
think it is very unusual for a Muslim
majority country. Yes, Bangladesh is a
Muslim majority country but we do not
Women may hold top political posts in Bangladesh, yet discrimination because of gender
is institutionalized, says women’s rights activist Sultana Kamal. In this country that claims
to be secular but where Islam remains the state religion, the rise of fundamentalism and
disruptions in the democratic process are having a direct impact on women’s status.
call ourselves a Muslim country. It is a
country where people of many religions
live, many cultures are alive in
Bangladesh and very well loved and
respected. But we have to be very honest
about the women we see at the top. They
are not there because they are women or
because they have come through a
process which has actually supported
women’s emancipation. They are there
because they bear a legacy.
I would be very honest here - when
we vote for Sheikh Hasina, we in fact vote
for her late father Sheikh Mujibur
Rahman, the first president of the
country. When we vote for Khaleda Zia
2 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
nothing
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
we vote for her late husband, General
Ziaur Rahman, the former military
dictator. People still bear the images of
these two very well known leaders.  
But then again the very fact that the
two women are there, running the
country and really taking control of
situations, gives other women a sense of
confidence, a belief that women can do it. 
Which identity is dominant in
Bangladesh? Bangladeshi identity or
Islamic identity? 
Many people wonder whether they are
Muslim or Bangladeshi first. This struggle
has its roots in the Pakistani period. The
main challenge to the people of East
Pakistan from the Pakistani military rulers
was that you had to prove you were a
loyal Pakistani. You had to prove you were
a true Muslim. They actually merged two
identities together. 
But people in Bangladesh generally
believe that we can have multiple
identities. Yes, I am a Muslim or born to a
Muslim family, I am also a Bangladeshi, a
woman, a human rights activist. I am
known by many different names. So
likewise, there will be Hindus and
Christians who will have multiple
identities. The people of Bangladesh
basically believe in pluralism, they believe
in Sufism. Their way of relating to nature,
to God, to whatever mysteries of life, is
dependent on their own perception of
self and nature. 
People’s love of Bangladesh is mixed
with love of the rivers, trees and nature. It
is very much related to the basic harmony
that they want to see everywhere. It is not
a confrontational culture, but one was
created artificially, constantly supported
by forces in the society that have been
able to capture power and influence
through the economic system,
educational system and cultural inputs.
Have Islamist fundamentalist forces
changed social and cultural life within
Bangladesh?
The fundamentalists have captured the
main sectors of the society, like banking,
insurance, medical and education. And
the worst influence is on education
because they have changed all the
curricula, they have changed all kinds of
information methods in the country.
People must accept the lessons they
teach or surrender to what they think is
the correct path of religion. 
They get into power or stay in power
by using the tool of fear. Whatever
degradation in society we see in
Bangladesh was because they used
weapons. They use religious dogma,
which tell us you cannot question
anything, so it is absolute surrender or
nothing. It’s a question of faith, nothing
else.
They are using freedom of
expression, democratic opportunities, to
give religious orders. They keep saying
we want the head of this person or this
individual should be hanged because he
is a traitor, whatever this person has said
is sacrilegious. These tactics scare
people. But you also notice that not
many people actually support all these
efforts. They talk against them and make
their opinions known as soon as they
know there will be not be any
repercussion or retaliation by the
fundamentalist forces. But there are
other forces in the society which support
them, give them courage and will
protect them when they are at risk and
that is what happens each time we have
an election.
There have been a number of court
rulings in recent years that no woman
should be forced to wear a burqa. But if
you go outside the capital people are
still wearing traditional Islamic dress. 
We have to remember women in rural
areas have little means of supporting
J Elections in 2008. In Bangladesh the lines of
women waiting to vote are almost always longer
than the men’s.
© Faizal Tajuddin (Kuala Lumpur)
themselves economically or socially. All
these people probably belong to the
lower middle class or poor sections of
the society, so their struggle is very
basic. They are using these tactics to at
least get out of the house. As they tell us,
‘Unless I wear a burqa, my family will not
allow me to go out.’ So, only to go to
school, or work or a meeting, they have
to use the burqa. 
How does it happen? In the rural
areas the men are also denied
opportunities and bullied by the social
leaders. Unfortunately, the social leaders
are also connected to religious hierarchy
and push the men to control their
women in that way. And since for many
years this country was ruled by the
generals who had a very strong alliance
with the religious forces, all these things
were promoted, deliberately nurtured
and protected by the state. That is why it
will not be so easy for all women to
refuse from one day to the next to wear
the burqa. 
You see many more burqas now in
Bangladesh than we saw in the Pakistani
time.  This is an outcome of disruptions
in the democratic system where people
were forced to surrender to certain
powers, to be silenced so that they do
not revive the spirit of the liberation war
of 1971. There was a direct conflict
between hard line groups opposed to
our independence and the powers that
actually fought for the liberation of
Bangladesh. 
K Khaleda, 15 years old, Rohyngia refugee in
Bangladesh.
© UNHCR/S.Kritsanavarin/November 2008 )
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Let’s talk about another major issue,
attacks on women that include
throwing acid on them and sexual
harassment of young girls, which lead
to suicide in many cases. Can these
practices be controlled only by
enacting law?
It is a social problem and it has to be
dealt with by social forces. We should
create an atmosphere where women
will get enough confidence that they
can fight it. Also, the state, the society
and the families will have to be involved
in protecting women. We need to
explain this to the families. We have to
make it clear that women have equal
rights and dignity in the country and
that has to be maintained. There cannot
be any compromise there. There has to
be a social movement about it. But then
laws are also helpful because they give
you a kind of a power and confidence
that you can also fight these legally.
Gender bias and prejudice against
women – is it institutionalised in
Bangladesh?
I would say yes, if you look at the
personal laws that exist in the country.
According to these laws, people are
governed by their religious laws and
those are very clearly discriminating
against women. But the state is not
doing anything about it. We have been
demanding since 1972 that there
should be a uniform civil code or family
code for everybody. The government is
not able to do anything about that and
and also in the 1950s and 1960s cultural
movements.  
I got involved in public life during
the country’s liberation war. I was in
India for some months during the nine-
month war. With my sister, I set up a
hospital for the wounded freedom
fighters. Before then I was engaged in
helping people with information,
shelter, assisting them to cross the
border. 
After our liberation in 1971, I started
working with women affected by the
war, because many came to my mother
with a lot of problems. A number of
women had lost their husbands and had
difficulties with their in-laws. Many
women wanted to remarry and keep
their children. That is how I became
interested in law and became a lawyer. I
felt I could be useful to those people, to
help them realise they do have rights
and they can live with dignity.
You were threatened on many
occasions and there were attempts on
your life. Did you ever feel you were
ready to quit? 
Not really, because I learnt from my
parents that the minute you quit, that is
half the defeat. Why let others feel that
they have won and abandon the causes
you are fighting for? That is the strength
of life: you will only lose your life once.
The fundamentalists did not approve
of my marriage to a Hindu, or to the
people that I associated with, so they set
fire to my house in 1995. We almost died.
Later they threw a bomb. But I never
worried about my own well-being or my
own life. Yes, I have responsibility
towards my husband and my daughter.
They have a claim on my life. But the way
I was brought up and the way I started
understanding the issues of life taught
me that you should never be afraid.
Being afraid is not the solution.  ■
Bangladeshi women’s rights activist
Sultana Kamal is Executive Director of
Ain-O-Shalish Kendra, a national legal
aid and human rights organisation.
Founded in 1986, the NGO is funded
notably by the Dutch embassy, the
German agency NETZ and Save the
Children. It also raises its own funds
through activities such as training and
publications. In 2010, ASK provided free
legal assistance to about 4000 women.
we still have a very confused view of
what is positive discrimination, what is
equity, what is an affirmative action? So
there is a lot of resistance within the
society reflected in the state policies.
There is controversy over how
Bangladesh is treating the Rohingya
ethnic refugees from neighbouring
Myanmar. What’s your view on this?
One impression I have is that these
people are also being used by
supporters of fundamentalist forces in
Bangladesh. That’s one thing. The other
problem as I heard from our foreign
minister is economic. The minute you
recognize them as refugees and you
start dealing with them according to the
treaties, it represents an economic
burden Bangladesh is not prepared for. 
Population is another problem.
Bangladesh is not being able to deal
with such a huge population.  
On the other hand, as a human
rights activist I would like to say yes, all
these problems are there. But there
should be a decent way of dealing with
them. I strongly feel that these people
also have certain rights and those rights
should be respected.
Tell us about yourself. What prompted
you to become a women’s rights
activist? 
I was brought up among people who
were social activists, political activists.
My parents were deeply involved in the
anti-British movement. Then my mother
became the pioneer of the women’s
movement in Bangladesh. She took a
leading role in the language movement
K Sultana Kamal at the launch of a project to build a
school for disadvantaged and orphaned children
(2010). © ASK, Dakha)
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
the centre of both movements. Our
activism started rather quickly.
What challenges did you face as a
woman human rights defender?
In the last five or six years, I have been
honoured with signs of recognition
internationally and also in my own
country. But if you ask people today
who do not believe that human rights
are universal, they will say that I am a
Westernized woman - though I never
studied or lived abroad; that I am anti-
religion - because I believe people must
have a right to have or not to have a
religion; and that I am anti-Pakistan -
because I believe Pakistan must live in
peace with its neighbours… 
But I also come from a society that is
full of dichotomy. You have violence
against women, women are looked
down upon, and yet Pakistan did
produce a very courageous woman,
Benazir Bhutto, to be the first woman
Prime Minister in a Muslim country. We
have people like me who are under
threat but also people who would stand
by me, protect and encourage me. So I
have learned a lot and I have a lot to be
thankful for.
As an activist, I have noticed three
things: you have to be thick-skinned;
you have to persevere; and you have to
constantly look for more solutions.
I recall when I started to work with
bonded labour workers – that is, slave
type practices. The judge would ask
them ‘Do you recognize her, is she your
lawyer?’ Those workers were so scared
they would say no. And I risked having
my license taken away because my own
clients said they had not engaged me.
But I had to persist because then the
litigant begins to have faith in you and
finally begins to speak. And that was
how the case of a woman bonded
labourer was taken up to the Supreme
Court and when that woman’s employer
accused her of lying, she put her hand
on her hip and said “Who is a liar - you
Interview with ASMA JAHANGIR by Irina Zoubenko-Laplante
On Human Rights Day - 10 December 2010 - Asma
Jahangir received the UNESCO/Bilbao Prize for the
Promotion of a Culture of Human Rights from
UNESCO’s Director-General, Irina Bokova, and the
Mayor of Bilbao, Iñaki Azkuna. She gave an interview
to the Courier on the day she received the Prize.
Irina Zoubenko-Laplante works for the  UNESCO
Division of Human Rights, Philosophy and
Democracy
A lawyer
with a
thick skin
You have spent your whole life
defending human rights.  What
inspired you to become a human rights
lawyer? 
I was brought up in a politically active
family. My father, Malik Jilani, was a
political leader who had always been in
the opposition and suffered all his life. I
saw how you had to go to court even
when you realize you are not going to
get any justice. Day after day I
understood the important work of
lawyers.
In the early 1980s, you set up an
NGO, the AGHS Legal Aid Cell, run
exclusively by women. 
Having finished my law studies and
obtained an LLB degree in law from
Punjab University, I realized that I was
not going to get a chamber to take me
in. To have one’s own firm appeared to
be the best solution. I worked this out
with two friends and my sister, Hina
JilaniThis was the time of absolute
oppression against women and side by
side the women’s movement was
coming along. There was also a lawyers’
movement. So we ended up being in
“It is the law that is delinquent,” retorts lawyer
Asma Jahangir when a judge tells her she is
always defending delinquent women. The
Pakistani militant stops at nothing in her efforts
to fight so-called honour crimes, to promote
women’s economic rights and, above all, to
defend the universality of human rights,
applicable to all without exception.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 2 5
© DR
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
2 6 . L E  C O U R R I E R  D E  L’ U N E S C O  . H O R S  S É R I E  . M A R S  2 0 1 1
or me? I will tell this court you are not
only a liar but an exploiter too.” That day
I thought the case was won! Today
bonded labour has not been completely
discontinued but a large number of
people have won freedom.
We have to have a thick skin too. I
remember in 1983 when in the name of
Islam a law was proposed that the value
of a woman’s testimony would be half
that of a man’s. Many of us, mostly
upper class women, not realizing where
we were going, came into the street and
were suddenly beaten by the police, our
hair pulled out. Eventually a mullah
declared in the mosque that our
marriages were dissolved and our
husbands had to divorce us - actually
none of them did.  It was difficult but it
gave us courage - not only to those 150
women in the streets and beaten by the
police but to a much larger number.
Since then we continued to multiply the
number of activists. 
When I was in danger, one of my
children said to me “Mother, if you do
not fight for women’s rights, they will
come only a minute later than they are
supposed to come.”  But I think it is that
one minute that human rights activists
work for.
What in particular made you
concerned about the situation of
women? 
When I started as a lawyer many women
were put in prison because of a new
law: any sex outside marriage was
considered a crime – as it is still
regarded today but in a diluted form.
Even women who were victims of rape
but could not prove it were put in
prison. And whenever I went to court,
the judge would say: “Don’t you get any
other clients except these delinquent
women?” And I would reply: “My Lord,
the law is more delinquent to put them
behind bars.” 
Women do face huge problems in
many countries, including mine, starting
with security of life. Women are
expected to behave in a certain way,
and if they don’t, they are sometimes
killed, which is known as “honour
killings”. When I first raised this question,
some judges said they did not see what
I was talking about. Gradually our
movement against honour killings took
root not only in Pakistan but got the
attention of people and organizations
across the world. We now have a lot of
support against this practice, whereas
only a few decades ago politicians were
saying they could not support people
who were talking against honour
killings, because it was against accepted
social norms. Now those politicians are
ashamed of having said that.
What can be done to accelerate
positive change for women?
First, advance women’s economic rights,
which are very much missing in many
countries. Women do not have the same
status as men; even when they are
working, they do not get equal pay. And
violence against women is rampant. We
have to start is by making women
themselves more aware, which has
increased tremendously. And secondly
it is necessary to sensitize organizations
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
L This young woman is one of many displaced persons who fled fighting in the Swat Valley, Pakistan, in June 2009. © UNICEF/NYHQ2009-0931/Marta Ramoneda
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
and institutions like the judiciary, the
parliament, the media, in favour of
women’s rights. We have made some
advances but not enough.
Will we be able to meet the UN
Millennium Development Goals, in
particular to reduce poverty through
promoting gender equality? 
I think we should commend the
aspiration of the United Nations but
obviously these are not going to be met
by the anticipated 2015 deadline. That
does not mean that we have to give up.
I think the question of children and
poverty is particularly acute today.
Children in marginalized sections of our
societies, children who have been
abused for sex, for pornography,
children who are often now abused for
beggary, children who have been sold,
they, I believe, are the first victims of
poverty.
Based on your experience as UN
Special Rapporteur on Freedom of
Religion or Belief, what do you think
about human capacities for tolerance?
This very delicate and intellectually
challenging mandate taught me many
things. For example, there is no country
in the world where prejudices do not
exist and at the same time there is no
country in the world where people are
not fighting intolerance. But this must
be recognized in the echelons of power
that should be establishing policies to
eliminate intolerance. Education is
particularly important but it depends on
what kind. In our own part of the world
people have been radicalized and
militarized in the name of education. We
want quality education, not only
through textbooks but through
interaction of children from diverse
communities. Education should
inculcate a genuine respect for human
dignity and not just teach taboos. For
example, I do not see that children are
taught to that people may dress
differently, a man may be dressed as a
girl but that does not mean that you
should look down on them. A woman
may cover her head but it does not
mean she is different in her thinking. I
do not see that in any educational
books – West or East. 
There are countries, often because
of conflict, that get blocked inside and
there is no cross-border interaction,
which is very important. At the same
time, I believe the world must remain
diverse, with different ideologies also.
But we have to underline there are
some red lines people must not cross. I
cannot expect you to think like me at
the point of a gun, I can persuade you
within the limits, not through abuse or
threat. If I begin to do that, it is clearly
intolerance. And if I make discriminating
legislation, it is clearly intolerance. And
to give the justification of legislation
being based on your own social and
religious norms is something
governments will have to rethink. It is
an insult to your own people to say they
have less dignity than others in this
world. The question of dignity is
therefore everywhere. 
Human rights defender work is not
easy. In my own country, we have
conflict and Islamic militants killing
people. Even they have rights. But when
we human rights defenders have to talk
about their rights, people wonder
whether we are not Taliban supporters.
Of course not, but even if a man is a
suspected Taliban, you cannot make
him disappear.
What is the role of a State in ensuring a
society’s progress?
I think the State is the last to come on
board. It is the time of civil society, in
particular of activists’ groups and
movements such as we can see at
present in the Latin America, in the mass
media. It is they who have carried out
campaigns and taken up vital issues. For
example, civil society and activist groups
in the West were the first to talk about
arbitrary detentions after the September
11th terrorist attacks. This movement
received an input from lawyers, from
human rights defenders, from students,
so all this is the combination of civil
society actors. 
How are democracy and human rights
linked? 
You cannot have human rights flourish
in a country that is non-democratic: we
have seen this time and again. At the
same time, we cannot say if there is
democracy in a country, there will be
automatically human rights.
Democracy can exist in all societies
but cannot be transplanted from outside
– democracy has to come from within
societies. Democracy does not start and
end with the electoral process which
may be its very beginning but true a
democracy means much more:  it means
institution building, inclusiveness,
empowering people. These are all
ingredients of democracy linked with
human rights.
In fact, human rights movements
focus on deepening democracy because
we need that in every society. Over the
last decades, we have witnessed the
stagnation of democracy even in the
Western countries with a much longer
experience of it. Human rights activists
have to work to connect both civil and
political rights and social and economic
rights to make democracies effective.
Do you believe that things are
changing for the better? 
Changing mindsets is the most difficult
thing. If I look back 30 years, I think there
has been change. We have become
more honest and this accelerates the
change of mindsets and younger people
really come forward to the scene of
public life and give it a new colour. There
was a time when you could not talk
against the government and not risk
prison. Today we do not have political
prisons in our country. That does not
mean we do not have human rights
violations, but we have gone several
steps forward. 
But we have also gone a step
backward as the world is becoming
more complex with new challenges and
threats. We should all be looking for
solutions to common problems. We
need to talk not just about human rights
monitoring but also determine where
we need sustainability, where we need
to do better, and what strategies we
should follow. One civil society leader
said to me many years ago: “Asma, you
can’t simply be a human rights activist
with two feet running on the streets, you
must use your head too”. I am learning
now that the feet must move with the
head. ■
Asma Jahangir, a lawyer and
President of Pakistan’s Supreme Court
Bar Association, served as Chairperson
of the Pakistan’s Human Rights
Commission as well as United Nations
Special Rapporteur on Freedom of
Religion or Belief. The prize recognized
her advocacy for human rights,
especially those of religious minorities,
women and children.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 2 7
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
In the Arab region, the debate on
women’s rights is currently focused on
the reform of family law. Indeed, in the
name of an Islam raised to the rank of
State religion, modern laws accord a
lower status to women than to men.
From the Middle East to North Africa a
normative system has been constructed
around women – and women in
particular – that is subordinate to Sharia
law or the fiqh [Islamic law and
jurisprudence] and which, in a variety of
forms, legitimizes a whole range of
amalgams, such as between religion and
political affiliation, political
commandment and the application of
Sharia law, marriage and religious
endogamy, etc. 
Family law cements the links
between religious and political orders,
turning the family into a citadel of male
domination. One only has to look at the
rules on marriage, which include
matrimonial subjugation, a ban on
unions between Muslims and non-
Muslims, and relationships between
marriage partners based on a duty of
maintenance, giving men the
predominant role. And then there are
the rules of descent and kinship, which
are based on patrilineal genealogy and
also apply to laws on nationality – a
Rights won, 
To understand the obstacles that block the path to women’s emancipation in Arab countries,
including Tunisia, where they have had the vote since 1957, the lawyer Sana Ben Achour
delves into family law. She exposes the pretence of the State’s endorsement of feminism,
which falls far short of meeting the exigencies of gender equality and indivisible rights.
SANA BEN ACHOUR woman cannot pass on her nationality
to her husband or children. 
Of the 22 members of the League of
Arab States, 16 signed the Convention
on the Elimination of all Forms of
Discrimination against Women in 1981.
However, they have nearly all voiced
substantial reservations, whether
specific or general, regarding one
measure or another in the text. It is thus
easy to understand that the feminist
movements that emerged in the 1980s
rallied around public policy issues to
protest against institutionalized
discrimination and the differences
between universal human rights and
national laws.
On 19 January 2011 in Tunis, thousands of
people marched in support of a secular state.
Sana Ben Achour’s Association of Women
Democrats was one of the main organizers.  © A.
Gabus, Tunis 
2 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Hostages of the political regime
It is interesting to note that economic,
social and cultural reforms have been
initiated by authoritarian governments –
often the offspring of national liberation
movements – exploiting family relations
as leverage for their national politics. As a
result, civil codes regarding the
individual and the family, although they
derive their origins from classic Muslim
law, are part of a legislative policy that
signals a certain conquest of modern
legislative reason. This was the case for
the Egyptian laws of 1917, 1920 and
1929, then laws on personal status in
Jordan (1951 and 1976), Syria (1953),
Tunisia (1956), Morocco (1957-1958) and
Iraq (1959). Other countries recently
rallied behind this model: Algeria and
Kuwait in 1984 and, nearer home,
Mauritania in 2001. In all of these cases,
the reforms led to changes in the law and
a restructuring of Islamic normative code
around women. This is because what is at
stake is siyassa tachrîya (“the making of a
legislative policy”), taking account of the
need for arbitration between the
principles of the organisation of identity
and civil society’s demands for equality. It
is precisely for this reason that the law on
personal and family status oscillates
between the spirit of tradition and the
spirit of innovation. 
Furthermore, not one of these
policies has been implemented without
authoritarian intervention by central
government – such as decrees from the
Head of State (as in Tunisia, under the
presidency of Habib Bourguiba),
regulations arising from a state of
emergency (as in Egypt under President
Anwar El Sadat) or dhahir of the King (as
in Morocco). Almost everywhere, they
have been accompanied by the
establishment of National Women’s
Unions, satellite women’s organizations,
heavily embedded within the State
apparatus and the party in power. And
these organizations serve as a conduit to
disseminate social policy regarding
maternal and child health, education and
literacy, rural development, the
popularization of new laws on personal
and family status. These forms of “State
feminism” ended up by taking women
hostage and using them as a shield of
stability for political regimes.
Maintaining the status quo 
Today, in countries that have been taken
over by Islamist movements and appeals
for conformity, these texts, marred by a
lack of democracy, still seem to have only
a precarious hold. They may be called
into question at any moment, as was the
case in Egypt with the Jihan law of 1979
(named after Sadat’s wife), which allowed
a woman to obtain a divorce
automatically during the year after her
husband’s second marriage. This law was
revoked in 1985, under the new article 2
of the Constitution that made Islamic law
the principle source of legislation. It was
the same in Tunisia when President
Bourguiba was deposed in 1987 and
there were increasing threats of a “return
to origins”. Once again the tutelary
intervention of top State authorities was
required to ensure that the law on
personal status was not touched, that its
principles became an accepted national
fact, and to come down hard on the
Islamist movement – once it had been
‘normalized’ – and, while they were at it,
on the democrats too. 
In other words, behind the scenes of
these legislative policies on the family,
not only the reform of traditional law is at
stake, but maintaining the status quo.
Any questioning of the traditional
asymmetry between the rights of men
and the rights of women would be a
threat to established public order. And
those in power permanently renew this
asymmetry when they grant legal
guarantees to women without ever
letting go of male superiority. In the
wider landscape of family law in Islamic
countries, Tunisia is undoubtedly the
country that has gone furthest in terms
of transgressing against holy law –
divorce by mutual consent legalized as
In December 2008, Sana Ben Achour was
elected president of the Tunisian
association of women democrats (ATFD),
whose main objective is the adoption of
universal values of gender equality, human
rights and fundamental freedoms, as well
as campaigning for the financial and social
rights of women.
A graduate in civil law and lecturer in the
Faculty of legal, political and social sciences
of Tunis, Sana Ben Achour is also a member
of the Tunisian League of Human Rights
(LTDH).Her father, the eminent religious
scholar El Fadhel Ben Achour (1909-1970),
became known for his criticism of
dogmatism, extremism and obscurantism.
early as 1956, the right to vote for
women in 1957, legalized abortion from
1962… But, like the other countries, it
has not been able to halt male privilege.
Which means the husband as head of the
family, the continued practice of the
dowry – even if it is just a symbolic dinar
– as a condition for marriage, the two-
thirds/one-third rule in favour of males
for dividing an inheritance, etc. Under
these conditions, one can measure the
gulf that separates the words of
politicians on reforms of the law on
individual status or improvements in
family law from the demands of feminists
regarding women’s independence, and
equal and indivisible rights. ■
L 'Sisterhood Solidarity', a sculpture by Italian artist
Silvio Russo, was presented to the United Nations in
1996 as a gift from Arab women around the world.
© UN Photo/Eskinder Debebe
© Sana Ben Achour
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 2 9
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The feminist struggles of past decades often reduced men to enemies, to be fought with any
possible means. Today, Italian women are mobilizing side by side with men, in order to keep
their precious gains and to make new demands, such as equal pay for equal work and
flexible working conditions that do not lead to precarity.  
‘We didn’t expect it.’ This was the first
answer that the organizers of the
demonstrations on 13 February 2011
gave to those persons who asked them
to comment on their initiative. The
organization in just a few days of a
national day of action, which succeeded
in spreading all over the world, must
have seemed an enormous challenge at
first. Everything started with a clear and
categorical movement of indignation,
which affected a very varied group of
women, who were members of the Di
Nuovo association and who had been
involved in the defence of women’s
rights for a long time. Several hundred
thousand people responded to their
call, one million according to the
organizers. Women who took to the
streets with their partners, their fathers,
their sons and their brothers, in order to
clearly make a stand for the
emancipation of Italian women. ‘Every
one of us made phone calls and
contacted their networks, and in no
time we got enthusiastic replies from
everyone’, said the young poet Elisa
Davoglio.
The slogan of the demonstration, ‘Se
non ora quando?’, which is a clear
reference to the title of a novel by the
famous Italian writer Primo Levi (1919-
1987) – ‘Now or Never’ in English –
clearly expressed the brutal degradation
of the depiction of woman in the media
and in Italian politics. The malaise that
led to this protest found its roots in the
erosion of gains that Italian women
thought were permanent, the fruit of
the struggle for civil rights and the
equality of the sexes in the 1960s and
1970s. This period of political struggle,
which forged an entire generation of
Italian feminists, seemed to have led to
major victories: family law was radically
modified (with the authorization of
divorce in 1974) and women obtained
the freedom to decide about pregnancy
(thanks to the abolition of a particularly
restrictive abortion law in 1981). The
fervour of those years seems to have
gradually died down during the
following decades, which saw a major
divide developing between the first
generation of Italian feminists and their
daughters and granddaughters. 
Let’s start again together 
Comparing this era to the current
mobilization of Italian women,
Francesca Izzo, a lecturer in the history
of political doctrine at the University of
Naples ‘L’Orientale’, observes how this
movement ‘very quickly built bridges
promoting communication between
the generations’, as a result of mutual
recognition. ‘On the one hand, the
generation that fought in the 1970s
became fully aware that their gains
risked being seriously challenged if they
did not find the courage to speak up
while recognizing the errors of the past.
On the other hand, the young
generations finally understood that the
rights and benefits which they had
enjoyed without realizing it were
threatened with disappearance. Having
reached that point, we said to ourselves:
‘Let’s start again together’.
GIUSY MUZZOPAPPA
Italian journalist
K The demonstration "Se non ora quando" in the Piazza del Popolo, Rome, Italy, on 13 February 2011
© Grazia Basile, Rome
3 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  
Now or Never
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Together, and with men. Elisa
Davoglio is very clear about this point:
‘Men gave us very precious assistance.
The mobilization was born in a climate
of sincere cooperation and spontaneous
sharing of reasons for indignation.’
Francesca Izzo goes further and
identifies a radically new aspect of this
issue compared to former feminist
movements: ‘Above all, young  people
could not understood, and rightly so,
the demands of the feminist struggles
of past decades, which often reduced
men to enemies to be fought by any
means. Young women today have the
same fears, frustrations and aspirations
as men of their ages, and they often feel
fragile and inadequate. They would
never support a mobilization where
only women had the right to feel
indignant.’ Cristina Comencini, the film
director and writer, who, with her sister
Francesca, contributed to organizing
the demonstration, noted, ‘it is the first
time that men have been on an equal
footing with women and have taken to
the streets side by side with them to
show their political and human
strength.’ 
A political contest 
‘Italy is not a country for women’ is
another slogan that was found on many
banners in the streets of Italy and
elsewhere. Cold hard statistics confirm
this. According to the 2010 OECD report
about education in the world, women in
Italy study more than men (they
represent 61 % of graduates), but have
great difficulties in entering the job
market. According to the report Salari in
Italia, 2000-2010: il decennio perduto
(Salaries in Italy, 2000-2010: the lost
decade) by the CGIL, the main Italian
trade union, it also appears that their
salaries are 12 % lower than those of
their male colleagues, on average.
According to the 2010 report by ISTAT
(National Institute of Statistics), the
female inactivity rate – i.e. the
percentage of women who are not
working or studying – is 48.9 %, which is
the highest level in the European Union
after Malta. The presence of Susanna
Camusso, the first woman secretary-
general of the CGIL, on the podium of
the Piazza del Popolo in Rome on 13
February is therefore even more
symbolic. Working conditions, the right
to choose between a professional career
and motherhood, the right to equal pay
with men,  the right to flexibility which
does not lead to lifetime precarity -
these are the issues in the political
contest started by the movement ‘Se
non ora quando?’ .
The discrediting of women’s roles in
society goes hand in hand with the
monstrous and deformed depiction of
women in the mainstream media. Last
year, a documentary by the women’s
rights activist Lorella Zanardo, entitled
‘Women’s Bodies’, made a considerable
impact: no Italian woman who saw it
can forget the grotesque atmosphere of
this montage of extracts from the
television programmes that are shown
on every Italian channel every day. The
idea of women being just bodies for
consumption has profound
repercussions, above all on younger
generations. It is precisely this which
enables the organizers of the
mobilization to ask deeper questions.
‘We launched this call in order to say
that it is not the country we want’, said
Elisa Davoglio. ‘To attain  this, we
decided to make the first move and
avoid any exploitation of our message,
by circulating it on our networks via
Facebook and by creating a blog from
which we could launch a debate that
was not controlled by the traditional
media.  We asked everyone to leave all
political and group membership
symbols at home, and we chose to
spread the message and guidelines
ourselves, with clear and simple words,
so as to prevent the traditional media
from taking over our mobilization in any
way.’
What are the next steps and the
next problems that the movement will
decide to face? The question remains
open. ‘There is no lack of objectives’, said
Francesca Izzo, ‘but we must know how
we want to attain them. Democracy is
fundamentally a constant struggle
between objectives and means. The
issue of women’s rights is at the heart of
the major crisis of democratic
representation. The enormous task in
front of us consists in reorganizing
democracy, an objective which needs
determination and patience.’ The
women in the ‘Se non ora quando?’
movement want to reclaim the 8 March,
International Women’s Day, which has
lost its meaning in Italy. Elisa Davoglio
concludes: ‘It is not just about
celebrating the fact of being a woman
for one day, about being given flowers,
or even about going to the restaurant. 8
March speaks about rights, work and
emancipation.’  ■
L Scene from the demonstration “Se non ora quando”. Piazza del Popolo, Rome, Italy, on 13 February 2011 
© Grazia Basile, Rome
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 3 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
3 2 . L E  C O U R R I E R  D E  L’ U N E S C O  .
A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
Interview with MÓNICA
GONZÁLEZ MÚJICA by Carolina
Jerez and Lucía Iglesias UNESCO
Do women do journalism differently?
As a woman journalist, what were your
advantages and the obstacles you had
to overcome throughout your career?
Let’s talk first about the advantages of
being a woman, because there are
some. We have a particular sensitivity,
which I think is very useful for
investigative journalism – a greater
capacity for perceiving who is telling the
truth, who is lying, who is hiding behind
a shield, a mask or a disguise. I also feel
that when women undertake
something, we are more persistent and
we only ease up when the work is done.
We’re hard-headed! And I say that
without being a feminist.
Of course there are obstacles,
particularly when aggressors, torturers,
attack us sexually in order to destroy us. I
discovered under the dictatorship that
rape is primarily intended to break us. No
one could enjoy raping a woman. The
pleasure is to humiliate a woman and rob
her of her identity. But in my case, on the
contrary, it made me stronger.
What do you consider your greatest
professional success? 
The most important accomplishment
for me was to be able to go from
dictatorship to democracy without
giving up journalism. I never gave it up
during the dictatorship, not in jail, not
tyranny
K Plaza Italia in Santiago, Chile, on 10 December 2006, day of General Pinochet’s death.
© Eduardo Aguayo, Santiago
under torture, not when my friends
were killed, or when I had to be
separated from my daughters, or when I
shared the pain of so many people in
this country. When democracy came, I
felt that there was so much to build.
What I did right was not to give up
journalism and I found a new way to
continue every time I was unemployed.
I managed to do this thanks to the
assistance of many people - I am not a
Superwoman. I am grateful to have met
people who supported me and
encouraged me to persevere when I was
the most afraid. In this profession, you
are put to the test every day and I want
this to go on until I die. 
What is the situation of investigative
journalism today? 
It is without any doubt the type of
journalism most severely under attack
If we do not speak out, we are accomplices, says Mónica González Mújica, laureate of the
2010 UNESCO/Guillermo Cano World Press Freedom Prize. Jailed and tortured during the
dictatorship in Chile, she never relinquished her right to free speech. Denouncing injustice
is what counts for her, beyond gender barriers.
Standing up to
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
L E  C O U R R I E R  D E  L’ U N E S C O  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 3 3
everywhere. Investigation was the first
victim of the economic crisis of 2008. It
was the most expensive journalists that
were laid off first, those who were
dedicated to investigation. As the
investigation’s journalism often is source
of problems and conflicts, the crisis was
a wonderful excuse to get rid of the
desk best equipped to investigate the
real, pressing issues that were decisive
for the lives of citizens. 
However, I must stress that the
quality of investigative journalism in
Latin America is at least as high as that
of investigative journalism in English-
speaking countries. And not only today,
because we also did this type of work
under dictatorships. In Chile, for
example, journalists denounced the
Pinochet regime crimes under his
dictatorship, running incredible risks.
Either journalists have to denounce
crimes and atrocities or they become
accomplices. And it is true that
investigative journalism always involves
great personal sacrifices and the use of
the journalist’s own funds, because, let’s
face it, no media organization will pay
journalists for months so they can carry
out an in-depth investigation into an
issue and reveal it to the world. 
Basically, I think that Latino-
American investigative journalism is
facing a major problem: the drug cartels
are eroding our societies. Their final
objective is to deprive us of pleasure,
happiness and life. This is why it is so
important to attack them, and it is also
why it is so important to guarantee that
journalists can investigate and inform,
contrary to the current practice in most
countries’ regions.
What is your view of the media
landscape in Latin America? 
Two problems pose an increasingly
urgent threat to the right of society to
be informed. First:  the formidable
concentration of media ownership.
Groups take control of several media
companies thus consolidating
television, radio and the written press,
while they maintain interests in other
sectors of production, such as
agriculture, mining, services, real estate,
etc. A media company cannot provide
objective reporting on corporations of
which its owner has shares. This is very
serious. Journalists are losing their
independence, their dignity and
essential skills.   
L Journalists demonstrating in Mexico City against attacks and kidnappings targeting them in the country. 
© Raul Urbina, Mexico
Mónica González Mujica is one of the
most committed and tenacious journalists
in Chile. Exiled in France after the coup
d’état in 1973, she returned to Chile in
1978, but was not able to practice her
profession again until 1983.  She has
managed the Centro de Información e
Investigación Periodística (CIPER) since May
2007. This journalism and investigation
centre is an independent non-profit
institution specialized in investigative
reporting. 
j Mónica González Mujica speaking at the
international conference on freedom of expression
held at UNESCO on 26 January 2011.
© UNESCO/Danica Bijeljac
The second threat comes from
authoritarian governments, which,
although they came to power
democratically, make journalists their
enemies and submit them to constant
threats. Here, once more, there is
unfortunately no opposition able to
defend freedom of information properly.
Because freedom of information is not
about supporting the government or
the opposition, it is about providing
quality journalism. Just as it is intolerable
that organized crime cartels go to war
on journalists, it is unacceptable for
democratically elected governments to
engage in authoritarian practices.
All this to say the Latin-American
landscape of media industry is,
objectively speaking, discouraging; it
shows the precariousness of journalism.
This is having a deep effect on society. 
It is democracy as a whole that is
undermined, because a badly informed
citizen easily becomes prey to petty
tyrants. We who lived through
dictatorships and who regained
freedom only at the cost of people’s lives
consider that we cannot let democracy
get weak and be manipulated by
authoritarian powers again. ■
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
time was an area exclusively dominated
by men. And when women were
gradually getting a share in the
development of journalism, especially in
central Afghanistan, the black rule of
Taliban gained ground. As a result,
women’s journalistic life in Afghanistan
has no long precedence. 
In the 1980s, a very limited number
of women such as Zakia Kohzad were
active in journalism, while in the 1990s,
under the Taliban’s authoritarian regime,
women journalists were almost entirely
non-existent. A few women such as
Belqais Maqiz and Fatana Ishaq Gailani
nonetheless managed to publish The
Slowly
but surely
There are about 300 women journalists in Afghanistan today, for a population of 25
million. After the repressive 1990s, the new millennium has opened the door for greater
freedom of expression. Threats, the weight of tradition and other obstacles remain, but
despite the arduous journey, Afghan women journalists are moving forward with
determination, says Humaira Habib.
HUMAIRA HABIB 
“I want to keep all the invitation cards I
have received for press conferences for
my daughters and grandchildren to see
in the future and to be proud of me,”
Zakiyah Zaki, journalist and manager of
the Voice of Peace Radio, in Parwan
Province, Central Afghanistan, said to
me when we were both participants in a
conference for journalists in Kabul. She
seemed nervous and was concerned
about anonymous threats she had
recently received. Two weeks later, she
was murdered in her home by gunmen.
It was in June 2007.
After three decades of war and
destruction, Afghanistan is in transition.
Affected by poverty, forced migrations,
and national and international plays of
policy, the country is now experiencing
an unprecedented profusion of media,
in a semi democratic society thriving
with unlimited freedom of expression.
Devoid of any experience of historical
evolution, these media have grown
suddenly, in the wake of political and
commercial propaganda. According to
Adila Kabiri, journalist and Professor of
Journalism at Herat University, women
had no place in journalism in
Afghanistan’s past. In its capacity as a
new science, journalism found a footing
in Afghanistan at the same time as the
country’s Constitution and for a long
Sima and Storey, two Radio
Sahar journalists, preparing
an early morning broadcast in
Heart, northwest Afghanistan. 
© www.valentinamonti.com 
K Herat tribunal. A woman petitioning for divorce is interviewed by Farawia, journalist for Radio Sahar.
© ww.valentinamonti.com 
3 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Afghan Woman (Zan-e Afghan) and
Hope (Rozaneh) in Peshawar in Pakistan
during this period.
A significant achievement of post
Taliban Afghanistan, 2001 onwards, is
the rapid and widespread development
of the media and support for freedom
of expression.  The country now boasts
its tens of radio and television
broadcasting stations, hundreds of
magazines and publications as well as
newspapers and periodicals and its
many media agencies and printing
offices.
Women have had an active presence
in the media and the social arena within
the past decade, reaching a level of
participation unprecedented in
Afghanistan’s history. The country is
now home to more than three hundred
woman journalists and managers of
publications. Women have established
more than ten radio stations and in
2010 some provinces in Afghanistan,
notably Herat and Bamyan, were chosen
to host women’s centres and
foundations.  
Despite the many social and
political restrictions, there are a lot of
Afghan women who have kept up their
activities in journalism. Yet a well-known
Afghan writer and poet, Najiba Ayoubi,
head of the media group Kilid, points
out women journalists should not be
satisfied, given the limited percentage
of them who participate in the
profession.
Examining the main challenges
confronted by women in the media and
the need to raise women’s share in this
area, Ms Ayoubi sees journalist training
institutions and centres for journalism
education as responsible for providing
greater opportunities for women. The
current situation reflects the fact that
Humaira Habib is head of the
Women’s Community Radio Station,
Radio Sahar, in Herat, Western
Afghanistan.
L In a village not far from Herat, a woman listens to the radio while she works.
© www.valentinamonti.com 
women have undergone immense
educational and literacy losses within
three decades of war in Afghanistan,
thus calling for positive discrimination
in their favor. According to Ms Ayoubi,
women have a lower share than men in
leadership roles in the largely male
designed media and fewer
opportunities for work as journalists. In
other words, gender issues should be
brought to the attention of media
officials and professionals in
Afghanistan.
Like all other fields of activity,
journalism is also a forefront of
challenges for Afghan women. Farida
Nekzad, winner of the Canadian
Association of Journalists’ award for
Freedom of Expression in 2007, believes
family restrictions are the main reason
preventing Afghan women from
entering the profession upon
graduation, thus pushing them towards
the teaching profession. Furthermore,
women suffer from a lack of social
relations, not much permitted for
Afghan women, and a basic
discriminatory attitude in their society
that sees women’s activity as less
significant than men’s.
Yet Nekzad believes insecurity in the
country is the first and foremost
problem facing Afghan women
journalists. A large number of women
have lost their lives for their profession
in the last decade, among them Shaima
Rezai and Shakiba Sanga Amaj. Other
journalists like Farida Nekzad and Najia
Khodayar have been severely
threatened, causing them to change
their profession.
The head of the Women’s Rights
Group for Afghan Women, Manizha
Naderi, sees the threats and attacks on
women journalists as a representation
of military violence in the country. She
believes Afghan women in general and
women journalists in particular are
attacked for their attributes, with the
perpetrators seeking to weaken
women’s social position.  
Fawzia Fakhri, founder of the Centre
for Women Journalists in Herat,
enumerates important factors for the
growth of journalism among Afghan
women, such as increasing the share of
women journalists participating in
international gatherings and adding
value to their profession at country
level. The more Afghan women enter
journalism, she believes, the more their
future will improve; better opportunities
and conditions must therefore be
provided for them.
Because Afghanistan is moving from
a traditional society towards a modern
society, everything has undergone
sudden, unprecedented growth and all
is imported from outside. In this
context, Afghan women journalists
believe patience is required to build a
better future and time is the remedy for
their security issues.  
Afghan women call for the support
of the international community to
resolve their security problems and
other challenges. They see international
support as an effective step towards
future development of their activities,
making it possible to eliminate threats
and spare women journalists the cruel
fate of Zakiyah Zaki. ■
©
 w
w
w
.v
a
le
n
ti
n
a
m
o
n
ti
.c
o
m
 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 3 5
Photographs illustrating this article are taken from
“Girls on the air”, a documentary filmed by Valentina
Monti.
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
International Women’s Day this year is focusing on the right
to a decent job.  Here, The UNESCO Courier looks at the case of
Algeria, which has seen a rapid expansion in job
opportunities for women since the 1990s. Today, Algerian
women are entering the job market armed with diplomas,
but they still come up against either job insecurity or the
glass ceiling. 
Conquering
the job market
FERIEL LALAMI 
“My name is Hassiba. I am 38. Married,
three children. I work as a technician in
a private sector company. To get to
work, I have to take two buses and start
out at least an hour and a half before
the office opens to be sure to get there
on time. I don’t want to risk getting
fired. It’s so difficult to find a job these
days. I can’t afford to lose my salary –
our family couldn’t survive on my
husband’s salary alone. The cost of living
is very high and you have to add what I
pay to the neighbour who feeds the
L Algerian women training to teach English, a
project funded by the United States State Department.
© Ruth Petzold, Alexandria
children when they come out of school.
My mother finds it hard to accept that I
have a job – in her day, women only
worked at home. But, despite the
difficulties, I am happy to have a
professional activity, to have colleagues
and to contribute to the family budget.” 
The story of this young Algerian,
from the Aïn Naaja district of Algiers,
which I documented in November 2010
as part of a research study on changes
in the family, shows that despite the
obstacles women in Algeria have
entered the jobs market sustainably. A
trend that has been confirmed slowly
but surely over the past three decades,
even if the results are not yet conclusive.
Indeed, with women making up only
15% of the entire workforce (a figure
that remained steady between 2007
and 2010), Algeria lags far behind its
neighbours Tunisia and Morocco, which
have 25% and 28% respectively. 
Even so, the proportion of working
women increased by 10% between the
1980s and the early 2000’s. Why? Above
all because of the sad episode in history
that some call the “Algerian tragedy of the
1990s” or “the second Algerian war.”
And also, the ending of State price
controls, public sector cuts and rising
unemployment that followed pushed
families into poverty. Women started
looking for work, with their families not
daring to throw the weight of tradition on
their shoulders – after all, they had to eat. 
Added to all of this is something
specifically Algerian – women who work
are better qualified than men. Over half
of working women, in 2003, had at least
secondary school qualifications,
compared to only one fifth of men. This
is essentially due to a deliberate policy
of democratising education developed
by the State, which from the end of the
colonial era saw a rapid progression in
the numbers of girls in school. So much
so that in 2010 girls made up 57% of the
student population. 
Another observation is that, up until
the 1990s, the majority of active women
were aged between 19 and 24 and were
unmarried. In most cases, marriage or
the birth of a child would put an end to
their career. Today, there has been a
considerable increase in the number of
married women working, with almost as
many (18%) as single women (20%).
But these statistics do not tell the
whole story. There is also a wider range of
jobs. Although their preferred sectors are
still teaching, health and administration,
women are now entering other areas,
such as journalism. At present 60% of
media workers are women. 
The glass ceiling and lack of job
security
These jobs also allow women to gain a
certain degree of visibility in the public
arena. Even so, there is no escaping the
fact that, as they move up in their
careers, including those that are
‘feminized’, women come up against the
glass ceiling – senior positions of
responsibility are reserved for men.
While women make up half of school
staff, in 2005 they held only 9.15% of
head teacher posts and 5.6 % of basic
education inspector positions.
3 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:56  Page 36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
On top of this, unemployment hits
women harder than men – 19.1 %
compared to 8.1 % respectively in 2010,
according to the National Office of
Statistics. Even worse, among those who
are most qualified, three times as many
women as men are unemployed – 33.6
% versus 11.1 %. Faced with a saturated
jobs market, women often choose to set
up their own small business in sales,
service or cottage industries. According
to the National Chamber of Commerce
(CNRC), between 2006 and 2007, the
number of small traders rose by 4%.
While these are often micro-enterprises,
the proportion of women employers
rose from 3 to 6 %. And a new finding is
that an increasing number of women
are becoming estate agents, travel
agents or agricultural managers. 
The regular increase in the number
of women in paid employment has also
led to the creation of informal jobs, such
as child minder or domestic cook. This
informal economy, generally reserved
for women, is also spreading to small
businesses and the private sector.
Creating yet more unstable, badly-paid
jobs without social security benefits. 
Women’s access to the job market is
also affecting family dynamics, bringing
women greater independence. The
model of “man as breadwinner” is slowly
becoming obsolete. But where in the
past women had to tackle a patriarchal
culture to gain paid employment, they
now face another obstacle, just as hard
to overcome – the extreme scarcity of
jobs. ■
An Algerian political scientist, Feriel
Lalami teaches at the University of
Poitiers (France). 
©
 A
-M
 T
o
u
rn
e
b
iz
e
, P
a
ri
s
Like other Global Public Goods, gender equality represents
long-term collective benefits that run up against short-
term special interests. UN Women, the new United Nations
entity for gender equality and the empowerment of
women, is called upon to surmount the main obstacles to
adequate investment in girls and women.
In the context of the international
economic downturn combined with the
food, energy and environmental crises,
the reflections on “global commons” and
finding global responses have gained a
new momentum. Yet while there is an
extensive literature on Global Public
Goods (GPGs)1, gender equality and
women’s empowerment are
conspicuously absent in these
discussions, despite the fact that it will
be impossible to achieve global
economic growth, accountable
governance and peace when half the
world’s population – women – are kept
outside of the global agenda setting
process. 
Investments in girls and women are
all the more important at a time of
budget constraints when only
investments with a high rate of return
and a significant multiplier effect are
placed on the agenda of donor
countries. The time has come to change
the perspective of development
funding, or international development
assistance. Altruism and geo-politics
must give way to a vision of provision of
utility for all. Girls and women must no
SANIYE GÜLSER CORAT and ESTELLE RAIMONDO
Gender
equality
a global public good
1. Global Public Goods have universal benefits and
require collective action at the international level
for their management. The environment and
human rights are examples of GPGs. 
longer be viewed as victims of
marginalization from the “mainstream”
development efforts but as critical
actors and agents of change who can
add significantly to the overall
productivity of national, regional and
global economies.
We know that women spend, on
average, 90% of their earnings on
education, health and the nutrition of
their families and communities while
men invest only 40% of their earnings in
these areas. Recent evidence
demonstrates that at the corporate
level, increased numbers of women in
top management positions tend to have
a positive effect on the performance of
companies and on their stockholders’
level of trust. Finally, at the macro-level,
evidence also shows that the simple fact
of having women in the workforce has a
positive impact on productivity. 
Gender equality in the political
realm, i.e. women’s inclusion in political
decision-making structures and
processes along with men, also has
powerful spill-over effects. At the local
level, for example, quotas for women in
the Indian Panchayat (local
government) show that women leaders
are more effective in delivering public
goods such as drinking water
infrastructure than their male
counterparts.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 3 7
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Rwanda provides a good example of
this correlation. Rwanda’s constitutional
reform imposed a minimum of 30%
representation for women in the
national parliament. Female members
of Parliament succeeded in putting
health and education at the top of the
Rwandan national agenda. The fast rate
of growth of the country is also
intrinsically linked to the active
participation of women in the labour
force in general (80 per cent) and as
heads of enterprises in particular – they
head 42% of enterprises in the formal
sector and 58% in the non-formal
sector.
In rare instances, such as in Liberia
or Guatemala, where women
participated in formal peace building
processes on an equal footing with
men, peace negotiations became more
constructive, inclusive and sustainable. 
Gender equality as GPG becomes
even more straightforward when the
Millennium Development Goals are
considered. Gender equality is critical
for achieving gender parity in
education, reducing child mortality,
improving maternal health and
eradicating poverty and hunger, as a
majority of the poor are women. As for
environmental sustainability, how can it
the “free-riding” by holding international
institutions and governments
accountable for their commitments such
as to the Convention on the Elimination
of All Forms of Discrimination against
Women (CEDAW) and the Beijing
Declaration and Platform for Action.2
Last but not least, it can surmount the
time inconsistency obstacle by putting
pressure on the Member States and
institutions to honour their obligations.
The new United Nations Entity for
Gender Equality and the Empowerment
of Women (UN Women) has the
potential to play this crucial role
provided that it has vision and strategic
leadership, sets an agenda and course of
action accepted by the major
stakeholders, and is equipped with the
requisite human and financial resources
to fulfil its responsibilities. ■
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ile
lja
c
A graduate of Bosphorus University in Istanbul (Turkey), Saniye Gulser Corat (left)
obtained a doctorate in political science from Carleton University in Canada, where
she was also a professor before becoming the Director of the Division for Gender
Equality at UNESCO.
Estelle Raimondo holds a Master’s degree in development economics from
Columbia University (USA) and one in international affairs from Sciences Po (France).
She is an Assistant Program Specialist in the Internal Oversight Service at UNESCO.
2. The Beijing Declaration and Platform for Action
resulted from the Fourth World Conference on
Women in 1995.
3 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
L Increasing the number of women executives
improves the performance of companies.
© Den_Bar pixburger.com 2011
be achieved if women, who constitute
the majority of those who safeguard
biodiversity, are kept at bay? Finally, how
can a global partnership for
development be achieved if women
either absent or are grossly under-
represented in policy and
decision-making?
What measures can be put in place
to ensure that gender equality
circumvents the fate of other GPGs
regarding “under-provision”? There is a
need to modify the incentives to
overcome three major obstacles: lack of
coordination among actors; “free-riding”
– letting others provide the good while
one enjoys its benefits; and time
inconsistency and public choice, as
gender equality is not at the top of the
agenda of election platforms. 
The United Nations as a system has
significant comparative advantages. It
can overcome the coordination problem
as it is mandated to serve as a platform
for Member States to come together and
address global issues. It can overcome
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Davos Man is a very particular kind of
beast. Powerful, worldly and often very
rich, he tends to be more familiar with
stock market prices than supermarket
prices and has all the right accessories: a
villa on the Côte d’Azur, a private jet on
call and a pet philanthropic project.
Davos Woman is worldly, wealthy
and influential, too. But mostly, she is
scarce.
Women attending this annual Alpine
schmoozefest of the global super elite
find themselves in a peculiar place: They
are members of that elite — but
relatively recent members with a
minority status.
Female participants still account for
only 16 percent of the total at the World
Economic Forum. Indeed, with so many
of the women shuffling through the
snow in their fur coats being spouses,
those who aren’t can easily find
themselves mistaken for one: “At a Davos
cocktail party people tend to assume
you’re a ‘wife’ rather than a C.E.O.,” said
Françoise Gri, the president of Manpower
France, who has made Fortune
magazine’s list of 50 most powerful
women in the world for the past seven
years. It is her second time in Davos.
“It still feels a little like a white men’s
club,” she said. “As a woman, one doesn’t
entirely feel like one belongs.”
Christine Lagarde, the French finance
minister and a Davos regular for over a
decade, described how “the male-
dominated chemistry” at the forum used
to affect her confidence. “You know
you’re competent, you’ve looked at your
files, but somehow you feel inhibited,”
she said.
Female elites do not live in a bubble
It is tempting to think about the rich and
powerful as a gender-neutral group that
operates in a borderless bubble of
privilege and whose disconnect to the
everyday lives of the middle classes in
their respective home countries has only
been exacerbated by the current
economic crisis.
But unlike many of their male peers,
women at the top have something
powerful in common with their less-
privileged sisters: “Gender equality is a
concern that cuts across the class divide,”
said Dominique Reiniche, who heads
Coca-Cola Europe. “Women at all levels
have a common cause.”
That helps explain why the rising
phenomenon of female philanthropy
often focuses on seeking to improve the
lot of less-fortunate women, said Jacki
Zehner, vice chairwoman of the Women’s
Funding Network and the first female
trader to make partner at Goldman
Sachs. Entertainers including Angelina
Jolie [USA] and Annie Lennox [UK] – both
recent Davos attendees – promote
women’s rights for the United Nations or
other organizations.
There are other elements that put
women perhaps less at risk of living in a
hermetically sealed bubble.
Even rich and successful mothers
tend to bear primary responsibility for
the children. That can hold back careers
or make the work-life balance
particularly hectic. But they stay more in
touch with society: they have the
primary relationships with nannies, often
women from more disadvantaged (and
perhaps immigrant) backgrounds. They
speak to teachers and interact with
mothers of their offspring’s friends.
They are also more likely to help with
child-related practical tasks, like birthday
parties and shopping. (“There is nothing
like teenage daughters to keep you in
touch with the world,” said Ms. Reiniche,
a mother of three girls.)
Often, female elites lack the sense of
entitlement among male elites, said Ms.
Lagarde. “Women, for all sorts of
historical, cultural and economic reasons,
have a tendency to stay more connected
with the real world,” said Ms. Lagarde,
herself a mother of two boys.
“I don’t know many men at that level
who would go to the supermarket to do
their own shopping, but I do,” she added.
Among others who do the same, she
said, are Anne Lauvergeon, chief
executive of the nuclear giant Areva;
Chancellor Angela of Germany; and
Lubna Olayan, a Saudi businesswoman.
Davos Forum:
women are the future
Last January’s World Economic Forum in Davos (Switzerland) brought together some 35 heads
of state and government and 2,500 decision-makers, and only 16% of them were women.
Nonetheless, the rate of women’s participation has practically doubled since 2001 and
according to Ben Verwaayen, one of the Forum’s founders, the future of Davos depends on it.
, KATRIN BENNHOLD, German journalist at the International Herald Tribune
This article is reprinted by courtesy of the
International Herald Tribune. Entitled “Women Make
Their Mark at Davos, Though Still a Distinct
Minority”, it appeared in the supplement “The
Female Factor” on 26 January 2011.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 3 9
Even rich and successful mothers
tend to bear primary
responsibility for the children.
That can hold back careers or
make the work-life balance
particularly hectic. 
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Being out of touch with the real world
is one of the most serious charges leveled
at the elites – and elite institutions like
the World Economic Forum.
Gender equality: a must-have
accessory
If Davos wants to remain relevant in
the decades to come, women need to
feature much more not just on the
participant list but as speakers
throughout the program, said Zainab
Salbi, founder of the humanitarian
organization Women for Women
International and one of the World
Economic Forum’s Young Leaders.
“I know many women who already
talk about no longer coming to Davos,”
she said ahead of this year’s meeting.
“The forum was a great 20th century
event, now it needs to prove that it is fit
for the 21st.”
Or, as Ben Verwaayen, chief
executive of Alcatel-Lucent and a
member of the forum’s foundation
board, put it: “Gender equality is about
future-proofing your organization — it’s
a license to be there.”
The sense of urgency has certainly
grown in recent years, particularly since
a French businesswoman who was
reportedly fed up at not being invited to
Davos set up a Women’s Forum in
Deauville, France.
The share of women participants in
Davos has almost doubled since 2001.
Women-related events, once relegated
to the early breakfast slot off-site, now
occupy prime slots in the main Congress
Center. There are receptions, dinners
and cocktails dedicated to female
networking.
This year, for the first time, forum
organizers agreed a 20 percent female
quota with their 100 top partner
companies, insisting they send at least
one woman among their five delegates
or forgo the fifth place. The quota has
more than doubled the number of
women sent from these companies.
Because it affects only 500 of the 2,500
participant slots, it hasn’t increased
overall female attendance, but it is, say
organizers, about as much as they can
force the issue.
“As a foundation that draws its
individual membership from the world’s
leading thousand businesses, we reflect
their gender balance,” said Saadia
Zahidi, Head of the forum’s Women
Leaders and Gender Parity Program.
Soon women might be getting help
from a very Davos corner: Nicole
Schwab, daughter of the founder of the
World Economic Forum, is introducing a
gender equality certificate to
companies that live up to (yet to be
defined) standards on equal pay, female
representation and employee
satisfaction with gender equality.
“The objective is that this certificate
becomes a competitive advantage for
companies who need to attract talent
and compete for investments,” said
Aniela Unguresan, Ms. Schwab’s partner
at The Gender Equality Project.
Now the elites just need to be
convinced that along with the yacht and
the yoga guru, a gender equality label is
a must-have accessory. ■
L One of the women participants at the Davos World Economic Forum, January 2011.
© World Economic Forum/swiss-image.ch/Michael Wuertenberg
4 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
If Davos wants to remain
relevant in the decades to come,
women need to feature much
more not just on the participant
list but as speakers throughout
the program
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Why is it necessary to look at climate
change from a gender perspective?
What do women contribute, in your
opinion? 
Men and women have a different
relationship to natural resources. So we
need to make use of both points of
view. Unfortunately when it comes to
finding solutions, the scales are tipped
in one direction. Strategies are all too
often implemented with a bias, only
from men’s point of view. It is also a
matter of defending women’s rights. We
have to remember that they make up
more than half of the world’s
population. So they should be included
when decisions are made, which has
not been the case up to now. 
Women are the guardians of crucial
knowledge for combating climate
change. For example, in many countries
and regions of the world, like Asia,
Africa, and South America, men have
opted for monoculture, while women
continue to cultivate a great variety of
plants in their gardens and plots.
According to the weather they predict
for the current year, they will choose
one kind of seed rather than another.
This diversity is a goldmine for
scientists who want to reintroduce
species that have disappeared in
certain countries because of farming
policies.  
In countries like Cuba, women have
sometimes kept up to 250 varieties of
Sowing the seeds 
LORENA AGUILAR was interviewed by Alfredo Trujillo Fernandez, Spanish journalist
of the future
As she speaks, Lorena Aguilar tosses her hair with the same energy she puts into every
word and emphatic hand gesture. For over 25 years, she has worked on developing public
policy on climate change, expanding knowledge on issues not yet addressed in terms of
gender equality.
bean, and 75 varieties of rice... In Peru,
there are as many as 60 varieties of
yucca. And in Rwanda, up to 600
varieties of rice! This is what the UN
Food and Agriculture Organisation
(FAO) claims, anyway. 
This wealth of diversity in seeds and
in the traditional knowledge linked to
them is both a treasure in itself and a
fantastic tool for combating climate
change. Firstly, because these kinds of
seed can adapt more easily to the
climatic conditions we are seeing today.
And then because this improved
capacity for adaptation means we will
be able to produce more and therefore
better deal with the food needs of the
world’s population. 
L Women working in the
fields in Kayanza, Burundi
© IUCN/Intu Boedhihartono 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 4 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
How are women in particular affected
by climate change? 
Women are more vulnerable, especially
during natural disasters related to
climate change. Researchers at the
London School of Economics (LSE)
looked at 141 disasters around the
world, and found that in those countries
where gender differences were most
marked, four times as many women
died as men! This is not because they
are weaker but because they have less
education. When a woman who has
never gone to school hears on the radio
that there will be winds of 260 km/h,
this means absolutely nothing to her.
She does not have the tools or sufficient
knowledge to respond to the threat. 
The same problem arises in Muslim
countries where a woman is not allowed
out of the home unless a male
accompanies her. In Bangladesh, in
1991, a hurricane killed almost 150,000
people. No less than 90 % were women!
They didn’t want to leave their home
without a man, or they didn’t know how
to swim. 
The study also found that, in
countries where the gender gap is less
pronounced, a natural disaster causes
about the same number of deaths for
each of the sexes. Our work at the
International Union for Conservation of
Nature (IUCN) consists of emphasising
the fact that women are agents for
change, with special knowledge and
skills, and the right to participate in
decisions and political life. 
What are you doing to encourage this
change? 
For a start, we present things differently.
It is not a question of arguing that
women are more sensitive or better, just
because they are women, or that it’s in
our nature to hug trees. Sentimentality
will get us nowhere! Our argument is
about development, it is technical and
scientific, positive and preventative. It is
an argument based on rights with
universal relevance. The Arab League
has become one of our main allies,
alongside countries like Finland and
Denmark.
This year, we have developed three
strategies that link gender awareness
and adaptation to climate change – in
Mozambique, Jordan and Central
America. Our action mainly involves
visiting each of these regions to see
what has been accomplished in terms of
combating climate change, and from
that point developing strategies
adapted to each particular situation.
This is not a model to be applied
uniformly. We take into account regional
specificities. 
In Central America, for example, the
seven countries in the region (Belize,
Costa Rica, El Salvador, Guatemala,
Honduras, Nicaragua and Panama) have
developed a common strategy for
mitigating climate change and adapting
to its effects. Women have been
consulted and asked to share their
knowledge. By integrating their needs
within this new strategy, we are able to
incorporate the gender factor into the
mitigation measures to be
implemented. 
Over 25 countries want to develop
similar actions, which will enable us to
reduce the differences that lead to a
higher mortality rate for women.  
How do communities feel about these
new projects? 
Some indigenous tribes in Central
America have been actively involved,
both in sharing knowledge and in
building capacity. Their knowledge is
Lorena Aguilar from Costa Rica is the
first woman from Latin America to
hold the post of Senior Gender Advisor
to the World Conservation Union
(IUCN)). 
©
 A
n
d
re
a
 Q
u
e
sa
d
a
-A
g
u
ila
r
fundamental. But, even so, we still
encounter a certain resistance. People
are afraid of repeating past mistakes. We
know for example that 70 % of the
poorest people in the world are women,
but when we look to see who benefits
most from cooperating in projects, we
find that the resources almost never go
to the women. But when they do
benefit, 95 % use these resources to
improve living conditions for the family,
while only about 15% of men do this.
That is why they are afraid that these
projects will once again be just for men,
as was the case when financial
compensation was paid to rural
communities to combat deforestation.
We have fears, and so do communities.
Specifically, what are your fears for the
future? 
We have many fears, because most
development programmes have never
taken gender inequalities into account,
and that is what we want to put right.
The World Bank evaluated over 200
projects on water resources and
concluded that those that were most
effective were always those that
promoted gender equality. What we
want to do is to attract global attention
to this fact. To point out this is a battle
that must be won and that we will
campaign to see this happen. ■
4 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
L Woman carrying wood for construction in Papua
New Guinea ©IUCN/Intu Boedhihartono 
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
“Where are you coming from?” was the
question that feminists most often asked
when someone, famous or not, spoke up
in the heated debates of the 1960s.
Where do you come from, to dare to give
your opinion?
Inevitably I am speaking from my
own territory, which in terms of time and
space already has a long history. A
territory totally inhabited by an
imagination built from the boundless
treasure of books, but also mapped
according to the real world, since life has
led me to grapple with existence in
countries passing through crucial
moments in their history. I was lucky,
then, to escape unscathed from the Latin
American continent as it was being taken
over by some of the worst dictatorships.
And I was able to follow, with my own
eyes, the dizzying changes taking place
in Asian countries like China and Japan. 
But I have to say I was never alone in
my travels. I moved amid a galaxy of
exceptional women united by a common
imperative: to observe, speak and create,
no matter what. 
Stars in my 
personal galaxy
She left her native Argentina
in 1974, shortly before the
military junta took control,
and travelled to the USA,
China, Japan and Italy before
deciding to settle in Paris
(France), seven years later.
During those years, an array
of female role-models
sustained her in her
loneliness. Luisa Futoransky
pays tribute to them here.
LUISA FUTORANSKY
I Else Lasker-Schüler : “Der blaue Jaguar und
Freytag” (The Blue Jaguar and Freytag), circa 1928.
© Michael Werner gallery, Berlin, Cologne and New York   
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 4 3
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
It felt sometimes as if we were going
backwards, but no, it was just that
during difficult times, we were moving
forward like crabs, diagonally.
As I emerged from my own romantic
period, when I was attracted almost
exclusively to artists with sad lives and
tragic endings, like Sylvia Plath,
Alejandra Pizarnik, Camille Claudel and
Charlotte Salomon, I began to admire
the battle of obsessive activists – who
were not always dealt the best hand –
like Janet Frame, Else Lasker-Schüler,
Tina Modotti and Frida Kahlo, to
mention just a few. And also great
travellers like Isabelle Eberhardt,
Alexandra David-Neel, Freya Stark and
Ella Maillart. 
Rereading these lines, I realise that
in my attractions I have gravitated
towards women who were
unappreciated. The ultimate unloved
woman would be Lilith, Adam’s
rebellious first wife, who turns up on the
odd cathedral portico, as part of
superstition, or in literature. I will
illustrate with the examples of two
ambiguous, contradictory figures who
endured long periods of suffering
caused by bodily vicissitudes and
incredible tragedies but who like the
phoenix ultimately experienced
resurrection and vindication. 
Just two women, out of the
hundreds I would have liked to salute.
There is not the space in this article to
talk about the great leaders like Golda
Meir, Bandaranaike – mother and
daughter – Indira and Sonia Gandhi,
Benazir Bhutto, Angela Merkel, Evita,
Michelle Bachelet or Cristina Kirchner.
And, even though I have profound
admiration for the tenacity of Carla del
Ponte and Mary Robinson, or the
courage of Karla Michel Salas and her
tireless campaign to bring the
controversial case of the murdered
women of Ciudad Juárez before the
Inter-American Court of Human Rights, I
cannot dwell on them here. I also
cannot say more about Waris Dirie, the
first woman to publicly denounce
female circumcision. This may be
essentially an African practice, but I feel
that her struggle needs to be shouted
from the rooftops, so that even more
people will follow her example. Indeed,
her cause has long been championed
by a centenarian with more energy than
many half her age, Rita Levi-Montalcini,
nicknamed “Lady Neuron”. Every day she
goes to the office of her foundation in
Rome to lend her support to education
programmes for African women. An
asteroid discovered in 1981 bears her
name, an appropriate tribute.
The road to emancipation that
women have trodden for almost a
century has been hard going – and
continues to be fraught with
ambiguities, contradictions, traps and
perpetual confrontations between the
forces of light and those that do their
utmost to relegate us to the kingdom of
darkness. The lives of two writers, two
dazzling stars that I want to extricate
from obscurity here, will serve as
examples – Else Lasker-Schüler and
Janet Frame.
Else Lasker-Schüler, a foreigner in her
own land
I have kept her portrait and her letters
close at hand for years. She was a mix of
contrasting characteristics - surrender
and arrogance, rebellion and submission.
And so much destitution, so much
poverty. But Else was above all an inner
voice, pursuing poetry, her poetry, to its
ultimate consequences. A gift and a
destiny. “Everyone loves my poetry, but
no-one loves my heart,” she used to say
lucidly and incisively.
Else Lasker-Schüler’s life was filled
with paradox. During the Nazi period, the
Germans added her books to the pile to
be burned as examples of entartete Kunst
(degenerate art). And yet only shortly
before, she had been awarded the Kleist
prize, Germany’s highest literary
distinction. In Israel, they didn’t like her
much either, which is to say no one read
her because she wrote in the language of
the enemy, the cursed language. Today,
her “bad motherland”, Germany, where
she was born, and Israel, where she is
buried, are fighting over her, each
claiming that she is “their” national poet,
calling her “the Muse of Berlin,” and “Star
of Weimar,” no less.
L German poet Else Lasker-Schüler, circa 1925.  
© Private collection
The works by Else Lasker-Schüler illustrating this
article are being shown from 21 January to 1 May
2011 at the Hamburg Bahnhof - Museum for the
Present, Berlin. The exhibition is organized by the
Jewish Museum in Frankfurt with the Berlin
National Gallery and State Museum and supported
by the Friends of the National Gallery.
4 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
But Else was above all an inner
voice, pursuing poetry, her
poetry, to its ultimate
consequences. A gift and a
destiny.
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Else was never satisfied with the
world as it is. She had to transform it,
changing history to suit her. Starting
with herself. She made up her age, her
grandparents’ occupations, the names
of her husband and lovers – the
Sulamite, the Prince of Thebes, Prince
Youssouf, Tino of Bagdhad. But the
reality was more arid, and often the pain
(the premature deaths of her brother
and her only son), the terror (the rise of
Nazism) and the poverty (writing never
earned her enough to live on) lurked
within the damp basements that were
her temporary dwellings. 
A very old bookseller in Jerusalem
who is dear to me remembers coming
across her in the one café where the
city’s insomniacs could go at the time,
Attara. Bizarrely dressed almost in rags,
eccentric as always and with no money
to pay for her modest order, she pulled
some gold foil wrappers from her
blouse and offered them to the irate
waiter as if they were gems or little suns. 
What Am I Doing Here? was the title
chosen by the publisher Salman
Shocken, a refugee in exile in the USA,
for his collected correspondence with
the poet. It contains bitter
recriminations against the earthly
Jerusalem’s harsh climate, its inhabitants’
lack of subtlety and the overall poverty
of its literary and cultural life. 
Expatriate nostalgia was Else’s
greatest sorrow. Her masterpiece, My
Blue Piano, is dedicated “to my
unforgettable friends from the cities of
Germany – and to those who were
driven out like me and are now
dispersed throughout the world. Yours
faithfully!” 
Posterity’s belated judgment
avenged her. On 20 November 2003, in
her acceptance speech for the Nobel
Prize in Literature, Elfriede Jelinek paid
homage to her: “As a schoolgirl I loved
the extravagant, exotic and colourful
personality of Else Lasker-Schüler. I
wanted desperately to write poems like
her, and even though I never did, she
made a considerable impression on me.” 
Janet Frame, at the edge of the
alphabet
In the 1950s, the mentally ill were given
electroshock treatments – Janet Frame
received about 200. Those who
administered the treatments were
conscientious, indifferent or relentless,
but none had any effect on her passion
for writing. 
Literature saved her life. In 1952, she
was at the Seacliff hospital in Otago, New
Zealand, about to undergo an operation.
The diagnosis – later proved wrong – was
schizophrenia. A lobotomy was planned,
to return her to ‘normality’. But just then,
out of the blue, the fairy godmother of
literature appeared – her first book, The
Lagoon and other stories received the
country’s most prestigious prize. 
It was a miracle that the surgeon,
Blake Palmer, and the Otago hospital
administrator happened to read that
very day in the papers that their patient,
Janet Frame, had just received the
Hubert Church Memorial Award.
To situate her in space and time – she
was born in Dunedin on 28 August 1924,
and passed away on 29 January 2004. 
An Angel at My Table, the 1990 film
Jane Campion based on Frame’s three-
volume autobiography, was awarded
the Special Jury prize at the Venice Film
Festival and propelled her into the
limelight. “Until Jane Campion’s film,”
said its subject, “I was known as the mad
writer. Now I am the mad, fat writer.” Her
forte was to scrutinise everything
fearlessly. She never forgot her friend
Nola and all the other women that had
no literary prize to save them from
lobotomies and who were irreversibly
turned into silent and docile zombies. 
L Else Lasker-Schüler: “Prince Yussuf of Thebes”, circa 1928, pastel and chalk, Indian ink, pencil and aluminum on
paper, 26.7 x 21.6 cm.
© Jüdisches Museum Frankfurt am Main. Ursula Seitz-Gray.
I Janet Frame, novelist and poet from New Zealand
(1924-2004).
© Janet Frame Estate/Reg Graham; Janet Frame Literary
Trust; www.janetframe.org.nz 
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Janet Frame is the most penetrating
and brilliant woman writer who ever
attempted to explore madness from the
inside. In her books, she defines her self
as a “migratory bird”.
In Faces on the Water, she notes that
total madness or death never come
when we seek or call them. Frame
establishes her voice in another world,
the world of the defeated, on the other
side, behind the bars, the sedatives and
the straitjackets – speaking for the
bodies and minds locked up inside the
prison of the asylum. 
As she was to learn to her cost, there
is a hierarchy among these patients:
there are the “good”, the “crazy” and the
resistant ones like herself who continue
thinking. They are the ones subjected to
electroshock, a trap that springs shut
“on the shadows of the deep”. 
There were five children in the
Frame family – a boy and five girls. Their
father was a railway worker, their
mother a maid, for a while in the service
of the family of writer Katherine
Mansfield.
Tragedy marked their lives several
times – two of the girls died from
drowning, ten years apart. The son had
epilepsy. 
As a child she was rejected because
she was unattractive, and in
adolescence she was mocked for her
excessive shyness. A teacher she was in
love with convinced her to have herself
committed after a clumsy suicide
attempt. She ended up spending eight
years in a psychiatric hospital, “an
imprisoned Now, an eternal Is-Land
without its accompanying horizons”.
Second amazing intervention by the
fairy godmother of writers: at the end of
her hospital nightmare she met Frank
Sargeson, mentor to promising young
New Zealand writers, who satisfied her
hunger for books and persuaded her to
write full time. He set her up in a cabin
on his property in Takapuna, north of
Auckland. A year later she finished her
first novel, Owls Do Cry. Sargeson also
helped her find the money to go on a
visit to Europe. 
London, Paris, Barcelona, Ibiza and
back to London, where she could not
find work because of her history of
mental illness. Once again, stigma, once
again she committed herself voluntarily,
this time to the Maudsley hospital. Third
visit of the fairy godmother in the guise
of the doctor, Alan Miller, who rejected
the initial diagnosis and erased any
trace of schizophrenia. He encouraged
her to undergo psychoanalysis and to
exorcise her past by putting her ordeal
into words. 
As the magic of numbers requires,
having written seven novels, she
returned home seven years later. And so
life goes.
From then on it was a succession of
prizes, grants, writer’s residencies,
distinctions, voyages and honorary
doctorates, but also controversy
surrounding her work and herself. And
periodic nominations for a Nobel Prize
that never came. 
“The edge of the alphabet where
words crumble and all forms of
communication between the living are
useless,” she writes. How true. ■
Luisa Futoransky, born in Buenos
Aires (Argentina) in 1939, wears several
hats: she is a poet, novelist, translator,
journalist and essayist. In English she
has published The Duration of the
Voyage (Editorial Junction Press, San
Diego, USA, 1997). (She has a website,
in Spanish:
tp://www.luisafutoransky.com.ar )
©
 T
a
m
a
ra
 P
in
ce
4 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
Michelle Bachelet, born in 1951, has been
Executive Director of UN Women since 2010.
She was President of Chile from 2006 to 2010.
Sirimavo Bandaranaike (1916-2000), Prime
Minister of Sri Lanka for three mandates,
between 1960 and 2000.
Chandrika Bandaranaike, born in 1945, was
President of Sri Lanka from 1994 to 2005.
Benazir Bhutto (1953-2007) was twice Prime
Minister of Pakistan.
Jane Campion, born in 1954, is a film director
and scriptwriter from New Zealand.
Camille Claudel (1864-1943), French
sculptress.
Alexandra David-Neel (1868-1969), Franco-
Belgian orientalist, also opera singer,
journalist, writer and explorer.
Carla del Ponte, born in 1947, is a magistrate.
Former Prosecutor for the International
Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia
(ICTY) and the International Criminal Tribunal
for Rwanda (ICTR), she is currently
Ambassador for Switzerland to Argentina,
since 2008.
Waris Dirie, born in 1965 in Somalia, is
Goodwill Ambassador for the United Nations
Population Fund (UNFPA).
Isabelle Eberhardt (1877-1904), Swiss writer.
Janet Frame (1924 - 2004), New Zealand
novelist and poet.
Indira Gandhi (1917-1984) was Prime
Minister of the Indian Union from 1966
to1977, and from 1980 until she died.
Sonia Gandhi, born in 1946 in Italy, entered
Indian politics in 1991, after her husband,
Rajiv Gandhi, then Prime Minister, was
assassinated.
Elfriede Jelinek, born in 1946, is Austrian
and laureate of the Nobel Prize in Literature,
2004.
Frida Kahlo (1907-1954), Mexican painter. 
Cristina Kirchner, born in 1953, has been
President of Argentina since 2007.
Else Lasker-Schüler (1969-1945) German
poet.
Rita Levi-Montalcini, born in 1909, is Italian
and laureate of the Nobel Prize in Medicine,
1986.
Ella Maillart (1903-1997), Swiss explorer,
writer and photographer.
Katherine Mansfield (1888 - 1923), writer
and poet from New Zealand.
Golda Meir (1898-1978), former Minister for
Foreign Affairs and Prime Minister of Israel. 
Angela Merkel, born in 1954, has been
Chancellor of the Federal Republic of
Germany since 2005.
Karla Michel Salas, a Mexican lawyer, is
laureate of the International “Abogados de
Atocha” prize (Castilla-La Mancha, Spain).
Tina Modotti (1896-1942), Italian
photographer.
Evita, alias Eva Perón (1919-1952) was First
Lady of Argentina, from 1946 until her death.
Alejandra Pizarnik (1936-1972), Argentinian
poet.
Sylvia Plath (1932-1963), American poet.
Mary Robinson, born in 1944, was the first
woman president of Ireland, from 1990 to
1997. She then became United Nations High
Commissioner for Human Rights, from 1997
to 2002.
Charlotte Salomon (1917-1943), German
sculptress and painter.
Freya Stark (1893-1993), British writer and
explorer.
Janet Frame is the most
penetrating and brilliant woman
writer who ever attempted to
explore madness from the inside.
In her books, she defines her self
as a “migratory bird”.
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Mother Teresa, with whom I had a 23-
year long  association, was a
multi-dimensional figure, both simple
and complex. Her attention to
whomsoever was with her at any point in
time — whether poor or rich, disabled,
leprosy afflicted or destitute — was
complete. Yet she also simultaneously
ran a huge religious order, the
Missionaries of Charity, that had taken
root in 123 countries by the time she
died in 1997. This included feeding
centres, schools, soup kitchens, hospices,
homes, leprosy stations for orphans and
abandoned children, drug rehabilitation
centres and home-visiting to comfort the
sick and elderly. All these were achieved
with a fair amount of precision and
regularity by the Sisters and Brothers of
her Order. 
The biography I wrote on Mother
was an accident. I had known her for a
number of years and helped her with her
concerns in Delhi. In all that time it never
struck me to write a book. One day when
we were in conversation she said
NAVIN CHAWLA 
Mother Teresa
the most powerful woman in the world
1. Capital of the Former Yugoslav Republic of
Macedonia
L Mother Teresa, with Navin Chawla and his family. © Navin Chawla
something enormously funny and we
both laughed. It was then that I
remarked that none of the books that I
had read about her had brought out that
side of her personality. Perhaps I should
write a book, I said. She was not inclined
to agree: “So many books have already
been written.” I blurted out: “Why,
Mother, does one have to be a Catholic,
can’t a bureaucrat and a Hindu write?” I
immediately regretted my words and fell
into an embarrassed silence for she had
never discriminated in any way. However,
she took that seriously and said: “All right,
but don’t write about me, write about
the work.”
Although she herself remained
fiercely Catholic, her brand of religion
was not exclusive. Convinced that each
person she ministered to was Christ in
suffering, she reached out to people of
all faiths. The very faith that sustained her
infuriated her detractors who saw her as
a symbol of a right-wing conspiracy and,
worse, the principal mouthpiece of the
Vatican’s well-known views against
abortion. Interestingly, such criticism
went largely unnoticed in India, where
she was widely revered.
I once called her the most powerful
woman in the world. She replied:
“Where? If I was, I would bring peace to
the world.” I asked her why she did not
use her undeniable influence to lessen
war. She replied: “War is the fruit of
politics. If I get stuck in politics, I will stop
loving. Because I will have to stand by
one, not by all.”
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 4 7
She devoted her life to
serving the weakest,
founding a multinational
charity in the process.
Portrait by a Hindu author of
Mother Teresa, an Albanian
Catholic who was born in
Skopje1 under the Ottoman
Empire and died in Calcutta,
India. She received the Nobel
Peace Prize in 1979 and in
2003 she was beatified by
Pope John-Paul II. 
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The large bequests and donations
were gratefully received and
immediately ploughed into wherever
the need was most pressing. Yet, it was
the “sacrifice money” that she always
remembered — the Kolkata beggar
who emptied his day’s earnings of a few
coins into her hands; the young Hindu
couple who loved each other so much
yet refused a marriage feast so that they
could offer her the money they thus
saved.
When Mother Teresa was alive, I had
expressed concern to her whether the
organization she had built from scratch
could be sustained after she passed on. I
had seen several other organizations
begin to wither away soon after their
charismatic founders died. The first time I
posed this question to her, she merely
pointed her fingers heavenwards. The
second time I asked, she set my question
aside with a smile saying, “Let me go
first.” On my persistence, she finally
answered, “You have been to so many of
our ‘homes’ (branches) in India and
abroad. Everywhere the Sisters wear the
same saris, eat the same kind of food, do
the same work, but Mother Teresa is not
everywhere, yet the work goes on.” Then
she added, “As long as we remain
committed to the poorest of the poor
and don’t end up serving the rich, the
work will prosper.”
As a Hindu, armed only with a certain
eclecticism, I found it took me longer
than most to understand that Mother
Teresa was with Christ in each conscious
hour, whether at Mass or with each of
those whom she tended. It was not a
different Christ on her crucifix and a
different one who lay dying at her
hospice in Kalighat. For Mother Teresa, to
love one’s neighbour was to love God.
This was what was essential to her, not
the size of her mission or the power
others perceived in her. She explained
this to me simply but meaningfully when
she said, “We are called upon not to be
successful, but to be faithful.”  ■
The 100th anniversary of Mother Teresa’s
birth will be celebrated globally between
August 2010 and August 2011.
A retired high-ranking civil servant,
Navin Chawla had a long association
with Mother Teresa. He wrote a
biography of the founder of the
Missionaries of Charity.
LAUTARO POZO
©
 O
sc
a
r 
M
o
n
sa
lv
e
, C
o
ll.
 C
a
sa
 M
u
se
o
 Q
u
in
ta
 d
e
B
o
liv
a
r, 
C
o
lo
m
b
ia
n
 C
u
lt
u
re
 M
in
is
tr
y,
 B
o
g
o
ta
energy into any task where she could be
useful. In her diary, she wrote: “(...) we
recruited entire villages for the
revolution, the motherland. Women
made uniforms, others dyed the cloth
(...). We dragged children around with
us, asking them to gather scraps of iron
and tin so that we could melt them and
make rifles, cannons, nails, horseshoes,
etc. In a word, I was a real war
commissioner, and I didn’t rest for a
moment until our revolution was won.”
In 1824, after the decisive battle of
Junín for the independence of Peru, she
was made captain of the hussars, then
colonel of the army of Gran Colombia.
The tireless Ecuadorian died in exile, in
Paita (Peru) in 1856. 
Yet her story does not end there, as,
in 2007, many years later, she was
posthumously promoted to General of
the Republic of Ecuador by President
Rafael Correa. ■
By this time, this very beautiful woman
and admirer of Bolívar had already
taken up arms on many occasions. As
early as 1809-1810, while she was still a
teenager, she had supported the
uprisings in Quito, her birthplace, where
the struggle for independence started.
In 1821, she helped to liberate Lima
(Peru), where she married and received
the decoration “The Order of the Sun”
from General San Martín. Back home in
Quito, she joined the battle of
Pichincha, which established the
independence of Gran Colombia. It was
when the Liberator marched
triumphantly into the city on 24 May
1822 that our two heroes met. They
remained inseparable until Bolívar died
in 1830.
From 1823 she became his secretary
and official archivist. A wise advisor and
skilled politician, she worked behind the
scenes for the great man, acting as both
confidant and mediator for the military
chiefs, from Sucre to San Martín. 
But, above all, she performed
miracles on the battlefield, recruiting,
arming, providing supplies, organising,
caring for the wounded, putting her
Manuela
Sáenz
liberator 
of the
Liberator
The bicentennial commemoration of Latin American declarations
of independence (2009-2011) has given official historians a
chance to glorify the heroes of this era. Manuela Sáenz Aispuru
from Ecuador is one of them. Born at the end of the 18th century
and nicknamed “liberator of the Liberator” by her lover Simón
Bolívar, she survives in memoirs only for saving his life in an
assassination attempt in Bogotá, the Colombian capital, in 1828.
She did much more.
Lautaro Pozo is Ambassador and
Permanent Delegate of Ecuador to
UNESCO
4 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
P
o
stscrip
t
“When I heard of the death of Édouard Glissant a flood of images came to me from a long and
fertile friendship.” This is how the Guadeloupian writer, Ernest Pépin, opened his vibrant
homage entitled “An unquiet global soul!” We publish an excerpt here, in memory of Édouard
Glissant, Editor in Chief of the UNESCO Courier from 1982 to 1988. 
Seeing the present as “a very exciting time” for Saudi Arabia, Princess Loulwah evokes youth –
and not oil – as the country’s wealth. Interview by Linda Tinio, UNESCO Bureau of Strategic
Planning.
The work of three global giants of poetry underpins a new UNESCO project, entitled “Tagore,
Neruda, Césaire: for a reconciled universal.”
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
The
Philosophy of
Tout-Monde
“When I heard of the death of
Édouard Glissant a flood of
images came to me from a
long and fertile friendship.”
This is how the Guadeloupian
writer Ernest Pépin opened
his vibrant homage entitled
“An unquiet global soul!” We
publish an excerpt here, in
memory of Édouard Glissant,
Editor in Chief of the UNESCO
Courier from 1982 to 1988. 
In the frenzy of his poems, plays, novels
and theoretical works, it is sometimes
difficult to follow the thread of Édouard
Glissant’s thinking. Yet we find his ideas
alluring, like the ‘field of islands’ he
wanted to build at the tip of Tout-Monde1.
Endlessly expanding the concentric
circles of writing in a state of high alert,
he irrigated a proteiform ‘system’ of a
rare density […]
For Glissant, the idea of the Tout-
Monde did not mean kowtowing to the
humbug of globalization. On the
contrary, it meant substituting the
“trembling” of the world for the myth of
an immutable identity. It stood for its
unpredictability! Its ‘globality’! 
Tribute to 
Édouard Glissant
By investigating the world, in all its
incessant movement, Glissant taught us
to renounce the idea of a levelling and,
when all is said and done, imperialist
unity. 
He made it impossible to make
assimilations, encouraging us to
appreciate the frictions, the lightning
strikes, the variations of a
heterogeneous intellectual and cultural
effervescence. How a Frenchman can
become Chinese, a Chinese person
Caribbean, a Caribbean, Finnish,
without losing anything of their identity.
Glissant taught us about plasticity
versus rigidity. All one has to do today is
to watch or listen to some of the
younger generation to understand this
alternative way of thinking of the world
and oneself. Glissant taught us that
identity is not a rosary to be recited but
a risk that one faces up to with the
imagination of the world. Not a denial of
others but an opening to others. ‘A loss
of identity!’ cry those nostalgic for
‘purity’. ‘No’ replies Glissant, a
reorganization of the self within the
creative instability of the world! 
His legacy to us is no less than a
philosophy fit for the 21st century. All
ERNEST PÉPIN
others condemn the components of the
world to endless and pointless
confrontations. A way of inhabiting the
world, without putting up barriers! 
His more recent work consolidated
his thinking about the Tout-Monde.
Places defy national straitjackets.
Connections defy borders. Exchange
abolishes isolation, bringing in its wake
a global-identity. An identity without
cultural hierarchies, without
imperialism, which is neither exclusive
nor excluding, and which is able to
accept without begrudging unexpected
forms of creation of humanity by
humanity! 
Because that was the issue – the
humanization of a world that is
conscious of and responsible for its
diversity! 
What emerges from this work and
this examination is its indiscipline. 
What I call ‘indiscipline’ is the non-
respect for ready-made theories, rigid
writing, aesthetics by consensus. It has
not been said often enough that
Glissant’s is a philosophy of dissidence,
of rupture.
Breaking with European and
Eurocentric reasoning. Breaking with
rigid anti-colonialist reasoning. Breaking
with notions of identity as the hostage
of essentialism. Breaking with the
disguised hegemony of globalization.
Breaking with language gaps. Breaking
with the dictatorship of imperial
languages. Breaking, finally, with a
certain conception of literature! 
With each break there emerges an
adherence to other values, other ways
of knowing, other aesthetics of writing,
other functions of the writer and of the
human being. 
He did not invite us to follow the
world. He invited us to run ahead and
wait for it where it was not heading! He
invited us not to write but to produce a
work of writing. He invited us not to
look for transparency but to respect
opacity where it appears. 
Postscript
©
 U
N
 P
h
o
to
/ 
Je
a
n
 M
a
rc
 F
e
rr
é
1. First formulated in a novel in 1993, then in a 1997
theoretical work, “Tout-Monde” became a
fundamental concept of Glissant’s universalist
thinking. An institute devoted to it was founded in
Paris (French-only website: www.tout-monde.com).
5 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Looking more closely, he stood,
alone, in defiance of that most deadly of
imperialisms – a mutilated and
mutilating vision of the world. That is
why he refused to be confined, while
always remaining loyal to his Martinique
and Caribbean. 
Before him stood the vast continent
of black identity, the sovereign empire
of a form of western philosophy whose
rebels he admired (like Rimbaud,
Breton, Arthaud, Segalen, etc.). While
refusing to be colonized, he chose to
build his own cathedral. And in his
honour, it was always built on the
foundations of human emancipation, as
can be seen with his creation of a
research institute in Martinique, setting
up a journal, Acoma, his constant
devotion to the Caribbean Carbet Prize
[Prix Carbet de la Caraïbe], launching the
Édouard Glissant prize, founding the
Institut du Tout-Monde, etc. 
Few have really understood him!
Many have admired him! Now the time
has come to read him! 
To me, a writer from Guadeloupe, he
has given the scope of his questions, the
fervour and generosity of his responses
and the exigency, devoid of all
chauvinism, of living in the world. 
May he be thanked for all of this! ■
Postscript
THE INDELIBLE SIGNATURE OF ÉDOUARD GLISSANT
“This intermingling, [in the Caribbean] however, was not passive assent to the
values imposed,” claimed the Martinican writer, Édouard Glissant, in an article in
the UNESCO Courier published in 1981 under the title “Creative contradictions,
the Caribbean genius has given birth to a new civilization”. A year later he was to
be appointed Editor in Chief of that magazine, a post he held until 1988. “The
Caribbean stands forth as a special setting in which nations and communities
interrelate, each with its own originality, sharing nevertheless a common future,”
wrote this philosopher of the universal, to whom we owe the concept of ‘Tout-
Monde’. He defined métissage not as a simple mingling of cultures, but as a
meeting of differences, thus helping to forge the notion of cultural diversity that
UNESCO defends today, just as it did then.
A few months after he took over as Editor of the UNESCO Courier, Édouard
Glissant had published an issue entitled ‘War on war; poets of the world at
UNESCO’ (November 1982), with contributions from internationally eminent
writers such as Adonis, Guinsberg, Labou Tan’si, Voznesensky, to name just a few.
Soon to follow were ‘Theatre of the World’, ‘Civilizations of the Sea’, “The Artistic
Genius of Latin America’, ‘The Story of the Universe’... He had set the tone: The
UNESCO Courier was going to establish itself as an open forum for intellectual
debate on an international scale. This ‘mark’ of Édouard Glissant still remains
indelibly imprinted on the pages of our magazine. – J. Šopova
For articles by Édouard Glissant in the UNESCO Courier, see:
http://www.unesco.org/new/fr/unesco-courier/edouard-glissant/
K Édouard Glissant was buried on 9 February 2011 at the Diamant cemetery in Martinique, not far from the slave memorial in Anse Cafard. © Elena Spasova
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
To what do you attribute Saudi
Arabia’s progress in moving toward
the Millennium Development Goal of
achieving universal primary
education?
It has always been planned with
forethought and according to the
country’s need. We had no problem
asking for help from UNESCO or the
United Nations to do some of the
planning for us. It is our will to do so. As
for the goal of having perfect education,
I don’t think anybody will reach it.
Hopefully we (Saudi Arabia) have
reached the point that we are aiming
for, supplying efficient service to the
nation and meeting the needs of the
country. 
What are the prospects for giving
Saudi education a more international
character?
Exchanges have always existed. If you
go back in our educational history since
the time of King Abdelaziz (founder of
the kingdom in the 19th century),
students have been sent to acquire
specialties all over the world. It is an
international system. I think the future is
being made at the moment in a lot of
areas in education. It is a very exciting
time for us in Saudi Arabia. We have
great examples like the King Abdullah
University. We are concentrating on
research now. And this is an area that
has been given a boost by the creation
of the King Abdullah University, which is
based on research. 
Interview by LINDA TINIO, UNESCO Bureau of Strategic Planning
What is the role of Saudi Arabia in the
dialogue of cultures?
The King is the one who launched the
whole idea of dialogue, both in Saudi
Arabia and outside. He has been behind
it all the way from the very beginning.
Saudi Arabia has always believed in
dialogue. It is very important. You
cannot do anything without dialogue. I
think that all the projects that the king
has put forward, all include dialogue –
in religion, culture, personal life, even
the way he is doing politics… Hopefully
everybody will follow his example.
How do you see the future of UNESCO-
Saudi Arabia relations?
Collaboration with UNESCO is not only
with the Arab Thought Foundation.
There are many areas in which we are
cooperating. I hope the university I’m
responsible for (Effat College) will also
collaborate with UNESCO. Not enough
people have either contributed to it, or
used the wonderful work that UNESCO
has done for the world. The dialogue
area is where UNESCO is well-known.
The whole policy of Saudi Arabia is
dialogue. I’m sure it will get better and
better.
What is the value of the younger
generation today in Saudi society?
They are our wealth. It is not the oil.
Youth is the wealth of our country. So
they are the people we need to
concentrate on. I was born in a
generation that was doing everything
for the country. The generation before
me who built the country did
everything for the country. Hopefully
the generations after us, we need to
give them that opportunity to serve
their country. ■
This column, launched by the Foresight
Section of UNESCO's Bureau of
Strategic Planning, tackles topics of
interest to the general public and the
Member States of the Organisation. It
features intellectual opinions likely to
foster UNESCO's reflection,
programming and action in its various
areas of competence.
Her Royal Highness Princess
Loulwah Al-Faisal is dedicated to
promoting women’s education and
social and family welfare. Since 1994,
Princess Loulwah has been the
President and Chair of the Board of
Trustees of Al-Maharat Cognitive and
Skill Development Center, Jeddah.
Since 1999, she has served as Vice
Chair and General Supervisor of the
Board of Trustees of Dar-Al-Hanan
School and Effat College, both
institutions reserved for women. 
Postscript
They are our wealth. It is not the
oil. Youth is the wealth of our
country. So they are the people
we need to concentrate on.
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ic
h
e
l R
av
a
ss
a
rd
5 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
Foresight
Youth is our
country’s wealth
Seeing the present as  “a very exciting time”  for Saudi Arabia,
Princess Loulwah evokes youth – and not oil – as the country’s
wealth.
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
The work of these three global giants of
poetry, born, respectively, in India, Chile
and France (Martinique), underpins a
new UNESCO project, entitled “Tagore,
Neruda, Césaire: for a reconciled
universal.” It was launched in June 2011
with the objective of inspiring
reflection, in both academic and artistic
milieus, on the universal values of
human society.
“The idea was put forward in 2008
by Olabiyi Babalola Joseph Yaï,
Permanent Delegate of Benin to
UNESCO and Chairman of the
Organization’s Executive Board,” explains
Françoise Rivière, who, at the time, was
Assistant Director-General for Culture at
UNESCO. “He received the backing of
the permanent delegations of Chile,
France and India,” she adds, then sums
up the gist of the project. “The main
objective was to establish a link
between these writers who have
marked their era and the current global
context, and to observe contemporary
problems in the light of their work.”
One of the most acute issues arising
today, which is of particular interest to
the project, is otherness, explains Annick
Thébia-Melsan, one of the project’s
Universal thought
Tagore, Neruda, Césaire
poetry in the service of 
a new humanism
creators. “Our relationship with the
other is no longer a theoretical
question,” says this Aimé Césaire
specialist, who published an interview
with the father of Negritude in the May
1997 issue of the UNESCO Courier. “We
have never regarded our specificity as
the opposite or antithesis of universality
[…]. Our concern has always been a
humanist concern and we wanted it to
have roots,” said the poet from
Martinique, adding “the universal is
reached by a deeper exploration of the
particular.”  
Rabindranath Tagore had said much
the same thing, in his own words, in a
letter to a friend in 1921, “…but by
nature all men are dwija or twice-
born….first they are born to their home,
and then, for their fulfilment, they have
to be born to the larger world” (UNESCO
Courier, December 1961). In a letter to
another friend in 1934 he added
“Individuality is precious, because only
through it can we realize the universal.”
(UNESCO Courier, January 1994). 
And Pablo Neruda, in a lecture given
at UNESCO in 1972, when he was
Permanent Delegate of Chile, said “I am
far from being an individualist – I
believe that man is only free to the
extent that he is a collectivist.” This idea
had appeared in his 1945 poem Song to
the Red Army on Its Arrival at the Gates of
Prussia: “I wanted to sing for you all, for
the whole of the earth, this song of
obscure words, to make us worthy of
the light that is coming.”
NOÉMIE ANTONY and
JASMINA ŠOPOVA
Other areas of convergence have
been identified within the “Tagore,
Neruda, Césaire: for a reconciled
universal” project, which aims to
stimulate thinking on five subjects in
particular: – poetry as mediator
between man and the world; a new pact
between humanity and nature;
emancipation versus all forms of
oppression; a certain vision of the
relationships between science,
knowledge and ethics; and the
educational heritage of these three
writers. UNESCO is also setting up a
sponsoring committee made up of
academics, scientists and artists whose
task will be to oversee the development
of the project and to help establish a
network for research and the exchange
of ideas. “A whole network of partners
has been established to implement this
project,” explains Edmond Moukala, the
programme’s coordinator. “We have
established links with universities,
research centres, NGOs, non-profit
associations, festivals as well as the
media, to plan conferences and
exhibitions and to encourage scientific
research projects and documentary
films.”
“Even though they moved in very different cultural circles, and almost never came across
each other in the course of their lives, the vision of these three giants of philosophy and
poetry converged,” says Irina Bokova, Director General of UNESCO, about Rabindranath
Tagore, Pablo Neruda and Aimé Césaire. 
“Poetry is always like an act of
peace. The poem is born just as
bread is born of the flour”
Pablo Neruda “The revolution in Martinique
will be made in the name of
bread, of course, but also in the
name of the air and poetry”
Aimé Césaire
Postscript
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1 . 5 3
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:57  Page 53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
RABINDRANATH TAGORE
(1861-1941) 
Indian aristocrat, poet, playwright,
musician, painter and teacher, was
awarded the Nobel Prize in Literature
in 1913. His work promotes respect
for cultural and linguistic identity, as
well as the dialogue between East
and West. He tackles the
fundamental questions facing
peoples who have fought for their
political independence.
As socially committed writers who
have helped make history,
Rabindranath Tagore, Pablo Neruda and
Aimé Césaire shared a vision of the
world that was both humanist and
poetic. The task of this project,
dedicated to them, is to challenge
minds in the contemporary world to
think about what humanism means
today. A task defined subtly by the
Haitian poet René Depestre: “This
expedition should lead us from the
homes of each of the three authors
towards other cultural areas and to a
whole, unified universe.” ■
PABLO NERUDA
(1904-1973) 
Chilean poet, diplomat and playwright
committed to the defence and
recognition of American Indian
civilizations. He opposed dictatorships,
oppression, social and racial exclusion,
injustice and economic exploitation.
His work was recognized with the
award of the Nobel Prize in 1971, two
years before his death and the military
coup in Chile.
AIMÉ CÉSAIRE
(1913-2008)
Martiniquan poet, playwright and
politician, is one of the founders of
the Negritude movement. His work is
a virulent critique of colonialism,
imperialism and slavery. He is one of
the great writers on the political and
cultural liberation of colonized
peoples, especially in Africa. 
FURTHER READING:
“The liberating power of words”, interview with Aimé Césaire, The UNESCO
Courier, May 1997, pp. 4-7.
http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0010/001059/105969eo.pdf#105954
“Rabindranath Tagore: a greater awareness of truth”, The UNESCO Courier,
January 1994, pp. 44-45.
http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0009/000969/096900eo.pdf#9689
“Rabindranath Tagore: Rebel with a Universal Cause”, The UNESCO Courier,
December 1961, pp. 4-27.
http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0006/000643/064331eo.pdf
“Rabindranath Tagore: ‘I have fallen under the enchantment of lines’” The
UNESCO Courier, August 1957, pp. 16-20.
http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0006/000676/067651eo.pdf#67668
“Rabindranath Tagore, Sentinel of the East”, The UNESCO Courier, Supplement,
May, 1949, p. 7.
http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0007/000739/073970eo.pdf#73982
For further information on the project, contact
Edmond Moukala, programme coordinator and a
specialist in intercultural dialogue:
e.moukala@unesco.org;
tnc_reconciled@unesco.org
“Every one of us is like an isolated line of a poem, knowing full well that he rhymes with another line, that
he has to find or fail to find himself.”
Rabindranath Tagore
Post-scriptum
5 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . A P R I L  J U N E  2 0 1 1
©
 F
o
n
d
a
ti
o
n
 P
a
b
lo
 N
e
ru
d
a
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
, P
a
ri
s
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/ 
D
é
lé
g
a
ti
o
n
 p
e
rm
a
n
e
n
te
 d
e
 l’
In
d
e
 
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:58  Page 54
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
L E  C O U R R I E R  D E  L’ U N E S C O  . A V R I L  J U I N  2 0 1 1 . 5 5
Museum International N°236 proposes a gender-oriented
approach to heritage, with articles containing insight into the key role
that women play in shaping and preserving world cultural heritage.
Chapter 1 explores women’s rights in relation to two UNESCO
Conventions: Convention for the Safeguarding of the Intangible Cultural
Heritage (2003) and the Convention on the Protection and Promotion of the
Diversity of Cultural Expressions (2005). Chapter 2 describes the different
levels at which women are present in the heritage Sector. Chapter 3
reviews the experience of women creating museums around the world.
Museum International N°236 redresses an imbalance by recognising
women’s role in culture and upholding their right to access it.
For more information, please contact: clt.museum@unesco.org 
Female Migration Outcomes: 
Human Rights Perspectives
Do women benefit from migration, and if so, how? UNESCO’s on-line
journal Diversities tackles this complex question, examining how
migrant women fare in terms  of gender justice, empowerment and
rights. Its purpose is to accompany ongoing work on migration and
gender at the international level.
Guest editors are Nicola Piper, Senior Research Fellow at the Arnold
Bergstraesser Institute in Freiburg, Germany, and Amber French,
Consultant in International Migration at UNESCO.
Diversities (www.unesco.org/shs/diversities) provides a platform for
international, interdisciplinary and policy-related social science
research in migration, multicultural policies and human rights.
Gender Equality: The Missing Link?
Rethinking the Internationally Agreed Development Goals
beyond 2015, Proceedings of the UNESCO Future Forum held
between 9 to 11 September 2010, Athens, Greece
Prior to the High-Level Meeting of the UN General Assembly on the
Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) in September 2010, UNESCO
held a Future Forum in Athens, Greece, with the participation of a
distinguished group of female leaders to focus on the crucial role of
gender equality for the realization of both women's rights and for the
achievement of the wider goals of development and peace. The
Forum allowed for a rethinking of the internationally agreed
development goals in terms of the missing link of gender equality, as
none of the IADGs (Internationally Agreed Development Goals) and
MDGs can be reached without empowering girls and women.
Pub: 2010; 172 pp
BSP/2010/RP/H/2
http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0018/001894/189403E.pdf
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:58  Page 55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
Five exceptional
women
scientists, one
from each
continent,
received the
2011 L’Oréal-
UNESCO For
Women in
Science Awards
on 3 March at
UNESCO
Headquarters. 
Silvia Torres-Peimbert
(Mexico) 
Astrophysics 
© V. Durruty and P. Guedj for
L'Oréal Corporate Foundation
Vivian Wing-Wah Yam
(China)
Chemistry
© V. Durruty and P. Guedj for
L'Oréal Corporate Foundation
Faiza Al-Kharafi 
(Kuwait)
Chemistry
© V. Durruty and P. Guedj for
L'Oréal Corporate Foundation
Anne L’Huillier 
(Sweden)
Attosecond Physics
© V. Durruty and P. Guedj for
L'Oréal Corporate Foundation
Jillian Banfield 
(USA)
Earth Science   
© V. Durruty and P. Guedj for
L'Oréal Corporate Foundation
The Courier 3 [Eng] [F].:Layout 1  6/5/11  09:58  Page 56
]]>
</page>
</document>
